<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 416-424</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY * 3 GOVERNMENT) .C R E T * - 232 (28).COPY NCKC A B I N E.T,THE BASIS OF SERVJpE ESTIMATES.The undermentioned Committee of Imperial Defence Papers are circulated, by direction of the Prime Minister for the consideration of the Cabinet with reference to Cabinet 34 (28),  Conclusion 6 (a).Note by the Secretary C.I.D. Paper No.892-B.Extract from the Minutes of the 236th Meetingof the Committee of Imperial Defence (Minute 6)*(Signed) M;F;As HANKEY, Secretary to the Cabinet.]2 Whitehall Gardens, S*Wol. July 13th, 1928*
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. ]Printed fo&apos;i the Committee of Imperial Defence.   July 1928.9*secret. Copy No.        ^ ^892-RCOMMITTEE OF  IMPERIAL DEFENCE.IMPERIAL DEFENCE PREPARATIONS. (Previous C.I.D. Paper No. 891-B.)The Basis of Service Estimates.Note by the Secretary.WHEN considering the reference from the Cabinet of His Majesty&apos;s Government in Great Britain (C.I.D. Paper No. 891-B) on the subject of the Basis of Navy Estimates, the Committee of Imperial Defence may like to be reminded of the circumstances in which decisions have been taken at various times during the last few years to base Service Estimates on the assumption that there will be no great war for ten years.2. The first decision on this subject was taken by the War Cabinet (which had not yet given way to a Peace Cabinet) on the 15th August, 1919. The discussions of the War Cabinet had been preceded four days earlier by a meeting of the Finance Committee of the War Cabinet at which the first suggestion had been made to proceed on the assumption that no great war was to be anticipated within the next ten years, and had been left for discussion between the Prime Minister (Mr. Lloyd George) and the Service Ministers    The pertinent decision of the War Cabinet was as follows: &quot; The Admiralty and the War Office and Air Ministry should work out their J Estimates on the following basis  (1.) It should be assumed, for framing revised Estimates, that the British Empire will not be engaged in any great war. during the next ten years and that no Expeditionary Force is required for this purpose.&quot;(There were six other decisions which it is unnecessary to reproduce here.)3. The above decision was not made on a scientific review of the prospects of the next ten years. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Balfour) was not present at the meetings either of the Finance Committee or of the War Cabinet at which the matter was discussed. Moreover, material was not available for a scientific appreciation. The Treaty of Versailles was signed but not ratified. None of the other Peace Treaties had yet been completed. The grouping of nations after the chaos of the War could hardly yet be discerned. Very considerable forces were still being maintained in such distant places as the Caucasus, Constantinople, Archangel, Iraq, and the Finance Committee had already discovered that it was imperative to cut down the expenditure on the Fighting Services. The ten years&apos; formula, therefore, was purely empirical.4. The decision of 1919, quoted above, is the only Cabinet decision laying down a ten years&apos; period as the basis for all Service Estimates. As will be seen below, the same principle has been applied to the particular case of war with Japan and to the particular case of Army Estimates, but the formula of 1919 has never been renewed as applicable to all the Services.[17873]
,5. The next mention of the ten years&apos;period is on the-26th November, 1924 (Cabinet 64 (24), Conclusion 2), when the Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested to the Cabinet that, the Committee of Imperial Defence should be asked to undertake the following enquiries :  ...... -;. , (1.) A fresh survey of the situation as a whole and the dangers to which the British Empire is exposed ; (2.) The desirability and practicability of renewing the decision taken by the Cabinet Committee on Finance on the 11th August, 1919, that the Fighting Services &quot;should proceed on the assumption that no great war is to be anticipated within the next ten years, although provision should be made for the possible expansion of trained units in case of an emergency arising &quot; ;(3.) A review of the cruiser programme, and, after an exploration of the whole situation, submit a Report to the Cabinet.6. As the result of a discussion on this proposal it was left to the Prime Minister to arrange the precise form of the Inquiry and the Terms of Reference after consulta-tion with the Ministers concerned. On the 9th February, 1925 (Cabinet 9 (25), Conclusion 2), the Cabinet appointed a Naval Programme Committee to consider the programme of construction for replacement of Cruisers and other warships. This Committee found that the Naval Power against which the Admiralty were measuring themselves was Japan. They therefore sought the guidance of the Committee of Imperial Defence upon the question of the probability of a war with Japan in any future period with which it was necessary for them to concern themselves. The Conclusions of the Committee of Imperial Defence, which were subsequently ratified by the Cabinet, included the following :-&quot; (ii.) The Committee accept the view of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that in existing circumstances aggressive action against the British Empire on the part of Japan within the next ten years is not a contingency serious-y to be apprehended.The Foreign Office should be responsible for warning the Cabinet and the Committee of Imperial Defence of any change in the international situation in the Far East which would necessitate a fresh review of the question.&quot;(Note. The whole of the Conclusions of the Committee of Imperial Defence on this subject are included in the note by the secretary, OLD. Paper No. 322-0).It will be noted that the above Conclusion applies only to the case of war with Japan. Since then the Admiralty have themselves decided to extend the date for the completion of the Naval Base at Singapore until 1937 (OLD. Paper No.&apos;306-C), and the time allowed for the completion of the first stage of the plan of defence of Singapore has been extended for two years-i.e., until the end of the financial year 1932-33 (234th Meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence).7. In regard to Air Defence, the Cabinet, at its meeting held on the .&apos;&apos;rd December, 1925, approved the recommendation &quot; That the Air Ministry should base their Estimates on the assumption that the completion of the scheme of Air expansion for home defence, approved by the Cabinet and announced in both Houses of Parliament on the 20th June, 1923, is postponed until the year 1935-36 &quot; (Cabinet 57 (25)).8. On the 28th July, 1927, the Cabinet approved the following formula as the basis of Army Estimates : -&quot; That it shall be assumed, for the purpose of the Estimates, that the British Empire will not be engaged in a European war during the next ten years, and that the immediate plans of the Army should be based upon preparedness for an extra-European war.&quot;It will be noticed that the above decision applies only to Army Estimates.9. In January, 1928, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was asked to advise the Committee of Imperial Defence, who were at the time considering the question of
the South African Coast Defences, as to the probable development of the political situation during the&apos; next few years. Sir Austen Chanibeflairi&apos;s opinion, as given in the Report-prepared by the Committee of Imperial; Defence for the Government of South Africa, was as follows :  &quot; -    - &apos;&quot; The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has informed the Committee that the situation existing with regard to France, Japan, and the United States of America, the only three naval Powers likely to be in a position to attack the South African ports, is, in his opinion, as follows: War with France, to whom good relations with ourselves mean so much, appears inconceivable. Japan has never been more peacefully inclined than at present, and the only thing that would arouse her would be a menace to her own interests in Manchuria. A direct quarrel with the United States may be regarded.as something that neither side would contemplate, though a danger might possibly arise if, in a war with a third Power, a naval blockade were instituted which caused inconvenience to United States trade. Such a war with a third Power the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs regards as very unlikely, at any rate for some years. He therefore suggests that the Committee of Imperial Defence might safely assume that no great war was likely to occur during the next ten years.&quot;TJMMARY.10. From the above it will be seen that the original decision to adopt the assumption that no great war was likely to occur for ten years was taken on the loth August, 1919, and that it applied to the Estimates of all three Services ; that it has never been specifically renewed as applying to all three Services, although a proposal to this effect was made by the Chancellor of the exchequer in November, 1924, and an opinion to the same effect has been given by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in January last. But each Service is in fact governed by decisions the effect of which cumulatively does not differ very widely from a renewal of the ten years period, viz., the Navy by the assumption of the 25th June, 1925, that in existing circumstances aggressive action by Japan within the next ten years is not to be apprehended ; the Army by the assumption, approved on the 28th July, 1927, that the British Empire will not be engaged in an European war during the next ten years ; and the Royal Air Force by the decision of December 1925 to postpone the completion of the scheme of Air expausiou until the year 1935-36.(Signed) M. P. A. HANKEY.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, July 2, 1928.
SECRET. Copy No.      53COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the Minutes of the 236^ Meeting held on July 5, 1928.******(6.) NAVAL POLICY: BASIS OF NAVAL ESTIMATES.(OLD. Papers Nos. 891-B^and 892-B.)(Previous Reference: GIB. Minutes of the 235th Meeting, Minute 18.)THE COMMITTEE had under consideration a Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, and Cabinet Conclusion thereon (Paper No. 891-B)7-and a Note by the Secretary (Paper No. 892-B).Mr. CHURCHILL said that the Cabinet or Committee of Imperial Defence had on three previous occasions given, as a rough guide for naval and military preparations, a statement to the effect that no major war need be expected for a period of ten years. As a result of this advice, it appeared to him that the Admiralty had based their policy on being ready for a major war at the expiration of the ten years. He felt sure that this outlook was not one which the Committee of Imperial Defence had in mind when they made their statement regarding the ten-years period. He now proposed that the basis of estimates for the Service Depart-ments should rest upon a statement that there would be no major war for a period of ten years, and that this basis should advance from day to day, but the assumption should be reviewed every year by the Committee of Imperial Defence.Mr. BRIDGEMAN said that, in accordance with the decision reached by the Cabinet on the 9th February, 1925, the Admiralty had prepared its programme with the object of achieving a state of readiness by the year 1935. He was in agreement that it would be more satisfactory if a proposal were accepted by which the ten-year limit could be advanced year by year for the accumulation of stores and oil, providing such a scheme did not prevent the Admiralty from maintaining the One-Power standard. Should the proposal, however, endanger the maintenance of a One-Power standard, both as rega.rds preparedness for war and material, he would oppose the scheme to the utmost.LORD BALFOUR was of the opinion that nobody could say that from any one moment war was an impossibility for the next ten years, and that we could not rest in a state of unpreparedness on such an assumption by anybody. To suggest that we could be nine and a half years away from preparedness would be a most dangerous suggestion. We had but a small Army and a Navy that we could hardly reduce. These must be maintained in the highest pitch of perfection. It would be wholly impracticable to suggest a scheme which allowed our arms a period of ten years in which to prepare.Mr. CHURCHILL agreed that the formula could not be interpreted to mean that we could dispense with our sailors and soldiers, but expressed doubts in regard to the phrase &quot;highest pitch of perfection.&quot; He demurred to the necessity of being at the same concert pitch for any given date now, as we had been prior to the outbreak of hostilities with Germany. To-day there was no likelihood of a great war, and there was therefore no need for us to be in the state of instantaneous readiness which was found necessary in the years immediately prior to 1914.[17919-3] is[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]1Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   July 1928.
LORD BALFOUR suggested that what was required was a revision of phraseology. A nation which expected to be attacked within a year was in a different position to one which had no particular anxieties.Mr. BRIDGEMAN observed that it would be difficult to decide what the expression &quot; concert pitch &quot; should mean.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN considered that there were two stages in the consideration of this problem. Firstly, there was the matter of principle, such as Mr. Churchill had suggested, which would guide subsequent detailed arrangements, and secondly, the application of that principle by the Departments when each item of expenditure came under review. As regards the first of these, he felt the Committee were in agreement. It was about the second that he saw the possibility of difficulty arising. &apos; With regard to the principle, he stated that, in framing defence policies, a compromise had always to be adopted. The desirability of certain measures as represented by the Service Departments stood on the one hand, and the need for husbanding our resources in peace so that we might be in a position to meet the difficulties of war lay on the other. It rested with the Cabinet to decide where that compromise should be drawn. He pointed out that the Foreign Office had the greatest responsibility in advising the Government with regard to the decision of what period of peace might be expected, and that no more expert opinion on such a subject could be obtained anywhere, but it would be impossible for the Foreign Office to give any guarantee in regard to the advice it gave. He recalled how Lord Granville in Mr. Gladstone&apos;s first Government had been told-by Lord Hammond, the Permanent Under-Secretary of the Foreign Office, fourteen days before the outbreak of the Franco-German War that the affairs in Europe had never been more tranquil or peaceful; further, after the experience of 1914, he believed that no Minister could definitely state that war was an impossibility for any given number of years. Referring to C.I.D. Paper No. 892-B, he considered that the Service Estimates should be based on such a hypothesis as was given on the 15th August, 1919, and that the language used should show that the ten years period was merely a^hypothesis for framing estimates. This hypothesis should be brought up automatically each year before the Estimates were made out. It should not be left to the Foreign Office to raise it. Meanwhile, it would not prevent the Depart-ments from expressing any fears regarding that time limit during the period between each yearly review. .Mr. CHURCHILL agreed with this proposal.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN asked that the Secretary of the Committee of Imperial Defence should be responsible that the subject was introduced on the Agenda of the Committee at a convenient period each year,SIR SAMUEL HOARE felt certain misgivings as to how such a hypothesis might be interpreted by the Treasury. If, he stated, it was to- be used in order to stop necessary developments, he must enter a caveat on the matter of interpretation.Mr. CHURCHILL said the different Departments had a right to urge their own views as to the interpretation, and if these were found to be at variance the matter would always be decided by the Cabinet. He was of the opinion that the ten-year basis should effect a reduction in the Estimates. It would not in any way hamper the development of ideas but would check mass production until the situation demanded it. -Mr. BRIDGEMAN pointed out the danger that might occur should some other country increase its Estimates. The Estimates would be for all the world to see, and should we have to increase our expenditure on the Service Departments owing to political considerations the attention it would draw would certainly not help to further a policy of peace.SIR JAMES PARR thanked Mr. Churchill and Sir Austen Chamberlain for the clearness with which they had set out their proposals. He added that a reduction in strength of the Navy would be regarded seriously in New Zealand and Australia, where there was a large body of opinion which saw in the increasing population of Japan a threat to the peace of the Western Pacific.THE PRIME MINISTER said that Sir Austen Chamberlain would make a statement in regard to the attitude of Japan later in the meeting.
Mr. AMERY agreed with, the general principle of a &quot; revolving credit of peace.&quot; It was in its application that he saw certain difficulties. He agreed that we could postpone from year to year the consideration of Estimates on a basis of ten years of peace, but we could not do this with regard to major projects such as replacement of ships, dockyards and the like. He suggested that, when once a decision had been arrived at to complete one of these heavy works within a certain period of time, that period should be adhered to. If we did not do this we might find ourselves in the position of having a great number of partially completed major projects on hand at a time when events might necessitate their completion. In such circumstances, not only would it become almost impossible to overtake arrears and complete the projects, but our difficulties in maintaining peace would be accentuated.SIR CHARLES MADDEN said he had two points regarding the sea-going Service. If the Fleet were to be reduced to a lower standard of readiness than existed to-day, and it were known in the Fleet that we were accepting a certainty of ten years&apos; peace, a great deal of the incentive for the personnel afloat to maintain its efficiency would be removed, and the conditions that were applicable in the 90&apos;s, when paint and polish came before gunnery, might be incurred by the carrying out of the proposed policy.By peace standard of readiness for the Fleet, he meant that the Fleet must, in peace, be comparable in numbers and size, both of personnel and ships, to each of the fleets of the Great Naval Powers.Except in the case of Capital Ships and Cruisers we are below this standard now with the United States, and below our recognised ratio with Japan.Mr. CHURCHILL remarked that there was no need to publish the fact to the Fleet.SIR CHARLES MADDEN, continuing, said it Avould be impossible to hide the fact from the Fleet when the whole matter of supply, numbers of officers and men and ships in commission were governed by such a decision. The second point was with regard to certain details in the Estimates being referred to the Naval Programme Committee. He felt that it was the responsibility of the Admiralty to decide what details in ships, stores and men were required to meet the decision of policy arrived at by the Cabinet, which at the present time was to maintain a one-Power standard with the United States. If the Naval Programme Committee were to take over the decision as to what constituted a one-Power standard for the Fleet, they would, it appeared to him, be usurping the responsibility invested in the Board of Admiralty.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN said he thought the First Sea Lord was speaking under some misapprehension. Responsibility must always rest upon the Cabinet, and, if they considered they needed certain machinery, such as the Naval Programme Committee, to arrive at their conclusions, it was a domestic arrangement for the Cabinet to decide upon. He was unaware what decision the Naval Programme Committee might come to, or what the Cabinet would decide; should the Admiralty feel that they were unable to maintain the naval power which they had been instructed to keep by the Cabinet on account of the detailed recommendations of the Naval Programme Committee and the Cabinet decision thereon, then it was for the Admiralty to represent the situation to the Cabinet.Mr. CHURCHILL said he did not see why all such detailed subjects as ammunition and personnel of the Fleet should necessarily be referred to the Naval Programme Committee. He hoped that an amicable agreement could be reached between the Admiralty and the Treasury without any reference to that Committee.SIR GRANVILLE RYRIE stated that he knew he was expressing, the opinion of Mr. Bruce and the Australian Cabinet when he said he was in full agreement with the proposal of basing the Service Department Estimates on an understanding that there would be no war for another ten years, and that it was safe to accept such an outlook from year to year. He did not consider Japan was really a potential enemy at the present time, and it was, therefore, a most inopportune time to start the con-struction of coast defences, which might well be obsolete before the danger from Japan justified their construction. In view of the large amount of money that America had invested in Australia, it was highly unlikely that the United States would countenance an aggressive policy on the part of Japan against Australia. Such a consideration must bear upon any decision that Japan might make.[17919-3]   .   . &quot; b 2
rTHE. PRIME MINISTER then asked Sir Austen Chamberlain to give a statement regarding the present political world outlook.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN said that, taking France first, he considered war with that country was inconceivable. Not only were good relations with our-selves of such great importance to the French, but they were not economically in a position to go to war. The same argument applied both to Germany and Italy. He could not imagine either of these countries contemplating a war with ourselves, at any rate for many years to come, and, in the case of Italy, friendly relations with Great Britain had always been one of the foundations of her foreign policy, on account of her extended seaboard.Turning to the United States of America, he repeated what he had said a few months ago when the South African Coast Defences were under consideration, namely, that a direct quarrel with the United States might be regarded as something that neither side would contemplate, though a danger might possibly arise if in a war with a third Power our action as belligerents caused inconvenience to United States trade. Obviously, however, our attitude as regards belligerent rights would at any time be conditioned by what the United States might be expected to stand. He suggested that if America made our attitude on belligerent rights a casus belli, we should not be able to afford to risk hostilities with her and would have to give way. It would, indeed, not even be necessary for the United States to take any warlike action against us in protest. They could close markets and financial sources of vital importance to us. Such a situation, he reiterated, was, in his opinion, the only one from which a war with America might arise, but he could not imagine that any British Government would be mad enough to create such a position.With regard to Japan, Sir Austen Chamberlain pointed out that that country was now passing through a period of internal change, the outcome of which was far too difficult to predict. At any rate, the Japan of to-day was different to the Japan of feudal times, and even of the Japan of 1915, when she was ready to level the 21 Demands at the head of China. It was a Japan that had suffered heavily in the earthquake; a Japan that had just given its population manhood suffrage; a Japan whose economic resources needed careful organising in view of her rapid development as an industrial country. Further, there was every indica-tion to show that Japanese public opinion viewed with dislike and alarm even such military action in China as Baron Tanaka&apos;s Government had recently taken at Tsinanfu, and was averse from widening her military commitments in that country. He could not say that Japan would never become a menace to the Empire, but Japan did not constitute such a menace now. Nor did he think that the attitude of America would be anything but a deterrent to the Japanese if they contemplated aggression against ourselves.The points of trouble at the present time were entirely different, and the one outstanding uncertainty was Russian policy. Of late Russia had been buying equipment and strengthening her army. On the other hand, he believed that the Russian Army was at the present time incapable of offensive operations on a large scale. Nor did he think that the present rulers of Russia wished to precipitate an external crisis, but they had continually to face immense difficulties internally, and one could never be certain what measures a Government in such a situation might take to divert attention from domestic and internal affairs.From the information at his disposal, Sir Austen Chamberlain said that neither Finland nor Poland, nor any of the border States considered themselves at the present time in much danger of Russian aggression. No doubt Russia was trying to keep the feud between Lithuania and Poland alive, and there was always a chance that Poland might lose patience and use forcible measures to gain her ends.Roumania, with a disorganized army and the absence of any commanding figure in the country, was perhaps rather open to attack, and the fact that Russia had never accepted the Bessarabian frontier might invite Russian interference. Speaking of the Balkans there was always a state of restlessness, but he was of the opinion that none of the States had any desire at present to provoke a war.While he felt it his duty to signalise these possible dangers, he did not believe that they were imminent, nor that it was impossible to avoid them. If, however, he was asked which was the country which seemed most likely to threaten the peace of the world to-day his answer was that Russia was the greatest danger spot. So far as we were concerned, any act of aggression by Russia on Afghanistan was what Would most concern us. In this case we should be involved not only in such obliga-tions as might rest on us by virtue of the Covenant, but the safety of India might be at stake.
To sum up, if it were not for the present condition of Russia and the uncertainty as to future Soviet policy, he would be without any grave doubts tha,t we could reckon on no war of any magnitude occurring during the next 10 years.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it would be possible to draw up an agree-ment on the lines given by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and he considered the most suitable date on which the reconsideration of the ten years&apos; basis should be taken would be some date not later than June of each year. This would not, however, remove any right from either the Dominions or any of the Departments to raise the whole question at any time between the yearly decisions of the Committee of Imperial Defence. He pointed out that the Cabinet must take every means it can of investigating how it can obtain the greatest amount of defence for the minimum of expense. He realised that the investigations such as might come to the Naval Programme Committee under these proposals might cause a great deal of trouble and additional work, but he felt it was essential that as many members of the Cabinet as possible should be acquainted with the technical difficulties so that they could assist their colleagues in coming to sound conclusions on the points at issue. He pointed out, however, that there would be no need to bring discussions to such Committees until the Departments concerned had been unable to reach a decision.He suggested that the Secretary should, in consultation with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, draft a conclusion recommending the automatic re-examination of the question annually, while acknowledging the right of any Department or Dominion Representative to ask for a reconsideration of this finding at any time.He suggested that the discussions on Items 1 (a) and 6 on the Agenda, dealing with Singapore and anti-aircraft guns for the Fleet should be postponed until a subsequent meeting.Mr. BRIDGEMAN asked that these questions should be dealt with as soon as possible, since undue delay might have serious consequences from the point of view of contracts.SIR PHILIP CUNLIFFE-LISTER agreed as to the desirability of dealing with these questions as. early as possible, and pointed out that delay would also affect his department, since there were three or four firms which refused to tender for contracts in South America unless a decision could be obtained in regard to the advancement of the Singapore scheme.SIR JAMES PARR asked wmether the conclusion reached by the Committee meant a reduction in naval forces, and a postponement of the completion of the; Singapore Base. His Government was naturally very interested in the latter question. &apos; SThe Committee of Imperial Defence agreed to recommend (a.) That it should be assumed, for the purpose of framing the Estimates of theFighting Services, that at any given date there will be no major war forten years.(b.) That this assumption should be reviewed annually by the Committee of Imperial Defence before the Estimates of the Fighting Services are drawn up, that is to say, not later than the month of June, and that it shall be the duty of the Secretary of the Committee of Imperial Defence to remind, the Prime Minister of this Conclusion at the appropriate moment and take his instructions as to placing the subject on the Agenda Paper of the Committee.&apos;c.) That it shall be the duty of any Department in His Majesty&apos;s Government in Great Britain, no less than the right of the Government of any Dominion, to ask&apos;the Committee of Imperial Defence to review the above Conclusion at any other time if, in the opinion of any of them, the circumstances had so changed as to render its application to the then existing conditions doubtful.******2. Whitehall Gardens, S.W 1. July 5, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
