<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/32/0 images: 37-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>

!/(Tb$ft document is the property of His Britannic Majesty1 s Government)SECRET.CABINET65/22.0OI10LUSIOWS of a meeting of the cabinet held at Ho. 10 Downing Street, S.W., on-Tuesday 7th November, 1922, at 4-15 p.iaPRESENT:-The Prime Minister(In the chair)The Most Hon. The Marquess of salisbury, K.G..G.C.V.0.,C.B.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Viscount Care,G.C.M.G.,    Lord Chancellor.The Most Hon. The Marquess curzon of Kedleston, K.G.&apos;,G.C.S.I.,G:.C.IcE.f Secretary/ of State forPo re ign Affairs.His Grace the Duke of Devonshire,.H.C..G.C.M.G.,G.C.V.O., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hen. Sir Philip Lloyd-Grearae, K.3.E.,M.C., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir Montague Barlow,E.B.E.,   Minister of Labour.The following were also present;-Sir Eyre Crowe, G.C .M.G. ,11. C. 3. ,Permanent Under-Secretary ofState for Eo^pign Affairs.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart., C.M.G.,Secretary of State for Air..Tice Admiral Sir Roger J.3. Eeyes,Bart.. H.CB. ,K.C .V.0. ,C.M.G. ,DS0. ,Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff.General the Earl of Cavan, H.P.,G..C.M.G.,G.C.V.0.,Z.C.3.,A.D.C. ,Chief of the Imperial General StaffAir Marshal Sir H.M. Tr eh chard,Bart., Z.C.B., D.S.O., A.D.C,Chief of the Air Staff.Lieut.-Col. Sir M.P.A. Hanlces?-, G.C.B.,............    ...........  Secretary
(This Document,, is the Property of His BritannicMajestY1,3 Government.)SECRET-CABINET  6 5 (?. ) .conclusions&amp;NS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,,  held at10, Downing Street, S3U,  on TUESDAY, NOVEMBER ?,1923,  at 4-2 0 p ,m,THE SITUATION After hearine from the Secretary of State for at CONSTANT I-.NOPLE,- Foreign Affairs a summary of the difficult situation which(Previous Ref^r- had arisen at Constantinople, based on recent telegrams -ence     Cabinet64 (22)., more particularly telegram No. 668 from the High 0ornmis-Minute 3.)sloner at Constantinople (Appendix I)  and telegramNo.  932-from General Harington (Appendix II),  as wellas a personal-ieb-gran from General Farington to the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff (No. 29 33), and after puttingquestions to the Chipf of the Imperial General Staff andthe Deputy Chief of the Naval Staf*% whose information and advice are summarised in Appendix lilt the Cabinet reachedthe foilowing Conelusione:-(a)  That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should send the attached message to the British Ambassadors in Paris and rome for immediate communication to theFrench and. Italian Presidents of theCouncil (Appendix TV), .NOTE. In order to avoid any unnecessarydelay4 Sir Eyre Crowe,  the permanent under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, arranged for a telephone message to be sent to the british ambassador in Paris during themeeting, instructing Lord Hardingeto warn II, Poincare&apos; to expect animportant message the. same evening.: (b)  That the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff should telegraph to General harington to the effect that the Government were in communication with the French and italian governments as to the extent to which theycould rely on support to the policy proposedby the Allied High Commissioners and Generalsat Constantinople, and that instructions
should he S&apos;--nt as soon as a r-ply wasreceived.(c) That the Cabinet should hold tlw-selves .in readiness to meet on the morrow after an answer was received from Paris.(d) That in his speech the same evening&apos; thePrims Minister should state that thesituation in Turkey is difficult but was satisfactory to the extent that the allied high Cornelssloners and Generals at Con-stantinople were unanimous,MOTE, In order to show the result ofthe above Conclusions^ the tv.rofollowinst telegrams are attachedlord H-ordihge&apos; s reply, receivedby telephone the samo evening,November ?th (No, 570) (Appendix V)Foreign ,Office Telegram to Sir H-,Ruvboid (Constantinople), des-patcited the same evening( kovembev 7th) (Append jy VI) .2,  Whitehall Gardens,  S . 1.1November 7, 1022;
APPENDIX I.Telegram No. 668 from Sir H, Rumbold, Con-stantinople, dated November 6thg 1932.mm URGENT.My telegram 66 5 and my telegram 666.After having examined situation this evening withGenerals, allied High Commissioners decided to addressfollowing identic telegram to their Governments&quot;Initial measures taken by new administration of Con-atantinople constitute not only serious blow to interestsand prestige of Allies, but also threaten to stop economic life of town. , As result of application of new customstariff, price of bread and of articles of primary necessityhas already doubled.    Certain articles indispensable to foreigners Are prohibited.   Justice between Europeans andOttomans is suspended.   Assumption of control by turkish authorities over Ottoman police, gendarmes and troops here is a grave danger to safety of allied troops and foreigncolony.Strong represent^tions will be made tomorrow to Natioaal-ist agent here in nare of Allied Powers .   But contingencythat these remonstrances will have as little effect asprevious ones must be considered.    I fear that a series ofthose measures which are alze ady in force in Anatolia will follow:    expulsion or deportation of Ottoman Christians,sequestration of their property, perquisitions in banks,prohibition &quot;or foreigners to come here or leave withoutauthorisation, arrests, arbitrary executions, etc.. etc.Allied Governments cannot allow a situation of this nature to develop in a zone occupied by their troops andhitherto administered by their   -epresentatlves withoutbetraying confidence of population and without sufferingan irremediable loss of prestige.   Moreover, normal opera-tions 0^* different services and allied controls can nolonger be re-established except under surveillance and immediate protection of allied forces of occupation.Armed conflict with police, gendarmerie and 2,000 Turkishgarrison troops here may ensue, ^he necessity for disarminglatter must be contemplated.&apos;. In agreement with allied Generals, High Commissionersar&quot; unanimously of opinion that establishment of a state ofsiege here is necessary if above&quot; measures are to be put into execution.    Nevertheless operation is a delicate on^ and mayprovokn conflict.    Available allied forces here consist onlvof about eight battalions two squadrons    an artillery group&quot;tanks    armoured cars and flying machines.   Assistance offle-^t can also&apos; be counted upon.High Co-miss icnere were unwilling to accept resoonsibilifcvfor such a decision without reference to allied Governments.&quot;They would be grateful for an immediate reply since everyday lost aggravates situation and renders a peaceful scflhi tiorless probable.
jv* their, aug^eation be not approved. High Commission-era consider t&apos;n:?y ar? no longer in a position to carryon task assigned to tbmm and request fr^ah ins tractions&apos;1
APramux II.Paraphrase of telegram No. 2933 from GeneralHaring^on to War Office, dated November 7,1922.Continuation/my 2925.    Three Parts.1st.Allied Generals met High Commissioners tonight and reported .their action with Rafet.   On their side high commissioners reported that Angora Government had takenupon themselves a series of preposterous acts includingdismissal of Ottoman Debt officials, an enormous increaseof customs dues, abolition of mixed Court and several other measures which High Commissioner has no doubt&apos;reported,for it is quite evident their action is aimed at Alliedprestige ar-d is quite indefensible.   An identic telegramis, I understand, b ing s*mt by High Commissioners recom-mending that situation be handed over to Allied Generals,It &quot;is quite evident that nothing&apos;but very determined action will succeed.    -If Government agree to see the matterthrough, right action to take$ in my opinion, is to issue a proclamation giving our position as the real occupiersunder Mudros Armistice, and making it quit^ clear thatRafet has broken the terms of that armistice and MoudaniaConvention and that these various acts are in violation of our occupation.Part,      &quot;Various acts should be enumerated in proclamationand then publicly cancelled by us .   Martial law, curfew,etc., should at the same time b- rigidly enforced,   A state&apos; of siege must he proclaimed and Turkish troops, gendarmerieand police must b^ disarmed.    It has been my one desire toavoid conflict in Constantinople but I s e no other- alter-native to this insult except extreme humiliation,    I musthowever have complete liberty of action to carry thisthrough,  as I only have 3 Guards battalions in Constant!-nople and this may mean a v - ry serious business,,    french have undertaken to look after Stamboul but I have very large and difficult area.    It would mean withdrawal    cf Ismid andChanak and. their occupation by Kemalists who within a fewdays could have &quot;some 36 to 40 battalions opposite eachfront and no doubt before very long a good number would getacross the Bo aphoru3.Last, Part,,I cannot think they would b    foolish enough to go to warin face of united front Allies are now showing and especially as they have no money, hut in their present rood they are undoubtedly capable of doing anything and yet profess they want to go to Peace Conference to obtain peace.   If we haveto take drastic action we should also stop installingTurkish administration into ^astern Thrace and Greeks woulddoubtlessly,be only too willing to -return.   Americans alsoare seriously concerned over the situation.    Importance of.de-&apos;-andine our withdrawal and that of fleet from Turkishports is so prepostero.ua that it will certainly revoke anysympathy that may be felt for Nationalists, Personally Ithink they will not dare to face it if Allies unite to showthey real!;/ mean business.    I should be glad of immediateinstructions as you will realise this m-ans a completereversal of military policy you have given me and from whichI cannot depart until further orders are giv-n re&apos;. ^ -/eanwliipall necessary plans will be made by Admirals and Generals.
APPENDIX III.

Summary of information and advice given by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff and the Deputy Chief of Naval Staff to the Cabinet on November 7, 1922 (Cabinet 65 (22))



The Chief of the Imperial General Staff, in reply to questions, stated that the previous orders to General Harington had been to the effect that he should regard the relative importance of the various areas in military occupation of the Allies in the following order:-

 1. Gallipoli Peninsula:

 2. Chanak:

 3. Constantinople:

 4. Ismid Peninsula,

Acting under those instructions, had a withdrawal become necessary, it would have been in inverse order to that given above, namely, from

 1. Ismid Peninsula:

 2. Constantinople:

 3. Chanak:

 4. Gallipoli Peninsula.

Since, under the terms of the Mudania Agreement, no extension or further fortification of the position at Chanak was permitted, the above orders had been modified and General Harington had been instructed that he should treat Chanak as an outpost and should withdraw to the Gallipoli  Peninsula if pressed. He himself did not agree with General Harington that there had any change in the military situation sufficient to justify a reversal of this order. The General Staff had been considering the situation and agreed that the Turks were bluffing. His advice was that General Harington should maintain the status ? as long as possible, but that he should, in conjunction with the Allied Generals, arrange for a secure base on the European shore of the Bosphorus from which the Allied forces could withdraw in case of necessity.

  Referring
!0 to a passage in the   personal telegram he had received fromGeneral Harington (No.2953), lord Cavan expressed the viewthat it did not mean that General Harington would be physically unable to extricate his forces at Constantinople,He could always fight his way to the shore, where his forces could be embarked by the Navy.     Replying to further questions,Lord Cavan said that the French forces at or near Constantinopleamounted approximately to nine Battalions, about 5,000 men.He promised to furnish exact figures,.     There was also avery small force of Italians.     Tifithout calling up battalionsfrom Chanak,    General Harington would have about 4,000 menat his disposal at Constantinople if he withdrew from theIsmid Peninsula.     Referring to a suggestion that the Turkisharmy could be prevented from crossing into Europe,  lord cavan said    it was necessary to bear in mind that the turks had about 8,000 armed men already on the European side ofthe Straits, who had filtered across, including 2,000 men in constantinople Itself, since increased presumably by the sultan^ personal guard of 5,000 now released from that. special duty.     The British troops at Constantinople were of excellent quality, but, in order to hold the Bosphorus,they would have to face both ways.      They could be supportedby reinforcements from the Gallipoli Pensinula and Chanakto the extent that transports vere available, but the numberof ti-ansports was now reducec-.      Should the situation becomesuch as to.require larger reinforcements, the French, he had reason to believe, had two Divisions in ,the neighbourhoodof Marseilles, which should be able to reach Constantinoplewithin about eight days from the date of sailing.      Substan-tial British reinforcements could not be despatched withoutmobilisation, and the first Division would reach- the constantinople area 31 days from the c!ate of mobilisation.
The Deputy Chief       the Naval Staff, in reply to qp.es-tions, said that the First Sea Lord held the view, whichhe himself strongly .shared, that the Navy could preventthe Turkish army from crossing into ^uropn ev-n acrossthe Posphorus.   The original plan had been to seize allthe available transport in the Straits.    Admiral Tyrwhittwas to have b^enin charge of this operation, and had beencoiafid -nt that, from a purely naval point of view, he couldcarry it out,   Political objections had been mad- to this plan owing to th&quot;* economic depend^noof Constantinopleon its communications with Asia, but, as a purely navaloperation, it was feasib1e.The- Chie-P of the Imperial Gen-ral-Staff advised thatthe. approaches by which the Turkish army could advance onlev-id could b e made v-ry difficult by the Haw,Admiral Koves supported this.
UrgentSuccessive demands made by Angora Government or byKemalist representative at Constantinople for evacuation ofallied military and naval forces, Turkish control of police and gendarmerie in capital, closing of Mixed Court, andassumption of complete fiscal and financial independence,have produced a state of affairs in which allies have todecide whether to resist these pretensions, whioh are indirect violation both Of Mudros armistice and of Mud-amiiaconvention,  or to abdicate their position.      The formeralternative may lead to crisis in Constantinople vhich,if firmly dealt with, would probably subside.      The latter would involve final destruction of allied prestige and earlywithdrawal.of allied foroes under conditions of no smallhumiliation.The High Commissioners and the Allied generals appearto be acting in closest co-operation, and have addressedidentical appeal for support to their respective Governments.It seems to His Ma.majesty&apos;s Government that this -should nowbe given.     We have been willing to make every possibleconcession to the Angora demands, including the return oftheir civil administration and gendarmerie to Chanak,Gallipoli, and Ismid areas, subject to allied supervision and control In those areas.     We were about to enter lausanne conference with warmest desire for a fair and reasonablesatisfaction of Turkish claims.      It is also possible thatAPPENDIX IVTelegram (by telephone) to Lord Hardinge,- (Paris),Foreign Office, November 7th, 1922, 6.0 p,m,No0414
their larger demands may contain a considerable element ofbluff and may mask a design to drive wedge between alliesor to test the measure of allied unit]/.In any event it seems to us-that the case has now arisen to demonstrate that unity, and, in M.PoincartfTs ownwords, quotes  in your telegram No.564,  that it is absolutely essential  for His Majesty&apos;s Government and the&apos;   French Govern-ment to preserve a united front on all questions that may arise out of the insupportable demands and attitude of theTurks.The immediate crisis is at Constantinople, wherewithdrawal of allied troops mould produce grave panic andmight lead to a repetition of deplorable scenes at Smyrna.The High Commissioners ire unanimouslv of opinion thatestablishment of a state of siege in city is necessary, andhave reported to their Governments that,  if this suggestionbe not approved, they arc no longer in a position to carryon task assigned to them,I shall be glad if you will see M.Poinoard at once,and ask if we may expect support of French Governmentfor action of allied representatives at Constantinople,If once it is realised that allies are absolutely united,and that there is no Question of division between them orof isolated action by any one of their number, and further that present Turkish attitude may render peace conferenceimpossible,  situation may still be saved.      The case is oneof extreme urgency,y&apos;o have received a telegram from General Harringtonin which he requests immediate sanction for measures tobe taken in accordance with advice of allied generalsand High Commissioners.IVe cannot give this authority until we know to what-
extent we may rely upon, the go- opera. ion of   Pre noliGovernment.Repeated to Homo No.257 in &quot;R&quot;,  substituting in lastline &quot;Italian Government&quot; for &quot;French Government&quot;,Code telegram to Sir R.Graham (Rome).Foreign Office, 7th November,1922,  9.0 p.m.No.356 (R).Urgen teParis telegram No.414 repeated to you to-day,Please make similar communication mutatis mutandis to signor Mussolini and ask. whether His Majesty&apos;s government can count on support of Italian Government&apos;.
- APPENDIX     Y.Telegram (137/ telephone) from Paris.Received 8*40 p.m*     November 7th. 192E.Bo. 570.Your Lordshipls telephone message of this evening.I have seen M. Poincare who told me that he had this morning approved General Pellet action for 00-operation with his colleagues at Constantinople and had authorised the proclamation of a state of siege If he andhis colleagues oonsider such a step necessary.As regards the last sentence in the message whichI have received, M. Poincare reserves his view on theground that it is premature to consider measures to betaken if the state of siege should prove insufficient toestablish and maintain order,M. Poincara wished me to tell Your Lordship thathe considers any delay in the meeting of the conferencemost dangerous and he is so apprehensive of the resultthat may ensue that he refuses to assume in any way the  &quot;-responsibility.     He told me that he has written me a notowhich I shall receive shortly, explaining his reasons.    Ishall not fail to forward it by telephone or tslegrara assoon as possible.   . He says that any delay would produoe acatastrophe.
AppendixviOode telegram to Sir H. Sombold,  (Constantinople),.Foreign Office, November 7th. 1922. 10.0 p.m.No, 547.      (R). &apos;Most Urgent.Your telegram No * 668,Your proposals approved.We learn from Paris that French Governmenthas already telegraphed instructions to the same effect.
With the Compliments ofthe Chief of the imperial General Staff
Paraphras eSECREHProm - General Harington, ConstantinopleTo - lar office2933    cipher 7th November 1922C.H.H.124     rersonal for C.I.G.S.You will have seen my 2925 and 2932 of today and my 2922of yesterday.    Kemalist attitude is quite impossible there is nodoubt, and Cabinet will have to make a decision as to whether to deal with it severely or completely surrender.      I thinkstrong and immediate action would be  successful but until I knowwhether I am free to let, Ismid and Chanak go I  cannot embark onthis .      Have always been chary of getting embroiled in this   ...town where we have three battalions of Guards and no guns, but their preposterous demands make retirement well nigh)5 impossible.At any rate they have succeeded in absolutely uniting the Allies.If we act quickly I think we can stop it, and whall be readyto do  so when I get your reply.      What their.object is I cannotconceive,  except that they want to get money as they have ruinedtheir chances for peace conference.Demonstrations have been prohibited and town is quiet tonightbut inhabitants are frightened.

</content>
</cab>
