<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/2/14 images: 202-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^jvvMmrWT IS THE PROPERTY Cf (59)  65.P HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY 1 S GOVERNMENT*COPY NO,13WAR    CABINET.APPLICATION ON PRICE INCREASES TO EXISTINGCOLLIERY CONTRACTS.Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.A difficulty has arisen over the decision of the WarCabinet authorising the Minister for Mines to permit a risein pithead coal prices to cover the increase in miners&apos; wagesA great deal of the coal sold for internal consumption in thicountry is sold under long term contracts which contain nobreak clause,  and in the case of this coal, the collierieswould be unable to take advantage of the permitted rise in coal prices until the existing contracts run out - in manycases not until next Spring or Summer.      The increase inminers&apos; wages takes effect from 1st November.This difficulty was considered on the 50th October bythe Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy, which decidedthat it gave rise to a general question of such importancthat it should be remitted to the War Cabinet.I circulate herewith a Memorandum, prepared by thePresident of the B ard of Trade in consultation with theSecretary for Mines, which sets out the alternative courses which are possible in the circumstances.J. S *Treasury Chambers, S.W.l031st October, 1959,

-1-GOAL.Application of Price Increases to existingcolliery contracts.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.1. The &quot;War Cabinet has already dealt with the increase inminers&apos; wages and has authorised the Secretary for Mines topermit a rise in coal prices to cover the increase granted.Ar.M. (39) 52nd Conclusions, Minute 9).   A new difficulty,however, has arisen.    It has heen found, as a result of the representations o^f the Mining Association that no less than 40per cent, of coal sold for internal consumption in this countryis sold for months    ahead without any form of &quot;break&quot; clause,and that therefore, as far as this coal is concerned,  the collieries would be unable to take advantage of the permitted&quot;rise in coal prices until some time next spring or summer.Meanwhile, of course,  the increase in miners&apos; wages will havetaken   effect from the 1st November.2. In order to enable this increase in miners1 wages to bemade hy the collieries as a whole, there appear to be only two alternatives, neither of them pleasant.3, One is to allow a rise in coal prices on that coal whichis free from contract, to he hig enough to cover the estimatedcost of increased wages over the coal industry as a whole.    Theeffect of this would obviously be nearly to double the permittedincrease in the cost of those collieries who were free toincrease the price.    In order to enable the collieries who arenot free to increase the price to cover themselves, it would beinecessary to pool receipts - a new measure which could certainlyonly he done hy regulation and might, in fact, need    (X^^.affirmative resolution by &quot;both Houses of Parliament.    It willbe realised that as a result of this procedure when a consumevbuys under a contract with a &quot;break&quot; clause he will be payingnot only an increase in price justified by the increased cost,

of production of the coal he buys, hut an extra amount due to thefact that some other consumer, perhaps a competitor of his,  isstill able to get his coal at the pre-war contract price.    Itwould, I think, he found extremely hard to justify procedure ofthis sort.4. The other alternative, however, is hardly less unpalatable.It is hy regulation,  despite existing contracts, to prohibit thesale of coal at anything less than a permitted price:    in other words, to interfere hy regulation with the contractual rightsof those consumers who have entered into a long-term contract.I need not stress to the War Cabinet how grave a decision thiswould he, not only as far as the coal industry itself isconcerned, hut having regard to the reaction it may have uponsimilar demands for the breaking of pre-war contracts which arebeing made hy other interests.5. Attempts have heen made to see whether it would be possibleto get the consumers who are protected hy a pre-war contractwithout a &quot;break&quot; clause to agree to some voluntary increase,but it has heen made quite clear, as a result of discussions,that no progress can be made on these lines.6,   &quot;We have, therefore, to choose between these two alternatives;and recognising the disadvantages that both of them have, I have come with reluctance to the view that the. second alternative -that of prohibiting sale below a permitted price - is thepreferable of the two.7.   In any case, I should not advise that this regulation should extend to coal sold either for export or for foreign bunkers.O.F.G.S.Board of Trade,31st October, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
