<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/260/0 images: 545-548</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP SECRET, CP. 51(36),HIS HRITAHKIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENT) &apos;iCOPY NO.                     CABINET            COMMITTEE ON CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCE,.                       REP 0 R T               The Cabinet at their meeting on 17th february,  1936        (Cabinet  7(36)   Conclusion 2) appointed a Ministerial        Committees under the Chairmanship of the Prime Ministers        with the folio-wing Terms of Reference               &quot;To consider the question of Co-ordination of                  Defence in the light of the Debate in                  Parliament on Fridays 14th February9 19365                  and the Cabinet discussions and report                  their conclusions0u               The attached Report of the Committee is cir-        culated to the Cabinet by direction of the prime Minister.                              (Signed)  M.P.A.  HANKSYo                               Secretary to the Cabinet,,2 9 Y/hitehall Gardens s 3.1.1.5    20th February5  19360
ej noO V t)                          CO-ORDINATION OF DSPgNCE,jnciples.           1.   The following principles are fundamental:-                     (l) The Prime Minister must he responsible for             directing the Co-Ordination of Defence.     This is essential             in time cf war and he must therefore have the opportunity             to study defensive problems first-hand  in time of peace.                     (2) The responsibility of the Service Ministers             must be maintained.                     (3) There must be a clear definition of             responsibility among all concerned. Prime            2.   At the present time the Prime Minister finds it stei?:.             impossible to undertake all the duties  of Go-Ordination             of Defence for the following reasons:-                          (a) the heavy all-round pressure of work;                          (b) the increase in the work of Defence                              Co-Ordination due to the heavy                              programmes for re-conditioning the Forces,                              increased in recent months by the Italo-                              Abyssinian crisis.                 3.   To meet the above situation, the  following             measures should be adopted:                     (l) The Prime Minister should retain the Chairman-             ship of the Committee of Imperial Defence and of the             Ministerial Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Require-             ments.                     (2) A Deputy Chairman of the Committee of Imperial             Defence should be appointed to whom the Prime Minister             proposes to delegate the following duties:-                          (i) the general day-to-day supervision and                              control on the Prime Minister&apos;s behalf                              of the whole organisation and activity                              of the Committee of Imperial Defence:                              the co-ordination of executive action and                              of monthly progress reports to the Defence                              Policy &amp; Requirements Committee on the                              execution of the re-conditioning                                - 1 -
pr-ogrammess  discernment of any points which either have not been taken up or arebeing pursued too slowly and (inconsultation with the Prime Minister or other ministers or Committees as required) of appropriate measures--for their rectification:in the Prime Minister&apos;s absence taking the chair at the Committee of Imperial defence and the Defence Policy and RequirementsCommit tee personal consultation with the Chiefs ofStaff together9 whenever be or they thinkit desirablesthe Chairmanship of the principal supply officers Committeesmaking recommendations as to any improve-ments that he thinks necessary in theorganisation of the Committee of ImperialDefence .Position        4o     The position of the Chiefs of Staffof CCS.Sub-Commit tee.   Committee -would &quot;be as follows - the individuals                composing it have a double function: each advises                his own political chiefs and acting together                the Committee preserves unimpaired the right to                submit confidential reports of their collective                military view to the Deputy Chairman of the                Committee of Imperial Defence.   It is not                proposed that meetingsof the Chiefs of Staff                Committee should normally take place under the                Presidency of the Deputy Chairman.   He would                supplement the present activities and initiative                of the Chiefs of Staff Committee by guidance                and initiative of his own.   His function should                be to ensure that every aspect is fully con-                sidered and that difficulties and differences                are frankly faced.( iii) (iv)  (v)
gtaff          5.      The following will he &quot;the organisation of organisation.               the Joint Planning Committee:-                    (a)  The present Joint Planning Committee                          will continue to function,  hut will                          he supplemented, hy  three officers                          drawn respectively  from the Navy,                          Army and Air Force,  who will be                          graduates of the Imperial Defence                          College.                    (b)  The three new officers will rank as                          junior to the present Directors of                          Plans/&quot;and will occupy that position                          in their respective Departments.                          Their main work will, however, he in                          connection with the Joint Planning                          Committee and their work in their own                          Departments will be chiefly in obtaining                          the necessary material for the preparation                          of Joint Plans. They will work under                          the Directors of Plans on reports to                          the Chiefs of Staff Committee.                         In addition the Joint Planning Committee                          will he provided with a whole-time                          Secretary.C.I.D.           6.      The above measures will he supplemented bySecretariat.                the following steps already approved:                     (a) the appointment of a Deputy Secretary to                            the Committee of Imperial -Defence:                     (b) the appointment of an additional officer                            to the Secretariat of the  Committee of                            Imperial Defence to act as  a whole-time                            Secretary to the new Joint  Planning                            Organisation (vide  5(h)  above).                7.      Appropriate measures to he taken in connection                with the forthcoming parliamentary debates to announce                the above measures of re-organisation  and to rebut                the mis-statements and injustices regarding the                existing organisation and its achievements.                  * i.e. Director of Plans in the Admiralty                    and analogous officers in the War Office                    and Air Ministry.80th February,  1936.

</content>
</cab>
