<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/260/0 images: 562-603</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1936.SECRET.                                                         Copy No.CP. 53  (36).CABINET.DISPUTE BETWEEN ITALY  AND ABYSSINIA.                               OIL SANCTION.         Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    THE Committee of Eighteen adopted a Proposal on the 6th November, 1935(Proposal IVA) that the existing embargo should be extended to cover petroleum and its derivatives, by-products and residues (among other articles)  as soon asthe conditions necessary to render this extension effective had been realised.    On the 22nd January, 1936, the Committee of Eighteen adopted a resolutioncreating a Committee of Experts to conduct a technical examination of theconditions  governing  the  trade in  and  transport  of  petroleum  and  itsderivatives, by-products and residues with a view to submitting an early reportto the  Committee of Eighteen on the effectiveness of the extension of measuresof embargo to these commodities.  This resolution was subject to proposals whichthe Committee of Eighteen might see fit to submit on the question to the politicaldecision of Governments.    The Committee of Experts met at Geneva  from the 3rd February to the12th February  under  the presidency of M. Gomez  (Mexico).  It wras composedof experts designated by the  United  Kingdom,  France,  Iran,  Iraq,  Mexico,Netherlands,  Norway, Peru, Roumania,  Sweden and  U.S.S.R.  The expertsappointed by His Majesty&apos;s  Government in the United Kingdom were Mr.  F. C.Starling, head  of  the Petroleum Department, and  Mr.  N. A.  Guttery of the mercantile Marine Department  of the Board of Trade.    The Committee&apos;s  report is annexed hereto.  It is being sent by the Presidentof the  Co-ordination Committee to all States represented thereon.  Those Statesrepresented on  the Committee  of Eighteen  have been asked by the president to suggest a date for the meeting of that Committee to consider the  report, andthe Committee has  been convoked for the 2nd March.    The Expert Committee&apos;s  report shows  that  if an embargo on oil  wereuniversally applied now, Italy&apos;s stocks of oil would suffice at the present rate of consumption for three to three and a half months.   (Point 1 of the Committee&apos;sfindings.) It also  shows that  if the United States of America were  to  limit their exports of oil to Italy to  the normal level of its exports prior to 1935, an embargo imposed by all League States  would be effective.   (Point  2.)  On theother hand, the only effect an embargo by States Members of the Co-co-ordination committee alone could have on  Italy would be to render the  purchase of oil by her more difficult and expensive.  (Point 3.)  (The  Committee&apos;s conclusion onthis point is not very clearly worded; but it is understood to mean that a purebyLeague embargo might have this effect, but certainly could have no other.)  the effectiveness of an  embargo on  the transport of oil (which, of course, would bepointless if the  United States were to co-operate by limiting their exports) wouldbe subject to the same  limitations.  (Point 5.)    It is thus  quite  clear that the effectiveness of an embargo turns on the readiness or otherwise of the United States of America to co-operate by a definite       T127831
limitation of their exports of oil to Italy at least to the normal pre-1935 level.The possibility suggested in Point 3 of the Committee&apos;s findings, that an embargoimposed by  States Members of the Co-ordination Committee alone might renderItaly&apos;s purchases of oil more  difficult and expensive, could not reasonably be held to be sufficient ground in itself for a decision to impose such an embargo, thoughits imposition on this ground will no doubt be advocated in some quarters inthis country.  The Experts Committee did not include  in its study the whole ofthe effects, financial, economic and other, which an embargo might have were it not to prove watertight.  Indeed, it would have been impossible for the Committeeto estimate the extent of additional difficulty and expense which a purely Leagueembargo would occasion to Italy.  The fact that Italy&apos;s only source of oil was theUnited States of America might have some effect on the price.  In view, however,of the enormous production of oil in the United States and of the large numberof companies which would be likely to  compete for any orders, it is understood tohave been the view of some members of the Committee that  Italy would be able tocover her oil requirements at a reasonable price.   Italy&apos;s difficulties would be enhanced by the fact that all  her oil would have to be shipped across the Atlanticinstead of being  drawn  from sources nearer  at hand.  Were an embargo  on transport to be added to a League embargo on oil, Italy would need, at her present rate of consumption,  some 225.000 gross  tons of foreign shipping in addition toher own tanker fleet.   It seems probable  that she would have to pay increasinglyhigh charter rates for such extra tonnage, but it is impossible to estimate the extra-cost that would be involved.     It appears, therefore, from the Experts&apos; Report      (1) that without co-operation on the part  of  the United States of America           an embargo on oil would not be effective;  and     (2) that the possibility of a purely League  embargo on oil and on transport           having  a  measurable  economic and financial effect on  Italy is not           sufficiently definite  to make it the sole basis of a decision to  impose           such an embargo.     On the  other hand, in my opinion, recent events in Abyssinia, the possibilityof further Italian successes  and the  consequent possibility of Abyssinian dis-integration  have  introduced important  new elements  into  the situation.   Myimpressions in this respect have necessarily been strengthened by the receipt inthe Foreign Office on  the 21st February of a  most secret message, intended for communication to The King,  dictated by  the Emperor of Abyssinia  to the british military Attache at  Dessie on the 19th  February.  I  must call my colleagues&apos;-attention to the  very  secret  nature of this &quot; communication.&quot;    The message,which was dictated in English, is not  wholly intelligible.  But its  main  purportis unmistakeably (a) that not enough has been done to help Abyssinia, particularly by the  United Kingdom, which  is referred to as the &apos;&apos; main defender of the abyssinian  cause,&quot; (b) that  the rejection of the Hoare-Laval proposals on thebasis of their injustice both by the  Ethiopian and by His Majesty&apos;s Governmentshowed an essential community of view,  and (c) that Great Britain should now,in order to avoid further bloodshed and  to justify the regime of &quot; internationallaw which she has always championed,&quot; bring Italy and Abyssinia to conclude an armistice and enter into negotiations.     This last proposal  is  explained by  the Emperor  on  the  ground  that signor Mussolini has already approached  the  Abyssinian Government with aview to initiating direct peace negotiations.  Information  which I have receivedfrom other sources leads me to think that this may be a  reference to the activitiesof the notorious Mr. Rickett, who has recently been in Rome and has since then beenin written communication with Mr. Colson, the American Financial Adviser tothe  Abyssinian  Government.  So far as  I know, nothing like a concrete schemeof  settlement has  emerged,  or could  perhaps  be  expected  to  emerge,  but theEmperor has undertaken in his message to let us know on receipt of our reply what proposals have been made should we desire the information.     The Emperor&apos;s message  closes  with an expression of His Majesty&apos;s viewthat the best hope for Abyssinia is  &quot;to tie it  to  England either in the  form ofa protectorate or in the form of a mandate without touching our independence.&quot;     However  embarrassing and  impracticable  this message may  be  in  certain respects, it undoubtedly constitutes an urgent appeal for help and is in  striking-contrast with the Emperor&apos;s earlier attitude against any negotiation so long as
Italian troops remained on Abyssinian territory.   The receipt of  this messagereinforces my conviction that so long as the Italian adventure appeared hopelessthere was a &quot;strong case for letting  the  present sanctions  have their effect,  eventhough its realisation might be slow, and for not aggravating relations betweensanctionist countries and Italy by taking further measures against her.   In thecircumstances, however, that are likely  to obtain at the moment of the meetingof the Committee of Eighteen, I feel&apos; strongly that inaction by the  Committeewould be  politically disastrous.  Not only would it be regarded as  a success forSignor Mussolini, but as a confession of impotence on  the part of the League.I have come to the conclusion,  therefore, that His  Majesty&apos;s Government  should at the forthcoming meeting of the  Committee of Eighteen make  it clear  thatthey are  willing to participate  in  an  embargo on the export of oil to Italyand  in a  prohibition of the transport  of  oil to Italy in  British tankers if theother members  of the  Committee are ready  to  do  likewise.     It might be argued that action  by the League which consisted merely in theapplication of sanctions which are known in present conditions to  be ineffectivewould not assist in maintaining its prestige and authority.  The following points should, however, be taken into consideration on the other side :       (1) The oil sanction has acquired a symbolic significance both in  Italy and           throughout  the rest of the world.  Failure to  apply it would  have a           psychological effect quite independent of its practical results.     (2) The imposition of an  oil sanction by the  League Powers would  be the           strongest possible form of pressure on the United States of America           to limit their exports of oil.   It would also be the best means of           restoring in the United States that respect for  the authority and           integrity of  the League, which was badly damaged by the  Hoare-           Laval proposals.    If we  take the long view this  is an important           consideration.     (3) If the Committee of Eighteen decides not to impose the oil and transport           sanction, criticism of its inaction will undoubtedly  be  based  on           Point 3 of the findings of the Experts Committee despite the fact that,           as shown above, such criticism would be of doubtful validity.     (4) Any action  by the  League   Powers  which  tended  to  show their           determination  to  carry  out their  policy  would  not  only  have  a           salutary psychological effect  in Italy,  but would in itself strengthen           that determination.     (5) It is possible that the Committee of Eighteen may think it necessary           to consider the reinforcement of the admittedly ineffective oil sanction           by some measures in regard to shipping.     There is a possible alternative course to which I feel it my duty to draw mycolleagues&apos; attention.   This would consist in an announcement by the Committeeof Eighteen that  the  ineffectiveness of the  oil sanction in present conditionsprecludes its imposition, but that the Committee is compelled  to proceed to theconsideration of other measures  calculated to bring hostilities to an end againstthe eventuality of the parties failing to  take advantage of the approaching rainyseason (with its probable cessation of  military activity) for  purposes  of  con-ciliation.   It could be allowed to transpire in the course of  the discussions inthe Committee that such methods might  comprise the laying down of terms whichshould be accepted by both parties within a given period.  Failing acceptance by italy, drastic action, such as a shipping sanction,  would be taken against Italy,or in the case of Abyssinian  recalcitrance, all  sanctions against Italy would beraised.  The claim of  the League to have the first and the last word in the fixing of the terms of peace  would be something of a novelty  and would require to bejustified by the argument that the States which have now been imposing sanctionsfor over three months are entitled to an overriding  say in the determination of conditions of peace.  But any drastic action by the League Powers against italy would, of course, greatly increase the risk of the war spreading to Europe,  andwould therefore need very careful consideration.  For this  purpose the Committeeof Eighteen might set up a Sub-Committee charged with the study of such other measures as would  bring hostilities to an end.     It is impossible to forecast with any accuracy what wall be the feeling of theCommittee of Eighteen when it meets.   But  it is not considered likely that therewill be any  great  enthusiasm for the  imposition  of an oil sanction in  present
circumstances.   Nevertheless, I think that the representative of His Majesty&apos;s-Government  should make  it  clear  that  the  United Kingdom  is willing  toparticipate in an embargo on the export of oil and on the transport of oil to italy in British tankers provided that the other members of the Committee are readyto do likewise.   In view of the possibility that the Committee may  think itdesirable  to reinforce the oil and tanker sanction with some measures in regardto shipping, it would be desirable that the competent department of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should immediately study the possibility of :     (1) prohibiting the bunkering  of Italian ships in League ports,     (2) prohibiting League shipping from visiting Italian ports,  and     (3) prohibiting the use of League ports by Italian shipping.     In the event of it being impossible to  reach agreement  in  the Committee&apos;of Eighteen on the  imposition of the oil and tanker sanctions, the representativeof His Majesty&apos;s Government should,  I think, have authority to agree  to  thealternative course set forth above,  namely, to join in an announcement  that  theineffectiveness of the oil sanction in present circumstances precludes its imposition,but that if the parties to the dispute fail  to take advantage of the approachingrainy season for purposes of conciliation, the Committee will be  compelled to resort to other methods of restoring peace,  and that the study of other alternative methods will be begun immediately.                                                                     A. E.     Foreign  Office,  February 22,  1936.
Dispute  between  Ethiopia  and  Italy      Co-ordination of Measures under Article 16 of the              Covenant of the League of Nations       Report of the Committee of Experts                          regarding   Petroleum and.  its  Derivatives,  By-products                      and Residues                 Geneva, February 12,  1936Presented by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs    io Parliament by Command of His Majesty                         LONDON  PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY MIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICETo be purchased directly from II.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses:    Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2;         York Street, Manchester 1;  1 St. Andre\v&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;                  80 Chichester Street, Belfast;                   or through any Bookseller                          1936                       Price yd. NetEthiopia No.  3 (1936)
CONTENTS.                                                        PageReport      ..      ....     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...   annex 1. Supply and Consumption   ...     ...     ...   8Annex 2. Substitutes    ...     ...     ...     ...         17Annex 3. Transport      ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  21Appendix   I. Imports of Petroleum into Italy, 1931-34  30Appendix  II. Imports of Petroleum into Italy, 1935...  34Appendix III. World Production of Petroleum     ...  37Appendix IV.-World Oil-Tanker Fleet.........  38
DISPUTE   BETWEEN  ETHIOPIA  AND   ITALY.CO-ORDINATION  OF MEASURES  UNDER  ARTICLE 16 OF  THE         COVENANT OF THE LEAGUE OF  NATIONS.               CO-ORDINATION  COMMITTEE.Report of the Committee  of Experts for the Technical Examination  of  the Conditions governing the  Trade  in  and  Transport of  Petroleum and ils Derivatives, By-Products and Residues.Geneva, February 12, 1986.                              I.  AT  its last  meeting on  the 22nd  January, the  Committee  of eighteen adopted the following resolution :      &quot; The Committee of Eighteen,     &quot; Recalling its Proposal IV A, of the 6th November, 1935,  to  the effect that measures of embargo  should be extended to certain  articles  as  soon  as the  conditions  necessary  to render  this  extension effective had been realised;     &apos;-&apos; Subject to the proposals which it may see fit to submit on  this question to the political decision of Governments :     &quot; Decides to create  a Committee of Experts  to  conduct a  technical examination of the conditions governing the  trade  in  and transport of petroleum and  its  derivatives, by-products and  residues, with  a view  to submitting an  early  report to the  Committee of Eighteen  on the effectiveness of the extension  of  measures of  embargo to the above-mentioned commodities;     &quot; Bequests its  President  to  invite certain  Governments  to  appoint experts to serve  on a Committee for this purpose.&quot;  In accordance with the terms of  this resolution, the President  ofthe Co-ordination Committee requested  certain  Governments to sendexperts to meet in Geneva  on the 3rd  February.  The  Committee,which met under the chairmanship of M. Gomez (Mexico) from the3rd February  to  the  12th  February, was  composed   of  expertsdesignated by the Governments of the United Kingdom, France, Iran,Iraq, Mexico, Netherlands,  Norway,  Peru, Eoumania, Sweden andthe Union of Soviet  Socialist republics.   The Venezuelan Govern-ment sent an observer.  At the  opening meeting,  the President  of the  Co-co-ordination committee submitted a list of questions to the experts, which, after certain minor modifications,  was adopted by them  as  their agenda.the President emphasised  the fact that the Committee of Eighteen
 desired at this  stage to submit to  a  technical examination only, the whole problem of the  effectiveness  of an- embargo on petroleum products,  and  the present  report is  strictly  confined to  such a technical examination.   By the term  &quot; effective,&quot; the Committee has understood the influence which this  embargo might have on Italy&apos; power to cover  the whole or the greater part of  her oil requirements. It has  not deemed it to be its function to include in its study the whole of the effects financial, economic and other that the embargo might have, even were it not to prove completely watertight.    Before setting  out the results of its work, the Committee wishes to emphasise at the  outset that the facts and the opinions  set forth below relate to the situation as it exists to-day or existed in the earlier years to which  consideration  is given, and that  they must not there- fore  be treated as applying to  the  future,  if, in the future,  there is any substantial change in general conditions.    In order to distribute its work,  the Committee appointed  three- Sub-Committees to study        (a) The  general problem of  consumption and supplies.       (b) The  possible use of substitutes.       (c) The  question of  transport.                                II.    After an examination  of the  reports  of  its  Sub-Committees, which  it  approved  after  discussion,  the  Committee  formed  the following opinions                              (a) Imports.    The total supplies  of petroleum and petroleum products  to Italy in the years 1932  to 1934, excluding bunker oil purchases by Italian ships in foreign ports for current needs, amounted on an average to approximately 2\ million tons per annum,  of which rather more than If million  tons were fuel oil.    These purchases have  increased  steadily from a total  of  about; 2 million tons  in  1931  to nearly 3 million tons in 1934, a  tendency j to  be found in other  principal consuming countries.   There was further increase in 1935, when it is believed that purchases may have j amounted to about 3-8 million tons.    Of the increase of  800,000 tons,  it will-be  seen from section (c)l below  that some  300,000 tons (i.e.,  about  40 per  cent, of  the I increase) is estimated to have been added to stock.                         (b) Consumption.   There are no reasons for supposing that Italy was  accumulatingabnormal stocks of petroleum prior to 1935.  It is probable  therefore that  her consumption of petroleum products up  to the end of  1934was  approximately equal  to her  total purchases.   Italy:s normal                         (&apos;)  Annexes 1, 2, 3.
tlyantoanait;cy!awer&apos;;(cileiDonsumption in recent years  had increased at  the rate of about13  per  cent,  per  annum.  Assuming  that  a  similar increase hastaken place in 1985 and  allowing for some  increase in Italian  con-sumption due  to greater industrial and military activity, consumption in that  year would have amounted to 8-5 million tons.  This figure includes the consumption in the theatre of war estimated to amountduring  the  last five months of the  year to a figure of 20,000  to30,000 tons per month.                          (c) Stocks.   The  total stock at  the end of  1934 probably  averaged about six weeks&apos; to two months&apos;  supply, or 400,000 to 500,000 tons.  If to this be  added  the  difference  between the purchases and estimated  con-sumption in 1935, amounting to 300,000 tons,  a  total of  700,000  to800,000 tons on the 31st  December, 1935, is obtained.   Stocks  mayhave increased during January 1936  by a further 50,000 tons,  and,it the end of January, may, therefore, have been equivalent to some two and a half to three months&apos; consumption.   If an embargo were imposed, there would be at the moment  ofits  imposition certain  supplies en route, representing about half amonth&apos;s supply to  be added to the stocks already in  hand.                     (d) Sources of Supply.   The  most  important  sources  from  which world markets  derivetheir supplies of petroleum are Colombia, Iran,  Iraq, Mexico, theNetherlands Bast  Indies, Peru, Boumania,  Trinidad, the  UnitedStates of  America,  the  Union of  Soviet Socialist  republics,  andVenezuela.  All these countries, with  the exception of  the  UnitedStates of  America, are themselves  Members of, or are territoriesbelonging to, Members of  the Co-ordination Committee.   The  largest exporters of oil are Venezuela and the United  Statesof America.  The  former  reports no direct exports to Italy.   Substantial quantities  of  Venezuelan crude  oil are  normallyrefined  in  the Netherlands West Indies  and refined  products aresported from these islands to Italy.  From the figures at the disposal of  the Committee,(2) it is clearthat the quantity of oil products available for export  from the UnitedStates of  America greatly  exceeds  Italy&apos;s probable demands.   Inpast years  relatively  small quantities of  oil  products  have  beenexported from the United States to Italy.  In the period 1931 to 1934,the  average percentage  of Italy&apos;s total  supplies provided by theUnited States were as  follows : Crude oil ...Petrol.....KeroseneFuel oil lubricating oilTotal.....14-9 9-4 5-2 3-548-3 6-6[12784](2) See Annex 1.B 2
    During  the last few  months,  these  exports have shown a very large  increase.  It is not  known whether the  recent  increase in exports will be maintained or whether any form of limitation will, in fact, be instituted.    In the case of an effective limitation being imposed, it would make but little difference to the effectiveness of an embargo imposed by States Members  of the Co-ordination Committee whether that limitation took the form of an absolute embargo or the reduction of exports to the normal level  of the United States exports prior to 1935.                          (e)  Substitutes.    Economy in  the  use of  petroleum  products by   the  use of substitutes could most easily be effected in the case of petrol  (motor spirit), for Italy has already had  some experience in the production and use of  such substitutes as alcohol, benzol, &amp;c.   The Committee considers that an economy of the order of 100,000 tons a year might be  possible  by an extension of production of these products in Italy or by increasing imports.  Any increase, however, in the demand for alcohol and benzol for the manufacture of  explosives  would naturally result in a reduction of this figure.    The  Committee has explained  in  Annex 2 the reasons for which it does  not  feel able to  estimate the extent to  which  any further economy might be effected  by the employment  of other sources of power, such  as  the  use  of gas-producer plants   on  motor  vehicles compressed gas or electric power.    As regards Diesel and fuel oils, which form by far the larger part of the oil imports of Italy, the Committee does not consider  that any appreciable  proportion of these oils could be replaced by substitutes Some  substitution of coal for oil might be practicable provided Italy can import larger quantities of coal.    As regards lubricating oils, it  would be possible to replace them to a limited  extent by oils of vegetable or animal  origin.    In view  of the possibility of obtaining by importation substitutes for petrol, the  Committee  is of the  opinion that if an  embargo is imposed on  petroleum and petroleum  products,  it  should  be extended to cover industrial alcohol and benzol.                           (f) Transport.    The Committee estimates  that  if Italy&apos;s supplies of oil had to bedrawn from  ports in the Gulf of Mexico, the Italian fleet might beexpected to  carry not less than  If  million tons (i.e.,  one-half oiItaly&apos;s consumption in 1935), or possibly as much as 2 million tons As  stated above, the present consumption is estimated at the rate ol about  3^ million tons per annum.   If  no economies in use were affected, therefore, Italy  would require somewhat over 225,000 tons gross of foreign shipping for her transport services.    Were an  embargo on  transport to  be  imposed by the  Members of the   Co-ordination Committee, there  would remain for this  purposevessels belonging to  the tanker  fleets  of the  United  States  and
Germany.  The German tanker fleet that is  suitable for transatlanticvoyages and from which vessels might be obtained for transportation(o Italy would appear to amount to about 90,000 gross tons, and thatof the  United States which is not engaged in the coastwise trade to between 300,000 and 500,000 gross tons according to the season ofthe  year.  If tankers  forming part of these two fleets were to be  diverted tothe  Italian trade, there  would be nothing,  so far as the Committee isaware,  to  prevent  the  owners  of  such vessels from replacing - thetonnage so diverted by tankers chartered from other States Members;of the  Co-ordination Committee.   Tankers of these other  States now engaged in the carriage  of oil to Italy would  become available for thispurpose.   Moreover, there  are at present some 340,000 gross tons of tankers laid up, half of which might be brought into commission, andsome 435,000 gross tons of tankers under  construction.  For an embargo  on transport  of  oil to Italy  to be  effective,measures of control would,  therefore, require to be taken by countriesnot  members  of the League of Nations.  On the other hand, evenwithout such measures  of control,  the  carriage of oil to Italy wouldbe rendered more  difficult  and more expensive were  an embargo ontransports by Member States to be imposed.  The Committee has  given consideration  to  the question  of  thepossible  form  of  such  an  embargo.   In   its  opinion,   the mostpracticable form would  be one which combined  (a) a  prohibitionagainst the sale of  tankers to States not applying the embargo, and(i) notwithstanding the special legal difficulties which might arise incertain  cases  in  connection  with  tankers  already  chartered,  a prohibition against the proceeding of tankers to Italy.  Accordingly :  (1)  The figures given above with reference to consumption,  tostocks  and to supplies which might be en route at the moment of theimposition of an embargo on the export of petroleum and petroleum products make it possible to estimate roughly the period which wouldhave to elapse  before such an embargo,  were  it to be  universallyapplied, would become  fully effective.   In the conditions prevailing at the  moment  of its session, the  Committee is of opinion that thisperiod  may be taken to  be about three  to three and  a half months.  (2)  In the event of such an embargo being applied by all states members of the Co-ordination Committee,  it would be effective if theUnited States of America was  to limit its   exports to Italy  to  thenormal level  of  its exports prior to 1935.  (3)  If  such an embargo were applied by the States Members ofthe Co-ordination  Committee alone, the only  effect  which it could have on Italy would be to render  the purchase of petroleum moredifficult and expensive.   (4)  In view  of the possibility of substitutes being used to some extent  for petrol  (motor spirit),   an   embargo  on  the   export  of petroleum  and  petroleum  products would be  strengthened were it ^tended to cover industrial alcohol and benzol.
    (5) The effectiveness of an embargo imposed by  States  Membersof the Co-ordination  Committee on  the transport of oil  to Italy  is subject to the same limitations as an embargo on exports.   Were these states alone to prohibit the use of tankers for the transport of oil toItaly,  it would be able to satisfy its needs  up to about 50  per cent.from its own resources, and  the rest  by means  of  vessels of other states, but with greater difficulty and  at greater expense.    (6) If  an  embargo  on  transport&apos; should be decided  on,  theCommittee is of the opinion that the most practicable form of embargowould be one which  would  prohibit tankers from  proceeding to Italyand would also prohibit the sale of tankers to  States not applying the embargo.    (7) Should  it be  decided  to impose an embargo on  petroleum,attention should be given to the necessity of taking suitable  measuresto prevent traffic by indirect routes, including  use of free ports, whichis of special importance as regards petroleum.ANNEX 1.                     Supply and Consumption.   The Committee  has studied the figures  of the sources of Italianpetroleum supplies and has endeavoured to estimate Italy&apos;s consump-tion in recent years and the stocks held by  her.   Wherever possible,the Committee has  used  statistics for the year 1935,  but in regard tocertain of the matters  dealt with, information  for  1935 is not yet available  and the Committee has then been  obliged to use the figuresfor 1934. (3)                             (a) Imports.   In Appendices I and II(4) are given  tables  showing the Italianimports of  petroleum  and its derivatives  and  the exports of these products  to  Italy from  the countries  from  which  she derives  her supplies.  The Italian import statistics record the entry of goods  into italy  when  they  pass  the  Customs  frontier.   As  considerable quantities of petroleum and its derivatives are purchased by Italy for   (3) The Committee would draw  attention  to the  fact that statistics olpetroleum present  special  difficulties, owing to the  fact that the variouspetroleum products bought, sold and used may  be  of varying degrees ofrefinement.  The total  statistics  of imports  or consumption are,  for  tliireason, open to the objection that they involve the addition of non-identicalunits.  This objection is, however, only  of practical importance when tliproportions in which these various products  contribute to the totals  var;from year to year.   (4) As  Italian  statistics are  not  available  after September  1935, apestimate has been made in Appendix II for the last quarter of the year basaion the tonnage of tankers arriving in  Italian ports.
	Italian import		Corresponding expc		statistics.		statistics.		Average	Year	Average	Year	1932-34.	1934.	1932-34-	1934.Crude ... ... .	135-1	142-9	160-8	221-7Petrol.......	321-4	348-2	345-7	395-4Kerosene	141-8	144-8	193-5	185-7Residual (fuel oil)	. 1,010-2	1,122-5	1,821-0	1,991-7Lubricating oil	66-3	65-7	95-3	137-7Total ...	. 1,674-8	1,824-1	2,616-3	2,932-2Cc) The annual figures were as follows:-19311932193319341935   In tons(000&apos;s omitted).   2,067-7   2,342-0   2,568-1   2,932-2   3,809-4use as bunkers in Italian ports,  for the requirements of the navy, forrefining in the  free ports of Fiume and  Trieste  and, from time  totime,  for storage in  tanks outside  the  Customs area, the  importfigures,  especially for crude petroleum and fuel oil, do not account forthe whole  of Italian  requirements.   It is necessary,  therefore,  toestimate these  requirements   from  the  export  statistics  of othercountries, in so far as they are  available.   It  would appear,  from  the evidence  afforded  by  these exportstatistics, that total purchases in recent years have  amounted, on anaverage, to 2-6  million tons per annum,  of  which 1-8 million hasbeen fuel oil.(.5)   These figures of total purchases do not generally include  bunkeroil purchased by Italian vessels in foreign ports  for current needs,and it is not possible to make an estimate of the amount of the bunkeroil so  bought.   On the  other hand,  any purchases  of bunker oil by foreign vessels are included.  There is no doubt, however, that theseforeign purchases in Italian ports are very substantially  less than thelarge Italian  bunker purchases abroad.   Exports to  Italy have increased  steadily, year  by year,  from atotal of  2 million tons  in 1931 to a total of nearly  3 million  tons  in1934(6)  and about 3&apos;8 million tons in  1935.    As there was.a rapid increase of exports in the autumn of 1935, especially from the United   (5) The export  statistics given  in the appendices refer only to the  ninemost important countries.  For the others, it has been necessary to interpolatethe Italian import statistics, which, for the reasons given above, are certainlytoo low.  The margin of error in the case of the export figures for petroleum, whichis mainly carried in special vessels sailing direct to their  final destination, isprobably not great.  It will be seen from the following figures that by far the major part  of the discrepancy between  Italian  import  statistics and theexport statistics given is  accounted for by fuel oil, which is largely used asbunkers  in seagoing vessels and does not cross the Customs frontier:                                  In metric  tons (000&apos;s  omitted).
States,  and petroleum  shipped from the latter country in Decemberwould not have arrived until after the new year, arrivals in Italy in1935  may have been somewhat perhaps 100,000 tons-less than theexport figures would seem to indicate.                         (b) Consumption.    There are no reasons for supposing that Italy  was accumulatingabnormal stocks  of  petroleum prior to 1935.   Her average workingstocks may have increased with the increase in consumption and theextension of  refineries; but it is probable that her  total consumptionup to the end of 1934 was approximately equal to her total purchases,or only  slightly less.    It is more difficult to estimate her probable consumption in 1935.Purchases increased between  1931 and 1934 by 45 per cent., which is equivalent to approximately  13 per  cent, per annum.   Had this rateof increase been  continued,  the consumption in  1935 would  haveamounted to 3&apos;3  million tons.   There were  certain  factors  whichwould result in an  increase in consumption namely,  the increasedindustrial and  military  activity in Italy itself,  the transport of troops and war material to Italian East Africa, the transhipment of oil from italy  to Italian East Africa.  . Against  these increases have to be  setsome reduction in the consumption of certain oil products, particularlymotor spirit  for  civilian use.   Sufficient data are not available  toenable  the Committee  to assess the value of each of  these factors.The increase in consumption due to the greater industrial and military activity in Italy itself  may  be material; the extra quantity of  fuelrequired  for the use of ships engaged in transport to Italian EastAfrica may not be large, as such oil-burning  ships as  are concerned would formerly have been engaged  in other work.    As regards the total  requirements for Italian East Africa, no official information  is available,  but from  various  particulars  available,including those of the movement of tankers, the  Committee is of theopinion that the consumption of petroleum products  in those territoriesduring  the autumn of 1935 has been of the order of 25,000 to 30,000tons per month, of which probably some 20,000 tons were motor spirit.The quantity of additional  motor spirit required  for use in italian east  Africa may possibly have been  offset by the economies effected inthe use of motor spirit in Italy itself.    Taking all  these factors into consideration,  the Committee thinksit  would not  be  unreasonable to  assume that  Italy&apos;s  aggregateconsumption during the course of the year 1935 may have amounted tosome 3&apos;5 million tons.                             (c) Stocks.    There is  no direct evidence available as to the stocks of petroleum products in Italy at the end  of 1934.  They are, however, not likelyto have exceeded six to  eight weeks&apos; supply or 400,000 to 500,000 tons.    If consumption  during 1935  amounted to 3-5 million tons  and
 imports  as  indicated  to  3-8  million  tons,(7)  the increase  in  stocks effected during the course of  the year would have been 300,000 tons. On the basis of these figures, the total stocks at the end of December last would have amounted to some 700,000 to 800,000 tons.    This  estimate  is not incompatible with the information available concerning Italy&apos;s storage capacity.  The Committee believes that the aggregate capacity of existing storage is about 1 million cubic metres. By a Decree dated the 24th October, 1935, all owners and  lessees  of depots exceeding 500 cubic metres are required to keep stocks of motor spirit and fuel oil equivalent to  70 per cent, of the total capacity  of their  storage  accommodation for these products.   The tonnage  of petroleum and its derivatives which might be held  in  storage tanks of a total-capacity of 1 million cubic metres depends, of course, on the specific gravity of the  products.  In  view of the nature of the known Italian imports, the co-efficient may  perhaps  be taken as 0&apos;85,  which would give a total storage capacity of 850,000 tons; 70 per cent,  of this total storage  capacity would therefore amount to 600,000 tons. A comparison of this figure with  the  estimated total stocks at the end of December last- viz., some 700,000 to  800,000 tons would leave 100,000 to 200,000 tons to be accounted for by storage tanks holding more  than the legal  minimum  required,  by  storage  tanks with  a capacity of under 500 cubic metres, by stocks held in tankers and by stocks held in the open.    The Committee would add that  the present  storage capacity  of Italy could,  of course, be increased during the course of the present year.   Open reservoirs with a limited capacity are not expensive; but normal storage tanks would be appreciably more expensive and would take a considerable time to construct.    On the basis of the records of tankers reaching ports in Italy  and the Italian colonies in  East Africa  during  January 1936, the imports during that month may be estimated at slightly under 350,000 tons, which may have rendered possible a further increase in  stocks during that month of some 50,000 tons.    Thus, on the basis of data not always adequate and of assumptions sometimes conjectural,  the Committee  estimates that  stocks  at  the end of January may have amounted to some  two and a half to three months&apos; supply at the rate of consumption in 1935.  In the case of certain petroleum products, the stocks may suffice for a longer period, and, of others, for a  shorter period than this.   If  an embargo were to be imposed,  supplies in transit to Italian; ports representing perhaps half  a month&apos;s supply would have  to be taken into consideration.                      (d) Sources  of Supply.   In considering  the  available sources  of supply, it may be well to distinguish between the sources from  which Italy has actually derived her supplies in recent  years and  the sources  which might be tapped   j7) This figure may be somewhat too high if, as is suggested above,  (a), avivals in 1935 were lower than exports.
under  changed conditions.  In Appendix  III is given a table  of the petroleum production of the world for the last four years.  It will be observed that the production of the countries mentioned in this tablewhich  are not Members of  the Co-ordination Committee is, with theexception of that of the United States, quite negligible.   In  the following table are  shown the exports,  specified accordingto the  nature of  the product,  of the main sources of supply for theinternational market in the  years 1933 and 1934 : Petroleum:  Exports of chief Sources  of Supply.Metric tons (000&apos;s omitted).    1933.       1934.Venezuela   Crude oil............    16,718  Fuel oil............      733  Gas oil   ......     ...    ...        59  Petrol    ............        46                                      17,556United States of America   Crude oil ............     5,088  Gasoline............     3,214  Kerosene  ...     ...     ...    ...     1,102  Eesidual......     ......     2,707  Lubricating oil  ...     ...    ...     1,081       Total        .........    13,192       Plus  bunker oil  for vessels         engaged  in foreign trade     4,745Iran(8) (1932-33 and  1933-34)-  Fuel oil  .........    ...     2,665  Crude oil............     1,335  Kerosene......     ......      278  Petrol    ......     ...    ...     1,497                                       5,775Netherlands West  Indies : Curagao    and Aruba  (Venezuelan oil) -  Eesidues (gas oil, Diesel,  Mazout)     9,858  Gasoline............     2,216  Kerosene  (petroleum)    ...    ...      278  Crude oil............     1,203  Lubricating oil   ...     ...    ...      10918,780   805    54    4719,686 5,720 2,680 1,208 8,811 1,00114,4204,3983,7411,565  4451,5247,275 Not yet available.13,664(8) Years ending June 22.(9) See footnote (12) on page 14.14,784(9
Metric tons (000&apos;s omitted).	1933.	1934.Roumania 		Crude oil ...	237	274Motor spirit ... ... ...	1,757	1,958Kerosene ... ... ... ...	951	1,085Gas oil	1,036	1,096Fuel and residual oil	1,791	2,021Other ... ... ......	59	62	5,831	6,496Union of Soviet Socialist RepubHes 		Crude oil ...		459Benzine and motor spirit	1,260	1,120Kerosene ...	570	447Gas oil	576	566Fuel oil............	1,534	1,546Lubricating oil ...	240	305Other petroleum products		128	4,894	4,571Netherlands East Indies 		Crude oil ...	248	413Besidual, fuel and Diesel	2,205	2,118Kerosene ...	451	531Benzine and petrol	1,156	1,242	4,060 .	4,304Mexico 		Crude oil ...	1,543	1,600Fuel oil ............	801	940Gas oil ...... ......	210	183Gasoline and kerosene ...	361	456Lubricating oil ...	46	43	2,961	3,222Colombia 		Crude oil ...	1,695	2,351Iraq-(1X)  Crude  oil............        ...         838(10) In 1933 &quot;crude&quot; includes &quot;other  petroleum products.&quot;    Exports began only in August 1934.
Metric tons (000&apos;s omitted).                                      1933.        1934.France-   Crude oil ...     ...    ...     ...        ...           6  Petrol    .........     ...        17           7  Other refined oils      ......        13          16  Eesidual     Gas oil............        44          60    Fuel  oil       .........       115         235    Road oil       .........        30          48  Lubricating oil   ...    ...     ...        19         111Peru   Crude oil ...  Petrol    ......  Kerosene ...  Fuel oil and gas oilPoland   Crude and fuel oil  Petrol    ......  Kerosene &apos;&apos; naphtha &apos;  Lubricating oil  ...238	483992	1,352355	38931	39210	1961,588	1,9764	CO50	5645	3159	62158	15276,357	84,956(12)             Total of the above  countries                (all kinds)   It will be seen from Appendix III that there are thirteen countrieseach of which in 1935 produced over 1 million tons of crude petroleum,Al! except one of these,  which  is the  largest producer  of all, are members of the Co-ordination Committee.  I1 wo of these countries-namely,  the Argentine and  India do not,  in  normal circumstances,export any oil.   The other eleven countries  all export  substantial quantities; five of them -namely, &quot;Venezuela, Iraq, Mexico, Colombiaand  Peru export  mainly  crude oil,  and  the  others Roumania,Union of  Soviet  Socialist  Republics,  Iran,  the Netherlands  east indies and Trinidad mainly export  refined products;  the  UnitedStates of America exports large quantities of both crude and  refined products.  The total exports of these countries was,  in 1934, about   (12)  Including 14,784,000 tons from the Netherlands West Indies, 1934,estimated from the 1934 exports from  Venezuela to Curasao and Aruba inthe ratio  which  the corresponding exports in 1933. bore to the  NetherlandsWest Indies exports in 1933, thus:       Venezuelan exports  to  the Netherlands West Indies:       (1934) 15,718 xl3)664 ^4784       (1933) 14,527
	Crude,.	% Petrol.		% sene	%	Fuel	% cants	%	Total.	%iiBce						39-1	2-0 64-8	47-1	103-9	3-5umania ......	54-2	24-4	84-9	21-5 92-5	49-8	736-1	37-0 5-8	4-2	973-5	33-2lion of Soviet Socialist Eepub-[ts  	6-4	2-9	114-8	29-0 42-9	23-1	631-3	31-7 19-0	13-8	814-4	27-8itherlands East Indies ......			9-9	2-5 ...		7-7	0-4 ...		17-6	0-6.... j.....			136-7	34-6 21-1	11-4	144-1	7-2 ...		301-9	10-3ilombia ... ...	74-1	33-4							74-1	2-5itherlands West ladies (Curacao ndAruba)	25-0	11-3	39-0	9-9 17-0	9-2	355-0	17-8 ...		436-0	14-9lited States of itneriea...	62-0	28-0	7-2	1-8 11-0	5-9	61-9	3-1 44-2	32-1	186-3	6-4iercountries ...			2-9	0-7 1-2	0-6	16-5	0-8 3-9	2-8	24-5	0-8Itountries	221-7 100		395-4 100 185-7		100 1,991-7 100 137-7			100 2,932-2		100   It will be seen from this table that the principal sources of supplywere Eoumania, the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, the Nether-lands West Indies,  Iran and the United States of America,  whichtogether accounted for 92-6  per cent,  of the total.  Although thestatement  does not show any  direct shipments from Venezuela toItaly, the  Italian import statistics include a small quantity.   The  exports  from  the  Netherlands  West  Indies  are  refined products obtained  from  Venezuelan  crude  oil.    The  Committeeconsiders that, as practically the whole  of the output of Venezuelancrude oil is exported for  refining elsewhere,  including about 15 percent, to  20 per cent, to the United States of  America, it is desirableto call special attention to the position of Venezuela.   It may be argued that the imposition of an oil embargo would inany event affect the position of Venezuela, since about 80 per cent.of its production of oil only reaches the  consuming countries  throughthe Netherlands West Indies.   But as already pointed out,  most ofthe remaining 20 per cent, is sent to the United States for  refiningand there is  no reason  why this proportion should not be  increased.Any oil exported to the United States  would  become  subject  to whatever regime might  be applied in the United States to trade with italy in oil products.  There are no technical reasons why Venezuelancrude oil should not be sent direct to Italy for refining.  According toj   66 million tons.   Taking crude oil and refined products together,  theI   United  States  of America  and Venezuela are  by far  the largest1   exporters.      The  sources from which Italy drew her supplies during the year   1934, the quantities being based on the export statistics of the supply-I   ing countries,  are shown in the following table :  .                                    Tons (000&apos;s).                                  Kero-               lubricating-
the information available to the Committee,  the  capacity of Italianrefineries is probably not less than 700,000 tons per annum.   The statement on  p.  12 shows that  the  United States  supplied6-4 per cent, of Italy&apos;s requirements  in 1934.  The average for theyears 1931-34 was  approximately  the same viz., 168,800  tons outof total purchases by Italy of 2,552,000 tons, or 6-6 per cent.The details are as follows :                                               As percentage of                                                  ITALIAN                                    Tons       total purchases                                (,000&apos;s omitted),  of these products.   Crude      .........       19-6           14-9   Petrol      .........       34-0            9-4   Kerosene    .........       10-4            5-2   Fuel  oil    .........       61-2            3-5   Lubricating oil    ......       43-6           48-3168-8            6-6   The position in the United States as regards production, imports and  exports is as follows :  During the past four  years, the outputhas varied from 107 million tons to 134 millions, the figure for 1934being 123 million tons.  For that year, the  imports of crude oil andrefined  products  were 7-1 million tons.  The home consumption ofthe  United  States  was  103-8   million tons  and   exports  were14-4 million tons, the difference  being accounted  for by the outputof solid products, by refinery losses  and changes in stocks.   Theproduction of  oil in 1935 exceeded that for  1934 by 11 million tonsand,  with the  enormous resources of  this  country,  there  is no practical reason  why  a much larger increase could not be secured without any abnormal development work being undertaken.   Besides  importing  substantial quantities of  crude  oil  fromVenezuela, the United States of  America also obtains supplies fromMexico and Colombia.   Assuming that all States Members of the  Co-ordination Committeewere to co-operate in an oil embargo,  the possible sources  of supplyof petroleum  other  than those  from  the  United  States  are  quiteinsignificant.   Italian  domestic   production  amounts  to  20,000  to30,000  tons per  annum, and  there is no reason  for believing thatit could be rapidly increased.  Even if supplies were  available, theycould not be developed without the expenditure of very large sums of money&apos;.   Production in  Albania has only just begun  and  theamounts  likely  to be obtained from  that  source  in  the  immediatefuture  will not,  it  is believed, prove  to be of  such importance as-materially to affect  the position.   Moreover, Albanian oil is reportedto be of  a poor  quality.   The other  countries  in which  Italy  hasinvested  capital   in  petroleum are Members of  the  Co-co-ordination committee.
ANNEX 2.                          SUBSTITUTES.                        I. Introduction.   The Committee has examined the possibility of Italy substitutingother products for petroleum products and thus effecting an economy in  its requirements of petroleum and  its derivatives, which would otherwise have to be imported.   The Committee is  of opinion that such possibilities exist,  but theactual extent of the economy which might  be effected will  dependon several factors :    (a) The possibility  of  producing the  necessary raw material on         Italian territory;   (6) The possibility of importing  such  raw material from  abroad;   (c) The possibility of manufacturing  or importing the necessary         plant  and machinery  for  the production or utilisation of         substitutes;   (d) The time required to secure  the production in Italy of large         quantities of substitutes, the construction of plants  and the         transformation of vehicles;   (e) The possibility of financing  these various processes  and of         paying for the necessary imports.   The production of substitutes is generally a costly  operation.  Thefinancial  charge which would, however,  devolve  upon Italy mightvary considerably according to whether the country was able  to effect the necessary production within  its own  territory or was obliged tohave recourse to importation.   On the  other hand, several of the factors  enumerated above areof  a non-technical character  and fall outside the competence of theCommittee.   It  is impossible, in these circumstances, to make  anyprecise estimate of the total  economy which it would be  possible for italy to effect by the  use of substitutes.                           JI.-Petrol.   The Committee has specially  considered the substitutes for petrol(motor spirit) which may be used in motor vehicles.   The  principal substitutes for petrol which,  for the  purposes ofits investigation, the  Committee  has regarded as of more immediateimportance are :    (1) Motor  alcohol ethyl  alcohol highly  concentrated;   (2)  Benzol;    (3)  Methyl alcohol (methanol, wood spirit);   (4)  Generator gas, produced in portable  gas  generators.
    As  additional  substitutes  for petrol which might come  under consideration in present circumstances  in  Italy, the  following may be mentioned :     (5)  Compressed coal-gas;    (6)  Compressed hydrogen;    (7)  Shale oil and  products  of distillation thereof;    (8)  Use of hydro-electric power either transmitted  by wire or by          the use  of  accumulators;    (9)  Other possible substitutes.    A short resume is given below of  the production and use of these substitutes.    1.   Motor Alcohol is used blended with petrol.  The percentage of alcohol used  in  the mixture  varies considerably,  but up to 25 per cent, (by volume) may be used without any adjustment of the motor. Whilst  the  calorific value of the alcohol mixture is somewhat lower than that of petrol, it has a higher anti-knock  value and  the  overall results  are similar.    When a mixture of motor spirit containing more  than 25 per cent. of  alcohol is used,  a certain  modification of  the motor becomes necessary, the degree of  adjustment augmenting with the percentage of  alcohol.    These alterations a certain pre-heating  of the  air, adjustment  of the fuel  inlet to the  carburettor, &amp;c.&apos; do  not entail any serious difficulties or any great cost.   It is even  possible, afterproper  adjustments have been  made,  to use  alcohol alone  as motorfuel.  In this case, it is, however, necessary, in order to  obtain any satisfactory effect or economy, to use a higher degree of compression than that for which the ordinary motors  are constructed.  This would entail more extensive  and costly changes.    In  Prance and Sweden, a  mixture  of  50  per  cent,  petrol and 50 per  cent,  motor alcohol is  used  with  good  technical  results for motor-buses.    If alcohol is to be used in motors,  it  should have a minimum degree  of concentration of  99-6 per cent.    It is produced from ordinary  strong  spirits (of  95-96&quot;) by one or  other of the  various special  methods of concentration, viz. :     (1)  Dehydration with calcium oxide (calcined chalk);    (2)  Dehydration with gypsum;    (3)  Distillation  with  certain salts  (acetate of alkalis,  &amp;c.) :  the          so-called Hiag  method;    (4)  Distillation  with benzol,  &amp;c.    Methods (3)  and (4) are those principally used;  method (2) also is used in Germany.    The manufacture  of  alcohol both for industrial purposes  and as motor   fuel is  carried  on  in   various  countries  in  Europe  on a comparatively large scale, its manufacture  being in many  countries regarded  as  a suitable outlet for an  existing surplus  production of
certain  agricultural  products,  or  a  by-product  in  certain  othermanufactures.   Thus, the raw material may be potatoes,  sugar-beet,corn, grapes, apples and other fruit, molasses, or refuse-lye from themanufacture of sulphite  cellulose:  technical alcohol is also obtained in the manufacture of yeast and by treatment of sawdust.  In Italy, according to information available to the Committee,  fivefactories working according to method  (8) above, with an aggregateyearly capacity of 50,000 to 60,000 tons,  have been erected or  arewider construction.  According   to  the  Zeitschrift  fur  Spiritusindustrie,  of  the23rd January,  1936,  some  very  large factories for the production ofraw  alcohol are  under construction  at  present  in  Italy.   TheCommittee considers  that further factories might possibly be erectedwithin a relatively short  space of time.  The  production of motor alcohol alone has  been given in variousperiodicals for the last year for which figures are available as :                                                  Tons.          Germany    ............   160,000                                                48,000CzechoslovakiaSwedenAustriaHungary14,000 8,000 8,000  Alcohol  for  drinking  purposes and for  industrial purposes  is produced  in addition  to  the above quantities and  some  part of it,might be  made  available  for the production of motor alcohol.  From  the information available, it would appear  that the Italianproduction of motor alcohol has hitherto been at the  rate of 6,400&apos;tons  per year.   It is  anticipated that  in 1936 the quantity of motoralcohol which may be produced will be 40,000 tons.   This quantitymight possibly be doubled by importation.   reference has  alreadybeen made to the practice in several  countries of utilising the over-production  of agricultural products  for  the  production  of  motoralcohol.   As this motor fuel is more costly  than petrol, it might beconsidered advantageous  to  those  countries  to dispose of some oftheir production by export under the circumstances being consideredby the Committee.  2. Benzol is used in  admixture with petrol,  the percentage ofbenzol in a mixture varying up to  a maximum of 40 per cent.  Theaddition  of benzol increases the anti-knock value of the fuel and alsoits power.   Benzol mixtures are also used  in various  countries foraviation  purposes, but the maximum  percentage  in  this case  wouldbe considerably lower than that already referred to,  as benzol has acomparatively high freezing-point.  Benzol is a by-product obtained during the carbonisation  of coalit gas-works and coke-ovens and by the distillation of coal tar.  Theprincipal   producing  countries  are  Germany,   United  States  ofimeriea,  United Kingdom, France and  Belgium.   The figures  for
production during the year 1934 in the case of these countries were as follows : Germany    .........    ...   275,000United States of America......   210,000United  Kingdom  ...     ......   195,000France      ............    74,000Belgium    .........  -  ...    53,000   Italy&apos;s  own  production  of  benzol in  1934 amounted  to  about ,000 tons.  An obligation to extract the maximum amount  of benzolfrom the gas produced at gas-works and coke-ovens in Italy  might beregarded as a possible means of increasing Italy&apos;s own  production ofbenzol.   Italian  imports  of benzol during  the  nine months January to september 1935 amounted to 11,600 tons  (or about 15,500 tons perannum).  In case of  need,  the  total  imports might be increased  to,say,  25,000 tons, thus making together  with Italy&apos;s own productionan aggregate quantity of about 30,000 tons available to Italy.   3.  Methyl Alcohol has been  used lately in Italy  in admixturewith petrol and motor alcohol, the proportions used being :    This  motor fuel is reported as having  given very  satisfactory results in a motor race (Rome-Paris).   Methyl alcohol,  or wood spirit  (methanol),  is  obtained as aby-product  from   charcoal-ovens   and   is   now   also   producedsynthetically.   The main countries of  production  are  the  United  States  ofAmerica, Germany,  Canada,  Sweden,  Finland and Austria.   The figures available to the  Committee regarding the productionof methyl alcohol, or wood spirit, are rather incomplete and somewhatuncertain; probably they do not include synthetic methanol.   The production in Italy was : Tons.Per cent.Ethyl alcoholMethyl alcoholPetrol322048Tons.1931-321932-331933-34  5851,3002,500The production of other countries was :  Tons.Germany  (1933)    ......Sweden (1934)     ......United States of  America (1933)2,8001,6003,000
   The  total quantity available  to  Italy in  admixture with  and assubstitute for petrol would probably not exceed 5,000 tons.   4.  - Use  of Portable  Gas  Generators. Motors  driven  by  gasgenerated in producers affixed  to  the vehicle are used  in  France,Sweden  and  some  other  countries, especially in motor  lorries  andbuses.   Such generators have also been introduced lately in Italy.   The  efficiency of the motor is reduced by some 25-30 per cent.,unless compression  in the cylinders is increased.   As  fuel,  various  carbonaceous  materials may  be  used e.g.,charcoal, wood or coal.   According to a communique issued on the 28th August, 1935, theItalian  Government is reported to  have  decided that,  before theend of December 1937,  all automobiles used in public transport ofpersons  should be  either fitted with  gas-generator-driven motors oradapted  to substitutes  for  petrol.   This  transformation, if  carried through, might result in an appreciable saving of petrol as motor fuel.   5.   Compressed Coal-gas has been used  in certain countries, incases  of emergency,  as  a  substitute for  petrol.  Technically,  thesubstitution  offers  no  difficulty whatever.   In the case  of  Italy, a country  possessing  practically no coal  deposits of her  own and wherethe gas  produced by the  gas-works from imported coal is needed inthe first place for illuminating and heating purposes, the use of thisgas as a substitute for petrol may  be dismissed as not probable onany considerable  scale.   6.   Compressed  Hydrogen  has  been  proposed  as  a  possiblesubstitute.    Italy,   in fact,  produces  considerable  quantities ofhydrogen  in  her  electrolytic plants, for the production of ammonia,nitric  acid and  nitrates.   Motors for the  use of hydrogen may,  however, be  considered asstill being, to a large extent, in an experimental stage,  and are, itis understood; likely to be rather complicated and costly.   7.   Shale Oil and Products of Distillation thereof. The treatmentof  bituminous  shale,  deposits of which are  to  be  found  in Italy,may yield a  certain quantity of oil which may be distilled to yieldpetrol and other  oils.   The cost  involved  in  securing  any largedevelopment  of these deposits would be considerable  and time wouldbe required,  but  the  Committee thinks  it desirable to  call attentionto  the matter.   8.   Hydro-electric  Power. An  extended use of  hydro-electric power may have to  be  reckoned with as a further possibility, for Italy has a  large potential capacity for the  production of electrical energy.   The  substitution of petrol-driven motors by  electric power might take the form  either of  an extended  installation of trolley-bus linesor of  an increased use of accumulator-driven motor-cars.
    The quantity of petrol which might be replaced in this way can,of course, only be a matter of conjecture.    9.   Other Possible  Substitutes. As is well known, petrol andcertain  other petroleum products  may be produced  by  syntheticmethods from coal,  lignite  or other  carbonaceous materials.   Theleading countries in the development of the method of productionhave  been Germany, the United  Kingdom and France.   In  thesecountries,  which  possess  large  natural  resources  in  coal  andbituminous  materials,  certain processes of manufacture  have, infact, been developed  on an industrial scale,  as the result of extensiveand extremely costly experiments.    Italy,  possessing  no  coal  deposits  of her own, has not, however,undertaken any developments in these directions.    A  supply of Italian  synthetic petroleum, products  may thereforebe regarded as out of the question  at present.    Finally,  the  Committee   considers  that  it  should  mention thepossibility of motor fuels being manufactured from certain  products of vegetable or animal origin, such as peanuts,  palm-kernels, olives,castor-oil, fish-oils, &amp;c.                *          *          *          *    As a result of its investigations, the Committee is of  opinion thatit  would be possible, by the  adoption and extension of the use of substitutes for petrol, to effect a material economy in the  quantityof motor fuel, which otherwise would have to be imported.    As the Committee has already indicated  at the beginning, various considerations have  to be taken into  account which  are  of a non-technical character and fall outside the competence of the Committee.It is impossible, in these circumstances, to make any precise estimateof the economy in petrol which it would be possible for Italy to  effect by  the use of substitute  fuels.    As some substitution  of imported  motor  fuels by home-producedfuels  is already taking place, it is considered that no serious  difficulty would be  experienced in  expediting  this  substitution immediately,and that,  subject to the  problems implicit  to the factors mentionedabove being  satisfactorily  resolved,  economies  of the proportionsindicated  by the Committee  might be obtained within a  relatively short  time.  The cost of substitute fuels will, however, be considerably higher than that of petrol.    In order  to  give some  indication  of the  extent  of  the possibleeconomy,  taking into account only those substitute fuels  in respectof which approximate figures can be given that is to say, the fuelsreferred to in  Sections  1,   2 and 3 of  the  present  report theCommittee would roughly estimate  this at 100,000 tons per annum.    Whatever the possible economy may be, however, it will remainnecessary,  in  any case,  for Italy to continue to import  considerable quantities of petrol.  As was explained above,  some of the principalsubstitute fuels existing at present can only be used by mixing  themwith  larger  quantities of petrol, which will have to be  imported inany case.
   It should, moreover, be added that alcohol and benzol are essential for the  production  of  explosives.   In  consequence, the greater the.demand for explosives, the less alcohol and benzolwill be availablefor motor fuel.            III. Petroleum Products other than Petrol.   Diesel Oil and  Kerosene. As  regards  substitutes for  petroleum products other than petrol, which form by far the  larger  part  ofthe imports of Italy, no substitutes of  any practical importance forDiesel  oil and kerosene may be  said  to exist in  Italy, at least  atpresent.   It is true that  certain fractions  of shale  oil  might beemployed as  substitutes  for Diesel  oil and  kerosene, but, as  setforth in Section 7,  the cost  and time  involved in securing any largedevelopment of the shale deposits  would be considerable.   Kerosenefor  lighting  purposes  in  lamps,   which it is estimated  representsrather  less  than half  of the  total quantity  of  kerosene  imported,might,  in extreme circumstances, be replaced by acetylene, produced as is  well known from carbide, in carbide lamps.   The introduc-tion, however, of such  lamps, in themselves rather  unsatisfactorysubstitutes,  would  take some time  and  considerable  cost.    some additional use of  electricity might also be employed for this  purpose.   Fuel oil  used under  boilers  by the mercantile marine may incertain  cases be replaced by coal without making  extensive changes to the furnaces and bunker  equipment.  . In many cases, substitutionwould involve  considerable alterations.   The substitution would,  ofcourse,  mean a corresponding increase of  imports of coal.   similar considerations would apply to fuel oils used in Italy for other purposes.In the  case  of naval vessels, such change of fuel  would in most cases be out of the question.   Lubricating mineral oils might to a  certain extent be replaced bylubricants made from  or containing vegetable  oils, such as  olive-oil,castor-oil, &amp;c, or animal fats e.g., fish or  whale oil.   But  for certainpurposes, such as the  lubrication of high-speed machinery, internal-combustion   motors, &amp;c,  the  general replacement  of high-grademineral lubricants is not regarded as practicable.
ANNEX 3.                            TRANSPORT.   The Committee has made a technical examination of the conditions governing the transport  of oil to Italy.(13)   It appeared to the  Committee  that  the problem could best bedealt with if they considered, first, the capacity of the Italian tankerfleet;  secondly, the extent to which it might  be possible for tanker tonnage belonging to non-member States to  be  transferred to theItalian trade; and, thirdly, the form of any possible  embargo on theuse of tankers belonging to member States for the carriage of oil toItaly, together with  the difficulties that might attach to  any suchembargo.             I. Capacity of the  Italian Tanker Fleet.   Details are attached  of the principal tanker fleets of the world as at the 1st  July,  1935 (see Appendix IV).  The  Italian fleet ofvessels  of 1,000  gross tons  and over is there  shown as sixty-sevenvessels of 329,319 gross tons.  It has since been increased, and at the17th January, 1936,  is  believed to have amounted to eighty-two(H)vessels of approximately 356,000 gross tons.  (There  are, in addition,the Italian  naval tankers,  which probably amount  to about 70,000gross tons.)   Of the 356,000 gross tons, 254,000  gross tons  are  recorded astrading on  the 17th  January last.   Of the remainder,  16,000  grosstons are reported as  being used as  depot ships, 42,000 gross tons aslying at Massowa or  Mogadiscio and  36,000 gross tons as laid up ornot having  moved for two months.   The balance of 8,000 gross tons is not  reported.   A number  of Italian tankers  are, because  of their age and size,not eminently suited  for ocean-going voyages, but if all vessels under ,000 gross  tons and  also all vessels over 30 years of  age  are omitted,a balance of 270,000 gross tons is  left,  and it must be  assumed, inthe absence  of detailed information as to the actual  condition of theindividual  ships, that this tonnage would be used,  if necessary,  fortransatlantic  voyages.   It appears that  Italy has, during  recent months, used a  number of these vessels  (aggregating  40,000  grosstons) for storage  purposes of oil in the Italian colonies in East Africa   (13) Throughout this chapter, any reference to  Italy  should be read  as including Italy and its East African possessions.       Including eight vessels under 1,000 gross tons.
and a number (aggregating 27,000 gross tons) for  the  storage of oil in Italy; but there is no reason to think that, if Italy were pressed fortanker tonnage, she would not arrange for any reserve required to beheld in less serviceable tankers, or  in shore tanks.   The Committee presumes that  Italy would, under the pressure of8 great emergency, make arrangements for  increased  storage of oiiin shore tanks, so as to release further tanker tonnage for the carriage of oil to Italy.  If this were done, it is possible that  the Italian tanker tonnage which could be sent over  the Atlantic for oil supplies might even be as high as  820,000 gross tons.  It is certainly not possible forthe Committee to say that this could not be  done if the Italian needwere sufficiently  great.   Ordinarily,  it could be assumed that a speed of 200 or more milesper day would  be attained by a fleet of tankers, but having regard tothe average age  of the Italian fleet, the Committee  thought it  well to assume that,  on  average,  the  vessels would  not do more than180  miles  per day at sea.   Allowing reasonable  time for loading,unloading, repairs,  &amp;c, this would mean that the  ships, if runningbetween Italy  and  the United States  Gulf ports, would, on average,make 4-75 instead of a normal 5 or 6 voyages per year.   The average  cargo-carrying capacity of  a tanker is approximately one-third  more  than  her  gross tonnage.   The  Committee is accordingly led to the conclusion,  on the information available to it,that, if the Italian  supplies of oil had to be drawn from the Gulf and270,000 gross tons were put into the  transatlantic  trade, the italian fleet might be  expected to carry not less than about  If million  tonsof oil  from the  Gulf to  Italy in  a year.  If, however, as much as320,000  gross  tons were put into the transatlantic  trade,  and theCommittee cannot say that this would be impossible, then the Italiantanker fleet would  carry as much as 2  million tons  a year.   The Committee  has not overlooked the fact that about 20,000 grosstons of tankers  are required for  the  carriage of  oil  (estimated to amount to 25,000 to 80,000 tons per month) from Italy to its colonies,but  it seems probable that  the  tonnage which has been left  out of account  above  would  be sufficient  for  this, even if  as  much as320,000 gross tons were  put into  the transatlantic  trade.   Vessels under other flags which might be employed in the carriage of oil to Italy from the Gulf could  reasonably be expected to make atleast five voyages a year, and the  carriage of 1 million tons of oil toItaly in such vessels would mean the employment for a year of tanker tonnage of  about   150,000  gross  tons  (cargo-carrying  capaeitv,200,000 tons).   In short therefore, the  position is  that for every million tons of oil in excess of If million tons or possibly 2 million tons (see  above)-which could be  carried  by the Italian  tanker fleet, Italy  wouldrequire to obtain the  use  of 150,000  gross  tons of  tanker tonnageunder other flags.
             II. Availability of Non-Italian Tonnage.    As regards  the second question -i.e.,  the extent to which tanker tonnage  belonging to non-member States  might be  used for the carriage of oil to  Italy details of the fleets in question will be foundin Appendix IV.   The three principal fleets are those of the UnitedStates of America, Japan and Germany, and it has not been thought necessary to consider the fleets of the other non-member States, as these fleets are very small.    The Japanese  tanker fleet is constantly being kept trading in theFar East,  and the Committee considers  it  altogether  unlikely thatthis fleet, or part of it, would be  diverted to Italian trade.    The German tanker fleet is at present  practically entirely engagedin trade  to  Germany, where the  German  tankers presumably are atan  advantage to-day  compared with foreign tankers, on account ofexchange difficulties.  The Committee does not, however, know of any measures  which would prevent  German  owners from diverting this tonnage to Italian trade  if they were  given sufficient inducement inthe shape of higher freight rates.  The German tanker tonnage thatis suitable for transatlantic voyages would appear to amount to about90,000 gross tons.    As regards  the  United States tanker fleet, a report issued by theUnited States Shipping Board Bureau on  the 30th September,  1935,states that, on that date, 258 tankers  of  1,721,648 gross tons  were employed in the  coastwise trade, and 69 tankers of 526,962  grosstons in nearby  and overseas foreign trades.  As, however, the amountof tanker tonnage employed in  the United States  coastwise  tradetends to increase  in the winter months, the Committee has examined the reported movements of United States tankers in the months ofDecember 1935 and January 1936 and has found that, in this period,the  number of tankers  employed  in foreign trades had  fallen to43 tankers of 316,000 gross tons.  Whilst only United  States  shipscan  be employed  in the  United  States coastwise trade,  there is noreason, so  far as the  Committee  is aware, why other vessels shouldnot be chartered  for and  employed in the United States  nearby and overseas  foreign  trades,   thus releasing the  United States tankersengaged in those  trades for the carriage of oil to Italy.   Further, in  this connection it  has to be borne in mind that,  in sofar  as the United States might be able to arrange for the supply of oil to ports in the northern Atlantic range from ports in  the Gulf in lieu  of from ports in  California,  an additional  amount  of  tonnagewould be made available for possible use  in  foreign trade because ofthe much shorter voyage involved.   The Committee has  also  examined the question whether  non-member  States would, in the event of any of their tonnage  being diverted to Italian trade, be able  to replace such tonnage by tankerschartered  from Member   States.   During recent  months there has
been a fair number of tankers belonging to Member  States engagedin the carriage of oil to Italy which, in the event of an  embargo, wouldbecome available for this purpose.  Secondly, there are, at the presenttime,  no  less than 340,000 gross tons  of  tankers laid up.   It isthought that,  if necessary, at least one-half of this  tonnage could be-put into  commission.  Thirdly, according to Lloyd&apos;s Register ship-building  returns for December 1935, there is 435,560 gross tons oftanker tonnage under  construction, and the  greater  part of this tonnage will, it  is reported, become available for service during theyear;  There seems little doubt, therefore, that any tonnage belonging&apos;to non-member States which may be diverted to Italian trade  can bereplaced.  From  the  foregoing  it appears  clear  that,  in  the event of  an embargo  on the use of tankers belonging to Member States, arrange-ments  could  be made by Italy and  non-member States for  a  veryconsiderable block  of tonnage belonging  to  non-member States tobe made  available for the carriage of oil to Italy, although there canbe no doubt that the carriage of Italy&apos;s supplies of oil in such circum-stances would be more difficult to arrange and  would be made more-expensive, owing  to  the fact  that  Italy  would  be precluded fromchartering in  the open freight market  and could  only  obtain  suchtonnage as was  required from the restricted market offered by  suchStates  as were not applying the embargo.                    III. Forms of Embargo.  As regards the form of any possible embargo on the use of tankers.for the carriage of oil to Italy, the embargo, if it is to be fully effective,would have to be such  as to prevent tankers of Member States from being used  (whether  by Italians or  by anyone else) for the carriage of oil to Italy.  For the sake of  completeness, the prohibitions should perhaps cover discharges to Italian ships,  but the possibility of  oilbeing transferred at sea from a tanker belonging to a  Member state to a tanker in Italy&apos;s  service need probably not be regarded as  serious-in practice.  It would clearly be necessary to prohibit,  in the first place,  the-direct sale to Italy of tankers belonging to Member States, and earlysimultaneous action by all  Member States would be required.   Itwould, however,  be necessary also to prevent  indirect  sales to Italy,and to this end all sales of tankers to States not actually applying the-embargo would have  to be prevented.  The Committee has considered the question of an embargo on the chartering of tankers.   A prohibition of  time chartering of tankers toItaly would not by itself prevent  the tankers being used for the carriage of oil to  Italy.   If the embargo was  one  against chartering, then it would be necessary for Member States to prohibit time chartering-of tankers to States not applying the embargo,  and to prohibit  voyage-
 chartering of ships for the carriage of oil to Italy, and also to prohibit the  use  for the carriage of oil  to Italy of  any tankers that might be time chartered by  their  nationals  from  other  Member  States.  A prohibition of all time chartering  of  tankers  to  non-member States would, however, mean a very serious  interference with tanker trades not  in any way connected with Italy.  Further considerable difficulty must arise in dealing with ships chartered by a Member State applying the  embargo  to a national of another  such State where that  national resides outside the  jurisdiction of the latter State.   Another  form of embargo might be either a prohibition against (a) the discharge in Italy of oil from tankers belonging  to  Member States or  (b) the proceeding of such  tankers  to  Italian  ports.  The latter would appear to be the more practicable, in view of the difficul- ties  which would arise if it were necessary, in cases  of  offences, to prove the  actual unloading of oil in Italy.   The  Committee  is of  the opinion that, if an  embargo on the use of tankers belonging to Member States for the carriage of oil to Italy is to be enforced, the most  practicable form of embargo would  be one  which combined :      (i) A prohibition against the sale of such tankers to States not           applying  the embargo;  and   (ii) A prohibition against the proceeding of such tankers to Italy.   A prohibition on the  proceeding of tankers belonging  to Member States to Italy might raise difficulties in the case of vessels chartered on voyage charters for the carriage of oil to Italy.  Such a prohibition would, of course, apply to vessels already on time charter and might, perhaps, raise difficulties for the owners of ships so chartered, which can, under the contracts already made, be used for world-wide trade. The  extent of  these difficulties  cannot, however,  be estimated in the absence of detailed information of these contracts.   It would  be necessary for the  States  enforcing  the  embargo totake  measures to watch  the movements of all their  tanker  vessels,and  also to take steps,  in cases  of  offences,  to  collect the  evidencerequired  to secure convictions  with the possible application of heavypenalties on  the owner and/or master.                          IV.-Cased Oil.   The Committee has further considered the  question of the prohibition-prohibition of the carriage to Italy of cased oil in ships belonging to member states, and has come to the conclusion that it would be impracticable to prohibit such carriage, having regard to the difficulties  attachedto the administration  of  any such prohibition.
                      V. Inland Transport.   Finally, as regards the possible transportation of oil to Italy fromneighbouring countries by rail or  inland  waterways, the  Committeeis of opinion that this would only arise as part of an attempt to securesupplies through States not applying  the embargo.  While certainpossibilities exist which might  be used, the Committee is of opinionthat, if any State  or States were giving facilities  to Italian trade inthis matter, the oil would  be more likely  to be carried by sea, since it would be much cheaper and  much more practicable, particularly ifconsiderable quantities were involved.
	(i) Italian Import Statistics.						(ii) Corresponding Export Statistics.					Country and kind.	Average 1931-34.		Average 1932-34.		Year 1934.		Average 1931-34.		Average 1932-34.		Year 1934.		Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight. 1 %	France  Crude ......... Petrol ......... Kerosene......... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating ......	18-1	1-9	24-1	2-4	72-4	6-4	i&apos;i-2 16-2	6-6 17-9	14-8 21-6	6-8 22-6	39-1 64-8	2-6 47-1Total ......	18-1	1-1	24-1	1-4	72-4	4-0	27-4	1-1	36-4	1-4	103-9	3-5Eoumania  Crude ......... Petrol ......... Kerosene......... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;o.) Lubricating ......	23-5 31-0 64-8 385-0 5-5	10-3 9-3 45-2 40-1 8-1	30-0 36-0 66-4 417-0 5-0	22-2 11-2 46-8 41-3 7-5	47-9 56-9 58-6 465-9 3-7	33-5 16-3 40-5 41-5 5-6	30-3 82-1 109-9 596-8 10-1	23-1 22-7 55-0 33-8 11-2	40-4 84-1 106-2 639-8 9-5	25-1 24-3 54-9 35-1 10-0	54-2 84-9 92-5 733-1 5-8	24-4 21-5 49-8 37-0 4-2Total ......	509-8	31-2	554-4	33-1	633-0	34-7	829-2	32-5	880-0	33-6	973-5	33-2                                           Imports of Petroleum into Italy,  1931-34            As recorded :  (i) in the Italian Import Statistics ;  (it) in the Export Statistics of the Exporting Countries.Source :  Official Trade Statistics.Note. The  percentages  are calculated  thus :  for each  kind, on the total of  its kind (e.g.,&quot; crude&quot;  on the total crude) ;  for the    total of  each country on the grand total (last line).                                                (In metric tons (000&apos;s omitted).)
Crude Petrol ......... Kerosene......... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating ......	38-5 78-6 46-2 318-3 7-2	30-1 23-6 32-2 33-1 10-6	34-1 79-2 42-5 317-2 6-9	25-2 24-7 30-0 31-4 10-4	7-3 91-3 39-4 258-7 6-4	5-1 26-3 27-2 23-1 9-8	12-1 115-5 50-8 732-9 16-5	9-2 31-9 25-4 41-4 18-3	16-2 107-4 49-9 719-3 15-1	LO-l 1 31-1 25-8 39-5 15-8	6-4 &apos; 114-8 42-9 631-3 19-0	2-9 29-0 23-1 31-7 13-8Total ......	488-8	29-9	479-9	28-6	403-1	22-1	927-8	36-3	906-9	34-8	814-4	27-8Netherlands Bast Indies  Crude ......... Petrol ......... Kerosene......... Residual (Fuel Oil, Ac.) Lubricating ......	48-1 &quot;i-o	14-4 6-i	51-8 &quot;i-3	16 -i 6-i	32-8 &quot;2-4	9-4 6-2	&quot;i-7 *5-6	1-3 6-3	&quot;3-3 &quot;.5-6	i-o 6-3	&quot;6-9 &quot;7-7	2-5 6-4Total ......	49-1	3-0	53-1	3-2	35-2	&apos;l-9	10-3	0-4	8-9	0-3	17-6	0-6Iran  Crude ......... Petrol .......... Kerosene......... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating ......	114-8 18-4 65-1	34-5 12-8 6-8	F6-4 19-1 65-1	33-1 13-4 6-4	117-3 16-4 86-9	33-7 11-3 7-7	98-1 22-3 99-2	27-1 11-2 5-6	108-6 18-0 114-2	31-4 9-3 6-3	136-7 21-1 144-1	34-6 11-4 7-2Total ......	198-3	12-2	190-6	11-4	220-6	12-1	219-6	8-6	240-8	9-2	301-9	10-3Colombia -Crude ......... Petrol ......... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating ......	39-0	30-4	52-0	38-5	63-7	44-6	61-0	46-5	69-7	43-3	74-1	33-4Total ......	39-0	2-4	52-0	3-1	63-7	3-5	61-0	2-4	69-7	2-7	74-1	2-5 :COCO
	(i) Italian Import Statistics.						(iz) Corresponding Export Statistics.					Country and kind.	Average 1931-34.		Average 1932-34.		Year 1934.		Average 1931-34.		Average 1932-34.		Year 1934.		Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%Netherlands West Indies (Curacao, including Aruba)  Crude ......... Petrol ......... Kerosene......... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	&quot;9-8 1-1 101-6	2-9 0-8 10-6	11-3 1-4 107-4	3-5 1-0 10-6	18-9 3-9 128-9	5-4 2-7 11-5	(a) 8-3 (a) 16-8 (a) 5-7 (a) 257-3	6-3 4-6 2-8 14-6	8-3 16-8 5-7-257-3	5-2 4-8 2-9 14-1	25-0 39-0 17-0 355-0	11-3 9-9 9-2 17-8Total ......	112-5	6-9	120-1	7-2	151-7	8-3	(a)288-1	11-3	288-1	11-0	438-0	14-9U.S.A.-Crude ......... Petrol ......... KsrossiiG Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating ......	27-1 . 38-2 12-1 50-8 51-5	21-2 11-5 8-5 5-3 75-6	19-9 30-6 11-7 54-9 51-1	14-1 9-5 8-3 5-5 77-1	24-0 22-7 23-2 67-0 51-7	16-8 6-5 16-0 6-0 78-7	19-6 34-0 10-4 61-2 43-6	14-9 9-4 5-2 3-5 48-3	28-2 21-3 13-0 64-3 45-8	16-3 6-2 6-7 3-6 48-1	62-0 7-2 11-0 61-9 44-2	28-0 1-8 5-9 3-1 32-1Total ......	179-7	11-0	167-3	10-0	188-6	10-4	168-8	6-6	170-6	6-5	188-3	6-4Venezuela  Crude ......... Petrol ......... Keroseno......... Residual (Fuel Oil,&amp;c.) Lubricating ......	&quot;i-6 16-3	6-5 1-7	&quot;i-9 17-5	6-6 1-7	&quot;&apos;o-4 2-1 23-8	i-6 1-5 2-1						Total ......	17-9	1-1	19-4	1-2	31-3	1-7						
Other countries (&amp;) 											1	Crude .........												Petrol .........	(d)10-9	3-3	4-2	1-3	2-9	0-8	(d)10-9	3-0	&quot;i-2	i-2	&quot;2-9	0-7Kerosene......	0-7	0-5	0-7	0-5	1-2	0-8	0-7	0-4	0-7	0-4	1-2	0-6Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.)	4-3	0-4	5-7	0-6	(c) 16-5	1-5	4-3	0-2	5-7	0-3	16-5	0-8Lubricating ......	3-9	5-7	3-3	5-0	3-9	5-9	3-9	4-3	3-3	3-5	3-9	2-8Total ......	19-8	1-2	13-9	0-8	24-5	1-3	19-8	0-8	13-9	0-5	24-5	0-8All countries 												Crude .........	128-1	100	135-1	100	142-9	100	131-3	100	160-8	100	221-7	100Petrol .........	333-0	100	321-4	100	348-2	100	362-1	100	345-7	100	395-4	100Kerosene.........	143-3	100	141-8	100	144-8	100	199-8	100	193-5	100	185-7	100Besidual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.)	960-5	100	1,010-2	100	1,122-5	100	1,768-5	100	1,821-0	100	1,991-7	100Lubricating ......	68-1 .	100	66-3	100	65-7	100	90-3	100	95-3	100	137-7	100Grand Total ...	1,633-0	100	1,674-8	100	1,824-1	100	2,552-0	100	2,616-3	100	2,932-2	100                                                                                                                CO(a) Average 1932-34.  Figures not available for 1931.(b) The figures on the Export side are a repetition of the Italian import figures,(e) Of which, British West Indies (Trinidad): 14-9.  In previous years: 0-0.(d) Of which, Straits Settlements in 1931:  26-9.  Corresponding figures 1932-34 were: 0-4, 0-2, 0-0.coCO2N3
Country and kind.	(i) Italian import statistics.						(H) Corresponding export statistics.		Jan.-Sept. 1935.		Oct.-Dec. 1935. (a)		Year 1935.		Year 1935.		Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%France  Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	10-7	1-2					12-3 24-0 17-1	2-3 1-0 13-9Total	10-7	0-7	17-1	1-9	27-8	1-2	53-4	1-4Roumania  Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	76-1 111-3 62-3 448-7 7-9	45-7 37-6 54-3 50-9 12-3					331-0 189-9 1,163-2 15-3	60-9 82-2 46-1 12-5Total	706-3	46-5	389-6	44-2	1,095-9	45-6	1,699-4	44-6U.S.S.R.-Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	46-1 20-5 121-4 11-7	15-6 17-8 13-8 18-2					42-8 16-7 500-0 17-7	7-9 7-2 19-8 14-5Total	199-7	13-1	128-9	14-6	328-6	13-7	577-2	15-2   (a) Estimated from the arrivals of  tankers in Italian ports.   There are noItalian statistics, from October inclusive.                   Imports of Petroleum into Italy in 1935As recorded (t) in the Italian Import Statistics ;  (ii) in the Export Statistics                        of the Exporting Countries.Source:  Official  Trade Statistics, supplemented by  data supplied  by  the    various delegations.Note. The percentages are calculated thus :  for each kind, on the total of its    kind (e.g., &quot; crude&quot; on the total crude);  for the total of each country, on    the grand total (last line).                           (In metric tons (000&apos;s).)
999w O dCountry and   kind.(i) Italian import statistics.Jan.-Sept.   1935.Oct.-Dec. 1935. (a)Year 1935.Weight.   %    W7eight.   %   Weight.   %     (ti)Corresponding    export  statistics.Year 1935.Weight.   %Netherlands East Indies-Crude...PetrolKeroseneResidual  (Fuel Oil,  &amp;c.)...Lubricating  Total[ran  Crude Petrol Kerosene  .. Residual   (Fuel  Oil,   &amp;c.) LubricatingTotaljColombia -  Crude  Petrol  Kerosene  ...  Residual   (Fuel  Oil,   &amp;c.)  Lubricating   Total Netherlands West Indies: (Curacoa, including Aruba)-  Crude  Petrol I Kerosene  ... I Residual   (Fuel  Oil,   &amp;c.)   _  ... I Lubricating   Total13-7 2-34-220-279-717-3100-3197-345-345-327-0 5-6137-3169-94-72-00-51-326-915-011-413-027-23-09-14-915-611-239-0112-720-24-4263-345-312-8282-68-91-60-85-90-271-112-0180-413-2 5-27-19-8263-56-9120-0(6);30-91-9120-0(b)3-211-722-0 7-5481-0510-54-03-319-113-4  (a) Estimated from the arrivals of tankers in Italian ports.   There are noHian statistics, from October inclusive.  (b) Approximate ; partly estimated.
Country and kind.	(i) Italian import statistics.						(U) Corresponding export statistics.		Jan.-Sept. 1935.		Oct.-Dec. 1935. (a)		Year 1935.		Year 1935.		Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%	Weight.	%TJ.S.A.  Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	16-5 5-9 32-4 40-5	5-5 5-1 3-7 63-0					206-6 50-2 4-0 152-7 63-3	53-3 9-2 1-7 6-0 51-6Total	95-3	6-3	157-1	17-8	252-4	10-5	476-8	12-5Venezuela  Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) t ... Lubricating	&quot;6-5 0-6 14-8	0-2 0-5 1-7						Total	15-9	1-1			15-9	0-7		Other coun-tries(c)  Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	45 -1(d) 1-2 0-5 11-1(e) 4-2	27-1 0-4 0-4 1-2 6-5					61-4(d) 5-2 0-8 23-1 9-2	15-8 0-9 0-4 0-9 7-5Total	62-1	3-8	37-6	4-3	99-7	4-1	99-7	2-6All countries  Crude Petrol Kerosene ... Residual (Fuel Oil, &amp;c.) Lubricating	166-5 296-0 115-0 880-9 64-3	100 100 100 100 100					388-0 543-5 230-9 2,524-4 122-6	100 100 100 100 100Grand total	1,522-7	100	882-0	100	2,404-7	100	3,809-4	100    (a) Estimated  from the arrivals of  tankers in Italian ports.   There are noItalian statistics, from October inclusive.    (c) The figures on the export side  are a  repetition of  the Italian importfigures.    (d) Of which Iraq :                       Jan.-Sept. 1935.    Oct.-Dec. 1935.    Year 1935.         Crude  ......     34-0              9-4            43-4    The years 1934 and earlier were  nil.    (e) Of which, British West Indies 8-1.
         Appendix III.World Production of  Petroleum.Country.In metric tons (000&apos;s omitted).1931.	1932.	1933.	1934.(a)	1935.(6)290 1 289	272 1 271	239 1 238	222 1 221	178 1 177116,877 194 116,683	107,776 131 107,645	122,679 144 122,535	123,212 178 123,034	134,701 180 134,5216,305 4,934 1,37.1	6,267 4,842 1,425	6,432 5,087 1,345	7,243 5,711 1,532	7,629 6,015 1,61423,016 1,689 3 2,542 50 1,340 17,192	22,618 1,887 5 2,288 218 1,313 16,907	23,310 1,951 14 1,834 230 1,762 17,483	27,090 1,999 2,386 235 2,158 20,298	29,257 2,100 2,571 243 2,343 22,00012,694 535 1,225 4,698 120 5,843 273	13,573 350 1,239 5,093 115 6,549 227	14,435 326 1,229 5,527 115 7,200 . 200	16,535 283 1,292 6,042 1,048 7,658 212	19,057 714(c) 1,286 6,143 3,571 7,34322,324	21,376	21,440	24,150	24,0007,725 229 74 16 630 6,756 20	8,255 230 75 27 557 7,348 18	8,301 239 79 27 551 7,387 18	9,420 315 85 20 529 8,467 18	9,415 430 81 16 520 8,350 18. 189,231	180,137	196,836	207,872	224,237Africa ... Algeria Egypt[forth America ... Canada United StatesCari bbean Mexico TrinidadSouth America ... Argentine Bolivia Colombia Ecuador Peru ... VenezuelaAsia (excluding U.S.S.R.) British Borneo India... Netherlands East Indies Iraq ... Iran ... Japan and FormosaO.S.S.R.Europe (excl. TJ.S.S.R.) Germany France Italy ...... Poland Boumania Czechoslovakia     World(a) Provisional.(b) Provisional.   Partly estimated.(c) Including Sarawak and Brunei.
Number, Gross Tonnage  and Nationality oj Oil Tankers (excluding Vessels               under 1,000 tons gross) owned in the World.                       (I/loyd&apos;s Register, 1935-36.)                              (July 1935.)Countries where owned.Oil tankers of 1,000 tons and upwards.Steamers.No.    Tons.Motor-ships.No.    Tons.Total.No.    Tons.Great Britain and IrelandCanadaOther British Dominions .America (United States)  .Belgium ...DanzigDenmark...FranceGermany ...Holland ...ItalyJapanNorway  ...Russia (Soviet Union)SpainSweden  ...Other countries        Totals256 17 26324  1W  3 30 13 40 53  8 63  3639071,395,062  38,928 189,3882,155,932   4,733   7,352  17,849 166,933  53,811 137,764 249,309  55,948 417,336   3,905  17,950 249,1425,161,342123  8  4 64  8 24(a)!  9  7 15 39 14 12158 19 10 14 10538 918,282  82,446  14,551 335,436  55,615 248,653  71,556  46,895  65,671 228,303  80,010  94,2431,147,221 113,371  60,075 116,531  56,146379 25 30388  9 25 12 37 28 79 67 20221 22 16 14 733,735,0951,445(fi) Registry since transferred to Panama.Wt.-2750 2/36 F.O.P. 12734 Gp. 3402,313,344  121,374  203,9392,491,368   60,348  256,005   89,405  213,828  119,572  366,067  329,319  150,1911,564,557  117,276   78,025  116,531  305,2888,896,437

</content>
</cab>
