<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/260/0 images: 622-625</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1936.SECRET.                                                         Copy No.CP.  58  (36).CABINET.AUSTRIA.PROPOSED  INCREASE  IN  THE  UNITED  KINGDOM  DUTY ON CERTAIN KINDS  OF                       FELT  HATS AND HAT SHAPES.         Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    ON the 2nd October, 1935, the Import Duties Advisory Committee submitted a recommendation for the increase of United Kingdom import  duties on certainkinds of felt  hats- and hat shapes.   No change was proposed in the existingad valorem duty on felt hats and felt hat shapes advanced beyond the earlier stages of manufacture, viz., 30 per cent., or in the duty on shapes in the earlier stages, viz., 25 per cent.; but it was recommended that a minimum specific dutyof fifteen shillings a  dozen should be imposed on velour felt hats  and on velourfelt shapes advanced beyond the earlier stages.    The proposed specific minimum duty would  not, of course, affect the betterclass hats  and shapes, but its  incidence in  the case of &quot; schoolgirl &quot;  hats wouldbe equivalent  to  a duty  of  about 50 per cent, ad valorem, and, in the case of popular grades of &quot; capelines,&quot; to between 36 and 38 per cent.    Approval of these recommendations has been delayed as  the result of  the unwillingness  of  the Foreign Office to agree to any tariff increases which would affect unfavourably the trade  of  &quot; sanctionist &quot;  countries  (in this case Czecho-slovakia)  to  any  material extent  during  the period  of  sanctions.   The&quot;sanctions&quot; aspect has now been disposed of by inter-departmental  agreement;but there remain  certain  important political objections owing to the effect of theproposed increase of duty on the internal situation in Austria.  These objectionsare so serious from the point of view of foreign policy, that I now feel bound tosubmit the matter for decision by the Cabinet.    Ever since the Stresa  Conference of 1932 and  even before, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have accepted the view that,  if Austria&apos;s independence was to  bemaintained, her economic position must be  strengthened, and, consequently, thather export  trade must, if possible, be increased.  Further, His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment  have  always urged  Austria&apos;s non-German neighbours, and also France,  tofacilitate the  import of  Austrian products.   They have also expressed their intention as far as possible to do the same as regards the United Kingdom market,and with this object  enquiries were set on foot  some time ago with a view  to possible facilities for  Austrian imports, e.g., timber,  into this country.  Thoughit was found impossible to assist Austria in this direction, Austrians at any ratehad had the impression that His Majesty&apos;s  Government would continue to affordAustria the facilities in the United Kingdom market which she at present enjoys.In this  connection reference may be made to the note which  Sir John Simonaddressed to Baron Franckenstein on the 3rd February, 1934 (see Annex 1).    The actual amount of Austrian trade  which would be affected  by the newduty is admittedly small about  36,000 but it is of considerable importance inthe Austrian balance of payments. The following is  an extract from a despatch      [12702]
just received from His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Vienna on the subject of Austriantrade in 1935 :          &quot; Austria&apos;s adverse balance with the United Kingdom, which amounted     to 1,600,000 Schillinge in 1934, was increased more than sixfold  during the     past year.  I most sincerely trust that  this increase may receive some real     attention with reference to our own favourable payment balance as a whole,     and in particular to the recommendation of the Financial Committee of the     League,  on  which   His  Majesty&apos;s   Government  are  represented,   of     the  14th May,  1935,  as  to the necessity of supporting the  efforts  of  the     Austrian Government to maintain and develop Austrian foreign trade.  The     question is certainly of the greatest importance in connexion with the policy     of His Majesty&apos;s Government towards, and the interests of His Majesty&apos;s     Government in, Austria.&quot;     It is, in any case, not so much the amount of trade which is at issue as theprinciple involved and the fact that an increase in duty on Austrian felt hats, &amp;c,would, as has been shown above, completely reverse the policy which His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have  consistently  followed  for  several years.   Hence, the political effect in Austria of any such  action  by the United Kingdom  would be  whollydeplorable,  and would almost certainly outweigh any small economic  advantage which might result for the British industries concerned.  A copy of a telegram which has  been received from His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Vienna is also attached(Annex 2).  It reinforces the view expressed in this memorandum.     I should add that when His Majesty&apos;s Government took the initiative in recommending economic and  financial support  for Austria to the  French andItalian Governments in 1933, they explained to the  Austrian Government that itwas impossible for them to take special measures to increase Austrian imports intoGreat Britain.  The Austrians had proposed an arrangement for a partial refundof  United  Kingdom  customs duties  on certain  characteristic  imports from austria, including hats, to act as a preference for Austrian trade;  this had to be refused, but it was refused with regret, and  left the Austrians with the belief inour willingness to help them if we  could.  The increase  in the duty on hats is inflat contradiction, therefore, with the impression which our  attitude has hithertogiven to the Austrians;  and will be interpreted as a douche of cold  water, due,perhaps, to some obscure political motive.     Although  this does not, strictly speaking,  come within the province of theForeign Office, I must also draw  attention to the fact  that any restriction ofAustria&apos;s export market is likely to have repercussion upon the financial situationin that country, thereby affecting the interests both of British financial houses andof His Majesty&apos;s Government themselves.     So far as  Czechoslovakia  is concerned (and its trade is calculated to  be  hit by  the proposed increase in duty to  the extent of  55,000 a year), I do not desireto labour the political objections;  but it will be observed that,  in  the  opinion ofHis Majesty&apos;s Representative in Prague, they  are by no means negligible seetelegram No. 2 from His Majesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires at Prague (Annex 3).     For all these reasons,  therefore,  I  submit that the recommendation of theImport  Duties Advisory  Committee  should be reconsidered.  If  it  is deemed necessary,  in the event of a rejection of the  recommendation being decided upon,to publish any reason for  the rejection, I suggest that some reference should bemade to political  reasons  and to  the well-known and  declared  policy  of  HisMajesty&apos;s  Government to  assist in the  political and economic rehabilitation ofAustria.                                                                     A. E.     Foreign Office, February 24, 1936.
ANNEX 1.                    Sir John Simon to M. Franckenstein.-(Extract.)Sir,                                        Foreign Office, February 3, 1934.    I HAVE carefully considered the note of the 17th ultimo in which you were good enough to address to me certain suggestions for the development of trade relations between the United Kingdom and Austria.    2.  His Majesty&apos;s Government are desirous of taking all such steps as maybe possible to assist Austria to improve  her financial and economic situation, and thereby to meet the critical situation in which she has been placed.  It is in thisspirit that His Majesty&apos;s Government have examined the proposals contained inthe memorandum which formed  the enclosure to your note.        ******                                                           JOHN SIMON.ANNEX 2.                    Telegram from Sir W. Selby (Vienna).(No. 11.)                                         Vienna, January 30, 1936.    YOUR telegram No. 9.    In my despatch No. 15 E. I referred to increased favourable British trade balance for  first  eleven  months  of  1935 as  compared  with  1934,  which Icharacterised as unfortunate, using the term with reference to Austrian economic difficulties, to which I have on several occasions drawn your attention.    Value of Austrian exports  of  manufactured goods to the United  kingdom has decreased a good deal, 81 million Schillinge in 1931 to 30 million in first elevenmonths of 1935, and that of hats and hoods from nearly 8 million to  only slighty more than 3 million.  Hats and hoods remain,  however,  most important exportarticles to United Kingdom to-day.    I would therefore really deplore this additional duty  in any case,  and  more so to-day, when we are especially anxious for our advice to be listened to on thesubject of co-operation  in the Danube  area and  whenas settlement of live claimsseems to indicate that Austrian  Government are, in general, anxious to meet ourwishes within their limitations.    While from British industrial point of view Austrian  hat exports are a secondary matter  to the Austrians, they  are of greatest  importance.   Proposedduty is accordingly certain not  only to cause unfavourable comment, but also toreceive wide attention here.    Moreover,  I would  observe that recent Credit Anstalt settlement will furtherburden the Austrians  considering the adverse  general payment of balance to united Kingdom.    During the past year my commercial counsellor  has received many complaintsfrom  both officials and business men of  crippling effects, particularly  on hatindustry, of existing British  duties.    (Repeated  to  The Hague, No. 5, Saving.)ANNEX  3.                    Telegram from Mr. Hadow (Prague).&apos;(No. 2.   Secret.)                                  Prague, January 30, 1936.    YOUR telegram No. 8.    In  the  course of private conversation yesterday President of  the  Republicindicated clearly to me that economic conditions were playing an increasingly important part in internal situation of  Czechoslovakia  and that his chance ofhis gradually drawing both Slovaks and German Czechs into co-operation with
the Government depended largely upon bettering economic conditions in theirrespective districts.    Chief  manufacturing centres  for  felt hats and  shapes  are Prague,  Brno,Strakonice (South Bohemia) and Novy Jicin (Silesia).  The  first three of theseare Czech districts, the last German speaking, but so  fa;r as I can ascertain, the factories are mostly in Jewish hands.   Abolition of the fez in  Turkey has alreadycaused serious difficulties to Strakonice in particular,  and closure or restriction of important British markets will mean a serious outcry and much suffering.    M. Benes told me categorically that,  if Great Britain wished to help  and support Czechoslovakia, by far the most  effective means of  so doing would beby keeping open her markets  to the Czech goods.    Particularly is this desirable if, as indicated in your telegram No. 1, Czecho-slovakia is  to be  encouraged to make economic  concessions to Austria at theexpense largely of her exports.    I therefore strongly urge that all possible resistance be made to recommenda-tions of Import Duties Advisory Committee.   If  unsuccessful, we must expectfurther application  of principle  already  enunciated publicly  by the PrimeMinister, that &quot; Czechoslovakia cannot buy  where she cannot sell.&quot;    (Repeated to  Vienna, Saving.)

</content>
</cab>
