<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/260/0 images: 626-628</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1936.SECRET.Copy  No,CP. 59  (36).CABINET.GERMANY.  PROPOSED INCREASE IN THE UNITED KINGDOM DUTIES ON DRESSED LEATHER.         Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    THE Import Duties Advisory Committee have submitted.a recommendation,.dated the 14th October,  1935, for the increase of United Kingdom import duties on certain  kinds of dressed leather by 15, per cent, ad valorem,  making a totalduty of 30 per cent,  ad  valorem., Final consideration has been delayed pending a decision, on the principle of  the  application of increased import duties  to&quot; sanctionist &quot; countries.  This has now been. disposed of by interdepartmentalagreement; but there remains the question of the connexion between the proposed increase of duty and  our general policy towards  Germany, which is the subject ofthe following submission.                                . .... The reason for the proposed increase of duty is protection  for the Britishindustry against the recent intensification of foreign competition.  The recom-mendation  states that  &quot; unusually large quantities of calf  leather have beenimported at prices which appear to bear little relation to production costs.&quot;  Theimports in question come mainly from Germany, though  also from a number ofsmall suppliers,  including the  Netherlands, Hungary, Finland  and  Denmark.Total imports in  1935 were in  value   2,072,000, of which   926,000 came fromGermany, imports from,Germany having nearly doubled as compared Avith 1934.Apart from this, however, the Import Duties Advisory Committee recommenda-tion is thought likely to  affect some of the leather falling under the heading &quot; allother sorts &quot;in  our statistics, total imports  of  which from  Germany were 192,836 in 1935.    The Import Duties Advisory Committee consider that the 1935 figures  are:abnormal, and that the  value of the trade to  Germany should normally not bemore than   500,000  per annum.  They do not expect the proposed increase of duty to, stop  the trade altogether.    The fact remains, however,  that if the recommendation of the Import duties advisory Committee  is accepted, His Majesty&apos;s  Government will be increasing toa high protective  figure  a duty  on an import of major concern to German tradewith the express  purpose of curtailing the German market  in  Great Britain.Moreover, besides the leather duties, the Import Duties Advisory Committee are considering the recommendation in the near future of further duties on severallesser items  affecting a  volume of German trade roughly estimated at about 200,000,   The extent to which that market has continuously shrunk during thelast seven years is shown by the following figures : German Exports to Great Britain.    (In million reichsmarks.)1929193019311932193319341935 (estimated)1,3051,2191,134 446 406 383 360[12701]
     This continuing decrease must be borne in mind in considering the ImportDuties Advisory Committee recommendation.     From the point of view of advantage for United Kingdom export trade and security  for financial payments there may be much to be said for refraining fromreducing German  imports  into the United  Kingdom to a lower level,  but it isunderstood that the  Treasury and the Board  of  Trade, while appreciating  therisk, do not consider that it is sufficiently menacing for them to reject the ImportDuties Advisory Committee&apos;s recommendation on  these grounds  alone.   In this connexion, I would  draw  attention  to a telegram from  His Majesty&apos;s Charged&apos;Affaires at Berlin dated  the 1st February, a copy of which is attached to thismemorandum.  It  therefore remains  for  the Foreign Office to call attention tocertain political considerations involved.     The dwindling of exports  to  the United Kingdom at a time when export markets  are  of supreme importance  to the national  economy  and perhaps  to social stability has not gone without comment in Germany.   The Minister  of economics, in a review of  German trade relations  in  1935, after referring  tothe  satisfactory working  of the  Anglo-German  Payments  Agreement, called attention to the increases  in Customs duties  imposed by  the  United  kingdom during 1935  on German goods.  The cumulative effect of a number of new  or increased duties on trades which are individually of  no great size has contri-buted to  reduce German  exports  continuously,  even since the time when  thefirst imposition of import duties  and  the  fall  of the   sterling reduced thevalue of German  exports  to the United Kingdom  by considerably more thanone-half  between 1931 and 1932.  This cumulative effect has recently been pointedout to the Foreign Office in private representations from the German  Embassy.During  this period, moreover, total German exports have suffered a continuousdecline,  except for 1935, when they recovered slightly.  But even  in 1935 theywere only 32 per  cent, in value of  total exports in 1929.    Each additionalobstacle imposed by the United Kingdom therefore tends to the existing distressin Germany.     We  are at present engaged  at the Foreign Office in an examination of thepossibility of making a last determined effort to reach  a European  settlement inagreement with Germany and France.   It is  therefore specially  important at this time to consider the possible political consequences of an increase in our existingduties, however much  this may  be justified from  the  point  of view of Britishindustry.  His Majesty&apos;s  Ambassador at Berlin,  who was recently in london for the purpose of consultation,  has informed  me that, in his view, the increasein duty  to which I have referred might have an inflammatory effect in Germanyand possibly lead the Germans to suppose (quite wrongly) that we were beginning to indulge in a policy of pinpricks.  It is even  conceivable, in his view,  that suchaction on our part  might give a handle to those Nazi extremists who are believed to be in  favour of the German Governments indulging in some retaliatory act.     We  cannot, I  think, disregard a warning of this sort from His Majesty&apos;ambassador;  and I  would therefore ask the Cabinet, before approving  thisrecommendation of the Import  Duties Advisory  Committee, most seriously  toweigh any economic advantages it may possess against the political disadvantagesand dangers to which I have referred.     If the Cabinet should, in fact, decide  that  the political  objections hereinadvanced are sufficiently strong  to warrant a rejection of the recommendation for the increased duty on  dressed leather, I  understand that it will be  necessaryto publish reasons for their decision.  In that event I would suggest  that  thereason given should be that, in view of the  special conditions governing Anglo-German  trade, requiring as they do the maintenance of German exports to thiscountry, the disadvantages of  the proposal on  general  grounds outweigh  theadvantages set forth  in the Import Duties Advisory Committee&apos;s recommendation.                                                                    A E.     Foreign Office, Febrtmry 24, 1936.
ANNEX.           Mr. Kirkpatrick to Mr.  Eden.-(Received February  1.)(No. 31.   Secret.)(Telegraphic.)                                   Berlin,  February 1,  1936.    YOUR telegram No. 24.    It is impossible to be certain  that the customs measures proposed would notexpose us  to counter-action  in  respect of payments agreement,  Dawes  and young Loans, &amp;c.  The exchange position in Germany  seems gradually to bebecoming  more difficult,  and  the  German Government is keenly  on the watchregarding measures likely to reduce German exports.   The Ministry of Economicsin a review of Germany&apos;s trade relations in 1935 after referring to the satisfactoryworking of the Anglo-German  Agreement  called attention to the increases incustoms duties imposed by  the United Kingdom  during 1935  on German goods.It is known  that Dr. Schacht would like to secure a reduction of  the  interest payments  on the Dawes and Young Loans  to British holders, though I do notthink under the existing conditions he would dare to press for this at the  riskof a  breakdown  of  the Anglo-German  Agreement.   The further substantialcustoms duties a,ffecting German exports  to  the United  Kingdom would be resented here, and might bring Dr. Schacht nearer to the  point of insisting  thatif the United Kingdom take measures  of reducing the exchange derived byGermany&apos;s internal exports Germans will not be able  to continue the full, if  any,Dawes and Young interest  to British holders.  Even  if he does not go so far as this the German  Government will strongly be tempted not to apply payments agreement  as generously as  they are now doing,   particularly  in respect of miscellaneous debts and repurchase of script.    The leather trade  in Germany is one of those which are chiefly dependenton exports, and short-time working has already been adopted in the trade owingto difficulties of maintaining  raw material  supplies,  and export markets.   Theeffect of a  further reduction of exports would be highly localised and immediatelyfelt by the trade.    On the other hand the German  Government desire both  to maintain goodpolitical relations with England and to preserve the payments agreement, whichis always quoted here as a  model  arrangement.   To rely on these  factors wouldbe a gamble.

</content>
</cab>
