<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/5/10 images: 190-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I ou   95&quot;--PHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET. Copy No.ftjP. (G)( 2+0)60.WAR CABINET.[The Shipping Situation in relation to the Ministry of Supply&apos;s programme memorandum by the Minister of SupplyaThe Minister of Shipping, in November last,  (W. P.   (g)(39) 89) estimated that it should be possible to ship to the U. K.2+7.0 million tons of imports in a full year.    Of this total he took 23.9 million tons to be an appropriate allocation for the raw materials v/ith which the Ministry of Supply is concerned.He now considers (wbpd(g) (2+0) 1+2) that it is not safe to assume that this 2+7 million tons will be available,  and he suggests that consumption should be cut down so that importationof materials for the Ministry of Supply could,  if necessary, bereduced by 10 per cent., i.e. , from 23.9 to 21,5 million tons.This 23.9 million tons does not represent the total requirements of raw materials as now estimated by the Ministry ofSupply.    The figure v/as probably based on an estimate of requirements for three months which was given to the Ministry ofShipping by the Ministry of Supply some months ago.    Since thenessential requirements, notably of iron and steel, have been rising^    and the revised requirements, based on the latest demands for materials from Government Departments and essential industries,would involve imports at the rate of 30^6 H million tons a year.It will therefore be seen that if, in accordance withthe Minister of Shipping&apos;s suggestion, consumption is to be cutdown in order to enable imports to be reduced to 21,5 million tons,SEThis excludes .78 million tons of molasses which, beingcarried in tankers, is a separate problem,1.

this will involve a reduction not of 10 per cent, hut of 30 percent., i. e. , from 30.6 to 21.5 million tons.These figures show the effects of the proposal for afull year.      But for the first year of war.  ending 31 si August,I9k0, the position may he much worse than this.      In trie first five months (according to the Trade Returns) about 7 million tonsof the raw materials included in the Ministry of Supply&apos;programme were imported.      If for the remaining period of seven months imports of raw materials came in at the suggested rate of21.5 million tons a rear, a further 12.5 million tons would be imported - making a total for the first year of only 19.5 million tons.It is perhaps not realised that the bulk of the Ministryof Supply&apos;s programme is covered from a shipping point of view bya very few materials, as is shown in the following table:-million tons.Iron and Steel and allied Materials (including ores) 1h. 9Timber 6.5Paper and Paper-making materials 3.0Textiles 1..9Non-Ferrous Metals 1.7Materials for SulphuricAcid and FertilisersAll Other Materials 1.2Total 30.6It will be seen that iron and steel and timber together make upmore than two-thirds of the total shipping requirements,  and onthe present figures add up to almost exactly the allocationsuggested by the Minister of Shipping for all raw materials.Of the requirements for paper and paper-making materials.

the largest item is for wood pulp (1.7 million tons),      Atpresent the hulk of this material comes from the Baltic and norway, nearly all in neutral vessels.      The imports of wood pulp have averaged 126,000 tons a month since the outbreak ofv/ar, which is not very far short of the requirement of 1h0,000tons a month.      Even if the importations of wood pulp from northern Europe were materially reduced it does not follow thatthe neutral vessels would be available for service elsewhere/here,since the main objects of their sailing to the U. K.   at all are,no doubt, to maintain their own exports and to. supply their own industries with coal.To reduce the timber programme v/ould be extremelydifficult.      Of the 605 million tons required, nearly hO per cent,is represented by pit props and pit wood, stocks of which are ata dangerously low level.      No noticeable reduction in theprogramme of shipment during the coming year could be made withouta serious risk of reducing coal production,      For the rest, the requirement of general soft woods, which to a large extentrepresents building timber and timber required for cases for theexport trade,  is only sufficient to maintain a very reduced rateof consumption, which has been arrived at by applying drasticcuts to all demands.Finally, I should like to add a word about iron andsteel as it accounts for some 50 per cent,  of the requiredtonnage-      The total demands for steel in various forms, as presented to the Ministry of Supply, amount to 1h million tons,including 009 million tons for home industry, 0n5 million for france,  and 2 million tons for exports.      This figure has beenreduced to 1io3 million tons by drastic cutting in the PriorityCommitteec      This revised supply figure of 11,3 million tons canonly be achieved if the present programme of imports of iron ore,scrap and semi-finished steel is fulfilled.     A reduction in theimports of ore could be met to some extent by installing further

blast furnace capacity based on home ores, and this is underconsideration;    but at best some twelve months must elapse before such furnaces could be in operation,,     Meanwhile theMinistry of Shipping have not found it possible to meet thepresent programme, and in consequence stocks of ore have fallendangerously low and in some places furnaces are actually beingdamped down on account of shortage of imported ores.It is clear that if imports of raw materials must bereduced as proposed by the Minister of Shipping, not only mustthe reduction of consumption of all kinds of commodities by thecivil population be much more severe but, in addition, there mustbe a reduction in the supply of materials below the levelnecessary to our present war effort and to the maintenance of exports even at their existing level.The Adelphi23. 2. hO.-(init. )      . L. B.


</content>
</cab>
