<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/75/ images: 13-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETCopy No. | of 3 CopiesMOST CONFIDENTIAL RECORDTOCC(82) 17th CONCLUSIONSWednesday 14 April 1982FALKLANDISLANDSPreviousReference:CC(82) 16thConclusions,Minute 3THE PRIME MINISTER said that any leaks of the latest ideas forsettling the Falklands crisis could prove fatal to the mission beingundertaken by the United States Secretary of State, Mr Haig, who hadhimself been insistent on this point.    On his first visit to London on8 April, the strength of British feeling about the Argentine invasion hadbeen brought home to him.    He had been left in no doubt about Britishobjectives:  withdrawal of Argentine forces;   restoration of Britishadministration;  and the wishes of the Falkland Islanders to be para-mount in any subsequent negotiation.    Mr Haig had then left for BuenosAires and returned with a set of proposals, the status of which wasunclear.    He appeared to have discussed some but not all of theseproposals with President Galtieri.    They were now embodied in a draftAgreed Memorandum, to be signed by Britain and Argentina. Thisdraft had been extensively discussed on 12 April between Mr Haig andthe British Ministers most closely concerned.    Agreement on arevised version of it had been reached.    This envisaged the withdrawalof all military and security forces from the Falkland Islands and theDependencies within a period of two weeks and banned their reintroduc-tion.    Forces involved in the crisis would return to their normalduties.    An interim Commission would be set up, consisting ofrepresentatives from the United States, the United Kingdom andArgentina, each supported by a small staff.    It would occupy a head-quarters on the Islands (not Government House) and each representativewould fly his national flag.    The traditional local administration wouldcontinue, including the Islands&apos; Executive and Legislative Councils, toeach of which one representative of the Argentine population would beadded.    Their decisions would be submitted to, and expeditiouslyratified by, the Commission.    The Commission would also beempowered to make recommendations to the British and ArgentineGovernments in the fields of travel, communications and trade betweenArgentina and the Islands;   but either Government would be free toreject such recommendations.    Meanwhile the various restrictions andsanctions imposed on Argentina as a result of the invasion would belifted.    The interim period would end on 31 December 1982, by whichtime negotiations were to be completed for a final settlement.    It hadbeen made clear to the Americans that Britain would regard self-determination for the Islanders as an essential element in suchnegotiations.    Mr Haig had intended to fly to Buenos Aires during thenight of 12-13 April.    But he had altered his plans on learning by1SECRET
SECRETtelephone that the Argentines were once more adopting an extremeposition, under which they would appoint the Governor of the Islandsand would be assured of sovereignty at the end of the interim period.He now appeared to have shifted them back to a more moderate stance,but was rightly not willing to visit Buenos Aires again until the prospectswere clearer.    He had therefore returned to Washington, after furthermeetings with British Ministers, on 13 April.    His latest suggestion, inthe face of Argentine pressure, had been to amend the provision fornegotiations on a long-term settlement to include a reference to UnitedNations General Assembly Resolution No 1514 (XV), which called for thedecolonisation of dependent territories and upheld both the principle ofterritorial integrity (which underlay Argentina&apos;s claim to the Falklands)and the principle of self-determination.    This possibility was now beingstudied.    It was not yet clear whether overall agreement could bereached.    Any document embodying such agreement would clearly beinterpreted differently by Britain and Argentina.    But the presentproposals had the major virtues of securing both Argentine withdrawaland the maintenance of the infrastructure of British administration.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that theUnited States was anxious to avert a conflict in the South Atlantic inwhich the Soviet Union was already dabbling.    All the evidence was thatthe Argentines had miscalculated.    United Nations Security CouncilResolution No 502 and the European Community import embargo hadbeen heavy and unexpected blows.    Commonwealth support for Britainhad been strong.    These pressures, together with the British TaskForce, had led them to contemplate a negotiated settlement under whichArgentine troops would be withdrawn.    It would be a remarkableachievement if this could be brought about, at a time when Britain&apos;smilitary position was still weak.    Negotiations were now at a verydelicate stage.    Mr Haig&apos;s next visit to Busnos Aires would be crucial.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that there were noArgentine naval vessels in the Maritime Exclusion Zone (MEZ) althoughthe build-up of forces on the Islands was continuing.    The Argentinepropaganda machine was active, for example putting it out that the air-field at Port Stanley had been extended to take Mirage aircraft.Britishnuclear-propelled submarines were enforcing the MEZ. IfArgentine warships entered the MEZ, it would be the clearest sign thatthey had abandoned the peace process.    The British Task Forcecontinued on its way south;   Mr Haig had agreed that it was right to addto pressue on the Argentinians in this way.    He himself would announcelater that day the doubling of the number of Harriers in the Task Forceand the adding of HMS Intrepid to the amphibious capability. Militaryplanning was proceeding on a worst case basis.    Argentine militarydifficulties should not be underestimated, notably in supplying andsustaining the morale of the forces on the Island during the winter.2SECRET
SECRETIn discussion there was general support for the manner in which the dis-cussions had been conducted, acceptance of the need for secrecy andrecognition that the best way forward lay in diplomatic and economicpressures on Argentina, backed by the Task Force continuing on its way.In Parliament it should be made clear that British policy aimed at thesupervised withdrawal of all forces from the Islands and an interimperiod of local administration leading to a final settlement in which thesticking point for us would be that the wishes of the Islanders wereparamount.In further discussion the following points were made -a. Although at the time of his first visit Mr Haig had tried toadopt a position of strict neutrality, by the time he left he hadrecognised the important principle which was at stake, namelywhether or not naked aggression should be allowed to succeed.Nevertheless, although he understood our arguments, Mr Haighad to maintain his position as a go-between.    He had to avoidany appearance of collusion with Britain if he was to carry theArgentinians.b. Whatever solution might emerge from negotiation, theArgentines would present it as some kind of victory and as theattainment of at least part of their objectives by military means.Their calculation might be that they would need two bites of thecherry instead of one.    It was vital to prevent a second bite.Continued United States involvement would be very important inthat context.c. Britain had been the victim of unprovoked aggression. Itwould not be right to accept that that had placed the Argentines ina better negotiating position.    The aggressor must not bepermitted to benefit from his aggression.    The wider principlewas even more important than the fate of the Islanders. Ifaggression was shown to pay, it would be a disastrous precedentfor the world as a whole.    Against this, it was argued that thesituation had to be dealt with as it existed.    Britain would needthe help of world opinion to get the Argentines to withdraw.There was also a risk of losing the broad support of Britishpublic opinion if a purely military solution were pursued and theprospect of all compromise ruled out.d. In any settlement it would be important to safeguardBritish title to South Georgia, the South Sandwich Islands and theBritish Antarctic territory.    Alease-backarrangement for theFalkland Islands might strengthen Argentina&apos;s territorial claimsin the Antarctic, which were sectorally based.3SECRET
SECRETe. It seemed possible that financial sanctions againstArgentina were not being pressed to the full for fear ofprecipitating her default.    This was understandable from thepoint of view of the banking community.    But care should betaken that Argentina was not for this reason enabled to sustainher present policy of aggression more easily.f. When the Task Force was within striking distance of theFalkland Islands, an air exclusion zone would be necessary aspart of a blockade and as a precondition to any assault.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that adiplomatic solution on the lines outlined would be a considerable prize.The withdrawal of Argentine forces would have been secured withoutmilitary action.    Argentina would gain representation on the interimCommission and on the local Councils;  and a commitment to negotia-tions to decide the definitive status of the Islands by the end of the year,although without any commitment to a transfer of sovereignty. Repug-nant as it was that the aggressor should gain anything from hisaggression, this seemed an acceptable price to pay.    But it would becrucial to ensure against a second invasion and the best way ofachieving this appeared to be to involve the United States Government inthe enforcement of the interim agreement and in the security of theIslands thereafter.The Cabinet -Took note.Cabinet Office7 June 19824SECRET

</content>
</cab>
