<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 8-8</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 8 (48) 29th January, 1948

1. Local Government Bill: Co-operative Societies.

A.B. Have agreed revised clause. Copies handed round.

L.P. has, however, raised the point tht. shares might be well above nominal value. But a) he wd. still have to disclose interest b) 1/100th wd. still limit interest in co.

In spite of this, I think it wd. be unwise to go back to clause limited to Co-ops. L.P. wanted it brought back.

H.M. There is scope for agreement.

Co-ops are straightforward.

May be said = we are letting in people with substantial financial interest.

R.S.C. Limit of 1/100th is surely a complete answer.

A.V.A. Co-ops wd. be content if limit were lowered to 1/200th.

H.M. Shareholder with £210 nominal cdn’t vote. £200 nominal might be £10 actual.

Agreed.

2. Parliament.

H.M. Business for next week.

3. National Health Service: Doctors.

A.B. If demand made for debate on B.M.A., it wd. be good to promise time at once. I wd. welcome a debate.

Clear tht. vast majority of drs. don’t want it.

P.M. Serious. Always told before tht. younger men at least favoured it.

A.B. They are campaigning now for more concessions. Later, when they have to decide as individuals whr. each shall come in, B.M.A. pressure will relax.

H.M. Worried. Talked with A.B. &amp; W.W.

Atmosphere of bitterness &amp; mutual distrust.

Not getting a reasonable discussion.

A.B. is issuing Press statement before plebiscite.

I wanted Jameson to give objective b’cast. May be wise to drop this because alleged can’t be objective.

46

A.B. Middle &amp; left-wing Press is on our side. Can’t appease the rest.

P.M. When do you want debate?

A.B. Soon as possible. Tories won’t ask for it: they don’t want to argue in H/C. because know dr’s case is weak.

A. Sustained information campaign regud to weaken dr.’s opposition.

They don’t know what is proposed. Hammer in facts betwn. now &amp; July. Can’t begin too early.

A.V.A. Only one pt. of substance = specialists’ remuneration.

A.B. But it’s B.M.A., not we, who decided to take plebiscite now.

Wd. like the Debate next week.

H.M. Will consider: may have to be week afterwards.

But if Tories won’t ask for it how do we get it? Do Govt. take responsibility – Motion or Adjournment.

W.W. Wait &amp; get ques. put to-day. See how it goes?

[Exit A.B.

4. Parliament Bill: House of Lords Reform.

A. H.L. debate adjourned. Explained circs.

Suggns in debate about length of time. W.W. &amp; H.M. are considering whr. any concessions cd. be made: it wd. be Cttee point.

Salisbury’s line = can’t wait for Cttee for this because we shd. be acceptg. principle of Bill by giving Second Rdg. Thus wants discns on composn of H/L. to begin before Second Rdg. If so, he will agree to pass Bill this Session. He wants to adjourn debate next week = he can carry that if he moves it.

Then he wants discussions a) on powers, limited to ques. of time and b) to see what prospects there are of real progress with ques. of reform.

Samuel willing to accept Bill if assured on a) alone.

I’ve said tht. if they throw it out, we will discuss nothing.

Suggest further talks (P.M., H.M. &amp; I.) to see whr. we can persuade them to give 2nd Rdg. by promising to begin talks at once.

Don’t want Govt. to appear unreasonable.

P.M. “Timing a Cttee point”. It isn’t because whole Bill is on timing.

Must indicate attitude on 2nd Rdg., towards amount of time.

Steel Bill as illustration. Introduced Nov ’48 = passed June ’49. etc., etc.

H.M. This illustration is all wrong (!)

47

Tho’ I agree time-table on Steel Bill is right.

R.S.C. But they have had all the time from 1st Rdg.

A. No. The trouble more often arises on amendment.

R.S.C. Of course they cd. delay a wrecking amendment as long as they choose.

A. Actual point of difference doesn’t get defined until late.

P.M. Ready to accept any adjustment consistent with principle that a Govt. shan’t be held up in legn in its last 2 years.

H.M. Primary ques: are we willing to discuss that.

R.S.C. Only that?

H.M. And reform, too.

H.M. Point a) must be settled in Cttee on this Bill.

Ready to have a) and b) discussed. But must be careful on a) – though they have complaint re late arrivals. We are vulnerable over last Session’s late arrivals.

G.T. Careful not to give away any principle, by implication. Don’t you concede right to challenge policy by conceding more time.

C.E. Not so much in H/L. points. Controversial points in a Bill are well known from moment of 2nd Rdg. in H/C. I wdn’t make any concession on time. We have temporarily lost initiative: we can recover it by allowing time to pass &amp; enact it under Parlt. Act. That wd. mean, however, disordering remaing. Sessions.

Fatal to Govt.’s reputn to decline to enter conference.

But must make it clear we are conceding nothg. on Bill.

If we are to discuss reform, other things must be considered e.g. Orders. Whole position between 2 Chambers must be considered. Opposition Leaders shd. therefore understand that, if we are going to discuss composition, at all, we are opening whole field of powers as well.

J. Can get Bill by 1949: not earlier, save by consent.

On period: stick to 12 months but add proviso tht. must be in H/L. at least x Parly. days. W’out that, H/C. cd. cheat by deliberately holding back Bill.

Settlement by agreement will last. If imposed, Tories will alter it.

Democracy is govt. by discussion.

Diffy. They undertake to ques. our Bill this Session: why shdn’t Govt. accept offer to discus? That is diff. argument to meet.

48

R.S.C. That’s O.K. for discn of this Bill – point a).

But point b) opens a much wider field: discussion provoked in Party &amp; in country.

J. Wd. it if we said – can’t reform H/L, unless this Bill passed therefore stronger H/L. wd. need more powers.

G.A.I. Controversy started already. No harm in discussing. Support J.’s view.

P.M. If H/L. is to be reformed, better done in this Parlt.

A.V.A. Before a Genl. Election?

H.M. Yes: for all we have in mind is a) abolition of hereditary principles b) life Peers c) women. Tht wd. be broadly acceptable to Labour Party save minority of abolitionists shd. mention it to Party &amp; Executive.

P.M. Merely tht. we are going to discuss w’out commitment: we don’t want any “line” at present.

A. Swinton has offered to pass or reject Bill this Session, if we will discuss, so that the “Ellis” point won’t arise.

R.S.C. Some value in that.

P.M. We shd. lose nothing by discussing.

R.S.C. But shd. make our condns clear in writing.

Letter to Salisbury with copy to Samuel.

To be drafted by P.M., with J., H.M. and A. } Agreed.

Draft to come to Cabinet on Monday }

P.M. Stand firm m’while on getting 2nd Rdg. (if we are going to discuss). Enough to get assurance they will accept or reject Bill this Session.

A.V.A. If you want H/L. reform in this Parlt. go on &amp; pay for it.

If you don’t, drop it.

Agreed: don’t insist on 2nd Rdg. as condn.

“deal with Bill finally this Session” is better formula.

[Exit C.E., W.W.

49

5. Antarctic: Deception Island.

P.M. Lr. from Govt. Not in friendliest way: surprised he hadn’t bn. there. Avoidance wd. do more harm than good.

No risk of armed conflict.

Agreed: let him visit Deceptn Island.

[Enter H.McN.

6. Palestine.

P.M. Not necessary for Cab. to consider all details, wh. have bn. considered by E.P.C. But sterling area ques. important.

R.S.C. Pal. &amp; Trans-Jordan inextricable on currency. Must put Pal. out. Must therefore extrude both. Shall, however, tell Trans-Jordan she can creep back later.

Will be indicated to P.M. of Trans-Jordan while he is here.

H.McN. Can we inform State Dpt. &amp; Ty. in U.S. a week ahead?

R.S.C. Yes. At v. highest level only in State Dpt.

H.McN. Fear we shan’t be able to prevent heavy criticism in W’ton.

C.J. Want to reserve my point (on E.P.C.) re Palestine Service.

A. Inform Doms. at top level only?

R.S.C. Yes.

Ty. Repvc will have to go to U.S. for discns on finance with U.N. Commn. Will F.O. &amp; C.O. discuss “who” with Ty.

A.V.A. Oil. All right if it goes as in memo. But must watch it v. carefully.

R.S.C. Must depend how things go on the spot.

[Exit McN.

[Enter H.G. &amp; B.

7. Wages.

G.A.I. “Stability”. Various industies made long-term agreements. But some signs of breaking out now because of rising prices.

Reduction of hours – slowed down now.

Leaders are steady: may exercise more influence over rebels.

Misprint in para. 3.

50

C.P. 28.

G.A.I. Recommend a statement.

Diffy: observance of agreements in entirety. Agreemt. fixes a minimum. Some employers pay more. That starts trouble. Cotton is serious example. Recent award, designed to bring up lower paid workers &amp; had a clause deprecating relative increases to higher-paid. Dunlops have offered 10% increase &amp; employees to regard minimum rate as the rate. We shall be discouraging employers from giving any increased rates.

Wages in industries etc. related to Govt. e.g. Nat. &amp; local Govt. staffs. or where Govt. grant paid. Recommend here tht. we shd. declare tht. we won’t pay for wage increases automatically.

Shd. make our intentns &amp; policy clear to T.U.C. &amp; try to carry them with us.

On draft statement: wages and salaries passive.

R.S.C. Have prepd revised draft.

Concluded this is most we can say.

But handling is vital.

a) Treat as 1st class State paper.

b) Ensure tht. all Chairmen of Tribunals have it, publicly.

c) Intensive publicity.

Do it at once. Before Ec. Survey. And print as App. to that.

Try to get T.U.C. to accept it. Then show it to N.J.A.C. quickly.

Am speaking in Scotland next week. Wd. like this out first.

H.W. Time to consider wording?

Para. 15 seems too weak. We shd. say, not only refuse automatic increase in prices, but shall review whole ques. on increase of wages by reference to national objectives.

G.A.I. Cd. R.S.C., H.M., H.W. and I settle draft?

Agreed.

A. Clarify para. on relativity.

A.V.A. Inducements to under-manned industries etc., means tht. others won’t be content to stay lower. And will produce competitive attractions.

R.S.C. Covered in 12 (c) &amp; (d).

H.W. Stopped automatic increases already. e.g. in distribution.

On R.S.C. (b): have Govt. Secretaries to all Boards: from M/L. and Joint Secy. from Prodn Dpt. concerned. And they shd. be properly briefed.

Agreed.

51

H.W. This is only effective way of influencing Bds.

H.G. a) Make it clear what you mean by “under-manned” industries.

A.V.A. Wages movements, if it continues, will mean revision of Service pay.

H.M. We have bn. living in a fool’s paradise.

There’s been continuing cycle. There’s bn. too much readiness to press for shorter hours.

Support this course. Not sure it’s enough.

Main immediate need is to educate rank &amp; file. T.U. leaders should do more. Ministers shd. make more speeches.

Weakness of employers.

R.S.C. Due to full employmt.

Agreed: Revised draft to be proposed by H.M.,

R.S.C., G.A.I., H.W.

Cab. to approve Monday.

P.M. to make statement in H/C next week.

H.M. How do you square T.U.C. in the time?

G.A.I. I cd. do it on existing draft.

H.M. P.M., G.A.I., &amp; R.S.C. cd. do that.

R.S.C. Aim at P.M.’s statement on Thurs. next.

H.W. Have M/L got enough organn to “Grape Vine” impending wage changes? We shd. know before claim preferred?

G.A.I. Thro’ Req. investigating officers. But can’t move too soon.

Will, however, take matter up again.

Transport Workers Claims.

B. Latham’s view: can’t refuse to meet some part of claim.

Advance of 7/6 + increased Sunday over-time = 10/3 a wk.

This rejected. Posn will now be reported to M/L.

G.A.I. Will handle the other claim with view to Ct./Enquiry, wh. cd. cover both.

G.A.I. When do I inform E.P.C. of coming wage claims?

H.M. As soon as it shd. be taken seriously.

Too late if you wait until claim is made.

52

H.W. Prodn Dpt. shd. be told at once of any coming claims.

R.S.C. Agreed: the 2 Ministers shd. then bring to E.P.C. if issue arising on it.

And monthly reports on wage trends – for incln in fortnightly reports.

</content>
</cab>
