<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 9-9</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 9 (48) 2nd February, 1948

1. Parliament Bill: House of Lords Reform.

A. Discussions with Salisbury &amp; Samuel: on basis of this memo. – save “delay” was said in para. 1.

P.M. and L.P. didn’t like “delay” and substituted phrase now in memo.

Because they meant “delay” to cover public agitation. They are likely to be difficult about new words.

They may move again for adjournment of Debate.

P.M. Point of tactics. Advantage to us to get Bill a) early &amp; b) with consent. Tories don’t want to give away their posn before entering discns. Nor do we. We won’t give way.

Ques: Shd. we put fwd. para. 1. wh. Tories won’t accept. Or a different formula wh. they wd. accept. Words don’t matter, really.

A. Salisbury has now suggested –

“shall not extend to any powers other than those at present possessed by H/L.”

P.M. That implies nothing: our para. 1 implies tht. our Bill needs amendment.

H.M. Para. 3 (b) shd. govern para 1. as well.

Salisbury’s formula admits discn of any period up to 2 years, viz., existing Parlt. Act.

Fact is we aren’t yet agreed on para. 1. Does that matter for today’s debate in H/Lords? An agreement in advance between Party Leaders may make it more diff. to persuade Labour Party &amp; Executive. Suppose our para. 1 is contested openly to-day and we then get agreement off-stage to another formula, it may be easier for us. Moreover, if Tories reject our reasonable para. 1, they will put themselves wrong.

J. Tories will never accept para. 1.

Are you in a better posn if you put this fwd. &amp; later accept a wider formula. Or if you accept a wider formula now?

A. What Salisbury wants is time in wh. to force an Election.

R.S.C. Put alternative formula.

C.E. That wd. concentrate attention on the 12 months period. The only ques. we are willing to discuss is allocation of that period between the 2 Houses.

P.M. My formula doesn’t point to the 12 months. “limited to discn of the period for considn of measures by the H/Lds.”

54

H.M. Then put para. 1 &amp; hold P.M.’s formula in reserve.

A.V.A. Fear consequences of going on with H/L. reform. Diffies with own Party.

A.B. Support that. Press suggest Govt. are ready to consider measures of reform wh. will never be acceptable to our Party.

P.M. Tories are admitting H/L. is weak. Can we refuse to discuss means of making it more sensible?

A.V.A. That was covered by our original offer to discuss after passage of Bill.

H.M. Yes: but

a) we must discuss ques. of time, on Bill itself.

b) We must keep straight with public opinion &amp; seem to be reasonable.

P.M. On par. 1. I wd. prefer to have our reference to “differences between the 2 Houses”.

H.M. They are entitled to reasonable facilities for putting ammendmts. to H/C.

P.M. I agree.

C.E. Can’t have hard &amp; fast rules. Must be a working arrangement between Parties.

A. Then may I put my para. 1. as it stands: &amp; keep in reserve P.M.’s formula.

Agreed.

2. National Health Service.

A.B. Wd. like earliest possible debate. Hoped for Thursday next: but told that’s not possible.

W.W. It’s not. Demand for discn of Leather Order.

H.W. That Order cd. wait.

H.M. But it’s 2 major Bills that are really in the way.

A.B. shd. not have discussed Business with Opposn or said in reply to P.Q. he wd. welcome a debate.

55

A.B. On 2nd point, I made no promise. Cab. had said it wd. be good to have a debate. I cdn’t do less than welcome it – adding that time was for the Leader of H/C.

On 1st, merely informal talk with A.E. Not negotiation. And it was after my statement in H/C.

W.W. A.B.’s P.P.S. came to me &amp; suggd Thursday. I said Fri. or Mon. might be poss. Then I had a message tht. Tories had agreed to Thursday. This made my posn v. diff.

P.M. Any ques. of fixing days must go thro’ Ch. Whip or Leader.

On 2nd point, agree with A.B.

H.M. Even that embarrasses me.

A.V.A. In general, yes. But when gt. controversy is developing, diff. for Minister not to welcome it.

{ General view: A.B. was justified in this instance.

{ Agreed: debate in H/C on Mon. next.

{ Agreed: Govt. Motion as in draft.

H.M. Does para. 3 preclude further concessions?

R.S.C. No.

A.B. But we must not make any more after adverse vote in plebiscite.

A. Don’t want to be commd to that now.

A.B. Spokesman? Wd. like P.M. to intervene. B.M.A. are turning this into personal attack on me.

P.M. A.B. and A.W. to open &amp; close?

A.B. Yes.

P.M. I will intervene if course of debate so indicates.

[Enter H.G., Barnes

3. Wages Policy

H.M. Introduced memo. Mentioned new title: not merely an export ques.: need for Dpts. to follow up on prices etc.

Points: a) Para. 5. Interest rates on “socialised” stocks. Admissn we have cut shareholders interest. Propose to delete.

b) References to wages turned into personal incomes.

We have gone too far: some mention of wages shd. be re-inserted.

Designed as statement by P.M. on Thursday.

56

Need for follow-up publicity. Ministers shd. make speeches, on brief by Ec. Inf Unit. So shd. T.U. leaders etc.

T.U.C. – to be informed in advance, not asked to agree text.

A.V.A. Many points for argument in this. E.g. does it tie down piece rates etc. Do we know the answers to those ques.?

R.S.C. Yes: piece rates provide greater output with greater earnings.

T.W. Para. 11 (a). Shd. we not stop at end of 1st sentence?

R.S.C. People think you can do this. Must indicate why you can’t.

A.B. Is it wise to make such a statement at all?

No action in it. Nearest approach to action is what is said on price fixing.

Don’t dissent from views. But is it wise to declare them?

Employees will use it to support their rejection of wage claims. Will be debated in H/C. Sound portentous but contains nothing.

We have an oblign in socialised sector. But we run away from that.

R.S.C. Essential. Must face run-away inflation &amp; try to stop it.

We have decided we can’t intervene in wage-fixing outside limits of our ordinary actions. Are leavg. it to collective bargaining. Least we can do is to inform the Bds. etc., of our views.

G.A.I. Essential to say somethg. of this kind.

Dangerous situation.

Even transport dispute is getting out of hand.

Main point is para. 11 (a). Makes our position clear.

Necessary to make that clear.

Not sure, however, whr. P.M. shd. make such a big do of this.

Cdn’t we use it quietly?

R.S.C. Last sentence in para. 13 is State policy of some importance.

P.M. What do you do if processes continue – havg. said “not possible” in 11 (a).

R.S.C. 11 (a) relates to incomes of individuals.

H.M. Shd. prefer words which don’t bang that door so hard. E.g. omit “possible nor”.

A.B. I wd. like to go further than the memo. on public sector.

R.S.C. Can’t do more than price &amp; subsidy control w’out directly intervening in wage negotn. My own view was in favour of a central Tribunal: but that wasn’t accepted.

57

G.A.I. That can’t be adopted w’out drastic change of system – and introdn of compulsory arbitration in all cases.

R.S.C. “Govt. shd. be abreast of best employers”

H.M. You will have diffy over this.

Agreed: Substance of document.

Presentation.

G.A.I. Put it formally to N.J.A.C. Publish afterwards as such.

Otherwise are we consulting or informing?

T.U.C. statement. They only got P.M.’s reply the other day – not in time for conference to be held in Feb.

Wd. strengthen T.U.C. posn to handle it thro’ them.

R.S.C. Don’t handle this with industry alone.

Must be put over to country &amp; push it hard.

Must therefore be declared in Parlt. And by P.M. because we regard it as of 1st class importance.

N.J.A.C. is not an industrial Parlt.

H.M. See what G.A.I. is getting at. T.U.C. &amp; employers shd. know what is coming.

But this must be debated in H/C.

T.U.C. statement was tepid. And in spite of it there came claim fr. transport workers, printers - &amp; off we go.

Need is to force public and industry to face realities.

Hands of T.U.C. leaders must be strengthened thro’ education of their rank &amp; file.

P.M. Must be Parlt. statement.

But advance discn with T.U.C. means leakage.

And N.J.A.C. meet on Wed.

Can’t submit document. Will tell them what we intend.

Agreed: announce in H/C. on Wed., when N.J.A.C. are

meeting.

C.E. Must it be read orally? So v. long.

Cd. you have a short oral version &amp; print as W. Paper in full.

A.B. Have a W. Paper – introduced by a P.M. Question.

H.W. Debate? Can it await Economic Survey.

R.S.C. P.M. cd. start at para. 11 and read the rest. “In the circs. expld in a W. Paper…..”

58

P.M. No: that wd. omit all verbal references to prices, incomes etc.

Agreed: P.M. to announce Wed.

Warn H/C. members it’s coming cf. by P.Q. askg.

whr. statement is to be made = say “to-morrow &amp; long”.

[Exit A. and W.W.

[Enter. J.S. Hall. G. Strauss.

4. Steel Scrap.

R.S.C. to arrange for working party to go into whole ques. &amp; report.

To cover also ques. of ship-brkg. in R. Dockyards.

</content>
</cab>
