<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 14-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 15(48). 19th February, 1948.

1. Parliament. [Enter W.W.

H.M. Business for next week.

[Exit W.W.

[Enter B., G.S., J.S.

H.G., Hall.

2. Food Prices.

R.S.C. Wd. have come in 29/2. in ordinary course.

Agreed with M/F. unwise in view of stabilisation policy.

Agreed p’pone 2 mos. Will cost £2 m. this year: £7 m. if it goes on

next financial year.

Whole ques. will have to be considered before Budget.

Agreed.

3. Economic Affairs.

R.S.C. Index of Prodn. Same results from Cambridge Survey (Times).

V. interesting tht. increase 7% over same period in ’46. despite

fuel crisis. V. encouraging.

T.W. But man-power increasing in ’47 because discharge from Forces.

R.S.C. No-one wd. expect so large an increase in productivity to be m’tained.

Coal.

Vol. absenteeism rising. Sat. workg. suspended at some pits.

But output at rate of 2.7 m. tons p.a. – cpd. 211 target.

H.G. Not so bad when normal seasonal decline is taken into a/c.

Steel scrap.

Diffy. with Steel Bd.

G.S. Hoping to smooth it over. [Exit C.E.

Thought it was their function to inform Cabinet.

Agriculture.

Spring sowings must be increased if we are to get wheat target.

T.W. Dec. was good month. Much will have bn. sown since figures of

4 Dec. We shd. reach target.

R.S.C. B/Payments.

£66 m. or 12 m. above last qutr. ’47 –

Egypt drawings. Gold drawings by Belgium. Doms. doing well, tho’ Austr. cd. do more still.

76

Genl. Trade Position.

119.5 m. But imports even higher.

H.W. Longer w. month. At 26 days, still highest since war &amp; 28% above

1938.

R.S.C. U.S. prices. Won’t help us much pro tem. because fixed contracts for

purchase fr. elsewhere.

H.W. Cotton yarn. 15-36 for following week. New record broken again.

Cotton is moving: &amp; yarn no longer b’neck. Can go all out for

increase all round.

Wool is doing even better. Get off to earlier start. Back to 90% as

cpd. with 70% in cotton.

E.B. Told Yorks. are jealous at excessive attention on amenities etc. in

Lancs.

H.W. Textiles Cttee began on Lancs: will turn to Yorks. next.

Yorks. won’t mind tht. Lancs. is so bad it needs concentrated

attentn.

G.S. Steel production at record levels.

H.M. Building. Are the workers coming free?

A.B. There is growing unemplt. in industry. Movemt. starting (Luton,

Newcastle etc.) of demonstrations tht. labour, materials etc., are

available if permission cd. be given to build.

Housing p’mme in danger of becoming unbalanced the other way.

Think target cd. be raised in ’49 to 180/200.000 vice 140.000.

If timber permits.

Otherwise, danger of losing transferable labour. Wd. wish to see

hard core of skilled men kept together, by raising maintenance

work.

A.W. The older men (65 &amp; up) are dropping out of industry altogether

because can’t turn to other trades.

T.W. From May we can absorb some into agric. bldg.

A.B. No: for the slack is in urban areas. If you push agric. bldg. too fast,

you will starve rural housing.

R.S.C. Use gang labour on this.

H.M. Index/Prodn. Can figures p. man/hour be obtained from some industries.

77

R.S.C. You can’t get it in detail.

H.M. Cotton. Publicity. Mtg. with P.M.

H.W. That is part of publicity plan. But must get some adminve ques.

settled first. Timing of publicity drive must be carefully

fixed. Due to begin 12/3: &amp; early Apl. appeal for over-time.

Coal Exports. U.S. repve at Geneva has agreed to recommend export

of 9 m. vice 13 m. from U.S. in next quarter. If that goes thro’ it’s O.K. in short run.

Danger will be writing much free coal into Marshall.

[Exit J.S.

4. Wages Policy.

a) Information on Claims.

H.M. This won’t do. Friendly intervention isn’t possible after formal

claim lodged.

Rpts. when available: can’t they go to Production Cttee, so that

Ministers may be aware.

P.M. As in brief. Want more “grape vine”.

G.A.I. x/ Then I had better make a periodical [weekly] report to Prodn Cttee

saying what we know.

A.B. Shd. we not tell the negotiating bodies in public sector to report as

soon as a claim is lodged. That is where wage cycle begins.

T.W. Agriculture. Resolns passed by Branches askg. for increased wages &amp;

reduced hours. Will culminate in annual Conf. in May. Value

of early reporting to Prodn Cttee wd. be tht. analysis of relativities

etc., cd. be made well in advance – for benefit of Ministers.

A.B. And Prodn Dpts. and Boards shd. also feed in information.

E.B. Danger of M/L. interfering with T.U. leaders unofficially.

V. serious situation will arise.

Either official intervention above board or none at all.

Will undermine integrity &amp; authority of T.U. leaders.

H.M. Govt. must face facts.

Movemt. becomes official and claims are made. (4 claims here for

reduced hours.) Then Govt. can’t move a hand because it’s

intervention.

All I ask is tht. P. Cttee shd. know early enough to consider wtr. there

is any action we can take.

Can’t control everything but wages &amp; leave that to laissez faire.

78

Agreed: a) periodical report as at x/.

b) all public Boards to report to M/Labour all

applns for increases of remuneration by

organised groups (incldg. salaried workers as

well as wage earners).

b) Enquiries about Price Increases.

G.A.I. Must be uniform line of reply by all Dpts.

Example: Catering wages. Bd. has fixed all details, after 5 years’

work, to start in March 1st. Bd. ask me if prices can be raised or

will I cancel Order. I can’t.

Transport also.

P.M. Issue = how far are we take a hand in this.

H.W. This is v. diff. Was to have bn. explored by officials this p.m.

Can’t avoid being consulted in advance. If we refuse, they will agree

an increase subject to Dpt. approving price increase.

Experience in past. Coal in spring ’44, when owners made rash

concessions subject to price increase &amp; strikes followed when

Govt. w’held the increases.

T.W. Special Review. Ask for no decisions this a.m. Cdn’t affect special

review – tho’ wd. affect annual review.

A.B. a) Surely M/L. must warn, if asked, on basis of W. Paper.

Otherwise, worst kind of syndicalism.

b) Bldg: both sides saw me this wk. &amp; suggd the 3rd shd. be put

on wages until result of piece-work seen. I’ve said it can’t be

put on tenders: must come out of productivity.

Same with Catering. Don’t let it go autom. on to meals.

R.S.C. That is what W. Paper says. Don’t let us advise on appln to

part-cases. Right time to decide “on merits” is when claim

settled &amp; appln for price increase made.

Only diff. case = undermanned industries. We must advise if asked

wtr. an industry is key or not. And M/L. shd. do so.

B. Transport. Claim will come to a head this p.m.

London Execut. have offered equivalent of 10/6 p. wk. increase.

Reported as dispute to M/L. because Union wdn’t accept.

Executive won’t go further. But have not w’drawn original

offer. If Union accept, they can have it. And effect on new

policy will be serious. But how can Executive w’draw offer,

save on direction from Minister.

Minister must choose between leaving alone &amp; risking increase and

directly intervening.

R.S.C. This = diff. issue altogether.

E.B. Totally against giving any informn in advance of Govt’s intentions.

79

Threatens whole T.U. movement. Bulk of wage increases in

past has come out of efficiency not price. I have always refused

as T.U. leader to combine with employer in approach to Govt.

Catering. No interference with legal machinery.

Joint approaches re prices: war-time attitude of mind due to

controls (!). Get away from that.

We shd. say: no guarantee of price increase: this must be decided

on merits of industry. If Govt. are responsible, there shd. be

proper machinery for costing.

H.W. Two points arise re approaches to Govt.

a) will you give an increase related to profit? Can’t say in

advance; need costings etc.

b) is this an undermanned industry? On this, you must be

prepared to say wtr. Govt. regard it as key.

This is my view. [Different from memo.]

A.W. What about claims by Police &amp; Fire Services. Claim to be

undermanned.

These surely shd. be resisted.

Go for raising real wages by increasing prices – as Chancellor

proposes.

Nothing to be got out of profits.

P.M. Public sector is the nub. What wages there? Any increase must

therefore go on to consumer. Ques. is: what firmness are we

to show towards claims in that area?

A.B. Problem: machinery to produce bankruptcies under full employmt.

I want to see 30.000 bankruptcies in bldg. industry.

Transport. Can’t you tell Executive they must find the money out

of economies. Tell them that in advance.

B. They have bn. told Govt. wd. be reluctant to increase fares.

R.S.C. Transport: diff. transitional case. Wd. be wrong to try to stop the

increase. But cd. they make a gesture, of p’poning a part,

because of W. Paper.

B. Deakin wants to defer such a gesture until after T.U.C. mtg.

Agreed: Stand on W. Paper. Reject increases condl on price

increases.

Inter-departmental arrangemts. to be handled by E.E.B. Cttee.

5. Use of Naval Dockyards. [Exit H.G.

H. As in Memo.

Sale of warships v. profitable: can’t be done w’out refit.

A.B. Can Prodn Cttee have a look at details.

80

R.S.C. Organn of dockyards: premium system for civil work etc.

Believe there is some surplus capacity.

Need for detailed discussion. Let it go to Prodn Cttee.

</content>
</cab>
