<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 29-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 30(48). 29th April, 1948.

1. Parliament.

H.M. Business for next week.

Criminal Justice Bill: House of Lords.

A. Conservatives will have free vote, incldg. Fr. Bench.

My plan = free for back-Benches, but Govt. Fr. Bench to support

H/C. vote.

H.M. A bit diff. in view of H/C. vote. Diff. to tie Ministers in H/L. when

those in H/C. were free to abstain and 44 did.

C.E. I have now announced with Cab. authority tht. Govt. accept decision

of H/C.

If H/L. delete Cl. 1., I shall have to stand on my announcement of

Govt. policy. Bad enough: but worse if Ministers in H/L.

have meanwhile indicated by abstention tht. they don’t accept

Govt.’s latest decision.

No free vote in H/C. on next occasion, after all.

A. b) Abolition of trial by Peers. Can I accept?

C.E. Yes. We refrained only because we thought it better for H/L. to ask

for it.

J. See what Tories will do in H/C. In 1936 or thereby W.S.C. decline to

support such a Bill, carried in H/L, pending wholesale reform of

H/L.

2. Cabinet’s Wedding Present to Their Majesties.

P.M. Read lr. of thanks from Lascelles.

3. National Health Service.

A.B. Latest estimate of plebiscite. In Scotland clear majority in favour of

Bill. In E. &amp; W. posn still uncertain. But I’m confident.

4. Housing Programme.

A.B. E.P.C. contemplated announcemt. before Scarboro’ conference.

Plowden says inopportune.

P.Q. now by Chas. Smith. Propose to answer: final figures can’t

be given until timber posn can be foreseen, after giving

152

explann of addl. approvals. Agreed.

5. Fascism: Mosley Meeting.

C.E. Mtg. Sat. in E. Ldn. No power to prevent.

But intends procn after. Met. Pol. have submd Order banning

procns in that area. I have consented. Will announce.

6. House of Lords Reform.

P.M. Conference broken down. Will issue W. Paper on course of

discussions – showing views of Parties. Agreed statement.

[Exit W.W.

[Enter Listowel.

7. Palestine.

E.B. Truce for Jerusalem now seems likely. Haifa position has however

again become serious. Violent attack y’day by Irgun on Jaffa:

B. had to intervene.

Strong &amp; continuous pressure fr. U.S.A. – tho’ no indicn of what

they will do. Trying to manoeuvre us into promising somethg.

with no clear assurance of their collaboration.

Have given another warning to Arab States not to act before 15/5.

Jews far better armed than Arabs.

Douglas has however asked us to prevent Abdullah fr. taking

any violent action. We expld his diffies – tho’ added we wd. press him if J. declared a truce.

Douglas put 4 ques:

a) wtr. if J. indulged in no disorder, we wd. prevent invasion

by Abdullah or other Arab States. We said yes.

b) wtr. if a truce we wd. press Arab States to accept it.

We said yes: if terms fair &amp; approved by Trust Council &amp;

of course if Jews accepted.

c) wd. we then play any part? We said, if agreemt. &amp; we were

asked to come in with others, we wd. consider.

d) after 15/5 wd. we play a part? We said same condns wd.

apply. Cd. give no undertaking in advance.

Cdn’t carry whole weight again.

Truce Commn have now urged Abdullah not to invade Pal.

By formal telegram – received this morning. Threatened

censure of U.N.

That is in accord with advice we have given to Abdullah. His diffy.

arises fr. fact his is only organised Arab Army - &amp; all Arabs

are pressing him to use it.

Stern &amp; figure gangs will have to be cleared up.

“We are on top of it until 15/5”: &amp; reason is beginning to prevail.

153

A.V.A. J. actions call for equal restraint.

E.B. But can’t invoice U.N. on that while we are respons. for law &amp; order.

A.B. We can’t do less than others – in view of our past associations.

Present policy: use our good influence with Arabs to prevent wider

outbreak of violence.

E.B. Yes.

8. Cyprus: Constitutional Reform.

L. These proposals are minimum that Const. Assembly will accept.

Full self-govt. not expected – nor are leaders fit for it.

These proposals go as far as is wise.

Main features a) Elected legislature – with reserved subjects.

b) Execut. Council respons. to Govr.

c) Leaders in legislature to be members of

Council – for educative purposes.

Our strategic needs will be met by empowering Govr. to control

Bills on defence subjects etc.

P.M. C.A. Cttee have discussed. Don’t like ½ way houses because apt to

be lessons in irresponsibility. But satisfied they are not

experienced enough to shoulder more responsibility than this.

E.B. Cdn’t go further now – because Palestine &amp; uncertainty re Cyrenaica. Must get posn of E. Med. stabilised before we go further than

this.

P.M. Wd. divert their attention from Greece.

[Exit L.

[Enter Brian Robertson.

9. Germany: Capital Punishment.

E.B. As in memo. a) B. subjects tried under B. law will be treated as here.

b) No interference with G. penal code.

c) No surrender of death penalty for offences v. Armies

of Occupation.

All. Genl. agrees.

H.M. Crikey!

J. I support this.

E.B. Stokes &amp; Skeff. Lodge will criticise. But if this is challenged Whips

must be on.

154

T.W. Do you mean to apply this policy before C.J. Bill passed.

E.B. Yes: so far as B. subjects go (under B. law) – as by C.E. in U.K.

C.E. Maxwell recently went to Germany examining work of courts.

R. have announced no death penalty under Law 10 because they

have abolished it in R. We are still imposing it &amp; hanging

5 a week for war crimes &amp; crimes r. humanity.

E.B. Shall work off backlog by 1/9. Can’t change my practice half way

down the list.

H.M. Will you announce in H/C.?

E.B. P.Q. by Skeff. Lodge. P’poned until Mon. Will say as little as I can.

[Exit Robertson.

[Enter Jay, Freeman, Nathan.

10. Civil Aviation: Purchase of M.S. Aircraft.

A. Put the facts re availability of U.S. Constellations wh. are to be

abandoned by closing of Eire Air Co.

Inconsistent with ‘Fly British’. But no modern B. aircraft for

Austral. routes until 1952.

Discussed with Ty. who said a) no dollars b) consultn re terms.

Effect on current B. bldg. limited to Solent Flying Boats.

Intended mainly for S. Afr. routes: but also in concert with

Austr. for F/Eastern routes. Six undelivered – of wh. one wd. be

taken but 5 might be countermanded for compensn of £½ m.

Ques: shd. we make a first offer. Other countries were nibbling. We

authorised him (Hartley) to negotiate subject to Ty. points.

He went.

Y’day was asked by M/Supply (not represented at my earlier mtg) if

Cab. cd. consider effects of this on:-

a) “Fly British” policy

b) current orders for B. aircraft industry.

Use of these Constellations on Austr. routes wd. save £1 p.a.[sic].

And Austr. are using Constellations.

D.J. Discussed with R.S.C. We felt that, if we cd. buy for sterling &amp; save

thereby save £1 m. a year, balance was in favour of buying. Only

involves cancelling 5 Solents: doesn’t mean stopping Solent

prodn. Shd. try to find other uses for them.

Fr. ‘Fly British’ not derived fr. desire to reduce dollar drain, but adopted

on its merits. That knocks out argument that we can buy these

for sterling.

Solents are essential for defence because we must keep Shortt Harland

in prodn. Cost of cancellation will be £½ m. wh. shd. be set

against saving on operation.

155

Shortt’s are hoping to sell Solents to Austr. for Tasman route. This

hope &amp; export prospects to Argentine etc., will be prejudiced

by this cancellation.

Is this really an exceptional case? Arguments used to-day can come in

every time Constellations are available f. sterling.

P.M. Constant changes of policy even types. Thought we were

abandoning flying boats.

V. costly subsidy posn.

What is use of abandoning chances of buying Constellns if B. types

are not competitive.

N. That is our problem in a nutshell.

Flying boats. Solents are being used because we had nil else to fly.

They are not satisfactory.

A competitive B. aircraft is neither available now nor certainly in

sight for years ahead.

Of 45 operating cos. throughout world not one is willing to buy a

4-engined B. aircraft.

Solent is tempy type – till 1954.

Chairman of Austr. Co. is interested in Solents &amp; may put

unexpected order in. Order for Tasman Co. was secured by me.

Austr. wd. take some of these Constellations &amp; have asked my good

offices to get 2 of them.

H.M. Is there really any ques. about this?

If M/S. can’t supply competitive types, we must go elsewhere.

V. extravagant over this. We deserve more criticism than we are

getting. Fantastic cost of development etc.

Worried about B. aircraft industry – pampered &amp; spoilt &amp; given

masses of money. And they produce nil!

A. General picture will be presented shortly.

Confine this discn to limited issue of Constellations.

A.V.A. Will 5 Constellations keep operation of route going or does it commit

us to buying more when available.

N. The 5 + what Austr. has shd. suffice for whole of interim period until

B. types become available.

T.W. Must the 5 Solents be cancelled?

N. May get another order for them.

P.M. Buy the 5 Constellations.

Don’t cancel at once the order for Solents.

</content>
</cab>
