<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 33-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 34(48). 31st May, 1948.

1. Palestine.

E.B. Fr. and U.S. were v. wobbly over this.

U.S. thought to be willing to support one resoln. But followg. day

U.S. denounced it in Sec. Council. Then U.S. Govt. said to me

they wd. support subject to amendments.

Sec. Council considered on Sat. Fr. moved amendmt (para. 31)

providing tht. if immigrants enter they shan’t be mobilised.

This isn’t acceptable to Egypt. Have tried to get them to agree.

Cyprus – camps are being held for 4 weeks standstill.

I adhered to Art. 36: to avoid 39, which wd. have admitted R. troops.

Statement in H/C. Can’t answer supplementaries. Arabs are mtg.

in Amman. Prefer therefore to wait until Wed., when I can tell

the whole story.

H.M. Put them off last week. By promising statement prob. Monday.

Wd be useful if E.B. were on Bench – to explain why he can’t make

a statement to-day.

E.B. Yes: I can say that. Wd prefer not to.

P.M. I will explain. E.B. can be present.

E.B. May my policy – on U.N. Resolutions – be formally endorsed?

A.V.A. No ques. of breaking our Treaty with Transjordan?

E.B. No.

Means breaking contracts to supply arms to Arab States pro tem.

Must be supported on that.

H.M. Cyprus. a) was understood we wd. empty the camps.

b) what shall we do with them eventually?

C.J. Will be done with consent of J. Agency.

R.S.C. Hoffman has told Senate Cttee he is satisfied re financial aid to

P. &amp; Transjordan.

E.B. Prospects for truce are good – save for complicn of Fr. amendmt.

2. Germany.

E.B. Conversns procdg. Brought Strang because familiar with detail.

a) Political Structure.

Pol. diffies in France – mainly from Blum &amp; Socialists.

172

Election to C. Assembly. Favoured by U.S. and us. Move now to

allow Land Parlt. to decide wtr. election or nomination.

Inclined to test that out. But suppose C.A. favour direct

election to a central Parlt. – wd. French veto that. The voting etc. wd. be in Lander.

Can’t continue Mil. Govt. much longer.

Shall we go ahead as proposed? And go on bi-laterally if French

dissent? Risking also any R. re-action? My view is that if we

yield to weakness of French it will create the very situation Fr.

fear.

b) The Ruhr: and Security against Germany.

Discn turned on what will happen when Mil. Govt. ends. Bound

up with disarmament &amp; containment of G.

On structure of Control over Rhur, there is agreement.

Trouble has bn: Fr. desire to get into technical management.

We have resisted that. Wd be a failure. Must restrict ourselves to allocation of output, over-all control, developmt. to fit with

E.R.P. Fr. cd. find no support for their view &amp; have at last

agreed present proposals.

Fears for future. Have seen U.S. Amb. &amp; have bn. assured Sel. Service Act will be carried this Session. Marshall’s speech on continuity

of f. policy v. any resurgence of G. was made with authority of Adminn.

c) Currency Reform.

Fr. are trying to p’pone. Sure we must press on with it. can’t relate G. to E.R.P.: can’t get on with wages or price policy.

Don’t intend to introduce it in Berlin.

If French decline to go on because their internal pol. diffies, what

shall we do? Propose to support suggn tht. we shd. tell Fr. that in that event we shall go forward in Br. &amp; U.S. Zone. O.K. for France because their Zone costs them nothing.

Political Structure.

R.S.C. P’ponemt. of date. Para. 7(a). Tel. 2888 Basic re currency says

fin. &amp; pol. action must be simultaneous. Does this mean

p’ponement of pol. is imposs. because of imposs. of delaying

currency?

E.B. They can be handled separately. Don’t intend to have currency

reform p’poned.

A. Attitude of G. people. Sub-division of G. Will they resist?

E.B. No: they say “get on with something.”

Will make it clear this isn’t inconsistent with G. unity, but a prelude to it.

173

P.M. What is G. view on direct or indirect election to C.A.?

E.B. They want elections. In Bizonia they shall have them. Must be sure it’s a G. voted act. Fr. are afraid of central Govt. being implied. We say: they can do it in Fr. Zone.

P.M. Elections on lists or of persons?

E.B. On present system of election to Läuder, wh. is compromise betwn. direct election and p.r. lr is not a list.

H.M. May Cab. see the Letter of Advice?

P.M. That is 2nd stage? During C.A.

W.S. Yes.

A.B. Can’t we see this in detail. It’s vital. cf. causes of collapse of

Weimar constitution.

P.M. Ques. is does that outweigh advantage of getting Fr. Zone included.

T.W. Too late to change system we earlier approved.

N.B. Safe to accept U.S. compromise – because Läuder will choose direct election method.

R.S.C. What propn is Fr. Zone?

P. 6 m. out of 46 m. V. small propn.

W.S. Robertson thinks all Läuder in B. &amp; U.S. Zones, save prs. Bavaria,

wd. prefer direct election.

P. Confirmed, subject to some doubt on N. Rhine/Westphalia.

A.W. Informing R. first. Won’t that give them chance to propagand.

E.B. Must deal fairly with 4th Occupying Power – and take chance on that.

A.B. Fr. demand for long delay. Makes no sense, qua Germany.

They refer to results of Elections in Hesse. Thought that was

defeat of Comm.

W.S. (There was a rise in a Right Party vote: but U.S. don’t accept Fr.

appreciation of this.)

E.B. I will circulate a final document – giving more detail. This is only

an interim guidance on policy.

174

R.S.C. If French don’t come in, can we then have direct elections?

W.S. That is U.S. intention.

E.B. Let’s get it clear with U.S.

P. Attitude of Germans. Only circs. in wh. Parties wd. prefer indirect

election = if they felt discredited &amp; cdn’t face the public.

That is a reason for going on, soon.

H.M. Can we influence work of C.A. To get a strong system, as near as

possible to strong 2. party system. Weimar failed because

sensitiveness to minority groups. Dangers of P.R. Splinter

parties = cause of Fr. weakness.

E.B. We had this as our aim in creating electoral system for Läuder.

Will circulate a separate note on this. System in practice has

produced a pretty strong Party lay-out.

a) Political Structure. Proposals approved.

R.S.C. Ruhr. How long will Authority last?

W.S. No limit is set. But not stated it will last for ever. Plan contemplates

to periods a) Mil. Govt. period. b) Thereafter contacts direct

from Authority to German Govt.

R.S.C. Last sentence in 3(d) on p.6. Means?

W.S. Read full text of article It means “sanctions.”

R.S.C. Shd. we not make it clear we adhere to our policy for socialisation of

Ruhr industries?

W.S. I have done so, throughout conference. But can’t include in results

of this conference any agreed statement on ownership.

E.B. G. people will look after this – pressures from German T.U.’s on

U.S. authies are already beginning.

R.S.C. Para. 3(b). “If no internatl body is set up…..” – Withdrawn.

P. Suggn tht. this is 1st step towards internatl control of all industrial

groupings in Europe. Cd. this be tried again?

E.B. But that covers countries outside G. Can’t be done by this Conference.

We are pushing that idea on [5 Power and] O.E.C.C.

A.B. Cd. we say this is knitted in with O.E.C.C.?

W.S. It is there.

175

Political: Adjustment of Land Boundaries.

R.S.C. Why take this ques. out of jurisdn of C.A.?

W.S. Popular consultn will take place before C.A. formed.

R.S.C. Will C.A. be able to revise boundaries.

E.B. We haven’t provided for that.

P.M. Will turn on Letter of Advice.

P. This ques. will be a red-herring. Better to keep it out of C.A.

E.B. I will consider wtr. C.A. will have to be precluded from handling this ques. of boundaries.

Security against Germany.

P. “A considerable period” vice “a long period” of occupn.

For this will be a knell to G.

176

</content>
</cab>
