<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 62-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 77(48) 2nd December 1948

1. Parliament.

H.M. Business for next week. Adjournment dates.

A.B. 2. Licensing Bill. Asked by Govt. supporters if this wd. involve closing Ldn. night clubs., like the 400. because imposs. for them to sell liquor after 11 p.m.

If so, this will give rise to trouble.

J. Run now on basis of bottle party.

C.E. Bill is aimed at stopping this very thing.

N.B. Tourism point in this.

H.W. We have had repns. on that basis since publn. of the Bill.

A.B. Wthr. resident or foreigner, shdn’t they be allowed some colour in their life.

J. Multiplication of regulations wh. people are determined to breach because they think them unreasonable. Gt. danger of general disrespect for the law.

A.B. Won’t get over “stag sandwich” problem by limiting opporties. for drinking – only by enlarging them. Make the law easier to obey.

A.W. But do you suggest pubs be allowed to keep open late. If not, there is unfairness.

Agreed. L.P. Cttee. to review this again on Friday.

Chief Whip to consider wthr. Bill be p’poned until later than next week. eg. by putting Films Bill Cttee stage in on Wed. 8/12. or by inserting

Supply Day on Food and Service Pay.

1. Parliament (resumed).

A. Wed. Cork wants motion on enquiry into war pensions.

A.V.A. Give H/C. answer. Discuss with M/Pensions.

[Enter E.Sh.

3. Iron and Steel Bill.

G.S. 1st May 1950 was selected a) on assumption that Bill passed this year 9 months wd. suffice. b) Altho’ we knew we cdn’t rest before Election if

323

H/L. opposed, we shd. be in strong bargaining posn. if 1st May was in Bill.

Duncan has now offered tht. if resting date is later than Election, industry will a) continue Steel Bd. b) State tht. they will pursue developmt. plans (present and next stage) in interim and c) will give us technical help on Bill.

We couldn’t have an open bargain.

Continuance of Bd. wd. be v. convenient.

Public statement as at b) wd. be v. important – politically advantageous for they cdn’t accuse us of retarding progress by naturalisn.

c) wd. also be valuable because we know less of this industry than eg. transport.

We can’t in fact rest before Election. Let’s give ourselves chance of getting a valuable quid pro quo.

H.M. Politics are difficult. Party wd. have to be handled.

Always recognised that, with 107 cos. and subsidiaries in addn, there wd. be need of substantial interval before resting. 1st May was inserted to draw just such an offer.

Genl. Election point is now. Difficult. But equally diff. to say you won’t give electorate chance to express view. Bound to be election issue anyhow.

Ques: do you come further into open? If you do, much to be said for inserting 1.1.51 date : ‘6 months after passing of Act’ invites obstruction.

Do we want smooth transition or flaming row?

Do you want to let it be said you turned down an offer of co-opn?

Public opinion wd. prob. prefer smooth transition.

Party : there are some doubts about Bill and some people wd. prefer smooth transition.

P.M. Also, economic blizzard if it came soon wd. be attributed to our action v. steel.

R.S.C. Two contingencies – H/L. pass or not. 1.1.51 is 17 mos. fr. date when H/L. shd. pass Bill : wd. imply we assume H/L. will reject.

Can’t therefore have a fixed date in Bill.

Must therefore fit either contingency. This means saying “not less than so many months after passing of Bill”.

If Bill rejected by H/L. it can’t be operated by 1/5 – only 2 mos. left.

Will have to p’pone sometime after March. Effect of doing that just before Election. Wd. be thought to mean cold feet.

Easier to do it earlier.

Pol. diffies. of doing it now. Don’t want to make a bargain. But on techn. side advantageous to get industry’s co-opn.

Ques. comes down therefore to attitude of Party assuming tht. whatever is said, everyone will guess it’s a deal.

Diff. to decide which is the more embarrassing course.

324

A.B. Gave my views at S.I.M. Further reflection since. Tried to meet views of H.M. and G.S. But can’t see what we get fr. this bargain as cpd. with gain to industry.

We are playing from strength. Opposn. have miscalculated – they haven’t stirred public opinion. We mobilised biggest vote in this Parlt. on 2nd Rdg. – spiritual regeneration of our Party.

Duncan is in a jam. Mistake made in resign. fr. Bd. They will come back, even tho’ we do nothing. Duncan is being accused of folly in refusing techn. advice because disagree with Govt’s politics confirmed at Genl. Election.

This wd. extricate him fr. his diffy. and create harvest of diffies. for us. Who will get advantage fr. public statement at (b)? We shall have agreed tht. issue is to be settled at Genl. Election. And they will behave anyhow because it’s their line tht. they are efficient.

Assistance under c) is important not at Bill stage but at opn. stage. We shall be saying we don’t regard 1945 mandate as conclusion.

This denies us any right to attack H/L. for frustrating it.

I want to be able to attack steel barons and land barons simultaneously.

You can’t sneak revolutions by stealth.

Harmonious transitions are not available. Therefore, make it a fight and make the best of it.

R.S.C. What wd. be effect of p’poning date by Order in April.

[Exit W.W.

A.B. Can say that is due to actions of H/Lords.

A. Politically, I sympathise with A.B.

Doubt if H/L. will reject on 2nd Rdg. Believe they will amend in Cttee. unacceptably. Might get agreemt. betwn. 2 Houses in this session. Don’t therefore amend Bill in any sense which invites H/L. to be more difficult.

A.V.A. Same situation wd. apply if you made an arrangemt. with the industry. That wd. be known to repves. of industry in Parlt.

G.T. Same view of this as of the compromise.

We decided to go on knowg. we shdn’t have Duncan’s help.

Support A.B.

C.E. Support A.B.

J. Support G.S.

Tories may want to show tht. any econ. diffies. are due to our Bill.

That wd. be awkward for us.

Don’t try to make a secret bargain. Can’t be secret.

But open agreemt. involvg. their co-opn. might get us out of that pol. diffy.

325

What interval is needed?

G.S. 6-9 months. If H/L. passed Bill in July we cd. do it by 1/5.

N.B. Vital ques : what will Tories say in Election. They will commit themselves to repeal of Bill. Awkward therefore for us if we have put into opn. before Election.

P.M. Don’t see danger of p’ponemt. just before Election. Shall have got the Bill.

R.S.C. But may appear we don’t expect to get back.

A.B. Answer is tht. H/L. made it imposs. for us to do it before Election.

(P.M. agreed with this).

A.W. Politically, we want an issue to fight on at Genl. Election.

H.W. Support A.B.

Bargain wd. invite H/L. to obstruct and delay.

If we can’t rest before Election best course is to p’pone later.

A.V.A. Support A.B.

But hope G.S. won’t discourage co-opn. by industry w’out a bargain.

G.A.I. Support A.B. Mainly because Duncan has taken initiative. Means he must have more to gain than us.

C.J. Mistake to bargain. Agree with A.B.

General agreemt. tht. bargain cdn’t be kept secret.

H.M. I wdn’t try to keep it secret.

Agreed ( don’t accept this offer.

( Duncan may come again.

G.S. Serious technical diffies. for the industry if we don’t get co-opern. of steelmasters. Put in early date to draft offer of co-opn.

A.B. We recognise these techn. diffies. But can’t sacrifice all our political advantages to get over them. And in the end Duncan &amp; co. will come to heel.

[Exit G.

326

4. Commonwealth Consultation.

[Enter C.M.

P.M. What replies?

N.B. N.Z., Pak., Ceylon and Rhodesia have given unqualified ‘yes’. Shall get yes fr. Australia.

Nothg. fr. S. Africa.

Qualified replies fr. Canada and India. Only specific point is 2 mtgs. a year of F. Ministers : general doubt of wisdom of writing it all down.

Hope we will agree. And, when A. comes in, try to get genl. agreemt. with prs. some loosening up on the 2 mtgs. a year.

P.M. V. little sense in Indian doubts.

A. Subject to x/ favour agreemt and publn.

C.J. Our procedure for discussg. Indian ques. in Colonies. High Commr. sometimes comes to see me. Can this continue?

P.M. Certainly.

Agreed : U.K. accept. [Exit C.M.

5. Military Training (Facilities) Bill.

H.M. Explained his later meeting.

E.Sh. Thought we had met J.’s points. Hoped we cd. go on with Bill.

Gave assurance we wdn’t acquire land any longer under D.R. 52.

Embarrassing for me.

H.M. This was temporary use, not acquisition.

E.Sh. Not altogether.

Ready to defer legn. but may have some diffy.

J. Let considn. of Bill proceed. Let W.O. see wthr. any diffies. do occur under existg. powers.

P’pone this Bill until after Genl. Election.

6. Salaries of the Higher Civil Service.

No member of the Secretariat was present at the discussion of this item.

</content>
</cab>
