<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/6/0 images: 66-66</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 81(48) 15th December 1948)

1. Parliament. [Enter W.W. &amp; Service Ministers

H.M. Business for week after Xmas Recess.

2. Eire.

P.M. Consequential Bill on Eire – early in new Session after Xmas.

Take note for purposes of p’mme.

J. Simon’s 4 questions.

a) Which office shd. handle Eire?

P.M. C.R.O. Status quo.

E.B. Danger of Irish votes.

P.M. Haven’t finally decided to give them the franchise.

E.B. Keep F.O. out of Irish business as long as possible.

[Exit W.W.

[Enter Ld. Advocate

3. Army and Air Force Courts Martial.

J. Navy weren’t represented on Cttee.

a) Legal member to retire and participate in decision.

b) Regular appeal in public hearing.

Diff. to argue not extending this to Navy. Propose therefore re-constitn. of Lewis Cttee to review naval procedure as a whole.

H. and A.V.A. agree.

This avoids putting Navy in posn. of rejecting the Rpt.

c) Status of pay of Ch. Judge Martial. Cttee equated to High Ct. Judge.

Dpts. have agreed to £3 – 3.500. salary. This will be criticised on grounds of status. At the moment cd. get a man at this price : will be easier later to get him at £5.000.

R.S.C.} The range for this job is much less than that of a High Ct. Judge.

H.M. } £3 – 3.500 shd. be enough for this.

d) Participn. of legal member.

E.B. Shd. not Ct. Martial include privates?

J. This was considered and rejected by Cttee.

P.M. V. short notice. Haven’t had Napier Rpt.

Many diff. points.

Wd. like to publish Rpts. and get public reactions before we decide.

This preserves discipline – hence officers only.

351

This elaborate procedure may do for peace – not for war.

Not happy about appeal : broader review under existg. system wd. do greater justice.

Will then be enough staff to man all these courts.

What of war?

J. Napier Rpt. recommends reverting then to appeal on paper.

P.M. But it’s in war tht. the trouble is likely to arise.

J. May get more in peace because Nat. Service.

H.M. Risk of being put into safeguards that won’t help the accused.

Elastic justice is more likely under existg. system. Ministers are free-er to take a human view.

Parly. Procedure. Clauses in Army Act wd. be convenient. But that must pass betwn end/March and 30th April. Diff. to put this stuff thro’ under those limits. Think therefore we may be forced to separate Bill.

E.Sh. Why was it assumed this must be done in annual Bill?

Agree with H.M.’s point on this.

Ques. of appeal court is the vital ques. And that is controversial.

Came up because attitude of Admy. I said my experience was more chance of justice under existg. system. Minister can take a/c of human considns.; and can obtain advice on legal points.

Believe existg. system is adequate, provided delays are removed. There is a case for other ranks being on ct. martial. But in practice he is afraid to go against officers. And officer more likely to be sympathetic to man that n.c.o. wd. be.

Also diffy. tht. it doesn’t apply to Admy.

Prefer therefore to deal with small points and for the rest make no change.

P.M. If you suspend this system in war, you will throw doubt on all war-time decn. of ct. martial.

H. Two Cttees in inter-war years. Both came down on opp. side to Lewis Cttee.

Estimated that 20% wd. appeal. But as now every sentence is reviewed. At Admy 42 a year in peace : and all reviewed.

Service men in Parlt. will realise diffce. under ct/appeal system.

Will know it lessens scope for review.

We don’t agree with appeal system now recommended.

C.E. Politically, we are bound to follow Cttee’s report.

I believe existg. system is better. But that won’t prevail against hysteria of H/C.

Doubt if £3 – 3.500 will get right man. I can’t get Met. Mags. now at £2.000 + pension for short service.

352

P.6 w’drawal of King’s prerogative. How cd. that be done?

Prerogative is exercised on mercy. Appeal Ct. decides on law.

J. Power of Crown to modify sentence or grant Free Pardon wd. remain.

H.M. P.Q.’s wd. be excluded also.

That wd. cause hysteria on other grounds.

J. These are the arguments adduced against a C.C.A.

P.M. But mil. law is essentially diff. from civil.

A.H. Support Ct./Appeal. a) No right to take Service men outside jurisdn. of civil courts – esp. now they aren’t all volunteers.

b) Experience at W.O. Somethg. unsatisf. In

present system. Rape or burglary : law of corrobn. is of vital importance : 3 lay members of Council deciding on paper w’out argument of counsel. J.A.G. is not enough to rely on for a man’s life or liberty. I advocated Ct. of Appeal when I was at W.O. Believe there shd. be one, even in war, for pts. of law.

A.V.A. My experience shows gt. fairness under existg. system.

But justice shd. appear to be done. Believe tht. on mixed law : fact Minister has heavy duty. Wd. welcome ct/appeal for those cases.

But believe that under this system many men will get less justice than they do now.

P.M. Why not publish Lewis Rpt. and let public opinion express itself.

No need to express Govt. views at once.

J. No objn.

We shall be asked what we have bn. doing since April.

We shd. have to define our attitude fairly soon.

E.Sh. We cd. say we have done some of the adminve. points.

R.S.C. Cd. J.A.G. hear counsel on diff. points of law.

P.M. Consider that.

Agreed : 1) Publish Lewis Rpt.

2) Extend enquiry to Navy.

[Exit A.H. and Hall.

[Enter Strang.

4. Germany : Occupation Statute.

E.B. As in memo.

Strang can answer ques.?

P.M. Is perpetual disarmament of G. intended? eg. Proclamation.

353

E.B. That is for Peace Treaty, not this.

P.M. “Just and lasting peace based on disarmament …” Permanent?

E.B. Can’t be : will have to allow some Army etc. in Peace Treaty.

R.S.C. This phrase is declaratory, not decisive.

Art. 3(7) will govern the position.

Art. 1 gives all powers. There may be power to establish Armed Forces

Reservn. preventg. that cd. go into Art. 2.

E.B. Agree : will instruct accordingly.

A. Art. 4(9). Bizone (E.P.C. discn). What dirns are contemplated?

H.W. Art. 2(g) covers cartels etc.

A.W. Does this settle G’s part in Europe of next 30 yrs?

R.S.C. Reserved under Art. 2(2) to Occupn. Powers.

E.B. But points the way.

R.S.C. Form of reservn. of our powers is so wide tht. German Govt. won’t see what they can do.

J. Agree : diff. to sell this to any self respecting Germany.

A.W. Europe won’t get right w’out Germany. France isn’t strong. Are we going to deny ourselves G. strength in re-constructg. Europe. One day we shall have to take risk of allowg. G. to re-emerge.

An ally eventually against Russia.

That risk not as gt. as after 1918.

European stability rests on balance of power.

E.B. Must watch risk of her siding with R.

Also can’t discount France. For w’out re-building her we are v. vulnerable.

Nov ’47 (because Comm. strikes in France) R. nearly got into France.

Don’t know which way G. wd. go. Too early to risk that.

But Germans are in control of much of G. trade and prodn. Not doing it in a v. socialist fashion. But they have shouldered the responsibility. Unless we retain control, we may get wrong kind of policy emerging in Germany.

My view has bn. cautious in handing over control to G.

P.M. Any note of progression in this?

E.B. Art. 24. gives that opportunity.

354

J. Complete case for reservg. our powers. But don’t advertise it.

Power of disallowance. You cd. do that quite briefly – rather than prescribe all the things they can’t do.

Doubtful if Germans will like form of this.

E.B. U.S. and France (for diff. reasons) wdn’t like too great an appearance of freedom to Germany.

Will re-consider in light of Cab. comments : but doubt if I can phrase all concerned.

Wh. Doubt J.’s philosophy.

To give power and use veto will cause greater frustratn.

R.S.C. Real diffy. is Art. 2. V. wide.

E.B. But (i) – (iii) are limiting.

R.S.C. Means stranglehold. Can’t you get same result without appearce. of doing it. No suggn. of what G. can do.

E.Sh. W.O. doesn’t want too low a ceiling on Occupn Costs.

E.B. Will look into the drafting of Art II.

A. Wdn’t U.S. draft of II. 2.(b) be preferable?

E.B. No: our version was devised to protect B/T. and Ty. interests.

P.M. Art. II reserves (a) directly and completely.

In the remainder you want to reserve only the right to control for the purposes there specified.

E.B. Will consider that.

</content>
</cab>
