<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/5/17 images: 140-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  January 1940.SECRET. Copy No. 4W.M. (40)17th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy o! this document.WAR CABINET 17 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet field at 10 Downing Street,S. W. 1, on Thursday, January 18, 1940, at 11 - 30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right, Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,President of the Board of Trade(Item 1).The Right Hon. E. L. Burgin, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 1).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Minister of Labour (Item. 1).Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. G. N. Flemming.Mr. P. K. Debenham.[20680]b
WAR CABINET 17 (40). )Contents.minute no. Subject. Page.1      Supply and Man-Power       ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     1032      Anglo-Soviet Negotiations : Summer 1939 ......       ...     109Proposed publication of Blue Book.3      The Air Situation     ..................     1104      The Naval Situation ...      ...       ...........     Ill5      The Military Situation        ...............     IllWestern Front.
1. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by theChancellor of the Exchequer covering a Memorandum on the labour requirements of the proposed War Programme submitted by an interdepartmental Committee of Officials to the ministerial committee on Economic Policy, together with a record of thediscussion on it in that Committee (W.P. (G.) (40) 9).The Chancellor of the Exchequer, in presenting the Report,paid a warm tribute to Mr. Humbert Wolfe, who had presided overthe Committee of experts which had prepared it, and whose recentdeath was a serious loss to the public service. This tribute was endorsed by his colleagues.The following were the chief points which were discussed inthe consideration of the Memorandum :  (1) Origin and Scope of the Memorandum.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that the Memo-randum had its origin in the recommendation of the Land ForcesCommittee, approved by the War Cabinet, that there should be afull statistical investigation of the labour demands of the proposedwar programme. It dealt only with labour demand and supply, andnot with such questions as the supplies of raw materials, exchangeor shipping, and to that extent its estimates might be regarded asoptimum figures (paragraphs 1 to 6 of the Memorandum).(2) The importance of the time factor.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to paragraph 5of the Memorandum, in which it was pointed out that, while therehad been a considerable increase in the industrial capacity of thecountry since the war of 1914-18, we were attempting in this war to develop our resources within a much shorter time-limit.(3) Labour deficiencies.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to the table in paragraph 11 of the Memorandum showing the estimateddeficiencies of labour in the main industrial groups concerned in thesummers of 1940 and 1941, i.e., the numbers which it would benecessaxy to draft into employment in those industries by thosedates, if the war programme was to be completed by the dates con-templated. In connection with the figures included in this table forship building and repairing, it was pointed out that the latest proposals under this head, as set out in the Report of the Lord privy seal (W.P. (G.) (40) 11), would result in considerably increased demands for labour, possibly by between 50,000 and 100,000 men.The Minister of Labour undertook to have these demandscalculated as for the same dates as those shown in the table inparagraph 11.(4) Employment of women on war production.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to the table in paragraph 12 of the Memorandum showing the percentages ofmen and women employed in some of the more important war industries before the war began. These figures were, of course, only of importance as showing the position from which we had to startin calling on women for the additional labour force required.Attention was drawn to the great differences in the extent to whichwomen were employed in factories engaged on similar work and theopportunity which this showed for increasing the employment ofwomen. .(5) The objective of the war production programme.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to para-graph 19 (3) of the Memorandum, recommending that, despite the[20680] B 2Supply andMan Power.(previous references:W.M. (39) 74thConclusions,Minute 5 (3),andW.M. (40) 3rdConclusions,Minute 7.)(previous reference:W.M. (39) 23rdConclusions,Minute 6.)
difficulties, the present programme should remain as an objective,and explained that there had been some discussion on this point inthe Economic Policy Committee. His own view was that thisrecommendation was not within the scope of the interdepartmental committee or of the Economic Policy Committee, and he was anxious that the difficulties should not be understated in the presen-tation of the case to the War Cabinet. He recalled the fact that lord Stamp&apos;s Survey was engaged on a report comparing the total requirements of the war programme with the resources availablenot only in labour, but also in regard to supplies of raw material;shipping and foreign exchange; and it was generally agreed thatthe programme as a whole would need to be considered in the lightof this survey. On the other hand, the Chancellor Of the Exchequerpointed out that there were urgent problems in the field of labour supply which needed immediate consideration, and the First Lordof the Admiralty stressed the advantages of having a definiteobjective, even if in the event it should not prove possible to attainit by the date originally proposed. :&apos;]The Lord Privy Seal thought that, without waiting for thecomplete statement being prepared by Lord Stamp&apos;s survey, theWar Cabinet could at once reach a conclusion. A very large additional labour force would be required, in the neighbourhood of,say, 1-1 and 2 million men and women : this broad fact should atonce be made known, in the most authoritative manner, to industryand labour, and the problems involved faced.(6) Area Organisation.The Prime Minister pointed out that the fifth of the sixrecommendations in section 4 of paragraph 19 of the Memorandumbefore the War Cabinet (W.P. (G.) (40) 9), namely, that which dealtwith training, might call for active initiative on the part of theGovernment; the remainder would for the most part depend on local action.The First Lord of the Admiralty referred to the areaorganisation developed by the Ministry of Munitions in the last war, which had then been responsible for the handling of these problems. In addition, these area organisations had been directly responsible for the production of large quantities of munitionsadditional to those produced in Government factories. Had this organisation been reproduced to-day?The Minister of Stiffly said that th.&amp; area organisation was already far advanced. The Committee which would deal with the birmingham area would be inaugurated the next day. Theorganisation now being set up consisted of Area Boards, whichcomprised civil servants, under which were grouped Area Com-mittees, consisting of representatives of employers and employed.The difference between this organisation and that set up in the last war was that Committees had then been given executive powers (i.e.,had been authorised to place orders), whereas now they were onlyadvisory. He was advised that to give executive powers to localcommittees might result in a slowing up in the placing of orders.The production officers who would deal with man-powerquestions were not subject to the Area Committees but to the area boards.The Lord Privy Seal said that the decision to refuse executive powers to local Committees had met with criticism.The First Lord of the A dmiralty thought that local committees would have little influence,over firms in their areas if they had notthe power to place orders.
The Prime Minister said that it would be unwise to be dogmaticat this stage on the final form of the area organisation. TheMinister of Supply should perhaps suggest, in his speech at birmingham, that the working of the area system would be reviewedfrom time to time in the light of experience.(7) Training by Employers.The Minister of Labour said that, if employers and TradeUnions were to co-operate in securing the man-power required forour programmes, they must realise how great an effort was expected of them. This would mean disclosing, subject to proper precautions,the man-power implications of these programmes.There were three branches of the problem new recruitment,training by employers, and training by the Ministry of Labour.Where State training could produce thousands of tradesmen,training by industry in the workshops could produce its tens of thousands. It was essential, therefore, to view the problem in proportion, and to remember that direct or indirect encouragement to employers to train men was far more important than theexpansion of State facilities.(8) Training in New Factories.The President of the Board of Trade said that it should bepossible to make use of new factories as training centres in the twoor three months between the time of their erection and the time theywere ready to start full production. Some of the parts made mighthave to be wasted, but the experience gained by unskilled men wouldbe very valuable.(9) Training by Special Instructors.The Prime Minister said that consideration should be given tothe possibility of increasing the number of persons in industryspecially qualified to act as trainers. The ordinary worker dislikedhaving to explain what he was doing to a novice. In large firmsthis question was properly dealt with, but it was apt to be neglectedby the small firms.The Secretary of State for Air said that he thought it wouldbe necessary to supply instructors and special training workshopsfor the Air Ministry factories. The problem of training amongsub-contractors was specially acute.The Minister of Supply said that he hoped that the scales of pay to be allowed for instructors and production officers would begenerous, as their work was of great importance. The degree towhich use was made of trainees in. different factories variedenormously, as did methods of training. It would be important toassist those factories which were now backward.(10) Government Training Centres.The Minister of Labour said that hitherto the Ministry hadconfined itself to training unemployed men to become semi-skilled workers, a process which normally took six months. They were ina position to train 12,500 men at a time, or 25,000 in the course of ayear. They had trained 100,000 men in the course of the last twelve years. At the moment, however, only 6,500 persons were beingtrained, of whom 2,500 were for the army, whereas at the outbreakof war the centres had been nearly full. They had made every effort to secure trainees, and had removed all restrictions on the ages of applicants. But it was to-day much easier for an untrained manto be absorbed directly into industry. He was, however, organisingan extensive campaign to recruit trainees during the next ten weeks.
If the capacity of the training centres was to be fully used, it mightbe necessary to secure as trainees persons now employed inunessential industries. But the allowances at present given totrainees were not large enough to induce persons to give up theirwages during the period of training.The Lord Privy Seal said that it might be desirable for theGovernment to make a, contribution to bridge this gap betweenearnings and allowances.The Prime Minister thought that as a general rule men now atwork in unessential industries would probably pick up theirengineering training best in a factory. A further point was whetherthe Ministry of Labour&apos;s training centres could be used to trainwomen.The Minister of Labour said that the training centres had not hitherto done much to train women, but what experience they had suggested that they could easily be adapted to this purpose. Thetraining centres might perform a useful function in the case of menat present employed by preparing them for factories where training facilities were poor. At present only the larger factories affordedspecial facilities for training. For the rest, training was done onthe job itself.In reply to the Prime Minister, the Minister of Labour saidthat he did not think it would be necessary to establish additionaltraining centres merely to train the unemployed likely to come forward for training. New training centres might, however, benecessary if the Ministry undertook the training of persons inemployment; but these would not come forward in any numbersunless the gap between earnings in employment and allowancesduring training were filled. It was important not to relieve the employer of his responsibility for training his staff; and it waspossible that, in view of the difficulty in securing trained labour,employers might be willing to contribute towards this gap.(11) Training for army tradesmen.The Secretary of State for War said that, if persons in reserved occupations were not called up, it would be necessary for the army to train the tradesmen required.The Minister of Labour said that it had been hoped that thearrangement whereby the age of reservation was raised in the caseof persons in reserved occupations called up for service as tradesmenwould provide the Army with the skilled labour it required.The Secretary of State for War said that he was advised thatthis had proved inadequate.The Minister of Labour said that it had been suggested thatskilled men in the Army were not always used on skilled jobs; that,in fact, dilution might be practised in the Army.The Prime Minister said that, though cases of misuse of skill and labour occurred in the Army, it appeared that the system wassound. It would be preferable to train men to serve as tradesmenafter they had been called up, rather than to take men away fromkey positions in industry to serve as tradesmen in the Army.(12) Recruiting programme for 1940.The question was raised whether the recruiting programme for1940, in which men up to the age of 27 would be taken into themilitia, would produce any marked effect on the Unemployment Live
Register. Speaking very roughly, the present unemployment figuresmight be analysed as follows :- Persons passing from, one job to another ... 500,000Hard core of &apos;&apos; unemployable &apos;&apos; persons ... 250,000Unemployed in the strict sense of the word ...        600,0001,350,000The Minister of Labour said that the impact of a compulsory military training on figures such as those would be comparatively small.The Secretary of State for War said the argument thatrecruiting should be quickened up, so as to reduce unemployment,ought to be used with great caution. The experience of the last war had shown that nothing was worse for a man&apos;s morale and enthusiasm than for the Government to accept him for militaryservice while it lacked the facilities for training him. We werehoping to avoid a repetition of that experience in the present war.Nevertheless, the position of the second-line Territorial Divisionsat the present moment was very much what he had described. Itwas important not to aggravate the problem.(13) The Army&apos;s Man-Power Needs.The Secretary of State for War reminded his colleagues that,quite apart from casualties in the field, the creation of 45 Divisions,out of the male population left over after the reserved occupationshad been filled, was going to be a baffling task. It had been estimated in the War Office that the men could only be found byadvancing the age of calling up to 45. A Memorandum on thesubject was under preparation in the War Office.(14) Recruitment of Labour by Advertisement.The President of the Board of Trade said that there had recently been a very uneconomic tendency for large firms engaged on armaments work to draw men away from small factories in the exporting trades. The armaments industry ought to go to theEmployment Exchanges for its men, but it sometimes advertised.This was largely the cause of the drawing of men away from thesmall exporting factories.It was generally agreed that advertisements of the kindmentioned were contrary to the public interest and ought to be stopped. It appeared that powers for this purpose already existed,but that it had so far been considered unnecessary to use them. Thequestion was whether the situation was acute enough to justifyprohibiting advertisements.The Minister of Labour undertook to look into this matter.(15) Public Opinion.The War Cabinet were reminded that, in his recent speech atthe Mansion House, the Prime Minister had referred to the need for large-scale adjustments in the labour situation, in particular fromone occupation to another, as an essential feature of our war effort.This was an aspect of the problem, which it was important to keepwell before the public.(16) Future Procedure.It was agreed that the essence of the problem lay in the figures in the Table on page .8 of the Memorandum annexed toW.P. (G.) (40) 9, which showed an estimated deficiency of 1,328,500persons in the industries under consideration at July-September* Engineering and metal goods, aircraft, motors, &amp;c, shipbuilding and repairing.
1940, and of 2,178,000 at July 1941. It was agreed that this Tableshould be kept up to date, in order to show the extent to which theposition was improving. At the same time, it was felt that a specific plan was required to deal with the situation. The WarCabinet should keep in close touch on the matter, in order todetermine whether the methods at present in view for meeting the deficiency were adequate or whether new methods must be adopted.The Chancellor of the Exchequer was invited to consult with theMinisters concerned with a view to submitting a plan for dealingwith the whole position in the light of the discussion which hadtaken place, and to report to the War Cabinet.The War Cabinet I. Approved the following statement as to the methods whichshould be pursued in dealing with the question of Supplyand Man-power : (i) The fullest use should be made of existingengineering labour by the process of sub-con-tracting on the widest possible scale,(ii) Steps should be taken to ensure that, subject to therequirements of the export trade and to* themost stringent . examination of exceptions,engineering labour should be employed only onpurposes directly connected with our war effort.(iii) Means should be found to open out the peculiarlyacute &apos;: bottle-neck &quot; created by the shortage of skilled labour through the adoption of dilution(including the introduction of female labour) andthe more even spreading of the available skilled labour through the whole of the engineering trades.(iv) A long-range policy should be adopted of trainingunskilled and semi-skilled labour to undertakeskilled work, through direct or indirectencouragement to employers and through theexpansion of State facilities for training.II. Took note of the following points made in discussion : (i) That the area organisation set up by the Ministryof Supply should, for the present, be on an advisory basis. This decision should be subjectto review in three months&apos; time.(ii) That, while the primary responsibility for traininglabour lay with industry itself, a number of lesswell-equipped firms would need to be helped bythe Government if they were to find the labour required sufficiently quickly.(iii) That the following were among the measures whichthe Minister of Labour would consider in regardto Government Training Centres: (a) the   provision   of   training   facilities . forunskilled men already employed inunessential industry, in order to fit themfor semi-skilled jobs in war production.It would be necessary, in this connection,to consider the question of the payment ofwages during the period of training, andthe question whether a contribution couldbe obtained from the employer;(b) the provision of special training facilities forwomen;* The words printed in italic were inserted by the War Cabinet.
Anglo-soviet negotiations:Summer, 1939.proposed publication of blue Book.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 7thConclusions,Minute 9.)2. In accordance with the Conclusion referred to in the margin, the War Cabinet had before them the draft of the proposedBlue Book on Negotiations with the Soviet Government in the summer of 1939 (W.P. (G.) (40) 7).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theFrench Ambassador had represented that the French Governmentwere uneasy as to the publication of this Blue Book, which they thought would give opportunities for attack on the following lines :first, that the Blue Book showed that at the beginning of thenegotiations the Soviet Government were willing to go further inthe way of agreement than France or Great Britain; secondly, that,while the British and French Governments had begun by settingtheir face against sacrificing the interests of the small Statesbordering on Russia, they had finally given way to the SovietGovernment on almost all points.[20680] c-, (c) the training of men who could act asinstructors of newly-recruited labour in new factories, or in existing factoriesturned over to war production;(d) a shortening of the period of training below6 months;(e) the extension of facilities to enable servingsoldiers to be trained as Army tradesmen.(iv) That consideration should be given to the possibilityof extending the arrangement whereby the labour force of a new factory was given a period of, say,two or three months&apos; training in the factorybefore it was ready for full operation,(v) That the Secretary of State for War and theMinister of Labour would consult together as tothe possibility of the better utilisation of skilled men serving in the Army,(vi) That it would be desirable that, in their speeches in the country, Ministers should stress the needfor changes from one occupation to another as anessential part of our war effort,(vii) That the Minister of Labour would give particularsto the national bodies representing employers andemployed as to the extent of the increase in war production required to carry out the Govern-ment&apos;s plans.(viii) That the Minister of Labour would consider further the question whether steps should be taken to prohibit the competitive recruitment of labour inthe munitions industry by public advertisement,(ix) That the Secretary of State for War would submit to the Chancellor of the Exchequer a statement as to the Army&apos;s requirements of man-power, onthe assumption that the Schedule of reserved occupations was adhered to.III. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to examine thequestion of Man-power in relation to Supply in consul-tation with the Ministers concerned, in the light of thediscussion which had taken place, and to submit to theWar Cabinet a plan showing the measures already inoperation and those proposed to deal with this urgentmatter. The War Cabinet expressed the wish that thisReport should be the first of a series which would indicate the measure of success attending the efforts tobuild up the labour force required for war production.
The French Government also thought that publication of ourBlue Book would oblige them to publish something themselves. Thiswould give rise to acute domestic controversy in France.The Foreign Secretary said that he had been unable to shakethe French Ambassador&apos;s point of view. He had asked the ForeignOffice to consider the alternative of a short historical narrative,without publication of any documents. Such a document had beenprepared, but it was clear that it would give rise to as many difficulties as publication of the documents themselves.Continuing, the Foreign Secretary said that he was disposed,if possible, to pay regard to French susceptibilities in this matter.It would be remembered that on the 13th December the PrimeMinister had replied to a Question by Mr. Boothby, M.P., to theeffect that it was proposed to publish a White Paper showing thecourse of the negotiations with the Soviet Government. TheForeign Secretary&apos;s inclination was that a statement should be madein Parliament referring to this Question and saying that a collectionof the relevant documents had been made, and that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment, having done this, had thought it well to review theposition in consultation with the French Government, who had been associated with them in the negotiations; as a result, they had cometo the conclusion, in which the French Government concurred, thatthe publication of this collection would not be opportune at thepresent moment and had better be deferred to a more appropriate time.The Foreign Secretary added that the Leader of the labour opposition was not keen on publication.There was also the complication that the White Paper had been laid in dummy. It had been suggested by the Authorities of theHouse that this might, in the present case, involve a Motion to with-draw publication, and that such a Motion might lead to a debate in the House.In the discussion which ensued, the opinion generally expressedwas opposed to publication of the Blue Book. It was felt that, inthe present state of opinion, a decision in this sense would beaccepted without difficulty.The War Cabinet-(i) Agreed that publication at this juncture of the proposedBlue Book on the negotiations with the Soviet Govern-ment in the summer of 1939 was inopportune,(ii) Invited the Prime Minister to consult with the Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasury, and with the Leadersof the Labour and Liberal Oppositions, in regard to any necessary arrangements which it might be desirable tomake to give effect to this decision.The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 16thConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Secretary of State for Air informed the War Cabinetthat there had been little air activity during the previous day. no enemy raiders had visited this country.Some patrols and escorts had been carried out by fighter command, though hampered by weather.There had been no operations by Bomber Command on accountof fog and low visibility.The majority of Coastal Commands and Patrols had had to be cancelled owing to bad weather conditions. Five patrols, however,had been flown, and it had also been found possible to provide airescort for eight Convoys.  No sightings had been reported.German Air Force activities had been sub-normal, owing, nodoubt, to the weather.
The Naval 4.   The First Lord of the Admiralty informed the war situation. Cabinet that the British steamship Cairn Ross (5,544 tons), outward(Previous bound, had been mined and sunk off Liverpool.  The crew had been reference: saved. The Port of Liverpool had been closed, but an alternativeW.M. (40) 16th  channel had since been opened.Conclusions, An unknown ship believed to be Norwegian had been shelledMinute 2.) on the previous day and set on fire by a U-boat 6 miles north ofMuckle Flugga (North Shetlands). Derelict, it had been subse-quently sunk by gunfire from H.M.S. Firedrake. Destroyers and anti-submarine vessels were at present searching for the submarine.H.M.S. Duncan, whilst escorting the outward-bound NorwegianConvoy, had been in collision with a Norwegian ship of the convoy,steamship Haukefjell. H.M.S. Duncan, badly holed, had beentowed home. There had been a snowstorm at the time of thecollision and the Haukefjell had been last reported as missing, onthe afternoon of the previous day, but air search for her had beenarranged.H.M.S. Keppel had collided with the French destroyer Jaguaroff Vigo on the previous evening. Both had been holed, but were proceeding to port.The armed merchant cruiser Canton, which had entered the clyde on the 13th after grounding off the Hebrides on the 10th, had had to be beached on the previous day the pumps having failed tocontrol the leaks.About 90 merchant vessels were now anchored in the MetbilBoads awaiting passage south. Weather conditions had made itimpossible to sweep a passage through the minefield north of the tyne for two days. Special measures bad been taken to provide protection for these vessels.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The Military 5.   The Secretary of State for War informed the War cabinet situation. that the move of the 48th Division to France had been completed on western Front. fche Previous evening.(Previous The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Reference:W.M. (40) 9thConclusions, Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,Minute 3.) January 18, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
