<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/62/44 images: 386-389</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF BIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted; for tKe&apos;:WdrhCat)ihdk^ Mtitil%$WJ?\mi    .......1   ru&apos;.v.&quot;:i&apos;i        y\ iiiv/ unrn -tails srajosi teroiiM tfi ioThe &apos; circulation/of &quot;this pajger has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of top secret copy No.W.P. (45) 139.5th March, 1945.WAR CABINET.STREET LIGHTING IN LONDON.Memorandum by the Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security.THE Chiefs of Staff in their report (W.P. (45) 126) state that unrestrictedgas street lighting in London would not materially assist aircraft launchingflying bombs but might provoke an attack by piloted aircraft (paragraph 10).They suggest that an inter-departmental committee be set up to examine andreport on all questions of relaxation as they arise.2. I have had discussions with the gas and electric industries and theauthorities concerned with installing unrestricted street lighting, and thefollowing points emerged : &apos;(a) If unrestricted gas lighting were allowed in London it would be essentialto allow unrestricted electric street lighting as well. Many importantstreets are lighted partly by gas and. partly by electricity, e.g.,Whitehall above Horse Guards is lighted by electricity and belowby gas; Edgware Road is lighted on one side by gas and on the other by electricity. Full gas lighting and dimmed electric lighting would create a patchwork of light which would probably be dangerous to traffic. In addition, the boroughs lighted mainly by electric lightingwould complain, rightly, that they were being unfairly treated.(&amp;) The intermediate standard of street lighting, both gas-and electric, hasnow been completed everywhere in London except for a few points.If full gas lighting were now allowed, it would take an appreciabletime and considerable effort (involving increased man-power) to installit where possible. The transition period would show patchy results which would be objected to by drivers.(c) Full street lighting is not easy to install. The main gas street lighting-bodies in London (the Gas Light and Coke Company and the SouthMetropolitan Gas Company) inform me that it would be impossiblefor them to put in more than a proportion of the full gas lightingpoints now even if allowed. The difficulty is man-power. Full gaslighting cannot be put in without proper lanterns (the intermediatestandard can), and man-power is not available to make these lanterns.&apos;&apos; Controllers &apos;&apos; and &apos;&apos; by-pass &apos;&apos; tubes are required in large numbers,but manufacturers cannot make them in sufficient quantities as theyhave not sufficient men. Maintenance would be required on muchmore than double the existing number of street lighting points; and250 additional men would be required by these two gas companies forthis purpose in London alone. - As street lighting is not as important as, for example, war work or housing repairs, the gas companies andthe manufacturers have not been able to get the necessary men. until they are available, gas street lighting in full is not practicable.[29366]
(d) Double summer *will be; introduced on. the 2nd April and street lighting &quot;alter that will be less important-in fact, at the requestof the Ministry of Fuel and Power, my Department asks lightingauthorities to put out their street lights altogether during the greaterpart of the period of Double British Summer Time. It therefore seemsundesirable to start installing full lighting for a week or two, as the gas companies say that only a portion could be completed in that time.They would prefer a much longer period, and a promise of some assist-ance in man-power for manufacture and maintenance before they were required to put in full gas lighting. They would like to have the summer in which to make the necessary arrangements, with a pro-visional promise of full lighting when the nights get darker in August1945.(e) Fuel consumption, if. full street lighting is brought in now, will be very greatly increased and will be much more than pre-war because neitherthe time-switches nor the man-power for switching out at night areavailable. Thus full street lighting, with powerful lights, would beon day and night and, besides increasing the consumption consider-ably, would be likely to cause protests from the public, who alreadyobject to the fact that the present dimmer standards have to remainalight all the time. The Gas, Light and Coke Company estimate theincreased consumption of coal over peace-time figures at about100,000 tons a year in their area alone.In view of the points made by the lighting authorities, I would suggest that,as full street lighting could not be fully installed before the longer summer days and could not be adequately maintained where installed, it would be preferable to look forward to installing full street lighting after the summer period, if theChiefs of Staff then agree. The lighting authorities could then take advantageof the summer months to arrange the manufacture of the necessary material andtry to obtain the necessary man-power for maintenance. . It should be made clear,however, that the installation, and more especially the maintenance, of full street lighting is mainly a question of man-power and some assistance in this directionis necessary if we are to get back to normal lighting.3. The Chiefs of Staff say that selected relaxations, such as the glare fromBeckton Works, which offer valuable industrial dividends, are acceptable.Selection in this matter is, however, a most difficult matter. When the lord presidents Committee allowed glare from coke ovens in areas outside London, I found ,it necessary, in addition, to allow glare from iron foundries, clay and limeWorks, &amp;c. It is practically impossible to allow Only selected works or selectedindustries to show glare, as often (as with coke and iron) they are in the samepremises and under the same ownership. Thus, if glare is allowed at Beckton, i feel we must allow it at all other glare-producing industries near London, andthey could probably show as strong a case as Beckton.In addition, other establishments and businesses in the neighbourhood could resonably claim the right to show lights which are less intense than those from acoke oven, and the result could hardly be less than complete relaxation.4. The Chiefs of Staff in a note attached to their paper suggest that noactual increases in lighting in the London area should at present be permittedWithout reference to them, in view of the assistance which might be given topickaback aircraft. In view of the recent activity by German piloted aircraft, itis doubtful Whether the public Would welcome an increase in lighting in or near london or other towns at the present time. Indeed it is likely that generally or incertain areas they would vigorously object.5. I, therefore, recommend that lighting authorities should be asked toprepare for full lighting at the end of the Double British Summer Time period,namely the 15th July, though the assurance that it will be possible to make thisrelaxation can only be provisional.H. M.Home Office and ministry of Home Security,Whitehall, S. XV. 1,5th March, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
