<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/61/46 images: 434-441</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
20HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC majesty 3 GOVERNMENT)(--------. .-------, -      - -S E Q R E TW.P.   (kb)  91 - COPY NO. 3 fe1QTH FEBRUARY,  19-J!-5..WAR   CABINETFAMILY ALLOWANCES/ ,4 /  i^&apos;Memorandum- by the Minister of National InsuranceAt the meeting of the War Cabinet on 9th February   I was asked to have a Clause drafted for consideration which would leave the treatment of the allowances paid in respect of thechildren of members of the Forces to be dealt with by regulations, as is already proposed in the-case of police and firemen&apos;s pensions.    I accordingly circulate the attached draft.The draft covers not only the allowances above referredto but also the corresponding- allowances paid under the warpensions scheme,  the civil Injuries schemes and certain othermiscellaneous schemes of a similar kind, together of coursewith the police and firemen who were previously covered.    It isI think, necessary that we should go as far as this, if we make the change at all.In view of the nature of the regulation-making powerhere proposed, I think also we ought to consider whether these regulations should not be subject to confirmation bypositive resolution in Parliament.I was also asked to prepare a draft statement for-consideration by the War Cabinet dealing with the question   -of Service pay and allowances.If the Clause is to extend not only to Service men butalso to war pensioners, war widows and civilian injurypensioners, the statement will presumably also have to make some reference to those classes.. If it is desired to confine the regulative power to service men and Police and Firernes only, the passages in square brackets in this statement could be omitted.W.A.J.Carlton House Terrace., S.W.L,- &apos; V ...&quot; I *   -10TH FEBRUARY,   19k5*?5   W.M.   (h-5) 17th Conclusions, Minute 3

FAMILY ALLOWANCES bill draft Clause as to Service Allowances, Civil Injuries,  etc.&quot; Allowances and Police-&quot;an&apos;a Flflinen^s Allowances(1)   &apos;The Minister may make regulations for the reduction orthe withholding of an.allowance in respect of a child for whom an allowance is being paid. -(a) in respect of the service of a member of thenaval, military or air forces of the Crown(including such nursing or other auxiliaryservice as may be prescribed), out of moneys provided, by Parliament;(b) under any Royal Warrant, Order in Council or order by His Majesty&apos;providing for awards inrespect of the disablement or death of personswho have served in any of the said forces, outof moneys provided by Parliament;(c) under any scheme made by virtue of the Injuriesin War (Compensation) Act, 1914* the Injuries inWar Compensation Act, 1914 (Session 2), theInjuries in War (Compensation) Act, 1915, theGovernment War Obligations acts, 1914 to 1916,the Pensions (Navy, Army, Air Force and.Mercantile Marine) Act, 1949, either as originally enacted or as amended by thePensions (Mercantile Marine) Act, 1942, or the personal Injuries (Emergency Provisions) Act,1939;    or(d) under or by virtue of the police. Pensions Act, 1921,or under or by virtue of any enactment  (whether public, general or local) relating to thepensions of firemen or any scheme or regulationmade under any such enactment&apos;.(2)    The Minister may by regulations make provision fortreating as not included in any family children in respectof whom there is being paid a pension for a fatherless or-motherless child -(a) in respect of any such service as is mentionedin paragraph (a) of subsection (1) of thisSection, out of moneys provided by parliament;(b) under any such instrument as is mentioned inparagraph (b) of the said subsection (1)yout &apos;of moneys provided by Parliament;(c) under any such scheme as is mentioned inparagraph (c) of the said subsection (1);    or(d) under or by virtue of the Police Pensions Act,1921, or any such enactment, scheme or regulations, as mentioned in paragraph (d)of the said subsection (1).

DRAFT    statement the effect of Clause 13 of the Bill is to give theMinister power to make Regulations which may either includeor exclude, service men /war pensioners, war widows and civilian injury pensioners/ from the provisions of the Act,The same principle applies to Police pensioners and firemen.The reason for this method of treatment is as follows.It is clear that the time has now come when the whole structure of Service pay and allowances must be brought,under thorough and complete review.The Government is now undertaking that review and itwill be completed before, the Family Allowances Bill is.brought into force.The review may arrive at its conclusion on the basis that family allowances under this Bill are to be payableor on the basis that they are not to be payable.The Minister in drafting his Regulations would carryout the conclusions arrived at as a result of that review.What I have said applies equally.to. the pensions of thePolice and Firemen./As regards war pensioners, war widows and civilianinjury pensioners, the Government, would desire to keepthe position open until the related question of what isto be done for the Armed Forces has been determined^/7&quot;.There is also the further point that it is an obviousconvenience to the recipient of any allowance that the allowance shall be paid in one sum on one day, &quot;rather thanin two sums coming from tv/o different sources, andpayable -&apos;it may be - on two different days.To achieve this result it will be obviously more convenient, for instance, to pay to the serving soldierwhatever may be adjudged to be the appropriate children&apos;allowance from that source from which he derives hischildren&apos;s allowance as it exists today./In the same way it will be more convenient to pay to the war.widow or the disabled war pensioner whatever may be considered to be the proper !children&apos;s allowancefrom the Ministry of pensions - instead of paying part from the Ministry of Pensions and part from the Ministryof National Insurance.And exactly the same consideration applies to thosereceiving children&apos;s allowances under the Civilian WarInjuries scheme - allowances which they are receiving- todayfrom the Ministry of pensionsjj7&quot;




</content>
</cab>
