<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/33 images: 200-201</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IB THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).&apos;&apos;       - - - - k copy No.      &apos;JtJSECRETW.P. (&amp;) (40) 233&apos; .September, 11th 19AO. . -t   -7/AR CABINET.&quot;OMNIBUS&quot;   COIMUNIQUE.&apos;   MEMDRANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF INFOPMATION.Sir Samuel Hoare has represented strongly that the jointAir, Army and Naval communiques issued hy the German and ItalianHigh Commands at a set time every day receive much greater publicitythan the shorter communiques issued by our Service Departments.The Spanish Press are nominally obliged to publish all officialcommuniques, but experience shows that only a certain proportion ofthe British communiques are publishedo     The remedy is to follow theGerman and Italian example and to issue every day an omnibus communiquebased on the communiques of the previous 2I+ hours,, together with any material available shortly before the issue of the communique.In view of the fact that the situation in Spain as described by Sir Samuel Hoare exists in a number of other foreign countries,I invited the Joint Intelligence Committee to consider the question.Their recommendations which have been accepted by the Chiefs of staff are set out in the Appendix.It is proposed that the communique should be prepared by representatives of the three Service Dcpartmentss the Ministry ofHome Security,  and the Ministry of Information, and should be issued   iat 12.30 p0m0 every day.      The Communiques would bear a serial number to make the suppression of any communique in the foreign press morediffioult.If the War Cabinet approves the proposal, it will be putinto effeot as soon as possible.D.C.September 11th,  19A0.APFENDJJC^Recommendations, of Joint Intelligence Committee.(l)   The Ministry of Information should prepare, in conjunction with theService Departments and the Ministry of Home Security,, a daily&quot;cmnibus communique&quot;^ primarily intended for foreign consumption,to include all important items of information enamating from theService Departments and the Ministry of Home Security for the past22f hours o
-   2   -(2) &apos; That this communique should also include as and when necessary,summaries designed to place information issued in its properperspective as regards the progress of the war as a whole, and togive necessary publicity to the sum of British successes,(3)   The issue of an &quot;omnibus oommunique&quot; primarily intended forforeign consumption, should not preclude the issue as heretoforeby Service Departments and the Ministry of Home Security of theirown communiques,, primarily intended for home consumption, but thatgenerally speaking the foimer should be a more colourfulamplification of the latter, plus any additional items ofinformation which may arise between the time of the issue of thelast Departments communique and the issue of the &quot;omnibuscommunique&quot;.(4)   This &quot;omnibus communique&quot; should be issued at the most suitable time to achieve the greatest publicity abroad.

</content>
</cab>
