<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/31/0 images: 263-272</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mis document is the property of His Britannic Majesty*s Government)SECRET.0 A B I g E t     57/22.CQNCLUSIOHS of a meeting of the cabinet held at Ho. 10 Downing Street, S.W, , at11 p.mf on Thursday, 5th October, 1922.P B   S B H I:-The Prime Minister     (In the chair)e Eight Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P,,    She Eight Hon. The Earl of Balfour,ord Privy Seal.K.G.,O.M., lord President of theCouncil-.he Host Hon. The Marquess Curzonf Kecllest on, K. G., G.C. 3,1., G.C. 1.1cretary of State for Foreignffairs.The Eight Eon. W.S, Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Si ght H on * Si r 1. Worthinet on-&apos;e Right Hon. The Viscount Peel, x^.o- tug.B.E., Secretary of State for India. Evans, Bart, G.B.E.,  Secretary of Statfor War.he Right Hon. Lord Lee of Ear eh am,,B,E,, K.C.B., First Lord of thetairalty.The Eight Hon. S. Baldwin, M.P.;President of the Boardvof Trade.Right Hon.  Sir A. Mond, Bart., M.P,The Eight Hon. H.A.L. Fisher, M,PJMinister of Health.he Right Hon. Sir A. Griffith-loscawen, M.P., Minister of Agri-ulture and Fisheries.President of the Board of education the Eight Hon.T.J. Macnamara, M73?.;tjMinister of Labour.lie Right Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwood,irt., K.C.,M.P., Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.The Eight Hon. The Earl of Crawford&amp; Balcarres, K.T., First commissioner of Works.The following were also present.-Sir Edward Grigg, K.CV.0.,G.M.ff.,     Admiral of. the Fleet the Earl Beatty,G.O.B. ,0.M, ,G.C.V,0.,B.S.O., first sea Lord.eaeral the Earl of Cavan, K.P., Air Chief Marshal Sir H.M. Trenchard,&apos;J.M.G.,G.C.Y.0., K.C.B.,ADC Gen. Bart. K.C.B. ,D. S.O. ,A .D.C., Chief oflief of the Imperial General Staff,    the Air Staff.jjeut.-0ol. Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B., ........................ Secretary.Zander E .H. Moore, D. S.G. ,E.K. ,*.*.................Assistant Secretary.
Conclusion 1,filth referenoe to Cabinet 56  22),/a meeting was  summoned as a matter of great urgency to considertelegrams whioh had been received from general harington in regard to the progress of the MndaaiaConference *She Secretary of State for War read the telegrams in the following order:-   2815 in 3 parts,2627, and D*2 of which the first part only of 3 partswas available *Later in the evening he re&amp;6 the first partof 2618.     These telegrams are reproduced in theAppend is-*During the Meeting Sir Horace Bumbo Id *telegram 80*83$ giving in full the reply of the Grandnational Assembly of Angora to the Paris invitation,was handeS round.After considerable aiseassion, mainly as tothe meaning of these very corrupt sad incompletefrom General Harington.telegrams/ the Cabinet agreed-2b at the information before them was insufficient to enable them to give any instructions to General Harington;That the&apos;Admiralty should send, immediatelya short advance message by wireless telegraphyinstructing General Harington to postpone his departure to Mudania until after he hadreceived a telegram from the War Office;That the secretary of State for War should send a telegram Informing General Haringtonthat     only   portiomof his telegrams had arrived, and that part of these were verycorrupt, consequently the Cabinet were unableto send him instructions as he had requestedbefore 10 s*m. the following morning;   thatas soon as possible full instructions wouldbe sent; and that in the meanwhile he should postpone his departure to Mudania;(a)(b)(d)That ...
(d) ( bat fee see re tar y of State iOr ForeignAffairs should send a telegram to t&amp;eBritish High Commissioner at Constantinople -notifying him that General Earington&apos;stelegrams were partly unintelligible,partly corrupt and Incomplete;   that ithad been necessary to ask General harington to postpone his departure to Mudania untilthe Cabinet had the material on which to base their instinctions;   that in the mean-while the High Commissioner should make an explanation of the points on which general harington required instructions, a ni should give an appreciation of the situation, inparticular on the Four points at issue, towhi ch General Haringtan had re flerred;   thathe should forward a copy of the documenthanded to the  emailsts by the allied generals, sad should say what were theimpossible proposals alluded to by general harington;   and that he should report what had happened in regard to the neutralacnes:(e) 3hat the Secretary of State for Foreign, Affaire should instruct the BritishAmbassadors in Paris and Rome to informthe French and Italian Governments respective-ly that, owing to tbe obscurity of telegramsreceived from General Harington, the BritishGovernment had been obliged to order GeneralHa ring t on to postpone bis return to Mudaniauntil full information of what had passedhad been received.
$fce SVftcm&amp;tloa (43) reference to Cabinet 561/28,of Saetem fhraoe.    0owlltt8lOT1 Xf %hii secretary of State for Foreignktf&amp;lve read SJelegrem llo.4?0 to Sir Horaotfiiasfeold giving the views expressed by M*Veniselostw regards the evacuation of Eastern Thrace-The $vim Minister requested Lord Oursonto make It quite clear to Sir H*Btuabeiath&amp;t &quot;fee &quot;effective allied control&quot; ofthe evaottatea area referred to in thefirst, sentence of the $eXegr&amp;m underiiscassJlon was intended to be &quot;control by Allied&apos; troops&apos;1&apos;.
tjhe Provisional ,3)      1th reference to Cabinet S6(B2), conclusions-jdaiai stratioapf Eastern Thrace.        location 1, same doubt was expressed as to whether,in the event of an impasse being reached inregard to the provisional administration of teatern Thrace, the matter was of sufficient importance to justify the British Foroes being used to prevent the Turkish Mb. tionaiiats frominvading Bastera Thrace,la this o eon action the prime minister asked Ma oolieago.es to consider, before thenext meeting, what would be the proper answer to the following question - &quot;Ssppose that adecision is tsken to instraet Geoeral Baringtoato allow the Turks to occupy Thsaee, and suppose the Greeks decline to accept;   in these cir-eamstances, to what lengths should the BritishGovernment be prepared to go to put pressure onGreeee?&quot;2   Whitehall Gardens, S.W./16th October .1982
0 IA .P &quot;P B y .D X X.CIPHER. S E C R E T.From s- General Bisrington.To     s- %&apos;ar Office,Repeated Dardanelles Defence Force, chapter HAS.D. 15.00 5/10.R.    19.IS 8/10 *$615 Cipher 5/10*     First of three parts.Today has been very long and difficult-   The Nationalistrepresentatives here have been very obstinate and ever since we came here they have tried to trap as into political measures.They are surrounded by representatives from AKOORA, FRAHKhXHBOUIhLIOH and others whilst HAM ID is a member of the conference.We refuse to toe drawn and have stuck to our guns.   My colleagueshove been loyal from start to finish.   The nationalistrepresentatives wish to adjourn at every turn and telephone toAFOGRA.     We have been most considerate and handed ISMET a document today on which we hoped to reach an agreement but hehas refused nearly every point,   le ore meeting again tonightto see If we can reach an agreement,   le still have four very important points connected with the evacuation of THRACE tosettle.PART g.They have practically threatened to resume operations unless wecan reaeh an agreement and it Is therefore a&apos; very serious mattersThis afternoon the Greek representatives arrived and we are tomeet them tomorrow morning.   It is very rough on the sea here and there Is very great difficulty In landing.   From start tofinish it has bees one long fight, I do not think they want tofight us if they can get Eastern Thrace without.     They keeptelling us that the Allied note has been accepted and that aConference has been asked for on October 15th hut I had no definite knowledge of this.     They are anxious to get us to agreeto sending troops to Thrace forthwith.   They have information that 40 villages were burned yesterday in Thrace.LAST PARTI have repeatedly said that the matter is in their hands andthey should accept entirely the Allied Mote when no doubt action would be taken without delay by the Allied Governments.   A lot of impossible proposals have been put forward by them regardingthe neutralisation of the Eastern portion of THRACE as a bufferwhich we have rejected.     They evidently made a trap for us withall this political weight and evidently thought they would catchus.   There is a possibility of our signing something tomorrowbut the Terms they are standing out for are really difficult.They want us to send troops Into Eastern Thrace immediately and I think this is necessary but as I have repeatedly said they must accept the Allies Kote.   The Intrigues all roundmake situation a very difficult one to handle.
S 39 0 B. S i&apos;*OSKaS IKSLIMB.Fromfos-$AB Oll?I0B. .20.30 5/10.B.21.30 5/10.2627 5/10.In order to consult H10i Gemiiisslemers Allied $eaeralsare returning from MOMtllA and arrive at Oon&amp;tsntinople20.00 hours today.    At 21*00 hours General ilaringten seessir IU Bffiiilseldf    Conference of High $cmaal set oners ttaorrowat ? 08.00 hoars.    Allied Generals tee fc&amp;ek MHPAtlA Fritey14*30 hours.
Frams-To:-U- at ia*S* Me&amp;n*Troopers.(H3Kl3iA&amp; E&amp;KX1GTQM TO MM CSWXOB&apos; 5/3.0*        3 Parts.Today at Conference after generals hat tone utmost tostrain their powers on points of detail with a view to mset-ing the Hatieaalists Ismet reverted suddenly to (Two groupsundecipherable) *    He maintained that putting together theAllied&quot; Sots of Jt&amp;th and Angara&apos;s reply seems to fee theeoneoetiou of ifEABS&amp;XIl BOUII^oiu     fhe basis in the event oila Conference talcing place is tax at S astern Thrace sfeall feerestored fully to the Batioaslists by Treaty of Peace with-out any Foreign control when the OBSIKS have once left (onegp. undea* I     Gharpy stated he was empowered to sign to this!affect. &quot;&quot; mS MZ3*l&quot;however and 1 declared our inability tomake any such ecu tract.    It was quite obvious that Pranklinhas twisted the Turks into I 2 groups undecipherable) theAllied Governments besides the French end authorise the generals to make political decisions.     It was decided bythe Generals after they had consulted together to adjournconference until October 6th at 14.30 hours so that theymight have time to return to Constantinople and to consultHigh commissioner and exohaage telegrams with theirrespeetive Governments.
f&amp; P T&apos;G x.35from.-   General H&amp;i?ingtos.So:-      War Officellepeated. Dardanelles Befeaaeo force.$.15*00 6th*E.10.00 Stfc* 616..        4/10.        fwo Parts.        1st Parts.A bat turn took place In Gonferenee today allied generals drew up a very reasonable programme within limit of their instructions but to each clause political objections were insinuated.     It is obvious that Turks are trying to anticipate Treaty.     Franklin Bouillon, very active and gives insuression that furks have bees promised by him more than Allied Generals can give within terms of conference.    At present main difficulties are:-(a)   Qlaiia of Turks to E&amp;BA AG AGE on grounds that Forts across J&amp;A-BXfSA will be source of danger is Greek occupation.fb)   Objection to limitation of number ofGendarmerie.(c) Objection to principle that Allied Mission&apos;&amp;should remain in any area evacuated by Greeksafter It has been taken over by Turkishadministration.(d) Turkish claim to right to carry out militaryoperations even after signature of militarycontention until ratified by So verss meatsconcerned.
Des. 16-00   5/10/82From General Haringtou, Ree. 20-16To War Office, repeated Dardanelles Defence Force.No. 2616.   4/10-     last part.Understand that another meeting of generals takes place tonight to seek solution but it will be difficult.Hint offered by Ismet today that $rationalists have other&apos;ways of reoccupying Thrace than by Armistice with theAllies but he would not admit, tshen I challenged him.   .that Turkish operations were directed against anyonebut Greeks.     Owing to bad weather 1 shall not meet GreekMission until morning of Oct. 5th.   Meanwhile I am warningChanek and Scutari to keep on the alert.Reference F.Q. telegram of Oct. 3rd it would be quite impossible for the Greeks to remain in Thrace afterwithdrawal of the- Greek Army.

</content>
</cab>
