<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/31/0 images: 369-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Ifjlis document is the property of His Britannic Majests&apos;s Government) 3 b 6C A B I ffl E g    65/22.COEGLU SICES Q  a meeting of the cabinet held at Ho. 10 Downing Street, S.W., on tuesday 10th October, 1928, at 5 p.m.PEBSIHThe prise Minister   (In the chair)Eight Eon. A. Chamberlain, It.p Privy Seal.Eight Hon. Viscount Birkenhead,rd Chancellor.Eight Eon. E,. Shortt, i.c.tM.?.,bretary of State for Home Affairs.1 Hight Eon.W.5. Churchl11* M. P.,Ire tar y of State for the Colonies.1 Eight Eon. Sir 1. Worthington-Ins, Bart, G.B.E.,M.P.., secretary state for War.Eight Hon. S. Baldwin, M.P.,ssident of the Boarfl of Trade.I Eight Eon. H.A.L. Fisher, M.P.,Isident of the Board of Education.t Eight Eon. T.J. Macnaiaara, M.P.,lister of Labour.The Eight Eon. The Earl of Balfou*fr,K.G..:Bord president of the Council.The Eight Eon. Sir Robert Horne,G.B.E.E.C.,M.P.,  Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Most Eon. The Marquess Gorzon ofHeoleston, h.G- ,G.C.3.I. ,G.CI.E.,Secretary of state for poa?eign Affairs.The Eight Eon. Viscount peel, G.B.B.,Secretary of State for India.The Eight Eon. Lord Lee of fareham,G.B.E.,, .CB., First Lord of $heAdmiralty.:The Eight Eon. Sir A. Mond, Bsrt.,M.P.Minister of Health.The Eight Eon. Sir A-Griffith-Boscawen,M.P.,   Minister of Agriculture   andfisheries.Thy Eight Eon. Sir Earner Greenwood,Bart., K.C.,M.P.f  Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.The Eight Eon. The Earl of Crawford&amp; Balcarres, K.T., First commissioner of Works.Also present sir Edward Grigg, E.C.Y.0.tC.M.G-*ut.-Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.3.....eut.-Col. Sir J.E.Chancellor,  .C.M..G. ,B.S.O., ............. seoretar]-.. principal assistant secretary, C.I.D.
THE SITUATION IN THE NEAR EAST.



THE MUDANIA CONFERENCE.

1. With reference to Cabinet 62 (22), Conclusion 1, the Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that no telegram had yet been received from Mudania, and in the circumstances he felt that no useful purpose would be served by discussing the terms of the Armistice.

THE PROPOSED PEACE CONFERENCE.

2. With reference to Cabinet 61(22), the Prime Minister asked the Secretary of State for foreign Affairs if he desired to continue the discussion of the arrangements for the Peace Conference.

 Lord Curzon on deprecated continuing the discussion of the Peace Conference arrangements at present. He sent a telegram to the High Commissioner at Constantinople asking him for his views on certain points and he was unwilling to advise the Cabinet on the subject until he had received a reply from Sir Horace Rumbold and had considered his suggestions. Lord Curzon mentioned that the Turks, who want no Allied troops on missions when they arrive in Thrace, had made a suggestion that in place of an Allied occupation of Eastern Thrace for 30 days, the Allies should take over the administration of Eastern Thrace for 45 days, after which it should be handed over completely. This proposal was also preferred by the Greeks. The Greeks also had made a proposal that the line in Eastern Thrace should be that fixed In 1915,that is to say, to the East of the Maritza River.(General Harington&apos;s telegram D.29).

Lord Curzon, in reply to a question as to how far M. Venizelos directed Greek policy, informed the Cabinet that M. Venizelos, in reply to a request from
the Greek Goveinraent that he should representthem &amp;broad,haii imposed certain conditions &quot;beforeaccepting the post.     The Greek Government had nowconsented to the conditions imposed by    Venizelosso that he is now the official representative of greece abroad and would, in all probability, repre-sent Greece at the Peace Conference,It was agreedTo await the receipt cf a telegramfrom Sladania and the reply of theSigh Commissioner to&apos;the telegramof the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs before continuing the dis-cuseion of the arrangements for thePeace Conference.2, Whitehall Gardens, s.w.1,/110th Oeteber,lt*  

</content>
</cab>
