<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/181/7 images: 104-107</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
\REFERENDUM ON EUROPEAN COMMUNITY MEMBERSHIPMemorandum by the Lord President of the council, We must now decide how and when to fulfil the commitment aboutEuropean Community membership in our October Manifesto that :  &quot;within12 months of this Election we will give the British people the final say,which will be binding on the Government - through the ballot box - on whether we accept the terms and stay in or reject the terms and come out&quot;.WORKING PARTY report. On the assumption that we shall neither wish nor need to haveanother General Election in the months ahead, there is no alternative tofulfilling the Manifesto commitment by holding a national referendum beforethe middle of next October.    This raises a range of political and practicalquestions.    It will also commit us to costs (of some millions of pounds)which cannot be assessed at this stage.    I have circulated separately a preliminary report by an official working party on the practical implications(C(75) 6).    This paper deals with the immediate political issues.NEED FOR REFERENDUM bill ,        As the Attorney General has confirmed, the holding of a referendumwill require legislation in order to adapt the electoral machinery for thepurpose; to authorise the required expenditure; to provide a statutory basis for any measures relating to the conduct of the referendum campaign;and - as Parliament can be expected to wish - to embody the terms of thequestion.DATE OF REFERENDUM4.        The earliest at which we can expect to reach a verdict onrenegotiation will be the second half of March - after the meeting of the heads of Community Governments in the European Council in Dublin.There will be advantage in holding the referendum as soon as possible thereafter.    From every point of view at home and as regards the Community,we should restrict to a minimum the unavoidable period of uncertainty beforethe &quot;final say&quot; of the British people has been expressed.1C(75) 7 COPY NO      4217 January 1975CABINET
5.;       I therefore propose that our aim should be to carry a ReferendumBill through Parliament in time to hold the referendum not later than theend of June - that is, before the summer holidays begin.    TheParliamentary timetable would be bound to be tight, but I judge that itshould be manageable in circumstances in which Parliament had come toaccept as inevitable the commitment to consult the British people throughthe ballot box and would see that the balance of advantage lay in doing sosooner rather than later,    I consider that we should now plan the referendum on this basis; but that we should also keep open the option of holding it in late September or early October since we cannot yet be sure that a June date will be practicable,TIMING OF REFERENDUM bill.        If this approach is agreed, I would also propose to put the referendum Bill to the Cabinet at the end of March - subsequent to our decision on the outcome of renegotiation.    That would be the moment atwhich to consider further the timing of the referendum.EARLY PARLIAMENTARY STATEMENT7.        We should make an early announcement of our intentions.    i suggest that there should be a Parliamentary statement by the PrimeMinister as soon as possible.    This should cover, as a minimum, our decision to hold a referendum as soon as possible after the completion of renegotiation; to introduce a Bill for the purpose at the appropriate moment, and to include the terms of the referendum question in the Bill.8. But we may also need to indicate the Government1 s view on someother important questions posed by a referendum commitment - while making clear that we shall be ready to consider subsequently any viewsput to us.    For example, what will constitute a majority which theGovernment would accept as binding?   How will the referendum result be counted and announced?    What will be the position of the Channel islands and the Isle of Man?   How do we intend to approach the handling ofinformation and the media?    There is much further work to be done onthese and other questions.    I am circulating separate papers on information policy (C(75) 8) and on the question of counting and announcing the referendum result (C(75) 9).recommendations. To sum up, I would ask my colleagues to agree that:a.        We should now decide to fulfil the October Manifestocommitment by holding a referendum.2
b. We should aim to hold the referendum as soon as possible after renegotiation is expected to be completed - that is, not later than the end of June - while keeping open the option of a referendumnot later than the beginning of October.c. Detailed planning - including the preparation of a referendum Bill to be submitted to the Cabinet in late March -should now be set in hand on the basis of a. and b.d. A Parliamentary statement should be made as soon aspossible,10.       I also ask my colleagues to note that I am circulating separatepapers as follows; as background information, a working party report by officials on the practical implications of a referendum (C(75) 6) and, for separate consideration, papers on the issues of information policy (C(75) 8)and on the question of counting and announcing the referendum result(C(75) 9).ifE privy Council Office17 January 19753


</content>
</cab>
