<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/280/0 images: 4-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOOUMBWT IS THIS PROPERTY uF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;b  GUV3HHHEMT.)B E G R 3 T.;.P. 246  (38).                                         Copy No,                              CABINET.                   IMPERIAL AIRWAYS AND BRITISH AIRWAYS.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer     and the Secretary of State for Air.1.     Our colleagues will remember that the cabinet decided (Cabinet 49 (38) Conclusion 17) that the questionsof policy involved by the contemplated amalgamation ofImperial Airways and British Airways should be discussedinformally at a meeting of Ministers,2.     That meeting has been held and those ministers present agreed in principle to the proposed amalgamation.They further agreed that as the amalgamated concern would,in any event at the outset, be largely dependent onsubsidies from His Majesty&apos;s Government it was necessarythat the dividends should be restricted to the limits usuallyassociated with public utility companies.   Such restrictionwould be in accordance with the views expressed, in theCadman Report and with the Government observation thereonto the effect that the Government were &quot;in agreement withthe principle underlying the proposal, namely that public money should not be used for raising dividends to unduelevels1&apos;.^.     After consideration of alternative forms of  -organisation the meeting came to the unanimous conclusionthat the most feasible form of organisation was that whichhad in fact been recommended to the Government Departments
concerned by Mr. Morison of Thomson McLintock and Companyafter a careful and detailed investigation,,   The scheme inquestion would involve the formation of a Public Corporation,under statute, to acquire the existing undertakings ofImperial Airways and British Airways at a figure to beagreed between the Government and the Directors of the two companies and approved by their respective shareholders.The Board of the Corporation would be appointed by theGovernment, though subsequent vacancies might be filled by the Board itself subject to the approval of theGovernment.   The Corporation would be a statutory body with certain statutory limits on its powers - in particular on the amount of its dividends or interest payable on itsstock.   The money required     (a)  for the purchase of Imperial Airways and            British Airways (say,  3,000,000)     (b)  for immediate development (say another  3,000,000)            and     (c)  for future development until such time as the            Corporation could stand on its own feet,would be found by the issue of fixed, interest stockguaranteed as to principal and interest by the Government.The annual subsidy would continue to be paid and would befixed in such a way as to cover the service of the guaranteedStock and to allow reasonable provision of reserves for development with a view to reduction of the need for futureguaranteed capital.    Capital would thus be raised on the cheapest possible terms and the subsidy, instead of catering,as at present, for dividends of 7^% to 10% on ordinary shares would be required to cover the low rate of interest(3% to 5-2%) payable on medium or long term guaranteed stock.
3rd,Novembert  1938.4.     Sir John Reith, as chairman of Imperial Airways,and Mr. Olive Pearson, as Chairman of British Airways, haveagreed in principle to amalgamation and to a public corporation.5..     Legislation would be required to set up theproposed Corporation and to give the Treasury power to guarantee principal and interest on its stocks.  The objectof this memorandum is to seek the authority of the cabinet for the preparation of the necessary legislation.6.     The date of the announcement to the House and the shareholders will have to be settled at the discussion withthe representatives of the companies.    Till that date itis most desirable that the decision should be kept completelysecret.                        (intl&apos;d&apos;d.)                           &quot;       K.W.

</content>
</cab>
