<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/280/0 images: 22-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY  OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.      SECRET,                                 COPY NO, /AO      CP, 248*  (38)           London  Traffic Problems  and  Charing Cress Bridge.,                  Memorandum by the. Minister  of Transport.         lo    On 14th October,  1937g I  submitted a memorandum (CP,243  (37)) dealing  with  the question  of a grant-(since made) towards  the new Waterloo Bridge.   I referred to tl-re proposal to build a  new bridge  in  the neighbourhood  of Charing Cross, as this scheme had a  bearing on the Waterloo Bridge  question, although I asked my colleagues to consider the latter proposition as an entirely separate issue and on its own merits,         2,    I  expressed the opinion that &quot;it may well be that it may prove  necessary to abandon the idea  of a new bridge at Charing Cross9 since  it has been represented to  me that in the best interests  of  London it would be well to  ascertain the effect of other measures  for  the improvement of  conditions in Central London which are  less  costly  and probably more  urgent than a new Charing Cross Bridge&quot;.              I  added that when Sir Charles Bressey&apos;s Highway Development Survey was available and a further report from the London Traffic  Advisory Committee  (who were  then considering the subject),,  I should be  in a better  position to reach some final decision about  charing Cross Bridge0   I have now received these two reports,         3,    Sir  Charles Bressey has expressed the opinion that the very  large expenditure which the scheme would entail could bebetter applied  to other improvements designed to deflect traffic from  the most crowded  centres.             The London Traffic Advisory Committee have informed me (on 2nd November, 1938) that while still adhering to their opinion
that a bridge will be needed., they realise that circumstances haverecently so entirely altered that there is little phance of moneybeing available to construct-this bridge for at least ten years0In the circumstances they feel that the acquisition of property to secure a line might prove uneconomical9 and they have withdrawntheir recommendations relative to the definition of a line and itssafeguarding.   The Committee suggest that the subject might bere-opened when national and local conditions are more favourableand when the effect upon traffic movement of the new bridgeconstruction and other road improvements now in hand has been ascertained,,      4-o  &apos; I am informed by Mr. Morrison that he and the majorityof the London County Council are not convinced of the need forconstructing such a bridge.   There has always been a substantial volume of opinion in favour of a new bridge at Charing Crosssbut each particular scheme proposed has produced great opposition,,      Do   The need for an early decision on the future policy inregard to Charing Cross Bridge ands in particular., as to whetheror not a route should be safeguarded;, is now pressing.,, as I havebeen ashed recently by a deputation from the London County Council?headed by Mr. Morrison., to approve the&apos; Council &apos;s proposals for thedevelopment of the area south of the River between the County Halland Waterloo Bridge,,   This scheme (for which the Council intend to seek powers in the coming Session) includes an improvedapproach to the new Waterloo Bridgev but does not provide either for the construction of a Charing Cross Bridge or for the necessaryapproach to such a bridge0      6.   MrB Morrison asked for my decision -          (a)  As to the grant to be made from the Road Fund towards                the cost ( 449?000) of the proposed road works  and          (b)  That the proposal  for a bridge at Charing Cross should                now be  stated to  be abandoned;,  or  at  least  postponed                iridefinitely9  arid that  the  development  which has  been
                           - j -          held up in the past pending          bridge should mm proceed unhampered by the          considerations the bridge would necessarily involve,,     7.  . I have examined the proposed scheme for the developmentof the South Bank and am satisfied that it is eminently desirablenot only on traffic grounds but also as providing a much neededimprovement to a part of central London which has long been aneyesore.          It has been agreed by the Treasury that the        will attract a grant from the Road Fund at the rate of 60 per cent,The question now is whether it is to be prejudiced and renderedunnecessarily costly by my approval being made subject toprovision being included for an approach to a new bridge atCharing Cross?     8B   The uncertainity during the past ten years about thefuture of Charing Cross Bridge has prevented much desirablereconstruction and development in the areas concerned.   I considit undesirable that this state&apos;of uncertainty should continue any longer unless there is a probability of the b ridge scheme beinginitiated within a measurable period.     9*   The estimates of  the cost of a Charing Cross Bridge vaI am advised, however, that the cost of a new bridge and of itsconnections with Long Acre,  Cranbourne Street and Waterloo Roadwould be in the vicinity of  -13,000,000*   The improvement of the approaches as far as Euston Road in the north and Elephant andCastle in the south would, of course, add materially to the cost.    10.   In my opinion It would be difficult to justify theexpenditure of so much money on this particular scheme, to the prejudice of other schemes which could be carried out with greateadvantage.          I do not consider that the construction of a new bridgeat Charing Cross can be regarded as a practicable propositionwithin a measurable period, and I feel unable t o justify thecontinued sterilisation of property,
E.L.B.Uth November, 1936.11.  I seek, therefore, authority:-        To inform the London County Council     that, as It is clear that in existing     circumstances the scheme for a Charing     Cross Bridge is not likely to be practicable-     within a measurable period,  the Government     do not propose to ask the London County     Council to hamper their scheme for the     development and improvement  of the area on     the South Bank.by requiring, as a condition     of a grant from the Road Fund, that there     should be provided a line of approach to     a new bridge at Charing Coras.

</content>
</cab>
