<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/280/0 images: 35-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fth November,  1938.JLLJLILIL2! *                                                00PY NO.__ifyj ,,P.252(38)                  0 A B IKE T.                          FUEL  ALLOTMENTS.       Memorandum by the Minister of /iff r i culture^a^d^Fist^erj-es^  -      1.   A Bill amending the law relating  to Commons is long overdue,      but pressure of more important Parliamentary business has so far      prevented its introduction as a Government measure.      2.   The Attorney General, has, however, raised a particular matter      affecting fuel allotments, i.e. land set out under Inclosure ACTS      with the object of supplying fuel for  poor persons.      3.   It is believed that,  in a number  of cases,  the  land cannot      now be conveniently dealt with by the  trustees,  as there are at      present restrictive statutory provisions which prevent the      trustees being authorised to sell,  or  let the land.      4.   AT the meeting of the Cabinet held on 2nd. November, 1938,      it was decided (Cabinet 52 (38) Conclusion 5) to adopt the      recommendation of the Home Affairs Committee, at its meeting      held on the 26th October,  1938, that a Bill dealing  with fuel      allotments would be suitable for introduction by a Private Member.      AS the ballot for private  Members&apos;  Bills takes place this week,      the matter is of some urgency,  and I have therefore  ventured to     &apos;assume that my colleagues  will  agree to the preparation of a Bill      dealing with this particular matter and to  its being entrusted      to a private Member for introduction.      5.  The Bill will provide a greater degree of elasticity in      dealing with these fuel allotments,  having  regard, to present day      conditions, and would authorise the Charity C,ommissionerS to      approve the sale,  or lease.   AS the Commissioners could be      trusted to ensure that the interests of all concerned would  be -      adequately safeguarded,  the  Bill should not be controversial.                                                    W.S.M.

</content>
</cab>
