<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/194/0 images: 10-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
13 DOCULiENT IS TEE PROPERTY OF HIS 3RITAIRIIJ MAJESgYJS GOTOMIjT) .C A3 I II E T. RELATIONS gBTTgEIT TTZ NAVY AIID THE AIR FORCE.The undermentioned Committee of Imperial Defence papers are circulated, by direction of the Prime Minister, in order that they may be taken note of by the CabinetLTote by the Lord Privy Seal fC.I.D. Paper No*S67-B).Extract from the draft Minutes of the 254ch Meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence.C R E T..Po 1C2 (28).(Sgi. ) LLP. A. HATTZEYSecretary to the Cabinet.r., &quot;Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I. April 3rd. 1928.COPY M
4 ^i u[This Document is Hie Property of His Britannic xMajesty&apos;s Government.&apos;] Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   March 1928.SECRET. Copy No. 29COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the DRAFT Minutes of the 234th Meeting, held on March 29. 192*.* * * * * j*(8.) RELATIONS BETWEEN THE NAVY AND AIR FORCE.(C.I.D. Paper No. 867-B.) (Previous Reference: C.I.D. Minutes of the 191st Meeting. Minute 8.)LORD SALISBURY drew attention to the number of instances in connection with the development of the Fleet Air Arm in which the Admiralty and Air Ministry had founcl it necessary to submit differences for adjudication by the Prime Minister. After making an Award in the last of these differences of opinion, he had felt, as one of the original members of the inquiry set up in 1923 to consider the points of difference between these two Departments, that he should place on record the intentions of the Cabinet and the Committee of Imperial Defence at the time of the original settlement in regard to the outlook which should govern the co-operation between these two Departments. It was only by the Admiralty \s and Air Ministry&apos;s acceptance of the form in which appeal should lie that continual applications to the Prime Minister for decisions on points of difference could be avoided.He had, by leave of the Prime Minister, brought this paper forward with the desire that it should receive the approval and authority of the Committee of Imperial Defence and the Cabinet, as he felt the acceptance of the spirit contained therein was the surest means of checking the continual demands by these Departments for arbitration.Conclusion.The Committee of Imperial Defence took note with approval of C.I.D. Paper No. S67-B.******2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, March 29, 1928.[17456a]
This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   March 1928.SECRET. Copy No.867-B.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.RELATIONS BETWEEN THE NAVY AND THE AIR FORCE. (Precious C.I.D. Papers Nos. 463-B, 503-B and 534-B.)Note by the Loud Privy Seal.THE attachment under the authority of the Admiralty of Naval officers to the Fleet Air Arm, which, however, is part of the Royal Air Force, necessarily presents certain difficulties. In order that all concerned should do their best to smoothe away these difficulties, it is important that they should clearly realise on what principle it is intended that these relations should rest.There are two views. The Fleet Air Arm may be considered a part of the equipment of the Fleet, hardly differing from any other specialised branch, such as Gunnery, or Torpedoes or Submarines. In this view the regulations would follow as near as possible those belonging to these other branches. The Arm would be equipped with crews which, for war purposes, would give the utmost confidence to naval commanding officers, on the assumption that they might be engaged upon active service to-morrow. All questions of continued training, of building up a reserve, of development on the technical side, would be subordinate to the full naval atmosphere which naval experts consider necessary to produce the best results in battle. For purposes in time of peace the arrangements would be such as suit the professional tradition and convenience of naval officers attached to the Air Service and of naval authorities who command them. In short, to all intents and purposes, in fact if not in name, the Fleet Air Arm would be absorbed in the Navy. I believe that a view somewhat on those lines is held by a great many sailors.The other view is that the Fleet Air Arm ought to be in the spirit as well as in the letter a part of the Roj^al Air Force. In this view, whatever naval colour it may be thought right to give to the Arm and whatever steps may be taken to secure the predominance of the naval element in its personnel, the Arm must in no sense be cut loose from its direct connection with the parent Air Service, and must not lose the advantage of the rapid development both in machines and in tactical skill which is the life-blood of a service in a condition of almost headlong evolutionary change and which the Navy only learn at second-hand.I believe that it was a conviction something like this last view which inspired the Balfour Report and the decision of successive Governments that there should be only one Air Service. When the evolution to which I have referred has reached a point of comparative stability it is of course possible that the first view will gradually replace the second, and that, ultimately, the Fleet Air Arm may be cut loose from the remainder of the Air Service and become in all respects a special branch of the Fleet like any other. But until that time comes during the years of freedom from a great war which are probably before us the second view is the only one by which we can secure that the evolution of the Naval Air Service shall have its full scope.In this order of ideas, on the one side, the Air Ministry must make it as easy as they can for the naval authorities to reconcile the divided interest in the Fleet Air Arm.   But on the other, the Navy must realise that, proficient as it is to the highest point in sea tradition and see sense and sea skill, it is necessarily second [17399]
to the Air Force in air sense and air skill and air development. Probably for many years to come such will be the case, and in this new element of naval equipment the Air Service must be the teachers and the Navy must be the taught; and the Air Service must retain in its hands not merely the building of the machines and the initial training of the pilots, but a sufficient representation in the crews of the machines to enable it to test the results and gain the experience which are necessary lor driving forward progress in air fighting under sea conditions. At the same time, the Navy, by multiplying the number of naval officers who pass through the Fleet Air Arm, may keep continually up to date the new knowledge which the rapid evolution of the Air Service every year brings forth.SALISBURY.March 15, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
