<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/194/0 images: 16-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
j&apos;I his Document is the Property of His Britannic xMajcsty&apos;s Government.]Printed.for the, Cabinet., ,    . ....    ,SECRET. Copy No.   &amp;war . 104 (28).CABINET.AIR OPERATIONS AT ADEN.Note by the Secretary of State for Aik.WITH reference to the short discussion about &quot;Aden at to-day&apos;s meeting of the Cabinet, I think my colleagues may be interested to read the attached minute by the Chief of the Air Staff giving a clear summary of the satisfactory situation which has been brought about by the use of the air arm there, according to the latest telegrams received from the Resident.From the point of view of the Air Ministry, I endorse Sir Hugh TrencharcTs recommendation that we should, in accordance with the Residenfs advice, take immediate advantage of the Imam&apos;s present pacific advances and endeavour to negotiate a satisfactory settlement on the simplest lines with all possible despatch.It is, of course, for the Colonial Office, in consultation with the Foreign Office, to advise on the political aspects of the situation.S. H.Air Ministry, March 28, 1928.Minute uy the Chief of the Am Staff.Secretary of State,1. I desire to place before you the following brief resume of the recent operations at Aden and to call attention to the situation which results from the surrender by the Imam of the two captured Sheikhs.2. I need not remind you that during the past five years the Imam and his followers have been encroaching into certain areas of the Aden Protectorate; and that during that time no active operations have been undertaken by British Forces (with the exception of one action when aircraft went to the assistance of a native tribe who were defending themselves against the Imam) until the Air Ministry took over operational control on the 1st January, 192S.3. On the 9th February, the Resident at Aden reported that the Imam had captured two Sheikhs who were in Treaty relations with us, and on the 20th February the Imam was informed that bombing operations would be carried out against him as a punishment for this outrage. After messages of warning had been dropped, Kataba was bombed on the 21st February, but owing to bad weather intervening air action was suspended between the 24th February and the 11th March, when bombing was recommenced against Kataba, Dhala and Mafalis. On the 7th March a representative of the Imam left Dhamar to suggest a truce, and on the 23rd March the Resident reported that the Imam had agreed to release the captured Sheikhs.4. When it was decided by the Cabinet that the Air Ministry should take over the control of operations in Aden, it was agreed that the land garrison should be reduced. Both before active operations were begun and also whilst they were still in progress part of the garrison the Aden Troop was reduced, and on the 11th March the Indian Infantry Battalion and the Fortress Company of the Royal Engineers left Aden.[17445]
5. The Resident, in telegrams addressed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies on the 13th and 17th February,&apos; communicated and appeared to endorse local apprehensions that the reduction in the land garrison and the withdrawal of the Habil Post would have an adverse effect on the tribes in the neighbourhood of Lahej. It was, however, decided that the reduction of the garrison should continue, and the Air Ministry informed the Resident that the Air Force should prove a more effective protection to the tribes than land forces.0. Such in outline have been the events which have led up to the latest developments which appear highly satisfactory, though it would be premature to assume that the situation has been finally stabilised.My object in sending you this minute is, however, to call attention to the Residents telegram of the 27th March,t urging that we should act quickly if we are to ensure a peaceful solution of our difficulties with the Imam. I whole-heartedly agree with the Residents advice. It is, in my view, of vital importance that the opportunity afforded by the present truce to arrive at a permanent sefetle-ment with the Imam should be accepted and that no effort should be spared to commence conversations with him immediately. If these conversations are unduly protracted, or if there is a loug delay before they commence, the present effect produced by the recent bombing operations will to some extent have worn off and we shall be unable to obtain such satisfactory terms as regards the future limits of the Aden Protectorate as we could obtain now, when the enemy, with the visits of our aircraft freshly impressed on his mind, is in pacific mood and, having learnt what the air arm can do, is apprehensive of what may follow, if air operations are resumed.7. Finally I should like to point out that these operations furnish yet another convincing illustration of the fact that air power achieves its results rather by undermining the morale of the enemy than by the infliction of heavy casualties-that it is, in short, much the most humane instrument at our disposal for dealing with problems such as that which has confronted us at Aden.H. TRENCHARD.Air Staff, March 28, 1928.* Nos. 12(1 and V26.t No 170

</content>
</cab>
