<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/194/0 images: 189-190</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I Tlrs Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1928.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.  29CP. 116 (28).THE I.KAK IX THE REVENUE.Memorandum iiy the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.THE daughters of Danaus, in classical legend, were condemned for ever to the depressing occupation of carrying water in sieves a penalty regarded by antiquity as appropriate to those who with murderous dagger requited the happy and fruitful rites of Hymen. Their modern counter-part, it seems to me, is a Chancellor of the Exchequer condemned, in the name of consistency to a similar youthful indiscretion, to the futile task of providing the gigantic expenditure imposed on us by our Imperial and domestic obligations with the leaky bucket of a worn-out fiscal system.It is a commonplace of fiscal policy that the imposition of an excise duty, unaccompanied by a corresponding customs duty, is bound to result in a progressive shrinkage both of revenue and of production owing to the influx of untnxed imports. The Chancellor of the Exchequer, Colonel Gretton and Lady Aster would all for once agree in regarding as sheer insanity any proposal to drop the import duties on beer and spirits while leaving the excise duties unaltered. The obvious principle here stated applies, however, no less when the excise is the cumulative result of a number of minor impositions charged on production, directly or indirectly, as when it is imposed eo nomine on the article produced. Rates, for instance, constitute a very definite tax on production: not only the rates imposed on the factory as such, but the rates on the working man&apos;s dwelling, which have to be found out of his wages, and the shopkeepers rates, which are added on to the cost of living and so again on to wages. Another direct excise on production is the taxation imposed on employers and employed under the name of insurance contributions. The consumption taxes, and even income tax, in so far as it affects the professional man&apos;s standard of remuneration, are further factors in making up the total excise which British production has to bear. That total excise, which on a very rough calculation I estimate to have been about 3 per cent. and consequently an almost negligible factor when our present fiscal policy was introduced, had risen to about 10 per cent, before the &quot;War, and is now probably not less, on an average, than 2(1 per cent.P7474]
An excise duty of &apos;2() per cent, on British production, with no corre-sponding customs duty on foreign production sold in Great Britain, that  apart from any disparity of wages, hours or exchanges is the primary handicap which British producers and a British Chancellor of the Exchequer have to contend with. Under that handicap the importation from overseas, practically all from foreign countries, of competitive articles, wholly or mainly manufactured, has grown to the unprecendented, almost incredible, figure of  322,500,000 iii 15)27. For the Chancellor of the Exchequer and for the local authorities that figure represents a loss of some  60,450,000 revenue, as compared with the revenue that would have accrued from British production of the same articles a gigantic leak in their bucket. That loss, together with all the cost of the measures of social assistance and relief provided by the Exchequer, the Kates, and the Unemployment Insurance Fund, to help the workers displaced by foreign competition, has to he made good by further rates and taxes, in other words, by a further raising of the excise on liritish production, with its natural consequence of increased foreign competition, still further leakage of revenue and still heavier burdens. There is no exit from this vicious circle except by the simple and obvious device of imposing on foreign inanu-factured imports an equalisation duty, corresponding approximately to the excise on British production. Until this is done British production cannot be said to enjoy free trade, even in its own home market. It is only after it has been done, and duties raised still higher, that any question of protection can be said to enter into the question at all. The question is not to-day one of free trade or protection, but of ordinary financial sanity.My colleagues may be familiar with that simple device, the lobster-pot, and may have marvelled at the curious perversity with which the lobster struggles vainly to get out through the narrow slits in the wicker sides of his prison, without ever thinking of availing himself of the ample orifice by which he entered. There is. I fear, something rather pathetically crustacean in our frantic search for ingenious and complicated devices that will extricate us from our difficulties, such, for instance, as the remission of a small part of the total excise imposed on British production in one form. viz.. factory rates, in order to reimpose it in another, when the simple remedy of imposing some kind of countervailing customs to balance and correct our internal excise is all the time staring us in the face. But I may be wronging the lobster. His reluctance to leave the lobster-pot by the obvious route may be due not to stupidity, but to political consistency or to fear that other lobsters will not follow, and that he may lose authority among them. Whatever the motive the end is the same : he gets boiled and turns red.   Ts Great Britain to share his fate?L. S. A.Dominions Office, Downing Street, April % 1928.

</content>
</cab>
