<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/194/0 images: 350-350</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majcsty&apos;s Government. \Printed for the Cabinet. April 1928.SECRET.C.R-131 (28).Indian Contribution for Home Effective Charges of theBritish Army.MEMORANDUM BY TUE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.The Secretary of State for War has circulated a Memorandum.9 on the subject of the payments required from India in respect of the training in this country of the recruits required for the British garrison of India.I am afraid 1 must at once take exception to the proposals iu para. 4 of the Memorandum. 1 do not at the moment wish to enter into the merits of the questions raised by Sir L. Worthingtou-Evans, but it is obvious that an unfavourable decision by the British Cabinet, either as to the continuance of the charges or their amount if continued, could not fail to lie regarded iu India as an outcome of the composition of the tribunal, representing as it would, with the exception of myself, only one party to the matters in dispute. As matters stand, the Government of India are convinced that the training charges ought to be borne entirely by ilis Majesty s Government ami that, even if it were decided that they ought to be continued, the amount claimed is excessive.Any decisions given iu regard to these traiuiug charges ought clearly to be the outcome of consideration by an impartial tribunal and this tribunal should consider not only the narrower question of the Capitation Rate but the wider one of the fiuaucial relations between His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Government of India.1 have been discussing this subject for more than a year with the Viceroy, and 1 have just received a long reasoned despatch from the Government of India in which, on the broadest grounds, they argue that no capitation payment should be made. I do not propose to trouble the Cabinet with their arguments in detail at present, because, to my mind, the whole aspect of the controversy (which, 1 would remind my colleagues, has been going on since 1859) has been altered by the appointment of the Statutory Commission. For two reasous. First, because the controversy (which is at present dormant, so far as the ludiau public are concerned is one which arouses acute passion among Indian politicians, and the Viceroy has just told me that a revival of it now, taken in conjunction with our recent decision on the Indianisatiou of the Indian Army, would have a very damaging effect on the prospects of the Commission^ enquiry. But there is a second and very weighty reason. The financial relations between His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Covernmeiu of India arc so important a factor in the constitutional and political problem that I think the Commission will be bound to review them generally. These relations -apart from particular agreements-arc generally governed by the Welby Commission Report, which was written 30 years ago. It is to be hoped that the Simon Commission will recommend the appointment of another Welby Commission, which would not ouly make recommendations regarding the financial relationships of the two countries iu the light of present-clay facts ami developments, but would also propose the establishment of some revised machinery for dealing with disputes regardiug the allocation of expenditure which are bound to oceur subsequently between the India Office and the various Departments of His Majesty&apos;s Government.What I wish to propose to my colleagues now is that the question of the Capitatiou Rate should be reserved for consideration by this new Wei by Commission, which, if not set up on the recommendation of the Simon Commission, must, I think, in any case be set up.Meanwhile 1 cannot impress too strongly on the Cabinet the importance of doing nothing to create still further opposition in India while the Commission is in being. I quit0 appreciate the desire of the Secretary of State for War to secure the increase which ue thinks is due. But, after all, no loss to Imperial revenues would be involved by delay, as, in accordance with an undertaking I have already given to him, 1 am willing that any decision reached, whether favourable or unfavourable to India, shall be applied with retrospective effect from 1st April 1920.Ism a Office, BIRKENHEAD,25th April 1928.&quot; CM&apos;. 180 (&apos;28).2718     7J   4.28

</content>
</cab>
