<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/194/0 images: 485-495</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS this  PROPERTY OF lilS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT),secret .&quot;.P.148 (28)oCOFY NO.C A b 1 N E T.AMERICAN PROPOSAL FOR A M3LTILATERAL TREATY FOR THS RENUNCIATION OF W.R.RECORD OF A CONVERSATION 3STWEEN SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN AND THE america AN AMBASSADOR.
Circulated by direction of Sir Austen Chamberlain for the meeting of the Cabinet to morrow morning.ItoEEIGN   Oi^ICB. 3rd May, 1928.
Record of a conversation between Sir Austen Chsonberlain and the American Ambassador, 3rd May 1928.(Despatch to Washington.)Sir,The American Ambassador sought an interview with me this morning; it lasted for an hour and twenty minutes and was of the highest consequence .?ir. Houghton began by reading an extract from a telc-graphic despatch which he had jtist received from Mr. Kellogg. Tn this telegram Mr. Kellogg stated that he had never contemplated a meeting of Foreign Ministers to discuss the American proposal for a multilateral treaty; that he saw no need for such a meeting and no usefulness in it; he did not understand hov Yotir Excellency could have derived the impression that he favoured it.     Mr. Hough-ton went on to say that from other sources the American Government had learned that there was a proposal In the air for a preliminary meeting of jurists and he read a further passage from Mr. Kellogg&apos;s despatch in v/hich the Secretary of State expressed himself with equal force and for the same reasons as entirely opposed to such an idea.     He saw no reason for such discussions; they could have no useful result .I told the Ambassador that I had listened with deep regret to his expression of Mr. Kellogg1s strong disapproval of both these suggestions.   There had evidently been a complete mis-understanding between Mr. Chilton and the Secretary of State. Thesuggestion/
*.7 4suggestion for a meeting of the Foreign ?t?ministers which I thought had emanated from Mr. Kellogg himself had seemed to me a most help-ful and fruitful one.     If it were prepared as the Locarno confer-ence of Ministers had been by a preliminary discussion among the jurists who could exchange inf5rmation and explanations, it v/ould probably greatly simplify and facilitate the task of the Foreign Ministers.     But if this procedure were rejected, what procedure did Mr. Kellogg contemplate?   How were the six Powers to reach agree-ment?   7/ere our Jfotes and despatches to go chasing one another round the world or was each of us to carry on a separate correspondence with Washington?   Surely anything of the kind would greatly increase our difficulties and Impede progress.     Besides there must be some Interchange of views between those who already had treaty obligations to one another, but if their jurists met alone without an American, what suspicions v/ould not their meeting breed?The Ambassador again stated that neither he nor Mr. Kellogg could see the need for any international conference.      o knew that Mr. Kellogg&apos;s view had been much influenced by the knowledge that theGerman/
German Government had been advised by Dr. Gauss that there -was no incompatibility between the American text and their existing obligations .     If Germany had been able to give a quick and unqualified acceptance of the American proposal, why cculd net the ether Powers do the same?   -hat after all was the difficulty?     I should have no doubt observed the speech delivered by Mr. Kellogg cn Saturday last in which he had explained the Intention and meaning of the American proposal. Summarising Mr. Kellogg&apos;s points, Mr. Houghton resumed them as follows: the right of self-defence was inherent in every treaty, it required no special reservation; the Covenant cf the League of Pations does not impose an obligation to go tc war and there is no contradiction between it and the American pro-posal to renounce a war as an instrument of policy.   The United States Government have no desire to injure the Covenant and equally they have no desire to interfere with the Treaties of Locarno, but any Pover which incurred the sanctions of Locarno would in so. doing necessarily have broken the proposed treaty fcr the renunciation of war which would thus, far from we&amp;ken-ing the w0rk accomplished at Locarno, support and buttress it.Mr./
J i 0Mr. Kellogg13 fourth point had boon tho Treaties of neutrality, by which were meant such engagements as united, for example, Prance and Poland.     Mr. Koughton said that he was not aware of the terms of that Treaty, but on my informing him of them he agreed that if, as urged by Mr. Kellogg, there was no contra-diction bet.vcen the American proposal and the Covenant of the League or the Treaties of Locarno, then there would be no contradiction between the American proposal aid the mutual obligations of Poland and Prance, narrowly restricted as they had been to the case of self-defence in the new version initialled at Locarno.Next Mr. Kellogg in the speech in question had mentioned the French observations about the case of a party which, after signing the American proposal, broke its engagement.     Mr. Kellogg had observed that ip30 facto the other Powers to the American Treaty would be released from all obligations towards the Treaty-breaking State.    There remained only the question of universality, and Mr. Kellogg held that, whilst most Powers would probably be ready to sign such an agreement, it would be an act of the highest significance for the maintenance ox peace even if it were oon-fined to the United States and the five great Powers immediately addressed.The Ambassador then developed his &quot;personal&quot; ideas upon this point.   He said Mr. Kellogg1s speech had met with the highest acceptance and approval in the United States.     The acceptance by Germany of the American invitation had been warmly welcomed;   any appearance of a check from another quarter, anyappearanae/
appearance of rcluotan.ee to make a solemn renunciation of the idea of settling differences by war and of finding some other means for their solution would have the most deplorable results, whilst on the other hand the broad acceptance of that groat prinoiple would throw into the shade all sorts of disturbing questions - belligerent rights or what not - and would, in his opinion, give a new safeguard to the present statizs quo in Europe and a new security that, if existing frontiers were ever to be changed, it must be by other means than war and would have a profound and lasting effect upon the maintenance of peace,   Mr. Houghton spoke with great earnestness both as to the danger to Anglo-American relations which v/ould arise from any appearance of reluctance on our part and as to the lasting advantages not only to ova- relations but to Europe of a hearty and unqualified acceptance of it.    Tviico, with particular reference to the effect on future American policy, he repeated that if I could see my way to sign the two articles of the American TreatjT in the form and in the spirit in which they were offered, the man who had done so v/ould still be considered., generations hence, as one of the great benefactors of the world.I replied to the Ambassador that. I trusted that my speech lait Thursday in Birmingham and my declaration in the House of Commons had shown clearly to him and to the United States Government that my own Government earnestly desired to go to meet the American proposal with the largest measure of sjnnpathy and acceptanoe.   tphe Ambassador might think that I wasundtily/
unduly under the imprescion of my experiences at Geneva; perh&amp;ps I was, hut it had been my not uncommon fate there to be confronted with large, generous propositions or engagements proposed, and sometimes accepted, by men, who if you examined those proposals quietly with them, admitted that they either did not mean what they said or that they were incapable of execution.     I was, I repeated, most anxious to take full advantage of tho proposal which had come from LIr. Kellogg, but I wanted to&apos; be sure that, if we signed the Treaty, we all meant the same thing and that we should not be exposed to subsequent accusations of bad faith because years afterwards we discovered that v/e had used language with different meanings.     Above all did I feel the necessity of caution in this respect as between ourselves and the United States of America, for Mr. Houghton knew as well as I did what charges of ill-faith had been spread against us in the United States in respect of the Washington Treaty of naval Disarmament, even though the United States Secretary of the ITavy had borne testimony to our loya?. observance of otir obligations.Here, I said, I must recur again to the Monroe Doctrine for, as I had before remarked to him, we too had our Monroe Doctrine in regard to Egypt and perhaps some other areas. Only yesterday in our Dote to the Egyptian Government we had reaffirmed oxxr Declaration of 1922.     If 3 wore at this momentproposing/
proposing to the House of Commons the immediate acceptance of the United Spates declaration, I should at once be asked whether that acceptance affected our declaration that we would not tolerate forcible interference by foreign Powers in Egypt.     When I had mentioned this subject to Mr. Houghton the other day, he had deprecated the p\.putting of such questions, but he had replied that for himself he would consider that the American proposal left our respective Monroe Doctrines unaffected, and that it must be assumed that a Power which renounced war would not deliberately provoke war by taking action which it knew must result in war.     Was that an answer, I enquired, which I might give in the House of Commons? Would it be acceptable to Mr. Kellogg?Mr. Houghton replied that that was his personal view. Everybody knew what would happen if the Monroe Doctrine were attacked, but nobody did attack it or desire to attack it any more than anyone desired to attack our position in Egypt. He could not see that either were menaced by anyone or were affected by the terras of Mr. Kellogg3s proposed Treaty.    I replied that if I could be assured of this it went a long way to remove my difficulties, though I could not say offhand that it neoessarily removed them all.Again/
Again Mr. Houghton pressed the larger aspects of the question. Again he spoke both of the vast possibilities which a plain and sweeping declaration such as Mr. Kellogg proposed would have and cf the grave consequences which might follow the failure of this effort for peace, and once again he deprecated most earnestly a conference of jurists or Ministers in which we should put to cne another questions to ascertain exactly ho?/ far we could go in the direction of war instead cf broadly announcing our determina-tion to settle our differences by other means.I told the Ambassador that I was very glad to have had this conversation with him, as, misled by the supposed willingness and even desire of Mr. Kellogg to have a conference of Ministers, I had been proceeding on different lines and I must now report to my colleagues at the earliest possible moment what he had said and consider the question afresh in the light of it.I was inclined to agree with Mr. Kellogg that the right of self-defence was inherent and that no special reservation of it was necessary.     The Covenant and the Treaty of Locarno were our principal international obligations and if, as Mr. Kellogg had explained, there was nothing inconsistent with them in the signa-ture of his proposed treaty, but that on the contrary the signature of that treaty would reinforce them, that covered our principal preoccupation which was that, in endeavouring to effect an additlon-al guarantee of the peace of the world, we should not destroy or impair the measure of security which we had already achieved in Europe.     v;ith the neutrality treaties I had already dealt.     In regard to the release of the signatories from any obligation to a power/
0Q1O 0 xPawer which resorted to war, Mr. Kellogg&apos;s speech seemed to have met the French point of view and though I thought that some States outside the six great Powers ought to be associated with the Treaty from the first, I had no doubt that those States would be willing and indeed anxious to join and I did not think that universality ought to be a condition of our signature.   Mr. Houghton had referred to what he spoke of as &quot;the unqualified&quot; acceptance of Germany, Mr. Houghton remarked the word \as Mr. Kellogg&apos;s.    I said that I had observed that Mr. Kellogg had used it and had been a little surprised.    I felt that it was an exaggeration.     I had Indeed been a little anxious at the first rumour that Germany was going to give an &quot;unqualified&quot; acceptance and had asked Dr. StreseC-mann to ,^ive me an opportunity for an interchange of views before the German Note was sent, as Germany and we had mutual obligations and I was very anxious that no difference should arise between us. &quot;hen my communication reached Dr. Stresemann, matters had already advanced so far that he was unable to comply, but I had been much reassured when I read the text of the German Note, for in that Note Dr. Stresemann had observed that Germany had certain pre-existing ob-ligations which she must observe, that these in her case were only the Covenant and the Treaties of Locarno and that she saw no contra-diet ion between the American draft and those obligations, and that ^erefore she was ready to discuss the  American draft at any moment. Thic  vas after all very much my owu position; provided we clearly under-st^otf what we meant and all meant the  same thing my purpose would be ach&apos;:-ed,    I did not refer to the further qualifications introduced into the last paragraph of the German ITote .A. c.

</content>
</cab>
