<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/30/16 images: 160-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1942.SECRET. Copy-No.W.P. (42) 486 (Revise).October 29, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.VISIT OF THE MINISTER OF PRODUCTION TO AMERICA.Note Prepared by the Minister of Production, as Amended and Approvedby the War Cabinet.*I recently proposed to my colleagues (W.P. (42) 424) that we should approach the United States Administration in order to reach an agreement providingfor long-range assignment of finished munitions. Increased supplies wouldhave greatly eased our man-power difficulties; guaranteed supplies would atleast provide a firm basis upon which to determine the allocation of our lastreserves of man-power between the forces and the factories.2. The need for this approach has become much more urgent because theUnited States Administration is now taking decisions which will determine theUnited States production programmes in 1943. The existing programmes are known to be substantially in excess of production possibilities and they are beingscaled down, in many cases drastically. Great pressure is being put upon usto share these reductions with the United States forces, and unilateral decisionsmay be taken at any moment. It is clearly necessary for us to make the strongestrepresentations to ensure the inclusion of our minimum needs in the revisedUnited States programmes.3. In my forthcoming visit to Washington, I propose to concentrate&quot; uponthree topics : (a) The integration of the British aircraft programme with that of theUnited States, with the special aim of improving quality.(b) The increase of the American shipbuilding and shipping programmes.(c) The guarantee of the minimum supplies of items of major importance which we need.(c) is a necessary preliminary to the decisions on man-power which we mustshortly take; I propose to inform the President and his chief advisers of thenature of those decisions, and of their relation to supplies that can be assuredto us from the United States.The United States Aircraft Programme.4. The President has apparently decided to fix a production objective of82,000 tactical aircraft for 1943. This represents a revision of the Presidentsobjective of 100,000 tactical aircraft laid down in January 1942 and confirmedten days ago. This new development brings the United States programme nearer to practical possibility. The programme can probably be achieved in actualnumbers, but not in high-quality aircraft. It.is still of the greatest importance that the programme should be examined from the point of view of the sacrifice of quality for quantity which it apparently involves. There is a further point ofinterest to us.   We should try to encourage the United States to lay increased* W.M. (42) 147th Conclusions, Minute 1.[245371
emphasis on bomber production of a suitable type, as these can fly the atlantic and certainly come into action, whereas though larger numbers of fighters canbe produced, many of these will not be shipable during 1943. Moreover, it is notin fighters that our shortage is the most serious. It is likewise important toensure that the programme allows for the preparation of United States bombers to enable them to participate in night bombing, the provision and assignment tous of adequate supplies of up-to-date aircraft for the Fleet Air Arm, and oftransport aircraft. It is furthermore necessary that capacity should be leftavailable for the all-important work of bringing in new types without disturbingoutput; examination of this aspect will lead to a combined study of Anglo-American future programmes.5. I propose to suggest the following specific modifications of the programmes :  (i) Fortress and Liberator should be at once modified to make them suitablefor night bombing.(ii) Capacity should be made available in the United Kingdom for theassembly of 400 Mustangs a month to be fitted with Merlin 61 engines.This would cause a reduction of from 25 to 30 Albemarles a month inour own programme. This loss should be compensated by deliveries ofUnited States heavy bombers to us.(iii) A switch in the United Kingdom production programme from Stirlings,Halifaxes and perhaps Wellingtons to Lancasters during 1943 isunder examination. Should this be decided upon, the resulting lossof output, which will not begin before mid-1943 and the extent ofwhich has not yet been determined, should be compensated bydeliveries of United States heavy bombers. The whole transaction is subject to the Prime Ministers directive that our bomb carrying capacity should increase on a steadily rising curve throughout 1943.(iv) For certain other theatres the Mustang could be fitted with the Allisonengine, leaving the remaining Merlin output from the Packard plantin the United States for other United Kingdom types.(v) Packard engine capacity should be increased to 2,000 monthly, and production should be changed over from Merlin 28 to Merlin 68.The United States Merchant Shipbuilding and Shipping Programmes.6. I understand that the President intends to raise the present UnitedStates merchant shipbuilding programme from 16,000,000 deadweight tons in1943 to 18,000,000. This will presumably supersede the recent recommendation by the Combined Chiefs of Staff to cut by 11 per cent, the allocation of steel platefor merchant shipbuilding during the last four months of 1942 a recommencla-tion which would lose seme eighty ships in 1943.7. This expansion of programmes is still insufficient to enable UnitedStates shipbuilding capacity to be used fully throughout 1943. I propose topress strongly for the further expansion of the programme to a minimum of20,000,000 deadweight tons in 1943. Our idea is that even 22 millions wouldbe a reasonable and most desirable target. The steel for any increase in the shipbuilding programme should be found at the expense of the American Armysteel allocation, which is three times as large as, and far in excess of, what theAmerican military effort outside the United States can employ in. 1943.8. The question of substituting escort vessels for merchant ships lies, inthe midst of this problem. To accept a loss of 6 or 7 hundred thousand tons amonth of ships with their invaluable cargoes as a basis for Anglo-American war effort would be a most melancholy conclusion. A ship which survives a year isworth two ordered to be built. A diminution in the losses at sea is far more valuable even than the increased volume of new construction.9. Our own shipping position is deteriorating seriously. The latest estimates of food and raw material imports show that for the half-yeardestocking must inevitably go much further than was approved by the lord presidents Committee last February. In the first half of 1943 in the absenceof further assistance from the United States our total imports are likely tobe only 9 to 9-Jr million tons, and consequently our import of raw materialswill be about 1-1 million tons below absolute minimum requirements, even if food imports are allowed to fall to a dangerously low level and estimated imports of
munitions into the United Kingdom are put at a low figure. This must mean that whatever steps we take, steel supplies will at best fall a million tons (about17 per cent,) below our requirements and our war production will be interfered with correspondingly. We can only be. sure of maintaining our war productionif we are able to obtain the use of a substantial amount of American non-tanker tonnage next year. The Prime Minister, in his memorandum dated the21st July, 1942 (W.P. (42) 311), wrote as follows :-&quot; We must be careful not- to let our position deteriorate to anunmanageable degree before we have a clear understanding with the UnitedStates as to the future. With this object we must now in the next few weekscome to a solemn compact, almost a treaty, with the United States aboutthe share of their new building we are to get in 1943 and 1944. Up till the time when the United States entered the war we had pretty well recoupedourselves for our losses by acquiring control of the shipping of continentalStates as they were successively subjugated by the enemy. No morewindfalls can be expected from this source. We can only expand our ownbuilding sensibly at dire expense to our war effort. Nothing we can do canchange our material import requirement appreciably. The tonnage needed to guarantee this must be a first charge. . . . The minimum stocks neededmust not be written down unduly. Serious bombing of our ports might wellham-string our intake for considerable periods, when we should be lostwithout something in the larder. Moreover, we should not start on the basis that the British should make a greater sacrifice of their pre-war standardof living than the American people.&quot;I propose, therefore, to ask for the transfer to this country of 2^ milliondeadweight tons, to be sustained throughout 1943. American assistance willalso be needed on a much greater scale than in the past for the supply of finished munitions from North America to overseas theatres of war. Assistance to theextent of about one million tons in tanker tonnage will also be required, though in view of the good treatment we are receiving in the tanker sphere, it may be best to make no special approach on this point.10. With the approval of the Cabinet, I propose to ask the President for adefinite undertaking that assistance will be given to the necessary extent.11. The pressure upon United States resources is such that our programmes in United States are heavily under fire. We are asked by Sir Robert Sinclairto scrutinise our demands afresh and to make some contribution which will ease the strain on other production programmes.12. The implications of this are serious. The Man-Power Survey shows thatif the expansion programmes of the Air Force and. the Navy are to be carriedout in full, the man-power requirements of the three Services between July 1942and December 1943, plus the corresponding growth in the munitions industries,amount to 2^ million men and women. The available supply, after taking accountof further measures which are before the Lord Presidents Committee, will still leave a deficit of, say, 750,000 persons by the end of 1943. This figure represents the absolute minimum deficit, based on administrative calculations of the furtherpossible intake, and taking into account that there may be some reductions in the requirement figures. No precise figure of the gap that must be filled by curtail-ment of British programmes can be given until the War Cabinet has examined the labour situation as a whole, and decided, among other things, what furthersacrifices are expedient in &quot;less essential &quot; industries. If the requirementsstand at 2^ million men and women, the &quot; gap &quot; may be anything up to 1^ million.When this has been done, there are no further measures which can be taken toincrease the degree of mobilisation.13.   The remaining gap could be bridged if (a) It were possible to replace some of our own output by further recourse to the production of United States and so make it possible to releasesubstantial numbers to the Services from the munitions industries.If this is not done then either (b) Our Services must wait longer to complete their equipment, or(c) We must reduce the scales of one or more of them.14.   In view of events in the United States it may well prove impoliticto pursue the first possibility.   This can only be judged on the spot, and I ask my colleagues to give me discretion to act as I find best.   If we are forced tocome to a decision to refrain from increasing our demands upon United States,[24537] - b 2
except for aircraft and for special types of equipment, the War Cabinet will then have to decide which of the other two courses must be followed.15. We can and should do something to meet the wishes of Washington andoffer some reductions from the present schedule of our requirements in cases wheredemands are out of balance, contain an excessive element of insurance, or havebeen calculated on over-liberal estimates of expenditure. Our Americanprogramme should be subjected to the same pruning process as we are applying to our general programmes; we should only ask the United States for require-ments which can be fully justified on operational grounds. The Departments arereviewing their requirements in United States on this basis.16. We must, however, be able to count on what remains. I propose to makeit clear in Washington that we must be assured that our limited demands will beas fully met as is humanly possible. Without firm commitments it will not bepossible to allocate our man-power to the best advantage. Taken as a globaltotal, our requirements are not a very great part say 10 per cent. of America&apos;swhole programme. Nor do they in general represent a very large part of the overall equipment of the British armed forces. But the significant fact is thatin a number of key items they are vitally important.17. I have set out in the Annex the proportion of our supplies for whichwe rely upon the United States.  The following shows some of the chief items : Per cent.Synthetic rubber ...      ...      ...      ......      ...      10040-ton tank transporters and 10-ton lorries   ...       ...      100Self-propelled artillery   ...       ...       ...      ...     nearly 100Transport aircraft ...       ...       ...      ...      nearly 100Landing  craft   (combined  requirements  in- Britishtheatres)        ...       ...       ...       ...      ...       ...        88Auxiliary aircraft carriers       ...       ...      ...       ....        85Escort vessels       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       77Light bombers and G.R. land planes   ...      .......        68Tanks        .....................        60Tank engines and track (for U.K. tank production) ... 40-50Fleet Air Arm aircraft* ..!       ...       ...       ...       ...        40Alloy steel..................      ...       34Carbon steel ...       ...       ...       ...      ...       ...        2818. These examples from the long catalogue of war supplies illustratethat the equipment of the Empire&apos;s forces in all three elements is a joint Anglo-American operation; that we laid our plans on the assumption of substantialsupplies from the United States, that American equipment is needed to balance the equipment which we produce, and that failure to receive these supplies wouldcompletely disorganise the arrangements which we have made. The bulk of our forces are already deployed and the completion of their equipment depends uponUnited States supplies of key items. It would be a deplorable waste of resourcesif the impact upon the enemy were delayed or reduced for lack of the suppliesupon which we counted when we made our plans. I shall impress upon theUnited States Administration the vital importance of the time of delivery; our requirements are in many cases for the early part of 1943, and will not continueinto the winter of 1943-44, so that ample supplies would be available for thedemands of the growing United States Army, if they could be postponed into 1944.19. Within this general framework, in addition to the air programme(including Fleet Air Arm) and the merchant shipbuilding and shipping pro-grammes, I propose to concentrate upon securing an assurance for the items inwhich we are most heavily dependent in 1943, of which the following are important examples : Escort vessels,Auxiliary aircraft-carriers,Tanks,Heavy trucks,Locomotives,20-mm. weapons, andRubber.* The supply of aircraft from the United States for. the Fleet Air Arm is 3,600 in arrears andthe Admiralty hope to secure increased requirements in the future.
20. What I am out to get is the inclusion of our minimum requirements in the United States programme on a basis of full equality with items of comparable strategic importance required by their own Services. I also hope thatthese requirements will be assured by long-term assignments as a recognition thatthere is a combined responsibility for the maintenance of the British war effort.I do not propose to ask for a protocol, but I aim to secure its equivalent.O. L.Ministry of Production,Great George Street, S.W. 1,October 29, 1942.
ANNEXBritish Dependence upon United States.(Per cent, shows proportion of British net requirements i.e., gross requirementsless stock which cannot be met from British Empire production.)I. Navy Capital ships, aircraft carriers,cruisers, destroyers, sub-marinesEscort vessels ...Aircraft escort vessels...Minesweepers  ...Moored and magnetic ...Other minor naval craftNaval armament and ammu-nitionOerlikon guns  ...Oerlikon ammunition ...Landing Force ships   ...Landing craft  ...Motor-boat enginesPer cent,dependence.Not applicable77       188       \Fleet 49     Iij56G4Slight,*99*88*98Notes.Requirements by no means covered, but nosupplies undertaken by United States.Proportion of requisitions in United states to total orders not allowing for casualties;deficiency only partly covered. Does not take account of expanded UnitedKingdom programme.Based on relation of requisitioning inUnited States to British building pro-sramme.British gun production to end-1943 will cover purely naval requirements, by then,but requirements are pressing and urgent,and need to be met considerably beforethe end of 1943.Rely upon United States for 60 per cent, ofNavy&apos;s requirements; if Army require-ments also are taken into account,&quot;dependence is 80 per cent. (See 20-mm.weapons for Army, below).Percentage of gross requirements to March1944 for combined Anglo-Americanoperations in British theatres to be met from United States production.For landing craft, motor gun-boats, motortorpedo-boats, motor launches, &amp;c,mainly for combined Anglo-Americanoperations.II. Aircraft Heavy and medium bombers...Light bombers and G.R. landplanesFighters ...Flying boatsTransports       ...       ...Carrier-based aircraft ...20-mm. aircraft cannon20-mm. H.S. ammunitionAircraft engines for UnitedKingdom production of operational aircraftBombs, H.E..........Bombs, incendiary   ....Radio equipment268761nearly 10040241230405Proportion of accruals to R.A.F. for period july 1942 to April 1943 of United Statesmanufacture, as in Arnold-Towers-Slessor agreement.Percentage required from United states for period July 1942 to April 1944. Re-quirements from United States arebeing increased.British requirements for United Kingdomaircraft production filled from UnitedKingdom production; R.A.F. has sub-stantial requirement for H.S. guns forground use.R.A.F. requirement only (see 20-mm.weapons for Army below)&apos;.Substantial other requirements of aircraftcomponents for United Kingdom aircraft production.250-lbs to 4,000-lbs.* These landing cr,aft are for use by United States as well as United Kingdom troops.
Per cent.dependence. note.III. Army (Provisional : subject to revision on basis of new requirement calculation and new production forecast.)Field, medium, heavy artillery, Slight Dependence of possibly 25 per cent, for heavy A.A. guns, anti-tank 6-pdr. A.T. guns,   and   ammunition toguns and ammunition match them.20-mm. A.A. weapons ...       ... ... Army is almost entirely dependent uponUnited States for meeting its require-ments of these weapons, M.A.P. production-tion of Hispano being only enough forR.A.F., and Navy production of Oerlikononly enough for Navy till Autumn 1943,allowing for United States assignments.Ammunition would be required entirely from United States, for United kingdom production of H.S. and Oerlikon ammu-nition not enough for RAF. and Navyneeds. Total dependence for 20-mm.weapons (all Services) is 50 per cent.;for ammunition 72 per cent.Dependence greater than this in next nine months; ammunition required from united States to match United States-produced guns. * .Bofors &quot;unsMachine   guns   and   infantryweaponsSmall armsSmall arms ammunitionTanks (including armament andammunition)S.P. artillery    .........40-ton tank transporters10-ton trucks6-ton trucksLight and medium trucksEngineer,   transportation   andsignal stores.Components for United King-dom A.F.V. production:tracktransmissionsenginesExplosives: T.N.T.......IY. ttaw Materials Carbon steelAlloy steelCopper  ...AluminiumMagnesiumRefined TungstenRefined MolybdenumRefined TantalumSynthetic rubber32Slight.5860nearlv 100100   .10050SlightConsiderable50224422Per cent,dependence,year to June30, 1943.28 )34 f18950505010040 per cent, of -303 rifle net requirements;100 per cent,   of  Thomson  guns and-30-in. rifles.Almost   wholly  dependent   upon   UnitedStates for -30-in., -45-in., -50-in.;  somedependence for -303-in.,&apos;and 9-mm. ball.British requirements largely covered by canada and United Kingdom; consider-able Dominion requirements in UnitedStates; entirely dependent upon UnitedStates for jeeps.Varies very widely between certain items,. for which dependence is negligible, andothers for which it is 100 per cent.Very approximate figures; tank programmebeing revised.Also heavy prospective dependence uponUnited States development of R.D.X.These figures represent the proportions ofour consumption which is not covered by united Kingdom production; to the ex-tent that we draw from stock, the actualdependence upon United States is less.Calendar year 1943.Wire and rod for radio valves for M.A.P.Britain will be entirely dependent uponUnited States for synthetic rubber sup-plies when these come forward in thesecond half of 1943.V. Machine Tools20Especially special type and critical tools.




</content>
</cab>
