<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/63/52 images: 568-571</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIO MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET.W.P. (45) 197.20th March, 1945.WAR CABINET.FUTURE DEFENCE POLICY IN THE SUEZ CANAL AREA.Report of the Suez Canal Committee.IN accordance with the terms of reference remitted to us by the War Cabinet,we have been investigating the various factors bearing upon the long-term policy to be adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Government on the future of the Suez Canal. we find it necessary to ask for a measure of political guidance from the War Cabineton certain points before we can proceed to finish our task.2. It is unnecessary in this Report to set out the full background to ourstudy. This was contained in a Memorandum submitted to the War Cabinet bythe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on the 7th September, 1944(W.P. (44) 507). Broadly speaking, there are two sides to the problem of thefuture of the Suez Canal. The first is the general method of administration which we should seek to secure. The second is defence. The two sides are relatedin that arrangements for the administration must be such as to secure to thedefence authority for the Canal the powers which it requires.3. The Committee first considered the future administration of the Canal.Various alternative suggestions were put forward in the Foreign Secretary&apos;sMemorandum. The issue was finally narrowed down before the Committee to two alternative courses of action, namely (a) That we should now work towards the conversion of the present canal company into a Public Utility Service under the control of the United Nations,on the general ground that an undertaking of this magnitude and internationalimportance ought no longer to continue to be in the hands of a profit-makingconcern. It would be necessary to secure French and Egyptian agreement to thispolicy, and this might involve financial compensation both to the shareholders ofthe Canal Company and to the Egyptian Government, which under existing arrangements is due to receive complete possession of the Canal in 1988. Thescheme for international administration of the Canal would provide for united nations supervision, and for the carrying out of the actual administration by asmall efficient and expert body representative of the maritime users of the Canal.(b) That we should not seek to change the existing arrangements for theadministration of the Canal, at any rate until much nearer the date when the concession lapses, but that we should concentrate as our immediate aim onsecuring satisfactory arrangements for the defence of the Canal. The arguments in favour of this course of action, which is supported by the Chancellor of theExchequer, are partly political and partly financial. It is suggested that inter-national management would be bad management; that the United States and russia, and possibly others, would desire to have a voice in the control; that thesuggestion for a change would cause offence to French prestige; and that theUnited States would fear that some similar proposal would be put forward forthe control of the Panama Canal. The financial argument is that compensation would be fixed at what may prove to have been the crest of the wave of theCompany&apos;s prosperity, and that the financial burden resulting from this compen-sation would mean that all hope of any reduction in the level of dues would haveto be abandoned for 60 years. A bargain made now would therefore be likely tobe a desperately bad bargain.4.   Before making any recommendation on the above courses of action,the Committee felt it necessary to examine the other side of the problem, namelydefence.   We were immediately brought up against the validity or otherwise of[29524]Copy No.
the British, objectives as stated by the Foreign Secretary in his Memorandum, asfollows :  &quot; (a) that responsibility for the defence of the Canal should be vested inHis Majesty&apos;s Government in perpetuity;&quot; (b) that the Canal dues should be fixed at the lowest rate compatible withefficient administration with a reasonable return to the shareholders,including the Treasury;&quot; (c) that the Canal should be so administered as to facilitate the exercise ofHis Majesty&apos;s Governments defence responsibilities.&quot;5. The crux of the matter is the validity of the first objective. This has sofar been stated bv the Foreign Office as an axiom. It is strongly supported bythe defence authorities in the Middle East and by the Chiefs of Staff and is fullyaccepted by some members of the Committee. Others, however, feel considerabledoubts about this objective. They feel that there is much to be said, not only for international control of the Canal, but also for international responsibility forits defence, as being more in harmony with the aims which His Majesty&apos;sGovernment are trying to realise in the new World Organisation. the considerations advanced in favour of this view can be summarised as follows : (a) It is desirable on general grounds that an undertaking of such importanceto the world at large should be under international control, and not under thecontrol of a single country, such as Egypt, or of a profit-making company.(b) If this is admitted, then the burden of defence should also be sharedamong the nations. The time has gone when Great Britain could afford to police the seas of . the world for the benefit of others. The United States and russia are composed of large compact land masses, and this geographicalfact tends to cause them to limit their commitments to the immediate vicinity of their territory. We, on the other hand&quot;, have an Empire which straggles acrossthe world, and which involves us in heavy commitments in many directions.There is a tendency on all sides to leave us to carry the burden of security overlarge areas of the world, which burden falls very largely on British taxpayersand on British man-power. This is a state of affairs which should not be allowedto persist, as otherwise our resources will be strained beyond the breaking-point.(c) The defence of the Suez Canal cannot be viewed separately from thegeneral defence problem of the Eastern Mediterranean and Middle East. Arewe alone to be responsible for keeping the peace throughout this area? would it not be to our advantage that other nations, and particularly the UnitedStates, should share in the problems of security and defence in this part ofthe world? It may be argued that it would not be in our interests to associateRussia in the control of the Suez Canal, and in the maintenance of its security.It is not certain, however, that the Russians would necessarily wish at any ratein present circumstances to take an active share in these matters, especially if russia gets satisfaction over the revision of the Montreux Convention.(d) The advantages of international assistance in the burden of maintainingsecurity in the Middle East could be combined with a larger British share inthe administration of the Canal. As the principal user of the Canal, and as the senior partner in the security of the area as a whole, we should be entitled tosuch a share.(e) It would be much easier to get the French and the Egyptians to acquiesce in new arrangements for the administration of the Canal if its control and securitywere declared to be the concern of the United Nations, than if we attempted toestablish the predominance of Great Britain alone.6. In view of the above considerations, the Committee felt it necessary to ask the War Cabinet to instruct them whether or not in. their further examination ofthis matter they should proceed on the assumptions (1) that responsibility for the defence of the Canal should be vested in HisMajesty&apos;s Government in perpetuity; and.(2) that His Majesty\s Government for political and. strategic reasons regard it as desirable that Great Britain should play the predominant part inthe defence and political control of the Middle Fast.(Signed) C. R. ATTLEE iChairman)(On behalf of the Committee).20th March, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
