<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/26 images: 286-293</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1943.The circulation of this paper^has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of most SECRET. Copy No.O OW.P. (43) 326.20th July, 1943.WAR CABINET.MAN-POWER.Memorandum by the Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security.AS desired, I have considered what further reductions can be made in theCivil Defence Services to help to meet the deficiency in man-power which isexercising the mind of the Government.2. These Services have been drastically pruned on previous occasions. It is perhaps not sufficiently realised what reductions have already taken place.At their peak periods the whole-time strength of Civil Defence consisted of Civil Defence General Services      ...       ...       ...      181,100N.F.S.............^     .........      136,200Police-Regulars and Auxiliaries  ...       ...       ...      103,900421,200On the 1st July, 1942, the whole-time strength was : Civil Defence General Services      ...       ...       ... 146,400N.F.S....................... 136,200Police Regulars and Auxiliaries     ......       ... 101,100383,700On the 30th May last the numbers had fallen as follows :  Civil Defence General Services      ...       ...       ...       108,700N.F.S................ ...      125,000Police Regulars and Auxiliaries  ...       ...       ...        92,000325,700By the end of this year I am pledged to reduce the Services to Civil Defence General Services     ...       ...       ...       102,300N.F.S.   ...       .........      -.........       122,200Police Regulars and Auxiliaries ...       ...       ...        84,100308,6003. Moreover, in order to meet the request of the Minister of Labour and national Service not to interfere with production by adding to industrial fatigue,I have, for the last few months, severely restricted my demands of part-timepersonnel to replace whole-time members of the Civil Defence Services released to industry or the forces.[25786]
4. Recent raiding in coastal towns has shown that the Services are no morethan sufficient to cope with their responsibilities for a moderate scale of attack.It is still possible from time to time for the enemy to bomb us, and I have to beready for raids any night (and in some places day), anywhere; and the characterof incendiary bombing makes this type of attack increasingly difficult to dealwith. Under certain novel conditions, too, a severe strain may be thrown on allthe Civil Defence Services, especially in London and certain coastal towns.5. In order indirectly to relieve the strain on man-power, I have tried toprovide that, while standing by, the Civil Defence Services shall, so far aspossible, undertake essential work for outside industry or for local authorities.6. I view with serious misgivings any further reductions in the whole-timestrength of the Services.7. Notwithstanding the sacrifices which the Civil Defence Services havealready made and the risk that further reductions may lead to avoidable disastersin particular areas, I feel that the Civil Defence Services, like other vital services,must, even though risks are involved, make a contribution to meet the deficiency in man-power. The Minister of Health and the Secretary of State for Scotlandare responsible for certain civil defence services, and I have not had an oppor-tunity of discussing with them the extent to which the services for which theyare responsible will share in the further cuts which I now propose. As the contribution on this occasion is mainly for the benefit of industry, and not forthe Armed Forces, we need no longer pay such close attention to the age of the individuals whose release may be offered. On the other hand, as the services asa whole have already been so substantially reduced, it is clearly necessary thatthose services in which bodily vigour and staying power are needed should bethe last to be affected by the further sacrifice. It is scarcely less important that the Fire Service Control Rooms, in which the great majority of the personnel are necessarily young women, should not suffer reductions which will result in serious disorganisation; similar considerations apply to women employedin the police service. In general, no further regular Police should be * allowedto go, nor should.police auxiliaries under 35 years of age. Only the CD. RescueServices in the General Services employ fit men of military age, and it would bevery unwise to weaken them to any appreciable extent.8. Subject to these considerations, I am prepared for my part to agree thatthe Civil Defence Services as a whole shall lose before the end of the year a further15,000 men and women, which will bring the total whole-time strength at the endof the year down to 2^3,600 as compared with the peak figure of 421,200. Detailsof this further cut for each service will have to be worked out with the Ministerof Labour and National Service in the light of service requirements on the onehand and, on the other, of current industrial needs. I attach great importance tomen or women not being discharged from the Civil Defence Services untilindustrial vacancies await them.9. I must further stipulate that the reductions shall be made, so far aspossible, from the less vulnerable areas.10. It will be understood that I may have to ask the Minister of Labour and national Service to provide additional part-time personnel to replace the whole-time personnel released to industry.11. As indicated, this further cut in the Civil Defence Services involvesrisks the responsibility for which my colleagues will, I&apos; know, share with theMinister of Health, the Secretary of State for Scotland, and myself.H. M.Home Office, S. W. 1,20*A July, 1943.







</content>
</cab>
