<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/192/0 images: 149-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fTHI-S TjOCUiXElI&apos;? IS THE P50PEKTY OF HIS  BHIJAKHIO MAJESTY1 S government) . SECRET-. .                                                          Copy Ho Q-P. 16 128).              .                                                                    *                            o A ,3 i   g T .         THE POSITION AT fSSHSVA IN i&amp;SAPD gt) SECURITY  AND         NOTE OP COJlVErsATIQi? SST.VSEN  .I-.03D CUSIlLnrjCT ASK)                        THE PfSUCTi A\t3AS?ADQ^         (Circulated  cy direction of the Secretary of                      State for Foreign Affairs).
&apos;.fhfe Poemncnt is  the Property of His Britannic  1;majesty&apos;s  Government.119LEAGUE OF NATIONS.January 24,  1928.CONFIDENTIAL.SECTION 1.j W.645/28/98]No.  1.        Memorandum communicated by Lord Cushendun, January 24, 1928.     I SAW the French  Ambassador at  his request yesterday afternoon, and  we discussed various aspects of the position  at  Geneva in regard to security ami disarmament for an hour and a half.     After referring to the present deadlock on disarmament, I told M. de Fleuriau how M, Boncour in December had said that if the deadlock continued it might be necessary to adjourn to a later date the resumption of the technical discussions on disarmament fixed  for the loth March.   I  asked whether the French Government would take the initiative of proposing an  adjournment.  In view of the imminence of their general election, it seemed to me very reasonable to argue that negotiations of the  importance and delicacy contemplated should be handled by  a fresh rather than  by an  expiring  Chamber.  M. de Fleuriau said positively  that the  French Government, just for electoral reasons, could not possibly take this initiative.   He explained  that  at  the forthcoming election the country  would revert  to  an old electoral system; on  account of this it was extremely difficult to forecast  the result, and old party divisions already showed  signs of the breaking up.  The present Government would therefore on no  account take  any initiative  which might  be distorted for electoral  purposes.    The discussion then  passed  to security, and I emphasised  how futile  it was for M. Boncour at Geneva  to harp perpetually on  the protocol  of 1924, suggesting always that it was our refusal to accept it which was preventing the  solution of the security problem.  I said that if M. Boncour, as I half suspected,  harboured the hope  that if a Labour Government were returned in this country they would sign the protocol, I  was perfectly convinced that he was wrong, and mentioned that Lord  Haldanc.  Mr. Snowden and Colonel  Wedgwood,  to name only a few, had already declared themselves against it, to say nothing of the fact that Mr. MacDonald himself had  abstained from signing it.   I added that it had  always seemed to me surprising that the French themselves should espouse it so warmly.   M. de Fleuriau declared himself personally no admirer of the  protocol, though he thought it had acquired sentimental prestige among rather  uneducated people.  He proceeded  to a digression on article 16 of the  Covenant, charging successive British Governments in particular, and the League of Nations generally, of having never had the courage to repudiate the words at the end  of the first paragraph obliging member States in case of war to prevent all intercourse not merely between their own nationals, but those of any other State, whether a member of the League or not, and nationals of the aggressor.    I brought the discussion back to the Locarno treaties and referred to some words used by M.  Briand  to Sir A. Chamberlain in December, in which he spoke of the possibility of providing security in the. east of Europe by an adaptation of Locarno to Russia and her neighbours,  and  1 asked  whether we might expect the French Government  to produce any concrete proposals in  that sense; the  recent FYench- Yugoslav Treaty did not seem  to meet  the  case.   M. de  Fleuriau replied  rather warmly that it  was not easy to adapt Locarno  to the east of Europe; the Locarno agreements were based on a historic and disastrous fact, and  the determination  to overcome it the blood-stained battlefields of Flanders, the Rhineland and Alsace- Lorraine and he argued that there was no such concrete historic fact in Poland  orthe Balkans, and  that, therefore, it was  no easy matter to find the subject  or theformula of guarantee.  I  replied that, though that might be so, M.  Briand had nodoubt considered the differences  when he spoke to Sir A. Chamberlain, and it wouldbe very helpful to know more definitely what he had  in mind.  1 went  on to say thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government viewed  with  dislike  a  general form of agreement whichimposed on them definite obligations to undefined nations; it would be easier for them to make a bilateral treaty after full consideration of their particular  relations withthe other party to it.  I added that, for this reason 1 quite appreciated that M. Briandmight wish to sign a treaty with the United  States,  but would by no means necessarilywish to extend it in the same terms to a number of other Powers.[347 aa-1]
Treasury, January 20, 1928.CUSHENDUN,  --------tuen raised the question of the military and naval deadlock in disarmament,rem.juumg M. de Fleuriau of our former conversation,  in which he had spoken of universal  compulsory  service  as  an  essential part  of democratic  France.   1appreciated his point of view, but this did not alter the fact that it was diametricallyopposed to our own and that of Germany and Russia, and did, in point of fact, pre-clude any real disarmament by land.   M. de Fleuriau claimed  warmly, and rathersurprisingly, that France to-day had no army not, at least, one comparable to ourown highly trained force.   He again contrasted the merits of compulsory militaryservice which meant that a voter who supported war involved thereby either himselfor  his family  directly with a  voluntary army a weapon  liable  to be  usedirresponsibly by the somewhat irresponsible democracies which characterised post-war Europe.  He made it quite clear,  as I anticipated,  that his Government couldnot be moved from the position of refusing to limit in any way their military trainedreserves.    After saying that this was not more than I had expected, I told M. de Fleuriauthat we felt at least as strongly that,  as regards naval armaments, there must berigid limitation by  classes, including two for  cruisers and  submarines.  After  all,surprise was admittedly an all-important element in war;  if we were to eliminatewar, let us rule out the factor of surprise by as rigid a limitation as possible. I under-stood that the main preoccupation of the French in naval matters was with Italy,and I could not see how the British proposals for rigid limitation would in any wayaffect French security  adversely vis-a-vis  Italy.  M. de Fleuriau,  after the usualremarks about the French being very behindhand in naval construction, said that hequite appreciated that we intended to  maintain our position as regards  limitationby classes; he was going to Paris almost immediately; there he. would report his con-versation,  and hoped to be able to bring back proposals when lie returned next week.

</content>
</cab>
