<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/192/0 images: 155-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
     This Document is the Properly of His Britannic Majcsty&apos;s Government.                                                                        122                    Printed for the Cabinet.   January 192S.SECRET.                                                   Copy No.   30CP. 18 (28).                                CABINET.THE CHINESE BOXER INDEMNITY.               NOTE BY THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER.    THE accompanying Memorandum which has been prepared in the treasury on the subject of the Boxer Indemnity has my full agreement.                                                                W. S. C.    Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,        January 27. 1928.                       THE CHINESE BOXER INDEMNITY.    1.  The British share of the Boxer Indemnity was fixed at a capital sum of 7,593,081, of which  1,131,000 represented private  claims and the remainder thereimbursement of British  naval and military expenses connected with the  Boxerrevolt.    2.  From  1901  to 1917 we received in all  5,576,089 ( 656,704 principal and 4,919,385  interest), out of  which  all the private  claims were  paid  off.   WhenChina joined the war in  1917 payment was suspended for five years, but  was resumed in 1922.    3.  In 1922  the British  Government agreed to devote the proceeds  of theBritish  share of the Boxer Indemnity to purposes mutually beneficial to  Chinaand Great Britain, and so  informed  the Chinese Government.  In recommendingthis proposal to  the Treasury the Foreign Office represented that &quot;the politicaland commercial  advantages  which  would be derived  by this  country from an allocation of Indemnity  Funds to the education of  Chinese on British  lines  ....would no doubt be of a substantial and far-reaching character.&quot;    4.  The payments which  have,(,made since 1922 at the rate of about  400,000a year have accordingly been made to  a  separate  fund, the Chinese IndemnityFund, under the authority of the China Indemnity (Application) Act,  1925, andthis fund  now amounts  to about  2,000,000.  The Government have announcedthat, subject to Parliamentary approval, they are willing to adopt in principle ascheme for entrusting the control and administration of the fund  to a joint Boardof Trustees in China.    5.  Meanwhile,  the  anarchy prevailing in  China has, on the one hand, made it impossible to carry out any such  educational schemes and, on the othor  hand,has involved tho British Exohequer in  additional  expenditure owing to  thodespatch of the China Defence Force, which will amount to about  4  million upto the 31st March next and a further  S00.000 annually until the China Defence      [16949]
Force is reduced or brought home, when there will  be a further heavy charge for transport.    6.  The  argument for recouping  this additional expenditure out of  thebalance on the China Indemnity Fund cannot be better put than in the words ofSir M. Lampson : &quot; It is, on the face  of it, absurd and even wrong voluntarily toreturn to the Chinese a huge sum,  in itself a reimbursement of former actualBritish expenditure, more or less in the nature  of a free gift to the Chinese at theexpense of the British taxpayer.&quot;    7.  The objection  raised is  that we should place ourselves in the wrong bygoing back upon pledges given to the  Chinese Government and reversing a policy announced to Parliament.   It must, however, be pointed out that the proposal to allocate the Fund to purposes for the  mutual benefit of Great Britain  and china was  not  in any way in  the  nature of a contractual  engagement.   It wasa spontaneous and unilateral offer made because we  considered that the changeof circumstances since 1901 made a change of policy on our part desirable.  Thechange of circumstances between 1922 and 1927 is, however, even greater than thechange of circumstances between 1901 and 1922.  It is obviously impossible whilethe present anarchy in China continues  to use  the  money  for  educationalpurposes, and even  if it  were  possible such action  would not, at the presentmoment, have tho  substantial  and far-reaching advantages  of a political and commercial character which were claimed for it in 1922.  So far, therefore, as theChinese are concerned, the  Government are under no  obligation, having  made  nocontract, and are just as much at liberty to change their minds now as they  werefive years ago.  On the other  hand, the Government as  trustee  for the British tax payer cannot justify diverting  the money from the Exchequer and  presentingit  to  the  Chinese unless they can claim that such diversion secures advantagessufficient  to  compensate for the additional taxation  involved, and under presentcircumstances this claim cannot be sustained.    The mere fact that an action  is  likely to  prove  unpopular in  China cannotitself   be  advanced  as a  final  argument  against  taking such action, and the disadvantage of  any  temporary  unpopularity must  be weighed against  theadvantage of obtaining t&apos;2 millions for the Exchequer, which is of a very concreteand convincing character.    8.  The claim will no  doubt be put forward in various quarters that if themoney is diverted  from its  present  destination it  ought  to be used to  pay compensation to British  Nationals who have suffered losses  during the presentdisturbances.  It would, however, be a most  dangerous principle for the british exchequer to accept  liability  for losses  caused by foreign Governments,  theresponsibility for which must rest with those Governments.  No compensation hasbeen provided for the far greater losses which have been suffered by British nationals in Russia.  Moreover, we have a very strong answer in this case.  We have resistedevery suggestion that the cost of  the Chinese Defence Force, which is maintained forthe protection of British property in Shanghai, should be borne, even in part, by theowners of that  property.   By bearing  the cost of these troops the taxpayer hasalready made a  very burdensome  contribution to the protection  of  the private property of the British community in China, and the proposed diversion of theBoxer Indemnity Fund will only grant a partial alleviation of his burden.    9.  Even  if it  were admitted that  our spontaneous  offer  to the ChineseGovernment constituted an irrevocable pledge, it could fairly  be argued  that ourpromise can only be held to mean that the Fund will  be allocated  to  educational and similar purposes  as  soon  as  tho situation in  China admits of  reasonableschemes being put into operation and  properly  administered.  At  present this ismanifestly impossible, and  for  this reason our  offer  cannot at present be carried into effect.    10.  A further  argument mentioned in the Foreign Office  telegram of  the23rd May is that a change of  policy would mean taking compensation for theaction of  a relatively  small faction  in the  middle of civil war  out of Fundspromised  to  China  as a whole. It is impossible, however, to draw this kind ofdistinction between the Chinese Government (or rather the  various  conflictingGovernments) and  the Chinese people.   Moreover,  the anti-foreign feeling in
 China seems now to be so widespread that it is more than ever difficult to treat the Chinese people as innocent and their various Governments as guilty.    11.  It is also  contended that,  the existence of a  large sum  ready and waiting for useful expenditure  ought to be a great argument with  the  Chinese in favour of  friendship and co-operation with us.   The same concrete argument would, however,  exist if it were  made clear that the current payments to  the Chinese&quot;Indemnity  Fund at  the  rate of I&apos;400,000 a  year  would again  be held available for educational  expenditure so soon as the present anarchy comes to an end and the China Defence Force can be withdrawn.    12.  On ihe above grounds there would  be ample  justification  for paying over to the Exchequer theWhole of the . 2 million now lying unused and  the  further payments of  -100,000 a year, so long as tho China Defence Force has to be retained. When the  China Defence  Force can be withdrawn, tho position would be exactly the same as if it  had been  possible  to inaugurate  these educational schemes in 1922.   There would be resources at the rate of X&apos;100,000 a year available, which was the position  then contemplated;  all that the Chinese would  have lost would be the amounts accrued during the  years in which  their own action  had  made itj impossible  to proceed with the educational schemes contemplated.    13.  In order to carry out any such  operation, it will be necessary to obtain legislation  amending tho Act  of  1925.   If it were  decided  simply to  take  theexisting Fund into the  Exchequer it could  be done by a single clause  in the next Finance  Bill, providing that, notwithstanding any provision  of the  Act of 1925,the sum at present held in the  China  Indemnity Fund  should be  transferredforthwith to the Exchequer,  as a part contribution to the expenditure incurred onthe China  Defence Force.   If  it were  decided to  go  further  and to appropriatefuture payments, the procedure to be adopted would require further consideration,but it could  probably be done by extending the clause suggested above so as toprovide in  addition  that the  future payments to the Fund  shall be similarlytransferred   to  the  Exchequer as  they accrue&apos;   until  Parliament  otherwisedetermines.

</content>
</cab>
