<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/192/0 images: 279-298</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the  Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]                    Printed far the Cabinet.  February ID2.S.SECRET.                                                            ^  I    CP. 34 (28).      MEMORANDUM  BY  THE  SECRETARY  OF STATE  FOR IXDJA.   I circulate a note dealing with  the principal points in our relations with Afghanistanwhich are likely to form the subject of conversations with the King of Afghanistanor his Ministers during his impending visit.   Appended to the note are four telegrams from and to the  Government of  India ;particular attention  is drawn to  that addressed  to the Government of India on  the2nd February, in regard to the  question of the possible request by Afghanistan for a cash subsidy.   INDIA OI KICK,8th February 1U28.BIRK EX HEAD.
SECRET.Relations with  Afghanistan.   The geographical position  of Afghanistan and lite present state of international relations  in  Asia make the maintenance and  development of friendly  relations with  that country  animportant aim of British policy.   It is very desirable, therefore,lo. do  everything that is possible on  the  occasion  of  KingAinanulla&apos;s  visit to  this  country to impress on him  both  thereality and  the value of  British friendship, and to  take anyopportunities that offer to develop friendly relations in a generalway.   So  far  as any requirements  of our own are concerned,wc  need  not  wish  to develop  the  political side of  the  visitbeyond general impressions.   Wc have no particular  desire tomodify the existing  treaty relations with Afghanistan, and none of the  matters of political  detail at present outstanding betweenthe  British  Government  and   Afghanistan are  of  sufficient importance  to  he worth  raising here.  But  the Afghan pointof view  is different.  It  seems  certain that  they will  expectsomething more than general  impressions, aud highly probablethat the mood in which  they leave this country will depend not so much on the general treatment that they receive  here as  onthe amount of satisfaction that  it is possible to give them  inregard to particular  political and material requirements.  there seems  little doubt, therefore, that, whether we desire it or not,political conversations of some  importance and deliuiteness willbe inevitable during the King&apos;s visit.   Sir Francis Mumphrys summed up his view of the position ina recent despatch (1th December 1927):     &quot;The principal  object of the tour is described by  the  Kinghimself as  a  personal  introduction to the  forms of Westerngovernment,  education  and  scientific  progress.  Apart  fromthese  considerations, however,  it cannot  be doubted  that  theKing&apos;s intention is  to stimulate England  and Russia in  theirrivalry to court his  friendship    It seems  a foregone conclusionthat he  will  attempt by conversations in  Condon to  initiatenegotiations for a new Anglo-Afghan  Treaty, and will attemptto obtain  the promise of British  assistance towards those objectswhich  he considers  most essential for the material  progress ofhis country.  ...  If  it  be  assumed that the tour will  becompleted successfully and that King Amanulla will be  able to consolidate his authority on his return to Afghanistan, it is  uponthe success or failure of  the conversations in London that  thefuture of  Anglo-Afghan  relations will to a large extent depend.If the  King returns  to Kabul with a larger cheque from Moscowthan he had  been able to obtain from  England, the trend ofAfghan policy is likely, for some years at any rate, to be towardsthe North rather than the South.&quot;    The assumption  of rivalry between England  and Russia asthe basis  of Afghan policy is of  course a commonplace, anil inthe present state of international relations  an assumption  ofantagonism between England and Russia will inevitably underlieany political conversations, even if  they are not explicitly basedon  it.    It  is important in this connexion to bear in  mind the historyof Anglo-Afghan relations between  11)19  ami 1921, and of  thenegotiations of  1921 that led up  to tho conclusion of  the existingtreaty.    The  treaty of peace made;  at  Rawalpindi in August  1919,which cancelled the  AnuYs subsidy and left. Afghanistan  (in  thewords of Sir Hamilton Grant&apos;s letter supplementing the treaty)&quot; officially free and  independent,&quot; put the Afghan Governmenton its good behaviour for six months.  The Amir was informed     2551   100 2,&apos;JS                                       A
that the  fust  consideration by which the British  Governmentwould be influenced in deciding whether to readmit him to theirfriendship would be his conduct of his foreign  relations, and thathis sincerity would  best  be proved by the dismissal  from  histerritory of all hostile foreigners, in particular  Bolshevik missions and Bolshevik agents.    Although  the conduct of the Afghan Government in  the interval did not give satisfaction, negotiations were resumed atMussoorie in April 1020.   The Mussoorie Conference terminatedin July 1020 with the presentation to the Afghan delegates of an aide wemoire outlining the terms of a treaty of friendship andthe conditions on which  it might be concluded.  There was noexplicit reference to  Russia, but the conditions  included anundertaking by the  Afghan Government to prevent to the best of their ability &quot;all action within  the boundaries of Afghanistan   .  .  .   by subjects of  other nations which may tend  to stirup strife  or produce  enmity against  the  British government within  the boundaries of India,&quot;  and &quot;the passage throughAfghan  territory to  the   British  frontier  ...  of personsraising agitation against the British Government.&quot;  The treatyof  friendship foreshadowed was,  while leaving Afghanistanentirely  independent  both in internal and  external  affairs, toprovide for assistance and concessions from the British Govern-ment in various directions, including a yearly subvention ofIS lakhs of rupees ( 120,000.   The subsidy previously receivedby Afghanistan, which had  been  increased from time to time,amounted  in  11)19  to  Rs. 20i lakhs ( 137,000) a year.  Underthe agreements with Afghanistan in  force up to 1919, the BritishGovernment of  course also controlled Afghan foreign  relations,and  in  return  gave a  guarantee of assistance in  repellingunprovoked aggression.)    Meanwhile  negotiations  had  been  proceeding  betweenAfghanistan and Russia,  both  at Kabul  and at Moscow.   (AnAfghan  Mission, under  Wali  Muhammad Khan,  who is  nowacting us  Regent in  Afghanistan during the  King&apos;s absence,visited Moscow in 1010, and Bolshevik emissaries arrived in Kabulin  tho autumn of that year.) A  preliminary agreement had beensketched out at  an early stage in  these negotiations, under  whichAfghanistan  was lo  undertake   to  facilitate the  despatch ofBolshevist  arms,  emissaries and  propaganda  to  the  Indianfrontier  tribes   ami  India.   The  Russo-Afghan  negotiationssuffered vicissitudes,  hut a provisional draft treaty was  agreedupon at  Kabul and  sent to Moscow  in October 1020.   This fact,naturally, greatly influenced the discussions that began at aboutthe same time on Afghan proposals for the resumption of British-Afghan  negotiations for  a treaty of friendship.  The  Amir was asked to supply details of the treaty  with Russia (a request whichhe ignored), and when His Majesty&apos;s  Government in December 1020 authorised the Government  of ludia&apos;s proposal  to despatch a Mission to Kabul it was with misgivings and without departing from the view that  no treat)7 oi friendship could  he concluded with Afghanistan if it ultimately  appeared  that the Afghans had committed themselves definitely to  a treaty with the  Bolsheviks including obviously anti-British provisions. The Viceroy informed tho Amir that the conclusion of a treaty would be conditional on his refusing  to allow the establishment in tho regions adjoining the Indo-Afghan frontier of Russian  Consulates, the  sole object of which was known to be to foster anti-British agitation.    The British Mission, under Sir Henry Dobhs, was at  Kabul from  January  to December 1021.   The same  period saw  the definite conclusion  of an Afghan treaty with Russia, which was signed at  Moscow on the  2Sth February and ratified at  Kabul on tho  4th  August.   The published version  of  this  treaty promised  the Afghans, among  other  things, a yearly subsidy of
 oue  million roubles in coin or bullion ;  it is  believed that an unpublished addendum promised  rides, aeroplanes, anti-aircraft guns  and a powder factory.   The  negotiations for a British- Afghan treaty  passed through many phases and were marked by violent  fluctuations.   For  present  purposes  it  will,  perhaps, suffice to notice,only some outstanding points.   From  the  outset the British proposals on the one hand insisted  on the exclusion of Russian Consulates from Eastern Afghanistan  and on  the other  promised  tho Amir  an  annual  subsidy (the figure of 18 lakhs mentioned  in the Mussorie  aide  mcmoire had risen by April  to 20o lakhs plus an initial payment of oG lakhs).   A  new phase, in which competition  between  Britain and Russia became more than ever the dominant note, was introduced in April by a request  from  the Amir  that  the British  Government  would guarantee help in arms and money  in  the  event of a  Russian attack being brought about  by  an Afghan refusal to ratify the Russo-Afghan treaty.   This  phase culminated in June with the acceptance of  an Afghan proposal  that  Afghanistan  should bring about a complete rupture  of relations with Russia (on the pretext of her treatment of Bokhara and  Khiva) in return for an annual subsidy of 40 lakhs of rupees ( 267,000), an immediate gift  of 20,000  rifles, 200 machine  guns, 12  mountain guns  and two  18-pounder   batteries,   with  adequate supplies of aimuu- nition, a gift of six  aeroplanes after six  months, material for the construction of a telegraph lino  from Kabul via Kandahar to Herat, and a promise of further assistance in money, munitions ami  aeroplanes,  to  the extent  deemed necessary by   the  two Governments after  consultation,  in   the  event oT  unprovoked Russian aggression.  These proposals for a so-called &quot;exclusive&quot; treaty,  however,  eventually  fell through after sonic  delays  and difficulties over minor  points, and it may be  doubled whether, on the Afghan side, they were ever in reality anything more than an attempt  to  find out how high  lite British Government could be induced to  bid.  Afghan policy then took a new  turn; the Russo-Afghan treaty was  ratified ;  and  alter the  Afghans had put forward  a treaty somewhat  on  the lines of the  original draft, including a subsidy of 20A  lakhs, what appeared  to be a complete  impasse  was  solved at the  last  moment by a proposal from   the  British side  that, as  the  Afghan refusal  lo  disclose completely the  contents of their  treaty with Russia had prevented the further discussion of a treaty on  the basis of  specially closefriendship, a treaty  providing for ordinary neighbourly relations should be  negotiated instead.  Eventually, after repeated  offers from the Amir  to repudiate the treaty just concluded with Russiaand to  revert to   the &quot;exclusive&quot; treaty  had  been rejected asimpossible, and  negotiations appeared  to have broken  downcompletely, the existing treaty, which has always been  described as one  of &quot; neighbourliness&quot; rather than  &quot;friendship,&quot;  was signed on the 22nd November 1021.   The Afghans   no doubt  recognise that circumstances  have changed very greatly since 1021  ;  but it cannot be a  matter forsurprise,  in  view of the  facts  set out above, if they open  anyconversations here by  endeavouring  to  recapture something ofthe atmosphere of the 1021 negotiations, with its promise ofshowers of money and   material  benefits.  It may bo  mentioned that towards the  end of those negotiations the Amir was  givenassurances, first, that if in future he should wish to free  himself from his  engagements  with  Russia,  anil should thereby  bringon himself unprovoked  Russian aggression, he  could  count on British support;  and,  subsequently, that if he  persisted in  hispurpose (as then declared) of getting  clear  of Russian  ontangle-ments  he would find that the  British Minister would certainlybo prepared to discuss  matters further on  his arrival at  Kabul.No discussion on those  lines has  in fact  been entered upon with
Sir Francis  Hunipkrys;  but  when  a crisis  arose  betweenAfghanistan  and Russia  over Urta  Tagai  (-January 1020)  the afghans at once asked whether His Majesty&apos;s Government wouldbe prepared to help Afghanistan in the event of war.   The peaceful settlement of the Urta Tagai incident  made it possible to avoid any direct answer to  the Afghan enquiry, andit  was  unnecessary even  to  give them a limited promise ofdiplomat it; support,  to which  His Majesty&apos;3 Government werewith some hesitation prepared lo agree  (though it is understood from Sir Francis Humphrys that the Afghan Government in  factattributed the Russian acceptance  of the settlement to diplomaticpressure  which they  imagined  the British Government  had brought  to  bear, and were  correspondingly grateful  until itoccurred  to  them  that if there were any question of a  quid  proquo  for Russia  it  woidd be for  them, and  not for the BritishGovernment, to  provide it).  Bur  it is possible that tho Afghanswill now again raise the general question whether His Majesty&apos;sGovernment  are prepared to enter into agreements with them ontho basis of  defensive  (or even offensive) common action withthem against Russia, or at least  to give them some  promise of support, against unprovoked Russian aggression.   Any suggestion of co-operation in any sort of offensive against russia should now presumably be ruled out at  once; and it is recognised  that,  even  the  most  guarded   hint  of defensiveco-operation   involves  the  danger  of encouraging   Afghanarrogance against  Russia, possibly to the point of precipitatinghostilities that might otherwise   be  avoided.  It is  a  questionwhether  it is desirable  to go any  further  than the  formulatentatively suggested by  the Committee of Imperial  defence sub-Committee for public use: &quot;That Britain could never regardwith  indifference the interference by  a foreign Power in  theexisting territory of a friendly Afghanistan, but  that the exactsteps which ought, in  that event, to be taken must depend uponthe circumstances of the moment.&quot;   Replies  on these  lines would dispose  of  any question ofco-operation  in direct action, military or political, against Russia.But the question still remains whether,  or to wdiat. extent, Russiaand  her anti-British aims are lo  be  admitted as matters to betaken  into account  in  discussions or treaties with Afghanistan.In its overt form, the question is  whether we should attempt toinclude  in  the  treaty or arrangements with  Afghanistan  anyparticular measures  explicitly directed to the protection of Britishinterests  against Russia;  in  tho  background, and not for opendiscussion, though it  affects all our relations with Afghanistan,is the question  how far  we must take Russia into  account, in another way, by lending  ourselves to Afghan plans for puttingtheir favours tip to auction.    It is very difficult-or  indeed  impossible to avoid  the latter process  altogether,  while Afghan friendship   is a matter of importance to us and Russia  continues  to bid on the other side. Jt  is  accepted  as  a  principle that we will not enter into an auction with Russia, and the  Afghans have  on  occasion been so informed.  But so long as it is common knowledge that. Russian threats are  prominent among the  pre-occupations of British policy  it  cannot be expected that the Afghans will abandon hope of exploiting the situation. Their own interests, it is  true,  may in our view  demand as clearly as British interests do  that  they should keep Russia at arm&apos;s length ; and  probably some  such consideration of self-interest may be counted upon to add a good deal to our side of  the balance in the last  resort.  But it is not at all certain that, the Afghans see their true interests as wo see them, and  it would be too much to expect that an enlightened perception of those interests would always turn tho scale against determined  Russian efforts,   if, therefore, it is important as it
admittedly  is to  secure  Afghan friendship, some element  ofbidding against  Russia, however  we  may  disguise  it, seemsunavoidable.  Sir F. Humphrys, as  has  already  been seen, goesso far as to.say that the trend of Afghan policy for some years is likely to be determined by the  relative size of the chequesobtained from London and Moscow during the present tour.    Whether we  should allow  the Afghans to derive  furtherbargaining  power  from Russia  by ourselves putting  forward proposals for the  inclusion  in our arrangements with the Afghansof specific measures  of protection against the &quot; Soviet menace &quot;is a matter for our own choice.  It is  suggested  that we shouldnot.   The only such measure  that  was in the end included inthe treaty arrangements of 1021 was  an undertaking by  the afghans that they would not &quot; give the opportunity of establishing a Consul-General or Consul  or  representatives  of the  RussianGovernment at the  positions and territories of Jelalabad, Ghazniand Kandahar which arc contiguous to  the  frontiers of India.&quot;This figures in a letter appended to  the  treat)-, as tho  quid proquo for  the grant  of  customs concessions in respect  of goods imported into  Afghanistan  through  India.   Opinions havediffered  as  to the.  practical value of  this provision; but it  is agreed that  if it is retained one result is to make  it  very  difficult,if not impossible, to  secure the appointment of  British Consulsin Northern Afghanistan.  There  is great force  in the view that whatever danger there is  to  India from  Russia arises  muchmore  from  the possibilities  of  Russian  intrigue  in NorthernAfghanistan, where there are at present no  Biitish reprosonta-tives,  than  from  anything that  is  to  be feared  from  thoestablishment of Russian representatives in Eastern Afghanistan,where British  Consulates  are already established.  This viewhas been adopted by the Defence of India  Sub-Committee of the-Committee of Imperial Defence in the  following passage  in their recent Report:     &quot; We  consider  that  steps should  be taken  to establishConsulates, with Englishmen in charge, at. both these places.0   It      n        ,      . r.,  ...        has been suggested  that this        Uemtaudilaznro-SLanf.           ^ inevitably WSlllt inthe Russians demanding Consulates at Kandahar aud Jelalabad.In our opinion this  contingency may be regarded without  anxiety.more especially if effect is ^iveii to the suggestion that Englishmenshould replace Indians as Consuls at the places in question.&quot;   The  suggestion  that the stipulation in  regard  to  RussianConsulates should  be  dropped is  further supported  both  by considerations of  tactics and by wider considerations of policy.It is probable, as  already suggested, that the Afghans will arrivewith  the expectation  of being  able  to  make  great  play  forbargaining  purposes with   British  nervousness  of  Russia and demands  for  safeguards  against  Russian   influence   (anexpectation, it may  be remarked,  that  is   not  likely to   be diminished  by  the  comments  of  tho  British Press,  which will no doubt continue lo couple most of their references to Afghanistanwith references to the &quot; Russian menace &quot;).  It is known  that the afghans hope to  establish a claim to facilities for  transit trade on general grounds of international practice, and thereby  to set free for other purposes the present quid  pro quo, viz.  the exclusion of Russian Consulates.   If it is found  that importance.is no longer attached on the British  side to this  stipulation, andthat no  other  stipulations of  an  anti-Russian character  are proposed, the Afghans will be in the position of  suddenly andunexpectedly having their  hand deprived of  what they probablyregard as its  strongest  cards, aud  tho British   position in any discussions will bo correspondingly strengthened.   As regards  wider  considerations of  policy,  it  is anomalousand in itself undesirable that we should  propose  to include in a
treaty  provisions  explicitly  directed  against  another  Power even though that  Power is  Soviet  Russia-and  particularly sowhen, as is the case with the arrangement in regard to RussianConsulates,  the provisions  conflict with the  provisions  of  an earlier treaty concluded between Afghanistan  and Russia   Theexisting  stipulation in  regard  to Consulates is also open to theobjections that it  infringes Afghan independence and  suggeststhe division  of Afghanistan into spheres of influence.   No similar provision is to  be found  in any of  the treaties  concluded byAfghanistan with  other Powers (even  in the treaty with Russia),or  in British treaties with  countries  in a  similar position, e.g.Persia.    It is suggested that  the time has gone by for the inclusion of provisions of this  kind  in treaties with Afghanistan, and that theproper basis for discussions now  is  that Afghanistan is a fullyindependent State, our treaty engagements with  which  should follow the ordinary lines of international arrangements.   If thisview is accepted, the attitude to be adopted  in  regard to  Russiaand Russian anti-British schemes will be, if not that they are amatter of indifference  to us, at any rate that  they do not enterinto the question of treaty relations with Afghanistan.    There is nothing inconsistent with this view in the Report ofthe Committee  of Imperial  Defence  Sub-Committee  on  IndianDefence.  D follows from what is said above  as to the reply tobe  made to Afghan suggestions  of  assistance against  russian aggression that  there can be no question at present of discussing with  Afghanistan  the  measures of military co-operation against russia  that are contemplated  in that Report as possibilities ofthe future.    Nor does the Report  suggest that there  is any occasion at  present for this, or for seeking to obtain from  the afghans any treaty provisions  or other  special engagements byway of preparing the way for such co-operation.  But the recent discussions   bring out   clearly the point  that there  are  twogoverning considerations by which any assumption of indifferenceto Russian  schemes must  in practice be tempered.  On the onehand, a definitely  friendly Afghanistan is a  primary condition ofBritish strategical plans for the defence of India ; on the otherhand, it.  is agreed  that the worst position of all  would  be lo havelo defend India on  her frontier faced by an Afghanistan which russia  by  peaceful means  had reduced  to a  protectorate and developed for war.  These  considerations  bring us back  to  thepoint that  we must in effect, in  our own interests, bid against russia  for   Afghan friendship, however  the  process  may bedisguised, to the  extent necessary to prevent  Afghanistan as awhole (or, it would perhaps be more accurate to say, the King orgoverning party) from falling away from frieudship with Britain,or, worse still, identifying themselves with  Russia to an extent that would be likely to  create the situation just  described.    This is  the justification for a  policy of granting  material assistance to Afghanistan on  a considerable  scale.   But here again it  is unnecessary, and very undesirable, that any assistance we may give should have any  avowed connexion with  Russiaor  Russian  assistance.  We can  without  admitting any suchconnexion give  assistance in ways that go to develop the common interests of  India and Afghanistan,  which  include  the main-tenancc  of  a strong and stable Government in Afghanistan, andit should be possible to keep  our  assistance1 within these limits(gilts  of arms, if they are  included, would  be  justifiable bythe desirability of strengthening  the central Government  of Afghanistan against the possibility of rebellion).    If the above general conclusions are accepted, any  discussions in  London   would  on  the  British side be conducted on  thelines  worked out  in some detail in  recent telegrams  from  theGovernment of India.
    Iii tho first instance, any Afghan suggestions for an offensiveanil defensive alliance, or other measures based on co-operation against Russia, should be  rejected firmly,  but of course in  asfriendly  a  way  as  possible.   Refusal could  be  softened  by a formula  on  the  lines suggested above,  and perhaps by addedexplanations that British public opinion is opposed  to entanglingalliances. This  opportunity or  whatever  other  opportunityfirst offers-might also, it  is suggested, be taken  to damp downAfghan expectations generally by explaining that we regard ourtroubled  relations with Russia as merely  a  passing phase; thatsooner or later  we shall  be friends again ;  and  that  in themeantime, though we must be  on  our guard, we are not goingto embark on any offensive or lay out our  policy on the  basis ofperpetual hostility.    The Afghans might then  bo expected to turn to a suggestion in general terms that the  existing  &quot; neighbourly &quot;  treaty shouldbe converted  into a  treaty  of &quot; friendship &quot; by which they  maybe taken  to mean a treaty  conferring more material  benefits  onAfghanistan.   Sir   F.  Jlumphrys has frequently  in  the  pastreported  tentative  moves  by the Afghans in this direction.  Thesuggestion can be met, as  proposed  by the Government of India,by the statement that &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government  will  be glad,if King  Amanulla  so desires, to emphasise  the closeness of theties between  the two countries in  a new treaty; and that  theywill direct His Majesty&apos;s Minister to  take the  matter upon theKing&apos;s return to Kabul aud  will  give him full instructions inthis regard before  he leaves London.&quot;   It might  be added  byway of a concession to  the  Afghans that  we should  be quite ready to dispense   with  the  one  years  notice  of terminationprovided for  in the existing treaty, if a new treaty is agreedupon.    It is  doubtful whether the Afghans  will,  in  any case,  press for the actual negotiation  of a new treaty in London ; they maybe  content  merely to see what they can get in  the   way  of preliminary  bids before going on to continue  the process  in moscow.   But, on  the other hand, they would probably like tohave  a   &quot;Treaty of London&quot; which would  sound well andemphasise the dissociation  of Afghanistan from India, and theymay well sec advantages in what are to our eyes the objections tonegotiating in London.  It is not improbable therefore that theymay propose  to inaugurate discussions  for a new  treaty duringthe King&apos;s visit  and to leave them to be continued  and concluded by the Afghan Minister in London,  with or  without assistants(a process during which they would  be able to test the possibilitiesof Moscow, with a  view  to conducting negotiations with  both countries simultaneously  thereafter).  From  the   British pointof view any proposal to negotiate in London wotdd obviously  boone to   be resisted. Experts   from  India would be  requiredto  deal   with technical clauses of. the treaty, as to  customs, &amp;c. ;and the  period  of  the King&apos;s  stay  in  this country would  be inadequate for  the purpose.   If Afghan  negotiators were left behind here they could do nothing without, reference to the King,and great inconvenience  and the entertainment of the Afghansin this country for  an indefinite  period wotdd  be involved.  Weshould probably in  the end be  driven by a process  of exhaustionto make  some sort  of treaty,  possibly not  particularly desirablefrom  the British point of view.   If  negotiations were transferredto Kabul, these inconveniences would bo  avoided,  and the policyof  exhaustion could not  be used  against us.   There would  beno special mission involved  in the negotiations-the  Britishnegotiator  in the  person  of the Minister would be at.  Kabul inany ease ; and even if  delays continued  indefinitely  or thenegotiations  lapsed altogether there would be nothing to  markthe fact and  to suggest  disagreement  as the departure  of  a
mission would.   (This  particular  difficulty  would  of  courseequally be overcome by-making the Afghan Minister in london the sole  negotiator on  the Afghan side;  but  it  is  doubtfulwhether the  Afghans would propose this, and, if  they did, theMinister would  not  bo  likely to bo entrusted with  any  functionsbeyond those of a post ollice.)  It will therefore be desirable to resist  to  the furthest  possible  extent  any  Afghan  proposals to open   detailed discussions  in  London;  but  it is  doubtful&apos;whether an absolute stand can  be made on this  point.   If theshortness of  the King&apos;s visit does not  deter  the  Afghans, theonly arguments that can be put to them would appear to bo thedifficulty  of  negotiating at so great a distance from sources oflocal  and technical  information  as to arrangements with India,which must be an important part of the treaty, and - though thisis the Afghans&apos; affair  rather than ours the convenience to theKing of  having  the negotiations carried on  under his own eyes,as his instructions will  be needed ou all questions of importance.If the  worst  comes lo  the  worst, it might be  possible  locompromise  on an arrangement  under which negotiations wouldbe inaugurated  here and  completed at. Kabul alter  the  british ministers return.  But this would  be very inconvenient.   Even  if the detailed discussion in  London of  a new treatycan  be averted, however,  the  Afghans  are likely  to ask  for something more  than the vague formula suggested above.  the obvious reply in the first instance would be to ask the Afghansto give some indication of  what  they themselves have in mind inthe way of treaty revision.  It  seems probable  that  they wouldthen put forward a claim  on general  grounds 10 free transit for imports through India, which is at present  tho quid pro  quo forthe exclusion of  Russian Consulates  from  Eastern Afghanistan.(In this  connexion,  an opportunity might naturally occur of informing the Afghans, if they had not  been informed already,thai we no longer  desire  to press the stipulation in regard to russian Consulates.  This statement, at this stage, might have avery useful sobering effect.)  The request  for  free transit  itselfneed  not  bo received  too  discouragingly;  the  Afghans might perhaps  be  told that examination  of this question has  alreadyboon  taken  up  in consultation  with the Government, of  India;but it would be undesirable to enter into detailed discussion ofthis  or other suggestions for minor alterations in the treaty e.g. for the  appointment  of au  Afghan  Consul at Peshawar or trade Agent at Chaman,  both of  which might  be accepted asrequests  that it  may be found  possible to consider favourably.   There arc   other possible suggestions  that   could  not  bereceived with any favour.   It would bo desirable to reject firmlyat the outset any suggestions for territorial concessions  or claims to a right of  interference of any sort in British  tribal territory.Tho  Afghans have  in  tho past  xiressed very  persistently their claims  to interest themselves on  behalf  of the  tribes  on theBritish side  of tho Durand line,  e.g. by attempting  to secure from  the British Government  a promise of amnesty  for tribesthat have taken part in frontier  risings or an extreme instancefrom  tho history of tho  1921  negotiations by demanding- the cession to Afghanistan, on the  principle of  self-determination, ofthose tribes on tho British side of the frontier -who  might, express a desire for  stieh cession.   In 1921  the interest of  the  AfghanGovernment  in  the  tribes beyond  their frontier was, in the end,admitted  to  the extent of attaching to the treaty  a  letter fromthe British representative to the Afghan Foreign Minister in the following terms :--    &quot;As  tho  conditions  of  the  frontier  tribes  of  the  twoGovernments are of interest to  the Government of Afghanistan,I inform  you that tho British Government  entertains feelings of goodwill  towards all the frontier tribes and has every intention
of  treating  them  generously,  provided  they  abstain   fromoutrages against the inhabitants of India.  I hope that tins letterwill cause you satisfaction.&quot;    (There  is also a mutual  undertaking, in Article  XI of thetreaty itself, that each Government will give notice beforehandto the other of any military operations of major importance thatmay appear necessary for  the  maintenance of order among thefrontier tribes on its own side of the line.)    It would  be preferable  now  not  even  to admit-as  theletter-quoted above did that  the Afghan Government  have  anacademic interest in the affairs of our tribes; and that admissionin any case was, of course, not to be interpreted as giving the afghans any claim to a voice in policy on the British side of the,line.  Nor  should we  wish to  invite, or avail ourselves  of, their good  offices with  our tribes  even  for  purposes  desirable  in themselves.  Particular  grounds  of  complaint  have  hithertoexisted  in  the  Afghan  practices of paying allowances to ourtribesmen  and summoning  them  to  meetings in   Afghanistan.These  are  difficult questions   that  it  has  not  hitherto been thought, and may still not  be, desirable to deal with explicitly ina treaty ; but they should be  borne in mind.    Another unacceptable suggestion that may possibly be  giventhe first place of  all is the revival of the cash subsidy formerlypaid by the Government of  India  to the Amir.   As will havebeen seen  from the account given above of the negotiations of1921, we have  not in the  past considered  the grant of such a subsidy inconsistent with a full recognition  of Afghan indepen-dence ;  nor did  the Afghaus themselves  apparently feel any difficulty on this ground  about accepting a subsidy from Russia.It is  possible that they are now  somewhat more  alive to  theincongruity between  the  receipt,  of  a  subsidy and   their,  if anything, superseusitive independence ;  but if they have anysuch feeling, it is probably not strong enough to preclude them from putting  forward the  request.  There  can be little  doubtthat cash is more than anyrhing  else the evidence of  friendshipthat the King would  really desire, and a subsidy can  always  berepresented as being  something in the nature of  tribute.  TheGovernment  of  India expect that &quot;King Amanulla will  againstand out  for a  cash  subsidy,&quot; which,  as  they say, we &quot;mustresist for a host  of reasons.&quot;  The objections are obvious.  Thesubsidy might be devoted to objects highly detrimental to Britishinterests,  aud  no  conditions  restricting those  objects  could probably be  enforced in practice.  The subsidy  could not  be withheld without  something like a breach in diplomatic relations.Once  embodied  in  a treaty, moreover, it would  be regarded  bythe Afghans as a  matter  of course,  calling for  no  particularreturn, or even gratitude, and to be used as a jumping-off ground for fresh concessions.  (For these reasons Sir Francis Ilumphrys,as explained below, has urged the substitution of a &quot;subsidy in kind.&quot;)   The  Government  of  India&apos;s view  is that &quot;in any circumstances that  can at  present be  foreseen,  a demand  for a subsidy should be resisted.&quot;    Whether resistance should,  what-ever the circumstances, be carried to the point of absolute refusal,during  any conversations in  London, to  consider the possibilityof a cash subsidy,  is  a  question  that appears  to  require some further consideration, and is beiug taken up separately.  Discus-sion of  the subsidy question  in 1921 was dominated, first of all,by the view that.  &quot; it  would  be absurd and  indefensible for the afghans to obtain subsidies from both Russia and Great Britainat the same  time,&quot; and  the question of a cash subsidy finallydropped when  the  Russian  treaty  was ratified.   If  events  inLondon took such a turn that a cash subsidy became the crucial question, it might be  thought  desirable to hold out some hopo(which, in effect, would be  a  promise) that a  British  subsidy    3051                                                13
LOwould be forthcoming if  the Afghans ceased to accept a subsidyfrom  Russia (and possibly, as a further condition, if  they also-ceased  to employ Russians  in  their  armed  forces).    But  theobjections to  such a course  are  very weighty, and,  whateverviews may be  held as to  the possibility of adopting it in the last resort, it will probably be agreed that it is extremely undesirable to adopt it if it can be avoided.    As the final upshot of discussion on broad  lines on an Afghanrequest for indications  of the nature of the treaty that we areprepared  to  contemplate, the Afghans could  be  assured,  asproposed by the Government of India, that &quot; wo hope that it willbe possible  to arrive at a mutual arrangement which will furthertho development of trade intercourse between the  two countries by the establishment,  in particular, of freer transit  and  thesimplification of  customs arrangements, and the extension  of consular posts  in tho  two countries  (? and which will promote the common  peace  on our borders by a mutual undertaking toremove dangerous criminals  from  the other country to a safedistance).&quot;   The same formula might apparently be used withoutdisadvantage, if  necessary, even if the Afghans brought forwardno suggestions of their own, or before they brought them forward.Tho last sentence of this formula involves difficult questions, andis  subject to some doubt pending  further consultation  with theGovernment  of India.   Tho  Afghans may raise the question ofextradition, not because  they  think an extradition  treaty is reallypossible at  present-for  they know  from  discussions  with sir F. Humphrys that it is not-but because they know  that this and connected questions are somewhat embarrassing for the BritishGovernment, as we do not administer the tribal territory on our side  of the Durand line, whereas  the Afghan Government doesadminister (or claims that it does) tho tribal territory on its side.Actual extradition is impossible from the British side because oftho primitive nature of judicial  arrangements in Afghanistan,and also, it is understood, from  the Afghan side because it is contrary to  Pathan ideas of hospitality.   Tho most that could be aimed at, probably,  would be a mutual undertaking  to removedangerous  criminals from the  neighbourhood of the  frontier.Even here, a fully reciprocal arrangement appears  impossible,.owing to the inability of the Oiovernment of  India to undertakeobligations  in respect of tribal territory.  Enquiry is being madeof the Government of  India as  to the precise  nature of thearrangements that they contemplate.    If the  Afghans  put  forward specific proposals, it  would inthe ordinary course  be desirable at the same stage to put forwardbalancing proposals of our own, and possibly to pitch them ratherhigh for bargaining purposes.  It would no doubt be well to mention that we should  wish  to  obtain the right  to appointConsuls at Herat and Mazar-i-Sharif,  There is little else of  any importance that we should desire  to include in a treaty, and no obvious bargaining provision that suggests itself.    It wouldprobably be  best to limit ourselves  at  this stage to  this  one proposal, especially as it is very undesirable, as has already been said, to enter into discussion of details in London.    This would exhaust the  discussion  of treaty revision in the strict sense, for it is agreed that, if gifts in  kind are lo be made to the Afghans, it  is  highly undesirable  to include  specific mention of  them in  the treaty itself, though the Government of India have  suggested that, if  necessary,  words could  bo inserted in the treaty (aud an assurance on the same  lines given before-hand to King Amanulla) to the effect  that &quot; Great Britain takes a  friendly  interest  in  the development of Afghanistan and is ready to co-operate  with the Afghan Government in measures designed towards the  promotion  of the  common  commercial interests of the two  countries.&quot;
   But here again it is not expected that King Amanulla will hecontent  lo leave  England  with nothing  more  than  a  vagueformula, and  the question  of  giving  more  specific  promises ofmaterial  assistance will probably  therefore  have  to be faced.This is not a new question, but has  in fact been under discussionfor some years past, as a matter of current policy irrespective; of treaty revision..  The result of these discussions  has  been  theapproval  in principle of Sir Francis llumphrys&apos; proposals Tor theadoption  of what he described as the policy of the  &quot; subsidy in kind.&quot;  This was, in brief, that King Amanulla should  be givenperiodically assistance in kind, up to a maximum value hithertoput at 7 lakhs of rupees (say,   02,000) a year, provided in eachcase that he had asked  for it and had earned  it, and that it wasto the mutual advantage of India and Afghanistan.  A beginningwas  made with the application of  the  policy  in the shape of ascheme for assisting the Afghans in regard  to the  realignmentand reconstruction of the Kabul-Khyber  road (a scheme which,if carried out. would  apparently  absorb  the  whole  amountcontemplated  as available for the &quot;subsidy  iu kind &quot; for someyears).  But  the policy has not come into effective operation, asafter  surveys  had been made and  a  plan of  operations worked out, the Afghans withheld their final acceptance of the scheme for reasons which have never  been altogether  clear, but the  realunderlying motive of which is believed to have been a hope thatthey  might after all be able to obtain  assistance in cash ratherthan in any other form.   Any form  of assistance  of  which  hopes  might now be  heldout should  comply with the  condition  laid down  in connexionwith the &quot; subsidy in kind,&quot; that it should promote  the common interests  of the  two  countries.  The formula proposed by theGovernment of  India  for  possible  inclusion  in a treaty  andquoted in the preceding paragraph is more restrictive  in that it includes  the  word &quot;commercial.&quot;  If  the purposes for whichfunds have to be provided from  Indian  revenues can  be repre-sented as promoting the common commercial interests of the twocountries, it will obviously be so much  the easier to justify theexpenditure to the Indian taxpayer ; but  it is not intended thatthe  restriction should  necessarily apply in  all cases, outside thetreaty.   It is  in India&apos;s interest, though not except indirectly a matter of &quot; commercial&quot; interest, that there  should be a strong and stable central Government in Afghanistan, and some possible forms of assistance e.g.   arms can be justified  by this test though they could hardly be held to he  covered, perhaps, by the&quot; commercial&quot; formula.    Tt may be laid down as a guiding  principle in  approaching the  discussion with the  Afghans of  possible gifts,  that  they should   be left  to  make  the first move  by indicating  their requirements.   Anything  volunteered  from  the  British  side would be likely thereafter to  be taken for granted and regarded by the  Afghans merely as  a  basis on  which  to found a  larger request.  Insistence on the point that the Afghans  should make the first move may possibly introduce a temporary check in the discussions; but it is  thought that the Afghans will be unable to stand out on this point.  We have it on Sir Francis Humphrys&apos; authority that the King and his tour are unpopular in Afghanistan, and it is probably a vital matter for him  that he should be  able to show some promise of material returns when he gets back.    Assuming that the Afghans ask for them, the following are forms of assistance that it is agreed might, be given  :     (1)  Road  development,  more particularly  the resumption of the suspended Kabul-Khyber scheme,  for  which everything is in train  the  moment  King  A mantilla accepts our  programme. The Government of India have expressed  tho view that  this road is  so essential for proper communication between the two
countries that the  Amir  should be given  no encouragement todiscard it in favour oT some other project.   (2) Telegraph development. -Tin; Government  of  India  have said  that they will  always  be  ready to give free construction or working parties within the south-eastern zone or Afghanistan.   (3)  Railways. It is agreed that  we should make no move in proposing railway construction; but that if and when KingAmanulla does  so  of his own accord, his proposals  (assuming,of course, that  they do not cake a  form unacceptable  to  us)should  be received as  sympathetically as possible.   Generallyspeaking, our preference would bo that an extension from LandiKhana to Kabul should  lie the first stage and  the linking  up ofChaman and  Kandahar the second.   But consideration of thopossibilities of  assistance  cannot, of  course, be carried very faruntil King .\manulla&apos;s wishes are  known.   (4) Civil Air Service. We should  be glad to assist in theestablishment of a civil air service between India and Afghanistan.The  Government  of India  are considering  technical details of proposals to this end.   (5) Reorganisation  of Customs, Posts and  Telegraphs. TheGovernment of  India have expressed their willingness  to assist in these  ways  at any  time  if  asked  (subject, possibly,  toassurances of proper treatment of their officers  if  lent), but itmight be  inadvisable for us to undertake reorganisation ourselves,in view of probable accusations of manoeuvring the  customs toour  own  advantage.   It appears  that  the reorganisation of the posts and Telegraphs  has already been  entrusted to a Frenchexpert.   (fi) Exchange bank. It is  thought that  the Afghans wouldprobably  not ask  for  British  assistance  in  this  matter unlessmanoeuvred into doing so.   If they did ask, the  Government ofIndia have  said that they would  be  prepared to  give a Britishbunk of standing a contingent guarantee of compensation in theevent of their premises or specie  being raided. It is recognisedthat, whatever the parent  bank, this branch woidd have to poseas the  National Bank of Afghanistan or under some similarca mouflagc.   (7) Munitions  of war. The Government of India would beprepared  to make gilts of lorries,  tents, and other  forms ofmilitary equipment ;  and  say  that they would not set their faceagainst a request for such military material as would help theAfghan  Government   to  quell  internal  disorder excepting,however, machine guns, and  also tanks until such time as theArmy in India is equipped with these.  They are  also prepared,if necessary, to present pack guns, of a type no.longer to be usedin their own field army, together with plants for the manufactureof ammunition.   These  possible offers mark  au  advance  on our  previousattitude vis-a-vis the Afghans.  In May 1925, when  the Afghansput  forward as the first of four definite requests for assistance inthe  internal  development of Afghanistan a request for the sale atconcession rates, or preferably the free gift, of rifles, ammunition,and  guns, the  objections  to complying with  this request were held to make a favourable reply impossible.    (8) Military and technical  training in England for Afghanyoidha. The Government of India point out tho  practical diffi-culties particularly lack of  preliminary training  and knowledgeof English but agree that our general attitude should be to helpif we can.  In particular they would like  to see tho experimentmade in  some  form, if possible, of  giving military training toAfghans in England.   They suggest that the most hopeful  lineis perhaps offered  by  the latest Afghan idea that,  a batch of young  military officers  should be attached to various militaryxtuits.   Given  six months  or so of  preliminary  training in
 England, the Government of India think that reasonably useful results  might  be obtained  with selected material.   We have heard that during the  King&apos;s visit to Italy arrangements were made for the training of 25 Afghans in aviation free of all coat to the Afghan Government, and Mr. Gould has received informa- tiou to the effect that the King will  request facilities for military training, aud probably aviation training, in England.    Suggestions for training in other directions could bo received sympathetically.  (It may be mentioned that a batch of Afghans are at present undergoing a course of training in police methods in  this country.)    It  would  be  desirable  as far  as  possible  to  keep  any discussions in London of material assistance  on rather general lines, avoiding definite commitments pending detailed considera- tion.   The Government of India have remarked that, while they recognise the efficacy of  all the above projects in their varying degrees  as means of improving Anglo-Afghan  relations, it  is of course obvious  that, apart from  political  considerations,  their cumulative cost would constitute  too great a burden  upon the revenues of  India  unless the  programme were  spread over a number  of years.  Each therefore would, they say, have to be considered on  its merits when the  time came, aud care would have  to  be taken that expenditure in any single year was kept within reasonable limits.    The  Government  of  India  mention  as possible gifts Afghan requests for which could  not be entertained      (a)  Gifts of machinery  for their factories in view of the         undesirability of devoting Indian money to the purchase         of British machinery to turn out goods which would         oust Indian goods from the Afghan market; aud    (6) Gifts of aeroplanes, spares, &amp;c, for the Afghan Air Force         so long as it is  in Russian hands.    The first suggested request, for machinery for factories, was one of the four  definite requests above  referred to, made by the Afghans in 1925.  It is now proposed  to look favourably on the other three (Nos. (7),  (1) and (S) above, to put them in  the order of preference in which they were put by the Afghans in  1925).    It is impossible to foresee with any certainty the actual course of  discussion with the Afghans in London, and it  may well be that the assumptions made in this  note as to the stages  through which they will  pass and the order in which these stages will be reached will prove to be  wrong.  But it is hoped that this wouldnot be found to prejudice materially whatever uses the note may otherwise have.   The  guiding principles on  the  British side ofthe discussions  will  in   any event  be the  same  and, minorquestions of tactics apart, the method in which particular issuesshould be  dealt with  would  not appear to depend to any great extent on the order on which the issues arise.[TELEGRAMS.
    Telegram from Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department, 3rd January J92S.    0 S.  It scents probable that  Amanulla  on his visit to London will broach thesubject of  closer relations,  and possible that he may even press for the conclusionforthwith of a new treaty of  friendship to signalise his visit, without wailing for the expiry of one years notice  under the treaty.   It is  advisable., therefore, to take stock of the treaty position in  advance.    Not that we think that wc should fall in with a proposal to negotiate  a treatyduring I lie visit,  or even  to negotiate it in  London at all.  True, it is  obviouslydesirable to humour Amanulla as far as possible on his visit, and the prior conclusionof a good treaty in London would take the wind out of the Russian sails, and  counterpossible evil effects of Moscow visit.   Moreover, as  the present treaty was concluded in Kabul, London would be the proper venue for the next.    Hut the arguments against attempting to negotiate a treaty in London are many.The technical difficulties alone would be great, for  much of a new treaty is likely tobe taken up with  a revision of customs and trade arrangements, ami the technical questions involved would be difficult of solution  unless a technical adviser of ours isattached to plenipotentiary and maintains close liaison with our technical departments.The negotiations would almost certainly be  drawn out  long past  the King&apos;s visit toEngland, aud there would be manifold  disadvantages in  the Afghan negotiatorsstaying ou indefinitely  in  London hotel  at our expense.   Protracted negotiations would,  moreover,  mean protracted absence of Humphrys (who we assume would be our plenipotentiary) from Kabul, where, important developments are to be expected onAmanulla&apos;s return as the result of his grand tour.    Hence,  if  Amanulla broaches the  subject of a new treaty in London, we  advise that he lie assured that His Majesty&apos;s Government will  be glad, if  he so desires, toemphasise  the closeness of the ties between the two  countries in a new treaty; thatthey will direct His  majesty&apos;s Minister to take the  matter up on  King*s  return toKabul ; and will give him full instructions in this regard before he leaves London.    But Amanulla  will  probably press for  a more  definite indication of His Majesty&apos;governments attitude particularly towards  his  own  desiderata.   These may  have developed since Humphrys analysed them in  his Despatch No. 5(5 of the -1th December1923, but in the main his analysis probably holds good.    (I) Subsidy. In particular,  everything goes  to show that Amanulla will  againstand out for a cash subsidy.  This we must resist for a host of  reasons.  After sevenor eight years of Anglo-Afghan relations without  one, it  would be retrograding toreinstitute  it.  If  reinstituted, we might  find our  subsidy  devoted  to schemes (e.g.eommunicatious north of the Hindu  Kush or Mahsud  allowances) highly detrimental to India&apos;s interests.  Furthermore, there  is the Afghan tendency to regard anythingguaranteed in a treaty as something  conferring no  merit on the giver, to be enjoyed by  themselves as a matter of course, aud to be used as a jumping-off  ground for freshconcessions.   Our  opinion  therefore  is that, in any circumstances which can atpresent, be foreseen, a demand for a subsidy should be resisted.    (2)  Free transit and simplification of trade  regulations. Recent review  of our obligations under the Barcelona  Convention  makes  it  fairly clear  that  AfghanGovernment could secure without undue difficulty a substantial enlargement of tradebenefits they are receiving under the treaty as far as goods in genuine through transitacross Tndia are concerned.   But the volume of trade  in genuine through transit is atpresent v*ery small.    In actual practice, great  majority  of goods  in so-called transit  are not alreadydestined for  Afghanistan  at the  time of entry into British Indian ports,  and thepractical difficulties we have experienced over differentiating between various classesof  trade for  purposes of  the treaty illustrate the  complexities of tho case  and thenecessity for close association between plenipotentiary aud our technical experts, whichwould hardly be feasible except in  Kabul.  Whole matter is still under examination,but it looks as if we shall he able to go some way towards simplification of procedure and free transit, at any rate for goods railed  direct from port to frontier station, butexpressly reserving to ourselves the right to withhold transit in the event of unfriendlybehaviour  as at present in the analogous case of State  goods.    (3) Consul at Peshawar. Hitherto we have resisted this appointment because ofscope Peshawar offers Afghan officials for  intrigue (vide the Afghan Postmaster up toJ919),  and because of  our stand  against inland consulates  generally.   But  local
makeshift arrangements  that  have had  to  be made  in  connection  with visea  have demonstrated the need  for an Afghan consular official  in Peshawar, where Afghantrade is of course considerable, and we are now prepared  to withdraw our opposition.Dangers of intrigue there must of course he, but the)- will  be lessened in the case ofa  Consul under  consular rules and  regulations on the  Government House list  andassociating freely with officials and  gentry.  The  appointment may perhaps tend to undermine  the  general  standing we have  hitherto taken against inland consulates,though Afghanistan  presents  no real analogy to countries  without overland  tradewith India.   This risk wc are prepared to take.    (4) Trade Agent  at  Chaman. Afghan  Government sets great store bv  thisappointment both for genuine  trade  agency purposes and,  in view of the ease ofsmuggling on the Quetta border, still more  as a preventive agency.   Here again the dangers of intrigue, which have hitherto made us  resist the appointment, woidd bereal.   But the obvious need for a trade officer  of the sort has forced us  to admit toChaman a subordinate of tho trade agent at Quetta, and it is questionable whetherthe dangers are  not greater with him that they would be with a recognised trade agentwith duties clearly defined in a  treaty and liable to recall  if he strayed outside them.    (5) Territorial readjustments, tOc. Any suggestions for territorial cessions  orboundary readjustments  or claims to right of interference of any  sort in our tribalterritory  should  be summarily rejected.   We are. however, prepared to entertainproposals for a reciprocal self-denying ordinance already ventilated with  the Afghan(iovernmeut in respect of Peiwar, vide Katodon 14 of February 1927, not.  to  buildnew posts within a specified  distance from  the  frontier.  It is questionable whether we could  extend  this  principle to the demolition of  existing  posts, but  the matter isunder detailed examination.    (ii) Extradition Treaty. There are almost insuperable difficulties to anything like a regular Extradition Treaty, owing,  in particular, to the elementary  state of judicialprocedure in Afghanistan and to our inability to enforce  our  writs in most of tribalterritory.   On the other hand, both Governments have felt the need for a  more definite understanding over outlaws of one country who take refuge in  the other.   a clause might therefore figure in the treaty to the effect that, while the formulation ofa separate extradition agreement is felt by  both Governments to be  premature, they recognise that it  is not (sic^ in  the interest of the peace of  the cpmmon  border  that each Government should undertake  at the request of  the  other to remove  to aueffective  distance from the frontier  any daugerous criminal wdio may  have takenrefuge in its tenitory after having committed a heinous offence in his own country.It  is clearly wise not to attempt  to  specify the distance  of removal.   Fifty mileswould  perhaps suffice in the  case of tin ordinary criminal,  but  woidd  be whollyinadequate in such a case as that of A jab.    This analysis  leads us to the conclusion that, if  the King presses  for assurance asto  the character of treaty we would be prepared to negotiate, he  might  bo  verballyassured that we hope that it will be possible to arrive at a mutual arrangement  whichwill further the  development of trade intercourse between the two countries by  theestablishment, in particular, of freer transit and simplification of Customs arrangements and the extension of Consular posts in the two countries,  and which will promote  thecommon peace on our borders by a mutual undertaking to remove dangerous criminalsfrom the other country to a safe distance.    Without, the  mention of a subsidy, however, or something substantial to  take its place, the King  is not likely to find satisfaction.  We are addressing you separatelyon  the Ministers various proposals for concrete assistance in kind.  But wo  agreewith him  that, whatever gifts in kind  may be decided  upon, it is  highly undesirable to  include mention  of them  in the  treaty  itself.   The  utmost  that could be  donewould  be the insertion  of words  to  the effect that Great Britain takes a  friendlyinterest in tho development of Afghanistan and is ready to co-operate with the AfghanGovernment in measures designed towards promotion of common commercial interestsof the two countries.  And an assurance on  these liucs  might bo given Amanulla.    lie may possibly raise tho question of being released  from obligation (vide  letterattached  to treaty) to exclude  Russian  Consulates  from south-eastern  zone as  ourcondition for the gift of trade  concessions.  It would  certainly  be raised in treatyaiegotiations.  Arguments in favour of dropping our stipulations  are strong:  (a) It
purports to infringe  sovereignty and  to  annul in an Anglo-Afghan Treaty what is granted in a Kusso-Afghan Treaty;  (b)  it suggests parcelling of Afghanistan intospheres of influence,  which is repugnant to the Afghan  Government; (c) it invitesa  counter-balancing  Russo-Afghan  restriction  on  appointment of British Consulsin North.    On the other hand, exclusion of Russian Consulates is valuable in itself.  Presenceof Russian officials so near our borders would be regarded by our tribesmen as a blow to British prestige, and entire absence of Russian trade interests would leave themfree to concentrate on well-financed  tribal intrigue  against us.  It is valuable also as  an established  principle from which others (like normal  exclusion  of Russianaviators from the South) may bo developed.  Hence, in  so  far as choice may prove to lie between Russian  Consuls on our borders and exclusion of British Consuls fromHerat aud Mazar-i-Sharif, we  believe that, in  the circumstances to-day, the balanceof advantage lies with  the latter, despite the fact that we want Consuls  in the Northboth for trade and intelligence purposes.    But with Afghanistan^ growing sense of international usage  it may only bea matter  of a  few years for her to recognise radical difference between allowingRussian Consulates in the South, where there arc no Russian trade interests, with the sole object, as Afghan  Foreign Minister has more than once admitted, of anti-british propaganda, and British Consulates in North, where our trade interests are considerable.Hence we took the view  that, while  we should seek to get on a par with Russia by securing treaty right  to establish northern consulates in return for an Afghan Consulin Peshawar  and Trade Agent in Chamau, wc should leave tho actual filling of  the appointments over for the present.   Though we should be sorry to lose security which definite treaty obligation  givesus against establishment of  Russian  Consulates, we recognise its  difficulties anddrawbacks.  There would clearly be advantages if we could simply rely on  Minister^powers of persuasion to  induce the Afghan Government  to  prohibit  what  would inevitably become a source of  friction in Anglo-Afghan relations.  It would, however,be dangerous to dispense  altogether  with a written guarantee.   While, therefore, ourstipulation might be  dropped from a formal exchange of notes attached  to treaty we feel  it should  be  replaced by a separate  warning  in writing that we should regardadmittance  of  Russian Consulates  on our  border as  symptomatic of unfriendlybehaviour within the  meaning of Trade Concessions Article.    Telegram from Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department,  3rd January 1928.    7  S.   Wc  have now  examined   Humphrys&apos; concrete proposals for  improvingA nglo-Afghan relations.    (1)  Road development. -In  our telegram  1323 S, 22nd October 1925, we acceptedthe principle of granting the Amir periodically assistance in kind, provided that he asked  for it, had earned it,  and  it  was to  the mutual  advantage of India and afghanistan.  We recognised  in  particular  that,  the  community of  Indo-Afghaninterests could hardly be fostered better than  by the civilising  influence of increasedtrade   aud  intercourse   that  would  arise   from   progressive  improvement  of communications.  This principle  we  have already put  in  practice  by  our  specificoffer to co-operate over the realignment of the Kabul-Landi Khana road.   Everythingis in train for the initiation of this work the moment, the Amir accepts our programme.If he does so it will  hardly be necessary to consider tho other road schemes in  thenear future, for the work is elaborate and will take a  considerable time to complete.So essential is this road for proper communication between the two countries that the Amir should be given no encouragement to discard it in favour of some other project.    (2) Telegraph development. This too has already been accepted  in principle,  and within the general conditions of the  subsidy in kind we  shall always  be ready togive free construction or working parties within the south-eastern zone.   Our schemesfor expending money on the exclusion of Russians from erecting and running wirelessinstallation in Afghanistan have dropped, at  any rate for the present, owiug  to the securing of the contract by a Frenchman.    (3) Railways. This subject has been dealt with separately, and  we need only sayhero  that we have throughout recognised  that, if the Amir  is set on railways, we can afford to run no risk of finding ourselves forestalled in railway construction by Russia,and must render him expert and financial assistance.
    (4) Civil Air Service. In our telegram  of  October  1925 we foreshadowed thepossibility of assistance over civil  aviation  on an  air route between  India and afghanistan.  Since  then  the arguments in favour of it  have strengthened, partly asa counter  if not a stopper to the Russianised Air Force, partly because of Junkers&apos;apparent anxiety to forestall us and partly because political effect, both in afghanistan and amongst  our tribes, of our great aeroplanes plying regularly  between  Kabul,Peshawar and Lahore would  be considerable.   We are examining tho financial effecton  the Air Ministry scheme  of substituting  a  three-engined  machine, which we are advised would be necessary to give the Service that stability which is essential for  its full political effect .    (5) Reorganisation of Customs and Posts and  Telegraphs. Any such assistance wewould gladly  render  at.  any time.  The difficulties are two-fold.  First, the ensuringof proper treatment for our officers, aud second and more serious, Afghan disinclinationto turn to us for such  services.  But the  important thing, even from our own pointof view, is the reorganisation of  the  services, not their  manning by Britishers, andaccording to the latest reports Frenchmen  have already  been engaged to reorganisethe Telegraphs.    (6) Exchange Iiank.--H.ere again  the chief  difficulty lies  in allaying the  Amir&apos;sapprehension  that  a  British bank  might  result in  undue  British influence, andmanoeuvring  him into asking for our assistance.  Should he do so we  would  beprepared  to give a  British  bank  of standing proposed contingent guarantee  ofcompensation  in the event of their premises or specie being raided, for its politicalby-products would  be considerable.   Whatever  the parent bank, tins branch would of course have to pose as the National Bank of  Afghanistan, or under  some similarcamouflage.    (7) Munitions of war. We recognise that grants of lorries, tents  aud other formsof military equipment are suitable  items in a subsidy in kind.   Nor would we setour face against the request for such  military material as would help tho AfghanGovernment to  quell internal disorder machine guns,  however, excepted, and alsotanks  until such time as  the army in  India is equipped with them.  We are also prepared, if necessary, to present pack guns, a type no longer to be used in our field army, together with  plants for manufacture  of ammunition.    (S) In addition, we have considered the  military and technical training of Afghanyouths in England as a medium for improving relations.   But it is beset&apos;with variousdifficulties, notably  lack  of preliminary training and knowledge of English.   Afghansshow no  signs so far  of  adopting the obvious solution  of  preliminary course in India.They are said to be  toying with the idea of securing English professors for  Kabul,but the normal conditions of service are not calculated to attract or keep Englishmenof the right stamp    Difficulties over admission  to Sandhurst seem  especially great,and a more hopeful line is perhaps Offered  by the latest Afghan idea that a batch  of young military  officers  should  be attached  to  various military units.   It seems possible  that, given  six  months&apos; or so preliminary training in  England, this proposal might lead to  reasonably useful results with selected material.  Success would meanso much  politically that  we should like to  see the experiment made in some form  or another.   In general, our  attitude  should  be  to  help  if we can.  The  tour  willprobably open the Amir&apos;s eyes to  some cf the practical difficulties.   Difficulties, and measures  to surmount  them, are  probably  best discussed in London, where theMinister might explore the possibilities further.    While we recognise tho ellicacy of  all these projects in their varying degrees  asmeans of improving Anglo-Afghan relations, it is, of course, obvious  that, apart from political  considerations,  their  cumulative cost would  constitute too  great  a burdenupon  the  revenues  of India unless  the  programmes  were spread over a number  ofyears.  In so far as the railway projects may result in  an  increase of trade, they canbo regarded to some extent as productive and included in  the calculation at somethingless than their full cost.  For  the rest, while we except the projects in principle, eachwould  have to be considered on  its merits when the time  came, and care would haveto be taken that  expenditure in any single year was kept within reasonable limits.    Among the possible Afghan gifts which we are not  prepared to entertain are :     (1) Gift of machinery for their factories, in view of the undesirability of devoting         Indian  money to tho purchase of British machinery to turn out  goods which         would oust Indian goods from Afghan market.    (2) Gift of aeroplanes, spares,  Ac, for their  Air  Force as long  as it is in         Russian hands.     2551
        Telegram from Secretary of Stale to Viceroy, doled 2nd February 1928.    317.  Foreign and  Political Department.   Your telegrams Nos. 0 S. and  7 S.,dated the 3rd January.    Subject to reservations indicated below, His Majesty&apos;^ Government agree generally with your  views and proposals.    It is to be hoped  that  it will not be necessary to enter into details with  Afghansin London, butl should he glad of your further comments on the following points:     (1)  Proposal to make  transit  facilities dependent on friendly behaviour.   I am not clear whether right proposed to be reserved is lo stop goods altogether or merely to  withhold   facilities  for free  transit.  Provision  in existing  treaty is for  totalstoppage, but applies only lo arms and ammunitions.   This is  obviously a special case and is described as &quot;right exercised  bv every  nation.&quot;  It  mav be desirable  toretain this special clause in regard  to  arms and munitions, but. I feel great doubt  asto  desirability of  attempting to extend provision  for controlling Afghan behaviour1)3* this rather anomalous method, and  should be disposed, even  if it  is proposed  togive Afghans facilities  going beyond the  letter  of anything they could secure underBarcelona  Convention, lo make  the concession outright.    Apart from Afghan objections, or objections  from ordinary international  practice to control  by impending  threat as such, it  could be  urged with some force that it  is unreasonable to  subject  operations of general trade to  the  uncertain ties of ourinterpretation of a vague  political condition.  Argument would, of  course,  have allthe more force if penalty proposed  is to stop transit trade altogether.  If proposed treaty provision were made, should wc  in practice ever enforce penalty or gain  morethan we should lose  lry threatening to do so?  I deal below with proposed specialuse of this provision in connection with Russian Consulates.    (2) Mutual undertaking as to dangerous criminals.  I assume undertaking in formproposed  could be given  in  respect of administered territory only,  and that  youcontemplate some arrangement failing short of full reciprocity, such  as  that proposedin Ilumphrys&apos; demi-official letter to Bray, No. 152, of the 8th April 1021 ?    (3) F.xclusion of machine guns  from any gift of arms.   What precisely is  yourreason  and have you in mind  any particular explanation to be given to Afghans?Have  you  considered argument  that  gift  of  machine  guns may  be particularly desirable  as  strengthening regulars  against  irregulars, and  thereby  helping   to stabilise Afghan Government?    (-1) Russian Consulates. Apart from doubts in (I) above as to provision in-TradeConcessions Article on which your filial proposal turns, I feel that desirability of that proposal in itself is very doubtful.   Afghans may well be suspicious and resentful  of proposal to secure by such  indirect means i.e. by attaching outside treaty an arbitrarymeaning to what  they may regard as in itself an unreasonable stipulation of  treaty an  end  which we do not choose to proclaim in treaty.   If  arrangement were not published  Afghans would  be (or would profess to be) the less able  to resist Russianproposals to  fill  Consulates,  and it  would  be  very  difficult  in  practice  to enforcepenalty.  If  arrangement  were  published   it might  be attacked  as  unreasonable  orimproper, and in any ease would lose its virtue, for it would in that event apparentlybe just  as well to make a straightforward deal as in  present treaty.   But apart  fromdifficulties of particular  method  you  propose, 1 greatly doubt  whether  it. is nowdesirable  to  continue to press for  exclusion  of Consulates  at  all.   You recognisestrong  arguments for dropping stipulations, and there is force  also in the generalobjection to attempting any longer to include in treaties with Afghanistan  provisionsnot in accordance with ordinary international practice.    Your view as to actual  practical  value of exclusion of  Consulates must, of course,carry greatest weight; but opinions on the  point have differed, and general view here is that appointment of  British Consuls in  North  is more important than exclusion  ofRussians from East.    I am strongly inclined  to view that  we should endeavour  to secure right to appointBritish  Consuls at Herat and Mazar-i-Sharif, and  if we cannot exclude Russians fromEastern Afghanistan  by direct  provision in treaty (objections to  which  I feel  to be almost, if not quite, conclusive)  we  should content ourselves by stressing to  Afghansabsence of legitimate justification  for Russian Consuls, and likelihood  that if  theywere  allowed their activities would create trouble.    It is worth remembering that every indication  we give of  continued anxiety as  toRussians is in some measure an additional invitation  to Afghans to endeavour to  trade
on  that feeling.  And if in  this particular instance Afghans found that we had droppeddemand for exclusion of Consulates, which they probably look forward  to as one oftheir best counters for bargaining if  it can  he detached from its present quid pro quoof transit facilities, our position in discussions should be greatly strengthened.        Telegram, from Secretary of Stale to  Viceroy, dated 2nd February 192S.    300.  foreign and  Political  Department.  Your telegram dated the 3rd January,No. (I  8.   In  view  of  possibility  that,  question of  a  cash  subsidy may assumeoutstanding  importance  in  any discussions with  Afghans,  it. seems desirable  to pursue analysis of this  question somewhat further than it is carried in  para. (I)  ofyour telegram, with which,  so far as it goes, we, of course, entirely agree.    Supposing  that Afghans put this question before  all others aud maintain  theirstand upon  it   in spite of all that wo can  do in tho way of stressing  incongruity withindependence, with British  ideas, and with ordinary international practice, wo  shallhardly  be  able to  avoid coming down more  or  loss  definitely to one of followingalternatives:      (1) Can wo  afford,  in spite of  possible risk  of throwing  Afghans entirely into         arms  of Russia,  to  maintain absolute  refusal  to  consider cash subsidy.         looking to Afghan self-interest and to generosity on  our part in other         directions (if opening  is  still left for  this)  to prevent whatever real risk         there  is from developing into a serious danger to British interests?     (2) If  not, should wo  take lino  that Afghans made  British subsidy  impossible         when  they ratified Russian  treaty, and hold out  hope that if they dispensed         with  Russian  subsidy (ami  possibly, as an  additional  condition,  avoided         employment of Russian personnel in their armed forces) British Government         would be  ready to reconsider  matter?  This  would,  presumably,  mean         a subsidy at least as large as that promised  by Russia, aud would  be open         to other special objections that are obvious.     (3) Arc objections  to (2) so weighty that  it  would on the  balance  bo preferable         oven  to waive  objection hitherto  hold so strongly to  simultaneous  Russian         subsidy and to contemplate grant  of a subsidy without explicit  conditions,         though  it could of course  purport to be for the development  of common         commercial  interests?  Subsidy could then bo smaller and there would not         be the same prospect, of continual wrangling over fulfilment of conditions.    1 do not at  present express any opinion on these alternatives,  and am of courseconscious  that  we  cannot, provide fully  beforehand for all  possible ways in whichproblem may present itself.  But it will  be a great advantage to have our minds asclear as possible,  and i shall be glad to have your  further observations.

</content>
</cab>
