<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/192/0 images: 301-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-   ^                                                         210   O  (THIS DOOUL-iBST IS THE PJi0P*.2TY OF^ HIS BglgA^IO KAJSSTys GOVZSlInSlIT).                           0 A E IE   2^                                 &quot;COPY No.                       BBOADOA3rx&apos;I?.&amp; OF COSTaoVSaSY.3 5 C R E T.  .     (Her. orandun by  the Postmaster General).CP.56(30).       1.  I attach, for the consideration  of the Cabinet             an application I have received from the Broadcasting             Corporation asJcing that the existing embargo upon  the             broadcasting of controversial natter should be renoved.                  2.  The question was considered by the Cabinet on             October 27th, 1926 when the Corporation was about  to be             constituted, and the Cabinet reached iiie  following             conclusions (Cabinet 54(26) and Paper 0.?.355(26))               &quot;(a) That the Postmaster General should not include in                     the licence to the ne&quot;./ Broadcasting Corporation,                     for the x^resent, any prevision authorising then                     to permit the broadcasting of natters of                     controversy;  but that the Corporation should be                     left to do its best tc improve the existing                     broadcast programmes without such powers.                (b) That after an experimental period  of six months,                     the Postmaster General should, if necessary,                     report to the Cabinet.&quot;                  li:e licence to the Corporation provides that  the             &quot;Postmaster General nay from tine to time by notice in             writing to the Corporation require the Corporation to             refrain from sending any broadcast natter (either             particular or general) specified in such  notice&quot;,  and the             Corporation were notified to refrain from broadcasting the             following matter -                (a) statements expressing the opinion  of the Corporation                     cn natter of public policy, and                (b) speeches or lectures containing statements  of                     political, religious or industrial controversy.                  5.  I thought it best to prolong the experimental             period referred to in the Cabinet conclusions (above) and             the prohibition has now boon in force for 15 months.  It                                                                  has
 h.X3 be..-n faithfully observed by the Corporation,  but has certainly prcvok :1 a considerable volume of criticism.  It is said that the progr un:.ea as  a reault are often dull  and anaemic,  and ooniplaint is  made  that it is a mistake to  debar the public from  the educative value of hearing informed statements and speeches  on matters which are of great current importance and general  interest.      4.   There are wide  variations in the policy  of foreign countries,  but there  is  some evidence to indicate that  the Corporation are  wrong in stating that the conditions under whioh controversial subjects are admitted are  becoming  less rigorous,  and I  am informed that in Germany there has been no change.                                  t      5.   While I  think it  is important   to maintain the existing  ban&apos; upon what are known as &quot;Editorials&quot;,  i.e., statements  expressing the  opinion of the Corporation itself,  I  personally should  be  glad to  see seme relaxation of  the general prohibition against controversy.   I adhere  to my view  that  it i3 Impracticable and undesirable  to  institute any form  of  Government censorship,  and  it must be  left  to the Corporation to  secure  impartiality  and  to  select  with oare  and discrimination  the subjects  which  should be broadcast  and the manner of treating them.   The Corporation will  always have  the  knowledge that  any serious blundermight result in a public outcry  which would probably  lead to  the embargo being  reimposed.      6.  The Cabinet may probably take  the  view that  if the controversy  &quot;ba/f&quot; i3  to be  removed,,  suoh removal ought to  prooeed by stages  and I  therefore  recomr.end that for the present permission should be given  to broadcast                                           p r ear r ranged
(Intld)   W.  M-T.GENERAL POST OFFICE.-    10th February,  1920.O        prearranged debatea without restriction cf subject, while        maintaining the existing batf upon single speeches, lectures,        etc.  This would enable public feeling to be tested in the        matter and would go seme way towards satisfying the demands        which are made.  At the same time this course would not be        open to the meat formidable objection which is levied at the        general admission of controversial speeches, namely, that if        a policy obnoxious tc certain sections of listeners be        broadcast, the broadcasting of a reply seme days or weeks        later does not repair the damage.
 THE BRITISH BROADCASTING CORPORATION             SAYOY HILL, LONDON, W.C.2.                                   l6th January, 1928.The Secretary,   General Post office,          iJoC * 1 sSir,     In adhering to the terms cf your letter of11th January 1927, which directed the Corporation to exclude frcan programmes religious, political or industrialcontroversy- the Corporation has been aware that it is notonly falling behind enlightened practice in other countries,but that it is also attracting a growing volume ofsubstantiated criticism frcm its listeners0     You will reca.ll that the Postmaster-General, whennotifying the Corporation that such restrictions -would be imposed, indicated that the question would be.* further considered by the Government when the Corporation was in aposition to make representations based upon practicalexperienceo  With the experience of the year&apos;3 workingbehind them the Corporation feel that the matter should now be reviewed,     It has been remarked that one of the reasons for thechange in Constitution was that a greater degree ofresponsibility might be vested in the directing body,,    &quot;In the Report of the Broadcasting Committee (1925)there is a recommendation that,  given guarantees of equalityand x^air treatment, a moderate amount of controversy shouldbe allowed, and it was suggested that the discretion of the hew authority should be upheld provided it be strong and impartial,  able to assess the nature and                                               extent
extent of the demand, and to act with, firm and consistentoiroiauopeotion.  The Corporation now desires permission to implement this policy based on experience both In thiscountry and abroad.     With regard to experience abroad, that of germany is most significant.  Ultimate Government control is secured by an elaborate structure of checks and balanceswhich are at any rate no more effective than the comparatively simple constitution of the Corporation.Controversial subjects are not only permitted but areencouragedo  The Berlin programmes in the last year or socomprise talks on many acutely controversial subjects, suchas     Views of European Socialist Leaders in Germany     Pietism and Educational Reform     &quot;Fordism&quot; and Industry     Monopoly and Competition in Relation to Prices     Pacts and principles in World Politics     The Dawes Agreement     L[a3ses and their Leaders     Population Policy     The Standpoint of the Churches to Cultural          Problems of To-day.                )     In other countries conditions are so different thatcomparison is not apposite.  It 32iould be noted, however,that controversial matter is permitted to an increasingdegree in almost every caser  In Italy and Russia thenational broadcasting systems are employed for politicaland cultural propaganda.  In the United States of Americathere is almost complete freedom.  In Hollandbroadcasting stations are regularly rented by differentreligious organisations for purposes of propaganda.  Inthe Eritish Dominions broadcasting is not suffioientlyco-ordinated as a public service to afford a usefulprecedent, but current controversy is included,,  Itappears from universal experience that the broadcaster                                              himself
himself is  the most competent oensor of  the fore and extentof controversial natter, and ttiat even where government control i3  30 remote and loose as to be  almost negligible,the self-interest or senoe of responsibility of thebroadoaster require that controversy should be prudentlyand taotfully introduced.     During the past year v;ell-lnfomed  and constructivecritics of  B,B.C, progr?.mr.e3 have deplored tho devitalisinginfluence of the absence of controversy.   On mostproblems of immediate interest the service is 3ilent, andif controversial subjects are broached at all it is donein a halting, inconclusive and even platitudinous manner.The application of the present policy involves the neglectof many opportunities cf informing public opinion on matters of vital importance.     If the corporation were permitted to introducecontroversy it is obvious that both the  choice and thetreatment of subject would necessitate most-1 carefulconsideration.  There could be no expression of viewscontrary to the interests of the State,  or on subjectslikely to offend religious or moral susceptibilities.Subjects would require to be presented In such a way as toensure adequate safeguards for impartiality and equality of opportunity.     The Eoard of Governors desires me to say that thisapplication is submitted after careful deliberation, theresponsibility and delicacy of the matter being fully realised.  The Corporation is satisfied that the extensionof the discretionary power, envisaged in the Report ofLord Crawford&apos;s Committee,  is  a natural and logicaldevelopment of the service, that opportunities are atpresent missed,  that the  power would not be misused,  that                                                       no
no partisanship would be shown, and that any newcontroversial matter weali be introduced gradually ande:-:p e r in en t al 1 y *     A recorsmendation on the subject, passed bySir Henry Eacow&apos;s Committee for Enquiry into the Relationcf Iroadca. tin.; and Adult Education, is attached.                      I am, Sir,                        Your obedient Servant,                 for TEE BRITISH BROADCASTING CORPORATION.                            JoCcV/. REIuH                                Director-General.
     That the committee, having in the course of its deliberations had occasion to discuss the question of controversy in Adult Educational Broadcasting, considers that the present ban cn controversy militates seriouslyagainst the effectiveness of broadcast education, andbelieves it to be of paramount importance that thegreatest possible measure of liberty should be granted  tothe B.Z.C., subject naturally to tiiat liberty beinghandled with the utmost discretion as regards both the choice of subjects and the impartiality of their treatment.( signed on behalf of the Committee)         W.H.  HADOV7.              Chairman.                 CGlf EtTTES.Sir U.E. Eadcw  (Vice Chiuicellor, Sheffield University).Professor W.G.S. Adorns (Gladstone Professor of Political     Theory and Institutions, Oxford).Ilr. E. Salter Davies (Director of Education for Kent).Capt. L.F. Ellis, D.S.C.,iI.C., (Rural Community Councils)Hr. G.K. Gater, C.II.G. ,De S.0. , (Education Off icer,London     County Council).Kiss Grace Endow (National Federation of V7oments     Institutes).Colonel J.E. Hitchell, 0.E.E.,M.G(Secretary Carnegie     United Kingdom Trust)Professor R. Peers (Department of Adult Education,     University College,  Nottingham).Hr. Arthur Pugh (General Secretary of the Iron and Steel     Trades Confederation and the British Iron Steel     and Kindred Trades Association).The Hon. Oliver Stanley,  II.P., (Parliamentary Private     Secretary to the President of the Eoard of     Education).

</content>
</cab>
