<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 27-34</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[Thfa Document is iht Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. JPrinted for theCabinet.  February 1921.SECRET.3CP. 2602.CABINET.SPECIAL WEEKLY REPORT ONUNEMPLOYMENT.No. 17.WEEK ENDED FEBRUARY 11, 1921.T. J. MACNAMARA,Ministry of Labour.
I. NOTE ON UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION IN UNITED KINGDOM ONFEBRUARY 11, 1921.The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent. The average for the ten years prior to the war, according to Trade Union unem-ployment figures, was 4-7 per cent.  It was as high as 7-8 per cent, in 1908 and 7-7 per cent, in 1909.Throughout 1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent, in September and 3-2 per cent, in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.The figures for 1920 are :- &apos; Per cent.To the end of-January February March April May June July August September October November December2-9 1-6 11 0-9 1-1 1-2 14 1-6 2-9 5-3 3-7 61Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges.	1920.										Avg. 27.	Sept. 24.	Oct. 8.	Oct. 15.		Nov. 12.	Nov. 19.	Nov. 26.	Dec. 3.	Dec. 10.Men 					CD					Civilians	86,476	73,644	82,609	85,451	u	134,868	129,222	126,877	137,222	148,391Ex-service ..	142,600	178,488	186,711	190,136		239,816	246,323	251,407	263,553	265,489Boys	17,608	16,226	17,004	17,135		21,872	21,579	20,754	21,379	21,885Women	58,982	61,149	68,922	74,416	o o	97,964	100,437	103,420	119,886	131,328Girls	17480	17,135	18,034	18,216		22,2^7	22,590	21,950	23,663	23,981Totals ..	818,096	346,642	373,280	385,354		516,757	520,151	524,408	565,703	591,074	1920.			1921.						Dec. 17.	Dec. 23.	Dec. 31.	Jan. 7.	Jan. 14.	Jan. 21.	Jan. 28.	Feb. 4.	Men  Civilians Ex-service . -Boys Women Girls	162,73^ 269,960 22,300 149,080 24,631	180,985 273,229 23,458 159,364 25,568	215,882 292,482 28,702 188,104 31,653	250,365 312,147 35,704 215,869 41,441	275,645 327,986 41,407 238,333 47,393	302,980 340,703 44,611 258,469 51,666	J 685,218* 47,758 277,759 54,585	720,567* 48,507 286,821 55,419	Totals ..	628,704	662,604	756,823	855,526	930,764	998,429	1,065,320	1,111,314	* Separate figures not yet available.
GENERAL.While unemployment has not become appreciably worse during the past week, there is at present no sign of any return to normal conditions, and hopes of a trade revival in March, which are entertained in the cotton industry, seem to have at present very little to justify them. The decision of the ship joiners to withdraw their apprentices from the shipyards will still further hamper work in this industry, and shipbuilding is now seriously affected by the continuance of this dispute. The improvement in ship repairing is, however, maintained in the South Wales ports. Slackness continues in the iron and steel industry, but a resumption of work in this trade is taking place in certain areas in South Wales. Short-time working is increasing in the cotton industry, but the position in the hosiery trade remains practically unchanged. A further slight improvement is reported in the boot and shoe industry, and enquiries are stated to be coming in more readily than has been the case for some time past. In the woollen industry very few orders are being received.&apos; Reports from agricultural centres indicate that unemployment is increasing among farm labourers through farmers objecting to paying the rate of wages laid down in the Corn Production Act. In the London area unemployment remains acute and work is very quiet at the docks.II. EMERGENCY WORK.The Prime Minister made a statement in the House of Commons on the 19th October on the proposals of the Government to provide against unemployment. He outlined schemes for employing a large number of fit ex-Service men in connection with the Housing Programme, on which negotiations with the trade unions were proceeding; and schemes for anticipating a four years&apos; programme for Arterial Roads in London and in the provinces; whilst at the same time pressing forward with the Ministry of Transports programme of road classification and maintenance grants.A further statement was made by the Minister of Labour on the 21st December, indicating that the further proposals of the Government included: a final endeavour to secure an agreement with the building trades for the admission of ex-Service men; a rapid extension of road construction schemes; the distribution by the Unemploy-ment Grants Committee, under the Chairmanship of Yiscount St. Davids, of a sum of  3,000,000 for the purpose of assisting local authorities on relief schemes other than house building and road work; and the amendment of the Unemployment Insurance Act (1920) in order to enable benefit to be paid to workpeople who had been unemployed since the Act came into operation and could not therefore qualify for benefit. It has since been agreed that the Unemployment Grants Committee shall also deal with schemes in respect of road work other than those undertaken by the Ministry of Transport.ROAD WORK PROGRAMME. (Information supplied by the Ministry of Transport.) (1.) London Arterial New Roads.No fresh Arterial Road Schemes in the London area have been notified by the Ministry of Transport since those mentioned in Report No. 16.There are now nineteen Arterial Road Schemes in the greater London area. Work has commenced on thirteen of these schemes and-the number of men employed on the 11th February was 1,107[Total men employed=1,107.][5661] B 2
(1a.) London Main Roads Maintenance.The following schemes of Main Road Maintenance in the London area have been notified by the Ministry of Transport since those mentioned in Report No. 16 : Hackney M.B.C. Gainsborough Road resurfacing. Estimated cost  5,500. Scheme under consideration.Finsbury M.B.C. Various roads paving. Estimated cost  5,525. Scheme under consideration.Main Road Maintenance schemes have now been arranged with twenty-one Local Authorities in the greater London area.[No particulars of number of men employed.](2.) Provincial Arterial New Roads.The following arterial road schemes in the provinces have been notified by the Ministry of Transport since those mentioned in Report No. 16 : Hartley, Wintney R.D.C, Widening road. Estimated cost  2,030. Grant indicated 50 per cent, and remainder loan on usual terms.Kingston upon Hull (East Riding and Hull C.B.). Widening of arterial road. Estimated cost  17,440. Grant indicated 50 per cent, and remainder loan on usual terms.Scunthorpe and Frodingham U.D.C. Construction of new road. Estimated cost  1,500. Grant indicated 50 per cent, and remainder loan on usual terms.Wellingborough U.D.C. Widening of arterial road. Estimated cost  6,000. Grant indicated 40 per cent, and remainder loan on usual terms.It is also stated that schemes are in course of preparation at Runcorn, Swansea, West Bromwich, Smethwick and Merthyr Tydfil.There are now seventy-seven areas in the provinces in which arterial road schemes have been arranged, and up to the 11th February work had actually commenced on sixty of these schemes.[Total number of men employed (including those for whom part-time employ-ment is provided^ 12,461.](2a.) Provincial Main Roads Maintenance.The following schemes of Main Road Maintenance in the provinces have been notified by the Ministry of Transport since those mentioned in Report No. 16 : 1. England and Wales.Wilts C.C. Bristol to Southampton Road (Salisbury section) resurfacing. Estimated cost  2,422. Scheme under consideration.2. Scotland.Fife (Dunfermline) D.C. Various roads, resurfacing. Estimated cost  4,256. Scheme under consideration.There are now ninety-two areas in the provinces in whicfy Main Road Mainten-ance Schemes have been proposed.[No particulars of number of men employed.]
HOUSING PROGRAMME.(3.) Housing: Progress with Sites: Lay-out of Roads and Sewers; brought forward as additional to the Main Programme.(a.) London Area.Reports have been received from 43 Local Authorities in the greater London area for week ended the 4th February with regard to the expediting of road and sewer work on housing schemes with a view to the employment of additional men.[Additional number of men employed so far as stated by returns^396.](b.) Provincial Areas.Reports have been received from 103 Local Authorities in the provinces for week ended the 4th February with regard to the expediting of road and sewer work on housing schemes with a view to the employment of additional men.[Additional number of men employed so far as stated by returns=3,082.](3 a.) Housing : Additional Progress on actual Housing Operations of LocalAuthorities since 19th October, 1920.On the 1st February there were 48,053 skilled men employed on housing schemes in England and Wales, as against 40,270 at the end of December, 37,024 at the end of November, and 32,974 at the end of October. As regards unskilled men, there were 48,710 employed on the 1st February, as against 41,093 at the end of December, 39,197 at the end of November, and 36,414 at the end of October.At the 1st February the additional labour still required for housing schemes was 11,285 skilled men (including 6,230 bricklayers, 1,734 carpenters, 1,952 plasterers) and 1,047 unskilled men.(4.) OTHER PUBLIC WORKS.Returns which have been received from forty-three Local Authorities in the greater London area and 103 Local Authorities in the provinces show that labour is being employed on schemes of relief works which are not being assisted by Govern-ment grants as follows: 	Number of Men at Work on February 1.	Additional Number not at Work for whom Employment is being provided.	Total.London area Provinces	2,033 3,709	611 3,343	2,644 7,052[Total number of men employed=9,696.(5.) Alternative Work at War Department Factories.A return rendered by the War Office in respect of the week ended the 5th February shows that alternative work was in progress at five national factories, and included waggon repairing, manufacture of medals, coin blanks, locomotives and new waggons and miscellaneous articles for the Post Office and for private firms.
(6.) VISCOUNT ST. DAVIDS&apos; COMMITTEE.In accordance with the announcement in the House of Commons on the 21st December, an Unemployment Grants Committee has been appointed under the Chairmanship of Viscount St. Davids to administer a grant of  3,000,000 which had been allocated for the purpose of assisting Local Authorities in carrying out approved schemes of useful work other than roads and housing. The restriction in regard to road work has since been removed.Works are approved only in areas where serious unemployment exists which is not otherwise provided for. Preference in employment is given to ex-Service men. Grants do not exceed 60 per cent, of the wages bill of additional unemployed men engaged, and the works undertaken are such as are approved by the appropriate Government Departments as suitable works of public utility.Up to the 11th February 103 applications for grants had been sanctioned in respect of seventy-eight Local Authorities. The total sum allocated by the Committee under these sanctions was  344,725.Returns received from 43 Local Authorities in the London area and 103 Local Authorities in the provinces show that the labour engaged on schemes for which a grant has been made is as follows : London area Number at work on the 4th February   ...        ...      1,181Additional number provided for ...        ...        834Provinces Number at work on the 4th February   ...        ...     4,468Additional number provided for ...        ...      1,834Total     8,317[Total number of men at present employed^8,317.](7.) SHORT-TIME IN GOVERNMENT ESTABLISHMENTS.The &quot; short-time &quot; system came into force on the 24th January, and took effect on that date in His Majesty&apos;s Dockyards and Admiralty Establishments and in the Royal Ordnance Factories, Woolwich Arsenal, and National Factories administered by the War Office. It will be introduced, where practicable, in all remaining War Departments, Industrial and Semi-Industrial Establishments with effect from the 7th february.The number of additional men engaged at Royal Ordnance and other Factories administered by the War Office on the 5th February was 1,457.The number of additional men engaged at His Majesty&apos;s Dockyards and other Admiralty Industrial Establishments on the 5th February was 4,619.[Total number of men engaged in Government establishments as result of adoption of short time=6,076.Alternative work has also been put in hand at His Majesty&apos;s Dockyards and other Admiralty Industrial Establishments.[Total number of workmen employed on alternative work at War Office Establishments ^ 2,703. ][Total number of workmen employed on alternative work at Admiralty Establishments=5,220.&quot;
(9.) SUMMARY OF LABOUR ENGAGED ON RELIEF SCHEMES.&apos; 1. Schemes assisted by Government grants : Arterial Roads ...        ...        ...        ...        ... 13,568Expediting of lay-outs on housing schemes ...        ... 3,478Other Public Works assisted by the unemployment grants Committee    ...        ...        ...        ... 8,317Alternative  work  at War  Office  and AdmiraltyEstablishments       ...        ...        ...        ... 7,923Adoption of short-time in War Office and AdmiraltyEstablishments       ...        ...        ...        ... 6,076Additional labour engaged by Office of Works (Emer-gency Programme)   ...&quot;      ...        ...        ... 2,6002. Public Works put in hand by Local Authorities without government grant    ...        ...        ...        ... 9,696Grand Total     51,658As reports for the week ended the 4th February have been received from only 146 Local Authorities out of 223 who were asked to supply information, it would appear that the Relief Schemes which have been inaugurated by the Government and by Local Authorities are finding employment for a number of men considerably in excess of 50,000.o(8.) OFFICE OF WORKS EMERGENCY PROGRAMME.The Office of Works have, with Treasury approval, put in hand a considerable amount of decorating and repairing work in Government Departments with a view to the absorption of unemployed painters and similar workpeople.Total number of men so employed up to the 10th February was 1,800 skilled men (90 per cent, of whom are painters or similar workmen) and 800 unskilled men.[Total additional labour engaged by the Office of Worl^2,600.]
CONFIDENTIAL,CABINET,REPORT (Noe 93) ON REVOLUTION-ARY   ORGANISATIONS IN THE UNITED kingdom*7 o 2 c 2 j.(C0P, 2303)*mi i.&apos; ik&quot;a aM     MIt is requested that this document may be treated as highly confidentiala2, Whitehall Gardens? S*Wa, 18th February. 19210-

</content>
</cab>
