<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 127-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1921.-SECRET.1EGYPT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.BY the establishment of the Protectorate over Egypt this country has been brought definitely within the circle of the British Empire. This Protectorate has been recognised by the United States, France and Belgium. It formed an integral factor in the negotiations which led up to the Treaty of Versailles. To these negotiations the Dominions were parties. It seems to me, therefore, impossible to upset this settlement in a fundamental matter of this kind without a further reference to the Dominions, such as can be made at the forthcoming meeting of&apos;the Imperial Cabinet.The fact that the Milner negotiations with the Egyptian Nationalists were made public without the King, the Cabinet, Parliament or the Dominions being consulted cannot abrogate their constitutional rights. Lord Milner has repeatedly stated that our freedom is wholly unimpaired. In these circumstances I strongly deprecate any alteration of the existing status of Egypt until after the matter has been considered by the Imperial Cabinet in June. It may well be that thereafter some better expression than the word &quot; Protectorate &quot; can be found, but the reasons for taking the Dominions into consultation seem to me to be of a binding nature. When the Prime Minister, during the debate on the Address, used language which indicated the importance which he attached to consultation with the Dominions, the immediate approval of all parts of the House, except the Labour benches, was manifest.In my view, we should say in effect to the Egyptians :  .&quot; We do not close any doors at the present time. On the contrary, we recognise that the Protectorate is not the best form in which our relationship should be expressed. We are not, however, prepared to take any steps to alter the status of Egypt as fixed at present, except in consultation with the self-governing Dominions of the British Empire. The Imperial Cabinet will meet in June, and we shall be very glad to receive about that time official or unofficial delegations from Egypt, and to enter into frank and full discussion with them with a view to a prompt and final decision.&quot;This is a position which we can certainly maintain both here and in Egypt, if we adopt it firmly and make it quite clear that we are not going to be hustled or wheedled out of it.w. s. c.Colonial Office, February 17, 1921.[56701

</content>
</cab>
