<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 445-445</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.]SECRET.CABINET.SOUTH KURDISTAN.Memorandcjm by the Secretary of State por the Colonies.I CIRCULATE a private letter from South Kurdistan, which has been put in my bands by its recipient.   It is a cheerful picture.w. s. c.Colonial Office, February 26, 1921.Sulaimani, South Kurdistan. This is rather a gloomy letter, but times here are not very cheerful. I will try and sum up the situation in a few words. The taxpayer will no longer pay for the cost of this country or rather Mesopotamia. The country having accepted the mandate from the League of Nations, Government is now trying to find a loophole so as to get out of it and withdraw the garrison. How will they do this ? They have devised the following : We are to erect a mock Arab Government, which Sir Percy Cox and everybody else knows will be a failure and cannot live. Never mind, it is hoped that the wind will not blow over this flimsy erection before we have had time to with-draw. It will then collapse, and the country will fall into such a state of anarchy as has never been seen before. It is quite the most disgraceful thing a civilised country has ever done. It is not as if they had asked for it, their only cry is, &quot; You have delivered us from the Turk, you are surely not going to hand us over to the Arab.&quot; We have destroyed all they had in the way of government, law and order, and we leave them saying, &quot; You are now a free nation, test du joli!&quot; Wait, this is not all. There is a far greater danger which is looming ahead the Bolshevik. He has made an agreement with the Kemalists, and they propose advancing into this country and Irak next spring. The Kemalists from the north, Bolsheviks through Persia, and here Bolshevik propaganda and money is inundating the country now. What are we&apos; going to do? Nobody knows, nothing is decided, nothing is being done. It seems as if home Government would like to be out of it before, but they cant, it is out of the question. They will probably end up by evacuating Persia and Mosul in a hurry and falling back on Bagdad. Bolshevik money is being spent freely to raise, a holy war in Central Arabia and on the eastern side of the Euphrates. On the whole the sky is dark and menacing.Now from our point of view, South Kurdistan. How are we to erect this plaster building ? We are well out of the military cordon, we have no troops to support us or to fall back on. The moment we let the local inhabitant know what our intentions are he will turn on us and cut our throats. My levy, which is now 500 strong, is loyal for the moment; but it has only sworn to serve the British Government and no other. If we let them down I cannot answer for them either. If the Bolsheviks or Kemalists come this way the whole country will go up. They will always favour the strongest, and anyway at heart they are all Kemalists. People in London and Bagdad will not realise this, or do not wish to. What are we doing it all for ? In the event of our getting out of it with our lives, to get the sack, good government having no more use for us. Bagdad is now being run by a woman and an arriviste, Miss Bell and Philby. Sir Percy Cox has no illusions on the subject. Home Government are at sea, and know nothing about this part of the world.[5728]

</content>
</cab>
