<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 492-498</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Circulated by the Chief Seoretary for Ireland).I submit for the consideration of the Cabinet my survey for the week ended the 28th ultimo.* vGENSBAD STATE UP THE OQuTTOY, Statistics of Outrages.The total number of outrages reported for the wooie is appreciably lower than that for the previous week, but the*deoreaeo; is only in the leas serious forms of outrages and unfortunately oannot be taken as indicating a general improvement.      Attacks on the armed forces of the Crown have become more frequent, and I regret to state that the area of active lawlessness is extending to counties which have hitherto been comparatively free from the more violent kinds of crime, notably County Donegal which is now removed from the small list of Counties in which no murders of polioe or military have yet taken piece.      The list of these Counties is now reduced to three, viz: Leitrim, queen s and Wioklow.The number of attacks on tho Crown forces for the week was 19, an increase of 3 on last week*s total, and the number of casualties inoreasod from 11 to 32*    Tho most importantenoountor with the rebel foroe3 during the week took plaoo on the 25th ultimo, between Ballyvourney and Maoroom in Co. Cork.      A party of police, composed of 76 Auxiliaries and 7 regular Constabulary were attaokeu by a body of rebelsS E Q, R. E T,mmmmm^mmmmmmimmmmmmmmmmmC.P.-26U.CABINET.SURVEY OF THE STATE OF IRELAND FOR WJIEK
ostimatod at 300 who wero strongly entrenched in the hills overlooking tho scene of the ambush and appeared to bo well supplied with firearms of various Kinds, including maohino guns.    After an engagement lasting about two hours military reinforoements arrived and the rebels withdrew but owing to the nature of tho oountry it was not possiblo for tho Grown forces to make an effective pursuit.     Tho officer commanding the Auxiliary Company was killod at the commencement of tho attaok and five oadets and two of the ro^ular police wore wounded, one of the latter mortally,      Two ambushes of polioe occur rod in County jonegal on tho  2nd ultimo, one near tho town of $onogal, Ballyshannon District, and tho other near MountCharles.      A oonstable was killed in each of these attacks^A sinister feature of the weok*s outrages is the number of oold-blooded assassinations of individual members of the Crown forces.    Ho less than ten such murders were committed during the week to the 26th ultimo0   five of the victims, boing police, and five military, and another five soldiers wore assassinated on the 28th ultimo, presumably as a reprisal for the execution of a number of rebels earlier on that day. With the exception of two of the police all the murdered men were killed while unarmed and in the case of five of the soldiers after having been taken prisoners.     In addition to these murders two civilians were assassinated on the ground of their alleged communication with tho police or military authorities.Three attaoks on occupied Polioe Barracks took place during the week (Ballybunion, Co. Kerry, and Golden and Dundrum, Co. Tipperary).      The attaok in oaoh case was beaten off without difficulty and with no oasualties to tho Polico.Raids on mails fell from 54 to 22 and raids for arms from 6 to,3.     Only one raid on the office of a rate collector
was reported, tho amount stolen Doing  53.Arroats for outrages or political offancos number3d 26 for the week.     Those figures do not include tho vary considerable number of -oorsons arrested and temporarily detained in military custody. Trials of civilian a bj^ Court MartialoSeventy-five trials of civilians by Court Martial took place during the week and resulted in sixty-throe convictions and twelvo acquittals.     Tho sontohoes imposed were as shown in the following summary;13 Sentences of penal sorvitudo   (3 years to 5 years)24       &quot;        &quot; imprisonment withhard labour. (28 days to 2 years)13       11       &quot; Imprisonmont with-out hard labour    (15 days to 2 yoars)1 sentence of Detention undo? penal discipline in aBorstal Institution for 3 years.8 Fines, 2. to  5.)1 Fine of  10. and forfeiture of blasting powder holdwithout a permit010TAL &quot;&quot;s3In one case the accused was bound over in his own recognizances to keep the peace and in another the sentenco was remitted by the Confirming Officer.    Tho remaining case was that of a Juvenile female offender, agod 13 years. Who was found in possession of a parcel containing a Lewis gun. 3 revolvers and a quantity of ammunition, and was sentenced . to detention in a itoman Catholic Female Reformatory until she attains the age of 19.    Pour of the trials Wore those of members of tho Hoyal Irish Constabulary who wore accused of larceny.    Two were found guilty and sentenced to imprisonment. The other two wore acquitted.    With the exception of these oases all the trials were for offences connected with the
present disturbed state of the oountry. Internment Orders.136 Internment Orders were made during the week, bringing the total numbor Df persons now interned to 2,120.3TASK 0? TEE) POLICE FORCES.Reoruiting for tho Royal Irish Constabulary resulted in a net increase of 79 in tho strength of tho Regular Force, and a not increase of 16 in that of the Auxiliary Division.     The number of resignations from the regular Constabulary fell from 71 to 47.    Brig.-aen. Crozior resigned from the command of the Auxiliary Division on the 22nd ultimo in circumstances which have since been made public and his place is being filled by Brig.-Gen.  .A.Wood, CM.&amp;., D.S.O.The following are the usual particulars of wastage and recruiting for the week: Regular Force..Strength on 80th February, 1921 ..................... 13,920Deaths during week...................... 5Retirements............................. 6Resignations............................ 47Dismissals or Dischargas ................ 6Total Wastage64Recruits.Ireland ... Gt. Britain22 121143Net increase79Strength on 27th February, 192113,999Auxiliary Division.Strength on 20th February, 19211,445Recruits29Resignations.............    7Discharged medically unfit - 1 Struck off.................    513Net increase16Strength on 27th February, 19211,461
The following are the corresponding- particulars forthe Dublin Metropolitan Polioe.Strength on 19th February, 19&amp;1.................1,123Rrt iremo nts........,............1Robignati ons................    1^Recruits......................*ljilNet decrease..............................._2^Strength on 26th February, 1921 ...............1,121IMPORTANT KINGrTS gggtg DJ^ISIOH V/I !IH INSPECT W FTOS OFMILITARY COURTS *An important judgement was delivered during the week by the Court of  ing&apos;s Bench in the case of Rex v. John Allen, a prisoner lying -under sentence of death imposed by a Military Court for the illegal possession of arms and ammunition.   The sentence was imposed in accordance with a proclamation of the Commander in Chief which required that all civilians within the Martial Law Area should surrender thoir arms and ammunition by the 27th Decembor, last, and announced that all each persons found in possession of arms and ammunition or explosives after that date would be liable on conviction by a Military Court to suffer the penalty of death.   The prisonerrs application was for writs of prohibition and habeas corpus directing the Commander in Chief not to confirm or permit the carrying out of the capital sentence, and it was argued on his behalf that the infliotion of the capital penalty for an offence not punishable by death at Commop/law or by Statute was outside the powers of the Commaaier in Chief, and that the appropriate punishment for the illegal possession of arms was prescribed by. the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act, 1920, and the Regula-tions made thereiuider, and by the provisions of the Firearms Act, 1920.    The appeal&apos;was dismissed by the Oourt, whioh
held unanimously that a state of actual rebellion at present exists in Ireland in the Martial Law Area, and that while this state continues the Civil Courts have no jurisdiction to inter fore with any action taken by the Commander in Chief for the purpose of quolling the insurrection and restoring order.(Intd)..    H.G.Irish Office, S.W. March 5th, 1921.
Statement showing Total Number of Serious Outrages from 1st January 193-9 to 22nd January 1921. Weekly totals to week ended 26th February, 1921 and Totals at that date.	Totals from		WEEK ENUT2P	*			Totals1SATUKS OF OUTRAGE.	1st Jan.1919 to 22nd Jan. 1920.	29th Jan. 1921.	5th Feb. 1921.	12th Feb. 1921.	19th Feb. 1921.	26th Feb. 1921.	to 26th Feb.1921.Courthouses destroyed		1	-	-	1	-	_ii_T?-T.n. Vacated Barracks destroyed	512	-	-	-	-	-	-    512K.I.C. Vacated Barracks damaged	119	-	-	-	1	-	120R.I.C. Occupied Barracks  clesfcroyed	23	-	-	1	-	-	24R.I.C. Occupied Barracks damaged			3	2	4	3	Raids on Mails	1,114	14		13	54	22	Raids on Coastguard Stations and Lighthouses					2		Raids for Arms	3.00tf	6	27	6	6	-	3,0^5Raids on Rate Collectors Offices	23	-	-		1	1	50Policemen killed	200 /	4	20	2 6	2	10	23bPolicemen Wounded	^10 j6	14	12	11 /5	3	_17	367Policemen Fired at etc.	not recorded	7	10	7	6	4	-Soldiers Hilled	54	2	1	1	-	k ^-	Soldiers Wounded	127	13	3	-   7	6		156Soldiers Fired at e&quot;fec*	not recorded	3	5	6	3	3	X Civilians Killed	45	3	6	4	7	2	Civilians Wounded	110	1	3	-	1	1	lloTOT A	L3      5,840	76	107	85	97	71	6.222Arrests for Outrages or Political *                                  Offences	-	113	101	125	81	26	-X   These figures do not include casualties in Ulster Riots during period June - September, 1920: 23    Civilian deaths occurred in Londonderry riots and 62 in Belfast riots during that period:lUB.    The above particulars do not include outrages of a kind which are not now being committed e.g. 119 raids on revenue Offices which occurred during months of April and May and resulted in the destruction of many sofficial documents and much other public property.    Minor forms of outrages (e.g. intimidation,  cattle- -driving, etc.) are also not included.COp      These figures in each case include one Special Constable. CJlCZ5

</content>
</cab>
