<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 553-575</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS D0CUM3HT IS tHE PROPERTY 03? HIS 3RITAK1TI0 MAJESTY S GOYERlIIffiliT,)COIfflDExlTIAL. Copy NoCABIiUilT,^0. P. 2679.(a,j, 273)ISilV^IgS BY GEgHyg Og REPARATION account TO DECEMBER 31st, 1920,I   U . ..    iMMMW in mm m   urn   mi 11    11M i h      II    I-----Tl-- i&apos;t---------Nw m wtniniiii^ii I IiThe accompanying statements prepared &quot;by the Reparation Commission showing:-(a) Deliveries by Germany on Reparation Account toDecember 3let, 1920;(b) Deliveries during the montfc cf December, 1920, and(c) Deliveries and payments in connection with Article235 of the Treaty of Versailles,are circulated for information in connection with the present series of meetings of the Allied Conference with the German Delegation, in regard to   Reparation.(Signed) H* P. A. HAMEY.secretary i Cabinet,2 Whitehall Gardens, 8.W.I. March 7th, 1921.
REPARATION COMMISSIONANNEX No 452/4..*.c,Approximate Statements by the Accounting Service of by Germany on Reparation Account.a Cumulative Statement of Deliveries to 31st December 1920b Monthly Statement of Deliveries during December 1920 andlc Approximate Return in connection with Article 235.Note. Detailed schedules   Annex 452/4 d   issued in Ronct
INNEX No 452/4.. 6. c.Statements by the Accounting Service of Deliveries by Germany on Reparation Account.t of Deliveries to 31st December 1920 and Distribution thereof.Deliveries during December 1920 and Distribution thereof, in connection with Article 235.!e. Detailed schedules   Annex 452/4 d   issued in Roueo.
Statement No. 1.1.1 AH LATIYi; TOTALS TO 3lSt DEGKMUER IQ20,APPROXIMATE STA&apos;1No.0 10 :&quot;)n 0a 7a 8 0 &apos;.) o 10 1111 o ! 2 0 I.&apos;; o 14 0 15 0/0 17 18 (.19 o20 21 22 23 o24 a 25 20o27 o28. 20 30o3J32 33 34 35 303738 3940 41 42 43 4445 40 47ARTICLE \ND ANNEXof 1&apos;eace treaty ami\umistick AGREEMENTS.Art. 109. Idem. Idem.Purl. VII, Art, 230 and Annex IIIIdem.[dan.Idem.Idem. Annex III. Annex I \.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem,Idem.[dim,Idem.Idem. -Annex V.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem. Annex VI.Idem.Part. VIII. Art. 244. Annex VII.Art. VIII. Idem. Idem. Idem.Art. 111.Art. 45-50. Art. 134.Idem. Art. 145, Art. 150 of Clause 2. Protocol 28 June 1919. Part. VIII. Art. 247.&quot;Arl. 32 -39. Art. 80. Art. 92.Arl. 99, Arl. 108. Arl. 109-114.Arl. 250. Idem, Idem. Idem.DELIVERIES,A. REPARATION IN KIND. Peace Treaty.Converted War Material sold by B. L. M. (i. :     Aeronautical........Military...........sold prior to B. L- M. G.Ships Steamers 1,000 G. T. and over.........- between 1,000-1.599 &apos;(!. T.....  Sailing Vessels 1,000 (i. T. and over. ....- &apos;    between 1,000-1,599 G. T.....  Fishing Vessels.......................No.383 38 9 240G. tv1,970,938, 48,710. 22,199.3,120.9,749.Inland Navigation Boats and Material (120 Barges).Livestock.   Horses............Cattle.............Sheep............ .- Goats.... v........Poultry..........Agricultural Material (See Item 31 Seeds........................Cement and kindred material................................................................. Glass Cylinders lor Miners&apos; Salaty Lamps,................&apos;.................................Goal delivered 1st September 1919 to 3 isl July 1920 (Converted tonnage).&apos;...........................- taken in charge by Allies at Posts of Control isI August to 31st December 1920 (Canverted tonnage)... Bv-Producls of Coal - Benzol................................................................         Coal Tar..............................................................-        Sulphate of Ammonia..................................................i-Dyeslufls............................................................1.............. v.&apos;,..Pharmaceutical Products.............................,.....................................Submarine Cables........................................................................Armistice Agreement of 11th November 1918.Rolling Stock.   Locomotives................................................  Wagons...................................................Fixed Railway Material (Including Sign.aU Shop and Permanent Way Material),,.Motor Lorries..................................................c.....Armistice Convention of 16th January 1919.Agricultural MaterialB. OTHER PROPERTY. RIGHTS, CONCESSIONS AND INTERESTS.Peace Treaty.Goal Mines situated in Saar Basin.................German school in French Concession at Shanghai......Properly in British Concession at Shameen..........Germany^ portion of capital of Stale Bank of Morocco, Properly in Kiaochow...........................Deliveries of Books, etc., 011 account of Louvain Library...............................Art. 254. -- Portion of German Imperial and Stale Debts to be assumed on account of former German territory, viz :By Belgium in respect 6t&quot;Mbfesnet&apos;,  upon and Malmedy...............................By Czccho-Slovakia in respect of Silesia.............................................By Poland in respect of Posen, Eastern Prussia, Allenstcin and Upper Silesia :(a) Territory in Ceded Area.................................................[b] Territory in Plebiscite Area..............................................By Memo].......____.........................................................By Free City of Danlzig .........................................................By Denmark in respect of Sebleswig................................................German Imperial and Slate properly informer German territories ceded to :Czecho-Slovakia...............................................................Poland (o) Ceded Area...........................................................-   (/j) Plebiscite Area........................................................MemelQUANTI	2tT. No.	No.	No.	No.	No.	No.	Kg,	0,	*\No.	M. T.	8,M. T.	9,M. T.	Kg.,	io,:	No. No. Tons. No.No.Shares
APPROXIMATE STATEMENT OF DELIVERIES AND    DISTRIBUTION THEREOF AS AT 31s( kliND.;40G. iv,970,938, 48,710. 22,190. 3,120. 9.749.QUANTITY.ESTIMATED VALUE.G,T.   2,054,728rled tonnage).........................to 3isl December 1920 (Csii verted tonnage).T.No.No.No.No.No.No.Kg.No. M. T. M. T.38,710 38,045 133,221 130,759 ... 17,488 34,970 2,362 0,801,310 //20,000 8,520,327 9,319,505 //i November 1918.Ml Way Material).th January 1919.CESSIONS AND INTERESTS.Stale Debts to be assumed on account Hory, viz :tnd Upper Silesia :M. T.      19,729 Kg.  ,10,787,827, Kg.        57,823 11No. No. ions. No.No.4,506 127,352 80,000 5,000130,549Shares11 11 112,200 11iciir German territories ceded tohistict// // 1111011 11 11 lnational currencies.P. M. P. iM. P. M.F.P. JVI.p. to,P, M.P. M. P. M.51,960,092 37,030 9,750,00031,430,000926,000 60,000 3,435,317,180 2,985,708,285 // // //275,648,348 7,581,394P. M. Bel. Frs,3,600,000117,044,786 19,099,039&apos; 1,870,000// // 11111111 11 11COLD MARKS.3,449,070 2,502 503,974494,393,9721,355,000 32,782,092 43,782,181 4,872,429 335,102 113,052 453.420 1,733,871 231,500 4,400 260,380.179 226,302,032 // //4,734,978 21,774,400 &quot;570,730 49*000,000410,939,820 618,408,11872,648,000 19,011,610550,000,000 3,000,000 700,000212,000000,000 &quot;290,00017,392,000580,000 5,109,000 2,000,00003,000,000tBASED ON ESTIMATESNo.GERMAN figure a(See Remark B.)4i 5 6 78)9i 10 *12 \ 13 14 15 10 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 2631,000,000 * 563,974 /3,247,000,0001,355,000 /237,500,000 *Included in item 31 * 1,733,871 / 231,500/ &apos;  4,400/ 380,000,000 * 425,000,000 *4,040,000/ 21,774,400 * 570,736/ 85,418,979 *571,000,000 * 946,000,000 * //Probably in No 50.29,000,000 *1,050,947,000 * 3,000,000/ 700,000/212,000/600,000/ 290,000/17,392,000/580,000/ 5,169,000/ 2,000,000/10,000,000*3.033,000,000 *232,000,000 * 514,000,000 * ^03,000,000/ipo,ooo,ooo *UNDISTRIBUTEDorINFORMATION NOT AVAILABLE.3,449,070 2,502 563,97477,502,656**n 11 11HII49,000,0003,000,00011600,000 290,00017,392,000580,000 5,169,000 2,000,00011Kii I63,000,00011UNITED STATES.111 u11H H H HII II H Kii1,334,89519,091,89511t.u 0
REPARATION COMMISSION.accounting service.ANNEX No 452/4*IftlBDTION THEREOF AS AT 31 si DECEMBER 1920 MADE BY GERMANY ON REPARATION ACCOUNTBASED ON ESTIMATES AND IN CERTAIN CASES ON FIGURES AUDITED AND BROUGHT TO ACCOUNT.UNDISTRIBUTED or INFORMATION NOT AVAILABLE.	UNITED STATES.	GREAT BRITAIN.	FRANCE.	ITALY.	RELG1UM.	JAPAN.3/149,070	u	a		//	//	02,502	a	a	a	0	0	0563,974	ii	a	a	ii	i	077,502,656	u	355,003,197	40,100,758	ii	3,805,934	0,888,426//	ii		1,355,000	0	*	u	ii	*	27,153,870	ii	5,628,822	0ii	i		24,291,930	a	19,490,251	0ii	u		3,501,746	ii	1,310,683	0ii	u	*	178,799	0	150,303	00	ii		//	0	113,652	0ii	0	*	//	a	453,420	0ii	ii	//	1,65^,386	0	70,485	a0	ii	ii	231,500	ii	*	ii	n	ii	4,400	ii	//	iiii	ii	ii	235,729,823	18,076,906	0,573,450	iiii	ii	n	106,285,311	29,745,412	19,259,070	aii	0	0	ii	//	//	00	ii		ii	//	i	0ii	ii	//	4,734,978	//	0	ii.ii	1,334,895	5,658,521	8,715,518	3,118,818	2,029,754	916,894ii	a	ii	//	378,573	137,567	54,59649,000,000	0	0	//	//	//	n	n	0	243,209,880	0	167,729,940	//ii	ii	ii	325,240,350	ii	293,107,768	0ii	ii	ii		0		0u	19,091,895	18,045,763	31,965,120	e	3,545,222	iiii	H	ii	10,888,514	0	2,723,102	i.a	0	n	550,000,000	0	0	* -3,000,000	ii		i	0	u	0//	ii		706,000	0	0	0	ii	i	n	0	ii	0&apos;ii	ii	i	0	0	212,000	n600,000	h               *	0	i	a	0	0290,000	)	n	ii	0	ii	0.17,392,000	a	H	n	0	ii	ii580,000	i	ii	i	0	0	t 05,109,000	0 &apos;	0	0	0	ii	02,000,000	*..&apos;	0	*	0	ii	0//		ii	0	ii		ii		ii	0	ii	0	h		0	ii	ii	a	0ii	*	1	0		i	II	//	//	ii		0	ii63,000,000	t	*	0		0	n//	ii		ii		n	0MAN FIGURE.% Remark B.31,000,000 * 563,974 /7,000,000 * 1,355,000/ 7,500,000 *ta in item 31 * 11,733,871 / 231,500/ &apos; 4,400/ 10,000,000 * 5,000,000 *^4,040,000/ ijl,774,400 * \ 570,736/ 15,418,979 *&apos;1,000,000 * [0,000,000 * //ibly in No 50. ; 19,000,000 *15,947,000 * 3,000,000/ I 700,000/212,000/600,000/ 290,000/J.302,000/580,000/ 5,109,000/ 2,000,000/10,000,000 *.3,000,000 *2,000,000* $,000,000 * 3,000,000/ 10,000,000 *LUXEMBOURG.0 iii 0 ii 0 0 0 ii 011,012,239 0t0 000h Ii 0iiII
ION.NY ON REPARATION ACCOUNT UNDER TREATY OF VERSAILLES AND ARMISTICE AGREEMENTSITED AND BROUGHT TO ACCOUNT.BELGIUM.3,805,9345,028,822 19,490,251 1,310,683 156,303 113,652 453,420 76,485 * //6,573,450 19,259,070 n i u2,029,754 137,567ii167,729,940 293,167,768ii3,545,222 2,723,102212,000JAPAN.6,888,426ii i a t i u IH III.916,894 54,596 iLUXEMBOURG.11,012,239 uOTHER ALLIED andASSOCIATED POWERS.No.10,427,001(Greece.)38 39( 40 41 42 434446A. The period for certain Gold Mark conversions is arbitrary pending determination of method.B. In the column headed &quot;German Figure&quot; the sign * indicates latest German valuation, which uiu14 milliard as shewn herein is accounted for largely by an item of 4 milliard for ships. 20 Figure&apos;, column may be totalled, the Reparation Commission iigure indicated by / has been1-32	1-2*3	3* 4-8* 4	* 5 * 6	4-8** 7	* 8 * 9	9* 10 * 11	10-14* 12	* 13	* 14	15* 15 * 16 17	16 19-2018	* 19	*20	21	22	23	*24	*25	26	*27	*28	19-20*29 *30	21-22 23 24-25*31	24-25* 26 27-2832	27-28*33	34	2935	36	3037	313233-34 35FiguNo figure available for total value of unsold material in the hands of the B. L. M. G,   rigi costs to 3ist December 1920 (including 13 &apos;j0 commission to R. T. h. G. on sales since payment of P. M. 10,000,000 by the R. T. H. G. to account of pre B. L. M.&apos;G. sales, k all have been remitted to Paris and London in equal parts, with which have been puG. M. 31,000,000 (P. M, 500.000,000) apparently purports to be value of material turneGerman give an estimate of P M. 1,000,000,000 which apparently purports to be value 0Tonnage and estimated value supplied by Maritime Service with the following note :   &quot; nage, and will require adjustment in due course in accordance with the values to be &quot;S. S. Bismarck&quot; (G. T. 56,000) allotted to Great Britain.   Olhcial rate of 10th JanuarAccording to latest German information, 1,001 ships (G. T. 4,625,718), said to&quot; have beer and yet to be surrendered, are valued at G. M. 7,3i0,302,824, representi,\g approximately this valuation to the tonnage shown as actually delivered opposite.   This results in a the Bureau of Inland Water Craft states that these figures do not include a number of c as to whether or not a credit will be given to Germany on account thereof.Unaudited actual quantities assembled by Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden, including diseas In accordance with provisions of Protocol B-64. dated 9 September 1919, and its subs hoof and mouth disease appear, from 10 0/0 ail(&apos; 20 &quot;j0 on the value of animals developi Unaudited actual quantities assembled by the Accounting Officer. Wiesbaden.   Unit value Audited quantities supplied by Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden.   Prices arc those actually^Converted tonnage figures include Coke at 3 tons actual equals 4 tons elleclive. Item 19 Essen (actual tonnage 8,504,827). Tonnage delivered to Luxembourg in excess of he tbe Mines from  1st August 1920 to 3ist December 1920. - M. T. 9,596,856.Basis of valuations is :i. For coal delivered for sea shipment via Ports of Rotterdam and xVntii. For coal, coke and lignite delivered by rail or water   pit head pri Hi. Transport costs included to Frontier stations only, based on the ave iv. AH deliveries on account of reparation prior 3oth April 1920 hDecember 1920.The above valuation works out to an average unit price of G. M. 30.23 on actual and G. M other than sea borne.A minimum valuation showing a reduction of G. M. 174,472,452 on items 19 and 20 hathe basis of ii, iii and iv (see Schedule 6 in roneoed Annex 452/4 d). Arrived at by applying the German valuation of G. M. 50 per ton to the Reparation Com No Deliveries prior to 31 st December 1920.Estimated average price per ton G. M. 240 obtained by Coal Bureau from FVencb Deleg Actual quantity and actual value compiled by Accounting Service from German Factory I German valuations of deliveries to 31 st October 1920 for both items totalling G. M. 225, Valuation by British Post Office.Numbers furnished by the Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden. The values given are derive Commission and accepted by Germany.German valuations apparently include G. M. 47,788,049 for 417 locomotives and G. M. Reparation Account.&apos;Unaudited actual deliveries furnished by Accounting Office Wiesbaden. 50,000 tons hav as of doubtful origin of which unofficial estimates attribute 00,000 tons to reparation.Number and provisionally estimated price furnished by R. B. K. Bureau.Unaudited actual quantities assembled by Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden. Excludes deli on prices asked in public sale by the Belgian Ministry of Agriculture according to listsValuation by Coal Bureau as follows :a) To capitalise at C1/2 &quot;/0 the estimated present profit per ton&quot;ofwould be CM. 385,000,000;b) To add to (a) Balance Sheet isI April 1919 value of the installationc) To add to (a) and (/)) an estimate by Mr, C. R. Muller of 200 million Alternative valuations by French Government are :i. G. M. 262,000,000 based on application of method (a) to present Sa or ii. G. M. 294,000,000 based on capitalisation at 5 &quot;/n of tho avcrago net The value of the Coal produced prior to date of cossion has been excluded due to unce 1/1 lb March 1919.Estimate by the Finance Service.   The French Government values the Properly 0 G. M. 2,512,000.   Valuation by the British Government of Sbamecn Property not yetit at 850 francs per share, inclusiveValuation of shares made by French Govon
^4-Statement No 1.CUMULATIVE TOTALS TO 3 1 St DECEMBER K)2 0.EREEMENTSREMARKS.termination of method.erman valuation, wliich under Groups A and B(Annex 020) totals about 18,430 million Gold Marks. The reduction of I lie German Figure to ahoul of 4 milliard for ships. 207 million for Djes tuffs, and 240 million for K nil way Carriage Park in surrendered territories. In order I list the &quot;German re indicated by / has been adopted where ao German valuation is available.nds of the B. L. M. G. Figures which are supplied by Accounting Officer, Berlin, represent sales, less P. M. 11,883,557 (G. M. 771,737) administration toR. T. II. G. on sales since 4th Nov. 19/20). Rales for Gold Mark conversion are those of the :17th of the months of encashment. Bern 3 re resents the I of pre B. L. M.&apos;G. sales, less provision of P. M. 250,000 for commission al 2 1/2 %. Out of the net receipts (P. M. 01,747,728) P. M. 45,000,000 in ts, with which have been purchased Frs, 5,185,800 three months !\ &quot;/,, National Defense Bonds and   95,000 three months (i &quot;/o Treasury Bills.to be value of material turned over to B. L, M.G. lor sale.l-ently purports to he value of all material sold prior to (he, B. L. M. G.filli the following note :   &quot;Values of the allotted tonnage are calculated iu all cases arithmetically upon the estimated value of the whole delivered ton-(dance with the values to be calculated according to age, type and class under Article VI of the Spa Agreement&quot;. Foregoing excludes the undelivered ; Official rale of 10th January 1920 (G. M. 15,727 to the  .) used for converting estimated values, averaged at  15.0.0 per ton.(l,025,718), said to have been delivered or to he in the hands of the Allied and Associated Powers and including 93 ships lying in South American waters .824, rcpresentiNg approximately (at G. M. 16,120 to the  )  OS per ton. The figure in the &quot;German Figure&quot; column has been obtained by aplying iposite.   This results in a deduction from the German figure of 4 milliard Gold Marks.0 not include a number of craft supposed to have been taken or removed by the Allied and Associated Power.&apos;. Definite information is not yet available account thereof.Wiesbaden, including diseased animals.   Estimated values based on average Gold Mark unit price of each category, as supplied to Germans (Annex 408). september 1919, and its subsequent modifications, the value has been reduced by G. M. 1,966,903 representing 10 0/0 on value of each trainload in which the value of animals developing tuberculosis, and in addition 100 &quot;/0 deduction for all animals dying within a prescribed priod after receipt, iccr. Wiesbaden.   Unit values are actual, being the prices in Gold Marks stated on the orders for these machines, H.   Prices are those actually fixed by Reparation Commission.Jils 4 tons elleclive. Item 19 furnished by National Delegations (actual tonnage 7,594,450). Tonnage figures (item 20) furnished by Accounting Officer&quot; Luxembourg in excess of her allotted programme has been debited to France, vide Decision of Assistant Delegates&apos; Meeting a5/io/ad. Shipments from I   M. T. 9,590,856.   Figures furnished by Accounting Officer, Essen.   AH valuations are furnished by Coal Bureau.Ports of Rotterdam and Antwerp (actual 3,413,697)   the average f. 0. b. price of 80/   per ton (G. M. 62,015); rail or water   pit head prices of the various qualities;itions only, based on the average rail, or rail and water, rates between the principal mines and the principal frontier stations;n prior 3oth April 1920 have been valued at the prices ruling in the month of April in accordance with Assistant. Delegates&apos; Decision No 53 of 17th 1. 30.23 on actual and G. M. 27.27 on converted tonnage, including sea borne coal, and to G. M. 21.51 on actual and G. M. 18.91 on converted tonnageJ452 011 items 19 and 20 has also been made hv the Coal Bureau under which all coal for sea shipment delivered via Rotterdam and Antwerp is valued on 1 452/4 d).i1 ton to the Reparation Commission actual lonnage figures.I Bureau from French Delegation, quantities furnished by Accounting Officer, Essen, ftice from German Factory Invoices.iii items totalling G. M. 225,525,008 disregarded as Reparation Commission figures are taken from German Factory Invoices&quot;The values given arc derived from the unitary estimates (191/1 value) indicated by Belgian Delegation, multiplied by the coefficient 1, 2 prescribed by the417 locomotives and G. M. 135,038,021 for 21,131 wagons restored under provisions of last paragraph of Article 250 and, therefore, not creditable to&apos;5csbadcn. 50,000 tons have been allotted to French Bailway Systems and 30,000 tons to Belgian systems. In addition 215,000 tons have been reported j 60,000 tons to reparation.. No valuation has been made.&apos;K. Bureau.Wiesbaden. Excludes deliveries of 12,48* machines under 20,000,000 Paper Marks Agreement for substitution of restitutions to France. Value based iriculture according to lists obtained from the Belgian Service of Restitution, Wiesbaden.   Gold Mark conversion at average rate during period of deliveries.[present profit per ton of Coal (viz Frs. &quot;ii f on basis [of iyi3-i4 production - 13,097,374 tons.   Al gold mark rate of   7Lli October 1920 the sum9 value of the installation of the Mine. &quot;IJusterbach&quot; G. M. 2,587,000; . R. Muller of 200 millions gold francs (6. M. 100,000,000) for unexploiled concessions.of method (a) to present Saar annual output, (9,000,000 tons). M at 5 &quot;/0 of the average net profit for the 5 pre-war years.&quot;been excluded due to uncertainly as to whether payment be made through the Food Account France has with Germany under the Brussels Convention olIjnt values the Properly of Shanghai ceded to France and China at 400,000 Chinese Taels, which converted at rale of 10 January 1920 represents)f Shameen Property not yet received.   No valuation of either of the properties has been supplied by the German Government.jfrancs per share, inclusive of 135 francs for 6 years unpaid dividends.   Gold Mark conversion al the rate of 10th January 1920.the value of three deliveries of books etc., on account of Frs 5,028,/i04 (191/1 value) provisionally fixed by the Commission as the vuluo of Louvain Library.Ik-
APPROXIMATE STATE1No.o 5 a 0 (i 7 u 8 o 9 o 10 h ! I o 12i;iu l&apos;lo 15 1.1 0 17 IS a 19 o 20 21 22 23 oS4 25 20o27 o 28, 29 30o3133 34 35 30373S 3940 41 42 43 44&apos;45 40 47 48 49 50 51ARTICLE AND ANNEX.of peace tukatv a .n 1)ARMISTICE AGREEMENTS,Alt, 109. Idem. Idem.Pail. VII, Ail. 230 and Annex III Idem.Idem,Idem. Idem.Annex III. Annex I \.Idem.Idem.Idem.       \  &apos; VIdem,Idm.It km.idem.Idem. cAnnex V. Idem.Idem. Idem. Idem. Annex \ I. Idem.Part. VIII. Art. 244. Annex VII.Ail. VIII.Idem. Idem. Idem.Art. 111.Art. 45-50. Art. 134.Idem. Art. 145. Art. 150 of Clause 2. Protocol 28 June ii)&apos;9-Part. VIJI. Ail. 247.*Art. 32-39. Art. 8G. Art. 92.Art. 99. Art. 108. Art. 109-114.Art. 250.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem. Art. 250.BUY Ell IES.A. REPARATION IN KIM). Peace Treaty.Converted War Material sold hy 15. L M. G. :     Aeronautical........-         -Military, sold prior to I). L. M. C........No,383389 -)40G, TV1,970,938, 48,710. 22,199.3,120.9,749.Ships Steamers 1,000 C. T. and over.............between 1,000 -1.599 G. T.........  Sailing Vessels l,(&apos;)00 (i. T. anil over . .  .....between 1,000-1,599 G. T.........Fishing Vessels...........................Inland Navigation Goats and Material1120 Barges]...........................................Livestock.   Horses.........................................................&apos;..........Cattle..................................................................  Sheep........,.,........................................,................- Goats.... v.......,................v........................Poultry.................................................................Agricultural Material (See Item 31)......................................................I Seeds...............................................................................Cement and kindred material............................................................Glass Cylinders lor Miners&apos; Safety Lamps,......................................,,.Coal delivered 1st September 1019 to 31 si July iq20 (Converted tonnage)............,...........  taken in charge by Allies at Posts of Control 1st August to 31si December 1920 (end\erted tonnage Bv-Products o( Coal - Benzol...........................................................- -      CoalTar.............&apos;.....&apos;........................................---       Sulphate of Ammonia..............................................Dyesluffs.................................................... .k..............Pharmaceutical Products.............................(...................................Submarine Cables.......................................................................Armistice Agreement of 11th November 1918.Boiling Stock.   Locomotives...........................................................  Wagons......................................,........................fixed Railway Material (Including Signal, Shop and Permanent Way Material)..............Motor Lorries.......................................................,................QUANTITYG, T.   2,05&apos;ilArmistice Convention of 16th January 1919.Agricultural MaterialIJ. OTHER PROPERTY. RIGHTS, CONCESSIONS AND INTERESTS.Peace Treaty.Coal Mines situated in Saar liasin..................................................German school in French Concession at Shanghai......................................Properly in British Concession at Shameen...........................................Cermany&apos;s portion of capital of Stale. Hank, of Morocco,.................................Properly in Kiaochow............................................................Deliveries of Books, week, on account of Louvain Library...............................Arl. 254.   Portion of German Imperial and Slate Debts lo be assumed on account of former German territory, viz :By Belgium in respect ofMoresnct,  upon and Malmcdy...............................By Czecho-Slowikia in respect of Silesia............ ................................By Poland in respect of Posen, Eastern Prussia, AHenstein and Upper Silesia :(a) Territory in Ceded Area.................................................[b] Territory in Plebiscite Area..............................................By Meinel....................................................................By Free City of Danlzig.........................................................By Denmark in respect of Sehleswig................................................German Imperial and Stale properly informer German territories ceded lo :Czecho-Slovafua...............................................................Poland (a) Ceded Area...........................................................    (i) Plebiscite Area........................................................Meinel......................................................................free Cily of Dantzig...........................................................Denmark (Schleswig)...........................................................Material of a non-military value banded over under the Armistice.........................T.	38No.	38No.	133No.	130No.	17No.	34No.	Kg.	0,801No,	20H. T.	S.520M. T,	9,319M. T.	10Kg.	10,787Kg-	57No.	/No.	12&apos;Tons.	81No.	No.	131Sharesa For details see explanatory roneoed Annex 452/4 il.Paris, ,H 1 st January 1921.
APPROXIMATE STATEMENT OE DELIVERIES AND   DISTRIBUTION THEREOF AS AT 31st DECEMBEBASED ON ESTIMATES AND ll\ CERrijr.(,938,i7io;1109, 1,120. B749.20 (Csnverted tonnage).Interests.ml on account.edcd lo :QUANTITY.ESTIMATED VALUE.national currencies.P. M. P. M. P. M.G,T.   2,054,728T. 38,710No. 38,045 No. 133,221 No. 130,759 No. 17,488No. 34,970 No. 2,302Kg.     0,801,310 //No. 20,000 M, T. 8,520,327 M. T. 9,319,505iiaM. T. 19,729 Kg. 10,787,827 Kg.57,823*No. No. Tons. No.No.F.P, M. P. *M. P, M.P. M, P. M.Sliaies4,500 127,352 80,000 5,000130.549 \ Ia ii ii2,200 ii- P. M.Bel. Frs.// // iiiiiii ii iiVn51,900,092 37,030 9,750,00031,430,000// // // // // a ii ii920,000 00,000 3,435,317,180 2,985,708,285 ii ii ii275,048,348 7,581,394// ii ii3,000,000117,044,780 19,099,0391,870,0000gold marks.Total.3,449,070 2,502 503,974494,393,9721,355,000 32,782,092 43,782,181 &apos;i,872,429 335,102 1 13,052 453.420 1.733,871 231,500 4,400 200,380,179 220,302,032 // //4,734,978 21,774,400 &quot;570,736 49*000,000410,939,820 018,408,11872,048,000 19,011,016550,000,000 3,000,000 700,000218,000000,000 290,00017,392,000580,000 5,109,000 2,000,00003,000,000Vo.GERMAN FIGURE(See Remark B.)2 3i8)9i 10 \2 ) 3 4 5 0 7 8 9 10y \i pii-552a34 35no I11 1 3m&apos;i5 46 VI 16 i9 30 3131,000,000 * 563,974 y3,247,000,0001,355,000/237,500,000 *Included in item 31 * 1,733,871 / 231,500/ 4,400/ 380,000,000 * 425,000,000 *4,040,000/ 21,774,400 * 570,736/ 85,418,979 *571,000,000 * 940,000,000 * tProbably in No 50.29,000,0001,050,947,000 * 3,000,000/700,000/a212,000/600,000/ 290,000/17,392,000/580,000/ 5,109,000/ 2,000,000/10,000,000 *3.033,000,000 *232,000,000 * 514,000,000 * ,^03,000,000/ 0,000,000 *14,021,088,860UNDISTRIBUTEDorINFORMATION NOT AVAILABLE.3,449,070 2,502 563,97477,502,05049,000,0003,000,00061)0,1)00 290,00017,392,000580,000 5,169,000 2,000,000nuii i63,000,000222,549,202UNITED STATES.1,334,89519,091,89520,426,790GREAT BRITAIN.355,003,1975,058,52118,045,763379,307,481Reparations. - Annex 452/4 a, b, c.
ION THEREOF AS AT 31st DECEMBER 1920 MADE BY GERMANY ON REPARATION ACCOUNT UNDEfiBASED ON ESTIMATES AND IN CERTAIN CASES ON FIGURES AUDITED AND BROUGHT TO ACCOUNT.UNDISTRIBUTED or information NOT AVAILABLE.3/449,070 2,502 563,97477,502,05049,000,0003,000,00061)0,000 290,00017,392,000580,000 5,109,000 2,000,00063,000,000222,549,202UNITED STATES.1,334,895 iiHnii ii19,091,89520,426,790GREAT BRITAIN.355,003,1075,058,52118,045,763379,307,481FRANC,40,100,7581,355,000 27,153,870 24,291,930 3,501,740 178,799 it a1,65^,380 231,500 4,400 235,729,823 100,285,3114,734,978 8,715,518243,209,880 325,240,350ii31,905,120 10,888,514550,000,000 i700,000 n1,082,070,883ITALY.18,076,906 29,745,4123,118,818 378,57351,319,709BELGIUM.3,805,9345,028,822 19,490,251 1,310,683 150,303 113,652 453,420 76,485Hii6,573,450 19,259,070 it i2,029,754 137,507167,729,940 293,107,708 ii3,545,222 2,723,102212,000520,413,423JAPAN.6,888,426* II II t IH0// // // ill f916,894 54,596 a7,859,916LUXEMBOURG.11,012,239h11,012,239iSJNs. - Annex 452/4 a, b, c.... ....
REPARATION ACCOUNT UNDER TREATY OF VERSAILLES AND ARMISTICE AGREEMENTSBROUGHT TO ACCOUNT.JAPAN.	LUXEMBOURG.	OTHER ALLIED and ASSOCIATED POWERS.i		*a	*	a	1	//6,888,426	a	10,427,001		(Greece.)t	a	aa	u	//u	a	aa	tl	ita	ii	iin	ii	na	a	iia	a	itii	a	ii&apos;.&apos; //&apos;&quot;	n	ait	a	iiii	11.012,239	nh	*	it1	ii	iiII.	u	ii916,894	a	a54,596	a	iiu	u	Itii	i	IIa	a	it	a	ii	a	iti	ii	ii	i	I*	ii	a$	a	iin	a	nn	a	*h	a	iiu	a	iiii	i	n* a	t	au	a	an	a	aii	a	aH	a	aa	a	i	a	a//	a	a	a	a	ii	l7,859,916	11,012,239	10,427,001No.40 41 42 434445 46 47 48 49 50 51KKMAA. The period for certain Gold Mark conversions is arbitrary pending determination of method.B. In the column headed &quot;German Figure&quot; the sign * indicates latest German valuation, which under Groups A14 milliard as shewn herein is accounted for largely by an item of 4 milliard for ships. 207 million for Figure&apos;, column may be totalled, the Reparation Commission figure indicated by / has been adopted wher1-31 2	1-2*3	3* 4-8* 4	* 5 * 6	4-8** 7	* 8 * 9	9* 10 * 11	10-14*12	* 13	* 14	15* 15 *16 17	16 19-2018	* 19	*20	21	22	23	*24	*25	26	*27	*28	19-20*29 *30	21-22 23 24-25*31	24-25* 26 27-2832	27-28*33	34	2935	36	3037	31 3238	39	33-3435 36 37 38-43 44 and 5045-49 51No figure available for total value of unsold material in the hands of the B. L. M. G. Figures which are costs to 31st December 1920 (including 13&apos;/, commission to R. T. H. G. on sales since 4th Nov. 1920 payment of P. M. 10,000,000 by the R. T. II. G. to account of pre B. L. M.&apos;G. sates, less provision of all have been remitted to Paris and London in equal parts, with which have been purchased Frs.G. M. 31,000,000 (P. M. 500.000,000) apparently purports to be value of material turned over to B. LGerman give an estimate of P M. 1,000,000,000 which apparently purports to be value of all materialTonnage and estimated value supplied by Maritime Service with tbe following note : - &quot;Values of the nage, and will require adjustment in due course in accordance with the values to be calculated acc &quot;S. S. Bismarck&quot; (G. T. 56,000) allotted to Great Britain.   official rate of 10th January 1920 (G. M.According to latest German information, 1,001 ships (G. T. 4,625,718), said trf have been delivered or and yet to be surrendered, are valued at G. M. 7,310,302,824, representixg approximately (at G. M. this valuation to the tonnage shown as actually delivered opposite.   This results in a deduction fromThe Bureau of Inland Water Craft states that these figures do not include a number of craft supposed as to whether or not a credit will be given to Germany on account thereof.Unaudited actual quantities assembled by Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden, including diseased animals. In accordance with provisions of Protocol B-64. dated 9 September 1919, and its subsequent modific hoof and mouth disease appear, from 10 0/0 and 20 &quot;/0 on the value of animals developing tuberculosiUnaudited actual quantities assembled by the Accounting Officer. Wiesbaden.   Unit values are actual, bAudited quantities supplied by Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden.   Prices aro those actually fixed by ReparConverted tonnage figures include Coke at 3 tons actual equals 4 tons effective. Bom 19 furnished by 1 Essen (actual tonnage 8,504,827). Tonnage delivered to Luxembourg in excess of her allotted prog the Mines from  1st August 1920 to 3ist December 1920. - M. T. 9,596,856.   Figures furnishedBasis of valuations is :i. For coal delivered for sea shipment via Ports of Rotterdam and Antwerp (actual 3ii. For coal, coke and lignite delivered by rail or water   pit head prices of the vari Hi. Transport costs included to Frontier stations only, based on tbe average rail, or ra iv. AH deliveries on account of reparation prior 3oth April 1920 have been valuDecember 1920,The above valuation works out to an average unit price of G. M. 30.23 on actual and G. M. 27.27 on con other than sea borne.A minimum valuation showing a reduction of G. M. 174,472,452 on items 19 and 20 has also been ma the basis of ii, iii and iv (see Schedule 6 in roneoed Annex 452/4 d).Arrived at by applying the German valuation of G. M. 50 per ton to the Reparation Commission actualNo Deliveries prior to 31st December 1920.Estimated average price per ton G. M. 240 obtained by Coal Bureau from French Delegation, quantitieActual quantity and actual value compiled by Accounting Service from German Factory Invoices.German valuations of deliveries to 31 st Gctober 1920 for both items totalling G. M. 225,525,008 disngValuation by British Post Olfice.Numbers furnished by the Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden. The values given are derived from the unit Commission and accepted by Germany.German valuations apparently include G. M. 47,788,049 for 417 locomotives and G. M. 135,038,021 ft Reparation Account.1Unaudited actual deliveries furnished by Accounting Olfice Wiesbaden. 50,000 tons have been allotted as of doubtful origin of which unofficial estimates attribute 00,000 tons to reparation.. No valuationNumber and provisionally estimated price furnished by R. B. K. Bureau.Unaudited actual quantities assembled by Accounting Officer, Wiesbaden. Excludes deliveries of 12,48 on prices asked in public sale by the Belgian Ministry of Agriculture according to lists obtained from trValuation by Coal Bureau as follows :a) To capitalise at 61/2 &quot;/,, the estimated present profit per ton of Coal (viz Frs.would be G.M. 385,000,000;b) To add to (a) Balance Sheet 1st April 1919 value, of the installation of the Mine &quot;1Lc) To add to (a) and (A) an estimate by Mr, C. R. Mulier of 200 millions gold francs (t Alternative valuations by French Government are :i. G. M. 262,000,000 based on application of method (a) to present Saar annual oulpi or ii. G. M. 294,000,000 based on capitalisation at 5    of the average net profit for the 5 The value of tbe Coal produced prior to date of cession has been excluded due to uncertainty as to w&quot; i4th March 1919.Estimate by the Finance Service. The French Government values the Property of Shanghai ced G. M. 2,512,000.   Valuation by the British Government of Shameen Property not yet received.   NoValuation ol shares made by French Government at 850 francs per share, inclusive of .135 francNo value yet placed on this item.Information supplied by Belgian Delegation.   This represents the value of three deliveries of books etc., onEstimate by Finance Service.   Conversion at rate of 16 Paper Marks to Gold Mark.   No german valuaThe sum G. M. 65,000,000 received from Denmark (representing at the rate of exebauge of 4.198 G. 1 to the account of the Bank of England, at the Federal Reserve Bank of New-York to be invested in UFor reliable figures the outcome of the deliberations of the Sub-Committee, specially appointed to superThis question is under consideration by the S. R. R. K. and no figure other than the German valuation
HEMARS.Tininalion of method., ,rman valuation, which under Groups Aid B( Annex 620) totals about 18,430 million Gold Marks.   The reduction of the German figure to about f 4 milliard for ships. 207 million for leslults, and 245 million for Railway Carriage Park in surrendered territories.   In order thsl the &quot;German indicated by / has been adopted wherao German valuation is available., Is of the R. L. M. G.   Figures which areipplied by Accounting Officer, Berlin, represent sales, less P. M. 11,883,557 (G. M. 771,737) administration R. T. H. G. on sales since 4th Nov. 19:10  Rates for Gold Mark conversion are those of the :17th of the months of encashment.   Item 3 re resents the pf pre B. L. M.&apos;G. sales, less provision of. M. 250,000 lor commission at 2 1/2 */,.   Out of the net receipts (P. M. 01,747,728) P. M. 45,000,000 in with which have been purchased Frs. 385,800 three months 4 % National Defense Bonds and st: 05,000 three months ti &quot;/u Treasury Bills.be value of material turned over to B. L;I. G. for sale.ttly purports to be value of all material id prior to the B. L. M. G.   .1. the following note :   &quot;Values of the lotted tonnage are calculated in all cases arithmetically upon the estimated value of tlie whole delivered ton-Ice with the values to be calculated acccling to age, type and class under Article VI. of the Spa Agreement&quot;. Foregoing excludes the undelivered official rate of 10th January 1920 (G. M.5,727 to the - .) used for converting estimated values, averaged at s615.0.0 per ton.25,718), said to&apos; have been delivered or ibe in the hands of the Allied and Associated Powers and including 93 ships lying in South American waters i, representixg approximately (at G. M. 6,126 to the  )   98 per ton. The figure in the &quot;German Figure&quot; column has been obtained by aplying isite.   This results in a deduction from le German figure of 4 milliard Gold Marks.lot include a number of craft supposed i have been taken or removed by the Allied and Associated Power.&apos;.   Definite information is not yet available count thereof.iesbaden, including diseased animals,   estimated values based on average Gold Mark unit price of each category, as supplied to Germans (Annex 408). Imber 1919, and its subsequent modificions, the talue has been reduced by G. M. 1,960,903 representing 10 &quot;/0 on value of each trainload in which value of animals developing tuberculosi, and in addition 100 &quot;&apos;0 deduction for all animals dying within a prescribed priod after receipt. , Wiesbaden.   Unit values are actual, hing the prices in Gold Marks stated on the orders for these machines. Prices are those actually fixed by Rcpariion Commission.i tons elleclive.   Item 19 furnished by National Delegations (actual tonnage 7,594,450).   Tonnage figures (item 20) furnished by Accounting Officer, emhourg in excess of her allotted progunine has been debited to France, vide Decision of Assistant Delegates&apos; Meeting 2.5/10/20.   Shipments from II!M. T. 9,590,850.   Figures furnished 1&apos; Accounting Officer, Essen.   All valuations are furnished by Coal Bureau.&apos;ts of Rotterdam and Antwerp (actual 303,697) - the average f. 0. b. price of 80/ - per ton (G. M. 02,015); Hpr water   pit head prices of the varjus qualities; is only, based on the average rail, or r&amp;i and water, rates between the principal mines and the principal frontier stations;prior 3oth April 1920 have been valud at the prices ruling in the month of April in accordance with Assistant Delegates&apos; Decision No 53 of 17th0.23 on actual and G. M. 27.27 on coiierted tonnage, including sea borne coal, and to G. M. 21.51 on actual and G. M. 18.91 on converted tonnage1 011 items 19 and 20 has also been mie by the Coal Bureau under which all coal lor sea shipment delivered via Rotterdam and Antwerp is valued on 2/4 (/).Sj to the Reparation Commission actual tonnage figures.:eau from French Delegation, qtiantitie furnished by Accounting Officer, Essen, from German Factory Invoices.mis totalling G. M. 225,525,008 disregarded as Reparation Commission figures are taken from German Factory Invoice.&apos;.values given arc derived from the uuitiry estimates (191/1 value) indicated by Belgian Delegation, multiplied by the coefficient 1, 2 prescribed by thelocomotives and G. M. 135,038,021 fir 21,131 wagons restored under provisions of last paragraph of Article 250 and, therefore, not creditable toiden.   50,000 tons have been allotted Jo French Railway Systems and 30,000 tons to Belgian systems.   In addition 215,000 tons have been reported300 tons to reparation.   No valuation hus been made.Jureau.sbaden. Excludes deliveries of 12,48? machines under 20,000,000 Paper Marks Agreement for substitution of restitutions to France. Value based tore according to lists obtained from tie Belgian Service of Restitution, Wiesbaden.   Gold Mark conversion at average rate during period of deliveries.em profit per ton of Ooal (vi/. Frs. Vf on basis [of ujiIJ-ii production - 13,097,374 tons.   Al gold mark rate of 27th October 1920 the sumdue. of the installation of the Mine &quot;Hosterbach&quot; G. M. 2,587,000;. Mufler of 200 millions goid fi &apos;ancs (G. M. 100,000,000) for unexploited concessions,ethod (a) to present Saar annual output (9,000,000 tons). 5 &quot;/o of the average net profit for the 5 pre-war years.excluded due to uncertainty as to whether payment be made through the Food Account France has with Germany under the Brussels Convention ofalues the Property of Shanghai ceded to France and China at 400,000 Chinese Taels, which converted at rale of 10 January 1920 representsimeen Property not yet received.   No valuation of either of the properties has been supplied by the German Government.:s per share, inclusive of 135 francs for 0 years unpaid dividends.   Gold Mark conversion al the rate of 10th January 1920.; due of three deliveries of books etc., 011 account of Frs 5,028,494 (1914 value) provisionally fixed by the Commission as the value of Lottvain Library.- rks to Gold Mark.   No Gei man valuation available.at the rate of exchauge of 4.198 G. M. to the Dollar 15,483,858 dollars) has been transferred half to the account of the Bank of France, and half Sank of New-York to be invested in United States Treasury Certificates of Indebtedness or in prime bankers&apos; bills yielding about 5 3/4&quot;/,, interest.Miimittee, specially appointed to supervise these questions, must be awaited.ire other than the German valuation can be stated.( Signed : George P. AULD, Accountant General. .
Statement No. 1 a.APPROXIMATE STATEMENT OF DELIVERIES (AND DISTRIBUTION THEREOF) OlBASED ON ESIin State-ii) en I No 1.* 5* 0* 7* 8 0* 10* 11* 12 *13* 14* 15 10 17 18 19*2021 22 23 *24 *25 2027 28 29 30*3I37ARTICLE AND ANNEXOF PEACH TKKATY ANDAltMISTICE AOHKKMKNTS.Article 109. Idem. Idem.Part VIII. Article 230. Annex III,Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem. Annex IV.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem-Idem.Idem. Annex V.Idem.Idem. Idem. Idem. Annex VI. Idem.Part VI11. Article 244. Annex VII.Article VII. Idem. Mem. Idem.Arl id:DELIVERIES.A. REPARATION IN KIND. Peace Treaty.Converted War Material sold by 15. L. M. 0.: - Aeronautical----.......    Military..............sold prior to B. L. M. G ..........Ships Steamers 1,000 G. T. and over No. I. - 0. T. 2,304.- between 1,000-1599 G. T.- Sailing Vessels 1,000 G. T. and over- -   between 1,000-1599 G.T.- Pishing Vessels.Inland Navigation Boats and Material..........Livestock Horses..........................- Cattle...........................- Sheep...........................- Goats...........................Poultry..........................Agricultural Material (See Item 3i)............//12,039.ii iiSeeds.Cement and Allied Material..............................I...................Glass Cylinders for Miners&apos; Safety Lamps...................f..................Coal. - Delivered ist Sept. 1919 to 31 si July 1920..........1..................Coal.   Taken in charge by Allies at Posts of Control isl to 31st December 1920 (Con-led tonnage)...........................................................By-products of Coal. Benzol.................................................Coal Tar...............................................Sulphate of ammonia (Includes November also)................Dyestulfs......Pharmaceutical products Submarine cables.......Armistice Agreement of 11th November 1918.Purl VIII. Article 247.Rolling stock.   Locomotives............,...............I..........Wagons............&apos;...............................Fixed railway material (including Signal, Shop and Permanent Way Material). Motor Lorries........................................(.,.........Armistice Convention of 16th January 1^19.Agricultural Material.B. OTHER PROPERTY, RIGHTS, CONCESSIONS AND ENTER H ST S.Peace Treaty.Deliveries ol books, etc., on account of Louvain Library.........................QUANTITY.G. T.No.No.4,40315311 11 11 111,406 n11 11 11Tons.   1,720,26011 11Tons.       0,569 Kgs.    1,126,722 -        19,121//(No transactions during December in respect to items 32 to 30 ami 38 to 51 on Statement No I.)\Aloil1Idlp.BqTotals!
REPARATION COMMISSION.ACCOUNTING SERVICE.ANNEX No 452/4 i.)IST1UBLT1G\ THEREOF) ON REPARATION ACCOUNT MADE BY GERMANY DURING DECEMBER 1920 UNDERBASED ON ESTIMATES AND IN CERTAIN CASES ON FIGURES UJDITKD AND BROUGHT TO ACCOUNT-I 1920 (Con-.-RKSTS.QUANTITY. .G.T.       14,403No.No.11 15311 n 11 n1,406 n11 11 11Tons.   1,720,260Tons.        0,560 Kgs.    1,126,722 -        19,121ISlatomonl No 1.)ESTIMATED VALUE.NATIONAL CURRENCIES,l&apos;.M. 1,0X7,310 1,033 9,750,000220,000P.M. 020,879,273P.M.Idem.44,028,159 2,048,274P.M. 1,579,550 Bel. frj.     30,000Totals.cold MARKS.55,801 55 503,9743,459,940139,540// ii a ii293,429 // ii it ii35,095,025// ii1,576,440 2,475,994 146,035ii192,21470,000G. M.   44,668,447UNDISTRIBUTEDorINFORMATION NOT AVAILABLE.55,8015.)563,974019,830UNITED STATICS.// ii ii ii n n n ii ii a iiii aji a400,835 // . ii400,835GREAT BRITAIN.500,172// //// // //* // // ii a iiii ii ii ii728,275&quot;1,294,447FRANCE2,893,708// ii ii&quot;iiIk ii ii II It ii ii23,4.08,447// ii1,570,440 535,444181,01028,055,1.15
Statement No % a[g december 1920 under treaty of versailles and armistice agreements.JUGHT TO ACCOUNT-							OTHER ALLIED	No	-						and	inTES.	GREAT BRITAIN.	FRANCE.	ITALY.	BELGIUM.	JAPAN.	LUXEMBOURG.		Slate-							ASSOCIATED	nient							POWERS.	Mo 1.	a		//	//	//.	//	//	1	ii	//	//	//	//	//	//	2	a	//	&apos; //	//&apos;	//	//	//	3  ;							1	* 4   I							1	* 5	500,172	2,893,708		*	ii	i		* 0							1	* 7							1	* 8	//	//	//	//	n	n	//	9II	//	//	//	139,540	ii	a	II	* 10ffl	ii	a	//	ii	a	a	II	* 11	a	ii	//	n	ii	n	II	* 12    ;B	n	n	//	ii.	ii	a	:                   n	* 13	ii	ii	//	ii	ii	a	ll	* 14B	ii	ii	//	293,429	ii	a	n	* 15	a	ii	//	ii	n	a	ll	16II	ii	ii	n	ii	ii	n	ll	17II	ii	a	ii	ii	ii	a	H	18-	ii	ii	n	ii	ii	a	ll	191 &apos;	n	23,408,447	6,234,595	3,889,330	n	2,102,653	ll	*2011	ii	//	a	//	n	//	ll	21     ;if	ii	//	ii	//	ii	//	ll	&apos;2211	n	1,570,440	n	//	n	//	Ii	23,5	728,275	535,444	230,500	227,097	287,177	//	ll	*24li	n	//	101,097	12,300	32,032	//	ll	*251	n	//	//	ii	//	//	ii  .	201		//	ii	n	a		//	27	a	//	ii	ii	ii		//	28		ii	n	ii	n		//	29	&quot;	i	ii	a	ii	*	//	30m		1 o i iii a	*&quot;t            it	ii   1 (iu			//	IF		lol ,UJ l)		1 J, Ivo	H			*. 01     I1	i		ii	70,000	ii	//		37	1,294,447	28,055,115	0,500,858	4,043,500	319,209	2,102,053										
REPARATION COMMISSIONACCOUNTING SERVICE.V\!\i:\ No li52/4cAPPROXIMATE RETURN OF DELIVERIES and made BY GERMANY AT 3 1st DECEMBER 1D2 IN CONNECTION WITH ARTICLE 23 5 (00LI) MARKS 20 MilA. ESTIMATED VALUE OK DELIVERIES PER STATEMENT u (ANNEX. 452/4/a). Exclusive of values shown in Annex 540 for Fixed Railway Material (C. M. 20,000,000), and Abandoned Material (G. M. 01,000,000).deductItems which cannot or may not he readily turned into Liquid Assets by 1st May 1921, viz. :fa) Provisional valuation of Saar Basin.[b) Proportion of Loans to he assumed by Cessionary Stales under Article 25&apos;l sCzeeho-SlovakiaDanlzig......Memel........Poland.......(c) Receipts on Louvain Library A/cAPPROXIMATE TOTAL ATTRIBUTABLE TO ARTICLE 235.add :B. PROVISIONAL FIGURES RELATING TO ITEMS CLAIMED BY GERMANY AS RANKING AGAINST ARTI. Gold Deliveries and other payments made for Food and Raw Materials (See Annex (320)........II. Saar Coal Production delivered to order of France prior to date of actual cession (See Annex 020III. Currency furnished to Armies of Occupation :at.U. S. A.................................................................................... i5.11.20Great Britain;................&quot;...............................................&apos;............. i3o. C.20France................................................................................... 3o.io.20Italy...................................................................................... 11Belgium................................................................................. 1. i.abIV. Goods and Services (including Billeting, Use of Barracks, Boadmaking, etc.), furnished to Armies of Occupation to oolb November 195 V. Expenses claimed by Germany on account of various Inter-Allied Commissions to 3oth November 1920 (See Annex 540)...........C. AGGREGATE AT 31ST DECEMBER 1920.Note. - 1. This total of G. M. 5,577,200,740 is contingent upon the settlement of the following questions, viz :Section A. Abandoned Material (estimated by the Germans at G. M. 2,5oo,ooo,ooo); Fixed Railway Materiel; Prices for Coal and Cattle delivered; Properly in Ceded Territories (estimated by the Germans at G. M. 4,/100,000,000, presumably both liquid and fixed asSection B. Foodstuffs and Raw Materials A/c.;Items creditable re Costs of Armies (Billeting, etc.);Allowance for Expenses of Plebiscites and Commissions. ^Note. ..... 2. The competent Services estimate (Annex 540) additional Deliveries and Credits between isl December 1920 and,9oo,i53,285 maximum, exclusive of the Schlcswig and Belgium Hems (G. M. 05,000,000 and G. M. 620,000 respectively) already note   3. During the month of December G. M. 70,937,33/1 have been brought to account. D. The Costs of Armies of Occupation reimbursable under Art 251 up to 3olh September 1920 approximate :U. S. A.......................................................................................Great Britain.........................................................................*........France..........................................................................- - *..........Italy.......................................____&apos;...............................
R E BA R AT I ON commission NACCOUNTING SERVICE,ANNEX No 452/4cflUMATE RETURN OF DELIVERIES AND payments made BY GERMANY AT 3 1st DECEMBER 1920, BWECTIOIN WITH ARTICLE 2H5 (COLD MARKS 20 MILLIARDS).OE DELIVERIES PER STATEMENT la (ANNEX 452/4/a).. iI\\ay Material (0. M. 211,(100,000), and Abandoned Material (G. M. 61,000,000),liquid Assets by 1 st May 1921, viz. :   I ales under Article 254 :0. M.I290,000 0,11)9,000 58o,ooo 17,392,000IE TOTVL ATTRIBUTABLE TO ARTICLE 235.0 ITEMS CLAIMED BY GERMANY AS RANKING AGAINST ARTICLE 235.and Raw Materials (See Annex 020)........trior to date ol&apos; actual cession (See Annex 020AT.i5.11.203o. (i.2000.10.20111. 1.20P. M.5o8,ooo,ooo 280,000,000 i,/i 78,000,000 1149,000,0002,321,000,000Ijacks, Roadmaking, etc.), furnished to Armies of Occupation to 3olb November 1920 (See Annex 540),. it Inter-Allied Commissions to 3oth November 1920 (See Annex 0/10)....... . ..................AGGREGATE AT 31ST DECEMBER 1920.G. M.550,000,00(123,431,000 212,0002,240,311,740 190,284450,000,000500,000,000 40,000,000G. M.2.911,392,044573,043,0002,337,749,0443,239,511,0305,577,200,674j Uingent upon the settlement of the following questions, viz S iermans at G. M. 2,600,000,000);ed by the Germans at G. M. /i,/ioo,ooo,ooo, presumably both liquid and fixed assets).dieting, etc.); .   .i nd Commissions.IX 540) additional Deliveries and Credits between isl Deccnibiu&apos; 1920 and 1st May 1921 at/G, M. 702,022,100 minimum and G. .M. lid Belgium Items (G. M. 05,000,000 and^G. M. 620,000 respectively) already included in A. supra.t 907,33/1 have beeu brought to account.under Art 251 up to 3olh September 1920 approximate :G,....................,............................................................      1,100,000,000................................................................................. ()5o,000,0()0.....,...........................................................................       1,200,000,000.................................................................................. 10,000,000.................................................................................. 175,000,0003,435,000,000
APPROXIMATE STATEMENT OF DELIVERIES (AND DISTRIBUTION THEREOF)BASED ONin Stale-mentally No 1,4 5 0 7* 8 9* 10* II* 12 t 13* 14* 15 10 17 18 19*202122 23 *24 *25 2028 29 3031ARTICLE AND ANNEXof peace treaty andarmistice agreements.DELIVERIES.Part Mil.Part Mil.Article 109. Mem. Idem.Article 230. Annex III.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem. Annex l\.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.Idem.IdemIdem.Idem. Annex V.Idem.Idem. Idem. Idem. Annex VI. Idem.Article 244. Annex VII.Article Ml. Idem. Idem. Idem.A. REPARATION IN KIND. Peace Treaty.Converted War Material sold by II. L. M. G.Aeronautic;!sold prior to B. L. M. G....... ...Ships Steamers 1,000 G. T. and over No. 1. - G. T.  2,364,-    between 1,000-1599 G. T. - u *- Sailing Vessels 1,000 G. T. and over - 5 12,039.-&quot;   -  between 1,000-1599 G.T.   - * //  Fishing Vessels. - *                *Inland Navigation Boats and Material.............................Livestock Horses.............................................- Cattle..............................................- Sheep..............................................- Goats..............................................- Poultry.............................................Agricultural Material (See Item 3i)...............................Seeds......................................................Cement and Allied Material.................................................Glass Cylinders for Miners&apos; Safety Lamps......................................Coal.   Delivered ist Sept. 1919 lo 31 si July 1930.............................Coal. - Taken in charge by Allies at Posts of Control isl lo 3isl. December 1920 (Conled tonnage)...........................................................By-products 01 Coal. Benzol................. ...............................Coal Tar...............................................Sulphate of ammonia (Includes November also)................Dycstulls.......Pharmaceutical products Submarine cables......Armistice Agreement of 11th November 1918.Rolling stock.   Locomotives.Wagons,ArlicliPart VIII. Article 247.Fixed railway material (including Signal, Shop and Permanent Wiry Material). Motor Lorries..................................................Armistice Convention of 16th January 1919.Agricultural Material.tB. OTHER PROPERTY, RIGHTS, CONCESSIONS AND INTERESTS.Peace Treaty.Deliveries ol books, etc., on account of Louvain Library.........................QUANTITY.G.T.      14,403No. 153// n11 11No. 1,406//Tons.   1,720,26011 11Tons.        0,509 Kgs.    1,126,722 -        19,121//No transactions during December in respect lo items 32 lo 30 and 38 to 51 on Statement No 1.* For details see explanatory roneoed schedules Annex 452/4 d.Paris, 31 si. January 1921.Reparations. -- Annex 452/4 a,
ANNEX No 452/4 b.UN THEREOF) ON REPARATION ACCOUNT MADE BY GERMANY DURING DECEMRER 1920 UNDER TREATY OFBASED ON ESTIMATES AND IN CERTAIN CASES ON FIGURES AUDITED AND BROUGHT TO ACCOUNT-QUANTITY.4,403153aa a1,4001,720,260ii a0,560 1,126,722 19,121ESTIMATED VALUE.national oukrkncies.I&apos;. M.1,0X7,310 *1,0330,750,000220,000* n ii n ii u ii n ii aP.M. 020,870,273P,M.Idem.44,028,150 2,648,274P.M. 1,570,550 Bel. Iri.     30,000Totals.gold marks.55,80155 563,9743,459,940//139,540ii293,42935,095,0251,576,440 2,475,994 146,035n192,21470,000G. M.   44,668,447UNDISTRIBUTEDorINFORMATIONNOT AVAILABLE.55,8015.)563,974019,830UNITED STATES.a460,835//400,835GREAT BRITAIN.500,172ii ii ii a728,275 a a1,294,447FRANCE2,893,70823,408,4471,570,440 535,444181,01028,055,115ITALY.// // /; // // // ii ii ii ii ii6,234,595a ii a230,500 101,697ii0,566,858
DECEMBER 1920 UNDER TREATY OF VERSAILLES AND ARMISTICE AGREEMENTS.It to account-GREAT BRITAIN.500,172728,2751,294,447FRANCE2,893,70823,408,447// a1,570,4 iO 535/144 aa.181,01028,055,115ITALY.0,234,595230,50(1 101,097ii0,566,858BELGIUM.a139,540// // a ii293,429// ii ii ii3,889,330// // n227,697 12,300ii11,19870,0004,643,500JAPAN,a287,177 32,032319,209LUXEMBOURG.2,102,0532,102,053OTHER ALLIED andASSOCIATED POWERS.Signed : GuoRgE P. ALU). Accountant General.&apos;
STICK AGREEMENTS,LUXEMBOURG,2,102,6532,102,653Igned : GEORgE P. AULD. Accountant General.&apos;OTHER ALLIED	No	in and		Slate-ASSOCIATED	nicntPOWERS.	No 1.//	1//	a// (	,i * 4	* 5	* 0	* 71	* 8//	9it	* 10ii	* 11a	* 12 i &apos;*i: ii	* l.) * 14ii	* 15ii	10ii	17ii	18ii	19ii	* 20ii	21ii	22ii	23ii	*24ii	*25.                  ii   ,	20	27//	28//	29	30	+.31//	37	A. ESTIMATED VALUE OF DELIVERIES PER STATEMENT In (ANNEX 452/4/a) (Exclusive of values shown in Annex 540 for Fixed Railway Material (G, M. 20,(100,1100), and Abandoned Material (G. M. 6i,j deduct :  Items which cannot or may not he readily turned into Liquid Assets by i^t May 19 u,      : -(a) Provisional valuation of Saar Basin.................................[b) Proportion of Loans to he assumed by Cessiouary States under Article 25&apos;j :Czceho-SlovakuDaulzig.....Memel.......poland.......(c) Receipts on Louvain Library A/APPROXIMATE TOTAL ATTRIBUTABLE TO ARTICLE 235.U)it :15. PROVISION VL FIGURES RELATING TO ITEMS CLAIMED BY GERMANY AS RANKDG AGAINI. Cold Deliveries and other payments made for Food and Raw Materials (See Annex 020).........II. Saar Coal Production delivered to order of France prior to date of actual cession (See Annex 020 ). 111. Currency furnished to Armies of Occupation :U. S. A.....Great Britain.France......Italy.......Belgium . . . .10.13o. 3o, KIV. Goods and Services (including Billeting, Use of Barracks, Boadmakiug, etc.), furnished to Armies of Occupation lo3olbNov( V. Expenses claimed by Germany on account of various Inter-Allied Commissions to 3oth November 1920 (See Annex &apos;.)!\o\.. .C. AGGREGATE AT 31 ST DECEMBER 1920.note.   1. This total of G. M. 5,577,2(10,7/10 is contingent upon tho settlement ol the following questions, viz :Section A. Abandoned Material (estimated by the Germans at G. M. 2,5oo,000,000); Fixed Railway Materiel; Prices for Coal and Cattle delivered ;Properly in Ceded Territories (estimated by ihe Germans al G. M. 4,\00,000,000, presumably bulb liqtd anjSection B. Foodstuffs and Raw Materials A/c.;Items creditable re Costs ol Armies (Billeting, week.); Allowance for Expenses of Plebiscites and Commissions.isotk. 2. The competent Services estimate (Annex 540) additional Deliveries and Credits between 1st Dccomun 19! i,9oo,i53,285 maximum, exclusive of the Schleswig and Belgium Items (G. M. 05,000,000 and ii. M. 620,000 respect rely )lnote   3. During the month of December G. M. 70&apos;,907,33/1 have been brought to account. D. The Costs of Armies of Occupation reimbursable under Art 251 up to 3olh September 1920 approximate :U. S. A...............................................................................Great Britain..........,................................................................France...............................................................................!Italy.................................................................................Belgium...............................................................................Paris, 3 1 January 1921Reparations.   Annex 452/4 a, b, ci
I MATE RETURN OF DELIVERIES AND PAYMENTSIMADE BY GERMANY AT 3 1st DECEMBER 1920, iECTlON WITH ARTICLE 235 (GOLD MARKS 20 MILLIARDS I.f DELIVERIES PER STATEMENT h (ANNEX 452/4/a)./ay Material (G, M. 20,000,000), and Abandoned Material (G, M. (Ji,000,000).d Assets by 1st May 1021, viz. :   is! under Article 2f)&apos;t :0. u.21)0,0000,109,000 080,000 1 7,392,000&apos;0TAL ATTRIBUTABLE TO ARTICLE 237).EMS CLAIMED RV GERMANY AS RANKING AGAINST ARTICLE 235.d Raw Materials [See Annex 020)........to date of actual cession (See Annex 021)at.15.11.20 3o. O.20P. H,,)0. 10.20//1.   1.20008,000,00O 280,000,000 1/178,000,00019,000,0002,32 1,000,000H, Roadmakiug, etc.), furnished to Annies of Occupation to 3otb November 1920 (See Annex 5&apos;i0). ter-Allied Commissions to 3olh November 11)20 (See Annex 54o)..........................GNEGATE AT 31ST DECEMBER 1920.G. M.550,000,00023,431,000 212,0002,240,311,7&apos;iO 190,284450,000,000500,000,000 40,000,000G. M.2.011,302,04&apos;t573,043,0002,337,749,0443,230,511,0305,577,200,074[Genl upon the settlement of the following questions, viz : turns at G. M. 2,5oo,ooo,ooo);fly the Germans at G. M. 4,/ioo,ooo,ooo, presumably both liquid and fixed assets).mg, etc.); commissions.)i0) additional Deliveries and Credits between  ist December  1920 and  ist May 1921 at G. M. 702,522,100 minimum and G. M.Jelgium Items (G. M. 05,000,000 and G. M. 620,000 respcclively) already included in A. supra.Ij33.^ have been brought to account.;prime Arl 251 up to 3olh September 1920 approximateC. M.1,100,000,000 i)5o,ooo,ooo1,200,000,000 10,000,000 170,000,0003,435,ooo,oooSigned : George P. AULD, Accountant General.

</content>
</cab>
