<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 615-616</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

CONFIDENTIAL.

Copy nO. 3

C.P.-2684.

CABINET.

LEAGUE OF NATIONS.

PUBLICITY 0F THE DISCUSSION OF THE COUNCIL.

Report presented by M. Hy?ans, Belgian Representative, and adopted by the Council in Paris on February 21st,1921.(Circulated for information.)

A Resolution adopted by tho Assembly on November 23rd 1920, has been laid before the Council; the text of this Resolution it as follows :-

"That the Council be requested to take into consideration the means for securing greater publicity for their discussions and decisions."

Lord Robert Cecil, in his statement with regard to this Resolution, made a suggestion to the effect that the  Council should consider the possibility of admitting the public, as often as possible to some of its more important meetings, in order to enable all nations throughout the world to be informed of what is taking place. He also laid emphasis on the advisability of extending the greatest possible publicity to the discussions.

There are, therefore, two points to be considered; Firstly, the question of holding the meetings of the  Council in public; secondly the publication of its decisions and discussions.

It does not seem possible to throw all tho meetings of the Council open to the public. Exchanges of views between Members of the Council must retain the characteristics of confidence, freedom and conciliation which are rendered necessary by the nature of the questions under discussion and the end ?avour to reach the desired agreements.


Public mootines hold hitherto have, in many cases, aroused little interest.     The reading out of numerous documents which have been accumulated during the Session, wearies the attention, while their very nuobor prevents them from being adequately reproduced in tho Press,It would, therefore, be a better plan to throw open to   tho public thoso meetings which the Council may regard as of special interest for public opinion.On the other hand the reports, the resolutions, and a short summary prepared by the Secretariat and approved by the Members of the Council, might. as tho work of tho Council proceeds, bo given at once to tho Press.I have, therefore, the honour to propose tho two following resolutions : -1.   The Council sh 11 docido that a meeting is to bo open to the public whenever it considers this course to be advisable or opportune.2.     Tho Secretariat will ensure th..-- immodiato publication of Resolutions and Kcoorts, and also of a short summary of the discussions which  shall have been, previously approved by the members of the Council.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I. 8th March, 1V21.

</content>
</cab>
