<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 634-635</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 0F HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

SECRET.

CABINET.

C.P. 2689.

LIQUOR CONTROL.

MEMO BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF EDUCATION.

I am sorry to trouble my Colleagues once more with a Memorandum upon the depressing subject of Liquor. The question has, however, been raised by the recent proposals of the Liquor Control Board and by the Minutes of the Food Controller and of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, and to these I wish to add a few observations.

(1) The removal of all restrictions upon Clubs would undoubtedly be welcome to a large section of the working class population. On the other hand, if the proposals of the Clubs outlined in the Food Controller&apos;s Minute are adopted, it would be impossible to maintain any restrictions whatever upon the hours of sale in Licensed Houses. The Cabinet must understand that the restoration of the pre-war position of the Clubs can only mean the abandonment of all the advantages gained for the Country by the restriction of the hours of sale in Licensed Houses. Those restrictions may be modified, though I should hope that no modifications will be allowed to interfere either with the closure of Licensed Houses in the morning or with the requirement of some period of closure during the afternoon. I am sure, however, that public opinion would not tolerate the complete disappearance of restrictions, which are generally felt to be in the public interest and are, I understand, welcome to all enlightened members of the Trade. I could not, however, be party to a scheme under which restrictions are retained for Licensed Houses and abolished for Clubs. I would rather see the whole fabric of restrictions abolished altogether.

  
(2) I trust that the Cabinet will not lightly abandon the requirement of prepayment in the case of liquor sold to domestic consumers. No regulation imposed by the Liquor Control Board has done more than the prohibition of credit to protect the wages of the working householder against devastating inroads. The case for it is very strongly felt amongst all those who have occasion to work among the poor.

(3) Whatever the decision of the Cabinet may be with respect to tho form which Licensing Legislation should take in England, the preponderant opinion in Wales will unquestionably be hotly opposed to any extension of the hours of opening, either of Public Houses,or of Clubs, and will earnestly press for some scheme of local option. Indeed for the past 40 years there has been a continuous and overwhelming majority of Welsh Members in favour of Local option and I, therefore, thinly that it will be necessary either that the Licensing Bill should contain a Local Option Clause for Wales upon which the House should be invited to vote free from the  intervention of Party Whips, or that the Government should afford facilities for the passage of a separate Bi11 for Wales, including Monmouthshire.

(Sgd.) H,,A,I. FISHER.

Board of Education, S,W.

?th, March, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
