<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 643-646</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PHIS DOCUKEKT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS ERI^HNIC foAJEEVTY^ government  11. NT,A question of policy has arisen in connection with tho government scheme for the prevention and treatment of venereal diseases which I think it necessary to submit to my colleagues because it includes not only medical Issues but moral and social issues of the first importance.Under the Government scheme (1) gratuitous treatment for persons suffering from these diseases is provided at Hospitals and other institutions in all parts of the country, and (2) a wide-spread campaign of publicity and education as to the dangers and effects of the diseases, and as to the necessity for early and skilled treatment has been undertaken.     Treatment is provided under schemes formulated by the larger Local Authorities and approved by the Ministry of Health, and the propaganda campaign is directed centrally by the National Council for Combating Venereal Diseases and in particular areas by the Local Authorities in each case under the supervision of the Ministry,     In a few cases &quot;ablution centres&quot; have been provided as an experimental measure, i.e. centres at which persons may be disinfected or may disinfect themselves under expert direction.2 . During the war various experiments were made by different armies in the direction of attempting to secure that men who, through promiscuous sexual intercourse, exposed thorn-selves to the risk of infection with venereal, disease should be disinfected, in order to stop the development of disease,,     In some cases suitable disinfectants were supplied to men inprevention and Treatment of Venereal Diseases,kernorandum by the l.inis tes or Heal theM jH r-33 opacketsii
&quot;packets&quot; and the men were instructed as to their proper use. In other cases arrangements were made for &quot;Ablution Centres&quot;.3.   An inter-departmental committee consisting of medical reprerentatives of the Army Council, Admiralty, Air Force, kini-try of tensions and Ministry of health j, was appointed after the Armistice and came to the general conclusion that although certain drugs, if properly and skilfully applied, are efficacious in preventing venereal disease, the most carefully organised system for the supply of these drugs in &quot;packets&quot; and the instruction of man as to their use, had not produced such a general reduction in the incidence of venereal disease as to counteract the disadvantages attending such a system.4.   The views of this committee were not universally accepted, there was considerable public controversy, and a committee was finally appointed last autumn by the National Birth-rate Commission, under the Chairmanship of the Bishop of Birmingham to consider tho question of the prevention of venereal disease.     Tho definite recommendations of the Committee appear to be that no difficulty should be placed an the way of either (i) the spread of knowledge as to the use and value of suitable disinfectants, or (ii)  the obtaining by individuals of such disinfectants from chemists or other sources.     With regard to the spread of knowledge, the committee contemplates that instruction should bo given, with the sanction of the Local Health Authorities, at &quot;Ablution Centres&quot;, or in other places, personally, or by posters or printed leaflets.    As. regards the obtaining of disinfectants, the Committee recommend that in areas in which a trial of the method of self-disinfection is being initiated and carried out by Local Authorities, approved disinfecting substances should be sold by chemists at a nominal cost, and. printed Instructions, approved by the Ministry of Health or the Looal Health Authority, as to the right use of disinfectants for prevention, with a warning against their use for the treatment of disease/
disease, should accompany all such sales and should be given by the Local Health Authority to persons applying for information and advice.     The Committee also considered the Question of providing &quot;Ablution Centres&quot; and express the opinion that Local Authorities should not be encouraged to provide expensive &quot;Ablution Centres&quot; all over thr- country for men who have &quot;brought disease upon themselves&quot; by their own misconduct, before it has been definitely ascertained that they are unable to disinfect themselves efficiently.5.   The publication of the report makes it essential that J* should announce whether there is to be any change in the policy of my Department which has hitherto been based upon the views of the Inter-departmental Committee.     The main point at Issue is what attitude should be adopted as regards self-dlsinfectioru6*   So far as I can judge the situation there Is general agreement on the following propositions.(i) that the only finally effective method of avoiding venereal disease is to abstain from promiscuous sexual Inter-course, and that a steady and continuous policy of public enlistment on this&apos; point and as to the risks of venereal disease and its resulting consequences on the general health of the community is essential,(ii) that disinfection immediately after exposure to risk is effective only to the extent to which It can be thorough-ly and Intelligently applied in the particular ease. &apos;&quot;&apos; Medical opinion is, however, divided as to (1) whether it is practicable to give such instruction to the civilian population as will ensure that the&apos; disinfectants are thoroughly and intelligent-ly applied;   (2)   whether the spreading of knowledge as to the efficacy of disinfectants will lead to persons&apos; running the risk of Infection who would otherwise avoid the&apos; risk, and thus increase the spread of disease;   (5)   whether the disinfectants will not be used in some cases for the treatment of developed disease with the result&quot;  that
that   proper   treatment will be delayed and the cure of the disease rendered more difficult and uncertain.There is also a marked divergence of opinion as to the social and moral results of according such official approval of a policy of self-disinfeoti n as would necessarily follow from the giving, of directions as to how disinfectants are to be u?ed.     It is contended that such a policy would inevitably lower the whole moral tone of the community and lead to an increase in promiscuous sexual intercourseuIvy own vie \n is that in the absence of any clear medical opinion in favour of the practicability and likelihood of success of self-disinfection we should not be justified In over-riding the objections advanced against this policy on moral and social grounds,I propose therefore that I should refrain from giving any official encouragement to a policy &quot;of self-disinfection and continue generally the present policy of public instruction and arrangements for free treatment, including a certain number of &quot;ablution centres&quot;, to the extent to which tho national need for economy admits.      The necessity of cleansing the person after exposure to risk would also be emphasisod, - t .Ministry of Health.G. ADDISON. 10. 3. 1921.

</content>
</cab>
