<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/120/0 images: 668-669</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCULU&amp;g 7.S gga PROP Jit. Y OP HIC BRITAIN 10 MAJESTY?S GOVERISM^ T ^GAB J. M iS gv jSQBEpS POR PROVISION OP IW^OSMfog HTi RPRET ATX0X1 ffl TOtjfl T^RU &quot;PRHtlTOJailO-ii TO EX gfflVIflji, MBH&quot;,3HET Memorandum by the    plater of labour.P.96.i.    Scute difficulty has occurred in the interpretation of the term &quot;preference to ex-Service men&quot; in connection with sohemes receiving grants from the Unemployment Grants Committee &quot;reference to ox-Service men is a condition t-ttachod by the Government both to grants made by the Unemployment Grants Committee and grants made by the Ministry of Transport for arterial roads.     It is also provided that labour for arterial roads should bo selected through the Employment Exchanges by special Selection Committees, and that labour for schemes under the Unemployment Grants Committee should be obtained from the Employment Exchanges, but not necessarily through Selection Committees.Z,    For the purpose of the erto-.it 1 road schemes, no interpretation of the word preference was given to ^election Committees, but in certain areas in which the question was raised by committees a ruling was given by the Department that, at the discretion of the Selection Committee, and subject to the general principle ol preference to ex-Service men being kept prominently in view, a few civilians might be engaged up to a number not exceeding one fourth of the whole.     This interpretation met the objection of Local Authoiities to the engagement of unmarried ex-Service men v,ho hi d. pernsos not served overseas while married civilians (many with young dependent children) regained unemployed. 1^   Z.    The Unemployment Grants committee take the view that preference to ew-Sorvioo men means that no civilians (married or single) should be engaged while eny ex-Service men suitable for the work-1-
remain unemployed in the district,, end the Committee propose to withdrew or cencel their grants in oasos in which this conditio is not observed.     I apprehend that the strict enforcement of this condition will cause considerable resentment and might result in Local Authorities refusing to co-operate with the Committee.4.        The oo-operation of Local Authorities Is essential to thesuccess of schemes to provide employment, and I suggest that th unemployment Grants Committee should he informed that, subject to tho general principle of preference to ex-Service men being always kept prominently in view. Local Selection Committees or Employment Exchanges should be entitled at their discretion to submit for employment on schemes receiving greats f;;om the Unemployment Grants Committee a few civilians not exceeding as a rule one fourth of the total number employed;   In a fow exceptional oases (eag, Coventry, where the proportion of ex-Service men among the unemployed As much lower than tho normal proportion), probably there should be a discretion to allow the proportion of ex-Service men employed to be less than three-fourths.(Signed)   T. J. MACKAKABA.Ministry of labour.n

</content>
</cab>
