<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/35/15 images: 150-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1943.BRITISH COMMONWEALTH OE NATIONS. .Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I think my colleagues should see the enclosed memorandum by Mr. Malcolm Macdonald, the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Canada, containing&quot;some thoughts on the post-war position of the British Commonwealth ofNations.&quot;C. R. A.Dominions Office, March 22, 1943.Memorandum.THESE rough notes set forth some thoughts on the post-war position ofGreat Britain and the British Commonwealth of Nations. They are naturallywritten with particular&apos;reference to. the position of Canada.After the war there will be at least two great Powers in the world. Theremay be a third. The two will be the United States of America and Russia. AboutAmerica&apos;s formidable strength there can be no doubt. Russia&apos;s strength alsoseems to be assured. She may be too exhausted at the end of her present titanicstruggle to count immediately as a major Power. Or she may decline if she isfor any reason deprived of the constructive leadership of Stalin and his principallieutenants. But we must assume that she will maintain her present form. if she does another one or.two Five-Years Plans will make her a nation just aboutas formidable as the United States of America will be.The third possible major Power is Great Britain. But she cannot hold that position by herself. It is true that her moral authority after the war willprobably be greater amongst wise peoples than either America&apos;s or Russia&apos;s, thather resistance to Germany has shown how resilient her strength is, and that the battle of Britain proved the virtues of her citizens to be as fine as they ever were.But these qualities alone will not make her one of the greatest Powers. Weightof numbers and massive material wealth are also necessary ingredients for anypeople aspiring to possess first-class political authority in the world to-day. The45,000,000 citizens of Britain cannot compete in the former respect with130,000,000 Americans.or with the 150,000,000 people in the Union of soviet socialist Republics. Nor can the tiny, even though highly industrialised, island of Britain compete in the possession of material riches with the mighty UnitedStates and a fully developed Russia.If Britain stands alone after the war, she will gradually sink to the positionof a second-class Power in world affairs. But there is a means by which she canretain a position of equal authority with America and Russia. That is if shemakes herself the central member of a group of nations who are collectively as important as each of those two others. Such a group already exists. It is theBritish Commonwealth of Nations.[25191]SECRET Copy No. OtiW.P. (43) 115.March 22, 1943.WAR CABINET.
I trust that we shall so conduct our foreign policy that we also assume addedauthority as the virtual leader of many of the small democracies of Europe, andother small countries elsewhere. Many of them would like to follow us, if wepay reasonable heed to their opinions and susceptibilities. Their general support would add considerably to our influence and prestige. But that is a matter which lies primarily in the bands of those who preside over our destinies in10 Downing Street and in the Foreign Office, and which those of us who areservants of the Dominions Office cannot directly influence.- The combined influence of the nations of the British Commonwealth can beas great as that of the United States of America alone or of Russia alone. IfIndia becomes a free and equal Dominion co-operating generally with the othermembers of the Commonwealth in international affairs, the combination will beall the more impressive and powerful.I do not mean to suggest for one moment that our policy should be one of competition with the United States of America or Russia. I believe with all myheart in sincere co-operation with both of them. But it should be co-operation on terms of equality. Otherwise neither of these Powers will be particularlyconsiderate of our interests or opinions. We are blinding ourselves to facts ifwe do not realise that American policy and Russian policy may both be influenced,and even guided, from time to time by individuals or groups of American and russian economic or ideological &quot; Imperialists &quot; who do not feel urged to respector defend British interests in the world, and who will not necessarily agree with,our objectives in international affairs.It therefore seems to me that one of the basic principles governing our foreign policy should be to keep the Dominions as closely attached to ourselves and in accord with us in international affairs as possible. This means treatingthem constantly as true partners in the Commonwealth of Nations, and payingdue heed to their opinions.II.During the first two years of the war events developed in such a way thatthe Dominions felt more closely bound .to us by affection and admiration thanthey have perhaps ever felt. The Dominions recognised to the full the debt whichfree and civilised men everywhere owed to Britain for her stand against germany in 1940 and 1941. Since then there has been some deterioration in the relation-ship between them and us. I need not analyse the present position in detail. I need only mention one or two outstanding causes for the changed mood.Australia&apos;s confidence in the wisdom of British policy was, rightly orwrongly, badly shaken as a result of the events which reached their climax in thefall of Singapore. The Canadians who naturally were not so exposed to the temptation to &apos;&apos; panic &apos;&apos; about Japan remained much steadier, and avoidedrecrimination even when their troops in Hong Kong were lost to a man. but other developments began to shake their high confidence in Britain. The firstcause of this was the establishment in Washington of a series of importantCombined Boards, on which Great Britain and the United States alone were represented, to direct various aspects of the war on behalf of the United Nations without any prior consultation with the Dominions. In some cases they weregiven only meagre or even no prior information on the subject. ResponsibleCanadians resented this. It was not only that they regarded the failure toinform them properly as a gross discourtesy. They felt that non-consultation in matters which might be of great concern to them was a breach of the constitu-tion of the British Commonwealth of Nations. All the trouble which aroseafterwards could have been avoided if Canada (and the other Dominions) hadbeen taken into our confidence beforehand.No responsible Canadian doubts the wisdom of supreme authority in thesematters being largely concentrated during the war in the hands of Great Britainand the United States, plus Russia in so far as Russia is prepared to co-operate.But they do not think that in all matters the United Kingdom and the UnitedStates, with or without Russia, should have exclusive authority at the highest level. They believe that in certain matters where one or more of the smallernations have a very considerable practical interest those smaller nations shouldbe admitted to some share in authority. Moreover, they think it prudent as ageneral principle that representative smaller Powers should be given a part inthe higher direction of suitable aspects of the conduct of the war. Otherwise,they fear, the smaller Allies amongst the United Nations will feel that the
United Kingdom and the United States are attempting to establish a dictator-ship by the Big Powers in international affairs which would in the long: run causeprofound suspicion and dissatisfaction.It was for these reasons that the Canadians pressed strongly their own,particular claim to full membership with Britain and America on the combined production and Resources Board. When the British Government at first resistedtheir claim they were deeply disappointed. When that Government latersupported them and got the proposal accepted, they were. correspondinglypleased. Most Canadian Ministers and officials&quot; do not think that Canada hasas good a claim to representation at the highest level on the other war-time Com-bined Boards and Joint Organisations, and they are at present more or less content with the existing situation.But the same issue arises in connexion with the international organisationof the post-war world. The Canadians attach the greatest possible importanceto this. Concessions which they have sometimes readily made in the stress ofwar will not be at all agreeable to them in peace. The matter is already being discussed in the particular case of the proposed Post-war Relief and rehabilitation-tion Organisation. Canada whole-heartedly supports the United kingdom governments view that the Policy Committee should consist of seven members(i.e., the four &quot; Big Powers &quot; plus three smaller Powers) as opposed to theAmerican, Russian and Chinese contention that only the Big Powers should sit on the Committee. Britain&apos;s championship of the smaller Powers in this casehas helped greatly to restore Canada&apos;s confidence in Britain&apos;s leadership.But the Canadians disagree with the distinction which the Foreign office telegrams to Washington on the subject seem to draw between post-war&quot;economic &quot; questions and &quot; political and military &quot; questions, carrying as itdoes the suggestion that whereas representative smaller Powers should beadmitted to some share of high authority in the settlement of the former, thelatter questions should be kept under the exclusive direction of the Big Powers..The Canadians feel strongly that the same general arguments in favour of admitting some measure of &apos;&apos; small Power &apos;&apos; participation apply both to economic&apos;and political questions..Their opinions on the subject are prompted only in a minor degree by anyfeeling that national, prestige requires that the small Powers in general and canada in particular should have a place in the higher direction of international affairs. The main reason for them is a sincere desire that after all the efforts and sacrifices of this second World War a new International Order shall beestablished which is practical and which gains the confidence and co-operationof all reasonable nations, great and small, in the world. They themselves would,not wholly trust a direction of affairs in which supreme authority lay exclusivelyin the hands of Great Britain, the United States of America, Russia and China.With all respect, they do not feel convinced that the events of our times showthat these Powers have a monopoly of wisdom. They are certain that otherDominions and other smaller Powers would share their doubts. If the smallPowers collectively lose confidence in and withdraw co-operation from the great powers after the war, the new International Order will be crippled from thebeginning. That is the unhappy result which the Canadians seek to avoid byurging generally that in all matters, political as well as economic, the great powers, who admittedly must have the predominant authority, should have-associated with them in a reasonable if modest measure selected smaller Powers.They are no more ready than any other Government to produce here and now ablue-print of the proper post-war international organisation. But, broadly, Ithink they would urge the following general principles : 1. An international organisation in which all the nations, great and small,are regarded as constitutional equals, and in which nothing ofimportance can be done except with the consent of at least a large:majority, if not all, of these nations as was the case in the League ofNations has been proved unworkable.2. The Big Powers (i.e., Britain, the United States of America, Russia, andpossibly China) should have special authority and powers in thepolitical and economic direction of international affairs.3. But they should not have exclusive authority. Some of the smaller powers should be associated with them, even in the highest direction of affairs.This does not mean that the same group of small Powers wouldfunction in every case. A number of different international bodieswill be required to direct different aspects of political and economic[25191] &apos;        b2
affairs. In the Canadian view, the Big Powers should be members ofall these bodies, whilst the selection of a few smaller Powers to be associated with it in, probably, each case would vary from case to case and from time to time according to functional or other considerations.4. These various organisations should theoretically all draw their authority from some super-assembly of all the nations, which should not meetoften, and should have little, if any, executive power. But, in avery general way, it would create at least the appearance of the wholeeffort at international co-operation being authorised by all nations.III.I do not know what opinion on these matters is held in the other Dominions.But it seems probable that, in principle, they agree with Canada. I have already expressed the view that Britain can only remain a Power of first-class importance,capable of dealing on terms of equality with the United States of America and russia, if she is, in fact, the head of a harmonious and co-operative BritishCommonwealth of Nations. If she does not now champion wholeheartedly the reasonable claims of the smaller Powers, including the Dominions, I think she willforfeit the Dominions&apos; confidence, and the British Commonwealth will lose its strength.There is another way in which I believe the Dominions in general, and canadian  particular, can be invaluable partners with us in post-war international affairs.We must make Anglo-American relations as friendly as they can be. Indeed,nothing is more important than that Great Britain and the United States shouldbe true comrades in international affairs, understanding each other, toleratingeach other&apos;s weak points and having confidence in each other&apos;s strong points, and both inspired by a real will to co-operate together. This is not going to be easy to attain. I need not expand on that. We shall need much resource if we are to overcome some of the obstacles in the United States which operate against a friendly feeling towards Great Britain.I believe that Canada can play a distinct part in helping to get Anglo-American relations right. I used to think that the suggestion that Canadacould act as &apos;&apos; interpreter &apos;&apos; between Great Britain and the United States was just a pretty but pious sentiment which had no value except in polite perorationsuttered to Canadian audiences. But during the last two years in North AmericaJ have come to realise that it is indeed a practical and potent political truth. for various reasons the British and the Americans do not naturally or easily com-pletely understand each other. The Canadians, on the other hand, understandboth peoples well. They are a nation with deep-set British traditions living inan essentially North American environment. They know the British much betterthan the Americans do. and the Americans much better than the British do.Americans will talk to Canadians with a frankness which they use with verv few people from Britain, and they will accept criticism from Canadians which theywould resent from our own countrymen. In fact, Canadians can often be helpfulthird partners in Anglo-American discussions.They will not be any the less useful to us in this sphere because on mostmatters they think and feel as we do rather than as the Americans do. Some-times in an Anglo-American controversy they will aeree with the Americansinstead of with us. But much more often they will take our side. I have beeninterested to notice how frequently when there is some, subject of major or minordisagreement between the Americans and ourselves the Prime Minister here,Members of his Cabinet and their principal advisers have agreed with the Britishand not the American point of view. Their opinions, which get a good hearing-and count for something with Americans, would most often support our side ofan Anglo-American argument. As, there are bound to be many Anglo-American-arguments after the war, this fact is well worth keeping in mind.I should like to add this. Canadian representatives can offer us something more than general sentimental support in these matters. Their ability is of a hio-horder. We have under-rated Canada&apos;s quality in the past. We, in Britain feltreasonably confident before the war that the Dominion would be with us if we o-otinto trouble. But I doubt whether any of us expected that Canada&apos;s&apos;contribution in war would have the magnificent power and generosity which it now displaysSome of her achievements-such as her part in the vast Commonwealth air training Plan, her varied munitions production, and her two &quot;billion dollargifts &quot; have far exceeded our expectations.
I believe that the strength and wisdom of her contribution in international discussions and actions after the war will likewise surprise us. The fact is that canada has &quot;grown-up &quot; in the last few years, despite all her internal difficulties;she has found herself. Amongst her leading public servants are men of finequalities. Some of her Ministers have marked ability. There is also in Ottawaa group of high officials who are still comparatively young mostly in their earlyor middle forties-and, whose influence over Canadian policy is and will continueto be at least as important as that of Ministers, whose tenure of office is moreprecarious. They are the heads of Government Departments and other officialbodies. They are able, enlightened and forceful. If we do not discourage them.,but on the contrary encourage them as well as their Ministers to be our colleagues in affairs, we shall find them good allies..   &apos; -&apos; &apos;&apos; .     &apos; iv.      ,It is easy to write down this general principle of Commonwealth co-operation.Admittedly it will be more difficult to realise it fully in practice. For one thing,at the same time as they are anxious to co-operate with us in international affairs,the Dominions are still hyperconscious of their status as free nations, and theyare sometimes still watchful lest their association with us should appear not freebut slavish. Therefore, on the occasions when they do not happen to agree with us they are over-inclined to tell us and the world so in a loud voice. Also, theyare sometimes shy about entering into forms of co-operation with us which might appear to non-comprehending foreigners to compromise their status of freeequality with us. The Canadians can be particularly sensitive about this sort of thing when they think that the Americans might misunderstand.But this element in the situation is still natural at such a comparatively early stage of the evolution of the British Commonwealth of Nations. - If we arestatesmanlike in Britain we shall recognise it and make allowances for it. Itdoes not in the least alter the main fact that the Dominions would dearly liketo be our partners in international affairs, generally following our lead and supporting us, if we will make that possible for them.For these reasons we should do everything possible to strengthen the tiesbetween Britain and, the Dominions, to improve the machinery of consultation and co-operation between us and them, and between Dominion and Dominion, andto encourage a close harmony of opinion in the Commonwealth on international affairs. Various actions can contribute to these ends. The time has come whensome new methods of promoting the unity of the Commonwealth can be developed.I here make only three or four suggestions which seem to me important. They are by no means an exhaustive list:  1. It would be of immense advantage if, after the war, the King and Queenwere to pay regular visits to the different Commonwealth nations.The periodic performance by the King and Queen, in person, of theirroyal functions in each Dominion would have an unique and powerfuleffect in making the nations of the Commonwealth happily conscious that they are all members of one family. Their Majesties&apos; position,qualities and popularity make it possible for them now to performas great a service to Britain and the Empire as any monarchs haveever done in British history.2. Save where it may be quite impracticable, we should be careful to consult the Dominions on all matters of major importance in international affairs before we take our own final decisions on policy. The Canadianshighly appreciate the remarkable efficiency with which the UnitedKingdom Government have generally kept them informed on manyaspects of the war and have consulted them on various matters. Butthe lack of consultation in the case of the establishment of the combined Boards caused the troubles which I have already mentioned.In war-time Canada is not prepared to make a public fuss about these things. But the resentment which this and some other cases have caused abides. It rankles, and we shall probably hear about it later.Let us avoid any more provocations of this kind. Quite apart fromthe fact that prior consultation is constitutionally required by the&quot; Commonwealth system, it seems to me that it also produces positivelygood results. We have had two recent examples of this. Thediscussions on certain aspects of post-war policy which took place between British Commonwealth officials in London in October greatlypleased the Dominion Governments, resulted in&apos;more community of
outlook between the United Kingdom and Dominion Governmentsthan might otherwise have been the case and, I understand, producedsome modifications in detail of the United Kingdom&apos;s draft proposalswhich were improvements. Likewise our exchanges of communica-tions with the Dominions Governments about the draft statement on colonial Policy which Lord Halifax afterwards presented toMr. Cordell Hull were welcomed by the Dominions, resulted in aconsiderable measure of Commonwealth agreement, and produced afinal draft which, if I may say so, seemed in general a better state-ment of our Colonial Policy, and in particular one more likely to commend itself to the Americans, than our own original draft.In this connection I would point out a significant development.If such a communication as that on Colonial Policy had been sentto the Canadian Government before the war, they would probably havelet it pass without comment. They would have been shy of adoptingany attitude or of assuming even the slightest indirect responsibility in connection with our Colonial Policy. Their readiness to offer ustheir opinions and help in this case is symptomatic of a greaterrealisation of the obligations of Commonwealth partnership, whichshould be encouraged. I feel sure from talks with Ministers and officials here that, if we continue to take them into our confidence and to consult them on such matters, they will overcome some of theirpast caution and be more and more co-operative with us.3. After the war United Kingdom Ministers should take advantage of the case and speed of air travel to visit the Dominions quite frequently.This should of course be a two-way traffic, or indeed a three-waytraffic, Dominions Ministers visiting not only London but also other dominion capitals. Such personal contacts would do much to promote the sense of partnership in the Commonwealth, and to establish under-standing and a close harmony of policy. Nor should London beregarded any longer as the capital of the Commonwealth. BothImperial Conferences and ad hoc meetings of commonwealth ministers to discuss specific questions should be held more frequentlyin Ottawa, Canberra and other Dominion capitals, as well as inLondon. In particular there should be more frequent and thoroughconsultations on Foreign Policy.4. There should be similar habitual exchanges of visits between highofficials of the British Commonwealth Governments. As I have indicated, Canada (and no doubt other Dominions also) has aremarkably able group of youngish public servants. The morecontact they have with our Ministers and principal officials the better,from many points of view. I would not rule out the possibility ofsome exchange of civil servants for temporary periods of work in eachother&apos;s capitals, though perhaps the political nationalism of someDominions would not let them go quite so far as that.There are other, more detailed ways in which the organisation of co-operation and consultation can be improved, but I need not burden these notes with furthersuggestions. The time seems ripe for a careful review of the whole subject witha view to giving the maximum cohesion and strength to the Commonwealth inthe world after the war.February 23, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
