<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/180/10 images: 120-124</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(74)T35 COPY NO   8019 November 1974CABINETCHANNEL tunnel memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Environment...&quot; - ii.1. In the spring, we agreed that we should keep open our options overthe Channel Tunnel by reintroducing the hybrid Channel Tunnel Bill(CC(74) 7th Conclusions, Minute^),2. This entails no commitment beyond the present Phase II of the project, and when we introduced the Bill last April we made it absolutelyclear that before Parliament was asked next year to decide whether toproceed with actually constructing the Tunnel (Phase III), a fullreassessment would be made.    Phase II provides for such a reassessmentand this is being augmented by advice from a group of independent adviserschaired by Sir Alec Cairncross.3. Owing to the General Election the Bill did not complete its passage through Parliament.    But on Monday of last week Parliament approvedMotions enabling us to reintroduce it while preserving its completed stages.THE RAIL LINK4. But one major change has occurred since our discussions last spring.A rail link between London and the coastal terminal of the Tunnel has alwaysbeen an integral part of the scheme - without it, indeed, the Tunnel would do nothing to help the British railway system in the way that most of us desire.5. Unfortunately the cost of the rail link has increased significantly.Last year, it was estimated to cost  123 million at February 1973 prices.British Rail have recently informed us of an increase in this estimate to 373 million at May 1974 prices, or more than double in real terms.    this estimate excludes additional environmental works which I may well have to concede in Surrey and Kent; the greater part of the cost of compensation forinjurious affection under the Land Compensation Act 1973; and the cost of enabling the link to carry freight which was admittedly not previously envisaged.    It is clearly impossible to contemplate an investment of this magnitude in the rail link.    British Rail are exploring the prospects of
negotiating with the Continental railway administrations, who still stand to benefit considerably from the traffic arising from the link, a joint approach to financing it which might restore its viability.    But I do not believe thatthe negotiations will produce capital assistance which would make theburden on the Exchequer tolerable.6.        More to the point, British Rail are investigating urgently the feasibility of a lower-cost rail option, and my Department hascommissioned a parallel study.7.        The other change since last spring is that our Parliamentaryback-bench opinion has turned more strongly against the Tunnel^1 thoughmore for emotional than for rational reasons.OPTIONS OPEN8. One option, obviously tempting, would be to seize the opportunityto cancel the Tunnel now.    I am Strongly opposed to this for the following reasons:la It would give the impression that we were meekly submitting to (largely ill-informed) back-bench pressure.2. It would make nonsense of the concept of the Cairncrossstudy.3, It would not mean any significant financial saving.4. It would be a grossly irresponsible way of conductingGovernment business and taking major investment decisions.    as opposed to the rail link, the cost of constructing the Tunnel itselfseems likely to hold reasonably steady in real terms.    Therefore,many intelligent, observers still think that a Tunnel, combined with a lower-cost rail link, would make economic sense.    (That is, that itwould cost less, in terms of economic resources, than thealternative investment in more ferries, hovercraft, port facilities,expensive roads, aircraft and airport facilities; for we havesomehow to carry the prospective increase in freight arid passengersacross the Channel.    In other words (to put the argument in itscurrently popular form), we could ultimately afford more houses and schools and hospitals if we built the Tunnel than if we spent evenmore on alternative forms of transport investment).5. I do not know if this is true, which is why I still have an openmind.    This is precisely what the Phase II studies are about and whatthe Cairncross Group is set up to advise upon.    It would in my view be quite wrong to cancel unilaterally before we have this furtheradvice.
PROPOSED COURSE OF ACTION9.        Quite apart from the Cairncross report, 1976 or some later yearcould well (given the need to investigate alternative and cheaper railoptions) be a more propitious year in which to start building the Tunnelthan 1975 looks like being.    I therefore propose the following course ofaction.    We should approach our French partners and tell them that wehave been taken aback by the new estimate for the rail link and do not see how we can proceed with a Hnk of the kind envisaged in the Treaty.    Weare, however, investigating with British Rail the feasibility of a lower-costrail option,    This will mean delay of a year (and preferably longer) fromnext summer before any decision is taken about whether to proceed withPhase III (which is the final and critical decision).    I cannot predict the outcome of these negotiations; it will not be easy to persuade either theFrench Government or the companies to accept postponement without commitment to going ahead with Phase HI by a specific date,10.       I would immediately announce in Parliament that we are notproceeding with the high speed rail link for which we have been planning,and are having discussions with the French Government about a new time-table for the project.    But in order to keep our options open, we shall,subject to anything unexpected which emerges from negotiations with theFrench, need to go ahead with the remaining stages of the Channel TunnelBill so that the Treaty can be ratified as early as possible in 1975,(Strictly speaking, the Treaty must be ratified by the end of the year, butthe French Government will, in all likelihood, not be unduly disturbed abouta slightly later date, provided that we are visibly seeking the requisiteParliamentary authority for ratification).11.        I would then bring the matter back to Cabinet some time next year for further consideration when we have harder information about:a. The reaction of the French to our request for a delay of ayear or more.b. The preliminary results of the investigation of alternativelow-cost rail options.c. The report of the Cairncross Group.12.       British Governments in the past have taken decisions on majorinvestment projects in a frivolous and insouciant spirit (for exampleConcorde and Maplin).    I hope and propose that we should do better in thecase of the Tunnel.    It will be tiresome to stand firm until we have moreup-to-date evidence for or against.    But I am prepared to accept this; and,I hope, so will the unfortunate Chief Whip.3
CONCLUSIONS13.        I invite my colleagues to agree:a. That the Channel Tunnel Bill be reintroduced on Report as early as practicable.    Before reintroduction, a statement would bemade about the Government^ attitude to the high speed rail link andour request to the French foi a yearTs delay.b. That there should be urgent investigation into the feasibility of a lower-cost rail option.c. That there should b&apos;e cons-citations with our partners in theTunnel project over the implications of the change of plan for therail link, and we should seek agreement to such&apos;delay over decisions about Phase III of the project as may consequently be necessary.    Ishould of course inform the French of our problems in advance ofthe statement at a,d. That I should bring the whole matter back to the Cabinet nextyear.ACDepartment of the Environment19 November 19744


</content>
</cab>
