<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/71/4 images: 40-47</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT;(81) 24th COPY NOinclusionsCABINET-CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Dowring Street onTHURSDAY 18 JUNE 1981at 10. 30 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MPPrime Ministere Rt Hon William Whitelaw MPcretary of State for the Home Departmente Rt Hon Lord Carringtoncretary of State for Foreign andmmonwealth Affairse Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph MPcretary of State for Industrye Rt Hon Lord Soamesrd President of the Councile Rt Hon John Nott IvIPcretary of State for Defencee Rt Hon Michael Heseltine MPcretary of State for the Environmente Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MPcretary of State for Walese Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MPcretary of State for Social Servicese Rt Hon David Howell MPcretary of State for EnergyThe Rt Hon Lord Hail shamLord ChancellorThe Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MPChancellor of the ExchequerThe Rt Hon Francis Pym MPChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster andPaymaster GeneralThe Rt Hon James Prior MPSecretary of State for EmploymentThe Rt Hon Peter Walker MPMinister of Agriculture, Fisheries and FoodThe Rt Hon George Younger MPSecretary of State for ScotlandThe Rt Hon Humphrey Atkins MPSecretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon John Biffen MPSecretary of State for TradeThe Rt Hon Mark Carlisle QC MPSecretary of State for Education and ScienceiSECRET
SECRETThe Rt Hon Norman Fowler MPSecretary of State for TransportThe Rt Hon Leon Brittan QC MPChief Secretary, TreasuryItem1.2.3.ALSO PRESENT4.The Rt Hon Mickael Jopling MPParliamentary Secretary, TreasurySECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMr M D M Franklin (Items 2 and 3)Mr R L Wade-Gery (Items 2-4)Mr R M Hastie-Smith (Item 4)Mr W N Hyde (Item 1)Mr L J Karris (Item 1)C ONT ENT SSubjectPARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSFOREIGN AFFAIRSAfghanistanArab/ IsraelIranCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSSheepmeatJoint Council of Finance, Economic and EmploymentMinistersCouncil of Economics and Finance MinistersTHE DEFENCE PROGRAMMEPage1111223iiSECRET
SECRETRLIAMENTARY   1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theFAIRS Rouse of Commons during the following week.FOREIGNAFFAIRSAfghanistanPreviousPreference:CC(81) 4thConclusions,Minute 22. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatthe Government were in process of launching a new initiative onAfghanistan.    The initiative had the support of Britain&apos;s EuropeanCommunity partners in poHtical co-operation, and it was intended that itshould be publicly launched at the meeting of the European Council at theend of June.Lrab/Israel3reviousleference;;C(81) 22ndConclusions,fcilinute 2anTeviousPerence:(81) 22nd|onclusions,inute 2THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that followingthe Israeli attack on Iraq&apos;s nuclear reactors there had been intenseactivity at the United Nations, where a crucial vote was likely to betaken later that day.    The Iraqis wanted a resolution which did morethan merely condemn Israel, but too extreme a draft would attract anAmerican veto, and in some circumstances it might even be impossibleto avoid a British veto.     The situation was a delicate one for theWestern powers and there was a real danger of alienating Arab opinion.He would be consulting the Prime Minister further on how Britain shouldvote.     Meanwhile the Prime Minister of Israel, Mr Begin, had renewedhis threats to destroy Syrian missile sites in Lebanon unless they weredi s mantled.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that theint^_nal situation in Iran was very disquieting.     There appeared to be nofuture for President Bani-Sadr, who for all his faults was a compara-tively moderate man.    The Ayatollah Beheshti, who was likely toemerge as the country&apos;s real ruler, was an extreme fanatic in the mouldof Colonel Qadhafi of Libya.    He was an Islamic fundamentalist, not aCommunist;  but the fundamentalist regime was likely in due course toprovoke its own downfall and might well then be replaced by the extremeLeft.The Cabinet -Took note.1SECRET
CONFIDENTIALpOUMJNITY[FFAIRSJheepmeatPreviousfceference:fcc(8l) 20thConclusions,Minute 2ioint Councilif Finance,Economic andEmploymentMinisters3. THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD saidthat, at the meeting of the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) on 15 June,the French Government, with German support, had continued to resistchanges in the clawback arrangements on exports of sheeprneat which hadformed part of this year&apos;s price package.    He had therefore maintaineda reserve on other elements of that package.    He was continuing topress the Commission tD find a suitable solution.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the Joint Council ofFinance, Economic and Employment Ministers on 11 June had passed offwithout difficulty.    Although the Belgians had shown some interest inholding another Joint Council, no such meeting would take place duringthe British Presidency.3reviousteference:;C(81) 21stConclusions,finute 3Council ofEconomicsnd Financ efinisters&apos;revious(eference;!C(81) 12thinclusions,finute 3THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER reported that discussion atthe Council of Ministers (ECOFIN) on 15 June on the problem of UnitedStates interest rates had been reasonably harmonious.    A sensible linehad been agreed which the Prime Minister would be able to put to theUnited States Government at the forthcoming Ottawa Summit meeting.The Council had also made useful progress on the Directive on Non-lifeInsurance Services and there now seemed a prospect that agreementcouM be reached during the British Presidency.The Cabinet -Took note.2CONFIDENTIAL
SECRET[the defence(programme&apos;r eviousInference:|C(81) 12thanclusions,linute 54. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Secretary of State forDefence (C(81) 31) and the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C(81) 33) aboutthe future defence programme and the financial basis on which it shouldbe planned.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that the basic probleunderlying his proposals was the fact that peace was becoming more andmore expensive to maintain.    The present defence programme was over-ambitious in relation to the resources available.    There was animmediate problem in relation to the level of current expenditure whichwould probably exceed the existing cash limit if drastic action was nottaken to curb it.    It would be necessary to impose a system of cashrationing on defence industries.    He could not accommodate increasesin armed forces&apos; pay within cash limits;   either the cash limits wouldhave to be adjusted or the Government&apos;s commitment on armed forces&apos;pay would have to be modified.    There were more serious problems inthe longer term.    It was unrealistic to believe that the resourcesavailable for defence c&amp;uld be significantly increased beyond the 3 percent growth in real terms to which the Government was alreadycommitted.    It was therefore necessary to make major changes tofuture plans in the defence programme.    Priority was accorded in hisproposals to the preservation of the Trident programme, various weaponprojects and building up combat stocks, particularly in Germany wherea dangerous lowering of the nuclear threshold had taken place. Itwould be necessary to come out of the military aircraft business afterthe completion of the Tornado programme and to relinquish suchimportant projects as the British heavyweight torpedo replacementprogramme.    So far as possible projects involving high technologywould be preserved but many equipment projects would have to be cut.In regard to the future force structure, his preferred proposals wouldinvolve reducing the British Army of the Rhine (BAOR) from fourdivisons to three, without a reduction of front-line effectives, andcutting regular manpower by up to 10, 000 men.    Any further reductionsin this direction would in his judgment place the cohesion of theAriance at risk.    The defence of the United Kingdom had been neglectedin the past and some additions were necessary in this area. Hisproposals therefore included running on the Phantom aircraft, divertingTornados to air defence, increasing the capability for protective miningand enlarging the Territorial Army (which would be a popular measureamong the Government&apos;s supporters).     The main brunt of the cutswould fall on the Royal Navy, particularly the surface fleet and itslogistic support.    Chatham Dockyard would be closed and Portsmouthrun down to a reserve role.    It would be necessary to give furtherthought to the future of Gibraltar Dockyard in the light of the argumentsput forward by the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary in correspon-dence.    In their present form the proposals would involve reducing thesurface fleet by some 20 hulls and declaring redundancies among Armyand Naval manpower     It might be possible, at some slight extra cost,SECRET
SECRETto reduce the severity of these measures by putting some olderfrigates into reserve and achieving the rundown in manpower bynatural wastage.     In the immediate future there was no roomwhatever in the programme for manoeuvre and it would be impossibleto accept a further squeeze on the volume of the programme duringthe process of translating it into cash terms.    It would be difficult,but he believed possible, to persuade Allies and the Governmentsupporters to accept the changes to the future programme implied inhis Defence Line (II); these, in his judgment, would actuallyrepresent an improvement in this country&apos;s military effectiveness.He could see no possibility of securing acceptance of the changesimplied by the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s proposals.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that he supported thegeneral approach of the Secretary of Strte for Defence&apos;s review, butits proposed future level of expenditure on defence was more than thecountry could afford.     Despite the high priority accorded by theGovernment to its defence programme, it was on this year&apos;s budgetproposals that the Government had come closest to defeat so far inthe House of Commons.    Britain was spending 5. 2 per cent of GrossDomestic Product on defence, which was already more than eitnerFrance or West Germany;   the Secretary of State for Defence&apos;sproposals would raise this level to nearly 6 per cent.     It was notrealistic in economic or political terms co plan at this stage torcontinuing major increases in defence expenditure to or beyond themid-1980s, and to do so was not even in the interests of the defenceprogramme, as a need for further radical reviews would undoubtedlyarise.     It would be preferable for the 3 per cent growth in realterms not to be extended beyOxid 1983-84;  if the Cabinet consideredthat such an extension should be made, the cost of it would hav j to bemet from other programmes.In discussion there was general agreement with the broad shape ofthe proposals contained in C(81) 31 and summarised in Defence Line(II) in Annex A to that memorandum.     These proposals might just besaleable to the Government&apos;s supporters tnd to Britain&apos;s Allies.There would be no possibility of selling the more severe proposalswhich must inevitably flow from the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;salternative financial basis.     Even so there was likely to beconsiderable opposition among the supporters of the Government,either on general defence grounds or because the proposals createdparticular constituency difficulties.The following were among the main points made in the course of thediscussion -4SECRET
SECRETa. It was regrettable but inevitable that the timing of thedecisions which the Cabinet was asked to take made itimpossible to relate the implications of the proposals to theirpossible impact on other public expenditure programmes.b. The proposals before the Cabinet would certainlyincrease the pressure upon the Government to abandon theTrident programme.c. The political presentation of the proposals would beeased if it could be shown that they were supported byprofessional military advice, that the resultant programmewould represent an improvement of military effectiveness,and if redundancies (as opposed to wastage) in Service man-power could be avoided.d. In the process of consulting Allies it would be desirableif the Supreme Allied Commander Europe (SACEUR) andSupreme Allied Commander Atlantic (SACLANT) could beconsulted, as their views would be influential.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the highest priority must be given to the defenceprogramme, and accepted that that entaiied lower priority to o^herexpenditure programmes.     The Government was not entitled tocommit itself to figures for the defence programme beyond 1985-86.With this qualification the Cabinet approved the general thrust of theSecretary of State for Defence&apos;s proposals as set out in C(81) 31,including the second resource option as set out in Annex A andAppendix J, and endorsed the figures up to and including 1985-86, asa basis for consultation with Allies.    So far as possible theSecretary of State for Defence should implement his proposals toreduce the size of the armed services without declaring redundanciesinService manpower.   Like every other programme the defenceprogramme should be expressed in cash terms, not in volume terms.The Cabinet agreed that there should be a realistic translation of thedefence programme up to 1985-86 from volume to cash terms;  but intaking account of relative price effects for defence expenditure itwould be important not to countenance excessive increases in over-head rates and wages of the kind which some defence contractors hadrecently been seeking to apply.     The cash figures for defence, likethose for other programmes, would be for review and final settlementat the conclusion of the current Public Expenditure Survey. Therewere a number of points of detail which the Secretary of State forDefence would need to discuss bilaterally with colleagues. Unlessoffsetting savings could be found for any proposals which, afterdiscussion, remained unacceptable to the particular colleagueconcerned, the matter should be referred to the Defence and Oversea5SECRET
SECRETPolicy Committee for resolution.    It was important tnat there shouldbe no public disclosure of the conclusions reached by the Cabinetuntil the Secretary of State for Defence had completed his consul-tation with Allies and made a statement to Parliament.The Cabinet -1. Authorised the Secretary of State for Defenceto enter into consultations with Allies on the basisof the broad thrust of his proposals as set out inC(81) 31, and of the resource line set out asDefence Line (II) in Annex A and Appendix J toC(81) 3i up to and including 1985-86.2. Recognised and accepted the implicationsthat these conclusions in relation to the defenceprogramme would have for subsequent decisions onreductions in other fields of public expenditure.3. Invited the Secretary of State for Defence -i. To discuss points of detail arising fromhis proposals bilaterally with colleagues andto bring these issues to the Defence andOversea Policy Committee or find alternativesavings if they could not be resolved.ii. To prepare drafts of an announcementto Parliament and of supporting documentation,for agreement with the Ministers concerned.Cabinet Office18 June 1981SECRET6

</content>
</cab>
