<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/78/1 images: 16-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1(84)KlusiohsTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO 65CONFIDENTIALrCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 12 JANUARY 1984at 10.30 amThePRESENT^Hon Margaret Thatcher MP Prime Minister ord^p Hon viscount Whitelaw esident of the CouncilRt H n Nigel &apos;CellRt B &apos;etarteller^ Nicholas Edwards MPgel Lawson MP of the Exchequer n James Prior MP rv of State for Northern Irelandl n Michael Heseltine MP ttry of state for Defenceeta*,ry of State for Wales he Rtotj pj? n Johri Biff en MP tlvy Seal^ RtVel? n Lord Cockfield r of the Duchy of LancasterhiSteJ n Michael Jopling MP f Agriculture, Fisheries and FoodThe Rt Hon Leon Brittan QC MP Secretary of State for the Home DepartmentThe Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph MP Secretary of State for Education and ScienceRt Hon Peter Walker MP tary of State for Energyon George Younger MP Sec^t^V of State for ScotlandThe Rt^*? Patrick Jenkin MP Secretar^^) State for the EnvironmentThe Rt Hon&lt;^orman Fowler MP Secretary o &gt; State for Social ServicesThe Rt Hon Tom Kin Secretary of StatThe Rt Hon Peter Re Chief Secretary, Trrliame ? John Wakeham MPRtThe Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP Secretary of State for TransportTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTntary Secretary, TreasuryMr Malcolm Rifkind MP Minister of State, Foreign and Commonwealth OfficeMr John Gummer MPMinister of State, Department of Employment4CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL1.2.3.4.Is.PARLIAMENTAIRSSECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMr A D S Goodall (Items 2-5)Mr D F Williamson (Items 2 and 3)Mr C J S Brearley (Item 1)Mr R Watson (Item 1)CONTENTSSubjectHousing Rates Bill FOREIGN AFFAIRS Middle East NigeriaSouthern Africa COMMUNITY AFFAIRSCommunity Budget and United K&quot;Agriculture NORTHERN IRELAND ECONOMIC AFFAIRSiiCONFIDENTIAL
ICONFIDENTIALBilldieEast&lt; s;ons 1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House of Commons during the following week.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the debate on housing benefit on theposition&apos;s Supply day on 19 January would give further opportunities criticism of the Government&apos;s planned reductions in this area, ently  3.4 billion was being spent and one in three households d the benefit.    She understood that some of these had above incomes.    This level of expenditure was unacceptably high, t resulted in part from a higher rate of take-up following anisation of the benefit arrangements and from increases ouse rents and rates.    She was most concerned that the be presented clearly and that those sections of the h argued for cuts in public expenditure in general, but against tWe 5 per cent cut in housing benefit, should be brought to realise what large sums were involved.   This was only.one feature, but a signif ican-t f eature, of the problem of&apos;containing welfare expenditure whi^h        general to Western European countries. This problem had been well ^discussed   in a recent report by the Organisationpn and Development, which could be quoted in &apos;s campaign to promote public discussion 1 with the rising level of social welfare seful to co-ordinate a campaign of ousing benefit on the lines of what had &apos; .Rates Bill.for Economic Co-o support of the Go of the issue of how expenditure.     It mi speeches by Ministers successfully been done oTHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THEc^^0NMENT said that he was grateful for the contribution colleagues (4^au^ade by their speeches.   He would be circulating updated briefing tb^r^y.    Statements in support of the Government&apos;s action would shortl^/fSe^forthcoming from a number of bodies representing trade and incThe Cabinet -Took note.2.      THE MINISTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND COMMONWI (MR RIFKIND), said that the Foreign and Commonwe^ at present in the Middle East.   He had visited Egy  10 January and Saudi Arabia from 10 to 11 January, a^; seeing President Assad of Syria in Damascus that day. and Jedda he had encountered strong criticism of the St} Co-operation Agreement between the United States and Isri speech the previous day restating the Government&apos;s positic Middle East conflict in standard terms had received widespi publicity.    In Jordan, Parliament had been recalled after a period of abeyance in an attempt by King Hussein to regain the initiative in the peace process and put pressure on Mr Yasser Ar^_ the leader of the Palestine Liberation Organisation, to go to Ammanx^/CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALKing Hussein himself had been admitted to hospital and was likely to be  out  of action for some days.    In the Lebanon, President Gemayel&apos;s new Security Plan, which would allow deployment by Lebanese Government forces outside Beirut, had suffered a setback and its implementation was uncertain.    The Foreign and Commonwealth Office was in touch with the other contributors to the multinational force (MNF) about tions for widening the involvement of the United Nations in the anon;    and the issues would be considered by the Foreign Ministers the four MNF contributors in the margins of the Europeanament Conference in Stockholm on 16 January.   There had been gaap^keant reductions in both the Italian and French contingents toMfhe^ENF, but the Lebanese Government wanted it to remain, and the Saudd^OtaS made it clear that this was their wish too.Hi eriaTHE PRitfE/MT-NISTER, summing up the discussion, noted that the Americanvcontingent to the MNF had now withdrawn within its base and there was no activity on the part of the French.    The British contigent continued to carry out its prescribed tasks and to attract widespread admLr^&amp;Lon and respect.    It must continue to be the Government&apos;s obnecyive to have the MNF replaced by a United Nations force.   But, srfteV^t&amp;e Secretary General of the United Nations could not take action rid^J^His. end without a request from the host country as well as an appropriate Security Council Resolution, agreement must first be reached/ meen the four contributing Governments which could then be f ollowen^a^Nb concerted demarche to President Gemayel.COMMONWEALTH OFFICE, said that Nigeria had been staged byt action by more radical junior ended and political parties ari and some of his colleagues ^ng well treated.   The new nuity of policy especially nternational Monetary Fund on rescheduling Nigeria&apos;s debts were t&amp;Xr.esume.    The new Government had sent a delegation to a number of capitals, including London where it was expected the following day.   The British High CommissionerTHE MINISTER OF STATE, FORE the recent military coup d&apos;e&quot; senior officers apparently to ranks.    The constitution had be had been banned.   Former Presiden were in detention but were apparen Nigerian Government was emphasising in the economic field, and talks withm Lagos had been instructed to have normal wo the new regime.   No official British comment volunteered, but if asked spokesmen would exp Government&apos;s disappointment at the overthrow of elected civilian regime.    It appeared that altho had had genuine majority support in last year&apos;s Ni election, there had been little enthusiasm within Ni Government, which had been increasingly regarded as well as corrupt.    The indications were that the change had been accepted by most of the population with reliefcontacts with coup had been British ocraticallysident Shagari general or his ive as imeCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE MINISTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH OFFICE, said thatthe last few weeks had seen major military and diplomatic developmentsin Southern Africa.   A major South African offensive into SouthernAngola - the largest since 1976 - had been mounted to pre-empt theannual infiltration into Namibia by the South West African People&apos;sOrganisation and to destroy a Soviet supplied missile base.having achieved their objectives, the South African forces were nowbi^Lng withdrawn.   Meanwhile the United Nations Security Council had  J opted two Resolutions strongly condemning South Africa. TheU/Wp^d Kingdom had supported the first Resolution, which called for thewfthd^a^al of South African forces from Angola, but had abstained(t6%etKeV with the United States) on the second because it came closeto c^&amp;&gt;*iJk f r economic sanctions against South Africa and appearedto encbireage military support for Angola from Cuba and the Soviet Union.ProspecNLg/for progress now centred on the South African Government&apos;soffer toMdisengage from Angola from 31 January 1984 and to observean extendable truce;    and on the resumption of contact between Angolaand the United States, which would start with a working meeting betweenthe two sides yfP^&amp;ve Verde the following week at which all relevantissues were to( e &lt;j)iscussed including the possibility of Cuban withdrawalThe Cabinet Took note.
CONFIDENTIALUsions3.     THE MINISTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH OFFICE (MR RIFKIND), reported that, contrary to some press reports, the meeting on 6~7 January between the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and the President of the European Commission, Monsieur Thorn, had been useful, onsieur Thorn had been concerned that the French Presidency might see e European Council in March only as a staging post to a laterlement and had been stressing to French Ministers that decisions, least significant progress, were needed in March.    It appeared that ench were suggesting in contacts with the Commission and other tates that the United Kingdom would be ready to accept a time-d degressive solution to the problem of budget inequity. The Cf a*pd Commonwealth Secretary had made clear once again that there was no^j^^i^K for this suggestion, which was not acceptable.    On the dispute^-\SMount of the risk-sharing element of the United Kingdom&apos;s 1982 refunds, ^me^Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary had now written formally to the Comn&amp;ssion.   Monsieur Thorn had not been completely negative, and had expressed readiness to act as an &quot;honest broker&quot; on this matter. It was suggested that this might be because the United Kingdom had expressed the firm view that&gt;^the Community was now in default on this payment, although it was j/cin^d out that other member states did not accept that they were in defaiISHERIES AND FOOD reported that, at the) on 9-10 January, there had been general ncy that the agricultural issues raised ast summer, which had been discussed Is leading up to the European Council rward in the Agriculture Council, icultural spending would continue to udgetary questions. The ver the Commission&apos;s proposals ere expected to be presented ^^4&gt; probably containing mainly ^of Ministers (Agriculture) ricultural structure. These measures had expired, and the Council did^ot reach agreement either on new measures or on a roll-over.    Since the schemes were no longer in existence, there would be no payments to farmers in the immediate future of these structural aids, including capital grai/fXs?ipd some aids in less favoured areas.THE MINISTER OF AGRICUL&apos; Council of Ministers (Agric? agreement with the French in the Commission&apos;s proposa unsuccessfully in the Specia in December, should now be car The strict financial guideline be treated with the other financi agricultural work programme would a on agricultural prices for 1984-85, the following week and would be restr freezes on farm support prices.    The Co had also discussed Community measures onThe Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food al United Kingdom lorries carrying lamb (including a co Zealand lamb) had been stopped by French farmers, who the lamb and distributed it to hospitals and other ch organisations, and apparently intended to make the Britis their lorries to Paris as part of a demonstration. Simila&quot; taken place recently against Dutch and Danish lorries in Fr United Kingdom had immediately made representations to the F authorities.   He had himself spoken to the French Minister of Agriculture, Monsieur Rocard, who had apologised and given an as that instructions had been sent from Paris to the local police to that the lorries were released.CONFIDENTIALrted that two nt of New en some ofers take ents had The
CONFIDENTIALThe Cabinet -Took note,83?THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said that he had visited p the previous day for talks with the Irish Minister of Justice, nan.    The Minister had at first been nervous of being put underessure to take more effective action on the security front, but 1 atmosphere had been reasonably good and the meeting had agreement on a number of measures to improve co-operation olice forces in the Irish Republic and Northern Ireland, appointment of Liaison Officers to the respective Police Talks would also take place between officials of the two pn possible ways to strengthen the law on incitement to oth countries.    Security co-operation remained a politicallyBthe* resufc betwee includi Headquart Government violence insensitive matter for the Irish Government, and the hostile receptionulation to units of the Irish Army and the Garda security operations in County Leitrim showed that surface south as well as north of the Irish nt British interest to ensure that there was no d order throughout the island of Ireland and Irish Government in pursuit of that d terrorist murders continued at a reduced eful meeting with the leaders of the eaux) and the Democratic Unionist Party re had been no breach of the As a result of that meeting he had nding in Northern Ireland that an r of crossing points on the border and from the Irish Republic.given by the loca Siochana during anarchy was clos border.    It was an general breakdown o to co-operate closely objective.    In Northern level.    He had recently had Official Unionist Party (M (Mr Ian Paisley), following confidentiality of the discus^ agreed with the General Office attempt should be made to close which afforded terrorists easy acThe Cabinet -Took note.5.     THE PRIME MINISTER said that she was propo customary at this time of year, the Cabinet sho discussion of the economic situation and prospe February, as a prelude to the Chancellor of the Ex of his Budget.    That meeting would have before it &amp; Treasury containing information about the trend over distribution of public expenditure between current and expenditure, as had been requested in earlier discussiThe Cabinet -Took note. Cabinet Office 12 January 1984vthat, as was ave a general^meeting early in ir&apos;s preparation i&apos;andum by the In the ilCONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
