<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/7/26 images: 210-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;sGovernment.SEGPETW.P.(G)(hO) 1768th July, J9h0.WAR CABINET.INDIA AND THE WAR.Memorandum, by the Secretary of state for India.In continuation of my memorandum W.P.(G)(hO) 173dated 6th July, I circulate herewith, for considerationby the War Cabinet, a revised draft of the statementattached to the previous memorandum as Appendix B.   the revision is the result of suggestions for amendment madeby the Governor-General which I received since theoriginal was circulated, and, ex*ept on one or two points of no material importance, the revised draft is in accord with the suggestions made to me by the Governor-General.L.S .A.ia Office,6th July, 19h0.Copy No.

REVISED DRAFT STATEMENT.1.   At this moment in the world struggle against aggression and tyranny His Majesty&apos;s Government feel assured that it is the earnest wish of the people of India to throwthemselves wholeheartedly and unitedly into the defence oftheir country and of the common cause.    They believe that thisunity of national purpose will be helped, and some of themisunderstandings which have arisen in recent monthsremoved, by a clear statement of their attitude to the steps to be taken towards the declared goal of british policy in India.2.    It is the firm intention of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment that India should attain, at the earliest practicable moment after the war, to her natural and rightfulposition as an equal partner-member in the BritishCommonwealth of Nations, as free to control her own affairs and shape her own destiny as the United Kingdom or theDominions.3*    His Majesty&apos;s Government recognise the right ofIndia herself to frame the permanent structure of theConstitution under which she is to regulate her own affairs.They intend,  therefore, that immediately on the conclusionof hostilities the whole constitutional position should be examined anew in all its aspects, central and provincial,by whatever constituent body may meantime be agreed upon forthis purpose by representatives of the principal elements in India&apos;s national life.h.    If the Constitution is to be devised by Indiansfor themselves it is essential that there should be agreementboth as regards the composition of the constituent body, themethod of selecting its members and the machinery by whichit will arrive at its conclusions, and as regards theconstitutional scheme which is to result from its labours.His Majesty&apos;s Government could not contemplate the transferof their present responsibility for the peace and welfare of India to any system of government whose authority is directly denied by large and powerful elements in India&apos;national life ,   nor could they be parties to the coercion ofsuch elements into submission to such a Government.    Theyare convinced that agreement is possible and that it is desired by the vast majority of the people of India.   Fortheir part they would be most willing, as they have alwaysbeen, to lend any assistance in their power to bring thevarious parties together and to help to find a solutionof the difficulties which have stood in the way of progressin the past.    Nothing would give greater satisfaction toHis Majesty&apos;s Government than that agreements should bereached and the work involved completed in time to enableIndia&apos;s new self-devised self-governing Constitution entering into force within a year of the conclusion of the war.5*    His Majesty&apos;s Government are prepared to accept asthe permanent structure of the new Indian polity any constitutional scheme that may be agreed by such a constituentbody.    This permanent structure would not, however,,necessarily of itself make provision for the existingresponsibilities and obligations which Great Britain&apos;s longconnexion has imposed upon her, or for that close co-operation in regard to Defence and foreign policy, the

2.necessity for which will subsist until India is able tomeet unaided her needs in this field.    The principalobligations here referred to, besides those relating toIndia&apos;s defence,  concern the fulfilment of obligations tothe Indian States to the extent that they do not join in and become part of the new Indian polity, and the securingof the reasonable rights of the existing members of thePublic Services.It is the vie?/ of His Majesty&apos;s Government that these obligations and needs can most appropriately be fulfilledthrough the provisions of an Instrument of Agreement asbetween His Majesty&apos;s Government and the proposed constituentbody acting on behalf of the new Government of India.    TheAgreement in question would be for a stated period of years.It, would be renewable by negotiation in so far as circumstances might require, and it would for its durationbe embodied in the Indian Constitution as an integral partof that Constitution and would enter into force concurrently with it. e6.    It is obvious that no such fundamental   /reconsideration of the existing Indian Constitution can takeplace in the midst of a great war.    But within the framework of that Constitution His Majesty&apos;s Government are anxiousto enlist to the full the active cooperation of all parties and elements in the political life of India.    In pursuanceof that object H.E.  the Governor-General has been authorisedto invite representative Indians to join his ExecutiveCouncil as well as to associate with them in a wider WarCouncil (which would meet at regular intervals)representatives of the Indian States and of other interestsin the national life of India as a whole.    His Majesty&apos;sGovernment trust that in the grave circumstances of to-day the general will of all parties to co-operate for the war effort may also lead to such a measure of common agreement in the provinces as may make possible at an early date the resumption with general assent of parliamentary governmentin those provinces which are now being administered underthe emergency provisions of the Government of India Act.His Majesty&apos;s Government hope and believe that in thisway India will be able even within the limits of thepresent Constitution    to play her appropriate part in theconduct of the war and to prepare herself for the tasks ofa full and free national life which lie before her.


</content>
</cab>
