<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/204/12 images: 125-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DQCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(78)112 COPY NO 8024 October 1978CABINETSEAT BELTS:   &quot;CONTRACTING-OUT CLAUSE&quot;Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department i. In his memorandum (CP(78) 110) proposing the introduction of legisla-tion to make the wearing of seat belts compulsory, the Secretary of State for transport considers the possibility, as a means of making such legislationmore acceptable to those who would otherwise be inclined to object to it as an^acceptable infringement of personal liberty, of including in the legislation a&quot;contracting-out clause&quot;, under which anyone, by making a written declaration,could contract out of the statutory obligation to wear a seat belt and the penalty for not doing so.2- In my view the objections of principle are such that I cannot regard itas an acceptable option.3- The object of the criminal law is to require all citixens to act (orrefrain from acting) in a particular way:  there is no place in it for opting out8imply because people object to the element of compulsion, which is what thisProposal would in effect provide.    The purpose of legislation is to enableParliament to pass laws binding on the whole community in circumstances in*hich Parlirment takes the view that the interests of society at large overridethe right of the individual to make his own decision.    The implications of a contracting-out clause would be to preserve the right of individual choice,whUe admittedly requiring a positive act to be taken to enable that choice to bee*ercised.    If we bel;eve that this is a field of conduct where individualchoiCe should still prevail over the public interest, we ought not to beProposing criminal legislation at all.4- I believe that the opportunity to opt out would be taken, not only bytho8e with a rooted objection to compulsory wearing of seat belts but also by many other people - passengers as well as drivers - as a precaution againstbeir*g found not wearing one.    I doubt if either the procedure or the actualhording of the declaration set out in the Annex to CP(78) 110 would do much toUrnit the numbers.    The numbers could be reduced only by requiring, andputting to the test, evidence of the ground of objection:  this leads me to question the staff estimates for the bureaucratic machine in paragraph 5 of the
Annex:  how it would operate is also not clear.    The police have misgivingsabout the difficulty of enforcing any law relating to seat belts:   of course, theywould do their best to enforce a law which was of general application, but theycould hardly be expected to put much effort into enforcing a voluntary law. i fear the courts would not take such a law very seriously either.    Indeed, ifthere were rigorous enforcement, it would create understandable resentment,since those caught would be merely those who had not taken the trouble to exempt themselves.    Thus the seat belt law, and the criminal law more generally, could only be brought into discredit.5- Legislation on seat belts is proposed because we are thought to haveexhausted the &quot;educational&quot; approach to seat belt wearing.     However that maybe, I am clear that the inclusion of a &quot;contracting-out clause&quot; in theiegislation would reduce its effectiveness to the level of a measure of publicPersuasion, not backed by the sanctions which are the essence of criminal laws.1 believe that that would not be a proper use of the criminal law, that it wouldbe unlikely to prove effective for the purpose intended, and that it would tend to diminish public respect for the rule of law.6- The Secretary of State for Transport recognises the&quot;, there areEjections to a &quot;contracting-out clause&quot; in seat belt legislation.    I think thatthey are so strong as to rule it out.    In my view the choice is betweenlegislation of universal application (subject to exemption on medical grounds)and no legislation at all.M RHome Office24 October 19782

</content>
</cab>
