<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/1/9 images: 122-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jr.) (39)Copy No.WAR      CABINET.Economic Warfare1st.    Monthly Report submitted by the Minister ofEconomic Warfare covering the period up to the11th.  Sept. , 1939.(Initialled)      R.  H.  C.Richmond Terrace, S. W.  1.12th.  September 1939-

SITUATION IN GERMANY.1 . At the outbreak of war, the chief weaknessesof the German economy were -(i)      A shortage of certain essential raw materials,(ii)     A shortage of labour, particularly skilled and agricultural,  labour,(iii)      The unsatisfactory condition of the railways,(iv)     Grave financial weakness.2. Although there is evidence that available supplies of a number of strategic materials and foodstuffsfrom stocks, recovery, salvage and maximum domestic production, might suffice to meet estimated consumptionfor a year of war or even more, depending upon the rate ofexpenditure of armaments, the size ofthe forces engaged,and the changing fortunes of war, there are a number ofequally important raw materials of which visible supplies should only suffice for six months&apos;  estimated wartimeconsumption or less.    These include -Iron Copper PetroleumChrome Tin CottonNickel Pyrites Jute

G 3surplus production should prevent the U.3.SPR. making good these deficiencies even if Germany obtainsunrestricted access to the Black Sea and a common frontier with Russia in Bessarabia.    Even so, if germany is to be supplied from this source, the U.3.3.R. must tosome extent do violence to her own economy.     Moreoverthere appear,   to be considerable difficulties in paymenthy Germany.U. Failing direct contact with the Sovietindustrial area of the South-eastern Ukraine, essentialGerman iron supplies depend primarily on the flow of ore from Sweden, Three months&apos; complete stoppage of thisnow would be extremely serious for Germany unless shemeanwhile occupied and worked the Lorraine fields, orcontraband control was ineffectively applied.5. It is estimated that even if her presentstocks and the output of her synthetic plants are not seriously reduced by enemy action, Germany must acquirefrom outside her own territory at least ki million tons of oil products in the first year of war.    She could probablydo this with some difficulty by possessing herself of thePolish and Roumanian oilfields, and more easily if the

Soviet surplus of about       million tons were also madeavailable to her.6. Expert railway engineers have been despatehedfrom Vienna to South Russia and intense production of rail tank cars has begun in Bohemia and the Ostmark witha view to obtaining the Soviet oil overland,    a numberof months must elapse before this becomes possible.7. German efforts to obtain last-minute suppliesof deficiency commodities before the outbreak of war have met with little success, except possibly as regards lead,manila hemp and sisal.     This has been due partly to financial stringency and partly to the rapid impositionby the Allies of measures for contraband control.8. The advance into Poland has made Germanypotentially self-sufficient in lead and zinc (exceptelectrolytic) and has given her valuable supplies ofgreen fodder and possibly dairy products.    The capture ofthe Teschen mines, which are reported not to have been damaged by the retiring Polish forces 9 should, relieve the tension in the supply of German coking coal and allow ofconsiderable exports to other countries as counter-value for goods and services;      this is particularly important for her relations v/ith Italy, since there are good railway

communications;, at present unencumbered by militarymovement and supply, between Teschen and the italian frontier.      This advantage may shortly be reduced bylosses in the Saar region.9. Solid evidence is now accumulating that italy has begun to place large orders abroad for rawmaterials strategic to Germany, reversing her immediatepre-war policy by making available exchange for thepurpose.10. German food stocks should be adequate for atleast a year of war.    The apparently unnecessarily low level at which certain rations have been fixed may be dueto an intention to raise the ration later as a counter-irritant to public nervousness over our economic pressure.The immediate effect of the issue of ration coupons beforehostilities had even begun was to give a severe shock to civilian morale.&quot;11. At the outbreak of war, Germany was calculated to be short of two million persons for labour inagriculture and industry.      Large numbers of workmenclassed as skilled have had quite inadequate training,and early reports on German war materiel describe the latteras of anything but a high standard of construction.    Female

labour was being increasingly employed in factories beforethe outbreak of war.    Although it is too early to express a firm opinion, the incidence of war should furthercomplicate the already acute labour problem.12. The overloading of the German railway system and lack of adequate replacements of permanent way and rolling stock in the past three years has seriously strainedthe Reichsbahn.      The main lines in the Ostmark were stillundergoing reconstruction on the outbreak of war in orderto carry the heavy German goods locomotives.     The outbreakof war will render more difficult the fulfilment of orders placed with industry earlier this year for essentialincreases in the locomotive and wagon park.      Although the mobilisation and movement of the German forces has hithertonot been reported as held up in any way through lack of:  i j i e : j : &apos;railway transportation, hostilities must necessarily continuetc   irhrcw an abnormally heavy burden upon the railways,against which, however, may be set off some alleviation dueto slackening of traffic from the seaports and reducedpassenger services.13. Holdings of gold and foreign exchange inGermany are small.      An investigation is proceeding with aview to a more accurate appreciation.    The gold acquired

through the annexation of Austria has been used up, as has also part at least of that obtained from Czechoslovakia.It is at present too early to estimate what effect theoutbreak of war will have on German credit overseas andon the barter or clearing agreements existing between germany and certain neutral countries, but already thereis sure evidence that German exports (e.g. to Roumania)have been curtailed.


</content>
</cab>
