<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/26/3 images: 18-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC majesty&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (42)42nd Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 42 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, April 6, 1942, at 6-45 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,Secretary of State for Dominion M.P., Lord President of the Council.Affairs.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,Secretary   of   State   for   Foreign      M.P., Minister of Production.Affairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Viscount Simon,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somervell,M.P., Attorney-General.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.[23673]
WAR CABINET 42 (42).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      India   ........ .................... 1932      Premature Disclosure of Information    .,......      .... 1933      Parliament    ....      ........................ 193Business of the House.4      Par East       ............................      194Defence of Singapore.
193W.M. 42 (42).1.   The War Cabinet had before them^-(1) W.P. (42) 147, covering the following telegrams : (i) No. 890 S. from the Lord Privy Seal to the PrimeMinister.(ii) No. 607 from Field-Marshal Smuts to the PrimeMinister.(iii) No. 904 S. from the Viceroy to the Secretary ofState for India.(2) Telegram No! 8230/0 from the Commander-in-Chief inIndia to the Prime Minister.(3) Telegram No. 912 S. from the Viceroy to the Secretary ofState.(4) A draft reply to the Lord Privy Seal prepared by the india committee.After a short discussion the War Cabinet -(1) Approved the despatch of the telegram drafted by the india Committee.(2) Asked the Secretary of State for India to prepare a short statement on the present position of the negotiations,which could be issued as guidance to the Press; and invited the Minister of Information to arrange for theSecretary of State for India to see the Principal Editorson the following day.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs tosend a short telegram to the Dominions informing them of the present position of the negotiations, on the basisof the statement to be prepared by the Secretary ofState for India.2. The War Cabinet had under consideration an article whichhad appeared in a newspaper on Saturday morning and whichlooked as though it was based oh an unauthorised disclosure ofinformation. The War Cabinet was informed that this was a subject on which there had been a good deal of discussion by outside bodies, on which the newspaper article could have been based. Thiswas not, therefore, a case in which legal action could be taken.Reference was made to several recent cases in which there was reason to suspect that there had been a leakage of information.The War Cabinet asked the Prime Minister to send round aNote enjoining discretion and asking that measures should be takento avoid disclosures in future. Qc^y^   cLX2EZ&amp;4m*3. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs raised thequestion of the business of the House when Parliament reassembledon Monday, the 13th April, and asked whether it was proposed thata statement should be made on the war situation.The War Cabinet-Agreed that no decision on this matter could be reachedfor the present.
Far East. 4.   The  War Cabinet gave further consideration  to theDefence of question of collecting information as to events at Singapore.Singapore. Major-General Gordon Bennett&apos;s report had now been received(Previous (W.P. (42) 145), and it was agreed that it was unfitted for reference: publication.   It was, however, urged that there was a considerableW.M. (42) 38th volume of opinion in the House which, while agreeing that an conclusions, enquiry at the present time was out of the question, wanted to minute 3.) be reassured that the Government were taking steps to collect all available information so as to profit by experience.The Prime Minister suggested that a statement might be madeon the following lines : Major-General Gordon Bennett&apos;s report, which had now beenreceived, was not suitable for publication. The Government were,however, collecting information wherever it could be obtained.Thus, Sir Archibald Wavell had been instructed to appoint anOfficer to collect such information as was of value from personswho had escaped from Singapore to India, and to send it to thiscountry.All the available information was being examined in order tomake sure that none of the lessons to be learned was neglected. Atthe same time, no hope would be held out that any report on thematter would be published, or any further Government statement on the matter made, within any foreseeable period. Still less would it be appropriate to pronounce a verdict on what had happened,while many of those who had taken part in these events were stillprisoners of war and unable to give their account of what had takenplace.-:, The War Cabinet-Agreed that a statement should be made on the lines proposed by the Prime Minister.Great George Street, S.W. 1,April 6, 1942./
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,It is requested that special care :r,ay be taken to?ensure the secrecy of this document.-     10MOST SECRET COPY NO.^CIPHER TELEGRAM-.042898Prom:    C-in-C, Indi;Desp.  0500    6/4/42oTo:        The War Office0 Reed. 0215    6/4/42.MOST IMMEDIATE8230/C cipher 5/4 MOST SECRET.Private for Prime Minister from General WavelleI am sure   you realise that I -am doing my utmostin close consultation with Viceroy and Lord Privy Ssalto go to furthest limit possible on question of defence in order to secure acceptance of scheme put forward byH.M.G,      I am convinced after careful consideration that it would not be possible to    separate my dualfunctions as civil and defence member without causingcomplete dislocation of machine but I am working outproposal to give effect to para. 20(c) of Lord Privy Seal&apos;telegram No. 890 on the lines suggested in his para. 24.I. have left it to Viceroy to safeguard position of civilso that he cannot be overridden by majority decision incouncil on essential matters -on defence.Co4 (Telegrams).To:    Col. E.I.C. Jacob,  only.
Far East. 4,   XJie War Cabinet gave further consideration to, theDefence of question of collecting information as to events at Singapore;Singapore. Major-General Gordon-bennett&apos;s report had now been received(Previous (W.P. (42) 145), and it was agreed that it was unfitted for reference: publication.  It was, however, urged that there was a considerable?W:M. (42) 38th volume of opinion in the House which, while agreeing that an conclusions, enquiry at the present time was out of the question, wanted to minute 3.) be reassured that the Government were taking steps to collect all available information so as to profit by experience.The Prime Minister suggested that a statement might be madeon the following lines : Major-General Gordon bennett&apos;s report, which had now beenreceived, was not suitable for publication. The Government were,however, collecting information wherever it could be obtained.Thus, Sir Archibald Wavell had been instructed to appoint anOfficer to collect such information as was of value from personswho had escaped from Singapore to India, and to send it to thiscountry.All the available information was being examined in order tomake sure that none of the lessons to be learned was neglected. Atthe same time, no hope would be held out that any report on thematter would be published, or any further Government statement on, the matter made, within any foreseeable period. Still less would it be appropriate to pronounce a verdict on what had happened,while many of those who had taken part in these events were stillprisoners of war and unable to give their account of what had takenplace.The War Cabinet-Agreed that a statement should be made on  he lines proposed by the Prime Minister.Great George Street,- S.W.April 6, 1942.1,/
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY-It is requested that special care may be taken tflfensure the secrecy of this document.MOST SECRET copy N0*-CIPHER- TELEGRAM,042898From;    C,-ir.-C.o, India,Desp.  0500    6/4/42*To:        The War Off iceo Reed. 0215    6/4/42.MOST IMMEDIATE8230/C cipher 5/4 MOST SECRET.Private for Prime Minister from General WavelleI am sure   you realise that I ;am doing my utmostin close consultation with Viceroy and Lord Privy S3alto go to furthest limit possible on question of defence in order to secure acceptance of scheme put forward byH.M..G.     I am convinced after careful consideration that it would not be.possible to    separate my dualfunctions as civil and defence member without causingcomplete dislocation of machine but I am working outproposal to give effect to para,  20(c) of Lord Privy Seal&apos;telegram No. 890 on the lines suggested in his para 24.I. have left it to Viceroy to safeguard position of civilso that he cannot be overridden by majority decision incouncil on essential matters -on defence.Co4 (Telegrams). To:    Col. E.I.G. Jacob,  only.

TO BE KEPT UNOF.R LOCK &amp; KEY,&quot; It is requested that speoial -iiare may be taken to ensurethe secrecy of this document. 1[ 1[Allotted to Private Secretary * S^g,Telegram from Viceroy to Secretaryof State for India, dated Delhi,03(! 38 hours,  6th April  1942;received 04=00 hours, 6th April 1948,IM!l&amp;DI.Al^EPrivatejand Personala     For your- own andPrime Ministers information^     On furtherconsideration of paragraphs 20(c) -and 24 of Cripps&quot;890, and given the present state of world opinionon the subjectg Commander-in-Chief and.I feel novery serious risks are involved in setting up andhanding over to an Indian Member of Council aportfolio Defence Co-ordination including duties of present Defence Co-ordination sect-ion along withsuch other non-essential functions of present   15Defence Department as Wave.ll thinks he can safelyinclude in the new portfolio:.2S But we are both satisfied- that in existingciroumstanoes it is not; repeal&apos;- not possible to takeaway from Commander-in-Chief l;he substance ofDefence Portfolio as now held by him in&apos;order to entrust it  to a representative Indian,5a We see no reason why Commander-in- Chief while continuing to perform all his eusen-trial functions asai- present should not ca styled War Minister if itis felt that this would make offer more attractive to Cong res Sc.

4i There can however be no question of majoritydecisions of Council being effective against therequirements of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentand itmust he for Commander-in-Chief and Governor-general to decide whether in a particular instance the directions of His Majesty1a Government are to been forced without further argument, or whethercircumstances permit and render it desirable todiscuss the matter further with Hs.M. government before H*M.Government*s decision is enforced.60

SECRET     XXX13Allotted to Private Secretary. 223.D E 0 Y P H E R     OF       HU6U1J,From   Viceroy to Secy, of State for India.Dated New Delhig 08.40 hours, 6th April, 1942.Reed, .10.00 hoursj 6th Aprils 1942,MOST IMMEDIATE..      PART TWO.912^Sc     To preserve relationships stipulationin preceding paragraph it is essential that the positionof the Executive. Council should not be glossed over inany clarification of offer.    This is more necessary&quot;because of the popular references to an Indian cabinet or National Government.The vital test of the Cabinet Government,namely responsible to an Indian Legislatives, does not and cannot exist in the interim period.     TheConstitutional responsibility of G-ovemor-General inCouncil must remain to Parliament, the Governors-Generalmust retain his powers of over-riding the ExecutiveCouncil3 and Secy.of State his powers of direction andcontrol over Governors-General in Council..     On theother hand non-official members of the Executive Councilappointed for their political influence will alwayspossess in their hands the weapon of resignation.    On aparticular issue, on the whole of the procedure&quot; or of substance,

usubstance? the question to be decided would be whether the Governor-General and His Majesty&apos;sGovernment attached so much importance to their own views that they would &quot;be prepared to face the resignation of the non-official members.-6* On the whole the test would immediatelyarise were a majority of non-official members to oppose for example the destruction of the industrialproperty as a military measure.

SECRET     XXX-&quot;    15Allotted to Private 3ecy0 334*X3ECYPHER_OF&apos;     TELEGRAM,From   Viceroy to Secy*of state for India.Dated New Delhi t 08,56 hours * 6*4.43*Reed,    10,00 hours, 6th April, 194:2,MOST IMMEDIATE,&quot;   &quot;&quot;       9X2.THIRD AND LAST PART.It could arise in its most acute form if thwywere to demand cessation of hostilities in Indiaagainst guns of His majesty&apos;s Governments?o There should he no doubt that Co-in-Co will&quot;be in effective control of ail functions of defence department remaining in his hands-.   Moreover 0.in-C.(through over-riding powers of (?Govemor-general  )if necessary) must also have as much control as isnecessary and practicable, - in areas outside field of active military operations, over functioning orother departments in matters affecting fighting valueof. aal facilities for Army-    On the other hand theviews of all members of Council at Council level onany matter (including matters falling within defence department portfolio) would of course have allinfluence that would Inevitably flow from danger oftheir resignation.8. Given a real desire to fight war, this position should satisfy Indian demands for a real and substantial degree of control and responsibilityover whole field of defence.

TO BE KEPT UNDER LOOK an increase K Y.It is requested that special care may betaken toensure the secrecy of this document.0 TJT W A R D___JP EJCj E &amp; R A li.Proi:&apos;:: Secretary of State for IndiaTo: Viceroy.Despatched 6 April, 1942, 8.4.0 p.m.441.HOST LOSDIATE.Superintendent Series.   Personal.    Host Secret.    Following for lord privy Seal.    .-.&apos;ar Cabinet to-day decided on following answer.Deggins.    Your paragraph 18 of 890-S l-aiscd a doubt since dispelled by your. 917-S whether it was clearly understood that the constitutional position of the Viceroy-&apos; s Council, however its personnel nay be changedor enlarged in pursuance of the invitation contained in (e) of the draft declaration, cannot bo altered in present circumstances.    The positionis and nust remain that the Viceroy in Council acts as&apos;a collective bodyresponsible to the Secretary of State and subject to the Viceroy&apos;special powers and duties under Sections 40 and 41 of Ninth Schedule  of act.    There should be no &apos;&quot;asunderstanding between you and indian political leaders on this point.2. As regards defence, far Cabinet agree -..iih you in regarding your20(a) as i: possible and fully share your misgivings as to 20(b).. In viewof \/avell&apos;s opinion, we wust definitely rule this out.    This leaves 20(c).3.    The actual application of 20(c) depends on the decision as to ahatsections of the present Defence Department can be transferred to an Indianmember, together with such additional duties as those jf co-ordinationwith Civil Defence, withoub impairing the authority of the Co: aandcr-in-Chief.    So loir; as this essential condition is understood and applied bhsWar Cabinet is /suite willing that the detailed arrangements should joe suchas comiend themselves to Viceroy, Comnandcr-in-Chief and yourself.There is no objection to the change of nomenclature suggested in yourparagraph 24.4.    You have not so far directly replied to the question containedin paragraph 3 of 42.6.    War Cabinet assumes t at you wish to secure agreement under 20(c) in the hope that thereby you wall ii-prove the chances of the scheme as a whole.    It is unnecessary to remind you ofthe danger of antagonising other elements in your efforts tcr secureadhesion of Congress in respect of the immediate position.    Ends.21.ISSECRET.&quot;HCf&quot;&quot;

10 Downing Street,S.W. 1.On several occasions in recent months there have been unauthorisediisclosures of information.Some have consisted of unauthorised anticipation, by several days, of thejfficial announcement of a Government decision.   Such anticipations are ofteni source of grave embarrassment to the Government; and the fact that they canjccur at all undermines public confidence in the security arrangements ofS&amp;overnment Departments and the discretion of public servants.On other occasions it has been disclosed that important matters of State,Jin which no decisions had yet been reached, were under discussion by Ministers.S&apos;ublic knowledge that a difficult and controversial issue is being considered isften sufficient to make a settlement more difficult, more particularly if currencygiven to misleading or tendentious forecasts of the decisions which theGovernment are likely to reach.I therefore ask my colleagues to take special steps to impress upon allncerned the need for exercising the strictest discretion in these matters.   Inarticular, I ask them to see that the following precautions are strictlyserved : First, it is incumbent on them to ensure that papers of the War cabinet or of Ministerial Committees should not be seen by any save their immediate advisers concerned in the formulation of policy.Secondly, all servants of the Crown, whether Ministers, members of theFighting Services or Civil Servants, must be more careful to observe duediscretion in regard to all matters of State. In particular, those who hold\ I high office must remember that the degree of reticence which they observeI I   in these matters will be taken as an example by those who serve under them.Thirdly, experience has shown that leakages of information have oftenoccurred as a result of the skilful piecing together, by representatives of thePress, of isolated scraps of information, each, in itself, apparently of little importance, gathered from several sources. The only safe rule is, therefore,never to mention such matters even in the form of guarded allusions, except to those who must be informed of them for reasons of State, until the time has come when disclosure, in whole or in part, is authorised.[23707]
I am prepared to recognise that reasons of State may require, inappropriate cases, the confidential communication of some information to a responsible Editor, Lobby Correspondent, &amp;c, for purposes of guidance;but such communications are only justified where it can be ensured that theconfidence and the terms on which it is given are respected.Fourthly, it is of the utmost importance in this connection that Press or public Relations Branches or Departments should not be informed of cabinet discussions or decisions until action has to be taken by such Branches orDepartments. The information then conveyed, and the instructions given as to its use, should be as precise as possible.W.S. c.14.4.42.



</content>
</cab>
