<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 110-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL -       108THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  October 1958C. (58) 222 Copy No. 5 723rd October, 1958CABINETTHE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECHES: THE PROROGATION OF parliament note by the Secretary of State for the Home Department andLord Privy seal i circulate, for the information of my colleagues; the text of The Queen&apos;sSpeech on the Prorogation of Parliament, as finally approved.R. A. B.Home Office, S.W.1,23rd October, 1958.54226
SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OF parliament my Lords and Members of the House of commons my Dear Husband and I derived great pleasure from our visit to theNetherlands in April. -I was pleased to welcome to this country the President of Italy andSignora Gronchi, and the President of the Federal Republic of Germany.I rejoice that the relations between this country and the United States ofAmerica are growing continually closer. My Government welcome the agreement concluded with the Government of the United States for co-operation on thedevelopment of modern weapons for purposes of collective defence.My Government have continued to support the work of the United nations organisation. They have maintained their efforts to bring about further progress towards disarmament.My Government have continued to play their full part in the north atlantic Alliance and the other regional pacts to which they belong.In response to an appeal by the Jordanian Government certain of MyForces were despatched to Amman to preserve the territorial integrity and political independence of the country. A few days earlier, United States Forces had landed in the Lebanon in response to a similar appeal from the Lebanese President and my Government had fully supported this action. My Government made it clear to the United Nations that British Forces would be withdrawn from Jordan either at the request of the legitimate Government or when satisfactory arrangements to preserve Jordanian independence had been made under United Nations auspices.As a result of action taken in the United Nations to improve relations between allthe Arab States, My Government have agreed with the Jordanian Government that my Forces should be withdrawn and this withdrawal is now taking place.My Government took part in the Conference at Geneva on the Law of theSea and have signed the resulting Conventions on the regime of the high seas, theterritorial sea, the continental shelf and fishery conservation. They have continued their efforts to negotiate a settlement with Iceland about fishery limits and have offered to submit the issue to the International Court of Justice. Meanwhile theyare affording protection to British vessels engaged in fishing in the high seas aroundIceland.The enthusiastic welcome which My Dear Mother received during herrecent visit to Australia and New Zealand has been a great joy to Me. TheFederation of the West Indies was established in January of this year and in AprilMy Dear Sister represented me at the inauguration in Trinidad of the federal legislature. She subsequently visited Guiana and British Honduras. more recently she has visited Canada. I was happy to hear from her of the warmth andloyalty with which she was greeted everywhere.My Government welcomed the opportunity for constructive partnershipoffered by the recent Commonwealth Trade and Economic Conference at Montreal.This meeting emphasised the important role which the countries of theCommonwealth are playing in measures directed towards the expansion of theworld economy and the improvement of living standards.The cordial reception given to My Prime Minister during his tour of India,Pakistan, Ceylon, Singapore, New Zealand and Australia afforded Me great satisfaction. The many discussions which he had with statesmen in these countriesserved to strengthen still further the ties of friendship within the Commonwealth.My Government have persevered in their efforts to overcome tfte obstacles to a settlement in Cyprus; and My Forces are discharging their unhappy task in the island with courage and integrity in the face of great difficulties.During the year an Act was passed enabling provision to be made for thegrant of a new constitution to Singapore and for the extension of Commonwealthcitizenship to all its citizens.
An Order in Council has been made providing for an all-AfricanExecutive Council in Sierra Leone under the presidency of the Governor.Members of the House of commons I thank you for the provision which you have made for the public services.My Lords and Members of the House of commons the constant endeavour of My Ministers to strengthen the economy has improved our balance of payments and fortified our reserves, while maintaining ahigh and stable level of employment for My People and securing greater stability in the value of their money. Additional legislation has been enacted with a viewto increasing employment in particular areas.Measures haye been taken to remove controls over the supply and retail prices of coal and over iron and steel scrap prices; to revise and codify the law relating to import duties; and to establish a Conservancy Board at Milford Haven.My Government have continued to support home agriculture inaccordance with the long-term assurances given to the industry, and have providedfurther assistance for the fishing industry. Legislation has been passed to repeal the disciplinary powers of the State over owners and occupiers of agricultural land andto modify the law relating to security of tenure and the arbitration of rentson tenanted farms. An Act has been passed to facilitate the drainage of agricultural land in Scotland. Fresh provision has been made with respect to the licensing and regulation of slaughterhouses in England and Wales.Acts have been passed to bring to an end certain emergency powers,notably those dealing with land used for defence purposes and opencast coal production, and to replace them, so far as necessary, with more limited permanentpowers.In accordance with the resolve of&apos; My Ministers to improve the institutions of government, machinery has been established by statute forre-organising local government in England and Wales.Changes have also been made in the rating system and in the system of exchequer grants to local authorities throughout Great Britain.A measure has been passed to permit the creation of life Peerages for menand women, carrying the right to sit and vote in the House of Lords. improvements have also been made in the law relating to the redistribution of seats m the Houseof Commons. *Measures have been taken to give effect to the majority of therecommendations of the Committee on Administrative Tribunals and Enquiries.The social welfare of My People has continued to be the special care ofMy Government. War pensions have been raised; retirement pensions and other benefits under the National Insurance and Industrial Injuries Schemes have been increased; and improvements have been made in the scales of National Assistance.An Act has also been passed to improve the arrangements for the industrial rehabilitation, training and resettlement of disabled persons.Legislation has been enacted to alleviate possible hards-hip to tenants ofcertain dwelling-houses released from control.The Maintenance Orders Act will achieve a useful measure of socialreform in England and Wales by facilitating the enforcement of maintenance orderswhile at &quot;the same time reducing -the number of men committed to;prison in default of payment.Important reforms affecting the welfare of children are :being effected byan Act amending the law of adoption and making fresh provision for rthe supervision of those who take children into their care for payment.MY Lords and-Members of the House of commons I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.

</content>
</cab>
