<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 130-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
19A SIDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(58)  2308th November, 1958COPY NO.CABINETMALTA: DOCKYARDMemorandum by the First Lord of the admiralty on 4th November the Malta Committee invited me to takecertain steps in order to avoid, if possible, the failure of the atlantic Shipbuilding Company which has directors in common with,and is managed by, Messrs. C. H. Bailey and Company Limited,who are taking over the dockyard at Malta.    If immediatearrangements which would prevent failure by the AtlanticShipbuilding Company at least for the next six months could not bemade, it was agreed that the matter should be brought before theCabinet without delay, and this, as explained below, I am now obligedto do.2.     With the Minister of State for Colonial Affairs and theMinister of State, Board of Trade, I have had informal and entirelyconfidential talks with Mr. Christopher Holland Martin, M. P. ,(a Director) and Mr. Tarn (the Deputy Manager) of Martin&apos;s Bank.3.      It appeared that the company&apos;s position is grave.   Theircreditors are pressing, and one of the bills for  35,000 discountedlast week (backed by Messrs. Bailey&apos;s) has been used almostentirely to meet payments due for wages and the engines for thesecond of the four ships in the contract due to be floated out next week.4.      The Export Credits Guarantee Department (E.C.G.D.) andMartin*s Bank have had urgent further discussions following our meeting with Mr. Holland Martin;  and both have gone as far asthey can to meet each other.   But E.C.G.D. cannot provide the type ofendorsement on their standard policy which Martin&apos;s Bank feel tobe essential to enable them to discount any further bills.5.     In discussion I assured Martin&apos;s Bank that the Admiralty hadconfidence in the firm&apos;s technical ability.   The first of the four ships has been accepted by the American Bureau of Shipping.   It hasbeen at sea for six weeks, and the company tell me that they have hadno complaints about her during this period.-1-
6.      From our discussions it became clear that Martin&apos;s Bank,as bankers to the firm, considered it essential that additional financeshould be provided to enable this  2j millions contract to be completed.The firm already have a small overdraft with them, and they wouldbe prepared to advance  250,000 -  300,000 if suitable guarantorscould be found.   With this in mind, I am proposing to seeGroup Captain G.A. Bailey, Chairman of Messrs. Bailey&apos;s, andSir Stanley Bell, Chairman of the Astley Investment Trust, early next week.7.      If this money can be raised there is a chance that Martin&apos;s Bankwould di discount the remaining three bills in respect of the first ship.In any event there would be a breathing space and time to consider further how to deal with the future bills as the Atlantic ShipbuildingCompany would have large overdraft facilities.8.     If all normal methods of obtaining adequate financial securityare exhausted, the only courses open to Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentare those under the Export Guarantees Act, 1949, Section II or III,i. e. the powers of exceptional guarantee or exceptional financing.9.      There would be considerable difficulties in the use of either of these Sections, but, if in the last resort Her Majesty&apos;s Government feelthat the Atlantic Shipbuilding Company must be kept alive for afurther period in the national interest, action may have to be taken inthis way.10.    The use of these powers involves the risk of calling directly or indirectly on Exchequer funds for:-(a) three bills immediately ( 105,000) together with,(b) a commitment to give the same treatment for subsequent bills.11.     The maximum liability, at the worst, in respect of these futurebills would be  1,053,000 in the middle of 1959.12.    Without these steps it appears inevitable that the AtlanticShipbuilding Company will go into liquidation.   Even then the firm&apos;sbackers will have to find about  300,000 additional working capital.   Iam investigating the possibility of such guarantees early next week.13.    As time is very short - the firm may be faced with bankruptcyin the middle of next week - I suggest that the Cabinet should now agree in principle to follow one of the courses in paragraph 8 if this becomesessential.   Even then there might be difficulty over the additional financedescribed in paragraph 6.S.Admiralty, S. W. 1.7th November, 1958-2-

</content>
</cab>
