<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 132-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1958C. (58) 231 Copy No.11th November, 1958 &apos;CABINETTHE FEDERATION OF RHODESIA AND NY AS ALAND : northern rhodesia  constitution memorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesWhen he visited Northern Rhodesia in 1954 my predecessor, Lord Chandos,made it clear that, before the end of the life of their Legislative Council then about to be elected under arrangements which he had laid down, consideration would need to be given to further steps in constitutional development which might thenbe taken. He indicated in particular that he thought those in Northern Rhodesiawho would be considering these matters should think along the lines of a formof franchise which would tend to make issues of race less dominant in Northern Rhodesian politics.2. It was one of the main tasks of the present Governor. Sir Arthur Benson,who took up his post soon afterwards, to try to work out, in consultation with allthe various interested parties in Northern Rhodesia, constitutional arrangements which would be suitable to the evolving conditions of the territory and would be calculated to meet the main objective laid down by Lord Chandos with whichI was, and am, in full agreement. After many months of discussions in northern rhodesia and of consultation with me, the Governor eventually worked out proposals which were published in Northern Rhodesia as a White Paper on28th March, 1958. As was made clear in that White Paper itself, these proposalsdid not commend themselves in every detail to every Member of the Northern Rhodesian Government. That Government, however, which includesrepresentatives of the United Federal Party and a European representing african interests, did sponsor the publication of the proposals for public discussion &quot; inthe belief that it was a good and honest scheme which merited the support andfaith of all sections of the community.&quot;3. As had been expected, the proposals of the Northern rhodesian government, after publication, were criticised by Europeans and Africans alike,but for completely contradictory reasons. Accordingly, in agreement with theGovernor, I invited representatives of all shades of opinion in the Northern Rhodesian Legislative Council to come to London to discuss the proposals with me.I had very full discussions with this delegation at the end of July. I was not ableto overcome the differences of opinion which had revealed themselves in northern rhodesia. I did, however, as a result of these discussions, gain a clear insightinto the minds of the various parties concerned, and, after thinking over carefullywhat they had all said, I concluded that the proposals of the Northern rhodesian government were in general suitable to the conditions of Northern Rhodesia andthat, subject to a certain limited number of changes, some of them important, theyshould be implemented.  I embodied my detailed conclusions in a despatch to the54304
Governor of Northern Rhodesia dated 10th September, and this despatch, togetherwith the proposals of the Northern Rhodesian Government, was published in thiscountry on 17th September as a White Paper (Cmnd. 530), a copy of which is annexed. The proposals as they now stand are briefly summarised inparagraphs 22-25 of the despatch (pages 10-11 of the Annex).^. 4. In my despatch I explained that provision would be made at an early date. by Order in Council to enable the arrangements for the delimitation of constituencies and the registration of voters to be undertaken immediately, but that provisionfor the holding of elections on the lines proposed and for the other arrangementsoutlined in the despatch would be left to a later Order in Council which would notbe submitted for Her Majesty&apos;s approval until there had been an opportunity for debate in Parliament. This was necessary, on the one hand, because elections mustbe held in Northern Rhodesia next spring and, on the other, because I had given  an undertaking in Parliament that Parliament would have an opportunity to debateany decisions which I reached on this matter before they were implemented.5. Like the original proposals of the Northern Rhodesian Government, mydecisions were criticised by the various parties concerned on familiar andcontradictory lines. In Northern Rhodesia the Africans continued to press forparity of representation in the Legislative Council and for a substantial lowering of the qualifications for the ordinary roll; they also protested against the decision that the ordinary vote should not be devalued. The Federal Party memberscriticised the decision that there should be two African Ministers, but on the groundthat portfolios should not be allocated by race, a ground which was inconsistent withtheir own previous proposal that there should be one African Minister and oneAfrican Parliamentary Secretary. They were, however, more concerned to secure some step such as the creation of a post of Chief Minister or the acceptance of a listof subjects which would be regarded as within the sole discretion of the Northern Rhodesian Government, which would represent a significant step forward in thedirection of self-government. Any development of this kind would at this stage be entirely unacceptable to the Africans and would almost certainly turn them fromreluctant acquiescence in the new Constitution to opposition, and possibly violentopposition, to it. But, after discussion witth the Federal Party members, theGovernor came to the conclusion that their objections, in so far as they were genuine(there is by no means agreement amongst them and a good deal of their oppositionis for public consumption in connection with the Federal elections), could be largelymet if I were to issue a supplementary despatch clarifying my views on these two points and on certain issues connected with the method of appointment of the unofficial Members of Executive Council. This I am prepared to do and theFederal Party members have been told so.6. At this point I should explain the interest of the Federal Government inthis matter. When the Federation was established it was stated in the relevantWhite Paper (Cmd. 8753 of 1953) that &quot; as regards amendments of the territorialconstitutions, the existing machinery and the responsibility of Her Majesty&apos;ministers in the United Kingdom remain unchanged, but Her Majesty&apos;s ministers would naturally seek the views of the Federal Government before advising her majesty.&quot; With this undertaking in mind I arranged for the Northern rhodesian government to send a copy of the White Paper embodying their original proposals to the Federal Government and to invite their comments. The Federal government made a number of comments which, for reasons which were set out in an officialletter from the Northern Rhodesian Government to the Federal Government, theGovernor of Northern Rhodesia did not then feel able to accept. When, however,I came to consider the matter myself I took the Federal Governments commentsinto account and one of the decisions which I made namely, the decision that theordinary vote should not be devalued in elections in the six special constituencies and the two urban constituencies reserved for Africans represented not only what i thought was right (having regard to certain other changes which I made at thesame time) but also an important concession to the views of the Federal government as well as to those of the Federal Party members in Northern Rhodesia. My ownconclusions were also given to the Federal Government before they were published.Their comments were invited and were put forward both by telegram and by a
Federal Minister who broke his journey home from a visit to the Continent forthis purpose. I did not, however, feel able to make any further alterations in response to these representations.7. The Federal Prime Minister had asked that publication of the proposals should be deferred until after the Federal elections. Because of my undertaking to Parliament and of the necessary time-table in Northern Rhodesia this was notpossible, and Sir Roy Welensky, the Prime Minister of the Federation of rhodesia and Nyasaland, was incensed that his request could not be met. Subsequently,however, the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations and h agreed thata Federal Minister should visit London immediately after the Federal elections to discuss with United Kingdom Ministers the representations which the federal government had made on this subject. Sir Roy Welensky professed himself to bevery grateful for our agreement to this and has told us that, if the United FederalParty win the elections, he will arrive in London on 19th November.8. Sir Roy Welensky was told at the time that I did not consider that I could make to the main structure of the proposals any alteration which was not generally agreed by all the parties concerned. I consider, however, that it is extremelylikely that he will urge very forcibly either that there should be no change in theConstitution of Northern Rhodesia before the 1960 review of the federal constitution or that I should drastically amend our scheme in a mannerdisadvantageous to Africans.9. There is one proposal namely, a proposal that candidates in the sixspecial constituencies (i.e., the rural constituencies which are inhabited by an overwhelming majority of Africans and are designed to return African candidates ifthe Africans so wish) must obtain the approval of two-thirds of the Chiefs in theirconstituency for their candidature before they can stand which is as strongly opposed by the Africans as it is by the Federal Government. It is, however,supported by the leader of the Federal Party in Northern Rhodesia, and theGovernor and his advisers consider that it is important to the preservation of theauthority of the Chiefs, on whom they greatly rely for the preservation of law andorder. If the leader of the Federal Party in Northern Rhodesia were to change his view on this subject and he is normally very liable to take guidance from theFederal Prime Minister on political matters I might find it advisable to decide towithdraw this provision. Apart from that I am sure that it would be a great mistake to make any changes in the proposals as they now stand. I am satisfied that they represent a balanced whole which is fair to all interests and that any change whichmight be made now in response to pressure from the Federal Government in favourof one side would impair that balance, and that it would therefore be wrong to makeit. Moreover to do so would have a very bad effect on the opinion of the africans in Northern Rhodesia, who already tend to suspect that our policy is too muchinfluenced by the Federal Government, and might well cause them to opposeviolently the new Constitution, in which there is reason to believe that they are otherwise likely to acquiesce. It would also be certain to result in the introductionof a note of bitterness and real hostility into the criticism which certain features ofthe proposals, such as the high franchise qualifications, are in any case likely to drawfrom the Opposition when they are debated in the House of Commons. It should,however, be possible to arrange that the clarifications in my proposed supplementarydespatch (see paragraph 5 above) should appear to have resulted from the FederalMinisters visit as well as from representations made in Northern Rhodesia.10. I accordingly ask my colleagues to agree that, in our forthcoming discussions with a Federal Minister on this subject, we should not make to thepoint of view of the Federal Government any concessions beyond that represented by my willingness to publish the supplementary despatch referred to inparagraph 5 above except possibly for the point regarding &quot; vetting &quot; by Chiefsreferred to at the beginning of paragraph 9 above. The Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations agrees to the course of action I propose.A. L.-B.Colonial Office, S.W. 1,10th November, 1958.
Northern Rhodesia.  Proposals for Constitutional Change(Cmnd. 530)CORRIGENDAPage 3.   S.I. 1958 should read S.T. 1958/1520.Page 4.   Appendix A should follow Appendix I page 12.LONDON: PRINTED AND published by HER MAJESTY-S STATIONERY OFFICE: 1958(31367)NORTHERN RHODESIAProposals for Constitutional -ChangePresented to Parliament by the Secretary of State for the colonies by Command of Her MajestySeptember 1958LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office price Is. 9d. net cmnd. 530
/////COLONIAL OFFICENORTHERN RHODESIAProposals for Constitutional -Presented to Parliament by the Secretary of State for the colonies by Command of Her MajestySeptember 1958LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office price 1*. 9d. NETChangeCmnd. 530
NORTHERN RHODESIAPROPOSALS FOR CONSTITUTIONAL CHANGEOn 1st August, 1958, the Secretary of State for the Colonies informedParliament that he would publish a White Paper containing his completeproposals for constitutional change in Northern Rhodesia. These proposals have now been communicated to the Governor of Northern Rhodesia in a despatch which is reproduced in Appendix I. The Government of northern rhodesia&apos;s White Paper referred to in the despatch is reproduced inAppendix II.The Secretary of State further indicated that he intended to implement the proposals in two stages. The first stage would include provision for the registration of voters and the delimitation of constituencies; it would also make provision for such local legislation as was necessary in preparation for the elections but would not enable those elections to be held until furtherspecific provision had been made.Her Majesty in Council has now been pleased to make the northern rhodesia (Electoral Provisions) Order in Council, 1958* which is being laid to-day.It is the intention of the Secretary of State for the Colonies to adviseHer Majesty in due course to make a further Order 4n Council containing the further provisions which are necessary to implement the scheme of constitutional change as a whole, and enable elections to be held.Colonial Office,llth September, 1958.* S.1.19583
Appendix AQUALIFICATIONS OF VOTERSOrdinary Voters(a)  720 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of property valued at  1,500); or(b)  480 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of property valued-at  1,000), plus primary education ; or(c)  300 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of property valued at  500), plus four years&apos; secondary education ; orid) Ministers of religion, sisters and lay brothers of religious orders whohave undergone certain stipulated courses of training and periods ofservice in tie ministry or religious order and who follow no otherprofession or gainful occupation ; or(e) Paramount Chiefs and other chiefs recognised by the Governor; or thosecertified by the Resident Commissioner in the Barotseland Protectorateto be of equivalent status.Special Votersid)  150 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of property valued at  500); orib)  120 per annum plus two years&apos; secondary education;id) Certain headmen or hereditary councillors, who are recognised as suchby their chiefs, and are performing unpaid service in such office to thecommunity;id) Persons who are in receipt of a monthly or annual pension earned aftertwenty years&apos; service with one employer.The wife (only one wife of a polygamous marriage) of any person in oneof the above categories may qualify if she fulfills the following quali-fications which will be required of every voter:(i) Simple literacy: Applicants must be able to complete in Englishwithout assistance the application to be registered as a voter.(ii) Age: Minimum age twenty-one.(iii) Nationality: Citizen of United Kingdom and colonies, Citizen of rhodesia and Nyasaland, or British protected person by virtueof&quot; connection with Northern Rhodesia.(iv) Residence: Two years in the Federation and three months in the constituency.Appendix B[This is in the same terms as given in Appendix C, to Appendix II]
APPENDIX IDespatch dated 10th September from Secretary of State for the colonies to Governor, Northern Rhodesia.Sir,At the end of July you were good enough to bring to London a delegation from the Legislative Council of Northern Rhodesia to discuss with me the changes to be made in the Constitution of Northern Rhodesia before theelection of a new Legislative Council. It had, as you know, been my hopethat I would be able to visit Northern Rhodesia so that the discussions couldbe held there. Unfortunately, this did not prove possible and I am most grateful to you and to the Legislative Council for having, at great incon-venience to yourselves, made it possible for the discussions to be held inLondon.2. In our discussions in London we were not breaking virgin ground.You and your Government had for a very long time been giving the most careful consideration to the constitutional arrangements which would be most appropriate for the Protectorate at its present stage of development.In March, 1958 your Government had published a White Paper containing proposals which, it was made clear, did not in every detail represent theviews of any individual member of your Executive Council but which yourExecutive Council had agreed to publish as a basis for public discussion.The proposals were designed specifically to present a balanced scheme whichwould take account of Northern Rhodesia&apos;s past history, its present actualconditions and its needs as part of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasalandcommitted to a policy of partnership between the races. Subsequently this white Paper had been discussed by various bodies throughout the territory and, in great detail, by Legislative Council. I had been able to informmyself very fully of public opinion in Northern Rhodesia by studying the records of the debate in Legislative Council and the many memoranda and letters which I had received both from organisations and individuals in theterritory.3. As was no doubt to be expected consideration of these matters withinNorthern Rhodesia did not lead to full agreement. Nor did it prove possiblein our discussions in London to overcome the differences of opinion whichhad revealed themselves in Northern Rhodesia. Nevertheless, I am certainthat neither the full consideration which was given to this subject in northern rhodesia nor our discussions in London were wasted effort; for, whilst itis now inevitable that I should reach my own decision regarding the advice tobe tendered to Her Majesty, I have been very greatly helped in doing soby the very full knowledge which I have gained through all these discussions of the nature of Northern Rhodesia&apos;s political problems and the views heldin all quarters about the kind of constitutional arrangements which will be best calculated to solve them. I should like to place on record my recognitionand deep appreciation of all the work which has been done on this subject in Northern Rhodesia.4. In the following paragraphs I set out the conclusions I have reachedregarding the advice which I should tender to Her Majesty in regard tothe Constitution of Northern Rhodesia and the considerations which have led me to those conclusions. I should perhaps add that, in accordancewith the understandings recorded in the Report of the Conference onFederation in London in January, 1953 (Cmd. 8753), the views of the Federal
Government have been obtained, but the responsibility for the conclusionsrecorded below rests entirely with myself and with Her Majesty&apos;s GoVern-ment in the United Kingdom.5. I am in complete agreement with your Government in their rejection,after most serious consideration, of schemes based on the separate repre-sentation of European and African interests in favour of arrangements which,would enable and indeed strongly encourage political parties to develop o.,non-racial lines and politics to cut across race. I recognise the sincerity of purpose behind the suggestions on the one hand that the territory shouldbe divided into separate spheres of influence for Europeans and Africansrespectively, and on the other hand that the interests of Europeans andAfricans should be directly represented in the Legislative Council separatelyby members drawn from the two races in equal numbers. But it seems tome that to adopt the first of these two courses would amount to a policy ofdespair, whilst the second could only be either a dead-end or a prelude to arrangements providing for the domination of one of the two main races assuch by the other of the two main races as such. All who have the futureof Northern Rhodesia at heart should, I am sure aim higher than this and seek to establish arrangements which will make every member of the Legis-lative Council regard himself as free from any obligation to promote thepartisan interests of any one race and indeed as obliged to promote theinterests of all persons in his constituency and which will in consequenceestablish confidence between the races ; it being understood that until suchconfidence has been adequately established it will be the duty ofHer Majesty&apos;s Government in -the United Kingdom, through the officialsappointed by the Secretary of State, to ensure that in the consideration ofcontroversial matters a proper balance is held.6. Consequently the changes to be made now must not be such as toperpetuate the present system of racial representation, but such as may make possible and encourage &quot; the return of men and women who are prepared and indeed disposed to consider and balance the interests of all racialgroups &quot;. I am aware that many Africans to-day feel doubt about these principles and that this doubt was reflected in the attitude of the african members of Legislative Council when the proposals of the Northern Rhodesian Government were debated. I believe, however, that this doubtarises not from a rejection of the principles themselves but rather from afear that in spite of the methods proposed to ensure it they will not be implemented. I understand this fear. But I am myself satisfied that it isonly when Northern Rhodesia has a constitution based in the main on these principles that it will begin to become apparent to the population as a wholethat it is only such a constitution with the incentives it will provide for publicmen to think in terms of the interests of the country as a whole, which canpoint the way towards a prosperous future free from racial strife.7. A common roll is an important principle of any such constitution. Inthe present conditions in Northern Rhodesia it seems essential to combinea qualitative franchise with the common roll. I recognise that any set ofqualifications which may be devised will inevitably exclude from the fran-franchise some who might be thought capable of exercising a vote with judg-ment, and include some who might not. Nevertheless it is, in my view, pos-sible to determine a level to go below which would mean including a largenumber of persons who clearly could not exercise a vote with judgment, asthe price of including a much smaller number of persons who had someclaim to be included. I recognise, however, that the introduction of a common roll with high qualifications in Northern Rhodesia will at first result in so
great a preponderance of European voters on that roll as to render some additional interim measures inevitable if the Africans are not to be left witha justifiable feeling that they are under-represented, and if the whole intentionof conducting elections on a non-racial basis is not to be defeated by thefact that, at first, those qualified to register as voters will be almost all of one^race. These measures are considered in paragraphs 9 and 10 below.lu 8. The qualifications proposed by your Government for the common rollare set out in paragraph 31 of the White Paper. The Legislative Council took the view that in addition to ministers of religion, sisters and lay brothers of religious orders who have undergone certain stipulated courses of training and periods of service in their religious orders should also be exempt fromsatisfying the means qualification in order to be eligible for registration.I accept their view on this point and propose that provision should be madefor the ordinary qualifications to be those set out in Appendix A to this despatch.9. Your Government have proposed that in order to avoid leaving the african race under-represented and in order to ensure that justice be done to their claims there should also be a temporary and lower set of qualificationswhich will enable a fair proportion of Africans to qualify at once, and thatthose qualifications should initially follow those set out in paragraph 31 ofthe White Paper, with the addition of the special provisions for certain head-men, hereditary councillors and pensioners referred to in paragraph 34, but should be raised periodically as set out in Appendix C to the White Paperuntil at the end of ten years all new applicants for registration should havethe ordinary qualifications and be registered as ordinary voters. Neverthelessall persons registered as special voters at the end of this period would remain so registered and continue to participate on that basis in futureelections. No person who had been registered as a voter would have his name removed from the roll because he subsequently ceased to possess the prescribed income or property qualification, though the name of anyperson registered as a special voter would be transferred to the ordinary voterssection of the roll, if he subsequently became entitled to be registered as an ordinary voter.10. I agree with the proposed qualifications for special voters, which are,for convenience of reference, also set out in Appendix A to this despatch.The provision for raising the qualifications for special voters by stages at intervals fixed in advance has been criticised in the mistaken belief that at each stage those who could not satisfy the new standard would be dis-franchised, thus bringing about a periodic reduction in the number of specialvoters until at the end of ten years there would be none left at all. This, ofcourse, represents a misreading of your Governments White Paper which makes it clear that there would be no such disfranchisement. The provision has also been criticised on the ground that the intervals at which the quali-fications are raised should be related to some objective fact such as a comparison of the numbers registered as special voters with the numbersregistered as ordinary voters. This seems to me to be a sound suggestion and I consider that it should be laid down that the qualifications shouldbe raised at each stage (see Appendix B* to this despatch) only if, by thedate in question, the number of special voters in the territory as a whole isnot less than the number of ordinary voters in the territory as a whole. IfAfricans take advantage of the opportunities which the new Constitutionwill offer them, this condition should, of course, be more than fulfilled from* See Appendix C to Appendix III.7
the beginning. But its inclusion will, I think, be a wise precaution and a legitimate protection of African interests against the effects of a possiblefailure to register by numbers of Africans unfamiliar with political affairs.11.1 agree with the view of the Legislative Council that provision shouldbe made so that (i) all prospective voters should be required to make adeclaration of allegiance to Her Majesty the Queen; (ii) any persons already on the Northern Rhodesia Voters&apos; Roll should be eligible for registrationas ordinary voters (but on the understanding sought by the Attorney-general in the course of the Debate that failure to provide within a reasonable period the further particulars which are ordinarily required for the purposes of registration of voters should entail the removal of their names from the roll);and (iii) there should be periodic assessments of the purchasing power ofmoney in the Territory and consequential adjustments of the franchisequalifications.  I propose that provision should be made accordingly.12. In framing their proposals for the composition of the LegislativeCouncil your Government have faced the crucial difficulty of ensuring that from the outset candidates for any contested seat will have to appeal to votersof every race ; that for the present nevertheless, and for so long as it remainsa vital consideration in their eyes, the voters in a predominantly Europeanor predominantly African area should be able to secure the return of a european or an African representative respectively; and that the arrange-ments devised to these ends should not themselves frustrate the ultimate aim off providing for the development of party politics on non-racial lines. your government have proposed to meet the difficulty by providing for a Legisla-tive Council composed of a Speaker and 22 elected members, 6 official members and 2 nominated members. 12 of the elected members wouldbe returned from 12 ordinary constituencies comprising in the main theCrown lands adjacent to the railway together with certain areas of NativeReserve and Native Trust Land closely connected with those Crown landareas, and from 6 special constituencies comprising the rest of the Territory.The greater proportion of the European population resides within the pro-posed 12 ordinary constituencies and the greater proportion of the Africanpopulation resides within the 6 special constituencies. In all those con-stituencies your Government proposed that all voters, whether they wereordinary or special voters, should be entitled to cast one vote, but that thetotal votes cast by special voters in an ordinary constituency should not count for more than one-third of the total ordinary votes cast in thatconstituency, and that the total ordinary votes cast in a special constituencyshould not count for more than one-third of the special votes cast in thatconstituency. For the return of the remaining 4 of the 22 elected membersyour Government proposed that the 12 ordinary constituencies should be grouped into two constituencies for the return of two members to seatsreserved for Africans, with a provision that the total ordinary votes cast ineach of the two constituencies should not count for more than one-thirdof the special votes cast in the same constituency; and that similarly the special constituencies should be grouped into two constituencies for thereturn of two members to seats reserved for Europeans with a provision that the total special votes cast in each of the two constituencies should not count for more than one-third of the total ordinary votes cast in thatconstituency.13. I am satisfied that the proposal to impose a check on the influence which the special voters will have when voting along with the ordinaryvoters in the 12 ordinary constituencies and in the two constituencies whichwill return members to seats reserved for Europeans is fully justified. but after the most careful consideration I am unable to agree that it would be
proper to limit in the same way the influence which voters with the fulland permanent qualifications should have in the six special constituencies and the two constituencies which will return members to seats reserved forAfricans. The admission of voters with lower qualifications than those whichwill eventually be the sole qualifications for registration is intended to meet a temporary situation in which a sufficiently representative number of africans is not yet qualified for the ordinary vote. The reduced qualifications^ A such voters makes it reasonable to set some limit on the influence whichthey may exert but no similar consideration exists to warrant the impositionof a limit on the influence of the ordinary voter. Nor do practical con-siderations require such limitation. The estimates of the numbers of personswho will qualify as special voters made it clear that such a provision is unnecessary in the 6 special constituencies where they could outnumber theordinary voters by more than six to one and in the two other con-stituencies affected the seats are reserved for Africans in any event. More-over to provide that the ordinary votes might in certain circumstances bedevalued might prove a disincentive to efforts to attain the qualificationsnecessary for the ordinary vote, e.g. among Africans in the 12 ordinaryconstituencies who might thereby as individuals find their influence on thereturn of Africans to the two reserved seats cut to one-third, although thosewere the candidates in whose election they felt the closest interest. Forall these reasons I do not propose that provision should be made for the devaluation of ordinary votes in any circumstances.14. I am satisfied with the proposal that candidates for all but the 6 specialconstituencies should be required to have the qualification of an ordinaryvoter, and that in the 6 special constituencies the qualifications of a specialvoter should suffice. In view, however, of the advantages of ensuring sofar as possible that a candidate who is returned by the votes of the com-paratively small numbers who will at first have the qualifications to registeras voters in those 6 special constituencies may be regarded by the rest ofthe inhabitants of that constituency as their representative, I consider thatthe proposed provision that candidates with special qualifications only should first obtain a certificate of approval of their candidature from two-thirds ofthe Chiefs in that constituency should apply equally to candidates who havethe qualifications of an ordinary voter and I propose that provision shouldbe made accordingly.15. I am satisfied that it will be proper to provide that civil servants in the service of the Government of Northern Rhodesia, with certain exceptions, may be granted leave if they wish to stand as candidates for election, on the understanding that, if elected, they would be requiredto resign. I take the view that this privilege may be extended as an experiment to teachers but should be withdrawn if it leads to abuses.Those to be excluded from this arrangement would therefore be all membersof the police service, and all other civil servants in the service of theGovernment of Northern Rhodesia who are concerned with the directionor implementation of policy to an extent which, in the opinion of the Govern-ment, would make it undesirable for them to take part in politics. I proposethat provision should be made accordingly.16. I agree that there will no longer be a need for any members nominatedfor the specific purpose of representing African interests a system whichhas served its purpose well but which neither Africans nor Europeans wishto perpetuate. I also agree, however, that a complement of two nominated members should be retained. It is my view that these two members shouldbe nominated by the Governor after such consultation as he thinks necessary and desirable and that, before making his nominations, the Governor should9
be enjoined to have regard to the &apos;two considerations set out in paragraph 59of the Northern Rhodesia White Paper and to the need to ensure that oncontentious issues the balance will ibe fairly held as provided in (3) of theResolutions quoted in paragraph 17 of that White Paper.17. I am satisfied that with the other changes in the composition of theLegislative Council now proposed it will be possible to reduce the numberof official members from eight to six without detriment to the ability of her majesty&apos;s Government to fulfil their ultimate responsibility for ensuring that,on contentious issues the balance is fairly held.18. I propose therefore that provision should be made for the composi-tion of Legislative Council to be as proposed by your Government anddescribed in paragraph 12 above with the modifications as regards the election of elected members and the appointment of nominated members specifiedin paragraphs 13-16 above.19. Your Government have proposed that in future the Executive council should be composed of the Governor as President, 4 ex officio Ministers and5 other Ministers (of whom four must have been &quot; ordinarily qualified &quot;candidates successful in the elections) ; that in addition there should be twoAssistant Ministers ; and that of the total of eleven ministerial posts notless than two should be filled by Africans, of whom one should be a Minister.I have given long and deep consideration to criticisms on the one hand thatto make any firm provision as to the race of future Ministers in the con-stitution is inconsistent with the general aim of enabling politics to developon a non-racial basis, and on the other hand that the position of a singleAfrican Minister without an African colleague who could sit with him inExecutive Council would be very difficult! I am in sympathy with the firstcriticism and hope that the time will come when race can be disregarded in ministerial appointments. I do not think, therefore, that the constitutionalinstruments themselves should make provision for the allocation of unofficialministerial offices by race. I am, however, certain that in practice it will benecessary for some time to come for such allocation to be made. I agree thata single African Minister would be in a somewhat difficult position even ifhe was placed in a position to discuss Executive Council business with an african Assistant Minister. It is accordingly my view that the constitutionalinstruments should provide for six unofficial Ministers and that for thepresent it should be an instruction to the Governor that two of these shouldbe Africans and four Europeans. In consequence I do not propose that provision should be made for the appointment of Assistant Ministers.20. In my view there should be no change in the obligations and respon-sibilities of the members of the Executive Council who should be styledMinisters. Those who accept office will, as at present be required to acceptcollective responsibility for Government policy, to support and vote with itin the Legislature, and to support thai policy both in public and in private.They will also, like their predecessors, be expected to devote all their time to ministerial work and to dispose of any private interests which might, in the governors opinion, conflict with their official duties and obligations.21. The proposals for whioh I intend that provision should be made before the next eleotion can, therefore, be summarised as follows.22. There will be a common voters&apos; roll containing both ordinary and special voters ; the ordinary and special qualifications will be ait the levelsshown in Appendix A to this despatch and will include the award of the voteto chiefs, ministers of religion and certain members of religious orders, certain
headmen and hereditary councillors and certain pensioners. In the Legisla-tive Council there will be a Speaker and thirty members of whom twenty-two will be elected, six will be officials and two nominated members.Northern Rhodesia will be divided into eighteen constituencies, twelve ofthem comprising the Crown land adjacent to the railway and certain adjoin-ing areas of Native Reserve and Native Trust land ; the other six will bejSJJT ,&apos;argely rural constituencies and will include some smaller areas of Crownf^-land away from the railway. Within the total area of the twelve ordinaryconstituencies there will be two further seats reserved for Africans, and withinthe total area of the six special constituencies there will be two further seatsreserved for Europeans. In all the twenty-two constituencies all votes willcount in full provided that in each of the twelve ordinary constituencies andthe two constituencies reserved to European candidates special votes may notin total count more than one-third of the total or ordinary votes cast.23. Candidates standing in all constituencies will be required to holdordinary qualifications except in the six special constituencies where special qualifications will suffice. Every candidate in a special constituency will berequired to obtain a certificate from not less than two-thirds of the recognisedchiefs in the constituency that they have no objection to his standing as a candidate.24. The Governor will preside over an Executive Council containingten Ministers consisting of four officials and six others of whom, for the timebeing, four will be Europeans and two will be Africans.25. The two nominated members of the Legislative Council will notbe there specially to represent African interests. They will be nominated by the Governor after the results of the elections are known and after such consultation as shall in his opinion be necessary. The Governor will inmaking his nominations have regard to the results of the elections, to the ability of those already elected to devote their full time to the work of aportfolio so as to provide for the full membership of the Executive Council,and to the need to ensure that on contentious issues the balance will be fairly held.26. When your Government published their White Paper as a basis for public discussion, they acknowledged that it was unlikely that every detailof the proposals contained in it would commend itself to every section of society in Northern Rhodesia. Equally it would be foolish to expect that the relatively small adjustments which it is proposed to make in them will makethe proposals fully acceptable to any of the interests mainly concerned. Itis, however, necessary to recognise that at the present time any proposalswhich were fully acceptable in one quarter would be likely to be consideredunacceptable in another a fact which points clearly to the need forarrangements which will tend to encourage a less racial outlook.27. I believe, however, &apos;that the arrangements proposed in the northern rhodesia White Paper, as modified in this despatch, are appropriate to theconditions of Northern Rhodesia and represent a fair compromise betweenthe interests of the various communities concerned. As will be clear fromthe earlier paragraphs of this despatch, their most important merit, is, inmy view, the fact that they are designed to provide all men in public life withan incentive to consider the interests of the country as a whole and of all its inhabitants, and not only the interests of people of their own race. they provide, to members of both races, increased opportunities for participating in the conduct of the territory&apos;s affairs both in Legislative and in ExecutiveCouncil without, however, undermining the ability of the Governor and his
officials to carry out their responsibility to H.M.G. in the U.K. for holdingthe balance in matters which affect the interests of one community or another,and are controversial. Under the existing Constitution there are only fourAfrican members of the Legislative Council and as the vote is confined toBritish subjects, only a handful of Africans are qualified to participate in theelections by which the elected members are returned; the African membersthemselves are not returned by direct election; and there is no African&quot;member on Executive Council. The increase in the opportunities afforded to Africans for participation in public affairs under thearrangements mow proposed is, therefore, naturally somewhat greaterthan tlhe parallel increase afforded under them to Europeans. Fromthe European point of view, however, the arrangements have the advantage that they are designed to ensure that the pace at which African influence in political life will increase in the future will be determined by the pace of their general advance rather than by arbitrary decisions taken from time to time.28. In order that Parliament may have :the opportunity, should that be their wish, to discuss these proposals before final provision is made for the holding of elections on the lines proposed, while at the same time ensuring that such elections, if finally determined upon, should not be delayed, I intend to tender advice to Her Majesty that provision should be made at an earlydate by Order in Council to enable the arrangements for the delimitation of constituencies and the registration of voters to be undertaken immediately thereafter. Provision for the holding of elections on the lines proposed andfor the other arrangements outlined in this despatch would be left to alater Order in Council, which would not be submitted for Her Majesty&apos;approval until there had been an opportunity for debate in Parliament. Ishall address a further communication to you on the subject of these arrangements.I am, etc.Alan Lennox-Boyd.
APPENDIX IIGOVERNMENT OF NORTHERN RHODESIAPROPOSALS for constitutional CHANGEINNORTHERN RHODESIAPresented to theNorthern Rhodesia Legislative Council28th March, 1958
contents part I Historical..................Part II The Present Position............Part III The Recent Constitutional Discussions ...Part IV Principles of Constitutional ChangePart V The Government^ Proposals:Summary of Proposed Constitution.........The Franchise    ..................Composition of Legislative Council.........Elected Members        ...      ...      ...      ......Qualifications for Candidates............Composition of Executive Council    .........Nominated Members   ......   &apos;.........Official Members        ...............Conclusion       ..................Appendix A.  Possible Constituencies    .........Appendix B.  Distribution of Electorate.........Appendix C.  Evolution of the Franchise        ......
Legislative Council	1924	1929	1938	1940	1945	1948	1954Official members: (includ-ing the Governor who was President of the Council until 1948) ...	9	9	8	9	9	10	8Unofficial members: Elected members Nominated   unofficial members   ...... African members	5	7	7 1	8 1	8 54	10 2 2	12 2 4Total        ......	5	7	8	9	13	14	18Total membership ...	14	16	16	18	22	24	265. The Governors membership and presidency of the Legislative Councilceased in 1948 when a Speaker was appointed.1 Appendices 2-3 to the Laws of Northern Rhodesia.2 Appendix 4 to the Laws of Northern Rhodesia.3 Appendix 17 to the Laws of Northern Rhodesia.4 Including two members nominated to represent special interests other than those of africans.PART I-HISTORICAL1. The Constitution of Northern Rhodesia is laid down by Her majesty in Council in Orders in Council.1 Royal Instructions2 issued by Her majesty in Council to the Governor of Northern Rhodesia contain supplementarymatter relating particularly to procedure and excising from the Governorsjurisdiction, and reserving for Her Majesty&apos;s pleasure, certain matters, for  ^?xample, matters relating to the Royal Prerogative. The former jurisdiction of the Government of Northern Rhodesia is further affected by the Federa-tion of Rhodesia and Nyasaland (Constitution) Order in Council, 1953.3 TheConstitution provides for an Executive Council and a Legislative Council.The Legislative council. Northern Rhodesia came under the administration of the Crown in1924. The first Legislative Council contained nine official members and fiveunofficial members. Constitutional development over the years gave the unofficial members first an equal strength (in 1938) and later a majority (in1945) on the Council.3. Special representation for Africans was first introduced in 1938 when a European member was nominated by the Governor to represent african interests. From 1945 to 1948 there were three nominated unofficial members to represent African interests. Africams were not represented by membersof their own race until 1948 when two Africans were appointed to the Counciland the number of Europeans nominated to represent African interests was reduced to two. Since 1954 there have been four African members inaddition to the two nominated Europeans.4. The table shows the composition of the Council at each stage of constitutional development since 1924:
The Executive Council6. Until 1939, the Government of Northern Rhodesia was conductedentirely by officials. Unofficial members were first appointed to ExecutiveCouncil at the end of 1939 but it was not until 1949 that an unofficialmember first held a portfolio. Since 1954 there have been four unofficial members of Executive Council, all of whom hold ministerial positions.The following table illustrates the changing composition of the Council oversthe years:Executive Council	1924	1929	1938	1940	1945	1948	1954Official members	4	5	5	5	5	7	5Unofficial members with-							out portfolio......	 	 	-  	4	3	41	 Unofficial members with							portfolio	 	 	 	 	 	 	41Total membership (exclud-							ing the President)	4	5	5	9	8	11	91 Including one member of the Legislative Council nominated to represent African interests.Two elected members undertook portfolios in 1949.
PART II-THE PRESENT position the Executive Council7. All the nine members of the Executive Council hold ministerial officeand are responsible to the Governor and to the Legislature for the administra-tion of Government departments within their portfolio. They form in effectfie equivalent of a Cabinet and the principle of collective Cabinet responsibility-applies to the decisions of the Executive Council. All members of the Govern-ment, both official and unofficial, sit on the same side of the Legislative Counciland constitute a Government front bench. One of the unofficial members isa nominated member of the Legislative Council representing African interests ;the other three unofficial members are elected members of the LegislativeCouncil.The Legislative Council8. The present (the tenth) Legislative Council was elected and nominatedin February, 1954, and contains eight official and eighteen unofficial members.Two of the unofficial members are appointed by the Governor to representAfrican interests, and four are Africans selected for appointment by the african Representative Council. The other twelve unofficial members areelected by an electorate which contains virtually no Africans. The LegislativeCouncil has a life of five years.The Franchise9. The franchise is open to all British subjects of twenty-one or overwho fulfil the following requirements and are not otherwise disqualified, e.g.,by insanity.  For registration as a voter, a Britsh subject must be (i) in occupation of a house or building to the value of  250 withinthe Territory ; or(ii) in possession of a mining claim ; or(iii) in receipt of an annual income of  200 per annum.He must have resided for a continuous period of two years within theTerritory and for three months in the electoral district for which registrationis sought. Married women of twenty-one years and over may vote on their husbands&apos; qualifications, but all voters must be capable of completing thenecessary application forms in English without assistance.10. The present franchise law in practice excludes Africans. All northern rhodesia Africans, save those who have been granted naturalisation, havethe status of British Proteoted Persons. The qualifications for registrationas a voter have remained virtually unchanged since 1925 and, although thevalue of money to-day is much lower than it was then, the income qualifica-tion of  200 a year is still above the earning powers of the vast majority of africans. This, added to the requirement that a voter must be a british subject, has resulted in the fact that there are only eleven Africans on the1957 voters&apos; roll. A candidate for one of the present twelve seats in theLegislative Council filled by direct election must, of course, be a registeredvoter.11. In consequence all these twelve seats are filled by Europeans. Thefour African members of the Legislative Council are returned, not by directelection, but by an electoral college system culminating in the AfricanRepresentative Council. The Governor is bound to appoint those whom the african Representative Council selects from amongst its members to be members of the Legislative Council.
PART III-THE RECENT CONSTITUTIONAL DISCUSSIONS12. The present composition of the Legislative and Executive Councilswas set out in an announcement issued in London in September, 1953. InJanuary, 1954, the then Secretary of State for the Colonies, the Right Honour-able Oliver Lyttelton, D.S.O., M.c. (now Lord Chandos), visited the Territory.,at the request of unofficial members of the Legislative Council and hek&apos;^discussions with all sections of the community about the constitution ana*--&apos;franchise of Northern Rhodesia. The communique issued at the conclusionof the talks affirmed that the composition of the Legislative and executive councils would be as set out in the announcement of September, 1953, andthat no change in the franchise should be made during the life of the TenthLegislative Council except by agreement of all concerned. It was, however,anticipated at the time that consideration would need to be given well beforethe end of the life of the Tenth Legislative Council to the further steps inconstitutional advance which might then be taken. In December, 1956, theLegislative Council passed a motion that constitutional talks should commenceduring the first quarter of 1957 and that an announcement of proposedconstitutional changes should be made during the first quarter of 1958.13. His Excellency the Governor accordingly began early in 1957, and continued through to the end of the year, a series of discussions with individual members and with groups of members of the Legislative Council and withcertain other leaders of political organisations.14. In the course of these discussions various proposals and plans were put forward. To all these the Government gave their most serious considera-tion. At one end of the scale there were suggestions for the division ofNorthern Rhodesia into spheres of influence for Europeans and Africansrespectively. It is the view of the Government of Northern Rhodesia that,whatever merits such a scheme might have had if introduced thirty years ago,the history of the intervening years makes it quite impracticable to-day whenthe Territory of Northern Rhodesia itself and the Federation as a wholehave each become unified and indivisible and are pledged to a policyof partnership of the races.15. At the other end of the scale was the proposal commonly referredto as &quot; parity &quot;. As advanced by moderate African opinion this requiredthat equal numbers of seats in the Legislative and Executive Councils shouldbe reserved under the constitution for Europeans and for Africans respectively,with a number of additional seats reserved for officials. A variation of thisproposal, put forward by the African National Congress, went even further and proposed that the same number of seats should be reserved for Africansas was reserved for European elected members and officials combined.16. To specify any form of parity in the constitution could not butconsolidate and perpetuate a racial outlook. Neither parity nor a system of reserved spheres of influence would be consistent with the first principle onwhich Government policy has always been based and which it is their objectto follow in the future constitutional arrangements ; that political parties should begin to develop on non-racial lines, and that politics should cutstraight across race. This is the policy which the Government have con-sistently followed and which they believe has always been generally acceptedby the people of Northern Rhodesia. It first found lucid expression in theMoffat Resolutions which were accepted by the Government in the LegislativeCouncil on 29th July, 1954.
17. The Resolutions were (1) The objective of policy in Northern Rhodesia must be to remove from each race the fear that the other might dominate for its ownracial benefit and to move forward from the present system of racial representation in the territorial legislature towards afranchise with no separate representation for the races.(2) Until that objective can be fully achieved a period of transitionwill remain during which special arrangements in the legislative and Executive Councils must continue to be made so as to ensurethat no race can use either the preponderance of its numbers or its more advanced stage of development to dominate the other for its own racial benefit.(3) During this period of transition, special legislation must be inforce to protect, to the extent that may be necessary, the interestsof either race. Meanwhile this Council notes and agrees with thestatement of the Secretary of State that it is the duty of her majesty&apos;s Government to ensure that on contentious issues thebalance is fairly held.(4) Every lawful inhabitant of Northern Rhodesia has the right toprogress according to bis character, ability and industry, without distinction of race, colour or creed.
PART IV-PRINCIPLES OF CONSTITUTIONAL CHANGE18. A number of the more general principles on which constitutional advance should be based have found wide acceptance among informed local opinion of all parties. The first is that already mentioned, that politics shouldbe encouraged to develop on party and not on racial lines: unless political parties can eventually cut across racial divisions it will be impossible to-achieve a united Northern Rhodesia.  Secondly, there should now begin eqF)move away from the present system of racial representation in the Legislative^&apos;Council, which by its very nature may predispose members to look moreEarticularly at the interests of their own race rather than the general weal.1 development of this second principle, the present method whereby african members are elected to the Legislative Council exclusively by Africans must give way to a system under which all elected members are put into theLegislative Council by means of a common machinery providing for the direct representation of all qualified voters in a geographical constituency.19. All parties are agreed that the new constitution must win the con-fidence of all the peoples of Northern Rhodesia ; the basic lines of constitu-tional advance now to be settled should therefore be durable, and not subjectto drastic change every few years. Moreover, the constitutional arrangements should ensure that the government of the country will continue to rest in thehands of responsible men, men with understanding and of sufficient education and experience of affairs to be able to reason and to exercise judgment betweenalternative courses of action. The electoral system must encourage the return of men or women who are prepared and indeed disposed to consider and balance the interests of all racial groups, and who are prompted primarily by a spirit of public service to the whole community ; it must discourage thereturn of extremists who would look to sectional interests alone.20. The franchise must therefore be one which will give the vote to thosewho are contributing to the wealth and welfare of the country and who are capable of exercising it with judgment and public spirit.21. The considerations involved in broadening the franchise in a multi-racial community similar to that of Northern Rhodesia have already beendiscussed in detail by the Franchise Commission, under the chairmanship ofSir Robert Tredgold, which was appointed by the Government of SouthernRhodesia and reported last year. The Commission rejected the concept of universal adult suffrage on the ground that it would lead in effect to aworse kind of racial representation than the present, because there would bean overwhelming majority of one race whose members are still for the mostpart comparatively uneducated and backward; and therefore subject toemotional appeals which might lead them in the cause of African nationalismto sacrifice their own best interests. The Government of Northern Rhodesiaendorse that view. They are, however, like the members of that Commissionfully conscious that&quot; no system that leaves any substantial section of the peoplelabouring under a justifiable grievance can, in the end, prevail&quot;, becausegovernment must ultimately rest on the consent of the governed.22. The basic fact, and therefore the crux, of the problem in central africa to-day is that the majority of Europeans here are still far ahead ofthe majority of Africans; and if the franchise were limited to europeans and to those few Africans who have, at the moment, achieved Europeanstandards, the African race would be seriously under-represented. this difficulty will persist for a number of years to come. If the dangers set outin the preceding paragraph are to be avoided, the problem of giving Africansa proper measure of representation can be solved only by adopting aqualitative franchise.
23. The Government consider that provision should be made for acommon roll, which would eventually be based on a single set of qualifications for the vote. In order to ensure, however, that all races may be properlyrepresented in the next decade, it will be necessary to have temporarily a set of lower qualifications in addition to the fixed and permanent higherqualifications.A 24. The common voters&apos; roll, so established, must from the outset produceffa Legislative Council on which, taking into account the presence of officials and nominated members, no race need fear the domination of another. Toestablish confidence, and to set extremism at a discount, a feeling must befostered amongst all races that, through their representatives, they are partici-pating in proper measure in the government of their country.25. The constitutional scheme which the Government now put forward in Pant V is based on these principles and the Government have rejectedproposals, like those of partition or parity, which are inconsistent with them.The scheme is set out in brief on pages 22 and 23. Its provisions are thendiscussed in detail.
30EXECUTIVE council the Governor would preside over nine Ministers as under:4 Ex officio ministers Other Ministers (of whom four must have been &quot; ordinarily qualified &quot;candidates successful in the elections).In addition there would be two Assistant Ministers (the equivalent ofParliamentary Secretaries), not members of Executive Council, but bound bythe executive councillors oath of secrecy, allegiance, and office, and withaccess as may be directed by the Governor to Executive Council memorandaand minutes. Each would work immediately and directly under the instruc-tions of his Minister at all times.It would be provided that, of the total of eleven Ministers and AssistantMinisters, not less than two must be Africans and one of these must be a minister.SUMMARY of legislative council the Speaker and thirty members, returned as follows: \22 Elected members: 12 from &quot; ordinary constituencies &quot; each returning,one member, which would together includlall the Crown land areas which are generallyadjacent to the railway line, plus certain areas of Native Trust land and native reserves which are adjacent to those Crownland areas.6 from &quot; special constituencies &quot; each returningone member, which would cover the rest ofNorthern Rhodesia (including those smallerareas of Crown land which are not generallyadjacent to the railway line).2 from two regrouped constituencies covering thetotal area of the &quot; special constituencies &quot; butspecifically reserved for European members.2 from two regrouped constituencies covering thetotal area of the &quot; ordinary constituencies &quot;but specifically reserved for African members.6 Official members.2 Nominated members.
PROPOSED constitution the FRANCHISEA common voters&apos; roll containing (i) Ordinarily qualified voters, with qualifications at the levels set by theFederal Government for their general roll.(ii) Specially qualified voters, with qualifications at the levels set by theFederal Government for their special roll, with an addition of thenature set out in paragraph 34. The special qualifications to beraised periodically from their initial level until they coincide withthe ordinary qualifications after a period of ten years.All votes would count in full, provided that (i) in the twelve &quot; ordinary constituencies &quot;, the total of special votesmay not count more than one-third of the total of the ordinaryvotes cast;(ii) in the six &quot; special constituencies &quot;, the total of ordinary votes maynot count more than one-third of the total of special votes cast;(iii) in the amalgamated constituencies, the total of special votes may not count more than one-third of the total of ordinary votes cast wherethe seat is reserved to a European member, nor may the total of ordinary votes count more than one-third of the total of specialvotes cast where the seat is reserved to an African member.CANDIDATES would have to be qualified as under:(i) In &quot; ordinary constituencies &quot; as ordinarily qualified voters.(ii) In &quot; special constituencies&quot; either as ordinarily or as speciallyqualified voters.(iii) In amalgamated constituencies as ordinarily qualified voters.Every candidate for election who had special qualifications only would berequired to obtain a certificate from two-thirds of the chiefs recognised underCap. 157 and Cap. 159 of the Laws in his constituency that those chiefs hadno. objection to his standing as a candidate. Such candidates with special qualifications who met this requirement would stand for election in thenormal way.
PART V-THE GOVERNMENTS proposals the Franchise26. The present &quot; common voters&apos; roll&quot; is a common roll only in name.1The present representation in Legislative Council is by racial divisions : andthe tendency is, therefore, naturally for European members to feel themselvesprimarily responsible only to a non-African electorate, and for the African^members to feel that they have no responsibility for interests other than$African interests. In a system where members are politically responsible toone section of the community alone there must be the danger that a memberwill from time to time feel himself precluded from advocating in public what he believes to be sound and right, for fear of causing offence to at least a section of the racial group he represents. Whilst a member must lead, as wellas follow, his constituents, it is natural and inevitable that, particularly as thenext election approaches, he should defer more and more to what he believeswill most easily win support from his constituents. A short view, rather thana sound long-term view of policy, is likely thereby to be encouraged.27. Without exception members of the Northern Rhodesia LegislativeCouncil have in practice demonstrated their determination, even under suchunfavourable conditions, to reach disinterested decisions in the interests ofNorthern Rhodesia as a whole. But the burden laid on them by these condi-tions is heavy ; their difficulties are apparent; and a political system whichsubjects the people&apos;s representatives to such difficulties is clearly wrong. Alegislature which is bound by constitutional provisions to come together asan assembly of separate sectional or racial groups, because it is answerable to different sections or races of the Northern Rhodesia community rather than to the community as a whole, cannot be or become a truly integrated body,or provide a government which feels itself dedicated to, because it is trulyresponsible for, the interests of all Northern Rhodesians.28. The task, therefore, is to broaden the present franchise, and to devise a different method of electing the members of the Legislative Council. At thesame time, it would not only be impossible it would be unwise to attemptin present conditions to abolish all racial representation at one stroke of thepen: past history and the present position cannot be entirely ignored : theLegislative Council today contains both Africans and Europeans, and must continue to do so. But plans must be drawn so that a definite and significantstep is now taken to ensure that all members of the Legislative Council should feel themselves responsible to an electorate composed not solely of membersof their own race, but of all races ; they must represent all the qualified votersin a geographical constituency; they must be returned by a commonmachinery of direct election ; and their outlook must be such that the govern-ment of the country is conducted by members of the different races working in partnership.29. The Northern Rhodesia Government believe that the confidence andbacking of the general public can be maintained and fostered only if allraces are fairly represented in the legislature and are made to feel thatthrough their representatives they are participating in the government of thecountry.30. They consider that there should be a common voters&apos; roll, and that every qualified person within a geographical constituency should be eligible to vote for any member who is to represent that constituency.  Ultimately1 See Part II, paragraphs 10 and 11.24
-. - inthere should be only one common set of qualifications for registration as avoter and the general standard should therefore be set from the outset. s Thevast majority of Africans have not yet attained this standard, but some whowould not yet be able to meet the proposed permanent qualifications haveprogressed far enough along the road to be capable of voting in a responsiblemanner.tt!r 31. The franchise scheme must do justice both to individuals and to the&quot; African race as a whole. It must give a voice to those and only to those who have achieved a certain standard, but it must avoid leaving the Africanrace under-represented and feeling that justice has not been done to theirolaims. The Government believe that these several considerations can be satis-fied by introducing a second and lower set of temporary qualifications whichwill enable a fair proportion of Africans to qualify at once, by giving the vote to all those who are approaching the threshold of European standardswhile excluding others who have not yet attained even this point. It isproposed that both sets of qualifications should initially follow those set forFederal elections, viz.:Ordinary Voters(a)  720 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of propertyvalued at  1,500) ; or(6)  480 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of propertyvalued at  1,000), plus primary education ; or(c)  300 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of propertyvalued at  500), plus four years&apos; secondary education ; or(d) Ministers of religion who have undergone certain stipulatedcourses of training and periods of service in the ministry andwho follow no other profession or gainful occupation ; or(e) Paramount Chiefs and other chiefs recognised by the Governor;or those certified  by  the  Resident Commissioner  in theBarotseland Protectorate to be of equivalent status.Special Voters(a)  150 per annum (or ownership, including leasehold, of propertyvalued at  500); or(b)  120 per annum plus two years&apos; secondary education ;(c) in addition the persons described in paragraph 34 would also beenfranchised for territorial elections.The wife (only the first wife of a polygamous marriage) of any person in oneof the above categories may qualify if she fulfils the following qualifications,which will be required of every voter:(i) Simple literacy: Applicants must be able to complete in Englishwithout assistance the application to be registered as a voter.(ii) Age: Minimum age twenty-one.(iii) Nationality: British Subject, Citizen of Rhodesia and Nyasaland,or British Protected Person by virtue of connection with northern rhodesia.(iv) Residence: Two years in the Territory and three months in the constituency.32. It is the Governmenfs policy so to improve the educational andeconomic standards of the African people that over the years more and moreAfricans may be expected to qualify at the ordinary levels.   In anticipation ,of a general improvement in standards it would accordingly be provided that
the initial low qualifications would be progressively raised in stages over tenyears until they merged with the permanent qualifications. After that stagewas reached there would be only a single set of qualifications, which must be fulfilled by all new voters; applicants who met these requirements would be registered as ordinary voters but all persons already registered as specialvoters would remain as such on the roll.33. As under the Federal electoral law, provision would also be madi^jfor a quinquennial review of the purchasing power of money. An increase or decrease of more than 10 per cent, would be reflected in a correspondingadjustment of the means qualifications by 10 per cent, up or down for eachcomplete 10 per cent, by which the purchasing power of the currency had increased or decreased since 1958.34. The Government have welcomed the decision of the Federal Govern-ment to award the vote to chiefs in their own right, without regard to themeans qualification, and propose that chiefs should be similarly enfranchisedas ordinary voters on the territorial roll. The Government also proposein the territorial franchise to exempt from the means qualification, though not of course from the other general qualifications, applicants within thefollowing additional groups for registration as special voters:(i) persons who are and have been for the past two years headmen orhereditary councillors, who are recognised as such by their chiefs,and who are recommended by their chiefs, and are performingunpaid service in such office to the community ;(ii) persons who are in receipt of a monthly or annual pension earnedafter twenty years&apos; service with one employer.Composition of Legislative Council35. The broadening of the franchise to enable people of all races to feelthat they are exercising a proper say in the election of members to representthem in the Legislative Council will permit African members to be returnedto the Council for the first time by direct election from constituencies.36. The Governments proposals, as detailed in the succeeding para-graphs, provide for a Legislative Council composed of a Speaker and thirtymembers 22 Elected members.6 Official members.2 Nominated members.Elected Members37. Northern Rhodesia would be divided into eighteen constituencies,each returning one elected member. There would be twelve &quot; ordinary con-stituencies &quot; which would together include all the Crown land area which isgenerally adjacent to the railway line, plus certain areas of Native Trust land and Native Reserves which adjoin those areas. There would be six &quot; specialconstituencies &quot; comprising the remaining land area of Northern rhodesia and including the remaining smaller areas of Crown land.38. The great majority of the European population resides within thearea of the twelve ordinary constituencies. The bulk of the African popu-lation resides in the rural areas covered by the six special constituencies.But it will not always be the case that the ordinary voters (who will atthe outset be in the main Europeans) have a clear majority in the electoralrolls for ordinary constituencies; nor will special voters (chiefly Africans)necessarily start with a clear majority in the electoral rolls for specialconstituencies.
39. Northern Rhodesia has not yet advanced to the stage where&quot; the colour of their members is of no concern to the electorate, wheither that elec-torate be predominantly black or white. It is the hope and belief of theGovernment that that time will come ; and it is a cardinal aim of the present scheme for constitutional advance that a significant step shall be taken nowaway from a political system founded upon race. It is proposed for that reason that all candidates shall seek election from a multi-racial electorate&apos;.md that political parties should find it necessary to appeal to the votersof all races in order to improve their chances of success.40. In moving towards this goal of a non-racial society, it is necessary togo gently. Until the present policy of racial partnership has proved itself a success under the more advanced constitution now proposed, it would befolly to expect support for a system in which the main racial groups might be forced to rely for advocacy of their interests upon representatives of a differentrace. If confidence is to be fostered, Europeans and Africans must each bemade to feel that they are fairly represented and that they are participating,to the fullest extent that they are fitted to do, in the government of thecountry.41. Arrangements must therefore be made to ensure that all Africanvoters who desire to be represented at this stage by African members know that their votes will carry sufficient weight to secure the certain return of an african candidate ; and that all European voters can similarly count onseouring that a European member is returned to represent their interests.42. This legitimate and at present prevalent desire on the part of bothmajor racial groups must be recognised as a fact. And the Government holdfirmly that it can be provided for now without damage to the achievement oftheir ultimate objectives of policy. The voting strength can be so balancedthat the return of a European candidate can, if constituents so wish, be assured in the &quot; ordinary &quot; (generally urban) constituencies ; and the return of an African candidate can, if the constituents so wish, be assured in the&quot; special&quot; (generally rural) constituencies. The Government propose there-fore to limit the influence which may be exercised by special voters on theresult of the election in an ordinary constituency ; and similarly to limit theinfluence Which may be exercised by ordinary voters on the result of an election in a special constituency.43. In each of the twelve ordinary constituencies all votes would countin full, provided that the total of special votes may not count more than one-third of the total of ordinary votes cast in that constituency. Similarly, ineach of the six special constituencies, all votes would count in full providedthat the total of ordinary votes may not count more than one-third of thetotal of special votes cast in that constituency.44. To stop the scheme of representation at this point would, however,leave it open to two main criticisms. In the first place, it could be held thatcertain sections of the electorate were in effect disfranchised, because neitherthe special (mainly African) voters in the ordinary constituencies nor theordinary (mainly European) voters in the special constituencies could expect to secure representation by one of their own race. In the second place, sincethe rival interests of town and country may at times he opposed, it would be undesirable for these opposing interests to appear to be represented mainly by.Europeans on the one side and Africans on the other.45. It is therefore proposed to create two additional rural constituenciesspecifically reserved for European members, and two additional urban con-stituencies specifically reserved for African members. The total area of the
six &quot; special&quot; constituencies would for this purpose he regrouped into twoconstituencies each containing one reserved seat for a European) and thetotal area of the twelve &quot; ordinary &quot; constituencies would be regrouped into two constituencies each containing one seat specifically reserved for an african.46. In elections for the two reserved seats for European members, alLvotes would count in full provided that the total of special votes will not be,allowed to count more than one-third of the total of ordinary votes cast;and in elections for the two reserved seats for Africans, all votes would countin full provided that the total of ordinary votes will not be allowed to countmore than one-rthird of the total of special votes cast.47. Every qualified voter would thus have two votes. His first votewould invariably count in full; but, in accordance with the provisions of earlier paragraphs, his second vote might, depending on the relative numberof ordinary and special votes cast in a given election, be devalued.48. In this way twenty-two directly elected members would be secured,of whom 12 would be members elected in twelve &quot; ordinary constituencies &quot; ;6. would be members elected in six &quot; special constituencies &quot; ;2 would be Europeans elected in seats specifically reserved for Euro-peans; and2 would be Africans elected in seats speoifically reserved for Africans.All these members would have been returned in elections at which electors ofevery race were able to vote and each would accordingly represent an elec-torate which included all racial groups.49. In the Governmenfs view candidates in each of the twelve separate&quot; ordinary constituencies &quot; should be required to have &quot; ordinary&quot; votingqualifications. Candidates in each of the six separate &quot;special constitu-encies &quot; should have either &quot; ordinary &quot; or &quot; special &quot; voting qualifications.In each of the four amalgamated constituencies returning European or african members to reserved seats, candidates for election should be required to have&quot; ordinary &quot; voting qualifications.50. Under the present electoral law every candidate for election must be nominated by a proposer, a seconder and not fewer than seven other persons.The proposer and seconder must be persons registered on the voters&apos; roll forthe constituency in which the candidate seeks election. It is intended thatthese requirements should still suffice for all candidates who possess ordinaryvoter*s qualifications. For candidates who have only a special voter&apos;s qualifi-cation it is considered that a further provision is required.51. The good government of every part of Northern Rhodesia depends on two separate bodies, the Legislative Council and its local authority. Thereare two kinds of local authority, the municipal councils and town manage-ment boards on the one hand and the chiefs-in-council, the native authorities,on the other. Local government in the towns is already closely linked withthe territorial centre of government and the Legislative Council, and theGovernment believe it important that a similar link should be forged betweenthe Legislative Council and the native authorities in the rural areas.Qualifications for Candidates
52. It is accordingly proposed that every candidate offering himseff for election who has only a &quot; special&quot; voting qualification should be required toobtain a certificate from two-thirds of the chiefs recognised by the Governorin his constituency that those chiefs have no objection to his standing as a candidate. The certificate would need to be signed in the presence of witnessesduly appointed by the Governor.53. It has been urged on behalf of Africans that. Civil Servants shouldnot be debarred from standing for election to the Legislative Council. It isundeniable that a number of the best educated Africans are today to befound in the ranks of the Civil Service, and the Government accept that a potentially important source of African members would remain untapped ifCivil Servants were ineligible to offer themselves as candidates. It is intendedtherefore to provide that Civil Servants, other than those described below,may be granted leave if they wish to stand as candidates for election, on theunderstanding that, if elected, they would be required to resign. Those tobe excluded from this arrangement would be all members of Her Majesty&apos;overseas Civil Service, members of the police and prison services, teachers,and other officers who are concerned with the direction of policy to an extent which, in the opinion of the Government, would make it undesirable for themto take part in active politics.Composition of Executive Council54. The Executive Council is under the presidency of the Governor andat present has five official and four unofficial members. Each member holdsa portfolio and all are collectively responsible to the Council as a whole andto the Governor.55. The Government recognise that, so long as Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in the United Kingdom remain ultimately responsible to the british parliament for the good government of Northern Rhodesia, the Governorcannot divest himself of the special responsibilities which are inherent in his office, and which he carries by virtue of the provisions of the Orders in council made in Her Majesty&apos;s name. The Government consider, however, that thetime has come to provide that the Governors advisers in Executive council should cease to be predominantly official and become predominantly unofficial.The able and disinterested manner in which unofficial members have carriedniinisterial responsibility during the past four years gives justification forrecommending to Her Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom thatExecutive Council should be reconstituted to provide for a majority of unofficial members as under:The Governor (President).4 ex officio Ministers.5 other Ministers (of whom four must have been &quot; ordinarily qualified &quot;candidates successful in the elections).In addition there would be two Assistant Ministers (or Parliamentary Secre-taries), not members of Executive Council, but bound by the executivecouncillor^ oaths of secrecy, allegiance and office and with access as theGovernor may direct to Executive Council memoranda and minutes. Eachwould work immediately and directly under the instructions of his Ministerat all times.56. The Government consider that provision should also be made forAfricans Ithemselves to play a more direct part in the administration. Itwould accordingly be laid down that, of the total of eleven ministerial posts(nine Ministers and two Assistant Ministers), not less than two should be filled by Africans, of whom one should be a Minister.
Nominated Members57. The present Legislative Council contains two unofficial * membersnominated by the Governor specifically to represent African interests. Underthese new proposals African interests will be fully and effectively representedwithout this special provision; and the proposed new nominated members would not have this specific duty laid upon them.58. A complement of two nominated members will however be retained^as an insurance that the increased requirement for Ministers who are notofficials, and in particular the need to find two Africans for ministerial office,can be met in the conceivable circumstance that the elections fail to returna sufficient number of candidates who are both able and willing to devotetheir full time to ministerial duties.59. The constitutional instrument would provide that the two nominated members were to be nominated by the Governor after the results of theelections were known, and after consultation with the leader of the partyreturned with the greatest number of seats. Before making his nominations,the Governor would be enjoined to have regard (i) to the results of the elections (so that there would be power to correct any unbalance in the designed composition of the Legis-lative Council that might be caused through freak elections); and(ii) to the ability and readiness of those already elected to devote their full time to the work of a portfolio (so that the Executive council may be composed in accordance with the design for it).Official Members60. The present step in constitutional advance will represent a significantmove towards the Governments declared policy of a franchise with no separate representation for the races. In none of the discussions which havebeen held, however, has it once been suggested that this objective can be fully achieved at once.61. Until each race has lost its fear of domination by another race for itsown racial benefit, the transitional safeguards referred to in the principles set out in paragraph 17 cannot be discarded. In particular, Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment must retain the means to fulfil their ultimate responsibility for ensuring that on contentious issues the balance is fairly held. The arrange-ments earlier described for the franchise and the proposed pattern of con-stituencies envisage the probable return to Legislative Council of fourteenelected European members and eight elected African members. To maintainthe balance, while yet making an important constitutional advance, theGovernment propose that the present eight official members of the LegislativeCouncil should be reduced to six.Conclusion62. The scheme described in the foregoing sections is summarised below.63. There would be a common voters&apos; roll containing both ordinary and special voters; the ordinary and special qualifications would be at the samelevels as those in the Federal franchise, and would include the award of the vote to chiefs and the further special variations set out in paragraph 34 above.In the Legislative Council there would be a Speaker and thirty members ofwhom twenty-two would be directly elected, six would be officials and twonominated members. Northern Rhodesia would be divided into eighteenconstituencies, twelve of them comprising the Crown land adjacent to the
railway and certain adjoining areas of Native Reserve and Native Trust land f&quot;the other six would be largely rural constituencies and would include somesmaller areas of Crown land away from the railway. Within the total areacomprised by the twelve ordinary constituencies there would be two furtherseats reserved for Africans, and within the total area of the six special con-stituencies there would be two further seats reserved for Europeans. In the twelve ordinary constituencies and in elections for the two seats reserved toEuropeans all votes would count in full, provided that special votes mightnot in total count more than one-third of the total of ordinary votes cast.Similarly in the six special constituencies and in elections for the two seatsreserved to Africans, all votes would count in full but the total of ordinaryvotes would not be allowed to count more than the same fraction of thetotal of special votes cast.64. Candidates standing in ordinary constituencies would be requiredto hold &quot; ordinary&quot; qualifications; those in special constituencies could have either &quot; ordinary &quot; or &quot; special&quot; qualifications, and those in the fouramalgamated constituencies would again require &quot; ordinary&quot; qualifications.Every candidate with a &quot; special&quot; qualification should be required to obtaincertificates from not less than two-thirds of the recognised chiefs in his areathat they had no objection to his standing as a candidate.65. The Governor would preside over an Executive Council containingfour officials, instead of five as at present, and five other Ministers of whomfour would be ordinarily qualified candidates successful in the elections. Inaddition there would be two Assistant Ministers, not members of ExecutiveCouncil but bound by the oaths of an executive councillor and workingdirecdy to the instructions of their senior Minister. It would be providedthat, of the total of eleven Ministers and Assistant Ministers, two must beAfricans and one of these must be a Minister.66. The two nominated members of the Legislative Council would not bethere specifically to represent African interests like the present nominated members. They would be nominated by the Governor after the results of theelections were known and after consultation with the leader of the majorityparty. The Governor would be enjoined in making his nominations to haveregard to the results of the elections, and to the ability of those already elected to devote their full time to the work of a portfolio. This provision guardsagainst both an unsound balance caused by freak elections ; and the possibility that the elections might throw up too few members who were both ready and able to devote their full time to a portfolio, or no Africans of sufficientcalibre to do so.67. In order to inject stability certain provisions of the scheme would beentrenched in the constitutional instrument so that the main lines of con-stitutional advance would be settled for some time ahead and the confidence of the people would not be continually jeopardised by the prospect of drastic changes every few years. The entrenched provisions would include the evolution of the franchise, the general principles governing the division ofthe country into constituencies, the relative weights to be attributed to ordinary and special votes, the number of members to be returned by amajority of ordinary voters, and the number of members to be returned bya majority of special voters. Once constituencies had been demarcated,however, the power to make boundary or such other changes as might inthe future appear desirable would be vested in the legislature.68. The Government are not sanguine enough to hope that every detailof the proposals now put forward will commend itself to every section of the complex society which is Northern Rhodesia.  Indeed, there is no member
of the Government itself who is in full agreement with every detail of theproposals when considered in isolation and would not like to. see some ofthem changed. Furthermore, it is possible that all political parties and many other bodies will not only express strong views on certain features of thisscheme but will also put forward constructive suggestions for amendmends and improvements. The Government expect that, in particular, criticismmay be directed most probably before full consideration and understanding^of the balances needed have been achieved against what will be termectP&quot; the complexity of the scheme&quot; ; and such critics are most likely to be encountered outside the boundaries of Northern Rhodesia, or indeed of rhodesia and Nyasaland, where, in very different conditions and with a muchmore homogeneous population, there is inevitably a failure to recognise that northern Rhodesia is, in hard and difficult fact, a complex society.69. This hard and difficult fact is the challenge which the Governmentof Northern Rhodesia, itself a complex and balanced body, has had to meet and has met over the past four constructive years. The Government willsay to such critics that these proposals represent a balanced scheme, designedspecifically to take account of the past history, and the present actual con-ditions, in Northern Rhodesia ; designed specifically to give the fairest possiblewind to the policy accepted and established for the whole of the Federation.The Government recognise, and ask both the country and external critics torecognise, that a change of detail inevitably means a change of balance.70. The Government make these claims for their scheme: it observesin all respects and begins to implement the principles set out earlier and generally accepted by all parties in Northern Rhodesia. In particular, it takes a definite step away from racialism, whilst reserving to each race thefull certainty that, in the (transitional period, their interests will be fully safaguarded, both by the retention of the -balance in the Legislative and executive Councils, and by their ability, for so long as it matters to them, tosecure the election of candidates of their own race to represent them in theLegislative Council. It offers at the same time an appreciable further measureof responsible government; and it sets a clear path for the development of full parliamentary government and self-government, in partnership andco-operation.71. We have come a long way from the arrangements of 1924. We haveespecially made a most significant advance over the past ten years. TheGovernment of Northern Rhodesia now put forward their scheme for public discussion in the belief that it is a good and honest scheme, which merits thesupport and faith of all sections of the community ; and that it will commend itself to all who have the future stability and prosperity of Northern Rhodesiaclose to their hearts.
m   1CONSTITUENCIESPossible Pattern of Ordinary, Special and Reserved Seat ConstituenciesThis table is included as an example to illustrate the proposals in the Paper, and should not be taken as more than a tentative planTwelve Ordinary Constituencies in generally urban areas. Chingola the Chingola and Bancroft Districts.2. Mufulira the Mufulira District.3. Nkana the Nkana Mine Township.4. KrrwE the Kitwe District excluding Nkana; and the Kalulushi District.5. Luanshya the Luanshya District.6. Ndola the Ndola Urban and Ndola Rural Districts.7. Broken Hill the Broken Hill Urban District.8. Lusaka Central the central urban area of Lusaka Municipality.9. Lusaka East the eastern parts of Lusaka Urban and Rural Districts; Crownland in that part of the Broken Hill Rural District which lies to the south ofthe Broken Hill Urban District; and the Feira District.10. Lusaka West the western parts of Lusaka Urban and Rural Districts.11. Southern Native land east of rail and Crown land in the Mazabuka andChoma Districts; and Crown land in the Kalomo District.12. Livingstone the Livingstone District.Six Special Constituencies in generally rural areas. Barotseland the Barotseland Protectorate.2. North-Western the Solwezi, Kasempa, Mwinilunga, Kabompo and BalovaleDistricts.3. South-Western Native land west of rail in the Mazabuka, Choma andBroken Hill Rural Districts; Native land in the Kalomo District; theGwembe, Namwala and Mumbwa Districts.4. Eastern the Fort Jameson, Lundazi and Petauke Districts.5. Northern the Kasama, Chinsali, Mpika and Isoka Districts and the Bembaparts of the Luwingu District.6. Luapula the Abercorn, Mporokoso, Kawambwa and Fort Rosebery Dis-tricts and the non-Bemba parts of the Luwingu District; Crown land inthat part of the Broken Hill Rural District which lies north of the Broken,Hill Urban District; and Native land east of rail in the Broken Hill rural district.Two Reserved Seats for Africans in urban areas. Copperbelt the area covered by the Chingola, Mufulira, Nkana, Kitwe,Luanshya and Ndola constituencies.2. South Central the area covered by the Broken Hill, Lusaka, Southern andLivingstone constituencies.Two Reserved Seats for Europeans in rural areas. Eastern Rural the area covered by the Eastern, Northern and Luapulaconstituencies.2. Western Rural the area covered by the Barotseland, North-Western andSouth-Western constituencies.
Type of seatOrdinarySpecialAfricanReserved.EuropeanReserved.ConstituencyAl.  Chingola   ...A2.  Mufulira   ...A3.  NkanaA4.  KitweA5.  Luanshya ...A6.  NdolaA7.  Broken HillA8. Lusaka CentralA9.  Lusaka EastA10. Lusaka WestAll. Southern   ...A12. LivingstoneTotal (A)Cl. BarotselandC2. North-WesternC3. South-WesternC4. EasternC5. Northern  ...C6. LuapulaBl.B2.Dl.D2.Total (C)Copperbelt...South CentralTotal (B)Eastern RuralWestern RuralTotal (d)Territorial total (OO+CC) or (BJ+CD)) ..estimated number ofOrdinaryvoters1,1561,5401,4601,4221,9602,7361.-8621,4901,7491,4871,22879618,88614411545490902421,12610,2748,61218,8868223041,12620,012Estimatednumber ofSpecialvoters2,2371,4311,5001,4381,9211,8641,1011,2501,0065012,13391317,2951,1644611,8781,0151,0301,8057,35310,3916,90417,2954,0433,3107,35324,648EstimatedtotalElectorate3,3932,9712,9602,8603,8814,6002,9632,7402,7551,9883,3611,70936,1811,3085761,9231,5051,1202,0478,47920,66515,51636,1814,8653,6148,47944,660Note -The value which it is proposed that ordinary and special votes should be givenis set out in the table on pages 22 and 23 and is explained in detail in paragraphs 37 to 48.DISTRIBUTION OF PROBABLE ELECTORATE BY CONSTITUENCIESDESCRIBED IN APPENDIX A &apos;
Qualification based on income to be registered as a special voter a person shall require an annual income of:at the commencement of the scheme  150 plus simple literacy, or  120 with two years&apos; secondary education;after three years  300 plus simple literacy, or  210, having completed acourse of primary education, or  150 with two years&apos; secondary education;after six years  450 plus simple literacy, or  3c1 having completed a courseof primary education, or  200 with two years&apos; secondary education;after eight years  600 plus simple literacy, or  390 having completed a courseof primary education, or  250 with two years&apos; secondary education.Qualification based on property to be registered as a special voter a person shall require immovable propertyworth:at the commencement of the scheme  500 plus simple literacy;after three years  750 plus simple literacy, or  600 having completed a courseof primary education, or  500 with two years&apos; secondary education;after six years  1,000 plus simple literacy, or  750 having completed a courseof primary education, or  500 with two years&apos; secondary education;after eight years  1,250 plus simple literacy, or  900 having completed acourse of primary education, or  500 with two years&apos; secondary education.After the expiry of ten years all new applicants for registration must have thepermanent qualifications described in paragraph 31 and will be registered as ordinaryvoters, but voters already registered as special voters will remain as such on the roll.No person who has been registered as a voter shall have his name removed fromthe roll because his income is less than that currently required by new applicants for registration.A person registered as a special voter who subsequently achieves the qualificationscurrently required by new applicants for registration as ordinary voters may apply tobe transferred to the ordinary voters&apos; section of the roll.(31316)   Wt. 553-7705   K24  9/58   D.L.EVOLUTION OF THE FRANCHISEProposed Progression of the Special Qualifications
Printed and published by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery OfficeTo be purchased from york House, Kingsway, London w.c.2423 Oxford Street, London w.l13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2109 St. Mary Street, Cardiff39 King Street, Manchester tower Lane, Bristol 12 Edmund Street, Birmingham 380 Chichester Street, belfast or through any bookseller printed in Great Britain
Printed and published by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery OfficeTo be purchased from york House, Kingsway, London \v.c.2423 Oxford Street, London w.l13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2109 St. Mary Street, Cardiff39 King Street, Manchester tower Lane, Bristol 12 Edmund Street, Birmingham 380 Chichester Street, Belfast -or through any bookseller printed in Great Britain

</content>
</cab>
