<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 176-180</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. November 1958C. (58) 23314th November, 1958CABINETTHE INTERNATIONAL COURT OF JUSTICE:UNITED KINGDOM RESERVATIONSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs in April 1957 we entered two new reservations to our acceptance of the compulsory jurisdiction of the International Court of Justice. One of these excepteddisputes which, in the opinion of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, affect our national security.2. The case for reconsidering our attitude in regard to this reservation is setout in detail in the paper annexed. The arguments in favour of doing so may besummarised as follows:  (a) At the time when the reservation was made it was very strongly criticised.Although these criticisms have since died down, they have not ceased,and it is difficult to produce a fully effective answer to them.(b) The United States Government have made a reservation in broadly similar terms to ours. There is now evidence that they may decide towithdraw or amend it. If they did so, it would be much more difficult for us to maintain our reservation.(c) In a case now before the International Court the Court may very welldecide that reservations like ours are invalid. If the Court should sodecide, we should have no option but to withdraw or amend ourreservation.(d) We have joined with the United States and Israel in bringing a case beforethe International Court against Bulgaria in respect of the shootingdown of an Israeli airliner. So long as we maintain our reservation inits present form, the Bulgarians may be able to quote it back at us and thereby escape the jurisdiction of the Court.3. The paper at Annex A also shows that, although we could withdraw the reservation and replace it by a new one in somewhat different form, there arestrong arguments against this course. If any change is to be made it would be best to withdraw the reservation altogether and not replace it.4. I therefore recommend that the reservation should be withdrawn. Thematter is of some urgency since the Courfs decision in the case mentioned inparagraph 2 (c) above may be made by the end of November or early in December.If we are to act it would obviously be better to do so voluntarily rather than after an adverse finding by the Court.S. L.Foreign Office, S.W.1,13th November, 1958,3\ Copy No. 554318bCONFIDENTIALTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
ANNEX AIn April 1957 when we were about to embark on our first series of nuclear testsin the central Pacific, we were faced with the possibility that Japan might attemptto take us before the International Court on the charge that the holding of such testsamounted to a violation of the principle of the freedom of the seas. As it wouldhave been open to Japan, pending a final decision in the case, to obtain an interiminjunction against us requiring suspension of the tests, and since it would in facthave been impossible to suspend them, we should have been obliged to refuse tocomply. In order, therefore, to prevent such a situation arising, we added a freshreservation to our acceptance of the Courfs compulsory jurisdiction excepting&quot; disputes .... relating to any question which in the opinion of the Government ofthe United Kingdom, affects the national security of the United Kingdom or of anyof its dependent territories.&quot; For political reasons, any specific reference to nuclear tests was avoided, but the passage italicised was deliberately inserted in view ofthe danger that the International Court might not hold that a question relating toour carrying out nuclear tests in the Pacific was a question relating to our national security.2. When the text of this new reservation became generally known, it led to considerable criticism, partly based on the pronouncements of certain of the judges of the International Court (including the United Kingdom Judge) in a case thenbefore it. This criticism was directed in particular at the phrase &quot; which in theopinion of the United Kingdom Government, affects,&quot; &amp;c. It was contended thatthis phrase, coupled with the reference to national security, was so wide as to enable us in practice to remove any case from the jurisdiction of the Court, and therebyeffectively to cancel out our professed acceptance of the Court&apos;s compulsoryjurisdiction. There were also other grounds of objection. We met these criticismsas best we could, but they were not all easy to deal with convincingly, and althougheventually they died down, they have never completely ceased.3. In the meantime there have been other developments which raise thequestion whether we ought not to reconsider our attitude in regard to this reservation:  (a) The United States have made a reservation to their acceptance of theCourt&apos;s compulsory jurisdiction which, while not in the same terms asours, is capable of having a broadly similar effect, and involves the samebasic point. It is a reservation in respect of matters which are withinthe domestic jurisdiction of the United States, &quot; as determined by theUnited States.&quot; This reservation has been criticised in the United States,and there have recently been indications, including public statements bythe United States Attorney-General and the Legal Adviser to the state department, that the United States Government may be consideringaltering it by the omission of the words &quot; as determined by the UnitedStates &quot; (certain extracts from what the Attorney General said are at annex B). If the United States took any such action while we continuedto maintain our own reservation, we should be exposed to a fresh round of criticism, and probably be pressed to follow suit, even though certain other countries, such as France, continued to maintain this type ofreservation.(b) The International Court has now before it a case called the Interhandelcase, between Switzerland and the United States, in which these issues are being raised. The indications are that the Court may well find, andis perhaps likely to find, that the type of reservation according to whicha country professing to accept the Courfs compulsory jurisdictionconfers upon itself the right to determine conclusively whether the reservation applies, is invalid and of no effect, as being inconsistent withthe purported acceptance of the compulsory jurisdiction. If this occurred, we should be forced to withdraw or amend the reservation,and it would be said that our critics had been vindicated. It would bebetter to have acted in advance.(c) We have joined with the United States and Israel in bringing a case beforethe International Court against Bulgaria. This case arises out of theEl Al incident, in which an Israeli aircraft carrying British, american and Israeli passengers and freight, which had inadvertently strayed over
the Bulgarian frontier in bad weather, was shot down and destroyedwith the loss of all the lives concerned. One of our difficulties in this case, without going into technicalities, is that so long as we maintain our national security reservation in its present form, Bulgaria could(because of the reciprocity rule) quote it back at us, and thereby escape the jurisdiction of the Court. As the bringing of the El Al case was undertaken by us more out of solidarity with our two co-plaintiffs than with any real hope of obtaining anything, this might not matter verymuch materially, but it would nevertheless be embarrassing. The El Alcase is still in its early stages, and therefore, while there may be certainprocedural difficulties, it ought not to be too late to put matters rightso far as this point goes.4. In these circumstances, it seems desirable to consider whether this reservation should be withdrawn or altered.  There are three possibilities:  (i) to withdraw the reservation altogether and not replace it;(ii) to withdraw it, and replace it by another specifically excluding theInternational Courfs jurisdiction in relation to nuclear tests;(iii) to withdraw it, but replace it by another merely omitting the words &quot; inthe opinion of the Government of the United Kingdom.&quot;5. Adoption of the first alternative would put us back in the position in whichwe found ourselves in April 1957. But even though, because of the Russianattitude, we now hold ourselves to be released from our recent undertaking to suspend tests for a year, we shall probably not carry out any further tests in the pacific* for some months or possibly a year. There is also the possibility that the geneva Conference may lead to an even more prolonged suspension. Consequentlywe have no immediate need of this reservation, and perhaps may not have anyneed of it for some time. If we withdrew it, we should be exposing ourselves to possible claims before the International Court in respect of past tests already held;but the risk of such claims being made does not appear to be great, and we could in any event protect ourselves against it by a suitably drafted passage in our noticeof withdrawal.6. If, having followed this course, we decided later that there must be a resumption of tests, it would then be possible to re-introduce a specific reservationon nuclear testing, and since any resumption of testing would in any event giverise to much criticism from various quarters, it may be that the simultaneousentering of a new reservation to the International Courfs jurisdiction on the subject would not add much to the outcry, particularly if it could be represented that theneed to resume testing, and to protect ourselves, was the consequence of Russianintransigence. On the other hand, a renewed reservation on the subject mightwell be regarded as an aggravation, and as a ground for further criticism.7. The second alternative (see paragraph 4) is open to the grave disadvantagethat, at the present juncture, it might politically be seriously embarrassing to entera specific reservation on nuclear tests. It would certainly be asked whether this meant that the Government definitely intended to resume testing in the near future.8. Adoption of the third alternative would be attractive but for the dangermentioned at the end of paragraph 1 of this paper. By following this course weshould avoid any specific mention of nuclear tests, while getting rid of the phrasewhich has principally attracted criticism and which the International Court may shortly declare to be invalid. However, we should still be faced with the fact that,if we resumed testing at some point, the absence of this phrase would deprive us ofthe certainty of not being taken before the Court. Consequently there are no realadvantages to be gained from this course.9. The conclusion appears to be that, if it is decided to change the presentposition, then of the three courses mentioned in paragraph 4 of this paper, the first would be the better. If the decision in the Interhandel case goes as expected (seeparagraph 3 (a) above) it would be better if we had simply withdrawn the reservation(since it would then no longer be of any effect). We should then obtain the credit* Possible small land tests (e.g., in Australia) wou&apos;d not raise the issue of the freedom of the seasor be open to any obvious attack on legal grounds.CONFIDENTIAL54318 b 2
Foreign Office, S.W.1,November, 1958.of having acted voluntarily, which we should otherwise lose. The decision in this case is most likely to be given about the end of this month or early in December,and therefore the matter has become urgent.10. One objection to following any of the three courses, and hence to anychange in the present position, is that, despite the fact that the reservation does not specifically refer to nuclear tests, its withdrawal or modification might be taken as implying an intention by the Government to abandon further testing. If so, thepolitical embarrassment of restarting tests and of reintroducing a coveringreservation would be increased.11.   Three subsidiary factors call for notice:  (a) Japan has now entered a standing acceptance of the International Courfscompulsory jurisdiction, without any reservations except as toreciprocity. As a result she will be free, as from 15th September, 1959,from the scope of another reservation we had made which would have prevented her from taking us to the Court even without our national security reservation.(b) We have signed, and are likely in due course to ratify, the Convention onthe High Seas which was one of the four Conventions drawn up atGeneva last April. We have also signed the Protocol on the compulsorysettlement of disputes arising under these Conventions drawn up at thesame time, which provides for a reference to the International Courtunless the parties to the dispute agree on another mode of settlement,e.g., arbitration. Without going into technicalities, it is possible thatwhen this Convention is ratified and in force, a country like Japan, ifa party to it, could base a claim against us in the International Court,about nuclear testing, because of the references the Convention containsto the principle of the freedom of the seas.. The reservation to our acceptance of the general compulsory jurisdiction of the international court would not apply to a dispute under the Convention.Consequently, although such a&quot; situation can probably be avoided, ifit did come about we might be forced before the Court in any event,and in that case the importance of continuing to maintain a reservationabout national security, would, so far as nuclear tests were concerned,be gone.(c) Although, for the reasons given in paragraph 6 of this Paper, withdrawalof the existing reservation would not prevent us from restarting testsif we want to, any element of uncertainty or of embarrassment about our doing so which might thereby be created would raise the questionhow far it was reasonable to continue to incur the very large (expenditure involved in maintaining the Christmas Island site in a stateof constant readiness for use.12. On the whole it seems best that we should withdraw this reservation,part of which may in any case be declared invalid by the International Court inthe near future, and which we could not now replace with a specific reservationon nuclear tests without grave embarrassment. A decision whether : or noteventually to reintroduce a reservation covering the matter, if we resumed testing,would have to be taken in the light of the circumstances at the time, though it mighthave to be taken at rather short notice.
ANNEX BExtracts from a Paper Entitled &quot; International Order under Law&quot; Read byMr. W. P. Rogers, Attorney-General of the United States, before the Inter-national Law Association Meeting in New York on 2nd September, 1958Published in the United States State Department Bulletin for October 1958With this history of the domestic-jurisdiction reservation before us, thequestion is whether this type of specific reservation by several nations as to thejurisdiction of the Court tends to impair or enhance a rule of law in international affairs. Should such reservations be retained in their present form? Just asdomestic courts could not function effectively if parties chose not to appear, so, too,the administration of justice by international courts is impaired and may be nullifiedif the nations can refuse to submit their differences to it.The time has come, I think, in the light of experience with the Court tore-examine the domestic-jurisdiction reservation of the unilateral type to determineif it should be retained or changed. If retained, it might be limited in some more reasonable way.The International Court needs more support if it is to succeed in theaccomplishment of its purposes. Without some step looking toward some enlargedjurisdiction it cannot hope to attain the position it should occupy in the world community striving toward a rule of law and justice.

</content>
</cab>
