<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 244-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS government.(58) 245 COPY NO.I&amp;-IJ3rd December, 1958CABINETCOTTON:  IMPORTS FROM HONG Kong memorandum by the President of the Board of trade the Cabinet may wish to have an up-to-date report on thenegotiations between the Cotton Board and the cotton textile industry of hong Kong.2.        As my colleagues will recall, the Cotton Board reached agreementwith the industries of India and Pakistan in the summer (C. C. (58) 53rdConclusions, Minute 5).    These agreements are conditional on arrange-ments being made with Hnng Kong which are acceptable to India and pakistan.    Since then the Cotton Board have been in negotiation with the hong Kong industry.3.        There are two main reasons for the long delay.    First, the hong Kong Negotiating Committee is an unwieldy body split by internaldissensions between the different sections.    They are still at odds on localquestions which do not directly concern Lancashire including whetherHong Kong weavers should remain free to use India and Pakistan as distinct from Hong Kong aara.    The latet-t news is that there is some hopethat these local difficulties may soon be resolved.     Until they are the hong Kong industry v/ill not enter into any understanding with Lancashire.4.        Secondly, the Cotton Board and the Hong Kong Committee have notyet been able to agree on a number of points of which the most important is the question whether there should be annual increases in the ceilingin each of the three years or whether, as Lancashire proposed (after thePrime Minister&apos;s private talks with leaders of the industry at theHarrogate Conference in October) there should be a flat-rate ceiling of115 million square yards a year.    The Cotton Board&apos;s view is that this figure provides scope for the Hong Kong trade to expand:  it is considerably above the actual figure for 1958.    The Hong Kong industry,while apparently ready to agree that the aggregate for the three years should be 345 million square yards, are however insisting on a system ofescalation which would mean 110, 115 and 120 millions respectively for thethree years.5.        It does not look as if the other points which are still at issue will prove insuperable but the view of the Governor of Hong Kong is that acceptance of a flat-rate ceiling would be a point of real difficulty forthe Hong Kong industry,6.        The present position is that after a discussion with the PrimeMinister, in which the Colonial Secretary and I took part, the Cotton Boardreplied last week to the Hong Kong Committee dealing among other points
with their reasons for insisting on the flat-rate ceiling.    Colonel Clague,the Chairman of the Hong Kong Committee, felt that to put an uncompromisingreply to the Committee at such a delicate stage would almost certainly lead to a breakdown.     However, a meeting of the Committee has beententatively arranged for Friday, 5th December, with a view to the reply from the Cotton Board being discussed in the light of any further commentsfrom the latter.7.        Officials are discussing the situation with the Chairman of theCotton Board, Lord Rochdale, to-day (3rd December).    It will, of course,be for the Cotton Board to decide whether, in the light of the reportfrom the Governor, the answer sent last week should be modified,particularly on the question of annually rising ceilings.8.        Meanwhile, it is encouraging that Colonel Clague has toldLord Rochdale that he would be prepared to endeavour to obtain his committee^ approval for an early announcement that they would be agree-able to any understanding becoming effective on 1st January, 1958,irrespective of the date of signature.    Such an announcement would be ofgreat political and psychological value here, and we are proposing to tell the Governor that if it would help him in getting the control arrangementsgoing (if only on an interim basis) by 1st January, we shall be glad tosend out to Hong Kong officials with expert knowledge of such matters.The Indian and Pakistan Governments and industries have been kept inclose touch with developments so that there will be no avoidable delay inconcluding matters with them once an understanding has been reached with Hong Kong.D.E.Board of Trade, S. W.l.3rd December, 1958.-2-

</content>
</cab>
