<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 317-319</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ItI1(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y*S GOVERNMENT)C.(58) 252 COPY NO.o13th December, 1958CABINETPR^JECTI^N OF THE commonwealth in THE UNITED kingdom memorandum by the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and the Chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterAt the request of the Prime Minister, consideration has beengiven to practical ways of promoting the Commonwealth ideal in Britain.2.        A thorough survey by officials has shown that knowledge and understanding of the Commonwealth in this country are unsatisfactory.This should not surprise us.   Little has been done by the Government to counter the widespread feeling that we can take the Commonwealth for granted and the Commonwealth is not prominently featured.3.        We are no longer handicapped by the feeling of many that thename Empire Day should be changed to Commonwealth Day(C.C.(58) 8lst Conclusions, Minute 9).4.        The wide interest shown in the prime Ministers Commonwealthtour suggests that there is scope for a modest programme of action bythe Government which should attract general support from the manyvoluntary organisations having some interest in the Commonwealth.   but these voluntary organisations are somewhat jealous of each other and wecannot look to them for a successful initiative.   The Government must give a lead.5.        The following practical steps are among those open to us now:-(i)  Expansion of the Commonwealth Instituted work in schools,including increased lecture service for schools and suitable smallCommonwealth exhibits for school use.(ii)  Publication for general sale of an up-to-date and well-prepared popular booklet about the Commonwealth ideal.(iii) Encouragement of sales in this country of the Central Officeof Information^ publications about the Commonwealth whichare prepared primarily for use by the Oversea information services, including the excellent illustrated magazine&quot;Commonwealth Today&quot;.(iv) Reduction of the hiring fees charged by the Central FilmLibrary of the Central Office of Information, for Commonwealthfilm s.-1-
(v) Preparation of a travelling Commonwealth exhibition fordisplay in leading cities and towns.(vi) Organisation by a series of &quot;Commonwealth Weeks&quot; inleading cities and towns, using the travelling exhibition as thefocal point and enlisting the support of local authorities, industryand commerce and others.(vii) Encouraging greater press and television interest in theCommonwealth.6.        Fortunately, we have two experienced and well-tried organisationsready to hand for this work; the Commonwealth Institute and the central office of Information.   Although the Commonwealth Institute is to move to new buildings which will not be completed until mid-1962, this does notrule out a useful expansion of the Instituted work in schools.   The central office of Information is already well-established as the executive Depart-ment available to Government Departments for the production of publicitymaterial, including wide experience of exhibitions work.7.        We should, of course, seek to enlist the support of the manyvoluntary organisations with Commonwealth interests and associations.The Nuffield Foundation are willing to sponsor a meeting of leading people in these organisations in preparation for holding in due course a Conferenceof Voluntary Organisations (possibly under.the sponsorship of the .Duke of Edinburgh).   A Commonwealth Educational Conference is planned to be held next summer in the United Kingdom.   We should also draw in local authorities, industry and commerce in much the same way as theEnglish Speaking Union recently did most successfully in a private venturein Sheffield.   (This venture was warmly supported by the City authorities,by local commerce and industrial interests and by the Trade Commission Officesthere were meetings addressed by prominent Commonwealth speakers,together with Commonwealth films and displays.)8.        If we can persuade the voluntary organisations to work closelytogether in support of a programme on these lines, so much the better.But this is bound to take time;  and responsibility for co-ordinating thismodest programme would appropriately fall to the Commonwealth Secretary,assisted perhaps by a National Consultative Committee and by regionalsupporting committees as necessary.9.        We need not engage in any formal consultation with other commonwealth Governments about action on these lines.   &quot;iur aim wouldbe to present the Commonwealth, as we see it, to our own people.   Weshould, of course, enlist the help of the High Commission Offices in London.10.       A programme on these lines need not be expensive.   For a sum ofabout  75,000 to  80,000 a year we should be able to make a considerableimpact on the problem of projecting the Commonwealth at home.11.       This seems to be a good time to make a start.   The MontrealTrade and Economic Conference aroused wider interest in the UnitedKingdom than was generally expected and next summer the importantCommonwealth Educational Conference will be held here.-2-CONFIDENT1AL
12. We invite our colleagues to endorse, in principle, the programmeoutlined in paragraphs 5 and 10 above.13.       The Chancellor of the Exchequer is aware of the proposals inthis memorandum but is not committed to them.H.CH.12th December, 1958-3-CONFIDE NT1 AL

</content>
</cab>
