<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 330-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(1C.(58) 256 COPY NO. jTj20th December, 1958CABINETRETAIL PRICE INDEX:   FORECAST FOR 1959Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service it is difficult, at any time, to forecast with any degree of accuracythe probable movements of the retail prices index  and it is even moredifficult now that the index in recent months has been moving within narrowlimits.   It is particularly difficult to forecast with any confidence theprobable movements of potato and beef prices next year.2. In certain respects 1950 has been a disappointing year fromthe point of view of home agriculture, and some-prices, notably potatoprices, have been above trend.   The prices of butter and cheese have been rising and may not fall back.   The index was very much affected in thesecond quarter of 195c by the shortage of potatoes.   The home crop thisyear appears to be inferior to last year&apos;s crop both as regards size and quality, and already in October the average price of potatoes was much higher than a year earlier.   Even with imports on a substantial scale wemust expect a marked rise in the price of potatoes in the first half of 1959.In the second half of the year there should be a substantial fall, assumingmore normal weather conditions.   Taking all these factors into considerationit seems likely that food prices will rise substantially in the first half of1959 compared both with the first half of 1958 and with November, 1958,but will fall back in the second half of the year.3. The index of prices of non-food manufactured products has beenroughly stable since October, 1957, although it rose slightly in the first few months of 1958 and then fell back as a result of cuts in purchase tax.The average price of imported materials used in producing this category of goods has apparently continued to fall throughout 1958, in contra-distinction to the movement of import prices in general.   It is thereforelikely that the index for this group will remain fairly stable (despite someincreases in wage costs) during the first half of next year but it seems likely that there will be some increase in the second half of the yearreflecting both higher wage costs and possibly higher import prices.4. Not very much increase is expected in the other components ofthe index of retail prices.   The cost of housing will probably rise a little,mainly because of increased local authority rents and rates, and there willprobably also be some increase in rents paid to private landlords since there is evidence that a substantial proportion of landlords (possibly about one-third) have not yet taken full advantage of the new legislation.   some increase is also expected in the prices of fuel, light, transport and servicesowing to increased wage costs.-1-HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
5. Taking into account the various factors mentioned above, itseems likely that the average index for the whole of 1959 may be about points higher than the average for 1958.   In the first half of 1959the index may well be over Z points above the corresponding level of1958 owing to some high food prices (especially potatoes) but by the endof the year the index may be not more than one point higher than twelvemonths previously.I.M.Ministry of Labour and national Service, S.W.1.19th December, 1958-Z-

</content>
</cab>
