<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/95/0 images: 350-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(58) 2632?.nd December, 1958COPY NO. \ 1CABINETSCOTTISH AVIATION LIMITEDMemorandum by the Secretary of State for scotland the Prime Minister has invited me to report to the cabinet or. the affairs of Scottish Aviation Limited.2.      Scottish Aviation Limited manufacture at Prestwick Airportthe Twin Pioneer, a short-range light passenger/freight  aircraft,particularly adapted for operation from short landing strips inundeveloped country.   About sixty Twin Pioneers have so far beencompleted or ordered, including thirty-six for the Royal Air Force,and the Company are reasonably optimistic about obtaining further orders, particularly from overseas.   The Company employs some,950 men at Prestwick, having dismissed some 400 men during thelast three months.3.      The Finance Corporation for Industry (F.C.I.) have lent ScottishAviation a total of about  3-f millions, and have made various effortsduring the past year to persuade one or other of the larger aircraftcompanies to take them into partnership: as a result there is apossibility of a merger with the English Electric Company, but theycannot be expected to reach a decision on this for a month or two.   Inthe meantime F.C.I. decided at the end of November that they could make no further advances to the Company, which will accordingly have nomoney with which to pay wages after the first week in January.   If theycould be enabled to survive until February payments will accrue fromthe Ministry of Supply and from commercial sources which would keep them going until the end of March, by which time a decision should bereached on the question of merger and further overseas orders mayhave been obtained.   The immediate problem is therefore to find about 100,000 in order to keep the Company in production through Januarywhile the possibilities of a merger can be further explored.4.      Unemployment in the Prestwick area at mid-November was1,255 or 3. 2 per cent, and the prospects of absorbing a large numberof men into other local employment if Scottish Aviation closed down arepoor.   About 100 of the men already discharged have been offeredemployment at St. Albans by Handley Page, but such a transfer of skilled men from Scotland to the South arouses fierce political criticism.The general anxiety about unemployment in Scotland is of course acuteand the closing down of the only firm in Scotland making air frames would produce a first class row.   On the other hand the Ministry of Supply-1-CONFIDENTIAL
feel that Government financial assistance to maintain Scottish AviationLimited as an isolated unit would not accord with present policy for theaircraft industry, which seeks to encourage the industry to concentrateinto stronger groups.   The Company themselves fully appreciate thatin the longer term they cannot survive unless they amalgamate with alarger undertaking.5.      Scottish Aviation claim that they have lost over  600,000 as aresult of a miscalculation in the cost of production of the military aircraft so far delivered.   The Ministry of Supply point out, however,that, while there mvght be a case for making an ex gratia  paymentif this claim were substantiated, an investigation of the Companyfsaccount would first be essential, and this would take at least nine months to complete.   No early or certain assistance can therefore be looked for from this source.6.      Since employment at Prestwick has not been sufficiently severetc b:.*ing it ivxo the list of places eligible for assistance under iheDistribution of Industry Acts, and threatened unemployment cannot betak-rs into the reckoning for this purpose, Scottish Aviation would notq&quot;.?.iify for assistance from the Development Areas (Treasury Advisory)Committee even if the Committee could be satisfied about their prospects of viability.7.     As a result of discussion, the Chancellor of the Exchequer has agreed that the Ministry of Supply should be authorised exceptionally tomake a special payment to the Company of  50,000 in respect of thefour aircraft which are at present being constructed for the Royal AirForce, on condition that F.C.I. provide a similar sum.   I have put this solution to Lord Weeks, the Chairman of F.C.I., and hope to have hisanswer before Cabinet meets.   If these arrangements are made, theCompany should be enabled to bridge the gap until they receive thefuicher payments due to them in February, and this will give vital timefor pursuing the possibilities of merger and of obtaining further orders from overseas.J.M.Scottish Office, S.W.1.22nd December, 1958-2-C CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
