<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/1/41 images: 550-561</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITaKT.10 MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)TO BE KEPT UNDcp iC%AND KEY,i cJJLloit is requestensurieciai care may be takon toicy of this document.COPY NO,WAR CABINETcARRANGEMENTS FOR THE VISIT OF DOMINION MINISTERSiNote &quot;by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I circulate herewith., for the consideration of the WarCabinet, a Memorandum dealing with the arrangements proposed for the forthcoming visit of Dominion Ministers to London.A, ft.Richmond Terrace, S0W0lo.18th October,  19390&apos;MEMORANDUM.A meeting was held on 13th October, 1939, at whichrepresentatives of Departments principally concerned werepresent, to discuss the arrangements for the forthcoming visit of Ministers from Canada, Australia, New Zealand andSouth Africa^      The recommendations of the Meeting are contained in the following paragraphsaObject of the Ministers   Visits0So The main object of the visits cf Ministers from theDominions was set one in paragraph 7 of the Report of a ministerial Committee., under the Chairmanship cf Lord Hankey(W.P.(G)(39) 10),  in the following termss-&quot;.o. o  It is probable that owing to the difficulty ofjudging events at so great a distance, the Governments and peoples of some cf -c,:e Dominions have not been able fully to realise the nature of the struggle on which we haveembarked, the magnitude cf our own effort, and the vitalneed for them to exert- their full war effort if the outcomeis to be successful^      We think that a more realappreciation of the problems confronting the Empire would beobtained if a Minister of State from each of the Dominionscould be spared to visit this country at once.      The    essence of any such arrangement would be that a Minister in the full confidence of his Government would be able to see for himself and report personally to his colleagues on the vast effortthat we ourselves are making? and would be in a position to convey to his own Government a clear picture of the best meanswhich they could employ to assist., &quot;3. While there is no intention of converting these visitsof Dominion Ministers into a formal Conference, every advantage will of course be taken of the presence here of

these Dominion representatives to arrange a certain number of joint meetings on matters of common interest during the 10days or fortnight from 30th October when it is anticipated that most, if not all. of the Delegations will be in this country,,Programme of Ministers&apos; Visitso40 Details of the times of arrival and composition31 ofthe Dominion Delegations are not yet available and it istherefore not yet possible to draw up a programme to cover thewhole period during which the Delegations are expected to bein this country,.      Furthermore, the individual views of theMinisters, when they arrive, must of course be consideredbefore the arrangements made for them are finally settled.It is proposed, therefore.- that the Secretariat ( see paragraph) should get in touch with each of the Dominion Delegationsas soon as possible after arrival, and arrange its programme.The Secretariat will be responsible for dove-tailing thearrangements of the various Ministers to avoid clashing,,      Assoon as the dates and times of the joint meetings have been fixed, the Secretariat will notify all concerned,,Departments should also get in touch as early as possible withany Dominion technical advisers with whom they will be dealingduring the visitoMatters for discussion - joint meetings.5. Having regard to the main object, for the which the visits to this country of Dominion Ministers have beenarranged ( see paragraph 2 above),  it is proposed that thefollowing subjects should be discussed at joint meetings:-Sub jectcJoint meeting to be attended&quot; by: -Foreign Policy and GeneralSituation,Two or three membersWar Cabinetoof theGeneral Strategic PositNature of War Effortrequired and ProbableTheatres of WarQDominion OverseasProgrammesoFinancial Policy,Civil Defence.    (Forinformation of dominion ministers only)0It is suggested that the meetings would best carry outthe intention of the visit if they were so arranged as to start by dealing with the general issues which form the background to our war effort, and dealt later with the particular problems with which the Dominion Ministers will be directly concerned.ion,Ministers (according tosubject) and Chiefs of Staff,Chancellor of the Exchequer.Minister of Home Security,HSee Appendix A for provisional list0

Separate Meetings,,60 In addition, discussions will no doubt be necessary on other questions? such as trade, shipping, food supplies, andeconomic warfare, as well as on matters of detail within theprovince of each Service Department      As, however, these discussions will be concerned with particular aspects of problems affecting individual Dominions, it will no doubt be convenient that as a rule they should take place at separate and not at joint meetings, and should be held in theDepartments concerned,  either on the Ministerial plane or onthe level of technical advisers, depending upon the composition of the Dominion Delegation concerned,,General Procedure for Joint Meetinggo7. Owing to the heavy demands on the time of the UnitedKingdom Ministers,  the arranging of meetings will present somedifficulty0      With regard to the joint meetings with some members of the War Cabinet, it is suggested for consideration that these might conveniently take place at the conclusion of normal meetings of the War Cabinet      For example on one ortwo occasions the War Cabinet meeting might begin at 11 army,and   a   meeting   with Dominion Ministers at mid-day0      It may also be found desirable to hold a final meeting of farewellat which the same procedure might be adopted-      Othermeetings would as a rule have to be held in the afternoon orevening, unless it proves possible to fit into the morningcertain individual discussions in Departments with ministers who do not attend the War cabinet secretariat andI ssue,.0f, Panpers080 The secretarial work connected with the visits ofDominion Ministers will be centralised in the War cabinet secretariat, -go which a Joint Secretary from the dominions office will be attached,.     All Papers will be issued from theWar Cabinet Offices,      It is hoped to keep a record of all important discussions that take place, and for this purposea,member of the Secretariat will attend all joint meetings,and also, wherever possible, the more important discussionsheld with individual Ministers in Departments;:      In the caseof meetings with individual Ministers, at which a member ofthe Secretariat is unable to be present, and in the case of discussions held between technical advisers and departmentalofficials, a short note of the proceedings, including, inparticular, a record of any decisions arrived at,  orundertakings given by either side, should be forwarded to the secretariat as soon as possible by the Departments concerned,9. In order that the Dominion Ministers may be brought upto date on political and strategical matters, an arrangement will be made whereby they will be given access to a selection of recent secret Papers at the &apos;7ar Cabinet office      Thisarrangement will avoid the danger of these secret documentspassing out of official safe custody0

10.       The gist of certain recent strategical papers hasalready been conveyed to Dominion Governments,.      In addition,as a basis for discussion with Dominion Ministers;  the Chiefsof Staff are preparing a short strategical paper dealing withthe reasons for anticipating a long war and the consequentneed for the maximum war effort on the part of the BritishCommonwealth.     A review-of the possible theatres of war willbe included in this paper,,      Except in the case of anystrategical papers of this nature, it will of course be theresponsibility of the Departments concerned to prepare for united Kingdom Ministers attending joint meetings any briefsthat may be thought necessary or desirable,,11.        Short Minutes summarising the discussions at jointmeetings will be circulated,Visits of Inspection,,12.        One of the main objects of the visits by dominion ministers will be attained if they are taken on visits of inspection to certain forms of war activity;    for example,the Central War Room, the Headquarters of the Air Defence ofGreat Britain,  a Plying   Training School,  and a munitionsfactory.      In addition,  they might be afforded an opportunityof seeing the work of the three Services in this country.13o        The arrangements for such visits will be made by departments concerned, programmes and time tables beingco-ordinated by the Secretariate      As far as possible, suchvisits of inspection will be arranged for a party which each dominion Minister and his staff will be free to join.Arrangements for the Indian Delegate014.        The Secretary of State for India is of the opinion thatthe Indian Delegate, Sir Muhammed Zafrullah Khan, a member ofthe Governor-General/s Executive Council, should attend thejoint meetings when political and strategical questions arebeing discussed,.      He has pointed out that, apart from anyother considerations, the absence of the Indian Delegate fromthe   more important meetings would presumably become known, andthis might have embarrassing effects from the political pointof view in Indiacchmond Terrance, S.W.I. ,18th October,  19 390

APPENDIX A.COMPOSITION OF DELEGATIONS FROM THEDOMINIONS AND TNDIA.CANADA.Hon. T.A. Crerar0 Minister of Mines and Resources,(Composition of delegation not yet known.)AUSTRALIA.Rt. hon RoGo  Casey0 D.S0O00 M.C. ,    Minister for Supply.Major General J. Northcott9       Deputy Chief of theM.V.O. General Staff.Group Captain W.D. Bostock.       Assistant- Chief ofthe Air Staff.Mr. N.K.S. Brodribb2 O.B.E.        Controller-Generalof Munitions Supply,A private Secretary.NEW ZEALAND.Hon. Peter Eraser,, M.P.    Deputy Prime Minister.Mr.  CAo Berendsens C.M.G. s      Permanent Head of prime Minister&apos;s Department.Lto-Colonel W.G. Stevens. Secretary, Organisationof National Security.A private Secretary.SOUTH AFRICA.Colonel the Hon. D. ReitZo    Minister for Native Affairs.A private Secretary.INDIA.Sir Muhammad Zafrullah k&apos;han 3 K. C. S. I.




</content>
</cab>
