<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 9-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)C. (60) 153 COPY NO.    \ f21st October, I960CABINETNATIONAL HEALTH SERVICE CONTRIBUTIONMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer in the light of our recent discussions (C. C.(60) 54th Conclusions,Minute 6), I put before my colleagues three different ways of approach tothe proposal to increase the Health Service contribution.Course I2.      First, there is my proposal substantially as it is, in C.(60) 148.Legislation would be enacted before Christmas, or at least by the end ofJanuary, to increase the contribution by Is. from the beginning of April.I am ready to accept that this increase should not be enacted in the samelegislation as the national insurance benefit increase;  it should be introduced as late as possible after the National Insurance Bill - perhaps at the end ofNovember or early in December.    To this extent it would be possible topresent the two operations as being separate.    I think, however, that thetwo proposals would have to be announced at the same time;  either in the debate on the Address or in the Second Reading of the National insurance bill;  to refer to the increase in contribution required for the benefitincrease, without at the same time referring to the proposal to increasethe health contribution, would lay us open to severe criticism.Course II3.      Or we might postpone the increase in the health contribution forthree months.    Thus, we might announce the shilling increase in the context of the general level of Government expenditure, at the same time that we publish the Vote on Account (the first occasion onwhich totalGovernment expenditure for 1961-62 is made public).     This would be asimilar timetable to that which was adopted for the 19 58 HealthContribution Bill - Ways and Means Resolution in the second half ofFebruary and enacted in time for administrative arrangements to be madefor the increase to be effective at the beginning of July.4.      The advantage of this course would be that we should relate theincrease to total Government expenditure at the time when this was havingthe greatest public impact;   we should be divorcing it from the insurance benefit changes and 30 reducing the chance of an accusation of bad faith;and we should not be prejudicing the Minister of Health in his policies toreduce Health Service expenditure.
5.     The disadvantages of this course are that I should lose three months&apos;revenue -  12 millions - in the first year.    Administratively, there mightbe an inconvenience for employers, and some small cost to the Exchequer,arising from a change in the value of the stamp three months after theprevious change.    In 1958, however, the stamp was changed twice infairly quick succession, the end of January for a rise in insurance benefits,and the beginning of July for a rise in Health Service contribution.Course III6.     A third suggestion was tentatively put forward by the Minister of aviation that there should be a sort of package to be announced in February:-(a) Concede Health Service drugs to private patients subject to arrangements being worked out so as to prevent abuse;  a figure of  2^- millions has been estimated for this;   Ibelieve it is on the low side, and I would prefer to assumenot less than  4 millions.(b) Abolish the prescription charge.     This now yields 12^; millions, offset by refunds to people on national assistance and war pensioners ( 2 millions).The immediate loss of revenue would therefore be of theorder of  10^: millions.    That is the minimum figure of loss;   the abolition of the charge may weaken the sense of discipline which the charge has imposed, directly in thecase of the patient, and indirectly for the doctor by seemingto imply that the Government are less interested in economy.Once the charge was abolished it would be extremelydifficult to reimpose it;   so we might be forgoing, by thisact, a useful source of revenue.    As it is, if the cost of drugs goes up, it is possible to raise the prescriptioncharge to Is. 6d. or 2s.(c) These two proposals show an immediate financial loss to theExchequer of some  12- 15 millions a year.    To offsetthis, and to maintain the extra yield which I need from the health Service contribution, I would have to require that the contribution be increased by Is. 4d. altogether, splitIs. Id. from the employee and 3d. from the employer.    Thetotal extra yield would be about  65 millions, and theproposal would add 3d. to the maximum employee contribu-tion set out in the paper by the Minister of Pensions(C.(60) 151).7. The case for this &quot;package&quot; proposal is that, while maintaining the net yield increase of  50 millions to help my long-term budgetaryproblem, we should be abolishing the unpopular prescription charge;and we should be fulfilling our pledge to private patients in a way which,by coupling it with the abolition of the prescription charge, would gain us the least political criticism.-2-
C !Z f I Vs- IB &quot;if. The case against Course III is that a move to make drugs freefor all, and especially to do so at this stage for the benefit of private patients, is incompatible with the Governments drive for better prescribingand for economy in this sector of public expenditure.    As recently asJuly, 1959, the Government, announcing that it regarded with favour theHinchcliffe Committee recommendation of a voluntary scheme for limiting -for a trial period of two years - the amount of drugs supplied on oneprescription, stated that the prescription charge would be reviewed in the context of the results of the scheme, the finances of the national health Service, etc. (Hansard, 15th July, 1959, Column 440).    To announce the abolition of the prescription charge so early as next February, whenthe voluntary scheme has been on trial for only half of the two-year period and before the cost of prescribing had shown any reduction, would meritcriticism of the Governments lack of grip on the situation.9. There are also the other objections put forward in our previousdiscus sion.10. I understand that the Minister of Health is opposed to thisproposal.11. As for the effective date of this &quot;package&quot;, assuming we wereto adopt it for announcement in February, it should not take any longer to enact than Course II, and I would hope that the increased contribution would be payable from the beginning of July.S. Li.Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1.20th October, I960.-3-

</content>
</cab>
