<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 16-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October I960The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of............................................................TOP SECRET Copy No. 5 6C. (60) 15524th October, I960CABINETTHE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECHES ON THE PROROGATION AND OPENINGOF parliament note by the Secretary of the CabinetI circulate for the information of the Cabinet copies of The Queen&apos;s speeches on the Prorogation and Opening of Parliament in the form approved by The Queen.The final wording of paragraphs 16 and 19 of the Opening Speech remains to besettled.(Signed)      NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,21st October, 1960.

SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OF parliament my Lords and Members of the House of commons I. I am deeply grateful for the many expressions of good will which came to me on the birth of My second Son, Prince Andrew. This year has also broughtme the great happiness of My Sister&apos;s marriage.2. In the course of the year the friendships existing between My People inthis country and peoples overseas have been reinforced by a number of visits.3. In April I had the special pleasure of welcoming to London the Presidentof the French Republic and Madame de Gaulle. I have been happy to greet heretheir Majesties the King and Queen of Thailand and, ten days ago, the king and Queen of Nepal.4. I was glad that the President of Peru was able to meet members of MyFamily when he came here in February and that I was myself able to receive thePresident of the Argentine Republic.5. I was moved by the warmth and sincerity of the reception accorded toMy Husband when he visited New York in June to open the British Exhibition.6. My Mother has visited the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland to open the great Kariba Dam. Both she and I were deeply affected by theenthusiastic welcome which she received throughout her journeys in theFederation.7. The visits of members of My Family to the Caribbean were a vividreminder to all My Peoples in that area of their links with the Crown and with my People in the United Kingdom.8. My Government have supported the work of the United Nations andits agencies and are taking their full share in the work of the General Assembly.My Government have continued to play their full part in the North atlantic alliance and other regional pacts.9. They have continued to take part in the Geneva Conference on the discontinuance of Nuclear Weapons Tests, in which progress has been made towards agreement on the prohibition of tests under effective international control.They played a notable role in the Ten-Nation Committee on Disarmament atGeneva and supported the resolution of the United Nations recommending theearliest possible resumption of international negotiations for disarmament.10. Meanwhile My Armed Forces have continued to contribute to peace and order throughout the world.II. By the signing of the Antarctic Treaty last December, the twelvegovernments concerned, which include My own and those of the United Statesand the Soviet Union, have agreed to co-operate in the peaceful use of theContinent in the interests of science.12. I was most happy to meet, in May, the Prime Ministers and other representatives of Commonwealth countries. Their meeting revealed a wide measure of agreement on international problems, notably on the need to lessenworld tensions and to promote the economic and cultural progress of the less-developed countries.   &apos;13. I have given My Assent to an Act which established the independentRepublic of Cyprus. Certain Sovereign Base Areas and other military facilities in the island are retained for the United Kingdom and My Government look forward to a long friendship with the new Republic.14. Two other countries for which My Government in the United kingdom have hitherto been responsible have achieved independence. In June I withdrewMy protection from the Somaliland Protectorate, confident that the long tradition of friendship between the British and Somali peoples will continue and flourish.. TOP..SECRET57861
2TOP SECRET15. This month Nigeria became the eleventh Member of the Commonwealth.I have shared in the joy with which that great country then received My Cousin,the Princess Alexandra. My Husband and I have very happy memories of our ownvisit to Nigeria five years ago and we, together with My Government and all my People in the United Kingdom, extend to My People there our warmest good wishes for the future.16. I have given My Assent to an Act which reflects the decision of theGovernment of Ghana to adopt a Republican Constitution.17. My Government in the United Kingdom have continued to give financial help to the less-developed countries, and in particular to Commonwealth countries,including loans and grants for development, welfare and reconstruction.18. Acts have been passed enabling the United Kingdom to take part inthe Commonwealth Scholarship and Fellowship Plan and making possible a freermovement of students and teachers between this country and the rest of theCommonwealth.19. The Commonwealth Economic Consultative Council, which met inLondon in September, agreed to initiate a Special Commonwealth AfricanAssistance Plan in order to give further help in raising the standards of life in less-developed Commonwealth countries in Africa.20. My Government have published their plan for My Overseas Civil Service,providing greater security for its members and making it easier for territories which achieve self-government to retain them in their employment.Members of the House of Commons21. I thank you for the provision which you have made for the public services.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons22. As part of their policy to assist the development of overseas countries,My Government have joined the new International Development Association andare contributing substantially to its resources.23. They have ratified the Convention establishing the European Free trade association, and have taken part in negotiations for remodelling the organisation for European Economic Co-operation with the United States and Canada asfull members.24. Support for home agriculture and for the fishing industry has been maintained. My Government have introduced improvement grants forhorticultural producers and their co-operative marketing associations. Theyhave brought to a successful conclusion the long campaign for the eradicationof tuberculosis in cattle in this country.25. An Act has been passed to help to provide additional opportunities for employment in those areas where high and persistent unemployment existsor is threatened.26. My Government have announced a substantial increase in the road programme. An Act has been passed to facilitate enforcement of the law on road traffic and to amend the law on parking and traffic regulation.27. An Act has been passed to improve the arrangements for licensing air services and to ensure that all airline operators maintain high standards of safety.28. Effect has been given to the main recommendations of the RoyalCommission on Betting, Lotteries and Gaming, by legislation providing for the registration of bookmakers, permitting the establishment of licensed bettingoffices, and replacing the outmoded law on gaming by provisions more acceptable to modern opinion.29. An Act has been passed which will give added protection to those whoinvest their savings in building societies.
30. An Act has been passed to control the location and conditions ofcaravan sites and to strengthen the procedure for enforcing planning control inEngland and Wales.31. In Scotland the law on mental health has been modernised and newprovision made for the care of those who are sick in mind.32. Measures have been taken to make legal aid and advice more widelyavailable. The right of appeal to the House of Lords in criminal cases has been extended and the law relating to contempt of court has been amended.33. The law relating to charities in England and Wales has been consolidatedand reformed, to enable the best use to be made of charitable resources for thebenefit of the community.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons34.   I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.

SPEECH.ON THE OPENING OF parliament my Lords and Members of the House of commons I. My Husband and I look forward eagerly to the series of visits we shall make next year in the Commonwealth, where we shall renew and extend thefriendships which we value so very highly.2. In the early part of the year we shall visit India and Pakistan, on the invitation of the Presidents of those countries; and I welcome especially this opportunity of seeing for the first time something of these two great nations of theCommonwealth.3. No less a pleasure is the prospect of our journey to Africa, where, later in the year, we shall visit the Republic of Ghana, Sierra Leone and the Gambia.We shall be happy to visit also the Republic of Liberia.4. . My Husband and I look forward with lively satisfaction to renewing ourfriendships with His Majesty the King of Nepal, His Imperial Majesty theShahinshah and the President of the Italian Republic when we visit their countriesnext year.5. Throughout the coming session, My Government will continue to giveresolute support to the work of the United Nations. The improvement of relationsbetween East and West remains a primary object of their policy. In particular,they will go on working for the success of the Geneva Conference on the discontinuance of Nuclear Weapons Tests and will do their utmost to achievecomprehensive disarmament under effective international control.6. My Government will play their full part in maintaining the North atlantic alliance and the other regional pacts to which they belong. My Armed forces will continue to make their contribution to the safeguarding of world peace.7. The friendship which links us to our great ally, the United States ofAmerica, is a powerful element in the defence of peace.8. My Government will convene a conference to review the Constitution ofthe Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland in accordance with the provisions ofthat Constitution.9. A Bill will be brought before you to enable Sierra Leone to achieve itsindependence within the Commonwealth.10. My Government hope that in Malta self-government can be restored onfirm foundations and that, with the co-operation of a Maltese Government, their efforts to expand the island&apos;s economy will be successful.Members of the House of Commons *II. Estimates for the public services will be laid before you in due course.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons12. My Government will seek to maintain a sound economy and to ensure awell-balanced growth of production in conditions.of high and stable employment.Their aim will be to preserve stability of the general level of prices and to further the expansion of overseas trade and strengthen the balance of payments.13. They have entered into negotiations under the General agreement on Tariffs and Trade, which they hope will result in a significant reductionin.trade barriers. They will continue to co-operate with their partners inconsolidating the European Free Trade Association. At the same time theywill work towards the political and economic unity of Western Europe, on a basissatisfactory to all the Governments concerned.57863
2TOP SECRET14. My Government will introduce legislation to enable the United Kingdom,in common with others of our friends, to help the Governments of India and pakistan to finance the construction of important works in the Indus River Basin.15. At home My Ministers are resolved to maintain a stable, efficient andprosperous agriculture. They will introduce legislation to reorganise and improveCovent Garden Market and to amend the law relating to land drainage in Englandand Wales.16. They will continue to support and encourage our fishing industry [and to seek a solution of the delicate problems of fishery limits, especially with thosecountries off whose coasts generations of our fishermen have won their livelihood].17. My Government will follow out their policy of advancing the social welfare of My People. War pensions will be increased and authority will be sought for increases in retirement pensions and other benefits, and in contributions, underthe National Insurance schemes.18. My Governments concern for young people will be shown by thecontinued expansion of schools and colleges and by greatly increased efforts to train and recruit more teachers. They will continue to encourage the expansionof the Youth Service and will authorise an increasing level of expenditure on the physical recreation of the young. Awards for students at universities and for thosetaking comparable courses at other institutions of higher education will be grantedon an improved basis.19. A high rate of house-building will be maintained, and the slum clearancedrive will continue. [A Bill will be introduced to amend the law relating to therespective responsibility for repairs as between landlords and tenants on short-termtenancies.] My Ministers will put forward proposals to amend the law of ratingand valuation and to facilitate the 1963 revaluation.20. My Government will endeavour to improve the protection of thecommunity against crime. The strength, efficiency and well-being of the policewill be their continuing concern; and they will seek to make more effective thevarious methods of penal treatment. They will introduce a Bill to provide, inEngland and Wales, better means of dealing with young offenders; to extendcompulsory aftercare to prisoners and so to discourage them from reverting tocrime; and to improve the management of approved schools. Proposals for legislation in the same field in Scotland will be laid before you.21. Legislation will be introduced to provide for a levy on horse-racing and,in England and Wales, to check abuses by registered clubs and to reform the licensing laws.22. Authority will be sought for an increase in the number of judges in theSupreme Court.23. My Government will persevere with measures to promote economic growth in the Highlands and Islands and to develop modern standards of livingthere; and they will put forward legislation to amend the Crofters (Scotland) Act.24.   A Bill will be introduced to extend the investment powers of trustees.25. Legislation will be laid before you to amend the Weights and MeasuresActs.  *26. Legislation is being prepared to provide financial assistance towards theconstruction of a new Atlantic liner to replace the Queen Mary.27. My Government will submit to you proposals for reforming the structure and functions of the British Transport Commission.28. They are preparing legislation designed to promote greater safety on theroads.29.   Other measures will be laid before you in due course.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons30.  I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon your counsels.


</content>
</cab>
