<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 32-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   November I960C. (60) 1581st November, 1960CABINETUNOFFICIAL SEAMEN&apos;S strike memorandum by the Minister of transport the seamen&apos;s strike has attracted attention to labour arrangements in the(shipping industry and given rise to demands for reorganisation of the NationalUnion of Seamen and revision of disciplinary provisions in the Merchant ShippingActs.2. Excluding Asiatic and African seamen engaged abroad, there are some140,000 active seafarers serving in British ships sailing from the United Kingdom.Of these some 50,000 are officers and some 90,000 ratings. Of these 90,000 ratingsnot more than about 3,000 have been on strike. Most of these are young men,though there has been a hard core of older men particularly on the north-east coast.3. Any changes in the organisation of the Union are, of course, a matter forits members. However, we should recognise its achievements in improvingconditions of service for the men. The success of the post-war &quot; establishedservice scheme&quot;, which has removed the casual basis of employment which obtained before the war, institution of regular paid leave, improvements in crewaccommodation and living conditions on board ship and the rise in basic monthlywages from  9 for an able-bodied seaman in 1937 to  20 in 1947 and  36 to-dayare all matters to which the Union have made an effective contribution. Actualhours worked on board ship are often long, but there has been a progressive reduction in the basic working week from 64 hours to 56, 48 and now 44. Theagreements recently concluded between the Union, the officers&apos; organisations and the shipowners are a good settlement from the seafarers&apos; point of view andhave been secured at a time when shipping is suffering a severe depression.4. For many years past, the Union have been moderate and responsible,conscious of a duty to adhere to the terms of their agreements and their constitution. There has been no official strike of seamen since 1911 (the Uniondeclined to join in the general strike in 1926 because they could not do so withouta ballot of their members) and since the war and until this year there have been only two small-scale unofficial strikes. But I believe it would be a profound mistake to regard this record as indicating undue subservience to either the shipownersor the officers&apos; organisations.5. The strikers&apos; leaders quite clearly feel that the Union does not move fastenough. It is difficult to assess the extent of this feeling among Union members.Only a small percentage of ratings have been on strike and some of these are reported to have been intimidated. One major, if not the main, cause has beenthe influence of the extremist Canadian union on the crews of ships whichtrade there.6. In my view, criticisms that the Union&apos;s constitution is undemocratic or that Union officials are out of touch with the men are unfounded. elected members from the branches, at least half of whom must be serving seamen andnot Union officials, constitute a majority of the executive council, which is the negotiating body, and of the delegates to the annual conference. There is a livelyCopy No.    g g57984THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
magazine and there are opportunities for seamen to see Union officials whenever they sign on and off ships and between voyages. They are, however, naturallydisinclined to attend meetings when they, come off their ships instead of goinghome to their families. With a high proportion of the members always abroadthere is little opportunity to organise mass meetings which are fully representative.7. There is now a demand that ships&apos; crews should be enabled to electrepresentatives or &quot; shop stewards &quot; who would negotiate on disputes arising onboard ship. Apart from industrial arguments, this raises an issue of authority and safety on board ship in which Her Majesty&apos;s Government have an interest. Anyproposal which might undermine the authority of the Master and officers mustbe viewed with concern and would need to be looked at carefully to ensure proper safeguards.8. The demands for revision of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, relateparticularly to Sections 221, 225 and 236 of the Act, which create penalties of finesor imprisonment for offences such as desertion, disobeying lawful commands andthe like. These provisions were framed largely in the interests of safety, whichwould be seriously prejudiced if discipline could not be fully maintained. this applies to ships in port as well as at sea. Similar provisions, of course, apply alsoin fishing vessels.9. These disciplinary penalties under the Merchant Shipping Acts do not, assuch, prohibit strikes. A seaman signs articles of agreement which place him under the authority of the Master subject to safeguards against abuse. while he is so engaged he cannot withdraw his labour without exposing himself to thesepenalties. But the agreements are terminable, either when the ship finishes hervoyage in the United Kingdom, or, in the case of running agreements (which are used in the North Atlantic passenger services and in the coasting trades), on giving a notice usually of 24 or 48 hours as provided for in the agreement. The Act thusonly limits the right to strike without notice and in breach of an agreement, andthis is not unreasonable in the particular circumstances of seafaring employment.The position is the same in ships of Commonwealth and foreign countries, andin some cases the penalties are more severe than ours.10. The Union have already had the Merchant Shipping Acts under review for some time past and have produced a report which, I understand, among other things proposes changes in the disciplinary sections. The shipowners and theofficers&apos; organisations have agreed to examine it to see whether agreed proposalscan be submitted to me. In this connexion both the shipowners and the officers&apos;organisations have emphasised the importance of disciplinary provisions on board ship.11. There have already been demands since Parliament reassembled for some government action to revise the Merchant Shipping Acts, and I agree that theyshould be reviewed. But as a result of many years of experience it is clear thatproblems of this kind, which involve industrial relations in the shipping industry,are better discussed in the first instance within the industry itself. The shipownershave indicated their willingness to discuss the National Union of Seamen&apos;s proposals on the National Maritime Board. This has the advantage that the officers&apos;organisations, which are also very much concerned, will take part in the discussions.I am assured by both the shipowners and the unions that there will be no delay in their examination of the problem which they have already begun. For mypart I am examining the relevant provisions of the Merchant Shipping Acts andalso the implications of Section 16 of the Conspiracy and Protection of PropertyAct, 1875, which expressly excludes seamen from the benefits of that Act. I shall then be in a position to consider whatever proposals originate from the discussions on the National Maritime Board. It is in my view well worth waiting to see howfar agreement can be reached in this way before the Government commits itselfto specific proposals.E. M.Ministry of Transport, W. 1,31st October, 1960.

</content>
</cab>
