<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 55-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
printed for the Cabinet. November I960The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of............................................................TOP SECRET Copy No.C. (60) 16821st November, i960CABINETTHE ECONOMIC situation memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer submit for.my colleagues&apos;consideration some reflections on current economic affairs.2. The international situation is more hazardous than it has ibee-n &quot;for someyears. The situation Shown in the United Kingdom is both uncomfortable andbaffling.The International situation. The United States and Canada have moved into a recession. This isdamaging to ojs as regards our own exports and as affecting general expansion of world trade.4. It is difficult to predict what will happen in Canada. So far as the UnitedStates is concerned, the recession is unlikely to be deep or prolonged. It may lastuntil the middle of next year. I doubt more pessimistic forecasts because the newPresident has been laying great stress on the need for expansion.5. In Europe, expansion seems likely to continue, although more slowly thanin recent years.6. Primary product prices remain low. The effect of this will be to keep downour exports to primary producing countries.7. The most disturbing feature of the international scene is the imbalancebetween certain European countries notably Germany on the one hand andthe United States and the United Kingdom on the other. This situation would be considerably eased (c) if the Germans revalued the Deutschemark or (b) if their prices rose, and -(c) if they took over more of the load of international lending and defence. At present there is some speculation against the dollar while the germans are experiencing strong inflationary conditions. The Germans are said to bepreparing to do something under (c), so far as foreign aid is concerned.8. This situation is inherently unstable. Various strains and stresses will show themselves in the next twelve months, of which the recent rise in the price of goldis the forerunner. We have been in touch with the United States authorities onthe question of gold and have agreed to keep in close contact with them. It is inmy view essential that we should do so and that we should all be ready to act in away which will minimise the damage to the economies of the West. We cannot sayexactly how the strains will show themselves.The Situation in the United Kingdom9. The United Kingdom is not earning nearly enough to meet its international commitments, but the reserves are benefiting&apos; from high interest rates and from the weakness of the dollar.58068
10. The expansion in economic activity here which we set in motion in 1958had reached a danger point early this year. In other words, the pressure of home demand was excessive. Our balance of payments was seriously threatened and it seemed likely that increasing demand for labour would again push up wages and prices.11. A series of measures of restraint was therefore adopted. Expansion hasnow been checked. I am afraid, however, that the reduction in exports has had as much to do with the checking of expansion as the measures of restraint put intooperation. The uncomfortable features in our situation are as follows:(a) Pressure on resourcesThe index of industrial production has been virtually steady at 121(average 1954 was 100), since last April. During this period unemployment has fallen after seasonal corrections from 377,000 to 334,000. Unfilledvacancies have risen from 297,000 to 332,000. Total employment has risen from 23,464,000 to 23,728,000. In view of the level of investment during recent years it is disappointing that production has been checked but so farthere has not been much checking of the pressure on the labour market.There has no doubt been some re-deployment of labour but the tendency ofemployers to hold on to their labour and use it less economically, socharacteristic of the period 1956 to early 1958, seems to have reappeared.(b) Wages and prices the index of retail prices, which has been practically stable since early1958, is likely to begin to rise very soon. This is partly because of seasonalchanges and partly-because our costs have been rising. The Minister of Labourrecently circulated to the Economic Policy Committee an appreciation of theoutlook for wage negotiations. It appears that new demands for higher wagesor shorter hours or both are following in rather less than a year on previoussettlements (in contrast to the last round, which took nearly 18 months tocomplete). In view of the high pressure of demand for labour over most ofthe. country, I think we must count on an increase in the index of hourly wage rates of about 6 per cent, between the second half of 1960 and the second halfof 1961, with a roughly similar increase in average earnings. This is certainlyin excess of the upward trend in productivity, and I think that we shall befortunate if we can hold the Retail Price Index to an increase of less than about three points in the next twelve months, most of it being likely for seasonalreasons to appear between now and the spring.(c) The Balance of payments the regular forecast of balance of payments prospects is now being completed. Since the beginning of this year imports have gone on increasingwhile exports have fallen away. Our poor export performance is due partly to the check to exports (especially of cars) to the United States, and to thelower incomes of primarily producing countries. But I think that the high levelof imports, and to some extent our disappointing export performance, are onlyto be expected when our domestic economy is under pressure. The forecastssuggest that we shall have a deficit on visible trade of about  200 millions inthe second half of 1960, and of  70 millions in the first half of 1961 againsta deficit of  63 millions in the second half of 1959, and a deficit of  30 millions in the first half of this year. Our receipts for invisible earnings have been disappointing and the current account prospects as a whole are for an actualdeficit of  160 millions in the second half of 1960 and a bare balance in thefirst half of next year. This is a drastic change for the worse, since it means that we are not even paying our way on current transactions.12. Meanwhile, our investment abroad on Government and private account,which ought to be financed from the surplus on current account (if we had one),is still increasing. On the other hand, there seems to be some substantial inwardinvestment: and at present our high money rates and the distrust in the UnitedStates dollar are causing a marked inward movement of funds, which must beregarded as speculative and transient. The forecast (a very uncertain one) suggeststhat our monetary position the combined result of changes in the reserves and inour sterling liabilities to other countries may deteriorate by  190 millions in thesecond half of this year and by about  100 millions in the first half of next, year.
TOP&quot; SECRET3It is clear to me that we cannot for long continue to borrow short and to lend longat this sort of rate; we are already in a position in which sterling must be extremelyvulnerable to any adverse movements.Government Expenditure13. This continues to go ahead remorselessly. The estimates- will not beready for a few weeks,&apos; but present indications are that they will show supply expenditure for 1961-62 as much as  330 millions above last year&apos;s Budget Estimates(plus the British Transport Commission deficit) an increase of nearly 7 per cent.A substantial further increase is expected in 1962-63.14. As illustrative of this remorseless tendency I would mention I have beenasked during the last few weeks to consider providing money for the following:(a) Students (the Anderson Report)(b) Police pay -(c) Congo(d) Increased cost of scientific research(e) Extra pay for the Civil Service(/) Pensions and National Assistance(g) University building(h) Overseas information15. All this means additional purchasing power, and additional calls on our resources and, therefore, an intensification of our difficulties in managing the economy and paying our way in the world.Some Credit Items16. Not everything is depressing. The level of investment is high and risingand our productive capacity must be rising with it. Secondly, confidence in sterlingis still strong. We have repaid all our debt to the International Monetary Fund,and owing to the increase in its resources agreed on last year (largely because ofprompting by my predecessor), our borrowing rights give us a bigger cushion than before against temporary difficulties. Thirdly, the rise in consumption at homeseems to have been checked. Stocks of material, work in progress and finishedgoods have been rising very quickly this year, and are likely to rise more slowlyor to become steady before very long. This should reduce our import bill and make more goods available for export. The balance, of payments estimates already-mentioned make some allowance for this but the timing of the improvement isdifficult to forecast.17. The employment situation at home is somewhat confused. The Octoberreport by the Ministry of Labour was of labour shortages distributed widelythroughout the country. Despite the difficulties being experienced by the motor,electronic, domestic appliances and furniture industries, the level of labour demandhad been maintained. For instance, in London and the South-East there had been no evidence that the recruitment of labour is becoming easier. In the Midlandsredundancies in the motor industry had not in October reached a level where any real problem of absorption into alternative employment had been experienced.Other industries in the region (including export industries) which had been short of labour had immediately benefited. The combined effects of the pressures onthe banking system, of hire purchase controls, and of the fall in exports in cars, have produced some difficulties in industries making consumer durable goods,particularly in cars and television sets. Nearly all of this has taken place in areasof high employment and I do not think that there is at present much danger ofunemployment rising to embarrassing levels indeed, some redeployment of thelabour force is precisely what we need.Conclusion18.-(a) On the external side we must be prepared for a difficult year. Ourprimary purpose must be to try to secure that world trade is maintained at a high level and the problems of imbalance are dealt with. This will call for close consultation with the new Administration in the United States and continuedpressure on Germany to make an adequate contribution to internationalequilibrium. We shall have to consider how to pursue negotiations with Germanyabout the cost of our troops stationed there.
db) At home, we are up against the old conundrum of how to achieve growthwithout inflation. How can we have growth without so increasing demand that wages, costs and imports all rise too sharply?(c) We shall almost certainly lose the price stability of the last two or threeyears. The cost of living is likely to go up by three points in the next three orfour months.id) There is likely to be a. continued deficit in our balance of payments as awhole.What ought we to do?19. It is clear to me that until the balance of payments position shows signsof distinct improvement, we shall have to continue to impose restraints on demand in the economy. There are difficulties about nearly all the measures which we are having to use. Thus I am doubtful whether changes in Bank Rate have mucheffect at home, although a higher Bank Rate does serve, as experience has shownin recent months, to pull in money from abroad and to protect us from a run onthe reserves. The special deposit scheme has clearly had a greater influence onhelping to restrain bank lending. Control over hire purchase terms is an effectivebut crude measure which can do considerable harm to particular industries. Theextent to which we can affect demand by accelerating or retarding capital investment programmes in the public sector is very limited, as the recent White Paper on investment has shown. I still think that physical restrictions, e.g., quantitativelimitation of imports or the imposition of building licences are open to great political and administrative objections, while a limitation of imports is a dangerousgame for a great trading nation to play.20. This brings me to the question of fiscal measures. I am bound to warnmy colleagues that unless the rate of increase in Government expenditure can bereduced I foresee the risk that we shall need a tough budget next year, especially as I am doubtful whether our overall balance of payments position will have shownmuch improvement by that time. I naturally contemplate this with regret since there is a good deal of evidence to show that the present levels of direct taxationare a disincentive to efficient economic activity.21. So far I have been talking about restraints on the economy. The questionwhich, however, we ought to consider is whether we can think of other ways in whichwe could move forward with confidence without having continuously to applyrestraints. Can we do something to ensure that British industry is more efficient,has greater competitive strength, is more export-minded? Is there any way of ensuring that an increase in economic activity is not at once rendered politicallydangerous by excessive wage demands and a heavy pull of imports?22. I suggest that there are certain specific heads under which we might consider possible action.(a) exports the President of the Board of Trade has already announced certain measures designed to stimulate them. Is any further action by the Governmentpossible?(b) Overseas ExpenditureWhat can be done to cut this down in the defence field or elsewhere?How should we tackle the problem of support costs in Germany?(c) Expenditure at homeWhat can be done about this?(d) ImportsAt present we are trying to reduce these by reducing the pressure of demand at home. Are there any further courses open to us?(e) AgricultureIt has been suggested that the agricultural industry could contribute more to relieving the adverse balance of payments.  Is there anything in this?S. L.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,18th November, 1960.

</content>
</cab>
