<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 153-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December I960C. (60) 191 Copy No.     5616th December, I960CABINETSUBSCRIPTION TELEVISIONMemorandum by the President of the Board of Trade andPostmaster GeneralConsideration to date the Home Affairs Committee discussed this question in May and concluded]that an experiment in subscription television should not be authorised in advanceof the Pilkington Committee&apos;s report.2. Several powerful- groups have staked a claim to participate in subscriptiontelevision if it comes. All the major film and relay firms, have an interest. Specialcompanies have also come into being, the five largest being:Rank/RediffusionBritish Home Entertainment Ltd. (Lord Slim, Lord Brabourne, Earl ofHarewood)British Telemeter Home Viewing (Guardian, Financial Times, British LionFilms)Associated British Picture Corporation Ltd.Associated Television Ltd., in conjunction with British Relay Wireless Ltd.3. The Rank/Rediff conclusion group have developed their own &quot;Choiceview&quot;equipment. They ask to be allowed to start an experiment in Darlington.4.   Considerations For and Against an Early ExperimentForA field trial is necessary to demonstrate:(a) Whether, and to what extent, the public are prepared to pay for subscribertelevision programmes.(b) What the correct basis of charge should be.(c) What type of equipment would be most suitable at the subscriber^ end.(d) Most important, that the British equipment is better than Americanequipment already being demonstrated in Canada, so that we shall notbe left behind in the race for what may prove t&amp; be a. very valuableworld market for equipment.Against(a) Equipment, as such, can be tested through a volunteer panel with existing programmes, or a demonstration can be staged in Canada whereRediffusion have wide interests.(b) Any experiment must at this stage be confined to line, and this would havea hostile reception from those groups interested in a. radio, service-.(c) A limited field trial might well give a false indication of consumer reactionand commercial prospects. (Commercial Television took some twoyears to prove itself financially.)(d) In general, no pattern should be set for a new service in advance of the planning of the broadcasting services of the country as a whole;the general effect on the broadcasting services should first be assessed.
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1960C. (60) 191 Copy No.16th December, 1960CABINET56SUBSCRIPTION TELEVISIONMemorandum by the President of the Board of Trade andPostmaster GeneralConsideration to date the Home Affairs Committee discussed this question in May and concluded]that an experiment in subscription television should not be authorised in advanceof the Pilkington Committee&apos;s report.2. Several powerful- groups have staked a claim to participate in subscriptiontelevision if it comes. All the major film and relay firms, have an interest. Specialcompanies have also come into being, the five largest being:Rank / Rediff usionBritish Home Entertainment Ltd. (Lord Slim, Lord Brabourne, Earl ofHarewood)British Telemeter Home Viewing (Guardian, Financial Times, British LionFilms)Associated British Picture Corporation Ltd.Associated Television Ltd., in conjunction with British Relay Wireless Ltd.3. The Rank/Rediff conclusion group have developed their own &quot;Choiceview&quot;equipment. They ask to be allowed to start an experiment in Darlington.4.   Considerations For and Against an Early ExperimentForA field trial is necessary to demonstrate:(a) Whether, and to what extent, the public are prepared to pay for subscribertelevision programmes.(b) What the correct basis of charge should be.(c) What type of equipment, would be most suitable at the subscriber^ end.(d) Most important, that the British equipment is better than Americanequipment already being demonstrated in Canada, so that we shall notbe left behind in the race for what may prove W be a. very valuableworld market for equipment.Against(a) Equipment, as such, can be tested through a volunteer panel with existing programmes, or a demonstration can be staged in Canada whereRediffusion have wide interests.(b) Any experiment must at this stage be confined to line, and this would havea hostile reception from those groups interested in a. radio service-.(c) A limited field trial might well give a false indication of consumer reactionand commercial prospects. (Commercial Television took some twoyears to prove itself financially.)(d) In general, no pattern should be set for a new service in advance of the planning of the broadcasting services of the country as a whole;the general effect on the broadcasting services should first be assessed.
The Pilkington Committee5. The terms of reference of the Pilkington Committee embrace subscriptiontelevision whether by line or by radio.6. If an experiment were to be authorised we should need to make it clear thatthis did not imply acceptance of subscription television as a future television service.We should now need to convince the Pilkington Committee, as well as parliament and the country that:(a) Approval of an experiment would in no way fetter the freedom of theCommittee to make any recommendations within its terms of reference.(b) If an experiment were successful, it would not prejudice the Government^consideration of the Committee&apos;s recommendations and would notnecessarily mean the Government would favour a subscription service in preference to alternatives and probably untried types of television programmes and vice versa.It would take at least nine months to mount an experiment and the results could notbe known until a year&apos;s actual operation.7. So far the Committee&apos;s views on an early experiment have beenuncompromisingly hostile. They are contained in a letter from Sir Harry Pilkington(Annex A). (The other major television questions before the Committee which theythink would be prejudged are listed in Annex B.)Other Policy Aspects of an Experiment8. In view of the many interests an experiment would need to be run by some form of consortium: more than one experiment might be necessary. We believeRank/Rediffusion would be prepared to take part in a consortium experiment if their equipment were used. The British Broadcasting Corporation and theIndependent Television Authority, among others, might be invited to participate.Parliament would no doubt wish to debate the terms of the Postmaster GeneraPslicence, since it could be said that we were bringing into being a third television programme-producing authority in addition to the Corporation and the Authority.Parliament would be interested in the control of programme content, balance,political and religious items; and especially perhaps in the basis of allocatinglicences and the financial conditions to be attached. The recent ConservativePolitical Centre pamphlet argues that existing contractors should not be givenadditional contracts; Rediffusion and Rank, and others interested, have large stakesin commercial television.conclusion.   The alternatives seem to be:(a) To postpone a decision about an experiment until after Pilkington has reported in about 18 months&apos; time.(b) To try to persuade the Pilkington Committee to acquiesce in an experimenton the explicit assurances set out in paragraph 6; plus perhaps the option to participate in some way in the experiment if they so wished.10.   We invite the views of the Cabinet.R. M.J. R. B.15th December, 1960.
Letter from Sir Harry Pilkington to the Postmaster General23rd November, I960.Dear Minister,,I put to the Committee the substance of the talk Mr. Hudson and I had with you and the President of the Board of Trade on 15th November about an experiment in subscription television. In doing so, I drew attention to the presidents view that it would be easier for the equipment developed here to compete in overseas markets if it could be shown at work.After going over the ground again, the Committee felt bound to conclude thatan experiment should not be authorised before it had reported. The essentialarguments are twofold. First, the issues of broadcasting policy prompted byproposals for subscription television are far-reaching and involve other major questions before the Committee. A decision to authorise an experiment would inevitably prejudge the answers not only to the question whether subscriptiontelevision should be introduced, but also the answers to the other questions. i must emphasise that these other questions are anything but trifling; the answers tothem will shape the future and purpose of broadcasting. In short, they are so important that, if they are prejudged, the Committee must ask itself whether its work would serve any useful purpose.The second essential argument is this. The Committee fully understand the presidents concern to promote exports. Even if they were pretty certain tomaterialise and to contribute significantly to our trade, it must be doubtful in theextreme whether they primarily should determine the future of broadcasting inthe United Kingdom.  But the export possibilities here must be problematical.There is one thing which has not yet been said plainly and perhaps ought tobe. It would be unrealistic to suppose that the export of equipment is more thanincidental to the main objective of those who are anxious to experiment. their main objective is surely to run a service of subscription television in this country;and that is a matter on which the Committee are to advise.Yours sincerely,(Sgd.)      HARRY PILKINGTON,Chairman.ANNEX BMajor Television Questions with which Pilkington Committee are ConcernedSome of the issues with which the Pilkington Committee is faced are:(a) What additional television services should be provided, i.e., how many and what nature? This includes the question of additional services for theBritish Broadcasting Corporation and the Independent television authority, Welsh television, &amp;c.(b) How shall they be financed?(c) Who should provide them?(d) Should they, or any of them, start up in the remaining frequencies inBand III and / or Bands IV / V. And how many can be catered for?(e) What is to be the future of the relay industry?(/) Is there a place for television for public showing this would clearly be acompetitor with subscription television for television material.(g) What will be the effect on the existing television service of any additionalservices recommended?December 1960.ANNEX A

</content>
</cab>
