<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 158-160</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  December 1960C. (60) 192 Copy No.       516th December, 1960CABINETFARM IMPROVEMENTS scheme memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food on 25th July the Cabinet, after consideration of a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (60) 118) asked me to give further considerationto the possibility of limiting expenditure under the Farm Improvements scheme by administrative methods and of finding other compensating savings by reductions in other forms of Exchequer assistance to agriculture; and to bring the matter before the Cabinet again in the autumn (C.C. (60) 45th Conclusions, Minute 4).2. The Farm Improvements Scheme was designed to increase the long-termefficiency of the agricultural industry by encouraging owners to improve the equipment of their farms, much of which had inevitably been neglected and fallenout of date in the 30 or so years before, during and immediately after the war.3. The scheme was set up as part of the Agriculture Act, 1957, which gaveeffect to an agreement with the Farmers&apos; Unions in talks following the 1956 annual review and recorded in a White Paper, Long-term Assurances for Agriculture,1956 (Cmnd. 23). There was then no accurate knowledge of the amount of workneeded to bring the equipment of our farms to reasonable efficiency. It was estimated that with the incentive of 33^ per cent, grants, some  150 millions wouldbe spent over the ensuing 10 years. This put Exchequer liability at  50 millions.This is the figure that was written into the Act with the proviso that it could, byorder, be increased to  55 millions.4. Time has shown that this was an under-estimate. By last September, i.e.,when the scheme had run for three years out of the 10, proposals costing in all 73 millions had been approved and it is estimated that others, submitted but notyet approved, would cost another  8 millions a total of some  81 millions. Granton these would amount to  27 millions. In short half the total sum provided forin the Act has been committed in less than one-third of the time.5. While there may in future be some falling off in the number of proposalscoming forward, it is certain that the  50 millions will be exhausted well beforethe 10 years are up. At the present rate, all will be committed before the end of1963; alternatively, if the scheme were to continue&apos;, with applications at the present rate, for the full 10 years, total grant payments would, in the end, be of the orderof  70 millions- 85 millions.6. An examination made last summer by the Agricultural Departments andthe Treasury produced the conclusion, with which Ministers, represented on the farm Price Review Committee concurred, that there were no worthwhilepossibilities of limiting expenditure by adminstrative means. The question has again been considered by officials, and I am satisfied that this conclusion is stillcorrect. Briefly, the initiative in submitting proposals in response to the incentiveof 33^ per cent, grants rests with farmers and landowners. There is no basis onwhich the Agricultural Departments can slow down the rate of applications, oraccept only some of those which satisfy the conditions of the Act.
7. I have considered the possibility of making savings elsewhere to compensate for additional expenditure under the scheme, but have come to theconclusion that this is not possible. We cannot make pound for pound cuts inthe value of the price guarantees for agriculture, if only because grants under thescheme are specifically excluded by the 1957 Act from the Annual Farm price review: but, of course, the more is spent on capital equipment, the more can we expect costs, which will be reflected in Annual Reviews, in future to be kept down.8. So the question to be resolved is whether to let the scheme run on as setout in the Act with grants at 33^ per cent, for the full 10 years or to curtail it insome way so as to keep expenditure within  55 millions. In this connection I would draw my colleagues&apos; attention to the terms in which this figure of  55 millions was presented to the Legislation Committee (Annex A) and to the House (Annex B). Iam satisfied that the financial provision in the Act was never envisaged as morethan a best estimate of the cost for the 10-year scheme certainly not as a ceilingon expenditure.9. I feel strongly that the right course is to allow the scheme to run for thefull 10 years at the present rate of grant:(a) This scheme is one of the most successful of all our forms of assistance to agriculture. It increases efficiency directly and reduces long-termdependence on Exchequer support.(b) The fact that the original estimates look like being exceeded is only an indication of the need for the 10-year scheme of modernisation and theextent to which 30 and more years of depression and neglect have left the long-term equipment of the land inadequate or out of date. 66f percent, of the cost is being met by landowners.(c) As was said in the memorandum to the Legislation Committee (Annex A),our agreement with the farmers in 1956 was for a ten-year Scheme of33^ per cent, grants. We could scarcely avoid charges of breach of faith if only three years after its introduction we announced that either the Scheme was to be limited in time or the grant reduced.(d) To cut either the rate of grant or the period of application would penalisethose who in good faith and for good reasons have been programmingtheir expenditure over the whole ten years of the Scheme.(e) The talks with the National Farmers&apos; Union which the Prime Ministerinitiated have only just been completed. The outcome will be incorporated in a White Paper. It would be most inopportune to makecuts in a programme of capital re-equipment whose continuance hasbeen implicit in all recent discussions on efficiency and incomes, andwhich results from the discussions with the Farmers&apos; Unions four yearsago.10. For these reasons I urge that we should decide now to continue theScheme for the full ten years at the present rate of grant. The announcementcould be made either when it becomes inevitable or when it seems most prudent to do so.11. This memorandum has been agreed with the Home Secretary and theSecretary of State for Scotland.C. S.Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, S.W. 1,16th December, 1960.
ANNEX AExtract from Memorandum to the Legislation Committee Dated26th February, 1957, by Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and FoodAGRICULTURE BILL, 1957Our agreement with the farmers incorporated in the White Paper provided forthe payment of 33J per cent, grants for a period of 10 years. We estimated that the grants were likely to cost something of the order of  50 millions. I propose that provision for this sum should be included in the Bill with power by Order to increasethe provision to  55 millions. I am, however, anxious to make it clear that we haveno intention, by a system of quotas or otherwise, to restrict the volume of grant-aidedwork from year to year with a view to keeping within this financial limit. For thispurpose, I would propose to include in my Second Reading speech a general statement on the lines attached to this note which has been agreed with officials ofthe Treasury by my Department.ANNEX extract from Second Reading Speech on the Agriculture Bill,25th March, 1957Clause 18 is the financial Clause, and states that the grants will be 33^ per cent.We estimate the cost at about  50 millions for 10 years. For constitutional reasons,we thought it desirable to put this figure in the Bill, though it is necessarily a veryspeculative figure. We worked it out rather like this. We estimate that, withoutany grants, the work of the kind covered by these schemes is running at about 8 millions a year at present, excluding work of a kind already aided under other schemes. We believe that with a stimulus of this sort, the flow might be doubled,say,  15 millions, of which  5 millions would represent the cost of the grant.We are now asking Parliament to authorise an expenditure up to  50 millions for 10 years, and to give us the power to increase that sum to  55 millions, if theestimates prove too low. If the expenditure seems likely to exceed that figure, weshall have to look at the question afresh when the time comes. If, on the other hand,the volume of work is less than we estimate, we are taking power to extend the period from 10 to 12 years.I cannot give a definite undertaking as far as .10 years ahead that never, in any circumstances, will there have to be a limitation of this expenditure. TheGovernment must retain freedom of action there, but I hope that we shall avoid any form of limitation and be able to allow the scheme free play and permit grant-aidedimprovements to go forward without restraint.

</content>
</cab>
