<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/103/0 images: 39-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^1                                                                          [v^^^/V^o   *. ^LmsecretTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT^Lw\                                        Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1960 ^--MC. (60) 195 Copy No. 32MxWw,               22nd December, 1960. IMjmM^Lm                                   cabinet ^Lmmoscow communist summit and its implications forthe west^Lw\ Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs^L-W                    The meeting in Moscow of representatives of 81 Communist parties from ^tW.10th November to 1st December resulted in the issue of a 20,000-word statement, ^L%M^--M               and an appeal to the peoples of the world.  Detailed notes on these documents ^LWM^Lm%               contrasting them with those issued after the last meeting of 12 Communist parties ^L%MMl-W              in 1957 are attached. lUmt2.   Why the Meeting was held.-The meeting took place as a result of the ^L-W^L-W               sharpening differences between Peking and Moscow. The main differences, evident ^L-M^L-W              since 1958 and acrimonious since September 1959, were not resolved in any way ^L-M^--W               by meetings which had been going on since last June.  They concerned Chinese ^L-Mdissatisfaction with Mr. Khrushchev&apos;s attitude towards the West in general and ^L%M^L-W    I         the United States in particular, and over apparent Soviet reluctance to encourage ^L-W^L-W               revolutionary action in the Middle East, Africa and Latin America.   Beneath ^Lm\these specific conflicts, which were couched in doctrinal terms according to normal M\-MCommunist practice, there were divergencies inherent in the different problems and WMWcircumstances of the two very disparate societies, and in the different background ^L%M^L%W                of their leaders.   In voicing their disagreement with Soviet policies, and in ^L%M^L%W               pursuing independent policies of their own, domestic and foreign, the Chinese ^L-Winevitably challenged Soviet leadership. This problem of leadership in turn became mjmm^Lwm               more basic and insoluble than all the other issues dividing the two parties- ^L-W^LWm               exacerbated by personal hostility between Mr. Khrushchev and Mr. Mao Tse-tung. WmxM^L%Wt                     3.   What happened at the Meeting and what will be the effect on intra-bloc ^L-WmxWW relations?--On the basis of the evidence available both overt and covert, I believe WMM^LmW               that the meeting resulted in a slight measure of compromise between the Russians ^L-M^L-M               and the Chinese though this may prove ephemeral; it produced no real ^-M^L%W               reconciliation of views.  Given the underlying nature of the conflict I do not in Wmxm^LwJ fact think that such a reconciliation was ever in the least likely at the meeting. It U-W\^LWl               was never more than a theoretical possibility that Mr. Khrushchev, as a result of^L-W               Chinese pressure, would have renounced the convictions evidently reached after ^L-w,^LWl               profound consideration and first enunciated at the 20th Party Congress in 1956 MxW}mwM ^Lm^L-W                     (a) {Global war is not fatally inevitable. M-Wm^Lwm                    (b) The peaceful transition to Socialism in individual countries and on a world ^L-M^LWl                             scale is now possible because of the increased strength of the Socialist ^LW\^LW]                             camp (the implicit consequence of this is that adventurist policies involve ml-m^L-W                             unnecessary risks). ^Lm\^Lwa               Nor, in the circumstances, was it ever really conceivable that the Chinese, who wmwa^L-W.               have more to gain by upsetting the status quo, would yield to Soviet arguments and ^LW\wM-W give up their more militant attitude on these questions. But if neither side were^LWl likely to yield completely to the other, it did not follow that an open split between^L-W.               them was likely to follow. It always seemed likely that the forces uniting Peking ^LW\^L-W and Moscow (their joint interest in preserving the monolithic structure and appeal^L-W of the bloc; and their military and economic inter-dependence) were bound tosecret^LWM 58241
SECRETprove stronger than their divisions.   The real points at issue in November,therefore, were:HHfl (a) How the two giants would succeed in papering over the cracks. HHJ(b) How far the Chinese would succeed in showing the Russians that there HHJwas widespread support in other Communist parties for the Chinese HHJview, and that the Soviet leaders would in the future have to takemore account of Peking as a second focus of Communist power. HHJ4. As regards the attempt to paper over the cracks the documents resultingfrom the meeting are elastic and general in their terms.  Mr. Khrushchev&apos;s main HHJH^H theses are affirmed.  The meeting no doubt represents something of a triumphfor him, and the immediate effect must be to strengthen his own personal standing, HHJand hence remove doubts amongst the world&apos;s Communist parties about theparamountcy of his doctrines on the non-inevitability of war, peaceful co-existence, HHJ&amp;c. Mr. Mao Tse-tung&apos;s face is saved by the militant tone and repeated emphasison struggle, and by the absence of any but the most perfunctory reference to thepossibility of negotiations with the West. But it appears from secret sources thatthe Russians had already formally accepted by last June the need for greater ^f^Mmilitancy and this has been reflected in their recent policies.  Most significant ofall: within the broad limits set by the documents there is little to inhibit either ^f^ftthe Russians or Chinese from pursuing divergent policies on specific issues.  In HHJgeneral, however, they are both likely for some time to emphasise publicly thepoints of cohesion. Basically, therefore, in terms of Sino-Soviet relations the actualdocuments have little new significance.5. On Chinese Influence.-We know from secret sources that the Chineseviewpoint was supported explicitly by six delegations, and that many othersremained neutral. The rivalry between the Soviet and Chinese leaders persistedthroughout the meeting; and the Chinese delegate in his final speech said that he HHJdid not agree with some of the formulations but had accepted the statement in theinterests of unity.   Some delegates even gained the impression that the era of HHJSino-Soviet co-operation was at an end.  However this may be, the meeting is a HHJmilestone in the evolution of the system of leadership in the Communist bloc. ^^flThe Soviet Communist Party remain paramount: but henceforth, if they areto avoid a repetition of the recent crisis, they will have to concert the main lines ^f^Mof their global policy more effectively by argument and persuasion. Conversely,the Chinese party, though still in second place, have secured tacit recognition of HHJtheir influence and the overt concession that, when disputes arise, party leaderswill hold meetings and consultations to reach joint views.Significance of the Meeting to the West6. In General.-I do not think that the West should derive too muchcomfort from the outcome of the Moscow meeting. It is true that the officialCommunist doctrine that war is not inevitable (which the Chinese had questioned)has been reaffirmed; and that the Chinese have now substantially endorsed theSoviet view of the disastrous consequences of nuclear war-a view which does notdiffer substantially from our own. The main change in fact from 1957 is in thedirection of greater-and exaggerated-self-confidence, and of a more forceful linegenerally. The 1957 declaration claimed only that Socialism was on the up-grade ^f^ftand was exerting ever greater influence upon the international situation. The newstatement asserts that in the world arena &quot; a preponderance of the power ofHHb Socialism over imperialism &quot; is becoming more manifest. To-day it is the Socialistsystem that determines the future course of world history. The time is not far offwhen Socialism&apos;s share of world production will be greater than that of capitalism.Already the present so-called general crisis of capitalism is credited to Sovietcompetition. The defeat for capitalism will be achieved in &quot; the decisive sphereof endeavour, the sphere of material production&quot;.7. The statement is revealing on the meaning which is currently attachedto the phrase &quot; peaceful co-existence &quot;. It is also studded with militant appeals ...&quot; to fill the peoples with a holy anger &quot;, to secure the abolition of military basesHHI and the acceptance of Soviet disarmament policies, to penetrate the Trade Unionsand stir up strikes-all these objectives governed by the phrase at the end of thestatement that &quot; the Communists see as their task the development of a decisive ^^floffensive on the ideological front&quot;. ^f^fiSECRET
SECRET8. Finally the class struggle is to become acute in colonial areas where the ^^fl^f^fi               complete collapse of colonialism is imminent. The struggle for national liberation^f^fi is second only in historical importance to the formation of the world Socialist HHJsystem. The creation of &quot; independent national democracies &quot;, with State planningfree from Western capital, becomes the next political objective. (Significantly the^f^ft models which the Communists had in mind seem to have been Cuba or Guinearather than India or even the United Arab Republic.)9. Specific Issues.-The statement and appeal cannot be looked upon as adetailed guide to future Soviet and Chinese policies towards the outside world.Nevertheless they are a general reflection of the lines the two countries will take ^k^k\and the following tentative assessment is suggested:The Soviet Union(a) Steps which Mr. Khrushchev believes might carry the risk of world warwill continue to be avoided. ^^H(b) He believes that he can mobilise sufficient power and public opinion to ^^Hprevent &quot; imperialists &quot; from fighting &quot; local wars &quot; to defend their^f^fi interests while the Soviet Union will be able to encourage &quot; just&quot; ^^Hstruggles of national liberation.^f^fi (c) &quot; Peaceful co-existence &quot;, involving as it does in Soviet terminology, the ^^Hideological, political and economic struggle, will be pursued relentlessly.(d) Mr. Khrushchev may feel obliged to demonstrate his title to world^f^ft revolutionary leadership by taking a generally more forceful line- ^^Hindeed he may have come to the conclusion many months ago that this ^^H^f^ft was tactically desirable.  The anti-Western and anti-United States tone ^^H^f^fl of the pronouncement will make it more difficult to revive the ^^Hatmosphere of Camp David.  Nevertheless Mr. Khrushchev is likely ^^H^f^ft to pursue his idea of high-level negotiations with the West on Berlin, ^^HGermany and disarmament (this has been confirmed by statements ^^Hmade since the meeting by Soviet leaders to the United States ^^HAmbassador in Moscow), though the eventual negotiations on these ^^Hsubjects would be no easier than before.  However, the commitment ^^Hto militancy and the pursuit of more forceful policies in other directions HHJwill persistently confront him with a tactical dilemma and he will try ^^H^f^ff to create situations in which the West will be compelled to negotiate HHJ^f^fi at a disadvantage. He will also be under increased pressure to present ^^Hthe outcome of any such negotiation as a victory. ^^H(e) Whilst continuing in general to support bourgeois nationalist Governments ^^H^f^fi                             which favour neutralist policies Mr. Khrushchev may be even more ^^Hfanatical and difficult on the subject of colonialism, and may be more HHJinclined than hitherto to encourage revolutionary situations in Africa, ^^HCentral America and Indo-China.  This may for example cause HHJ^f^ft                             repercussions on the present difficult situation in Laos.  There may^f^M be increased and competing Sino-Soviet intervention in Latin America. HHbIn North Africa Mr. Khrushchev will no longer be able to let his policy HHIon Algeria be governed exclusively by Western European considerations HHbas he did in late 1959 and early 1960.(/) On disarmament and nuclear tests, the Russians seem confident that HHIWestern Governments will eventually be forced by the pressure of their HHI^f^fi                             own public opinion to accept Soviet terms.  Disarmament in fact, likepeace, will be imposed. HHh(g) The omission from the statement of all reference to Peking&apos;s admissionH^| to the United Nations should not be taken to imply any change of Soviet HHflpolicy in this respect.  The 1957 declaration made no such reference.Moreover the &quot; appeal&quot; does make the point as part of the diatribeagainst the United States.China10. It must be assumed that for the time being at least Peking will pay lipservice to the common doctrine enunciated in the Moscow statement.   Soviet HHflWWW               opposition is, however, unlikely to have moved the Chinese from their convictionSECRET58241 b
WMM SECRET^WWM that Communism needs more aggressive leadership.  Their future foreign tacticsare likely to be governed by the following considerations: WmWM^Mwt (a) They will remain, within the limits imposed by economic difficulties, asvigorous and uncompromising as ever in the promotion of their aims W-wmand in their attitude to the capitalist world. They may step up their ^L3Mm-MM aid and political intervention abroad and may embark on more extreme mWM^LWt measures than hitherto involving, for example, shipments of arms to ^L3MLatin America and tropical Africa, and intensive military and political ^LwUtraining of Communists from key under-developed countries. M-W^-%m Since 1953 the Chinese have been careful to avoid action calculated to ^LwM^mmW involve them in full-scale war with the West. Nothing that happened ^LjMat the conference is likely to change their policy in this respect. There ^LjMis, for example, no indication that the Soviet Union has promised them ^LjMcloser military support. ^LjMWmvM 11. Conclusions(a) The Communist Summit meeting succeeded for the sake of Communist ^mwM^MwM bloc unity in papering over the cracks in the dispute between Peking ^mwMand Moscow, but did not resolve the fundamental differences, as indeed ^mwMwM-m it was never likely to do. WKmU(6) Relations between Moscow and Peking may for a time be more outwardly ^mWM^LjM friendly and much lip-service will be paid to unity; but neither side is ^LjMmmm likely to feel inhibited from pursuing its previous policies, and Peking ^LmM^Mm will not be inhibited from trying to secure an increasingly important ^mW.^Mm position in the bloc. ^mm^LmW (c) For the outside world the outcome of the meeting probably means little -^M^MwM basic change in the policies which China and Moscow will pursue on ^mm^MwM specific issues but there may be some intensification of the cold war ^mm^Mm. which Mr. Khrushchev seeks to dignify under the name of &quot; peaceful ^mW^Mm co-existence&quot;.   While, therefore, the outbreak of nuclear war has ^Lmm^kmm probably been brought no nearer by the Moscow meeting, neither has ^mTM^kmm the achievement of normal peaceful relations between the Communist ^mW^Mm and non-Communist world.   It is possible of course that Mr. ^mW^LWl Khrushchev may again conclude, as he did in 1959, that a less militant ^mTM^k3m attitude than he is now pursuing, would be advantageous to the Soviet ^mW^k3m Union. But whereas Marshal Stalin, who did not have to account for ^mW^L3M his actions to anyone, found it easy to change his policies overnight, ^mmMr. Khrushchev, in the new circumstances which prevail in the Soviet ^mm^Mm Union and to the Communist world as a whole, would have to move ^mW^mwM much more carefully. ^mmmm* mmmForeign Office, S.W.I,^Mm 22nd December, 1960. ^mWi SECRET i
SECRET^LM THE MOSCOW STATEMENT OF 1st DECEMBER, 1960wMwi                 The statement is interesting both for the changes from the last bloc declaration Mmm^L%Wt            made in Moscow in 1957 and for the way it deals with points at issue between Peking ^--w^-WM            and Moscow. ^L-u1960 Compared with 1957 1m^L-m                 2.   Compared with the 1957 declaration which was signed only by the 12 parties ^-wm^L%W            of bloc countries, this year&apos;s declaration carries 81 signatures, representing parties wMWM^Lwg            from all over the world. There is a comparable expansion in the tone of confidence ^--M^L%M            disclosed which verges on euphoria.   The 1957 declaration claimed only that ^--MwMxW            Socialism was on the up-grade and was exerting ever greater influence upon tmxm^L-W            the international situation. The new statement asserts that in the world arena &quot; a ^LW\^L%W            preponderance of the power of Socialism over imperialism &quot; is becoming more ^--MM-Wm            manifest. To-day it is the Socialist system that determines the future course of world Mx-M^L%Wt             history. The time is not far off when Socialism&apos;s share of world production will be -W-M^Lwm            greater than that of capitalism. The defeat for capitalism will be achieved in &quot; the ^--Mdecisive sphere of endeavour, the sphere of material production&quot;. ^L-M^L-W            Sino-Soviet Dispute ^L-WwMXm                  3.   Much of the Moscow statement reaffirms positions on which Moscow and ml-M^Lwm            Peking have long agreed. The forces uniting the two Powers have, not surprisingly, ^--M^Lwm            proved stronger than the causes of division. However on the latter the statement ^--M-WWM            represents a considerable victory for the Soviet point of view.   It endorses mUm^Lw\            Mr. Khrushchev&apos;s main theses particularly on: ^--M(a) The non-inevitability of war.(b) The horrors of nuclear war. -mjm^Lwm (c) The change in the world balance of power making possible the peaceful wM-M^L-W                           transition to Socialism.wM-W                  4.  The Chinese appear to have secured some minor concessions, e.g., on the wMxW^L-M definition of &quot; independent national democracies &quot; and in the harsh languages used^L-W about the United States and Yugoslavia; it may also be fair to assume that^L-W the militant tone and repeated emphasis on struggle and the absence of any but the^L-u            most perfunctory reference to the possibility of negotiations with the West, owe much mWMm^L-M            to Chinese inspiration. ^L-W5.  The main points are as follows: ^L-W(a) War and Peace^L%W This section of the statement endorses the Soviet thesis, first formulatedMl-W                  at the 20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (C.P.S.U.) ^LWl^L%Wt in 1956, that the strength of the Socialist camp is now such that wars are not^L%M                  fatally inevitable. It also endorses the more far-reaching pronouncement of W\mM^LM                  the 21st Congress of the C.P.S.U. in January 1959 that: ^-M^L%W &quot;There will arise a real possibility of eliminating world war from the^Lwm life of human society even before the complete victory of Socialism, while^L%W capitalism remains in a part of the world.&quot;^Lwm The fight for peace is declared to be the prime task of the Communist parties;earlier Chinese statements have tended to treat the fight for peace as secondary^L%W to the fight for the destruction of imperialism. In its only reference to localM\%M wars the statement says that it is possible to combat and stamp out effectively^Lwm such wars started by the imperialists. Among the examples quoted in support^L-M of this view are Algeria, the Congo and Laos.^fl SECRET
H                                                            SECRET ^LWwMM                       (b) Peaceful Co-existence M-WMThe statement endorses the Soviet contention that peaceful co-existence ^LXwrnbetween countries with different systems is the only alternative to nuclear war ^LmWand moreover offers favourable opportunities for the development of the ^LmWstruggle both in capitalist and colonial countries.   &quot; Peaceful co-existence ^LmWamong States does not mean ... a rejection of the class war. Co-existence ^Lmwmbetween States of differing social systems is a form of class struggle between ^LWWSocialism and capitalism. . . . Peaceful co-existence of States with different ^Lmmsocial systems does not mean a reconciliation between the Socialist and ^Lmmbourgeois ideologies.   On the contrary it implies an intensification of the ^LmWstruggle of the working class and of all the Communist parties for the triumph ^Lmwmof Socialist ideas.&quot;   The statement contains only one vague and passing ^LmWreference to the desirability of negotiations with the West, nothing about the ^LmWneed (more than once mentioned by Mr. Khrushchev) for mutual concessions ^LmWas necessary to enable agreements with the West to be reached, and nothing ^Lmwmabout the advantages of personal contacts between Eastern and Western ^LmW(c) Underdeveloped Countries ^LmWThe section on underdeveloped countries is a compromise. The statement ^Lmwmthat independence can be won &quot; both through armed struggle and by non- ^LmWmilitary methods &quot; represents a victory for the Soviet view, since the Chinese ^Lmwmhave hitherto held armed struggle to be the &quot; principal &quot; and &quot; most important &quot; ^Lmwmmeans. On the other hand there is a Chinese emphasis in the comment that the ^LmW&quot; national  bourgeoisie&quot; in  underdeveloped countries,  though  it  &quot; can ^LmWmmwM                      participate in the revolutionary struggle &quot;, remains &quot; unstable &quot; and &quot; inclined \mmm\to compromise &quot;.  In the passage on &quot; independent national democracies &quot; ^Lmmfwhich follows the Russians and Chinese have apparently tried to define the ^LmWkind of State which they would like to see taking the place of former colonies ^LmWand dependent territories.  The result is a description which fits extremists ^Lmmflike Cuba and Indonesia better than moderates like India and Egypt-a point ^LmWwhich the Chinese may use to reinforce their arguments that economic aid from ^LmWthe Soviet bloc should be distributed more selectively. ^LmW(d) Intra-bloc Relations ^LwMWhile stressing that all parties are independent and have equal rights, the    M1 ^LmWstatement stresses that the C.P.S.U. &quot; has been and remains the universally ^LmwmmWM                      recognised   vanguard   of   the   World   Communist   Movement&quot; andthat its example &quot;represents the revolutionary principles of proletarian ^LmWinternationalism applied in practice&quot;.   This appears to be as definite an ^LmWassertion of Soviet primacy as anything in the 1957 declaration. However, the ^LmWpossibility of further Sino-Soviet disagreement is implied in the sentence: ^Lmmf&quot; When this or that party raises questions about the work of another brotherly ^LmWparty, its leadership of the party in question and, when necessary, meetings ^Lmwmand consultations are held.&quot; ^LmW(e) Economic Competition and United States Imperialism ^LmWThe emphasis in the opening section of the statement on material ^LmWproduction as &quot; the decisive sphere of human endeavour &quot; is typically Russian ^LmWWLW                      and the Chinese may have had some difficulty in accepting the assertion, WmmWattributed to Lenin, that the Socialist countries will &quot; influence the developmentof world revolution chiefly by their economic construction &quot;.  On the other ^h\jmhand the Chinese have obtained a rather more thorough going and unqualified ^LmWcondemnation of the United States than was included in the 1957 declaration. ^L\m\SECRET
-&gt;r SECRETANNEX BTHE &quot; APPEAL TO THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD &quot;From the meeting of representatives of 81 Communist and Workers&apos; Parties,Moscow, November 1960.-Published 12th December, 1960This appeal is the successor to the &quot; Peace Manifesto &quot; issued after theConference of Communist Parties held in Moscow in 1957. Both documents makethe point that war can and must be prevented, but the appeal of 1960 is moreemphatic than the manifesto of 1957 both on the menace of war and on the forcesranged against it. The general tone is also more intense.2. The following points are common to the 1957 manifesto and the 1960(a) End the arms race.(b) Ban the manufacture, testing and use of atomic and hydrogen weapons.(c) Abolish foreign military bases.(d) Prevent the rearmament of Germany (and that of Japan, says the 1960appeal).(e) Support&quot; peaceful co-existence&quot;.3. The following points occurred in 1957, but are not repeated in 1960:(a) &quot; Demand an end to the plotting and military provocation of the|B imperialists in the Middle East.&quot; (This is obviously passe.)(b) &quot; Demand from your Government that in the United Nations they pursuea policy of peace and opposition to the cold war.&quot;  (This description twW^^hardly fits the behaviour of the Soviet bloc during the present session.That may be why the 1960 appeal, although it also calls for an end tothe cold war, does not link this with the United Nations.)4. The following points appear for the first time in the 1960 appeal:(a) &quot; Combat attempts by the Governments of the imperialist Powers toinvolve new countries in the cold war &quot;-an obvious reference to the(b) &quot; Demand the conclusion of a peace treaty with the two German Statesand the conversion of West Berlin into a demilitarised free city.&quot;(c) &quot; Do not let the United States monopolies rob the heroic Cuban people oftheir freedom, by economic blockade or armed intervention.&quot;(d) &quot; Insist on the immediate conclusion of a treaty on general, complete andcontrolled disarmament.&quot;Conclusion5. The appeal of 1960, like the manifesto of 1957, is simply an endorsementof current Soviet policy.SECRET

</content>
</cab>
