<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/197/18 images: 452-470</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 88, .     1      , COPY NO       Q16 October 1977 01CABINETTHE LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1977-78AND the QUXEN&apos;3 SPEECHESNote by the Lord President of the council. By a series of decisions taken in recent months we have alreadysettled the main planks of next Session&apos;s programme.    We are firmlycommitted to proceeding with the Scotland Bill, the Wales Bill and theEuropean Assembly Elections Bill.    These Bills, even with considerablystricter guillotines on the two devolution Bills than contemplated in theCabinet discussion on 21 July (CM(77) 27th Conclusions, Minute 3), willtake up a high proportion of the parliamentary time available for government legislation next Session.2. There will be at least ten Bills next Session in the Essential category;brief details are in Part I of Annex A.    These Bills cannot be avoided, andwill need about a quarter of the available parliamentary time.3. The Bills mentioned above constitute a full legislative programme buta thin one.    The Queen&apos;s Speeches and Future Legislation Committee (QF)recommend the inclusion in the programme of three other Bills, listed inPart II of Annex A, on which there is a very strong case for action next session.4. A manifestly overloaded fourth Session of the present parliament would not be in the Governments interests, and the above programmerepresents the maximum to which we should commit ourselves in The Queen&apos;sOpening Speech.    It leaves little margin for an Autumn Finance Bill, or for anyother legislative contingencies of the kind which almost invariably arise.Shorter recesses than desirable, and an Autumn spill-over may becomeUnavoidable -5. There is a number of other highly desirable Bills (listed in Part II of annex A) which would certainly be included in next Session&apos;s programme if our room for manoeuvre was not so limited, and which we shall wish tointroduce as soon as parliamentary time can be found.    QF consider thatthe Speech should say so, specifying the most attractive of these Bills.This will make known our future intentions, avoid an unduly barren opening speech and keep faith with the interests concerned, helping us to contain the pressures for a larger legislative programme than can possibly beac commodated.1
6. Part IV of Annex A lists other Bills which have been put forward for inclusion in next Session&apos;s programme, and shows how it is proposedto deal with each.7. I am arranging an early approach to the Opposition about Bills in parts III and IV of Annex A which seem suitable for Second reading committee procedure in the Commons.    If this procedure is agreed, these bills can be introduced in the Lords when ready.    (The Lords are likely,even so, to be short of legislative business during the first three months ofthe Session, since most of the Bills in the programme wiH have to start inthe Commons.    But there is no practicable remedy for this situation. )8. The plans set out above result from a thorough examination of theposition by OF, with the assistance of colleagues responsible for Bills.QF would have liked to be able to promise more Bills firmly in The Queen&apos;sSpeech, but the parliamentary time in the Commons is not available.    Theywould have liked to give higher priority to a number of Bills, but were unableto identify any Bills which could be given lower priority to make thenecessary room.    Their proposals steer a course between on the one handan unduly thin Queen&apos;s Speech, and on the other hand a greatly overloadedSession which would be even more damaging to the Government.    i recommend that the Cabinet should endorse them.9. Drafts of The Queen&apos;s Prorogation and Opening Speeches are attached at Annexes B and C, for consideration by the Cabinet.M FPrivy Council Office6 October 19772
AM EX a legislative PROGRAMME 1977-78(Other than the Scotland Bill,  the Wales bill and the European Assembly Elections Bill)I.     ESSENTIAL BILLSBroadcasting Bill, required (regardless of any wider decisions on Annan)to renew the IBA Act 1973 before its expiry.Transport Bill, required to increase the limits on passenger servicegrants to BR and to provide for the financial reconstruction of the NFC;will also implement some of the more attractive proposals in the recentWhite Paper, on public transport plans, bus licensing, heavy lorries andcar parks.Civil Aviation Bill, required to increase the borrowing power of the CAA;will also provide for the airlines to bear the cost of airport security arrangements, and amend the law in the light of the Laker Skytrain case to ensure that the Government can give effect to the policy of only one british airline on each long-haul route.Power Stations (Financial Arrangements) Bill, required to provide legisltive authority to pay compensation to the CEGB for advancing Drax B.a-Atomic Energy Bill, required to implement United Kingdom obligations under the United Kingdom/Euratom/lAE&apos;A Agreement and thus to safeguardsupplies of uranium ore.Continental Shelf Act 1964 (Amendment) Bill, required to provide statutorycover for the Department of Energy contribution to the Ministry of Defencecosts of patrolling oil and gas fields.Participation Agreements Bill, required to exempt oil participation agree-ments from the Restrictive Trade Practices Acts, under which certain provisions of such agreements might otherwise be declared void.1
Weights and Measures Bill, required by 1979 to provide for the changeoverfrom the minimum to the average contents system for pre-packed goods, as required by e.c. directives;    whether it is necessary to legislate next session rather than the Session after still under consideration.Trustee Savings Banks Bill, required to make clear that Trustee savings banks have powers to grant mortgages.Company Law Bill, required to implement e.c. second directive on companylaw;    will also provide for Register of Business Names to become self-supporting, and may include other desirable reforms of company law,possibly including some related to industrial democracy.Solomon Islands Independence, required to give effect to recentindependence settlement.II.   OTHER BILLS IN THE programme .     Shipbuilding Industry.     The Government is committed to givingfinancial support for a shipbuilding redundancy scheme.     A short Billis needed to provide for the necessary payments, with effect from1 July 1977.     The CSEU accept the need for the scheme and want early legislation.     Not to go ahead next Session seems almost unthinkable.2.     Inner Cities.     The Government is committed to a policy of partner-ship with some major cities, with a substantial increase in urban programme funds.     Legislation,  as promised in the inner cities white paper, to enhance the powers of these and selected other local authorities with serious inner area problems to assist industry, is an essentialcomponent of this policy.3*     Housing.   The Prime Minister1s exchange of letters with Mr Steelrenewing the arrangement with the Liberals commits us to legislationnext Session providing help for first-time buyers.     The Bill could also increase the Housing Corporations guarantee powers to raise privatefinance, which would greatly help employment in the construction industrywithout adding to public expenditure, but could be controversial.
III. HIGHLY DESIRABLE BILLS,  to be introduced as soon as there isparliamentary time (in order of priority).4.     Merchant Shipping.     Badly needed reform of law relating primarily to safety and conditions of work at sea.     Wanted by both unions andindustry, not politically contentious, and the Government is firmlycommitted to legislating as soon as practicable.5.     Post Office Workers.     To ensure that Post Office workers have theright to take normal industrial action.     Would be popular with the party and the unions.60     Employment and Training.     Power to take new measures againstunemployment without the need for primary legislation;    and (if agreement is reached among all concerned) arrangements for collective funding ofindustrial training.     It would be better not to mention in the Speechthe possibility of new powers to deal with unemployment which cannot be firmly promised.7&apos;0     Medical.     Merrison Committee proposals on reconstitution of GMC.Early legislation most desirable for sake of relations with medical profession.     It is hoped that the Opposition will agree to SecondReading Committee procedure.8.     Education.     To deal with the position of parents on choice of schools;   to implement (subject to the outcome of consultations) some ofthe Taylor Committee recommendations on school governors;    to make provision for industrial scholarships and grants;    to provide for othergrants to LEAs.     Would have wide appeal.9.     Suppression of Terrorism.     To give effect to the European convention on this subject.     Of international importance.     We have publicly declaredthat we will ratify the Convention as soon as possible and have been urgingother countries to do so.     Possibility of Second Reading Committeeprocedure to be explored.3
10.   Crown Agents (incorporation).     To incorporate the Crown Agents witha defined constitution and functions, and to prescribe the Government&apos;spowers and responsibilities.     The Government has been firmly committed to this since 1975, and the forthcoming Pay Report will cause pressuresfor early action.11.   Local Government (Functions).     To restore some powers to formercounty boroughs and remove overlap of powers between counties anddistricts.     No firm policy decisions yet taken;   not to be mentionedin Queen&apos;s Speech oiidng to this uncertainty.12.   Judicature (Northern Ireland).     Major and much needed re-organisationof higher courts, on lines of Beeching reforms in England and Wales, toimprove administration of justice and relieve strain of coping withterrorism and other crimes.13.   Consumer Protection.     Strengthening of existing legal provisions on the safety of products;   improvements in law on fair trading;   protec-tion for small depositors against banking collapses;   provisions for credit unions, facilitating consumer co-operation and the borrowing ofmoney at reduced rates of interest;    control of tobacco substitutes andadditives.     Consumer package of wide appeal, would have Liberal support.Consideration being given to whether this would need one, two or threeBills.14-   Nurses, Midwives and Health Visitors.     Major and much neededre-orgrnisation of these professions, as recommended in Briggs Report.Would set up new machinery only - funds for bringing about improvements,eg in training of nurses, not yet provided in PESO.     Possibility of second Reading Committee to be explored.IV.   OTHER DESIRABLE BILLS15.   Official Secrets Acts.     A modified version of the Pranks Committeeproposals, on lines already announced.     It has still to be settledwhether this Bill should be promised as soon as time can be found (ie trans-ferred to Part III) or whether the Speech chould promise &quot;legislative proposals&quot;, ie a White Paper.4
16.   House of Commons Administration.     To give effect to recommendationsof Bottomley Committee, establishing a House of Commons Commission-     Toproceed next Session only if it can be taken through with little or noexpenditure of prime time.17.   Fi1ms.     To increase the statutory limit on public funds for the1TFFC, which may be reached in about 18 months&apos; time.     Speech couldannounce intention to do this, leaving open whether the Bill could wait until the Session after next or be slipped in next Session.18.   Mu1tip1e Registration.     To implement 1973 Speaker&apos;s conference recommendation preventing second-home owners from registering at morethan one place for electoral purposes.     Pressed by Liberals, butbalance of political advantage in early legislation still underconsideration.19,   Domestic Proceedings and Magistrates&apos; Courts.     The changes made when divorce law was reformed have not yet been carried over intodomestic proceedings in magistrates&apos; courts.     This Law Commission bill would do so.     Much needed reform, of appeal to women1s organisations.Possibility of Second Reading Committee procedure to be explored.20.   Public Lending Right.     The possibility of a non-statutory schemeis being considered.21 .   Hare Coursing.     Might be taken up by a Private Member.22.   Electricity Supply Industry.     To provide for the re-organisationof the industry in accordance with the policy collectively agreed and announced.     There seems little prospect of fitting this in next Session.24. Local Government (Attendance Allowances). To be considered furtherwhen the Robinson Committee report is received.24.   Firearms.     Tighter control over shotguns.     Small prospect offitting this in next Session.5
25.    State Immunity.     Ratification of European Convention making it easier to sue foreign Governments.     Possibility of Second reading committee procedure to be pursued.26.   Gun Barrel Proof.     To enable the United Kingdom to join permanentInternational Commission for Proof of Small Firearms.     It is hoped thatSecond Reading Committee procedure will prove possible.Other Bills for which the possibility of Second Reading Committee mightbe considered, if there is room for any additions to those mentionedabove, include those on Ancient Monuments, Coinage, Prevention of Fraud(investments) and Theft.6
ANNEX draft PROROGATION SPEECHMT LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS,My husband and I look back with delight and gratitude on the events whichmarked my Silver Jubilee at home and overseas, and the visits which we made tmany parts of the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth,I was pleased to welcome Commonwealth leaders in London for the 1977Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting, for which my Government werethe hosts.    The intensive and friendly discussions there strengthenedthe Commonwealth relationship and contributed towards the solution of certaininternational problems.My Government played an active and constructive part in the activitiesof the European Communities, which included two meetings of the EuropeanCouncil, one in London, and held the Presidency of the Council of ministers for the first six months of 1977.My Government have played a full and positive role in institutions to promoteinternational development and efforts to create a more just and stableeconomic order, and in discussions on the problems of world unemployment and inflation; they were hosts to the Downing Street Conference of theleaders of the seven major industrialised countries.Legislation has been passed to enable the United Kingdom to ratify amendments to the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund and to assistUnited Kingdom trade and the provision of aid for the poorest countries.Special assistance has been given to southern Affrican refugees.My Government have continued their efforts to promote a negotiated settlement in Rhodesia.
My Government has been active, in co-operation with other Western membersof the Security Council, in working for a settlement in Namibia which will bring the country to independence in a manner which will moot with international acceptance and will give the people a chance to selectfreely their own government *My Government have continued to attach importance to the development ofdetente, and of constructive political and economic relations, with theSoviet Union and the countries of Eastern Europe.    They have continuedto work for mutual and balanced force reductions in Central Europe.   Theyare participating with the Governments of the United States and theSoviet Union in discussions aimed at the negotiation of a ComprehensiveTest Ban Treaty.My Government were pleased to act as hosts at the Ministerial Meeting ofthe North Atlantic Council which was attended by Heads of Government inLondon in May, and which established new programmes of work in the politicaland defence fields.MEMBERS OP THE HOUSE OP COMMONS,I thank you for the provision which you have made for the honour and dignityof the Crown and for the public services.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OP THE HOUSE OP COMMONS,My Government have given continuing priority to their policy of restrainingprice levels, and of the fullest possible co-operation to this end with bothsides of industry.   The second round of vouluntary pay policy has been fullyobserved throughout the economy, and the way has been prepared for an orderly return to normal collective bargaining.   Legislation has been passed to make new provision for the scrutiny and effective control of prices,and a new Price Commission has been appointed.   Successful steps have beentaken to restore confidence in the financial markets and improve thebalance of payments.2
jmme,My Government remain deeply concerned about the continuing high level ofunemployment, and have introduced additional employment and trainingmeasures to tackle this problem, including the youth opportunities progrcMy Government have maintained their policy of strengthening industrythrough the development of the industrial strategy, through industrialassistance schemes, and through the work of the National Enterprise Boardand the Scottish, Welsh and Northern Ireland Development Agencies,Legislation was enacted to bring into public ownership the aircraft andguided weapons, shipbuilding and marine engine building industries.Negotiations for the acquisition by British Shipbuilders of a major partof the ship-repairing industry are in progress.An Act has been passed to enlarge the Post Office Board so as to allow an experiment in industrial democracy.Legislation has been enacted to give the National Coal Board additional powers and provide the framework   for the further development of the coalindustry, and to make further provision for the financing of British NuclearI^iels Limited and the Radiochemical Centre Limited,   My Government arecompleting the award of licences, all involving majority state participation,under the Fifth Round of off-shore petroleum licensing.Steps have been taken to ensure further safeguards in the management of nuclear waste, and full and public consideration of the problems relatingto nuclear development; a public inquiry has been set up to examine theproposal for the construction of an oxide fuel reprocessing plant at WindscaleLegislation has been passed extending United Kingdom fishery limits to 200 mil&quot;tribute is due to the hard work of the fishery protection units in enforcing the new limits.3
A new and favourable Air Services Agreement with the United States of america has been signed.An Act has been passed to reform patent law and to make posssible theUnited Kingdom*s participation in certain international agreementsincluding the European Patent Convention,In Northern Ireland the Royal Ulster Constabulary, supported by my armed forces, have continued to enforce the law with impartiality and deserve thehighest praise for their success in reducing the level of violence.My Government have maintained the aim of a just and lasting constitutional settlement, and they have taken measures to combat the economic and social problems in the Province, including new incentives for investment.My Government have published Green Papers discussing possible changes inthe arrangements for financing local authorities.My Government have continued to develop a housing policy, designed, to deal more effectively with the most pressing needs and to broaden housing opportunities.Proposals have boon published, for a comprehensive housing policy for the longer term, and legislation has boon enacted to place statutory responsibility for assisting the homeless on local housing authorities.My Ministers have announced new initiatives for the regeneration of innerurban areas, including the expansion and adaptation of the urban programme and the offer of partnership arrangements betxfeen central government andselected local authorities.Proposals have been laid befor you for strengthening the water industryand for the future of the British Waterways Board,My Government have reviewed, the development programme of new toxms in Englandand have established a new programme for their completion.4
My Government have published a White Paper setting out their proposals forthe future development of transport policy to meet economic and socialneeds.   An Act has been passed to provide continued financial support to theBritish Railways Board and the National Freight Corporation,Provision has been made for increases in social security benefits and warpensions.   Legislation was enacted making a number of changes in the field of social security, including supplementary benefit.   The new Child Benefitwas brought into payment for all children, including the first.My Government have continued to promote and encourage voluntary effort and a sense of caring in the community, and I hope that the community spiritfostered by the celebrations of my Jubilee will be strengthened and devolped in the years to come.My Government have published a Green Paper setting out proposals on education in schools, with particular regard to the curriculum, standards of performance, the training and employment of teachers and the preparationof pupils for the needs of adult life.An Act has been passed to amend the criminal law, particularly in relationto conspiracy, and to improve its administration; and the process ofreforming the laitf has been continued with the Administration of Justice Actand other measures.My Government welcome the passage of the Unfair Contract Terms Act, which marks animportant advance in consumer protection.   Grants have been made to maintainthe provision of help to consumers.Among the Acts passed in relation to Scotland were measures concerned withthe modernisation of the law of marriage and with the enforcement of planningprocedures.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS,I pray that the blessings of Almighty God may attend you.5
ANNEX CDRAFT OPENING SPEECHNOTESquare brackets indicate that the text may need revision, eg in the light offurther discussion of the policy.MY LORD AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS,/I look forward to paying a State Visit to the Federal Republic of Germanynext May.7My Government re-affirm their general policies in international relations and defence.   They remain fully committed to the aims of peace and collective security; of detente, disarmament and prevention of the spread of nuclear weapons; and of an expanding and more stable world economy-In the pursuit of these aims my Government will continue to make their full contribution to international discussions and to the activities of theUnited Nations, the Commonwealth and the North Atlantic Alliance.My Government will continue to play a full and co-operative part in theactivities., the development and the enlargement of the European economic community; and the work within it for policies which also fully reflect the interests of the United Kingdom in the fulfilment of these aims.My Government will continue to contribute modern and effective forces tothe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation, and to play their full part in thecurrent Alliance studies of East/West relations and of the Alliance&apos;^ defence programmes.   They will continue to participate constructively in the importantmeeting in Belgrade which is being held as part of the follow-up to theFinal Act of the Conference on Security and Co-operation in Europe, willabide by the provisions of the Final Act and will continue to seek fulfilment of its provisions by other signatories.My Government will continue to take part in international efforts to combatrecession and promote a more stable world economic order, and a fairerdistribution, within an expanding world economy, of the world&apos;s wealthbetween rich and poor nations; they will continue to make s^iecial efforts to help the poorest countries and the poorest people.
My Government will work for a just and lasting peace in the Middle East,and the further improvement of relations between the United Kingdom andall the countries in the area.   They will continue to co-operate with allconcerned in the search for a lasting settlement in Cyprus, where theywelcome the resumption of intercommunal talks.My Government will continue to work for a negotiated settlement in Rhodesia,on the basis of the proposals published on 1 September, which are designedto provide a secure future for people of all races.   They hope during thecurrent session to introduce legislation to enable Rhodesia to proceed toinedpendence on this basis.MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS,Estimates for the public service will be laid before you.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS,Following the strengthening of the financial position and the balance ofpayments, my Government look forward to a developing and sustained improve-ment in the economy, while maintaining financial stability.   The highest priority will be given to consolidating the success of the attack on inflation.Through the Industrial Strategy, my Government intend to achieve a fundamentalimprovement in industrial performance.   My Government will continue to take effective action to reduce high unemployment through manpower measures and topromote industrial training.    In these matters, and in preparing for a sustainedgrowth of output and a lasting reduction of unemployment in the years to come,my Government will work in close co-operation with the Trades Union Congress andthe Confederation of British Industry.My Government will continue to urge internationally the importance of sustainedgrowth in the strongest economies and the need for adequate official finance tobe made available on appropriate terms to countries with continuing deficits intheir balance of payments.My Government remain firmly committed to establishing directly elected Assembliesfor Scotland and Wales.   Separate Bills will be introduced for this purpose for Scotland and Wales.2
My Government will bring before you the results of the consultationsthat have taken place on the consultative document &quot;Devolution: theEnglish Dimension&quot;.In Northern Ireland my Government will maintain their aims of establishing a devolved Government acceptable to both parts of the community; eradicatingterrorism by the prosecution through the courts of those responsible forviolence and by continuing to develop the effectiveness of the Eoyal ulster constabulary, supported by My Armed Forces; strengthening the economy;and improving the social environment.Legislation providing for the election of United Kingdom members of theEuropean Assembly will be re--introduced0/My Government will continue their consultations on industrial democracywith a view to producing proposa?s commanding general support, and will bring forward legislation amending company law.   They will continue toencourage the further development of industrial democracy in the nationalised industries./My Government will also hold consultations about the form of arrangementsfor encouraging profit sharing through the tax system./The operation and effectiveness of competition policy will be reviewed witha view to bringing forward proposals for improvements in the legislation and institutions governing the maintenance of competition and the encouragement of industrial efficiencyA Bill will be introduced for the provision of public funds to financepayments to redundant shipbuilding workers in the public sector.My Government will continue to encourage the efficient production, processingand distribution of food with the aim of meeting a greater proportion of our national needs from United Kingdom agriculture.   They will seek further improvement in the operation of the Common Agricultural Policy.3
My Government will continue to seek major reform of the Common FisheriesPolicy.   They will aim to secure conditions which will meet the needs ofthe British fishing industry, conserve fishing stocks, and ensure adequate supplies to the consumer.A Bill will be laid before you to amend the Civil aviation Acts.Legislation will be introduced to sustain and promote further the developmentof transport policy to meet economic and social needs, including those of rural areas.Legislation will be brought before you to provide assistance for first-timehome buyers.A Bill will be introduced to further my Governmenfs proposals for theregeneration of inner urban areas.My Government wish to introduce as soon as Parliamentary time can be founda number of further highly desirable measures of reform. These Bills willrelate to -- merchant shipping, including safety and discipline at sea;- the right of Post Office staff to take industrial action;- the composition and powers of the General Medical Council;- the law on education, including the choice of school and the management and government of schools;- the European Convention on the Suppression of Terrorism;- the establishment of the Crown Agents as a statutory corporation;- the organisation of the higher courts in Northern Ireland;- consumer protection and co-operation, including provisions on the safety of products, the protection of small depositors, credit unions,fair trading and the control of tobacco substitutes and additives;- the establishment of new bodies responsible for professional standards,education and discipline in nursing and midwifery./Legislative proposals will be brought forward for the reform of section 2of the Official Secrets Act 1911*7
My Government will bring forward proposals relating to broadcasting in theUnited Kingdom.Measures will be brought before you to reform public sector housing subsidiesin Scotland; to improve criminal procedure and reform the criminal justicesystem; and to extend the powers of Scottish local authorities in relationto their direct labour organisations.My Government will make further progress with their programme of law reform.Other measures will be laid before you.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS,I pray that the blessing of almighty God may rest upon your counsels.6 October 1977


</content>
</cab>
