<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/44 images: 416-431</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)149th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 149 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, May 31, 1940, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Lord President of theCouncil (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Items 11-13).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (items-10 and 14).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P.,  Secretary  of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Secretary   of   State   for   Scotland(Items 11-13).The   Right   Hon.    Ernest   Bevin,Minister of Labour (Items 11-13).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-10).Air Chief Marshal R. E. C. Peirse,Vice-Chief    of    the    Air    Staff(Items 1-10).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander.-M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty(Items 1-10).The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air (Items 1-10).The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 1-10).The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information (Items 1-10).The Right Hon. R, S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister     of     Agriculture     andFisheries (Items 1-13).Admiral  of  the  Fleet  Sir - dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-10).Lieutenant-General R. H. Haining,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff (Items 1-10).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.[21367a]
WAR CABINET 149 (40).Contents.minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      The Western Front..................     321Withdrawal of the B.E.F.The British 2-pdr. anti-tank gun.2      The Air Situation     ..................    322B.A.F. operations.Coastal Command.Enemy activity.3      The Naval Situation..................     322Withdrawal of the B.E.F.Proposed blocking of Dunkirk.Attacks on trade.4      The United States of America      ...      ...       ...       ...    323Supply of destroyers.Supply of aircraft.5      Norway......      ..................     3246      Invasion of Great Britain    ...      ...      ...       ...      ...     3247      Italy........................    325Probable intentions.Policy to be adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Government.8      Italy     ........................     325Action against Italians in the United Kingdom.9      The U.S.S.R................      ......    326Appointment of a British Ambassador to Moscow.10 Portugal         ..................... 32711 Agricultural Wages  ...      ,.............. 32812 Railwaymen&apos;s Wages ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 33113 General Wages Policy         ............... 33114      Western Front (contd.)        ...............    332Withdrawal of the B.E.F.
The western front.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 148thConclusions,Minute 1.)Withdrawal ofthe B.E.F.1. The Secretary of State for War said that personnel asfollows had been evacuated up to 7 a.m. that day : B.E.F.-FitCasualtiesTotalA Hies Mostly French124,6489,230133,87811,666145,544Later in the meeting the following figures were given of thosereaching this country up to 12 noon :  B.E.F.-FitCasualtiesA Hies139,2449,48014,811Total ...163.535The Secretary of State for War said that he had spoken on the telephone that morning to Lord Gort who had said that the british force left was equivalent in number to one corps. The germans had been attacking the Corunna Line near Furnes. There were indications that a major attack was being mounted, but it was not known whether it would be launched that day, or on the following morning. Lord Gort had given orders which it was hoped wouldresult in the greater part of the remaining personnel beingembarked on the night 31st May-lst June.Evacuation by daylight was proceeding steadily.The First Sea Lord said that there was a swell on the beacheswhich was delaying embarkations, but would probably abate later.The Secretary of State for War said that Lord Gort askedwhether he ought to hold on as long as possible, in order to evacuateas many French as possible, or whether when he judged that itwas not safe to delay any longer, he should order the withdrawalof the remaining British troops.He had told Lord Gort that the second was the course whichwe wished him to pursue.The Lord President of the Council thought that this was certainly the view of the War Cabinet.The Secretary of State for War said that it was hoped to embark during the day 5,000 French troops, which formed part ofthe French Corps which had been taking part on the defence ofthe Corunna Line.The Secretary of State said that he was becoming anxious about the safety of Lord Gort himself, and he had it in mind to giveLord Gort a direct order to come home that day.Lord Gort was now visiting General Blanchard at Dunkirk.The Secretary of State proposed to telephone to him later in the morning telling him that two motor boats would be waiting for him at a fixed hour, say 3 p.m. and that he must then return. Lord Gortwould probably be able to persuade General Blanchard to embarkwith him.Lord Gort would be instructed to hand over command of theremaining British troops to one of the Corps or DivisionalCommanders.The Lord President of the Council said that he fully agreed with the Secretary of State for War&apos;s proposal, and he felt sure[21367a] b 2
The British2-pdr. anti-tankgun.The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 148thConclusions,Minute 2.)E.A.F.operations.coastal command.Enemy activity.2. The Vice-Chief of the Air Staff said that heavy cloud hadhindered operations on the previous day.Bombers had carried out attacks on troops, M.T. columns, road and rail junctions in Belgium and north-east France.Our fighters had flown a large number of sorties to Dunkirk,but only two enemy aircraft had been seen, one of which had beenbrought down.During the night there had been a number of bomber sortiesagainst troop concentrations in Belgium, while the oil depots at hamburg had been attacked by 18 Hampdens.Two of our bombers and one of our fighters were missing, andone other fighter had crashed.An enemy destroyer and two small merchant vessels had been seen at the entrance to the Nord Fjord, and some 30 ships in Bergenharbour.A conoy of sailing vessels and trawlers had been attacked offthe Lister Light.There had been a number of enemy reconnaissances off the east coast, and some enemy aircraft had been plotted after dark in theNorth Foreland and Thames Estuary area.A convoy was reported to have been attacked and a ship sunk.Shipping in the Downs had been attacked.Thirty-eight aircraft, believed to be mine-laying, had beenplotted during the night between Harwich and the Isle of Wight.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.The Naval 3.   The First Sea Lord said that he had sent a special signalSituation. to the Naval Authorities in charge of embarkation arrangementsWithdrawal of that equal opportunities were to be given for the embarkation ofthe B.E.F.        French and British troops.  A copy of this signal had been given tothe French Naval Mission.   Some French destroyers were taking part in the operations, but so far there was no sign of the 100 fishing vessels which they had promised to send.The following losses had occurred during the last twenty-four hours: Sunk.French destroyer Siroco torpedoed by Motor Torpedo Boat with about 750 French troops on board. About 200 survivors had beenpicked up by British vessels.that the other members of the War Cabinet present took the same view. He knew that the Prime Minister, who had expressed thehope that the War Cabinet would not hesitate to take decisionsduring his absence, was of the same opinion.The Lord President of the Council said that he had heard very-good accounts of the effective use which our troops had made oftheir 2-pdr. anti-tank guns, especially if fire was held until theGerman tank was at 600 yards distance. The French 25 mm. anti-tank gun was said not to be giving as good results.The Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that therewas some evidence to show that our 2-pdr. gun was not provingsuccessful against the largest type of German tank, which was veryheavily armoured in front (though less heavily armoured at the rearand on the sides). The German tactics were always to keep thefront of these tanks facing their enemies.The War Cabinet Approved the instructions which the Secretary of State forWar proposed to give to Lord Gort in regard to his returnto this country.
Proposedblocking of dunkirk.Attacks on trade.S.S. M.ona&apos;s Queen, 1,756 tons.S.S. Fenella, 2,376 tons.S.S. Lorina, 1,578 tons.S.S. Spinel, 650 tons.On fire.H.M.S. Sabre. She had reached Dover and was not seriously damaged.S.S. Clan Macalister, 6,787 tons.S.S. Worthtoivn, 868 tons.Damaged.H.M.S. Anthony.H.M.S. Mosquito.H.M.S. Whitehall.S.S. Princess Maud.A total of 222 naval vessels and 665 ships and boats had beenemployed in the operations.In reply to the Foreign Secretary, the First Sea Lord said that three British and one French destroyer had been sunk, and13 damaged in the recent operations. Those which were damagedmight be out of action for varying lengths of time, but the majorityshould be back in service within three months.The First Sea Lord said that all preparations were ready forthe sending of block-ships to close Dunkirk harbour at theappropriate time. It would be necessary to obtain Frenchconcurrence before action were taken, and he suggested that a message might be sent to the Prime Minister, so that he could raisethe question with M. Reynaud during their present meetings. Itwas most necessary that this blocking should take place, and the timefor carrying it out might arrive very quickly.The following enemy attacks on trade had taken place in thepast few days : Uruguay, 3,425 tons, Argentinian, sunk off Cape Finisterre.Two French trawlers and an unknown ship sunk, all in thesame neighbourhood off Cape Finisterre.Mari Jose, 2,477 tons, French, torpedoed and sunk West ofUshant.Stanhall, 4,831 tons, British, reported sinking 150 miles fromLand&apos;s End, probably torpedoed.Fulham Four, 1,5S4 tons, damaged by aircraft attack in the thames Estuary.H.M.S. Weston had sunk a U-boat off Orfordness at 1 a.m. onthe 31st May, and had picked up 3 Officers and 22 Ratings fromthe crew.The War Cabinet-Invited the Lord President of the Council to communicate with the Prime Minister in Paris, and propose that heshould obtain the concurrence of the French Governmentto our blocking of Dunkirk harbour, when in our judgmentthe right moment had come to do it.United States ofAmerica.Supply of destroyers.(previous reference erences:W.M. (40) 141stConclusions,Minute 9, andW.M. (40) 124thConclusions,Minute 12.)4. In connection with the losses of, and damage to, destroyersrecorded in Minute 3, the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said that he had considered whether a further approach should bemade to the President of the United States with a view to obtainingAmerican destroyers for our use. This matter had been in abeyancesince the 20th May, but be thought that it should now be reopened,especially as there was evidence to show that the United States were seriously considering taking part in the war on the side of theAllies to the extent of giving credit and supplies.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he would welcomefurther action in this matter.
Supply of aircraft.(previous references:W.M. (40) 135thConclusions,Minute 3, andW.M. (40) 126thConclusions,Minute 3.)The Lord President of the Council thought that, if such an approach were made, it would be best to take the line that we couldassume that the President was willing to help us the limiting factor being the attitude of Congress and the public but that we wished to remind him again of the form which American assistance should take, if we were to derive the maximum advantage from it.Later in the Meeting, the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs drew attention to telegram No. 867 from Washington, in which itwas suggested that there might be a number of civil aircraft inAmerica suitable for conversion into short-range night bombers,which could be purchased from their present owners or fromproducers.The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider the lines on whicha British approach should be made to the President ofthe United States of America for the release of Americandestroyers, and to advise the Prime Minister how best to proceed.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Air, in consultation withthe Minister of Aircraft Production, to examine thesuggestion in regard to the purchase of civil aircraft inAmerica suitable for conversion into short-range nightbombers.Norway.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 148thConclusions,Minute 9.)5.   The First Sea Lord read to the War Cabinet awhich had been received from Lord Cork during&apos; the night,telegramandwhich had been considered by a meeting of Ministers and Chiefs ofStaff, under the Chairmanship of the Prime Minister, at 11 p.m.A record of the discussion which took place is contained in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Conclusions.Minute 10.)Invasion of 6.   In conection with a discussion of possible methods by great Britain. which the Germans might attempt to invade this country, reference(Previous was made to an intelligence report to the effect that they were reference: preparing amphibious tanks of a super-heavy kind which could beW.M. (40) 148th landed on beaches.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs enquired whetheradequate machinery existed in the Service Departments for investigating reports of this nature, not only from the point ofview of the reliability of the information, but from the scientificpoint of view, i.e., as to the feasibility of the suggested form of operation and the need for devising counter measures.It was explained that it was the duty of the IntelligenceDivision of each of the Service Departments to draw attention tothese reports, when the matter would be immediately taken up bythe appropriate technical branch. At the request of the lord president of the Council, the First Lord of the Admiralty under -took to make enquiries as to the consideration that was being givento this particular report.The Lord President of the Council said that he was proposing to set up a scientific committee under the Home Defence Executive,and he hoped that Lord Swinton would act as Chairman of it.This would ensure that any issues of this nature affecting HomeDefence were promptly considered from the scientific point of view.
Italy.probable intentions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 148thConclusions,Minute 6.)Policy to beadopted by HisMajesty&apos;sGovernment.7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew theattention of the War Cabinet to telegram No. 747 from HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador at Rome (dated the 29th May) reporting that Signor Mussolini had left for his country seat. He would return to Rome on Saturday or Sunday and would then make animportant statement in public.He also drew attention to telegram No. 731 DIPP (dated the29th May) from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Rome setting outseveral courses open to the British Government in their relationswith Italy. This telegram defined the four major alternatives asfollows : (a) While taking all Naval and Military precautions that are open to us, to await the moment chosen by signor mussolini for war-like acts.(b) To offer concrete concessions to Italy on a scale likely to bea sufficient inducement to Signor Mussolini to breakaway from Germany. They would need to be on a verylarge scale indeed.(c) To adopt a policy of restricting supplies to Italy of rawmaterials for armaments and deficiency commodities,especially oil.(d) To demand from Signor Mussolini an explanation of hisintensive pre-mobilisation of military preparationswhich, in view of his alliance with Germany and of thefact that Italy is not threatened by the Allies, can haveno other aim than that of aggression against the Alliesor their friends in the Mediterranean.The Foreign Secretary said that our present policy was amixture of alternatives (a) and (c) and he could only assume thatwe must continue this line of action and that there could be noquestion either of an ultimatum to Italy or of substantial concessions.The War Cabinet endorsed this view.Italy.Action againstItalians in the united kingdom.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 148thConclusions,Minute 7.)8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that wehad told the French Government that we had ground for believing that if war broke out with Italy, the Italian Government would deal leniently with British subjects in Italy; and that it seemed likely that it would be fairly easy to come to an arrangement withthe Italian Government on the lines of the plan which we had inmind for sending back to Italy, Italians now in England.We had now had the French Government&apos;s reply. (TelegramNo. 311 DIPP from Paris.) They had given us a free hand andhad told us that they proposed to intern only 18,000 of the 1,850,000Italians living in France as they believed that the rest would beinoffensive. About 1,000 persons including leading bankers, &amp;c,as well as Consular staffs would be returned in the diplomatictrain.The Foreign Secretary suggested, however, that for the momentwe should take no action, provided always that the Home secretary was satisfied that he could lay his hands very rapidly on the listed&quot;desperate characters &quot; as soon as Italy committed any hostile act.The First Sea Lord reported that production of beach mineswould begin in a week&apos;s time at the rate of 10,000 a week and would rise later to a rate of 20,000 a week.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.
In the meantime His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Rome should continueto make arrangements for British subjects to leave Italy, but these arrangements should receive no publicity.The Chief of Naval Staff said that an Admiralty Officer wasconferring with the Home Office that morning as to the provisionof a ship for the repatriation of Italians.The Secretary of State for Home Affairs said that all prepara-tions had been made to round up the Italian &quot; desperate characters &quot;very rapidly as soon as the necessary instructions were given.In regard to the suggestion that it would be better to arrestthese particular Italians at once in order to safeguard aircraft factories and other important plants, he explained that action hadalready been taken to stand off all Italians employed as key men in industry and in electrical power stations, and that the Power Stationbelonging to the Volpi organisation had already been taken over bythe Electricity Commissioners.The War Cabinet-(a) Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Rome to continue making unobtrusivearrangements for British subjects to leave Italy.(b) Invited the Minister of Information to take steps to securethat no publicity should be given to these arrangements.(c) Invited the Home Secretary to keep in instant readinessthe arrangements already made for arresting at short notice the Italians in this country listed as desperatecharacters.&quot;(d) Invited the Secretary of State for Air to communicate tothe Home Secretary any special cases in which he wfshedto recommend that immediate action should be taken toavoid any risk of sabotage, &amp;c, by Italians in thiscountry.U.S.S.R.Appointment ofa british ambassador to moscow.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 146thConclusions,Minute 13.)9. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew theattention of the War Cabinet to telegram No. 249 from HisMajesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires at Moscow, reporting a Tasscommunique to the effect that the Soviet Government were unableto accept Sir Stafford Cripps or any other person in the capacityof Special Ambassador. If the British Government really wishedto conduct negotiations on trade, it could do this through a regularlyaccredited Ambassador in Moscow.The Foreign Secretary said that it was not clear how this announcement was related in time to our latest offer in regard toSir Stafford Cripps&apos;s Mission, which we had understood fromM. Maisky would meet the objections of the Soviet Government.It was possible that, as a result of pressure by the Soviet Govern-ment, we might have to agree to appoint Sir Stafford Cripps asAmbassador, and he wished to have the authority of the WarCabinet to adopt this course if we reached a position where, in hisopinion, there was no satisfactory alternative. In that event, itwould be necessary to ask Parliament to pass an Act of Indemnity(such as had been suggested if the Spanish Government had been unwilling to accept Sir Samuel Hoare as a Special Ambassador) inorder to safeguard Sir Stafford Cripps&apos;s position in regard to hisseat in Parliament.The War Cabinet agreed to leave discretion of this matter to the Foreign Secretary.
2 it10. The War Cabinet had under consideration a Report bythe Chiefs of Staff on Portugal (W.P. (40) 180).The Chief of Naval Staff introduced the report on behalf ofthe Chiefs of Staff.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that dr. Salazar&apos;s policy was undoubtedly pro-Ally; and the only danger was that he might be forced to change that policy by the pressure ofevents in Spain, if the war were to spread to the Mediterranean.Nevertheless, whilst this contingency was, he hoped, remote, it wasperfectly right that it should be faced and that all the necessarypreparatory steps to meet it should be taken.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs asked that heshould be allowed to send a summary of the report and its recom-mendations to the Dominions. The Union of South Africa wouldbe closely concerned with the proposal in paragraph 2 (c) of theReport for the capture of the Port of Beira and of the railwayleading to it through Mozambique, and he had no doubt that theUnion would be prepared to co-operate in providing the necessarymilitary forces. Similarly, the Governments of Australia and NewZealand were vitally interested in all matters involving possible action by the Japanese, and consequently would wish to be informed of the views of the Chiefs of Staff in paragraph 2 (/) of the Report.The War Cabinet then went through the recommendations inthe report seriatim and agreed as follows : Recommendation (a). To await the detailed operationalexamination which was being carried out by the Chiefs of Staffon the possibility of seizing the strategic points in the cape verde Islands and the Azores in the event of Portuguesehostility.Recommendation (b). To take note that the admiralty would take the necessary action when the time came to keepharbours in Portuguese island and colonial possessions underobservation.Recommendation (c). To invite the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs to take up with the Governments of SouthernRhodesia and the Union of South Africa the preparation of a plan for the capture of the railway from the southern rhodesian frontier to the coast of Mozambique and of the port of Beira, on the understanding that this plan would includethe provision of military forces by the Union of South africa as well as by Southern Rhodesia.Recommendation (d). To take note that it was not theintention to take any military action in regard to the railway from Northern Rhodesia through the Belgian Congo intoAngola.Recommendation (e). To invite the Secretary of State forIndia to request the Government of India to take such steps as would enable them, in the event of war with Portugal,immediately to seize Goa, Daman and Diu.Recommendation (/). To invite the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs to bring to the particular notice of theGovernments of Australia and New Zealand the recommenda-tion of the Chiefs of Staff on the possibility.of a Japanesedescent on Portuguese Timor, and to inform those Govern-ments that this recommendation had been endorsed by the WarCabinet.Recommendation (g). To take note that it would not bethe intention to carry out operations against the mainland ofPortugal.Recommendation (A)-To invite the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to take up the suggestion of setting up an[21367a] c(previous reference:W.M. (40) 123rdConclusions,Minute 11.)
Intelligence centre under the auspices of His Majesty&apos;s embassy, Lisbon.Recommendation if). To invite the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to obtain the views of His Majesty&apos;ambassador at Lisbon on the question of the possibility of organising British communities in Portugal both for intelli-gence purposes and also for combined action in the event ofcivil disturbances.The War Cabinet also authorised the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs to send a summary of the Chiefs ofStaff Report (W.P. (40) 180) to the Governments of theDominions.Agricultural 11,   The War Cabinet had before them a Note setting outWages, (a) the proposals of the Minister of Agriculture on agricultural wages and the consequential adjustment of farmers&apos; returns,together with a draft statement; (&amp;) the comments of the treasury on this proposal; and (c) an extract from the Minutes of the Meetingof the Food Policy Committee, held the previous day, at which this discussion had been considered (W.P. (40) 184).The Minister of Agriculture said that the Governments policyof obtaining increased food production could not be achieved without increasing the labour force of the farming industry, whichwas insufficient even to sustain the present rate of production,owing to losses both of young and old workers to other industries.Agriculture had been losing labour to building works (e.g., aero-dromes) in the country, and also (but to a less extent) owing to adrift to the towns. Whereas a man got about 38s. a week for workon the land, he could get up to 80s. a week for unskilled building work in the same area.He (the Minister of Agriculture) agreed with the Minister ofLabour that it would be necessary to apply compulsion to secure thenecessary number of workers on the land; but this was not practicable as long as there was so great a disparity betweenagricultural wages on the one hand, and the wages of other forms ofemployment in rural areas on the other. Before the present crisis,there was already a demand for increased wages by the farmworkers; no figure had been agreed upon, but a rate of 42s. a weekhad been in contemplation. There was general agreement that, ifthe Government wanted increased food production, they must assurereasonable prices to the farmer. Some increase in the price ofagricultural products was inevitable, not only to cover increased wages, but also to cover increased costs of production. In some casesincreased prices could be obtained from the consumers, while inother cases new or increased subsidies from the Ministry of food would be necessary.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the consideration ofthis question had been greatty embarrassed by the premature disclosure in the Daily Express on the 28th May, 1940, of a fairlyfull account of the present proposals. On the merits of the proposal,it must be realised that it would introduce a violent change into british agriculture; and, though advocated as essential during theimmediate crisis, its effects on the national economy and on agricul-ture, in particular, would be very serious. First, this proposal wasacutely inflationary; second, prices of agricultural products couldnot support wages on the level proposed, with the result that therewould need to be either a drastic readjustment disastrous to farmersor large subsidies from the Exchequer; thirdly, there was the danger that, if it were decided to subsidise these wages, the process mightspread to other industries with increasing inflationary effect.
bill the Minister of Labour said that the present proposals shouldbe judged against the background both of the general wages policywhich he was pursuing and the measures which he was taking to regulate the supply of labour. (The record of the ministers statement on these questions is contained in Minute 13 below.)Continuing, the Minister said that, as regards agricultural labour,he had arranged with the Minister of Health for the issue of a circular to local authorities, the effect of which would be to secure an interchange of labour between agricultural workers on the onehand and employees of rural local authorities (e.g., men working on the &quot;roads) on the other hand. In this way he hoped to obtain,for the main part by agreement, a substantial increase in the numberof agricultural workers, which would be of the greatest value at thepresent time, where there was urgent need for singling the sugar beet crop. This was heavy work, for which women workers werenot suitable. The men must be paid the rate of wages appropriate for the job, but it was difficult to force local authority employeesdrawing 48s. a week to work on the land for 38,?. a week. He hopedalso that it would be possible to secure the return to agriculture ofa substantial number of workers who had gone into industry, andto achieve this he proposed to instruct the Employment Exchangesthat men who had formerly been in agriculture, who reportedthemselves unemployed, should be sent back to the land. The TradeUnions had agreed to this process of &quot; regulation.&quot; He was anxious to establish a rate of wages appropriate generally for men employed in rural areas. This would not be comparable with urbanrates; and special account would need to be taken of such factors as rent. He proposed, for example, that in the case of the betterequipped rural cottages the assessment should be allowed to rise upto not more than 12-J- per cent, of the minimum wage. He believedthat such measures, adopted now, would save the Exchequersubstantial subsidies on agricultural rehousing after the war. Ifagricultural wages were raised in the manner proposed, he would feel justified in stopping the drift from the country, in introducing-interchangeability of employment in the countryside, and inordering men to return from industry to agriculture. All these measures were necessary if the Governments food production policy was to be achieved. The aircraft producer obtained his labour bypaying what wages he liked, and no doubt the farmer could havedone the same had it not been for the control imposed on the priceof his produce. Finally, he did not share the apprehensions thatworkers in other industries might demand that their wages alsoshould be subsidised. No part of the Trade Union movementclaimed advantges where these could only be secured by depressingthe standard of other workers.The Minister without Portfolio did not regard the proposed increase in agricultural wages as acutely inflationary, though itwould no doubt be so if in fact it led to a general increase in wagesand prices. He welcomed the proposals of the Minister of labour to establish an equilibrium in the wages scale for a period of eight months. From the national point of view, he thought it important that the prices of staple commodities should be stabilised at as lowa level as was practicable, since all recent wage claims had been based on the rise in the cost of living. As regards agriculture, itwould not be easy to secure the return of workers from otherindustries even at a level of 48s. a week.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that the present scheme had been worked out for the conditions obtaining in England andWales and would,require to be adjusted in various directions before it could be made applicable to Scotland. One of the questions whichwould have to be considered was whether there should be a national minimum wage in Scotland. Hitherto both farmers and farmworkers had been opposed to such a course. In view of the hirings[21367a] d
which had taken place on the 28th May, there was less need inScotland for compulsory powers to keep men on the land; theposition, therefore, in the case of Scotland was different from thatin England and Wales. In any announcement he might make, he did not propose to mention the figure of 48s., since, until discussions had taken place, he did not know what the Scottish figure wouldbe. It was essential that the steps taken to cover farmers&apos; increased costs through increases in the prices of their produce or throughsubsidies should be adequate. This applied not only to Ministry ofFood purchases, but also to purchases by the Ministry of Supply,e.g., wool. The prices paid for agricultural produce of all kindsmust be sufficient to cover the whole range of the farmers&apos; activity.It should be realised that even to-day existing prices were not sufficient for this purpose.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he hadbeen greatly impressed by the general policy outlined by the Ministerof Labour; if this could be achieved, a great contribution to the life of the post-war countryside would have been secured. Thepresent scheme provided, so far as the farmers were concerned, forthe increased wages and costs to be covered by increased prices; butthere were many rural workers employed by landlords, whose wages would be affected by the changes proposed; the present scheme made no provision for enabling landowners to pay such higher wages.He had at first thought that in the present crisis it might be possiblefor the Government to apply compulsion ruthlessly, and without regard to the wages structure; but if the Minister of Labour con-sidered that this was impracticable, he was prepared to accept his view.The Minister of Labour said that there were definite limits tothe use of compulsory powers. It was surprising, indeed, to seethe way in which workers had accepted compulsion. The minershad agreed to men being prevented from leaving the mines, to men being compelled to return to the mines, and to the institution of widespread training schemes for new entrants. In general, he believed that he. possessed the goodwill of 80 per cent, of the TradeUnions; but this was only because in various directions he was trying to remove the sense of grievance. As regards wages, if he could not secure his ends by agreement, he would have resource to compulsory arbitration.The Lord President of the Council said that a difficult,responsible, and overwhelmingly important task had been imposed on the Minister of Labour, when he had been given the duty of ensuring adequate supplies of man-power for our war effort. Thosedifficulties might well be insuperable, if the gap between agricultureand industrial wages were too wide. He had. been greatly impressed by the Minister of Labour&apos;s statement regarding the steps whichhe was taking to introduce an orderly system for the regulation ofwa^es in time of war. He felt sure that the correct course was to stabilise wages so far as possible. Personally, he was prepared tosupport the present proposals made in regard to agricultural wages.The Lord President of the Council appealed to his colleagues to do all in their power to prevent the recurrence of leakages inthe press such as had occurred on the present occasion.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in the circumstances he was prepared to withdraw his objection to the plan submitted.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries said that animportant part of the plan was that the prices of agricultural produce should be fixed at a level sufficient to cover all the farmers&apos;increased costs of production. In particular, the prices of thisyear&apos;s crop would need to be adjusted, since otherwise the farmers would be unable to carry on until the next crop.
Railwaymen&apos;s 12.   In the course of the discussion on agricultural wagesWages. recorded in Minute 11 above, the Chancellor of the Exchequer saidthat the Minister of Transport had reported further wages demandsby the railwaymen amounting in the case of certain classes to 3s. aweek.The Minister of Labour said that, long before the grant byParliament of the recent Emergency Powers, the claim for a furtherwages increase had been put forward by the railwaymen. Negotia-tions on this claim, which was in no way connected with agricultural wages, had broken down a fortnight previously. In general, wageshad risen on account of the war by from 6s. to 8s. a week. The minershad obtained an increase of 6s. hd. and the railwaymen so far had obtained 4s. He had been asked to discuss the matter informallywith the Trades Unions, and he had advised them to settle. Theyhad been asking for 10s. on top of the 4s. already obtained. If,therefore, they now obtained 3s. their total increase since the war would be about 7s. The leaders had promised to use their influence to keep the prospective rise as small as possible.At the conclusion of the discussion on agricultural wages, theChancellor of the Exchequer asked whether the decision reachedimplied that he should agree to the additional 3s. a week asked forby the railwaymen.The Lord President of the Council thought that this matter should be left to be decided by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.This was agreed to.General Wages 13.   In the course of the discussion recorded in Minute 11Policy. above, the Minister of Labour explained that as regards the general(Previous wages problem, he had asked the Trade Union Council and the reference: Employers&apos; Confederation to dispose of all claims for wagesW.M. (40) 23rd advances which had been tabled or were pending on the 22nd May,Conclusions, the date of the grant by Parliament of the present EmergencyMinute l.) Powers, in such a way as to secure some measure of uniformity. Hehad asked them also not to relate the advance strictly to the cost ofliving index number, since, owing to enemy action, it might happenthat a scarcity of some particular item might cause an increase inthe index of a kind which would not justify an increase in wages.As regards the future, he felt that if agreement could be reached forthe period up to next March, we should have tided over the worst of our difficulties. He had, therefore, proposed that for the nexteight months, all normal wage applications should be suspendedand that a body should be set up under an independent Chairman,which at four-monthly intervals (i.e., at the end of October 1940and February 1941) would review the position, and report whethera general wages advance was justified.In considering the question of wages advances, it should berealised that large sums would be saved to the Exchequer throughThe Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would discuss this aspect of the question with the Minister of Agriculture.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed to authorise the Minister of Agriculture to makea statement on the subject of agricultural wages and the consequential adjustment of farmers&apos; returns in theterms set out in enclosure to Annex I of W.P. (40) 184.(2) Took note that the statement referred to above was appro-priate only to conditions in England and Wales, and thatadjustments would need to be made before a statement could be made in regard to Scotland.
the measures which he was taking to regulate the supply of, say,labour. He hoped by putting a stop to advertising and by checkingpoaching to restore order in the wages structure. His plans foremploying labour so far as possible in its own region would alsosave substantial sums of money on billeting, travelling, and onallowances paid to induce men to transfer from one district toanother. The Government had imposed upon him the duty ofissuing orders for the regulation of labour, but these orders wouldnot be effective unless he could give to the workers a conviction thatthey were being fairly treated in the matter of wages.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The western front (eon-tinued).Withdrawal ofthe B.E.F.14. The Secretary of State for War reported that he had spoken again to Lord Gort on the telephone. Lord Gort had been to Dunkirk, where he had seen the French Admiral and general blanchard, and had urged the latter to leave with him. general blanchard had not been very responsive, and Lord Gort gathered that General Weygand had given him no orders.The Secretary of State for War said that he had been speaking to the Prime Minister (in Paris) on the telephone, and had suggestedthat the Prime Minister should propose to General Weygand that orders should be given to General Blanchard to leave with Lord Gort.Lord Gort had reported that 6,000 French had been embarkedin the last few hours. The French were very short of food, andit would be a great help if we could provide some. arrangements to this end had been made.Continuing, the Secretary of State said that he had toldLord Gort that a boat would leave Dover at 4 o&apos;clock and wouldbe ready to take him off about 6 that evening. He had givenLord Gort clearly to understand that he should not delay his departure any longer. Lord Gort had decided to entrust the command, when he left, to General Alexander.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,May 31, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
