<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/1/0 images: 3-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property-of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Governing,]sx        Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence:  January 1915.SECRET. G-l.                                                     K\COMMITTEE  OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.THE  WAR.Memorandum by Sir John French, January 3,  1915.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,           January 3, 1915.
SECRET.MEMORANDUM BY SIR JOHN FRENCH,            JANUARY 3, 1915.    TELEGRAM No. 2632 of the 2nd instant, containingthe remarks of the First Lord of the Admiralty  uponthe loss of the battleship &quot; Formidable,&quot; raises  in  acuteform the consideration of a problem which I have beenearnestly  studying for some  weeks.    Only the numerical weakness of the army under mycommand, the great scarcity of  artillery  ammunition,and the want of a sufficient force  of up-to-date, heavyartillery has prevented me putting forward  those viewsbefore.    It will tend to a better understanding of the situation,if I state brieiiy what  I conceive to be  at the presentmoment the relative strengths of the opposing forces oneither side of the European Theatre of War.    The  conclusions  arrived at  by  my IntelligenceDepartment throughout the  war have turned out to beexceptionally accurate.  Those regarding  the  Westernand Eastern Theatres respectively are attached as anappendix to this memorandum.    In the Western Theatre  they show a  superiority infavour of the Allies over the German forces cf 1,172guns, 500,000 effective rifles,  and  65  regiments  ofcavalry.    In  the Eastern  Theatre it is  estimated that theRussians  had, about  the 10th  December,  2,200 guns,30,000 effective rifles, 18 regiments of cavalry, and 500squadrons of  Cossacks over and above  the combinedforces of the Germans and Austrians.   The losses  since  suffered  by the enemy  in  thattheatre, following upon their  numerous  unsuccessfulattacks during the last two  or three weeks of the year,must have modified this comparison largely in favour ofthe Russians,  whilst it is well known that  at least  amillion  trained Russian troops are lying close behindtheir fighting line, ready to reinforce it as soon as armsand ammunition are available.   I come now to the consideration of Germany&apos;s furthermilitary resources up to the 1st January, 1916.   Her  resources in personnel at the beginning of thewar consisted approximately  of      Trained men (21 to 45)      ..     ..     4,800,000     Untrained men (17 to 45)     ..     ..     5,000,000Total9,800,000Deduct for men employed in mines, fac-  tories of munitions of war, dockyards, &amp;c.1,00.0,0008,800,000[138]B
    Germany appears to have mobilised -      79 ccp-ps and 11 cavalry divisions      -.    3,600,000      Add for L. of C., say......     200,000              Total field army and L. of 0...    3,800,000      Casualties have amounted  to  at  leapt       1,500,000.  To replace this number in       part there have been taken, say     ..    1,000,000            Making total absorbed in ranks of    4,800,000    It seems probable that all the trained men have beenabsorbed, and  that Germany&apos;s  reserve  now consists of4,000,000  men,  none  of  whom  were  trained  at thecommencement of the war.    In the  middle  of October  the  1914  class,  lessvolunteers and men called out in August say, 500,000men entered the depots, where possibly 300,000 moremen,  Ersatz reservists, were  training, making a total of800,000 men under training at one time.   This wouldseem  to be the limit that can be  trained in Germany atone time.    -     .  &apos;  This  would  provide  for  a possible  six  new  corpsunder training, as well as for the wastage of war.  Thefirst six  new corps are not likely to be . ready beforeMarch or April,  to be followed by six  more corps sixmonths later. :  - ..    These, reinforcements will  require  officers,  staffs,artillery,, transport, and  many other requisites.  Thereis &quot;also the question of ammunition.     &apos;..&apos;-               -  &apos;.&apos;  From this brief numerical appreciation of the situa-tion&quot;.. it. will be seen  that,  although -: the  threateningattitude of. Russia  in the East will probably prevent theGermans  from, withdrawing any of their1 troops from.&apos;that theatre, the progress made  in. the training of newformations throughout the present  year  may enable the.enemy to so far  reinforce and supplement their troops-here as to wipe out their  existing  inferiority, and evenonce  again  make - themselves  superior  to us&apos;. - As the &apos;training of these new formations has in part been going ,on  since last October, the process of gradual reinforce--&apos;ment  on &apos; this  side  may probably, begin in  March orApril.         &quot;.  &apos; &apos;  -  -  &apos;  &apos;  .    - -&apos;. -  ----- .  . .-&apos;  -  It seems, therefore, of the utmost importance that weshould  take the  offensive  and  strike  at the  earliest,possible moment with all our available strength.- -&apos;- .&apos; -. .&apos;-&apos;  -    General Joffre told  me, in  a conference I had withhim at Chantilly on the 27th December, that this wasentirely his  view  ; and,  further,  that  he  was  givingpractical effect to that view by massing as  many troopsas he could make available at two different points in theallied line which offered the best chance of strikingmost  effectively at the enemy&apos;s communications.    The Cominander-in-Chief requested  me to do all inmy power to assist him by relieving the French forcesemployed to the north of the line I hold as  quickly ascircumstances would allow and troops became available,so  that he might make himself as strong as possible atthe decisive points of attack.    In the same interview General Joffre  expressed him-self as willing to acquiesce in the-desire  put forward bythe British Government that the  British.and  Belgiantroops should work together on  the northern flank ofthe French and  in  touch  with  the British fleet.   Itherefore conceived a plan of amalgamating the British
and Belgian forces in such a manner  as  would enableme to effect the relief desired by General  Joffre withinthe next two or  three  weeks.   I placed my proposalsbefore  His Majesty the  King  of the Belgians;  but,after consultation  with his Government, His  Majestyfinds himself unable to fall  in with  this plan, whichnecessarily involves a  considerable  dislocation of hisarmy.    His Majesty was, however,  good enough to assureme of his cordial and energetic  co-operation, and I havereason to hope that he  will be  able to place a consider-able force of artillery at my disposal if necessary.    Had my  proposed  plans been  acceptable  to theBelgians 1 think it would  have  been possible for me tohave organized a sufficient force with which, in conjunc-tion with the  Fleet, to have effected  the  capture ofOstend  and  Zeebrugge and relieve  the Navy of thesubmarine anxieties and threats mentioned by the FirstLord in the telegram referred to above.    In order to attain the  double objective (i) of reliev-ing the French troops and thus strengthening the alliedforces at the decisive  points, and (ii) of undertaking avigorous offensive to effect the  capture of Ostend andZeebrugge, it is absolute^ necessary that I should havemore troops, a  liberal supply of artillery ammunition ofall kinds, but especially high  explosive, and a sufficientnumber of heavy guns.    I have been constantly told that the ammunition and .the guns will be available by the middle of this month, and if this is actually so there will be nothing,  so far asthese requirements are  concerned, to hinder the progressof the operations I have outlined.         . .&apos;    As regards troops, however,  I should require at leastfifty battalions of Territorials or the &quot; New &quot;Army, andas many more as could  be made available in the time.&apos;    In making these calculations I am taking into accountthe probable arrival of the  Canadian troops  and the 29th Division  towards  the end of this month, and theother contingents which I have been  told will  be sentbetween now and the 1st April.    This general statement of the situation,- as it  presents --itself .to  n\y understanding, necessarily&apos;involves&apos; some&apos;:: consideration of  the organization which it&apos; is&apos;intended, to -adopt for the  various units  and forces which  are no\\runder training all over the United  Kingdom,  and aredestined  to reinforce the  British Army in the  field atvarious intervals of time throughout the current year.    The experience I have gained during this war leadsme to  a  very  decided  conclusion that it would not beadvisable  to organize  troops so raised and so  trained,and having  only such officers and staff as are available,in any higher  units than  brigades ;  at any rate  untilsome time after they have joined the forces in the fieldand gained considerable experience.  I will go further,and say that a  large proportion of these troops would bemost usefully employed in battalions.    I feel quite sure that to put an army, corps or even adivision,  composed  of  these troops and  organized inthe manner  proposed,  straight into the  field undercommanders and staff  who are inexperienced in up-to-date  European warfare might easily become a  positivedanger.    In expressing this view I am only placing on record .the opinions  which  the experience of the  past five
months! fighting has  caused me to form, and I knowthey are held strongly by  the  principal commanderswho have served under me throughout that time.   It follows from what I have said that the formationof armies  would, in my opinion,  be  attended  by evengreater danger.   I am strongly  of  opinion that an organization  inthree armies will fully suffice for the largest number ofmen which can become available for some considerabletime ; and I recommend strongly that some organizationfor the new forces be adopted which will admit of thembecoming  gradually accustomed to what is  required c.them in war by enabling them to light side by side witn.troops who have had experience  of it and from whomthey can learn and glean confidence.   Coming  to the  detailed  arrangements which mightbe made to give effect to the opinions I have  expressed,I will deal first with the Territorial Forces.  1 am notsure as to  the exact number of battalions which have sofar left the country, but I  believe  I am near the markin supposing that at least 105 still remain at the disposalof the Secretary of  State for War.   If 50  of these were.sent to me at once, 55 battalions  would still  remain for-purposes of home defence.   My  experience of  such  battalions as  have already-joined the Forces under my command leads me to feelconfident that by trsing  tins suggested reinforcement inthe same way I should be  in a much better position.tocarry out the objectives laid clown in a previous paragraphof this memorandum.    As no  official information has ever reached me as tothe  organization, numbers,  or  composition  of  what isknown  as the &quot;New&quot; Army,  I  am  in comparativeignorance as to how that Army  actually stands to-day  ;but  from  what 1 have been told,  1 believe  that a verylarge number of excellent men have been under trainingat   Aklershot, Salisbury,  and  other  military  centres,and have  now  attained  a  considerable  standard  ofefficiency.    It would seem  that many brigades formed  in thisway are now, or shortly will be, sufficiently trained to lake their places  in the field at  once  if amalgamated with units otherwise composed  of troops with  tried experience in war.    Judging from my experience of the present war,  I see  no  reason why any bad  results would follow the extension  of  existing organizations.   I  know nothing to prevent the addition of  a brigade to every existing division in the field or of a division to an army corps, or the  extension in  the number of  army  corps  which compose an army.     The methods which I have advocated  in this memo- randum of  using all  the troops  which are being trained now and prepared to  reinforce the Field  Army have the double advantage of utilising the troops immediately they become available, and allowing them when they reach the  fighting line to benefit by the accumulated experience acquired during the war by the organizations and staffs.with which they will then be associated.     It may be said  that the extension of the Army in the field by large numbers of infantry, without a correspond- ing increase in the  artillery, will adversely affect  the military homogeneity of the forces in the  field.     In reply I will refer once more to the negotiations I
am  carrying  on with His Majesty  the  King of  theBelgians under  sanction of  the French Commander-in-Chief.  As I have hinted in a former paragraph, I feelsure I can rely upon the loan of at least 150 to 200 gunswhenever I may require them.  As regards ammunition,my  conference with General Joffre  assures me that Ican rely on considerable  help from the French if, by theadoption  of these suggestions, my plans can be carriedthrough a  help in this respect which I have  reason toknow they are well able to afford.   Again I write  without  any  official  or reliableinformation as regards the  new forces  in preparation,but I believe, later  on considerable  artillery  reinforce-ihents will be available in our own country.rissG
APPENDIX.COMPARATIVE Strength English, French, and German Forces in France and Flanders,                                     December 29, 1914.	Guns.*	Establishment Rifles.	Effectives Rifles.	Cavalry Regiments, other than -Divisional Cavalry.English French Total, Allies.. German .. Difference in favour of the Allies	924 5,100	165,000 1,044,000	156,000 . 1,044,000 &apos; -	... 43 40 - -	6,024 4,852	1,209,000 1.105,000	1,200,000 . . . 700,000	83. .13f.	1,172	104,000	500,000	65* There is no definite information regarding the guns of Von Falkenhausen&apos;s group.I Not on the front, but possibly in Belgium.                                             NOTES.    1.  It is assumed that  the  French effectives in rifles are approximately equal to establishment, and theEnglish slightly below establishment.  In the case of the Germans, the effectives of  the ^th, 6th, and 2ndarmies  are  based on  prisoners&apos; statements, but they are always changing.   The effectives of the otherGerman armies are taken to be two-thirds of establishments.    2.  It is assumed that French and  German  effectives  in guns are  equal to establishment.:&apos;. This iscertainly  incorrect, as the  French have brought up  large numbers of naval and fortress guns, and  theGermans have large numbers of  heavy guns in excess  of establishment. &apos;       . &apos;.&apos;                . V    3.  TheMJelgian army has  been omitted altogether from this table.             &apos; .  -COMPARATIVE Strength  of Russian,  German,  and  Austrian  Armies  in East  Prussia,                         Poland,  and Galicia, December 29, 1914. /.-	Guns.	Establish -ment Rifles.	Effectives Rifles.*	Cavalry Regi-ments, other than Divisional Cavalry.	. Cossacks and. other Reserve Squadrons, fRussians Germans Austrians.. Total, Enemy Difference in favour of Russia	6,000 2,186 1,614	1,400.000 576,000 780,000	900.000 350,000 520,000	65 48 35	600 100	3,800	1,356,000	870,000	83	100	2,200	44,000	30,000	18	500    * Two-thirds of establishment: a purely arbitrary number, but may serve for comparison.    \ European Cossacks  only:  there  939  squadrons  in all.  Austrian squadrons are reserve  units ofvarious kinds.    NOTE. This table must not be taken as an accurate statement of the  respective forces.  It is probably^approximately correct in the case of the Germans, a rough approximation in the case of The Russians, and amere  guess in the case of the  Austrians.  It assumes 100 Russian divisions in this theatre, that the warstrength  of the Austrian  army is sixty-one  divisions, as stated on p. 13,  &quot;Notes on Austrian Army, 1914,&quot;and that of this strength  one-fifth is employed against Servia and four-fifths against Russia, also that theAustrian troops on the Roumanian and Italian frontiers are Landsturm and depot formations not forming partof the field army.
EXPANSION  OF THE BRITISH ARMY IN THE FIELD.    1. The following proposals are based on the assump-tion that the &quot; First New Army&quot; will become availableto reinforce the British Army in the field in the coarseof the spring or early summer of this year.    2. The experience already gained during the war hasproved  that whole units or even formations may have tobe  temporarily  withdrawn from  the  front  to  rest  andrefit on account of the heavy casualties and exhaustioncaused solely by fighting.   During  the next few monthsthis process of attrition will be aggravated by sicknessdue to the severe  climatic conditions.  &apos; 3. It is therefore  desirable that all formations, frombrigades  upwards,  should be reinforced  in  excess oftheir normal establishments  . in  order to  provide  amargin  by which  their  commanders   can  organizeadequate reliefs and  so maintain efficiency.   This maybe  done as follows: Infantry Absorbing-   (ct.) Complete every  infantry  brigade  to         5 battalions     ..      ..      ..    17 battalions.   (b.) Add 1 infantry brigade (4 battalions) to         each division   ..      ..      ..    48    ,,   (c.) Add 1 battalion as corps  troops to each         corps, including cavalry corps     ..     7    ,,                 Total ..      ..      ..    72    ,,   Artillery                                   -   Unless  an adequate  supply of ammunition can beensured, it is  useless to  add  to the number of guns inthe field.   This question has  been discussed on anotherpaper, and the following proposals are  based on  theassumption that the required  amount is forthcoming :-                                         Absorbing  .   (a.) Add 3 18-pr. brigades  to each corps         organized as corps artillery       ..    18 brigades   (6.) Complete G divisions now with the force         with their brigade of 4&apos;5-in. howitzers     6    ,,   (c.) Complete G divisions  now with force         with their 6U-pr. battery  ..      ..     6 batteries.   Royal Engineers                                           Absorbing    Add 1 field company to each division    ..   12 field companies.   Signal Service, Medical, and A.S.G. Units of the NewArmy should be distributed to expand the establishmentoL; their  respective units in proportion to the increasedsize of brigades and divisions.   4. The above proposals will absorb the whole of  the&quot; First New Army.&quot;  The British Army in the field willthen consist of the cavalry corps, Indian cavalry corps,and two  armies each of three corps of  two divisions offour infantry brigades.   5. As soon as  the  &quot; Second New Army &quot;  becomesavailable for service  abroad further reorganization willbe necessary.  The most convenient plan would  be toform three armies  each of three corps  of two divisions.Each army would thus have two divisions of the SecondNew Army to absorb.
   It Is proposed that this should  be carried  out  byregrouping  brigades and divisions  in the corps andarmy.   6. This makes provision for  the Second New Army.Further large reinforcements would  be dealt with in asimilar  manner, in  accordance  with  the conditionsobtaining at the time.POINTED AT THE FOHEIG5 OITICE BY C* B. HAEE1SOS.-11/1/1915.

</content>
</cab>
