<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/1/0 images: 23-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence. February 1915.SECRET.G.-4.COMMITTEE  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.THE WAR.After Six Months.An Appreciation by Lord Esher.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,           January 29, 1915.
AFTER  SIX MONTHS  OF  WAR.AN APPRECIATION BY LORD ESHER.    AFTER six months of fighting, the military initiative still remains with Germany,and, in all parts of the world,  except the.Far East, the Allies have been forced  tostand upon the defensive.    The  German  objective  has been clearly  shown  to aim, both  by  her  militarywriters and her strategy, at establishing German domination  over a  belt of  territoryextending from the northern  coasts of France and Belgium up to the Persian Gulf.    Although, according to Napoleon, the whole art of war consists in a well-reasonedand strictly judicious defensive,  he added that this should, in all cases,- be followed byaudacious and rapid attack.  So far, except in  sporadic instances, this has been foundimpossible, with the result of what appears to be a deadlock both in the Western andEastern theatres  of war.   This  deadlock may  partly be occasioned by severe winterconditions, but, on  the other hand, it may be caused by  the physical and  materialconditions of  modern war, that appear to tend rather in  the direction of  siege than offree manoeuvre.    Under these circumstances,  it becomes important  to survey the whole theatre ofactual and potential conflict,  so as to endeavour to ascertain the moral factors at workamong the  peoples engaged in strife,  as well as among the neutral nations  moredirectly affected, and thus to endeavour to determine the probable course of events.                                   Germany.    The  aims and achievements of  Germany have  already  been  referred to,  andalthough  it may safely be  assumed that the German Armies  have not succeeded  ineffecting  all  that  was  hoped  for  by  German statesmen,   they have  neverthelessaccomplished a great deal.  They have conquered  Belgium, and they have establishedstrong defensive positions in Antwerp and  along the  coast as far as Ostend.   Theyhave erected powerful barriers against the advance of the Allies from the sea coast  tqthe frontiers of Switzerland.   They have prevented the Russian Armies from breakingthrough into Silesia, a territory  vital to Germany, and  they have checked the Russianinroad into East Prussia and the  plains of Hungary.   Under German influence theTurks  have occupied the second city of Persia,  and the Dardanelles  have  been closed.to the merchant  traffic of  the Allies.  Although Germany  has failed to seize theFrench capital, and although Austria has been unable to establish herself in Belgradeor to maintain the integrity of Galicia, it  cannot  be  claimed that, on balance, theadvantage of the  war, so far as it  has been fought, is  on the side of the Allies.Germany has undoubtedly experienced  severe losses outside the main theatre of  war.Her possessions in the Far  East and her numerous Colonies have  fallen, a prey  toJapan and Great Britain.  Her  mercantile  marine  has been swept  from the seas, andher armies have been  depleted by stupendous losses.  She can,  however, never seriouslyhave expected to fight under any other  conditions.  German military theories of  war,resting^ mainly upon  &quot;rapid and audacious attack,&quot; were  bound to lead to a vastexpenditure of human life.  The quarrel with  England  necessarily meant to her theclosing  of the  open seas and the  disappearance  of the   German flag from hercolonial  possessions.   Long  ago  her soldiers and  statesmen must have  counted,at  any  rate,  upon  blows  of  this  kind,   which  they  have  probably  assumedwould only be temporary until  a victory won in  the main theatre of  war wouldenable them to  regain their lost possessions.   The  attrition of  German manhoodfrom  losses  in  battle,  of  German  wealth  by  English  sea&quot; command,  of  the       [238]                                                              B.
                                        2material of war by  lack  of  imports, of raw material,  are grave considerations ina war prolonged over a period of years ;  but their immediate and vital effect in a warof moderate duration is extremely difficult to estimate.    The Allies naturally  exaggerate  the effect  of  these  extraneous causes whenattempting to form an opinion as to the final result of this  great  struggle, while theGermans, on the  other hand, probably  minimise them.  From  the  purely militarystandpoint it is desirable to ignore them and to assume that if Germany is to be beaten,she must be defeated in battle  by military  forces that  have decisively assumed themastery over hers.    Looking solely to what Germany has accomplished after six months  of war, itcannot be denied that, acting on interior lines, she has established for herself a strongdefensive position in territories beyond her borders, and that when spring comes theresult of the campaign will turn upon whether she is able,  in the words of Napoleon,to follow this up by &quot; audacious and  rapid attacks &quot; which will leave her victorious inthe field.                                      Austria.    The position of Austria is complicated by her ever-present racial problem.   Herarmies are not homogeneous, and her military power is weakened by conditions overwhich her rulers have no  control.   In the past Austria has constantly  failed as afighting  power.  Her failure, therefore, to-day is no new  thing.   In the Napoleonicwars she was beaten over and over again.   By the joint forces of France and Italy shewas defeated at Magenta and Solferino.   She  was crushed by Prussia after  a six weeks&apos;campaign in 1866.  Yet in spite of all these failures Austria has remained a  greatPower, thanks to her central strategical position in Europe, her natural wealth, and thepride of her aristocracy.   To count  upon the defection of Austria  as a fatal weaknessto Germany might easily lead to  a grave miscalculation of the chances of  the presentwar.  Her armies, though frequently beaten,  appear to have recuperative  power, andher natural resources are so elastic that internal disagreements and the ever-presentconflict between the German and Hungarian  temperament should not be considered afactor of too great  importance  in  estimating  the military value of Austria to her ally.Whatever amount of  friction there may be between the Hungarian oligarchy and otherportions  of  the Austrian Empire, it  must always be remembered  that the antipathybetween Hungarian and Slav is far more  acute than that between the Hungarian andGerman.  It may happen  that Hungarian sentiment will, from time to time, induceAustria to  consider  the  question of a  separate  peace, but  so long as the EmperorFrancis Joseph lives it is unlikely that Austria will secede from the Alliance.                                    Turkey.    The great value of Turkey to  Germany is to demobilise in  the central areaof conflict considerable forces of  Russian and  British troops, to rouse a certain amountof friction in the Mahommedan world, and possibly, if the war continues, to provideGermany with raw material which she cannot  obtain elsewhere.    Turkish troops, too, are not  an  entirely  negligible factor, although they are notof the quality which distinguished  them  forty years  ago in the Shipka  Pass.  Theintervention of  Turkey in the war  has already had and will  continue  to  have aninfluence upon the attitude of the Balkan Bloc, and unless a  blow can be deliveredwith effect at the direct communications between east and west, Turkey might becomea.very grave factor  in this  war, should Servia on the one  hand be crushed  by aGerman army,  or should the attitude  of the Balkan  States become less  friendly tothe Allies.                                    France.    After six months of  war, the position in France  appears to  be the  following;France was  not as well prepared in August  last as the highest military opinion inthis country considered her to  be.  The Committee  of  Imperial  Defence had  beentold over and  over again  by the  General Staff that France was so ready for war andthat her armies were so admirably  commanded, trained, and provided,  that therecould be no question of an immediate invasion on  a  large scale of French territory,and, furthermore, that if the assistance of Great Britain was immediately forthcoming^
&quot;France conld not be  invaded  at all.   It cannot  be  questioned  that  the highestmilitary authorities in this country believed that the result  of  the  first  battles ofthe war would be highly favourable to a  Franco-British  force, whether the attackwas  made through  Alsace and Lorraine, or whether  the  first  battles  took placeupon  a  front  between  Namur and  the  Vosges.    The  rapid  advance of  theGerman Armies  and  the retreat of  the  Franco-British  force came therefore as asurprise.  How far France was unprepared, how far the strategy of the French GeneralStaff was at fault, what were the causes that led to Von Kluck&apos;s manoeuvres during theadvance on Paris, why the German Armies did not  occupy  Calais  in the month ofSeptember, are all matters which now  can only have an  historic  interest.  . Thesituation to-day appears to be this-that from Antwerp and Ostend to the frontiers ofSwitzerland a deadlock has been established, and that within  different  sectors of thislong line army corps and divisions of the opposing forces are face to  face  in trenchesso strongly protected that the war has degenerated into a state of siege  on both  sides.The moral factors in this condition of things are of importance.  It remains to be seenwhether, as many French officers believe,  troops subjected for a long period to warfareof this kind degenerate and become incapable of  active operations.*   But the graveraspect of the situation is  the  effect of a prolonged and static  war upon the moral ofthe French civilian population and of French politicians.  No one who  has been muchin France can fail to become aware of  the gradual weakening  of  French  sentimentabout Belgium, and the growing indifference of the French  middle classes to the fateof the Belgian people.  These sentiments are not confined to civilians, but. to someextent have  already permeated  the  leaders of  the  French  armies and the Frenchsoldiery, f  Constantly it  is said that  the Belgians have chosen in  the past to liveluxuriously, and  have conspicuously failed to prepare  themselves to defend theirliberties and  their country.   Credit is  given  them  for the fight they made,  butmore  grudgingly than  was  the  case a  few months  ago.    The  logical  Frenchmind, looking very straight at actualities and inclined always to accept accomplishedfacts, is a strategical element of considerable  importance,  when, in view of  thechances  of  its long continuance, the future of  this war is being  considered.  Itis difficult for anyone who has not moved among the peasantry of  the districts thathave felt the severe pressure of the war, and still more among the people inhabitingthe southern provinces where the pressure of war has not been felt at all, to realisethe vital importance of obtaining  a decision at the earliest possible moment.^  TheFrench military leaders are keenly alive  to the danger of any great prolongation ofthe war.  &quot; Pourvu  que  les civils tiennent&quot; is a phrase you hear constantly on thelips of soldiers.    The French middle and lower classes, laborious and  thrifty, are beginning to berestive at the conditions under which  they are living.   If their economies are to befurther depleted by the failure of  Russia  to pay her debts to France there will followfurther diminution of patriotic  fervour.   From  every family death  has taken a toll,and death and povertv are damping her enthusiasm.    The universal instinct, therefore, of  soldier and  civilian appears to be that it isessential to bring about a rapid decision.  The urgent enquiries  about the forcesavailable, or likely to be  soon available, in England are largely the outcome of a. moralweakness, which has become apparent among many sections of the French people.  Itmust never be forgotten that the French Armies are at their maximum strength.  Theircadres can be replenished by drafts, and their losses in  battle made good.-  But in thehighest quarters it is admitted that there  are no  reserves of troops that can be trustedto hold their own as large fighting units, and  that no fresh armies  can be formed orofficered.   These are basic facts of the situation in France.                       .:     The deficiencies in war material, partly the result of faulty preparation, partly theresult of enormous and unforeseen expenditure  of ammunition^, &amp;c,  have now beenmade good.   The output of shells is now thought to be sufficient to meet the demandsof any attacks by the German Armies, or by an advance following a successful attemptto break through the German lines.     The French Generals, however, and especially the  younger ones, are keenly aliveto the conditions of modern war so novel to them and so foreign to their habits and    * Many French officers have told me that they view with misgiving  the  manner in which their  menhave accommodated  themselves to trench life,  so foreign to their previous notions and  to the Frenchtemperament.    t A very distinguished French general used this language.    *i    people livn&apos;S&apos;m    actual rears of the trenches are far keener and more determined upon revengethan those at a greater distance.  South of Orleans interest in the war slackens conspicuously.    5 In the battle of the Aisne, along the whole front, 180,000 shells were fired off per day.       [238]                                                          &quot;     C
while confident in their ability to resist attack, even at the odds of five to one, they arenot so sanguine of being able to break through the barriers that have been erected bythe Germans along their immense front.     The main interest of average Frenchmen, whether soldiers or civilians, is to freeFrench soil from the invader and to recover their lost provinces.   Should they see theirway clear at any moment to achieve these objects, the temptation cannot  fail to bestrong and resistance to it hard.   They cannot be blamed when their  sufferings  andlosses are remembered.  That they will be loyal to their Allies may be assumed, but astate of things might  arise in which the heart  of France would no longer be in thefight.                                     Russia.     Up to the present time Russia has failed to make good  the  expectations of herAllies.  This  is  no  reflection upon her good  will  or her fighting powers.  It isonce more the  result  of inadequate  preparations   for  war.    It was anticipatedwhen war broke out that before this date the Russian armies would be well withinthe  boundaries  of the German Empire.  They  have been  held . up by the  lack  ofwar material as well as by the remarkable fighting powers of the German troops, andthe  skilful  leadership of Von. Hindenburg.  Again time is an important  element inattempting to estimate the chances of the future.  France and England, containing theGerman armies on the Western Frontier, have looked to Russia for the main attack.  Sofar the Allies have been disappointed, and there  are  symptoms of a  deadlock on theEastern Frontier similar to that which prevails in the west.     A serious  factor in  the problem is the psychology of  Russia as a Great Power.Over and over again in the past she has proved to be inconsequent.  In the Napoleonicwars her attitude constantly varied.  The Peace of Paris in 1856  came  upon  Europewith some surprise, as no one could maintain that Russia had been exhausted  by theattack upon the Crimean Peninsula.  Twenty years later, when the victorious Russianarmies were at  the  gates of  Constantinople, she failed in  spite of the Treaty of St.&apos; Stephano to push home her victories.   Can anyone imagine Great Britain or Germanyflinching at such a moment ?  Can it be supposed for an instant that, placed as Russiathen was, England or Germany would have failed to occupy Constantinople, in spite ofany external threats.      The end of the Japanese war is another case  in point.    After stupendous efforts,&apos;and just as the forces of Japan were weakening, Russia agreed to a peace through themediation of the United  States.  These  curious  and  inconsequential acts  have beenattributed hy some to the character and action of the Russian Czars, but the mysticismand irresolution of Alexander were intensely Russian and are inherent in the House ofRomanof and in the  heart of every Russian.                                      *      These are  circumstances  that cannot be ignored in any attempt to estimate andsurvey the forces arrayed against each other at the present  time.   No one doubts theloyalty and good intentions of Russia at the present moment, but the Russian character and the Russian temperament are factors that cannot well be left out of account.                                      Japan.      The action  of the Japanese is necessarily limited to the Far East. It is known that J apan is disinclined to take  an active part in the European  theatre of war.  If she could be tempted to do so, it would only be at the invitation  of Russia, and this invitation is  not likely to be forthcoming. : In what degree  her activities  in the European field would be acceptable to the United States and the  British  dominions oversea is a question which would require  careful handling before her armies were invited to take a share in the investment of Germany.  The heaviest blow delivered at German world-power has been at the  hands of Japan by the capture of Kiaochow, and, although her sphere of action has been limited, it has provided the Allies with a prize that, in the eyes of Germany, is the greatest  that has been won from her since the war began.                                     England.      The  main functions which  this  country has performed  in the cause of  the Allies has been to contain  the German Fleet, and although to confine the enemy s main fleet is not necessarily to command the seas, the Admiralty in the present case, and under
-the peculiar  conditions  dependent upon the  German coast-line, has succeeded incombining both operations.                                          .   .    Secondly, British  sea  power has  maintained intact  the  communications of theAllies with the western half of the world, and practically over its oceans and seas.    Thirdly, England  has been  the  base of  supply for  her  own army and for thearmies of the Allies, it  not having been forgotten that  the  English people have to bemerchants while they are soldiers, and that trade and maritime force are dependent oneach other.  These are notable naval achievements.    On the other hand, she has certainly gone further  in the direction of continentalwarfare than the traditions of the country and its ancient policy would have suggested.The hatred, if so strong  a word may be.used, of the English people for continentalwars has been one of their strongest characteristics, and  it  was  this hatred  that Pittmade the  foundation of what he called  &quot; his system of  strategy.&quot;   Pitt&apos;s legacy tohis country  was  a well-adjusted combination of  land  and  sea  force,  and  thesuccesses of 1759-that  immortal year were  due to the use that he made  of  theamphibious  power  of  this country.    When  the  army of  Sir. John  French wascommitted  to war  on the Continent there  was  no irrevocable  breach  of  thisgreat principle,  but, as time went on,  and  reinforcement and reinforcement was-sent to France,&apos; absorbing all  the available  military reserves  of the country,  itsamphibious  power was  gradually  sapped,  and has, at  the  present  time,  beenpractically destroyed.  During the  Seven Years&apos; War  the  conflict between, differentschools  of thought, settled first  in  one sense  and then in  another, produced  resultsmemorable and highly  instructive.  It is worth while to recall the  fact that, in spite ofFrederick the G.reat&apos;s perilous position and the  desire that he felt for strong reinforce-ments in the immediate area of military strife,  his strategical  grasp told him that thearmy of a  sea power wholly committed to continental fighting lost half its strength.  It isas true to-day as it then was, that our military power, used  amphibiously in  combina-tioh with the Fleet, can produce results out of all proportion to the numerical strengthof our Army.  Otherwise the silent action of  the Grand Fleet, and the response of thecountry under a voluntary system of recruitment  to Lord Kitchener&apos;s call,  haveproduced results that prove beyond all question the determination and capacity of theEnglish people to fight through this war to a successful finish.  If England. was leftstanding alone, she would, thanks to  her intangibility, have; nothing to fear from theresult of the conflict with  Germany.   It is questionable,  however, to what extent sheshould allow her military policy to  be dictated by the necessarily narrower outlook ofher Allies.   That the most absolute frankness should prevail between those in chargeof conjunct operations is obvious; that communications  between those in charge ofthe military policy of France and Russia on  the one hand, and the military policy ofthis country on the other, should be frequent and comprehensive, is equally obvious.But final  decisions  can  only rest with  those  who, at the moment, have charge ofher  destinies.   The maxims of  war that  premise  when the  offensive  is  taken,the  massing  of every  possible unit  at  the  vital  point  of  attack,  are indis-putable ;  but when it  is a  question of siege warfare, or  of  a defensive,  actingmainly  as  a containing force,  these maxims carry by no  means the same weight.Policy, naval, military, and diplomatic, focussed  by one intelligence and wielded by asingle authority, is by  far the most effective force of which a. nation can dispose.  It isthe weakness  of our system  of  government, based  upon the requirements  of peace&apos;conditions, and it is the weakness also  of nations allied together against a common foe,that the maximum  velocity  of  potential force can. never, be used  at the  suprememoment and in the vital direction.                          ...     These drawbacks are inevitable, but they are worth  recalling, as they can  beminimised by careful  combination and  sometimes  by courageous and independentaction.     That England  can stand the wear and tear of  war  better  than her Allies  is asource of strength to  her, but  it is also a source of weakness.   It will enable her tostaud firm when others may be inclined  to waver, and. so  far it  is eminently to heradvantage ; but, on  the other hand, it may tempt the English people to disregard orto  underestimate the  stamina  of those  nations  with whom we are acting, and uponwhose endurance, if great results are  to be achieved from  this war, we are  bound torely.                                     Neutrals.     Careful  observation of neutrals in war is not less important than a careful watchupon the  enemy.  There are two classes of neutrals whose attitude must at all times
be profoundly interesting to a belligerent Power.  There is the neutral State that forspecific reasons  may be induced to take part in the war, either on our side or againstus, and there is the neutral State that under no  circumstances will come  in on ourside, but might  if provoked become obstructive or dangerous.     In the present war, the first category is composed of those States  lying on thesouth  of the German and  Austro-Hungarian Empires, that is to say, Italy  and theBalkan Bloc, and in the north there is Holland.  So far, the diplomacy of the Allies.has failed to induce any of these  Powers  to  take  part in the war against our enemy.Whether diplomacy may yet  succeed, or whether some  more  direct action  may berequired, are questions which  can never be absent from the minds of the statesmencontrolling the operations of the Allies.     As the war becomes more static, and as the  deadlock increases, it becomes moreurgent to introduce some fresh  and stimulating  element  into the conflict.   As the firesmoulders, it becomes more urgent to poke it in the centre.  It is for this reason thatthe indrawing of the Balkan States becomes more urgent day by day.  This is not theplace in which to discuss or even to suggest methods of political and military  strategywhich might be used for such a purpose.  It is, however, vital to keep in mind thenecessity of using every means, diplomatic  or other, within  that broad sphere&apos;that isgathered round the navigable waters of the Danube, and  to  remember that, as hasbeen  often pointed out, English power  exerted to  the  full has  depended for  threecenturies upon  her capacity to make  herself felt in that central and historic  sea thathas been called  &quot;the old  womb of Empire.&quot;    In the second category of  neutrals stands the United States.  An eminent writeron naval strategy has  over  and over again laid stress  upon the fact that it is  a law ofmaritime warfare which cannot be omitted from strategical calculation with impunity,that every  step  towards gaining commaad of the sea tends to turn neutral sea Powersinto enemies, and, therefore, that the proh nged exercise of belligerent rights, even ofthe most undoubted kind, produces an interference with  trade that becomes more andmore oppressive.    It  is  within the  radius of these considerations  that our difficulties  with theUnited States arise.   These  difficulties are patent and increasing ones.   Their  growthkeeps  pace with the advance of  our  control over the  waterways of the world.  Thatthey will diminish is not  likely, and  they suggest  another and  cogent reason  againstthe prolongation of the war, even for one day beyond what is absolutely inevitable.                                   Conclusion.    The conclusions I  venture  to draw from this  attempt to appreciate  the  presentconditions of the war are these :     1. A war of attrition, though less favourable to Germany than to her  foes, entailssacrifices upon the Allies, the pressure of which might bring  about  proposals for apremature and disastrous peace.              .    2. That  England, owing to  her  intangibility, may  underrate the sufferings of Iher Allies.    3. That a decision can best be achieved by violent  and &quot; eccentric &quot; attack.    4. That as an amphibious Power England alone is  in a position to deliver it.    5. That the moment has come.                                                                         :   E.   I    January 27, 1915.PRINTED AT THE FOREIGN OFFICE BY C. R. HARRISON.-1/2/1915.

</content>
</cab>
