<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/1/0 images: 35-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for.the Committee of Imperial Defence.  February 1915.SECRET.G.-7COMMITTEE OP  IMPERIAL DEFENCE.THE  WAR.Some Further Considerations on  the Conduct of the War.Memorandum by Mr. Lloyd George, Chancellor of the                   Exchequer.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,          February 22, 1915.
SOME FURTHER CONSIDERATIONS  ON  THE          CONDUCT OF THE WAR.   I AM  anxious  to  pnt  before  my colleagues a fewconsiderations on  the general situation.   It must beacknowledged to be one of the utmost gravity, and onewhich, if  it is not taken  in hand at once firmly andboldly, may end in irretrievable disaster for the cause ofthe Allies and for the future  of the British  Empire.-This may  very well appear to some of my colleagues tobe the language of morbid pessimism, but I hope, beforethey come to  that conclusion, they will do  me thehonour of  perusing the reasons set forth here which haveled me to  this conclusion.   The press and the country have up  to the presenttreated the progress of the war as one of almost unbrokensuccess.   Their method is a  simple one.   Every trivialmilitary incident which turns to  our   advantage ismagnified  and elaborated  in headlines  which  occupyhalf  a column and  descriptions  which take  a page.On the other  hand, grave  misfortunes  such as thosewhich have befallen the armies of  our  Russian Alliesin the course  of the  last  few days  are  relegated toa few lines of type,  whilst  they are explained awayin a column of leaded matter.  I am afraid that manywho have  a more intimate  acquaintance  with the  factsare pursuing the  same  mental process.   They concen-trate their gaze upon those incidents and aspects of themilitary situation which suit their hopes, whilst  theydeliberately shut  their eyes  to  developments whichmight conduce to  the awakening of their fears.  Theonly pathway to ultimate success  is  paved by reality.Unless we look facts, however unpleasant, in the facewe shall never grapple with them.   What  are the salient facts of the  situation ?  Not ayard of German territory is now in the occupation ofthe Allies.  Practically the  whole  of Belgium  is  inGerman occupation.   Some  of the richest departmentsof France and  Russia are  now  firmly held  by  theenemy.  The Germans are now in possession of largertracts of  allied  territory  than they  have ever  heldbefore.  A still more serious fact;  whilst they main-tain  possession of the  country occupied by them inthe West   with  comparative ease, they have  at lastestablished  a  complete  military  predomination  inthe East.   It is true  that they drove the Russians outof East Prussia some  months ago,  and the Russianscame back afterwards; but as Lord  Kitchener  pointedout, there  is a serious difference between what happenedthen and  what is occurring  now.  Then the Russians    [328]                                  B
 were in a position to bring np considerable reserves to overpower the enemy, and the German reserves were not ready to take  the  field.   Now the position is entirely reversed.  Large German reserves have taken the field. The remarkable  report  circulated  by Lord  Kitchener from the pen of a Dutch officer points out  that after sending huge reinforcements to East Prussia and North Poland  to overwhelm   the  Russians,- they  have still numbers behind them they could throw  in, but which have not been sent to  the frontiers  because there is no room for them.    That is the German position now.  What  about the Russian position ?   Three months ago they had reserves to deal  with the check  which they sustained in East Prussia;  now they  have  none. .  That is  the one dominant and challenging factor in the situation.  To use  a ring phrase, the Russians  for the moment have been completely &quot; knocked out;&quot; that is, the Russian offensive is broken and. cannot  be reconstituted for some months.   Reverting again to  the  report of the Dutch officer, he states that it is the&apos;view taken by the military authorities in Germany, and, what is more important, the view taken by the Balkan States (vide Heathcote-Smith&apos;s Report).   Who is prepared to  stake-his authority on a prediction that this pessimistic view of the situation in the East will turn  out  to  be incorrect ?  The Russians may have men, but  they have no rifles.  Where are the rifles to  come  from ?  Their factories are turning these rifles out at the  rate of 45,000 a month ;  that is,  by the end of  the year  they will be  able: to arm another half million men.   Meanwhile, they are losing their men atthe rate  of  300,000 or 400,000  a month, according tothe  War  Office  Report.  They  are losing  more inprisoners alone than the 45,000, and in as much as they are retreating, the rifles left by their wounded and their dead on  the  battlefield  must also  be picked  up by the enemy. Their factories cannot overtake the losses inrifles.                              ...   In order to estimate  truly  what,  this means  to theprospects of  the Allies, I think it desirable that we  should consider what the numbers of the armies engaged on bothsides are.   The  French have, according to  our  War Office, three  millions of men now under arms.   In  arriv-ing at this  figure every allowance lias been  made forcasualties and  for men whose services cannot be  sparedby the  Government from  factories, railways,  &amp;c.   -In addition to that the War Office estimates that there would be  another 1,200,000 men fit and available for military service in France if properly equipped and trained. That is, France has three-fortieths of her population  under arms, and another 3 per cent, might  be. called upon if there were arms available.  If we apply the same per- centages to the German and Austrian population, it will give us  a clear  idea of the magnitude of the problem with which we are confronted.  By applying the French proportions  to the  enemy  countries, we should be assuming that the aggregate casualties  of  Germans and Austrians are  three times  those  of France-a very favourable assumption for the Allies.   On  this basis Germany would now have 5,000,000 men under arms and Austria-Hungary  3,700,000.   Germany  would also, on the same hypothesis, have a further reserve of  2,000,000 men who could  be drawn upon, and Austria-Hungary would have 1,500,000.  The first figure of  5,000,000 for
Germany and  Austria-Hungary  under arms    ..Turkey has at least..France has under armsGreat Britain barelySerbia   ..have  ..   8,700,000       500,000      --  9,200,000  ..   3.000,000  ..   2,000,000       200,000      --  5,200,000                 Total    ..      ..      ..    4,000,000Having regard to the superior equipment of the Germano-Austrian forces and to the fact that when we come toattack them they will be found to have entrenched theirpositions in allied  soil, it is  idle  to hope for  victoryunless  we secure a.  great  numerical superiority overthese forces.   Where  can we hope  to find it ?  Russiacannot now, according to the War Office report, put andmaintain 2,000,000 of fully armed and equipped men onall her assailed frontiers.  Even if she could, that leavesus with a  deficiency of 2,000,000.  It will be observedthat in the figures which I have given I have creditedGreat  Britain  with  2,000,000.   When  can  she  put2,000,000 into the field ?   When  can she put 1,000,000into the fighting line ?  Is it quite certain that  by thetime 1,000,000 are ready, Germany will not have addedat least another 1,000,000 to her reserves ?   I am sorry to draw so menacing a picture, but Ishould, indeed, be happy if I thought the appearance ofthe landscape did not justify the gloomy colours withwhich I have attempted to paint it.  The Dutch reportcirculated by Lord Kitchener gives  still more alarmingfigures.  If these be even approximately accurate, wecould  not  hope  to  bring the   war  to  a  successfultermination for years to come.   But even with my moremoderate  figures, the  problem is the most serious withwhich British statesmen have ever been faced.     [328]                                   CGermany corresponds exactly with those given in the WarOffice estimate and in Sir John French&apos;s estimate.  Thesecond figure has. not been taken into account by them,but I fail to see why, if France has this reserve in herpopulation, Germany and  Austria do not  possess thesame resource.  The Austrian figure is larger than theWar Office estimate by 1,000,000, but it corresponds withreports which have come from time to time from Austria-Hungary as to the number of men which  are either atthe front-or in course of being trained.  That number ofmen fit for .arms they must  possess, and nothing but ashortage  of  rifles, guns,  and  other equipment couldaccount for  their not  putting   them into  training.Germany, according to all reports, is supplying Austriawith all the rifles  she needs.   The reports received by the Intelligence Departmentof the War Office indicate that the shortage of rifles inGermany and Austria is. not comparable to that whicheven France  and  Great Britain suffer from.   I think,therefore,  it would be safe to  assume that  Germany andAustria between them have at least 8,700,000 men nowenrolled in their armies.  That would put them in the sameposition as France, having regard to the relative popula-tion  of the  three countries.  It  would also be  safe,further, to assume that they  have  in reserve another4,500,000 who could  be called up  for training.   Let us take the first figure and  see how the Alliesstand in reference to it: 
    The first thing to do is to find out exactly where; we stand.  Who  can present a  reliable  estimate  of the military resources of the  Allies ?  We ought  to have a conference between  the military authorities of the three countries, at which a candid exposure of the  position of each  country is made and  some  military  convention agreed  to  as to our future action.   General Paget is a good  soldier,  but  his  qualities  are  not  altogether fitted   for  a  detailed investigation   into   questions of  equipment.    We   know  approximately  at  any rate  how  France  is  situated.   We  have not  the slightest notion  what the position of Russia  is.   I strongly urged as far back as  October  that  we should take drastic measures to ascertain accurately the Russian position as to  equipment and  munitions.   We  are entitled not  merely to ask  but to demand frankness from our Russian Allies.  Russia is not in this war to help France and Belgium and ourselves.  France came in to assist Russia when she was menaced ; Belgium came in on account of France ; we came in to protect Belgium ; so that indirectly we  are in because Russia was attacked. Germany  was  not merely at peace with  us but was extremely anxious to maintain the peace  not merely with us,  but with France  as well.   She  engaged in this war to try conclusions  with Russia before  Russia was pre- pared to attack her.  We  are helping Russia  with men, with material, with money.  France and ourselves have already advanced 50,000,000 or 60,000,000 of  money to Russia and we have promised another 100,000,000.  We are  therefore  justified in demanding  candour from Russia.   Germany knows  all- about the Russian forces, their  numbers,  disposition, and equipment.   All we want  is that our  great  Ally should supply us with information which her enemies already possess.    What next ?  Every effort must be made to increase the  number of men whom we  can put into the field and to shorten the period ,in which they could  be put into the  fighting lines.  How is that to be done ?  If France could put 3,000,000 of  men under arms and  Germany 5,000,000, then the whole  of the Allied  countries oughtto be able, on the basis of  population, sooner or later to. arm 20,000,000.   That may  be  an impossibility, but it is an indication  of the enormous reserves of men fit to bear arms that the.Allies have to draw upon.  Theproblem resolves itself  into one of :     (1.)  The training and equipping of these men in the        shortest space of time ;    (2.)  The maintaining of the status quo  without any        appreciable  aggravation  until   the  Allied        countries are prepared to throw overwhelming        forces into the battlefield.    How are these two objects  to be attained ?   The first and the greatest difficulty  is equipment.   The number of men we could put in the field is seriously limited by the  out-put of guns and rifles.   In this respect we have a great advantage.  We are at a disadvantage as corn- pared with the Germans in one material respect, but we are  at a great advantage in other respects.  As  to the disadvantage, the Germans and Austrians between themhad, even at the commencement of the war, much larger supplies of war  material and  more extensive factories for  the turning out of further  supplies than  the allied
 countries possessed, and they have undoubtedly since made much better use of their manufacturing resources for the purpose of increasing that output.   Germany is the best organised country in the world, and her organi- satioh has told.    Those  are  the  disadvantages.   What  about the advantages?   The manufacturing resources  at the disposal of  the Allies are enormously greater than those which Germany  and  Austria can  command.   Tn this computation Russia barely counts, but the manufacturing resources of France and Great Britain between them are  at least equal to those  of  Germany and Austria, and the seas being free to them they can more easily obtain  material.    But   apart  from  that  they  have practically the whole of America, which is  the greatest manufacturing country in the world, and Japan, to draw upon.    I believe that France has strained her resources to the utmost, and she can hardly do much more.  She has now abolished the sale of absinthe, and  that will have an appreciable effect upon the productivity of her work- men.  She is, therefore, doing all she can to contribute. I do not believe Great Britain has even yet done anything like what she could do in the matter of increasing her war equipment.   Great things have been accomplished in the last few months, but I  sincerely believe that we could double our effective, energies  if we organised our factories thoroughly.   All the engineering works of the country ought to be turned on to the production of war material.   The population ought to be prepared to suffer all sorts  of  deprivations and even hardships whilst  this process is going on.  As  to America, I feel confident from what I have heard  that we have  tapped only  a small  percentage of  this great available reserve of supply. ^   Special attention should be given to the laying flown of machinery which is essential to  the turning out of rifles and cannon.   I hear it takes months  to complete these machines ; but even if they are only ready in Sep- tember, we shall need them  all.  My  first suggestion therefore, would be that full powers should be taken, if we  do not already possess them, as I think we do, to mobilise the whole of our manufacturing strength for the purpose of turning out at  the  earliest possible  moment war material.  I have always thought that our complete command over the railways equips us with the necessary powers without resorting to legislation.  But legislation which  would enable us to  commandeer  all the works in the  United Kingdom  and, if necessary, to  deal  with labour difficulties and shortcomings, would undoubtedly strengthen our hands.  We might even take full powers to close public houses altogether in areas where arma- ments  were  being manufactured.  As  to our  railway powers, I made the suggestion that they should be used some time ago to.the War Office.  I  am not  sure of the extent  to which that has been done.   Now  with regard to the raising of the men.  Francehas probably brought every available man she can spare into  line.  That is far from being the case  with either the British Empire or,with Russia.   Great  Britain, on the   French basis,  ought to  have 3,500,000  men nowunderarms  instead  of 2,000,000.  The colonies oughtto have,  on  the  same basis, 1,200,000  men  instead of100,000..  . I  believe  we could with a special effort raise    [328]                          &quot;          D
our  3,500,000 or,  if that be found inconsistent  withthe turning out of the necessary equipment, we couldcertainly raise 3,000,000.  I still think it  is unnecessaryto obtain compulsory powers.  The  young  men  of thiscountry will enlist in  our  armies if it is brought hometo them that  their  services are needed.   I  venturedto suggest some time ago that the  best method  ofdoing  so  would  be  by determining  the  quota  eachcounty  and town ought to contribute  in proportionto its   population,  and  leaving it to  local  pressureand  local patriotism to  do the rest.  If  we  officiallyannounce  that a particular county.is expected to-con-tfibute, say,  10,000 men  ; that  up  to  the  present0,000  have been  enrolled, in  that county,  and that4,000 more ought to  enlist in order to make up thequota, local pride will fill up the ranks for us.   Some means ought also  to be taken to induce our self-governing colonies to take upon themselves a larger shareof responsibility in the  matter of  levies.   They  areunder the impression now that they  are doing all that isexpected of them.  The  peril ought to be brought to them.The  optimistic telegrams which we publish have deludedthem into the belief that all is going well,  and that allthev need do is to send a few thousands  to the MotherCountry as a token of  their sympathy and esteem forher.  When they realise that she is in real peril, I donot doubt their response.   Russia, on the French basis, ought to have 12,000,000men under arms.  That is probably  more than she couldequip for some years, but having regard  to her primaryresponsibility as far as  the  Allies are concerned for thestruggle, the numbers of her men ought  to bear somerelation  to her  enormous  resources  in   vigorousmanhood.   All this must necessarily take time. We have hithertoproceeded as if the war could not  possibly last beyondnext autumn.  Wo should  now  take exactly the otherline assume that it wall last not  merely  through theyear, but  conceivably  through next  year  as well.Capital therefore ought  to be spent on laying downmachinery which will  enormously  expedite the  outputof rifles, cannon, and all other machinery and munitionsof war towards the latter end of the  year and the begin-ning of the next.  If  it  turns  out that  my  estimate&apos;errs  on the side of pessimism the worst that happenswill  be  that we shall have spent  a  considerable amountof money, we  shall have caused a considerable amountof inconvenience to  the population.   But all that isnothing compared with  the disaster of having to faceanother year of war with inadequate preparation.   Thisthe public will never forgive after the warning  we  havereceived, nor ought they to be expected to forgive.   But what is to be clone  in the meantime ?  It looksas if during the best part of the present year the Alliesmust content themselves to be in a  position of militaryinferiority to Germany.  During this period the best wecan  hope for is that we shall be able to hold  our own.Can we even accomplish this without summoning some.fresh forces to  our  aid ?  Having  regard  to the over-whelming forces at the disposal of  Germany there is atleast an  element  of   doubt.   There  are  only twodirections  in which we  can turn  for any  prospect  ofassistance-the Balkan States and Italy.   The BalkansAve  might  conceivably   have  brought   in   some
months ago, but  the  Allies have  been  unfortunatein. this   quarter.    We  have   only   succeeded  inbringing   in   the   Turks   against    us   withoutengaging - any  other Balkan Power  on  our  behalf.Is it  too late to do anything now?  Lord  Kitchenerpointed out the other day at the Council that the Ger-mans had  taken risks     attacking the Russians withtheir  full forces before they were quite ready, in orderto be prepared  to meet the attack of our reinforcementsin April.   With the one exception of our initial actionagainst Turkey where our promptitude was  unmistak-able, our risks  have all been in the contrary direction;we have generally taken them too late.  The momentousstep we  have taken in attempting to force the Darda-nelies  must have a decisive effect  one way or the otheron the Balkans.  Are we prepared for either or for anyevent ?   If  this great movement succeeds then,  if  we areprepared  to take   immediate  advantage  of  it itsinfluence may be decisive as far as the Balkan Statesare concerned.   This  means that  if we  have a  largeforce ready, not merely to  occupy Gallipoli,  but totake any other  military action Avhich may be  necessaryin order to establish our  supremacy  in  that quarter,Roumania,  Greece,  and,  I  think,  very probably, Bul-garia, will  declare  for  us.  If, on the other hand,  wehave  no  force on the spot  adequate to  cope with theTurkish  army,  it  may  be that most  of the effect ofsuch a brilliant coup might be lost.   To bring Bulgaria,Roumania, and Greece in with Serbia  means throwingan aggregate  army  of  1,500,000   on  to  the Austrianflank.   This will not  only  relieve the  pressure  onRussia, but indirectly  on  France.  It  will tend  toequalise  things, and th^s give us time to re-equip theRussian Army.    Now let us take the other contingency the failureof  the Dardanelles  effort.   Unless  it  is at  oncecountered,  such  a  failure  will be disastrous  in theBalkans, and might very well be  disastrous through-out  the  East.   The Bulgarian  general  pointed  outthat  not  merely Bulgaria,  but Roumania  and  Italyhave a good deal  to  gain  in the way  of territoryby throwing in their lot with Germany.   There is onlyone guarantee against a catastrophe being precipitatedin that quarter as the result  of a repulse in the Darda-nelles.  There  must be a  strong British force thereavailable to support our friends.   Is it quite  out of thequestion that we should anticipate our April preparationshy three  or four  weeks  and thus follow  the Germanexample of taking risks so as to arrive in time ?    The  sending of a  large expeditionary  force  un-doubtedly involves large preparations ships, transportsto carry  troops  and their equipment  to Salonica orLemnos, also preparations  for  transporting   them  upcountry ;   and   the  Committee of Imperial  Defencedecided  some weeks ago that  these preparations shouldbe immediately undertaken,  so that if  an  expeditionwere at any time determined upon, no delay need ensiteowing to lack of sea or land transport.  1 understandthat the Admiralty have done all that was  entrusted tothem in this respect&quot;; 1 know nothing of the steps takenby the War Office respecting the railways and the roads.    My final suggestion is that a special diplomaticmission, based on our readiness to despatch and maintain
a large expeditionary force in the Balkans should imrne-d lately be sent to Greece and Roumania to negotiate amilitary convention.  Germany has not depended uponher  ordinary  diplomatic   representatives  where  thesituation presented &quot;any great possibilities, friendly orhostile to  her welfare.   She sent  Von  der Goltz  toConstantinople, Sophia,  and Bucharest; Von Billow toItaly ;  Dernburg to  America. She has not depended uponher Bax-Ironsides in critical situations.   No doubt  theyare very good men in their way,  but the  mere fact thatthey have remained so long in inferior diplomatic berthsproves that, in the opinion of the Foreign  Office, theirqualities are not of the first order.                                         D. LI. G.   P.S. Since writing the above I have read a remark-able report from General Paget, which confirms  inessentials the vieAV I have repeatedly expressed as to theBalkan situation.  I was privileged  to see  this docu-ment through the courtesy of the Prime Minister.  Irespectfully suggest  that  every  member  of the WarCouncil should have an opportunity of perusing reportsAvhich  bear so intimately on decisions they are asked tocome to.  To consult them without trusting  them withthe only information which makes their judgment worthhaving is worse than futile.                                         D. LI. G.  February 22, 1915.lEIKTlD AT THE FOBEIGN OKFICE BY C. E. HAEEISON. 26/2/1915.

</content>
</cab>
