<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/1/0 images: 104-107</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.  March 1915.SECRET.G-17.COMMITTEE  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.THE   WAR.Russia and  Constantinople.Remarks  by Admiral of the Fleet  Sir A. K. Wilson                 on Paper G-ll.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,             March 15, 1915.
REMARKS  BY  SIR A. WILSON ON G 11.                     (1.)   THE  opinion  expressed  by  the  Defence Committee in 1903, that  the Russian occupation of  Constantinople   would  not  fundamentally alter  the  present   strategic  position  in   the Mediterranean,   was arrived  at   under  very different conditions  from those that  exist  at  the present time.   &quot;We had at that time a large fleet  both  in  the Mediterranean  and  in the  China  Seas,  which appeared to be sufficient to deal with any fleet the   Russians  then  had,  whether  they  were stationed in the Baltic or the Black Sea.  The Russo-Japanese war had not  then taken place, and attention had not been called to the enormous difficulty  Russia   afterwards  experienced  in bringing her ships in the Baltic to the support of her fleet in the Far East.   The position of the Russian ports has up to  the present  made  it  quite  impossible for  her to dispute the command of the sea with us, and  she has consequently not attempted it, but as soon as the state of her finances admits of her creating a new fleet and making its headquarters  in  the Black Sea she may,  if she likes, become a very formidable opponent to us indeed.   Whatever the position may have been in 1903, there is no donbt that -under present conditions a hostile  Russia in possession  of Constantinople could  make our  communication  through   the Mediterranean  with  Egypt and India  almost impossible.  A strong  force of submarines  established inthe Dardanelles would be able to intercept and destroy  a very large proportion  of the  ships attempting to pass between  Crete and the coast of Africa, on  the route  to  Alexandria or  the Canal.  A fleet at Alexandria could not be kept supplied with  fuel,  nor  reinforcements sent   to Egypt, except through the Red Sea.   No  new fortified      [409-1]
 base that&apos;we could make would improve matters in this respect, and an island base could not be furnished with supplies except at great risk.   It may be assumed that when Turkey is driven out. of Europe, the occupation of Constantinople by Russia is inevitable,  as even  if some small- State were put  in  possession, the arrangement would only be a  temporary one until Russia felt herself strong enough to turn it out.  It is, there- fore, best to consider our future  policy under these conditions.   After  the war, Russia being  relieved  for  a considerable time from any danger of aggression by Germany or Austria will be  able  to  devote herself to internal affairs, the development of her trade,  and  to   strengthening  her  position  in Asia.   Russia and Great  Britain will  be left  face to face as  the two dominant  Powers  in  Asia.   If they are antagonistic, Russia  would  be  in the stronger position, as, although she could not pass through the Suez Canal or the  Straits of  Gibraltar,. she could bring her whole military forces against India, which could only be reinforced and supplied by the long sea route.   The only way  to avoid a competition in arma- ments far in excess of  anything that  we have undergone with Germany is to establish friendly relations and close co-operation  with  Russia in the affairs of Asia.                     (2-)Sir Arthur Wilson,  No consideration of the effect produced uponthe strategical position which would be createdafter the war by the Russian possession of Con-stantinople and the Dardanelles is possible withoutdealing with the changes in naval materiel con-sequent upon the submarine.  It is certain eitherthat the submarine will dominate all narrow watersand render them impassable for heavy ships andfor commerce, or that alterations will be made bybulges and bidkheads to the underwater structureof large ships, which will  render them&apos; immunefrom  the submarine.   In the former case,  weshould have to recognise that the Mediterraneanin time of war would, like the North Sea, becomealmost entirely a mare clausum.  We could notthink of it as a sea road for transports to  India.In the- latter case, assuming we build  transx^orts,
merchant vessels, and  heavy  ships  &quot;which  are&apos;immune  from submarine attack, the control ofthe Mediterranean will rest with the superior seapower, and that control would not be affected toany vital degree by a Russian ownership of  theDardanelles.                                   W.  S. C.  March 13, 1915.                     (3.)First Lord, - It is impossible to foresee what form defenceagainst submarines will  take  in the future, butit is hardly likely that ships can  be made proofagainst  torpedoes without  at the  same timegreatly   impairing   their  sea-going  qualities,economy,  and  speed,  so that merchant  shipswhich would have to be used for transport andsupply purposes would be greatly handicappedin their ordinary work if they had to carry outthe necessary modifications.  Moreover,  although  bulges  and  additionalwatertight subdivisions  might prevent a shipftom being  actually sunk  by a torpedo, shewould in  any case be seriously damaged by theexplosion, and would  require docking before shecould be  considered again efficient.  1 think some system of trapping by means ofnets  and  explosive  charges  offers  the  bestprospect  of success as a means  of  destroyingsubmarines, but it does not seem likely that anydefensive measures likely to  be  devised in thenear future will  do more than slightly  reducethe risk from submarine attack.  Of course the French  submarines  can equallyinterfere  with our line of communication throughthe  Mediterranean, but France alone cannot  atthe  same  time put  an army on  the   Indianfrontier.  Even  if   we  could  eliminate  submarinesaltogether,  the  possession  of  Constantinoplewould still give a great strategic advantage  toRussia.                                  A. K.  W.  March  15, 1915.PRINTED AT THE FOHEIGN OFF1CK IT C. E. HAKEISOX.-23/8/1015.

</content>
</cab>
