<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/1/0 images: 145-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
       Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.  September 1915.SECRET.G.-21.COMMITTEE  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.Report on the Weather  on the Shores  of the iEgean  Sea        during the Winter Months with  Charts.Prepared under the direction of Sir W. Napier Shaw, Director                of the Meteorological Office.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,            September 7, 1915.
fM.O. 224CONFIDENTIAL.    (Provisional  Issue.)MEAN   MAXIMUM  AND  MINIMUMTEMPERATURES  AND  RAINFALL           FOR  SEPTEMBER.PLACE.)ng. 10&quot;W.-0o  Bilbao  Corunna  Oporto  Valencia  Lisbon  Alicante  Cartagena  Cadiz -    Gibraltar    Oran -   -   -   -    Nemours  -   -   - ong. 0o-10oE.    Turin-   -    Genoa-   -    Marseilles -    Perpignan -    Barcelona -    Mahon    Palma    Tones- ,   AlgiersLong. 10QE.-20oE.    Trieste   -    Pola  -   -    Ancona    Leghorn    Lesina    Pelagosa    Rome -    Foggia    Naples    Lecce -  *Corfu-    Palermo    Catania   ...    Malta -    Tunis-   -    Gabos -    TripoliLong. 20&quot;E.-30oE.    Sulina-   -    Braila-    Bucbarest  *Burgas    -    -    -  *Monastir   -  *Gallipoli   -   ^  *Salonica  *K.avala   -  *Trikala   -       .-  *Larissa  *Volo -   -   -   .  *Arta -  *Lamia  *Missolongi -  *Chalchis   -  *Smyrna  *Argostoli (Cephalonia)  *Patras    -   -  *Athens   -   -  *Andros  *Samos  *Zante -  *Nanplia  *Syra -  *Calamate  -  - -   -  *Sparta  *Naxos    -   -  *Cythera  *Thera (Santorin) -  *Canea-   -   -   -  *Candia    Benghazi  -    Sidi Barani -    Alexandria -TEMPERATURE.MeanMax. 0F.77717783758379797979817275778485S383777180788380828490858487777674778080798684828784868487848484797981848186867982788380848685MeanMin. 0F.565359596266656666676358655762626850626160656569686969714239525662546662646060626063676464666867676670666968636870676668727272RAINFALL.ID.3-823T92-991-462-801-891-221 061-420-670-712-604-962-051-773-372-241-650-431-144-843-622-443-272-721-022-871-422-802-133541-501-231-160-870-550-47 1-69 1 06 1-46 0-79 2-05 1-38 201 1-14 1-34 0-94 1-06 1-18 1-97 1-10 0-79 0-91 0-71 1-26 1-14 0-55 0-63 0-00 1-26 1-06 0-83 0-94 1-26-0-39 0-83 0-43 0-55 0-78 0-12 0-00 0-08Mm.9781763771483127361718 66126 52 45 86 57 42 11 29123 92 62 83 69 26 73 36 71 54 90 38 31 37 22 14 12432737205235512934242730502820231832291416 032272124321021111420 3 0 2
MONTHLY METEOROLOGIC                  OF THEISSIL&amp;CL by Authority of the Meteorological Committee.
WBM&quot;___1_.___________,________________LICALBAS  Conxmitte&amp;    Wliile the depressions which traverse the Mediterranean in August are mostlylimited  to  the  Gulf  of Genoa,  Northern  Italy  and  the Adriatic,  those  otSeptember are more widely distributed  and follow three principal mean tracks.Of  these No. 1 leads  from Southern Spain to the  Gulf  of  Genoa;  No. 2 leadsdown the Adriatic, crossing Greece  and the Aegean Sea, and paasing into AsiaMinor; No. 3 follows approximately the  40th parallel, bending finally northwardsover the Black  Sea.   During the past  eight&apos;years 17 well-marked  depressionshave occurred in September, and 50 per cent, of these have  followed one or otherof these tracks, the remainder having traversed portions of two or even three ofthem in the course of their passage of the Mediterranean, which occupies generallyfrom three to seven days, according to the course taken by the depressions.    The Daily Weather Chart (A) for 8 a.m. on 9th Sept., 1909, shows  a depressionwhich, a8 it passed up the East Coast of Spain into South-Western France,  gave riseto strong winds in the Gulf of Lyons and the western  Mediterranean.    Daily Weather Chart (B) for 8 a.m.  on 19th Sept., 1911, shows a depressionover Greece and the Aegean which caused strong southerly winds and a high sea at Athens, as well as in the Southern Adriatic.appeared in South-Western France on the 14th and passed, over the Gulf of Lyons to the head of the Adriatic, where, on the 1south-easterly direction along the Eastern Coast oi  the Balkaii Peninsula; then crossing  the  northern part  of the  Aegecontinuing along the Coast of Asia Minor  to Sinope, it finally crossed the Black Sea to the Sea of  Azof.    The conditions which favour strong northerly winds in the Aegean Sea are shown in the Daily Weather Chart C,for Sjim^on S(Here high pressureexists over the Balkan Peninsula, whileOyrenaica no longer forms an isolated areaof high pressure. Oni  &quot;were very strong winds and a high sea reported from Athens, but gales and rough sea occurred also on the west of Greece and the south of Italy.    In September depressions do not ordinarily pass along  the southern shores of  the Mediterranean, as is the case LD the winter, thoughthey occur at  times in Algeria to the south of  the Atlas ranges, or  pass over them from the Mediterranean.occasion i  Isobars are dpand are numbeJ  The  computl6,000 feet) are ilvelocity in inetJ  The frequencjlength of the lilobservations at.number of obselpoint of observal  Scale of freqi  The force ofby the feathers  The mean ten!shown in black  The mean teJthe depth of 1.1following scale :l
  ist are mostly  ,ic,   those  ol   nean tracks.   No. 2  leads  kng into Asia Iv northwards    depressions   one or other   ven three  of   ies generallyI jftiona.IB a depressionlljnce,  gave rise   a depressionof disturbances.      (I)It had first;p M a high sea at Athens, as well as in the Southern Adriatic.  sfulf of Lyons to the head of the Adriatic, where, on the 17th, it took a Iliriinsula,- then  crossing the northern part of the  Aegean  Sea,  and   he Black Sea to the Sea of Azof.   Sea are shown in the Daily Weather Chart C,for 8fun.,on Sept. 9th,1913.   longer forms an isolated area of high pressure.  On this occasion not only   nd rough sea occurred  also ou the west of Greece and the south of Italy.   rn shores of the Mediterranean, as is the  case in the winter,  though   tss over fchem from the Mediterranean.EXPLANATION.  Isobars are drawn in red showing the mean pressure of the day,and are numbered in millibars and inches :- IOIS mb.1,89-89 in.)  The computed  mean  currents of  the upper  air (1,500  to6,000 feet) are indicated by arrows in red ; the figures denote thevelocity in metres per second and miles per hour:-                                       9 metres per  second                                      20 miles  per hour.  The frequency of winds is  shown by wind-roses in red.   Thelength of the lines indicates the proportion which the number ofobservations at any one point of the  compass bears to the wholenumber of observations.   The centre of the  wind-rose is on thepoint  of observation.  beale or frequency :   i_i_i_i_i   per cent.  The force of the winds  in the Daily Weather Charts is shownby the feathers on the arrows  :                                          Beaufort.                                            No.                                            0                                            1-3                                            8,9                                           10,11                         Indicates direction without statement                             as to force.  The mean temperature  for  the month in degrees Fahrenheit isshown in black figures beside the station to which it refers,  The mean  temperature of the surface  of the sea is shown bythe depth of blue shading  ou the  sea  area according to thefollowing scale:                   Over 75-    pv-^^j                  70&quot;-75*     p^-::-^&quot;:^&quot;l                  Under 70   t  .......... 0S1CalmLightStrongViolent
mIImfII Hi ong. 10oW.-0o.    Bilbao     -    -    Corunna    Oporto    Valencia   -    Lisbon    Alicante    Oarfcagena -    -    Cadiz    Malaga    Gibraltar    Dran -    -    Nemours   - ong. 0o-10oE.    Turin-    -        -    Genoa-    -    -    -    Marseilles -    Perpignan -    Barcelona -  jj  Mahon    Palma  I  Tenes-    -    AlgiersLong. 10QK-20oE.    Trieste    Pola  -         -    -    Ancona    Leghorn    Lesina    Pelagosa    Kome-    -    -    -    Foggia    Naples    Lecce -    -    -    -   *Corfu-    -    Palermo    Catania    .-    Malta -    Tunis -    Gabes-    -    -    -    TripoliLong. 20&quot;E.-30oE.    Sulina-    Braila-    -    Bucharest   * Burgas    -    -    -   *Qanst!antJn^ple   *Monastir   *Gallipoli    -   *Salonica   *Kavala     -   *Trikala   *Larissa   *Volo  -   *Arta  -   *Lamia   *Missolongi  -   *Chalchis   *Smyrna   *Argostoli (Cephalonia)   *Patras   * Athens   *Andros   *Samos   *Zan.te -     -    -    -   *Nanplia   *Syra  -     -    -    -   *Calamate  -    -    -   *Sparta     -    -    -   *Naxos   *Cythera   *Thera (Santorin) -   * Canea -   *Candia     Benghazi  -     Sidi  Barani -     Alexandria -Long. 30oE.-45oE.     Batum     Samsun    -     Trebizond  -     Kyrenia     Famagusta -     Limassol   -    -    -     Beirut     -     Port Said  -    -    -     Cairo -77717783758379797979817275778485838377718078838082849085848777767477808079868482878486848784848479798184818686798278838084868575888990868890565359596266656666676358655762626850626160656569686969714239525662546662646060626063676464666867676670666968636870676668727272636763657270663-823-192-991-462-801-891-221 061-420-670-712-604-962-051-773-372-241-650-431-144-843-622-443-272-721-022-871-422-802-133-541-501-231-460-870-550-471-691 061-460-792-051-382-011-141-340-941-061-181-971-100-790-910-711-261-140-550-630-001-261-060-830-941-260-390-830-430-550-780-120-000-0812-28 2-13 3-03 0-20 0-16 0-35. o-oo o-oo9781763771483127361718 66126 52 45 86 57 42 11 29123 92 62 83 69 26 73 36 71 54 90 38 31 37 22 14 12432737205235512934242730502820231832291416 032272124321021111420 3 0 2311 54 77  5  4  9  0  0* These places are shown ou the inset Alap of Greece and the /Kgeati.mm
continuing ahf    The condHere high prelwere very sta[    In Septetthey occur atl    In the month of September  considerable changes take place in the meteorological conditions ofabruptly than that  from Spring to Summer  conditions, and signs of the  altered distribution of  atmclow pressure system  which has been lying over the  Persian Gulf and Arabia withdraws  southwards alin the Eastern  Mediterranean changes notably in  consequence.   The mean pressure increases by 4 r1 mb. (0&apos;03 in.) in Southern Italy.   In the Western Mediterranean the  changes are but slight.   Thqtimes this extends to the  Balkans, when it has considerable effect  on the circulation of  winds in the    The  prevalent  winds  in the Eastern  Mediterranean  are much the same as in August, but  the )JBosphorus  and the northern part of the Aegean Sea North-easterly winds prevail, but at the coastwith an increasing proportion of  other directions at  the inland stations.   In  the Mediterranean, Soutllprincipally west  and south-west winds.  In  the Western  Mediterranean  the prevalent wind directions!    As mentioned in the description of  the mean  tracks of  disturbances, strong winds are  no&apos;i comifnorthern portions which the depressions usually traverse at this season.    Temperature falls gradually  during the month,  but the  reduction of the summer temperature iswith that of August amounts to 4&quot; F.  in the Levant, Lower Egypt., Greece and  the  Aegean, thoughof Spain  the fall amounts to 4-6&quot; F. and in the Adriatic  to 5-50 F.  The coast stations of Algeria shcl    On the African Coasts, in the Levant, in Greece and  in the Aegean Sea, where the  summer monlpractically rainless,  but from the Bosphorus  to Crete small quantities lof rain  are usually recorded  algreatly from year to year, since it usually occurs in connection with  thunderstorms.  The rainfall the!measurements  extending over a series of years.                                                    \]    The sea-temperature in this month approximates to the mean temperature of the coast at most sithe Black Sea, off the West Coast of Italy, and in  the neighbourhood of the Balearic Islands the melNorthern Aegean Sea, to the west of Sardinia,  and  in the Straits  of Gibraltar the conditions are revjalong the coast of Palestine,  where they range  from 80&quot; F. to 81&quot; F.PRINTED  UNDER THE  AUTHORITY  OF  HIS  MAJESTTS STATIONERY  OFFICE.M.O. WTO. soo. S/lC. U.B. a3ST/s/lS.
w20*P^SSS^^^ong*ttlfi Eastem&quot;Coast oi the Balkan^TSSS^^^y^se^tase-south-easterly aireowu      s              Sinope, it finally crossed the Black Sea to the Sea of Azof.                     Q  ,  G., ,OI,MlrtZ?jffial^SKd8 in the Aegean Sea are shown in the Daily Weather Chart ^^^^Ki3;Here high V^^^r^i; hi  .     reDOrted from Athens, but gales and rough sea occurred also on the west of Greece and the south ot Italy.WeiSS                                                            the Mediterranean, as is the ease i*  the winter, thoughthey wcufat times in Algeria to the south of the Atlas ranges, or pass over them from the Mediterranean.  eorological conditions of the  Mediterranean as the  summer type gives place to  the autumn type.  This  change takes place  more lered  distribution of atmosphere pressure are usually apparent in the weather charts between the 10th and  20th of the  month.   The I withdraws southwards as the Monsoon conditions of the  Indian Ocean diminish  in intensity,  and the mean distribution of  pressure In pressure increases by 4 mb.  (0-12 in.) in the Levant, 3-4 mb.  (0-12-0-09 in.) in  the  Black &quot;Sea, 3 mb.  (0;09 in.)  in the Aegean, and  lgcs  are but slight.   The  pressure gradient over Egypt  remains steep.   An isolated high  pressure area&apos;lies over Cyrenaica, and at rcnlation of winds in the Aegean Sea.   as in August, but  the Southerly and Westerly winds are increasing, and  the  predominance of the Northerly winds is  les-s.   In the  revail, but at  the coast stations  in Greece their proportion is less.   Northerly winds prevail in the southern part of  the Aegean Sea  the Mediterranean, South  of  Crete and  on the coast of  Egypt northerly and north westerly winds predominate, while  the Levant Las  prevalent  wind directions aie practically the same as those for August. [strong winds are  no&apos;4 common  in the southern and south eastern parts of the  Mediterranean Basin, but  are  mainly restricted  to thejle summer temperature is  not  very marked until Ootober.  The  fall of the  mean  temperature of  the  day in September  as  compared I and  the Aegean, though some of  the coast stations, as Alexandria, record rather  less.   On the west  of  Italy and on  the East Coastjfevst  stations of Algeria  show about 3&quot;  F.  decrease of temperature.St., where the summer months are  practically rainless, the first signs  of the rainy season appear in  September.   In Egypt  the month isjfem are usually recorded at  most stations.   Although the  mean rainfall of  the month in Greece and the Aegean is  small, it variesUrstorms.  The rainfall therefore at any place may in  some years  be  as much as five times the amount  of  the mean value derived fromif        .                                                   .                                       &apos;Mii&quot;&quot;e  of ttle coast at  most stations, but  departures from this  occrir.   In the Levant, on the coasts of  Egypt, in the Western portion of fie Balearic Islands the mean sea  temperature is above that of  the land.  In the immediate  neighbourhood of the Dardanelles, in the Itar the conditions are  reversed, and land temperatures are  the higher.  The highest sea-temperatures are to  be found  in the  LevantEXPLAfMAT  Isobars are drawn in red showing theand are numbered in millibars and iner  The  computed  mean  currents of6,000 feet) are indicated by arrows in rJvelocity in metres per second and milel  The frequency of winds is shown bjlength of the lines indicates the propqobservations at any one point of the elnumber of  observations.  The centrepoint of observation.  Scale of frequency :-  i_!L_  The force of the winds in  the Dailylby the feathers on the arrows :-0siCalmLightStrongViolentIndicates dl    as to fc  The mean temperature for the monflshown in black figures beside the static  The  mean temperature of the snrfathe depth  of  blue shading on  thefollowing scale :                   Over 75&apos;:    I                  70o-75o     I                  Under 70&quot;  IOFFICE.IPrinted at the Meteorological Office, South Kensington, London, 8.W.By WrstAN &amp; Sobs, Ltd., Fetter Lane, London, B.C., and Heading.
fS 1 depressionHie, gave rise  Ihffiefat Athens, as well as in the Southern             jf^JJ  foi Lyons to the head of the Adriatic, w hereon the17ft, it took a  bsula; then crossing  the northern part of the Aegean bea, and  j Black Sea to the Sea of Azof.         rt^a^-m nn Snnt 9th 1913   , are shown in the Daily Weather Chart ^g^ffi  uger forms an isolated\^^Jff^^^^^   rough sea occurred also on the west or ureece a -    ;      tinmenli shores of  the Mediterranean, as is the case in the  winter, tnongnfl over them from the Mediterranean. ice to  the  autumn type.   This change takes place  more %r charts between the 10th and 20th of the month.   The  Qinish  in intensity, and the mean distribution of  pressure I.) in  the  Black Sea, 3 mb.  (0;09 in.) in the Aegean, and Bn isolated high  pressure area&apos;lies over Cyrenaica, and  at  the predominance of  the  Northerly  winds is less.  In the Hy winds prevail in the southern part  of  the Aegean Sea  I north westerly winds predominate, while the Levant has  e  Mediterranean Basin, but are mainly restricted to the  mean  temperature of  the day in September as  compared  rather less.  On the  west of  Italy and on the East  Coast  -iny season appear in  September.  Tn Egypt the month is  the month in Greece and the Aegean is small, it varies  as five times the amount of the mean  value derived fromsfcevant, on the coasts  of Egypt, in the  Western portion of&apos;i&amp; the immediate  neighbourhood of the  Dardanelles, in the fe highest sea-temperatures are to he found in the Levant  Isobars are drawn in red showing the mean pressure of the day,and are numbered in millibars and inches :-                                       lOIS mb.                           &quot;           1,29-89 in.)  The  computed  mean currents of  the  upper air (1,500 to6,000 feet) are indicated by arrows in red ; the figures denote thevelocity in metres per second and miles per hour:                                        9  metres  per  second.                                       20 miles per hour.  The frequency of winds  is shown  by wind-roses in  red.   Thelength of the lines indicates the proportion which the number ofobservations at any one point  of the compass bears to the wholenumber of observations.  The centre of the wind-rose is on thepoint of observation.Scale of frequency:per cent.  The force of the winds in the Daily Weather Charts is shownby the feathers on the arrows :-0Beaufort.   No.    0   1-3CalmLightStrong      ...     8,9Violent     ...    10,11Indicates direction without statement    as to force.  The mean temperature for the month in degrees Fahrenheit isshown in black figures beside the station to which it refers.  The  mean temperature of the surface of the sea is shown bythe depth  of  blue shading on  the sea  area according to thefollowing scale :                   Over 75&apos;&apos;        ^ - &apos; :-I                  70&quot;-75o     I  &apos;         1                  Under 70o  I           1Printed at the Meteorological Office, South Kensington, London, 8.W.By Wtman &amp; Sobs, Ltd., Fetter Lane, London, B.C., and Heading.
I______M.O.  224CONFIDENTIAL.   EAN  MAXIMUM AND MINIMUMTEMPERATURES  AND   RAINFALL            FOR  OCTOBER.        PLACE.Long. JCTW,-O0    Bilbao    Corunna    Oporto    Lisbon    Cadiz -   -   -    -    Gibraltar  -    Malaga    Cartagena -    Alicante  -   -    -    Valencia    Nemours  -    Oran         -    -Long. 0o-l(TE.   .    Turin-    Perpignan -    Barcelona  -    Marseilles  -    Nice -   -    Genoa-   -   -    Mahon    Palma    Tones-   -   -    Algiers    Bona -   -   -    -Long. 10oE.-20oE.    Trieste    Pola -    Ancona    Lisina    Pelagosa    Leghorn  - &apos;  -    ivDIuS &quot;&apos;   -       -    Foggia    rsap&apos;ies    -    Lecce -    -   -   -    *Corfu-    Catania    -    Malta -    Tunis -    -   -    -    Gabes -    TripoliLong. 20oE.-30oE.    Sulina-    Braila-    Bucharest  -   * Burgas    -   -   -   ^Constantinople -   -   *Gallipoli   *Salonica   -   -   -   *Kavala    -   *Trikala    -   -&quot;   -   *Larissa   *Volo -    -   -   *Arta -    -   *Lamia    -   -   *Missolongi  -   *Chalehis   -   -  &apos; .   *Smyrna   *Argostoli (Cephalonia)   *Patras    -   -   &apos;   * Athens   *Andros    -   -   .   *Sainos   *Zante -    -   -  &apos; -   *Nauplia   -   -   .   *Syra -    -   -   -   *Calamate   -   *Sparta  :  -   *Naxos    -   -   -   *Cythera   -   -   *Thera (Santorin) -   *Canea-    -   *Candia    -   -  ;  Benghazi   -   -
                      OF  THE               &apos;   &apos;     CH.Ai:Issued by Authority of the. Meteorological Committee.
    In September the majority of the depressions which traverse the Mediterraneanpass  to  the  north of  the 40th  parallel, but  in  October  they are  more  widelydistributed, at id range  as far as the  African Coast  and even to  the south of it.Fewer disturbances pass along the west coast of  Spain into  the Gulf of Genoa, buta much larger number enter the Mediterranean from the Bay of Biscay over south-western France.   Of  these (path No. 1) a proportion move over northern Italy andthence into Central Europe, while others pass eastwards over the Black Sea.  PathNo. 3 along the Adriatic coincides with the tracks of some depressions, and a largenumber pass from west to east between the parallels of 30o and 40&apos; (path No. 2). Amuch larger proportion pass over the Black Sea, the Aegean and the  Levant thanin September, two or three depressions traversing these regions each year.    Thedepressions winch enter from the Bay of Biscay are frequently  of considerableintensity and give rise to gales and rough sea in the Gulf of Lyons.  In the AegeanSea and the T-astern  Mediterranean the  strongest  winds occur when atmosphericpressure is high over  Southern Russia, and a steep gradient extends from there to   _________._______^____________________Egypt and tlitji Sudan.   Depressions of some intensity passing to the  north of the Aegean Sea occasionally cause strong southerly winds in.the Aegean Sc-a, but these are less common than the northerly gales.     The Daily Weather  Chart (A) for 8 a.m. on  the 25th October,  1908, shows the conditions accompanying a depression which had been lying over the WesternMediterranean for some days, and on this date developed considerable intensity ; strong north-westerly winds occurred in the Gulf of Lyons and south-easterly winds inthe Gulf of Genoa, as well as strong southerly winds on the coast of Sicily and the south of the Adriatic. At  the same time the high  pressure over Southern Russiaproduced a steep gradient  over the Black Sea and the Aegean, causing very strong northerly winds and a high sea at Athens.     The Daily Weather  Chart (B) for 8 a.ui. on the 16th October, 1911, illustrates stormy weather in the -Egean Sea which was due to a high pressure occurring over theBalkans and South-Eastern Europe.  Violent northerly grinds aud a very rough sea  were recorded  at Athens on this and the three following days, during which time thehigh pressure sysMm maintained its position.     The Daily  Weather  Chart (C) for 8  a.m. shows the conditions prevailing on the 24th  October, 1912, when a depression of some intensity passed, over the Black Sea,causing strong southerly winds with a rough sea and rain at Athens.  Conditions became more settled on the following day as the depression moved TO the eastward.     Some depressions lend to  persist for two, three aud eveu more days in  the Western Mediterranean without much change \A position, hut  those which passfurther eastward usually  maintain  their rate of movement, except in some cases where they are delayed on the Syrian coast, causing unsettled weather in  the levant.Iditions,  whichIlly  establishedlulation of airloccupies SouthRoumania and Southern Russia is abnormally high.   These winds haveoften a greater velocity than would be anticipated from the barometricffradient,  and  are descending winds  of  the &quot;Bora&quot;, type  coming  down &quot;ftni^ the high-Jgff-dgi^^JBajfen Peqinanhv and  Greece.  They are     Sea  Temper.ature.-In. contrast to  September,  when the  coaststations  in  several regions had  temperatures above  that of  the sea, inCctober  the. sea temperatures are everywhere above that of the coastTemperatnres.. OVER. 75&quot; F.  are - now restricted ,to . the . Eastern  portio  Isobars are dland are numhel  The  computi(5,000 feet) are ifVELOCITY IA MEA   i ue rrequendlength of theobservations at Inumber of obsepoint of observi   Scale of freqi  The force ofby the feathers I  The mean terjshown in black  The mean teithe  depth of iffollowing scale:
IE Mediterranean[Ire  more  widely ithe south of it,;Bf of Genoa, but ffeeay over south- ibhern Italy and Hack Sea.   Path lijms, and a large 1 path No. 2). A the  Levant  than eke I) year,    Thejlof considerable[I in the Aegean rhon atmosphei iclas from there to  n____________________;ihe north of  the Aegean Sea occasionally cause strong southerly winds inIn.: FK the conditions accompanying a depression which had been lying over  the Western*;Jltroiig north westerly winds occurred in the Gulf of Lyons and south-easterly winds insfhe south of the Adriatic.  At the same time the high pressure over Southern RussiaSi northerly winds and a high sea at Athens.jijfeH stormy weather in the vKgeun Sea which was due to a high pressure occurring over the? fweu were recorded  at Athens on this and the three following days, during which time theIIn the 24th October, 1912, when a depression of some intensity passed over the Black Sea,I Became more settled on the following day as the depression moved to the eastward.I! the Western Mediterranean  without much change U1 position, but  those which passIp where they arc delayed on the Syrian coast, causing unsettled weather in the  Levant.E  Isobars are drawn in red showing the mean pressure ol the day,and are numbered in millibars and inches - IOI2 mb(29 89 in.)  The  computed  mean currents  of  the  upper  air  (1.500 to(i,000 feet) are indicated by arrows in red ; the figures denote theVELOCITY HI METROS PER SECOND AND MILES per hour  .--                                        ^ metres  per second.                                        20 miles per  hour.  &quot;Trie irequency of winds is shown  by wind-roses  in red.   Thelength of the lines indicates the proportion which the number ofobservations at any one point of the compass bears  to  the wholenumber of observations.  The centre of the wind-rose is on thepoint of observation.Scale of frequencyper cent.   Temperature In contrast to September, when  the;coast  in several  regions had temperatures above that of the  sea, injr the. sea temperatures  are  everywhere above  that  of  the coastTatures over 750 M\ are now restricted to the  Eastern l^rtion  The force of the winds in the Daily Weather Charts is shownby the feathers on the arrows :                                             Beaufort,                                              No.                O          Calm               0               y         Light       ^     1-3               X*         Moderate          4-7                           Strong      ...     8,9              IFF&quot;         Violent     ...     10,11                           Indicates direotion without  statement                               as to force.  The mean temperature for the month in degrees Fahrenheit isshown in black figures beside the station to which it refers.  The mean temperature of the surface of the sea is  shown  bythe  depth of  blue shading on  the  sea  area according  to  thefollowing scale :-                  ,_                   Over 15&apos;   1 ,    :  : &apos;  ]                   70o-75o     I-           j                   Under 70&apos;  I            &apos;
PLACE. Long. 10oW.-0o.     Bilbao     Corunna     Oporto     Lisbon     Cadiz-     Gibraltar  -     Malaga     Cartagena -     Alicante     Valencia  -     Nemours  -     Oran  -   -    -    - Long. (T-KTE.     Turin -   -    -    -     Perpignan -     Barcelona  -     Marseilles  -     Nice  -   -    - -   -     Genoa-   -    -     Mahon     Palma    ...     Tenes-    -     Algiers   -     Bona  -Long. 10oE.-20&quot;E.     Trieste     Pola   -     Ancona     Liana    -    -    -     Pelagosa  -.,     Leghorn  -    -     j.vDJS6 -   -     Foggia     Aap*ies     Lecce -    -     -    -    *Corfu-     Catania     Malta -   -    -    -     Tunis -   -    -    -     Gabes-     Tripoli Long. 20oE.-30oE.     Sulina-   -     Braila-     Bucharest  -   * Burgas   -    -    -   ^Constantinople  -   *Gallipoli  -   *Salonica   *Kavala   -    -   *Trikala   *Larissa   *Volo  -   -    -&apos;    -   *Arta  -   -    -    -   *Lamia   *Missolongi -   *Chalchis  -    -  &apos;  -   *Smyrna   -   *Argostoli (Cephalonia)   *Patras   * Athens   *Andros   *Samos   *Zante -   -    -   *Nauplia   -    -   *Syra  -   *Calamate  -   *Sparta   *Naxos   *Cythera   *Thera (Santorin) -   *Canea-   *Candia     Benghazi     Sidi Barrani     Alexandria - Long. 30oE.-45oE.     Odessa     Batum    -    -     Trebizond -     Samsun     Kyrenia     Famagusta -     Beirut     -     Port Said  -     Cairo -TEMPERATURE.   RAINFALL.MeanMax. 0F.6864686872.7171697572606968667775766573726870757480 380636466686874716974737578757775757676747372757674777873 .737177738178827083828486MeanMin. 0F.504952576057585155604850505754615953.40555454 JO 60 61 65 62 67484644505761575653525756586058556061596262636064625664626261626861695857686863In.5-515-943153-393-392-521-852-523-311-772-403-582-403-313-426-307-874-103-352-203-152-916-144883-943-982-135-794-962-05 t O / 3-35 6-34 3-98 2-60 3-39 1-58 1-02 1-541-611-261-501-582-522-801-730-873-311-891-615-322-402-991-141-734-493-351-731-731-933-822-281-693-423-311-021-610-870-941-810-470-630-321-389-493-352-761-021-890-080-04Mmf140151 80 86 85 64 47 64 84 45 61 91 61 84 87160200104 85 56 80 74156124100101 54147126 52TIT III 85 161 101 66 86 40 26 39 41 3? 38 40 64 71 44 22 84 48 41135 61 76 29 44114 85 44 44 49 97 58 43 87 84 26 41 22 24 46 12 16 35241 85 70 26 48  2  ]* These places are SHOWN ON the inset Map OF Greece AND the .^Eyean.Meteorological Office/South Kensington, London, S.W.
i 30-AO- &apos; ffiiiifl .., L i		B. 8A.M. I6.X. 1911. i 1 Scale, i:5o,ooo,ooo. ------i 1		30 3d      C. 8a.m. Z4.X. 1912.30 ao  Scale, 1.30,000,000.H I G h3f &apos;io- ]gypt and tlii&apos; Siiqthe Aegean Sea. hu     The Daily  WeattjMediterranean for somdthe Gulf of Genoa, as \]produced a steep gradjd     The Daily  WeatlBalkans and Sou1-h-Eashigh pressure sys :em m     The Daily  vVeatrjcausing strong so utlusrlj     Some depressionsfurther eastward miuaiO152025; m-100 Nautical IdileJ).   5&apos;M 100 Statute  Milet-&apos;-M KilomstresTbc1   03lO!7 mb;.(30-03in.)ioisUbT/ys y(30-ofein.)V^2,,^/1015 mb&apos; (39-97inJ\0 660A&apos;   KIOI5(29 97iIOI8(3006^oE.of Greenwich.2600IOI9 mt(30-09 i4Q.42403838261016(30 C74mb.oin)\VI   .?J --a.   BfCn.7T\V3 j\^en\\\1016 mb.(30 00 in.)10&quot;20     Pressure The autumn type of meteorological  conditions, which began to develop in the  latter  half of September, is fully established by  October.    In  the Eastern  Mediterranean the  circulation  of  air currents is influenced mainly by the high pressure which occupies South and South-Eastern Russia,  and extends over the Balkans and  Greece. The low pressure over the  Persian Gulf has disappeared,  and one has formed in the  Sudan to the South, of Khartoum, towards  which the winds of Upi^r Egypt and the Sudan circulate round a high pressure area of no great intensity lying over Cyrenaica  and tbe Eastern  Sahara.    The Western Mediterranean shows a well-marked low pressure area having its centre over Corsica and Sardinia, with a  detached  area of low pressure in the Adriatic.  Lying- between the Algerian higlf-pressure area  and the westward  extensions of that of South-Eastern Europe, it is open on the North-West to invasion of depressions coming from the Atlantic, -and in some years these are very numerous.    Generally the principal features of October weather are the depressionswhich invade the Mediterranean from the West and North-West, and thehigh pressure in Southern Russia which is at times sufficiently developedto cause strong northerly and north-easterly gales in the yEgean Sea.    Winds.-The winds of  the Western Mediterranean are determined by the depressions which traverse it,  and  as many of these are  of con-siderable intensity, stormy weather is  not uncommon during the  month. At  Marseilles strong  north-westerly and  north-easterly  winds  are frequent as most of the depressions pass to the south of this place.    In the Eastern Mediterranean, in consequence of the  well-dennedbarometric gradient from Russia to the Sudan and the moderate intensityof the depressions which traverse it at this season, the prevalent winddirections are fairly  definite.    North-easterly  and  northerly   windsprevail in the iEgean, and northerly and north-westerly winds in Egypt.    In the jEgean Sea strong winds  (Beaufort Kos.6:JjO)-occur,  as manyas  63  days of  this character having been recorded in  the past  twelveyears.   Of these  about 20 per cent, are from the  southward, and  arecaused by depressions passing &quot;from West to East across the Black Sea.The remainder,  over 80 per cent.,  are northerly winds of  the type  ofthe &quot; Bora &quot; of the- Adriatic, and  may occur whenever the pressure over Roumania. and Southern Russia is often a greater velocity than  v?ould gradient,  arid are descending windl from the  high, land  of the Balkan! associated with, fine weather rather neighbourhood of  the  land develorj Smyrna, compared with those  of Atl the whole width of the iEgean, but f away  from the  high  land.   As i position  but slowly,  these strong nori to four,  and occasionally even  seven.I    These northerly gales are general] I but not invariably, as the deveiopmei northward may coincide with a dim] the Mediterranean, and the passageI ranean to the South of Greeoe unj some exceptional!y protracted and via]    Bainfall. The  rainy   swison occasional  thunderstorms becor-ies ml the Western  Mediterranean, the  Ocif which  falls in September, in conseq-j which  occur  in the  course  of  this recorded on the French Coast and In the Central portion of the MediteJ proportionals rather less, but corisicof the Adriatic,  which is  within tJ In the -Egean Sea- and Greece,  Octlthat  of September, when it is  asso-lstorms.   In October falls of rain injassociated with the various depressionMediterranean.  Streams and marshJsummer are now filled,  and  all vegetj    In Lower  Egypt rain is scanty.the Coast, with, in some years, athunlthe sum  of rainfall in this  month.S.W.PRINTED  UNDER  THE  AUTHORITY  OF   HIS  MAJESTYS STATIONERY  OFFICE.W.O. B2BS. S00.3/IS.  M.O.B3B7/S/I5.
   Twran Sea, but these are less common than the northerly gales,the Aegean o^,                          .     ..  nr,tinhfir -igna ahowgIPUP^9l^it-J^^TSdffi sTron^                                          of.the Adriatic  At the sa^ne time the high pressure over Southern EusS1aT^lkaJs Mid South-Bwtern Europe. Violent northerly grinds and a very rough sea were recorded athiJrh measure system maintained its position.mgn pressure ojB&apos;,                .^Southern Russia is abnormally high.   Theso -winds havejl- velocity than  would  be anticipated from the barometricI are  descending winds  of  the &quot;Bora&quot; type  coming down[8 land  of the Balkan Peninsula  and Greece.  They  arell fine weather rather than  unsettled weather,  and in  theI of  the  land develop  violent gusts.    Observations  atsired  with those of Athens, show  that  these winds affectlh  of the ^Egean, but they are probably  of less intensityiHe  high  land.   As high-pressure  systems  change  theirjUHvly, these strong northerly winds may prevail from one(Ccasioually even seven and  eight days.ijperly gales are generally  associated with a rising barometer,jlbly, as the development of a high-pressure system to theV coincide with a diminution of pressure on the shores of[mean, and the passage of a depression along the Mediter-M South of  Greeoe under these conditions  has producedBpljy protracted and violent northerly gales in  the .%ean.ii-Tho  rainy  season  which began  in September  with  derstorms becomes much  more general  in October.   In  editerranean, the October rainfall is about  double that  September,  in  consequence of the numerous depressions   the course of this  month.  Considerable amounts are    French Coast and  along the western coast of Italy.  jortion of the Mediterranean, including  theAdriatic, the  .ther Jess^ but considerable quantities fall at the  head  ,  which is  within the influence of many depressions.  Sea  and Greece, October rainfall is more than double  iber,  when  it  is associated usually with locaTthunder-  ober falls of rain increase in &quot;frequency and are often  the various  depressions which now traverse the Eastern   Streams and  marshes which had dried up during the    filled,  and all  vegetation revives.  gypt  rain is scanty.  A few  showers at Alexandria and  in some years, a thunderstorm at places inland, represent  iiall  in  this month.     Sea  Temperature In.. contrast to September,  when the j coaststations in several regions had temperatures above that of the sea,  inOctober the  sea  temperatures are  every where above that of the coastTemperatures over 750  F. are now restricted to the Eastern  jjortionof  the Levant,  while  most  of  the Western Mediterranean does notreach 70o F.   Generally it may be  said that  the sea surface temperatureof the Mediterranean is about 4Q to 5Q F. lower than in September.     Mist and Fog The number of observations of mist and  fog arenot  sufficient to  justify  any complete representation of its distributionin this month.   Along  the steamer track from Gibraltar to Port Said10 per cent,  of the observations between Spain and Morocco recordedmist;  east of this the percentage is lower,  being between 5 per cent, and6  per cent,  up  to the 15th  meridian, with  somewhat higher  valuesbetween Sicily and Tunis.  In the Eastern Mediterranean the proportionis less, being between 2 per cent,  and 3 per cent, from Sicily to PortSaid, though higher values occur to the South and West of Crete, andto the South of the Adriatic.   On the Coast of France and in the Gulfof Genoa about 10 per cent,  of  observations record mist or  fOg, whilealong  the Western coast of  Italy  the proportion&apos; is about 7 per  cent.In the iEgean conditions vary greatly; at Athens Observatory  mist  isrecorded in  -October on  about  fouT - days  out. of  five,  while - on thesteamer track up to the Dardanelles 3- per cent, to 4 per cent, is aboutthe  average  amount.     Temperature.^ Temperature  falls rapidly   in  October, and  themean temperature of the day at coast stations of the Northern partsof the Mediterranean is from 60 F. to 80 F. below that of September,while  on the African and Syrian  Coasts it amounts  to  about 40&apos;F.In Greece and the ^Egean Sea the mean maximum has fallen from about830 F. to about 740 F.,  and the mean minimum  (from  about 650 F. to60o F.,. while the absolute minimum may  be  between 450 F. and 500 F.     The lowest mean temperatures occur on the Coast of France,  atthe  head of  the  Adriatic and in the Black  Sea, where the mean  tern-perature of Odessa is 620  F;  The highest mean  temperatures are dis-tributed along the African Coast  from  Tunis eastwards  and  up  theCoast  of Syria._.____BJEKEE  Isobars are drawn in red showing the meaiand are numbered in millibars and inches  The computed  mean  currents  of  theIS.O00 feet) are indicated by arrows in red ;  tlvehoiiy hi metres per s&amp;soad and mites per a  Trie ireqiieiieybt w inds is shown  by winlength of  the  lines indicates the proportionobservations at any one point of the  compas.number of observations.  The centre of thepoint of observation.   Scale of frequency   &quot;_1_j!_  The force of the winds in  the Daily Weatby the feathers on the arrows               Q         Calm              S*         Light       ^                          Moderate                          Strong                          Violent                          Indicates direction                              as to force.  The mean temperature  for the month in dashown in black figures beside the station to wlj  The mean temperature of the surface of tlthe  depth of blue  shading on  the sea areifollowing scale :                   Over 75&quot;   i            1   j                  70 -75      1           J   :                  Under  70&apos;  1      -1Printed &amp;t&apos; the Meteorological Office, South Kensington, Londaa, S.W.By Wyhak &amp; Sons, Ltd., Fetter Lure, London, E.C., and Heading.
 i)f  considerable .  In the AegeanMen atmosphericilef northofthe0 Aegean Sea occasionally cause strong southerly muds in&quot;HI:SH,,. conditions accompanying a depression which had been lying over the Western Si mr    thSw-rinTwNo birred in the Gulf of Lyons and south-easterly winds in ife&quot;outh of  the Adriat,&quot; At the same time the high pressure over Southern Busstaftlomly SeT^t^ffi^S was due to a high pressure .oaa,rring over the j$, wireM-orded at Athens on this and the three following days, during which time theII the ?4th October. 1912, when a depression of some intensity passed over the Black Sea, S-ime more    etl on the following day as the depression moved to the eastward. lit    ten,     ter[,,,ean without  much  change of position, hut  those which pass Ivhere thev arc DHHRJEDUNJLIO Syrian coast, causing unsettled weather in the Levant. &apos;J-*        40&apos;                          45&quot;     temperature lu contrast  to September,  when the  coast   -^jsev-eral regions had  temperatures above that of the sea, in     $ sea temperatures arc  everywhere above that of the coastlrtflltes over      F. are  now restricted to the Eastern  portion Vbigant,  while  most of  the Western Mediterranean does notMINI  ^encrauy &apos;1 may ^e  said that  the sea surface temperature..).;.;- Sterranean is about 40 to 50  F. lower than in September. . v&quot;ilnd Fog: The number of observations  of mist and  fog are     it to  justify any complete representation of its distribution^ifeith.   Along  the steamer track from Gibraltar to Port SaidHHI of the observations between Spain and  Morocco recorded        this the percentage is lower, being between 5 per cent, and       up  to the 15th meridian,  with  somewhat higher  values     :jjly and Tunis.  In the Eastern Mediterranean the proportion v yjg between  2 per cent,  and 3 per cent,  from Sicily to Port   0h higher values occur to the  South and West of  Crete, and     t of the Adriatic.  On  the Coast of France and in the Gulf     -pout  10 per cent, of  observations record mist or  fog,  while     --Western coast of Italy  the  proportion  is about 7 per cent.     Tan conditions vary greatly; at Athens  Observatory mist is     1 October on about  four  days  out. of five,  while  on the     Ik up to the Dardanelles 3 per cent, to  4 per cent,  is about     I amount.     Stature Temperature  falls  rapidly  in October, and the     ijrature of the day at coast stations of  the Northern  parts     Berranean is from 60 F. to 80 F. below that of September,   Ht African  and Syrian Coasts it amounts to  about 40  F.        the ^Egean Sea the mean maximum has fallen from about       YUT  740 F., and the mean minimum  tfrom about 650 F. to        the absolute  minimum may be between 45D F. and 500 F.      j est mean temperatures occur on  the Coast of France, at       the Adriatic and in the Black  Sea,  where the mean tern     I Odessa is 620  F. The highest mean  temperatures are dis-     I ig the  African  Coast from  Tunis eastwards  and  up the     I ri _;_   &apos;        _&apos;EXPLANATION.  Isobars are drawn in red showing the mean pressure 0! the day,and are numbered in millibars and inches - 1012 mb.(89 89 in.)  The  computed mean  currents  of  the  upper  air  (1,500 to(i,000 feet) are indicated by arrows in red ; the  figures denote thevelocity hi metres per second and miles per hour                     ^--9 metres  per second.                                        20 miles per hour.   ine frequency ot winds is shown by  wind-roses in red.   Thelength of the lines indicates the proportion  which the number ofobservations at any one point of the compass bears  to the wholenumber of observations.   The centre of the wind-rose  is on tin:point of observation.   c,   ,   j- ,              0     as     50     -75     100   bcaie or frequency :-  1-1-1--1-1    per cent.  The force of the winds in  the Daily Weather  Charts is shownby the feathers on the arrows0CalmLightModerateStrongViolentBeaufort,   .N0.    0   1-3   4-7   8,9  10, 11Indicates direction without statement-    as to force.  The mean temperature for the month in degrees Fahrenheit isshown in black figures beside the station to which it refers.  The mean temperature of the surface of the sea is  shown  bythe  depth of blue  shading on the  sea  area according  to  thefollowing scale:                   Over 75&quot;    1 -           I                  70o-75T     I           3                  Under  70&quot;  L    .....]Printed at the Meteorological Office, South Kensington, London, S.W.By WTMAK &amp; SOW, LID.. Fetter Lane, London, B.C., and Keadtyg.
                                  Temperature.    6. The mean temperature of the  day from October to April is  given in Table Ifor the four groups of  stations.  In all there is a considerable fall  of  temperatureamounting to from 90 to 10o F. in November as compared with October, and Januaryis in  every case the month having the lowest mean temperature.    7. Tables II and III give the mean daily maximum and the mean daily minimumtemperatures for the same stations, and thus indicate the limits between Avhich thetemperatures experienced during the  day will ordinarily lie.  Here too January is themonth of the lowest temperature, and the  maximum daily  temperature  ranges from54\50 F.  among  the  islands to 49&apos;S0 F. on the north  coast of the iEgean,  while theminimum daily temperature is everywhere about 10o F. lower.    8. The absolute minimum or lowest temperature recorded varies considerably, andthe stations in the north coast and the  west coast groups are therefore shown separately,in Table IV where the mean of the lowest temperature recorded in each month duringthe period for which observations  are  available is  given.  This indicates the lowesttemperature which is to be expected in each month.    9. At  all  stations except Cythera, off  the south  coast of Greece, temperaturesbelow freezing point have been recorded  in  January,  and  usually in  Februaryas well.    10.  At the same time  years  vary greatly in  this respect,  and  much lowertemperatures are frequently experienced, especially on the north and west coasts.  Thelowest temperatures which have been recorded during the period for which observationsexist are : -                                                                    0 F.        Constantinople    .,     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    24-3        Kavala  . .      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    21-9        Salonica  . .      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    19-1        Volo    ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    19-4        Ohalchis ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..   -19-4        Athens  ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    21-2        Cythera  ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    28-4        Audros  ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    26-0        Syra    ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    30*5        Naxos   ..      ..     ..      .,      ..      ..     ..      ..    29-8        Santorin ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    28-4        Smyrna  ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     .,      , .    264        Samos   ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      ..     ..      ..    25-1    These lowest temperatures have in most cases been recorded in January, but thoseat Chalchis, Cythera, and Syra occurred in February.                                    Snowfall.    11. Table VII, which shows the number of days  on which snow fell,  may  bereferred to in connection with low temperatures.  At Constantinople snow falls on theaverage on  18 days in the year, January and February being the months most affected,since each has on the average b&apos; days of snowfall.    12. Kavala  and  Salonica experience exceptionally low temperatures when  thenortherly winds  sweep down from the highlands of Macedonia, and at Salonica snowfalls on about 5  days in each year, the greatest number recorded in  any one monthbeing  9  in January  1903.   For Kavala  no  snowfall  has  been recorded,  but itprobably occurs.   On the 23rd January, .1903, the temperature at Salonica fell to 190 F.,and from the 16th to the 25th was between 19QF. and 260F. at night; snow fell on thefirst two days, and on the 23rd and  24th the water of the bay was covered with iceabout half an inch thick for over a very considerable area.                                     Frost.    13. Frost is  only rarely recorded at stations south of Athens, where it occurs onthe average 4 times in the  year.  On the north coast of the iEgean it is much morefrequent, the corresponding  numbers  for Volo and Salonica being 10  and 20, and forSmyrna 14.   At  Volo in January 1905 frost was recorded on 15 days.
88                                    Rainfall.    14. The mean monthly rainfall is given for each station in the north coast groupin Table V, the other groups  are  represented by mean values which depart but littlefrom the values for  any station in the group.   December and January are, in mostcases, the wettest months, though on the east coast November is the month of heaviestrainfall.  As Athens is  the  only station from which daily observations for a series ofyears are available, it is difficult to  speak with certainty as to the relation of rainfall tothe different winds, but at-Athens rain occurs  with northerly winds as well as withsoutherly and  south-westerly winds, and the same probably holds good for other partsof the iEgean Sea.    15. The rainfall is well distributed through the month, as  may be  seen fromTable VI, in which the average number of rainy days in each month are given fromNovember to March; these  number from 6 to 8 in each month at Kavala and Salonica,and about 10 to 12 at other  stations.                                     Winds.    16.  In consequence  of  the  redistribution  of  atmospheric pressure  which takesplace  in September, the  Eastern Mediterranean  has the  high-pressure  system ofSouthern Russia to the north and north-east, with a less developed high-pressure arealying  over  Tripoli and Cyrenaica to  the  south.   The Mediterranean, the waters ofwhich are warmer than the air temperature of the land from October onwards, becomesa well-defined area of low pressure,  and lies  in the track  of numerous cyclonicdepressions which traverse  it from west to east.  The predominance of the northwinds which was  so  strongly marked throughout the summer months, and whichcontinued in  September and most of October, becomes markedly less in the wintermonths,  November to March, when the southerly and the south-westerly winds increasein importance.  But even in  the winter the northerly winds  outnumber the  southerlywinds very considerably.   As the stations for  which observations  are available aresituated   on a deeply-indented coast-line and  have usually high land  immediatelybehind them,  local variations of the normal wind directions occur at many stations.    17.  In Table VIII therefore the averages  for the four west-coast stations and thefour island stations are given as being  sufficiently representative of these regions.AVind roses for all  these and many other stations in Greece, the. iEgean Sea, and theBlack Sea are given in the monthly meteorological charts of  the Mediterranean, whichare  now in course of publication.   The wind directions in the different months  fromNovember to  March do not  differ very markedly, so that  mean values for the winterseason,  November to March, have been  given in Table VIII, where the  numbersindicate the number of times in 100 observations that the wind blows from the directionsnamed.    18.  At Constantinople (Bojuk Dere) northerly winds outnumber the southerly inthe  proportion of 5 to  3; at Kavala  easterly winds are more  numerous;  while atSalonica, while northerly winds  predominate, the high percentage of calms (33 percent.) is noticeable.  In  both the west coast and the island  groups the  northerlywinds are the more numerous, being about 5 to 3 southerly winds.                             Gales and State of Sea.    19.  Detailed information regarding  the force of the wind in the iEgean  Sea isscanty, being usually limited to the average force  or velocity of the wind during amonth, without any reference to individual days.  For Salonica the average number of&quot;strong&quot; winds is given for each month  on  the basis  of  11 years  of  observations.These winds are probably of force Beaufort No. 6 and upwards, and the majority ofthem may be attributed to the  northerly winds which have been  already mentioned(see Table IX).
    20. Athens  is the only station  in  the iEgean Sea from which daily observationsof wind and sea are available for any  considerable period.  At Smyrna the wind isreported on daily for 8 years, but not the sea disturbance.    21.  On examination, the daily weather  reports from Athens  for  the  12 years1902-1913 show that  strong winds and rough  sea were reported as  existing at 8 a.m.on a large number of  days.   These have been abstracted, and their  distribution is set.out in Table X, where all days on which sea was  reported as &quot; rough,&quot; &quot; very rough,&quot;or &quot;high &quot; are shown, even though in some cases  the wind  is given as being as low asBeaufort Scale No. 5* (moderate).  Additional columns (Nos. 3 and 4 for each month)give the number of days on which the  reports  give the wind as  being  of  gale force,omitting the days on which it was less  strong.  In the fifth column the number of galesof over 2 days&apos; duration is entered.    22. Practically all  the strong  winds lie between N.W.-N.E.,  which  have beenclassed as northerly, or between S.S.E.-S.W., which have  been classed  as southerly,but a few westerly winds,  usually of no great  strength, are recorded, and  these havebeen included in the northerly or southerly group, according as they  followed a  gale ofthe former or the latter character.    23. The gales of  October are  of the same type as  those  of September, and  aremost conveniently discussed apart from those of the winter months.    24. At Athens strong winds (&quot; moderate&quot;  to &quot; violent &quot;) and rough seas (&quot;rough  &quot;to &quot; high &quot;) were recorded  on 85 days  in September and 63 days in October  in  thecourse of twelve years.  Of the 85 days in September the wind was from between northand north-east on 79 occasions, and from south on 6 occasions.    In October northerlywinds were recorded  on 52 days and  southerly  winds on 11  days. The details aregiven in Table X.   During- these twelve  years no strong  winds were  reported fromAthens  in  the  daily  weather,  reports,  except  from X.-N.E. or  S.-S.W.   Thefrequency of these gales varies  considerably from year  to year ; thus  in  September1909 and in October 1903 and  1909 none were recorded,  while 12 and 13 occurredin  September in  the years   1902  and 1907  respectivelv,  and 9  in October 1908and 1913.    25. The conditions which determine these strong winds at Athens are well deiined.The southerly and south-westerly gales occur when  a depression passes  from west toeast across the northern part of the  iEgean  Sea  or across the Black  Sea, and itsapproach  can usually be  indicated by meteorological observations  at Malta and  tin-Italian stations, which show the  advance  of  such a low-pressure system.   Thesedepressions move at  a moderate speed, so that  their effect  lasts in the  iEgean  Seausually for one and only occasionally for two days.    26.  The great majority  of the gales in September and  October (93 and  83 percent.) are from the north, and these occur when the atmospheric pressure is  abnormallyhigh over the Balkans, the Carpathians, or Southern Russia,  so that a  comparativelysteep gradient is formed towards the south.  These gales  may be of any duration, sincethey depend upon the occurrence of a high-pressure system  to the  northward, whichprobably changes its position  but slowly, and in the twelve years under review theirduration lias been from 1  to 8 days.   Since they  are associated with high-pressureconditions, a barometer at any station in the iEgean will  usually  rise, but  this  is  notinvariably the case, since the  formation of a high-pressure system over Southern  Russiamay coincide with a reduction of pressure or the shores of  the Mediterranean.    27.  In September  1902  a depression  passed along  the  Mediterranean while  thepressure over the Balkans was rising, and the  combined effect of  these  two  causesresulted  in. a northerly gale, which lasted for 8  days; a similar  case occurred inSeptember 1906.              *Beauforfc Scale No. 5 Moderate Breeze.                       V  ^jjstrong Winds.                  &apos;1        No. 8 Gale.                       ,,  No. 9  Strong Gale.
     28.  The velocity of the wind in these northerly gales, which are frequently from 6  to 8, and occasionally 9 (strong  gale), on the Beaufort Scale, is in  excess  of that which would be anticipated from the barometric gradient, and is due partly to the air descending abruptly from the high ground to sea level.   Thus  these winds are similar in their  general character and mode of  occurrence to  the &quot;Bora&quot; of  the Adriatic. Like  it,  they are  characterised by strong gusts and  by a very  variable period  of duration.     29.  Daily observations are available for  a  few (6)  years  from Smyrna, and the wind observations there show that the gales recorded at Athens occur also at Smyrna; but they appear there to be of somewhat diminished intensity.     30.  It may be said, therefore, that northerly winds of gale force are liable to occur at any time  in  September and October, when  the atmospheric  pressure over the Balkans and Southern Russia is sufficiently high;  that  these gales may last for from 1 to 4, and occasionally even 8 days; that they affect the whole of the /Egean, but are less violent away from the high land; that they are associated with line rather  than xmsettled weather.    31.  In each of the six months, November to April, the Mediterranean occupies an area of low pressure in the mean distribution of  atmospheric pressure for the month, high-pressure  areas  lying to the north  and north-east over  the  Balkans, Southern Russia, and to the north-east of the Caspian Sea on the one haud, and over Tripoli and Cyrenaica on the other.    32. Normally, therefore, the winds blowing over Mgean Sea are  northerly, and thisis well illustrated in the 12-year period under review, during which  a total of 273 days show  strong  northerly  winds,  while only 113 days  of  strong southerly  winds arerecorded, these being distributed as follows : Winds.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Northerly .. Southerly Total	4G 26	39 32	66 19	46 10	43 12	33 14	72	71	85	56	55	46    33. As the rapidly moving depressions, which traverse the Mediterranean in largenumbers during the winter months, are largely effective in causing the strong winds inthe iEgean Sea, gales Of considerable duration are less common during the winter thanin September and October, when a high-pressure system is stationary over the  Balkanarea, frequently causes several days of high wind.  In September and October 17 galesof over two days&apos; duration were recorded, and these comprised 73 days.   During thesix months November to April, 27 gales of more than two days&apos; duration occurred, andthey included 108 days, Or about half the  frequency of the gales of the autumn months.    34. In November the high pressure which lies over the Balkans is less pronouncedthan in October, and though it is  maintained throughout  the winter months, it  has nolonger so  dominating  an  influence as it exercised in the  autumn.  In the  wintermonths, and especially in November, December, and January, numerous depressionspass along the Mediterranean from west  to&apos;east, or across the Balkan Peninsula  andthe Black  Sea.  According as they pass to the-north or to the south of the iBgeah Sea,they gife rise to winds from southerly or  northerly directions, which are frequently ofgale force whenever the intensity of the depression  is considerable.  Southerly galesmay occur when the  depression centre  is Over Italy or the Adriatic, and  strongnortherly  gales arise when a high pressure over the Balkan  area coincides with thepassage of a depression from the neighbourhood  of Malta towards the  Levant.   Manyof these depressions are of no great extent, and move with considerable rapidity, oftencovering 500 nautical miles  in the 24 hours, so that change in direction and windforce may take  place rapidly  and with little warning.   They also may vary greatly inintensity in their transit of the Mediterranean.
                                  Mist and Fog.    35. The observations for mist and fog are too few to give a satisfactory guide tothe conditions existing in the winter months.   The coast stations are much affected bytheir local conditions,&apos; and the results  recorded vary widely.   Athens records mist onfrom  20 to 24 days  in each month, Chalchis records but 2  or  3 days  in  the  year,and Volos about the same number.  At the islands of  Andros and Santorin an averagenumber of 20  and 24 days for  the 7 months from  October to April are recorded asmisty or foggy, while at Syra and Naxos the number is but 10 and 3 respectively.    36. At Salonica the average number during these same months is 20, of which thegreatest number occur in December.  While  the average number of misty and foggydays in this month is  6, there were 25 such days in December 1910 and 15 in 1909.                                    Summary.    37. Temperature is low during  December, January, and February, and on thenorth coast of the iEgean Sea sharp frosts may occur  during any of these months.  Itshould be noticed that the northerly winds are  usually dry, so that the cold is felt asmuch keener than the reading of the thermometer would indicate, since the relativehumidity may be  very low, 40 per cent, at 8 A.M. having  been recorded at Athens notinfrequently during a northerly gale.    38. The rainfall is fairly considerable  at all stations, averaging nearly 3 inches permonth from November to February, except at Salonica and Kavala, where the amountis much less.    39. Snow falls at most stations two or three times in most years, and much morefrequently (18) at Constantinople.    40. The winds are  mainly northerly (40 per cent, to 50 per  cent.), but  southerlywinds constitute  about 20 per cent, to  30 per cent., and this  proportion holds fairlywell  for  all the winter months  (November to  March).   October  has  a greaterpredominance of northerly  winds, and  as  regards its winds is more closely related toSeptember than to the winter months.    41. The information relating to gales  and state of sea is limited to the neighbour-hood of Athens, but such data as are available from Salonica and Smyrna in no wayconflict with those of Athens, where 3 to 5 days of gales (Beaufort, Nos. 8 and 9) arerecorded in each month on the average.    42. The conditions  of high pressure  over Southern  Russia which favour theoccurrence of  northerly gales can  be  notified in  the forecasts of the MeteorologicalOffice from day to day, but  gales do not invariably occur when such conditions occur ;in fact, it often happens that after one or two days of high wind a day of comparativecalm  may  occur,  to  be  followed the  next day by a renewal  of the northerly  gale.Depressions traversing  the Mediterranean may cause northerly and southerly winds,according as their centres pass to the south  or north of the point concerned, and inmost cases the advance of such depressions can be indicated in the daily forecast; butit may be difficult to anticipate closely the course which the centre will follow.    43. The extreme conditions  which  may be  anticipated  at Gallipoli  may  beapproximately estimated from the  results  recorded  at other  stations  in the NorthiEgean Sea.    The lowest temperature Avhich is likely to be experienced in January will probablybe about 280 F. or, if this winter  should be an exceptionally cold one, 26Q F.    Three or  four occurrences of snowfall and six  or eight of slight frost may bereasonably anticipated.    Four or five days of strong winds  seem to be indicated by the records of Salonica,and of these one-third are ordinarily from the south-west.
MEAN Temperature.Place.	October	November	. December.	January	. February.	March.	April.North coast West coast Islands Bast coast	0 P. 0 F. 62-6 52-7 67-6 i 57 2 69-4 1 59-9 66-2 57-6		46-4 51-6 55-2 50-7	41-4 48-2 52-5 47-1	0 F. 43-5 50-7 53-8 49-6	48-4 53-6 55-9 52-2	0 P. 55-9 58-8 60-6 59-2* TABLE II. MEAN Daily Maximum.							Place. j October. !		November.&apos; December.		January.	February.	March.	April. DF. 63-3 66.9 64-8 64-6North coast West coast Islands East coast	0 F. 69-6 74-3 72-9 72-0	58-8 63-0 64-2 &apos; 63-5	0 F. 52-3 57-7, 59-4 56-7	0 F. 48-2 53-2 54-5 52-5	49-8 56-3 57-4 55-4	DF. 55-4 59-9 59-7 56-1	TABLE III. MEAN Daily Minimum.							1 i ! Place. ! October, j November.! 1			December. 1	January.	February.	-March.	April. 0 P. 49-1 51-1 54-3 53-2North coast West coast Islands East coast	0 F. 57-9 59-0 63-0 61-7	0 F. 49-3 51-4 55-4 54 - 5	43-2 46-0 51 -3 48-2	&quot;F. 39-4 41-4 47-1 43-9	0F. 39-9 42-8 48-0 46-4	O 43-7 45-9 49-6 40-6	            TABLE IV.MEAN of Absolute Minimum of Month.Place.	October.	November.	December.	January.	February.	i March. \ April. 1	Constantinople Kavala Salonica Volo ...... Chalclris Athens Cythera Islands East coast . f.- -	0 P. 48-4 48-0 44-8 , 48-2 ! 48-9 51-3 ! 54-9 ; 56-3 47-1	&quot; P. 37-9 36-1 32-0 37-0 38-8 41-5 45*7 46-0 38-7	0 P. 83-3 33-4 26-4 30-9 34-3 34-7 40-3 40-6 30-4	CP. 28-2 22-8 23-7 27-5 31-8 31-6 37-6 37-9 28-0	0 P. 26-2 29-1 26-8 30-6 33-4 33-1 38-5 39-2 29-5	0F. 30-6 34-9 30-6 34-0 34-7 35-8 41-5 41-2 28-8	0 P. 36-7 41-2 36-7 39-2 40-1 43-9 46-4 46-8 42-6Meteorological Office, September 7, 1915.
MEAN Monthly Rainfall, in inches.Place.	October.	November.	December.&apos; January.		February.	March.	April.Constantinople Kavala ... Salonica West coast .. Islands East coast	2-52 0-87 1-73 1-73 1-14 2-76	4-02 2-72 1-97 2-87 2-91 4-02	4-80 3-23 1-97 3-11 3-58 3-62	3-42 2-80 1-26 2-13 3-39 3-15	2-72 3-19 0-87 1-81 2-24 2-28	* 2-44 2-72 1-10 1-73 1-61 2-91	1-65 1-93 1-61 0-94 0-94 2-60The rainfall in inches at the undermentioned places is given for comparison with the amounts shown in Table V : 							Place.	October.	November.	December,	January.	February.	March.	April.London Salisbury Glasgow	2-64 3-77 3-&apos;58	2-34 3-35 3-55	2-20 3-60 3-96	1-78 2-78 3-40	1-72 2-60 2-79	1-71 2-24 2-66	1-76 2-31 2-15TABLE VI. MEAN Rainy Days, per month.							Place.	October.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Constantinople Kavala Salonica West coast Islands East coast	6 3 6 6 4 6	11 8 7 0 18 10	14 9 8 10 11 12	12 6 0 10 12 12	11 10 6 10 12 11	10 8 6 10 8 11 j *	8 6 7 6 5 7TABLE VII. DAYS on which Snow fell.							Place.	October.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Average per annum  Constantinople Number in 12 years  Salonica ... &apos; .. Number of days in 8 years  Volo Chalchis Athens Andros Syra Naxos Santorin Number in 4 years  Samos ..		0-6 6 1 2 2 * *	2-9 6 2 4 6 7 1 3 1 * *	5*5 25 5 15 15 12 5 5 5 1	6-0 13 9 12 9 12 11 10 11 1	3-0 9 3 1 3 1 2	0-2 2
WIND Directions.  Percentage.  November to March.Place.	N.	N.E.	E.	S.B.	S.	S.W.	W.	N.W.	C.Constantinople (Bojuk Dere) Kavala Salonica West coast .. Islands Smyrna Samos .. .. .. ..	20-5 12-0 20-2 24-4 28-0 10-4 . 5-5	29-8 2-0 12-0 11-3 20-4 15-2 5-8	1-9 30-0 9-3 5-0 5-4 19-6 11-2	1-0 7-0 5-4 8-3 6-8 12-3 11-5	13-3 11-0 3-2 11-1 13-4 12-8 11-5	17-2 7-0 6-0 9-1 10-4 3-5 2-3	2-4 13-0 3-6 8-4 7-4 8&apos;6 3-1	2-9 8-0 6.-9 19-4 6-0 2-5 22-1	10-8 10-0 33-4 5-3 2-6 12-1 27-0                TABLE  IX.AVERAGE Number of Days of &quot; Strong Winds.Place.	October.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Salonica	2-4	4-3	3-0	5-1	4-1	5-7	3-7
Year.	October.					! November.					December.					January.					February.					March.					Days of Wind, Beaufort, !	April.				Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 5-9.		Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 8 and 9.		*Gales over 2 days&apos; duration.	Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 5-9.		o u-i J3 cS CD 23 . 9 CO co O ft		.les over 2 days&apos; duration.	Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 5-9.		Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 8 and 9.		*Gales over 2 days&apos; duration.	Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 5-9.		Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 8 and 9.		&quot;Gales over 2 days&apos; duration.	Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 5-9.		Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 8 and 9.		*Gales over 2 days&apos; duration.	Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 5-9.		Days of Wind, Beaufort, NTos. 8 and 9.		*Gales over 2 days&apos; duration.		era 1 CO o	Days of Wind, Beaufort, Nos. 8 and 9.		*Gales over 2 days&apos; duration.	N. j S.		N.	s.		N.	S.	N.	S.	a O *	N. S.		N. S.			N.	S.	N.	S.		N.	S.	N.	S.		N.	S.	N.	S.		N.	s.	N.	S.	1902 1903 1904 1905 1906 1907 1908 1909 1910 1911 1912 1913 Max. number in any year	1 0 2 0 8 8 9 0 8 5 2 9	1 0 1 6 0 0 0 0 0 1 2 0 0	1 0 2 0 2 3 5 o 4 5 1 6 (1	1 0 0 2 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0	h V	7 2 7 2 6 8 4 1 0 3 2 4	0 0 0 0 0 0 3 5 7 1 G 1	3 4 1 2 5 1 0 0 1 1	0 1 0 0 0 2 5 5 4 1	h h h h	6 3 3 4 5 2 2 2 3 3 1 5	1 5 2 1 7 4 6 0 2 0 0 4	3 2 2 4 2 1 1 2 1 1 1 3	1 3 2 1 3 1 2 0 0 0 0 2	h Is	5 6 o o 8 3 6 7 10 3 11 3 1	0 4 1 1 0 1 2 2 4 1 3 0	n o 4 3 4 3 2 5 7 1 4 2 7	i 0 1 1 0 0 1 1 1 4 0 2	h h h h h h h h	4 6 1 2 3 7 3 2 1 4 6 7	0 2 0 0 2 1 1 0 0 2 2 0	2 4 1 2 6 o O 2 1 1 4 4	0 0 0 2 1 0 0 0 0 1 0 2	1.3 h h	7 5 6 1 2 6 4 8 0 2 2	1 0 2 0 o 0 0 0 2 2 1 1 0	4 3 5 1 1 2 3 0 3 3 1 2	0 0 0 0 2 0 0 2 0 1 1 0	18 13 1 j,	6 1 2 2 3 3 0 6 1 3 5 1	0 6 0 0 2 i 2 0 0 0 3 0	3 1 1 3 2 0 4 1 1 3	0 4 0 1 1 2 0 0 0 0	Is 23 Is h				2 i		8	7	5	5		G	7	, 1 a i			11	4		4		7					7	3	5	2	V	6	G	4	4	&apos;* 1B. &amp;c, means 1 gale of 6 days&apos; duration.																				PRINTED AT TUB FOKEIGN OWICE liV C. R HAKKISON. 11/9/1915.															

(30 S//S 3SS0) F.Q./S-

</content>
</cab>
