<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/1/0 images: 358-363</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property, of His Britaimic Majesty&apos;s Government]      Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.  October 1915.SECRET.G.-30.COMMITTEE OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.The  Winter Climate  of the  Balkan  Peninsula.Memorandum  prepared in  the  Meteorological Office.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W,,     October 15,1915.
MEMORANDUM ON THE WINTER  CLIMATE  OF THE  BALKAN                           PENINSULA.    WHILE the climate of Greece and the iEgean Sea is of the Mediterranean type,characterised by a hot summer, a mild winter, and a maximum rainfall in the wintermonths, that of the Balkan Peninsula is of a wholly different type.    Rainfall is distributed fairly equally throughout the year, with a minimum in thewinter and a maximum in the spring and early summer.  The summer temperature ismoderately high, but the temperature in winter  falls  very much below that of othercountries  which border on the northern coasts of the Mediterranean, and at Sophia240 F. has been recorded in January.   The cold, dry winds which sweep down fromthe Steppes of Southern and South-Eastern  Russia, where  the  pressure is normallyhigh  during  the winter months,  account for the  moderate rainfall and  the lowtemperature which are experienced.    In  Southern Serbia meteorological stations  are  scarce,  but  in Bulgaria sometwenty have been in operation  for from ten to fifteen years, and from their observationsan estimate of the  climate can be  formed which wiU apply also to the mountainousregion of Southern Serbia.   The following stations have been utilised : 	Altitude.	Latitude N.	Longitude E.	Remarks.Group I  Constantinople Kavala Salonica Group II  Monastir Uskub .. Group III  Tchepelare Samokov.. Rilski Monastir Kustendil Sophia Group IV  Burgas Stara Zagora Kazanlyk.. Haskovo Philippopoli	Feet. 246 39 7 2,034 804 3,625 3,117 3,855 1,722 1,804 49 768 1,220 640 525	o / 41 2 40 55 40 39 41 1 42 0 41 44 42 20 42 8 42 17 42 42 42 29 42 25 42 37 41 56 42 9	0 / 28 28 20 7 23 7 21 23 21 26 24 42 23 34 23 21 22 41 23 20 27 29 -25 28 25 24 25 25 24 45	Transition zone between Mediterranean and Balkan climate. Western Macedonia. High-level stations. liumelian Plain.    Of  these, the first group of three represents a climate transitional between that ofthe Mediterranean and the Balkan climate ;  some  snow falls every winter, and ratherlow temperatures are not uncommon.  In  January 1903 the harbour of Salonica wascovered  with ice half an inch thick on two  consecutive mornings during  a north-easterly gale.    Monastir and Uskub represent the climate of Western Macedonia, and are theonly stations there for which the observations extend over a period of several years.    The five stations of the third group are all situated at altitudes of over 1,700 feet,and may be taken as fairly representing the  climate of the hill country of the CentralBalkans.    The stations of the  last  group  lie in the Rumelian  Plain and  the foot  hillssiuroiinding it.      [1143]                                                          B
                                 Temperature.    The mean temperature of the  day for each group of stations is given in Table I,where it will be seen that  from December to February the mean temperature in theBalkans remains very near,  or may be below, freezing point even for places in theRumelian Plain.    In Table II the mean minimum temperature (the mean of the lowest temperaturesrecorded on each day of the month) is given for each of the  four groups, except thatthis information is not available for Uskub.    For all  Balkan  stations this mean daily minimum  is  below freezing point inDecember, January, and Februaryrand also in November and March at the hill stations.This table represents the lowest temperature of  the day as experienced on the average.But on many days lower temperatures occur, and in Table III the mean of the lowesttemperature recorded in each month over a period of eleven years is given.  It may beanticipated, therefore, that such temperatures will be  reached  in  each month at theplaces mentioned.    Here the extreme severity of the winter weather in the Balkans is well shown, forat all stations temperatures much below freezing point occur from November to March.In January, which is the coldest month, the minimum temperature  at two hill stationsmay be expected to reach, or even fall below, O0 F. each year.    If the lowest temperatures recorded  during the eleven  years  1900-1910  areconsidered (Table IV), the. exceptional character of  the  Balkan winter, even in theRumelian Plain, is clearly seen.    At all the hill stations except one in Groups II and IH temperatures below 0o F.have been recorded in December as well as in January and February, while they alsooccur at two places on the Rumelian  Plain.   The lowest temperature was recorded atSophia, where 240 F.  has occurred once.  These exceptionally low temperatures are dueto the position of the Balkan region, which comes under  the  influence of the area ofhigh atmospheric pressure which exists over Southern Russia and Central Asia duringthe winter months.                                   Rainfall.    The amount of rain which falls during the winter months  is  not large, and themean rainfalls of the winter months do not. differ greatly from, one  another  (Table V).Where the Mediterranean type of  climate prevails, the maximum monthly rainfalloccurs in  the  winter, but in the Balkan region the winter is a period of diminishedrainfall.   The  amount in  any month may  vary  considerably  from year to year,according  as more or fewer depressions  pass  over  the  district.  In Table VI thegreatest amount recorded at  any stations of a group, during the eleven years for whichrecords are available, is stated.  This may  be taken  a*s an indication of the greatestamount of  rain which might occur in the month.    The number of rainy days in each month varies but little  either from  month tomonth, or from one region to another, and eight to ten days per month represent theordinary number of them which occurs.                                    Frost.    In Table IX the average number of days on which the  temperature was below320 F. is given, as well as the average number of days in each month on which it didnot  rise above  that figure.  Considering  the  very  low  minimum temperature,  thenumber of days of the latter category is not large.    In the  colder years of the period reviewed,  however, protracted frost is  notuncommon, and at hill  stations frost may occur every night throughout December,January, and February, while frost  throughout the day is then experienced on fromhalf to three-quarters of the days in these months.                                    Snow.          I    Snow may be expected  at any time from November to April,  and in December,January, and February it falls frequently.   On  thet average one day in three or fourrepresents the frequency of  snowfall in these months, and in the colder years the snowmay lie throughout January  and February in the region represented by Group III,  and.occasionally &quot;throughout March as well/                                                       H.  G. LYONS,                                                                  Major,  R.E.    Meteorological Office, October 15, 1915.
Mean Temperature CF.Place.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Group I ,. II * * * * a . III a * * * * * a, a, I V a a a * * *	53 44 38 44	47 35 32 37	41 30 26 32	44 36 31 36	48 45 37 43	56 53 46 52TABLE II. Mean Daily Minimum Temperature CF.						Place.	November.	December.	I January. ! February.		March.	April.Group I 1T* JJ JLX a a a a a a jalll aa aa aa JJ IV a a a * a a	48 38 31 36	42 29 26 32	36 23 19 26	38 30 23 31	41 36 30 34	49 42 36 40* Monastir only.TABLE III.Mean Monthly Minimum Temperature 0F.Place.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Group I Monastir TJskub Tchepelare Samokov Kilski Monastir Kustendil Burgas Stara Zagora Kazanlyk Haskovo Philippopoli	35 23 23 10 13 18 20 24 23 22 17 -25	31 11 14 4 8 12 14 18 18 17 14 19	25 7 7 -7 0 3 5 13 11 9 3 11	27 13 14 2 4 9 13 19 19 17 15 19	33 25 - 28 10 13 15 21 24 26 24 21 27	39 31 40 18 23 23 30 33 32 30 30 33
Absolute Minimum (lowest recorded Temperature QF.).! Locality.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Constantinople Kavala.. Saionica Monastir Uskub Tchepelare Samokov Eilski Monastir Kustendil Sophia .. . Burgas Stara Zagora .. Kazanlyk * Haskovo Philippopoli	-4 -1 18 13 1 . 9 23 22 8 25	a a -7 -2 12 -6 -7 9 18 17 -4 19	24 22 19 -1 -14 -19 -14 -12 -8 -24 1 2 -6 -4 4	a a -15 -6 -8 -8 -15 9 1 -1 -9 -1	a a&quot; a * -4 4 4 11 -1 14 16 18 16 18	12 19 18 23 23 25 28 26 27 31Table V. Mean Monthly Rainfall (inches).						Locality.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Group I &apos; II a a * * * * III * a * &apos;* * * aj IV a a * * a *	2-91 2-24 1-89 2-40	3-35 2-28 2-01 1-81	2-48 1-69 1-73 1-89	2-32 1-89 2-36 1-73	2-09 1-38 2-56 1-81	1-73 2-09 1-85 1-81Table  VI.Maximum Monthly Rainfall (inches).Locality.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.In Group&apos; III IV ..	5-35 6-54	5-43 4-13	4-49 6-10	4-25 3-94	4-53 4-49	5-28 5-51Table VII. Rainy Days.						Locality.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.-Group I &quot;,) II a a .a a a a )J &apos; III a * a a a * ,V IV	9 7 10 10	10 8 9 9	8 8 10 8	9 8 10 9	8 7 10 9	7 9 10 9
Average number of Days of Frost at Night/Frost all Day.Locality.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Group III TV	15/2 8/1	23/4 14/2	28/8 23/6	22/4 12/2	20/1 9/0	8/0 1/0TABLE IX. Average number of Days of Snowfall/Ground covered with Snow.						Locality.	November.	December.	January.	February.	March.	April.Constantinople Salonica .. .. TJskub .. .. Group III iv .......	1/0 0-3/0 1-4/0 5/6 .3/2	3/0 0-7/0 2-1/0 7/11 3/4	6/0 1-4/0 4-7/0 9/24 7/14	6/0 0-7/0 3-5/0 9/17 5/8	3/0 0-4/0 1-0/0 7/12 4/9	1/0 o-i/o 0/0 4/3 . V0PBINTED AT THE FOBEI&amp;N OMIOK BY O. E. HABEMOIf. 19/10/lW15iTABLE VIII.

</content>
</cab>
