<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 150-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINET.         MEMORANDUM BY SECRETARY  OF STATE  FOR INDIA.    I circulate for the information  of my colleagues an extract from a  letter fromthe Government of India regarding the Resolution (No. XIV) of the Third Assemblyof the League of Nations in the matter of the proposed scheme for a general Treatyof Mutual Assistance.                                                                      PEEL.    11th January 1924.  Extract from letter from Government of India (Army Department), to Secretary of                     State for India, dated 22nd  November 1923.    .   .   .  .   The substance of this Resolution  is embodied in the Draft Treaty of mutual Guarantee which was drawn  up by Lord Robert Cecil and is included in theannexures to your letter.  Stated  very briefly, the provisions  of the Draft Treatyamount to this, that the  parties  to  it should agree to reduce their  armaments andthat, this condition  having been fulfilled, they should  mutually agree to go to  theassistance of one another when attacked  or threatened with attack by any Power,whether that Power is a  party to the agreement or not.   Under clause 17 of the Draft,India&apos;s obligation would be restricted to rendering assistance to such Asiatic, powers as might decide to accept the Treaty.    In the  first place, it should  be noted that none of India&apos;s potential enemies in asia is  a member of the League of  Nations, and  that, consequently, the immediate result of India&apos;s  reducing her  armaments would be to weaken  her  military position vis-a-vis a definite and proximate danger.  This  position, however, might conceivably be accepted  if there were  sure grounds for believing that the other Asiatic Powers,members  of the  League of Nations,  would not  only accept the Treaty of mutual guarantee, but would also be prepared and would be able to render  to India effectiveassistance in the event of her being attacked or threatened  with attack.  The Govern-ment of India are, however, of  opinion that it is impossible to expect that this lastcondition  could  in any circumstances  be fulfilled.  Further, the remoteness of  india from  the  headquarters  of  the  League of Nations, the peculiar character of India&apos;sfrontier problems and her comparative geographical  isolation  in Asia, added  to theserious practical difficulties of setting in operation the preliminary measures designedto prevent and, when necessary, to meet aggression, combine to render impracticableany commitment  on  the part of  India to a reduction of armaments based on thehypothesis that  at the  requisite  moment the assistance of Japan,   China, Siam orPersia could be relied upon.  For  analogous reasons, and for other  reasons which itis hardly  necessary to elaborate, it  would be most inexpedient for India to undertake the responsibility of going to the assistance of Japan, China and  Persia when attackedor threatened with attack.     In expressing these  views, the  Government of India realise, of  course, that themilitary and foreign  policy of  India is largely  governed by that  of His  Majesty&apos;sGovernment;  but subject  to any special considerations  which may   weigh  with  HisMajesty&apos;s Government  in  this matter, the Government  of India  are definitely ofopinion that for  the reasons stated above they should decline to accept for India theDraft Treaty of.Mutual  Guarantee.SECRET.CP. 18/24.6968    100  1.24[&quot;This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]               (Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1924.)

</content>
</cab>
