<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 217-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT  IS. Tir PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MA JETTIES GOVERNLIENT *C. R E. T . 26/24s-f n Qi ; 8,BRITISH  DYESTUFFS .. AGREEMENT      Memorandum by the  First Lord of the Admiralty,        The proposed Agreement between the British dyestuffs corporation and the German Interssen Geminsohaft is basedon: (l) the complete mutual interchange of patents,processes,  etc., between the two Companies; (2) the llmi-tation of the British Industry to the British Isles anda portion of the British EmpireJ (3) the settlement of all questions as to where research and manufacture are to be *carried on by&apos;two joint  Committees; (4) the assignment tothe Germans of 50 per cents of the profits of the BritishIndustry over and above   200,000 for the first five yearsand  150,000 afterwards.  The Agreement is binding for 50years(        If the assumption is that the British DyestuffsIndustry is not to be effectively helped, or able to helpitself, in the course of the next  50 years; that it can never, within that period, aspire to hold its ov/n even inthe Empire market;, still less in any foreign marketj thatduring the next 50 years our research work in connexionwith dyeing and all its  &quot;auxiliary and intermediate pro-ducts&quot; - of such vital importance to our national defence in connexion with explosives, etc. - will be on a smaller scale than that of the Germans, then, no doubt, this isthe best of a bad bargain0  But I  cannot bring myself tobelieve that when the experience of the Uar showed us the vital importance of developing a great  Dye Industry of ourown and encouraging our own chemical research we Intendedto set so early and so complete a limitation upon ourdevelopment,   I am not objecting in principle to co- operation with  the German industry on reasonable terms;
my objection is to stereotyping and limiting an industry, withalmost infinite capacity for development, for 50 yearst        The difficulty is increased, by the fact that our government is a large shareholder in the British dyestuffs corporation and therefore a party to this Agreement,  this makes it morally impossible for us to&apos;endeavour afterwardsto break down the Agreement&apos;by any fresh effort to build up an independent British dye industry or by measures aimed atcapturing for such an industry the Empire and foreign marketsI have said nothing about the&apos; objections to the agreement as involving Government co-operation in setting up a worldmonopoly in restraint of free competition - whereas up tothe present we have been stimulating competition - and tothe detriment of the consumer i        Personally I would strongly urge the&apos;rejection of theAgreement  as contrary to national policy, lay the whole factsbefore the public and leave it to&quot;our successors to decide whether they will help the industry or let it go under, ourown hands remaining free to revive it again when we have thepower to do. so,  Failing that, I would suggest thatwe should at once dispose of all Government interest and control in thematter for any figure the Corporation will give, and&apos;leavethe matter as a purely business arrangement between two .private Corporations,.  That would, at any rate, leave- our hands free to look after the matter in the national interest at a  later date,                            (Intd,.)    L. St A,anuary,  1924,

</content>
</cab>
