<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 345-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0 A B IJ STCOMPOSITION OP CABINET COMMITTEES.(Note by the Secretary)0I circulate herewith, for the information of ministers the composition and terms of reference of the Home AffairsCommittee, the Unemployment and Housing Committee and theAgricultural policy Committee,as agreed by the Cabinet attheli&quot; Meetings -vn the 23rd and 28th January, 1924 respectiveCabinets 7 (24) and 0 (24),Secretary to the Cabineto2, Whitehall Gardens,  S;Wilo4th February, 1924.
                                                           o n ol0  HOME AffPAIRS C 0:1.1 IT TEE.                                 w ? 0    At their Meet in;: on  28th January,  1924 (Cab,3 (24)  Oon-clusion 8.)  the Cabinet  agreed:-          That  a Committee of Home Affairs should          he composed as follows:-               The  Lord  Chancellor (in the Chair)               The  Lord  President  of the Council               The  Home  Secretary               The  Minister of Health               The  Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster               The  Financial Secretary of the Treasury               One  of the law Officers of the Crown                      Mr, R.B. Howortha Seoretary          Others Ministers should be invited to attend          if either their Parliamentary or Departmental          interests were affected by the business          before the Committee,          The function of the Home Affairs Committee          should be, as  in tho past, to relieve tho          Cabinet of the detailed consideration of          the large volume of legislative and admin-          istrative work referred to the Cabinet,          while leaving to the Cabinet the ultimate          decision on these questions,2.    TJIIEMPLOU^HT MD..KOHSIHQ COMMITTEE.     At their Meeting on the 23rd January, 1924,  (Cab,7 (24)Conclusion 30) the Cabinet agreed:-          That a Committee, composed as follows:-     Mr. Sidney Webb  (President of the Board of  Trade)                                        (in the Chair).     Mr, Clynes  (Lord Privy Seal)     Mr, Philip Snowden  (Chancellor of the Exchequer)     Mr,, Tom Shaw  (Minister of Labour)     Miss Margaret Bondfield  (Parliamentary Under Secretary,                                    Ministry of  Labour)     Mr, John  Wheatley,  (Minister of Health)     mr Charles Trevelyan  (President, Board of  Education)     Mr. ?.W.  Jowett, 1011&apos;&apos;  (Pirst Commissioner of Works)     Mrc Walter  R0 Smith  (Parliamentary Under Secretary),                          (Ministry  of Agriculture &amp; Fisheries),     Mr, James Stewart  (Under  Seoretary of Health for  Scotland)            other Ministers, such as the-Heads of            the Service  Departments, being invited            to  attend  for  consultation when tho            business rendered  it desirable,         x                                                  C          &apos;  with -Mr. R.B, Howorth as Seoretary,      should meet at once, with power  to appoint      Sub-Committees in  order  to investigate all                    -1-
2 i &amp;          aspects of the  question of Unemployment          and the connected question of Housing,          and to make  definite recommendations  to          the Cabinet  as  to what wet suras for dealing          with these subjects are practicable and          desirable:     At their Meeting  on  the 28th January,  1924 (Cab.8 (24)Conclusion V. ), the Cabinet agreed-that the Minister ofTransport should be added to the Unemployment and  Housing,Committeo.     In pursuance of the  above Cabinet decision theUnemployment and Housing  Committee have appointed  thefollowing Sub-Committees:--     UEEMPL0YMSET SUB-C0MMITTE2.The Minister of Labour (Chairman)The President of the Board of Trade (ex officio)The Minister of transport the Financial Secretary to the Treasury$he parliamentary Seoretary to the Ministry of Health.The Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour.       Mr. R.B.Howorth )                      ) Secretaries.       Mr.V,&apos;.Eady      )BOUSING SUBCOMMITTEE.The Minister of Health  (Chairman)The president of the Board of Trade (ex official)  .The pirst Commissioner of ForksThe Under Secretary of Health for scotland the Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour.Mr. E.F.C.Mosse, Ministry of Health, (Secretary).   3*   AGRICULTURAL  POLICY  COMMITTEE.    At their  Meeting on  the 23rd January,1924  (Cabinet  7(24) Conclusion &apos;4.)  the Cabinet agreed;-          (a)    That a Committee,composed as  follows:-               &quot;&apos;r,^.-\                         .               *                 Mr.Eoel  B^xton (Minister of  Agriculture                    and  fisheries)  (in  the  Chair),                 Lord Parmoor (Lord president of  the&apos;Council)                 Sir Sydney Olivier (Seoretary  of State  for                                           India)                 Mr-.Adamson (Secretary  for  Scotland)
     should meet  at  one a  to enquire  into  the     position of  Agriculture,, with full discre-     tion  to  consult all  tho agricultural and     urban,interests concerned  in such manner     as  they deem most convenient, and to make     recommendations to &apos;the&apos; Cabinet:(b)   That the Chancellor  of the Exchequer     should be consulted  as to  the  financial     aspects of any recommendations  before     their submission to  the  Cabinet:(c)   That the Minister of Health should be     consulted in regard  to any proposals     affecting rating before  they are  submitted     to  the Cabinet; any other  Departments     affected being consulted in the sane   &apos;  manner.

</content>
</cab>
