<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 427-429</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
dooument is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)-^GOVERNMENT POLICY AND THE LAMP VALUATION DEPARTMENT.   / .J      In its Election Manifesto the Labour- Party declared thatit proposes to restore to the people their lost rights in theland,  including minerals, and to that end will work for re-equipping the Land Valuation Department,  securing to thecommunity tho economic rent of land and facilitating theacquisition of land for public purposes.      It is clear that any proposals which tho-present Governmentmay introduce in connection with unemployment and housing will involve tho purchasing or renting of large areas of land, whethertho work is undertaken by public bodies or private enterprise.As soon as it is known that the Government proposes to undertakenational work which has hitherto been done by private enterprise,or to grant credit facilities to municipalities or private companies, such a pronouncement will cause land values to soar todizzy heights.  There is a grave possibility that tho schemes will fail through over-capitalisation, or become of an uneconomiccharacter if general prices (and wages) fail.  It is thereforeurgently necessary that the information as to valuation beavailable as a corrective to the sale or renting of land atinflated, prices.      Section 4 of the Finance Act of 1909-10 made it compulsory ..that all transfers by sale or leases exceeding  14 years shouldbo registered in the Land Valuation Department.  This Section wasrepealed by Section 58 of the Finance Act of 1935.  During thoDebate on 3rd July, 1925, the present prime Minister (Mr. J.Ramsay MacDonald) said:        &quot;These returns are not dusty pieces of paper.  They keep     the Valuation Department in touch with the day to day and0 A B I N E T.E T.
     Week  to week  transactions  in  the  sale and purchase of     land......  That  is why  the landlords&apos; section of this     House want  to abolish  this provision of the law......     I  am  not  in favour of  this ciauVp being abolished simply     because I happen  to be in  favour  of the taxation of land     values, but because I  feel that this information is     necessary for the protection  of the public.&quot;     Mr.  Austen Chamberlain&quot; said:        &quot;The Government attach,  the greatest importance to     having as accurate information as possible as to the     valuation of  land......  VJq need  that information for     the purpose of taxation  and for the purpose of advising     public departments and authorities when they are purchasing     land. It has proved to  be of the greatest assistance to     the Valuation Department for  all  valuation purposes,     providing as  it does an  exhaustive and progressive     indication  of the movements of values of the property     market.   It is really  essential,  if the Valuation     Department  is to  give  that -assistance which it ought .     to be able  to give to  public  authorities, and especially     to the State,  when purchasing, and if it is to exorcise     that  intelligent  supervision  and  chock, it ought to be     exercised over the valuations tendered to it in Death     Duties, and all questions  of  valuation that come before us.&quot;     Sir  Leslie Scott said in  1922:       &apos; &quot;The records of the Department have been maintained     continually for a. series of years,&quot; and that &quot;to break the     continuity  would  be  in fact to multiply many times over the     work  that would have to  be done at some future date to     onable valuers to get  the  information necessary to form     their opinion.&quot;     As Section 4 of*the Finance  Act  of  1909-10 which providedfor the creation of the Land  Valuation Department was repealedby Section 38  of tho Finance  Aot,  1923, it should bo possiblefor a clause to  be added  to the Finance Bill of  1924 repealingSection-38,  1933.   This would enable the Land ValuationDepartment to  bo re-nestablished through the same type oflegislation  that established  it and would  effectually proventthe Houso  of Lords from, throwing out the measure.  At the sametine, a clause should  be  added  which would make  the work of the department retrospective, and this would bnablo  the information to be brought  up to date,      It might be  considered  desirable for tho Primo Ministerto make a pronouncement regarding  the  policy of the government towards the  taxation of Land  Values.-  If it wero stated thatthey proponed  to bring in r-uoh  a measure at an early date, this might have the effect  of  encouraging land owners to dispose of
     parcels of  land  and  by  thus  putting  large holdings on the     market, the value  of land might bo kept down, or at least     become stabilised.   There is  little  doubt that  the foar;of     imminent  taxation  would encourage them to sell.  Last year,     Sir  John  Simon introduced a  Bill which is to have a further     reading in  March of  this year.  It is very necessary that     tho  Prime Ministor should make a statement on the matter in     his  speech  when  ho announces  the policy of tho  Government     in the Bouse when  parliament  resumes its sittings.                                      A. H.31st  January,  1924.

</content>
</cab>
