<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 514-521</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Tula  Document  ia  the Property of His Britaaoio; Majesty&quot;a Government). 3  B  0 R B I.                       CABIiBI, 0. P. 6S(S4)                   COMMITTEE OP HOME AFFAIRS,                   FRIEHDLY SOCIETIES Bill .           Memorandum &quot;by the Finerclaj Secretary to the Treasury.                  Cabinet approval ia doaired for the introduction,        in the forthcoming Session, of the attached Bill, which is        understood to be non-contentious and was to have been        introduood by the late Government in the Autumn Session of        last  year.                  The memorandum prepared by the Chiof Registrar        of Friendly Societies on the occasion when the Bill was ccsn-        sidered  by the late Home Affairs Committee is attached, -        This  memorandum explains the position which is unchanged        except that the urgent need of passing the measure into        law has  becomo still more pressing.                  Since the meaauro was last considered it has        been  suggested that opportunity ohould be taken to provide        that  the post of Chief Registrar, which has hitherto boon        confined to barristers of twelve years&apos; standing, should        be opened to Assistant Registrars, who are*thornsolvea        usually  either barristers or solicitors.    It is proposed        to add a olauao to tho bill giving effect to this suggestion.  TREASURY., a.W.     5th February, 1924.Copy Ho
            FRIENDLY SOCIETIES BILL,          This Bill is the necessary corollary of tho0-position amendment to Section 4 of tho IndustrialAsaurrjaco Bill, 1923, accepted hy the Government on theReport Stage in tho House of Commons, the Bill having already passed tho House of Lords (ooc Hansard for 16thMay, 1923, vol. 164, col, 521-525)-   She amendmentincreasesj in tho case of industrial assurance companies,the aggregate amounts which under Section 62 of the friendly Societies Act, 1896, can legally he insured orpaid on the death of children under 100          It was accepted &quot;upon the strict understandingthat hon. members opposite will not oppose any measure which may be necessary to oxtond this proposal to friendly societies and trade unions - it cannot be done in -ShisSession, but it may have to be done in another Session bya short non-contentious Bill&quot;.          Tho Bill makes a general amendment to Section 62of the Friendly Societies Act, 1396, and thereby Bjafces theincreased amounts apply in tho case of the other bodies which are subject to that section, namely ordinary friendly societies., collecting societies and trade unions.   It is brought forward for tho Autumn Session because the industrial assurance Act,  1983, coomonoos on January 1st, 1924, and itis extremely desirable that this Bill-should come into force on that date also for the following reasons:          (1)  Whoroas the Industrial Assurance Act, 1983, .applies throughout to industrial assurance companies endcollecting societies, whioh arc defined in Section .1 of the                                                      lV&apos;&apos;!&quot;.
 Act,  and to industrial assurance business  as  defined in the same section,  whether conducted by one class  of body or by the other,  Section 4, as it at present stands,  only extends the limits  of the sums payable on the death of children in the case of industrial assurance companies.    This was nob in the least intended, and during the debate lb was assumed that the extension applied in the case cf  collecting societies as well; but I think there can be no reasonable doubt that, on a proper construction of the section, it only applie-a to the companies,         (2)  Section 4 itself is inartistically drafted, although it is perfectly comprehensible.    The defect of it is that, in the exception, which forms  the latter pa-y-t of sub-section (1) of the section,  the words cited from tho Friendly Societies Act, 1895, Section 62,  for which other words are substituted, do not in fact exist in that Act, though, it contains similar words of the seme purport.         (3)   Section 62 of the Friendly Societies Act, 1095, applies to all registered friendly societies (including collecting societies) and is also applied to trade unions by Section 2 of the Trade Union Act Amendment- Act, 1876.    Unless the present Bill is passed, these other bodies will remain confined to the old limits, whereas industrial assurance companies, which are  in keen competition with them.  for. the assurance of children, will have the advantage of the  extended limits,          As far as the merits of the Bill  itself, apart from the legal reasons for its passage, are concerned, it is
 intended to, meet the largely  increased cost  of  funerals and everything connected with them,  which is referred to In detail in cols.&apos; 523 - 525  Of Hansard Vol. 164  and  is unquestionable.          The passage off the Bill before January 1st,  1924, is urgently asked for by the  National  Conference  of Friendly Societies,  by important individual  societies such as the Ancient Order of Foresters and  the Hearts  of Oak Benefit Society  and by the  collecting  societies,  or such of them as have.grasped that Section 4  of the Industrial Assurance Act has not increased the  limits in their cass^ In a letter to the Hearts of  Oak on  July 4th last the Prime Minister expressed the hope that it  would be possible tointroduce the Bill in. the Autumn Sessions.(SD).   Go  STUART ROBERTSON,
[14 GEO.  5.]      Friendly Societies.                  1                      DRAFT                          OF A                 BILL                           TO  Amend  sections sixty-two and sixty-five of  the  A.D. 1924.    Friendly Societies Act, 1896,  and for purposes    connected therewith.  BE it enacted by the  King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,       by and with the advice arid  consent of  the Lords  Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in  this present  Parliament assembled, and by tbe  authority of the same, 5 as follows:       1. (1) Section sixty-two of  tbe Friendly Societies Assurances   Act, 1896 (which relates to assurances on children), both on chil-   as  originally enacted and as applied to trade unions and &amp;ren&apos;&amp; uves   industrial assurance companies, shall have effect as if for10 that section tbe  following section were substituted:       &quot; A  society or  branch,  whether registered or   unregistered, (shall not insure  or  pay on tbe death of a   child  under the ages hereinafter specified any  sum of   money which when  added to any amount payable on the15 death of  that child by any other society or  branch [or   by any trade union  or  industrial assurance company]   exceeds tbe amounts hereinafter  specified;  that is to   say :-       (a) In the case of a child under three  years of age,-20          six pounds;       (b) In the  case of a child under six  years of age,            ten pounds.       (c) In the case of a child under ten years of age,.            fifteen pounds.&quot;              61-1
2Friendly Societies.      [14 GEO. 5.]A.D. 1924.Short title,commence-ment and extent.    (2) Section sixty-five of the Friendly Societies Act,1896, shall have effect as if for the words &quot; five years &quot;there were substituted the words &quot; three years,&quot; and asif for the words &quot; ten years &quot; there were subsituted thewords &quot;six years,&quot;  and as if at the end of  subsection (1).thereof there were inserted the words &quot; or for the payment&quot; in the whole of a sum exceeding fifteen pounds on the&quot; death of a child under ten years.&quot;    (3) Subsection (1) of section  four of the industrial assurance Act, 1923, shall be repealed from the words&quot; except that&quot; to the end of the subsection.    2. (1) This Act may  be cited as  the friendly societies Act, 1924.    (2) This Act shall come  into  operation on the  first day  of  July, nineteen hundred  and twenty-four,  butshall  not apply to any assurances effected before thatdate.    (3) This Act shall not extend to Northern  Ireland.1015

Friendly-  Societies.             DRAFT               OP A         B   I   Ii   liTo amend sections  sixty-two and sixty-  five of the Friendly  Societies Act,  1896,  and  for  purposes connected  therewith.XLVIII.  (1.)7th February 192461-1

</content>
</cab>
