<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 793-839</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
b^jicjOT;NT C R E.T. , . 68 (24),IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT^                   CABINET.                 GOVERNMENT^  BILLS.            Note by the Lord chancellor.         The legislation originating in tho Department ofthe Lord Chancellor which I shall propose to my colleagues as suitable  for introduction during the forthcoming Sessionis as follows     1,  The  Judicature Consolidation Bill.This Bill consolidates the law relating to the Supreme. Court,effects  a very considerable - simplification, and proposes to repeal 40 Acts completely and 67 in part reproducing thorn inone enactment,   Tho Bill was introduced last Session and wasconsidered by the Joint Committee of both Houses on Consolida-tion Bills who had almost completed their labours upon it,This Bill will be ready for introduction upon the sitting ofthe House,     2*  Thg^dministr-ation. of Justice Bill,   This Bill dealswith the machinery of civil justice in the Supreme Court.It is largely an adjunct to the Consolidation Bill, many ofits clauses being directed to remove ambiguities or inconsis-tsncies  discovered in the process of consolidation.   It last session  passed through all its stages in the House of lords and received a Second Reading in the House of Commons.        It is for the most part non-contentious, but Clause 2,which deals with trial by jury in the Supreme Court in civilcauses may give rise to discussion.                             -1-
        The object of the Clause Is to restore generallyspeaking to the litigant the right to a trial by jury incivil cases on the common law side in the High Courtalmost on the lines.on which it existed before the passingof the Juries Apt, 1918.   That Act to meet the emergenciescaused by the War made cotisiderable inroads upon the right.The right was restored in part hy section 2 of the Aot of1920, but the wider extension of the right is now thoughtpracticabls, and the  section of the.Act of 1920 istechnically defective,   The present Clause is criticised on the ground that it dees not go far enough, reserving, asit does, a discretion to the Judge to order a trial withouta jury if he thinks that the case is &quot;more fit- to be triedwithout a jury&quot;.    Experience has shown that there is needfor giving some discretion to the Judge, and  it is difficultto find any appropriate words to limit the exercise of thatdiscretion,.   The Clause has the additional advantage, fromthe point of view of those who desire to preserve the right-that the right will henceforth depend upon Statute and notupon rule,,     3. Oyjjalnal  Justice Bill.   This Bill deals mainly with the machinery of- criminal  justice.   It  was introducedlast Session, passed  the Lords and received a Second reading in the  Commons,,   No  political question arises upon any ofits  provisions, but  several of them encountered oppositionduring  the  Second Reading Debate in the Commons and may require modification  before the Bill  is introduced.   TheBill  to be  introduced this  Session will.contain amendments of the  law  on  certain matters  to which attention has been called  since the  Bill was originally  introduced.          !                -2-  h                           ;P;
      4,    County Courts^ B1,11JL   This  Bill  is  of some  importance. It is designed  to  introduce  a  new financial and administrative system for the  County Courts,  and with that object  to  make possible  the placing of  the  inferior  officials  employed in those Courts upon  the civil  establishment, with defined rates- of pay and provision for superannuation.   As regards  the superior  officials, that is  the Registrars of the Courts, the purpose of the Bill is to make them to a greater degree than heretofore whole-time servants of the State, and to bring to an end the present system under which many of them&apos; depend  for their remuneration in part upon the varying profits of the Courts,,  The main  provisions of the Bill form the subject of  an agreement with&apos; the organisations of Registrars on the one hand  and clerks and other officers on the other.  The Bill contains  in addition some minor amendments on matters of procedure in the County Court Acts:.   This Bill will be ready for introduction  when Parliament begins to sit.    Having,regard to the nature of  some of its provisions, which are largely financial,  it is doubtful whether it is  possible to introduce the Bill.in the House of Lords,  It was introduced last  Session in the House of Commons, but time did not permit it to receive a Second Reading,  though the then Government were  pledged to its introduction and passing.                 5.   A series ox Bills  consequential upon        the passing of the Law of Property j.ct,  1922,    The Law of property Act is  a very far-reaching and revolutionary measure,  and as  a consequence of its passing it  is  necessary&apos; to amend  and consolidate the remainder of the  law relating to real property.   During the progress  of the  Bill  for the Act  of 1922 accordingly pledges wero given  that when  it was passed  it  - should be split  into its component parts  and that each such part should be consolidated.with the Statutes  governing that portion of  tho law to whioh it  reletedv                                               /When
     Yfhen  this work is completed the whole of the real     property law of England will be contained in some six  ,     Statutes in a single volume,  This work, for which a     year  was allotted, has. proved to be even more  difficult     than  had been anticipated, and it was found impossible to     introduce the Bills during 1925,  The Bills -  which are     sis in number - have now been drafted and submitted to an     expert Committee presided over by Mr, Justice  Homer,  The     Committee have made good progress and I expect to receive     their report in six weeks or two months when the Bill will     be ready for introduction.  The Bills do not raise any     contentious question from a political point of view,          6.  Crown Proceedings Bill,  Public opinion both     within and without the legal profession has. for long been     exercised by the inequalities of the lav/ which affects the     position of the Crown as a litigant in civil matters.  The     matter has been rendered more acute by what has been     regarded as the arbitrary conduct&apos; of the Government in     proceedings which have followed upon the war.  Accordingly     lord  Birkenhead appointed a Committee of Judges, ^jowyers and     Civil Servants to consider the question which  is, from a     technical point of view, of great difficulty,,  This Committee     has made some progress, and I hope to be in a  position to     submit to my colleagues before the close of the present     Session a Bill placing the Crown, so far as may be, upon     the same footing as the subject in matters of  civil procedure&apos;.                                      (Tntd,)  H.e of lords, Oth January 19 24,
(HOME AFFAIRS&quot; COMMITTEE),AMIHISTr-^TIOH Off JUSTICE BILL.CABINET.           The attached Bill is circulated inconnection with paragraph 2 of tho Lord Chancellor&apos;sflote on Government Bills (0.P.68  (24)).2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1,      February 6th.., 1924.
Administration of Justice Bill.ARRANGEMENT  OF CLAUSES.Clause. 1.  Power to dispense with holding of  assizes in places       where unnecessary. 2.  Trial with jury in High Court. 3.  Qualification for certain offices in Supreme Court. 4.  Tenure of officers of Supreme Court. 5.  Office of Accountant-General. 6.  Distribution of business in High Court. 7.  Power to include ex-judges in commissions of assize. 8.  Appointment of deputies for Supreme  Court officers. 9.  Amendment  as  to  business  in,  and  officers of,       Supreme Court.10..  District registrars of High Court.11.  Amendment as to district probate registries.12.  Rules of Supreme Court.13.  Trial with jury in county courts and other inferior       courts of civil jurisdiction.14.  Amendment of s. 11 of County Courts Act, 1919.15.  Transfer to county court of money recovered in High      Court by infants, &amp;c.ltf.  Amendment as to funds in court.17.  Amendment  as  to registration of deeds of arrange-       ment.18.  Amendment  of  Bills  of Sale  Acts, 1878 and 1882,      with respect to local registration of bills of sale.19.  Administration bonds.20.  Enrolment and engrossment of instruments.21.  Provision as to fixing of fees.to be taken in Supreme       Court.22.  Repeal of certain obsolete enactments  relating to       administration of justice.23.  Power to revoke and vary orders.24.  Short title, interpretation, extent, repeal and com-.       mencement.     SCHEDULE    I. Qualification for certain offices in       the Supreme Court.     ScHEDtFiiE  II. Enactments containing and regula-       ting matters with respect to which rules of court       may be made.     SCHEDUXE  III. Enactments repealed.11-5A
                         DRAFT                            03? A                    B    I   L    L                             TO    Amend  the  law with respect to  the jurisdiction  A.D. 1921      and business of the  Supreme Court in England      and  with  respect  to  the  officers  and offices      thereof  and  otherwise  with  respect  to  the      administration of  justice  in England.    BE it enacted by the  King&apos;s  most Excellent Majesty,.         by and with the advice and consent of the Lords    Spiritual  and Temporal,  and Commons, in this present    Parliament assembled, and by the  authority of the same, 5  as follows:         1. (1) If at any time it appears to the Lord Chief Power to    Justice of England  that  there is no business  or no sub- dispense    stantial amount of business to be transacted at the assizes withholding    then about to be held at any place on a circuit  and that piaCes whore10  having regard to all  the  circumstances of the case it is unnecessary.    desirable that an order should be made under this section,    he  may, with the concurrence of  the Lord  Chancellor,    by order direct that assizes shall not on the occasion &apos;of    that circuit be held at that place, and where any such15  order is made  then, notwithstanding any  enactment or &apos;    custom  to the contrary, assizes shall not on that occasion    be held at the place specified in the order.       (2) There may be included in  an  order made under    this section provision for any  matters (including any20  of the matters mentioned in paragraph (3) of section two    of the Winter Assizes Act, 1876) for which it appears to 39&amp;io Viet.    the Lord Chief Justice  to be necessary or  proper to c&apos; 57-    make provision with a view  to giving full effect to the   order.11-5
 A.D. 1924.      2. (1) The following provisions shall have effect in   ,   :,    relation to the trial of causes in the High Court: Trial with                                        bjury iu High      (a) In the  case of causes assigned to the  ChanceryCoiirt-               Division  the  trial shall,  unless it  is  otherwise                   ordered by  the  court  or a judge,  be without 5                   a jury:               (b)  The court  or a judge may order the trial without                   a  jury of any cause which immediately before                   the  commencement of the Supreme  Court of36 &amp; 37 Viet.          Judicature Act, 1873, could without the consent 10c- 66-               of the parties have been tried without a jury :               (c)  Any cause, not being a cause to which paragraph                   (a) or paragraph (6) of this subsection applies, in                   which there is a claim in respect of libel, slander,                   malicious prosecution, false imprisonment, seduc- 15                   tion or breach of promise  of marriage shall, if                   any party thereto makes  an application in that                   behalf, be tried with a jury :               (d) Any cause, not being a cause to which one of the                   preceding paragraphs of  this subsection  applies, 20                   shall, if any party thereto  makes an application                   in  that behalf, he tried  with a jury,  unless in                   the  opinion  of the court or a judge the cause                   is more fit to  be tried without a jury :i                      Provided that  if on the trial of any cause, 25                   which has under paragraph (d)  of this subsection                   been ordered  to  be tried with a jury, it appears                   &apos; to the judge that the cause  is more fit to be                   tried without a jury,  he  may notwithstanding                   the previous order direct  that the cause shall be 30                   tried without a jury:               (e) Nothing in thjs section shall affect                          (i) the right  of  any  party under section20 &amp; 21 Vtet.            twenty-eight of the Matrimonial Causes Act,c. 85.                  1857, to insist on having  contested  matters 35                      of fact tried with a jury ; or                         (ii) the power of  the court or a judge in                      a  case to  which  section   fourteen of the52 &amp; 53 Viet.            Arbitration Act, 1889,  applies  to  make  ano. 49.                  order for the  trial  of  a  cause in manner 40                      provided by that section :
    (2) In this section the expression &quot;cause&quot; includes  A.D. J924.any action, suit, matter or other proceeding requiring tobe tried, other than a criminal cause or matter.    3. A person shall  not be qualified for  appointment Qualificatiito any of the offices in the Supreme Court specified in the iol pertainfirst column of  the Eirst Schedule to this Act unless he   is  a person  of  the description specified in the second Court.&quot;&apos;0   column of that Schedule in respect of that office :       Provided that  notwithstanding  anything  in  this10 section any person who holds any office in the Supreme   Court at the commencement of this Act shall be qualified   for appointment  to  any office to  which he  might have   been appointed if this Act had not passed.       4. (1) Any officer of the Supreme Court who by Tenure of] 5 virtue of the provisions of section one of the Supreme officers of   Court Officers (Retirement, Pensions, &amp;c.) Act, 1921, is f-^m&amp;   required to vacate office at the end  of the completed year n &amp; 12   of service in the course of which  he attains the age of Geo. 5, c. 58.   seventy-two years shall, subject to .the  provisions  of  the20 said section  and subject as  hereinafter provided, hold   office during  good behaviour:       Provided that the power  to remove any  such  person   from  his office  on account  of misbehaviour shall  be   exercisable   by   the  Lord Chancellor, and the  Lord.25 Chancellor shall  have  power to remove any such  person   from  his office   on  account  of inability to  perform  the   duties of the office.        (2)  Every officer  of  the Supreme  Court, not  being   an officer to whom  subsection (1) of this section applies,30 shall hold office during His Majesty&apos;s pleasure.        (3)  In  the  application of this section  to registrars   of the  Probate,  Livor.ce and Admiralty Division  of  the   High Court,  the  President of the said  Division shall  be   substituted for the Lord Chancellor.35      5. (1)  There shall be an Accoimtant-General of  the Office of   Supreme Court,  and all powers and  duties  which under nCn0&quot;^tant&quot;   the Court  of Chancery  (Funds) Act, 1872, or any Act g^g&quot;&apos;   amending that Act, may be exercised or are to be performed Ci 44,   by the Paymaster-General shall become powers and duties40 of the  Accoimtant-General,  and references  to the Pay-   master-General in those Acts or in any rules made under          11               A335&amp;36 Viet.
A.D. 1924.  or for the purposes of those  Acts before the commence-          ment of this Act shall be construed as  references to the          Accountant-General.              (2) All  money, securities and  other property Tested          in the Paymaster-General for or on behalf of the Supreme          Court at the commencement of this Act shall, by virtue          of this Act and without any transfer or assignment, become          vested in the Accountant-General.              (3) The Clerk of the Crown shall be the Accountant-          General.              (4) The office of the Accountant-General shall be an          office of the Supreme Court.Distributionof business in HighCourt,10Power toinclude-ex-judges incommissionsof assize.     6.  (1) The Lord Chancellor may, if at any time itappears to him desirable so to do with a view to the more convenient administration of justice, by order direct that 15any jurisdiction vested in the High Court in respect ofany matter which by any enactment or any  rule or order made under any enactment is assigned to any Division ofthe  High Court shall, notwithstanding that enactment,rule or order, be assigned to such other Division as may 20be  specified in the order and shall be exercised either byany special judge or judges or by all the judges of that other Division:     Provided  that an  order shall  not  be  made  underthis subsection  except with  the concurrence both of the 25President of the Division to which the  jurisdiction is atthe time assigned and of the President of the Division towhich the jurisdiction is to be transferred.     (2) Where under any enactment a right of appeal tothe High  Court or to any Division of the High  Court is 30given from  decisions  given by  county  courts  in pur-suance  of  the jurisdiction vested  in county courts  inrespect  of any matter, the Lord Chancellor  may, not-withstanding anything in any enactment, by order direct to which  Division of  the High  Court  the appeal from 35any such decision shall lie.     7.  It shall be lawful for His Majesty to include  inany commission of assize any person who has held theoffice of a judge of  the Court of Appeal or of  a judge ofthe  High  Court, but  nothing  in  this  section  shall  be 40deemed to require  any person  who has held office  asaforesaid  to act as  commissioner  of  assize  unless  heconsents so to  do.
[14 GEO. 5.]   Administration of Justice.        8-(1) Where  any officer of the  Supreme Court  A.D. 1924.   is absent from illness or other  reasonable cause,  he may, ^pp^.   with the approval  of the Lord Chancellor and subject to meut of   the provisions  of this section, appoint a  deputy,  and if deputies for 5 being so absent  he fails to  make  such an appointment, Supreme   the Lord Chancellor  may appoint a deputy.              officers        (2) Every deputy appointed under this section shall   have  all the powers and authorities of  the officer  for   whom he is appointed to act.10      (3) A person shall  not be qualified  to be appointed   under this section to act as a  deputy  in any office unless   he is qualified for appointment to that office.        (4) Nothing in  this section shall affect the  power   of the President  of the Probate, Divorce  and Admiralty15 Division of the High Court  under section thirty-five of   the Court of Probate Act, 1858, to appoint any person 21 &amp; 22   to discharge the duties of any  officer appointed  under Viet. c. 95.   the Court of Probate Act, 1857  or the Court of Probate 20 &amp; 21   Act, 1858, or be taken to  authorise  either the  Lord Viet.c-7720 Chancellor or any  officer so  appointed as  aforesaid to   appoint a deputy in any case to which the said section   thirty-five, applies.        9. (1) Directions  under  section  twelve  of  the Amendment   Supreme Court  of Judicature (Officers) Act, 1879, as to as to business25 the business to be performed  in, and the duties of the ^and  .   officers of, the central office  of the Supreme Court shall, Supreme &apos;   instead  of being given by rules of  court, be  given  by Court.   order of the Lord Chancellor.                           *2 &amp; 43                                                         Viet. o. 78.        (2) The clerks employed in the offices of the Supreme30 Court shall be classified in  such  manner as the Lord   Chancellor, with the concurrence of  the  Treasury, may   by order direct, and shall be employed in such capacities,   as the Lord Chancellor may by order so direct.        (3) Erom  and after the commencement of  this Act,85 the  power to  appoint  any person to be a clerk in  the   office of the master in lunacy  shall be  vested in and   exercisable by the Lord Chancellor, and that office shall   be included among the offices of the Supreme Court.        (4) The  central office  of  the Supreme Court shall40 comprise and shall be deemed  always  to  have comprised   the officers and persons employed in the Court of Criminal   Appeal.                                                  1       11                  A 4
 A.D. 1924.    .  .(5) For the purposes of this-section  the expression           &quot;the  offices  of /the Supreme  Court&quot; shall  include  the           department of  the official solicitor to the Supreme Court,           the bankruptcy department and the companies (winding-           up)  department,  but  shall  not   include  the principal  5           probate registry.District          10. (l) Any person being the registrar  of a countyregistrars of  court or being  a solicitor of the  Supreme Court  of  notHigh Court.  1(ss   jian   ye  yearg&apos;  standing shall be qualified,  for           appointment as district registrar of the High Court.        10           .    (2) The  Lord. Chancellor  may,  if  he  thinks  fit,           appoint two  persons  to  execute  jointly the office  of           district registrar in any district registry, and may  in           any  case  where joint  district  registrars  are appointed           give directions with respect  to the division between them  15           of the duties of  the office and, may, as he thinks fit,           on the death, resignation or removal of a joint  district           registrar, either appoint another  person to be joint district           registrar  in the place  of the person so dying, resigning           or  removed,  or  give -directions  that the   continuing  20           registrar shall act as sole registrar.               (3) On any vacancy occurring  in the  office  of a           district registrar,  any  , person  being  a person qualified           for  appointment.as district registrar  may be appointed           to acb as  provisional  district registrar for  such  period  25           not exceeding six ;months from the date pn which  the           vacancy occurs as the Lord Chancellor may direct.               (4) The  power to make appointments to  the office of           district registrar and provisional district registrar shall be           vested in the  Lord Chancellor.                            30               (5) All  acts authorised or  required to be done  by,           to or before  a- district registrar may be  done by,  to or           before a provisional district registrar appointed under this           section, and a provisional district  registrar shall receive           in respectof the period during which he so acts remunera-  35           tion on a scale not higher than the scale applicable in the           case of the registrar of the district for which he is appointed           to act.                (6) Every  district registrar and  provisional  district           registrar shall be an officer of the Supreme Court, and no  40           person who  is, or  is acting as, the district  registrar or           the  provisional district registrar  of  any  district  shall,
\l4i GEO. 5.]    Administration of Justice.720   either  by himself or his partner, be  directly or indirectly  A.D. 1924,   engaged as  a solicitor  or  agent for&quot;&apos;a  party to  any   proceeding whatsoever in the registry of that district.        11. The President of  the  Probate,  Divorce  and  Amendment 5 Admiralty  Division  of  the High  Court  (in  this  Act  a? t0 district   referred to as &quot;the President of the Probate Division&quot;)  Probf?   may, with the concurrence  of the Lord Chancellor and the   0   Treasury, by order determine  the  districts for  which   district probate  registries  are to  be established and the10 place at which the registry for any such district is to be   established, and the districts and places as determined by   the order shall  be in substitution  for  the districts and   places  respectively specified  in Schedule A. to  the Court  20 &amp; 21 Viet.   Of Probate Act, ,1857.                                    s. 77.15      12.^-(-1) Eules  of  court may be made under the  Rules of   Judicature   Acts,  1.873;  to 1910,  for ; the  following  Supreme   purposes:                 &apos; &apos;                          Conn.        (a) Per regulating  and prescribing  the procedure            (including the  method  of  pleading)  and the            practice to be followed in.  the Court of Appeal            and the  High  Court respectively in all  causes            and  matters whatsoever in or with respect to            Avhich  those courts respectively  have for the            time being jmisdiction (&quot;including  theproeedure25          and practice to  be followed in the offices of the           - Supreme  Court and in  district registries), and            any  matters incidental  to  or relating  to any            such  procedure  or  practice,  including  (but            without prejudice to the generality of the fore-30          going description) the manner in which, and the            time within which,  any applications which under            this or any other Act are to be made  to the            Court of Appeal or to  the High  Court shall be            made:35      (b) For regulating and prescribing the procedure on            appeals from any court  or person to  the Court            of Appeal or the  High Court, and the procedure            in connection with the transfer  of. proceedings            from any inferior  court to  the High Court or40          from the High  Court to any&apos;inferior court:     .        (c) For regulating the sittings of the Court of Appeal            and the High Court, and of the divisional courts            of the High Court, and of the  judges  of the
 A.D. 192*.,    /    ;  High Court  whether  sitting  in  court  or  in                   chambers:               (d)  For prescribing what part of the business  to  be                   transacted and the  jurisdiction to be exercised                   by judges of  the High Court in chambers  may  5                   be transacted or exercised  by masters of  the                   Supreme  Court,  registrars  of  the  Probate,                   Divorce  and  Admiralty  Division,  or   other                   officers of the Supreme Court:               (e) For regulating any matters relating to the costs  10                   of proceedings in  the Court of Appeal or  the                   High Court:    &apos;           (/)  For  regulating and prescribing the procedure                   and  practice  to  be followed  in  the Court  of                   Appeal  or the High Court in cases in which the  15                   procedure or practice  is regulated by any enact-                   ments in force at the commencement of this Act                   (including so much of any of the Acts set out in                   the Second Schedule to this Act as is specified in                   the third column of  that Schedule), and  for  20                   repealing any of those enactments so far  as                   they  relate  to matters with respect to  which                   rules may be  made under this section:               (g)  For regulating or making provision with respect                   to any other matters which are regulated or with  25                   respect to which  provision is made  by the rules                   of the  Supreme  Court in force  at  the  com-                   mencement of this Act, or  by  any  rules  or                   regulations so in  force with  respect to practice                   and procedure in matrimonial causes or with  30                   respect  to applications  and  proceedings  under21 &amp; 22 Viet.          the Legitimacy Declaration Act, 1858.c. 93.                                             ,         .-               (2)  No rule of the Supreme Court which may involve          any increase of expenditure  out  of public funds shall  be          made except with the concurrence of the Treasury, but  35          the validity of any rule of the Supreme Court shall not in          any proceedings in any court  be called in question either          by the court or by any party to  the proceedings on the          ground only that it was a rule  to which the  concurrence          of the Treasury was necessary and that  the Treasury did  40          not concur or are not expressed to have concurred in the          making thereof.
        (3)  Section one of  the Rules Publication Act, 1893  A-.D..&apos;l924.    (which requires notice to be given of a proposal to make  56&amp;&quot;5Ty;ct    statutory rules) shall not apply to  rules of the  Supreme  c. 66.     &apos;    Court. 5      (4s) All rules  of court made before the commence-    ment of this Act under enactments  repealed  by this Act,    and all  rules  and  regulations with  respect to practice    and procedure  in  matrimonial causes or with respect to    applications  and   proceedings  under  the  Legitimacy10  Declaration Act, 1858, made before the commencement    of  this Act under section fifty-three of the Matrimonial  20 &amp; 21 Viet.    Causes Act,  1857, or under that section as applied by  c-  H5,    section four  of the Legitimacy Declaration Act, 1858,    shall, notwithstanding the repeal of enactments effected15  by  this Act, continue in force and  shall have effect as if    made under this section.        (5) Nothing,  in this section shall affect the power    conferred by section one hundred and thirty-two  of  the    Bankruptcy.  Act,  1914,  of  making  general  rules  for  4 &amp; 5 G-eo. 5.20  carrying into effect the objects of that Act, or the power  c-  59-    conferred on the  President  of the  Probate Division  by    section  thirty  of  the Court of Probate  Act,  1857, as  20 &amp;  21 Viet.    applied by  section  eighteen of the  Supreme  Court of  a-77-    Judicature Act, 1875, of making rules and  orders with  jjs^39v&apos;ct.25  respect to the  practice and procedure in non-contentious   probate business, and the power to make rules of court   under this section shall  not extend to the matters with   respect to which rules or orders  may be  made  by virtue   of the enactments  mentioned in this  subsection. 30     13.-(1)  The following provisions  shall have effect Trial with    in relation to the trial of actions in a county court or any J&quot;&apos;T &apos;u    other inferior court of civil jurisdiction:                 courts7and        (a) In actions within  the equity jurisdiction of the courts&apos;^&apos;61             court, and  in actions  in  which  the  amount civil juris--35          claimed  does not exceed five pounds, the  trial diction.             shall, unless otherwise ordered by the court or a l^^52 Viot&apos;             judge, be without a jury:        (b) Any action, not being an action to which para-             graph (a) of this section applies, in which there 40          is a claim in respect  of  libel, slander, malicious             prosecution,  false  imprisonment,  seduction  or
A.D. 1924.Amendmentof s. 11of county courts Act,1919.9&amp;10Geo.5.o 73.        breach of promise of marriage, shall, if any party        thereto so requires, be tried with a jury :    (c) Any action, not being  an action to which para-        graph (a) or paragraph (b) of this section applies,        shall, if any party thereto  so requires, be tried 5        with a jury, unless the court or a judge is satisfied        on an application  made by any party thereto        that the action  is more fit  to  be tried without        a jury:          Provided that if  on the  trial  of  any action 10        to which paragraph (c) applies it appears to  the        judge that the  action is more fit  to  be tried        without  a jury, he may,  notwithstanding that        no application has been made for a trial without        a  jury  or that any such  application has been 15        refused, direct that  the  action  shall be tried        without a jury.    (2) In this section the expression &quot; action &quot; includesany matter or other proceeding requiring to be tried, andthe expression &quot; equity  jurisdiction&quot;  in relation to  a 20county  court means the equity jurisdiction given to county  courts by  section  sixty-seven  of the  county courts Act, 1888.    14. The following proviso shall be substituted forproviso (ii)  to subsection (1) of section eleven of. the 25County Courts Act, 1919 (which relates to costs of actionscommenced in the High Court  which  could have been commenced in a county court) -    &quot;(ii)  if  in   any action  the  claim  is for a debt or         liquidated demand only for a sum of  twenty 30         pounds  or upwards and&apos;               (a) the defendant pays the amount claimed           or a sum of not less than twenty pounds within           the time limited in that behalf by the endorse-           ment  made  on the writ in accordance with 35           the rules of &quot;the Supreme Court; or              (b) the plaintiff, Avithin twenty-eight days           after the service of the writ or  within such           further time as may be allowed  by the court           or a  judge,  obtains  judgment in  default of 40           appearance or of defence for a sum of twenty           pounds or upwards; or
[14 GEO. 5.]Administration of Justice.n                ((?) the plaintiff, within twenty-eight days  A.D. 1924.              after  the  service of the writ or within such    &apos;              further time as may be allowed by the court              or a  judge,  obtains  under any rule of the 5            Supreme Court providing for summary judg-              ment without trial an order empowering him              to sign judgment for a sum of twenty pounds  ,              or upwards,  either unconditionally or unless              that  sum is paid into court or to the plaintiffs10            solicitor;            the plaintiff shall, unless  otherwise ordered  by            the court or a judge, be entitled to costs on such            scale as may be prescribed by rules of court.        15. (1) Where in any cause or matter in the King&apos;s Transfer to-15 Bench  Division  of  the  High Court, money  is  in any county court&apos;   manner recovered  by or on  behalf  of, or adjudged or &quot;fc&quot;&quot;&quot;^ .q   ordered to  be paid to or  for the benefit of, a person who i^Xcotirt   is an infant or of unsound  mind, the High Court or a by Infants,   judge may  order  the money  or any part thereof to  be *c.20 paid into  or transferred to  the   county  court  of  the   district  in which that person resides or such other county   court as the High Court or  judge may order,  and the   money  or  the part  thereof to  which the &quot;order relates   shall thereupon be paid or transferred accordingly, and25 shall, subject to any special order or direction of  the   High Court or a  judge and to rules of court, be invested,   applied  or otherwise dealt with for the benefit of that   person in  the same manner as if it had been money paid   into a county court in proceedings  under the Workmen&apos;s30 Compensation Act,  1906 to  1923, and ordered  by the   judge of the court to be invested, applied or otherwise   dealt with.        (2)  The. provisions of this section  shall apply to any   money which in  proceedings under the  Datal  Accidents35 Acts, 1846 to  1908, is recovered  by or  adjudged  or   ordered  to be paid  to  the  widow of the person killed   as  they apply  to money recovered by  or  adjudged  or   ordered to be paid to an infant.        (3)  The Lord Chancellor may, with the  concurrence40 of the Treasury, by order prescribe the fees to be charged   in respect  of the  payment and investment of  money or   the application  thereof or dealing therewith  under this   section.
 A.D. 1924.      (4) Where, before the commencement  of  this Act,          any money recovered in any cause or matter in the King&apos;s          Bench Division of the High  Court, by or on behalf of a          person who is  an infant  or  of unsound  mind  has  been          paid  to the. Public Trustee,  it shall  be lawful for the 5          Public Trustee to  pay that money, or so much of it as          remains  in  his possession, into the county court of the          district in which that person  resides, and any money so          transferred shall be invested, applied, or dealt, with in the          same manner as if it had been  paid into the county court 10          under subsection (1) of this section.               (5) County court rules may be made  for the purpose          of carrying  into effect the provisions  of  this section, so          far as they relate to the receipt of money into the county          courts and the  investment thereof or application thereof 15          or dealing therewith and the duties of registrars of county          courts, and  any such rules may provide for the transfer          of money paid into a county court under this section from          one county court to another.Amendment      16. (l) The  following   paragraph shall  be  sub- 20as to funds  stituted  for paragraph  (9) of section eighteen  of the35 &amp; 35Viet. Court of  Chancery (Funds) Act, 1872 (which  givesc. 44.     &apos; power - to the Lord Chancellor, with the concurrence of          the&apos; Treasury,  to make rules  for  carrying  that Act into          effect):-                                              25                   &quot; (9)  Dealing with-                      - (a) accounts on which the balance of money                     and securities  together amounts to less  than                     five pounds;                       (5) accounts on which that balance amounts 30                     to five  pounds or  more, but  less than  fifty                     pounds, and  which have riot  been dealt with                     for a period of five years;                       (e) accounts on which that balance amounts                     to fifty pounds or  more  and which  have not 35                     been dealt with for a period of fifteen years;                 and providing  for the publication  of lists of all or                 any of such last-mentioned accounts.&quot;               (2) Accounts  in such  form  as the Treasury  may          direct, including all such accounts as  may be necessary 40          for  carrying into  effect the orders of the High Court,          shall be kept for the purposes of  the  Court of Chancery
   (Funds)  Act, 1872, as amended by the Supreme Court A.D. 1924.   of Judicature  (Funds, &amp;c.) Act, 1883, and this Act, and       &apos;   separate  accounts  shall  be kept  for the  transactions-   under  those Acts  of the  Accountant-General  of  the 5 Supreme Court and of the National Debt Commissioners   and  of the liability  of  the  Consolidated  Fund under   those Acts.        The accounts  to  be  kept  as  aforesaid shall  be   examined by the Comptroller and  Auditor  General, and10 the Treasury shall  cause copies of  the accounts certified   by the Comptroller and Auditor  General, together  with   his report thereon, to be sent to the Lord Chancellor and   to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.        17. (1)  The  office for the registration of deeds  of Amendment15 arrangement under the Deeds of Arrangement Act,  1914 aB t0 fegis-   (in this section referred to as &quot;the Act of 1914&quot;),  shall ^^0f   be transferred to the Board of Trade, and the registrar for arranI,ement   the purposes of the Act of 1914 shall be appointed by the     Q.eo 5^   Board  of Trade,  and  references  in &apos; that  Act  to  the e. 47.20 registrar of bills of sale or to the registrar for the purposes   of that  Act shall be  construed  as   references to  the   registrar so appointed.        (2)  Subsection (1) of section  five of the Act of 1914   (which provides that a copy of every deed to be registered25 shall be presented  to the registrar)  shall have effect as   if it provided that there shall be presented to the registrar   such number of copies of the deed and of every schedule   or inventory annexed thereto or referred  to therein as  he   may deem  to be  necessary for the purpose of carrying30 out the requirements  of the Act of 1914 as amended by   this section.        (3)  Paragraph (c) of section six  of the Act of  1914   (which provides that  a short statement of the nature and   effect  of the  deed shall be entered in the register)  shall35 cease to have effect.        (4)  Subsection (2) of section twenty-six of the Act   of 1914 (which  provides that section twenty-six of the    Supreme Court of Judicature Act, 1875, as amended by 38 &amp; 39 Viet.    any subsequent enactment, shall apply to fees under the 0. 77.40 Act of 1914), shall apply only to fees to be taken in the    Supreme Court in respect of  matters arising  under the    Act of  1914 as amended  by  this section,  and save  as    aforesaid all fees whatsoever  under that Act shall  be
A.D. 1924.  prescribed by order made by the Lord Chancellor with the          concurrence of the Treasury and not otherwise.           ,,.   (5.)  Subject to  the provisions  of  subsection  (4)  of          this section, rules for carrying into effect the provisions of          the Act  of 1914, as amended  by this section, other than 5          the  provisions of section seven thereof, may be  made by          the Lord Chancellor with the concurrence of the President          of  the  Board of Trade, and, subject,  as aforesaid, the          expression &quot; prescribed &quot; in. the Act of 1914 shall mean          prescribed by rules made under this subsection.           10               (6)  This  section shall  be  construed as  one with the          Act of 1914.AMENDMENTof BILLS-of sale ACTS,1878 AND1882, WITHRESPECT TOLOCAL REGIS-TRATLON of bills OF SALE.45&amp;46 VIET.C. 43.41&amp;42 VIET.C. 31.ADMIUISTRA-TION BONDS.20,5-21 VIET.&apos;C. 77.9&amp;.10GEO.5.C. 26. -10 &amp; 11GEO. 5. C.81. .  .18. (1) Section  eleven of the  Bills  of  Sale  Act(1878) Amendment Act, 1882 (which makes provision for &apos;the local, registration of the contents of bills  of sale), 15shall have effect as if it required the registrar of bills of sale to transmit to county court registrars copies of the.&apos;bills instead of abstracts  of the contents of the  bills, and references in that section to the abstract transmitted  andthe abstract registered shall be  construed accordingly.    20    (2) Section ten of the Bills of  Sale Act, 1878, shallhave effect as though it required the presentation to the registrar on the registration  of  a bill of sale, in additionto the copy of the bill&apos;of, sale mentioned in paragraph (2)of that.section, of such number of  copies of the bill  and 25every  schedule . and  inventory annexed thereto as the registrar,  may  deem  to be  necessary for  the purpose ofcarrying out the requirements of the said section eleven  .as amended by this section.    19.-(1) Every administration bond shall, instead 30of being given  as  provided by section  eighty-one of theCourt of  Probate Act, 1857, as  amended by the  Grant ofAdministration (Bonds) Act, 1919, and section  eighteenof the Administration of  Justice Act, 1920, be  given tothe. principal  probate registrar  by&apos;his official name, and 35may be  so  given  notwithstanding  any vacancy  in  theoffice  of  principal probate  registrar, and; the  principalprobate, registrar  for the time being shall have  power toput in  suit any administration bond  given under  thissection or to assign, it in accordance with the provisions 40of this section to some other person.       -
582         (2) Where it; appears to the satisfaction of the Court  A:D. 1924:    or. a judge that the condition of an administration bond    has  been  broken, the  court  or judge   may,  on  an    application  in  that  behalf,  order  the  principal probate  5 registrar to assign the  bond  to  such person  as may  k be  specified in the order, and the person  to whom the    bond is assigned  in  pursuance  of the order  shall  be  -    entitled to sue thereon in his, own name  as if it had been    originally given to him instead of to the principal probate 10 registrar, and to recover thereon as trustee for all persons    interested the full amount recoverable in respect of  the    breach of the condition thereof.         (3) Without prejudice to any proceedings  instituted    before the commencement of this Act, any administration 15  bond given before the commencement  of this Act  under    any enactment  repealed by this Act, or which  is to  be    enforceable  as  if  it  had  been given  under any such    enactment, may be put in suit or assigned as if it had    been given  to the principal probate registrar Under this 20  section.        (4). References  in  this  section  to the  principal    probate  registrar  shall, so  far as  relates to the  putting    in suit or the assigning of an administration  bond during    any period when the office of principal probate registrar 25  is vacant,  be construed  as including  references to  the    senior registrar for the time being of the  principal probate    registry.&apos;   i s &apos;          i  &apos;o.   t  j*       .,&quot;        (5)  The provisions of this section shall  apply  to    any bond to  be  given by  a-receiver of real  estate.under SO  section twenty-one of the Court of Probate Act, 1858, as  &apos;.they apply to an administration bond.        20.-(1) Any  instrument  which   is  required   or Enrolment    authorised tinder or in pursuance of the provisions of any audengross-    enactment  tp be enrolled  or engrossed  or  enrolled  and j&quot;,^,^^35  engrossed in any manner in the; Supreme Court shall be    deemed to haye been duly enrolled, engrossed, or  enrolled         &apos;    and  engrossed in. accordance with those  provisions if; it is    written on  such material and  has been filed  or otherwise    preserved in such manner ,as . the  Master  of the Rolls40  may by order direct. .,         .        (2)  The power of the Master of the Rolls.to prescribe    the-fees-  tp.be, paid on the: enrolment and&apos;filing of deeds    under, section,  twenty of  the Administration of  Justice        11                   B
A.D. 1924.Provision asto fixing of fees to betakeu inSupremeCourt.38 &amp; 39 Viet,c. 7-7.Repeal ofcertainobsoleteenactmentsrelating toadministni-tion ofjustice.Power to revoke andvary orders.&apos; Short title, interpreta- tion, extent, repeal and commence- ment.Act,  1920,  shall  be exercised by  him  subject  to the &apos;-concurrence of the Treasury.    21. Any enactment authorising  the making of  rules of court for imposing or fixing the amount of any fees tobe  taken  in  connection with proceedings in the Supreme 5Court  shall cease  to  have  effect, and  provision forimposing  or  fixing the  amount of any fees to which anysuch enactment relates may be made by means of orders under  section  twenty-six of  the  Supreme  Court ofJudicature Act, 1875 :                                  10     Provided that nothing in this section shall affect the validity of  any rule of court so made before the  com-mencement of  this Act, and any  such rule shall  haveeffect as if it were an order made under  the said  section twenty-six.                                             15     22., Whereas the  enactments  set out in Part  I. ofthe Third Schedule to this Act have to the extent specifiedin the  third  column of that  Part  of that Schedule bylapse  of  time or   otherwise  become   unnecessary orobsolete,  and it is  desirable  that they  should,  with  a 20view to the consolidation of  the enactments  relating to;the  Supreme Court, be forthwith repealed;     Now, therefore, the  enactments aforesaid shall be repealed to the  extent specified as aforesaid.     23.  Any order made under this Act  by the  Lord 25Chancellor,  the Lord Chief Justice of  England, or thePresident of the  Probate Division  may  at any time be revoked, varied or amended by a subsequent  order madeunder this Act by the Lord  Chancellor, the Lord  chief justice of   England, or  the  President  of the  Probate 30Division, as  the case may be.      24.-(1)  This Act may be cited as the Admimstrationof Justice Act, 1924.      (2) In  this  Act the expression &quot; solicitor *&apos; means solicitor of the Supreme Court.                       A-35      (3) This Act does not extend to Scotland or Northern Ireland.      (4) The enactments  set out in Part II. of the Third&quot; Schedule to this  Act are hereby repealed to the extent specified in the third column of that Part  of that Schedule. 40      (5) This,.Act shall come into  operation on the first day of           , nineteen hundred and twenty-four.
50 9SCHEDULES.A.D. 1924.FIRST  SCHEDULE.Section 3.QUALIFICATION  FOE, CERTAIN OFFICES IN THE               SUPREME COURT.Office..1. Permanent  Seore-  tary to  the  Lord  Chancellor    and  Clerk of the Crown.1015   2. Master,    King&apos;s      Bench Division (in-20    eluding the Kings      Coroner and Attor-      ney and  Master of      the Crown Office).   3. Official Referee  -254.  Master in Lunacy30    5. Registrar in Bank-35    ruptcy  and Com-      panies  (Winding-      up).        11   Persons qualified for appointment.1. (i) A  practising barrister of not less      than ten years&apos; standing ; or (ii) A barrister of not less than ten years&apos;      standing who has during the ten      years immediately preceding his      appointment  been employed in      some legal capacity  under the       State, or who has during part of      that period been employed in such      a capacity  and during  the re-      mainder of that  period been in 1      practice as a barrister.2. (i) A  practising  barrister of not less      than ten years&apos; standing ; or (ii) An official referee;  or(iii) A master  in lunacy.3. (i) A practising barrister.of not less       than ten years&apos; standing ; or (ii) A master, King&apos;s Bench  Division.;       or(iii) A master in lunacy.4.-(i) A practising barrister of not less    than ten years&apos; standing;  or (ii) A master, King&apos;s Bench  Division ;    or(iii) An official referee.5. A  practising barrister or  practising  solicitor  of not less  than  ton years&apos;  standing.       B 2
       Office.              Persons qualified for appointment. ,6.  Master,  Chancery -6.-(i) A  practising Solicitor of not less  Division.                   than, ten years&apos; standing ;  or                       (ii) A master, Taxing Office;  or                      (iii) The official solicitor to the Supreme 5                             Court.7.  Master,    Taxing  7. (i) A practising solicitor of  not less  Office.                     than ten years&apos; standing;  or                       (ii) An  admitted  solicitor of  not  less                             than ten years&apos; standing who has 10                             during the ten years immediately                             preceding his appointment been                             employed  as deputy or  assistant                   &apos;          master or-as deputy or  assistant                          ..  to  the official  solicitor  or as a&apos;15                             clerk hi the  offices  of the Royal                             Courts of  Justice,  or  who has      .        ,              . during part of that period been                             employed   as  such  deputy   or  &apos;                          assistant  or  clerk  and  during 20                             the remainder of that period been                             in practice as a solicitor;  or                      (iii) A master, Chancery Division ;  or                      (iv) The official solicitor to the Supreme                          .,. Court.                          25S. Legal  Visitor in  8. A  practising  banister  or practising   Lunacy.               solicitor  of not  less than  ten years&apos;                         standing.   .9. Official   Solicitor  .9.- (i) A practising solicitor of  not less   to   the  Supreme         than ten years&apos; standing; or      30   Court.              (ii) An  admitted  solicitor of  not..less                             than ten years&apos; standing who has                             during the ten years immediately                             preceding  his  appointment been                             employed as deputy or  assistant 35                             master  or as deputy or  assistant                         1    to the official solicitor  or as clerk                             in  the offices.of the Royal Courts                             of  Justice,  or who has during                             part of that period been employed 40                             as  such deputy  or assistant  or                             clerk and  during  the remainder                             of  that period been in practice as   &apos;   -   &apos;  ;                 &apos; a solicitor;  or    &apos; .                      (iii) A master, Chancery Division; or   45&apos;                       (iv)  A master, Taxing (Office.
584SECOND  SCHEDULE. A.D. 1924.Section 12.ENACTMENTS CONTAINING AND  REGULATING  MATTERS   WITH RESPECT  TO WHICH  EULES  OF COURT MAY                        BE MADE.Session and Chapter.&apos;&apos;i  Will.  &amp;  Mar. c. 18.108 &amp; 9 Will. 3.  c. 11.15 i &amp; 5 Anne     c. 3.20  39 &amp; 40 Geo. 3 : &apos;   c. 36.    10  Geo.  4.    11 Geo. 4. &amp;25    l  Will  4.     c. 36.    3&amp;4 Will.4.     c. 42.    1  &amp; 2 Viet.30   c. 110.    3  &amp; 4 Viet.      e. 65.    3  &amp; 4 Viet.      c. 82.35  5 Viet. o. 5 -    5  &amp; 6 Viet.      c. 86.Title or Short Title.An Act  to -prevent  malicious  informa-  tions in the Court of  King&apos;s Bench.An Act for the better  preventing of frivol-  ous   and  vexatious  suits.An   Act   for   the  Amendment of the  Law and  the better  Advancement    of  Justice.The Transfer of Stock  Act, 1800.The Court Funds Act,  1829.The    Contempt   of  Court Act, 1830.The  Civil  Procedure  Act, 1833.The  Judgments Act,  1838.The Admiralty Court  Act, 1840.The  Judgments Act,  1840.The Court of Chancery  Act, 1841.The Exchequer Court  Aot, 1842.Enactments afiected.The whole Act  so far as tin-  repealed.The. whole  Act so far .as un-  repealed.Sections twelve and thirteen.The whole Act-so far as un-  repealed.The whole Act so far as un-  repealed.The whole Act so far as uu-  repealed.Sections sixteen and eighteen.Sections fourteen and fifteen.Sections seven, eight, and nine.The whole Act so far as un-  repealed.Section four.The whole Act  so  far as nn-
A.D. 1924.Session and Chapter.	Title or Short Title.	Enactments afiected.5 &amp; 6 Viet. e;97. 12 &amp; 13 Viet. e. 109. 15 &amp; 16 Viet. c. 76. 20&amp;21 Viet. e. 77. -20&amp;21 Viet. c. 85. 21&amp;22 Viet. c. 93. 21 &amp;22 Viet. c. 95. 21 &amp; 22 Viet. c. 108. 23 &amp; 24 Viet. c. 149. 24 &amp; 25 Viet. c. 10. 30 &amp; 31 Viet. e. 47. 36 &amp; 37 Viet. c. 66.	The Limitations of Actions and Costs Act, 1842. The Petty Bag Act, 1849. The Common Law Procedure Act, 1852. The Court of Probate Act, 1857. The Matrimonial Causes Act, 1857. The Legitimacy De-claration Act, 1858. The Court of Probate Act, 1858. The Matrimonial Causes Act, 1858. The Court of Chancery Act, 1860. The Admiralty Court Act, 1861.. The Lis Pendens Act, 1867. The Supreme Court of Judicature Act, 1873.	Sections four and five. 5 The whole Act so far as un-repealed. Sections one hundred and twenty-six, one hundred and twenty-seven, one hundred 10 and thirty-t&apos;wo, two hundred and ten to two hundred and&apos; fourteen, and two hundred and seventeen to two hundred and twenty. 1&quot; Sections twenty-four, twenty-six and thirty-one. Sections thirty-nine,- forty rone to forty-four, forty six, and forty-nine. o\J Section three. Section twenty-three. Section thirteen. 25 Sections two, three, five, and six. Sections sixteen, eighteen, twenty-five, twenty-six, 3.0 twenty-eight, thirty-three, and thirty-four. The whole Act so far as un-repealed. Sections forty-six, sixty-four 35 and sixty-six.
mixJo J[14 GEO. 5.]    Administration of Justice,21THIRD  SCHEDULE.A.D. 1924.ENACTMENTS REPEALED.         PART  I.Section 22,Session and Chapter.Short Title.S Eliz. c. 2  - 10    7  Will. 4 &amp;       1 Viet. c. 30    3  &amp; 4 Viet.       e. 65. 15 5  &amp; 6 Viet.       c. 103.    15 &amp; 16 Viet.       c. 73. 20  15 &amp; 16 Viet.       c. isO.     15 &amp; 16 Viet.&apos;       c. 87.     20 &amp; 21 Viet.,25    e.77.     20&amp;21 Viet.       c. 85.     21 &amp; 22 Viet.       c. 95. 30 21 &amp; 22 Viet.       c. 108.     24 &amp; 25 Viet.       K. 10.     30 &amp; 31 Viet. 35   c. 87.    - 32 &amp; 33 Viet.       e. 89.     32 &amp; 33 Viet.       c. 91. 40An Acte whereby the  Defendant    maye  recover his Costes  beinge  wrongfully  vexed.The  Superior Courts  (Officers) Act, 1837.Extent of Repeal.The whole Act.Section nineteen.The  Admiralty Court  Sections twenty and twenty-one.  Act, 1840.The Court of Chancery  Act, 1842. .The  Common  Law  Courts Act,  1852.The Court of Chancery  Act, 1852.The Court of Chancery  Act, 1852.The Court of  Probate  Act, 1857.The Matrimonial Causes  Act, 1857.The Court of  Probate  Act, 1858.The Matrimonial Causes  Act, 1858.The Admiralty Court   Act, 1861.The Court of Chancery  (Officers) Act, 1867.The Clerks of Assize,   &amp;c., Act, 1869.The Courts of Justice   (Salaries and Funds)   Act,. 1869.   jIn  section eleven  the  words  from  &quot; and  every  solicitor &quot;  to the end of the section.Section twenty-six.Sections nineteen,  twenty arid  twenty-three.Sections three and four.Sections eighty-eight and ninety  four.Sections  thirty-seven,  thirty-  eight, and forty.Sections seventeen and twenty-  eight.Sections five and fourteen.Sections  thirteen,  twenty-one,  twenty-three, and thirty.The whole Act.Paragraph (2) of section three.  .Section eight.
82Administration .of Justice.    [14 GEO. .5.]A.D. 1924.Session and Chapter.35 &amp; 36 Viet.  c. 44.36 &amp; 37 Viet.  c. 66.Short Title.Extent of Repeal.38 &amp; 39 Viet.  c.  77.42 &amp; 43 Viet.  c.  78. 44 &amp; 45 Viet.   c. 68. 53 &amp; 54 Viet. V o. 44.&quot;54 &amp; 55 Viet.  .&apos;&apos;c, 14.  -The Court of Chancery  (Funds) Act, 1872.The Supreme Court of  Judicature     Act,  1873.The Supreme Court of  Judicature    Act,  1875.The Supreme Court of  Judicature (Officers)  Act  1879.The Supreme Court of  Judicature    Act,  1881.The Supreme Court of  Judicature   &apos; Aotj  1890. -The Supreme Court of  Judicature (London  Causes) Act, 1891.Section twenty-five.in   section   twenty-nine   the  5  words from &quot; and subject to  any restrictions &quot; to the  end  of   the  section, in  section  thirty-two   the  words  from . &quot;and  such  Order&quot;  to   the  10  words &quot; and patronage  but,&quot;  in  section  thirty-three   the  words  from  -&quot;every docu-  meut &quot;to the end of the sec-  tiou,  section  forty-four,  in  15  secti6n fifty-two the words &quot; cr  a  Divisional Court thereof,&quot;  &apos;  and  in section eighty-four  the  words from  the  beginning of  the section to the words &quot; from  20 . time to time determine!&quot;In- paragraph  1  of - section  twenty-three the words  from  &quot;and in particular&quot;  to  the  words &quot; any of them.&quot;         25In  section   ten   the  words  &quot; or  has practised for five  &quot; years as  a special pleader  &quot; or as a special pleader and  &quot;- barrister,&quot;  arid  sections 30  sixteen and twenty-six.Section eleven.Section two.The whole Act.0040Section 24.Part II.7 Will. 4 and  . 1 Viet. e. 303 &amp;  4 Viet.  c. 65.5 &amp;  6 Viet.  c. 103.The Superior Courts  (Officers) Act, 1837.The Admiralty Court  Act, 1840.The Court of Chancery  Aci, 1842.Section thirteen.Section eighteen.Section six.45
Session and Chapter.Short Title.Extent ot Repeal.   15 &amp;16 Yict.     c. 80.5  20 &amp; 21 Viot.     c. 77.15  20 &amp; 21 Viot.      o. 85.    21 &amp; 22, Viot.      o. 93.20  21 &amp; 22 Viet.      c. 95.    24 &amp; 25 Viet.25    c.  io.    35 &amp; 36 Viet.      c. 44,36 &amp; 37 Viet.  c. 66.    38 &amp; 39 Viet,45   o. 77.    39 &amp; 40 Vie i      c. 59.11The Court of Chancery  Act, 1852.The Court of Probate  Act, 1857.The      Matrimonial Causes Act, 1857.The Legitimacy Decla-  ratiou Act, 1858.The Court  of Probate  Act, 1858.The  Admiralty Court  Act, 1861.The Court of Chancery (Funds) Act, 1872.The  Supreme  Court  of  Judicature  Act,  1873.The  Supreme  Court  of  Judicature  Act,  1875.Tbe  Appellate Juris-  diction Act, 1876.cSections seventeen and twenty-  one.Section   nineteen,  in   section  eighty-one  as  amended   by  the Grant  of  Administra-  tiou (Bonds) Act, 1919, the  words  &quot; or in the case of a  &quot; vacancy in&apos; that office to a  &quot; registrar of  the  principal  &quot; probate registry&quot; and the  words &quot; the Court of Probate  &quot; or.&quot;Sections  thirty-six, fifty-three,  fifty-four and sixty-seven.In section four the words from  &quot;and the  powers&quot;   to  the  words &quot; before the court.&quot;Section  fifteen, and  in section  twenty-one  the words  from  &quot; probate Act &quot;  to the end of  the section.In  section  twenty-seven, the  words &quot; or deputy.&quot;In section eight the words from  &quot; and shall&quot; to the  end of the.  section,  the  first  paragraph  of   section  nineteen,   and  section twenty.In  paragraph  (2)  of section  thirty-four the  words  &quot; ex-  &quot;  cept  appeals  from county  courts,&quot;  in  section sixty  the  words    from   &quot; and   Her  Majesty&quot; to  the end of  that  section, in section eighty-three  the words &quot; and the  qualifica-  tions,&quot; and in section eighty-  four the words from  &quot; any  &quot;  officer  of   the   Supreme  &quot;  Court&quot;   to   &quot; order   of  &quot;  removal.&quot;Sections   thirteen,  seventeen,  eighteen,  twenty-two  and  twenty-four. Section   sixteen,  in  section  seventeen  the  words  from  &quot; and rules  of court for&quot; to   the  end  of  the section  and   Bection twenty-two.
A. I). 1924.Session and Cnaptcr.	Short Title.	Extent of Uepcal,42 &amp; 43 Viet. c. 78. 44 &amp; 45 Viet. c. 59. 44 &amp; 45 Viet. c. 68. 46&amp;47 Viet. c. .29. 46 &amp; 47 Viet. c..49. 47 &amp; 48 Viet. e. 20. 47 &amp; 48 Viet. c.,61. 52 &amp; 53 Viet. c. 49. 53&amp;54 Viet. e. 5. . 53 &amp; 54 Viet, c. 44. 57 &amp; 58 Viet. o. 16. 58 &amp; 59 Viet. c. 39. 8 Edw. 7. e. 47...	The Supreme Court of Judicature (Officers) Act, 1879. The Statute Law Re-vision and Civil Procedure Act, 1881. The Supreme Court of &apos; - judicature Act, 1881. The Supreme Court of . Judicature (Funds, etc.) Act. 1883. The Statute Law Re-vision and Civil Procedure Act, 1883. The Greek Marriages Act, 1884. The Supreme Court of Judicature Act, 1884. The Arbitration Act, 1889. The Lunacy Act, 1890 The Supreme Court of Judicature Aet, 1890. The Supreme Court of Judicature (Pro-cedure) Act, 189,4 The Summary Jnris-diction (Married Women) Act, 1895. The Lunacy Aet, 1908	Subsection (4.) ,of section nine, sections ten, eleven, thirteen, eighteen and twenty-two. 5 In section six the words from &quot;matters with respect&quot; to the words &quot; and to all.&quot; Section twenty-two. 10 Subsection (2) of section four. o . &apos;.&quot; 15 Section six. In section one the words from &quot;or with such rules&quot; to the 20 end of the section. Section twenty-three. Section twenty-oue. 25 In subsection (3) of section one bundled and eleven the j words &quot;must be a barrister &apos;&quot; of not less than ten years&apos; 30 &quot; standing and &quot; and in sub-section (5) of that section the words &quot;number and,&quot; and in subsection (2) of sec. tion one hundred and sixty- 35 three the words &quot; being a barrister of not less than five years&apos; standing.&quot; Section three. 40 Section five and the Schedule. In section eleven the words from &quot; rules of court &quot; to the 45 end of the section. Section four.
587ession and Chapter.Short Title.A.D.&apos; 192-LExtent of Repeal.8  Edw.  c. 69.4. &amp; 5 Geo. 5.  e. 17.10152025  9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.      c. 25.The Companies (Con-  s^Iidationl      Act,  1908.The Deeds of A rrange-  ment Act, 1914.10&amp;11 Geo..  i). 81.3035The Grant of Admiuis-  tration (Bonds) Act,  1919.The Administration of  Justice Act. 1920.In subsection (1) of section two  hundred aud thirty-eight, the  words &quot; and  ees &quot; so far as  they  relate  to  the   High  Court,Section four, in subsection (1)  of  section  five the  words  from &quot; in  like  manner&quot; to  the  words   &quot; to  be  filed,&quot;  paragraph (c) of section six,  in subsection (4)  of section  thirteen the words from &quot; and  the &quot; to the end of the section,  in  section twenty-seven the  words  from  &quot;aud  for the  purposes&quot; to the end  of the  section, section  twenty-eight,  in  section  twenty-nine the  words from &quot;but this&quot; to the  end of the seotiou, and in sec-   tion thirty the  interpretation  of &quot;prescribed.&quot; The whole Act.Section two,  subsection (1) of  section three, and in subsection  (1)  of  section eighteen the  words &quot; taken to or for the  &quot; use  of  His Majesty,  and  &quot; subject  as aforesaid  shall  &quot; be &quot; and subsection  (2) of  that section.
Administration of        Justice.           D R A E T              OF A        13   ILLb amend the law with respect to the jurisdiction  and  business  of  the Supreme Court in England and- with respect to the officers  and offices thereof and  otherwise with respect to the  administration of justice  in England.II.  (5.)Uh February 1924.11-5
CABINET.             HOKB  AFFAIRS  COMMITTEE.               COUKTY COURTS BILL.     The attaohed Bill is circulated In connectionwith paragraph 4 of the Lord Chancellors Note on government bill (CP. 68 ( 24)  ).2, Whitehall  Gardens, S.W.1.     February 7th, 1924,
County  Courts  Bill.ARRANGEMENT  OE  CLAUSES.Clause. 1.   Appointment,  qualification,  &amp;c, of registrars  of      county courts and provision as to high bailiffs. 2.   Payment of registrars and high bailiffs. 3.   Appointment of assistant registrars, clerks, and other      officers of county courts. 4.   Retirement and pensions of registrars. 5.   Court service to be pensionable. 6.   Fees in workmen&apos;s compensation proceedings. 7.   Amendment of s. 59 of principal Act. 8.   Minor amendments of principal Act. 9.   Expenses.10.   Short title, interpretation, extent, and repeal.     SCHEDULES.12-3
                     D R A F T                        OF A     .  - [   .  &apos; -    .r  &apos;  :v;&apos;                BILL                         TOAmend the law relating  to  Officers  of   County  A.D. 1924.  Courts  in England  and of  District Registries  of  the  High Court  in  England  and to  make  further  provision with respect to such County  Courts  and  proceedings therein,   for  purposes  incidental thereto.   BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,         by and with the advice and consent of  the Lords   Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present   Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows :         1. (1)  From and after  the commencement of this Appoint-   Act  there shall, subject to the provisions of this section, ment, quali-   be a registrar  for every court who shall be  appointed fication&apos; &amp;0-   by the Lord Chancellor.                               of 00unty10      (2) No person shall be qualified to be appointed a courts and   registrar unless he is a solicitor of not  less than seven provision as   years&apos; standing.                                       b0ailifs        (3) The Lord  ChanceUor  may,  if  he thinks  fit,   appoint a person to be registrar of two or more courts.15      (4) The Lord Chancellor  may, if he thinks fit, in the   case of a court in a populous district appoint two persons   to execute jointly the office of registrar of the court, and   may in any case where joint registrars are  appointed   give directions with  respect to  the  division  between20 them of the duties of the office,  and may, as  he thinks   fit,  on  the  death, resignation  or removal of a  joint   registrar,  either   appoint  another person  to  be  joint   registrar in  his  place, or  give directions that the con-   tinuing registrar shall  act as sole registrar.       12-3              A 2
AD. 1924.      (5) Where after the  commencement of this  Act a          vacancy occurs in the  office of  high-bailiff of  a court          no person  shall be appointed  to that office, and there-          after  the registrar of that court shall by virtue  of his          office be the high-bailiff of the court.                     5              (6) Notice of a  vacancy occuring in the office  of          registrar or high  bailiff of a court i shall be forthwith          given to the Lord Chancellor by&apos; the judge of the court.              (7) If in any case the Lord Chancellor thinks it          expedient  so to  do, having- regard to the amount  of 10          business to be performed  by the  registrar of any court      .... .-  as such together with the business (if any) to be performed          by hunas high-bailiff of&apos; the court or as district registrar          of the High Court, he may, with the concurrence of the          Treasury, direct that the  registrar shall not, directly or 15          indirectly, engage in practice as a solicitor or carry on          any employment of such a nature as will in. the opinion of          the Lord Chancellor prevent him from properly performing          his duties as registrar.              A registrar in whose case a direction is given  under 20          this subsection is in this Act referred to as  &quot; a whole-time          registrar.&quot;              (8) The  Lord  Chancellor shall,  before  giving any          direction under which  a person will on appointment as          registrar be, or under which a  person holding the office 25          of registrar will become, a whole-time registrar, take steps          to satisfy himself that the health of the person concerned          is satisfactory.               (9) Nofhing in this section shall disqualify a registrar          appointed before the  commencement of  tins Act from 30          continuing to hold his office.Payment of      2.-(1) Every  registrar; shall be paid such salary,registrars   ^0 ]je either exclusive of the remuneration of any officershamff? &quot;   0^ ^e  court  and of any  other expenses.of his office or          not, as the Lord Chancellor may from time to time with 35          the consent of the Treasury direct, and, where the  salary          is inclusive of such remuneration and expenses as afore-          said, the Lord Chancellor may, if he thinks fit and subject          to the consent of the  Treasury, specify what part of          that  salary  is applicable to the  payment  of the said 40          remuneration and expenses.               (2)  Every high bailiff,of a, court, shall be paid such          salary, exclusive, of the remuneration of  any officers, as
    the Lord Chancellor may from time to time with  the  A.D. 1924.    consent of the Treasury direct.                          &apos;  - t.      ,  3. (1) Subject as  hereinafter provided, the Lord Appoint-    Chancellor may, with  the concurrence of the Treasury ment of  5 as to numbers and salaries, appoint in connection with assistance .s*ant    any court such assistant registrars, clerks, bailiffs, ushers, 0ifr]ja anJ-i    and messengers as he may consider necessary for carrying other offi-    out the work of the court, and may from time to time cers of    direct what duties shall be performed by those  officers county. i o respectively, and may, if he thinks fit, remove any such courts-    officer from his office :        Provided  that no person shall  be  qualified to  be    appointed an  assistant registrar unless he is  a solicitor    of not less than seven years&apos; standing.                      &quot; 15     (2)  Where there is  an assistant registrar, the Lord    Chancellor may direct  which  of the  powers and duties    of the registrar are to be exercised  and performed  by  &apos;  -    the assistant registrar, and the  assistant registrar shall,    when  exercising the powers  or  performing  the  duties20 specified in the direction, be deemed to be the registrar.       : (3)  Where a registrar is  paid  a  salary inclusive of    the remuneration of any officers, whether the part of the    salary applicable to the payment of that  remuneration is    specified under the last preceding section of this Act or .25 not, those officers  shall, notwithstanding anything  in    this section,  be appointed and be removable by  the    registrar. &apos;        (4)  The Lord Chancellor may, subject to the consent    of  the Treasury as to numbers  and  salary, appoint as30  officers in his  department such examiners  and other    officers as  he may consider necessary for the purpose of    controlling the accounts of county courts.       4.-(1) A  registrar to whom  this  section  applies Retirement    shall vacate his office at the end of the completed year and pensions35  of service  in the course of which he attains the  age  of of registrars.    seventy-two years:       Provided that  where the  Lord  Chancellor considers    it  desirable in the public interest to retain any registrar    in his office after he attains the age of seventy-two years,40  he may,  with  the approval of the Treasury, from time    to time authorise his continuance in  office up to such       12                     A3
  A.D. 1924.  later age, not exceeding seventy-five years, as he thinks    -    fit.               (2) The provisions of the Superannuation Acts, .1834           to 1919 (in this Act referred to as &quot; the Superannuation           Acts&quot;), shall apply to registrars to whom this section 5           applies, subject to the following modifications :                (a) The  superannuation allowance on   retirement                   shall be  in accordance  with the  provisions of                   the  First Schedule  to  this  Act  instead  of                   in  accordance  with the  provisions  of  the 10                   Superannuation Acts:9 Edw. 7.        (b) Section two of the  Superannuation  Act,  1909c&apos;10,               (which authorises the  grant of  a gratuity in                   case of death), as  amended by section two of4&amp;5Geo 6          the Superannuation Act, 1914, section three of 15c. 86.               the  Superannuation Act, 1909 (which provides                   for the application of the Act to  existing male                   civil servants),  and subsection (2) of  section six                  of the Superannuation Act,  1909 (which relates                  to compensation  on abolition of office), shall 20                  not apply: &apos;. Vicr.c.26.     (c)  Section ten of  the Superannuation Act,  1859,                  (which prohibits  the grant  of superannuation                  allowance to a person under the age of  sixty                  years except upon evidence  of infirmity), shall 25                  not apply, but a superannuation allowance shall                  not  be granted under this section to a person                  who is under the age of seventy-two years, unless                  the Treasury are satisfied on a medical certifi-                  cate that  he is incapable from infirmity of mind 30  .               or body of discharging the duties  of his office,                  and that the infirmity is likely to be permanent,                  or  unless he has served fifteen  years  as  a                  registrar and has  attained the age of  sixty-five                  years:              (d)  A registrar shall, for the purposes of the Super-                  annuation Acts, be  deemed  to have served in                  the permanent civil  service  of the State  not-                  withstanding that he has not been admitted to                -  office with a certificate  from the Civil Service 40                  Commissioners.35
[14 GEO. 5.]County Courts,5(3)  This section shall apply to  any registrar A.D.1924.(a) who  is  a  whole-time  registrar within  themeaning of this Act;  or(b) to  whom a salary has  been assigned under    section forty-five of the principal Act and who    gives notice in the prescribed form and within    the prescribed period of his desire  to accept    the provisions of this Act relating  to retire-    ment and pensions: 10     Provided that if a registrar who was, immediately    before his appointment as registrar, an assistant registrar    gives nptice in the prescribed form and within the pre-    scribed period of his desire to continue subject to the    provisions  of this Act  relating to the retirement and 15 pensions of persons in court service, he  shall for the    purposes of retirement  and pension  be deemed not to    be a registrar to whom  this section applies, but to be a    person employed in court  service.        (4)  For  the purposes  of ^subsection  (2)  of  this 20 section the period of service  shall be reckoned, in the    case of a whole-time registrar, as from the date on which    he becomes a whole-time  registrar, and, in the case of    any other  registrar to  whom  this section  applies, as   from the date on which  the  order, by virtue  of  which 25 the salary was assigned,  came into operation.&apos;        (5)  The provisions  of this  section  shall  apply to   the registrars of  the district registries of the High Court   at Liverpool and Manchester as they  apply to registrars   &quot;6f  county courts, but in  the  case of any such district 30 registrar who holds office  at the commencement of this   Act only if he gives notice in the prescribed form and   within the prescribed period of his desire  to accept the   provisions of this section.        5.-(1) Subject  to  the  provisions  of  this section Court ser-35 employment in court service  shall, in the  case of any vice to be   person as respects whom  a  direction in that behalf is PCJnsionabl   given by the Lord Chancellor with the  concurrence of   the Treasury, and &apos;&apos; hether the employment commenced   before or after the commencement of this Act, be deemed40 to be for all purposes employment  in  the civil service of   the State,  and if  a certificate has been issued to him   by  the  Civil  Service Commissioners, allowances  may be12A  4
 AD 1924 &apos; granted  in his case accordingly under the Superannua-  &apos;  -  &apos;  tion Acts:               Provided that except in so far as the Treasury may          in any case  direct, no account  shall be taken for the          purposes of this section  of court service before the issue  5          of the certificate.            &apos;   &quot;,               (2)  Employment in court service  shall, in relation          to a person  in whose case a direction has been  given          under this section, be deemed  to be employment in a          public department within the meaning of section four of  1050&amp;51 Viet, the  Superannuation Act,  1887,  as amended by-sectionc 67,      three of  the Superannuation Act, 1914.4&amp;5Geo. 5.c. 86.           (3) In the case of  a  person  employed  in  court          service who  was  appointed  to his office before  the          commencement of  this Act, any-salary  or remuneration  15          received  by him from any source whatsoever in&apos; respect          of that office  during any period of  which account may          be taken for  the  purpose of this section shall, for the          purpose  of authorising the  grant of an allowance or a          gratuity  under this section, be deemed to have been paid  20          out of moneys provided by Parliament.               (4) Where any person  who was employed at the          commencement of this Act in court service and in whose          case a direction has been given under this section is in          consequence of the provisions of this  section required, by  25          reason only of. his having attained any age, to retire from          court service, the Treasury may, if he has been required          to devote his whole time to employment in court service          and if he had  attained the age of fifty-five  years  on or          before&apos; the twelfth day  of May, nineteen hundred  and  30          tWenty-three, grant to him by way of compensation such          gratuity, not exceeding twice the amount of the salary          and  emoluments received by him from whatsoever source          during his last year  of  employment,  as may seem to        ;., them just.                                             35               The decision of the Treasury on any question  which    &apos;;     arises as to  the  application of  this subsection to  any          person or as to the amount of any gratuity thereunder          shall be  final.               (5)  The provisions of this section  shall have effect  40          notwithstanding anything in any contract made between          a registrar, a high bailiff, or a district registrar and any          other person.               II                .   &quot;  &quot;                 &apos;  &apos;   .
       6. (1) The  Lord Chancellor may, with the con-  A.D. 1924.   currence of the Treasury, remit any fee to be paid on     -    any  proceedings in a court under the Workmen&apos;s Com- Fee!?    ,   pensation Acts, 1906 to 1923, either in whole or in part, ^T^J 5 on an application in that behalf made  in the prescribed tion pro-   manner by the person by whom the fee is payable.       eeedings.       (2) Where in any case a workman  who has applied   for  arbitration  under  the  Workmen&apos;s Compensation   Acts,  1906 to  1923, satisfies the registrar that there  are10 prima,  facie grounds for  arbitration, and  that if  he is   required to pay fees he will or may be prevented from  .   taking proceedings or  will  suffer undue hardship,  the   registrar may allow the payment  of  all or any of  the   fees  to  be  postponed  until the  conclusion  of   tbe15 proceedings.       (3) Paragraph (9) of  the Second  Schedule to  the   workmen&apos;s Compensation Act, 1906, shall be amended (* Edw. 7   so as to enable a  fee to  be charged  on   recording a c. 58.   memorandum under  that paragraph.20     (4) Paragraph (13)  of the Second  Schedule to  the   Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act, 1906,   (which  provides   that no court  fee,  other  than in respect of medical   examination, shall be payable in respect of proceedings   in a court under that Act prior to the award) shall cease25 to have effect.       7.-(1) Section fifty-nine of the principal Act (which Amendment   relates to ejectment actions) shall have effect as if  for of s. 59 of   the words  &quot; one month from  the day  of service of  the Principal   summons&quot;  there  were  substituted the words &quot; such  c &apos;30 time as may be prescribed by rules of  court,&quot; and as if   the following subsection were added thereto               &quot; (2)  The rules of&apos;court prescribing the pro-         cedure under this section may make  provision  for         authorising  any  proceedings which have  been35       brought under section  one hundred and thirty-         eight or one hundred and thirty-nine of this Act,         but  which ought to have been brought under.this         section, to be amended and to be continued under         this section,  and for  the procedure on  any  such40       amendment.&quot;       (2) This section shall  come into operation on the   first day of October, nineteen hundred and  twenty-four.
 A.D. 1924.      8. (1) Section four of  the  principal Act (which        provides for the  alteration of county  court districts)^&quot;d.    shall be amended as follows : ments of        (a) The powers under that section shall be exercisedprincipal            by order  of the Lord Chancellor instead of  by 5Aot--   -             His Majesty by Order in Council:               (&amp;) Where an order  is  made under that  section  for                   the discontinuance of the holding of any court                   there  shall be power to  make provision in the                   order  with respect to proceedings which may 10                   have been commenced in  that court:               (c) Any order made under  that  section  may  be                   varied or  revoked  by  a  subsequent order                   thereunder.               (2) There shall be payable to brokers and appraisers 15          in  respect  of  the matters mentioned  in  section  one          hundred and  fifty-four  of  the  principal  Act  (which          regulates the  sale of goods taken  in  execution)  out          of the produce of goods distrained  or  sold  such fees          as may with the consent  of the Treasury be  prescribed 20          instead of the poundage mentioned in that section,               (3) The power to make orders as  to fees under          section  one hundred  and  sixty-five of  the  principal          Act (which  relates to  orders as  to   fees)  shall  be          exercisable  by  the Lord Chancellor with  the concur- 25          rence of the Treasury instead of by the Treasury with          the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor, and the following          sections of  the  principal Act, that  is to say                    Section one   hundred  and  sixty-nine  (which                relates to accounts of fees and fines);              30                   Section one hundred and  seventy (which relates                to the accounts to be furnished to the Comptroller                and  Auditor-General);                   Section one hundred and seventy-one  (which                relates to the audit of the accounts of registrars);  35                   Section one hundred and seventy-two  (which                provides that the Treasury shall  make rules for                securing balances of money in the hands of the                officers of every court);                   Section one hundred and eighty-three  (which 40                provides for the keeping of  a registry of judg-                ments);          shall have  effect  as  if  &quot; the Lord  Chancellor&quot; were          therein substituted for  &quot; the Treasury.&quot;
        (4) Section one hundred and eighty of the principal  A.D. 1924.    Act (which requires all  summonses and other  process          issuing out of a county court to be under the seal of the    court) shall  have effect  as though for the  words &quot; all 5  &quot; summonses and other process issuing out  of the said    &quot; court&quot;  there  were   substituted  the words  &quot;all    &quot; summonses issuing out of the said court, and all such    &quot; other  documents  so issuing as may be  prescribed,&quot;    and as though for the words &quot; other process purporting &quot; 10  there were substituted the words &quot; such other documents    purporting.&quot;       , 9. All salaries  allowances and other sums  payable Expenses.    under  this Act  shall be paid out  of moneys  provided by    Parliament. 15      10. (1) This  Act may be  cited as  the  County short title,    Courts Act, 1924, and shall, except in so far as it amends interpreta-    the  Workmen&apos;s Compensation  Acts, 1906 to  1923,  be hon, extent    construed  as  one with the County Courts Acts,  1888 to and rePeal-    1919, and this Act and the last-mentioned Acts  may be 20  cited together as the County  Courts  Acts, 1888 to 1924.        (2) In  this Act,  unless  the  context otherwise    requires, the  following expressions have meanings hereby    assigned to them respectively, that is to say.:--        &quot; Court &quot; means county court: 25      &quot; Court  service &quot; means  employment as  an assistant            registrar, or as a clerk, bailiff, usher or messenger            in the service of a  court, or employment as  a            clerk in the  service of a district registry of the            High Court, and includes employment  in those 30          capacities simultanously:        &quot; Registrar &quot; means registrar of  a court:        &quot; The principal Act &quot; means the County  Courts Act, 51 &amp; 52 Viet.            1888:                           &apos;             c- 43.        &quot; Solicitor &quot; means solicitor of the Supreme Court: 35      &quot;Prescribed&quot; means prescribed by order made by            the Lord Chancellor.        (3) This  Act extends only to England.        (4) The enactments set out in the  Second Schedule    to this Act are  hereby repealed to the extent specified40  in the third column  of that Schedule.
A.D. 1924.                   SCHEDULES.Section 4                     FIRST SCHEDULE. SCALE OF REGISTRARS&apos;  SUPERANTJATION ALLOWANCES.  .  1. An annual allowance not exceeding one-ninth of the lastannual salary  may be granted after the completion of a period 5 &apos;of service of five years.    2. Where  the period of service, completed exceeds five years,there may be  granted an annual  allowance not exceeding one-ninth of the last annual salary with an addition of one-thirty-sixth of that  salary for each completed year&apos;s service in excess 10of five.    3. The maximum allowance shall be  two-thirds of the lastannual salary.Section ii,                  SECOND  SCHEDULE.ENACTMENTS  REPEALED.                 15Session and Chapter.	Short Title.	Extent, of Repeal.31 &amp; 32 Viet. c. 71, 46 &amp; 47 Viet. o. 52. 51 &amp; 52 Viet, c. 43.	The - County Courts Adrhi-ralty Jurisdic-tion Act, 1868. The Bankruptcy Act, 1883. The County Courts Act, 1888.	Section seventeen. 20 Subsection (14) of section one hun-dred and twenty-two. Sections twenty-five, twenty-nine, and thirty in section thirty-one 25 the words from &quot; Provided that&quot; to the end of the section, in section thirty-three the words &quot; whom the judge shall be &quot; em-&quot; powered to appoint and&quot; and 30 the words from &quot;provided that&quot; to the words &quot;dismissed by the judge,&quot; in section thirty-four the words &quot;by the successor of the &quot; high bailiff or by the judge &quot; and 35 the words from &quot; and such wages &quot; to the end of the section, sections
Session and Chapter.	Short Title.	Extent of Repeal.51 &amp; 52 Viet. e. 43 cont. 5 3 Edw. 7. o. 42. 10 6 Edw. 7. c. 58. 15 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. e. 73.	The County Courts Act, 1903. The Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act, 1906. The County Courts Act, 1919.	thirty-six, thirty-seven, thirty-eight and forty-four to forty-seven, and in section one hundred and fifty-four the words from&quot; and the brokers &quot; to the end of the section. Section six. In paragraph (9) of the Second Schedule tho words &quot;without fee &quot; and paragraph (13) of that Schedule. Section fifteen from the beginning to the words &quot; court and &quot;.A.D. 1924.ii

County  Courts.             DRAFT               OF A         BILLTo  amend the law relating  to Officers  of County Courts in England and of  District Registries of the High Court  in&quot; England  and to make further  provision with respect to such County  Courts  and proceedings therein, and  for purposes incidental thereto.III. (3).1th February 1924.12-3

</content>
</cab>
