<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/164/0 images: 1124-1125</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
\miB DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRIT/JftilC MAJESTY &apos;3 QOVbRHMlsHT],SECRET.CP. 99. (24).                                 Copy No. _^___                        C A B I N E T.  :                 W.AR  CHARGES (VALIDITY).  BILL.                      Milk Licence charges.           Memorandum by the Minister of. Agriculture and Fisheries *            The draft of the War- Charges (Validity) Bill, which has  been circulated by the President of the Board of Trade, proposes to  legalise  the levy of 2d. a gallon in respect of milk purchased in the  four South-Western Counties which was declared illegal by the House  of Lords  in the case of the Attorney General against tho &quot;Wilts  United Dairies.            In the Bill as introduced by the late Government the milk  charges were not&quot;included, and the late Minister of Agriculture  definitely announced in the House on two occasions that the Government  had decided that Parliament would not be asked to reverse  the definite  decision  of the House of Lords.           . Oh the strength of this assurance milk producers in the  four counties  have expected, to recover from the milk distributing  companies 2d,  a gallon in respect of the milk sold during  the operation  of the charge,  and it is believed that every member of Parliament  and  every candidate in those counties has pledged himself to  support the  farmers&apos;  claims.            If the Bill is introduced in its present form,  with tho  inclusion of the. milk charges, it will constitute a distinct  reversal  of the decision of the late Government and will be bitterly resented     *  by the farmers.  It is true that  they have no legal claim  against  the distributing companies, but the National Farmers1  Union believe that  they cab  put sufficient pressure  on the  companies to  obtain repayment;  end the V/ilts  United Dairies,  the largest  company concerned,  indicated                                1.
some time ago that.if they were successful in contestingthe legality of the charge they would, return to the farmersthe siuas levied,                               ;;          I feel hound, therefore, in the interests of the farmers to press for the exclusion of the milk charges from the Bill,  I think It is doubtful if the inclusionof the charges could be carried in the House of Commons,and in any case I feel that at this stage it would be unwise to antagonise the farmers by reversing the decisionof the late Government on a matter to which the farmersattach importance but which is not material from the pointof view of the Exchequer,                                  N.B.MINISTRY OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES,             11th February 1924*

</content>
</cab>
