<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/205/0 images: 246-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   Jidy 1929.SECRET. . Copy No.    38CP. 228* (29).CABINET.SIR SAMUEL WILSON&apos;S REPORT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I HAVE already circulated to the Cabinet Sir S. Wilson&apos;s Report on his. recent visit to East Africa, together with a Strictly Confidential Memorandum* by him in which he emphasises certain points in the Report. In placing his recommendations before the Cabinet, I feel that I ought to add a few observations on that portion of them which is likely, in my opinion, to be more provocative of public controversy than the rest, namely, the recommendations regarding the reconstitution of the Kenya Legislative Council and the grant of an unofficial majority on that Council.These words, &quot;unofficial majority,&quot; are apt to cause alarm to many public bodies and individuals to whom they connote little, if anything, less than &quot; responsible government.&quot; The difference between the two need hardly be stressed. Unofficial majorities are a well-known and well-established feature of Colonial legislatures. There are at present twentj&apos; official members of the Kenya Legislative Council, and there are obvious practical advantages to be derived from the abandonment of a system under which so many important officials are obliged to waste a considerable portion of their time sitting in the Council merely in order that they may be able to record their votes when required. Apart from this, it may, with some fairness, be said that the grant of an unofficial majority in Kenya is not likely, in the event, to make a very great difference.In the first place, it is generally admitted that for the past few years the government of Kenya has to a large extent been carried on as a &quot; government by agreement.&quot; A very large proportion of the work of the Council has been performed by Select Committees, and on these Committees unofficial members have frequently been in a majority. Again, I am of the opinion that Sir S. Wilson has secured an important concession from the elected members in inducing them to agree that the nomination of the members to represent general, including native, interests should, under his proposed Scheme, be left entirely to the discretion of the Governor, who will thus be able to ensure that men of broad-minded views are selected for this purpose. If the Scheme is adopted, I propose that an instruction should be issued to the Governor to ensure that the members nominated to represent general, including native, interests, should not represent an accretion to the settler element in the Council, but should be drawn from such classes as lawyers, missionaries, business men,-retired officials, &amp;c, and that there should be no distinction of race. It will be quite open to the Governor to nominate one or more Indians for this purpose, if suitable individuals can be found.Furthermore, it has been agreed that either the High Commissioner or the Governor of Kenya should be given powers of veto and of certification; and the Secretary of State for the Colonies will, of course, retain his present right of signifying His Majesty&apos;s disallowance of any Ordinance. It will be seen, therefore, that, in spite of the grant of an unofficial majority, the risk of any objectionable legislation passing into law would, by virtue of the safeguards provided, be practically negligible.Apart from the question of the Kenya Legislative Council, Sir S. Wilson&apos;s Scheme is non-political in character, being concerned mainly with the co-ordinationCP. 202 (29).[19643]
of the essential economic services. For this reason it cannot, I think, be fairly compared with the work of such a body as the Simon Commission, with its deep political implications. I would therefore suggest that it is not necessary to submit the matter to a Joint Committee of both Houses, as has been strongly urged-iii certain quarters. It would be necessary, if the Scheme is approved by the Cabinet, to give facilities for debate, but, subject to that, steps might be taken at once, to put it into effect. The actual arrangements for setting up the requisite machinery will of necessity take a considerable time : and it has been very strongly represented to me that public opinion in East Africa is specially liable to sudden changes, and that if any undue delay takes place in giving effect to the Scheme, the present atmosphere of general agreement, which is as exceptional as it is auspicious, may very quickly be dissipated.Objections to the Scheme are to be anticipated from the Government of India. But if that Government is to be consulted, it might be difficult to resist a request that consideration should also be given to the views of the Government of the Union of South Africa, whose interests are closely linked up with those of East Africa. Indeed, I understand that it was several times suggested to Sir S. Wilson in East Africa that the Union Government should be consulted before any action whatsoever was taken in East Africa. In the circumstances I would urge that any protest from the Government of India should not be allowed to prevail if the Cabinet agrees with me that Sir S. Wilson&apos;s Scheme is, on its own merits, both practicable and desirable.P.Colonial Office, July 22, 1929.

</content>
</cab>
