<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/13/26 images: 426-437</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. 2 0 8It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.MOST SECRET. COPY NO.   \kW.M.   (40) 148th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 3.Confidential Annex.(30th May, 1940.)PRANCE.communications from theFrench Govern-ment.Report from8wayne Mission.Report byGeneral Spears.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR informed the War Cabinet of a telegram which had beenreceived from the Swayne Mission stating that two british Officers had been sent to carry out a reconnaissance of the Oise Canal.     Their reportrevealed an unsatisfactory position as regards theFrench preparations,  the general impression being that the enemy would have no difficulty in breakingthrough at any point.     The matter had been broughtto the notice of General Georges, who had explainedthat the French Division carrying out this work wasa poor one.     A further inspection would be carriedout by British Officers.THE PRIME MINISTER read a report which hehad received from General Spears on the conditionof the French Army South of Amiens0     The -french troops here had been fighting hard for eight days and were very hard pressed.      The French blacktroops had proved unsatisfactory.     General Weygandhad given the odds as three to one against the French.Time had never been so precious, and he (general weygand) had begged that the British should sendevery possible soldier to the Somme.     One british division would make all the difference.     GeneralSpears had pointed out that this was quite impossible,but General Weygand had again repeated his fear ofthe certainty of an onslaught on the French Army,concluding with the words &quot;Nous sommes a la limite&quot;.Later in the meeting a further long messag(from General Spears was read.Discussxon followed as to the policy to beadopted in regard to the requests for further assistance which were being received from the FrenchGovernment.THE PRIME MINISTER drew the attention ofthe War Cabinet to the requests which were being received from the French for further Divisions tohelp on the Somme Front, for R.A.F. assistance, forco-operation in appeals to President Roosevelt andfor concessions to Italy, and said that he could notresist the conclusion that, when we refused theserequests, as we must, the French would use theserefusals as an excuse for giving up the struggle.In his own view , it would be quiteunreasonable to denude the essential defences of thiscountry to send such small fully trained and equippedforces as were available to fight on the Somme front,where they could not possibly make any appreciableeffect in relation to the large German forces which would be shortly available for pressing- 1 -

^hiuond Terrace, S.W.1.an attack.     When we were ahle to organise andre-equip the men now being withdrawn from Prance;when the regular battalions now being withdrawnfrom overseas had arrived;    when further Dominionforces had reached this country;    then indeed weshould not need all our available forces for homedefence.     We should therefore certainly tell theFrench that, if they could hold out in the meantime,we should send them help as soon as we were able todo so, but we should make it quite clear that we hadno forces that we could send at the present moment.He suggested that he and the Lord Privy Seal,accompanied by the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff,  should go to Paris the next day to explain theposition to the French on these lines.     The meeting should be treated as a meeting of the Supreme WarCouncil.There was general agreement with this view,the following being the principal points made in thecourse of discussion.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that three Divisions would in the ordinary way have been due to go to France during June, the canadian division;    the 18th and 52nd Divisions;    the restof the troops in England would not be ready for somemonths to come.     The Canadian Division was ready togo at once, but it would be running a serious risk to send it out of the country.      On the other hand,it was essential to do what we could to improve theFrench morale, and it was from this point of viewvery important to assure the French that we meant tohelp them as soon as we could, if they could onlyhold out.THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said thatit would be useless from every point of view to send to France troops that were only partially trained orequipped, but every day that the French could be induced to hold out would be of value to us, and weshould therefore do all that we could to give theFrench hope and encouragement.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRSurged that from this point of view,it was mostimportant to bring out that our decision not to send troops immediately was dictated only by the fact thatno troops were available.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY suggestedthat the French should be encouraged to continue thestruggle by quoting to them all the evidence from various sources showing that, owing to economic difficulties Germany could not continue the strugglemuch longer, if only she could be prevented fromsecuring an immediate success.The War Cabinet:-Gave general approval to the line whichthe Prime Minister proposed to take inhis discussion with the French Government,as indicated above.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY-S government most SECRET.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO,W. M. (40) 148th C^N^USJONg^J^yTE,^.Confidential Annex.(30th May,  1940).i NORWAY,(Question of&quot;Informing theNorwegianGovernmentIf withdrawalof our forces.The War Cabinet had before them aMemorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs regarding the communication to the norwegian government of the decision to evacuate allied forces from North Norway (WoP0(40) 181).THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS,said that in his memorandum he had reached thefollowing conclusions.(a) That we should adhere to the decisionto withdraw from North Norway.(b) That we should offer to bring off as many Norwegian troops as might wishto leave, as well as the King and government.(c) That we should discharge our moral obligation to the Norwegians by giving notice to them in advance of our intentions, so as to free ourselvesfrom the charge which had been levelledagainst King Leopold.There was,  in addition,  the practical point that in order to maintain our control overNorwegian shipping we should avoid,  so far aspossible,    alienating the sympathy of the Norwegiancrews.He emphasised that it was not intended to mention any date to the Norwegian Government soas to avoid any risk of news of our intendedoperations leaking out:    at the same time,  ifmovements of troops between Narvik and Bodo took,place, the Norwegians might well,guess what wasafoot.    It was understood that &quot;the date contemplatedfor the start of the operation was the 2nd June,? whentroops would begin to leave s. and that it would be com-pleted by the 7th June.He had presumed that there was no questionof reconsidering the decision to carry out totalevacuation, and he had the^fore rejected thesuggestion that a token Allied Force might be leftat Narvik in order to prevent the Norwegians fromcollapsing altogether and making terms with theenemy;. partial evacuation would, however, subjectus to the strain   of continuing to maintain a force from which&apos;complete withdrawal was designed to relieve us.

In the discussion which followed,the followingpoints were made in favour of reconsidering thedecision to withdraw:-(i)    The effect of a withdrawal would he aserious blow to our prestige.    TheGeneral in command of the French troops had already expressed his determination to remain, although he had since been told to carry out the orders of theBritish Commander.(ii)    Narvik was now in our hands and theenemy forces which we could &quot;contain&quot;by continued resistance would be greaterthan the forces which we could use against them if we withdraw.(iii)    The effect of the withdrawal on ourmerchant shipping position would be veryserious;    all Norwegian ships in neutral ports would be at risk and we might lose the services of some 70% of Norwegiantanker tonnage and 50% of the otherNorwegian merchant tonnage.    (Thesepercentages represent the proportion of norwegian tonnage not in Allied ports.)(iv)    If Italy were to enter the war against us and we were eventually forced to fightGermany alone,  we should alienate theopinion of the remaining neutrals by ourdesertion of Norway.The principal points urged in favour of withdrawl were the following:-(i)    The Chiefs of Staff were clear that, fromthe military point of view, the whole force at Narvik ought to be evacuated.      If partof the force was left, it would be necessaryto leave with it at least a proportion ofthe anti-aircraft guns now in the Narvikarea.      It was true that the Hurricaneaircraft now disembarked in this area couldnot be removed.      But even if only a tokenforce was left, there would be demands thatthe air force should be replenished,  and the drain on our resources would continue.Moreover, recent Naval losses made it of vital importance to free for other employment the Destroyer Flotilla now employed on convoy work to Narvik.(ii)    The Norwegian Government must realise thattheir only chance of regaining the inde-pendence of their country was to continue as Allies of this country;    and that inpresent circumstances the defence of theBritish Isles was of paramount importance,not only to us but to themselves.

The civilian population of North Norway-would he relieved of persistent air attacksif the troops were withdrawn;    such of theNorwegian forces as remained could continueguerrilla warfare in the difficult countryaround Narvik.The risk of the loss of the NorwegianMercantile Fleet., including tanker tonnagewas not so great as had been represented,since we could seize any Norwegian merchant ships in our own ports and could controlthose in neutral ports by charteringarrangements.     Any reluctance the crewsmight display to take service with usmight be overcome by the incentive to earn a livelihood, which would otherwisedisappear, since the Germans could not use the Norwegian tanker tonnage, even if itwere not available for our use.It was pointed out that the French Governmenthad not yet been informed of the decision to evacuateNarvik and that, before the Norwegian Government couldbe notified of our intentions, it would be necessary to.secure   at least the acquiescence of the French in theproposal.      It would also be desirable to keep LordGork informed of the position.The War Cabinet agreed:-(a) To invite the Prime Minister toinform M. Reynaud the following day that it had been decided towithdraw the Allied   froces from northern Norway, and to securehis agreement tfl this course.(b) To invite the Foreign Secretary toprepare a draft telegram to Sir C.Dormer, instructing him to speak tothe King of Norway and the norweigen minister of Defence on the lines proposed in paragraph 5 of his memorandum on the understanding:(i) That the instructions would notbe despatched until the PrimeMinister had secured the agree-ment of the French Government.(ii) That the offer to bring away theKing of Norway and his ministers should be framed in persuasiveterms, and should make it clearthat the King would be warmly welcomed in this country.(c) To invite the First Lord of theAdmiralty when action had been taken under (a) and ( b)   to; inform LordGork ? ccordingly.Richmond Terrace, S..W. 1.(iv)




</content>
</cab>
