<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/63/17 images: 232-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;document IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTI7th^clvsionsCOPY NO75CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 4 MAY 1978at 10. 30 am present the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp prime Minister^Rt Hon Michael Foot MPlrd President of the Councilto^ Rt Hon Denis Healey MPncellor of the ExchequerIj^Rt Kon David Owen MP/^etary of State for Foreign and&quot;Oftimonwealth affairs^Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn MPlfcf etary of State for Energy  Rt Hon Peter Shore MP&apos;-c*etary of State for the Environment*Rt Hon Bruce MiUan MP*etary of State for Scotland.&apos;5eRt Hon Fred Mulley MPWtary of State for Defencejj* Rt Hon David Ennals MP^fetary of State for Social ServicesRt Hon Lord Peart*d Privy seal the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for the Home department the Rt Hon Shirley WiPiams mp secretary of State for Education and science and Paymaster GeneralThe Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Albert Booth mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Edmund Dell mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Joel Barnett mp chief Secretary, Treasury4SECRET
J* &amp;t Hon John Silkin MP The Rt Hon Roy Hattersley MP8ter of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food     Secretary of State for Prices and consumer Protectionj^^t Hon William Rodgers MP The Rt Hon Stanley Orme MPtetary of State for Transport Minister for Social security the Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the FOLLOWING WERE ALSO present :-^*t Hon Samuel Silkin QC MP The Rt Hon Michael Cocks MPtGey General (Item 3) Parliamentary Secretary, TreasurySECRETARIATSii John hunt mr W I Mclndoe (Item 1)Sir Clive Rose (Item 2)Mr M D M Franklin (Item 2)Mr P Le Cheminant (Items Z and 4)Mr P Mountfield (Item 3)Mr D E R Faulkner (Item 1)Mr C H Wilson (Item 4)contents subject PagePARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS foreign affairs rhodesia 1Relations with China and the Soviet Union pay OF DOCTORS AND DENTISTS AND UNIVERSITY TEACHERS draft WHITE PAPER ON INDUSTRIAL DEMOCRACY 7
^MENTARY   1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons during the following week.    It was hoped to propose that the adjournment for the Spring Bank Holiday would bre from Friday 26 May until Tuesday 6 June.JTJGN 2. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that&quot;-S in the debate that was to take place in the House of Commons that day he expected to be pressed by the Opposition for some indications of&quot;s*a movement towards recognition of the internal settlement and the liftingof sanctions.    In his view we should not at this stage contemplateii0Us recognition or taking any steps leading to the removal of sanctions: to^7fi\nCe: do either would involve not only a break in our close co-operation with;cl &apos; 16th the United States, but would also bring us into conflict with most other8ion8, members of the United Nations.    Even the South African government would probably prefer us to continue on our present course, though they could not admit this publicly.    This view was also held by many people in Rhodesia and had been expressed to us recently by aRhodesian Service officer.    The stage had not been reached where itwas possible to have any confidence in the future of the internalsettlement.    If it were to succeed this would only be as a result ofMr Smith being held to every detail of what he had undertaken. Thiswould require pressure to be maintained not only by his Nationalistpartners but also by continued efforts on our part.    Internally much would depend on the reactions of the guerrillas in the Tribal TrustLands.    It would be wrong to judge opinion in Rhodesia by reports onthe situation in Salisbury as the Press tended to do.    This was a mistake the Conservatives had made in 1971-72 when they had failed to remember the 5 million Rhodesians in the Tribal Trust Lands. Hisimmediate aim was to continue, with the United States, efforts to get adialogue going between the Patriotic Front and the Salisbury Four.This could best be pursued by private negotiations and he proposed to station a Foreign and Commonwealth Office official in Southern africa to work on this jointly with an American representative.    We shouldalso keep in touch with the Front Line Presidents.    It was clear that neither President Kaunda of Zambia nor President Machel ofMozambique wanted Cuban involvement, but if no progress were made this must be regarded as a serious possibility.    This was howeverunlikely to happen so long as we maintained our efforts to achieve a negotiated settlement.The Cabinet -Took note.1
. ^ns The Cabinet&apos;s discussion is recorded separately.Ltunathe&apos;-t3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Prices and Consumer Protection (CP(78) 50) recordingdiscussions in the Ministerial Committee on Economic Strategy Sub-Committee on Pay Negotiations (EY(P)) about the recommendations ofthe Doctors&apos; and dentists Review Body (DDRB) and about the pay of university teachers.    The Cabinet also had before them the report ofthe DDRB (CP(78) 47), a minute dated 2 May from the Secretary ofState for Prices and Consumer Protection to the Prime Ministerrecording an EY(P) discussion on the persionability of deferred payawards, and a letter of 2 May 1978 from the Secretary of State for education and Science to the Secretary of State for Prices and consumer Protection about the pay of university teachers.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR PRICES AND consumer protection said that EY(P) had agreed unanimously, subject to onereservation, that the recommendations of the DDRB concerning the 1978pay settlement should be met in full.    These involved an overallincrease of 10 per cent in pay, divided unequally between differentgrades in the medical profession.    The reservation concerned thequestion of increments forgone during stages 1 and 2 of pay policy. Alarge majority of EY(P) favoured an early announcement of the 10 percent decision.    The Sub-Committee disagreed on the question of a forward commitment to implement the full pay scales recommended bythe DDRB.    Some felt that no such commitment should be given.Others wished consideration deferred until the report of the top salaries Review Body (TSRB) were available.    If an early announce-ment were needed, a majority thought that the forward commitmentshould extend over three years, which would distinguish the doctorsfrom armed forces, firemen and, probably, the police; othersfavoured the two-year period recommended by the DDRB.    On thequestion of increments, the tentative view was that the missingincrements should be restored, and the costs subtracted from the costof the following year&apos;s pay settlement, but a majority of the Sub-Committee would prefer to postpone a decision on this point, and thusan announcement of the overall settlement, for one week, pendingconclusion of a review by officials of the whole question of paymentafter 1 August 1977 of previously withheld increments.    The separatequestion of pension rates concerned other groups, including the armed forces, as well as doctors and dentists.    The issue was whether to base pensions upon the full rates recommended by the Review Bodies
but not yet in payment, or whether to relate pensions solely to actualrates of pay.    A majority of EY(P) favoured the notional calculation,particularly in view of the precedents already created including thespecial pensions provisions for Members of Parliament.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES said that these were difficult issues.    The Cabinet should not underestimate the strong feelings within the medical profession, despite the lack so far of anyorchestrated publicity campaign.    The profession felt that they had done badly in the past, and the DDRB calculation that it had fallen28 per cent behind other employment confirmed this.    The doctorswere however a relatively well-paid group.    It was necessary to make an early announcement at least of the 10 per cent award for 1978. Itwould be much easier to persuade the profession to accept this if itwere accompanied by a clear statement about the forward commitmentrecommended by the DDRB.    Tc postpone this would almost certainly lead to conflict with the junior hospital doctors, who could be expectedto have the support of the consultants unless there were a clear indication of the Government&apos;s longer-term intentions.    Such action would have serious consequences for the Health Service.    The ReviewBodies themselves saw their recommendations as a single package,and might resign if it were not implemented in full.    The cabinet would in his view be forced to accept it eventually, and it would be preferable to do so right away and not be forced to concede later underthreat.    There were attractions in phasing out the anomaly over threeyears, but this would mean an artificial attempt to distinguish doctors and dentists from the armed forces, when the two Review Bodiesoperated under similar terms of reference and from the same evidence.In discussion it was first argued that the doctors should be given a choice of a flat 10 per cent increase for all grades, or an overall10 per cent increase   divided as proposed by the Review Body.Against this it was pointed out that the &quot;kitty principle&quot; waspermissible under the existing pay guidelines and had been widelyapplied.     There was in any case no chance of securing agreementwithin the profession and it was preferable to accept the Review Bodyrecommendations on distribution as they stood.In favour of a firm forward commitment to phase out the remainder ofthe anomaly, it was argued that the Government could rest upon the firm advice of an independent review body.    Indeed, were it notprepared to do so it should have abolished the Review Bodies at thebeginning of the present pay policy.    Having failed to do so, it was not easy for the Government to override or ignore their recommendations.Most unions could be expected to accept that the awards resulted froman independent assessment akin to arbitration and would not seek to exploit the position.    The DDRB recommendations implied a catchingup by the medical profession with other comparable groups whose pay
had moved ahead faster.    It did not mean that the doctors would maintain their living standards when all other sections of thecommunity had suffered a fall.    The risk cf repercussions had alreadybeen acknowledged when the Government gave forward commitments tothe Fire Service and to the armed forces.    The Cabinet should recognise the real industrial power of the profession, particularly ofthe junior hospital doctors, who would unscrupulously exploit public sympathy as they had done in the past.    Such an approach was not likely to damage the prospects of agreement with the unions on paypolicy this summer:  their tacit acquiescence in Government policy wasin any case the most which could be hoped for.    It would be important to make a start on eliminating other anomalies during the next payround.    Indeed this was a strong argument for a lower level of basicincreases to offset the cost of dealing with anomalies. Fortunately,the reduced rate of price inflation made it reasonable to hope formoderation in pay claims in tne next round.    This would allow a more flexible policy to operate than had been possible in the present stage.The politically sensitive cases of top salaries and of Members ofParliament could oe dealt with on their merits as they arose though theproblems here were emotional rather than real.    The problem of the pay of the non-industrial Civil Service as a whole could well pressntmuch greater difficulties particularly as the Cabinet had already agreed to the restoration of pay research from Apiil 1979.    It would be politically very difficult to xefuse to implement the findings of the pay research Unit when these were available.    However, in the process ofdealing with anomalies, there was a good case for amalgamating the pay research machinery and the Review Bodies, to avoid a leapfrogsituation developing, though this might well not be possible before aGeneral Election had taken place.Against forward commitments, it was argued that it would be dangerous to extend these beyond the existing &quot;law and order&quot; group of the armed forces, police and firemen.    It was important to preserve the specialstatus of the armed forces.    During the present phase of pay policy,Ministers had been very careful, with these exceptions, to resist the concept of indexation or any automatic restoration of relativities. Tocreate further favoured groups now would imply the prospect of similar treatment for top salaries and Members of Parliament and indeed the thrust of the Cabinet&apos;s discussion might well point to theneed for early action on the latter group.    Moreover the Cabinet hadalready recognised that there were 200-300 groups who might claim that they were entitled to special treatment.    It was particularly difficult to give favourable treatment to the relatively well-paidmedical profession, when the low-paid groups had been rigorouslytreated early in the present pay round.    The findings of the review body were themselves suspect, and it was not clear that doctors had fallen as far behind as 28 per cent.    The DDRB recommendationsmeant that the doctors would receive 9 per cent in 1979 and in 1980, on top of the going rate for that year.    This could have damaging
consequences.    It also meant restoring previous fixed relativities.To do this would determine the shape of the pay policy for the ne-tt twoor three years, without any proper consultation with the trade unions.It would damage the prospects of an agreement with the unions in Julymany of whom could find plausible reasons for seeking to restore therelativities which obtained in some particularly favourable past year.The unions as a whole could not be expected to acquiesce in a policy ofgeneral restraint if some groups were specially protected and therewas, of course, already growing pressure within the trade union movement for the restoration of relativities lost in the first phases of incomes policy.    Even in the public sector, nurses and schoolteacherswould seek to follow the precedents established for other relatedprofessions.    This would create enormous strain in the rest of localgovernment service, which was relatively poorly paid.    There wereprecedents for overriding the recommendations of Review Bodies, and cabinet need not be frightened of doing so in this cace.As to the period over which the anomalies should be phased out, it was argued that it was difficult to distinguish doctors from other groups.The junior doctors would certainly threaten industrial action if theywere offered three-year phasing.    And the university teachers wouldrequire similar treatment if industrial action by them was to be avoided.    This need not create a precedent for the TSRB;  the groups which it covered had often been treated differently from the rest.There was no merit, therefore, in waiting for the report of the TSRB,which might well be delayed until mid-June.In discussion of university teachers it was argued that they had alreadyturned down an offer to phase out their agreed pay anomaly over threeyears, and that they should now be offered whatever phasing wasdecided on for doctors and dentists.In discussion of the problem of lost increments, it was argued that thiswas a misnomer.    Because of the operation of incremental pay scales,nobody would be permanently disadvantaged by being required to forgoincrements which would have brought his salary above  8,500 a yearduring stages 1 and 2.    The problem arose because of the AttorneyGeneraTs advice that from 1 August 1977 an employer no longer hasprotection under the Remuneration, Charges and Grants Act 1975 to defer implementation of a pre-policy contractual obligation. the repercussions of this advice were still being studied, and a furtherleport would be made to the Cabinet in due course.    There had been no public interest in this question so far, and it was unlikely to beraised at the time of any announcement.    If it was, the answer shouldbe that the question was still under review.5
On the question of pensionability, it was argued that there were alreadystrong precedents for basing pensions on notional rates of pay ratherthan those actually in payment.    Notional rates had to be thoseestablished either by an independent review body or in negotiation, andpromulgated.    The precedents were almost entirely confined to thepublic sector which already had the benefit of relatively attractivepension terms.    Those affected would primarily be better paid,although junior Servicemen and their dependants would also be covered.There was a case for differential treatment for Cer /icemen, given thatthe whole of their working life was not usually spent in the Servicesand that many Servicemen attached considerable importance to their pension rights as an incentive to remain in the armed forces.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed by a majority to accept in full the recommendations ofthe Review Body on the pay of doctors and dentists, both as to the size and distribution of the immediate pay increase, and as to the forwardcommitment to eliminate the pay anomaly in two instalments inApril 1979 and in April 1980.    The Cabinet also agreed that theuniversity teachers1 quantified pay anomaly should be removed in twoinstalments in October 1978 and October 1979.    The decision onuniversity teachers should be announced at the negotiating meeting next day.    He would himself announce the decision on doctors and dentistsby way of Written Parliamentary Answer on 9 May.    The Cabinet also agreed by a majority to the principle that wherever notional pay rateshad been established, accepted by the Government and promulgated, as for example in the case of the armed forces and doctors and dentists,pensions should be based upon these notional rates and not upon theactual rates in payment at the point of retirement.    The Chancellor ofthe Exchequer should arrange for the question of &quot;lost increments&quot; tobe further examined by EY(P), and for the results to be reported backto Cabinet.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister1 summing up of their discussion.6
4. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the draft White paper on Industrial Democracy (CP(78) 48), and the related memorandum(CP(78) 49) by the Secretary of State for Education and Science and paymaster General.    They also had before them a note (CP(78) 51Revise) by the Secretary of the Cabinet about the level of unionisationin companies and letters dated 2 May 1978 from the PrivateSecretaries to the Minister for Social Security and the Secretary ofState for Northern Ireland to the Prime Minister&apos;s Private Secretarysuggesting amendments to paragraph 1 and paragraph 17 of the draft white Paper respectively.THE PRIME MINISTER invited the Cabinet to resume discussion of thedraft White Paper, starting at paragraph 31.In discussion it was noted that when the Trades Union Congress (TUC)had been consulted about the draft White Paper they had expressedvery strong views about the need for there to be a reference inparagraph 31 to the objective of parity between employee and share-holder representatives on boards.    It was argued  that this point would be a key factor in influencing the trade union response to theWhite Paper and their willingness to make progress on the lines it proposed.    If there were no reference to parity as an objective unioninterest in employee representation on boards would be much weakened.As a result unions would continue to seek to increase their power alongtraditional lines rather than by sharing responsibility and the chances of reducing conflict within industry would be lost.     The TUC/LabourParty Policy Document published in July 1977 had reaffirmed a commitment to parity and it would be politically damaging to go backon that commitment especially in what might be an Election year.The proposal in the White Paper that the initial level of representation on boards should be one third would also be seen as abandonment ofthe Bullock formula which gave trade unions a form of parity throughequal representation with the management representatives under theZx + y formula.    One-third representation would be regarded as quite inadequate by active trade unionists who would not understand why theBullock approach had been dropped.    Without at least a perspective ofparity in some form the document would lose its meaning for trade unionists.    On the other hand it was argued that a commitment in theWhite Paper to parity as an objective meant taking one particular viewabout the way in which industrial democracy would develop in theUnited Kingdom.    It should not be assumed that board representationwould necessarily move towards parity.    Employee directors could,as in Sweden and Denmark, see their role primarily as a source ofinformation for collective bargaining.    The trade unions in those twocountries considered that this role could be satisfactorilyaccomplished without parity and were net pressing for it. WhilstBullock had taken the view that parity was the objective it would be wrong to pre -empt any other possibility.    By no means all trade7
unionists wanted parity and indeed the trade union movement wasdeepl/ divided on the issue.    Moreover whilst there were uncertain-ties about how the trade unions might react if there were a reference toparity in the White Paper there could be no doubt that its inclusionwould cause a violent reaction from industrial management. Thepossibility of constructive discussion with the Confederation of BritishIndustry on the White Paper would be lost.    Industrial investment would be discouraged, particularly inward investment. and politically there was a zisk of alienating a large pa-t of the business community which was specially undesirable in a pre-Election period.The White Paper and subsequent legislation would not prevent adoptionof parity within companies where both employees and managementwanted it.    It was also argued that there might be advantage inincluding a passage in the White Paper which would make it clear thatGovernment did not exclude parity and indeed saw advantages in it provided the circumstances were right.    It would not however be rightto impose parity on reluctant companies.    Adoption of parity wouldalso mean accepting new concepts of employee responsibility with a clearer definition of the role of employee representation on boards.There might also be a reference to experiments in the nationalised industries where management and employee representatives werematched in numbers but there was an independent third element.In discussion of paragraph 36, concerning the method of selection ofemployee representatives for board membership, it was noted that the tuc had objected to the proposals and that an alternative version re-drafted on lines suggested by them had been circulated as Annex B to cp(78) 49.     This alternative draft split paragraph 36 in two, the first part dealing with the provision of a right to appeal by a trade unionagainst the method of selection proposed by the Joint RepresentationCommittee (JRC) and the possibility of a similar right being extendedto any substantial homogeneous group of employees;  and the secondwith the possibilities of setting out statutory criteria by which anysuch appeal would be judged and of a requirement for election in whichnominations would be allowed from groups of employees whether or not they were members of trade unions.    It was argued that inclusion inthe White Paper of either paragraph 36 ae in the circulated draft or the revised version in Annex B to CP(78) 49 raised again the question ofgiving statutory rights to non-trade unionists.    The Cabinet had decided in relation to appeals about the composition of the JRC itselfthat non-trade unionists should not be able to appeal.    It would be inconsistent to take a different view in relation to tha method ofselecting board representatives.    The proposal to give rights to non-trade unionists would cause great offence to the trade union movement.It would therefore be acceptable to amend the draft as circulated inorder to include an appeal for trade unions but nothing should be said about non-trade unionists.    On the other hand it was argued that thecase for recognising the voice of non-trade unionists was much stronger
in relation to the selection of board representatives than in relation tothe composition of the JRC.    In the case of the latter an employercould always have parallel consultations with non-trade unionistswhereas in relation to board representation there could be no suchpossibility.    Either non-trade unionists were given certain rights by legislation or they were totally excluded.    To publish a White paper on industrial democracy which totally denied rights to non-trade unionists in this key area would be indefensible and would leave theGovernment open to serious criticism.    It was, however, also argued that democratic principles would be sufficiently upheld by the proposal that there should be a ballot of all employees on whether or not they wanted board representation.In further discussion the amendments proposed in Annex D to CP(78) 49relating to paragraph 31, 41 and 43 were accepted along with theproposed reference to Northern Ireland set out in the same Annex. Itwas agreed that the revised passage relating to institutions set out in annex C to CP(78) 49 should be included in place of paragraphs 50-53of the circulated draft.    It was also agreed that the White Paper shouldnot contain a reference to the proposed Trade Union National EducationCentre.    In discussion ot the revised material prepared by theMinister for Social Security to replace paragraph 1 of the draft white paper as circulated it was argued that, although this gave a livelierpresentation, it went too far towards an explicit presentation of theproposal as an extension of trade union power and collective bargainingstrength.    The version of the opening paragraph circulated by theSecretary of State for Education and Science and Paymaster General,which amalgamated the Minister for Social Security&apos;s draft with theWhite Paper draft, was generally preferred.    It was agreed not toaccept the amendment proposed to paragraph 17 by the Secretary ofState for Northern Ireland as the point made did not seem appropriate to a White Paper on Industrial Democracy.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that themajority view of the Cabinet was that the White Paper should notendorse parity as an objective.    Any move in that direction would necessarily be some years ahead and would have to be the subject offurther legislation.    Endorsement of parity now could well prejudice the prospect of making any progress towards industrial democracy onthe lines the White Paper would advocate and this had to be the decidingfactor.    There should, however, be a passage in the White Paper tothe effect that the Government recognised that there were strongly heldviews amongst trade unionists in favour of parity;  that the government did not exclude this objective;  but that it believed that the developmentof industrial democracy should go ahead on a step-by-step basis andthat any future developments beyond one-third representation shouldtake place after a substantial period of experience and be subject to whatever conditions seemed appropriate in the light of that experience.
As regards the method of selection of board representatives theCabinet took the view that the existing paragraph 36 should bereplaced by paragraph ?6 and 36a. in the second part of Annex B to cp(78) 49 except that the final sentence of paragraph 36 should be incorporated into paragraph 36a.    The Secretary of State for education and Science and Paymaster General should prepare a revised version ofthe White Paper taking account of the Cabinet decisions on parity andselection of board representatives and the other amendments which cabinet had agreed in discussion, and should then nubmit it to him.He would arrange for it to be circulated to Cabinet colleagues for any final comments.    Colleagues should, however, restrict these topoints of drafting and not substance.    He would then arrange for publication as soon as possible.    Publication of the White Paper wouldbe in the names of himself, the Secretary of State for Employment,the Secretary of State for Trade and the Secretary of State for education and Science and Paymaster General.    He would make thestatement in the House.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion and invited theSecretary of State for Education and Science and paymaster Genera.1, to be guided accordingly.Cabinet Office4 May 1978
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NOCABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION annex cm(78) 17th Conclusions, Minute 2Thursday 4 May 1978 at 10. 30 amw^GN In discussion it was suggested that the reactions in Parliament to anFAIRSunwise remark made by the Chief of the Defence Staff during his recent visit to China could have unfortunate domestic political^ ^ons with        implications.    Some people would exploit the situation in order toaad the try to align the United Kingdom with China against the Soviet Union.* Union Indeed the Conservatives were already exploiting the incident to theGovernment&apos;s disadvantage.    Conversely it would also be suggestedthat because unequivocal support had not been given to what the Chiefof the Defence Staff had said, the Labour Party&apos;s policy wasexcessively pro-Soviet.    Furthermore it would be said that themilitary authorities were not under proper political control. Finally,the Chief of the Defence Staffs remarks would in practice make it more difficult to improve relations with China because of the way inwhich these remarks had been highlighted by the Russians.In further discussion it was argued strongly that we needed to keepthis incident in proportion.    Over the last three years and followingsignificant political changes in China we had deliberately been taking steps to improve our relations with that country.    There was a bigexport potential to the Chinese market which we should explore.There was also nc reason why defence issues should not be discussed with the Chinese.    The possibility of defence sales had been raised as a result of Chinese interest, although no decisions had been takenin this field.    It should be perfectly possible to continue our efforts to improve our relations w&quot;th China while maintaining good relationswith the Soviet Union.    There was full political control over themilitary authorities in this country and the present Chief of theDefence Staff would be the last person to question this.    He mighthave made an error in his choice of words on this one occasion, butit had to be remembered that all Service (and North Atlantic treaty organisation) planning and exercises inevitably looked upon theRussians as the potential enemy.    The incident was not an important one and had been put in its proper perspective by the prime Minister&apos;remarks in the House of Commons on 2 May.1
THE PRIME MINISTER said that the particular incident which had given tise tc the discussion should not be exaggerated.    Following his statement in the House, interest had died down and the Conservativesshould not be given the opportunity to exploit it.    It was to our advantage to maintain good relations with the Governments of bothChina and the Soviet Union.    But there was great suspicion in thecountry of the Soviet Union and the Governments future prospectswould suffer if the Conservatives were able to label the Labour Partyas being pro-Soviet.    It was in the national interest that theGovernment should maintain inter-State relations with the Soviet Unionat a good working level, but it would be wrong to encourage thedevelopment of inter-Party relations.    These would not reflect theviews of the people of the country and any association of the Party withthe extreme Left could only be damaging to its electoral prospects.The Cabinet -Took note.Cabinet Office8 May 19782

</content>
</cab>
