<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/59/0 images: 168-184</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).C RET.Copy No.CABINET    55  (28) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.  10,Downing Street, S.W.1., on WEDNESDAY,November 28th,  1928, at 11. 30 a.m.AGENDA.1 .2.3-4.FOREIGN AFFAIRS.     (if required).PROPOSAL THAT EXPERT COMMITTEE ON OPERATION OFDOMINION LEGISLATION AND SUB-CONFERENCE on merchant SHIPPING LEGISLATION SHOULD MEET INCANADA.(Reference Cabinet 51  (28) Conclusion 5(c))*Memoranda by the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs,(Co?.  529 (23)    -   already circulated).IRISH FREE STATE. CONTEMPLATED ISSUE OF TRUSTEESTOCK IN LONDON.Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,covering Treasury Memorandum.(CP. 366 (28)    -   already circulated)HOUSE OF LORDS REFORM.(Reference Cabinet 5 (28) Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.(CP. 365 (28)    -   already circulated).EXPENDITURE ON PUBLICITY FOR THE BRITISHINDUSTRIES FAIR.(Reference Cabinet 51  (28) Conclusion 6).Memorandum by the President of the Boardof Trade.(CP. 339 (28)    -   already circulated).
6.      RECOMMENDATIONS OF COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRS.The Pensions  (Governors of Dominions)  etc. Bill(Reference H.A.C.  13th Conclusions (28)already circulated).         TO TAKE NOTE OF:-OJERSEA TRADE PROSPECTS.Memorandum by the President of the Boardof Trade,  covering InterdepartmentalMemorandum.(CP.  350 (28)    -    already circulated).(Signed)-    M.P.A. BANKSY,Secretary, Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.,27th November,  1928.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)pj^C R E T. Copy No.CABINET    55 C28).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.1.,  on WEDNESDAY,November 28th,  1928, at 11.^0 a.m.* m *PRESENT:-The Right Hon.  Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (In the Chair)0The Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P., Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C.B.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt. ,M.P., Secretary of Statefor Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthing ton-Evans,Bt. ,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.,C.M.G. ,M.P. , Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of theAdmiralty.Ihe Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M,P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.1-President of the Board oiEducation.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K.G, ,M.V.O. , first commissioner of Works,The Right Hon.Lord Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.H. ,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.The Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.0.,M.P.,  Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.W.E, Guinness, D.S.0.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P., Minister ofLabour.The Right Hon.Lord Cushendun, Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster.
THE KING?S 1.   The Home Secretary made a report to theILLNESS .Cabinet regarding the Kingfs illness.The attention 0&quot;*&quot; the Cabinet was drawn to atelegram in regard to the state of the Kingfshealth which had been sent on the previous evening,on behalf of Lord Stamfordham, in response to enquiries addressed to him, by the Foreign Officeto British diplomatic representatives in certainCapitals8 as well as by the Dominions Office tothe Prime Minister of Canada Cthe intention being to repeat it to other Dominion Prime Ministers)and which is likely to be published in thosecountries and Dominions.   The Cabinet  remarked that this telegram, though based on the previousseries of communiques, gave a somewhat different-impression from the latest announcement issued bythe Hing&apos;s medical advisers in this country.   Inthese ciroumstanoes the Cabinet felt it desirableto obtain a more detaib d opinion from the King&apos;smedical advisers than is contained in the dailybulletins .The Home Secretary then left the Meeting to visit Buckingham Palace.The Cabinet agreed  That the following report, addressedto the Pome Secretary by His Majesty&apos;smedical  advisers, should be published:-BUCKINGHAM PAL.ACE.28th November, 1928.,* 9 a .m .My dear Home Secretary,I gather from you that theCabinet wish for a more detailedopinion about His Majesty&apos;s illnessthan is contained in the dailybulletins.-1-
1 P 9.5 0 0Will you therefore inform them as fellowsThe King is suffering frominflammation (congestion) of theright lung with extensive plasticpleurisy cn the right side whichas you know is a painful condition.Such an infection must from its nature be serious0   In all illnessesof this character there must beanxiety which will continue for thepresent but I am happy to say thatthe King passed a quieter night,that the condition of the lung showssome improvement and that his strength is maintains doSo far then the illness is beingcontrolled, its force lessened, itssymptoms axleviated and I hope itsduration will be curtailed.Yours sincerely,DAWSON OP PENN.(Signed)STANLEY HEWETT .-la-
2. The Cabinet were informed that the prince of Wales, whc is on a visit to Kenya, is proceeding at once to Dar-es-Salaam and that H.M.S.ENTERPRISEis sailing from Aden to bring His Royal Highnesson the first stage at any rate of his journeyhome .The First Lord of the Admiralty was asked tomake arrangements to enable His Royal Highness tojourney home by sea as rapidly as possible.The Prime Sinister informed the Cabinet thatthe Prince of Wales had expressed a desire to travel part of the way by air, in order to expedite his journey.    The Cabinet felt consider-able doubt as to whether it was in the publicinterest  that Fis Royal Highness should proceed by air for any part of the journey, and left thePrime Minister, after consultation with theSecretary of State for Air on the aerial aspectsof the question,  as well as with Sir Lionel Halseyand Sir Godfrey Thomas, to draw up and approve a reply to HeR0H. The Prince of Wales.
THE SECRETARY 3. The Prime Minister offered a warm welcome,0? STATE PGRFOREIGN AFFAIRS, on behalf of the Cabinet, to Sir Austen Chamberlainon Ms return from the long Journey undertaken forthe sahe of Ms health, and at the same timeexpressed the thanks of the Cabinet to theChancellor cf the Duchy of Lancaster for themanner i:i which he had discharged the arduousduties or Acting Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs during Sir Austen Chamberlain&apos;s absence.-3-
1 p.*ANGLO-american relations .(Pi-previous reference:Cabinet 52(28),  Con-elusion 5.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs stated that, having only just returned to theForeign Office, he did not yet wish to raise anyquestion of foreign policy.   He warned theCabinet that the most difficult question appearedto be our relations with the United States ofAmerica,    Sir Austen Chamberlain hoped to be ina position to deal with the most immediate questionarising in that connection, namely, the reply tothe United States Note on the sublect of theAnglo-French compromise proposals on the reduction and Limitation of Naval Armamentsq at the next meeting of the Cabinet.   Later on he wouldprobably have to ask for a Special Meeting ofthe Cabinet to consider the broader question ofour relations with the United States.-4- -
i 0 iIMPERIALRELATIONS.The propoaedExpert Com-mittee on theOperation ofDominionLegislationsnd Sub-Confer enoeon MerchantShippingLegislation.(Pr evi previous reference:Cabinet 51(28), Con-clusion 5(c)5. The Cabinet had under consideration thequestion of whether the Prime Minister of Canadashould be sounded as to the desirability of holding in Canada the Expert Committee and theSub-Conference on Merchant Shipping legislation to be set up as a consequence of the recommenda-tions of the Imperial Conference, 1926.In this connection they had before them thefollowing documents:-A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs (paper c.P.-S29  (28)):A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs (PaperCoPo-360 (28)) covering a despatch from Sir William Clark reportinga conversation with Mr R.B0Bennett,KoC0,s the Leader of the Opposi-tion in Canada.After the Secretary cf State for DominionAffairs had erearaarised the reasons given in his memorandum in favour of holding these meetings at ottawa, the President of the Board of trade informed the Cabinet that it would be possibleto send experts to Canada, but on wider groundshe deprecated the holding of the Conferences inthat country.   He pointed out that South africa and the Irish Free State, both Dominions with avery small mercantile marine, intended to raise questions of the highest constitutional importancein connection with the Sub-Conference on Merchant,Shipping Legislation.   Prom the point of view ofthe desirability of our representatives being intouch both with the Ministers who had been concern-ed with the Imperial Relations settlement of 1926and with experts on the practical side of theseshipping problems (who were only to be found inLondon) he strongly deprecated holding the Confer-ence out of this country.
Sir Ana ten Chamberlain reported to the Cabinetthat in a private conversation Mr Mackenzie king had mentioned that Canada had received a goed manyvisits from distinguished British citizens duringthe last year, and Sir Austen thought, therefore,that the Canadians themselves might prefer to hold the Conference in this country.The Secretary of State for Dominion affairs agreed that these considerations outweighed themore general advantages of holding the Conferencein Canada.The Cabinet, while appreciatingthat, for sentimental reasons,there were advantages of e generalis^ture in holding Conferences inOana&amp;a or other Dominions, consid-eroS that the reasons given bythe Resident of the Board of Traderen&amp;sx-ed it imperative that theparticular Confsrenoes undereonsideraticn eiioald be held inLondon,,
THE IRISH 6.    The Cabinet had before their, a Note byFREE STATr .- the Chancellor of the Exchequer (Paper 0o?o-366ContemplatedIssue of (28)) covering a Memorandum by the Treasury, inTrustee Stockin London. regard to the desire of the Free State Governmentto raise before Christmas a large Loan on theLondon money market, and mainly from Britishrather than Irish subseiibers, in which thesituation arising from the refusal of the FreeState Government to comply with certain conditions laid down by the Treasury for such Loans under theColonial Stocks Act in 1900 is referred to .The question was postponed, inorder that the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs, who, like other members of the Cabinet, had only received the Treasury Lfemo-ran dum shortly before the Meeting,should have time to study theConstitutional aspects of thequestion0The Secretary was instructed toplace the subject on the agenda for next week.
tfOUSE OF 7. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum byLCRDS REFORM.the Lord Privy Seal (Paper C.P.-365 (28)) reporting(Previous that in the course of the next fortnight twoReference:Cabinet 5 Motions upon the reform- of the House of Lords,(28), Con-clusion 4.) one next Thursday from the Liberal benches by LordBuckmaster, and the other on December 11th fromthe Conservative side by Lord Clarendon, were tobe moved.   The Lord Privy Seal raised the question as to what answer was to be given, pointing outthat the Government could not, without futility,avoid an expression of opinion.The Lord Privy Seal reported that since hewrote his Memorandum at the Prime Minister * suggestion, Lord BuckmasterTs Resolution had beenwithdrawne   The Government were therefore facedonly with a Debate on December 11th on the motion of certain Conservative Members of the House ofLords .   The text of the Motion was not yet available, but Lord Salisbury was given tounderstand that in all probability it was likelyto refer not to the powers of the House of Lordsbut to the personnel, and that it would proposethat the Hereditary Members of the House should bereduced by some form of election and that anotherele-&apos;- ent should be introduced so as to give adequate representation to the political Parties at presentinadequately represented.From a discussion which followed,  the general view of the Cabinet emerged that a Motion conceivedjon the above lines might be commended in general terms by the Government speakers, but there was&apos; a desire that the Government should not be committed
in any way to specific action, and that if thequestion of the powers of the house of Lords was raised in debate the Government speakers should reply to the effect that it was far too importanta subject for them to express an opinion upon whenit was not included in the Motion.The Lord Privy Seal was asked by a member ofthe Cabinet to consider a proposal that, as leader of the wouse of Lords, he should say that FisMajesty5 s Government have always regarded a changein the personnel of the house of Lords as worthy of consideration and would be glad to go further into the matter, but only if there was agreement among the different Parties thereon.The subject was adjc-mmed untilthe next weekly Meeting of theCabinet, when the lord Privy Sealhoped that he might be able toobtain the text of the Motion forDecember 11th.
THF BRITISHindustriesPAIR.(previous reference:Cabinet 51(88 h Con-conclusion   6 .)8. The Cabinet had &quot;before them a Memorandumby the President of the Board of Trade (Paper 0a?.-359 (28)) on the subject of a possible contribution of  25,000 from the empire Marketing Fund towardsthe British Industries Fair *   In his MemorandumSir Philip Cunliffe-Lister recalled that in January1928, a similar proposal had been made and that allthe Dominions had concurred in it except AustraliacHe suggested that a further appeal should be madeto the Commonwealth Government.After a long discussion the Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Chaicellor of theExchequer and the Presidentof the Board of Trade, inconsultation, should prepareend circulate a Memorandum inregard to the effect during the&apos; last two years of the ImperialPreferences and of recent legis-lation in    some of the Dominionsoonneoted therewith, on the trade of this country as compared withthe trade of other countries withthe Dominions:(b) That on the receipt of the above memorandum further consideration should be given to the question raised in Paper CP.-339 (23).
NAVAL CON-STRUOTTONPROGRAMME.The Type ofCruiser for1928-29.(previous reference:Cabinet 29(28), Con-elueion 2 .)9.   The First Lord of the Admiralty reminded his colleagues that on May 17,  1928, at theMeeting referred to in the margin, the cabinet had approved his proposal that the two Cruisersto be laid do^-n in 1928-29 should be the Class *Air&apos;type.    In view, however, of the negotiations  that were then proceeding with the United States ofAmerica in regard to the Kellogg Pact and othermatters, h^ had been ashed not to make any announcement on the stibject at that time.Mr Eridgeman said that the Admiralty had now reached the stage of placing orders, and he was liable at any moment to be questioned on thesubject in Parliament.   He asked if there was any objection to his making an announcement on thesubject In the near future if pressed to do so.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To reserve the question forconsideration at their next meeting:(b) That, if pressed for information in the meanwhile, the First Lordof the Admiralty should reply that he was not prepared to make an announcement at present.
THE PENSIONS( GOVERNORSOP DOMINIONS)PILL a(previous reference:C abine t 6(28),  Con-clusion 8 &amp;Appendix.)10 . The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State fcr the Colonies (F.A.-39(28))  covering a draft Pensions  (Governors of dominions    etc,)Bill, together with the recommendation of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon(H.A.O. 13th Conclusions  (28), Para.l).In accordance with the latter recommendation the Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction inthe House of Commons of thePensions (Governors of Dominions etc.)Bill in the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-39 (28), subjectto the substitution on page 3 lines12 and 23 of the words &quot;the State&quot;for the words &quot;a colony&quot;,  and toany other necessary minor alt era-tions, on the understanding thatthe Secretary of State for theColonies would confer with theParliamentary Secretary to theTreasury respecting the time tobe found for the Bill and thatits further progress must in any event depend upon the absence of serious opposition to its provisions .
11. The Cabinet had before their; a Memorandumby the President of the Board of Trade (paper cp.-355 (28)), covering a Memorandum on TradeIfprevious Recovery and Unemployment, which had been drawn; Reference*.Cabinet 50 up by the Board of Trade, the Ministry of(23),  Con-clusion I0) Labour and the Department of Oversea Trade after consideration of reports received from HisMajesty&apos;s Commercial Counsellors, Secretariesand Trade Commissioners, who had been instructedto furnish information on this subject.The Cabinet took note ofthe above Memorandum.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,November 28, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
