<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/6/29 images: 388-391</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-;l5 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS, BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 3 GOVERNMENT. RET.Pi. (R.H4Q)   149,m MAY,   1940.COPY NO.   52-WAR CABINET.COAL POSITION.Seventeenth Fortnightly Report submitted by theSecretary for Mines covering the period 1st &apos;to 15th May, 1940.(Previous Paper:    Paper No. W.P.   (R.)(40) 136)(initialled)- &apos;D. \R.. G.Richmond Terrace,B*.  1.-
SEVENTEENTH FORTNIGHTLY REPORT SUBMITTED 3Y THE SECRETARYFOR MINES COVERING THE PERIOD 1ST - 15T1I MAY,  1940.COAL POSITION.SUPPLIES.Considerable pressure has suddenly been put upon the state of surelies by the&quot; need for compensating France for the loss of coalhitherto obtained from Holland and Belgium.      The amount involvedmonthly is in the region of 400,000 tons of coal and 100,000 tons of coke, and increases France&apos;s current requirements approximately from1,500,000 to 2,000,000 tons per month plus an additional 200,000 tensfor the Empire (exclusive of stocking requirements).      As the amountof United Kingdom coal previously available for export to neutral countries had been reduced to the barest minimum,  the availability ofcoal for export to neutral countries must now depend on the extent towhich (a) coal can be diverted from the home market,  i.e.  from publicutility undertakings, household consumers - or:non-essential industrial undertakings, or (b) production can be expanded, or (c) both.This substantial increase in French requirements has introduced a new element into the internal supply situation which, - prior to&apos; the invasion of the Low Countries,  had seemed to be improvingsatisfactorily,  due mainly to the maintenance of the pest-Easterrecovery in production.     Deliveries of coal to domestic consumers anlindustrial undertakings had for the most part caught up with current-consumption and,  in the case of the public utilities, had exceeded it.Some difficulty has inevitably been experienced, however, in meetingthe demands of industry on account of the acceleration of war productioThe house coal position has now become less urgent because of the seasonal decline in demand and the maintenance,  in London and parts ofthe Southern Counties, of the restriction of deliveries to individualconsumers to 5 cwts.  a fortnight.      In the case of the public utility undertakings,  coal deliveries have been well in excess of current consumption,  the latest returns showing for the week ended 11th May separately of deliveries sufficient to enable both the gas and electricityworks of the country as a whole to raise their stocks on the average tthe equivalent of an 8 weeks&apos;  supply (at the winter rate of consumptioby the end of September.      Steps are being taken to improve supplies tworks which have not kept pace with the general improvement.The Department has continued to assist the movement of coal to domestic consumers and public utility undertakings by maintaining a programme for rail transport from Northumberland, Durham and theM.   (A.) D.  to London and the South of 170 trainloads of coal a week. &apos;There was some modification of this programme over Whitsun,  involving the withdrawal of 55 trains, but the full programme has now been resumed.It had been intended that when .the state of supplies permitted,steps should be taken to take up the slack in demand for household cosduring the summer by inducing consumers,  partly by a lifting of the ration,  to build up their own private stocks,  as well as by laying dowstocks on Government account.      Recent developments across the Channelare making it necessary to review the whole position in the light ofFrance&apos;s increased requirements,  shipment facilities to France, apossible closing of our North East Coast Ports,  etc.
-2-PRODUCTION AND EMPLOYMENT.   -.  ..       -.:- \ - 7. . \.     A&apos;&apos;Production has &quot;been practically maintained., - &apos; The numbers employedremain fairly constant,  and there have been only negligible variations in the time&apos;worked at the pits.&apos;   .&apos;- -    ESTIMATED QUANTITY OP SALEABLE COAL PAISSD.. .., - Week ended   - Corresponding week-&apos;&apos; &quot; V:----19.40- 19:39.Tons &apos;&apos;.   &apos;  Tons.   20th. April &apos; 4,852,600.       .-&apos; 4, 856,-70027th&apos; -&apos; &quot;  &quot; : ; -.4^866,500 ; 4,818,1004th &quot;May - &quot;  4,828,500 4,515,300   . .&apos;-.&apos;;&apos;7p11th     &quot;      (provisional)     4,727,500 .    4,705&apos;, 900Wage Earners. , ?      . :  A1 -     V..&apos;     - .20th April &quot;&apos;&apos;&apos;       &apos; &apos;A , 76-3,200  - &apos;   &apos;r    772., 000. &apos; 7     - -27th- .        &apos;- &apos;  r:]   -   &apos; -&apos;.Y-:&apos;&quot;&quot;: - -.   . : 763,4-00 -- &apos;        773,500      -4th May :     &apos;. .&apos;7&quot;. - .--; 753, 500-  -&apos; 774,100.    ., Vj   : .11th -(provisional) .   -: .763,300-       &apos; 1   775,600      . .Number-employed in the week ended -9th September,- 1939.,: . A.. /.        1-&quot;- -J -.j(as;,748,:600&apos;i.  1 :     -   &quot;&quot;&quot;Time Worked (days).        :       . jt - &apos;1- 20th April-    &quot;       &apos;&apos; ...   .    5.65&apos; / $.44 &quot; J      &apos; &apos;27th    &apos;.&quot; &quot;&apos; 1 1       &quot; -     5.,66   -   &apos;       &apos;    &apos; 5.344th May 5. 57 5.0211th     &quot;       (provisional) 5.60 5.25EXPORTS.Immediately on the invasion of the Low Countries Ministerialauthority was secured for the diversion to Prance during the second half of May of practically the whole of the coal that would have been supplied to neutral destinations during that period.      It is estimatedthat this and other ad hoc measures will make available an additional250,000 tons of coal for Prance in May.      The question of the rate ofsupply in June is under urgent consideration.
TonsTons20th April27th     &quot;4th May11th     11(provisional)Bunkers for foreign going vessels.20th April27th     &quot;4th May11th   - 11  -(provisional):Total quantity of coal shipped abroad(including the coal equivalent of coke and manufactured fuel).20th April27th4th May11th     &quot;      (provisional)COAL PRODUCTION COUNCIL.524,200672,200650,300640,100154,200159,800161,500165,800716,100869,800874,100856,100.713,800826,600905,900807,200144,200195,800163,600188,600931,9001, 065, 500.1,156,000.- ,066,100The Coal Production Council is continuing the organisation of anational drive for increased output.      Production   Committees compose;of owners&apos;   and&apos;,   -workers &apos;   representatives,  to co-operate with theCouncil, have now teen formed in all the districts with the exceptioncf Scotland, :and the smaller districts which Lord Portal has yet to visit,  namely, North Vales, Cumberland, Forest of Dean, Somerset andKent.      In each area the registers of unemployed are being examined b;a panel consisting of a representative of the owners and workers andthe manager of each local Labour Exchange.Lord Portal is giving as much publicity as possible to this drivfor increased output,  and spoke over the &quot;Wireless&quot;, on the 15th May,emphasizing&apos;the importance - of increasing output and appealing to the mineworkers for their co-operation. . :,&apos;

</content>
</cab>
