<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/28/2 images: 28-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT is THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S G0YERNMEN3-Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1942.MOST SECRET.W.P (42) 372.Auaust 23, 1942.Copy No^TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.FUTURE OPERATIONS.Minutes of a Conference held at Cairo, August 4, 1942.BY direction of the Prime Minister, the attached Minutes of a Meetingheld at Cairo on August 4, 1942, with the Prime Minister in the Chair, are circulated for the information of the War Cabinet.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES,Secretary of the War Cabinet.Great George Street, S.W.1,August 23, 1942.Minutes of a Meeting held in the British Embassy, Cairo, at 1800 hours on tuesday, August 4, 1942.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, Prime Minister and minister of Defence.Field-Marshal J. C. Smuts, PrimeMinister of the Union of SouthAfrica.General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Admiral Sir Henry Harwood, Com-mander-in-Chief, Mediterranean.The Right Hon. R. G. Casey, Ministerof State.General Sir Archibald Wavell,Commander-in-Chief, India.General Sir Claude Auchinleck,Commander-in-Chief, Middle EastForces.Air Chief Marshal Sir Arthur Tedder,Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief,Middle East.Secretary.Colonel E. I. C. Jacob.[24253]b
THE SITUATION IN THE MIDDLE EAST.SIR ALAN BROOKE said that the object of the review by the Chiefs ofStaff* which was before the meeting was to study the action which we mighthave to take in the Middle East theatre of war in the event of a serious threat to the Persian Gulf oilfields developing from the Caucasus. It might benecessary to consider whether to hold Egypt and attempt to drive the Germansout of North Africa or to abandon such projects and concentrate on the defenceof the Persian Gulf. The Chiefs of Staff had been largely influenced by a reporttfrom the Oil Control Board, in which it was stated that the loss of Abadan andBahrein would probably lead to a 20 per cent, cut in our various fields of activity.The Middle East, India, South Africa and Australia would be the places mainiyaffected. It was very hard to come to any conclusion on the Russian situationor to estimate the extent of the Russian resistance north of the Caucasus. TheRussians were believed to have ten to fifteen Divisions in that area, but some ofthese might withdraw eastward to defend the Volga. The Russian strategy mightwell be to concentrate everything on keeping their front intact from Stalingradnorthwards along the Don, and to let the Caucasus go. In such a case Germanlight forces might penetrate to Northern Persia in October or November. Theywould not be in great strength, so that if we could arrange for a modicum ofdefence we might hold them until the winter, during which we could build up our strength for the spring campaign. The 5th Division was already moving from india and the 51st and 56th Divisions were on their way from the UnitedKingdom, possibly to be followed by one United States Armoured Division.These formations might be directed to the Persian Gulf or, alternatively, theymight be brought to Egypt, thus releasing battle-worn formations to go to Persia,where they, could be reconstituted and re-equipped. The Chiefs of Staff felt that whatever else happened it was essential to hold Abadan, without which it wouldbe hard to carry on the war. It would be preferable to lose Egypt rather than to lose the oil.The United States Armoured Division, to which he had referred, had been offered by. the Americans, who were very anxious to get their troops into actionthis year. It was an offer quite independent of the offer of Sherman tanks and self-propelled guns, which were now on the sea. The date of its move was uncertain, as it would be necessary to weigh up the advantages of its arrivalagainst those of the arrival of drafts to bring existing formations up to strength.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the United States Chiefs of Staff were most anxious for the early arrival of their armoured Division so that it could get into action as soon as possible. Mr. Hopkins, General Marshall and admiral King had recently visited London to discuss combined plans. They had come over most desirous for the establishment of a second front in 1942 if therewas any possibility of it being done successfully. The plan which had beenunder consideration was a landing to capture a bridgehead on the CherbourgPeninsula. Its object would be twofold. First of alls as a means of withdrawingGerman troops from the Eastern front, and, secondly, as a preliminary step tothe large-scale invasion of the Continent in 1943. A great flow of United states troops to the United Kingdom was allowed for and was in progress. This plan had been most earnestly, discussed by the United States and British Chiefs ofStaff and had finally had to.be rejected as unprofitable. The arguments against it were overwhelming. From the point of view of weather, a landing could notbe carried out later than September, and by that month few American troops. would be ready to take part. The size of the forces which could be landed wereinsignificant compared with the strength which the Germans could mass againstthe landing during the winter, if not earlier. &apos; Moreover, the resources whichwould have to be used up in the operation, and particularly the special landing craft, were required for the training and organisation of the much larger, forces which could be employed next Spring. The smaller operation, in fact, wouldhamstring the larger.When the matter had been fully studied there was unanimous agreement onall sides that it should not be proceeded with unless something very unforeseenoccurred such as a crack in the German power of resistance. It was at this stage that attention was directed to the alternative of operations in North Africadesigned to gain possession of the whole coast from Casablanca to Tunis. the obvious strategic advantages of a successful operation of this kind came to berecognised by the United States Chiefs of Staff, and the enterprise had alwaysappealed strongly to the President. Very soon it had proved possible to reach an unanimous settlement on the broad outline of the operation and it had been* C.O.S. (42) 357. f CCS. (42) 352.
arranged that plans and preparations should proceed with the utmost speed and energy.The Prime Minister then gave a general outline of the nature and scope ofthe operation and explained that, although the reactions of the French could notbe predicted with any certainty, it was hoped that by placing the American flagin the forefront at each landing place resistance would be at the most half-hearted.The only point on which there was not at present complete agreement was theeffect of this operation on preparations for the big operation on the Continentnext year. The United States Chiefs of Staff inclined to the opinion that theContinental operations would be nullified by the diversion of resources to north africa, but he was inclined to regard the matter more in the light of a postpone-ment by three or four months of the invasion of the Continent. The Presidentagreed with this view, and in any case the flow of United States troops to theUnited Kingdom would be maintained to the maximum extent possible. This,coupled with the obvious signs of preparation throughout this summer, wouldbe of great assistance in maintaining a state of uncertainty in the minds of theGermans.The policy having thus been settled between ourselves and the United States,he had thought it best to go to Russia and to give Premier Stalin an account ofour plans. Stalin would undoubtedly dislike the idea of there being no second front in Europe this year, but it would be necessary to convince him of the great advantages which would accrue to the common cause from a success in north africa. If the Germans attempted to meet us there, they could only do it withforces withdrawn from the Russian front, while, at the same time the direct threat to North-West Europe would remain. We should be carrying out a flankingmovement to the main battle. We could not in any way be accused of a breach of faith since the matter had been quite clearly put to M. Molotov in an aide-Memoire* which had been handed to him when he visited London recently.(At this point the Prime Minister read to the meeting the relevant parts of the aide-Memoire in question.)SIR ALAN BROOKE gave further details of the reasons which had ledto the rejection of the plan for operations in Northern France this year, and pointed out that they would neither cause the Germans to withdraw forces fromthe East nor would they serve as a preliminary to the invasion of the Continentnext year, since we could not count on maintaining ourselves in France duringthe winter.The discussion then turned on the situation developing north of the Caucasus.THE PRIME MINISTER observed that the Caspian Sea, the CaucasusMountains and a neutral Turkey would together form a good shield for ournorthern flank provided that the Russians would hold the Caucasus chain and provided that we could support them with air forces which would prevent the domination by the Germans of the air over the Caspian. A scheme for movingtwenty squadrons to that front had been worked out, but he was not prepared to divert anything from Egypt until a decision had been reached in the western desert. The battle in the Western Desert was of vital importance to the wholewar, and he felt it would be wrong to withdraw forces which could take part init in order to prepare what could only be a weak defence in the north.FIELD-MARSHAL SMUTS said that to do so would be to create a situation of the same kind as that which had faced us when we went to Greece.He enquired what forces could be in Northern Persia by October on theassumption that we could not send anything from Egypt. He understood thatif the Russians did not defend the Caucasus the threat to North Persia might develop by that month.SIR CLAUDE AUCHINLECK said that the forces which would beavailable would depend upon the rate of. arrival of reinforcements. He thought there might be three to four Divisions and the best part of an Armoured Division.The limiting factor,, however, would be transport, of which there was a greatshortage throughout the Middle East. He must emphasize the fact that withthe resources now available or in sight there would not be enough transport toenable him to conduct a large offensive in the Western Desert and at the sametime to prepare a mobile defence in Northern Persia. He was doing everythinghe could to reduce scales of transport throughout the Army, but it was evidentthat the further he advanced in the Western Desert, the greater would be thedemands on transport. If he launched an offensive he might find that the threatfrom the Caucasus was developing just when he was in the middle of his advance.* Circulated with the Confidential Annex to W.M. (42), 73rd Conclusions. June 11, 1942.[24253] . V b 2
It was 1,200 miles from Cairo to the Caspian Sea, and our front there would be served only by one railway, whose facilities were strictly limited. The Germans,on the other hand, would be backed by a very good railway system north of Tabriz.THE PRIME MINISTER enquired whether anything was going to besent off from Egypt to Persia that might act in the battle in the Western Desert.He did not propose that any Air forces should be moved until after a decisionhad been reached in the battle.SIR A. TEDDER pointed out that if his squadrons were to reach theCaucasus front in October they should be coming back from the Western Desertnow to re-fit, and their ground installations should be starting to move across.In recent weeks he had been operating with every squadron which he could findin support of the battle in the Western Desert. These squadrons had been operating at about 60 per cent, of their full strength, since although the repair of aircraft had been rapid, the flow of new aircraft had not been enough to buildup his strength. Wastage in fighter squadrons had been about 100 per cent,per month, of which 50 per cent, had been completely written off. Provided the flow of aircraft to the Middle East could be maintained at the right level and provided the United States squadrons arrived according to programme, he feltconfident that he would be able to meet the demands which would be made upon him.SIR ALAN BROOKE thought that if the necessary transport could be madeavailable and adequate air forces could be moved to the Northern flank, any threatwhich might develop there this autumn could be met. He felt that the rightstrategy would be to try and block the enemy&apos;s advance on the Caucasus whilestriking in the Western Desert, with the object eventually of joining hands in north Africa with the Forces coming from the West.FIELD-MARSHAL SMUTS enquired whether the Germans would notconsiderably reinforce their air forces in the Mediterranean theatre.SIR A. TEDDER thought that it should not be assumed that they wouldnot, particularly if things began to go badly for them in the Western Desert.SIR ALAN BROOKE said that the Chiefs of Staff had examined thisquestion and were of the opinion that the Germans would be forced to concentratetheir air resources to maintain their Russian offensive. Everything dependedfor the Germans on success in Russia. Their object must be to try and eliminateRussia this year so as to avoid another active campaign in the Russian winter,SIR CLAUDE AUCHINLECK pointed out that the Germans might havecounted on having to fight on against the Russians in 1943.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed, and drew attention to references madeby Hitler in his recent speech to the steps which had been taken to avoidadministrative difficulties in the coming winter. He did not think that theRussians would drop out of the war this year, though it remained to be seen whether the Germans could mount other large-scale offensives on the russian front before the winter started.The Prime Minister then asked for the views of those present on the decisions which had been taken in London.FIELD-MARSHAL SMUTS said that he was in complete agreement withthe idea of operations to clear North Africa. Success would not only greatlyease our transportation difficulties by opening the Mediterranean, but wouldenable us to threaten the Axis in their weakest spot.Ms,. CASEY said that he was extremely relieved to hear of the decision whichhad been taken, with which he was in complete agreement.SIR CLAUDE AUCHINLECK said that he was entirely in favour of an operation to clear French North Africa if there was any chance of success. Hesuggested that much could be done to prepare the way by the judicious useof money.SIR ALAN BROOKE explained the arrangements which had been made toco-ordinate the activities of S.O.E. with military plans. A special organisation was being set up under the control of the Allied Commander-in-Chief, who wouldbe General Eisenhower.SIR ARCHIBALD WAVELL recognised the advantages of operations in north-West Africa, but drew attention to the risks which were being run inIndia.  There were three dangers against which he had to guard.   The &quot;first was
the Japanese danger. He would not feel secure in India or in Ceylon until hehad an adequate air striking force. Nor would the Eastern Fleet base itself in ceylon until this striking force was available, to keep the Japanese at arm&apos;slength. It appeared that the proposed operations would still further delay thebuilding up of the Eastern Fleet and of the air striking force. Japanese cruisershad been recently sighted steaming through the Malacca Straits, and he had only been able to gather together 10 Wellingtons and 12 Blenheims to act against them if they came into the Bay of Bengal.The second danger against which he had to guard was that of internaltrouble. He did not expect anything serious unless the general course of the warcontinued to deteriorate. The third danger was a German advance to thePersian Gulf, the loss of which would be fatal to India. It was to meet this threat that he had offered to send the 5th and the 2nd Division. The former wason the move, and he could afford to wait ten days before a decision was takenabout the latter. He enquired what were the present chances of a successfulbattle in the Western Desert.SIR CLAUDE AUCHINLECK said that his intention was to destroy theenemy in his present position. For this purpose it would be necessary to wait until the reinforcements which he had now received were ready to fight. Thiswould not be until the middle of September. An opportunity might occur before then, which he would certainly seize; but for the time being the troops in the8th Army had exhausted their effort, and rested infantry were required to breaka way through the minefields and other defences with which the enemy wasconsolidating his position. He was not prepared to commit himself to any date,but he would certainly take advantage of any favourable turn in the situation.The Germans had a superiority in tanks of the highest class. Our Valentines,Stuarts and Crusaders were useful, but could not be pitted against the GermanMark III and IV.THE PRIME MINISTER then read to the meeting extracts from thememorandum* which he bad written and which the Chiefs of Staffs had sent toGeneral Wavell, laying down the conditions in which operations for the recaptureof Burma might be launched. He hoped that General Wavell would continue tothe best of his ability to prepare for these operations, and he drew attention tothe telegram in which the Chiefs of Staff had stated their intention of providingGeneral Wavell with what he needed in landing craft and assault ships by december 1942.The Prime Minister then referred to operations in Madagascar, and said that it was hoped that the capture of Majunga and Tamatave might beachieved before the rains in October. Admiral Somerville and General Platt hadbeen asked if they could carry out these operations with improvised assaultshipping.FIELD-MARSHAL SMUTS said that when he had passed throughNairobi he had discussed with General Platt the situation in Madagascar andthe release of the South African Brigade. General Platt had said that if theChiefs of Staff were satisfied that Diego Suarez could be held by the East AfricanBrigade alone he would be prepared to release the South African Brigade. Hehad said that he intended to go forward with the operations.SIR ALAN BROOKE said that the threat to Diego Suarez was certainlyvery small, as it was unlikely that any Japcinese expedition could be launchedagainst the place.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he would be reluctant to see the SouthAfrican Brigade withdrawn until the operations were over. He recognisedField-Marshal Smuts&apos;s desire to extricate the Brigade so that it could train forits armoured role, and he thought that the matter should be further examined.Summing up the position the Prime Minister said that he intendedto find out while in Moscow what forces the Russians had disposed for the defenceof the Caucasus and thus to estimate the extent of the danger which might arise on that flank this year. On his return the whole situation could be reviewed inthe light of the information which he had obtained and the final decisions as toour policy could be reached. In the meanwhile nothing could be done which wouldin any way detract from our effort in the Western Desert. A decision as to the move of the 2nd Division from India could also remain in suspense until his return.Cairo, August 4, 1942.* Circalated as Prime Ministers Personal Minute D. 128/2, July 12, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
