<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/107/0 images: 77-83</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1961C. (61) 156 Copy No.    5 87th October, 1961CABINETTHE EUROPEAN SOCIAL CHARTERMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Council of Europe have been engaged in drafting a European SocialCharter since 1953 when it was first proposed by the Consultative Assembly. Thework was recently completed and the Charter is to be signed at a ceremony inTurin on 18th October.2. The text of the Charter is attached. It is largely concerned with labourmatters but contains also health, social security and social welfare provisions.Part I is a declaration of aims; Part II contains provisions designed to ensure the effective exercise of certain specific rights; Parts III, IV and V deal with formal andprocedural matters. Annex A to this Paper contains comments on the provisions in some detail. Government Departments concerned were consulted at the draftingstage, and have recently confirmed their position on the final text. NorthernIreland has also been consulted.3. In order to ratify the Charter a member country must accept the declarationof aims in Part I and a minimum of ten of the nineteen Articles in Part II, of whichat least five shall be drawn from a list of seven specified Articles. The UnitedKingdom has no difficulty in accepting the declaration of aims and on the basis ofexisting law and practice it can accept fourteen articles (and parts of some others),including six of the seven specified Articles (see Annex B). It could thus ratify the charter by a wide margin. The undertakings we accept would apply to Britishsubjects in the United Kingdom and to nationals of other Contracting Partieslawfully resident here.4. Most of the principles and provisions of the Charter are already recognised by the member countries of the Council of Europe so that its significance restslargely in its becoming a manifestation of the social rights and standards common to Western Europe.5. I recommend that the United Kingdom should sign the Charter and indue course ratify it.6.   The Minister of Labour concurs in the terms of this paper.H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,6th October, 1961..59775THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
ANNEX ACOMMENTS ON THE PROVISIONS OF THE CHARTERPreamble to the CharterThe Preamble is not part of the legal instrument and imposes no obligations.It could, however, be invoked later in the interpretation of the Charter. For that reason, the Governmental Social Committee took particular care with the&quot; discrimination &quot; paragraph which is now in a form acceptable to the UnitedKingdom.Part I of the Charter2. This declaration of social rights and principles is fully acceptable to theUnited Kingdom.  Some points to note are:(a) They have to be accepted by all Contracting Parties as &quot; aims of policy &quot;.(b) No date is mentioned for fulfilment of the aims, and there is no requirement to report on them.(c) Contracting Parties may restrict the rights and principles, provided therestrictions can be justified under the terms of Article 31 of the Charter.3. The paragraphs of Part I largely speak for themselves, but there are two important interpretations to bear in mind:(a) The Social Committee agreed that paragraph 7 would not require specialprotective measures except where physical and/or moral hazards wereevident and of a sufficiently general nature to warrant action.(b) A note in the Appendix to the Charter makes it clear that paragraph 18 isnot concerned with the question of entry into a country (but withemployment).Part II of the Charter (Articles 1 to 19)4. These are the substantive clauses corresponding to the rights and principlesof Part I. The obligations extend to one&apos;s own nationals at home, and to nationals of other Contracting Parties as defined in paragraph 1 of the Appendix to the charter. Comments on the individual Articles are given below. In examiningthese Articles, the relevance of Article 31 (Restrictions) and 33 (Implementation byCollective Agreements) should be kept in mind.Article 1. The right to work5. This Article is acceptable to us. It is one of the compulsory Articles. Theinelegant text of paragraph 1 is a compromise evolved at the Tripartite Conferenceheld by the Council of Europe in 1958. There, the Workers attached greatimportance to the words &quot; full employment&quot; being mentioned. (They are also mentioned in the Convention of the European Free Trade Association.) Theobligations of paragraph 2 in relation to foreign workers should be interpretedwith reference to the restrictions permitted by paragraph 18 of Part I and by article 31.Article 2. The right to just conditions6. Article 33 allows the obligations of this Article, to be assumed on the basisof collective agreements covering the great majority of the workers concerned. Wecannot accept paragraph 1 as it anticipates the course of collective bargaining whichis traditionally a matter left to Employers and-Workers in the United Kingdom.Paragraphs 2, 3 and 5 are acceptable to us under the terms of Article 33. The case for accepting paragraph 4 rests on the terms of section 60 of the Factories Act, 1937,and the limitations on hours of employment in coal mines.CONFIDENTIAL59775 B
CONFIDENTIAL\Article 3. The right to safe and healthy conditions7. This Article should present no difficulty for the United Kingdom. Factoryemployment, agriculture, mines and quarries are among the employments for whichsafety and health regulations have been issued. There are measures of supervision and we would no doubt consult, as appropriate, employers and workersorganisations on the matters in paragraph 3. The Article implies no obligation toissue safety and health regulations for all spheres of employment.Article 4. The right to a fair remuneration8. The main point to notice about this Article is that in the first fourparagraphs Governments are required to do no more than &quot; recognise the right&quot;.This we can do for three of the paragraphs but not for paragraph 3 on the rightto Equal Pay. This is because there is no Equal Pay among the Governments ownindustrial employees or among the domestic grades of hospital staff in the national health Service. Acceptance of this paragraph could be regarded as morallycommitting the Government to do something about unequal pay in those spheresat least. Our final attitude on paragraph 5, deductions from wages, must await the outcome of the recent report of the Karmel Committee on the Truck Acts onthis subject. Paragraphs 4 and 5 are qualified by notes of interpretation in theAppendix to the Charter.Article 5. The right to organise9. This Article, one of the &quot; compulsory &quot; Articles, is acceptable to us. Itswording is similar to that of Articles 8(2) and 9(1) of . International LabourConvention No. 87 which we have ratified. The last two sentences of the Articlemake reservations on the armed forces and police. Article 31 would give sufficientcover for these exceptions, but the Social Committee decided to retain them in theArticle 5 both because exceptions for the armed forces and police are common toall member countries, and to avoid possible confusion in any comparisons with international Labour Organisation Convention No. 87 where similar reservationsare made.Article 6. The right to bargain collectively10. This Article is also one of the &quot; compulsory &quot; Articles and is acceptable to us. Paragraph 4, with its recognition of the right to strike, gave rise to considerable discussion. The wording from &quot; including&quot; to the end of the paragraph was inserted at the Tripartite Conference after a strong plea from theWorkers that there should be an explicit reference to this right in a Charter meantfor the free countries of Europe. The Charter will be the first internationalinstrument adopted to recognise this right. It is not, however, an unqualified right(&quot; conflicts of interest&quot;, &quot; subject to obligations arising out of collective agreements &quot;); and Article 31 allows Governments to impose limitations including,as made explicit by the note in the Appendix to the Charter, the possibility ofregulating the exercise of the right by law. Our own acceptance of the text rests on the exceptions allowed by Article 31: we have, for example, restrictions on theright to strike of workers in gas and electricity undertakings. Such restrictionscould be justified as being &quot; prescribed by law ... for the protection of publicinterest, &amp;c, ...&quot; (Article 31). By accepting the paragraph we are called upononly to recognise the right concerned: there would, for example, be no obligation on the Government to declare illegal strikes called in contravention of the termsof collective agreements.Article 7. The right of children and young persons to protection11. Paragraphs 1, 4 and 7 of this Article are unacceptable to the UnitedKingdom; paragraph 6 is acceptable through the terms of Article 33; paragraph 8with the interpretation in the Appendix to the Charter; and paragraph 10 with an agreed interpretation that special protective measures were needed only wherephysical and moral dangers were evident and of a sufficiently general nature to warrant action. The remainder of the paragraphs are acceptable as drafted.Article 8. The right of employed women to protection12. Paragraph 1 is acceptable; paragraphs 2 and 3 are unacceptable in theabsence of relevant legislation; paragraph 4 is acceptable. This last paragraphextends to women in general and not just expectant or nursing mothers as withthe other paragraphs.
Article 9. The right to vocational guidance13. This Article is acceptable. Its obligations &quot;... to provide orpromote ... &quot; are qualified by the term &quot; as necessary &quot; thus leaving a widediscretion to the Contracting Party.Article 10. The right to vocational training14. This Article is acceptable as drafted. The phrase &quot; by appropriate measures such as &quot; in paragraph 4 means that the measures suggested are examples of what might be done, where appropriate, to encourage the full utilisation of facilities. There is no obligation to use those measures necessarily. The wholeArticle comes within the scope of Article 33, but our acceptance does not turnon this.Article 11. The right to protection of health15. This Article raises no problems for the United Kingdom, and is fullyacceptable.Article 12. The right to social security16. This is one of the &quot;compulsory&quot; Articles and is not, as a whole,acceptable to the Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance. Paragraph 1establishes a general principle and is acceptable. As to paragraph 2, the Ministerof Pensions and National Insurance feels that, although we have ratifiedInternational Labour Organisation Convention No. 102, it is not desirable that weshould further tie ourselves to it through this Charter. Paragraph 3 is regardedas embarrassing in that it might be quoted in support of claims for higher benefitrates or other improvements or against any proposals there might be in the future for some restriction in the scope of our social security provisions. Paragraph 4 isalso not acceptable to the Minister of Pensions because it appears to create an obligation to make an agreement with any other country which ratifies the Charter.Article 13.-The right to social and medical assistance17. This is also one of the &quot;compulsory&quot; Articles. It is acceptable to theUnited Kingdom. Possible marginal difficulties were foreseen here and there byNorthern Ireland in relation to aliens, but the terms of Article 31 (prescribed by law in the public interest) were considered to allow the flexibility needed. Thegeneral position of aliens is defined in paragraph 4. There, the term &quot; inaccordance with their obligations &quot; was inserted because the European convention on Social and Medical Assistance may be ratified with reservations. We have ratified this Convention with a reservation on assistance to persons refusingrepatriation (to cover Northern Ireland&apos;s residence conditions).Articles 14-1718. These Articles, cast in rather general terms, are largely concerned withsocial welfare matters. They are acceptable to us, and no special difficulties arise.Article 16 on the right of the family to social and economic protection is one of the&quot; compulsory &quot; Articles. It was included largely to placate a social welfare lobbyinside and outside the Governmental Social Committee. The phrase &quot; by suchmeans as &quot; in Article 16 is understood to mean that the provisions following are onlyexamples of what might be done.Article 18. The right to engage in a gainful occupation in other member countries19.  This Article is acceptable given one or two interpretations:(a) The note in the Appendix to the Charter stating that the paragraph 1 isnot concerned with the question of entry into a country (but withemployment regulations).(b) The interpretations of paragraphs 2 and 3 endorsed by the Committee ofMinisters to the effect that there is no obligation to &quot; simplify &quot; or&quot; liberalise &quot; where existing formalities or regulations are already simpleor liberal, and that the undertaking in respect of &quot; other charges &quot; doesnot preclude nominal charges to meet direct administrative costs.(c) Reference to Article 31 (Restrictions) to justify reserving certain occupationsto one&apos;s own nationals or making them subject to conditions in the case
Part III of the Charter (Article 20)22. This Article is mainly concerned with the minimum requirements for ratification. Contracting Parties must accept Part I as a declaration of their aims in the social field, and a majority of the provisions of Part II as specified inArticle 20. Their choice of Articles must include five out of seven stated Articles(1, 5, 6, 12, 13, 16 and 19) these are the so-called &quot; compulsory&quot; Articles.Obligations may be assumed on the basis of State law and practice or, in certain cases, on the basis of collective agreements applying &quot; to the great majority of theworkers concerned &quot;. (See Article 33.) At one time there was pressure to makethe whole of Part II compulsorily acceptable either at once or in stages. Thepresent formula, widely acceptable, is the result of long discussions andcompromises.23. Paragraph 3 allows Contracting Parties to accept further obligationsbeyond the minimum at a later date. Paragraph 5 was hardly worth insertion in its present form but represents the remnant of rather more complex proposals on inspection. It was felt that to cast it as a separate Article would draw undueattention to its poverty.Part IV of the Charter (Articles 21 to 29)24. This part covers the supervision of obligations and is acceptable to theUnited Kingdom. Biennial reports by Governments of provisions accepted inPart II (Article 21) will be examined first by a Committee of Experts (Article 24)and then by a Sub-Committee of the Governmental Social Committee representingratifying countries (Article 27). The Consultative Assembly (Parliamentarians)will receive the conclusions of the Committee of Experts for comment (Article 28),and finally the Committee of Ministers may make any necessary recommendations to Contracting Parties (Article 29). A similar procedure for reports on provisionsof Part II not accepted by a Contracting Party will be followed &quot; at appropriateintervals as requested, by the Committee of Ministers &quot; (Article 22).25. The Charter also gives non-governmental bodies a role in the implementation procedure. Contracting Parties are obliged to send copies of their reports to certain national organisations of employers and trade unions and to forward any comments on those reports&apos; to the Council of Europe if so requested by those bodies (Article 23). The International Labour Organisation will be invitedto attend the Committee of Experts in a consultative capacity (Article 26); anda limited number of observers from international employer and trade unionorganisations and international voluntary bodies in the social field will be invitedto the Governmental Sub-Committee (Article 27).of aliens. This interpretation was made explicit in relation to theexercise of public functions and occupations connected with national security and defence.The right of the Foreign Secretary in certain circumstances to withhold passportsunder the Royal Prerogative is consistent with paragraph 4 in that: (a) the paragraph is concerned only with the recognition of a right and not its application;(b) the sorts of circumstances in which the Prerogative is exercised would undoubtedly be covered by Article 31 (prescribed by law in the public interest).Article 19. The right of migrant workers and their families20. This &quot; compulsory &quot; Article is acceptable subject to the interpretation inthe Appendix to the Charter defining &quot; family of a foreign worker &quot; as &quot; at leasthis wife and dependent children under the age of 21 years &quot;. Italian agreement to this interpretation was obtained only on the understanding that governments would be willing to give sympathetic consideration to deserving cases in (other)categories.21. By a note in the Appendix to the Charter the terms of Articles 1 to 17are to be interpreted in the light of Articles 18 and 19. This has no practical effect for the United Kingdom although one or two other countries purported to see init (via Article 19 (4)) authority to give foreigners unequal treatment if necessary on those matters in Articles 1 to 17 not mentioned in Article 19 (4).
September 1961.59775cPart V of the Charter (Articles 30 to 38)26. This part contains various general provisions and final clauses all of whichare acceptable to the United Kingdom. The most important is Article 31 whichallows Contracting Parties to impose restrictions on their obligations under Parts Iand II for various reasons (e.g,, public interest, national security) provided that therestrictions are &quot;prescribed by law&quot;. Law is understood to include statutory regulations and constitutional prerogatives. The provisions of Parts I and II dothemselves mention some restrictions, but only where they are of the first importanceor are generally found in the Western European countries. Other restrictions,perhaps particular to one or two countries, are to be justified under Article 31. this approach was deliberately adopted both to present as positive a text as possible(compare the draft United Nations Covenants on Human Rights) and to give room for restrictions which might properly be needed from time to time in the future:some flexibility is needed in the field of social rights with their frequently changingcontext.27. Other Articles of Part V cover such matters as derogations in time of war or public emergency (Article 30); implementation of certain provisions by collective agreements (Article 33); amendments to the Charter (Article 36); and denunciation of the Charter or of any of the substantive clauses of Part II (Article 37). Thereis also a useful territorial application clause (Article 34) whereby obligations towards non-metropolitan territories are on a &quot; contracting-in &quot; basis.28.   The Charter will enter into force after the fifth ratification (Article 35).
6CONFIDENTIAL(ANNEX BEUROPEAN SOCIAL CHARTERA = Acceptable;   U = Unacceptable;   D -- Doubtful.C = Article included in the &quot; compulsory group &quot; (five out of seven to be accepted).* = Within the tenns of Article 33.The following table indicates how far the provisions of Part II of the Charter1seem acceptable to the United Kingdom. Part I of the Charter is fully acceptable:Right to work C(1) A(2) A(3) A(4) ARight to just conditions *(1) U(2) A(3) A(4) A(5) A3. Right to safe and healthyconditions Right  to fair  remunera-tion (1) A(2) A(3) U(4) A(5) D5.  Right to organise-A6.  Right  to bargain collec-tively C(1) A(2) A(3) A(4) A7.  Right of children and youngpersons to protection (1) U(2) A(3) A(4) U*(5) ARight of employed women to protection (1) A.(2) U(3) U(4) ARight to vocational guidance-A10. Right to vocational train-ing-*(1) A(2) A(3) A(4) A11.  Right   to protection   ofhealth (1) A(2) A(3) A12.13.Right  to  social  security-C(1) A(2) U(3) U(4) URight to social and medicalassistance C15.  Right of the disabled-(1) A(2) A16.  Right of the family CA17.  Right   of   mothers   andchildren A18.  Right to engage in employ-ment in other countries (1) A(2) A(3) A(4) A19. Right of migrant workers to protection and assistance- C(1) A(2) A(3) A(4) A(5) A(6) A(7) A(8) A(9) A(10) AParagraphs   Articles(1)(2)(3)(4)AAAAAUD(6) A*(7) U*(8) A(9) A(10) ATotal59101701451914.Right to benefit from social welfare services (1) A(2) ASeptember 1961.

</content>
</cab>
