<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/107/0 images: 204-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1961C. (61) 184 Copy No.   3 521st November, 1961CABINETBERLINMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs my colleagues will be aware that the further probes which it was hoped wouldtake place in Moscow following up the conversations with the Soviet ForeignMinister, Mr. Gromyko, in the United States and in London have not materialised.There are a number of reasons for this; in the first place the chance of fruitfulconversations in Moscow was prejudiced by the incidents on the sector boundaryin Berlin; a second cause was President Kennedy&apos;s reluctance to get involved in discussions of substance with the Russians before a German Government hadbeen formed which could engage its responsibility and, finally, there was a reductionof pressure by the Russians.2. It seems clear that the idea of &quot; probing &quot; without getting into substanceis now depasse. In a manner of speaking the German Ambassador in Moscow,Dr. Kroll, has already carried out the probe which we had in mind. He suggested,apparently on his own initiative, a formula which involved, amongst other things,a Four-Power agreement covering the freedom and viability of West Berlin, access to it and the presence of Western troops there as a prerequisite to an agreement on negotiations for a German peace treaty and related questions and resumptionof negotiations on disarmament. There was nothing really new in this, but it had never been put to the Russians in such a concrete form or in a way which offeredscope for wider ranging discussions if an arrangement could be reached over Berlin.Mr. Khrushchev&apos;s reaction was that these proposals were workmanlike and he agreed to them in principle. He also made it fairly clear that, though he wantsnegotiations, he is ready to wait a reasonable time for the Western position to be cleared.3. This gives us more time, but it also means that when the talks with theRussians eventually take place, Mr. Khrushchev will expect to get straight intoquestions of substance. The conclusion is, therefore, that we must try to reach agreement with our Allies on a detailed negotiating position as soon as we can.4. A good deal of work has already been done on this question, but mostlyof a preliminary nature. The Ambassadorial Group in Washington have been working for several weeks on a paper, largely of German origin, which sets outthe different points likely to arise in negotiations with the Russians. This paperdefines what negotiations should achieve, what is negotiable and what is not, andalso sets out the margin for negotiations. The paper will in due course be supplemented by a paper on tactics and it is intended that both shall serve asguidance in further talks with the Soviets and in eventual negotiations. The textis annexed to this paper so that my colleagues may be aware of the issues aroundwhich arguments are likely to turn. It has not yet been approved by Governments,though it is largely in line with our views and those of the Americans. The attitudeof the German and French Governments towards it is not yet known.5. In general, the sensitive points for the Germans on which the russians are likely to press very hard are:(a) acceptance of the existence and authority of the Deutsche DemokratischeRepublik;(b) the political relationship between West Berlin and the Federal Republic;60009THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
t(c) recognition of the Oder-Neisse line;(d) limitation of nuclear weapons for Germany.In the discussions in the Ambassadorial Group the Germans have shown themselvesaware of the need for increased practical dealings with the East Germans on thepart of the Western Powers as well as of themselves. We have brought home to tthem the need for some form of interim action by the Western Powers overGeimany&apos;s eastern frontier, and I am hopeful that some acceptable formula canbe worked out to cover these two points. On the other hand they claim thatBerlin is constitutionally a part of the Federal Republic and it will be very difficultto get them to agree to any attenuation of existing links. This is a matter onwhich the Russians feel very strongly and we shall have to apply pressure in orderto make the Germans give up some of the more obvious political links, such asmeetings of the Federal German Parliament in Berlin. Whether we shall get them, to go far enough to satisfy the Russians is another matter. As regards thequestion of limitation of nuclear weapons, we think that the Germans couldreaffirm their intention, which is already enshrined in the Western european union Treaty, not to manufacture atomic, bacteriological and chemical weapons.It might also be possible for the Americans and ourselves to declare our intentionnot to transfer control over nuclear components of weapon systems to third Powersnot possessing them. The Germans might by separate declaration comply witha United Nations resolution whereby non-nuclear Powers disclaim their intentionto claim control over nuclear warheads. The Germans regard these ideas withsuspicion since they fear they might help the Russians to achieve their object of imposing an inferior status on the Federal Republic and weakening Germanyand the West militarily; but I do not despair of getting the Germans to be reasonableon this point, provided that the Russians do not pitch their demands unreasonablyhigh.6. All these ideas will be discussed between President Kennedy and Dr.Adenauer who is at present in Washington. The Presidents main purpose willbe to discover from Dr. Adenauer whether the basis of the Western position for possible negotiations with the Russians is acceptable to the Germans. If so, thenext problem will be to persuade General de Gaulle to negotiate and to accept this basis for negotiations. Much therefore depends on the result of the Presidentsmeeting with Dr. Adenauer and also of the meeting which the Prime minister is to hold with General de Gaulle later this week.7. General de Gaulle has a rooted opposition to negotiating with the Russiansso long as they refuse to take practical measures to reduce international tensionwhich they themselves have created. It may be therefore that he will oppose Frenchparticipation in any discussions with the Russians, regardless of Dr. Adenauer&apos;attitude. He may stick to the view that we should simply stand pat and await furtherRussian moves. If so, we must try to convince him that the Berlin situation cannotbe allowed to drift or deteriorate. Since 13th August it has changed radically forthe worse. West Berlin has now become a liability to the West and it is positivelynecessary to try to improve it. If nothing is done there is a grave danger that the life of the city will wither away under our eyes. To some extent this is happeningalready, but the trend will be aggravated if the Western Powers remain inactive. Inthese circumstances Mr. Khrushchev cannot be expected to come forward with proposals, as General de Gaulle apparently thinks he should. It is therefore a western interest to demand negotiations for the purpose of improving the situationin Berlin by agreement. To demand negotiations on this basis is quite a different matter from acceding to pressure for negotiation because of threats to alliedcommunications with West Berlin. It would enable us, incidentally, to put forwardour own ideas as to the sort of arrangement we should wish to see enforced forBerlin as an independent German city protected by allied forces, enjoying freecommunications with the outside world and living a life of its own.8. If General de Gaulle or Dr. Adenauer agree to negotiations, our aim mustbe to finalise the Western negotiating position without delay. If not, a WesternFour-Power meeting will have to be held to resolve our differences.H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,20ih November, 1961.
ANNEX a paper ON THE WESTERN NEGOTIATING POSITION UNDERDISCUSSION IN THE AMBASSADORIAL GROUP in washington(Draft as at November 1L\)This paper is intended to define:what negotiations should achieve;what is nonnegotiable;    and the margin for negotiations.This paper will be followed by a paper on tactics, and bothare intended to serve as guidance in further contacts with the soviets and in eventual negotiations.Ac      SUBSTANTIVE QUESTIONSI.What Negotiations Should achieve the aim of negotiations should be to achieve positive resultswith regard to:-1.   maintenance of Western rights concerning Berlin- presence of forces and free access for military personnel and civilians;2.    improvement of access facilities- preferably by international highway or, at least,their maintenance on the same basis as at present;and3o    assurance of West Berlin&apos;s freedom and viability- including the Berliners1 rights to preserve freedomof choice as to their general way of life and to preserve their ties with the Federal Republic.(a/The scope of Western concessions must be determined by the degree of Soviet preparedness to give something - particularly with regard to the future stability of the Berlin situation./II.(a)   The German delegation desires a concerted interpretation of West Berlin&apos;s present legal situation on the assumptionthat it is considered to form part of the Federal Republic,but with full rights of a &quot;Land&quot; suspended hy virtue ofoccupation law.
(a) We could accept the view that an explicit confirmation ofthese rights is not necessary unless doubts arise as totheir validity, owing to given circumstances.    See also paragraph III 3 a.(b) The Western Powers could not accept a substantial reductionin the level of their forces in Berlin, as the Soviets arelikely to demand.    They could, however, consider making adeclaration to the effect that they would:1)    freeze their forces at present levels;2)    make token reductions in the size of their forces;3)    from time to time, examine the possibility of reducing their forces if developments permit.(c) a contingent of U.N. troops[might be acceptable in addition     (particularly if therewere some U0N. institutions housed in the city) on theunderstanding that their presence will be symbolic and.wdllnot limit the powers cf the Western garrisons].[is not acceptable, whether rex)lacirig Western troops or as anadditional contingent;    same position as to neutral troopswithout a U.N. mandate.    (German Delegation).The foilowing are points relating specifically to Berlinon which, there can he no compromise:(a)1,    the unchanged source of Western rights;    v &apos;2.    protection of West Berlin by forces of the three powers Cb)(c)a Soviet contingent in West Berlin is definitelyunacceptable;3*    Freedom of access to the outside world at least asgood as it now isj    and1+.   West Berlin&apos;s relationship with the West, and with theFederal Republic in particular, at least to remain ingeneral as at present.The following points are formally agreed Western policyrelating to Germany as a whole on which there can be no compromise&amp;lo   Reunification on the basis of self-determination remains the aim of the Western Powers.    The right of the Germanpeople to self-determination must be asserted.   A Sovietacknowledgement of the right to self-determination would greatly help toward a modus Vivendi.    The western governments in any case must include in anything theysign a formula which keeps the door open.2.    Recognition of the &quot;GoDoR.&quot; remains unacceptable./3.11 - 194
3.    The final determination of the boundaries of Germany      /must await a peace settlement for the whole of Germany.^&apos;The question of European security should be dealt with only inthe context of a wider German settlement [ or in connexion withdisarmament. ]^)III.The Margin for Negotiations1.    The essential objective of an &quot;understanding&quot; preceding the conclusion, of a separate treaty between the Soviet Union andthe &quot;GoD.Ro&quot; would be a practical arrangement on access afterthe entering into force of the treaty.      They should try to reach an agreement limited to access to West Berlin, but see paragraphk below.   No understanding is possible unless the Soviets givea guarantee that in practice free access to West Berlin for Alliedpersonnel [as well as for Germans](c) will remain   as it is now or be improved after a peace treaty.In order to reach an agreement in accordance with Section I,we could consider:a)    An i?.vberriational autobahnWe might propose a corridor exempt from East Germanjurisdiction.(i) As a starting position a &quot;free corridor&quot;, under the exclusive control of this three Western Powers,might be proposed.(ii) Secondly, there might be proposed an InternationalAccess Authority for Berlin which should, withoutexercising any sovereign right   over the territory of the Federal Republic, the &quot;G.D.E.11 authorities,or the Government of West Berlin, and ?/hile payingrent for use of facilities in the territory of these authorities, keep the Helmstedt-West Berlin highwayopen to traffic and in good repair, and ensure thatno charges are levied on through traffic using thishighway except by the Authority and operate the berlin Air Safety Centre and any facility in west berlin, the operation of which is essential tosafe travel in the Berlin air corridors./(iii)(a) See III 1 c below.(b) An exception from this principle can be envisaged withrespect to unilateral declarations of NATO and the warsaw pact Organisation concerning non-aggression and renunciation of force [and with respect to production of ABC weapons and transfer of nuolear warheads].    See also paragraph IIIk d.(c) Unbraclceted language does not cover free access by Germans.The position to be taken on this point remains to -beconsidered, particularly with relation to.free anduncontrolled passage by air.
(iii) In both cases it has to be decided- whether East German traffic should be completelyexcluded from this autobahn (e.g0 by fencing offthe autobahn from East German territory) orwhether mixed traffic might be acceptable;- whether the existing autobahn from Helmstedt could he used or whether a new autobahn would have to be constructed which would exclusively serve thepurpose of chanelling the free traffic to and from berlin;- whether the autobahn would have to be enlarged (e.g.to eight lanes) or to be supplemented by a railroador monorail and certain auxiliary installations(pipelines, powerlines, telephone cables etc.).-(iv) In any case, it would he desirable to preservein addition to the international autobahn, theother existing access routes for the use of Germancivil traffic and under controls as presently appliedto this traffic(v)     Consideration could he given to a possible united nations role in connexion with improvement of accessprovided there was Otherwise some UoN0 presence inBerlinsb)   j^Q-S^bili^ty^j/ith respect to access proceduresThere can be no direct negotiation with the &quot;GoD.Ro&quot; on allied access rights,      [Provided this principle is maintained,there can be flexibility in dealing with the appropriate EastGermans in the practical exercise of these rights.][in certain circumstances, representatives at the technicallevel of the &quot;G^DtR.&quot;, and of the Federal Republic acting on&quot;behalf of the Three Powers could make arrangements for procedures and modalities for the exercise of Allied rightScThe Three Western Powers could state that their experts wouldbe prepared to deal on a non-political level with East Germanson practical arrangements* ]Technical aspects of access (railroad schedules, autobahn feeetc.) can be handled on the same working level between theFederal Republic and the &quot;GoD.Ro&quot; as now.We can go as far as, but no further than, the formula in existing contingency plans for acquiescence in East Germanimplementation of existing autobahn and rail procedures.    Thiswould hold true both in direct discussions with the Soviets [orEast Germans] and in unilateral statements (&quot;Solution C&quot;)c.      Certain amount of acquiescence in status quoThe Western Powers could consider making it known to the soviets that they would confine themselves to protesting againstthe conclusion of the separate peace treaty as a violation of former agreements and to labelling the treaty void as far asstates which do not recognise the &quot;G.D.R.&quot; are concernedo/TheSiiCKET
The undertaking of the Federal Republic, &quot;never to have recourse to force to achieve the reunification of germany or the modification of the present boundaries of the federal republic&quot; (included in the Paris Treaties of 195^!-) can berepeatedo   This undertaking can be repeated vis-a-vis theSoviet Union [and guaranteed by the three Western Powers.]If necessary, the undertaking could be broadened in orderto cover the Cder-Neisse lineo      [The three Western governments in their formula about reunification (see Section II) couldspecify that Germany should be reunified within the existingfrontierso    They could also make a statement that when germany was reunified and the time for a peace settlement had come, theOder-l\Feisse line would then, in their view., be the eastern frontier of Germany,]Unilateral non-aggression declarations of NATO and the warsaw Fact Organisation would be acceptable (a formal treaty would he excluded)s^     Formula to satisfy Soviet request for respect of &quot;GDR&apos;if necessary, the understanding could embody a formula,according to which the Western Powers would &quot;respect the rules and regulations of the authorities Yirhich exercise functions inthat area.&quot;(a)Other formulas under consideration:[&quot;respect the rules and regulations of the authoritiesin the G.D.R.11-][&quot;respect the functions of the GoD.Ro authorities&quot;][Jrespect the authority of the Government in East Germany&quot;][&quot;respect the responsibilities of the authorities in east germany&quot; ]2a     An all-Berlin proposal might be put forward in the firstinstance including removal of the wall and free circulation inthe whole of 3erlin.      This might also provide for the establish-ment of certain international institutions in Berlin3*     In connexion with the status and the factual situation of west Berlin:a.?    The status should last until reunification.   Alternativelynothing would be said about duration.,b. The impression that West Berlin is being transformedinto a &quot;free city&quot; in the sense of the Soviet demands must be avoided.c. Establishment of international institutions wouldnot be excluded.    The presence of the European Office of the U.N.or of specialised U.N. agencies in West Berlin can be accepted and might be advantageous.sovereigntyj/d.(a)    This will require description^
d.    No limitation or control of activities in West Berlinnot applying equally in East Berlin would be acceptable,,   no agreement which would give any excuse for Soviet or &quot;GDR&quot;intervention in, or limit essential freedoms in, West Berlinwould be acceptable..    (Only to be used if the Soviets raise thisquestion.,)e*    There should be no Soviet guarantee for West Berlin&apos;sfreedom and viability which would provide them or the EastGermans with any basi    to interfere.     &quot;We should avoid in an understanding any language which might give the Soviet Union orthe East Germans an obvious pretext for intervention. It wouldbe desirable to get a Soviet pledge not to interfere and. not to let the &quot;GBR&quot; interfere.U. Should the Soviets insist on broadening the scope of negotiations, other questions will have to be considered.a.    A proposal for plebiscite in the whole of Germany,preferably put forward near the beginning of East-West negotiation;;b-*    A. request to reestablish the principle of freedom of movement in Germany.Co    The Federal Governments proposal concerning theestablishment of three technical commissions.[d. Large-scale measures against surprise attack, forinstance the creation of an inspection zone reaching from the atlantic to the Urals.    However, Soviet proposals concerningzones with special military status (especially zones free of atomic weapons) should be rejected.J[e.   Nontransfer of atomic weapons and rockets:[The Federal Government is opposed to any such agreement between the United States, the UnitedKingdom and the U.S,S.R0][British suggested response:We could not agree to include limitations on nuclear .and rocket weapons in the &quot;understanding&quot; because of the implication that this might give the Soviets an excuse for intervention.   But the Federal Government mightissue a new declaration reaffirming its renunciation of the manufacture of nuclear, biological, and chemicalweapons.    Some East European governments might alsorenounce the production of these weapons.    The UnitedStates, United Kingdom, and Soviet Governments mightissue declarations affirming their intention not to relinquish control of nuclear weapons to governmentsnot already possessing such weapons.]

</content>
</cab>
