<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/107/0 images: 279-281</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1961C. (61) 198 Copy No.      5 229th November, 1961CABINETFINANCING OF MEAT RESEARCH   .Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council and Minister for ScienceProposals to establish a meat research centre have been under consideration for over three years. Agreement in principle was reached a year ago but there remains a difference of opinion on how additional research should be financed,which discussions in the Home Affairs Committee, and directly between theMinisters concerned, have failed to resolve. The Chief Secretary to the treasury and the Agriculture Ministers have discussed this matter. As we were unableto agree it was decided that I should set out the main arguments on each side and invite our colleagues to decide between them.2. The capital cost of the new centre was estimated in 1958 to be about 360,000 with annual running costs building up over five years to about  100,000.(No doubt the present cost would be appreciably greater.) It will in any case benecessary to rehouse the existing meat research activities at Cambridge when the lease expires in 1966.  This might involve capital expenditure of up to  250,000.3. There is agreement that an expansion of meat research would be desirable.The point at issue is whether this expansion should be made conditional on a financial contribution by the meat trade. The idea of obtaining voluntary contributions from the various interests in the meat trade has been examined anddiscarded as impracticable. Some form of compulsory levy is therefore unavoidableif any trade contribution is to be obtained.Agriculture Ministers&apos; View4. The Ministers of Agriculture oppose the collection of a contribution fromthe trade for the following reasons:(a) The only existing legislation under which a levy could be collected is theIndustrial Organisation and Development Act, 1947. This requiresconsultation with the interests affected before an Order is made, andalso specifies that the charge is divided among the different classes of undertaking in the industry in accordance with a &quot; fair principle &quot;.(b) The only methods that have been suggested for collecting so small a levyare deduction from deficiency payments under the Fatstock GuaranteeScheme, and the imposition of a levy at slaughterhouses. Neithermethod could be held to constitute a &quot; fair principle &quot;; the formerwould divide the cost between the farmer and the first purchaser (inmost cases the wholesaler) leaving out processors and retailers; thelatter would fall in the first place on the occupier of the slaughterhouseor the person presenting the animal for slaughter, either of whommight not be the owner of the animal at all, so that there would be aseparate operation to recover the levy from one or more other personsif the &quot; fair principle &quot; was to be observed.60036THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
View of the Minister for Science6. I must record the view of the Agricultural Research Council, which isdistinct from my own. They point out that much fundamental research on food(e.g., fish, milk, fruit and vegetables) is financed by the Government without a contribution from the trade. They are also opposed to a levy as they fear thatsectional interests in the trade, if major contributors to the cost of research, willexert pressure to influence the programme that might be difficult to resist. their main concern, however, is over the delay that has resulted from the failure to reach a decision on the financial issue; this delay is not only giving rise to increasingplanning and administrative difficulties but, more serious, it is leading to a loss ofconfidence in the future among the scientists concerned.7. For my part, I fully share the CounciFs anxiety about delay, without whollyendorsing their view, as expressed above, on the general issue. My main concernis to see that the proposals for a meat research centre should be put into effect assoon as possible, however they are financed. In general, I am in favour ofcontributions by industry to research, whenever it is- practicable and equitable, andI would be perfectly prepared to accept one here. However I do not think thatthe case for a levy is particularly strong. The research would mainly be fundamentalin character and would probably, after a considerable interval, benefit the consumer(c) There are serious practical objections to using the machinery of the priceguarantee for collecting a levy. Moreover, the days of the FatstockGuarantee Scheme may be numbered since there is little hope of retaining it indefinitely under the Common Market.(d) As regards a levy at slaughterhouses, Ministers have already approved a proposal for the cost of meat inspection, at present borne by localauthorities, to be recovered from the meat trade. This would be doneby imposing a levy at slaughterhouses, to bring in  600,000 a year.Discussions have already opened with the trade who have expressedstrong opposition. Negotiations might become impossible if yet anothercharge was proposed. There would in any case be serious practicaldifficulties in trying to collect the two charges together.Treasury View5. id) The Treasury take the view that, if the increasing amount ofGovernment money now being allocated for scientific research is tobe used to the best effect every effort must be made to secure a contribution from industry wherever practicable. The Department of scientific and Industrial Research (D.S.I.R.) have always operated onthis principle with their Research Associations which are expected tofind a large and in some cases increasing amount of their financial support from industry. This applies as much to the five food research associations as to all other research associations. The Treasuryrecognise the special position of agricultural research largely forhistorical reasons but see no reason why food research, including meatresearch, should not follow the main D.S.I.R. pattern.(b) The Treasury have never been committed to any particular form of levybut only to the principle that a contribution should be obtained. TheTreasury would not object to some method alternative to the use of the1947 Act, such as the taking of explicit powers to make a levy for thispurpose in the Agriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill now in preparation. (The Ministry of Agriculture regard this as impracticable.)(c) The Home Affairs Committee took the view that a levy should be raised to pay for meat inspection whatever decision was reached on the financing of meat research. If, however, it is thought necessary tonegotiate the two levies simultaneously then it seems to the Treasuryunlikely that the difference between  600,000 and  700,000 a year will prove a fatal obstacle.(d) In an effort to avoid delay the Treasury have offered, as an exceptionalmeasure, to provide the whole capital cost initially on the understandingthat half the running costs and capital charges should be recovered fromthe trade.
or taxpayer (by lower prices or subsidies) at least as much as the producer. on present proposals the case can be distinguished from research conducted byD.S.I.R&apos;s. Research Associations. These Associations are set up and run by theindustries concerned, and although D.S.I.R. have a degree of influence over their programmes, the industries have the main responsibility for initiating and controlling the research. The research is of an applied nature and of direct benefitto the industry that supports it. Thus, I would not oppose Treasury ministers in their desire to secure a contribution from the meat trade if it were reasonably practicable to obtain one. The arguments on the other side seem to me to be practical and political in character. It seems clear from the arguments advanced by the Agriculture Ministers that a proposal to impose a levy would run into strong opposition from the farmers and other sections of the meat trade, and that theGovernment could not expect an easy passage for an Order under the industrial organisation and Development Act, 1947 (which requires affirmative resolutions),or for any new legislation which would have to be introduced to permit a researchlevy to be collected by other machinery. The Cabinet will wish to consider how far this could be justified for a saving of  100,000 a year.8. It will in any case be necessary to make an early start on the provisionof new buildings for meat research. In order to have premises ready by 1966when the present lease expires, the Agricultural Research Council must obtain a site early in the new year. If the Cabinet decide that a levy should be imposedthere will inevitably be many months of delay while trade interests are consulted and the necessary Order is made or new legislation prepared and brought intoforce. The Council will therefore need authority to proceed at once with theacquisition of land and the planning of the buildings before these steps are completed.conclusion.   I invite the Cabinet either:(a) to agree that meat research should be wholly financed by the Exchequer,in view of the objections to a trade contribution put forward by the agriculture Ministers; or(b) to decide that the project should be authorised and should proceed, butthat a trade contribution for half the running cost and capital charges should be secured as proposed by the Chief Secretary to the Treasury,if necessary under new legislation at an early date.HAILSHAM.Office&apos;e of the Lord President ofthe Council, S.W.1,28th November, 1961.

</content>
</cab>
