<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/107/0 images: 348-353</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed, for the Cabinet.   December 1961C. (61) 209 Copy No.     628th December, 1961CABINETNUTRITIONAL services memorandum by the Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster general  attach for my colleagues&apos; consideration a summary of the Report of aCommittee of Officials who have been studying an area of expenditure costing theExchequer nearly  100 millions, net, a year: the Nutritional Services, comprisingschool milk, school meals, and welfare milk. I consider that we should give earlyattention to the main conclusions of the Report, bearing in mind the necessity, onthe urgent economic grounds explained in my Memorandum C. (61) 199, for substantial savings arising from policy decisions.2. This is the first time these services have been looked at as a whole by expertssince they took shape in the war and the immediate post-war years.3. The Report, after examining present levels of nutrition and the evidenceindicating what groups are still nutritionally vulnerable, points to the conclusionthat something like half this expenditure could be saved: in other words, it goes to people who do not need. it. To take the example of welfare milk, the familiesreceiving it (some 95 per cent, of those qualified) do not in any way correspond tothe families who might be nutritionally vulnerable. And to take school meals, it isanomalous that while only half the school children in England and Wales (and only one-third in Scotland) take the subsidised school meal, there is no evidenceeither that the majority of these are nutritionally vulnerable, or that those who donot take the meal are nutritionally worse than those who do.4. The Report points out that protection for those most at nutritional riskcould be obtained by charging normal prices for all foods, subject to:(a) retention of free school milk;(b) retention of the present charge for welfare milk to families with four ormore children;(c) retention of the present school meal charge of Is. Od. for families with lessthan, say,  12- 14 a week, depending on the number of children;(d) the existing remissions and reductions for families within the scope ofNational Assistance.This would cost  50 millions, so that nutritional safeguards for those most at riskcould be obtained for approximately half what we are spending on them at present.5. The alternative courses outlined in the Report are a thought-out whole after examination of all the available evidence, but the Report does not make an ad hoccall for economy. The retention of free school milk for all and cheap welfare milk for the larger family would demonstrate the Government^ continued confidence in milk as a food.6. Complete withdrawal of the welfare milk subsidy might, it is estimated,involve a drop in annual consumption of some 60 million gallons. This is 3-75 percent, of total liquid milk consumption. But a concession for larger families, suchas the Committee proposed, would make the reduction in consumption less than this. The loss of income to the Milk Marketing Boards (estimated as  2- 5 millions60099b
a year per 20 million gallons) on the Committee&apos;s proposal would in the current^year have to be made good by the Exchequer at an annual cost of  5- 7 millions!^In later years the arrangements would depend among other things on the outcome of the agricultural price review, and any secondary effects on farm incomes froma lower manufacturing price might have to be taken into account. I recognise thatat the present time Government action reducing the demand for milk will makethe handling of the milk problem at next February^ annual review more difficult.Ji^lvertheless, even the figure of  7 millions (and it should prove to be less, than&quot;this, in view of the continued subsidy for larger families) has to be considered in the context of a saving on the proposal for welfare milk alone of  20 millions;, aproposal which in its turn forms part of a larger whole.7. The Minister of Health believes that the proposed changes in welfare milkarrangements, subject possibly to minor adjustments, could be made withoutadverse nutritional consequences, and considers that they are justifiable on meritsin the context of health finance generally.8. Another possible substantial saving in the social service field referred toin the Treasury paper circulated in June with C. (61) 88 is a concentration of family allowances in favour of the larger family, eliminating the allowance for the two-childfamily and allocating part of the saving to the family with three or more children,which I understand would reduce expenditure on family allowances (estimated at 135 millions for 1962-63) by some  34 millions. I have not yet discussed this withthe Minister of Pensions and National Insurance, but mention it here in case mycolleagues would wish to consider some action on those lines as an alternative.9. A curbing of older forms of social service expenditure is the right way to free resources for the many new tasks in this field (education, housing, hospitals),which we have to tackle. The services referred to in this paper are leading examples of large expenditures which started in very different social conditions from thosewe have to-day, and have continued with little basic change over many years. Asbetween the two, the changes in family allowances would entail early legislation,whereas those in the nutritional services would not. In my judgment we have passed the stage where nutritional services expenditure on the present scale isrequired, and it is here that for my part I think we should seek the substantial savingthat is necessary. If my colleagues agree with this view that  47 millions can be saved under this heading, it may be that the situation will not require us to pursue the question of family allowances at this time. But I see no chance of fulfilling the pledge given by the Chancellor of the Exchequer not to allow the Estimates for1962-63 to show an increase in real terms of more than 2-J per cent, over those for1961-62, without savings of that order from somewhere in this field.H. B.Treasury Chambers, S.W. I,8th December, 1961.
ANNEXCHILD NUTRITIONReport by OfficialsWe have examined, first, the general level of child nutrition now attained. the scientific advisers tell us that great caution is needed in interpreting the available evidence: professional opinion has become less confident in interpretation asknowledge has increased. It can reasonably be said, however, that the evidence of unsatisfactory nutrition among children at present is slight, and that definite evidence points to &quot; watchful concern &quot; only for children in comparatively poorhouseholds (breadwinner income below, say,  12 a week) with 4 or more children.This group constitutes perhaps a little more than 5 per cent, of the total number ofchildren in the country.2. We have considered three services Welfare Milk, School Milk and school meals . The cheap Welfare Milk concession is taken up for about 95 per cent, ofthe children entitled to it (those under 5). In maintained schools in England andWales 93 per cent, of primary and 66 per cent, of secondary school children takethe school milk; in Scotland the figure for all schools is 88 per cent. In both casesthe milk is an important element in children&apos;s nutrition. About one-half of theschool children in maintained schools in England and Wales and one-third of thosein Scotland take School Meals. These are important not only in the nutrition butin the social and dietetic education of those who take them.3.  The cost to the Exchequer of these services is:4. We have sought to consider how best to get value for money from these services. During the last 30 years, over which these services have developed, therehas been a great change in the standard of living throughout the community andthere is no clear evidence that on nutritional grounds it is necessary to retain the mall at their present levels. As a result of our investigations, therefore, we havedevised possible alternative modifications for each service and have tried, for alternative lower levels of aggregate expenditure, to indicate an appropriatecombination of services and the results that might be expected to follow.5.   Before describing these modifications we would stress three points:(i) Our work has assumed the present basis of family allowances.  A changein them would alter our calculations. For example, a change in ratesbenefiting the larger families could mitigate some of the consequences of some of the alternatives we have considered. But we have concentrated our attention upon the nutritional services as such becausethe effects of family allowances on nutritional levels cannot bequantified.(ii) We have assumed that the nutritional concessions at present given forwelfare foods and school meals for families on National Assistance or who are otherwise necessitous will be maintained in all cases. school milk is at present free for all.(iii) If changes are made, we would attach particular importance to the effectivemeasurement of their results. Our impression is that the presentcriteria of adequate nutrition need revision and that too little is known about the distribution of the nutritional benefits of the present servicesand of the possible effects of changes in them.6. In what follows we have worked on the basis that the children who arenutritionally vulnerable are those in low wage-earning families with four or more1961-62  MillionsSchool MealsWelfare MilkSchool Milk5726149760099b 2
children. The information available to us suggests that this is a reasonably saf ^basis on which to work, but in certain circumstances some low wage-earner families with three children (all under five) could come into the vulnerable zone and somight families with average wage incomes and four or more children. The less the expenditure on nutritional services the greater is the risk of enlarging thevulnerable zone. But the available evidence suggests that not even the complete abolition of the services would extend the vulnerable zone beyond the largestlimits indicated above, which include about 20 per cent: of the total number ofchildren. The extent to which nutritional factors still play a part in growth ratesfor children is a matter on which the evidence is inadequate. In the absence of adequate evidence our scientific members consider that some reservation on whetherand how far growth rates might be affected by reduction of the subsidies is required.School Meals &apos;&apos;7. Meals at school, apart from their nutritional importance to those who take them, are designed educationally to play a significant role in fostering goodmanners, social discipline and sound dietetic habits. The average cost per meal,including overheads but excluding capital costs, is 2s. Id. The present charge is Is. In 1960-61, under scales operated by local authorities, 1\ per cent, of thechildren in England and Wales receiving meals (i.e., per cent, of all schoolchildren) and 21 per cent, in Scotland (i.e., nearly 7 per cent, of all school children)received free meals, and some also received them at charges of less than Is.8. For meals we have considered two alternative proposals. The first takes the form of recasting the present subsidy arrangements so as. to concentrate thesubsidy almost entirely on the meals of those children whose families are leastlikely to be able to afford an adequate substitute. The other is a more modestincrease in the charge for all families. We describe them as X. 1 and X.2.X.l.   This would establish a three-tier system of payment as follows:(a) Free provision or charges of less than Is. for the lowest incomegroup, on scales taking account of family size (about 6\ per cent,of families with school children).(b) The present charge of Is. for children in families with incomes of upto  2Jr- 2 10s. higher than would qualify for the free provision-this would apply to, say, another 10 per cent, of families, andwould incorporate an allowance for family size in relation toincome. It would be possible, in Scotland, as an alternative, tohave a graduated charge for those families producing the sameoverall financial result.(c) A charge of 2s. per meal (almost the full cost of the meal at present,including overheads but excluding capital costs) for all other children.This plan is.designed to safeguard the position of the lower income groups, and thecost, though.it would depend to some extent on thoreduction in.numbers receivingmeals, would be of the order of, say,  30 millions, as against the present  57 millions.The remissions could, if thought advisable, be further enlarged at increased cost,which we put at  5-7 millions, to retain the existing Is: charge for children whosedaily travel to school is.provided or subsidised by local authorities. Such children are the clearest case of those who have to have school meals, but the criterionadopted might nevertheless be criticised on the grounds of equity by other classesless easily identified of children who have to take the school meal. The Ministry ofEducation consider that inevitable variations in local practice, and administrative difficulties make such a criterion unsatisfactory. If, however, this proposal, withthe additional concession for children who live at a distance from school, were adopted, it is estimated that the children liable to pay more than the present charge would be a minority of those at present taking meals.X.2.   Provision of meals free and at reduced charges would continue as now&apos;      &apos; and there would be a modest remission in Scotland, as now, for those with more than one child at school. Apart from this the charge wouldbe raised by 6d. to Is. 6d.  This would cost about, say,  40 millions as against the present  57 millions..X.2 would be less favourable to the lower income groups (broadly those next aboveNational Assistance standards) than X.l.  By the same token X.2 would be more
 avourable than X.1 to people in the higher income groups, particularly those withWly one child at school. Although a graduated scale below Is. for families in or near the National Assistance range is worked at present we consider that extensionof the scope of intermediate rates in the context of a charge of Is. 6d. as a concession to families above National Assistance levels would give rise to unduecomplexity.9. In the costing of the above proposals we have not assumed any reductionin the numbers receiving meals. Either proposal would probably result in a markeddecline in the numbers taking the meal and it is not unlikely that the decline under either proposal would be about the same. It might even be less under X.1 (havingregard to the remissions) than under X.2. A reduction in the numbers of mealsserved would result in additional saving on capital account and, provided it wasadequately reflected in reduced overheads (which would not be achievedimmediately) also on current account.Welfare Milk10. The retail cost of milk is 8d. a pint. The present subsidy for pregnantwomen and children under five is 4d. a pint and is virtually all taken up. The costis  26 millions in the year 1961-62. Here we have considered three possibilities.In each of these the present arrangements for free supplies for families at theNational Assistance level would continue and this is taken into account in the revised cost:Y.l. Withdrawal of the subsidy, except for families of four or more children(including as four-child families those with three children and anexpectant mother). The cost would be about  6 millions instead of 26 millions.Y.2. Withdrawal of the subsidy for all except families with three or more children (including families with two children and an expectant mother).The cost would be about  12 millions.Y.3. Reduce the subsidy by 2d. making the price 6d. for all families except the family with four children (or three children and an expectantmother), who would continue to be entitled to milk at the present priceof 4d. a pint.  This would cost about  16 millions.11. Nutritionally some cases of low wage-earning families with three children,all under five, might become at risk if they reduced their milk consumption to thefull extent implied by Y..1. Under the other two proposals the evidence availableto us does not suggest that any families would become vulnerable even if theyreduced their milk consumption to the full extent of the additional money theywould have been called on to pay.12. All these plans would entail more complex rules of entitlement and administration than at present because of the new criterion of family size at some additional cost to Departments, including the National Assistance Board.Reference to family allowance entitlement would cover most, but not all cases,and the Health Departments would have to devise rules to overcome this. On theother hand Y. 1 and Y.2, in that they substantially reduce the numbers of familiesentitled, would, on balance, be cheaper to administer than the present scheme.Y.3, with its greater complexity, would be more expensive to administer than thepresent scheme. Still more complex schemes (e.g., one with three tiers of price)we have felt bound to reject on administrative grounds alone.School Milk13. The alternatives here lie in our view between a charge of 6d. a week for milk at school which would reduce the present cost of  14 millions to  7 millions we describe this as proposal Z. 1: and retaining the present free provision whichwe describe as Z.2. Z.1 would result in some fall in uptake and would raise thequestion of some remission of the charges for the necessitous (as at present for school meals) but this would be troublesome in relation to the amounts involved.The alternative of a cash payment to National Assistance cases would not be satisfactory. The result of Z.1 could, therefore, be some nutritional loss amongthe poorest families.14. If the amount of milk consumed fell as a result of putting into effectproposals of the kind set out above, then there would be an impact on theExchequer in that for every 20 million gallons decline in liquid sales the income
of the--Milk.Marketing Boards would fall by about; 2J millions-.a year and und^the guarantee arrangements most of this loss would have to be made up by tW^Exchequer in the first instance. Unless special provision were made to thecontrary, however, about four-fifths of this annual loss would thereafter be passed on to the Boards. Apart from this, discontinuance or material modification ofthe Welfare Milk and Milk in Schools schemes would be criticised by the milk industry as implying that the Government had changed their view on the valueof milk as a food, and the industry would no doubt argue that this would underminetheir sales campaign.15. As noted in our terms of reference, the powers to provide welfare milk(and the Vitamin Supplements, even at cost prices as at present) expire at the endof 1964. Any of the courses we have proposed would therefore require legislation(presumably in the 1963-64 Session) either to continue the appropriate parts ofthe Emergency Laws (Repeal) Act, 1959 beyond 1964 or replace them with newpowers. The existing charge for welfare milk, and charges for school meals and school milk can be altered by amending orders, supplemented in detail by administrative action. The entry into force of the different adjustments we have discussed, and so the fructification of the savings, would depend mainly on the complexity of the arrangements that had to be made.16. We should, perhaps, refer to the changed situation as regards milk whichmay arise as a result of atmospheric pollution by radio-active substances. Weare advised that the present danger is from radio iodine, and that the most vulnerable age group is 0-12 months. If it becomes necessary, adequate protection for this age group can be obtained by replacement of liquid milk with dried orevaporated milk, of which adequate supplies will be made available. The longer term hazard will be from strontium 90, but on this our present advice is thatthe content in milk should not reach a dangerous level for any age group fromthe bomb tests to date. We therefore consider that our arguments need not beaffected by dangers to the milk supply from the atmosphere.Conclusion17. The difference between the proposals on meals (X.1 and X.2) is about 10 millions if the concession for distance from school is not included in X.l.If it is included X. 1 would still cost about  3 millions less than X.2. The differencebetween the first two proposals on welfare milk (Y.1 and Y.2) is about  6 millions:the third proposal Y.3 would cost about  4 millions more again. The differencebetween the proposals for school milk (Z.1 assuming no remission for necessitouscases and Z.2) is about  7 millions.18. Thus, as against the present  97 millions, it would be possible to have,for  43 millions, a programme (X.1, Y.1 and Z.1) which would go a long distancetowards concentrating the subsidies in favour of the most vulnerable groups.Such a programme could, however, be justified in relation to the families most atnutritional risk only if it could be accompanied by adequate remission arrangementsfor the school milk charge, which would add to the cost and be disproportionatelytroublesome to administer.19. For  70 millions, it would be possible to have X.2, Y.3 and Z.2. Thiswould not be much better for the families most at risk than X.1-Y.1-Z.1. It wouldbe better than X.1-Y.1-Z.1 for families who are in any case well above any possibility of nutritional concern.20. Between  43 millions and  70 millions, there is, of course, a wide range of alternative intermediate possibilities. Of these, X.1 and Y.1, combined withZ.2 (retention of free school milk), would cost  50 millions. This appears to us as practicable, and it would give protection to those most at nutritional risk.On nutritional grounds, a combination of X.1 (charging up to 2s. for school meals)with one or other of proposals Y.2 (which would protect the remaining identifiedarea of nutritional risk the poorer three-child family where all children are underfive) or Y.3 (which would retain some subsidy on welfare milk for all families)would be preferable to a straight Is. 6d. charge for school meals and withdrawalof the welfare milk subsidy for all except four-child families. There are, of course,non-nutritional factors (the educational aspect, of school meals and the impact onthe milk industry) which are not included in a nutritional assessment.December 1961.

</content>
</cab>
