<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/107/0 images: 370-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET348C. (61) 213 COPY NO.  ^11th ,P^cejrnjD^^196lCABINETSCHOOL MEALSMemorandum by the Minister of education the memorandum by the Chief Secretary, Treasury (C. (61) 209)is based on an expert report which has only just been circulated.    It isvaluable to have this subject of child nutrition studied as a whole, but none of us has had time to consider the report.   But since we are being askedto take urgent decisions I think it right to let my colleagues have myimmediate reactions on the political and administrative implications of theproposal made by the Chief Secretary, Treasury.2.      The report infers that the risk is very small, that many children would be under-nourished if the charge were raised to two shillings forsome 85 per cent of all those now taking dinners.3.      This judgment depends on whether the children who now takeschool dinners and would not take them at two shillings would get as gooda meal in other ways.   Some would go home.   We can presume that these will be properly fed.   Others, including those where both  parents are working, would bring sandwiches.   In theory a packed dinner could bedietetically adequate:  but it is unlikely that a good many families wouldprovide a properly balanced lunch.   Others would go to a fish and chipscafe where they would be likely to spend something on the food and oftensomething on the juke box.   This last possibility is already disturbingsome schools where the charge is only Is.   We should have to expect a sharp increase in the fish and  chips alternative, how great we cannot say,but teachers and social workers would make much of their dangers to health  and behaviour of which they already have experience.4.      The school dinner has great educational value besides being agreat convenience for children v/ho cannot easily get home and back atdinner-time.   While most teachers recognise the educational and socialvalue of school meals, the part they have to peform in supervising themeals is one of their most debated grievances.   I am due to discuss  thisgrievance with the teachers&apos; representatives.   If the full cost of the mealwere charged, considerably more children would bring their own food andthis would increase the difficulties of the teachers during the mid-day break.It would turn the school meal into a restaurant service and make those whohave loyally supported it for its educational and social value feel thatthey had been let down by the Government.-1-
5.      The Means Test suggested in the experts&apos; paper would have to be administered by the local education authorities on a demand from the parenteither for exemption or for half rate.   Nealy 3^ million   children from about 2 million f amilie s now take school meals. Of every 100 of these families,it is estimated that between 6 and 7 would continue to qualify for free meals and another 10 for the half rate.    The Means Test would have to be appliedto a number of families in excess of those accepted for a reduction, sincenot all would be found to qualify.   I  this 16-17 per cent of families areto be given remission, some 25 per cent might have t o be subjected tothe means test.   This process would be widely resented both by the families and also by the local education authorities and teachers who wouldbe involved in it.6.      liaising the charge involves shifting the burden from people whohave no children at school to those  who have.   I am by no means sure that this squares with the Tory principle of helping the family as the basic unit in society.7.      The very great majority of the families who would have to pay more if the charge were raised would be wage and salary earners whosesupport for an incomes policy we are about to seek.   I have not had timefully to study the alternatives in the report.   My mind is open on theprinciple but I wonder if the two policies are consistent - the incomes policy and the proposed change in the charge for school meals.D. E.Ministry of Education, W. 1. ,11th December, 1961-2-SEGHET

</content>
</cab>
