<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/13/0 images: 20-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.6(55)								24th January, 1955



									[Enter B.H.

		1.	Coloured Immigrants.



Ll.G.	Osborne is seeking leave on Wed. under 10 min rule to introduce Bill to regulate immigration into U.K. of persons other than citizens of Br. Isles.

		May be useful kite.  But how shd. we vote?



H.C.	Abstain – at this stage.  There may be no division.  If leave is declined it wd. estop Govt. legn.  But that is lesser risk than voting for unknown.



O.P.		Cd. junior Ministers vote as they please?  It may be beaten.



P.M.		They needn’t be whipped to abstain.



J.S.		Tell them to vote for it or abstain : shdn’t be in diff. lobbies.



P.M.		Ministers shd. abstain : no junior Ministers to vote against.





		2.	Formosa.



A.E.	U.S. have moved long way to meet us – over guarantee to Quemoy.

	Plan is now to go to Sec. Council on Wed. or Thurs. – U.K. warning Moscow &amp; Peking in advance.

	We shd. go along with them in this.  Otherwise, outcome will be increased hostilities.  W’drawal fr. Taachens &amp; Quemoy might encourage Chinese to think Formosa can be had for the taking.

	Have seen U.S. &amp; Can. Ambassadors.  Also H. Morrison.

	Draft of tel. to W’ton read to Cabinet.

	N.Z. will raise it in Sec. Council.  U.K. will do utmost to persuade Ch. to come.  If they don’t, we are not committed to do more than consult U.S. on next step.



Sal.	It is for us to warn Moscow &amp; Peking tht. there is real danger of a clash.



Sw.		Doms wd. support this initiative.



H.M.	C.O.S. have prepared note on strategic issues.

	These islands are not essential to defence of Formosa, tho’ useful for shipping control.

	Opposed evacuation of Quemoy wd. be difficult : 5 Divns.





		3.	Export Trade.



A.E.		Cd. we have general discn. on prospects?



R.A.B.	Yes : I will submit memo, with P.T., on external finance &amp; economic outlook.



A.E.		Useful if we cd. have it before P.M. mtg.

								[Enter B-C., H.Watk.



		4.	Japan and G.A.T.T.



W.		Repns. regarding effects on Lancs. of Indian competition : cotton cloth.



H.A.		This is not the sort of cloth U.K. ought to make, in long-term.



K.	What is objn. to admn. of Japan subject to our right to invoke Art. 35 at any time : D. in offl. report.



R.A.B.		Discussed in E.P.C. V. difficult.

	Can’t take v. negative line.  Nor can we go for simple admission.

	I favour middle course suggd. by Econ-Secy. to E.P.C.  Make admission condl. on good behaviour by Japan, in trade practices &amp; commercial treaty.  Is this not easier to defend?  Wd. put max. pressure on Japan.  Wd. avoid action under Art. 19, wh. wd. invite reprisals v. our trade.

	Believe this is least diff. posn. to defend, politically.



P.T.	I rejected that, as worst of all worlds.

	I wd. sooner accept F.O. view &amp; admit J. subject to Art. 19.

	Middle course involves admitting J. in 3 yrs’ time w’out the safeguards.  How cd. we fight Election on that?

	Wiser, on whole, not to admit J.  But if Cab. wish to do so, do it : &amp; defend it as action taken.

	Under middle course no safeguards wd. be obtainable under G.A.T.T. what cd. you then get by a commercial treaty.



Sw.	Also diffies. qua Doms.  Once you say we will admit J., now or in 3 yrs., you must re-orientate tariff policy.  This wd. mean declaring intention to repeal free-entry under Ottawa preferences.  Act.  We are doing much trade under preferences – 90% in A &amp; N.Z.  These are v. gt. political &amp; econ. diffies.

R.A.B. said preserve right to act under Art. 35.  That wd. be all right.  But cd. you, under middle course.



P.T.	Doubt if you cd. get agreemt. on that in G.A.T.T.  You cd. prob. retain Art 19 rights – if you were v. firm with U.S. &amp; Japan.  And you cdn’t act under Art. 19 until sitn. was v. serious.  This course cd. only be justified on over-riding grds of f. policy.



A.E.	My feelings :	a)	J. is in uncertain condn.  Pol. consequences of our takg. lead in opposing her entry mght be v. serious.  Chance of J. lining up, in 3-4 yrs., with China.

		b)	We have said we believe in multi-lateral trade &amp; preaching it to U.S. &amp; others.  U.S. now beginning to move twds.  What we asked them to do.  Firm exclusion of J. wd. look odd, in light of that.

	Therefore favour something on lines of E in officials’ report.



P.T.	Impressed by A.E.’s a) and b).  On long view can’t keep J. out.  But fear pol. dangers of F.  Fixed date before we must admit J., &amp; wdn’t be able to negotiate Art 19 safeguard.

	My 3rd. course is much easier to defend politically in U.K. than middle course.



R.A.B.	Middle course is better fr. pt. of view of general economy. – but not of Lancs. or impending election.



P.T.	Amendment to Art. 19 wd. enable you to impose discriminatory quotas v. Japan.  True, some might use that v. us.  But must pay some price for admittg. J. to multi-lateral trade world.  B/T., on balance, think it safe.



R.A.B.	Under-developed countries wd. think we were going back on our policy.  All this in interests of Lancs.



P.T.	Not Lancs. alone – also light engineering, toys etc., 



H.W.	Many of industries tht. wd. be affected are in developmt. areas.  They wd. be damaged as much as Lancs.



A.E.	Action by us under Art 19. might provoke U.S. to use it v. us.



P.T.	Sw. problem re Ottawa will arise anyway.  Course (C) wd focus attentn. on it.  We wd. move gradually on it. case by case.



Sw.	Suppose we cd. negotiate this with Doms ….



P.T.	You might do it, case by case : arriving at a list of goods.



R.A.B.	Can we m’tain the free entry for Doms?  V. big ques.

	Does P.T.’s (iii) include – a) amendmt of Art. 19

				b) commercial Treaty

				c) 

	A v. tough negotiation.



P.T.	Yes : but we cd. enlist U.S. support, if we say firmly tht. this is our price for admitting J.



Sw.	Fear tht., if we took this course, A. might accept J. in G.A.T.T. but insist on raising tariffs v. her and therefore v. us, to protect her secondary industries.  Both A. &amp; N.Z. wd. then be subject to v. strong U.S. pressure : &amp; they see importance of keeping J. with the West on defence grounds.



H.M.	Are we Free Trade or Protectionist.

	Cd. we take middle course w’out pledging ourselves to admit in 3 yrs.



D.E.	We are in worst posn. to get s’guards fr. J. because binding of our tariffs.  We want to buy time to negotiate that with Doms.  I favour course (iii) if we can get s’guards.  Worth waiting to discuss with Menzies &amp; prs. some others.



Sw.	Cd. carry (iii) if Doms. supported it as well as U.S.  But not unless.



O.P.	Must speak to Menzies before we decide.



A.E.	We may then be late in negotiatg. amendmt. of Art 19 in Geneva.



P.T.	We cd. afford to wait 10 days.



D.S.	What about course (i), with promise to see how we cd. do better.

	Wd. not this be a lever to get concessions out of U.S.



P.M.	Defer decision for 10 days so that we may ascertain view of Menzies &amp; prs. other.  P.M.’s – informally. M’while my disposn. is in favour of course (i) – doubt if more than that is practicable.



Sw.	Cd. we produce memo. for discn. with Menzies.



A.E.	Cd. 3 or 4 of us meet to discuss it further?  Then to report to P.M. wtr we can afford to wait 10 days.  A.E. to convene B/T., RAB, Sw., H.A., W.

						[Enter S.Ll., G.Ll., Att.G.



	5.	Railways.



H.W.	Final Rpt.	i)	criticism of both sides.

			ii)	fair wages in natd. industry is better put – comparable.

			iii)	enquiry : shd. I pursue this with parties on basis of report.  I wd. sooner do that on exploratory basis because importce. of carrying both parties along on this.



P.M.	(iii) wd. be normal procedure.



Sal.	Refces. to economy &amp; efficiency are v. feeble – e.g. “not immediately germane to ques of wages”.

	Shall prob. find men won’t face these problems.  What then?



H.W.	Wasn’t w’in their t. of r.  Hence their caution.  But they have made it clear tht. they think there is much room for improvement.



B.C.	Too wide an enquiry mght stop decentralisation plans wh. are now procdg.

	B.T.C. wd. be willing to have enquiry limited to man-power efficiency.



W.	Removal of redundancy alone won’t work any miracle.  Complete re-organn. is what is needed.  And in process of that you will have best chance of curing redundancy &amp; restrictive practices.  “Punitive” enquiry will only cause friction.



H.W.	Must get Unions to make public promise to co-operate.



W.	But on re-organn. not on redundancy alone.



K.	Para. 74 put it v. well.  “Just claims” have now bn. met.  I wd. have manpower enquiry while iron is hot.  Politically v. necessary to have it.  Don’t wait for modernisation.



R.A.B.	Para. 76 is v. dangerous because of delay.

	Watch public re-actions : then get B.T.C. to start limited enquiry at once.



H.A.	Assocn. of Unions with enquiry is most important point.



D.E.	Shd. it not cover managemt. also?



B.C.	Yes : “use of man-power by B.T.C.” wd. cover both.



W.	Shd. be held in private, if men’s co-opn. is to be secured.



P.M.	When shd. debate be held?

	Surely M.P.’s will need time to consider repts.

	Defer for as long as possible.



B.C.	How do we answer P.Q.’s m’while?  Must soon be able to promise debate.



H.C.	Shall have to say it to-morrow – on re-arrangemt. of business.  But Opposn. may not want it next week.



						    			[Exit Att.G., B.C.

									[B.H., S.Ll. 

									[H.W.





		6.	Parliament : Allowances for Peers.



Sal.		Debate to-morrow on Samuel’s Motion on H/L. reform.

	Wanted to say we wd. soon have to face problem of allowances.  Does R.A.B. think I can say less?



RAB.	Can’t be done before junior Ministers – wh. I wd. like to do but others don’t.



H.C.	What has this to do with junior Ministers?  Nothing.



Sal.	Can I say “at earliest practicable date” vice “at an early date”. – Approved.





	7.	Fog.



D.S.	Want to make statement to-morrow, in order to remove wind from Nabarro’s sails.

	I don’t want to do more than [express approval in principle].



Sal.	You wanted previously to promise legn.



D.S.	W’draw this now.  [] will suffice for to-morrow.

	But Nabarro’s Bill will go thro’, containing 9/10 ths of what is necessary lacking only financial provns.

	I believe tht. on 2nd. Rdg. of that Bill we shd. find it had all-Party support.



Sal.	Cab. shd. know what report recommends.  Radical change in domestic habits to be enforced by Orders imposing smokeless zones.  No coal fires : &amp; pay more for other appliances.



H.C.	Don’t assume it will be so popular.

	Plan is to improve Nabarro’s Bill.  To improve it, money will have to go in.  Are we to establish new principle tht. by such a manoeuvre private Member can force Govt. to propose a charge.



R.A.B.	Ready to make some financial concessions.  But, if there’s no time for Govt. legn., say so.



D.S.	Let me say [] but make no promise of legn.

								[Exit G.Ll.

								[Enter Gammans

	8.	Political Broadcasting in Wales.



H.C.	Must have early consultn. with Oppn.

	This shd. not be allowed



A.E.	Talk to Labour Party.  If they don’t agree, come back to Cabinet.





</content>
</cab>
