<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/13/0 images: 35-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.21(55)							7th March, 1955



		1.	Foreign Affairs : Sir A. Eden’s Mission.

								[Enter B.H.



A.E.	Matters not covered in tels.



	(a) Egypt.  Noticeable concern about econ. plans – as are all M/E. countries.

	Had hoped Nasser wd. be co-operative over Israel.  He wasn’t tough, but said timing wd. need care.  Gaza therefore doesn’t help.

	(b) Pakistan.   M. Ali was v. helpful at Bangkok.  Took our line on all points.

	(c) Bangkok Conference.   No diffies.

	(d) Formosa.   D. was v. worried.  Stump was stupid.  His line was tht. i) Nat. morale was low and (ii) that islands are essential to defence of F. arguments of C.I.G.S. failed to move him on (ii) and (iii) tht. F. was vulnerable to attack.  Next day we saw article (Times) by Adml. Radford saying opposite of (ii) &amp; tht. invasion of F. was impossible.  Shows confusion even w’in. mil. circles in W’ton.

	D. admitted tht. he had sought President’s authy. to bomb m’land of China to check build-up of Comm. forces in islands.

	Shows tht. U.S. naval authies. are quite ready to have war with China now – for now’s the time.  They wd. fight it by air attack on m’land.



P.M.	They wdn’t need our mil. support and haven’t sought it.  For this (viz., islands) they wdn’t get it – tho’ for Formosa they probly. should.



A.E.	(e) Malaya.   Impressed by what I saw.  Hard core of 3.000 or so bandits – unlikely ever to surrender.

	Impressed by our men : but divided organn., since Templer left, is awkward – as is also relationship of Macdonald.  Will consult ALB on this.

	Elections coming.  Inevitable, but some qualms.  They are the only elections being held in S.E.A. – no other country there is sufficiently democratic or stable, outside of India.

	(f) India.   Nehru put himself out to welcome me.  Banquet at Govt. House – incldg. Viceroy’s bodyguard on stairs – &amp; N. proposed Queen’s health at end.  Moving speech on new relns. betwn. Britain &amp; India (b’cast &amp; filmed) – in wh. he said he wished India to preserve all the best of British raj, Parly. Govt. etc., &amp; forget the less happy things.  Local elections : results declared while I was there &amp; Communists lost heavily.  Clear tht. N. wants to work closely with us.

	(g) Baghdad.   Discussed our adherence to Iraq/Turkey Treaty.  Think we cd. work out means of association with it.  They accept our squadrons at Habbanyyah &amp; Shaiba on training basis.  But all hangs on Nuri.  They want our help : may be difficult to get them to pay for it.

	Circulated draft of statement to be made in H/C.  

	Have given much thght to ques what we shd. say on Formosa.  U.K., almost alone, have said nothing.  I cd stop half way down p 5 : but it is difficult to avoid giving any view.  Have done my best, in this, for U.S. viewpoint.  Para (4) is safe if, as we understand, Formosans wd. never vote for return to m’land.

	No disclosure at present of my recent exchanges with Peking.



Sal.	Is (4) wise?  At what date?  What about Cyprus?  Why not put it more vaguely in (5).



Sw.	Doms. wdn’t like (4).



H.M.	If (1) – 3) cd. be achieved, then considn. cd. be given to future of F. and to Chinese repn. in U.N.



Sal.	I will repeat statement in H/L.



		Approved subject to amendments.

		Sw. to give it to H. Comms. of Doms. Tues. a.m.



 						[Enter G.Ll., H.W., Low, B.C.





		2.	Coal Prices.



P.M.	Why do this now?



R.A.B.	Inflation shd. be checked.  Welcome steps to curb consumer expensditure.  	Showing itself in b/p.  Coal is being sold in U.K. at prices lower than it cd. fetch abroad – and in addn. we are importg it. Any move wh. makes coal scarce (?expensive) therefore helps b/p.

	Moreover, N.C.B. deficit gives appearance of weakness in our economy.

	10% increase wd. do nothg. to wipe it off.  I therefore favour 12½% proposal.

	New N.C.B. : this is a moment to do it.

	E.P.C. agree now tht. it shd. be presented solely on basis of making N.C.B. pay.

	Economy in use of coal wd. reduce imports and/or increase exports.



B.C.	No early prospect of economy of manufacturg. industry.  Rlways cdn’t economise.



A.E.	Effect on competitive power of manufacturg. industry – in exports.



G.Ll.	Fuel cost in most engineering products is only 3%.

	This increase wd. mean only 2% increase in cost of steel.  eg. 10/= on a price of £30 a ton.



B.C.	B.T.C. will ask for increased fares &amp; freights – and this wd. add to it.



H.W.	Will also, as it works thro’ economy, increase the c/living.  Cd. we cover N.C.B. for this next year and hope they will meet increased costs by other means next year : viz., prefer 10% vice 12½%.



		Discussion adjourned.

								[Exit B.C., G.Ll.





		3.	Japan and G.A.T.T.



Low.	In view of A.E.’s advice P.T. does not now want to make statement in f’coming debate.



		4.	Wed.’s debate : Cotton industry.  



P.T. proposes amendment.  Draft 



Low 		submitted.  Approved.  Will be shown in advance to Lancs. 	group.



H.C.		Cd. be tabled by P.T.  



A.E. 		Better that P.M.’s name be on it &amp; R.A.B.’s.



</content>
</cab>
