<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/13/0 images: 51-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.9(55)							3rd May, 1955



		1.	Industrial Disputes.			[Enter B-H., B.C., G.Ll.



		Railways.



W.M.	T.U.C. persuaded ASLEF to accept variant, w’out a difference.  This is dividend from 3½ yrs close assocn. with T.U.C.



P.M.	Gt. relief that this strike has bn. averted.



		Docks.



W.M.	Awkward sitn. on Merseyside continues.



		Coal : Doncaster.



G.Ll.	Unoffl. dispute over piece-rates for face-workers, in 13 pits round Doncaster, which have resisted a new system put in by N.C.B. in Yorks with agreemt. of N.U.M.

								[Exit G.Ll.





		2.	Afro-Asian Conference : Loss of Indian Airliner.



H.	Suggest P.M. thank Nehru &amp; urge him to keep Chou up to mark on supply of facts.



A.L.B.	Gs statement taken, coming here by bag.  Enquiry procdg.  Diffy. is that no-one will talk in guest-house m’tained by us for Chinese Communist visitors.



H.M.	I have draft reply, wh. I will concert with C.R.O. and M/C.A. &amp; C.O.  Indonesians are not pressing on with enquiry.



								[Exit B.C.





		3.	Cotton.



P.M.	P.T. to see Lobby, after statement today.

	Draft statement handed round.



R.A.B.	I am ready to make the further concession on p.t., tho’ I personally believe it wd. be a mistake.  My advisers think it will involve a revision of structure of tax, prob. after only a few months.  During that time posn. will be unsound.  Won’t harm to mention possibility of a review – will help to keep Yorks. from making too much trouble.  Tho’ we shall lose some revenue, we hope to keep that w’in bounds.

	These consns. must be weighed v. political needs. 



		Agreed : concession shd. be made.

			  draft statement approved, with amendmts.





		4.	Queen’s Speech on Prorogation.



		Approved subject to amendments.





		5.	Colonial Immigrants.



Ll.G.		As in memo.  Need for enquiry – because of extent of ignorance of 		implicatns.

	But what do we say in Election?



P.M.	I wdn’t commit Govt. now to legn.  Wd. prefer to say : this is matter on wh. we shall prob. need to have formal enquiry.



K.	Agree.



A.L.B.	So do I.  Promise of legn. wd. provoke expn. of all differing views &amp; wd. encourage ‘forestalling’ immigration.

	Enquiry is needed – for public education.



H.	Support that view.



P.M.	No announcement by Govt.  As individuals admit growing gravity of problem &amp; say it mght be v. suitable for public enquiry.



		Advice to candidates to be considered by Business Cttee. &amp;

submitted to P.M.

								[Exit B.H.





		6.	European Defence.



H.M.	Fr. &amp; G. have agreed on Rocchling steel-works.  Ratificns. will be completed on 5/5.  Time-table can now go fwd. – with a view to issue on 11/5 of invitation to R.





		7.	Rating : Valuation in Scotland.



J.S.	System discourages private bldg. because gives inadequate return to owners of rent-controlled property.  Disguises real value of property. 

	Will be attacked as addl. burden on tenants to adv. of rich landlord.  But in fact owners’ rates are reflected in rents.

	If this has to be tackled, we must do it early in new Parlt.



R.A.B.	Accept in principle.  Reserve ques wtr valuation shd. be done by I.R.



J.S.	Will keep that open – tho’ I may begin by resting on Cttee’s. recommns.



D.S.	Wd. prefer I.R. basis.  If assessors accepted for Scotland, some l.a.’s might want to resume valuation in E. &amp; W.

	Support rejection of Soru’s recommn. on Equal. Grant.



R.A.B.	Para. 10. needs further consultn. with Ty.



		Agreed :	D.S., J.S., &amp; RAB to confer.

				Draftsman to proceed.



H.C.	Shd. this be foreshadowed in Election campaign?



P.M.	Certainly not.  Wait until Parlt. is elected.



H.	Then you will only mention subject to Q. Speech.





		8.	Cyprus.



A.L.B.	Debate on Thursday.  Shd. we disclose incitement to violence by Crossman when in Cyprus in March?  



H.C. 	Has he bn. reproved officially?



ALB.	No, only in general terms.  



R.A.B. 	Cd. you rely for this on report of official, when you have taken no official action v. him on it.



</content>
</cab>
