<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/4/3 images: 24-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (G.) (40) 3.WAR CABINET.CONTROL OF LAND TRANSFERS IN PALESTINE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State fur the Colonies.1. The. Pledge in the White Paper.THE members of the War Cabinet will recall that the White Paper of May1939, on Policy in Palestine (Cmd. 6019). contained the following paragraphs : &quot; The Administration of Palestine is required, under Article 6 of theMandate, &apos; while ensuring that the rights and position of other sections ofthe population are not prejudiced,&apos; to encourage &apos; close settlement by Jewson the land,&apos; and no restriction has been imposed hitherto on the transferof land from Arabs to Jews. The Reports of several expert Commissionshave indicated that, owing to the natural growth of the Arab population andthe steady sale in recent years of Arab land to Jews, there is now in certain areas no room for further transfers of Arab land, whilst in some other areas such transfers of land must be restricted if Arab cultivators are to maintain their existing standard of life and a considerable landless Arab population is not soon to be created. In these circumstances, the High commissioner will be given general powers to prohibit and regulate transfers of land.These powers will date from the publication of this statement of policyand the High Commissioner will retain them throughout the transitional period.&quot; The policy of the Government will be directed towards the developmentof the land and the improvement, where possible, of methods of cultivation.In the light of such development it will be open to the High Commissioner,should he be satisfied that the &apos; rights and position &apos; of the Arab population will be duly preserved, to review and modify any orders passed relating tothe prohibition or restriction of the transfer of land.&quot;2. Thus, the policy embodied in the White Paper constitutes an unequivocalpromise. This policy was framed in the knowledge that war might come andwith the intention that it should be carried out in peace or war. The argumentsbeing put forward in favour of our now shelving or abandoning it must beconsidered in the knowledge that if we do that we shall be breaking the pledgedword of His Majesty&apos;s Government.3. In accordance with the statement quoted in paragraph I above, thePalestine Order-in-Council was subsequently amended to enable the High Com-missioner to make regulations prohibiting, restricting and regulating the transferof land in Palestine. In general, the proposal is to divide the country into three categories, in one of which the transfer of Arab land to any person not being aPalestinian Arab would still be subject to no restrictions, while in another itwould be regulated, and in a third prohibited altogether. Transfers of land inmunicipal areas throughout the country would continue to be free from restriction.The High Commissioner for Palestine has been in consultation with me for somemonths past with regard to the details of the proposed regulations, and I havenow agreed upon a final draft of the regulations with him.[20620] n
4. Strong representations have been made by the Jewish Agency forPalestine, both to the High Commissioner and to myself, as well as byDr. Weizmann personally to various members of the Government, in favour of theabandonment or, failing that, the postponement of these regulations. The mainarguments of the agency are that:  (i) This new legislation is quite unnecessary for the protection of the Arabs,and will only add to the tribulations of the Jewish race at a moment when the war has increased their insecurity and persecution in Europe,(ii) The present support of the Jews in Palestine and throughout the worldfor the Allied cause will be gravely prejudiced if effect is now givento this part of the White Paper policy. The Agency point out that,while frankly maintaining their opposition to the White Paper policy,they have expressed their readiness to lay aside for the duration of thewar their quarrel with the British Government; and they considerthat, in the spirit of a political &quot; truce,&quot; we should be prepared to suspend action to implement the White Paper,(iii) American Jewry in particular will be greatly offended by ourproceeding with the White Paper policy, and their influence willthereby tend to shift from the pro-Ally to the Isolationist camp in theUnited States.5. I do not wish to deny that the introduction of these regulations will be a severe blow to that section of Jewish opinion which hoped that the emergency ofwar would find us unable to carry out our declared intentions. I have given thismatter most anxious thought, but I find no reason to deviate from a carefully considered line of policy on this account. On the contrary, I think that thearguments in favour of proceeding with these land regulations are decisive, bothon the strict merits of the case and also on grounds cf political expediency in thecircumstances of the war. Nor do I believe that Jewish support throughout theworld is to be gained or lost by bargaining.2. The Merits of the Case.6. Eirst as regards the merits of the case. The land policy laid downin the White Paper, to which the proposed regulations will give effect, is basedon the findings of a number of impartial and expert Commissions spread overmany years. As long ago as 1930 Sir John Hope Simpson, who was sent to palestine specifically to enquire into the land problem, warned the Governmentthat owing to the naturally increasing Arab population and their uneconomicmethods of cultivation, there was already a serious congestion of populationover most of Palestine and that there was comparatively little land left for settlement by new immigrants. Other investigations followed, and in 1936 theRojral Commission in their Report summarised the conclusions of the earlierenquiries into the land question as follows : (1) Unless there is a marked change in the method of cultivation the land of Palestine is unable to support a large increase in the population.(2) Any such change must necessarily be a very slow process spread overmany years. It depends largely on the extension of education in theArab villages.(3) It is on the extension of irrigation, combined with the regularised controlof the water resources of the country by Government, that reliancemust mainly be placed for any marked increase in the productivity ofthe land.(4) There is already congestion on the land in the hill districts.7. The members of the Royal Commission expressed themselves unanimouslyin agreement with these conclusions, and the following extracts from their reportindicate the lines on which they thought that the solution of this question mustbe found :  &quot; We are of the opinion that this alienation of land (i.e., transfers ofland from Arabs to Jews) should only be allowed where it is possible toreplace extensive by intensive cultivation, which really means in the plainsand not, at any rate at present, in the hills.&quot;
&quot; We have no hesitation in saying that at present, and, indeed, for manyyears to come, the Mandatory Power should not attempt to facilitate the closesettlement of Jews in the hilly districts generally.&quot;&quot; So far as the plains are&quot;concerned, we consider that, with due precau-tions, land may still be sold to the Jews.&quot;8. The Commission considered that further settlement of Jews in such areas as were possible could best be secured by means of large-scale development by public utility companies, but they qualified this suggestion by emphasisingagain their view as to the limited areas where it was practicable, as follows-&quot; It is necessary, however, in order to prevent undue optimism, to statethat, in our view, at present such areas are few and, as far as we can see. onlyto he found in the plains and not in the hill districts.&quot;9. The Woodhead Commission in the following year confirmed these conclusions, and after careful examination the High Commissioner and I havedecided that their plan of partition affords on the whole, with certain deviations^generally favourable to the Jews, a sound basis for the delimitation of zones inwhich land sales from Arabs to Jews should remain free, be restricted or be prohibited respectively.10. It will be seen that, though these various Commissions have sometimesexpressed different views on other topics, t-are is one matter on which they have all been consistent and unanimous, that is. the need for control of land sales.The proposed regulations have been framed to give effect to their conclusions.A sketch of the details is given in the appendix to this Memorandum, and I will bring a map to the meeting of the War Cabinet at which this paper is discussed\o show the zoning of the country.11. It seems to me that it would be wrong to ignore any longer &quot;the clearwarnings which we have received for so many years from a series of authoritativeCommissions about the serious congestion of the Arab population in certain areas. In the first place, we have an obligation under Article 6 of the Mandateto facilitate close settlement of Jews on the land only so long as we ensure that&quot; the rights and position of other sections of the population are not prejudiced.&quot;It would be a breach of the Mandate not to safeguard the Arabs now. Secondly,from the practical point of view, if we allow land sales to continue unrestricted,even for the duration of the war, the Jews, fearing restrictions later on, will undoubtedly make purchases wherever they possibly can, with the result that,within a few years, we shall have a landless Arab problem of such dimensionsthat it will be extremely difficult to find any solution to it. In fact, good government in Palestine demands these restrictions. Moreover, nothing is more likely to contribute to the possibility of further disorders than the existence of alarge landless Arab population.12. The merits of the case are in no way altered by the outbreak of war;land purchases have not ceased; on the contrary, the High Commissioner reportsthat purchases of land are still being made and there is plenty of evidence thatZionist organisations are taking active steps to raise funds for the particularpurpose of land purchase in Palestine.13. Nor can it reasonably be argued that these restrictions involve unduehardship to the Jews. Land&quot; purchases will not be stopped. They can becontinued on a considerable scale in all the areas containing the best land inPalestine, while the areas in which purchases will be prohibited are for the mostpart the poorest areas and those where the settlement of Jews has hitherto madelittle or no progress. Further, there is room for considerable additional Jewishsettlement on the land which they already own. The High Commissioner has reported that recent calculations based on the figures of lot viable adopted by theWoodhead Commission show that in the proposed &quot;regulated&quot; area 59,234Arabs are managing to live on land sufficient to support &quot;properly some 31,300,while in the same area 13,155 Jews are living on land sufficient to support 18.400.In the proposed &quot;prohibited&quot; area, 459,730 Arabs are managing to live on land sufficient to support properly only some 273,900, while 4,625^Jews are livingon land sufficient to support 6,300. In the proposed &quot; free &quot; area the land already in Jewish possession should suffice for a Jewish rural population of some 60.200,[20620] B 2
whereas the actual Jewish rural population is only 47,500.  It is clear from thesefigures that control of land purchases in Palestine is, in fact, overdue.14. Moreover, the proposed regulations do not lay down boundaries betweenfree, restricted and prohibited areas which are to remain fixed for all time. Ifimproved methods of cultivation can be introduced and closer settlement becomespossible, some prohibited areas may become restricted and some restricted areasmay become free. As the White Paper says: &quot; The policy of the Governmentwill be directed towards the development of the land and the improvement, where possible, of methods of cultivation. In the light of such development it will beopen to the High Commissioner, should he be satisfied that the &quot; rights and position &apos;* of the Arab population will be duly preserved, to review and modifyany orders passed relating to the prohibition or restriction of the transfer of &apos;lam!.&quot; A good deal of attention has already been devoted by the departments of Agriculture and Education to raising the standards of Arab husbandry, andit should be possible to make steady progress in this sphere of education whennormal conditions are restored.15. I would mention another consideration of some importance. Thisproposal to divide Palestine in a manner which tends to concentrate Jewishsettlement in certain broad areas will facilitate a solution of the palestine problem ultimately on federal lines. I still think that is the solution to which weshould work during the transitional period contemplated by the White Paper,and I know that such a solution commends itself to Dr. Weizmann and the jewish agency generally.3. The Political Expediency.16. I turn to the question of the political expediency of issuing these landregulations now. I agree that there is much force in the arguments marshalledin the memorandum (W.P. (G.) (39) 163) circulated recently by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty. Jewish influence is important in the United States of America,but we should take note that there are signs that this influence is increasinglysuspect to American opinion. The most vocal part of it will be extremely criticalif we decide to proceed with the land regulations, which have now become asymbol of our intention to pursue the White Paper policy -a policy which the zionists purpose to smash. The organised Zionists in America may be tempted to use their influence to counteract pro-Ally sentiment in the United States, andto embarrass President RoosevelCs friendly efforts. I doubt whether they willin fact do this, for the reasons which I mention later. Nevertheless, if therewere no other considerations of political expediency to be borne in mind thanthose mentioned in the First Lord&apos;s memorandum, it might be that, contrary towhat good government in Palestine requires, we should follow the course whichhe proposes for the duration of the war.17. But there are other serious considerations to be weighed. The FirstLord says rightly that it was &quot; not for light or sentimental reasons that lord balfour and the Government of 1917 made the promises to the Zionists &quot; at themost critical hour of the last war. But it was also not for light or sentimentalreasons that the same Government of which Lord Balfour was Foreign secretary in the last war made promises to the Arabs. It was desirable then, and it is again now, to have the Arab world with us. And in determining the degree oftheir friendship for Great Britain, the Arab peoples not only of Palestine itself,but throughout Arabia and in Egypt, are powerfully influenced by our policy inPalestine.18. The Arabs are not satisfied with the White Paper. They do not dislikeit as much as the Jews do, for it does go some way to protect their position, butit does not meet their aspirations in any of the fields of immigration, landlegislation, or constitutional questions. The neighbouring Arab States, includingEgypt, have sought, both before and since the war, to persuade us to interpret the policy in a direction more friendly to the Arabs. We are resisting pressure for concessions to Arab opinion as firmly as we are resisting pressure from Jewishquarters. We can hold the position so long as we abide by the White Paperpolicy.
19. What Arab opinion is most afraid of is that the pressure of influentialJewish opinion in London will induce us to alter that policy in a direction more advantageous to the Jews. The Arabs have watched this process at work on previous occasions. For example, the Statement of Policy of 1930 caused a violentreaction from the Jews and resulted in an &quot; interpretation &quot; of that policywhich robbed the Arabs of advantages which they had expected from the originalstatement. Again, proposals to which the Government was committed in 1936for a Legislative Council, which went some way to meet Arab desires, but was unacceptable to the Jews, was defeated in Parliament as a result, the Arabsallege, of Jewish influence. These events made the Arabs feel that any promises of the British Government which held out to them some hope of their interests inPalestine being protected would shortly be withdrawal. Though they have been partly reassured by what has been done so far in furtherance of the White Paperpolicy, they are fearful that the promises to the Arabs contained in it will still be withdrawn as a result of Jewish influence. The High Commissioner reports thatthe Arab villagers generally are already beginning to question the sincerity of HisMajesty&apos;s Government on account of our apparent inability to check Jewish illegal immigration and of the non-appearance so far of the land regulations. If in response to the present Jewish agitation these regulations were to be held insuspense, it would be regarded as the final proof that Britain cannot be relied upon to keep faith with&quot; the Arabs. That feeling would be shared equally byArab opinion both within and beyond Palestine, and by the Governments in allthe neighbouring States who took part in last year&apos;s London Conference. this aspect has been put to me strongly by the High Commissioner, who in the courseof a recent telegram deprecating any postponement of land legislation, says: &quot; But, if further argument is needed, it lies in the fact that, if the issueof the regulations is deferred, the Arabs as a whole, both in and out ofPalestine, will assess the motives operative with exactitude and assume that,under the stress of war. His Majesty&apos;s Government &apos; again &apos; intend to scraptheir promises. This will throw everything back into the melting-pot again,and His Majesty&apos;s Government might as well reconcile themselves to the factthat their good faith will never again receive credence in Arab circles. I also find it very difficult to imagine in what terms either His Majesty&apos;ammbassadors in neighbouring States or we here could explain away HisMajesty&apos;s Governments line of action.&quot;20. If such an utter loss of confidence in us were to occur, the worst fearswhich exist in the Arab world as to what further concessions the Jews mightwring from His Majesty&apos;s Government in later stages of the war and at thepeace conference would be confirmed. The result might well be a renewed,reinvigorated effort at rebellion in Palestine, born of desperate patriotism.Beyond Palestine public opinion in Transjordan, Iraq and Saudi Arabia wouldbe aroused so that it would be difficult for their Governments, even if they wished, to prevent assistance being given to the Palestine rebels. The influence of our best and wisest friends in Arabia, like Ibn Saud, would be crippled, andthe effect on our relations with Egypt would be no less embarrassing, whilst the delicacy of the problem with which the French have to deal in Syria wouldbe increased. Anti-British feeling would receive fresh encouragement in the moslem world, and opinion in India would not be unaffected. We cannot rule out altogether the possibility that our troops and police in Palestine itself mighthave to be engaged in suppressing new disturbances, supported from outside,which would banish the possibility of reducing our military forces there, andmight even require the despatch of additional troops. Such a situation would naturally be exploited to the utmost by our enemies. It seems to me that the scales of political expediency are weighted on the side of maintaining the policywhich we have already declared as an attempt to deal fairly between Arab andJew in Palestine, and which will on the whole maintain our good relationswith the Arab world.21. It is true that the Jewish reaction will be extremely unfriendly. Thisis inevitable whenever we take any step which is not acceptable to them, and theywill feel particularly aggrieved about any restriction of their power to buy landin Palestine, for they have relied on this power to gain for them in time completedomination of Palestine.   But I doubt whether their opposition would be as
tiserious as they now make out. There will be violent criticism and abuse to start with, and then relations will gradually settle down to normal again. It is a partof the Jewish technique to over-state the trouble that lies ahead if we take actionoffensive to them. There is always a strong mixture of bluff in their gloomyforebodings. Dr. Weizmann, for instance, has been prophesying extremely serious results from the step I now propose. He prophesied much more serious results before the publication of the White Paper itself, trying to make our fleshcreep then with the emphatic assertion that the White Paper would usher in the worst period of hatred and bloodshed that Palestine had ever known, and thatit would destroy the prospect which he then alleged to exist of some early Arab-Jewish agreement. Indeed, he said that reconciliation between the Arabs and Jews would become impossible for ever. What happened? Of course, there wastrouble, and serious trouble. Jewish illegal immigration, in particular, presentedus with a delicate and baffling problem. Nevertheless, physical strife was reduced and there was such steady improvement in the security position that within two months we were able to remove a brigade of troops and to contemplate the removal of another, if required, elsewhere. And with the passage of time we have witnessed the beginnings of a new tendency towards co-operation betweenArabs and Jews. Dr. Weizmann himself, when pleading with me a few weeks ago against the introduction now of land regulations, contradicted his ownprevious confident assertion by saying that there was a distinct tendency towardsagreement between both communities in Palestine, that it was more hopeful than he would have dared to prophesy twelve months ago, and that the introductionof new land legislation would destroy this hopeful movement! The fact is that only when the Government take a firm stand and tell the Jews that the national home cannot develop beyond a certain point unless the Jews themselves cometo an agreement with the Arabs, will the Jews use their powers to effect such anagreement. As long as they think they can extract further concessions out ofthe Government they will not waste their energy and skill courting the Arabs.As a happy solution to the Palestine problem depends primarily on some kind ofagreement between the two communities in the country, I urge that statesman-ship requires continued firmness from the Government now.22. So far as the Jews in Palestine are concerned, the High Commissionerexpresses the opinion that the indignation which the publication of the regulations will evoke has already been discounted to a considerable extent. So far as theJews beyond Palestine are concerned. I doubt whether they will stretch theircriticism to the point of active opposition. Neither in America nor anywhereelse have they any real choice but to support the Allied cause in the war. for if Britain is defeated the chance of their people in Central Europe being freed from their present cruel persecution is lost. Moreover, Britaiifs defeat in war would be a signal for Arab risings against the Jews in Palestine itself andwould inaugurate a period of most bitter civil war which might well end inthe wiping out of the promising National Home which is now establishedthere.23. I have given some consideration to the possibility of avoiding controversywith the Jews, while at the same time safeguarding the position of the Arabs,by reaching a &quot; gentlemairs agreement&quot; with the Jewish Agency under whichthe Jews would undertake, during the period of the war, not to enter into any negotiations for the purchase of land in &quot; prohibited &quot; areas or, without Govern-ment&apos;s approval, in &quot;regulated&quot; areas, thus obviating the necessity for theintroduction of formal regulations at this stage. But the objections to thisappear insuperable. It would usher in a period of negotiation with the jewish agency in which they would endeavour, in return for their agreement, to getall the proposed boundaries altered, and in the end they would be likely to refuseto become partners in a scheme wfhich restricts so severely their prized freedom to buy land. Even if the Agency were persuaded to enter such an agreement,our objective would be far from fully achieved, because there are large numbersof Jews and Jewish organisations over whom the Agency has no control andwho would buy in spite of any undertaking given by the Agency. And finally,Sir Harold MacMichael tells me that such a &quot; gentleman&apos;s agreement&quot; would arouse the suspicions and fears of the Arabs in Palestine and Transjordan just as effectively as a straight postponement of the land regulations, with equallygrave results.   I think that the Arabs of neighbouring States would adopt the
same attitude, and that all the arguments stated in paragraph 20 above thereforeapply to this suggestion.24. If we do decide to proceed with these land regulations we should, ofcourse, accompany their publication with an explanatory memorandum and withother propaganda designed to anticipate and counter criticism by showing, first,that they are necessary if we are to fulfil our obligation under Article 6 of theMandate to safeguard the rights and position of the Arab population whilstfacilitating Jewish settlement on the land, and, secondly, that the regulationsthemselves permit a steady development of further Jewish land purchases and settlement in important areas of the country. It should also point out that the boundaries to be set between the different areas are not necessarily final, butcan be modified as circumstances permit. Such an explanatory memorandum is already being prepared. I suggest that the same points should be incorporated in the telegram which it is proposed to send to Washington containing a replyto the message from Dr. Brandeis and his colleagues.4. Recommendations.25.   I therefore recommend that (a) the High Commissioner should be authorised to issue the land regulations which he has prepared;(b) their issue should be accompanied by an explanatory memorandum onthe lines indicated in the preceding paragraph;(c) the same explanatory points should be incorporated in the telegram whichit is proposed to send to Washington containing a reply to the message from Dr. Brandeis and his colleagues.M. M.Colonial Office,January 11, 1940.
APPENDIX.Palestine Land Regulations.Outline of Proposals.In the delimitation of the zones, and in the application of the principles onwhich transfers in &quot; restricted &quot; areas shall be permitted, the regulations followclosely the proposals made in the Woodhead Commission^ Report; where thereare variations from those proposals they are generally favourable to the Jews.The hill country and the Gaza area (where there is congestion) and the Beershebaarea (where survey and investigation of title have not yet been carried out), areto be areas within which further sales of land by Arabs to any person not aPalestinian Arab will, for the present at any rate, be prohibited. In the plains,and in the Negeb, on the other hand, Jews will still be able to purchase land fromArabs either freely or subject to certain restrictions. Land purchases will besubject to no restrictions in the greater part of the maritime plain. In theremainder of the plains, and in the Negeb, however, it is proposed that sales byArabs to persons who are not Palestinian Arabs shall only be permitted whenthe transfer falls within one or other of the following classes :  (1) It is made for the purpose of facilitating the irrigation of, or con-consolidating or expanding, holdings already in the possession of thetransferee or of his community, and the land to be transferred iscontiguous to such holdings;(&apos;2) it is made for the purpose of enabling land held in undivided shares bythe transferor and the transferee to be parcellated; orCS) it is in furtherance of some special scheme of development in the jointinterest of both Arabs and Jews to which Government may havesignified its approval.Finally, as already stated, the transfer of land in municipal areas through-out the country will remain unrestricted.

</content>
</cab>
