<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/57/2 images: 33-44</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government f\CC(75) 32nd COPY NO      ^ UConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 3 JULY 1975at 10. 00 amPRE sent the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food
The Rt Hon Harold Lever MP The Rt Hon Lord ShepherdChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster Lord Privy seal the Rt Hon Fred Mulley MP The Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and Science Minister for Overseas development the Rt Hon Robert Mellish MP The Rt Hon John Silkin mp parliamentary Secretary, Treasury Minister for Planning and local government the FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Edmund Dell MP Mr Alan Williams mp paymaster General (Item 4) Minister of State, Department of prices and Consumer Protection (Item 4)secretariat sir John hunt sir Patrick Nairne (Item 2)Mr P Benner (Items 1, 3 and 4)Mr T F Brenchley (Item 2)Mr E J G Smith (Items 1 and 2)Mr A D Gordon-Brown (Item 4)contents item                                                       Subject page 1.                   PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS 12.                  FOREIGN AFFAIRSUganda 2Rhodesia 23.                 PAY OF MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT 34.                 LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76 6
1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons during the following week.    At this stage of the session it was inevitable, if unfortunate, that provision had had to bemade for three Supply Days.    The Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury, had given evidence to the Procedure Committee about the substantial number of Supply Days which had to be accommodated within a Session^ but the Committee&apos;s report had not yet beenreceived.It was reported that it was not proposed to move a timetable Motion onthe Employment Protection Bill, since it now appeared that there had at an earlier stage been written agreement with the Opposition on an informal timetable. The Bill&apos;s prospects seemed reasonably good, and the Lord President of the Council and the parliamentary secretary, Treasury, would keep a close watch on its progress.    TheCabinet noted that the debate on 7 July on a Private Member&apos;s Motionabout a United Kingdom Bill of Rights would need to be handled withsome care and sympathy, in particular because of the implications for Northern Ireland.parliamentaryIffairs1
ffOREIGNIffairsUganda(Previous[&quot;Reference:(cC(75) 30thfConclusions,; Minute 22. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat President Amin had announced that President Mobutu of Zairewould act as an intermediary in all dealings between the UnitedKingdom and Uganda,    This was not an arrangement which could continue for very long, but he had sent President Mobutu a telegramexpressing his gratitude for the intervention which had led to thereprieve for Mr Hills, and putting three questions that aroseimmediately.    These were, what he understood Mr Hills&apos; fate would now be;  whether he had any information about the two Britons whomPresident Amin claimed to have arrested;  and whether there was nowany need for him to visit Kampala6    He had it in mind also to raisethrough President Mobutu the question of the future of other Britishsubjects in Uganda.I RhodesiaPreviousiReference:CC(75) 30th^Conclusions,minute 2THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the visit to Rhodesia of the Minister of State for Foreign and Common-wealth Affairs (Mr Ennals) had been useful.    He had formed theimpression that both Mr Ian Smith and the African National Council(ANC) wanted serious negotiations.    The differences between them were however still very wide.    Rivalries within the ANC were alsocomplicating the issue.    It was possible that these might be resolvedat a meeting which members of the ANC would be having with otherAfrican leaders in Lusaka.    We should await the outcome of thismeeting before considering the next steps.The cabinet took note of the statements by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary,
3. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the handling of thereport of the Top Salaries Review Body (TSRB) about the pay and allowances of Members of Parliament.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had the previous evening metrepresentatives of Government backbench supporters, who had strongly urged that the Government should reach an immediate decision on their attitude towards the Review Body&apos;s recommendations and make a very early announcement.    They felt that an immediate increase in pay was essential in order to relieve the serious financial hardship which some Members were suffering.    It was clearthat feeling was running high and that many Government supporterswere in a rebellious mood.    There was a genuine danger that in theabsence of an early announcement of increases in Members&apos; pay therewould be abstentions, or even hostile votes, which could imperil theGovernments position in Parliament,In discussion there was endorsement of the Prime Minister&apos;sassessment of the state of Parliamentary opinion.    Not only were some Members suffering real hardship: they were also being required to work under unprecedented pressure because of the excessive demands of the current legislative programme.    the dangers of rebellion or non-co-operation were real.In further discussion it was argued that, although the state of opinionamongst Members made an increase in pay inevitable, it was out ofthe question in present circumstances to accept in full the TSRBrecommendation in respect of the salary element.    The proposals onallowances could, however, be agreed.    The compromise which hadthe best prospect of pacifying Members without seriously imperillingthe development of the Governments counter-inflationary policy would be to increase the salary element to about  6,000 a year; andthis might be justified by reference either to the increase in the retail price index which had occurred between the last pay increase and the cut-off date which would form part of the counter-inflationarypackage to be announced shortly, or to the application to Members ofParliament of the successive pay increases which had beenpermissible under the various provisions of incomes policy which had applied during that period.    For the immediate future, the policies which were now being worked out would apply to Members ofParliament as to all other people; but it was for consideration whether the Government should indicate that for the long term they accepted the full TSRB recommendations in principle.In discussion of the timetable for publishing the report andannouncing the Governments attitude, it was argued that, althoughthe discontent produced by delay in announcing a decision wouldinvolve serious Parliamentary risks, it would be even more dangerous
to announce a decision while the current discussions with the TradesUnion Congress (TUC) and the Confederation of British Industry werein progress,,    The ne&amp;t few days were crucial to the possibility of achieving agreement on voluntary measures, and it would be follyduring that time to do anything which would worsen the atmosphere inwhich discussions were taking place,    Tais pointed strongly todeferring any announcement about Members1 pay until the discussions with the TUC had been completed.    In any case, it would benecessary to inform the TUC in advance of the line which was to betaken.    Presentationally it would be undesirable to deal with members&apos; pay as an isolated issue;  and the announcement should therefore present the Governments decision on it in the context oftheir conclusions on the wider question of the principles which should determine the handling of the remainder of the current pay round andoutstanding arbitration and other special cases (including the salaries of the Chairmen of nationalised industries).    Policy on these mattersmust be settled very urgently.    And the public acceptability of a pay increase for Members of Parliament would be greater if arrangements could be made for individual Members to indicate to the Press indetail the nature and severity of their financial problems.    It wouldalso be pre sentationally helpful, both in relation to Members&apos; pay andmore widely, if it could be indicated that members of the Cabinet andpossibly other Ministers - who, unlike other Members of Parliament,had enjoyed a recent salary increase - were prepared to accept a cut in their total emoluments.    If such a cut were made, it would benecessary to consider whether anything could or should be done tosafeguard Ministers&apos; penion rights;  and a similar question would arise in relation to Members of Parliament generally to the extent that the full TSRB recommendations were not accepted,,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that he should later the same day announce, in replyto an inspired supplementary to one of his Parliamentary Questions,that the TSRB report would be published in about ten days time, and thatthe Government^ attitude towards its recommendations would be announced at the same time.    He would explain that it was necessaryto consider the recommendations in the context of the Governmentsdecisions as to the principles which should determine the handling of pay claims outstanding from the current pay round, of claims whichhad gone to arbitration and of any other anomalous cases;   and that,since consideration of the report had necessarily taken some little time, any increases that were agreed would be payable from 13 June,the date when the TSRB report was signed.    He would seek to arrange a further meeting with Government backbench supporters beforeanswering the Question.    On the substance of the matter, the cabinet agreed that the TSRB recommendations on allowances should beaccepted in full, and that for the time being the salary element should
be increased to about  6, 000 a year. The latter could be justified interms both of increases in the retail price index and of the successiveprovisions of incomes policy during the relevant period.Urgent consideration should now be given in the context of the currentwork on counter-inflationary policy to the attitude to be adopted towards claims outstanding from the present pay round, and also tothe question whether there should be a cut in Ministers&apos; emoluments.The Cabinet would resume discussion of these matters during thefollowing week.    Consideration should also be given, though in a longer timescale, to measures to protect the pension rights ofMinisters and Members, and to the desirability of exploring with members of Parliament the establishment of a link between their pay and that of some outside analogue - for example, a House of Commonsofficial grade.    But in the meantime it should be made clear that theGovernment were not seeking to reject the TSRB recommendation thatthere should be biennial reviews.He would arrange for circulation to the Ministers concerned ofinformation about the measures which he had put in hand to ensurethat Political Advisers were treated comparably with permanentcivil servants.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.
CONFIDENTIALviSGlSLATIVE 4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Lord PresidentJROGRAMME of the Council (C(75) 73) on the legislative programme for 1975-76.r/5-76THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that the heavyprogramme of legislation in the current Session was causing an intolerable strain on Members and had brought the printing arrange-ments near to breakdown.    He nevertheless hoped it would be possibleto get to Royal Assent all the Bills which had been introduced, except the Aircraft and Shipbuilding Industries Bill; but some major Billsstill had a long way to go.    His plan was that both Houses should return for an extended spillover of about four weeks on 13 October,with the new Session starting in the week beginning 10 November;  andit would be necessary to sit for a few days in the week beginning4 August.    It was essential to avoid a repetition of the present difficulties during the next Session.    The Queen&apos;s Speeches and future legislation (QL) Committee had accordingly applied five criteria in deciding the claims of each Bill for a place in the programme:whether it was essential to the Governments economic or socialstrategy;  public expenditure and manpower implications;  electoraldesirability; the need to legislate in 1975-76;  and the Bill&apos;s state of readiness.    These criteria could be reduced to a single criterion -whether enactment next Session was vital to the Government as awhole, for political, economic, social or other reasons.    No bill which did not pass this test should find a place in next Session&apos;programme; and indeed there were positive arguments for keepingsome attractive legislation for the following Session.    The list of programme Bills in Appendix III of his paper represented a programme of realistic size which would take up all the parliamentary time available, and it should not be enlarged.In discussion of the pressure on Parliamentary time and the size ofthe programme, the suggestion was made that the Session should beextended and that the need for annual Sessions should be looked atafresh.    It was pointed out, however, that the Session might have tobe extended until April if there were an autumn Budget, and that anextension would cause problems over Private Members1 Bills and supply.    Some of the difficulties over Parliamentary time were caused by Bills not being ready until late in. the Session, and by theintroduction of a high proportion of Bills in the House of Commons,It was also suggested that the shortage of Parliamentary time was a self-inflicted wound, and that the Government should approach theOpposition with a view to trying out next Session a few radical changessuch as the grouping of a number of Bills into a single MiscellaneousPowers Bill;  arranging timetables for all Bills;  and, when the drafting of a Bill was held up, holding the Second Reading debate on a white Paper and putting the Bill, when introduced, straight intoCommittee.    It was however pointed out that QL Committee&apos;srecommendations already included a number of combined Bills, and
CONFIDENTIALthat proposals would shortly be put forward for a wide review ofParliamentary procedure.Doubts were expressed about the priority of a number of ProgrammeBills in Appendix III, and the following reasons were advanced fortheir inclusion in the programme:a. The combined Bill on Parliamentary Pensions andPublic Offices (Salaries) would be necessary to implement theforthcoming Top Salaries Preview Body report on Members1pensions; it would save Parliamentary time and avoid the riskof a row on future occasions when the salaries of the comptroller and Auditor-General and the parliamentary commissioner for Administration were increased.b. The combined Bill on Drivers&apos; Hours and Records and minimum Driving Age, etc, was needed to give effect to european Economic Community obligations of a kind which theUnited Kingdom had hitherto always honoured and which would come into effect on 1 January 1976.    This Bill might beintroduced in the House of Lords.c. Legislation on Official Information (franks committee) was a Manifesto commitment of considerable importance, and there was a need for The Queen&apos;s Speech tomake clear the Governments intention to proceed, though notin terms which guaranteed the passage of legislation in1975-76;  this legislation might be combined with any legislation arising from the report of the Radcliffe Committeeon Ministerial Memoirs,d. Legislative measures to tackle problems of race relations were essential, and all the more important in viewof the shortage of resources to deal with problems ofdeprivation.e. The Government was committed to legislation on thePost Office (Giro) and on Trustee Savings Banks, and thepreparation of these Bills was well advanced.In discussion of Bills in the Reserve list in Appendix IV of the paper the following points were made -a. The Government was heavily committed to the Bill on public Lending Right, and if it were not introduced next session a Private Member might succeed with a Bill and getthe credit,7
b. A separate major Bill on Construction IndustryContracts (the Lump) was now unlikely.    This would be unwelcome to the Trades Union Congress (TUC), and it wouldbe desirable for presentational reasons to set up the proposedConstruction Industry Manpower Board by statute rather thanby Order, even though the latter would be technically possible.c. The Bill on New Towns was of higher priority than theRoad Traffic Bill in the Programme list; this Bill should beplaced in the programme, and the Road Traffic Bill put in theReserve list.d. The Bill on Private Practice was a Manifesto commit -ment which satisfied all the criteria used by QL Committee.There had been great difficulty with the trade unions, who hadbeen prevented from taking action into their own hands only ona promise of legislative action by the Government,    Theposition could not be held for another year, and an undertaking in The Queen&apos;s Speech to legislate in 1975-76 was essential toavoid further trouble.e. There was some support for including the Bill onConspiracy in the programme.    On the other hand it was notyet clear whether the TUC would support a Bill confined tolimiting the penalties for conspiracy, while the law commission had not yet reported on the law of conspiracy as awhole.f. Legislation on Weights and Measures was essentialnext Session because unit pricing and the standardisation ofcontainers, which were strongly supported by the TUC, were dependent upon it.    The metrication provisions of the bill would be more controversial (which pointed towards intro-duction earlier rather than later this Parliament) but wereimportant to avoid the need for industry to run dual productionlines in both metric and imperial standards.    This Bill mightbe started in the Lords.g. The policy on Civil Aviation was under review, and ifthe conclusion were reached that changes involving legislation were required, this legislation would then be of the highest priority for political reasons and to avoid uncertainty in thecivil aviation industry.h. There were four other Department of Trade Bills in theReserve list, all worthy and necessary measures which wouldimplement international commitments and make other much8
CONFIDENTIALVneeded improvements.    None need be controversial and eachwas suitable for introduction ir the Lords or for SecondReading Committee procedure^THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet approved the recommendations of the QL Committee set outin C(75) 73, subject to the modifications of some of the detailed proposals which had been agreed in discussion.    The New Towns Billshould be placed in the Programme list and the Road Traffic Bill inthe Reserve list.    Further consideration should be given to thepossibility of combining the Bills on Nuclear Power Stations(Financial Arrangements) and Oil and Gas Fired Power Stations(Restrictions of Fuel) in a single Power Stations Bill, and to a similar arrangement in respect of the Post Office (Giro) and Trustee savings banks Bills, though combination would not be worth while in thelatter case if the Opposition were to agree to Second reading committee procedure for the non-controversial Trustee savings banks Bill.    The Reserve Bills with the strongest claims for inclusion in the programme were those on Private Practice, onWeights and Measures and on Civil Aviation (if required following thepolicy review), and these three Bills should be treated as a toppriority category within the Reserve list;  they would have first call,after the Programme Bills, on drafting resources and on Parliamen-tary time, and the position relating to these Bills would be looked atagain when the content of The Queen&apos;s Speech was decided.    Thepossibility should be considered of marking the importance and status of the Construction Industry Manpower Board by some means otherthan legislation, for instance establishment by Royal Charter.    TheLord President of the Council planned later to bring forward proposals relating to possible reforms of Parliamentary procedure.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion, and invited theMinisters concerned to be guided accprdingly.Cabinet Office3 July 19759


</content>
</cab>
