<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/53 images: 515-529</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1973____CM (71) 53rd Copy No. 11ConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 4 November, 1971,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environment(Items 3-7)The Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Davies, mp, Secretary of State for Tradeand Industry and President of the Board of trade the following were also present:Mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, chief secretary, Treasury (Items 5-7)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Ian Gilmour, m p, Minister ofState for Defence Procurement (Item 7)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. E. thornton mr. N. F. cairncross sir Philip adams mr. P. J. hudson mr. B. G. tucker mr. K. T. barnett mr. I. T. lawman mr. T. C. Platt
contents item Subject page 1     Parliamentary Affairs        ...............      32     Oversea Affairs.....................      india/PakistanFar East: Five-Power Defence arrangements the Anglican Dean of Johannesburg3     Industrial Affairs     ..................      4Heathrow Airport Strike4    Select Committee on Procedure^ Report on the Processof Legislation        ..................      55     Prescription Charges..................      86     School Milk    .....................      97     The State of the Shipbuilding Industry    .........     13
secret parliamentary 1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be takenAffairs in the House of Commons in the following week.The Prime Minister said that it was a matter for satisfaction that so many of the Governmenfs Bills had already been introduced.Oversea 2.   The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the affairs Prime Minister of India, Mrs. Gandhi, had expressed, during herIndia/Pakistan visit to this country in the previous week, pessimistic and almostPrevious        fatalistic views about the East Pakistan situation.  She had appearedReference:      to   think   that   the   only   chance   for   progress   towards   aCM (71) 51st   political settlement lay in discussions between the President of conclusions,    Pakistan, President Yahya Khan, and Sheikh Mujib, the EastMinute 3       Pakistan leader.  Even if such discussions could be arranged,however, the outcome would remain highly doubtful, if only forthe reason that Sheikh Mujib no longer commanded the loyaltyof the Bangladesh activists in East Pakistan.  The Governmentof India were giving some support to the Bangladesh guerillas, inthe belief that, if they failed to do so, the guerillas would be drivenincreasingly into the hands of the Chinese Government.   Therefugee situation remained obscure; and no clarification had yetemerged from the approach to the Secretary-General of the united nations which he had reported at the Cabinet&apos;s last discussionof the subject.   Mrs. Gandhi, despite her own forebodings and theproblems which the refugees created for her, had so far failed toco-operate in proposals that United Nations&apos; aid should be sought in reversing the flow of refugees.The Prime Minister said that he had gained the same pessimisticimpression from his own discussions with Mrs. Gandhi. Theinternal stresses in India resulting from the presence of some ninemillion refugees were increasing, especially since the refugees, as aresult of receiving relief under United Nations auspices, were infact enjoying a better living standard than many of the local people and were competing with them in the labour market. Mrs. Gandhihad appeared convinced that these tensions would inevitably growworse. As regards the wider international scene she had said thatthe Indo-Soviet Treaty of Friendship was the consequence of India&apos;sgrowing fear of China, which had been sharpened by the news of president Nixon&apos;s intended visit to Peking.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthere were grave dangers in the present situation; forces were operating in both India and Pakistan which could lead to war. Itwould be helpful if the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretarycould circulate a memorandum to the Cabinet defining the extentof our interests in the sub-continent and indicating what action might be taken to help to safeguard them.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion and invited the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary to circulate a memorandumaccordingly.136638-4a 2
Far East:Five-PowerDefenceArrangementsThe AnglicanDean ofJohannesburgThe Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the Anglo-Malaysian Defence Agreement (AMDA) had been terminated on1 November and Notes bringing into force the new Five-PowerDefence Arrangements had been initialled. Inasmuch as these arrangements gave us an agreed basis for the presence of our Forces,while relieving us of our AMDA commitment, the outcome was satisfactory.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that he had con-sidered the case of the Very Reverend Conville ffrench-Bey tagh, whohad recently been sentenced to five years&apos; imprisonment in South Africafor offences under the Terrorism Act. But he had concluded thatany intervention on his behalf would not be helpful. It was virtuallycertain that the Dean had engaged in activities which were illegal inSouth Africa; and, if he was guilty, the sentence was the minimumthat the Court could have imposed. The widespread revulsionwhich the sentence had aroused was attributable to the state ofSouth African law rather than to the action of the Court.The Cabinet (2) Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary.confidential industrial 3.   The Secretary of State for Employment said that the civil affairs Air Transport National Joint Council (CATNJC), which representedHeathrow the employers and the unions in the airline industry, had askedAirport Strike to meet him urgently about the dispute which had given rise to the unofficial strike of ground staff at Heathrow Airport. The stoppage,which was in protest at the award of a contract for ground-handlingservices for a foreign airline to General Aviation Services (GAS), aBritish subsidiary of a Canadian-owned company, was the latest of aseries of disputes arising from the decision of the British airports authority (BAA) two years previously to authorise GAS to provide an alternative source of ground-handling services for the smallerairlines, which otherwise relied on the major airlines for these services. The present action, ostensibly based on fear of redundancy,constituted a challenge not only to the BAA but also to the conclusionsof a court of inquiry, set up by the previous Administration, whichhad found in favour of BAA&apos;s decision. It was important now to stand firm in support of the BAA against pressure by militantelements, even though the major airlines, in pursuance of theirown interests, were also pressing the BAA to give way.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed with the Secretary of State for Employmentthat the BAA should be supported by the Government in standingfirm. Moreover, it was important that the initiative in publicity in relation to the dispute should not be left with the strikers; and theLord President of the Council and the Secretary of State for employment should consider how the facts of the situation could best be publicly presented.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.
SelectCommittee on procedure^Report onthe Processof LegislationCONFIDENTIAL4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the lord president of the Council (CP (71) 121) about the Select Committeeon Procedure^ Report on the Process of Legislation.The Lord President said that the Ministerial Committee on parliamentary Procedure had considered the Select Committeeon Procedure^ Report on the Process of Legislation, which hadbeen published during the Summer Recess. A large majority of theSelect Committee&apos;s proposals were acceptable; and the Governmentshould therefore gain credit by taking the initiative and giving aprompt response. In particular, early use could be made of somevaluable procedural changes. He accordingly proposed to informthe House of Commons of the Governmenfs proposals on a numberof the recommendations in a statement on Monday, 8 November.The Select Committee had made two proposals for furtherinquiries. The first, for which there was clearly a case on generalParliamentary grounds, was that a Joint Committee of both houses should be appointed to inquire into the procedures and practice by which the control of each House over delegated legislation wasexercised and to report how they might be improved. There was,of course, a likelihood that such a Committee would include in its recommendations the need for more time to debate Prayers andwould also turn its attention to the present powers of the House ofLords in relation to Statutory Instruments. Nevertheless, it wouldbe an advantage to the Government if such an inquiry was inprogress when proposals for the use of delegated legislation consequentabout United Kingdom membership of the European Communitiescame to be debated. The Ministerial Committee proposed, therefore,that this recommendation should be accepted.The most important recommendation made by the SelectCommittee was that the Government should appoint a Committee,including Members and Officers of both Houses, to review the form,drafting and amendment of legislation and the practice in thepreparation of legislation for presentation to Parliament. the ministerial Committee had concluded that this recommendations should be accepted, subject to further consideration of the composition and terms of reference of the Committee. Before the SelectCommittee had reported consideration was being given to a proposal that there should be an internal Government inquiry into thelegislative process; but the conclusions of an inquiry of that nature would be unlikely to command such general acceptance, on a matter on which there was widespread dissatisfaction, as those of anindependent inquiry. Moreover, Officers of each House, who could make a useful contribution, would be unwilling to take partin a purely internal inquiry. It would be preferable for Ministersnot to be members of the proposed Committee, since they would beplaced in an invidious position if the Government should decidenot to accept any of the Committee&apos;s recommendations. In anycase; it would be impracticable for those Ministers who could mostusefully become members of the Committee to do so in view oftheir commitments in the coming year. The Ministerial Committeehad accordingly considered that the Committee should be a small
independent body, chaired by a former Minister from either House,and that the membership should include some other former Ministers,some Peers, an Officer from each House, and possibly a formerParliamentary draftsman and a retired senior civil servant who had had practical experience of Departmental work in connection with legislation. The terms of reference of the Committee would need further examination; in particular, it would be necessary to considerwhether the inclusion of the words &quot; and the practice in the preparationof legislation for presentation to Parliament&quot; in the terms ofreference suggested by the Select Committee might extend the scopeof the inquiry into matters which must remain the responsibilityof Government. If these words were omitted, however, there might be criticism that the Committee would be handicapped inundertaking the comprehensive review for which there was a widedemand; and it might be preferable to rely on the Committee&apos;sgiving a reasonable interpretation to the terms of reference proposedby the Select Committee.The Ministerial Committee had also considered that theGovernment should accept the recommendations of the SelectCommittee on the use of pre- and post-legislation Committees,while indicating that the scope for such bodies would be limited inpractice to issues on which there was no political controversy. Thiswould be more acceptable than remitting the recommendations tothe new Committee of Inquiry; and the Government would retain their freedom of manoeuvre in settling the terms of reference of thatinquiry.As regards the recommendation that the question should beput forthwith on the Motion for Third Reading of all Bills, heand the Chief Whip had now come to the conclusion, in the lightof the prevailing climate in the House of Commons, that therewould be no point in offering to consider it with the Opposition;and the simplest course would be for the Government to accept it,In discussion of the inquiry into delegated legislation it wassuggested that the proposed Committee would inevitably consider anumber of controversial questions and the Government would be unlikely to be able to accept all the recommendations which emerged. These questions included the means by which amendmentscould be made to Statutory Instruments when they were laid beforeParliament and the criteria for determining whether an Instrumentshould be subject to the Affirmative or Negative Resolution procedure.On the other hand, it was not practicable for the Government to reject the recommendation, which would be generally welcomed byMembers. There was considerable dissatisfaction over parliamentary control of delegated legislation; and particular expression might begiven to this when Parliaments functions after the United kingdom had joined the European Communities were discussed. Moreover,the appointment of the inquiry into delegated legislation wouldmake it possible for a decision on most of the other recommendationsof the Select Committee relating to Statutory Instruments to be deferred.In discussion of the recommendation that the Governmentshould appoint a Committee to review the form of legislation it was
suggested that it would be important that the matters which wereto be the subject of the inquiry should be expressly defined. an examination of the manner in which Bills were drafted would meetthe concern which had been expressed in a number of quartersand would be acceptable. It would also be reasonable that the inquiry should comprise the way in which Bills were dealt with in both Houses. It would not be acceptable, however, that theCommittee should be able to make recommendations about themanner in which a Government reached decisions of policy beforethe process of drafting legislation began. Nor should the Committeebe empowered to consider such matters as the establishment ofParliamentary Committees to examine the Governments policyproposals before they were put into legislative form. In most cases discussion with the Opposition before Bills were introducedwould be pointless; and, with few exceptions, pre- and post-legislationcommittees would be impracticable. It was not unnatural that members should be concerned that they were not consulted inadvance about legislative proposals, despite the fact that therepresentatives of interests affected by the proposals were oftenbrought into confidential discussion. But this was inevitable;andthe Green Paper procedure should help to allay the dissatisfactionto, some, extent.In discussion of the remaining recommendations of the SelectCommittee it was suggested that there was merit in the proposal that explanatory memoranda should be drafted to give a description of the purposes and the effect of a Bill. This recommendations should therefore be accepted, at least in principle. There might also be an advantage in agreeing to consider the recommendation that it should be possible for certain Bills which had been to SecondReading Committee to be carried forward to the following Sessionof Parliament, although it was recognised that this would tend toerode the long-established principle that public legislation shouldnot be carried over to a succeeding Session. It seemed likely thatthe Opposition would agree to the recommendation that a secondDeputy Chairman of Ways and Means should be appointed andthat they would be willing to provide a Member from their sideof the House. The proposal to meet up to  200 of the draftingexpenses of each of the first ten private Members&apos; Bills in the ballotwould probably only go part of the way to cover these expenses;and in some cases organisations which had, for their own purposes,put drafting resources at the disposal of the Private Member would benefit.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the Lord President should make a statement inthe House of Commons on the following Monday indicating theGovernments views on the Select Committees Report, as theyhad emerged from the discussion. In particular it would be unacceptable that the decision whether a Statutory Instrumentshould be subject to the Negative or to the Affirmative resolution procedure should be taken out of the hands of the Government;and it Iwould be necessary for the evidence given to the inquiry into! delegated legislation to take account of this point.  It should136638-4B* 2
also be made clear at the appropriate time that the government did not necessarily commit themselves to accept the inquiry&apos;srecommendations. While the proposal that the Government should appoint a Committee to inquire into the form of legislation was acceptable in principle, further consideration should be given to its terms of reference with a view to excluding questions relating to the processes of policy formulation and consultation. The recom-mendations relating to the use of pre- and post-legislation committees should be given only a limited acceptance. The Opposition neednot be consulted about the recommendation that the question should be put forthwith on the Motion for Third Reading of allBills. As regards the recommendations relating to explanatorymemoranda on Bills it would be preferable for the Governmentto indicate that they agreed in principle; and the proposal thatcertain Second Reading Committee Bills should be carried overto the following Session need not be rejected outright but might befurther considered. Subject to these points, the Cabinet approved the proposals in CP (71) 121.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Lord President to make a statement, taking account of the points in the Prime Ministers summing up, in the House of Commons on the following Monday.(3) Invited the Lord President to give further consideration tothe terms of reference of the proposed inquiry into theform of legislation and to bring forward recommendations to the Cabinet.prescription charges      jPreviousReference:CM (71) 50thConclusions,Minute confidential&apos; 5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum (CP (71) 124)by the Secretary of State for Social Services on prescription charges.The Secretary of State for Social Services said that, following the Cabinefs earlier decision not to proceed with a scheme of charges related to the cost of individual prescriptions, it wasnecessary to consider how the savings which that scheme had been designed to yield could be recovered in whole or in part by anincrease in the fiat rate charge. The Health Ministers now proposedthat provision should be made in the Bill on National health services charges, which had a place in the main legislative programme for 1971-72, to relate the flat charge to the average cost of aprescription. There would be power to vary the relationship;but, in so far as the average cost of prescriptions increased, the flat rate charge would be correspondingly increased annually by administrative action. If the relationship between the average cost of prescriptions and the flat rate charge established in April1971, were to be maintained by an increase in the flat rate from1 April, 1972, the increase would be from 20p to 23p and would
yield an extra  4 million a year. If it was thought that, in view ofthe initiative for price stability taken by the Confederation ofBritish Industry (CBI), the increase should be limited to 5 per cent,the extra yield would be only  1^ million a year; and it was questionable whether the adverse publicity which it would attractwould make it worth while. An alternative course would be to defer the increase until after the expiration of the CBI&apos;s initiative;an increase to 25p would be involved if it were deferred to September1972. He proposed to enter into discussion with the organisations concerned about the possibility of making six-monthly &quot; season tickets&quot; for prescriptions available for sale in chemists&apos; shops.Meanwhile, it was necessary to make an early announcement of theabandonment of the scheme of graduated charges originally proposed.In discussion it was pointed out that the proposal to relate the flat, rate charge to the average cost of prescriptions would addconsiderably to the volume of controversy already involved in the government&apos;s legislative programme. Indeed, it was already probablethat in view of the pressure of other Bills it would not be possibleto find time for a National Health Service Charges Bill at all. Theabandonment of the Bill, however, would involve abandonment of other charging provisions, dealing with exemptions from charges for dental treatment and with optical charges; and, if these measures,which were foreshadowed in the White Paper of October 1971, werenot carried through, it would be desirable to make an early announcement of their postponement.In further discussion it was recognised that a system involving a fixed relationship between the charge and the average cost ofprescriptions was free from the disadvantages of the earlier graduatedcharges scheme and would secure buoyancy in the revenue. the automatic operation of the scheme, however, would tie the hands ofthe Government and might produce inconvenient results in particularsituations.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that no further action should be taken for the timebeing as regards the flat rate charge; and the Cabinet should considerthe situation again in the spring of 1972. Meanwhile, theannouncement of the abandonment of the system of graduatedcharges should take account of the strong possibility that it wouldnot be possible to introduce any legislation in the current session on National Health Service charges; and it should be so framed as not to exclude the possibility of future change in the system bywhich the level of the fiat rate charge was settled. The health ministers should prepare the announcement in consultation withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Lord President.: The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministefs summing up of their discussion.School Milk 6.  The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Secretary ofState for Education and Science (CP (71) 125), the Secretary ofState for Scotland (CP (71) 122) and the Secretary of State for wales (CP (71) 123) on the provision of school milk.
The Secretary of State for Education and Science said that under the provisions of the Education (Milk) Act, 1971, educationauthorities were required to discontinue the supply of free milk to pupils over the age of seven. No local authorities in Englandwere defying the Act. But most Inner London boroughs, whichwere not education authorities, were supplying school milk by using their power to apply the product of a Id rate, which attracted rate support grant (RSG), for the benefit of the inhabitants of the area.The effect of local government reorganisation would be to reducethe number of local education authorities and to increase thenumber of authorities who could act in this way if they chose to do so.In addition, at least one education authority were providing mid-morning beverages other than milk to children between the ages of seven and 11. The authorities concerned were therefore circumventingthe spirit of the Act; but they were not acting illegally. She was convinced that the policy embodied in the Act was right; and thedifficulties which had arisen were due to the fact that educationauthorities and teachers were not prepared to sell milk in school,although there would be no difficulty in collecting the paymentsimultaneously with the money paid for school meals. before considering any action in relation to authorities in England, however,it would be wise to await the results of dealing with those in Scotlandand Wales who were acting in clear breach of the Act.i The Secretary of State for Scotland said that in Scotland fiveeducation authorities were acting in defiance of the law. Localauthority accounts in Scotland were audited by accountants in private practice; and the auditor could deal with improper expenditure at any time without specific authority for an extraordinary audit.He had now received a report from the auditor in respect of theMidlothian County Council, which by a narrow majority haddetermined to defy the law. An informal approach to the council had been approved by the Home and Social Affairs Committee;but this had been unsuccessful. Individual councillors now haduntil 10 November to decide whether they were determined to continueto defy the law. If they did not desist from their defiance, theywould be automatically surcharged unless he was satisfied thatthose concerned had acted reasonably or in the belief that their action was authorised by law or that the action in question tookplace in such circumstances as to make it fair and equitable that asurcharge should not be made. He intended to interpose a further&apos;stage by informing the Council officially that he proposed to determinethat the expenditure was illegal and that certain named councillorswould be surcharged unless the Council ceased to contravene thelaw and did not incur further unlawful expenditure. There was apossibility that the Council would cease their defiance. If theydid so, he would use his power to ensure that no one was surcharged.If they continued their defiance, it would be about two months before any wages or salaries were arrested to meet the surcharge.If necessary, property could be impounded for sale; but therewould! be no question of imprisonment and the councillors wouldnot be disqualified. The amount involved on the auditors present report was of the order of  6 for each councillor; but, if defiance of the law continued, the total potential surcharge would increase at the rate of about  1,000 per month.
The Secretary of State for Wales said that in Wales only one authority, the Merthyr Tydfil Council, were acting in defiance ofthe law, having resolved to do so by a large majority. An informalapproach to the Council had been unsuccessful. In Wales an extraordinary audit could be carried out by the District Auditorat the direction of the Secretary of State. If the Auditor formed the view that unlawful expenditure had been incurred, he was required to give those concerned an opportunity in public to explaintheir action. If he subsequently decided that the expenditure was in fact illegal, he would have to disallow it. Subject to appealto the High Court (since the surcharge would exceed  500), thecouncillors would then be surcharged and automatically disqualified from membership of any local authority for five years. He had power, under the proviso to Section 228 (1) of the Local government act, 1933, to sanction expenditure which would otherwise be unlawful;and he would use this power if the Council desisted from theirdefiance. &apos; Disqualification of the councillors concerned would reduce the Merthyr Tydfil Council to nine or ten members. If thecouncillors refused to pay the surcharge, they could be sent to prisonfor civil, debt. The political consequences in Wales would in any event be serious. If it were agreed that the Secretary of State forScotland should make the proposed further approach to theMidlothian County Council, he suggested that he should at thesame time take the broadly parallel action of directing the DistrictAuditor to carry out an extraordinary audit in Merthyr Tydfil. Thealternative would be to await the outcome of the approach to theMidlothian County Council. But the two Councils were probably in close touch; and a delay was not likely to be helpful.In discussion it was suggested that open defiance of the lawcould not be allowed to continue unchecked. Otherwise, other local education authorities would supply milk illegally or be encouraged to find ways of circumventing the spirit of the Act;and defiance of the law by local authorities might extend to furtherfields. In any event action to deal with the unlawful expenditure was automatic in Scotland and had already started. On the otherhand the action proposed would seriously embarrass the Government,particularly since it seemed likely that individual councillors were determined to appear as martyrs. At least one local authorityofficer, however, had refused to sign a cheque in respect of expenditure incurred for the; unlawful provision of milk; and as a result theauthority concerned had desisted from their defiance of the law.It would be helpful if some way could be found to encourage other local authority pfficers to act in the same way, perhaps by makingthe signature of a cheque in such circumstances illegal.In further discussion it was argued that it was wrong that the penalties for unlawful expenditure by local authorities should fallon individual Councillors, who were thus enabled to presentthemselves as martyrs. It would be more satisfactory and moreconsistent with the philosophy embodied in the Industrial relations act if the penalties fell on the Council as a body. The cost wouldthen be met from the rates; it would not be taken into account for RSG purposes? and the councillors would have to answer to theirelectors.   On the other hand it could be maintained that the
councillors concerned ought to be personally responsible for adecision to incur unlawful expenditure; and it would be wrong forthe ratepayers to be called upon to meet the cost.In further discussion it was suggested that further consideration should be given to the feasibility of allowing free milk to be supplied by local authorities provided that the whole cost fell on the ratesand was not taken into account in computing RSG. This mightavoid some of the difficulties to which reference had been made,since not all local authorities would wish to provide school milk ifthe full cost fell upon the rates. On the other hand such an approach would tend to make it more difficult for the Government to controllocal authority expenditure; and it would be argued to be inconsistent with the principle that, in resource terms, local authority expenditure was part of public expenditure. In general, lawful local authority expenditure qualified for RSG because local authorities were not permitted to raise money other than through the rates, which it was recognised were not in themselves adequate to meet local authority expenditure in full.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that the alternatives of taking the action proposed in respect of Scotlandand Wales or of allowing local authorities to continue to defy thelaw were unattractive. The Secretary of State for Scotland wouldknow by Wednesday, 10 November, whether the Midlothiancouncillors were determined to continue in their defiance of the law.The Cabinet should consider the position further on the following day in the light of the councillors&apos; decision. Meanwhile, theChancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation with the other ministers concerned, should examine urgently the various suggestions whichhad been put forward in discussion and should consider to what extent they might contribute to a less unsatisfactory solution of theproblem. In discussion reference had been made to the unhelpfuladvertisements of the Milk Marketing Board drawing attentionto the fact that free school milk was no longer supplied for pupilsover the age of seven. The Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food should discuss these advertisements with the Board.!    The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe other Ministers concerned, to proceed accordingly.-(3) Invited the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food!    &apos; to discuss  with the Milk Marketing Board theiradvertisements drawing attention to the fact that freeschool milk was no longer supplied for pupils overthe age of seven.
The State of the 7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the SecretaryShipbuUding of State for Trade and Industry (CP (71) 126) on the state of theIndustry shipbuilding industry.The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that a report prepared by officials for the Sub-Committee on the shipbuilding industry of the Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy (EPC),which had been charged with the task of reviewing the state of the shipbuilding industry and the measures necessary in relation toshipyards which seemed likely to face closure, had made proposalsfor a new general subsidy for the industry. The decision reached by EPC in the previous December and reaffirmed in May was thatthere was no case on economic grounds for giving special support to the industry other than that afforded by the Home Credit Schemeand by &quot; Shipbuilders&apos; Relief&quot;, although on regional employmentgrounds any major closures ought to be phased over a period.There was a substantial risk that further shipbuilding firms, almost all of which were in development areas where unemployment washigh, would run into severe financial difficulties during the coming months; and, since some of them, unlike Cammell Laird, werefirms in which the Government had no stake, it seemed desirable for the Cabinet to consider the broad issues involved before detailed consideration was given to any scheme of assistance on employment and social grounds. In his view there was little prospect of developing a viable shipbuilding industry except by the deliberateintervention of the Government; and this would involve a substantialdeparture from present policies. Even if it were agreed to follow that course, it would take time to develop the necessary measures;and the Government would still face the immediate problem of the expected collapse of major shipbuilding firms. While a scheme ofrescue could be devised, its adoption would be in plain contradictionwith the Governments announced policy towards industry ingeneral and the shipbuilding industry in particular. There wasno case on industrial grounds for adopting such a policy; and itmight, indeed, militate against the evolution of a sound shipbuilding industry in the longer term. It would cost perhaps  40 million or more. Its justification would be to preserve employment; and,before he considered measures to save shipbuilding firms for that reason, he wished his colleagues to review the fundamental questionsof industrial policy which would be at issue.In discussion, it was generally agreed that in existing conditionsof high unemployment generally and few alternative job opportunitiesin prospect in the affected areas, the Government could not contemplate &amp; succession of failures among major shipbuildingconcerns and the heavy redundancies which this would entail, both at the yards and in the firms which supplied them. It would accordingly be necessary to suspend, for the time being, theapplication of the established policy of accepting that, when concernsceased to be viable, they should be allowed to go into receivership.This conclusion did not, however, imply abandonment of the established strategy either in general or, in the longer term, in respectof the shipbuilding industry.b        .   ; SECRET
&apos;It was suggested, however, that the help to be given to keepshipbuilding firms solvent in order to maintain employment in the short term would desirably be channelled through some agency,which would be charged to secure, in return, the industry&apos;s acceptanceof the recommendations of the Commission on Industrial relations in their report on the shipbuilding industry, together with agreement to a suitable scheme to eliminate overmanning and to alleviate the hardship of the consequent redundancies, perhaps on the lines of the redundant Mineworkers Payments Scheme. By this means itmight be possible progressively to reduce the industry to a sizeat which it would be viable in the longer term and so to escape the dilemma posed in CP (71) 126 that an industry with an assuredfuture could be developed only if the Government themselvesplayed a direct part in reorganising and redeveloping it, at heavycost to the Exchequer.... On the other hand it was argued that the degree of overmanningwhich persisted in the industry was only one element in the problem.T^he principal weaknesses of the industry were poor management and inadequate facilities. Until the management was replacedthere could be no confidence that the problems of overmanningand bad labour relations would be successfully dealt with or that ascheme on the lines which had been suggested would be effective.Given an inefficient and badly-located industry and little prospectof securing sufficient new orders to keep it fully employed, no private capital was likely to be forthcoming to modernise the industry&apos;sfacilities, still less to establish new facilities in more suitable locations,such as Hunterston. It was therefore misleading to suppose thatan;; efficient, modern shipbuilding industry could be evolved simplyby a process of reduction and concentration. If such an industry were considered a desirable objective of policy, it could be securedonly by Government action to reconstruct the industry on a national basis; and the Government would have to be ready to deploy thenecessary resources for the purpose, perhaps through a suitableagency, albeit of a radically different kind from that mentioned in discussion. Meanwhile, we should in any event face the problemhow best to stave off the collapse of important parts of the industry.: In further discussion the following points were made . (a) Even if it were necessary to devote as much as the  40 millionmentioned in CP (71) 126 to preserving employment in shipbuilding,this was still below the average cost of  10,000 per job to establishalternative employment in development areas.(b) If the Government were to avoid being faced with the needfor a succession of rescue operations to prevent precipitate closures,it would be necessary to develop clear policies for dealing with theproblems of the industry in the short and medium term and to devise a consistent approach and appropriate measures for resolvingthem.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that, while the Governmenfs basic industrial strategyremained valid, its application to the shipbuilding industry must be modified for the time being.   In order to prevent the collapse of
major parts of the industry and the consequent increase in umemployment additional assistance to the industry must now becontemplated. The Ministerial Sub-Committee on shipbuilding and the Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy should consider,in the light of the recent report by officials on the state of the industryand the levels of unemployment in the affected areas, how immediatehelp would best be provided. They should also consider further,with reference to the medium term, the suggestion made in discussionfor a scheme which would effectively eliminate overmanning in theindustry and would promote acceptance of the necessary redundanciesby providing compensation to prevent hardship.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion./.,.&apos;.:.&apos;,Cabinet Office,4 November, 1971mil -Sr

</content>
</cab>
