<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/56/20 images: 194-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
so       ^-   /   /THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENT 9 printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1944.mThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited, it is issued for the personal use of .T^rrV?f^f^T^^...................,................TOP SECRET Copy No.     31W.P. (44) 570.13th October, 1944.YIAR CABINET.S.O.E. ASSISTANCE TO &quot; OVERLORD.&quot;Memorandum by the Minister of Economic Warfare.I think that my colleagues would be interested to see the attached account ofthe contribution made by S.O.E. and the patriot armies to &quot; Overlord.&quot;2. In presenting it, I should like to pay a tribute to the zeal and ability-with which the officers of my Department have laboured these four years to achieve such results, and also to my predecessor, Mr. Dalton, under whose auspicesthe foundations of this now very large organisation were laid.S.Ministry of Economic Warfare, W. 1,13th October, 1944.The Task.S.O.E. came into existence as the result of a War Cabinet Memorandum ofthe 19th July, 1940,* which combined under the Minister of Economic warfare the three separate Departments formerly interested in Sabotage work, and laidclown that the new organisation was &quot; To co-ordinate all action, by way of sub-version and sabotage, against the enemy overseas.&quot; In carrying out this workS.O.E. would receive the co-operation of the Services Intelligence departments and of S.I.S., would be responsible for obtaining the agreement of the ForeignOffice or other Ministries to operations likely to affect their interests, and by closeliaison with the Chiefs of Staff would ensure that the planning of irregularoperations was in step with the general strategical conduct of the war.2. So wide a directive has led to the gradual build up of a large GovernmentDepartment with many ramifications, in which officers from the Navy, Army andAir Force have collaborated with diplomatists, scientists, engineers and civilservants, permanent as well as temporary. Underground warfare was an unknownart in England in 1940; there were no text-books for newcomers, no old hands to initiate them into experiences of the last war. A new technique had to be evolvedand lessons had to be learned in the hard school of practice. New instruments and weapons had to be invented, and for this research stations and factories had to beprovided. British subject;? w ith intimate knowledge of the occupied territorieshad to be collected and taught their job. Above all, natives of those countries hadto be obtained, tested and trained.Initial Steps.3. It was evident from the beginning that S.O.E. could not hope to fulfil itsdirective without the sympathy and co-operation of the exiled Governments of* W.P. (40) 271.[28366] B
the occupied countries, and every effort was therefore made to impress upon them the possibilities and the potential importance of subversive warfare. This wasnot always an easy task when dealing with Ministers more accustomed to, andmore interested in, political and propaganda work than in clandestine sabotageand paramilitary operations; but as communications with occupied Europe were re-established,&apos;the strength of the resistance feeling became apparent, and by 1942S.O.E. could count on the co-operation of all the authorities representing theoppressed peoples.4. The foundations of any plan for building up resistance activity werecommunications and supplies. W/T operators were among the first Agents to be despatched to occupied countries, their messages at first being handled by S.I.S.This traffic, however, increased so much that in 1942 S.O.E. established its ownsignals stations to handle it. At the time of Overlord &quot; we had a very largenumber of W/T sets in operation in Northern Europe and as many as 260messages were being received in a day, increasing by D + 80 to 720 per day. a staff of 350 operators and cypherines was necessary to deal with this from threespecially constructed stations in England. But in 1941 the commencement wason a very humble&apos; scale. Other methods of communication were a very limitedcourier and passenger traffic maintained by &quot; pick-up &quot; operations : a Lysanderor a Hudson landing in France was able to bring back not only agents but alsopapers and reports which could not be transmitted by W/T. &quot; land lines &quot;(that is to say, chains of &quot; safe &quot; houses and couriers) for the passage of S.O.E.agents and papers were also established and controlled by a Section specialisingin clandestine communications.Eeception Committees.5. Supplies of arms and sabotage equipment were sent both by sea and by air. By M.T.B., fishing boat and fellucca stores were delivered in bulk, particu-larly.to Norway and, in the early years, to France; but the difficulties of this method of transport, enhanced by the increasing German surveillance of the coastal areas, restricted the output and served to put the emphasis on supplyby air. This in itself involved a developed organisation on the ground, to layon the operation by W/T and to provide a &quot; reception committee&quot; to controland light up the ground, and to dispose of the containers.6. The reception committee had to be carefully trained. Its pivot was theorganiser, and second to him only, the W/T operator, who himself had undergonemonths of training in England which included not only morse but also codes,security, maintenance and self-defence. The organiser, having collected his team of patriots, and instructed them, selected a reception ground far from anybuildings and which the R.A.F. had to approve. Then all arrangements weremade by W/T between the organiser and S.O.E. London for the delivery. Theorganiser would stipulate what &quot;stores&quot; he required, so many sten guns,explosive charges, W/T sets, telephone wire cutters, silent pistols, time fuses,incendiaries, &amp;c. These had to be carefully packed in the S.O.E. packing station in specially constructed &quot;containers&quot; designed to fit into the bomb-racks of aircraft and attached to parachutes. They measured 5 feet 8 inches by 15 inches,contained enough arms and stores (including in winter food and clothing) forseven men, and weighed about 2 cwt. loaded, but were mostly made so as to divideup into portable separate sections immediately they were received. When it is realised that by mid-1944 S.O.E. was sometimes despatching as many as T.OO0containers a night, it will be appreciated that the packing and despatchingorganisation grew to very large dimensions.7. The drop had to be made on a moonlight night (which in itself reducedoperational time by 50 per cent.), until late in 1943 special radio apparatus andtechnique were invented that rendered practicable a limited extent of dark nightdropping. Every detail having been arranged and confirmed on W/T, the pro-blem remained that the weather conditions must be suitable and local enemy \activities not too great. These factors were not known until a few hours beforethe start of the aircraft, by which time it was difficult to apprise the organiser intime for him to inform his reception committee, who were scattered and oftenhad to come long distances. There was only one way of doing this by pre-arranged code messages on the B.B.C. evening transmission. A warm tributeof gratitude must be paid by S.O.E. to the B.B.C. for their continued co-operationduring these long years-a co-operation given at the direct expense of the services for which the B.B.C. was primarily responsible.   Others who listened in to the
B.B.C. foreign service must often have been perplexed and perhaps irritated by long streams of incoherent and ridiculous sentences called &apos;&apos; messages personnels &quot;(by 1944 as many as eighty or ninety every night) such as &quot; Le chat cle mon onclea cles ycux bleus &quot; or &quot; Josephine aime Victor.&quot; but when the members of the reception committee heard their particular message they trudged forth intothe night.8. On the reception ground they had to wait long hours in the cold, oftenin vain, for sometimes the aircraft would get shot down, sometimes it would missthe ground, sometimes it would fail to see or not be satisfied with the receptioncommittee&apos;s signals. But when the waiting men heard the hum of the engine,they would emerge from the shadows and flash with electric torches (anythingbrighter was too dangerous) the prearranged morse letter and the aircraft wouldanswer. Then down came the parachutes, some of them bearing stores, some ofthem bearing men. The reception committee thereupon had to hide and distributethese as quickly as possible, because enemy agents had also heard the aircraft and would soon be on the search.The R.A.F.9. In 1940 and 1941 S.O.E. and S.I.S. had only a flight of aircraft at theirjoint disposal. These were increased in the winter of 1941-42 to a squadron;and in March 1942 two squadrons were assigned to S.O.E. and S.I.S. operations.The nature of the work demanded specialised aircrew training and navigation of avery high order, and no pilot could achieve such a high percentage of successful&quot; drops &quot; at the commencement of his period of duty as at the end of it. Thelimits of human endurance involve taking pilots off duty after a prescribednumber of operational hours, so the work was necessarily constantly being doneby newcomers as well as by more experienced men. which substantially reduced the number of successes. Taken as a whole, however, the percentage becamesteadily better. Without the sustained effort and courage of the R.A.F. indropping supplies, often after long journeys in the face of adverse weather conditions and enemy opposition, to an inconspicuous pin-point marked by feebletorches, Europe&apos;s cry for help would have gone unanswered.The Organisers.10. The officers who undertook the work of organisation, together with their supporters, knowingly took risks more fearful than the odds of battle. For the gestapo net of agents and informers was widely thrown; every meeting, messageor movement was a source of danger, and the wireless operator was a speciallyweak link on account of the risk of being D/Fd. No organiser in these yearsever went to sleep without wondering whether he would survive the morning.Those arrested were fortunate if they were killed in resisting, or were afterwardsshot, for prolonged and barbarous torture awaited them at the hands of the gestapo. Many committed suicide in order not to betray their comrades, andothers died with their secrets inviolate. But inevitably these merciless interroga-tions produced some evidence and led to further arrests. Nevertheless, the workwent on, and the very atrocities of the enemy embittered and strengthenedResistance through its martyrs. At the time of &quot; Overlord &quot; S.O.E. had some293 organisers and agents who had been trained in England at work in theS.H.A.E.F. area. Over 1,200 men had been sent to the &quot;field&quot; since the1st October, 1943, of whom 297 had disappeared. Of these, it is known that 64had given their lives, often in circumstances of great heroism, and the followingdecorations had been awarded for gallantry in the field : Distinguished Service Order   ...      ...      ... 13Distinguished Service Cross   ...      ...      ... military Cross    ............... 23Order of the British Empire   ...      ...      ... 5Member of the British Empire ...      ...      ... 11Distinguished Conduct Medal ...      ...      ... 11Military Medal............... 24British Empire. Medal   ...      ...       ...      ... 6   .Mention in Despatches......      ...      ... 4If foreigners had been eligible for the Victoria Cross, there had certainly beenactions which had warranted its bestowal.[28366]
11. Within the framework laid down by the War Cabinet, and upon the twinpillars of communications and supplies, S.O.E. began to build up subversiveorganisations in all the occupied countries of Europe. Coup-de-main attacks against specific targets were the first operations to be mounted by S.O.E., and thereports of the members of the teams upon their return to this country gave an encouraging picture of the general hatred of, and opposition to, the Germaninvader. Of the countries concerned, France inevitably held a leading place&apos; inall planning and preparation by reason of her size and of her strategic positionbut owing to her special political circumstances, the organisation of Resistancethere proved particularly sluggish and complicated. Whereas in the case of holland, Belgium and Norway, S.O.E. were able to co-operate with the legitimateand acknowledged Governments, in the case of France there was no such authorityqualified to speak for her people, while internally the Vichy regime gave an excuse for inaction and apathy. There is little doubt that in 1940 Petaincommanded the overwhelming support of the French people. General de Gaullewas regarded as a mad brigadier (surrounded by a handful of adventurers) whohad pinned his faith to the broken reed of England. Not even the Battle of britain aroused any spirit in the French people as a whole,, but thenceforwarda trickle of the braver hearts began to filter out of France to join us.Training of Agents.12. One of the first preliminary steps that S.O.E. had to take was the recruitment of nationals of the occupied territories who had found shelter in thiscountry or abroad. Most of them came from the refugee &quot; armies/5 but theirselection was a delicate matter in view of the difficulty and secrecy of the work.They had to be brave, intelligent young men not given to wine or women forsuch men &quot; talk.&quot; Their patriotism had to be above suspicion. It was therefore necessary not only to train them but also to give them along period of testingand probation before we could be sure that they were made of the right stuff.13! Volunteers were called for to serve as &quot;Paratroops.&quot; When they hadbeen accepted after interview, they were sent to schools in the country wherethey were taught paramilitary fighting in successive stages. All this time theywere being carefully watched. If they were considered unsuitable, they were returned to their units; if they made good, they were passed on to the successiveschools where they learned parachute dropping, W/T, codes, security, sabotage,secret inks, cyphers, &amp;c. It was not until the final stages that they were toldwhat they were really wanted for, and asked if they would volunteer for thework. This very elaborate sifting and training was the foundation of S.O.E.work, and ultimate success has amply justified the syllabus, but the systeminvolved long months of training, and the&quot; establishment of over fifty schools,because for security reasons neither the various stages nor the various nationalitiescould be mixed. They all had to be kept separate. The administrative work thatfell to S.O.E. in this respect was therefore very great, and it must be rememberedthat not only the pupils but also the instructors had to be trained.14. A corollary of the training of agents was the preparation of forgedpapers, passports, ration cards, &amp;c, for them. A forging factory was thereforeestablished that included the special manufacture of the different sorts of paperrequired. Here the most beautiful forgeries were turned out that would haveprovoked the envy of Professor Moriarty. Of the thousands of forged documentsemanating from this factory not 1 per cent, was ever detected by the enemy. the agents also had to be provided with local currency. Supplies of these currenciesin the United Kingdom were extremely limited or non-existent and S.O.E. there-fore had recourse to dealings on the Black Market of Europe. Before longdemands were also received from the Service Departments for currency particu-larly from the Air Ministry for &quot; Escape Purses &quot; for aircrews. To date S.O.E.&apos;ssurreptitious purchases include : &apos;700 million French francs. -22-5     ,,     Belgian francs.8-5    ,,     Dutch Gulden.4        ,,     Norwegian Kroner.6-5    ,,    Fceichsmark.Nearly all these notes are in small denominations and it has been no mean featto obtain such a bulk clandestinely from the countries concerned and bring the notes safely to this country.  But this is anticipating the story.
The&apos;British and French Sections in France. &apos;15. By March 1941, S.O.E.&apos;s first recruits were ready to go to the field.Their activities and reports convinced General de Gaulle that Resistance was a force to be reckoned with, and after some persuasion, the Fighting Frenchproceeded to make their own contacts through S.O.E. A second French Sectionwas accordingly created to work in liaison with General de Gaulle&apos;s staff. TheBritish circuits already in being were, however, maintained and expanded, since it was recognised in this country that many Frenchmen, although, definitely anti-German were not pro-de Gaulle, and from the very beginning His Majesty&apos;sGovernment reserved its right to contact any Resistance elements in France of whatever political faction, while giving General de Gaulle such facilities as heneeded for his own work.16. The continued existence of the British-controlled circuits became a boneof contention between General de Gaulle and His Majesty&apos;s Government, but the soundness of our policy was proved by the success of the section and the extentof the support given by Frenchmen in France. A second reason for maintaining the British section in France was the very low security &quot;standard of fighting french Headquarters. Security is an indispensable condition of existence toclandestine organisations, and the British Section was able to benefit all the time from its more stringent precautions both at Headquarters and in the field. If allthe subversive organisations in France had been under the control of fighting french Fleadquarters, it is probable that a network of efficient and active circuitscould never have been maintained in the face of the repeated Gestapo drives. Asit was, the existence of the two organisations in France allowed for complementaryactivities, and they were of considerable assistance to each other. The BritishSection became known throughout underground France as the &apos;&apos; Reseau Buck-master &quot; from the name of the British colonel who commanded it and who also had the honour of being&quot; Public Enemy No. 1 &quot; on the Gestapo list. There were some seventy British officers serving the Section in France; most of them were british subjects, who were, of course, bilingual, but about a quarter were French-men who were given British commissions. On the Liberation of France general de Gaulle paid us the compliment of offering all these officers commissions in theFrench Army of the same rank as they held in S.O.E. a graceful tribute to their training and efficiency.17. The methods used by the two sections were very different. The nucleus of the British circuit was the Organiser with his W/T operator, and round thesenuclei small watertight circuits were gradually built up all over France. If the gestapo succeeded in breaking up a circuit, a new organiser would-be sent to thearea concerned and the work would begin again. In general, the size of thecircuits was limited; in some cases it became considerable, but a large, organisa-tion nearly always proved insecure in the long run, and the organisers were told to confine themselves to establishing small bodies of well-trained and entirelyreliable, men. Fighting French Headquarters, on the other hand, for political reasons aimed at reaching the masses of the French people. General de Gaulle,having failed to create his own Resistance Movement responsible directly to him,began in 1942 to try to make contact with those indigenous Resistance Movementsalready in existence. To this end French liaison officers and W/T operators were despatched, together with a co-coordinator to control their activities, andResistance leaders and politicians representing every shade of French political opinion were brought back to this country. By the end of the year most of thegreat Resistance Movements had agreed to recognise de Gaulle&apos;s military, though not his political, leadership.The Purpose of Sabotage.18. 1941 and 1942 were the lean years for Resistance. Europe had beenstunned by the lightning German advances. Apathy and confusion were stillwidespread. As the months went by, however, German domination with itsrestrictions and brutalities itself acted as a stimulus to revolt. But time was needed for action and reaction to develop to a stage at which S.O.E. could take advantage of a widespread anti-German feeling. Meanwhile, the buildinghp of subversive groups proved a slow process, prolonged always by the specialrisks and casualties of underground warfare, in which one arrest would wipe outmonths of patient work. Further, the amount of material that S.O.E.&apos;s very limited air transport resources enabled it to despatch to the field was tantalisinglysmall;  Although our output of aircraft was now mounting rapidly, and the Air
Ministry were ever anxious to help S.O.E., new claimants for aircraft wereincreasing even more rapidly, and S.O.E. found the anti-U-boat campaigncompeting with it for long-range bombers.19. Sabotage was undertaken for two purposes : First, to attack selectedenemy targets of military or economic significance; secondly, and even moreimportant, to create and foster the spirit of resistance to the Axis. The houndswill not. follow unless the horn is blown. Just as the Yugoslavs rallied round Titobecause he gave them the lead, and deserted the supine Mihailovic, so occupiedEurope gathered in ever-growing circles round trained S.O.E. agents who showedthem how they could strike blows for their liberty. German repression only addedfuel to the flames.20. A third result gradually emerged and proved of high importance to&quot; Overlord.&quot; The ferment created among the oppressed populations by thealternate process of sabotage and repression forced Hitler to spread his forcesall over Europe to protect his installations and to terrorise the populace. ThusD-day found the Germans insufficiently concentrated. How S.O.E. and theF.F.I. then assisted to delay the German concentration will be related later., O.S.S.21. In 1942 the entry of America into the war led to the formation of an american organisation under General Donovan (a prominent New York lawyer)known as O.S.S. with a directive analogous to those of S.O.E., S.I.S. and P.W.E.combined. It accordingly became important for S.O:E. to co-ordinate its activitieswith our new Allies, because nothing would have been more disastrous thancompeting and conflicting American &quot; lines &quot; over Europe. The task was not always easy. However, very cordial personal relations were established, and aco-ordination maintained which was facilitated by the fact that the americans were unable to provide any properly trained personnel, and until the last stageswere therefore obliged to leave nearly all the work to S.O.E. They could,however, contribute substantially to the large air lift required to prepare the&quot; field &quot; for D-day and their airborne resources were of very material help to theF.F.I. at that stage.The Tide Turns.22. By the beginning of 1943, S.O.E. had succeeded in establishing sub-versive groups in all the occupied countries of Western Europe. This had meant a great expansion of the Home organisation to meet the greatly increased demandfor services from abroad. New weapons had been devised and manufactured,and ever more powerful and smaller wireless sets camouflaged in many differentways. A camouflage factory was started to cater for the different conditions ofevery country. Not only wireless sets but all sorts of &quot; stores &quot; were camouflagedto assume the most innocent appearance. The improvement in the Allied fortuneshad given new hope. The will to resist had strengthened, and sabotage was onthe increase in Norway, Holland, Belgium and Denmark. In France the BritishSection was increasing the number of its circuits and intensifying their activities.The Fighting French organisation in the field had taken definite shape : theSupreme Resistance Council, presided over by a personal representative ofGeneral de Gaulle, controlled the civilian, political and military affairs of the resistance Movements through a rigid structure of Zonal and regional commitees; but while the political side of the work had progressed well, theefforts of S.O.E. to organise sabotage and paramilitary activities in co-operationwith Fighting French Headquarters had, except for the blowing up of RadioParis, met with little success. The effect of the invasion and liberation of north africa was to enhance the French sense of alliance and participation, and make ,available enlarged resources of personnel and new bases. The consequent german occupation of Southern France, while immediately disadvantageous as it resultedin many arrests, caused a powerful resurgence of Resistance feeling of which.O.E. was not slow to take advantage. In particular, the former Armee derArmistice now began to come into the open and to make contact with S.O.E.organisers (although on the understanding that General de Gaulle was not to beinformed of their position), and their numbers swelled the ranks of the resistantsby several thousand.1943 Plans.23. In their directive for 1943 the Chiefs of Staff, while still emphasising the paramount importance of planned sabotage, instructed S.O.E. to strengthen the paramilitary side of their organisations.    The importance of this side or
S.O.E. work was accordingly impressed upon the Governments of the occupied countries and upon the Resistance Movements themselves. In all the countries of western Europe the tempo of Resistance quickened, inspired, in part by the belief that the Allies would invade the continent that year. In France the ResistanceMovements showed more willingness to respond to directives on target priorities,and the rate of sabotage increased enormously. By the summer of 1943 the dailyaverage of blocks, rail cuts and derailments had risen to over 100, and this was accompanied by a seasonal outbreak of agricultural sabotage of crops, farmmachinery, &amp;c. Attacks on electricity installations, on German Detachments andcollaborators also increased, and S.O.E. were successful in carrying out two majorsabotage operations : the first against the Gigny barrage on the Saone, which prevented the transport southward of German naval craft for five weeks at thetime of the invasion of Sicily, and the second a concerted attack on the powersupply of Le Creusot. In order to save French lives, an agreement was reached with the Air Ministry that R.A.F. attacks on locomotives should cease, whileS.O.E., through its organisations in the &quot;field,&quot; instructed the railway workers to sabotage their own engines. This policy was to the mutual advantage of theFrench and of Fighter Command and proved very successful. Both the Britishand the Fighting- French circuits took part in the increased activity and theGiraudist groups of the Armee de 1&apos;Armistice were by now also fully operationalagainst the enemy.The Releve and the Maquis.24. About this time the Germans and Laval instituted the &apos;&apos; Releve &apos;&apos; underwhich Frenchmen were press-ganged to work in Germany.&apos; This development was particularly dangerous to Resistance, since it resulted in the removal to germany of the young men who were the most active element of the population, and manyof them chose outlawry in the mountains rather than deportation. S.O.E. policy was not to encourage open guerrilla warfare, since this was premature in everysense, but to contact such Maquis groups as had formed themselves in suitableareas and to supply them with sufficient material to maintain morale. Liaisonmissions of British, American and French officers were despatched to contact thelargest groups, particularly in the mountainous country East of the Rhone, with instructions to consolidate the sound elements and organise them for paramilitarywork.25. S.O.E. also forged many thousands of French Ration cards and provided many millions of French Francs (since repaid) to enable isolated refugees from the Releve to sustain themselves on farms with the help of elder men orwomen who were in this way enabled to buy necessaries on their behalf. Thus theMaquis movement came into being and continued to grow.26. Throughout 1943 the Air Ministry were able to place more aircraft a tour disposal and stores deliveries increased, although they never satisfied the enormous and growing appetite of the &quot;field.&quot; At the end of the year, anumber of aircraft based in North Africa were made available to S.O.E., andthese were able to niake deliveries to Southern France. Regular W/T com-munications were maintained and the links between the S.O.E. Headquarters andthe field were strengthened by the visits of S.O.E. officers to the field on toursof inspection.The Gestapo Strikes.27. The intensive activity in France during 1943 was certain, within thenormal cycle of Resistance, to provoke strong German counter-measures. In june the Gestapo struck : fifteen principalsvand several hundred subordinates of theFighting French organisation were arrested. General de Gaulle&apos;s personal representative is believed to have died under torture, and it became clear that theenemy, by infiltration and betrayal, had obtained extensive knowledge of thecentral set up of the Gaullist organisation and of its leaders. At the same time a concentrated Gestapo drive succeeded in breaking up the very important British-i controlled circuit based on Paris, but&quot; insomuch as the essence of the S.O.E.I system Avas control from London by W/T and watertight circuits in France, the! penetration was confined to that area and the rest of the British organisation wasI unimpaired.28. Officers sent from England to the Fighting French organisation were able to hold together the essential elements of Reception Committees and com-munications, and S.O.E. took advantage of the occasion to insist on the institution of a new system on a regional basis, avoiding the over-centralisation which we had
constantly criticised and whose failure had been so disastrous. In the case of theBritish Section, an S.O.E. officer was sent to Paris to review the position, andas a result of his report, part of the old group was reconstituted, while arrange-ments were made for the despatch of new organisers to that area. The blow wasa severe one, especially in its effect on paramilitary activities, but Resistance isextraordinarily resilient and the wave of sabotage did not abate.low Countries and Scandinavia.29. In the other countries of Western Europe the story was, in general,the same. Severe losses were inflicted in Belgium, Norway&apos; and Denmark, andparticularly in Holland where the Gestapo were successful in penetrating ourorganisation and working the W/T communications for some time before theywere discovered. New organisers were, however, sent to the field, to restart thework. Throughout the year sabotage&apos;&apos; increased, and in Denmark especially a major campaign was planned and carried out with marked success.30. Our chief organiser in Denmark is a remarkable man. At the time ofthe invasion of his country he was engaged in commerce in a -British colony, andwas at once interned by the British authorities as a possible Fifth Columnist.Having cleared himself after several months&apos; effort, he obtained his release and ultimately succeeded in working his passage to this country. Directly he arrived in England he was, of course, taken over by the Royal Patriotic Schools, and againplaced in detention, from which he was rescued by the head of the S.O.E. DanishSection on the look out for new recruits. A long period of intensive trainingfollowed in which his outstanding qualities manifested themselves and he wasgiven a British commission. It was not until April 1943. that he was droppedinto Denmark, and by August he had the whole country ablaze. He has wellearned the D.S.O. which has been awarded him.Corsica.31. As the campaign in Italy developed, the rare opportunity presenteditself of a small-scale dress rehearsal for &quot; Overlord.&quot; Corsica had been allotted to S.O.E. as a field of action because the shortage of shipping precluded a regularinvasion. Conditions were ideal. &quot;Maquis&quot; is a Corsican word meaning thegreat tracts of mountainous scrub that exist in that island, the population largelyconsist of high-spirited hereditary guerillas, and the bulk of the occupying forces were second-grade Italians. After an initial set-back, the man was found whowould unite the activities of all the clans and parties, and the organisation andarming of the groups from the Algiers base (by submarine as well as by aircraft)went forward rapidly. When the Italian surrender came, S.O.E. struck, and theGermans had no longer any possibility of holding the island. The Corsicans rosethroughout the country and inflicted some 2,000 casualties on the withdrawingenemy. British prestige rose to the embarrassing point that many Corsicansdemanded that their country should join the British Empire!&quot; Overlord &quot; Planning.32. The first and most difficult task in the organisation of Resistance the raising of morale from the slough of Vichy defeatism, and the establishment of widespread circuits sufficiently deep-rooted to survive the Gestapo inquisitions had by now in the main been accomplished. In the autumn of 1943 the Chiefsof Staffs directives to S.O.E. began to place increasing emphasis on the assistance that could be given by Resistance to the military invasion of the Continent, and accordingly S.O.E. planning became orientated more and more towards D-day.In September, pending the appointment of the Supreme Commander, S.O.E. in western Europe was placed under the operational control of COSSAC, underwhose direction (and later that of S.H.A.E.F.) all plans were thenceforth drawnup. In January 1944 the appropriate sections of S.O.E. and of O.S.S. wereintegrated to constitute a combined Headquarters covering Resistance in western europe, later known as Special Force&apos; Headquarters (S.F.H.Q.). A similarintegration was effected at Algiers to cover the A.F.H.Q. area.Preliminary Phase.33. S.O.E. assistance to &quot;Overlord&quot; was divided into two stages preliminary attacks on the German war machine in the West, and preparations for action on and after the assault. For the former, S.O.E. already had the means to hand for normal sabotage work, and during the six months before D-day
activities were intensified and directed against targets according to their priority.The efforts of the Germans to repair the damage gave evidence of the importanceof the targets, many of which were attacked again when repaired, thus adding tothe strain imposed on the enemy. Industrial works of value to the German army were attacked by groups in the field and by special coup-de-main parties; dozensof factories, especially aluminium, ball-bearing, rubber and liquid oxygen, weresabotaged. Between September 1943 and June 1944, 98 major attacks were carried out against vital industrial plants, and thousands of t minor acts of sabotage contributed to the further disorganisation of the German war effort.A &quot;Blackmail&quot; campaign run in conjunction with Bomber Command was successful in inducing a number of factory managements to sabotage their ownfactories rather than suffer air bombing, the Peugeot Motor Works and theTimken ball-bearing factory, amongst others, being put out of action in this manner. Attacks on communications were given high priority, and the intensifiedcampaign against locomotives achieved considerable success. By D-day 1,000locomotives had been sabotaged, for the most part by the railway men themselves.In addition, there were innumerable attacks on turntables, cranes and other railtargets and countless derailments and rail cuts. In Denmark on two occasionssystematic rail cutting over a wide area paralysed traffic for several days. Themain inland water-way systems of Belgium and France were continually underattack, and considerable disorganisation was caused by the frequent closing of key canals. The Rhine-Rhone traffic, already once suspended by the destructionof the Gigny barrage in the summer of 1943, was once more held up by a second attack in January. At one moment M.E.W. and the Admiralty reported that only one water-way remained open to serve the important industrial North-east of France, and within a few days S.O.E. succeeded in cutting that last link also.34. Electricity installations were favourite targets : in the nine months before D-day, 52 major attacks on transformers were carried out, at least fivepower stations were damaged, and hundreds of high-tension cables and pylonswere destroyed. Particularly effective were attacks on the hydro electric powersupplies for Paris. Many factories were forced to close down as a result of thereduction in electricity output and the difficulties of distribution thus effected.German transport plans were correspondingly embarrassed by the consequentexhaustion of coal stocks. Attacks on petrol and oil were high in priority, andmany reports were received of the sabotage of trains, motor transport and ships carrying these materials. One particular instance is reported of 300,000 litres of oil and 200,000 litres of petrol being destroyed.35. S.O.E. had been asked to carry out sabotage designed to impede theG.A.F., but it was found impossible to attack German aircraft on their airfields.Nine major attacks were, however, carried out on factories making aircraft parts and accessories, of which an outstanding example was the sabotage of the Ratierairscrew factory at Toulouse, as a result of which the Germans lost an output of300 variable pitch airscrews per month. Shipping was attacked throughout theperiod, particularly in the Scandinavian countries. In the nine months beforeD-day a total of 18 ships were sunk, 14 in Denmark and 4 in Norwegian ports.Most of this was achieved by &apos;&apos; Limpets &apos;&apos; which are time-fuse operated bombsthat adhere to ship&apos;s bottoms under water by powerful magnets. They are placedin position while the ships are in harbour by divers or men leaning over the sides of rowing boats on dark nights.36. Every effort was made to weaken German morale by propaganda, by thedistribution of false Ration Cards and by more direct attacks. In France aloneconfirmation was received of the execution by Resistance of 103 Gestapo agents and 51 collaborators, and the derailment, with heavy casualties, of at least12 troop trains. The evidence of captured German documents seems to show thata large measure of success was achieved by these attacks, and the Germans became increasingly conscious and afraid of the unrelenting hostility of the populations ofthose countries they had professed to &quot; liberate.&quot; The dispersal of enemy troops and their concentration in areas removed from the bridgehead became one of themost important tasks demanded of S.O.E. Unrest and sabotage throughoutoccupied territories forced the Germans not only to maintain their forces oftroops and police in these countries, but also to disperse them widely in the townsand villages to enable them to maintain order and protect installations. In areas where the Maquis had already started overt resistance, they were forced to mountpunitive expeditions during which they suffered appreciable casualties. in denmark there was a garrison of 4 divisions in August 1943. By January this had been increased to 6, by March to 8, and in August 7 divisions were still there.[28366] c
Increased Airlift.37. The second phase of S.O.E. assistance to &quot; Overlord,&quot; covering activitieson and after D-day, involved first the preparation of reserved plans aiming athampering and obstructing enemy reinforcement movements, principally by the disruption, at a given moment, of his communications wherever vulnerable,whether by road, rail, telephone or telegraph; and secondly the establishment in suitable areas of forces equipped to undertake guerrilla warfare and so to divertenemy troops from the bridgehead during the vital period immediately afterD-day. To carry out this S.H.A.E.F. directive, it was essential that deliveries of supplies, to the field should be vastly increased. At the beginning of the yeartwo squadrons of Liberators were allotted to O.S.S.: this brought our resourcesup to a total of four squadrons based in England. In addition, a very Largesupplementary effort from Bomber Command (3 Group) and A.E.A.F. (38 Group)was made available early in the year at the direction of the Prime Minister.Deliveries were aimed at covering the reserved D-day plans as first priority,while the supplementary effort was employed principally on operations to theMaquis areas of South-East and Central France. It was no simple matter toincrease deliveries at such a rate. Many new reception committees were immediately required and it took them some time to become efficient at thedrill. About 5 per cent, of the large deliveries of arms fell into the hands ofthe Germans who had taken to stationing false reception committees at likelyspots with torches which they flashed at aircraft. But in spite of these setbacksand of very bad weather a steadily mounting total of stores was despatched andcontainers were now counted by the thousand instead of by tihe hundred. in planning and supply, priority was naturally given to France.The Maquis&apos;s Part.38. Resistance groups in the immediate coastal zones could not be countedupon to give much assistance, owing to the presence of so many enemy troops,and this, had also made their equipment specially difficult. Efforts were there-fore concentrated on building up Resistance in the areas of German localreserves, with the object of interfering with the movements of enemy armourby causing serious dislocation on the railways and roads; and in the strategic,back area for the attack on supply dumps, installations and headquarters. Onthe instructions of the Prime Minister, special attention had been paid to build-ing up strong Resistance Forces in the mountainous country east of the Rhonevalley in order to cause a major diversion; while, at the same time, preparations were made for the-development of large Maquis groups in other suitable areas such as the Vosges, Massif Central and Brittany.Penetration of Administrations.39. In the other countries of Western Europe Resistance was developed and maintained at full strength in order to force the Germans to retain large troopformations in these areas, and to aid deception. Resistance there was not intendedto be called into the open, but was to continue with sabotage and clandestineactivities, thus constituting a constant threat of a large-scale rising in the enemy&apos;srear. In the Low Countries activities were concentrated against enemy communi-cations, and in Scandinavia against the enemy&apos;s production of war material.40. In all countries another technique was being developed at the same time the penetration of administrative services such as police, fire-brigades, railwaymanagement or unions. In every country the transport workers were in the vanof Resistance and their organisations directed the campaign. A telling example of the unobtrusive technical sabotage carried out by the railwaymen came to lightwhen a Canadian officer visited the round house at Dieppe immediately after itscapture in order to re-establish transport on the important supply route toNeufchatel. Six engines were in the shed, all bearing placards stating theirdefects; the minimum repair period was stated at three months. As the officer wasexpressing his disgust the foreman came into the shed and took down the placards,saying &quot;Pour les Allies demain soir.&quot; The police were more patchy, thoughoften helpful, and in Denmark constituted an invaluable shield. These types of activity were the most difficult for the Germans to combat, and their results cannotbe assessed even now, though the important part played by the police was demon-demonstrated in the liberation of Paris.The Eve of D-day.41.   By the beginning of June 1944 three main plans for action againstrailways, roads and telecommunications were ready in detail.   In France 570
railway targets, 30 road cuts on important routes and 32 telecommunicationtargets were prepared for immediate action, while a very large number, inaddition, had been planned and would be executed if the necessary explosives and weapons could be delivered. Each plan had its general stand-by message and each individual target its action message all to be transmitted over the B.B.C. In theMaquis areas, Resistance was prepared and eager for open warfare against theenemy. It was estimated that the French forces of Resistance numbered 276,000,of which 152,000 were armed. The French had at last learned the necessity for local devolution and for despatching good officers to take command, and inspec-tions by French and British officers found efficiency rapidly improving.- 42. In Belgium the two main Resistance organisations, one military andone &quot; civil,&quot; were ready to play their part. The Belgian plan was divided into three phases : (i) Clandestine sabotage of the key railways, telecommunications and bridges.(ii) General harassing action by independent sabotage and minor guerrilla,  action.(iii) Guerrilla warfare based on chosen strong points or laagers under thecomplete control of the military organisation.The total strength of Resistance in Belgium was returned at 65,000, of whom ithad only been possible to arm 7-8,000.43. Attempts to contact the Dutch Resistance Movements after the breakup of the organisation in that country had failed and it was therefore impossibleto make any forward plans for their employment. In Norway 20,000 and in denmark 18,000 men w^ere ready for action, but of these only approximately one-quarter were armed. The days of preparation were over and Resistancethroughout occupied Europe was awaiting the call to action.&quot; Jedbtjrghs.&quot;44. Plans were also made for establishing adequate liaison with the variousmilitary formations operating in the field and to this end &quot; Special Force &quot; staffs of British, Canadian and American officers were recruited and trained for attach-ment to Army Groups and Armies. The functions of these Staffs were to providethe commander of the formation to- which they were attached with informa-tion and advice on resistance and its potentialities, and to send back toS.F.H.Q. indications of operations which would assist the armies. On the otherhand, in order to guard against the possibility of a breakdown of communications with the field, specially trained reserves were prepared and held ready in Englandand North Africa. These were of four types : small teams of British, Frenchand American officers with a W/T operator named &quot; Jedburghs,&quot; who could be dropped to Resistance Groups needing assistance, and whose function was toprovide leadership, W/T communications and up-to-date orders from S.F.H.Q.;American Operational Groups, consisting of highly trained paratroops with/T operators; &quot; Bardsea &quot; teams who could be sent to reinforce the PolishResistance groups in the Lille area of Northern France, where some 200,000 Poleswork in the mines; and lastly, a number of trained organisers who were held in readiness for special missions.&apos;The B.B.C. Calls.45. By the Spring of 1944 arms deliveries had become so frequent that the&quot; messages personnels &quot; on&apos; the B.B.C. were distributed over their transmissionsto France at 1330, 1430, 1930 and 2115 hours. To these the leaders of the resistance Groups used to listen whenever they could, not only when they wereexpecting a despatch of arms to their group, but also because they knew that inthis way they would be warned when the&apos;Allied invasion was coming. each group had its allotted targets and each was expecting a &apos;&apos; stand-by &apos;&apos; message aswell as a subsequent &quot; action &quot; message.46. At 1-30 p.m. on the afternoon of the 1st June, 1944, the Resistanceleaders listening to their home wireless sets or to the midget communicationsreceivers which S.O.E. had sent out for the purpose, suddenly heard the messagethey had memorised for months, and which S.H.A.E.F. had now instructed S.O.E.to transmit. It was the &quot; Stand-by! &quot; Could it at last be true? The wordquickly went round. More ears were listening to the 2-30 p.m. broadcast and again there was the &quot; Stand-by.&quot;  It was repeated at 7 - 30 p.m. and at 9 -15 p.m.[28366] d
The next- day on all four transmissions the same &apos;&apos; Stand-by &apos;&apos; messages camealong. Even then Resistance Groups could scarcely believe it. The date hadbeen so long postponed; the Germans seemed so strong. But they made theirpreparations, their targets were reconnoitred, their arms were dug up from theirhiding places. Then came the 3rd June. There were plenty of &quot;messagespersonnels,&quot; but none of them were &quot;stand-by&quot; or &quot;action&quot; messages. Thesame thing occurred on the 4th June. What had happened?. Had the planmiscarried? Was.the weather in the channel too bad? Everyone was listeningagain at.l -30 p.m. on the 5th June, but again there were no &quot; stand-by &quot; messagesand no &quot; action &quot; messages. The next two transmissions were the same. Thenat 9-15 p.m. on the evening of the 5th June there came the &quot; action &quot; messages,which Resistance had been waiting for for three years and more. The hour had at last come!47. Resistance went into action at once; the transition between the twophases, from sabotage to guerrilla warfare, was clearly marked by the executionof D-day plans. In France, where the greatest immediate effort was expected,Resistance was now united into a single federation as the &quot; Forces Franchises delTnterieur &quot; E.F.I. -and its command was vested by S.H.A.E.F. in GeneralKoenig and passed out of the direct operational control of S.F.H.Q. and of S.O.E.48.. The great gamble was no longer on the spirit nor even on the prepared-ness of the French, but on the German reaction. Would they, in anticipation orconcurrently, take such repressive and punitive methods as to overwhelmResistance entirely ? In the event the Germans reacted as tardily and inefficientlyagainst the interior as against the exterior enemy. This, combined with theincreased supplies and a wave of enthusiasm throughout the occupied countries,ensured a degree of success beyond the dreams even of S.O.E.The F.F.I. Strike.49. In France the D-day plans were executed with efficiency and despatch-Prearranged railway targets were attacked all over the country, and the generalchaos was enhanced by spontaneous acts. The local congestion built up valuabletargets for the Air Force; for instance,&apos;at Lille 51 trains were held up at once.Messages from the field reported 486 successful rail cuts in France and thederailment of 180 German trains in the immediately post-D-day period.Moreover, this level of sabotage was maintained. In mid-July the nine mainarteries in the North were still being cut from two to five times daily; and by august 668 locomotives had been destroyed and 2,900 attacks on railways hadbeen reported. The confusion on the railways drove the enemy to the employ-ment of road transport, and here again the F.F.I. were waiting for them.Signposts were changed round to point the wrong way; in many places the tallpoplar trees that ornament French roads were felled across them; scores of thousands of midget mines the size of a pill-box, designed in the S.O.E. researchstation and known as &quot; tyre bursters &quot; (which make a hole the size of an orangein any tyre that passes over them), were strewn on all the roads the Germans were likely to use. Convoys of vehicles and marching troops suffered numerouscasualties in ambushes, and were continually forced to halt and drive back thepatriot forces before proceeding. By August 220 important road and rail bridgeshad been either destroyed or badly damaged and traffic everywhere wasslowed down.50. The third D-day plan was also being executed. By August 380 cuts ontelecommunications had been reported and numerous power lines had been putout of action, particularly those converging on Bordeaux, Tarbes, Lyons, Dole,Le Mans, Orleans, Lille and Paris. At the request of 21 Army Group, successful attacks were carried out by Resistance on military telecommunications in theimmediate neighbourhood of the bridgehead at such centres as St. Lo, Avranches,Caen, Rouen and Amiens, and the enemy was forced to make extensive use of wireless for operational matters.The German Pinned.51. The effect of this activity, combined with the action of the Allied AirForces, was tremendous. The German troops moving to the bridgehead area foundtheir communications everywhere in a state of chaos, and it was estimated thatthe normal delay on the forward movement of their advance was between 48 and72 hours, while in exceptional cases it was much longer. When they finally reachedthe battle area, they were frequently in a state of considerable disorganisation,short of vehicles, equipment and men. The experiences of the &apos;&apos; Das Reich &apos;&apos;Division ordered from Toulouse to the battle area were typical.  Its first elements
left the Toulouse area on D-day: but the last elements, of the Division did not reach the St. Lo area until D *17. The total distance involved was approximately450 miles and it has been estimated that the greater part of this Division tooktwice or even three times as long to do this journey than it would normally havedone. Much of the credit for the delay imposed must go to Resistance, for thereis ample evidence that the Division was directly attacked and delayed by theF.F.I. in the early stages of its move before it was affected by air attacks. one german company, which took the easterly route, fought the F.FT. at Tulle and again at another point further North. They hanged 80 prisoners in the firstengagement and&apos;shot 200 after the second. Another element of four companieswas attacked on the 9th June some. 10 miles North of Tours. In the course of aprotracted fight, which held up the enemy for three days, 20 F.F.I. were taken prisoner and later hanged. The 4 S.S. Panzer Gren. Regt. left Montauban byroad on D + 2 and took nearly two weeks to reach Normandy-a delay almostentirely due to diversions forced upon them by the F.F.I. At Limoges on the10th June the Regiment encountered an F.F.I. force approximately 10,000 strong.This force had destroyed a number of bridges and was trying to occupy the town.On the previous day the Regiment had sent a detachment to the aid of one of itsbattalions which had been surrounded by approximately 4,000 F.F.I. at Gueret,50 miles to the N.W. It was not until the 14th June that the battalion was ableto leave for Tours, a delay of five days. The detachment then returned to Limogesto rejoin the main body. Meanwhile the battalion commander of III Bn. hadbeen kidnapped whilst passing through a village 20 miles S.W. of Limoges, andthe battalion spent three days in a useless search. It is believed that this was the incident which caused the Germans to perpetrate the most wholesale and deliberateof their atrocities in France, the massacre of Oradour-sur-Glane.The Maquis Rises.52. Meanwhile, in areas where Resistance was ordered to remain clandestine,.continued successful sabotage was carried out and over ninety sujch attacks were made in the post D-day period, covering a wide range of targets. Inother regions, such as Brittany, the Massif Central, the Morvan, the Jura andthe Savoy Alps, Resistance was becoming stronger and more active. &quot; Jedburghs &quot;were despatched to many areas and most successfully fulfilled their role ofleavening the mass and focussing its activities. The value of a well-briefedLiaison Officer was illustrated in the surrender of General Elster and his 18,000troops at Beaugency, where the&quot;&quot; Jedburgh &quot; was largely responsible for thetriangular negotiations between the American and German Commanders and theF.F.I.53. On a higher level, and to cover wider areas, special Liaison Missionswere sent to co-ordinate and control activities. The arrival of these Alliedofficers in the field at this stage strengthened the links between S.H.A.E.F. andthe F.F.I. and ensured that the full weight of Resistance was directed inaccordance with military requirements instead of being dispersed andunco-ordinated. Large numbers of enemy troops were contained by these Maquisgroups. Where major German formations were directed against specific areas as in Correze and the Vercors (where the enemy employed parachute troops) theMaquis were broken up and dispersed; but in general, it was the Germans whowere on the run, and wherever true guerrilla&quot; tactics were used the F.F.I. were able to inflict casualties at an average rate of perhaps five to one. In all these directions the F.F.I. reached a crescendo of activity in the course of which theyfreed many towns and wrought incalculable damage to German transport,signals and supplies. -54. In selected&apos; areas the Special Air Service, whose activities were co-ordinated through an S.A.S. Liaison Section at S.F.H.Q., were also using the help of Resistance to execute their intensive tasks. In Brittany a joint S.A.S./S.F.H.Q. effort resulted in a general rising of the French, which assumed suchproportions that all organised opposition was absorbed, and the advance of theThird United States Army was considerably assisted.&quot;The Belgians Act.55. On the flank of the landing, the Belgians, though sadly underequipped,were also playing their part with proportionately even greater success. Betweenthe 10th and 20th June, 153 sabotage operations were carried out, including ahigh proportion of railway and road obstructions. Sabotage of telecommunications-tions was widespread and effective.  During July clandestine attacks on all types
of communications increased, 800 rail cuts were reported together with 42 derail-ments and the destruction or damage of 65 railway and road bridges. In the scandinavian countries^ Resistance was not called into the open, but clandestinesabotage was continued. In Norway, attacks were carried, out against petrol and oil stocks. In Denmark, the tension prevailing as a result of the Allied invasionand the increase of sabotage culminated during the first week of July in aspontaneous general strike in Copenhagen, in which the German authorities were forced to give way to the demands of the Freedom Council.56. By D -f- 6 or 7, Resistance had already accomplished its primary taskin &quot; Overlord.&quot; From then on, the increasing weight of extra supplies and the stimulus of the Allied successes made themselves felt in growing guerrilla pressure on the German movements. Large-scale deliveries of stores were made to the mostimportant Maquis areas in daylight by the 8th U.S.A.A.F. and the build-up of resistance continued. Indeed, restraining the F.F.I. from precipitate actionbecame quite a problem. It is not possible to assess accurately the casualtiesinflicted on the enemy by Resistance, but claims amount to about 30,000 killed and wounded, and 35,000 prisoners.General Koenig in Charge.57. Resistance was able to help in other ways to an unexpected degree.Counter-scorching plans succeeded in preserving important bridges and port facilities, especially in the south of France and at Antwerp. ExperiencedResistance elements showed an aptitude for infiltration through the enemy linesfor tactical purposes. Resistance also assumed direct military functions of a secondary order. Thanks to the unification of command on a military basis under General Koenig, the F.F.I. were increasingly entrusted with the task of dealingwith the Germans overrun in the speed of the advance and generally acting asflank guards and communication troops. This task became very important as thesweep of the United States 3rd Army developed. By the date of the landing onthe Riyiera, the F.F.I were dealing practically unaided with the whole of central and South-West France.58. The later thrusts in the British area were similarly supported byResistance in Belgium and, according to its limited scope, in Holland. Only inthe Ardennes was guerrilla action ordered, but rounding-up activities developedclose behind the drive, and in Belgium the Resistance forces proved to have a stronger internal discipline than the French and therefore were better adapted to fill their ancillary role. A successful railway strike in Holland and the provisionby Resistance of a secret underground telephone line, which later was for sometime the only means of communication between the 1st Airborne Division atArnhem and 30 Corps, were most important contributions to the exploitation ofthe military situation.59. In fulfilment of the tasks allotted to them, Resistance everywhereachieved a degree of success that is partly to be accounted for by the.weakness andpreoccupation of the Germans. But the main factor was, as it always must be,the courage and zeal of the patriots and of the gallant officers who organised andled them. The long delay before the Allied invasion of Europe had proveddisheartening to the Resistance groups, and had afforded opportunity to the gestapo to penetrate many and break up a few of them; but in every other respect the time-factor was favourable and helped in the solution of the basic problems of organisation and supply. Particularly valuable was the progressive. stretchingof German effort and man-power in all directions, with the result that theirreaction on D-day was feeble and suffered from crucial delay. Upon the founda-tions laid by S.O.E. from 1940 onwards, and strengthened in the three years before the invasion, strong and flexible Resistance organisations had been built up in- every country of Western Europe, ready to play their part in the liberation of their countries. When the time came, the courage, devotion and discipline ofthese patriot forces proved to be an important factor in the success of the Alliedinvasion. It is worth reflecting on what might have been the situation had therebeen no organisation thinking of and working for these gallant men during the darkyears from 1940 onwards. It was the knowledge that there was someone in the free world outside Festung Europa who had not forgotten them and who was trying tohelp them see the light at the end of the tunnel which kept Resistance alive. Thefact that the spirit of Resistance in Europe did not die during four bitter yearsof occupation may well be looked.upon as the major contribution of S.O.E. to theAllied cause.



</content>
</cab>
