<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 12-12</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W&apos; - &quot;-Swiss,  / t &apos;\ his Document  5s  theHis Britannic tf:Circulated by the Secretary of State for India,\ I. lor *-SECRET.               l/rom Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department, S//i March 191.9.^^TjTqn^^^^                ^ece&apos;ve(&apos; ^^n&apos;       a,m*)         -Secret.  Our telegram of  the 7th March.  Afghanistan,  it  is confirmed that      Nasrulla  and Inayatulla and  all Sardars  left for Kabul early in the week.   Only      normal staff remains at Jalalabad.  It is believed  in  Peshawar that British Agent      also left for  Kabul this week, which would explain the non-receipt of reports  from      him  after 2nd March.   According to travellers by last caravan  from Kabul  all is      quiet in  Kabul  and  Europeans  are not  interfered with in any way.  All reported      quiet in  Kandahar up to 3rd  March.   Sulaiinan Khel(s) jirga  now assembled at      Sandeman appears apathetic.  We have received nothing from Amaiiulla,  Nor has      Afghan Envoy.                        From Viceroy, L2th March 1919.                          (Received 1.7th, 12.30 p.m.)    Secret.  My telegram of  11th March.  Afghanistan.   Telegram of 11th Marchfrom British Agent, who has apparently proceeded to Kabul, reports that all is quietand that Europeans  are safe  and returning to  India under adequate protection.Messengers arriving from Kabul by caravan report that all was  quiet when  they left,that Europeans were going  about freely, and that Amir has not  yet seen Nasrulla andInayatulla, who are under surveillance.  Habibuila&apos;s mother is said to be striving forand Ulya Hazrat to be opposing reconciliation between Amir and  Nasrulla.   Soldiersin Jalalabad are reported anxious at non-receipt of  confirmation of increase of pay toRs. 20.  Lack  of news from Kabul has made Afghan officials anxious and  suspiciousthat their private letters are being intercepted.

</content>
</cab>
