<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 55-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
aaORET,                   WAR OABIHFTlrT.7ClO.,       COFflNuMCE OF EMERGENCY LEGISLASflOB./(,0&apos;W.of a- iotter from Sir William Graham Greene  to-tho Secretary of tho Homo Affaire Comaittoe).                                  Ministry of imiiticna of War,                                       Whitehall  lace,                                            S.YM.                                      20th March, 1919.Dear Lieutenant Evans,     On looking at  the draft of tho Bill to provide for tho eon-tinuance of War 3mergenoy Legislation which has Just boon olroulot-sd,I notice that one or two slight alterations which wore suggested to the Secretary of Lord Cave1 a. Committee ha\re not been made.   I attach a copy of tho correspondence Which passed between myself andMr.Kemp at the time, and you will soo that ho accepted certainalterations which were made in the Roport, but which were not also at the seme tine- made in the Schedule to the Bill.   the alteration in the Bill which should have boon mado to correspond with the amendment in tho Report Is mainly that affectingRegulation 45 on;Pago 17.   The limitation should read - &quot;exceptparagraphs (003) end (t)) of.sub-s-ootion (1)&quot;.   As you will noticefrom tho correspondence, ^r, emp agreed that    .ah.oxi.ll be retainedand not oxooptcd as shewn in the draft.      There is also another alteration affecting 8A on Pago 13which is mainly a question of drafting.   The Priority of WorkGrdcr has now undergone the modification contemplated at thedate of ay letter to Mr.Komp,  aTid it would be preferred that thelimitation should run as follows:-          &quot;So fsr as related to orders as to priority of work           in force at the passing of this. Act&quot;.     I notice in tho text of the Bill on Pago 3 on line 32,  the word&quot;of&quot; should,  I think, bo &quot;or&quot;.     I have mentioned these alterations to Sir Frederick Liddoll,but he says that the matter is now in your.hands  and ho wishedmo to mention it to you.                       Believe me,                            Yours very truly,                                 (S igno d) W *GRAHAM GRSEHE.Li outenant G M Evan s.     Ass&apos;GuBonrrot&amp;ry to the War Cabinet,         2,  Wh i t eh al 1 Gar dens ,  S rW-,1.mJk^miJ^W^mmn. iff, his britapio majesty;s tvmmm),&apos;

</content>
</cab>
