<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 199-201</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Cove mm.(463)fNATIONAL FACTORIES&apos; TO BE RETAINED UKPBRQJ^^jglNT CONTROL AS A NUCLEUS OF ARMAHgHT PRODUCTION,        Hien last the Far Cabinet din cussed, onFebruary 14th, the question of the disposal of national factories, and in particular of the &quot;factories known as necessary for the Government to retain permanent control)it was decided that                 %&quot;The Minister of Munitions should re-examine the provision for shell-filling, in the light of the above discussion.   (Yfar Cabinet Minutes 653 (i)  ).A Departmental memorandum on the subject isattached,        In view of the largo stocks which arc at presentin hand,.. I consider that the shell and cartridge fillingcapacity which it is proposed to retain at Voolwich,Hereford, Banbury and. Gloucester, taken in conjunctionwith the arrangements which are being made to retain a balanced proportion of the plant at the three factorieshanded over to the War Office (Georgetown, Aintree andChilvrell), will provide an ample margine of security andthat the decision arrived at by tho Cabinet, as to theretention of Class A factories, on the above date calls for no modification,Class A factories (i.e. those over which it might prove24.iiie19.
MEMORANDUM ON CAPACITY RETAINED FORSHELL AND CARTRIDGE FILLING.        The proved Filling Capacity of the Shell and. CartridgeFilling Plants expressed in tons of I-    &quot;or Tropellants filledweekly was as follows :-&quot; &apos;TTF.        ;R.L.Cartridges;H.E,    i (inciudinc 4.5&quot;);  Assembly(tons)  I     (tonsT_I (Number)National factories which.Ij^ is proposed to retainWoolwich                   200Hereford                 1,075Gloucester                  20Banbury .                  - 160National Factories handedover to the War OfficeChilwellGeorgetownLiverpool (Aintree)Other National FactoriesHayesLeedsTho TradeTOTAL3505501J500  310  450  175  5504/440760590270: 1,0,50120,000120,0003,570170,000150,000 70,000200,000-130,000960,000Average Aotual FilledWeekly in 3rd Qr. of 191812,9502,550844,000           Of this capacity, it has been decided&apos;to retain(with the plant in situ) that at Woolwich, Hereford, Banburyand Gloucester ( except s hell filling at this Factory)&apos;! while,the hydraulic presses at Chilwcll are also being kept forthe presents  Thus the shell filling capacity which it isproposed permanently to retain ariounts to 1,435 tons weekly .or 32/i of the War Capacity.    The Cartridge filling  ,capacity to be retained amounts to 900 tons or 25^. These figures
are respectively     and 35/6 of the average weekly amountsactually filled during the third quarter of 1918*  In addition,Hereford and Banbury between them would fill 250 ton3 of Lydditeper week into Shells *  If 18-pd.r. block oharges made at Herefordare supplied to Gloucester the capacity of Woolwich and Gloucestertogether for assembling CUP1, Ammunition amounts to 25^ of theWar Capacity^     It should be remarked, however, that filling capacityexpressed as a tonnage varies considerably in accordance withthe particular natives and types of shells and cartridges dealtwith, and. that If plant were changed over to filling other naturesthan those for which it was intended there would be a loss of efficiency.-   -  Gloucester is at present being utilised mainly as anexplosives store, but will probably be required for breakingdown ammunition.in the near future.  Woolwich, Hereford, andBanbury are all engaged on breaking down ammunitiono  In theirpresent state these factories could revert to filling almost as fast as the labour could be taken on and trained and should reach full capacity within six months *     Arrangements are being made for retaining during the transition period a&apos; balanced proportion of the Plant at thePilling Factories handed over to the ^ar Office, viz;- Georgetown,Aintree and Chiiwell, without interfering with their use forAmy purposes.-                                  - &apos; -    ..   -     It should bo stated that the&apos;filled aimnunition. in stockin this&apos; country and &apos; all&quot;Theatre3 of. War, would last about 21weeks at the-, average rate of expenditure,obtaining during tholast.year of the War*

</content>
</cab>
