<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 229-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT&apos;-.25th March 1919.WAR CABINET.ordination of Demobilisation Section).   WEEKLY APPRECIATION No.12.DEMOBILISATION.The following table shows tho progress of demobilisation:-Branch.NumbersDemobilisedw.0.13.3.19,NumbersDemobilisedw.e.20,3.19.Total NumbersDemobilised to20,3.19.Off,   O.R.Off.   O.R.Off.   O.R.NAVYARMYR.A.P.  436  9,1743,375 91,247  914 .10,488 .  3893,819  677 7,73186,23910,365 6,245  144,71949,984 1 67,101 7,018  143,961.TOTAL.4,725 110,6094,885  104,335    63,247 2,155,781Strength as at 11th November 1918.Branch.Officers.Other Ranks,Total, All Ranks,NAVYARMYR.A.P, 37,850162,866 27,100  360,0003,583,258  251,000  39V,8503,746,124  278,100.TOTAL.277,8164,194,2584,422,074.       The general rate of demobilisation continues to.decline,       The total number demobilised weekly (all arms and all ranks)for the last four weeks was as followsWeeks snding27.2.1919 6.3.191913r3.191920.5,1919Number.170,535150,418115,634109,220.
       Further progress has  been made in the release of DomobiUsersland Pivotal Men,  viziNames putforward by labour Dept.ReleaseOrdersissued.Numbersactually knownto be releasedj/iRMY x R.A.F.     tol20th March.Pivotal Menbemobilisers211,933 60,46211/ 2 ^311 43,64764,736*56,661*TOTAL:272 ,395241,558101,397NAVY to20th March.Pivotal MenDemob i Users.15,076 3,00913,129)2,776 )12,948.TOTAL:18.08515,90512,943.              The  figure  given here  represents  the  number  of           dispersal  certificates  of Pivotal  Men and  Demobilisers           analysed to  date,  i.e., roughly 84$.      The analysis of dispersal  certificates  shews  that  the follow-ing  industries and  occupations have received a large influx oflabour from the  Forces*-        Industry.Coal &amp; Shale MiningEngineeringAgricultureCommercial &amp; ClericalBrick &amp; Building TradesRa1lw a ys &amp; Transport.    Total Analysed% of total demobilised).230,000233,000174,000236 ,000170/000JNIMPLOYMBNT .       The  total number of Ou.t-of-v!ork Donation Policies remaininglodged  on the 14th March amounted to 988,619,  and of those Policies52.Af arc h:Id by women and girls,  25.9,;&apos; by members of H.K.Forces,and  23.if by civilian men and boys.    The total of 988,619 shows a decrease  of 3,613 on tho previous  week&apos;s figu.ro., 992,252 (amended).       This decrease may be attributed to three causes, viz:-       (1)  Stoppage of donation in Ireland under the revised                                              regulations.       (2)  Stoppage of donation in Gt.Britain in consequence of               scouting in comparison with ration books recently               carried out.       (5)  Increase of civilian policies that have exhausted theI              first 78 days&apos; donations are awaiting decision as               to extension.
-3-     Details will be f-mnd In the Appendix of the unemploymentin Industries covered by the 1911 and 1916 Acts and in uninsuredIndustries.              ?ercentago of. Unomployment in Industries              cov4rea&quot;&quot;by&apos; the. Acts of. 1911 and&quot;T916&apos;r&apos;&quot;           21st February   .......  10.71/1           28th February ...  ,....  10,71$            7th March  &quot; .........  10,81/6 (amended)           14th March    .........  10.37$     The analysis of policies lodged by Industries (given inthe Appendioea) shows an increase of u:^mpleyme.nt occurred intho uninsured trades, though the &quot;rate is considerably less thanthe normal.   There has been a general reduction of policieslodged in the insured trades.     The total of Unemployment in the Engineering and IronFounding Trade is now 192,876 whilst the local unsatisfied de-mand is 4,359.   Unemployment In Building and Works Constructionnow amounts to 63,614, whilst the demand for labour locallyunsatisfied in this occupational group is 3,426.   Unemploymentin Shipbuilding is new 16,029 and&quot;the local unsatisfied demandamounts to&apos;2,961.     The divisions in which the most Unemployment is found arestill the West Midlands and the North Western.   In the formerUnemployment is now 412 per 10,000 of population, and in tho latter357.   The Division in which there appears to be least unemploy-ment is Wales, with 100.5 per 10,000 cf population.   A large increase has occurred in the London k South Eastern Division.     An examination cf the total number of policies that haveexhausted the original period of donation sh^ws that of every 100policies held by men, 70,7 were the subject of applications forextension.   Of these, 38.9 have been extended, 3.1 have been re-fused and 28.7 await decision.   Of every 100 policies held byw-:men, only 41,7 were the subject of applications for extension,and cf these 12.7 have received extension, 4.6 have been refused,and 24,4 are awaiting decision.   The fact that in a large numberof cases (notably women)  no application for extension has beenmade may be ascribed  (1) to the greater stringency of the quali-fying oonditions of the new period of donation, and (2) to thelower scale of donations&apos; offered.25-3-19.A. C. GEDDES.
No.jmber  of  Civilians  &amp;  H.M.P,  Out-of-Work Donation Policiesamaining  lodged  on  Friday 14th March 1919,  with tho Percentage to    tho total  v/orkers in oach Industry.5.REDINDUSTRIES,*Total    dgfi&quot;   %   &quot;&quot;IlglT     $   &apos;  LotgcV,     %Workers  14/3/19 14/3/19 7/3/19  7/3/19 28/2/19 28/2/19&quot;Pols. jdgd.ding  &amp;  7-&apos;orksonstruetion.buildingtieering &amp;founding  of VehiclesIllingj Packing- Making &amp;o. iltionfie a Is &amp;c,. &amp; Steellac tion.[l ManufacturesIk,Tiles See.jr Insuredistrles.  593659  2661881412693  167660   89583  253913  104915  163650  324297   31450  153702 63614 16029192876 14914  9063 28099  6685  5463 23504  1375  785910.72  65925 6.02  1734913,65 197717 8.90  1451410,12921211,07  33616 6,37   6788 3,54   6265 7,25  24027 4,37   1494 5,11   811011,10  63564 6.52  1614614.00 200390 8.66  1171510.28   862213,24  37308 6.47   6315 3,83   5991 7.41  214464.755.272128766010.71 6.0714.18 6.99 9.6214.69 6.02 3.66 6.61 6.77 4.98jl InsuredIstries,3561710   369481   10.37 385017   10.81 381285   -10.71SURED INDUSTRIES.culture         1175000pyance of MenJods &amp; MessagesIs &amp; Quarries.iles-Cottonfiles-Woollen forsted.jilcs-Other, in-Jg Printing,Ing &amp;c.ercial.J, Drink ItJbac c c.iers in Drossptic OfficesServicesral Labourerslory97500001030000 500000 270000 3600001700000 480000 7500002500000LaDourers \Workers Sc. )No re&quot;          x- liable          )figures          Available.Ir Uninsuredidtrios.  8989 81509 15009 71878  5499 38095 41180 18655 35325 75560137446&quot;90015  .77 8.36 1.4614;38** 2.04   FIGURES.10.58   MOT YET11875668691386263417 56252.423.884.713.02AVAILABLE. 17616 33898 74665126665 86901 1.01 6.86 1.3512.60 2.0832600    9.O633341&apos;   1,963.674.522.99ll Uninsuredb&apos;,tr1i?,q,,__619138567335AND TOTAL.988619948620fine total number  of workers  in each Industry has been calculated thus:- Insurod Trades, Books  current  Jan.1919;  for Uninsured Trades, Z.8.July k Census Figures  1911.                           (Board of Trade)    full amount of unemployment  in the Cotton Trade is&apos; not shown:lain figures for  O.W.D.Policies  lodged under the Cotton Control BoardImo are not included.

</content>
</cab>
