<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 240-242</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IK-,.IV/ riarms                 J h[s Document is the Property o^                 His pritannic Maiosty&apos;s Government. SECRET.    For the information of Members of the Board.iB^^^^KEiY APPRECIATION OF MASTERS 0? NAVAL INTEREST.   No. 14,         &apos; V\           Week ended 22nd March.  1919.               1         NORTH SEA AHS-fiAHHie.                 Of the 9 German Submarines reported in last week&apos;s            Appreciation to be en route from Heligoland,  7 have            arrived at Harwich and one was reported to  be in tow of            three Dutch vessels making for Holland.                 Two additional Submarines commenced the journey from            Heligoland during the week, one of which has arrived at            Harwich.                 A Submarine which was found derelict in the North            Sea was towed into Gorieston.                            ADRIATIC.                 The advisability of reinforcing  or withdrawing our            Naval Forces in the Adriatic has recently been discussed.            The existing Forces are probably not  sufficient to cope            with any serious trouble following on the final decisions            of the Peace Conference, and should the Italians as a            result of  these decisions have to withdraw from places they            now occupy, they are unlikely to do so  without endeavouring            to provoke some incident.   From a purely Naval point of            view, complete withdrawal presents advantages, but might            be regarded as a success for Italian  policy.   The            presence of our ships also no doubt prevents bloodshed in            the Adriatic coast towns,  and is a support  in the  process            of opeaing up trade with Serbia6                 There are delays on the part of  Italy in raising            the blockade of the Adriatic Coast, and the War Council            is to be approached to ensure that proper steps are taken.            The Italian^representative on the Blockade  Committee has            produced a draft of a proposed Italian  decree, which does            not so much    raise the Blockade as  indemnify Italian            subjects against legal proceedings for  trading with            Adriatic Ports.  In&quot;effect, it rescinds the Italian            Trading with the Enemy Act as regards the Adriatic Coast.                 In view of the seriousness of the  coal shortage we            are do inn; all in our nower to increase  the  tonnage            available for loading&apos;to Italy this month-364,000  tons            will be shipped to Italy during March.                             MEDITERRANEAN.                 The Italian Colonial Minister is to discuss with            HoM. Ambassador,,at Rome what can be done to counteract            the effects of &quot;Lilj^s&quot; visit to Misurata.  The British
the Black Sea.                  we ich  are     Two Russian Submarines  and  3 Armed  Merchantmen, not previously reported,  are now said to be  at Astrakhan,     Orders have been given for  British  troops to be evacuated forthwith from Trans aspia.  The TurcomanGovernment begs for reconsideration of the decision or atleast the protection which a British representativeattached to them would afford.   They offer details of theirseafaring Deople to assist the British in manning ships for use on the Caspian under the White Ensign.                 RED  SEA,     The Resident at Aden has been  instructed to suspendraising the present restrictions onDhow  traffic in theRed Sea, as the present permit system  prevents ArmsTraffic on a large scale,     &quot;Diana&quot; has been withdrawn  from the Arabian blockade and sent to Suez in connection with the  disturbances inEpyot, and for the same reason &quot;Carlisle&apos; (en route toChinal is temporarily detained in Egyptian waters.&quot;Verbena&quot; is being sent to Port  Sudan  to guard the W/TStation so as to allow of the British  detachment being withdrawn to Khartoum.            BLACK SEA AND DANUBE.     Regular sailings to Constantinople and Black SeaPorts are about .to be resumed by the various lines whichwere trading to those places before the War.     French and Greek troops have been obliged  towithdraw from Kherson, but the French are  still inoccupation of Odessa, where the situation  has temporarilyimproved,,     In the Crimea the situation is serious,  as Bolsheviktroops have already a^roached close to the Isthmus ofPerekop, which is held&quot;by only 400 Volunteers,     Further Hast the Bolsheviks have captured  Berdianskon the North coast of the Sea of Azov ana  are within 60versts of Novocherkassk.     Admiral Troubridge is consulting at Bukharest withthe Commandant of the Lower Danube so as to arrange theco-operation essential for navigation.     Two ex-Austrian monitors and a motor  launch underCaptain Haggard have proceeded to Baja, which is 030 milesabove  Sulxna? in connection with Army movements in occupied territory and four monitors nave  proceeded toBuda-Pesth in view of ths situation created by  the refusal of the Hungarian Government to accept the  neutral zone laid down by the Peace Conference anl the  ordersgiven to Hungarian troops to attack the Rumanians.                   CASPIAN,
                 CHINA,     The S.S.  &quot;Atreus&quot;,  nNore!!...and &quot;Novarra&quot; have leftHong Kong with l&amp;ffl German men. women  and children for repatriation from China and there are  more to follow.                 FRANCE.     Vice-Admiral Amet is being relieved as HighCommissioner at Constantinople&quot;by M.  de France.  The latterhas already represented his country diplomatically atseveral capitals,,     Resignations of officers in the French Navy have become so numerous as to  cause a very serious situation,The Minister of Marine has issued instructions that noresignations are to be forwarded to him until further orders.There is grave dissatisfaction, more especially amongstthe junior officers with the. present pay and prospects,It is reported in the press that the pay of all raqks bothin the Navy and Army is about to be raised,,  The new scale shows a very substantial improvement, a Commander ora Lieutenant-Colonel receiving  600 a year,     Ali work on re-floating the &quot;Mirabeau&quot; has had to be suspended owing to a general stiike at Sevastopol,             -    SPAQL     The German Submarine UCC*  481 which had been internedat Ferrol since last March and which was to be deliwreu tothe French on the 15th..Marohs  escaped  from the harbour theday before.   The T0B. &quot;Halcon&quot; went  in pursuit and  claims to have hit her with a shell.   The submarine sank,probably entirely through the  a/hion of her crew, who werepicked it) by the boats of the   &apos;HalconThere appears to be some possibility of salving the submarine, which  is lying .in 16f fathoms  of water,.   It is reported from Madrid thar,an attempt was  made on the part of the crew of the  U*B\24to sink their ship when in tow of a  French Tug, and thatshe had to be hurriedly docked,IADMIRALTY,  S.W.    25th March,  1919e                         SAST  AFRICA.              Orders have been given for Dar-es-Salaam DockyardO        to be handed over to the Civil administration and  for         the naval personnel to return to England.

</content>
</cab>
