<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 248-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY ?F HIS BRITA?TriC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVETMENT) .rv              -  s  -                                 ..5 E C R J T.    /   /                /         &apos;  WAR PABINET. G.T * 7034 *               RKSPCySIBIIITY FQR THE SUPPLY OF AIRCRAFT.             (Memorandum &quot;by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.)       I  sent the  following memorandum to Lord Inverforth and General Seely on the 28th ultimo       My attention has &quot;been called to the correspondence between the Ministry of Munitions and the Air Ministry on the subject of the proposed re-transfer to the latter of full responsibility for the supply of ail aircraft, including engines.  I oannot but think that this proposal is inconsistent with.the polioy of the Govern- ment in  setting&apos; up a central Ministry of Supply and as at present a&amp;vined  I do net  feel able to concur in. it.       It will be  remembered that lord Inchoape1e Committee on Contracts recommended that the Ministry of Supply, should deal with all Government purchases exoept food and highly t4chr.i?al supplies for the  Navy;  I  realist; that this polioy oannot be carried out completely at onoe; ana, if. the question were one of tne transfer now for  the.first, time of responsibility for aircraft supplies to a central .Ministry of Supply, there mi*ht be good reasons against suoh an  arrangement for tha moment.  But the Ministry of Munitions have successfully dealt with ihese supplies during ;the Y/ar and their retransfer to the Air Ministry appears to me tc be a retro- grade step:.  The  Air Ministry  will have to set up their own contracts inspection- and  accounts branches with.consequent duplication of staffs and expense.  It Is noticed that the Minister of Munitions expresses the,hope that, so far as practicable,  the Air Ministry will limit their contract -work to the/ordering ef machines or aeroplanes and engines as complete units,  leaving any detailed orders for parts etc., and particularly for those articles of which the Ministry of Munitions have, large stocks, to be obtained from the Ministry of Munitions,  -Obviously however there will be difficulty, and probably additional expense, in carrying out this arrangement.       The principle&apos;on which the proposed re-transfer is based is stated to be the distinction between standardised and non- Standardised articles.  But the Ministry of Munitions have not during the war been confined to the former category, and it appears to me that so narrow a restriction of the scope of the Minister of supply as is involved by this proposal would make him little more than&apos; an agent of the War office, with the addition possibly of the functions of the stationery Offioe.  On this ba-sis only it. might not be easy to justify  to parliament the creation if .a Ministry of Supply.     .. ; -       .For these reasons I &amp;3k for a reconsideration of the pro- posal made in this correspondence, or that-the. Cabinet should be asked to decide the point  at issue.       In reply I have received from. Lord Inverforth and General Seely the. attached memorandum and letter..  /It will be seen that General Seely desires to carry out the retransfer to his Department whilst Lord Jnverf--rrth realises      &apos;    the strong objections to the withdrawal of. this work torn, the Ministry of
supply and ig willing to have tho matter reconsidered. Bothrefer to the Report of sir James Stevenson&apos;8 Committee, acopy, of which is also attached&apos;.      I think that the point in dispute is of -sufficient importance &quot;to call for a cabinet decision.  -Departments arenever likely to Welcome -the- transfer of their powers of self-supply to the flew Ministry, and if ,the Ministry-is to be deprived at the,outset of powers -which it already exercises.I think it will be crippled from the&apos; start, and will prove &apos;a useless duplication of Staff and machinery.  I am unable tounderstand why the existing.arrangement should not continue.It has admittedly been a great improvement on the.cider system.                               (initialled)  A.0.Treasury,  S.W. 1.     23rd  March,  1919.,
MEMORANDUM BY GENERAL SEELY.

The question of the allocation of aircraft supplies between the Air ministry and the Ministry of Supply was referred it by the Secretary of State for tho Royal Air Force to a Committee, a copy of whose Report is appended to this Memorandum.

It will be seen  that they arrived unamimously at the conclusion that the line of division between the two Departments should be that the Ministry of Supply should undertake or the Air Ministry the supply of all stores and of standardised aircraft supplies, whether technical or non-technical, and that the Air Ministry should itself  undertake the supply and production of such aircraft and  ?ical supplies as are not yet standardised.

The basis for this conclusion was that aircraft and engines are a highly technical supply which, at the present time and for many years to come will remain in tho experimental and development stage and subject to rapid changes of design which can only be transferred into production if the user, the designer, and the producer are in the closest possible relationship. The Committee were convinced that this close relationship would not be forthcoming if use, design and production are delegated to different Departments of State.

They considered whether the needs of the situation could be met by constituting the Ministry of Supply as the contract and finance department for the Air Ministry in respect of non- standardised supplies but came to the  conclusion that this course was not feasible.

To Report of the Committee was approved by the Secretary of State for the Royal Air Force and the Minister of Supply and the detailed arrangements necessary to carry it out are in course of preparation by the two Departments. The arrangement arrived at con scarcely be regarded as a re-transfer of work, to the Ali Ministry in view of the very close relations which have been maintained between the Ministry and the Directorate of Aircraft Production in the Ministry of Munitions during tho War.

It will be realised that the Ministry of Supply will Undertake as work of considerable cost and importance for the Air Ministry; in fact the Air Ministry, which at an earlier stage welcome the establishment of a Ministry of Supply, h? gone as ? in the direction of using that Ministry as is, in the judgment of the Secretary of State, compatible with the vital interests of the development of aviation in its present stage.

The I? Committee itself admitted that there must be a captions to the general policy of supply by one department and in the view of the  Secretary of State, the supplies to be retained by the Air Ministry are clearly in the same class as the naval supplies included in the proposed exceptions.

It should be added that the Secretary of State for the Royal Air Force mentioned the matter to the Prime Minister before approving the Report of the Committee and obtained his general approval of the action proposed.


REPORT Off COMMITTEE 70 H0IMIDI1R POSITION CF           221 AIRCRAFT TEC HIT I CAP AIT SUPPLY is part^INTS.MEMBERS.         Sir Jaiacs St cvcnson, Bart.  ( Chairman)         Sir Arthur Duckham. K.C.B.         Brig.Genoral R.K. Bagnall-Wild,         Major General E.L. Ellington.         Sir Arthur Robinson, K.CB.         Sir James&apos;Mastbrton Smith, K.C.B.                       Mr. fl. Hut chins. Secretary.To tho Right Honourable Winston S. Churchill, M.P,    Secretary of State for &apos;7ar and. Secretary cf State for Air.Sir,(1)    The Committee appointed under your minute, dated l8thJanuary  1919, addressed to the  Secretary of the Air Ministry,(topy of which is attached hereto, Appendix  &quot;VV has consideredthe proposals you have put forward in that minute, and begs toreport as follows(2)    In the first place the Committee desires to point out thataeroplanes and aerr engines  are a highly technical supply whichis at the present time, and  for many years will remain, in the experimental and development stage, and therefore subject torapid changes in design which can only  be translated into production if the user, the  designer, and the producer are in the closest  possible relationship.    The Committee is convinced thatin practice this close relationship \&apos;rill not be forthcoming ifuse, design, and production  are delegated to different department&amp;of the State.(3)    The Committees investigations have shewn that the success which has attended the work  of  the Aircraft Production Departmentof the Ministry cf Munitions has  been the practical recognitionOf this  fact. &quot;  Although  in  theory Design and Production are nowunder a  different Department to the user, in practice the Depart-ment is  so organised that the closest association exists betweenthe Air  Force as the Ueer,  the Ministry of Munitions as theTechnical and Production  Department, and the Manufacturers as theDesigners.   Under the organisation of  the Aircraft production department the Technical  Department is  staffed by the Air Force,and forms the connecting  link by  which  the experience of the useris brought tc the assistance of the design and development of aeroplanes and aero engines.    Further  the placing under one headJ^LJ^Oj^hX^             and Inspection departments has obviatedthe difficulties and iTT^rhjrir^rl^ pnrrod^a  check on the progres-of aircraft development In the  wast&apos;..    The&quot;&quot;Oorcn-Utijo believes thaany attempt at the present time to divorce design from proinctionand inspection would not  be  wise,(4)    The proposition before the committee before, therefore, resolvesitself into a consideration  cf  two alternatives, viz: placing thethroe Departments under the  Air Ministry, or placing them underthe Ministry cf Supply.   Soaring in mind the fact with which theCommittee prefaced their  report viz., that the aeroplane and theaero engine are still  in  an  experimental stage, it appears to theCommittee that the reasons for  adopting the  first alternative are far more weighty at the present time than the advantages of havin-a common Supply Department for  such highly technical articles.both as  a fighting machine and  as a. commercial factor, is in thehands cf the Air Ministry and anything  which may tend to cripnleor reduce the efficiency  of  that  Ministry must be to the detrimen-
  fff  the  development  cf  aeronautical eei&amp;noe, the importance of which[I is  apparent  to  oil  at  the present time.  ($)    The  Committee therefore  eonoiders that until the aeroplane  and aarc  engines  emerges from the development stage and becomes a  standard  article, their design  and production should be transferred  tr  the  Air  Ministry.  (6)    On the  other hand  it  is  important that the Fighting Force  should  be relieved  as  far  as possible of the supply of stores and  war material,  and as it has  been decided by the war Cabinet that  a Ministry  of  Supply shall be set up for this purpose, the  Committee considers that  all stores and aircraft supplies of a  standard  character  (whether  technical or non-technical) should be  retained  through  the Ministry of Supply, and that as from time to  time aircraft  supplies become standardised, so the responsibility  fcr supplying  them.should  be transferred to theMinistry of * Supply. .  (7)    The  Committee has  also considered the alternative proposi-  tion that the  Ministry of  Supply should become the Contraot and  Finance Department  for the Air  Ministry in respect of aeroplanes  and a.err  engines.  Thia proposal was found on examination to be  difficult to put  into  practice  as the necessity for closely  following up production from the earliest  stages in Aeronautical  Supply is closely, allied  to  the Technical  and Inspection fepart-  raents and could not be delegated to the Contracts Branch.&apos; It is  therefore thought best for the  present that the.whole question of  the production, the placing  of  contracts,  and the finance of non-  standard aircraft supplies,  should be undertaken by the Air  Ministry. ......  (8)    If these proposals are adopted the Hinistry of Supply will  provided the Air Ministry with  a large quantity of Stores and  Standardised material, and further will be taking over other  aircraft  supplies as  they become standardised.  The Committee  is  therefore. .of opinion that the Ministry  of  Supply should have  a representative  on the Air  Council.  :  RBCOimiTlATIOHS.  (9)    The.Committee therefore  recommends         ii)    That the  Ministry  of Supply undertake for tho Air         Hinistry the supply and  production  of all stores and cf         standardised aircraft supplies  (whether technical or         non-technical).         (ii)  That the  Air Ministry undertake the supply and         production of  such aircraft technical  supplies as are not         yet  standardised.         (iii) That such portions of the Technical, Inspection and         Supplies Departments  as  are required by the Air Ministry be         transferred to  that body.         (iv)  That the  Ministry  of Supply be represented on the Air         Council.                        We haye  the honour  to be, Sir,                              Your obedient Servants,                               (Signed)  J.  Stevenson (Chairman)  &apos;                                        E.L.Ellington                                        ..W.A. Robinson.                                        AM7.E. Iuckham.                                        &amp;.E. Baaaiall Wild.                         _            J, Mn,fft. prtnn switzerland tVi._
Ministry of Munitions Of Far-,        &quot; - &apos; . -rail Place, .SJ.1,                 4th March,  1919, Dear Ohamberlaln,              Many thanks for letting me see your Memorandum on the proposed transfer to the Air Ministry of the respono- ibllity for the supply of aircraftI fully appreciate the force of your arguments. and indeed it was not altogether without misgiving that I agreed to the proposed arrangement, But Churchill and I &quot;/ere both impressed by the report of a .strong Committee under Sir James Stevenson.  The view of thi3 Committee uas that aeroplanes aid aero-engines were a highly technical supply which,, at the present time and for many years to. comej would be still in the experimental stage and therefore subject to&apos; rapid ch^ges of design which could only be trans- latecl into production if the designer, producer and user&apos; were In the closest relationship, and that on this.-ground, the Air Ministry; which must, necessarily be the user, was best fitted. to undertake design and production also.  The Committee point - ed cut that although in theory dv-ign and production are now under a Department distinct f ror: ihe using Department, in .practice under the existing (organisation of the Aircraft Pro- auction Department the. Technical Branch is staffed by the Air ,Poree and forms, the connecting link, by which... tha experience* of the user Is  brought to the assistance of design and de- velopme^t.  As a further reason for the transfer to the Air Ministry, they urged that that Ministry would be responsible for the future development of the aeroplane not only as a fighting machine but also as a commercial factor, and that anything which might.tend to cripple or reduced-he efficiency of that Ministry must be to the detriment of aeronautical science generally and of the progress of commercial aeronautics               It might of course be possible, while trans-f errix Design to the Air Minisi.ry, to remain production and inaoea-t;: on (except in the case of purely &quot;experimental orders) in the ha.ids of the Ministry of Supply*  An arrangement on these lines has been come to with-the Far Office as regards Guns and other vmrw- like stores, but I think it is likely to b c  more difficult to work in the case of aircraft, as recent experience shows that the number of alterations in design during production is much greater with the latter than in the case of a fairly standard- ised article like a Gun.,               31 feel however that.  whatevrcase can be made out for it, the proposed arrangement does o .institute a rather serious breach in the principle underlying the&apos; establishment of a Ministry of National Supply and weakens our position in probable Ing otherlepartmsnas to abdicate their purchasing functions; and/ptrsonally, -I should be quite ready to reconsider the whole question if Churchill is  mis a willing tc do so,  You may, however, perhaps think it sufficient if the arrangement is definitely recognised on both sides as a provisional one, to he reviewed at the expiration of say two years,  by which time the new Supply Ministry should have got its machinery into ruaam *.g order and should also oe  to a great extent freed from its pra- occupation with the question of the disposal  of surplus property.Yours s incerely,   (Signed) Inveriorthr

</content>
</cab>
