<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 404-406</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;RSJOBJ^F  ffiE           OF THE M:K0m,L INDUSTRIAL aOMOTOE.             1%     Memorandum by the Minister of labour.    A      In  continuation of my note of yesterday&apos;/ I circulate to my       r colleagues  this memorandum on matters arising out of the Report of the provisional Joint Committee of the Industrial Conference.      The Industrial Conference reassembles on Friday., April 4th, to consider the Report presented by its Provisional Joint Committee,  it will be  necessary for the Government to announce the attitude which it is prepared to adopt in regard to the several recommendations, and I feature  to  advise tbe Cabinet to follow the line indicated below. \                                                  should      (I) Hours.  I am of opinion that the Government/accept the principle t?:at  a maHmum normal working week of 48 hours should be legally e^ablished and are prepared to introduce legislation for this purpose as * soon  as possible.  They should also agree that the Bill should apply generally to all employed persons (except Seamen and domestic servantsJ, subject  to the qualification proposed by the Provisional Committee,  that provision must be made for exemption from, or variation of, the terms of the Bill in proper cases.  In order to give the neoessary elasticity to meet  the case of particular trades,  the provisional Committee outline the safeguards which they suggest should be included in the Bill, in paragraphs 3 to  11  of their recommendations in regard to hours (paragraphs 5 and 6 of their Heport).  These safeguards the Governnemt 3hould accept generally and be prepared to incorporate in the Bill subject to any modifications that may be found necessary.  These safeguards provide for exceptions being made to the general rule for a 48 hour week by the following methods. -    (a)  Lower maximum. V/here an agreement has been made between the  representative organizations in any trade providing a shorter working  [  week than 40 hours, the Minister may make an Order prescribing that  number of hours for the whole of the trade concerned.    (b) Higher maximum.  The Minister concerned may make a similar Order  i  in  any case where ah agreement has been made between the representative I  organizations for a higher maximum than 48 hours.&apos;    (c) Application for variation.  Application may be made to the  Icinist ef*&quot;by either&quot;Employers or Employed for the variation of the  maximum hours established by the Act or for total exemption, from the  Act.  &apos;The Minister must thereupon summon a conference of the representa-  tive organizations of the trade and failing agreement between them, he  may remit the matter to a competent authority for enquiry.  On receipt  of tbe latterfs report,  he may then make an Order,for variation or  exemption as the case may be,  and attach such conditions as he may think  fit.     Under this procedure the case of an industry like Agriculture,  to e strict 48 hour week really covM. not be applied, will be amply safe- guarded -      The Provisional Committee themselves suggest that the Act,  when   t passed,  should not come into operation for 6 months,  in order to give  I full time for the necossary variations and exemptions to be granted.      (2). Overtime. In regard to overtime systematic overtime ought to te discouraged,  ft ea&amp;not however be entirely avoided and where it has to be worked it is imposed that (a)  trade organizations in organizedgrades, (b) Trade Boards: in less organized trades, or (c)  the appropriate Minister in default of either,  should determine the extent to which overv time  should be permitted and under what conditions, following the                              1. -                                /same
  same procedure as in the case of variations  and exemptions  from the  48 hours week.  411 overtime should he paid  for in accordance with the  custom of each trade and district concerned,  hut in  no  ease should less  than time and a quartor he.pad.fi except Where the rate of wages is  conditioned by the fact that more than the normal nuraboff of hours is  worked.  Generally speaking, no person should he required to work more  than 48 hours per week without payment of overtime,  hut a special  provision will have to he rro.de for cases  like that of the continuous  *  processes in the Iron and steel trade, where the change;of  shift re-  quires men to work more thaw 48 hours  in  some weeks, but less in others.1 In such cases the excess should not he accounted as  overtime.       (3). Wages.  She aotual wording oi the Provisional  Oommitteers  reoommendsrEions with regard to minimum rates is  not  very clear,  but I  think that the main recommendations can be accepted.   The first  is tha  principle that minimum rates of wages should he  established  by legal   j  enactment in order to ensure that no class of workers should fall below  tho standard off reasonable min?.mum*  It would., however   bo impossible  to put this principle into legislation until jrnas beon determined by what  methods and by what successive steps effect &quot;should be given  to it. In  order to deal with these matters the Government  should adopt thB  seoond of the Provisional Committee1s recommendations, viz.  the  immediate appointment of a Commission to report  within three months  as to the measures which ought to bo taker,.  Its Terms of Reference  should be as follows;-       &quot;In order to provide for the universal extension of legal  minimum rates of wages and the improvement of the means  for  their  administration, a Commission is appointed.  i    (1) To consider -         (a) to extend the principle of tho mininum wage to workers             employed in occupations for which no  agroemont or Trade             Boards exist.         (b) to amend the Trade Boards Acts in order to faoilitato and             expedite as far as possible the prooodure for fixing  minimum             rates.       (2) to advise on the means of carrying out  the  nocossary adminis-  &apos;   v*-          trative work&quot;.       The Provisional Committee p^pose that this Commission  should be  composed of equal numbers of representatives of  the  Employers1  Associations and Trade Unions, with a Chairman nominated by  the  Government,  This, however, does not socm an altogether  appropriate  form of Commission to deal with a question of such general interest  to the ooiBmunity at large.  Che Government should, therefore, appoint  a certain number of independent members to assist the ijhairman,  as in  tho case of tho Sankoy Commission.  It is suggested  that there should  be 4 Employers, and 4 Workmen TO be appointed by and. from tho  Provisional Committee of the Hation&amp;l Conference; and 1  Independent  Chairman and 2 independent persons appointed by  the  Government.           War Advances. Tho Government should; I  think, agree to  extend^  tho Wagos (temporary Regulation) Act for a&apos;further 6 months, and to  refer the question of &apos;7ar advances to the Interim Court  of  Arbitration as proposed by tho Provisional Committee.       (5) Unemployment.  Tho Provisional Oommitteo have recognised that  their rocommondations undor this head are of a tentative character  and that the problem requires fuller investigation than they have hadm time to give to it.  Tho Government, 1 oreforo,  should propose to rofer tho matter to the Uation:.-! Indus .rial Council at the earliest  possible- date as it is one on v;hich c- ..octivo action must be taken  with the least possible delay, but on which Lotion in order to be                              2,                          /of f octivo
 effective can only be taken after full enquiry*  Tliey agree4 howevor, to the principle that provision against unemployment should, be extended, and that the  subject of continuation of education during unemployment for young  persons, tho employment ,0$ married women and widowst and the age at  which children should enter employment require further consideration.      ( 6) ffatioHal Industri   0 ounci 1/&apos; The (Jovernmont should wolcomd the  establishments IhraVrT&quot;oiHTlfatioriXTHJ?uslJrlal. Council to advise it on general  questions affecting iyidaotil&amp;l relations9 disputes, and legislative proposals affecti :;g :.:u.iv.stry *,, It is&apos; doubtful, however..* whether the Minister of labour should as  is suggested el ways preside,as,/controversi&amp;l&apos; mti.ers must of ton come up for discussion.&apos; it may therefore bo preferable that he should have power to nominate a substitute.  As regards  the Standing Committee, it seems desirable that the general community should bo.to sono extent represented. Questions must often arise for discussion which will have a general as well as a pvre]y industrial bearing; and on these questions it will ,be of  assiru/^iace to tho Committee itself  if persons qualified by eoorcjruo iajcwlodge or other experionoe can assist in their discussions. I suggest that the Government therefore should propose that 8 Assurors should be appointed by tho Government, who should have the right  of being present  at  the meetingeof  tho Standing Committee and. ofI spE&amp;Urhg, but who should not be entitled  to vote.                                           (Sgd) R*S.Borne.1.1V.19.

</content>
</cab>
