<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 492-496</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FOOD. HODTOI03J. Xjt^..99E$&amp;i$$X Order under Defence of the Realm Regulation 2M.      The  Board have withdrawn from possession of a holding known as Woodend Croft, Lhanbryde, Elgin, which was taken over &quot;by them on End September 1918 in order that adequate arrangemonts might he made for the  cultivation of the holding during the absence on Military Service of the 0&apos;c&apos;cupier,  who has- now resumed occupa- tion.    M ^Sulghate  of Ammonia.    Further licences issued by the BoardnSHng The&apos; VoYaT&quot;limntlty in respect of which licences have been  issuod during the  month of March for delivery in tho March - May period to 14,000 tons.    The total amount, - the sale  of which has been  licensed so far this season,  is 58,000 tons as  compared v/ith  the  Boards estimate of 60,000 tons to the end of May.       :JBasiq ,Slag.    At a meeting- of the Scottish Basic  island* Advidofy  &quot;Commrt^ee  in these  offices on the  31st March it was decided to ask. for  an additional 6,200 tons from Teeside Works, the output from  Scottish works being insufficient to meet the demand in Scotland.    &apos;J^9i$3l .P,P.eions.     Difficulty  has  been experienced in securing suitable men to work the Board1s  tractors,  and representations have been made by various  Committees and Engineers in charge of the tractors  that,in order  to obtain a suffioient number of  skilled workers,  the  rate of remuneration offered should be increased. Owing  to  the  recent  frosty weather considerable arrears  of plough- ing remain to be  overtaken,  and it has become apparent that some additional remuneration-must be given if the  tractors are to be kept fully employed.    It has  been decided,  therefore, that an extra  acreage bonus  should be  offered in the  hope, that this will have the  effect  not  only of  attracting skilled workers but of increasing the acreage  worked.                    ;     The  bonus&apos; now  offered - whioh takes effect as from  31st March  and is  in  addition to  the bonus  already paid of 6d per acre ploughed and 2d per acre  for other operations - is  as followg:-     Ploughing-...........1/- per  acre over 10  aores                                        in any one week.     Grubbing..........  6d    do           20   do  do     Cultivating .........  6d    do,          25   do  do     Harrowing -  single  stroke .  .  Id    do.          90   do do     Disc ,Harrowing  - each stroke.  3d    do,          30   do  do 4.  Allotments..     With a view to ascertaining the progress of the allotmentmovement in Scotland during the current year the Board haveissued/PvEKM KEDAOTG TO THE WORK OF TH3 BOARDpi? AGRXCDXOTE FOR SOOTLAID for the Week       m ondlng gndjURIL,&apos; 19191
 /issued a circular to 105 Allotment&quot;Associations requesting information on the following points:-      (1) whether the demand for plots in addition to those          presently occupied continues,  and&quot;      (2) whether there has &quot;been any disposition on the&apos; part          Of allotment holders to -give up their allotments          si$ce the cessation of hostilities. &apos;. 5.    Heather Burning.                          &apos;&apos;&quot;,&apos;      The powers under Defence of the Realm Regulation 21, whereby agricultural tenants may burn heather up till 20th april  are still in force.   In this connection the Beard have asked District Agricultural Exeoutive Committees to use their influence to secure a considerate and reasonable.exercise of the concession contained in the Regulation. During  last season a number of complaints were received of damage  by heather burning and,the Board are satisfied that the damage reported wag due to failure&apos;.Mx the part  of certain agricultural tenants to give notice to  landlords and,other- wise comply with tho terms of the Regulation. 6:.......&apos;r Sup^Lgr,of^LjBtbour ,^,.A^xipttlteal&apos; Companies.      An intimation has been received from the War Office that etll men belonging to Agricultural Companies who are working on  farms are to be withdrawn on a fortnightVs notice,, and either  demobilised or transferred to; the, active units of the Army,    The number of men so employed in&apos; Scotland is 3,700 and it will in many eases be veary difficult for farmers to  replace them.   - -7.^  Army Mares for Breeding Purposes.     As  the&apos; demand  for mares  under the  above  Scheme  exceeds the probable supply^  no  further applications  are  being re-&apos;oeived.&apos;  .  The figures to date are:-                                      Light Draught.   Huntor.lumber of  applications received         1200          &apos;,, 51   n       mares  supplied                  90-8.  ; Grain Prices 1919.          .              have  .     The Board/communicated to the Scottish Press the fol-lowing announcement In regard to the  prices of the cerealcrop of  1919e-     The prices  guarantee.;,  by the  Government  for  1919 graincrops are  as follows     (1) Wheat,  71/lld per  or.  of  480 lbs.  (or 75/61 per or,                                        &quot;   of 50&apos;4 lbs).     (2) Barley, 6l/6d per  qr.  of  400 lbs.  (or 68/loJ-d per &amp;                                            of,448 lbs).     (3) Oats, 44/ld  per qr.  of 312 lbs.  (or  47/6d per qr. ot                                           336 lbs).     The/
                              w 3 **        /The guarantee  applies to the  proportion of  the  entire   produce  of each cereal normally sold;   and  not in respect  of   the  proportion consumed on the farm.         It has  been decrded  to give effect  to these guarantees   by means of the machinery  of Fart X, of the Corn  Production   Act  1917.   This involves  payment to growers of any differ-   ence  between  &quot;average  prices11  and guaranteed prices,  on the   basis of a yield per acre  of 4 qrs, of  wheat,  4 qrs.  of barley,   and 5 qrs.  of  oats respectively.         It has been decided  to take four-fifths  In  the  case  of   barley and  two-thirds  in the  case of oats,  as  the  proportion   normally sold.    The grower  of  wheat will therefore be paid   for each acre four times the  difference between 71/lld and ;   the average market price ascertained for the seven months com-   mencing  September 1st.&quot;1919.    The grower of barley will re-   ceive&quot; for each  acre four times  four-fifths  of  the  difference   between  61/6d and.the  average  price of barley  similarly deter-   mined.   The grower of  oats will receive for each  acre five   times two-thirds  of the difference between 44/ld and the aver-;   age price of oats similarly determined. .      .  .&apos;:  /       These guarantees are  subject to the provisions of Clause   2(b)   of the Corn Production.Act 1917, which states - &quot;If ItI   &quot;appears to the Board that any  such land has.been negligentlyi   &quot;cultivated, the Board may either withhold altogether the)   &quot;payments to which the occupier would otherwise have been  &quot;entitled or may diminish the amount, of those payments toI   &quot;such extent as the Board think proper to meet the circumstances-!   &quot;stances of the case&quot;.j QOI&amp;BCTION OF STATISTICS and -RETURNS RELATING TO AGRICULTURE.f  Returns under the Potatoes (Scotland)  Order, 1918.,----       The tabulation of the returns for 1st March has now been  completed, and a summary table is appended showing the  results.    The stocks of potatoes remaining on farms at 1stf  March exceed those remaining at 1st  March .1918 by 56 per cent.
III.   DEMOBILISATION of AGPJCuXTURAL W0E2ERS.             The figure8 are aa follows:-                                 Ho.  of  Men  .    flo.  of Men                                 applied for.      Released.      Aberdeen   . *.............     1445              694      Argyll..................      413              816      Ayr.....................      464              202      Banff  ...................      312              199      Berwick  ..........,......      265              169      Bute....................      107-               71      Caithness...............      237              136      Clackmannan  .,...........       35               17      Dumbarton...............       67               39      Dumfries................    .  484              267      Elgin  ..______.........      270              160      Hfe.....................      420              233      ?orfar  ..................      533              291      Eaddington..............      266              156      Inverness............,,.      536              292      Kincardine..............      292              169      Kinross.................       46               26      Kirkcudbright...........      221              151      Lanark..................      576              318      linlithgow  ..............      Ill               61      Midlothian..............      327              167      Nairn  ...................       57               41      Orkney..................   .  , 423              151      Peebles.................   !.:   94               53      Perth...................      571              292      Renfrew..........216             -108      Boss....................      342              144      Roxburgh................      346              228      Selkirk.................     .56               32      Shetland................      287               98      Stirling ..........----...      161               95      Sutherland..............      136               79      Wigtown.................      275              119                       TOTALS  ..    10391             5554
TABLE showing the Quantities of Potatoes held &quot;by Growers  (of 5 acres or more) in Scotland on 1st Maroh 1919 and  the Quantities consumed or delivered during February 1919.1.   Estimated Quantities remaining on the  Premises  on 1st    March 1919.                  Variety.                 ^uantitjr,                                            Tons.               Abundance Group .........    5,200               Arran Chief.............  110,000               Golden Wonder Group .....   14,000               King Edward 711 .......,.   64,900               President Group.........   44,000               Up-to-Date Group........   18,000               Other Varieties.........  143,000                             TOTAL  ....  406,000II.   Quantities consumed or delivered during February 1919,                  Variety.                 S^Pfl^l&apos;                                            Tons.  1,000 23,500  3,000  8,000  5,000  4,000.69^000^lOTJB:-  The following counties are excluded from the scope of 1       the inquiry:-  Shetland, Sutherland,  Ross and Oromarty        (except districts of Easter Ross and Black Isle),        Inverness (except districts of Inverness and Aird),        Argyll (except districts of Cowal and Kintyre).The quantity returned as remaining at 1st February (i.e.the sun of Heads I and II) was 475,000 tons.    On 1stFebruary 1918 the quantity returned as remaining on thepremises was 355,000 tons.   As shown above the quantityremaining on tho premises at 1st March 1919 is 406,000,while the stocks that remained at 1st March 1918 were260,000 tons.The quantity shown above as consumed or delivered during february was 69,000 tons, as compared with 95,000 tons during February 1918,Abundance Group .....Arran Chief ............Golden 7/onder GroupKing Edward Vll ......President Group ........Up-to-Date Group .......Other Varieties........              TOTAL s...

</content>
</cab>
