<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/77/0 images: 550-551</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Senior Assistant Secretary* * &apos;Memor^lpi as to the proposal to grant Free Passages-^^-^r^^^nis country to-ex-soldiera and their WALL GN^^dependants to settle abroad.      1*     It is underetood that the proposal is that by theend of this year 15,000 men, with their dependants, say 45,000souls in all, shall be given passage at Government expense to countries abroad, presumably the greater portion to theDominions 4      2.      The passenger space involved for such numbers isvery large, and except on the North Atlantic, where any suchmovement would probably not take place until tae beginningof next year, it is not seen how it could be provided withoutretarding the repatriation of Dominion troops.  It is presumedit is not intended that this should occur*       30       The existing arrangements with the companies for passages at Government rate do not apply to such cases, anda special agreement would have to be negotiated with the conferences for a rate for these passengers.  Such a rate should presumably be  negotiated by the Emigration authorities with the assistance of the Ministry of Shipping.  Oncesuch rates are fixed, it is not considered that the Ministryof,Shipping should have anything further to do with thearrangements^ the passengers booking direct with the companies and the Government Emigration, or other Authority, paying thepassage money.carry out this scheme the Dominions in question should beentrusted with the arrangements, in order to secure that theyafford the assistance in passage money they have in the pastafforded to anmigrants, and to ensure that the individuals are acceptable to the Dominions.  The Imperial Government  wouldthen be simply in the position of contributing to4.It is suggested that if it is decided to/the
the Dominion scheme for assisted emigrantso         5,    Further, if the Government decides to assistthis emigration, it should be made clear that passages arenot likely to be available in any number before the endof this year; otherwise there is sure to be a great deal ofdisappointment o8th April,  1919.

</content>
</cab>
