<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/12 images: 120-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  January 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (42)12th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 12 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet war room, S.W. 1, on Monday, January 26, 1942, at 10-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon.- C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Supply.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.Contents.Subject. PageParliament      ........      ........      ............     64Prime Ministers Statement on Tuesday, 27th January.The Dominions representation in London.[23387-21
Parliament. Prime Minister said that he had been giving furtherPrime consideration to the passage in his speech in which he would dealMinister^ with the arrangements for Allied co-ordination in the Far East.Statement on Further reflection confirmed him in the opinion that we should beTuesday, very ill-advised to embark at this stage on the long process whichQl&amp;s-iS11^3^^^!^011^0- cleai*ly be necessary, if we were to persuade the AustralianFar Sa^^e^nu^uuxitaaQoveiinmen^. ^ reverse jjje view which they had expressed, and to reference: agree to a Far Eastern Council being set up in London. On groundsW.M. (42) 11th of logic there was much to be said for the view which they had putConclusions,Minute 4.)The Dominions.representation in London.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 11thConclusions,Minute 5.)forward that the Council should be set up in Washington. It was clear that they felt very strongly on the point, and he (the PrimeMinister) was greatly averse from bringing strong pressure to bear upon them.In discussion, the view was expressed that, on practicalgrounds, the arrangement agreed to in Washington, whereby aFar Eastern Council was to be set up in London, would prove far more advantageous to the interests of the Dominions than thearrangement for which Australia and New Zealand had nowexpressed a preference. Before long they might well come round to this view. It was, therefore, important that we should communicate to the Dominions our willingness to agree that theCouncil to deal with Far Eastern matters should be set up in washington and not in London, in such a manner as would conveyno sense of grievance on our part. Further, from this point of view,it was important that the Dominions should continue to maintainadequate representation here, so that London could, at any time,again become the focus for discussion with the Dominions on far eastern matters.It was suggested to the Prime Minister that he should include in his speech on the following day a short passage indicating our desire and intention to provide improved methods of co-operationwith the Dominion Governments, in defence and supply matters, soas to enable the Empire to act as a whole. [This would carry with it the implication that, while we had agreed to the suggestion madeby the Australian and New Zealand Governments for the settingup of a Pacific or Far Eastern Council in Washington, it was no part of our policy to encourage separatist tendencies.]This suggestion met with general approval.The Prime Minister read to the War Cabinet the passage inhis speech dealing with Dominion representation in London. he proposed to make it clear that, while we were perfectly willing toagree that an accredited representative of each of the DominionGovernments should have the right to be heard in the War Cabinetin the formulation and the direction of policy, we could not acceptthe claim that such representatives should have &apos;&apos; full membership of the United Kingdom War Cabinet.&quot;The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that any public statement on this matter should take the form of saying thatthe facilities asked for by Australia and New Zealand wereavailable to the other Dominions if so desired, but should not makea definite offer which would call for an immediate and specificanswer.The War Cabinet-I. Settled the terms of the following telegrams, and authorisedtheir dispatch : (a) From the Prime Minister to the President of theUnited States informing him of the australian and New Zealand Governments&apos; wish that aPacific Council should be set up in Washington,
not limited to the A.B.D.A. area, and comprisingrepresentatives of the United Kingdom, theUnited States, Australia, China, the netherlands and New Zealand.(6) To the Prime Ministers of the Governments ofAustralia and New Zealand, informing them thatthis action had been taken.(c) To the Prime Ministers of the Governments ofCanada, the Union of South Africa and NewZealand, informing them that we had agreed tothe request of the Australian Government thatan accredited representative of that Governmentwould have the right to be heard in the WarCabinet in the formulation and the direction ofpolicy, and indicating that the same facilities were available to the Governments of Canada, theUnion of South Africa and New Zealand.II. Instructed the Secretary to inform Sir Earle Page that,on further consideration, it had been found necessarythat the Prime Minister should include in his speech onthe following day a statement of the facts, in narrativeform, as regards the proposed Far Eastern Council, butthat this would be done in such a manner as to leave thefuture open.Great George Street, S.W.1,January 27, 1942.






</content>
</cab>
