<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/9/0 images: 224-243</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1946.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (46) 168.18th April, 1946.CABINET.IMPORT PROGRAMME FOR MID-1946 TO MID-1947.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I attach a report of the Balance of Payments Working Party on the Depart-mental import programmes for the second half of 1946 and the first half of 1947,and the Treasury&apos;s proposals for meeting them.2. Imports for the second half of 1946 are likely to fall substantially belowthe programme agreed in February. This is because of shortage of food and rawmaterials supplies. The trend of exports is encouraging. The position for theyear 1946 therefore looks a bit better than it did when my colleagues examined theposition last in February. We then budgeted for a deficit of  770 millions in1946 which I warned my colleagues at the time was dangerously high.3. I now propose an import programme for the second half year of  600millions, divided at in paragraph 21 of the Annex. This would provide someimprovements in the diet within the limits of available supplies. It wouldprovide raw materials and machinery for industry to a sufficient extent, subjectto physical availability. It would provide some increase in the imports of consumer goods. The level of imports would be about 75 per cent, by volumeof 1938.4. The deficit for 1946 on this programme is estimated at  687 millions.This is a little better than we feared last February, but it is still ominously large,and there can be no general relaxation at present of our stringent limitation on overseas expenditure or of our export drive.5. A provisional programme of  590 millions is suggested for the first halfof 1947. This is designed to balance our target income on current account,excluding &quot;transitional&quot; post-war costs such as overseas military expenditure and relief. We must plan to achieve this balance, apart from these special costs,in the first half of 1947 in order to enable us to meet the shock of making sterlingconvertible a year after the passage of the United States Loan. I recommend thatwe make this a definite target.6. The proposals in the report are based on the assumption that we shall getthe United States Loan. But Departments cannot wait till then before pro-ceeding with purchases. If my colleagues approve the programme for the second half of 1946,1 shall be prepared to give immediate authority for purchases against it from all sources except the United States dollar area and Sweden, subject, ofcourse, to special points which may arise on individual items. Clearance forGovernment purchases in United States must, as far as possible, wait thepassage of the United States Loan, but, where it is necessary on supply grounds to make purchases, I shall treat individual applications on their merits.7. If the United States Loan is rejected by Congress, we shall, of course,have to make a rapid review of this import programme and heavy cuts will certainly be necessary, particularly on that portion which is to be drawn from united States dollar sources.H. D.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1.18th April, 1946.
ANNEX.BALANCE OF PAYMENTS WORKING PARTY.Import Programme for mid-1946 to mid-1947.Note by the Treasury:THE Balance of Payments Working Party must now recommend to ministers a final import programme for the second1 half of 1946 and a provisionalone for the first half of 1947. For this purpose, we assume that the United StatesLoan goes through; procurement procedure in the intervening period of uncertainty is set out in paragraph 23 below.First Half of 1946.2. Departments now estimate imports in the first half at  477 millions, or 48 millions below the programme of  52-5 millions determined by the Cabinetin February. This is analysed in Appendix A; the shortfall is primarilyaccounted for by the critical development of world food supplies, coupled withthe United States steel strike and deterioration in the supply position of certain other raw materials. The shortfall is resulting partly in cuts in consumption and partly in rapid exhaustion of stocks, in many cases below the danger point.Import Requirements in 1946-47.3. Departments have submitted their import requirements for the second half of 1946 and the first half of 1947; these have been examined by the ExchangeRequirements Committee; the following are the figures after adjustment by theTreasury in the light of this examination. The requirements and the Treasuryadjustments are explained in Appendix B; the figures as stated here are subjectto revision in respect of a few items still under discussion. The Treasuryconsiders that the adjusted requirements can be taken as realistic on supply grounds for planning purposes; they provide for some replacement of stocks whenthe latter have been exhausted below danger-level as a result of failure of imports in the first half-year.	1st half,	2nd half,	1st half,	1946.	1946.	1947.	Estimate of	Adjusted	Adjusted	imports.	requirement.	requirement	 m.	 m.	.  m.Food: basic   ...	J      0*7fk	( 260	240supplementary	f     Z/V)	I   60	55Raw materials	150	205	220Machinery	8	12*	14Other manufactures ...	10jt	18*	22Tobacco	31&apos;	26	24Seeds and cattle	7.1	12	8	477	594	583Allowance for prices	...	20	25	477	614	608The comparison between successive half-years is greatly distorted by seasonalityof supplies.4. The purposes of the requirements are not directly comparable; they maybe epitomised as follows : Fpod. The basic programme is the supply required to maintain con-sumption at the average level of the year July 1945 to June 1946. the supplementary programme represents desired improvements mainly in meat,dried egg, fresh fruit and1 vegetables and canned fruit. Supplies may notbe available to the extent requested in the supplementary programme, butthe adjusted basic requirement is believed to be realistic.Raw Materials. The amounts required to keep industry fully employed,subject to physical availability. Allowance is made for an increase to a six-page paper.
Machinery. The amount required by industry on a fairly liberal treat-ment of import licence applications.Other Manufactures. The available supplies of goods needed by industry (e.g., textile yarns); imports of consumer goods to meet especiallypressing shortages (e.g., furniture) and to release home-produced supplies for export; imports of less essentials from war-shattered countries; importsunder token import policy to re-establish pre-war trade connections with countries which make satisfactory financial arrangements with us.Tobacco. The amount required to employ manufacturing capacityfully; this will suffice to meet home demand plus a large export.Seeds and Cattle. Estimate of the Ministry of Agriculture.5. These cannot readily be reduced to a common denominator. The basicand supplementary food programmes, if achieved, would provide a significantimprovement in the protein content and in the variety of the diet twhich apartfrom fats would certainly not be worse than the pre-war national average.. the raw material programme is the amount available towards feeding a total manu-facturing and building activity which is estimated in the Economic Survey for1946-47 (E.S.W.P./3/46) to provide in spring 1947 a level of building andindustrial maintenance and re-equipment 10-15 per cent, above pre-war, a levelof exports 25 per cent, above pre-war, and an increase in civil consumption of manufactured goods from the present level of some 65 per cent, of pre-war to85-90 per cent, of pre-war. It is unlikely that as much as 10 per cent, of the raw material import programme is related to the improvement of civil consump-tion of manufactured goodis.6. Some allowance has again been made for an increase in prices. For thesecond half of 1946, the proposed allowance is  20 millions; commitments havebeen made for much of this programme. For the first half of 1947, an allowance of  25 millions is suggested, i.e., 5 per cent, on the food and raw materialprogrammes. Substantial changes in prices by early 1947 will tend to be reflected in export prices, too; when exports are on the same total scale as imports, theeffects on the balance of payments cancel out. There is, however, a time-lag,and the  25 millions is designed to allow for it. If international allocation ofscarce supplies breaks down, and prices run wild, this provision for the first halfof 1947 may prove much too small.External Purchasing Power.7. - Overseas income and expenditure in the period (apart from imports) areanalysed in Appendix C. The accounts have been divided between currentreceipts and payments, which relate to the normal peace-time needs of the economy, and transition receipts and payments, which represent the cost ofwinding up the war (overseas military expenditure, relief, Germany, &amp;c). Thebalance-sheet is as follows : Exports (payments) ...Net other current receipts ...Current net income ...Transition net expenditureAvailable for buying imports8. The Board of Trade&apos;s forecast of recorded exports for 1946 is up from 700 millions to  900 millions, and the corresponding payments from 550 millions to  745 millions. The new estimate is probably conservativelyrelated to manpower targets.9. The Treasury has re-examined our overseas financial commitments, andhas taken steps to curtail them and, perhaps more importantly, to prevent new commitments from being incurred. The scale of these transition commitmentsthroughout the world nearly  500 millions net in the eighteen months to June1947-r-is the root of our embarrassments; the figure of transition expenditureexcludes the possible impact upon our balance of payments of our financial arrangements with Western European Allies (see paragraph 7 of Appendix C).[31692] b 21st half,	2nd half,	1st half,1946.	1946.	1947. m.	 m.	*      m.4-295	4-450	4-550-    5	4- 15	4- 40+ 290	4-465	+ 590-195	-170	-1254- 95	4-295	4-465
10. The position now looks more favourable than it did in January.Nevertheless, in the first half of 1946 expenditure will exceed income by over 380 millions, which will be met by drafts on our reserves and by further mountingof sterling balances, to the extent that our creditors continue to be willing togo on accumulating sterling. If the import requirements were accepted in full,the deficit in the second half-year would be well over  300 millions a deficit for the year of some  700 millions, a figure which looks tolerable only alongside the previous estimate of  770 millions.Size of Import Programme.11. In fixing the size of the import programme, we must concentrate uponmeeting the shock of making sterling convertible about the middle of 1947. the target must be to balance our current account i.e., apart from transition expendi-ture in the first half of 1947. Only if we do this, can we face the financial obligations of the United States Loan Agreement with confidence.12. We therefore recommend an import programme for the first half of1947 which balances our target income on current account. Once the balance is achieved, and the international position of sterling established, we shall beable to expand imports when our exports grow further. We shall by no meansbe out of the wood if we achieve this target; our basic imports of food andraw materials will, in any case, require to increase as more supplies (e.g., of sugar and fats and timber) become available, and the sellers&apos; market for our exports may not last long. But we should be on the way towards long-termequilibrium.13. In the second half of 1946, basic imports will still be scarce. Thedifficulty of expanding supplementary imports to compensate, however, is theburden of maintaining them in future periods. The effect in future periodsbecomes cumulative as the increased basic supplies become available. We feel,however, that some risks might be run with food, and a large supplementaryallocation made. A general expansion of consumer goods imports (apart from&quot; iron ration&quot; imports and the substantial increase which will arise from the&apos;&apos; token &apos;&apos; and &apos;&apos; war-shattered &apos;&apos; policies) must wait.14. We propose a firm import programme of  600 millions for the second half of 1946 and a provisional programme of  590 millions in ihe first halfof 1947.   This would give the following balance : 1st half, 2nd half, 1st half,1946.             1946. 1947. m.  m.  m.Imports      ..........-477 -600 -590Current net income ...       4- 290 4- 465 4- 590Current deficit      ......       -187 -135Transition net expenditure      -195 -170 -125-382 -305 -125The deficit for 1946 would be  687 millions; the current balance would beachieved in the first half of 1947. The volume of imports on this programme in the period mid-1946 to mid-1947 would be around 75 per cent, of 1938,compared with the current level of 60-65 per cent, (see Appendix D).Distribution of Programme.15. We make the following proposals for the distribution of this programmeof  600 millions in the second half of 1946 and  590 millions in the first halfof 1947. The allowance for the first half of 1947 is provisional. If exports fail to develop as estimated, we shall have to back-pedal sharply in the firm programmedetermination for the first half of 1947.Food.16. (a) A basic  260 millions for the second half of 1946 and  240 millions for the first half of 1947.   No formal programme revision needed.(b) A supplementary programme of  46 millions for the second half of 1946,of which  13 millions from war-shattered countries and not more than 17 millions from United States and Canadian dollar sources.   If more is
available from war-shattered countries, it can be got without impinging uponthe rest of the supplementary programme.(c) A supplementary programme of  37 millions for the first half of 1947,of which on present indications  2 millions will come from war-shatteredcountries and about  18 millions from United States and Canadian dollar sources.Raw Materials.17. A programme of  205 millions for the second half of 1946 and 220 millions for the first half of 1947. No formal programme revision needed.This provides  1 million in each half-year for extra newsprint to increasethe size of newspapers to six pages after the passage of the United States Loan.Manufactured Goods.18. (a) A machinery programme of  12^ millions and  14 millions for thetwo half-years as programmed; if the responsible Departments consider that a more liberal policy would be desirable in the interests of industrial efficiency, theTreasury would agree.(b) An industrial and consumer goods programme of  18^ millions and 22 millions for the two half-years of which  7 millions and  8 millions in thetwo half-years from war-shattered economies (and more if available in the second half of 1946) and  11^ millions and  14 millions respectively from other sources,this to include the token import policy at  2 millions and  3 millions respectively.(c) As a whole, this represents a substantial expansion in these imports fromthe level of  10^ millions in the first half of 1946. There should be no generalexpansion of consumer goods imports, apart from what is provided in the war-shattered and token import policies. The ceilings set out in (b) broadly correspond with the amounts demanded in the requirements for specific items, adjusted foravailability. The Treasury must of course reserve its position on individualitems within this ceiling, as in the food and raw materal programmes.Tobacco.19. &apos;(a) It is not necessary to settle yet the purchases at the United StatesSeptember auctions, which govern the position to September 1947. This must await the passage of the United States Loan. As matters stand, there is apossibility of reducing the purchase below the programmed level at a risk of having to draw stocks down to minimum levels by September 1947 if additional supplies are not available from the Canadian crop later in the winter.(b) The remainder of the programme (apart from supplies from north america) to stand.Seeds and Cattle.20. The estimate of  12 millions in the second half of 1946 and  8 millions in the first half of 1947 to stand.21.   The programme would thus be (in   millions): .1st half, 2nd half, 1st half,1946 1946 1947(estimated actual).       (firm).            (provisional).Food: basic        .....-1 270 ( 260 240supplementary    ... ) (  46 37Raw materials     ......     150 205 220Machinery          .....,       8 12  14Industrial  and   consumer goods     .........      101 181 22Tobacco    ...      ......      31 26 24Seeds and cattle  ......        7-g 12 8477 580 565Allowance for prices     ...... 20 25600 590
22. No allowance has been made in this programme for additional petrolpurchases should Ministers decide to abolish petrol rationing ( 11 millions a year).The Treasury does not consider that this additional expenditure of  5^ millions in U.S. dollars in the second half of 1946 can be afforded; in the first half of 1947,it would be possible on our present estimates only at the expense of the supple-mentary food programme. The Treasury recommends that this matter be deferred until the next programme determination.23. If this programme is approved, the Treasury will be prepared to giveauthority for new purchases against it from all sources except the U.S. dollar area and Sweden, subject to special points which may arise on individualitems. It is hoped to clear Sweden fairly shortly; clearance for United Statespurchases must as far as possible await passage of the United States Loan.Departments are requested to provide the Treasury with a list of the items on, their programmes for which they will on supply grounds require authority forprocurement before the end of June.APPENDIX A.Imports in the First Half of 1946.1. At the programme determination in February (CM. (46) 14th Con-clusions) the Cabinet approved a programme of  525 millions for the first halfof 1946. Departments now estimate that imports in this period will be 477 millions, as follows : January-June 1946.	Approved by	Revised	Cabinet.	estimate.	 m.	 m.Food............	281	270Raw materials	160	150Machinery	12	other Manufactures       &apos; ...	11	ioiTobacco	31	31Seeds and cattle	9	7i &apos; 2Allowance for prices	21		525	4772. The programmes approved by the Cabinet for the half-year had alreadybeen reduced by  27 millions below stated requirements to allow for failures insupply; this allowance, however, has in the event proved insufficient, and theactual imports against the programmes are expected to fall short bv a further 48 millions. J3. The lack of basic supplies has affected the food, raw material, and manufactured goods programmes alike, as the following examples show :-Estimated shortfall in certain programmed imports, January-June, 1946.	Original	Revised Estimate.Food (basic) 	Programme.	of Arrivals.Wheat         ......	(th. tons) .     2,396    .	1,841Maize, barley, oats ...	,,   ...        552	211Oilseeds and nuts   ...	946	520Animal fats ...	70	45Meat.....&apos;.	...        543	463&apos; Bacon and ham-	147	97i Cheese	127	108
- Original Revised EstimateRaw Materials- ^ Programme. of Arrivals.Steel......... (th. tons) 560 240Copper        ...... 186 128Lead......... 86 63Softwood      ...... (th. stds.) 374 355Woodpulp    ...... (th. tons) 506 376Building board       ... (mil. sq. ft.) .71 59Phosphate rock      ... (th. tons) 415 321Manufactured Goods Mining machinery ...         ( &apos;000) 585 385Textile machinery  ...            ,, 1,045 452Furniture.    ......            ,, 820 220Cotton yarns and manufactures ,, 1,100 610Woollen and worsted yarns and manufactures   ...            ,, 650 4004. Substantial involuntary savings of foreign exchange have thus become possible. It may be approximately estimated that the saving in United Statesdollars has been of the order of  10 millions, despite the fact that failure ofsupplies elsewhere has hindered the shift away from United States sources ofsupply.5. The following table shows the geographical distribution of the estimatedarrivals : Estimated Arrivals, January-June, 1946 : Geographical Distribution.Canada	United States	and New-	Other	Sterling	War-		Dollar.	foundland. Countries		Area.	shattered.	Total.	 m.	 m.	 m.	 m.	 m.	 m.Food       ......	53-9	52-4	53-4	101 1	8-9	269-7Raw materials ...	17-2	18-8	48-2	61 1	4-7	150-0Manufactures	9-6	1-4	4-0	1-0	2-7	18-7Tobacco   ...	26-4	1-0	0 1	3-7	01	31-3Seeds and cattle	0-2	0-1	0-3	6-7	0-3	7-6	107-3	73-7	106-0	173-6	16-7	477-appendix B.Import Programme from mid-1946 to mid-1947.1.   Departments state their desired imports as follows : 2nd half, 1946.        1st half, 1947. m.  m.Food: basic    ...      ,........      271 254supplementary          ......        bU ^Raw materials          ....      ......      2 * %Manufactured goods  ....      .......       f* ifTobacco          ............        ?6. - ^Seeds and cattle        ..... 12617 6172. The requirements are summarised in the accompanying tables. Theyhave been examined by the Exchange Requirements Committee.Food.3. The basic requirements (Table II) are to maintain the average con-sumption standard of the year July 1945 to June 1946 a period of greaterstringency in the staple foods than the war years.   The4 required basic imports
are put at  271 millions for the second half of 1946 and at  254 millions for thefirst half of 1947.   The following are the underlying assumptions : (a) United Kingdom production of food is assumed to be appreciably lower than in previous years; deliveries are estimated as follows: 	July 1944 to	July 1945 to	July 1946 to	June 1945.	June 1946.	June 1947.		(&apos;000 tons.)	Wheat (for milling)	2,193	1,543	1,465Barley and oats   ...	1,805	2,481	2,088Potatoes (ware for human			consumption)	6,046	6,029	6,010Edible pulses	58	96	104Sugar (as refined)	388	504	444Carcase   meat   and   offal			(home fed)	748	806	695Bacon   and   ham   (home			killed)          ...      :..	82	103	83Fish (landed weight)	362	692	1,024Milk for liquid consump-			tion  (million gallons)	1,218	1,281	1,315Milk products	155	143	150Eggs         .........	192	207	216(b) United Kingdom stocks (except for canned meat) are assumed to bedrawn down to the minimum level for efficient distribution (and some-times below it). These levels will in general have been reached by mid-1946, when stocks will be 3-6 million tons, compared with-4 million tons at mid-1945. It is proposed if possible to hold this level (subject to variations due to seasonality of supplies) in mid-1947. In the year under consideration, no general saving in importswill be possible by drafts from stock.(c) The requirements have been calculated at present contract prices.  prices are likely to rise in the remainder of this vear. The Treasury con-siders that an addition of  15 millions would be appropriate to coverthis as well as to cover such switches as may be necessary to high-cost sources in the second half of 1946 to maintain basic supplies.4. The requirements for the second half of 1946 include  10 millions inrespect of oils and fats, supply of which is not yet in sight, but to obtain whichthe most energetic efforts are being made. Neglecting possible price increases(allowed for in 3(c) above), the Treasury considers that the cost of the actualimports on the basic programme is unlikely to exceed  260 millions in the second half of 1946 and  240 millions in the first half of 1947.5. The amounts of dried egg and orange juice to be included in the basic programme are under discussion between the Treasury and the Ministry of Food.The figures above are related to the requirements as stated by the Ministry ofFood, and are subject to reduction in the light of the examination now takingplace.6. The supplementary requirements (Table III) stand at  60 millions forthe second half of 1946 and  55 millions for the first half of 1947. These repre-sent desired improvements on the consumption level of mid-1945 to mid-1946.The main elements are meat, dried egg, fresh fruit and vegetables and canned fruit.7. The diet during the next year will inevitably be weak in fats. If the basic programme were achieved, and if the supplementary programme were carried out in full, taking into account the tremendous expansion of fish con-sumption, the protein content of the diet would be very good, and there wouldbe some improvement in the variety of the diet. The availability of a numberof the supplementary items (especially bacon and dried egg) is doubtful, and orders for the dried egg would have to be placed before the likely date of passageof the United States Loan.
. Raw Materials.8. The raw materials requirements (Table IV) submitted jointly by theBoard of Trade and the Ministry of Supply are  214 millions for the second half of 1946 and  234 millions for the first half of 1947.(a) The requirements are based upon the estimated capacity of industry to absorb materials, within the possible limits of fuel and labour. stocks are in general estimated to fall during the period to effective minimumlevels.(b) The required amounts of certain materials (e.g., timber, steel) may notbe wholly available. Allowing for this, the Treasury considers thatthe actual cost of this programme is unlikely to exceed  205 millions in the second half of 1946 and  220 millions in the first half of 1947.(c) The requirements have been calculated at present contract prices.   TheTreasury considers that an increase of  5 millions would suffice tocover such price increases as may take place in the second half of 1946.(d) The requirements are not in general related to essentiality of end-use;the criterion is the absorptive capacity of manfacturing industryrather than the end-use of the product. Control of the latter is ingeneral exerted at the manufacturing rather than the raw materialend, e.g., by licensing of manufacture, export targets, &amp;c.(e) The newsprint programme is based on the assumption that the six-pagenewspaper will be introduced at an early date (cost  1 million perhalf-year). The pulp and paper programme generally is subject tofurther review in the light of the Swedish financial negotiations;the requirements provide in accordance with the previously arranged&apos;&apos; minimum&apos;&apos; plan for an expansion of paper consumption (exceptnewsprint) to a rate of about three-quarters of pre-war in the second half of 1946; a slight further increase is provided for the first half of1947.Manufactured Goods.9. These requirements (Table V) submitted jointly by the Board of Tradeand the Ministry of Supply, total  34 millions in the second half of 1946 and 42 millions in the first half of 1947 as follows : (a) Machinery. Requirements,  12^ millions and  14 millions in the twohalf-years. This assumes continuation of the existing screening pro-cedure, by which manufacturers wishing to import machinery must showneed and inability to get a suitable machine in time from UnitedKingdbm production. This is interpreted by Departments liberally,and the great majority of applications are granted. The figures include requirements submitted by the Ministries of Agriculture and fuel and Power.(b) Industrial Goods. Requirements,  5 millions and  6 millions in the twohalf-years. The big items are textile yarns and manufactures andfilm base.(c) Consumer  Goods. -Requirements,   10 millions  and   10^  millions.The principal items are furniture, footwear and rugs (part of whichare of course &quot;industrial&quot;). These imports are related primarily to particularly pressing shortages, although they contain someimports of less essential goods (bulbs, perfume, &amp;c.) from war-shattered countries. The supplies of some items under (b) and (c)are uncertain, and the Treasury considers that  14 millions and 16 millions are safe figures to take for programme purposes.(d) Token   Imports. The   Board  of   Trade   has  included  figures  of 2^ millions and  4 millions, for the two half-years to cover importsunder the &apos;&apos; token import&apos;&apos; policy. This provides for the admissionof imports to a value up to 20 per cent, of pre-war from overseasmanufacturers who had a pre-war trade in manufactured and brandedgoods with United Kingdom; the concession is open to countries with which we have made satisfactory financial arrangements, and alist is prepared in agreement with these countries of the goods towhich we should grant this concession. Canada is the first countryto take advantage of this; this may involve imports from Canada of
 330,000 a year. The concession is being offered to United States,and extensions will be made to the list according to the wishes of thecountries concerned. The Dominions and Switzerland are probableapplicants. The scope of this policy and the rate at which it willbe translated into imports into United Kingdom is still uncertain,and the Treasury considers that we should budget for lower figures i.e.,  2 millions and  3 millions in the two half-years,(e) Extra &apos;&apos; war-shattered &apos;&apos; imports. The Board of Trade has includedcontingency figures of  4 millions and  7 millions for furtherimports from war-shattered countries in the two half-years. supplies are now beginning to become available, and it is difficult to makeprecise forecast. The Board of Trade estimate, however, assumescontinued development of the policy into 1947, Avhen its energeticapplication will raise difficulties on the grounds of discrimination.On a neutral assumption about the policy in 1947, the Treasury con-siders it reasonable to budget for  2-V millions and  3 millions in thetwo half-years.10. The adjusted manufactured goods requirements may thus be put at 31 millions for the second half of 1946 and  36 millions for the first half of1947.Tobacco.11. The required tobacco purchases (Table IV) are  26 millions and 24 millions in the .two half-years. These are framed on the following assumptions : &apos; :   ] (a) Amount of imported tobacco manufactured will rise from 175 million lbs.in the first half year of 1946 to 190 millions in the first half year of1947. There is available capacity for this.(&amp;) Consumption in United Kingdom will increase in 1946 as the civilpopulation grows, and will be stabilised through the period mid-1946 to mid-1947. There will be a large margin available for export,taking into account the fall in Service demand overseas; over theperiod as a whole, the supplies available for export would be about125 per cent, of pre-war.   There is an ample market.(c) Stocks of United States tobacco at the minimum point this year (end-September) are estimated at 176-5 million lbs. or 7-3 months&apos;consumption; the required purchases of 298 million lbs. would main-tain them at this level.    The minimum level for manufacture is! - 6^ months&apos; stock.   If it were desired to reduce stocks to rock-bottomby end-September 1947, the purchasing programme could be reducedby 20 million lbs., equivalent to  2f millions in the year.(d) The statement of  requirements by the  Board of Trade includes8 millions from Canada; more supplies may be available if this cropis successful, and the Board of Trade&apos;s intention is to buy as muchas it can. This can be used in substitution for United States tobacco;if United States supplies are adequate, manfacturers would substi-tute it for Rhodesian. It would be very risky to reduce United Statespurchases in the hope of getting additional Canadian, because theCanadian crop is a very fluctuating one, and when the United Statessales take place, the prospects for the Canadian crop are not known.The latest exports are not favourable.12. There is no need to take a decision yet on the size of the purchases from the United States crop next September.Seeds and Cattle,. 13. The requirements (Table IV) are estimated by the Ministry ofAgriculture at  12 millions in the second half of 1946 and  8 millions in thefirst half of 1947.
14.   The total requirements as adjusted are therefore as follows : 	2nd half,	1st half,	1946.	1947.	 m.	 m.Food : basic ...       ...       ...       ...	260	240supplementary	60	55Raw materials	205	220Machinery	12i	14Industrial and consumer goods	14	16Token and extra &quot;war-shattered&quot;	4J-	6Tobacco        ...	26	24Seeds and cattle	12	8	594	583Allowance for prices	20	25*	614	608* See paragraph 6 of report.APPENDIX C.Overseas Income and Expenditure (other than Imports).1. The Treasury and the Bank of England consider that the most appro-priate presentation of overseas income and expenditure at this time makes asclear a distinction as possible between current receipts and payments andtransition receipts and payments. , The current account relates to the normal peace-time needs of the economy; it includes imports, exports and the customaryinvisibles, such as film remittances, shipping receipts and interest on overseasinvestments; this is the amount that reveals our progress towards long-termbalance. The transition account covers the large Government receipts and pay-ments which arise in the process of winding up the war; overseas military expendi-ture, relief, the cost of supplying the British zone in Germany, loans and advancesof a predominantly political character of which no repayment is in sight, &amp;c.2. In marginal cases, the distinction inevitably becomes misty. Relief ship-ments from United Kingdom are included in the current account as &quot; exports,&quot;although our contribution to U.N.R.R.A. is in the transition account; for technical reasons, the cost of providing oil and shipping for the overseas forces appears in the current account; &quot; normal &quot; overseas Government expenditure (e.g., diplo-matic representation, the cost of the peace-time elements in our overseas armed forces, &amp;c.) is included in the transition account because it would be purelyarbitrary at this stage to guess a &apos;&apos; normal&apos;&apos; figure for inclusion in current account.3. Much of the &quot; transition &quot; expenditure will continue for a considerable period ahead.Current A account.4. The Board of Trade estimates recorded exports at  185 millions in thefirst quarter of 1946, rising to  210 millions in the second quarter,  240 millions in the third quarter and  265 millions in the fourth quarter. This is equivalentto payments lagged for three months of  295 millions in the first half of1946 and  450 millions in the second half, rising to  550 millions in the first half of 1947.5.   The following are the estimates of other net current items in 1946 : .  millions.Oil transactions ...      ...       -40     As in Appendix D of B.P.W.P./3/46.Foreign Exchange cost of United King-dom imports 28; of military purchases19; of tankers 24, totalling 71. foreign exchange earnings of British companiesby sales to third countries of 31.
Adjustment for exports of oil equipment......Shipping......Civil aviationFilm remittances...Interest, profits and dividends (excluding oil) .Diamonds and fursRe-exportsMiscellaneous  millions.Supplies to British companies from United- 28*      Kingdom are recorded as &apos;&apos; exports &apos;&apos; butare not debited as an exchange cost to the oil companies above.4- 5     Non-tanker.- 4     Includes Constellation aircraft.   Ministryof Civil Aviation estimate.-16 Assumes small income from British filmsoverseas.4- 57     Bank of England estimate.-1- 8 Estimated proceeds to balance of - payments of markets in London.4-13     From imports in the import programme.+ 15 Insurance, commission, New Zealand foodpremium. (4), .&amp;c, plus substantialunidentifiable net receipts.4-10This figure is not comparable with the corresponding figure in the previous pro-gramme determination paper; certain items included then are now carried to the transition account, and vice versa.6. The division between the half-years of the &quot;other&quot; item may beestimated as a deficit of  5 millions in the first half of 1946 and a credit of 15 millions in the second half-year; the credit in the first half of 1947 may beestimated at  40 millions. The dynamic items in the account are oil and shipping.Transition Account.7. The most important items for payments-   millions.Net overseas military ex-penditure   .....       ...      250t1946 are listed as follows:- Estimate for financial year  200 millions,allowing for sales of surpluses overseas,N.A.A.F.I. expenditure, payments ofaccumulated arrears, &amp;c.U.N.R.R.A.......	80	Excluding services provided in United Kingdom.Germany   ...	50t	Net deficit on operation of British zone.Greece	18	Political loans, &amp;c. .Far Eastern relief and re-habilitation	.29	Burma, Hong Kong, Borneo; advances.Colonies	161	Contribution to Colonial deficit, Colonial development and welfare, &amp;c.Diplomatic,        publicity, U.N.O., &amp;c.	12t	Canadian settlement	11	Pajunents to Canada of 36 in respect of claims and counter-claims, less 25 for deficit in our current payments in first two months of 1946, offset in the settle-ment.Miscellaneous net payments	15t 481	* This is an accounting adjustment, arising from the fact that all shipments from theUnited Kingdom are recorded as exports; as only the foreign exchange costs of the British oil companies are taken into account in &quot;oil transactions &quot; above, this additional adjustment mustbe made. ... &apos;: &apos;- ...... ,f These items will continue at a substantial level for a considerable period. &apos; ; . ; &apos;
  millions.Receipts Cotton and other raw- material stocks ...Wool Agreement ...Lend-Lease pipelinePayment  by  France   forarmaments       ...      ...2028*32The import programme includes shipmentfrom His Majesty&apos;s Governments&apos; over-seas stocks. This item must thus comeon the credit side.Imports provided by United States afterthe 31st December, 1945, under pipelinearrangement, settlement for which (has-already been scored in 1945 accounts.36116* These items will continue at a substantial level for a considerable period.The deficit on the transition account is thus estimated at  365 millions in 1946.This may be distributed very approximately for it is largely a matter of chance-when large single items are paid at  195 millions in the first half-year and 170 millions in the second half-year. The corresponding deficit on the transitionaccount in the first half of 1947 may be put at  125 millions.8. The transition account as set out above does not include the effect of the-impact upon our financial reserves of our financial arrangements with France andthe other Western European allies. To the extent that these countries financetheir deficits with us in 1946 by the sale to us of sterling securities, we shall beselling them our exports without receiving corresponding payment in the current account. The same applies, of course, to sales to sterling area countries to theextent to which they are in fact paid for by a drawing down of their sterling balances.A vailable Ftinds for Buying Imports.9. The position in these accounts, excluding imports, may thus be sum-marised as follows (in   millions) :-Exports      ...Net other current receipts1st half	2nd half	1st half1946.	1946.	1947.4-295	4-450	4-550-   5	4- 15	4- 404-290	4-465	4-590-195	-170	-1254- 95	4-295	4-465Current net incomeTransition net expenditureAvailable for buying imports10. The figure of  390 millions available in 1946 for purchasing importscompares with a figure of  305 millions in paragraph 16 of the Appendix to cp. (46) 53. The latter assessment, however, excluded a number of &quot; transition &quot;items (e.g., Germany) for which it is now possible to make a reasonable estimate..The estimates then current of our transitional liabilities were altogether too low;the increase in these on more detailed examination, coupled with the more completeanalysis&apos; of the impact of oil upon the balance of payments set out inB.PW.P./3/46 has absorbed more than one-half of the prospective increment of income arising from the radical upward revision of the Board of Trade&apos;s exportestimates.
APPENDIX D.Comparison with 1938.1. Comparison of the recommended import, programme with 1938 is asfollows: Programme* from mid-Retained Imports 1938.     1946 to mid-1947.		at	at	Quantum	at 1938	programme	programme	as % of	prices.	prices.	prices.	1938.	 m.	 m.	 m.	 m.Food...      ...      .........	380	790	583	74Raw materials	245	470	425	91Machinery  ...	18	45	261	59Industrial and consumer goods ...	66	150		27Tobacco	21	40	50	125Seeds and cattle   ...	9	25	20	80	739	1,520	1,145	75* As in paragraph 21 of report.2. The proposed programme is thus 75 per cent, by volume of the level in1938. The prices used in the programme (representing present contract prices,before the extra allowance for price rises) appear to have risen by 105 per cent.f.o.b. since 1938; this represents in part an increase in prices in individual sources of supply, and in part the effect of the switch from pre-war low-cost sources to post-war high-cost sources of supply (especially North America).3. Food and raw materials will be at about 75 per cent, and 90 per cent, of1938 respectively; these imports are limited primarily by supply considerations in these programmes. The price data for machinery, industrial and consumer goods are much less reliable; the evidence suggests that the volume of consumer goods imports may be of the order of 40 per cent, of 1938, and that of industrialgoods (mainly in peace-time an interchange of semi-manufactures between UnitedKingdom and Western Europe) may be only of the order of 20 per cent, of 1938.Table I. United Kingdom Import Programme, 1946-47.: Geographical Distribution.(  millions.)			Canada								U.S.		and		Other		W	xr			dollar		Newfound-		countries	Sterling	shattered.		Vn-		area.		land.		n.e.s.	area.	area.		allocated.	Total.					July-December		1946.			Food-										Basic  ...	60	7	56	1	53-7	83-0	8	-0	10-0	271-5Supplementary	18	7	9	2	8-9	9-9	13	-1		59-8Total   ......	79	4	65	3	62-6	92-9	21	1	10-0	331-3Raw materials  ...	26	3	28-	2	78-2	74-5	7	-0		214-2Tobacco ...	22	5			0-1	3-6	0	1		26-3Machinery	10	1	6	4	1-7	0-1	0	2		12-industrial goods...       ^	1	4	0	2	1-6	0-3	1	6		5-1Consumer goods...	1	0	i	3	2-8	1-3	3	6		10-0Supplementary imports							4	0	2-5	6-5Seeds and store cattle ...	&quot;6	6	0	4	0-3	9-9	0	6		11-8Total......	141	3	95	8	147-3	182-6	38	2	12-5	617-7					January-June		1947.			Food-										Basic  ---	28	8	51	7	57-3	107-1	9	5		254-4Supplementary	28	1	5	7	9-0	9-7	2	1	...	54-6Total   ......	56	9	57	4	66-3	116-8	11	6		309-0Raw materials  ...	38	8	26	5	78-1	82-6	8	1	...	234-1Tobacco ...	20	3	1	0	0-1	2-7	0	1		24-2Machinery        ...       ...	11	1	0	6	2-0	0-1	0	3		14-industrial goods	1	8	0	1	1-7 &apos;	0-5	2	0		6-1Consumer goods	1	0	1	4	2-7	1-9	3	-5		10-5Supplementary imports					0-3		.   7	0	4-0	11-0Seeds and store cattle ...	0	6	0	4		6-5	0	-3		8-1Total   ......	130	5	87	4	151-2	211-1	32	-9	4-0	617-1
Table II. Food Import Programme, 1946-47-.Basic Proaramme.Wheat and edible grainFeeding-stuffsOilseeds, oils and fatsSugar, starch, glucoseMeat and bacon   ...Fish . ...Butter, cheese, milk eggs        ......Fruit and vegetablesTea, coffee, cocoa ...Beer, wines, spiritsMiscellaneousTotal1st half,	2nd half,	1st half,1946.	1946.	1947. m.	 m.	 m.35 0	39-7	40-24-4	7-8	13-723-1	30 0	27113-6	15-7	14-468-1	50-1	51-211-5	12-3	8-336-9	34-7	31 1181	32-9	13-923-6	15 0	21 122-3	21-9	22-59-4	7-6	6-93-8	3-8	41269-6	271-5	254-3Edible grain and starchCarcase meat and offalPoultry   ...       .....Canned meat     ....Bacon, and hamDried milk        ...       ..Dried egg .....Canned fruit and vege-tables ...Citrus fruitOther  fruit   and  vege-tables ...Beer, wines, spiritsOther foodsTotal   ...Edible grain and starchCarcase jneat and offal...Poultry&apos;...Canned meatBacon and ham ...Dried milk dried egg......Canned fruit and vege-ables ...Citrus fruitOther  fruit   and vege-tables ...Beer, wines, spiritsOther foodsTotal   ...Table III. Food Import Programme, 1946-47.Supplementary Programme.(  millions.)CanadaU.S. and Other Wardollar   Newfoiind- countries Sterling shatteredarea.        land. n.e.s.        area.       areas.Jnhj-December, 1946.0-3 ... 03-30-1 * &apos;0-4 0-60-54-40-97-25-70-118-70-97-66-21-310-61-10-3*5-20-80-11-41-10-60-22-81-10-72-42-22-02-510119-28-99-813-1January-June, 1947.0-22-20-21-82-01-21-30-20-30-11-00-63-13-60-11-20-11-10-728-1 5-7 9-0 9-7* Less than  50,000.2-1Total.0-912-91-01-10-910-2-171359-81-514-90-42-86-2-1-310-60-65-254-7Notes.(1)(2)(3)(5) .(6)(7)(8)(9)(10)(1)(2)(S)(4)(5)(6)(7)(8)(9)(10)Notes.(1) Meat. The programme will permit an increase in the allocation of meat for manu-facturing purposes (sausag;c, :neat pies, &amp;c.) and an increase of 2d. per head per week in theordinary ration throughout the period.(2) Poultry. Additional supplies are believed to be available. This programme will providefor Christmas and may also have some effect on the black market.(3) Canned meat. This programme will permit additional allocations on points.(4) Bacon. If these supplies can be obtained, the ration can be increased by 1 oz. per head per week.
(5) Dried milk.-This programme will permit restoration of allocations to manufacturers(chocolate, bakers, ice cream, &amp;c).(6) Dried egg. If this programme and the basic programme are fulfilled and if home production of shell eggs comes up to present expectations, consumers would receive 69 eggs or their equivalent in the six months, July to December, 1946, and 77 in the six months, january to June, 1947. Comparable figures for July to December 1945, and January to June 1946, are51 and 55 respectively.(7) Canned fruit and vegetables. The Ministry of Food state that these imports would be widely welcomed.(8) Citrus fruit. This programme would allow for further increases in supplies, but these would, still be very much below pre-war levels.(9) Other fruit and vegetables. The programme provides for increased imports of freshvegetables, mainly from Europe; also bananas and apples.(10) Beer, wines and spirits. The major part of this programme is for hops from Europe.Table IV.Raw Materials Import Programme, 1946-47.	1st half.	2nd half,	1st half,	1946.	1946.	1947.	 m.	 m.	 m.Iron and steel	......        8-0	18-6	29-9Non-ferrous metals       ...	......      21-6	28-9	29-3Timber	......      17-9	39-3	32-7Textiles    ......	......      47-1	56-4	70-6Pulp and paper   ...	......      12-6	19-3	19-1Hides, &amp;c. ...	......      11-8	15-4	15-3Fertilisers ...	......        5-3	6-3	6-miscellaneous	......      25-7	29-9	30-8Total     ......	......     150-0	214-2	234-1Tobacco Import Programme, 1946-47			-	1st half,	2nd half,	1st half,	1946.	1946.	1947.	 m.	 m.	 m.United States	......      260	22-5	20-3Canada	......        10	...  -	10Rhodesia   ...	1-5	2-0	0-5India        ...       ...      ...	......        1-2	0-9	1-1Nyasa	...                 1-0	0-6	1-other countries	0-2	0-3	0-3Total	......      30-9	26-3	24-2M.A .F. Import Programme, 1946-47.	1st half,		2nd half,		1st half,	1946.		1946.		-1947.	 m.		 m.		 m.Seeds        ...      ...	1	4	2-2		1-8Cattle       ..........	......    &apos;   6	2	9-6		6-3Total	.......   &apos;   7	6	11-8		8-1	Table V.				Manufactured Goods Import Programme, 1946-47						1st half,	2nd half,		1st half,		1946.		1946.	1947.	Machinery 	 m.		 m.	 m.	Agricultural   ...	2-1		1-5	3	0	0-4		0-8	0	3Steel making ...      _____	0-2		2-8	2	1Textile ...	0-5		11	1	other   ...      ...	4-8		6-3	7	5Total	8-0		12 - 5	14	1
1st half,	2nd half,	1st half,1946.	1946.	1947. m.	 m.	 m.4-3	3 3	3-90-8	1-8	2-25-1	5-1	6-industrial Goods Board of trade ministry of Supply  ...Total      ........Consumer Goods Board of Trade  -Furniture      ......      ...      0-2 3-2 4-2Carpets ......      ...      01 0-6 1-other   ......      ...    . ...      3-0 4-2 2-ministry of Supply Drugs, medicines, &amp;c.Other............Total      .........Allowance     for     &apos;&apos; tokenimportsAllowance for imports from war-shattered countries   ...Total      .........1-4	1-3	1-50-9	0-7	0-65-6	100	10-5	2-5	40...	4-0	7-018-7	34 1	41-7




</content>
</cab>
