<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/9/0 images: 410-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (46)  17729TH  APRIL,  1946.FUTURE OF THE IRON AND  STEEL industry memorandum by the Lord president of the CouncilHaving regard  to the proceedings- in the House of Commons onWednesday, 17th April, it is des ir abl e . that we should consider how the parliamentary position on iron and .steel should be handled.      There is considerable pressure for a debate, whichwill become greater when the White Paper is published,  containing the technical report of  the Iron and Steel Federation.2.      The Opposition has a case for  a one-day debate,  especially if the Government proceed under emergency powers and the control board uses these powers to pledge public credit in the interim period;    indeed, the Opposition might put down a Vote of censure.      Should legislation be required for  the transitional arrangements (though I  trust it will  not),   the case for a specialdebate is less strong, but even in that event an- emphaticexpression of opinion by the House of Commons might bring the ironand steel industry to  a more co-operative frame of mind.    Ifit should be decided  to give a day for a debate, it could takeplace on either a Government or an Opposition Motion.      on balance, I  think a Government Motion would be best:    it wouldenable the Government to state its case better  and the Motion,when carried would have the au.thc.rity of the House of Commonsbehind it in inviting the co-operation of the industry.COPY NO.^V)       *****cabinet.      The Motion might be on the following lines:-&quot;That this House approves the decision of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to transfer to the ownership of the nationappropriate sections of the  iron and steel industry witha view to its   efficient organisation in the public interest;and invites the co-operation of the industry in thenecessary transitional arrangements&quot;.4.      The Chief Whip  tells me  that the   legislative programme willbe materially Inconvenienced if a day is given in May to iron andsteel:    but I am advised by the Minister of Supply that he would wish the debate  to  take place not later  than the end of May.II   5.      If my colleagues agree I would propose  to include an announce-I   ment  that a day will be given to a Government motion on iron and\   steel, in my Business -Statement to the House on Thursday, 2nd May.6.      So far as administrative arrangements are concerned,  thePrime Minister has agreed that further  action should now be takenby the Ministerial Committee on the Socialisation of Industries.The next step in this respect would appear to be for the Ministerof Supply,  to bring before that Committee his proposals regardingthe composition and duties of the Control Board  to be set up inthe  interim peri od, with  an indication of the powers under whichit will operate. H MPrivy Council Office, S.W. 1.29TH APRIL,  1946.+   The draft of the White Paper will be circulated as CP. (46)  178 for consideration by the cabinet with this paper.




</content>
</cab>
