<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/9/0 images: 476-507</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;s GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  May 1946.SECRET Copy No.CP. (46) 185.3rd May, 1946.CABINET.SCIENTIFIC MAN-POWER.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.AS my colleagues will remember, I appointed in December 1945 a Committee,under the acting chairmanship of Sir Alan Barlow, with the following terms ofreference : &quot; To consider the policies which should govern the use and developmentof our scientific man-power and resources during the next ten years.&quot; To submit an interim report on very broad lines at ,an early date soas to facilitate forward planning in those fields which are dependent uponthe use of scientific man-power.&quot;At a later date to make recommendations as to the establishment ofpermanent machinery for carrying out surveys as to the best use of ourscientific resources in the national interest.&quot;This Committee have now fulfilled the first part of their terms of reference and I attach a copy of their report on Scientific Man-power problems. As willbe seen from the summary of conclusions (paragraph 67 of the report), theCommittee find that we are threatened with a very grave shortage of qualifiedscientists unless urgent steps are taken to double the output of science graduatesfrom the Universities. They accordingly recommend that the Government shouldsponsor an ambitious University expansion programme at the earliest possible moment. I am in general agreement with the conclusions to which the Committeehave come, as I attach the utmost importance to ensuring that the nation hasavailable an adequate supply of qualified scientists. If we do not do so we cannotmaintain, far less improve, our position in the world and our standard of lifeat home. I sincerely nope, therefore, that the Committee&apos;s recommendations willbe accepted by the Cabinet.I announced my intention to appoint the Committee in the House of commons on the 29th November, 1945, and in answer to a Question in the House of commons on the 14th February I undertook to give careful consideration to the question of publishing the report on Scientific Man-power when it became available. TheChairman of the Committee informs me that the report has been drafted witha view to publication if the Government decide to adopt such a course. In viewof the very general interest which has been shown in the deliberations of theCommittee, and the need to secure a wide acceptance among educational authoritiesin. general and the Universities in particular of the case for an urgent expansionof the Universities, I think that the report should be published immediately.I accordingly seek the approval of my colleagues : (i) To publish the report forthwith.(ii) To accompany its publication with a statement in the House of commons to the effect that the Government are in general agreement with theconclusions of the Committee, which they recognise will involve asubstantial liability on the Exchequer, and commend them to theimmediate and serious consideration of the Universities with a viewto the formulation of detailed proposals in consultation with theUniversity Grants Committee.The Chancellor of the Exchequer concurs in this Memorandum.(Initialled)      H. M.Office of the Lord President of the Council, S.W. 1,3rd May, 1946.[31770]

PROOFSCIENTIFIC   MAN-POWERREPORT OF A COMMITTEE APPOINTED BYTHE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCILPresentedLONDONHIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY office net cmd.
CONSTITUTION OF THE committee sir Alan Barlow, Bart., K.C.B., K.B.E. (Chairman).Sir Edward V. Appleton, G.B.E., K.C.B., F.R.S.Professor P. M. S, Blackett, F.B.S.Mr. Geoffrey Crowther.Sir Alfred Egerton, F.R.S.Sir George Nelson.Professor S. Zuckerman, C.B., F.R.S.Dr. C P. Snow, C.B.E., Scientific Assessor.Mr. A. Gunn, M.B.E., Labour Assessor.Mr. M. T. Flett, Secretary.Mr. E. J. C. Dixon  ^CONTENTSParagraphsPREAMBLE............     ............ 1I.-INTRODUCTION       ......     ...     ......     - 2-5II. THE IMMEDIATE PROBLEM-(1) DEMOBILISATION     .................. 6-8(2) EMERGENCY ACCOMMODATION         ...     ...      ... 9III.-THE LONGER TERM PROBLEM-(1) SUPPLY AND DEMAND     ...     ...     ......... 10-23(2) DOUBLING THE OUTPUT OF SCIENTISTS ...      ... 24(i) The Talent Available   ...      ...      ...      ...... 25-27(ii) Comparison with other Countries   ......... 28(iii) The   Relation   between    Science    and    otherFaculties (a) Engineering and Technology   ......... 29-34(b) The Humanities   ...      ............ 35(iv) The Capacity of the Universities to Expand (a) The Need for Money     ......      ...      ... 36(b) Other Impediments to Expansion    ...... 37-44(c).The Problems of Individual Universities   ... 45-54(3) THE QUALITY OF SCIENCE TEACHING    ...... 55(4) THE EFFECT OF OUR PROPOSALS (i) The Supply of Graduates during the ten years  ... 56-57(ii) The Assessment of Priorities ...      ...      ...      ... 58-60(iii) The Position after 1955.........     &apos;...      ... 61-62(5) THE IMPLEMENTATION OF OUR PROPOSALS ... 63-66IV. SUMMARY OF CONCLUSIONS   ............ .  67
m.To the Et. Hon. Herbert Morrison m p   rnTTT, -nCouncil : ^urrison, m.I ., the Lord President of the sir,PREAMBLE1. We were appointed by you on the 9th December, 1945, to considerthe policies which should govern the use and development of our scientificman-power and resources during the next ten years and to submit a reporton very broad lines at an early date so as to facilitate forward planning inthose fields which are dependent upon the use of scientific man-power.We now have the honour to submit the following report.I-INTRODUCTION2.   We do not think that it is necessary to preface our report by stating at length the case for developing our scientific resources.   Neverbefore has the importance of science been more widely recognised or so many hopes of future progress and welfare founded upon the scientist.I By way of introduction, therefore, we confine ourselves to pointing outJ that least of all nations can Great Britain afford to neglect whatever benefitsI the scientists can confer upon her.   If we are to maintain our position inI the world and restore and improve our standard of living, we have noI alternative but to strive for that scientific achievement without which our trade will wither, our Colonial Empire will remain undeveloped and our lives and freedom will be at the mercy of a potential aggressor.3. The problem of scientific man-power during the next decade fallsinto two distinct parts. The immediate tasks are to bring back our qualifiedscientists to civil life from the Forces and from the innumerable civilianoccupations in which they have been serving the Forces; to guide them into peace-time occupations according to the needs of reconstruction; andto make good the physical damage which war has inflicted on ourUniversities and research establishments. The longer term problem isto provide sufficient qualified scientists to meet the nation&apos;s requirementsduring the reconstruction period and thereafter. The two problems aredistinct and we deal with them separately.\Definitions4. We should explain here that for our purpose we define &quot; qualified[scientists &apos;&apos; as persons holding degrees in the mathematical, physical,chemical and biological sciences, together with the small number of menand women who, without being university graduates, are members ofrecognised scientific institutions with a membership status that is accepted as the equivalent of a university degree in these subjects.29
Similarly we define the &quot; demand &quot; or &quot;requirement &quot;for scientists asthe number of qualified scientists who are wanted to fill recognised scientificposts. Finally we have for convenience used &quot; leakage &quot; to represent shortlythose people with scientific qualifications who are not at any given timein employment in this country definitely scientific in character, and&quot; wastage &quot; to mean a reduction in the available number from &quot; leakage &quot;and other causes taken together. These last words are used in a purelystatistical sense and carry with them no implication that we consider that allqualified scientists ought to walk narrowly within their own subject. On thecontrary we believe that much benefit would result from the wider diffusion of scientific knowledge and scientific methods throughout all spheres of activity.5. We are satisfied that the demand for scientists over the next fewyears will exceed the possible supply not only as a whole but separately ineach major branch of science. Consequently we have not attempted todeal with the separate needs for each category of scientists. Indeed, toestablish a reliable quantitative assessment of demand and supply for eachscientific subject would involve a formidable statistical enquiry which, ifattempted, would seriously have delayed the presentation of this report.Demand will no doubt exceed supply by different amounts in differentsubjects, but we think .that the determination of the demand for each particular type of scientist may safely be left for later attention.II.-THE IMMEDIATE PEOBLEM(1) DEMOBILISATION6. In considering this question we have, had the benefit of the advice of the Ministry of Labour and National Service and have obtained theviews both of the Board of Trade and of the military authorities. Thequalified scientist is clearly a key man and we are satisfied that applicationsfor his release, whether from the Forces or from civilian war work, are be ingtreated with consideration and expedition by the authorities concerned,Some delay is of course inevitable in tracing a particular man who may beserving in the Army overseas and there are occasions on which themilitary commander on the spot (with whom must rest the ultimate decision whether a serving soldier can be released under Class B) feels it essentialto retain a man on grounds of military necessity. But we are satisfiedthat this power is not being exercised unreasonably.7. Release by nomination, of course, only affects scientists whosepre-war employers are anxious to secure their return or who, by some means, have established contact with their prospective employer. We have examined carefully whether anything can be done to improve the facilitiesfor placing qualified scientists who have secured their release but have noappropriate job waiting for them. In this work the Appointments Depart-ment of the Ministry of Labour and National Service has a vital functionto perform and we consider that, as its value depends fundamentally on thecomprehensiveness of its scope, every possible means should be used toensure that both individuals seeking an appointment and employers seekingscientific staff are aware of the facilities which it offers, and make full useof them. We have considered but have, with some hesitation, rejected thepossibility of inviting the Ministry to make available at all demobilisationcentres a pamphlet giving men coming out of the Forces comprehensiveinformation about existing professional vacancies. Such a pamphlet couldnot in equity be restricted to professional vacancies and any attempt tomake it cover all vacancies would almost certainly break down in this
period of acute and general man-power shortage. In any event we do notbelieve that by this time there is any large number of qualified scientistsitill in the Forces or that there is a significant number who on demobilisa-tion have had to take employment in which their scientific qualifications arenot adequately used.8. We would here remark that the scientist in industry cannot workin isolation and is most fruitfully employed as a member of a balancedteam of scientists, engineers, technical assistants and other ancillary staff.At the moment the shortage of man-power in these latter categories isalmost as acute as the shortage of trained scientists. We appreciate thereasons that have led the Government to restrict the number of Class b releases to a comparatively small proportion of those under Class A, butwe would urge the authorities responsible for Class B releases to consider sympathetically any cases in which it can be clearly shown that the workof a scientist is being held up by the lack of a particular experiencedassistant.(2) EMERGENCY ACCOMMODATION9. For many years one of the chief burdens of the reports of theUniversity Grants Committee has been the shortage of buildings. As long ago as 1936 the Committee stated that there was in the Universities a keensense of dissatisfaction with the accommodation which they described. Thewar has led to a serious deterioration in the position and the need of Collegesthat have suffered war damage is now desperate. For example, unlessurgent measures are taken to remedy the situation, it is unlikely thatUniversity College, London, will be able to accommodate as many as 20 percent, of the students who wish to enter it in October 1946. We recommend,therefore, that everything possible should be done by the release of suchuniversity accommodation as is still requisitioned by the Government andby making available suitable emergency accommodation to meet theimmediate needs of the Universities, particularly of those Colleges that have suffered war damage.III. THE LONGER TERM PROBLEM(1) SUPPLY AND DEMAND10. To arrive at our existing capital of qualified scientists we have had made an actuarial calculation based on the ascertained output of qualifiedscientists over a number of years and the recorded death rate for these years. In such a calculation a fundamental factor is the average activelife of a scientist, the length of which can only be estimated after allowingnot only for the easily assessable incidence of retirement on grounds of age and of death but for other forms of leakage from the profession as well. Inthe Civil Service the average professional life is 30 years, and we haveused 30 years in making our calculation. As a result we arrive at a figureof 60,000 as the absolute maximum potential capital of qualified scientistsin 1946.11. But there can be little doubt that the young Civil Servant who hasalready chosen his profession is more likely to remain a Civil Servant thanthe student who has just passed his final examination in science is toremain in definite scientific employment. Moreover, in our calculationssome allowance must be made for graduates who came from overseas and returned home after securing their degrees and also for people who onlystudied science in order to pursue other subjects, notably medicine.[31651] o*
12 We know that there were 45,000 scientists registered on the Ministryof Labour&apos;s Central (Technical and Scientific) Eegister at the end of 1945,,and our existing capital must therefore be somewhere between 45,O0G )and 60,000. The Ministry of Labour inform us that, to the best of their belief, the Eegister covers between 80 per cent, and 85 per cent, of workingscientists, and, in all the circumstances, we have come to the conclusionthat it is unlikely that the nation has at its disposal to-day a force of morethan 55,000 qualified scientists.13. The assessment of future demand is no less problematical. Wehave studied the available results of a number of recent enquiries, among them one carried out by the Industrial Eesearch Committee of theFederation of British Industries on the probable demand for research anddevelopment workers in industry in the post-war years. As a result wehave arrived at a figure of approximately 70,000 as the estimated minimumdemand for scientific workers in this country and in the colonial service in1950. Of this total roughly 30,000 represents teachers in the universities and secondary schools.14. We are conscious that too much reliance cannot be placed on this figure and there is, indeed, reason to believe that it represents an under-estimate (perhaps a serious under-estimate) of the number of scientistswhom the nation could usefully employ once peace-time industry gets into full production and science begins to build upon the many advances that ithas made under the stress of war. We hope, indeed, that this is so, as wehold strongly that there is even now insufficient appreciation of the potentialities of well-directed scientific effort. But for the reasons whichwe set out below, we fear that it will prove to be beyond practical possibilityto add even 15,000 qualified scientists to our existing capital within thenext five years, and we have therefore thought it well that our estimateof future demand should be a cautious one.15. It is only to the Universities that we can look for any substantialrecruitment to the ranks of qualified scientists. The proportion that hascome from other sources in the past is very small indeed and we do not favour any attempt to add a responsibility for producing a substantial number of pure scientists to the existing and prospective burdens of theTechnical Colleges. Generally speaking, the university is an essential stage in a scientist&apos;s education and in any event the Technical Colleges will behard put to it to produce the number of technologists that are required tosupport and apply the work of the scientists.16. Before the war the British Universities were turning out on theaverage some 2,500 scientists each year. The rate of output fell in the late30&apos;s but recovered during the war and the science faculties are nowpractically full. On the assumption that the faculties continued to be fullbut did not expand their output, they would turn out perliaps 12,500scientists during the next five years.17. The Universities have, however, already indicated that they areprepared to expand their output provided that the necessary finance is forthcoming. In May 1945 the University Grants Committee invited allUniversities in Great Britain and the three University Colleges of Exeter,.Nottingham and Southampton to formulate an estimate of the expansion in their student body which, ignoring financial considerations, they wouldcontemplate when they had returned to normal conditions.   The estimates
received by the University Grants Committee in reply to this enquiry show considerable divergencies among the Universities. Oxford and Cambridge,xor instance, did not feel that they could expand their numbers at all abovetheir pre-war level, while the English Civic Universities as a body thoughtthat an expansion of the order of 85 per cent, might be possible within thefirst post-war decade. Taken as a whole, the replies of the Universitiesenvisaged a potential increase in student population during this decade ofapproximately 45 per cent, over the pre-war strength. The figures givenwere not all sub-divided between the various faculties, but it is,probablethat, in view of the more elaborate equipment which it requires, sciencewould not expand quite proportionately to the expansion in arts. Let ussay that it would expand by about 40 per cent.18. If we were to accept this estimate, we should come to theconclusion that, from a pre-war average annual output of 2,500 scientists,the Universities&apos; estimates would yield by 1955 an output increased to 3,500per annum.19. The Universities were not asked to estimate the rate at which theirexpansion could be achieved, but for obvious reasons it is likely that, ifthings were left to run their course, the curve of expansion would rise veryslowly in the first years of the decade. If, however, we can assume thatthe progression from 2,500 to 3,500 scientists per annum were made at a uniform rate and that in each year of the decade the number graduatingwould be 100 more than in the year before, the additional number of qualified scientists in 1950&apos; would amount at most to 1,500.20. Towards the 1950 requirement of 70,000 we have, therefore, on this basis a gross supply of 69,000 scientists. But so far no allowance has beenmade for wastage. Death and retirement will take its toll of our existing capital. We must assume that a proportion of trained scientists will go into other professions and we must also- assume that a proportion of theannual output from the universities will be foreign students. We cannotpretend to have estimated the extent of this wastage accurately. Wastageduring the war years was small but the circumstances were quite exeptional and a return to a more normal rate must be expected. It is not unreasonable to assume that the trained man-power available in 1950* would be less than60,000, perhaps no more than 55,000.21. But a review of demand over five years is an inadequate basis forany recommendations regarding provision for the training of scientists wherethree years is the minimum period of university education, and it is there-fore necessary to have regard to the movement of demand after 1950. Inthe absence of estimates, even of the provisional kind upon which our 1950figures are based, we can only make the broadest assessment of thepossibilities. We do know, however, that in education the effect of the raising of the school-leaving age by one year in 1947, the establishment ofthe County Colleges and the subsequent raising of the school age by a second year will result in a further steep increase in the demand for teachers withscientific qualifications. Between 1950 and 1955 an additional .15,000teachers will be needed, the curve of demand flattening out after the latteryear. In industry we estimate that the exceptional demands caused by theneeds of recoversion will have been determined by 1950 and that thereafterany expansion in demand will reflect mainly the increasing application of science. A steady but not exceptional rise in the employment of scientistsin central and local government service is probable. Taking all the knownfactors into account wre feel justified in assuming that by 1955 the demandfor scientists will be not less than 90,000,    -[31651] c* 2
22. Towards this total demand we can set our present capital and thenew scientists to come from the Universities between 1946 and the endof 1955, less the wastage over those years. On the assumption that the universities expand according to the figures that they returned to theUniversity Grants Committee and, neglecting the effect of conscription,we make an approximate calculation of our new capital as follows:  (a) Present capital ...       ...       ...       ...      55,000(6) Additions to capital   .........      30,000-      85,000For wastage, in the absence of any better figure we may again assume that, in science as in the Civil Service, an average professional life lasts30 years and make an allowance of, say, 3,000 for new science graduateswho do not enter the scientific professions in this country.   Hence:  (c) Reduction of present capital ...       ...       18,000(d) Loss from new capital...       ...       ...        3,000- 21,000leaving us with (e) Net capital at 1955    ......... ...      64,00023. Thus against the 1955 estimated demand of 90,000 we could not expect more than 64,000 under present plans. In the face of these figures,we consider that, if national recovery and our material progress are not tobe dangerously hampered by lack of trained scientific ability, the outputof scientists must be raised very much above the level of the presentUniversity proposals. It is too early to attempt to estimate exactly whatthe output should be once the nation has settled down to peace-time conditions but we are satisfied that the immediate aim should be to double the present output, giving us roughly 5,000 newly qualified scientists perannum at the earliest possible moment.(2) DOUBLING THE OUTPUT OF SCIENTISTS24. An expansion in the output of qualified scientists involves problems that are to a great extent common to all faculties faced with a demand for a substantially increased output of graduates. It is hardly open to doubt that many faculties will find themselves in this position and, as we have no desire that science should receive&apos; exceptionally favourable treatment, wehave, in the following paragraphs, spoken where it seemed to us appropriate,in terms of the development of the Universities as a whole.(i) The Talent Available25. We need to form an estimate of the proportion of the populationthat is inherently fitted to benefit from a university education. We attachvery great importance to this question, as whatever happens, the quality of our university graduates must not be sacrificed to quantity. In few other fields are numbers of so little value compared to quality properly developed.Character, temperament and wider qualities of mind are, of course, as impor-tant as intellectual acuity and the test of fitness for the Universities is notintelligence alone. Moreover, before it enters the University, intelligencemust be trained and the associated personal qualities matured to a standardthat we would not wish to see lowered. (In para. 38 below we deal withthe effect of this factor on the supply of qualified entrants to the Universitiesduring the next few years.)26. We have surveyed the results obtained in recent years en thedistribution of intelligence, as measured by &apos;&apos; intelligence tests,&apos;&apos; among the
whole population and among samples of the members of certain Univer-necessities.(L) We are encouraged to consider these results to be fairly reliable,^specially in view of the wide experience gained during the war in their use by the Services. The following results are especially relevant to out enquiry:  (a) At present rather less than 2 per cent, of the population reaclT the universities. About 5 per cent, of the whole population show, on test,an intelligence as great as the best half of the students, who amount to1 per cent, of the population. We conclude, therefore, that only about one in five of the boys and girls, who have intelligence equal to that ofthe best half of the University students, actually reach the Universities.It cannot be assumed that all of these have the other innate capacitiesnecessary to a university career. It must be allowed, indeed, that manyboys and girls of high intelligence would not desire a university career;yet there is clearly an ample reserve of intelligence in the country toallow both a doubling of the University numbers and at the same time a raising of standards.(6) The investigations also show clearly that the great majority of theintelligent persons, who do not reach the Universities, are ex-pupils ofthe elementary schools. If university education were open to all on thebasis of measured intelligence alone, about 80 per cent, would be expectedto come from those children who started their education in the public elementary school and only 20 per cent, from those whose education hadbeen in independent schools. In fact, at the present time only about40 per cent, of university entrants are ex-pupils of elementary schools,whereas 60 per cent, are from independent schools. Thus, among universityentrants, elementary school pupils are only half those to be expected, andthose from independent schools about three times as many as expected.These figures, rough and incomplete as they are, do make clear thata high proportion of the reserve of potentially able students comes fromfamilies that are unable to afford the cost of higher education. If, therefore,it is not to be lost to the Universities, greatly increased financial assistanceboth at the secondary school and at the university level is essential.27. We conclude, therefore, that there is available in our populationa large reserve of innate intelligence and that, even allowing for the other factors, there are more potential graduates than we could hope to take into our universities by any degree of expansion practicable within thenext ten years. This would still be true if the standard of intelligenceat which the individual is regarded as suitable for a university educationwere materially higher than it is to-day.(ii) Comparison with other countries28. In considering the number of students who ought to proceed to a university, comparisons are often made with other countries. We wouldecho the warning of the University Grants Committee in their quinquennialreport of 1936, and draw attention to the difficulty of ensuring that the institutions taken into account are of comparable status, that the studentsare studying similar subjects at comparable intellectual levels, and thatstatistics  are obtained  for the  same  year in the  countries  compared..(*) The University data consist.of the test of a sample of graduates of ScottishUniversities carried out by Professor Godfrey Thomson and of a sample of Manchesterundergraduates carried out by Dr. Leybourne-White. The Committee are deeplyindebted to Dr. Leybourne-White for her ready and invaluable assistance in makingniese results available and to the Simon Fund for Research at the University ofALanchester for making her research possible.
Nevertheless we agree with the Committee&apos;s conclusion that when liberalallowance for margins of error in the basis of comparison has been made,it did not look as though, in England at any rate, there was an undulylarge provision of facilities for university education, unless, indeed, it beheld that university education was being altogether overdone elsewhere.Judgment here is commonly influenced by accounts of graduate unemploy-ment in Europe in the years following the financial crisis of 1931, but weare not disposed to think of the future in terms of recurrent unemploymentcrises whether of graduates or of workers generally. We attach importancetherefore to the fact that such figures as have come to our notice suggestthat, even if the student population in British Universities were doubled,we should still fall short of a number of European countries and certainlyof the United States of America in the relative provision we have made for higher education.  &apos;(iii) The Relation between Science and other Faculties(a) Engineering and Technology29. In the figures that we have quoted we have made no estimates forthe vitally important studies in engineering and related technologies whichbefore the war accounted for roughly 40 per cent, as many university studentsas the pure science schools. The close relationship between pure science andthe various branches of engineering cannot be over-emphasised, nor the fact,to Which attention has been drawn in reports made both- in this countryand in the United States of America, that, whereas no one can doubt thevalue of our achievement in fundamental science during the war, we werenot always so successful in those applications of science which lie in the field of engineering and technology. We have, therefore, read with interest thereport presented- to the Minister of Education by the Committee under theChairmanship of Lord Eustace Percy which was appointed to consider theneeds of Higher Technological Education in England and Wales and therespective contribution to be made thereto by Universities and technical colleges.30. The Percy Committee, reporting in July 1945, drew a distinctionbetween the functions of &quot;&quot;Universities and Technical Colleges. Industry,they said, must look mainly to the Universities for the training of scientists and mainly to the Technical Colleges for technical assistants and craftsmen.Both Universities and Colleges must share the responsibilities for educatingthe future senior administrators and technically qualified managers ofindustry. We are more particularly concerned here with the need for thosewhom the Percy Committee call engineer-scientists and developmentengineers. There must be a large increase in the number of these highly trained technologists capable of appreciating the latest progress in the research laboratories and applying the results to practical engineering orprocesses in industry. The solution offered by the Percy report is thedevelopment of full-time technological courses of university degree standardat a selected and limited number of Technical Colleges.31. We cordially support this recommendation. Moreover, in view ofthe consideration that we give below to the problem of university expansion,we would also/support Lord Eustace Percy&apos;s opinion, given in a Chairman&apos;note attached to the report of his Committee, that the Government shouldtreat the Colleges of Technology as a group and develop among them some major university institutions. Some, situated in University Cities, might become the Faculties of Technology of the neighbouring University after a period in which standards had been worked out with the University on thebasis of mutual acceptance of each other&apos;s teaching.   Others, geographically
remote from existing Universities, might qualify for independent universitypowers, and it will be seen from paragraph 52 below that we would welcomehe establishment, of new University Colleges of this sort.32. We are glad to observe the great importance which the PercyCommittee attach to the provision of post-graduate research courses as anessential feature of these Colleges and to the facilities for inter-change of advanced research students and staffs between them and the Universities.Indeed, we would welcome any arrangements between existing universities and the selected Technical Colleges which would tend to establish a basisof mutual esteem and to raise the currency of high technological qualifica-tions to full university degree standard.  ,33.   But the measures recommended by the Percy Committee for technical Colleges will not absolve the Universities from their responsibilityfor training a high proportion of the nation&apos;s first-class technologists.   Wethink, indeed, that the Universities should aim, by the provision of courses in the engineering sciences and full facilities for post-graduate research, to attract into technology a greatly increased number of students of outstanding-ability.   Certainly the expansion in the numbers of technological students atI  the Universities should not be less than that which we recommend in theI  case of pure science.   In the course of their expansion and development webelieve that both the Universities and the selected Colleges will have toprovide training for such qualifications as chemical engineer and engineer-\  physicist, in addition to such existing schools eLs engineering and mechanicali  sciences.34. Finally, in order to provide technologists of the highest possiblequality, we think that urgent consideration should be given to the develop-ment of two or three Institutes of Technology, preferably in UniversityCities, whose aim should be to provide graduate and post-graduate courses and to conduct research of a standard at least equal to that demanded of candidates for doctorate degrees in the Universities.I . .(b) The Humanities35. It is not within our province to consider the future &quot;demand forgraduates in the humanities, languages and the fine arts and we are not qualified to do so. We have been informed, however, that here too thereexists a need for a very substantial increase in the available supply of trained ability, and if this should prove to be the case it would be a matterof great satisfaction to us. For we attach very great importance to the atmosphere of an association of men and women which takes all knowledgeas its province and in which all branches of learning flourish in harmony.Such an atmosphere has a great part to play in completing any student&apos;seducation and preventing him from becoming a narrow and cloisteredspecialist. In particular would we deprecate any attempt to meet theincreased demand for scientists and technologists at the expense of studentsof other subjects (even if, as is unlikely, the Universities could be persuaded to make such an attempt) or to give any preference to science studentsover arts students in such matters as military service.(iv) The Capacity of the Universities to Expand(a) The Need for Money36. The great bulk of the money required for university developmentmust come from the Exchequer and we are satisfied that, more than anyother single factor, the Universities&apos; response to any call for expansion will depend upon a wise and generous financial policy towards them on the part
Nevertheless we agree with the Committee&apos;s conclusion that when liberalallowance for margins of error in the basis of comparison has been made it did not look as though, in England at any rate, there was an unduly ]large provision of facilities for university education, unless, indeed, it he jheld that university education was being altogether overdone elsewhere.Judgment here is commonly influenced by accounts of graduate unemploy.ment in Europe in the years following the financial crisis of 1931, but we Iare not disposed to think of the future in terms of recurrent unemploymentcrises whether of graduates or of workers generally.   We attach importancetherefore to the fact that such figures as have come to our notice suggestthat, even if the student population in British Universities were doubled,we should still fall short of a number of European countries and certainly jof the. United States of America m the relative provision we have made for 1higher education.  &apos;(iii) The Relation between Science and other Faculties. (a) Engineering and Technology29. In the figures that we have quoted we have made no estimates forthe vitally important studies in engineering and related technologies whichbefore the war accounted for roughly 40 per cent, as many university studentsas the pure science schools. The close relationship between pure science andthe various branches of engineering cannot be over-emphasised, nor the fact,to which attention has been drawn in reports made both- in this countryand in the United States of America, that, whereas no one can doubt thevalue of our achievement in fundamental science during the war, we werenot always so successful in those applications of science which lie in the field of engineering and technology. We have, therefore, read with interest thereport presented- to the Minister of Education by the Committee under theChairmanship of Lord Eustace Percy which was appointed to consider theneeds of Higher Technological Education in England and Wales and therespective contribution to be made thereto by Universities and technical colleges.30.   The Percy Committee, reporting in July 1945, drew a distinction Ibetween the functions of Universities and Technical Colleges.   Industry, they   said, must look mainly to the Universities for the training of scientists 1and mainly to the Technical Colleges for technical assistants and craftsmen. 1Both Universities and Colleges must share the responsibilities for educating Ithe  future senior administrators and  technically  qualified  managers of industry.   We are more particularly concerned here with the need for those Iwhom  the  Percy   Committee   call  engineer-scientists   and   development Iengineers.   There must be a large increase in the number of these highly Itrained technologists capable of appreciating the latest progress in the&apos;research laboratories and applying the results to practical engineering orprocesses in industry.    The solution offered by the Percy report is thedevelopment of full-time technological courses of university degree standard jat a selected and limited number of Technical Colleges.31. We cordially support this recommendation. Moreover, in view ofthe consideration that we give below to the problem of university expansion, 1we would also support Lord Eustace Percy &apos;s opinion, given in a Chairman&apos;note attached to the report of his Committee, that the Government shouldtreat the Colleges of Technology as a group and develop among them some major university institutions. Some, situated in University Cities, might 1become the Faculties of Technology of the neighbouring University after a period in which standards had been worked out with the University on thebasis of mutual acceptance of each other&apos;s teaching.   Others, geographically I
remote from existing Universities, might qualify for independent universityowers, and it will be seen from paragraph 52 below that we would welcomehe establishment of new University Colleges of this sort.32. We are glad to observe the great importance which the PercyCommittee attach to the provision of post-graduate research courses as anessential feature of these Colleges and to the facilities for inter-change of advanced research students and staffs between them and the Universities.Indeed, we would welcome any arrangements between existing universities and the selected Technical Colleges which would tend to establish a basisof mutual esteem and to raise the currency of high technological qualifica-tions to full university degree standard.  ,33. But the measures recommended by the Percy Committee for technical Colleges will not absolve the Universities from their responsibilityfor training a high proportion of the nation&apos;s first-class technologists. Wethink, indeed, that the Universities should aim, by the provision of courses in the engineering sciences and full facilities for post-graduate research, to attract into technology a greatly increased number of students of outstanding-ability. Certainly the expansion in the numbers of technological students atthe Universities should not be less than that which we recommend in thecase of pure science. In the course of their expansion and development webelieve that both the Universities and the selected Colleges will have toprovide training for such qualifications as chemical engineer and engineer-physicist, in addition to such existing schools as engineering and mechanicalsciences.34. Finally, in order to provide technologists of the highest possiblequality, we think that urgent consideration should be given to the develop -ment of two or three Institutes of Technology, preferably in UniversityCities, whose aim should be to provide graduate and post-graduate courses and to conduct research of a standard at least equal to that demanded of candidates for doctorate degrees in the Universities.(b) The Humanities35. It is not within our province to consider the future &quot;demand forgraduates in the humanities, languages and the fine arts and we are not qualified to do so. We have been informed, however, that here too thereexists a need for a very substantial increase in the available supply of trained ability, and if this should prove to be the case it would be a matterof great satisfaction to us. For we attach very great importance to the atmosphere of an association of men and women which takes all knowledgeas its province and in which all branches of learning flourish in harmony.Such an atmosphere has a great part to play in completing any student&apos;seducation and preventing him from becoming a narrow and cloisteredspecialist. In particular would we deprecate any attempt to meet theincreased demand for scientists and technologists at the expense of studentsof other subjects (even if, as is unlikely, the Universities could be persuaded to make such an attempt) or to give any preference to science studentsover arts students in such matters as military service.(iv) The Capacity of the Universities, to Expand(a) The Need for Money36. The great bulk of the money required for university developmentmust come from the Exchequer and we are satisfied that, more than anyother single factor, the Universities&apos; response to any call for expansion will depend, upon a wise and generous financial policy towards them on the part
of the Government. We have been most forcibly impressed, by the effectof monetary uncertainties upon the development of our Universities. their whole atmosphere is impregnated by a conception of financial stringencycaused not only by current lack of funds but by the fear that at some future date their income from benefactors, and mainly of course from the Exchequermay suddenly diminish, leaving their governing bodies without funds tomeet their inescapable commitments. In 1938, British Universities receivedabout  3 millions in grants from the Exchequer and from local authorities.Too much stress cannot be laid on the comparison, but it is pertinent to pointout that in the same year American Universities, serving a population some three times as large, received from public funds no less than  32 millions.We were glad to note that for the financial year 1946-47 the University grantshave been increased from  5-65 millions to  9-45 millions and that in announcing this increase in the House of Commons on the 22nd February,1946, the Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in order to encourageUniversities to plan future developments over a term of years, he had told the University Grants Committee that he should be prepared, if good causewere shown, to ask Parliament to vote even larger capital sums. We hopethat it will be possible for the Government to persuade the Universities thatin future they will be able to rely upon adequate and continuing assistancefrom the Exchequer towards any project for which, in the Chancellors words,good cause is shown.(b) Other Impediments to Expansion37. We have inquired into the reasons why the Universities have not found it possible to budget for an expansion during the next decade greaterthan that shown in their returns to the University Grants Committee. these reasons and our comments upon them may be briefly summarised asfollows :  The Supply of Students38. While it is agreed that a large proportion of the population isinherently capable of benefiting from a university education, some Universityauthorities doubt whether during the next ten years a sufficient proportionof this talent will have been trained to the point at which it can enter theUniversity without causing a serious deterioration in the Universities&apos;intellectual standards.This fear is understandable. The recent Education Acts will not resultimmediately in a substantial increase in the number of young people com-completing their secondary education and it might be argued that the rather higher proportion of weaker students to be found in Scottish Universitiesbefore the war reflected the fact that, under pre-1944 conditions, Scotlandwith her much larger proportionate university population was alreadybeginning to &quot; scrape the pot &quot; for suitable material. We do not accept thisexplanation of the situation in Scotland before the war but even if we didit must be remembered that England has a long way to go before heruniversity population is proportionately equal to Scotland^. Moreover, forthe next two or three years the Universities are likely to be besieged byprospective students returning from the forces; a very considerable propor-tion of fully-trained young persons is still being lost to the Universitiesthrough a variety of reasons, mainly economic, and the new Education Actswill not take long to show their effects. While, therefore, it is conceivable that somewhere about 1949 there might be some difficulty in filling a greatlyincreased number of University places, we think this is unlikely. We are quite satisfied that, if such a dearth should occur, it would be of brief duration,provided always that sufficient financial assistance is forthcoming to ensure
that able students are not prevented from going to the University by lackof means.%BuiUings39. The available University buildings are inadequate even to accom-accommodate properly the existing student population. The shortage of building labour and materials prevents the Universities from embarking immediately on any substantial building programmes. The position is further complicatedfor Universities like Glasgow and Liverpool which are in the middle of large towns and can, therefore, only build new accommodation near their mainsites by destroying houses and other buildings.We recognise the inadequacy of existing university buildings and theimportance in present circumstances of not adopting any means of remedyingit that would accentuate the housing shortage. But even on the mostmaterial grounds, universities are as essential to the nation&apos;s prosperity asfactories, and their claims upon building resources ought to receive the samepriority. Some Universities are already finding it possible to increase theiraccommodation by running up one-storey buildings of light factory type which serve admirably for laboratories or lecture rooms or even hostels and whose construction is economical of labour. The possibility of usingneighbouring country houses or vacated military camps as temporary annexesto Universities might be explored with advantage and as the building positionimproves, we would hope that, within two or at most three years, the universities-ties will be able to embark on a substantial programme of permanent building.Meanwhile, in the present educational emergency much could be done to increase the size of the student body, if staffs and students were preparedto accept a measure of temporary inconvenience. In some cases an increase could, we think,&apos; be achieved by extending the shift system so as to make full use of those periods during which lecture rooms and laboratories are notat present in use.Staff40. The Universities are experiencing an acute shortage of - suitableteachers. In some sciences such as physics and chemistry, in which theoutput of graduates has continued at a high rate during the war, there are probably sufficient qualified men available to teach increased numbers ofS students, but in other sciences (and incidentally in the arts faculties) theI University authorities may feel that it is premature to expand the studentI body until more teachers have been trained.We are not convinced that, if the Universities started a vigorous recruitingI campaign, an adequate supply of science teachers of sufficient calibre would not be forthcoming. From the evidence that we have heard, we believeI that in scientific subjects there is considerable first class material available- and that the reason why it is not, generally speaking, flowing towards theI Universities is partly the attraction offered by the Government&apos;s newI Scientific Service but also, ignorance of the university careers that are open1 to scientists of good academic attainments and, in some instances, inadequateI salaries offered by the Universities.41.   In this connection we make the following recommendations:  (a) The Universities should be invited to make a comprehensive survey of their staff requirements in the light of the expansion to be aimedIat.(p) All university vacancies should be notified as a matter of routineto the Appointments Department of the Ministry of Labour and national Service which in this respect can fulfil a particularly
valuable function in making the vacancies known to prospectiveapplicants.(c) The Universities should consider whether it would not be possiblt]for an increased proportion of their staff to be taken direct intothe lecturer grade. Before the war the majority of unversity teachers entered their profession at about the age of 24 and were quite content to start as assistant lecturers. Many of the applicants for university posts now available, however, are between28 and 30, and a large number of them are married men withfamilies. Moreover, there are many whose pay and allowanceduring their period of military service were worth upwards of 1,000 per annum.42. We would emphasise, however, that we are opposed to any attemptto increase the student population by adding substantial additional teachingresponsibility to the individual members of a faculty. Generally speaking,indeed, the load on the teachers of science is already too great and theiropportunity for research far too small. In our opinion it is essential thatthe average teacher should have more and not less opportunity for his ownresearch than he has had in the past. As an emergency measure it may insome cases be. justifiable to increase the amount of teaching done by an individual in order to obtain the maximum number of new graduates as soonas possible, but we hope that such instances will be few. Indeed, as will beseen from paragraph 55 below, we consider that any increase in the studentbody should be accompanied by a somewhat greater proportionate increasein the number of teachers. Even on this basis, however, we believe that inthe science faculties, at least, a vigorous drive for new teachers would meet with a very considerable measure of success.Colonial and Overseas Students43. Looking at the problem from the narrow national point of view, itmust be remembered that whereas the British Universities rightly regard it as a duty to take a proportion of students from the Commonwealth andfrom foreign countries, in present circumstances every student enrolled from overseas excludes a student from the United Kingdom. There is, moreover,strong evidence that foreign students are more anxious than ever before tocome to this country to obtain their degrees and for post-graduate study,and the Foreign Office are gravely concerned about the proportion of applications which have to be refused.We believe that the national interest demands that we should acceptinto our Universities as many as possible of these overseas students, butwe cannot accept that they must necessarily be accommodated at the expenseof our own. The obvious solution is to enlarge the Universities until theycan take all students who wish to enter them and are capable of profitingfrom the education they provide.44.   To sum up, while there are formidable obstacles to the expansionof the Universities in the immediate future, we do not think that, once the urgency and the importance of the nation &apos;s need for more graduates is .widely appreciated, and provided that the Universities&apos; financial misgivingscan be removed, they need necessarily prove insuperable.(c) The Problems of Individual Universities45. While it is possible to make certain wide generalisations that are 1broadly applicable to British Universities as a whole, any effective :programme of expansion must take account of the individual problems Ifacing each separate University.   The following table shows how differently
(he various groups. of Universities responded to the idea of expansionwhen it was put to them by the University Grants Committee.Oxford and Cambridge ...London    ..:      ...English Civic UniversitiesUniversity of WalesScottish Universities	Maximum		No. of		Students	No. of	in first	Per-Students	post-war	centage1938-39.	Decade.	Increase.11,000	11,000	 7,500(2)	11,500(2)	5312,700	23,700	862,800	4,200	. 509,500	. 12,600	3243,500	63,000	45We have not attempted to examine in detail the particular needs ofI individual Universities, but we would like to record the following provisionalI views on this question for the consideration of whatever body becomesI responsible for the expansion programme.I Oxjord and Cambridge46. We regret that neither of the ancient Universities has found itj possible to suggest any permanent expansion in its student body. WeI realise that any expansion would have to be of modest proportions if ita was not to affect the character of Oxford and Cambridge, and we do notI wish to suggest any measure which would destroy the residential characterI which is so essential to their educational system. Nevertheless, we feelI that Oxford and Cambridge should regard it as a duty to make someI contribution towards meeting the nation&apos;s enlarged requirements and weIthink that the University authorities might- be asked to give earlyI reconsideration to the possibility of accepting a somewhat larger student1 body. It might, for instance, be possible to achieve this end by theI enlargement of some of the smaller of the existing Colleges and thei foundation of one or more new Colleges.9 London: 47. The problem here must be considered in terms of the circumstancesiof each separate College and the appropriate rates of expansion might beIvery different in different cases. If, however, there were any substantialiexpansion in the numbers enrolled in the University as a whole, serious^administrative difficulties might arise that could only be solved by a policyjof decentralisation. Possibilities that have been suggested to us are the[upgrading of those of the constituent Colleges, viz., University and King&apos;s,f which already embrace many faculties, to major University status; thelassociation of groups of colleges such as those at South Kensington withsinew foundations in complementary faculties and residential facilities to[form ,a complete University institution; the expansion of University/facilities in East and South London; and the separation of the external^examining function from the internal teaching and research function. These[matters are outside our competence, but clearly there is no reason why[there should only be one University in London or why an area with a population of over 8,000.000 people should only have accommodation for   ess than 20,000 students within its boundaries.I (2) Excludes Medical schools and the Institute of Education totalling some 6,500[students in 1938-39.
The English Civic Universities and the University of Wales48. It will be seen from paragraph 45 above that the English Civic.Universities are themselves prepared, if adequate finance is forthcomingto increase their student body by no less than 86 per cent. We considerthat in some instances even this is an appreciable under-estimate of what could be done. We believe, for example, that the Sheffield region couldultimately support a University considerably larger than the 1,500 students who represent its expansion programme (although even this involvesdoubling the pre-war size of the University) and we believe that Universitieslike Liverpool and Leeds ought to aim at a student body of not lessthan 4,000.49. But if the Civic Universities are to expand they must be assured of an adequate nucleus of real ability round which to build. Oxford,Cambridge and London have in the past exercised a quite disproportionateattraction on talented students.50. This drawing power results from the high value that is placed uponthe degrees of the older Universities and from the greater amenities and, tosome people, from the greater social distinction that they offer to their members. It is reinforced by a scholarship system that gives students wholeave home for their university education more money than those whoattend their local Civic Universities, thus conferring at once a measure offinancial independence and freedom to enter fully into university life uponthe former but not upon the latter.We believe that the present system, which tends to concentrate the major proportion of State and county scholars into three Universities, isfundamentally bad not only for the regional Universities, whose wholeintellectual level suffers from the lack of a sufficient number of outstandingstudents, but also for the three Universities themselves. We cannot believethat either Oxford or Cambridge would wish to become almost entirelya &quot; scholarship University &quot; or would benefit from such a development.51. There are few things more important than to find a solution to this problem. Clearly it will not be easy. The attractive power of the CivicUniversities must be raised by their own effort. Among the needs of first importance are halls of residence and greater facilities for corporate lifegenerally; indeed, it is scarcely possible to exaggerate the importance ofthese. The vigour of their teaching and the excellence of their researchwill have its effect, but the efforts of the Universities themselves must be supported by the State and consequently we recommend that the educational authorities should consider urgently means by which scholarsmight be distributed more equitably. Possible schemes which have beensuggested to us are the allocation of an annual quota of State and countyscholars to each University and the making of special grants to individualUniversities for the endowment of scholarships and research scholarships.Special financial provision might also have to be made to enable the CivicUniversities to obtain their share of the best teaching talent.The English University Colleges52. When all possible expansion has been achieved by the Universitiesthere will still remain a large gap to be filled. The existing UniversityColleges of Nottingham, Southampton, Exeter, Hull and Leicester oughtto be able to make a substantial contribution towards filling it. ahof them are well situated to serve as university centres and each of themought we think to aim at earning full university status at the earliest possible date. Moreover, there are several large centres of population in which newUniversity Colleges could profitably be established.
The Scottish Universitiesf&apos; 53. Here the possibility of expansion is considerably less, as the propor-tion of the total population which already receives a university education ismuch larger than that in England and Wales. We cannot, however, believethat even in Scotland we have yet approached the limit of what is eitherpossible or desirable in the national interest. ---New University Institutions54. Finally we think that, while giving all possible facilities to theexisting Universities and University Colleges to expand themselves, early consideration should be given to the foundation of at least one new University.We recognise that such a foundation must have time to develop and that,taking into account the difficulty of providing accommodation, its contributionto the need for graduates would probably be small for some years after itsbirth. But there is nothing sacrosanct about the present number of universities in the Kingdom and we are attracted by the conception of bringing into existence at least one University which would give to the presentgeneration the opportunity of leaving to posterity a monument of its culture.Moreover, there is some reason to believe that a number of able teachersfrom the existing Universities would welcome the opportunity of re-enactingin the twentieth century the exodus which is said to have led to the founda-tion of Peterhouse in the thirteenth. We also believe that such a proposal would receive warm support from informed opinion and the general bodyof the public.(3) THE QUALITY OF SCIENCE TEACHING55. So far we have concerned ourselves with the need to raise the numberof qualified scientists. Quality is, however, at.least as essential as quantity and the quality of a scientific training depends largely on the standard of the research work upon which it is based. Strong research schools are needed inall university science departments not only for the intrinsic value of theresearches and their value to the teachers themselves but also for training the able students in methods of research. Three years of undergraduate studydo not make a trained scientist; an additional two or three years&apos; research isessential for a considerable proportion of science graduates. Hence we areof the opinion that the proper training of a first-rate research scientist, andalso of the higher grades of teacher, cannot be accomplished in much lessthan the five or six years already accepted as necessary for the training ofa doctor. We hold strongly, moreover, that as an essential part of anybalanced expansion in the science faculties, there should be not only an expansion in the number of teachers somewhat larger proportionately thanthe expansion of the number of students, but an expansion in research schools for training purposes apart from the needs of the students, and an increasein the financial grants that are made specifically towards research byUniversity staffs.(4) THE EFFECT OF OUR PROPOSALS(i) The Supply of Graduates during the next ten years56. It will be seen from paragraphs 20 and 23 above that, even on themost optimistic view of present plans, we are likely to be several thousandscientists short of our requirement in 1950 and 1955. In considering whateffect the acceptance of our recommendation, that the output of scientificgraduates should be doubled at the earliest possible opportunity, may haveupon this shortage, it is necessary to take into account the following factors :  (a) It takes at least three years to qualify for a university degree and a proportion of students must do a period of post-graduate work before
they can be considered properly qualified.   Even, therefore, ifit were possible to double the intake of the Universities i?tOctober 1946 there would be no substantial rise in the output ojqualified graduates until 1949 at the earliest.(6) It is too much to hope that the Universities will in fact be able to double their intake in 1946. There will be more than enoughapplicants for places but we very much doubt whether, evenassuming that teachers are available, the Universities will be ableto carry through such a formidable task of reorganisation in the fewmonths available before the opening of the academic year. More-. over, while much can be done to solve the accommodation problemsby recourse to temporary expedients, even the flimsiest buildingtakes time to construct and the most suitable existing building,time to convert for university purposes.(c) As far as recruitment to the Universities in the years succeeding1946 is concerned we have set out above our reasons for thinking that this is the least serious of the problems which must be faced. (,s) We have, moreover, brought to. the attention of theGovernment our view that, if the intellectual standard of graduates is not to suffer, it is desirable that science .students(&quot;)should be allowed, if they wish and if there is room for them, tocomplete their full course and obtain their degrees before doing their period of military service. But military service must be done and, assuming that it lasts for a period of two years, it will mean that at any given time the equivalent of two years&apos; output of graduates will be soldiers and not scientists.57. If we take these factors into account, the only possible conclusion is that whatever is done to increase the output of science graduates, thenation will be seriously short of scientists in 1950 and that without heroicefforts it is unlikely that supply will have finally overtaken demand evenfive years later.(ii) The Assessment of Priorities58. This conclusion means that if we are to make the best use of ourlimited supply of scientists, some system of priorities must be established.We recommend that in the immediate period of reconstruction the order ofpreference should be :  1st. Teaching and Fundamental Research.2nd. Civil Science, both Government and Industrial.3rd. Defence Science.59.   We. have the following comments on this order of priority: -(a) Clearly the quickest way to remedy the shortage of scientists is toensure that a sufficient number of qualified teachers is available and the sooner this can be done, the sooner the output of newgraduates will reach the desired level.(3) In the academic year, 1946-47 in fact, the Universities may be so full of menreturned from the Forces, that relatively few new entrants direct from school will find places. If this occurs, we consider that any boy who has to wait one or twoyears to enter a University should be permitted if he wishes to start his militaryservice directly on leaving school, rather than, as we recommend in general, after his university course.(4) This recommendation was confined to science students because they are theonly students about whom we are qualified to speak. We must repeat, however,that we do not wish to claim any preferential treatment for the scientist.
(p) Scientific advance must proceed simultaneously both in the basicand applied fields. During the war basic research had, perforce,to be severely limited, and its rapid rebuilding must be on thehighest priority. Since we must look to the Universities for the -major part of our basic science, a generous and immediateendowment of the research schools of the Universities in equip-ment, technical staff and general research facilities is essential.(c) We have given defence research the lowest place in our order ofpreference, partly because of the great strides which it made underthe impact, of war and partly because the immediate needs ofother branches of science seem clearly more pressing. But it mustbe remembered that we are in a period of revolution in the technique of armaments that will have the profoundest effect upon future strategy and tactics. Consequently, the defence services must maintain not only a nucleus of able scientists butalso adequate development establishments if we are not to fallbehind in that technical equipment upon which our place amongthe nations may depend.(d) The order of priority set out in paragraph 58 applies only to theperiod of reconstruction. It should be the business of the Govern-ment to keep it constantly under review so as to ensure that itis speedily revised should circumstances demand.60. The means by which any system of man-power priorities is to be implemented in peacetime must be largely financial. It is true that, withinthe Government service, arrangements can be made to direct scientists to whatever work is currently of the greatest importance. But there will becompetition between industry and universities and within industry itself,and the distribution of available scientific man-power will depend on theprospects which each competitor can hold out to the individual scientist.We do not suggest that, generally speaking, the Universities should attemptto pay their scientific workers salaries similar, to those offered in industry,because to a large number of scientists, academic life has an appeal whichcannot be assessed in terms of money. But university salary scales and theinducements which an academic career can offer must be considered with the competing attractions of industry in mind. Generally speaking, far too much of a Professor&apos;s time is taken up in dealing with petty administrativequestions and both the efficiency of departmental administration and the amenities of professional life could be greatly improved if scientists couldbe provided with the secretarial assistance and office machinery that theaverage business man regards as essential.(hi) The Position after 195561. We are faced by the apparent dilemma that if the supply of scientists is to catch up the demand within, saj , the next 15 years, theoutput of scientific graduates must be increased to not less than 5,000 perannum, but that if such an output continues indefinitely there may be a danger of substantial overproduction unless the demand continues toincrease rapidly.62. If the active life of the average scientist should prove to be in theneighbourhood of 30 years, an output of 5,000 science graduates per annumpostulates an ultimate total force of 150,000, or over one and a half times the force which we consider will be required in ,1955. The Universities may therefore have misgivings about attempting to provide accommodation andteaching staff sufficient to cater for 5,000 science graduates per annum. Wethink, however, that the dilemma is more apparent than real.   In the first
place although the demand for scientists may not reach 150,000 for marryyears to come, there is reason to expect that for an indefinite period it wil1continue to expand for, apart from the increasing application of the physica.and chemical sciences not only to research, but also to production in industry, there is a wide and expanding field for the application of thebiological sciences.Secondly, by 1955 a large proportion of the accommodation at present used by Universities will be fit only for demolition and need not be rebuilt ifthe demand for it has ceased to exist.Finally, we hope and believe that scientific training will come to be in greater demand as a foundation of a general education. Hence we do notbelieve that, even if the demand for recruits to the scientific professionsshould at some future date, fall below the supply, it is likely that a reductionin the student body in science faculties would take place.(5) THE IMPLEMENTATION OF OUR PROPOSALS63. If it be accepted that we must. double our output of scientificgraduates, the magnitude of the task to be faced must be recognised. Thefollowing summary of the problems involved is by no means exhaustive:-(a) Each University. and University College in the Kingdom must beinvited to consider its position and form an assessment of the way in which it can. best contribute to the expansion demanded.(6) The needs of individual sciences must be assessed and related to theexisting capacity of the Universities, to the demands of each other and to their associated technological services.(c) It is probably not possible to assess statistically the demand forgraduates in the humanities and other branches of learning. Butthe expansion of the*se faculties cannot be left entirely to trial anderror if there is to be no danger of a growing &quot; lack of balance&quot;in the Universities.(a1) A university building programme will have to be drawn up that shallensure that the accommodation problem is solved as quickly aspossible and with the minimum interference with the demands of housing, school education and industry upon the available building resources.(e) Every assistance must be given to the Universities in finding andattaching to themselves as teachers, sufficient men and women of proper calibre.(/) Arrangements need to be made to ensure an adequate supply of thebest students from the schools. The magnitude of the problem is great but it must be faced. If the best available talent is&apos; to reach the Universities, then financial assistance must be made availableto the great majority of university students. With the increase inresidential facilities in the Civic Universities the need will be allthe greater.(g) The many problems raised by the continuance of conscription mustbe tackled.(h) The parallel needs of the special Technical Colleges must be met and a regional and national system developed for knitting together the Schools, the Technical Colleges, the Higher TechnicalInstitutes, the Universities and Industry.(i) Finally, this heavy programme will have to be financed very largely atthe expense of the Exchequer. The cost will be large in relation toprevious university expenditure, although not in relation to other government educational or research expenditure.   It clearly must
be borne largely by the Exchequer, although we hope that privatebenefactors, to whom the Universities have been so heavilyindebted in the past, will continue to show their generositytowards the foundations in which they are personally interested and will not be led to think that the value of their gifts wrll be diminished or that the need for them has gone.64. We must here record that we are unanimously opposed to anyinfringement of the cherished independence of the Universities, even if itcould be justified on the ground that it would facilitate the execution ofthe expansion programme.65. We do not, however, believe that the maintenance of the universities&apos; independence is in any way incompatible with the extensionand improvement of the machinery for adjusting their policy to the needsof the country. Such a step well in any case become inevitable, if the tax-payer assumes the main financial burden of the expansion programme,and we have no reason for believing that the Universities themselves wouldnot welcome it. Eor, although the informal Committee of Vice-Chancellorshas served as a valuable organ for co-ordinating and formulating Universitypolicy, it has no permanent secretariat attached to it and there is some reason to believe that the Universities have found their developmentseriously handicapped by the lack of such material as the detailed and comprehensive statistics which the Government would have to compile and keep up to date to serve as the foundation of the expansion programme,66. The chosen instrument for the maintenance of relations betweenthe Government and the Universities in the past has been the university grants Committee and wTe do not think that the expansion programme which we envisage calls for the replacement of that Committee by any neworgan of Government. The Committee came into existence in 1919 undera Treasury Minute which appointed it &apos;&apos; To enquire into the financial needs of University Education in theUnited. Kingdom(3) and to advise the Government as to the applicationof any grants that may be made by Parliament towards meeting them.&quot;Its growing importance can be judged from the fact that the grants forwhich it was responsible rose from  1 million in 1919-20 to  2-25 millions in1986 and have in the current financial year increased to over  9 millions.We have no criticism to make of the admirable work which the university grants Committee has done and is doing. Indeed, we think that the mutual confidence which rightly exists to-day between the Committee and the universities will very greatly facilitate the execution of the expansion programme. But the State has perhaps been over-concerned lest thereshould be even a suggestion of interference with the independence of the universities and, from the terms of, reference quoted above, it is clear thatthe University Grants Committee was originally intended to be a somewhatpassive body whose main function was to criticise proposals put forward by the Universities and which was not itself expected to make any attemptto suggest possible developments involving expenditure to Universityauthorities. We gladly recognise that the Committee has.not in fact beencontent to accept so passive a role but we think that circumstances demand that it should increasingly concern itself with positive University policy. Itmay be desirable for this purpose to revise its terms of reference and strengthen its machinery.(a) Si nee the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, the University Grants Committeelias restricted its activities to Universities in Great Britain.L31651J D*
IY. SUMMARY OF CONCLUSIONS67.   The Immediate ProblemDEMOBILISATION(1) We have enquired into the procedure for expediting the return of scientists to civil life; we believe that it is adequate to presentneeds and we have no improvements to recommend.   (Paras. 6-7.)(2) The fullest possible use should be made of the facilities offered bythe Appointments Department of the Ministry of Labour.(Para. 7.)(3) Applications for the release of experienced assistants under Class Bshould be considered sympathetically where it can be shownthat if release is not granted the work of a scientist will be held up.   (Para. 8.)EMERGENCY ACCOMMODATION(4) Everything possible should be done to meet the immediate needsof Universities for accommodation, particularly the needs of those that have suffered war damage.   (Para. 9.)The Longer Term ProblemSUPPLY AND DEALAND(5) Our estimate of the position in 1950 and 1955 may be summarisedas follows:  Minimum requirement  of  Qualified . 1955Scientists    ......      ......      .   70,000 90,000Maximum number likely to beavailable if expansion in the out-put of graduates is limited to that envisaged in the returns furnished by the Universities to the Univer-sity Grants Committee   ...... 60,000 64,000Deficit............. 10,000 26,000(Paras. 10-22.)(6) It is essential therefore that the output of scientific graduates shouldbe increased very much above the level of expansion at presentenvisaged by the Universities; the immediate aim should i&quot;to double the present output giving us approximately 5,000 nescientists every year, at the earliest possible moment.   (Para. 23beDOUBLING THE OUTPUT OF SCIENTISTSTHE TALENT AVAILABLE(7) There &apos; is available in the population a large reserve of innateintelligence. Its size is such that, while recognising the needfor other qualities also, we assume that there is available more suitable material than we could hope to take into our Universitiesby any degree of expansion practicable within the next ten years.But financial assistance must be forthcoming on a larger scaleif much of the available talent is not to be lost to the Universities.(Paras. 25-27.)
COMPARISON WITH OTHER COUNTRIES-   (8) Even if the total student population in British Universities weredoubled,  this  country would still fall short  of  a number  ofEuropean countries and the United States of America in the-relative provision which it makes for higher education.   (Para. 28.)TECHNOLOGICAL EDUCATION(9) (a) We support the recommendation of the Percy Committee on higher Technological Education that there should be developedat a selected and limited number of Technical Colleges, full-timetechnological courses of University degree standard. (Paras.29-30.)(b) The status of these higher technological colleges and the bondsbetween them and the existing Universities (including facilitiesfor post-graduate research) should be strengthened wherever possible so as to raise the currency of technological qualifications.(Para. 32.)(c) The increased facilities to be offered by Technical Colleges does notrelieve the Universities from their responsibility for training ahigh proportion of the nation&apos;s first-class technologists; theexpansion in the output of graduates should -be not lessproportionately in technology than in pure science.    (Para. 33.)(d) Urgent consideration should be given to the development, preferably in University Cities, of a few Institutes of Technology designedto maintain the highest possible standards of study and research.(Para. 34.)THE HUMANITIES(10) We hope to see a substantial expansion in the number of studentsstudying the humanities; the humanities should not be sacrificedto the need for an increased output of scientists and technologists.(Para. 35.)THE CAPACITY OF THE UNIVERSITIES TO EXPANDFinance(11) It is of great importance that the Universities should be assured thatin future they will be able to rely on adequate and continuingassistance from the Exchequer towards any project for which good cause is shown. &apos; (Para. 36.)Students of Requisite Standard(12) We are reasonably sure that even in the next few years there will beno lack of trained students to fill the expanding universities.(Para. 38.)Accommodation(13) We make a number of proposals which might help to mitigate theuniversity accommodation problem (para. 39); we attach greatimportance to the provision of halls of residence and other facilitiesfor corporate life in the Civic Universities.    (Para. 51.)
Teachers I(14) In science at least there is ground for believing that a vigorous drive&quot;for new university teachers would meet with a very considerable measure of success; we make certain detailed recommendations regarding the steps which the Universities might take to secureadditional teachers.   (Paras. 40-41.)(15) To improve teaching efficiency, and to give individual teachersadequate time for their own research, any expansion in the numberof students should be accompanied by a proportionately largerexpansion in the number of teachers.   (Para. 42.)Overseas Students(16) Everything possible should be done to meet the demand of studentsfrom the Commonwealth and from foreign countries for places inBritish Universities and to increase the size of the Universities toenable these students to be accepted without excluding studentsfrom this country.   (Para. 43.)THE PROBLEMS OF THE INDIVIDUAL UNIVERSITIESOxford and Cambridge(17) The two ancient Universities should regard it as a duty to make a contribution towards meeting the nation&apos;s enlarged requirements forgraduates; this might be possible by the enlargement of some of thesmaller of the existing colleges or by the foundation of one or morenew colleges.   (Para. 46.)London(18) There is scope for an expansion in the student population of LondonUniversity although such expansion may involve adopting a policyof decentralisation.   (Para. 47.)English Civic Universities and the University of Wales(19) A really substantial expansion here depends to a considerable extent on the Universities concerned being able to compete with Oxford,Cambridge and London for the limited supply of talented students;to this end the Civic Universities must improve their amenities andthe educational authorities should consider urgently a revision ofthe scholarship system.   (Paras. 48-51.)The University Colleges.(20) The existing University Colleges can be substantially expanded andthe possibility of founding new University Colleges in large centres of population should be considered.    (Paras. 31 and 52.)Scotland(21) There is, we think, still scope for expansion in the size of the ScottishUniversities.   (Para. 53.)A New University(22) The possibility of bringing into existence at least one completely newUniversity should be considered as soon as possible.   (Para. 54.)
THE QUALITY OF SCIENCE TEACHINGACUITIES FOB RESEARCH(23) This depends largely on the quality of research and every effort should therefore be made to ensure that adequate facilities for research areavailable  for  post-graduate students  and  for  university staffs.(Para, 55.)THE EFFECT OF OUR proposals the SUPPLY OF GRADUATES(24) When all possible measures have been taken to expand the output of graduates the nation will certainly be seriously short of scientists in1950 and is unlikely to have an adequate supply by 1955.(Paras. 56-57.)TEE ASSESSMENT OF PRIORITIES(25) In the allocation of our limited supply of scientists during the recon-struction period the order of preference should be :  (i) Teaching and Fundamental Research;(ii) Civil Science, both Government and Industrial;(hi) Defence Science. (Para. 58.)(26) It is important to maintain an adequate nucleus of able scientistsworking on the problems of defence.   (Para. 59 (c).)(27) The order of priority set out in conclusion (25) should be kept under constant review by the Government. (Para. 59(d).)(28) As one means of implementing this order of priority the attractionsof an academic career should be improved. The provision of moresecretarial assistance and office machinery for university teacherswould not only contribute to this end but would materially increasethe efficiency of the Universities.   (Para. 60.)TEE POSITION AFTER 1955(29) We do not think that the Universities need be deterred fromexpanding their facilities in order to produce 5,000 scientificgraduates per annum by any fear that this will leave them withexcessive staffs and accommodation once the demand for qualifiedscientists has levelled out.   (Para. 61.)THE IMPLEMENTATION OF OUR PROPOSALS(30) We hope that an increase in Exchequer grants to the Universitieswill not result in a diminution in private benefactions. (Para. 63 ( ).)(31) If our proposals are accepted by the Government, their implement a-tion must not involve any infringement of the independence of the universities; but we think that such independence is not inconsistent with a greater degree of co-ordination betweenuniversity policy and the needs of the country than has existed in the past,   (Paras. 64 and 65.)(32) The Government &apos;s part in any expansion programme should, weconsider, be the responsibility of the University Grants Committeewhich ought to be put in a position to concern itself more positivelywith university policy than it has done in the past.   (Para. 66.)68. In conclusion we would like to guard ourselves against an imputationwhich we fear that our report may lay us open, namely that we are&apos; imbued
with a narrowly materialistic view of the functions of a University. We are well aware that the training of specialists is not the only or even the mofimportant function of a University and we know that the Universitiesthemselves will strive to ensure that every student can seek the full lifewithin their precincts and that specialised knowledge is not bought at theexpense of wisdom.69. We wish to acknowledge most gratefully the invaluable help whichwe have received from our assessors and from our secretarial staff.Signed on behalf of the Committee:J. A. BARLOW, Chairman.M. T. Flett, Secretary,13th April, 1946.[31651] Wt.-4/46 F.O.P. Gp.340



</content>
</cab>
