<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/84/0 images: 157-168</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/2^ASINGAPORENote by the Secretary of State for the colonies in our discussion of my paper C.A.(56) 36 - nowcirculated as C.P.(56) 274 - at the Colonial Policy Committee certain points arose on which my colleagues sought additional information, andit may be useful if I circulate the notes below.Composition of Consultative Committees.(Paragraphs 18(a) and 19 of C.A.(56) 36)2. Tae suggestion is that there should be two separatecouncils.(i) An Internal Security Council or CommitteeThe Chief Minister would take the chair at this because it is concerned with internal affairs,and the United Kingdom representative and theGeneral Officer Commanding would be members.There would also be a representative of theFederation of Malaya, and such Ministerialcolleagues as the Chief Minister wished to have on it.     If this is not a voting body the actualnumbers are of no great importance.     This body would meet regularly and would be the means bywhich on the United Kingdom side Singapore ministers could be pressed to take action in these fields, andby which they in turn could explain to the UnitedKingdom representatives their plans for dealing withsubversive problems.    The two sides of thisCommittee would be jointly served by the SingaporeIntelligence Committee whose product would beavailable both to Ministers and to the UnitedKingdom side.     In addition there would be day today contact between the two sides on all these subjects through the United Kingdom representative^staff.    In addition there will be a Security liaison officer attached to the United kingdom representative^ staff, with the normal functionsof liaison with the Singapore Government.    (He isalready there and has been accepted by the singapore Government).-1-SECRET ,C.P.(56) 277 COPY NO.    ^8th December, 1956.CABINET
Since this would deal with matters which are theresponsibility of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, it would be under the chairmanship of the United Kingdom representa-tive who would have with, him anyone he wanted, including an appropriate military representative.   There would be no need to have a Federation representative on this Council.On the Singapore side the Chief Minister and ministers most closely concerned would attend.   This body would serve as a forum for the discussion of action required tobe taken in Singapore in conformity with international obligations assumed by Her Majesty&apos;s Government andin particular for the co-ordination of any action taken bythe   Singapore Government in trade and commercial affairs which they wish us to delegate to them.   (We said in our offer last April that &apos;&apos;Her Majesty&apos;s Government propose,subject to safeguards in respect of Her Majesty&apos;governments international commitments, to delegateresponsibility for trade and commercial relations to theGovernment of Singapore and consider this would properly bedone by means of a despatch issued on the coming into forceof the constitution, the terms of which would be agreed withthe Government of Singapore in advance. &quot;)Functions of United Kingdom Represervative and Queen&apos;s Representative(Paragraphs 20-26 of C.A.(56)&quot;36)3. It is of course our hope that we can secure agreement thatat least for a substantial interim period these two functions shall be combined in the person of the United Kingdom representative, (i. e. thepresent Governor, under whatever title he may have in the new constitution).If and when the function of being the Queen&apos;s Representative becameseparate and given to a local personage it was my intention that thefollowing should be their general functions.(i) The Queen&apos;s RepresentativeI believe Lim Yew Hock will agree that Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment should hava the final say about who should beappointed, though naturally there would have to be consulta-tion with Singapore Ministers.   Pie would be theconstitutional figurehead in Singapore, representingSingapore on&apos;ceremonial occasions and assenting to legislation (subject to such arrangements as we may make to give the United Kingdom representative a say in egislation affecting external affairs or defence).   He wouldequally have the normal constitutional functions of a governor General relating to the resignation of Governmentsetc.   But his primary function would be that of a figureheadexemplifying the fact that the people of Singapore were running their own affairs.
\7LcWe shall have to think of the right name for the UnitedKingdom representative i. e. the head of the United Kingdomside of this dyarchy.   There have been several suggestions -&quot;Defence Commissioner&quot;, &quot;Resident Minister&quot;, &quot; Agent-general&quot; - but these can be considered in due course.   Thename &quot;High Commissioner&quot; which we originally consideredwould suggest a diplomatic appointment, and the office willbe very much more than that.   The United kingdom representative would cease to play a leading part in theceremonial life of the community.   He would however be inconstant touch with Ministers through the two Councilsmentioned above and through his own personal cultivation of their friendship.   He would receive all Cabinet papers and minutes as well as the product of the SingaporeIntelligence Committee and the Singapore Special Branch(through the Security Liaison Office).   In addition thereshould be statutory requirements that he be consulted insuch matters as legislation affecting external affairs and defence, appointments to key positions (on which seeparagraph 4 below) etc.   He would of course have his ownsmall secretariat handling day to day external affairs and defence business which would be in day to day touch withSingapore Ministries concerned.   He should thus be incomplete touch v/ith the internal situation in Singapore andin regular contact with Ministers.   He would have no powers day by day within Singapore but would have thestatutory pov/er to suspend the constitution and assume responsibility for the Government.   He would equally beerapowe:;ed to call on military forces for assistance inthis matter (and should undoubtedly have a scheme of operations in readiness to meet such a contingency).   Thedifficulties of suspending the constitution would depend onthe circumstances.   It might be done at the request ofMinisters.   It might be done to remove an objectionableGovernment in circumstances where the population of singapore v/ould fully support the move.   Or it might haveto be done in circumstances in which action would arousegreat popular resentment.   The resources at the disposalof the United Kingdom representative would vary accordingto which circumstances applied.   If Ministers acquiesced orthe population were with us he could count on the police forceand the civil service.   If the whole circumstances were hostile he might be dependent (as in any case a Governormight be, with the progress of Malayanisation, even if therewere no constitutional advances) aLcnost entirely on british military support until, if it were necessary and possible, the basis of a civil administration could be formed by the re-call or transfer of officers to supplementwhat European officers at that time remained.   The processof Malayanisation, which we cannot halt, but which is now proceeding more circumspectly than the Singapore government at first proposed, will in any constitutionalcircumstances reduce the resources available for UnitedKingdom purposes.   It is important therefore that we usewhat influence and devices we can to persuade officers,and particularly police officers;, to continue to serve.
Colonial Office, S.W.1.7th December, 19564. Lim Yew Hock lias already offered continuing employment to senior police officers.   It is the intention, in the general M&amp;layanisationprogramme, that next year appointments should be made on therecommendations of independent Public Service Commissions (modelledon the principles of the Civil Service Commission here).   Senior policeposts are to be excluded from the responsibility of these commissions and for the present appointments to them are to be made by theGovernor in his discretion after consultation with the Public service commission.   Under any new constitutional arrangements I shall hope tocontinue this practice for so long as the Head of the United Kingdom sideis also the Queen&apos;s Representative.   If and when the Queen&apos;s Representa-tive becomes s. local personage we must then make arrangements to seethat we have a proper say in the appointment of these senior officers.There are various devices we might try.   While it might be difficult for singapore Ministers to accept that, when they have their own Queen&apos;representative, Her Majesty&apos;s Government should still appoint theirsenior police officerss they might, for example, be amenable to asuggestion that the appointments should be made by a consortium of interests (United Kingdom, Federation of Malaya and Singapore) on thesame principLe described in the first sentence of paragraph 19 of my paper.General5. All the details of these arrangements will have to be worked out further in the closest consultation with the military.and civil authorities in Singapore once we have some general idea of whereLim Yew Hock stands.A. L.-B,
Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1956SECRET Copy No.C.A. (56) 3630th November, 1956CABINETSINGAPORE: CONSTITUTIONAL development memorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesGeneralThe Chief Minister of Singapore, Mr. Lim Yew Hock, is coming to london in December to discuss with me arrangements for a conference on the future constitution of Singapore. He is most anxious that this conference should beconclusive and he therefore hopes during the December talks to reach an informalagreement with me on what he regards as the major issues to be settled at the formal conference.2. My colleagues will recall that, for reasons which we published at the timein a White Paper (Cmd. 9777), the Constitutional Conference on Singapore, held inApril and May of this year, failed to reach agreement. Fortunately this failuredid not, as some feared it might, lead to disorders in Singapore. After theconference, the Chief Minister and leader of the Labour Front Government,Mr. Marshall, resigned and was succeeded by a member of the same Party, LimYew Hock. Lim Yew Hock took office with a programme which contained two main points:  (i) to prove that Singapore was worthy of a further measure of internal self-government by dealing firmly with present problems, including theproblem of Communist subversion; and(ii) to ask for a further conference at an appropriate time at which fullinternal self-government for Singapore would be sought.3. Lim Yew Hock has already given evidence of his determination to tackleCommunist subversion. His Government have ordered the deportation of certainaliens and the detention of other persons who have been actively concerned withsubversive activities, including activities among the Left-wing Trade Unions andthe Chinese Middle Schools, the two main spheres of Communist activity. He hasalso ordered the dissolution of a number of organisations engaged in clandestinesubversive activities, including the Communist-dominated Singapore ChineseMiddle Schools Union. He has shown admirable patience and firmness duringthe consequential riots which were themselves an indication of the extent to whichthe Communists felt their power to be threatened by the Chief Minister^ policy.By these measures he has committed himself and his Party irrevocably to a firmstand against the Communists; and in doing so he has attracted the support of theLiberal Socialists, the most numerous Opposition Party in the Legislative Assembly.In the Legislative Assembly debate after the riots, the policy and actions of the singapore Government were endorsed by a vote of 25 to 4. Although it is too early to make any final assessment of the effect of these actions, there areencouraging signs that in following this policy the Labour Front Government maybe winning support from the large body of inarticulate opinion in Singapore whichis opposed to Communism but has hitherto waited in vain for a firm lead against it.4. There is thus quite a new situation and atmosphere in Singapore comparedwith that prevailing when the April Conference was held with Mr. Marshall. Atthat time the present Constitution had been in force only for one year, and therehad been little evidence that the locally elected Government were prepared to50843 b
tackle the difficult problem of Communist subversion. By the time the nextconference can take place the present Constitution will have been in force for nearly two years. The locally elected Government have broadened both their experience and support, and have shown evidence of firm determination both to govern andto combat subversion.Preparations for the 1957 conference. At the end of the last conference I announced that I would be preparedto meet again a delegation from Singapore to discuss constitutional development.There can thus be no question of my refusing to call the further conference whichLim Yew Hock has requested for February/March next year. It would be very dangerous to allow this second conference to break down. The issues on whichit would break down would command little sympathy in this country, and theconsequences in Singapore would be far-reaching and possibly violent.6. To ensure that we do not enter into this further conference without someconfidence that it will succeed, I have invited Lim Yew Hock to come to london in December to preparatory talks. I consider I must reach informal agreementwith him in these talks on the main features of the new Constitution, and this paperseeks the agreement of my colleagues to the line I propose to take.Objectives of Policy7. The patent political destiny of Singapore is to be reunited with theFederation of Malaya. I think responsible political leaders in Singapore recognisethat earlier suggestions that Singapore should become an independent State in itsown right are in the nature of things illusory (though there may still be pressure from extremists for &quot; independence &quot;). On present form, however, it will be someyears before there can be any fusion of Singapore and the Federation of Malaya,and our immediate policy must therefore be directed towards an interim period(during which the Federation of Malaya will separately become independent).8.   There are three principal objectives of United Kingdom policy:  (i) to prevent Singapore being taken over by the Communists;(ii) to preserve its character as a major international sea port and a centre ofeconomic activity in which there is a large British investment; and(iii) to maintain it as an effective military base for United Kingdom forcesin South-East Asia.These objectives are not in any order of priority, though clearly the first conditionsall others.Basic Choice of Policy9.   There are two courses open to us:  (i) to make a political settlement with the Singapore Government designedto secure a period of settled government or(ii) to resist further concessions, if necessary at the risk of a breakdown ofthe second conference, in order to retain some degree of directauthority.The Arguments for a Settlement10. I set out below the arguments for seeking a political settlement. Theyare massive.(a) There are two forces at work in Singapore nationalism and Communism.If we do not satisfy the desires of nationalism for the management bythe people of Singapore of their own affairs, the forces of nationalismwill become willingly or unwillingly the tool and ally of Communism.Communist exploitation of thwarted nationalism is too common a feature of the present political scene to require any further exposition,but it is basic to the proper handling of the whole situation to recognisewith what jubilation the Communists would greet a second breakdown in the negotiations.
The Argument for withholding Further Advance11. A settlement with Singapore will, as I shall show, involve some advance on the offer made to Singapore in April. The chief argument against an advance on what has already been offered is that it would be unwise, knowing theCommunist threat, to relinquish the right to intervene directly in the internal affairs of Singapore. It was of course on our insistence on the retention of this right that the April Conference broke down. 1 believe it was right at that pointso to insist, and I believe our insistence induced a new sobriety in the Singapore government and a new realisation on all sides in Singapore of the dangers ofsubversion and the responsibilities of government. Our stand had had its effect.But I am now satisfied that to insist again in the next conference that we retain some direct authority to interfere in the internal affairs of Singapore (apart fromthe general power to suspend the Constitution) will end the conference indisagreement, and will, for reasons I have already set out, benefit no one but the communists. They have been challenged and we must, despite the inherent risks,back those who have had the courage both to challenge and to fight.50843O (b) The tide of nationalism runs with immense strength throughout South-east asia and the independence won in India, Burma, Indo-China,Indonesia, and now promised to Malaya, makes the stream run all the stronger in Singapore. We are now well into the second year of fullyrepresentative Government in the Colony. Although the present constitution retains certain officials in the Council of Ministers and gives reserve powers to the Governor, the effective Government isalready in the hands of elected Ministers. It is those Ministers whohave so boldly tackled the problem of Communist subversion and whodealt so firmly with the recent riots. They will not willingly be heldback from enjoying in name that full exercise of political authority which they have already accepted in practice, above all after theirresolute challenge to Communism. As the Governor has put it, the hand that has grasped the nettle will not be restrained from pluckingthe fruit.(c) Our decisions on the future of Singapore will in present circumstances beof the greatest significance in Asia. Our credit for the generous andimaginative handling of emergent peoples stood high after thesettlement with Malaya early this year. Our enemies have sought touse the action taken by the Government in the Suez crisis to destroythat credit and to undermine the relations of confidence and understanding which we have built up in our Far Eastern associations.Many who want to be our friends have been disturbed and worried. Inmany ways therefore our decisions on Singapore will be regarded as a test of our true intentions. A generous settlement acceptable to thepeople of Singapore will do much not merely to strengthen thewaverers but to reassure Asian opinion as a Whole of the fundamentalintegrity and liberality of our Colonial purposes.(d) There are now no political elements in Singapore who would back a continuance of the status quo. The conservative element the moderate, well-to-do, middle class Chinese, represented by the LiberalSocialist Party are as fully committed to &quot; merdeka &quot; as is theGovernment behind whose recent campaign against subversion theyhave fully aligned themselves. If a settlement acceptable toresponsible political opinion in Singapore is not reached, we are left with no allies. The Government have said they will&apos;not be able tocarry on if the next talks fail, and no other Party will form aGovernment. And with the progress of Malayanisation in theGovernment service our ability to govern the Colony directly with any sort of local acquiescence must be seriously questioned. We could notin fact achieve the objectives in paragraph 8 above on our own (saveperhaps by a repressive form of government strongly backed by troops).Even this would play into Communist hands. We need allies in the pursuit of these objectives, and an agreed settlement offers the best hopeof securing stability, sustaining the present broad political line-up against Communism and preserving our mercantile interest.
Internal Security16. Lim Yew Hock is quite clear that if Her Majesty&apos;s Government insist on retaining a power of intervention in internal affairs, it would amount to nothing in practice. The moment it was exercised, he argues, the Singapore Governmentwould be bound to resign, and we should be forced to suspend the constitution and take over direct rule, since no other Party would allow themselves to be brandedas &quot; Colonial stooges &quot; by taking office in such circumstances. He is content toleave with us the right to suspend the Constitution, and asks why we should thenpress to retain powers which in practice would be entirely illusory, and whoseretention would be bitterly opposed and resented by political leaders in the territory.Even if we were able to obtain reluctant acquiescence to the retention of such powers at the next conference, which seems unlikely, they would, he claims, bethe subject of continuous attack and agitation in Singapore, they would weaken the position of any Singapore Government who agree to their retention, and the resultant &quot; settlement &quot; would be no more than an uneasy truce.17. These are cogent and well-founded arguments, and I have since beenthinking them over carefully, in consultation with the Governor. We are boundto recognise that this very situation already exists. Although the present constitution gives the Governor wide reserve powers, elected Ministers have infact been responsible for internal security policy since they first took office, and despite the dangerous situation, the political consequences to be expected from using the Governors reserved powers have been such that we have not at anytime felt it possible to use them. All action has been taken in accordance withthe wishes of elected Ministers, who have publicly taken the responsibility. Indeed,I am doubtful whether a &quot; Colonial &quot; Government could have acted so firmly andvigorously against the Communists, particularly in the Trade Unions, as the electedGovernment has been able to do with growing popular support. There can be nodoubt that, in the present advanced political state in Singapore, our only effective powers are those of guidance and persuasion; that a &quot;tough&quot; policy towardssubversive elements can be undertaken successfully only by an elected Government;and that any powers of intervention we sought to retain under a new constitution would be of no more value to us than are our present reserved powers. It can be argued that the existence of those powers has in itself a restraining effect.   I doThe Basis of a Settlement12. I have gone into these arguments thus fully because it is essential thatour basic policy should be rightly determined before its detailed implementationis discussed. I am convinced that we should now go after a political settlement acceptable to responsible opinion in Singapore. This is the Governor^ view aswell as mine, and it is fully supported by the Commissioner-General (Sir RobertScott).13. The starting point of our conference will be the offer made by her majesty&apos;s Government in April, and set out in detail in Appendix 8 to Cmd. 9777.In brief we offered complete internal self-government, under a High Commissionerinstead of a Governor, with the United Kingdom Government responsible for external affairs and defence, but retaining a right to make Orders in Councileffective in Singapore in discharge of those responsibilities alone. The conferencebroke down because Marshall would not agree to the retention of this right bythe United Kingdom.14. After the April Conference had broken down, Marshall made an unsuccessful attempt to resuscitate it by suggesting that he might be able to acceptthe retention of limited powers by Her Majesty&apos;s Government provided three otherconcessions were made: that the affairs of Singapore should be transferred to theCommonwealth Relations Office; that Singapore should have a Malayan (i.e., localGovernor-General or equivalent as Head of State, separate and distinct from theHigh Commissioner, who would simply be the representative of Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment; and that the United Kingdom&apos;s exercise of its overriding powers should be made subject to affirmative resolutions of the House of Commons.15. I discussed all these issues with the present Chief Minister in July, and set out in C.A. (56) 25 an account of our talks. As I explained in detail in that paper, Lim Yew Hock is anxious for a settlement and regards two issues as crucial the control of internal security, and the appointment of a Malayan Head of State.
&apos; 2h .xnot believe this to be true in the circumstances of Singapore. A well-intentionedGovernment would ignore them, because we should be behind it; an ill-disposedGovernment would deliberately challenge them.18. I therefore consider, and the Governor agrees, that we should not press to retain direct powers of intervention in internal affairs, provided-(a) there is satisfactory machinery established for constant consultation between Ministers and representatives of Her Majesty&apos;s Governmenton internal security matters;(b) United Kingdom security and intelligence requirements are properly met.This means principally a full recognition by the Singapore Governmentthat internal security is a joint United Kingdom / Singapore interest,and full access to the products of the Singapore Special Branch, &amp;c.19. I would like to leave open, for negotiation with Lim Yew Hock, adecision on the precise machinery to be established under paragraph 18 (a) above.I recorded in C.A. (56) 25 that he had suggested that, while he could not accept any direct United Kingdom control in internal security matters, he thought somecontrol could be exercised by a Defence and Security Council containingrepresentatives not only of the United Kingdom and Singapore but of theFederation of Malaya, with voting so arranged that Singapore Ministers could beoverruled only if the Federation representative voted with the United kingdom representatives against them. This would put the responsibility squarely on theshoulders of the Federation Government and he claimed that Singapore ministers could then loyally accept decisions made by this body. He also claimed that theinterests of the United Kingdom and of the Federation in internal security matterswould inevitably be the same. There are a number of difficulties in this proposal.There is the general argument that if Her Majesty&apos;s Government are to retain some control, then the exercise of that control should not be handed over to theindependent Government of the Federation of Malaya. It is also extremely doubtful whether the Chief Minister of the Federation, despite various assurances of friendly co-operation given to Lim Yew Hock, would lend himself to anarrangement which would so embroil his Government in the affairs of Singapore.Both the Governor of Singapore and Sir Robert Scott believe that in practice suchan arrangement could very easily come to grief, either if the United Kingdom andFederation representatives together outvoted Singapore Ministers on an issue which the latter regarded as absolutely vital; or if Singapore Ministers wereoutvoted in a series of matters none of which were in themselves of first importancebut which cumulatively produced a succession of defeats which Ministers regardedas intolerable. Both the Governor and Sir Robert Scott recommend that weabandon such a clumsy voting body and simply establish consultative machinery(on which the Federation of Malaya could be represented without the invidioustask of holding the scales). This may be the right answer and will certainly bea good bargaining counter. But my present intention is to discuss Lim Yew Hock&apos;sown suggestion further with him before recommending that, we should take this line.   I have not yet made up my mind the best solution to recommend.The Queen&apos;s Representative20. The Chief Minister attaches great importance to the proposal that a local&quot;personage&quot; should become The Queen&apos;s Representative under the nextConstitution. He does so not on grounds of any transfer of power, but because he claims this to be the key to a political settlement offering the possibility of an extended period of reasonable political calm between Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentand Singapore. His argument is that so long as a British official remains inGovernment House as not only the representative of Her Majesty&apos;s Government,but also The Queen&apos;s Representative, local agitators will be able to persuade localuninformed opinion that Singapore is still under &quot; Colonial&quot; rule, howevergenerous and advanced the Constitution granted by Her Majesty&apos;s Government.He claims that, if there were a local personage as the figure-head in government house, political passions could be stilled and the ground cut away from under thefeet of the current anti-Colonial and anti-European agitators through whom the communists seek to advance their interest.21. His conception of this appointment is that it should be truly a figure-head.He told me he was quite prepared for the United Kingdom Representative to
continue to enjoy those of his present rights e.g., the right to see all Cabinet papers and conclusions-which we felt necessary, and for Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentto appoint The Queen&apos;s Representative.22. I should note at this point that, in advancing this argument, and theearlier argument regarding internal security, Lim Yew Hock claimed that thesettlement which he considered would follow our agreement on these points wouldbe in the direct strategic interest of Her Majesty&apos;s- Government. He suggested thatit was against our strategic interest to provoke any situation in which our rightto be in the bases in Singapore was dependent on a Treaty or Agreement. these could be denounced. But if we could make a settlement in Singapore which would satisfy the mass of the people that they had been emancipated from &quot; Colonialism,&quot;we could divert pretensions to &quot; independence &quot; and ensure a maintenance of thestatus quo which would leave us in the bases as of existing right.23. These arguments again are most shrewdly conceived, and the Governorsassessment, with which I agree, is that the Chief Minister is right in his judgment of the local effect, of a concession of this kind. I recognise that the appointmentof a local personage to be The Queen&apos;s Representative would be unprecedented atthe present stage of constitutional development, and that for Commonwealthreasons he would have to have some other title than &quot; Governor-General.&quot; Butthis is the first of our &quot; smaller territories &quot; those for whom we can foresee noultimate independence on their own to have made this suggestion and it maybe that, if we can devise some arrangement on these lines which satisfies localnational pride without making the territory independent of the United Kingdom,,we shall have taken a pragmatic step towards the solution of a difficultconstitutional problem, and shall have demonstrated once more the adaptabilityof our Commonwealth arrangements.24. There are a number of arguments against making this concession. Itwould remove the United Kingdom representative from his present position at thecentre of affairs and thus, unless consultative arrangements were carefully made and successfully operated, reduce his opportunities for influencing policies and decisions. (These would in any case be lessened by his removal from theChairmanship of the Council of Ministers, which we have already promised.) Hewould cease to be the Head of the Public Service: this might affect the morale ofexpatriate officers, although I think most of them recognise that their futuredepends on the Singapore Government and on Her Majesty&apos;s Government ratherthan on the Governor or United Kingdom representative. And it would in some quarters be hailed as a sign of reduced British authority and lead to a loss ofconfidence in the business community and amongst those inarticulate sections ofthe population who have not grasped that we are no longer controlling theday-to-day administration of the island. The Governor considers, however, thatthe business community would quickly re-adjust and recover.25. I have weighed these considerations most carefully, in consultation withthe Governor, and have also had the Commissioner-general&apos;s views on them. Weare all of the opinion that we must go for a settlement which will have a chanceof stabilising the situation in Singapore for some time to come, and that to achieve this we should be prepared to make the imaginative concession over the&quot; Governor-General&quot; for which the Chief Minister has asked. I believe it mayindeed be the key to a new and stable arrangement. It will certainly be pressed,and I do not think we could in any case successfully defend in the House ofCommons or in the country a breakdown of the next conference which could be shown to have turned, amid all the immense issues and conflicts in Asia to-day,on the occupancy of Government House.     .26. Both the Governor and the Commissioner-General agree, however, thatwe should seek to delay carrying out this concession until the new Constitution hassettled down, so that the United Kingdom representative can remain at the headof affairs for. a transitional period. I hope we might get agreement to a period oftwo years before the local personage becomes the Queen&apos;s Representative, thoughthe Governor, considers this might be regarded as delaying tactics, and that we might have to settle for a year. If my colleagues agree in principle, the possibilitiesof an interim stand-still can be sounded out during my talks with Lim Yew Hockin December.
Strategic Interests27. In making these recommendations about a political settlement, 1 havehad constantly in mind their effect on our strategic position. 1 have tried toestablish what I consider will be necessary for a political settlement in Singapore.I believe that settlement is essential to achieve the third of the objectives set out inparagraph 8 above the maintenance of Singapore as an effective military base for united Kingdom forces in South-East Asia. If we now adopt policies whichprovoke hostility and continued agitation in Singapore, we shall move into a periodof mounting tension, with all its possibilities of riots and strikes, and we shall divertand divide the present strong anti-Communist drive. We could hold on by force,but eventually we would have to make some kind of settlement. The danger wouldthen be that we had to settle with forces or Parties committed to our departure from the Island, or at the best demanding a form of independence which requiredus to put our rights in the bases into a Treaty or Agreement. It is surely a primaryUnited Kingdom interest to avoid this. We are hoping to negotiate a reasonably satisfactory Defence Agreement with the Federation of Malaya (though theattitude of the Malayans on certain clauses has hardened since Suez): but that agreement, negotiated with great goodwill on both sides, has of necessity to take account of Malayan sovereignty and is bound to be restrictive in its effect. No such restrictions will apply in Singapore while the status quo can be maintained: andif we had to operate from Singapore it is important that the bases should be free from the threat of sabotage and strike. I therefore suggest that our best chanceof securing both these conditions is to settle now with Singapore on the lines I have proposed.The Position of the United Kingdom Government28. If I am able to secure agreement with Singapore leaders on the lines suggested above, our position vis-a-vis Singapore would be as follows:  (i) We should be responsible for the external affairs and defence of Singapore(subject to any arrangements which we might make to delegate someauthority in trade matters to the local Government: these would haveto be carefully negotiated so as not to prejudice our final responsibility).(ii) We should have consultative and advisory machinery with the Singapore government covering (i) above, and internal security.(iii) We should retain the right to suspend the Constitution and assume controlof affairs.(iv) The Singapore Government would be completely responsible for internal affairs.(v) At a later stage, the United Kingdom Representative would cease to combine the functions of representing both Her Majesty!s Governmentand The Queen, and the latter function would be transferred to a localperson.29. Although the changes involved would have the appearance of making aconsiderable advance, they v/ould, in terms of the exercise of power, makeremarkably little effective change from affairs as they are now. Point (i) aboveinvolves no change of principle. As regards (ii), officials and the Governor are ina minority on the present Council of Ministers, and short of over-ruling ministers by using reserved powers their functions are consultative and advisory. the reserved powers we hold at present in addition to (iii) could not be used without a major political crisis and would probably even now, given the unanimity of political parties about &quot; Merdeka,&quot; lead quickly into our having to suspend the Constitution.And in practice (iv) already obtains. Our only ultimate sanction now or in thefuture is to take over the Government completely, and rule with troops. Thissanction would remain. If the now strong democratic forces in Singapore were defeated, and the Communists tried to seize power, we should have to be readyto move in and take over. The constitutional advances I have proposed will make no difference to our duty or abilities in all this, save that, if a crisis came in a fewyears&apos; time, we should have few European civil servants on whom to depend, andwould have to have military government. This will be so, whatever the newConstitution.
Colonial Office, S.W. 1,29th November, 1956.Recommendation30. I believe this paper gives a realistic appraisal of the political facts in singapore, and that my proposals offer the best hope of stabilising the situationand defeating Communism. I seek the agreement of my colleagues to my entering into negotiations with Lim Yew Hock on the general lines indicated in it, and summarised in paragraph 28 above.A. L.-B.

</content>
</cab>
