<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/84/0 images: 255-256</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1957SECRET Copy No. CJ gC.P. (57) 98th January, 1957CABINETEUROPE AND THE UNITED nations memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues some observations on theposition of Europe in the United Nations.2. It may not be generally realised in this country how weak the positionof Europe is in the United Nations and how much it has deteriorated since the days of the League of Nations.3. Comparison between these two institutions shows that on 1st January, .1930(to take a convenient date) there were 53 members of the League, who could conveniently be grouped in the following categories:  British EmpireEurope (excluding the United Kingdom) ...Latin AmericaFar East..................AfricaMiddle East..................The United States were not members of the League; the Latin American members were not, as now, at all under the influence of Washington and could be relied onto have a European outlook. Except for the 6 Afro-Asians the remaining48 members were Europeans or the conscious inheritors of the European tradition.The leading figures at Geneva were Lord Robert Cecil, M. Briand, M. Benes,M. Politis, M. Titulesco, &amp;c.  It was, in a word, a European Assembly.4. The situation in New York to-day is sadly altered. The 80 members ofthe United Nations can be conveniently grouped as follows:  Free Europe (including the United Kingdom)    ...      ... 17Old Commonwealth          ...      ...      ...      ...      ... united States and Latin America............ 21Afro-Asians   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 26Communist countries        ...      ...      ..       ...      ... 10Others (China, Israel)        ............... 25.   It will be seen that:  (a) Europe far from enjoying preponderance in the Assembly now only has17 seats out of 80. There are no European figures who dominate the scene. In the atmosphere of New York the Latin Americans are lessEuropean-minded than they were in Geneva.(b) The Afro-Asians are only 1 short of the number (27) required to constitute the one-third necessary to block certain Assembly resolutions. WhenMalaya and the Gold Coast have joined the United Nations the afro-Asian group will occupy 28 out of 82 seats and can constitute a third.51009
2(c) Free Europe and the Old Commonwealth can only muster 21 votes (or 20,so long as South Africa stays away). They must therefore secure thesupport of the United States and/or some Latin American States inorder to obtain a third.(d) The Afro-Asians and the Communists, who are basically hostile to Free:   iEurope, already occupy 36 out of 80 seats.  Communist China, Malaya,Nigeria, Gold Coast, Algeria and possibly other new countries mayjoin the United Nations in the course of the next decade. Certain freecountries, such as France, Portugal or South Africa may leave inprotest against the treatment of Algeria, Goa or the Indian problemrespectively. If this occurs the Communists and Afro-Asians may shortly constitute an absolute majority. They are apt to bring amixture of malevolence, ignorance and irresponsibility to the conductof affairs in the United Nations.6. All this constitutes a menace to the future of the United Kingdom, europe and the free world. I do not suggest that there is anything to be done at themoment. But I think it right to call the attention of my colleagues to the position.S. L.Foreign Office, S.W.1,7\h January, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
