<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/84/0 images: 257-261</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  January 1957SECRET Copy-No.CP. (57) 1010th January, 1957CABINET&apos;COAL RESOURCES IN africa note by the Secretary of the CabinetThe note at Annex A summarises the conclusions of an Inter-DepartmentalOfficial Committee which was set up under Treasury Chairmanship, and which reported to the Economic Secretary to the Treasury, on:  &quot; The possibility of expanding coal production in Commonwealth territories in africa, having regard to:  (a) the possibility of looking to Africa as a source of United kingdom imports;and (b) the wider sterling area interests.&quot;2. The Cabinet will wish to consider how the conclusions of the Committeeshould be conveyed to Parliament. For this purpose a draft parliamentary statement is attached at Annex B.(Signed)        NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,9th January, 1957.
Printed for the Cabinet. January 1957SECRET Copy No.CP. (57) 1010th January, 1957CABINETCOAL RESOURCES IN africa note by the Secretary of the CabinetThe note at Annex A summarises the conclusions of an Inter-DepartmentalOfficial Committee which was set up under Treasury Chairmanship, and which reported to the Economic Secretary to the Treasury, on:  &quot; The possibility of expanding coal production in Commonwealth territories in africa, having regard to:  (a) the possibility of looking to Africa as a source of United kingdom imports;and (b) the wider sterling area interests.&quot;2. The Cabinet will wish to consider how the conclusions of the Committeeshould be conveyed to Parliament. For this purpose a draft parliamentary statement is attached at Annex B.(Signed) NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,9th January, 1957.
ANNEX ASUMMARY OF REPORT OF THE INTER-DEPARTMENTAL working party ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF COAL RESOURCES IN the african commonwealth the Working Party have looked into the possibility of developing Africancoal as a source of exports to the United Kingdom and to other countries.2.   Markets(a) United KingdomSubject to quality and price, there is a possibility but no certainty thatthe United Kingdom would provide a continuing regular market for coal imports; large coal is more likely to be needed than other types. (In 1956,total coal imports were about million tons, of which a little over 3 million tons were from the United States.)(b) EuropeThere is a probability that Western Europe will provide a continuingmarket for small and coking coal.(c) ElsewhereA moderate-sized market might exist in Pakistan, but there are no othermarkets of significance.3.   QualityIf the United Kingdom is to import coal it must be of a quality suitable toour installations. African coals are different from the types used in the UnitedKingdom. For the European market, the quality difficulties might be less than for the United Kingdom.4.   Prices and FreightsThe United States is the main source of United Kingdom and European coal imports. Freight rates have fluctuated widely; tentative estimates indicate thatfreights from African ports would always be higher than those from the UnitedStates, the difference increasing as rates rise. The f.o.b. price of African coal, tobe competitive, would always have to be less by this margin than the United Statesf.o.b. price.5.   Potential supplies available information on coal resources in Nigeria, South Africa, SouthernRhodesia, Swaziland and Tanganyika has been examined. This examinationshows that a continuing surplus of African coal for export could be produced, but every scheme investigated depends on additional capital 1i1vcs ihicul in mines and/orrailways. Estimates range from  3 million for j-l million tons from Nigeria to 50 million for 5 million tons from Tanganyika. All resources require time for development but 2 million tons from Southern Rhodesia might be achieved fairlyquickly.conclusions. All schemes would require some additional capital investment: and allbut one would require some time for development.7. There is no certainty that there will be a continuing requirement for theimport of coal into the United Kingdom over the next ten years and any development in Africa based on the expectation of a continuing United kingdom market would therefore involve a risk. This risk must be considered in relationto price and quality. Most African coal is cheap at the pithead, but at freightlevels current in October 1956, all African coals except Nigerian would have a pricedisadvantage in the United Kingdom. Nigerian coal would have a qualitydisadvantage. Given the uncertainty of United Kingdom demand, any directUnited Kingdom grant or loan for development cannot be recommended.
. 8. European demand is more certain, but except possibly for some^Mediterranean ports, price considerations will be much the same here, and theUnited Kingdom Government would not be justified in making extraordinaryefforts to provide finance for developing African coal for Europeanmarkets, or to persuade the Government of the coal-producing territories to divert resources to it against their own judgment. It is suggested, however, thatthese other Commonwealth Governments should be encouraged lo acquaintthemselves with the facts of the European market, and that the United kingdom should acquaint the various European countries with the information availableonAfrican coal.9. This report was drawn up in October 1956; and its conclusions take no account of subsequent developments in the Middle East nor of the currentdifficulties in the United Kingdom&apos;s oil supplies. The conclusions, however, arenot essentially affected by the new circumstances; the possible coal developmentsurveyed would in any case be too long-term to help immediately; andconsiderations of price and quality must continue to make United States coal more economic and suitable for the United Kingdom than African coal, whatever maybe the longer-term implications of Suez.ANNEX BDEVELOPMENT OF COAL  RESOURCES  IN  THE AFRICANCOMMONWEALTHDraft Parliamentary statement on 23rd July last I, the Minister of Fuel and Power, informed the House thatan inter-departmental investigation was to be made of the issues involved, so faras the United Kingdom is concerned, in the development for export purposes ofcoal resources in Commonwealth countries and territories in Africa, I am nowable to tell the House of the conclusions reached as a result of this investigation.The Committee which was set up has made a detailed examination of the available information on coal resources in the Union of South Africa, in the Federation of rhodesia and Nyasaland and in Nigeria, where coal is already being produced,and in Tanganyika, where detailed investigations have been made. Possibilitiesof developing coal production exist in Swaziland and other territories, but are stilltoo remote to be assessed in any detail.2. For the purposes of its investigations, the Committee looked into questionsof capacity, of cost, of quality, and of markets.3. In regard to capacity there is no doubt that Commonwealth countries in africa could provide substantial quantities of coal for export, but in all casesadditional capital investment would be required. In all cases, too, time would be needed for development before coal could become available for export.4. In regard to costs, in those cases where estimates were available, the capitalexpenditure would range from about  3 million for \-\ million tons a year to about 50 million for 5 million tons a year. This is not expensive in relation to thecapital costs of developing coal in the United Kingdom, and it appears that Africancoal would be cheap at the pithead in comparison with United Kingdom ar american coal. However, distance to a port for shipment abroad and the cost of sea freight must also be taken into account. Allowing for this, the Committee saw no prospect that African coal could be brought to the United Kingdom at a pricecompetitive with that at which United Kingdom coal can be produced, nor doesthere seem any likelihood that it could compete in the future.5. While investment in developing African coal resources cannot thereforebe regarded as an alternative to investment in our own mines, the Committeelooked into the possibility that those resources might be developed to replace our,present coal imports, especially of American coal. It is true that given the cheappithead price it appears that African coal could be sold f.o.b. at a price eithercomparable with or less than the f.o.b. price of American coal.   However, the
distance by sea to the United Kingdom from the African ports which would bagfeused is greater than from the United States, and sea transport costs would bewhigher. The difference would vary according to the African port and the general level of world freight rates; the variations can only be tentatively estimated, but atfreight levels current in October 1956 the extra transport costs might range from-about  1 to over  2 per ton, artd, except in the case of Nigerian coal, they would more than offset the lower f.o.b. price of African coal. The total cost per ton tothis country of importing it would thus be greater than that of importing Americancoal.6. The question of quality is important because United Kingdom appliancesand plant are naturally designed to use indigenous coals, and when coal is importedit should be similar in character to our own coal in order to give reasonableflexibility in distribution and use. Most African coals are substantially different intheir characteristics from the types now in use in the United Kingdom. This is notto say that they are inferior coals, but it does mean that they are not ideally suitedfor use here. With some exceptions their volatile matter content differsappreciably from that of the normal run of United Kingdom coals and all have acomparatively high ash content. Most of them have a lower calorific value thanimported American coal. Consequently African coals wouid not be worth to united Kingdom consumers as much ton for ton as coal which suits our habits and installations; some may be quite unsuitable for the requirements which may have-to be met by imported coal. In the case of Nigerian coal, the differences incalorific value and other characteristics are particularly marked and vitiate pricecomparisons on a purely ton-for-ton basis.7. Even if the examination of these considerations showed more favourableprospects, there would still be the question of the existence of a market in theUnited Kingdom, for a sufficient number of years after the African coal could bemade available for export, to justify incurring the capital expenditure involved.As to this, there must be considerable uncertainty in estimating the supply and demand position for years ahead, but the carrying out of the Coal Board&apos;s presentdevelopment plans and the contributions which oil and atomic energy are expectedto make to meeting our fuel requirements, do hold out the prospect of our being able to dispense with imports of coal. It cannot therefore be regarded as certainthat the United Kingdom would provide a continuing regular market for Africancoal. As far as we can assess the future at present, there would therefore be a risk,to put it no higher, that if any developments in Africa were undertaken for the specific purpose of supplying coal to the United Kingdom market, there would notbe a continuing need for the coal after it became available.8. Taking all these considerations together the uncertainty of the UnitedKingdom&apos;s continuing need and the lack of any clear advantages possessed byAfrican coal in quality or in price Her Majesty&apos;s Government would not feel justified in giving any direct financial assistance to the development of African coal for the United Kingdom.9. The Committee has also considered whether coal supplies from AfricanCommonwealth countries could be developed for sale to other markets, thusbenefiting the sterling area&apos;s overall balance of payments. The recent Report ofthe Energy Commission of the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation on &quot; Europe&apos;s Growing Needs of Energy &quot; suggests that in the rest of western europe the continuing need for coal imports may be more assured than in theUnited Kingdom. But given the many claims on the United Kingdom, and on commonwealth and Colonial Governments, for worthwhile investment in theCommonwealth, the possibility that a project might be developed for other marketsis not enough to justify the United Kingdom Government itself in makingextraordinary efforts to provide finance for it, or in attempting to persuade other commonwealth or Colonial Governments against their own judgment to divertscarce resources to it.10. Her Majesty&apos;s Government intend to take steps, however, to ensure thatthese other Commonwealth and Colonial Governments are encouraged to acquaintthemselves with the facts concerning the European markets for coal, and will thus be aware of their possibilities; also to take steps to acquaint other european countries with the various potential supplies of African coal and the available information about them.

</content>
</cab>
