<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/83/3 images: 54-60</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   &lt;0k CC(86) 3r^0^ Conclus ion&amp;i^/^		COPY NO

%	CABINET	

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street on THURSDAY 23 JANUARY 1986 at 10.30 am		

I   k Th^	PRES	ENT

	on Margaret Thatcher MP Prime Minister	

The Rt Hon Viscount Whitelaw ^ Lord President of the Council	% 1	The Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St Marylebone Lord Chancellor

The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MP Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs		^.The Rt Hon Leon Erittan QC MP ^Secretary of State for Trade and Industry

The Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP Chancellor of the Exchequer		  $ie^t Hon Douglas Hurd MP Seji^vary of State for the Home Department

The Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph MP Secretary of State for Education and	Science	Th^^tl^Hfkn Peter Walker MP Secrepary&gt;pDf State for Energy

The Rt Hon George Younger MP Secretary of State for Defence		The Rt^Jn Nicholas Edwards MP Secretary of State for Wales

The Rt Hon John Biffen MP Lord Privy Seal		The Rt Hon NortfGmXFowler MP Secretary of Bmatv for Social Services

The Rt Hon Tom King MP Secretary of State for Northern Ireland		The Rt Hon MichaxM.^jap^-i.ng MP Minister of AgricuT^jabfe- Fisheries and Food

[The Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP Secretary of State for Transport		The Rt Hon Lord Young^^O^raffham Secretary of State for Em^&amp;yment The Rt Hon Kenneth Clark^^S*   Paymaster General

The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker MP Secretary of State for the Environment		

The Rt Hon John MacGregor MP Chief Secretary, Treasury		The Rt Hon Malcolm Rif kind QCCm^^ Secretary of State for Scotland^,,^^^^


   	ALSO PRESENT			

% &lt;6	The Rt Eon John Wakeham MP			

	Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury			

	J SECRETARIAT			

i	Sir Robert Armstrong yxv/ Mr D F Williamson	(Items	2-5)	

	Mr C L G Mallaby	(Items	2-5)	

	Mr A J Langdon	(Item	  )	

	Mr R Watson	(Item	1)	

	CONTENTS			

Item	Subject			Page

1.	PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS			1

	Westland			1

2.	FOREIGN AFFAIRS ({OV			

	L&apos;S0th0 Uganda			1 1

	People&apos;s Democratic Re&lt;mjMjS.c of South	Yemen		2

	International Tin CouncM/V*A			2

	Group of Five Meeting //&gt;\			3

3.	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS			

	Intergovernmental Conference	?		3

	Agriculture &apos;X			4

4.	ECONOMIC AFFAIRS		-v	4

5.	NORTHERN IRELAND AFFAIRS	c	k	5


   1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House of Commons in the following week.

I

lestland piTS^OolE PRIME MINISTER said that she would make a full statement m the NA^WifiSse of Commons later that day about the circumstances in which the &apos;^&lt;&lt;&amp;n    nts of a letter from the Solicitor General to the former Secretary /f/JjEhte for Defence had at the time been made available to the press. Xha^eS^ential point that she would emphasise would be the importance of ensur^ig that there was nothing misleading in statements made on behalf of roejfiw^ernment at a time when commercially sensitive judgments about Westlano&apos;^pfuture were being taken.

The\pabinet -

Took note, and expressed their sympathy and support foi^the Prime Minister.

  SB!

FOREIGN	2. THE FOREIGN A1TOAk$^K)NWEALTH SECRETARY said that the Lesotho

AFFAIRS	Paramilitary	Force (fcM^toad deposed the former Prime Minister, Chief

|___ Jonathan, in	a coup on Zo^knuary. The country was now under the

Lesotho	control of a	Military C  6*$yCzSS. chaired by Major General Lekhanya,

Commander of	the LPF. King^ftoshoeshoe II remained Head of State. Chief

Jonathan was	at a house in~p  ff^ountry. Other former Ministers had been

ordered to remain in their irome^iN The South African blockade of the Lesotho border appeared	in place but the Military Council

was negotiating with the South ^rean Foreign Minister. There were 600 British citizens in Lesotho;vjjer^ppeared to be safe. A curfew had been imposed and the situation vis oA. Chief Jonathan had not been popular with the Front Line StatesMwrt^&amp;eneral Lekhanya would be suspect I	in their eyes as a possible South Afr^ap^puppet.

Uganda	THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thtfEAthe ceasefire in Uganda

had broken down. There had been clashes between&lt;/he National Resistance Previous	Army and Government forces. Shops and busine    5hji3Nbeen closed. The

Reference:	British community in Kampala had been advised t  Qs  ay.at home. The

(jc(86) 2nd United Kingdom&apos;s offer of assistance - consist insmall military Conclusions,	advisory team, some aid and a contribution in castro^p^raterial towards

Minute 3	logistic back-up for monitoring a ceasefire - remain^d   T^l^the table.

But it was dependent on an end to the fighting and tne &apos;mclementation of the peace agreement of 17 December 1985. Kenya appear  (^^  Obe reluctant to commit troops for the monitoring of a ceasefire. TaAMjia^lso had* reservations. The Government were continuing to ensure ctrt^Kenya and Tanzania expected no more British assistance than was actually jot offer.

Mk


   IUL

PeoSi^/s	THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the evacuation of

lemoqvy&amp;K	foreigners from the People&apos;s Democratic Republic of South Yemen was

|epuMie^5v proceeding well. HMY Britannia, along with French and Soviet vessels, louth Yenw  \ ha&lt;* evacuated up to 1,200 persons, including 21 British citizens, from Little Aden in the previous two days. All British citizens in Aden Irevious \X*&apos;V/&apos;&apos;itself seemed now to have been evacuated. The merchant ship &quot;Diamond leference: v^Qikincess&quot; evacuated 248 foreigners, including 22 British citizens,   C(86) 2nd &apos;Os^rQm Mukalla, three hundred miles east of Aden. A fleet survey vessel, Conclusions, &apos;vMB^ydra, was trying to evacuate 42 foreigners including one British linute 3	from Al Gaider further north. It appeared that only about eight

Bri    K.citizens were now in any part of South Yemen. Her Majesty The Queen^kad agreed that HMY Britannia should remain in the area as long as was i^gjSeflfsary for the evacuation. But the Government hoped to arrange for HM  /Bp  fannia to reach New Zealand in time for The Queen&apos;s visit there rr&amp;n 22 February to 2 March.

The political situation in South Yemen remained confused. The rebels appeared to have gained the upper hand. The British Ambassador,

Mr Arthur MarsbipfiN, who was aboard HMY Britannia, had estimated that 10,000 people nujgtNf have been killed in the fighting. The Soviet Government were^x^yWg to negotiate a conclusion to the fighting, but so far without succeivg^/AThere was no sign of Soviet or Ethiopian intervention in SolQ^&apos;Yemen. The Soviet Embassy in Aden had been among the buildings damaged&apos;/wp&quot;the fighting.

The unusual co-operarMwTb^tween the United Kingdom and the Soviet Union in this evacuation was sjpat&amp;lised by the presence on HMY Britannia of a representative of the SdSrai  \Embassy in Aden, who recently had been maintaining the communica^Lpna^between Moscow and the Soviet Embassy.

In a short discussion, it waAjra  fcd that the Royal Navy and the British Ambassador and his staff had&apos;^^rwj.dely congratulated for their roles in this evacuation. The Royal   f&amp;yxHad indeed acted in the best traditions of the Service.

I

International THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY ^ id that the meeting that week Tin Council of the International Tin Council (ITC) had focused on a new proposal put forward by Japan on 21 January. This proposal was not, as it stood, a satisfactory basis for settling the problems o  ^  ne ITC. But it did represent an attempt to make progress. The Graverqjment were now trying to move matters forward, by combining the besc^^enwnts of the Japanese proposal and the earlier &quot;Newco&quot; proposal put fcimw&amp;y&gt;y independent financial experts.	/si!

In a brief discussion, it was noted that the Japanes^^TOMign Minister, Mr Shintaro Abe, had that week told the Secretary of Stlre^for Trade and Industry that the Japanese Government did not attach iTOjKtMce to the precise details of their proposal. Moreover, when the Orauj^eUor of the Exchequer had raised this subject at the meeting in London&gt;*rafvirevious weekend of the Group of Five, France had said that she was&apos;wiHiftg in principle to contribute to a settlement, subject to the ques^x^p-f how


   I	much money would be involved. This had left the Federal Republic of

Germany isolated in the meeting of the Group of Five, and she had said .  2*. that she would reconsider her refusal to negotiate about a rescue

operation for the ITC. These were hopeful signs that progress might be possible.

%

   Group of	gjirOJANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that there had been a meeting in

   Five Meeting Coniron the previous weekend of the Group of Five, consisting of the

Fir(gfi  S^linisters of	the United	Kingdom,	the United States, the Federal

RepuWftfq^f Germany,	France	and	Japan. The only difficulty about the

meetr&amp;Miad been that some people who were not involved in it had raised unrealistic expectations of	its	results.	The meeting had discussed the

question of interest	rates.	It	had been	felt that, given the prospects

of lower rates of inflation, there were reasonable prospects of interest rate&amp;^Sming down in the coming year. But the other countries in the Group raf F/uve preferred the United States to make the first move, and the Adminv2j3  iJ  &gt;on in Washington was divided on the question of an early move. Thanneooing of the Group of Five had also discussed fiscal policy and the piiSwiwof international debt.

The Cabinet -

Took note.

\

COMMUNITY	3. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEAWfH^S^CRETARY said that the results of the

AFFAIRS	Intergovernmental Conference we&amp;&lt;r spkl subject to the remaining

I---	reserves. The United Kingdom&apos;s   x^rft^pon, however, was satisfactory.

Inter-	The	Dutch Presidency had now put faredrd	a text on the effect of small

governmental	and	medium-sized businesses of meas	n the working environment.

Conference Although the Italians and Germans had&gt;nroi&lt;^yet accepted it, this issue was unlikely to be an obstacle. Italyr&apos;S&apos;reserve on the whole package Frevious	was being maintained until the Italian TQarliament had been consulted

Reference:	but, in the light of the moderate attitude in the European Parliament,

|C(86) 1st	the	Ital ian Government would probably be	able to obtain sufficient

Conclusions,	support to lift its reserve. The Danish	Parli/  j5e&gt;it, however, against

Minute 4	the	advice of the Danish Government, had	now frejeqjbed the conclusions	of

the Intergovernmental Conference. The DanishMinister,

Mr Ellemann-Jensen, had been in London on 22 Jam(aryyand was visiting other member states; he was receiving the message&apos;-tHSaf/he expected: the package was not renegotiable. The Danish Goverrmevtzffe&amp;xea&amp;y to call a national referendum, which it would probably win. ISE^irffothe other hand, Denmark was not able in the end to ratify the agrewmpftt, then some improvements in Community procedures and decision-makina^ra  &amp;t still be made without Treaty change on the lines advocated by the^rnijrad Kingdom at an earlier stage.	^


   Jfi?5  /&lt;  ture	the MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that the Council of

Ministers (Agriculture) on 20-21 January had reached conclusions on certain special arrangements for the import of meat into the Community,

&apos;	The Cabinet -

Took note.

1

ECONOMIC	CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the financial markets

HlFFAlRS	wer^^jZry-nervous, mainly as a result of the considerable fall in oil

priceS^^iice the beginning of th   year. The fall in the value of sterlfwg had not been on the same scale, partly because of the widespread expectation of further rises in interest rates. It might not be possible to come through the present difficult period without such a *1	rise.	^__^

In a brief diicyraion the following points were made -

a.	If thersubstantial rise in bank base rates, the building soci^^  ^would be obliged to raise mortgage rates. This might be an ara(  i  *bvfor allowing the sterling exchange rate to take some of tK^^^in in the present situation; but the effect on mortgage rates was^M^t one of the factors, which would have to be taken into accountC^n^fyaching decisions on interest rates.

b.	The dependence ofTm^wiited Kingdom economy on the price of

oil tended to be exagg*0K  d\ The Chancellor of the Exchequer would that day be publishort fact sheet putting the matter into perspective.	Uy&apos;

c.	While industrialised coif  tipi^   which were not oil producers would benefit far more than tfJ^Urri^ed Kingdom from the fall in oil prices, it seemed that the bal5iraAj   positive and negative effects for the United Kingdom might be fc^ieast neutral and perhaps if anything slightly favourable.

The Cabinet -

Took note.	((()


   LoRT  ^^O	5* THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said that by-elections

tRELANK^&gt;\ were taking place that day in the 15 constituencies in Northern Ireland IkFFAlRS^V^ from which Ulster Unionist Party (UUP) and the Democratic Unionist Party &gt;^2\(DUP) Members of Parliament had resigned in protest at the Anglo-Irish Irevious ^O&apos;jVvgreement of 15 November 1985. The Unionist parties were expected to Reference:&apos;^^^rf&amp;hieve a very large vote. The outcome as between the two Roman   c(86) 2nd /^tarcholic parties, the Social Democratic and Labour Party and Sinn Fein,    Conclusions, &apos;^.wjraTless predictable. The situation in Northern Ireland was moving into Minute 5	*	V^ro    qtially dangerous phase. The Unionist leaders had no clear ideas

aawtat/tbe policy they should adopt after the by-elections. It was pos^Mj  &gt;that the current co-operation between the UUP and th   DUP would breaVlrowK It was not clear whether re-elected Unionist Members of Parlidi  e$/would stay at Westminster or would withdraw after a period.

The Govefulment should react in a carefully balanced way to the outcome of the by^  lections. He himself would be making a broadcast for this purpose. Ministers should say that the Anglo-Irish Agreement would continue to be implemented. Rather than dismissing the by-election results as insi^jrrMcant, Ministers should show that they took those results serxousiWj Jfhfiy should point out that there were misunderstandingsT^TN^rthern Ireland about the significance of the Agreement and say V  ha^/tfie Government would seek to dispel these by working for wider re^OTpjxion of the benefits to be derived from the H	Agreement. Such a stOTj  ^hv the Government would avoid the risk of

encouraging a &quot;laager	lty&quot; among unionists.

The Cabinet -	\4Cj)

1.	Took note.	   x&apos;vX v

2.	Invited Ministers to &lt;B  %&lt;J!lded by

the suggestions of the Secr  i^r^rsof State for Northern Ireland in their rea^ions to the results of the by-elections tha^dav in Northern Ireland.	cCo/

I	1

Cabinet Office

23 January 1986	\C_.

I	V3)l



</content>
</cab>
