<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/140/0 images: 566-577</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CML1529t^january YZ-l969COPY NO.    6 5CABINETpay of overseas telegraph o^ratorsln ttJe&quot;post&quot;6fficeMemorandum by the Lord Privy SealThis history of the present strike of Overseas TelegraphOperators and sympathetic action among other of the Union cf PostOffice Workers (upw) members (at present stopping overtime andSunday working on the telephones and a one-day strike of all postal and telephone staff) goes back to the troubles which led the ministerial Committee on Prices and Incomes to agree to settlementst.c cover both central pay increases and productivity awards to postmenand telephonists last year.     In each case these settlements werepreceded by industrial unrest, and the productivity elements paid tothe postmen, and expected by the telephonists (though not Post Officeofficials) to result later this year from the current calculations,exceed what could strictly be justified by reference to achieved saving in costs.     Postmen received 4 per cent (3 per cent central pay increase and 1 per cent described as for productivity) and telephonistsS\ per cent (5 per cent central pay increase and \ per cent forproductivity already secured) from 1st July, 1968^ and telephonistsexpect a further award, retrospective to 1st January, 1969, whencurrent calculations of savings are completed.    Overseas TelegraphOperators (OTOs) after rejecting an earlier offer of 5f per cent plus1 per cent, rejected a final offer of 5 per cant plus 2 per cent whichexcluded payment for the procedure - Overseas Tape Relay Unit(OTRU) - which had been in operation from 1963 to 1967 and isconsidered to be covered by the basic pay determined after pay research in 1966 of the rates paid for comparable work outside.    Anadditional week, after 31st December, the date limiting the amount of retrospection, was conceded, originally to allow the upw leadershipto canvass support for the offer, but instead they conducted a ballotamong the OTOs and announced on 11th January that they had gotsupport for strike action.2.     The Ministerial Committee on 14th January rejected a proposal by the Postmaster General to offer 5 per cent only, leaving productivityto be negotiated later.    The Union were already publicly demanding anadditional 4 to 5 per cent.    The Committee considered that productivity agreements should precede pay agreements and that the UPW claim should be resisted and if necessary referred to arbitration even at therisk of a strike.    The OTOs went on strike on 20th January.    The-1-CONFIPEIMTIAL

Press, on hints from Mr. Jackson, the UPW leader, began to allegedifferences between Ministers.    At the Ministerial Committee on prices and Incomes on 23rd January the Postmaster General proposedto renew the Governments previous offer of 5 per cent with a further2 per cent productivity increase for the introduction of a specificchange in practice (received revision) six weeks after the date ofagreement, but to reeerve the position of the OTRU for further discussion to be held between then and July.    The committee decided against this because it would mean giving in cn the major issue in the face of determined industrial action.     The Committeewere prepared to reconsider the position if circumstances changedsignificantly or an acceptable alternative formula could be devised.3.     My memorandum to the Prices and Incomes Committee,annexed, describes events following discussion at the parliamentary committee, on Monday morning, 27th January, of a minute from thePostmaster General to the Prime Minister, including a reference tothe loss of overtime earnings that would follow the productivitymeasures, especially OTRU, which incidentally caused the difficultieswhich led to the closing of OTRU in 1967.    The position is that theUPW continue to rely on industrial action, although they cannot afford to compensate their members for a total strike, and have declared their intention to resist technological change now or in future unless their co-operation is paid for at once in each specific case.    In thecase of OTRU this would in fact mean paying twice.S.Civil Service Department, S. W. 1.29th January, 1969

PAY OP POST OFFICE OVERSEAS TELEGRAPH OPERATORSMemorandum by the Lord Privy SealMy colleagues will remember that when we discussed this issue last week the Committee decided (P.I.(69)3rd Meeting,23rd January) to reaffirm &quot;their previous decision not togrant a pay increase of 5% ..... from 1st July 1968?unaccompanied by a firm productivity agreement&quot;.   The Onionof Post Office Workers then decided to escalate industrial action, involving telephonists and the postal workers.Because of this the Parliamentary Committee asked me on the morning of Monday, 27th January to invite the U.P.W. to ameeting, at which the Postmaster G-eneral and the joint parliamentary Under Secretary of State of the Department ofEmployment and Productivity would also he present, in orderto reaffirm the decision which had already been taken by thePxaces and Incomes Committee, to &quot;bring home to the unionthat there was nc disagreement between Ministers, and at thesame time to explore the scope for further negotiations.2,     The meeting with the Union took place yesterdayevening, and as my colleagues will know from the statement which the Postmaster General made in the House yesterdayevening, and from what was said to the Press, the result wasa complete deadlock.3.     There was, of course, on the Government * a side verylittle room for manoeuvre.   But we used the meeting toindicate that on two points the Government were prepared togo some way to meet their demands.   First, we made clear,that an offer made by the Post Office some little time agostill stood, that in relation to the pay offer of 5% plus2% for the productivity improvement known as &quot;receivedrevision&quot; we were quite ready to have the 2% adjustedretrospectively; after the new arrangements had been intro-duced, on the basis of local costings.   There was therefore no question of the Government insisting in relation to thisparticular measure on the Union &quot;buying a pig in the poke&quot;.The second was to say that if the U.P.W. was not prepared tosubmit this issue to the Civil Service Arbitration Tribunalwe would be prepared to agree, if the U.P.W.&apos; accepted the proposition, to set up an ad hoc Tribunal, to be chaired by1

Professor Clegg, the Chairman of the Civil ServiceArbitration Tribunal, who is not only a Professor ofIndustrial Relations at Warwick University, but from his experience in this field (including a period as a full-timemember of the National Board for Prices and Incomes), aswell qualified as anybody to sit in judgment on these issues.To this specially constituted tribunal there could be addedtwo members, chosen by the U.P.W. and the Official Siderespectively.h.     What emerged very clearly was that the U.P.W. wereadamant that they were not prepared to submit to arbitration,not only this particular productivity agreement for the relatively small numbers of Overseas Telegraph Operators,but for the future any other productivity agreement in thewhole field for which they were responsible.    These agreements were, the Union insisted, a matter for negotiation, and not for arbitration: what they left unsaid, but it was quite clear that this was what they were saying, was that wherethere was deadlock in negotiation the alternative to the employer giving way was industrial action.5.     At the end of the meeting the U.P.W. made it clear thatthere were two alternatives (they spoke of three but twoof these amounted to the same thing):(i) that if the Postmaster General would offer them 5%without strings of any kind they would immediatelycall off the strike, or(ii) if we would offer them 5% plus 2% for &quot;received.   .  revision&quot;, to be adjusted retrospectively afterlocal costings,  and to agree that the re-activationof the other productivity arrangement, O.T.R..U.,should be considered separately, they would recommend to their Executive Committee that they should consider accepting this.6.   They made it quite clear that their position was thatin no circumstances would they accept the re-activation ofO.T.R.U. without payment.    This, as the Committee are aware,would, if O.T.R.U, is to be re-activated, involve payingtwice for this productivity arrangement.   As my colleagues may remember O.T.R.U. had been introduced, and was working,when the pay of the Overseas Telegraphists was last reviewedfollowing pay research.    It was taken into account in the survey which the Pay Research Unit made of the work of the grade, and so in determining what was paid for comparablework outside.   Payment for it is therefore already builtinto the pay rates of these people..7.     At the briefing meeting which I had v/ith my colleaguesbefore we met the Union, the Postmaster General put forwardan argument which had not been brought to the attention ofthe Committee.   He said that if fully implemented, the2

re-introduction of O.T.R.U. would result on average in a loss of take-home pay equivalent to 10% of basic pay,compared with the proposed Post Office offer of anincrease of 5% * 2%.   We were unable to assess the forceof this new argument in the absence of any detail as to how these figures had been arrived at.    However, it was agreedthat this was a matter of   great   importance, and thePostmaster General has undertaken to make details available for we discuss this issue (tomorrow evening).Conclus i ons8.      (i) It is clear that the Union is not likely to shiftits position unless we are prepared to face upto the industrial action they have already planned, and which they may extend, over thenext week or two.   And unless we do so they willnot accept any form of arbitration on the broadissue.(ii) In considering (i) we shall need to assess thepoints made about take-home pay set out inparagraph 7 above.(iii) Now that positions have been taken up on bothsides so firmly and publicly there would notappear to be any possibility of a compromise,short of the Post Office saying that on reconisdertion, for operational reasons they have decidedthat instead of persisting in the re-activationof O.T.R., U. they should get ahead with the moresophisticated machinery which, in any case, theywere planning to introduce in two to three years&apos;time.S.Civil Service Department,S.W.1..28th January.  1 g6g




</content>
</cab>
