<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/140/0 images: 704-747</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT)C(69) 23 COPY NO.10th March, 1969CABINETGREEN PAPER ON HIGHWAY STRATEGYMemorandum by the Minister of transport the Ministerial Steering Committee on Economic Policy on18th February invited me to redraft the proposed Green Paper onHighway Strategy and recirculate the final text about a week before publication,2.       Publication is fixed for 26th March and the paper is now beingprinted byHMSO,    Although copies of the proof of the text are not yet available I am circulating copies of the revised text at Annex A,    I hopealso to circulate proofs of the revised maps very shortly.3.       The majority of the amendments are designed to emphasise theimportance of roads to regional development, to indicate the extent towhich the proposed strategic network will serve the regions as a whole,and to show how individual local needs will be taken into account when-developing new or improved links between the strategic network and particular areas,4.      The national map now shows more detail, as suggested by theCommittee, including regional boundaries, all the existing and proposed new Towns, major town expansions and many more place names,    Welshroads are omitted altogether, as agreed.    Four large-scale maps will   .also be published showing more clearly how the proposals affect theindividual regions.    I have carefully considered the Committee^suggestion that these regional maps should also show the relationship between the proposed network and the existing road system.    This would add substantially to the cost of production, but, apart from that, if wepublished maps showing this degree of detail, we should inevitably be faced with costly and premature problems of planning blight because theline of the new roads in the network would appear, to members of the-1-

public, to be more precisely fixed than they are at this stage of planning.I have, therefore, after consultation with the Paymaster General,reluctantly decided that we must avoid giving so much detail.    I will certainly ensure, however, that the Regional Economic Planning councils are given all the detail they need to assess the proposals comprehensivelyfor each region.R.W.M.Ministry of Transport, S.E.1.6th March, 1969-2-

ANNEX AROADS FOR THE future a NEW INTER-URBAN PLANMinister&apos;s ForewordRoads make an important contribution to economic growth bothnationally and in the regions.    They have to be planned ahead and.their economic consequences foreseen.   We need a new strategy for building and improving national roads in the 1970s and early 1930s.    The first1,000 miles of motorway will be completed in the early 1970s.    Butit is no longer sufficient to plan in terms of so many miles of road since the nation is concerned with effective networks rather than with individual roads.   After a good deal of work on appraisal of thefuture traffic situation on the whole of the existing network oftrunk roads and taking into account the requirements of industry,exports, regional development and other relevant factors, we havebeen able to plan a network of national routes not only to give ahigh economic return on the vast sums involved, but also  to meet thesocial and developmental needs of the regions and of the country as a whole.I must emphasize that this paper deals only with the inter-urbantrunk road plan.   As the paper explains, the development of the newnetwork represents only one part of the future road programme.Substantial sums will also be spent on improving other inter-urbanroads serving particular local areas and on links with the main net-work.   In addition, there is the whole problem of urban road develop-aent, to which a large part of the future road programme will be devoted.    This paper, does not however attempt to deal with urban roads./The

- 2 -IThe proposed inter-urban trunk road strategy needs careful thought, detailed planning and public support.   All these are most likely If there is a,general discussion on the aims of the strategy and on the details of the proposed network - a discussion which isbased on known facts and in which all sections of public opinion playapart.    There is no monopoly of wisdom on this subject and ratherthan, put forward a cut and dried plan, I have decided to publish thisreen Paper as a basis for discussion.   The suggestions in it are not,at this stage,, firm government policy.   Instead, they are an indication of current thinking,    i hope all those interested.will study the paper and let us have their views.

introduction.     This paper outlines a proposed new strategy for future trunk roaddevelopment beyond the present road programme and suggests, for public discussion, a network of national routes which might be selected for improvement to a high standard throughout their length.2.     These national routes are the direct responsibility of theMinister of Transport who is the highway authority for trunk roads inEngland (whether they are motorways or ordinary all-purpose roads).The network at present covers over 5,.900 miles of road.   In.Scotlandand in Wales roads are the responsibility of the. Secretaries of State\ for Scotland and Wales respectively.   Future highway proposals for wales are described in the White Paper &quot;Wales:    The Way Ahead&quot;(CMND.3334) published in July 196? and proposals for Scottish roadswill be published shortly.    The proposals for Scotland and Wales will,mesh in with the strategy for English roads outlined in this paper.The Present Road Programme],    During the 1960s and for the first few years of the 1970s the road(i)    the establishment of a much needed basic network of high quality routes - mostly motorways - to provide the vitalaccess between regions and between the major cities;(ii)    the comprehensive development of other important routesserving the needs of shorter distance transport;(iii)    the improvement of a great many routes by specific works atplaces where this is most needed.   These isolated scheme shave had the object of eliminating the worst bottlenecks,programme has had four objectives:-/relieving- 1 -

relieving time-consuming and economically wasteful congestion and meeting regional development needs;    and(iv)    to devote a substantial and growing part of the programme to road works in urban areas.4.     By the early 1970s, when all the schemes already in the inter-urban programme are finished, we shall have some 1,000 miles of motorwayand 1,000 miles of high-class dual carriageway all-purpose trunk roads,plus a large number of smaller individual trunk road improvements whichhave reduced traffic congestion and accidents.Forward Planning5.     The programme of road building and improvement must continueafter this to meet the rising tide of demand for road space and it willbe important that every road scheme is well planned to fit national and regional needs and that the resources devoted to it are well spent.While the programme can. only go forward at whatever rate the resources-available at the time will permit, it is still necessary to decide,before the present strategy comes to an end in the early 1970s, what sort of pattern of modern highways is needed and how the available resources should be allocated to obtain the best possible economic and social advantages from them.6.     One fact which affects the rate at which.resources for inter-urbanj roads might be available is the competing demand for roads in urban areas.    To the extent that resources for all road works must be kept within certain limits for reasons of over-riding-national economic importance, the plans for inter-urban roads must make allowance forthe increasing need for road improvements in urban areas.    This paper/ does- 2 -

I . -   &apos;does not attempt to discuss the very difficult problem of urban roadswhich needs to be considered in the context of travel needs and physical planning.    This is being examined in land use/transportationstudies in the conurbations and similar studies in other towns andcities.    It is intended to provide for an increased programme of urban road building to ensure that the needs of towns and cities canbe met as well as those for inter urban roads as put forward in this paper.7.     The Ministry of Transport has already taken action to ensurethat a large number of new highway schemes will be at an advanced stage of design and preparation ready to follow on the existing programme in the early 1970s.8.     The first step in selecting these schemes was to assess in asmuch detail as possible the conditions that would ^xist by 1980, on each of the 2,000 or so sectors of trunk road in England, if nothingwere done beyond the improvements already in the programme.    Presentconditions were known and future traffic growth was estimated, taking into account such things as the changed travel patterns that would arise from the growth and redistribution of population, including theestablishment of new towns and development of existing ones.    Byassessing the level of congestion and accidents that would be causedby 19801 traffic on each stretch of road, it was possible to identifythose sections where the worst conditions would occur and which,therefore, appeared to justify first priority.   However, before deciding whether investment in a particular scheme represents goodvalue for money it is necessary to assess with some accuracy the costof the improvements needed and the benefits they offer including any/special- 3 -

I special regional benefits there may be.   A large number of schemes are therefore being prepared to a point where reliable cost/benefitevaluation can be undertaken.   Well over  500 million worth of such1 schemes have been announced for preparation and others will followI until an initial pool of  1,000 million worth of schemes have beenchosen for evaluation.I The Benefits of Road Improvement9.     The direct economic benefits derived from a road improvementscheme can be measured by calculating the savings in time, operatingI costs and accidents;    the values attributed to them added togetherj give the total direct benefits over a period of time and these canbe expressed as a percentage of the capital cost to give a rate ofI return on investment.    The rates&apos;of return for most inter-urban schemes,1 calculated in this way, are very high.1-10.   In addition -. to the direct economic benefits there are othersI &apos;! which flow from the construction of new and improved roads.    these include benefits of commercial value like regularity in deliveryI leading to lower stock holding, the use of larger and faster vehiclesI suited to better roads and particularly the stimulation of new industrial development that would not otherwise have occurred.    These,too, will be given weight in assessing new road schemes..111.   The benefits, derived from isolated improvement schemes are.largely confined to those which arise on the length of road concerned and its immediate environment.   Where, however, it is possible toimprove a route comprehensively throughout its length or to provide&apos; a new high standard route to take the traffic from a number of existingroads, additional benefits arise, mainly from the concentration of the/longerI - 4 - &apos;

longer distance traffic on the new route.    The attraction of suchroutes is demonstrated by the much higher rate of traffic growth onthe motorways compared with other inter-urban roads and in the steadygrowth on the motorways compared with other inter-urban roads and inthe steady growth of traffic on comprehensively improved roads likethe A.1.   What is not always so clear is that these routes, also havethe effect of relieving the roads which formerly carried the traffic to a degree which enhances their value very considerably.    For example,the transfer of the heavy streams of longer distance vehiclesfacilitates the circulation of local traffic on essential localbusiness.    There is thus a strong case for basing a future highwaystrategy on the careful selection of roads for comprehensive improve- ,sent rather than upon a series of isolated improvements to the mostcongested lengths of the trunk roads network.    It would relievetraffic congestion on these roads but do so as part of a consciousplan to direct the traffic to a more effective network of routes.    Thisoan be achieved by considering routes as a whole and by studying thepossibilities of developing new routes as well as improving existingtones to cope with future traffic needs.    Successful regional or localtransport plans demand advance knowledge of the sort of major highwayslihich are likely to exist in 20 or 30 years time.   A comprehensiveroute strategy would provide it.    It would also provide the sort offorward information which industrial and commercial interests willIfind invaluable in planning the future of their businesses.She Proposed Strategy12.   The Ministry^ proposal is that a substantial part of the futurePad programme should be concentrated on the comprehensive development.  /of a- 5 -

of a number of carefully selected trunk routes of major importanceto the country which would progressively complement the 1 ,000 milemotorway network.    These routes when completed,&apos; together with themotorway network and other routes already raised to a high standard,would provide the country with a main system of high class roads to  -which all important centres of population - existing and projected -would, or Could, easily be connected.Choosing the Network13.    The Ministry have given very careful thought to assessing theextent and pattern of the network of routes on&quot;which future resources should mainly be concentrated.    Their assessment is shown in the enclosed maps.    The routes marked in blue represent new.roads whichwill have been completed and existing roads which will have been improved when the existing programme is complete.   Routes marked, inred are those which in the Ministry&apos;s estimation should becomprehensively improved to form together with the blue routes,  themain national network.    It is emphasized that the Maps do not attemptto show the improvements which will also be taking place on other-trunk roads or on the complex of local authority roads serving all areas of the country.H.    This network, put forward by the Ministry for consideration, isbased in the first place on an objective assessment of inter-urbantraffic needs in the 1970s and early 1980s.   It takes full accountof all the facts and estimates available to the Ministry about presentand future traffic needs, accidents, overload and economic loss on every section of trunk road, as well as the latest available traffic/census- 6  -&apos;. -:    . V

,   The proposed strategy does not, however, mean an end to isolatedImprovements.    There will, be many places where new or improved linklads to the network are needed to serve a particular area or wherewere congestion or traffic hazards on other trunk roads will justifyrealised and sometimes fairly extensive roadworks, even though thelad as a whole may not qualify for comprehensive improvement.    TheseMividual improvements cannot be detailed on the maps and the preciseton they would take and their respective priorities can only be decidedoverall planning progresses.    The intention, however, is to continuedevote a significant proportion of total resou.rces to deal withich situations and it is envisaged that over  600 million will bepent in this way in addition to the sums devoted to comprehensivee improvements.-&apos; /Economic- 7 -census figures.    Particular attention has also been paid to the needsof industrialists and exporters and to planned changes in the pattern of industry and population.15, The precise standard of these road improvements and their actualalignment will be determined as detailed planning proceeds.   Many will undoubtedly be built as motorways. &apos; In other cases new or improvedhigh, standard all-purpose trunk roads will offer the best solution,lit the Ministry.envisage that dual-carriageway roads will be providednail cases.   On this basis it is estimated that the proposedstwork shown in red on the enclosed Maps would cost about  1,600llion to complete at present day prices.ink Roads and Localised Improvements &apos;

Economic Growth17.   A national highway strategy must be considered in the light of .the important contribution, it can make to national and regional economic growth.   Wherever major routes are built they provide aneconomic stimulus to the areas through which they pass and to those,distant areas brought into closer contact with the nation&apos;s maineconomic centres.   Greater accessibility, reduced transport costs,improved reliability of delivery and service, reduced storage anddepot needs all increase the ability of any area successfully to developits economic activities and make it more attractive to industry and business.    In particular, roads can substantially reinforce the majormeasures the Government are already taking to ensure a better balance in economic development throughout the country.   It has been acomparatively straightforward matter to take account of the effect on traffic volumes, vehicle ownership and economic activity which, willflow from existing plans for regional development and. the associatedgrowth and redistribution of population.     This is reflected in theproposed, strategic route network and it will be seen from the map,for example, that all the New Towns so far designated will be wellserved by the network.    In subsequent proposals for regional and localroad construction linked to this network, full account will be taken of the wider economic and Social benefits that connection to the network can provide especially in areas where economic stimulusis particularly needed.&apos;8t  Roads are also key elements in the long-term planning strategies&quot;hich are being prepared for each region with the advice of the Regional/Economic- - 8 -

oEconomic Planning Councils.    The national routes which traverse a region and the other roads which meet regional and local needs,including those to New Towns and to areas subject to major economicchange such as the Special Development Areas, must all the considered together and integrated into a comprehensive regional road programme which will ensure maximum economic growth.Economic Appraisal and Standard of Construction19.   A new and more advanced technique for appraising the directeconomic benefit of highway networks has been developed in the ministry and is in course of being applied in a way which will permit comparisonsto be made of the economic value of substantial road networks,including comparisons between alternative networks for the trunk road system as a whole.    It will also permit the value of a system of comprehensive improvements to be compared with chat of a similaramount of unconnected works, to establish the additional benefits whichmight flow from the former.    The method is described in the Appendix.Priorities and Tlrnescale20.   It is neither necessary nor desirable at this stage of planning to attempt to decide on the order of priority for the improvementsproposed within, the broad strategy.    This will emerge in the courseof detailed planning and the publication of the present proposals willin no way replace the normal processes of scheme selection and negotiation with local authorities and other interested parties - nor,Q  course, the statutory procedures.    The intention is to retainat this early stage the maximum flexibility of choice about the priority of individual; routes and schemes. ./21.- 9 -   -&apos;&quot;

- TO -CONFIDENTIAL/T.U.C.( -21.    This flexibility also applies to the plan as a whole even afterthe network has been agreed.   It will be possible bo modify the network if this is shown to be desirable in the light of future developments.    It is to be expected that proposals will be made fromtime to time for additions to the network,  (e.g.    for new links tocarry traffic to the roads in the network) rather than for its radicalrevision.    If these are substantiated and agree.&apos;&quot;! their implementationbecomes a matter of priorities in the manner set out in the previous paragraph.22.    As to timing, any forecast made now can only indicate the approximate order of time and must therefore be related to a span ofyears.   As indicated in earlier paragraphs the Ministry envisage thatto carry out the comprehensive improvements now proposed and at thesame time to undertake a substantial amount of work on other inter-urban roads would.cost in all some  2,250m. over a period of 10 to 15years from 1.972.Public Participation23.   As stated in the Foreword, the primary purpose of this green paper is to invite public discussion of the Ministry&apos;a proposed highwaystrategy and the suggested strategic network shown in the enclosedmaps.   In particular, the Minister is inviting those organisationswhose standing and interest in the planning of roads is of special importance (like the Regional Economic Planning Councils and the localauthorities) to let him have their comments:    also those which representthe road users, the hauliers, the passenger vehicle operators, themotorists..and the cyclists.   He is asking for the views of thoseorganisations with a more general but important interest (e.g.    the

- 11 -T.U.C. and the C.B.I.) and is also open to receive those of anyother institution or organisation and of individual members of thepublic.    The opinions and proposals received will be carefullyevaluated u3ing, where appropriate, the appraisal techniques described above. ; &apos;:?24.    The plan in this Green Paper is not a proposal containing orbased upon firm design proposals for individual roads.    What is being put forward for consideration is a broad strategic plan.    The detaileddesign and location of particular improvements -will emerge in thenormal course and the usual facilities will then be provided for public inspection of. proposals and intervention.    The publication ofthis network is intended to provide the opportunity to influence broadplanning at the earliest possible stage.Conclusion25.    When the appraisal of the networks and comments and suggestionsreceived by the Ministry has been completed and tested, the minister will announce the firm route network which will be the basis of the strategy.   Much will depend on the public response to this paper butthe present intention is to announce the plan before the end of 1969.
















</content>
</cab>
