<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/58/0 images: 133-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
rX)CuMENT IS THE PROPERTX &quot;OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).0 R E T. COPY NO:_V !5^E* CABINET    59 (28).MEETING OP THE CABINET to bo held at 10, Downing StreetrS JiUl... on WEDNESDAY, JULY 18TH, 1928, at a.m.AGENDA.1.      STABILISATION OF WAR PENSIONS.(Reference Cabinet 36 (28) Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the Minister of Pensions.(CP. 208 (28) - already circulated).Report of Departmental Conference,(CP. 236 (28) - already circulated).2.      FOREIGN AFFAIRS - IF REQUIRED.3.      PROTECTION OP BRITISH TRAWLERS ON THE MURMAN COAST.Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs,(CP. 295 (28) - circulated herewith).THE BASIS OF SERVICE ESTIMATES.(Reference Cabinet 34 (28) Conclusion 6 (a)).Npte by the Secretary, covering CommitteeOf Imperial Defence Papers,(CP. 232 (28) - already circulated).5.      THE POST OFFICE AND TELEGRAPHS (MONEY) BILL.Note by the Postmaster-General covering DraftBill and White Paper,(CP. 238 (28) - circulated herewith).6.      BEAM V? IRE LESS AND CABLE COMPANIES .(Reference Cabinet 37 (28) Conclusion 4 (c)).Note by the Secretary, covering Version for publication of Report ojf the Imperial wireless and Cable Conference.(CP. 225 (28) - already circulated;).
7.      THE USE OF GAS IN THE SUPPRESSION OF CIVIL DISTURBANCES.Memorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State for War,(CP. 228 (28) - already circulated).Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal,(CP. 237 (28) - already circulated).8.      THE INDIAN STATUTORY COMMISSION.(Reference Cabinet 36 (28) Conclusion 7).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India,(CP. 231 (28) - already circulated).9.      THE &quot;NO TAX&quot; MOVEMENT IN THE BARDOLI TALUKA, BOMBAY.(Reference Cabinet 37 (28) Conclusion 10).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India,(CP. 229 (28) - already circulated).10.    THE PUBLIC WORKS LOANS BILL.Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury, covering Draft Bill,(CP. 224 (28) - already circulated).11.    THE ISLE OF MAN (CUSTOMS) BILL.Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury, covering Draft Bill,(CP. 233 (28) - already circulated).(Signed)   M.P.A. HANKEY,Se eretary, Cab inet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1.July 17th.. 1928 4
DOCUMENT IS TEE PROPBRTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT).Copy No.CABINET   59 (28).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,18th July, 1928, at 11,30 a.m.PRESENT:-The Eight Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (In the Chair).e Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.II.P., Secretary of State for&apos;Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.H.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.he Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forIndia.[he Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O.,H.P., Secretary of State forScotland.the Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.lie Right Hon.W.E. Guinness, D.S,0.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.ie Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.The Earl of Balfour, K.G.,O.H., Lord President ofthe Council.The Host Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C,V,0,,C.B.,Lord Privy Seal.The right  Hon.Sir William Joynson-HIcks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary of statefor Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-evans bt.,G.B. ti&apos;.,M.P,, Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon. sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.The Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,First Commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Lord Cushendun, Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:-Major The right  Hon.G.C. Tryon, M.P.,Minister of Pensions.(For Conclusion 3).
INTERNALTRANSPORT.ProposedEnquiry into(previous reference:Cabinet 29(28)    Con-conclusion 7.)1,   The Prime Minister read to the Cabinetthe suggested composition and Terms of Referenceto the proposed Royal Commission on Transport:-The Right Hon. Sir Arthur Griffith-Boscawen (Chairman) *Major The Hon.John Astor, M.P,The Earl of Clarendon.Major H.E,Crawfurd, M.P.,Sir Ernest Riley, K.B.E.,Mr J. Learmonth.Sir William Lobjoit, O.B.B.Alderman Frederick Montague, M.P.The Marquess of Northampton.Major Salmon,  C.B.E., M/T?Mr W.R.Smith.Sir Matthew Gemmill Wallace, Bart.TERMS OF REFERENCE.To take into consideration the problems arising out of the growth of road traffic and, with a view to securing the employmentof the available means of transport in GreatBritain (including transport by sea coastwiseand by ferries) to the greatest publicadvantage, to consider and report what measures, if any, should be adopted fortheir better regulation and control, and,so far as is desirable in the public interest,to promote their co-ordinated working anddevelopment.The Cabinet agreed to the proposedmembership and Terms of Reference,and that the-Minister of transport should announce it in the House ofCommons,
INDUSTRIALTRANSFERENCEBOARD.(previous reference:Cabinet 36(88), Con-cliision 5.)2. The Prime Minister informed his colleagues that the Labour Party had wished to move a vote of Censure in regard to the Unemployment policyof the Government.   They had now agreed to raisethe question on a Supply day and desired to take it on tuesday next, July 24th.   Fe intended, ifpossible, to obtain a postponement.   It was,however, highly desirable that the Cabinet shouldhave a full discussion on the question of Uhemploy-ment as soon as possible, with a view to decidingtheir policy before the Debate.   He hoped, there-fore, that the Cabinet Committee would do its best to report before Tuesday July 24th, on which datehe would like to hold a Meeting of the Cabinet.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the question of holding aMeeting of the Cabinet on Tuesday,July 24th, either in the morningor the afternoon, should be leftto the Prime Minister to decide onMonday, July 23rd, in accordancewith the progress made by the CabinetCommittee:(b) That the Report of the industrial transference Board should not bepublished until the Cabinet had decided their policy.
inSTABILISATION0p WAR PENSIONS(previous reference:Cabinet 36(28),  Con-oTusion 4 .)3. The Cabinet again considered the questionof the Stabilisation of War Pensions, and had before them the Memorandum by the Minister ofPensions (Paper C.P.-808 (28); which had been before the-- at their previous Meeting, togetherwith the Report of a Departmental Committee(Paper CP.-236 (28)) regarding the possible effect of the stabilisation of War Pensions uponpost-War pensions in the Fighting Services.    Thegeneral conclusion of the Inter-departmental conference was that the stabilisation of WarPensions should not in any event entail any additional expenditure on the part of the service departments.The Secretary of State for War, while notoffering any opposition to the proposals of theMinister of Pensions, warned the Cabinet that difficulties might arise owing to the fact thatex Army Officers were being treated differentlyfrom the men, insomuch as the pension of theformer varied in accordance with the cost of1 living, though this did not, apply tot he rank and file.The Cabinet agreed  To approve the proposals of theMinister of Pensions set forth in Paper CP.-208 (28) for apermanent stabilisation of thepresent rates of pension and other allowances and grants so far asthey are expressed to be dependenton the cost of living, accompaniedby certain conditions to safeguard our future liabilities .
the racecourse betting bill.(previous reference f er ene e:Cabinet 57(28), Con-clusion 1.)4.   After hearing a statement from theChancellor of the Exchequer on the measures he proposed to take in regard to the Betting Taxif the Racecourse Betting Bill should become law,the Cabinet agreed  That Mr Churchill should take anearly opportunity to make thefollowing statement in the Houseof Commons:-It is not practicable to substitute ascheme of graded licences in the presentFinance Bill, but I am prepared to con-sider carefully the possibility of doing so next year.   As an interim measure of relief, should the Race-Course Betting Billbecome law I propose to modify the schemeof the Duty so as to double the presentcharge for certificates and to reduce theexisting rates from 2% to 1% on the course and from Zi$ to 2% elsewhere.   amendments to effect the reductions in rates will beput down on the Report Stage of the finance bill to take effect from the 1st October,but as any proposal to increase the charge for certificates would involve the re-committal of the Bill I do not contemplate that the increase from  10 to  20 shouldoperst e before next year, and itmight be that it woiild be superseded by anew scheme of graded licences.   The reduc-tion of rates will involve a surrender ofrevenue of  lj millions this year as corn-pared with the Budget estimate, but it isclear that that estimate will not berealised if the present rates are main-tained.
EGYPT. 5. Referring to the discussion at the Cabineton the subject ot Egypt at the Meeting referred(previous reference: to in the margin, the Secretary of State for cabinet 37(28), Con- Foreign Affairs formally drew the attention of elusion 5.)his colleagues to his Despatch No .718 to lord lloyd describing his conversation with HafizAfifi, the new Egyptian Foreign Minister.
TEE UNITEDSTATES of America .The Multi-lateralTreaty.(previous reference e:Cabinet 38(28), Oon-concluslon 2.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that the reply to  heUnited states of America in regard to theproposed Multilateral Treaty, approved at theprevious Meeting for circulation to the Dominions,had subsequently been altered in the circumstancesmentioned in the Note he had circulated to theCabinet (Appendix 1^.A copy of the Note as sent to the Dominionsafter the approval of each member of the cabinet had been obtained Is attached in Appendix II.Sir Austen Chamberlain further informed theCabinet that the same morning he had handed tothe Charge&apos; d&apos;Affaires of the United States ofAmerica in London our own reply and those ofAustralia, New Zealand, South Africa and India.The American Charge d&apos;Affaires had expressedthe view that the replies ought to have afavotirable reception in Washington.   Sir austen chamberlain afterwards, in conversation with theCharge&apos; d5Affaires, had stated that he welcomed the American proposal, first because he was always glad to co-operate with the United Statesof America in any matter, and, second, because he was specially glad to observe the renewedinterest of the United States of America in maintaining the peace of the world.   He hadfarther pointed out that the result would depend on what the United States of America didin the event of some nation breaking the Treaty.If they merely adopted an attitude of reprooftowards the aggressor, not much progress wouldhave been made;   but if they refused to give any sort of aid to an aggressor then, in his view,
Mr Kellogg would have made a great contributionto the peace of the world.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairsalso gave the Cabinet a summary of the Belgianacceptance of the American Note, in which stresswas laid on the importance to Belgium of maintain-ing the Covenant and the Locarno Treaties.
cabinet procedure.(previous reference:Cabinet 6(28), Con-clusion 16.)7.   The Prime Minister alluded to thedifficulty which had been encountered by theCabinet Office and the Foreign Office in communi-cating with members of the Cabinet on the previous friday evening, when, on receipt of the French note, it had been necessary, as a matter of great urgency, to obtain their views in regard to the revised reply by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to the American proposals forthe renunciation of war.    He asked each o^ hiscolleagues to give Instructions to his private secretary, at week-ends or on other occasions when Ministers were leaving! London, to notifyhis address (including any changes in address)to the Cabinet Office, in order that, in caseof emergency, any necessary communication couldbe irade with the least possible delay.The Cabinet agreed to this proposal,and the Secretary was instructed tocommunicate with the Private Secre-tarie3 of Cabinet Ministers .
8. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that the Tangier agreement had been initialled on the previous day.   It didnot remove all the difficulties, but wouldconsiderably ease the situation.   Above all,its usefulness was greatly enhanced by the adherence of Italy,   He mentioned the arrange-ments that were being discussed for the signature of the Treaty by M, briand, te^Primo de Rivera,M. Mussolini and himself.
RUSSIA.protection ofBritish Trawlerson the MurmanCoast.(previous reference:Cabinet 25(33), Con-elusion 6.)9.   The Cabinet had before them-a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(Paper C,P.-235 (28)) raising, by arrangement with the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries,the question of what, if any, protection shouldbe afforded to trawlers on the Murman coast,and covering a Memorandum, containing alternative suggestions.theAfter examining various suggestionscontained in the Secretary of State&apos;s Memorandum,the Cabinet inclined to the view that the choicerested between adherence to the previd.us warningagainst fishing in the Murman coast outside the3-mile limit but within the 12-mile limit, andthe sending of an armed escort capable of pro-tec ting the trawlers and with orders to protect them outside the 3-mile limit, if necessary,as was done before 1923.The Cabinet agreed  That, in order to give time tothe members of the Cabinetgenerally, and in particular tothe First Lord of the admiralty and the Secretary of State forScotland, who were closely con-cerned, the final decision shouldbe postponed until the following week.
THE BASISOff service estimates.(previous reference:Cabinet 24(28), Oon-elusion 6(a).)Anti-aircraft guns for th&quot;Fleet.10.The Cabinet had before th.em a Note by theSecretary (Paper G.P.-352 (28)) covering thefollowing documents on the subject of the Basisof Service Estimates:-A Note by the Secretary to theCoimnittee of Imperial Defencesummarising previous decisions on the subject (C.I.D. Paper No.892-B):An Extract from the Minrtes ofthe 2S6th Meeting of the Committeeof Imperial Defence held on July5, 1928, containing the followingr ec omraendations: -(i) That it should be assumed,for the purpose of framing the Estimates of the Fight-ing Services^ that ab &amp;r.ygiven date there will be no major war for ten years.(ii) That this assumption shouldbe reviewed annually by theCommittee of Imperial Defencebefore the Estimates of theFighting Services are drawnup, that is to say, not later than the month of 0&apos;ane, andthat it shall be the duty ofthe Secretary of the Committeeof Imperial Defence to remind the Prime Minister of this conclusion at the appropriate moment and take his ins true-tlons as to placing the subject on the Agenda Paper of theCommittee.(iii) That it shall be the duty ofany Department in His Majesty&apos;sGovernment In Great Britain,no less than the right of theGovernment of any Dominion,to ask the Committee of ImperialDefence to review the aboveConclusion at any other time if, In the opinion of any oftheaa, the circumstances had8 0 changed as to render its application to the then existing conditions doubtful.A Note by the Secretary (Paper C.P.-240(28)) on the subjeot of Anti-aircraft guns for the Fleet, covering an agree-ment reached between the Admiralty andthe Treasury on the subject of the pro-vision of anti-aircraft gun3 for theFleet.
i   iThe Cabinet took note of and approved  (a) The recommendations of the Committeeof Imperial Defence at the 236thMeeting, referred to above:    and(b) The agreement reached between theAdmiralty and the Treasury on thesubject of the provision of anti-aircraft  uns for the Fleet, asset forth in Paper C.P.-240 (28).
fe^ postnfpXOB ANDSubgraphsfjlONEf) BILL,1928.(previous reference:1 Cabinet 6,i (28), Con-[ elusion 8 &amp;j Appendix.)11. The Cabinet had before them a Note by thePostmaster-General (Paper cp .-238 (28)) covering a draft Post Office and Telegraphs (Money) Bill,together with an Explanatory Memorandum,    Inthis Memorandum it was explained that the objectof the Bill was to obtain Parliamentary authorityfor the issue of advances for capital expenditurerequired for the Postal and Telegraph systems(the capital expenditure on which had hitherto been borne on the Votes) as well as for the telephone systems.   The Bill would authorise theissue of  27,500,000, of which it was estimated 25,000,000 would be required for the telephone service and  2,500,000 for the Postal and &quot;&quot;elegra-phic services .   It was anticipated that this sum,when added to the unexpended balance of 4,200,000 available as at the 30th June fromthe previous Act, would meet the capital require-ments up to the 31st March, 1931.The Cabinet approved the intro-duction in the House of commons of the Post Office and Telegraphs(Money) Bill.
fgg^yr WIRELESSIAND CABLEOCMPANIBS .(previous ousRefer once;Cabinet 3.7(28)    Con-elusion 4(c).)12.In accordance with a decision at their previous Meeting, the Cabinet had before thema version of the Report of the Imperial wireless and Cable Conference which had been prepared with a view to publication (Paper CP.- 25 (28))The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the above Report for publication as a White Paper assoon as the replies from theDominions were received:(b) That there should be a Debate onthe subject in the House of commons before Parliament rises.-14-
wjS USE OP GASra THE suppression-SXON OP CIVILDISTURBANCES .(previous reference:Cabinet 25(28), Con-elusion 1(f).)15.The Cabinet had before them the following documents in regard to the use of gas in the suppression of civil disturbances:-A Memorandum, by the Secretary ofState for War (Paper 0oF.-228 (28))stating that the General OfficerCommanding in Egypt had put forward for consideration a proposal forthe use of Tear Gas by Britishtroops for the dispersal of largehostile gatherings should troublearise in Egypt, and summarising the previous history of the ques-tion and stating the arguments forand against the proposal:A Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal(Paper C.P.-237 (28)) urging, thatthis was not the moment when any decision for the us-e of gas in thecase of civil disturbance could becontemplated.In the course of the discussion attention was drawn to the difference between the lachryma-tory gases which had been used-in the UnitedStates for Police purposes and the lethal gaseson which so much stress had been laid in the debate a few days before in the House of Lords.The Cabinet were reminded that during theGeneral Strike the Secretary of State for war had been given authority by the Cabinet to issue instructions to the General Officers Commandingpermitting the use of &quot;Tear&quot;gas in any case wherea situation became so serious- as to involve thealternative between that course &quot;and the use of firearms (Cabinet 25 (26), conclusion (f)).One suggestion was that the pub?ic would require a good deal of education before such distinctionscould be made;    another suggestion in the same order was that,  in order to bring the distinctionhome to the public, a different nomenclature
us-should be adopted for the two kinds of gas;a third suggestion was that when the questionnext came up for discussion internationally,either at Geneva or at the Washington Conference,the use of lethal gases might be barred, an exception being made in the case of lachrymatorygases.   On the whole, the Cabinet inclined tothe view that the moment was inopportune foropening the question in any form, althoiigh itwas a matter which might well be taken up by theGovernment in office after the next GeneralElection.
^ indianstatutoryMission.(previous reference:Cabinet 36(28), Con-elusion 7.)14. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for India (Paper C.P.-231 (28)) in regard to a proposal by the viceroy to amend the Warrant o* the Indian statutory commission so as to authorise the Commission toco-opt 7 persons who may have been recommendedby the Indian Legislature to be associated withthem throughout their Inquiry, and to directthese 7 persons to write and sign a Report tothe Ring   thus giving a different .status tothe Committee which it had always been intended that the Indian Legislature should set up.   LordSirkenheadTs Memorandum covered correspondenceon the subject, in the course of which theViceroy had in effect  appealed to the Cabinet toconsider favourably hi3 proposal, which hadalready been rejected by th^ Secretary of state in a telegram dated June 20th which-had been circulated to the Cabinet.    The Secretary of Stateasked the Cabinet to approve a draft telegram to the Viceroy which was also attached to his memorandum, giving reasons for rejecting thepropos al.After a statement by the Secretary of Statefor India, the Cabinet approved the terms of thedraft telegram attached to Paper C.P.-231 (28)).
INDIA .The &quot;No Tax&quot;Movement inthe BardoliTaluka, Bombay.(previous reference:Oabinet 37(28), Con-clusion 10) .15. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for India (Paper C.P.-229 (28)) covering further correspondence inregard to the &quot;No Tax&quot; movement in the BardoliTaluka, Bombay.The Secretary of State for India informed the Cabinet that he had not yet heard what happened at the conference between the Viceroy ofIndia and the Governor of Bombay, nor had he heardthe results of the Deputation headed by Mr Patelwhich was to be received by the Governor of bombay.   He proposed to keep the Cabinet informedo-f further developments.-18-
mHB FJBLICLOANS BILLWORKS(previous reference cabinet 3(28), conclusion 4.)16.   The Cabinet had before them a Menoran-dura by the Financial Secretary to the Treasury(Paper CP.-224 (28)) covering, and asking for authority to introduce during the present Session,the Public Works Loans Bill.The Prime Minister said he had been givento understand that the Bill could be postponed until November or December, in which case thenew Bill would enable the Government to carry onuntil after the General Election.   He would therefore prefer to take the Bill in the newSession6f Parliament.The Cabinet agreed  That the matter should be dealtwith by the Prime Minister, inconsultation with the Chancellorof the Exchequer .
the isle op man(&quot;customs) bill.(previous reference:Cabinet 3(38),  Con.elusion 4.)17.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Financial Secretary to the Treasury(Paper C.P.-233 (28)) covering and giving explain-nations regarding the Annual Bill confirming theCustoms Resolutions of the Manx Legislature,and asking for authority to introduce and proceedwith the Bill at once.The Cabinet approved the intro-duction in the House of commons of the Isle of Man (Customs) Bill.
WESTERN 18.The Seeretary of State for Scotland broughtSHLANDSREAMER to the notice of &quot;the Cabinet, as a matter ofSRYTCES.-urgency, a Memorandum (Paper C.P.-241 (28)) inregard to the Western Highlands Steamer Services.This Memorandum dealt with a scheme which hadbeen laid before the Select Committee of theHouse of Commons on behalf of the L.M.S. RailwayCompany and Coast Lines, Limited, under which those Companies would jointly undertake theservices hitherto performed by contract with theG-overnment by Messrs David MacBrayne, Limited.Particulars were given both of the new proposal and of the MacBrayne Agreement.   The proposal ofthe L.MCS. Railway Company, however, was subjectto a condition that they should be absolved ofall cost of obtaining any powers necessary toenable them to co-operate in the undertaking,and as the Select Committee&apos;s further proceedingswould depend on the decision of this point theSecretary of State asked, as a matter of urgency,whether his colleagues would authorise him to saythat the Companies would be absolved of the costs of obtaining powers if a scheme involving legisla-tion should ultimately be agreed upon.The Secretary of State for Scotland informed the Cabinet that he could not give an exactestimate of the amount of the costs involved,but from such enquiry as he had been able to makeit appeared to lie between  500 and  2,000,according to the extent of the opposition.The Cabinet approved the proposal ofthe Secretary of State for Scotland,provided that -
(a) The Bill is so limited as tosecure the Company no generalshipping (or air) powers as contemplated by them at onestage;(b) The legal expenditure ofthe Company be subject to the prior consent of the Secretaryof State for Scotland, so as toprevent extravagance in selectionor payment of Counsel, etc;and(c) The expenditure under theproposal be a first charge onprofits over 5 per cent.-2 2-
REDUCTIONAMD LIMITA-TION of armaments .(previous reference:Cabinet 36(28), Con-clusion 2.)19.   The Lord Privy Seal reminded theCabinet that before they separated it would benecessary to approve instructions for the Chanftlorof the Duchy of Lancaster, who in August would beattending further meetings of the PreparatoryCommission prior to meetings ofr-the Assembly ofthe League of Nations at Geneva. &quot; At a meetingof the -Sub-Committee -of the Committee of ImperialDefence on the previous day he had learned thetenor of the French reply to the request that theFrench Government should confirm certain proposals made on his own responsibility by the French naval representative on the Preparatory Commission.At first sight the reply appeared promising.Lord Salisbury added that, after a further meetingof&quot;the Committee of Imperial Defence Sab-Committee,he proposed to hold a meeting of the CabinetCommittee on Disarmament Policy on the following monday, and he would like to know whether theCabinet would like the Committee to take the-responsibility for dealing with these questionsor whether they would like to reserve the final-decision to -themselves.&quot;The-Cabinet asked that the Cabinet-Committee on Policy might report&apos; to them at &quot;their next regular--- weekly Meeting.a* &quot;Whitehall Gardens, .S.W.1,July 18, 1928. --2 3-
APPENDIX   I.NOTE BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN-^-^X;3TgT--TREATY FOR THE RENUNCIATION OF WAR.I have now received (very confidentially under cover of a letter from M. Fromageot to Sir cecil Hurst) the actualterms in which the French Government propose to reply to theUnited States.In Sir Cecil Hurst*s report on the meeting of Juristsit was stated - &quot;it is, however, important that the under-standings on which each government accepts the proposed peacepact should be set out in its reply in order that they maybe known to all the governments concerned&quot;,    In the draftapproved by the Cabinet we have discharged this task literallyand have devoted three paragraphs to explaining why we considerthat there is no Inconsistency between the American proposal and Article 16 of the Covenant.     On the other hand the Germanreply treats the point so obscurely that, as I pointed out to theCabinet, no one, and least of all Mr, Kellogg, is likely toperceive that it is there.The French reply is not quite so disingenuous, but itskates very lightly over the thin Ice.     It deals with the pointin two short sentences.     The first sentence (in I 3) statedthat &quot;it results&quot; from the new preamble that &quot;the signatoryPower which may henceforth s^eek, by a personal recourse to war,to promote its own national&apos; interests, will find itself deprived of the benefits of the treaty&quot;.     This wqrding is taken from the text of the preamble with; the exception o\f the words which Ihave underlined.     The second sentence occurs later where thedraft note states that *none of the pr&amp;vi&amp;ions of the new treaty
conflicts with the provisions of the Covenant of the Leagueof Nations.&quot;It is by the deft insertion of the two words underlined -&quot;personal&quot; and &quot;own&quot; - that the French Government considerthat they have given sufficient expression to the &quot;Gaus&quot; inter-pretation, i,e., have safeguarded the case where a Leaguesignatory attacks a League non-signatory.     These words maywell escape general notice.     Mr. Kellogg will certainlyrefrain from challenging them unless he is obliged to do so.In view of the character of the French reply I am clearlyof opinion that it would be a mistake for us to enter into an elaborate argument on a subject which the other Powers havetreated so lightly.     To do so would make it appear thatwe were far harder to please than the Germans or even theFrench and were creating difficulties which those Powers hadnot raised.     We should concentrate upon ourselves the wholeforce of whatever criticism there may be and the proposed treaty might be wrecked upon our note.In these circumstances I advise that our draft shouldbe amended in the form shown on the print which I now circulate afresh.     Sir Cecil Hurst is satisfied thatthis is sufficient and, if sufficient. It is clearly wise.If my colleagues accept this v^ew Immediate notifica-tion of the proposed changes should-be made to theDominions for time presses.     I should be grateful, there*fore, if those of my colleagues whoN agree to the altera-tions would telegraph the single wor*d &quot;Yes&quot; to me at theForeign Office.      If any of them thii$k that the matter should be further discussed I would a*sk them to telegraph&quot;Wait&quot; and in that case I would request? the Prime Ministerto summon the Cabinet on Monday morning.(Initialled)   A-0.Foreign Office,13th July, 1928.
SECRET.The following is a literal translation of the text of the proposed French reply which has just been com-municated very privately by Monsieur Fromageot toSir Cecil Hurst.TRANSLATION.draft of a note to be addressed to the United states ambassador in reply to his note of the 23rd June lastcovering; a now draft of the Renunciation of War Treaty.In your note of the 23rd June last Your Excellencywas good enough to transmit a revised text of the draft treaty for the Renunciation of War, accompanied by theInterpretations which the Government of the UnitedStates propose to give to that document.I request you to be so good as to impress upon theUnited States Government with what great interest theGovernment of the Republic has taken cognisance of thisfresh communication which is of a character to facili-tate the signature of a treaty, the successful conclusionof which is the heartfelt wish of the French nation as well as of the American nation.It follows In the first place from the new Preamblethat the object&apos; of the proposed treaty is to perpetuatethe pacific and friendly relations within the contractual,conditions in which they are to-day established betweenthe interestedriations:   that the essential condition isthat the signatory Powers renounce v^ar &quot;as an instrument of their national policy&quot;; and that further the signatory Power i*hich shall hereafter se^k, by a personal
resort to war, to promote its own national Interests,will be denied the benefits of the treaty.The Government of the Republic is happy to say thatthey are in agreement with these new provisions.The Government of the Republic is happy, furthermore,to take note of the Interpretations which the Governmentof the United States attaches to the new treaty in orderto give satisfaction to the various observations whichhave been formulated on the part of France0These observations may be summarised as follows.Nothing in the new treaty either restricts or corn-promises In any way the right of personal defence.     each nation still remains free in this respect to defend its territory against an attack or an invasion;    that nationalone is competent to decide if circumstances require a recourse to war for its own defence.In the second place none of the provisions of thenew treaty conflicts either with the provisions of theCovenant of the League of Nations or with those of the treaties of Locarno or of the treaties of neutrality.Furthermore, any violation of the new treaty by oneof the Contracting Powers would completely liberate theother Contracting Powers from their obligations towardsthe Power breaking the treaty.Finally, the invitation to sign the treaty which ithas already extended to all the Powers signatory of theActs concluded at Locarno and which It is disposed toextend to the Powers parties t6 the treaties of neutrality,rtogether with the circumstance&apos;that it will be open to the
other powers to accede, is of a nature to give to thenew treaty, in the measure in which this is practicallydesirable, the character of universality which conformsto the views of the Government of the Republic.Thanks to the precisions which have thus been madein the new Preamble and thanks to the interpretationswhich have furthermore been given to the treaty, theGovernment of the Republio is happy to observe that thenew Act can be reconciled with the engagements of existingtreaties to which Prance is also a contracting party and which it is naturally her strict duty fully to respect In all good faith and loyalty.In these circumstances and conditions the Governmentof the Republic is perfectly disposed to sign the treaty as proposed in Your Excellency&apos;s note of the 23rd June,1928.At the moment when the Government of the Republicthus gives the assurance of its contribution to the realisation of a.project which has been long in contemplate-tion and of which it has, since the beginning, realised the full moral significance, it desires to render homageto the generous spirit with which the Government of theUnited States has made this new manifestation of humanfraternity, which conforms fully to the deep aspirations of the French people and of the American people and whichresponds to the sentiment of international solidarityshared ever more and more among the nations.
Foreign Office,sir, July 18, 1928.i am happy to be able to inform you that after carefully studying the note which you left with me on the 23rd june, transmitting the revised text of the draftof the proposed treaty for the renunciation of war, his majesty&apos;s government ingreat britain accept the proposed treaty in the form transmitted by you and willbe glad to sign it at such time and place as may be indicated for the purpose by thegovernment of the united states.my government have read with interest the explanations contained in your noteas to the meaning of the draft treaty, and also the comments which it contains uponthe considerations advanced by other powers in the previous diplomaticcorrespondence.you will remember that in my previous communication of the 19th may explained how important it was to my government that the principle should berecognised that if one of the parties to this proposed treaty resorted to war in violation of its terms, the other parties should be released automatically from their obligations towards that party under the treaty. i also pointed out that respect forthe obligations arising out of the covenant of the league of nations and of the locarno treaties was the foundation of the policy of the government of this country,and that they could not agree to any new treaty which would weaken or underminethese engagements.the stipulation now inserted in the preamble under which any signatory powerhereafter seeking to promote its national interests by resort to war against anothersignatory is to be denied the benefits furnished by the treaty is satisfactory to my government, and is sufficient to meet the first point mentioned in the preceding paragraph.his majesty&apos;s government in great britain do not consider, after maturereflection, that the fulfilment of the obligations which they have undertaken in thecovenant of the league of nations and in the treaty of locarno is precluded bytheir acceptance of the proposed treaty. they concur in the view enunciated by thegerman government in their note of the 27th april that those obligations do not contain anything which could conflict with the treaty proposed by the united statesgovernment.my government have noted with peculiar satisfaction that all theparties to the locarno treaty are now invited to become original signatories of thenew treaty, and that it is clearly the wish of the united states government that all members of the league should become parties either by signature or accession. inorder that as many states as possible may participate in the new movement, i trust that a general invitation will be extended to them to do so.as regards the passage in my note of the 19th may relating to certain regionsoi which the welfare and integrity constitute a special and vital interest forour peace and safety, i need only repeat that his majesty&apos;s government great britain accept the new treaty upon the understanding that it does not prejudice their freedom of action in this respect.i am entirely in accord with the views expressed by mr. kellogg in his speech of the 28th april that the proposed treaty does not restrict or impair in any way4515   [17937]7 atherton, esq.,&amp;c.,    &amp;c,    &amp;c.
the right of self-defence, as also with his opinion that each State alone is competent to decide when circumstances necessitate recourse to war for that purpose.In the light of the foregoing explanations, His Majesty&apos;s Government in GreatBritain are glad to join with the United States and with all other Governmentssimilarly disposed in signing a definitive treaty for the renunciation of war in theform transmitted in your note of the 23rd June. They rejoice to be associated withthe Government of the United States of America and the other parties to theproposed treaty in a further and signal advance in the outlawry of war.I have the honour to be,with high consideration,Sir,Your obedient Servant,ATTSTEN CHAMBERLAIN.

</content>
</cab>
