<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/153/0 images: 17-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(70) 79 COPY NO        g ,j12 October 1970CABINETSTEEL prices note by the Minister of technology, At the meeting of the Ministerial Committee on Economic Policytoday it was agreed that I should not accede to the recommendation of theIron and Steel Consumers1 Council that the British Steel Corporations(bsc&apos;s) decision to increase steel prices by 5 per cent on average shouldbe rescinded.    I propose to announce this in terms of the attachedstatement,2,        Without the present increase the BSC will make a loss thisyear and hence add to their accumulated deficit of  30 million sincenationalisation.    Even with it they will make no more than  20 million and will be unable to make any payment on their public dividend capital(pdc) for the fourth year running.3, The main underlying reasons for this unsatisfactory situation are:-a. The period of poor trading and low prices to mid-1969 which meant that the Corporation ended its first two years (September1967-September 1969) with accumulated losses of over  40 million and outstanding pdc obligations to the Exchequer of at least 90 million,b. Inherited shortages of capacity and, during the past year,major operating difficulties which have severely reduced output and hence profitability at a time of peak demand, despite successiveprice increases.c. Slow progress in reducing manpower through rationalisationand productivity deals, partly on account of the acute labour difficulties last year (of which the Port Talbot strike and the recognition dispute are examples) and partly through the very high steel demand which is causing the Corporation to keepuneconomic plant operating at maximum outputs a more rapidrate of closure of old plant would result in even higher importsof semi-finished or finished products to meet home demand,
d. Cost increases in bought-in materials, including the presentcoking coal increases ( 19 million), as well as for ore, scrap etc.4. Of these b remains especially important and accounts for about four-fifths of the  108 million deterioration since last February in theCorporation^ profit expectations for 1970-71.5.        I am discussing this unsatisfactory situation substantively withthe Chairman and will inform my colleagues of the outcome as soon aspossible, together with my proposed further action.    A major improvementwill be needed not only to reduce the burden on the Exchequer but also to beable to demonstrate in the Common Market negotiations that the BSC is nota vehicle for indirect Government subsidisation of industry.    Officials willbe reporting to the Chancellor and me by the 19th of this month whatfinancial disciplines are necessary.6,        In the meantime an announcement is urgently needed becausedelay costs  1 million a week and we have already gone past the BSCTsintended date for implementation of 1 October.7.        Accordingly, subject to the views of my colleagues, I propose to announce our decision immediately.J DMinistry of Technology SW112 October 19702
STEEL PRICES:    STATEMENT BY MINISTER OF technology the Government has received from the Iron and Steel Consumers1Council a report on the British Steel Corporation^ proposalto increase its prices for steel products &quot;by 5% on average,and on related matters.   The Council recommended that, inaccordance with Section 6(6) of the Iron and Steel Act, 194-9*as revived and amended by the Iron and Steel Act, 1967 ? theCorporation should be directed not to implement the price proposals.The Government, having studied all aspects of the matter, hasdecided that it should not so direct the Corporation, and accordingly the following statement of its reasons is laid beforeParliament.2   The Government welcomes the thorough examination which theCouncil has given to the bsc&apos;s case.   It regards the existenceof an independent and well-informed Consumer Council as animportant safe-guard of consumers&apos; interests and a spur to theefficiency of the nationalised industry;   and it has attachedparticular importance to the Council&apos;s report in reaching its decision.3  However, apart from the consumers&apos; viewpoint, represented bythe Council, the Government must have regard to issues of general economic policy and to the overall financial and commercialsituation of the Corporationi4  On this latter, the Government has had in mind four main considerations.   First, the Corporation^ results for the current year have worsened still further from the estimates made when theproposal was put to the Council:   whereas the Corporation, during august and September, was expecting a profit of  10- 15m in thecurrent financial year on existing prices, it now expects to makea loss on account of continuing operating difficulties.   Second,the Government does not believe that the pressures on the corporation to improve its efficiency will be lessened by the price increase which will give a profit of only  20m in the current year,insufficient to enable the Corporation to offset its accumulated deficit of  30m.   Thirdly, the Government does not accept theCouncil1s suggestion that it should rescind its earlier decisionto permit the increase in coking coal prices amounting to  18m in afull year;   one nationalised industry cannot be allowed to subsidiseanother.   Finally, even with the price increase, UK domestic steel prices will still not compare unfavourably on average with thosein other countries./5   The Government
5   The Government is considering with the Corporation themeans of applying greater financial disciplines to its affairs in the future; and intends to set a statutory long-termfinancial objective to have effect from the start of the corporations next financial year in April 1971-   It is essentialthat the Corporation arrest the current unsatisfactory deterioration-tion in its finances and make every effort to improve itsprofitability by rigorous control of performance and cost saving.6   The Chairman will keep the Government informed of progress at regular intervals including improvements in the Corporation^procedures and plans for controlling costs and maximisingefficiency.7   The Government is also considering the Consumers&apos; Council&apos;suggestion that some diversified activities should be hived off.Ministry of Technology12 October 1970


</content>
</cab>
