<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/153/0 images: 130-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYT3 GOVERNMENT50CP(70) 89 COPY NO16 October 1970CABINETGOVERNMENT INITIATIVE ON MAINTAINING ESSENTIALLOCAL AUTHORITY SERVICESNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister, I am circulating the attached note by officials for consideration by the Cabinet at their meeting on Monday19 October.    The note will be considered by the Official Committee on emergencies during Monday morning; and the results will be reported to cabinet orally.Signed   BURKE trend cabinet Office SY/116 October 1970
LOCAL GOVERNMENT MANUAL WORKERS STRIKEMANPOWER NEEDED TO MAINTAIN ESSENTIAL services memorandum by the Ministry of Housing and LocalGovernment1.     The estimates in this paper are based on the following assumptions(a) sewage disposal works should be kept operating(though at reduced efficiency) where the effluentthey discharge might have some effect on publicwater supplies;(b) pumps in the sewerage system should be keptoperating where there would be flooding ofstreets or houses if they stopped;(c) that refuse should be removed if it becomesstinking and offensive.These considerations have wider effects than rules limitedto strike action which has a significant effect on public .health but they do not include pollution of rivers which maykill fish or make them offensive (rivers which are already ina bad condition will become offensive more quickly than the comparatively clean rivers used for water supply).     Nor dothey cover the mere accumulation of rubbish however large thepiles.2.     Sewage disposalIn England 47 water undertakings are dependent in come degree on water drawn from the lower reaches of rivers.These undertakings have been classified in four categories1
CONFIDENTIAL    .A    where the risk of pollution is high and closure of intakes would cause difficulty in maintainingfull supplies.     4 undertakings with 5 intakesbetween them;B     where the risk of pollution is not high but whereclosure of intakes would cause major supplyproblems.     4 undertakings with 4 intakes;C     where the risk of pollution is not high and whereclosure of the intake would cause some limitedproblems in supply.     17 undertakings and 17 intakesD    where closure of intakes would only lead todifficulty in maintaining supplies in the longterm (e.g. if reservoirs drawn down abnormallycould not be refilled before next Spring.)22 undertakings and a somewhat larger number ofintakes.3.     The Ministry of Housing estimate that to maintain sewage disposal works in operation (as defined in paragraph 1)category A intakes would need57    drivers  .66     craftsmen286    unskilled labourabove category B intakes6575315above category G intakes195   driversdriverscraftsmenunskilled labour205   craftsmen545   unskilled labourabove category D intakes450 drivers450 craftsmen900 unskilled labourthese figures are cumulative (i.e. those for category D arethe total requirement).
confidential.     Sewage- pumping stationsThere are many sewage pumping stations;   it is impossible without contacting all local authorities to identify them andidentification would not disclose those which might fail(many are automatic and will run for a long time unattended).The Ministry of Housing propose that the possibility of pumpfailure be catered for by having 100 mobile units so far aspossible stationed in different parts of the country.     Eachunit consisting of:1   driver1    craftsman3   unskilled labourA total of 100 drivers, 100 craftsmen and 300 unskilled labour.Special arrangements exist (and troops are on stand-by) for london.     These are not included in any of the precedingfigures.5o    Refuse disposalAs with sewage pumping stations refuse disposal can onlybe tackled by mobile teams since it is impossible to forecastwhere help would be needed,     100 mobile units would berequired each consisting of:1   driver2   unskilled labour1   mechanical equipment operatorA total of 100 drivers, 200 unskilled labourers, 100 mechanicalequipment operators.6.     Supervisory StaffSewage disposal works serving large towns are very big,very complex chemical (or more accurately bio-chemical)factories.     They cannot be run without the full and willingco-operation of their managerial staff.     The forcedattendance of the supervisory staff would be of no value.The same is true of the larger pumping stations.     Refusedisposal would be carried out in the absence of co-operation.Supervisory staff have, with some exceptions, tried to keep their works going but it is not possible to say how they wouldre-act to the use of troops.     Their attitude might depend upon the degree to which they were convinced that there was a real emergency.7.     Emergency regulations in the absence of emergency regulations troops (orvolunteers) can only be used to operate local authority plant
CONFIDENTIALif invited by the authority.     It is possible that some localauthorities would be unwilling to ask for assistance.     Ifthis happened Eraergencsr Regulations would have to be made before action could be taken or plant opera/ted.8.     Effect on.Local^Authorities and othersIf at this stage in the dispute troops are used fairlywidely in circumstances where serious danger to public health or water supplies is not involved it is problematical whetherthe result on balance will be to encourage the local authorityemployers to stand firm.     Such action would no doubt bolsterthe resolve of some authorities who are now wavering and strengthen the resolve of those who wish to stand firm in anycase.     It would not however change the views of authorities who for political and other reasons are in sympathy with theUnions8 claim.     Moreover, some authorities, who are at presentfollowing the lead of their national negotiators might find theuse of troops unwelcome because of the serious risk that other staff e.g., supervisors and maintenance workers whose co-operation is essential for the maintenance of service, even if troops areavailable, might withdraw their labour.     This situation wouldbe aggravated by the imposition of troops on unwillingauthorities.     It would also raise further complications, inparticular local authorities resistance might be considerablebecause of the implication for their constitutional and statutory position.9.     It is difficult to gauge how the public would react towardswider use of troops.     Whilst no doubt willing to accept useof troops and volunteers where there is manifest danger to public health or water supplies, or even gross damage to amenitymany people would no doubt take a less sympathetic view of their use if it appeared that a major purpose was not to protect thepublic and maintain essential services, but as a demonstrationto impress the Unions and the authorities of the Government1sdetermination to resist the strike.     Against this background the use of troops would no doubt attract a sharp reaction from most unions and might in the present climate be seen by the tuc as a deliberate attempt by the Government to provoke aconfrontation.     This would have effects on current oranticipated disputes with the following:(a) Mine workers:   now voting on whether or not tohold an official strike;(b) NHS ancillary workers:   who are represented by thesame unions as the local authority manual workers and closely related to their conditions of service;(c) MS electricians;(d) Workers in the Water Supply Industry whose workers are also represented by the same unions as thelocal authority manual workers;(e) electricity supply industry workers.
15.     Local Authorities will, judged by enquiries they havealready made, ask for very much larger numbers than those given above because they tend to think in terms of normaloperation of their works.     The figures in this paper are theMinistry of Housingfs estimate of the minimum numbers reauiredto keep these services operating to the reduced standards and in the limited areas defined in paragraph 1.Ministry of Housing andLocal Government S.W.117 October, 1970.
CONFIDENTIAL10.     Department of Health and Social Security assessmentIf no settlement is reached in local government and the strikes of local authority manual workers continue, there willbe strikes starting after 1st November by N.H.S. hospitalancillary workers who have made a similar claim,they rejected a similar offer to that originally made by the local authorities.DHSS state that these strikes are likely to take place in selected hospitals and in selected departments of hospitals e.g.laundries, portering, stoking, transport, etc.     The assessment of the Health Department&apos;s (EO(70)30; is that the initialrequirement for servicemen   in hospitals would be 1,000 stokers,250 drivers.     Volunteers can &quot;be expected to come forward in response to local appeals from hospitals.     Driving, catering,domestic and portering work would present less difficultiesthan work in laundries or boiler houses.11,     Problems of Ministry., of....defence should there be a requirement for the extensive use of servicemen, it might be impossible to provide the numbers required, particularly of skilled men, without temporarilydegrading our defence capabilities.     These penalties would,therefore, require careful consideration at the time.     also it must be borne in mind that many of the tasks involved arevery unpleasant and are not good for the image of the Services.The possible effects on, for example, Service recruiting shouldbe considered before using servicemen for such tasks as refuseclearance.12.     wales in general there are no water supply intakes sufficientlyclose to sewage works discharges for concern to be felt, andthe effluents are so small a part of river flows as to beinsignificant.     The Welsh Office are preparing figures comparable to those given for England.13.     scotland the Scottish Office are submitting a separate paper.14.     Total manpower requirement for England the Ministry of Housing&apos;s estimate of the manpower needed is:650   drivers550   craftsmen100   mechanical equipment operators forrefuse clearance1,400   unskilled labourersTo this must be added a number, being estimated by the Ministryof Defence for military administration.


</content>
</cab>
