<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/153/0 images: 154-162</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fcS1 ilia %a ij ( C   document IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS government cp(70) 91 COPY NO    g g26 October 1970CABINETAIRCRAFT PROJECTSMemorandum by the Prime Ministerc1, When v/e resume cur consideration of the aircraft industry, mycolleagues might like to bear in mind the following points.PUBLIC EXPENDITURE2, (a)  Civil aircraft projects; estimated costs the latest estimates for future public expenditure on the projects underconsideration are as follows -1970-71 1971*72 1972-73 1973-74 1974-75 1975-76 TOTAL1. RB 211-22        30 30 - - - 60(additional provision ifBAC 311/-61not supported)2, BAC 311/RB 211-51(includingGovernmentshare of theadditionalcost of -22)a. If the Bank     24 37 34 38 27 19 179and privateinstitutionsfind  25 m.for the -221sieiit
1970-71 1971-72 1972-73  1973-74 1974-75 1975-76 TOTALb. If the Bank     19 27 34 38 18 10 146and privateinstitutionsfind  40 m.and rolls royce are able, asthey have offered, tofind  18 m.towards thedevelopmentcost of the-613. Additional       - 0.5 2 5 3 0,5 11cost of developing the-61 for astretchedLockheed4.   Concorde?      52 43 31 21 15 11 174development5, Concorde:        13production(net - bracketsindicate aninflow)24 49 4914 (39)       110Total (lines 0. ,., ,,,, ^.o   o v,     t v\      89 104 U6 113 60 (8)       4742a,3,4 and 5) v &apos;iiNOTES: 1.      Line 1 - Rolls Royce would also be expected to requestadditional launching aid of some  10- 20 million for alimited stretched version of the -22, but no account hasbeen taken of this possibility.2.      Line 2b - The Rolls Royce contribution is speculative.3.      Line 3 - Doubtful starter.4.      Line 4 - These figures are based on an estimate ofdevelopment cost of  800 million at January 1970 prices.This may rise to at least  850 million.
5.      Line 5 - While much of this shculd be recovered in the longterm there Is a strong probability of significant Governmentlosses being incurred on production; BAC and Rolls Royceare insisting on Government indemnities.5,      The Government are at present contributing  3 million a yeartowards Rolls Roycers civil aero-engine research, not onlyon these projects, and the firm have asked for this to beincreased.(b)       Aircraft launching costs; escalationThe following table compares the initial launching cost estimates andoutturn of a number of major recent aircraft and aero-engine projects.Launching Cost  m      % Increase	Initial	Actual or		Estimate	Latest Estimate	VC 10/Super VG 10	36,2	39.5	9%BAC 111/200/300/400	26, 5  	33	28%Trident 1	23.3 p	23.2	NilTSR 2	90	270	200%Nimrod	21.1	24.3	14%Concorde airframe	100	480	380%BAC 311	140 *	NA	NASpey (all civil variants)	32.2 p	33.9	5%Olympus for Concorde	50	320	540%RB 211-22	65. 5*	137.5	110%RB 211-61	60 *	NA	NAOriginal estimates included allowance for cost inflation so the bulk of theincrease shown is in real costs.- i r ...* Original estimate included some allowance for cost inflation, but some ofthe increase is due to unexpectedly fast cost inflation.&quot;*At March 1970 price levels; actual launching aid will be increased to coverwage and material cost escalation.NOTES: 1,      The above figures deal only with launching costsj except inthe case of Concorde/Olympus the Government have not been involved in financing production.
2.      There is no common pattern of over-run.    The mostserious excesses have been in respect of projects involvingsubstantial new technological developments j the -22 engine,like Concorde/Olympus and the TSR 2, fell in this category.The Ministry of Aviation Supply believe that the BAC 311 willnot involve substantial new technological developments, norwill the -61 engine if the -22 is successful.(c) BOAC operating subsidy in addition to the public expenditure cost of development and productionof Concorde, BOAC have estimated that they would lose  3 million a yearper Concorde at first, declining after a few years to  1 million a year.These figures are open to some argument at this stage8 and BOAC mayhave an interest in exaggerating them.    On the other hand, however, it isknown that BOAC based their calculations on an assumed price of$24 million per aircraft, as opposed to the current estimate of $28 million.(d) Other claims on the contingency reserve the following claims for additional public expenditure which are not specifically included in the White Paper estimates and are thereforepossible claims on the unallocated contingency reserves for the next four years have already been identified (the figures are, of course, veryapproximate):  million at 1970 Survey Prices	1971-72	1972-73	1973*74	1974-75Space (post-Apollo)	1	2	8	15Steel: Accelerated				investment	40	40	40	40Thames Barrier (lift-type)	2	6	12	22Electricity (23% margin)	20	35	65	70Power station conversions )		c	i	uCoking coal blending plants)	**	O	i	*-BP rights issue	50		-	Additional family support	-	8	15	15Interim upratings of				Supplementary benefit	-	20	20	20Total113117167182Unallocated contingency reserve(i.e. excluding the agreedprovision for the 1971 and1973 social security upratings)60155210280
SECi&amp;ETThese figures make no provision for possible additional expenditure, atpresent unquantifiable, on assistance to Harland and Wolff, Shorts, andthe Mersey Docks and Harbours Board; nor for that on the development ofcommercial radio,AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY(a)       BAC and Rolls Royce: Companies1 forecasts of current and futureoutput by valueBAC1970 1974BAC 311 4 67Concorde 37 91Other aircraft 72 52(BAG 111, Lightnings, Canberra,Jet Provost, Jaguar, MRCA/Guided Y/weapons 49 43Total 162 253Rolls Royce  m	1970	1974RB 211-22	33	67RB 211-61	Nil	7Olympus	17	65Other civil engines	61	44Military engines	79	113Aero-engine spares, repairs, misc.	99	172installations		Industrial and marine oil engines, cars, etc	64	97Total	353	565(b)       Major European firms: airframeCountry Firm Total EmploymentUnitedKingdomBAC36,800Major ProjectsC ollaborative)* Concorde* Jaguar* MRCABAC 111BAC 311Guided weapons
Country Firm Total EmploymentUnited HSA 31,050KingdomShorts 5,676Westland 7,421AircraftFrance SNTAS 42,000(FormerlySud-AviationNord-Aviation etc)Dassault/ 12,600BreguetGermany Messerschmitt 20,000Bolkow*- Bl ohmMajor Projects(*Collaborative)HarrierBuccaneerNimrodTrident*A300BGuided weaponsSkyvanBelfastParts for -22Other sub-contractwork* Joint Anglo/FrenchhelicoptersOther helicoptersCaravelle* Concorde*Anglo/Frenchhelicopters*Transall*A300B*AtlantiqueMystere etcGuided weapons and aerospaceMirage*JaguarVariable geometryprototypeMystere* Me r cure*Atlantique*MRCA*A300BVTOli projectsF 104 (under licence)*Transall*AtlantiqueHelicopters
Country-GermanyFirm Total EmploymentVFW-Fokker 12,000ItalyDornierFIATNetherlands    Fokker-VFWSwedenSAAB-SCANIA5,0005,500(including those engaged on enginework)3, 0008, 000(onaeronauticaland electronicwork)(c)       Major European firms; aero-enginesUnited Rolls Royce 70,000KingdomF raneeSICE C MA17, 700Major Projects^Collaborative)*Transall*A300B*F23*VFW 514(short-haul jet)Assorted(has withdrawnfrom A300B)*MRCA* Me r cureAssorted*A300BF27 (feeder)*F28 (short-hauljet)*VFW 514 etc*AtlantiqueDrake nViggenSaab 105* Olympus* Ad our (for Jaguar)*RB 199 (for MRCA)RB 211-22RB 211-513pey*M45H (for VFW 614)* Olympus*M45MAtar seriesTurbomeca4, 000* Ad our
Major ProjectsCountry Firm Total Employment        (* Collaborative)Germany MTU 10,000 *RB 199Other projectsalone or in association with R..nicholls RoyceItaly FIAT - *RB 199Other work onlicence from orin association with Rolls RoyceEH  1110 Downing Street SW126 October 1970


</content>
</cab>
