<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/153/0 images: 227-229</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
wjS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(70) 98 COPY NO        5629 October 1970CABINETCABINET BUSINESSNote by the Prime minister have felt on several occasions in recent weeks that memorandahave been presented to the Cabinet without adequate consultation betweenresponsible Ministers and those of their colleagues most directly con-cerned and without a sufficient attempt to resolve differences of opinionor to narrow areas of disagreement by the normal processes of inter-departmental discussion.    I know that we have all been working underabnormally heavy pressure and have been trying to conform to a very-tight timetable which has been largely imposed upon us by events which wedo not control.    Nevertheless, I hope that we may henceforward adopt amore deliberate and considered pattern of working and may, in particular,allow more time for proper discussion between Departments and Ministersbefore the Cabinet are invited to settle such major differences of opinionor conflicts of interest as remain.     It is only in this way that we shallprotect Ministers from the dangers of hasty and premature decisions and avoid cluttering the Cabinet with proposals which have not been completelyco-ordinated.2.     I have therefore instructed the Cabinet Office that henceforwardthey should work strictly to the normal rules, which require that nomemorandum should be circulated to the Cabinet unless-(i)     The Ministers directly concerned have not only agreed itstext, particularly as regards the presentation of the factsinvolved, but have also satisfied themselves that all the!   prior processes of normal interdepartmental discussionhave been exhausted and that there is no alternative to a reference to Cabinet.(ii)     The financial implications of the memorandum have been cleared, or at least clarified, with the Treasury.(iii)     Its manpower implications have similarly been cleared,or clarified, with the Civil Service Department.1
(iv) There will be an interval of at least 48 hours between the circulation of the memorandum and its appearance on aCabinet agenda.It is the duty of the Cabinet Office to enforce these rulesf and i must ask all my colleagues to co-operate in making them fully effective.E H10 Downing Street SWT29 October 1970i i2


</content>
</cab>
