<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/129/0 images: 58-64</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IB    &apos;&quot;lOS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(67)5517th April, 1967COPY NO.CABINETEUROPE: A POSSIBLE WHITE paper note by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister I circulate forconsideration by the Cabinet, at their meeting on TUESDAY,18th APRIL, 1967 the attached memorandum by officials on apossible White Paper.0(Signed)    BURKE trend cabinet Office, S. W. 1.17th April, 1967
EUROPE:   A POSSIBLE &quot;WHITE PAPERReport &quot;by the Chairman of the Official Committee on EuropeThis memorandum sets out for consideration by the Cabinet the resultsof an examination by officials of the possible timing and content of a white Paper or Papers on the Approach to Europe in the light of the oralAnswer on this subject given by the Prime Minister on 13th April(Hansard Volume 744, Ho. 178, Columns 1368-1371).2.     The gist of the Prime Minister&apos;s Answer (Column 13^9, lines 1A-29)Is as follows:&quot;The most convenient thing at this stage would be if the statement made by my right hon. Friend to a private meeting were now madeavailable in full to all hon. Members, and more generally, andwhen the series of meetings end and I make a statement, my speech on that occasion should also be made available.   The right hon.Gentleman can then be assured - which was his concern - that nothing was said at the private meeting which was not madeavailable to all hon. Members and to the public.   I will consider,immediately after that, the question whether a fuller White paper is necessary.&quot;The terms of this statement would cover the issue of one or moreWhite Papers or similar documents.3.     As regards timing, this matter needs to be considered in the context of the Cabinet&apos;s programme for further consideration of the Approach to europe (CC(67) 20th Conclusions, Item 2).   On the basis there set out,namely that the aim should be for the Cabinet to reach a decision, andfor a Parliamentary Debate on it to be held before the Recess, startingon 12th May, the timetable would need to be approximately as follows.3a.   The Prime Minister&apos;s speech to the Parliamentary Labour Party,which would form part of the White Paper or similar document envisaged bythe Prime Minister&apos;s Answer, is due to be made on 25th April.   If theremainder of the material for that document, including or comprising(see below) the Foreign secretary&apos;s speech to the Parliamentary LabourParty on 6th April had already been printed by 25th April, the completeddocument, including both these speeches and any other material (see below)could we think be issued by say the end of that week, i.e. 28th April.
SECRET * Ig4.     This would he, on the Cabinet&apos;s present programme, about a week orten days before their final decision, which officials assume would bethe minimum interval which would be acceptable.   Allowing, on the best estimate we can secure (which is being checked), some eight or nine daysfor the consideration and printing of the whole of the necessary material,issue of the completed document containing both the Prime Minister&apos;s andthe Foreign Secretary&apos;s speeches, and possibly other material by 28th Aprilwould involve sending all the material other than the Prime Minister&apos;sspeech for printing by about Wednesday, 19th or Thursday, 20th April.   any material additional to the two speeches would, therefore, have to beprepared and cleared for printing very quickly.5.     If alternatively the speech by the Foreign Secretary   were issuedearlier, that would involve two &quot;Papers&quot;, and would underline the questionconsidered below whether additional material should be included in one orother of these papers, and so complicate the problem of timing.   In the context of the Prime Minister&apos;s Answer referred to above and of previousstatements on this subject, the additional material would consist of non-confidential information gathered during the course of the recent discussions with Heads of G-governments of the countries of the european economic Community (e.c.).6.     There is here something of a dilemma in that on the one hand theissue of a document consisting of the two speeches to the parliamentary labour Party might be open to criticism as failing to provide sufficientinformation in regard to the recent European discussions or indeed,insufficient coverage of the. very wide scope of the subject of the implications of the entry of the United Kingdom into the e.c.;   whereas onthe other hand a wider coverage would, in proportion as the scope of the document was widened, create difficulties both of timing and of substance,in view of the variety of opinions held on this question.7.     Nevertheless from preliminary consideration officials have given tothis problem, it seems likely that an objective summary of the non-confidential information gathered during the recent European visits couldbe made available and cleared, if special priority were given to this, intime to meet the timetable in paragraph 3 above.   Since the question ofBritish entry into the e.c. and its political, economic, and socialimplications has been widely and publicly discussed ever since, and indeedeven before the foundation of the e.c. in March 1957? it would reasonably be argued that the issue of a document or documents containing the speeches ofthe Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary to the Parliamentary Labour Partytogether with an objective summary of the non-confidential informationgathered during their European tour could be justified as providing adequateinformation for purposes of Parliamentary and public discussion.
8.     There has &quot;been and still is a demand from a number of quarters, otherthan HM Opposition, for such material, most notably from the First Secretaryof State&apos;s Consultative Committee for Industry and from the Trades UnionCongress.   A White Paper or similar document on the lines suggested above would be of some assistance to the First Secretary of State in relationto his Industrial Consultative Committee on Europe, which will have to meeton or around 1st May, i.e. after the Prime Minister&apos;s speech to theParliamentary Labour Party and before the final decision by the Cabinet.It would not give them as much information as they have been led to expect,but would provide some basis for more detailed discussion of the issues involved in the approach to Europe.9.     If such a document were issued by say 28th April it would materiallysimplify the problem whether there should be a further and fuller white paper, the possibility of which is covered by the Prime Minister8s Answerquoted in the second paragraph of this memorandum.    Such a furtherdocument could hardly be issued between 28th April and a decision by theCabinet together with a Parliamentery Debate on it before the start of the recess on 12th May, unless it were simply a White Paper containing the government&apos;s Statement to Parliament on their decision and the reasons which underlay it.   This would in any event be a likely procedure;    and ifsuch a &quot;White Paper were followed, as it could be, by the publication by theCentral Office of Information of a 48-page booklet now in draft, setting out the main facts about the nature of the e.c. and its policies, togetherwith a similar statement of the corresponding facts about the UnitedKingdom (e.g. descriptions of the agricultural policies of the e.c. and theUnited Kingdom), Ministers might feel that, against the background of almost a decade of public discussion of the e.c. and the implications ofBritish membership of it, sufficient material for purposes of publicinformation had been provided.10.   Ministers are accordingly invited to decide -(a) whether the Foreign Secretary&apos;s speech to the parliamentary labour Party on 6th April should be issued in advance of or at the same time as the Prime Minister0s forthcoming speech to that body on 25th April, or should be issued separatelyas soon as possible;(b) whether the two speeches should be supplemented by a summaryof the non-confidential information gathered during therecent European tour, and whether the resulting documentshould be issued as a White Paper or in some other form;
(Signed)   w&quot;,A. WIELDCabinet Office, S.W.1.17th April 1967(o)   whether in the light of the decisions on (a) and (b) abovethere should be a further YvTiite Paper containing thestatement the Government would make to Parliament about their decision on the approach to Europe;    and whetherthis should be followed by the publication of the COIbooklet now in draft describing the institutions and policies of the e.c., together with a description of corresponding United Kingdom arrangements and policies.11.   The Cabinet&apos;s present timetable for consideration of the approach to Europe, with relevant dates, is attached for information.
ANNEXEUROPE:    THE PRESENT TIMETABLECabinet))17th - 20th April20th April (Thursday)27th April (Thursday) Cabinet)4th May       (Thursday) Cabinet7th May       (Monday)12th - 29th May(14th May, Whit Sunday)19th - 26th May (friday -Pridajr)27th - 28th May (Saturday -Sunday)29th May (Whitsun Bank Holiday)29th May - 2nd June (Monday -Friday)3rd - 4th June (Saturday -Sunday)Foreign Secretary in washington for SEATOConsideration of the Approach to europe for a decision in time fora Debate before the RecessReputed likely date for conclusionof Kennedy RoundParliamentary RecessForeign Secretary in MoscowPrime Minister in Canada


</content>
</cab>
