<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/129/0 images: 96-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth AffairsLast September, when v/e were considering the policy which weshould follow on PJhodesia at the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos;Meeting, many of us were worried about the problem of whether thevalue of the Commonwealth association to us might be outweighed bythe extent to which it affects adversely our own policies and interests.We are now of course considering the possibility of British member-ship of the European Economic Community v/hich will have an impact on Commonwealth interests in a number of ways.2.       I accordingly asked my officials to prepare a broad analysis ofthe value of the Commonwealth, identifying and assessing the variousgeneral factors.    I think that my colleagues will find it helpful to have this study by way of general background and I attach a copy at Anne::.C(67) 59COPY NO,24th April, 1967CABINETTHE VALUE OF THE COMMONWEALTHH.B.Commonwealth Office, S.W.1,24th April, 1967
THE &quot;VaLUE OP TEA CPMMOKp;ALTHDevelopments in the Commonwealth in recent years have raised the question whether for Britain disadvantages in theCommonwealth relationship may now outweigh the advantages(paragraph i).2.     The Commonwealth can no longer he regarded as an association in which Britain could count on getting her own way end where the other Members normally supported Britain.Of the present twenty-six Members all but five fall within the afro-Asian world.      Many seek to exert pressure-group tacticson us inside the Commonwealth association.      This has beenexacerbated &quot;by the fact that the most important issuescurrently engaging the Commonwealth have racial connotationsand arouse strong emotions.      (paragraphs 2 - 10).3.     The Commonwealth corresponds with reality in that it is&quot;built on historical facts and shared traditions.      The extensiveand diverse non-governmental links ere impressive and important.The Commonwealth is a bridge between races.     And it providesopportunities for Britain to influence other Members,(paragraphs 11  -12).k.     The main present disadvantage to Britain of theCommonwealth today is th. t it provides a ready-made forum forpressures on Britain, &quot;but it is doubtful whether it hampers us,as is sometimes argued,  in foreign policy, trade, aid ordefence matters (paragraphs 13 - 16).5.      There is a high level of trade between Britain and other commonwealth countries. Though it is^becoming loss important andpreferences are diminishing,    it is still important to us.(paragraphs 17 - 19).6.      If Britain joins the !v .B.C. this may well progressivelyaffect our ability to play as large a political role in theCommonwealth as in the past.     Economically, the importance of/   the
tlie Britain-Commonwealth relationship will he much reducedthrough the disappearance of preferences and reduction of commonwealth imports into the United Kingdom, (paragraphs 20 - 227.     pven if the Commonwealth association as such were todisappear, this would not alter the fact that, as a result of past history wo have with individual Commonwealth countriesspecially complex and extensive interests,      (paragraphs 23 - 25)8.     If the Commonwealth were now or in the foreseeable future to break up, the assumption must be that it would not gustquietly disintegrate but would break up in hostility towardsBritain,,     We should then be released from the special pressuresby our partners as a Member of the Commonwealth.     But the disadvantages would be serious.     Our prestige throughout theworld would take a heavy knock.     Our economic interests in thoseCommonwealth countries hostile to us would suffer.     The loss ofBritish influence in Commonwealth Africa would add to instabilityin that Continent.    (paragraphs 26 - 29)9.     Looking to the future, the old historical links are likelygradually to diminish in so far as these derive from the days ofBritish Imperial Rule.     But there are other cohesive factors and new ones are developing.     The present difficulties shouldnot be permanent.     The Commonwealth association provides us,and Canada and Australia, with special opportunities for playinga role in the&quot;major issues of rich and poor, coloured and white,which will face the world over the next fifty years.     We shouldnot throw this association away.    (paragraphs 30 - 5k) *10.   There are some ways In which we might reduce the existingdisadvantages for us.     Wo should make it clear that we are notprepared to sustain the Commonwealth at any price, that the doctrine of &quot;freedom to differ&quot; applies equally to Britain andwe should seek to avoid pressure groups building up atCommonwealth meetings.     But we should encourage Commonwealth-wide meetings on practical matters of co-operation, particularly/   in
in support of the non-governmental Commonwealth links.The commonwealth  / .alth has an. important role of value to Britain,to the other Members and to the world,    (paragraph 35).
THE VALUE OP THE COMMONWEALTHSection I       -     Changes in the Commonwealth,Section II     -     The Commonwealth As It is.Section III    -      If the Commonwealth Broke Up.Section IV     -     The Commonwealth in the Future.Section V       -     Possible Amelioration.
 HE, VALUE OF THE COmmWEALTHDevelopments in the Commonwealth in recent years have raised the question whether for Britain disadvantages in the Commonwealthrelationship may now outweigh the advantages.,    A commentator hassummarised one point of view as followss-&quot;It can be argued that, so long as the Commonwealth asa visible organisation was within Britain&apos;s control on matters of importance to Britain,  it served Britishinterests.    Now it has escaped from control,  it is anexpansive luxury; British policy could he more individual and more aware of direct British interests if theCommonwealth did not have to he appeased,&quot;This paper examines recent changes in the Commonwealth, andconsiders current advantages and disadvantages, future potential,and the possible amelioration of some of the contemporarydifficulties.1.      CHANGES IN THSS COffiOMliALTH2.     On the basis of our experience with the old Commonwealth andwith India, Pakistan and Ceylon it was judged to be to our advantage that Commonwealth Membership should be accepted as theright objective for our dependent territories:-(a) for the purpose of maintaining our influence and interests in those countries;(b) in order to retain and strengthen specially friendly relations between Governments and peoples on a broadCommonwealth basis;(c) by enhancing&apos; our international status;(d) because this was a link which the countries themselveswished to retain,3.      There was always a price to pay for this - in the modificationof our policies in response to pressure from Commonwealth countries.But the modifications of policy imposed on us had not been more/ than
CONFIDENTIAL- 2 -than marginal until in recent years when the price sought from ushas increased in the context of the Rhodesia problem.    How far thebalance of advantage for Britain has thus in fact been changed isdebatablej we have naturally resisted attempts to get us to paytoo high a price.    But certainly the collective pressures ha\egrown greater.L,     This has arisen from the interplay of(a) the changing composition of the Commonwealth&quot;(b) methods of procedure within the Commonwealthj(c) the particular policy issues which arise in theCommonwealth forum.&apos;Composition of the Commonwealth5.     The Commonwealth now consists of 26 Members.    Of these allbut four (Britain, Canada, Australia and Pew Zealand) would classthemselves as &quot;developing countries&quot;.    Only Britain, Canada,Australia, India and Pakistan have anything but the most narrowinternational interests and obligations.    11 out of the 26 areAfrican countries who concentrate emotionally and materially onAfrican issues.    18 out of the 26 are emotionally involved inracial issues (India, Ceylon, Malaysia, Jamaica, Trinidad, Guyanaand Barbados in addition to the African countries).    Only five(Britain, Canada, Australia, Pew Zealand and Malta) can beregarded as classed with certainty outside the Afro-Asian world interms of International pressure-group politics.Commpnwealth. Prpcedu^e s6.     Mr. Nehru defended India?s association with the Commonwealthon the grounds that the Commonwealth did not get in the way ofIndia&apos;s complete freedom of action.    The classic Commonwealthdoctrine emphasised that &quot;freedom to differ&quot; was an essential element of Membership&apos; and there was general agreement to avoidattempts to formulate joint Commonwealth policies,  joint attitudesor joint programmes of action (except occasionally in a verygeneralised way on very broad topics - e.g. disarmament).
7.     But in recent years a majority of Members have found themselves sufficiently in agreement on certain major issues to wish to assert their majority positions in order to impose policy decisions on the other Members,,     This has been only too vividlyapparent at Meetings of Prime Ministers over Rhodesia, whereAfrican and. racial issues combine.     But the same tendency is beginning to show elsewhere - etg, at Finance and Trade meetingswhere the ganging up of the developing countries in suchinternational organisations as UNOTAD has been repeated in theCommonwealth environment.      Inopportunely for us, a new emphasis is being placed on the concept of the &quot;consensus&quot; which suits themajority interests.      The Commonwealth Secretary-General, withthe example of the Security Council no doubt in mind, has giventhis concept support and publicity.     ;.Ve have, so far, avoidedvoting procedures in the Commonwealth;    but acceptance anddevelopment of the consensus thesis could also be disadvantageous.Policy Issues8.     The impact on British interests of these developments - thenew composition of Commonwealth Membership and the use of pressure-group methods - has been exacerbated by the fact thatsome of the most important issues currently engaging theCommonwealth are Rhodesia, South Africa and development aid.      Itis precisely on these issues, whatever differences of views and policies may otherwise exist between themselves, that the majorityof Commonwealth Governments find themselves in a natural alliance and one that is directed primarily to criticism of and attacks on british policy.      Intransigent views on these subjects have anappeal to their home audiences which these Commonwealth Governmentscannot resist.9.     We in Britain had for long benefited from the abilitylargely to stage-manage Commonwealth Meetings ourselves.     Aconsiderable limitation on that ability was an inevitableconsequence of the growth of the Commonwealth and the changing,/ and- 3 -
SB- k -and reduced, status of Britain in the world.     Moreover, there are good grounds for arguing that some reduction in the Commonwealth&apos;s&quot;Anglo-centricityw would be a healthy thing and make for a moreeven sharing of responsibilities within the Commonwealth.      Inpractice, however, the changes have taken place in ways and under conditions which have, in the short term at any rate, involvedserious disadvantages for Britain.10.   Since, therefore, the Commonwealth at present tends to operate as a special pressure group on Britain over importantpolicy issues of particular significance and. delicacy for theBritish Government, it is tempting to suggest that the removalof this pressure group must be a gain for us.     But there are other elements in the balance sheett-(a) the advantages of there being a Commonwealth in theworld of today and for Britain hex^self;(b) the disadvantages to Britain of a break-up in theCommonwealth arising from hostility to Britain onthe part of the majority of the Members.11 *    THE COMMOF?-r.EAI,TH AS IT IS11.   In spite of the obvious difficulties there is generalagreement that, on balance, the Commonwealth is &quot;a good thing&quot;.This was certainly the underlying assumption in the cabinet decision of 10 September, when it was agreed that major concessionsshould if necessary be made at the then forthcoming PrimeMinisters&apos; Meeting in order to prevent a break-up of theC ommonwe a1th.Advantages12.   The main advantages of the Commonwealth ares-(i)    It corresponds with reality.     It has a historicaljustification and the association is firmly based onshared traditions.     We speak the same language andunderstand each other&quot; - all the more so because we/have
: &quot;   5   &quot;have largely common systems in administration, the law,the armed forces, education, British merchanting andhanking traditions and interests.    Oxbridge, Sandhurst,Shakespeare, the authorised version of the Bible are allgenuine links.    Even if the Common-wealth were a &quot;farce&quot;it is not &quot;phoney&quot;.(ii)    These are affinities not only between Governments butalso between peoples.    Some of them, for special reasons and in differing degrees, exist with othercountries outside the Commonwealth such as Ireland andthe United States.    But there is no doubt that theexistence of the Commonwealth association greatly helpsto sustain and facilitate such links.    In the newcountries the Commonwealth association provides an acceptable multilateral &quot;cover&quot; for links (e.g. betweenthe Armed Forces) which might otherwise be at risk as&quot;imperialist&quot; influences.    In this country, and to a lesser but increasing extent among the older Members,  itencourages a wide range of beneficial interest and activity in the other countries of the Commonwealth,(iii)      The non-governmental multilateral and bilateralinstitutions within the Commonwealth are of an- impressive extent and diversity.   They cover a wide field - educational, medical, cultural, scientific,economic, financial,  commercial, legal.    These are the links which the Commonwealth Foundation has been set upto encourage,A .(iv)    The modern Commonwealth was a triumphant technique tocover the process of decolonialisation, turning &quot;Empire&quot;into &quot;Commonwealth&quot;.    This both enabled us to extricateourselves from colonial responsibilities with honour and psychologically cushioned the shock for the peopleof Britain in adjusting to a new era (though it may also have encouraged some illusions).CONFIDENTIAL /(v)
- 6 -(v)    The Commonwealth association helps Britain to exert influence on other Commonwealth Governments.While we are at present concerned about pressures on us by other Commonwealth Governments, we shouldnot under-estimate our own continuing influence on them, and the opportunities for us to exercise it which the Commonwealth association provides.    TheCommonwealth association also brings into play themoderating influences of the old Commonwealth andthe less extreme Afro-Asians,(vi)    The Commonwealth association gives to each of its members a greater status internationally than itwould enjoy if the Commonwealth did not exist (part ofthe respect paid to British views in Washington isdue to their appreciation of Britain&apos;s Commonwealthrole and the opportunities it provides for British influence, particularly in Africa and Asia).(vii)    The multi-racial nature of the Commonwealth and theway in which it acts as a bridge between white,black, brown and yellow is not merely a well-worntruism.    It is no less a valid and important truth;and regarded as such by Commonwealth Members as awhole.    Moreover,  it is a factor of special, and perhaps critical, significance in relation to what may well be the most explosive problem in the worldover the next half century.P i s a d v an t a ge s13:.   As indicated in Section I, the main disadvantage to britain of the Commonwealth as it is today is that it provides a ready-made forum for pressures to be brought to bear on theBritish Government to make concessions.    These are frequentlycontrary to British interests and sought by a process of blackmailin the interests of preserving a semblance of Commonwealth/concord.
concord.     How far the removal of this forum would significantlyreduce the pressures on Britain is debatable.     We should stillbe exposed to pressures in the United Nations and, howeverunsatisfactory our recent experiences have been in CommonwealthConferences, it is fair to say that in general commonwealth representatives have behaved more responsibly and have been moreresponsive to British arguments and influence within theCommonwealth environment than in the United Nations,,      It can. be argued that the existence of the Commonwealth enabled Britain to buy time over Rhodesia and that, in the absence of a Commonwealthforum, we should have had more difficulty in deferring damagingintervention by the United Nations.     Nevertheless,  in a specialsense, Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings in recent years havecontained examples of Britain clutching vipers to her bosom - andpaying for it.1h.   There is a substantial volume of opinion which, whatever the realities, believes that the Commonwealth association imposesdisabilities on Britain;    that these could be removed if itdisappeared;    and that we are paying unreasonably for themaintenance of an association with a number of countries who seemnever to give us support and always to oppose and criticise us in public and in offensive terms. &apos;&quot;15.   There are criticisms that the Commonwealth hampers our foreign policy, involves us in defence commitments and isexpensive in terms of aid.     The case is debatable.      Suchconcessions as we make to Commonwealth interests in conductingour foreign policy are compensated for by the internationalstanding we derive from the existence of the Commonwealth.     Nor dcour Commonwealth commitments seriously hamper our trade negotiations and - though the intorests of certain commonwealth countries are a major factor - it is not the Commonwealth,association that has so far prevented our entry into Europe.Our Defence Review policies and deployment have not had to he/adjusted
CONFIDENTIAL- 8 -adjusted to meet requirements arising from Commonwealth Membershipas such.   Admittedly   the lion&apos;s share of our aid goes to other commonwealth countries, hut this has &quot;been inevitable forhistorical reasons.    In any case a large part of our aid is inBritish interests and it is arguable that, even without theCommonwealth, we should still find it expedient to continue todo as much in those countries which are now in the Commonwealth.16,     The presence of coloured immigrants in Britain is the causeof much complaint,  particularly in the areas most affected, andis undoubtedly a contributory cause in public opinion for theunpopularity of the new Commonwealth.    But the entry of immigrants is our own responsibility and is now under strict control.Economic Relations viflthin^the^Commonwealth^17.     Prom the economic point of view the most importantrelationship within the Commonwealth has been that between britain on the one hand and the rest of the Commonwealth on theother.    Traditionally we exported manufactures to them;    theyexported raw materials and foodstuffs to us,    But they no longerprovide a sufficiently growing market for our manufactures, andwe are no longer able to absorb most of the expansion in their output of raw materials and food.    However,  though Britain andthe rest of the Commonwealth are less important to each othereconomically than they once were,  the Commonwealth is still a market worth over  1,300 m. a year to us (which is about a quarter of our exports) and still provides slightly over a quarter of our imports.18.      The maintenance of this high level of intra-commonwealth trade is due in part to the existence of the commonwealth preference system.    But preferences are already diminishing.Moreover in the Kennedy Round, Australia and Canada are offering&quot;to bargain more of them away in exchange for improved outletselsewhere.    So, to a lesser extent,  are we.
-9 -190     On the financial side, our ability to provide commonwealth countries with development capital - whether by way of private investment or aid - has diminished.    Those Commonwealth countrieswhich are large holders of sterling are likely in the course oftime to reduce those holdings as our exports of long-term capital to them decline,,    The poorer countries, which are heavily dependent on aid, are able to obtain from us only a small proportionof the money they need from abroad, and so are increasingly having to obtain it from other financial centres, notably the UnitedStates and Europe, and this inevitably leads to changes in the pattern of their trade0The Commonwealth and British Membership of E.E.C.20e     There is nothing formally incompatible in Britain&apos;s joiningE.E.C. and in Britain&apos;s continued membership of the Commonwealth,,Other Commonwealth countries are closely involved in groupingsof their own regions, but none of them are as close as ours wouldbe with Europe if we accept the Treaty of Rome.    It must beexpected that in practice membership of EJ.C. will,  in allfields, progressively strengthen our links with Europe arid have an effect on our links with the Commonwealth.    There will beintangible consequences in the political and cultural fields.Politically the changes could be considerable, but the extent and pace of change will depend on how both Europe and theCommonwealth evolve and develop.    Britain&apos;s membership of E.E.C.is likely to lead to a diminution of our function as the lynch-pin of the Commonwealth, and the Commonwealth&apos;s continuedvitality will depend, more than in the past,  on the importance which other Commonwealth Members attach to it and the extentto which they wish to give it active and effective support.At the same time Britain may have a special role to play as a link between the two organisations;    this could be important indissuading the European countries from an inward-looking postureand in encouraging contact and understanding between them and the developing countries, /21,CONFIDENTIAL
- 10 -21.    In the economic field, British membership of E.B.C. willcreate difficulties, which have been clearly identified in other papers,  over bilateral trading and commercial relations with anumber of individual Commonwealth countries.    More generally ifwe join the E.E.C., most of the preferences we give to theCommonwealth will disappear;    and indeed we will have to applyreverse preferences against a number of Commonwealth countries.In this situation those Commonwealth countries will obviously cease to grant preferences to us.   And the effects of-the levy system,  of increased production in the U,K.,  e,g.  of cereals, and of reductions in consumption, e.g.  of butter, because of higher prices, will all serve to reduce our imports of food from theCommonwealth.    Even how the belief in Commonwealth countries thatwe are likely to join E.E.C.  is encouraging them to bargain awayour preferences;    thus the possibility that we may join is alreadyhaving effects upon our exports to the Commonwealth,22.   AS indicated in the preceding section, the economic value ofthe Commonwealth to us,  and of us to the Commonwealth,  is declining.This decline will be markedly accelerated if we join E.E.C.    It  is obviously not in our interest that it should decline unless we gaincompensating advantages elsewhere.    If we do not join E.E.C. it willhe in our interest to do all we can to arrest the decline in thepreference system and to make cle :r our determination to maintain and if possible intensify the Commonwealth economic connection.Our Bilateral Interests23.    In identifying the effects of the Commonwealth on Britishpolicies and interests,  it is important to differentiate between those arising from the Commonwealth association as such, and thosearising from our interests vis-a-vis individual commonwealth countries which would remain whether or not the Commonwealthcontinues.    It is misleading to talk about the effects and interests of &quot;the Commonwealth&quot; when what are really at issue arethe effects and interests of our relations with individual,  or groups of, Commonwealth countries.    The following examples/illustrate
CONFIDENTIAL- 11 - 98illustrate the point.(a) Even if there were no Commonwealth, the stability and economic progress of India would continue to he a major British interest both because of our economic stake in the country and because of India&apos;s key importancevis-a-vis China.    Similarly the need to maintain some sort of balance between India and Pakistan in our aid and other policies would remain,(b) In the defence field the decision to maintain a british military presence in the Par East was based on a complex of considerations such as the desirability of our continuing to play a world role and to contribute tothe containment of China, the undesirability of creating a vacuum or chaos in the Malaysia/Singapore area and our general relations with the United States, Australia,New Zealand, Malaysia and Singapore.    None ofthese sire considerations arising from the Commonwealthassociation as such.    Of course our relations with thelatter four countries are coloured by the fact that theyare also Members of the Commonwealth.    But the basis ofour relations with Australia and New Zealand (and the implications for our defence policy) would not beaffected if the Commonwealth were to disappear.    Nor wouldsuch an event affect the main arguments in favour of ourstaying in our Singapore base for the time being.(c) Much of our aid to Commonwealth countries arises fromthe fact that they were very recently dependent territories of ours.    Our aid to those commonwealth countries which achieved independence since 1957 began,in most cases,  as a part  of the decolonialisationprocess;    it was a golden hand-shake marking our sense ofsome continuing responsibility for their welfare in theimmediate post-independence period and recognition thatour imperial rule had not completed the process of making them viable and fully equpped for an independent existence.CONFIDENTIAL /(d)
- 12 -(&amp;)    Commonwealth or no Commonwealth our very largecommercial and financial stakes in, for instance,Australia and India will continue to he importantcons i de ra t i ons.2h.     Thus the disappearance of the Commonwealth association would not alter the fact that, as a result of history and in a variety of ways, we have with individual Commonwealth countriesspG c is lly complex and extensive interests.25.     At the same time - and this is partly at any rate the resultof our own propaganda - it is a fact that many new commonwealth countries believe it to be Commonwealth Membership as such whichsecures for them preferential treatment from Britain - e.g., tradepreferences,  sterling area arrangements, Commonwealth sugar agreement etc.    In fact these need not necessarily be affected ifthe Commonwealth were to disappear (we still grant preferences to south Africa and the Republic of Ireland, and the sterling areaincludes non-Commonwealth countries).    Per contra some of these arrangements are at the present time out of balance,  so far as british interests are concerned,  and we may have to review themin any event.    It is possible that modifications in these benefitsprovided by Britain would affect the desire of some of the new commonwealth countries to maintain their &quot;Membership.    Probablytiming and the spacing out of major changes would be an important consideration.    It is for instance only recently that general acceptance has been secured for the restrictions - and very severeones - which we now impose on the entry of Commonwealth citizensinto Britain,  the   privilege of free entry into Britain havingpreviously been thought to be an essential element in theCommonwealth association.1110     IF THE COMMONWEALTH BROKE UP26.      There are two prefatory comments to be made:-(i)    We are not considering the matter ideally and looking at what might be the position if the Commonwealth did/not
--13 &quot;not exist.    The Commonwealth does exist as a factand we are looking at what would he the results ofa break-up0(ii)    The assumption must be,  if the Commonwealth breaks up,not that it just quietly disintegrates, but that itbreaks up in hostility towards Britain,,On these assumptions the balance sheet looks as follows.Pros27.      The advantage we would positively gain would be a release from the special pressures brought to bear upon us by our partnersas a Member of the Commonwealth, and, as a result,  some increasedfreedom of manoeuvre in our bilateral relations with individualCommonwealth countries.    It can reasonably be argued that,  ifthere never had been a Commonwealth, relations satisfactory to britain would have been established on a strictly bilateral basis with the individual countries.    It may be that,  in the case ofmany if not all of the African and Caribbean countries, where our interests are small in comparison with our total interestsoverseas and where our influence has had a very limited effect,such a bilateral relationship would have been healthier for both countries and would have relieved Britain of the obligations andvulnerability to pressure which arise from the Commonwealthassociation.   At the same time it must be noted that theprospects of reverting to a bilateral relationship satisfactory to Britain would be highly problematical following a situationwhere the Commonwealth had broken down as a result of highlyemotional hostility on the part of the majority of commonwealth countries towards Britain,    Such hostility would no doubt be mitigated by considerations of self-interest (particularlyfinancial and economic self-interest) in the former commonwealth countries.   But a period of most severely strained relationswith at least a dozen former Commonwealth countries simultaneouslycould not be avoided./Cons
- 14 -Cons28,   We should suffer serious disadvantages:(i)    Our prestige throughout the world would take a very heavy knock.    Whatever we were able to salvage (e.g, byway of a continuing association with the Old commonwealth and possibly some other Members) we should have proved that the Commonwealth was indeed a farce and that all our previous aspirations and policies were based onillusion.    The Government would be discredited and eventhe Monarchy would be affected,(ii)    Our economic interests would suffer.    It is impossible toquantify the extent to which they would be affected, sincemuch would depend on how many countries remained friendly to us and wished to preserve a special relationshipperhaps in a new form of association, the degree of hostility of those who left, and the decisions which we ourselves took about continuing aid and other specialrelations in each case.    But if, as must be assumed,feelings ran high,  it seems certain that many expatriateofficers in African countries would come home, that theposition of British businessmen abroad would be affected(even if British concerns were not expropriated^   and thatBritish interests would suffer in the award of futurecontract s,(iii)    In the circumstances envisaged, British influence in commonwealth Africa would be removed and the continuance ofBritish aid, at least at anything like its present scale,would he difficult if not impossible.   As a result, theCommonwealth countries in Africa would be more unstableeven than at present and would invite attention from outside.    Whether the Americans or the Chinese could take our place seems an open question.    If a wholesale Africanwithdrawal led the Asian Members of the Commonwealth tofollow suit, some very difficult questions would arisee/If
If India were to withdraw in anger, the consequences to ourvery extensive economic relations with that country could hefar-reaching.    A rupture &quot;by Singapore and Malaysia couldinvolve the sudden and humiliating withdrawal of our defence facilities.(v)    Our relations with the United States would he adversely affected.    The Americans have shown that they attach greatimportance to our influence in Africa and Asia and to our continuing to play an effective role in &quot;both continents.&quot;  a situation in which Britain was regarded in Africa and Asiaas a hostile power would he most serious for them and forour relations with them.29.    In sum, therefore,  if the Commonwealth were to break up weshould greatly damage our present position in the world, the risks of serious instability in Africa and possibly in Asia would beincreased,  and our valuable commercial interests in those areas wouldhe endangered.IV.    THE C0MMQNWEALTH IN THE FUTURE30.   The common historical links which nave been basic for theCommonwealth association, derive from the days of British imperialruleo and as such they may be expected to diminish with the passageof time.    It is nut, however;,  a necessary consequence that this process will mean the eventual disappearance of the commonwealth as an institution.    The old cohesive factors may well be replaced by new ones - the Commonwealth Secretariat and the CommonwealthFoundation are both very recent experiments.    Much will depend onBritain&apos;s attitude.31.   We have drawn attention to the present difficulties which theCommonwealth pressure group creates for Britain.    At the same timeour own influence on other Commonwealth Governments is notnegligible and it could be greater if the future provides a morefavourable environment.    There are prospects of this.    The present/difficult ies
-,16;/-difficulties should not be permanent and may well be comparatively short-term.    Primarily they arise from &quot;colonialism&quot; in two senses:-(a) The acute interest and concern of the new Commonwealth countriesin our liquidation of our colonial responsibilities - above allRhodesia.(b) A &quot;new-colonialist&quot; attitude on the part of the new commonwealth countries themselves.32.   &quot;New-colonialist&quot; is used here to describe the persistence of a colonial attitude after independence - the maintenance of the charac-1 teristics of colonial politicians in the last stages of dependent territories, who feel free to make any criticism they wish, or any demandthey wish, of the &quot;Imperial&quot; power, but regard any criticism or demand by the latter as an expression of imperialism automatically to be resented.    The &quot;double standard&quot; arises from immaturity, and from theprevious close relationship arid consequent lack of a broad diversificationof contacts and interests with other countries.    It is reasonable to suppose that these sources of difficulty will progressively lessen inthe years ahead.    The present discontents are real enough; but any final judgement ought to depend on whether we see the potential valueof the Commonwealth, in terras of our own interests, as sufficientlygreat to make worthwhile an attempt to work our way through the dis-comforts and difficulties of the Commonwealth in its present phase,133.   It is possible that other members of the Commonwealth could helpI to find acceptable final solutions to the problems of some of the dependent territories for which we remain responsible; some for instancemay in course of time join with Commonwealth countries in one way or another (the Solomon Islands protectorate with Papua/New Guinea andsome of the small Caribbean territories might eventually pass into theorbit of Jamaica or Trinidad or into a wider Caribbean grouping) 5 whilemore generally Canadian interest in the Caribbean and Australian and-pew Zealand interest in our Pacific territories,  are valuable assets.gShese various possibilities would be less likely if the Commonwealthassociation were to disappear.341   Of the major issues facing the world in the next 50 years, popu-lation growth, instant communications,  and the eventual necessity for&apos;he whole North Atlantic technological and industrial base to findgreater markets than the North Atlantic area itself can provide,  allcombine to make perhaps the most important task that of finding somemodus Vivendi between Western haves and the African, Asian and SouthWrican have-nots,  and some way to bring the under-developed majorityinto a self-sustaining world system of prosperity.    We in Britain are/adjusting
17 -adjusting ourselves to a position as.a leading power in the &quot;top-middle&quot; category,     We no longer command the resources of athese major issues of rich and poor, coloured and white, theCommonwealth association provides us,  and also Canada and -Austral!with special opportunities for doing so.     There is in the Common-whalth a complex of links, not only political, hut economic,educational, administrative and professional, which are directlyrelevant.     It would he a. grave matter for us, both nationally andinternationally, if we. were seen to he throwing away a specialasset which could give Britain a position of central importance inthe world in, say, the last two decades of this century, out of proportion to her comparative economic and military strength.V,    POSSIBLE AMELIORATIONS35-   While the existing disadvantages of the Commonwealth for usshould not he permanent, there may also be ways in which thesedisadvantages could be reduced.      The following are possiblepointers for further study:-(a)   The main disadvantage of the Commonwealth for us atthis time is its tendency to act as a. pressure group on us.     This could be exacerbated if other commonwealth countries were to believe that our policies weredominated by fears for the future of the Commonwealth,In calculating our interests, the maintenance of theCommonwealth association is an important factor to be weighed, but not the only one.      It is important,therefore, that other Commonwealth countries shouldnot be lulled by the impression that, however offensive and difficult they may be, Britain can always be relied on in the last resort to ensure that theCommonwealth is sustained.     We are not prepared to sustain the Commonwealth at any price to ourselves.major world power.    But if Britain still has arole to play in/This
CONFIDENTIAL 103- 18 -This has hecone apparent to other Commonwealth countriesin the course of the Rhodesia negotiations and has had a healthy effect:    they themselves have been forced to ask whether the break-up of the Commonwealth would be a matterof comparative indifference to them and have answered inthe negative.    Where there is a possibility of oneCommonwealth country leaving without dragging others with it, we should be able to adopt an even firmer posture.If the occasion arises we may need to make it clearthat while we do not ourselves choose to dismember theCommonwealth,  the classic Commonwealth doctrine of&quot;freedom to differ&quot; applies to Britain as much as toany other member.(b) We have long abandoned the concept of trying to deal inthe same way and on the same footing with all countries ofthe Commonwealth, but It may be that there is scope for usto pursue more consciously and more strictly policiesbased on bilateral considerations.    We should not bethought to defer to views expressed by a commonwealth government simply because it is a Commonwealth Governmentwhich expresses them.    Our governmental relations with feenewer Commonwealth countries are in any case evolvingtowards a relationship more like  that which subsists between this country and foreign countries,  or between other western countries and the developing countries in whichthey have substantial economic interests.    It is not in our interests that such countries should continue for too longafter the ending of Colonial rule to regard theCommonwealth association as primarily involving an obligation on Britain to provide them with unilateralbenefits, financial and political.(c) We should not unnecessarily expose ourselves to commonwealth pressure group tactics.    It will be to our advantage if there are fewer Commonwealth-widemeetings on policy issues,  since these tend toCONFIDENTIAL /facilitate
- 19 -facilitate end exacerbate such tactics.     With theCommonwealth Secretariat in being this will not be primarily under our control and the Rhodesian problemmay force further Prime Ministerial meetings on to us.Nevertheless it should be our general policy for thepresent not to initiate proposals for Commonwealth-wide meetings on high policy matters (e.g. PrimeMinisters and Trade Ministers) and on occasion ifnecessary to oppose them (e,g, over Common Marketnegotiations - though of course we should arrange the fullest consultation by other means).At the same time we should encourage Commonwealth-widemeetings on practical matters of co-operation, andespecially those which suoport the multifariousCommonwealth links in the professions, etc.  (e.g.medical conferences, meetings of Law Officers,Speakers, etc.)..      The links between peoples in theCommonwealth are of a great variety and depth.     Theyare important now and have a high potential value for the future.     We should continue to lay particularstress on them.We should closely scrutinise particular Commonwealthinstitutions or arrangements if these seem no longer to be operating in our interests, though the timing and inter-relntion of any major modifications will need watching if we are not to over-strain the-Association itself.Public opinion in this country is naturally affrontedat the violent and blackguardly attacks made onBritain by some Commonwealth leaders in Africa, orof -African origin,  and asks v/hether we are paying too high a price to maintain a Commonwealth associationwhich includes such obnoxious critics.      In our/publicity
- 20 -publicity we should aim to put this present probleminto perspective.     We should, also seek to presenta realistic picture.of the Commonwealth as it istoday and to discourage illusions.     TheCommonwealth is not c. single cohesive group andit cannot be expected to act just as an instrument for support of British policies.     But it has animportant role of value to Britain and the otherMembers and. to the world, at large.Commonwealth Office, S.W.1.7 April, 1967.


</content>
</cab>
