<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/129/0 images: 122-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TOP  SECRETG 6Copy No.C(67) 6024th April, 1967CABINETTHE APPROACH TO europe memorandum by the Prime Minister and theSecretary of State for Foreign affairs on 23rd March and again on 6th April the Cabinet agreed thatthe right procedure for our further consideration of the approach to europe would be for us first to assess the results of the discussions which we had with the Heads of Government of the Six countries and toconsider such further studies of the European problem as the cabinet might think necessary, before coming to a definitive consideration  ofthe decision whether, when, and on what conditions to seek membership of the European Economic Community (e.c.).    We have now had discussions in some depth of the results of our European tour, and of anumber c*f further studies of the effect     membership of the EECwould have on our domestic and external pesition.     In our discussions of procedure we proposed, and the Cabinet agreed, that for thedefinitive stage of our discussions it would be right for us topresent a paper setting out the alternative courses before us in regardto membership of the e.c. and their respective advantages and dis-advantages.    This we now do.2.      A number of alternative courses can be formulated, based uponpermutations of the basic decisions whether or not to apply for membership of the e.c. or some other form of relationship with it, andwhen to do so i. e, now, later, or not at alPso far as the foreseeable future is concerned.     Our discussions may be clearer if we firstconsider whether there is any satisfactory or acceptable means, otherthan full membership, of securing such closer economic relationship with the e.c..    When General de Gaulle at the end of our visit to Parisspeculated on this subject (see C(67) 33, Annex, page 48) I at oncerejected his suggestion of associate membership because this would bea kind of second-class citizenship which would impose on us many,perhaps most, of the obligations of membership with few of the rights.It would fail tp give us an equal or adequate vsice in Community councils and so prevent us from playing our part in developing what we and thewell disposed members af the e.c. think EuropeEs role and positionin the world ought to be, whether in specialised fields such astechnology, or in world affairs generally.    It would also prevent us from intervening in the eec&apos;s vital discussions on financing the common agricultural policy (c. a. p. ) in 1969-70.1-TOP  SECRET(97294)
3.      Nor would it be realistic to regard the other suggestion made by-General de Gaulle at the same time, i. e, to establish &quot;something new and different&quot; as a genuine option,,     In the context of the immediately preceding remarks it must rather be seen, at least in part, as a tacticaldevice to discourage us, and the Five as well, from seeking earlymembership of the e.c. for the United Kingdom and as a tacit admissionof concern that the reasons he had hitherto relied on to justify excludingus from the Community had to a large extent been eroded.     Nor can we see what this &quot;something new&quot; might be, save either a project toreshape the e.c. so radically as to require years of negotiation (whichthe Five would not countenance) or one involving the retention of the eec with a free trade area, including ourselves, built around it.    Thelatter would be a rather superior form of association, a sort of Class IIAcitizenship:  and again it would be unrealistic to suppose that the Frenchor, indeed, the Five would give us the industrial free trade advantages of membership within the Community without the correspondingobligations in regard to agriculture, external tariffs, and economic&quot;union&quot;, since these were a vital part of the terms on which the presentCommunity was established.4.      It would therefore seem best for these and other reasons, bothdomestic and external, for us to focus our consideration upon full membership of the Community.     The main alternatives before us in this context, covering the various possibilities from one extreme to the otsher,would seem to be four,A. To decide that we should not apply now for membership of theCommunity, either on the basis that it is not a body of which we should wish to become members on any terms we could expect to negotiate inthe foreseeable future or that we do not think we could secure such termswithin such a period as to make an early start practical politics.B. To decide to seek from the Community, in either bilateral orcollective discussions, further information and assurances about ourprospective membership, on the grounds that we do not yet have sufficientto enable us to decide whether to apply for membership or not.C. To decide now in principle and to announce (since it would bedifficult to conceal for long a decision in principle) that we intend toapply for membership, subject to our receiving further information and assurances about it;  and that meanwhile we shall delay our application - in other words a post-dated or open-dated conditionaldeclaration of intent.D. To decide now to make early application for membership ofthe e.c. and to that end to request either new negotiations or a resump-tion of those suspended after the French veto in January, 1963,5,       Y/e consider that these are the only logical choices before usbecause they represent, respectively, a negative decision;   a postpone-ment of the decision;  a conditional decision, with the onus on us whether to implement it;   and a firm decision, with the onus whether to implereentit placed as far as possible on the Six i, e. on their being willing tonegotiate acceptable terms.    In the following paragraphs we analyseeach of these courses in turn.
Course A - A Negative Decision6.       Course A covers, theoretically speaking, two decisions, namely to answer the basic question whether or not to apply for membership ofthe e.c. by either &quot;No&quot; or &quot;Not for some time&quot;.     But, unless we assumesomething for which we cannot legislate (namely, a change of circum-stances within a reasonably short space of time, say 12 to 18 months,which would almost decisively tip the chances of membership of the eec in our favour) there is really only one option here.    First, weshould clearly find it extremely difficult to announce and to justify adecision that we would never join the Community;  and, if only for over-riding internal and external reasons of presentation, we should prefer to say, if our answer was a negative one, &quot;Not at present&quot; ratherthan &quot;Never&quot; or even &quot;No&quot;.7.       Second, whilst we might retain hopes that sooner or later member-ship of some new and acceptable relationship with the Community might become open to us, the immediate effects of either of these negativedecisions would be similar, both at home and abroad, because the con-sequences of either decision would be, barring the unforeseeable changesreferred to in the preceding paragraph,, to rule out for all or most of the effective lifetime of this Parliament the possibility of membership, and perhaps even of a new decision to apply for membership.    At home, thiswould be likely to make membership a major issue of Party political controversy, which in turn would have withering effects on the possi-bilities of membership in the foreseeable future, and would considerablydamage the prospects of a revival of private investment in productiveindustry on which we greatly rely for the achievement of a faster rateof economic growth.    Abroad, a negative decision of this kind wouldbe ill received in the United States, which has all along supported our membership of the e.c., EFTA countries would at once wish to knowour view of the future of EFTA;   and some of them would not easily be put off v/ith the status quo.    Some Commonwealth countries would see that for some time the Community, save to some extent on temperateagricultural produce, would offer them the advanatages of a european market four times greater and with a faster grov/th rate and less balanceof payments constraint than ours;  and some Commonwealth countries could be expected to follow the lead of Nigeria and the East african territories in seeking to negotiate for association with the e.c., or at least for trade agreements with it.Course B - Postponement of a Decision in order to seek FurtherInformation8,       This course, in theory, could be pursued either multilaterally orbilaterally with individual countries of the She.     To the extent that itwere done multilaterally, it might become more of a negotiation, sincethe She would then be obliged to speak with one voice;  but it could bemade clear that no commitment was involved.    But the tempo in which such purely exploratory talks could be conducted, in view of the prioritythe She would naturally accord to their own affairs., national and communal,would be likely to be slow.    If the talks were bilateral, they could be useful, though less conclusive, and their tempo could be quicker;  but without a multilateral confrontation there could be no guarantee that anything acceptable to one member of the Six would be acceptable tothe others, and the French would see that we were seeking to avoid a veto or obstruction by them, and would accordingly seek to establish a common line among the Six.
The advantages of this course are:That some Germans and Italians believe that further detailedexploration of a satisfactory basis for negotiations would be advantageous - but they also have in mind that it would absolvethem from any immediate responsibility towards us,That we should not be exposed to a risk of collective refusal orinability of the Six to agree to negotiate.That it would keep most of our options open, save of course theimportant one of securing entry by 1969, before the E C&apos;discussions of common policies, especially on agriculturalfinancing, have reached a definitive stage.The disadvantages of this course are:That it would allow the momentum and interest generated by our european tour to be dissipated in proportion as the explanatory discussions v/ere prolonged^That it is likely to be seen as the result of our failure to agree on any more definite course and that it would, therefoz*e, betaken as discouraging by those who are the keenest supporters of our membership and as an encouragement by those, such asthe French, who are concerned that we should not press ahead.That it would certainly be used by the French to sow distrust ofour sincerity and determination, thus losing one of the principalassets which we have gained by the recent round of discussions with the Six.     The French, who have been rather thrown offbalance both by the seriousness of our approach and, to a lesser degree, by their own election results, would be able easily to recover lost ground.That in these circumstances it is very doubtful whether the rev/ould emerge from the continuation of the probe at whateverlevel any further assurances on which we could place relianceand that in any event we could hardly expect to conduct such afurther probe without revealing more than might be desirableof our negotiating position.That, while we continued our explorations, the Community v/ouldcontinue its development v/ithout our being able to influence it.And the more time we lost, the more likely it v/ould be that theCommunity v/ould come to finalise or develop communal policies -such as the renegotiation of its agricultural financing arrange-ments, its association arrangements with African countries andits policies in such fields as technological collaboration, commonpatents, commercial, and transport policies - without our participation.
11.        The procedure which could be followed if this course were adoptedwould depend on whether the further exploratory talks were multilateralor bilateral.    If a multilateral probe v/ere envisaged, an ad hoc meetingof the Six would have to be requested.     This might be refused on theground, as the French and perhaps others might well argue, that, as there is no application in, there is nothing to discuss.    But for thereasons above, bilateral meetings would probably be preferable.     Theycould be ari*anged ad hoc to discuss different subjects, or to cover ageneral discussion of all outstanding problems with which we areconcerned, e0 g. on the exact manner of handling capital movements,the sterling question, and the questions arising out of the common agricultural policy^    Or discussion could take place in the standingbilateral Economic Committees with Benelux, France, Germany andItaly.    But it is doubtful whether such bilateral discussions would beproductive - the Six would be likely to concert a common line whichwould be limited to what the French would accept;  at best the Fivewould be uncertain what the French would accept and so would fallback on a non-committal line, and the French would either make difficulties or avoid commitment;, as suited them best012,       There would have to be an ^imouncement to the effect thatthe Government required further information in order to enable itto decide whether the conditions existed for a fruitful negotiation.If this course were adopted, it might be enough to explain both toEFTA countries and to Commonwealth countries, through the diplomaticchannel, that we did not propose to take any final decision at this stagebut to proceed merely with further exploration,,     There would thus be nothing to stop the process of further bilateral discussion with the Sixbeing initiated at any time.13,       The central fact that this course would be one of postponing adecision would entail presentational difficulties, both general, i. e.arising from the absence of a decision, and particular, in respectof the various disadvantages indicated above, to which attention would inevitably be drawn in the course of discussion of its announcement athome and abroad.     Careful presentation would be necessary to counteradverse reactions;   and we should not be successful in this unless thefurther explorations were seen to be pursued usefully and with vigour;in which event a decision following these explorations would have to betaken within a limited space of time, by say the autumn of 1967 at latest;probably with little more information than we now have.Course C - A Decision to apply for Membership in Principle, but to engage in a Further Period of probing before actually applying14.       This is a compromise between Courses B and D.  It would involvea definite decision, and an announcement (it could hardly be concealed)that we intended to apply for membership subject to clarification of certain points (on which we should be keenly questioned at the time of theannounc ement).15.       The advantages of this course are:(i) That if we wish to seek membership it is more positive thanCourse B (though, of course, less positive than Course D),It is probably the minimum consistent with maintaining any satisfactory momentum,
(ii) It has the other advantages - (ii) and (iv) under Course B above -- of not exposing ourselves to-a refusal by the Six to negotiate,and of keeping options open,16.       The disadvantages of this course are:(a) It might still be taken as discouraging by those of our friends in. the Community who advocate rapid movement,(b) It has the disadvantages - (c) and (d) - of Course B above,- misrepresentation by the French and no results withoutrevealing our negotiating position.(c) It may give the appearance of an uneasy compromise in which,whilst appearing to take a positive decision and go ahead, we still prefer to keep our options open.(d) It v/ould risk (because  the decision in principle to apply for entry subject to further exploration would have to be announced)producing all the pressures in Parliament, from EFTA, theCommonwealth and special interests in the United Kingdom,which might be expected from Course D, whilst giving thesepressures more time and more scope (in respect of the assurances we should be seeking) to build up,17,       The procedure to be followed under this course would be thesame as for Course B, except that the announcement of our intentionto explore further would be accompanied by a statement that theGovernment were convinced, following the tour of the Six capitals,that, given goodwill, the conditions for a successful negotiation existed.The further exploration would have to be represented as merely seekingconfirination or elaboration of certain points.    There would have to beprior EFTA and Commonwealth consultation, in view of the commitment in principle to membership of the Community which the course wouldinvolve.     The actual application to join the Community v/ould be deferred until after the further exploration had taken place;  meanwhile it would benecessary to present the decision in a positive light both at home andabroad, if domestic, foreign and Commonwealth pressures, and Frenchsapping techniques, were not to frustrate our decision before we cametc act on it.Course D - To apply now for Negotiations for Early Membership of theCommunity18,       The advantages of this course are:(i)  it gives us the best hope of being able to influence the futured development of the Community at a stage when it is stilldeveloping (see paragraphs 26 and 27 below).(ii)  It is clear that we have a better chance of securing modification-  - of the Community^ policies in our favour from a position of membership than from a position of candidate.(iii) It provides us with a clear position which should command respect. in all quarters even if it is not universally supx^orted,
(iv)  It will maintain the momentum and initiative which we have now. gained, following our European tour,(v)  It is the course strongly recommended to us by our best friends- . in the Community.(vi)  Short of a negotiation, we cannot really determine at all precisely what terms will be available to us,(vii)  It gives the French - on the assumption that they would still prefer- . to exclude us from membership - less room for manoeuvre.Any objections they put forward are more likely to berecognisable as the political pretexts they would be,(viii)  It would frustrate what is probably at present France&apos;s principal- - objective - to stop us getting as far as submitting an application;in any case it is the only means of determining whether theFrench would in fact oppose our entry to the point of againdeliberately frustrating it,(ix)  Even if our application fails we shall still have demonstrated oursincerity and determination, both at home and abroad,     (Anycourse short of Course D would expose us to the imputationof not really having tried).     Moreover, to have tried andfailed would be the best basis for proceeding to some alternative arrangement, if it were available and desirable.At the meeting of the Cabinet on 20th April the view-was widelyexpressed that the dynamic-required to make a &quot;go-it-alone&quot;policy workable could best - some argued could only - beachieved in the climate of a rejection of Britain&apos;s application by the e.c..    It was further argued that, while AFTA was not an immediate possibility, encouraging developments in anAFTA or partial-AFTA direction might follow a hostile EECdecision, particularly if the United States as a result moved into a more aggressive posture vis a vis France.19.       The disadvantages of this course are:(a) There can be no guarantee that negotiations, once opened, would succeed. .,(b) There can be no guarantee that an application for membership would in fact lead to negotiations.     (A refusal by the Six tonegotiate is however highly improbable, though the Frenchwill no doubt attempt to impose delay.     But the more simpleand  jfcssaightf forward tfbe application the more likely it is to be acceptable to the Community and to inhibit opposition frominside it).(c) Some Ministers and officials of Community Governments -especially some Germans and Italians - profess to believethat further exploration is needed in order to provide anadequate basis for negotiation.    But see paragraph 9(i)above.
20.       The procedures involved in this course are that after theannouncement of the decision in Parliament, and a debate on it,and after consultation with EFTA and the Commonwealth, andbearing in mind the problems of tinring with regard to the Kennedy-Round (see the general considerations of timing in paragraph 29 below),the application should be made to the Chairman of the Community Councilof Ministers,,     The application could be presented in this country, and tothe Community, in a positive light as an historic decision offering the eec and ourselves the advantages of economic, technological and political development which would measure up to the role which Europe, if only forits own sake, should play in the world of the last third of our century,,After the Community has had time to consider and respond to thisapplication, it might be possible, if our application were made sufficientlyquickly, to arrange for an inaugural meeting to take place before the summer holidays, followed by negotiations proper.    It is difficult toestimate how long they would take, given the scope of-even a simplifiednegotiation, and given that we may meet with delaying tactics on thepart of the French.     Thereafter ratification would be needed by the parliaments of the United Kingdom and the Six members of theCommunity 0    It is difficult to see how the formalities necessary tocomplete our membership of the Community could be completed muchbefore the end of 1968, and more probably it would be early in 1969.21.       This timetable is highly relevant to a number of other considera-tions which are of special importance in the event of a decision to takeCourse D, though they are also relevant to Courses B and C in so far asthey might lead to negotiations for entry, albeit rather later thanCourse D.     The most substantial items among these considerations are the objectives we should be seeking in any negotiation for full membership, the progress of our own economic recovery and the likely development of the Community over the next few years;  butit will be necessary to consider also the outcome of consultations with the Commonwealth and EFTA and of the final negotiations in the kennedy Round,     We have already had some discussion of these andsome of them will require further discussion if we decide to followCourse D, but the more salient points need to be decided m principlenow,22,      As for our objectives, it is already clear from our discussions that we should need to aim at securing for New Zealand special arrangements to assure her export income over a period long enoughto make it certain that in practice this income will, in one way or another, be permanently assured.    For the rest of the Commonwealth,we should need to seek terms broadly similars mutatis mutandis, tothose provisionally agreed in the 1961-63 negotiations, and, inparticular, to carry over the offers then made of association for independent African and Caribbean countries and for most dependent territories, coupled with comprehensive trade agreements to cover the requirements of certain Asian countries.    We shall also need tomake arrangements in respect of the Commonwealth Sugar Agreement.For ourselves, we shall need to secure, again as a minimum, arrange-ments to reduce to tolerable proportions the burden the common agricultural policy will otherwise impose on our balance of payments and to assure the other points covered in discussion of C(67) 44,agriculture and the Common Market, including adequate transitionalperiods,    For other items we have discussed, notably freedom ofcapital movements, regional policies, free movement of labour andtariff adjustment, we shall need transitional periods and some under-standings to meet our special problems.
TOP SECRET &apos;     :  11523.      EFTA countries will expect us to assist them to become members or associate members and to avoid resurrection of the tariff barriersEFTA has abolished.     We should certainly do our best to ensure that other EFTA countries who wish to become members or associates ofthe e.c. are able to do so;  and we should not wish to reirnpose tariff barriers against such countries.    For such EFTA members as are unwilling, or prove unable, to accept obligations of Community member-ship or associate membership we should aim to achieve the most favourable timetable for the reimposition of tariffs.24.      In our view, the negotiating points should be kept as few and assimple as possible, confined to the items of major importance identifiedby the Cabinet&apos;s discussions.    In our view if this is done, there is a good prospect that the Six as a whole would find it very difficult to reject our application.    We should, however, at this stage, bear two things in mind.First, if we are to secure entry in time to particpate, de facto or de jure,in the critical formulation of Community policies over the next few yearsand, indeed, to achieve entry despite French opposition, it will benecessary to keep the negotiations as short and simple as possible.Second, our chances of securing good terms are much better as amember than as a candidate for membership (see paragraph (iii));and we should therefore, on both this and the preceding count,simplify so far as possible both our application and the subsequent negotiations.     The general reservations we made during our Europeanvisits will enable us to do this without curtailing our freedom during and after the negotiations.The Progress of our Economic Recovery25.      We have said that we would only enter the Community with a healthy economy and a strong balance of payments, and that we are determined to restore the strength and stability of our own economy.In view of the likely timetable for negotiations with the Communityset put in Course B (paragraph 6 above), there must be a delay until1968 or early 1969 before we could actually enter the Community, evenif we apply for negotiations at once.    In our talks with the Six, wetherefore said that, so far as our own economic situation was concerned,we should be ready to negotiate as soon as the Six were ready (C(67) 33,Annex, page 10).    Whether we seek to join the Community or not wecannot afford to permit a recurrence of the inflationary conditions andof the consequential deficit such as we encountered on assuming office;and, provided we do not do so but continue to develop the policies weare now following of controlled reflation with a better regional balanceand a reduction of Government overseas expenditure, we shall be doing all we can on our own to develop an increasingly sound economic position.26,      A separate memorandum is being circulated about the impact whichentry to the ESC might have on our balance of payments a.nd on our economy generally on the basis of certain assumptions.Development of the Community27,      It now seems likely that the proposed meeting of the Pleads ofGovernment of the Six at Rome, in connection with the 10th anniversarycelebrations of the signing of the Treaty of Rome, will take place about25th May,    If we were to decide to apply for entry, our application
lieshould be made before that meeting.    In other respects, however, themeeting is unlikely to produce any startling new developments.    Therehas been talk of re-launching the idea of discussions on political unityor some form of political consultation;  but we have been assured bymost members of the Community that no major developments may beexpected from this meeting.     There is, however, a much more substantial consideration.    The Community continues to developwhether or not we are inside it.     The common agricultural policyis now much more defined than it v/as at the time of the last negotiations.As the Community continues to develop and to settle its own policies, newproblems will be raised for us unless we, by gaining entry, can get into aposition to influence the development of these policies.28,      1969 is a particularly significant year in the development of theCommunity - their own &quot;transitional stage&quot; under the Treaty of Romeends with 1969.    Before the end of 1969 the Community must negotiatethe new agricultural financing arrangements to replace the existingones which lapse at the end of that year;  we have already discussed the importance of this factor.     The Yaounde Convention, which governsthe association of African States with the Community, and so is ofimportance to many members of the Commonwealth, expires at theend of May, 1969;  unless it were prolonged, negotiations to replaceit will have to begin well before this date.    La two major areas thereforewith-which we are concerned, our prospects of achieving satisfactorylong-term arrangements depend substantially on membership of theCommunity by that year - or at least upon our being so close to member-ship of the Community that we must be allowed a full voice in the renegotiation arrangements.    We must also remember that the EEChas already started discussions of a number of other communal policies^notably those on patents (important for technological development),commercial policy and transport policy,,    If we are right in thinking that a negative decision, or even an insufficiently positive decision,now might postpone our chances of entry until the period of the nextParliament, say 1971 or 1972, we might then find that entry at thattime presented us with greater problems and offered us less opportunityto influence Community policies in the more outward-looking directionswe (and for the most part, the Five, EFTA and the Commonwealth) would wish.Conclusions29.      We have set out in this paper the alternatives before us in regardto the approach to Europe, and their relative advantages and disadvantagesas these appear to us, with a view to their providing the basis, in the lightof all our previous discussions since last October, for a definitivedecision.    We now invite our colleagues to decide which of the fourcourses in paragraph 4 of this memorandum we should follow,30.   , It is our view that the right decision v/ould be to follow Course D,and make an early application for negotiation for entry.    In that event,we should make a new application, rather than seek to resume thenegotiations initiated by the previous Administration,    Clearly wecould not contemplate an unconditional application, i. e. one that fails to secure the minimum conditions for entry which our discussions areestablishing.     On the other hand to demand the prior acceptance of conditions before applying for entry would strengthen opposition to us
in the She and we might get the application returned &quot;invalid&quot;.    the statements we should make in connection with any application underalternative D should therefore stress our willingness to accept theTreaty of Home and the spirit and organisation of the Community,But in announcing to Parliament that an application in this form wasbeing made, we should make it clear that, as is generally known,there were a number of substantial problems that needed to be resolved as part of the process of British entry and that thesemust form the principal subject matter of the negotiations.    Whatthese are, the Cabinet has still to decide - there would appear to be some four or five, and they should be included in the parliamentary statement as the &quot;essential British and Commonwealth interests&quot;which should lie at the centre of our negotiations.H.W.G, B010, Downing Street, S.W.I.24th April, 1967


</content>
</cab>
