<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/129/0 images: 165-168</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY:S GOVERNMENT)C(67) 6427th April, 1967COPY NO.6CABINETSCOTTISH AGRICULTURE AND THE COMMON MARKETMemorandum by the Secretary of State for ScotlandThis memorandum attempts a br&amp;ef summary of the possibleimplications for Scottish agriculture of accepting the common agricultural Policy of the e.c. as it stands.    My reason for circulatingthis paper is to emphasise the crucial importance of the Hill and UplandSector not only in the Scottish farming structure but to the whale Scottisheconomy,2. The following table shows that of the 25,000 full-time units whichcomprise Scottish agriculture, 40 per cent are hill and upland farms andthey contribute about one-third of Scottish farm output.Broad Type Categories of Scottish Farming	No. of		Agi&apos;ic,	Area^	Type	full-time	Proportion	Crops &amp;	rough	Output	units	%	grass %	grazing %	%Mainly Dairying	6,925	28	31	5	33Arable	6, 640	27	32	2	28Intensive	1, 240	5	1	-	7Hill &amp; Upland	9,770	40	36	93	31Total	24,575	100	100	100	1003. These areas rely for their income almost entirely on the saleof store cattle and store sheep (for which there is no price guarantee)supplemented by the hill grants - the Hill Sheep, Hill Cattle and WinterKeep grants.    The hill grants are in effect a recognition that hill andupland farmers get little or no direct benefit from the price guarantee.The return from the market for store cattle and store sheep depends inthe final analysis on the strength of demand for beef and lamb and on thelevel of the guaranteed prices which the lowland fattener receives for theend product.
4, There seems a good prospect that the end price would improveboth for cattle and sheep under the Common Agricultural Policy (C. A. P. )and this would be a favourable factor for the hills and uplands since itwould tend to improve the store markets.     The factor which makes hilland upland farming extremely vulnerable is that their net farm income(on which these farmers have to live and finance their enterprises), andwhich for most farms is within the range of  75 0 to  1,5 00 per annum,is entirely dependent on production grants, essentially the three hillgrants.    Without the hill grants very few hill or upland farmers would show any profit at alL    Including the additional assistance given at the1967 Annual Review the hill grants now provide total assistance of about 9 million in Scotland.5. Apart from the hill grants, hill farms and particularlyupland farms obtain substantial benefit from the Calf Subsidy (andupland farms, until its recent abolition also benefited considerably from the Ploughing Grant - included in the above table under &quot;othergrants&quot;).    Taking all   the production grants together, the hill andupland farms are of course the main beneficiaries, since the arableand dairy farms get the direct benefit of the price guarantees.6, Speaking generally, the Border hill and upland farms are better endowed than their counterparts in the Highlands.    It is,however, a matter of degree.    If the hill grants were totally abolishedwithout any replacement, then there is no doubt that the vast majorityof hill and upland farmers would face a disastrous situation whichwould quickly result in a very substantial loss of confidence in the futureof farming in these areas the continued existence of which has consider-able social significance.    It would also have a pronounced impact onlowland farming systems since these latter areas would increasinglyhave to breed and rear their own store cattle and store sheep.7. The Scottish farming position in respect of the other maintypes, dairying, arable and intensive bears a much closer resemblanceto the circumstances in other parts of the United Kingdom, and may bebriefly summarised as follows.8. There are about 6,900 dairy farms mainly in the south-west of Scotland contributing about 33 per cent of Scottish output of whichnearly two-thirds is milk.     Possibly 40 per cent of our milk producersare on goodish land and are relatively large enterprises comprising about60 per cent of the total Scottish dairy herd.    The other 60 per cent of ourmilk producers comprising the remaining 40 per cent of the cows includethe upland dairies on inferior land and with on the whole smaller enter-prises, sometimes of a family kind.     The larger farms, after surmountingthe difficulties of adjustment, should be able to hold their own since theirstandard of management is generally high.     The smaller dairy farmslocated mainly in the central belt of Scotland - north Ayrshire andLanarkshire in particular - would be in very considerable difficulty and circumstances might well force many of them out of dairying and intolivestock rearing unless they could substantially enlarge their enterprises,-2-
9.     There are about 6^.640 arable farms, mainly in the east ofScotland, and mostly large or medium-sized units; they tend to be smaller in size and poorer in land quality in the North-east-    Arablefarms contribute between 25 and 30 per cent of Scottish output.    Of their main enterprises, cereals should become substantially more profitableand cattle and perhaps sheep fattening rather more profitable.Potatoes and sugar beet are uncertain and might go either way.     on balance this category of farming should gain and their main problem would be one of adjustment to the new conditions.    A reasonable transition period, together with replanning grants, would help with these problems.10.     There are about 1,200 Intensive units specialising in pigs, poultryand horticulture.     Generally, these forms of production would meetincreasingly severe competition, but given the necessary scale ofproduction and efficiency of management, the poultry and egg specialistsshould be able to meet the challenge.     In the case of bacon pig production(as distinct from fresh pork which is more an English speciality andenjoys a high degree of natural protection) the going is likely to be toughparticularly for the small and medium-sized producer, but the more efficient bacon pig specialist should survive.    Our raspberry growersshould at least maintain their position, but there is more of a questionmark concerning tomatoes.11.     The above more detailed assessment of the Scottish farmingsituation illustrates the need for the safeguards mentioned in Part II ofC(67) 44.    In respect of Scottish agriculture the vital safeguards are;-(a) retention of the hill grants without limit of time, either intheir present form or in some other form of roughlyequivalent worth;(b) replanning grants to assist those enterprises which havedifficult problems of adjustment during the transition period;(c) maintenance of existing arrangements for liquid milk;(d) a transition period of at least seven years.W. R.Scottish Office, &quot;Whitehall, S. W. 1.26th April, 1967


</content>
</cab>
