<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/129/0 images: 306-325</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2 77SECRET * 1 1THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY rS GOVERNMENT)bbC(67) 68 COPY NO.28th April, 1967CABINETTHE APPROACH TO EUROPE:INFORMATION FROM OVERSEAS POSTS ON THE ATTITUDEOF-FOREIGN COUNTRIES^OSt&quot;CONCERNED&quot;&quot;&quot;Note by the Foreign secretary the Cabinet on 20th April &quot;took note that the Prime minister would consult the Foreign Secretary regarding the circulation to theCabinet of information from overseas Posts on the attitude of. theforeign countries most concerned&quot; in our approach to Europe(CC(67) 22nd Conclusions, Minute 2)0     This followed discussion inwhich it was suggested that the Cabinet should have available to them the latest advice from our Embassies in the more important member countries of the Community as to the likely reactions of those countries to an early decision to proceed at once with a further development of the approach to Europe.2.      The Prime Minister and I felt that the best way of proceedingwould be to obtain a fresh and up --t o   the -minute assessment from our Ambassadors in the Community countries and Washington andfrom the Head of our Delegation to the Communities in Brussels,We did not think it necessary to consult our European Free trade association (EFTA) Posts, since the attitudes of our EFTA partnerswould be manifest at the Ministerial meeting of the EFTA Council on28th April.3.      The text of my telegram to our Ambassadors in e.c. Posts and washington and of their replies is at Appendix I.    At Appendix II is the record of my conversation about our approach to Europe with herr Brandt on 12th April which was also referred to in the Cabinet^discussion.G.B.Foreign Office, S. W, 1,28th April, 1967
Appendix   IA.        FOREIGN SECRETARY&apos;S TELEGRAM OPINSTRUCTIONS TO H.M. representatives in E.E.C.  POSTS AND WASHINGTON.P.O. Telegram No. 1 206 to Bonn of 2k AprilFor a forthcoming discussion with my colleaguesI should he grateful to have your assessment, in thelight of all the information available to you, including any recent discussions between British Ministers and ministers of the country to which you are accredited, ofthe likely reaction of that Government in the event of(a) H.M.G.&apos;s deciding, at an early date,  toapply for membership of&apos;the Ccfflpmunity.(b) Deciding not to proceed with the questionof membership of the Community, at least for the timebeing.(c) Deciding to pursue further bilateralconsultations with member countries of the community to seek further information and assurances before reaching a decision.2.        You should not consult the Government to which you are accredited in making this assessment.3.       It would be helpful to have also the assessmentby HMRR in Community posts of the extent of support which we might expect in the event of H.M.G.&apos;s deciding to apply for Community membership and how far they thinkan application could be successfully prosecuted.     Ishould be grateful for a considered telegraphic replynot later than the morning of Thursday, 27 April.k. I should be grateful for a reply fromSir J. Marjoribanks assessing not only the attitude ofthe Commission, but his view of the attitudes of community Governments, as seen from Brussels.B.        H.M. REPRESENTATIVES &apos; REPLIES.1 . Brussels Telegram No. 216 of 2k -april the answers to your questions are as follows.-(a)       An early application by H.M.G. for membership of the L.E.C. would be very warmly welcomed by the Belgian Government, assuming always that it was/ not
2.not accompanied by reservations or qualificationsgoing beyond what the talks which the Prime Ministerand you had with Belgian Ministers in February have ledthem to anticipate.       It would also be warmly welcomed by the main opposition party (the Socialists)and by the bulk of Belgian opinion.     Those whoearlier had reservations, due to the fear thatour accession might endanger what had already been achieved within the E.E.C. seem to have been reassuredby the statements by Belgian Ministers at the timeof your visit that none of the problems posed appearedinsoluble.(b) Such a decision would cause great disappointment to the Government and in the country&apos; generally? the more so because all recent reports from London have given the impression that a decisionto apply was now highly probable.       It would generally be interpreted as a decision to abandon hopeof joining the community, since it would be thoughtthat it would be extremely difficult to revive the momentum which has now been generated.     And M. Spaak&apos;soft-proclaimed view that time is not on our side is widely shared.      It would have the effect of turningthe attention of Belgian Ministers increasingly to developing and strengthening the community, withouttoo much regard for the outside world.      It wouldhave a very depressing effect on importers of British :\goods, many of whom have been holding on in the face of increasing tariff difficulties in the hope that weshall before too long become members of the community.(c) This too would be regarded by BelgianMinisters as a depressing outcome and would be taken as a sign that H.M.G. were halfhearted in their approach,.     Belgian Ministers do not consider in thelight of the visit of the Prime Minister and yourselfthat such further consultations are necessnyvat thisstage.2.        The Belgian Government would warmly support aBritish application insofar as they are able todo so.       They are however conscious that the weightwhich the;  alone, or the Benelux countries together,carry in the deliberations of the six is limited andwithout clear German and Italian backing, they mightsoon lose heart.       They would not wish to go tolengths which might risk breaking up the community.3. In my recent talks with M. Harmel, including an informal one at dinner a few nights ago, I have]been struck by his relative optimism.      He acceptsof course that the Q. eneral does not want us in, but he does not believe that a second veto would be possible.He thinks that the negotiations might prove verydifficult, but, perhaps because he is personally sovery keen to see us in the community, he seems reluctant to admit that they could fail.- o  o   o o   aThe Hague
2. The Hague Telegram Jjo...  156 of 25 AprilI assess the likely reaction of theNetherlands Government to the three alternative coursesas follows:(a) They would warmly welcome a decision by H.M.G,  to apply for members;ership at an early date.(b) They would be damaged by a decision notto proceed, even for the time being.       Thev would regard,it as missing what could be the lac,t chance of biddingfor membership and would be likely to interpret it as indicating that we were losing interest in the E.E.C.and groping for other solutions(c) I believe that they would be upset andpuzzled at a decision to pursue further bilateralconsultations, unless there were some clear indication that these would be likely to improve the prospects forour admission^    and they would be disturbed at theprospect of further delay in taking the decision ofprinciple.2. Briefly, the Netherlands Government want us inthe Community because they believe that this is essential for the healthy economic and political development ofEurope.       They have never wavered in this.      They haveno illusions about the difficulty of overcoming Erenchobjections to our entry, but they believe that delaywill only result in a hardening of existing positions and loss of momentum.       They fully understand ouranxiety to avoid a second rebuff, but they believethat we can play our hand to avoid this,3. In the event of a decision to apply for community membership we could count on maximum supportof Holland in pressing counsels of reason in paris and in encouraging solidarity among the other community countries.       Support would, however,  stop short of breaking up the six.     Hoi].and is admittedly a smallcountry and it is realised here that the attitude ofGermany is crucial, but the stature of Dr. Luns givesHolland added importance among the six, and he seemsto be developing increasingly close and intimaterelations with M. Couve de Murville.       The netherlands government fully realise that early success is problematicbut they regard our membership as a historical necessitywhich can in the end be achieved.     For this however they regard an early and straightforward bid for membershipas the essential preliminary./       3.Luxembourg telegram
3&quot; Luxembourg Telegram No.  65 of 25 AprilDecision (a) would be wholeheartedly approved onunderstanding that this means, that Britain claims no permanent special position, hut wishes to joinCommunity as an equal partner accepting the treaties and subsequent Community decisions subject only totransitional or other arrangements to meet specificUnited Kingdom difficulties as outlined by Prime Ministerand yourself during your discussions here.      these difficulties are sympathetically viewed and not regardedas- insuperable.       A British guarantee on recourse to article 108 would certainly be welcome.      Luxembourgsees Britain&apos;s &apos;propcr place as being within Europe andhopes that British membership would not only add strength to Europe but act as a balancing factor among partnersparticularly in any discussions on political cooperation,which is dear to their hear to as ultimate! y this is theonly guarantee of their independent existence.2. Decision (b) would hardly be understood.Werher at least believes that progress has been made andmany issues cut down to size, in this process thestatesmen of the Five have helped. To cry off now would disappoint our friends and fortify those whosuggested that we were not serious in our intentions.We have heard much lees since your round of visits than before it, of the view that the present time is notpropitious and that Britain is not yet European enoughto be an acceptable member.3. A postponement &quot;for the time being:i would beconstrued as lasting for our generation.       The general view is that the present momentum is an essential factorfor success.h. Luxembourg would sec no point in decision(c).     They believe that the main issues are now clear and that the next stage must be discussion on the basisof an unequivocal application.5. Luxembourg will give us support up to the crucial point at which it would be really useful.But I doubt if they -would go further and risk either aconfrontation with the French or damage to such cohesionas the Sommunity has already achieved.     They believethat provided we are modest in our demands and determined in pressing them success is possible as well as desirable.They themselves will certainly raise no new obstacles.k&apos; HiS. DeJ^qtiqji^^j^^ No. 88 of25: April.It is widely assumed in the Commission and asfar as I can judge amongst member Governments that H.M.G.will in the near future declare in favour of an applicationfor membership.       Interest here is concentrated on thenature and date of the statement and the indications itmay give about H.M.G.&apos;s minimum requirements and hopesfor the dates and methods for starting and finishing thenegotiations.
2. A decision on the liies of (b) in your telegramunder reference would be a great surprise, and a seriousdisappointment to our friends -such as the Dutch and ammuni-tion for those who have argued that we never have been properly &quot;European1&apos;.3. A decision on the lines of (c) runs the risk ifhaving consequences similar to a decision for *(b).      It isdifficult to convince anyone concerned with the Communitychat more bilateral consultations would provide trie best wayof furthering an application which must under the Treaty of rome be considered multilaterally.      Hence the risk that sucha decision would be regarded as a sign that we are not really serious.ho Apart from President Hallstein most members of theCommission expect and would welcome a decision on thelines of (a) in your telegram under reference.      I have heard that view from Rey, Mans holt, Colonaa, Levisandri andVon der Groeben.     Marjolin has never advocated delay inputting in an application althougn he has reservations aboutwider membership.       Hallstein would prefer to see lengthybilateral discussions between the Commission and thisDelegation.       I believe the Commission as a whole areassuming that an application is likely&apos;to be maae by us inthe next few weeks and they are prepared to acquiesce inthe view that this application will pose firmly thequestion of enlargement of the Community which if baulkedonce more will permanently damage the prospects of thecommunity system.      Our friends in the Commission wouldlike us to be very firm about keeping our application on the table until the problem is dealt with.5. The extent of the support we can obtain frommember Governments and the Commission and the chances of success vary inversely with the conditions we mayattach to our application.      If we can confine ourrequests to transition periods except for the special difficulties of sugar and New Zealand and rest on the argument that agricultural finance is,a problem which we canconsider Jointly with fellow members of the C ommunity afterentry, provided that suitable transitional arrangements can be made before then to relieve the balance of payments problem for the U.K., I consider that the French would find it difficult to block our application without revealingthat their veto was another arbitrary intervention of theGeneral.6. It seems generally accepted here that the FrenchGovernment will do everything possible to avoid taking such a drastic step in isolation.       They will probablyfirst try to make our effort run into the sands.     If theycan pick on conditions explicitly or implicitlj^ attachedto our application and force discussion within the Sixbefore they will agree to open negotiations,  they couldpostpone the opening of substantive negotiations until the turn of the year and would be well placed (as they arein the -jhair of -the Council of Ministers from January-June,1968) to run them on until after the summer of that year./       7     .... .The attitude ...
IICRET2 8 J7. The attitude of the Five will also bedetermined by the nature of our application.      If we make things easier for the French we shall make itharder for the F&apos;ive to support us.       Reductions in the degree of support they would offer could be expectedif we on our side give the French the occasion forinsisting on pre-discussions within the six before coming to the conference table with the UoK.8o. To sum up.       I consider that course (a)would be favoured by the majority of the Commission andby the five member Governments if cast as a straight-forward request for negotiations with a view to membership&quot;on the basis of article 237 of.the Treaty.5. Paris Telegram No. 363 of 26 AprilIn answering the questions in your paragraph 1we must still assume that the personal reactions ofGeneral dc Gaulle will determine those of the FrenchGovernment.    But wo should not lose sight of the factthat a number of French Ministers arc positively infavour of an early British entry provided that our approach is what they would regard as whole-hearted andunambiguous and that wo do not ask for unacceptableconcessions from the Six.      Senior Ministers in this group include M. Mcssmcr (who revealed his sympathieswith surprising frankness in his recent talk in london with the Minister of Defence), M. Joxe, who probablyoxorciscs as much influence as anyone on the Generaland is a good friend of ours, and M, Pisahl, who nowcarries greater responsibilities on the domestic front.M. Edgar Faure has shown an increasing interest inBritish entry since his private meeting with you herea year ago.    He should carry some weight on theagricultural side.    Even M. Debre, I am told, is nowin favour of Britain&apos;s entry as a moans of buildingan independent &quot;Europe&quot;.    Of the others, M. Pompidou,though personally not hostile, has boon noticeablydiscouraging recently, both in public and in private;and M. Couvc&apos;s advice will, I belieVe, be the leasthelpful to us.    But I would guess that support for our entry among his Ministers is sufficiently strong to bean additional element in making the General anxious toavoid any appearance of a French veto.2. Your paragraph 1 (a.).    Reports from the french ambassador in London and a study of the British pressmust by new have led the French Government to expectan early application by H.M.G,   The General would notbe pleased by this decision, but ho could hardly be surprised by it,    I would not expect o. sharply hostile reaction, but rather one of cautiously negativercsorvo.    Much would depend on the terms of theannouncement,  of any Ministerial statements accompanyingit or elaborating on it, and of any personal messagesent to the General.    French spokesmen would take any opportunity which public statements offered them tocast doubts on British readiness and capacity to enter the e.c. on terms acceptable to its present members./____The
7.The French Government would he likely to reserve their position ponding discussion with the Five.; for whichthey would call, and to play for time meanwhile.    Theymight for instance argue that there wore still dangerousuncertainties about our application which must be clarified before it could be accepted.3. Your paragraph 1 (b).    Reaction would probablybe one of scarcely disguised relief.   The decisions would be treated as confirmation of the view that whenit came to the point, Britain would be unable to adapther ways to those of the continental Six.    After the expectations which have now been built up, the decisions would lead the French Government to expect that the momentum of the British effort to enter tho e.c. wouldbe lost and any new attempt postponed for years ratherthan months.    The General would be encouraged to assertFrance&apos;s own leadership to ensure the solidarity of the six under French influence, and to promote his version of an independent  &quot;Europe&quot;.    He would, however, alsowish to maintain sufficiently close relations with britain to preserve such technological and othercooperation as suited France and to deter Britain fromthrowing in her lot permanently with America.A. Your paragraph 1 (c).    The General would preferthis to (a) since it would give him more time to buildup &quot;Europe&quot; the way he wants it while Britain was stillexcluded, and more freedom to argue with the Russiansthat rapprochement with France was more important tothem than rapprochement with Britain because Britaincarried less weight in Europe.   He could hardly oppose the proposed bilateral consultations, but the french would continue to play up the difficulties.    He mighttry to promote some new initiative -a Six which would makeit increasingly difficult for.thorn to entertain a Britishapplication later this year or in 1968.5. Your paragraph 3-     For The reasons explained abovI do not think that we can expect any support for our application from tho French Government as such.     Ibelieve, however, that provided always that it were madein the simplest possible terms with the minimum ofaccompanying conditions (whether expressed in the letterof application itself or Ministeral statements commenting on it), there would be a considerable volume of support for it in France.    In Parliament we could expect support from the Federation, from Locanuet&apos;s Centre Group andfrom Giscardiens.    Some, perhaps even many UvNvR.G-aullists are in fact favourable, but we could not count on their open support in Parliament.    In the Council ofMinisters itself there would be supporters.6. The chances of success for an application arevery hard to estimate from here.    It is first of all necessary that our minimum terms should he acceptable to the Six as a whole.    Then we must succeed inconvincing the General that British entry is in theinterest of France and of the kind of Europe he wants.The whole tenor of my last conversation with him on20 March makes me think that wo have not yet done/. . othis.
8.this.   Nevertheless I think that there is a chance that it could he done, though it would take time todo it.    I think it is probable that he has not yetmade up his mind.7. The problem is essentially to convince theGeneral that he is wrong in thinking that, howeverstrong British feelings towards &quot;Europe&quot; may now be,permanent forces  (necessites) will always make herturn towards Le Grand Larges    away from Europe and towards America.    This would require both personalcontacts and, since he would continue to watch Britishaction criticially and sceptically, consistent decisionsever the widest possible field of policy, political,economic and technological.8.        The Immediate objective must be to deter him from blocking negotiations or delaying them seriously.The negotiations themselves must bo so conducted as togive him no opportunity to represent plausibly thattheir success is impossible.    On the contrary ho mustbe brought to think that it is inevitable and the lesserevil.    If then he can be allowed to believe that it is his vision and leadership which has brought Britain into&quot;Europe&quot;, he may in the end yield with a good grace.6. Bonn Telegram No. 667 of 26 april the desire to sec the Community enlarged by the accession of Great Britain as well as other EPTAcountries was a main feature of the Government&apos;s policydeclaration to the Bundestag last December, and the significance of this objective for Kiesinger himself canbe seen in his remark to the Prime Minister yesterday that since 1950 he had worked for the participation of britain in the task of achieving European unity.    Per compellingreasons of self-interest, both economic and political,the Federal Government reflecting in this all three main political parties, German industry and trade unions andpublic opinion generally, is strongly in favour ofBritish membership of the Community.     But the attitudeof Prance puts the Germans in a dilemma.     Because of the priority given by the coalition government to theimprovement of Franco-German relations the many signs ofFrench opposition to British entry have affected Germanviews on the tactics and timing of a British application and explain the caution tempering undoubted Gormansupport and goodwill which you and the Prime Ministerfound during your visit to Bonn in February and which also characterised the Anglo-German discussions atK3nigswinter in March.2.        Brandt1s successful talks with you in London a fortnight ago showed that he now accepts that, in theevent of a British decision to apply for membership,the arguments for definite early action outweigh those previously advanced for delay until the autumn.    ThePrime Minister&apos;s talks here with Kiesinger and Brandtwere equally encouraging and showed that Kiesinger hasalso been brought round to this view.   My own/...  impression
impression of these talks is that Kiesinger has movedconsiderably, and is now more positive in encouragingH.M.G. to apply for membership and less pessimisticabout our chances of success.   An important factor was his impression that de Gaulle&apos;s opposition was now lessrigid than at their first meeting in January.3. Against this background my answers to yourquestions arc as followss-(a) An early decision by H.M.G. to apply for membership of the Community would be seen as anhistoric stop towards that strong, united and independent Europe which is a major goal of german foreign policy.    Certainly the Federal Governmentwould have preferred if possible to avoid any strain on Franco-German relations at this particular moment.It has, however, become clear to the Germans as aresult of cur recent talks in Rome, London and Bonnthat our decision, if in favour of accession, shouldbe taken and implemented quickly, and that their earlier preference for a slower timetable, basedpartly on genuine practical considerations but partlyalso on sheer reluctance to have to choose between london and Paris is unrealistic.      Both Kiesingerand Brandt have accepted that it is desirable that.M.G. should make its position absolutely clearbefore the Rome Summit.     The Federal Governmentcould therefore be expected to welcome our decision,though without any disposition to underrate thedifficulties and strains to which our move would be bound to give rise, both in Franco-German relations and within the Community itself.   The clearer andsimpler the application and the fewer the basicproblems for solution mentioned in this context,the stronger German support should be.(b) Such a decision would revive the suspicions ofthose, both within the Federal Government and outside,who have only recently become convinced of our determination to throw in our lot with continentalEurope.    It would deeply disappoint all those -Ministers,  officials, politicians, industrialistsand others - who have kept support for british entry alive during a period when Germany has beenbeset by many other grave problems.    It would alsostrengthen the tendency, already apparent, forexample, in the results of the recent meeting ofthe Finance Ministers of the Six in Munich, toalign German policies increasingly on those ofFrance, both in the further development of theCommunity and in other fields.(c) This course is in line with the advice we haveuntil recently been receiving from the federal government but Brandt (and apparently Kiosingcralso) have now accepted that it is no longercompatible with the case, which they accept, for keeping up the momentum, more especially beforethe Rome Summit of the Six.    It might well be interpreted as evidence of failing determination/...... or
10.or divided counsels in London, which could dogreat harm.h*&apos;        The robust statements of Brandt in Brussels on10 April, and again in the House of Commons and to thepress during his London visit, as well as the encouragingattitude of Kiesinger himself in his talks with the PrimeMinister, are clear evidence that we should have the full support of the Federal Government in Paris as elsewhere.Their support would not extend to bringing pressure toboar on the French, still less to contemplating any action which could break up or even temporarily paralyzethe Community.   Kiesinger has said on several occasionsthat such pressure would not work, and that his Governmentneither could nor would attempt to use it.    This is alsothe S.P.D. view.     But, short of this, the Germans would do their best to overcome French objections on all points on which they themselves were satisfied.     Wo could not of course expect them to make the running for us in Paris,but provided that our arguments and our requirements weredemonstrably reasonable in German eyes wo should find themready advocates of our cause.5.        The Germans never forget that the chances of anapplication succeeding depend upon President do Gaulle,whose ultimate decision nobody can predict, but they arereluctant to accept hew much their own actions mustinfluence this decision.   Kiesinger has said before thatfor de Gaulle tho question is one of timing.   Tho Germansdo not anticipate a second French veto, at all eventsah initio, but they are not optimistic about preventing the French using the Brussels machinery skilfully to delaymatters.   Hence their strong advice to keep any applicaticas short and as simple as possible.7.        Rome Telegram No. 3k5 of 26 AprilFollowing are my replies to your questions;(a) Tho Italian Government is publicly committed towork for British membership, which most Italiansregard as essential for a united and democraticEurope.   They will, I am sure, welcome an earlyapplication.    They have boon expecting a decision by H.M.G. since January last and I believe theywill be both pleased and relieved when the dye hasbeen cast.     There will still be some anxiety, moreamongst officials than in the Government, about thedifficulties ahead, especially in connexion withthe Rome Summit.     But if our application is madewith confidence and contains the minimum of conditions it will create a political momentumhere which will override these doubts.(b) I think that, the Italian Government would beaghast at a British decision not to proceed further.They would regard it as extinguishing for the fore-secable future their cherished hopes of a united,democratically stable, powerful Europe.   H.M.G.would be held to have rejected &quot;Europe&quot;, and tohave done so because the British people fearedto
11.to follow thorn at the critical moment.   TheItalians would then soc no choice hut to makethe best they could of the community of the Six,knowing that this would, make them the prisonersof de Gaulle so long as he lives, and probablyof Germany thereafter.    I think it fair to saythat, after the /&quot;&quot;grp, undec.    ?expectations^/aroused by the evolution of public opinion inthe United Kingdom and by the seriousness ofH.M.G.&apos;s approach over the last few months adrawing back now would be thought very near abetrayal.   This would be felt particularlystrongly by the Socialists.    We should find it very difficult if not impossible to rallyItalian support for a third try later on.(c)       The Italian Government do not see any pointin further bilateral consultations.   They cannot see what further assurances we could realisticallyexpect to extract from individual members of theCommunity.   A decision, therefore, to &quot;pursuefurther bilateral consultations&quot; would beconsidered here equivalent to an admission ofdefeat.    It would be regarded as evidence that.M.G. had now accepted the French view that thedifficulties were too great.    It might well bethought that wo had resigned ourselves to aEurope fashioned by de Gaulle.2. As regards your paragraph 3, I think we can beconfident that the Italian Government would support aBritish application and do their best during the nego-tint ions to make it succeed.    But they would not riskbreaking up the Community rather than see us fail.Their courage will be measured by our skill and determination and by the attitude of their other partners.In particular it will depend on our being able to showthat British entry will advance the Community1s develop-mont on the basis of its existing achievements, therebygiving no reasonable ground for Erench veto.   PresidentSaragat, who has great influence, -can be expected to throw his whole weight behind uss    so can Nenni and bothwings of the United Socialist Party.   Mora, the PrimeMinister, and less certainly Colombo, would also belikely to do their best.    Fanfnni too will help if he thinks it will assist his own advancement, i.e. if hejudges that success is possible.   Against these Gaullistinfluence will no doubt be exercised through the ExtremeRight in Parliament and in the Ministry of ForeignAffairs.3. But when all is said, a vigorous and confidentlead is, in Italy, half the battle.
8. Washington Telegram Ho. 1376 of 26 April(Note.    Paragraph. A of this &quot;telegram should be read in conjunction with the following extract from theForeign Secretary&apos;s conversation with Mr. Rusk on18 April in Washington;&quot;Mr. Brown asked whether the Americans thought that,if the Kennedy Round had not been completed by 8 May(which he made clear was for us the absolute deadline)and we went ahead with our application it would bepossible for this to be seized upon and, if the kennedy round broke&apos;   down (for an engineered or other reason),used as an excuse for this failure.    We did not thinkthat the French would argue that way, and this view hadbeen confirmed by H.M. Ambassador in Paris.Mr. Rusk said that it certainly could not be used as a reason, but might conceivably be made a pretext.Nevertheless he indicated clearly that his view, andthat of the others with him, was that we should not be deterred by this consideration.&quot;)There is no doubt that despite the preoccupationsrelating to international liquidity and the Kennedy Roundreferred to in paragraphs A and 5 below, a decision byH.M.G. to apply for membership of the e.c. would be warmly welcomed by the U.S. Administration as a whole.    It is their considered judgement that British membership wouldbe in the long-term interest of the United States becausethey believe it would lead, in time, to the creation of apolitically and economically strong and stable Europe,better able to contribute effectively to the achievement of the fundamental free world aims which are common tothe United States and Western Europe.    Conversely, adivided Western Europe would both compound the relativeweakness which militates against the achievement of theseaims, and increase the dangers of uncontrolled nationalism.In recent years the Americans have regularly   reviewed their original judgement that the economic^disadvantages to american trade interests entailed by wider economic&apos;integration in Europe will be outweighed by the political advantages.     Despite the strains imposed on theirpatience by unforthcoming European attitudes in the kennedy Round and international liquidity negotiations,they still regard this judgement as valid.2. Given this policy position, I am satisfied thatthe Americans would consider that the prospects for a successful British application would be improved if it ismade as soon as possible, and, conversely, that a loss ofmomentum would harm our chances.    Other things being equal,therefore, the Americans would strongly favour an earlyapplication and would tend to regard a decision to delaypending further bilateral consultation either as a tacticalerror on our part, or as evidence that we were less thanwholehearted in our approach.    Either judgement could, Ithink, have repercussions on their future assessment of ourvalue to them as an ally in the longer term.    This would apply even more strongly to a decision not to proceed withthe question of membership,/. * o * 3 *
/Appendix II3.        The Americans have few illusions about cle Gaulle1 attitude to British entry but thoy believe that we can and should make any French veto politically costly toFrance.    For this reason, thoy hope that wc would make our application as crisp and as unqualified as possible,and at the same time play up our interest in the politicalcontent of the e.c., thus minimising the opportunities forthe French to demoralise the Five in the course ofprotractod negotiations about&quot;conditions of our entry.1+. So far as the timing of our application is concerned,however, the Administration is bound to be concerned atthe possible effect on the Kennedy Round of a Britishapplication to join the e.c. if it wore to bo made beforethe negotiations were complete, which now seems unlikely to be before 15 May.     The Americans would certainly prefer the announcement of an application to bo delayed until afterthe conclusion at any rate in substance of these negotiations,if this could be conveniently arranged.    If, on the otherhand, the choice lay between an application before this date and a significant delay in applying, the state department and Mr. Rusk at least would, I think, favour anearly application.   Mr. Roth&apos;s office, however, consideringthe problem from the point of view of the tactical situationin Geneva, might well have some reservations, although they would probably eventually accept the State Department&apos;sjudgement on the wider political considerations involved.At all events, I feel sure the Americans would wish to begiven advance notice of our intentions 1    and, if anannouncement were to bo made before settlement of the kennedy Round, wo should discuss with them privately ways of mitigating its potentially harmful effects.    such discussions would certainly need to include Mr. Roth aswell as the State Department.5.       In view of the uncertain state of talks on inter-national liquidity in which we and the Americans have tended to find ourselves in the samo camp, the U.S.Treasury would at least hope that there would not be anyinterruption in their close cooperation with us arisingfrom the reserve currency roles of sterling and the dollar.Because of the sharp differences between the e.c. members and the Americans on certain aspects of the liquiditydebate and the patent desire of the U.S, to drum upsupport from third countries, the U.S. Treasury has somereservations on whether our entry would be in their best interests.    As in the case of the Kennedy Round, the americans would hope to be given some warning if therewore any likelihood of our modifying our stand on thosefinancial matters now under discussion, though thoy seemto regard it as inevitable that our policy from now onwill be to seek to find a compromise between the opposing&apos;points of view.
APPENDIX    IIEXT.; ACT FROM THE RECoRD OF MEETING BETWEEN TEEFOREIGN SECRETARY AND THE GERMAN FOREIGN MINISTERHELD IN THE FOREIGN UPFICE AT 3.uu P.M. on 12 APRIL,. I967Britain and the EECAfter welcoming Herr Brandt, Mr. Brown said that he andthe Prime Minister had given their Cabinet colleagues afull report of their round of consultations in Europe.The Cabinet had held two full meetings devoted to thissubject and there would probably be two or three moremeetings to come.    The Parliamentary Labour Party was also considering the subject.2.      Three problems arose.   Firstly we were under an obligation to consult EFTA, but could not risk embarrassingleaks,   We still had to work out the way in which consultationwith EFTA could best be organised.    Secondly he would welcomeHerr Brandt&apos;s advice on how we should proceed if we diddecide to apply to join the e.c.   Did Herr Brandt think thatthe proposed meeting of the Six Heads of Government shouldtake place before any application?   He would also be interested to know what the purpose of the meeting would be.    Thirdly,did Herr Brandt think that the Kennedy Round should be successfully concluded by 30 April?3*      Herr Brandt said that he&quot; appreciated the opportunityafforded by this visit of discussing various urgent problems.With reference to British entry into the e.c. the GermanPosition was well-known and had been outlined by him in brussels on 10 April.    The Federal Government hoped that britain and other EFTA countries would join the e.c., along the lines which had been discussed.    He had said in Paris/and o o0
and elsewhere that this corresponded with German interestsand there should he no doubt that this was the Germanposition-    It was also understood that the Federal Governmentwould have to discuss the question with those who haddoubts on the subject.   He would be seeing Mo Couve deMurvllle on 27 April in Bonn in the course of the regularquarterly consultations between fhe Foreign Ministers of thetwo countries.U.      The French had now proposed that the meeting of the six Heads of Government should take place between 20 and3&apos;.; May.    There would be a discussion on various problems(including perhaps the question of the fusion of theexisting executives though this, and the question ofHallstein&apos;s successor, would first have to be discussed between him and Mo Couve) but his impression was thatGeneral de Gaulle was not in favour of a fixed agenda.5o      He thought that everything possible should be done to conclude the Kennedy Round by 30 April or very shortly afterwards.He hoped that the problems between Britain and the e.c. could besettled satisfactorily within the next fortnight and that the newinstructions sent to the Commission would not cause difficulty.6.       In conclusion Herr Brandt said that when they heard what our plans were in connexion with membership of the Community theFederal Government would try to be as helpful as possible and to getthings started e/en if real discussions could only take placelater this year.    He enquired whether Mr.  Brown had been asking for his advice with regard to consultations with EFTA.7-       Mr. Brown explained that he was not asking for advice onthis point but had merely wished to draw it to Herr Brandt1 attention.    The problem was to work out a way of honouring our commitment to consult EFTA before any decision was taken and atthe same time keep in our own hands control of the date of any announcement.    If we did apply, it might well be that fhe/procedure.0.
procedure followed would lead to parallel applications by otherEPTA countries to join the Community and Herr Brandt might wishto consider the problems which this could raise.8.       Herr Brandt said that he supposed that Denmark, norway and the Irish Republic might apply at the same time.9,      Mr. Brown said that although there were divided views in sweden the Swedish Government might also well make an application.10.     Herr Brandt said that the prospect of a number of applications did not scare him,11.     Mr. Brown said that it might nevertheless affect general de Gaulle&apos;s attitude and Herr Brandt might wish to consider how this aspect could be handled.    It was, of course, not correct tothink that Britain, if she joined the e.c., and the other new members would represent a kind of separate block within theCommunity: there would be a. mach more fluid situation.12.     Mr. Brown said that against the possibility of early action by HMG it would be useful to be assured of German supportbefore the Rome meeting.    The British Government had to maintainthe momentum.13*     Mr. Mulley said that it was important to maintain the momentum not only in Europe but also internally.    It would create a very bad impression if through the requirement ofadapting to an external timetable the Cabinet were thought to be unable to take a decision on the question.14*     Mr. Brown enquired whether the Governments of the six would not expect to have a letter from H.M.G. on thesubject to discuss at the Rome meeting.15*     Herr Brandt said that if the Secretary of State wasreferring to a letter solely in the context of the Romemeeting, then it should be a letter to the six Governments butnot to the Community; the Rome Dieting was not part of theCommunity machinery.
Mi^^rojwi said that,  supposing a decision was taken   toapply Ior membership and ELM. G.  applied to the Council ofMinisters and informed the individual governments, the Romemeeting could presumably consider the subject.17-    Herr Brandt pointed out that the Rome meeting was nota meeting of the Council of Ministers;    General de Gaullecould refuse to agree to the matter being on the agenda andinsist on its being remitted to some other meeting.    HerrBrandt remarked incidentally that he would he Chairman of theCouncil of Ministers from 1 -July.    In reply to a questionhe confirmed that his view was that the submission of a formal written application was not so important as a publicpositive decision by H.M.G.  and that it would be helpful ifthe latter could be taken before the Rome meeting.IS-     Mr. Brown said that a public positive declaration would amount to the same as writing a letter.19.     Herr Brandt said that a public statement could be combined with letters of application to the six governments and the Chairman of the Council of Ministers.    Alternativelythe six governments could be told, of H.M.G&apos;s.  intentions and each individual Government could be informed that H.M. G. was ready for further bilateral discussions before actuallyputting in our application.    In reply to a question fromMr. Brown, he confirmed that the six governments would wishto held a meeting to discuss British entry which would notnecessarily be in the form of a meeting of the Council ofMinisters.    He agreed, rather reluctantly,  that  it could bediscussed at the Rome meeting.20&apos;     Sir 0.  01 He ill pointed out that if H.M.G. made anapplication before the Rome meeting&apos; the Heads of Governmentwere under no compulsion to discuss it.    But until any application was made there was no question of the CouncilUJ- ministers discussing it;    but they would have to do sobefore long once application had been made.SECRET
21.    Herr Brandt then said that a telegram hearing on these aspects had just been received from the German Embassy inParis.   According to this telegram General de Gaulle was willing to discuss various problems in Home without anyfixed agenda.    These were listed as the development of theCommon Market into an economic union, the fusion of theexecutives, East-West relations and other problems.    It wasonly the question of British membership that the General wouldnot yet consider a suitable subject for discussion at theconference table in Some,    If the other members of theCommunity agreed with these ideas, General de Gaulle would attend the Rome meeting.   Herr Brandt thought that this information was in line with what M. Alphand had said at thetime of the W.E.U. meeting in Rome about the need to findways and means of discussing the question of British entrywithout doing so officially at the conference table.    (On a subsequent occasion Herr Brandt said that the information about the French attitude contained in this telegramcome from Italian sources.    He therefore added that itshould be treated very confidentially).22.    Mr. Brown said that if a British application was made before the meeting it would, presumably be hard to give general de Gaulle the assurance that he needed.    If theGeneral was allowed to prevent discussion of any application,this would amount to a veto right at the beginning and wouldhave very harmful effects.    If an application had been madethe time of the Rome meeting the General could, surelynot prevent at least a procedural discussion of how it shouldbe handled.    If this opportunity was missed we should find ourselves in the holiday season.23.    Herr Brandt said that the Federal Government would consider the matter in the light of later knowledge of theBritish position.


</content>
</cab>
