<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/129/0 images: 425-432</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(67) 78COPY NO.6 49th May, 1967CABINETSOUTH ARABIAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsIntroductionMy colleagues agreed on 16th March (CC(67) 13th Conclusions,Minute 3) that Her MajestyJs Government should put proposals for south Arabian independence by 1968 to the Federal Government.    The(a) The Federal Government should be told that we wished to arrangeindependence on 1st November, 1967.(b) They should also be told that we could not (as they had asked)surrender sovereignty in Aden Colony, or the control of internal security there, before independence.    We recognised, however, thatthe Government of independent South Arabia would face very difficult problems if it secured control of Aden and full independence on the same day, at the time of subversive attack on them supported from the Yemen,where major Egyptian forces would remain.    We would be ready to meet their most acute apprehensions on this by -(c) stationing a composite naval force off South Arabia for up to six months after independence on 1st November.    This would be to deterexternal aggression and to counter attack of organised foreign militaryaggression nevertheless occurred.    We were not however prepared toplay any role over internal security after independence or to stationforces on-shore,2.       The following developments, in chronological order, have takenplace since(a)    On 17th and 18th March, Mr. Thomson put the proposals to theFederal Supreme Council.     The spirit of the offer was welcomed, but its content was not.    The Federation did not think a purely navaldeterrent would be credible;   clearly doubted whether we would in theevent commit it against actual aggression;  and considered that a six months commitment would in any case only postpone the evil day by too short a time to solve their problem.     Mr. Thomson pressed theFederal Government to think hard about an offer which constituted, forus, a difficult modification of our defence review decision that thereshould be no defence commitment of any kind after independence.    TheFederal Government eventually agreed to think it over for one month.essentials were-
(b) The United Nations Mission went to Aden on 2nd April.    the terrorist organisations demonstrated their ability to dictate a completestrike, to mount a maximum effort of violence, and to ensure that theirboycott of the Mission was widely observed.    The Mission, as mycolleagues know, achieved nothing and left after less than five days.In subsequent discussion at Dorneywood it emerged that the Missionexpected us to stay in South Arabia for as long as required to ensurethat the United Nations resolutions were made effective.    This could easily mean years rather than months.    We must continue to keep theUnited Nations in play, but this particular Mission will not in fact helpmuch.(c) We have made repeated efforts, at Ministerial as well as official level, to get the &quot;Front for the Liberation of Occupied South Yemen&quot;(FLOSY), particularly Al Asnag, first to give at least minimumco-operation to the United Nations Mission, and secondly to talk with usabout the future.(d) For reasons and in circumstances the Cabinet know,Lord Shackleton went to Aden.    He reinforced our efforts over FLOSYand eventually made approaches to both Makkawee and Asnag.    Theonly response to these (after an initial expression of willingness onAsnag&apos;s part but not Makkawee&apos;s) has been a blank refusal to talk on any basis short of recognition of FLOSY as the sole organ representative ofSouth Arabia.    This is neither true nor possible to pretend.    TheUnited Arab Republic (UAR) Government have professed to regretFLOSY&apos;s extreme attitude.    This is probably true where F.LOSYJsboycott of the United Nations is concerned, but there is no sign thatthe UAR is trying to call off violence;  on the contrary, it continues tosupport FLOSY and to supply the terrorists.    There are currentindications that the more extreme FLOSY leaders like Basendwah standhighest in Egyptian favour.(e) On 27th April the Federal Government replied in writing to our proposals at 2(a) above.    They reject independence on 1st November,1967.    They now say that their ground forces will not be ready for their full assumption of internal security responsibility until 1st March, 1968,and (accurately) that their naval and air arms will be ready onlymonths after that.     They say that they will accept independence on1st September, 1968, but provided that:-(i)  v/e turn over internal security in Aden State fully to them on1st March, 1968;(ii)  British forces remain in support in Aden State until 1st September, 1968;(iii) we extend them a Defence Guarantee for up to three years after1st September, 1968;(iv) we can get a new constitution in force well before 1st September, 1968.This package is unacceptable to me and, I imagine, to my colleagues.
3.       Lord Shackleton returned here to report on 27th April.    I should like at this point to pay tribute to the energy and resource which lord Shackleton and his officials have shown in achieving so much inthe very few weeks in which they have been in South Arabia.    Apartfrom the efforts over FLOSY mentioned above, they have been in touchwith the Federal Government and other political groups and withextremist elements other than FIiOSY.    In all this they have of coursehad the full support of the High Commissioner.Problem4.       Lord ShackletonJs report confirms the impressions I had formed from other reports from Aden.    The pressures on the federal government are such that its chances of survival after our departureare very shaky unless it can somehow attract effective support from outside its ranks.    The public estimate of its chances is a major factor in getting such support, and the degree of foreign backing it isthought to have in turn affects that estimate.    More than two years of intensive intimidation have, as v/e knew, paralysed political life in aden.    In the last lap towards independence, the contrast between ourimpending departure and the continued Egyptian presence in the Yemenis further sapping confidence and resolution.    The success of the strike and disorders over the United Nations Mission has made mattersworse, despite the marked achievement of our forces in controllingthem with the minimum loss of life on either side.    The fact that the terrorist groups are now assassinating one another does not restore the confidence of Arab politicians and officials who risk being shot by either side.    There is deepening demoralisation in the Arab and eventhe British public service, and senior Arab officials have shown an increasing tendency to go on indefinite leave or resign.    The starkestalternatives would be either to cut our losses and get out as quickly aspossible whatever the consequences;   or to undertake to stay until the egyptians leave the Yemen.    Our decisions over the Defence Reviewrule out the latter alternative.    The former, and its consequenceslocally, would bring such discredit upon us that I am reluctant to contemplate it.     We must therefore make further efforts to improvematters.    Lord Shackleton entirely agrees.5.       In practical terms, this means further efforts towards the twoobjectives v/e decided in December.     The first is to ensure that thereis an effective government in the territory while we complete our military withdrawal.    From this point of view Lord Shackleton arguesthat on his return to Aden it would be difficult to tell the federal government that they must take or leave our offer in March as it stands.    We have admittedly warned them that if we cannot agree withthem on the date of independence v/e have, and must exercise, thepower to declare one.    But to face them with 1st November, 1967,despite their radical dissent might take much of the remaining heartout of them.    They might disintegrate or at best fall into passivesullen resentment.    Their forces might then deteriorate if not turnhostile.    Our withdrawal would be impeded if that happened and, ofcourse, the ensuing situation after independence would be disorderly,to our discredit,    There is, therefore, a case for going back to thedate of January, 1968, on which my colleagues decided in December, oreven a little later (the High Commissioner has mentioned 1st Februaryas a date which would both give the transformed Federal forces a littlemore time to shake down, and a little more time for any constitutionalprocesses v/e may be able to promote).
6.       It can be argued that deterioration has gone so far that a shortextension of this kind would not be of any real advantage to the federal government,    But, in the main for no fault of theirs, over twomonths have gone by without progress since my colleagues last considered the matter.    Our forces would also find it a little easier to get out in good order if they had two additional months to complete the process.    And if there is any chance that short extension will help over the political prospects we should not lose it.    On this basisI recommend that we should revert to an independence date for south Arabia of January, 1968, which for practical purposes wouldmean a date between 1st January and 15th January;  and that we should inform the Federal Government that we shall be prepared to use ourlegal powers to impose this if they cannot agree to it.7.       I understand that the composite naval force which v/e offered for six months from 1st November could, though with greater difficulty, be available and fully effective for six months from thebeginning of January.    For the same first reason of trying to holdthings together until we go, I recommend that it should be offeredaccordingly to the Federal Government, on the same conditions as before (paragraph 1(c) above).8.       The Secretary of State for Defence and I are considering whether we could also offer a strike capability by bomber aircraftbased on Masirah and Sharjah, perhaps for a rather longer period.This offer might serve to clinch the deal if the Federal Governmentwere already disiDosed to accept it, and it will be examined further.9,       Neither Lord Shackleton nor I think that these measures could at best achieve more than the first object of holding things togetherwhile we get out.     Our second objective, which is to give the new state a chance of survival after our departure, requires more.     Theessential here is political improvement.    The possible courses seemto me to be;(a)    A real broadening of the Federal Government into an all-embracing caretaker government including FJLOSY, theNational Liberation Front (NLF), the South Arabian league and the Eastern Aden Protectorate&apos;(EAP) States.    I amseeking to arrange round table discussions in a final effort to achieve this and are trying to get the United Nations tohelp and participate, and even better, take an initiativethemselves.    I must however warn my colleagues that the chances are slim in the extreme.    FLOSY seems to beobdurate against it.    The UAR have no obvious interest in promoting it.    The other political parties are afraid of anything which will bring terrorist attention to them.    TheUnited Nations Mission spoke unrealistically of &quot;dissolving&quot;the Federal Government before any central caretakergovernment could be formed; we have no legal power to do this.    The Mission also suggested that if we failed to bringthe EAP States into the caretaker government they could not look at. any less comprehensive solution, however good initself.    This is equally unrealistic: the best must not bethe enemy of the good, and the EAP states seem likely toremain on the fence for much the same reason as the political parties.     Yet such United Nations views could again inhibitthe rapprochement the situation requires.
(b) Rapprochement between the Federal Government and FiLOSY.The Federal Government have said they would play: FJLQSYhave said they would not, but bilateral talks, which I amcontinuing to pursue, might still bring them round.    Aswithin course (a), we should be dealing with a future powerreality, inasmuch as FLOSY has Egyptian backing which is going to remain a powerful factor.    FLOSY support is however mainly Adeni, and largely Yemeni in Aden at that:it cannot carry the whole territory.    Resistance to FILOSYafter independence might involve civil conflict.(c) Rapprochement of all concerned except FLOSY.    This wouldgive us a wider based government especially if it could include representatives of the EAP states, but would carry the disadvantage (unless the Egyptians changed their course) thatEgyptian-supported terrorism v/ould still operate from itsbase in the Yemen.(d) Rapprochement between leading elements in the federal government and FLQSY&apos;s rival terrorist organisation, theNational Liberation Front.    The NLF has few well knownleaders and none of international stature.    But in theinternecine struggle recently it has shown signs of getting the upper hand over FLOSY in Aden.    It is opposed to egyptian domination, which in political terms, like Yemeniassociation, is a handicap to FLOSY within South Arabia.There is some evidence that elements of the Federal forces and the NLF see common ground.    We have had clearindications from some Federal Ministers that they are intouch with the NLF, and the latter have also spoken of thesecontacts.    This is not a development we should promote,but it may come about naturally, and then win wider support.If it does come about, and if the other courses above have failed, we could live with it as helping to keep a semblanceof authority together until our withdrawal is complete.Just conceivably, evolution of this kind could go so far as tooffer a chance that the new State could survive after independence.   Given the unpromising prospects of the othercourses, I recommend that we should do nothing to impedethis evolution and should where possible and desirablefacilitate it if it develops by itself; for example by some relaxation of emergency measures after the Services1families have left.(e) To continue backing the Federal Government.    This we areinevitably doing till something better emerges.    But neitherthe population nor the Federal Government themselves find it credible enough for the future to be decisive.    And ourdeclarations in favour of broader government have made theFederal Government seem provisional only.
10.       Lord Shackleton has argued that, if we are to hold a governmenttogether till independence, and if we are to give South Arabia a realchance of independent survival thereafter., we should be prepared to go further.     He thinks that there would be a case, if internal securitycould first be improved, for land-based RAF fighter aircraft rotatingto Khormaksar (Aden) airfield after independence, because of theirgreat psychological effect on the morale of the South ArabianGovernment; and for surrendering control of internal security in Adenitself a few months before independence, because of the chance itwould give the South Arabian Government to tackle its own problems.But in his view both these proposals must be contingent on the establish-ment of a much broader-based government which in our judgment was likely to survive and so be able to maintain effective control.    I donot however recommend these courses.    We are accountable inter-nationally for our declared intention to remove the base on independence,and to Parliament for internal security in Aden Colony untilindependence.    Moreover, Lord Shackleton would attach less importance to this proposal if it proved possible to make the offer ofland-based bomber aircraft from Sharjah and Masirah.11.       I should add that Lord Caradon came over on 5th May to talk tome and to Lord Shackleton about the problem from the United Nationspoint of view, and that he concurs in my reasoning about the united nations aspects.12.       I have also had to consider, and have now taken, a difficult decision over personalities.    The High Commissioner,Sir Richard Turnbull, has held his post for over two years.    He hashad a very difficult time.    He has brought imagination, hard work anda wealth of administrative experience to his task.    None of it has been to much avail against the background of terrorism and that of ourimpending departure    He is now a tired man, yet the months aheadare likely to be the most difficult yet,, when different qualities ofinternational experience and flexibility   also seem required.    I havehad this in mind since the end of February but there could be noquestion of a change on the eve of the United Nations Mission, whosearrival was then expected at any time..    Since then Lord Shackletonrsreport has confirmed my feeling   that a change is needed.     I have therefore recalled Turnbull and arranged for Sir Humphrey Trevelyanto take his place.    Trevelyan, as my colleagues will know, has the ability for the job and experience varying from the Indian Civil service to being H. M. Ambassador in Moscow, Baghdad, and - far from least -Cairo at the time of Suez.    I shall inform Parliament after our meetingon Thursday but am trying to keep the change secret until then,13,       In summary, I should like my colleagues:-(a) to agree to the suggested change in our plan since March:independence in January, 1968 instead of 1st November, 1967,    Thiswould have the consequence that the naval deterrent force would be offered for six months from January, not November^(b) to agree that the Federal Government must be told that this is our firm decision;-6-
(c) to note that the courses before us are those at paragraph 9 above and that the first we must try is the convening of a round-table conference, if possible with United Nations help, in a final effort tosecure the co-operation of all political elements in the territory;(d) to note that I propose to introduce an Independence Bill in June,for enactment before the Summer Recess; and that we must be readyto announce our policy fully in the debate on the Second Reading of that bill, probably in the second half of June,G. B,Foreign Office, Su W. 1,9th May, 1967-7-


</content>
</cab>
