<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/47/1 images: 12-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 101.11th February, 1944.WAR GABINET.FOREIGN-LANGUAGE PERIODICALS.Note by the Minister of Information.SOME doubts were expressed at the meeting of the War Cabinet on the4th February last (W.M. (44) 15th Conclusions) about the position of the variousforeign-language periodicals published in this country and about His Majesty&apos;sGovernment&apos;s relation to them. , In particular, the question was raised why this or that publication is not suppressed if it persistently attacks another ally orotherwise imperils Allied unity. Accordingly, the following brief notes are circulated in an attempt to summarise the position.B. B.Ministry of Information,11th February, 1944.1. The only general power of suppressing publications in this country is that given to the Home Secretary by Defence Regulations 2 (c) and 2 (d). The basisof this right of suppression is that a publication is &apos;&apos; fomenting opposition to the prosecution to a successful issue of any war in which His Majesty is engaged.&quot;The sins of these periodicals, however, hardly come within this category.2. Nearly all these foreign-language periodicals have come into existencesince the outbreak of war to meet the needs of the foreign refugee communities.But it is only since the 16th August, 1940, that a licence to publish has been necessary. -Such licences are obtained from the Ministry of Supply on therecommendation of another Government Department (in the great majority ofcases the Ministry of Information) and can be revoked on notice. It follows thatif a periodical which was first published after the 16th August, 1940, ceases tojustify its existence, as by continually fomenting Allied discord, it can be suppressed by revocation of its licence. This power has been resorted to on occasions when a periodical has become unsatisfactory. But unfortunately some ofthe troublesome productions date from before the 16th August, 1940. Their rightto publish is the same as that of any other organ of the free Press in this country.3. The right to publish is quite distinct from the right to get paper to usein publishing. In general, the amount of paper that periodicals may consume is limited by general regulations of the Ministry of Supply. But the specialcircumstances attending these war-time foreign-language periodicals, with nopre-war datum line, have led to a system under which their paper consumptionis regulated by ad hoc directions of the Ministry of Information, and the paperstocks required are debited to the Ministry of Information and remain itsproperty. If a periodical under this regime pursues an unsatisfactory editorialpolicy it is within pur power to deprive it of all connexion with His Majesty&apos;sGovernment by declining to approve of its further publication and withdrawingour paper stocks. At least then it does not receive our support. Moreover, ifit was first published after the 16th August, 1940, it necessarily disappears.Bat if such a periodical can continue to publish without licence (as it can if itwas first published before the 16th August, 1940), the withdrawal of HisMajesty&apos;s Governmenfs support does not necessarily involve its disappearance.Paper may lawfully be obtained in the market and production continue withoutthe Governmenfs being able to prevent it. The only difference would be that suchproduction would normally be of a reduced number of copies, since the generallimiting provision applying to all periodicals&apos; paper consumption would give a lower output than that permitted by special Ministry of Information concession.[26918]






</content>
</cab>
