<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/26/0 images: 98-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY  OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1953.secret.C. (53).9th conclusions copy No.  4 ICABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W.I., on Wednesday, 11th February, 1953, at 630 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor   the   Home   Department   and&apos; Minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton.M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl Alexander of tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.Also present:The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury.Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. G. Mallaby.ContentsNo. Subject Pa8e1      Sudan ... .......^702     Egypt    ...      ... &apos;      . \:&quot;;.:.:;/;V; //&quot;V     713      Corporal Punishment  ...      ...       .....
1. The Foreign Secretary recalled that on 3rd February theCabinet had approved the text of a telegram to Her Majesty&apos;s Ambas-ambassador in Cairo setting out their requirements on the two major pointsthen outstanding in the negotiations with the Egyptian Government onthe future of the Sudan, viz., safeguards for the Southern provinces and control over the replacement of British officials in the Sudan. Asa result of his further discussions with the Egyptian Government the ambassador had now obtained satisfaction on both these points. Thelatest draft of the proposed Agreement included safeguards for theSouthern Provinces which were acceptable to the Governor-Generalof the Sudan; and it provided that the replacement of British officials should be subject to review, if necessary, by an International Corn-mission. Having thus secured acceptance of the conditions laid clownby the Cabinet, the Ambassador had provisionally arranged to initialthe final text of the Agreement on the following day. The foreign secretary had considered whether this could be delayed for a day,in order to give the Cabinet longer time in which to examine the final text. But the Egyptians would not be willing to sign the agreement on a Friday, which was their Sabbath, and signature on a Saturdaywould involve publication some time before an announcement couldbe made in Parliament. The choice, therefore, lay between authorising the Ambassador to initial the Agreement on the following day, orpostponing its conclusion until early in the following week. TheForeign Secretary was reluctant to accept so long a postponement;for the Egyptian Government were subject to strong pressure to adhere to the agreement which they had concluded with the Sudanesepolitical parties, and any delay on our part at this stage involved therisk that they would withdraw some of the concessions which we hadextracted from them in the negotiations. The Sudanese were determined not to lose this opportunity of concluding an agreement which included Egypt&apos;s renunciation of her claim to sovereignty overthe Sudan a claim which all previous Governments in Egypt had maintained since 1819. The draft Anglo-Egyptian Agreement whichhad now been evolved was much more satisfactory, from our point ofview, than the agreement which the Egyptians had made with the sudanese political parties some months ago; but that agreementequally involved Egypfs renunciation of her claim to sovereignty overthe Sudan, and the Sudanese would certainly insist on standing bythat if we lost the present opportunity of concluding a more satis-factory agreement on an Anglo-Egyptian basis. In that event, weshould find ourselves opposed by both the Egyptians and the Sudan-ese, and we should be powerless to prevent them from going forward on the basis of their earlier agreement.The Prime Minister said that he was gravely concerned about the reception of the proposed Anglo-Egyptian Agreement by publicopinion in this country. He had received disturbing reports of a dis-cussion on this subject which had been held by the Foreign Affairsgroup of Government supporters in the House of Commons. All but avery small minority of those present at this meeting had been highlycritical of the Governments handling of the Sudan situation. there seemed to be widespread anxiety about this among Government sup-porters ; and, from what he had heard, he doubted whether the foreign secretary&apos;s proposals would command a sufficient measure of support in the Conservative Party. He feared that the proposed agreement would be represented as an ignominious surrender of our responsi-bilities in the Sudan and a serious blow to British prestige throughoutthe Middle East. He believed that it would be sharply criticised bythe Press. It seemed likely to involve the Government in serious political difficulties, which would doubtless be exploited to the fullby the Opposition. He would, therefore, prefer that no decision should be taken until early in the following week, by which time itwould be easier to forecast the probable reaction of public opinion in this country.In discussion it was pointed out that the proposed agreement was the logical outcome of the long-standing promise to confer on
othe Sudanese people the rights of self-government and self-deter mina-tion. The expectation had been held out to the Sudanese that theywould achieve self-government by the end of 1952. It was against this background that the terms of the proposed Agreement wouldhave to be defended to public opinion in this country. And it wouldbe much easier to defend the Agreement which we had now negotiatedwith the Egyptians including, as it did, satisfactory safeguards forthe Southern Provinces and reasonable provision for the replacement of British officials in the Sudan than be forced to accept the much less satisfactory arrangement which the Egyptians had negotiated withthe Sudanese political parties behind our backs. There was no doubtthat the latest draft of the Anglo-Egyptian Agreement was a great improvement on that: several valuable concessions had beenextracted from the Egyptians in negotiations during the past fewweeks. Nothing would now be gained by delay. Apart from therisk that the Egyptians might withdraw some of the concessions whichthey had made, it was in our interests that the negotiations shouldnot be drawn out any longer; for it was most desirable that the sudanese elections should be held before the onset of the rainy season,and this could not be done unless the preliminary arrangements were completed by the end of February.At the same time, the Cabinet recognised the importance of satisfying Government supporters, before any public announcement was made, that the balance of advantage lay on the side of concludingan Anglo-Egyptian Agreement in the terms now proposed. Therewas undoubtedly a great deal of misunderstanding and uncertaintyon this question among Government supporters in the House of Com-mons. The Foreign Secretary had originally proposed to authoriseHer Majesty^ Ambassador in Cairo to initial the Agreement on thefollowing morning, and to explain its provisions to a private meetingof Government supporters in the early afternoon before making apublic announcement about it in Parliament. It was, however, thegeneral view of the Cabinet that it would be preferable for the foreign secretary to explain the position to a representative meeting of Gov-ernment supporters interested in foreign affairs, and to satisfy him-self that he would be able to command their support in the course which he proposed, before the Cabinet finally decided to authorisethe conclusion of the proposed Agreement. In order to avoid delay,this meeting might be held that evening.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to explain the proposed anglo-Egyptian Agreement on the Sudan to a repre-sentative meeting of Government supporters interested inforeign affairs to be held at 9 -30 p.m. that evening.(2) Agreed to take a final decision on this question later in the evening when the Foreign Secretary had reported theresults of the meeting to be held in accordance with conclusion (1) above.Egypt. 2.   At the Prime Ministers request, the Minister of Defence(Previous explained to the Cabinet the disposition of British and Egyptian forcesReference: in Egypt and the nature of the operations which would be under-G.C. (53) 5th taken by British troops if, as a result of a breakdown in the negotia-Conclusions, tions with the Egyptian Government, there was an outbreak of minute 10.) disorder in Egypt involving attacks on our positions in the canal zone, whether by guerrilla forces or by Egyptian military units.
corporal punishment.(previous reference:C.C. (52) 99thConclusions,Minute 8.)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland (C. (53) 51) regardingthe attitude to be adopted by the Government towards a private member^ Bill designed to empower superior courts to order corporal punishment as a penalty for felonies involving personal violence.The Home Secretary said that, as explained in the Appendix toC. (53) 51, this Bill had serious technical defects: as drafted, it wouldnot achieve its purpose, and it could not be made to do so by amend-ments introduced in the Committee Stage. He proposed that, in theSecond Reading debate on 13th February, the Government spokes-man should take the line that this was not a good Bill, because of thetechnical defects to which he had referred, and also that this was nota good time at which to propose the restoration of corporal punish-ment, because there had not yet been a sufficient opportunity to judge the effect, as a whole, of the new methods of treatment introduced by the Criminal Justice Act, 1948. The decision would be left to a free vote of the House, but he hoped that members of the Govern-ment would not vote contrary to the advice given by theGovernment spokesman.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that in the debate on the Criminal Justice (Amend-ment) Bill on 13th February the Government spokesman should advise the House in the terms proposed inparagraph 3 (b) and (c) of C. (53) 51.(2) Agreed, that in the Division at the end of the Second reading debate on this Bill Government supporters should beallowed a free vote.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,12th February, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
