<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/26/0 images: 394-404</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1953SECRETC.C. (53)50th ConclusionsCABINETCopy No.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Tuesday, 25th August,&apos; 1953, at 3 p.m.-    &quot; V- Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the&apos;Chair).The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil. ..The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary, of State for commonwealth relations.&apos;The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and Local/Government.&apos; .. 1 ,The Right Hon. Sir &quot;David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and Minis-ter for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,&apos; M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.G., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,.   M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,&apos;   Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. J. P.. L. Thomas, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty (items-6):The Right Hon. Lord De L&apos;Isle and dudley, Secretary of State for &apos;Air,(Items 1-6).The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Items 1-6).The Right Hon. Henry Hopkinson,M.PL, Minister of&apos; State for colonial affairs (Items 1-6). -Lt.-General Sir Harold Redman, Vice-Chief of the Imperial&apos;General Staff(Item I).-Secretariat :    - .The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.
Contents .Minute&apos; No. .  - Subject.&apos; Page.1      Kenya    ... ...      ...      ...      ...    1012    &apos; North Atlantic Council     ,   ...   .&apos; ... &apos;   . ...      ......     10.military Planning. - i .3      Germany         ...      ......-   &apos;         ...      ....... 102Four-Power Meeting.. 4&apos;    Persia    ...&quot;          , .,. &apos;   ... 103&apos; 5 \6 .   Egypt &apos;      .    .... f ..&apos;  .,.      ... .    .:. 104,7.    Match Industry ... ...  &apos;  ...      ... :   .......... -T05; 8      Tariff Policy     ...      .... ........     105&quot; No-New-Prefererice &quot; Rule..Time-bar under Article XXVIII.  -9.     Tariff Policy     ................      .......     106Japan and the G.A.T.T.10      Atomic Energy Organisation -----    ...      ...      ...      ...     10711      The Cabinet     ... -   ...    &apos;       .   ...      ...      ......     108
2*% 4Kenya.       &apos;(previous reference:C.C. (53) 49thConclusions,Minute 4.)1. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof State for Colonial Affairs (C. (53) 238) giving an up-to-dateappreciation of the present situation in Kenya. ,The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said that the newsurrender policy, which had been announced since the Cabinefs last meeting, did not in any way reduce the need for reinforcements:indeed it had been launched on the assumption that these reinforce-ments would be sent.&apos; The Secretary of State for War said that since the last discussionhe had again reviewed the proposed composition of these reinforce-ments, and he was satisfied that the brigade headquarters should accompany the two infantry battalions. The Prime Minister saidthat he remained doubtful about this1 and would discuss it in greater detail with the Secretary of State for War.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Government of kenya were, unlikely to be able to bear the additional cost involved by the despatch of these reinforcements and it must be assumed thatthis decision would increase the overseas defence expenditure falling on the United Kingdom Exchequer.,    . -The Cabinet , (1) Authorised the despatch of two further infantry battalionsfrom the United Kingdom to Kenya. ;(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would decide, in con-&apos; sultation with the Secretary of State for War, whether these battalions should be accompanied by. a brigade headquarters. .. (3) Agreed that the despatch of these reinforcements should be announced within the next few days, and invited theMinister of State for the Colonies, after consultation withthe Secretary of State for War, to submit a draft of the-  &apos; proposed   announcement   for   the   Prime   Minister^approval. ,North atlantic council.(previous reference:C.C. (53) 29thConclusions,Minute 7.)Military.Planning.2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the lord president (C. (53) 234) proposing that the North Atlantic council should be asked at their next meeting to approve a new basis for themilitary planning of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation(N.A.T.O.).The Lord President said that N.A.T.O.&apos;s military planning.was still related to the original objective of building up by 1956 forcesstrong enough to resist a Russian aggression. Most of the membersof the North Atlantic Alliance now believed, however, that the dangerof such an aggression had receded and that military strengths shouldbe adjusted to the needs of a prolonged period of international tension without war. The military planning of the Organisationought therefore to be brought into line with the new political con-ception of the strategic risks. In paragraph 6 of his memorandumhe had put forward an outline of a new defence policy which theNorth Atlantic Council might be asked to adopt at their next meeting.He recognised, however, that the Council were unlikely to adopt thisunless it had the support of the United States Government; and he therefore recommended that in the first instance Her Majesty&apos;ambassador in Washington should be instructed to ascertain whetherthe United States Government would join with us in making proposals on these lines at the next meeting of the Council.    -The Chancellor of the Exchequer supported this proposal. he drew particular attention, however, to paragraph 6 (c) of the memo-randum, which proposed that N.A.T.O. planning should in future be
Germany.Four-power meeting.(previous reference:  &apos;C.C. (53) 49thConclusions,Minute 8.)3. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Lord President(subsequently circulated as C. (53) 242) covering a further draft of.a &apos;reply to the Soviet notes of 4th and 15th August. This took account&apos; of drafts put forward by the United States and French governments and of the drafting discussions which had been proceeding in Parisbetween officials of the three. Governments.      1The Lord President said that it was now proposed that the reply should be delivered to the Soviet-Government on 4th September and published on the following day. This would meet the views of theFederal Chancellor of Western Germany. As regards the form of theproposed:reply, it would be noted that the phrase to which obection had been raised in the Cabinets last discussion had been omitted:there was to be no reference to &quot;freedom of action in internal and external affairs &quot; by an all-German Government in the period beforethe conclusion of a Peace Treaty. The main question of substance^still outstanding was whether the agenda.for the Four-Power meeting should be limited narrowly to the future of Germany. On this theLord Presidents preference was for a reply in the terms of para-graph 4 of the draft annexed to C. (53) 242. This stated that it was desirable that the Four-Power Meeting should concentrate on theGerman problem and in the first instance on the question of free elections and the status of the future German Government, but went.on to say that this need not preclude the four Foreign Ministers fromdiscussing all aspects of. the problem of German unity nor even fromconsidering the general principles of a German Peace Treaty.In discussion it was argued that a reply, in these terms would be criticised in this country as representing an abandonment of theoriginal conception of a Four-Power Meeting as outlined in thePrime Minister&apos;s speech of 11th. May. From&quot; this point of view itwould be preferable that the reply should include some reference tothe possibility of wider discussions which might leacf to a more general settlement of outstanding international issues..The Lord President said that he saw&quot;Tittle prospect of securing agreement-to the inclusion of such a reference. It had been decidedat the Washington talks that the Four-Power Meeting should bebased on the assumption that roughly the present level of forces in aggregate, plus German forces, would be available over the next few;years. In presenting this proposal, both to the Americans and tothe Council,&apos; care should be taken to avoid any implication that the.United Kingdom Government1 would thereby be committed to con-tinuing their defence expenditure at its present level.The Cabinet  \ ,(L) Endorsed the policy outlined in paragraph 6uof C. (53) 234,and invited the Lord President to seek to persuade theUnited States Government to join the-United KingdomGovernment in,putting forward/proposals on these linesat the&apos;next meeting of the North Atlantic Council.- (2),Agreed that, in presenting to the United States Governmentand to.the North Atlantic Council the proposal in para-graph 6 (c) of C. (53) 234, care should be taken to avoid any implication that the United Kingdom Governmentwould thereby be committed to continuing their defence- expenditure at its present level. 1    -    -(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would try to arrange fora meeting to be held in the autumn at which he and someof his colleagues might discuss with a 1 senior military officer of N.A.T.O. the current military plans of N.A.T.O.,for meeting&apos;a Russian aggression in Europe.
Persia. 4.   The Lord President gave the Cabinet a brief account of the(Previous        loyalist revolution in Persia, which had resulted in the overthrow ofReference:      Dr. Musaddiq&apos;s Government. There was reason to believe that, ifC.C. (53) 20th   this military coup d&apos;etat had not succeeded, a Communist revolutionConclusions,    would have been attempted; and it was in our interests that GeneralMinute 4.)       ZahedFs Government should become more firmly established since,with the disappearance of Dr. Musaddiq, a Communist regime was now the only alternative. The new Persian Government would standin immediate need of financial assistance from abroad.  The UnitedStates would probably be disposed to offer this; and, unless we wereprepared to sacrifice all prospect of re-establishing British influence in Persia, we should be well-advised to join with them in extendingfinancial assistance to the Persians and in seeking an early solutionof the Anglo-Persian oil dispute.The Prime Minister endorsed this view. In present circumstances it would be easy for the Americans, by the expenditure of a relatively small sum of money, to reap all the benefits of many years of Britishwork in Persia. He therefore hoped that the task of supportingGeneral ZahedFs Government might be undertaken on an Anglo-American basis.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would deprecateany hasty offer of a loan to. General Zahedi. It could be repaid onlyin oil; and the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, having developed other sources of supply, were now less interested in securing a resumptionof the flow of oil from Persia. It would be premature to offer a loan to a Government which had not yet resumed diplomatic relations with us. And we might find it embarrassing to be lending money to Persiawhen we were obliged to refuse applications for development loans from friendlier countries in the Middle East and even from our partners in the Commonwealth. He suggested that we should in thefirst instance ascertain the views of the United States Government,and that any offer of financial help which we might give should insome way be made conditional upon a satisfactory settlement of the oil dispute.The Cabinet Invited the Lord President to consider further, with theChancellor of the Exchequer, the possibility of renderingsome financial assistance to the new Persian Government,and to ascertain what were the intentions of the UnitedStates Government in this regard.44798-2 * b 3concerned only with the future of Germany; and a formula offering to join in a general review of the world situation, which his repre-sentative had put forward in the current discussions in Paris, hadalready been rejected by the United States and French Governments.He believed that the British public now expected that a Four-power meeting, if it were held, would be concerned only with the futureof Germany; and it was material that the second of the two Sovietnotes was in fact concerned only with the German question. In thesecircumstances he thought it unlikely that the United States andFrench Governments would accept any wider formula than that proposed in paragraph 4 of the draft annexed to C. (53) 242. He was,however, willing to try to secure their agreement to the addition, atthe end of that paragraph, of the words &quot; as a step towards a general settlement.&quot;The Cabinet Approved the draft reply to the Soviet notes annexed toC. (53) 242 on the understanding that the Lord president would do his utmost to secure the addition, at the end ofparagraph 4 of the draft, of some such words as &quot; as a step towards a general settlement.&quot;
3S&apos; efPUBLIC RECORD office group/Class ...Cfl6.JoMj_____Piece_____________CLOSEDUNTIL
- \Egypt.(previous reference:C.C. (53) 49thConclusions,Minute 2.)6. The Lord President reported the latest developments in thedefence negotiations with the Egyptians. There now seemed to be some prospect of obtaining an agreement within the limits of the concessions approved by the Cabinet at their meeting on 18th August.The Prime Minister said that the United Kingdom delegation in Cairo had done well. They should be encouraged to maintain the firm attitude which they had shown.The Secretary of State for War said that we could be morecertain of being able to complete the withdrawal of our combatanttroops from the Canal Zone within the suggested period of 18 monthsif further progress could be made with the preparation of military installations in Cyprus. The Prime Minister said that there shouldbe no acceleration of this work until an agreement had been reached with the Egyptians. ^The Cabinet-Took note of these statements.
Match industry.       7.   The Cabinet&apos; had before them a memorandum by the,  , President of the Board of Trade (C. (53) 233) about the report of the monopolies Commission on the British match industry..  The President of the Board of Trade explained that manufac-- ture of matches in this country was a monopoly of the British MatchCorporation (B.M.C.), which was a-party to two agreements withthe Swedish Match Company regulating the supply of matches to&apos;.    the home market and.to overseas markets.  The Monopolies Corn-mission had concluded that the system as a whole operated againstthe public interest but had refrained from recommending that itshould be broken up on account of the economic advantages whichwe derived from the sharing of overseas markets.  The commission had recommended price control but this had been found to be impracticable.   B.M.C. had now made proposals. which met manyof the Commission^ recommendations but failed to go to the rootof the matter.   The-choice lay between continued partnership withthe Swedes or competition.  Although the latter would involve risking&apos;  , the loss of overseas earnings-of about half a million sterling a year,the President, considered that on wider grounds the government ought to exercise their powers under the Monopolies Act to declare&apos;       unlawful an agreement between B.M.C. and the Swedish MatchCompany for the continued sharing of the British market.  Approvalof such an agreement would expose the Government to the criticism that its professed belief in free competition was insincere. In practice,&apos; the revival of competition would have little effect on the price of.   matches. -,. - .&apos; The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that.the course recom-mended by the President of the Board of Trade was unsound oneconomic grounds. Apart from the probable loss which it would&apos; . involve in our balance of payments, it would upset our trading rela-tions with the Swedes and would almost certainly compel us tointroduce before long a tariff on matches. He would not, however,wish to press these objections if the Cabinet considered that they, were outweighed by-political considerations on the other side.The general view of the Cabinet was that, although the continu-ance of partnership was likely to be to our greater economic&apos; / advantage, previous declarations of their policy left the Governmentwith no alternative but to choose-the course recommended by thePresident of the Board of Trade.    :The Cabinet     / .  ,v  1Agreed that the President of the Board of Trade, in his- further discussions with the British Match Corporation,should proceed on the basis that the Government were unwilling to approve any agreement for the continuedsharing of the British match market between B.M.C. andthe Swedish Match Company.Tariff Policy.(previous reference:&apos;C.C.(53)41stConclusions,Minute 8-):&quot; No-New-Preference &quot;Rule. ,,81 The Cabinet had before them a, memorandum by thePresident of the Board of Trade (C.&apos; (53) 237) seeking approval of a proposed basis &quot;for enlisting United States support for a modificationof the rule of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.)prohibiting Commonwealth countries from increasing margins, ofpreference in their trade with one another.The President of the Board of Trade said thafthe Americansnow appeared to be willing to support us in seeking a general waiver of the &quot; no-new-preference &quot; rule which would be applicable to all goods for which we had not until,now, made any tariff concession to&apos; &quot; bind &quot; existing rates of duty. The waiver would require us inany given case to consult with other foreign countries interested in
the item affected on the risk, if any, that an increase in the margin ofpreference might lead to a substantial diversion of trade from thosecountries to Commonwealth sources of supply.   If it were agreedthat there was no risk of any substantial diversion of trade, the, &apos;    .   waiver would apply-automatically. If this were not agreed, we should, be entitled to seek the arbitration of disinterested contracting parties in the G.A.T.T.; and, if the arbitration went against us, we shouldnot be able to proceed under the general waiver.  In these circum-stances we should have to seek an individual waiver to allow us to. increase the preference in question notwithstanding the risk of asubstantial diversion of trade. It would be open to us to go aheadwithout this waiver if in critical circumstances we judged this to benecessary in order to repair or prevent serious injury to our domestic producers; in this event, however, foreign countries would be free,. - to the extent that they actually suffered from such diversion of trade,, to retaliate against us and to do so without having to seek prior approval in the G.A.T.T.By means of such a waiver&apos; we should regain an importantdegree of freedom in regard to our tariff and, in particular, shouldbe enabled to give almost complete effect to the Cabinet&apos;s earlier decision to impose certain horticultural duties which were desired by the National Farmers&apos; Unions (N.F.Us). Some criticism of theGovernment would be inevitable in regard to those few items forexample, apples, pears and dried peas which could not be dealtwith on the basis of these proposals, but this must be faced.. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he agreed that theseproposals represented the most satisfactory solution of this problem,which we were now likely to be able to obtain.Time-bar under       The President of the Board of Trade said that, under present article XXVIII, arrangements in the G.A.T.T., we and all other contracting parties were due to recover, as from 1st January, 1954, freedom under1, ,      Article XXVIII of the G.A.T.T, to re-negotiate duties which were atpresent &quot; bound.&quot; The Economic Policy Committee had agreed thatthere would be advantage in letting the present time-bar lapse but,on reconsideration, he now recommended that we should join withthe Americans and the Canadians in sponsoring an extension of thetime-bar for a further twelve or eighteen months.The Cabinet Approved the proposals of the President of the Board ofTrade in C. (53) 237 in regard both to the &quot;no-new-preference &quot; rule and to the time-bar for negotiations underArticle XXVIII of&apos;the G.A.T.T.; and authorised him toarrange for these proposals to be communicated to other commonwealth Governments.9. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the President ofthe Board of Trade (C. (53) 239) and the Lord President (C. (53) 240) .on the attitude to be adopted by the President of the Board of trade at the eighth session of the contracting parties to the General Agree-ment on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.) on the Japanese Governmenfsproposal that Japan should be accorded provisional association withthe Agreement. ...The President of the Board of Trade said that, since the cabinet had decided that we should seek to have the issue of Japan&apos;s accession to the Agreement deferred for a further period, the Japanese had asked for &quot; provisional association&quot; with the Agreement. In his view any form of Japanese association,&apos; however provisional, must inevitably set the pattern for Japan&apos;s later association on a permanent basis. He was therefore in favour of our endeavouring to join with australia, New Zealand, South Africa and, probably, France inTariff Policy.Japan and theG.A.T.T.(previous reference:C.C. (53) 47thConclusions,Minute 4.)
Atomic Energy 10. The Lord Privy Seal recalled that at their meeting onOrganisation. . 10th August the Cabinet had accepted in principle the general scheme(Previous devised by the Waverley Committee for transferring responsibilityReference: ( for atomic energy to a public Corporation, but had asked theC.C. (53)48th Paymaster-General and the&apos;Minister of Supply to consider how bestConclusions, to ensure, within that general scheme, that the Service DepartmentsMinute 9.) , could look to the Ministry of Supply as their sole supplier of completeatomic weapons. Agreement had now been reached on thisoutstanding point.   The essence of the agreement was as follows:  (i) The Services would order atomic weapons from the Ministry ,of Supply, which would be the sole Service ApprovalAuthority for the weapon  as  a whole and for its&apos; component parts.(ii) The Ministry of Supply would place contracts with theCorporation for development, associated research andabstaining from voting when the question of Japan&apos;s provisionalassociation was raised and in stating that we could not ourselves beparties to it.The Lord President said that he would deprecate the course recommended by the President of the Board of Trade on general grounds and would greatly prefer that we should accept Japan&apos;sprovisional association with the Agreement, which the Japanese were themselves willing to make subject to the safeguard provided inArticle XXIII, subject to a provision which would enable her majesty&apos;s Government at any time to discontinue the provisionalassociation between. Japan and themselves if in their view suchdiscontinuance had become desirable.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, as it seemed likely that Japan would be accorded provisional association and possiblethat Australia, New Zealand and South Africa would not, when thetime came, oppose such association, it had seemed to him preferable that we should not antagonise the Japanese by opposing it but shouldrather rely on the safeguards provided in Articles XXIII and XXXVof the Agreement. \   .The Commonwealth Secretary said that it was important that inthis matter we should act in concert with Australia and New Zealand;and he knew of no reason for believing that Australia, in particular,would be ready to withdraw her opposition to any form of Japaneseassociation with the Agreement. He was himself in sympathy withthe view of the President of the Board of Trade but if, contrary toexpectation, it became clear.that we should not have the continuingsupport of other Commonwealth Governments in declining to become a party to Japan&apos;s provisional association, it would be open to us to reconsider our attitude.Several other members of the Cabinet expressed support for thisview.    , - &apos;      .....   -The Cabinet  &apos;(1) Authorised the President of the Board of Trade, at the forth-coming session of the contracting parties to the G.A.T.T.,to seek the co-operation of other commonwealth countries in abstaining from voting on the question of japan&apos;s provisional1 association and in stating that wei could not ourselves be parties to it.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in the event ofhis being unable to obtain the co-operation of the other commonwealth Governments concerned, to submit the&apos; matter for further consideration by the Cabinet..      .
The Cabinet.(Previous     &apos;Reference:  iC.C. (53) 47thConclusions,Minute 2.)- 11. The Cabinet agreed that, unless urgent business requiredan earlier meeting, their next meeting should be held, on Tuesday,8th September.       -   *Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,26th August, 1953.i &apos;. . production of- the .&quot; atomic cores&quot; and of such other&quot;: -      &apos; -   components. of atomic weapons as might be agreed, &apos;        between the Ministry and.the Corporation.O,    (hi) The designated Minister would, however, be&apos;responsible&apos;&apos; - &apos;      for determining the programme of general research bythe Corporation on the nuclear and associated compo-nents of atomic weapons. -;&quot;..&apos;,Thus, general research at the Atomic Weapons Research Establish-ment at Aldermaston would be within the control of the minister responsible for atomic energy generally, but development and produc-tion of the atomic parts of weapons would be the subject of contractsplaced with the Corporation by the Minister of Supply. -.The Lord Privy Seal&quot; said that this agreement met the views expressed in the Cabinefs discussion on .10th August. Work could now go forward on the preparation of a-detailed plan for transferringresponsibility from the Ministry of Supply to a public; Corporation.The Cabinet-        &apos;. \       ;Took note of this statement by the Lord Privy Seal.

</content>
</cab>
