<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/26/0 images: 509-511</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1953SECRET Copy No.      qCC. (53)66th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at JO Downing Street, S.W. I,on Friday, 13th November, 1953, at 11 -30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, Secre-tary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary  of  State for  theColonies.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. the Earl Alexander of tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The   Right   Hon.   Gwilym   Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.The following were also present:The Right Hon. J. P. L. Thomas, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Lord De L&apos;Isle and dudley, Secretary of State for Air. -The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Supply.The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury.  -Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.ContentsNational Service45222-1
The Cabinet considered the arrangements for the debate, to beheld in the House of Commons on 16th and 17th November, on theOrder in Council extending the operation of the National Service Actfor a further period of five years.It had been agreed through the usual channels that on the first day of the debate discussion would be based on an Opposition motion,and that the vote on the Order in Council would be taken on thesecond day. The Opposition had now tabled a motion in the following terms:  &quot; That this House, whilst accepting the necessity for nationalservice in present circumstances, nevertheless considers that thetime has now arrived when the period of service should be deter-mined by Parliament on an affirmative resolution not less fre-quently than once a year.&quot;&apos;It was likely that some Members with pacifist views would force a division on this motion; but, if the Government were ready to accept it, it could be carried by an overwhelming majority. Even so, how-ever, there was no assurance that the Labour Opposition would vote in support of the Order in Council on the second day. For, although their motion accepted &quot; the necessity for national service in presentcircumstances &quot; and the Order in Council did no more than extend theprinciple of national service for a further five years, the Governmentwould be obliged to make it clear in the debate that they saw no earlyprospect of reducing the period of service below two years and it was likely on that account that the Labour Opposition would feel able todo no more than abstain from voting in any division on the Order.The Prime Minister said that he had at first been disposed to thinkthat the Government might accept the Opposition motion. Parlia-ment already had many opportunities to challenge in debate theperiod of national service, and it might be argued that the adoption ofan affirmative resolution procedure would do no more than regularisethe existing position. Moreover, the annual Army Acts were them-selves a precedent for giving Parliament a regular annual opportunityto authorise the continuance of the obligation to a particular period ofnational service. It might well have been worth while to accept theprinciple of annual Parliamentary approval by affirmative resolutionif the Opposition had been willing in return to give a positive vote, inthe division on the Order in Council, in favour of extending nationalservice for a further five years. This, however, they were unlikely todo. And the Service Ministers also feared that the adoption of asystem of annual Parliamentary decision on the period of service would create an atmosphere of uncertainty about the future course ofnational service which might prejudice recruiting for regular service with the Armed Forces.In discussion the Service Ministers reaffirmed the view that theForces could not be maintained at the strength required to meet fore-seeable commitments over the next few years unless the two-year period of national service were maintained. This was speciallyimportant as an incentive to induce national service men to accept a regular engagement for three years. The Governmenfs acceptance ofthe Opposition motion would be widely interpreted as foreshadowinga change of attitude towards the period of national service. Thiswould prejudice recruiting for regular service in the Forces, and itwould also discourage our friends in the North Atlantic Alliance.In further discussion it was pointed out that these and other argu-ments against the proposal for annual affirmative resolutions had beeneffectively deployed by the Prime Minister in his speech in the Defencedebate in the House of Commons on 5th March. The proposal now put forward in the Opposition^ motion had then been embodied in a labour amendment to the Government motion inviting the House to approve the Defence White Paper; and the Prime Minister had invited the House to reject that amendment. In view of the arguments then
used against this proposal, it was bound to be assumed, if the Govern-ment now accepted it, that circumstances had changed since March.This, indeed, was implied by the phrase in the present motion that&quot; the time had now arrived &quot; to adopt the system of annual review ofthe period of service. The impression would certainly be created that since March there had been some change in the international situa-tion which justified a change of policy. This was not so in fact; andto give the impression that it was so would be inconsistent with theGovernments general approach to the present international situation.Thus, in view of what had been said in the debate on 5th March, theGovernment now had no alternative but to resist this opposition motion.The Cabinet Agreed that, in the debate in the House of Commons on16th November, the Government should invite the House to reject the Opposition motion proposing that the period ofnational service should be determined annually by Parlia-ment by affirmative resolutionCabinet Office, S.W.1,13th November, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
