<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/26/0 images: 566-569</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY  OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1953SECRET Copy No. .- l-    4GIG. (53)76th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, 3rd December, 1953, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer (in the Chair)The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P.,   Secretary  of   State  for   theColonies.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.The   Right   Hon.   Gwilym   Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Selwyn LloydM.P., Minister of State.Q.C.The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury.Sir Ivone Kirkpatrick, Foreign Office(Item 3).Mr. G. Mallaby.........      Secretary.45362-1
Contents:minute no. Subject Page.1      Uganda Protectorate    .........      ...      ...      ...      1512      Parliament       ............      ...      ......     151Business in the House of Commons.3      Persia     ........................     1514      Television Development        ...      ...      ...      ......     152
Uganda 1.   The Lord Privy Seal said that in the course of the debate onProtectorate.    the deposition of the Kabaka of Buganda the Opposition had drafted(Previous        a motion of censure on the Government for its handling of AfricanReference:      affairs and had issued this to the Press.  In the event, however, theyCC. (53) 75th   had not put this motion down for debate and, after a series of hesitation-Conclusions,     tions and changes of intention, had now said that they did not wishMinute 4.)       to put the motion down for fear of prejudicing any negotiations thatmight be continued with the ex-Kabaka.   A situation had beenreached, therefore, in which the world at large knew the terms inwhich the Opposition wished to censure the Government, but theGovernment was denied an opportunity to rebut the charges in theHouse of Commons. In these circumstances might it not be wise forthe Government to ask for a motion of confidence in its handling of colonial affairs?The general view of the Cabinet was that, in spite of the unusualand confusing tactics of the Opposition, the general impression lefton the public mind was that the Colonial Secretary had presented anunanswerable case for the deposition of the Kabaka and that it was because of this that the Opposition had not pressed their motion of censure. In these circumstances it would be wiser to let the matterrest and not to press for a motion of confidence which, in the publicview, had already been convincingly given. It would, however, be right to issue a statement to the Press, drawing attention to theincorrect and unjustifiable tactics adopted by the Opposition.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the Government should not press for a motion of confidence in its handling of Colonial affairs.(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal and the Chief Whip to issue asuitable statement to the Press about the tactics adoptedby the Opposition in this matter.Parliament. 2.   The Lord Privy Seal pointed out that, as there was to be noBusiness in the motion of censure and no motion of confidence on the GovernmenfsHouse of handling of Colonial affairs, the business in the House of CommonsCommons. for Thursday, 10th December, remained to be settled. The choicelay between the Mines and Quarries Bill and the Import Duties(Additional) (Fruit and Vegetables) Order. An undertaking had beengiven to the Opposition that the Mines and Quarries Bill would notbe taken until a later date.The Cabinet-Agreed that the business in the House of Commons on I0thDecember, should be the Import Duties (Additional) (fruit and Vegetables) Order.Persia. 3.   The Minister of State said that he had received a message(Previous        from the Swiss Minister in London that the Persian Government were reference:      willing to accept the formula suggested to them by the Foreign Secre-CC. (53) 74th   tary to enable Ambassadors to be exchanged between Persia and theConclusions,    United Kingdom.   The Persian Government had asked for anMinute 3.)       immediate reply so that the agreed communique could be issued on 5th December, at 10-30 a.m. He had communicated this message tothe Foreign Secretary in Bermuda; but, as it was most important notto let this opportunity slip, he hoped that the Cabinet would authorise him to welcome the Persian approach and to agree to the issue of the communique, without waiting for an answer from the Foreign Secre-tary.   As this was the result for which the Foreign Secretary hadbeen striving, he had no doubt of his approval.   The terms of the
joint communique, after referring to the decision of the United King-dom Government and the Persian Government to exchange Ambas-sadors, went on to state that the two Governments would proceed at the earliest mutually agreed moment to negotiate a settlement ofthe oil dispute on terms which would safeguard the aspirations and interests of both parties.The Cabinet Authorised the Minister of State to welcome the approachby the Persian Government and to agree to the issue of ajoint communique on 5th December, at 10-30 a.m.Television 4.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, following theDevelopment.   Cabinefs last discussion on television, he had received a message(Previous        from the Prime Minister asking that no discussions between the reference:      Postmaster-General and Lord Waverley should be held before theCC. (53) 75th   Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary had returned.    He had conclusions,     accordingly sent a message to the Prime Minister, pointing out that minute 5.)       the Cabinet had not contemplated any form of negotiation with LordWaverley but were only anxious to hear what positive suggestions he might have to make; no action, however, would be taken unless thePrime Minister chose to express further views.   He would raise thismatter again at the meeting of the Cabinet on 8th December.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer and agreed to resume discussion at their meetingon 8th December.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,4th December, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
