<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/26/0 images: 592-600</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY  OF HER BRITANNIC   MAJESTY^   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1953SECRET Copy No. 45C.C. (53)80th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Friday, 18th December, 1953, at 3-00 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P.(Except for Items 3-5)Prime minister the Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crooksiiank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft.M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. the Earl alexander of Tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Item 1).Mr. H. A. W Atkinson, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Labourand National Service.Secretariat:   &apos;The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. G. Mallaby.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.45517b
contents minute no. subject      Egypt     ......      ......Defence Negotiations.Visit of Members of Parliament to Egyp2      Public ExpenditureCivil Supply 1954-55.3      Food Prices4      Agricultural Policy     ......5      EducationTeachers&apos; Superannuation.6      Town and Country Planning Act, 194778Alan Nunn May
EgyptDefenceNegotiations.(previous reference:CC. (53) 79thConclusions,Minute 3.)GVisit ofMembers ofParliamentto Egypt.GPublicExpenditure.(previous reference:CC. (53) 46thConclusions,Minute 4.)Civil Supply1954-55.1. The Foreign Secretary said that there were some indications that the Egyptian Government might be contemplating a course ofaction hostile to our interests. This might possibly be the conclusionof a non-aggression pact with the Soviet Union, or further attacks upon our forces in the Canal Zone, or penal measures against Britishsubjects living in Egypt. In this event it might be right to break off thedefence negotiations and to stand upon our rights under the 1936Treaty, which did not expire until 1956. We should then proceed inour own time with the re-deployment of our forces in the Middle East.He did not propose to give any advance warning to the egyptian government but simply to await further action on their part orfurther approaches for a resumption of defence negotiations.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.The Chief Whip reported that the explanations given by theMinister of Defence and the speech made by the Foreign Secretary inthe debate on the previous day had failed to allay the anxieties of thegroup of Government supporters in the House of Commons who were concerned about the Governments Egyptian policy. They were not proposing to withdraw their motion and there was some reason tobelieve that they would continue to express public dissatisfaction withthe Governments policy.The Prime Minister said that he hoped that ConservativeMembers of Parliament would be dissuaded from accepting the invitation of General Neguib to visit Egypt at the expense of theEgyptian Government. It would be lacking in dignity to accepthospitality from a Government which had encouraged acts of hostility against British troops and indulged in abusive propaganda against this country. If Government supporters wished to visitEgypt at their own expense that was a matter for them. He suggestedthat the Chief Whip should write to the Members concerned invitingthem with the Prime Minister^ authority to refrain from availingthemselves of General Neguib&apos;s invitation.The Cabinet-(2) Invited the Chief Whip to make known to the ConservativeMembers of Parliament concerned the Cabinefs wish thatthey should not accept the hospitality of the egyptian government at this juncture.455172. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (53) 355) on the prospects forcivilsupply expenditure for the financial year 1954.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the response to his request for economies in civil supply expenditure had been disappoint-ing. The cost of the remaining food subsidies and of&apos;the subsidies to British agriculture was a heavy continuing burden. The housing programme had been so successful that the number of subsidisedhouses was now well above the target, but he hoped for some ease-ment when the emphasis was shifted from new construction to repairs.He also expected some definite savings on stock-piling and on civil defence. He asked that all spending Departments should makestrenuous efforts to find economies between now and February, sothat he might be able to present a balanced Budget and to maintainconfidence in sterling.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Departmental proposals for expenditure on stock-pilingamounted to  79 millions. This was  27 millions more than last year.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster suggested that these pro-posals should be further examined: he believed that there was scopehere for some economy.B 2
Food Prices.(previous reference:CC. (53) 57thConclusions,Minute 7.)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Food (C. (53) 350) proposing that the increases in the price ofcertain foods which the Cabinet had approved on 13th October shouldbe brought into operation from 21st February, 1954.The Minister of Food said that it had previously been estimatedthat these increases would have the effect of bringing the subsidiesdown to an annual rate of  220 millions by the end of the current year. It was now clear that these increases would not suffice for thispurpose. A further contribution of  10 millions could be made by increasing the price of pork by 3d, per pound. But, apart from that,savings could only be found by increasing the price of milk or of bread. -The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Labour, said that duringthe next three months thirty-five different claims for increased wages,amounting to a total of  300 millions, would have to be decided. Themain argument now used in support of claims for increased wageswas the high price of food.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he did not think theCabinet should at this stage decide to raise the price of milk or bread.The other price increases ought, however, to be brought into operation on 21st February.The Cabinet-(1) Approved the following price increases to take effect from21st February, 1954: -Butter Ad. per pound.Cheese 2d. per pound.Beef 2d. per pound. -Pork 3d. per pound.(2) Agreed to consider in January whether there should be some increase in the price of bread or milk.agricultural policy.(previous reference:CC. (53) 55thConclusions,Minute 6.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secre-tary of State for Scotland and the Minister of Agriculture (C. (53) 351)proposing the basis of a long-term agricultural policy.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that the cabinet should defer detailed consideration of this memorandum until thefigures and estimates had been further considered by the Departmentsconcerned. Further clarification of the issues involved could be madeby officials: the results should then be reported to the ministerial committee on Food and Agriculture, who would in due course submit their recommendations to the Cabinet.(b) The Home Secretary said that current expenditure on civil defence did no more than present a facade of preparations; but hewould consider, with his colleagues on the Civil Defence Committee,whether it would be possible to keep this expenditure within the limitssuggested by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Prime Minister said that all spending Departments should review their estimates with the greatest care in the forthcoming weeks and should, wherever possible, propose reductions to the Treasury.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer (C. (53) 355).(2) Invited the Ministers responsible for civil supply expenditure to re-examine their estimates for 1954 with a view to securing all practicable economies.
Education.Teachers&apos;Superannuation.(previous reference:C.C. (53) 18thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the&apos; Secre-tary of State for Scotland and the Minister of Education (C. (53) 354)seeking approval for legislation to raise the contributions towardsteachers&apos; pensions from 10 per cent, to 12 per cent, of salary and tomake certain other changes in the teachers&apos; superannuation scheme.The Minister of Education said that, in accordance with the cabinet&apos;s previous conclusions, the local education authorities and the teachers had now been consulted on the working of the superannua-tion scheme. The local education authorities had accepted the need to increase the rate of contribution from 10 per cent, to 12 per cent.The teachers were firmly opposed to any raising of the rate. TheMinister thought, however, that despite their objections it would be right to increase the contributions. The net relief to the exchequer in the financial year 1954 would be about  2-3 millions in Englandand Wales and about  310,000 in Scotland. The annual increase inteachers&apos; contributions would range from  4 5s. to  8. There wouldcertainly be public criticism of the proposed increase, and it wouldin particular be said, that the Government were by this meansincreasing their difficulties in recruiting new teachers. If the increase was to be made, it should be announced at the same time as the government&apos;s acceptance of the Burnham Committee&apos;s recommenda-tions for an increase in teachers&apos; salaries. The double announcement should be made in the first week in January.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the actuarial deficit on teachers&apos; pensions was increasing rapidly and this economy oughtto be made. Although it would not produce an actuarial balance, itwould at least mitigate the mounting Exchequer liability.The Cabin ct-be(1) Agreed that teachers&apos; pensions contributions shouldraised from 10 per cent, to 12 per cent, of salary.(2) Authorised the Education Ministers to announce this decisionearly in January, simultaneously with the Governmenfsacceptance of the Burnham Committee&apos;s recommendations for an increase in teachers&apos; salaries.(3) Took note that legislation to amend the Teachers&apos; Super-annuation Acts would be introduced as soon as possible after the Christmas recess.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The Board of Trade should be associated with the studiesto be undertaken by officials.(b) There was some evidence to suggest that large families were now consuming less food. It was known, however, that numbers of wage-earners were spending a disproportionate amount of their earnings on tobacco, drink, television sets and football pools. Ifexpenditure on these items were reduced there would be enoughmoney in the average household budget to allow for an-adequateconsumption of food at current prices. It was suggested thatpublicity might be given to an analysis of the average wage-earner&apos;expenditure. The Chancellor of the Exchequer undertook to consider this point.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the issues raised in C. (53) 351 should be further considered by the Ministerial Committee on Food and agriculture, assisted by officials of the Departmentsconcerned, including the Board of Trade.(2) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer would con-sider the points noted in paragraph (b) above.
Town and country planning Act,1947.(previous reference:C.C. (52) 97thConclusions,Minute 1.)6. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Minister of housing (C. (53) 346) and the Chancellor of the Exchequer(C. (53) 349) on the method of financing compensation payments under the forthcoming Bill to amend the Town and Country planning act, 1947.The Minister of Housing recalled that in their White Paper(Cmd. 8699) the Government had undertaken, instead of buying alldevelopment rights for  300 millions, to pay compensation, on thebasis of the admitted claims against the  300 millions, in each particular case in which planning permission was refused or localauthorities acquired compulsorily land in respect of which such a claim had been established. He was anxious that such compensation payments should not be charged on the Vote in the year in which theywere paid. The forthcoming Estimates would be seriously distortedif they included provision for paying off the backlog of compensation payments which had already fallen due and might amount to as muchas  60 millions during the first two years. In subsequent years theannual charge was likely to be a relatively small one. There were alsopolitical considerations to be taken into account. In their handling of this matter the Government had so far been able to avoid revivingthe controversy to which it had given rise in the past and it would beregrettable if such controversy were now to recur. He feared that, ifthe charge for compensation payments were borne on the annualDepartmental Vote, the Government would be accused of sacrificingplanning and proper land-use to short-term financial considerations.In practice his Ministry exercised close control over the decisions oflocal planning authorities, and the amount of compensation due ineach case where planning permission was refused would be limited tothe admitted claim. In these circumstances there did not seem to himto be any serious risk in his proposal that these compensation pay-ments should be financed from the Consolidated Fund and amortisedby annual charges on the Votes. If, however, the Chancellor of theExchequer should feel bound to persist in his opposition to thisproposal, he would be ready to explore with him the possibility ofsome compromise arrangement whereby 1 Parliament might be specifically invited to vote in advance a fixed sum say  75 or 100 millions which should be sufficient to cater for the backlog ofcompensation payments already due and for the further sums likelyto become payable by way of compensation during, say, the next10-15 years. A fixed advance of this kind could similarly beamortised by annual charges on the Votes.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had felt bound to oppose the Ministers proposal that compensation should be financedat the expense,of the Consolidated Fund because such an arrange-ment would involve a departure from the traditional practice of theTreasury whereby, expenditure which would not be recoverable oryield revenue was made subject to scrutiny by the House of Commonsthrough the normal supply procedure, including Estimates. TheMinister&apos;s original proposal was also, in his view, open to theobjections that Parliament would thereby be deprived of effective control over expenditure which depended on decisions taken bylocal authorities and that the Government would expose themselvesto the criticism that they had chosen to remove from fullParliamentary control payments of a kind which would primarily beof benefit to land-owners. He naturally regretted the necessity toinclude in Estimates the substantial sums required to provide thesecompensation payments in the opening years, but he had accepted this as an inevitable consequence of the scheme which the Govern-ment had adopted. He was, however, ready to examine more closely the compromise proposal which the Minister of Housing had now outlined. While it was true that even this proposal would not bring the compensation payments within the scope of fullParliamentary control over expenditure, Parliamentary approvalwould have been specifically obtained for the proposed advance, andthe subsequent amortisation of this advance by annual charges on the
PUBLIC RECORD office group/Class ,m-CA^Jc2e6_____Piece________ Li____________CLOSEDUNTIL
Votes would provide further opportunities for parliamentary discussion of the scale and trend of expenditure. Before agreeing to any such arrangement, however, he would need to be fully satisfiedthat it would not be open to criticism as being financially unsound.The Cabinet Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to give furtherconsideration, in consultation with the Minister of Housing,to the possibility of inviting Parliament to approve a specificadvance to cover the initial heavy cost of compensation payments, and the charge in respect of payments falling dueduring a limited period thereafter, under the forthcomingBill to amend the Town and Country Planning Act, 1947.
AlanNuan 8.   The Cabinet were reminded that, on his release from prisonMay. at the end of 1952, Alan Nunn May had undertaken not to leave(Previous this country for a period of 12 months.   During that time, despiteReference: the efforts of the Ministry of Labour, no suitable employment had .C.(53)2nd been found for him: his funds were now running low, and it was conclusions, possible that in the New Year he might accept an offer of employmentMinute 10,) abroad.In discussion the Cabinet reaffirmed their view that it would bea shock to public opinion, both here and in the United States, if thisman sought employment abroad.The Cabinet Invited the Home Secretary to do his best, in consultationwith the Minister of Labour, to ensure that Alan Nunn Mayshould remain in the United Kingdom.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,18th December, 1953.\

</content>
</cab>
