<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 60-65</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET Copy No.CP. (51) 157 m :Sth June, 1951CABINETCO-ORDINATION OF RADIO AND CABLE ACTIVITIESNote by the Secretary of the CabinetIn a note (CP. (46) 162) circulated on 18th April, 1946, particulars were given of the terms of reference and composition of the Radio and Cable Board and ofcertain other committees dealing with radio and cable activities. A further note(CP. (47) 257) was issued on 12th September, 194?, giving certain changes in theorganisation of the Radio and Cable Board and the other committees.&apos; 2. A Working Party was set up in December 1949 with the following termsof reference:-&quot; To review the arrangements for inter-departmental co-ordination overthe whole field of radio and cable activity, with special reference to radioresearch and production, and to recommend any changes in the existing arrangements which may seem desirable.&quot;This Working Party reported jn July 1950, and its conclusions and recommenda-tions can be summarised as follows: Conclusions(i) There is a need for standing specialist interdepartmental committees tocover common technical problems in this field.iii) In those cases where issues of policy arise with which standing specialistcommittees are unable to deal, or where direct consultation at theofficial level between Departments concerned fails to resolve theproblem, the issues will almost certainly have to be resolved at ministerial level. .(iii) Long-term and fundamental research is being covered by the Departmentof Scientific and Industrial Research, which is kept aware of problemsconfronting the industry.(iv)&quot;&quot;Existing inter-departmental committees deal satisfactorily with the co-ordination of the development and standardisation of valves and othercomponents, but not of equipment and techniques which demands theharmonisation of Staff Requirements.(v) The Defence Research Policy Committee are keeping under continuous review this important problem of harmonisation of Staff requirements which the British Joint Communications-Electronics Board have alsostarted to attack.(vi) The functions of existing specialist inter-departmental committees areadequately co-ordinated by the sponsoring departments:(vii) The Postmaster-General has statutory duties in the field of frequencyallocation, his direct responsibility for which he cannot relinquish.Iviii) The opportunities for co-ordination of radio navigational aids betweenmarine and air interests are few and there is a difference of opinion between the two sides on the question whether special co-ordinatingmachinery is necessary.40640 B:  ; r    , Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1951 &apos;
(ix) A large and effective committee structure exists for the co-ordination ofnavigational matters affecting civil and defence air interests.(x) The Joint Civil and Services;,^elec^mmunic^tion^,Committee is a usefulforum for discussion of operational matters affecting both civil and defence interests.   ..............Committee of the Joint Civil and Services TelecommunicationsCommittee.The Co-ordinating Committee on Radio Navigational Aids.The Inter-depaftmental Cable and Wire Committee.The Automatic Telegraphy Policy Committee.The Scientific Publications Committee.(ii) The Post Office should co-ordinate all civil requirements in respect of research, development and production (except where a Service Depart-ment or the Ministry of Supply has taken a specific responsibility or where definite! liaisons exist) in the same way that the Ministry of Defence,: co-ordinates all defence requirements.(Hi) Questions, of frequency allocation and planning (apart from day-tO-day;:.frequencylallocations) should be dealt with by the Frequency Committeewhich the Post Office proposes to set up.(iv) The terms of reference of the Joint Civil and Services TelecommunicationsCommittee should be amended so as no longer to exclude radio navi-&apos;gational aids and this Committee should review existing arrangements;-.,.-w. in this field.; : :; (vj The membership of this committee should vary according to the subjects-ii under discussion, and should be at a sufficiently high level.3. The Prime Minister has now-approved a reorganisation of the committeestructure dealing with radio and cable problems in accordance with the general recommendations of the Working Party. Certain committees are to be dissolvedand the terms of reference and composition of certain other committees altered in themanner set out in the Annexes to this memorandum. The Frequency committee referred to in recommendation (hi) above will be formally constituted as a CabinetCommittee with terms of reference and composition as in Annex III. The terms ofreference and composition of committees not mentioned in this paper ,remain unchanged.4. On the research, development and production side, the co-ordination of allcivU requirements (except where a Service Department or the Ministry of supply has taken a specific responsibility, or where definite liaisons exist) lies with theGeneral Post Office. The existing organisation for co-ordinating Service require-ments for research, development and production remains unchanged.(Signed)NORMAN BROOK..8.HOCabinet Office, S.W. 1,Sth June, 1951.--^vtfjwy;....it
List of Bodies which are to be DissolvedThe Radio and Cable Board.The Research Development and Production Committee. .The Frequency Sub-Committee and the Telecommunications Sub-Committeeof the Joint Civil and Services Telecommumcatipns Committee.The Co-ordinating Committee on Radio Navigational Aids!  -fi - :  fThe Inter-Departmental Cable and Wire Committee.The Automatic Telegraphy Policy Committee.The Scientific Publications Committee.ANNEX IIJoint Civil and Services Telecommunications committee terms of. ReferenceTo co-ordinate departmental, telecommunications ;and other Signals activitieswhere this is necessary and desirable. . - -Such activities may include radio, submarine cable, overland cable, visual signaling, radio navigational aids, radar and: radio sites. They exclude research,development, production and matters covered by the Defence Services LinesTelecommunications Board and the Frequency Committee.CompositionChairman Sir Stanley Angwin.Deputy Chairman  ...Chairman, B.J.C-E.B.Members Foreign office home Office.Board of Trade.-Colonial Office.Commonwealth Relations Office.Ministry of Transport.Ministry of Civil Aviation.General Post Office.Admiralty.War Office.Air Ministry.B.J.C-E.B.Joint Secretaries-B.J.C-E.B.General Post Office.Cabinet Office.RemarkThe Committee reports to the Defence Committee.40640 B 2
Ms.Frequency Committee      &apos;. Terms of Reference \To formulate the policy governing the regulation of radio frequency usageand the planning and allocation of frequencies. .;,Notes- ... ,   f&apos;.       L ^(1) The Joint Frequency Planning Panel of the B.J.C-E.B. act as the agent ofthis Committee in matters of detail.(2) The Frequency Assignment-Committee,(Committee &quot; B &quot;) of the B.J.C-E.B.act as the agent of this Committee in day-to-day assignment offrequencies.CompositionChairman  . ..   .......General Post Office.Members .      Foreign office home Office. &apos;   &quot; - - &quot;Colonial Office.Commonwealth Relations Office.. Ministry of transport ministry of Civil Aviation.General Post Office.Admiralty.War Office. .  .Air Ministry.B.J.C-E.B.Joint Secretaries General Post Office. -Cabinet Office.Remarks r. - - &quot;:1. In view of the constitutional responsibility Of the Postmaster-General forfrequency matters, the Committee will report to Ministers as necessary throughhim. c1    1        ,&apos;, r2. When appropriate, representatives of; the British Broadcasting corporation or Cable and Wireless, Ltd., may be invited to meetings of the. Committee.
Members Foreign office home Office.Admiralty.War Office.Air Ministry.B.J.C.-E.B.Secretary General Post Office.RemarkThe Committee reports to the Chiefs of Staff Committee and, consults as appropriate with the Joint Civil and Services Telecommunications Committee.Defence Services Lines Telecommunications Board&apos;       Terms of ReferenceTo co-ordinate the individual dBmlncl^ of the Defence Services as regards linetelecommunications in-the United Kingdom (and elsewbere(if $pjreauested/by/^heChiefs of Staff). ... - &apos; - -jH.. Ui (jim-     -CompositionChairman  .General Post Office. &apos;.....


</content>
</cab>
