<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 137-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY  OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1951SECRET Copy No. 31CP. (51) 168ISth June, 1951CABINETCONTROL OF DELEGATED legislation memorandum by the Home SecretaryMy colleagues will recall that on 19th March, when the Opposition wereabusing the right to put down motions praying for the annulment of orders, Ioffered on behalf of the Government to enter into discussions with a view to seeing whether the House could not,more effectively exercise its function of keepinga check on the Executive. (The text of the statement I then made is given in annex A.) I subsequently had some correspondence with the Leader of theOpposition in which he drew attention to a recommendation of the Select Committeeon Procedure of 1946 that a Select Committee should be appointed in the coming session, or, preferably, that the House of Lords should be invited to concur in the, appointment of a joint committee, to enquire into the delegation of legislative powerand the procedure of the Houses in relation thereto; and, following on a meeting which I had with him on 26th April at which he promised to let me have his views and those of his colleagues on the prayer procedure, he has now written statingthat it is their view that an enquiry of the kind recommended by the SelectCommittee of 1946 should be carried out (see Annex B).2. The recommendation of the Select Committee of 1946 was made after theyhad considered suggestions by the former Clerk of the House (Lord Campion)(i) that the Scrutinising Committee&apos;s terms of reference should be extended toenable it to report on the merits of a Statutory Instrument, as an exercise of thepowers delegated, and (ii) that the Scrutinising Committee might be empoweredto enquire into and report on any grievances arising out of Statutory Instrumentsactually in operation. The Select Committee heard evidence on these suggestionsfrom a number of witnesses, all of whom, except the Opposition Chief Whip(Mr. James Stuart), were opposed to them. The memorandum submitted by the leader of the House (Mr. Morrison) contained the following paragraph:  &quot; The Government cannot recommend either of the additional functionsproposed for the Select Committee on Statutory Rules and Orders. The first would mean that Ministers would have to attend before the Select Committeeto defend the policy embodied in subordinate legislation; the second wouldhave the effect of enabling the Select Committee to enquire into all phases ofGovernment administration within the very wide field now covered by delegated legislation.&quot;In their Third Report the Select Committee stated that the opportunities for discussing delegated legislation in the House were extremely limited and not altogether satisfactory. They referred to the suggestions made by Lord Campionas going some way to supplement the inadequate and unsatisfactory oppertuinities which the House possessed for exercising its control over one aspect of administra-tion, but they did not touch on the objections to these suggestions, which had beenbrought out in the evidence given to them. They concluded that the delegation of legislative power raised issues beyond the scope of their investigation and they accordingly recommended that there should be a further enquiry.3.  The words used in the recommendation of the Select Committee on procedure were &quot; to enquire into the delegation of legislative power and theprocedure of the Houses in relation thereto.&quot; These terms of reference would includefar more than an enquiry into the prayer procedure and would cover an examination,40751 b
similar to that carried out by the Donoughmore Committee, of the principles onwhich Parliament should confer on Ministers the power to make delegated legisla-tion. I do not think that the recent troubles about prayers would in any wayjustify an enquiry of this kind and the words used by the Leader of the opposition in earlier correspondence with me do not suggest that he is asking for more than an enquiry by a Select Committee into the procedure of Parliament for dealing withstatutory instruments. If, however, my colleagues agree that we do not want to reopen the whole question of the use of delegated legislation it will be necessary tomake the point clear in any reply to the Leader of the Opposition.4. On the assumption that all that the Opposition are asking for is an enquiry into the procedure of Parliament in dealing with statutory instruments, it is still aquestion whether we ought to agree to an enquiry even with this limited scope.In the Government statement of 17th March, 1947, on the Third Report ofthe Select Committee on Procedure, their recommendation was dealt with asfollows:  &quot; The Government consider that such an enquiry would be premature solong as the scope and form of subordinate legislation are influenced by war-timepowers and until experience has been gained of the working of the statutory instruments Act, 1946.&quot;In a debate on this Government statement on 4th November, 1947, the leader of the House (Mr. Morrison) said that the Government were not opposed inprinciple to the suggestion of an enquiry but they thought the time was not yetripe for such an enquiry, and later in the same debate I said that from time to timethe matter would have to be considered but that just at the moment the time was not ripe for a further Committee.5. It is true that the scope and forms of subordinate legislation are stillinfluenced by war-time powers in the sense that many Statutory Instruments arestill made under war-time powers (e.g., those relating to price regulation) which havebeen extended into peace-time, but we can hardly argue at this date that there hasnot as yet been enough experience of the Statutory Instruments Act. Moreover, theredo not seem to be any concessions of substance which could be offered to theOpposition as an alternative to an enquiry. At the same time there are objectionsto the institution of an enquiry. Both the evidence given to the Select Committeeof 1946 and, so far as I am aware of them, the views of those Departments who are mainly concerned with delegated legislation seem to show beyond doubt that thereare no radical changes in the procedure for dealing with delegated legislation whichwould not destroy or seriously impair the virtues of flexibility and speed whichit possesses, compel Parliament to spend unnecessary time over details and makeimpossible demands on the time of Ministers and civil servants. The question ofproviding for a greater measure of Parliamentary control over delegated legislation was recently considered very fully by an official committee in connection with theFull Employment Bill, and the conclusion reached was that there were strongpractical objections to all the alternative methods of doing this. (The relevantparagraphs in the report of the official committee are given in Annex C.)6. It follows that, if a Select Committee is appointed to enquire into theprocedure for dealing with delegated legislation, the result is likely to be at best afew recommendations for trifling changes and there is a risk that the Committeewill put forward proposals which would seriously hamper any Government. While,therefore, I do not think that we can resist the request that a Select Committeeshould be appointed, I think it essential that in agreeing to the appointment weshould do so not on the assumption that there is something radically wrong with theexisting system but rather on the ground that it would be useful to have the positionreviewed now that the Statutory Instruments Act has been in operation for some4J years. It is important that the Government should avoid being put into theposition of having agreed that the existing procedure is unsatisfactory and havingaccepted the obligation of putting forward for consideration by the Select Committeesome alternative system.7. It will be noted that the recommendation of the Select Committee of 1946expressed a preference for an enquiry by a Joint Committee of both Houses andin a letter to me, dated 3rd April, the Leader of the Opposition spoke of &quot;an enquiry, affecting as it does both Houses of Parliament&quot;  A joint, enquiry would
be appropriate if it were to include the wider question of the extent to which legis-lative power should be delegated but, as indicated in paragraph 3 above, I thinkthat we should avoid an enquiry of this kind. If the enquiry is restricted to theprocedure for dealing with statutory instruments, I can; see no justification for bringing in the House of Lords, and their inclusion would inevitably complicate the enquiry and greatly diminish the chances that any recommendations emergingfrom the enquiry might prove acceptable. I would therefore suggest that, if we agree to any enquiry, we should stipulate that it should be restricted to procedure in the House of Commons^8. If a Select Committee were appointed during the present Session it wouldbarely have time to begin work before the Recess and the proposed enquiry is not so urgent as to justify its meeting during the Recess. I therefore propose that in replying to the Leader of the Opposition I should say that we think that the appoint-ment should be postponed till next Session.      &apos;9. To sum up, I should be glad to have the views of my colleagues on thefollowing points:  ,Should we agree to an enquiry by a Select Committee into the procedure for dealing with delegated legislation, notwithstanding that the evidence given to the Select Committee of 1946 and the recent examination of thesubject by officials suggest that there aTe no radical changes in theexisting procedure which could be made without seriously impairingthe virtues of delegated legislation and making undue demands on thetime of Ministers and officials?Should the terms of reference of any enquiry be so restricted as to excludean examination of the principles on which legislative powers should be delegated by Parliament to Ministers?Should any enquiry be confined to procedure in the House of Commons?Should the appointment of a Select Committee be postponed till next session?J. C. E.Home Office, S.W. 1,ISth June, 1951.40751
Text of Statement by Home Secretary on 19th March, 1951Motions to Annul Orders (Procedure)The Secretary of State for the Home Department (Mr. Ede): I beg to move,&quot; That the Debate be now adjourned.&quot;This Order can be prayed-against until 11th April. Therefore it cannot beregarded as really urgent. But, even if there were other considerations, we neednot reach a decision on it to-night. I think it is as well that, as on this Motion wecannot discuss the merits of the Order, we should have an opportunity of consideringthe way in which this House is being treated by the continual moving of thesePrayers for no other reason than the physical exhaustion of hoft. Members and ministers of the Crown.A speech was delivered last week in a village which I know very well, the villagof Banstead.   In that speech it was announced that harrying Was to be carried onI had an uncle who was a Master of Harriers for an area which covered the villagof Banstead.   Harriers are used to hound hares.   The Opposition has chosenthe wrong hound for the animal it is hunting. We are not hares. [Hon. Members.-&quot; Rabbits.&quot;]  Nor rabbits.  We are an animal which, when attacked, has anothertrick beside that of running away.I suggest to the House that it is time we considered where the reputation of this house will go if there is a much longer continuation of the process to which we havebeen subjected during the past few weeks. Let me say at once that I have noobjection to all-night sittings and, in fact, during the last Parliament, and in others in which I have satj my appearance at about 11 - 30 p.m. has frequently been received with groans because it has been regarded as ah indication that we were going to situntil the early hours of the morning. My view is that, if we are going to have anall-night sitting, let us have it, and not break off at about three o&apos;clock with themaximum amount of inconvenience for hon. Members and the staff.We are told that the Opposition wish to work according to rule, and that theyrely upon the rules of the House to enable them to continue this pressure; but pastmajorities in this House have ensured that the majority, no matter how small, shallbe able to get its way if it is determined to do so. Down to 1881, there was completefree speech in this House. The debate started, and could be continued so long as there were hon. Members willing to speak because the rules of the House were drawnup in the eighteenth century by two parties, whose members mainly consisted, asregards the back benchers, of fox-hunting squires; and it is from them that we getthe name of &quot; Whip &quot; for those who see that people are in the pack when requiredThen, the Irish came, and they were neither fox-hunters nor squires [An honMember: &quot; They were fox-hunters.&quot;] Perhaps, but not the type of fox-hunter whohad come here. On 1st March, 1881, they had kept the House sitting for forty-onehours, and Mr. Speaker Brand entered the Chamber at nine o&apos;clock in the morning and, without any Standing Order, announced that he was going to put the QuestionHe did so, in order to maintain the dignity.of this House; and from that date,successive Oppositions, by pursuing the same tactics, have compelled a steadydiminution in the free speech formerly accorded in this House, and we have hadthe Closure, the Kangaroo, and the Guillotine as subsequent processes.His Majesty&apos;s Government are anxious to maintain the maximum amount of free speech in this House [Interruption]. Well, during the past week we have seenhow greatly that spirit has been appreciated by the Opposition. I have had hon.Members opposite coming to me and asking during the night, &quot;&quot;When are we goingto have the Closure?Mr. Erroll: No.Mr. Ede: Never have such indignities been inflicted by an Opposition upon their own hon. Members. The other night, eleven hon. Members on the other sidewere on their feet when the Deputy Chief Whip moved the Closure. They were sobored by one another that when the question was put they did not challenge it.They have shown a strange reluctance, after arguments which ought to have endednot in a Prayer but in a motion for impeachment, to go into the Lobby in supportof their own Prayer. It was suggested to me by two ingenious friends of mine thatthe back benchers opposite had received orders from the Front Bench not to go into
the Division Lobby and, of course, any two tellers that the back benchers providedmight have been severely censured. After all, if all the people who had beendenouncing us had gone into the Lobby, they could not all have been disciplined,even by the right hon. Gentlemen opposite. Not even Lord Margesson would have attempted that.This House has a very great and honourable tradition, which it is the duty ofeach succeeding generation to maintain in order to pass it on to its successors.This is the first time that on matters of administration it has been made perfectlyplain, not merely by irresponsible back benchers like the hon. Member forAberdeenshire, East (Mr. Boothby), but [An hon. Member: &quot;What about &quot;TheRed Flag&apos;? &quot;] If the hon. Member had been here on the day &quot; The Red Flag &quot;was sung, he would have known that it was not the first song that was sung onthat day. The first choral effort came from the Opposition. Not merely by anirresponsible but ebullient back bencher like the Member for East Aberdeenshire,but on Saturday night by the Leader of the Opposition, this policy has been endorsed.It is part of the duty of the House to keep a close check on the Executive. Itis one of the fundamental1 duties not merely of the Opposition but of every Memberof the House to see that a close check is kept on the Executive. One of the ways of doing it is by the Prayer method. We are anxious that there should be no denialto the Opposition of this method of checking the Executive. But it is onlyreasonable to say that this method should be operated in circumstances whichenable the House to perform its duty of checking effectively. That has not beendone during the past fortnight or so.We are exceedingly anxious that this method should be continued effectivelyand we are willing to enter into conversations with either the right hon. Gentlemanwho marshals the forces opposite or the platoon-sergeants who are put up each onhis appropriate night to conduct the guerrilla warfare in order that the House maybe kept out of bed. We do not think that is an effective way of the Housedischarging its duties, but we are willing to consider with those who have this suddenexcess of piety the way in which they can pray at a time when they are more likelyto be effectively heard both in this House and in the country.. One of the astonishing things is that the whole of their efforts have passedunrecorded as far as the details of their criticisms have been concerned, and weare most anxious that they should not be put at that disadvantage any longer.Many suggestions have been made to me by hon. Friends of mine sitting behindme as to the way in which this could be done, but I should prefer to-night not todeal with any of them, but to leave the field quite open for free discussion, so thatthe House can discharge its historic duty in circumstances that will enable it soto act as to reflect credit on itself and to make its criticisms effective.I sincerely hope that this offer, which is made in all sincerity and genuineness,will be considered by hon. Gentlemen opposite. For let me tell them this, thatthe casualties in any war of attrition will not be on this side of the House. too many of my hon. Friends have spent all their lives on one night shift a week forthem to be deterred in any such contest as this. But I make this appeal, in thename of sound democratic government in one of the few places where that stillflourishes, that we shall bring an end to the episodes which have done no credit tothis House during the past few weeks, and that we shall seek to discharge ourduties in a way that will ensure that the public interest shall be served and thatthis House shall retain its just reputation as a place for reasonable discussion.ANNEX BWesterham 93 Chartwell,Westerham,Kent.My dear Home Secretary, 5 th June, 1951.You will remember that it was agreed at the meeting in your room at the Houseof Commons on 26th April that I should forward you in writing my views and thoseof my colleagues on Prayer Procedure, and I have been giving this matter carefulconsideration since then.The Select Committee on Procedure in 1946 took a great deal of evidence onthis subject: three days were spent in examining Sir Charles MacAndrew, Doctor
D. K. Allen and Doctor E. C. S. Wade, and most of the other witnesses were also asked questions about delegated legislation. The Committee finally reported:  &quot;A Select Committee should be appointed in the coming session, orpreferably that the House of Lords should be invited to concur in the appoint-ment of a joint Committee to inquire into the delegation of legislative powerand the procedure of the House in relation thereto.&quot;This was not done, but it is still our view that for a long-term answer to thequestions raised by Prayers such a Committee is desirable.Yours sincerely,. (Signed)        WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.ANNEX CExtract from Annex to Gen. 343/4V -Parliamentary Control42. The question of Parliamentary control of delegated legislation is a very -important one in relation to this Bill, because the powers to make orders underPart II and Part III are and must be very wide, and are bound to be criticised as ausurpation of the functions of Parliament by the Executive. We have thereforeexamined a number of possible procedures for giving a more effective control toParliament than is at present provided in the draft Bill. The Bill gives the usualpower of annulment by negative resolution (clause 21) and an opportunity to reviewannually the general operation of the Bill when Ministers&apos; reports are laid beforeParliament (clause 22). We realise that these provisions are not likely to satisfy theParliamentary critics, but our efforts to improve on them without prejudicing theworking of the Bill have been unsuccessful. The fundamental difficulty is that thereasons which justify the delegation of powers, viz., the complexity of the subject matter and the need for a flexible instrument to meet unforeseen changes of circum-stance, are also reasons for not imposing a close Parliamentary control. The best that one can hope for is a compromise solution which goes some way to meet theParliamentarians without unduly fettering the exercise of the delegated powers.43. We examined first the possibility of requiring a limited category of themore important orders to be laid in draft, and of giving Parliament an opportunity,not only of rejecting a draft order in toto, but also of making amendments to it.The power of amendment has been given on rare occasions, the latest example beingsection 475 of the Government of India Act, 1935, but its feasibility has neverreally been tested in an important and controversial field. It would be necessary to devise a procedure which would give the Minister in charge of an order ah oppor-tunity to examine amendments, after hearing the arguments for and against, and tomake his final decision, possibly involving alternative amendments, at a later stage.The procedure would also have to provide means for obtaining agreement betweenthe two Houses (unless the power of amendment were to be confined to the House ofCommons). In fact the approval of an order might involve in each House two of thethree main stages of a Bill, committee and report. It would no doubt be possible totake the committee stage in a standing committee, but even so the potential demands on the time of Ministers, members and officials would be formidable.44. There is, moreover, a serious practical objection to laying orders under theBill in draft, whether with or without a power of amendment. The type of order which Parliament would wish to see in draft, and to have power to amend (if sucha power were given), is an order which imposes a new form of control or extendsan existing power of control to a new field. An order of this type, however, mustalmost invariably come into operation directly its terms are known; advance publica-tion may defeat the whole purpose of the order. For example, if a new rationing scheme were to be preceded, by publication and debate in Parliament, there wouldprobably be a run on existing stocks of the goods proposed to be rationed.
45. We have considered two possible methods of getting round this difficulty.The first is to follow a precedent contained in s.44(3) of the Government of india act, 1919, and to leave it to the Minister concerned to decide which orders are to belaid in draft. The Bill would have to give some indication of the lines on which his discretion would be exercised, but would leave him power to exclude any order which could not, in the public interest, be published in advance. This has attractivefeatures, because the Minister would be the best judge of the kind of orders whichwere of sufficient general interest to be suitable for Parliamentary examination.Unfortunately all the main departments concerned agree that such a discretionwould be extremely embarrassing, because the Minister would be compelled to exclude practically all the important orders which Parliament would most like to concern itself with, and would be constantly bombarded with criticism for failing to make the section work.46. The second possibility which we considered was to put some kind ofobligation on the competent authorities to consolidate from time to time their principal control orders, and to lay these consolidation orders, or at any rate themore important ones, in draft. Periodic consolidation is a fairly common feature of orders made under Defence Regulation 55, at any rate in the more active fields ofcontrol, and the laying of a consolidation order would give Parliament an oppor-tunity of reviewing the machinery of control in a particular section of industry andwould thus be supplementary to the more general annual review under clause 22. Inpractice, however, we think that Parliament&apos;would be very dissatisfied with a pro-vision on these lines, which would give no opportunity for considering the making of new law but only one for reviewing existing law. Moreover it would be difficultto frame a provision which would put a reasonable obligation on the competent authority and would result in a representative, but not too large, class of ordersbeing submitted to Parliament.47.  Assuming, therefore, that any procedure involving the laying of orders indraft is impracticable, we have considered whether the negative resolution property -cedure could be extended by adding to the power of annulment a power torecommend amendments. Any such recommendation would have to be embodied in an amending order made by the appropriate Minister: for the only satisfactory method of amending a statutory instrument already in force is by an amendingstatutory instrument printed and published in accordance with the Statutory Instru-ments Act. There is no precedent for a procedure of this kind, and the practicalobjections are formidable, but it may be worth examining how it would work out.i   Recommendations for amending the order would be put down within the sameperiod of forty days as a motion for annulment. The form of motion would be similar to that of amendment of a Bill, i.e., it would specify the precise verbal altera-tion to be made. The Minister would indicate whether he accepted the proposal as it stood, or accepted it in principle, or was prepared to consider it, or rejected it.There would be no further &quot; stage &quot; in Parliament, but the Minister would give effectto any recommendation which he accepted, or any other undertaking given by him,by means of an amending order. If he was unable to give effect to a recommenda-tion which had been carried, the Bill might place him under a statutory obligationto lay an explanatory statement before Parliament within a prescribed period. Thewhole procedure would be comparatively simple if the right to recommend amend-ments were confined to the Commons, but not if it were extended to the Lords.We do not think that any independent right to recommend amendments giving rise to an obligation of the Minister to give effect to the recommendation or lay an explanatory statement can be given to the Lords.  It is true that they have anindependent right of annulment by negative resolution, and have always used it with great discretion, but a power of amendment is a very different thing from a power to reject a Government proposal in toto (as has been shown by the Lords&apos;proceedings on Bills), and they would probably exercise the former power freely.Our conclusion is that, if a right to recommend amendments is to be given to bothHouses, the amendments will have to be agreed between them.-48.  A provision of this kind, whether limited to the Commons or extendedI   to both Houses, would go a long way to meet Parliamentary criticisms of this aspect of the Bill, and would dispose of the frequently expressed argument that the onlyi   way of registering a protest against sOme particular feature of an order is by votingfor the annulment of the whole order. Moreover, from the administrative point ofview, amendments suggested in Parliament sometimes result in valuable point is  being raised which Ministers are glad to meet, and. a definite procedure for making
such suggestions would encourage this process. The practical objections, however,seem to us so great that we cannot recommend its adoption in the Bill. It would establish a precedent which would always be cited Whenever a power of delegated legislation was given and would be very difficult to resist. It would give the officialOpposition, or a group of back benchers, endless opportunities to waste the time ofMinisters and officials and to wreck the Parliamentary programme; for the Govern-ment would find it very difficult to resist demands for adequate facilities to debateamendments placed on the Order paper. Even under the present procedure, theMinistry of Food have found that a negative Prayer is invariably put down when-ever an order affecting any branch of food rationing is made, and feel that, if thepower of amendment were added, the situation, would rapidly get out of hand. Wewould also add that the present procedure does give a much more effective oppor-tunity than Members of Parliament are willing to admit to suggest amendments on points of detail to Ministers; there have been several occasions on which amendingorders have been made to meet points so raised.49. We have considered whether the practical objections to the proposal would be mitigated by conferring the power of recommending amendments, at anyrate in the first instance, on a committee; our view is that nothing would be gained.A committee such as the present Statutory Instruments Committee would certainly not be a suitable body to exercise such a power, and it would be necessary to setup something like a standing committee on a Bill which would represent the strengthof the parties and on which the appropriate Minister could defend the policy under-lying the order. If all orders made under the Bill were referred to such a committee,and they were given a power of recommending amendments, it would hardly bepossible, even if there was no deliberate obstruction, for them to get through thebusiness.50. Our conclusion is that the Bill should remain in its present form, with thetwo Parliamentary safeguards contained in Clauses 21 and 22. One other sugges-tion, which we think just worth mentioning, is that the Statutory InstrumentsCommittee should have their terms of reference enlarged so as to enable them toconsider the merits of orders made under the Bill. This suggestion was put forward in the memorandum of Sir Gilbert Campion (now Lord Campion) appended to thereport of the Select Committee on Procedure in 1946, and was rejected by theGovernment on the ground stated in paragraph 12 of their memorandum to theCommittee, viz, that it &quot; would mean that Ministers would have to attend beforethe Select Committee to defend the policy embodied in subordinate legislation.&quot; we agree with this view, which indeed was put forward in our last paragraph when wewere considering the possibility of enabling a power to recommend amendments to be exercised by a committee. The Government could hardly allow a committeeof private members, on which the Government as such was not represented, to issuereports on the merits of Government policy on important and controversial matters such as food rationing or direction of labour. In the evidence before the SelectCommittee on Procedure Sir Charles MacAndrew and Sir Cecil Carr expressedthe view that, if merits were to be considered, the semi-judicial character of thepresent Scrutiny Committee would be destroyed. It may be mentioned that theSpecial Orders Committee of the House of Lords already have power to reporton orders which seem to them &quot; to raise important questions of policy or principle,&quot;and therefore can consider merits. In practice, however, they tend to confine them-selves to points of a more or less formal character, which supports the argument that this kind of committee is not really a suitable body to examine government policy. Moreover, it does not seem likely that an enlargement of the ScrutinyCommittee&apos;s terms of reference would meet Parliamentary criticism of this aspect of the, Bill to any appreciable extent.


</content>
</cab>
