<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 149-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
) NOTEC.P.(51) 170The attached memorandum will beconsidered at the meeting of the Cabinettomorrow, Thursday, 21st June, afterItem 1.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,20TH JUNE, 1951.
-    109IS -DOCUMENT -IS-THE PROPERT Y-OF- HIS -BRITANNIC- MA JEST Y *S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP.(51) 170 COPY NO._20TH JUNE, 1951CABINETVALIDITY OF EMERGENCY ACTSMemorandum by the Home secretary in the case of Willcock v. Muckle a Divisional Court of the King&apos;bench Division will be considering next Monday the question whether theNational Registration Act, 1939, has been brought to an end by an Order-in-Council made last October (S.1.1950 No. 1647) which was only intendedto bring to an end the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act, 1943, and theCourts (Emergency Powers) (Scotland) Act, 1939.    I think that I ought to warn my colleagues of the difficulties in which we may be placed, if (as i hope will not, in fact, happen) the decision goes against the continuingvalidity of the National Registration Act.2. During the war, a number of temporary Acts (some 42 in all) were passed containing a provision enabling the Act, or particular provisions ofthe Act, to be brought to an end on a date declared by Order-in-Council&quot;to be the date on which the emergency that was the occasion of the passingof this Act came to an end&quot;.    In 1944, the Law Officers advised that theemergency was not necessarily one and the same for all the Acts, and accordingly since the beginning of 1946 some 21 Orders-in-Council havebeen made bringing a number of Acts to an end on various dates, while 15Acts (the remainder having been repealed) are still regarded as in force.The position of the various emergency Acts was reviewed by the lord presidents Committee as recently as 21st April, 1950 (L.P.(50) 4thMeeting, Minute 2) in the course of a general examination of the duration of emergency powers.3. The argument of the appellant is that there is only one &quot;emergency&quot;which was the occasion of all these Acts, and that that emergency hasalready been ended by Orders-in-Council already made, in particular bythe Courts (Emergency Powers) (End of Emergency) Order, 1950:    andthat the National Registration Act, 1939, has for this reason come to anend and with it the power to require the production of identity cards.   -The argument on the other side, briefly, will be that only an Order-in-Council expressly declaring the end of the emergency that was theoccasion of the passing of the National Registration Act, 1939, can bringthat Act to an end, and that no such Order has been made.4. If the court gives judgment for the appellant, I understand thatit can only do so on grounds which will be equally applicable to the otherActs of Parliament concerned.    On this principle, these Acts willprobably have to be regarded as having come to an end on the date declared by the first of the &quot;End of Emergency&quot; Orders, the Regional CommissionersAct (Expiry) Order, 1946 (S.R. &amp; C. 194-6 No. 164), namely, 11th June, 1945.The more important of these, acts are the Armed Forces (Conditions ofService) Act, 1939, the Import, Export and Customs Powers (Defence) Act,
IS39, the Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions Act, 1939, the ImportDuties (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1939, and the Goods and Services(Price Control) Acts, 1939 to 1S43,5. Over much of the field affected, the existing machinery would no doubt continue to operate for a week or so, provided that there wasa prospect of remedial legislation.    There would, however, be some immediate repercussions.    For example, a landlord who had applied toa Court for possession would be able to plead successfully that the rent restrictions Act was no longer in force.    In addition there would be general uncertainty as to the law, and troubles would soon mount up.There would be confusion about the rates of import duties.    The removalof import control would make exchange control less effective.    It wouldbe difficult to prevent the export of strategic materials to communist countries or of materials which were essential for United Kingdomrearmament.    A number of price control orders would become invalid.Some reservists could not legally be retained.    Moreover, everythingdone since 1945 under the authority of these Acts could be called inquestion.6. Accordingly, if the case were decided in favour of the appellant,it would be necessary to introduce forthwith, and to endeavour to passwith the minimum of delay, retrospective legislation validating all theActs concerned.J-. C .E.Home Office, S.W.1,20TH JUNE, 1951.
1,39, the Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions Act, 1939, the ImportDuties (Emergency Provisions) Act, 193$,: and the Goods, and Services(Price Control) Acts, 1939 to. 1543,5,         Over much of the field aXfected,&quot; the existing machinery would no doubt continue to operate for a week or so, provided that there wasa prospect of remedial legislation.    There would, however, be some immediate repercussions.    For example, a landlord who had applied toa Court for possession would be able to plead successfully that the rent restrictions Act was no longer in force.    In addition there would be    * &quot;.general uncertainty as to the law, and troubles would soon mount up.There would be confusion about the rates of import duties.    The removalof import control would make exchange control less effective.    It wouldbe difficult to prevent the export of strategic materials to communist countries or Of materials which were essential for United Kingdomrearmament.   A number of price control orders would become invalid.Some reservists could not legally be retained. , Moreover, everythingdone since: 1945 under the authority of these Acts could be called inquestion. - &apos; .V/-&apos;-,   i -k - &apos;6.        Accordingly, if the case were decided in favour of the appellant,it would be necessary to introduce forthwith, and to endeavour to passwith the minimum of delay, retrospective legislation validating all theActs concerned.   .J-.C.E.Home Office, S.W.1,20TH JUNE, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
