<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 157-164</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cm mlu(a*uJ^(J&amp;*   -  -     r^rPT4^WM6713/56B1 loom. 4-si wa.&amp;oo. 05113. record copyTHIS  DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY   OF   HI8   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;8   OOYBRNMEHT;             The circulation o  this paper has been strictly limited,It ie issued for the personal use of...................................top secret &apos;a * , ,   /   ,    n a ^C.P.(51) 172 ^C^TV^^^r.29TH JtJNE, 1951CABINETPERSIASEIZURE CFABADAN ISLANDMemorandum by the Chiefs of StaffWe have examined the action which it will be necessary to take if we are to mount an operation to seize Abadan Island and to hold it foran indefinite period. Details of the action, and of its implications, are set out in the Annex.TIMING2. If the preparatory action is authorised forthwith (on 2nd July), theleading elements of the force could reach Ahadan about 19th August. any delay in authorising this preparatory action will result in a correspondingdelay in the date of arrival at Abadan.ACTION REQUIRED FOR THE PREPARATORY PHASE3.    Royal Navy(a)   Action required the commissioning of a number of amphibious warfare craft.(b;   ImplicationsThe immobilisation often destroyers or ipigates; notcommissioning two fast minelayers; taking about oOOjiatings froni theReserve Fleet.    This effect could in part be offset wiilrin about twfs monthsby calling up Royal Fleet Reservists and Z Reservistgfwhich woulp be essential. v I4.   Army!-(a)   Action requiredTo bring the force in the Middle East whiffli is to carry out theoperation up to higher establishment.    This will requ&amp;e some 10,000 men.(b)   Implications(i) The retention of regulars and recall of regular reservists.(ii) Legislation to enable selective retention of national servicemen to be applied when require^.
(iii) The call-up of Z Reservists on existing plans formobilising the units concerned. I(iv) The extension of overseas tours.5.    Royal Air ForceIt might be necessary to retain some specialist reservists,atpresent under training and to call up for an indefinite period Somespecialist reservists shortly due for training.6.    Shipping(a) Action required(i) The assembly and retention in the Middle East of about six personnel ships and ten MT/store ships.(ii)  The assembly in the United Kingdom Of eleven personnelships and twenty MT/store ships to move replacementforces to the Middle East, should the operation bemounted. *(b) Implications(i)  Interference with normal passenger shipping programmes,(ii)  Interference v/ith the import programme (including iron ore) and to some extent with the export programme.(iii) Possibly some effect on American assistance in the bulkimport programme, notably iron ore and cereals,.7*   Air TransportIt will be necessary to charter some civilian aircraft.ADDITIONAL. ACTION REQUIRED IF THE OPERATION IS MOUNTED8.    Army(^)  Action required(i)-.r-The. despatch to the Middle East of 3rdlits appropriate reinforcement far thjjjto 6,000 men, &apos;    ?ifantry Divpurpose, a:lion andlountihghi:(ii)  The embodying of one First Contingen^^rritorial ArmyDivision,    This would amount to aboffl 19,000 men.&apos;&apos;    V&quot; Iff&apos;(iii) The creation oijj kjfjteinforcement pool to^-^replace casualties in Persia.i
9* &apos;        We recommend that the Cabinet should:-(a) Authorise the immediate implemention of the preliminarymeasures outlined in the Annex and in particular inparagraphs 3 to 7 above.(b) Take note of the additional action which will be required should it be decided that the operation is to be mounted(paragraph 8 above).(Signed)  FRASERW.J. SLIMr JiC, SLESSOR29TH JUNE, 1951.(i) An extension of those fisted in paragraph 5(b) above.(ii) A proclamation embodying one Territorial Army .Division. &apos; &apos;-&apos;(iii) Some-interference with the current Z Reservists&apos;training scheme,RECOMMENDATION
P I . ANNEX , .i   - -*---- 1*.I&apos;&apos;    In this paper we examine the action it will be necessary to take if we are to be prepared to mount an operation to capture Abadan Islandat short notice.    We have set out the implications that would arise from taking such action.    Our conclusions are as follows:-NAVY2. One cruiser, two frigates and one LST are in the operationalarea now.    Two further frigates or destroyers can be made available to accompany and escort the amphibious force.    Including the LST now inthe Persian Gulf 12 LSTs with 36 LCAs embarked, a Maintenance Ship anda HQ Ship can be assembled in the Canal Area and ready for service by not earlier than 6th August, if the order to prepare the amphibious force is given on 1st July.       5   more LSTs could arrive by mid-September.11 LCTs can also be provided by not earlier than 6th August if required.3. The man-power requirement for all these ships and craft amountsto about 2,150 and could only be met by the immediate immobilisation of10 destroyers or frigates in local UK flotillas or about to commission for service, by not commissioning two fast minelayers, and by taking about600 ratings from the Reserve Fleet.    These could in part be replaced in about two months&apos; time by calling up Royal Fleet Reservists within thepresent permitted ceiling, but a further call-up including Z Reservistswill be essential to make good the remainder.4. If the .11 LCTs are not required, 250 men will be saved, and thiswill reprieve 2 of the 10 destroyers or frigates from immobilisation.!       ARMY5. The following land forces will be required for the operation andwill be found from within Middle East resources.1(a) 1st Infantry Division (less one brigade)(b) 16 Parachute Brigade.   .     !(c) One Armoured regiment.6. * Should the operation be launched it will be necessary to replace the above forces by one division from the. United Kingdom.    Cf the two divisions at present in the United Kingdom, 6th Arm^hred Division isco^nmitted to SHAPE at the end of this.year; the reifacement formationfor the Middle East must therefore be 3rd Infantry division,&apos; ; &apos; :        )   &apos;7.     !&apos;     Preparations for the mounting of the dperal^n at Shortlnoticewill involve immediate action to bring: -(a)    Units of the operational force to higher estfplishment.(b) The fighting units 61lj ment less 10% antI       ment.ijrd Infantry Division t$ higher establish-administrative units to lower establish-b^ing decided to mtkist the operation and to sendI last it will be necessary to replace 3rdIn the event of itrd Division tb the Middlejivisjlon since this formation aljt present.constitutes the Strategic Reserve.
0,i s;:   This should be effected by embodying First Contingent Territorial army   on the basis of one division in roulement for a period of three monthsij! each.I!!9. The action described in paragraphs 7 and 8 above will necessi-tate calling up 33,000 men (or 36,000, see (a) below), the breakdown ofwhich is as followst-(a) 1st Division, 16 Parachute Brigade Group and one armouredregiment - 8,000.    (If those under, 19 years old are not    - (eligible for Persia an additional 3,000 men will be required),(b) 3rd Division - 6,000. .(c) One Territorial Army Infantry Division - 19,000.10.         The following further implications will arise:-(a) The creation and maintenance of a reinforcement pool to replacecasualties in. Persia.(b) There will be some interference with the current Z Reservisttraining scheme which will not, however, be interfered with more than is essential,11, *      The above measures will require(a) The retention of regulars and recall of regular reservists.(b) Legislation to enable selective retention of National Servicemento be applied when required.The call-up of Z Reservists on existing plans for mobilisingthe formations affected.(c)(d)   A proclamation embodying one Territorial Army Division.M -hi;i2.(e)    The extension of overseas tcjurs.AIR FORCE .;i The (following air forces would be required:p.(j; !    I j(iy - 24 Hastings. - ; \-Wmjl (ii)ij   5- MR Transport Squadrons,,,(iii);- 2 Fighter/Ground Attack Squadrons.(iv):1 I Fighter Reconnaissance Squadron.&quot;(v)jl  1 Light Bomber Squip:i I. J*( ii...I^13^&apos;,,, iji The squadrons requij \feA are now stationed in line Middle East, but&quot;some&apos; shortage of radar equimheij^iuppiyjfrorri the United Kingdfombt and pexsonnel may exfstj necessitating
14.ibelow.i The implications of providing the forces required are examined15. The air forces required will represent the larger part of theMiddle East Air Force.    The replacement of these squadrons could onlybe effected from BAFC where the only tactical units are available,BAFO squadrons, however, have been assigned to SHAPE and any with-drawal might have serious repercussions in NATO,    We do not, however,consider that replacement of whole units will be necessary, at least untilthe situation at Abadan is clarified.    Two Vampire Squadrons will remain-in the Canal Zone.    Replacement of the C and R and some technical andadministrative personnel in the Middle East might involve the retentionof specialist reservists at present under training and the calling up foran indefinite period of specialist reservists shortly due for training.SHIPPING16. We consider that the early mounting of the operation should notbe prejudiced by the forces required for the assault and immediate follow-up of phases of the operation having to await the arrival of the personnel ,and MT ships from the United Kingdom.    We therefore consider that inorder to avoid delay in mounting the operation, and also to reduce thenotice of which the assault force can arrive in the Persian Gulf to 14 days,the necessary shipping must be prepositioned in the Middle East.    Thiswill take one month, and at a preliminary estimate would consist of 6personnel ships and 10 MT stores ships.17. If the operation is mounted there will be a further requirement of an estimated 11 personnel ships and 20 MT store ships to bringreplacement units from the United kingdom to the Middle East.18. It follows that in order to avoid a gap of up to five weeks in the replacement of units in the Middle East by 3rd Infantry Division from theUnited Kingdom it will be necessary also to earmark and hold shipping asshown in paragraph 17 above.19.(a)(b)The implications of taking up shipping are as follows:-Owing to the present high demand on passenger ships the taking up of personnel ships will interfere with the normal passenger. shipping programme.-The (military freight programme can only be undertaken at theexpense of existing import programme including iron ore, andat some -Cost to the export programmje, inclitding that to theSouthern.dominions and anthracite toi Canada.&apos; &apos; 1Immobilisation of dry cargo ships may have.jits effect on.american assistance in bulk import programme notaply iron ore and cereals.AIR TRANSPORT120J. We consider that it ijlljjlssential to reinforce those units in theMiddle;! East earmarked for the operation as quickly as possible.    Thism k e:si&apos;&apos;it necessary to use air transport to J life&apos;those reinforcements not affected by innoculation delays,&apos;1 In the..event these numberB would not bey g&amp;sat; but since the manor ty of R.A.F. Transport Commknd is already:C-a)&apos;iy committed it will be ne^ess ary to charter some civilian ajircraft.3 .       o



</content>
</cab>
