<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 266-269</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JREPORT OF BROADCASTING committee memorandum by the Home secretary the statement in paragraph 7 of CP. (51) 183 that the proposalfor independent Broadcasting Commissions for Scotland, Wales and NorthernIreland made by the Beveridge Committee &quot;may appeal to Nationalistsentiment in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland&quot; is, so far as wales is concerned, very much of an understatement.   The facts are that all three Welsh organisations who gave evidence before the Beveridge Committee(the New Wales Union, the Welsh National Party and the Welsh Parlia-mentary Party) were unanimously in favour of an independent broadcasting corporation for Wales - a proposition which had the support of themajority of the Welsh local authorities.   Even the Beveridge Committee&apos;proposal is therefore regarded in some quarters as inadequate, though ithas been accepted by the New Wales Union and the Welsh National Partyin a statement sent to the Prime Minister on 23rd May ( a copy of which is  *annexed ) as &quot;the acceptable minimum&quot;.   This statement ends with thefollowing paragraph:-&quot;The time has come for Wales and her leaders to set their facesfirmly against any less adequate proposals which would be adenial of the united declarations which have been published;and to stand together in this matter. &quot;2. Resolutions supporting the Beveridge Committee&apos;s proposal havebeen received from six local authorities in North Wales, including onecounty council (Flintshire).   It is certain, therefore, that the rejection of the Beveridge Committee&apos;s recommendations will be strongly opposed bysome quarters in Wales including some not irreconcilably Nationalistic.The reasons given for the decision to reject the Committee&apos;s recom-mendations will, in consequence, be subjected to close examination.   the paragraph in the White Paper in which these reasons are given (paragraph 19)has been considerably redrafted, but I doubt whether the reasons now givenwill convince Welsh sentiment.   To begin with, the only practical difficulty which is mentioned is the fact that the responsibility of members of the commissions&apos; staffs would be divided, and interchange and promotion withinthe whole Corporation made more difficult.   This is the sort of argument which is commonly used to block proposals for devolution and it is unlikely to carry much weight.  As regards the other two objections mentioned inthis paragraph, it seems to me that, looked at from the point of view of Wales,they are not really objections at all, but simply the natural consequence of allowing some measure of independence in Wales,   It is obvious that this would affect the collective responsibility of the Governors for the activities of theCorporation as a whole, but this is precisely what Welsh sentiment desires.Similarly, the division of responsibility would be bound to be an obstacle to the development of coherent policies, because its whole object would be toenable a distinctive policy for Wales to be developed.(THIS DOCUMENT -IS THE-PROPERTY- OF-HIS 3RITANNIG-MA JESTY^S GOVERNMENT)secret.P.(51) 187 COPY NO.2ND JULY, 1951. CABINET
3. It appears from paragraph V of C.F. (51) 183 that it is feared thatif an independent Commission were set up for Wales it would make&quot;irresponsible financial and other proposals which the Corporation wouldhave the odium of turning down&quot;.   It is not clear what evidence there is forthinking that an independent Commission would not do its best to workharmoniously with the Corporation and it is difficult to see why thealternative scheme should work any better.   According to paragraph 21 of theWhite Paper, &quot;all major questions of policy and administration relatingto their areas, including finance and capital development, will be settled inconjunction with the Broadcasting Councils&quot;.   If there is a disagreement between the Corporation and one of the Councils it seems most unlikelythat it will be possible to conceal it and the same sort of difficulty istherefore likely to arise.4. I would also point out that opposition to the rejection ofthe Beveridge Committee&apos;s proposals is likely to come not only from theNationalist elements in Wales and Scotland, but also from those who are opposed on general grounds to monopoly in the B. B. C.   The proposal for independent Regional Commissions was the only recommendation in the beveridge Ccmmittee,s Report which weakened this monopoly.J. C. S.Home Office, S.W.1.,2ND JULY, 1951.
annex the FUTURE OF BROADCASTING IN WALESStatement by the New Wales Union and the welsh National PartyIt is understood that the Government will shortly publish a white Paper outlining a policy for the control of Broadcasting in Britainfrom the beginning of 1952 onwards.   Attention is therefore drawn to theviews expressed by Wales in favour of an independent 3roadcastingCorporation.   This was supported by a majority of the Welsh CountyCouncils (with no contrary resolution) and by more than fifty other LocalAuthorities.The three Welsh organisations which submitted evidence to LordBeveridge&apos;s Committee were unanimously in favour of an independentBroadcasting Corporation for Wales:  and in the powerful memorandum which was submitted by the Welsh Parliamentary Party, the position is described in these words:&quot;We, the Members of Parliament of all the constituencies in Wales, representative of all the major political parties,wish to submit to you our case for an independent broadcasting corporation for Wales.   This desire, we know, is shared bythe overwhelming majority of the Welsh people.   As proof ofthis we need only refer to the resolutions on this matterpassed by a large majority of our Local Authorities, ourChapels and Churches, our educational institutions and othercultural bodies and organisations. &quot;In its report Lord Beveridge&apos;s Committee recommends theappointment of a Commission (of five) for Wales, with powers &quot;to initiate and frame a Home Service for its Region&quot; (page 190) and to ensurethat Wales &quot;has its own distinctive voice on the ether&quot; (page 161). &quot;this does not come up to the Welsh demand for an independent Corporation,but at the present time we suggest to Wales that this is the acceptableminimum.The time has come for Wales and her leaders to set their facesfirmly against any less adequate proposals, which would be a denial of theunited declarations which have been published;  and to stand together inthis matter.May, 1951.\


</content>
</cab>
