<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 284-290</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I -    210-US DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJEST Y*SGOVERNMENT-)secret C.P.(51) 192 COPY NO.   316TH JULY, 1951CABINETPERSIA:  RULING OF THE HAGUE COURTMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate to my colleagues a copy of a paper whichwas considered by the Persia Committee of the Cabinet on the6th July on The Hague Courfs recommendations on the persian oil dispute.   The Persia Committee were in general agreementwith the conclusions reached in this paper.H. M.Foreign Office, S.W.1,,6TH JULY, 1951.
PERSIARULING- OF THE HAGUE court the Foreign Office Legal Advisers&apos; appreciation ofthe Court&apos;s ruling is annexed.2, The following are the preliminary views of ForeignOffice officials on the political implications of the ruling:(a) When the dispute &quot;began, world opinion generallywas unfavourahle to us.     &quot;Nationalism&quot; had too strong an appeal, anything that savoured of&quot;Colonialism&quot; was suspect and in any event therewere a good many countries happy to see theBritish in difficulties with a weak State.(b) We then held virtually only two cards;negotiation with the Persians, and the Company&apos;legal rights.     We played the first, makingprogressively generous proposals, and lostj    thecard however is still on the table.     Meanwhile,our attitude of reason and restraint swung world opinion definitely in our favour.     Even pandit nehru, pronounced Nationalist though he is, hascounselled moderation on Mussadiq;     and theUnited States Administration seems now to be ina position in which it cannot help supporting us,if not so fully as we might wish.(c) Our second card, the Company&apos;s legal rights, hasscored heavily in the International Court.Almost any injunction from the Court would havebeen to our advantage, and that which has beengiven seems, in all the circumstances, to be thebest for which we could have hoped.     perhaps the most important feature of it is that the contemplated Board of Supervision is to Toeestablished by agreement between the PersianGovernment and the British Government;   H.M.Government thus have a clear locus standi.Further, the decision does offer a basis for asolution, given goodwill on both sides.(d) Our readiness to implement the Court&apos;s decision is not in question.     Initial Persian reaction isreported by the press to he against doing so - as indeed was to be expected.     Nevertheless it isno light matter for any country to flout thedecision of the highest legal authority in theworld.     If the Persian Government decide to doso (and we must await their final pronouncement)world opinion will Toe even more solidly in our favour.     The only quarter to which the Persianscould look for solace would be the Soviet, andnot even Mussadiq is likely to turn to Russia.Persians in generally are mortally apprehensive,and always have &quot;been, of their northemneighbour.Further, successive Persian Governments (includingMussadiq, when he became Prime Minister) haveexpressed their entire adherence to the united nations - under whose aegis they extricated them-selves from the trouble with Russia in 19H-6.
These factors make it inevitable that there shouldhe an increasingly large body of moderate opinion in Persia which will he alarmed at any suggestion. that Persia, by ignoring a decision of the Inter-national Court, should virtually outcast herself.(e)   Having obtained a ruling from the Court, we should at once accept it publicly, inform the PersianGovernment accordingly, and nominate our membersof the Board of Supervision (possibly suggesting aname or names for the 5th member), and then do our best to avoid any action which might be contrary tothe ruling of the court,3, The Hague Court1s ruling must influence all futurethinking;    and two questions require immediate review in thelight of it: ...(i) Whether or not to modify the existing policy of keeping British personnel in the oilfields aslong as possible;(ii)   Military movements,tj.. As regards (i):   There have been two schools of thought regarding withdrawal,     H,M, Ambassador at Tehranand the present representatives of the Company on the spotbelieve that withdrawal forthwith would bring the Persiansto their senses:    that Mussadiq himself might well not be influenced by it, but it would create such alarm generally in persia that his replacement by another Government would behastened;    and that it would-then be possible to negotiate a settlement which would bring the Company back.     They also consider that tension among British staff has almost reachedbreaking point.     The other school of thought, subscribed toby the Company Board and opinion here, holds that once theCompany left it would probably not be able to return.Dislike of the Company is general in Persia and, if the installations fell derelict, it is quite possible that anyPersian Government would prefer to try to build up theindustry again with a scratch team of technicians rather than to invite the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company back.     Further, wehave long argued that, if the Company were forced out of persia and the installations closed, chaos would ensue anda Communist regime probably emerge:     that state of affairs will be delayed so long as the Company has d. foot in Persia,Finally, unless we oould prove beyond question that conditionshad in fact deteriorated to a point at which our people could not longer stay, public opinion here and in America wouldinterpret withdrawal as weakness.5, The Courfs ruling now requires the A. 1,0,0. tocontinue operations. This, it is suggested, must be decisivefor the present,g. As regards (ii), the question of taking military action to protect British lives remains unaffected.   legal action to protect the installations has already been taken,and the Courfs interim injunction will be conveyedautomatically to the Security Council, which to that extentwill now be officially cognisant of the dispute.     We are nowin a strong moral position, and it would seem unwise to jeopardise it by premature or overt action outside the united nations,     If, despite the Courfs ruling, the Persians take further action against the Company, it would be for considera-tion whether we should at once appeal to the Security council or both appeal and take simultaneous military action toprotect the installations, 6th July. 1951,
ANNEXAppreciation of the Court&apos;s RulingThe ruling can he regarded as generally favourable to H.M. Government&apos;s point of view.     It was inevitable thatit should contain certain recommendations addressed to bothsides.     These are, however, of a general character and fairlyself-evident, i.e., not to take any action which might prejudice the ultimate decision of the Court on the merits and not to take any action which might aggravate or extend the dispute.     These provisions are followed by two recommeda-tions which do precisely what we want, namely indicate that-nothing should be done to hinder the carrying on of theCompany&apos;s operations as,carried on before 1st May and thatthese operations should be carried on under&quot;the Company&apos;smanagement as constituted before 1st May.There then follows a recommendation clearlyinserted as an inducement to the Persians to accept theproposals as a whole.     It is recommended that a Board of supervision be set up, consisting of five members, two eachto be appoined by the two Governments and a fifth, a nationalof a third State, to be appointed by agreement between them or, in default of such agreement and upon a request jointlymade by them, by the President of the Court.     It will be seenthat either Government could block the setting up of theBoard by refusing to agree on the fifth member and by refusing to join in a request to the President of the Court to appointhim.The functions of the Board are as follows:-(1)   to ensure that the Company^ operations are carriedon in accordance with, the recommendations of theCourt;&apos;(2)   the Board may agree with the Company&apos;s modifications in its managerial arrangements, but in default of such agreement, the management continues as before 1st May;(3)    the Board is to audit the revenue and expensesaccounts of the Company and is to ensure thatall revenue in excess of what is required forthe conduct of normal operations   is paid intobanking accounts to be selected by the Board,but only on the undertaking of the banksconcerned not to dispose of the funds exceptin accordance with the decisions of the court or the agreement of the two parties.While this latter provision may not representexactly what we should have liked, it does not constitute aground for refusing to accept the findings of the Court as awhole.Action to be taken&apos;on the resolution(1)   Public statement.     It seems desirable to issue atthe earliest possible moment a formal statement to the effectthat H.M. Government accept the findings of the Court in their entirety, are willing for their part to carry them out and aretalcing up immediately with the Persian Government the questionof setting up the proposed Board of Supervision.
(2)    Action vis-a-vis the Persian Government.     The obviousand correct course is to inform the Persian Government that.M. Government are prepared to nominate their two members ofthe Board and to enter into discussions with the PersianGovernment for the nomination of the fifth member and to request the Persian Government to nominate their own two members.     It would probably also be desirable to draw theattention of the Persian Government to the two provisions inthe Courfs findings about not hindering the operations Ofthe Company as they were carried on before 1st May and aboutthe operations being carried on under the Company&apos;s managementas constituted before 1st May.     On this basis, we can makea specific request to the Persians, e.g., to withdraw fromAbadan the members of the Persian Board who have beeninterfering in the management, to cease requiring tankermasters to sign the Persian form of receipt, etc.      Itseems desirable to seize the opportunity formally to request the Persians to desist, in the light of the finding of theCourt, from all those specific actions which, in our view, .have been hindering operations or which constitute aninterference with the management of the Company.(3)    Military measures.     While we should take ormaintain all necessary steps to be prepared to protect british lives and evacuate the staff of the Company, itwould seem undesirable to bring this out into the open orto give them any special publicity or prominence.     To do so,might be represented by the Persians as action calculated toaggravate or extend the dispute and therefore as contraryto the second of the Courfs recommendations.     If, of course,the Persians flatly reject the recommendations, refuse toco-operate in setting up the proposed Board, they would notbe in a position to quote these reoommendations against us,but until the position is clearer, we should avoid anything which might give the Persians a handle for saying that wewere not ourselves complying with the recommendations.(h)   Further withdrawals of staff.     There is a danger that further withdrawals of staff may be represented as anaggravation of the dispute or as action which is itselfcalculated to hinder the carrying out of the operations of theCompany.     From this point of view we ought probably toavoid any deliberate withdrawal of staff as an act of policyin itself.     There is, however, nothing in the Courfsfindings to prevent staff being withdrawn if such action is &apos;necessitated by, or is the consequence&apos; of, prior Persian actionmaking the carrying on of operations impossible.     Forinstance, any Persian action such as their action overtanker receipts which makes it necessary to reduce production or eventually to stop it altogether, would fully justifyprogressive withdrawal of staff.     The same would applyto any continuance of Persian interference in the managementwhich would make the carrying on of operations under theCompany^ direction impossible.     For the moment we oughtprobably to announce that staff will be kept if the Persianscease all interference..h,
(5)   Appeal to the Security Council,     Under Article i+1of the court  s Statute the interim measures recommendedby them are automatically notified to the Security Council.No positive duty is laid on the security Council in thematter, but it would of course be open to either&apos;party to appeal to it.     Should the Persians reject or fail to complywith the recommendations it would be open to H.M. Government&apos;to ask the security Council for a resolution calling uponthe Persian Government to comply with the findings of theCourt.     Such a resolution would be vetoed by the russians and would therefore have no positive effect, but it wouldbe likely to secure a majority in the Council, thus having a moral effect.     This moral effect would be somewhatreduced if, as is. not at all unlikely, the resolution took the form of calling on both parties to comply with the findings.     Appeal to the Assembly would also be technicallypossible but it does not appear to be the appropriate actionin the circumstances.This note has been cleared, in its general line,with the Attorney-General.


</content>
</cab>
