<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/46/0 images: 388-392</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETNOTECP.(51) 210The attached paper will beconsidered under Item 3 of the agenda for the meeting of the Cabinet to beheld on Thursday, 19th July, 1951, at10.0 a, m.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,18TH .1UL.Y, 1951.
this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MA JEST Y&apos;S- GOVERNMENT)secret.F.(51)210 COPY NO.   318TH JULY, 1951CABINETEXPORTS TO PERSIAMemorandum by the President of the Board of trade my colleagues wish to consider the implications arising out ofthe departure of ships for Persia carrying steel rails and sugar.2. In GEN. 363/7 the Official Working Party on Persia recommended(on 23rd June) that the following measures should be taken either when oilceases to flow under the control of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company or when theCompany withdrew from Persia:(i)   The termination of the clause in the Memorandum of Understandingunder which we provide dollars for Persia&apos;s essential requirements not obtainable for sterling.(ii)   The consequential removal of Persia from the group of countriesregarded as key markets for United kingdom exports and the denial of scarce materials such as steel.3. I think that my colleagues have taken no formal decision in this sense.   They have, however, been in favour of administrative delays in the licensing and shipment of exports, more particularly of steel rails (and accessories) and sugar, provided always, as I understand it, that no publicityresulted such as would prejudice the possibility of an amicable solution ofthe oil dispute.4. On 12th July I reported to my colleagues the imminent departureon the 14th July of s, s. Bahristan carrying 2,900 tons of steel rails andsleepers, and of s. s. City of Norwich carrying 1,200 tons of sugar,   (Actual finalloadings were about 2,500 tons and 1,600 tons respectively.)   There had beenrecent Questions in the House of Commons about shipments of rails to persia and the reply had been given that it was not thought appropriate to discontinueexports and that the situation was being closely watched,5, My colleagues will recall that while I expressed the view thatthese exports should not be allowed to go to Persia, I pointed out that any formalembargo upon them at this stage might be thought to be inconsistent with the ruling of the Hague Court that no prejudicial action was to be taken by either side (although possibly we were no longer bound by that ruling in view of persia&apos;s repudiation of it), and that it might embarrass Mr. Harriman in his mission to the Persian Government.  As I understood the views of my colleaguesat the time, there was general agreement that no publicity ought to be given at that time which would suggest that we were instituting economic sanctions and it was suggested that instead of revoking the export licences, some subter-fuge or other should be adopted to prevent the two ships sailing.   Onesuggestion was that the Ministry of Transport should hold the ships for aboiler inspection:  another that the crews should be given a week&apos;s shoreleave.   At the conclusion of Cabinet I immediately communicated their decision in this sense to the Minister of Transport.-1-
6. In the late afternoon the Minister of Transport came to see me and explained that it would be quite impossible without publicity to detain theships by the use of any device of this kind and that the only courses open were either to revoke the export licences and unload the embargoed cargoes or to arrange with the ship owners that the cargoes would either be unloadedat Aden or Basra or would be brought back to this country.   At this time itwould have been difficult to consult with my colleagues, although no doubt I might have been able to make contact with them at Reuters1 Dinner.   In thecircumstances, however, it seemed to me that as the whole object of theexercise decided upon by the Cabinet was to avoid publicity, the better course was to allow cargoes to go, after ensuring with the ship owners that the boatscould, if necessary, be stopped later from unloading in Persia.   In the eventof any questions being raised about the matter, I should then have been ableto say that while technical reasons had made it inconvenient to stop thesecargoes leaving the United Kingdom, effective steps could still be taken toensure that they would not reach Persia.   This was the course which we adoptedin connection with a shipment of tyres for China.   It was a course which seemedto me fully to satisfy public opinion and I must confess I see no reason to suppose that the action taken in regard to these two cargoes would cause public anxiety, while on the other hand it is clear that it has avoided so far publicity which might have been embarrassing,7. Further ships are shortly due to leave.(a) s.s. Floristan loaded 260 tons of steel sleepers for Persiain Middlesbrough and is now in London loading cement forPersian Gulf ports and explosives for the War Office.(b) s. s. Avristan was due to start loading 1,500 tons of cube sugar inLondon today (18th July).(c) s. s. Kohistan is due to load 800 tons of sleepers in Newport tomorrow(19th July).(d) s. s. Gorjistan is due to load 800 tons of sleepers in Newport on 23rdJuly.8. As to (a) the boat is not due to leave until Friday and h. M. Customs can ensure that it does not leave before then.As to (b) the Ministry of Food will ensure that loading of the sugardoes not take place.In the case of (c) and (d) export licences are being withheld forthe time being.9. The following general action has been taken by the Departmentsconcerned.(i)  The Ministry of Transport are in touch with the shipping lines(Strick &amp; Ellerman) who for the time being are refusing to loadrails or sugar for Persia.   Their position is delicate.   They arealready in difficulties with the Persians at Abadan about non-delivery of certain machinery.(ii)  The Ministry of Food are in touch with Czarnikow&apos;s about preventing the loading of sugar.
(iii)  The Board of Trade are in touch with the Iron &amp; Steel Federation   0 Q 9about holding back deliveries of rails to the ships, ** &quot;(iv)  The Board of Trade are still delaying the issue of export licences for all goods.     In particular bulk steel export licences issued recently with Persia as an excluded destination havenot been recalled.   It has however been explained that licences for Persia will be considered on an individual basis.   For thetime being the issue of such licences will be delayed.   Wherethere are still extant bulk licences which do not exclude Persiathe Board of Trade are getting in touch with the firms concerned.10. This sum of delaying action  appeals to co-operation and confidential explanations must before long result in publicity.   The interestsapproached rightly expect protection against claims for breach of contract.In the case of the rails contract Persian observers are actually in the UnitedKingdom and may well ask questions which could not long be denied an answer.There are reports that the Teheran press has already announced a Unitedkingdom ban on shipments of steel and sugar.   The Persian Embassy are also as-dng embarrassing questions about our attitude towards supplies of other equipment.Matters for Decision11. It is for my colleagues to decide whether they now wish byformally withholding export licences and the like to impose economic sanctionson Persia.   The decision   of the Hague Court was that no prejudicial action was to be taken by either side.   I understand that we are resting ourselvesupon that decision in deciding for the present not to engage in any organisedevacuation of the Company&apos;s staffs.   Indeed, reliance on the decision of theHague Court may continue to provide great strength for our position.   on the other hand, we are not entitled to take advantage of the Hague decision inone respect and depart from it in another.   We must be quite clear that if weimpose economic sanctions we are departing from the decision of the Hague court, as, in my view, we are entitled to do in view of the fact that the PersianGovernment have already repudiated it.12. If my colleagues feel that no more cargoes of rails or sugar (orother scarce commodities) should be allowed to leave, whatever currentpublicity may be involved, the necessary overt action must be taken:   inparticular there must be an immediate revocation of export licences, and trading interests must be informed that no more licences will be issued for scarcecommodities for Persia.13. If it is felt that such publicity would prejudice the chances of an amicable solution of the oil dispute and more particularly of the HarrimanMission, the alternative would be to abandon the present delaying action (since it cannot continue without producing publicity) on the clear understandingthat the appropriate Departments should forthwith make preparations so that theymay be in a position to prevent the landing in Persia of any cargoes en routeshould that course become desirable.   (The sugar and rails will already bePersian property.) Presumably the most certain method of ensuring this wouldbe to requisition.   It seems to me that it will be a perfectly good answer to questions in the House, if the situation becomes irremediable, to say that at thetime of the departure of the vessels we had to avoid prejudicing the result of theHarriman Mission.14. I must emphasise that a clear decision has to be reached.   We can-not rely longer on administrative and other delays.   My own inclination would bethat in order to avoid publicity at this delicate juncture we should allow vessels tobe loaded and to depart on the understanding set out in paragraph 13.   But thematter is obviously one of foreign, not trading, policy.H.S.Board of Trade, S. W. 1. ,18TH JULY, 1951. o


</content>
</cab>
