<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 24-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jtms docrtment is the property of his britannic majest/s government.]GERMANY.CONFIDENTIAL.Bps Ikxc 16101/92/18]&amp;&amp;   3 203[august 6.]section 1.Report of the Committee of Experts appointed to Study the Frontier to he laid down between Germany and Poland in Upper Silesia as the Result of the Plebiscite,[with map.]IN order to fulfil the task entrusted to it, the committee first examined the question of the interpretation from the legal point of view of the provisions of the Treaty of Peace relating to the. frontier in Upper Silesia, and the principles which must in consequence be followed in tracing the frontier. The committee subsequently endeavoured to apply these principles in practice.I.From the point of view of the legal interpretation of the treaty, an examination of the preliminary discussions and of the various provisions of the treaty relating to Upper Silesia led to the following conclusions which were adopted unanimously by the committee: 1. In the absence of an unanimous vote of all the inhabitants, either for Poland or for Germany, the plebiscite cannot result in the allocation of the territory en bloc and therefore the voting in the territory as a whole need not be considered from the point of view of comparing the aggregate German vote with the aggregate Polish vote.2. The allocation of the different parts of the territory must be based primarily on the wishes of the inhabitants expressed by communes, geographical and economic considerations must be taken into account for making the necessary corrections in the results, where the results founded exclusively on the wishes of the inhabitants are in practice incapable of realisation in any particular locality.Geographical reasons exclude the creation of &quot; enclaves.&quot;Economic reasons call for an investigation, wherever necessary, of the question whether there are groups of population whose economic interests are inseparable (&quot; solidaires &quot;).3. No account need be taken of administrative divisions other than communes.II.In accordance with the above juridical principles, the committee agreed, in view of the plebiscite results (see map showing votes by communes), to discard a solution based on the allocation of the territory en bloc and on the consideration of the vote as a whole.The committee examined in turn the. lines prepared by the British and Italian commissioners and by the French commissioner in Upper Silesia, and also the lines proposed by the Italian Government. On both sides criticisms were made of the lines proposed by the commissioners in Silesia, and on both sides new lines were put forward which were intended to conform to the treaty (see the map annexed).The lines proposed, and the discussions to which their examination gave rise, showed that on some points the members of the committee held the same views, but on other points no agreement could be arrived at.The committee took note of the fact that there were two considerations common to the British and French lines : 1. That the result of the voting by communes showed that in the western part of Upper Silesia a region existed the population of which had declared definitely in favour of German sovereignty ; and[6743 /-1] 1 B
(2.) That in the eastern part a region existed which constitutes an economic whole.The committee agreed that in the south the frontier should start from the town of Oderberg and run northwards along the River Oder to the southern outskirts of Estibor.Beyond Estibor an examination of the annexed map shows that 1. The British line goes north-east to the south-west of Gleiwitz, and the French line follows very much the same direction ; in fact, on this part of the line the discussion showed no hopeless divergence of view.2. North of the mining area the two lines differ completely ; but the British delegation recognised that the French line follows more exactly the result of the voting, and bases the British line on the desire to compensate Poland for the allocation to Germany of certain Polish communes in another area. On this part also of the two lines the divergence of view does not seem irreconcilable.3. There remain the parts of the frontier in the area lying between the two portions described above.The British line is based upon the opinion that the northern part of the mining area constitutes an industrial triangle which is indivisible in itself, though separable from the southern part of the same area (this triangle is marked (D) on the annexed map), and that the vote therein gave a large majority in favour of Germany. For this reason the British delegation allocates the whole triangle to Germany, and this, in the opinion of the British delegation, entails attaching to Germany the region to the west and north-west of the triangle, so as to ensure to the triangle the necessary means of communication.The French line is based upon the opinion that the industrial area constitutes a whole and includes the regions of Pless and Eybnik, and that there is no justification for treating as a separate indivisible whole the area comprised in the northern zone, described by the British delegation as the industrial triangle.In these circumstances, while, on the one hand, allocating to Germany a somewhat large number of Polish communes surrounding isolated German communities so as to avoid &quot; enclaves,&quot; the French delegation explains that, on the other hand, it joins the German communities of the triangle to the Polish communities of the industrial area, including Pless and Rybnik, because the former are regarded as inseparable from the latter.The British and French lines are respectively supported by the following con-siderations : (A.)-British Argument.The indivisibility of the &quot; industrial triangle,&quot; as maintained by the majority of the technical experts, entails the allocation to Germany of this area, of which the majority of the inhabitants voted German, unless its allocation to Germany would necessitate the sacrifice of communes which voted Polish with majorities exceeding in the aggregate the German majorities in the triangle. As a matter of fact, the creation of a territorial connection between the triangle and the German communes to the west, which would be reasonably satisfactory from the point of view of adequate railway communication, would only entail the sacrifice of about 177 communes which voted Polish, with aggregate majorities of about 24,000. This figure is much smaller than the 60,000 majority which the Germans attained in the triangle.It is admitted that the allocation of these communes to Germany entails some sacrifice for Poland, and it is in order to meet this loss that, so far as possible, compensation is given to Poland in the north.The French line is criticised by the British and Italian delegations upon the ground that no satisfactory proof is forthcoming to demonstrate that the industrial triangle cannot be severed from the Pless and Rybnik mining area to the south, and that, if the principles of the treaty are to be adhered to, the area to be regarded as indivisible, and allocated without regard to the results of the voting in individual communes, must be kept as small as possible.It is also maintained that there is no justification for allocating to Germany the Polish communes in the central area lying to the west of the French line, except for the purpose of establishing a territorial connection with the German communes in the triangle. The French line allots these Polish communes to Germany, while the great German communes close by in the triangle are allotted to Poland.
Further, the adoption of the French line would almost exactly reverse the result of the voting. Whereas seven-elevenths of the population of the plebiscite area voted for Germany, seven-elevenths are allotted to Poland.In the total area allotted to Poland the Poles only just number more than half the population (52 per cent.), while in the area allotted to Germany the Germans number 77 per cent. Of the total number who voted for Poland in Upper Silesia, nearly 80 per cent, are included in the area allotted to her, whereas of the total number who voted for Germany only 50 pel cent, are included in the area allotted to her. The plebiscite provisions in the Treaty of Versailles contain no stipulation which justifies the adoption of one standard for the Poles and another for the Germans.(B.) - - French A rgument.A study of the frontier line in Upper Silesia must be dominated by the necessity of taking into account first of all the wishes of the inhabitants, but, in order to interpret these wishes correctly it is necessary to bear in mind the circumstances in which the plebiscite was decided on and its purpose.The authors of the Treaty of Versailles, when framing the provisions concerning Upper Silesia, undoubtedly had in mind its allocation to Poland. The &quot;Conditions of Peace&quot; handed to Germany on the 7th May, 1919, provided simply and purely for such transfer. When these clauses were modified by the institution of a plebiscite, the desire was to facilitate the acceptance by Germany of the allocation of all or part of Upper Silesia to Poland by confronting her with a wish formally expressed by the inhabitants. This view was inspired by the principle of the liberation of peoples which was affirmed by the Allied victory and which shaped the territorial clauses of the various treaties of peace. Throughout, the liberation of oppressed nationalities was kept in view. When the nationalities were intermingled, the frontiers were drawn with the primary purpose of withdrawing the oppressed from the oppressors, the oppressed nee repre-senting the indigenous elements of the people. This is particularly true of Upper Silesia. The Polish population there has preserved a national consciousness so intense that it has been able for many centuries to maintain itself against foreign domination. The wishes of this population must be doubly sacred.Nevertheless, the frontier cannot follow exactly the ethnographical map of the voting because of the intermingling of the races, and therefore, as laid down in the treaty, geographical and economic considerations must be brought into play as a second element, on the condition, however, that it must never be forgotten that the wishes of the.population hold far the foremost place in the elements to be taken into account. Applying these principles, the French delegation notes that an examination of the map showing the voting of the communes of Upper Silesia, as lard down in the treaty, indicates that in the west, in the area, adjacent to Germany, there is an almost compact mass of German communes, whereas the eastern part, adjacent to Poland, is occupied by a mass of Polish communes. The purpose has therefore been to lay down a line separating these two masses, so far as possible only leaving in German territory Polish communes which were isolated from the others by a band of German communes, and in the same way attaching to Germany various isolated German units, separated from the German bloc by Polish communes of small importance and in which the German minority is, in the aggregate, very strong.On the other hand, it has not seemed possible to separate from the Polish mass, which surrounds it on every side, the isolated German units of the industrial area. These isolated units cannot be attached to Germany without disorganising their economic life, for they are part and parcel of the industrial area of Upper Silesia. If one sets out to attach them to Germany one is obliged (1) to attach to Germany at the same time other areas whose life is linked up with some isolated German units, and, (2) in consequence, to attach to them still further Polish territories, in order to ensure communications between the isolated units and Germanv. One is led on in this way so to encroach on the Polish mass that one arrives at a solution such as that proposed by the British delegation, which only allocates to Poland 137,347 Polish voters out of 479,000, i.e., less than 80 per cent, of the Poles of Upper Silesia who by their votes indicated a wish to be attached to Poland. Furthermore, on the pretext of ensuring the life of an industrial area which is arbitrarily carved out, Poland is only left with areas equally arbitrarily carved out, and deprived of the necessary elements of their economic lifeThe French delegation considers that if economic considerations are brought in in order to correct the frontier line, one must not be limited to an examination of the -single case of the area called the V industrial triangle,&quot; the alleged indivisibility of which
is only based really on topographical relations (density of the population, tramways, electric power stations, &amp;c.) i.e., on human creations which can always be modified; moreover, it is purely arbitrary, as Colonel Percival defined the triangle as something different from that which is so defined by the British delegation.The industrial region of Upper Silesia must be considered as a whole. The industrial basin consists of the whole area in which the exploitation of the mineral wealth has caused the establishment and development of the industry and has imposed on the country an industrial character in substitution for an agricultural character. The industrial, basin extends both to the notth and to the south, well beyond the industrial triangle as artificially formulated, and is continually developing to the south.The isolated German units, as also the other places in the basin, extend their economic relations beyond the limits of the triangle. On the other hand, in the triangle itself, important centres have no interdependence. Thus, Gleiwitz and Kattowitz are not interdependent, but are each closely connected with areas outside the triangle (Gleiwitz with Peiskretscham and Laband, Kattemty with the Pless area). If, therefore, in accordance with the treaty, one must bring into account the geographical situation of the localities (and not an area arbitrarily declared to be indivisible), the situation must be examined in respect of each isolated unit as regards the whole industrial area.The French delegation, faced with the British theory of the indivisibility of the triangle, has not found it possible to examine the feasibility of detaching the isolated German communities from the Polish mass which surround them. It considers that, in the absence of a special study of the isolated German communities, the whole mining basin can only follow the fate of the Polish majority in which it is embedded.The French delegation has limited itself to laying down a line as much in accord as possible with the results indicated by communes in the ethnographic map. Anxious at the same time to reduce to the minimum the number of Germans comprised in the Polish zone, the delegation has examined, one by one, the isolated communities with German majorities outside the industrial area. To enable these isolated communities to be attached to Germany, to facilitate their life and their communications with areas which are really German, the French line allocates to Germany the Polish mass which makes a salient towards Oppeln, and this without concealing the risk run by uniting to Germany the Polish population whose patriotic ardour was shown in the course of the recent insurrection. The French delegation, on the other hand, has pushed its desire not to include within the Polish borders one more than the minimum number of German inhabitants, so as to respect the balance of votes in the plebiscite, so far as to leave in German territory the Lublinitz area which the British line gave to Poland, and which has an indubitable importance as regards railway connection between Upper Silesia and Posnania.One is in this way led up to a line giving Poland a territory in which the majority of the population is Polish, and will find the national aspirations satisfied (373,761 voting Polish, against 341,261 voting German). In the territory allocated to Germany 366,344 voting German remain German in accordance with their desires and despite the protests among them of a minority of 105,598, who voted Polish.This result, if regarded as a whole, leaves to Germany the majority of those who voted German (366,344 out of 707,605 , whereas the British proposal gives Poland less than a third of those who voted Polish (137,247 out of 479,35:;).To reach a solution giving Germany a larger proportion of those who voted German, it would be necessary to enter into a study of the isolated German communities and their relations with the surrounding Polish areas,&apos;a study which the views of the British delegation on the alleged indivisibility of the industrial triangle constituted by it rendered impossible in the committee.The technical experts, to whom certain questions concerning the indivisibility of the industrial triangle were referred, have suggested that, if for political reasons it became essential to.consider the division of the triangle, it would be necessary : 1. To fix the frontier so that, in each part of the basin so separated, the conditions necessary for its existence and development could be realised ; and2. To ensure, by creating some kind of technical organisation, the economic unity of the industrial basin for a period sufficient to allow the two- parties to become independent of each other, and to ensure that the establishment of a political frontier should not create difficulties which might summarily arrest or handicap the life of the industry.
To conclude, the work of the Expert Committee, while indicating clearly the respective points of view of the British, French and Italian delegations, lias indicated complete agreement on the legal principles to be followed in tracing the frontier, and on a certain number of points which are not without importance for the purpose of arriving at a solution, which the committee, though unable itself to achieve, hopes that it may have facilitated.August^ 1921.[6743 /-I]
UPPER SILESIAPLEBISCITE AREAScale I: 600,000

</content>
</cab>
