<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 106-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This document ia the property of His Britannio Liajesty^ Government ).CABINETSECRET. ---------COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRS.JURIES BILL, (Memorandum by the Home Secretary),Unless a Bill placing the preparation of jury lists upon a satisfactory footing is passed early next year, the position will be that-in July 1922, the whole of the obsolete and costly machinery for preparing jury lists which has been in abeyance during the War will revive and come into force.   The Juries Act, 1918, which dispensed with some of the ordinary procedure, will have expired,    Separate jury lists will have to be prepared and printed.   The cost of this in Bristol alone has been estimated at  4,000,   Each of the 10 Assize cities for the first time will have to bear the expense of preparing lists.   They are at present saved from this by the Emergency Act which is being continued for the present year but cannot be continued indefinitely from year to year.   The fact that the method which these cities are now using under the Emergency Act of simply marking the names of jurors on the electors&apos; list is working quite well affords a strong argument for the present Bill, which adopts the same method but assigns the duty of marking the names to the Assistant Overseers instead of leaving it to the Town ClerksThe Bill should certainly be passed early next Session in the interests of economy?    but it deals with a complicated subject not administered by - any one public department, and it will be a great advantage to have it introduced and published now so that the criticisms and suggestions of those concerned may be considered before the Bill is re-introduced next year.   I propose to introduce it now and shall be glad to have the concurrence of my colleagues in this course,,E ,S0LL12th August, 1921,
Juries Bill.MEMORANDUM.1. The main effect of this Bill is to abolish, in the interests of economy, the existing system under which separate jury lists are prepared and printed, and to enable the register of electors to be used as a basis for the formation of the &quot; jurors book &quot; from which the panels of jurymen are drawn.2. The question whether a saving of expense could not be effected by combining the jury lists with the register of electors was raised by a question in the House of Commons on the 22nd November 1920, and again in the present-Session (10th March 1921), and the Home Secretary on the latter occasion replied that lie hoped to introduce a Bill for the purpose at an early date. The present Bill gives effect to the Home Secretary&apos;? under-taking.3. It is not possible to state the total cost of the preparation of the jury lists in England and Wales, but it is anticipated from information which is available in the case of particular areas that a considerable economy will be effected by the adoption of the new plan.Thus, in the case of the Metropolitan borough of Wandsworth, while the cost of printing the present jury list is about 500/. per annum, it is estimated that the cost under the new system will not exceed 250 . in the year in which the change is made, and that in subsequent years it will not exceed the trilling sum of 15Z.The existing System.I. Counties. The present procedure, which depends on the Juries Act, 1825, and amending Acts of 1862 and 1870, is as follows: The clerk of the county council issues a precept to the overseers of the parishes within the county, requiring them to make out lists of all persons within their respective parishes who are qualified and liable to serve on juries.The overseers thereupon fill up the appropriate forms with names of the persons in their area liable to serve on156-4 A
juries, arranged in alphabetical order, specifying which of those persons are qualified as special jurors, and setting out in separate columns their addresses, occupations and qualifications.These lists are , then printed, and, after being signed by the overseers, are posted on the first three Sundays in September on the principal door of every church, chapel, or public place of religious worship within the area.&apos; -Special petty sessions are held in the last week of September for the purpose of revising the. lists. The overseers attend at the sessions with the lists, and the justices, acting either on evidence given before them or on their own knowledge, strike out the names of persons not qualified or not liable to serve, insert names which have been improperly omitted, and rectify any other errors or omissions. There is no appeal from the decision of the justices, and no person whose name is retained on the revised list can claim exemption from jury service except on the ground of illness.The lists thus revised are certified by the justices to be true and proper lists, and are then forwarded to the clerk of the county council, who is required to arrange the various parishes and townships in alphabetical order under the hundred in which they are situated, and the hundreds again in alphabetical order. The lists are subsequently made up by the clerk of the county council into a book known as the &quot; jurors book,&quot; which is delivered to the sheriff for use during the year beginning on the first of January next, and he, on the expiration of his term of office, delivers it to his successor.The costs incurred by the clerk of the county council in performing his duties in connexion with the preparation of the jury lists and the jurors book are borne by the county, as is also the small fee to which the clerk to the justices is entitled. The costs incurred by the overseers in connexion with the preparation and printing of the lists are defrayed out of the poor rate of the parish.5. Boroughs. Tor the purpose of the preparation of the jury lists municipal boroughs (other than boroughs. which are counties in themselves and for which separate commissions of assize are issued) are treated as part of the county in which they are situate.It has been sometimes contended by quarter sessions boroughs that the inhabitants of such a borough are exempt
from liability to serve on juries at the county assizes, but the Law Officers, on a case submitted to them in June last, advised that this contention is without foundation.The foregoing remarks do not apply to jurors for borough quarter sessions and for borough local courts for under s. 186 (1) of the Municipal Corporations Act, 1882, jurors for those courts are drawn from the burgess roll.6. In cities, boroughs, and towns which are counties of themselves the burgess roll, or a list prepared in some customary manner, lias hitherto served as the jurors list; recently, however, a question was raised as to the legality of this procedure, and on a case submitted to the Law Officers it was decided that the provisions of the Juries Act, 1825, applied to these counties corporate in the same Avay as to counties at large. The position was only realised late in 1920, when it was too late to prepare jury lists for the year 1921, and in consequence the Juries (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1920, was passed, making temporary provision for the preparation of jury lists in these places for 1921. It is proposed by a Bill now before Parliament to continue the provisions of this Act for another year.7. City of London. The Act of 1S25 does not apply to the City of London where the preparation of jury lists is carried out by the Secondary, the officer who summons juries.8. The existing system has been modified temporarily by s. 6 of the Juries Act, 1918, Avhicli gives power by Order in Council to modify, for the purpose of avoiding unnecessary expense and labour, the provisions of the Juries Acts, 1825 and 1862, as to the preparation and publication of jury lists. That Act, however, will, if the termination of the war is fixed for September 1st, cease to have effect on March 1st next year, and so could not apply to the preparation of jury lists for the year 1923.tThe Proposed System.9. The main proposals of the Bill are as follows : The existing procedure for making out jury lists is abolished, and in the future the jury lists will be com-bined with the register of electors.It must be observed that it is not proposed that the electors&apos; register as such should form the jurors book; only those of the electors who possess the necessary156 A 2
qualifications will be marked, and (except to the small extent mentioned in para. 17 below) the Bill does not in any way affect the qualifications now required for jurors and special jurors.The scheme of the Bill is that the registration officer, in making out the autumn register of electors, shall place a distinguishing mark against the names of the persons in the lists who are qualified and liable to serve as jurors and special jurors respectively, and, to enable him to perform his duties, he is empowered to require the overseers of any parish within his area to supply him with particulars with respect to any such persons; the Bill retains the power given to the overseers by the existing enactments of obtaining access to the information required for the discharge of their duties.The exact form of the mark to be inserted in the register is left to he prescribed by Order in Council. It is contemplated that it will consist merely of the letter &quot;V or the letters &quot;S.J.&quot; in ( ) inserted after the person&apos;s name, and the present practice of inserting a juror&apos;s qualification will be abandoned. To insert the qualifications would necessitate a new column in the register and thus involve very considerable additional expense.10. The new jury lists consisting of the marked registers will no longer be subject to examination by justices at petty sessions, but (subs. (4) of cl. 1) any person specified as a juror in the lists, will be able, within one month after they are published, to apply, to a court of summary jurisdiction for a declaration that he is entitled to have his name removed from the lists.11. The Bill preserves the position of counties, of cities and towns for which separate commissions of assize are issued as independent areas, but otherwise the jurors book for a county will include the inhabitants of all boroughs in the county area, so far as they are qualified and liable.12. The jurors book will be made up by the clerk of the county council from the marked registers covering the county area in substantially the same manner (mutatis mutandis) as that in which the jurors book is now made up from the jury lists.13. The expenses incurred by registration officers under the Bill are in general to be treated as expenses incurred in the performance of registration duties under the Representation of the People Act, 1918.   The effect
of this is that they will be borne as to one-half by the locality and as to the other half by the Exchequer. It is, however, considered that it&apos; is reasonable, seeing that under the existing system none of the corresponding expenses now fall on the Exchequer, that the expenses incurred in marking the first register, which will be considerable as compared with the marking of any new names added subsequently from year to year, should be left to be defrayed entirely by the locality.Any expenses incurred by overseers will continue to be paid out of the poor rate of the parish.11. Clause 2 reproduces the existing law contained in s. 12 of the Juries Act, 1870, under which persons included in the jurors book are liable to serve not-withstanding any disqualification or right to exemption, except on the ground of illness.lfi. Clause 3 (following the recommendation in para. 231 of the Report of the Departmental Committee on Jury Law and Practice, which reported in 1913, Cd. 6817) provides that, in case of a borough having a separate court of quarter sessions or a separate civil court, the jurors for those courts shall be drawn from the persons whose names are included in part of the jurors book relating to the borough, instead of from the burgess roll.16. The system now in force in the City of London is stated in the Report of the Departmental Committee (para. 97) to be satisfactory in every way, and it is therefore not proposed to alter it; clause 5 contains the necessary saving.17. Clause 5 also provides that the Rill is not to affect the qualification or liability of persons to serve as jurors, except to the extent that a person who is not registered as an elector will no longer be qualified or liable. The only substantial result of this will be to relieve from liability aliens domiciled in England or &quot;Wales for 10 years or upwards who are now qualified and liable for jury service under s. 8 of the Jurors Act, 1870, certain women who own but do not occupy some land in the county where they reside, and, so long as they are excluded from the franchise, conscientious objectors.It has been suggested that women under 30 will no longer be qualified for jury service; this, however, will not be the case, as women can be registered as local government electors under the age of 30.
Juries Bill.MEMORANDUM.CXXVI.   (4.)3rd August 1921.
Juries Bill.AllEANGEMENT OF CLAUSES.Cliinse.1.  Alteration of method of preparing jurors book.2. Persons included in jurors book liable to serve, notwithstanding disqualification or right to exemption.3.   Provisions as to juries in boroughs.4.   Interpretation.5.   Short title, saving, extent, and repeal. Schedule.i63-14
DRAM1OP A.bill to amend the law with respect to the preparation A.D. 1921. of Jurors Books, and otherwise to amend the Law relating to Jurors and Juries, in England and Wales.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with   the advice  and  consent  of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of 5 the same, as follows: l.--(l) After the commencement of this Act lists Alteration of the persons qualified and liable to serve as jurors of method shall cease to be prepared in accordance with the provi- ?f J^^jJJJJF sions of the Juries Act, 1825, as amended by any subse-        400 &quot; 10 quent enactment, and the jurors books shall be prepared   ^q0, in accordance with the following provisions of this section.(2) Subject to the provisions of this section, it shall be the duty of every registration officer within the15 meaning of the Representation of the People Act, 1918, 7 &amp; 8 Geo. 5. in making out in pursuance of that Act the electors Ci 64-lists for the autumn register for any year, to specify therein in the prescribed manner which of the persons included in the lists are qualified and liable to serve as20 jurors, and which of the persons so qualified and liable are qualified to serve as special jurors.(3) For the purpose of enabling registration officers to perform their duties under this section the overseers of every parish shall, if so required by the registration 25 officer of their area, furnish to him, in the prescribed63-14 A 2
A.D. 1921. manner, particulars with respect to the persons in their parish who are, on the date on which the qualifying&quot; period for registration in the autumn register ends, qualified and liable to serve as jurors or qualified to serve as special jurors. 5Por the purpose of their duties under this subsection overseers shall have all such powers of inspecting dupli-cates, tax assessments, and poor rates as are by section eleven of tlie Juries Act, 1825, given to them for their assistance in completing the jury lists, and any expenses 10 properly incurred by them under this subsection shall be paid and allowed to them out of the poor rate of the parish.If any overseer fails to comply with any of the requirements of this subsection he shall be liable on \fr summary conviction in respect of each offence to a fine not exceeding ten pounds.(4) If any person who is specified as a juror or as a special juror in the electors lists for the autumn register claims that by reason of some disqualification or ex- 20 emption he ought not to be so specified, he may at any time within one month next after the publication of the lists apply to a court of summary jurisdiction for a declaration that he ought not to be so specified.Rules may be made by the Lord Chancellor regulating 25 the manner in which applications are to be made under this subsection and providing for the notification to the proper authority of tlie decision of the court on any such application.t     (5) The clerk of the council of every county shall 30 in every year, as soon as may be after the latest date for the publication of the autumn register, obtain copies of the register for all such registration units as are corn-prised in whole or in part in the county, and shall, not later than the first day of December next following, cause 35 such parts of those registers as relate to any part of the area of the county to be formed in the prescribed manner into a single book, and that book shall, so far as relates to the persons specified therein as jurors, be the jurors book for the county for the year beginning the first clay 40 of January next.The clerk of the county council shall deliver the jurors book, as soon as may be after it has been prepared, to the sheriff of the county, and every sheriff on quitting
office shall deliver the jurors book to the succeeding a.D. 1921. sheriff.Every registration officer shall, on demand, supply to the clerk of the county council, free of cost, such 5 number of copies of the autumn register as the clerk may reasonably require for the purposes of this Act.(6) Any expenses properly incurred by a registration officer in the performance of his duties under this Act shall, subject as hereinafter provided, be deemed to be 10 expenses incurred by him in the performance of his duties under the representation of the People Act, 1918, in relation to registration:Provided that every registration officer shall certify the amount by which the expenses incurred by him in15 connection with the preparation of the autumn register for the year in which this Act comes into operation have been increased by reason of the provisions of this Act, and for the purpose of computing the amount which under subsection (4) of section fifteen of the Representa-20 tion of the People Act, 1918 (which provides for the payment out of moneys provided by Parliament of one half of the amount paid by the council of a county or borough, in respect of registration expenses), is to be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament, the amount paid25 by any council shall be decreased by the amount so certified.If any question arises as to the correctness of any certificate given under the foregoing provision by a registration officer, that question shall be referred to the 80 Secretary of State, and the decision of the Secretary of State in the matter shall be final and conclusive.(7) Provision may be made by Order in Council under section thirteen of the llepresentation of the ,   People Act, 1918-35 (a) for enabling persons qualified and liable to serve as jurors or qualified to serve as special jurors to be specified as such in the autumn register for the year in which this Act comes into operation without having been previously inserted in the10 electors lists, and for making so far as relates tothe operation of this Act in that year any consequential modifications in the provisions thereof:63 ,    A 3
Persons included in jurors book liable to serve, not-withstanding disqualifica-tion or right to exemptionA.D. 1921.        (b) for enabling persons whose names are included as new voters in the electors lists for the spring register in any year and who are qualified and liable-to serve as jurors or qualified to serve as special jurors to be specified as such pro- 5 visionally in those lists and in that register:(c) for making such adaptations in any enactments as are necessary for giving full effect to this Act :(d) otherwise for carrying this Act into effect. 102. (l) Every person whose name is included in the jurors book as a juror or special juror shall be liable to serve as such, notwithstanding that he was entitled by reason of some disqualification or exemption to claim that he ought not to be specified in the electors list as a juror 15 or special juror :Provided that nothing in the foregoing provision shall affect the right of any person to be excused from attendance on a jury on the ground of illness or, if a woman, for medical reasons. 20(2) The notice to be published by the registration officer under paragraph 6 of the First Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, 1918, (which prescribes the duties of the registration officer in the preparation of electors lists), shall, in the case of the autumn 25 register, include a notice to the effect that the names of persons specified in the electors lists as jurors or special jurors will be included as such in the jurors book, but that any person who is so specified may, if he is aggrieved by being so specified, apply at any time within one month 80 next after the publication of the lists to a court of sum-mary jurisdiction for a declaration that he ought not to be so specified, and that every person whose name is included in the jurors book as a juror will be liable to serve as such, notwithstanding that he might have claimed 35 disqualification or exemption.Provisions 3. (1) In the case of any borough having a separateas to juries court of quarter session or a borough civil court the m boroughs. persong whose names are included in so much of thejurors book for the area comprising the borough as 40 relates to the area of the borough shall be qualified and liable to serve on grand juries in the borough and on juries for the trial of issues joined in either of those courts.
(2) The clerk of the council of a county shall, on A.1). 1921. demand, supply free of cost to the persons charged with the return of jurors in a court of quarter sessions or civil court in any borough in tlie county, a copy of so much 5 of the jurors book for the county as relates to the area of the borough.4. In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires  Interpreta-The expression &quot; prescribed &quot; means prescribed by tl0n* Order in Council under this Act: 10 The expression &quot; county &quot; includes a county of acity and a county of a town for which a separate commission of assize is issued: The expression &quot; clerk of the county council&quot; means in the case of such a city or town as 15 aforesaid the town clerk :The expression &quot; sheriff&quot; includes any personcharged with the return of jurors : The expression &quot; overseers &quot; means, in relation to a metropolitan borough, the town clerk, and in 20 relation to a parish to which the Vestries Act, 13 &amp; U Viet.1850, applies, the vestry clerk. c-5. (1) This Act may be cited as the Juries Act, Short title,1921. saving,extent, and(2) Nothing in this Act shall alter or affect  repeal.2o (a) the preparation of jury lists or the jurorsbook in the City of London; Or(&amp;) the qualification or liability of any person to be summoned to serve and to serve as a juror or special juror on any jury in the 30 High Court or at assizes, or in any county court, except that a person whose name is not included in the register of electors shall not be qualified or liable so to serve.(3) This Act shall not apply to Scotland or Ireland.35 (4) The enactments mentioned in the Schedule to this Act shall be repealed to the extent specified in the third column of that Schedule.
SCHEDULE.Enactments Repealed.Session and Chapter.    i	Short Title.	Extent of Repeal.6Goo.4.c. 0	The Juries Act, 1825.	Sections five, six. eight, nine, ten, 5 twelve, and forty-live ; in section forty-six the /words from  &quot;shall refuse&quot; where they first occur to &quot; application or,&quot; and the words &quot; certified to him by any justice of JO the peace as aforesaid &quot; ; in section fifty the words from the beginning to &quot; heretofore accustomed &quot; ; the Schedule.25 &amp; 26 Viet, c. 107.	The Juries Act, 1862.	Sections four, five, six, eight, nine, and 15 ten, and the Schedule.33 &amp; 34 Viet, c. 77.	The Juries Act, 1870.	Sections eleven to fourteen.45 &amp; 46 Viet, c. 50.	The Municipal Corporati o n s Act, 1882.	Subsection (1) of section.one hundred and eighty-six.                           20

Juries^DEAFTOF ABILLTo amend the law with respect to the preparation of Jurors Boots, and otherwise to amend the Law relating to Jurors and Juries, in England and Wales.XLVII.   (14.)3rd August 1923.63- 14

</content>
</cab>
