<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 265-269</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] SECRET.Draft Note to Russian Soviet Government.cSys _-  r- (Circix 1 ated by Secretary of state for IndIa ) .i-iii-lh&quot;&apos;the Trade Agreement concluded with the Russian Soviet Government on 16th March that Government undertook to &quot;refrain from any attempt by military or &quot; diplomatic or any other form of action or propaganda to encourage any of the &quot; peoples of Asia in any form of hostile action against British interests or the British &quot; Empire, especially in India and in the independent State of Afghanistan.&quot; It is with great regret that His Majesty&apos;s Government (hid themselves obliged to inform the Russian Soviet Government that this undertaking has not been observed.From the acts and sj)eeches of various responsible officials of the Soviet Government, no less than by the activities being displayed by its agents in various directions, His Majesty&apos;s Government are forced to the conclusion that the overthrow Of British rule in India still constitutes the main object of the Soviet Government^ Eastern policy in spite of the solemn pledges contained in the preamble to the Trade Agreement. Thus M. Lenin, speaking at the Congress of the Third International, of which he is a member, on 28th June 1921, used the following words : &quot; We must use this breathing space in order carefully to prepare the revolution: in capitalist States . . . ; A very important factor for the development of the world revolution is the awakening of millions of workers in the colonies and dependencies. This fact presents us with a most important task, which consists in helping these enormous masses of backward individuals on the road to world revolution.&quot;Identical views have been expressed by M. Stalin, at once Minister for Nationalities in the Soviet Government and President of the Eastern Secretariat of the Third International, in making his report to the Central Committee of the Third International on 1st June 1921, when he stated that &quot; the general guiding purpose of &quot; the Eastern Secretariats policy lies in exerting pressure on the Powers of Western &quot; Europe through their colonies. .... The problems of the West would, be&quot; &quot; incomparably easier of solution- if the external power of France and England could &quot; be undermined.&quot;In reviewing the work oC the Eastern Secretariat during the period 1st February 1921 to 1st June 1921, M. Stalin states that &quot; a treaty has been concluded guaranteeing &quot;friendly relations between the Soviet Government and Afghanistan, through which &quot; the Communist International maintains direct contact with the South and British &quot; India, propaganda in which area is the primary objective of the Eastern Secretariat,&quot; and that &quot; continuous though unofficial relations have been maintained with several &quot; native leaders in the Indian Provinces.&quot;Finally, M. Stalin claims that the Eastern Secretariat has established a united front, with Turkestan as its base, stretching from Southern India and embracing the whole Moslem world.M. Eliava, in making his report to the Central Committee of the Communist International on 5th June 1921, stated that:  &quot; The Soviet Government had been placed under the necessity of cloaking the &quot;aims of the Communist International in a nationalist guise. The policy &quot; pursued by us has already proved its expediency, and it is sufficient to &quot; point out that, in combating British imperialism, we succeeded with &quot; difficulty in 1919 in defending Turkestan from British influence, whereas &quot; in 1921 we are already taking the offensive against the&apos; foundations of &quot; capital in India itself.&quot;M. Nuorteva, in his report to the Congress of the Third International on 26th June 1921, covering the period 1st February 3921 to 1st June 1921, draws attention to the 11 gigantic work accomplished by the Eastern Secretariat&quot; during the four months under review and the success which he claims has attended it, and states that the whole attention of the Secretariat was directed to elaborating ;i system for supplying the Eastern organisations with ail they require.From further information at the disposal of His Majesty&apos;s Government it is known that it is the intention of the Secretariat of the Third International to establish 4522      100   S.21 A
propaganda bases in Egypt in order to support the Egyptian Nationalist movement in its antagonism to Great Britain.His Majesty&apos;s Government are fully aware of the attempts being made, both by officials of the Soviet Government and members of the Third International, to give effect to the policy described above.The fact that these activities are being carried out to a large extent by the Third International and its agents cannot, in the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Government, absolve the Soviet Government of responsibility. His Majesty&apos;s Government have ample proof of the continued close connection between the Soviet Government and the Third International. 1   r   - : .    .     . .-.Apart from the fact that the Third International can obviously only be tolerated on Russian soil with the direct approval and encouragement of the Soviet Government, many prominent members and officials of the Soviet Government are also members of the Third International, such as M. Zinoviev, M. Radek and M. Bukhaiin, and others either take a prominent part in the activities of the latter or else, though not actually holding an official position under the Third International, yet attend its deliberations and give their moral support to its activities. For example, -M. Lenin&apos;s speech quoted above can only be described as a direct incitement to the Third International to persevere in its anti-British propaganda.Reference has already been made to M. Stalin&apos;s mention of the Russo-Afghan treaty as an instrument to guarantee friendly relations with a State whose territory is an important channel by which &quot; the Communist International maintains direct contact with &quot; India. Article X. of this treaty (which is a public document and has been officially communicated to His Majesty&apos;s Government by M. Krassin) and the supplementary clause amplifying this Article show how these friendly relations, so necessary to the Communist International for the execution of its policy, are guaranteed, namely, by the annual payment of a free subsidy of 1,000,000 roubles in gold or silver coin or bullion; by the construction of a telegraph line from Kushk through Herat and Kandahar to Kabul, and hy the readiness of the Russian Republic to place at the disposal of the Afghan .Government &quot;technical and other specialists.&quot; And in fact cash no doubt part of the first instalment of the annual subsidy-is known to have arrived in the capital of Afghanistan.Further, this treaty contains two Articles Nos. IV. and V.-providing for the establishment of Russian Consulates at selected places in Afghanistan, and specifically at Herat, Maimana, Mazar-i-Sharif, Kandahar and Ghazni; to the question .of these establishments special attention was drawn in Sir R. Horne&apos;s note of 16th March, yet His Majesty&apos;s Government notice that on 5th June last a message was sent from M. Chicherin to M. Suritz in Kabul, instructing the latter that the clause in the Russo-Afghan treaty &quot; regarding opening up of Consulates on the Indian frontier cannot be given up by us owing to economic reasons &quot; ; and they are also aware that no one knows better than the Russian Commissary for Foreign Affairs that there are no economic reasons 10 justify the opening of Russian Consulates in these districts. Apart from the inference to be legitimately drawn from M. Stalin&apos;s expression of view, already quoted, of the importance of the Russo-Afghan Treaty, His Majesty&apos;s Government possesss indisputable evidence in official messages exchanged between the Soviet Government in Moscow and the Russian Envoy in Kabul, that the former throughout have regarded these Consulates as prospective centres of propaganda, and that their utility in this respect is the reason - for which they have continuously pressed for the Afghan Governments consent to their establishment. In spite of the protest made by Sir.R. Home in March, M. Suritz was able to inform the Afghan Foreign Minister in May that the incumbents designated for these Consulates with full personnel were accompanying M. Rosenberg, who shortly after arrived in Kabul.The above are not the only activities of the Soviet Government and its agents in Afghanistan to which His Majesty&apos;s Government must take exception. His Majest,y&apos;s Government hold a mass of indisputable evidence in the shape of official messages -exchanged between the Moscow Government and the Russian Envoy in Kabul, that Jamal Fasha (to whose activities also specific objection was raised in Sir R. liorne&apos;s Note of 16th March) was despatched to Afghanistan by the Soviet Government and that the lines of policy he is following were dictated to him from Moscow and that its execution is supervised by the Russian Legation in Kabul.On 6th August 1920 a message was transmitted to M. Suritz by M. Karakhan that he was sending to Kabul Jamal Pasha and with him Kazim Beg and Barkatullah. (a notorious Indian revolutionary).
On 2nd September 1920 a message was forwarded to M Stiritz from Tashkend : &quot; We pin much faith on Jamal, who is acting in accordance with an agreement &quot; concluded in Moscow between Soviet and Turkish revolutionary Governments.&quot;On 4th March of this year M. Suritz reported to the Moscow Foreign Office : &quot;Jamal wishes chicherin to be informed that he is surprised at the silence of &quot; Moscow . . . All work will be carried out under the supervision of Russian &quot; Legation. If Moscow&apos;s authority is not given in a fortnights time Jamal will be &quot; obliged to give up his task   ...&quot;On .18th January M. Suritz complained to Moscow that certain funds which he had been expecting had not been despatched. &quot; I was informed that half a million &quot; was being sent, and on strength, of this have given approval to several of Jamafs &quot; projects which are of utmost importance to our cause.&quot;The nature of these &quot; projects &quot; is indicated by this passage in M.&apos; Suritz&apos;s message of 3rd February to the Commissar at Taslikend and to Moscow Foreign Office :&apos; &quot; Work among the tribes. Jamal appointed id direct this work and I have &quot; given him Rs. 1,50,000. Waziristan representative summoned to Kabul to confer &quot; with Jamal. We have (been) asked despatch immediately arms and amniimitidir&apos; &quot; for tribesmen. These should be of English pattern if possible, and we should &quot; assign Rs. 10,00,000 for this purpose. Expenditure will be carried out directly by &quot; him with our co-operation.&quot;The identity of the Waziristan representative &quot; is well known to British officers on the North-West Frontier of India, as are those of his principal assistants. Their actions are closely followed, and the Indian Government is informed of their receipt from time to time of supplies of money, arms, and ammunition for distribution to the tribes now in arms against the British forces. These activities are continuing with unabated energy to the present time.&quot;Of.Jamars efforts under the inspiration and with the support of Moscow to -form  a  corps   d? elite   in   Afghanistan,   of   the   cost   of   maintenance   of  his Mission, including  the  Turkish  officers  assisting  him, of allowances from  the, Soviet Government to his family, of all these and  other points  His&apos; Majesty&apos;s Government have equally indisputable evidence.It is obvious from the terms of his letter of credentials to the Amir of Afghanistan that Jamal&apos;s selection for the work he has undertaken was due largely to the appeal which his nationality and religion might be expected to make to the sympathies-of the people of Afghanistan and the fanaticism of the frontier tribesmen;; it was, in: fact, but an incident in what M. Eliava describes as the gradual approach of the Soviet Government and Third Internationa] to their fundamental object, the creation&apos; of a powerful united Moslem movement which would deal the final blow against the power of capital and destroy the colonial system upon which the power of Western European capital rests. That the direction of this movement, of -which Jamal is but the instrument, lies with the Soviet Government is clearly shown by the fact that when Bedri Bey and Aii Fuad Pasha make suggestions or give directions to Jamal as to the policy to be pursued by him, they are careful to say, the former&apos;: &quot;This idea of mine is the result of conversations with Chicherin, Karakhan, and, especially, Stalin,&quot; and the latter, as recently as 23rd June : &quot; I have spoken&apos; to the : Soviet and the Third International,&quot; before giving his directions.His Majesty&apos;s Government also have evidence of continued intrigue with- Indian revolutionaries in Europe, of which complaint was made in Sir R. Horne&apos;s Note. After lengthy negotiations between the Soviet Government and Ghattopadhyaya, some- of these individuals, who were then taking refuge in Berlin and other places in Europe, were invited by the Soviet Government to attend a meeting in Moscow on 25th May 1921 in order to discuss the best means of provoking a revolution in India. They were supplied with funds through M. Kopp, the; official representative of the Soviet Government in Berlin, who also supplied them with vises to their passports.Ghattopadhyaya has been assisted financially by the Soviet Government to&quot; the extent of 15,000 Swedish kronen, whilst in addition every member of the Indian Revolutionary Society who attended the Moscow meeting had all his exjyenses paid and received additional monetary assistance in amounts varying from 5,000 to 15,000 marks.His Majesty^-Government are likewise aware that the Soviet Mission in Berlin have afforded facilities for communication between members of the Indian Reyolu-tionary Society in Berlin, which, as is well known to the Soviet Government, is plotting against British rule in India, and their associates iu Moscow, thus directly assisting anti-British intrigue.4522 a 2
For some considerable time the Soviet Government has been trying, to persuade a , well-known Indian anarchist,. Dr. llaliz, who has been studying the manufacture of , bombs, in Vienna, to proceed to Afghanistan to supervise a bomb depot on the borders of India in order to facilitate their importation into India. Dr. Hatiz has now, with tho assistance of the Soviet Government, undertaken the task of manufacturing smokeless powder in Kabul, and has received from the Soviet Government the sum of 10,000 kronen lor expenses connected with his wife and children.In Sir..Pi. 1-Iorne&apos;s note the attention of M. Krassin was invited to the obnoxious work of the Tashkend, propaganda, school, the -temporary? &quot;iba-se- for&apos; Indian work,&quot; in -which emissaries were trained before despatch to India, Instructions issued, as is known to His Majesty&apos;s Government, in March from Moscow for the intensification of Eastern propaganda, particularly in Turkestan and on tho Indian frontier, have not been cancelled ; a special allocation of 2,000,000 gold roubles was sanctioned for the purpose, and Tashkend and, if possible, Kabul were selected as the bases for the work. His Majesty&apos;s Government are aware that the base at Tashkend has&apos; not yet been transferred, as was intended, to Kabul ; they are no less well aware that the anti-British endeavour of which the Tashkend base was the &quot;centre,&quot; has not ceased. Kativesof India returning through Afghanistan who have within the last two months-been intercepted on the Indian frontier have made no secret of the fact that they had been sent to Tashkend by Soviet Government officials for training in propaganda-methods and had been provided with money and other facilities to make their way to. India.As regards Persia, His Majesty&apos;s Government have the strongest reasons for believing that the policy of the Soviet Government is directed principally against British interests ; and so little has it solely in view the interests of the Persian peoples that the Soviet Commissar at Tashkend, reviewing the general situation and informing M. Suritz of the signature of the Russo-Persian treaty, stated that the Persian agreement was looked upon as a scrap of paper.M. Nuorteva made the following, statement on 26th June 1921 : &quot;In the near &quot;future, with the inevitable changes in the life of Persia, we shall have at our &quot; disrjosition in the immediate neighbourhood of India a base amply sufficient for the &quot; completion of this task.&quot;M. Karakhan, after describing the part that Eastern nations would take in a general upheaval, recently stated that &quot; with regard to Persia the latest information &quot;tended to show that as a result of the combined efforts of the representatives of , &quot; Soviet Russia she would adopt a line of conduct calculated to accord to&apos; the general &quot;political situation.&quot;M. Rothstein, whose actions, in contravention of the undertakings made by the Soviet Government in the trade agreement, have called forth a special report from His Majesty&apos;s Minister in Tehian, would appear to be acting in accord with the views expressed above. He is importing large sums of money, much of which he is known to spend on propaganda ; he has a staff of nearly a hundred persons, many&apos; of whom are actively engaged in propaganda, and he and his staff by personal visits and other means have sought to influence members of the Mejliss and other Persians of good standing against His Majesty&apos;s Government. He is also known to subsidise certain Persian newspapers in order to carry on a press campaign against Great Britain. -It is clearly recognised that M. Rothstein is doing everything possible to conceal his real activities, and seeks to place the responsibility of autifBritish action and the formation of revolutionary bodies on to third parties ; as, for instance, when a protest was made to him by the Persian Government on 4th July 1921, on the occupation of liesht, he stated that this was carried out by the Azerbaijan Soviet Government, whose activities the Moscow Government had difficulty in controlling, whereas His Majesty&apos;s Government are fully aware that the Soviet Government is in a position to control the policy of the Azerbaijan Government should it so desire.That the Soviet Government itself is cognisant of M. Rothstein&apos;s activities admits of no doubt, and he was officially informed on 24th June last that M. Chicherin had decided to have a revolutionary committee in Tehran, though the whole committee was not yet ready for despatch.Finally, not content with his own activities, M. Rothstein seeks the co-operation of the newly appointed Soviet representative at Kabul, with whom he stated he would work in harmony, at the same time asking him to urge the Afghan Government to replace their present representative in Tehran by an energetic man. who would unite with Persia against the common enemy, viz., Great Britain.
His Majesty&apos;s Government are fully aware of the real motives underlying the policy of the Soviet Government in supporting the Turkish-Nationalists and affording-them considerable assistance in money and arms of every description. The Soviet Government have used every persuasion in order to prevent the Angora Government arriving at a peaceful solution with the Entente Powers, and in order to exert still stronger pressure have assembled considerable forces on the borders of Anatolia and have suggested to ,the Angora Government that these forces should be sent into Anatolia for their active support.The reason for this action is clearly apparent; Turkey is regarded in M. Stalin&apos;swords as &quot;the teitadei1 of the Mohammedan &quot;world representing the nibst real threat to the power of Europe in general and the Entente in particular.&quot; Whilst M. Karakhai; in his recent report upon &quot;The situation in the Near East&quot; states that &quot; Angora, with its branches in Samarkand in the East&apos; and Cairo in the&apos;&quot; West is the spiritual and administrative centre of the united front of oppressed &quot; natives spreading from the Ganges in the East to the Nile in the West. The revo-&quot; revolutionary enthusiasm of the Moslem population of this continent inspired by Angora &quot;is disciplined to such an extent that no important event can take place without &quot; the sanction and knowledge of the Angora centre, which in its turn completely&quot;&quot; co-ordinates and regulates its instructions in accordance with our proposals and &quot; desires.&quot; Similarly, M. Eliava in his report quoted previously, says : &quot; The Angora Government, for example, can serve as a unifying force. The extension of its &quot; influence to Afghanistan and the Mohammedan tribes of India is now essential, for &quot; without that the separate races will never be in a position independently to raise &quot; the standard of open struggle against their oppressors.&quot;In Sir Robert Home s - note His Majesty&apos;s Government signalised a number of the activities of the Soviet Government upon the cessation of which they must insist as an essential corollary of the conclusion of any agreement between the two Governments.. From the examples that have been adduced above, it is clear that these activities have in no way ceased, and there is a particular reason why His Majesty&apos;s Government should choose the present moment to call attention to the fact and to give the Soviet Government another opportunity of fulfilling their solemn undertaking.   It has been made clear that these activities involve the expenditure of large sums of Russian money on anti-British propaganda in the East in particular, mention has been made of the annual subsidy offered to the Afghan Government.   His Majesty&apos;s Government believe that the Soviet Government will agree with them that there is a double impropriety in the continuance of such expenditure at a time when Russia is pleading before the civilised world, in forma pauperis, for the relief of 35,000,000 of her starving people.    They therefore formally call upon  the  Soviet Government  to cancel the clauses in the Russo-Afghan treaty which provide for the rendering of monetary assistance to the Afghans, and to withdraw their promise of aeroplanes and munitions.   His Majesty&apos;s Government, for their part, declare that they are animated by no feelings of hostility towards the Soviet Government as such.   But they are obliged to take all legitimate measures to defend themselves against the proceedings of a Government which by the mouth of its leading representatives and agents has avowed that the primary object of its eastern policy is the overthrow of British rule.

</content>
</cab>
