<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 453-456</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JThi jDooiiment is the Property of. His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1921.SECEET.c p.-3263.cabinet.WEEKLY SURVEY OF THE STATE OF  IRELAND.Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland.I SUBMIT for the consideration of the Cabinet my survey for the week ended the 22nd instant.General State of the Country.Observance of Truce Conditions.There has been no change in the general state of the country since my last report. The truce arrangements continue to work without violence, but I know that Sinn Fein Volunteers are openly drilling in many parts of the country, and that there has been an increase in the activity of Sinn Fein Courts. Representations in regard to both these matters have been made to the Chief Sinn Fein Liaison Officer, who declines to accept the view that a violation of the terms of the truce is involved in either case. There is undoubtedly some force in his contention that by collecting their men for the purpose of drilling the local Sinn Fein leaders are able to keep them under supervision and proper control.A matter of more practical importance is the alleged requisitioning of money for the maintenance of the Irish Republican Army. Activities of this kind undoubtedly constitute a very serious violation of the truce, but the Sinn Fein Liaison Officer has stated explicitly that if such requisitions have been made they are quite unauthorised, and he has promised that the matter will be taken up immediately by the heads of the organisation.Disturbances in Belfast.The dangerous state of party feeling in Belfast is evidenced by a number of sporadic acts of violence committed without apparent provocation and having no assignable motive other than sectarian animosity. a serious outrage of this character was perpetrated on the night of Sunday, the 21st instant, when a bomb was thrown in Tyrone. Street (a Catholic quarter), damaging 9 houses and injuring 6 persons, one of whom, a girl of 20, was removed to hospital in a dangerous condition. On the following night an attack was made with bombs and rifle and revolver fire upon the Catholic quarter of North Queen Street, and considerable damage to property was committed. The disturbance was quelled by the Police about 11-30 p.m., and no further outbreak has since occurred.Trials of Civilians by Court-Martial.Twenty-seven trials of civilians by court-martial were concluded during the week, resulting in 16 convictions and 11 acquittals. The following is an analysis of the sentences imposed :  12 sentences of penal servitude (3 years to 15 years). . 2 sentences of imprisonment with hard labour (1 year). 2 -fines (51.)Total   16Eight of the convictions were for the possession of arms and ammunition and severe sentences of penal servitude were imposed (15 years in 2 cases, 10 years in 3 cases, 5 years in 2 cases, and 3 years in 1 case). Sentence of 5 years&apos; penal servitude was imposed in 2 cases for offences under the Whiteboy Act, and sentence of 3 years&apos; penal servitude in 1 case for the possession of documents relating to the[6857]
20th instant: Total orders made           ...          ...          ... ...      4,245Orders cancelled for reasons other than release 152Releases ordered ...         ...          ...          ... 412&apos;   -        564Number of persons now interned    ... ... ...      3,681The number of appeals awaiting hearing is 22.In consequence of the escape from an internment camp of Mr. James Staines, the brother of the well-known Sinn Fein leader, Mr. Michael Staines, the Commander-in-chief has issued an order forbidding the further grant of parole to internees unless Mr. Staines surrenders himself for reinternment.State of the Police Forces. The following figures show the present position of the Irish Police Forces : Royal Irish Constabulary.Regular Force.Strength on the 14th August, 1921 ... ... ...     14,170Deaths during week        ... ... .... 1Retirements        ...         ... ... ... 5Resignations       ...         ... ... ... 21Dismissals or discharges   ... ... . - - - 14Total wastage ... 41Recruits             ...         ... ... ... NilNet decrease       ...         ... ... ... 41          41Strength on the 21st August, 1921 ... ... ...     14,129Auxiliary Division.Strength on the 14th August, 1921 ... ... ...      1,485Resignations       ...          ... ... ... 6     ,, -Discharged medically unfit ... ... 1Dismissal           ...         ... .... .... 1Total wastage &apos; ... 8Reinstatement        ...    .... ... ... net decrease -     ...         ... 7 7Strength on the 21st August, 1921 ... ... ....      1,478Dublin&apos;Metropolitan Police.Strength on the 13th August, 1921        ... ... ... 1,124Wastage            ...         ...         ... ... NilRecruits             ...         ...         ... ... 4Net increase   ....         ...         ...     .    ... 4 4Strength on the 20th August, 1921        ... ... ... 1,128Irish Republican Army. The acquittals included the case of a Head Constable of the Royal Irish Constabulary who was charged with manslaughter, and the case of a Constable charged with assault. Another Constable charged with assault was convicted and sentenced to a fine of 51. or 2 months&apos; imprisonment in lieu, but con-firmation of the sentence was withheld by the Confirming Officer.Internment Orders.The following statement shows the position as regards internments up to the
Present Political Situation in Ireland.According to official Sinn Fein announcements, the terms of Mr. de Valera&apos;s next reply to the Prime Minister have now been considered by Dail Eireann in secret session, and the reply is expected to be delivered in London this week. The secret of its contents has been well kept from the public, and the Irish press has indulged in little speculation on the subject. As to one thing, however, there appears to be no room for doubt, and that is the almost universal desire on the part of the people of Southern Ireland for an immediate peace. Reports from all sources indicate that the public confidence that negotiations must end in a settlement is as strong as ever, and despite the tone of Mr. de Valera&apos;s recent speeches, the possibility that the Sinn Fein leaders will take any action intended or calculated to bring about a retfurn of the conditions which prevailed before the truce appears nowhere to be seriously contemplated by the public.H. G.Irish Ofjice, S.W. 1, August 24. 1921.
Statement showing Total Number of Serious Outrages from January 1, 1919, to july 16, 1921.Weekly Totals to Week ended July 23, 1921, and Totals at that date.		Week ended 					Nature of Outrage.	Totals from Jan. 1, 1919, to July 16,1921.	July 23,1921.	July 30, 1921.	Aug. 6,1921.	Aug. 13,1921.	Aug. 20,1921.	Totals to Aug. 20, 1921. %Courthouses destroyed     ..	88			-			88E.I.O. vacated barracks destroyed   ...	522						522B.I.C. vacated barracks damaged   ..          ..	121						121B.I.C. occupied barracks destroyed	25						25E.I.O. occupied barracks damaged	267						267Balds on mails    . j	2,567			...			2,567Baids on coastguard stations and lighthouses..	97						97Baids for arms   ..	3,220						3,220Baids on offices of rate collectors and Petty Sessions clerks..	122						122Policemen killed	405						405*Policemen wounded	682				1		683fPolicemen fired at, &amp;c.     ..	Not recorded						* *Soldiers killed	150						150Soldiers wounded	345						345Soldiers fired at, &amp;c.	Not recorded						Civilians killed ..          ..          ..	196						196Civilians wounded           ..	185						,    185Totals     ..         ..     *   ..	8,992				1		8,993Arrests for outrages and political offences							: - - f, \* This figure includes six Special Constables, t This figure includes ten Special Constables.1 These figures do not include casualties in Ulster riots during period June-September, 1920;. twenty civilian deaths occurred in Londonderry riots and sixty-two in Belfast riots during that period.JJ.B._The above particulars do not include outrages of a kind which are not now being committed,eg 119 raids on revenue offices which occurred during months of April and May, 1920, and resulted in the destruction of many official documents and much other public property. Minor forms of outrages (e.g., intimidation, cattle-driving, &amp;c.) are also not included. The Agreement for the cessation of hostilities came into force on the 11th July, 1921.o

</content>
</cab>
