<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 563-568</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
POOMgg IS SE  PHOEKIgEY CP EIS BRIMIHCMkJSSTY f.S. GOVEHHMEIEg.CAB IKE T.jaTEBIMffil-CBAl BKIGRAgTON G OfeiMISSlOlI.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.HBT        1.        The first General Conference of the International 7sE7CLabour Organisation, held at Washington in 1919, passed the following Resolution -&quot;It is resolved that the Governix.^   Body of the &quot;International Labour &quot;Office shall cons-titute an &quot;international oommission, which shall, while &quot;giving due regard to the sovereign righte of each &quot;State, consider and report what measures can be &quot;adopted to regulate the migration of workers out &quot;of their native country, and to protect the interests &quot;of wage earners residing in another country than &quot;their own.   She representation of the States in the &quot;-European Continent on the commission shall be limited &quot;to one-half of the total membership of the Commission.. &quot;The said Commission shall present its report at the &quot;sear ion   of the International Conference in 19 0M.2. In pursuance of this Resolution, a commission was,appointed, of which Lord Cave became the Chairman on the nomination of the British Government.     In consequence of pressure of other work, Lord Cave was compelled to resignthis appointment before the Commission met, and Lord XJllswatetook his place.fc.        In the Autumn of last year the International Labour Office drev? up a Questionnaire and circulated it to all Members of the Organisation to elicit information upon which the&apos; Commission could base its recommendations.     Che replies of the British Government to this Questionnaire were prepared in consultation with the Departments concerned in emigration and immigration.     When the Commission met on the End August last, it was in possession of a series of proposed draft conventions or recommendations prepared by the International
386Lib our Office, Lord Ullswater had received the views of the Government upon these proposals at meetings of the Inter-national Labour Committee, held under the Chairmanship of Sir kontague Barlow.4. -      $he Commission held fourteen sessions and rose on 11th August.    It adopted  9 Resolutions, which are incor-por&amp;ted in a report which will be presented to the Governing Body of the International Labour Organisation at its meeting next October.Lord Ullswater has forwarded me a copy of the full report: and also a short memorandum on the work of the Emigration committee-s&amp;ion, and I am circulating the latter as likely to be of interest to the Cabinet.I fully endorse Lord TJllswater&apos;s conclusions as to the desirability of the Government being represented on any international organisation which may be created as a result of tho Commissions Resolutions.  .5. I should like to place on recor-d my appreciation ofLord Ullswater&apos;s services.(Initialled ) . *E .  J. M.Linistry of Labour, 29th .august. 1921.
387INT3R1JATI0NAL   EMIGRATION   CO&amp;IISSIOir.h&amp;^L &quot;by Lord XJI1 swatar.1.      In forwarding the accompanying report of the International Emigration Commission, and the Minutes of Proceedings,* it is perhaps desirable that I should make the following general observations.2.     The unexpected absence of representatives of Australia, Argentine and the United states resulted in the interests of immigrating oountries being left in the hands of the Canadian, Brazilian and South African Delegates, only the former of whom could be described as an expert on immigration legislation and practice.    The South African representative also felt himself compelled to leave the Commission about half way through our deliberations.    On the other hand the Vice-Chairman ol the Commission, M. de Michelis, Commissioner-General of ^migration in Italy, an acknowledged expert, was able to advance the well-developed emigration policy of his country.    In this he had the entire support of the v/orkars1 Delegates, all of whom were from emigrating countries, and few objections to. his proposals came from other Government representatives.3.     The Commission came to.the conclusion that its decisions would be better expressed in the form of Resolutions than as Draft Conventions or Recommendations for adoption at future General Conferences of the International Labour Organisation. This conclusion will, I think be deemed wise.    In the process of transforming these Resolutions into Draft Conventions or Recommendations, whereby Members of the Organisation will be called upon to assume definite obligations, the International Lshour Office and the General Conferences will be ablo&quot;&quot;to -^a?* not reproduced. - 1 -
greater regard to the special interests of particular countriesthan was feasible on the part of the Commission.4.     The Resolutions fall broadly under three categories -(1) Those defining the obligations of the emigrating and immigrating oountries vis-a-vis the I.L. 0.(2) Those imposing obligations upon emigrating countries, and(3) Those specially affecting immigrating countries. In the Resolutions under the first category it will be found that the scope of the International Labour Office in regard to emigration matters is more closely defined than in the past,, There is no longer any question of giving the Office executive powers, and suggestions are made for providing it with expert advice on the many technical issues involved.The second class of Resolution is directed to controlling emigration agenoies and co-ordinating national services with a view to protecting the emigrant from exploitation and securing him work under fair conditions in his new country. Certain desiderata are laid down with regard to the recruiting of bodies of workers for service abroad, but these are matters which are mainly of concern to continental countries.The third class of Resolution sook to engage the immigrat-ing countries to facilitate the admiesion of foreign workers and to give them equality of treatment with nationals.    It will be observed that these Resolutions are not so developed as others and some of the proposals made under this category stand referred to the permanent Committee (see below), for further consideration.5.     The Commission has recommended the Governing Body of the Organisation to oreate a permanent Committee to assist the Technical Emigration Section at Geneva in its examination of some of the more difficult problems, such as universal social insurance;   uniformity of hygienic conditions on board ships;
medical examination of emigrants before embarkation, etc. Although the multiplication of oommittees under the International Labour Organisation may be deprecated, on grounds of expense, I am satisfied that this particular Reoommendation is desirable.   The interests oonoerned in the regulation of immigration are important and varied;   they go far beyond the relations of employers and employed, and raise issues affecting transportation, public health, and passport control.   It seems desirable, therefore, that the International Labour Office should have expert advice on these matters before attempting to frame international laws affecting emigration. In any event, the proposed Permanent Committee and its body of experts will probably be regarded as a satisfactory alternative to the proposal of the Brazilian Government that tho Commission Itself should he constituted permanently,   The Brazilian Government were prepared to entrust to the Commission, so constituted, the duty of directing the flow of emigration aocording to the state of the world&apos;s unemployment, and of acting as the organ of oonoiliatlon in difficulties whioh might arise between Governments in regard to Immigration. 6*     I need hardly add that although the question of inter-imperial migration has been expressly excluded from the jurisdiction of the Commission, a principle whioh was accepted by the Commission without demur, it is necessary that Groat Britain, both as a oountry of trans-migration and as one vitally interested through shipping companies in the trans* portation of emigrants, should secure adequate representation on the Permanent Committee.    It would also be desirable that British experts should be amongst those consulted on the numerous technical issuos involved,7,     She 2Cjf Resolutions, agreed to by the Commission, willbe found amongst the documents appended hereto.   They stand in
the order in which they were discussed and adopted.   Mo attempt has &quot;been made to group them or arrange them in any logical order of sequence,    Imperfeotions in their phraseology must bo attributed to the conditions under whioh the work was carried out.   Amendments to original resolutions in English were proposed in Frenchs rapidly translated, and incorporated, in the test and vice versa.    The difficulty of carrying on the work in two languages simultaneously accounts for any lack of homogeneity of phraseology which may be observable.f Sgd)      UlLSYifASSR

</content>
</cab>
