<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 610-613</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for ike Cabinet.   August 1921.SECRET.: CP. i!i 11CABINET. MOPLAH  RIOTS.II.I circulate to my colleagues the following further telegrams which have been received from the viceroy on the subject of the Moplah riots.E. S. M.29th August 1921.From Viceroy, Home Department, 26tli August 1921.9210Clear the line.Continuation of my telegram No. 481 of to-day. Following- is report from Head-quarters, Madras District, for 6 p.m., 25th : &quot; (? Calicut) is quiet. The railway has been made good as far as Tautur, working southwards from Karur. The railway from Calicut has been repaired up to nine miles from Calicut towards Malapuram, and a column has left Calicut for Malapuram. The force from Podanur will proceed to Kuttipuram this day, as soon as the railway bridge at mile 377.7 has been repaired. It is intended to send a force from Kutti-puram to Malapuram on the 27th instant, the remainder of the force continuing the repairing of the railway towards Tirur.&quot; At the request of the civil authorities a platoon of the 86th Carnatic Infantry has been called out from Trichinopoly to Karur, and it has been, necessary to post a guard over the Cauvery bridge at Erode of one platoon of the South Indian Railway Auxiliary Force.&quot; The health of the troops remains good.&quot;From Viceroy, Home Department, 26th August 1921.9222Your telegram dated 24th August, No. 4359. Moplah outbreak. Rowley, Assistant District Superintendent of Police, and Readman, Inspector of Police, Special Reserve, killed, as far as our information goes. We have repeated to Madras, asking them to report direct to you if any officer killed other than those mentioned. We presume you refer only to British officers.From Viceroy, Home Department, 26th August 1921.9229490 Poll. Moplah riots. Martial Law Ordinance signed by Governor-General and promulgated to-day. Applies to Walavanad, Ponnani, Eruad and Calicut Taluks. Full text follows by mail.From Viceroy, Home Department, 27th August 1921.9224Clear the line.Correspondence ending with my telegram of the &apos;26th instant, No. 490. Following report dated 26th, time 1 a.m., received from Headquarters, Madras District: &quot; Situation (? reports omitted) 17 hours (? have been sent) Madras Press.   No further developments to report (? at Madras) regarding military in Malabar, where troops are making steady progress.   Widespread robbery and violence  directed 4559      100   8.21
against Hindu population in Ernad and Walluvanad Taluks is reported. Mahomedan riot at Karur dealt with by police, supported by small detachment of Indian Infantry. Patrol train from Calicut reached Tirur, rescued two men, Leinsters, previously reported missing. Calicut quiet. Movable column from Calicut reported within four miles of Malapuram still advancing.&quot;From Viceroy, Home Department, 21th August 1921.9228Home No. Poll. Following telegram received from the Government of Madras: &quot; District magistrate, Tricliinopoly, wires. Report received from Deputy Superintendent Police, Karur, of disturbances at Theatre Hall last night, where police used firearms. One casualty amongst rioters. District magistrate proceeding Karur with police and 30 Carnatic Infantry.&quot;Following report received from Officer Commanding detachment, 86th Carnatics, dated 26th instant, time 12.30 :  &quot; District magistrate, Karur, considers situation restored to normal, and has given written authority for return military to Trichinopoly by 15.30 train to-day, which I am complying with.&quot;From Viceroy, Rome Department, 21th August 1921.9230Moplah riots. Following substance of Press reports received this morning. Landing party disembarked from Comus and marched through big bazaar Moplah town&apos; with police guides and colours flying. On 25th, Moplahs attacked Poonoor estate and attempted assassination of Tippets, manager, who had miraculous escape. Mob murdered Eaton of Pullengoda estate and burnt bungalow. Mrs. Eaton safe. Keralla rubber estate reported attacked ; bungalows, factory, dispensary burnt, and cash and property looted. Managers believed to have escaped, but nothing definitely known. Later message that Brown safe ; two more landlords, probably Hindus of Mavooruporte, reported to have been murdered; post, offices at Augandipuram and Nilambar looted and Sub-Registrar&apos;s office at Kaipananchey demolished. Calicut Press correspondent wires: Telegraph wires probably require months to restore. Letter said to have been received from Raja Nilambar, states that he is again threatened and asks for assistance. Should there be any trouble in Calicut, Moplah quarters will be at once bombarded by Comus.2. District magistrate, Malabar, issued following communique : - &quot; The district magistrate had received information, that a number of war knives were in existence in Tirarangadi in contravention of the &apos; Malabar Offensive Weapons Act 20 of 1851 &apos; ; it was also necessary to arrest, for incitement to outrage, certain persons in Tirurangadi under section 8 of the &apos; Moplah Outrages Act.&apos; Anticipating that resistance Avould be made, a requisition was made for detachment of British troops to support police, and party arrived at Tirurangadi before dawn on the 20th. Searches were made and three men arrested, and a small party of reserve police left behind to continue the search of warrantees. Kizhikkapalle Mosque was entered by Moiolah police officers, who removed their boots before entering the mosque. In (sic) Mampuron Mosque, which is on the other side of the river, was not approached by anybody. Between hours 1.1.30 and 2 p.m. determined attack was made from two sides of the force of the police and troops by armed bands coming from Tanur Parappanan-gadi and adjoining Amshoms on the west, and from Tirurangabi and Amshoms on the east as far as Ponmala and Kottakkal. The attacks were beaten off, but two officers were surrounded and butchered by the mob. The force stayed the night at Tirurangadi. At this time the railway station at Parapannangadi, and thence along the railway line to Feroke, being attacked constantly by armed Moplahs. On the way for the first four miles the railway line bad already been cut in several places as far as Feroke. This attempt to make searches and arrests under legal warrants, in clue conformity with law, had been the signal for an outburst of fanaticism throughout Ernad, Walluvanad and Ponani, directed first against European officials
421    iFrom Viceroy, Home Department, 21th August 1921.9225Clear the line.Moplah riots.   Following telegram, dated 27th August, received from Government of Madras:  &quot; Malabar internal situation, 26th. Affected area now includes Kurumbranad Taluk, which has been entered by large parties of Moplah rebels. Indian troops have been requisitioned from Cannanore to meet and deal with these. Owing to disorgani-sation dt runners and communications the whole of affected area now threatened with famine. Planter Eaton of Pullangod estate now definitely reported killed. Planters Brown and Colebrooke have arrived&apos; safely Ootacamund. Planter Tippets escaped Calicut. Relief party sent for planter Norman. The Forest 0&apos;fficer&apos;s bungalow, Nilambiir, also Range Officers quarters and lines gutted. District Forest Officer, Chandy, rangers and forest (? subordinates) all prisoners. Palghat Sub-Divisional Magistrate reports plundering houses and liquor shops and boasting that Swaraj established. Incursion into Wynaad threatened. Emergency issue arms and ammunition to Planter Units Auxiliary Forces being ordered.   Relief force reported. ,within four miles Malapuram, 26th. Railway Calicut restored except 10 badly damaged miles. Special Civil Officer hopes to be able established (sic) contact with Calicut to-night. Reference our telegram No. 480, Political. No further casualties of European officers to report.&quot; itfFurther telegram received asking that Martial Law may be extended to Kurambrauad and Wynad Taluks. Governor-General of India in Council has approved, and notification issues by Gazette Extraordinary this evening.From Viceroy, Home Department, 28th August 1921.9274Clear the line.Moplah disturbances. Following is summary of situation report at 6 p.m. on 27th August, telegraphed by General Officer Commanding, Madras district : Movable column from Calicut reported to have reached Malapuram. Report not yet confirmed. Railway cleared and opened to mile 386. Ninety sailors from Comus marched through Calicut town. There has been disturbance at Quilambi, ten miles north of Calicut. Detachments of troops from Cannanore sent to Quilambi to deal with disturbance. Movable column left Kuttipuran 4 a.in. on 27th, to effect junction with Calicut forces. Progress of column - not yet reported. One platoon of Leinsters with two Lewis guns has been sent to Judalur, presumably to relieve and evacuate planters who may be hard pressed. At Hammarpet auxiliary force has been mobilised to guard Treasury.&quot;From Viceroy, Home Department, 29th August 1921.9302Malabar disturbances. Following telegrams received from Headquarters, Madras. First, dated 27th August, 18.35 hours :-&quot; Have had to draw on British Army School of Education for services of few officers in connection with rebellion in Malabar. So far have requisitioned five. Am short of officers for extra appointments, so hope my action approved.&quot;Second, dated 29th August, 11.35 hours : &quot; Following is situation report for 09.00 hours. This morning, Calicut movable column has returned to Calicut, bringing Malapuram detachment in with it. It had an action with rebels on 26th instant at Pukkatur. Moplah casualties were about 400 killed.   Our own were two killed and one officer and five other ranks wounded.aand non-officials and latterly against Hindu. Jemmis and other public offices have been looted everywhere ; Manas and Kovilakoms pillaged, Hindus murdered and forcibly converted, and the line cut to an extent regarding which there is no information.&quot;
Kuttipuram movable column was reported at Malapuram on 27tli instant. To-day there are columns from Malapuram, Calicut and Tirur, converging on Tirurangacli. Railway line now open to Calicut having been repaired by temporary work.&quot;Above in continuation of previous telegram of 29th August.   No. 515 Pol.From Viceroy, Home Department, 29th August 1921.9303Reference military telegrams dated to-day.   Following received from Madras : &quot; Malabar District Magistrate reports that detachment Leinsters and Special Police Force that left Calicut on 25th for relief of Malapuram was attacked Pookotur, few miles from Malapuram, by large body rebels, about 11 o&apos;clock morning 26th. Mopillas were armed with carbines captured from r)olice stations they had looted, as well as with some sporting rifles and swords and war knives. They displayed their traditional ferocity and eagerness for death, and after five hours&apos; fighting were beaten off, their casualties being estimated at 400 killed. Two British soldiers reported killed, and an officer and five men wounded. Lancaster, Assistant Superintendent of Police, was shot and has since died. Secretary of State informed. Detachment reached Malapuram, where they found all safe and well, and has returned with Malapuram garrison to Calicut. Railway is now temporarily repaired through to Calicut for day running. No further news of rebels from Nilgiris border, nor from Kurambranad.&quot;   No. 516 Pol.

</content>
</cab>
