<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/127/0 images: 692-694</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
is POCUMEET IS SEE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).sJ5 ORE 0?. I ^0.P.-3284. 0 A BI B E fe, *2ARMENIAN REFUGEES&apos;^(I) Telegram from High Commissioner of Iraq, to Secretary of State for the Go Ionics, dated 25 th August, 1921.(II) Telegram from High Commissioner of Iraq, to Secretary of State for tho Colonies, dated September 3rd, 1921.(Ill) Telegram from Secretary of State for the colonies to High Commissioner of Iraq, dated September 6th, 1921.(Circulated by the Secretary of State for the Colonies).Telegram from the High Commissioner of Iraq to the Secretary cf State for the Colonils, dated 25th August. (Received Colonial Office 7*45 a.m. 26tit August 1921.)Your telsgram of ^3rd August 325 arrived mutilated but I under-stand you to require a guarantee that closiiro of camp will not be completed until Visible means of support have been found for the Armenians.       If this is correct camp will have to be maintained ladefinitely uatil repatriation effected.       My telegram dated 11th July 286 gave proposal, based on the assumption that no further fund would be available.       Armenians are proving most obstrviotive and in many cases have definitely refused profitable employment offei^ed e*g. (a) vide my telegram of 17th August 399.      Work rofusod at ICaerishirii and elsewhere.      (b) Two Arab landowners in Basra near site of presOn&apos; camp volunteered to settle 200 families on condition that landowners supply seed ploughs pumps animals and small advance of cash taking in return one half of crop.      This they have refused *     A labour depot was started in Basra and broke down after a few days.      It 4vas found that soi-disant skilled labourers could not pass the required tests while output of unskilled was below local standard. In view therefore of the inefficiency and indolence of the Armenians themselves it is impossible to obtain any guarantee from employers.     My telegram dated 2nd August 358.    These
Persian Armenians have now-reached.&quot; &quot;Baghdad and I am endeavouringto send them to Persia for work with Anglo-Persian Oil and inmeanwhile to provide them with shelter.     A party of 202 Assyrians Kahnmar&apos;from the oamp have asked to be sent to Mosul and this isbeing arranged 440 AOTenians have also asked to be sent to Mosul and enquiries are being made /to the reason of this request.     To assist me....in the camp General Headquarters has kindly permitted, (that) Colonel Baking General Headquarters representative at the base to inspect and advise.     Copies of reports follow but he Is satisfied after careful consideration of ail alternatives that administra-.. tively the only satisfactory solution is repatriation to Batum, . This by merchant ships would cost between  6,400,000 and  6,500,000 and it is presumably impraeticablo unless prize ships can be. found to work the voyage more cheaply.COX.11*Telegram from tho High Commissioner of Iraq to the Secretary of State for the Colonies-,    Dated 3rd September. (Received Colonial Office 4.53 a.mc 4th September 1921).458My despatch 18th July 12655   Assyrians settlement in Mosul are suffering from acute outbreak malaria.    Am also anxious lest dispersal of thousands of refugees result in insanitary^ encampments being set up in big: towns.     Moreover divisional adviser Basrah telegraphs that situation of Armenian refugees is becoming worse ar.d many will shortly be in dangef1 of starving.    He endorses view given in last paragraph of my telegram  5th August 426.    I trust therefore that you will lo&amp; counting at my disposal to meet eventualities i 40,000 saving I have shown in actual dispersal scheme given), -in above qiioted despatch.COX.
TELEORAL.Prom:Secretary of State for the Colonies,To :Sir Percy Co:-:.Pat e d6th. September, 1921.Personal.i have now seen for first time the telegrams about the Armenians.    i am not prepared in any circumstances to. face an increase of expenditure either by Vote or overspending on their account.    Anything necessary for their upkeep beyond the sums already taken by the Government must be provided by charitable institutions.    The case of Armenians who have definitely refused work should be dealt with by an immediate and final cessation of assistance.    This would enable such funds as remained to be concentrated upon people for whom no work can be found. . Your proposals for closing the camp and making a gift of money and rations from the limited funds available is approved.I am confident you will do your &quot;best to make the lavish aid. which the Government has given go aa far as possible. But there will be much suffering in England and Scotland this Winter among people only too willing to work, and I cannot burden the. British Exchequer further on account of Armenian or other refugees who:.: we have now maintained for over three years.    On the other hand, any funds raised voluntarily by sympathisers in this  country will be at once transmitted to them.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.6th September, 1921:.

</content>
</cab>
