<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/96/0 images: 97-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AGENDA.I.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS.2.    PALESTINE.(Reference Cabinet 50 (38) Conclusion 3)Report by Cabinet Committee.CP. 237 (38) - already circulated.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies,covering draft White Paper.CP. 241 (38) - circulated herewith.8.    MANUFACTURE OF TOXIC GAS FOR USE IN WAR.Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence,covering extract from Minutes of the 333rd Meeting ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence, together withMemorandum prepared by the War Office and Air Ministry,CP. 220 (38) - already circulated.4.    GOVERNMENT BUSINESS;    THE LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMMES FOR1938-59 and 1959-40.(Reference Cabinet 36 (37) Conclusion 11 &amp; Appendix)14th Conclusions (38) of Committee of Home Affairs,covering classified Lists of Bills for the 1938-39and 1939-40 Sessions -   circulated herewith.5.    THE KING18 SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF PARLIAMENT.(Reference Cabinet 50 (38) Conclusion 7)Draft Speech prepared by Cabinet Committee.CP. 239 (38) - to be circulated.(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT)SECRET. COPY NO.CABINET     52 (58)Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10 downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, 2nd NOVEMBER, 1938,at 11.0 a.m.
ioo6.    ESTABLISHMENT OF A CANCER SERVICE.Joint Memorandum by the Minister of Health and theSecretary of State for Scotland.CP. 232 (38) - circulated herewith.7,    PROPOSED ADOPTION SOCIETIES BILL (PRIVATE MEMBER1SBILL).Memorandum by the Home Secretary.CP. 238 (38) - already circulated.8.    CONCLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.15th Conclusions (38) of Committee of Home Affairs -to be circulated.(i)   Czechoslovakia (Financial Assistance) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 48 (38) Conclusion l)Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury, covering draft Bill.H.A. 31 (38) - already circulated.(ii)   Prevention of Fraud (investments) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 50 (38) Conclusion 10)Memorandum by the President of the Board ofTrade, covering draft Bill.H.A* 30 (38) - circulated herewith.(iii)   Housing (Financial Provision) (Scotland) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 50 (38) Conclusion 9)Memorandum by the Secretary of State forScotland, covering draft Bill.H.A. 29 (38) - circulated herewith.(iv)   Expiring Laws Continuance Bill.(Reference Cabinet 39 (37) Conclusion 27)Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury, covering draft Bill.H.A. 28 (38) - already circulated.(Signed)     E.E. bridges secretary to the Cabinet.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.28th October, 1938.
SECRET. COPY NO,CABINET      52 (38)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10 Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,2nd NOVEMBER, 1938, at 11.0 a,m,PRESENT:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (In the Chair)Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,G.C.V.O., O.B.E., K.C., M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.Right Hon.Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor.Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G.,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs.Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and Secretaryof State for the Colonies.Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E.,K-C, M.P., Minister forCo-ordination of Defence.Right Hon.L.    Hore-Belisha, MoP.,Secretary of State for War.Right Hon.John Colville, M.P.,Secretary of State forScotland.Right Hon.W.S. Morrison, M.C., K.C.,M.P., Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Health.Right Hon.E.L. Burgin, M.P.,Minister of Transport.E.E. Bridges, M.C.The Right Hon.The Viscount Runciman,Loid President of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.,G.B.E., C.M.G., M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir John Anderson, G.C.B.,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Map.,Lord Privy Seal,The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,G.CoS.I., G0C0I.E., Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G., D.S.O.,M.C., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.The Earl De La Warrj^Presidentof the Board of Education,The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.The Earl Winterton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.Secretary.
1.      THE PRIME MINISTER offered a welcome to theLord President of the Council and the Lord privy seal.    The Lord .President of the Council was an oldfriend whom they were glad to have among them once more.    The new Lord privy Seal had been known tothem for many years as Sir John Anderson.    He would now have to contend with the splendour of hisreputation and achievements in other fields and the expectations which those achievements would arouse.He had every confidence that Sir John would achievesuccess in this new field of activity.
CHINA-Interferencewith H*M. Shipson the WestRiver.(previous reference:Cabinet 51(38), Con-clusion 5).F.R.Sh.(3sO 3.2.      THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he had nothing to report in regard toforeign affairs except as to the Gunboats in China.Our Ambassador had made a protest in Tokyo.    TheJapanese authorities in Tokyo, while outwardlyfriendly, took the view that the matter must besettled locally.    Between this attitude and theobstruction made by the Japanese local Commandersin China,  it had been difficult to reach a settlement.The Japanese authorities had taken the view thatthey had no wish to be obstructive, but that theships concerned were in the war area and wereobstructed not merely by the Japanese battle linebut, in one case, also by the battle line of theChinese forces.    Late on Tuesday evening,  afterconsultation between the Foreign Office and theAdmiralty, the latter had instructed the two ships that thej&apos;- might proceed on their way at theirown discretion.    H.M.S. CICALA had sailed at a-m.  on Wednesday.    H.M.S. ROBIN was furtherup-river, and it would be much more difficult forher Commander to extricate hero    If the ROBIN hadto wait, our prestige would not be   very much affectedowing to the fact that the Ship was at present in what was definitely a war area.    The matter wasone which must be left to the British Commander-in-Chief in China and the Commander of the ROBIN.Meanwhile we would continue to exercise pressureat Canton and Tokyo.In reply to a question by the Prime Minister,the Foreign. Secretary explained that the orders which
had previously been issued to the Gunboats tosail on Tuesday morning had been postponed for24 hours as Sir Robert Craigie had.held out hopes of a settlement.The Cabinet took note of theabove statement.
mXIG GAS FOR     4. The Cabinet had under consideration a MemorandumE IN WAR.  by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence ^C.P.-220anufacture(38))  circulating, in accordance with a request by theCommittee of Imperial Defence, a copy of a letter dated.26th July, 1938, from the Air Ministry to the Secretary,Committee of Imperial Defence, covering a memorandum prepared, by the War Office and Air Ministry on theManufacture of Toxic Gas for Use in War (C.I.D. PaperNo. 1465-B), together with the Conclusions reachedthereon by the Committee of Imperial Defence at their333rd. Meeting (Minute 6), which are reproduced as .-Appendixtto these Minutes.    The Minister suggested, that,in the light of these Conclusions, his colleagues would wish to consider the use of gas as a retaliatory measure in war, and the scale on which provision for the manu-facture of gas should be made.THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCE, in introducing the paper, explained the history of thematter.In 1937 the War Office had put up proposals for theexpenditure     of  5 million on the erection of twofactories with a capacity of about 520 tons a week.The Chancellor of the Exchequer had not felt able toagree to this course, but had authorised the erection ofa factory with a capacity of about 170 tons a week.     Hehad objected to fuller provision being made, since firsthe wanted to be assured whether the latest view of gaswas that it v/as as effective a weapon against the oivilpopulation as high explosive or incendiary bombs;secondly, the Chanceloor of the Exchequer had thoughtthat the use of gas even as a retaliatory measure shouldbe considered by the Cabinet in its political aspects.
bThese questions were dealt with in the Joint Memorandumby the War Office and Air Ministry.     It was plain thatGermany was making large preparations in this matter.     Theuse of gas was regarded by the Air Staff as complementary tothe use of high explosive and incendiary bombs.     The factthat we should be able to use gas ourselves in retaliationmight be of considerable value in deterring other countries from this form of attack.       At a later otage it might benecessary that we should let it be known that we were in aposition to retaliate, but for the time being, and until a capacity had been built up, it was desirable that our actionin this matter should be kept secretoAs regards the extent to which provision should be made,he thought that it was now agreed that it would suffice thatwe should provide a capacity of 300 tons a week and a warreserve of 2,000 tons.     He asked the Cabinet to approve theuse of gas as a retaliatory measure and the provision of capacity of 300 tons a week, plus storage of 2,000 tons.THE PRIME MINISTER said he did not think it was possibleto distinguish between the use of gas and other agencies of destruction.     We should not ourselves be the first to make-use of this weapon, but he thought that we must have it sothat we could retaliate if others used it0     He hoped that-the Cabinet would agree to the course proposed.The Cabinet agreed --(a) That it was necessary that provision should be made by this country forthe use of gas as a retaliatorymeasure in war.(b) To take note that the Departmentsconcerned had been authorised -(i) to complete the Kernetfactory to provide capacity for a total weekly output of300 tons;(ii) to complete storage for awar reserve of 2,000 tonsof gas.
government business.legislativeprogrammes1938-39, and1939-40.[(previous reference:Cabinet 36(37), Con-clusion 11and Appendix.)5. The Cabinet had before them the 14th Conclu-sions (38) of the Committee of Home Affairs, recommend-ing for adoption a classification of the Billssuggested by Departments for the parliamentary session 1938-39, and containing the Committee^detailed conclusions on the Bills (See Appendix II)jtogether v/ith a tentative list of Bills suggestedby Departments for the 1939-40 parliamentary session (See Appendix III).)The Cabinet agreed -To adopt the proposed classification of Bills and the Committee&apos;s detailedconclusions on the Bills subject to thefollowing comments:-EKS-yfss) 11.   Census of Production Act (Amendment).THE PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OP TRADEexplained that a note should he addedthat it would only he necessary for this bill to be passed into law by the autumn of1939 if it was decided to hold a census of Production in 1940.   Owing to the abnormal position in industry as a resultof the Rearmament Programme there was much to be said for postponing the census of Production.Royal Marines.It was agreed that this Bill, besidesextending Section 9 of the Naval EnlistmentAct, 1853, to the Royal Marines,- shouldalso indemnify the Admiralty in regard to action taken during the recent crisis.Clubs.Some discussion took place on this bill.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR HOME affairs said that he could only introduce quite a small Bill, which would not satisfy the sections of opinion which were mostin favour of the introduction of theClubs Bill.     Notwithstanding the frequentundertakings which the Government had giirenin regard to legislation on this matter
he thought that on the v/hole the right course would be to rnalce no attempt tointroduce this Bill in the 1938-39 Session.After disctission, it v/as agreed thatthis Bill should remain in the presentList but should not be included in anypublished list of the Bills which it wasthe intention of the Government tointroduce in the. 1938-39 Session.At the same time it would be unnecessary tosay definitely that it was not proposed tointroduce the Clubs Bills during thepresent Session.Electricity Supply.THE MINISTER OF TRANSPORT pointed outthat the matter was bound to be raised ifa reference to this Bill v/as not includedin the King1s Speech.THE PRIME MINISTER said that there wasno chance of getting this Bill through inthe present Session, and that he thought the right course was to state this factopenly when the question v/as raised.It v/as agreed that this Bill should therefore be deleted from the GovernmentLegislative Programme for the 1938-39Session.NOTE:- The necessary alterations have been madein the classified list of Billsrepresenting the Government LegislativeProgrammes for 1938-39 and 1939-40,attached as Appendices II and III.It
THE KING&apos;S speech on THE OPENINGOP PARLIAMENT.(previous reference:Cabinet 50(58), Con-clusion 7. )&apos; njt.5u-tsi)s.6.      The Cabinet had under consideration adraft of the King&apos;s Speech on the Opening ofParliament (CP-  259 (58)) in the form agreed bythe Cabinet Committee.THE PRIME MINISTER said that since the speech had been drafted, decisions had beenreached in regard to the arrangements for air raid Precautions and National Voluntary Service.He suggested,  and the Cabinet agreed, that a paragraph on this matter should be included inThe King&apos;s Speech, to be drafted by himself,  theHome Secretary and the Lord Privy Seal-The Cabinet also agreed that the PrimeMinister and the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries should draft a sentence to precede the paragraph on Agriculture.It was agreed that,  in view of thepresent state of the negotiations with theUnited States for a Trade Agreement, a paragraphon this matter was not called for.The Cabinet went through the draft speech paragraph by paragraph and made thefollowing amendments or modifications:-The first sentence should be modified bythe inclusion, after the reference tothe Anglo-German Declaration made atMunich, of some reference to the putting into effect of the Anglo-Italian Agreement,The paragraph relating to the visit ofthe King and Queen to Canada should bebrought up so as to follow immediately on the two paragraphs dealing with the visits to this country of the King of roumania and the President of the french republic.    Subject to His Majesty&apos;s
approval, the paragraph relating to t:.eKing and Queen1s visit to Canada shouldalso be amplified by a reference to TheKing&apos;s decision to accept an invitation from president Roosevelt to visit theUnited States of America.The wording of the paragraph dealing withthe Spanish conflict should be reconsideredin the light of the statement to be madeby the Prime Minister as to putting intoeffect the Anglo-Italian Agreement.The v/ording of the paragraph on defence should also be reconsidered in the lightof the following suggestions which woremade:-First, that it was not wholly accurate to speak of theemergency having brought out certain deficiencies.    Thus it mightbe better to speak of &quot;deficiencies which remain to be remedied&quot;.Second, that the proposals would notnecessarily be laid before Parliament.It might be better to speak of &quot;taking steps&quot;.Third, that it would be better to say thatthe review of these matters by ministers had been completed.That an addition should be made on thesubject of Unemployment.    This might wellfollow the paragraph dealing with tradeand industry and the development of overseas markets.Subject to the above amendments ormodifications, the Cabinet approved the draft King&apos;s Speech on theOpening of Parliament,  attached to cp.  239(38), for submission toHis Majesty.
11 AA CANCERSERVICE.Establishmentof.7.     The Cabinet had under consideration a joint memorandum by the Minister of Health and theSecretary of State for Scotland (CP. 232 (38))seeking authority for&apos;the introduction of a Bill forthe establishment of a Cancer Service, with the objectof making available modern facilities for diagnosisand treatment over the whole country.In introducing this Memorandum, the MINISTEROP HEALTH said that this was a matter in which agreat deal of work had been done by his predecessor.Cancer represented perhaps the biggest gap in ourhealth services.     It caused 200 deaths a day, ofwhich three out of four did not have the benefit of proper facilities for treatment.     A scheme hadbeen devised to cover the whole country, and to be run by the larger Local Authorities, with the help of a Government grant.     The scheme also providedfor the purchase of radium by means of a loan to bespread over sixty years.j The Minister of Health said that he hadbeen in touch with the leaders of the Cancer Campaign,who had undertaken to do everything in their powerto support the voluntary campaign.     Arrangements had also been made to secure an option on the supply ofradium from Canada, so that an announcement on thelines proposed would not result in the price being raised against the Government.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR SCOTLANDassociated himself with what the Minister of Healthhad said.      It was significant that there were nowtwice as many deaths from cancer as from tuberculosis.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF LANCASTERemphasised the importance of the scheme being worked
through the Voluntary Hospitals.The Cabinet agreed:To approve the proposals of theMinister of Health and the Secretaryof State for Scotland set forth in cp. 232 (38).
OPTIONOIETIES8. The cabinet had before^e them a kemoranaum bythe Secretary of State for Home Affairs    (G.P. 258 (38);requesting the approval of his colleagues to the intro-duction into Parliament of a Sill the main object ofwhich would be to regulate the activities of Adoptionsocieties and other agencies that arrange for theadoption of children.      The i3ill v/as one which couldsuitably be introduced by a Private Member.TUB CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER and theLORD CHANCELLOR strongly supported the Home secretary&apos;sproposals.THE SECRETARY uP STATE POR SCOTLAND observed thatit might be necessary to deal separately with Scotland,as the adoption of children there was governed byseparate Acts,      The Inquiry by the Committee referredto in the Home Secretary&apos;s memorandum hao not extendedto Scotland.rThe Cabinet agreed:To approve the proposals in CP. 238 (38)in regard to the proposed AdoptionSocieties Bill.
THECZECHOSLOVAKIA(FIIL^FCIALI^ASSISTlKCS)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 46(38), Conclu-sion (1)).FTR9.     The Cabinet had under consideration a Memorandumby the financial Secretary to the Treasury (JJ.A.-31(58)) covering the Craft Czechoslovakia (Financialassistance) Bill, the principal objects of whichwere t? authorise (i) the reimbursement of the advance of  10 million to the Ban!: of England, and(ii) the guarantee of a Czechoslovak Government loan:together v/ith the following recommendations thereon by the Committee of Home Affairs (II.A.C. 15thConclusions (3C), Minute l):-&quot;(l) To approve the Czechoslovakia(Financial Assistance) Bill inthe form of the draft annexed toII.A.-31 (58), subject to subse-euent decisions of the Cabinet whenthe discussions v/ith the French andCzechoslovak Governments have beencarried further, and subject alsoto any drafting or other minor alterations that may be foundnecessary or desirable:(2) To authorise the introduction ofthe Bill as approved in the Houseof Commons.THE LORD C AITCELLOR pointed out that Clause 2of the Bill as drafted made it appear that the Govern-ment had decided to make a further advance over and above the advance of  10 millions dealt v/ith in Clause 1.The Government had not in fact yet reached any suchdecision;    Clause 2 therefore appeared to conferdiscretion to decide what further sum should be advanced.     This might give rise to some misunder-standing.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he assumed that thetotal figure to be inserted in   Clause 2 (which v/as now blank) would be filled in when the Governmenthac reached a decision, and before the Bill v/asintroduced.
TIIS LORD CHANCELLOR said that there was a -practical difficulty involved.     U&amp;ny mouths might ensue beforethe Government was in a position to know what sun it wasnecessary to advance under the proposed Guarantee.     he understood, however, that the Treasury felt that legislation should be introduced before Christmas to regularise the position in regard to the advance of  10millions, which had already been promised.THE CHANCELLO?. 0&apos;.? vHE EXCHEQUER said that he would look at this point again.Subject to further investigation of thepoint raised by the Lord Chancellor, theCabinet approved the recommendationsof the Home Affairs Committee as setout above.NOTE.The Chancellor of the Jncheouer anticipates thatit should be possible for the Government todecide the amount of the guaranteed loan before christmas.      .&quot;f not,  the right course would inhis view be to introduce a Bill dealing only withthe reimbursement to the Eank of England(Clause 1 of the present Sill).
THE PREVENTIONOP FRAUD(INVESTMENTS)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet *0(38) Con-clusion 10.)10.The Cabinet had before ther-. a Note by thePresident of the Hoard of Trade (&quot;H.A.-30 (38)),covering the draft Prevention of Fraud (investments)Bill, which, in pursuance of the Conclusion mentionedin the margin, is to be reintroduced at the beginningof next Session, with two important changes indicated by the President in Ifis covering Note:    together withthe following recommendation by the Committee ofHome Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 15th Conclusions (38),Minute 2)&quot;To authorise the introduction in theHouse of Commons of the Prevention ofFraud (investments) Bill in the formof the draft annexed to H.A.-30 (38),subject to settlement o^ the out stand-ing points mentioned at the meeting and subject also to any drafting orother minor alterations that may befound, necessary or desirable.&quot;The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs.
J9CTHE HOUSING(financial provisions)(SCOTLAND/BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 50(58), Con-clusion 9 .)11.    The Cabinet had under consideration a.Memoran-dum by the Secretary of State for Scotland (H.A.-29(38))  covering the draft Housing (Financial Provisions)(Scotland) Bill, dealing-with the financial arrange-ments for subsidising the building of working-classhouses in Scotland:    together with the following recommendation thereon by the Committee of HomeAffairs (H.A.C. l^th Conclusions (38), Minute 3):-&quot;To authorise the introduction in theHouse of Commons at the beginning ofthe new Session of the Housing (financial provisions) (Scotland) Bill in the formof the draft annexed, to H.A.-29 (38),subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that may be found necessary or desirable, with a view to the passageof the Bill into law before the christmas recess&quot;.The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs.
1 ^7THE EXPIRING LAWS    120 The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum byCONTINUANCE BILL.the Financial Secretary to the Treasury (H0A.-28 (38))(Previous covering the draft Expiring La&quot;rs Continuance Bill,Reference:Cabinet 39 which must become law by the 31st December, 1938,(37), Con-elusion, 27 o) together with the following recommendation by theCommittee of Home Affairs thereon (H.,AaC5 15th Conclu-sions (38) , Minute 4) :-&quot;To authorise the introduction in theHouse of Commons of the Expiring laws continuance Bill in the form of thedraft annexed to H.A.-28 (38), subjectto the determination by the Cabinet ofthe question of the continuance orotherwise of the Special Areas Act,1934, and subject also to any dra.ftingor other minor alterations that may befound, necessary or desirable, with aview to the passage of the Bill into law before 31st December, 1938.&quot;The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home affairs
NEXT MEETING 13. THE PRIME MINISTER informed the CabinetOP THE CABINET:that a Report by the Committee on Defence Programmes(Reference:Cabinet 50 (38) and Acceleration, which was appointed at the meetingConclusion 4).referred to in the margin, would be ready forFJ^. .5&quot; 3 (3 J ^circulation before the week-end.THE CABINET agreed:To meet on Monday, 7th November,1938, at 3.0 p.m. to consider this Report.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,2nd November, 1938.
SECRET.APPENDIX.  COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the Minutes of the 333rd Meeting, held on October 6, 1938.* * * * * *(6) THE MANUFACTURE OF TOXIC GAS FOR USE IN WAR.(C.I.D. Paper No. 1465-B.)(Previous Reference: C.I.D. Minutes of the 307th Meeting, Minute 4.)THE COMMITTEE had under consideration a copy of a letter dated the26th July, 1938, from the Air Ministry to the Secretary, Committee of ImperialDefence, covering the Memorandum prepared by the War Office and the AirMinistry (C.I.D. Paper No. 1465-B).SIR KINGSLEY WOOD said that the proposals contained in the War Officeand Air Ministry Memorandum for the provision of toxic gas for use in war hadbeen under consideration for some time. The question of the manufacture of gason the scale proposed was, of course, a matter for Cabinet decision, and theMemorandum had been drawn up with a view to setting out the strategic andpolitical aspects of this question. It was desirable that early decision should bereached on the question whether we were to proceed with the manufacture of gasfor two reasons first, because it would take 12 to 18 months for the proposedfactory to get into full production, and secondly, because orders for the weaponsfor the use of gas could not be placed pending this decision.Referring to the summary of the Conclusions in paragraph 30 of thememorandum he called particular attention to the very thorough arrangements which Germany were making for the provision of gas and its employment in war(sub-paragraph (i)) and the fact that gas was not an alternative, butcomplementary to high explosive and incendiary bombs. To place us in a positionto retaliate, if necessary, against the employment of gas against this country,the recommendation was made in sub-paragraph (v) that immediate steps shouldbe taken for the provision of gas on an initial scale of 300 tons per week.SIR WARREN FISHER said that the Chancellor of the Exchequer was prepared to agree to the immediate construction of the factory at Kemet. Forthe rest, the Chancellor thought that a second factory should not be set up, andthat the question of the extent to which poison gas should be manufactured and used was a matter of policy for decision by the Cabinet.Conclusions.The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed (a) That the question of the policy to be adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment regarding the use of gas as a retaliatory measure in war wasa matter for Cabinet decision.[18034-6]
(b) To endorse the conclusions recorded in paragraph 30 (i), (ii), (iii), (viii)and (ix) of the Memorandum, which were as follows : &quot; (i) There is no doubt that Germany is making very thorough arrange-ments for the provision of gas and its employment in war. Sheis well ahead of this country, and consequently it is necessarythat measures should be initiated at once to enable us to retaliate, should gas be used against us in war.(ii) Gas is not alternative to, but complementary to the high-explosivebomb and the incendiary bomb, and if used in conjunction withthem will hasten the work of dislocating and disorganisingthe national life and demoralising the community.(iii) The employment of gas as well as high-explosive and incendiary bombs would augment the effectiveness of our air offensive to a degree unattainable by other means.*******(viii) All practicable means should be employed to accelerate thecompletion of passive defence measures in order to offset inpart the reduction in our power to retaliate,(ix) The production of gas for offensive purposes is a corollary to theprovision of anti-gas measures. The knowledge that we possessgas to be used in retaliation will have a reassuring effect athome, and be a strong deterrent to its employment by potentialenemies abroad. Positive knowledge that we do not possessgas, however, is likely to be dangerous and to encourage its use against us.&quot;(c) To authorise the Departments concerned to take action forthwith : (a) To complete the Kemet factory so as to provide capacity for a weekly output of 300 tons (including 50 tons for army require-ments) (paragraph 30 (v) and (vi)).(b) To provide storage capacity for 2,000 tons reserve supply of gasrequii-ed to tide over the period during which the Kemetfactory is being raised from a peace to full war output (para-graph 30 (vii) ).(d) That, pending the Cabinet decision on the question of policy, no furtherfactory for the manufacture of toxic gas should be built.(e) To invite the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence to submit C.I.D.Paper No. 1465-B, together with the above Minutes, to the Cabinet.^      *^ *x* *k*Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,October 6, 1938.
APPENDIX II.1938-39 Session.Government Legislative Programme. $List of Bills furnished by Departments.(A) Annual or Compulsory Bills.(B) Urgent or Essential Bills (other than those named in List (A) ) : (i) Bills which must become law by certain dates;(ii) Other Essential Bills.(C) Useful Bills, mainly Non-Controversial.(D) Bills suitable for introduction by Private Members.(E) Bills not yet. ready, or Bills required in certain events : -(i) Bills which in certain events will become Urgent or Essential,(ii) Other Bills not yet ready.(F)-Consolidation Bills.(A) Annual or Compulsory Bills.Department.Bill or Subject.Required by.Treasury ...      . .&apos;  1. Expiring   Laws   Continuance,  Christinas, 1938.1938; 2. Consolidated Fund, 1939      ...  March, 1939.3. Consolidated Fund (Appropria-; Summer, 1939.tion), 1939! 4. Public Works Loans, 1938 or Christmas, 1938.1939I 5. Finance, 1939 .........! Summer, 1939.fiK-SSfa)&quot;^ g. Isle of Man Customs, 1939 ...  Summer, 1939.War   Office    and    Air;  7. Army and Air Force (Annual)! 30th April, 1939.MinistryGeneral Post Office   ...   8. Post    Office    and    Telegraph j July. 1939.Ff?.5l(5t])is. (Money)(B) Urgent or Essential Bills* (other than those named in List (A) ).B (i). Bills which must become Law by certain Dates.t(Bills of which the principles have received recent Cabinet approval.)Scottish office. Housing (Scotland) (financial provision)I2. Reorganisation(Scotland)31st December, 1938. Secretaryof State&apos;s pledge. See Cabinet50 (38), Conclusion 9.of Offices I Highly desirable by 31st December,1938. Reference Cabinet 36 (38),Conclusion 7. To give effect tothe recommendations of theDepartmental Committee on there organisation of the depart-ments subject to the Secretary ofState.5 The list which follows incorporates a few amendments made by the Cabinet, on theoccasion when the Committee&apos;s recommendations were adopted (Cabinet 52 (38), Conclusion 5).* In view of the financial unsettlement in many parts of the world, the Treasury point outthat Parliamentary time may be needed for other urgent or essential Bills, which cannot atpresent be foreseen.t Parliamentary time will be required for a resolution appointing two additional common law Judges.X Parliamentary time will also be required, probably before Christmas&apos;1938, for the approval,.by resolution under Standing Order 71, of a new contract with Messrs. MacBrayne relating tothe payment of a subsidy in respect of the Western Isles Steamer Services.[18126]
Department.Bill or Subject.Required by.Board of TradeCensus   of   Production(Amendment)4. Mining     Industry     (WelfareFund) AmendmentMinistry of Agricultureand Fisheries5. Lard6. Wheat Act (Amendment)Ministry of Agricultureand Fisheries and scottish office. *Milk industry act! Autumn,   1939.    See  Cabinet   1(5(38),   Conclusion   11.     It   will,however, only be necessary forthe Bill to be passed into lawas early as this if it is decidedto hold a census of productionin 1940.   Owing to the abnormalposition in industry, as a resultof the re-armament programme,there is much to be said for the postponement of the census ofproduction.31 st March, 1939.   A short Bill to restore the Fund to a penny perton    for    five    years.      see cabinet 30 (38), Conclusion 9.Introduction announced by theSecretary for Mines on 29th July,1938 (House of Commons official report, Col. 3489).November,   1938.     The   Cabinet-decided on the 28th July, 1938(Cabinet 30 (38), Conclusion 3(c)) that, in return for a reduc-tion in the duty on lard as partof a Trade Agreement with theUnited States of America, baconcurers should be given a priceguarantee   for   lard.     On   theassumption that a Trade Agree-ment containing the lard dutyreduction is concluded with theU.S.A.,     legislation    will    berequired before the new baconcontract period under the BaconIndustry   Act   begins   on   the1st December, 1938.Easter,   1939.    To  effect  certain amendments in the Wheat Act,1932, and in particular to providefor    further   reviews    of    theStandard Price.    This Bill hasbeen deferred owing to lack ofParliamentary time.   In order toenable a Standard Price Com-mittee to be set up and to reportwell before the end of the cerealyear (31st July, 1939), it is desir-able that the Bill should be given  an  early  place.     Suitable for introduction   in   the   House   ofLords.    See  Cabinet  49   (38),Conclusion 10.30th   September,   1939.      It   isdesirable, however, that the Billshould  be  passed   as  early  aspossible   in   the   new   session.Object will bo to give effect tothe proposals in the White paper of July, 1937 (Cmd. 5533) and subsequent statements.     Intro-duction deferred from the sessionnow ending owing to congestion of Parliamentary lusiness.   see cabinet 29 (38),* Conclusion 12.* Ministry of Health are also interested.
(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)Department.	Bill or Subject.	Required by.Board of Trade...... Ministry of Labour* and Scottish    Office    (or Treasury)	8. Bills to put into effect Trade Agreements with India and Burma 9. Special,    &amp;c,   Areas   Loans Provision	1st January, 1039. See Cabinet 36 (38), Conclusion 4. A Bill may be wanted when the Special Areas Acts come to an end in March, 1939. A Depart-mental Committee of which Sir Horace Wilson is Chairman is making recommendations on this subject to the Cabinet. If wide in scope the Bill might become the responsibility of the Ministry of Labour; if, however, its only provision is to extend the loan facilities, the Bill will be the responsibility of the Treasury.* See also the Ministry of Labour proposals in connection with Unemployment Insurance, in list B (ii), where it is shown under Note (6) that legislation may be required before Christmas, 1938;B (ii). Other Essential Bills.(Bills of which the principles have received recent Cabinet approval.)Department.	Bill or Subject.	remarks.Treasury Lord           Chancellors Department Home      Office      and Scottish Office India Office Scottish Office......	1. Czechoslovakia:          financial assistance to 2. Building Societies 3. Limitation 4. Criminal Justice 5. Bills to amend the Government of India Act and the Govern-ment of Burma Act in various particulars G. Marriage (Scotland)   ......	Reference Cabinet 48 (38), Con-clusion 1. The Cabinet has approved the principle of legislation (Cabinet 32 (38), Conclusion 14), the nature of which will be decided by the Cabinet Committee on Building Societies in the light of an action in the Chancery Court. The Treasury may then be responsible for the introduction of a Bill as a matter of urgency. To secure greater simplicity and uniformity in the Statutes of Limitation and to remove anomalies. In the Session now ending the Bill passed all its stages in the House of Lords, but was not proceeded with in the House of Commons. See Cabinet 23 (37), Conclusion 7, and Cabinet 17 (38), Con-clusion 11. Suitable for intro-duction in the House of Lords. Announced in the King&apos;s Speech for the 1937-38 Session. See Cabinet 4 (38), Conclusion 11, and Cabinet 29 (38), Con-elusion 8. Non-controversial. See Cabinet 50 (38), Conclusion 6. -Reference Cabinet 14 (38), Con-clusion 15. To give effect to certain recommendations of the Departmental Committee on the marriage law of Scotland. The Bill has received a first reading in the House of Commons in the Session now ending. Suitable for introduction in the House of Lords.[18126] ij 2
Department.Bill or Subject.Remarks;Board of Trade.7. Prevention of  Fraud  (Invest-ments)8. Insurance9. Cotton Industry (Enabling)10. Patents    and    Designs(Amendment)Ministry of Agriculture ill. Poultry Industryand    Fisheries    and!Scottish OfficeActsSee Cabinet 50 (38), Conclusion 10.A Bill was introduced in July,1938, and received a FirstReading in the House ofCommons. It should be pro-ceeded with early in the new session.See Cabinet 49 (38), Conclusion 15.To give effect to the recom-mendaticns of the DepartmentalCommittee on Compulsory Insur-ance (Cmd. 5528) and to certain recommendations of the earlierDepartmental Committee on theAmendment of the AssuranceCompanies Act, 1909 (Cmd.2820). See Bill No. 22 in thepresent list.See Cabinet 20 (38), Conclusion 7.The Government are committed to the introduction of a Bill, if itreceives enough support inLancashire.The Bill seeks to validate old-established practices of thePatent Office and is of someurgency. See Cabinet 34 (38),Conclusion 4. Possibly suitablefor introduction in the House ofLords.To give effect to the proposals contained in the statement bythe Ministry of Agriculture andFisheries on 11th July, 1938, inwhich it was stated that legisla-tion will be introduced as soonas possible. See Cabinet 30 (38).Conclusion 8.(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)Lord Chancellor&apos;department orTreasuryTreasuryHome OfficeAdmiraltvScottish Office12. Public Trustee General DepositFund   PR. 57 (7.13. Savings Bank14. Government Industrial Ein-ployees&apos; Superannuation15. *Air Raid Precautions (public utilities)16. Royal Marines ...17. Water and Drainage (Scotland)The Public Accounts Committeehave taken an interest in this bill, which ought to be intro-duced in 1938-39.   A hybrid Bill.Provisional on Staff Side acceptingTreasury proposals.To make statutory provision as tothe preparation of air raidprecautions schemes and thepayment of Exchequer contribu-tions to public utility under-takings.An emergency Bill, the passage ofwhich in peace time has been recommended by the War Legis-lation Sub-Committee. Toextend Section 9 of the NavalEnlistment Act, 1853, to theRoyal Marines. The Bill hasnow become urgent, in view ofthe recent emergency. It isnecessary to indemnify theAdmiralty for certain action taken on mobilisation. Shouldbe non-controversial.* Scottish Office and Ministry of Health are also interested; the latter particularly as regardsthe transfer of hospital functions to that Department from the Home Office.
Department.Bill or Subject.Remarks.Board of Trade ..Ministry of Health anilScottish office ministry of labour ministry of Transport.18. Export Guarantees Act,  1937(Amendment)19. Cancer20. Unemployment Insurance^^.5-4^^)5-.21. Restriction of Ribbon Develop-fj.     ment   Act,   1935   (Amend-ment)22. Compulsory Insurance of MotorVehiclesAn amending Bill is required inorder to extend the statutory limit of the guarantees whichmay at any time be outstanding.This limit was fixed bv the Actat  50,000,000. At tlie presenttime the aggregate liabilitiesamount to approximately 45,000,000.To impose obligation on localauthorities to make arrangementsfor diagnosis and treatment ofcancer.A Bill or Bills to amend theUnemployment Insurance Act,1935, on various points, includingthe following:  (a) To amend existing provisionsregarding the credit of contribu-tions to juveniles in Scotland.(/)) To amend the section dealingwith supplementary schemes ofUnemployment Insurance. (Thisprovision may be required before christmas, 1938.)(c) To amend the law relating tothe payment of UnemploymentBenefit in respect of holidays and suspension from work.A final decision has not beenreached with regard to the raising of the salary limit for Uneinploy-ment Insurance from  250 ayear to  400 a year, in accord-anee with the report of theUnemployment Insurance Statu-torv Committee of february,1936.May be included under the Insur-ance Bill to be introduced bv theBoard of Trade (see Bill No. 8in the present list).(C) Useful Bills, mainly Non-Controversial.(Bills of which the principles have received Cabinet approval.)Home office. ClubsScottish Office2. Deer (Scotland)3. Education (Scotland)To deal with the sale of drink in&quot; bogus &quot; clubs. This Bill(which is likely to be highly controversial) was announced inthe King&apos;s Speeches for the last,two Sessions. See Cabinet 16(38), Conclusion 9.Reference Cabinet 2 (38), Conclu-sion 8. Suitable for introduction in the House of Lords.To amend the law relating to medical inspection, feeding and clothing of school children, inScotland. Reference Cabinet 42(37), Conclusion 10.
(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)DepartmentBill or Subject.Remarks.Privy Council Office ...   4. Medical Acts AmendmentHome OfficeAdmiraltyAir MinistryScottish office ministry of Agricultureand fisheries ministry of HealthNorthern Ireland MiscellaneousProvisions6. Miners&apos; Nystagmus7. Greenwich   Hospital  Pensions8. Heston AerodromeF.R. Zl (&quot;^) lb.9. Southampton Water   ...10. Police (Scotland)       ......11. Public Health (Scotland)12. Poor Law Amendment (Scot-land)13. Law   Reform   (miscellaneous provisions) (Scotland)14. Agricultural Credits15. Diseases of Animals16. Mental Treatment17. Town and Country planning a short Bill to amend the MedicalActs (i) by simplifying theelection of direct representativemembers of the General MedicalCouncil; (ii) by making provi-sion for the registration of empire diplomas, in SanitaryScience; (iii) by providing thatamendments to the BritishPharmacopoeia shall not comeinto force until a reasonable time after their publication. The Billis asked for by the general medical Council and is expectedto be non-controversial. Suitablefor introduction in the House ofLords.To transfer the administration ofthe Lunacy Fund in NorthernIreland from the Lord chief justice to the Exchequer.To give effect to the recommenda-tions of a Departmental Commit-tee. Could be introduced inadvance of the Report of theRoyal Commission.Non-controversial. To confer uponGreenwich Hospital the powers which the Superannuation(Various Services) Act, 193S,conferred upon other public bodies.To close three roads which atpresent cross the area purchasedfor the extension of the aero-drome.To reserve an area of water for the exclusive use of flying boats atthe Empire Flying Boat Base.To facilitate the voluntary con-solidation of police forces inScotland and to amend thelaw relating to police.To deal with infectious clistuberculosis, ambulances andlaboratories, atmospheric pollu-tion, and camping.To give effect to the recommenda-tions of the Committees onvagrancy and settlement.Bill to make miscellaneous amend-ments of the Scottish Law.(Minor legislation amendingSection 17 of the Improvementof Land Act, 1864, might beincluded.)To improve the facilities for long-term and short-term credit forfarmers. Possibly non-eonten-tious.To facilitate the establishment ofEradication Areas, by amendingPart IV of the Agriculture Act,1937.   Possibly non-contentious.Amendment of Lunacy and MentalTreatment Acts. To be followedby Consolidation Bill see List F.Minor amendment of Town and country Planning Act, 1932.
Department.Bill or Subject. Remarks.Treasury ...      ....   1. Hall-marking of foreign plate; See Cabinet 50 (38), Conclusion 8.(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)Home Office    ......Scottish     Office     and ministry of HealthScottish Office......Ministry of Agricultureand Fisheries2. Adoption Societies bill . Wild birds protection4. Marriage5. Feu Duties and Long Leases(Scotland)6. Improvement of Land (Scot-land)7. Custody of Children (Scotland)S. Salmon (Scotland)9. Rabbits10. Fuel allotment.........To facilitate marriage in caseswhere one party resides in Scot-land and the other in England.To   amend   Section   17   of   theImprovement of Land Act, 1804.A possibility.(E) Bills not yet ready, or Bills required in Certain Events.(E) (i). Bills which in Certain Events will become Urgent or Essential.*(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)Board of Trade.1. Insurance of British shipping and Cargoes in Time of War2. Canadian-Australasian line.Assistance   toIndustrythe   Shipping4&quot;. Coal Export trade  Bill may be required to authorise a permanent partnership agree-ment for the insurance of shipsagainst King&apos;s Enemy Risks; todeal with the insurance of cargoes in time of war; and todeal with compensation to sea-men in respect of death or injury or loss of effects.To implement the proposed arrange-ment with Canada, Australia andNew Zealand to assist the build-ing of two new liners. It is not likely that the ships will be ordered until shipbuilding costsfall substantially.Representations from the industry may be expected early in 1939,or perhaps earlier as regardstramp shipping.Proposals by the coal industry for assisting their export trade bymeans of a levy on output are under consideration. If theGovernment decide that pro-posals on these lines should beadopted, legislation in 1938-39may be necessary (though itmight be possible to proceed byOrder under the Coal Mines Act,1930). The Cabinet are aware of the proposals (Cabinet 34 (38),Conclusion 2).* In the event of an emergency it would become necessary to pass into law at short notice aconsiderable number of Bills.  These are not included in the lists in Annexes I and II.(D) Bills Suitable for Introduction by Private Members.(Bills of which the principles have received recent Cabinet approval.)
(Bill of which the principles have received recent Cabinet approval.)Department.	Bill or Subject.	Remarks.Ministry of Transport...	1. Road Haulage Rates...... 1	To put into effect the broad principles of a Report by the Transport Advisory Council, in accordance with an announce-ment made in February, 1938. See Cabinet 3 (38)*, Con-clusion 11.(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)		Treasury Home Office Colonial Office ... Air Ministry Scottish Office.......	2. Income Tax Codification 3. Medicine Stamp Duties 4. Redistribution  ... 5. Welsh Burial Grounds... 6. Colonial    Development    Act, 1929 (Amendment) 7. Colonial Service Pensions 8. Precautionary   arrest   of   air-craft 9. Highlands and Islands	May be ready either for 1938-39 or for 1939-40. It is possible that legislation will be required in 1938-39 to deal with these duties, which were the subject of a report by a Select Committee in February 1937. If legislation is to be introduced it is as yet uncertain whether it will be included in the Finance Bill of the vear or in a separate Bill. It is not yet known whether a Redistribution Bill will be required. To transfer the Welsh burial grounds, at present vested in the Welsh Church Commission, to the Representative Budy of the Church in Wales. Inquiries are being made as to the possibility of obtaining agreement for a Bill of this character. In the absence of agreement it would probably not be practicable to proceed with it, and the indications at present are that agreement is unlikely. Early legislation will be needed in the event of the proposals of a Departmental Committee, now sitting, being accepted. Proposals have been made to Colonial Governments that a central fund should be consti-tuted by Act of Parliament to provide for pensions to widows and orphans of officers of the Unified Branches of the Colonial Service. If Colonial Govem-ments generally accept the scheme it will be desirable that it should be brought into opera-tion as early as possible. To enable effect to be given to the Rome Convention of 1933 on Precautionary Arrest of Aircraft (e.g., in satisfaction of a creditor &apos;s claim). Administration     and     economic	10. Church of Scotland (Property and Endowments) (Amend-ment)	development.E (ii). Other Bills not yet Ready.
Department.Scottish Office (contd.)Board of Trade...Ministry of labour ministry of Transport.General Post OfficeBill or Subject.11. Probation (Scotland)12. Weights and Measures18. Closure of the Clearing Office(Enemy Debts)14. Regulation    of    wages    andconditions15. Road Traffic Acts (Amendment)1G. Road Accidents ......17. Wireless Telegraphy.Remarks.Amendment and consolidation.See Criminal Justice Bill in list B (ii).To legalise the use of milk bottlesas measures. Suitable for intro-duction in the House of Lords.Among other objects, the bill would appoint time limits forclaims in respect of property, &amp;c,under the Treaty of Peace Orders.Measures relating to the retaildistributive trades and to thecotton industry may possibly benecessary.Minor amendments.To give effect to the recommenda-tions of the Transport AdvisoryCouncil with regard to cyclists,especially if they are supportedby the Select Committee of theHouse of Lords on the Preven-tion of Road Accidents. further legislation may also be requiredto give effect to other recommen-dations by the Select Committee.(F) Consolidation Bills.(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval,)Air Ministry.   ...Scottish Office s.?.-9(3^eMinistry of HealthGeneral Post office. Bill or Bills to consolidate theAir Navigation Acts, 1920and 19302. Local  Government  (Scotland)3. Education (Scotland).4. Mental Treatment Consoli-dation5. Water6. Post Office Consolidation.May be required.Amendment and consolidation.To follow Mental Treatment Billin List (C).Consolidation with minor amend-ments.
APPENDIX III.1939-40 Session.Government Legislative Programme^List of Bills furnished by Departments.(A) Annual or Compulsory Bills.(B) Other Essential or Useful Bills, or Bills required in certain events.(C) Consolidation Bills.(A) Annual or Compulsory Bills.Department.jTreasury ...      ... I 1.I 4.I .o.! 0.War   Office    and    Air : 7.MinistryBill or Subject.Expiring   Laws   Continuance,1939Consolidated Fund, 1940Consolidated Fund (Appropria-tion), 1940Public Works Loans, 1939 or1940Finance, 1940 ...Isle of Man Customs, 1940 ...Army and Air Force (Annual)Required by.Christmas, 1939.March, 1940.Summer, 1940.Christmas, 1939, or March, 1940.Summer, 1940.Summer, 1940.30th April, 1940.(B) Other Essential or Useful Bills, or Bills required in Certain Events.(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)Department.remarks.Home OfficeTndia office. Police Courts (^Metropolis)&apos;2. Shops Acts Amendmenti 3. Police Grant4. Celluloid...;&quot;). Coroners ...6. Amalgamation      of      SmallBorough Police Forces7. Draft Address to be submitted. to both Houses of Parlia-government for approval on thesubject of the Proclamationon the inauguration j ofFederationTo give effect to the recommenda-tions of a Departmental Com-mittee for the reorganisation ofthe work of the Courts of summary Jurisdiction in London.To make minor amendments of the shops Acts and possibly toamend the law as to Sundaytrading.To put the Exchequer grant in aid of local police expenditure on a statutory basis.To  implement   the   recommenda-tions of a Departmental Com-mittee   for   preventing   dangerfrom celluloid toys, &amp;c.To amend the law as to Coroners&apos;Inquests.To provide for the merger of smallborough   forces   in  the  countyforces.The necessity for this is stillremote.* Duplication between this list and that for 1938-39 has been avoided, i.c, if a Bill appears in the list for 1938-39, it will not be found in the present list. It will be appreciated, however,that there may be an urgent necessity for the passage into law in 1939-40 of a Bill which fails to reach the Statute Book in 1938-39.
Department.Remarks.Air MinistryScottish office board of Trade.8. Military Lands Acts Amend -ment9. Poor Persons Representation(Scotland)10. Agricultural Holdings (Scot-land) Amendment I11. Coal Mines Act, 1911 (Amend-ment)12. Bill to deal with holding com-panies controlling public-utility bodiesMinistry of Agriculture j 13. Agricultural    Marketing   Actsand Fisheries (Amendment)14. Agricultural Returns Act, 1925(Amendment)Ministry of Transport..15. Allotments16. Improvement of Livestock   ...17. Commons Regulation ...18. Electricity SupplyA possibility. To simplify the pro-cedure for imposing restrictivecovenants on lands adjoiningRoyal Air Force aerodromes, andto enable bye-laws to be madefor coastal bombing areas uponwhich a land bombing area doesnot abut.It will be necessary to await thethe Report of the Royal Commis-sion on Safety and Health in coal Mines. It is possible thatthe Royal Commission will report before the end of 1938.The Chairman of Committees inthe House of Lords has suggestedthat a Joint Select Committeeshould be appointed to considerthe question, but it is unlikelythat a Bill will be ready in1939-40. (It is not certain,although it is probable, that theBoard of Trade would beresponsible for the Bill.)Probably necessary as a result ofthe report of the Falmouth Com-mittee on Imposition of Penaltiesby Marketing Boards.To extend the powers relating tothe collection and utilisation ofagricultural statistics.To give effect to certain recom-mendations of the AllotmentsAdvisory Committee. Suitablefor introduction by a private member.To amend the law with respect tothe licensing of bulls, stallionsand boars.Probably non-contentious in themain.On 27th October, 1937, the Ministerof Transport was authorised toprepare a Bill (Cabinet 39 (37),Conclusion 16). See, however,Cabinet Conclusions of 6th Julv,1938 (Cabinet 31 (3S), Conclu-sion 14), which read as follows :  &quot; The Cabinet approved theconclusions and recommendationsof the Cabinet Committee as setforth in CP. 151 (38) and summarised above.1 &apos;** The Cabinet Committee referred to had been invited to &quot; advise the Cabinet as to whetherthe Bill should be proceeded with in the forthcoming Session of Parliament, giving special consideration to the advantages and disadvantages of this course from a political point of view.&quot;At the end of their Report the Cabinet Committee summarised their Conclusions andRecommendations as follows:  &quot; (a) In spite of the need for the reorganisation of electricity distribution, the proposed bill should not be introduced in the&apos;last year of the present Parliament;(b) Any interim measure to prevent the worsening of the present position of theelectricity distribution industry would be open to many of the same. objections as a majorBill for the reorganisation of the industry, and to some of them in a more acute, form;(c) No further statement..should be. made for the . present. as. to - the: Gov.erniiienti&apos;s&apos; intentions in. regard to legislation, but .the matter, should be lefi in _ab.eya.nqe uhtjlt the. ,:autumn.&quot;!l1&apos;v&quot;&quot;i-&quot;J;;&apos;, j^n^j -      *&apos; *^,J;.c..V f siti     VJlijW^io? JaajjiVs ita ad vroi -mitt cabinet
Department.Bill or Subject.Remarks.Ministry   of   Transport(co ntd.)19. London Passenger Transport20. Raihvav Works ...A Bill may be required extending the scope of the london passenger Transport (Agree-ment) Act, 1935, or providingfor a further programme ofworks on somewhat similar lines.A possibility. To inaugurate afurther programme of railwayworks on the completion of thepresent programme.(C) Consolidation Bills.(Bills of which the principles have not received recent Cabinet approval.)Scottish Office ...1. Lunacv and Mental Deficiency(Scotland)2. Public Health (Scotland) Con-solidation.3. Housing (Scotland) Consolida-tion.Amendment and Consolidation.

</content>
</cab>
