<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/40/0 images: 21-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (52)  83rd Conclusions(1st October, 1952 - 11.0 euro.)THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that H.R.H.  the duke of Edinburgh was anxious to learn to fly, and provisionalarrangements had been made for&apos;him to receive elementary flying training at an air-field near London under the guidance of a royal Air Force instructor.    It was not intended that he shouldlearn to fly jet aircraft or undergo the full training course ofa Royal Air Force pilot, but he would be trained to a standardwhich would enable.him to fly his own aircraft with safety.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he felt grave doubts about this proposal.    It was arguable that,  in view of his publicposition and responsibilities, His Royal Highness should notexpose himself to unnecessary risks.    Once the training nowproposed had been completed, he might be tempted to take the much greater risk of learning to fly jet aircraft.    And, once hewas a qualified pilot,  he might wish to pilot aircraft in whichthe Queen was a passenger.    THE COMMONYffiALTH SECRETARY andTHE LORD PRIVY SEAL supported the views expressed by the PrimeMinister.Other Ministers thought it unnecessary to raise objection to the proposal.    It v/as pointed out that King G-eorge VI(when Prince Albert) had earned his wings as a pilot in theRoyal Air Force in the first world war;    and that the Dukes of Windsor, Gloucester and Kent had all learned to fly in the period between  the two wars.    Flying was now widely regarded as a normalmeans of transport;    and young men who were in a position to learn to fly thought it little more hazardous than learning to drive a motor-car.    It would certainly be a great disappointmentto His Royal Highness, and to the Royal Air Force, if he wereprevented from fulfilling his wish to learn to fly.
THE ERIME MINISTER said that, in view of this division of&apos; opinion, he would discuss the matter with the duke of Edinburgh during his forthcoming visit to Balmoral,and would if necessary bring it up again at a later date forfurther consideration by the Cabinet.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1, ,3RD OCTOBER, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
