<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/40/0 images: 53-56</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.48It is issued for the personal use of...&apos;top secret- cabinet copy No.CONFIDENTIAL ANNEXG.C.(54) 48th Conclusions ( /w- i](8th July, 1954 - 11. 30 a. m.)I WASHINGTON&amp;TALKSif (previous reference:gC.C;(54) 47thI Conclusions,Minute 4)proposed meeting with&apos;M. MalenkovTHE PRIME MINISTER said that earlier that morning hehad received President Eisenhower&apos;s reply to his message aboutthe possibility of a bilateral meeting with M. Malenkovj    Thiswas,read to the Cabinet (Washington telegram No. 1406).    ThePrime Minister said that he hoped that, if further explanationswere given, a more favourable response might be elicited fromthe President;  and he read to the Cabinet the text of a further message whifch he was proposing to send to him (Foreign office telegram to Washington Not 3228).    He suggested that the cabinet should take no final decision until a further expression of the presidents views was available.    He made it clear, however, thathe would not be disposed to accept an invitation to meet m. Malenkov in Moscow.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that in the draft message to the President reference was made to the possibilityof a meeting at Stockholm or Vienna.    He hoped that the PrimeMinister would also mention the possibility of a meeting at Berne.He himself believed that the meeting might have quite a differenteffect on opinion abroad if it were held at Berne immediately afterthe end of the Geneva Conference.    This, in his view, would bemore than a geographical difference.    It would seem much morenatural that he and M. Molotov should go from Geneva to Berne,at the end of the Conference, in order to confer there with thePrime Minister and M. Malenkov.    THE PRIME minister agreed to include, in his message to the President, a referenceto the possibility of a meeting at Berne.THE PRIME MINISTER said that some of his colleaguesmight think that the Cabinet should have been consulted before hehad sent to M. Molotov the personal and private message embodied in Foreign Office telegram to Moscow No. 873.    It had been hispractice as Prime Minister, both during the war and since thepresent Government took office, to exchange personal messageswith Heads of Governments and more particularly with thePresident of the United States.    Most of these messages had been seen before despatch by the Foreign Secretary, who could alwayssuggest that reference should be made to the Cabinet if he thought this necessary.    The Prime Minister hoped that he would continueto enjoy the confidence of his colleagues in continuing a practice which,, in his opinion, had proved beneficial in the conduct ofpublic affairs.
THE LORD PRESIDENT said that he was glad that this,opportunity had been given to discuss the constitutional aspectsof this matter.    He did not contest the right of a Prime Ministerto determine policy.    But, if a Prime Minister took a&apos; decision ofpolicy which involved the collective responsibility of the wholeGovernment without prior consultation With his Cabinet colleagues,any.of his colleagues who dissented from the decision mightthereby be forced to the remedy of resignation.    The message which the Prime Minister had sent to M. Molotov, though framed as a personal enquiry, was in his opinion an important act of  -foreign policy;  and it would have been preferable that the cabinet should have been given an opportunity to express their views on it before it was sent.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that he also regarded this as an important act of policy, on which the Cabinet should havebeen consulted. For, although it was presented as a personalenquiry, it was bound to commit the Government to some extentto the view that this was an opportune moment for a meeting ofthe kind suggested. For his part, if his view had been sought,he would have been inclined to advise against making such an .approach at the present time.. THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that a distinction couldbe drawn between an informal enquiry and a formal proposal fora meeting.    The latter could clearly not have been made withoutthe approval of the Cabinet.    But he had not thought that theCabinet would be in any way committed by a personal and preliminary enquiry; and he had understood that the foreign secretary, whom he had consulted, was of the same opinion.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY recalled that a draft of the message had been sent to the Chancellor of the Exchequer, andit had been in his mind at the time that the Chancellor would bring it to the notice of his Cabinet colleagues.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUEP. said that thedraft had reached him during the afternoon of Saturday, 3rd July,when he was in Norfolk.  - The telegram embodying it had been addressed to him personally, and copies had at that stage biJen showonly to senior officials in the Foreign Office and to the PrimeMinisters Private Secretaries at 10 Downing Street.    Therewas nothing in the telegram to suggest that the views of theCabinet were being invited.    Indeed, before he had been able to despatch his own comments, which he had formulated after discussion with senior Foreign Office officials, a further telegram had been received from the Prime Minister enquiringwhether the message had been transmitted to Moscow.    This had confirmed his view that he had not been expected to invite theviews of other Cabinet colleagues&apos; - and it would in any eventhave been very difficult for him to do so when Ministers were dispersed at the week-end.THE LORD PRESIDENT said that the message had been dispatched to Moscow on 4th July.    The Prime Minister and theForeign Secretary had arrived in London on 6th July and could then have held full consultation with their Cabinet colleagues.Was the message so urgent that its despatch could not havebeen delayed for three days ?
THE PRIME MINISTER said that, in his anxiety to loseno opportunity of furthering the cause of world peace, he mighthave taken an exaggerated view of the urgency of the matter.There had seemed no reason to delay what he regarded as a personal and informal enquiry which could not commit hiscolleagues.THE COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that in his view the constitutional position was clear.    A Prime minister was certainly free to conduct unofficial personal correspondence with Heads of other Governments.    But, equally, in suchcorrespondence a Prime Minister would take care to avoid committing the Cabinet to any act of policy without their prior approval.    The practical question was whether any particularmessage, sent in the course of such personal correspondence,had the effect of committing the Cabinet.    Though it was clearthat this had not been intended on the present occasion, had itproduced this effect?THE LORD PRESIDENT said that in his opinion the cabinet&apos;s freedom of action had to some extent been limited bythe message which the Prime Minister had sent.    When theCabinet came to take a decision on the substance of the issue,they might wish to decide that it would be preferable not to go forward with this project for a meeting with M. Malenkov.    But,if they so decided, and if the Russians then chose to givepublicity to the messages exchanged between the Prime Ministerand M. Molotov, the public would be left with the impression thatthe Prime Minister had wished to arrange such a meeting but had been deterred from doing so by his Cabinet colleagues.That consideration might now influence the Cabinefs eventualdecision.THE COLONIAL SECRETARY said that the constitutional position was as stated by the Commonwealth Secretary.     Thepractical question was v/hether the collective responsibility of theCabinet had in any way been involved by the informal approach which the Prime Minister had made to M. Molotov.    For himselfhe did not think it could be denied that it was now more difficult for the Cabinet to decide that this was not an appropriate moment for a bilateral meeting of the kind suggested in that message.Nevertheless, he thought it was still open to the Cabinet todecide not to proceed further with this project.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed with this view.     Itmight well be that, when President Eisenhower had replied tohis further message, he would be convinced that it would be preferable not to proceed further with this project.    In that event he Would not feel obliged to give M. Molotov any detailedreasons for his decision.    It would suffice to thank him again for his cordial message and to say that we did not think it
practicable to proceed further with this project at the presenttime.    This, however, must be left for consideration in thelight of a further expression of the Presidents views.The Cabinet -Agreed to resume their discussion of thisquestion when President Eisenhower had replied to the further message which thePrime Minister now proposed to send him.Cabinet Office, S.W.i.10th July, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
