<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/40/0 images: 83-85</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINET

MOST CONFIDENTIAL RECORD

C.C.(57) 64th Conclusions, Minute 1

(6th September, 1957 - 3.15 p.m.)

Syria (Previous Reference: C.C. (57) 63rd Conclusions, Minute 7)

The Cabinet had before them a note by the Prime Minister on the situation in Syria, together with Foreign Office telegram No. 3370 of 28th August to Washington and telegrams No. 1728 and 1729 of 5th September from Washington.

THE PRIME MINISTER informed the Cabinet that, in the light of their earlier discussion of this situation, he had sent a personal message to the United States Secretary of State, Mr. Dulles, outlining the implications of the alternative policies of retrieving the situation by direct intervention or attempting to contain it by preventing Communist infiltration from spreading beyond the borders of Syria. Mr. Dulles had subsequently made it clear that, in the opinion of the United States Government, a policy of containment would be liable to be ineffective and that, unless more effective steps could be taken to remedy the situation, Syria&apos;s immediate neighbours would probably fall in rapid succession, while Turkey would be left in a dangerously isolated position. He therefore inclined to the view that action should be taken now to retrieve the situation before it was too late, despite the difficulties and dangers which such action would involve. He intended to discuss this proposal with President Eisenhower on the following day and had asked for a very early indication of our views.

There could be no question of the Cabinet&apos;s reaching a final decision on this matter at the present time. It would first be necessary to obtain from H.M. representatives in the countries concerned an independent assessment of resent developments in the Middle East, and to explore in greater detail with the United States Government the form of the action which might be taken and the possible


TOP SSSRSTconsequences for the Wests It would be isspoiJtsntj however, that these discussions should not reflect any reluctance en our part to takeadvantage of this opportunity to establish betssssn the United Statesend ourselves a ussity of policy and action in the Middle Easts Suchan opportuniiy might not recur for a vexy long time and it would be unwise to neglect it, provided that the implications of the actionenvisaged had been thoroughly explored in e&amp;vssce       that both governments were convinced of the wisdom of tbs  cdh$ palicyaMr* !&amp;uHesi appeared to be acting at the moment largely cn his &amp;minitiativej   and it was not clear how far Ms policy would eossaBdthe approval of President ELsenteowsa?&apos; and the support of his colleagues in the United States Goveraments  2t was important, therefore 9 toestablish v&amp;iether President Eisenhower was prepared to endorse thispolicy with his personal authority,). In&apos; discussion there was general agreement that it was becoming increasingly urgent to arrest fee process of Sovietsubversion in the Middle East.  Recent experience had9 however, shewathat it was difficult for a democracy to iraolflsaait its policy by forcewithout incurring the eondoanation of world opinion!   end the UnitedStates Government should not be encouraged to suppose that an act of intervention, in Syria would be accepted by the United nations asreadily as they appeared to expect.  Moreover, it would be important to agree with the United States Government the ultimate objective ofany action to retrieve the situation in Syria and the form of thepermanent settlement of the Middle East which should result from suchaction.   In any event it might be desirable that, as a preliminary,the Middle Eastern States should be encouraged and assisted toestablish a egrdiqn embassy&amp;tgirq round Syria, and that Hur&amp;wes-Ssld ghoulcif possible, resume the leadership of the Government of Iraq,.  Thesituation might be further reinforced if the United States could be persuaded to become a full  Bember of the Bagdad Past. If and when itTOP SBC8SC
was agreed that further action should be undertaken, it would be necessary to consider carefully the occasion and the means, and the possible reaction of the Soviet Union. It would also be necessary to decide how far it would be expedient that the United Kingdom should be actively involved.

THE PRIME MINSTER said that, in the light of this preliminary discussion, he would send a further message to Mr. Dulles indicating that, if his proposals represented the approved policy of the United States Government, we ourselves would be disposed in principle to support them, but that, before the Cabinet could be expected to reach a firm decision, it would be necessary for them to be explored in more detail. United Kingdom representatives would be ready to proceed to Washington for this purpose in the near future. It might subsequently be desirable that he should himself discuss the matter with President Elsenhower.

The Cabinet -

(1) Took note that the Prime Minister would send a further message to the United States Secretary of State on the lines which he had indicated.

(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for H.M. representatives in the countries concerned to be instructed to furnish, as a matter of urgency, their own appreciation of recent developments in Syria and the probable consequences if no action was taken to arrest the increasing Soviet penetration of that country.

(3) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to consider how far, and at what point, it would be desirable to consult certain other members of the Commonwealth on this matter.

Cabinet Office, S.W.1.

7th September, 1957



</content>
</cab>
