<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/94 images: 544-547</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)SECRET Copy No.     L\7/.P.G.  (40) 2947th November 1940WAR   CABINETOVERSEAS AIR COIvMUNICATIOHSMemorandum by the Minister of Information.The deterioration of air transport facilities has virtuallydenied the Ministry of Inf ornaation two of the most immediate andcompelling forms of propaganda.   Nothing can replace a steady andprompt service of newspapers and of newsreels.     A trickle of this    jmaterial arriving weeks or months late has a disastrous effect. Ishould therefore like to support most strongly any programme of overseas air development put f forward &quot;by the Air Ministry which might help us to repair this gap in our effort.2.     The interests of the Ministry of Information are closely alliedwith those of the General Post Office,  and the despatches of Empireand other Press correspondents are an important hut not &quot;bulkyaddition to the air mail.    I think it, however, desirable to placeon record the minimum freight requirements for our own material whichwe should wish to be added to those requirements mentioned by thePostmaster General.   These are briefly of the following orderUnited Kingdom - Lisbon 6,000 kilograms per weekUnited Kingdom - Cairovia Lagos 450 &quot; &quot;     &quot;United Kingdom - Stockholm 230        &quot; &quot;     &quot;In addition a service between Egypt and the Balkans is of special importance.   The large amount asked for on the Lisbon route is toenable us to take full advantage of the Trade Agreement with Spainas well as for pro )aganda purposes in Portugal: it represents a large increase on our existing allocation, which in any case it is vital tomaintain.   The Ambassadors have frequently urged us strongly toincrease our efforts in this direction, to which they attach thegreatest importance.3.     The above particulars are based on known requirements today butit should be borne in mind that propaganda in its various forms tends to grow and therefore we should hope that our needs will from time totime be met under the Secretary of State for Air&apos;s proposals.4.     I should like also to draw attention to the question of priority.The material sent by air is part of a planned programme. Newsreels and. newspapers must be in regular continuous supply. Any break in the seriesat once arouses suspicion and largely destroys their value. It istherefore essential to accord to them a high priority such as willguarantee their regular reception.7th November 1940Initialled D.C;




</content>
</cab>
