<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/16/0 images: 392-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
GIBRALTAR CSUTA COMITTEE*

(letter from l.S. Amery to Lord Curzon 10/5/1917.)

10/5/1917

Dear Lord Corson,

I think: you will be interested in the enolosed note of a talk I hod with a very intelligent and well-informed Frenchman yesterday.   The point of view about Spanish Morocco was new to me, and I don*t see much probability of the Spaniards being induoedto clear out by concessions elsewhere. But apart from that, the Branch desire to have unified control in that regioin seems to me natural and one that does not directly conflict with our interests.   My real difficulty is, if we hold geuta the enclave will be so small that the French could probably, turn us out any time they wanted to.   Small places a* e not going to be easily defensible in future, and if anything on&apos;those lines were done I am sure that we ought not to insist on retaining not only Ceuta but Tangier and Tetuan with a frontier right across the Peninsula, This, it might be said, at once means a much larger garrison than we have been accustomed to at Gibraltar.   As a matter of fact it need not mean anything of the sort as long as we are on good terms with Franco.     If we once are on bad terms we shall want large forces wherever we have frontiers with her, not only round Ceuta but in Nigeria, Gold Coast, etc.

As regards the Syrian question, It looks as if the failure of Russia practically puts French ambitions In that quarter out of the field altogether at any rate unless there should be an entirely new and favourable turn in Russian affairs.   The real question is whether we can still secure our minimum, viz. Palestine.   Robertson&apos;s paper just circulated on the military effeot of Russia1s secession seems to me unduly pessimistic on that topic.   I do believe we could at the least drive the Turk north of Jerusalem and probably to the Plain of Megiddo.     It would not be wholly Inappropriate if this great Armageddon ended on that historic battle-ground from which the word is derived.

2,

Whitehall Gardens, 3.H.

(sd) L.3. Jancry.


336

GIBRALTAR CEUTA COMMITTEE. 11

I had a talk this afternoon with M. Phillippe Millet, son of. &apos;a former Govenor-General of Algeria, formerly correspondent of the &quot;Temps&quot; and very much in the Inner circles of French C&lt;xlonlal ,?olitlos.   He raised the question of possible territorial arrangements with France, e.g. Gambia, St Pierre and Miquelon, etc. But after . &quot;beating about the bush a little said that in his view by far the most important Colonial question for France was to get rid of Spain in Northern Morocco.   Hot only 13 Morocco in his view more important to France than any other colonial possession can be, because it is really an exteation of that new France on the South of the Mediterranean of which Algeria was the beginning, but also administration was made extremely difficult owing to thefact that the tribes, did what they ldked on the territory nominally,subject to Spain and continually raided over the &quot;border.   From that point of view he was very anxious that the Spanish claim to Tangia should not be recognised but the situation kept in 3tatu quo till after the war when Spain might be bought out by some substantial concession elsewhere, e.g. a slice of the Cameroons adjoining their present colony.   He said he fully realised our natural anxiety to have no interference with the control of the Straits of Gibraltar, and as far as he was concerned he was quite willing that we should hold Ceuta as well as Gibraltar and to give guarantees against the fortifications of Tangia, provided onl$ that France could have the rest of this territory which shut off her part of Moroooo from its natural access to the sea.   He did notaqggpet the possibility of any bargain between us and Spain by which we. shoul d take Ceuta in exchange for Gibraltar, and I did not hint at it.

He said that this was Ms view and that If Lyautey and others who had studied the subject, but he did not think that the French Foreign Office had really given it much thought, while French Colonial, opinion had been much more ocoupied with the question of SjTia to which he attached loss importance in view of the fact that it was much further from France and could never become an integral part of France in the sense in which this might become true of Morocco. We touched on the question of Palestine, and I said that, speaking for myself, I should like to see Great Britain in control of Palestine beoause without it it would be extremely difficult to secure any tolerable reilway communication between Egypt and Mesopotamia. Apart from that, I wa^/ln favour of the French having the very largest possible extent of Syria, and made it clear that the British view was that we AoulSL welcome the French in Syria as partners in resisting any attempt on the part of the Germans to push down from Asia Minor. He seemed to welcome the idea and from the way he spoke we was either completely unaware, or pretended to be so, of the Sykes-Pioot agreement.   For Instance, he was quite interested and exoited at the thought that the French Sphere might extend to Alexahdretta, and I said that we had always regarded Alexandretta as a possible entrance for us to the Eastern florid, but that if we could get our through connection from Egypt via Palestine we did not want another entrance. He has been asked by the French Committee of Syria to draw up &amp; system, of government based on the largest 4r &apos;.   . possible measure of autonomy, and he will no doubt convey my views about Palestine to them.   I laid stress on my views being purely personal and based not on the desire to enlarge our territory or diminish France^ share but on the need for effective communication with Mesopotamia.   -

I also took the opportunity of his referring to the Arms TraffLo from Spanish Morocco into French territory to tell him that we had a grievance against France in connection with the Jibuti Arms Traffic, and when he mentioned the Cameroons I told him that we regarded the   present partition as one in which we had made enormous sacrifices to WFrance and expected something in the nature of compensation elsewhere if the provisional partition were made permanent.

(ad) L.S. Amery

2, Whitehall Gardens,&apos;S.W. 8th May 1917,



</content>
</cab>
