<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/270/0 images: 623-635</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
y345B C R E T.I circulate for the consideration of my colleagues a recommendation from the Committee of Imperial Defence that new formulae, to cover defensive preparations in the Mediterranean and Red Sea, should be anproved in substitution for those adopted on the 24th February last (Cabinet 9 (37), Conclusion 4,  and C.I.D- Paper No.l332-B).,P. 183 (57).CABIN E T.THE MEDITERRANEAN.ASSUMPTIONS TO GOVERN DEFENSIVE PREPARATIONS.Draft Note by the Minister for Co-ordinationof Defence.(Intd.)   T.W.H.I., Whitehall Gardens, S.W.19th July, 1937.
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   July 1937.SECRET. Copy No.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the DRAFT Minutes of the 296 A Meeting, held on 5th July, 1937.(1) THE   MEDITERRANEAN:   ASSUMPTIONS TO  GOVERN DEFENSIVE PREPARATIONS.(C.I.D. Paper No. 1332-B.)(Previous reference : C.I.D. Minutes of the 290th Meeting, Minute 6, and295th Meeting, Minute 4.)THE COMMITTEE had under consideration a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs concerning the probability of war with Italy (C.I.D. Paper No. 1332-B), discussion of which had been adjourned at the 295th Meeting.SIR THOMAS INSKIP, at the request of the Prime Minister, summarised the discussion which had taken place at the previous Meeting. The main point at issue had been whether it was necessary or desirable to lay down as a definite proposition the formula suggested by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that &quot; Italy cannot be considered as a reliable friend and must for an indefinite period be regarded as a possible enemy, especially if she can count on the goodwill and potential support of Germany, or if the United Kingdom were involved in difficulties elsewhere.&quot;The Chief of Naval Staff had informed the Committee that the Joint Planning Committee were engaged in the preparation of an appreciation of the strategical situation in the Mediterranean, Middle East and North-East Africa in a war with Italy on three hypotheses, namely : (i) A unilateral war with Italy.(ii) A war in alliance with France and Belgium against Germany and Italy, (iii) A war in alliance with France and Belgium against Germany, Italy and Japan, with Russia neutral; or, alternatively, with Russia as an ally. -    (I&apos;.: ^ . - l: c :;&apos;j&apos;;cT.  A -It had been suggested that consideration of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s Memorandum might be deferred until this appreciation was available for examination, but it had been urged, on the other hand, that a formula of some sort defining our defensive policy vis-a-vis Italy was necessary in order to provide a basis for planning.THE PRIME MINISTER observed that it had been laid down as a corollary to the existing formula that &quot; no very large expenditure should be incurred on increasing the defences of &quot; the Mediterranean and Red Sea ports. He presumed that the Staffs would wish to know whether that instruction still held good or not.LORD CHATFIELD agreed, and pointed out that the question resolved itself very largely into one of priorities. There were limitations to our industrial production, and a decision would have to be taken whether our present programmes were to be modified in order to provide increased security in the Mediterranean against Italy. No doubt the Chiefs of Staff would be required ultimately to submit to the Committee their recommendations on this question. [15524-1] B
Mr. EDEN agreed that ultimately a report of this nature would be required, but he suggested that the immediate question was whether we were not at present working on a formula which did not accurately state the position as it existed. It was true that, even if the present formula were modified, the Chiefs of Staff might recommend no change in our present programmes, but the Foreign Office wished to ensure that the Committee of Imperial Defence was not working on false premises with regard to Italy.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that, as a matter,, of practical politics, the question was to what extent we should make preparations to meet the contingency of war with Italy. Fie doubted whether it was necessary to place on record in specific terms that Italy.&quot; must for an indefinite period be regarded as a possible enemy.&quot; Such action on the part of the Committee of Imperial Defence was, he thought, quite unprecedented. He recalled that it had been laid down by the Cabinet in 1933 that &quot; No expenditure should for the present be incurred on measures of defence required to provide exclusively against attack by the United States, France, or Italy.&quot; Would not it meet the Foreign Office&apos; point of view if Italy were merely excluded from the above list instead of being specifically labelled as a probable enemy for an indefinite period ? It was possible, however, that the Staffs might wish to have some more precise guidance regarding defence preparations against Italy.Mr. EDEN thought that it would be only right to place Italy in the same category as Germany it would be grotesque to omit Italy from any list of probable enemies at the present time. He asked in what category Germany stood now.SIR MAURICE HANKEY said that by a process of exclusion Japan, Germany and Russia were left as the principal possible enemies, although they were not specifically described as &quot; probable &quot; enemies.SIR THOMAS INSKIP enquired whether there was any distinction between &quot; probable enemies &quot; and &quot; possible enemies.&quot; Presumably all countries except the United States and France were to be considered as &quot; possible enemies.&quot; He considered that most important thing to do was to assess the relative priorities of defence preparations against possible enemies.SIR SAMUEL HO ARE agreed that it would be only right to place Italy in the same category as Germany, but he concurred in the view that this should be done by implication, rather than specifically in a definite formula.Mr. MALCOLM MacDONALD also agreed in this view. He disliked the idea of a definite formula for Italy or Germany, since the logical conclusion then would be to have a formula for every country.LORD ZETLAND emphasised that the present formula regarding Italy did not represent the facts of the situation. He referred to Italy&apos;s hostile attitude towards us in the Arab countries and particularly in the Yemen. This attitude might cause us considerable trouble in connection with Palestine. There could be no doubt that Italy was at present definitely hostile to us owing to her ambitions in the Near East.Mr. ORMSBY GORE said that as Secretary of State for the Colonies he could only support the representations of Lord Zetland. The position in the neighbourhood of Aden and in the Red Sea as a result of present Italian policy was very serious.Mr. EDEN said that his main concern was to modify the existing formula, which was undoubtedly incorrect.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the formula might read as follows :- &quot; Italy cannot be considered as a reliable friend and must be omitted from the decision of the Cabinet of the 15th November, 1933, which says : &apos; No expenditure should for the present be incurred on measures of defence required to provide exclusively against attack by the United ,   .   States, France or Italy.&apos; &quot;
At the time that decision had been made Italy was considered as a reliable friend, whereas Germany had never been so considered. He asked whether this modified formula &quot;v^kdd be satisfactory from&apos; the point of view of the Chiefs of Staff.LORD CHATFIELD enquired whether the Chiefs of Staff would.have to consider this formula as a warning of increased danger from Italy. In other words, were further defence preparations against Italy to be taken as a result of it? The next item on the Agenda, the counter-bombardment defences of the Mediterranean ports, was an example of the problems which arose in this connection.THE PRIME MINISTER said he realised that the Service Departments and the Chiefs of Staff would perhaps require more general instructions. The question was whether the situation had so changed since the existing formula had been decided that we should now contemplate large expenditure on defence preparations against Italy. He thought that the Service Departments had sufficient general knowledge of the international situation to determine the scale of expenditure which was reasonable.Mr. DUFF COOPER felt that it was most desirable for the Committee of Imperial Defence to give its technical Sub-Committees clear guidance as to the political background for defence planning. For example, as the Chief of Naval-Staff had pointed out, the Sub-Committee, whose Memorandum on the Counter-Bombardment Defences of the Mediterranean Ports was to be considered as the next item on the Agenda, would wish to know whether the formula proposed by the Prime Minister was to be considered as a warning of increased danger. . If it was, presumably their report should be referred back to them for reconsideration in the light of the new ruling.SIR THOMAS INSKIP did not see how general instructions could be given to the technical Sub-Committees, The whole question was largely one of priorities. Italy was now obviously to be considered as a potential enemy, and therefore various defence measures were no doubt desirable in the Mediterranean. The question whether 9-2-inch guns or 13-5-inch guns were to be installed in the Mediterranean ports, however, must be considered in the light of the relative risks involved.THE PRIME MINISTER said he would like to offer some observations on the general question. It seemed to him that we need not be afraid of attack by Italy, either in the Mediterranean or elsewhere, unless she were sure of German support. If Germany were contemplating hostile action or became engaged in. hostilities against us, there was little doubt that Italy would join in and take the opportunity to fish in troubled waters. The ideal, no dOubt, was to be prepared to fight Germany or Italy or Japan, either separately or in combination. That, however, was a counsel of perfection which it was impossible to follow. There were limits to our resources, both physical and financial, and it was -vain to contemplate fighting single-handed the three strongest Powers in combination. He did not leave out of account the fact that we should probably have allies in such a war, notably France, but France at the present time was not in a very strong position to give us much help. He was greatly concerned about the position of France. The country might recover very rapidly in the face of danger as it had often done before, even when it seemed to be in a most perilous condition. Nevertheless, the fact had to be faced that we could not at the present moment Count on any very effective support from France.In foreign affairs there were two aspects to be considered, first, our prepara-tions for defence and, second, our foreign policy. These two had to be correlated, since each influenced the other. He thought that we ought so to direct our foreign policy that we did not quarrel with Germany. If we could do that, he did not feel that we need fear any sudden attack by Italy. But even on the assumption that we could maintain good relations with Germany, he still thought that we should regard Germany as our greatest potential danger and should give first priority to defensive preparations against that country. In that case, defensive preparations against Italy should be considered as of only secondary importance.LORD ZETLAND said he fully agreed with the Prime Ministers reading of the situation.  There was, however, present in his mind one point which vitally concerned India.  Admittedly, Germany was our chief danger, but Italy lay on [15524-1] B 2
the flank of our main line of communications to India, Australia and New Zealand. He thought, therefore, that we ought to protect ourselves against any sudden attack by Italy on this vital line of&apos; communications. Italy realised our weak point, and no doubt for this reason was intriguing with the Arab countries. She had a great block of territory oh the western side of the Red Sea, and, if she extended her influence also to the eastern side, she could certainly embarrass us very considerably.Mr. DUFF COOPER enquired whether there was any danger of Italy trying to force the hand of Germany if, for example, her internal situation became very difficult. Might she rely on Germany following her and attack us first on her own ?Mr. EDEN pointed out that this contingency was visualised in his memo-randum.   He thought that it was a distinct possibility.SIR SAMUEL HOARE said he agreed with the general analysis given by the Prime Minister. There was little danger, he thought, of Italy starting a unilateral war against us, if there were no chance of Germany joining her. He therefore entirely agreed that first priority should be given to our defensive preparations against Germany. It was possible, however, to push the issue of priorities to extremes, in which case nothing at all would be done in the Mediterranean. He thought this would be a fatal mistake. During his tour in the previous year in the Mediterranean he had been much struck by the nervous-ness which was apparent in that area. No doubt this was due to some extent to Italian propaganda, but there was certainly a feeling there that we were quitting the Mediterranean. He felt most strongly that although we should concentrate first against Germany, we should at least do enough in the Mediterranean to show that we intended to stay there for good. It might be open to question whether or not heavy guns at Malta and Gibraltar were of vital importance, but he thought that it was essential to do more in the Mediterranean and Red Sea than we were doing at present.LORD SWINTON said he was much impressed by the Prime Minister^ analysis. We had to face the fact that we could not prepare against every enemy in every quarter, and therefore our policy should be to provide the best deterrent we could against war. The surest way of doing this was to build up a deterrent against Germany, so that she would realise that it was not worth while going to .war with us. He felt therefore that it was unwise to do anything in the Mediter-ranean at the expense of defensive preparations against Germany. He emphasised that the staffs must have political guidance and that it was the duty of the Minister in the Committee of Imperial Defence to give it. As the Prime Minister had pointed out, we had to make our foreign policy go hand in hand with our defence preparations. At a recent meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence the question of ensuring naval base facilities at Alexandria had been considered and the Committee had agreed with the view expressed by the Chiefs of Staff that it was highly desirable to obtain a dock at Alexandria. We had an alliance with Egypt and he felt that we must rely on this alliance as the key to the whole situation in the Mediterranean; to be sure of having the co-operation of Egypt was probably of greater importance than having heavy guns in the Mediter-ranean ports. In considering our strategy in a war with Italy we must look at the situation as a whole and decide what things were vital. . The possession of full facilities in Egypt was certainly one of these things, and the control of the port of Flaif a was probably another.Mr&quot;. HORE-BELISHA said he agreed with the Prime Minister that the contingency of a single-handed war with Italy might be left out. He suggested that consideration of this contingency by the Chiefs of Staff was unnecessary, since it would be based on an unreal hypothesis. If this contingency were ruled out and only that of war against Germany in alliance with Italy were considered, the importance of defensive preparations against Germany would retain their proper perspective. As a matter of practical politics, it was impossible to put more defences into the Mediterranean without upsetting our present programmes. He suggested that the Chiefs of Staff should base their recommendations for any defensive measures against Italy on the assumption that we should be at war with Germany at the same time as with Italy.
r, SIR JQHN SIMON agreed with the Prime Minister as to the-paramount importance of defensive preparations against Germany. It was impossible tq achieve security in every direction, and we had therefore to decide in what quarter the emphasis should be placed. He did not think anyone would dispute that our chief danger came from Germany. If we could achieve reasonably good relations with that country, we should have nothing to fear from Italy. At the same time; it was essential to do enough to deter Italy from a &quot; mad-dog &quot; act. It would be for the Staffs to say what this amounted to. He had been much impressed by the answers given to the Australian Delegation by the Chiefs of Staff (C.I.D. Paper No. 450-C).  At the end of Paragraph 10 of this paper it was stated &quot; The intervention of Italy against us would at once impose conflicting demands on our Fleet. Our policy must be governed by the principle that no anxieties or risks connected with our interests in the Mediterranean can be allowed to interfere with the despatch of a Fleet to the Far East.&quot;These words were reiterated in Paragraph 33 of the paper. Admittedly the hypotheses under consideration were not the same as those now being discussed, but it was noteworthy that the Chiefs of Staff stressed the importance of main-tainingpur principal objective and not permitting diversion of our forces. For the same reason, he himself would deprecate any large diversion of effort to the Mediterranean, since this could only be done at the expense of defensive preparations against Germany.Mr. EDEN said he agreed with the views which had been expressed by the Prime Minister, and also with Sir Samuel Hoare&apos;s emphasis on the need for taking some defensive measures in the Mediterranean. Although Germany was undoubtedly our greatest danger, he was impressed with the risk that Italy might fire the train of the explosive material in Europe to-day, feeling that she would liave Germany behind her. A situation might arise very much like that which had caused the Great War. In that case Austria, secure in the knowledge that she would have Germany&apos;s support, had lit the match. It was for this reason that he felt the building up of a deterrent against Italy had a considerable secondary importance as a safeguard against the danger from Germany. He agreed with Lord Zetland as to the danger of Italian propaganda in the Middle East. No doubt this was to some extent Italy&apos;s reply to our rearmament programme, but he thought we should consider what steps we should take to combat the increase of Italian influence in the Mediterranean and Red Sea. The question of Italian propaganda was becoming of increasing importance and he considered that it was one which would require careful examination in the immediate future.THE PRIME MINISTER said that from the course of the discussion it appeared that there would be no objection to allowing the latter half of the present formula to stand, namely:  &quot; That in the above circumstances no very, large expenditure should be incurred in increasing the defences of these ports, but at the same time some steps should be taken to bring them up to date and to increase their efficiency.&quot;In due course, no doubt, proposals in accordance with this part of the formula would be submitted to the Committee of Imperial Defence, but they would have to be conditioned by the necessity for affording first priority to building1 up a deterrent against Germany. He suggested that the first part of the formula might be re-worded as follows : -. &quot;(a) Italy cannot be considered as a reliable friend and must be omitted from the decision of the Cabinet of the 15th November, 1933, which says &apos; no expenditure should for the present be incurred on measures of defence required to provide exclusion against attack by the United States, France or Italy.&apos; (b) Priority in defensive preparations in Europe should be given to the provision of a deterrent to aggression by Germany, and the decisions to be taken after the receipt of the review by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee of the strategical situation in the Mediterranean and the Red Sea, will have to be governed by this conclusion.&quot;
SIR SAMUEL HOARE agreed with this formula. He asked whether the Chiefs of Staff could detail clearly in their report what was the present situation of our defences in the Mediterranean and what was being done there.SIR CYRIL DEVERELL said that in 1935 the Defence Requirements Committee had drawn up a programme for the modernisation of the defences on a twelve-year plan. Since that time certain additional defences had been approved, and the proposal now was to fulfil the programme in five years. Pro-vision for this had been included in the sum of  204 millions for the requirements of the Army which had been recently approved by the Cabinet. The first year&apos;s programme on the five-year plan had been carried out; and sanction had been given to the second year&apos;s expenditure, but with the proviso that no commitments should thereby be incurred for subsequent years. It was only fair to say therefore that something was being done in all the ports in the Mediterranean and the Red Sea.SIR SAMUEL HOARE said that it would be very helpful if the Chiefs of Staff could set out clearly the details of all the defences both existing and proposed. He had gained the impression that the proposals were on a very small scale.THE PRIME MINISTER referring to the terms of reference given to the Joint Planning Sub-Committee by the Chiefs of Staff said that he felt it was probably unnecessary to consider the contingency of a unilateral war with Italy.LORD CHATFIELD said that the Joint Planning Sub-Committee had almost completed their task, and it was rather late in the day to give them fresh instructions. That part of their Report which dealt with a unilateral war with Italy, could, of course, be ignored, if desired. He enquired whether the Chiefs of Staff should instruct the Joint Planning Sub-Committee to carry on with the: additional report which they had been asked for as the result of the suggestion contained in the last paragraph of the Foreign Office memorandum.Mr. EDEN said that he thought it would be very helpful to obtain the views of the Chiefs of Staff on these points.Mr. DUFF COOPER suggested that the defensive preparations in the Mediterranean would probably be the same in a single-handed war with Italy as in a war with Italy and Germany in alliance.LORD CHATFIELD agreed, and said that the Chiefs of Staff felt that we could never afford to give up our hold on Egypt, Palestine and the Red Sea. If we were involved in a war with Japan, it was conceivable that we might have to let the Mediterranean and Malta go for the time being, and rely on regaining-possession after our ultimate victory. It would be essential, however, to keep-control of Egypt and the Middle East.LORD SWINTON concurred and thought that the Chiefs of Staff should consider what were the vital issues from the purely strategical point of view.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was easy to conceive any number of hypotheses, but it seemed better to him to concentrate on the most likely contin-gencies. In his view a unilateral war with Italy was unthinkable; but if we were involved in a war with Japan or Germany, Italy might join in. That, therefore, should be the hypothesis upon which the Chiefs of Staff should base-their appreciation. Moreover, it would ensure that defensive preparations, against Germany received first consideration. The possibility that Italy would start the war was not, of course, excluded. The best insurance against such a-contingency, however, would be a friendly Germany.SIR SAMUEL HOARE repeated that he held very strongly that we should do more in the way of bringing up to date our defences in the Mediterranean. Their weak condition was having a very bad effect, and might prove a temptation, to Italy to commit a &apos;&apos; mad-dog &apos;&apos; act.Conclusions.The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed (i) to recommend to the Cabinet that the following formulae, to cover defensive preparations in the Mediterranean and Red Sea, should be-
approved in substitution for those adopted On the 24th February, 1937 (Cabinet 9 (37), Conclusion 4) : (a) that Italy cannot be considered as a reliable friend and must be omitted from the decision of the Cabinet of the 15th November, 1933, which says &apos;&apos; no expenditure should for the present be incurred on measures of defence required to provide exclusively against attack by the United States, France or Italy.(b) that priority in defensive preparations in Europe should be givento the provision of a deterrent to aggression by Germany, and the decisions to be taken after the receipt of the Review by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee of &quot; the strategical situation in the Mediterranean, Middle East and North-East Africa &quot; will have to be governed by this conclusion.(c) that in the above circumstances no very large expenditure shouldbe incurred in increasing the defences of the ports in the Mediterranean and Red Sea, but that at the same time some steps should be taken to bring them up to date and increase their efficiency.*(ii) To take note that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs intends to formulate proposals for the examination of the steps which might be taken to combat the anti-British propaganda now being carried on by Italy in the Mediterranean and the Middle East.Tt&quot; &quot;7\* *Jt&quot; &quot;VV&quot;* Retained from the February formula.3 Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, July 5, 1937.
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   June 1937.SECRET. Copy No,   1381332-B.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.PROBABILITY OF WAR WITH ITALY. (Previous C.I.D. Papers Nos. 1311-B and 441-C.)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.THE Committee of Imperial Defence, at their 288th meeting (Minute (5)) of the 11th February, agreed to recommend That Sub-Committees of the Committee of Imperial Defence should base future enquiries, in respect of Mediterranean and Red Sea defended ports, on the following assumptions : (I) The Mediterranean is a vital link in our imperial communications. (II) Italy cannot be counted on as a reliable friend, but in present circumstances need not be regarded as a probable enemy.This recommendation was approved by the Cabinet on the 24th February, 1937 (C.I.D. Paper No. 441-C); and since that date the formula, &quot; Italy cannot be counted on as a reliable friend, but in present circumstances need not be regarded as a probable enemy,&quot; has formed in part the basis of at least five Papers drawn up in the Committee of Imperial Defence and its Sub-Committees : (a) Paper No. I.D.C. 310 of the 2nd April, relating to the defence of ports abroad and providing for installation of armaments.(6) Paper No. 446-C of the 27th April, 1937, in which the Joint Oversea and Home Defence Committee recommended that heavy guns should not be installed at Gibraltar and Malta, but that 9-2-inch counter-bombardment armament should be accepted as a sufficient deterrent.(c) Paper No. 447-C of the 4th May, which discusses the potentialities of cyprus as a naval, military and air base.(d) Paper No. O.D.C. 1340 of the 10th May, relating to air raid precautionsin Kenya.(e) Paper No. J.D.C. 319 of the 19th May, which discusses the defences of malta.At the 1st meeting (the 19th April) of the D.P.P. Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, I suggested that the dangers to be apprehended from Italy required reassessment. The purpose of this paper is to reassess them; and the fluidity of foreign international relationships and the unpredictable nature of many of Signor Mussolini&apos;s actions, dispenses me, I hope, from any apology for traversing a decision reached with the assent of the Foreign Office as recently as last February. The importance of a correct appreciation of the course of Italian policy needs no emphasis, for it is manifest that serious decisions may flow from any such appreciation which would affect, first, the conduct of foreign relations not only with Italy, but with Germany and other foreign countries; secondly, the appropriations to the defence services; and, thirdly, all the strategic plans elaborated in times of peace for meeting attacks from no matter what quarter.9301   [15374]   [15551] B
-. 2. A serious effort to enter into relations of confident friendship with Italy-began in November last and reached its conclusion in the Joint Declaration of the. 2nd January, 1937. Attention,may first be directed to a series of events occurring not only before, but more particularly since, that date, which it is difficult to reconcile with any settled determination on Signor Mussolini&apos;s part to respect legitimate British interests : (a) a resolution of the Fascist Grand Council of the 1st March adumbrating increased military expenditure, and the greatest possible measure of economic self-sufficiency, which is justified on the ground that &quot; only, with the aid of science, courage, and a spirit ready for any development can peoples less richly endowed resist the possible aggression of countries richer in money and possessors of greater natural resources &apos;&apos;; (6)* the naval, military and aerial development of Southern Italy and of the narrow waters between Italy and North Africa, the development of bases at Massaua and Assab, and the rapid expansion of a native army in Abyssinia; (c) a decision (the 10th April) to institute a High Command for North Africa, with control over land, sea and air forces, to constitute a white metropolitan army corps in Libya, and to develop first-class communications throughout the colony; (d) Signor Mussolini&apos;s declara-tion at the Campidoglio on the 23rd March of the &quot; inevitability of the nation being summoned to meet the test of war&quot;; (e) Signor Mussolini&apos;s remark to Herr von Schuschnigg at Venice at the end of April, that &quot; he would match with the United Kingdom gun for gun, ship for ship, aeroplane for aeroplane,&quot; and that &quot; he had the advantage over England in man-power, particularly pilots &quot;; (/) Admiral Cavagnari&apos;s declaration on the 5th May, that Italy would add to the number of her battle cruisers and other types of ship in order that Italy should be capable of operating on the high seas. This resolution, he said, had been taken in view of the recent unmistakable decision of the State which already possessed the strongest navy in the world. It was clear that wars fought on a single frontier were a thing of the past. A European conflict would soon develop into a world conflagration, and it was on the high seas that the first issues of the war would be determined. Consequently, the Italian navy must become an oceanic navy, and this, he said, was the most important change that must now characterise Italian naval programmes in the near future; (g) General Valle&apos;s declaration in the Senate on the 15th May, 1937, that &quot; a great change had taken place in the future strategical employment of the Italian air forces. The centre of gravity of its influence had completely moved from the Padana valley towards the Mediterranean, the Red Sea and the Indian Ocean. As a consequence, all air bases in those zones had been strengthened, i.e., Sicily, Sardinia, the iEgean Islands, Pantelleria and Tobruk &quot;; (A) Signor Mussolini&apos;s claim to be protector of Islam; and a very extensive campaign of propaganda and intrigue in the Near and Middle East designed not only to impress local opinion with the value of Italian friendship, but also to represent England as treacherous and effete; (i) the emission from Bari, in both Italian and Arabic, of broadcasts vilifying British policy in Asia and Africa, and the British administration in India and elsewhere; (j) the recurrent and bitter hostility against the United Kingdom of the Italian Government-controlled press; (k) the Italian refusal to participate in any form in the celebration of the Coronation, and the insulting if fragmentary-references to it in the Italian press.3. This catalogue of events is not by any means exhaustive : some of the headings such as &quot;Anti-British propaganda&quot; could be expanded almost indefinitely; but, though I should hesitate to base a considered estimate of the fundamentals of Signor Mussolini&apos;s policy solely on such manifestations of fear, envy, petulance or pique, its cumulative effect suggests serious doubt whether his actions are consistent with the assertion that Italy is a &quot; satisfied Power,&quot; or with a desire often declared for friendship with ourselves doubts whether the terms on which his wholehearted friendship could be had can be reconciled with the adequate protection of British interests. In explanation or palliation of Italian behaviour it can not unreasonably be urged that Italy imputes to ourselves a determination&apos; which, in the opposite case she would certainly herself entertain -to enjoy in due course a revenge for the humiliation inflicted upon us (in conjunction with other members of the League of Nations) as critics and opponents of her aggression against Abyssinia; that Italy genuinely believes our rearmament to be directed against herself; that Italy suffers immoderately from* These developments were en train before the 2nd January.
a consciousness of her subordinate status among the other Great Powers; that public references to her in the press and elsewhere in England have given easily intelligible umbrage; that the invitation of an Abyssinian representative to the Coronation was construed as a political gesture; that fear of unemployment renders continually increasing rearmament unavoidable; and that the enthusiastic support of domestic opinion can only be elicited by an exaggerated chauvinism. But even when full weight had been given to all these considerations and others which can be adduced to support the view that no fundamental conflict of interests or policy need exist between Italy and Great Britain, and that sufficiently conciliatory behaviour on our part will presently re-establish relations with our-selves as free from anxiety as those which existed before the Abyssinian expedition was launched, there is a heavy residuum for which further explanation must be sought.4. In a paper (CP. 335) circulated to the Cabinet on the 14th December, 1936, I wrote :-&quot;Italy is the only Great Power lying wholly inside the Mediterranean Basin, and it is a commonplace of Italian political thought that her future depends upon the relative degree of sea and air power which she can exercise there as compared with other nations. The most important limitation upon her exercise of military force (in the wide sense of the word) is the fact that of the three gates of the Mediterranean, one, namely, the Dardanelles, is commanded by Turkey, and the other two, namely, Suez and Gibraltar, by ourselves. These circumstances had a relatively small influence upon Italy&apos;s policy during the early period of her career as an independent nation, during which she cheerfully acquiesced in a situation which left her in a military sense at our mercy; the Great War and the Treaty of London, however, gave a powerful impulse to her ambitions which the disillusionment of the Peace Settlement did nothing to diminish. In 1922 Mussolini came into power and from this moment onwards the efforts of Italy to assert herself in one way and another rise in a steady crescendo marked, among other things, by the Fiume incident, the Corfu incident, the acquisition andfortifi-cation of the Dodecanese and the construction of a first-class military base in the Island of Leros; and terminating in the Abyssinian expedition which, we are now told, had been the subject of Mussolini&apos;s dreams for fourteen years.&quot;These sentences suggest where the dominant motives of Italian policy must be sought and their purport is reinforced by a striking speech made at Milan on the 1st November, 1936, in which Signor Mussolini clearly demonstrated Italy&apos;s preoccupation with the restraints upon her freedom of action implied by British control of ingress to and egress from the Mediterranean. Having derided the prospects of disarmament and of the organisation of collective security, he affirmed that &quot;a virile nation relied on its own resources for its defence and did not place its destiny in the hands of others.....Italy had not forgotten andwould not forget that the League of Nations had organised methodically and with devilish diligence a siege against the Italian people; it had tried to starve them and through the sufferings of women and children to break down Italianresistance.....Italy is an island in the Mediterranean.   This sea is for GreatBritain a road, one of the many roads indeed a short cut by which Great Britainreaches its outlying territories more quickly.....If for others the Mediterraneanis a road, for us it is life.&quot; In a public reply, I demurred to Signor Mussolini&apos;s words and described the Mediterranean as being in our view &quot; an arterial road &quot; freedom to use which was for us a vital interest; adding that &apos;&apos; it should in our view be possible for each country to continue to maintain its vital interest in the Mediterranean not only without conflict with each other, but even with mutual advantage.&quot; Arising out of this interchange of ideas, the Anglo-Italian Declaration of the 2nd January included a statement that &quot;freedom of entry into, exit from and transit through the Mediterranean is a vital interest both to the different parts of the British Empire and to Italy, and that these interests are in no way inconsistent with each other.&quot; Phrases, however, are in themselves insufficient to modify policies, a^id no public declaration of this or any other kind has sudden power to alter hard facts, or maturely deliberated ambitions. The facts in the present case are; in my view, briefly as follows : Italy&apos;s front door opens upon our arterial road and present Italian aspirations towards expansion [15374] L b 2
of power and influence are virtually irreconcilable with a situation where police control of that road is in our hands and not in hers. These police powers should, in her view, be, if not monopolised by her, at any rate shared with us in such a way that, even if Great Britain should continue to be able in certain circum-stances to forbid free passage along that road to Italy, yet that Italy should in certain circumstances be able to forbid the use of that road to us.5. Thus, from whatever angle one studies the attitude at present adopted by Italy towards the United Kingdom, there is clear evidence of a definite ill will in the whole trend of Italy &apos;s present foreign policy. Opinions may differ -as to the original cause of this ill will-as well as to its durability should conditions alter. But so long as it exists we are bound to consider whether, and in what circumstances, it might impel the Italian Government along a line of action leading to war with the United Kingdom.6. That Italy should enter upon a war with us which she would have to conduct to a conclusion single-handed is for the time being the least of several possibilities. The case in which she would be most likely to do so would arise if the Fascist regime felt itself, for either domestic or external reasons, to be in imminent danger. We have been warned by Sir E. Drummond (and the warning cannot be disregarded) that in such case Signor Mussolini might prefer self-immolation to revolution or decay.7. On the other hand, there is a considerably greater possibility of Italy entering upon a war with us which she would have to conduct to a conclusion single-handed if she could count either on the British Empire being deeply involved in difficulties falling short of war (e.g., strained relations with Germany, or France; extensive civil disturbances in Palestine or India), or such benevolent neutrality on Germany&apos;s part as would in effect gravely embarrass us and prevent us from concentrating our efforts against Italy.8. As to the possibility of a combination of Germany and Italy against us, two major considerations should be borne in mind. The first is this : if Germany and Italy did not begin actual hostilities against us simultaneously if Italy were initially to refrain from taking overt part in an Anglo-German war she would nevertheless take advantage of our preoccupation elsewhere to strengthen the Italian and weaken the British political and military position in the Mediter-ranean and Red Sea basins without any regard to the legality or propriety of the means employed to this end. Immediately, therefore, on the outbreak of war with Germany, or even during a period of very strained relations between the United Kingdom and Germany, what I may call a para-military situation would arise between Italy and this country in the course of which, if no adequate preparations had previously been made to resist the use or threat of force by Italy against ourselves or our friends in those areas, we and the countries aligned with us might suffer such a loss of influence or even territory as would prove irreparable without eventual recourse to arms. Such a situation might soon lead, in effect even if not in form, to a simultaneous conflict with both Germany and Italy.9. The second consideration of political importance to be borne in mind is this: the United Kingdom and Italy positively jostle each other in the Mediterranean and Red Sea areas with the discomfort and risks inevitable in such a state of affairs. Here is a powerful argument in favour of adequate preparations for resistance to illegitimate Italian pressure, and its relation to the possibilities of war with Germany must also be brought into account. We have already considered the course Italy would take in the event of very strained relations between the United Kingdom and Germany, but the course of German policy in case of hostilities with Italy is equally interesting. In such circum-stances Germany would be strongly tempted to exploit our preoccupation in the Mediterranean for her own advantage and a night well embark on adventures likely to precipitate a general conflict. It is surely in just such a conjunction of circumstances that the danger of war with Germany is most readily found; and, if this be so, it is manifest that adequate preparation to resist pressure from Italy and consequently to prevent that pressure from being recklessly exercised, is an important if indirect means of preventing a conflict between this country and Germany from breaking out.
10. The effects on the probability of war with Italy, of war or severely strained relations between the British Empire and Japan have not been men-tioned. Of these it is perhaps enough to observe that what has been said about the indirect results of Anglo-German tension applies, but with a good deal less force, to Anglo-Japanese tension.11. From the foregoing it will be seen that I find myself unable to agree that the formula mentioned in paragraph 1 is now on a satisfactory basis to govern our policy and plans for defence in the Mediterranean and Red Sea, and I suggest tentatively that the assumption might be altered to read somewhat as follows : Italy cannot be considered as a reliable friend and must for an indefinite period be regarded as a possible enemy, especially if she can count on the goodwill and potential support of Germany, or if the United Kingdom were involved in difficulties elsewhere.12. It may, however, be felt, as I myself feel, that neither this nor .any other formula is here and now discoverable which will suffice as a ready .and reliable basis for the numerous decisions constantly called for in regard to policy, strategy, and appropriations. Much fresh light might, however, be thrown on such questions if His Majesty&apos;s Government were enabled to form an accurate picture of what shape the United Kingdom is in at this moment to conduct single-handed a war with Italy (a) if the latter were to rush into it from motives of despair, as described in paragraph 6, without waiting to assure herself of foreign support or encouragement; and (b) if, as described in para-graph 7, she could count on the goodwill and potential support of Germany, or if the United Kingdom were involved in difficulties elsewhere.13. I should be grateful, therefore, if the Chiefs of Staff could prepare a report on this subject at their early convenience. In doing so they will probably find it useful to state at the same time what alterations in our present establish-ments, dispositions, and plans, would be required in order to bring our defence measures to a pitch of efficiency which (a) would ensure a rapid defeat of Italy, not only in the first but- also in the second of the eventualities I have envisaged, and (b) would prevent a combination of Germany and Italy against us in the circumstances outlined in paragraphs 8 and 9.Foreign Office, June 15, 1937.

</content>
</cab>
