<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/270/0 images: 636-638</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1937.SECRET.CP. 184 (37). Copy No.CABINET.The Decision of the Congress Party to aocept office under the Government of India Act, 1935.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.On 7th July, after prolonged discussion, the Working Committee of the Indian National Congress the inner controlling &quot; Cabinet &quot; of that body passed a resolution recommending that supporters of the Congress in the Provinces where that Party had obtained a majority in the Legislatures should be &quot; permitted to accept office where they may be invited thereto.&quot; I attach to thiB memorandum the full text of the Working Gommittee&apos;s resolution.2. It is well known that, in spite of the general policy of &quot; combating and endeavouring to bring to an end&quot; the Act of 1935 with a view to the early achievement of independence consistently set out as the main purpose of the Congress, opinion in the Provinces has been strongly, and increasingly, in favour of acceptance of office, but that the President (Jawaharlal Nehru) in particular and those elements in the High Command which are at one with him have.been equally strongly in favour of abstention, with a view to bringing about an immediate deadlock. Mr. Gandhi, though no longer a member of the Working Committee, has made his way once more to the centre of the stage and has undoubtedly exercised a predominant influence in the events of the past few months. Though his influence has on the whole been exerted in favour of the acceptance of office, there can be little doubt that his main motive has been a determination to manoeuvre the Congress through a critical period without an open split in its ranks.3. It will be remembered that the first demand made by the Congress as the condition of acceptance of office in any Province was that the Governor should give a specific undertaking that in no circumstances would he use his special powers for the purpose of setting aside his Ministers&apos; advice in regard to their constitutional activities in other words, that he would conduct himself forthwith as a &quot;constitu-tional Governor.&quot; The Governors had no option but to refuse to give the assurance demanded and the Congress representative whom each of the Governors had invited to form a Ministry had no option, under the instructions conveyed to him by the Working Committee, but to decline to do so.4. With the situation as it then stood I dealt at some length in the House of Lords on 8th April. It was being impressed upon me by the Viceroy and the Governors that there was much apprehension amongst the Services, the Minorities, and even the Princes, lest the Government were about to make some concession in. the matter of the reserve powers, and I found it necessary to adopt an attitude, so far as the special responsibilities of the Governors were concerned, which was characterised by Lord Snell, who admitted none the less the justice of my conclusions, as one of unduly &quot; stiff correctitude.&quot; Lord Snell was, of course, unaware of the imminent risk of a landslide amongst the Services and the Minorities. Reports from the Governors showed that the statement had a steadying &quot;effect, andy having made.it clear that the safeguards provided by the Act were not to be tampered with, I found it possible at a later stage, by means of answers to questions in the House of Commons and a further statement in the House of Lords on 6th May; to give a picture of the working of the Constitution which made it plain that there was no risk of the Governors interfering gratuitously in the day-to-day administration of their Provinces, or indeed, of them treating their Ministers, from whatever party they might be drawn, as other than partners in a common enterprise. I received ample intimation that the more moderate elements in the Congress were satisfied with this explanation, and in particular that Mr. Rajagopalachari, the Congress leader in Madras, was willing to accept it as sufficient justification for assuming office.
5. The influence of the Left Wing, however, was still strong on the Working Committee, which a little earlier had put forward a new device for restricting, if not eliminating, the use of the Governors&apos; special powers. Their position was expressed in the following terms on 29th April: &quot; The Committee considers that the pronouncements on the policy of the British Government by Lord Zetland and Mr. Butler are utterly inadequate to meet the requirements of Congress. . . . The past record of the British Government and its present attitude show that without the specific assurances as required by Congress a popular Ministry would be unable to function properly without irritating interference.&quot; The assurances do not contemplate the abrogation of the rights of a Governor to dismiss the Ministry or to dissolve the Provincial Assembly when serious differences of opinion arise between the Governor and his Ministers.&quot; But the Committee has a grave objection to the Ministers having to submit to interference by Governors; with the- alternative of themselves having to resign office instead of the Governors taking the responsibility of dismissing them.&quot;The understanding now sought was that in cases of serious difference between the Governor and hie Ministers, the Governor, if he came to the conclusion that he was unable to accept the advice tendered to him, was to hold himself bound to dismiss them. Mr.. Gandhi was astute enough to create the impression that it was more a matter of form than of substance that was in dispute. But it was quite clear to the Viceroy and myself that there was a great deal more in the formula proposed than appeared upon the surface. It would be open to the Ministers, for example, to decide that any matter over which they determined to break was a serious matter and by so doing to force the Governor to dismiss them. And I have little doubt that the importance attaching to the formula in the eyes of some at least of those who were pressing it is to be found in the fact that they saw in it a means of disabling the Governor from bringing his reserve powers into play at all, while at the same time putting him in the position of appearing to be responsible for the rupture of relations with his Ministers, when in fact it was the Ministers who insisted on the relationship being terminated. To have placed the Governor in such a position would have been very unfair to him in relation to the Minorities and others whose interests he is required to protect; and it is significant that the Chief Minister in the Punjab, who is a Moslem, protested publicly and vigorously against the acceptance of the formula.6. I have already stated that the Working Committee&apos;s resolution, of 7th July was the outcome of prolonged discussion which ended, it seems clear, in an irreconcilable difference of opinion. The Governor-General, who in a message to the peoples of India on 22nd June had elaborated the explanation of the working of the Constitution previously given, himself informed me a few days before the decision was reached, that he had no great expectation of a decision- in the sense now taken. I conclude that the feeling in favour of office acceptance was sufficiently strongly voiced, by the Provincial representatives, who were summoned to state their case to the Working Committee, to make it apparent that insistence by the Left Wing on refusal to accept office, or to make terms which were known to be unacceptable to the Government, would have involved a definite split in the Congress Party. Such a split may still! develop, but evidently the controlling minds in the Working Committee thought it essential to avoid it at this juncture.7. The reaolutibn of 7th July is, comparatively speaking, a straightforward and realistic production. It is at least as satisfactory from our point of view as anything that we were hoping for. The reference to the election manifesto of last August and its statement that the purpose of sending Congressmen to the Legis-Legislatures would be &quot; not to co-operate in any way with the Act, but to combat it and make an end of it &quot; was only to be expected. This phrase is equivocal and was meant to cover more than one point of view. It does not necessarily imply any activity of an unconstitutional nature, and I am informed that when it was adopted attempts to commit the Congress definitely to &quot; wrecking &quot; the Act were success-fully resisted. I do not disguise from myself the fact that Nehru certainly and quite possibly Gandhi also have in mind the renewal of mass civil disobedience at some
Appendix.The Congress Resolution of 7th July 1937.The All-India Congress Committee at its meeting held at Delhi on 18th March passed a resolution affirming the basic Congress policy in regard to the new Constitution, laying down a programme to be followed inside and outside the Legislatures by Congress members in such Legislatures. It further directed that in pursuance of that policy permission should be given for Congressmen to accept office in the Provinces where the Congress Party was satisfied and could state publicly that the Governor would not use his special powers of interference or set aside the advice of Ministers in regard to their constitutional activities.In accordance with these directions the leaders of the Congress Party who were invited by the Governors to form Ministries asked for the necessary assurances. These not having been given, the leaders expressed their inability to undertake the formation of Ministries, but since the meeting of the Working Committee on 28th April Lord Zetland, Secretary of State for India, Lord Stanley, Under Secretary of State for India, and the Viceroy, have made declarations on this issue on behalf of the British Government.The Working Committee has carefully considered these declarations, and expresses the opinion that though they exhibit a desire to make an approach to the Congress demand they fall short of the assurances demanded in the terms of the All-India Congress Committee resolution as interpreted by the Working Committee in its resolution of 28th April. Again, the Working Committee is unable to subscribe to the doctrine of partnership propounded in some of the aforesaid declarations.The proper description of the existing relationship between the British Government and the people of India is that of exploiter and exploited, and hence they have a different outlook upon almost everything of vital importance. The Committee feels, however, that the situation created as a result of circumstances and events that have since occurred warrants the belief that it would not be easy for the Governors to use their special powers.The Committee has, moreover, considered the views of Congress members in the Legislatures and of Congressmen generally.The Committee, therefore, has come to the conclusion, and is resolved, that Congressmen be permitted to accept office where they may be invited thereto, but it desires to make it clear that office is to be accepted and utilised for the purpose of working in accordance with the lines laid down in the Congress election manifesto, and to further in every possible way the Congress policy of combating the new Act on the one hand and prosecuting a constructive programme on the other.The Working Committee is confident that it has the support and backing of the All-India Congress Committee in this decision and that this resolution is in furtherance of the general policy laid down by Congress and the All-India Congress Committee. The Committee would have welcomed an -opportunity for the direction of the All-India Congress Committee on this matter, but it is of opinion that delay in taking a decision at this stage would be injurious to the country&apos;s interests and would create confusion in the public mind at a time when prompt and decisive action is necessary.6325       Conf 3   Wfc 8177/P 8   85   7.87    IOPstage and in some form. But I think that there is a reasonable expectation that once these Ministries are in the saddle and are faced with definite responsibilities, they will learn to resist attempts on the part of the Central caucus to keep them in leading strings and will refuse to accept dictation. At all events, I feel no doubt that we have grounds for satisfaction with this latest development, which at least guarantees some practical experience of the new Constitution in all the Provinces and may prove to be a turning point in the history of our dealings with Indian nationalism.Z.India Office,12th July 1937.

</content>
</cab>
