<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/270/0 images: 641-644</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
o k ct o 3 b(THIS DOCUMENT IS. THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.) SMB C R E T.fl.P. 186 (37). COPY NOCABINET. -&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;THE MARRIAGE BILL. Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor.On the 18th March I circulated to the Cabinet a Memorandum (CP. 98 (37)), describing the position as itmight he expected to be if the Marriage Bill should pass,pointing out the additional duties which the Bill- would layupon the Probate, Divorce and Admiralty Division.-I indicated that the Bill,  if passed, would in-three ways add very materially to the duties of the Division, (l)   By reason of the addition to the grounds moonwhich a petition may be presented, there will be an- -       ... .......... -&apos;. * &apos;   &apos;increase, and possibly a large increase, in the number ofpetitions.(2)   Owing to the fact that cruelty will become a ground for divorce and not as hitherto a ground only for judicial separation, each case based on cruelty may be expected to occupy the Court for a longer period than at present.     In a large proportion of the suits for judicial separation based on cruelty, the parties are persuaded by the Coxirt to enter into a separation deed.     But when cruelty becomes a substantive ground for divorce this will be impossible.     Experience shows, moreover, that cruelty cases when fought are almost invariably long.
(3)    The hearing-ojT.e,aeh.-Petttion-will, by reason of the additional and stricter duty laid upon the Court,be more extensive in timecI also drew attention to the fact that, Lhe Diyorce Court was in arrear with its work and was falling further into arrear,  and that the Admiralty work was on the increase and appeared to be likely to increase still further.I, therefore,  suggested that if the Bill should pass, Parliament should be asked to sanction the permanent addition of one Judge t-o the Probate, Divorce and Admiralty Division together with the addition of another whose re-appointment should be contingent upon the passing of a Resolution by &quot;both Houses when satisfied that the work of the Division was such as to require the vacancy to be filledoThe Cabinet considered my Memorandum cn the 24thMarch,   and agreed,  amongst other things (Cabinet 13 (37),Conclusion 16);&quot;to take note that,  if the Marriage Bill passed into law,  it would be necessary to strengthen, the Judicial Bench in the Probate,  Divorce and Admiralty Division&quot;&quot;It now appears almost certain that the Bill will pass.      Such amendments as have been made in each Houseduring its passage have not lessened the certainty thatits provisions will increase the work of the Divisions as Ianticipated in March..Meanwhile, the situation in the Court itself has deteriorated considerably..      On the 25th June,  the defendednon-jury list was worse by over 50 cases than it was on thecorresponding date in 1936, arid by over 100 \t.;:?s e than itwas on the corresponding date in 1955.      The average date
of setting down of the defended non-jury cases being dealt with in the last week of June was the previous 22nd September;    and there was, therefore, very little prospect of the Division disposing of all the cases set down last Long Vacation before the commencement of this Long Vacation. There are over 1?000 undefended cases awaiting trial and the President of the Division has therefore announced that one Court will, if possible, take undefended cases on every day of the last two weeks of the term.      This may not be possible by reason of the demands of the Admiralty cases and in any case it will be at the expense of the defended non-jury list,  the time available for which will also be curtailed by Divisional Court and Judgment summonses.Furthermore,  the Admiralty writs issued up to the 1st July exceeded those issued in 1936 up to the end of September.      This is a very marked increase in the actual number of writs, and the position is aggravated by the fact that big ships and large amounts are involved,  and that the cases are more likely to come to trial than in the past.It has not been possible to find assistance for the Division from among the Judges of the King&apos;s bench division.      The Supreme Court of Judicature (Amendment) Act,1935, authorised the appointment of two additional Judgesfor the King*s Bench Division with power to fill vacanciesonly upon   an Address from both Houses of Parliament.      Thenumber of the Division has since been reduced byresignations and the vacancies thus arising can only be filled upon the passing of Resolutions   based  on the stateof the work in that Division.,.     Although there has been an unfortunate amount of absence through ill-health among the
Judges of the Divisions,  I see no reason to suppose that at present it would &quot;be possible to justify an application to Parliament based on the state of work in the King&apos;s Bench Division.During the passage of the Marriage Bill through the House of Lords,  it has become apparent that members ofthat House attach great importance to the duties imposed oupon the Court, under what-is now Clause 4, to satisfy itselfthat the petition is not presented or prosecuted incollusion, and it would seem that a similar feeling isentertained generally in the House of Commons.      It is,therefore, necessary that the numbers of the Division shouldbe such that the Judges have sufficient time to investigate the circumstances of each case thoroughly.I suggests therefore, to my colleagues that the time has come to prepare legislation in accordance with my provisional proposal in March, and the Cabinet conclusion reached in that month and set out above, and I therefore propose that instructions should be given for thepreparation of a Bill for the purpose.(Inld. )    HoHouse of Lords,14th July,  1937.

</content>
</cab>
