<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/46/14 images: 154-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January .1944.Copy No.WAR CABINET,ANGLO-AMERICAN DISCUSSIONS UNDER ARTICLE VIINote by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.ON the 20th January I circulated to my colleagues a memorandum bySir Hubert Henderson on the Economic History of the Inter-war Period(W.P. (44) 41). I think that my colleagues would also be interested to read theattached notes which I have received from the Lord President written by theEconomic Section of the War Cabinet Secretariat, commenting on the last threepages of Sir Hubert&apos;s document, in which he deals with the Anglo-american proposals discussed at the recent Washington talks.J. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,31st January; 1944.SECRET.W.P. (44) 64.31st January, 1944.NOTE BY THE ECONOMIC SECTION OF THE WAR cabinet secretariat.Sir Hubert Hendersons lengthy historical analysis of the inter-war periodcontains many points of great interest for the discussion of post-war economic policy. A number of his points might lend themselves to different interpretationand emphasis. But this note is confined to the last three pages of his paper; the account which he there gives of the proposals emerging from the recentWashington talks is in danger of giving a misleading picture of some of their most important features. In particular, the V/ashington proposals were devisedso as to learn from the lessons of the past and to avoid the mistakes of the inter-war period.2. Sir Hubert argues that, &quot; stripped of their institutional trappings, theschemes which are emerging from the Anglo-American expert discussions closelyresemble the policy pursued in the 1920&apos;s,&quot; a policy which he has described asan attempt &quot; once again to reconstruct a war-shattered wrorld on the basis of afreely working economic system, international credits, the reduction of trade barriers and the outlawing of quantitative regulation.&quot; This is not, in fact, an accurate description; and it may, therefore, be useful to enumerate the ways inwhich the Washington proposals differ fundamentally from the solutions triedin the inter-war years and, in fact, avoid &quot; the unwisdom of repeating the1920&apos;s.&quot;(i) The Control of Capital Movements.3. The Washington proposals quite properly leave room for privatelyfinanced international investment. But, as Sir Hubert admits, they also leaveroom for, and in suitable cases make obligatory, the national control of capital movements. In view of the great disturbances caused during the inter-war yearsby unregulated flights of capital from one centre to another, the importance ofthis point can scarcely be over-emphasised.[26809]
(ii) Adjustments of Exchange-Rates.4. The Washington proposals do not reintroduce rigid exchange-rates, suchas caused the United Kingdom such trouble between 1925 and 1931. Quiteproperly, they attempt to prevent unnecessary exchange fluctuations; but theypreserve the right of a country to depreciate its currency if that be necessary toremove a fundamental disequilibrium. What is equally important, they obligea country not to depreciate its currency unless this be necessary. With these rules in the 1930&apos;s we should have been able to depreciate sterling, but the americans could not have retaliated with a depreciation of the dollar, which was quite unnecessary and which, by 1937, had more than offset the depreciation of sterling, so that the dollar-sterling exchange-rate in that year was actually higherthan before our departure from gold.5. Sir Hubert recognises this, but argues that rules of this kind for the regulation of international economic relationships are difficult to maintain. Thisis true; but it is only another way of saying that the problem with which we shallinevitably be faced is one which will be difficult to solve. Sir Hubert, however,offers no solution. He desires the introduction of &quot;a reasonable degree of&apos; rigidity &apos; &quot; for the &quot; protection of human welfare &quot;; and, as he quite rightlyargues, tfuYwill incidentally make it less attractive for a country to depreciateits currency, because its exports will be rigidly restricted by the import controlsof its neighbours, so that exchange depreciation cannot expand its markets. but such rigidities would, of course, frustrate any action (e.g., through increased efficiency in our export trades) to increase this or any other country&apos;s exports;and for a country which will have to expand the volume of its exports perhaps50 per cent, above the pre-war level in order to pay for its essential imports theprospects held out by Sir Huberts &quot;reasonable degree of &apos; rigidity&apos; &quot; are notencouraging.(iii) Quantitative Regulation of Trade.6. &quot;The Washington proposals are not based upon &quot;the outlawing of quantitative regulation.&quot; The misuse of such restrictions (and they are liableto the grossest misuse) is to be prevented, and their use for legitimate purposesis to be subject to accepted rules of the game. There are three such purposescontemplated.First, a country which has a seriously unfavourable balance of payments isto be permitted to restrict imports on a non-discriminatory basis, while countries with favourable balances are not to be allowed to do so.Secondly, if any country has so favourable a balance of payments that its currency becomes &quot; scarce,&quot; all other countries, so it is planned, will be free to impose discriminatory restrictions against its exports. It is hoped that itwill not prove necessary to make more than temporary use of these rules. Inany case, it is difficult to conceive of two rules less like the rules of the inter-war period for dealing with serious balance of payments problems in an orderly way.Thirdly, it is contemplated that a code of rules should be worked out for the quantitative regulation by international agreement of those commodities in whichthere is a severe maladjustment between world supply and demand. It is not proposed that there should, in no circumstances, be such quantitative arrange-ments, but rather that they should not be used unless necessary and that, whenused, they should take account of consumers&apos; interests and of the need for a progressive and orderly shift from high-cost to low-cost production.(iv) State Trading.7. By suggesting that &quot; the schemes emerging from the Anglo-Americanexpert discussions closely resemble the policy pursued in the 1920&apos;s &quot; which hehas previously stated to be based on &quot;a freely working economic system,&quot;Sir Hubert may give the impression that the Washington proposals in some wayprohibit State intervention and, in particular, State trading. This is, however,not the case. The Washington proposals recognise the probability of an extensionof State trading. They attempt, for the first time, to work out a set of principlesor guiding rules of conduct to limit, as far as is practicable, the nationalisticmisuse of this instrument without limiting the range of its development., (v) Economic Nationalism and the Reduction of Trade Barriers.8. Sir Hubert suggests that the evils of economic nationalism in the inter-war years have been much exaggerated. In fact, however, there were veryconsiderable evils introduced in the inter-war years by a proliferation of trade
barriers, many of which had no real justification on balance of payments or other grounds but were examples of unrestricted economic nationalism. Of this, theAmerican Hawley-Smoot tariff an excessively high tariff imposed by a maincreditor country is only the most glaring example. It is true that there were many efforts during the 1920&apos;s to reduce trade barriers and some little progress was made in certain cases in retreating from the excessive barriers erectedimmediately after the last war. But nothing like the Washington proposals on commercial policy was ever in effect, or, indeed, contemplated, whereby excessivetrade barriers of all kinds would be held in check, with effective safeguards ofthe needs of countries with balances of payments difficulties.(vi) The Prevention of Economic Depressions.9. It is among the most notable omissions from the lessons which sir Hubert draws from the history of the inter-war years (which covered theperiod of the Great Depression) that he does not include in his &apos;: Conditions ofInternational Economic Order &quot; the need for co-ordinated national as well asinternational measures for the prevention of economic depressions. TheWashington proposals, on the other hand, envisage vigorous policies to preventthe recurrence of world-wide depressions; and for this purpose they contemplateinternational organisation for the co-ordination of international economic policies and for the exchange of views on national policies. Some internationalpolicies (such as Buffer Stock control of primary products or the proper planning and timing of international investment) are directly designed to help maintaininternational economic activity. Other elements of international policy discussed at Washington for the adjustment of balances of payments (such as therules for exchange-rate adjustments and for the use of quantitative regulationof trade) will free countries from preoccupations about their balances ofpayments, so that they may concentrate more effectively on internal policies ofstabilisation. In view of the policies of internal deflation and international&quot; beggar-my-neighbour &quot; with which the threat of world depression in 1929 and1930 was greeted, this programme cannot be held to repeat the mistakes of theinter-war period.Great George Street, S.W. 1,28th January, 1944.






</content>
</cab>
