<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/12/12 images: 106-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT. )WAR CABINET.SITUATION IN SPAIN.Note by the Prime Minister.I circulate for the information of my colleaguesa letter and memorandum which I have received fromCaptain Alan Hillgarth, R.N., our Naval Attache in Madrid,v&apos;/. S . C.Downing Street, S.W.1,,20TH SEPTEMBER, 1940.BRITISH EMBASSY,MADRID,13.9.40.Dear Prime Minister,.   Things are going much &quot;better here than they appearto he.     The Germans are getting desperate and the spaniards obstinate.     Our wonderful fight is impressingthem, in spite of the press here,I enclose a short note on the Spanish situationwhich I have sent to the Admiralty, with the approval ofthe Ambassador.     I only bother you with it when you are so busy because the Moroccan aspect is so important andI have tried to explain the dangers.(Signed) ALAN HILLGARTH,

NOTES.ON THE SITUATION IN SPAIN.General Franco has lost almost all his prestige.He is regarded, by everybody, as being asleep and im&amp;erthe thumb of his brother-in-law, Serrano Suner, theMinister of the Interior.The country is not really governed at all.     Everyauthority countermands the orders of the others.     the lack of transport and the inefficiency of party officialsadd to the mess.     Peculation and bribery are worse thanat any time in the past century.     Yet no one wants a return to the republic, which also failed because itcould not govern.     a constitutional monarchy might work,but would be blamed for too many of the mistakes of itspredecessors, and, in any case, Spain is not yet enoughadvanced to deserve a parliamentary system at all.      some kind of military dictatorship, with or without a king,of the mild form remembered as that of Primo de Rivera,appeals to most Spaniards as the best solution.Force is added to their argument by the way inwhich the Army, (including the other armed forces) remains the one stable element.     At the moment the all importantMinistry of the Interior and all the principal posts incivil government, administration, censorship, education,customs, communications and police (other than the CivilGuard) are held by members of the Falange Party.     Fortyper cent of the party are professional log-rollers ofno particular political affiliation.     Fifty per cent areex-communists or ex-anarchists.     Only ten per cent arehonest.     The result is not totalitarianism but a muddlethat baffles description.In the middle of this chaos the Army now standsout as the one hope of the State.     Behind it are rangedall the decent elements, the business man, big and small,the workmen, the professional man, the church the liberalintellectual, every honest man in gaol, the landowner,big and small, the tradesman, the artisan and, in shorteverybody except the criminals.     General Franco isregarded as having betrayed Spain, by complacency   ratherthan by treachery, and to be so much in the power of hisbrother-in-^law as to be past hoping for.     He is no longerreckoned as representing the Army at all.The country is in such a state that, if the germans were not on the frontier, the Falange, and with it bothFranco and Serrano Suner, would almost certainly disappearover night.     Since Germany and Italy back Falange andSerrano Suner (not Franco, who is looked on as too luke-warm), the generals dare not move for fear of a german invasion.     They have achieved cohesion in the last threemonths and have taken certain measures, such as getting rid of Yague (Air Minister) and Sanchez Mazas (Minister without portfolio), and they have made definite plans, both civil and military, to fight if they must.     I believe they willresist invasion if it comes, but they are not prepared to provoke it.      They are not yet ready to arrest Serrano Suner,depose or shelve Franco and abolish Falange.     All these things they want to do and could do to-day, but they feel,rightly, that action of that kind would bring about Germanintervention, so they are marking time while the feeling ofthe country in their support gains strength every day.

Germany hoped that Spain would enter the Warsoon after Italy.      Germany could gain nothing from Spainas an ally except a few minerals, some ports and aerodromes strategically useful and the road to attackGibraltar and go far to close the Mediterranean.      she could not feed Spain,,     Spain would he starved in four weeks.      The lines of communication to Gihraltar (or toLisbon, for Portugal would have to-be included) are very long, and there are no petroleum resources in Spain.     YetGermany undoubtedly considered Spain would be more usefulthan not and was put out when arguments, persuasion andthreats disguised as hints (either by herself or by Italy)failed to produce the desired result.      This negative was due to the generals using their remaining influence withFranco and making a stand, in the Council of Ministers.Germany has now to decide whether to abandon thispolicy and to invade Spain, to make one last attempt to persuade her or to drop the whole thing and to acknowledge,to herself, that Spain must remain a neutral.The first possibility, invasion, is at first glanceeasy.      Spain&apos;s army is ill-equipped and nothing likemobilized.,      Her Air Force is rotten.      An unadvertisedattack along main roads by motorized divisions would soonovercome resistance,      I calculate that the first Germanvehicles could reach the Gibraltar area in 6 or 8 days,without heavy forces, of course,     But an invasion of this sort, even when backed up by innumerable units of allarms, could not succeed in limiting itself    to main roadsif there were any opposition.      It would be necessary to occupy the whole country, a singularly difficult,mountainous country, and the Spaniards are a singularlytough, cruel, stiff-necked people.      Twenty divisionscould not hold down the whole of Spain,      If the Spaniardshad help from abroad, thirty divisions would not be enough.And the corner embracing Gibraltar and Cadiz could be heldindefinitely if we lent a hand.The Spanish generals&apos; plans have taken all thisinto account. They are contemptuous of the Frenchcollapse and optimistically reckon they can hold theirown against a German onslaught far more successfully than   do, but on broad lines their plans envisage delayingaction and raids on communications while theyawait the help    they feel sure we should send.That is not to say that any of the generals or,indeed, many of the Spanish people are pro-British, forthey are not.     They dislike us heartily.     But they areanti-^-Falange and anti-German., and as Germany^ enemy weshould, in their reckoning, hasten to their help if theyhad to fight Germany.     It is not a subject for Anglo-Spanish staff talks beforehand.     Only the more importantgenerals have thought about it so far.      If we showed afinger, German propaganda would have a chance to get itacross that we were to be the invaders.Germany must realise the difficulties in whiehan invasion would involve her, and she is reluctant to acknowledge bpcin as a permanent neutral (especially asSpanish dislike of Ccrmany is patently on the increase).

She is, therfore, driven to make a last attempt to persuadeSpain to come in oft her sideeThere are several signs at the moment that Germany-is getting rather desperate about Spain.     The reliablyreported despondency of the German Ambassador and hisCounsellors, the heavy bribing and consequently even moreunrepresentative character of the Press, additionalinfluence in police activity, visits of new tradedelegations with big promises, frenzied attempts to impede the progress of our trade talks.,,,.,  these things andothers she a- a high degree of anxiety.     But in order to persuade Spain, which means persuading the generals,Germany only has two real opportunities left.(a) By succeeding in her attack on England, she could make any European country come to heel,(b) By tricking the generals over Morocco, she might set up such a situation that they found, themselves at war with us before they realised what had happened.This is the danger point.Morocco is a Sultanate and a divided Protectorate.We are much too much inclined to consider French Moroccoas a French colony,,      In fact it is the part of the sultan&apos;s dominions protected by the French, just as Spainprotects a narrow strip in the north and. an international body the small area of Tangier.     Under the agreement of1904 Spain was to have a slightly wider zone to protectthan she actually got when the occupation took place,and this has always rankled.      Spain reasons that Franceis in a state of flux and that if the Petain Governmentcollapses she, as the other protectorate power in Morocco,has a right to assume protection over the French zone, ifnot the whole at least some part.      If General de Gaullestaged a coup dvetat in French Morocco, Spain wouldremember that she does not recognise de Gaulle and wouldassert her claim vigorously, especially if the coup ledto fighting or to trouble with the tribes,     Spain has just reinforced her army in the Spanish zone by two divisions and is feeling very much on her toes about thismatter0     And the vital importance of it is that over thisquestion of French Morocco and the 1904 agreement everySpaniard is agreed.Here is Germany&apos;s opportunity.     Any action byHis Majesty&apos;s Government or by General de Gaulle that doesnot take this question into account beforehand may playstraight into Germany&apos;s hands.There is considerable ground for believing thatSerrano Suner&apos;s present visit to Berlin is connected&apos;withthe Moroccan question,(Signed)    ALAN HILLGARTH.Captain R.N.Naval Attache,Richmond TsT^ap.e. S.W.1. ,




</content>
</cab>
