<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/9/34 images: 346-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1940.secret copy No.W.P. (40) 254.July 9, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND.. KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.COMMENTS ON THE RECENT CONVERSATION BETWEEN HISMAJESTY&apos;S AMBASSADOR AT MOSCOW AND M. STALIN.THE telegrams in Annex A contain the instructions sent to Sir S. Crippsin anticipation of his being granted an interview by M. Stalin, and the telegramsin Annex B contain the account of the interview which has now taken place andSir S. Cripps&apos;s observations thereon.2. M. Stalin&apos;s remarks to Sir Stafford Cripps may be considered to constitute an authoritative, statement of Soviet policy.3. M. Stalin made it clear, whatever his real feeling may be, that he is notprepared to agree that the danger of Germany dominating Europe is real, and still less that it constitutes a threat to the Soviet Union or calls for Sovietintervention on the side of the Allies. On the contrary, we are told that Soviet-German co-opeiation is to continue, and the impression gained by His Majesty&apos;ambassador was that the Soviet Union will, in any case, not be ready to meet aGerman attack until next summer.4. M. Stalin&apos;s reference to the Balkans shows that it is no part of his policy to force a Soviet-German clash in that region. Germany, we are told, can obtainall that she wants without invading Roumania and is not likely to attack Turkey,while the Soviet Union for her part has no intention of risking a Balkanadventure.5. One Soviet ambition, however, still remains to be satisfied in Europe the control of the Dardanelles. This M. Stalin would quite understandably prefer to achieve by peaceful means. He therefore suggests that Great Britain should help in improving relations between Turkey and the Soviet Union.6. In considering this suggestion we should all no doubt desire to do everything that we can to detach the Soviet Government from Germany and drawthem into our orbit. But in applying this policy we must always bear in mind the difficulty of assessing M. Stalin&apos;s &quot;sincerity on the one hand, and the cardinalimportance on the other of doing nothing to alienate the Turkish Government.The friendship of Turkey is vital to us for the following reasons  (1) Turkey is our Ally.(2) Turkey is a Mediterranean Power and, as such, can provide valuableMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.bases for our Fleet.
(3) Turkey lies on the direct route between Europe and our vital spheres ofinterest in the Middle East namely, Iraq, Palestine and Transjordan.(4) Turkey is the leading member of the Balkan Entente on the one hand, andthe Saadabad Pact on the other, and thus has great influence on thepolicy of all the countries in the Near East and Middle East.(5) Even though Turkey failed to carry out her obligations to us under thetreaty on the entry of Italy into the war, our treaty has neverthe-&apos;less during the war months been of enormous value in denying turkey to the Germans, and should continue to have this value.(6) Now that Turkey fears the Soviet Governments policy as regards the black Sea and the Straits, there is a growing danger that she mayreverse her policy altogether and throw herself into the arms ofGermany if she ever suspected that we were negotiating with Russiaat her expense.(7) In the event of a long war Soviet economic support to Germany may become a decisive factor, and it is impossible to exclude the possibilityof a Soviet attack on British interests in the Middle East. In such circumstances we might feel obliged to retaliate and this we couldonly do if Turkey were on our side.7. Fortunately the Turks are themselves anxious to improve their relationswith the Soviet Government, and it is clearty in our interests that they should do so. A recent telegram from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Angora showsthat any approach on the part of the Soviet Government, either direct or through his Majesty&apos;s Government, would receive sympathetic consideration there, andas he points out, it would be worth much if the present Turkish suspicion of theSoviet Government could be allayed. I should be in favour, therefore, of puttingto the Turkish Government M. Stalin&apos;s proposal that we should act as inter-mediaries so as to bring about a rapprochement between the two Governments.8. But if we do accede to this Soviet request, we should do so with noillusion about the probable results. We have no reason to trust M. Stalin, and hisremark that the Soviet Government are nervous as to some sudden action byTurkejr has, to say the least of it, an insincere ring and does not give us muchground for confidence.9. The basis on which we should have liked to construct a Turco-Sovietentente would have been the common interest which the two Governments had in preventing Germany from reaching the Black Sea. There is nothing, however,to indicate that M. Stalin is ready for such a form of co-operation, though nodoubt, as Sir S. Cripps hopes, it might develop out of an agreement over theStraits. But the fact must be faced that the prospects of an agreement over theStraits are by no means promising. It is probable that the only arrangement onthis subject which M. Stalin would consider satisfactory would be one whereby the Turks were deprived of their control of the Straits and the Soviet Unionleft free to use them in all circumstances. Moreover, M. Stalin&apos;s aim, no doubt,is to exclude the warships of all non-Black Sea Powers from the Black Sea both inpeace and war, including those of Great Britain.10. The chances, therefore, of any satisfactory agreement being reached are small. But, nevertheless, it would be worth while to make the attempt sincethe discussions which would ensue would (a) give us a breathing space, during which the Mediterranean position may inprove;(b) reveal the measure of M. Stalin&apos;s sincerity;(c) give us an opportunity of seeing whether it would be possible for Russiaand Turkey to co-operate together against the danger of Germanpenetration in the Balkans and the Black Sea. Such co-operation,though unlikely, would be of inestimable value to us.11. Another reason why I am disposed to favour an attempt to improve relations between Turkey and Russia is because we want, if possible, to forestallthe danger of a definite clash occurring between the two Governments in whichwe might ourselves be involved. Thus, His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Angorareported on the 28th June that the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs had informed him that, if the Soviet Government were to occupy other points on the
Black Sea or at the entrance to the Bosphorus it would mean war, and that inthat event Turkey would ask for our assistance under the Treaty of Alliance, andin particular for the despatch of a British naval force into the Black Sea. Suchan appeal would be highly embarrassing to us, because (1) It would be difficult for us to give Turkey adequate naval support againstthe Soviet Union;(2) We do not want ourselves to be involved in war with the Soviet Union;(3) To refuse such an appeal might well have the consequence of drivingTurkey into the arms of Germany.This fact constitutes, therefore, a further reason why we should do every-fhing in our power to prevent a deterioration in Soviet-Turkish relations.12. Although it may well be argued that we need not take our fencesbefore we come to them, it may also be asked what we should in fact do if,having failed to bring the Russians and Turks together, the Soviet Union and turkey drifted into war and the Turkish Government called upon us to assist them. We have no loophole in the treaty comparable to that of which Turkeyhas the benefit and under which she cannot be asked to go to war with theSoviet Union. We might, however, presumably argue that it would be an impossible position for us to go to war with Turkey&apos;s enemies so long as Turkeyinsists upon remaining a non-belligerent where our enemies are concerned, andthat the best course would be for Great Britain to become a non-belligerentvis-a-vis of the Soviet Union, just as Turkey is a non-belligerent vis-a-vis ofItaly. This at any rate might force Turkey into war with Italy. Indeed,we should in any case be entitled to insist that Turkey should go to war with italy in return for our going to war with the Soviet Union. But, whateverline we take, we should above all have to avoid saying or doing anything likelyto force Turkey to appeal to Germany.13. It may be that the Soviet Government are not likely to press theDardanelles claim to the uttermost. It is hardly likely that they would provokethe Turks into war, unless they are acting in collusion with Germany. Suchcollusion would seem to be particularly difficult in the case of the Straits, which germany and the Soviet Union both covet, Germany as a bridge leading to Asia,and the Soviet Union as a waterway leading to the Mediterranean. On theother hand, it is conceivable that, if he were subtle enough, Hitler might egg-on the Russians to threaten the Straits, in the hope that the Turks, realisingthat we could not help them, would turn to Germany for help and thus giveHitler an opportunity of establishing himself on the Straits as the friend andally of Turkey. It seems likely, however, that M. Stalin would have the fore-sight not to fall into such a trap.14. The conclusions, to which I would invite the Cabinet to subscribe, afterstudying Sir S. Cripps&apos;s telegrams in the light of the considerations set forth in this paper, are the following :  (a) We must avoid in our dealings with Soviet Russia anything which mightalienate Turkey, who is essential to us.(b) We should work to bring Soviet Russia and Turkey together (1) becausewre would like to get them to collaborate against the common Germandanger in the Black Sea; and (2) because we wish to prevent a clash between them which might involve ourselves in war with SovietRussia.(c) The present situation is such that we ought, while bearing in mind (a)above, to test the Soviet Government&apos;s real intentions by offering toact as intermediary between the Soviet Government and the TurkishGovernment, as suggested by M. Stalin. I would propose, with thisobject, to send instructions to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Angorain the sense of the draft telegram in Annex C.HJuly 9, 1940.
&apos;ANNEX A.(1)Viscount Halifax to Sir S. Cripps (Moscow).(No. 165.  Dipp.  Secret and Immediate.) Foreign Office, June 24, 1940.I HAVE given consideration to possibility of turning to account evidentSoviet fear of consequences to Soviet Union of complete German victory. AsStalin alone controls Soviet policy, I feel that our one chance of securing changein Soviet policy is personal approach to him. I presume he would not refuse youan audience if you asked for one as bearer of special message from PrimeMinister. You should therefore, if you see no objection, ask to see him in orderto deliver a personal message from Mr. Churchill, as given in my immediately following telegram.2. This message will give Stalin the occasion, if he wishes to profit by it,to enlarge on the views and intentions of the Soviet Government in the face ofthe sudden overthrow of all military and political equilibrium in Europe. Youwill no doubt be careful not to give him the impression that we are running afterhim in order to ask him to pull the chestnuts out of the fire for us, or dictatingto him where Russia&apos;s real interests lie in the present crisis. On the other hand,if he makes any approach you should at once express our willingness to consultand to co-operate.3. You should also, if possible, convey to Stalin the fact that we realise thatthe Soviet Governments ability to grant or to refuse vital supplies to Germanyplaces in their hands a powerful wreapon; and that while it is not our business to say how they should use this weapon, the manner of its use must naturallyhave an influence in the present crisis upon the negotiation of a mutuallyprofitable trade agreement, such as the Soviet Ambassador officially proposed toHis Majesty&apos;s Government last April, and which the latter are still anxious tobring about.4. I trust you wall be able to avoid, if you are sounded by Stalin or Molotoff,any discussion as to the attitude His Majesty&apos;s Government would adopt if theSoviet Government were now to occupy Bessarabia (see your telegram No. 345).If you are, however, questioned on this matter you should say that you have noinstructions, but that you presume that the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwould be largely conditioned by that of the Turkish Government.5. Should the question of the Baltic States be raised, you may affect tobelieve that the Soviet Governments recent action was dictated by the imminenceand magnitude of the German danger now threatening Russia, in which case theSoviet Government may well have been justified in taking in self-defence such measures as might in other circumstances have been open to criticism.6. A further telegram will be sent to you on the subject of our policy in theEar East as it affects our relations with the Soviet Government. Pending itsreceipt you should avoid the subject.(2)Viscount Halifax to Sir S. Cripps (Moscow).(No. 166.  Dipp.  Secret and Immediate.) Foreign Office, June 25, 1940.MY immediately preceding telegram.Following is text of Prime Minister&apos;s message:  &quot;2. At this time, when the face of Europe is changing hourly, I should liketo take the opportunity of your receiving His Majesty&apos;s new Ambassador to ask the latter to convey to you a message from myself.&quot; 3. Geographically our two countries lie at the opposite extremities ofEurope, and from the point of view of systems of government it may be said that
they stand for widely differing systems of political thought. But I trust thatthese facts need not prevent the relations between our two countries in the inter-national sphere from being harmonious and mutually beneficial.&quot;4. In the past indeed in the recent past our relations have, it must beacknowledged, been hampered by mutual suspicions; and last August the SovietGovernment decided that the interests of the Soviet Union required that theyshould break off negotiations with us and enter into a close relation with Germany.Thus Germany became your friend almost at the same moment as she became ourenemy.&quot; 5. But since then a new factor has arisen which, I venture to think, make sit desirable that both our countries should re-establish our previous contact, sothat, if necessary, we may be able to consult together as regards those affairs inEurope which must necessarily interest us both. At the present moment theproblem before all Europe our two countries included is how the States and peoples of Europe are going to react towards the prospect of Germany estab-lishing a hegemony over the Continent.&quot; 6. The fact that both our countries lie not in Europe but on herextremities, puts them in a special position. We are better enabled than othersless fortunately placed to resist Germany&apos;s hegemony, and as you know the BritishGovernment certainly intend to use their geographical position and their greatresources to this end.&quot;7. In fact, Great Britain&apos;s policy is concentrated on two objects one, tosa-ve herself from German domination, which the Nazi Government wishes toimpose, and two, to free the rest of Europe from the domination which germany is now in process of imposing on it.&quot; 8. The Soviet Union is alone in a position to judge whether Germany&apos;present bid for the hegemony of Europe threatens the interests of the soviet union, and if so, how best those interests can be safeguarded. But I have feltthat the crisis through which Europe, and, indeed, the world, is passing is sograve as to warrant my laying before you frankly the position as it presents itselfto the British Government. This, I hope, will ensure that, in any discussion that the Soviet Government may have with Sir S. Cripps, there should be nomisunderstanding as to the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government or of their readiness to discuss fully with the Soviet Government any of the vast problemscreated by Germany&apos;s present attempt to pursue in Europe a methodical process by successive stages of conquest and absorption.&quot;(3)Viscount Halifax to Sir S. Cripps (Moscow).(No. 174.   Immediate.) Foreign Office, June 26, 1940.MY telegram No. 165 of 24th June.Situation in the Far East, as elsewhere, has been profoundly affected by theFrench collapse, and we are having to take stock once more of our position in thelight of our existing resources and of the growing clanger that Japan may be forced into the war by the extremist party.2. In these circumstances I think that it would be unsafe for you, in any discussions you may have, to go further than you did in your conversation withM. Molotov as reported in paragraph 3 of your telegram No. 312.*3. We do not yet know how far Japan&apos;s attitude of hostility will be carried,nor what attitude the United States of America will adopt towards this newthreat to the status quo in the Far East. At this moment, when we are taking-steps to ascertain the answers to these two questions, any suggestion that we were already in negotiation with the Soviet Government about the Far East would be bound to arouse suspicion in various quarters, and might thus endanger suchprospect as we have of preventing hostilities from spreading in the Far East,and at the same time safeguarding our own position in the altered circumstancescreated by the disappearance of France.* Sir Stafford Cripps informed M. Molotoff on the 14th June that we desired to do our utmost to prevent any further hostilities in the Far East and that lie imagined that this was equally the desire of the U.S.S.B.
ANNEX B.(1)Sir Stafford Cripps to Viscount Halifax. (Received July 3.)(No. 399.  Immediate.  Most Secret.)       Moscow (via Bucharest), July 1, 1940.I PRESENTED the Prime Minister^ message to M. Stalin at 6-30 this evening and talked with him till 9-15. I had previously given the message andits translation to M. Molotov at 5 p.m., so that they could have a preliminary discussion upon it. The main points which were made by Stalin were as follows(extensive notes were taken by Mr. Dunlop of the conversation, and I propose tosend the important parts of these in following telegrams) :.&apos; 1. Germany cannot dominate Europe without command of the seas, and inany case she has not the strength to dominate all Europe. He does not believe,either, that such is her intention from what the Germans have told him, but heis not so simple as to rely on their statements, but rather on the facts.2.   Whoever dominates Europe will dominate the world.3. Russia has no intention of going further into Roumania or the Balkans.She does not wish to get embroiled in the Balkans, and she is afraid that she orany other country that tries to stabilise the matter in the Balkans will get soinvolved.   It is primarily a question for Turkey.4. Relations with Turkey might be improved. The Soviet Government werenervous as to some sudden action by Turkey and did not know how much might provoke it. They would welcome the help of His Majesty&apos;s Government in bringing about that improvement. They have no thought whatever of doing anything hostile to Turkey in the Black Sea or Bosphorus, but the question ofcontrol of the Straits is one that ought to be dealt with and all Black Sea Powersought to have some say in it. Until this question is settled, relations with Turkeywill not be wholly satisfactory.5. He agreed that Germany&apos;s desire for Roumanian oil was dangerous, buthe did not think that Germany would now attack Roumania, as, with theMediterranean closed, she would be getting all Roumanian oil anyway. Nor didhe think that Germany would attack Turkey, though these were possibilities notto be excluded from consideration.6. As to trade agreement with Great Britain, the Soviet Government had their agreement with Germany, which they would not break, one of the termsbeing that they supply a part of non-ferrous metals for goods manufactured forthem in Germany. It was of no service not to state frankly that some of the imported metals would be so used [sic], and if this was an impediment to anagreement with us he was sorry, but it could not be helped.7. There was absolutely no intention of Russia using her trade agreementwith Germany against Great Britain.8. The general tenor of the whole talk was friendly and severely frank and,as a result, I think that trade negotiations may start shortly.9. The points which I stated I would refer specifically to you I will dealwith in separate telegrams [two groups undecyp her able J.(2)Sir Stafford Cripps to Viscount Halifax: (Received July 2.)(No. 400.  Immediate.  Most Secret.) Moscow, Jidy 1, 1940.THE points of most immediate importance which emerged from our conversation was that which concerned Turkey and the Balkans.It is clear that the Soviet Government would welcome our assistance in arriving at better understanding with Turkey, particularly with regard to theStraits. If we could achieve this now we should, I feel, be in a fair way toharmonizing the real interests of the three countries and thus creating best possible guarantee against German aggression in [ % the Balkans].
3. The fact that the Soviet Union would welcome our intervention in thisdirection gives us an opportunit)^ of taking an initiative which should greatly increase our prestige in the Balkans and Near East.4. Following verbatim extracts from our conversations will, I think, serve to illustrate and emphasise this argument.(3)Sir S. Cripps to Viscount Halifax. (Received July 4.)(No. 401.   Most Secret.) Moscow (via Bucharest), July 2, 1940.FOLLOWING is a continuation of my telegram No. 400 : On my observing that a deterioration of Turco-Soviet relations would be most unwelcome and indeed embarrassing to His Majesty&apos;s Government, Stalinreplied that those relations were &quot; not bad &quot; but that the Turks were &quot; too fondof the political game&apos;&apos; and were liable to produce such unexpected tricks that itwas difficult to guess in which direction Turkey would &quot; make a spring.&quot;2. I observed that she would certainly do so if there were any threats toIstanbul or to the present status quo in the Black Sea or the Straits. HisMajesty&apos;s Government would, however, be glad to do anything they could toimprove relations between Turkey and U.S.S.R. Stalin replied that the SovietGovernment would have no objection if such an attempt were made. &quot; We donot,&quot; he said, &quot; intend to attack Turkey or join in a coalition against her, but during the last meeting with Sarajoglu no agreement was reached.&quot; Whatdanger threatened Turkey 1 The Soviet Government could not take into accountimaginary dangers invented in order to be exploited.3. It was wrong, Stalin continued, that the Straits should be under the exclusive control of a single Power which might abuse its position. On mysuggesting that it might be a good thing to discuss the matter afresh with theTurks, he replied that Sarajoglu, when he was here, had been &quot; offended by the mere mention of the Straits.&quot; There had been no question of any discussion.I suggested that His Majesty&apos;s Government might conceivably be able to assistby encouraging the Turks to reach some agreement. If he wished I should beglad to ask His Majesty&apos;s Government to use their good offices. Stalin repliedthat he would be glad of [the (sic)] steps that His Majesty&apos;s Government might take in that direction.(4)Sir S. Cripps to Viscount Halifax: (Received July 4.)(No. 403.  Immediate.  Most Secret.)       Moscow (via Bucharest), July 2, 1940.MY telegram No. 399.My general impression gained from interview was that Stalin is at themoment professing to accept German protestations at their face value to excusehimself [group undecypherable] acting in concert with us against Germany. Heprobably feels that Union of Soviet Socialist Republics is not ready and thatanyway he can stall off a German attack until it is too far on in the year to make such an attack likely before the frost breaks next Spring.2. Measures recently taken (a) to lengthen working day and week (b) toraise an internal loan of 8 milliards (announced yesterday) confirm that [ ? extra]efforts are necessary before Union of Soviet Socialist Republics is fully prepared.Stalin relies on our mastery of seas to stop Germany from achieving Europeandomination at least until the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics is prepared.But he also desires to be friendly to us and not unhelpful in our fight withGermany provided we reciprocate desire to be helpful in such ways as we can.He will not, however, do anything openly to antagonise Germany at present orto break his agreement with her.3. I believe that through excellent and ingenious device of Prime Ministersmessage a good relationship has been established which will enable future talks with M. Molotov to be more productive than they otherwise could have been.
It is, however, of the utmost importance that nothing should be written or said in England to destroy growth of better relations, as they are so sensitive here toeverything of that kind.4. I am fully satisfied with the general trend of the talk and particularly with the way in which Stalin welcomed our help in regard to Russo-Turkishrelations, seeing that a few weeks ago, according to the Soviet Ambassador, SovietGovernment took the view that we had no longer any concern with matters inthe Balkans. I am also of the opinion that they take the view that america is substantially an Ally of ours which may be important and that when a peace comes to be worked out it will be important for the Union of Soviet socialist republics to have a good basis of understanding with Germany&apos;s opponents ifGerman domination is to be guarded against.5. I did not, of course, touch upon the question of territories occupiedby the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics since the war, but this, too, is aquestion which will have to be gone into and dealt with if we are to have close relations with Soviet Government. Nor was the question of the Far East raisedor discussed. When I came out from the meeting Japanese Ambassador waswaiting to go in and had obviously been there some time. I have no idea whether he was also to be received by Stalin or only by Molotov.6. As regards the immediate future, I derived very definite impression thatthe best approach to closer relations will be achieved by some measure of sub-stantial agreement in regard to Turkey and Straits rather than prior conclusionof a trade agreement.(5)Sir S. Cripps to Viscount Halifax. (Received July 4.)(No. 404.  Most Secret.) Moscoiv, July 2, 1940.MY telegram No. 399.As regards general attitude of the Soviet Government towards Great Britainand Germany, Stalin said that the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics had nothing but a non-aggression pact with Germany, and this pact was in no sensedirected against Great Britain. Its basis had been common desire to get rid of&apos;&apos; old equilibrium &apos;&apos; in Europe, which, prior to the war, Great Britain and france had sought to preserve. If the Prime Minister wishes to restore the oldequilibrium,&quot; Stalin went on, &quot; we cannot agree with him.&quot; I replied that, inmy belief, &quot; old equilibrium &quot; had disappeared, and the question now confrontingeveryone was what the new equilibrium was to be. Stalin signified his assent. I said that in the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Government there must be someequilibrium, and not the hegemony of a single Power.2. Stalin had said that Germany would be unable to establish a hegemonywithout the control of the seas, and that in his discussions with &quot; the represen-tative of Germany &quot; he had seen no signs of any wish to attain such hegemony.I agreed with him as regards control of the seas, by the exercise of which GreatBritain, and Great Britain alone, was in a position to prevent a german domination of the world. Hence, also, the importance of rendering the blockadeas effective as possible. As regards Germany&apos;s intentions, both outpourings of individual Germans and information from their own secret sources had left HisMajesty&apos;s Government little room for doubt. Hitler was aiming- at universaldomination. Stalin observed that he paid little attention to the statements of individual Germans they were a military people, whose statements did notnecessarily reflect their true aims. He was, he said, not so simple-minded as tobelieve the German disclaimers of the desire for hegemony, but he was persuadedof the physical impossibility of such a thing.3. It is, I think, perfectly clear that if we are to develop a closer politicalcontact with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics we must make up our mindsabout the nature of &apos;&apos; equilibrium &apos;&apos; for which we are working. Presumably &quot;itmust be one in which this country plays an important part, and it is on this point,above all, that the Soviet Government will require reassuring.
(7)Sir S. Cripps to Viscount Halifax. (Received July 3.)(No. 409.  Most Secret.) Moscow (via Bucharest), Jidy 2, 1940.MY telegram No. 399.I attacked the subject of trade negotiations by asking whether Anglo-soviet relations were sufficiently friendly to warrant our assuming that the goodsobtained from us would not be re-exported to Germany.2. Stalin replied in concluding their economic agreement with germany the Soviet Government had only taken into account the disposal of [ ? their] ownsurplus products and not goods of which they themselves were importers. Sincethe war there had been shortage of the non-ferrous metals, e.g., nickeland copper.In addition they urgently needed natural rubber, tin, machine tools and machinery. They had not undertaken to deliver any non-ferrous metals toGermany with the exception of a part of those required for the execution of Sovietcontracts. They had recently taken delivery of a partly finished cruiser, a numberof three-axle lorries and certain aircraft and, as further contracts were executed,further supplies of non-ferrous metals would be sent to Germany. If thisarrangement proves an impediment to trade with His Majesty&apos;s Government,then such an agreement would not be achieved.3. I replied although I had no specific instructions, I believed that thepurpose of His Majesty&apos;s Government was to prevent an export of such metalsto Germany for her own requirements. I did not believe the arrangement towhich Stalin had referred would prove an insuperable obstacle to our negotia-tions, but I undertook to ask for instructions on this question.4. I concluded by expressing hope that it would be possible to proceedshortly with trade talks with M. Mikoyan.   M. Stalin intimated his assent.ANNEX C.Draft Telegram to A ngora.(Immediate.) Foreign Office, Jidy      , 1940.MOSCOW telegram No. 399 (paragraph 4) and Moscow telegram No. 400[of the 2nd July].There are obvious reasons for suspecting the sincerity of M. Stalin&apos;s sugges-tion that His Majesty&apos;s Government should help the Soviet Government in bringing about an improvement in Turco-Soviet relations with special referenceSir S. Cripps to Viscount Halifax. (Received July 4.)(No. 408.  Most Secret.) Moscow, July 2, 1940.MY telegram No. 399.Stalin was distinctly sceptical about the imminence of a German offensive inthe Balkans. While such a development could not be excluded entirely, themain motive was now absent, for Roumania was no longer making difficulties about the export of oil to Germany. Moreover, any Great Power which embarked on adventures in the Balkans would find itself drawn into the role of a &quot; super-arbitrator,&quot; and obliged to maintain an &quot; army of pacification.&quot; U.S.S.R.certainly had no intention of doing any such thing. If Germany and Italy,for their part, were prepared to take action on these lines, he agreed with methat Balkan States would have a common interest in resistance, but then every-thing would depend on Turkey, whose present attitude was uncertain.2. Reverting at a [J group omitted] stage to Roumania, Stalin said thatthe requirements of the U.S.S.R. had been clearly stated in their official com-muniques.  They had no further designs whatever on that country.
to question of the control of the Straits. The arrangement which M. Stalinprobably has in mind regarding the Straits is one which, would exclude GreatBritain entirely from the Straits, while leaving the Soviet Union free to use them in all circumstances.2. Nevertheless, in view of M. Saracoglu&apos;s remark to you (your telegramNo. 629) that if Soviet Union were to approach him regarding Soviet aims inthe Black Sea he would be prepared to give the matter consideration, it seemsonly logical that His Majesty&apos;s Government should accept the present Sovietinvitation to act as intermediaries. I have also in mind the first two paragraphs of your telegram No. 7043. Although we have no illusions regarding the probable results, it is worthwhile making an attempt to start such discussions seeing how valuable it wouldbe to us if we could bring Russia and Turkey to co-operate together against german penetration in the Balkans and the Black Sea. In any case such discussions would have the advantage of giving a breathing space during whichthe position in the Mediterranean may improve, and of proving the measureof M. Stalin&apos;s sincerity.4. Unless, therefore, you see objection, please inform the Turkish Govern-ment of M. Stalin&apos;s remarks in this connexion to Sir S. Cripps and enquire whether they would agree to His Majesty&apos;s Government asking the SovietGovernment to state more precisely what they have in mind.5. You should make it quite clear that in proposing this His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have no intention whatsoever of suggesting that the TurkishGovernment should renounce any of their rights under the Montreux Convention,nor that any special rights should be given to the Soviet Union. At the sametime they could not agree to waive any of their own rights as secured by theConvention.



</content>
</cab>
