<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/8/0 images: 176-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[Tliis document is the Property -of His Britanaic Majesty^ go^mmeat.) -Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1918.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 505.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10,Downing Street, S.W.,on Thursday, November 21, 1918, at 12 noon.Present:The Right. Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Austen Chamberlain,M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Assistant Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Reading,G.C.B., K.C.V.O., His Majesty&apos;s HighCommissioner and Special ambassador to the United States of America.Major-General P. P. de B. Radcliffe,C.B., D.S.O., Director of MilitaryOperations (Tor Minutes 1-3).Brigadier-General G. Iv. Cockercll, C.B.,Sub-Director of Military(for Minutes 7 and 8).IntelligenceField-Marshal the Viscount French oeYpres, K.P., G.C.B., O.M., G.C.V.O.,K.C.M.G., Lord-Lieutenant of Ireland(for Minutes 9-12).The Right Hou E. Shortt, K.C.,M.P., Chief Secretary for Ireland (for minutes 9-12).Sir L. Worthington Evans, Bart., M.P.,Minister of Blockade (for Minute 7).Rear-Admiral G. P W. Hope, C.B.,Deputy First Sea Lord (for minutes-4).The Right Hon. W. H. Long, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D.,M.P., Minister of Reconstruction (for minutes 9-13).The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., President of Local GovernmentBoard (for Minutes 9-13).The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, L.L.D.,M.P., President, Board of Education (for minutes 9-13).The Right Hon. R. E. Prothero, M.V.O.,M.P., President, Board of Agricultureand Fisheries (for Minutes 9-13).Mr. J. R. Lamb, C.B., Assistant Under-Secretary for Scotland (for Minute 12).Professor W. G. Adams (for Minutes9-12).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Major the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement.Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.
GermanIlltreatment ofBritish Prisoners.1. WITH reference to Imperial War Cabinet 37, Minute 2, theDirector of Military Operations said that the opinion at general headquarters, France, was that there had been a good deal ofexaggeration in the newspapers in regard to the German ill-treat-ment of British prisoners. In front of the British Army, only thoseprisoners who were working close up to the line, and were abandonedwhen the German Army broke, were in a destitute condition.Further back, our prisoners were in receipt of three days&apos; rations,and the enemy were doing all they could for them. It had to beremembered that the roads were blocked, and that the Germans were finding it difficult to get back themselves.The Secretary of State for the Colonies asked whether the WarOffice had received any information in regard to&apos; those british prisoners in Germany who had never yet been identified.The Director of Military Operations replied that, as far as he knew, there was no information as yet, but that he would ask the adjutant-General.Army ofOccupation.2. With reference to War Cabinet 503, Minute 1, the Directorof Military Operations said that precise information had now beenreceived respecting General Foch&apos;s dispositions in regard to theArmy of Occupation. It was proposed that 10 British divisions should be actually in German territory, and 20 British divisions in reserve in France and Belgium; there would be 17 French divisions in German territory, and 20 French divisions in reserve ; there wouldbe 9 American divisions in German territory, and 10 in reserve.General Smuts called attention to the very large number ofBritish troops which it was proposed to employ in the Army ofOccupation ; indeed, adding the 150,000 troops required for the garrisons of India and the Mediterranean to the proposed 30 divisions for the Army of Occupation, there would be very little demobilisation of the British Army at all ; yet the Committee over which he presidedwere taking steps for demobilisation.To this the Director of Military Operations replied that until it was absolutely certain that the Germans had laid down their arms, Marshal Foch could not afford to take any risks. It was reasonable to expect a relaxation in regard to the Army of Occupationlater on, perhaps by the middle of December, or Christmas, after thebridgeheads on the Rhine had been occupied.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that the wholequestion of the Army of Occupation should be discussed in France,and that the Chief of the Imperial General Staff,, after his return from his visit to Belgium, should proceed to Paris and discuss thematter there.Occupation of 3. With reference to War Cabinet 502, Minute 5, and Appendix,Batum. whereby the War Cabinet had approved, inter alia, of proceeding with the occupation of the Baku-Batum Railway, the Director ofMilitary Operations said that, in order to clear the Turks out of the. region of Batum, it wmuld be necessary to send a Division fromGeneral Milne&apos;s Army.The War Cabinet authorised The Director of Military Operations to telegraph to general milne, warning him to be prepared to send a Division toBatum as soon as the naval situation in the Black Seapermitted.The Secretary of State for the Colonies asked whether it was-proposed to use any Dominion troops in this connection, because he understood that the Dominion Commanders-in-Chief were making arrangements to repatriate their forces as soon as possible.The Director of Military Operations replied that it was not intended to use Dominion troops for the occupation of Batum.   With
Surrender of theGerman High SeasFleet.4. The Deputy First Sea Lord read to the War Cabinet a tele-gram from the Commander-in-Chief of the Grand Fleet, to the effectthat the Grand Fleet had that morning met 5 German battle cruisers, 9 battleships, 7 light cruisers, and 49 destroyers of theGerman High Seas Fleet, which had surrendered for internment andwere being brought to the Firth of Forth. Admiral Hope added that20 German submarines had surrendered to Admiral Tyrwhitt, atHarwich, on the previous day.Peace Conference:German Colonies.5. With reference to Imperial War Cabinet 37, Minute 8, theSecretary asked whether he should write to the representatives ofthe Dominions to ask them to prepare their case in regard to thecaptured German Colonies.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that the views ofthe Dominions in this matter had been expressed repeatedly, and hewould therefore like first to go through the telegrams on the subjectbefore asking the Dominion representatives to present their case.The War Cabinet decided- To leave this question to the discretion of the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.Preparation ofBrief for PeaceConference.6. With reference to War Cabinet 488, Minute 1, general smuts said that he would like to know whether the Cabinet as awhole desired to read the brief which had been written, and whichhad assumed very large proportions. He supposed that the delegates to the Peace Conference would certainly wish to read the brief, buthe did not know whether each member would want to see it.The War Cabinet decided that The  question should be deferred until further progress hadbeen made with the brief.Blockade and trading with theEnemy Policy.7. The War Cabinet had before them two Memoranda by Sir L.Worthington Evans (Papers E.D.D.C.-71 and 73) in regard toblockade questions.Mr. Chamberlain said that both these papers had been fullvdiscussed by the Economic Defence and Development Committee onthe previous day, when the Committee had recommended that thepolicy outlined in these Memoranda should be adopted by the WarCabinet.Sir L. Worthington Evans said that, if the policy were agreed to,instructions would have to be given to the Ministry of Blockade, theBoard of Trade, the Foreign Trade Department, and the War trade department. The Ministry of Blockade should then negotiate toobtain the agreement of the Associated Governments to the policy,and thereupon the other Departments should carry it out.The War Cabinet agreed to the recommendation of the EconomicDefence and Development - Committee, that the policy outlined by the Minister of Blockade in his Memorandashould be adopted.regard to the alternative of using General Allenby&apos;s troops insteadof General Milne&apos;s, the Director of Military Operations said that he did not think the troops in General Milne&apos;s force who would now besent to Batum had been away from home any longer than general allenby&apos;s troops, because, while General Milne&apos;s divisions had actually been in the East longer, individuals had changed and themalaria cases, for instance, had come home.
Relaxation of censorship Ruleswith regard toMeetings of theWar Cabinet and inter--Allied  -Conferences.8. The War Cabinet had before them a copy of a letter fromthe Director of the Press Bureau to the Secretary of the WarCabinet (Paper G.T.-6325), asking whether there could now be a relaxation of censorship rules with regard to the meetings of theWar Cabinet and the Inter-Allied Conferences.The War Cabinet agreed that the censorship in this respectshould now be removed.The Secretary asked whether the War Cabinet desired thatformal notices should be issued to the press, giving the names ofthose present at War Cabinet Meetings.The War Cabinet decided that Such notices should not be issued.Ireland and theGeneral Election:Treatment ofSinn FeinCandidates.9. The War Cabinet had under consideration a joint note by theLord-Lieutenant of Ireland and the (mief Secretary for Ireland(Paper G-.T.-6298) regarding the release of interned Sinn Feincandidates and the circulation of republican literature. This notesuggested that none of those persons at present interned should be released for the purpose of election contests, and suggested, in regardto literature, that it should be left to the Lord-Lieutenant and theChief Secretary to act as they think best in each case that might arise.The War Cabinet approved the recommendations of the Lord-Lieutenant and the Chief Secretary.Ireland:Development ofIndustrialResources.10. The War Cabinet had before them a joint memorandum bythe Lord-Lieutenant and the Chief Secretary for Ireland (paper g.T.-5858) asking for authority for the use of 2,000,000L for thepurpose of industrial and agricultural development in Ireland, suchsum to be expended in the form of loans, on the authority of theGovernment of Ireland, without reference in each particular case tothe Treasury.Mr. Short stated that it was proposed to establish a Committeeof the Irish Privy Council, to advise the Lord-Lieutenant withregard to the carrying out of the proposed schemes and othermatters, and that the scheme in question was part of a scheme forthe establishment of a definite Department of Beconstruction inIreland.   The Minister of Beconstruction, Dr. Addison, had agreed.The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out that Mr. Shortt&apos;proposal involved a big departure from ordinary Treasury practice,and until the matter had been fully examined by the Treasuryofficials he could not agree to its submission to the Cabinet forapproval.The Secretary pointed out that in War Cabinet 266, Minute 9,a somewhat similar authority had been given to the then chief secretary.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that this authority had never been utilised, and at his request The War Cabinet postponed the matter until the opinion of theTreasury could be obtained in regard to the scheme.Ireland: 11. Lord French stated that, in his view, any relaxation of theGeneral Conditions. Defence of the Realm Act at this moment would make it impossibleto govern Ireland. Similarly, any reduction of the military garrison of Ireland would be fatal. Although Ireland was superficially quiet,it was seething with discontent and rebellious intentions underneath.There bad been several cases where this rebellious feeling had brokenout.    He instanced the forcible seizure of explosives in Dublin in
August, and the more recent attack upon Cork Prison by a gang ofmen who had overpowered the warders and succeeded in liberatinga prisoner awaiting trial on the charge of shooting a policeman. Onthe whole, the&apos;re was greater public confidence throughout Ireland,owing to the strong attitude taken by the Government, and people were not so frightened of the terrorist activities of the extremesection as they had been some months ago. The police were being fully supported by the Administration and by the military, with theresult that the confidence of the police, which had been undermined,was now restored. On the whole, the machine was working well,but it was only the presence of a big force in Ireland and the supportgiven by the Administration to the police that kept the countryquiet. Although he was convinced that the present system ofgovernment would have to be changed, and some form of Home Ruleset up, he was confident that Home Rule in any form was impossible at this moment.Mr. Long stated that, owing to the policy of alternate strengthand weakness which had -been shown by successive Irish Administra-tions in the past, the public had been forced to keep one eye on theGovernment and one eye upon the rebels, in case the turn of thelatter should come. We were at the present moment passing through a most critical phase in the history of Ireland. We wereface to face with an organised movement to overthrow the Govern-ment of Ireland and to reassert the authority of a terrorist SinnFein minority. However, owing to the vork of Lord French andMr. Shortt, and more particularly owing to their support of thepolice, the authority of the law was being maintained. He hopedthat this policy would continue and would receive the support of theGovernment.Lord French and Mr. Shortt both agreed with this view.Mr. Herbert Fisher asked how large the physical force party was    Lord French and Mr. Shortt both agreed that it was small.Mr. Chamberlain pointed out that if strong government was inany way relaxed, it would not be the majority of the Irish people who would rule, but the small physical-force party.Mi&apos;. Shortt stated that, in the coming election, he thought aboutsixty Sinn Fein members would be returned at the polls, and theNationalist Party reduced to twenty. No doubt, as soon as theelections were over, the Sinn Feiners elected would ask to be released in order to come to Westminster, although they had no intention of coming to Westminster, and the present idea was to set up in ireland a Provisional Government on the lines of the Ulster ProvisionalGovernment, which had been drawn up by Sir Edward Carson in1914.Mr. Herbert Fisher asked whether there was any possibility of dividing the Sinn Fein forces.Mr. Shortt replied that, although there were certain indications that such a division was possible, it was extremely unlikely at thepresent juncture.Lord French pointed out in this connection that, whereas theTransport Workers&apos; Union had proposed to separate from Sinn Fein,they were now again working together and had come to an arrange-ment with regard to the elections.Mr. Long stated that most of the moderate men were leaving the Nationalist Party and were not seeking re-election, while evenamong those who were left there seemed to be a great many divisions.Mr. Shortt agreed with this view, and added that from the veryfirst Mr. Devlin had not been loyal to Mr. Dillon. The separation of some of the best men who had hitherto formed part of theNationalist Party at Westminster might lead to the formation of a central Party in Ireland who would co-operate with the IrishGovernment to get practical things done.Mr. Long stated that he thought the suggestion which lord french   had in mind, of setting up an Advisory Council with
statutory authority to assist, the Irish Government, would be mosthelpful, as the Government in Ireland had always been isolated frorrcontact with the Irish people, and it had been difficult for themembers of the Irish Government even to meet representativeIrishmen.The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that he had recentlyspoken to Mr. Dillon and Mr. T. P. O&apos;Connor, who had agreed thatfor the present nothing could be done in regard to Ireland otherthan to enforce the law.Provision of Land 12. The War Cabinet had before then the Report (Paper G.-225)for Settlement and of Lor(j Cave&apos;s Committee appointed by War Cabinet 412, Minute 3,other Purposes. Qn the 15th Ma^ 191Q^ m regard to the provisjon Gf land for soldierson demobilisation.Dr. Addison read to the Cabinet the main provisions recommendedby the Committee, and urged the approval of the Report of theCommittee.Mr. Prothero stated that, while he was in agreement with thedecisions of the Committee, he thought that the proposals were quite inadequate for dealing with the critical situation which had now arisen owing to the signing of the armistice and the comingGeneral Election. He thought that the proposals of the Committeewould not enable the Government to get land quickly enough or insufficient quantities. He hoped that the Government would face thequestion in real earnest, and would be prepared to lay out a sum of anything from 20,000,000Z. to 30,000,000Z. in the first year for theacquisition and equipment of land through the County Councils.The State would have to undertake to pay, at the end of eachfinancial year, the difference between receipts and expenditure. Theguarantee of a large sum now was the only thing which could savewhat had now amounted to an emergency situation. He had beenendeavouring to see the Prime Minister in regard to this question,and had taken this, which was the first opportunity to raise this new proposal.Mr. Long said that he agreed with Mr. Protherp that the wholeof this question would be raised at the Election in a difficult form,and that the problem must be faced immediately. With regard tothe proposed utilisation of County Councils, he feared that while, onthe whole, the County Councils had done excellent public work,there was suspicion of them in many quarters, and he urged thatin ever3&apos; county composite bodies, containing nominated members aswell as County Councillors, should be appointed to carry through some such scheme as had been suggested by Mr. Prothero. It wasalso desirable that any money granted for equipment should beavailable as much for land provided voluntarily as for land acquired by County Councils.Mr. Shortt asked whether Ireland was excluded from the pro-visions outlined in the Report of Lord Cave&apos;s Committee, as he would very much like several of the proposals, such as those in connectionwith reclamation, afforestation, and the provision of agriculturalcredit, extended to Ireland.Dr: Addison replied that, for the present, it had not been pro-posed to extend the provisions to Ireland.The War Cabinet approved the proposals of Lord Cave&apos;sCommittee (Paper G.-225) and of Mr. Long&apos;s suggestion with regardto grants for equipment, and requested Lord Cave&apos;s Committee to meet at the earliest possible date,and, if possible, daily, to consider and report upontheproposal made that day to the Cabinet by Mr. Prothero,, with a view to their arriving at an early decision in thematter.
Committee on 13. The &apos; War Cabinet took  note   of the   Prime  MinistersHome Affairs. decision To appoint Mr. Herbert Fisher to be Acting Chairman of theCommittee on Home Affairs, and to appoint Sir auckland geddes to be a member of the Committee in theplace ofLord Downham.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,21st November, 1918.oThe War Cabinet further decided To add Sir Auckland Geddes to the Committee.


</content>
</cab>
