<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/149/0 images: 27-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fefc DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT)C(70) 43 COPY NO.   6310th March. 1970CABINETIMALTA: AGREEMENT ON FINANCIAL assistance memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign aridCommonwealth Affairs and the Secretary of State for DefenceBackgroundWhen the question of financial aid to Malta was discussed in Cabineton 1st May, 1969 (CC(69) 20th Conclusions), it was decided that we should stand firm on the offer, originally made in January, 1969, of a division ofthe remaining  23 million due to Malta for the second five years of theFinancial Agreement in the ratio of 50 per cent granfc:50 per cent loan.This decision was taken in the belief that, if we made it quite clear that wewere not prepared to make further concessions, the Malta Governmentwould reluctantly accept these terms.    Our proposals v/ere formulated inan aide memoire of 8th May, 1969 (Annex ).      Dr. Borg Olivier refused toaccept them and has not altered his position since.    Meanwhile no aid fundshave flowed to Malta since 31st.March, 1969.2,      We have in the meantime explored the possibility of establishinginterim arrangements for one or two years, within the framework of the50:50 basis over the whole five years, which might tide Dr. Borg Olivierover until his general election (which has to be held at l&amp;tesfc by mid 1971),leaving for the time being the question of the ultimate settlement under the1964 Aid Agreement.    Lord Robens, Chairman of the Joint steering committee for Malta, also put forward similar proposals designed to allowcash to flow for approved development projects in advance of a settlement ofthe dispute.   Here again Dr. Borg Olivier has not been prepared to accept any proposals for an interim settlement except on a basis that would give him nearly all the money he wanted in the form of grant during the first two years.    These initiatives have consequently come to nothing and there appears no future in pursuing them.3,      We are thus left in the position that after more than a yearDr. Borg Olivier has not accepted the 50:50 offer put to him in January, 1969and reaffirmed by the Cabinet in May, and proposals for interim arrangements have brought us no nearer a resolution of the aid negotiations.
Prospects for agreement4.       There are not now, any more than when the Cabinet considered thequestion in May, &quot;1969, good economic grounds for making aid available on more generous terms than 50 per cent grant:50 per cent loan.    But thecrux of the matter is political, not economic.    It is politically impossiblefor Dr. Borg Olivier to accept less favourable terms for the secondfive years of the Financial Agreement than applied for the first(i.e. 75 per cent grant.25 per cent loan).    Dr. Borg Olivier told theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary as much in London on 15th May, 1969;on 23rd September he stated in the Malta Parliament that &quot;the British offeris not an adequate basis for the second five years of the financial agreement&quot;, and in a statement to Parliament on 11th February this yearhe said that his Government &quot;would not be cowed by the suspension ofBritish aid&quot;.    This bears out the view of our High Commissioner inValletta that Dr. Borg Olivier would prefer to defy us and borrow the moneyhe needs locally rather than capitulate.Strategic and political importance of Malta5.      As our purely national requirements in Malta have declined (theonly remaining major operation in support of a national obligation which we might have mounted from Malta was under our 1953 Treaty commitment toLibya, which of course no longer applies), the abiding interest in the Islandis primarily a NATO one.    The importance of this, however, is increasing.The expanding Russian naval presence in the Mediterranean, together withthe actual and potential use by the Prussian navy and air force of facilities in Egypt and Algeria to support and consolidate that presence, has been amatter of great concern to us and to NATO for some time.    This concernhas recently been further increased by the revolution in Libya which hasmade it very much more difficult than before to prevent that country fromcoming under hostile influence, with the result that most of the North Africancoastline is potentially hostile.    We need to consolidate all theMediterranean footholds where the West at present still has an advantage over the Soviet Union,6.      NATO will thus have both a positive and a negative interest in Maltain the future.    The positive interest is to preserve the use of defence facilities in the Island which will be of Increasing importance as a meansof countering the Russian military presence.    These facilities include, ona very tenuous basis of agreement between NATO and Malta, the NATOnaval headquarters for the Mediterranean, our base, communications and radar facilities used by NATO (use of the radar facility in particularis a valuable extension southwards of the NATO air warning system); above all there are the facilities available to us under the Defence agreement which will be used primarily by maritime reconnaisance, air defence andstrike aircraft deployed in support of NATO Mediterranean naval forces.The NATO interest has newly been brought out again in a recent report to the nato Commander in Chief for the Southern Region.    The reports firstconclusion is thats
&quot;The location of Malta in its dominant position in the central mediterranean is a powerful influence on the security of the linesof communication throughout that sea.    The availability of itsfacilities could influence the security of the southern flank of nato and have an impact on allied naval operations in theMediterranean&quot;.Studies in the Ministry of Defence have shown that these facilities cannoteasily or cheaply be reprovided elsewhere (in Sicily or Southern Kaly8for example).    Nor, for reasons of politics and geography, can existing facilities in Cyprus or Gibraltar substitute for those in Malta.7,      The negative interest is even more important; it is to deny Malta to the Russians and to keep the Island firmly linked with the West,    It wouldbe militarily a very serious matter if the Russians were enabled toestablish or to use bases in Malta; and politically it would be a resoundingblow to NATO*o and our own prestige if Malta, which has for so long been so closely linked with the West, were to turn neutralist.    It would seriouslyundermine the confidence of the Mediterranean members of the Alliance,who are in any case not the most robust.    If Malta were subsequently luredinto the Soviet camp, the effects would, of course, be still more serious.Political considerations8,      It is therefore most important that, by the time our Defence and finance Agreements with Malta expire in 1974, a much closer associationshould have been established between Malta and NATO, and that our ownresponsibilities in the Island should have been transferred to the Alliance.We are considering separately how best to achieve this; but it is alreadyclear that the key will be the manner in which our own relationship withMalta is allowed to develop over the next three or four years.    This in turndepends on our attitude to the question of aid.    Already the secretary general of NATO has several times expressed his concern that no solutionhas been found to the disagreement between Her Majesty-^ Government andthe Malta Government.9.      The matter is becoming increasingly urgent, as the malta government have borrowed heavily from the Central Bank to finance currentdevelopment and are due to repay the loans by 31st March; the 1970-71budget is due to be introduced in early April; and Mr. Mintoff is taking advantage of the Malta Governments difficulties.    For domestic political reasons in Malta, therefore, a settlement becomes no easier as timepasses.    Unless a settlement is quickly reached on terms acceptablewithout loss of face to Dr. Borg Olivier, the position of the malta government will be much more difficult and the prospects of retaliatory action more likely.    If the financial aid dispute remains unresolved, thereare real risks of a serious souring of our relations with the Maltese, oftheir deciding to forgo our aid altogether and of their ceasing to provide facilities under the Defence Agreement.-3-
10.      Mr. Mintoff has repeatedly declared his refusal to co-operate withNATO.    Under a Government led by him, the best we could expect wouldbe to retain the use of our facilities in Malta only on a national basis (withthe consequent loss of any prospect of shifting the financial burden orsharing it with our Allies), and then probably only to a restricted extent and at a high price.    Thus on present form, our longer term objective of associating Malta more closely with NATO will stand a much better chanceof being realised if Dr. Borg Olivier continues as Prime Minister.    this in turn would be more likely if he were to emerge without dishonour fromthe aid negotiations, which have become a key election issue.    If we canreach a settlement over aid and follow this up by persuadingDr. Borg Olivier&apos; to move in the direction of a closer association betweenMalta and NATO, Mr. Mintoff, if he wins the election, might find itdifficult to repudiate these engagements.    In any case, we should continueto control the disbursement of fundsj thus, in the event of a refusal to implement the present Defence Agreement, which lasts until 1974, weshould be entitled to curtail or suspend aid, since the operation of the aid Agreement depends upon the continued implementation of the DefenceAgreements11.      By corning to terms with Dr. Borg Olivier now over the aid agreement there would be no question of our acting in a partisan way.The Opposition in Malta is even more vociferous than the Government inproclaiming that a settlement is overdue, and public opinion is united with both Government and Opposition in believing that United Kingdom aid is inpart a return for the continued use of military facilities.    Feelings are beginning to run high.    If we do not reach what can be represented in malta as a fair settlement, this will work directly against our defence interests.    It will provide a grievance which, whoever becomes PrimeMinister, would at the best be an embarrassment to him and at worst give him a stick to beat us with.    Playing for time will not help us to get better terms;  on the contrary, now that this is becoming a public electoral issue,we can expect the Maltese attitude in all matters to harden and their thoughtsto turn to retaliation rather than compromise.12.      These are risks which we ought not to take.    We would certainlyfind it difficult to explain to public opinion in this country, and to our NATOAllies, why we were prepared to jeopardise the military facilities in malta and the whole of Malta *s long term relationship with the West, for the sake of what would be seen as a comparatively small sum of money, (in practice 5. 75 million over a period of five years).Conclusions13.      We therefore consider that v/e should now seek to reach a finalaccommodation with Dr. Borg Olivier.    In our view this means that weshould be prepared to offer up to 75 per cent grantj25 per cent loan overall,although we should naturally try to secure better terms.
14.      It should also be our aim during the course of negotiations to reachfavourable understandicgs with Dr. Borg Olivier about the detailed arrangements for the continued use of the airfield at Luqa (due for review),the question of payment for the transfer of equipment (to the value of about 300, 000) to the Malta Land Force, and a closer association of Malta withNATO.Recommendation15.      In our view the importance of Malta and the risks attendant on a failure of the financial aid negotiations justify our being prepared to offerup to 75 per cent grantj25 per cent loan overall, if necessary, to secure asatisfactory conclusion to the negotiations, and we invite our colleagues1agreement to proceed on that basis.M.S.D.W.H.Foreign and Commonwealth Office, S. W.1,10th March, 1970
Annex &amp;Following is text of Aide Memoire handed to Dr. BergOlivier&apos;s Advisers in London on 8 May.The British Government have given careful study to the aide Memoire conveyed to the British High Commission in Vallettaon 1 April.The British Government have noted the considerations whichit appears from the Malta Government^ Aide Memoire were takeninto account by them in reaching their conclusion that theoffer made to the Prime Minister of Malta by the Minister of overseas Development on 16 January was unsatisfactory.      In theview of the British Government, these considerations are notwell founded.In the first place, the British Government are unable toaccept the contention that the rundown vjf the British forces in malta is being carried out otherwise than in strict accordancewith the Agreement on Mutual Defence and Assistance of21 September &apos;19oh.Secondly, the Malta Government will recall that it was inorder to meet their apprehensions regarding the problems thatmight flow from their decision to reduce British forces in malta that, in March, 1967, after further consultation with the malta Government,  the British Government subsequently modifiedthe rundown programme.     The modifications to the programmethat were then conceded will result in additional defence expenditure in Malta of  10 million in the period of therundowno     Their subsequent decisions to station in Maltacertain R.A0Fo aircraft and to increase their naval presence in the Mediterranean are making a further contribution to the maltese economy.
Thirdly, the British Government ce-operated with the malta government in establishing the Joint Mission for Malta whichwas charged with reporting means of strengthening Malta&apos;industrial base and creating additional employment, and which led to the establishment of the Joint Steering Committee.     Ithas been the latter&apos;s task to report on progress achieved onthe recommendations of the Joint Mission and to make recommendations to the two Governments as to the remedial measures that should be taken by either of them to counteracteconomic and social problems arising from the rundown ofBritish forces in Malta, with particular reference to the absorption and re-training of persons becoming redundant.     ThejSritish Government regard it as significant that on 31  March,19o9, after two years, the number of Maltese registered asunemployed as a result of the rundown was only 93? of whom\S were undergoing training courses and 22 were awaiting suchcourses.Finally, the British Government have noted that, accordingto the annual report of the Central Bank of Malta and thefigures quoted by the Malta Minister of Finance in presentinghis budget last month, all aspects of the Maltese economy have continued to make rapid progress.     Thus between 1967 and 1 968gross national product, private consumption, bank deposits and malta&apos;s official external reserves all made significantincreases.      Meanwhile the Malta Minister of Labour is reported as saying on 28 January, 1969 that, during 1969 and 1970, the expected additional demand for labour would be very close tothe additional supply.      In these circumstances the BritishGovernment are unable to follow the suggestion in the MaltaGovernments Aide Memoire that there is any case for the BritishGovernment further to offset the effects of the rundown.The British Government cannot accept the Malta Governmentssuggestion that the Agreement on Mutual Defence and assistance and the Agreement on Financial Assistance should now be revised.Nor would it be possible for them ta make any payments to the malta Government otherwise than on the basis of the FinancialAssistance Agreement.     But the British Government, for their- 2 -CONFIDENTIAL
part, have at all times been ready and willing to make thepayments to the Malta Government that are contemplated by that agreement and in particular they are prepared to resume withoutdelay the uncompleted discussions with the Malta government over the various matters which, under the Agreement, have tobe settled between the two Governments before such paymentscan be made.     As regards the particular question of therelative proportions of gift and loan far the five yearp ending31  March, 197U, they regret that they are unable to go beyond their offer of an offer of an overall division of 50% gift,5O70 loan0     This offer which in the British Governments view is fair and generous to the Malta Government, remains open.On this basis, they would be glad to arrange the earlyresumption of the incompleted discussions.


</content>
</cab>
