<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/149/0 images: 226-228</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENTSTARTING DATE FOR THE EARNINGS-RELATEDPENSIONS scheme memorandum by the Secretary of State for Social services in the White Paper on the Earnings-Related Pensions Scheme,published in January 196% the target date for the introduction of the new scheme was given as April 1972, although it was realised that this would present an extremely tight timetable both for drafting the Bill and gettingit through Parliament, and for the administrative preparations requiredto introduce changes of the magnitude involved for the Government machine and for employers generally, including in particular the consequent amend-ment of occupational schemes to adapt them to the new State scheme.2.      The Government^ own administrative preparations are well advanced but there have been increasingly strong representations from therepresentative bodies concerned with occupational pension schemes -notably the Life Offices Association, the National Association of PensionFunds and the Corpcwtation   of Insurance Brokers Society of PensionConsultants - urging deferment on the grounds that it will not be possibleto achieve the necessary modification of occupational schemes for anApril 1972 start.    Occupational schemes will need to accommodatethemselves, not only to the new Government pension scheme, but also tothe requirements as to the preservation of occupational pension rights,and to the new tax provisions incorporated in this year&apos;s Finance Bill.They will be faced with formidable financial, administrative and legalproblems which will throw a very heavy strain on the limited number of expert advisers in this field - over 60,000 individual schemes will beaffected - and they are convinced that the necessary work of examination and modification cannot be completed in time for a 1972 start.    Theyemphasize the need to allow time for adequate consultation with themembers of occupational schemes about the prospective changes.    they also point to the difficulties of persuading employers, in present electoralcircumstances, to make an early start in preparing for the new scheme.3,      While in public pronouncements up to now I have adhered to April 1972as the target date, I have also made it clear that I was considering very carefully the representations made to me.    In the light of the case now made by organisations concerned with occupational pensions, and inparticular because of the need for adequate consultation with employeesC(70) 60COPY NO11th May, 1970CABINET1
over amendment of occupational schemes, I consider that April 1972 is nolonger a realistic target date.    Since the new scheme must start at thebeginning of a tax year, this means a full year rs deferment to April 1973.4.      We cannot, without harmful consequences, postpone much longer a firm announcement on the starting date of the new scheme - certainly notbeyond mid-June.    In view of the publicity given to the problems facingoccupational pension schemes, it is becoming increasingly difficult tomaintain the credibility of 1972.    Both we and employers have a great dealof planning to do and much machinery and other equipment to order, andit is essential to have a firm date for this purpose.    Moreover, we haveshortly to send to print certain leaflets for publication as soon as the Billreceives Royal Assent, which will have to contain a starting date,Implications of deferment5.      It seems likely that there is a general expectation among those withdirect knowledge of the problems that the starting date will have to be deferred.    The Trades Union Congress will regret deferment, but attachas much importance as we do to adequate consultation with employees on changes in occupational schemes, which would be impracticable with a 1972starting date.    So far as benefits are concerned, the increased ratespayable under the new scheme will emerge only gradually over the first twenty years and a year&apos;s deferment will not be very significant, assuming,as I intend, that the introduction of the attendance allowance (the newbenefit . for the very severely disabled) and the improved pension provisionfor widows under 5 0 would still start in April 1972.    So far as contributionsare concerned deferment will no doubt come as a relief to some of those whose contribution rates would be increased under the new scheme(particularly for employed married women who will be brought incompulsorily for the first time);   it will be regretted by others who see a prospect of a reduction in their contribution rate.    The deferment of theintroduction of the main earnings-related scheme need not, however, imply any deferment of the introduction of full preservation of pension rights in occupational schemes; we have all along made it clear that this require -ment would not become effective until some yaars after 1972.     The effecton expenditure of deferment of the earnings-related scheme to 1973 wouldbe to postpone frcm 1973-74 to 1974-75 expenditure of the order of 90 million - very largely the extra cost of unemployment and sickness benefit for married women brought compulsorily into insurance by the new scheme.6.      I seek the agreement of my colleagues to an announcement duringReport Stage of the National Superannuation and Social Insurance Bill(immediately after the Whitsun Recess) -.that the general starting date forthe new scheme will be April 1973.    I would propose at the same time tomake it clear that the deferment would not apply to the introduction ofattendance allowance or to the improved pension provision for widows under50, both of which would start in April 1972,RHSCDepartment of Health and Social Sec*H?%, SE1Hth May, 19702


</content>
</cab>
