<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/149/0 images: 300-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
llS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER. BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS government 9C(70) 68 COPY NO    b d27 May 1970CABINETTHE QUEENTS SPEECH ON THE prorogation of parliament memorandum by the Lord President of the council. I attach a draft of The QueenTs Speech on the Prorogation ofParliament, which has been prepared by the Group of Ministers consideringarrangements for the Dissolution of Parliament and takes account of theviews expressed by Ministers in charge of Departments.2, In some cases the draft assumes the completion of business whichat present is still unfinished.    The only substantial uncertainty concerns the reference in paragraph 31 to increasing the security of occupants of tiedcotfcages.    This will have to be deleted if we find that we must accept an opposition amendment made in the Lords on the subject, which is likely;we shall know later today.3. In order that the Prime Minister may submit a final draft forThe Queen*s approval this evening, I should be grateful if colleagues would let me have any final comments by 5. 00 pm today, 27 May.    I am sorrythat the timetable does not allow for a more leisurely consideration.T F privy Council Office SW127 May 1970
THE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OP PARLIAMENT:MY. LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OP commons.     My husband and I and The Princess Anne had the great pleasure ofvisiting New Zealand and Australia and of attending the Cook BicentenaryCelebrations in both countries,,   V/e were also very pleased to visitSiji and Tonga,    The Prince of Wales was able to accompany us to new Zealand and on part of our tour to Australia.2.     My Government have maintained their application for membership of the European Communities, and negotiations to this end are likelyto open shortly,3. My Ministers have made a full contribution to the North atlantic alliance, which is the foundation of our security, and have sought todevelop better understanding between East and West.4.     My Government have continued to play an active part in thedisarmament negotiations and have followed up with vigour their proposals for a complete ban on biological methods of warfare.     Theywelcome the entry into force of the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of nuclear Weapons.5,     My Government have urgently pursued their efforts to promotethrough the United Nations a settlement to the dispute between theArab states and Israel, and have continued their efforts to help bringpeace to the countries of Indo-China.6.     My Government welcomed the end of hostilities in Nigeria, and havemade a substantial contribution to post-war relief and rehabilitation.
CONFIDENTIAL^7.     My Government have welcomed the condemnation by the security council of the latest racialist policies of the illegal rof;i...e in southern Rhodesia.     They have worked to make existing economic sanctions more effective.8.     My Government welcomed the peaceful settlement, through the good offices of the Secretary-General of the United Nations, of the long-standing difference with the Imperial Iranian Government over Bahrain.9.     New Constitutions have been introduced in the British SolomonIslands Protectorate and the Seychelles.   Tonga will cease to be aProtected State on 4 June and My Government look forward towelcoming her as a Commonwealth partner.10. In this 25th Anniversary Year of the United Nations iiy Governmentis taking a leading part in promoting its work.11.   My Government have announced substantial increases in oversoasaid for the next three years.12.   My Ministers have continued their efforts to promote peace andharmony in Northern Ireland.   Acts have been passed to establish the Ulster Defence Regiment and to enable police forces in GreatBritain to be more closely associated with the Royal ulster constabulary.MMBiWS OV THri HOUSiS OP COMMONS13.   I thank you for the provision which you have made for thepublic services.2C
MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS14-.   My Government have pursued successful policies to strengthen the economy and the balance of payments so as to provide the basis for sustained and accelerating growth in conditions of highemployment.   A large surplus in the balance of payments has been achieved, and external indebtedness has been greatly reduced.15.   My Government have continued to work with other governments toimprove the international monetary system.16.   A statement has been presented to you on My Government&apos;s futureplans for public expenditure.17.   The pay structure of my Armed Forces has been radically revised to give proper recognition to their qualifications and responsibilities.18L   An Act has been passed providing for equal, pay for men and women.19.   My Government have proposed major reforms to modernise industrial relations.20.   Legislation was introduced to establish a Commission for industry and Manpower to take over and develop the work of theNational Board for Prices and Incomes and the Monopolies Commission.21.   A Bill was introduced to make certain reforms relating to industrial safety and health and an inquiry into all aspects of thesubject has been set up.3f CONFIDENTIAL J
L22.   Acts have been passed to promote greater safety and iiarrcvecliving conditions for those serving in the Merchant Navy and fishing fleetse,23.    An Act has been passed to assist the film industry.24.    Regional economic development has been further encouraged,especially in the development areas, and legislation has been passed to assist intermediate areas and to encourage the speedy clearariceof derelict land.25. Bills were introduced to reorganise the electricity supply industry and the gas industry, and to enable the G-as Council to search for, market and refine petroleum.26.   A Bill was introduced to continue the Government1 s powers toassist the coal industry.27. Legislation was brought forward to raise the limit on guaranteesunder the Shipbuilding Credit Scheme.23. A Bill was introduced to transfer the ::u clear fuel and radio-chemical business of the United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority toGovernment-controlled companies.2CJ.    A Bill to reorganise the ports was presented, to you.30.   My Government, have [JublJshod piano lor- the future strategy i&apos;oi*inter-urban roads in England.4
31.     My Government have continued to encourage the selective expansion ofhome agriculture.    An Act has been passed introducing new arrangements forthe marketing of eggs;   rationalising the grants payable to assist fixed capital investment in agriculture;   and increasing the security ofoccupants of tied cottages.32.     My Government have continued to take steps to restrain increases in food prices and to promote the safety of food for the consumer.33.     My Government have brought forward a measure to provide strong,comprehensive and flexible powers to control the availability of dangerousdrugs and to check their misuse.34.     A Bill was presented to advance further the reorganisation of secondary education on comprehensive lines.     Progress has been made inreplacing old schools, increasing the numbers of qualified teachers and reducing oversized classes.35*     the expansion of higher education has continued, and student placesprovided have far exceeded the forecasts of the Robbins Committee on higher Education.36.     My Government have announced further proposals to intensify the fight against the pollution of the environment, and measures were introduced toreduce aircraft noise and to discourage pollution of the sea by oil.   I have appointed a Commission on Environmental 1ollution.37.     My G-overnment have put forward proposals to reform local governmentin England and Wales.38.     An Act has been passed to limit increases in rents of local authority and private tenants.    Assistance to home buyers under the option mortgagescheme has been increased, and other measures have been taken to provide more and better homes.     Orders have been made to raise the income limits which govern the entitlement to rate rebate.
39.   Proposals for controlling labour-only sub-contracting in t:-econstruction industry were laid before you.40.   An Act has been passed to reorganise local authority personal social services.   New proposals have been made for the future administration of the National Health Service in England and in wales.41. Improvements in existing health and welfare services have continued, with special emphasis on hospitals for the mentally handicapped and other long-stay patients.42.   Proposals have been put before you for new schemes of national superannuation and social insurance based on earnings-relatedcontributions.43.   My GroVernment have taken steps to make further improvements inthe levels of benefits provided under the Supplementary BenefitsScheme.44.   Legislation has been passed to reform the feudal system inScotland and the Scottish law of heritable conveyancing.45,   An Act has been passed to modernise the law re-latins; to theconstruction of highways in Scotland.46.   An Act has been passed to reconstitute the High Court with a family Division;    to extend the power to dispense with t.&apos;ie holding of assizes;   and to iinprovo the arrangements for Lin; recovery ofcivil debts.o
(CON	IFI	DEN1	riAi)47.   Further advances have been made in the reform of the law.Legislation has been passed to extend the powers of the courts to make financial provision in matrimonial disputes and to giveeffect to various proposals of the Law Commission.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF commons I pray that the blessing of Almighty G-od may attend you.7(CONFIDENTIAL )

</content>
</cab>
