<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/155/2 images: 10-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTCF(7l) 2 COPY no January 1971CABINETRHODESIA; EXCHANGES WITH MR, StiitTHNote by the Secretary of State for Foreign andCommonweakh affairs at our meeting on 19 November 1970 (CM(70) 39th Conclusions,Minute 2) I said that the Rhodesian reply to cur first communication hadbeen disappointingly negative, but that we should not regard this asputting an end to these exchanges.    The Rhodesian reply (Annex A) to oursecond communica.tion (A&amp;nex B) reached London on Christmas Eve,   It is considerably less terse than its predecessor.     It rejects the Fearlesstalks as a starting point for future discussions and makes it clear that,in the Rhodesian view, the 1969 Constitution is the only possible basis for discussion,    There is no mention of the principles and, inparticular, of that of unimpeded progress to majority rule which Iemphasised and asked Mr. Smith to reflect upon in our first communication of 3 November.    The reply does, however, tscMy agree to consider thosechanges to the 1969 Constitution which Her Majesty !s Government would consider necessary fox a settlement and asks for a statement of these,2,     E we now formally accept that the 1969 Gons&amp;ifaa^&amp;on could be the starting point for a negotiation, this would be a major concession toMr. Smith.    Although it is becoming fairly clear that unless we do, nonegotiation will be possible, I believe that we should make a further effort to probe Mr. Smith&apos;s attitude to the points of principle which must beestablished as the basis for any negotiation before we decide to make this concession.3.     There seems to be advantage in sending a further letter to Mr. Smithbefore the Singapore Conference provided that we can be reasonably sure that it is not likely to provoke an announcement by him that he considersthere is no further point in these exchanges.     The attached draft reply(Annex C) should avoid this risk,    It goes some way to accepting thatthe 1969 Constitution could be the point of departure for any negotiations,but does not formally concede this at this stage.4,     1 . my colleagues approve the proposed reply I would arrange for itto be sent by HM Ambassador in Pretoria about the end of this week.A. D-foreign and Commonwealth Office, SW14 January 1971
ANNEX a text OP LETTER PROM AIR VICE MARSHAL HAWKINSTO HM AMBASSADOR, PRETORIA, DATED 21 DECEMBER 1970I am directed &quot;by the Rhodesian Government to reply to your letter of the lhth December in the following terms.At the time of the ^Fearless&apos; talks the constitution in force in Rhodesia was the 19&amp;5 Constitution, which hadbeen accorded de jure recognition by the Rhodesian Courts.If the two Governments had reached an agreement which necessi-tated changes in the Rhodesian Constitution, that constitution would have required amendment by the Rhodesian Parliament.It was made clear to the British Government that if no agreement was reached in the course of those negotiations the rhodesian government would itself prepare a new Constitution which v/ould be designed to meet the long-term needs of Rhodesia,In due course this was done and a referendum of the electoral,was held in June 1969.    This referendum resulted in overwhelmingsupport for the proposed new Constitution and for the assumption of republican status.    The new republican Constitution came  ;into effect on 2nd March, 1970, and among its provisions were increased and more effective African representation in theAssembly and the introduction of a Senate, the membership ofwhich includes ten African Chiefs.    The new Constitution was clearly accepted by the population as a whole and the numberof Africans who cast their votes in the general election which followed was greater than in any previous election.    It wasalso accorded full de jure recognition by the Rhodesian Courts.Although de jure recognition has been withheld by the BritishGovernment there can be no doubt, five years after its assumption of independence, as to the de facto status of the rhodesian government and Constitution,- 1 -SECRET AND PERSONAL
It was in the light of the foregoing that the suggestion :was made in the letter of 13th November that a suitable starting point for negotiations would &quot;be the factual position thatRhodesia is now an independent sovereign republic.    Theconstitutional situation in Rhodesia has altered fundamentallysince the previous British Government &quot;broke off negotiations and it would be unrealistic not to recognise this fact.   Itwould therefore be equally unrealistic to attempt to resume negotiations at the point where they were broken off.The letter of 13th November was not intended to mean thatthe Rhodesian Government do not wish to pursue the possibilityof negotiations.    The intention was to propose a realistic and practical starting point for such negotiations, having regardto the altered circumstances in Rhodesia.The Rhodesian Government believe that changes in thepresent Constitution are neither necessary nor desirable.The constitution was designed to foster racial harmony andto further the interests of all sections of the population.This objective is clearly being achieved, because the relationsbetween the races have at no time been better than they are today.The Rhodesian Government would therefore be reluctant to makeany changes which might prejudice the present satisfactoryposition, particularly if these were being made with thedubious aim of endeavouring to placate outside opinion.    Theyappreciate, however, that the British Government may wish tosuggest changes and for their part the Rhodesian Governmentwould welcome a complete statement of those changes which theBritish Government suggest are necessary.The British Government have pointed out that any settlementmust be one that they can commend to the British parliament.Equally the Rhodesian Government must make it clear, not only that any changes to the new Constitution must be such that the rhodesian Government can commend them to the Rhodesian parliament,but also that they would have to be passed by a two-thirds majority.- 2 -SECRET AND PERSONAL
ANNEX B.TEXT OP LETTER PROM HM AMBASSADOR, PRETORIATO AIR VICE MARSHAL HAWKINS, DATED 14 DECEMBER 1970I am instructed by Sir Alec Douglas-Home to reply to your letter of 14 November.Sir Alec is confident that Mr. Smith and his colleagues will realise it is out of the question for the British Governmentto accept as the starting point for any negotiations &quot;thatRhodesia is an independent Sovereign Republic&quot;.   No countryin the world recognises this.   Nor are any likely to unlessthe British Parliament is able to legislate as a result ofagreement between Britain and Rhodesia.   The purpose therefor of a negotiation would be to find a settlement which her Majesty&apos;s Government could then commend to the british parliament and which would enable Rhodesia to achieve that international recognition which will otherwise continue to be denied her.    The consequences would in Sir Alec&apos;s view betragic if the opportunity to achieve such a settlement were not taken now.   There will not in his opinion be another chance.He would therefore be grateful if you would seekconfirmation that the message in your letter of 14 november was not intended to mean that Mr. Smith and his colleaguesdo not wish to pursue the possibility of negotiations.    I amasked to add in relation to the reference to the RhodesianParliament in your letter of 14 November, that Sir Aleclsconcern at this time is not with questions of constitutionalmethod or formulation, but with establishing whether thereexists a sufficient degree of common ground on principle and intention to enable realistic negotiations to take place as Sir Alec suggested in his first letter, the &apos;Pearless&apos;talks took place on the assumption of unimpeded progress toSECRET AND PERSONAL
majority rule.    There was no timetable, but the principle was preserved.    If the degree of agreement which had been achieved in those talks could be the starting point for freshnegotiations it would greatly reduce the area for discussion and it should be possible to reach a settlement without undue delay.Alternatively, if Mr. Smith wishes to propose, some other basis of negotiation Sir Alec would be interested to know hisviewsoSir Alec hopes therefore that Mr. Smith will respond tothese enquiries so that a basis for discussion may be found.Once such a basis is established it should be possible tosettle without difficulty the method of negotiation which willmost surely bring the result which both sides would like to see.^ 2 -SECRET AND PERSONAL
CCrDCTannex cDRAFT LETTER TO H.M. AMBASSADOR, PRETORIA,TO AIR VICE-MARSHAL HAWKINSI am instructed by Sir Alec Douglas-Home to reply to your letter of 21 December.Sir Alec was glad to learn that your previous letterof 13 November was not intended to convey that Mr. Smithdid not wish to pursue the possibility of negotiations.     Hispurpose in suggesting that the common ground which was established during the Fearless talks could be the starting point for fresh negotiations was in order to reduce the area for discussion^     This would have made it easier to reach agreement;    indeed he would like to emphasise once more that agreement on that bosis could be rapid.     Since howeverMr, Smith considers that this would not be practicable inpresent circumstances, Sir Alec would be prepared to accept that any discussions designed to achieve a settlement could have a different point of departure.As my letter of 1k December indicated, Sir Alec&apos;s priorconcern is that of establishing whether there exists asufficient degree of common ground on principle and intentionto enable realistic negotiations to take place.    Your letterimplies that Mr. Smith would be prepared to contemplateamendment of the 1969 Constitution.   That Constitutionprovides for parity of representation as its ultimate goal;but as Mr0 Smith is aware, the British Government are publiclycommitted to seeking a settlement on the principle ofunimpeded progress to majority rule6    It would help sir Alec,in considering whether a fresh starting point for realisticnegotiations can be found, to know whether Mr. Smith acceptsthat any such negotiations v/ould have as one of their objectives the amendment of the 1969 Constitution so as to accord with this principle *- 1 -
There are a. number of statements in your letter which sir Alec could not accept or endorse;    hut if an understandingcan he reached on the initial point of principle referred toabove, he believes it should be possible to find a way tomake further progress.The objective in any negotiations which may take place would certainly be to find a basis for settlement whichwould foster racial harmony and further the interests ofall sections of the population of Rhodesia,,     Sir Alecbelieves that changes can be worked out and that the objectives can be assured on a lasting basis, provided talkscan be started with the negotiators, sharing the same aimeIt is his view, in face of the growing disparity in numbers,that it will not be possible in the longer term to createcircumstances in which it is to the advantage of all races towork together^ through parties based on political principlesrather than on race, unless the principle of unimpededprogress to majority rule is accepted,,


</content>
</cab>
