<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/61/0 images: 87-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[j^OOTJMBHT IS TKB PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAITi&quot;IC MAJESTYTS QOVERLMENT) ,IrJLfi B T- Copy No.C A B I N E T    27  (29).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat%0, Downing Street, S.W.1., onWEDNESDAY,  July Jjrd,  1929,  at11.0 a,m.* * *PRESENT;-The Right Hon.  J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P. ,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).Right Hon.dPhilip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.HI Right Hon.&quot;1J.H. Thomas, M.P. ,[Lord Privy Seal.phe Right Hon.I Lord Parmoor of Frieth, K.C.V.O.IK.C., Lord President of theIGouncil.[The Right Hon.[J.R. Glynes, M.P. , Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.II Right Hon.Tom Shaw, C.B.E.,M.P.,Secretary of State forWar.pie Right Hon.gArthur Greenwood, M.P. ,BHinister of Health.II Right Hon.INoel Buxton, M.P., Ministerof Agriculture and FisherieEpe Right Hon.\ William Graham, M,P. ,president of the BoardHI of Trade.11 Right Hon.HWilliam Adamson, M.P.-,secretary of State fornj Scotland.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield, Secretary ofState for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies,The Right Hon,Lord Sarikey,  G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood B enn, D,S,0,,D.F.G. ,M.P&apos;., Secretary ofState for Ind.ia.Brig.-General The Right Hon.Lord Thomson,  C.B.E.,D.S.O.,Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon..Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.Tire Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan, M.P.,President, Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.A.V. Alexander, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.Sir M.P.A. Hankeyj G*C.B. , G.C.M.G____....... Secretary
1.   The Cabinet took note that the secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, after consultationwith the Prime Minister, had arranged for HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom to berepresented at the League of Nations Assembly bythe following: -The Prime Minister (for part of the time).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,The President of the Board of Trade (fcrpart of the timejViscount Cecil of Ghelwood(in connection with the PreparatoryCommission),Sir Cecil Hurst,Mrs Swanwick .Substjtude Delegates.The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.Mr Noel Baker,Mrs Hamilton,and that the above would be announced on thefollowing day.
EGYPT. 2. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumprevious circulated by direction of the Secretary of StateReference: ,Cabinet 24 for Foreign Affairs  (Paper C.P.-181 (29)) on the(29),  Con-clusion 2.) subject of Egypt, containing a narrative of themore important political events as affectingEgypt since February,  1924.The Cabinet took note of the intention of theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs to send atelegram to the High Commissioner in Egypt, at theend of which he would suggest that, having regardto the wide divergence between the High commissioner and the late Secretary of State for Foreign affairs on matters of policy as revealed by recent corres-pondence,  and the consequent likelihood that thesame divergence of view would arise with the presentSecretary of State, Mr Henderson would like todiscuss the whole question of our policy in Egyptwith Lord Lloyd on his return to England on leave,and that he would not conceal his doubts as towhether Lord Lloyd&apos;s point of view could be harmon-ized with that of the present Government.The Cabinet agreed  -That, in his conversations with theHigh Commissioner, the secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs should beauthorised to make it clear that hehad sent the above telegram with thefull support of the Cabinet.In regard to the Secretary of State&apos;s conversa-tion with the Prime Minister of Egypt, the cabinet agreed  That the Secretary cf State forDominion Affairs, the Secretaryof State for War and the Secretaryof State for Air should be available as a Committee to assist the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs in his. negotiations.
THE PERMANENTCOURT OPINTERNATIONALJUSTICE AT THEHAGUE.The optional clause.(previous references:Cabinet 18(29)    Con-clusion 8andCabinet 26(29), Con-elusion 1 and appendix.)3.   The Cabinet took note that the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs would shortlycirculate a Memorandum in regard to the signing of the Optional Clause embodied in the Statute ofthe Permanent Court of International justice and the question of reservations thereto.
pAH LTAME NT AR Y 4.    The Cabinet took note that the Pri:i e Minis -PROCEDURE.ter the same afternoon would be askink Parliament(previous reference:Cabinet 26(29), Con-elusion 6.)to agree to the following arrangements as regardsEusiness:-(a) The whole of the time up to the christmas Recess to be devotedto Government Business, subjectto an undertaking that a  Committeeshould be appointed to re-examinethe Standing Orders with a view toadjusting the arrangements for private members&apos; Bills to the practice ofrecent years of beginning the Sessionof Parliament in the autumn insteadof early in the year:(t) An adjournment before the end ofthe present month:(c) The Session to continue until afterMidsummer, 19 30:(d) The business before the next adjourn-ment to be confined to the followingessential legis lation:-Two Bills m connection with unemployment .An UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BILL.A HOUSING BILL.An IRISH FREE STATE AGREEMENT BILL,and one or two minor Bills .The Cabinet also agreed  (e) That if enquiry were made as to the dropping of the Second Part of theFinance Bill, the Prime minister would state that the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer would answer a question on the subject on the following day.( f) That the Lord Privy Seal should open the Debate the same afternoon in orderto set forth the Government&apos;s policy on the subject of Unemployment, andthat the First Commissioner of v-orksshould wind up the Debate.
:       5.    In taking note that the following Pillswould be considered by the Committee of Home affairs on July 4th and July 5th, -THE COLONIAL DEVELOPMENT BILL.THE GOVERNMENT OP INDIA (ADEN)  BILL.THE IRISH FREE STATE (confirmation of AGREEMENT)  BILL,  1939.A BILL TO GIVE EFFECT TO THE geneva convention ON ARBITRAL AWARDS.THE UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (AMENDMENT)BILL.THE HOUSING (FINANCIAL PROVISIONS) ACT1924 (AMENDMENT)  BILL.A BILL- TO FACILITATE THE DEVELOPMENTOF RAILWAYS AND OTHER PUBLICUTILIT UNDERTAKINGS -the Cabinet agreed  (a) That as the above Bills have to beintroduced in Parliament at a very early date, Ministers should, have authority for this as soon as the bills have been approved by theCommittee of Home Affairs andwithout prior confirmation by theCabinet:(b) That this arrangement should beexceptional and solely to meet the urgent circumstances of the presentsituation.NOTE. Since the Meeting of the Cabinet the isle of Man (Customs) Bill has been added.
GERMANY.Reparations .(Pr ev ionsReference:Cabinet 26(29)    Con-cliision 4.)6. The Cabinet had before them: once more thefollowing documents in regard to Reparations byGermany:-The Report of the Committee of experts (Paper C.P.-167 (29)):A Summary of the Events priorto the presentation of theReport of the &quot;Young&quot; Committeeand also of that Report (paper cp.-174 (29)):A Memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (Paper C.P.-17 5 (29)) .In addition, the following was circulated shortly before the Meeting:-A Memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (Paper C.F.-191 (29))  containing proposals as to the order and method bywhich the Report of the Expertsshould be handled between theGovernments concerned.After a discussion of a preliminary characterthe Cabinet agreed  That the question of the method and procedure in handling the Report ofthe Experts should be remitted tothe Chancellor of the Exchequer andthe Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.
THE UNEMPLOYMENT 7 . The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by insurance BILL.the Minister of Labour (Paper CP.-169 (29)) in(Previous regard to the serious financial position of the reference:Cabinet 49 Unemployment Insurance Scheme, containing the(28), Con-clusion 3.) following recommendations as regards immediate action:-(i) That the Exchequer contribution should be increased on the&quot;equal-thirds&quot; basis from 6d. to7-gd, as from 1st&quot; April,  1929,i.e. by  3,500,000 per annum.(ii) That immediate interdepartmentalconsideration should be given tothe question of relieving theUnemployment Insurance Scheme ofthe charge in respect of personsnot possessing the 30 contributionqualification and the provision tobe made for them, with a view to legislation in the autumn.As to legislation, a Bill pro-viding further money must be passed during the Summer Session.It would be quite short but would of course require a financial resolution.- The Cabinet approved the above proposals and authorised the Minister of Labour to study thequestion of Unemployment Insurance Departmentallyand in consultation with other Ministers concerned,with a view to the preparation of an Amending Bill,but not to make any public announcement as to theintroduction of further legislation until after theapproval of the Cabinet had been obtained.
3.       The Gabdnet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs(Paper CP,-188 (29)) covering a telegram fromthe High Commissioner in Canada on the subject ofthe Suggestion discussed by the Canadian cabinet for calling an Inter-Imperial Economic Conference.In this Memorandum it was pointed out that aConference with Dominion representatives was dueto meet in London at the beginning of October todiscuss various matters outstanding from theImperial Conference of 1926 on the legal and constitutional side, and that it world be inconvenient that there should be two Inter-imperial conferences going on concurrently, one in Londonand one in Ottawa.After preliminary discussion,  theCabinet agreed -(a) That the subject of empire trade should be remitted fordiscussion by the Chancellorof the Exchequer,  the lord privy Seal,  the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs,  andthe President of the Board ofTrade.NOTE;-    The above Ministers agreedto meet in the Chancellor of theExchequer&apos;s room at the Treasury onMonday next,  July 8th,  at 11.0 a.m.(b) That the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should send a message to the Prime Ministerof Canada warning him that HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom are likely to be engagedwith important international conferences until the end ofOctober.EMPIRE TRADE.(previous reference:Cabinet 26(29), Con-conclusion ion 3 .)
HOME-PRODUCED 9.     The Cabinet had before them-the followingMEAT AND BREADFOR THE FORGES, documents in regard to proposals  for the supply ofhome-produced meat aa d bread for the Forces:-(previous reference: A Memorandum by the Minister ofCabinet 17 Agriculture and Fisheries (Paper(29), Con- CP.-185 (.29)) recommending the elusion 1.) adoption of the proposals madeby the late Government, namely, thathome-fed beef should be supplied tothe Army, Air Force and Navy in home ports during the six months from October to March on six days in each week;    that on one day aweek the existing frozen muttonration should be continued;that the flour supplied to Armyand Air Force bakeries during the six months after harvest should contain 25 per cent, of Englishwheat.A Memorandum by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty (Paper CP.-186 (29))stating, inter alia, that theproposal would involve an extracharge to the Navy Votes estimatedat about  45,000 for the six months in question, for which no provision has been made in the Estimates forthe current year, and adding thatthe Admiralty would prefer not toadopt the proposal.A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for War (Paper CP.-189 (29))stating, inter alia, that theproposal would involve an additionto Army and Air Force expenditureof about  200,000 a year, with nocompensating reduction and no benefit to the Services, and urgingother considerations against theadoption of the proposal,A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs (paper cp.-190 (29)) circulating aMemorandum received from theAustralian and New Zealand Sextionof the Imported Meat Trade Associa-tion,  Incorporated, giving reasonsagainst the proposal of the Ministerof Agriculture and Fisheries.The Cabinet agreed -That the suggestion of the late government did net commend itself as a business proposal and shouldbe rejected.
UNEMPLOYMENT,Trans f erence(previous reference:gabinet 50(28), Con-clusion 1.)10.   The Cabinet took note of a Memorandumby the Minister of Labour (Paper CP.-187 (29))on the subject of the transfer of miners, coveringan Appendix describing the existing TransferScheme.    In her Memorandum the Minister of Labourreached the conclusion that the arrangements needoverhauling and extension in various particulars,but that the idea is fundamentally sound.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.July ^rd, 192C

</content>
</cab>
