<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/241/0 images: 9-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^  DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT.)SECRET.p.P.  152  (5-3),o COPY NO. &amp;CABINET. REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OP ARMAMENTSe Policy of the United Kingdom Delegation at Geneva9I circulate for the information of my colleagues the accompanying Conclusions of the meeting of Ministers which .was held on Friday, 5th May, in accordance with Cabinet 35 (35), Conclusion 6*(Intdo) J.H.T,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l0, 9th May, 1933.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)SECRET. COPY NO,A B I N S TREDUCTION AND LIMITATION    OF ARMAMENTS.CONCLUSIONS   of a Meeting of Ministers held .at 10j Downing Street, S.7/.1-., on Friday, 5th May,  1936, at 2.30 p.m.The Right Hon. J.H.Thomas, M.B.,Secretary of State for Dominion   Affairs0(in the Chair.)he Eight HonDViscount Hailsham, The Right Hon.Sir John Simon,Secretary of State for far,    &apos; G..C.S.I. , K.C.V.O. , O.B.E. , Kj M.P., Secretary of&quot;state forFore i gn Affairs .he Right Hon. Sir P. Cunliffe- The Most Hon. the Marquess of.Lister, G.B.E. , M.C., M.P. , Londonderry, K.G. , M.V.O.-,Secretary of State for the Colonies,,        Secretary of State for Air,The Right Hon. Sir Henry Betterton,LabouroTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:Mr. Anthony Eden, M.C. , M.F., Parliamentary Under Secretary, Foreign Office.&quot;wing Commander E. J. Hod so 11 . o c o . . . e o . o    Secretary.
THE COMMITTEE met to continue the discussion in regard to the disarmament position at Geneva which was initiated at the Cabinet this morning, and, in particular, had under consideration telegram No.  199 L.N. from His &apos; Majesty&apos;s Consul, Geneva, dated April 26th, 1933.-VRAGRAPH 2, LORD HAILSHAM explained that there was-no intentionALIBRE OPiJHS.. that we should retain the sole right to possess 4.5 inch guns. He suggested that, to make the position quite clear, the reference to guns of 105 mm. calibre should be deleted.CONCLUSION.It was agreed :-(i)    that, in Article 19 of the United Kingdom Draft Convention,  the reference to guns of 105 mm.  calibre should be deleted and the figure 4.5&quot; only should be quoted.      The Article in question should now read as follows:-&quot;The maximum limit for the calibre of mobile land guns for the future shall be 4.5&quot;.      Existing mobile land guns up to 155 mm. may be retained but all replacement or new construction of guns shall be within the maximum limit of 4.5&quot;.The maximum limit for the calibre of coast defence guns shall be 406 mm.&quot;(ii) That an alteration will, also, be required to Article 22, third paragraph, which should now read as follows:-&quot;All guns above 4.5&quot;  shall be destroyed so soon as they are replaced by new guns of or &quot;below 4.5&quot;.&quot;PARAGRAPH 3, DESTRUCTION OF MATERIAL.MR. EDEN suggested that,  in regard to tne question of the destruction of material prescribed by Article 22, the periods should correspond to those laid down for the transformation of Continental armies to militia bases, or,  in other words, should correspond with the period of the Convention.
CONCLUSION.It was agreed -that the periods to &quot;be prescribed for the destruction of material under Article 22 should correspond with the period of the Convention which, at present-  is assumed to he five years.paragraph 4, MR. EDEN explained to the Committee the positionMS.in regard to tanks, stating that,  if, as he believed, we could not agree to a truce, then the only alternative appeared to be numerical limitation, granting the right to Germany to have a token figure.      He warned the Committee that it was likely the United States were going to suggest limitation by numbers throughout the whole Convention, which would,  of course, apply to tanks. The objection he saw to giving Germany the right to possess a small number of tanks,   apart from the violation of the principle of disarmament, was that both the Prime Minister and President Roosevelt had, more or less, categorically...stated that they would not agree to any rearmament by Germany.      He added, also,  that all other . countries except Prance and ourselves were prepared to abo-1 ish tanks.LORD HAILSHAM described briefly to the Committee the War -Office policy in regard to tanks,and intimated that the figure for tanks which we might have to insert in the Convention was considerably in excess of the number we actually possessed, but the figure represented the programme to which the War Office were working.      He\
added that,  if the Convention was for a short term, it might perhaps he possible for a smaller figure to he inserted, provided there was a definite safeguard by which we could expand if the situation demanded.8IR PHILIP - CIJNLIPFS-LIST3R suggested that, in the White Paper of the 17th November,  1932, he thought we had already made an admission in regard to Germany and the question of tanks.      On page 5 in paragraph (2)(a)  the following words appeared:-. &quot;The admission of equal treatment would make it impossible to deny,  in principle,  to Germany the right to possess a limited number of such weapons, but the question whether this would be so in practice, and,  if so, what number will he sufficient, depends upon a consideration of the purposes to be      served   by  each national army.      In any case , the point is one for negotiation and not for decision in advance of discussions at Geneva in which Germany would take part.&quot; We had, therefore, admitted,  in principle,  the right for Germany to have tanks but had reserved the question of the numbers.
MR. EDEN added that the Prime Minister had definitely said that there was to he no re-armament of Germany, hut if it was agreed that she should have a certain number of token tanks, then he thought we ought to insert a figure for Germany in the Table0LORD HAILSI1AM5 in answer to a question from Mr.Thomas reiterated that, provided there was a clause which would safeguard his position in case of a definite war scare, then it might be possible for him to put in a fewer number of tanks,,    Normally, so far as he could see, the total at which the War- Office were aiming would not be completed in live years.SIR JOHN SIMON referred Lord Hailsham to Article 88 of the draft Convention which concerned derogations, and which he thought met Lord Hailsham&apos;s point.Continuing, he suggested that Germany might be given a token figure on the basis that equality was only to he attained by stages, and that we had never made any promise that Germany would at once be conceded full parity in all respects.CONCLUSION.It was agreed -(a) that since it was impossible to agree to a Tank Truce, the only alternative was to allow German;/ to have a token figure which could probably best be decided by negotiations on the spot.    It should be made quite clear in the course of these negotiations that the principle had always been accepted that Germany should reach equality by stages and not in the form of an omnibus concession.(b) that the figure to be inserted in the Tables of the number of tanks to he allowed to the United Kingdom might be in accordance with the probable progress of the War Office construction programmes the actual number being dependent on the duration of the Convention and the provision of a definite safeguard that, in time of emergency, it would be possible to derogate from the figures finally inserted.
MR. EDEN added that the Prime Minister had definitely said that there was to &quot;be no re--armament of Germany:   hut if it was agreed that she  should have a. certain number of token tanks, then he thought we ought to insert a figure for Germany in the Table,LOUD HAILSHAM, in answer to a question from Mr.Thomas, reiterated that, provided there was a clause which would safeguard his position in case of a definite war scare, then it might be possible for him to put in a fewer number of tanks.    Normally, so far as he could see, the total at which the far- Office were aiming would not be completed in live years.SIR JOHN SIMON referred Lord Hail sham to Article; 88 of the draft Convention which concerned derogations, and which he thought met Lord Hailsham&apos;s point.Continuing, he suggested that Germany might be given a token figure on the &quot;basis that equality was only to be attained by stages, and that we had never made any promise that Germany would, at once be conceded full parity in all respects,CONCLUSION.It was agreed -(a)    that since it was impossible to agree to a Tank Truce, the only alternative was to allow German;/ to have a token figure which could probably best be decided by negotiations on the sooto    It should be made quite clear in the course of these negotiations that the principle had .always been accepted that Germany should reach equality by stages and not in the form of an omnibus concession.(&quot;b)    that the figure to be inserted in the Tables of the number of tames to be allowed to the United Kingdom might be in accordance with the probable progress of the War Office construction programme, the actual number being dependent on the duration of the Convention and the provision of a definite safeguard that, in time of emergency, it would be possible to derogate from the figures finally inserted.
PARAGRAPH   5, MR. EDEN said that it would greatly assist him ifBOMBING INOUTLYING he could have a precise indication of what was intendedREGIONSoby &apos;bombing, for police purposes in outlying regions&apos;.    were such operations to be confined to our own territory o?, if not, what areas had we in mind and what justification could we put forward for exercising  &quot;police&quot; functions in them.MR. THOMAS said he did not think it would be diffi-cult to make a convincing case in view of the responsibill-ties which the United Kingdom had undertaken.    He thought, also, that the South African Government would strongly support us in this matter,    lie had a great many commitments which no other country had assumed, and he thought, therefore, we had every justification for our reservation.;,LORD LONDONDERRY said that it was almost impossibleto define outlying areas, particularly from a geographicalpoint of view, and remarked that it was equally impossibleto forecast what areas would be peaceful at any one time,or what areas would be in a state of unrest.    He suggested the following definition of outlying areas for considerationby the Committee -&quot;Areas where, owing to inaccessibility or other causes, control by the ordinary forces of law and order is impracticable or ineffective.&quot;SIR JOHN SIMON said that he had also been given a formula which had been prepared in the Foreign Office, which was rather more elaborate. This formula was as follows&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom propose to retain the right to employ, in outlying-regions of British territories and territories under British protection or mandate, air action forI
police purposes5 as being in their opinion, at once the most humane and in certain circumstances the only effective system of pacification.,    By &quot;outlying regions&quot; they mean undeveloped and sparsely inhabited areas where, owing either to their inaccessibility or remoteness from centres of civilisation ov to climatic conditions, ground operations would require the tise of disproportionately large forces and involve the risk of unnecessarily heavy casualties on both sideso    The areas &quot;which they have principally in mind   are the northern frontier districts of India, the Aden Protectorate and the mandated territories in the middle east; but if other suitable means of pacification were unavailable it might prove necessary to employ air action in other similarly remote British territorieso&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government have been asked by the Iraqi   Government to state that they consider that the right to employ air action within Iraq cannot be relinquished under present conditions, and His Majesty&apos;s Government associate themselves with this view.&quot;In the event of the necessity arising for the employment of air action, His Majesty&apos;s Government, for their part, would propose to furnish the Permanent Disarmament Commission with a full report of the circumstances, and would welcome any enquiry -which that Commission might consider necessary.&quot;
ME. EDEN? in answer to various questions, said that a number of amendments had already been tabled to our reservation, and,  in particular, by the Afghan Government, who seemed to assume that we might under this reservation retain the right to bomb in Afghanistan.SIR PHILIP CUNLIFFE-LISTER,  referring particularly to position of Iraq, said that in point of fact, it was the presence of our Air Force   there that prevented the Turks from invading&apos;Iraq through the Kurdish Mountains. If the threat of bombing was removed, we should, he &quot;thought, want a very large force of infantry in lieu. It seemed to him that it was impossible for us to surrender our bombing rights in Iraq,&apos; and,  at the same time,  to keep -faith with our Treaty with that country.      He wanted to know what answer could be given to particular questions on this point which might possibly arise.LORD LONDONDERRY,  agreeing with Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,  emphasised that by our Treaty with Iraq, we guaranteed to protect them from external aggression.SIR PHILIP CUNLIFFE-LISTER agreed, and asked whether it could, in fact, be called bombing for police purposes if we attacked Turks coming through the Kurdish defile.MR. THOMAS referred to a Despatch from Sir Francis Humphrys,    in which he had explained    that Iraq was relying on the unfettered use of air forces for the maintenance of its integrity.      He fully realised Mr. Eden*s difficulties, and suggested that it might he possible for us to say that we only required to reserve bombing for police purposes, and had no intention of bombing any other country unless they violated our territory.      In answer to a question from-7- :
Sir John Simon., -who suggested that when somebody moved to delete the  reservation to Article 34,  we might find ourselves alone,  he suggested that we could rely on the Dominions to give us their supnort,  and more particularlys South Africa-SIE PHILIP CUNLIFPE-LISTER thought that we could make out a very good case in view of our special responsibilities, and that we could say straight out that if we were forced to do away with our present methods, which were both humanitarian and economic, we should have to increase very greatly the numbers of our troops.MR.  EDEN said that if we insisted on our exception, Prance would presumably ask also for an exception in Morocco, and Italy probably in North Africa.MR.  THOMAS said in that case we should have their support.SIR JOHN SIMON said it seemed to him that it was a case in which no formula of words or compromise was possible, and that it only remained for us to resist any amendment to Article 34.SIR PHILIP GLiNLIPFE-LISTER reiterated that he thought if we took a realistic line, we had an excellent case.      All we were asking to do was to preserve what   we had been doing for years..      We could point to the fact that in all the countries       which we administered, we had carried out no offensive operations by bombing, but by means of using the Air&apos; Forces for police purposes, we had been enabled to save many lives and maintain peace and quiet.      It seemed to him that there was no relation   between    the way we used our Air Forces in outlying regions and  the bombing of open towns in a great war.
We had used our Air Forces for police purposes in mandated territories, and as far as he knew, the League Mandates Commission had. always approved our action. He thought that every country knew perfectly well that the methods for which we were claiming exemption were in an entirely different category from open offensive warfare.ME. EDEN said he would &quot;be very grateful if he  could be given some guidance on the lines of either of the formulae prepared by Lord Londonderry or the Foreign Office.MR. THOMAS agreed, and asked the Secretary to arrange a small Drafting Committee to ddal with this point.CONCLUSION.It was agreed;-(a) that it was essential for us &apos;b6 retain the reservation to Article 34,\permitting police bombing in outlying regions^(b) that in putting forward our case for the maintenance of the reservation to Article 34, it could be explained that we were only asking to preserve the right of action which we had been taking for a great number of years, in some esses under the actual aegis of the League MandatesCommissionj    that there was every difference in the world between offensive bombing in a war and the type of bombing we employed for the maintenance of peace in outlying regions, which experience had shewn was both humanitarian and economic. It might further be pointed out that if this right was no longer conceded,  it might be necessary for us very greatly to increase the numbers of our military effectives.(c)    to instruct the Secretary, in consultation with the Departments concerned,  to prepare a Note for the guidance of Mr. Eden, on the&quot; lines of those suggested by the Secretary of State for Air and the Foreign Office^-9-s   The Note drawn up and agreed by the drafting Committee on Monday, May 8th, 1953.  is attached as an Appendix- -
rRENGTH OF MR. EDEN drew the attention of the Comi.ii.ttee toMINION AIRROES. the fact that various Dominions were apparently intending to insert very large figures in respect of the size of their air forces.        New Zealand apparently wanted 125, when she, in fact, possessed at present only ahout 30; Canada somewhere about 200,  and Australia in the region of the same figure,      Added to the total of 500, which had &quot;been suggested for the United Kingdom,  the grand total of 1400 was reached,,  which was, in fact, nearly three times the number of aircraft permitted to any other power.      The United States had suggested that since they had parity at sea with the British Commonwealth,  they would like to have parity on the same basis in respect of aircraft.LORD LONDONDERRY said that the American case was in fact that they wanted the figure of 500, which had been suggested for the United Kingdom,  to include the Air Forces of the Dominions as well.MR. THOMAS suggested that in view of the financial position in the Dominions,  it seemed    a little difficult that they should claim such large figures for their air forces.SIR PHILIP CUNLIFFE-LISTER, referring particularly to Canada,  said that although in point of fact practically all the aircraft were military and were flown by personnel in uniform,  the tasks on which they were engaged were purely civil.MR.  THOMAS said he might be able to help if he called the Dominions into conference,  explair      the position to them,  and endeavoured to get them to accept some reduction.
4 JT*1 sir JOHN SIMON9  in answer to a question from Lord Londonderry5 said he thought that the naval and air position vis-a-vis the United States were two entirely different things.      It was true that   an Australian battle-ship    could come to the assistance of the British Fleet, but he did not see that a squadron of aeroplanes from Australia could be used in the same way at all.MR. THOMAS, after a farther short discussion, agreed that it might be better to have the Conference with the High Commissioners in this country,  and said he would keep in touch with Mr. Eden on this point.CONCLUSION.It was agreed;-that the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs should arrange for a Conference  of the High Commissioners of the Dominions in this country,  in order to discuss with them the figures they proposed to insert in the tables in the Convention for the numbers of aircraft, with a view to seeing if it was possible to arrange for a reduction in the figures which it was. understood&apos;they are at present contemplating.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, 5th May,  193 3.
APPEH D I X oINTER-DEPARTMENTAL DRAFTERFORMULA REGARDING THE DEFINITION OF BOMBING IN OUTLYING-PLACES.&apos;&apos;Note by the Secretary.In accordance with Conclusion 5 (c) of the Meeting of Ministers held on Friday, May 5th, 1933, a meeting was held with representatives of the Foreign Office, India Office, Colonial Office, and Air Ministry, and the attached formula was agreed.Particiilar attention is drawn to the following points in connection with this formula:-(a) In case the Afghan Government should be inclined to raise any questions as to whether the formula contemplates the possibility of bombing in Afghan territory, it is suggested that Mr. Eden might explain privately to the representativeof the Afghan Government that such is not our intention.    So far as India is concerned the outlying regions which we have in mind would be British territories or territories under British protection.(b) The foimiula suggested is made entirely applicable to &quot;outlying regions&quot;.    This may mean, so far as interpretation at Geneva is concerned, that we are debarred from taking air action in the last resort in any place which cannot properly be described as outlying, e.go in defence of a British cantonment in India.    The Air Ministry are particularly anxious that this possible implication is fully appreciated.(c) The question of our position vis-a vis the Sultan of Muscat and the Arab States on the Persian Gulf was considered.    It was felt to be difficult to put in any specific reference which would, in fact, cover the position if we were asked by any of these local rulers to assist them with air action.    Legally speaking, these
States are independent and they are not members of the League of Nations. It is assumed that we should be perfectly covered if we took any action at their request but attention is drawn to this point in case any questions should arise in future.(d) A paragraph has been inserted covering the position of the Iraqi Government.      A telegram has been despatched to Iraq, seeking the support and agreement of the Iraqi Government in including this para-graph in the formula.     Unless and until a favourable reply has been received from the Iraqi Government,however, obviously this paragraph cannot be used.(e) No mention has been made of the question of reporting any action of His Majesty&apos;s Government to the League.       There is particular objection to making any specific provision for such reports from the point of view of the Government of India.      In recent years frequent occasions have arisen for separate minor air operations and the Government of India might be putin a very invidious position if, as is very possible,  air action took place only in India and with considerable frequency there and they were forced to make reports to Geneva at  comparatively short intervals.    If pressed on this point, it is suggested that Mr. Eden should refer to Article 77 of the Draft Convention and should intimate that machinery exists under this Article whereby any complaints can be investigated.    If , Mr. Eden should be further pressed on this point,  it is requested that he should refer the matter back again to His Majesty&apos;s Government,  so that the Government of India can be consulted.     The Secretary of State for India does not feel able to accept any proposal beyond the suggested reference to Article 77 under this head unless the Government of India have been consulted..  (Signed)    E.J.  HODSOLL.Secretary.8th May, 1953.
FORMULA REGARDING THE DEFINITION OF BOMBING INOUTLYING PLACES,His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom propose, to retain the right to employ,  in outlying regions of British territories and territories under British protection or mandate and in disturbed frontier areas, air action forA/&apos; v AA&apos; a police purposes,  since in their experience it is in certain circumstances the most humane and the only effective system of restoring order.     By &quot;outlying regions&quot; they mean undeveloped or sparsely inhabited areas where, owing either to their inaccessibility or remoteness from centres of civilisation or to climatic conditions, ground, operations would require the use of disproportionately large forces and involve the risk of unnecessarily heavy casualties on both sides.     Among the areas they have in mind are the Aden Protectorate, the Mandated Territories in the Middle East, and the frontier tracts of India;   hut if other suitable means of pacification were unavailable it might prove necessary to employ air action in other similarlyremote territories..     A      -His Majesty&apos;s Government have been asked by the Iraqi Government to state that they consider that the right to employ air action within Iraq cannot he relinquished under present conditions, and His Majesty&apos;s Government associate themselves with this view.

</content>
</cab>
