<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/241/0 images: 63-64</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GQVERNMK?*T.SECRET. :- Copy No... ^7.&apos;...CP. 188(53). CABINET.EXTENSION OF OPERATION OP UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE ACT,   1950.Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Labour.Most of the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance Act,-u1930, cease to have effect after 30th June, 1933.     From that date!&quot; Ithe Unemployment Insurance Acts,  1920-1929, would have effect as if the 1930 Act had not been passed unless steps ore taken to continue the operation of the 1930 Act before 30th June.      Two results v/ould be that transitional payments would cease for more than half the present recipients and the &quot;genuinely seeking work&quot; condition would again become one of the conditions for the receipt of Benefit.It will clearly be impossible to bring into operation by 30th June the comprehensive Unemployment Insurance and Assistance Bill which we have promised.      It is necessary, therefore, to extend the existing provisions temporarily.As regards the period of extension I suggest that it should be for twelve months.If this extension is only for (say) six months (i.e.  to 31st December) we should be almost certain to require a further extension because it is unlikely that the new scheme can come into operation &quot;by 1st January of next year.      Moreover, it would involve taking two supplementary estimates this financial year in respect of transitional payments since if we only ask for an extension in the first place to 31st December we could only submit an estimate to cover that period, and we should have to go to Parliament again for further money to cover the period between the end of December and the end of March, 1934.
A proposal to extend for twelve months may he criticised on the ground that it shows that the Government do not intend to pass general legislation till next year.       This would, however, he met by a statement of our intentions which must in any event be made when the Extending Bill is before the House and in which we should make it clear that it is our intention to pass general legislation this Session and to bring it into operation at the earliest practicable date.The Bill will almost certainly have to be based on a Financial Resolution Provision has been made in the Budget for an additional expenditure of  22,500,000 under this head.In answer to a question by Mr. Buchanan on 11th May the Prime Minister promised that an announcement on the subject of this extension would be made at the earliest opportunity.       The following question has been put down for next Thursday 18th May and I append the reply which I should propose to give;-Mr. Lawson, - To ask the Minister of Labour,  if he is now in a position to state what action the Government will take when the present unemployment insurance arrangements end in June this year;    and whether he is contemplating introducing a Bill at an early date.Proposed reply.      The Government have announced that they intend to introduce comprehensive legislation on this subject this Session.        It will not be practicable, however, to bring this legislation into operation by 30th June and a Bill for prolonging the existing arrangements temporarily will therefore be introduced at an early date. I ask for approval of this reply and for authority to introduce the Bill and pass it into law by 30th June.(Intld.)  H. B.15th May 1933.

</content>
</cab>
