<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/241/0 images: 138-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 ft p 1 vO/THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) SECRET.C.F.   140(35). COPY NO.        4&quot;^)CABINET. PERSIA AND THE ARMS TRAFFIC CONVENTION.REPORT BY THE STAINING- MINI STEP. IAL SUB-COMMITTEE FOR QUESTIONS CONCERNING THE MIDDLE EAST.The Cabinet at a meeting held on Wednesday, 24thMay, 1933, had before them a Memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs (CP.  136(33))  raising an urgent question in connection with the proposed arrange-ments for control of arms traffic in the Persian Gulf.2. The Cabinet agreed: -&quot;(a)  that the question raised in the above paper should he referred at once for consideration by the Middle East Committee;(b)  that the conclusions of the Middle East Committee should he submitted to an early meeting of the Cabinet&quot;.3. The Sub-Committee met as a matter of urgency at p.m. , on Thursday, 25th May, and considered the abovepaper, together with a memorandum by the First Lord of theAdmiralty, which is circulated as CP.  143(33).      In theabsence of the Secretary of State for Foreign. Affairs arepresentative of the Foreign Office attended the meeting.4. The following alternative courses of action, as given in CP. 136(33), paragraph 5, were considered: -(a) Rip Majesty&apos;s Government could ignore the Persian representations and continue to press for a convention closely reproducing the provisionsof that of 1925, and, in particular, including the Persian Gulf and the Gulf of Oman in the Special Maritime Zone;    or(b) An attempt could be made to meet the Persian wishes by excluding the two Gulfs from the Maritime Zone provided for in the Convention, and by dealing with them in the two separate instruments proposed in paragraph 4 of Paper No.  CP.  136(33).
The observations and conclusions of the Sub-Committee are as follows:-5. The Sub-Committee consider that if the traffic in arms is to lie controlled at all, the right of verifying the flag of any suspicious vessel is  essential.   Otherwise any vessel engaged in gun-running can secure itself &quot;by the illegal use of the Persian flag.      They note that His Majesty&apos;s ships have no power to stop genuine Persian vessels , even though they are carrying arms.      It, was explained, however, that even if course (a) were to he adopted, no right would be secured of verifying the use of the Persian flag, since Persia would not be a party to the Convention.6. The dangers that would arise were the Persian Govern-merrt to claim and try to exercise a right to interfere with vessels other than those flying the Persian flag (e.g., British   Indian or Bahreini dhows) were alluded to, and it v/as agreed that this eventuality must in any case be guarded against.      In this connection it was pointed out that the Persian Government had categorically stated that under the bilateral convention proposed in alternative (b) they v/ould undertake reciprocally to forego any such claim (vide paragraph 4 of CP.   136(33)).     It was suggested that the Foreign Office should approach the Persian Government and ask them to agree to the arrangement suggested in paragraph 9 of CP.  136(33) , i. e. , the verification of the flag of suspicious vessels by His Majesty&apos;s ships. 7. The Sub-Committee felt that any abandonment of theright of verifying the use of the Persian flag v/ould facilitate the traffic in arms, and possibly in slaves;    whereas the object of both the Arms Traffic Convention now under discussion at Geneva and the naval preventive measures in force was to restrict this trade.      They realised the advantage of an amicable agreement with the Persian Government which would preclude interference with Indian or Arab shipping. &quot; 2r
S.    Conclusion *(l) That unless the right of verifying the flag of suspicious vessels is retained it will he impossible in practice to control the traffic in arms in the Persian Gulf and the Gulf of Oman,      If this right  is to he lost in any case,  courses (a)  and. (b)   as stated would he equally objectionable;(2) That there can be no question of extending reciprocally to Persian ships the right to verify the    flag of British   Indian and Arab vessels;(3) That   the most advantageous course of actionto His Majesty&apos;s Government would be alternative (b)5  as modified by paragraph 9 of Cabinet Paper No.  CP.  136(33) 5  i.e,s  to secure the right of verification of flag in the case of the Persian flag only;  and that an effort should be made to persuade the Persian Government to agree to this course;(4)  That if our existing powers of control in the Persian Gulf are to be list in any case,  there would, be certain advantages in obtaining a guarantee from the    Persians  that they would not claim any rights of control over vessels other than those flying the Persian flag.(Intld.)    P.G-L.26. 5.33.

</content>
</cab>
