<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/241/0 images: 330-342</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1933.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.        41CP. 149 (33).CABINET.I CIRCULATE, for the information of my colleagues, a memorandum prepared in the Foreign Office on the measures which can be taken to compel observance by Germany of her obligations under Part V (Military, Naval, and Air Clauses) of the Treaty of Versailles.J. S.Foreign Office, May 30, 1933.THE concluding paragraphs of the memorandum respecting the organisation of the German police auxiliaries enclosed in the French Ambassador&apos;s communica-tion of the 5th May, 1933 (Annex I), state that &quot; If the Reich were not soon to take the measures necessary to re-establish a normal situation as regards the police, the Government of the Republic would be unable to admit the continuance of a state of affairs clearly contrary to the obligations contracted by Germany, and from which she is not entitled to free herself by unilateral action. The Government of the Republic sincerely hopes that were such a situation to arise, the British Government would be ready to concert with it on the measures necessary to put an end to a definite infraction of the treaty, and of the subsequent agreements which laid down the manner in which the treaty should be applied.&quot; These passages in the French memorandum must be read in conjunction with the state-ment in M. Paul-Boncour&apos;s speech in the Senate on the 4th May, 1933, in which he said that &quot;If Germany does not abandon these organisations (i.e., the illegal associations, auxiliary police, &amp;c), then the Treaty of Versailles must be applied.&quot; The obligations assumed by Germany in respect of her police force are set forth in a separate Memorandum. The &quot;illegal associations&quot; mentioned by M. Paul-Boncour are, of course, no new phenomenon. They have been a problem ever since the Allied Governments started to enforce the military clauses of the Treaty of Versailles. Another memorandum shows how the problem has been dealt with and to what degree the taint of illegality attaches to them.2. But it must not be lightly assumed that if the German Government in the near future is to be summoned to apply the Treaty of Versailles, it will merely be because of illegal measures it has recently adopted in regard to the police and the associations. If this was the sum total of Germany&apos;s offences. His Majesty&apos;s Government and, indeed, the Members of the League Council might hesitate to force matters to an issue; but the attitude of the German Government has recently shown itself so aggressive that it is necessary to take into account the possibility of Germany deciding to rearm on a large scale, either clandestinely or as an open act of defiance. It is in the anticipatory light of this possibility that the present Memorandum should be read, and not merely in the light of the German Govern-menfs recent tinkerings with the police and the &quot;illegal associations.&quot; Also, for the purpose of this Memorandum it is assumed that Germany does not accompany a violation of her disarmament obligations with an unprovoked recourse to war; if she were to do so, the legal position would be simple.6882   [8621] b
3. In. considering what &quot; measures &quot; could be taken &quot; to put an end to a definite infraction of the Treaty,&quot; and what is meant by &quot; applying &quot; the Treaty pf Versailles in a case in which the Treaty has been violated, it is necessary to consider the question of rights and obligations under two aspects : (a) The Treaty of Versailles (including for this purpose the subsequent disarmament arraiige-ments made between the ex-Allied Governments and the German Government); and (&amp;) the Treaties of Locarno, the Covenant and the Pact of Paris. It may be stated at once that Part XIV (guarantees) of the Treaty of Versailles cannot be employed. As the evacuation of the Rhineland has been completed before the expiry of the period laid down by the Treaty, the ex-Allies cannot make use of the provision in Article 429 which enabled the evacuation to be delayed in the event of the guarantees against unprovoked aggression by Germany not being con-sidered sufficient. Part XIV does not provide for re-occupation of the Rhineland save in the event of non-compliance by Germany with her reparation obligations; and the &quot; International Agreement on the Evacuation of the Rhine-land Territory&quot; of the 30th August, 1929 (Cmd. 3417), contains no provision or reservation respecting re-occupation.4.   Article 213 of the Treaty of Versailles provides that :-&quot; So long as the present Treaty remains in force, Germany undertakes to give every facility for any investigation which the Council of the League of Nations, acting if need be by a majority vote, may consider necessary.&quot;If then any of the ex-Allies considers that the Treaty of Versailles or some subsequent agreement or decision taken under it has been violated by Germany in the matter of some provision of Part V (Military, Naval and Air Clauses), the first step is, presumably (unless the facts are notorious or undisputed), a demand for an investigation under Article 213. In 1924 and 1925, the Council of the League approved rules for the conduct of an enquiry of this nature; and on the 11th December, 1926, the Council adopted a report (Annex II) which elucidated these rules.(&apos;) According to this report, &quot; The Conncil of the League of Nations, acting by a majority vote, shall decide in conformity with Article 213 of the Treaty of Versailles whether it is necessary to hold an investigation, and it shall then specify the object and the limits of such investigation. The Commission of Investigation shall act under the Treaty arid on the instructions of the Council; the Council&apos;s decisions shall be taken by a majority vote. . . . . To render an effective investigation possible, the Commission shall apply to the German Government, who will procure without delay the assistance of the competent authority.&quot;5. The powers possessed by the Council of the League under Article 213 are powers of investigation only, i.e., enquiry into and determination of the facts. If the result of the investigation is to establish facts which any of the ex-Allies considers to constitute a violation by Germany of an engagement into which she entered under the Treaty of Versailles, there arises between the ex-Ally concerned and Germany a dispute. The League (see Sir Cecil Hurst&apos;s minute of the 27th January, 1925 : Annex III) is not a party to this dispute. But, whilst its role (see Sir C. Hurst&apos;s minute), &quot;under Article 213 will have been fulfilled by its enquiry into and determination of facts, its role under the terms of the Covenant as an organisation for endeavouring to bring the disputants to a harmonious conclusion of their quarrel Will begin.&quot; A refusal by Germany to admit an investigation would amount to a breach of Article 213 and would in itself produce a dispute.6. It is essential that any such dispute should not be handled in such a Way as to expose the ex-Allies to the possibility of sanctions resulting from a breach of their own international obligations, and it is therefore necessary to consider carefully the treaty provisions applicable to such a dispute. Even when the coercive measures in contemplation do not involve the use Of force, it will still be necessary that they should not be applied until the whole of the procedure provided for in the Covenant and the Treaties of Locarno as set forth in the following paragraphs has been exhausted.(J) In the one case where a violation of the military clauses of the Treaties of Peace was referred to the Council of the League of Nations, the latter, for reasons which need not be discussed here, decided not to use the machinery established by the above decisions, but to deal with the matter by means of an del hoc, committee drawn from the . Secretariat (for details, see Annex to Memorandum on Disarmament of ex-Enemy Countries, 13609, Confidential)..,
7. It will be convenient, in the first instance, to assume that the dispute&quot; is between France (or Belgium, whose treaty position is identical with that of France) and Germany. Article 3 of the main Locarno Treaty and the Locarno Arbitration Convention between Germany and France (Cmd. 2525) provide for the settlement by peaceful means of &quot;all questions of every kind which may arise between them and which it may not be possible to settle by the normal methods of diplomacy.&quot;(2) Under these treaties disputes &apos;&apos; with regard to which the parties are in conflict as to their respective rights &quot; (i.e., disputes of a legal character) are, except in cases where a special procedure is laid down in other conventions, to go to an arbitral tribunal or to the Permanent Court; the parties may, however, agree to submit the dispute to the Permanent Conciliation Commission set up under the Franco-German Convention, in which case the dispute only goes to an arbitral tribunal or the Permanent Court if the conciliation procedure fails. All other disputes go to the Permanent Conciliation Commission, and, if this procedure fails to produce a settlement, to the Council of the League, which is to deal with them under Article 15 of the Covenant. If Germany refuses to submit the dispute to peaceful settlement, France must, under the last paragraph of Article 5 of the main Locarno Treaty, bring the matter before the Council, which will propose what steps should be taken; the parties to the Treaty &apos;&apos; shall comply with these proposals.&quot;8. In the circumstances contemplated Germany may dispute the existence of the facts alleged to constitute a breach of her disarmament obligations, or contend that they do not constitute a violation of those obligations, or raise some legal defence, such as that the failure of the ex-Allies to disarm has released&apos;her from those obligations. In any One of these events the dispute would be of a legal character and should be referred to an arbitral tribunal or to the Permanent Court. It would seem that only in the event of Germany admitting without seeking to excuse a violation of her disarmament obligations would the dispute be one for the alternative procedure of conciliation, followed, if necessary, by a reference to the Council.9. If the case goes to judicial decision, and if either the decision is in favour of Germany or Germany complies with it, the dispute is settled. If Germany refuses to comply with a judicial decision given against her, the last paragraph of Article 5 of the main Treaty of Locarno applies and France has to bring the matter before the Council of the League; the Cojaicil is to propose what steps are to be taken and all the parties to the Treaty are to comply with those proposals. It follows from this that (1) if Germany refused to. comply with the Council&apos;s proposals she would be committing another breach of her treaty obligations, (2) if the Council made proposals for enforcing the judicial decision, the other parties to Locarno would be bound to carry out those proposals.(3) The position and powers of the Council under these Locarno provisions are the same as under Article 13 (4) of the Covenant; but the effect of the provisions in question is to give to the Council&apos;s proposals greater force than they possess under the Covenant. It may probably be assumed that, for the purpose of making such proposals, the Council must be unanimous, not counting the parties to the dispute; the question of the nature of the proposals which the Council might make will be considered later.10. If the dispute is of a non-legal character and is accordingly submitted to a procedure of conciliation, either party can, if agreement has not been reached within a month from the termination of the labours of the Permanent Conciliation Commission, bring the dispute before the Council, which is to deal with it under Article 15 of the Covenant (Article 18 of the Franco-German Locarno Arbitration Convention). If the Council succeeds in effecting a settlement of the dispute, the matter will be disposed of, and the Council is to make a public statement about the dispute and the terms of settlement (Article 15, paragraph 3). If no settle-ment is reached, the Council &quot; either unanimously or by a majority vote shall, make and publish a report containing a statement of the facts of the dispute(2) This obligation is reinforced by (a) Article 12 of the Covenant and (fa) Article 2 of the Pact of Paris (cmd. 3410), by which Germany and Prance have agreed that &quot; the settlement or solution of all disputes or conflicts, of whatever nature or of whatever origin they may be, which may arise between them shall never be sought except by pacific means.&quot;(3) This also applies to the case where Germany refuses to submit the dispute to peaceful settlement see last sentence of paragraph 7 above.
and the recommendations which are deemed just and,proper in regard thereto;&quot; (Article 15, paragraph 4). If this report by the Council is unanimous except for one or more of the parties to the dispute, the Members of the League agree that they will not go to war with any party to the dispute which complies with the recommendations of the report (Article 15, paragraph^). If no such unanimous report is reached, the Members of the League can &quot; take such action as they shall consider necessary for the maintenance of right and justice &quot; (Article 15, paragraph 7).11. At this point it will be convenient to consider the hypothesis of the dispute being between the United Kingdom and Germany. In that case the Locarno Arbitration Conventions would not be applicable, but since the dispute would presumably be one &quot; likely to lead to a rupture,&quot; Article 12 of the Covenant would apply, and the dispute would have to be submitted either to judicial settlement (which could be done under the Optional Clause) or to the Council. In the event of a submission to judicial settlement, the position would be the same as that indicated in paragraph 9 above in the case of a Franco-German dispute, except that the last paragraph of Article 5 of the main Locarno Treaty would not be applicable, with the result that (i) the Council would have no specific power to make proposals in the event of Germany refusing to submit the case to judicial decision (though it could deal with the situation under its ordinary powers);&quot; (ii) in the event of Germany refusing to carry out a judicial decision, while the Council could (under Article 13 (4) of the Covenant) propose steps to be taken to give effect to the decision, there would be no obligation on the parties to the Locarno Treaty to comply with those proposals. In the event of the dispute being of a non-legal character and being referred to the Council, (&quot;) the position would be precisely the same as in the case of a Franco-German dispute, which had been referred to the Council after a failure of the conciliation procedure.12. It will be seen, therefore, that a situation may arise in which (1) the Council(5) might, under the last paragraph of Article 5 of the main Locarno Treaty, propose steps to deal with a refusal by Germany to submit a dispute to peaceful settlement; (2) in the case of a dispute of a legal character the Council(5) might, under the last paragraph of Article 5 of the main Locarno Treaty and Article 13 (4) of the Covenalit, propose steps to give effect to a judicial decision with which Germany refused to comply; (3) in the ease of a non-legal dispute, the Council^) might (under Article 15) make recommendations involving steps to he taken against Germany with the object of putting an end to her violation of her disarmament obligations; (4) in a non-legal dispute where the Council had failed to make a unanimous report, the ex-Allies concerned would be entitled (under Article 15 (7)) to take such action as they might consider necessary with that object. In so far as action taken under any of these headings consisted of measures like economic pressure which did not involve the use of force, no difficulties resulting from treaty obligations not to resort to force would arise, and the important questions which would present themselves as to the possibility and probable effect of such measures, and the position in relation thereto of States not parties to the dispute, are not within the scope of this memorandum. But in relation to forcible measures involving the invasion or occupation of German territory,, while in the circumstances postulated no question of their compatibility with the Covenant would arise, it is necessary to take into account the provisions of Article 2 of the Treaty of Locarno and of the Pact of Paris.13. Under Article 2 of the main Locarno Treaty, Germany and Belgium and Germany and France mutually undertake that they will in no case attack or invade each other or resort to war against each other. This provision does not, however, apply (with other exceptions not now relevant) to &quot; action as the result of a decision taken by the Assembly or by the Council of the League of Nations or in pursuance of Article 15, paragraph 7, of the Covenant, of the League of Nations, provided that in this last event the action is directed against a State(4) His Majesty&apos;s Government could if they liked refer the dispute to the Assembly instead of the Council, which France could not do under Article 18 of the Locarno Arbitration Convention. For the sake of simplicity this possibility is disregarded in the present memorandum.(5) This means the Council acting unanimously, the votes of the parties to, the dispute not being counted. -.&apos; ,   .     .,./&apos;.. -.      , (&quot; .,.. .   ,
299rj k) hJwhich was the first to; attack/&apos; &apos;rTt follows that an invasion&apos; or :occupatibn; of German territory would be permissible only in the following cases     ! :(1) Where Germany had refused to submit the dispute to peaceful settlement or to comply with an arbitral or judicial decision, and where the Council had unanimously, the votes of the parties to the dispute not being counted, decided (under Article 5, last paragraph, of Locarno) to propose such an invasion or occupation;(2) In the case of a non-legal dispute which had been submitted to the Council under Article 15, where the Council had unanimously, the votes of the parties to the dispute not being counted, agreed to a report . recommending such an invasion or occupation.14. It may, perhaps, be contended that in the latter case the invasion or occupation would be permissible if recommended only by a majority of the Council under Article 15 (4). This argument does not, however, appear sound; in the case of a majority report under paragraph 4, paragraph 7 applies, under which &quot;the Members of the League may take such action as they consider necessary for the maintenance of right and justice,&quot; but under Article 2, paragraph 3, of Locarno the invasion of German territory is only permissible in a case falling under Article 15 (7) if such action &apos;&apos; is directed against a State which was the first to attack.&quot;15. It should be added that the provision in Article 12 (1), which forbids &quot;resort to war&quot; until three months after the Report by the Council, would presumably not be regarded as applicable to an occupation of German territory which had been recommended by the Council.16. The question arises whether there is in fact any possibility of the Council unanimously recommending action of this nature. All that can be said is that this would largely depend on the actual circumstances of the case and the attitude which the public opinion of the world adopted towards them. In the event of the Council failing to recommend action of this nature, or even of its failing to make any unanimous recommendations at all, measures such as economic pressure not involving the use of force would be permissible so far as the treaties discussed in this memorandum are concerned, though there may be other instruments, such as a commercial treaty with Germany, which might be inconsistent with such action.17. Article 2 of the main Locarno Treaty does not apply to the United Kingdom, which is consequently not bound by the limitations resulting from that article on the power to attack or invade Germany (see paragraph 14). Assuming that the necessary procedure for the peaceful settlement of the dispute had been adopted (see paragraph 12 above), it is only the provisions of the Pact of Paris which His Majesty&apos;s Government have to take into account in relation to the invasion or occupation of German territory.18. As regards the Pact of Paris, the correspondence which preceded its signature (see Annex IV) makes it sufficiently plain that the Pact does not forbid war in cases where it is undertaken in pursuance of the provisions of the Treaty of Locarno, and, if so, it could not forbid military measures such as the invasion or occupation of German territory in cases where such action were taken in virtue of that treaty. Action of this nature, if taken in pursuance of a unanimous recommendation by the Council in one of the cases (1), (2) or (3) set out in paragraph 12 above, could not be regarded as a recourse to war &quot; as an instrument of national policy.&quot; But invasion of German territory carried out merely on. the strength of a majority recommendation of the Council (and consequently under Article 15 (7) of the Covenant) would probably be held to constitute a violation of the Pact of Paris. The proposed Declaration not to Resort to Force which is at present before the Disarmament Conference, and Mr. Roosevelt&apos;s similar proposal of the 16th May, must be disregarded since it is not at present known whether or in what form either of them will be adopted, but it is probably safe to assume that they would not exclude action of the nature contemplated in cases where it would be permissible under the Pact of Paris and the Treaty of Locarno.19. One form of forcible action against Germany which has not so far been considered is a &quot; pacific blockade &apos;&apos; (without declaration of war) of the German
coast. Such action does not appear to be covered by the prohibition in Article 2 of the main Locarno Treaty to attack or invade Germany. Action of this nature might conceivably be recommended by the Council in the circumstances dealt with in paragraph 12 above, but, apart from any questions as to its practicability and effect, the position of States not parties to the dispute would obviously cause difficulties which are not within the scope of this memorandum.20. In the special case of a violation by Germany of the provisions relating to the Rhineland demilitarized zone (Articles 42-44 of the Treaty of Versailles), the procedure of conciliation provided by the Locarno Arbitration Conventions can be applied, in accordance with the International Agreement on the Evacua-tion of the Rhineland Territory (Cmd. 3417). It is, however, also possible to employ the procedure laid down in Article 4 of the main Locarno Treaty, under which an alleged violation of the provisions in question is brought before the Council. If satisfied that such violation has been committed, the Council will notify its finding to the other Locarno Powers, who are then to come immediately to the assistance of the complaining Power. It will be noticed that the processes which have to be gone through before sanctions can be applied to Germany in the event of her infringing Part V of the Treaty are so curtailed in the case of her violating Articles 42 and 43 of the Treaty, that it is possible for the Locarno Powers in the latter case to proceed at once to the invasion or occupation of German territory as soon as the Council is satisfied(6) that a violation has been committed. The reason for this distinction is that, whereas an infraction of Part V of the Treaty of Versailles merely constitutes a dispute between Germany and the other signatories of the Treaty, an infraction of Articles 42 and 43 is, according to Article 44, to be regarded as the commission of a hostile act against the other signatory Powers, and, as such, is tantamount to a resort of war in the sense of Article 16 of the Covenant.21. In conclusion, it may be convenient to indicate the position of Germany&apos;s eastern neighbours Poland and Czechoslovakia. These countries concluded at Locarno arbitration treaties with Germany which are practically identical with the Franco-German and Belgo-German treaties, and consequently the position of Poland and Czechoslovakia as regards the procedure to be adopted for dealing with a dispute arising out of a violation by Germany of her disarmament obligations is identical with that described in regard to France and Belgium in paragraphs 7-10 above. Poland and Czechoslovakia are not parties to the main Locarno Treaty and are consequently not bound by the undertaking not to attack or invade Germany; their position in this respect is identical with that of the United Kingdom (paragraph 16 above) in that the Pact of Paris is the only treaty obligation which they have to take into account.22.   The above considerations seem to lead to the following conclusions : (i) In the event of a violation by Germany of her disarmament obligations,it is essential that the complaining Powers should proceed in strict accordance with their obligations under the Covenant and the Treaty of Locarno, even if the coercive measures contemplated do not involve the use of force;(ii) Normally the first step would be a request to,the Council of the Leagueof Nations to carry out an investigation under Article 213 of the Treaty of Versailles;(iii) If the result of the investigation is to establish facts regarded as constituting a violation of Germany&apos;s obligations, the resulting dispute must, if between Germany and France or Germany and Belgium, be submitted, according to its nature, either to judicial settlement or to conciliation followed, if necessary, by reference to the League under Article 15. If between Germany and the United Kingdom, it must go either to the Permanent Court or to the Council;(iv) In the event of Germany refusing to submit the dispute to judicialsettlement or to comply with an arbitral or judicial decision, the matter must be brought before the Council under the last paragraph of Article 5 of Locarno;(6) The Council can satisfy itself on this point either by an ad hoc enquiry, or by using the method of investigation which has been created for implementing Article 213 of the Treaty of Versailles.
(v) The invasion or occupation of German territory would (subject to paragraph (vi) ) be permissible if, but only if, the Council acting unanimously (the votes of the parties to the dispute. not being counted) recommended such action under Article 5, last paragraph of Locarno or Article 15 (4) of the Covenant; &apos;.i(vi) In the case of a sufficiently serious violation of Articles 42 or 43 of theTreaty of Versailles, a shorter procedure can be employed, and the invasion or occupation of German territory would be permissible as soon as the Council had satisfied itself that such a violation existed;(vii) Subject to any difficulties arising from instruments like commercial treaties, measures such as economic pressure not involving the use of force would be permissible (whether or not the Council had made a unanimous recommendation to that effect) assuming that the procedure prescribed for the settlement of the dispute had been adopted. The same is probably the case as regards a &quot; pacific blockade &quot; of German ports. The practicability and possible effects of such measures are not within the scope of this memorandum.
Annex    I. French Ambassadors Note, May 5, 1933 (Germany print, May 5, Section 1).Annex   II. lie port on the Eules for the Conduct of Investigations under Article 213 of the-Treaty of Versailles.Annex III.-Sir C. Hursfs Minute of January 27, 1925.Annex IV. Extracts from the Correspondence respecting United States Proposal for Kenunciation of War (Cmd. 3109 and 3153).ANNEX   I.[C 4103/245/18]Note from the French Ambassador--(Received May 5.)L&apos;AMBASSADEUR, de France avait immediatement fait parvenir a son Gouvernement la lettre que son Excellence le principal Secretaire d&apos;Etat de Sa Majeste&quot; aux Affaires elrangeres avait bien voulu lui adresser le 11 avril dernier au sujet de 1&apos;organisation de la police auxiliaire allemande.M. Paul-Boncour a prie M. de Fleuriau de remercier Sir John Simon de cette communication et de lui remettre une note ci-jointe en copie qui expose la maniere de voir du Gouvernement francais au sujet du document britannique.M. de Fleuriau saisit, &amp;c.Ambassade de France, Londres, le 5 mai 1933.Enclosure in Annex I. Memorandum respecting the Organisation of the German Police Auxiliaries.1. LE Gouvernement de Sa Majeste britannique a fait ressortir dans sa communication du 11 avril 1933 a l&apos;Ambassadeur de France a Londres que 1&apos;organisation d&apos;une police auxiliaire en Allemagne contrevenait a la decision notified au Gouvernement allemand dans la Partie III de 1&apos;Annexe I de la note alliee du 4 juin 1925. Le Gouvernement de la Republique est heureux de constater 1&apos;accord des deux Gouvernements sur ce point.2. D&apos;apres le Gouvernement britannique, la decision alliee n&apos;aurait toutefois 6te&quot; admise qu&apos;implicitement par le Gouvernement allemand dans sa note du 23 octobre 1925.De l&apos;avis du Gouvernement francais, T acceptation du point de vue allie par le Gouvernement allemand est plus qu&apos;implicite. La note de 1&apos;Ambassade d&apos;Allemagne du 23 octobre rappelle, en effet, que rinexecutidn des demandes des allies empeche ceux-ci de considerer comme accomplies les obligations imposees a 1&apos;Allemagne par le traite; elle ajoute que le Gouvernement allemand est a meme de faire savoir a la Conference des Ambassadeurs qu&apos;un nombre considerable des demandes enum^rees a la Partie III de 1&apos;Annexe I a la note collective sont executees et dans une liste des &apos;&apos; demandes executees &apos;&apos; est indiqu^e sous le chiffre 1, comme le rappelle d&apos;ailleurs le Gouvernement britannique dans le deuxieme paragraphe de sa note : &quot;Police; suppression des corps de police auxiliaire et des volontaires.&quot;L&quot;organisation d&apos;une police auxiliaire en Allemagne n&apos;est done pas seule-ment, aux yeux du Gouvernement francais, la violation d&apos;une decision reguliere-ment prise en vertu du traits, mais d&apos;un accord intervenu entre les Gouverne-ments allies et le Gouvernement allemand pour 1&apos;execution de ce meme traite.Cet accord s&apos;est d&apos;ailleurs trouve confirme par un echange de lettres des 21 et 23 decembre 1926 entre la Conference des Ambassadeurs et 1&apos;Ambassade d&apos;Allemagne a Paris.    Dans sa lettre du 23 decembre, M. von Hoesch faisaitLIST  OF ANNEXES.
.   3-9 ,savoir explicitement queJaSftlSC^tefei^^e^ggaJd^cWait &quot; d&apos;accord avec la fixation des effectifs de police en Allemagne &quot; precisee dans la lettre de la conference du 21 decembre et &quot; sous les conditions y mentionnees.&quot;Au cours d&apos;une demarche effectuee le 6 avril dernier par 1&apos;Ambassadeur dela Republique a Berlin pour demander au Gouvernement du Reich ce qu&apos;il compt,ait faire pour mettre fin a un etat de choses contraire aux traites et accords&apos;en vigueur, M. von Neurath n&apos;a pas conteste les arguments juridiques qui lui ont ete exposes et s&apos;est borne, pour justifier les mesures prises par M. Goering, a irivoqiier la situation particulierement troublee que traversait 1&apos;Allemagne.3. Le Gouvernement britannique n&apos;estime pas, d&apos;autre part, disposer de preuves suffisantes pour lui permettre de soutenir que les effectifs et les armements de forces de police auxiliaire depassent les chiffres autorises.A cet egard, le Gouvernement frangais croit devoir noter tout d&apos;abord qu&apos;aux termes memes de Tarrete de M. Goering, la police auxiliaire vient non pas se substituer a la police existante, mais la renforcer. II est logique de penser que ses effectifs et ses armements s&apos;ajoutent done aux effectifs et aux armements deja existants. D&apos;autre part, le Ministre allemand des Affaires etrangeres, dans sa conversation du 6 avril avec 1&apos;Ambassadeur de France a Berlin, a admis que le Commissaire prussien avait autorise pour la Prusse un recrutement allant jusqu&apos;a 50,000 hommes, c&apos;est-a-dire le doublement des effectifs reguliers. M. von Neurath a ajoute, il est vrai, que le chiffre de 25,000 recrues n&apos;avait pas ete depasse et que les nouveaux policiers n&apos;etaient armes de fusil qu&apos;avec l&apos;obligation, leur service accompli, de les laisser dans les casernes. Cependant, 1&apos;augmentation des effectifs et des armements de la police dans une mesure considerable n&apos;est, dans ces conditions, plus contestable.4. Pour ce qui touche a la zone demilitarisee, le Gouvernement britannique ne pense pas disposer d&apos;une documentation suffisante pour prouver que les effectifs de police dans la zone rhenane depassent de plus de 200 hommes les chiffres con-venus et qu&apos;il y ait, en consequence, manquement de la part du Reich aux engage-ments pris par lui dans 1&apos;echange de lettres des 18 et 19 Janvier 1930 entre la Conference des Ambassadeurs et 1&apos;Ambassade dAllemagne a Paris.Le Gouvernement francais reconnait volontiers qu&apos;il n&apos;a sur les effectifs de police en zone dernilitarisee que des indications fragmentaires. Elles etablissent cependant que ces effectifs s&apos;elevaient fin mars a environ 3,000 hommes de plus que le total fixe par les accords germano-allies. Au surplus, les declarations de M. von Neurath a 1&apos;Ambassadeur de France a Berlin ne permettent pas de douter que les effectifs reguliers de la police ne soient depasses en Prusse rhenane comme dans le reste du Reich.5. Tout en se defendant de vouloir admettre un manquement a une decision prise en execution du traite, le Gouvernement britannique note pour conclure quul serait faoheux a Theure presente de poursuivre avec 1&apos;Allemagne une discus-sion irritante sur la question de la police auxiliaire, alors que cette question pourrait recevoir une solution dans le cadre des decisions que la Conference du Desarmement va etre amenee a prendre.Le Gouvernement de la Republique veut, comme le Gouvernement britannique, esperer que les d6bats de Geneve permettront de resoudre, pour 1&apos;avenir, la question des polices allemandes. II ne se dissimule pas qu&apos;une demarche entreprise aupres du Conseil de la Societe des Nations, sans attendre Tissue des discussions en cours a la -Conference du Desarmement, serait susceptible de compliquer encore une situation dej a delicate; il a pris note enfin de 1&apos;assurance donnee par M. von Neurath a 1&apos;Ambassadeur de France a Berlin que 1&apos;intention de son Gouvernement n&apos;etait pas de proceder a un reinforcement durable de la police reguliere. Dans ces circonstances, le Gouvernement de; la Republique se trouve d&apos;accord avec le Gouvernement britannique pour reconnaitre qu&apos;il est preferable de ne pas donner momentanement d&apos;autre suite a 1&apos;affaire.Si, toutefois, les espoirs communs des deux Gouvernements devaient etre d6cus et si le Reich ne prenait pas a bref d^lai les mesures necessaires pour retablir, en ce qui concerne la police des divers &quot; pays,&quot; une situation normale, le Gouvernement de la Republique ne pourrait pas accepter que persistat un etat de ehoses manifestement contraire aux obligations que 1&apos; Allemagne a contractees et dont il ne lui appartient pas de se degager par sa seule volonte. II ne saura.it, en effet, rester indifferent a des manquements au traits, dont certains peuvent etre d&apos;importance secondaire, mais qui, en se multipliant, acquierent, par leur nombre meme, un caractere surlequel il n&apos;est pas permis de se meprendre.
Dans ce domaine, toute tolerance injustifieS risque d&apos;etre interpr^tee comme un encouragement a des initiatives plus graves encore. Les termes de la communi-cation adressee a 1&apos;Ambassadeur de France ,donnent au Gouvernement de la Republique le ferme espoir que, dans la&apos; situation ainsi envisagee, le Gouverne-ment britannique serait pret a se concerter avec lui sur la methode a employer pour mettre fin a un manquement caracterise au traite et aux accords subs^quents qui en ont fixe 1&apos;application.ANNEX II.League oe Nations. Communicated to the Council. &apos; C. 724 (1), 1926, IX.Execution of the Military, Naval and Air Clauses of the Treaties of Peace.Report by M. Benes.Adopted by the Council on December 11, 1926.Geneva, December 11, 1926. GN this occasion and in reply to certain questions submitted by the German Government regarding the regulations adopted by the Council on the 27th September, 1924, and the 14th March, 1925, I propose that the Council should give the following explanations : 1. The Council of the League of Nations, acting by a majority vote, shall decide in conformity with Article 213 of the Treaty of..Versailles, whether it is necessary, in any particular case, to hold an investigation, and it shall then specify the object and the limits of such investigation. The Commissions of Investigation shall act under the authority and on the instructions of the Council; the Council&apos;s decisions shall be taken by a majority vote.2. To render an effective investigation possible, the Commission shall apply to the representative appointed by the German Government or to his delegates, who will procure without delay the assistance of the administrative, judicial or military authority competent under German law. Such investigation shall then be carried out and findings reached as the Commission, acting within the limits of its instructions, may consider advisable, the interested party being given a hearing (contradictoirement).3. The prohibition laid down that the nationals of a State subjected to the right of investigation shall not form part of commissions of investigation, shall be understood in the sense that the nationals of the State in the territory of which an investigation is undertaken, shall never form part of a Commission holding such investigation. 54. It is understood that the provisions of Article 213 of the Peace Treaty with Germany, relating to investigations, shall be applicable to the demilitarised Rhine zone as to other parts of Germany. These provisions do not provide in this zone, any more than elsewhere, for any special control by local standing and permanent groups. In the demilitarised Rhine zone such special groups, not provided for in Article 213, shall not be set up except by convention between the Governments concerned.5. The explanations given in Articles 1, 2 and 3 above naturally apply to cases-under Articles 159 of the Treaty of Saint-Germain, Article 143 of the Treaty of Trianon, and Article 104 of the Treaty of Neuilly.
HANNEX III.Extract from an Opinion by Sir C. Hurst on the Powers of the League of Nations under Article 213 of the Treaty of Versailles (embodied in a Foreign Office Letter to War Office, Admiralty and Air Ministry of January 27, 1925).NO provision in the Treaty of Versailles, Part V, or in the Covenant of the League of Nations, confers any general power upon the League or upon the Council of the League to enforce the provisions of treaties in general or of the disarmament clauses of the Treaty of Versailles in particular. What Article 213 does is to confer upon the Council of the League the power to hold investigations, i.e., to enquire into and determine the facts.The military, naval and air clauses of the Treaty of Versailles providing for the disarmament of Germany fall into two groups : (a) Those which impose a transitory obligation upon Germany which she was bound to fulfil within a limited -period, and (b) those which impose upon her permanent obligations, such as the provision relating to the construction or acquisition of submarines or that relating to compulsory military service. Special organisations were set up to control the execution of the transitory clauses (see Article 203), and for the permanent clauses the League of Nations was given the right of investigation. This right of investigation is the sole function conferred upon the League in connexion with Part V (the military clauses).One of the great difficulties in the way of any scheme for the limitation of armaments is the difficulty of ensuring its observance, and the chief difficulty in the way of ensuring observance is the difficulty of getting at the truth. Presumably, therefore, it was considered by the framers of Part V of the Treaty of Versailles that if the League was given a power which would enable it tp investigate the facts and get at the truth, the probability of Germany violating the disarmament clauses would be greatly minimised, if not entirely removed.The Treaty of Versailles has no status different from other treaties, and the League of Nations has not been given any general function or duty of enforcing the provisions of all treaties. The action which the Council can take on the report of a commission of investigation is thus very limited. Such a report will establish the fact whether or not a breach of the treaty has been committed. The type of decision which can then be taken by the Council is, for instance, to publish the report, or. to communicate it to all the other members of the League, or to consider the question of strengthening the machinery for making further investigations in the future. The Council certainly has not the power of setting all the other members of the League in motion for the purpose of applying coercion to Germany merely because she has broken a treaty engagement.What, then, is the position where an investigation ordered by the Council under Article 213 results in the establishing of some violation by Germany of her treaty engagements under the military, naval or air clauses of the Treaty of Versailles 1 It is that Germany has violated the engagements which she has entered into with the other parties to the Treaty of Versailles. There would then arise between them and Germany a dispute, but it is a dispute in which the League of Nations will not play the part of a party to the dispute. The role of the League will be that of endeavouring to prevent war and of bringing the parties to the dispute to an amicable solution. The parties to the dispute will be Germany on the one side, and one or more of the Allies on the other. The role of the League under Article 213 will have been fulfilled by its enquiry into and determination of facts, and its role under the articles of the- Covenant as an organisation for endeavouring to bring the disputants to a harmonious conclusion of their quarrel will begin. The Council of the League will then act under Article 11 of the Covenant (which necessitates the concurrence of the parties to the dispute in any action thus taken, as well as unanimity of all other members of the League represented on the Council), or, under Article 15, which excludes the parties to the dispute from the calculation with regard to unanimity and provides also what is to. happen if the non-parties to the dispute cannot arrive at a unanimous conclusion among themselves.
Extracts from the correspondence respecting the United States proposal for the renunciation of war (Cmd. 3109 and 3153).THE exchange of correspondence which preceded the signature of the Kellogg Pact contains certain passages in which the French, German, British and United States Governments define their conception of the relation of the Pact to the Covenant of the League of Nations and incidentally to the Locarno Treaty.On the 26th March, 1928, the French Ambassador in Washington informed the United States Government that &quot;if it is clearly understood in a general way that the obligations of the new pact should not be substituted for, or prejudice in any way, previous obligations contained in international instruments such as the Covenant of the League of Nations, the Locarno agreements or treaties guaranteeing neutrality whose character and scope cannot be modified thereby, then the differences of opinion which have appeared in the course of previous phases of the negotiation have to do more with words than with the reality of the problem facing the two Governments to-day.On the 27th April, 1928, the German Government informed the United States Ambassador in Berlin that &quot;In so far as Germany is concerned the only international agreements which need be considered as liable to be affected by the provisions of the new pact are the Covenant of the League and the Locarno-Rhineland Pact; Germany had not entered into any other international engagements which could be affected by the new proposal. In the view of the German Government the observance of the obligations devolving under the Covenant of the League and the Rhineland Pact must remain immovably fixed. The German Government are, however, convinced that these obligations do not contain anything which could in any way conflict with the obligations fore-shadowed in the draft pact of the United States. On the contrary, the German Government consider that the binding obligation not to resort to war as an instrument of national policy can only tend to strengthen the basic principles of the League Covenant and the Rhineland Pact.On the 19th May, 1928, His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom informed the United States Ambassador in London that they &quot;appreciate the scruples which have prompted the suggestions by the French Government. The exact fulfilment of treaty engagements is a matter which affects the national honour;  precision  as to  the scope  of such engagements is, therefore, ofimportance.....The preservation of peace has been the chief concern of HisMajesty&apos;s Government and the prime object of all their endeavours. It is the reason why they have given ungrudging support to the League of Nations, and why they have undertaken the burden of the guarantee embodied in the Locarno Treaty. The sole object of all these engagements is the elimination of war as an instrument of national policy, just as it is the purpose of the peace pact now proposed. It is because the object of both is the same that there is no real antagonism between the treaty engagements which His Majesty&apos;s Government&quot; have already accepted and the pact which is now proposed. The machinery of the Covenant and of the Treaty of Locarno, however, go somewhat further than a renunciation of war as a policy, in that they provide certain sanctions for a breach of their obligations. A clash might thus conceivably arise between the existing treaties and the proposed pact, unless it is understood that the obligations of the new engagement will cease to operate in respect of a party which breaks its pledges and adopts hostile measures against one of its co-contractants. For the Government of this country respect for the obligations arising out of the Covenant of the League of Nations and out of the Locarno treaties is fundamental. Our position in this regard is identical with that of the German Government as indicated in their note of the 27th April. His Majesty&apos;s Government could not agree to any new treaty which would weaken or undermine these engagements on which the peace of Europe rests. . . . Mr. Kellogg has made it clear in the speech to which I have drawn attention that he had no intention by the terms of the new treaty of preventing the parties to the Covenant of the League or to the Locarno Treaty from fulfilling their obligations.&quot; Further, in a note dated the 18th July, 1928, Sir Austen Chamberlain pointed out to the United StatesANNEX IV.
oCharge d&apos;Affaires in London &quot; that respect for the obligations arising out of the Covenant of the League of Nations and of the Locarno treaties was the foundation of the policy of the Government of this country, and that they could not agree to any new treaty which would weaken or undermine these engagements. . . . His Majesty&apos;s Government in Great Britain do not consider, after mature reflection, that the fulfilment of the obligations which they have undertaken in the Covenant of the League of Nations and in the Treaty of Locarno, is precluded by their acceptance of the proposed treaty. They concur in the view enunciated by the German Government in their note of the 27th April, that those obligations do not contain anything which could conflict with the treaty proposed by the United States Government.&quot;On the 23rd June, 1928, the United States Charge&quot; dAffaires in London informed His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom that &quot; The Covenant imposes no affirmative primary obligation to go to war. The obligation, if any, is secondary, and attaches only when deliberately accepted by a State. Article 10 of the Covenant has, for example, been interpreted by a resolution submitted to the Fourth Assembly, but not formally adopted owing to one adverse vote, to mean that: &apos; It is for the constitutional authorities of each member to decide, in reference to the obligation of preserving the independence and the integrity of the territory of the members, in what degree the member is bound to assure the execution of this obligation by employment of its military forces.&apos; There is, in my opinion, no necessary inconsistency between the Covenant and the idea of an unqualified renunciation of war. The Covenant can, it is true, be construed as authorising war in certain circumstances, but it is an authorisation and not a positive requirement.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
