<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 99-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IMPERIAL &quot;WAR , CABINET.With the Secretary&apos;s Compliment Circulated to the Imperial War Cabinet at the request of Sir Robert Borden.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, 21st June, 1918.
THIt Oeeifltotnt U W Property of Hva ^ritaiinlc M.f&apos;8 Oov\: :-nent.Colonel W. Dally imt.QANADIAH GOVT^HHENT LIQUOR REGULATIONS: 1917 - 19iaM EHORAHDUH PROM THE PRIVY COUNCIL OFFICE, OOVSRIMSNT OF CANADA FOR CiffiCTJLATION AT THE IMPERIAL WAR CABINET, 1918By the end of 1917, the sale of intoxicating liquor was prohibited as a war measure in all the Provinces of Canada, save Quebecj   and In February 1918 the Legislature of that Province passed a Province.^wide measure prohibiting the s&amp;lo of intoxicating liquor after the first day of Hay 1918*    Inder the constitution of the Dominion it is beyond the power of the Provincial Governments to control the importation or manufacture of, or inter-provincial traffic in, Intoxicating liquor*    To make prohibition a fact throughout the Dominion it was therefore necessary for the Federal Government to supplement the prohibitory legis-lation of the Provinces*In November 1917 it was forbidden by the Dominion Government as a war measure to use food-stufifs for the distillation of potable liquors. In the same month the quantity of malt manufactured and the quantity of barley used in the manufacture of malt were both limited in the Interest of food production.On December 22nd 1917, the Prime Minister made the following statement.&quot;On December 17 the people gave to the &quot;Government an unmistakable mandate for the vigorous &quot;prosecution of the war and for tho employment of all &quot;the country?a energies and rosouroos necessary to &quot;achieve victory^    It is essential, and indeed vital, &quot;for tho efficient conduct of tho war that wasteful &quot;or unnecessary expenditure should bo prohibited, and &quot;that all articles capable of being utilised as food &quot;should be conserved.    It is beyond question that tho &quot;use of liquor affects adversoly the realisation of &quot;this purpose&quot;*thisFollowing   -itHatomont was tho announcement that the War Committee of tho Cabinet had come to tho conclusion that further regulations should be introduced to prohibit?zap
(a) The importation of liquor into Canada.

(b) The transportation of liquor into any part of Canada ? where its sale is illegal.

(5) The manufacture of intoxicating liquor in Canada.

In fulfilment of the Government&apos;s policy as announced by the Prime Minister, Orders-in-Council were ? under the War Measures Act 1914, as follows:-

1. Oders-in-Council, 22nd December 1917, prohibiting the importation of all intoxicating liquor into Canada on and after said date, subject to provision for importation of liquor after said date which had been bona-fide purchased for importation on said date.

2. Order-in-Counc11, 11th March 1918:

(a) prohibiting the manufacture of intoxicating liquor within the Dominion of Canada after the 1st day of April 1918, save for permitted purposes;

(b) prohibiting the transportation of any intoxicating liquor into any prohibited area after the said 1st day of April 1918.

(c) prohibiting the sale of intoxicating liquor which is in or which is to be delivered within any prohibited area,

3. Intoxicating liquor is defined in both Orders-in-Council, as any liquor or beverage containing more than two-and-one-half per cent of proof spirits; this is the standard already adopted by the Provinces.

4. The importation, manufacture, transportation and sale of intoxicating liquors for sacramental, industrials, artistic, mechanical, scientific and medicinal purposes are permitted under all Orders-in-Council.

5. Although the greater part of the Province of Quebec is under local prohibition laws - as the Province-wide measure does not go into effect until the 1st of May. 1918, the prohibition of manufacture in that Province does not become operative until the 31st day of December 1918.

Copies of the Orders-in-Council of the 22nd December 1917 and 11th March 1918 are annexed hereto 

OTTAWA, May 18th, 1918

not reproduced.



</content>
</cab>
