<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 141-142</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
.1Iiimi f. Dally km.fohi.s.. Doqumenti s t the, property of JUjl Britannic Majesty&apos;. 8 Government). 8jt.War Cab ine.t,&quot;Release of. Agricultural Labouror JI13,itaryrr Seryice&quot;. leraorandum by the President of the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries.On May 8th, 1918,&quot;We0,409 M,7, an agreement was made that the Board of Agriculture for England and Wales should endeavour to release 30,000 men between the ages of 19 and 31.I desire to report to the War Cabinet the result of the effort to fulfil the agreement.A quota was fixed for each County, and the &quot;War Executive Committees were asked to find the men,    With one exception, I &quot;believe that they have done their utmost.On the Board&apos;s figures, 15,588 men have been found under the Proclamation.     All are more or less skilled, and half are horsemen and ploughmen.From the men between the ages 23-31 it has proved almost impossible to find the 14,412 required to complete the total, -They are not only more skilled but more experienced;   they are tho key-men of the farms.The difficulty in finding the men arises from two facts which are established by the effort to find the quota,(l)   The number of Grade 1 men within the limits of age proves to be much fewer than the Board supposed.     For instance.   In Gloucestershire, out of 1,100 men between the ages of 19-31, only 517 prove to be Grade 1;   in Berkshire, out of 995, only 337.     In Norfolk, out of 600 cases^examined.-b^tween-the ages-23*31, only 80 were Grade 1. (2)   The men who are eligible prove to he the very men on whom the cultivation of the land depends.For instance.     In order to ohtain 500 men, Northanks schedules 89 waggoners, carters and horsemen, 20 ploughmen, 19 shepherds, 9 engine drivers, and 69 cowmen, and yet fallsm   1   mitj
short of its quota by 73,     In order to obtain 400 men, West Sussex schedules 126 ploughman and carters, 6 shepherds, 12 engine drivers, 45 cowmen,   clacktmlths and wheelwrights, 6 farmers,   In order to obtain ?50 msn, JSasf Sussex scLedules 99 ploughmen and carters, 4 shepherds, 60 cowmen, 1 tractor driver, .  1 wheelwright, 14 farmers.     In Norfolk it is stated by the Committee that in 90 cases out of 100 the men scheduled were the men who kept the farms going, and skilled steam ploughmen have had to be included.The results show that if 30,000 men are taken from agricul-ture the harvesting of the extended acreage of corn crops will be endangered, the root and forage crops, already in difficulties by reason of the weather, will often be abandoned, and a serious decline in the production of food next year must be anticipated.     Disaster will follow to many individuals.     The Board have evidence that the cultivation of many farms.must necessarily be abandoned and in a far greater number of cases the farmers will cut their programme down to a minimum.It will be remembered that in response to the Government appeal farmers have made a great effort to increase the production of home-grown food.     They are working under the greatest difficulties with regard to labour;   they find their best men taken while the remainder are very generally disinclined to do more than the minimum&apos; dayfs work,,     In consequence farmers are almost universally in revolt and embij&amp;cered at wHnat they consider the Government1 s failure to keep the promises upon the strength of which they embarked upon extra cultivation.I submit therefore that the Government must rest content with the clean cut of 15,538 men taken under the Proclamation,R.B. PROTHEBO.June 22nd, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
