<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 174-177</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
II$HIS PQOPHEilfg? IS THE HiOPElRTY Off HIS BBITANNIO MAJESTY&apos;3 aOTOMBOTl*129SEORJfi- nB   o a b i m e yt*&apos; TKlilATmNT Off AIJEg BmilESd-ftlemorandum &quot;by Sir EtTroup^Allegations are appearing in the Press, to the effect that permanent officials of the Home Office have, contrary to the policy of the Government,, been endeavouring to protect alien enemies from internment or repatriation..   There is no foundation whatever for this suggestion.   The permanent officials of the Home Office have, since the beginning of the Tar., carried out whatever.was the policy of their Chief, and the policy of the Home Secretary has always been the policy of the Government, .   .In the first days of the Vfar the only persons interned were enemy agents, suspects, crews of German ships, and a&apos; certain number of German reservists.   About October. 1914, at Lord Kitchenerrs instance, the internment of enemy civilians was oarried out on a large scale, and by the end of two or three weeks some 20,000 had been rounded up by the Police, acting under instructions from the Home Office, and were placed in camps under Uilitary control,   L little later, on 11th November, the Cabinet decided, again at the request of Lord Kitchener, that the T7ar Office should take direct responsibility for releasing interned civilians and that, a large number of Austrians and Germans should be released on parole.   The steps taken by the Y/ar Office led to the release of about 2,700 alien enemies, but in February 1915, on -strong representations from the Home Office, Lord Kitchener agreed to drop the policy of general release and to restrict release to. special cases,.*./- , *After the sinking of the &quot;Lusitania&quot;&apos;, a definite policy was adopted by the Government &quot;and announced to the House of Commons by Lir, Asquith on 13th llay5. 1915* He stated that the general policy would be to intern all adult males of enemy nationality, or, if over military age, to repatriate them, but
that there would be eases for exceptional treatment where this was-required by &quot;Justice or humanity&quot; and that those oases would be dealt with by an Advisory Committee of a Judicial character. At the same time tho responsibility for internment and repatria- , tion was transferred from the &apos;7ar Office to the Home Office.The policy announced by Lir. Asquithj which resulted in ISjOOO additional internments, has been&apos;steadily carried out by successive Home Secretaries - by Sir John Simon, by I.ir. Samuel and/ with some increased strictness, by Sir George Cave.   It has never come formally before the present War Cabinet, but its results were considered when the Cabinet agreed to the withdrawal of guards from vulnerable points? and it has been repeatedly debated in Parliament and successfully defended by the Homo Secretary.   The great mass of alien enemies of military ago have remained in internment, only those being exempted who were recommended   for exemption by the Advisory Committee; and some even of these have from time to time been sent into internment if they ceased to be in useful employment or for other reasons.. Ho appreciable number has been released from internment, except those who have been repatriated under the Agreements, and a certain number (about l,650x.) who have been temporarily released on licence for definite employment on work of national importance, chiefly agriculture*In all, 32,000 alien enemies were interned, of whom sevens-eighths were Germans.   Those who remain here uninterned (6^000 Germans, of whom one-third are of military age, 5*500 Austrian^, and 1,000 (Turks and Bulgarians) consist of four classes.  (l) Aliens of friendly nationality, such as Alsatians and Poles; (2) Old men and invalids;x nearly all of these are Austrians; and five-sixths of them are employed in agriculture. The experiment has proved so far completely successful; the work of the men has been of service to the country, and there have been no escapes or serious misconduct,, The employers are un3er terms not to continue their employment when British labour is available after the ITaiV
(3)   Portions who, being frfc* from all susipicion, areemployed in specially. important industries, from which they could not fro removed&quot;without detriment to the interests of this Country;(4)   Persons who, also free from suspicion, have lived here for many year3 and have married British wives and have British born or-ildron.   Of the Germans, 4,000 have British wives or British born children, and 2,700 havo sons serving in B.M. Forces.There are only a very few oases that - do not come&quot; into one or other of these four classes. &quot;-   If the Government should decide to.adopt a more strigent policy, some of the last mentioned class might perhaps bo interned without, doing much harm,-but none of the other classes could.be interfered with without exciting strong opposition which would be better founded than the ^present press agitation. It would ,be an outrage to intern men of the friendly nation-alitios for whose cause we are now fighting;: to intern cripples and Invalids merely because they are Germans would be outdoing the worst features of Prussian policy: to intern skillsd workmen who cannot be replaced or men engaged in agriculture at the present time would clefinitely damage the national interests; and tho only class left from whom additional persons could be found for internment would be men who have lived hero for many years - some from infancy - who have adopted English habits and are of English sympathies., and. many of whom have children fallen in the War or now fighting in our Armies.All mala alien enemies who are not interned havo boon called on, if physically fit,      undertake national service;and a considerable number havo been sent to work in Oamps under tho Road. Board or the Timbor Controller,The number of alien enemies whu have been allowed bythe Police and military authorities to continue to live inprohibited areas in England and Wales \k 1*800, most of them
*132woman anr] ehil&amp;ron.   Jhoy. fcave boon rspoatodly sifted and none loft who could be removed without &quot;hard3hip or injustice&quot;. Iks &quot;Oommisaion-oonsiiHing or Sir Alan Sykss, ii,Pfl, and Sir Louis Dane, who reviewed all the permits in 1916, reported that the work of tho Police had already beon &quot;very well done,&quot; that persons who oould be. a danger to the State had boon excluded, and that &quot;after this review few can be&apos; rosiding in prohibited areas whoso presence could even justify popular suspicion or discontent on social or commercial grounds*&quot; .In connection with, the present press campaign, it should bo noted that the first attack on the Home Offlee was a leader in the Daily Mail 011 tho day after Sir George Cave left for Holland: and that the personal attack on Mr. Pedder was made onthe morning after he left to inspect the internment Camps in the Isle of Man.   The answer to the question how many applications for internment from Scotland Yard or the Military Intelligence -Branch have been refused by Mr. Pedder is none:   any such applications would be refused only by the Home Secretary./but it is believed that there are few, if anya such cases.

</content>
</cab>
