<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 266-267</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;Political.,Intelligence Department,June 26th, 1918.Foreign Office.SOCIALISTS TOWARDS PEACE.Prom &quot;Social-Demokraten&quot; of 5th June, 1918. An article signed by Hjalmar Eranting.After giving a summary taken from &quot;Vorwarts&quot; of the speeches of Ebert, Scheidemann and Gradnauer (at a meeting of the Socialist party executive) on the memorandum from the representatives present at the Inter-Allied Socialist Conference in London, Branting writes:   &quot;The Platonic resolution for a peace by understanding in accordance with the 19th July resolution, taken together with the support given by the Party to the Offensive and its declaration in &quot;Vorwarts&quot; that peace must now be won by the victory of the German Arms, is not likely to disturb Hindenburg1s and Ludendorffs sleep to any appreciable degree.As regards the speeches, Ebertls is couched in a conciliatory tone, though to refer to the Stockholm declarations as an answer to the London Conference is to evade the issue.   Scheidemann1s speech, on the other hand, was directly provocative.   To accuse the Entente Socialists of &quot;annexationism&quot; when they expressly maintain on all points the right of self-determination of nations, cannot delude anyone outside Germany, and if they are in essentials in accord with their Governments in this regard, that reflects favourably on those Governments, and not unfavourably on the Entente Socialists.     0ne&apos;s only fear is that after the submissive attitude taken up, relative to Brest-Litovsk and the menace to the West, there is the same agreement on the German side between the war aims of the Xrovernment and of Scheidemann ,*   the certainty is, however, that included in these is not the-self-determination of nations. Brest-Litovsk and Bukarest have shown the -world how matters stand
as regards annexations and contributions.   Finally, tho charges brought against the Entente Socialists, that they are mainly responsible for these peace treaties, to combat which the German Majority Socialists have done nothing,, reads more like a bad joke than anything else.26.6.18.

</content>
</cab>
