<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 268-270</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS. DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S,B 0 R, E.T,G.T.- 4961. WAR   CABINET.TREATMENT OJ1 AIM ENEMIES&apos; AND PERSONS Off...   .  ^---i^f^y TOggT---^ . -Memorandum (No.2.) by Sir Edward Troup.( Reference War Cabinet 435, Minute 9.)Mr. Chamberlain has suggested that I should supplement certain paints in my previous note&apos;? which was written before I knew that the matter was coming Immediately before the War Cabinet-(1) With regard to the action of the Advisory Committee in granting exemptions,the statement, which I understand has been made, that the Committee required proof that a man was dangerous before interning or repatriating him, must have been made under  a complete misapprehension.   The great mass of Germans were interned without any evidence of their being,hostile or dangerous.   Broadly speaking, all Germans of military age with less.than thirty years residence (whether they had British wives and children or. not) were interned, except &quot;friandllas&quot;, invalids, and a small number engaged in essential industries: and men who would otherwise have been exempted were at once.interned or repatriated if the Police or the Military Authorities expressed an opinion that they were dangerous or that their sentiments were hostile.   Such statements were accepted without question except in a few oases where the aliens produced positive evidence of their good faith find loyalty to this country.Possibly there has been some confusion with the case of British subjects of hostile origin or associations interned under No. 14-B of the Defence of tho liealm Regulations.   Alien enemies are interned as such under theljoyal Prerogative, and no reason for the internment need be given; but when a British subject of hostile origin is proposed to be interned under No. 14-B of the Defence of the Realm Regulations some prima facie ground for &apos; believing him to be a danger to the realm has to be alleged before the Committee can recommend his internment.   The position with regard to such British subjects has been that if prima facia grounds of suspicion were alleged by tho $aval or Military Authorities the Committee recommended internment unless they were satisfied by affirmative evidence that there was nothing in the case.   In some cases,&apos;even if the Committee was not itself satis-fled that any case of suspicion was established, they recommended internment en a definite statement from Colonel  ell or Captain Hall that he had reason   to believe the man was dangerous.(2) The question has been asked why old men and invalids were not repatriated.   Ths answer is that a large number were       . repatriated.   Of those who remain, some were too ill to travel; others were persons who had resided in this country for many years, whose children or other near relatives were British born and in England, and who had no ties or connections or       means of living in Germany.   These were regarded as cases which came within Mr. AsquiWs statement that exemptions would be made on grounds of humanity.-&amp; 1 faG.Tv 4931.&apos;
- 2 **(3)   With regard to naturalized persona of German origin, the right course.appears to bo to proceed at onoe with tho Bill which has already &quot;been introduced in tho House of Commons, and which would, have boon read a second time a fortnight ago if the Home Secretary had not gone to Holland.     The Bill, in spite of suggestions in the Press, is a strong one., and might, if necessary, be further strengthened in Committee.The suggestion, that all Germans should be de-naturalized who have acquired British nationality during the last 25 or 30 years would not b,e satisfactory.     It would not touch the case of Jonas&apos;, who was naturalized 42 years ago, nor that of Hahn alias Vernon, who was the British born son of a naturalized German, while it would damage our cause by alienating many men who are fighting in the Army or doing other patriotic service.     13ven if the proposal wore limited to men naturalized since the war began it would hit Baron Schroder whose naturalization was granted on the imperative demand of Lord Cunliffe as being essential to our financial measures at the beginning of the war.,    Further a hard and fast rule would give ground for the suggestion that the British Government, like the German Government, treats a solemn obligation as a scrap of paper when the mood suits it.     I do not think Parliament would agree to this whereas the principle of denaturalizing in oases of suspicion can easily be defended.(4)   If anything further is to be done with regard to the uninterned Germans, (who are the main object of the newspaper agitation), it would have to be.a fresh review of the exemptions, but as the cases were all reviewed about a year age by Sir George Cavers instructions, I do not wish to make any suggestion on this subject in his absence.I may, however, point out that such a review, while it might be useful if it would calm the newspaper agitation, would not, I believe, touch the real danger&apos;   (a)   From 3rd August, 1914, when 22 known German spies were arrested, up to the present time, the Germans at large in this country have been sifted again and again,, and a spy is now less likely to be found among them than in any other class of aliens.(b) If the exemptions are reviewed, it would still be necessary on political grounds to exempt most of the Polish Jews, who as a class ought, I believe, to be distrusted.     A day or two ago the Home Office interned a Polish Jew, who had disregarded the a&quot;1 lens regulations and was open to some suspicion on other grounds &apos; J.ch may or may not be well founded, and immediately we have a letter from Mr. *.7ickham Steed of &quot;The Times&quot;, saying that we are alienating the sympathies of an oppressed, and friendly race.(c) For the last three years the German attempts.at espionage in this country have been carried on almost entirely by neutrals, some of German origin, some not.     If any information is now being communicated to Germany, it must be through neutrals, either by the crews of neutral ships (though every precaution is taken) or by another neutral channel.(d) If all Germans were interned, it would be likely to give a false sense of security.     No absolute safeguard is. possible, and what is required is continual watchfulness in all directions.   Before the war British subjects with no German blood have been guilty of espionage, and since the War several such have had to be interned under Regulation 14*B.
(5&quot;)   A good deal of the Press agitation turns on the employment of so-called Germans in the public service. &apos;   I believe the fears on this head are baseless, but the oases could no doubt be reviewed without much trouble..     Such a review would probably show in almost every case a clear record of loyal and useful service which ought not to be lost to the oountry at the present time.   In the Home Office for instance there are only two men with German names (which they changed early in the War] * one is a man whose grandfather came to this country before 1800, and whose grandfather and father were both British officers:   the other is a Jew, whose family settled in England some 70 or 80 years ago, who long before the war was markedly anti-German, and who was one of the founders of the Civil Serrioe Cadet Corps and an officer in the A.S.C.&apos;(T.f.).(Signed)   EDWARD TROUP.HOME OFFICE,26th June, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
