<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 285-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IX228mZ   P0V7bJR   SITUATION.;The important Memorandum on the Man-PowerSituation (G.T.4872) &quot;by the Minister of National Servicesuggests two considerations, both of which appear toconcern matters vital to the successful prosecution ofthe War.It may be that the Members of the War Cabinetarc taking steps to deal with both matters   but, as it is not within my knowledge that they are doing so, it may not be without advantage to submit this Memorandum for their consideration.1. USE OP HEIh       The organisation of our forces in different theatres of war is doubtless influenced by special geographical, climatic and other considerations. In order therefore to secure as fair a comparison as may be with the organisation of other Armies under similar con-ditions, the present Memorandum is confined to the &quot;British Army raised in Great Britain&quot; which is serving in Prance and Italy and therefore excludes those enlisted elsewhere, whether for the Army or for auxiliary services. ) The following table is prepared from Appendix II* and is confined to the British, French and German 3?orcesserving in France and Italy:-Combatant Strength&apos;Ration Strength.   Difference.Percentage of Combatantto Ration Strength&apos;.1,386,000. 1,975,000. 2,662,0^0.2,059,000-Z, 661, CO. 3,348,OCC.673,000. 686,0&apos;-(). 686,000.67.3. 74.E. 79.5.
It will be observed that the percentage of combatant to ration strength in the British Army is 12$ less than in the German and 7$ less than that of the French Army.     If the proportion of combatant in the British Army were as high as that in the German Army, it would mean that our combatant strength in France and Italy, without any increase of those on the rati.-n strength, would be increased by about 250,000, the equivalent, I believe, of about 15 Divisions. These figures are s-..- striking and the issues involved fraught with such mmentous consequences, both to our offensive power on the Western Front and to the drain upon our man-power at home, that the causes of this disparity should, I suggest, be subject to the most critical analysis, if that is not being dune at present.It may conceivably be that the Germans are able to secure a higher pr.portion of combatants by making a greater use of Belgian prisoners or other civilian labour, but any suggestion of this kind would require to be most carefully examined before being accepted as accountable for the difference.An Army organisation suitable to the needs of a small force, such as we possessed before the&apos;War, is not necessarily the most economical as applied to vastly larger masses of men.In the case of a large number of i Divisions, for example, we do not necessarily obtain either/
either the most economical or the most competent services &quot;by Q repetition of a complete form of divisional organisa-tion appropriate to a small number of divisions acting separately or not as a part of a vast force,     The Engineering and Transportation problems, for example, of our Forces in France, treated as a whole service for the whole force might conceivably be dealt with, both more effectively and economically, by being dealt with as a whole whilst retaining a sufficiency of these services attached to the different units for the discharge of those duties which are special and necessary for that unit as a unit.2. Tiii,- CONSIDERATION OP &apos;7aR PHOBIAS.      I do not know what the arrangements are for the comprehensive and scientific study of matters of the kind already referred to or for the ready examination and adaptation of new methods so far as the experiences of the v/ar may justify then.     The readiness and resource of our enemies in adopting new methods in war, whether of tactics, the use of different arms, transport or otherwise, both for defensive and offensive purposes, of which the experiences of the past year furnish numerous illustrations, as well as the successes which the Memorandum under discussion indicates they have achieved in obtaining a very high percentage of combatant strength to ration strength, sugges that they are equipped with staff organisations of a singularly open-minded and competent character. They/
They have, of course, the immense advantage of having had through many years a large mass of men trained to study the, arts of war and have had a much greater field of selection than we have had.     In four years, we cannot fairly be expected to overcome these drawbacks in creating and training the staff for an Army ten or twenty times the size of that which existed before the war and these drawbacks which are so con-siderable with ourselves must necessarily be the greater with respect to our American Ally.     But the recognition of these drawbacks only makes the more urgent the necessity of leaving no course unexplored and no step untaken which may diminish them in any degree.My colleagues of the War Cabinet and my Rt. Hon. Friend, the Secretary of State for War, know full well that in making these observations, I an suggesting no reflection upon those who have performed such prodigies in getting together and staffing our great new Armies.     But these great new Armies raise new and special problems and they must contain amongst them somewhere a great number of the most alert and capable minds of our race, and I suggest that any and every means - however novel and however out of accord with tradition -- should be taken, if thereby we can secure the more effective direction and assembly of skilled and capable thought to the problems of the War.C. ADDISOU.27th June, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
