<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/55/0 images: 395-397</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot; &apos; 1    &quot; &apos;   ,,,&apos;/       1.*-JOCOMBB! IS TUB PROPERTY OP HIS BHITAHKIC SOVBRMC5HT.\315^ WAR QABIKHEUj&amp; *997- &apos; &apos;   &quot;SPITZBERGBN.vMemorandum &quot;by the Foreign Off left,Previous Papers O.T.1330. Q,T,14;89. G.T.1494. War CabineT&quot;l96, Minute llf and War &quot;Cabinet 365, Minute .11,Copy oi i^ote from U..S. ot s, ior ffojji^n Affaire toSecretary, \Var Cabinet.30)The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Secretary of the War Cabinet and with reference to War Cabinet Minute 365&quot; of March 13th last, item No%ll, respecting Spitsbergen, begs fceave to transmit, herewith, a memorandum prepared in the Foreign Office showing the present position with regard to the islands.The position as it stood in July 1917 &quot;was explained 1494 in a memorandum dated July l?tft, 1917f which was forwardedto Sir M. Hankey, who is also in possession of the correspondence between the Foreign Office and Admiralty during this year on the subject.Lord Hardinge of Penshurst is to request that the enclosed memorandum may bp circulated to the War Cabinet and their instructions requested thereon at an early date.Foreign Office,June 29th, 1918.
11 E li 0 H A 11 I) U MiIn tho &apos;&apos;7ar Cabinet Llinute 365 of liaroh 13th Item 11. . tho Foreign Office was directed to oonfer with the Admiralty on the subject of the Spitsbergen position and report to the War Cabinet. A letter ha&amp; a2ro;:;dy boon sent to the Admiralty,.,&apos;in which it Was-pointed out that ono of tho reported provisions of tho Russo-German ?eaoe Treaty appeared to show that Germ?my intended to secure Russia&apos;s support for .&apos;.:.n endeavour by her to obtain a seat on the Commission for the administration of Spitsbergen when the question came up for decision at tho end of the war.    The German representative, if supported by the Russian^ would be in a position to dominate the Commission if the only other countries represented were llorway and Sweden.    i;Ir. Balfour therefore proposed, if the Admiralty concurred, to suggest to the French Government that Prance and Great Britain should also claim representation on the Commission, that it should be ascertained whether Norway and Sweden would look favourably on such a proposal, and that the United Stages Government should be asked whether they were still interested in Spitsbergen and whether they had any views as to the German action.    Before doing so, however, Mr. Balfour request^ ed that tho position should bo once more examined from the naval point of view, sinco the ovents which had ocourred in Russia sinoe the Admiralty had last expressed thoir opinion that Spits-borgen possessed no strategic importance, and the possibility of the Arctic Sea becoming the only available route botwoejf this country and Siberia^ might perhaps have affected the naval view as to the strategic importance of Spitsbergen.The Admiralty replied that they had re-examined tho quostion of tho value oi Spitsbergen as a naval base and found no reason to alter1 the vlows given in Sir John Jollieoers lottor to the Seoretary of the &apos;7ar Cabinet of July 22nd, 1917./    They oon-sidered that the only practical measures to prevent Germany oh-taining eventual control of Spitsbergen were diplomatic, and oon-curred in the aotion which Lir. Balfour proposed to take.Replies have now been received from the countries addressed. The French Government agreed that a position In which Germany was able to dominate the Commission was unacceptable;   they were ready to consider any solution proposed by Great Britain or other interested States, and to claim to be also represented on the Corn-mission,    With this objoot they instructed the French ministers at Stockholm and Christiania to Join their British oolleagues in any action which they might take in the matter, especially with a view to ascertaining whether a proposal to admit to the Commission British and French and ovontualiy United States representatives would be favourably rogardod by the Swedish and Norwegian Govern-monts *, ,The Norwegian Government replied that they would welcome French and British representatives on tho eventual Spitsbergen Administrative Commission,   -Tho Swedish Government replied that thoy had no objection to all the contracting Powors being represented on tho Commission,
o*** $ mmThe United States Government replied that they were not at present in a position to state whether they might in the future have an interest in the settlement of affairs relating to Spitsbergen,The position, therefore, is that the Admiralty remain of opinion that Spitsbergen possesses no strategic importance for this country;   that in the event of Germany&apos;seeking to obtain a dominating position on the Commission by the admission of a representative, a claim by the French and British Governments for representation will be favourably regarded by Norway and Swedenj   that the United States attitude is doubtful, though it seems very unlikely that they would oppose such a claim.   No other countries except Russia have any particular interests in Spitsbergen.Foreign Office,June 29th, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
