<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/131/0 images: 395-397</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
OCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS GOVERNME N T)51671116 COPY NO.    ^4th July, 1967CABINETDEFENCE WITHDRAWALSMemorandum by the Lord President of the council I recognise that the plans  or much more drastic and rapidwithdrawal from the Far East and Middle East worked out by theDefence Secretary go a long way to meet the demands of those of uswho felt that the conclusions of the first Defence Review were inadequate,and left us with worldwide commitments far beyond our economic strength.    Nevertheless there are three important aspects of the newplans where, even at this late hour, further revision seems to meessential.2.      The most striking feature of the timetable of withdrawal is itsprolongation over a period of 8.-10 years.  I can see the advantages ofthis leisurely phasing at this stage when the project is being discussed with our allies.    A prolonged timetable has obvious attractionsparticularly to the Governments whose economies will be chieflyaffected.     In terms of negotiations it is obviously easier to break themin gently to the idea of our going.    But when we turn our attention from the negotiations to the actual withdrawal the disadvantages of thisleisurely phasing loom large.    For the British Government it involves the need to maintain the posture of withdrawal and of slow post-imperialist decline over nearly a decade.    For our allies it means adecade of uncertainty when Britain will be announcing the next cut-back of her commitments.    I have little doubt that whatever phasingwe work out now and irrespective of whether we announce it or not,the plan of withdrawal will be knocked sideways long before theprocess is over.3,     Nevertheless we are sometimes advised that our wisest course is to sell to our allies in our public statement the project of a lengthywithdrawal while tacitly accepting as the basis for our own actions the likelihood that we shall actually get out faster.4,     I find this line of argument both dangerous and unconvincing.Although it is less than three years since we came to office we arealready in the middle of the second drastic revision of defence plans.Each fresh revision widens of course the credibility gap.    It is surelyunwise to try to allay our allies1 anxieties about our intentions bycommitting ourselves to revised plans that will shortly require yet another revision.
3rd July, 1967 -2-SEcise?Middle East5.      I would recommend a rather different treatment of the middle and of the Far East.    In the former area the case for cutting our military commitments as soon as possible has been greatly strengthened by recent events.    In the Arab world a British miLitary presence is an embarrassment to our friends and a provocation to our enemies and does not seem to strengthen our own hands in negotiations.    I believethat we should now decide to opt out of CENTO and to cancel our treaty obligations in the Persian Gulf as soon as this can be done withoutrepercussions.6.      I recognise of course that as long as we remain in the Far east the Cyprus bases will be of special technical Importance,    NeverthelessI would urge that here too as in Malta we should plan for the removalof the British military presence as soon as possible.Far East7.      I accept that in the Far East the position of Hong Kong is uniqueand that in Singapore there are strong social and political arguments for a withdrawal carefully calculated to maintain political stability.Nevertheless I would like to see the Cabinet insist on a study of the praticability of a revised timetable with envisages completeevacuation of the mainland within five yearsQThe Far Eastern British military presence8.      In the paper presented to Cabinet by the Secretary of State for defence (C(67) 117) the continued British military presence in the far east has been reduced, after we leave the mainland, to a capability.This notable advance towards realism v/ill however be reversed ifunder pressure from our allies the actual capability we maintained isredefined as a British presence in Australia.    It is difficult to suppose that after nearly ten years of steadily declining military strength inthe area a British military presence would Be credible either to our allies or to our enemies.    In fact it would be a residual delusion ofgrandeur with which we would delude only ourselves.    It would surelybe better to eradicate it now once and for all from our plans.Economic Aid9.      The plans presented by the Secretary of State include a formidable commitment to provide economic aid over a very long period on a scale sufficient to make up the economic damage causedby our departure.     The more leisurely the phasing of our withdrawalthe easier it will be for the Governments affected to extract the pricethey want for our going.    It seems to me essential that in our negotiations we should be careful to avoid even the implicit assumptionthat  the scale of our aid must be sufficient to cover the damage ourdeparture causes and that the phasing of the withdrawal should bedetermined by the economic interests of the aress affected.    Insteadof prciongLagthe withdrawal in order to appease our allies, I should prefer us to insist on a period shorter than they deem tolerable,accepting in exchange a somewhat higher scale of economic aid.    the shorter the period the more generous the aid; the more leisurely thewithdrawal the more drastic the reduction of it.R. H, S. C.Privy Council Office, S. W. 1.


</content>
</cab>
