<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/209/4 images: 91-103</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTQ OC(80) 29 COPY NO31 May 1980CABINETUNITED KINGDOM COMMUNITY BUDGET CONTRIBUTIONAND RELATED QUESTIONSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign andCommonwealth Affairs1. After the Luxembourg European Council, it was agreed that ForeignMinisters would try to resolve the questions left outstanding then. TheLord Privy Seal and I attended a meeting ot the Foreign Affairs Council on29 May which ran on until the morning of 30 May.    This meeting, togetherwith a parallel meeting of the Agricultural Ministers, succeeded in producingproposals on the whole range of issues.   I attach a note describing theoutcome of these negotiations and showing how matters have progressedsince the Dublin and Luxembourg Councils.   I reserved the Government&apos;sposition on these proposals and undertook to consult my colleagues. Theproposals were the result of a long, difficult and laborious negotiation.2. On the Budget the basic difficulty at Luxembourg was that we couldnot get the right combination of amount and duration.    We have now got theprospect of a three-year solution.   Although the figure for our netcontribution for 1980 is higher than we would have hoped, that for 1981 iswithin our target area and better than was on offer at Luxembourg, and therefund for the two years taken together comes out higher than we wereoffered then.    Overall it represents a refund of two-thirds of our netcontribution.   The formula we have been able to obtain for 1982 is, I think,a reasonable one.    The way in which the figures are now defined is complex,and falls short of the ideal.    But the mixture of a lump sum repayment anda risk-sharing formula if our uncorrected net contribution is higher thanexpected sets clear limitations to our financial obligations.    Moreover, wehave a firm commitment to a restructuring of the Cdmmunity Budget withinthe 1 per cent Value Added Tax (VAT) ceiling.3. On Agricultural Prices, although the average increase of 5 per centis rather higher than we would like, the effect of the proposals on the RetailPrice Index (RP1) is minimal.    We are offered substantial benefits in thispackage, including the continuation of the butter subsidy, the suckler cowpremium and the refunds on whisky exports.1SECRET
SECRETOn Sheepmeat, we have achieved a potential settlement which,through the introduction of a Community financial deficiency payment^ stem in the United Kingdom, safeguards the interests of our farmers,our consumers and of New Zealand.    Although it also involves interventionin France and the possibility of export refunds, it does not do so in such away as to damage these interests.5. On fisheries, we now have a text which gives nothing away on access,protects the interests of the fishermen and sets the scene for negotiationsin the Fisheries Council, where they belong.6. I am satisfied that we could not further substantially improve onthe present agreement by prolonging the current negotiations.    We have&amp;ome a long way since Dublin.    Our partners are anxious to avoid acrisis, and the confusion which would be caused by the French national|bieasures on agriculture, but have, I am convinced, reached the limit toBhich they are prepared to go to avoid these eventualities.    I note, for scampie, that President Giscard is already under fire from the FrenchPress and the Gaullists for agreeing to go this far.    If we do not accept|what is now on offer, I see no alternative to a prolonged and bitter crisisfcithin the Community involving damaging action by the Commission andlur partners agrinst us and, of course, by us against them.    The damageBlight be lasting.7. I consider that this agreement, chough giving us less than we wouldReally have wanted, does bring about a very marked improvement in ourbudgetary position and does not involve us in damaging concessions inlather fields.    We have the commitment to a general review of the operationof the Community Budget and to avoiding a re-emergence of our presentInacceptable burden.    We ohall oee that the Community abides by it.C foreign and Commonwealth OfficeBl May 19802
CONFIDENTIAL|iMUHY BUDGET CONTRIBUTION AND RELATED QUESTIONSGETITheltable attached (Annex &apos;I) compares the offer put forward at theeigiBAffairs Council with the final offer made at Luxembourg by Chancellor|inidjjand President Giscard, on a range of possible outcomes.    The text ofHSRlusions is at Annex III. -The figures in Table 2.2.1 of the Public Expenditure White Paperlifferent from those used in the negotiations and in the Table at Annex IIse they include our contribution to that part of the Community budgetffly overseas aid) which is not allocated to individual members by the Commission.    The last White Paper contained an estimate57m for the unadjusted UK net contribution in 1980.    In the Househave subsequently suggested the figure could be as high asThe latter figure is fractionally below 2bn. EUA, and allowingifference in definition, the outcome would be fairly close toin the attached table.jic ypenditure White PaperjThelessential feature of the Luxembourg offer was the absence of asfwtory arrangement for 1982.    At the Foreign Affairs Council on 29 May,ijorireview was offejred by mid-1981;    and if this is not achieved, thelisslon will make proposals along the lines of the 1980/81 formula andCoufcil will act accordingly.    If the formula were adapted for the&apos;erelce between 1981 and 1982 in the same way as it has been for the&apos;erefce between 1980 and 1981, then, assuming an unadjusted nettribiition of 2,500 mEUA, the adjusted contribution would be 854 mEUA,ThBexamples illustrated in the attached table show that the losses in3 art broadly offset by the gains in 1981.    On certain assumptions about[unadjusted outcome, it could lead to a lower aggregate UK net contributioFoi 1980, the new offer would result in a higher UK net contribution than538|mEUA offered at Luxembourg by between 71 and 175 mEUA, dependingcanuiiHj.usted outcome.    For 1981 no risk sharing was offered at Luxembourgj thel formula offered on 29 May is likely to lead to a better result,mdflg on the unadjusted outcome, the improvement could be in the range164*] UA.
&gt; PRICES ACKAGEThe main features of the CAP prices package are as follows:-) The avefbage price increase overall is about 5 per cent.) On milk, the target price would increase by 4 per cent.  The basic co-responsibilityvy on fapers&apos; deliveries to dairies would however also increase from 0.5 to 2.0 pernt of the price, with a lower rate of 1.5 per cent on the first 60,000 kilogramslivered by producers in less favoured areas.  Thus the net increase would beper cent for most producers (and less in Germany because of monetary change),additional supplementary levy would be applied in 1981/82 if deliveries of milk1980 exceed the 1979 level by more than 1.5 per cent.  The details of thepplementary levy would, however, have to be agreed.) The other main proposal affecting milk producers is the limitation on theyment of grants on dairy farm investments.  This is now framed in a manner whichoids discrimination against UK producers.  National aids to dairy farmers&apos;ivestment would no longer be payable. Aid under Community schemes would bemited to provision for a herd of 60 cows or an increase in the size of the oducers&apos; herd of not more than 15 per cent.i) The UK butter subsidy of 13p per ]b, financed wholly from Community funds,)uld be continued.&gt;) On beef, the guide price would increase by 4 per cent but the effect on producers&apos;sturns and consumers&apos; prices in the present year would be less than this. Theroposals would enable us to continue our beef premium scheme.  There would be a newubsidy of 20 ECU per cow ( 12), funded     100 per cent by Community funds anday able on cows in specialised beef herds.f) On cereals, the target price increase is 6.25 per cent, with the interventionrices increased by 4.5 per cent.  The production refunds on cereals used in starchanufacture would be reduced.g) On sugar, the minimum beet price would increase by 4.0 per cent.  There would beio changes in the quota arrangements for 1980/81.  This is, however, less significantiow that world sugar prices have risen to around the level of the Community price, so;hat currently there is no significant disposal cost falling on Community funds.
Wrhe proposals provide for a 10 per cent saving to be made on the costs ofSessed fruit and vegetables.  On wine some changes have been agreed that shouldfk.p to contain the costs falling on Community funds.f(Bon whisky, the Council has accepted a commitment to adopt the necessaryregulation by the end of this year for the payment to the UK of the returns onCommunity cereals used in exported scotch whisky.   This commitment covers retrospectivepHent of some  40 million net due to the beginning of 1980.  At current cerealpies, the annual payments due would be some  16 million per annum.2. The main implications for UK interests are as follows:-(a) UK Producers The proposals would increase UK producers&apos; returns by about 1($r (after allowing for feed price increases) in a full year.  Most of the benefitwoiic: go to the cereals and beef sectors, with UK milk producers probably sufferingHall net reduction in returns because of the co-responsibility levy.  The overallease would not prevent a further fall in the industry&apos;s real net income.1(bl UK Consumers The proposals would produce an increase of about 0.7 per cent inthaFood Price Index, and about 0.2 per cent in the R.P.I., when all effects had workedthrough. The UK butter subsidy offsets much of the effect of the price increases,being worth some  108 million to consumers.(c)| Community Expenditure The proposals are estimated to increase Communityexp nditure by some 240 million EUAs in 1980 and by about 1000 million EUA| in   full year.  These figures make no allowance for production and consumptionresponses to higher prices in future years.  About one-fifth of the additionalexp nditure would be in the UK.1
MEIHEEPMEie proposalsie main features of the sheepmeat proposals are as follows:-a)   sriable premium  In the UK there will be no intervention buying. Instead;hen /ill be a variable premium (ie deficiency payment), paid to UK producersfrom Miunity funds and making good the difference between the average UK marketirice and a &quot;guide level&quot;, set at the level of the intervention price operated inrthei nember countries and on the same seasonal pattern.  This premium will berecov red on lamb exported.  As a result, the return to the producer or trader fromsale on the British market will be higher than the return from selling to France[ato sven somewhat above the French intervention price.  There should accordinglyfbe rifisales of British lamb&apos; into French intervention.1(b) ^Intervention in other countries  In other countries, intervention will befavaJBble from August to December at 85% of the basic price, ie well below the,recent level of French market prices.  Sales into intervention should be relativelylight] because when the French market is weak there should be little or no importationfrom pie UK to depress it further.I(c) Reference prices  In all countries reference prices will be set which will actas aluarantee of average producer returns.  Where the average market price is lowerI than Ihe reference price an annual compensatory premium will be paid to make good thediffJence between the two (or between the intervention and reference prices if thisis  Her). These reference prices are to be aligned in four equal annual steps.Afterlfour years UK producers will thus benefit from the same guarantee as those inall other member countries.  The UK producer&apos;s return will be sustained by the UKvarialle premium (bringing his return up to the level of the French interventionprice) and a further compensatory premium to bring it up to the common reference price.(d) lew Zealand   The whole regime will come into effect only if and when New Zealandagrees on the volume of her imports into the Community in exchange for a reduction inthe listing tariff of 20 per cent ad valorem.  This gives New Zealand theoppoBunity to ensure that the total arrangements are acceptable to her and do notdama  her trading interests. :&apos;:  &apos;&quot; -
liM Export refunds Provision is made for export refunds, but these are subject toNpftealand being satisfied on the regime in general, and to a Council Declarationthat   funds must be operated in conformity with international obligations and so asnotjto prejudice agreements with third country suppliers.  This leaves New Zealandfree    negotiate, as part of her voluntary agreement with the Community, in relationto jo.&apos; refunds should operate, as well as having the power to block the scheme as awhole. (Mr Gundelachr has told Mr Talboys that these arrangements give New Zealandavjto over export refunds distinct from its veto over the regime as a whole.)(ii) Implications for the UKI    The main implications of these proposals for the UK are:-(al The guaranteed return tc UK producers would be increased by 17 per cent in1980/&apos;1, and almost certainly rise substantially thereafter as reference priceswere harmonised.  Total paymenjts from Community funds to British producers couldrisf towards  100 million per annum at the end of the four-year transition. Frenchiljgal barriers to imports frjom the UK would be removed.(b) UK consumers would benefiit because the use of deficiency payments, and theirreavery on exports, would tend to keep British lamb in Britain when Continentalprjes were low, thus keeping UK market prices down; while the higher guaranteed pricewomd ensure a production increase and ample supply. The arrangements to be negotiatedby lew Zealand would ensure a continued supply of New Zealand lamb.(c) The UK economy would benefit from the financing from Community instead ofnational funds of an increasing producer guarantee on our production, which approachesonejhalf of total Community production.(d) | The provisions for New Zealand give her an effective veto over the introductionofjhe scheme and an opportunity to negotiate not only on the volume of her importsand&apos;a tariff reduction but also on the operation of export refunds and on othermatters of interest to her.
FISHERIESl( Ihe proposed text on fisheries is in Annex II.   Its main points are as follows:-(a) Paragraph 1 records a Council undertaking to adopt, in parallel with theapplication of the decisions to be taken in other areas, a common fisheriespolity covering all outstanding issues in time for them to take effect by 1 January1981lat latest. Others may later seek to argue that this establishes someinterdependence between the adoption of a common fisheries policy and the applicationIf the budgetary settlement.  But in fact it simply sets the timetable for thenegotiation of the CFP.  The proposed timetable is unexceptionable:  we wouldourselves like to have a satisfactory CFP agreed by the end of the year.lb) Paragraph 2 sets out guidelines for the policy.  Point A satisfactorily meetsbur requirements for a conservation regime based on scientific principles.   Point Brefers to a division of catches that takes specific account of some of the factorslotfiich we attach importance and leaves room for us to argue for the validityof others. Point C refers satisfactorily to controls, and Point D to structuralmeasures. Point E deals with agreements with third countries in a satisfactoryway J particularly in stipulating that offers of trade concessions should be subjectto the maintenance of stability on the Community market.Re) Paragraph 3 deals with access in satisfactory terms.   It does not mentionrenal access&quot;, and it refers to all existing texts which are helpful to us inIrguing our case.  German attempts to preclude the possibility of preferentialaccess outside 12 miles have been successfully resisted and they are left to put theirpiews in a unilateral declaration.  It would have been preferable for this paragraphpo have formed part of paragraph 2, but the inclusion of the word &quot;furthermore&quot;lean be regarded as giving it equal weight with the considerations listed there.(d) Paragraph 4 remits the outstanding fisheries issues to a Fisheries Counciliscliduled for 16 June, in terms which allow us to insist that access should beIn the agenda, so that the Council can deal with all outstanding issues together.In brief, this text, while not making positive headway in directions we wouldto move, does not appear to prejudice further negotiations in the Fisheriescil.
Possible OutcomesPossible OutcomesPossible Outcome1. Unadjusted net contribution2. Adjusted for agriculture package3. Refund now proposed4. Net contributionA178417841175609B C1900 20001880 20001247 1287633713A	B	C	2240	2320	2400	25002140	2200	2400	25001410	1440	1565	1646730	780	835	% &apos; 8545. Refund proposed at Luxembourg6. Net Contribution12465381342 1462538 538124689413428581462938nil[2500]7.    1Improvement1 over Luxembourg-71 -95 -175+164        +98 +103
ANNEXIL DECLARATION ON THE COMMON FISHERIES POLICYjlKhe Council agrees that the completion of the Common Fisheries Policy is aconcc itant part in the solution of the problems with which the Community isconfronted at present.  To this end the Council undertakes to adopt, in parallelwith     application of the decisions which will be taken in other areas, thedecisions necessary to ensure that a common overall Fisheries Policy is put intoeffec at the latest on 1 January 1981.I2.-an compliance with the treaties and in conformity with the Council resolution of3Nov ber 1976 (the &quot;Hague Agreement&quot;), this policy should be based on the followingguide] ines:(a) rational and non-discriminatory community measures for the management ofresources and conservation and reconstitution of stocks so as to ensure theirexploitation on a lasting basis in appropriate social and economic conditions:(b) fair distribution of catches having regard, most particularly, totraditional fishing activities, to the special needs of regions where thelocal populations are particularly dependant upon fishing and the industriesillied thereto (i) and to the loss of catch potential in third country waters:(c) effective controls on the conditions applying to fisheries:(d) adoption of structural measures which include a financial contributionby the Community:(e) establishment of securely-based fisheries relations with third countriesand implementation of agreements already negotiated.   In addition, endeavoursshould be made to conclude further agreements on fishing possibilities, inwhich the Community - subject to the maintenance of stability on the Communityrnarket - could also offer tradeconcessions.3. furthermore, Article 103 of the Act of Accession shall be applied in conformitywitlfthe objectives and provisions of the Treaty establishing the European EconomicCommunity, with the Act of Accession, inter alia Articles 100-102 and with theCouncil resolution of 3 November 1976, in particular Annex VII.1.
4  lie Council agrees to take up again the examination of the proposed regulationsirJil(a) (technical measures of conservation) and (c) (control) at its session onib juie 1980, and also on this occasion to begin examination of other proposals,inclping a proposal on quotas for 1980 which the Commission undertakes to presentin good time.iCF* Paras 3 and 4 of Annex VII of the Council resolution of 3 November 1976.
S S 600 CONFIDENTIALCONFIDENTIAL I  .FRAME GENERAL ;    &apos; &quot;FM UK REP BRUSSELS 300958Z MAY 80ID FLASH FCO ,TELE6RAM NUMBER 2654 OF 30 MAYINFO PRIORITY BRUSSELS, COPENHAGEN, THE HAGUE, ROME, DUBLIN,PARls, BONN, LUXEMBOURG,FOREIGN AFFAIRS COUNCIL, 29-30 MAY.CONVERGENCE/BUDGETARY QUESTIONS. f   : % .MIPTi FOLLOWING IS TEXT OF CONCLUSIONS.   . ;&apos;^L, *   &apos; &apos;t. THE NET UNITED KINGDOM CONTRIBUTION FOR 1980 WILL BE .&quot;&apos;CALCULATED ON THE BASIS OF THE PRESENT COMMISSION ESTIMATE(1,784 MEUA). 1,175 MEUA WILL BE DEDUCTED FROM THIS FIGURE.      - t {THIS LEAVES A UNITED KINGDOM CONTRIBUTION OF 609 MEUA FOR   ^   ( . &quot;1980. O2. THE NET UNITED KINGDOM CONTRIBUTION FOR 1981 WILL BECALCULATED ON THE BASIS OF THE COMMISSION ESTIMATE OF .2,140 MEUA. THE UNITED KINGDOM&apos;S 1980 NET CONTRIBUTION WILLBE INCREASED BY A PERCENTAGE EQUAL TO THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN1,784 AND 2,140 MEUA, NAMELY 19.9 PER CENT OR 121 MEUA. THE NETUNITED KINGDOM CONTRIBUTION FOR 1981 THEREFORE BECOMES 733 MEUA.% THE UNITED KINGDOM CONTRIBUTION, BAS^D ON THE ABOVECALCULATIONS, IS REDUCED FOR 1980 AND 1981 BY 2,585 MEUA(1,175 PLUS 1,410).4. IF THE UNITED KINGDOM&apos;S ACTUAL CONTRIBUTIONS FOR 1980AND 1981 ARE HIGHER THAN 1,784 AND 2,140 MEUA RESPECTIVELYTHE DIFFERENCE WILL BE SPLIT - FOR THE FIRST YEAR 25 PER CENT WILLBE BORNE BY THE UNITED KINGDOM AND 75 PER CENT BY THE OTHER 8MEMBER STATES. FOR THE SECOND YEAR - INCREASE FROM 730 TO 750TO BE BORNE IN FULL BY THE UNITED KINGDOM* FROM 750 TO 850,50 PER CENT TO BE BORNE BY THE UNITED KINGDOM AND 50 PER CENT BYTHE OTHER 8 MEMBER STATE31 ABOVE 850, 25 PER CENT TO BE BORNE BYTHE UNITED KINGDOM AND 75 PER CENT BY THE OTHERS.5. PAYMENTS OVER THE PERIOD 1980-82 SHOULD BE MADE BY MEANSOF THE ADAPTED FINANCIAL MECHANISM AND THE SUPPLEMENTARYMEASURES PROPOSED BY THE COMMISSION. THE FINANCIALMECHANISM WILL CONTINUE TO FUNCTION AUTOMATICALLY UNTIL THEEND OF 1982.6. THE CREDITS ARE INSCRIBED IN THE BUDGET OF THE FOLLOWINGYEAR, FOLLOWING THE PRECEDENT OF THE FINANCIAL MECHANISM.AT THE REQUEST OF THE UNITED KINGDOM THE COUNCIL CAN DECIDEEACH YEAR ON A PROPOSAL BY THE COMMISSION TO MAKE ADVANCESTO PERMIT THE ACCELERATED IMPLEMENTATION OF THESUPPLEMENTARY MEASURES.CONFIDENTIAL
COOTICENTIAL7. FOR 1982, THE COMMUNITY IS PLEDGED TO RESOLVE THEPROBLEM BY MEANS OF STRUCTURAL CHANGES (COMMISSION MANDATETO BE FULFILLED BY THE END OF JUNE 1981. THE EXAMINATION p|SHOULD CONCERN THE DEVELOPMENT OF COMMUNITY POLICIES,WITHOUT CALLING INTO QUESTION THE COMMON FINANCIALRESPONSIBILITY FOR THESE POLICIES, WHICH ARE FINANCED FROMTHE COMMUNITY&apos;S OWN RESOURCES, NOR THE BASIC PRINCIPLESOF THE COMMON AGRICULTURAL POLICY, TAKING ACCOUNT OF THESITUATIONS AND INTERESTS OF ALL MEMBER STATES* THISEXAMINATION WILL AIM TO PREVENT THE RECURRENCE OF V^-Iff ACCEPTABLE SITUATIONS FOR ANY OF THEM),    IF THIS IS NOTACHIEVED, THE COMMISSION WILL MAKE PROPOSALS ALONG THE LINESOF THE 1980-81 SOLUTION AND THE COUNCIL WILL ACT ACCORDINGLY,8. THE COUNCIL REAFFIRMS THE CONCLUSIONS ADOPTED BY IT (IN &apos;ITS COMPOSITION OF MINISTERS OF ECONOMIC AFFAIRS ANDFINANCE) ON 11 FEBRUARY 1980 ((CF ANNEX TO DOC. 5081/80PV/CONS 5 ECO/FIN 9)),. WHICH INCLUDED REFERENCE TO THE 1 PERCENT VAT OWN RESOURCES CEILING.9. IT JS IMPORTANT FOR THE FUTURE WELL BEING OF THECOMMUNITY THAT DAY TO DAY DECISIONS AND POLICY MAKING SHOULDFUNCTION EFFECTIVELY AND THIS PARTICULARLY DURING THE PERIODWHEN THE REVIEW FORESEEN IN PARAGRAPH-7 IS UNDER WAY. WITHTHIS OBJECTIVE IN MIND ALL MEMBER STATES UNDERTAKE TO DOTHEIR BEST TO ENSURE THAT COMMUNITY DECISIONS ARE TAKENEXPEDITIOUSLY AND IN PARTICULAR THAT DECISIONS ON AGRICULTURALPRICE FIXING ARE TAKEN IN TIME FOR THE NEXT MARKETING .SEASON. %0:FCO PASS ADVANCE COPIES TOt- ...&apos;. &apos; *M IfFCO       PS/80F8, PS/LPS, PS/PUS, BRIDGES, HANNAY, SPRECKLEYCAB       SIR R ARMSTRONG, FRANKLIN, ELLIOTT, WALSHKAFF       ANDREWS, HADLEYTSY        PS/CHANCELLOR, SIR K COUZENS, HANCOCK, MICHELL* ASHFORDTHOMSON, MISS WRIGHT (+7 COPIES)NO 10 ALEXANDERBUTLER. ^ADVANCED AS REQUESTED]FRAME GENERAL  ECD(l)CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
