<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/33/37 images: 318-321</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THB PROPERTY; OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERMfflM&apos;)secret copy NO.January 22nd, 1 9L.3v/AR   CABINETRED ARIVIY DAYMemorandum by the Minister of information am reporting to the War Cabinet the arrangements that the Ministry ofInformation is maiding for the celebration in this country of Red Army Day,   Theactual day which commemorates the formation of the Red Army is 23rd February,and it is observed in the UBS.S.R, as an important national event.   Next23^d February is the 25th anniversaryFor convenience we are holding the formal celebrations in this country on Sunday, 21st February,The V/ar Cabinet will recall that last October they discussed the advantageof organising some official demonstrations in November to commemorate Russia&apos;ssuccessful resistance to the Germans.   Attention was drawn to the importanceof such demonstrations being, if possible, officially inspired, as so many difficulties arise from large-scale ceremonies of unexceptionable purpose butambiguous pcrentagee   The Foreign Secretary and myself were instructed to consult on the subject, but in the result no satisfactory occasion presei   i 1itself, and I recommended that we should reserve our energies for a major officialcelebration on this coming Red Array Day,In London wc arc organising a big celebration at the Albert Hall, at whichthe Foreign Secretary has promised to deliver an address.   Our general purpose is to present the idea of the admiration and gratitude that are felt by thepeople of this country for the fight that the U.S,S,RB has made against the axis powers.    Invitations have been extended to representatives of the AlliedGovernments, all members of H.M.G., the oivic representatives of the London boroughs, etc., and the Services, Civil Defence workers and representatives ofother war-time activities have been invited to take part in a demonstrationparade at the close of the ceremony.   Invitations are also being extendedindifferently to all organisations concerned with Anglo-Soviet affairs and it ishoped that by this means the effective celebrations of the day will be loft to official organisation.The Ministry of Information has also secured that local ceremonies will takeplace in a number of the principal provincial cities at which I am grateful tomany of my colleagues for having consented to speak.These ceremonies aro taking place under the joint auspices of the localcivil authorities and the Ministry and follow the same lines as the centralcelebrations in London.B*B*22nd January. 19^-3se W.M.(4S) 131st Conclusions, Minute 12.




</content>
</cab>
