<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/180/0 images: 92-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(5HI3 PXUM3HT IS THS PB0PJ2RTY 02&quot; HIS BBXU0JIIO MAJBJSTY*S GOVEatfMBNa&apos;)Copy Ho.   ,5 OSLATHB COAL SITUATION.Setter oonveying Government answer to reply of the l^lala^ jSegooiatlpn Tf^&amp;reaiJ^Ttaln to^pro^paalg of ^E^Hovernman^.(See also CP. 202 (26) and CP. SX1 (26).)10 Downing Street, S.W.1, 22nd May, 1926.Bear Sir,I am desired by the Prime Minister to acknowledge tbe reoeipt of your letter of the 21st May conveying the answer of the Mining Association to the proposals that he recently laid before them.     He greatly regrets that your Association have thought it neoessary to adopt the uncompromising attitude oonveyed in the enclosure to your letter.He is aware that the immediate oause of the present deadlock is the refusal of the Miners&apos; Federation to consider any concession that would give suoh a reduotlon in ooets of prod-action as the Royal Commission pointed out was indispensable, and he recognises that so long as this attitude is maintained, further negotiations must be futile.     He reoognises, too, that, while the attitude of the Miners1 Federation remains exactly what it was last July, the Colliery Owners have made someadvances from their original position in order to try to reach a settlement.But he profoundly disagrees with your Association in attributing the troubles of the industry to &quot;political interference&quot;.     The Government have, in many instances, made it clear that they do not desire to interfere in trade disputes
in which there 1b an Indication that the parties are able and willing to settle those disputes for themselves. But he would point out that what is oalled &quot;political Interference&quot; in the Mining Industry has been entirely due to the incapacity, now again so conspicuously shown, of that industry, unlihe ^ther industries, to settle its disputes for itself.   He deplores your Association&apos;a apparent inability to recognise that it was quite impossible for any Government to have stood aside in matters where the national well-being is so vitally and disastrously affected.Tho essential feature of the proposal laid before you by the Government was that both sides should agree to leave the crucial point of the dispute - the figure of minimum percentage on basis in the various districts -to be determined in the last resort by arbitration.    This is a prinoiple that has over end over again been accepted by other great industries.    It is true that the attitude of the other side has made it at present impossible of application in the present dispute, whatever were the attitude of your Association.   But the Prime Minister cannot refrain from the comment that, in summarily rejecting- the proposal as one that &quot;seeks to Import an element of ooeroion into the machinery of negotiation&quot;, your Association appears to show an inadequate appreciation \oth of the nature of the proposal and of the gravity of the present situation.I ani. Sir,Yours faithfully, (Signed) RONALD WATEBHOUSB.$he Secretary,Mining Association of Great Britain, General Buildings, Aldwyoh, W.C.2.

</content>
</cab>
