<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/180/0 images: 200-202</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. !Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1926.SECRET.CP. 234 (26).Previous Paper CP. 93 (26).CIRCULATED BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE  KOI;   iKnlA.Despatch from II.\l.\s Minister, Kabul, to H.M.\? Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London, No. 35, dated 7th May 1926.I have the honour to address yon further regarding the dispute between Afghanistan and the^Soviet Government over the island of Urta Tagai. In my last despatch (No. 9 of 1926) I laid stress on the Afghan Governments conviction of the justice of their case and of the mockery they would have to face if they surrendered to the Russian claims. A deadlock had been reached. Both sides had agreed to a commission to decide the ownership of the island, but the Afghans insisted on and the Russians as stubbornly opposed -there-occupation of the island by Afghan troops before the commission was appointed. Military preparations on a considerable scale were made, but the tension was suddenly relaxed on the 3rd February, when M. Stark gave way on the vital point. In my telegram No. 16, I acquainted you with the terms of the agreement reached. The island was to be immediately evacuated by the Russians and occupied by a platoon of Afghan soldiers as before; a commission was to report within six months on the responsibility for the incident of December last and on the rights of ownership in the island. Some time elapsed before effect was given to this agreement, and it was not until the 28th February that Soviet troops evacuated and Afghan troops occupied the island. The Afghan members of the commission left Kabul on the 16th March, and were expected to meet the Russian commissioners early in April.2. The immediate clanger of conflict has thus been averted, but it would he unwise to assume that the incident is closed. The commission is composed of three members from each side without an umpire, and it is hardly likely that they will come to any definite conclusion. A unanimous finding on the questiou of responsibility for the incident of December last will perhaps be arranged. - But neither side, in my opinion, will meekly surrender its claim to the ownership of the disputed territory. Possession, to the Afghan mind, is fully 99 per cent, of the law, while the Russians are believed fry many to have no intention of abandoning the island for good. Legal questions of considerable complexity will probably be raised, and having had no-access to any of the papers on which, the Afghans rely, I find it difficult to give any useful opinion on the legal aspect of the case. I may, however, supplement the observations I made on this subject in my despatch No. 9 by answering, as far as I am able, the questions raised by the Government of India in their telegram No. 209 S, dated the 2nd February 1926.I understand on good authority that the island, which measures not less than 160 square miles, is inhabited all the ;year round by about twelve hundred persons,, the large majority being Lakkai Uzbegs, who have only lived there since 1921, and are bitterly hostile to the Soviet. The remainder are Tajiks, who are indigenous and number perhaps 150. The island annually produces a crop of cotton and rice, but is used mainly for grazing cattle. It possesses well-grown timber, chiefly willow, which is exported in considerable quantities. Land revenue is recovered mainly in the form of grazing dues. . The villagers themselves live in permanent mud buildings, but the Afghan troops appear to occupy temporary quarters made of wood. The ground, though marshy in parts, is said to be solid enough to allow of a metalled road being-made across it, but it is doubted by the Afghan War Minister, whose old home is in this neighbourhood, whether the island would be the most suitable site for a bridge-across the Oxus.3. It is possible that, if the Afghans make out a strong legal case, the Russian-commissioners will admit their claim. I think, however, that this is very doubtful. Unless the Russians receive some quid pro quo before the commission publishes its report, I find it difficult to believe that they will give in. The quid pro quo demanded would probably be some concession in Afghanistan for trade, or for the construction of roads, telegraphs, or railways, the object in either case being- the employmeut of more Russian personnel in the country. But it is always possible that public opinion, in Afghanistan would forbid any such concession, in which event I anticipate that the 1236      100   6.26
finding will be a solid vote of three against three.   The Afghans being in possession it will be for the Russians to take the next step.   They may perhaps let the matter rest, unwilling to waste the results of several years&apos; diplomatic labours, but it will be prudent to contemplate the possibility of their continuing to press their claim, and of their doing so, in the last resort, by force.4. I have little doubt that war would be the Afghan reply to forcible tactics. Conceit has blinded them to the inequality of the Russian and Afghan military forces and the conviction has recently grown upon me that the Amir and the majority of his people consider they are equal in the field to anything which the Soviet can produce. At the present moment, with the snow-bound passes of the Hindu Kush in full view, they undoubtedly have misgivings; but a few mouths hence climate will be on their side and I believe they will be sanguine of victory.The overweening confidence in their military power is no new growth. Duriiio-the visit of the Dane Mission to Kabul in 1904 Amir Habibullah wrote a memorandum in which he spoke seriously of attacking Russia while&quot; she was occupied with a war against Japan. The Amir asked for no assistance from British troops, but only for British money and munitions of war. Japan, he said, with 400,000 troops had brought Russia to her knees. What could not Afghanistan do with a martial population of 8,000,000 (now asserted by Afghans to have increased to 15,000,000) and with the help of crores of her co-religionists on whom Russia had trampled ? Religions war and rebellion, were the weapons in which the Amir chiefly trusted. His strategy is interesting : &quot;At the first stage, her railways and telegraphs would be stealthily cut. At the second stage, the road would he blocked and grain withheld from her. Thirdly, the mountain passes would be made as barriers against her. Fourthly, such a fire would be set ablaze in her territories that it would be impossible to extinguish it.&quot;Habibullah believed that, helped by British money and munitions, his military power was stronger than Japan&apos;s. &quot; From their innate bravery,&quot; he wrote, &quot; I consider one of my men equal to two foreigners in any place.&quot;I believe that a feeling very akin to this exists to-day as it certainly existed in 1919 born of ignorance but genuine. The observations of my European colleagues, and my own conversations with Afghans of widely differing status, support my opinion.The fall that awaits this pride can hardly be a matter of doubt. If the view expressed by Mr. Dane to the Amir was true in 1904, &quot; that British military authorities were unanimously of opinion that the Afghan army alone, however much increased, would be unable, at all events in the first instance, to resist a Russian advance,&quot; it would be doubly true to-day. Twenty years have seen little improvement in the efficiency and equipment of the Afghan troops ; they have learnt none of the lessons taught by the Great War. Except in a defensive, guerilla campaign, I think there is little doubt that they would fail miserably.5. There is insufficient evidence at present to enable me to form a definite opinion as to the real motive of Russia in undertaking this enterprise. The easiest explanation is that Moscow, Tashkent, and Monsieur Stark blundered throughout ; but since it is dangerous to impute imbecility to one&apos;s opponent, I do not think that it would be wise to accept this conclusion as explaining everything. The immediate cause of the conflict was apparently the attempt of some 300 Tajiks to return to their native country from Badakhshan, where they had taken refuge from Bolshevik persecution in 1920. The Afghan guards at Urta Tagai tried to prevent the refugees from crossing the Oxus and were thereupon attacked and ousted hy Russian troops. This is an indication of the great importance which the Soviet Government attaches to the repatriation of these refugees, whose numbers, in Afghanistan, though gradually diminishing, are still probably not less than 60,000. They realise that the presence in Afghanistan of a colony of exiles, still nursing resentment against the Bolshevism which forced them to leave their country, will be a serious obstacle to the expansion southwards of any of the newly formed Nationalist Soviet republics in Central Asia. They have been negotiating for some time with the Afghan Government for tho repatriation of these refugees, who have been promised an amnesty and financial assistance if they return. The refugees themselves, if assured of safety in their own country, would probably escape gladly enough from the exactions of Afghan officials in a province which is even more ruthlessly administered than old Bokhara. B&apos;it the Afghan Government realise, that they have in the refugees a valuable weapon
--against the Soviet in time of trouble, and they are as loth to let them go as they, would be to sever connection with the malcontent Wazirs and Mahsuds who occasionally find a haven of refuge in southern Afghanistan.It appears probable, therefore, that the Russian and Afghan Governments had reached an impasse over this question of repatriation and, in my opinion, the Russian seizure of the island was intended to force an issue. They felt that they would at least be in a jDOsition to bargain satisfactorily with the Afghans, and at the best they might retain the island permanently and, by bridging the Oxus, facilitate the Bolshevising of the Uzbegs and Tajiks of northern Afghanistan. The explanation put forward by the Russians, that the occupation of the island was merely a measure -of self-protection against the raiding gangs of Baser. ?chis, seems to me insufficient to explain the facts. The Izvestiya of 5th March 1926, in an article on the settlement of the crisis, said that the island, at the time of the incident, &quot;was now due to enter the newly-formed State of Tajikistan.&quot;There can be little doubt that the extension of its political frontiers in Central Asia is the settled policy of the Soviet Government. A Russian attack on India, with .a united Afghanistan as an ally, seems to me in any conditions that can be foreseen to be chimerical. But the gradual enticement of the Clzbegs, Tajiks, and Turkomans into the Soviet fold, until all Afghanistan north of the Hindu Ivush is a Russian province, appears to be a practicable policy. If it is ever brought into effect, the menace to India will be within measurable distance. Shorn of her northern provinces, Afghanistan as an Amirate would hardly continue to exist, and the problem of dealing with a dismembered and distracted neighbour along more than a thousand miles of frontier would present to the Government of India difficulties and embarrassments the gravity of which it is almost impossible to over-estimate.6. If the possibility of another crisis arising as suddenly as it did last December cannot be discounted, I would urge the necessity of considering beforehand what His Majesty&apos;s Governments attitude will be in the event of the Afghan Government appealing for British diplomatic support. The restitution on the island of the status quo ante the incident of December 1925, pending the decision of the mixed commission, has fortunately simplified the issue, for in the event of a deadlock resulting the Russians may well hesitate to employ force a second time to achieve their object. It is true that His Majesty&apos;s Government have no longer any legal or moral obligation in the matter of Afghanistan&apos;s northern boundary. At the same time it seems that the change in our position is a tactical rather than a real one. It can hardly be held that our interest in the inviolability of Afghanistan has ever been prompted by anything but considerations of InchVs safety. Those considerations hold good just as much to-day as they did 50 years ago. His Majesty&apos;s Government, vide Mr. Ramsay MacdonalcVs telegram No. 30, dated the 8th July 1924, agreed that the Afghan Government should be informed that the old British guarantee of the integrity of Afghanistan&apos;s northern frontier no longer held good, and that in the event of Russian aggression the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government would be guided entirely by their own interests, and that the nature of those interests would depend largely on the extent to which die conduct of Afghan policy had in the meantime contributed to the tranquillity of India and its immunity from foreign intrigues. Both the conditions implicit in the above declaration of policy appear to me to be relevant to the case under discussion.It is clearly in the interests of His Majesty&apos;s Government to prevent the absorption of any part of Afghanistan into the Soviet system, and the Ainir&apos;s behaviour on the Indian frontier during the last two years has fulfilled our most sanguine expectations.7. If the commissioners fail to reach agreement and the Amir, apprehensive of a Russian attack on the island, were to apply to me for assistance, I feel that to turn a cold shoulder to his appeal would make him despair and would drive him to the conclusion that, British sympathy being unobtainable in any circumstances, his only hope lay in throwing in his lot with the Power whose policy was causing him the greater anxiety. I recommend, therefore, that, should such an occasion arise, I should be instructed to offer him the diplomatic support of His Majesty&apos;s Government, making it clear that their support would be strictly confined to endeavours to promote a peaceful solution of a dispute which Afghan interests imperatively demand should be settled without bloodshed. Such a solution could probably be best obtained by both parties agreeing to accept the decision of a disinterested arbitrator.8. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Secretary of State for India and the Government of India.

</content>
</cab>
