<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/180/0 images: 337-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1926.SECRET.Copy No.CP. 249 (26).CABINET.SPECIAL EE PORT  ON   UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 129.   May 1926.THIS Report indicates, so far as this is possible, the effect of the dispute in the Coal-mining Industry upon the remaining industries throughout the country. Statement (A) below shows the course of unemployment during May, whilst Table (B) analyses the figures of persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at the 31st May.(A.) Number of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges inGreat Britain.	1924.	1925.	1926.						 	May 26.	May 25.	Apr. 26.	May 3.	May 10.	May 17.	May 24.	May 31.	Increase since Apr. 26.Men . . Boys . . Women Girls ..	754,553 33,669 194,893 32,511	925,506 32,947 199,797 28,272	764,192 28,953 156,783 31,949	846,670 32.513 190,612 36,121	1,123,653 49,776 344,076 58,391	1,178,406 48,991 331,507 53,840	1,174,108 46,954 326,449 50,168	1,207,041 45,986 313,374 47,811	442,849 17,033 156,591 15,882Total..	1,015,626	1,186,522	981,877	1,105,916	1,575,899	1,612,744	1,597,679	1,614,212	632,335V 1 1 above figures represent the number of persons registered at Local Offices as applicants for employment. In the main they relate to persons who had claims to benefit current and were not at work on the dates given. - .,,&apos;&apos;/-,,-. m t ,a..^..^,(2.) The figures above for the fire weeks in May are exclusive of persons in the Goal-mming industry who ceased work on account of the dispute which commenced on the 1st May.(3.) The latest figures available, viz., for the weeks ended the 7th and 14th June, 1926, are given in Part (D) of this Report.The percentage of unemployment (Great Britain) in the insured industries at the end of May 1924        .... .... .... 9&quot;2,,   1925     .............        lo/e,,     1926       ............ -  14 2The figures given in Table (A) above cover the five weeks ended 31st May,1926.   It will be seen that during this period there has been a total increase of632,335 in the number of persons registered as unemployed.   The increase was most rapid during the week ended the 10th May, 1926, which was the first weekaffected by the general strike and totalled 470,000.   Apart from a slight dropduring the week  ended the 24th May, the figures have gradually increased.Unemployment showed the largest  numerical  increase among men, but wasproportionately greater among women, where the increase was 100 per cent, overthe five-week period.    It should be mentioned that the total figures at the26th April were the lowest reached in the number of persons registered asunemployed since 1920, and there is no doubt that had it not been for the general strike and the coal-mining dispute the figure would have tended to become lower still.
(B.) Analysis of the Number of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at the 31st May, 1926.	Wholly Unemployed.	Temporary Stoppages.	Casuals.	Total.Men Boys.. Women Girls.. h Total..	716,373 27,450 105,725 27,838	415,270 18,358 206,745 19,941	75,398 178 904 32	1,207,041 45,986 313,874 47,811	877,386	660,314	76,512	1.614,212A comparison of the above table with the figures for the 26th April, that is, the last week before the coal dispute on the 1st May and the general strike on the 3rd May, shows that the major portion of the increase in unemployment was clue to temporary stoppages in industry. The number of wholly unemployed increased during this period by about one-fifth, whereas the number of persons involved in temporary stoppages was almost quadrupled; there was very little change in the number of casuals unemployed.(C.) Unemployment in Insured Industries.The latest date for which unemployment figures by industries are available is the 24th May, 1926, at which date the percentage unemployed in Great Britain and Northern Ireland was 14&quot;5, as compared with 9&apos;2 at the 26th April, 1926, with 10&apos;9 at the 25th May, 1925, and with 9&apos;4 at the 26th May, 1924. The dispute in the Coal-mining Industry and the general stoppage of industry consequent on this dispute during the period 4th May to 12th May inclusive had a far-reaching effect on trade in general, and the table below shows those industries in which the increase in unemployment was greatest during the month of May: Industry.N umber of Insured Persons recorded as Unemployed at May 24, 1926.Increase compared with April 26, 1926.All Insured Industries.Cotton   &apos;&apos;   .. Steel Melting, Iron Puddling, Iron andSteel Rolling, &amp;c. General   Engineering,   Engineers&apos;   Ironand Steel Founding Woollen and Worsted Pottery, &amp;c. BuildingBoot and Shoe, &amp;c, Trades Manufacture of Tin-plates Distributive Trades Textile Bleaching, &amp;c. HosieryManufacture of Pig-iron Brick and Tile, &amp;c, Making Construction and Repair of Motor VehiclesCycles and Aircraft.. Shipbuilding and Ship-repairing Coal-mining Tailoring Railway ServicePublic Works contracting, &amp;c. .. Iron  Ore and  Iron Stone Mining a&apos;nd Quarrying . . .1,719,362*152,910116,219107,839 54,119 34,313 73,075 28,292 21,208 99,601 28,607 18,245 15,059 16,30721,478 92,695 106,609* 14,701 16,739 31,0209,873625,54096,20275,4 9737,626 29,107 24,650 17,948 17,879 16,692 15,163 14,384 12,171 11,633 11,6039,064 8,799 8,729 7,476 7,36b 7,3407,273* Exclusive of persons in the Coal-mining Industry who ceased work due to the dispute which began on the 1st May.
It will be seen from the above table that the Cotton Trade and the Iron and Steel Industry were the two most hardly hit industries during the period (though the increased unemployment in the Cotton Industry cannot be ascribed wholly or mainly to the lack of fuel), whilst General Engineering, Woollen and Pottery Trades suffered to a lesser extent. The effective result of the dispute in the Coal-mining Industry has been to retard the improvement in the chief industries during previous months, whilst the lack of fuel and transport difficulties has caused a large number of Iron and Steel Works to close down, and much short-time working has been introduced in other industries. It should be mentioned that the prospects in the Cotton Industry, which shows the largest increase during the period, considered quite apart from the general stoppage, are very doubtful and the systematic short-time working in this industry is a definite plan to curtail production.(D.) Latest Figures.The latest figures of unemployment published are those for the 7th June, giving the total number on the registers as 1,609,119. This is a decrease over the position at the 31st May amounting to 5,093, but shows an increase over a year ago of 317,928. The preliminary figure for the 14th June is 1,629,900, showing an increase in one week of 20,781.A. STEEL-MAITLAND.Ministry of Labour, -June 22, 1926.

</content>
</cab>
