<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/180/0 images: 444-559</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This document is the property of H*s Britannic Hajesty&apos;s Government,,)0 A B I 2T E T.j5t.272 (26) . FAOTPRIES   BILL.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.I circulate to my colleagues a revised draft of the Factories Bill,     As they are aware,  it has been announced that the Government intend to pass this Bill into law next Session, and a promise has been given that it would be introduced this Session in time to allow of its examination by the parties interested, and to give an opportunity for consultation in regard to it, in the Autumn.     Recently in reply to a Question in the House I stated that I hoped to introduce the Bill this month.The Bill has been   thoroughly examined by the Home Affairs Committee and, in its bearing on the work and interests of the Government Departments, by an Inter-Departmental Committee, and the only question which remains unsettled is as to the provisions to be inserted in the Bill for the regulation! of the hours of employment of women and young persons.     When this question was under discussion last year, .it was complicated by considerations in regard to its bearing on the general question of the 8-hour day and 48-hour week.    That question, however, has been set aside for the time being,  and the question of the regulation of the hours of women and young persons in factories has therefore to be dealt with as one of factory administration, that is,  it has to be regarded from the point of view of the protection of women and young persons employed in industry,    The position is as follows.    The statutory hours allowed by the existing Acts are 10 daily and weeklyfor textile factories, and IOf daily and 60 weekly, with overtime in addition in certain industries, for non-textile factories.    These hours were regarded in many quarters before the war as too long, and a movement towards the shortening of
the hours had already begun.    This movement received a considerable accession of strength from the experience of the war.   At the present time in the great majority of cases women and young persons are normally working not more than 48 hours a week,  though they can and do work additional hours (within the special statutory limit of 60) when necessary.The Labour Government,  in the Bill which they introduced in 1924, proposed to limit the hours of women and young persons in factories to 9 in the day and 48 in the week, with only a limited amount of overtime for certain classes of industry which are subjected from time to time to exceptional pressure of work.After thinking over the whole question very carefully, i put forward for the consideration of my colleagues the proposals which appear in Chapter 6, particularly clauses 66 and 67,  of the revised draft.The retention in the Bill of tha hours laid down by the existing Factory Acts is of course out of the question.    The assimilation of textile and non-textile factories, which have hitherto had different regulations as to the hours of employ-ment will in any case make that course impossible.    i think it is clear too, that it will be very difficult, and from the political point of view unwise,  to insert a scheme of hours of employment in the Bill which is markedly less favourable to women and young persons than the arrangements as to hours under which they are actually working.    The cry has already been raised in connection with the mining problem that the Government are attacking the existing hours of work, and the cry will be renewed with greatly increased vigour and probably much greater effect on public opinion if anything like the existing statutory hours are retained in the Factories Bill.i accordingly recommend that the Government should propose in the Factories Bill to lay down for women and young persons hours of employment which correspond to the existing conditions, in other words, to prescribe a 48-hour week with a
Mi:liberal provision as to overtime for all classes of factories and for young persons as well as for women, which will enable employers to adjust the hours of employment to meet the pressure of work.    The number of permissible hours of overtime employment which I have inserted in the Bill is 100, with a maximum limit of 6 hours overtime in one week.    These figures of course are subject to reconsideration.    100 hours overtime in the year means on the average an additional 2 hours a week and raises the average total of hours of employment per week to 50.    If my colleagues, think a greater elasticity is desirable in the case of industries which are subject from time to time to exceptional rushes of work, I shall be disposed to agree and to recommend that in order to meet such cases, the Secretary of State should be given power to allow additional hours - at any rate for women and young persons over 16 - up to a maximum,  say, of 150 in the case of particular industries which are specially subject to periods of pressure and in which the circumstances seem to him to justify it.    A provision of this sort would correspond to the existing overtime provisions in the Factory Act of 1901 (sections 49 and 50)*It might also be desirable to give a general power of suspending the operation of the hours provisions in the Bm and of substituting other provisions in grave economic crisis involving national danger.These provisions, with the other provisions in the Bin such as the clause continuing the two-shift system, would I hope be sufficient to give industry all the elasticity it needs in arranging the hours of work for women and young persons,  and at the same time to satisfy the desires of a very-considerable number,  both in our own Party and in the country at large, who desire to see a real step forward taken in the improvement of the conditions under which aur women and young persons work in the factories of the country.
ISth July,   1926.Unless this done, I am afraid that the Government will lose much of the credit which ought to come to it from the passing of the new Factory Bill, and that the passage of the Bill itself may be rendered much more difficult.W.J.H.
Factories Bill.ARRANGEMENT OF CLAUSES.Application op Act.Clause.1.   Application of Act.Part I.Health (General Provisions).2.   Cleanliness.3.   Overcrowding.4.   Temperature.5.   Ventilation.6.   Lighting.7.   Drainage of floors.8.   Sanitary conveniences.9. Power of district councils to enforce certain provisions of Part I.iO. Powers of inspector as to sanitary defects remediable by district council.11.   Powers in case of default of a district council.12. Power to make orders for special medical super-vision.Part II.Sapett (General Provisions).13.   Prime movers.14.   Transmission machinery.15.   Other machinery.16.   New machinery.17.   Vessels containing dangerous liquids. 18.   Maintenance of fencing. 19.   Self-acting machines.20.   Cleaning  of  machinery by  women and  youngpersons. 21.   Hoists and lifts. 22.   Chains, ropes and cranes.23. Construction and maintenance of passages and stairs.24.   Safe means of access. 127-1 a
Clause.25.   Precautions  in  places  where  dangerous   fumesaccumulate. 26.   Steam boilers. 27.   Steam receivers.28.   Exemptions as to steam boilers and steam receivers. 29.   Compressed air receivers. 80.   Means of escape in case of fire. 31.   Regulations, &amp;c, as to means of escape in case of fire.82.   Safety provisions in case of fire. 33.   Provision as to fire drills in certain factories. 34.   Power to make orders in cases of special clanger. 85.   Power of court to make orders as to dangerousconditions and practices. &apos; 36.   Power   to   make   orders   as   to unhealthy   or dangerous factory.Part III.Welfare (General Provisions).37. Supply of drinking water.38. Eirst-aid.39. facilities for sitting.40. Supply of protective clothing.41. Welfare orders.Part IY.Health, Safety, and Welfare (Special Provisions and Regulations).Special Provisions.42.   Removal of dust or fumes.43.   Prohibition of spitting.44.   Meals in certain dangerous trades.45.   Prohibition of use of white phosphorus in manu-facture of matches. 46.   Prohibition   of   employment   of   female   youngpersons in certain processes. 47.   Prohibition of employment of women and youngpersons in lifting excessive weights.
[16 &amp; 17 Gko. 5.]Factories.iiiClause.48. Prohibition of employment of women and young persons in certain processes connected with lead manufacture.49. Regulations for employment of women and young persons in processes involving use of lead corn-pounds.50.   Metal-grinding factories. 51.   Humid factories. 52.   Underground rooms. 53.   Basement bakehouses. 54.   Laundries.Regulations.55.   Power to make regulations for safety and health.Supplementary Provisions.56. Importation of articles made with prohibited materials.57.   Sale and importation of certain materials, &amp;c. 58.   Power to take samples.Part V.Notification and Investigation of Accidents and Industrial Diseases.59.   Notification of accidents in factories.60. Power to extend to dangerous occurrences pro-visions as to notice of accidents.61.   Notification of industrial diseases.62. Inquest in case of death by accident or industrial disease in factory.63.   Power to direct formal investigation of accidents.6L Duty of appointed doctor to investigate and report in certain cases.Part VI.Employment (Women, Young Persons, and Children).Prohibition of Employment of Children.65.   Prohibition of employment of children. 127 a 2
Hours and Holidays.Clause.66.   General conditions as to hours of employment ofwomen and young persons. 67.   Overtime employment of women. 68.   Notice fixing hours of employment. 69.   Restriction  of  employment   inside  and  outsidefactory on same day. 70.   Prohibition of use of certain rooms during mealtimes.71.   Prohibition of Sunday employment. 72.   Annual holidays.73. Power to suspend certain provisions of Part VI. in emergency.Special Exceptions.74.   Exceptions as to employment of women and youngpersons in shifts. 75.   Exceptions as to male young persons over sixteenemployed in shifts. 76.   Exceptions as to simultaneous hours for meals and rest.77.   Exceptions as to employment during intervals. 78.   Exceptions  as to use  of certain rooms duringmeal times. 79.   Exception as to Saturday.80. Exception as to Sundays and Saturdays in 3 wish factories.81.   Exceptions as to fish and fruit preserving. 82.   Exceptions as to creameries.83. Exception relating to male young persons em-ployed in bakehouses.84. Provision for protection of women and young persons employed under exceptions.85. Notices, registers, &amp;c, relating to special excep-tions.Certificate of fitness for Employment of Young Persons under the age of Sixteen Years.86. Certificate of fitness for employment of young persons under the age of sixteen years.87. Power of inspector to require certificate of capacity for work.88.   Saving.
ass[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]        Factories. vPart VII.Special Applications and Extensions. Premises in respect of which Owner is liable.Clause.89.   Tenement factories.90.   Premises  where  part  of   building   is   separate factory.Institutions.91.   Institutions.Docks, Wharves, Quays, Warehouses and Ships.92.   Docks, &amp;c. 93.   Ships.Building and Engineering Works. 94*.   Building and engineering works.Lead Processes carried on in Places other than Factories. 95.   Employment of women and young persons in processes involving the use of lead carried on in places other than factory.Part VIII. Home Work.96. Lists of outworkers to be kept in certain trades. 97.   Employment of person in unwholesome premises.Part IX.Particulars op Piece-Work and Wages.98.   Particulars of work and wages to be  given to pieceworkers.99.   Modification of foregoing section in relation to weavers.100.   Weights and measures used in ascertaining wages.Part X.Miscellaneous.101. Notice of occupation of factory. 102.   Affixing of abstract and notices.
Clause. &apos;103. General registers.104. Preservation of registers and records.105. Periodical return of persons employed.106. Duties of persons employed.107. Prohibition on deductions from wages.Part XI. Administration.108.   Appointment and duties of inspectors and clerks and servants.109.   Powers of inspectors. . .110.   Power of inspector to conduct proceedings beforemagistrates. 111.   Certificate of appointment of inspector. 112.   Appointment and duties of appointed doctors. 113.   Pees of appointed doctors. 114.   Provisions as to local authorities. 115.   Provisions as to orders of Secretary of State.Part XII:Penalties and Legal Proceedings.116.   Pines for contravention of provisions of this Act. 117.   Pines in case of death or injury. 118.   Pine for offence by parent.119.   Porgery of  certificates, false  entries, and false declarations.120.   Penalty on person actually committing offence forwhich occupier is liable. 121.   Power of occupier to exempt himself from fineon conviction of the actual offender. 122.   Proceedings against persons other than occupiers. 123.   Owner of machine liable in certain cases insteadof occupier.124.   Prosecution of offences , and recovery and appli-cation of fines. 125.   Evidence in summary proceedings. 126.   Service of notices and documents, &amp;c. 127.   Certificate of  birth in  case of  young  persons under eighteen. 128.   Power of county court to modify agreements. 129.   Power of county court to apportion expenses. 130.   Application of Arbitration Act, 1889.
[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.] Factories. viiPart XIII. Interpretation.Clause.131. Factories to which Act applies. 132.   General interpretation.Part XIV.Supplementary.138.   Application to factories belonging to the crown and public authorities. 134.   Inspection of certain premises. 135.   Expenses of Secretary of State. 136.   Application to Scotland. 137.   Repeals.138.   Short title, commencement, and. extent Schedules.
[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.] Factories. lDRAFT op aBILLtoConsolidate,  with amendments,  the enactments a.d. 1926. relating to- Factories; and for purposes con-     -nected therewithBE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : Application op Act.1. Except where the contrary intention appears the Application provisions of this Act shall apply to all factories, as of Act. defined by this Act.10 Part I.Health (General Provisions).2. Every factory shall he kept in a cleanly state, Cleanliness, and free from effluvia arising from any drain, closet, urinal or other nuisance, and, without prejudice to the 15 generality of the,foregoing provision (a) All accumulations of dirt and refuse shall be removed daily from the floors and benches of workrooms, and from the staircases and passages ; and127-1 A
2Factories.[16 &amp; 11 Geo. 5.]The floor of every workroom shall he cleaned at least once in every week ; andAll inside walls and partitions, and all ceilings or tops of rooms (whether those walls, partitions, ceilings or tops are plastered or not), and all 5 Avails, sides and tops of passages and staircases, shall (i) if they have a smooth impervious sur-face, he washed with hot water and soap at least once in every period of fourteen months; 10 -and(ii) if they are painted with oil paint or varnished, he repainted or re-varnished at least once in every period of seven years, and washed with hot water and soap at least once 15 in every period of fourteen months ; and(iii) in other cases he whitewashed or colour-washed before occupation as a factory and thereafter at least once in every period of fourteen months : 20Provided that (i) except where the inspector for the district in any case otherwise requires, the provisions of paragraph (c) of this section shall not applyto any factory where mechanical power is not 25 used, and less than ten persons are employed; and &apos;.(ii) where it appears to the Secretary of State that in any class or description of factories or parts thereof, the provisions of paragraphs (b) 30 or (c) of this section are not required for the purpose of keeping the factory in a cleanly state, or are by reason of special circumstances inapplicable, he may, if he thinks fit, by special order direct that those provisions shall not 35 apply to such factories, or parts of factories.0ver. 3. (1) A  factory shall not  be so  overcrowdedcrowding.     while work is carried on therein as to be injurious to the health of the persons employed therein.(2) Without  prejudice to the  generality of the 40 foregoing provision, a factory shall be deemed to be so overcrowded if the amount of cubic space in anyA.D. 1926. (b)(o)
workroom allows for every person employed in the room, A.D. in the case of a room used or constructed or converted -for use as a workroom before the passing of this Act, less than two hundred and fifty cubic feet or, in the case 5 of any other room, less than four hundred cubic feet, and in calculating the amount of cubic space in any room not constructed or converted for use as a workroom before the passing of this Act, no space more than fourteen feet from the floor shall he taken into account.10 (3) The Secretary of State may, by special order, extend the said proportion of cubic space (a) for any period during which artificial light other than electric light is employed; or(b) as regards any particular process; or15        (c) as regards any factory or part of a factory which is also used as a sleeping apartment.(4) If the inspector for   the district  so requires there shall he affixed in the workroom a notice speci-fying the number of persons who, having regard to the 20 provisions of this section, may be employed in that room.4. (1) Effective measures shall he taken for securing Temp and maintaining a reasonable temperature in each work- ture-room, and the measures so taken shall be such as not to allow the escape of any injurious or offensive fumes into 25 the air of any workroom :In every workroom in which a substantial proportion of the work is done sitting the temperature shall not, after the first hour during which work is going on, be allowed to fall below sixty degrees.30 (-2) At least one thermometer shall be provided and maintained in correct working order in a suitable position in every workroom in which a substantial proportion of the work is done sitting, and in any other place in which the Secretary of State may by special order so direct.35 (3) The Secretary of State may, by special order, for any class or description of factories or parts thereof, prescribe a standard of reasonable temperature, prohibit the use of any methods of maintaining a reasonable temperature which, in his opinion, are likely to he injurious40 to the persons employed, and direct in what positions thermometers shall he provided and maintained. 127-1 A 2
A.D. 1926.Ventilation.Lighting.5. (1) Effective measures shall he taken for securing and maintaining a constant supply of fresh air in each workroom to ensure that the room is adequately ventilated, and for rendering harmless, so far as practicable, all the fumes, dust and other impurities generated in the course 5 of any manufacturing process or work that may be injurious to health.(2) The Secretary of State may, by special order, prescribe a standard of adequate ventilation for factories or for any class or  description of factories or  parts 10 thereof.6. (1) Effective measures shall be taken for securing and maintaining sufficient and suitable lighting in every . part of the factory in which persons are working or passing. 15(2) The Secretary of State may, by special order, prescribe a standard of sufficient and suitable lighting for factories or for any class or description of factories or parts thereof, or for any process.(3) All glazed windows and skylights of workrooms 20 shall, so far as reasonably practicable, be kept clean on both the inner and outer surfaces and free from obstruc-tion.7. Where any process is carried on which renders the floor liable to be wet to such an extent that the wet 25 is capable of being removed by drainage, effective means shall be provided and maintained for draining off the wet.8.-(1) Sufficient and suitable accommodation in the way of sanitary conveniences shall be provided and main-tained, regard being had to the number of persons employed 30 in or in attendance at the factory, and also, where persons of both sexes are or are intended to be employed or in attendance (except in factories where the only persons employed are members of the same family dwelling there), with proper separate accommodation for persons of each 35 sex.(2) Where the Secretary of State is satisfied that in the administrative county of London or in any place 53 &amp; 54 Viet, where section twenty-two of the Public Health Acts c. 59. Amendment Act, 1890, is in force, any district council 40is willing to undertake the duty of enforcing the pro-Draiuage of floors.Saiiitnry convenience-ences.
visions of this   section, and  that  that  duty  will  he  A.D. 1926. satisfactorily performed by the council, he shall by order        delegate to the council the duty of enforcing the said provisions.5 (3) The Secretary of State shall, by special order, determine what is sufficient and suitable accommodation within the meaning of this section.9. (1) The foregoing provisions as to cleanliness, Power of over-crowding, temperature, ventilation, drainage of floors, d*^tri(ijs t 10 and sanitary conveniences shall as respects any factory in enforcecer-which mechanical power is not used and which forms part tain pro-of a dwelling-house or shop, or is adjacent to a dwelling- visions of house or shop in the same occupation, he enforced by       J-the district council.15 (2) Where the Secretary of State is satisfied that the duty of enforcing all or any of the said provisions in all other factories in which mechanical power is not used, or in any class or description of such factories will be satisfactorily performed by a district council willing to20 undertake the duty, he shall by order delegate to that council the duty of enforcing such of the said provisions as may he specified in the order.(3) Every district council shall keep a register of all factories situate within their district with respect to 25 which the duty of enforcing any of the said provisions is imposed upon or undertaken by them.10.  (1) Where an inspector finds any act, neglect, Powers of or default, in relation to any drain, sanitary convenience, inspector as water-supply, nuisance, or other matter in a factory jg/eglJgta1730 which is liable to be dealt with by the district council remediable under this Part of this Act or under the law relating to by district public health, that inspector shall give notice in writing of council, the act, neglect, or default to the district council, and it shall he the duty of the district council to make such35 inquiry into the subject of the notice, and take such action thereon, as seems to that council proper for the purpose of enforcing the law, and to inform the inspector of the proceedings taken in consequence of the notice.(2) An inspector may, for the purposes of this section, 40 take with him into a factory a medical officer, of health, sanitary inspector, or other officer of the district council.A 3
A.D. 1926.Powers in case of de-fault of a district council.(3) &quot;Where notice of an act, neglect, or default is given by an inspector under this section to a district council, and proceedings are not taken within one month for punishing or remedying the act, neglect or default, the inspector may take the like proceedings for punishing or remedying the same as the district council might have taken, and shall be entitled to recover from the district council summarily as a civil debt all such expenses in and about the proceedings as the inspector incurs and as are not recovered from any other person, and have not been incurred in or about any unsuccessful legal pro-ceedings.Power to make orders for special medical supervision.lo11.-(1) If the Secretary of State is satisfied that the provisions of this Part of this Act which are enforce-ahle by a district council, have not been enforced by 15 any district council, he may, by order, authorise an inspector to take, during such period as may be men-tioned in the order, such steps as appear necessary or proper for enforcing those provisions,(2) An inspector authorised in pursuance of this 20 section shall, for the purpose of his duties thereunder, have the same powers in regard to any such matters as he has with respect to other matters under this Act, and he may, for that purpose, take the like proceedings for enforcing the provisions of this Act, or for punishing or 25 remedying any act or default, as might be taken by the district council; and he shall be entitled to recover from the district council summarily as a &quot;civil&apos;debt all such expenses in and about any proceedings as he may incur and. as are not recovered from any other person. 3012.-(1) Where it appears to the Secretary of State that in view of the amount of sickness among the workers in any factory or class or description of factories or for some other reason that special provision ought to be made at that factory or at factories of that class or description to secure 35 the health of persons employed therein, he may, after consultation with the Minister of Health, by order require the occupier to make such reasonable provision by arrangements for the special medical supervision of the workers and otherwise (but not so&apos; as to include 40 medical treatment) as may be specified in the order.(2) If, in the case of any order proposed to be made for factories of a particular class or description,; the
majority of trie occupiers of factories of that class or A.D. 1926. description, dispute the reasonableness of the require-   ments in the proposed order or any of them, the objection shall be referred for settlement to a referee in accordance 5 with the rules made under this section, but the Secretary of State may refer any objection, though not made by a majority of the occupiers, if he thinks desirable.(3) The Secretary of State may make rules as to the time within which, and the manner in which, notice of 10 objection to any proposed order may he made, and to the selection of, and procedure before, a referee, and the costs of the proceedings before the referee (including the remuneration of the referee).Part II.15 Safety (General Provisions).13. (1) Every flywheel directly connected to any prime prime mover and every moving part of any prime mover, movers, except such prime movers as are mentioned in suhsec-tion (3) of this section, shall he securely fenced, whether 20 the flywheel or prime mover is situated in an engine-house or not.(2) The head and tail race of every water wheel and of every water turbine shall be securely fenced.(3) Every part of electric generators, motors and rotary 25 converters, and every flywheel directly connected there-with, shall either be securely fenced or be in such position or of such construction as to be safe to every person employed or working on the premises as it would be if securely fenced.30        14.-(1) Every part of the transmission machinery xrans-shall either he so fenced or be in such position or of such mission construction as to be as safe to every person employed or machinery, working on the premises :Provided that while the speed of the machinery is so 35 reduced as not to exceed six revolutions per minute, the foregoing requirements shall not apply as respects a person approaching the machinery for the purposes of lubricating it or of shipping or unshipping belts thereon.A 4
A.D. 1926. (2) No belt, strap or rope, when not in use, shall be       allowed to rest or ride upon a revolving shaft which forms part of the transmission machinery.(3) Efficient devices or appliances shall be provided in every room or place in which work is carried on so 5 as to stop promptly the transmission machinery in that room or place.(4) Suitable striking gear or other efficient mechanical appliances shall be provided and used to move driving straps on fast and loose pulleys which form part of the 10 transmission machinery, and any such gear or appliances shall be so constructed and maintained as to prevent accidental restarting of the machinery :(5) The Secretary of State may by order exempt any class of machines from any of the requirements of the 15 last two foregoing subsections of this section, if he is satisfied that the fulfilment of any such requirement is unnecessary or impracticable for that class of machines.Other 15. (1) Every dangerous part of any machinery,machinery,   GiYiev than prime movers and transmission machinery, 20 shall either be so fenced or be in such a position or of such construction as to be as safe to persons employed or working on the premises :Provided that where the safety of a dangerous part of any machinery cannot be secured by means of a fixed 25 guard, the requirements of this subsection may be deemed to have been complied with if a device is employed which automatically removes the hand of the operator from, or prevents it approaching, that part.(2) &quot;Where the Secretary of State is of opinion that 30 any safety device which-(a) makes it impossible to expose a dangerous partof machinery whilst in motion; or(b) stops a machine forthwith in case of danger,is suitable for use in connection with machinery of any 35 class, he may by special order direct that the device shall be provided for use in connection with such class of machinery as may be specified in the order.(3) Any part of any material or article which is dangerous while in  motion  in any machine shall, if 4 
practicable, either be securely fenced or he in such a  A.D. 1926. position as to be as safe to every person employed or working  on the premises as it would be if securely fenced.5        16. (1) In the case of any machinery intended to New be driven by mechanical power constructed after the machinery, date of the passing of this Act - .(a) no set-screws, bolts or keys on any revolving shaft, spindle, wheel or pinion shall be allowed 10 to project unless so encased as to prevent clanger;and(ft) all spur and other toothed or friction gearing not so situated as not to be exposed shall be completely encased.15 (2) Any person Avho sells or lets on hire any machine constructed after the date of the passing of this Act which does not comply with the requirements of this section shall, unless he proves that the machine was sold or let on hire for use outside the United Kingdom, be guilty20 of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds.(3) The Secretary of State may by order apply the preceding subsection to machinery which does not comply with the requirements of any other provision of this Act 25 specified in the order, or of any order or regulation made under this Act and so specified, but any order made under this subsection shall relate only to machinery constructed after the date of the order.17. Every  fixed  vessel,  structure,  sump  or pit Vessels 30 containing any scalding, corrosive or poisonous liquid, j^&quot;^1^1&quot;^ the edge of which is less than three feet above the JiqU&quot;(is. adjoining ground or platform, shall either be securely covered or he securely fenced to at least that height, unless the nature of the work makes such covering or 35 fencing impracticable.18. All fencing or other safeguards provided in Maintenance pursuance of the foregoing provisions of this Part of this fencing. Act shall be of substantial construction, and constantly maintained in position and in an efficient state while the 40 parts required to be fenced or safeguarded are in motion or in use, except when any such parts are necessarily exposed for cleaning, lubrication, or examination.127 B
10Factories. [16 &amp; IT Geo. 6,1A.D. 1926.Self-acting machines.Cleaning of machinery by women and young persons.  .Hoists and lilts.19. (1) In any factory or part of a factory to which this sub-section applies no traversing carriage of any self-acting machine and no material carried thereon shall be allowed on its outward or inward traverse to run within a distance of eighteen inches from any fixed 5 structure not being part of the machine, if the space over which it runs is a space over which any person is liable to pass, whether in the course of his employment or otherwise:Provided that nothing in this subsection shall prevent 10 any portion of the traversing carriage of any self-acting cotton, worsted or woollen &quot;spinning machine being allowed to run to a point twelve inches distant from any part of the head stock of another such machine.(2) The foregoing subsection applies  15(a) to any factory erected after the thirty-first   &apos; -day of December eighteen hundred and ninety-:    five; and     ;(6) to any factory or part of a factory reconstructed after the passing of this Actand   ; 20(c) to any extension of or addition to a factory made after the passing of this Act.(3) A person employed shall not be in the space between the fixed and the traversing parts of a self-acting machine unless the machine is stopped with the 25 traversing part on the outward run, but for the purpose of this provision the space in front of a self-acting machine shall not he included in the space aforesaid.20. A woman or young person shall not clean any part , of a prime mover or any transmission machinery 30 while in motion, or any part of any machine the cleaning of which would expose that woman or young person to risk of injury either from that machine or from any adjacent machinery. .. ,       r-21. (1) Every hoistway or liftway shall, if not com- 35 pletely. enclosed, be efficiently protected by a substantial enclosure to a height of at least six and. a half feet at the bottom, and, subject as hereinafter provided, in the case of a way inside a building, to at least that height at every landing. The protection shall be such as to 4,9 prevent any person falling down the way or coming into contact with any moving part of the hoist or lift:
Provided that a platform hoist shall not be required   A.D. 1926. to be protected at the top landing by an enclosure exceed-ing a height of three and a half feet.(2) At every opening giving access to a hoist or lift 5 there shall be provided a door or gate not less than six feet in height, or if the opening is of less height than six feet, of a height sufficient completely to close the opening. In the case of a hoist or lift constructed or reconstructed after the passing of  this Act, the door10 or gate shall be so fitted that it cannot be opened except when the floor of the hoist or lift is level with the landing at the opening, and that the hoist or lift cannot be moved away until the door or gate is closed; and in any other case the door or gate shall be so fitted- if it is15 reasonably practicable to make any alterations required, and in any event shall be kept closed and fastened except when the hoist or lift is at rest at the opening.(3) The hoist or lift, and, where the hoistway or lift-way is wholly or partly enclosed, the inside of the enclosure, 20 shall be so constructed as to prevent any part of any person or goods carried in the hoist or lift being trapped between any part of the hoist or lift and any fixed structure or the counter-balance weight.(4) The following requirements shall be observed in 25&apos; connection with every power-driven hoist or lift which is used for raising or lowering persons whether together with goods or otherwise : (a) If the hoist or lift is suspended by ropes or chains, there shall be at least two such ropes or30 chains, separately connected thereto, and eachcapable, with its attachments, of sustaining the whole weight of the hoist or lift and its maximum working load; and in the case of a hoist or lift constructed or reconstructed after the passing35 of  this  Act an  efficient safety  device shall also be provided and maintained in working order which will hold the hoist or lift with its maximum working load in the event of the breakage  of the  ropes  or   chains   or   their40 attachments;(b) The maximum working load which the hoist or lift is designed to carry shall be marked conspicuously on the hoist or lift, and the hoist127 B 2
or lift shall not be used for raising or lowering a heavier load; (c) Efficient automatic appliances shall be provided and maintained in working order to prevent the hoist or lift over-running. 5(5) Every part of every hoist or lift, including the mechanism, gates and fittings thereof, shall be thoroughly examined by a competent person at least once in every six months, and a report of the result of every such examination in the prescribed form and containing the pre- 10 scribed particulars shall he signed by the person making the examination and shall, within fourteen days, be entered in or attached to the general register.(6) The foregoing provisions of this section shall not apply to a continuous hoist or lift or to a hoist or lift not 15 connected with mechanical power, and the expressions &quot; hoist &quot; and &quot; liftway &quot; shall he construed accordingly, hut every hoist and lift not connected with mechanical power and the hoistway or liftway thereof must he securely fenced. 20(7) If it be shown to the satisfaction of the Secretary of State that it would he unreasonable in the special circumstances of the case to enforce any requirement of this section in respect of any class or description of hoist, lift, or liftway, he may by order direct that such require- 25 ment shall not apply as respects that class of hoist, lift, or liftway.(8) Every teagle opening or similar doorway used for hoisting or lowering goods or materials, whether by means of a hoist or of a lift connected with mechanical 30 power or otherwise, shall he securely protected by a door or gate to a height of three and a half feet, and shall be provided with a hand-grip on each of the door jambs. Every such door or gate shall be kept closed and fastened except when hoisting or lowering of goods or materials 35 is being carried on at such opening or doorway.Chains, ropes        22.  (l) The following provisions shall be observed and cranes,   in respect of every chain or rope and chain or rope sling -used for the purpose of raising or lowering persons, goods or materials :  4,0(a) A table showing the safe working loads of every kind and size of chain rope or sling in use, and,a.d. 1926.
in the case of a multiple sling, the safe working  A.D. 1926. load at different angles of the legs, shall be      T&quot; &apos; posted in the store in which the chains, ropes or slings are kept, and in prominent positions on 5 the premises;(b) No such chain, rope or sling shall be used for any load exceeding the safe working load;(c) No such chain, rope or sling shall be used after ithas shown signs of excessive wear or corrosion 10 or of other serious defect;(d) Every such chain, rope or sling when in use shall he examined at such intervals as the Secretary of State may by special order direct;(e) Every such chain or chain sling, unless made of 15 steel or iron which has been subjected to such other form of heat treatment as may be approved by the Secretary of State, shall he annealed at least once in every fourteen months, or, in the case of chains or slings of 20 half-inch bar or smaller, or chains  used inconnection with molten metal or molten slag, in every six months;(f) A register in the prescribed form and containing the prescribed particulars shall he kept with25 respect to all such chains, ropes or slings, exceptfibre rope slings. (2) Every crane, winch, transporter or runway shall have the safe working load plainly marked upon it, and in the case of a crane so constructed that the safe 30 working load may be varied by the raising or lowering of the jib, shall either have attached to it an automatic indicator of safe working loads or a table showing the safe working loads at corresponding inclinations of the jib.(3) No person shall work on or near the track of 35 an overhead travelling crane in any place where he is liable to he struck by the crane, until the driver of the -crane has been warned that the person is working in that place and effective means have been taken to prevent the crane from approaching within twenty feet of the place 40 where he is working.23. (1) All floors, steps, stairs, passages and gang- Construction ways shall he of sound construction and maintained in ^an^m&quot; good repair. of passagesand stairs.
14,Factories.[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.jA.D. 1926. (2) All stairs shall be provided with proper and substantial handrails.(3) All openings in floors shall be securely fenced, except in so far as the nature of the work renders such fencing impracticable. 5Safe means 24. (l) Safe means of access shall be provided to of access.     every place at which any person has at any time to work.(2) A person shall not be employed or work at any place which is more than twelve feet from the ground, unless either the place is one which affords secure foot- 10 hold and, where necessary, secure handhold, or adequate means are provided by fencing or otherwise to ensure his safety.(3) If it be shown to the satisfaction of the Secretary of State that it would be unreasonable in the special 15 circumstances of the case to enforce any requirement of this section in respect of any place or class of place, he may by order direct that such requirement shall not apply as respects, that place or class of place.25. (1) Where persons engaged on work which has 20 to be carried on inside any structure or place are exposed to the risk of being overcome by dangerous fumes which are liable to accumulate therein : (a) The structure or place, if not open to the air, shall be provided with a manhole not less than 25 twenty inches long and eighteen inches wide; and(b) No  person shall enter the structure or other place for any purpose unless (i) all practicable means have been taken 30 for removing any fumes which may be present, and he is wearing a belt to which there is securely attached a rope of which the free end is held by a person outside ; or(ii) he is wearing a suitable breathing appa- 35 apparatus;(c) Suitable  breathing apparatus and an oxygen reviving apparatus shall be provided and main-tained in good condition and so as to be readily accessible, and shall be periodically inspected 40 in the prescribed manner; andPrecautions in places where dangerous fumes accu-tnulate.
(d) A sufficient number of the persons employed   A.D. shall he trained and practised in the use of       -such apparatus and in the method of restoring respiration.   :.5 (2) No work shall be permitted in any boiler, furnace, or flue until it has been ventilated for a sufficiently long time to make work safe, for the persons employed.(3) The Secretary of State may grant exemption from compliance with the requirements of paragraphs (c) and 10 (d) of subsection (1) of this section in any case where he .  is satisfied that compliance with these requirements is unnecessary.26. (1) Every steam boiler, whether separate or Steam one of a range  boilers15        (a) shall have attached to it (i) a suitable safety valve, separate from any stop-valve, which shall be so adjusted as to permit the steam to escape at a working pressure not greater than the maximum per-20 missible working pressure and shall, in thecase of any new boiler taken into use after the commencement of this Act, be fixed directly to the boiler ; and(ii) a  correct steam pressure gauge con-25                 nected to the steam space and easily visibleby the boiler attendant, which shall indicate the pressure of steam in the boiler in pounds per square inch, and have marked upon it in a distinctive colour the maximum permissible 30 working pressure ; and(hi) at least one water gauge of transparent H material to show the water level in the boiler,and, if the working pressure in the boiler normally exceeds  forty pounds  per square 35 inch, the gauge shall be provided with an efficient guard but not so as to obstruct the reading of the gauge ; and(iv) a suitable stop valve connecting the boiler to the steam pipe ; and40 (v) where it is one of two or more boilers,a plate bearing a distinctive number which shall be easily visible ; and
16[Factories.[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]1926. (b) shall he provided with means for attaching a test pressure gauge; and(c) unless externally fired or of the water tube type, shall he provided with a suitable fusible plug or an efficient low-water alarm device. 5For the purposes of this subsection a lever-valve shall not be deemed a suitable safety valve unless the weight is secured on the lever in the correct position.(2) Where a range of two or more steam boilers has a common blow-off pipe or blow-off pipes delivering into 10 a common sump, the blow-off valve or tap on each boiler shall he so constructed that it is impossible to remove the key until the valve or tap is closed. Not more than one key shall be in use for any such range.(3) Every steam boiler and all its fittings and attach- 15 ments shall be maintained in efficient working order.(4) Every steam boiler and all such fittings and attachments other than any stop valve shall be thoroughly examined by a competent person at least once in every period of fourteen months, and also after any extensive 20 repairs : and the person making any such examination shall first examine the boiler when it is cold and the interior and exterior have been properly prepared, and again examine it when it is under normal steam pressure.The examination under steam pressure shall he made 25 on the first occasion when steam is raised after the examination of the boiler when cold, or as soon as possible thereafter, and the person making such examination shall see that the safety valve blows off at a working pressure not greater than the maximum permissible working 30 pressure.(5) A report of the result of every such examination in the prescribed form and containing the prescribed par-ticulars (including the maximum permissible working pressure) shall wdthin twenty-eight days be entered in or 40 attached to the general register, and the report shall be signed by the person making the examination, and if that person is an inspector of a boiler-inspecting company or : association, countersigned by the chief engineer of the company or association. 45
(6) An occupier shall not take into use any new steam boiler unless it is stamped with the name of the manufacturer of the boiler and with a distinctive number and unless the occupier shall have obtained from the 5 manufacturer of the boiler a certificate specifying the maximum permissible working pressure of the boiler, and stating the nature of the tests to which the boiler and fittings have been submitted, and an occupier proposing to take into his own use for the first time a steam boiler 10 which has previously been used shall not take the boiler into use until it has been examined and reported on in accordance with the two preceding subsections.(7) A steam boiler shall not be used except in accord-ance with any conditions of safe working which may be &apos;!) specified in the report of the examination.(8) The person making the report, or, in the case of a boiler-inspecting company or association, the chief engineer thereof, shall within twenty-eight days send to the inspector for the district a copy of the report in every case where 20 the maximum permissible working pressure is reduced, or the examination shows that the boiler cannot continue to be used with safety unless certain repairs are carried out immediately or within a specified time.(9) If the person employed to make the examination 25 fails to make a thorough examination as required by this section or makes a report which is false or deficient in any material particular, or being the chief engineer of any boiler-inspecting company or association permits any such report to be made, or fails to send to the inspector for the 30 district a copy of any report as required by the preceding subsection, he shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds.(10) If the chief inspector is not satisfied as to the competency of the person employed to make the examina-35 tion or as to the thoroughness of the examination, he may require the boiler to be re-examined by a person nominated by him, and the occupier shall give the neces-sary facilities for such re-examination. If as a result of such re-examination it appears that the report of the40 examination was inadequate, or inaccurate in any material particular, the cost of the re-examination shall be recover-able from the occupier summarily as a civil debt, and the report of the re-examination purporting to be signed 127 0
A.D. 1926.Steamreceivers.Exceptions as to steam boilers and steam receivers.(iii)1015by the person making it shall he evidence of the facts stated therein.(11) This section shall not apply to the boiler of any ship or of any locomotive which belongs to and is used by any railway company, or to any boiler belonging to or exclusively used in the service of His Majesty.(12) In this Act the expression &quot;maximum permissible working pressure &quot; means, in the case of a steam boiler which has already been used, that specified in the report of the last examination under this section, and, in the case of a steam boiler which has not been previously used, that specified by the maker.27. (1) Every steam receiver, not so constructed as to withstand with safety the maximum permissible working pressure in the boiler by which it is supplied, shall be fitted with (i) a suitable reducing valve or other suitable means to prevent the safe working pressure being exceeded; and(ii) a suitable safety valve so adjusted as to permit the steam to escape as soon as the safe working pressure is exceeded; and a correct steam pressure gauge,  which must indicate the pressure of steam in the receiver in pounds per square inch ; and (iv) a suitable stop valve ; and(v) except where only one steam receiver is in use, a plate bearing a distinctive number which shall be easily visible. The safety valve and pressure gauge shall be fitted either 30 on the steam receiver or between the steam receiver and the reducing valve, if any.(2) Every steam receiver and the fittings attached thereto shall be maintained in efficient working order, and shall be periodically examined so far as practicable.     35(3) A record in the prescribed form shall be kept in the general register of the result of every such examination.28. The chief inspector may by written certificate S3S, except from any of the provisions of the last two pre- 40 ceding sections of this Act any class or type of steam boiler or steam receiver to which he is satisfied that such2025
provision cannot reasonably be applied.   Such exception  A.D. 1926 may be unqualified or may be subject to such conditions as may be contained in the certificate.29. (1) Every receiver which forms part of an Compressedair receivers.5 air-compressing plant shall.(a) have marked upon it so as to be plainly visible the safe working pressure ; and(b) have attached to it a suitable safety valvewhich shall allow the air to escape as soon 10 as the safe working pressure is exceeded; and(c) have attached to it a correct pressure gaugeindicating the pressure of air in the receiver in pounds per square inch ; and(d) have attached to it a suitable drain-valve or 15 tap; and(*?) be provided with a suitable manhole, handhole, or other means which will allow the interior to he thoroughly cleaned; and (/) be thoroughly cleaned and examined at least 20 once in every period of twenty-six months.(2) Every such receiver and the fittings attached thereto shall he maintained in efficient working order.(3) A record in the prescribed form shall be kept in the general register of the results of every examination 25 under this section.30. (1) Every factory to which this section applies Means of shall he certified by the district council as being provided es*aPe ^ with such means of escape in case of fire for the persons oa 6 0 ire&apos; employed therein as may reasonably be required in the30 circumstances of each case and if any person uses as a factory any premises which have not been so certified, he shall be guilty of an offence and liable on conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds and to a further fine not exceeding five pounds for each day on35 which the offence continues after conviction thereof.It shall be the duty of the council to examine every such factory and, on being satisfied that the factory is so provided, to give such a certificate as aforesaid. The certificate shall specify precisely and in detail the means 40 of escape provided, and such particulars as to the nature of the processes carried on, maximum number of persons 127 C 2
A.D. 1926. employed or proposed to be employed, and other matters taken into account in granting the certificate, as the council may consider it desirable to record. The certifi-cate shall be attached by the occupier to the general register, and a copy of it shall be sent by the council 5 to the inspector for the district.(2) If, after the grant of a certificate, the occupier proposes to make any extension or alteration in the factory - premises or to increase materially the number of persons employed or to commence to store or use highly inflamatory- 10 mable or explosive material, he shall give notice to the council of his intention.(3) If the council on receipt of the notice mentioned in the preceding subsection are of opinion that the con-ditions in regard to escape in case of fire will be affected, 15 or if at any time they are satisfied that by reason of altered conditions the existing means of escape have become insufficient, they may cancel the certificate, and thereupon a new certificate shall be obtained from the council. 20(4) A factory which has been furnished with a certificate in pursuance of subsection (1) of section fourteen of the Factory and Workshop Act, 1901, and a factory in respect of which a notice issued in pursuance of sub-section (2) of that section has been complied with, or 25 in respect of which an award has been made under subsection (3) of that section and has been complied with, shall be entitled to receive a certificate from the district council without further examination unless since such compliance any action has been taken of which 30 notice would have been required under subsection (2) of this section if that subsection had been in force.(5) If it appears to an inspector that dangerous conditions in regard to escape in case of fire exist in any factory to which this section applies he may give notice to 35 the district council, and it shall be the duty of the council forthwith to examine the factory, and they shall have power to require such alterations as they may deem necessary. The occupier shall forthwith carry out any such alterations, and upon their being carried out the 40 council shall inform the inspector of the action which has been taken and may amend their certificate or issue a fresh certificate.
[ 16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5,1Factories.21Where notice is so given as aforesaid and action is a.d. 1926 not taken by the district council within one month for remedying the dangerous coiiditions, the inspector may take the like action as the council might have taken 5 and shall be entitled to recover from the district council summarily as a civil debt all such expenses as the inspector may incur in so doing, and as are not recovered from any other person, and are not expenses incurred in or about any unsuccessful legal proceedings.10 (6) If the occupier of any factory erected before the passing of this Act is aggrieved by the refusal of a district council to grant a certificate under this section or by being required by a district council or by an inspector under this section to carry out any alterations at the15 factory, he may appeal to a court of summary jurisdic-tion, and the decision of the court shall be binding on the occupier and the council or inspector.(7) This section applies to every factory (a) in  which   more  than  twenty   persons   are 2() employed ; or(b) of which the construction has been completed, or which has been adapted for use as a factory, after the passing of this Act, and in which ten or more persons are employed on25 any floor  above   the   ground  floor  of  thebuilding; or(c) of which the construction has been completed before the passing of this Act and in which more than ten  persons are employed above 30 the first floor of the building or at a greaterheight than 20 feet above the ground level; or(d) in which explosive or highly inflammable materials are stored or \ised.35        31.-(1) The Secretary of State may make regula- regulations, tions as to the means of escape in case of fire to be pro- &amp;0, as t0. vided in factories or any class or description of factories, ^caoehi and the provisions contained in the Second Schedule to oase&apos;of fiu-e. this Act shall apply to any such regulations.40 It shall be the duty of the district council to see that the requirements of any such regulations are complied with, and if a certificate has already been issued in
A.D. 1926. respect of a factory which is not in conformity with the regulations, the certificate shall he cancelled and a new certificate shall he obtained from the district council.(2) Every district council shall, in addition to any powers which they possess with reference to the pre- 5 vention of fire, have power to make byelaws providing for means of escape from fire in the case of factories or any class or description of factories, and sections one hundred and eighty-two to one hundred and eighty-six of the Public Health Act, 1875, shall apply to any byelaws 10 so made ; but such byelaws shall not contain any pro-visions inconsistent with any regulations made by the Secretary of State under the preceding subsection.Safety pro- 32. (1) While any person is within a factory forvisions in    the purpose of employment or meals, the doors of the 15 ease o   rr.   factory- an(j Gf any ro0m therein in which such person is, shall not be locked or fastened in such manner that they cannot be easily and immediately opened from the inside.(2) Any doors opening on to any staircase or corridor 20 in any factory from any room in which more than ten persons are employed, and in the case of any factory constructed or converted for use as a factory after the passing of this Act, all other doors at the factory also, shall, except in the case of sliding doors, be constructed 25 to open outwards.(3) In any factory constructed or converted for use as a factory before the passing of this Act, in which more than ten persons are employed, any door, which is not kept continuously open, at the foot of a staircase affording 30 for workers a means of exit from the factory shall, except in the case of sliding doors, be constructed to open outwards.(4) Every window, door, or other exit in a factory giving access to any means of escape in case of fire, 35 other than the means of exit in ordinary use, shall be distinctively marked by a notice printed in red letters of an adequate size.(5) In every factory or part of a factory where more than twenty persons are employed above the ground floor, 40 or where any explosive or highly inflammable material
is handled or stored, there shall be provided for giving  ^--D. 1926. warning in case of fire an alarm signal system, the signals of which shall be clearly audible throughout the factory or building.5 (6) In every factory all means of escape in case of fire shall be maintained in good condition and free from obstruction.(7) In every factory the contents of any room shall not be so arranged or disposed that there is not a free 10 passageway for all persons employed in the room to a door or other exit.38. In every factory or part of a factory, not being Provision as a factory licensed under the Explosives Act, 1875, or a &apos;0 fil&quot;e ^.nlls factory for the manufacture of explosives under  the factories&quot;115 control of a Government Department, where more than twenty women or young persons are employed above the first floor or more than twenty feet above the ground level, or where highly imflammable or dangerous material is handled or stored, there shall be conducted in the20 prescribed manner at least once in every three months a fire drill in which all the occupants of the factory or part thereof shall take part.34. Where it appears to the Secretary of State that, Power to in view of the number and nature of accidents occurring make orders25 in any factory or class of factories, special provision ought m    j?,0? to be made at that factory or at factories of that class to g^cia  an&quot; secure the safety of persons employed therein, he may by order require the occupier to make such reasonable pro-vision by arrangements for special supervision in regard30 to safety, investigation of the circumstances and causes of accidents, and otherwise as may be specified in the order.35. (1) If on complaint by an inspector a court of Power of summary jurisdiction is satisfied either  cou^ t035        (a) that any part of the ways, works, machinery, or as toplant used in a factory is in such a condition dangerous or is so constructed or is so placed that it conditions cannot be used without danger of bodily injury ; a^g8prac&quot; or &apos;L&apos;&apos;&apos;40        (5) that any process or work is carried on or anything is done in any factory in such a maner as to
A.D. 1926. threaten or tend to the bodily injury of anyperson ;the court may as the case may require by order (i) prohibit the use of that part of the ways, works, machinery or plant, or, if it is capable of repair 5 or alteration, prohibit its use until it is duly repaired or altered ; or* (ii) require the occupier to take such steps as may be specified in the order for remedying the danger complained of. 10(2) Where a complaint has been made under this section, the court or a justice may, on application ex parte by the inspector to the effect that the use of any such part of the ways, works, machinery, or plant, in-volves imminent danger to life, make an interim order 15 prohibiting, either absolutely or subject to conditions, the use thereof until the earliest opportunity for hearing and determining the complaint.(3) If there is any contravention of an order made under this section, the occupier and any person entitled 20 to control the use of the part of the ways, works, ma-chinery, or plant shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, and to a further fine not exceeding five pounds for each day on which the contravention continues after conviction thereof. 2538.  A court of summary jurisdiction may, on complaint by an inspector, and on being satisfied that any factory or part of a factory is in such a condition that any process or work carried on therein cannot he so carried on without danger to health or to life or limb, by order, 30 prohibit the use thereof for the purpose of that process or work, until such works have been executed as are in the opinion of the court necessary to remove the danger.Part III.Welfare (General Provisions). 3537. (1) There shall be provided and maintained at suitable points conveniently accessible to all persons employed an adequate supply of wholesome  drinkingPower to make orders as to uti-healthy or dangero us factorySupply ofdrinkingwater.
water from a public main or from some other source A.D. 1926. approved in writing by the district council.(2) Each drinking water supply shall be clearly marked &quot; Drinking -water,&quot; and a supply of drinking water 5 which is not laid on shall be contained in suitable vessels, and shall be renewed at least daily; and all practicable steps shall be&apos;taken to preserve the water and vessels from contamination.38. (1) If mechanical power is used in a factory First-aid. 10 there shall be provided and maintained so as to be readily accessible a first-aid box or cupboard of the prescribed standard, and where more than one hundred and fifty persons are employed an additional box or cupboard for every additional one hundred and fifty persons.] 5 The number of first-aid boxes or cupboards required under this provision shall be calculated on the largest number of persons employed at any one time, and any fraction of one hundred and fifty shall be reckoned as one hundred and fifty.   &quot;Where the persons employed are20 employed in shifts the calculation of the number employed shall be according to the largest number at work at any one time.(2) Nothing except appliances or requisites for first-aid shall be kept in a first-aid box or cupboard.25 (3) Each first-aid box or cupboard shall be placed under the charge of a responsible person who shall always he readily aArailable during working hours. A notice shall he affixed in every workroom stating the name of the person in charge of the first-aid box or cupboard30 provided in respect of that room.(4) If an ambulance room is provided at the factory and such arrangements are made as to ensure the immediate treatment there of all injuries occurring in the factory, the chief inspector may by certificate 35 exempt the factory from the requirements of this section to such extent and subject to such conditions as he may specify in the certificate.39. There shall be provided and maintained for the Facilities use of all female workers whose work is done standing fo1&apos; sitting. &apos;10 a sufficient number of seats to enable them to  take advantage of any opportunities for resting which may occur in the course of their employment. 127 D
water from a public main or from some other source A.d. 1926. approved in writing by the district council.(2) Each drinking water supply shall be clearly marked &quot; Drinking water,&quot; and a supply of drinking water 5 which is not laid on shall be contained in suitable vessels, and shall he renewed at least daily; and all practicable steps shall betaken to preserve the water and vessels from contamination.38. (1) If mechanical power is used in a factory First-aid. 10 there shall be provided and maintained so as to be readily accessible a first-aid box or cupboard of the prescribed standard, and where more than one hundred and fifty persons are employed an additional box or cupboard for every additional one hundred and fifty persons.] 5 The number of first-aid boxes or cupboards required under this provision shall be calculated on the largest number of persons employed at any one time, and any fraction of one hundred and fifty shall be reckoned as one hundred and fifty.   Where the persons employed are20 employed in shifts the calculation of the number employed shall be according to the largest number at work at any one time.(2) Nothing except appliances or requisites for first-aid shall he kept in a first-aid box or cupboard.25 (3) Each first-aid box or cupboard shall he placed under the charge of a responsible person who shall always be readily available during working hours. A notice shall he affixed in every workroom stating the name of the person in charge of the first-aid box or cupboard30 provided in respect of that room.(4) If an ambulance room is provided at the factory and such arrangements are made as to ensure the immediate treatment there of all injuries occurring in the factory, the chief inspector may by certificate 35 exempt the factory from the requirements of this section to such extent and subject to such conditions as he may specify in the certificate.39. There shall be provided and maintained for the Facilities use of all female workers whose work is done standing for sitting. 40 a sufficient number of seats to enable them to  take advantage of any opportunities for resting which may occur in the course of their employment.127 D
26factories.[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]40. Where protective clothing is prescribed to be necessary for the use of persons employed in any process, suitable protective clothing shall be provided and main-tained for the use of every person who is exposed in the usual course of his employment to acids or to any noxious 5 or offensive substance liable to cause injury to person or clothing.41. (1) Where it appears to the Secretary of State that owing to the conditions and circumstances of employ-ment or the nature of the processes carried on, provision 10 requires to be made in relation to any of the matters to which this section applies, for securing the welfare of the persons employed or any class thereof, he may by order require such reasonable steps to be taken in connection therewith as may be specified in the order. 15(2) The following are the matters to which this section applies: Any of the matters dealt with in the foregoing pro-visions of this Part of this Act; arrangements for preparing or heating, and taking, meals ; ambulance- 20 lance and training in first-aid ; rest rooms ; arrange-ments for supervision of persons employed.(3) Orders under this section may (a) be  made  for  a  particular  factory,  or for factories of any class or group or description ; 25(b) be made contingent in respect of particular requirements upon application being made by a specified number or proportion of the employed persons concerned, and prescribe the manner in which the views of the persons 30 employed are to be ascertained;(c) provide for the employed persons concerned being associated in the management of the arrangements, accommodation or other facili-ties for which provision is made, in any case 35 where a portion of the cost is contributed by the persons employed; but no contribution shall be required from the persons employedin any factory, except for the purpose of providing additional or special benefits which, 40 in  the opinion of the  Secretary of State, could not reasonably be required to be pro-vided  by the employer  alone, and  unless
two-thirds at least of the employed persons  A.D. 1926. affected in that factory, on their views being        ascertained in the prescribed manner, assent.(4) If, in the case of any order proposed to be made 5 for a particular factory, the occupier or, in the case of an order for factories of a particular class or group or description, the majority of the occupiers of factories of that class or group or description, dispute the reason-ableness of the requirements in the proposed order or 10 any of them, the objection shall be referred for settle-ment to a referee selected in accordance with rules made under this section, but the Secretary of State may so refer any objection though not made by a majority of the occupiers if he thinks desirable.15 (5) The Secretary of State may make rules as to the time within which, and the manner in which, notice of objection to any proposed order may be made, and as to the selection of and the procedure before a referee and the cost of the proceedings before a referee (including20 the remuneration of the referee).(6) This section shall not apply to factories in which the only persons employed are members of the same family dwelling there.(7) The Secretary of State may by special order 25 extend the matters to which this section applies  to matters other than those mentioned in this section.(8) An order under this section may impose duties on employed persons in connection with the use of any facilities provided, and (in the case of tenement factories) 30 on owners.Part IV.Health, Safety; and Welfare (Special Provisions and Regulations).Special Provisions.35        42. (l) In every factory in which, in connection Removal of with any process carried on, there is given off any dust dust oror fume of an injurious or offensive character or any fumes-substantial quantity of dust of any kind, all practicable 127                           0 2
A.D. 1926.Prohibition of spitting.Meals in certain dangerous trades.Prohibition of use of white plios-phorus in manufacture of matches.Prohibition of employ-ment of female young persons in measures shall he taken to protect the workers against inhalation of the dust or fume, and to prevent its accumulating in any workroom, and in particular, where the nature of the process makes it practicable, exhaust appliances shall be provided and maintained, as near 5 as possible to the point of origin of the dust or fume, so as to prevent it entering the air of any workroom.(2) No stationary internal combustion engine shall he used in any workroom unless it is so enclosed as to prevent any iujurious fumes from the engine entering the 10 air of the room..43. Where a notice is exhibited by the occupier in any room in the factory that spitting on the floor or walls of the room is forbidden, any person who spits on the floor or walls of the room shall be guilty of an offence 15 and liable on summary conviction to a line not exceeding twenty shillings.44. (1) Where in any room in a factory lead, arsenic or other poisonous substance is so used as to give rise to dust or fumes, or any highly silieions dust is 20 given off in connexion with any process carried on, a person shall not be permitted to take a meal or to remain during the times allowed to him for meals in that room, and a suitable messroom shall be provided or other suitable provision made for enabling the persons employed in that 25 room to take their meals elsewhere in the factory.(2) Where it appears to the Secretary of State that, by reason of the nature of any process carried on in any class or description of factories or parts thereof to which the foregoing provisions of this section do not apply, the go taking of meals therein is injurious to health or other-wise undesirable, he may, if he thinks lit, by special order extend those provisions to such factories or parts of factories. \\     , r^gj45.  (1) No person shall use white phosphorus in the manufacture of matches.(2) For the purposes of this Part of this Act the expression &quot; white phosphorus&quot; means the substance usually known as white or yellow phosphorus.46. (1) Where in any part of a factory (a) the process as of melting, or of blowing glass 40 other than lamp blown glass : or(b) the process of annealing glass other than plate or sheet glass ; or35
1015(c) the evaporating of brine in open pans, or the stoving of salt, is carried on, a  female  young  person  shall  not  he employed in that part of the factory.(2) The Secretary of State may by special order extend this section to any process in which, on account of the special circumstances, it appears to him undesirable that female young persons should be employed.47. (1) A woman or young person employed in a factory shall not lift, carry or move any load so heavy as to be likely to cause injury to such woman or young person.(2) The Secretary of State may make special orders prescribing the maximum weight of the load which may be lifted, carried or moved by women or young persons of any age ; and any such orders may relate either to women or young persons generally or to women or young persons employed in any class or description of factories, or when engaged in any process.20        48. A woman or young person shall not be employed in any of the following operations : (a) work at a furnace where the reduction or treat-ment of zinc or lead ores is carried on :(5) the manipulation, treatment, or reduction of ashes containing lead, the desilverising of lead, or the melting of scrap lead or zinc :the manufacture of solder or alloys containing more than ten per cent, of lead :the manufacture of any oxide, carbonate, sul-phate, chromate, acetate, nitrate, or silicate of lead:(e) mixing or pasting in connexion with the manu-facture or repair of electric accumulators :(f) the cleaning of workrooms where any of the 35              processes aforesaid are carried on.49.  (1) A woman or young person shall not be employed  in  any process involving   the use of  lead compounds if the process is such that dust or fume from a lead compound is produced therein, or the persons 40 employed therein are. liable to be splashed with any lead2530(c) (d)A.D. 1926.certain pro-cesses.Prohibition of employ-Ei ent of women and young per-sons in lifting ex-sucessive weights.Prohibition of employ-ment of women and young persons in certain processes connected with lead manufac-ture.Regulations for employ-ment of women and young persons in
30Factories. [16 &amp;17 Geo. 5.jA.D. 1926.processes involving use of lead compounds.compound in the course of their employment, unless the following regulations are complied with as respects all women and young persons employed : (a) where dust or fume from a lead compound is produced in the process, provision must he made 5 for drawing the dust or fume away from the persons employed by means of an efficient exhaust draught so contrived as to operate on the dust or fume as nearly as may he at its point of origin : 10(b) the persons employed must undergo the pre-scribed medical examination at the prescribed intervals, and the prescribed record must be kept with respect to their health:(a) No food, drink, or tobacco shall be brought into 16 or consumed in any room in which the process is carried on, and no person shall be allowed to remain in any such room during meal times :(d) Adequate protective clothing in a clean condition shall be provided by the occupier and worn by 20 the persons employed :(e) Such suitable cloak-room, mess-room, and washing accommodation as may be prescribed shall be provided for the use of the persons employed :(./) The rooms in which the persons are employed, 25 and all tools and apparatus used by them, shall be kept in a clean condition.(2) It shall not be lawful to employ in any process involving the use of lead compounds any woman or young person who has been suspended after medical examination 30 from employment in any such process on the ground that continuance therein would involve special danger to health.(3) The method of ascertaining whether any corn-pound or mixture is a lead compound within the meaning 35 of this section shall he such as may be prescribed.(4) In this section &quot; prescribed &quot; means prescribed by an order made under this section, and the expression &quot; lead compound &quot; means any soluble compound of lead which is declared by order of the Secretary of State to be a lead 40 compound for the purposes of this section, and includes a mixture containing any such compound, but does not include an alloy containing lead.
a..u. 1926.Metal-grind-ing factories.(5) The provisions of subsections (3) (a), (4), and (5) of section forty-one of this Act as to welfare orders shall apply with respect to orders made under this section as they apply with respect to orders made under that section.5 50. Where the grinding of metal implements is carried on in a tenement factory, the following provisions shall apply: (1) Where drums are used hand rails must be fixed over the drums and kept in proper repair:10 (2) Where chains, hooks, or other fastenings are used to secure a grinder&apos;s horsing or seat, such chains, hooks, and fastenings shall be maintained in an efficient condition for such purpose:(3) In every room constructed or converted for use 15 as a grinding room after the passing of thisAct, there shall be provided a clear space of not less than six feet between any stone, or where splash boards are used between the splash board, and any wrall towards which the stone runs :20 (I) Except in pursuance of a special exemption granted by the Secretary of State, a grindstone shall not be run (a) in line with any other grindstone; or (6) in front of and in the direction of any 25 fireplace; and it shall he deemed to be so runif the distance between either edge of the stone and a parallel line passing through the centre of the fire is less than three feet; or (c) so that any part of the stone is within 30 six feet of a fire.51. (1) In every humid factory in which regula- Humid tions made under this Part of this Act, with respect to factories, humidity, are  not for the time being in  force, the following provisions shall apply : 35 (a) The humidity of the atmosphere shall not atany time be such that the difference between the readings of the dry and wet bulb thermo-meters is less than that indicated in the table of humidity set out in the Pirst Schedule to4,0 this Act, or such other table as may he substi-tuted therefor by the Secretary of State by special order:
Factories. [16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]( ) (i) There shall he provided and maintained in correct working order, in every room in which artificial humidity is produced, two hygro-meters, conforming to such conditions, as regards construction and maintenance, as may 5 be prescribed;(ii) One hygrometer shall be fixed in the centre and one at the side of each room, or in such other position as is directed or sanctioned by an inspector, so as to be plainly visible to the persons employed ;(iii) A copy of the table of humidity shall be kept hanging up near to each hygrometer ;(iv) The occupier or manager or other person authorised for the purpose shall read 15 the hygrometers twice daily, namely, between ten and eleven o&apos;clock in the morning and between three and four o&apos;clock in the afternoon on every day on which any persons are em-ployed in the room in the morning or afternoon 20 as the case may be, and shall record the readings on the prescribed form provided for each hygrometer ;(v) The forms on which the readings of each hygrometer are recorded shall be kept hung 25 up near the hygrometer, and when filled shallbe preserved at the factory for reference. The entries recorded in the form shall be prima facie evidence of the humidity of the atmo-sphere and temperature in the factory : 30Provided that where as respects any room notice has been given in the prescribed manner to the inspector for the district that it is intended that the humidity of the atmosphere should never be greater than will maintain a difference 35 of at least four degrees between the readings of the dry and wet bulb thermometers, the pro-visions of this and of the last preceding paragraph shall not apply as respects that room so long as at least that difference is maintained 40 and a copy of the said notice is kept posted in the room.(c) No water which is liable to cause injury to the health of the persons employed, or to yield
effluvia, shall he used for artificial humidifi-  A.D. 1926. cation, and for the purpose of this provision        any water which absorbs from acid solution of permanganate of potash in four hours at sixty 5 degrees more than half a grain of oxygen per gallon of water, shall be deemed to be liable to cause injury to the health of the persons employed.(2) The occupier of every humid factory shall, at 10 or before  the time at which artificial  production of humidity is commenced, give notice thereof in writing to the chief inspector.52. (1) In the industries or processes to which Underground this section applies work shall not he carried on in any rooms-15 underground room which is certified by the inspector for the district to be unsuitable for the purpose as regards construction, light, ventilation, or in any other respect.If the occupier feels aggrieved by any decision of an inspector under this section the matter shall, in 20 accordance with rules as to procedure and costs (including the remuneration of the referee) made by the Secretary of State, be referred to the decision of a person appointed (in default of agreement) by the judge of the county court having jurisdiction where the factory is situate.25 (2) The foregoing provision shall not apply to any underground room used only for the purpose of storage or for any other purpose which may be excepted by order of the Secretary of State.(3) In this section the expression &quot;underground 30 room &quot; means any room which or any part of which is so situate that half or more than half the whole height thereof, measured from the floor to the ceiling, is below the surface of the footway of the adjoining street or of the ground adjoining or nearest to the room.35 (4) Any certificate issued under this section may be withdrawn by the inspector for the district if such alterations are made as in his opinion to render the room suitable.(5) This section applies to the following industries 40 and processes, and processes incidental thereto namely : Cabinet-making; Glass bevelling; 127 E
A.D. 1926.Basement, bakehouses.Laundries.Letter-press printing; Laundry work ;Manufacture and repair of boots and shoes ; Making up of other wearing apparel; Upholstering ;Any process in the  preparation of  food human consumption.forThe Secretary of State may by special order extend the provisions of this section to industries and processes other than those specified in this subsection. 1053. (1) A basement bakehouse shall not be used as a bakehouse unless it was lawfully so used at the date of the passing of this Act.(2) For the purpose of this section &quot; basement bake-house &quot; means a bakehouse any baking room of which 15 is so situate that the surface of -the floor is more than three feet below the surface of the footway of the adjoining street, or of the ground adjoining or nearest to the room ; and &quot; baking room &quot; means any room used for baking, or for any process incidental thereto. 20(3) The provisions of this section shall be enforced by the district council, and the provisions of Part I. of this Act as to the power to act in default of the district council shall apply in the case of any default of the district council under this section. 2554. In every laundry (a) if mechanical power is used, a fan or other efficient means shall be provided, maintained, and used for regulating the temperature in every ironing room, and for carrying away 30 the steam in every washhouse ;(&amp;) all stoves for heating irons shall be sufficiently separated from any ironing room or ironing table, and gas irons emitting any noxious fumes shall not be used. 35Regulations.Power to 55. (1) Where the Secretary of State is satisfiedTionsim^&apos; ***** any manui&quot;acture&apos; machinery, plant, process, or de-safety and    scription of manual labour, used in factories is of suchheal th.a nature as to require special measures to be taken for 40
securing the safety or health of the persons employed in  A..D. 1926. connexion therewith, or any class of those persons he may, subject to the provisions of this Act, make such regula-tions as appear to him to be reasonably practicable and 5 to meet the necessity of the case.(2) Regulations so made may apply to all the factories in which the manufacture, machinery, plant, process, or - description of manual labour is used (whether existing at the time when the regulations are made or afterwards 10 established) or to any specified class or description of such factories. They may provide for the exemption of any specified class or description of factories either abso-lutely or subject to conditions.(3) Regulations so made may apply to tenement 15 factories  and   in such   case may impose   duties  on occupiers who do not employ any person.(4) No person shall be precluded by any agreement from doing, or be liable under any agreement to any penalty or forfeiture for doing, such acts as may be 20 necessary in order to comply with the provisions of any regulation so made.(5) Regulations so made may, among other things, (a) prohibit the employment of, or modify or limit the period of employment of, all persons or25 any class of persons in connection with anymanufacture,  machinery,  plant, process, or description of manual labour; or(b) prohibit, limit, or control  the  use  of any material or pi&apos;ocess; or30 (c) modify or extend any provisions of this Part ofthis Act with respect to any class or descrip-tion of factories;and may impose duties on owners, managers and workers as well as on occupiers.35 (6) The provisions contained in the Second Schedule to this Act shall apply to regulations made under this section.Supplementary Provisions.56. (1) &quot;Where by any regulations made under this Importation40 Act the use of any material or process is prohibited, of articles His Majesty may by Order  in  Council  prohibit the127 E 2 materials.
A.D. 1926. importation into Great Britain or Northern Ireland of        any articles in the manufacture of which the material or process has been employed.(2) It shall not be lawful to  import into Great Britain or Northern Ireland matches made with white 5 phosphorus.(3) Any article the importation of which is pro-hibited by or under this section shall be deemed to be included amongst the goods enumerated and described in the table of prohibitions and restrictions contained 10 in section forty-two of the Customs Consolidation Act, 1876.Sale and im-        57. (1) It shall not be lawful for any person to sell poi tation of   or t0 offer or expose for sale, or to have in his possession materials     ^or ^ne PurPoses of sale, any matches made with white 15 &amp;c. phosphorus, and, if any person contravenes the provisionsof this section, he shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, and shall forfeit any such matches in his possession, and any matches so forfeited shall be destroyed or otherwise dealt with as 20 the court may think fit.(2) Where under any regulations made under this Act the use of any material or process is prohibited, and the importation of any article in the manufacture of which the material or process has been employed is 25 prohibited, the Secretary of State may by order extend the provisions of this section to any such article.Power 58. (1) An inspector may at any time take for to take       analysis sufficient samples of any material in use or samp es.      mixed for use in the manufacture of matches. 30(2) An inspector may at any time take for analysis sufficient samples of any substance used in a factory which he suspects to be used in contravention of any regulation made under this Part of this Act, or to be injurious to the persons employed. 35(3) If the occupier of a factory refuses to allow an inspector to take samples in pursuance of this section, or to give him facilities for the purpose, he shall be deemed to have obstructed the inspector in the execution of his duties : 40Provided that the occupier may, at the time when a sample is taken under this section, and on providing the
necessary appliances, require the inspector to divide the   a.d. 1926. sample into two parts and to mark and seal and deliver to him one such part.(4.) A certificate purporting to be a certificate by the 5 Government Chemist at the Government laboratory as to the result of an analysis of a sample under this section shall in any proceedings under this Act be evidence of the matters stated therein, but either party may require the person by whom the analysis was made to be called as a 10 witness.(5) It shall not be lawful for any person, except in so far as is necessary for the purposes of a prosecution for an offence under this Act, to publish or disclose to any person the results of an analysis made under this 15 section. If any person acts in contravention of this provision he shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds.Part V.Notification and Investigation oe Accidents and 20 Industrial Diseases.59.-(1)  Where    any    accident    occurs    which Notification either__ 0^ acc&apos;dentsin factories.(a) causes loss of life to a person employed; or(b) disables any such person for more than three 25 days from earning full wages at the work atwhich he was employed,written notice of the accident, in the prescribed form and accompanied by the prescribed particulars, shall forthwith be sent to the inspector for the district.80 (2) Where any accident causing disablement is notified under this section, and after notification thereof results in the death of the person disabled, notice in writing of the death shall be sent to the inspector for the district as soon as the death comes to the knowledge35 of the occupier of the factory.(3) Where any accident to which this section applies occurs to a person employed and the occupier of the factory  is not  the   actual   employer   of   the   person killed or injured, the actual employer shall immediately 4)0 report the accident to the occupier, and in default shall
a.u. 1926.Power to extend to dangerous Occurrences provisions as 1.0 notice of accidents.Notification of industrial diseases.be guilty of an offence, aud liable to. a fine not exceeding five pounds.60.-(1) If the Secretary of State considers that, by reason of the risk of serious injury to persons em-ployed, it is expedient that notice should be given under 5 the foregoing section of this Act in every case of any special class of explosion, fire, collapse of buildings, accidents to machinery or plant, or other occurrences in a factory, the Secretary of State may by order extend the provisions of that section to any such class io of occurrences, whether death or disablement is caused or not.(2) The Secretary of State may by any such order allow the required notice of any occurrence to which the order relates, instead of being sent forthwith, to be 15 sent within the time limited by the order.61. (1) Every medical practitioner attending on or called in to visit a patient whom he believes to be suffering from lead, phosphorus, arsenical or mercurial poisoning, or anthrax, contracted in any factory, shall 20 (unless such a notice has been previously sent) send to the chief inspector of factories at the Home Office, London, a notice stating the name and full postal address of the patient and the disease from which, in the opinion of the medical practitioner, the patient is suffering, and the 25 name and address of the factory in which he is employed or in which the disease was contracted, and shall be entitled in respect of every notice sent in pursuance of this section to a fee of two shillings and sixpence, to be paid as part of the expenses incurred by the Secretary of 30 State in the execution of this Act.(2) If any medical practitioner, when required by this section to send a notice, fails forthwith to send the same, he shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding forty shillings. 35(3) Written notice of every case of lead, phos-phorus, or arsenical or mercurial poisoning, or anthrax, occurring in a factory shall forthwith be sent by the occupier in the prescribed form and accompanied by the prescribed particulars to the inspector for the district; 40 and the provisions of this Act with respect to the notify-cation of accidents shall apply to any such, case in like
16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]       Factoi^ies.manner as to any accident as is mentioned in those a.d. 1926. provisions.(4) The Secretary of State may, by special order, apply the provisions of this section to any other disease 5 contracted in a factory.62.- (1) Where  a  coroner holds an  inquest on inquest inthe body of any person whose death may have been case of deathcaused by any accident or disease of which notice is ^rh li^trialrequired to be given by this   Act, the coroner  shall jisease jn10 adjourn the inquest unless an inspector or some person factory, on behalf of the Secretary of State is present to watch the proceedings.(2) The coroner, at least four days before holding the adjourned inquest, shall send to the inspector for the 15 district notice in writing of the time and place of holding the adjourned inquest.(3) The coroner, before the adjournment, may take evidence to identify the body, and may order the inter-in ent thereof.20 (4) If the inquest relates to the death of not more than one person, and the coroner has sent to the inspector notice of the time and place of holding the inquest at such time as to reach the inspector not less than twenty-four hours before .the time of holding the2ii same, it shall not. be imperative on him to adjourn the inquest in pursuance of this section if the majority of the jury think it unnecessary so to adjourn.(5) An inspector shall be at liberty at any such inquest to examine any witness, subject nevertheless to 3U the power of the coroner to disallow any question which, in his opinion, is not relevant or is otherwise not a proper question.(6) Where evidence is given at an inquest at which an inspector is not present of any neglect as having 35 caused or contributed to the accident or disease, or of any defect in or about the factory appearing to the coroner or jury to require a remedy, the coroner shall send to the inspector for the district notice in writing of such neglect or defect.40 (7) Any person having a personal interest in or employed in or about or in the management of the factory  in or  about which  the  accident  or  disease
A.D. 1926. occurred or was contracted shall not be qualified to serve   on the jury empannelled on the inquest; and it shall be the duty of the constable or other officer not to summon any person disqualified under this provision, and it shall be the duty of the coroner not to allow any such person 5 to be sworn or to sit on the jury.(8) Any relative of any person in respect of whose death the inquest is being held, and the occupier of the factory in which the accident or disease occurred .or was contracted, and any person appointed by the order in 10 writing of the majority of the persons employed in the factory, and any person appointed in writing by any association of, persons to which the deceased at the time of his death belonged or to which any person employed in the factory belongs, or by any association of employers of which 15 the occupier is a member, shall be at liberty to attend and examine any witness either in person or by his counsel, solicitor, or agent, subject nevertheless to the power of the coroner to disallow any question which, in his opinion, is not relevant or is otherwise not a proper question. 20Power to 63. (1) Where it appears to the Secretary of Statedirect formal that a formal investigation of any accident or disease oTaccicfents11 occurring or contracted in a factory and its causes and circumstances is expedient, the Secretary of State may direct that such an investigation be held, and with respect 25 to any such investigation the following provisions shall have effect : (a) The Secretary of State may appoint a competent person to hold the investigation, and may appoint any person or persons possessing legal or special 30 knowledge to act as assessor or assessors in holding the investigation:(5) The person or persons so appointed (hereinafter called &quot; the court &quot;) shall hold the investigation in open court in such manner and under such 35 conditions as the court may think most effectual for ascertaining the causes and circumstances of the accident or disease, and enabling the court to make the report in this section mentioned :(c) The court shall have for the purposes of the 40 investigation all the powers of a court of summary jurisdiction when acting as a court in hearing informations for offences against this Act, and
all the powers of an inspector under this Act, A.D. 1926. and, in addition, power :   (i) to enter and inspect any place or building   the  entry  or inspection  whereof5 appears to the court requisite for the saidpurposes;(ii) by summons signed by the court to require the attendance of all such persons as it thinks fit to call before it and examine10 for the said purposes, and to require answersor returns to such inquiries as it thinks fit to make;(iii) to require the production of all books, papers,  and documents which  it considers15 important for the said purposes ;(iv) to administer an oath and require any person examined to make and sign a declaration of the truth of the statements made by him in his examination :20 (d) Persons attending as witnesses before the court shall he allowed such expenses as would he allowed to witnesses attending before a court of record; and in case of dispute as to the amount  to  be  allowed, the  same  shall   be25 referred by the court to a master of the Supreme *;Court, who, on request, signed by the court, shall ascertain and certify the proper amount of the expenses: (e) The court shall make a report to the Secretary30 of State stating the causes  of the accidentor disease and its circumstances, and adding any observations which the court thinks right to make :(/) The court may require the expenses incurred 35 in   and   about   an   investigation  under thissection (including the remuneration of any person appointed to act as assessor) to be paid in whole or part by any person sum-moned before it who appears to the court to 40 be responsible in any degree for the occurrence of the accident or disease, but any such expenses not required to he so paid shall be deemed to be part of the expenses of the Secretary of State in the execution of this Act:127 P
A.D. 1926. (g) Any person  who  without  reasonable  excuse(proof whereof shall lie on him) either fails, after having had the expenses (if any) to which he is entitled tendered to him, to comply with any summons or requisition of 5 the court, or prevents or impedes the court in the execution of its duty, shall he guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and in the case of a failure to comply with a requisition for making any return \q or producing any document to a further fine not exceeding ten pounds for every day on which such failure continues.(2) The Secretary of State may cause the report of the court to be made public at such time and in such 15 manner as he may think fit.D&quot;tyof 64. (1) It shall be the  duty of  the appointeddoctor to1    doctor to investigate and report-investigate (a) upon cases of death or injury caused by exposure and report to fumes or other noxious substances, or due 20 in certain to any other special cause specified in instruc-tions of the Secretary of  State as requiringinvestigation; and(b) upon any case of death or injury which the inspector for the district in pursuance of any 25 general or special instructions of the Secretaryof State may refer to him for that purpose; and(c) upon any case of disease of which notice is sent under this Act.(2) The appointed doctor, for the purpose of an 30 investigation under this  section, shall have the same powers as an inspector, and shall also have power to enter any room in a building to which the person killed, injured, or affected has been removed..     Tart VI.     ;  .  ^ ;     35Employment (Women, Young Persons and Children).Prohibition Prohibition of Employment of Children.of employ-men t of 65. (1) A child shall not be employed in a factory children.      or about the business of any factory. ^
(2) The provisions of this section shall be in addition a.D. 1926; to and not in derogation of any provisions contained        in the Education Act, 1918, the Education (Scotland) Act, 1918, or any other enactment prohibiting the employ -5 ment in a factory of persons who are under an obligation   -to attend school, and references in those provisions to the Factory and Workshop Acts, 1901 to 1911, shall be construed as references to this Act.Sours and Holidays.10 66. (1) Subject to the provisions of this Part of this General con-Act with respect to overtime and to the special exceptions ditions as to allowed under this Part of this Act, the period of em- h?urs of temf&apos;i . -in 1-1,1. ployment orpioyment and intervals tor meals and rest for every women anti woman or young person  employed in a factory shall young per-15 conform with the following conditions, namely :  sons-(a) the total hours worked, exclusive of intervals allowed for meals and rest, shall not exceed ten in any day or forty-eight in any week; lb) the period of employment shall not exceed twelve 20 hours in any day and shall not begin earlier than six o&apos;clock in the morning and shall not end later than eight o&apos;clock in the evening, or, on Saturday, two o&apos;clock in the afternoon ; (c) a woman or young person shall not be employed 25 continuously for a spell of more than four anda half hours without an interval of at least half an hour for a meal:Provided that where a rest interval of not le6s than fifteen minutes is allowed in the course of 30 a spell, the spell may be increased to five hours;(c?) a woman or young person shall not be employedduring any interval allowed for meals or rest; (e) the period of employment and intervals allowed for meals and rest shall be the same for all 35 women and young persons employed  in thefactory.(2) For the purposes of this Part of this Act (a) &quot; period of employment&quot; means the period on any day between the hour at which the 40 employment first commences and the hour atwhich the employment finally ends; and12V E 2
4 k . Factories.        [16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1926. (b) employment shall be deemed to he continuous  unless interrupted by an interval of at leasthalf an hour.(3) The foregoing  provisions  shall&apos; not  apply  to any person holding a responsible position of management, 5 and not usually employed in manual labour.67.    Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing provisionsof this Part of this Act the period of employment for women and young persons may be extended in any factory by means of overtime subject to the following conditions:-(a) overtime shall not be worked for more than one hundred hours in any period of twelve months or for more than six hours in any week;(b) the total hours worked, including the overtime, shall not exceed eleven on any day;    and(c) before employing women or young persons on overtimeon any day, the occupier of the factory shall reportto the inspector for the district and enter in theprescribed register such particulars of the employment as may be prescribed, and the occupier of any factory at which women or young persons are employed overtimeshall cause a notice containing the prescribedparticulars to be kept posted in the factory duringsuch time as may be prescribed.(2) Different periods of employment and different intervals may be fixed for different days of the week.
Factories.[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1926. (b) employment shall be deemed to be continuous  unless interrupted by an interval of at leasthalf an hour.(3) The foregoing  provisions  shall not  apply to any person holding a responsible position of management, 5 and not usually employed in manual labour.Overtime 67. (1) Notwithstanding anything in the foregoingemployment provisions of this Part of this Act the period of employ-of women.    ment for women and youug persons may be extended inany factory by means of overtime subject to the following conditions: (a) overtime shall not be allowed on more than one hundred days in any peiiod of twelve months or on more than six days in any week ; and(b) the total hours worked, including the overtime, 15shall not exceed eleven on any day ; and(c) before employing women or young persons onovertime, the occupier of the factory shall serve on the inspector for the district a notice of his intention to do so, and shall enter in the pre- 20 scribed register such particulars of the employ-ment as may be prescribed; and the occupier of any factory at which women or young persons are employed overtime shall cause a notice to be kept posted in the factory during such time as 25 may be prescribed.(2) Every notice required by this section to be served or posted shall contain such particulars of the employ-ment as may he prescribed.Notice fix- 68. (1) The occupier shall fix within the limits 30ing hours of allowed by this Part of this Act, and shall specify in a employment. nofcice which shall be posted in the factory (a) the period of employment for the women and young persons employed in the factory;(6) the intervals allowed for meals or rest to such 35 women and young persons ;and, subject to the special exceptions allowed under this Part of this Act, no woman or young person shall be employed otherwise than in accordance with the notice except by way of overtime. 40(2) Different periods of employment and different intervals may be fixed for different days of the week.
(3) A change in the said periods or intervals shall A.D. 1926. not he made until the occupier has served on the inspector b5fBfor the district, and posted in the factory, notice of his intention to make the change, and shall not be made 5   oftener than once in three months, unless for special cause allowed in writing by the inspector.(4) &quot;Where an inspector, by notice in writing, names a public clock, or some other clock open to public view, for the purpose, the period of employment and the intervals 10 allowed for meals or rest in that factory shall be regulated by that clock.69. (1) A woman or young person shall not, except Restriction during the period of employment, he employed in the oE employ-business of the factory outside the factory on any day ^uToutsideJ.5 during which the woman or young person is employed in factory on6 the factory both before and after the dinner hour. same day.(2) Eor the purposes of this section a woman or young person to or for whom any work is given out or who takes out any work to be done by him or her20 outside a factory, shall be deemed to be employed outside the factory on the day on which the work is so given or taken out.70. Subject to the special exceptions allowed under this Part of this Act, a woman or young person shall not 25 during any part of the intervals allowed for meals he allowed to remain in a room in which a process is then, being carried on.71. A woman or young person shall not (subject to the special exceptions allowed under this Part of this Act) 30 be employed on Sunday in a factory or about the business of a factory.72. (1) Subject to the special exceptions allowed under this Part of this Act, the occupier of a factory shall allow in each year to every woman and young person 35 employed in the factory the following holidays :  In England and Wales the whole of Christmas Day, Good Friday, and every bank holiday, unless the occupier not less than two weeks before any one of those days affixes 40 in the  factory a notice that he intends to substitute for that day some other day as a whole holiday;Prohibition of use of certain rooms during meal times.Prohibition of Sunday employment.Annual holidays.
A.D. 1926.Power to suspend certain pro-visions of Part VI. in emergency.In Scotland (a) Two days, not less than three months apart, to he fixed by the town council of any burgh or where there is no such council, fixed by the occupier; and 5(b) Pour whole holidays fixed by the occupier.(2) At least half of the said whole holidays shall he allowed between the fifteenth day of March and the first day of October in every year.(3) A notice of every whole holiday shall be posted 10 in the factory during not less than four weeks before the holiday and unless the notice has been so posted, a whole holiday allowed on that day shall not he deemed to be a wdiole holiday allowed in compliance with this section:Provided that no such notice shall be required in 15 England or Wales if the whole holiday is Christmas Day or Good Priday or a bank holiday.(4) A woman or young person shall not be employed in the factory or about the business of the factory on a whole holiday fixed by or in pursuance of this section.      2073. The Secretary of State may, in the event of accident, or breakdown of machinery or plant, or other unforeseen emergency, make an order suspending any of the provisions of this Part of this Act as to hours and holidays for such period as may be specified in the order, 25 hut so far only as may be necessary to avoid serious interference with the ordinary working of the factory.Special Exceptions.Exceptions 74.  (l) The Secretary of State may, on the jointas to employ- application of the occupier of any factory or the occupiers ho womeifand   ot an^ c^ass or description of factories, and the majority youno    L    0* the workers employed in the factory or class or des-persons in    description of factories, make an order authorising the employ-shifts, ment of women and young persons of the age of sixteenyears and upwards in that factory or class or description 35 of factory at any time between the hours of six in the morning and ten in the evening on any weekday except Saturday, and between the liours of six in the morning and two in the afternoon on Saturday, in shifts, averaging for each shift not more than eight hours per day. aq
(2) Every order made under this section shall he - A.D. 1926. . published in the London Gazette.  (3) Any order made under this section shall continue in force for a period of five ye irs unless revoked by the 5 Secretary of State upon the ground that the conditions at the factory or class or description of factories to which the order relates have been substantially changed, or that there has been a failure to comply with the conditions upon which the order was made, or that in his opinion 10 abuses have arisen in connection with employment per-mitted by the order.75. (1) Male young persons who have attained the Exceptions age of sixteen may be employed on a system of shifts as t0 male outside the hours specified in this Part of this Act for ^&quot;o^1&quot;&quot;15 the commencement and end of the period of employment, s-,xteen in the industries or processes and subject to the conditions employed in hereinafter -specified, on work which by reason of the shifts, nature of the industry or process requires to be carried on continuously day and night, and any such shift may20 end on Sunday morning not later than six or begin on Sunday evening not earlier than ten.(2) The industries and processes to which this section applies are : the smelting of iron ore ;25 the manufacture of wrought iron, steel or tin-plate ;processes in which reverberatory or regenerative furnaces are used in connection with smelting of ores, metal rolling, forges, manufacture of metal tubes or rods, or such other classes of work as30 may be specified by order of the Secretary ofState, and are necessarily kept in operation day and night in order to avoid waste of material and fuel;the galvanising of sheet metal or wire (except the 35 pickling process) ;the manufacture of glass ; the manufacture of paper.(3) The conditions above referred to are as follows :---(a) the number of shifts worked by any such 40 person shall not exceed six, or, as respectspersons employed in the smelting of iron ore, seven in any week;
A.P. 1926. (S) a period of not less than sixteen hours shallelapse between the end of one shift and the beginning of the next ;&apos;c) no male young person shall be employed between twelve midnight and six o&apos;clock in the morning 5 in two consecutive weeks.(4) Nothing in this Act shall prevent the employ-ment of male young persons between the ages of fourteen and sixteen in two-day shifts in those industries in which they could be lawfully so employed at the date of the 10 commencement of this Act under section fifty-four and fifty-five of the Factory and Workshop Act, 1901, and the Secretary of State may, by order, direct that such con-ditions as he may consider necessary for the purpose of safeguarding the welfare and interests of the persons 1&amp; employed shall apply to such employment.Exceptions ij 76,, The provisions of this Part of this Act which as to simul- reqUire that all the women and young persons employed hourTfm- in a factory shall have the intervals allowed for meals or meals and    rest at the same hour of the day shall not apply  20rest- (a) to persons employed in any process on which byreason of the nature thereof work requires to becarried on continuously ; or(b) to different sets of persons employed on differentprocesses :Provided that all persons employed in the same set have their intervals for meals and rest at the same time, and that, if the inspector for the district so require, a list of women or young persons employed in the factory, or in 30 any set in the factory, and the times allowed for meals or rest for each set shall be affixed in the factory;(c) where a mess-room or canteen is provided and maintained by the occupier to the satisfaction of 35 the inspector for the district and it is necessary to divide the persons employed into sets for the purpose of taking meals therein ; or(d) where the Secretary of State on being satisfiedas respects any class or description of factories 40 or parts of factories that it is necessary by reason of any special circumstances to except factories25
116 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.JFactories.49of such class or description or such parts thereof ^ d ]y26-from those provisions, and that the exception        can he made without injury to the health of the women and young persons  affected thereby, 5 makes a special order excepting the same.- 77. The provisions of this Part of this Act with Exceptions respect to the prohibition of employment during any as to em-interval allowed for meals or rest shall not apply to any d&apos;^.(Il^ent male young persons employed in the manufacture of intervals. 10 wrought iron, steel or tinplate, or in the manufacture of paper or in the melting, blowing or annealing of glass.78. The provisions of this Part of this Act with Exceptions respect to the prohibition of the use of certain rooms &quot;s to use during meal times shall not apply  of cert*m.53 rooms during15        (a) where persons are employed in any process on meal times, which by reason of the nature thereof work requires to be carried on continuously ; or(o) where different sets of persons are employed on different  processes   and   have   different  meal20 intervals ; or(c) where the Secretary of State on being satisfied as respects any class or description of factories or parts of factories that it is necessary by reason of any special circumstances to except2g factories of such class or description or suchparts thereof from those provisions and that the exception can be made without injury to the health of the women and young persons affected thereby, makes a special order excepting the30 same.79. (1) Where it is proved to the satisfaction of Exception the Secretary of State that the customs or exigencies of as to the trade carried on in any class or description of factories, Saturday, either generally or in any particular locality, require some35 other day in the week to be substituted for Saturday as the short day, he may, by special order, grant to factories of that class or description a special exception, authorising the occupier of every such factory to suh-stitute some other day for Saturday, and in that case this40 Part of this Act shall apply in the factory as if the substituted day were Saturday, and Saturday were an ordinary work day.127 G
A AX 1926.Exception as to Sundays and Satnr-days in J wish factories.Exceptions as to fish and fruit preserving.Exceptions as to cream -erics.(2) In the case of newspaper printing offices, the Secretary of State may by such order authorise the sub-stitution of some other day for Saturday in respect of some of the young persons therein employed, and in the case of factories the work in which by reason of the 5 nature thereof requires to be carried on on six full working days in the week, the Secretary of State may by such order authorise the substitution of some other day for Saturday in respect of some of the women or young persons therein employed. 1080. Where the occupier of a factory is a person of the Jewish religion, a woman or young person of the Jewish religion may he employed on Sunday, subject to the condition that the factory must be closed on Saturday and must not be open for traffic on Sunday. 15Where the occupier avails himself of this exception, this Part of this Act shall, as respects women and young persons of the Jewish religion, apply to the factory in like manner as if in the provisions thereof respecting Sunday the word Saturday were substituted for Sunday, 20 and in the provisions thereof respecting Saturday the word Sunday, or, if the occupier so elects, the word Priday, were substituted for Saturday.81. (1) The provisions of this Part of this Act prescribing the general conditions as to hours of employ- 25 ment and those relating to annual holidays shall not apply to women and  young  persons employed  in processes connected with (a) the preserving and curing of fish; or(6) the cleaning and preparing of fruit during the 30 months of June, July, August, and September,where such processes require to be carried out immediately on the arrival of the goods at the factory in order to prevent them from being spoiled.(2) The exceptions to which this section applies shall 35 be subject to such conditions as the Secretary of State may by special order prescribe.82. In the case of creameries or other factories in which milk is treated, or in which any food product is manufactured from milk, the Secretary of State may, if 40 and so far as it appears to him to be necessary for the
preservation of the milk or any product thereof, by special  ajd. 1926. order vary the conditions as to hours oil employment        and holidays applicable to women and young persons and allow their employment on Sundays : 5       Provided that the hours worked in any week by any such women or young person shall not exceed sixty.83. The period of employment in the case of a male Exception young person who has attained the age of sixteen years relating to may begin at five o&apos;clock in the morning in that part of paring&quot;&quot;8 10 a bakehouse in which the process of bread baking is employed in carried on. bakehouses.84. Where it appears to  the Secretary of State Provision for that the adoption of any special provision is required for wommMj&quot; the protection of the health of women or young persons y^jung per-15 employed in pursuance of a special exception under this p^oyadunder Part of this Act, he may by special order direct that exceptions, the adoption of the provision shall be a condition of such employment.85. (1) An occupier of a factory, not less than Notices, 20 seven days before he avails himself of any special ex- registers, &amp;c. ception under this Part of this Act, shall serve on the relat.inS t0SPCCltllinspector for the district, and affix in his factory, notice exceptions, in the prescribed form of his intention so to avail himself, and whilst he so avails himself shall keep the notice so 25 affixed.(2) Before the service of the notice on the inspector shall not be deemed to apply to the factory, and after the service of the notice on the inspector it shall not be com-petent in any proceeding under this Act for the occupier 30 to prove that the exception does not apply to his factory, unless before the event in respect of which the pro-ceedings are taken he had previously served on the inspector for the district notice that he no longer intended to avail himself of the exception.35 (3) The notice so served and affixed must specify the hours for the beginning and end of the period of employment, and the intervals to be allowed for meals or rest to every woman and young person, where they differ from the ordinary hours or intervals.40 (4) An occupier of a factory shall enter in the pre-scribed register and report to the inspector for the district127 G 2
A.D. 1926. the prescribed particulars respecting the employment of a woman or young person in pursuance of a special exception.Certificate of fitness for employment of young persons under the age of sixteen years.Certificate of fitness for Employment of Young persons under the age of Sixteen Years. 586. (1) Subject to the provisions of this section, a young person under the age of sixteen years taken into any employment in a factory shall not remain in that employment after the prescribed period unless within that period he has been examined by the appointed 10 doctor and certified by him to be fit for that employment.(2) The certificate by the appointed doctor may be given (a) in respect of employment (i) in a particular factory ; 15(ii) in any group, class, or description of factories;(iii) in a  particular  process or class or description of work ; and(b) upon condition that the person concerned shall 20 not be employed in the employment unless and until any physical defects specified in the certificate have been remedied, or that he shallbe subject to be re-examined after an interval specified in the certificate, or on both those 25 conditions.(3) Where a certificate under this section in respect of any young person is granted by the appointed doctor upon any such condition as aforesaid, the young person shall not be employed except after compliance with the 30 condition.(4) The Secretary of State may, after consultation with the Minister of Health, by order transfer to the local authority the duty of arranging for the medical examination and certification of young persons under the 35 age of sixteen years under this section.(5) The Secretary of State  may  make  rules  for prescribing (a) the manner in which and the place at which examinations under this section shall be con- 40 ducted:
(b) the form of certificates under this section ; A.D. 1926.(c) the facilities to he  afforded  by  occupiers  of factories for the purpose of examinations under this section;5 (d) Any other matter which the Secretary of State may consider desirable for the purpose of giving effect to this section.(6) It shall be the duty of every local education authority under the Education Act, 1921, to arrange for10 the production to an appointed doctor for his confidential information of so much of the school medical record of a young person under the age of sixteen years as may be necessary to enable him to carry out effectively the examination under this section, and  the  Minister  of15 Health may, after consultation with the Secretary of State, make rules for the purpose of securing the observance of the provisions of this subsection or may arrange that the Board of Education, after such consultation as afore-said, may make such rules on his behalf.20 (7) Eor the purposes of this Act the expression &quot; local authority &quot; means as respects a county the council of the county, and as respects a county borough the council of the borough.(8) The Secretary of State may by order exempt 25 from the operation of this section any factory or class or description of factories in wrhich mechanical power is not used.87. Where an inspector is  of  opinion   that the Power of employment of any young person under the age of inspector to30 sixteen years in a factory or in any particular process ^&quot;^f t ^ or  kind  of  work  in a factory is prejudicial to his capacity for health or the health of other persons, he may serve work, written notice thereof on the occupier of the factory requiring that the employment of that young person35 in the factory or in the process or kind of work, as the. case may he, he discontinued after the period named, therein, not being less than one nor more than seven days after the service of the notice, and the occupier shall not continue after the period named in the notice40 to employ that young person (notwithstanding that a certificate of fitness has been previously obtained for the young person), unless the appointed doctor has, after the
A.D. 1926.  service of  the notice, personally examined the young        person, and certified that he is fit for employment in the factory or in the process or kind of work, as the case may he.Saving. 88. The provisions of this Part of this Act shall he 5in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of the Employment of Women, Young Persons and Children Act, 1920, and of any other enactments relating to the employment of women, young persons and children.Part VII. 10Special Applications and Extensions.Premises in respect of which Owner is liable. Tenement 89. (1) The owner (whether or not he is one of factories.      j,]ie occupiers) of a tenement factory shall, instead ofthe occupier, he liable for the observance, and punishable 15 for non-observance, of the following provisions of this Act, namely : (i) The provisions in Part I. with respect to over-crowding, ventilation (so far as compliance therewith necessitates the supply of mechanical 20 means), the drainage of floors, sanitary con-conveniences, and (except in the case of any room which is occupied by not more than one tenant) cleanliness, temperature and lighting ;(ii) The provisions in Part II. except those respecting 25safe means of access, precautions in places where dangerous fumes accumulate, cleaning of machinery by Avomen and young persons, and those respecting seif -acting machines in so far as they relate to persons employed in a 30 factory or to machines supplied by the occupier thereof: Provided that the occupier shall be jointly responsible with the owner for the observance of the provisions with respect to the maintenance and use of guards and other 35 safety appliances;(iii) The provisions in Part III. with respect tosupply of drinking water and washing facili-ties so far as compliance therewith necessitates any structural provision; 40(iv) The  provisions of  Part IV. with respect  tometal grinding factories, and (in the case of any
room which is occupied by more than one tenant)  A.D. 1926. removal of dust or fumes : Provided that in the        case of metal grinding factories it shall be the duty of the occupier to see that the horsing 5 chains,   hooks and   fastenings for  grinders&apos;horsings or seats are kept in efficient  con-difcion;(v) The provisions of Part VI. as to notices fixing the hours of employment; and 10 (vi) The provisions of Part X. as to affixing anabstract and notices;and for the purpose of the foregoing provisions the whole of a tenement factory shall be deemed to be onefactory :15 Provided that any occupier may affix in his own tenement the notice with respect to the period of em-ployment, and times for meals, and thereupon that notice shall, with respect to persons employed by that occupier, have effect in substitution for the corresponding notice20 affixed by the owner.(2) The provisions of Part II. of this Act conferring power to make orders as to unhealthy or dangerous factories shall apply in the case of a tenement factory as if the owner were substituted for the occupier.25        90. Where a part of a building is let off as a Promises separate factory, the provisions of Part I. of this Act where part with respect to cleanliness and lighting, and the pro- j*f ,^ul]^f visions of Part II, of this Act with respect to maintenance factory. of passages and stairs, shall apply to all passages and stairs30 serving the part so let off, and the owner of the building shall, instead of the occupier, be liable for the observance of the said provisions and of the provisions of this Act relating to the provision and maintenance of sufficient sanitary accommodation, to steam boilers, to means of35 escape and (so far as they relate to matters within the control of the owner) safety provisions in case of fire, to hoists and lifts, and to the cleanliness of the sanitary accommodation when used in common by several tenants.Institutions.40        91. (1) Where in any premises forming part of an Institutions, institution carried on for charitable or reformatory pur-poses, not being premises subject to inspection by or
A.D. 1926. under the authority of any Government department, any   manual lahour is exercised in or incidentally to the making, altering, repairing, ornamenting, finishing, washing, cleaning, or adapting for sale, of articles not intended for the use of the institution, the provisions 5 of this Act shall, subject as hereinafter provided, apply to those premises notwithstanding that the work carried on therein is not carried on by way of trade or for the purpose of gain, or that the persons working therein are not employed under a contract of service or appren- if; apprenticeship.(2) If in any institution to which this section applies the persons having the control of the institution (herein-after referred to as the managers) satisfy the Secretary of State that the only persons wrorking therein are persons 15 who are inmates of and supported by the institution, or persons engaged in the supervision of the work or the management of machinery, and that such work as aforesaid is carried on in good faith for the purposes of the support, education, training, or reformation of persons 20 engaged in it, the Secretary of State may by order direct that so long as the order is in force this Act shall apply to the institution subject to the following modifications: (a) The managers may submit for the approval 25 of the Secretary of State a scheme for the regulation of the hours of employment, intervals for meals, and holidays of the inmates, and if the Secretary of State is satisfied that the pro-visions of the scheme are not less favourable 30 than the corresponding provisions of this Act, the Secretary of State may approve the scheme, and upon the scheme being so approved this Act shall, until the approval is revoked, applyas if the provisions of the scheme  were sub- 35 stituted for the corresponding provisions of this Act:(b) The medical officer of the institution (if any) may, on the application of the managers, be appointed to be the appointed doctor for the in- 40 stitution :(c) The provisions of Part X. of this Act as to theaffixing of an abstract and notices shall not apply,  but  amongst the particulars required
to be shown in the general register there shall A.D. 1020 be included the prescribed particulars of the        scheme, or where no scheme is in force the pre-scribed particular^ as to hours of employment, 5 intervals for meals, and holidays,   and othermatters dealt with in this Act:(d) In the case of premises forming part of an institution carried on for reformatory purposes, if the managers of the institution give notice to10 the chief inspector to that effect, an inspector shallnot, without the consent of the managers or of the person having charge of the institution under the managers, examine an inmate of the institution save in the presence of one of the15 managers or of such person as aforesaid: Pro-vided that the Secretary of State, on being satisfied that there is reason to believe that a contravention of this Act is taking place in any such institution, may suspend the operation of20 this provision as respects that institution to such extent as he may consider necessary :(e) The managers shall not later than the fifteenth day of January in each year send to the Secretary of State a correct return in the prescribed form,25 specifying the names of the managers and thename of the person (if any) having charge of the institution under the managers, and such particulars as to the number, age, sex, and employment of the inmates and other personsSO employed in the work carried on in the insti-tution as may be prescribed, and shall, if any requirement of this paragraph is not complied with, be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding five pounds.35 Docks, Wharves, Quays, Warehouses and Ships.92. (1) The following provisions of this Act shall Docks, &amp;c. apply to every dock, wharf or quay (including any line or siding which is used in connexion therewith and is not part of a railway) and every warehouse, as if they 40 were factories ; and as if the person having the actual use or occupation thereof or of any premises within the 127 H
58Factories. [16 &amp; 11 Gbo. 5.]A.D. 1926. same or forming part thereof, were the occupier of a        factory : (a) the provisions of Part I., with respect to sanitary conveniences;(b) The provisions of Part II., with respect to steam 5 boilers (including the provisions as to exemp-tions as to steam boilers), and to the power to make orders in cases of special danger and to make orders as to dangerous conditions and practices; 10(a) the provisions of Part III., with respect to welfare orders;(d) the provisions of Part IV., with respect to regulations for safety and health;(e) Part V. ; 15(/) the provisions of Part IX., with respect to weights and measures used in ascertaining wages ;(g) the provisions of Part X., with respect to theaffixing of an abstract, general registers, and 20 duties of persons employed;(h) the provisions of Part XI., with respect to powers and duties of inspectors;(i) Part XII.(2) The provisions of Part II. of this Act with respect 25 to prime movers, transmission and other machinery (other than the provisions relating to new machines) main-tenance of fencing, cleaning of machinery by women and young persons, hoists and lifts, chains, ropes and cranes, and maintenance of passages and stairs, shall apply to 30 every warehouse as if it were a. factory and as if the person having the actual use or occupation thereof were the occupier of a factory.(3) Subject as hereinafter in this subsection provided provisions of this Act mentioned in paragraphs (6), 35 (d), (e), (7i) and (i) of the foregoing subsection shall apply in relation to all machinery and plant used in the loading and unloading or coaling of any ship in any dock, harbour or canal, as if such machinery or plant were machinery or plant in a factory, and as if the 40 person using the machinery or plant were the occupier of a factory.    For the purposes of this  provision the
[16 So 17 Geo. 5.JFactories.59expression &quot; plant&quot; includes any gangway or ladder  A.D. 1926. used by any person employed to load or unload or coal a ship :Provided that the provisions of this Act mentioned 5 in the said paragraph (b) shall not apply in relation to any machinery or plant which is on board a ship and is the property of the ship owner.93. The following provisions of the Act shall apply Ships, to any work, not being work done by the master or crew10 of a ship, of constructing, reconstructing, repairing, refitting, finishing or breaking up of a ship or in scaling, scurfing or cleaning boilers or cleaning bilges, or other-wise preparing for sea. a ship in a harbour or wet dock; and for the purpose of such provisions the ship shall be15 deemed to be a factory, and any person undertaking such work, shall be deemed to be the occupier of a factory: (a) the  provisions of  Part IIL, with respect to welfare orders;2()        (6) the  provisions  of   Part IV., with respect  to regulations for safety and health;(c) Part V.;(d) the provisions of   Part XL, with respect  topowers and duties of inspectors; 25       (e) Part XII.Building and Engineering Works.94.--(1) The following provisions of this Act shall Building and apply to building operations undertaken by way of trade engineering or business, and to any line or siding which is used in works-30 connexion therewith and is not part of a railway, subject to the modifications hereinafter contained : (a) the provisions of Part L, with respect to sanitary conveniences;(b) the  provisions  of Part II.,   with   i-espect  to 35 machinery (other than the provisions relating to new machinery), maintenance of fencing, chains, ropes and cranes, steam boilers (including the provisions as to exceptions as to steam boilers) and to the power to make orders as to 40 dangerous conditions and practices ;127 H 2
A.D. 1926. (c) the provisions of Part III., with respect to first  aid and welfare orders ;(d) the provisions of  Part IV.,  with respect  to regulations for safety and health ; 0) Part V.; 5(/) the provisions of Part X., with respect to affixing of an abstract, general registers and duties of persons employed ;(g) the provisions of Part XL, with respect to powers and duties of inspectors ; 10(h) Part XII.(2) The following provisions of this Act shall apply to engineering works undertaken hy way of trade or business, and to any line or siding which is used in connexion therewith and is not part of a railway, subject 15 to the modifications hereinafter contained: (a) the provisions of Part I., with respect to sanitary conveniences;(6) the provisions of Part II., with respect to steam boilers (including the provisions as to exemp- 20 tions as to steam boilers), and to the power to make orders as to dangerous conditions ;(c) the provisions of Part III., with respect to firstaid and welfare orders ;(d) the provisions of Part IV., with respect to regu- 25 lations for safety and health ;(e) Part V.;(/) the provisions of Part XL, with respect to powers and duties of inspectors;(g) Part XII. 30(3) The provisions of this Act in their application to building operations and engineering works shall have effect as if references to any place where the operations or works are carried on were substituted for references to factories, and references to the persons undertaking by 35 way of their trade or business such operations and works were substituted for references to the occupier of a factory, and with such other necessary adaptations as may be prescribed :Provided that such of the provisions of this Act as 4,0 require general registers to he kept and copies of the
prescribed abstract and regulations to be kept posted A.D. 1926. up on tbe premises shall be deemed to be complied with   if the general register is kept at an office of the person undertaking the operations or works, and copies of the abstract and regulations are kept posted up at each office, yard, or shop of the person undertaking the operations or works at which persons employed by him on the operations or works attend, and in a position where they can easily be read by such persons.10   Lead Processes carried on in Places other than Factories.95. The  provisions of  this Act which  relate to the regulation of the employment of women and young persons in processes   involving the use of lead corn-pounds shall apply where women and young persons are 15 employed in any place other than a factory, and(a) if any person employs a woman or young person in contravention of any of those provisions in any such place, he shall be liable on summary conviction  to  a  fine not  exceeding twenty20 pounds;(6) an inspector shall, in relation to any such place, have the same powers and duties as if the place in which the woman or young person was employed were a factory;25 (c) the provisions of tins Act which require notifica-tion to be sent to the chief inspector, or to the inspector for a district, of lead poisoning con-tracted in factories shall apply to lead poisoning contracted by a woman or young person employed30 in any process involving the use of lead corn-pounds carried on in any place other than a factory.Employment of women and young persons in processes in-volving the use of lead carried on in places other than factory.Part VIII. Home Work.35        96. (1) In the case of persons employed in such Lists of out-classes of work as may from time to time be specified by workers to special order of the Secretary of State, the occupier of be &apos;ce.pt in every factory and every contractor employed by any trades, such occupier in the business of the factory shall 40        (a) keep in the prescribed form and manner, and with the prescribed particulars, lists showing
A.D. 1926.Employment of peraon in nn whole-some pre-mises.the names and addresses of all persons (herein-after referred to as outworkers) directly employed by him, either as workmen or as contractors, in the business of the factory, outside the factory, and of the places where 5 they are employed; and(b) send to an inspector such copies of or extracts from those lists as the inspector may from time to time require; and(c) send during the month of February and the 10month of August in each year copies of those lists, showing all outworkers so employed by him during the preceding six months, to the district council. (2) Every  district  council   shall  cause  the  lists 15 received in pursuance of this section to be examined, and shall furnish the name and place of employment of every outworker included in any such list whose place of employment is outside its district to the council in whose district his place of employment is. 20(3) The lists kept by the occupier or contractor shall be open to inspection by any inspector, and by any officer duly authorised by the district council, and the copies sent to the council and the particulars furnished by one council to another shall be open to inspection by 25 any inspector or officer of any Government Department.(4) This section shall apply to any place from which any work is given out (wh.e th.er the materials for the work are supplied by the occupier or not), and to the occupier of that place, and to every contractor employed 30 by the occupier in connexion with the said work, as if that place were a factory.(5) In the event of a contravention of this section by the occupier of a factory or place, or by a contractor, the occupier or contractor shall be guilty of a,n offence 35 and liable to a fine not exceeding ten pounds.97.--(1) Where work in respect of which this section applies is carried on for the purpose of or in connexion with the business of a factory in any place which is in the opinion of the district council injurious or dangerous 40 to the health of the persons employed therein, the district council may give notice in writing to the occupier of the factory or to any contractor employed by him that the
place is so injurious or dangerous, and if the occupier A.D. 1926. or contractor after the expiration of one week from the   receipt of such notice gives out work to be done in that place he shall, tmless it is proved to the satisfaction of 5 the court dealing with the case that the place is not in fact so injurious or dangerous, be guilty of an offence and liable to a line not exceeding twenty pounds.(2) For the purpose of this section any place from which work is given out shall be deemed to be a factory.10 (3) This section shall apply in respect of such classes of work as may be specified in a special order made by the Secretary of State.Part IX.Particulars of Piece Work and Wages.15       98. (1) Subject   to   the   provisions  hereinafter Particulars contained  respecting weavers  in the worsted woollen of worlc ami and cotton trades, every person paid by the piece, who Z^iTto&apos; ^ is employed in a factory or in the business of a factory piece-outside the factory, whether directly by the occupier workers:.2() or by any contractor employed by him hi connexion with the factory, shall, in order to enable him to compute the total amount of wages payable to him in respect of his work, be furnished with particulars of his work and of the rate of wages applicable thereto, as follows :-25 (a) The occupier or contractor shall furnish him with particulars of the rate of wages applicable to his work either (i) by  furnishing   him   with  a  written statement of such particulars at the time when30 the wrork is given out to him ; or(ii) in the case of persons employed in a factory, by exhibiting such particulars on a placard in the room where the work is done, or, where a placard is not practicable, in a book35 or books which shall he kept in such placeconvenient for the persons employed as the inspector for the district may direct: (b) In the case of a worker employed in a factory the occupier shall exhibit on a placard in the 40 room where the work is done the basis and
A.D. 1926. conditions, if any, according to which the ratesof wages are regulated :(e) The occupier or contractor shall furnish in writing to the person employed such particulars of the work as affect the amount of wages 5 payable to him (except so far as they are ascertainahle by an automatic indicator) at the time when the work is given out :Provided that (i) where the rates of wages applicable to any 10work are not ascertainable before the work is given out, the particulars shall be furnished in writing as soon as practicable after the work is completed;(ii) where such particulars of the work as affect 15 the amount of wages are ascertained by an automatic indicator, and a placard containing particulars as to the rate of wages is exhibitedin each room in pursuance of an agreement between employers and persons employed and 20 in conformity with the requirements of this section the exhibition thereof  shall  be a sufficient compliance with this section;(iii) where the work is of a standard kind whichis sufficiently indicated by the materials given 25 out and which is denoted in a placard or book exhibited or kept as aforesaid, and containing the rate of wage for the work, by a description or name sufficiently indicating its nature it shall be sufficient to furnish persons employed 30 in the factory with such particulars of the quantity or weight of the work to he done as affect the amount of wages payable ; and(iv) if particulars of the amount of work on which the person is paid are not ascertainable until 35 the work is completed, such particulars shall.as soon as practicable after the completion of the work, he furnished in writing to that person.(2) This section shall apply to any place from which any work is given out (whether the materials for the 40 work are supplied by the occupier or not), and to the occupier of that place, and to every contractor employed by the occupier in connexion with the said work, as if that place were a factory.
(8) The particulars, either as to rate of wages or as to work, shall not he expressed by means of symbols: Provided that the occupier or contractor may describe any work which is of a standard kind known to the 5 persons employed by a particular figure, number, letter, or name, or combination thereof, by means of such figure, number, letter, or name, or combination thereof.(4) Where the work is done in common by a gang of persons, the particulars required to be given shall be  10        (a) the rate of wages applicable to the work done by the gang and the proportions (if fixed by the employer) according to which the wages of the several members of the gang are calculated; and(b) such particulars of the work done by the gang 15 as affect the amount payable to the gang ;and the occupier or contractor may in lieu of furnishing each member of the gang with written particulars of the work, furnish them to the member of the gang (if any) to whom the wages of the gang are paid, or may exhibit 20 them on a placard in the department or place in which the work is done.(5) If the person employed is required to return any written particulars or to hand them on with the work to another person employed, either  25        (a) a copy shall be furnished to the person employed which he may retain for his own use; or (A) a book shall be supplied to that person in which he may enter such particulars, and which shall be produced by him for examination by the 30 person receiving  the work on behalf of the employer, who shall initial the entry if found correct.(6) Any placard or book exhibited or kept in pur-suance of the foregoing provisions of this section shall 35 contain no other matter than particulars of rates of wages or work, and shall be exhibited or kept, as the case may be, in such a position as to be easily accessible and read by all persons to whose work the particulars relate.(7) Where an automatic indicator is used for ascer-40 taining work, the indicator shall have marked on its case the number of teeth in each wheel and the diameter of the driving roller, or such other particulars as will enable the accuracy of the indicator to be checked : 127 I
A.D. 1926. Provided that in the case of spinning machines withtraversing carriages the number of spindles and the length of the stretch in such machines shall be so marked in substitution for the diameter of the driving roller(8) The Secretary of State, on being satisfied by the 5 report of an inspector that the provisions of this section require to be modified in order to adapt them to the circumstances of any class of work, may, if he thinks fit, by special order make such modifications in the application of the provisions to that class as may in his opinion be 10 necessary.(9) If the occupier or contractor fails to comply with the requirements of this section or fraudulently uses a false indicator for ascertaining the particulars or amount of any work paid for by the piece, or if any 15 employed person fraudulently alters an automatic indi-cator, the occupier, contractor, or person employed, as the case may be, shall he guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, and in the case of a second or subsequent conviction within two years 20 from the last conviction for that offence, not less than one pound :Provided that an indicator shall not be deemed false if it complies with the requirements of this section.(10) If any person employed, having received any 25 particulars required by this section, whether they are furnished directly to him or to a fellow workman, dis-closes the particulars for the purpose of divulging a trade secret, he shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds. 30(11) If any person for the purpose of obtaining know-ledge of or divulging a trade secret, solicits or procures a person employed to disclose any such particulars, or with that object pays or rewards any such person, or causes any such person to be paid or rewarded for dis- 35 closing such particulars, he shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds.(12) In this section the expression &quot; person employed &quot; includes any contractor employed by the occupier of a factory on the business of the factory outside the factory, 40 or employed by the occupier of a place from which work is given out in connexion with the said work, except a
.., f 16 &amp; 17 Gbo. 5.] Factories. 67:&apos; ocontractor who does not personally do any part of the A.D. 1926; work which he undertakes :Provided that a person employing a contractor shall not he liahle to a fine for any failure to furnish him with 5 particulars if he shows to the satisfaction of the court that he had reasonahle ground for believing that the contractor was the occupier of a factory and that the work given out would be wholly done by persons employed by the contractor and no part thereof by the contractor 10 personally.99. The last foregoing section shall apply in Modification relation to weavers in the worsted, woollen and cotton of foregoing trades   subject   to   the   following   modifications   and rekidoii^bexceptions :  weavers.15 (a) as respects weavers in the worsted and woollen (other than hosiery) trades, particulars of the rate of wages applicable shall be furnished both in the manner provided in paragraph (a) (i) of subsection (1) of that section and in the manner20 provided in paragraph (a) (ii) thereof :(b) as respects weavers in the cotton trade, par-ticulars of the rate of wages applicable shall be furnished in the manner provided in paragraph (a) (i) of subsection (1) of that section :25 ((?) in the case of every other worker in the worsted, woollen and cotton trades the following pro-vision shall have effect in lieu of paragraph (a) of subsection (1) of that section, that is to say, particulars of the rate of wages applicable30 to the work to be done by each worker shall be furnished to him in writing at the time when the work is given out to him, except that if the same particulars are applicable to the work to be done by each of the workers in one room it35 shall be sufficient to exhibit them in that room on a placard not containing any other matter, and posted in a position where it is easily legible:(d) provisoes (i), (hi) and (iv) in subsection (1) and $4,0 subsections (4), (5), (8) and (12) of that section shall not apply in relation to weavers in the worsted, woollen, and cotton trades :127 I 2
used in ascertainingA.D. 1926. (e) the proviso to subsection (3) of that section shall  not apply as respects the worsted, woollen, and cotton trades.Weights and 100. (1) Every Act for the time being in force measures relating to weights and measures or weighing or measur- 5 ing instruments shall extend to weights, measures, and weighing instruments used in a factory for the purpose of checking or ascertaining the wages of any person employed therein, in like manner as if they were used for trade, and the Board of Trade may, after consultation 10 with the Secretary of State, by order direct that any of the provisions of any such enactment shall extend to such measuring instruments used in factories for such purposes as aforesaid as may be specified in the order. 15(2) Every inspector or other person authorised under the Acts relating to weights and measures or weighing or measuring instruments to inspect or examine weights and measures shall inspect, stamp, mark, search for, and examine the weights and measures and weighing and 20 measuring instruments to which those Acts are extended by or under this section, and for that purpose shall have the same powers and duties as he has with respect to weights, measures and instruments used for trade.Part X. 25Miscellaneous.Notice of 101. (1) Every person shall, within one monthof &quot;factor011 ar^er he begins to occupy, or to use any premises as, o  ac ory.    &amp; factory, serve  on the inspector for the district a written notice stating the name of the occupier or the 30 title of the firm, the postal address of the factory, the nature of the work, the nature and amount of the moving power, if any, and the name of the district council within whose district the factory is situated.(2) &quot;Within  one month  of the date upon which 35 mechanical power is, after the commencement of this Act, first used in any factory, the occupier shall serve on the inspector for the district a written notice stating the nature and amount of such mechanical power.(3) Where an inspector receives notice in pursuance 4,0 of this section with respect to a factory, in relation to
which a district council is responsible for the enforce- A.D 1926.merit of any of the provisions of Part i. of this Act,   he shall forthwith forward a copy of the notice to the district council.5        102. (1) There shall he kept affixed at each entrance Affixing ofof a factory at which employed persons enter, and in such abstract andother parts thereof as an inspector for the time being notlces-directs, in the prescribed form, and in such position as to be easily read by the persons employed in the factory 10       (a) the prescribed abstract of this Act; and(6) a notice of the address of the inspector for the district and the superintending inspector for the division; and(c) a notice of the name and address of the appointed 15 doctor for the factory; and Id) a notice of the clock (if any) by which the period of employment and intervals for meals and rest in the factory are regulated; and (e) every notice  and  document required by this 20 Act to he affixed in the factory.(2) If any person pulls down, injures or defaces any abstract, notice, regulations or other document posted up in pursuance of this Act, he shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding five pounds.25 103. (1) In every factory there shall he kept a general  register, called the general register, in which there shall registers, be entered in the prescribed form (a) the prescribed particulars as to the young persons employed in the factory; and 30       (6) the prescribed particulars as to the washing, white-washing or colour washing, painting or varnish-ing, of the factory ; and(c) the prescribed particulars as to every accidentand case of industrial disease occurring in the 35 factory of which notice is required to be sentto an inspector ; and(d) the report of every examination of a steam boiler and the record of every examination of a steam receiver and compressed air receiver made in^0 pursuance of this Act; and(e) every special exception of which the occupier of the factory avails himself; and(f) such other matters as may he prescribed.
A.D. 1926. (2) There shall he attached to the general register       a copy of the certificate of the district council relating to means of escape in the case of fire.(3) Where any entry is required by this Act or by any order or regulations made under this Act to be 5 made in the general register or in any other register or record, the entry made by the occupier of a factory or on his behalf shall, as against him, be admissible as prima facie evidence of the facts therein stated, and the fact that any entry so required with respect to the observance 10 of any provision of this Act or of any order or regulation, thereunder has not been made, shall be admissible as prima facie evidence that that provision has not been observed.(4) The occupier of  a factory shall  send to an inspector such extracts from the general register as the 15 inspector may from time to time require for the purpose of the execution of his duties under this Act.Preservation 104. The general register and every other register or an^recorh   recoi&quot;d kept in pursuance of this Act shall be preserved&apos; *-  and shall be kept available for inspection by any inspector 20 or by the appointed doctor for at least two years after the date of the last entry in the register or record.105. (1) The occupier of every factory shall, on or before such days as the Secretary of State may direct, at intervals of not less than one nor more than five 25 years, send to the chief inspector a correct return speci-fying, with respect to such day or days, or such period as the Secretary of State may direct, the number of persons employed in the factory, with such particulars as may be prescribed, as to the hours of employment 30 of women and young persons employed, and as to the age, sex, and occupation of other persons employed.(2) The occupier of any place to which any of the provisions of this Act apply shall, if so required by the Secretary of State, make  a like return to the chief 35 inspector.(3) The Secretary of State may, for the purpose of facilitating the rendering of the returns under this section by occupiers of factories, arrange for the consolidation of those returns with any other returns which he or any 40 other Government department is empowered to call for from occupiers of factories.Periodical return of persons em-ployed.
(4) If the Secretary of State so directs the intervals A:D. 1926. at which returns are to he made under this section, may,        notwithstanding anything in this section, be the same as the intervals at which a census is directed to be taken 5 under the Census of Production Act, 1906.106. (1) No person employed in a factory or in any Duties of other place to which any provisions of this Act apply shall persons em-interfere with or misuse any means, appliance, convenience Ploye(1-or other thing provided in pursuance of this Act for 10 securing the health, safety or welfare of the persons employed in the factory or place.(2) It shall be the duty of every person employed in a factory or in any other place to which any provisions of tills Act apply to carry on his work in accordance with 15 this Act, and where any appliance is provided for his use under this Act to use such appliance.107. Save as otherwise expressly provided under Prohibition this Act, the occupier of a factory shall not make any on doduc-deduction from the sum contracted  to be paid by him liions from 20 to any person employed or receive or allow any person     0 in his employment to receive any payment from any such person in respect of any thing to be done or provided by the occupier in pursuance of this Act.Part XI.25 Administration.108. (1) The Secretary of State, with the approval of Appoint-the Treasury as to numbers and salaries, may appoint such ment and inspectors (under whatever title he may from time to time &apos;s&apos;utl6S oi in  fix) and such clerks and servants as he tbinks necessary X^^and&quot;30 for the execution of this Act, and may assign to them servants, their duties and award them their salaries, and may appoint a chief inspector (in this Act referred to as the chief inspector) with an office in London, and may regulate the cases and manner in which the inspectors, or any of them,gg are to execute and perform the powers and duties of inspectors under this Act, and may remove such inspectors, clerks, and servants.(2) In the appointment of inspectors of factories in Wales and Monmouthshire, among candidates otherwise
72Factories.[16 &amp; 11 Geo. 5];A.D. 1926.1 equally qualified, persons having a knowledge of the Welsh        language shall he preferred.(3) Notice of the appointment of every inspector shall he published in the London Gazette.(4) The salaries of the inspectors, clerks, and servants, 5 and the expenses incurred by them, shall be deemed to be expenses of the Secretary of State in carrying this Act into effect.(5) A person who is the &quot;occupier of a factory, or is directly or indirectly interested therein or in any process or 10 business carried on therein, or in a patent connected therewith, or is employed in or about a factory, shall not act as an inspector.(6) An inspector shall not be liable to serve on any jury or in any parochial or municipal office. 15(7) Such annual report of the proceedings of the inspectors as the Secretary of State directs shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.(8) A reference in this Act  (a) to an inspector refers, unless it is otherwise 20expressed, to an inspector appointed in pur-suance of this section;(b) to the inspector for the district or to the super-intending inspector for the division refers, as respects any factory, to the inspector in charge 25 of the district, or the superintending inspectorin charge of the division, in which the factory is situate.(9) Any notice or other document required by this Act to be sent to an inspector shall be sent to such 30 inspector as a Secretary of State directs, by declaration published in the London Gazette or otherwise as he thinks expedient for making the same known to all persons interested.Powers of  -        109. (l) An inspector shall, for the purpose of the 35 inspectors,    execution of this Act, have power to do all or any of the following things ; namely, (a) to enter, inspect, and examine at all reasonable times, by day and night, a factory, and every part thereof, when he has reasonable cause to 40
believe that any person is employed therein, and A.d. 1926. to enter by day any place which he has reasonable cause to believe to lie a factory ; and (/;) to take with him in either case a constable into 5 a factory in which he has reasonable cause toapprehend any serious obstruction in the execu-tion of his duty ; and(a) to require the production of the registers, cer-certificates, notices, and documents kept in pur-10 suance of this Act, and to inspect, examine,and copy the same ; and(d) to make such examination and inquiry as may be necessary to ascertain whether the enactments for the time being in force relating to public15 health and the provisions of this Act are com-plied with, so far as respects the factory and the persons employed therein; and(e) to examine, either alone or in the presence ofany other person, as he thinks fit, with respect 20 to matters under this Act, every person whom he finds in a factory, or whtom he has reasonable cause to believe to be or to have been within the preceding two months employed in a factory, and to require every such person to be so ex-25 amined and to sign a declaration of the truthof the matters respecting wdnch he is so examined: Provided that no one shall be required under this provision to answer any question or to give any evidence tending to criminate himself; and 30 (/) to exercise such other powers as may be necessary for carrying this Act into effect.(2) The occupier of every factory, his agents and servants, shall furnish the means required by an inspector as necessary for an entry, inspection, examination, inquiry, 35 or the exercise of his powers under this Act in relation to that factory.(3) If any person wilfully delays an inspector in the exercise of any power under this section, or fails to com-ply with the requisition of an inspector in pursuance of 40 this section, or to produce any register certificate notice or document which he is required by or in pursuance of this Act to produce, or conceals or prevents, or attempts to conceal or prevent a person from appearing before127 K
A.D. 1926. or being examined by an inspector, that person shall be deemed to obstruct an inspector in the execution of his duties under this Act.(4) Where an inspector is obstructed in the execution of his duties under this Act, the person obstructing him 5 shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding five pounds; and where an inspector is so obstructed in a factory, the occupier of that factory shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds; and in the case of a second 10 or subsequent conviction under this section in relation to a factory within two years from the last conviction for the same offence, a fine not less than one pound shall be imposed for each offence.110. An inspector, if so authorised in writing under 15 the hand of the Secretary of State, may, although he is not of counsel, or a solicitor, or law agent, prosecute, conduct, or defend before a court of summary jurisdiction or justice, any information, complaint, or other proceeding arising under this Act, or in the discharge of his duty 20 as inspector.111. Every inspector shall be furnished with the prescribed certificate  of  his  appointment,  and  when visiting a factory or place to which any of the  pro-visions of this Act apply shall, if so required, produce 25 the said certificate to the occupier.112. (1) The Secretary of State, and, if the Secre-tary of State so directs, the chief inspector, may appoint a sufficient number of duly qualified medical practitioners to be appointed doctors for any of the purposes of this 30 Act, and may revoke any such appointment:Provided that where under this Act the duty of arranging for the medical examination or certification of young persons has been transferred to the local authority for any district, the appointed doctor for those purposes 35 in that district shall be appointed by the local authority.(2) A medical practitioner who is the occupier of a factory, or is directly or indirectly interested therein, or in any process or business carried on therein,&apos; or in a patent connected therewith, shall not be the appointed 40 doctor for that factory.Power of inspector to conduct proceedings before magistrates.Certificate of appoint-ment of inspector.Appoint-ment and duties of appointed doctors.
(8) The appointed doctor for any factory shall have   A.D. 1926. power at all reasonable  times to inspect the general register of that factory.(4) The Secretary of State may make rules pre-5 scribing the duties of appointed doctors.(5) If and so long as there is no appointed doctor for a factory, the poor law medical officer for the district in which the factory is situate shall act as the appointed doctor for that factory.10 (6) References in the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act, 1925, to a certifying surgeon shall be construed as references to an appointed doctor appointed by the Secretary of State or chief inspector under this section.113.  (1) The fees to be paid to appointed doctors Fees of 15 for carrying out their duties under this Act shall be such appointed as may be determined by the Secretary of State, and such doctors-fees shall, in the case of any examination or certificate with respect to the fitness of a young person for employ -ment in a factory and in the case of any examination in 20 pursuance of regulations of a person  employed in a factory, be paid by the occupier of that factory, and in any other case shall be defrayed as an expense of carrying this Act into effect.authorities.114. (1)   In  this Act, the expression &quot;district Provisions 25 council&quot; means  as to local(a) as respects the City of London, the commoncouncil;(b) as respects any other part of the administrativecounty of London, the metropolitan borough 30 council;(c) as respects any other borough, including a countyborough, the borough council;(d) as respects any urban or rural district, the urban or rural district council:35 Provided that for the purposes of the provisions of this Act relating to means of escape in case of fire the London County Council shall, as respects the whole of the adminis-trative county of London, be substituted for the common counoil and the metropolitan borough councils.127 K 2
A.D. 1926. (2) The expenses of a council under this Act shall be defrayed (a) in the case of the City of London out of the general rate;(b) in the case of the London County Council as 5 part of their expenses in the execution of the London Building Act, 1894, as amended by any subsequent Act, and in the case of any other county council out of the county fund;(c) in the case of a metropolitan borough council as 10part of their expenses in the execution of the Public Health (London) Act, 1891;(d) in the case of any other borough council or urban district council as part of their expenses in the general execution of the Public Health 15 Acts, 1875 to 1908; and(e) in the case of a rural district council as generalexpenses incurred in the execution of the Public Health Acts, 1875 to 1908, except to such extent as the Minister of Health may, having regard 20 to local circumstances, see fit to direct that such expenses shall be defrayed as special expenses and in that case any expenses defrayed as special expenses shall be charged to the con-tributory place in which the factory is situate.     25(3) The medical officer of health of every district council shall (a) in his annual report to the council report specifically on the administration of and furnish the prescribed particulars with respect to the 30 matters under Part I. and Part VIII. of this Act wdiich are administered by the district council, and shall send a copy of his annual report or so much of it as deals with those matters to the Secretary of State; and 35(b) give written notice to the inspector for the district of any factory coming to his knowledge in which no abstract of this Act is affixed, in accordance with this Act.(4) The powers conferred by this Act on district 40 councils shall he in addition to and not in substitution for any other powers which they may possess.
(5) Tor the purpose of their duties with respect A.D. 1926. to factories under this Act and under the law relating to public health, the district council and their officers shall, without prejudice to their other powers, have all such powers of entry, inspection, taking legal proceedings, or otherwise, as an inspector has.115. (l) The following   provisions shall apply to Provisions assuch orders made by the Secretary of State in pursuance to orders of of this Act as are in this Act referred to as special Secretary of-i a      i State.j-U orders : (1) The order  shall be  under  the hand of the Secretary of State and shall be published in such manner as the Secretary of State thinks best adapted for the information of all persons 15 concerned, and shall come into operation at thedate of its publication, or at any later date mentioned in the order :(2) The order shall be laid as soon as may be before both Houses of Parliament, and if either House20 of Parliament, within the next forty days afterthe order has been so laid before that House, resolves that the order ought to be annulled, it shall after the date of that resolution be of no effect, without prejudice to the validity of any-25 thing done in the meantime under the order orto the making of a new order.(2) Any order made by the Secretary*y of State under this Act may be made subject to such conditions as he may see fit, and may contain such supplemental and 30 consequential provisions as may be necessary for giving full effect thereto, and may, except as herein otherwise expressly provided, be varied or revoked by a subsequent order made in like manner as the original order.Part XII.35 Penalties and Legal Proceedings.116. (1) In the event of any contravention in or in Fines forconnexion with or in relation to a factory of the provisions of contraven-this Act, or of any regulation or order made in pursuance *&apos;^ongof this Act, for which contravention no express penalty is thi^Act.
78,Factories.[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1926. provided by this Act, the occupier or (if the provision contravened is one in respect of which the owner or manager is made responsible) the owner or manager shall he guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, and, in the case of a continuing offence, 5 to a further fine not exceeding five pounds for each day during which the offence continues after conviction thereof.(2) If the occupier avails himself of any special exception allowed by or in pursuance of this Act and fails to comply with any of the conditions attached to such 10 exception, he shall he deemed tc have contravened the provisions of this Act.(3) If any persons are employed in a factory other-wise than in accordance with the provisions of this Act or of any regulation or order made in pursuance of this Act, 15 there shall be deemed to be a separate  contravention in respect of each person so employed.(4) In the event of any contravention by an employed person of any provision of this Act or of any regulation or order made in pursuance of this Act for which no express 20 penalty is provided by this Act,.he shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding five pounds; and the occupier of the factory at which the contraven-tion occurred shall, whether or not any legal proceedings are prosecuted against the employed person, also be liable 25 to a fine not exceeding ten pounds unless he proves that he has taken all reasonable means to enforce the provision and prevent the contravention.Fines in case        117. If any person is killed, or dies, or suffers any of death or    bodily injury or injury to health, in consequence of the 30 injury,        occupier or owner of a factory having neglected to observe any provision of this Act or any order or regulation made in pursuance of this Act, the occupier or owner of the factory shall be guilty of an offence, and, without prejudice to any other penalty, liable to a fine not exceeding one 35 hundred pounds, and, in the case of a second or subsequent conviction in relation to a factory within two years from the last conviction for the same offence, not less than ten pounds for each offence, and the whole or any part of the fine may be applied for the benefit of the injured person 40 or his family, or otherwise as the  Secretary of State determines :
Provided that  . A.D. 1926.(a) in the case of injury to health the occupier or owner shall not he liable under this section unless the injury was caused directly by the5 neglect; and(b) the occupier or owner shall not be liable to a fine under this section if an information against him under this Act in respect of the act or default by which the death or injury was10 caused, has been heard and dismissed beforethe death or injury occurred.118. If a child or young person is employed in a Fine for factory contrary to the provisions of this A.ct, the parent offence by of the child or young person shall be liable to a tine not Parent-15 exceeding five pounds, unless it appears to the court that the offence was committed without the consent, connivance, or wilful default of the parent.119. If any person  Forgery of(a) forges or counterfeits any certificate for the ^S^SS&apos;&apos; 20 purposes of this Act; or an(j fa]se(b) gives or signs any such certificate knowing the declarations,same to be false in any material particular; or ic) knowingly utters or makes use of any certificate so forged, counterfeited, or false as aforesaid; 25 or(d) knowingly utters or makes use of as applying to any person a certificate which does not so apply; or(e) personates any person named in a certificate ; 30 or(,/) falsely pretends to be an inspector; or(g) wilfully connives at the forging, counterfeiting, giving, signing, uttering, making use, or personating as aforesaid ; or35 (h) wilfully makes a false entry in any register,notice, certificate, or document required by this Act to be kept or served or sent; or(i) wilfully makes or signs a false declaration under this Act; or40 (/) knowingly makes use of any such false entryor declaration,
A.D. 1926w he shall he guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months.120. Where an act or default for which an occupier or owner is liable, is in fact the act or default of some agent, servant, worker or other person, that agent, servant, worker or other person shall be liable to the like penalty as if he were the occupier or owner, as the case may be.Penalty on persons actually com-mitting offence for which occu-pier is liablePower of occupier to exempt himself from fine ou con-viction of the actual offender.121, (1) Where the occupier or owner of a factory 10 is charged with an offence against this Act, he shall be entitled, upon information duly laid by him and on giving not less than three days&apos; notice of his intention to the prosecution, to have any other person whom he charges as the actual offender brought before the court at the 15 time appointed for hearing the charge; and if, after the commission of the offence has been proved, the occupier or owner of the factory proves to the satisfaction of the court (a) that he has used all due diligence to enforce the 20 execution of this Act; and(6) that the said other person had committed the offence in question without his consent, con-nivance, or wilful default,that other person shall be summarily convicted of the 25 offence, and the occupier or owner shall be exempt from any fine.   The person so convicted shall, in the discretion of the court, be also liable to pay any costs incidental to the proceedings:Provided that the prosecution shall have the right in 30 any such case to cross-examine the occupier or owner if he gives evidence and any witnesses called by him in support of his charge, and to call rebutting evidence.(2) When it is made to appear to the satisfaction of an inspector at the time of discovering an offence       35(a) that the occupier or owner (as the case may be) of the factory has used all due diligence to enforce the execution of this Act; and(b) by what person the offence has been committed ;and - 40
(a) that it has been committed without the consent,  A.D. 1926. connivance or wilful default of the occupier or owner and in contravention of his orders,the inspector shall proceed against the person whom he 5 believes to be the actual offender without first proceeding against the occupier or owner of the factory.122. Where, under this Act, any person is substi- Proceedings tuted for the occupier or owner with respect to any a ainst provisions of this Act, any order, summons, notice, or  therTlia 10 proceeding which for the purpose of any of those pro- occupiers, visions is by this Act required or authorised to be served on or taken in relation to the occupier or owner is hereby required or authorised (as the case may be) to be served on or taken in relation to that person.liable in certain cases15        123. Where in a factory the owner or hirer of a Owner of machine or implement moved by steam, water or other machine mechanical power is some person other than the occupier of the factory, the owner or hirer shall, so far as respects instead of any offence against this Act committed in relation to a occupier.20 person who is employed in or about or in connexion with that machine or implement, and is in the employment or pay of the owner or hirer, be deemed to be the occupier of the factory.124.  (1) All offences under this Act shall be pro- Prosecution 25 secuted and all fines under this Act shall be recovered 01 offencessummarily. and recovery*&quot; and applicn-(2) In any proceedings under this Act  tion of fines.(i) it shall be sufficient to allege that the factory is a factory within the meaning of this Act;30 (ii) it shall be sufficient to state the name of theostensible occupier of the factory, or the title of the firm ;(iii) the court shall, if required by either party, cause minutes of the evidence to be taken 35 and preserved.(3) Where, with respect to or  in consequence of any accident in a factory, a report is made by the court appointed to hold a formal investigation under this Act or under the Boiler Explosions Acts, 1882 and 1890, or a 40 coroner&apos;s inquest is held, and it appears from the report,127 L
A.D. 1926. or from the proceedings at the inquest, that any of the provisions of this Act, or any orders or regulations made thereunder, were not complied with at or before the time of the accident, summary proceedings against any person liable to be proceeded against in respect of such non-com- 5 compliance may be commenced at any time within three months after the making of the report or the conclusion of the inquest.(!) A summary order may be made for the purposes of this Act by a court of summary jurisdiction in manner 10 provided by the Summary Jurisdiction Acts.(5) All fines imposed in pursuance of this Act shall, save as otherwise expressly provided for by this Act, be paid into the Exchequer.(6) Where a proceeding is taken before a court of 15 summary jurisdiction with respect to an offence against this Act alleged to be committed in or with reference to a factory, no person shall be qualified to act as a member of the court who is the occupier or owner of the factory, or the husband, wife, parent, son, daughter, 20 brother, or sister of the occupier or owner of the factory, or a person engaged in, or an officer of any association of persons engaged in, the same trade or occupation as a person charged with the offence.(7) A conviction or order made in any matter arising 25 under this Act, either originally or on appeal, shall not be quashed for want of form, and a conviction or order made by a court of summary jurisdiction against which a person is authorised by this Act to appeal shall not he removed by certiorai-i or otherwise, either at the instance of the 30 Crown or of any private person, into a superior court, except for the purpose of the hearing and determination of a special case.Evidence 125. (l) If a person is found in a factory at anyin summary   time at which work is going on or the machinery is in 35 pioceeuingb. motiorjj except during the intervals for meals or sleep, he shall, until the contrary is proved, be deemed for the purposes of this Act to have been then employed in the factory :Provided that this enactment shall not apply to a 40 factory in which the only persons employed are members of the same family dwelling there.
20(2) Where in any proceedings under this Act with A.D. 1926. respect to a child or a young person it appears to the court that that child or young person is apparently of or below the age alleged by the informant, it shall lie on the 5 defendant to prove that the child or young person is not of or below that age.126. Any notice, order, requisition, summons, and Service of document required or authorised to be served or sent for notices andj. ,i -    .   i documents,the purposes of this Act  &amp;c10 (a) may be served and sent by post, or by delivering the same to or at the residence of the person on or to whom it is to be served or sent, or (where he is the owner of a factory) by delivering the same or a true copy thereof to his agent, or15 (wdiere he is the  occupier of a factory) bydelivering the same or a true copy thereof to his agent or to some person in the factory; and(b) where it is required to be served on or sent to the occupier of a factory, shall be deemed to be properly addressed if addressed to the occupier of the factory at the factory, with the addition of the proper postal address, but without naming the person who is the occupier.127. Where the age of any person under the age Certificate.of.25 of eighteen years is required to be ascertained or proved birth in case for the purposes of this Act any person shall on pre- of 7ounS sen ting a written requisition in such form and containing ^&quot;fg^jg such particulars as may be from time to time prescribed by the Minister of Health, and on payment of a fee of30 sixpence, be entitled to obtain a certified extract under the hand of a registrar or superintendent registrar of the entry in the register under the Births and Deaths Registration Acts, 1836 to 1901, of the birth of that person ; and such form of requisition shall on request be35 supplied without charge by every superintendent registrar and registrar of births, deaths, and marriages.128. If any occupier of premises which have been Power of let as a factory is prevented by any agreement from county carrying out any structural or other alterations in the oor&apos;r.t&apos;t0 40 factory which are necessary to enable him to comply agreements with the provisions of this Act or of any regulation or order made under this Act and is unable to obtain on 127 L 2
A.D. 1926.Power of county-court to apportion expenses.Application of Arbitra-tion Act, 1889.52 &amp; 53 Viet, c. 49.Factories to which Act applies.reasonable terms the consent to those alterations of the person whose consent is necessary under the agreement, he may apply in accordance with county court rules to the county court, and the court, after hearing the parties and any witnesses whom they desire to call, may make such an 5 order setting aside or modifying the terms of the agree-ment as the court considers just and equitable in the circumstances of the case.129. Where in any premises which have been let as a factory any structural or other alterations are required 10 in order to comply with the provisions of this Act or of any regulation or order made under this Act or in order  to  conform   with any standard or requirement imposed  by or   under  this  Act  and  the  owner  or occupier  as the case may be  alleges that the whole 15 or part of the expenses of the alterations jought to be borne by the occupier or owner, the owuier or occupier may apply in accordance with rules of  court to the county court, and the court after hearing the parties and any witnesses whom they may desire to call, may make 20 such an order concerning the expenses or their appor-tionment as the court considers just and equitable in the circumstances of the case, regard being had to the terms of any contract between the parties, or in the alternative the court may at the request of the owner or occupier 25 determine the lease.130. The Arbitration Act, 1889, shall not apply to proceedings under this Act except in so far as it may be applied by regulations made under this Act.Part XIII. 30Interpretation .131. (1) Subject to the provisions of this section,  The expression &quot; factory &quot; includes -Any premises or place wherein   or  within the close or curtilage or precincts of which any 35 person is employed in manual labour by way of trade or for purposes of gain in or incidental to any of the following purposes, namely (a) the making of any article or of part ofany article; or 40
101520253035(6) the altering,  repairing, ornamenting,  A.D. 1926. finishing, cleaning, or washing, or the breaking        up or demolition of any article; or(c) the adapting for sale of any article; and to or over which premises or place the employer of the persons employed therein has the right of access or control :The expression &quot; factory &quot; also includes (with-out prejudice to the generality of the foregoing definition) (i) any premises in which electrical energy is generated, converted, or transformed for supply by way of trade or for the purposes of traction on any railway, tramway or other means of public conveyance, or for use in or in connexion with any other industrial or com-mercial undertaking, or for lighting of streets, ptiblic places or public buildings or institutions; but the application of this Act to transformer stations in which there is no moving machinery and in which no person is regularly employed shall be subject to such exemptions and modifications as the Secretary of State may by order direct;(ii) any yard or dry dock in which any ship is constructed, reconstructed, repaired, refitted, or finished or broken up ;(iii) any premises or place in which the business of sorting any material or articles is carried on by way of trade or as a preliminary to or for the purposes of the work carried on in any factory ;(iv) any premises or place in which the business of filling bottles or containers or packing articles is carried on by way of trade;(v) any premises in which the hooking, lapping, making-up or packing of yarn or cloth is carried on;(vi) any laundry carried on as ancillary to another business, or incidentally to the purposes of any public institution ;(vii) any premises or place in which loco-motives vehicles or other plant for use for
A. H. 1926. transport purposes  are  constructed,   recon-  structed, or repaired ;(viii) any premises in which letter-press printing is carried on ;(ix) any premises or place used in connec- 5 tion with a theatre for the making adaptation or repair of dresses or stage properties :The expression &quot; tenement factory&quot; means any premises where mechanical power from any prime mover within the close or curtilage of the 10 premises is distributed to different parts of the same premises occupied by different persons for the purpose of any process, in such manner that those parts constitute in law separate factories :Any line or siding (not being part of a railway) 15 which is used in connexion with a factory, shall be deemed to be part of the factory ; if any such line or siding is used in connexion with more than one factory belonging to different occupiers, the line or siding shall he deemed to be a separate 20 factory :A part of a factory may, with the approval in writing of the chief inspector, be taken to be a separate factory.(2) Any workplace in which, with the permission of 25 or under agreement with the owner or occupier, two or more persons carry on any work which would constitute the workplace a factory if the persons working therein were in the employment of the owner or occupier, shall be deemed to be a factory for the purposes of this Act, and 30 the provisions of this Act shall apply as if the owner or occupier of the workplace were the occupier of the factory and the persons working therein were persons employed in the factory.(3) Any premises in or adjacent to and belonging to a 35 mine or quarry in which the only process carried on is a process ancillary to the getting, dressing and preparation for sale of minerals shall not be deemed to be a factory.(4) &quot;Where a pla.ce situate within the close, curtilage, or precincts forming a factory is solely used for some 40 purpose other than the process or handicraft carried on in the factory, that place shall not be deemed to form
part of the factory for the purposes of this Act, but  A.p. 1926. shall, if otherwise it would be a factory, be deemed to be a separate factory.(5) A place or premises shall not be excluded from 5 the definition of a factory by reason only that the place or premises is or are in the open air.(6) The exercise by any child or young person in any recognised efficient school, during a portion of the school hours, of any manual labour for the purpose of instructing 10 Mm in any art or handicraft shall not be deemed to be an exercise of manual labour for the purpose of gain within the meaning of this Act.(7) &quot;Where the Secretary of State by special order so directs as respects all or any purposes of this Act, 15 different branches or departments of work carried on in the same factory shall be deemed to be different factories.132. (1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise Genera! requires, the following expressions have the meanings i&quot;tcrpretn-bereby assigned to them respectively, that is to say :        tlon-20        &quot; Appointed doctor &quot; means in relation to any pro-vision of  this Act a medical  practitioner duly appointed to act for the purpose of that provision:&quot; Bakehouse &quot; means any place in which are baked bread, biscuits or confectionery from the baking 25 or selling of which a profit is derived :&quot; Bank holiday &quot; means a holiday under the Holidays 38 &amp; 39 Viet. Extension Act, 1875 : c. 13.&quot; Building operation &quot; means the construction, repair, or alteration of a building and the preparation for, 30 and laying the foundation of, an intended building,but does not include any operation which is an engineering work within the meaning of this Act:&quot; Child &quot; means a person who has not attained the age of fourteen years :35        &quot; Degrees &quot; means degrees Fahrenheit:&quot; Engineering work &quot; means the construction, repair, or alteration of any harbour, dock, pier, inland navigation, tunnel, bridge, viaduct, sewer, gas work or water work :40        &quot; Fume &quot; includes gas or vapour:
A.n. 1926. &quot; Humid   factory &quot;  means   a   factory in  whichatmospheric humidity is artificially produced by steaming or other mechanical appliance: &quot; Machinery &quot; includes any driving strap or band : &quot; Night &quot; means the period between nine o&apos;clock in 5 the evening and six  o&apos;clock in the  succeeding morning :&quot; Owner&quot; means the person for the time being receiving the rackrent of the premises in con-nection wuth which the word is used, whether 10 on his own account or as agent or trustee for any other person, or who would so receive the same if the premises were let at a rackrent:&quot; Parent&quot;   means   a   parent   or guardian of,  or person having the legal custody of, or the control 15 over,  and  includes  any person   having  direct benefit  from the  wages of. a  child or young person :&quot; Prescribed &quot; means prescribed for the time being by the Secretary of State : 20&quot; Prime mover &quot; means every engine motor or other appliance which provides mechanical energy derived from steam, water, wind, electricity, combustion or other source :&quot; Process &quot; includes the use of any locomotive : 25&quot; Kail way &quot; means a railway within the meaning of the Railway Employment (Prevention of Acci-dents) Act, 1900 :i  Sanitary conveniences&quot;  includes  urinals, water-closets,  earthclosets,  privies,   ash pits,  and  any 30 similar convenience :&quot; Ship,&quot; &quot; vessel,&quot; and &quot; harbour&quot; have the same meaning as in the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894 :&quot; Steam boiler&quot; means any closed vessel in which for any purpose steam is generated under pressure 35 greater than atmospheric pressure, and any super-heater :&quot; Steam receiver&quot; means any vessel or apparatus other than a steam pipe or coil used for containing steam under pressure greater than atmospheric 40 pressure for the purposes of heating, boiling, drying, evaporating, vulcanising, or other similar purposes :&quot; Transmission machinery &quot; means every shaft, wheel, drum, pulley, system of fast and loose pulleys, 45
coupling, clutch, driving strap or other device by  A.D. 1926.which the motion of a prime mover is transmitted        to or received by any machine or appliance : &quot; Week&quot; means the period between midnight on 5 Saturday night and midnight on the succeedingSaturday night: &quot; Woman&quot; means a woman who has attained theage of eighteen: &quot; Young person &quot; means a person who has attained 10 the age of fourteen but has not attained the ageof eighteen.(2) A woman, young person, or child who works in a factory, whether for wages or not, either in a process or in cleaning any part of the  factory used for any15 process, or in cleaning or oiling any part of the machineiw, or in any other kind of work whatsoever incidental to or connected with the process, or connected with the article made or otherwise the subject of the process therein, shall, save as is otherwise provided by this Act,20 be deemed to be employed therein within the meaning of this Act.(3) Eor the purposes of this Act an apprentice shall be deemed to be a person employed.(4) Where any operation or thing is required under 25 this Act to be performed or done at specified intervals, each such interval shall be deemed to commence as from the date  on which  the  operation  or thing was last performed or done.Part XIV.30 Supplementary.133.  (1) This Act applies to factories belonging Application to the Crown and to building operations and engineering to factories works undertaken by or on behalf of the Crown; but ^e0Q^&quot;^ntc in case of any public emergency the Secretary of State .anj p^Tio&apos; 35 may, by order, to the extent and during the  period authorities, named  by  him,  exempt from  this Act any factory belonging to the Crown or any building operation or engineering work undertaken by or on behalf of the Crown, or any factory in respect of work which is being127 M
A.D. 1926.Inspection of certain premises.Expenses of Secretary of State.Application to Scotland.done on behalf of the Crown under a contract specified in the order.(2) A factory belonging to or in the occupation of the Crown or any municipal or other public authority, and a building operation or engineering work undertaken 5 by or on behalf of the Crown or any such authority, shall not be excluded from the operation of this Act by reason only that it is not carried on or undertaken by way of trade or business or for the purpose of gain.(3) The powers conferred by this Act on a district 10 council shall, in the case of a factory belonging to or in the occupation of the Crown, be exercised by an inspector under this Act; and any notice required by this Act to be sent to a district council shall in any such case be sent to the inspector for the district. 15134. Where in any premises which are subject to inspection by or under the authority of any Government department any manual labour is exercised, otherwise than for the purposes of instruction, in or incidental to the making, altering, repairing, ornamenting, finishing, 20 washing, cleaning, or adapting for sale, of any article, and the premises do not constitute a factory by reason that the work carried on therein is not carried on by way of trade or for the purposes of gain, or by reason that the persons employed in the work are not working under 25 a contract of service or apprenticeship, the Secretary of State may arrange with the department that the premises shall, as respects the matters dealt with by this Act, be inspected by an inspector appointed under this Act, and where such an arrangement is made, such inspectors 30 shall have, as respects such matters as aforesaid, the like right of entry and inspection as is conferred on inspectors of the department concerned.135. The expenses of the Secretary of State in carrying this Act into effect shall be defrayed out of 35 moneys provided by Parliament.136. This Act shall apply to Scotland subject to the following modifications : (1) The Scottish Board of Health shall, except in the section of this Act relating to repeals, be 40 substituted for the Minister of Health and the Scottish Education Department shall be substi-tuted for the Board of Education.
f 16- &amp; 17 Geo. 5.] Factories. 91(2) In subsection (4) of  the section of this Act  A.D. 1926. relating to the prosecution of offences and the recovery  and  application of  fines, the  Lord Advocate shall be substituted for the Secretary 5 of State.(3) The   expression   &quot; district  council&quot;   and   the expression &quot; local authority&quot; mean the local authority under the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897 ; and the expenses incurred by such 10 local authority under this Act shall be defrayedout of  the public health general assessment levied under the said Act of 1897.(4) The expression &quot; sanitary inspector&quot; means sanitary inspector within the meaning of the15 Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897; the expres-sion &quot; local education authority under the Education Act, 1921,&quot; means &quot; the education authority under the Education (Scotland) Act, 1918&quot;;   the  expression  &quot; court  of  summary20 jurisdiction &quot;   and   the   expression   &quot; county court&quot; mean the sheriff court, and refer-ences to the judge of the county court shall be construed as references to the sheriff; the expression &quot; information&quot; means petition25 or   complaint ;   the   expression   &quot; informer &quot;means petitioner, pursuer or complainer; the expression &quot; defendant &quot; means defender or respondent; a reference to a coroner&apos;s inquest shall be construed as a reference to a public30 inquiry held under the Patal Accidents Inquiry(Scotland) Act, 1895, or the Patal Accidents and Sudden Deaths Inquiry (Scotland) Act, 1906; the expression &quot; attending before a court of record&quot; means attending an inquiry under the35 last-mentioned Acts ; the  expression &quot; master of the supreme court&quot; means the auditor of the sheriff court; references to sections one hundred and eighty-two to one hundred and eighty-six  of the  Public  Health Act, 1875,40 shall be construed as references to sections one hundred and eighty-three to one hundred and eighty-seven of the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897; the reference to section twenty-two of the Public Health Acts Amendment Act,127 M 2
a.D. 1926. 1890, shall be construed as a reference to section twenty-nine of the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897; the expression &quot; recognised efficient school&quot; means any public or other school under government inspection ; the expression &quot; owner &quot; 0 means the person for the time entitled to receive or would, if the same were let, be entitled to receive the rents of the premises, and includes a trustee, factor, tutor or curator, and in the case of public or municipal property, applies to 10 the persons to whom the management thereof is entrusted; the expression &quot; poor law medical officer&quot; means the medical officer appointed by the parish council; the expression &quot;Births and. Deaths Regulation Acts, 1836 to 1901,&quot; 15 means the Births Deaths and Marriages (Scotland) Acts, 1854 to 1910; references to a justice or to a superintendent registrar shall not apply.(5) The section of this Act relating to inquest in case of death by accident or industrial disease 20 in factory shall not apply.(6) All matters required by this Act to be published in the London Gazette shall, if they relate to Scotland, be published in the Edinburgh Gazette either in addition or in substitution as the case 25 may require.(7) All offences under this Act shall be prosecuted and all penalties under this Act shall be recovered under the provisions of the Summary Jurisdiction (Scotland) Acts at the instance of the procurator 30 fiscal or of any inspector.(8) The court may make and may alter or vary summary orders under this Act on application by the procurator fiscal or by an inspector presented in common form. gg(9) It shall not be an objection to the competency of an inspector to give evidence as a Avitness in any prosecution for an offence against this Act that the prosecution is brought at his instance.(10) Every person convicted of an offence against 4,0 this Act may be found liable in expenses.Repeals. 137. Subject to the provisions of this section the enactments referred to in Part I. of the Third Schedule
to this Act are hereby repealed to the extent specified A.D. 1926. in the third column of that Schedule :  Provided that (a) The  foregoing  repeal  shall not  affect the 5 operation of any enactments repealed by thisAct, in their application to any quarries or pit hanks as defined by the Factory and &quot;Work-shop Act, 1901; except as respects any pre-mises which are a factory within the meaning 10 of this Act; and(b) any order, regulation, requirement, appoint-ment, or agreement made or certificate  or notice given under any enactment repealed by this Act shall continue in force as though it had 15 been made or given under the corresponding provision of this Act; and(i?) the regulations made by the Secretary of State under the Factory and Workshop (Cotton Cloth Factories) Act, 1911, and in force at20 the date of the commencement of this Act,shall continue in force as though they were regulations made under Part IV. of this Act but with the modification that fifty degrees during the first half hour of work25 and  fifty-five  degrees  thereafter   shall  besubstituted as the minimum temperature to be maintained in every humid and dry shed; and(d) Subsection (2) of section two of the Factory 30 and Workshop Act, 1901, as set out in Part II.of the Third Schedule to this Act, shall continue in force as respects work places within the meaning of the Public Health Act, 1875; and35 (e) the provisions of the factory and workshop act, 1901, which are set out with the necessary modifications in the Fourth Schedule to this Act (being provisions the administration of which has under the Ministry of Health Act,40 1919, and the Scottish Board of Health Act,1919, been transferred to the Minister of Health in England and Wales and to the Scottish Board of Health in Scotland), shall
continue in force as though enacted in this Act, and shall continue to be so administered; but the Minister of Health or in Scotland the Scottish Board of Health may by order, delegate any powers under the said provisions 5 to such local authorities as he or they may think proper.Short tide, 138. (1) This Act may be cited as the Factoriescommence-     Act, 1926. incut Midextent,. (2) This Act shall come into operation on the first 10day of January, nineteen hundred and twenty-seven.(3) This Act  shall not  except  where  otherwise expressly provided, extend to Northern Ireland.A.D. 1926
SCHEDULES.A.D. 1926.FIRST SCHEDULE,Table of Humidity.dry bulb thermometer readings. degrees fahrenheit.ii.wet Bulb thermometer readings. degrees fahrenheit.1015202530354,0455050		48y51		4952		5053		5154		5255		5356		54]57		5558		5659		5760		5861		5962		60     -63		61 ;64 &apos;		6265		6366		6467		6568		6669   &apos;		6770		6871		68-572		6973		7074		70-575		71-576		72( 1		7378		73-579		74-580		75-581		7682		76-583		77-584		7886		7986		8087		80-588	-	81-589		82-590		8391		83-592		84-593		85-594		86
A.D. 1926.1st Boh.  eont.Form op Record. Form for recording the Readings of the Thermometers.Name of Occupier__Address of Factory     _&quot;    _.Room( Number or Designation j Process carried on_Number of Operatives I, Cubic contents_cubic feet.Date.	Readings of Thbbmombters in Dkgrees Fahrenheit.				If no Artificial Humidity is produced in the 24 hours, insert in&quot; this column &quot;None.&apos;Month and Day.	Between 10 and 11 a.m.		Between &apos;6 and 4 p.m.			Dry Bulb.	Wet Bulb.	Dry Bulb.	Wet Bulb.	1015l2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31202530354045(Signed)Occupier or Manager.
1. Before the Secretary of State makes any regulations he shall publish, in such manner as he may think best adapted for informing persons affected, notice of the proposal to make the 5 regulations, and of the place where copies of the draft regula-tions may be obtained, and of the time (which shall be not less than twenty-one days) within which any objection made with respect to the draft regulations by or on behalf of persons affected must be sent to the Secretary of State.10        2. Every objection, must be in writing and state (a) the draft regulations or portions of draft regulationsobjected to ;(b) the specific grounds of objection ; and(c) the omissions, additions, or modifications asked for.15 3. The Secretary of State shall consider any objection made by or on behalf of any persons appearing to him to be affected which is sent to him within the required time, and he may, if he thinks fit, amend the draft regulations, and shall then cause the amended draft to be dealt with in like manner as an original20 draft.4. Where the majority of the occupiers of the factories affected by the proposed regulations dispute the reasonableness of the requirements in the proposed regulations, and the Secretary of State does not amend or withdraw the draft 25 regulations, he shall before making the regulations direct an inquiry to he held in the manner hereinafter provided. The Secretary of State may also direct an inquiry to he held in regard to any objection, though not made by the majority of the occupiers, if he thinks desirable.30 5. The Secretary of State may appoint a competent person to hold an inquiry with regard to any draft regulations, and to report to him thereon.6. The inquiry shall be held in public, and the chief inspector and any objector and any other person who, in the 35 opinion of the person holding the inquiry, is affected by the draft regulations, may appear at the inquiry either in person or by counsel, solicitor, or agent.7. The witnesses on the inquiry may, i  the person holding it thinks fit, be examined on oath.40 8. Subject as aforesaid, the inquiry and aU proceedings preliminary and incidental thereto shall be conducted in accordance with rules made by the Secretary of State.127 NSECOND SCHEDULE. A.D. 1926.
A.D. 1926. 9. The fee to be paid to the person holding the inquiry- shall be such as the Secretary of State may direct, and shall be2nd Soh. deemed to be part of the expenses of the Secretary of State in&apos;eont&apos; the execution of this Act.10. Regulations shall be laid as soon as possible before 5 both Houses of Parliament, and if either House, within the next forty days after the regulations have been laid before that House, resolve that all or any of the regulations ought to be annulled, the regulations shall, after the date of the resolution, be of no effect, without prejudice to the validity of anything 10 done in the meantime thereunder or to the making of any new regulations. If one or more of a set of regulations are annulled the Secretary of State may, if he thinks fit, withdraw the whole set.&apos;11. Notice of any regulations having been made and of 15 the place where copies of them can be purchased shall be published in the London and Edinburgh Gazettes.12. Printed copies of all regulations for the time being in force in any factory shall be kept posted up in legible characters in conspicuous places in the factory, where they may be con- 20 veniently read by the persons employed. In a factory in Wales or Monmouthshire the regulations shall be posted up both in English and Welsh.13. A printed copy of all such regulations shall be given by the occupier to any person affected thereby on his application.    2514. If the occupier of any factory fails to comply with any provision of this schedule as to posting up or giving copies, he shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding ten pounds.
THIRD SCHEDULE.A.D. 1926.Enactments repealed. Part I.Session and Chapter.38 &amp; 39 Viet, c. 55.53 &amp; 54 Viet.10   c-59-54 &amp; 55 Viet, c. 76.151 Edw. 7. c. 22 20 6 Edw. 7.. e. 49 6 Edw. 7. c. 5325 7 Edw. 7.c. 10 7 Edw. 7. c. 398 Edw. 7. c. 42301 &amp; 2 Geo. 5. c. 21.35 6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5. c. 31.-10 &amp; 11 Geo. 5. c. 62.4013 &amp; 14 Geo. 5. c. 42.Short Title.Extent of Repeal.The Public Health Act, 1875.The Public Health Act, 1890.The Public Health (Lon-don) Act, 1891.The Factory and workshop act, 1901. Tho Census of production act, 1906. Notice of Accidents Act,1906.The     Employment     ofWomen Act, 1907. The Factory and workshop act, 1907. The   White   PhosphorusMatches Prohibition Act,1908.The Factory and Workshop(Cotton Cloth Factories)Act, 1911. The Police, Factories, &amp;c.(Miscellaneous     Provi-sions) Act, 1916. The Women and YoungPersons (Employment inLead   Processes)   Act,1920.The Workmen&apos;s Compeusa-tion Act, 1923.In section ninety-one the words &quot; factory, work-shop, or &quot;.Section twenty-two so far as it relates to factories.In section two the words &quot; factory, workshop, or &quot;, and in section thirty-eight the words &quot;factory, workshop and&quot; and the words &quot; factory, workshop or &quot;.The whole Act so far asun repealed. Section ten.Section four and section five so far as it relates to factories and workshops.The whole Act so far as unrepealed.The whole Act.The whole Act.The whole Act.Sections seven, eight and nine.The whole Act.Subsections (1) of section twenty-eight and section twenty-nine.127
A.D. 1926.o PAKT  II.3kd Soh. COIlt. SeOTION 2 (2) OF THE FACTORY AND WORKSHOP ACT,  1901,AS CONTINUED IN FORCE.2. (2) Every.....workplace within the meaning ofthe Public Health Act, 1875, must be kept free from effluvia 5 arising from any drain, wafcercloset, earth-closet, privy, urinal, or other nuisance, and unless so kept shall be deemed to be a nuisance liable to be dealt with summarily under the law relating to public health.Fourth SCHEDULE.10Prohibition of employ-ment of women after childbirth.Sanitary regulations for bake-houses.Penalty forbakehousebeingunfit onsanitarygrounds.Provisions op the factory and Workshop Act, 1901, administered by the Minister op Health.61.-An occupier of a factory shall not knowingly allow a woman or girl to be employed therein within four weeks after she has given birth to a child. 2597. (1) It shall not be lawful to let or suffer to be occupied or to occupy any room or place as a bakehouse, unless the following regulations are complied with : (a) A watercloset, earth closet, privy, or ashpits must not be within or communicate directly with the bakehouse ;(6) Every cistern for supplying water to the bakehouse must be separate and distinct from any cistern for supplying water to a watercloset;(c) A drain or pipe for carrying off fecal or sewage matter must not have an opening within the bakehouse.(2) If any person lets or suffers to be occupied or occupies any room or place as a bakehouse in contravention of this section he shall he guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding forty shillings, and to a further fine not exceeding five shillings for every day during which any room or place is so occupied after a conviction under this section.98. (1) Where a court of summary jurisdiction is satisfied on the prosecution of an inspector or a district council that any room or place used as a bakehouse is in such-, a state as to be on sanitary grounds unfit for use or occupation as a bakehouse, the occupier of the bakehouse shall be liable to a fine not exceeding, for the first offence, forty shillings, and for any subsequent offence five pounds.20253035
(2) The court of summary jurisdiction, in addition to or   a.D. 1926.instead of inflicting a fine, may order means to be adopted by       -----tlie occupier, within the time named in the order, for the 4th Soh-purpose of removing the ground of complaint. The court may, ^- cont&apos; 5 on application, enlarge the time so named, but if after the expiration of the time as originally named or enlarged by sub-sequent order the order is not complied with, the occupier shah be liable to a fine not exceeding one pound for every day that the non-compliance continues.10        99. (1) AH the inside walls of the rooms of a bakehouse, Lime-wash-and all the ceiling or tops of those rooms (whether those walls,       painting, ceilings, or tops are plastered or not), and all the passages and a&quot;bake- mS staircases of a bakehouse, must either be painted with oil or houses, varnished or be limewashed, or be partly painted or varnished15 and partly colourwashed ; and(a) where the bakehouse is painted with oil or varnished,there must be three coats of paint or varnish, and the paint or varnish must be renewed once at least in every seven years, and must be washed with hot water 20 and soap once at least in every six months ; andlb) where the bakehouse is limewashed, the limewashiug must be renewed once at least in every six months.100. (1) A place on the same level with a bakehouse, and Provision as forming part of the same building, may not be used as a sleeping to sleeping 25 place, unless it is constructed as follows ; that is to say places nearla) is effectually separated from the bakehouse by a par-tition extending from the floor to the ceiling; and(b) has an external glazed window of at least nine super-ficial feet in area, of which at the least four and a half 30 superficial feet are made to open for ventilation.(2) If any person lets or occupies or continues to let or knowingly suffers to be occupied any place contrary to this section, lie shall be guilty of an offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding, for the first offence, twenty shillings, and for any 35 subsequent offence five pounds.109. If the occupier of a factory or of any place from Making of which any work is given out, or any contractor employed by wearing any such occupier, causes or allows wearing apparel to be made, aPPai&apos;el cleaned, or repaired, in any dwelling-house or building occupied J B^*et 640 therewith, whilst any inmate of the dwelling-house is suffering fever or from scarlet fever or small-pox, then, unless he proves that lie small-pox. was not aware of the existence of the illness in the dwelling-house, and&apos; could not reasonably have been expected to become aware of it, he shall be guilty of an offence and fiable to a fine45 not exceeding ten pounds.
110. (1) If any inmate of a house is suffering from an infectious disease to which, this section applies, the district council of the district in which the house is situate may make an order forbidding any work to which this section applies to be given out to any person living or working in that house, or 5 such part thereof as may be specified in the order, and any order so made may he served on the occupier of any factory, or any other place from which work is given out, or on the contractor employed by any such occupier.(2) The order may be made notwithstanding that the person 10 suffering from an infectious disease may have been removed from the house, and the order shall be made either for a specified time or subject to the condition that the house or part thereof liable to be infected shall be disinfected to the satisfaction of the medical officer of health, or that other reasonable precautions 15 shall be adopted.(3) In any case of urgency the powers conferred on the district council by this section, may be exercised by any two or more members of the council acting on the advice of the medical officer of health. 20(4) If any occupier or contractor on whom an order under this section has been served contravenes the provisions of the order, he shall he guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding ten pounds.(5) The infectious diseases to which this section applies are 25 the infectious diseases reqtiired to be notified under the law for the time being in. force in relation to the notification of infectious diseases, and the work to which this section applies is the making, cleaning, washing, altering, ornamenting, finishing and repairing of wearing apparel and any work incidental thereto, 30 and such other classes of work as may be specified by order of the Minister of Health.a.d. 1926.4th sch.  cont.Prohibition of home work in places where: there is infectious disease.
Factories.DRAFTOS aBILLTo consolidate, with, amendments, the enactments relating to Factories; and for purposes connected therewith.XCII.   (1.)\Wh July 1926.127- 1

</content>
</cab>
