<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/33 images: 362-369</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  March 11)40.MOST SECRET.JCopy No.W.P. (40) 53.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.NAVAL PROGRAMME   1940-41.Battleships.THE five &quot; King George V&apos;s &quot; ordered in 1936 and 1937 should all at lastbe completed before the end of 1941. In 1938-39 Parliament approved the Lionand Temeraire, and in 1939-40 the Conqueror and Thunderer. these four 16-inch-gun ships are the first vessels to be built by the Navycomparable in gun-power to the contemporary ships of all other naval powers. Since the outbreak of war it has been decided to delay the hulls of theLion and Temeraire, and only to press on with their gun-mountings, which are ayear behind.  No work has yet been done upon the Conqueror and the Thunderer.2. Had peace continued, it would have been necessary in the face of foreignprogrammes to seek authority for building two more battleships or battle-cruisers of the 1940-41 programme. There would thus be the following ships under construction after the &quot; King George V&apos;s &quot; are finished : 1938-39Lion1939-401940-41Temeraire 16-inch-gun ships alreadyConqueror sanctioned by Parliament.Thunderer .A.B.
in view of the uncertainties of the war, it is proposed instead to make further progress on the Lion and Temeraire; to postpone decision in respect of theConqueror and Thunderer till the autumn, and to build for the programme of thecurrent year 1940-41 only one ship, the Vanguard. By using the four spare15-inch gun turrets of the &quot; Ramillies &quot; Class, this battle-cruiser can be producedsix months earlier than the existing 16-inch design of the Conqueror andThunderer at a saving of  2,000,000. Thus, instead of six ships, four of whichhave already been sanctioned by Parliament, it is proposed only to buildthree now.3. The Board of Admiralty, however, consider the future prospects so serious in view of the long time it takes to build capital ships, that they ask thatthe decision not to proceed with the 16-inch-gun ships Conqueror and Thundererat once, shall be reviewed before the end of the calendar year, when the position should be clearer.4. It is also proposed to give very strong additional deck-armour to two ofthe four old &quot; R &quot; class battleships so as to fit them for action within range ofthe enemy&apos;s shore-based aircraft. These improvements, at the cost of about-61,000,000 apiece, will make these old vessels effective units by the autumn of1941. They may therefore play a part in the present war. It is also proposedto build a new hull and engines at a cost of a million for the turret of the monitorMarshal Soult, which may be needed for inshore work.Cruisers and aircraft carriers.5. In order to pi&apos;provide for the most urgent and very large small-craftprogramme, it has been decided to ask for no new aircraft carriers this year andno cruisers of any kind, other than the six of the Dido class already approvedby the Treasury since the war, which were, in fact, in part substitution for twoof the four Fiji Class Cruisers of the programme approved by Parliament for1939-40.This must be regarded as a serious decision in naval policy appropriate tothe conflicting needs of the present and the future.Small craft, destroyers and beloiv.6. Destroyers. Sixteen were approved by Parliament for the programmeof 1939-40, and sixteen others, plus six requisitioned from Brazil, have beenapproved by the Treasury since the outbreak of war. It is proposed to buildsixteen more in the programme of 1940-41. Twenty escort destroyers of mediumsize were approved pre-war, and thirty-six since. It is proposed to include anotherthirty-four of these indispensable vessels of speedy completion in the programmeof 1940-41. Fifty-six whalers (anti-U-boat type for long distance action) were approved before the war, and sixty since the outbreak. It will be necessary to con-tinue filling their slips as fast as they are vacated, and I am advised that anotherthirty can be begun during 1940. This programme will be revised in the light ofthe U-boat war, and the North Sea Barrage.   Twenty-four submarines have been
approved since the war, and over sixteen more will be required in 1940-41;Twenty-two minesweepers have been similarly approved and twelve more are needed. Fifty-two trawlers are under construction and fifteen remain&apos; to be ordered under Treasury approval, and it is proposed to add another hundred in1940-41. To twenty boom-defence vessels already sanctioned, ten should beadded in the 1940-41 programme. About  10,000,000 will be required for additional mosquito craft (Motor Torpedo Boats, Motor Anti-Submarine Boats,Motor Launches, tugs, salvage vessels, yard craft, &amp;c). Treasury sanction will,of course, be sought in each individual case.7. To arrive at these figures it has been necessary to reduce the programmerecommended by the Sea Lords by nineteen submarines, twelve escort destroyers,and twenty whalers. The reduction has been made in order to set free moresteel for merchant shipbuilding. The preservation of the proper balance betweenNaval and Mercantile requirements of steel may be expected to become increasingly important.8. To sum up : the programmeconstruction sanctioned since the warCapital ships ...Aircraft carriers8-inch gun cruisers&quot; Dido &quot; class......&quot; Belfast &quot; classDestroyersEscort destroyersSubmarinesMinesweepers   ...Whalers ...Trawlers ...   ....Boom defence vessels ...together with the necessary mosquito craftof 1940-41,  plus the emergency newtogether amount to :-NilNilNil6Nil327040349014730(already sanctioned)(16 already sanctioned.plus 6 requisitioned)(36 already sanctioned)(24(22(60(47(209. It will be seen that the guiding principles of Admiralty policy in new construction for this year are to sacrifice the entire aircraft-carrier, cruiser and light cruiser construction (except light cruisers already approved by the Treasurysince the war) and to suspend with one single exception the normal capital shiplong-term programme in order to provide for the largest developments of the anti-U-boat and anti-mining flotillas.W. S. C.March 2, 1940.[20814b]b 2
TABLE I.1940 New Construction Programme.Type cf Ship.	Estimated Expenditure in 					Total.	1940.	1941.	1942.	1943.	-1944!	I5-in. Battle Cruiser Marshal Soult 16 Destroyers 34 Escort Destroyers       ... 30 Whalers......... 16 Submarines      ...       ... 12 Minesweepers   ... 10 Boom Defence Vessels 100 Trawlers Small Craft.........	400,000 1,100,000 3,700,000 3,150,000 2,600,000 3,500,000 750,000 350,000 2,700,000 3,000,000	2,000,000 4,850,000 8,800,000 790,000 3,300,000 1,080,000 450,000 4,300,000 6,000,000	2,600,000 750,000 2,300,000 1,000,000	2,500,000 150,000	400,000	8,509,000 1,100,000 9,300,000 14,400,000 3,390,000 6,800,000 1,830,000 800,000 7,000,000 10,000,000	21,250,000	32,170,000	6,650,000 j	2,650,000	400,000	63,120,000These estimates can only be regarded as approximations giving an indication on broad linesof the order of expenditure likely to be incurred.
TABLE II.Total Estimated Costs of New Construction by Financial Years.Note. These Estimates can only be regarded as approximations, giving an indication on broad lines of the order of expenditure likely to be incurred vear bv vear.1940.1941.1942.1943.Programmes up to and includingthe 1939 Approved Programme(excluding Conqueror andThunderer) ...       ...Additions to 1939 programme approved before the war (i.e.,long-term projects and addi-tional needs)War Emergency Programme and construction subsequentlyauthorised1940 New Construction Pro-gramme (Table I)Total    ......53,000,0004,900,00041,600,00021,250,000120,750,00025,500,000 j 11,000,000 j 4,500,000590,00015,950,000     3,200,00032,170,000 !   6,650,000 j 2,650,00074,210,000 I 20,850,000,150,000




</content>
</cab>
