<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 137-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
REPORT BY LIEUT.-COLONEL E.A.PLUNKETT, LIAISONOFFICER, AFTER THIRD VISIT TO SALONIGA, APRIL23rd - MAY 22nd.      (1) THE RECENT OFFENSIVE AND THE MILITARY SITUATION.      Twenty months have passed since the first arrival ofAllied troops at Salonica and so far no success of any realimportance has been gained, while cur recent failure andheavy losses have raised the morale of the Bulgars at amoment when it was low, and have proportionatelydiscouraged the Allied forces. Practically all the resultsobtained might equally well have been effected by holdingthe defensive positions round Salonica.      All cpinions, however, agree - including the FrenchGeneral Le Bcuc, who commands the French Army Group, andwho carried jut the main attack in the Loop of the Cerna -that an opportunity to deal a heavy blow at the enemyrecently existed.      In order to have any real ohance of gaining asuccess in future, drastic changes are necessary in theCommand and Staff at French Headquarters (see end of (c) .),and unless the French agree to make these changes, furtherexpenditure on the Salonica Army, beyond what is necessaryfor its safety, will be entirely wasted.          OUTLINE OF THE RECENT OFFENSIVE.        General Le Bouc summed up the offensive in thesewords, &quot;Pin-pricks everywhere and not even synchronised&quot;.Operatirns were oarried out on different parts of the lineas follows:-                                                  Night
NIGHT OF 24th/25th APRIL.  British 16th Corps attacked onL. DOIRAN - VARDAR front.Then ensued a long interval owing to a heavy fall of snowin the mountains,NIGHT OF 8th/9th MAY,  Second attack on above front,9th MAY.  2 French divisions, 3 Italian &quot;brigades and 1Russian brigade attacked in the Loop of the Cerna.11th MAY,  An attack on a smaller scale on the above front.16th MY.  Two French divisions attacked near Monastir.17th MY.  Small French attack in Loop of the Cerna.20th MY.  Serbian 2nd Army attacked the heights ofMOGLENITSA.     Serbian 1st Army (half of their total force) did notattack at all, because the offensive of the Serbian 2ndArmy failed.     Two French divisions (one in Group, and one in ArmyReserve) a short distance in rear, remained inactive duringthe CERNA operations.  These divisions were apparently ear-marked for employment against Greece.     During the above period, the British 16th Corps carriedcut with success various minor operations, as also theFrench 122 nd Division and the Greek Nationalist Divisionworking alongside, and the British 12th Corps gained asmall success on the night of 8th/9th Hay.  Otherwise, allthe various attacks were costly and unsuccessful.     The losses were, I believe, as follows    Britishabout 5,000, French 4,500, Italian 3,000, Russian 1,500.I left Salonika without hearing of the Serbian losses,but, although several units wero badly cut up, theirtotal losses were probably not groat,
2.  gtfdated oper-ions intoossion onfferentitions ofe front.vionoentrat-ck of Armyamander andfloieritneral Staff.ck ofeparation.     &apos;5flia general failure all along  the line  resulted  fromthe following causes     (a)  2he Salonika front is divided  into sections,from 33 to W, and is occupied by a great  admixture  ofnationalities as followsj-British, Frenoh and Greek, Serbian  (with Russian Brigadeattached), French (with Russian Brigade  attached),Italian, French.          Each of the above (except in the case of  onecombined attack by French and Italians)  carried out anindependent operation of its own,     (b)  No attempt was made to withdraw troope frompart of the line and to conoentrate with a view toattacking in depth and breaking through  at any point                               4or points.     (c)  General Sarrail is not in touoh with thedifferent armies at Salonika and entirely lacks theconfidence of the troops under his command.          During the operations he did not,  either  bypersonal visits or by means of Staff officers, keephimself adequately informed of the situation on thedifferent parts of the front,          The result was the series of isolated andharmless attacks desoribed above, all of which theenemy easily dealt with in succession,     (d)  General Le Bouc informed me that owing to laokof time no preparations had been made for the mainattack, such as are necessary for a suooessful attackon m organised defensive position.It
    It will be seen from trie above that practically allthe trouble at Salonika begins and ends with the presencethere of General Sarrail.    Though a man of great personality, who at firstcreates a most favourable impression, he has shownlittle military capacity. When speaking of militarymatters he gives the impression of not having his heartin the business, and har. at Salonika acquired the univer-sal reputation of being interested in politics ratherthan in war-.    He has got rid of several Staff Officers, whose viewson the military situation differed from his own, and hasnow as Chief of Staff General Michaud, who is content towork as Sarrail directs, but who is generally regardedin the Allied Armies as quite incompetent.                                4(3).   FUTURE MILITARY POSSIBILITIES.  VIEWS OF               GENERAL LE BOUC.On 9th May at the French front I discussed the situationat length with General Le Bouc who commands the FrenchArmy group which carried out the main attack.    General Le Bouc spoke with the utmost candour of thefutility of the recent operations, and said that beforethe offensive began he had protested to General Sarrailagainst the latter&apos;s proposed conduct of operations.                                            General
jsful;ivepossibleortumn.t events that  arainedk wouldV7onzh.     General Le Douc stated definitely that in his  opinion:-        (a) -..:e had missed an opportunity of breaking through            the enemy front and gaining a decisive  success, and        (b) The opportunity would probably a^ain occur  in  the            autumn, a more favourable time as regards weather            than the Spring.     General Le Bouc further said that he had submitted adetailed plan for the Cerna attack which was not accepted  by-General Barrall. This plan involved the concentration underone command of the following force                4. French divisions.                o Italian brigades                2 Russian brigades.                Serbian 1st  :rmy (3 weak divisions).                V/ith, if possible, 1 or 2 British divisions.     The general idea was to break through in the Cerna loop,with the main force * and to keep back the Serbian 1st Army inorder to push on through the gap and exploit the success,  onaccount of their greater marching powers and endurance.Judging from the fact that part of a Russian Regiment, withoutthe help of reserves, actually broke through and reached thevillage of Orle, which is some distance in rear of thehostile defensive lines, Le Bouc&apos;s plan should at least havegained some considerable success.Although
     Although their success was possible, andmay again be possible in the future, it willbo a pure waste to send men and material toSalonika, beyond the minimum essential to thesecurity of the force which it is decided toleave there, unless the French agree to replaceSarrail,.    His successor must be a Generalwho will confine his attention to the conductof military operations, and who has the abilityand prestige and personality necessary todominate and command the mixed force.-  at Salonika.The military problem on this front is diffioultenough to tax the powers of the best commander,and nothing but the best will be of any use.     Further, the carnmander should have - Iagain quote General Le Bouc - a General Staffcomprising one officer of each nation represent-ed at Salonika, and,a specially selected officeras Chief of Staff.  ,                - .          4. POSSIBILITY OF A WITHDRAWAL TO             WltHIrt THE SALONIKA DEPEttflBS OR             ALTOGETHER FROM SALONIKXT-     Lt. General Milne considers that at thisstage a withdrawal would have a deplorable effect.      The Serbians would, at the first,sign of aretreat prwbably desert wholesale, and we shouldalso leave exposed to possible ill-treatment bythe enemy all the inhabitants in rear of ourlines who have been working fer us er friendly to           5. THE SERBIAN ARMY.    I discussed the situation with the Chief ofStaff, Serbian Army, who is a first rate officerand highly, thought of by the Allied Staffs, justaftor General Sarrail had ordered the offensiveto cease.
        He V7U.3 very aiscourged ana  stuitea that  the  ^uetrianswere oarrying on aetive propaganda among the  Serbian troops.according to him they might be able  to hold the  Army togetherfor another tnree or four uionths, out if it oecuue evident  tothe men that they were destined to spena the  remaining periodof the war on the Macedonian mountains withtut anypreppect oftii ititut, their way back into serbia  they would prooably  disperseand r^o over to the Austri-dne.  tempting offers have  been madeto them to go back to their land and families, and they  were a]-ready inclined to say that when their officers spoke to  them ofthe allies helping them to recover their country they were  de-ceiving them.       Should the Serbian Army be lost, our position rn  theSalonika front would be materially .,e.s.^ana-i,  i&apos;or the purposeof Macedonian warfare they are superior to any European  troopsowing to their endurance and marching powers, and they would bedifficult to replace.       It may be argued that txiere c^n be no  real danger of theSerbians &amp;cing over to their traditional enemies, the Austrians,and in the ease of the upper classes this is  probably true.       It should be remembered,  however,  that the soldiers  areall pes*e iiits,  that liicny of them have now been under  arms con- tinuously for five years,  that they have suffered most  severehardships, and that they are generally iterant  of tne con-dition cf their homes and families.   AU invitation  to go backand resume work on their farms must  appeal to them,   if theysee no chance of fighting their v/ay back.
EMPLOYMENT OF GREEK NATIONALIST TROOPS.      Sarrail has as yet shown no intention to makefull use of the Greeks, of whom there will shortly beat Salonica three divisions.      These men are all volunteers, of good physiqueand very keen on doing their best.  They are nearlyall trained Reservists, many cf whom have seen serviceduring the Balkan wars.      In January last the 16th British Corps Commander,who had at the time some Greek units under his command,spoke highly of them and said he could do with asmany more as were available while during the recentfighting they have done good work alongside the French.Though not first class troops, it is probable that ifproperly treated they would fight at least as wellas some of the French colonial troops.                                4       The Greek troops at Salonica are discouragedby their unsympathetic treatment by the French, -Sarrail is reported to have said that they were onlyfit to make roads &amp;o. in rear of the army - andunless they are better treated,  they will not do thegood work of which they are capable.                                E.A.PLUNKETT.WAR OFFICE,1-6-1917.                                Lt.-Col.,                                              G.S.

</content>
</cab>
