<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 248-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Despatch Uo. 115.  - ;.,ajor Croat, Military -ittache7, Madrid.     I have tho honour to report that the French militaryAttaohe,  General Denvignes had an interesting audience yes tor-   imparted to mo.        His iia^aety told General ^onvignes that Germany was   more poworfni than the Allies thought,  and in a poo it ion &amp;o   resist for a very long time yet.   His latest information froa   Austria however  was that that country,  rurkey and Bulgaria,   were completely  exhausted.   Ho thought  it possible that the   Italians would take rrioots, but  considered that if they did   BO thoy would fool thoy had accomplished enough, and would   put an ond to their offensive. Uo said that,  though Austria   mi^ht apparently be billing to discuss  terms of poaoe,  the   :i -eror hold that to make a separate  peace would be an  act   of treason to Germany.  If,  however,  Italy could continue her   offsnsive through the month of Juno and possibly of July, and   HUBSia could also be persuaded to attach,  than Austria  would   be obliged to ask for very  substantial  help from, Co many, which   that country would be unable to afford.  L&apos;he Amperer of Austria   would then consider hieiself at perfect  liberty to negotiate   a  separate peace.  Ho was apparently  of opinion the Allies   would not be able to make this combined and sustained effort,   but eaid that, if thsy could,  another month or two or evenExcellency                                            week -he  lit. Hon.     Sir Arthur Harding, ;  .  .u.t  ;,,,B,           etc., ate,  etc.                        xday with the King of ;;pain, some details of which he has
week or two, might see the end of the war. As regards food, he was convinced that the Central Powers would be able to hold out until the crops came in, and considered that, unless Austria were detached, the war would drag on into another winter, and most probably end in an inconclusive peace.

I have considered His Majesty&apos;s views on Austria, as given me by General Denvignes, worth reporting to Yours Excellency, as he is so closely connected with that country and has, as a rule such excellent information about it.

                                                                       I have the honour to be,

                                                                           Sir,

                                                                       Your Excellency&apos;s most                                                                         obedient,

                                                                       humble servant.

                                                              (Sd.) Josceline  C.H. Grant, Major

                                                                           Military Attaché.

 

</content>
</cab>
