<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 256-256</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                              219S S C g E T.G.T.- 954                 I A E   CABINET.PBOPUCTION OF DRIED POTATOES AND          POTATO jtOUg.   (Note by Sir Alfred Mona).    In view of the \rery largely increased acreage that hasbeen planted with potatoes,  it would not appear unlikelytnat there may be a considerable over-production of potatoes.The result of this will be to lead to a somewhat immediateglut and low prices, unless  some steps are taken to regulateand conserve the supply between the present and next year.In view of the position which arose last year, owing to noprecautions having been taken, the available supply ofpotatoes ran out for all practical purposes before the newcrop came in,  and, therefore it would seem essential thatthe Pood Controller^ Department should seriously considermethods of avoiding a repetition of this state of things.     In connection with this matter, I would like to drawattention to the question of the production of driedpotatoes and cf potato flour.  Both these materials areused on a very large scale in Germany, and the use ofpotato flour has, undoubtedly, largely helped that countryto eke out the insufficient  cereal supply.  I am not awarewhether any plant for this purpose exists in this country,but information on this point should be easily obtainable,or if it is not, should be obtainable from countriessimilarly situated to Germany on the Continent.     I observe from the Daily Notes, No. 625 of the WarTrade Intelligence Department that the Swedish Governmenthas granted a subsidy of 750,000 kronor for the purposeof erecting potato drying kilns.   If anything is to bedone in this country this year, immediate steps shouldbe taken to investigate this problem and the necessaryplant should be erected and  ready to operate beforeNovember of this year, when  the main crop will belifted.(Initialled)   A.M.H.M. Office  of Vorks.      5th June,  1917.

</content>
</cab>
