<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 327-334</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property,of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]Printed for the War Cabinet.  June 1917.NAVAL  WEEKLY APPRECIATION, 2. There is  no change in the general situation.                        SUBMARINE ATTACK ON TRADE.    THE following tables indicate the intensity of the submarine  attack on  tradedaring the past week :     Comparison of the tonnage and number of  British ships entering or clearing toor from the United Kingdom, with the amount lost by submarine and mine en routeto or from ihe United Kingdom.                    Period 2Sth May Zrd June (inclusive).      British Vessels Overseas Voyages (including French Bay and Norway).No.	Arrivals.	Sailings.		Sunk by Submarine or Mine, &amp;c.*							Tonnage.	No. A.	Tonnage. B.	To United Kingdom.			From United Kingdom.			Other Voyages.A. A.				No.	Tonnage.	Per cent. of A.	1 No. 1 Tonnage. I		Per writ. of 13.	112	514,850	97	515,624		42,147	Vessels 8-0:3 Tonnage 8-11	4	13,178	Vessels 4-12 Tonnage 2-05	Nil* Exclusive of commissioned vessels and troopships.Xumber of  Ships sunk by Submarine and Mines during each of the last three Weeks.Week ending 	i3ritish Ships.		Allied and Neutral Vessels.	Over 1,600 tons.	Under 1,600 tons.	June 3 .. May 26 .. May 19..	15 18 18	3 1 9	38 40 19    Submarines have been particularly active to the north and north-west  of Scotlandand Ireland, and traffic was suspended in this area on the 3rd June.    The comparatively few sinkings on the South of Ireland route are probably due toa more effective patrol of  the approach  route by  the United States  destroyers  fromQueenstown.    The first Atlantic convoy which left the U.S.A. on the 24th May should arrive inport on the 8th June.  Another convoy of twelve merchantmen left Hampton Roads ont&amp;e 4th June under escort of H.M.S. &quot; Carnarvon.&quot;      [649 2J
2    The English Channel has been singularly free from mines this week, the &quot; U.C.&quot;boats having apparently concentrated their efforts on the east coast.    On the 2nd June the transport &quot; Cameronian &quot; was sunk by a submarine in thevicinity of Alexandria, sixty-three officers and men being reported  as missing.   Threeother British ships were sunk in the Mediterranean during the  week.    The Japanese Government has  approved of the despatch of four recently com-pleted  torpedo-boat  destroyers to the  Mediterranean, where they  should  arrive inAugust.  The following Japanese naval forces are now working  in direct co-operationwith the British :     In  the  Mediterranean, one light cruiser and eight destroyers  for escort and anti-submarine  duties ;  escorting Australian troop  transports in the Indian Ocean andPacific, three armoured cruisers and six light cruisers; patrolling in vicinity of MalaccaStraits, two light cruisers.    Twenty-four American torpedo-boats are now operating  off  the  south coast ofIreland.                          OPERATIONS IN THE ADRIATIC.    A further report has been received of the action which took place on the 14th Maybetween the British cruisers &quot;Dartmouth&quot; and  &quot;Bristol&quot;  and three Austrian lightcruisers.   The Austrians were returning from raiding the Otranto Straits patrol.  TheBritish cruisers were accompanied by Italian torpedo craft, the Allied force being underthe command of Rear-A.dmiral Acton, Royal Italian Navy.    The action developed into a running fight at indecisive ranges, the chase beingeventually abandoned by the Italian Admiral owing to the approach of Austrian battle-ships  from Cattaro.   One of the Austrian cruisers is believed to have been seriouslydamaged by gun fire.    Unfortunately the &quot; Dartmouth &quot; was torpedoed by a submarine on her way backto Brindisi, but. she remained afloat and was eventually  towed into harbour.   A Frenchdestroyer was also sunk by a mine whilst leaving Brindisi to take part in the action.    The raid and the resulting action must  be viewed as a minor  operation, but itshows how quickly offensive action on one side or the other brings about results, evenin the Adriatic, which, throughout  the war, has  more nearly approached  a state ofabsolute stalemate than any other main theatre of operations.    The operation also illustrates the importance of concerted action between differentarms.   The  guns of the Austrian  cruisers would by themselves merely have made anoise  compared with the  immeasurably  greater  results  that were obtained by  co-ordination between the gun, torpedo, and mine.    Despatches  have also  been received from the Rear-Admiral Commanding theBritish Adriatic Squadron describing the bombardment of  the aerodrome and railwayjunction  at  Preseno  by the  monitors &quot; Earl of Peterborough  &quot; and &quot; Sir ThomasPicton &quot; on  the  24th May, the intention  being to assist in  the advance of  the Italianarmy.   The  monitors, which were accompanied by Italian  torpedo-craft, were heavilyattacked by enemy aircraft  flying low, and also by a somewhat feeble  fire from theshore  batteries.    Good results appear to have been obtained by the British gunfire, and two Austrianseaplanes were brought  down by  Italian aircraft and British  anti-aerial  guns, theoccupants being made prisoners.                          OPERATIONS IN DOVER AREA.    The Royal Naval Air Service have during the last week successfully bombed thefollowing places on the Belgian coast:          Seaplane base at Ostend. once.         Zeebrugge mole and shipping, three times.         Bruges docks and  shipping, four times.         Naval workshops and docks at Ostend, once.         St. Denis Westrem aerodrome, once.
    On  the  5th instant the naval workshops at Ostend were bombarded by monitors,with light cruisers aud destroyers from  Harwich  covering  the operation.  Navalaircraft were also of great, assistance in correcting the fall of shot  and driving off theenemy aircraft.  A running fight at long range ensued between the covering force and&quot;six  of the enemy destroyers.   One of the latter  was sunk and another  seriouslydamaged.  Our ships had no casualties.    On the 26th May two small monitors and the destroyer &apos;: Leven &quot; engaged at longrange four enemy &quot;destroyers  about 12 miles north of Dunkerque.   After  a shortengagement the enemy retired.                        OPERATIONS IN THE NORTH SEA.    On the 25th to 26th May the aeroplane carrier &quot; Manxman &quot; was sent  out fromRosyth, accompanied  by two light cruisers and seven  destroyers, to search an areaabout 130 miles to the eastward of Tynemouth for Zeppelins.   Nothing was seen.    A telegram has been received from His Majesty&apos;s Minister in Norway stating thatthree British  destroyers are  reported to have chased a German merchant ship intoNorwegian  territorial waters and  torpedoed her.   The Commander-in-Chief, GrandFleet, reports that she was  flying German  colours and refused to obey the  order toheave to.   The matter is being enquired into.              SUMMARY OF NAVAL  INTELLIGENCE.   Export of Swedish Ore in Baltic from Oxeldsund to Germany.During week ending April 28th, 1917  ...       ...    34,363 tons.      ,,        ,,   May 5th    ,,    ...       ...    29,515  ,,                   May 12th        ...       ...    47,213  ,,                              AIR INTELLIGENCE.1. General Information.    (a.) With  reference to the attack on the  steamship &quot; Birchgrove &quot; reported lastweek, it has been ascertained that  the torpedo-carrying seaplanes are of the Brand en-burger  type, and have twin 150-h.p. engines.   Their speed in still  air  is 52 knots(about GO statute miles an hour).  They carry an 18-inch Whitehead torpedo, weighingabout 1,680 lb.    (b.) It is reported that preparations are being  made on a large scale for aeroplaneraids on England.    (c.) According to the press, a &quot; Government Air  Traffic  Bill&quot;  will  shortly bepresented to the Reichstag for the establishment of a &quot; Central European Air TrafficSystem.&quot;2. German Rigid Airships.    Number known to have been destroyed since the war, 19.    Number reported to have been destroyed since the war, 31.    Approximate number of naval airships in existence,  21.    Approximate number of military airships in existence, 20.WEEKLY INTELLIGENCE REPORT, JUNE 6, 1917.                                    Brazil.    On the 1st June, Brazil revoked her neutrality as  regards Germany and U.S.A.,and the Government was authorised to act similarly towards other Entente Powers inreturn for facilities for free importation and exportation.
Brazil wants from us :     Removal of coffee from the prohibited list of import?.    Freight for other national produce.    Material for naval construction and  repair.    Assistance from Armstrong^ to finish the half-constructed dock at Rio.    Possibly a loan.Brazil could lielp Great Britain in following ways:      Opening ports to our men of war   ...   Not of so much importance now that U.F.                                            Squadron is patrolling Brazilian coast.     Docking our ships at Rio ...       ...   They have been doing this throughout the                                            war.     Patrolling Amazon when raider is in  They have been asked to do this.       the vicinity.     Giving  Great Britain  a  share in the  Apparently the U.S.A.  are to repair  and       German tonnage seized.               will presumably control these ship;-;.                                     Russia.    Baltic. There is no information of any operations by the  Fleet.  Ilelsingforsappears to be settling down after the visit of Kerensky, but at Kronstadt the Councilof \Vorkmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Deputies appears to be in open revolt against the ProvisionalGovernment and trouble is feared, especially as many of  the troops in  Petrograd  arebelieved to be unreliable.    Black Sea. A controversy has lately arisen between Admiral Kolchak, Commander-in-Chief, Black Sea  Fleet, and the  Council of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos;  Delegates atSevastopol, in  which Admiral  Kolchak  threatened  resignation.   The  matter  has,however, been settled in his favour, to the satisfaction of all parties.  Admiral Kolchak&apos;sname has been mentioned as a possible dictator for all Russia.    The following characteristics of  Admiral Kolchak have been received  :          &quot;He is  a man brought up  in Admiral von Essens school, and has many of    his former chiefs characteristics.  He is bold, shrewd, and energeiic.         &quot;He appears to be the strongest  and most  able personality  of all Russian    naval officers, and has dealt with the situation in the  Black Sea with vigour  and     decision.  His handling of the fleet at the time of the revolution  was very tactful,     and gained the confidence of all ranks and ratings.&quot;                                    Sweden.    German  submarines operating  in  the Gulf of Bothnia have sunk  six  Swedishvessels, and three others have been seized and sent to Swinemiinde.    German  airships have been active off the Sound and East Coast of Sweden, and ilis reported that Swedish T.B.&apos;s fired on a Zeppelin in the neighbourhood of  Ystad,since the latter was cruising over territorial waters.    Naval Staff,         June 7,  1917.

SECRET  THE  WORLDSUBMARINES.o IVtrograd....... AREA	JZsttni numb er 1-	cutccL s out) on. Types	JVuntber of&apos; AttxLcTtx by &apos; MM Ships	Number of \ attacJtS by J[nrriiimt, -Shipi	Estimated/ vaTuue of attacks			1	V Type.			tin ft oilier vessels	Known,	Probable Possible Improbable		A					-------		I	B		J		\				C		z					--	D	3		z				-	___/__	1							F	If							/__G	Z	1						H			t													Totals	Zl	9	/&amp;	- * 1			&quot;z		&quot;X&quot; This estimate cannot he very reliabbj, t oiv the telegraphic reports only.				is it is ma/iJxi			RAIDERS. NUMBER OUT last definite posilioru and date irv RED Last report which TrvcLy refer to Slap iiv BLACK.								R&quot;ftDirgo Gnrr^A(jMmufililUi-3!&quot;.iW    T^to-^S&apos;C 1  \&apos;-.12 0&quot;MO&quot;160&quot;  EmI flPrepared Taj the HydrograpMoDep^ of the Admirally 23r.aMay, 1917 , under the Superintendence of l^iir^Adnnral J.F.Parry, C.B.Hyarogmpb.e]
&apos; R^ar-Aamiral J.EParry, C.B..Hyarographer.


</content>
</cab>
