<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 339-342</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>

liny further communications should beLed&apos; not to any individual by name,L SECRETARY,r D 0F Agriculture for Scotland,f&quot;&quot; 29 St. Andrew Square,             Edinburoh.&quot;Undents are requested :-[auote the Number, Bate, and HeadingLrA W&quot;&quot;- to   they rePly&apos;i MldL ,w communications on different subjectsLn separate tetters.j    itfb...................jjaphio Address-&quot; BOAS, EDINBURGH.&quot;BOARD OF  AGRICULTURE  FOR SCOTLAND,                  29 ST.  ANDREW SQUARE,                                 EDINBURGH.                          1st  June,  1917.       Sir,                         SHEEP  SHEARERS *                   I am directed by the Board of,Agriculture for       Scotland to state that they have been  in  communication       with  the National Service Department on the subject of       the supply of qualified  men for the sheep shearing season,       and have been informed that the War Office  have issued an       Order to Commanding Offloors asking them  to deal promptly       with  all applications for such men and to grant them       agricultural furlough for a period not exceeding one       month provided the men applied for can be spared from       their units.   No men in Category HA&quot;  are to be sent, but       those in lower categories will, as far as possible, be       made  available.                   The general  procedure to be followed by       Dlstriot Agricultural Committees in dealing with appli-       oations  for sheep shearers le indioated in  the following       extract  from a communication received  from  the National       Servioe  Department.                   &quot;It would be well that you should instruct       your  Food Production Committees to ascertain in time the       number of men whose services are really necessary to       farmers  /The Secretary,    District Agricultural Committee,
farmers for this class of work.          In each case the Reports should be made by theCommittee to the Sub-Commissioner of Agriculture for theDistrict in order that the regular procedure may befollowed in meeting the demands as far as this can be done.It would be well if the farner, when making the demand forlabour, could name a particular soldier, giving his name,number, Company, Unit and present Depot, in order that theapplication might be made from this Office for tho servicesof the particular man.   As you will see, there is no uso inapplying for any man in Category &quot;AM, but if a man in alower Category can be indicated, it would facilitate thisDepartment in obtaining the soldier,  as otherwise we have nomeans of ascertaining what shepherds are available through-out Units in Scotland.          If there is likely to be any pressing demand forthis class of labour,  it would be advisable that requestsshould be mads at as early a date as  possible.M                      I  am,  Sir,                          Your obedient Servant,                                H.  M.  OONAOHSR                                      Secretary.
MEMORANDUM  to AGRICULTURAL EXECUTIVE COMMITTEES.                      LABOUR.          The Board have received representatione  to  theeffect that jn some districts agricultural  labourers  are,notwithstanding the necessity for increased food production,failing to put in a full day&apos;e work  and  it  has  thereforebeen considered desirable to print  in leaflet  form theappeal recently made by the  Prime Minister.  Ten  copiesOf this leaflet are enclosed, and the Board would  be  gladif Committees would arrange  for its  distribution to farmworkers in any part of their district where they considerthat such a step is necessary.   The required number  ofcopies of the leaflet will be forwarded  on  application.BOARD  OP  AGRICULTURE  POR  SCOTLAND,        29 Stt- Androw Square,            EDINBURGH.      .  .        6th June,  1917 .

</content>
</cab>
