<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 358-360</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
          On May 8th. I reported to the War cabinet thatthere was a shortage of at least 100,000 gallons a week ofspirits needed for war and for essential industrial purposes.The War Cabinet then, decided (War Cabinet 134,  Minute 12) that -&quot;the Minister of Munitions should requisition the necessaryspirits from bond, paying the owners cost of production,plus a reasonable profit, but not the present highly inflatedprices.&quot;          Before taking action in this sense, I referred thepoint to the Advisory Committee on Alcohol supplies, arepresentative Body which I had appointed earlier in theyear to advise me in these matters.  The Report of thisCommittee has been received and has already been circulatedto the War Cabinet (Memorandum C.T. 867).          It will be seen from this Report that the shortageof spirit is now about 500,000 proof gallons per month andthat the shortage is likely to rise to a considerably higherfigure later in the year.  The Committee, after consideringthe various proposals for meeting this shortage, State thatin their opinion the most desirable course would be toincrease the output of molasses spirit by augmenting thequantity/
quantity of molasses now available for distilling.   Forreasons summarised on page 7v of their Report,  they havefelt unable to recommend the withdrawal of spirit frombond and its distillation to the required strength.In order to give effect to their proposal, the  Committeefurther recommend that the five tank steamers engagedin the molasses traffic should be retained on this serviceand that later in the year, if possible,  one or twoother steamers should be diverted to the. same traffic.The list of steamers so engaged at the time of  thepresentation of the Report is given in paragraph 27.         : The question of the best means  for meetingthe undoubted shortage- of spirit which exists has nowbeen raised; in an acute form by the action of theShipping Controller . in; withdrawing the 7,Manx I3les&quot;,one. of.the five tank steamers: engaged on&apos;the molassestraffic,, in order:.to-divert it to the transport ofNavy fuel. .          If this policy is to be maintained, I shallhave no alternative but to.give immediate effect, on aconsiderable scale, to the War Cabinet instruction withregard to the withdrawal of spirits from  bond.   I am notsatisfied, however, that the serious Political  and -financial/                                 ;.-
8th June,  1917,financial issues involved have been fully taken intoaccount, or that the intimate connection between thequestion of commandeering stocks  and the question  ofcompensation for goodwill in the  case  of the best  knownwhisky brands has been thoroughly considered.  Beforetaking action, I should therefore be glad to receivefurther instructions from the War Cabinet..

</content>
</cab>
