<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/15/0 images: 400-402</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.Intelligence Bureau.341Department of Information.DBTS/008.WEEKLY REPORT ON BULGARIA. VIII.    i   I------....      ,, .       (June 8, 1917).Bulgarian Socialist Delegations  to  Stockholm.     On their way to Stockholm the Delegations representing thetwo Bulgarian Socialist parties spent some time in Berlin.It will be remembered that the &quot;Narrow&quot; (pacifist) Socialistparty refused the two places offered them in the officialSocialist Delegation.  These were accordingly filled by twoother &quot;Broad&quot; Socialists,  Asen Tsankov and Pastukhov, thuscompleting a Delegation of six.  The Narrow Socialistssubsequently sent independently two delegates of their own,Kolarov and Kirkov.   They left nearly a week after the BroadSocialists, but met  in Berlin.  The Broad Socialist organNarod and the independent paper Utro contain a series of lettersfrom Tsankov as to their reception and impressions of Berlin.Tsankov asserts that Kirkov&apos;s explanations of the aims of hisparty as regards peace were listened to with great misgiving,not only by the Majority Socialists in Germany, but also by theHaase group, and declares that this latter group, on the otherhand, entirely assented to the aims set forward by the BroadSocialists of &quot;the national union of Bulgaria, which is notconsidered annexation&quot;.  The Narrow Socialist organ RabotnicheskiVestnik makes great  fun of this assertion and declares that theBroad Socialists are at least good at self-advertisement, ifat nothing else.     From Berlin the Socialists proceeded to Copenhagen and thenceto Stockholm.  In Copenhagen the Broad Socialists found a
                            -2-congenial soul  in Mr Borbjerg,  the notorious pro-German DanishSocialist leader, and Tsankov sends an account of a conversationwith him showing that they were both practically agreed as towar aims.  Since their arrival  in Stockholm both Sakarov andSakyzov, on behalf of the Broad Socialists, have given inter *views to the Swedish press, and have put forward very stronglythe Bulgarian national demands  for the incorporation of Dobrogeaand Macedonia in the Kingdom.Other Important Visits.     According  to a late wire Mr Radoslavov has left for Berlinaccompanied by  the chief of Tsar Ferdinand&apos;s political Cabinet.Other people of importance who  have recently been paying visitsare Dr ^eisskircnner, Burgomaster of Vienna, and the famousWar Correspondent Roda-Roda.  Everything possible is apparentlybeing done to fit together the  peace intrigues of Bulgaria andthe Central Powers,Occupied Territories.     As usual considerable attention is being paid to theBulgarisation of the occupied territories.   The Utro (May 23)announces that  the Minister of  Public Instruction (Peshev)is well satisfied with the result of the first school examinationsin the Morava Valley.  It must  be especially gratifying toMr Peshev and his colleagues that the labour and money they havespent in forcing Bulgarian culture on the conquered Serbianpopulation are  having the results they hoped for.  In &quot;Old&quot; Serbiagenerally the regime of extortion continues.  The DistrictGovernor of Prokuplje, which has recently been th^ centre ofthe Serbian rising repressed &apos;by the Bulgarian authorities with
such brutality, has now managed to raise  3,796  leva  ( 160)  forthe Bulgarian Red Cross, and  has been  congratulated  by the  Societyon his  success.  It might have been  thought  that  the populationof Prokuplje were more in need of this money than the people,whoever they are, for whom  it is needed.     The festival of St. Cyril and St. Methodius  v/as celebratedthroughout Bulgaria and the occupied territories  on  May 24, andv/as a great occasion for patriotic and chauvinistic  displays.Harodni Prava  (May 26) contains a page and a half of telegramsfrom different Bulgarian colonies in Dobrogea dilating on theentirely Bulgarian character  of the  province and  the necessityfor its permanent union with  Bulgaria.Economic Conditions.     The Utro  (May 23) declares that during  the past two daysthere have been heavy rains in many  places,  with  an  excellent  resultas regards harvest prospects.  This  yea^s harvest in Bulgariapromises to be &quot;one of the  best in Europe&quot;.Bulgarian  Intrigues Abroad.     The Bulgarian press on May 26 announces that in order  toestablish  good relations between Bulgaria and Latin  Switzerland,so important educationally  to Bulgarian  students, the BulgarianGovernment has decided on the creation of a  Consulate General  atGeneva. Mr Milchev, himself  an old  student  of  the University  ofGeneva, has been chosen for this post.  The  obvious  intention  is  toconduct a  counter-campaign  to that carried on by  the SerbianPress Bureau in Geneva.                                             A.W.A.L.                                                 June 8,  1917.

</content>
</cab>
