<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/50/47 images: 460-470</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1975CM (72) Copy No. 0146th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Wednesday, 25 October, 1972at 11.30 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth Affairs(Items 1 and 2)The. Right Hon. Anthony Barber,mp,  Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for Defence (items-4)The Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy Seal (Items 1-4)The Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustryhe Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Secretary of State for northern ireland the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord President ofthe council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Chancellor of the duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for employment the following were also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,   The Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury qc,mp, Attorney-General (Items 4-6)
Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. J. B. hunt mr. H. F. T. smith mr. K. T. barnett mr. J. anson mr. I. T. lawman contents item Subject page 1     Oversea Affairs.....................      3Icelandic Fisheries DisputeVietnam2     European Summit Meeting   ...............      33 The Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament ... 54    Northern Ireland     ..................      55     Industrial Affairs     ..................      5Meetings with the Confederation of British Industryand the Trades Union CongressPay Negotiations in the Electricity Supply industry     Housing Finance Act..................      8
SECRETEuropean 2.   The Prime Minister said that the/Communique issued atSummit the end of the Summit Meeting of the enlarged European Corn-Meeting munity in the previous week showed substantial progress in mostfields and was a remarkable achievement for a two-day Conferenceeven though the ground had been carefully prepared by foreign ministers and officials in advance. From the United Kingdom&apos;spoint of view we could be well content with the results. As long ago as May we had defined our Summit aims as a balanced approach to economic and monetary union; a date for the introduction of a regional policy which would take account of the needs of the oversea Affairs 1. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the icelandic Prime Minister had sent the Icelandic Prime Minister a messageFisheries suggesting that negotiations about the current fisheries disputeDispute should be resumed.   The Icelandic Government, however, werePrevious        seeking to insist that any further discussions must include considera-Reference:      tion of some limitation on the sizes and types of our trawlers. the cm (72) 45th   industry would probably be willing to give some private assurances,Conclusions,    in general terms, about the nature of the fishing fleet in the fore-Minute 2       seeable future; but we could not accept any formal or publiccommitment in this respect, especially as regards the use of freezervessels, since, although we did not use vessels of this kind in the fishing grounds off Iceland, we must try to avoid creating a precedentwhich could have consequences in other parts of the world.  If it proved impossible to resume negotiations, naval frigates wouldprobably have to be sent into the 50 mile zone; and the practiceof fishing in &quot; havens &quot; would have to be adopted, with damaging consequences for the size of the British catch.Vietnam The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that littledetailed information was so far available about the most recent negotiations conducted in Hanoi and Saigon by Dr. Kissinger, thechief adviser on national security to the President of the UnitedStates, President Nixon. The discussions in Hanoi seemed to havemade some progress; but the President of South Viet-Nam was apparently seeking to insist that a cease-fire should depend uponcertain conditions which the North Viet-Namese Government would find it difficult to accept. In particular he was trying to secure anundertaking that a cease-fire would be accompanied by the with-drawal of all North Vietnamese forces from South Vietnam. it now seemed doubtful, therefore, whether a cease-fire would beachieved before the Presidential Election in the United States; butPresident Nixon had probably demonstrated his desire for anhonourable peace sufficiently clearly to ensure that the Vietnamesewar would not constitute a major obstacle in his electoral campaign.The Cabinet-Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary.
enlarged Community; progress on industrial policy and the removalof non-tariff barriers; a Community energy policy; a common and positive approach to the next multilateral trade negotiations;progress on political co-operation; and action in the context of aidpolicy to alleviate the indebtedness of the hardest pressed countries.We had substantially secured all these objectives except the last.The German Government had been unwilling to accept any newcommitment on aid for the time being; and the French Governmentwould not agree to any waiver of debt service. The agreed formula,however, left it open to us to raise this matter afresh at a later date.The level of discussion at the Conference had been high, except fora prolonged and largely irrelevant argument about direct elections to the European Assembly, which the Dutch Government had insti-gated for internal political reasons. There had been general regret at the absence of the Norwegian Government, for whom it was accepted that some special arrangement must be found, even thoughit could not comprise the advantages of full membership of theCommunity.In addition he had also had separate and detailed discussions with the President of France, M. Pompidou, and the Chancellor ofthe Federal German Republic, Herr Brandt. He had explained our policy as regards economic and monetary union to the french president; and the latter had not raised difficulties about the timing of our return to a fixed parity. He had also taken the opportunityto emphasise to M. Pompidou our view that discussion of the projected Mediterranean Agreements should not be conducted ina way which would unduly alarm the United States Government.The discussions about the enlargement of the Community, thenegotiations in connection with the European Free Trade Area non-candidate members and, more recently, the extensive preparations for the Summit Meeting had so preoccupied the Community for thepast year as effectively to prevent decisions on future developments in advance of our accession. We now had an opportunity to play a leading role in these developments. The agreements reached atthe Summit Meeting, however, were necessarily expressed in termsof major objectives of policy; and much hard work would now berequired in order to secure their detailed implementation. TheMinisters concerned should therefore satisfy themselves that their departmental organisations were adequate to this new and additionalfunction and that the staffs involved were equipped with the qualities of temperament and judgment which would be needed in the subse-quent negotiations.The Cabinet- /Took note, with approval, of the statement by the PrimeMinister.
The Queen&apos;sSpeech on theOpening ofParliamentPreviousReference:CM (72) 45thConclusions,Minute 5NorthernIrelandPreviousReference:CM (72) 45thConclusions,Minute 6SECRET4. The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland informed theCabinet of recent developments in Northern Ireland. His statement and the conclusions reached were recorded separately, and issuedonly to The Queen, the Prime Minister and those Ministers who hadto take action.The conclusions are recorded separately in the standard file held by the Secretary of the Cabinet.IndustrialAffairsMeetingswith theConfederationof BritishIndustryand theTrades UnionCongressPreviousReference:CM (72) 45thConclusions,Minute 3SECRET5. The Prime Minister said that there would be a furthertripartite meeting on the following day between the Government, the confederation of British Industry (CBI) and the Trades UnionCongress (TUC) about prices and incomes policy. Since the last meeting special working groups under the aegis of the national economic Development Office had been examining the problems involved in implementing a flat-rate pay increase and in ensuring an effective system of price restraint. Representatives of the retailtrade, who had been brought into consultation, had put forward proposals for restraint on retail prices which appeared reasonable.The TUC representatives, however, had so far argued that price increases could only be effectively controlled by statutory machinery,although it had been pointed out to them that no Government hadbeen able to devise any effective statutory system for this purpose.The Ministers primarily concerned had examined whether it wouldbe possible to propose some reserve statutory control applying to major items. But even this would present very considerable diffi-culties; and, if it were introduced, Parliament and public opinion would expect it to be matched by an equivalent control of wages.Among the other points which the TUC might be expected toraise was the futur6 of the Industrial Relations Act. Here it would be appropriate to continue to maintain that the Government would beprepared to consider amendments to the Act after a reasonable time had elapsed in which its practical operation could be tested.If the TUC representatives pressed for an increase in pensions, theGovernment could offer to take the outcome of the tripartite agree-3. In the course of a brief discussion the Cabinet agreed thatit would not be possible to decide, until after the meeting with the confederation of British Industry and the Trades Union congress on the following day, the most appropriate form of reference inThe Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament to the Govern-menfs policy for reconciling a more rapid growth of national output and real incomes with a reduction in the rate of inflation. It wouldbe necessary to give urgent consideration to this question on the27 October.
merit into account in determining the amount of the 1973 uprating;but, if the TUC sought to insist on some earlier relief for pensioners,the only practicable course appeared to be a lump sum payment.If they argued that pay awards to lower-paid workers would be frustrated by reductions in means-tested benefits, a change in thebenefit system could be proposed under which the award periods for free school meals, family income supplements and free welfare milkwould be extended from the present 6 months to 12 months, withthe result that pay increases would have no immediate effect onbenefits. As regards rents, the TUC representatives had not pro-posed any change in the rent increases which were to be made in1972; but they had requested some modification in the increases in local authority rents which would take place in 1973. In reply itwould be possible to point to the effect of rent rebates on the amount paid by the great majority of lower-paid workers; and the averagerent increase was in any case lower than the TUC representativesappeared to suppose. If they pressed the point, the Governmentcould offer to extend the arrangements for rebates; and this couldbe done by Order. If, however, they tried to insist that the Housing(Finance) Acts should be so amended as to reduce the rent increases which local authorities were required to make in 1973, it wouldseem appropriate to maintain that the present arrangements hadbeen considered and approved by Parliament and that the conse-quent rent increases should be one of the factors to be taken intoaccount in determining the level of the proposed flat-rate increasein wages. Finally, it would be necessary to discuss the levelof the flat-rate pay increase itself. This would depend to some extent on the decisions about the manner in which it should be imple-mented. If it was agreed that it should be treated as a supplement to amounts paid under existing arrangements, there would be no need to make allowance in the calculations for the effect of wagedrift, although account would need to be taken of the value of any concessions made to pensioners. Some adjustment would also need to be made in those cases where there was a reduction in hours.In addition it would be necessary to ask the TUC representatives to demonstrate how they proposed to monitor wages in such a way as to match the arrangements which the CBI were already operatingfor monitoring prices.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the statement by the PrimeMinister.PayNegotiationsin theElectricitySupplyIndustryThe Secretary of State for Employment said that the fourunions representing the manual workers in the electricity supply industry would probably decide to announce some form of industrial action after a joint meeting on 27 October. It was difficult to fore-cast the form of such action; but it seemed likely that initially itwould be limited to a &quot; go-slow &quot; and a refusal to co-operate withmanagement, although more militant elements would perhaps press for one-day strikes at different power stations each day. Muchdepended on the outcome of the tripartite discussions with theTrades Union Congress (TUC) and the Confederation of British
Industry (CBI) on 26 October. If the TUC agreed to a flat-ratepay increase or to a pay supplement for all workers, the other unions would probably urge the electricity unions to accept a lowersettlement than it would be possible to achieve as a result of voluntary bargaining. Indeed, it seemed possible that Mr. Chappie,the President of the Electrical, Electronic and TelecommunicationUnion, who was in a position to determine the joint attitude of thefour electricity unions, would prefer that there should be a nationallyagreed level of increase, with some form of statutory backing, whichthe four unions would then have to accept, since this would satisfythem that any increase in which they acquiesced would not on this occasion be subsequently exceeded in other settlements. If,however, there was no tripartite agreement on 26 October or the outcome was an agreement which the electricity unions felt unableto accept, they would probably decide on 27 October either to fix3 November as the date for industrial action if meaningful negotia-tions had not started in the meantime or to prescribe another and later date by which action would be taken if a settlement had not by then been reached. In these circumstances it was difficult to forecast the effect which industrial action would have on electricity supply.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said that,if the electricity unions decided to take industrial action, it wouldbe essential to be ready to take all possible steps to mobilise publicopinion in support of the Governmenfs policy. For this purpose the co-ordination of publicity arrangements would be the responsi-bility of his Chief Press Secretary who would report to the lord privy Seal and the Civil Contingencies Unit. It was important thatall Ministers should be ready to speak publicly, as appropriate, in defence of the Governmenfs attitude and that all speeches andstatements should be subject to prior clearance through the co-ordination machinery. Further consideration should also be givento means of ensuring that the Governmenfs policies were given amore fair and objective presentation by the industrial correspondentsof the Press.The Industrial Relations Policy Committee would meet again onthe morning of 27 October in order to consider the Governmenfsattitude to the electricity negotiations in the light of the outcome ofthe tripartite discussions with the CBI and the TUC on 26 October.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministefs summing up of their discussion. /
housing finance ActPreviousReference:CM (72) 43rdConclusions,Minute 5The Secretary of State for Wales said that the five recalcitrantauthorities in Wales were now reconsidering their position; andthere were some signs that the councillors of Merthyr Tydfil, whohad asked for a meeting with him during the following week, might change their attitude. If so, it was reasonable to hope that the other local authorities, whom he would also be meeting, would follow the example of Merthyr. By contrast with the Secretary of State for the environment he was convinced that, if he instituted extraordinaryaudits in Wales, the local authorities would welcome this chance ofprocrastination, together with the possibility of legal proceedingswhich could be represented as involving the &quot; martyrdom &quot; of thecouncillors concerned. If, therefore, the five Welsh local authoritiesmaintained their defiance, it would be appropriate to proceed to theappointment of housing commissioners. The local authorities concerned, and their officials, had expressed their willingness toco-operate with such commissioners.6. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the steps whichmight be taken to deal with local authorities who maintained their refusal to give effect to the provisions of the housing finance legisla-tion. They had before them memoranda by the Secretary of Statefor the Environment (CP (72) 110) and the Secretary of State for wales (CP (72) 111).The Secretary of State for the Environment said that in Englandonly 8 local authorities were still refusing to implement the legisla-tion; and it was hoped that four of these would shortly conform.After a study of the individual circumstances of the local authorities concerned he had come to the conclusion that, once default orders had been made, the most effective action he could take would beto institute extraordinary audits. This would demonstrate theGovernments concern to protect the authority&apos;s ratepayers againstthe misconduct of certain councillors; and it would bring pressure to bear on the councillors responsible, since they would be at riskof a surcharge which would automatically disqualify them fromelection, or from being a member of a local authority, for five years.The steps which would be taken by the district auditor were set outin CP (72) 110. These could result in councillors being sent to prison for contempt if they refused to declare their incomes; butit was unlikely that councillors of the local authorities concerned would be likely to go to this extreme. It would be preferable toavoid the appointment of housing commissioners because theauthorities in England would welcome such appointments inas-much as they would place on the Government the odium of enforc-ing the October 1972 rent increases and would diminish the risk thatthe councillors responsible might be surcharged. Moreover, if localauthorities considered that they could rely on housing commissionersbeing appointed, they would be the more inclined to refuse toimpose the further rent increases which would be needed in thefollowing year.
The Secretary of State for Scotland said that he had arranged for public enquiries, which were necessary in Scotland before a default order could be made, to be held in the third week ofNovember in relation to four of the remaining 22 recalcitrantScottish authorities. In order to bring pressure to bear on all theauthorities concerned he now proposed to delay making the pay-ment of the residual element in the first of the six-monthly housingsubsidy instalments. Under the administrative arrangement it hadbeen intended to make these payments on 10 November; but he now proposed to inform the authorities on 6 November that no decision about the payments could be taken until their intentions as regards implementation of the legislation had been clarified.This course was unlikely to aggravate the attitude of the localauthorities concerned; and it would at the same time anticipate the criticism which the Government would otherwise be liable to incur if they made the payments. The similar payments in Englandand Wales were not due until the end of December. If the Cabinetconcurred in this course, he would proceed in consultation with theother two Secretaries of State; and he would consult the PrimeMinister and the other Ministers principally concerned after thenext meeting in the current series of tripartite discussions aboutprices and incomes policy between the Government, the confederation-tion of British Industry (CBI) and the Trades Union Congress (TUC).The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that, after taking account of any representations made within the prescribed period of one month, the secretaries of State for the Environment and for Wales should be ready to makedefault orders in respect of any local authorities who showed no sign of changing their attitude, such orders to require the default tobe remedied within a specified period, which would normally be14 days. The Cabinet also agreed that in considering subsequentaction designed to bring pressure to bear on the local authorities to implement the legislation it would be necessary to take account ofdifferent local conditions. It would therefore be open to the Sec-retary of State for the Environment to institute extraordinary auditsafter he had made default orders; while in Wales the Secretary ofState should proceed with his preparations for the appointment of housing commissioners at the appropriate time. In order to bring pressure to bear on the 22 defaulting authorities in Scotland theSecretary of State for Scotland should delay paying them the instal-ments of the residual housing subsidy. The three Secretaries ofState should, however, act only after consultation with one another;and particular care should be taken to co-ordinate the timing of thefurther steps which they respectively contemplated. It was important that no indication of these steps should be given until after the next tripartite meeting between the Government, the CBIand the TUC. This would give the Cabinet an opportunity toconsider the matter further in the following week, if necessary; andthe Secretaries of State should in any event continue to keep theCabinet closely informed of developments in the situation.
Cabinet Office25 October, 1972.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers surnmingup of their discussion and invited the Secretaries of Statefor Scotland, for the Environment and for Wales to proceed accordingly.


</content>
</cab>
