<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/176/0 images: 27-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY.    lglilS DQCUMggr       THE PROPERTY^OF HIS BRITAHftlC MAJESTY&apos; S GQVERIIMExOT )^CASH ON DELIVERY COFlilTTEE.REPORT.Perms of At their meeting on June 26th, 1925 (Cabinet 31 (25)Kef er enoe^&quot; Conclusion .&quot;1 ), the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum(CP, 291 (25 )) by the Postmaster-General asking for authorityto establish a Cash on Delivery service in connection withthe Inland Parcel Post, and. agreed that the proposedestablishment of such service, as well as the possible development of the Parcel Post itself with a view to assistingagricultural interests,  should be considered in the firstinstance by a Committee composed as follows:-The Lord Chancellor      (In the Chair).The Home Secretary.The Secretary of State for Air.The Kinister of Agrieulture &amp; Pisheries-.The Secretary for Scotland.The First Commissioner of Works.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Postmaster-General,The Committee have been furnished by the Postmaster-General with valuable information as to the making cf a Cash on Delivery service in the Dominions and abroad.__General   2.     A general Cash on Delivery service, unrestricted inKajbEon[Pelivery     respect either of the goods carried or the nersons utilizingP it,  has for long formeypart  of the postal organization ofmany foreign countries, and has in recent --ears b&apos;en adoptedin many parts cf the Empire.      The evidence shows that such a service works successfully and tends to rapid expansion.3.      While it cannot be said that there is any general public demand for a. Cash or; Delivery service in this country,I -1-4I
there is no reason to suppose that the institution of such a service would not meet with the success which, has attended its adoption abroad,,4,      The opposition in Great Britain to a general Cash on Delivery service is based upon the fear of the retail trader that such a service will lead to a transfer of custom from the local retailer to the large urban stores. While the evidence shows that in Canada and elsewhere the opposition of retailers has quickly been overcome by experience, that the service is largely used by retailers and repair firms,  and that it has the support of their Trade Journals, it may he doubted whether the opposition of the British retailer would be  so easily satisfied,-, In view of the possibility of such opposition the Committee have examined the practicability of a limited service designed primarily to meet the needs of agriculturen b.     There appear to be only two practicable alternative schemes for an Agricultural Service -A0    To prescribe a list of agricultural products or articles used for the industry of agriculture which may be- sent Cash, on Delivery3 and to restrict the use of this system to producers,  i,e. farmers and small holders cBc    To prescribe a  short list of articlescommonly produced by small holders, e0g* butter,  cheese, cream, eggs, poultry, honey, fruit and vegetables, and to restrict the use of the service to these articles but to allow anyone to avail   himself of it.
g0     in the view of the Postmaster General the administrative difficulties incidental to scheme A . or any other scheme restricted to certain classes of users, are well-nigh insuperable.    As the parcels will be dealt with at some 20,000 Post Offices,   clear and simple Instructions for the guidance of the local staff are essential if innumerable conflicting decisions are to be avoided and fraud prevented, and the Committee are assured that it would be iimpracticable to frame watertight regulations which would be intelligible to the public  and the staff of the Post Office, or to administer the regula-tions effectively without considerable public inconvenience and friction.    An extract from a Memorandum by the Postmaster General indicating the hind of difficulties anticipated by him is attached (bee Appendix).     Further, it may be noted that there is no Post Office,  precedent for a service which is9expressly restricted to a particular section of the community, and. the desirability of creating such a precedent may be doubted.7.       Scheme b is open to substantially less administrative objection than scheme a, but it may prove difficult in practice to limit its scope as proposed -to those articles normally produced by the small holder and the small farmer* For example there is considerable pressure from the Fishing industry for a Cash on Delivery service, and it fright be necessary to include fish in the scheme.8.       Apart however from administrative difficulties thereis a grave financial objection common to all types ofrestricted ser ice.    On the assumed mption that  the service mustbe self-supporting it  has been calculated that while inthe case, of a general unrestricted service the Cash onDelivery fee which would have to be charged,  in additionto the parcel postage charge, would be 6d for a parcel upto the value of 20/- with a graduated ad valorem scale forparcels of higher value, the fee for a service restricted-3-
to agriculture on the lines of scheme A or B, would have to be 8d for parcels up to the value of 20/-, with a like increase for articles of higher value.    The following table shows the parcel post and cash on delivery charges appropriate to parcels of average weight falling within Scheme B*-	Average Vs eight *	Parcel	OVGyD	Total Post		Fo stasis	charge0	Office charge.Butt er	  lbs	9d	8d	l/od,Cheese.	3 lbso	Sd.	8d.	l/5d.Gream	-L2	6do	8d.	l/2d.Eggs	4    &quot;	9do	8d.	1/5 doPoultry	5    &quot;       . .	1/-	lOd.	1 /lb dchpney	2    &quot;	9d,	3d,  ,.	l/5d.Fruit	10    &quot;	l/3dc	8d.	l/lldeVegetables	10    &quot;	l/3&apos;cL.	8d.	l/lld09.        The	C o mini ttea.., ha v o	reluctant!	y come to	the conclusionthat in the Qi.	ise of a cash on delivery		system res	triotedeither to persons engaged in agriculture or to certain kinds of agricultural   produce, the total Post Of floe-charges plus the cost of pecking would be prohibitive and that no suchsystem could be introduced with any prospect of ultimate success,IC     In these circumstances the Committee report *--Cabinet(l)       (by a majority)that they cannot recommend the/ to entertain proposals for the establish-ment of an Agricultural cash on delivery service.(2)      that, apart f ro m the political diff icult the scheme for a general cash on delivery service set out in the Postmaster General&apos;s iioraorandum (C.Pr291 (25))  is open to no &quot;obj action and would,  if adopted, give the maximum1 degree- of assistance to the agri-oul t ural I n t or est s 0Signed on behalf of the CommitteeCAVE,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.Y/.1, Chairman,9th December, 1925.
It is obvious that the administrative difficulties of working a scheme on these lines will be enormous.     As the parcels will he handed in at some 20,000 post Offices it is eminently desirable that some clear and simple regulations should be provided for the guidance of the local staff. Otherwise inconsistent decisions will constantly be given which the Department will have to defend if challenged.     But I see no possibility of framing regulations which will cover the numerous borderline cases nor will it be easy to preserve consistency even if they are referred to Headquarters.      All sorts of questions will constantly arise and anomalies wi11 be brought up against the Department;    e.g., would a co-eperative dairy, a bacon curer,  or a private owner who sells the surplus produce of his garden,  come within the category of thnse who are entitled to use the post..     If a farmer is entitled to get a spare part for his [Ford van,, can he also get one for his own car;    if he can get physic for his animals why should he not be able to obtain it C.Q.D. for himself;    is fish to be included or excluded-..     if included, must it be sent by the fisherman himself or may the G-rimsby cr Aberdeen distributor use the C-O-D.  service&apos;.     A person may be  said to  &quot;produce&quot; poultry and possibly pheasants; but can anyone be said to produce grouse.      can a farmer  (or ? a farm labourer)  obtain boots or clothing C.O.D.-     A farmer could presumably send jam C:..6 *D * i could a firm like the Tiptree Co. in Essex, whioh grows most cf its own fruit,  do sr*;    could the same&apos; firm send marmalade;    if so-,, could a firm which grows no fruit but manufactures jam use.C.O.D.

</content>
</cab>
