<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/176/0 images: 223-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
It! iHIS -DOCmgigT .13  TUB PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAIN! C 21AJgSTY&apos;S government??.B11 EITT. )IRISH BOUHDARYiletter from Chairman of the Irish. Boundary Commissi on&quot; to the&quot; Prime&quot;Minis ter .The Prime Minister has received the attached communication from Mr. Justice Feetham.It is being sent to the Press for immediate publication in accordance with arrangements made with the Chairman of the Boundary Commission.S 1 C RET.Copy Ho .o.p. 533 (55).CAB I B E T.(Signed)M.  P.  A. HAHEEY.Secretary, Cabinet.2 .Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1. 17th December, 1925,
6, Clement&apos;s Inn, London, W.G. 2, December 7th, 1925.The Eight Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.Dear Mr. Baldwin,The Agreement of the 3rd December entered into between the British Government, the Government of the Irish Free State and the Government of Northern Ireland will, if it receives the necessary confirmation, relieve the Irish Boundary Commission of the duty of making an Award determining the boundaries between Northern Ireland and the rest of Ireland. I am writing this letter to you on behalf of my colleague, Mr. Fisher, and myself, with reference to our position, as representing the Commission, in the new situation which has thus arisen.Notwithstanding the fact that if the new Agreement is confirmed there will now be no Award, the Commission feels it essential that the Beport which has been prepared to accompany this Award should still be presented, and this Beport, as arranged at the recent conference between the Commission and the be presentatives of the three Governments concerned, will be presented to the British Government.It was, as you are aware, the desire of the Commission that its Beport should be published with as little delay as possible, but the be presentatives of the Government of the Irish Free State and of the Government of Northern Ireland have expressed the view that publication of the Beport, and especially of any portion of it which sets out and explains detailed decisions affecting particular areas, would hamper the attainment of the objects which both Govern-ments have had in view in entering into the new Agreement.I need hardly assure you that we are most anxious to do whatever we can to assist in securing the establishment of peace in Ireland on firm foundations, and that we do not wish to press any proposal which might in any way interfere with or prejudice the prospect, opened up by the new Agreement, that this great result will now be achieved by the united efforts of the Government of the Irish Free State and the Government of Northern Ireland.Under the circumstances we feel therefore that we must defer to the views expressed on behalf of the two Governments, and concurred in by the British Government, and refrain from pressing for the publication of our Beport at the present time.You will, however, appreciate that the speculative and mislead-ing statements which have been current, as to the character of our proposed Award and the basis of our decisions, make us regret very much that we are debarred from clearing up the position by stating exactly what we have decided and why. While therefore we feel [13849b] b
2that we must. acquiesce in the proposed course of withholding, for the present at any rate, publication of our Beport, we trust that publicity may be given to the following statement.The Line embodied in the draft Award, which we had intended to sign, is the Line agreed upon by the Commission at meetings held before the 20th November, the date of Dr. MacNeilPs with-drawal, The agreement reached by the three members of the Commission, with regard to embodying in a unanimous award the Line as recorded in the Commission^ Minutes of the 17th October, has already been referred to in the statement which we issued for publication on the 23rd November. The Beport has been compiled subsequent to Dr. MacNeill&apos;s withdrawal. The Commission had taken the view that a unanimous Award would render unnecessary and undesirable the presentation of a formal report entering into the pros and cons of the various questions raised before it, and into local detail; but the withdrawal of Dr. MacNeill rendered it in our opinion necessary that such a Beport should be presented.So far as Mr. Fisher and myself are concerned, we wish it to be known that our decisions with regard to the Line embodied in the draft Award have been based on certain definite views as to the correct interpretation of Article XII of the Articles of Agreement for a Treaty between Great Britain and Ireland, and the principles which should govern its application. These views are set out in the Beport. But as the Beport itself is not to be published now, we are stating them in similar terms, but in a condensed form, in this letter.The Commission was at an early stage of its enquiry, before any sittings had been held for the hearing of evidence, invited to give in advance its decision on certain questions as to the interpretation of Article XII. The Commission declined to make any pronouncement on such questions at that stage, and intimated that it was prepared to give to all parties concerned opportunities of urging their views on such questions before the Commission, and that while reserving its decision on such questions it was prepared to hear and receive evidence in support of claims made affecting. territory on either side of the border.The Commission heard, both at the outset and at the close of its enquiry, argument by Counsel on behalf of the Government of the Irish Free State as to the interpretation of Article XII. The hearing of evidence and arguments on the subject of the claims made in respect of different districts occupied the Commission for several months, during which the Commission heard at length the views of both parties to the controversy, as voiced by the representatives of the various bodies and groups which appeared before it.Various contentions with regard to the interpretation of Article XII of the Articles of Agreement for a Treaty between Great Britain and Ireland, and the principles which should govern its application, were put forward in the course of this long enquiry.
For convenience of reference we will here set out the Article itself, which reads as follows :  ,  \ .Article XII:-&quot;If, before the expiration of the said month, an address is presented to His Majesty by both Houses of Parliament of Northern Ireland to that effect, the powers of the Parliament and Government of the Irish Free State shall no longer extend to Northern Ireland, and the provisions of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920 (including those relating.to the Council of Ireland), shall, so far as they relate to Northern Ireland, continue to be of full&apos;force and effect, and this instrument shall have effect subject to the necessary modifications.&quot; Provided that if such an address is so presented a Commission consisting of three persons, one to be appointed by the Government of the Irish Free State, one to be appointed by the Government of Northern Ireland and one, who shall be Chairman, to be appointed by the British Government, shall determine in accordance with the wishes of the inhabitants, so far as may be compatible with economic and geographic conditions, the boundaries between Northern Ireland and the rest of Ireland, and for the purposes of the Govern&apos;--ment of Ireland Act, 1920, and of this instrument, the boundary of Northern Ireland shall be such as may be determined by such Commission.&quot;The principal questions raised by such contentions may be thus summarised : (1.) What is the meaning and effect of Article XII as viewed in relation to the Articles of Agreement as a whole?(2.) What is the scope of the powers and duties entrusted to and imposed upon the Commission by Article XII?This second question includes the following more specific questions : (a.) In determining the future boundaries between Northern Ireland and the rest of Ireland, what regard is the Commission to pay to the existing boundary? Is it the duty of the Commission to make an entirely fresh determination of boundaries, and to lay down a new line of division without regard to the existing boundary, or is the Commission required to start its work on the basis of the existing boundary, and to treat that boundary as holding good except where considerations of which the Commission is entitled to take account justify its alteration ?(b.) Does the Article enable the Commission, in determining the boundaries between Northern Ireland and the rest of Ireland, to shift the existing boundary in either direction, that is, either so as to include in the Irish Free State territory at present forming part of Northern Ireland, or so as to include in Northern Ireland territory at present forming part of the Irish Free State, or is the power of the Commission confined to shifting the boundary in one direction only? In other words, is the Commission required, in carrying out its work, to respect the integrity either of Northern Ireland or of the &quot;rest of Ireland&quot; as defined by existing boundaries&quot;?
4(c.) Can the Commission make changes in the existing boundary which involve the transfer of large areas and populations to one side or the other, or is its scope ; restricted to the making of minor modifications in the existing boundary? &quot; :  (3.) What is the relation between the three different factorsmentioned as affecting the determination of boundaries_wishes of inhabitants and economic and geographic conditions? In what sense is the reference to economic and geographic conditions to be understood, and what arc the areas in relation to which such conditions are to bo taken into account?(4.) What qualifications entitle persons to rank as &quot; inhabitants &quot; whose wishes are to be considered, and by what procedure are the wishes of inhabitants to be ascertained?(5.) In considering the wishes of inhabitants with regard to the determination of boundaries, what is the position with regard to majorities and minorities? Is unanimity to be required, or is a bare majority one way or the other to be sufficient?(6.) On what principle should units of area be chosen or defined for the purpose of ascertaining the wishes of inhabitants?We propose now to state the general conclusions reached by us as to the answers which should be given to these questions. The views stated in these answers are based on, and embody the results of, a full and detailed examination of the arguments advanced.It is necessary to make one or two general remarks by way of preface before coming to the questions themselves.The answers to be given to the, questions stated depend (i) on the actual terms of the proviso to Article XII, which provides for the setting up of the Commission; (ii) on the proviso as considered in relation to the precedingclause of the Article to which it belongs; and (hi) on the whole Article as considered in relation to the other provisions of the instrument of which it forms part.Further, the Commission was asked to take into account the historical circumstances which led up to the Articles of Agreement for a Treaty, and the conditions actually existing at the date when these Articles were signed, which, it was said, defined the nature of the problem which Article XII was intended to solve. It was urged that such circumstances and conditions throw light on the question of the interpretation which should be given to Article XII, and evidence bearing on this aspect of the case was received by the Commission.In support of views advanced as to the interpretation of Article XII evidence was also offered as to various statements made on the subject by signatories to the Articles of Agreement,
both in the course of the negotiations and subsequent to the actual signing of the Articles, but the Commission regarded such evidence as inadmissible and declined to receive it.The terms of the Proviso to Article XII which define the functions of the Commission are general and not specific. If this Proviso is compared with the provisions with regard to the settlement of boundaries contained in the Treaty of Versailles (Articles 88, 94/97 and 109) or in the Treaty of St. Germain-en-Laye (Articles 49/50), to which reference nas been made in the course of arguments addressed to the Commission, a striking contrast is at once apparent. In the Articles referred to in those Treaties general terms are employed, corresponding to but not identical with those contained in the Proviso to Article XII, but they are supplemented by a series of specific detailed provisions which give in each case precise directions (1) as to the extent of the areas to be considered, i.e., the regions or areas which are recognised as being within the range of boundary variations, (2) as to the means by which the wishes of the inhabitants of such areas are to be ascertained (the method specified being a plebiscite for the conduct of which full provision is made in each case), and (3) as to the units of area which are to be used for the purpose of such ascertainment. Article XII gives no specific directions on any of these points, but leaves to the Commission discretion to determine these points for itself subject to the general terms used, and in the light of such circumstances as the Commission^ examination of the actual position in the territory on either side of the existing boundary may reveal.Having made these general observations, we now proceed to state the answers which should in our opinion be given to the questions stated above.Our Ansivers are as folloivs: (1.) The meaning of Article XII is that if the Address therein referred to is presented, Northern Ireland shall continue to exist as a province of the United Kingdom in accordance with the provisions of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, subject to the &quot; determina-tion&quot; of boundaries, for which machinery is set up under the proviso, and its terms require that once such an Address has been presented the several Articles of Agreement for a Treaty shall be modified, so far as necessary, to give effect to all the consequences which under the provisions of Article XII follow upon such presentation.To the extent thus indicated Article XII necessarily becomes&apos; on the presentation of such Address a governing Article in the light of which the other Articles of the Treaty must be read, and to which in case of conflict their provisions must yield.(2 a.) The Commission is required by the proviso to Article XII to &quot; determine the boundaries between Northern Ireland and the rest cf Ireland.&quot;  Until the boundaries have been altered by the Commis-[13849b I b 2
sion ,&quot; Northern Ireland&quot; is the. region constituted as such by Section 1 (2) of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920; that is to say the region consisting &quot; of the parliamentary counties of Antrim, Armagh, Down, Fermanagh, Londonderry and Tyrone, and the parliamentary boroughs of Belfast and Londonderry,&quot; and &quot;the rest.of Ireland &quot; is the region constituted as &quot; Southern Ireland&apos; by.the same section-that is to say, the region consisting of &quot;so much of Ireland as is not comprised within the said parliamentary counties and boroughs.&quot; The Commission having to deal with these two ascertained territorial entities must start from the existing boundaries of those entities; that is, it must start its examination of the whole question on the basis of the division marked by the existing boundary, and must treat that boundary as holding good where no. sufficient reason, based on considerations of which the Commission can properly take account, is shown for altering it.(2 by), In determining the boundaries between Northern Ireland and the rest of Ireland under the terms of the proviso, the Commission has power to shift the existing boundary line in either direction, it has no more and no less authority to take land from the Northern Ireland side of the existing boundary and give it to the Free State, than it has to take land from the Free State side and give it to Northern Ireland. It has the same authority and duty in each case, namely to make whatever transfer of territory is involved by a. determination of the boundary in accordance with the terms of the Article.(2 c.) The fact that the wishes of the inhabitants are to be a. determining factor shows that the scope of the Commission^ work is not limited to a mere correction of irregularities in the present boundary; at the same time no wholesale reconstruction of the map is contemplated by the proviso the Commission is not to recon-stitute the two territories, but to settle the boundaries between them. Northern Ireland must, when the boundaries have been determined, still be recognisable as the same provincial entity; the changes made must not be so drastic as to destroy its identity or make it impossible for!it to continue as a separate province of the United Kingdom with its own parliament and government for provincial affairs under the Government of Ireland Act. The same principle applies mutatis mutandis to the &quot; rest of Ireland,&quot; which must, after the determina-tion of the boundaries, retain its identity as the Irish Free State as constituted under the terms of the Treaty, and be in a position to function as a self-governing Dominion &apos;&apos; in the Community of Nations known as the British Empire.&quot;The Commission starting its examination of the question on the basis of the existing boundary must first consider the wishes of the inhabitants adjacent to that boundary, and where it finds an area of sufficient size and population to merit separate consideration which is at present on the right side of the boundary, that is on the side where its inhabitants wish to remain, the-existence of that area will in itself be a reason against making an alteration which
would involve its transfer to the wrong side, and help to indicate the point beyond which alterations intended to give effect to the wishes of the inhabitants should not extend.No. precise rule can be laid down as to the requirements which must be fulfilled in the case of individual areas in order to entitle the wishes of their inhabitants to prevail. The conditions of an individual area cannot be considered alone, but must be. considered in relation to conditions in adjoining areas, and different factors, such as comparative numbers of population, and strength of majorities, must be taken into account.(3.) Under the terms of the Article the wishes of the inhabitants are made the primary but not the paramount consideration. The first point for the Commission to consider in dealing with a particular area is the question of the wishes of the inhabitants of that area, but such wishes are only to prevail &apos;&apos; so far as may be compatible with economic and geographic conditions.&quot; The intention of the Article as indicated by its reference to such conditions is that the Commission should take into account the economic and geographic relations between different areas, and should avoid drawing a boundary line which, by its defiance of economic or geographic conditions, would involve,&apos; as the result of its adoption, serious economic detriment, or geographic isolation, to communities on either side of it.It is therefore the duty of the Commission to overrule the wishes of inhabitants, whether for or against transfer, where the result of giving effect to such wishes would be incompatible with economic or geographic conditions in the sense indicated. On the other hand economic or geographic considerations may give extra strength to a case for transfer which rests in part on the wishes of the inhabitants, but where the evidence available does not show the existence of a decisive majority in favour of transfer.(4) and (5). &quot; Inhabitants &quot; in Article XII means persons having a permanent connection with any particular area concerned. Temporary or casual residence within an area cannot be regarded as qualifying a person to have his wishes considered on the question whether the permanent destiny of the area is to be in one country or another.The Article contains no provision for ascertaining the wishes of inhabitants by a plebiscite taken for the purpose, which is the only means by which precise figures as to the wishes of the inhabitants could be ascertained. It is clearly impossible to conduct a plebiscite in the results of which any confidence could be placed except under the authority of special legal provisions of a comprehensive and stringent character.The absence from the Article of any provision for a plebiscite affords ground for inferring (1) that it was not the intention of the parties to the Treaty that the Commission should ascertain the wishes of the inhabitants in that manner, and (2) that it was not
intended that the Commission should, in seeking to give effect to the; wishes of the inhabitants, rely on the verdicts of bare majorities as sufficient to justify alterations of the existing boundary.As it has not been open to the Commission to ascertain the wishes of inhabitants by a: direct vote, the Commission has necessarily had recourse to other sources of information, such as census returns, election results and evidence of persons claiming to speak on behalf of inhabitants in different areas or to have knowledge of their views.  .&apos;The Commission has been invited by both parties to the boundary controversy to rely upon the census returns of 1911. showing the religious denominations to which inhabitants belong, as affording an indication of the wishes of the inhabitants, the members of Protestant denominations being reckoned as wishing to be in Northern Ireland and Eoman Catholics as wishing to be in the Irish Free State. The evidence heard from both sides, taken as a whole, strongly supports the view that in the areas to which it relates religious and political divisions do to-day, broadly speaking, correspond, and that apart from special circumstances affecting limited areas the 1911 Census returns may still be relied upon as showing with approximate accuracy the proportionate numbers of Catholics and Protestants in the different districts.In examining these census returns for the purpose of ascertain-ing the wishes of inhabitants, allowance must however be made lor many factors, which cannot be determined with precision, e.g., the extent to which the returns include temporary residents who are not entitled to be reckoned as. inhabitants, or persons under age and therefore not qualified to vote.The question of what majority of the inhabitants, estimated on the basis &apos;i of census figures and the other information available, should be regarded as sufficient to justify an alteration in the existing boundary is a question to be determined by the Comrnis-sion according to its discretion, with due regard to the above considerations, and to facts disclosed in the course of its enquiry as affecting particular areas.,&apos;, With regard to the exercise of the Commission^ discretion on this question, while unanimity is neither to be expected nor required, the Commission should adopt the principle that the case for a change on the basis of &quot; the wishes of the inhabitants,&quot; apart from economic or geographic considerations one way or the other, is not made out unless the majority in favour of the change appears to be a substantial majority, i.e., a majority representing a high proportion of the total number of persons entitled to rank as inhabitants of the district directly concerned.(6.) The Commission, being required to determine the boundaries in accordance with the wishes of the inhabitants, should seek, in those areas which are recognised as falling within the range of boundary variations, to follow the wishes of inhabitants as closely as-is reasonably possible, and should therefore-be prepared to take
as a. unit of area, in relation to which the wishes of inhabitants are to be ascertained the smallest area which can fairly be entitled, having regard to its size and situation, to be considered separately, and with regard to which separate data are available.If the Commission were to adopt the suggestion that large areas such as the County or the Union should, on administrative grounds, be regarded as indivisible units, it would find itself compelled on such grounds to refuse to treat separately particular portions of a county or union where the inhabitants differed from the majority in the county or union as a whole, and therefore to override the wishes of the inhabitants of such portions. The Commission would thus in effect be setting up a new factor, administrative, considerations, as superior to the wishes of the inhabitants.The Commission, not being required to adopt any particular type of local division as the unit of area in reference to which the wishes of the inhabitants should be ascertained, is free to mark out, for the purpose of its work, as occasion requires, convenient units of area in the light of the three factors which it is required to take into account wishes of inhabitants, economic and geographic conditions.The decisions of the Commission with regard to the new boundary, as embodied in the draft Award, were arrived at in accordance with the views above set out as to the interpretation of Article XII, and the principles which should govern its application, and represent, as we believe, a fair estimate, based on all the information available and evidence received, of the different factors which the Commission was required by Article XII to take into account.While we may regret that the Agreement of the 3rd December has been so framed that, by reason of its provisions, our decisions are not now destined to take effect, we would again express, in concluding this letter, our earnest hope that the larger settlement, accepted by both Irish Governments, for which the Agreement provides, may bring to the people of Ireland benefits far greater than any which could have resulted from a new determination of boundaries, even if embodied in a unanimous Award.I remain,Yours very truly, (Signed)    EICHAED FEETHAM.

</content>
</cab>
