<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/176/0 images: 291-296</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
QGNi IDENTiAL LIBRARY,-[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]SECRET. Copy No.      0CP. 539 (25J.CABINET.THE MOSUL QUESTION AT THE LEAGUE OP NATIONS.Further Report by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.ON my arrival at Geneva on the 6th December, I learnt that the Sub-Committee of the Council, presided over by the Swedish representative (M. Unden), were chiefly preoccupied with two points. The first was whether, if the Turks persisted in refusing to acknowledge the validity of the reply of The Hague Court and to accept the award of the Council as a binding decision, I should follow the same line, a matter with regard to which I had intimated our right to reserve our freedom on the 19th September. I was told that M. Unden was hoping that I might do this and so afford an opportunity to the Council to evade a decision. I accordingly, after consultation with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and Lord Cecil, conveyed privately to the Sub-Committee my view that my statement of the 19th September referred only to the position in so far as it depended on the assurances given on either side at the Council meeting in September 1924, but that, in view of the decision of the Court, which took cognisance only of the Treaty of Lausanne and advised that no subsequent declarations had in any way weakened or modified the position of the parties under the treaty, there could, of course, be no question of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment repudiating their treaty obligations. The second point on which, I was informed, M. Unden was laying stress was the vagueness of my declaration of the 3rd September with regard to the renewal of the treaty relations. Nothing less than a definite mandatory responsibility as complete as that of other mandates would satisfy him, if the Commission^ recommendation was to be accepted. On this point I had a memorandum prepared and communicated to the Sub-Committee, which showed that the decision taken by the Council in September 1924, coupled with the Iraq Treafay and its subsidiary agreements, did in fact place His Majesty&apos;s Government in the same position of responsibility towards the League in respect of Iraq as the Syrian Mandate placed the French Government in respect of Syria.These two preliminary moves would seem to have placed M. Unden in some difficulty, and although he still circulated to his colleagues a memorandum in favour of partition, to which a very effective reply was, I understand, circulated by M. Quinones de Leon, the Spanish representative, his hopes of persuading the Council to his point of view, or even of seriously dividing it, were reported to be weakening. They were shortly to be damped still further by the moral effect of two further factors in the shape of General Laidoner&apos;s reports and of the unreasonable attitude of the Turkish representatives both towards the Council and towards his own Sub-Committee.The opening meeting was held on the 8th December, and it was noticed at once that Rushdy Bey, though present in Geneva, did not attend in person, but was represented by Munir Bey, the Turkish Minister in Berne. M. Unden presented a report in which he recommended the adoption of the consultative opinion of the Permanent Court of International Justice. I then briefly referred to the statement made by me on the 19th September, giving expression to the view as to our obligation under the Lausanne Treaty, which I had already conveyed privately to the Sub-Committee, and asked for a definite decision by the-Council.Munir Bey read a long statement traversing the legal conclusions of The Hague Court, and towards the end, basing himself on the reference by the Court to [14017] j3
the fact that the function of the Council also included conciliation, pressed strongly for an endeavour to reach a decision by mediation. M. Unden pointed out that the Council had certainly not lost sight of their mediatory function in this matter.When the President put the adoption of the report to the vote, Munir boldly claimed that for this purpose unanimity, inclusive of the Turkish and British votes, was required. The Council adjourned in no little trepidation and confusion, and after an hour and a halfs secret conclave, at one stage of which they were practically decided to give way to the Turkish bluff, pulled themselves together, and, without being able to agree upon any answer to be given to the Turk,,left it to M. Scialoja, the President, to use any argument he liked, but to inform the Turk that the Council could not have its acceptance of the reply of The Hague Court vetoed by the opposition of an interested party. From that moment I felt our case was won, for, once the Council had proved itself capable of a decision on any-thing at all, it would feel less terrified of further decisions. Accordingly, on re-entering the hall, the President announced that whilst, in his opinion, this was a matter of procedure on which a bare majority of votes was sufficient, it was in any case sufficient to point out that under Article 15 the votes of the parties concerned could not be counted in reckoning unanimity. On this basis a unanimous vote was taken with only the Turk voting against.In the discussion just before the adjournment, Munir Bey had produced a prepared declaration in which he said that the Turkish Delegation had no authority from the Grand National Assembly to submit to arbitration so vital a national issue, and that if the Council decided to regard this as a matter of arbitra-tion, the Turkish Delegation could not take further part in the proceedings or defend its case before the Council. After the Presidents statement he repeated the substance of this, saying that he could only regard any decision the Council might take as a recommendation of which he could take cognisance and which he could communicate to the Grand National Assembly, adding that once he and his colleagues were faced by an arbitral award their powers as a delegation came to an end.Before the session closed I raised the question of the report of the special representative, General Laidoner, who was due to return on the following day from his investigations on the Iraq frontier, and pressed for it to be raised at a public sitting of the. Council at the earliest possible opportunity. It was arranged that the report should be taken on the morning of the 10th December, but the Turkish representative took advantage of the position arising out of the Turkish refusal to accept the arbitral powers of the Council to decline to attend the&apos;meeting. In the letter in which this decision was communicated, the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that &quot; Since the members of the Council who voted for the adoption of The Hague Court&apos;s opinion regard the Council as having the right to take a binding decision without counting the votes of the two interested parties, and since the Turkish Delegation have no powers to represent Turkey save before the Council acting in accordance with either Article 5 or Article 15 of the Covenant, the Delegation regret that they cannot accept the invitation which they have just received, although they would have been disposed to accept if the authority which they possess permitted them to do so.&quot;It was perhaps fortunate for the Turkish representative that he was absent from this meeting, since General Laidoner&apos;s report constituted a complete vindication of the charges which I had brought forward in September both as to the violation of the frontier and as to the deportation of the Christian population of the frontier zone, charges which Rnshdy Bey had declared to be absolutely devoid of any foundation whatever. The report while laying no stress on tribal raiding or on the Turkish charges as to our aeroplanes flying north of the Brussels line, definitely confirmed the occupation during the summer and autumn by Turkish military posts and patrols of villages south of the Brussels line. General Laidoner did not, however, regard these incursions, which had not been recently repeated, as of any consequence in their bearing on the Council s decision. He insisted, however, that the Council would have to take into account the deportations, in view of the serious and easily comprehensible agitation and nervousness which they had caused among the Christian population south of the Brussels line and in the whole of the Mosul vilayet, as well as among the pro-Iraq Moslem population of Mosul. I need not here recapitulate those portions of the report, or of the more detailed additional report prepared by the officers who actually examined the Christian refugees, which deals with the actual story of the
deportations, of the pillage, outrage and massacre which preceded them, and of the appalling barbarity with which they were actually conducted. They must, I think, have made it clear to most members of the Council that it was impossible in the interest of a so-called compromise, to hand over a large Christian population to a rule under which atrocities of this character are apparently inevitable and, indeed, a matter of deliberate, systematic policy.Meanwhile the Sub-Committee, before proceeding to the framing of a report, decided to make at any rate a final effort to discover whether the parties were still so far apart that any further attempt at mediation was obviously futile. I was accordingly summoned on the 11th December to a secret meeting of the Sub-Committee. M. Unden informed me that he had recently had a private conversation with Tewfik Rushdy and had gathered the impression that the Turks would be ready to consider any proposal for a frontier line which would permit of the town of Mosul being given to Turkey. I replied that I fully recognised the desirability of some agreement with the Turks, but the difficulty arose out of the fact that there was at present no common ground upon which such an agreement could be based. From the British point of view, the Turkish demand for a large portion of the territory of Iraq was purely aggressive, and had for its object the entire reversal of the status quo established since the war. At the end of the war the Iraq State had been constituted as a natural entity from the ethnical, economic and geographical points of view. It was limited by natural frontiers, beyond which no attempt had been made by the British Government to penetrate. The arrangements between the Principal Allied Powers, and with the League itself, for the establishment of the Mandate had been made on the basis of an Iraq constituted as at present, with its present frontier. This frontier had in substa,nce been accepted by Turkey in the Treaty of Sevres. It was true that a subsequent Turkish Government had neither ratified this treaty nor accepted the frontier, and that from a technical point of view the state of war between Great Britain and Turkey had continued right up to the date of the Treaty of Lausanne. But, except for unimportant incidents, there had been no act of war on the Iraq frontier All that had happened was that the Turkish renunciation of sovereignty over Iraq had remained technically in suspense, as had been made clear by the International Court at The Hague, until the moment when the frontier was finally fixed. Internally, Iraq had not only been an economic and geographical unit, but the administration in all parts of the territory had been on uniform lines. The northern districts of Iraq had shared in the election of King Feisal, in the election of the Constituent Assembly, which had framed the constitution of Iraq, and in the election of the present Iraq Parliament, which had expressed its earnest desire for the maintenance of the unity of the country and for the renewal of its treaty engagements with Great Britain.To give back to Turkey any substantial part of this young country, which had made such great steps, with British assistance and under the auspices of the League, in the direction of a development on entirely different lines from that of pre-war or post-war Turkey, would not merely mean replacing the inhabitants concerned under the hostile domination of an alien race, but would be a death-blow to the future life of the Iraq State.Dealing with the suggestion that security could be attained even with a naturally indefensible frontier such as that of the Lesser Zab, by some form of Security Pact coupled with demilitarisation, I pointed out that in the first place complete demilitarisation of the frontier zone was impossible in a country inhabited by armed tribes and, in the second place, that the attitude of Turkey towards her international obligations was not such as to encourage any confidence in her will or capacity to adhere to the provisions of any Security Pact.I then went on to point out what would be the fate of the population of the northern districts of Iraq if they were returned to Turkey, and called attention to General Laidoner&apos;s report and to the undoubted exodus of the Christian population which would result from the drawing of a frontier anywhere south of the Brussels line. The Minority Clauses of the Treaty of Lausanne had not protected the Goyan Christians. What reason was there, then, to suppose that any new arrangement could be made to protect any Christian population living in the territory which it was suggested might be handed back to Turkey ? These were the reasons which led His Majesty&apos;s Government to come to the conclusion that they could not possibly agree, of their own accord, to the cession of any part of the territory which was at present administered by the Government of Iraq. They [14017] &apos; b 2
had submitted to the Council their request for what they regarded as constituting a proper frontier for Iraq. This demand seemed to them just, and they hoped that it would be accepted by the League. They were, however, quite prepared in the interests of peace to discuss with Turkey any modification of this frontier, or, indeed, to accept the Brussels line, and even to consider its fresh delimitation with a view to removing purely local difficulties; but they could not consistently with their obligations go any further than this, and it did not seem to me, from what M. Undeii had said, that this afforded any possible basis for direct discussion with the Turkish representative. There could, in fact, be no starting point for such discussion before the underlying question of principle was settled. Once it was decided whether the Turkish or Iraq claim to the vilayet was justified it would be possible to discuss adjustments and modifications of that decision, and the British Government would be only too anxious to do so.The Turkish delegation had been invited to attend a similar meeting. The Turkish representative replied that as he had not received an answer but merely an acknowledgment to the letter in which he had refused to attend the previous Council meeting, he had not the necessary powers to discuss the Mosul question officially with the Sub-Committee until the Turkish Assembly had pronounced itself concerning the Council&apos;s &quot; recommendation &quot; of the 8th December to accept the opinion of The Hague Court. Meanwhile, however, he was always ready to meet the members of the Sub-Committee privately if a proposal were made to him which he felt able to recommend to his Government and Assembly with a view to facilitate a solution. The Secretary of the Sub-Committee, M. Avenol, replied that the Council desired, in accordance with the opinion of The Hague Court which had been adopted, only to use its powers of decision if its mediatory action failed. The Council had never ceased to exercise this function and wished the Sub-Committee to make a final attempt at mediation. This was the object of the meeting to which the Turks had been invited. The Turkish representative replied that ever since the Mosul question first came before the Council Turkey had received no conciliatory proposal from that body regarding the settlement of the dispute. He had therefore read the Secretary&apos;s letter with great astonish-ment. It was inconceivable that the Sub-Committee meeting should be regarded as destined to terminate the mediatory role conferred on the Council by Article 3 of the Treaty of Lausanne unless conciliatory proposals had been made without his knowledge to Great Britain and rejected by her. Turkey, as was well known, had repeatedly given proof of her conciliatory spirit.This correspondence practically summarises the Turkish attitude, which was maintained until the end of the session. The result was that the Turks dropped almost entirely out of the picture. Tewfik Rushdy made a flying visit to Paris, with the object, it was said, of attempting to enlist French and Russian support. M. Briand, who was in the country for the week-end, resolutely declined to return to Paris, and M. Berthelot refused either to see the Turkish representative or to arrange for him to be received by M. Briand. I am told that Tewfik Rushdy also failed to obtain an audience with M. Chicherin, and all that he succeeded in doing was to discuss the situation, with the Turkish Minister in London, who had crossed over to Paris to meet him, and with the Turkish Ambassador in Paris, Fethy Bey, whose statement at last year&apos;s Council meeting he had recently repudiated.   He returned to Geneva furious with the French and very depressed.The Sub-Committee, at this stage, really came to an end, owing to the divergence of view between its members, and became merged in a series of secret and informal sessions of the Council as a whole, excluding myself and, of course, the Turk. At these meetings the Council, while apparently all over the place, gradually drifted more and more definitely towards accepting the main recom-mendation of the League Commission in favour of the Brussels line, only the Swede and the Japanese holdingjmt at all in favour of the Turkish claim. The real danger now lay in the anxiety of many of the members to avoid, or at any rate postpone, any decision at all, and to avert this the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs had to exercise all his great personal influence over the President and some of his colleagues. At one stage no little perturbation was caused by the publication of an answer given by the Prime Minister to a Supplementary Question in the House of Commons, which led the Council to suppose that there was some difference of opinion between the British Government at home and its representatives at Geneva on the subject of the extension of British responsibility for Iraq.   The Foreign Secretary was informed that nothing less than a written
undertaking, signed by him as well as by myself, would now meet the -case or avert a postponement of any decision till March. Fortified by a telegram from the Prime Minister to the effect that there had been no change of policy and that my instructions held good, I drafted an assurance, which Sir A. Chamberlain and I signed, and a covering letter, the two documents between them bringing out clearly the essential points in my instructions. These were informally submitted through M. Avenol, who acted throughout as Secretary, Sir Eric Drummond standing on one side as a member of an interested nationality, and approved. They were to have been, formally accepted from us on the 13th or 14th by the President and M. Unden. But while we waited a further development occurred. M. Unden suddenly sprang on his colleagues a report in which he accepted the Brussels line solution, but made its adoption purely provisional and subject to ratification by another Council after we had fulfilled the conditions by concluding the necessary treaty with Iraq. His colleagues were too overjoyed by M. Undehs surrender to them on the main principle to have the heart to fight him over the method of its application, though M. Scialoja insisted that the decision of the Council must be definite, subject only to the fulfilment of the conditions, and not open to reconsideration by a future Council. On this basis the drafting of the actual report, nominally the report of M. Unden and his Sub-Committee, was actually left to M. Scialoja. After two days of agitated incubation in the intervals of further secret meetings the report was duly laid before the Council in public on the evening of Wednesday, the 16th December. In accepting the decision of the Council I expressed my gratitude to the Council and all concerned, while still emphasising my regret that our claim for a rectification of the Brussels line had not been considered. The Foreign Secretary followed and held out an olive branch to the absent Turk, who, true to the attitude which he had taken up throughout, had declined to attend the meeting and had contented himself with circulating a letter in which he refused to accept the decision of the Council.L. S. AMERY.December 24, 1925.o


</content>
</cab>
