<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/10/0 images: 28-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Gabinet.   April 1919.SECRET.1 OWAP CABINET 557.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at the Deader of the House&apos;s Room,House of Commons, on Wednesday, April 16, 1919, at 4 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The   Right Hon. the Earl Cuuzon   kedleston, K.G., CCS.I., G.C.I.E.The Eight Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The following were also present:The Right Hon, A. Chamberlain, M.P.The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.C.B.,G.B.E., M.P.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milker.G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., First&apos;Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., Minister of Reconstruction and national Service.The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, LL.D.,M.P., President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon. Sir R. S. Horne, K.B.E.,K.C.&apos;, M.P., Minister of Labour.The  Right Hon. G.Food Controller.H. Roberts, M.P.Mr. Thomas Jones, Acting Secretary.Budget Proposals.1. THE Chancellor of the Exchequer submitted his proposalsfor the forthcoming Budget, and, subject io certain minor suggestions,the proposals were approved by the War Cabinet.2.i The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theBoard of Inland Revenue, dealing with Land Values Duties and the valuation under Part I of the Finance (1909-1910) Act, 1910(Paper G.-239), together with a covering note by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer, suggesting that a careful enquiry should be instituted by means of a Select Committee of the House of Commons.The War Cabinet approved the appointment of a Select Com-mittee of the House of Commons, as proposed by theChancellor of the Exchequer.[826]-541Land ValuesDuties.
2Financial Conditionof Europe.3. The Chancellor or the Exchequer outlined1 certain proposalsfor providing credits for the relief and reconstruction of Europe,and promised to forward a copy of the scheme to the Prime Minister,and to circulate copies to the War Cabinet.Eeport of the Com-mittee of the In-dustrial Conference.4. With reference to War Cabinet 553, Minute 5, the WarCabinet had before them the Report of the Committee of theNational Industrial Conference (Paper G.T.-7057), together with aMemorandum by the Minister of Labour (Paper G.T.-7057 a).The Minister of Labour said he proposed to call a meeting ofthe Provisional Committee on the 29th April, in order to announce the reply of the Government to the recommendations of theIndustrial Conference. The recommendations of the Committee,which were agreed to by representatives of employers and work-men, dealt chiefly with hours, wages, and the setting up of aNational Industrial Council. They recommended a maximumnormal working week of forty-eight hours, but provided for thenecessary elasticity in applying this standard week to the conditionsof particular trades. There were obvious difhouhies in meeting thecase of farm workers, seamen, and domestic servants, and provision would have to be made for exemption from, or variation of, theterms of any Bill in such cases.The Committee recommended recognition of the principle of minimum rates of wages by legal enactment, in order to. ensurethat no class of workers should fall below the standard of a reason-able minimum. In his (Sir Robert Horne&apos;s) opinion the publicwere quite ripe for some such pronouncement. The fixing of anygeneral national minimum would, however, be difficult, and would lead to criticism, inasmuch as in certain cases it would be deemedtoo high and in others too low. The Committee suggested theimmediate appointment of a Commission to report within threemonths as to the measures which ought to be taken under this head.He thought the Government could agree to the establishment ofa minimum wage, and should set up a Commission to consider thebest way of fixing up minima in the various trades.It was further proposed to set up a National Industrial Council,consisting of some 200 representatives of employers and 200 repre-sentatives of workmen, to be chosen on some scheme of representa-tion formulated by each side. The Council would meet twicea year, and would work through Sub-Committees. The working expenses would have to be borne by the Government. It had beenonce suggested that direct representatives &apos; of the Governmentshould sit on the Industrial Council, but in his opinion it would hebetter to keep the Council purely an advisory body which shouldmake representations to the Government.If the War Cabinet approved, he proposed that the PrimeMinister should address a letter to the Provisional Committee, con-surveying the Governments general approval of their recommendations.Sir Robert Home then preceded to read a draft of the proposedletter. &apos; .,,]The First Lord of the Admiralty7 called attention to the special position of agriculture, and to the recent decision to appoint aCommission to examine the present position and prospects of theindustry. It would be impossible to extend to all farm workers amaximum of 48-hours&apos; week, and it had to be borne in mind that the farm workers were not so effectively organised as some of the other large trades of the country. Perhaps the Minister of Labour would examine the relation of the proposed Agricultural Commission to theIndustrial Conference. ;. The Prime Minister suggested&apos; that the case of agriculture might be met in his letter by the introduction of a phrase emphasising itsspecial position. He regretted that the Conference had not boldly faced
the case for a contributory insurance scheme for dealing with unemployment. He thought that a sentence might be included inthe letter drawing attention to the fact that the labours of theindustrial Conference were being closely watched on the Continent.The Secretary of State for War strongly approved recognition ofthe principle of wage minima. In his opinion the real answer ofordered society to Bolshevism was the frank recognition of minimum standards and open access to the highest posts in industry.The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the reply proposed by the Minister of labour to the Report of the National Industrial Conference,subject to the inclusion of a reference to agriculture.(b.) To approve the payment by the Treasury of the expenses ofthe National Industrial Council, its Committees, and itsSecretariat, when set up.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,April 17, 1919.oY


</content>
</cab>
