<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/10/0 images: 40-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic M3jesty&apos;s Grovernment.1Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 10.19.SECRET.X JWAR CABINET, 560.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W,, on tuesday, April 29, 1919, at 12 noon.Present:The Eight Hon. A. Bonar Law (in the Chair).The Eight Hon. The Earl Ccrzon orKedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Eight Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.The following were also presentThe Eight Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., Minister of Eeconstruction and national Service.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P,Secretary of State for War.Major-General P. P. de Eadcliffe, C.B.,D.S.O., Director of Military Operations(for Minute 3).Major-General B. E. W. Childs, C.M.G.,Director of Personal Services (for minute 3).C. Harmsworth, Esq., M.P., Parliamen-tary Under-Secretary, Foreign Office (for minute 1).The Eight Hon. H. W. Forster, M.P.,Financial Secretary, War Office (for minute 3).The Eight Hon. The Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Eight Hon. W. Long, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.Admiral Sir E. E. Wemyss, G.C.B., C.M.G.,M.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.The Eight Hon. T. J. Macnamara,LL.D.,M.P., Parliamentary and Financial Sec-retary, Admiralty (for Minute 3).Captain&quot; A. G. Horn am, Director, TradeDivision, Admiralty (for(Minute 1.)Mr. Thomas Jones, Acting Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Store, C.B., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.Mr. G. M. Evans, Assistant Secretary.[82G]- 57GB
2Relaxation of theBlockade ofGermany.1. With reference to War Cabinet 558, Minute 1, the WarCabinet had under consideration a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for War (Paper G.T.-7149) relating to the relaxation of theblockade of Germany.Mr. Bonar Law said that he did not think it would be advisable for the Cabinet to discuss this question at this moment, when wewere on the eve of presenting the Preliminary Peace Terms toGermany. The subject had been discussed by the War Cabinet onthe 17th April (War Cabinet 558, Minute l), when Loid robert cecil had been present, and he thought it was unnecessary to go beyond the decision then arrived at.The Secretary of State for War said that he wanted to make it quite clear that his military advisers had held the view for sometime that it would be desirable to raise the blockade to some extent,as there would be less chance, if this were done, of Germany relapsinginto complete anarchy ; and if Germany were allowed to do a certainamount of trading, the threat to re-impose the blockade would have greater effect than if it had never been raised.Lord Curzon said that certain military authorities, togetherwith the French, were against the giving up of our sole remainingoffensive weapon. It had been stated that if the blockade was withdrawn it would be easy to re-impose it at any given moment.This, however, was not so in reality. In his view, the blockadeshould be retaiued until it was known whether or not the germans would sign the Preliminary Peace Terms.The first Lord of the Admiralty agreed with Lord Curzon. Hesaid that the blockade machinery had been built up after muchlabour, and if it were once raised it would take a considerable time tore-impose it. In his view, it would not be advisable to take any action at the present moment on the Secretary of State for Warsmemorandum. (The War Cabinet took note of the memorandum by the Secre-tary of State for War on the relaxation of the blockade ofGermany (Paper G.T.-7149), but, in view of the fact that negotiations with the German Peace Delegates would takeplace during that week, came to no decision.Russia:Recognition of admiral KolchaksGovernment.Situation in north russia.2. The Secretary of State for War said that he hoped Mr. bonar law, during his visit to Paris, would draw the Prime Ministersattention to the memorandum which had been prepared by the WarOffice (Paper G.T.-7117) regarding the recognition of admiral kolchak&apos;s Government, and, if possible, to obtain his views upon it.On the previous night a telegram had been received to the effectthat Admiral Kolchak expected to be in Kotlas by the end of Mayor the beginning of June. If this was the case, it would greatlyfacilitate future operations. He thought it would be advisable,however, before Admiral Kolchak was recognised, to obtain adeclaration from him regarding his democratic policy on landquestions, &amp;c. The people of this country should be reassured thatwe were not endeavouring to reinstate a Czarist regime.The Secretary of State for War said he also hoped Mr. bonar law would draw the Prime Ministers attention to the General StaffPaper (P.-114) on the situation in North Russia. It was mostimportant that some decision should be arrived at on the questionsset forth in this memorandum.Naval Pay (Men 3. The War Cabinet had under consideration, the Admiraltyonly). proposals as to the pay and allowances of the Royal Navy and theRoyal Marines (men only) (Paper G.T.-7144).The Chancellor of the&quot; Exchequer said that the Admiralty,before the present First Lord went there, bad appointed a committee
3WG 560of naval officers, under Admiral Jerram, to receive evidence of thevarious ports in the United Kingdom, and to go into the wholequestion of the pay and allowances of the Navy. This Committeehad reported some five weeks previously, and the present Admiraltyproposals, which were based upon the recommendations in that report, had been placed in his hands about a week ago, and hadbeen immediately referred by him to the financial experts at theTreasury, whose report on the proposals he had now received.This matter was one of very grave importance. In the firstplace, the acceptance of the proposals would mean that the pre-warrates of pay of the Navy would be more than doubled. A more serious consideration was the effect that would be produced on theproposals to be put forward by the War Office and the Air ministry for the rates of pay of the post-war Army and Air Force respec-tively. Altogether it would mean an addition to present taxation of at least 25,Ou0,0O0L if pre-war numbers were maintained. Itappeared to him unfortunate that the Committee had been composedentirely of naval officers, and had included no one representing other interests who might be entitled to ask what basis, whether cost ofliving or any other basis, had been taken in arriving at the proposedrates of pay.With regard to the proposals now under consideration, some of the  rates, particularly those for the higher-skilled ratings, appearedto bear little or no relation to civil pay, not even to the pay ofdockyard workers, who were themselves under the Admiralty.Generally, he would prefer to keep the rates of pay for the earlier years of service lower, and increase them by a higher amount in the later years of service. The Financial Secretary to the admiralty had told him, in conversation, that, in order to secure the security and contentment of the Navy, it was essential to accept the recom-mendation of the Jerram Report, and that the Admiralty would view with serious misgivings the effect upon the Navy of a refusal to do so.With regard to the scale of allowances now proposed, theAdmiralty stated that the pay had been increased to such an extent that it would be necessary proportionately to increase allowances inorder to induce men to obtain higher qualifications and good con-:duct badges, and that they therefore recommended allowances whichwere in some cases in excess of those proposed by Admiral Jerram&apos;sCommittee. On this point, however, he pointed out that good conduct pay in the Army had been abolished, and he should have thought that the Admiralty might very well have considered the advisability of abolishing it in the Navy, too. He trusted the WarCabinet would not sanction any allowances higher than those recom-mended in the Jerram Report.&apos;5Another point arose from the proposed allowances to engine-room artificers. Until recently the latter had been the best-paidartizan class in the Navy. A short time ago, however, theAdmiralty had brought the pay of the shipwrights up to the same level, accepting at the same time the condition laid down by theTreasury that there should be no further increase in the pay ofengine-room artificers in order to bring them ahead once more. Thepresent Report, while still observing that condition in the letter,actually nullified it by proposing to give engine-room artificers special allowances on obtaining certificates of capability.The proposals with regard to National Health Insurance wouldhave a considerable effect on the War Office.The Admiralty proposed that all these increases should be ante-dated to the 1st February, 1919. This was&apos; the date from whichthe bonus granted to men in the Armies of Occupation was madepayable. ** It appeared from the subsequent statement of Dr. Macnatnara that theChancellor of the Exchequer had misunderstood him. What had, happened. wasthat these additional allowances had been included by Admiral Jerram&apos;s Committeein their Report on the initiative of the Board of Admiralty.
The First Lord pointed out that this was also the date of the interim increase in the pay of the Navy.The Financial Secretary to the Admiralty, in reply to a question by Mr. Bonar Law, said that at the date of that announcement no promise had been given that further increases would be ante-dated.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said he could see no reasonfor ante-dating these increases, which would cost, it was estimated,about 840,000L (G.T.-7144, p. 7).The First Lord pointed out that Admiral Jerram&apos;s Committeehad proposed that the increases should be retrospective to the1st October, 1918.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said it was not proposed togrant the increases to all men who were in the service on the1st February. but that the increases should be ante-dated for thosemen only who were in the service on the date on which the announce-ment was made. He was of the opinion that it would be impossibleto hold such a position. He understood the Admiralty did not presscertain proposals of the Jerram Committee with regard to pensions.As regards pensions generally, the effect of the present proposals would be to more than double the pre-war rates. The War cabinet had set up a Committee to consider the questions of the pensions ofthe three-armed services, and they had hoped, before anythingdefinite was settled, the proposals of all three services would becorrelated and brought somewhat into line. Before the War Cabinetsettled the details of naval pay he would have liked them to havecorresponding proposals from the War Office and the Air Ministry.If, owing to the delay in dealing with the Fleet&apos;s grievances, andwith the consequent growth of discontent in the Navy, that wereimpossible, he would propose that the War Cabinet should confinethemselves to accepting the rates of pay recommended by theJerram Committee, that the proposed allowances put forward bythe Admiralty should be carefully re-examined, and that theincrease in pay should have no retrospective effect.The First Lord said that the Admiralty appreciated the heavy burden placed upon the Chancellor of the Exchequer at thepresent time. The Committee under Admiral Jerram had beenappointed by the First Lord&apos;s predecessor. Even if the Committeehad been constituted otherwise than it was, he did not believethat they would have come forward with any less proposals thanthose now before the War Cabinet. A Committee had beenappointed in the Grand Fleet for the same purpose, and their recommendations bore out those made by Admiral Jerram.The whole question of naval pay had been brought to a head at christmas. Men, who had not had leave for a long period, had thengone home and discovered their wives and children in far poorercircumstances than the wives and children of men employed on government work of even less importance than they themselves hadbeen performing. So much so was this the case that many of them,rather than burden their wives with the additional expense of theirupkeep at home, had returned to the Fleet before the expiration oftheir &apos; leave. The loyalty of the men was splendid, and -allattempts to work on their grievances in order to sap this loyaltyhad proved ineffective. Then, like a bomb-shell, had come theminers&apos; demands, and the men would have been more than humanif they, had not felt how badly they were paid, and had notexperienced, bitterness when they saw the results obtained bycollective bargaining. It was impossible to exaggerate the seriousness of the position. Unless the Jerram Report were adopted,there would be a feeling of the most intense bitterness amongst themen, and a great opportunity would be given the agitators to fomentunrest and insubordination. It was important that the acceptanceol the Jerram Report should be announced as soon as possible. Onthe last occasion on which the War Cabinet had discussed the pay of the Navy, when the interim increase had been decided upon, the
Admiralty had only adopted the word &quot; bonus,&quot; as applied to thatincrease, in order to meet the views of the War Office ; but it had put them in great difficulties. He was strongly of the opinion thatthe Navy would accept nothing less than the present recommendations.The Secretary of State for War said that as soon as he hadreceived the present Admiralty proposals he had asked that theyshould be examined by the same Committee as had decided the pay of the Armies of Occupation, The time had been too short for themto go into the matter thoroughly, and he was not in a position tosay exactly how the pay of the Army and the Air Force would beaffected. The latter, in one respect, was very similar to the royal navy, namely, in the high percentage of technical experts which theService necessitated, and it was likely, for that reason, to be a veryexpensive Service. He thought he was justified in saying, however,that the effect produced by these proposals on the post-war army would be serious. It should be possible to make concessions to long-service men in the Navy in such a way that it would not prejudice the rates of pay to be decided upon for the comparativelylarge number of short-service men in the Army, as the present proposals would do. It might even make it impossible to obtain anArmy large enough to meet our responsibilities. He was strongly of the opinion that the War Cabinet should postpone considerationof the question until they had before them the views of the WarOffice and the Air Ministry. The future efficiency of the militarymachine would be gravely compromised by precipitately acceptingsome of the present recommendations. The responsibilites of theArmy had greatly increased, and would be governed largely by events, for example, the amount of additional territory which we hadto guard. It was mainly on account of the possible effect upon theArmy that he objected to an immediate acceptance of the Admiraltyproposals.The Financial Secretary to the Admiralty said that the matter was so urgent that the Admiralty were not hi a position to wait forthe War Office views before putting forward their proposals. Everywitness before the Jerram Committee had asked that the decisions should be announced by the last day of March. The Jerram report had been received by the Board of Admiralty on the 27th March,and a very difficult situation would arise unless the Admiralty wereprepared to announce their recommendations almost immediately.With regard to the question of making the increases greater in the later years of service, he pointed out that the Jerram Reportproposed to do a great deal more for the higher ratings than for thelower ratings.The Secretary of State for War said that the private soldier,on the basis of the Admiralty proposals, would have to receive4s. a day.The Chancellor of the Exchequer observed that it was proposedto give 4s. a day to the able seamen, but he did not assent to the proposition that this necessarily involved 4s. for the private soldier.The Financial Secretary to the Admiralty explained that thatwas the rate recommended both by the Jerram Committee and theGrand Fleet Committees. Most of the witnesses before the JerramCommittee had asked for pay at the rate of 5s. lOd. a day. the witnesses before the Grand Fleet had asked for as much as Is. Sd.a day. The Admiralty, however, had adopted the recommendationsof both Committees, for 4s. a day.With regard to the proposed increases in allowances, the sub-substantive pay was increased to such an extent that, unless the non-substantive pay was increased proportionately, there would be noinducement to the men to take the higher qualifications ; in fact, itwas&apos;only in the higher ratings that the increases in non-substantiveallowances were proposed (Appendix 2 to the Admiralty Report,Paper G.T.-7144). The total cost on this account, which amountedto 16&apos;,00dL, did not appear to be too much pay in the interests of efficiency.[826]-5/6 C
With regard to the proposals that all increases should have aretrospective effect, the men were unanimous that they should beante-dated to the 1st October. The only criticism that had beenmade upon the interim increase granted on the 1st February wasthat it had not been ante-dated to the 1st October. If the recom-mendation of the Jerrani Committee, that the increases should be retrospective to the 1st October, were adopted, it would mean anincrease of G,O00,00OZ. or 7,000,0001 The Admiralty, however^were prepared to ante-date the increase to the 1st February, and tomeet the criticism that would be levelled at them for their refusal toante-date it still further.Lord Curzon suggested that, in view of the objections of theTreasury and the War Office, the matter could best be settled by aConference between the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the First Lordof the Admiralty, and the Secretary of State for War, with their financial advisers. They should be able to arrive at a decision in aweek&apos;s time.Mr. Bonar Law said lie agreed that that would be the best wayof proceeding, but he doubted if the War Cabinet realised the urgency of making some early announcement. The matter had aroused agreat deal of feeling, as could be seen by the number of questionsbeing asked in the House.]The First Lord pointed out that these recommendations werethe minimum which the admiralty could recommend, but the situation had been disclosed in the House of Commons, and great pressure hadbeen brought to bear both there and in the press. Two or three members of the Board of Admiralty&apos; who were not naval officersthought that the proposals did not go far enough. On the whole, theBoard were satisfied that these proposals were just, but thoughtanything less would not be just. He agreed that the effect on thearmy of adopting these rates of pay for the Navy must be consider-able. The moment we returned to a peace footing, however, it wouldbe necessary to reduce the British Navy as far as was consistent withour safety, taking into consideration the navies of other countries ;but even for a much reduced navy it would not be possible to getthe men unless we were prepared to pay them.The Chancellor of the Exchequer enquired whether the FirstLord felt that it might he possible to keep the rates of pay for theearlier years of service fairly low, and to give their increases later inthe years.The First Lord replied that he had gone into that questionexhaustively, and he felt it was not possible to reduce the pay of thelower ratings below that now proposed.Mr. Bonar Law said that, in spite of the urgency of the question,he felt that the War Cabinet should not come to a definite conclusion on the subject without knowing what it was likely to mean withregard to the Army and the Air Force. But, in considering this,they would have to consider the effect, not on the pre-war rates of pay in the Army, but on the present rates of pay.The Secretary of State for War said he hoped that the FirstLord, if he adhered to eivino- the whole of the benefit which he nowproposed to the Navy, would try and adjust it in such a way as tohave the least effect on the Army rates of pay. Every poundincrease spent on the Navy might mean an increase of 31. spent onthe Army.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to the factthat the proposals did not deal either with officers or warrant officers, who would have to be taken into consideration, and theWar Cabinet should not lose sight of the fact that the present proposals, if accepted, would have to serve as a basis for the ratesof pay for the commissioned ranks.Mr. Bonar Law suggested that the War Office and the AirMinistry should report upon the Admiralty proposals now beforethe War Cabinet, that the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the First
7WC 560Lord of the Admiralty, and the Secretary of State lor War should then consider together on the matter, and that the War cabinet should consider the question again in a \veek&apos;s time.The First Sea Lord said that he quite realised the force ofeverything that had been said at the War Cabinet that morning,but he felt he should put before them the point of view of the blue-jacket, a point of view which he had made it his duty to studyduring his service. The Admiralty had done everything possible tokeep down unrest and excitement in the Navy, but there werepeople about who made it their business to agitate-people whowere prepared to foment unrest amongst the men even by makingfalse representations and spreading false reports. Unless some definite promise were given in the House of Commons immediately,it was quite possible that these agitators might get at the men evenin the course of the next week.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he desired to enterhis serious protest against the action of the Admiralty in appointing a committee such as that under Admiral Jerram, and in bringing forward proposals such as the present without any previous consulta-tion with the other Departments concerned. Had the War Office,the Air Ministry, and his own Department been consulted in thematter, the Admiralty would have been in a better position todetermine the general lines on which to proceed.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) The Admiralty proposals should again be considered bythe War Cabinet on Wednesday, the 7th May, 1919,after consultation between the Chancellor of theExchequer, the First Lord of the Admiralty, and theSecretary of State for War, when they had received thereports of the War Office and the Air Ministry withregard to the probable effect of these proposals upon therates of pay of the Army and the Royal Air Force.(6.) The First Lord of the Admiralty should be authorised to answer questions in the House of Commons in the sense that the matter was now under consideration by theWar Cabinet, and that it was hoped to announce thedecision in the following week.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,April 29, 1919.Jo

</content>
</cab>
