<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/10/0 images: 104-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.!Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1910.secret war CABINET 569.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onMonday, May 19, 1919, at 11.30 am.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., Minister of Reconstruction and national Service.Major-General J. E. B. Seely, C.B.,C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Under-Secretaryof State for Air (for Minute 1).The Right Hon. Lord Ernle, M.V.O.,President of the Board of Agricultureand Fisheries (for Minute 1).Sir A. D. Hall, K.C.B., M.A., F.R.S.,Secretary, Board of Agriculture andFisheries (for. Minute 1).Sir Malcolm Ramsay, K.C.B., assistant secretary to the Treasury (for Minute 1).Mr. C. A. McCurdy, M.P., parliamentary secretary to the Ministry of Food (for minute 1).Sir L. Worthington Evans, Bart., M.P.,Minister of Pensions (for Minute 1).Sir Edward Trotjp, K.C.B., K.C.V.O.,Permanent TJnder-Secretary of State,Home Office (for Minute 1).Mr. F. H. Oates, C.B., Board of Education(for Minute 1).The Earl of Lytton, Civil Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minute 1).The Bight Hon. Sir R. S. Horne, K.B.E.,K.C., M.P., Minister of Labour (for minute 1).The Right Hon. Lord Inverforth, Ministerof Munitions (for Minute 1).The Right Hon. Sir A. Mond, Bart., M.P.,First Commissioner of Woi*ks (for minute 1).Sir A. Durrant, M.V.O., H.M. Office ofWorks (for Minute 1).Lieut.-Colonel N. G. Scorgie, DeputyController, H.M. Stationery Office (for minute 1).Mr. J. Anderson, C.B., Secretary, Ministryof Shipping (for Minute 1.)Sir W. A. Robinson, K.C.B., C.B.E.,Secretary, Air Ministry (for Minute 1).Mr. G. E. P. Murray, C.B., Secretary,General Post Office (for Minute 1).Mr. B. B. Curitt, Assistant Secretary,War Office (for Minute 1).Mr. Thomas Jones, Acting Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Storr, C.B., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. burgis, Assistant Secretary.[826]-643B
Office Accommoda- 1. With reference to War Cabinet 550, Minute 2, and1 Wartion and Demobili- Cabinet 568, Minute 3, the War Cabinet had before them, a memo-satl0n- randum by the Minister of Reconstruction regarding the staffs ofGovernment departments (Paper G.T.-7246), together with aMemorandum by the First Commissioner of Works, on the general question of Government accommodation in London (paper g.T.-7262).The Minister of Reconstruction said that he had been askedto put forward some suggestions for dealing with dying Govern-ment departments and sub-departments. After looking into theposition, the most hopeful way of dealing with the problemappeared to him to divorce from the working departments those parts of them which were in process of liquidation. For example,the Ministry of National Service had no functions left at all, and only had a staff dealing with the liquidation of accounts. Thesame was the case with the Ministry of Reconstruction. many other departments were in the same position. His suggestion was,therefore, that these staffs should be moved to the AlexandraPalace, and that there they should be under a Chief Liquidator,the Chief Liquidator being allowed a staff of 10,000. Unlesssomething of this kind was done, the process of liquidation woulddrift on for years, involving the occupation of important business premises and hampering work generally. At the present momentthere were some 19,500 men and women engaged on liquidationwork, many of whom were supervising work well within the limits of their full capacity. By a concentration such as he had sug-gested, it would be possible to reduce extensively these administra-tive staffs.Mr. Bonar Law said that he thought Sir Auckland Geddes&apos;suggestion should be adopted in principle. One of the most diffi-cult problems with which the Government was faced at the moment was the charge of extravagance, and the House of Commons wasvery concerned with the slow process of demobilisation of staffs and the relinquishing of requisitioned premises. This state ofaffairs must end, and he was certain that if the Government didnot take drastic action they would be pressed to appoint a SelectCommittee of the House of Commons to go into the question. Hethought the next step, in order to carry out Sir Auckland Geddes&apos;scheme, would be for each department to send to the Minister of reconstruction a list of its staff engaged on liquidation work, andthat then someone should be appointed to take charge of it as soonas possible.The First Commissioner of Works said he doubted whetherit would be practicable to house the proposed Liquidation Depart-ment all in one place, owing to transport and catering difficulties.The full capacity of the Alexandra Palace (which had been sug-gested by Sir Auckland Geddes as a suitable building) was 4,000,provided the Home Office moved out the enemy aliens internedthere. Another building, King George the Fifth Hospital, would hold 4,000. This building was now occupied by the War Office asa military hospital.Sir Edward Troup said that it would not be possible to moveout these enemy aliens at once unless the War Office provided other accommodation. The War Office also used the Alexandra Palacefor combatant prisoners. The Home Office had no objection to giving up the Alexandra Palace, provided that new accommoda-tion was provided within a reasonable distance of London. Thiswas necessary, as the Committee presided over by Mr. JusticeYounger was dealing with the cases of all interned aliens andwould be interviewing individual prisoners.Some discussion then took place regarding the necessity forthe War Office holding such a large building as King George the fifth Hospital, in the centre of London, when there were severalhospitals in the Provinces with vacant beds. It was pointed outthat there were 2,000 beds in King George the Fifth Hospital,
only 1,400 of which were occupied, and attention was drawn tothe fact that there were many thousands of vacant beds in theProvinces.Mr. Cubitt, representing the War Office, said it was proposedto vacate the King George the Fifth Hospital at the end of June.There was a scheme for vacating the Great Central Hotel and con-concentrating the officers from that hospital in grounds belonging tothe London County Council. This would necessitate the erection of huts, and would cost some  5,000. On the other hand, it would save some  23,000, which was being paid for the Great CentralHotel.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that the WarOffice should furnish a return showing the number of camps inoccupation; the uses to which they were being put; and particulars of prisoner camps which had been closed.The Minister of Reconstruction said that, although he couldnot vouch for the accuracy of the statement, he was informed thatthe War Office were closing provincial hospitals in the interestsof the medical profession in London, and that one of the reasonsfor the War Office wishing to retain the King George the FifthHospital was that it was useful for clinical research.The Minister of Pensions drew attention to the fact that several of the hospitals in the Provinces were in schools,infirmaries, and other buildings belonging to local authorities whowere anxious to get back their premises. His suggestion was thatthe War Office and the Ministry of Pensions should go into thequestion and submit a proposition to the War Cabinet. He him-self was interested in the reversion of some of these hospitals, and could not consent to letting them all go.The Minister of Labour mentioned that a great number ofhuts would soon be required in the agricultural districts throughthe, lack of housing accommodation. In a short time a, number ofsoldiers wrould come to the end of their unemployment donation,but employment could be given them on the land&apos;, provided thataccommodation was available. He would be willing to go into thisquestion with the President of the Board of Agriculture, theMinister of Supply, and the War Office.The First Commissioner of Works then drew7 attention to thefact that the Aircraft Production Department, with a staff of3,000, occupied most important business premises in Kingsway.Sir Auckland Geddes and himself had interviewed a deputationof the tenants on the previous Friday, and Sir Auckland Geddeson. behalf of the Government, with his (Sir A. Mond) concurrence,promised to restore their premises to them, if possible, by December. He would like to mention that the Government was in a veryweak position regarding the compulsory occupation of business premises after the De Keyser case, and most of the premises werebeing occupied on very slender rights.The TJ nder-Secretary for Air (who entered at this moment)said that it was convenient that the Aircraft Production Depart-ment should be in close proximity to the Air Ministry, but he must confess that it was not absolutely essential.Some discussion then took place as to whether the aircraft production Department was at the present moment under thedirection of the Secretary of State for Air or the Minister ofMunitions, and it was pointed out that the decision arrived at bythe-War Cabinet in this connection (War Cabinet 564, Minute 3),&quot; to approve, subject to the Prime Minister&apos;s ratification, therecommendations of Sir James Stevenson&apos;s Committee,&quot; had not met with the approval of the Prime Minister, and the matter wastherefore still in abeyance.Mr. Bonar Law said that there was no reason why theMinister of Munitions should not deal with the question of(a) ascertaining how large a part of the Aircraft production department could be housed on the outskirts of London; (b) how643        &quot; \ B 2
-J-far it was possible to reduce the staff, without prejudicing thesettlement of the question as to which Department shouldultimately be responsible for aircraft production.The Minister of Reconstruction said that, from the point ofview of trade, the holding on to requisitioned business premiseswas having a very bad effect; but, linked up with this matter, wasthe bigger and wider question of how far it was necessary tocentralise the staff of a Government department in the vicinity ofWhitehall. His experience was that portions of a great numberof departments, who were engaged purely on routine work, couldbe housed, without adversely affecting their work, elsewhere thanin the vicinity of Whitehall. He suggested that the First Com-missioner of Works should form an estimate of the amount of accommodation required in &quot;Whitehall by each department, andthen make the department justify any increase over and above theFirst Commissioners estimate.Mr. Anderson said that there were no doubt some small sub-departments of the Local Government Board which could be movedout of Whitehall, and he had been looking into the question.Before the war, departments had always gone on the principle of concentration, but, as far as the Local Government Board was con-cerned, there was no doubt that any saving in the space occupiedby the headquarters staff by a removal to the outskirts of london of small sub-sections would be far more than offset by the addi-tional requirements of the new Ministry of Health. The HealthInsurance Commission had, from the outset, practically restrictedits premises in Buckingham Gate to headquarters staff.Sir Auckland Geddes said that what applied to the LocalGovernment Board also applied to the Board of Trade, and therewas no reason why the Patents and similar departments should be housed in Whitehall Gardens.The First Commissioner of Works then drew attention to paragraph 5 of his Memorandum, in which he stated that he hadbeen examining the question of the permanent housing of theMinistry of Supply, and, as the result of conferences with LordInverforth, he recommended that the staff of the Ministry ofSupply, numbering, say, 2,800, should be permanently housed in imperial and Caxton Houses, together with some adjacentaccommodation to provide for the balance of their requirements.Imperial House was already on lease, Caxton House would haveto be acquired, some portions probably compulsorily, as a largenumber of business firms had leases there.M&apos;r. Bonar Law said that this suggestion looked as if sir alfred Mond wanted to do the very thing which the Governmentwas endeavouring to avoid, i.e., taking over the premises ofbusiness firms.The First Commissioner of Works pointed out, however, that since the war five new Ministries had been created, and office accommodation for them must be found somewhere. If theMinistry of Supply was housed as he had suggested, it wouldrelease the Hotel Metropole, which was very expensive.The Minister of Munitions said that he could move out ofthe Hotel Metropole in twenty-four hours, provided that other accommodation was given to him. He hoped to discharge 5,000of his staff by the end of June, and a further 5,000 by the end ofJuly. He did not propose that the staff of his new ministry should exceed 3,000. He would like to draw the attention of theFirst Commissioner of Works to the Clothing Factory at Pimlico,which was a bad factory but-which would make good offices.The Minister of Reconstruction said that there were two other matters in connection with the subject which he would liketo mention: (a) the space occupied by the Dominions and Allies:he thought pressure should be brought upon them to release the accommodation they held as soon as possible;. (b) the ranges of premises in occupation by the War Office for barracks.    These
premises were not in the business area, but it was a matter ofsome importance.Mr. Bonar Law said that, in this matter of the reduction&quot;of staff and the release of premises, the permanent heads of depart-ments could give a great deal of assistance, and he would like themto realise that these questions were, from a Parliamentary pointof view, of the very greatest importance; he appealed to them,therefore, to give every assistance in their power.. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would like the heads of departments to draw the attention of the Treasury toany liquidation work which was being carried on for which little or no return was expected. It was sometimes the case that largestaffs were used for liquidation purposes in order to save anamount not at all commensurate with the cost of the staff engaged on the work. He would also be glad if the Food Controller would consider the future of the Sugar Commission.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) The Secretary of State for War and the Minister ofPensions should examine the question of releasingbuildings used as military hospitals in the london area, and make proposals for the consideration of theWar Cabinet.(5.) The King George the Fifth Hospital should be freed atthe earliest possible moment by the War Office.(c.) Sir Auckland Geddes should go into the question of therelease of the Alexandra Palace, in consultation withthe War Office and the Home Office.The War Cabinet were of the opinion that theAlexandra Palace should be released, and requestedSir Auckland Geddes to report whether, and how soon,the wishes of the War Cabinet could be carried out.(d.) The Minister of Labour, in consultation with the WarOffLe, the Ministry of Munitions, the Local Govern-ment Board, and the Board of Agriculture, should ascertain to what extent huts could be provided in agricultural districts for the housing of discharged soldiers whom it was proposed to employ on the land.(e.) The Minister of Food should consider the question of thefuture of the Sugar Commission, and report to&apos; theWrar Cabinet at an early date.(/.) The Minister of Munitions and the Under-Secretary ofState for Air should examine the question of how far it was possible immediately to reduce the staff of theAircraft Production Department, and whether it waspossible to house any of the staff in offices not in thecentre of London.(g.) The Departments should send to Sir A. C. Geddes par-ticulars of any sections engaged on liquidation workwhich might suitably be transferred to the proposedLiquidation Department.Supplementation of --------;----5-----separation allowances.2. The War Cabinet took note (1.) That the Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Pay Committee, at ameeting held on the 29th April, 1919, decided (paper g.T.-7179):-(a.) To accept the principle of supplementationin the case of men retained compulsorily inthe Army and men continuing their servicewithout any break: but that supplementa-
tion should not be granted to men enlistingfor the first time, or re-engaging afterdemobilisation or discharge.(&amp;.) That the Ministry should, for the present,continue the administration of the grant ofsupplementary allowances.(c.) That the Ministry of Pensions, after con-sultation with the War Office as to the precise wording to be employed, should circulate to Local War Pensions Com-mittees a letter conveying the decision ofthe Committee; and(2.) That the Treasury had agreed to the issue of the circularreferred to in (c) above.The War Cabinet decided To approve the above decisions of the Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos;Pay Committee.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,May 19, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
