<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/141/0 images: 418-443</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
68C(69) 42 COPY NO0__29th April, 1969CABINETCOMMONWEALTH IMMIGRATION;  COMPULSORY entry certificates FOR SETTLEMENTNote by the Secretary of State for the Home department at a meeting on 24th. April, the Committee on Immigration imdCommunity Relations agreed to a proposal from me that we should takethe opportunity presented by the Immigration Appeals Bill (now awaitingCommittee consideration in the House of Lords) to make entry certificates for settlement by Commonwealth dependants compulsoryinstead of optional.2.       The proposal is set out in detail in my memorandum to theCommittee, a copy of which is annexed.    The Committee noted thatcare would be needed in presentation but concluded that it would be right to make the change.    The difficulties would be reduced if thesame change were made in relation to aliens1 dependants and I proposeso to arrange - to the extent, that is, that visa abolition arrangementsleave us free to do so.3.      I bring the matter to the notice of the Cabinet because our action will attract some attention and because in the Parliamentary Committeein November we thought that the proper course was not to enter into any commitment for or against the introduction of compulsory entry certificates but to ventilate the arguments before the Select Committeeand then to consider further.    At that stage, one of the points we hadin mind was the importance of avoiding any appearance of relating ourown actions to the urgings of the Opposition.4.       That consideration does not at present apply.    On the other hand,it has become clear that the Select Committee will not consider the issueuntil next Session when we might have difficulty over securing time forthe necessary legislation;  and meanwhile the case on humanitarian andadministrative grounds for making the change has gained in strength.The principal object is to ease the very difficult conditions which havebeen experienced in recent times at the ports of entry (especially london airport) by transferring the scrutiny of applications for admission of as many immigrants as possible to their country of origin.    The introductionof an appeals system is a convenient occasion for making the change.DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER. BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)

5.      As to presentation, we can show that what we are proposing J.8perfectly proper and is patently in the interests of intending immigrants.The necessary amendments to the Bill, which are quite straightforward,ought to go down within the next few days if we are to ensure reasonable time for consideration in the remaining stages in both Houses.    I ammeanwhile arranging to make sure the purpose of the amendments isunderstood by Mr. Arthur Bottomley (the Chairman of the SelectCommittee), Mr. Frank Cousins (the Chairman of the community relations Commission), Mr. Quintin Hogg and a number of others.JL*. j. c.Home Office, 8.W.I.29th April, 1969-2-

COMMONZ/KALT H JUKI I ORATION: COMP ULSORYENTRY CERTIFICATES FOR SETTLEMENT1,    The purpose of this note is to suggest that we should lookagain at the question of making entry certificates compulsory for settlement while it is still possible to do this in this Session,by amendment of the Immigration Appeals Bill in the House of Lords.Shortcomings of the present system,    I am concerned by the difficulties of continuing with thepresent arrangements under which claims for settlement in thiscountry are in most cases not examined before immigrants arrivehere.     These arrangements are burdensome to operate in practice.As is explained later in this note,  there is a substantial problem in obtaining accommodation at London Airport for passengers held for further examination, and some of the individual cases highlightthe shortcomings of the system.     For example, in the recent caseof Miss Amina Patel the Home Office and the High Court spent morethan seven weeks trying to discover the truth about the relationship of this girl to a man who was said to be her father, and who wasresident in this countryB     All this time this young girl had to be detained, and in the end she was sent away.     A single case ofthis kind requires an immense amount of effort to be directed attrying to unravel the truth, in most trying conditions for allconcerned;   and the prolonged detention, and eventual return, iscertainly harmful to community rel at ions.     The prevalence ofattempted evasion and the impossibility of relying on documents ororal testimony means that the genuine immigrant is necessarilysubjected to careful, and it may be prolonged, examination indistressing circumstances;    and experience has shown that so longas entry certificates remain an optional facility they will not beobtained by most of those who come here for settlement.     Only one in eight of those who came from India in 1968 as dependent relativeshad entry certificates.     (The number of Indian citizens refused admission rose from 620 in 1967 to 1 ,263 in 1 968 and has indeeddoubled in every year since control was instituted.)3o The difficulties are largely confined to immigrants coming from India and Pakistan. The contrast with the West Indies is most marked.     Apparently because B.O.A.C. have a monopoly on air

traffic from ph.o West Indies they are able to insist on theobtaining of entry certificates before immigrants set out, andthere is no problem on arrival in this country.     They cannotfollow this course on other routes, on which there is competition between the air lines.     Clearly a system of compulsory entry certificates for settlement would not work as smoothly in India orPakistan as it does in the West Indies because of the shortcomingsof the Asian systems of registration of births, marriages anddeaths;   nor would compulsory entry certificates for settlementhelp with the problem of the bogus visitor or the bogus student.But what the system would do would be to give a clear passage tothe genuine immigrant who had obtained a certificate before setting out, and this would relieve him of the hardship and distressnecessarily involved by prolonged examination in this country, andalso of the apprehension of being refused entry.     Further, bysiphoning off these cases it would enable the immigration service to concentrate on the doubtful ones, and so to oarry out their task more effectively.Recent consideration of the questionIj.,    It may help if I summarise the recent history of theconsideration of this issue.     On 7th October 1968 (london(68) hthMeeting) we examined it on the basis of a comprehensive report by officials (ICR(68) 12) which set out as follows the main arguments for the introduction of compulsory entry certificates -(a)    it would relieve both the immigrants and the immigrationservice of the strain caused by the present system;as fewer passengers would have to be detained and returned to their own country community relations wouldbe relieved of an irritant;(c)    there would be a better prospect of compiling an effective register of entitled dependants.The reasons against the introduction of compulsory entry certificates were put by officials as follows -(i)    the numbers of immigrants entering would not be reduced;(ii)    legislation would be required which would be likely tobe controversial and might exacerbate race relations;and the legislation would have to be passed quickly toavoid a rush by wives and children;(iii)    the system would have to be operated inflexibly;anyone coming for settlement without a certificatewould have to be refused entry, and this might be afocus of continuing criticism;(iv)    there might be pressure for appeals against refusalsof certificates to be heard overseas, and this would be expensive;    and in any event to make certificatescompulsory would require increases in the staffing of entry certificate offices, and so increased overseas expenditure;2GQK3FGE)EEMim[L

COKHFDB3EMTBALdraff io from jbho West Indies they are able to insist on theobtaining of entry certificates before immigrants set out, andthere is no problem on arrival in this country.     They cannotfollow this course on other routes, on which there is competition between the air lines.     Clearly a system of compulsory entry certificates for settlement would not work as smoothly in India orPakistan as it does in the West Indies because of the shortcomingsof the Asian systems of registration of births, marriages anddeaths;   nor would compulsory entry certificates for settlementhelp with the problem of the bogus visitor or the bogus student.But what the system would do would be to give a clear passage tothe genuine- immigrant who had obtained a certificate before setting out, and this would relieve him of the hardship and distressnecessarily involved by prolonged examination in this country, andalso of the apprehension of being refused entry.     Further, bysiphoning off these cases it would enable the immigration service to concentrate on the doubtful ones,  and so to carry out their task more effectively.Recent consideration of the questionh.    It may help if I summarise the recent history of theconsideration of this issue.     On 7th October 1968 (ICR(68) hthMeeting) we examined it on the basis of a comprehensive report by officials (ICR(68) 12) which set out as follows the main arguments for the introduction of compulsory entry certificates -(a) it would relieve both the immigrants and the immigrationservice of the strain caused by the present system;(b) as fewer passengers would have to be detained and returned to their own country community relations wouldbe relieved of an irritant;(c) there would be a better prospect of compiling an effective register of entitled dependants.The reasons against the introduction of compulsory entry certificates were put by officials as follows -(i)    the numbers of immigrants entering would not be reduced;(ii)    legislation would be required which would be likely tobe controversial and might exacerbate race relations;and the legislation would have to be passed quickly toavoid a rush by wives and children;(iii)    the system would have to be operated inflexibly;anyone coming for settlement without a certificatewould have to be refused entry, and this might be afocus of continuing criticism;(iv)   there might be pressure for appeals against refusalsof certificates to be heard overseas, and this would be expensive;    and in any event to make certificatescompulsory would require increases in the staffing of entry certificate offices, and so increased overseas expenditure;

(v)    the change would he resented by some commonwealth countries;    the Old Commonwealth would regard it as evidence of the further weakening of ties with theUnited Kingdom and the New Commonwealth as introducing a covert element of racial discrimination intoimmigration policy;    and there might be measures of retaliation from India,,5,    The Official Committee did not recommend the adoption of compulsory certificates.     It was suggested that instead India and pakistan might be invited to co-operate in the introduction of asystem of control.     We agreed with this conclusion.     The note ofour discussion records the majority view that, while legislation could be i^resented as being in the interests of the immigrants, itwuld be likely to be misrepresented;   and that the change mightexacerbate race relations without giving us any control overnumbers entering.     We concluded that the better course would benot to announce a decision on the matter, but to take theopportunity presented by the appointment of the Select Committeeon Race Relations and Immigration to set out the arguments for and against the introduction of compulsory entry certificates while inthe meantime endeavouring to persuade India and Pakistan toco-operate on some system of control.j,   Subsequently, in the debate on the Expiring Laws ContinuanceSill (Official Report, 13th November columns hhl-h) I said thatMs was a practical matter, not raising a point of principle, thatit was a question of balancing the administrative pros and cons,ana that the subject was one that might well benefit from study1 ky the Selectect Committee,     The  arlimsrontary CommitteeIionsidered the matter on 28th November (on the basis of my paper&apos;(68) 15), and agreed that the proper course was mot to enterInto any commitment for or against the introduction of compulsoryentry certificates, but to ventilate the arguments before theSelect Committee, and then to consider further.

Recent developments7P     Since November there have been a number of relevantdevelopments -(a) We have concluded (I .C.R. (68)6th Meeting:    item 2) thatthere is no prospect of securing the co-operation of Indiaor Pakistan in any effective plan of voluntary control.(b) The Select Committee are confining their attention inthis Session to the problem of the coloured school-leaver,and so there is no prospect of their making any report aboutentry certificates until, perhaps, July 1970.(c) In the course of the debates on the Immigration AppealsBill Members from both sides of the House have supported theintroduction of compulsory entry certificates.(d) The pressure on accommodation at London Airport forimmigrants held in detention is becoming intolerable,,particularly at week-ends.     There are only some two dozenplaces at the airport.     The surplus passengers have to beput into hotels, i:f  there is nc need for detention in the strict sense, or penal institutions.     The hotels aroundLondon Airport are becoming more and more reluctant to accommodate Commonwealth immigrants, and the airline companies are contesting the obligation resting on them to pay for the accommodation of passengers held under refusal or forfurther examination because the longer periods of detention,and the detention of larger numbers of people, are provingmore and more expensive for them.     (We are hoping to amend the Immigration Appeals Bill in the House of Lords tssclarify the obligations of the carrying companies:    thecompanies will pay for accommodation unless the passengerheld a work permit, employment voucher, visa or entry certificateor is eventually admitted - for example by winning an appeal against the refusal;    feut public funds will meet the costwhere the passenger held no such document of entitlement andthe refusal   is sustained.)     The search for suitable accommodation is putting a severe strain on the immigrationservice.     The introduction of the appeal system, with entry certificates remaining an optional facility, may make mattersworse rathei? than better.     The appellate authorities willhave power to grant bail, but many immigrants will not havethe means to find accommodation near London Airport, wherethey will have to come for the hearing of the appeal.    Theprovision of semi-secure hostel accommedation on a -substantial scale is likely to prove necessary and will be expensive,(e) At the time of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos;Conference there was general agreement by all the commonwealth countries that it was for &quot;ach country to decide for itself onthe conditions under which it would permit citizens of othercountries to enter.     This suggests that there should not begrave Commonwealth repercussions from making entry certificatescompulsory for settlement, a step which would be taken in theinterests of the genuine   immigrant.     We would make it cleark

to Commonwealth Governments that the dependants&apos; right of entry was not being taken away or deferred, and that therewould be rights of appeal both against a refusal to issue a certificate and against the refusal of admission of the holder of a valid certificate,,Legislation8.    The Immigration Appeals Bill will soon go into Committee inthe House of Lords, and could be amended to make entry certificatescompulsory for settlement .     The amendment would coverCommonwealth citizens with a statutory right of entry - that is.,wives and children under 16 of people resident here.     The bill would then be brought back to the Commons and passed into law,and in fixing the timetable for this we would have to bear in mind the possibility of a rush developing to &quot;beat the ban&quot; (seeparagraph 11),9,    The effect of the change in the lav/ would be to preserve thestatutory right of entry of wives and children under 16 coming tojoin husbands and parents who had been accepted for settlement,but to say that the right should be exercisable only if the passenger had obtained an entry certificate from the appropriaterepresentatives of the United Kingdom Governments     And for thosewithout a statutory right of entry (children over 16, dependentparents etc.) coming here for settlement there would be a paralleladministrative requirement to obtain an entry certificate beforesetting out, as we have introduced for male fiances.Rights of appeal10,   If we were to make entry certificates compulsory for settle-ment, it would be essential to introduce a right of appeal immediatelyboth against a decision to refuse to issue a certificate and alsoto cover the rare case in which the holder of a valid certificateis refused entry on arrival here - for example, where the certificate has been obtained by misrepresentation.     Such rightswill become available when the appeal provisions of the immigration appeals Bill are brought into operation, but this could not be doneimmediately without appointing the Immigration Appeals tribunal and adjudicators, and making the complex rules of procedure forthe appeal system (on which the Council on Tribunals have to be consulted) at an impossible speed.     Instead, these rights could oeintroduced on a non-statutory and temporary basis, pending theintroduction of the statutory appeal system, as with the arrangementswe made for appeal by United Kingdom passport holders in EastAfrica.     I would state that I would regard myself as bound by thedecisions of the &quot;adjudicators&quot;.     Appeals would be heard in thiscountry, as is envisaged under the Immigration Appeals Bill (seelast sentence of paragraph 16 for representation of appellants whoare overseas).

11,   While there is hound to &quot;be some risk of a rush &quot;to beat theban&quot;, it seems unlikely that this could assume seriousproportions in the kind of time-scale envisaged.   The situationis not comparable with that of the Asian community in Bast Africawhere heads of households had taken out United Kingdom passports &apos;as an insurance, and where many passports were issued during thelong build up -to the crisis.   The Indian and Pakistani dependantsF/ith rights of entry are the wives and children of men alreadyhere, and their general practice is not to take out passports, initself a lengthy process, until shortly before they are to cometo the United Kingdom.   There are not, the available informationsuggests, a large number of people holding passports in readiness; nor is it likely that those who had obtained passportscould quickly raise the fare for a journey to the United Kingdom,as was the case with many of those in the comparatively wealthycommunity in East Africa.Cost12,   The fact that passports cannot be taken out quickly in Indiaand Pakistan also suggests, that if entry certificates were madecompulsory our offices there would not at once be swamped with applications.   But in the longer term there would be a very substantial increase in work, and a need for increased staffing(some increase would in any event be necessary when thestatutory appeal system was introduced).   The report by theOfficial Committee (paragraph 19 of I.C.R. (68)12) put this additional overseas cost, over and above the cost inherent inthe introduction of the appeal system, at  50,000 a year.Against this have to be set the savings in expenditure at home.They cannot be quantified, but clearly we shall be able to do with a smaller increase in staff and port accommodation if manyof the difficult cases are processed overseas.   I should be surprised if there domestic savings did not significantlyexceed the increase in overseas expenditure.Paragraphs 21-25 of I.C.R.(68)12 referred to the possibleadditional cost of the overseas medical examination of applicants for entry certificates.   I believe that this can be disregarded.   The entitled dependant cannot be refused entry on medical grounds and I think that it would be wrong to take sucha power.   There is power in such cases to impose a requirement that the passenger report after entry for medical examination and this seems adequate.   In the case of the person without a fight of entry (children over 16, dependent parents) there ispower to refuse entry on medical grounds, and this would remain the position if a (compulsory) entry certificate were obtained; but so rarely is it necessary to exercise the powerthat it does not seem justifiable to require all applicants tobe medically.examined overseas by a doctor approved by us,although, depending on the Commonwealth country, we couldencourage applicants to obtain a medical certificate.6

CONFQIDIiSMTn&amp;LAliens13,   If entry certificates were made compulsory fcr commonwealth citizens,  it might he argued that, to avoid discrimination, weshould take, parallel steps for aliens; hut, for the following reasons, I consider that there should he no change in theexisting arrangements for them.Ill,   The 37 visa abolition agreements that we have signed make itimpossible for us to refuse entry to aliens who come here for settlement without having obtained something corresponding to anentry certificate.   It is true that visa abolition agreements arevery far from being aimed at freedom for settlement.   They areconcerned with freedom for travel.   The countries of western europe have abolished visas for nationals of many countries; butthey maintain strict control over settlement.    The- reason why thevisa abolition agreements cause us difficulty in this context is because they are based on Continental systems of immigration,which have little in the way of effective control at the point of entry, but much more in the way of subsequent internal supervisionthan we favour.   So these agreements provide for the unhinderedpassage of frontiers.   The most that we could do, consistently with these agreements, would be to say that aliens were not to beadmitted for settlement on arrival; but, by far the largestcategory of aliens coming for settlement consists of the wives(mostly European)  of British subjects, and to admit them on atime condition when they arrive, often just after the marriage and with their husbands, would be a peculiarly unattractivepiece c*f bureaucratic rigidity.15.   Alien admission fcr settlement is on a modest scale.   fewer than L,000 aliens a year are admitted for settlement and nearly3,000 of these are wives of the resident population admittedwith, or to join, their husbands (if the husband is an alienand still on a time condition, the wife will be admitted on atime condition also).   Of the remaining 800 or so cases the greatmajority are the children or elderly parents of aliens already accepted here as members of the resident population..    In most ofthese cases their arrival will have been the subject of priorapplication to the Home Office and approval, and there are no substantial problems of identification, etc., at the port of entry.   The number who come for settlement without prior approval is only about 200 a year and they are admitted on atime condition and advised to make out their case for settlement to the Home Office.El&amp;lic. Presentation and consultation16.   If we legislate to make entry certificates compulsory, carewill have, to be given to the public presentation of the case forthe change.    In moving the amendment to the Immigration AppealsBill we can consistently refer to ^ur earlier speeches on theBill and in the Expiring Laws Continuance Debate as showing that&apos;he point was one that we had long been considering; we can say7C O M FIB E M T Q A L

that we havo only just reached a decision, in the light of theviews expressed in Parliament, and that having reached a decisionit is sensible to give erroot -to it in tho only way in which this can he done promptly.17.   Generally, in public presentation of the change we would saythat the dependants1 rights of entry were not being taken awaynor was their exercise being deferred; that the change was intended to give an easy passage to the genuine immigrant; andthat it should reduce the number of cases in which commonwealth immigrants have to be held for examination, and also the numberof cases in which we have to refuse entry and send the passengertack to his country of origin.    We would emphasise theintroduction of the rights of appeal, and we should enlist the aid of the immigrant organisations to assist and &quot;representappellants, on the lines envisaged for the statutory appealsystem.18.   The need to keep a change in the law secret would preventwidespread consultation before the amendment was tabled; but,it is were decided upon I would explain the position to theChairman of the Select Committee, and I would seek theco-operation of the Chairman of the Community Relations Commission,and the Chairman of the Race Relations Board,   And our high commissioners in the Commonwealth countries concerned would haveto be fully briefed, and consulted abiut the staffing if the entry certificate offices and the procedure envisaged forappeals,O O M FIB) E M T1 A L



JW , CONFIDENTIAL[document IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS GOVERNMENT)C(69) 432nd May, 1969THE RELEASE OF OFFICIAL, INFORMATIONMemorandum by the Lord Privy SealIntroductionAt their meeting on 21st March the Parliamentary committee considered a memorandum by the Prime Minister (G(69) 21) about therelease of official information.    The general feeling of the Committeewas that the Government would be unwise to set up an inquiry into thissubject, but that there might be advantage in publicising the Government^record in making information available, either in a White Paper or insome other form.    The Committee took no final decision on whether to publish a White Paper but asked me to consider what might be included.The Freedom of Publication (Protection) bill.       The Committee also asked me in consultation with the paymaster general to advise the Attorney General on what he should say about thismatter when the Freedom of Publication (Protection) Bill was debated inStanding Committee.    When this debate took place on 16th April, the attorney General explained that the Governments examination of the issues involved was now well advance.nced; and that they intended to make astatement to Parliament about the matter shortly.    He also made itclear that the Official Secrets Acts, with which Clause 3 of the Bill was concerned, in no way limited a Government from authorising the disclosure of information in any circumstances that it judged to be appropriate.    He urged the Committee to reject Clause 3 on the groundthat it would be wrong to throw open to argument in the courts thequestion whether or not the public interest was prejudiced in anyparticular case by the publication of official information.3.       The supporters of the Bill are using Clause 3 to advance theirargument that the terms of the Official Secrets Act are too wide and canbe used to prevent the publication of information which is embarrassing to the Government of the day, although not prejudicial to the publicinterest.    Mr. Eyre, the Billys sponsor, offered to withdraw the ClauseB copy NO.        wCABINET-1-CONFSDENTIAL


</content>
</cab>
