<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/69 images: 698-701</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1945.SECRET.W.P. (45) 319.21st May, 1945.WAR CABINET.DEFECTS IN THE MAY ELECTORAL REGISTER.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.IN the Memorandum of the 1st May (W.P. (45) 278) which the Secretary ofState for Scotland and I circulated to the War Cabinet, attention was called to certain defects in the May electoral register and suggestions were made asto amending the legislation. The War Cabinet, at their meeting on the 4th May(W.M. (45) 58th Conclusions, Minute 6), reached no decision on our proposals but &quot; invited the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland, inthe light of the discussion, to prepare and submit to them a draft of an Electoral(Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill.&quot; A draft of such a Bill will be brought beforethe War Cabinet in due course, but in view of the many representations whichare being made to me by M.Ps., both by correspondence and by parliamentary questions, it is desirable that I should be authorised to make in Parliament some general statement about certain classes of persons who will not be able to voteat an election for which the May register will be in operation.The most important- of these classes is that of persons, including evacueesand &quot; directed workers,&quot; who have moved from the address in respect of whichthey were registered on the 31st January (the qualifying date) and will be prevented by distance from voting in person and are not eligible to vote by post.In W.P. (45) 278, it wras suggested that provision might be made by legislation to enable such persons to apply to be entered on the Absent Voters List so thatthey can vote by post, and in any statement that is made it would be desirable toindicate that consideration is being given to the question whether the statutory provisions relating to absent voters shall be amended so as to enlarge the classesof persons enabled to vote by post.Secondly, representations are being made about individuals whose nameshave been omitted from the register because the machinery for the compilationof the register has not operated with 100 per cent, efficiency. From such testsas it has been possible to make it appears that the number of ijersons so omittedis not more than a minute fraction of the total electorate, but such omissionsnaturally provide a special ground for grievance. Strenuous efforts are being-made to correct such omissions or errors and by the time the October electoralregister is compiled there is every hope that these defects will have been rectified.Thirdly, complaints are also made about omissions from the Service register.It is estimated by the Service Departments that about 90 per cent, of the service voters will be on the register, and this is a satisfactory percentage, but there arecertain small classes of Service voters whose declarations were not received in timefor entry on the May register. They include emergency commissioned officersin the Indian Army and persons similarly situated in the Colonial Forces whowere made eligible for registration by the Representation of the People Act, 1945,and had only a short time in which to make and send home their declarations,some Service voters about whom there had been delay in notifying the electoral registration Officers that they had reached the age of 21, and some merchant seamen who had been liberated from prison camps in Germany. As regardspersons in these classes no difficulty will arise in respect of the October reguster,since declarations which were too late for the May register will be in time forthe October register.I submit, for consideration, a draft of a statement which I propose to makein the House of Commons, if the War Cabinet agree.Home Office, Whitehall, S.W.1,21st May, 1945.Copy No.[29934]
Draft of Statement to be made in Parliament.Hon. Members have drawn attention both by Questions and correspondence tothe fact that some persons will not be able to vote at an election for which theMay Register will be in operation. There are three classes of persons affected.First, some names have been omitted from the Register because the machinery forcompilation has not operated with 100 per cent, efficiency. Secondly, there are some Service voters whose declarations were not received by the 15th March, thelast date for the receipt of Service declarations. Thirdly, there are persons,including evacuees and &quot; directed workers,&quot; who have now moved from the address in respect of which they were registered on the 31st January (the qualify-ing date) and will be prevented by distance from voting in person, and are noteligible to vote by post.As regards failures in the methods of compilation, much as the Governmentregret these failures, it is only fair to the officers concerned to point out that thedifficulties which are inevitable on the first occasion of the operation of a new procedure have been greatly aggravated by staff shortages and the necessity inmany places of making shift with inexperienced assistants. Taking the electorateas a whole, it would not seem that the proportion of persons affected by theseomissions is more than a minute fraction, though this is of course no consolationto the individuals in question. Strenuous efforts are being made to correct thesedefects in methods of compilation, and there is every hope that as regards the october Register there will be little cause of complaint on this head.As regards the Service voters it is estimated by the Service Departmentsthat 90 per cent, of these voters will be included in the May Register, but thereare certain comparatively small classes of Service voters whose declarations werenot received in time for the May Register. For the October Register the qualifyingdate is the 30th June, and this should afford ample time for the receipt of anylate Service declarations.As regards persons who have moved away from the constituencies in whichthey are registered as electors, the October Register will pick up those who movedbetween the 31st January, the qualifying date for the May Register, and the30th June, but there will also be removals after that date, &quot;and with a view to meeting these cases consideration is being given to the question whether thestatutory provisions relating to absent voters might be amended so as to enlargethe classes of persons enabled to vote by post.



</content>
</cab>
