<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/85/0 images: 59-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
57SECRETC.(57) 15COPY NO.29th January, 1957CABINETOVERSEA broadcasting memorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster asterBy direction of the prime Minister a Ministerial Committee hasbeen constituted under my Chairmanship, with the following terms ofreference:-2.      This Committee will proceed to review the oversea information services and to report to the Cabinet as rapidly as possible.    But,without prejudice to their final recommendations, I anticipate that theCommittee may recommend significant changes in the scope and direction of the oversea information services, with consequentialmodifications in the expenditure which they entail.    These modifica-tions cannot be settled in time to be reflected in the 1957-58 Depart-mental Estimates as published.     I therefore propose that - with the exceptions noted below -- those Estimates should be submitted by departments, scrutinised by the Treasury, and published in theordinary way, but that a statement should be made at the time of theirpublication, indicating that a review of the oversea information services is being undertaken and that, when that review is complete, somerevision of the Estimates will probably be necessary.3.      This proposal is subject to a reservation on oversea broadcasting.The first task of the new Committee has been to consider a draft reporton oversea broadcasting, which was put in hand by a Committeeconstituted for that purpose under the previous Administration.    Thisreport was originally intended to be a self-contained piece of work.But now that there is to be a wider review of the oversea information services generally, there are obvious advantages in deferring decisions on the oversea broadcasting services until it can be seen how changesin those services are related to modifications elsewhere on oversea information services as a whole.    This is the more important in that,insofar as changes in the oversea broadcasting services may involvereductions in those services in certain cases, they are likely to be strongly opposed by the B. B. C.    This opposition will be more easilydealt with if the proposals for oversea broadcasting can be seen as but one element in a coherent and integrated policy for the oversea informa-tion services generally.&quot;To review the scope and direction of the oversea information services, including the present arrange-ments for oversea broadcasting.&quot;
4.      The Committee have therefore come to the conclusion that their final recommendations on oversea broadcasting should be put forwardsimultaneously with, and as part of, their proposals on the scope and direction of the oversea information services.    But there are twospecific issues on oversea broadcasting on which decisions are neededforthwith and should be reflected in the B.B.C. External Services vote for 1957-58 as originally published.    Both these issues, discussed below,relate to the Middle East, where the need for strengthening our broad-casting services is urgent and self-evident.Expansion of the existing services.      Up to 30th October, 1956, the following services in Arabic weretransmitted to audiences in the Middle East:-(i)  the B.B.C. Arabic Service on short wave from thiscountry (4&quot;l hours a day);   and(ii)  a service transmitted on medium and short wavefrom Cyprus (over 15 hours a day) by the near east Arab Broadcasting Station (N.E.A.B.S. orSharq al Adna).     This was owned by a british commercial company.6.      On 31st October, the facilities provided by share wererequisitioned for Her Majesty&apos;s Government and used to broadcastprogrammes produced by the Foreign Office (the Voice of Britain),by the B.B.C., and originally by the Allied Command in Cyprus.    Acomposite service of 15 hours a day is now furnished as to over two-thirds by the Foreign Office and rather less than one-third by the B.B.C.7.      Fresh arrangements are now urgently required.    The N.E.A.B.S.cannot be regarded as able to re-institute an effective service.    nor can the Foreign Office, for both political and practical reasons, maintainthe Voice of Britain much longer.    On the political plane, there isconstant danger of embarrassment, both on the question of principle and because broadcasts cannot be prepared (like statements of government policy) in a form which will stand up to public scrutiny.    Moreover, thestaff in Cyprus are living in extremely difficult conditions, and theCypriot and Arab staff, who are under the threat of EOKA terroristaction, may leave at short notice.    A decision concerning the futureof the Voice of Britain is therefore urgently required;  and the aim should be to bring it to an early end.8.     An increase in the B.B.C&apos;s Arabic service would in any eventhave been desirable.    The B.B.C. are willing to double this service toprovide 9j hours daily;  they hope to be able to do so within 2.-Z\ months from the time a decision is taken.    The additional expenditure involved(in respect of staff and programme costs) is estimated at about 30,000 a year on the B. B. C. Vote.9.      There is also an urgent need for the provision on a permanentfooting of relay facilities for the B.B. C&apos;s Arabic service in the middle east.    These can most rapidly be provided by the share transmitters,as these cease to be required for the Voice of Britain.    This would,of course, mean that Her Majesty&apos;s Government would have to purchase
the assets of the N.E.A.B.S. at an agreed price, which is estimated at about  200,000 on the Foreign Office Vote.    It would be for subsequentdecision whether we retained ownership of the assets and operated thestation ourselves, renting transmitting time to the B.B.C.,  or whether we sold the assets outright to the B.B.C. (increasing the Grant in Aidproportionately for this purpose) and left it to the B.B.C. to operate thestation.    In either case Her Majesty&apos;s Government would have to meetthe operating costs, which are currently estimated at about  180,000a year.Provision of a second service10.     Prior to the Suez crisis, there had already been purchased bythe Foreign Office at a cost of  49,000 an additional high-power medium-wave transmitter, which was originally intended to relay the B.B.C&apos;sArabic Service.    The question arises whether this additionaltransmitter should be used in order to increase the power of B.B.C.relays, or for some other purpose.    It has been urged by the ForeignOffice that, in order to fill the vacuum left by the cessation of broad-casts from share, there is a need to provide a &quot;light programme&quot;, ofentertainment and straight news only, which would be directed to the.uneducated masses in Arab countries (as distinct from the moresophisticated audience to which the B.B,C&apos;s programmes are addressed).A programme of this kind would have the object of attracting a massaudience away from CairoR&amp;dio - which, if it can be achieved, is animportant objective.    Such a service could not appropriately be under-taken by Her Majesty&apos;s Government;  nor is it likely that the B.B.C.could, or would, undertake it.    It would therefore have to be run by acommercial organisation;  and this would have the advantage that itwould enable the Government to recoup some, if not eventually all, ofits costs and would stimulate exports to the Middle East.     On theother hand, it is difficult without further study to judge the practicability of establishing such a commercial organisation, or its financial implications-tions, including the likely commitment on Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentto subside the operation.    Further consideration should be given to this possibility.    But we must decide now whether we should proceed toinstalLthetransmitter forthwith, in the expectation that it will be needed for one purpose or another, or whether we should defer its installationuntil our policy is more clear.    If it is decided to proceed immediately,the transmitter could be installed in Cyprus in June, at an estimatedcost of  140,000 on the Foreign Office Vote.    In my view, we should proceed forthwith to install the transmitter which we have bought,in order not to waste precious months.    The position of the Chancellorof the Exchequer on this point is reserved.11.     In brief, therefore, I recommend that:-(a) The B.B.C&apos;s Arabic Service should be permanentlyincreased to 9\ hours daily, and the Voice of britain phased out as the B.B.C&apos;s output is increased.(b) Her Majesty&apos;s Government should purchase the assets of the N.E.A.B.S. at an agreed price,and the transmitting time on the share stations should be rented to the B.B.C. for a period of six months, without prejudice to the final arrangements.
(c) Authority should be given for the Ministers concerned to explore the practicability and financial implications-tions of setting up a commercial organisation to runa &quot;light programme&quot; directed to the masses in arab countries.(d) The second transmitter, which we have already bought,should be installed forthwith, and further considera-tion should be given urgently to the best means ofsecuring its most effective operation.C.H.Office of the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster, S. W. 1.29th January, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
