<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/85/0 images: 79-80</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
GOVERNMENT expenditure memorandum by the Minister of education quite agree that the prospective increase in the civil estimates of  280 millions affords an occasion for reflecting upon our general social policy.    But I would urge my colleagues that decisions about economies should be made in the light of our social policy, and not simply in relation to this figure of  280 millions.2.      Government expenditure, in itself, is neither more nor lessinflationary than any other kind of expenditure.     What really matters,surely, is the fraction of the gross national product devoted to allthe main categories of expenditure, public and private.    Providedthat this fraction is not excessive, then it may very well be quiteappropriate for a particular item of Government expenditure to riseas the economy expands.    I think it can be shown that we are spendingrather less than 3 per cent of the gross national product on education.The school population will be increasing in the near future and willcontinue to rise until 1960/61, but so, one hopes, will the gross national product.    So far from being excessive I should myself have thoughtthat it could be quite strongly argued that this is an insufficientproportion if our professions are to be taken seriously.    Speakingfor myself, therefore, I am not unduly alarmed at my own Departmentsshare of the increased Civil Estimates.3.      I now turn to the actual proposals in the Chancellor^ paper(C. (57) 16).    I wish vigorously to contest the proposition that a sound economy can be assisted by penalising parenthood.     I shouldindeed regard such a proposition as quite contrary to everything thathas been said about our future policy or the opportunity State.4.      If it is proposed to cut family allowances and also to attackfree school milk and subsidised school meals, the effect will becumulative.    In addition to losing 8s. on the second child, the two-child family would have to find an additional 2/2d. a day for school meals and milk.    The effect on the weekly budget of such a familyabove the free meals income scale limit will be a net additionof nearly 19s. a week.    Socially I should regard the combined effect as most serious, and I should question whether we could hold itpolitically.5.     The School Meals Service is utilised in differing degreesin different parts of the country, but wherever it is used it can besaid with confidence that it operates directly for the benefit of the child.    The school meal goes into the child&apos;s stomach.    The service the circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of...........................TOP SECRET Copy No. M.C.(57) 1930th January,1957.CABINET
is most used wherever children live a long way from school.   Theproposal to charge the full economic cost will, therefore, strike mosthardly the agricultural worker who is already one of the least wellrewarded in the community.   An easing of the income scales for freemeals cannot help the normal wage-earner.   There would thus be a bigincrease in the very small number of children who now take sandwichesto school.   This would be bad for them and bad for the social life of theschool.   Taken as a whole, I do not think that the proposal would be viewed either at home or abroad as a courageous move.6.      In June the Cabinet decided not to impose any increase beyond anadditional Id. per dinner which could be defended within the existing policy of making the charge cover the cost of food (CM.(56) 43rdConclusions).   The circular which announced this increase stated -&quot;The Minister himself is convinced of the value of theservice as it exists today; he would not wish to see anyradical alteration in its present pattern. &quot;7,      I now turn to the question of school milk, which is at presententirely free.   My objections to an increase in the charge for the mealwould apply equally to a charge for milk.8.      Moreover, the imposition of such a charge would raise serious administrative difficulties.   At present the distribution of milk withinthe school causes little or no practical difficulty.   If a charge were imposed it would be necessary to make arrangements for the weeklycollection from each child of small sums of money, and these sumswould have to be properly accounted for.   There would need to bearrangements for seeing that the milk was drunk by the children whohad paid for it.9.      It is also necessary to bear in mind the attitude of the teaching profession.   Under the present law the supervision of children is theonly duty which teachers can be required to perform in connection withschool meals or milk.10.    Many of them do undertake other tasks (e. g. the collection ofdinner money) voluntarily.   But there has been some unrest in the profession recently over this matter and it is not proving easy to hold the present position.   The changes proposed, which would add a further and especially irritating need to collect pennies for school milk wouldcertainly exacerbate the situation and might lead to a general refusalby the teachers to continue to perform any voluntary tasks in connectionwith meals or milk.   If this happened the service could be maintainedonly by coercive and contentious amending legislation or by appointingnumerous additional paid staff at a very considerable cost, for which no allowance has been made in the estimate of savings.11.    Finally, consider the effect on wage claims.   My own convictionis that the rise in the cost of parenthood would result in an overpoweringdemand by the Trade Unions for higher wages and that, so far fromhelping us to balance our economy, these proposals would in fact produceindustrial unrest on a scale which could not fail to interfere with our economic life.   If the wage demands were met we should have to face afurther instalment of inflation, since demands are always out of proportion to the actual increases in the family budget and apply to the unmarried aswell as the married.H.Ministry of Education, W.l.30th January, 1957

</content>
</cab>
