<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/85/0 images: 190-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THlJj DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government secret,(57) 50 COPY NO.27th February, 1957CABINETSOUTH WEST AFRICA company memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the Tsumeb Corporation Limited, American-controlled, seek totake over the South West Africa Company Limited (S.W.A.CConsentis required - for control of the Company to pass from the United Kingdom,and for its domicile, i. e. for tax purposes, to be transferred from theUnited Kingdom to South Africa.Transfer of Control- 2.      This is equivalent to American investment in the Sterling Area;our normal practice is to approve this unless it involves &quot;positivedisadvantage&quot; to the United Kingdom or the Sterling Area country concerned,    S.W.A.C. is a producer of vanadium;  there are other sources of vanadium;   but the question may well not arise because Tsumebhave given us a written assurance that S. W.A.C. will continue to minevanadium for sale to the United Kingdom;   that is to say under presentpayment arrangements to be paid for in sterling.The South African authorities do not object to the transfer.Transfer of Domicile3.      It is a condition of the Tsumeb bid that the domicile of S. W. A. C.should be transferred to South Africa,     I am advised that this should beallowed, provided that Tsumeb first acquires at least 75 per cent ofS.W.A.C&apos;s issued capital.Other Bids4.      Tsumeb is not the only bid in the market for S.&apos;W,A.C.    The otherbids do not involve my approval.    To refuse Tsumeb therefore might beregarded as discrimination against an American Company and be theobject of criticism on that account.conclusion.      Consent to transfer of control and domicile will probably attractcriticism from both sides of the House.    Criticism might be justifiedif we were jeopardizing a vital source of vanadium;   but we are not.     We
188ENDcannot afford to do without American investment unless there is some&quot;positive disadvantage&quot; in it.     We certainly do not wish to seem to discriminate against the U.S.A.6.      I propose to give the consent asked for;  but remembering the controversy to which the rather similar Trinidad Oil case gave rise, Ithink that my colleagues will wish to know of it.P.T.Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1.27th February, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
