<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/58/0 images: 56-56</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1953SECRET Copy No.   6 3C. (53) 118th January, 1953CABINETICELAND FISHERIES dispute memorandum by the President of the Board of trade at their meeting on 18th December, 1952 (C.C. (52) 106th Conclusions,Minute 6) the Cabinet agreed in principle that Her Majesty&apos;s Government should refer the Iceland fisheries dispute to the International Court of Justice. The cabinet invited me at the same time to examine the possibility of revoking the Open GeneralLicence for the import of fish from Iceland and of imposing quota restrictions should such measures prove eventually to be necessary. The Cabinet also invited the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries to have a discussion with representativesof the fishing industry with a view to enabling Her Majesty&apos;s Government to informthe International Court that if the restrictions on our trawlers imposed by the Iceland Government were raised pending a decision by the Court, the ban onlandings of Iceland fish in this country would also be lifted. The outcome of theMinister of Agriculture^ discussions with representatives of the fishing industry on 30th December are recorded in C. (53) 4.2. Action by Her Majesty&apos;s Government to exclude Iceland from the scope ofthe Open General Licence for the import of fish would be open to serious objectionson commercial policy grounds. Such action would be patently discriminatory and her Majesty&apos;s Government would be forced to report it to the Organisation for european Economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.) and to defend it there. Indeed, whenthe Iceland Government recently raised at O.E.E.C. the ban on Iceland fish imports,the Economic Secretary, Treasury, was at pains to point out that the ban was notthe result of action by Her Majesty&apos;s Government, but that, on the contrary, we gave an Open General Licence for fresh fish from Iceland. Moreover, our 1933Trade Agreement with Iceland accords Iceland full most-favoured-nation treatment as regards imports. Accordingly, action against Iceland alone would be out of thequestion unless Her Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared to go so far as to give notice to denounce the 1933 Agreement with Iceland.3. Quite apart from the objections referred to above, it would, I think, be indefensible for Her Majesty&apos;s Government to take retaliatory action againstimports of fish from Iceland if the dispute is referred to the International Court andso long as it is under consideration by that Court. The question what action, ifany, Her Majesty&apos;s Government could take to protect United Kingdom interests, if and when the International Court has given its judgment, must depend on the natureof that judgment.P. T.Board of Trade, S.W. 1,8th January, 1953.43518

</content>
</cab>
