<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/58/0 images: 166-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1953SECRET Copy No. g QC. (53) 2622nd January, 1953CABINETRENTS AND REPAIRSMemorandum by the Minister of Housing and Local government there are various methods by which an &quot; amendment of the Rent RestrictionActs &quot; can be carried out.But it should not be forgotten that this phrase is just a euphemism for &quot; putting up rents.&quot;2. &quot; Putting up rents &quot; (as is shewn in C. (53) 24) has something, but not verymuch, to do with stopping houses from falling down.3 &quot; Putting up rents &quot; can be done in different ways. All of them are boundto be unfair and full of fantastic anomalies, because we start from a hopelesslyillogical system of rents.(a) There are &quot; old controlled &quot; rents (that is rent first controlled in 1914, andnever released from control). These (broadly speaking) are the lowestrents and the houses of the poorer classes.(b) Then there are &quot; new controlled &quot; rents (that is rents controlled in 19.14,&quot; decontrolled &quot; by stages between the wars, and &quot; recontrolled &quot; in1939). These (broadly speaking) are better and newer houses. Recentinvestigations by the Inland Revenue have shewn that there is a widevariation in the increases that occurred then in the rents of houses even of the same kind and in the same street; and that, on the whole thelevel of these rents is higher than had been generally supposed.(c) Then there are &quot; new tenancies &quot; that is houses that have been let forthe first time since the second war. Whilst these are let at prices fromwhich appeal can be made to Rent Tribunals the basis of assessment is left to the Tribunals and is by no means uniform.4. No satisfactory or equitable system of fixing maximum rents is reallypossible except on the basis of a hew and universal valuation for rating.Owing to the bungle made about the 1948 Act, this is not possible till, say,1955 or 1956.5. The easiest way of &quot; putting up rent &quot;is a general percentage increase. Thishas certain advantages:  1(a) It &quot; seems &quot; reasonably fair (although, as shown by paragraph 3, it is reallyvery unfair).(b) It was done before in 1920, and therefore has the advantage of followingprecedent (although, when it was done before, the great and artificialvariations of rent did not exist).(c) No individual rent rises for any individual tenant by more than the generalpercentage increase (30 per cent, 40 per cent, or whatever may beagreed). Under any other scheme, very great increases (up to 100 percent, or more) are authorised in some cases that is, where rents arevery low.(d) It is probably the only method applicable in Scotland, owing to the compli-cations of the Scottish rating system. But there the variations betweenrents of new controlled and old controlled houses are not so great.43577
6. But I have never liked the percentage increase plan for the following reasons:  (a) It is not easy to connect the idea of increased rents with the fact of repairshaving been done recently or being seen to be done (although it would,of course, be made a condition that the house should be in good tenant-able repair). -lie(b) If the present rent structure is illogical and unfair, it is obvious that a percentage increase accentuates those anomalies. &apos;..)7. Another suggestion, made by Lord Ridley&apos;s Committee in 1945, is for RentTribunals to adjudicate.I think there are strong objections to elevating what can be a convenient piece of machinery, designed for particular and special cases, into one for general applica-tion. The administrative task would certainly be very heavy.Moreover, on what principles would the Tribunals act?What instructions would we give them?If none, the result will be chaotic. But if we succeed in devising a clear set of principles which are capable of being translated into instructions, why should wenot act upon them ourselves?In effect the proposal would mean setting up a parallel machine to that operated by Inland Revenue for valuation for rating. (In fairness to Lord Ridley&apos;s Com-mittee, this machine did not exist when they reported.)8. The only other practicable scheme we can devise is to relate the rise inpermitted rent to the statutory deduction for repairs, under the Rating Acts, inaccordance with the ascertained cost of repairs to-day.It would be provided, that (a) the house was in &quot; good and tenantable repair &quot;;(b) that the landlord had recently spent not less than the specified sum inrepairs.This is the plan outlined in C. (52) 299, to which the Cabinet gave provisional approval.9.. The assumption underlying the scheme, based on evidence advanced by various professional institutions, (such as the Chartered Surveyors) is that thestatutory deduction for repair really was enough to keep the house in repair in1939. So, if the cost of repairs is now three times what it was, an addition of twice the statutory deduction to the rent should enable the landlord to maintain thehouse.(The Girdwood Committee will produce a formal report as to the precisefigure.)10.   To be equitable, therefore, the rent should rise by twice the deduction;the landlord should spend altogether on the house three times the deduction.(For he is supposed to spend the present deduction already.)11. Investigation of a number of houses in London and the Provinces hasbeen made since the Cabinet discussed the scheme. The results are shown in the table attached. Column 7 shows what the new rents should be. From thesefigures, I judge the plan to have two serious defects, (a) The increases in the lowest rents would be as much as 100 per cent, or even higher. Although this might be logical, it would be insupportable. These rents are, no doubt, &quot; old-controlled &quot; houses, (b) It would also make the rents of some of the &quot; new-controlled &quot; intolerably high. It would even put them (we are told) above what theywould reach in a free market.12. To overcome this we have tried the idea of an upper limit or maximum.The limit suggested is twice the present gross value of the house. (Rents now higherthan the maximum would not be reduced.)Column 8 of this Table shows the result. This would deal with the higherrents, and keep them from going above a free market rate.13. But it would not deal with (a) the very low rents. It is right that these should go up. If a tenant is offered a new local authority house, his rent will go up enormously. And even a tenant of an existing local authority house may findhis rent go up a lot. But is it right that rents of old houses should go up so suddenly?To double a man&apos;s rent is pretty stiff-although, of course, his neighbour, with asimilar house, is paying far more.   Nevertheless, a man thinks of his own budget.
14. So I would suggest another mitigating device. I suggest that in certain cases, these rents should reach the maximum permitted by stages say, over  years. This I would call the escalator principle. The formula would be asfollows:  No rent should be increased in the first year by more than 33^ per cent.;nor in the next year by more than another 33^ per cent.; and so on, until thefull increase is attained. Thus, if the present rent is  12 and the new maximumis  22 the rent at the various stages would be  16,  20,  22. ;Column 9 of the Table shows the result.15. There would be a rent book for each controlled house, and the figuresof the present rents, the permitted increases, &amp;c, would by statute be shown therein.16. This question next arises. With these limiting provisos, will there be enough extra money to induce the landlord to do the job? I think so, except possibly for the lowest rented houses. Anyway, there will be more than there isnow, and the scheme is admittedly a stop-gap.17. But since these limitations do reduce the money the landlord might expect to get (if the plan were logically and universally applied), I think we should make some corresponding reduction in the obligation he must assume.18. Before he gets any increase in rents the landlord at present is supposed to have spent on repairs an amount equal to the statutory deduction on the average over a specified period.He is to get in extra rent a sum equal to twice that amount. Therefore, heshould in logic have spent a sum in repairs equal to three times the statutorydeduction.  (Paragraph 9.)In view, however, of the two limiting or stopping factors introduced intothe scheme, I think he should only have to show expenditure equal to twice thestatutory deduction.19.   The landlord therefore will have to certify:  (a) that the house is in &quot; good and tenantable repair &quot;;(b) that he has spent the required amount on repairs.20.   How is this to be administered?It is not an easy problem.I had hoped that 19 (a) the state of the house could be certified as the resultof a physical inspection by a local official. It is clear now that this is out of thequestion. One of the Town Clerks whom we consulted confidentially told us itwould take four years in his city. So we must rely on making the landlord certifythe fact, with the right of the tenant to appeal to the local authority, for a specificexamination of his house. (If the appeal were sustained, the additional rent wouldnot be payable, as in the Rent Act of 1923.)21. The landlord, in giving notice on the tenant, would have also to certifythat he had spent in repairs on the average per annum not less than twice thestatutory deduction.He would have to satisfy the local authority that he had done so (for any period which follows the introduction of the Bill the local authority might wellrequire receipted accounts. For the previous period, they would have to be&quot; reasonably satisfied &quot;).22. Recourse would be to the County Court in cases falling under para-graph 20, if the tenant refused to pay after the Local Authority&apos;s decision; and incases falling under paragraph 21 on a dispute as to the facts of the expenditure.23. The date of the period within which the landlord must have spent moneyrecently on repairs must be fixed by statute. If you make it a long period (say,two years or three before the passing of the Act till the date of the notice), youinclude more landlords and you raise more rents. If you make it a much shorter period (say, from the passing of the Act), you include fewer landlords and raisefewer rents; but you will help to connect the fact of an increased rent muchmore forcibly in the mind of the tenant with the actual carrying out of repairs.I should be inclined to make the period start from 1st January, 1953., but I wouldlike the advice of my colleagues.
Ministry of Housing and Local Government, S.W. 1,22nd January, 1953.24. Before final decisions need be taken as to certain vital points e.g., maximum rents, operation of &quot; stopping &quot; devices or escalator principle, andperiod for repairs, we hope to have some further figures from the Valuation Office.Unfortunately, the sample from which the Tables are composed is rather small.25. There are one or two minor, but important, matters which might be dealtwith in the Bill:  (a) Rent Tribunals should be authorised to determine increases of rent whereservices (e.g., heating in a block of flats) are provided.(b) Houses belonging to non-profit-making organisations such as housing associations and Trusts, as well as New Town corporations shouldbe excluded from rent restriction; also all houses belonging to oracquired by local authorities (at present for technical reasons some are excluded).26. If these proposals are acceptable, I should like authority to get a Billdrafted as soon as possible. We could draft the Bill and yet leave open the points of detail set out in paragraph 24 for further consideration and decision.H. M.
HOUSES IN london	2		3	4	5	6	7	8		9		1								Max. rents	f		,\					Statutory				if stopper	Max. rents if further stopper			iDate			Gross		No. in	Present	Max. rents	of twice	of one-third at a time applied			Datebuilt	District		value	deduction	sample	rents	if twice	G.V.				built							S.D.added	applied	1st year	2nd year	3rd year				(G.V.)	(S.D.)											 	 		  p.a.	  p.a.	  p.a.	  p.a.	  p.a.	  p.a.	A. Built	before 1919											A. BullC. 1850	Edmonton B.		13	5	25	15-23	25-33	25-26	20-26	25-26	25-26	18501890	Walthamstow B.    f		15	6	14	15-16	27-28	27-28	20-21-3	25-26-6	27-28		1				2	30-31	42-43	30-31	30-31	30-31	30-31													18501850	Battersea M.B.      f		18	7	37	18-22	32-36	32-36	24-29-3	30-36	32-36		\				3	25-29	39-43	36	33-3-36	36	36													18811900	Chislehurst and	r	20	8	1	12	28	28	16	20	24		Sidcup U.D.-				6	18-27	34-43	34-40	24-36	30-40	34-40			I			1	44	60	44	44	44	44	1865	Hammersmith M.B.		26	9	20	28-35	46-53	46-52	37-3-46-6	46-52	46-52													19081900	Lewisham M.B.     f		30	10	2	31-33	51-53	51-53	41-3-44	51-53	51-53						6	44-53	64-73	60	58-6-60	60	60		L				1	63	83	63	63	63	63													19071912	Wembley B.	r	35	11	14	50-55	72-77	70	66-6-70	70	70			i			1	71	93	71	71	71	71													18801880-90	Islington M.B.	r	40	12	2	30-31	54-55	54-55	40-41-3	50-51-6	54-55						6	41-48	65-72	65-72	54-6-64	65-72	65-72		L				1	74	98	80	80	80	80													19051900	Battersea M.B.	r	50	14	1	34	62	62	45-3	56-6	62						13	47-66	- 75-94	75-94	62-6-88	75-91	75-94	1880					9	70-100	98-128	98-100	93-3-100	100	100													19051910	Edmonton B.        f		70	18	1	75	111	111	100	111	111						1	225	261	225	225	225	225	B.-Built	after 1918											B.-Built1934	Uxbridge U.D.		17	7	10	29-36	43-50	34-36	34-36	34-36	34-36	19281937	Staines U.D.		19	7	16	34	48	38	38	38	38	19351934-35	Edmonton B.        f		22	8	1	- 39	55	44	44	44	44	1934-36	\				3	51-61	67-77	51-61	51-61	51-61	51-61		L				1	73	89	73	73	73	73	19351934	Walthamstow B.   ...		24	8	8	54	70	54	54	54	54	19301936	Wembley B.		30	10	68	54	74	60	60	60	60													1935?	Ealing B.......		35	11	74	59-60	81-82	70	70	70	70	1937	Edmonton B.		40	12	6	69-71	93-95	80	80	80	. 80													19321929	Wembley B..		50	14	4	90-100	118-128	100	100	100	100	1934	Croydon C.B.		80	20	4	95-110	135-150	135-150	126-6-146-6	135-150	135-150	1935												1936												1934 ^
houses Outside london	2 ,			3	4	5	6	7	8 Max. rents if stopper of twice G.V. applied   p.a.	9		Date built	District			Gross value (G.V.)  	Statutory deduction (S.D.)  	No. in sample	Present rents   p.a.	Max. rents if twice S.D.added   p.a.		Max. renl of one-thii 1st year   p.a.	s if further -d at a timt 2nd year   p.a.	stopper j applied 3rd year   p.a.A. Built	before 1919											1850	Yeovil R.D....	r i		7	3	4 3 11	6 10-13 14-16	12 16-19 20-22	12 14 14-16	8 13-3-14 14-16	10 14 14-16	12 14 14-161850	Hoole U.D.			11	4	13 3	10 15	18 23	18 22	13-3 20	16-6 22	18 221881	Watford B. ...			15	6	1 13 3 1 6	10 16-18 20-23 29 33	22 28-30 32-35 41 45	22 28-30 30 30 33	13-3 21-3-24 26-6-30 30 33	16-6 26-6-30 30 30 33	20 28-30 30 30 331908	Scarborough B.	i		22	7	16 12 5	16-22 36-44 45-47	30-36 50-58 59-61	30-36 44 44	21-3-29-3 44 44	26-6-36 44 44	30-36 44 44   . &quot;1907	Portsmouth C.B.	(		25	7	9 11	21-33 40-48	35-47 54-62	35-47 50	28-44 50	35-47 50	35-47 501880	Plymouth C.B.	\		30	8	3 5 1	28-33 52-59 65	44-49 68-75 81	44-49 60 65	37-3-44 60 65	44-49 60 65	44-49 60 651905	South Shields C.B.			40	10	4	36-45	56-65	56-65	48-60	56-65	56-651880	Scarborough B.			50	10	5	60-70	80-90	80-90	80-90	80-90	80-901905	Southend C.B.			70	14	7	65-85	93-113	93-113	86-6-113	93-113	93-113B.-Built	after 1918											1928	Macclesfield R.D.			13	5	7	26-31	36-41	26-31	26-31	26-31	26-311935	Beverley R.D.			16	6	22 -	25	37	32	32	32	321934-36	Norwich C.B.			18	7	9	.   32	46	36	36	36	361935	Sheffield C.B.			21	7	104	26-32	40-46	40-42	34-6-40	40-46	40-461930	Northampton C.B.			25	7	1 2	32 70	46 84	46 70	42-6 70	46 70	46 701935	Northampton C.B.	\	r	30	8	3 5 1	27-39 44-52 78	43-55 60-68 94	43-55 60 78	36-52 58-6-60 78	43-55 60 78	43-55 60 781932	Hoole U.D.	i		35	9	1 1	37 52	55 70	55 70	49-3 65	55 70	55 701935	Southport C.B.	\	-	45	10	13 8 1	56-68 75-80 -  100	76-88 95-100 120	76-88 - 90 100	74-6-88 90 100	76-88 90 100	76-88 90 1001936	Leicester C.B.			50	10	4	75-80	95-100	95-100	95-100	&quot;95-100	95-1001934  x	Cambridge C.B.			80	16	2	110	142	142	142	142	142

</content>
</cab>
