<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/22/1 images: 10-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.  February 1942.secret copy Ho. 15W.P. (42) 71.February 7, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY./It is requested that special care may be taken to/ensure the secrecy of this document.    \fWAR CABINET.RUSSIA.Note by the Minister of War Production.WHEN we parted, the Cabinet took the decision to refer the Russianissue to the United States without a recommendation.This, in my judgment, was a mistake. I am in favour of a recommenda-tion accompanying our submission to the Americans. Indeed, a failure on our part to provide such a recommendation may look like flinching from our clearresponsibility.But, if the Cabinet find it impossible to agree on a recommendation, maywe not appeal to public opinion, so that the people may settle the deliberationon our behalf.Here are the reasons why I recommend that a firm and determineddecision should be taken to persuade the Nations allied with us to give recognition to Russia&apos;s demand for security : Russia asks for the 1941 frontiers with Finland, Roumania and theBaltic States. These frontiers fall short of the frontiers she possessed in Tsaristtimes.At the moment we entered into alliance with Russia, the past was allforgotten. No basis for a confident collaboration was possible, except that whichrecognised Russian territories as they stood at the moment when the Germanonslaught made the Russians our Allies.The Baltic States are the Ireland of Russia. Their strategic control byMoscow is as essential to the Russians as the possession of the Irish bases wouldbe valuable to us.As for Russia&apos;s claims on Finland and Roumania, these two countries have,by throwing in their lot with Germany, forfeited all right to our consideration.Finland is fighting against us in this war in order to get strategic frontiersat Russia&apos;s expense. She wants more than the territory she lost to Russia. Andif Finland loses the war, then, in justice, she must concede strategic frontiers toRussia.We should be grateful to the Russians for giving up their territorial claims against Poland. On that account alone we should give immediate adherencei  their present moderate demands.The issue is not one which permits of any delay.B.February 7, 1942.[23445]




</content>
</cab>
