<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/9/43 images: 450-455</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECEET. CoPy N0-W.P. (40) 263.July 12, 1940.to be kept under LOCK and KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.POLICY IN THE FAR EAST.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.THE attached paper is to some extent out-of-date in view of the instructionssent to Sir R. Craigie in Foreign Office telegram No. 671 of the 11th July. Thepaper may, nevertheless, still be useful and I accordingly circulate it herewithfor the information of my colleagues. -h.Foreign Office, Jidy 12, 1940.[21504a]

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  July 1940.SECRET. / Cowy No./July 9, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.POLICY IN THE. FAR EAST.Memorandum, by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.IT was suggested last week in Cabinet that, during the time when sir R. Craigie was having his first conversation with the Japanese ForeignMinister on the subject of the Japanese demands, the Foreign Office should prepare a short note setting out their estimate of the wider political issues involved in the question of the Burma Road. The Chiefs of Staff were, I under-stand, to prepare a similar note upon the possibilities of Japanese action in theevent of the Japanese Government deciding to press the matter to the point of open hostilities.  I append the Foreign Office note below.H.Foreign Office, July 9, 1940.Policy in the Far East.THE Chiefs of Staff suggest in W.P. (40) 249 that the alternative to yieldingon the Japanese demands will be war with Japan. The reasons for which theForeign Office consider that Japan would be unlikely to resort to total war areas follows :  Military.(a) We cannot rely on any armed assistance from America; but theJapanese are uncertain on this point and cannot rely on their not affordingus such assistance.(b) Although a large part of the Japanese navy is free to operate against us, the army and a portion of the navy are occupied in China.Economic.(a) In the event of total war against the British Empire, Japan willlose all her trade with the Empire except in territories that she may succeed in seizing.  Even there the return may be slow at first in materialising.(5) The likelihood of an American embargo is -at least considerable.(c) Japan could not replace by her seizures of territory the trade which she would lose by (a) and (b).Historical.There is nothing in Japanese history to support the theory that theJapanese extremists, if they came into power, would throw all discretion tothe winds. The Japanese are cautious by nature, and the method usuallyfavoured is to choose a point at which to push, to withdraw if resistance isoffered, but to push on if it is found that opposition is weak or yielding.11105   [21504]
2. The probability is, therefore, that if Japan decided to react to a refusalon the Burma road, the first action would be, as Sir R. Craigie has suggested,something in the nature of a blockade of Hong Kong; possibly renewed pressure on our economic interests in China. More forcible action would develop slowlyand gradually if it developed at all.3. All this is, however, admittedly a matter of opinion, and ^at, the presentcritical time, with our preoccupations in Europe and.the necessity of avoidingfull-scale hostilities in the Far East, it would naturally be rash to decide simplyon the basis of conjecture as to the action which the Japanese might take. TheForeign Office fully appreciate, therefore, that there may be good grounds foryielding to the Japanese demands in the hope that serious difficulties with Japanmay thus be avoided for a time. Before any decision is taken, however, they feelthat the effect of a decision in this sense on our relations with other countries and our general position in the Far East ought to be weighed.4. The effect on the U.S.S.R., United States, China herself and neighbouringterritories are considered below  U.S.S.R.It is impossible to say exactly what effect our yielding to the Japanesedemands would have on the U.S.S.R. Possibly the Soviet policy of assistingChina would be intensified. Alternatively, or even simultaneously, the SovietGovernment might reach some arrangement with the Japanese.United States.Both President and State Department dislike our making concessionsand would prefer not to see us yield, except to force. American Governmentcircles might understand our complying with the Burma road request, butpublic opinion, particularly powerful in the pre-election period, would regard it adversely. Result: America would be less disposed to help us,not only in the East, but also in the West.Chiang Kai-shek.Closure of the Burma road would deal a material and moral blow atChiang Kai-shek. Material supplies,, especially from America, help, ofcourse, to keep China&apos;s military resistance going. But even more important is the moral support which His Majesty&apos;s Government have afforded. Thewithdrawal of this would mean considerable discouragement for the ChineseNational Government. The result might be a great increase in the influence of Russia, which would control the sole remaining channel of supply.Alternatively, Chiang Kai-shek might decide to make a peace with theJapanese at the expense of foreign interests. We might expect the altitudeof China towards Great Britain to become very hostile.Neighbouring countries.Anything likely to check the advance of Japan is likely to be welcomedin the surrounding countries, e.g., Thailand, Indo-China and the netherlands east Indies. On the other hand, to yield would mean a loss in our prestige in all these countries, and especially in British territories, e.g., Malaya,Burma and India. It should not be forgotten that our position in the far east has been defended in recent years by prestige rather than by military force, and we should not lightly allow it to be further diminished.5. Apart from these considerations, it is certain that, as Sir R. Craigiehas pointed out, a yielding on the Burma road question is likely to be followedby further demands from the Japanese, which would be more difficult and morehumiliating to concede. Sir R. Craigie does not claim that it would achieve forus more than a lull, at the end of which the threat of forcible action would still remain. Moreover, to give way to- a demand emanating from the extremists willnot help the more moderate Japanese Government.6. For these reasons the Foreign Office would urge that we should not yieldto the demand on the Burma road at least until an attempt had been made tobring about a comprehensive settlement in the Far East on a wide basis. Asto the desirability of this, the Foreign Office are in full agreement with theChiefs of Staff and are examining the possibilities at this moment.Foreign Office, July 9, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
