<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/20/20 images: 172-193</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET. Copy No.W.P. (41) 297UZao C.O.S. (41) 723)December 4, 1941TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 118)oi theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 November 27th, to0700 December 4th,1941[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Boom
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.1.   Naval forces have sunk a tanker and a supply ship bound for Libya.A merchant raider or supply ship has been destroyed in the South Atlantic.U-Boats are concentrated in the Gibraltar area, where one has been sunk.Our shipping losses, though somewhat heavier than of late, have beenmoderate.E-Boats have again been active off the East Coast.Home Waters.2. On three nights during the week Motor Torpedo Boats and MotorGunboats have attacked E-boats and armed escorts of enemy merchant ships inthe Straits of Dover, with inconclusive results. H.M. Destroyer Mendip and oneof H.M. Drifters, escorting a coastal convoy, each shot down an enemy aircraftoff the Humber on the 1st December. On the same day H.M. Minesweeper Rosswas damaged by aircraft off Aberdeen.It is estimated than 8,500 tons of enemy shipping have been sunk and28,000 tons damaged by our aircraft.  Details are given in the Air Situation.Mediterranean.3. Light forces continue to operate.off the Libyan coast in support of our military operations, and cruisers, destroyers and submarines have been disposed to intercept reinforcements by sea.On the 1st December H.M. Ships A urora and Penelope, with two destroyers,sank the Italian Destroyer Alvise Da Mosto (1,628 tons, six 4-7-inch guns), a10,000 ton laden tanker, and a supply ship, believed to be carrying stores andammunition to Libya. The tanker had previously been seriously damaged by our aircraft. In addition, 11,000 tons of enemy shipping has been sunk or damaged by our aircraft; details are given in the Air Situation. H.M. Destroyer Jackalwas torpedoed by enemy aircraft to the eastward of Tobruk, but returned to alexandria under her own steam. The Polish Submarine Sokol claimed two hitson an enemy destroyer lying at anchor in Navarino (south-west Greece), and onthe 21st November probably sank one ship in an escorted convoy to the south-westward. H.M. Submarine &apos;P.31 sighted a force of cruisers and destroyerssouth of Taranto and claimed one hit on a cruiser.During the week approximately 35,000 tons of French shipping eastboundand 6,500 tons westbound have passed through the Straits of Gibraltar underescort.South Atlantic.4. On the 1st December H.M.S. Dorsetshire, about 650 miles north-east ofTristan da Cunha, intercepted a supply ship or raider resembling the s.s. Elands-fontein (10,800 tons), which was scuttled after a warning shot had been fired.Owing to the suspected presence of U-boats no survivors were picked up.An American merchant ship has picked up seventy-two survivors, five ofwhom have since died, from H.M.S. Dunedin, which was torpedoed and sunkon the 24th November.Australia.5. Extensive sea and air searches have failed to locate any survivors ofH.M.A.S. Sydney. It has been ascertained from interrogation of survivors ofthe raider, which is now known to have been the Steiermark (9,400 tons, armed with six 5 - 9-inch guns, and above- and under-water torpedo tubes) that the actiontook place on the 19th November, 175 miles south-west of Carnarvon (WestAustralia).  Both ships were heavily on fire and the raider subsequently blew up.Anti-Submarine Operations.6. The Dutch Submarine 0.21 torpedoed a German U-boat about 110 miles east of Gibraltar and picked up twelve survivors. H.M. Corvette Totland madea promising attack on a U-boat, which had previously sunk a ship in convoy tothe north-east of the Azores, and one of our aircraft claimed to have damaged aU-boat in the Western Approaches. A number of other attacks have been carriedout by surface vessels and aircraft in the Western Approaches&apos; and Gibraltararea, but in no instance was there any definite evidence of destruction.
Enemy Intelligence.7.   There is no change in the position of the main units.The old French cruiser Gueydon at Brest has had her superstructure alteredand two small naval vessels have been placed astern of her. This composite vesselhas been camouflaged to give the appearance of a large ship, which it may beintended to substitute for a German battle cruiser or cruiser, if one of them leavesthe port.U-Boats.There has been no activity on the convoy routes in the North Atlantic, andU-boats are now concentrated in an area east and west of Gibraltar. At leastfour U-boats are operating in the South Atlantic.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.8. One ship in an outward bound convoy and another sailing independentlywere sunk by U-boats, north-east of the Azores and in the Gibraltar arearespectively. Another ship reported that she was being shelled by a U-boat 200miles south-west of the Azores.On two nights in the week E-boats attacked coastal convoys off the Norfolkcoast, sinking three ships.Two ships were mined and sunk off Aldeburgh and Cardiff.No ship has been sunk by aircraft, but one ship was damaged in the St.George&apos;s Channel and a fishing trawler was bombed and abandoned off the shetlands.A report has recently been received that the s.s. Empire Pelican (6,463 tons)and s.s. Empire Defender (5,649 tons), which were proceeding on government service from Malta to Gibraltar, were sunk by aircraft off the coast of Tunison the 14th and 15th November respectively, and that French naval units picked up survivors.Protection of Seaborne Trade.9. During the week ending the 3rd December, 972 ships, including231 Allied and 26 neutral, were convoyed. Two cruisers, four anti-aircraft ships,one ocean boarding vessel, 72 destroyers (including 25 United States destroyers)and 98 sloops, corvettes and minesweepers were employed on escort duties. Sincethe beginning of the war, 93,706 ships have been convoyed, of which 474 have been lost by enemy action.Imports into the United Kingdom during the week ending the29th November totalled 1,002,000 tons, compared with 602,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average for the past ten weeks of 919,000 tons. oil imports were 358,779 tons.British Minelaying.. 10. During the week mines have been laid off the north-west of Scotlandand the Norwegian coast. Minelaying by aircraft has been carried out in theBaltic and off French Biscay Ports.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.11. E-boats have recently been active off the East Coast, and, in addition toattacking convoys, are believed to have laid mines in the war channel.Minelaying by aircraft has taken place in the Thames Estuary, the bristol channel and off the Ffumber.Twenty-one magnetic and six acoustic mines have been destroyed during theweek.  The mine totals are now : magnetic 1,550, acoustic 1,176, and contact 1,063.Enemy Merchant Shipping.12. A Norwegian broadcast on the 29th November stated that the coastalmotor vessel Vindafjord was attacked and sunk by a Hudson aircraft north ofStavanger on the 28th November. Four of the crew and 25 passengers were lost.According to a report dated the 26th November a raft marked Supergawas recently washed ashore near Inada to the south of Burgas in the Black Sea.This Italian tanker (6,154 tons) was last reported at Burgas on the25th September. The Russians claim to have sunk a large tanker in this localityat the beginning of November.[23226] b
Recently there have been reports that the German ships Braunfels (7,847tons), Drachenfels (6,342 tons) and Ehrenfels (7,752 tons) and the Italian s.s.Anfora (5,452 tons), will try and escape from Mormugao (Portuguese India).American Intelligence.13. There are no major changes in the American dispositions in the Pacific.The forces to the west of the Panama Canal consist of nine battleships, three aircraft carriers, twelve heavy cruisers, eleven light cruisers, upwards of seventy-five destroyers, and some forty submarines. Of these about two-thirds are stationed at the Sandwich Islands and the others on the Pacific coast.vichy French Intelligence.14. The following is the latest information regarding the present state of readiness of the main units of the Vichy French Fleet: Richelieu.At Dakar. Lying alongside No. 3 Mole, where she has been since the 5th July,1941. Temporary repairs completed. One gun in upper after 15-inch turretout of action, otherwise main and secondary armament complete. Starboardoutboard propeller removed. Present estimated maximum speed 23-g knots. Itis reported that the ship is looked upon as part of the fixed defences of the port,and that there is no immediate intention of moving her.Jean Bart.At Casablanca. Forward lower turret only mounted. A recent report has stated that this turret is in operating condition, although there is no evidencethat missing breech blocks have in fact been fitted. Recent reports also indicatethat work is being carried out on ship, believed in connection with installation of A.A. armament. It has also been reported that decks are being strengthenedto resist incendiary and dive-bombing attacks. Hull reported to be very foul,and ship is probably not capable of more than 20 knots. Used as training ship.Upper structure has been painted yellow to blend with nearby buildings. Hullgrey.Dunkergue.At Mers-el-Kebir (Oran). Temporary repairs to hull completed. Main and secondary armament complete. Reported that damage to electrical and fire controlinstallations cannot be repaired locally owing to lack of material and technicalequipment. Ship requires dry docking. Starboard outboard shaft is out of commission from effects of shell-fire in July 1940, and in present conditionreported capable of 18 knots only on three shafts.Strasbourg.At Toulon.   In full commission and fully effective.   Last docked May 1941.Provence.At Toulon.  Believed fully effective.MILITARY SITUATION.(An outline map showing Axis operations against Russia is included in this resume as an inset.)Russo-German Campaign.Finland and Leningrad Sectors.15.   There has been no change.Central Sector.16. On the Moscow front the Germans have, during the past week, madeprogress in three directions : :(a) From the Klin area both eastwards and south-eastwards to points about35 miles from Moscow;(&amp;) In  the  area  of  Novo  Petrovskoje   (about  30  miles  W.N.W.  of moscow); and
(c) By an advance from the area Tula-Uzlovaya north-eastwards in thedirection of Kaschira and Ryazan.Further south the eastward thrust towards Riazhsk has made progress.South-east of Orel the Germans have also advanced against what was probably only slight Russian resistance.Ukraine.17. In north and central Ukraine the Germans have gained some slightadvantage in a number of areas, but the position virtually remains the same.It is in the extreme south that the situation has been drastically changed bythe events of the last few days. Here the Russian Southern Army Group,despite a long period of very heavy fighting and severe casualties, has managed,by means of a counter-attack on a considerable scale, to recapture Rostov. It is interesting to note that this success was euphemistically described by the Germansas &quot; the evacuation of the centre of the town in accordance with orders so thatthe necessary measures of reprisal might be taken against the population, whohad illegally taken part in the battle in the rear of the German army.&quot;Crimea.18.   There has been no change.Conclusions.19. The battle for Moscow continues to rage fiercely and the position isstill serious. Up to the present the direct attacks on the Russian capital havemade comparatively little progress, and the Germans are apparently attempting,with some success, to carry out encircling movements from the Klin and Tulaareas.An attack from the Tula area has also developed eastwards. Here theGermans are attempting, to cut the important railway running from Moscow toRostov via Riazhsk and Voronezh.The Russian success at Rostov is of great importance. It is at presentimpossible to say whether the Germans will soon be able to launch a counter-attack and regain their lost ground, but, in any case, their time-table for an advancethrough Caucasia and any subsequent operations against the Middle East musthave been seriously upset.Operations.Libya.20. The operations in Libya during the period 18th to 25th November were described in last week&apos;s Resume.Throughout the 24th and 25th November preparations were made for an offensive towards Sidi Rezegh and Bir el Hamed from the south. This offensivewas to be carried out in conjunction with a further thrust by the Tobruk Garrisondirected on El Duda.Operations on November 26.21. The attack on Sidi Rezegh was launched by New Zealand troopssupported by &quot;I&quot; tanks during the night of the 25th/26th November. By the morning, after heavy fighting, the position had been recaptured, as had Bir elHamed, 5 miles further north.By 1530 hours the Tobruk Garrison had reached El Duda.Meanwhile, the reorganisation of our main armoured forces was proceedingapace. General Auchinleck reported that the tank situation was much improved and that vehicles were still being recovered.Operations on the 27th November.22. Early on the 27th November, a New Zealand battalion, supported by&quot; I &quot; tanks, effected a junction with the Tobruk Garrison at El Duda and the gap between the two forces was closed.On the same morning, it became evident that General Rommel had recalledall his armoured forces in the frontier area to the Sidi Rezegh battlefield. Asa result of this order, a party of about 60 armoured fighting vehicles, including[23226] e 2
both tanks and armoured cars, with a quantity of M.T., evidently containingthat part of the German garrison of the Halfaya position which it had beenpossible to withdraw, moved westward along the Thigh Capuzzo.At about 1500 hours, the column reached a point 12 miles south of Gambutwhere it was engaged by our armoured forces with 120 tanks. The battlecontinued throughout the afternoon and night; 14 enemy tanks being destroyed.250 M.T. vehicles were, however, believed to have escaped westwards.Operations on the 28th November.23. At 1400 hours the tank battle was still in progress 5 miles east of SidiRezegh between the British armoured forces in the area and about 70 Germanand Italian tanks, whose object was evidently to drive back the New Zealandtroops from the Sidi Rezegh-Bir El Hamed area. It is not yet clear how GeneralRommel had managed to augment his tank force for this battle. By the afternoonover 600 German prisoners had been captured, including the Commander of 21stArmoured Division.Meanwhile, a force of about 45 tanks from the Italian Ariete Division waslocated during the morning some 30 miles east of El Gobi moving northwards. a mobile column was detailed to prevent the junction of this force with the enemyeast of Sidi Rezegh.By this time Tobruk was being used as a base for the supply of the forcesabout Sidi Rezegh.24. In the frontier area our troops north and west of Sollum were heavily attacked about Capuzzo and Sidi Azeiz by an enemy force from the Sidi Omar-Sollum-Halfaya triangle. Touch was lost with the Formation Headquarters andit was feared that our losses in this area had been heavy. Meanwhile, a force was being concentrated in the Sheferzen-Sidi Omar area, with a view to restoring the situation and severing the supply line between the Bardia area and the enemy&apos;forces in the Sollum triangle.25. By this time over 4,000 German and Italian prisoners had been evacuated from Cyrenaica.Operations on the 29th and the morning of the 30th November.26. The battle about Sidi Rezegh continued throughout the 29th november and the following night.On the afternoon of the 29th November the New Zealanders were attackedfrom the north-east by what have now been identified as the remnants of the21st Armoured Division, directed on Bir El Hamed, and from the south-westby part of the 15th German Armoured Division, directed on El Duda. Theenemy&apos;s aim was evidentlv to encircle our forces in the area and cut them off fromTobruk.In the evening, the enemy succeeded in capturing El Duda, but was drivenout by a counter-attack during the night. A strong force of tanks was operating against the southern flank of the German force attacking from, the west while the21st Armoured Division was continuously and successfully attacked in the rearby mobile columns detailed for the purpose.27. Earlier in the day, the Ariete Armoured Division had been located some miles south-east of Sidi Rezegh moving northwards to support the German21st Armoured Division. In an engagement on the afternoon of the30th November, with a force of 60 of our tanks, the Ariete Division suffered heavy casualties and 19 tanks are said to have been seen burning. -28. In the frontier area, the situation was being progressively cleared up and contact was gained with the troops in the Sidi Azeiz-Capuzzo area, whowere found to be intact, but who had been out of wireless touch since the26th November.Operations on the 1st and the 2nd December.29. On the 1st December, by attacking with all his available tanks on an arrow front, the enemy succeeded in recapturing Sidi Rezegh and Bir El Hamed,thus bringing about a junction of the two German armoured divisions andsevering the Tobruk corridor.
El Duda remained in the hands of the Tobruk Garrison and the troops southof the breach were temporarily withdrawn southward to the line of the TrighEl Abd to reorganise.30. The 2nd December and the following night were devoted to reorganisation -sation and redisposition of forces on both sides. While our tired troops werebeing replaced by reserves, enemy M.T. columns were reported to be movingsouthward towards El Gobi and eastward along the Trigh Capuzzo. The enemy on the Trigh Capuzzo were being harassed by our mobile columns while patrolshad been pushed westward from our formations about Capuzzo and Bardia.Summary.31. It is impossible to give anything in&apos; the way of a firm estimate of the opposing tank forces remaining in the field. Returns of the strengths of our ownunits and of vehicles recovered have not yet been collated, while reports of theenemy&apos;s casualties and strengths in the various engagements have been made inthe heat of battle and cannot be regarded as accurate.At the time of writing, the opposing forces have fallen apart without adecision having been reached.The enemy was evidently surprised by our preliminary moves and GeneralRommers armoured forces have been brought to battle and a great part of themdestroyed. On the other hand, the fighting has been bitter and casualties heavy and the enemy has been able to cover the Tobruk corridor and reconcentrate those parts of the two German armoured divisions which have survived the first fourteen days of the campaign.East Africa.The Gondar Operations.32. After the surrender of General Gazzera and the enemy forces in theGalla Sidamo province of Southern Abyssinia on the 4th July, Italian resistancewas confined to the Gondar area just north of Lake Tana. The Italians had spenttime and material strengthening the naturally formidable position of Gondar,which is situated in mountainous country, well adapted for defence. Moreover,the few roads leading to the area could not carry during the rainy season the traffic required for the maintenance of an attacking force of any size.For these reasons the Commander-in-Chief, Middle East, whose commandat that time included East Africa, decided to contain the enemy with a small force until September, when the rains would have ceased and the roads againhave become usable.33.   The troops allotted for the purpose consisted of 1st Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders,3/14 Punjab Regiment,A Sudan Defence Force detachment, andEthiopian patriots.This small force fulfilled its role with conspicuous success up to the22nd September, when the 25th East African Brigade arrived from Massawa, and operations on a larger scale began.Italian Forces and Dispositions.34. The Italian forces in the Gondar area, which comprised the triangleWolchefit-Kulkaber-Chelga, were estimated at 19,000 Italian and native troops and 76 guns.   They were commanded by General Nasi.These forces were disposed as follows  Wolchefit area (30 miles north of Gondar) : 3,000 rifles and 19 guns.Wolaich area (10 miles north of Gondar) : 2,200 rifles and 5 guns.Immediately south of Gondar: 3,100 rifles and 18 guns.Feroaber-Kulkaber position (25 miles south-east of Gondar) : 1,800 rifles and 12 guns.Gorgora area (at the north end of Lake Tana) : 1,200 rifles.Chelga area (25 miles west of Gondar) : 3,800 rifles and 22 guns.By this time the enemy&apos;s air force had dwindled to a total of five aircraft,three fighters and two bombers.
35. The increased pressure first made itself felt in the north, and on the28th September the Italian outpost commander at Wolchefit surrendered with3,000 men, about half of them Italian.The road from Wolchefit to the south had, however, been heavily mined andit was some weeks before the 25th East African Brigade were in front of theenemy&apos;s next position, just north of Wolaich.Meanwhile the 26th East African Brigade had been relieved from theblockade of French Somaliland and arrived in the Gondar area during the first week of October. The conduct of all the operations was then taken over by major-General C. C. Fowkes, G.O.C., 12th African Division.Original Plan.36. General Fowkes&apos;s original plan was to deliver the main attack from thesouth-east along the Debra Tabor-Gondar road with the 25th and 26th east african Brigades, supported by 16 guns, with the object of seizing the roadjunction south of Azozo and then destroying the various enemy groups in detail.In addition, three subsidiary advances were to take place as follows :  (a) From the north, along the Wolchefit-Gondar road by two battalions withfour guns.(b) From the south, along the western shore of Lake Tana, by an Ethiopianbattalion.(c) From the west, along the Gallabat-Chelga road by a Sudan defence force Battalion with two guns.Patriot forces were to co-operate with all four columns.Air support was to be provided by :  One squadron Mohawk fightersOne squadron Hartebeeste army co-operation aircraftOne squadron mixed bombers of the RA.F. and South African Air Force.The advance of the main column was to be delayed until the subsidiaryadvances had created the greatest possible diversion of the enemy&apos;s forces. Thewhole operation was timed to begin during the first week of November.Plan of attack revised.37. By the beginning of November, however, it became apparent that owingto the unexpectedly heavy and late rains, the road Debra Tabor-Gondar wouldnot be capable of maintaining a force of two brigade groups, while there were indications that the enemy in the Wolaich position were ripe for attack from thenorth. It was therefore decided to alter the plan and direct the main attackalong the Wolchefit-Gondar road, carrying out a containing attack, with one battalion only, in the south-east.Owing to the delayed arrival of some essential guns from the Middle East,the attack was finally postponed until the third week in November.Progress of the Operations.38. Details of the advance on Gondar have not yet been received and it istherefore difficult to present a connected picture of the operations. It appears,however, that since the capture of Wolchefit the 25th and 26th East AfricanBrigades had been steadily moving south as fast as repairs to the road would permit.39. While the main body was thus slowly advancing, patrols and patriotbands maintained constant offensive activity in front of the enemy&apos;s positionastride the road on the natural defensive lines Wolaich-Ambazzo. The enemy were also subjected to continued attacks from the air. As a result of these operations a number of the local tribal chieftains, who had hitherto sided withthe Italians, joined our forces, and by the 17th November Kamant Hill andVentincinque, important outposts of the enemy&apos;s position, had been captured.Meanwhile, the 25th East African Brigade had been side-stepped to thesouth-east with the object of severing the line of communication between Gondarand the enemy positions in the Feroaber-Kulkaber area. This force occupiedZagadi, 10 miles north of Kulkaber, on the 19th November; and two days laterKulkaber was captured with 2,300 prisoners. The garrison of the Feroaberposition was thus isolated.
In the west, the Sudan Defence Force battalion advancing along the road from Gallabat was in contact with the main position, 7 miles west of Chelga, bythe 18th November, and on the 20th November captured an important outpost3 miles north of the town. The operations of this force are believed to havecontained at least three black shirt battalions and three Italian colonial battalions.At the same time, the Ethiopian battalion, which had advanced up the shore of Lake Tana, had invested Gorgora and was pushing steadily northward.Patriot forces worked in the closest co-operation with all our columns andtheir presence was to a great extent responsible for the high rate of desertion fromthe enemy&apos;s native units.In addition the enemy, wherever they could be located, were subjected tounremitting attacks by the co-operating R.A.F. and South African Air Force squadrons.The Surrender.40. As the advance progressed, it became increasingly evident that theenemy&apos;s morale was deteriorating as the result of our land and air operations and his shortage of supplies. Desertions were frequent and there were rumours of mutiny amongst his native troops. For example, after our forces took TaddaEidge, 7 miles to the south-east of Gondar, Colonel Toreli, commanding an Italianreserve brigade, appears to have ordered a counter-attack, which his troopsrefused to carry out. Under these circumstances, General Fowkes decided thata direct attack on Gondar fortress from the east would produce quicker resultsthan the attack on the Wolaich position originally planned. The 26th east african Brigade was accordingly diverted to the south-east, leaving a smallcontaining force in the north. By the 25th November this brigade was 8 miles south-east of Gondar.41. On the 27th November General Nasi surrendered the fortress of Gondarand all the troops under his command. The prisoners amounted to 11,500 italians and 12,000 native troops. These figures are considerably in excess of previousestimates of the size of the garrison and may be assumed to include a proportionof non-combatant personnel.Intelligence.Low Countries and France.42. It is reported that some formations from the Russian front have gone to France to rest and refit. One report mentions in this connection a total of five or six divisions. Confirmation of this is still awaited. On the other hand, the constant despatch of drafts eastwards from France has brought a proportion ofthe divisions in that country to well below strength.Pending further information, therefore, it is impossible to raise the estimate for German forces in the Low Countries and France above the former figure of27 divisions, of which two are in the area between the River Gironde and theSpanish frontier and three in Holland and Belgium.Balkan States.43. There are persistent reports of the movement of German troops south-eastwards through Yugoslavia, Salonika being mentioned as the destination. Itis probable that there has been a reshuffle of German garrisons within the12th. Army (the German Army responsible for the Balkans), and it is possiblethat the Germans have been forced to undertake fresh commitments in the Aegeanarea because of increased doubt of Italian capacity. It is also possible that thetransfer of troops is connected with the replacement of German units sent from bulgaria to South Russia.-It is estimated that the total number of German divisions in the Balkans isstill 14.Greece.44. Reports have been received from time to time of the construction ofbarges and small craft both on the mainland of Greece and among the islands.Latest information suggests that concrete barges are being built in large numbersat Varkisa (12 miles S.S.E. of Athens).  These vessels are unhandy and not likely
to be used for traffic between the islands or along the coast, which is normally-conducted by caique. They are more probably intended for landing purposes,possibly as part of long-term preparations for an eventual invasion of Turkey.They are said to be able to carry 1,000 men.Yugoslavia.45. Press reports state that open warfare and sabotage are increasing along the Dalmatian coast, noticeably in the Split area. Resistance is said to be strongin the mountains of Montenegro, where Italian aerial bombing has &quot;had little effect, and it is believed that the Germans are being forced to intervene in an effort to restore order in territory nominally occupied by the Italians. ThoughGerman control has again been generally established in Serbia, disturbances stillcontinue.Roumania.46. The rise in the level of the lower Danube, owing to heavy rainfall,indicates that the river is unlikely to freeze early this winter.Far East.47, Should the talks between the United States and Japan break down, andshould the Japanese decide on military action, present indications suggest thattheir first step would be to occupy Thailand, with a view to acquiring air bases in the southern part of the Kra Isthmus, and thus be in a better position, ifnecessary, to threaten Malaya. Such a move would be a natural precautionarystep to any later action against the oilfields in Borneo.Malaya.48.   Two field regiments armed with 25-pdrs. have arrived in Malaya.Volunteer forces in Malaya were mobilised on the 1st December.AIR SITUATION.General Review.49. Bad weather prevailed throughout most of the week and, with theexception of night attacks on Hamburg, Dusseldorf and Emden, no major operations were carried out by Bomber Command. Our aircraft effectivelyattacked enemy convoys between the coast of Norway and Channel ports.50. In Libya our aircraft have dominated the battle area, and providedclose support for our ground forces. Successful attacks have been made on aerodromes, and on enemy shipping in the Central Mediterranean.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.51. Apart from anti-shipping operations (see &quot;Coastal Operations&quot;)there is nothing to report.Night.52. Bomber Command, taking advantage of the only two nights whenoperations were possible, carried out a heavy attack on Hamburg and raidedDiisseldorf and Emden on a lighter scale.53. A total of 344 sorties were despatched (compared with 258 last week);396 tons of H.E. bombs (including 19 of 4,000 lbs.) were dropped, and nearly25,000 incendiaries. During the remainder of the week bad weather at homeand on the Continent prevented further operations.54. One hundred and twenty-two aircraft released 160 tons of HE. bombs and 8,900 incendiaries on Hamburg. Detailed observation was hampered bysearchlight dazzle and ground haze. Numerous fires, however, were reportednear Berliner Thor, Altona and Altendorf railway stations, in the Rotherbaumdistrict, on the Blohm and Voss shipyards and in the dock area.
55. Large and medium-sized fires resulted from the attack on dusseldorf,where 68 tons of H.E. bombs (including ten of 4,000 lb.) and 8,000 incendiaries were released. At Emden, a similar weight of bombs caused many fires in theOld Town and near the railway station and docks. Two smaller-scale raids were made on Ostend. During the week&apos;s operations 18 of our bomber aircraft were lost.United Kingdom.56.   Fighter Command flew 1,025 sorties by day and 188 sorties by night.57. No outstanding feature of interest characterised enemy operations during the past week, which were on a small scale. Three enemy bombers were shot down at night by Beaufighters.58. From the character of German Air Force operations during the past few weeks, it appears that the policy of conserving the long-range bomber force on the Western Front is still being rigorously pursued, possibly because ofincreasing difficulty in maintaining units at operational strength in other theatres of war.Coastal Operations.59. Coastal Command flew 169 patrols (313 sorties) and provided 31 convoy escorts (48 additional sorties). Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Commandtotalled 299 (695 sorties) and, in addition, fighters escorted our bombers in their attacks on shipping off the Coast of France.60. In spite of unfavourable flying weather, aircraft of Coastal and FighterCommands continued to harass enemy shipping both in daylight and by night.61. Eight Hurricane bombers, with fighter protection, destroyed a 2,500-ton merchant vessel and a flak ship off the French coast; a second flak ship was set on fire and the fighter escort shot down two Me. 109&apos;s which approached.On the same day, a further eight Hurricanes (of which three are missing) bombedshipping in Boulogne Harbour, where they encountered intense and accurateA.A. fire. The results of the attack, which was carried out from a low level,could not be observed. Eleven fighter squadron sorties were flown as escort andcover for these Hurricane bombers.62. Hudsons sank a 5,000-ton vessel off Borkum and a 1,000-ton tanker inHardanger Fjord, and reported hits on hostile shipping in Norwegian waterstotalling over 17,000 tons. Beauforts, operating off The Hague, left a 1,500-ton ship listing, and off Borkum, hit another of 4,000 tons, causing large explosionsamidships; they claimed hits on other ships totalling 5,500 tons.63. Nineteen aircraft were despatched to lay sea-mines off the frisian islands, in the Jade and Weser rivers and off Kiel and Brest.64. Offensive activity by the German Air Force continued to be directedalmost entirely against shipping, but this policy was attended by little success.Shortly after dusk on the 1st December attacks took place off Aberdeen, in the bristol Channel, Cardigan Bay and Dublin Bay, but only slight damage was caused.65. Enemy minelaying aircraft operated on five nights of the week in the humber, the Thames Estuary, off the Cornish Coast and in the Bristol Channel.Central Mediterranean.66. On the night the 27th/28th November a very successful attack wasmade on Naples by 21 Wellingtons. One 4,000-lb. bomb hit the Royal Arsenaland another fell on the railway junction. Other hits were made on the torpedofactory, the Imam aircraft works and on two other factories; three oil cisternswere set on fire and several other large fires were started.67. Naval aircraft, operating under the A.O.C., Malta, made a night attackon Castel Benito aerodrome, Tripoli (L), where one enemy bomber was blown up and others probably damaged; on another night they dropped bombs on therailway lines at Noto (40 miles S. of Catania).[23226] c
68. In daylight, four Blenheims carried out a very successful raid onbarracks south-east of Mellaha aerodrome. The barracks were hit, as well asM.T. and a fighter on the aerodrome. A total of four Beaufighters madethree attacks on M.T. on the Tripoli (L)-Sirte road; at least 28 lorries were damaged, seven petrol tankers set on fire and four others hit, while one Italianbomber was shot down.69. On the 29th November six Blenheims attacked shipping in NavarinoBay and harbour in very bad weather, obtaining five direct hits on a tanker of5,000 tons, which was set on fire; near-misses were made on a laden merchant vessel of 8,090 tons. On another day two merchant vessels escorted by a destroyer were attacked north-west of Navarino; one ship of 4,000 tons whichwas set on fire was abandoned by the crew, while the other, a vessel of 2,000 tons,was damaged. Blenheims made two separate attacks on the tanker Mantovani,approaching Tripoli (L), which was carrying more than 10,000 tons of fuel oiland ammunition; a number of direct hits were made, and two bombs burst in the engine-room; the vessel was down by the stern and was finally sunk by a naval force.Libya.70. In daylight our bombers and fighters operated in close support of our ground forces, although the military background to these operations during theweek has remained confused. The German Air Force failed to maintain a high level of activity, which is due probably to supply difficulties, our successful attacks on enemy aerodromes, and particularly to the enemy&apos;s lack of fighters.A few large enemy formations were encountered, but it is noteworthy thatour continuous fighter sweeps and numerous bombing attacks met with so little opposition.Day Bombing.71. An enemy column of tanks and M.T., which crossed the frontier on the25th November, was attacked by two squadrons of light bombers on the 27th.south-east of Gambut, and many direct hits were made on M.T. vehicles. This wasa preliminary to their engagement by British armoured units. Two othersquadrons bombed, very effectively, a M.T. camp and a large dump west of el Adem; the dump and many vehicles were completely destroyed. During thesetwo operations our aircraft encountered intense A.A. fire, and one Blenheim was shot down and eleven other aircraft damaged. Hurricanes carrying bombs also attacked and dispersed a stationary party, believed to be a Staff Conference, inthe Trigh Capuzzo area.72. The following day a squadron of Blenheims reported good results fromits attack on M.T. north of the Bardia-Tobruk road. Four other squadronsoperating independently successfully bombed M.T., an aerodrome, and military objectives between El Gazala and Barce; four Blenheims are missing from these operations.73. On the 29th November and the two following days our attack was con-centrated in the El Adem and Sidi Rezegh areas. Sixty to seventy sorties weremade each day by mary lands, Blenheims, and Hurricanes carrying bombs, andwere directed principally against M.T. and A.F.Vs., a large number of which were destroyed or damaged. On the 2nd and 3rd December operations were severelyrestricted by rain and very low cloud. mary lands attacked supply dumps atBardia and obtained some direct hits. Attacks were also carried out on enemy concentrations of M.T. in the Sidi Rezegh area and along the Trigh Capuzzo, andmany direct hits were made. Fighter protection was provided in most of these attacks, and very few casualties were sustained by our bombers.Fighter Operations.74. Our fighters, in addition to providing fighter escorts, carried outfrequent offensive sweeps. They fought the enemy whenever possible anddominated the battle area. A very successful engagement occurred on the30th November, when two squadrons of Tomahawks intercepted about 30 Ju. 87sescorted by fighters north-west of El Gobi. Our fighters forced the dive-bombers to jettison their bombs and in the subsequent combat 15 of the enemy aircraft
were destroyed and 15 others damaged; we lost only three Tomahawks, and allthe pilots were saved. On the following day, one of our sweeps intercepted20 Ju. 88s escorted by 12 fighters, and another engaged 18 Me. 109s; seven enemy aircraft were destroyed, four probably destroyed, and three damaged; six of our fighters were shot down, the pilot of one being safe. Fighters also included intheir operations attacks on ground targets, as a result of which they sustainedsome casualties, probably from A.A. fire; in one of these attacks an armouredcarand 30 lorries, many of which were troop-laden, were destroyed.75. Attacks on enemy aerodromes were carried out by fighters, as well as by day and night bombers. Some of the results were difficult to estimate accurately,but at least 82 enemy aircraft were destroyed or damaged on the ground.Hurricanes and Beaufighters attacked Jedabya aerodrome on three occasions, andBarce, Derna, Martuba, and Mersa Brega (43 miles south-west of Jedabya) were also attacked, and it was during these raids that the majority of the above aircraft were put out of action.Night Bombing.76. At night, Wellingtons concentrated their attacks on the harbour and shipping at Benghazi, in which support was provided from Malta on two occasions; the Cathedral and Italia moles were repeatedly hit, resulting in large fires which were visible from a great distance. Two ships were also hit,one by a 4,000-lb. bomb. Four attacks were made on Derna aerodrome, wherereconnaissance aircraft had reported a large concentration of enemy aircraft;fires were started at dispersal points.Enemy Activity.77. Few offensive operations were undertaken by enemy long-range bombers,other than small-scale raids directed against our railway communications overthe frontier. In one of these attacks a Ju. 88 was shot down and the crewcaptured. The small scale of effort appears to indicate that the difficulties ofmaintaining the serviceability of Ju. 88s under desert conditions have not been overcome.Russia.Russian A ir Force Operations.78. It is believed that the Russians have now at least 1,000 aircraft inthe southern sector, where for the time being they have gained air superiority.German Air Force Operations.79. The continued low scale of German Air operations on all sectors of theRussian front is probably due to prolonged bad weather and withdrawal of all types of units to Central Germany for refitting.&quot; The decrease in German air strength on this front has deprived the ground forces of air support on the scale to which they have been accustomed, and, at the same time, has enabled theRussian Air Force to be employed with increasing effect, particularly againsttroops and supply columns. The German Air Force no longer retains air superiority in certain sectors.80. The Russian success at Rostov is likely to affect seriously thedevelopment of operations against Caucasia. An important advanced air basehas been established at Taganrog, and if dislodged from here the German AirForce will no longer be able to operate so effectively against the Rostov area and russian communications to the east and south, except with long-range bombers-moreover, the loss of supplies and equipment of all kinds accumulated in thisforward area must inevitably, have a delaying effect on further air operationsdirected towards Caucasia.81. Air operations during the past week have been very limited; a smalland ineffective bombing attack was made on vessels off the Kola Peninsula atthe entrance to the White Sea and minor harassing attacks have been made with small numbers of aircraft on Leningrad and Moscow, and on the southern frontagainst railways running east from Voroshilovgrad. There is little evidence thatany extensive operations have been undertaken either against Sebastopol or against the Russian forces advancing from Rostov.[23226] c 2
HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.82.   Bombing has been again on a very small scale.No damage of national importance was caused.By Day.83. On the 30th November a single raider bombed and. machine-gunnedLongside aerodrome near Peterhead. There was one fatal service casualty andsome stores were damaged.By Night.84. Although bombs were dropped on five nights of the week, there are butfew important incidents to record.At Ramsgate on 27th/28th November, H.E. and incendiary bombs causedfour fires. The following night two parachute mines fell at Swansea. One personwas killed.Damage.85.   At Ramsgate house property and public utilities were damaged.One parachute mine fell in the centre of the town at Swansea andanother in the dock area. Property was affected over a wide area and a flourmill and a bridge were damaged. In the dock area damage was caused to somecoal wagons and the railway track.Casualties.86. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 on Wednesday,3rd December, are 2 killed and 11 seriously injured.
APPENDICES I, II and iii will be published monthly.APPENDIX IY.Enemy Merchant Ship Losses.As all enemy mercantile tonnage losses are now subject to review and assess-ment by a Special Committee which issues a report fortnightly, the table givingenemy losses will be based in future on these reports and will be included once a fortnight instead of weekly as hitherto.Figures for the period ended the 16th November are as follows : Enemy Merchant Ship losses as assessed to 16th November, 1941.Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously Damaged.		Damaged.		Total.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German Italian Finnish Useful to Enemy... Total	365 332 3 36	1,630,160 1,418,528 6,460 74,228	98 61 1 10	255,806 296,303 4,000 33,259	147 68 ii	539,192 351,884 45,457	610 461 4 57	2,425,158 2,066,715 10,460 152,944	736	3,129,376	170	589,368	226	&apos;936,533	1,132	4,655,277In addition to the above there are Russian claims estimated at about 400,000gross tons sunk; also some 36,000 gross tons of Finnish shipping seized in allied ports. Also nearly 500,000 gross tons of enemy merchant tonnage is inUnited States and South American ports and no longer at the disposal of theenemy.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.November 27. A/S Trawler Kingston Andalusite damaged in collision offPortland.November 28. A number of M.T.B.&apos;s and M.G.B.&apos;s damaged by gunfire inan engagement off Dunkirk.November 29. M.G.B. 89 damaged by gunfire in an engagement withE-boats.December 1 -M.T.B. 71 and M.B. 100 damaged by gunfire in an engagementwith E-boats.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers:  1 killed; 12 missing; 2 wounded.Ratings :  22 killed; 16 missing; 7 wounded.
Operational Aircraft Battle Casualties.0700 hours, Thursday, 27th November, 1941, to 0700 hours, Thursday,4th December, 1941.British.Bombers ...Fighters ...Coastal ...Army Co-Op.TotalMetropolitan Area.In the Air.1836128On the Ground.German.bombers fighters miscellaneous destroyed.52ProbablyDestroyed.Damaged.-   4Total      ...... no account is taken of aircraft destroyed on ground.British.Bombers...Fighters ...Coastal ...TotalMiddle East.In the Air.51924On the Ground.German.Bombers ...Fighters ...miscellaneous total destroyed.6511ProbablyDestroyed.Damaged.10717Italian.Bombers  ...FightersMiscellaneousTotalDestroyed.21618ProbablyDestroyed.33Damaged.4In addition to the above, 1 unidentified German or Italian aircraft was damaged in the middle east, and at least 82 were destroyed or damaged on the ground.
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week from Air Reconnaissance and Intelligence sources : Germany.Berlin. In the raid of the 7th/8th November, the Spandau Power station was hit and damage caused in the Flensburger Strasse adjoining the Belle VueStation.-Worms. A large boot and shoe factory and surrounding property has been destroyed.General. It is learnt that some time ago the German Government, to augment their propaganda that notwithstanding our claims no damage had been caused to the Kxupps Works or the town of Essen, invited neutral ambassadorsand consuls to make a tour of inspection. They arrived in the evening and wereaccommodated at the best hotel. Their tour of inspection, however, was cancellednext morning for meanwhile the RAP. had come. The visitors were glad toleave, but found difficulty in getting to the station by reason of the fact that mostof the streets in the neighbourhood of their hotel were closed.&apos; &apos;   :&quot;.:&apos;V   - : : - - : ^     - :-     : :&quot;   &apos;&apos; : - &apos;   &apos; &apos; . ;   &apos;      &apos;&apos;   -v:   -:&apos;  ::.:.Occupied France.General. Over 1,900 tons of alcohol were destroyed in the fighter attack onthe distillery at St. Sauveur le Vicomte. On the 2nd November three locomotivesat Lison were rendered useless owing to their boilers being perforated by gunfire,and at Crouay Station another locomotive suffered a like fate.In the second half of March a submarine was damaged at Lorient and takento St. Nazaire for repairs.Denmark.Aarhus. In the raid of the 21st/22nd October, two patrol ships were sunkin the harbour and the damage caused to the port led to the suspension of traffic to Kalundborg.Italy.Naples. In the third week of November, the goods yards were hit and railcommunication to Rome again affected. The large and well-known &quot; Cirio &quot;canned goods factory has been destroyed.Sea-Mining.The Swedish steamer Hedda, of 1,502 tons, was mined and sank in theHuibert Gat on the 22nd November.






</content>
</cab>
