<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/206/0 images: 24-28</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOttUIEHT IS THE PROPERTY 0? HIS 33ITEK:?IC MAJESTY&apos; S G0VS3N1 !EI1T ).EGRET .F.  55  (29)CabinetSIGjvaTUxA- OF THE OPTIONAL CLAUSE.Note &quot;by Secretary.1. The attached Note by the Prime Minister (0.0.(29) 24)was communicated on September 19th to the only members ofthe Committee that ooula have attended a meeting that day,namely the Lord President of the Council, the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs, the Secretary of State forIndia and the First Lord of the Admiralty   As a result itwas agreed that a meeting was unnecessary and the fourMinisters named above signified their approval of theaction proposed by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs in his telegram No, 116 of September 17th.    In doing   sothopirct Lord intimated that the Board of Admiralty proposedto prepare a paper setting out their views which they hopedwould be considered before ratification takes place.&quot;2. The Seoretary of State for Dominion Affairs in approving the proposal forwarded the following note tothe Prime Ministor.&quot;Prime Minister.I entirely concur in the  course proposed in the telegram from the Seoretary of State for Foreign Affairs No.116 of the 17th September.    You will be glad to hear that I have just received a telegram from South Africa from which I gather that General Hertzog agree a to the formula now proposed and is instructing Mr. Louw to sign accordingly.    There is Just one small outstanding point but this need give riso to ne difficulty at all.    Is -ill now be necessary to consult Newfoundland ana Southern Rhodesia, who are not separate members of tho League, and, when, the time oumes fur ratifioation, to sucuro that ourCopy Me,
ratification covers these two parts of the Empire also,    I will taico the necessary action in this, as soon aa we hear from Geneva that signature hau taken plaoe.(Sgd,) Passfiela. 1809.29&quot;3, The necessary action was taKien the same evening toaoquaint the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs of the Prime IvUnister^ approval to the formula of acceptance for the Optional Clause as stated in his telegram ilo0116.(Sgd0 ) MaP0Aa KAXKZY. Secretary to tho Cabinet,,Whitehall Gardens,  S.V7.L, , September 23rd, 1929,
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

SECRET.

? (29) 24.

CABINET

Copy No.

COMMITTEE ON THE OPTIONAL CLAUSE.

Note by the Prime Minister Covering copy of a telegram received from the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.

I send this to the Special Cabinet Committee on the Optional Clause and subject to its concurrence, I agree.

(Ftd.) J.R.M.

18th September, 1929

From SWITZERLAND.

Decode. His Majesty&apos;s Consul. (Geneva).

September 17th, 1929.

No. 116. L.N. (R).

Immediate.

Following from Secretary of State for Prime Minister :-

Following are terms of formula for acceptance of optional clause agreed at meeting yesterday afternoon attended by delegates of all parts of the Empire except Irish Free State (which have already signed under a formula excluding practically all reservations):

"On behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government in United Kingdom and subject to ratification I accept as compulsory ipso facto and without special convention on condition of reciprocal jurisdiction of Court in conformity with article 36 paragraph 2 of Statute of Court for a period of ten years and thereafter until such time as notice may be given to terminate acceptance over all disputes arising after ratification of present declaration with regard to situations or facts subsequent to the said ratification.
&quot;Other disputes in regard to which parties to dispute have agreed or shall agree t^ have recourse to some other method of peaceful settlement and:v,li:v&apos;. -&quot;Disputes with the government of any pther member of the League which is a member of the British Commonwealth of Nations all which disputes shall be settled in such a manner as parties have agreed er shall agree and&quot;Disputes with regard to questions which by International Law,,  fall exclusively within jurisdiction of United Kingdom.&quot;And subject to condition that His Majesty&apos;s Government reserve right to require that proceedings in Court shall be suspended -in respect of any dispute which has been submitted and Is under consideration by the Council of the League of Nations provided notice to suspend is given after dispute has been submitted to Council and is given within ten days of notification of Initiation of proceedings In Court and provided also that such suspension shall be limited to period of twelve months or such longer period as may be agreed by parties to dispute or determined by a decision of all members of Council other than parties to dispute.&quot;I propose to sign on Thursday with declaration in above form falling Instructions to the contrary.Delegations of Dominions concerned and India are telegraphing to their governments with a view to signature on their behalf in a similar form.Points on which present formula departs from that set out in your telegram of August 1st  to Dominions are:(a) That inter Commonwealth disputes are excluded specifically instead of being excluded by mere use of word &quot;International&quot;.(b) That time limit is reduced from 15 years to 10.
(c) That domestic jurisdiction questions are excluded.(d) That final suspensory clause is restricted by provisions ensuring that, notice to six spend is given immediately after initiation of proceedings       the --other party and operates for a period not longer than twelve months unless period is extended by parties or by Council.

</content>
</cab>
