<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/206/0 images: 29-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S S C R E T,CP. 256  (29).COPT NO,C A B I N E T.THE HAGUE C0ITE2KE3CE,  1929.Noto &quot;by the Deputy Secretary ^ CaM.net.I circulate herewith,  for the informationof the. Cabinet, the Conclusions of Conferences ofMinisters held:-(.&amp;)    at 2 Whitehall Gardens, S.Y/. 1.,  on August 23rd, 1929,fb)    at 10 Downing Street, S-W. 1.,  on August  24th,  1929.These Conclusions will be taken note ofat the meeting of the Cabinet to be held on September25th,  1923,(sgav)   To JONES,Deputy Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens,    SeW- h ,September  3rd,  1929,
pi rTHIS hOCUMEJJT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BhllLJQJIC M^JESTfS GOVERHM^riT) .10ST SECRETInt/A/47ft   (1)COPY NO,GABIES T.NOTES of Conference of Ministers held at 2, Whitehall Gard.ena, S,\\0 10, on 23rd August, 1929,at 5 psm0PRE S E 1 T,The Rt. Eon Lord Pawafield, Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs and the Colonies.The Rt. Eon Lord Sankey,G.B0E, Lord Chancellor,The Rt0 Eon0 W. Wedgwood BenIlt      The Rt. HonaThomas Shaw, C.B.E. ,B6Sc0o, D0F3Co, M. P Secretary of State for India.Brig0Gen0 The Rt0 Hon. Lord Thomson, s B0E., Ba S,0,,Secretary of State for Air,M0Pe, Secretary of State for War.The Rt. Hon A0 V. Alexander, M0P,, First Jjord of the Admiralty.Mr. T 0 Jones.... Beputy Se ore tary,Cabinet,1. The Conference assembled at a few minutes&apos; notice onreooipt of a telephone message from tho Prime Minister who wished to take advantage of the presence of Ministers at the Meeting of the Cabinet Committee on the Optional Clause to ascertain their views on a proposal received from the Chancellor of the Exohequer that the Cabinet should meet at The Hague on Sunday next,  25th August,,    The Committee had dispersed shortly before the receipt of the Prime Kinister&apos;s message and Lord larmoor had left for the country, but it vfga  found possible to assemble the Ministers mentioned above. 2. The Secretary read to the meeting the telegramsexchanged between the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Prime Minister earlier in the day  (Higue to Lossiemouth No. 10  (W)  ) and losaiemouth to The Hague No. 6 (W) ) and the full telegrams which the    Chancellor had sent to the Prime Minister on August 22nd  (The Hague to Lossiemouth lr0o3  (?/)),
which are reproduced in the Appendix,    The Seoretary added that the prime Minister while  prepared to go to The Hague With three or lour colleagues, was very doubtful of the wisdom of doing so in all the airouRLtaiices, 3. In the course of the discussion which enouod it waspointed out that while there were advantages in.consulta-tions on the spot, a meeting-of the Cabinet in a foreign oountry was without precedent   and a full mooting would be impossible,    Iven if described as a Conference of Ministers it would be bound to be regarded as moat unusual and startling.    The proper course would appear to be that set forth in the Prime Mini Liter&apos; a telegram to the Chancellor of the Exchequer on August 17th, 1929  (Lossiemouth to TheHaguewo,1  (V/)   )   which was as follows:)&quot;If there should beilly a deadlock, thePrime Minlstor suggests that the formula which the Delegation should use is that it wishes to go to London to - consult the Prime Minister and Cabinet colleagues.&quot;It was pointed out that if it was undesirable for all three British Delegates to leave,  one eoulu remain at The Hague to keep in touch with proceedings there.The Conference agreed that the Seoretary should tele-phone to the Chancellor of the Exchequer in the above sense, and should propose a meeting of the Cabinet in London on Sunday 25th August. 1929, at 12 lioon.2, Whic-hall Card as,  3.7.1., August 23rri,  1929.
hiAPPSHPIX.f-Slf-majesty&apos;s^iS^^i-0 33 3.emout-h, Ho . 10 (tf)),towards midnight M. Jaspar brought tho latest proposal from tho other Creditor powers.      It is not one/ that we fool at liberty to accepts,     Unless something quite unexpected occurs, therefore, the deadlock will be complete when the Inviting powers meet this afternoon.Could we have C&amp;meet here Sunday?(Losslemonth to the Hague, Hov 5 ^(W)Jr.I agree to cross on Saturday evening with some of my colleagues.es unless in the meantime the -views of the British Delegation ^avo changed.      Should there be any change, be good enough to let me have notice at onco,(The Hague to Lcsslemouth, Ho.8i    (W) ) -At the meeting with Briand on Tuesday, Chancellor of Exohequer indicated that essential point was to recoup, to Great Britain in some way the loss of  2,400,000 a year sustained under the Plan and that on other points there appeared good prospect of accommodation.French Ministers replied that it was politically impossible for thorn to accept any alteration in Young table of distribution.      But they were prepared to make every effort to secure for Great Britain out of the surplus of the last five months
of Dawes not only  5 millions for debt cover provided for in the plan but further cash payment of  10 to  12-g-millions.    Both these payments would be made mainly at expense of France and represented in their view the maximum that she could be expected to pay,  particularly as she would have to compensate the smaller Powers (by remitting their debts to France) for abandoning their claims on the surplus-      There might also be objections from Germany whom they undertook to approach With a view to getting their assent.    They would support us in pressing Italians to cisgorge but anticipated great difficult.. .Subsequently Lorcheur saw Leith Ross-and was very gloomy as to possibility of full satisfaction of cash claim.      French and Belgians intended to guarantee approximate!;; 50$ of sum required end he thought that Italians under pressure might be prepared to pay another 10$..      ?or the rest,  the only hope was that Chancellor would take political satisfactions for balance of his claim,,Chancellor saw Pirelli yesterday morning and had a frank but fruitless interview.    Pirelli refused to make any advance upon his previous suggestions namely (a) a concession which was largely illusory as regards reparation coal,  and  (b) an offer to co-operate in putting through a  genoral settlement of the debts for liberation ana ceded properties and  to allocate to-4-
us an unspecified proportion ox any receipts that they themselves obtained from Czecho-sloyafcia under such a settlement.    Chancellor again repeated that unless a substantial contribution towards meeting our loss was forthcoming from Italy a breakdown was inevitable&apos;. Meanwhile the Germans have intervened and at a meeting of the inviting powers Wednesday evening Strescmann expressed great anxiety about a possible breakdown of the Conference, because of its effect on German credit ana its political repercussions.    If this occurred the Creditor Powers would probably lose more than any possible sacrifices involved in the dispute about the distribution of the annuities.      He proposed a provisionalarrangement which would,  as from the 1st September, secure to Germany the advantages of the lower annuities under the Young Plan,  leaving the creditor powers to agree subsequently about distribution.    Briand said definitely that if the Young Plan was not adopted, the Dawes Plan must continue;    he saw no other course,    The Chancellor was more sympathetic but thought the ill effects of a breakdown in Germany had probably been exaggeratedo    He did not regard the suggested, provisional arrangement as practicable.    He repeated that our demand in regard to the distribution of tho annuities must be met, and he urged that the other creditor Powers should
now come &quot;to a definite decision.    Stresemann then advanced the wider considerations ox European reconstruction and political reconciliation.Jaspar after meeting saw Chancellor alone and said that he was still extremely anxious for a settlement. When he ashed at what percentage of his full demand we would settle Chancellor said that if Jaspar could induce Italians to make an offer similar to that of &quot;raaoe ana Belgians we could begin to tall: business .,The above was draftee; last night,  but in view of the late hear it was not then sent.    The meeting of tin inviting powers is continuing this r-iorning,I now learn that Germans in spite of Stresemann1s special request for socecy disclosed the vho..e story of their proposal to prsss late last night adding that Briand and. Chancellor opposed it.    This misrepresents our attitude as we sympathise in principle &quot;cut fear it is impossible in practice.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS -TEE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.)MOST SECRET int./A/47.  (8)COPY NOCABINET   .NOTES of a Conference of Mini stere held at No. 10 Downing Street,  S.W.(l),  on Saturday, August 84th, 1929 at 8.15. P.M.P R E S E NThe Right Hon. Ramsay Mac DonaId, M. P , Prime Minister      (in the Chair).The Right HoiuLord Parmoorj K.C.v&quot;.0* Lord President of the Council *-?he Right Bon Lord Sankoy, G0BWE.    Lcrd Chancellor.The Right Hon. Wedgwood Bern, M.P. Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Thomas Shaw, 0 .B..E . ,M.P ,, Secretary of State for War,The Right Hon. Lord Thomson., O.BoE*,    Seoretary of Seato for Air .The Right Hon. Alexander,MSP*.    First Lord of the Admiralty0Mr.    T. Jt:nt3;Deputy Secretary., Cabinet.
Bia Hague i, The Conference-ence (which had been&apos;summoned at short notice Conference -ffeparatlchs. upon the receipt of a telephone message from the PrimeReference Cabinet 29 (29) Con-clusions 6).Minister from Catterick)  considered the situation at the Hague in the light of recent telegrams which had been exchanged between the prime Minister and the British Delegation (Appendix),      Some Ministers present had been able also to read an account of proceedings at the Hague by the Secretary of the Cabinet and the British Delegation which had been circulated that morning.  (CP. 238 (29)).THE PRIME MINISTER reviewed the whole position and in the discussion which followed warm appreciation was expressed of the magnificent stand made by the British Delegation in giving effect to the Cabinet policy as agreed cn July 17th. 1929*      It was recognised, at the same time, to be important to prevent, if possible, the serious financial and political results of a breakdown, especially after so much had been gained in the way of restoring the prestige cf this country the Conference considered the proposal that Ministers should cross to the Hague for consultation- as had been suggested by the British Delegations      It was umders&quot;t&apos;f;ad that this suggestion was made primarily in order to enable the Delegation to comply with the Cabinet Minute of duly 17th, and because of the danger of the Conference at the Hague breaking up if the British Delegation came-over to London to consult their colleagues.      On the other hand Ministers present were agreed that there sere serious objections to Cabinet Ministers at this stags leaving London to participate either In consultations or negotiations at The Hague.
9 9After considerable discussion the Conference apreed that the following message, drafted       the Prime Minister, shouldbe sent immediately to the British DegelationJ-!!The Cabinet Committee met tonight and considered, so far as they had information, the situation at The Hague. They are delighted with the standmade and the vindication of the claim of this country to fair treatment which it does not receive by the Experts&apos; Report.     What we have now to consider is the complete effect of any action taken at The Hague.    &apos; The Committee is of opinion that if a substantial offer, say 70 to 80 per cent of the claim, were met, the country would accept that because (l) we have made a position which will prevent a repetition of what we have had to fight, and (2) it would avoid the unknown but certainly trouble seme political and financial repercussions which would folio;? upon a complete break.     It weald be necessary, however, to make this suggestion after the other creditors have said their last word to ue and should be included in our reply to that wordc     This could be done by referring to the inflated estimates made by the creditor nations and saying that if they would in reality give what they say they are giving it would make a settlement possible.      Or something to that effect.The- opinion of the Committee is that, with that expression of view, they will leave the decision as rega rds the final word tv the Delegation with the further desire that if the worst cornea, the delegation will make it clear that the responsibility is net theirs as the unfairness of the Report to us Is beyond question.&quot;2, Whitehall Gardens ,  3 .W . 1. August    24th, 1929.
9 4APPBKDIX.-L3PE0HS FROM THE DEPUTY SECRETARY CP THE OiBINBT TO ..SSAGE HO. &quot;---(*) TE5 SECH3 TARY OP BRITISH DELSGATI ON, E AGUE .RD AUGUST &apos;-------?--29,5.20 p.m,The Prime Minister requested me to takeadvantage cf a meeting of the Committee on the optional Clause to consult with the Ministersavailable.      There were six ministers presentand they are agreed, with the Prime Minister,that for important reasons it wa-uld be bettertc hold a meeting of the Cabinet in london on Sunday at 12 noon,  and for the british delegation or&apos;some of them to come overon Saturday nightn      If necessary one memberof the Delegation might remain at the Hagueto keep in touch with the proceedings there.Ministers are agreed that the c ourso recommendedby the Prime Minister in the formula sent inhis telegram of August 17th should be followed.THE HAGUE TO LOHDOH.13 LEPEOKE Prom the Chan cell or of the Bx c hsouer to theESSAGE HO. &apos; &quot; &quot; &apos; &apos;2(W)  23rd pri-ijo Minister.UGUST, 19291.35 p.m. The position here is most critical.    If wecam homa we think it probable that the Conference would break up.    It is essential for us tor^r.ain here during the next two or three critical days.   We may perhaps receive another offer shortly. Therefore, we think it would be better if you. came over on Saturday night tc dismiss the who.&apos;, e position on Sunday and to  decide whether or not we  should leave the Conference should there be no satisfactory offer forthcoming.

</content>
</cab>
