<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/206/0 images: 176-190</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 - 9i- U O&apos;2l: 13 300ji.i4-nL 13  THS PuiiB.:,KIY 0? KIS       1 ZMi&apos; 13  . L.J 333Y ; 3   &quot;3 3.a:?\3 3NT )IS E 0 RE T. ^&apos; &apos; OUPY NO. JQ0 Po  72  (29). &apos;0 &quot; COMilTTE^ ON BRITISH GOAL INDUSTRY.NATIONALISATION OP MINERAL ROYALTIES.Note &quot;by the Acting Chairman of the Committee.I circulate herewith,for the consideration of the Gabinet,a memorandum &quot;by the Secretary for Mines on the Nationalisation of Mineral Royalties.I understand, that the Chancellor of the Exchequer will circulate a Memorandum on the financial aspects of these proposals.The Committee on the British Coal Industry consider that the provisions dealing with the mineral royalties should be incorporated in the Bill which is to be introduced this Session dealing with the questions of Hours and Re-organisation in the Coal Industry. and. the Committee recommend -the Cabinet to authorise the inclusion of such provisions in the Bill.(Sgd.) J.H. THOliAS. Acting Chairman of the Committee.2, Whit shall Gardens, S -Yi. 1. 12th October,  1929.
I 9 0j- t* *this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC I&apos;I/.JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. SECRETB.C.I.   (29) 3. COPY NO.        j jjCABINETCOAL    COMMITTEE. NATIONALISATION  OF MINERAL ROYALTIES.Note &quot;by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate to my colleagues the accompanying memorandum by the Secretary for Mines on the nstionalisa-tion of mineral royalties, which was promised in the memorandum circulated on the 13th July (B.C.I.  (29) 2).W.Q.Board of Trade,15th July, 192 9.
SECRET.NATIONALISATION OF MINERAL ROYALTIES. I.        INTRODUCTORY.* That all minerals except gold and silver are the propertyof the owner of the land under which they lie was definitely established by judicial decision in 1568.     For 350 yearstherefore they have been freely dealt with like any other formof private property.     It was not until the latter part of the nineteenth century, when the mining industry grew to be of paramount national importance, and the Miners&apos; Federation became a political force, that questions began to be raised whetherthis form of private property was consistent with the national interest.      In 1889 these questions were referred to a RoyalCommission of which Lord Northbrook was Chairman and LordMacnaghten and Mr. T&apos;Illiam Abraham the most eminent members.Reporting on the 24th March, 1893, the Commission recorded thegeneral verdict that&quot;the system of royalties has not interfered with the general development of the mineral resources of the United Kingdom, or with the export trade with foreign countries.They made certain minor recommendations, to most of which effect, has been given by subsequent legislation.Four Inquiries in recent years have arrived at conclusions less favourable to the royalty owners.     These are the Coal Conservation Committee  (Lord Raldane, Chairman;    Sir :,dam Nimmo, Chairman of Coal Sub-Committee), the Acquisition and Valuation of Land Committee  (Sir Leslie Scott, Chairman)  the Coal Industry Commission (Mr. Justice Sankey, Chairman) and the Royal Commission on the Coal Industry  (1925)    (Sir Herbert Samuel, Chairman).     All the members of all these bodies committed themselves to the view that the system of private ownership of minerals does impede production in certain ways, and that there is a case for legislation to remove those impediments.
The various oircumstances in which the private ownership of minerals causes them to be left unworked or to be worked uneconomically are set out seriatim in the &quot;XIV Points&quot; enumerated on pages Q and 7 of the Third Report of Sir Leslie Scott1 s Committee, and recapitulated in the final P.eport of the Coal Owners &amp;c, on the Sankey Commission (page 42),    They tnay be briefly summarised as&apos; follows(i) When the owner refuses, without sufficient reason,  to lease or work the minerals.(ii) When the owner demands exorbitant terms for the minerals.(iii) When a Lord of the Manor or&apos; Copy-holder refuses to join in a lease of the minerals.(iv) When it is impossible to obtain agreement between numerous owners of small parcels of minerals,  or between tenants in common.(v) When the owner of minerals is under some legal disability which prevents him from exercising his rights.(vi) When the owner of minerals oannot be found.(vii) When a right of support is exercised unreasonably.(viii) When minerals are unnecessarily left in barriers between properties.(ix) When wayleaves are refused, or unreasonable terms are demanded for them.(x) When the necessary surface rights cannot be obtained on reasonable terms.(xi) When restrictive covenants have been imposed for the protection of the surface owner.(xii) When terms of a mining lease are unduly onerous, or,  owing to unforeseen circumstances, have become so.(xiii) When the &quot;lay-out&quot; of a mineral field, owing to the accidents of surface ownership,  is,  from the technical mining point of view, unsatisfactory.
HZThe Coal Industry Commission and the Samuel Commission proposed one form of remedy;    the Coal Conservation Committee and^the Leslie scott Committee another.    The Commissions recommended that the State should acquire the property in all coal and underground wayleaves.    The Committees recommended that minerals should be left in private ownership, but that the owners, in the last resort, should be subjected to the dictation of an independent authority,  charged with the preservation of &quot;the national interest&quot;.    The only substantial difference between the recommendations of the two Committees is that the first proposed to entrust this overriding power to a Ministry of Mines and Minerals, the second to a Committee of both Houses of Parliament.The Mines (Working Facilities and Support) Act,  1923, as amended by Part II of the Mining Industry Act,  1926 has carried out in principle the recommendations of the two Committees.    It adopts as its &quot;sanctioning authority&quot; not the Committee of Parliament proposed by the Leslie Scott Committee, but the Court of the Railway and Canal Commission.    Otherwise the procedure prescribed follows generally their recommenda-tions,    The Court is empowered to make orders granting to applicants the right to work minerals or an &quot;ancillary&quot; right required for the 11 proper and convenient&quot; working of the minerals, when it has proved to be &quot;not reasonably practicable&quot; to obtain the rights in question by private arrangement.    The Court may also relieve colliery owners of onerous conditions militating against the best development of coal.    The applicant must apply in the first instance to the Mines Department, whose business it is to examine the facts, and, if they are satisfied that a orima facie case has been made out,  to send the application on to the Commission.    Tho
js-Put in its extreme form by Mr.Smillie on the Sankey Commission, when he took his stand on the Psalmist&apos;s &quot;The earth is the Lord&apos;s and the fulness thereof&quot;.-4-Commission then hear the case argued before them and either grant or refuse the Order asked for.    Before granting any right they must be satisfied that &quot;it is expedient in the national interest&quot; that it should be granted.Advocates of the nationalisation of royalties justify their proposal on two main grounds, which may for convenience be called the &quot;utilitarian&quot; case and the &quot;political&quot; case. The utilitarian argument is that this is a simpler and more effective way than the Working Facilities Acts of meeting the &quot;XIV points&quot;.    The political argument is that in a system of private ownership of minerals there is something contrary to the funamental principles of public policy and equity The Samuel Commission gave, in other words, the same two reasons for nationalisation.    They appeared to realise, however, that the utilitarian oase would havo been a great deal stronger when the development of minerals was still in its early stages. Their view was, however, that &quot;the present generation should not be deterred by the difficulties that attach to the problem from undertaking to redeem the error of the past&quot;.    What is perhaps of more practical importance than redeeming any politioal or judicial errors of the past is the question whether the engineering errors of the past are redeemable, or future ones avoidable, by means of nationalisation, and the fact is that mining development in the main has now passed beyond the stage in which haphazard small soale unscientifio development is possible to a stage at which practical necessity compels large scale long sighted propositions.    This fact, combined with the existence of the Working Facilities
legislation leaves the utilitarian case for nationalisation of minerals to-day a less strong one than it might have &quot;been some generations ago.At the same time it is a fact that certain colliery owners hove recently been declaring themselves in favour of State ownership of minerals, if only for the reason that private ownership involves contractual obligations as to minimum rents and other matters which sre an obstacle to closing an unremunerative pit and therefore militate against &quot;rationalisation&quot;,LEGISLATIVE PROPOSALS.The form of legislation necessary to give effect to the nationalisation of royalties has more than once been considered departmentally, for nationalisation was the avowed policy of the Coalition Government in 1919 and 1920, and was under consideration by the previous Labour Government. The stock scheme contemplates that on an appointed day the property in all coal and associated minerals in situ will vest in the Crown; that the compensatiL on to be paid to the owners will be the equivalent of the market value of their minerals at that time as determined by the Valuation Department of the Inland Revenue; that that obligation will be discharged by the issue of terminable annuities; that the State ?:ill be substituted for the existing lessor in every current coal mining lease ( in so far as the lessor!s rights and obligations ore derived from his ownership of the minerals, not of the surface );    that the State will be given the power to grant new leases and (subject to appeal to the Railway and Canal Commis slon) to cancel or vary existing ones; and. that a royalties fund will be created, guaranteed by the Exchequer, into which will be paid the royalties reserved by the Crown in its leases and out of
which will he paid the interest on the annuities.      The provisions for the compulsory acquisition of surface rights, which had to form part of earlier schemes, have become unnecessary owing to the passing of the Working Facilities Act.OBJECTIONS  TO THE LEGISLATIVE PROPOSALS.The administrative difficulties of any scheme ih which all the coal in the country simultaneously changes fr\om private to public ownership are very great, though not perhaps insuperable.     To make a complete valuation in the limited time, involving as it would the examination of the claims of vast numbers of small land-owners who thought, rightly or wrongly, that there was coal under their small plots of land, would be a gigantic task.      To create upwards of  100,000,000 of fresh debt is not a course to be undertaken lightly.     To present a man who is already a millionaire with the equivalent of perhaps another million of public money is open to political attack.     The necessity for examining every coal mining lease in the country, of separating what relates to the minerals from what, relates to the surface (not always an easy task) and of adjusting in each the new tripartite relationship between the lessee, the Department   as mineral lessor, and the ex-royalty owner as surface lessor, presents an administrative problem of the first magnitude.      The large additions that would be necessary to the staffs of the Inland Revenue and the Mines Department would not commend themselves to public opinion,POSSIBLE ALTERNATIVE LEGISLATIVE PROPOSALS.Is there, then, any scheme of nationalisation that would be free from the objections enumerated above?     If they are
examined it will&quot; be seen that they arise almost entirely from the simultaneity of the process proposed.   The key to their avoidance may therefore lie in devising a gradual process; th*. time at which minerals are to be taken over being dictated by considerations partly of convenience and partly of the utilitarian objects in view.In the case of undeveloped minerals these considerations suggest that it would be sufficient for the State to acquire them only when State ownership serves any practical purpose, that is to say when it is proposed to work them.   This has the advantage of combining the maximum of administrative convenience with the achievement - so far as it goes - of all the utilitarian advantages.   The procedure would be simple. There would be no dealings between the prospective colliery owner and the owner of the coal (as such) at all.   The former would apply to the Department (or other State authority) for a lease of a specified area of minerals.   The Department, if satisfied that the proposed lay-out was a proper one, would grant a lease on such terms as it thought fit.    It would then advertise for claims for compensation from the owners of the minerals, to be made within a certain date, and pay them in terminable annuities, the interest on which, during their currency, (guaranteed of course by the exchequer) would be met out of the State royalties.In the case of coal already in lease, considerations of convenience indicate a similar process, viz., that when a lease expires the remaining minerals (if any)  should be treated in the same way as undeveloped minerals:    if and when anyone wants to :\rork the;-; it is to the Crown that application must
HIbe made; as soon as a lease is granted the minerals become the property of the Crown, and the previous owners are entitled to compensation.   But this does not go far enough       / to satisfy the utilitarian case.    It is part of that case that the State ownership of minerals would enable faulty lay-outs to be corrected, facilitate the absorption of the inefficient by their more efficient neighbours, and so forth.   Fully to meet the utilitarian case, therefore, it would be necessary also to provide that the State may at any time buy up any particular minerals in lease (or being worked by the proprietor) without waiting for the lease to expire, and, if desirable in the national Interest, cancel the lease, and  rant a fresh one. A ri/ht of appeal to the Railway and Canal Commission would no doubt have to be given to the lessee whose lease the Department proposed to cancel, and he would, of course, have to be compensated if he was damnified.Thus   all royalties would be gradually acquired, as and when they were created or re-created, or otherwise when utilitarian reasons arose for acquiring them, and all the difficulties would be avoided that are Inherent in the haste of a simultaneous scheme - a haste that is quite unnecessary from the utilitarian point of view, since, from that point of view, a very large part of the minerals now being worked might just as well remain for the present in private hands.   There Would be no necessity to value all minerals within a limited time;    no flood of doubtful and petty claims for compensation; no serious addition to the national debt at any one time;    no distribution of vast sums to royalty owners;    existing mining leases would not have to be examined and their rights and obligations re-distributed;    little, if any, addition would have to be made to the staff of the Inland Revenue and not so serious an addition to that of the Mines Department.
It is true that this &quot;gradual&quot; scheme has one disadvantage ae compared with a &quot;simultaneous&quot; scheme.    Under the latter, all coal vests once and for all in the Crown on a certain day, claims for compensation must be made within a certain period; and then the thing is finished.   All coal belongs to the Crown in future;    the man whose coal was of no appreciable value, or who did not know that he had any coal, will (very properly) get nothing for it, and it may prove in years to come that the State has acquired a valuable asset very cheaply.   Under the &quot;gradual&quot; scheme everyone who may in future be found to have workable coal, even though he does not know it now, will be entitled to be paid full value for it just at the time when Its value is greatest.   But on the other side of the account must be set the fact that under a &quot;simultaneous&quot; scheme the State will certainly pay for- some coal from which it will never get any return, and the possibility ought not perhaps to be altogether disregarded that some other source of power might supersede coal and the State be left with a worthless commodity on its hands for which it had paid large sums that the taxpayer would be called upon to honour.    It might moreover be possible to attach to the &quot;gradual&quot; scheme a proviso that nothing should be paid for any coal the existence of which cannot be proved within five years from the passing of the Act to have a commercial value.The device of the authors of &quot;Coal and Power&quot; for meeting thepoint is worth quoting in full.    After recommending that all coalnow in lease should be acquired outright on an &quot;appointed day&quot;,they express the view that it would be too expensive to acquireoutright all undeveloped coal in the same way, and continue:&quot;We &quot;propose (i) that all land-owners who believe that minerals lie under their land should be entitled, for a period, say, of five years, to make by way of anticipation a claim for compensation, to become effective in the event of the minerals being taken over;
(ii) that If no claim be lodged within the stipulated period the right to make a claim for compensation should lapse;(ill) that all such claimants should be required to assess the value of their own mineral rights, which assessments should be recorded with the Inland Revenue Department for the purpose of estimating the death duties and other taxation due from the estates to which they refer;(iv) that the State should be empowered to take over the minerals concerned, or any part of them, at any time, at the valuation placed on them by the land-owner, or, at the option of the State, at a valuation to be determined by arbitration.&quot;This proposal is. In effect, that compensation should be paid for each parcel of minerals acquired, at whatever time the State thinks fit to acquire it; that the amount of compensation, however, should be the value of the parcel not at that time, but at some previous date - possibly many years before.     Now the recognised method of valuing undeveloped minerals is to estimate the probable full royalty value of the minerals when they come into working ( x), the length of time that is likely to elapse before that date (y years) and then to find the present value of an annuity of  x deferred for y years, the rate of interest being taken at about 10-15 per cent.    In the result, the present value that coal would have if it were about to be Immediately worked is divided by two for every 7^ years for which the working is likely to be deferred.    Thus coal which is not likely to be worked for 20 years is worth now only 25 per cent, of what its value will be then, and coal wliich is not likely to be worked for 50 years, only 1 per cent.   But the present value of a deferred annuity is a contradiction in terms unless it implies an immediate, not a deferred, payment.   To adopt the present value of a future benefit as the purchase price of that benefit and then to delay payment of it to some future date is obviously Indefensible.The proposal of the Samuel Commission was that the State should acquire all minerals developed or undeveloped at their market price, subject to these two points, viz., that minerals which have no present market price should be acquired for nothing, and that the State should have the option, for a specified period, to decide whether any area or property should be excluded from the scheme.
Such is the hroad outline of a possible scheme for the gradual nationalisation of royalties, that avoids the serious administrative and political difficulties of a &quot;simultaneous&quot; scheme but secures all Its utilitarian advantages.  -   lb has been assumed, In formulating it, that it Is not enough to acquire minerals as and when leases are granted to work them, but that it is also necessary to take a selective power to acquire minerals already being worked, and to cancel leases and Issue fresh ones.     When the scheme comes to be examined,  it will be necessary to weigh very carefully the arguments for and against this part of it.      On the one side it will be said that the scheme Is absurd without it, for the State would be left without power to achieve one of the nost Important objects of nationalisation - that of promoting efficient production by &quot;tidying up&quot; the lay-out of existing coalfields  - and that if nationalisation is any use it ought to be applied, or at least capable of application, not only to undeveloped minerals but also to all developed minerals, instead of merely to the residue of them that may be worth working at the end of existing leases.      On the other side, it will be argued (probably with truth) that there is not nearly so much that can be done in the way of &quot;tidying up&quot; as people outside the Industry seem to think, and that, so far as there is scope for it, it will be quite enough to do It gradually, as leases fall in;    that all colliery owners would be in a state of uncertainty whether their coal might not be bought up and their leases cancelled, and this would check developments, repairs and re-equipments;    that this objection, coupled with the extreme administrative simplicity of nationalisation only when leases are issued, outweighs any advantages that there might be in taking the additional power. Possibly a middle course might- be devised by which the addition-al power should be taken but its exercise subjected to such limitations as would remove any reasonable apprehension from the minds of efficient colliery owners.
THE   COST.There is contained in Appendix 39 of the Samuel Commissions Report an estimate by the (then) Chief Valuer of the Valuation Department of the Board of Inland Revenue of the cost of acquiring mineral rights in coal under the &quot;Samuel Commission&apos;s&quot; proposals.     His estimate, on the basis which he specifies, was that the immediate purchase of coal royalties, wayleaves and rights in undeveloped coal would cost  92 million, or, allowing for contingencies,  100 million.Payment would presumably be made in a guaranteed Government stock, and a draft on State credit would have to be made to the extent of the stock issued.How much would he issued immediately or at any one time would depend upon whether a &quot;simultaneous&quot; or a &quot;gradual&quot; scheme were adopted.Under a &quot;simultaneous&quot; scheme one may assume a more or less immediate issue of the  100 million estimated.     Under a &quot;gradual&quot; scheme it is at least conceivable that the cost might ultimately be even more, owing to a higher price being paid for coal at present undeveloped.     But when regard is had to the later date at which payment would be made fcr such coal the cost reckoned over a period of years would not be greater.     Indeed it would probably be less In the end, owing to  the fact that under a simultaneous scheme some payment would probably be made for some coal which would never in fact be worked or bring any return in royalties.The financial result of the transaction to the State Is examined on page 81 of Volume I of the Samuel Commission&apos;s Report.     Account must be taken, they point out, not only of the interest and sinking fund in the loan, but also of such matters as the loss of Mineral Rights Duty, and of some part
of the income tax and super tax now paid upon the royalties and wayleaves; of the cost of the rates paid by mineral owners in Scotland; and of the cost of acquisition and of management and collection.     Their conclusion was that the transaction should Just about &quot;pay its way&quot;.They did not appear to contemplate any change in the average yield per ton of royalties and wayleaves *     It must however be remembered that if the State as mineral owner is going to make it easier for colliery owners to give up the working of &quot;unprofitable&quot; coal, (e.g,f by relaxing obligations as to minimum rents) the result may be to reduce the average yield of royalties and to make the whole transaction an unprofitable one.     One way to meet this point would be to provide that minimum-rent conditions in a lease should be ignored in assessing the value of the minerals subject to it, but &quot;pro tanto&quot; this would amount to &quot;confiscation&quot;.Another consideration arising out of the same point is that, in so far as nationalisation of minerals is going to help rationalisation of the industry by facilitating the closing of superfluous pits, it follows that some minerals would have been paid for which subsequently will not be worked or yield any return.

</content>
</cab>
