<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/206/0 images: 359-362</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Pooament is the Property of Hfo Britannic Majesty&quot; s Governments]Printed far the Cabinet.   October 1929.SECRET. Copy No.   35CP. 286 (29).CABINET.BAGHDAD AND HAIFA RAILWAY AND PIPE-LINE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.WITH reference to the recent discussion in Cabinet on the subject of a Baghdad-Haifa railway and pipe-line, and the direction then given that the situation should be carefully watched by the departments concerned, I think my colleagues may be interested to read the summary which I circulate herewith of the latest information in regard to French activities for securing an alignment through Syria.It will be noted that on the 1st October five French military aircraft, engaged on a survey of the pipe-line, flew from Syria to Iraq (Mosul).It is significant that the French Government should have placed French military aircraft at the disposal of a survey party in the employ of the Iraq Petroleum Company.T.Air Ministry, October 21, 1929.Note by Air Staff.Summary of Recent Information concerning the French Projects for a Railway and Pipe-Line from Syria to the Iraq Frontier.1. Extract from a note of a conversation between Sir Henry Dobbs (then High Commissioner for Iraq) and M. Ponsot (High Commissioner for Syria) on the 8th February, 1929, at Beyroute.(Begins) : &quot; Oii the 8th February at Beyroute, M. Ponsot spoke to me about the pipe-line and railway from Baghdad to the Mediterranean. The points he made were : (a.) That the French Government had decided to build a railway at an early date from Horns to the Euphrates via Palmyra. Its terminus would be either Abu Kemal or Deir Ez Zor. When that was done no one but a madman could contemplate the railway or pipe-line terminating at any other place than Tripoli. He showed me volumes of &apos; etudes &apos; on this projected railway.(6.) That expert French engineers had shown that an excellent port for oil tankers could be constructed for 100 million francs at Tripoli.   British arguments that the winds at Tripoli were too bad were therefore baseless.&quot; (Ends.) [20042]
2. Extract from a note of a conversation between Sir John Chancellor (High Commissioner for Palestine) and M. Ponsot at Beyroute on the 19th March, 1929.(Begins): &quot;I asked M. Ponsot if he had any recent information as to the proposal to construct a &apos;railway from Baghdad and a pipe-line from Iraq to the Mediterranean.M. Ponsot said that he regarded the construction of a railway from Tripoli to open up the interior of Syria and a pipe-line from Tripoli to Iraq as important French interests.He had studied carefully the topography of the country, and it was clear to him that there would be no serious difficulty in constructing a railway line from Tripoli via Palmyra to Deir-ez-Zor on the Euphrates. That line, and also a line from Damascus to Palmyra, were necessary for the development of a large area of fertile country.As regards the pipe-line, he had no doubt that the most favoured route from Iraq to the Mediterranean would be to a terminus at Tripoli. On that route there was no mountain range and no depression to be crossed. The country to be traversed, too, was favourable for motor transport; there would therefore be no difficulty in constructing a pipe-line without the assistance of a railway for the transport of materials.He recognised that the development of the harbour at Haifa was of great importance to Great Britain. Haifa would probably become a naval centre, and, as a station on the overland route to Iraq and India and also as a terminus for a pipe-line from Iraq, it might have considerable strategic importance.There was no need to assume that French, and English interests in regard to those matters were irreconcilable. He understood that to enable a pipe-line of the length proposed to pay its way two million tons of oil per annum must be carried by it. He believed that before long the output of the Iraq oil-field would be about eight million tons per annum, so that there would be ample room for two pipe-lines.&quot; (Ends.)3. Extract from letter from Mr. Williams of the Colonial Office to the Deputy Chief of the Air Staff, dated the 11th April, 1929 :  (Begins) : &quot; Major Holt of the Iraq Railways, who recently carried out a survey on behalf of the Turkish Petroleum Company of routes for a trans-desert pipe-line, called at the Colonial Office a, few days ago. In the course of conversation he stated that the Turkish Petroleum Company had been given an explicit assurance that, whatever might be the cost, and whatever might be its natural disadvantages, the Erench Government would build a first-rate harbour at Tripoli if it were decided to bring the pipe-line there. In view of this assurance, the Company have reversed their previous decision to send out four experts to report on the suitability of Tripoli as the western terminal of the pipe-line. They have decided, instead, to send out an American pipe-line expert a Mr. Towle to examine and report on a route for a pipe-line from Tripoli to the Iraq oil-fields, and particularly to find a way across the great saline depression between the Tigris and the Euphrates, which is one of the chief obstacles to be encountered on this route.Mr. Towle, who will be accompanied by a French and a British Engineer, will start in September, and will probably make a cursory examination of the alternative route to Haifa surveyed by Major Holt. He will be in possession of Major Holfs reports and of the data submitted by the latter.Major Holt added that he had learnt from Turkish Petroleum Company circles that the French had decided to build a railway to Abu Kemal.&quot;    (Ends.)4. Reports from British Liaison Officer in Syria.(a.) A report, received in February 1929, from the British Liaison Officer in beyrout, stated the French authorities had for some time been preparing data for the eventual construction of a new railway line from Syria across the desert to the Iraq frontier on the Euphrates. The railway was stated to be primarily a strategic one, with the object of conveying troops to the Euphrates area and the Upper Jaziret, without passing through Turkish territory.
Possible alternative alignments were reported to be as follows :  Route 1 : Damascus-Paimyra-Deir Ez Zor. Route 2 : Homs-Palmyra-Deir Ez Zor. Route 3 : Aleppo-Rakka-Deir Ez Zor.Route 1 has the disadvantage of the greatest distance, but it has the advantage of serving the great military centre of Damascus, whose dose proximity to the Djebel Druze and the Port of beyrout would be a consideration. This route would be approximately parallel to the southern frontier between Syria and the two British Mandates of Transjordan and Palestine.Route 2. This route has the advantage of shorter distance, and of joining at Homs the branch line from Tripoli across the only gap in the Lebanon and the Alouite Mountains (the Trouee de Horns). The advantages of the Tripoli-Horns railway and road have been very strikingly brought out within the last week when road and railway from beyrout to Rayak and Damascus were blocked, and con-sequently all drafts, officers returning from leave, &amp;c, had to be taken in a coasting boat from beyrout to Tripoli and from there distributed via Homs Junction to Aleppo and the Upper Euphrates on the one hand, and Rayak, Damascus and the Djebel Druze on the other.The route via Homs is looming particularly important nowadays as the question of the pipe-line coming through Syria is being talked of on all sides. If it comes through Syria, the most obvious and favoured route is through Homs to Tripoli; consequently, if a railway were constructed for apparently military purposes across the desert, it would do a great deal towards persuading the Turkish Petroleum Company to adopt that route and not the longer and more unprotected route to Haifa.Route 3. This route is fairly short, in comparison with the others and has the advantage of being the nearest to the troublesome area along the Turkish frontier, yet not too near. From a constructional point of view, it is probably the easiest, as the line of the valley of the Euphrates would be followed most of the way. It would connect directly with Aleppo, whose military importance for the north of Syria is as great as Damascus for that of the south. Commercially and internationally, this route would probably be most useful, as it would serve as a direct line between Europe, Konia and Baghdad; therefore, if this route was determined upon it would be with the idea of cutting out the Turkish Nisibin railway once and for all.(b.) A further report from the British Liaison officer in beyrout, received in March 1929, transmitted information suggesting that the Homs-Palmyra-Deir Ez Zor alignment would be the route selected. This alignment would give access to the Mediterranean at Tripoli via the railway through the Lebanese mountains.The terms of the report were as follows : Two experts from Paris have lately arrived in Syria to study the question of the enlargement of the port of beyrout and a proposed railway which has lately been suggested from Homs to Palmyra and Deir Ez Zor.This railway is primarily a strategic one to enable the French to move troops to the Euphrates area without being obliged to use the railway which constitutes their northern boundary with Turkey. It will make Homs an important junction, for from Homs runs the only line through the Lebanese mountains to the coast at Tripoli. Thus the influence on the future route of the Turkish Petroleum Company&apos;s pipe-line may be affected by this project.5. Secret Intelligence Rejmrt.Information received from a secret but not necessarily reliable source in March 1929 stated that the French authorities in Syria had decided upon the construction of a railway from Homs to Deir Ez Zor.The object of this scheme was to intensify still further the French propaganda in favour of the Syrian route for the projected pipe-line from Iraq.6. Extract from Telegram (No. 287) of the 4Jh October to Air Ministry from Air IIeadquarters, Baghdad.&quot; On the 1st October five French military Potez aircraft, which are engaged on pipe-line surveying on behalf of the Iraq Petroleum Company, arrived at Mosul and left next morning.&quot;
7. Report from British Liaison-.&apos;Officer, beyrout, 17th September, 1929, regarding this survey.Permission has been asked by the Iraq Petroleum Company Mission, which arrived in this country last month, for three of its members, Mr. Towle, American, Mr. Douglas, British, and M. l?armentier, French, to carry out an aerial reconnaissance of part of the country which may be traversed by the pipe-line from Mosul to the Mediterranean. The French authorities are placing military aircraft at their disposal and, with the permission of the Iraq authorities, they propose starting their reconnaissance on the 25th September. The line which they will follow will be :  Outward :   Rayak-Forklos-Palmyra-Abu Kemal-Ana (Euphrates)-Tekrit (Tigris).Return.: Tekrit-Deir Ez Zor-Forklos-Homs.They are arranging for the Standard Oil Company in Iraq to dump petrol at Ana and Tekrit.8. Extract  from   Report   to   the   Air  Ministry  from   Headquarters,   R.A.F., Transjordan, dated the 20th September, 1929.Pipe-line and Proposed Horns-Heir Ez Zor Railway. The mixed British-Franco-American Mission of the Iraq Petroleum Company, having devoted a month to Tripoli, are now moving eastwards between Tripoli and Horns on the first stage of their survey. The air reconnaissance has been postponed until the 30th September or after. Meanwhile, the press reports that a special commission will meet on the 10th October next, at the Ministry of Public Works at Damascus, to examine the request made by the D.H.P. (Damas, Hama et Prolongements) Railway Company for the grant of a concession to construct a railway line from Homs to Deir ez Zor via, Palmyra.Air Staff, October 18, 1929.

</content>
</cab>
