<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/206/0 images: 396-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

SECRET.

COPY. NO. 38.

C.P. 291 (29)

(Also F.S.(29) 15)

CABINET.

FIGHTING SERVICES COMMITTEE.

SECOND INTERIM REPORT.

POLICY AS REGARDS THE SINGAPORE BASE.

On September 25th, the Cabinet referred to us two Memoranda on the subject of the Singapore Base, namely:-

A Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty on the subject of the policy as regards Singapore (Paper C.P. 243 (29): also Paper F.S. (29) 11),

and

A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War on the subject of the Defences and their cost (Paper C.P. 254 (29): also Paper F.S. (29) 12).

This Interim Report deals with the former Memorandum, namely, the question of policy. A separate Report will be submitted in regard to the defences.

THE PRESENT POSITION.

2. The policy of the Government, as recommended by this Committee, towards the Singapore Base was explained by the Prime Minister to the Committee of Imperial Defence at the 244th Meeting hold on July 25th. A copy of the Prime Minister&apos;s
considered s tat accent was subsequently transmitted by despatch to tho Prime Ministers of the Dominions.3. Tho text of tho Prime Minister&apos;s statement is attached   ikvrxcnvoTQjk) ,    It will be noted thatthe Conclusions (which, however, wore described as&quot; for the momentv) ir. eluded the following:-(2) That the financial gain which would result from a complete stoppage would, when all obligations are taken into account, be compare-lively small.25       H       S        55       K       55(5) The Jackson Contract for the com-pletion rf a graving dock will be proceeded with.4,  In his Memorandum (Paper CP.-243 (29)) the First Lord of the Admiralty emphasises that if, as the Graving Dock&quot; near s couplet ion, workshops, stere-sheds, railway lines, etc. , are mat, provided and equipped, the DogIb on which s.o much money has been spent will be incapable of being used-    &quot;To hav spent 30 much money&quot;, be continues,  &quot;upon the provision of Docks and then to leave them in such a condition that adequate use ciuld mt be made of them without undertaking further work extending over a period of years, would not seem to be an easily defensible position . .. . &quot;    Up to the^ present time, therefore, no orders have been given for the closing down of any of the work   referred to, since without it the Graving Dock would itself be incomplete as a unit, and much of the work must r.oc^ssarily be carried on concurrerltly with the building of the do ok.
5.   The progress towards naval disarmament madein the Prime Minister&apos;s conversations, first withthe American Ambassador and afterwards with president Hoover in Washington, and the acceptance by all the Powers concerned of an invitation to aConference on the subject to begin in London in thethird week in January, 1930,  constitute new factors in the situation.    For example, tho officialinvitation to the forthcoming Conference contained the fallowing passage:-&quot;The question of battleship strength was also touched upon during the conversations, and it has been agreed in these conversations that, subject to the assent of other signatory Powers,    it would be desirable to reconsider the battle-ship replacement programmes provided for in the Washington Treaty of 1922, with the view to dlniinishing the amount of replacement construction implied under that Treaty&quot;.We are aware that differences cf opinion exist between rations in regard to the size cf thecapital ship, smd it is understood that the naval authorities at Washington arc less favourable than the British Admiralty to a reduction.    Inview, however, of the inclusion of the passagequoted above in the official invitation, and ofthe strong world cpinion in favour of economy inthis most expensive type of warship, wo think itwould be a mistake to assume that there is no possibility of important decisions being reached by the Conference on the subject.6. In this connection we notice that, in reply to the Prime MiirLster&apos;s question &quot;What would be the kind of Singapore Base required if the first-class
9 i 9eJ1 A rJbattleship was iraterially roduoed in size orceased to exist?11, the Admiralty,   &quot;vhileemphasising that a mere reduction in the size ofcapital ships would not affect the noed for twod o cks, st at ed: -&quot;If all Capital Ships were to be scrapped within the next few years, &apos; the existing commercial docking facilities at Singapore, in con-junotien with the &quot;Admiralty Fdoating Pcok5 would be sufficient, assuming that the abolition of tho Capital Ship resulted in a propor-ticnal reduction in global toKnage&quot;.7. V/liile we must disclaim all attempts to forecast what will be the effect of the DisarmamentConference on the future of the Capital Ship, weconsider that to continue the entire Singaporescheme in complete disregard of the possibilitiesof the Conference would be indefensible.    Pendingthe results of the Disarmament Conference, there-fore, we recommend:-(l)   That the work on tl?e Singapore Base should be slowed dewo as &quot;much as possible:(2)  That all work that can be suspended should be suspended:(3)  That no rev/&quot; work ^should be embarked  -(Sgd) .  PHILIP SNOWDEHo A ct ing Chairman*Whiteha11 Gardens, S.W.1. fotober 22, 1929.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. ] - Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   July 1929.MOST SECRET. AMMEXUHB A. Copy No.      99337-C.(Also Paper No. 955-B.)COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.POLICY  REGARDING NAVAL  CONSTRUCTION  PROGRAMME  and singapore.(Previous C.I.D. Paper No. 336-C.)Statement by the Prime Minister at the 24Ath Meeting of the Committee ofImperial Defence.I MADE a statements yesterday in the House of Commons regarding the intentions of the Government on the matter of Naval building. This is only, part of a general re-examination of the problem of defence in relation to the political state of the world, which the Government is undertaking. We desire that the whole of our defence policy should be co-ordinated and put on a thoroughly scientific and systematic basis and related to the international policy which we are striving to get the other nations to pursue along with ourselves.2. As a key to what we have in our minds, I might, perhaps, conveniently refer to what took place when Lord Haldane entered the War Office in 1905, and the investi-gations on which he based his policy. Obviously, in this survey-, the position of Singapore must be carefully considered. The points arising out of it may be summarised as follows : (1.) The conditions of the international situation governing Imperial strategy, and perhaps of Imperial strategy itself which prevailed when the Singapore base was projected have undoubtedly changed. What modifications in the conclusions come to in those days is now required 1That is the large overruling problem. In addition to that, however, some important details have to be considered, as, for instance (2.) What is the most recent view of Coast Defence in relation to the Singapore base ?(3.) What definite problem would have to be faced as regards the nature of the action which would have to be taken in the event of war breaking out and Singapore being the centre either of offence or defence ?And, however remote or doubtful to some of our minds it may be, we cannot overlook altogether this further question : (4.) What would be the kind of Singapore Base required if the first-class battleship was materially reduced in size or even ceased to exist ?3. Obviously, upon an up-to-date answer to these questions the plan of Singapore must be devised. In that devising, this also must be made clear that public money must not be wasted upon work which is unlikely to be of continuing value. It is our duty to take into account the possibilities of Naval agreements and the general effect of the pact of Peace upon the handling of international policy, which used to depend as a last resort upon available forces.* C.I.D. Paper No. 956-B.[19668]   [20041]3 1 a -
July 25, 1929.4. Since Singapore was first devised, its possible use for commercial purposes has steadily crept into the scheme. How far could a Naval base there be utilised for commerce, and what modification would be required so that the Docks might be available to the fullest extent for commercial ships 1 Further, if a military Air Base is developed at Singapore, how far could such a base be used for commercial aircraft and be a link in a chain of Imperial and world air communication ?5. I have formed my statement mainly in the nature of questions because that indicates precisely the present mind of the Government. It is enquiring, and I can assure you that it will continue to enquire before big decisions are taken. But you will gather irom the nature of the questions that the Government has a general policy in its mind. It is working steadily towards international agreements to remove those questions which have hitherto been the causes of disputes from a settlement by force to one by conciliation or arbitration.6. It is not the intention of the Government, however, to proceed with any policy which could accurately be described as one of hasty &quot;scrapping.&quot; Its idea is that as security is found, stage by stage by the establishment of sure means of peaceful settlement, so military organisation will accommodate itself to the new circumstances.7. As you know, a small Committee has been surveying the present position at Singapore, and amongst other things has been considering the following : (1.) Commitments made to the Dominions as well as to Colonies and Dependencies, like the Straits Settlements, Hong Kong and the Malay States.(2.) Contracts already entered into for the execution of work.(3.) Progress already made like the presence of the Floating Dock and thecommencement of the graving dock. (4.) The present position of the defences in relation to recent experiments.8. The Committee&apos;s conclusions for the moment are : (1.) That the Dominions should be kept fully informed of what is passing in its mind.(2.) That the financial gain which would result from a complete stoppage would,when all obligations are taken into account, be comparatively small. (3.) Whilst there is disagreement about defences, the original scheme, suspendedby our predecessors, will remain in that condition. (4.) For at least the next two years an Air Force Squadron drawn from home forces will be based at Singapore. (5.) The Jackson Contract for the completion of a graving dock will be proceeded with.Our conclusions will be transmitted at once by telegram to the Dominions, and we earnestly hope that those who are principally concerned will endorse them.

</content>
</cab>
