<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/66/0 images: 432-437</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVgRNMENT) .S E C R E T. Copy No.cabinet    25 (51).[meeting of the Cabinet to be held in the PrimeMinister&apos;s Room, House of Commons, onFRIDAY, April 2^th,  1931, at.0 p,m.AGENDA.1.      REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.     THE FRANCO-ITALIAN NAVAL AGREEMENT.     (if required).(Reference Cabinet 2if (31) Conclusion 2)..2,      THE BUDGET.(Signed;    M.p.A. HANKEY,Secretary,  Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens,   3.W.123rd April, 1 931 ..
o(THIS DOCUMENT IS TIB PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT^SECRET. Copy No._____CABINET    25  (31 ) .CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.1.,, on FRIDAY,April 22fth,  1931,  at 2.0 p.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).:.p,The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.F.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor, K. C.V..0 . ,K. C.Lord President of theCouncii.The Right Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P..,Secretary of State for home Affairs.The Right Hon.Tom Shaw, C..B.E . ,M.P. ,Secretary of State forWar.The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.H.B. Lees-Smith, M..P. ,President of the Boardof Education.The Right Hon.A,V. Alexander, M.p.,First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield,Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey,  G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C. ,M.P&apos;. , Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon.Arthur Greenwood, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Christopher Addison,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.The Right Hon.W. Graham, M.P. ,President of theBoard of Trade.The Right Hon.William Adamson, M.P.,Secretary of State forScotland,The Right Hon.Herbert Morrison, M.P.,Minister of Transport...The Right Hon.T. Johnston, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel Sir M..P.A. Hankey, G.C.B. ,G. C.M.G. ,........____  Secretary.
bill the   CHANCELLOR 1.    The Prime Minister and the whole CabinetOP THE EXCHEQUER.welcomed the Chancellor of the Exchequer back after his recent illness.
REDUCTION AND 2. The Cabinet had before them a Note by theLIMITATION of armaments. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theThe Franco- First Lord of the Admiralty (C.B.-106 (31))ItalianPosition. circulating the text of a French Memorandum on the franco-Italian Naval question, together with the(previous reference: draft of a reply.Cabinet 24(31), Con- The actual text of the French proposal was setclus ion 2.)F.Rforth in paragraphs 14 and 15 of their memorandum as follows:-&quot;14. The work of drafting theagreement will be pursued by the experts on the following basis:-&apos; (a) The question of the construc-tion of limitable vessels tobe completed before December3lst,  1936,  is settled as laiddown in the Bases of Agreement.(b) In so far as the constructionof limitable vessels to becompleted only after December31st, 1936, is concerned, and provided a more general settle-ment is not arrived at at theDisarmament Conference of 19 32,there will be no laying down before July 1st,  1935, by which date it will have been possiblefor the Conference which, underArticle 23 of the London naval treaty, is to assemble in thebeginning of that year to giveits decision.On this same date the provisionsof the agreement dealing with the laying down of tonnage will come toan end.In any event France and Italy willbe able to lay down as froo: January1st, 1934, the replacement tonnageof ships which will become overagein 1937 and 1938, as well as thetonnage to be devoted to the comple-tion of the 70,000 tons of capital ships whose construction is author-is ed under Article 1 of the london naval Treaty&apos; .15. In other words, the agreement on the construction to be completed before December 31, 1936, will bearat the same time upon the totalconstruction which can be undertakenbefore July 1st; 1955,&quot;
The draft reply rejected the French proposals,on the ground that their effect would be to impose upon His Majesty&apos;s Government the necessity ofinvoking Article 21 of the London Naval treaty in order largely to increase the tonnage built and building fixed until 31st December, 1936, by theLondon Naval Treaty.    It further contained a .suggestion as to whether a fair solution of thepresent difficulty could not be reached by incorporate-ating in the proposed Declarations the provisionsof the last sentence of Article 19 of the Treaty ofLondon in accordance with the following formula&quot;Subject to any further agreementlimiting naval armaments which may-be reached at the General DisarmamentConference of 1932, or at the naval conference which will take place in1935 in aocordance with Article 23 ofthe Treaty of London, the additionaltonnage which France and Italy may lay down before December 31st, 1936, shallbe the replacement tonnage of vessels which will become overage In 1937,1938 and 1939&quot; .The Cabinet approved the above draft reply.
nil the BUDGET FOR1931-32.(previous reference:Cabinet 22(30), Con-clusion 1.)3 - The Chancellor o^ the exchequer comrrunicatedto the Cabinet full details of his financial pro-posals for the forthcoming Budget, which were approved by the Cabinet.In view of the great importance of secrecy,the financial details, in accordance with precedentare not recorded in the Cabinet Minutes,2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1,April 24,  19 31.

</content>
</cab>
