<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/52/4 images: 43-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret \(i^r,. K tHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cm(73) 26th COPY NOConclusionsCABINET53CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 10 MAY 1973at 11. 00 am present the Rt Hon Edward Heath mp prime minister the Rt Hon Sir Alec Douglas-Home mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St MarylefaooBLord chancellor the Rt Hon Anthony Barber mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Robert Carr mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon Peter Walker mp secretary of State for Trade and industry the Rt Hon The Earl jellicoe lord Privy seal the Rt Hon Maurice Macmillan mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon William Whitelaw mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon James Prior mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Geoffrey Rippon QC mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Gordon Campbell mp secretary of State for Scotland(Items 1 and 2)The Rt Hon John Davies mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon Peter Thomas QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Joseph Godber mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food (Items 1-7)The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC mp minister for Trade and Consumer Affairs
THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO present mr Patrick Jenkin MP The Rt Hon Francis Pym mp chief Secretary, Treasury Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury(Items 7 and 8)Sir Michael Havers QC MPSolicitor GeneralSECRETARIATMr J J B hunt mr H F T smith mr P BermerMr K T barnett mr I T lawman mr D evans contents item                                                   Subject page 1              PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS 12              PAKISTAN BILL 13 OVERSEA affairs middle East 4Spain and Gibraltar 4Icelandic Fisheries Dispute 54             EUROPEAN COMMUNITY AFFAIRS 65 INDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSThe Motor Industry 7British Steel Corporation 7Civil Service 7Harland and Wolff 7Prices 86              NORTHERN IRELAND 97             ROBENS REPORT ON SAFETY AND HEALTH AT WORK 108 REFERENCE TO THE MONOPOLIES COMMISSION OFCERTAIN RESTRICTIVE PRACTICES IN THE PROFESSIONS   13iisecret
PARLIAMENTARY  I, The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the affairs House of Commons during the following week.y Q1


OVERSEAAFFAIRSMiddle east previous reference:CM(73)Conclusions,Minute 23.        THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat the conflict between the Lebanese Government and the palestinian elements in the Lebanon might have widerrepercussions in the Middle East.    The Lebanese Prime minister had resigned; the Syrian Government were threatening to intervene;and our Embassy in Cairo had been warned that President Sadat ofEgypt had meant what he said when he had referred to the need totake military action against Israel.    We had urged the egyptian government to use their best efforts to abate the tension and to help to restore calm in the Lebanon;  and we would maintain these representations.    But President Sadat might not be able to retain control of events for much longer.Spain andGibraltarTHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that atthe end of his discussions with the Spanish Foreign Minister,Senor Lopez Bravo, it had proved impossible to reach agreement on a communique in view of the difficulty of devising a formula todeal with the question of Gibraltar.    Senor Bravo*s political position in Spain was precarious;  and he might feel obliged to saypublicly that he regarded our exchanges on Gibraltar as having cometo an end.    He had suggested, however, that, even if we could not agree to relinquish sovereignty over the Rock itself, we might agreeto cede sovereignty over the isthmus, while continuing to use it,by agreement with the Spanish Government, on the basis of a lease.Although this suggestion presented serious difficulty, we had undertaken to study it further.The Cabinet -1. Took note of the statements by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary.4
IcelandicFisheriesDisputePreviousReference:CM(73) 25thConclusions,Minute 2THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that sincethe failure of the Ministerial discussions in Reykjavik on 3 and4 May there had been no developments in our fisheries dispute with Iceland;  and there had been no recent incidents on the fishinggrounds,THE PRIME MINISTER said that in the course of the discussionswe had indicated that we would be prepared to reduce our catch from170,000 tons, which the International Court of Justice had prescribedas its limit, to 145, 000; but the Icelandic Government had made no concessions in response,,    We must now make it plain, therefore,that, in the absence of any agreement, we regarded the ruling ofthe International Court as holding the field and that the figure of145, 000 tons had been suggested only in the context of a settlement which would be satisfactory to us in other respects.The Cabinet -2, Took note of the statements by thePrime Minister and the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary,5
EUROPEAN 4. THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF LANCASTER saidCOMMUNITY that Community business was now moving into a more activeAFFAIRS phase with the submission by the Commission of proposals on the wide range of subjects covered by the European Summit inOctober 1972.    We had been energetic in pressing the Commissionto develop constructive ideas taking account of United kingdom interests and the proposals as they stood were generally very satisfactory to us.    The next few months would see intensivediscussions which would probably lead to the development of a major negotiating package towards the end of the year.    If wewere to get the best outcome, it would be important to undertakeselective bilateral lobbying with some of our Community partners.In discussion the following points were made -a. The opportunity should be taken during the summerto put to Parliament the more encouraging picture whichwas now emerging of our membership of the Community;this would help to eoisj&amp;fc&amp;racfc some of %kx% criticism wMehhad b*aen made recently.b. It should be our objective to overcome thedifficulties which were being caused to exporters,especially small firms by the complexity of theCustoms arrangements within the Community.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion said that theprogress of work to date on the Summit programme was satisfactory.    The problems arising from the complications of theCommunity Customs procedures should be given further consrdera-tion in consultation with the Confederation of British industries and other organisations concerned.The Cabinet -1.      Took note with approval of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.2.      Invited the Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry, in consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster, to consider how to overcome thedifficulties to exporters caused by the Communitycustoms arrangements.6
5. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT saidthat industrial action in the motor industry had now ceased as aresult of the resumption of work at the British Leyland MotorCorporation bus and truck plants in Lancashire and at Rubery Owen,where the terms of the settlement were subject to the agreementof the Pay Board.    The situation at Ford*s was still confused,since the Am alg am ate d Union of Engineering Workers and theGeneral and Municipal Workers Union had taken no decision attheir meetings earlier that week on the recommendation by thejoint union negotiating team for an official strike.    The transport and General Workers Union were due to consider the recommendationlater that day.    But, meanwhile, mass meetings of workers atsome of the Ford plants had voted to accept the Company&apos;s offer;and it was clear that even the union conveners were divided in theirattitude.    There was some hope that a settlement might be reached on the following day in the negotiations at VauxhalPs.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that thedispute which had led to strike action by 4500 blast-furnace menat the British Steel Corporation^ Scunthorpe works had now been settled and steel production had been resumed.    But there appearedto be no action which the Government might take to assist inresolving the inter-union dispute about representation of the middlemanagement at the Anchor Works.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that the Annual Conference of theCivil and Public Services Association (CPSA) had decided by an arrow majority to ban preparatory work on the pension and otherincreases due to take effect in October unless they were granted the full pay increase which pay research suggested was warranted.It had been announced that morning, however, that the ExecutiveCommittee of the CPSA would meet on the following Thursday to reconsider the matter.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said thatno progress had been made in settling the pay dispute at Harlandand Wolff, which involved interpretation of the existing productivityagreement and the terms of a new settlement under Stage 2 of the pay policy.    The President of the Boilermakers Union,Mr McGarvey, continued to stand firm in recommending acceptanceof the management offer; but local union officials were insisting on payment of the productivity bonus before discussing the Stage 27
settlement.    The Managing Director of Harland and Wolff had nowdismissed the steel-workers because of their refusal to work; buthe had agreed not to dismiss other shipyard workers whose jobswere now at risk.    While it was necessary to support his judgmentthat Mr McGarvey&apos;s policy would prevail, the dispute couldm 3 an while have a serious effect on the Company1 s prospects of returning to profitability.The Cabinet -1, Took note of the statements by the Secretaryof State for Employment, the Lord Privy Seal andthe Secretary of State for Northern Ireland.THE PRIME MINISTER said that public criticism of increases in food prices, which were difficult to control, had increased theimportance of adopting a very firm attitude towards price increasesgenerally.    The justification for all proposals to increase prices should be subjected to the closest scrutiny.    It was an inadequatejustification for a price increase that the level of the priceconcerned had become anomalous in relation to other prices.    TheTrades Union Congress (TUC) had accepted that anomalies on paycaused by the Stage 1 and Stage 2 pay policies could not be resolvedduring Stage 2;  and the same attitude must be adopted on prices.The closest control over price increases was essential if there wasto be any hope of securing the tuc&apos;s agreement to a realistic pay and prices policy in Stage 3.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that the ministerial committee on Counter-Inflationary Measures were about to considera number of cases in which nationalised industries wished to submit proposals for price increases to the Price Commission.    It was argued that, while it would be difficult to avoid accepting that the nationalised industries might proceed with proposals for recoupingallowable cost increases, the helpful attitude of the Chairman ofthe British Steel Corporation as regards the recent increase in steel prices might provide grounds for expecting the Chairmen ofthe other industries concerned to be equally co-operative inminimising the impact of price increases.    In particular, theyshould be pressed to consider the scope for further reductions in costs as an alternative to increases in prices.    It was still not clear, for example, that the Post Office had given sufficientlyserious consideration to the savings on the postal services whichmight be secured by the elimination of the second delivery and of saturday deliveries.
ftThe Cabinet -2.        Took note that the Ministerial Committeeon Counter-Inflationary Measures would giveurgent consideration to the question of price increases by the nationalised industries.northern ireland previous reference:CM(73) 25thConclusions,Minute 46, The Cabinet were informed that the security position continuedto be satisfactory, although it remained to be seen what reactionthere would be to the forthcoming extradition from Northern ireland to the Irish Republic of a man accused of an offence of murderwhich the court had decided was not a &quot;political&quot; crime.    TheNorthern Ireland Constitution Bill was to be published during thefollowing week;  and it was planned to move its Second Reading inthe House of Commons on 24 May.I9
ROB ENS REPORTON SAFETY and health ATWORK7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (CP(73) 60) about the implementation of the Report ofthe Robens Committee on Safety and Health at Work.THE HOME SECRETARY said that the Report had been published in July, 1972, and that a statement had been made at the timeindicating that the Governmenc intended to take early action to achieve its broad objectives.    Since then the Home and social affairs Committee (HS) had been considering how the Report could best be implemented.    There had been general endorsement ofthe broad principles on which it was based, including the proposedconsolidation of the main statutory enactments concerned; but it hadnot been possible to reach agreement on the practical stepsrequired to give effect to them.    There were two main problems -the functions and scope of the proposed new central Authority;  andthe extent and location of Ministerial responsibility for its activities.    HS had concluded that the choice effectively laybetv/een two schemes.    The first, which they had designatedModel A, envisaged an Authority with full executive responsibilityover the whole field of safety and health, including the integrationand management of all the relevant central Inspectorates,    Thesecond (designated Model C) envisaged that Departments would retain some or all of their existing responsibilities relating to the health and safety of workers and of the public, together with theirseparate Inspectorates; but that the new Authority would have aco-ordinating and advisory role over the entire field, togetherwith executive responsibility for the Factory and some otherInspectorates and the central initiative on safety matterstranscending particular industries.    The arguments which hadbeen advanced on behalf of each of these two schemes were summarised in Appendix 4 of CP(73) 60.In discussion it was suggested that Model C would suffice to giveeffect to the broad principles underlying the recommendations inthe Robens Report and would in fact be the preferable solution forthe following main reasons:-i. Model A would cause major administrative problemsif applied to the agricultural industry, to which specialconsiderations applied,.    The Agricultural Ministerstraditionally administered for agriculture a wide range of functions calling for an intimate knowledge of farmingproblems and practice;  and Model A would involve a very unsatisfactory fragmentation of the present agriculturalsafety staffs.
ii. Model A would also be inappropriate in relation tothe Alkali Inspectorate which dealt with a wide range ofenvironmental problems extending well beyond hazardsarising at places of work.    It had long-standingrelationships with local authorities, as well as with theDepartment 0s the Environment, which it would be a mistake to disturb.    Moreover, the Confederation of BritishIndustry (CBI) and the Chemical Industries Association had represented that the Alkali Inspectorate should not be merged in a central Authority for safety and health at work.iii. In relation to schools and hospitals an Authority onthe lines proposed in Model A would be liable to generatepressure, which it might not be practicable to resist, for substantial capital expenditure to improve the standards ofheating and lighting.    Such expenditure, however, could notbe met within existing programmes.    In any event it wasinappropriate for the proposed central Authority to havegeneral powers in relation to hospitals and schools, sinceonly a small proportion of the occupants were employees.iv. It was essential that advice on policy matters shouldcontinue to be available to Departments from theInspectorates,    The Department of Trade and Industry,for example, could not dispense with the advice of the nuclear Installations Inspectorate in relation to a wide range of difficult and important issues affecting the nuclearindustry.On the other hand it was argued that the Robens Report had made out a very strong case on practical grounds for the establishmentof a strong and unified central Authority.    Recent experience -for example, in relation to lead pollution and to an incidentinvolving an explosion in a liquefied petroleum gas store - had shown how unsatisfactory the present fragmented arrangements could be in practice;  and corrective action would be expected by both sides of industry and by the general public.    If it were not taken, it would be suspected that the Government had deferred tovested Departmental interests.    Moreover, Model A alreadyincorporated a number of departures from the recommendations in the Robens Report, which had been made in response torepresentations by the Ministers concerned;  and, if therecommendations were diluted still further, it was doubtful whetherthe Government could claim that the Report was being accepted atall.    Unification of the Inspectorates under the new authority should enhance the standing of the individual Inspectorates withoutsacrificing their respective identities;  and they would continue tobe available to give policy advice to Departments.    Relations with11
outside bodies - for example, those between the Alkali Inspectorateand public health Inspectors - would continue unchanged.    Moreover,in some important respects, of which the administration of theAlkali Acts was one, Model A did not envisage any interference with existing Ministerial responsibility.    The great majority of thencn-Governmental interests which had been consulted favouredacceptance of the recommendations of the Report;  and some would feel that even Model A involved an excessive degree of departure from them.    Acceptance of the Report should yield substantialpolitical advantage, whereas its rejection would involve the loss ofa valuable opportunity for tripartite co-operation;  and any suggestion that the Government were indifferent to the safety and health of workers would be liable to produce a hostile reaction by public opinion aTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that Model C would involve so substantial areduction in the benefits to be expected from the reorganisationthat it might well not be worth disturbing the present arrangements;and they accordingly concluded that the balance of the argumentinclined in favour of adopting Model A.    This, however, need notnecessarily debar limited departures from the detailed proposals in Appendix 2 of CP(73) 60, provided that these were kept to theminimum.    Any Minister who wished to propose such changes should inform the Home Secretary as a matter of urgency, indicating the reasons for his view.    Subject to the outcome of any discussions with the Home Secretary, the Secretary of State for employment should proceed with the consultations which must precede thepreparation of legislation.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the prime minister s summing up of their discussion and invited the Home Secretary, and theSecretary of State for Employment, inconsultation with any other ministers concerned, to proceed accordingly.12
REFERENCE TOTHE MONOPOLIESCOMMISSIONOF CERTAINRESTRICTIVEPRACTICES INTHEPROFESSIONS8. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Home Department (CP(73) 61) about the reference tothe Monopolies Commission of certain restrictive practices in the professions.THE MINISTER FOR TRADE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS recalled that the Government had decided that the Fair Trading Bill should provide for the professions to be exempt from the scope of the restrictive Practices Court and the Consumer Protection AdvisoryCommittee.    This had been on the basis that where appropriatethe Government would refer restrictive practices in the professionsto the Monopolies Commission on the lines that the Commission hadenvisaged in their recent general report on the professions.    Inthe event, the provision in the Bill providing for the exemption ofthe professions had been struck out at Committee Stage.    TheHome and Social Affairs Committee (HS) had agreed that it must be restored at Report Stage, which was being taken the following week,but considered it unlikely that the House of Commons would agreeto the necessary amendment unless the reference of certainprofessional practices to the Monopolies Commission was announced at the same time.    HS had however been unable to agree on the content of the references.    He himself considered that in view ofthe public criticism which, rightly or wrongly, was being directed at the legal profession, one reference must be concerned solelywith the legal profession.    He had suggested that the matters referred should be architects&apos; scale fees, certain practices of thelegal profession (for example, the two-counsel rule and the ban onpartnerships at the Bar) and (when the Fair Trading Bill becamelaw) restrictions on advertising by solicitors.    Alternatively hewould be prepared to accept references relating to all the practicesof architects and of the Bar and to the restrictions on advertisingimposed by a number of professions.THE LORD CHANCELLOR said that it would be undesirable to refer the question of partnerships at the Bar to the Monopolies commission the matter was already being examined by the Bar itself, and in any event a ban would be likely to have serious effects on theadministration of justice.    More fundamentally, it would beobjectionable to make a reference relating only to the legal profession;  to single them out in this way would be unnecessary,inappropriate and damaging to the profession^ standing and image.It would indeed be undesirable to take any action which tended to weaken the independence and integrity of the professions and thus toxisk damage to one of the most valuable features of this country&apos;national life.   He therefore favoured referring only practices which were common to several professions.    A possible coursewould be to refer the scale charges made by architects, surveyorsand perhaps some other professions, and the restrictions on
advertising imposed by accountants, stockbrokers, veterinarysurgeons, the Bar and (when possible) solicitors.    It could alsobe announced that the Government intended to discuss with the law society the possibility of improving the machinery for dealing withcomplaints against solicitors.In discussion it was argued that the overriding objective must beto secure the restoration in the Fair Trading Bill of the provision which had been struck out at Committee Stage,    In order to secure this it was essential that certain professional practices should bereferred to the Monopolies Commission.    It was doubtful whetherit would suffice for all of the references to be in general terms.It was desirable that at least one should relate to the legal profession specifically;  and the reference of the two-counsel ruleseemed likely to be welcome to many Government supporters andto the public generally, while being much less offensive to the legal profession than the reference of the ban on partnerships at the Baror of the Bar generally.    Moreover, it could be stressed that a reference to the Monopolies Commission was intended only toprovide an opportunity for an impartial and independent assessmentand carried no implication that the practices in question wereobjectionable.    It would be helpful if, in addition, it could be announced that the machinery for dealing with complaints againstsolicitors was to be reviewed.THE PRIME  MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the amendment which had been made to the fair Trading Bill in Committee must be reversed at the report stage, and mat to secure this it would be necessary to announce that certain professional practices were being referred to the monopolies Commission,    The matters referred should be thescale fees charged by architects and surveyors, the two-counselrule at the Bar and the restrictions on advertising applied byaccountants, stockbrokers, veterinary surgeons, the Bar and (whenthe Fair Trading Bill had become law) solicitors.    In addition, anannouncement should be made of the Governments intention todiscuss with the Law Society the possibility of improving themachinery for dealing with complaints against solicitors.The Cabinet -1, Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister^ summing up of their discussion.14
2.        Invited the Minister for Trade and consumer Affairs -i. to arrange for references to bemade to the Monopolies Commission, asindicated in the summing up, and for anannouncement xo be made accordingly;ii, in consultation with the LordChancellor, to consider the form and content of the announcement of theproposed discussions with the Law Societyabout the review of machinery for dealingwith complaints against solicitors.Cabinet Office10 May 197315

</content>
</cab>
