<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/18 images: 164-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1942.SECRET. Copy No.   44W.M. (42)18th Conclusions.^ TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 18 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, February 9, 1942, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Minister of Health (Item 1.)The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right. Hon. Lord Reith, Ministerof Works and Buildings and first commissioner of Works (Item 1).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.Contents.minute no. Subject.1      Reconstruction ProblemsProposed Central Planning Authority.2     U.S.S.R.................Page.94[23454-1]
... . 1. The War Cabinet had before, ,theni a, Memorandum by theMinister without Portfolio (W.P. (42)^0). &quot;This Memorandum setbut the recommendations made by the Committee on EeconstructionProblems, on the action which should be taken to fulfil the Govern-ment&apos;s pledge to set up a Central Planning Authority.Discussion turned mainly on the form which the proposedCentral Planning Authority should take. &apos; 1     &apos; -On the one hand, it was pointed out that there was considera$]$pressure, particularly in the House of Lords, for action, on, the lin%proposed in the Ministers paper. The view was expressed that this ^section of opinion, which had made itself strongly felt, would not.be fully satisfied by anything short of the establishment of a separateMinistry of Town and Country Planning.On the other hand, objection was felt to the creation of a new ministry at this juncture.The general view of the War Cabinet was that the existingfunctions in regard to town and country planning should be trans-ferred to the Minister of Works and Buildings, whose title shouldbe altered to &quot; Minister of Works and Planning.&quot;It was also urged that it was hardly necessary, and perhapsmisleading, to describe the proposed body of Ministers as a&quot; National Development Executive,&quot; and that the establishment atthis juncture of a body of this kind, which comprised a number ofMinisters who were fully employed on duties concerned with thewar, was open to criticism.The War Cabinet&apos;s conclusions were as follows : (1) The existing statutory duties in regard to town and country planning, exercised by the Minister of Health inEngland and Wales, should be transferred to theMinister of Works and Buildings, whose title should be changed to &quot;Minister of Works and Planning.&quot; TheMinister&apos;s planning functions should be on the lines proposed in paragraph 6 (vii) of W.P. (42) 20.(2) The Minister of Works and Planning should be assisted bya Committee of Officials representing the Departmentsconcerned. The main functions of this Committee wouldbe to ensure that, so far as possible, the national policyof urban and rural development was carried out as asingle and consistent whole.(3) This body should have access to a Cabinet Committee of theMinisters in charge of the Departments concerned (seeparagraph 6 (iv) of W.P. (42) 20) under the Chairman-ship of the Minister without Portfolio. The functionsof this Cabinet Committee would be to settle matters inregard to town and country planning which could not bedetermined at the official level and on which referenceto the War Cabinet was unnecessary.(4) This Cabinet Committee would supersede the Council ofMinisters sitting under the Chairmanship of theMinister of Works and Buildings, to co-ordinate thework of forward planning with the current administra-tion of existing powers. , 4(5) The Secretary of State for Scotland would be responsiblefor the exercise in Scotland of the functions in regard totown and country planning to be exercised in Englandand Wales by the Minister of Works and Planning.(6) A public announcement should be made on the above lines inreply to Lord Samuel&apos;s Motion on the followingWednesday. The terms of the announcement would, ofcourse, be adjusted to meet the position of Scotland.
2.   The War Cabinet had before them- M&quot;J&apos;;;&apos;!(a) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for. ForeignAffairs (W.P. (42) 69), containing the drafts of two telegrams to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington^;compiled in accordance with the Conclusions of the last meeting of the War Cabinet.(b) A Memorandum by the Minister of Production (W.P.(42) 71).After a short discussion, the War Cabinet -Approved the despatch of the draft telegrams, subject tothe deletion of one paragraph in the first telegram(paragraph 14 (i)).Great George Street, S.W. 1,February 9, 1942.U.S.&amp;R.(previous reference::W.M. (42) 17th\      Conclusions,Minute 5.)(7) Ail announcement of policy for urban and rural cjevelpprment, on the lines set out in Annex &quot; B&quot; to W.P. (42) 20,was approved. :&apos;:&apos;wq&apos;:n,;
..... 1,   The War Cabinet had before, ,thera a Memorandum by theMinister without Portfolio (W.P. (42).20). * This Memorandum setbut the recommendations made by the Committee on reconstruction problems, on the action which should be taken to fulfil the Govern-ment&apos;s pledge to set up a Central Planning Authority.Discussion turned mainly on the form which the proposedCentral Planning Authority should take. &apos;       &apos; \lOn the one hand, it was pointed out&apos; that there was consioler^ipjigpressure, particularly in the House of Lords, for action on, thelines!proposed in the Ministers paper. The view was expressed that this,section of opinion, which had made itself strongly felt, would hotbe fully satisfied by anything short of the establishment of a separateMinistry of Town and Country Planning.On the other hand, objection was felt to the creation of a new ministry at this juncture.The general view of the War Cabinet was that the existingfunctions in regard to town and country planning should be trans-ferred to the Minister of Works and Buildings, whose title shouldbe altered to &quot; Minister of Works and Planning.&quot;It was also urged that it was hardly necessary, and perhapsmisleading, to describe the proposed body of Ministers as a&quot; National Development Executive,&quot; and that the establishment atthis juncture of a body of this kind, which comprised a number ofMinisters who were fully employed on duties concerned with thewar, was open to criticism.The War Cabinefs conclusions were as follows : (1) The existing statutory duties in regard to town and country planning, exercised by the Minister of Health inEngland and Wales, should be transferred to theMinister of Works and Buildings, whose title should be changed to &quot; Minister of Works and Planning.&quot; TheMinisters planning functions should be on the lines proposed in paragraph 6 (vii) of W.P. (42) 20.(2) The Minister of Works and Planning should be assisted bya Committee of Officials representing the Departmentsconcerned. The main functions of this Committee wouldbe to ensure that, so far as possible, the national policyof urban and rural development was carried out as asingle and consistent whole.(3) This body should have access to a Cabinet Committee of theMinisters in charge of the Departments concerned (seeparagraph 6 (iv) of W.P. (42) 20) under the Chairman-ship of the Minister without Portfolio. The functionsof this Cabinet Committee would be to settle matters inregard to town and country planning which could not bedetermined at the official level and on which referenceto the War Cabinet was unnecessary.(4) This Cabinet Committee would supersede the Council ofMinisters sitting under the Chairmanship of theMinister of Works and Buildings, to co-ordinate thework of forward planning with the current administra-tion of existing powers.(5) The Secretary of State for Scotland would be responsiblefor the exercise in Scotland of the functions in regard totown and country planning to be exercised in Englandand Wales by the Minister of Works and Planning.(6) A public announcement should be made on the above lines inreply to Lord Samuel&apos;s Motion on the followingWednesday. The terms of the announcement would, ofcourse, be adjusted to meet the position of Scotland.BeopnstraotionProposedCentralPlanningAuthority.(previous reference:w;m; iii) nthConclusions, &apos;Minute 5.)
(7) An announcement of policy for urban and rural desvelpp-ment, on the lines set out in Annex &quot; B&quot; to W.P. (42) 20,was approved.2.   The War Cabinet had before them- :.....\[(a) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (W.P. (42) 69), containing the drafts of two telegrams to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington^:compiled in accordance with the Conclusions of the last meeting of the War Cabinet.(6) A Memorandum by the Minister of Production (W.P.(42) 71).After a short discussion, the War Cabinet -Approved the despatch of the draft telegrams, subject tothe deletion of one paragraph in the first telegram(paragraph 14 (i)).Great George Street, S.W. 1,February 9, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
