<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/283/0 images: 140-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                                    I (Go(THIS DOCUrlSIIT IS TH3 PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC IAJE3TY&apos;S (K)vT3RHHEHT) 5   G   IL Ta CP. 42 (59).                                   COPY HQ.   3-                       CAB I IT E T.                COhPIJITSAIIOP FOR PEACB-TIPE            IITJURIES TO MBM3BRS OF CIVIL DEPTJ1TCE                         SERVICES.            Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seala      1.    As  foreshadowed in my previous memorandum (CP. 26 (59))      on the question of pay in time of war for volunteers serving      whole-time in civil defence, I now put forward proposals for      compensation in respect of death or disablement attributable      to injuries sustained by volunteers in the course of peace-      time training.   In view of the undertakings which I have      given both i?:i the House of Commons and to the Trades Union      Congress General Council a very early announcement of our      intentions is essential.    .  2.    In  dealing with this matter we do not start with a clean      sheet.   Since 1957, Insurance schemes have been in operation      to cover risks during training to A.3.P. volunteers and      Auxiliary Firemen.   Local Authorities have been encouraged      to take  out special Policies for this purpose and their      expenditure on premium payments ranks for grant from the      Exchequer.   For Auxiliary Firemen, whose training is longer      and involves more serious risks, the premium is 3/- per head      per annum, and the insurance policy has been generally adopted      by Local Authorities:  for A.R-P volunteers the premium is 6d.      per head per annum, and the benefits available are substantially      less than those offered to the Auxiliary Firemen.   this policy      has not been so widely taken up.      5.    The terms of these two Policies are for convenience set      out in parallel below.
A..R.P. Volunteer1.		auxiliary 1 i ary xii reman.Death	 500	 1,000Loss of sight in &quot;both eyes	 500	 1,000Loss of two limbs	 500	 1,000Loss of one limb and sight in one eye	 500	 1,000Loss of sight in one eye	 250	 500Loss of ore limb	 250	 500Total disablement (where not already-covered by lump sum payment)	 5 a week limited to 52 weekSc	 3 a week for 52 weeks and thereafter  2 a week for 10 further years0Permanent partial disablement	Nil, apart from lump sumso	Some small allowance in cases not covered by lump sums, Reimbursement of reasonable medical feesoAn examination of	the existing	Insurance Policiesreveals serious defects^   It has been found that with  theextension of A.R.P. training now necessary the terms defining the conditions under which injury must be sustained if  it isto be accepted for compensation are too narrowly drawn,  andthe same point arises in lesser degree in the case of auxillary Firemen.   But more serious is the absence of proper cover for permanent disablement whether total or partial.   If, therefore, the present arrangements forsecuring cover by Insurance Policies taken out by LocalAuthorities, and aided by Exchequer grant, were to becontinued, it would be necessary to see that the coverwas appropriately extended, with a consequent increase  inpremium and grant payment.   On the assumption that some250,000 Auxiliary Firemen have to be covered at 3/- a headand 1,500,000 A.R.P. Volunteers, including reserves-, at say
2/- a head, the total annual premium hill would amount  to 187,500, on which some  125,000 would he payable  as  grant.Having regard to the limited number of claims likely  to arise, so far as can be judged by past experience,  such-grant payment would be wasteful in the extreme, and Ipropose accordingly that the risks should be carried  by theGovernment.5.   If this proposal is adopted, it becomes necessary  toconsider what terms the Government should offer.    two considerations are, I suggest, axiomatic - (l) We  must  offergenuine cover, i.e. make good the deficiencies of  theexisting Policy terms;  (2) we cannot at this date, and atthis juncture, offer terms that taken as a whole are  less favourable than those which large numbers of volunteersalready enrolled have been led to expect, and. which have forsome time now been accepted by the Government for  purposesof grant.     Moreover, we shall, in my view, be most likely to escape possible criticism and the difficulties that may arise from &quot;repercussions&quot; on other rates of compensation nowpayable in other cases, e.g. compensation for peace-timeinjuries in the Services or Workmen1s compensation, if  wecan represent that the Government are in effect talcing overexisting commitments, but with such modifications as arenecessary to give adequate cover and are, therefore,  ingeneral more beneficial to the volunteers.   I should propose accordingly that, if and when the Government takeover compensation for these volunteers, the terras that have already been offered under the Insurance Policyschemes should be amended as indicated in the following paragraphs.
6 (a)   &apos;7e should retain the principle of lump sura payments on death.   These payments are attractive and v/ell understood,and probabl3r more acceptable in many cases than pension termssuch as are available for the widow of a Territorial.   In that case the widow, if she is under 40, is not incapacitated andis without dependent children, receives 10/6 a week.    From40 to 60 the allowance is 17/6 a week and at 50 is 20/- aweeko   There is an additional allowance for dependent children of 5/- a week per child.   But in all cases  the widow loses any right to pension under the contributory pensions Act, and her pension allowance, of course, ceaseson re-marriageo   (b)    Under the terms of the Insurance Policies theselump sum payments are payable to the deceased&apos;s estate without regard to any question of the needs of dependants.   I proposethat they should be confined to dependants and scaled downaccording to need.   At the same time I should propose thatthe maximum payment on death in respect of the A.P.P.volunteer should be increased from  500 to  600, the  maximumpayable to a widow with children under the Workmen&apos;s  Compen-sation Act,   This change will be essential if the suggestionI make later in this memorandum is accepted,   (c)    The effect of my proposals on these lump surapayments may be shown as follows:-Compensation Payment for Deaths      A.R.P. Volunteer.     AuxAuxiliary Firemen.For widow with oneor more dependent children 600 1,000For widow withoutdependent children 400 700For a motherlessdependent child orchildren 500 500For other relativeswholly or mainlydependentnot exceeding  500not exceeding 5500
                                                      Id ^7.   The disparity between the payments proposed for thefiremen and for the ..0ihp, volunteer respectively will, ofcourse, be challenged, and indeed has already beenchallenged in informal conference with me by bothrepresentatives of the T.U.C General Council and of theNational Confederation of Employers&apos; Organisations0   Bothsides have emphasized that,  although admittedly the risksin the two cases may he very different, the fact of death-is precisely the same for the widow who is left, whethershe is the widow of an auxiliary fireman or of an A.R.P.volunteer..80   If it were possible,  I am clear that it would bedesirable to avoid this anomaly, but the solutions proposedby the T.U.C. on the one hand and by the Employers on the&apos;other, have not unnaturally been diametrically opposedoThe T.U.G. have urged that the terms of the A.R.P. volunteershould be raised to the level of those for the fireman andthe National Confederation has suggested that the fireman&apos;rate should be scaled down to the level of that of theA..E.P0 volunteer.9.   While I should have been glad to have avoided this difficulty, I am clear that at this date it is impossibleto withdraw the higher figure now approved in the case offiremen, which has formed part of the terms on which alreadysome 100,000 men have been enrolled;  we cannot offerbenefits materially lower than those that have already been declared.   On the other hand, I am advised that to bringthe A.R.P. volunteer up to the same level would have repercussions which would be highly embarrassing to theDefence Departments both directly in regard to the auxiliary Forces, and indirectly in regard to the regular forces.   There would further be a substantial risk of serious repercussions on the proposed war terms foruniform and civilian personnelo
                                                      1 U iJ10.   In these circumstances I think we must abide by thedifference in the terms offered in case of death to thesetwo classes of volunteer, and that the difference must be defended on the grounds  -     (a) that we are taking over existing commitments and         adjusting the terms as reasonably as we can, and     (b) that the risks which auxiliary firemen are called         upon to face are definitely far higher than those         in A.P.P. service,  and that more attractive terms         of compensation may properly be made available.     The propriety of relating these death payments in some measure to family needs will, I think, be generally-accepted.11.   Apart from this, I think that the terms offered mayconveniently be aligned to secure equality of treatment asbetween the Auxiliary Fireman and the A.S.P. volunteer.   Itv/ould be possible, in my view, to withdraw the lump sumsnow payable for certain specified injuries representingeither total disablement or a measure of permanent partialdisablement, provided that we offer adequate pension ratesin lieu.   We cannot, however, entirely withdraw thecompensation rate of  3 a week now payable for a period of12 months in both cases for total disablement.     After careful consideration of the problem in all. its aspects I have come to the conclusion that the best  solutionwill be found to lie in the adoption of the following terms,to be applied both to A.R.P. volunteers and to AuxiliaryFiremen:-     Total disablement -  3 a week for six months and thereafter the following pension rates, which are slightly lower than those now contemplated under the War Code:-
          30/- a week for a single man.          35/- a week for a man with wifea          40/- a week for a man with wife               and one dependent child.          With an additional allowance of 3/-            a week for each additional            .dependent child up to a maximum            total allowance of 49/- a week.     For permanent partial disablement proportionate rates would be paid, disablement being assessed on the degree  of physical incapacity and a percentage scale  applied to theabove rates (excluding the  3 a week) as in the case of similar Service pensions.,     In addition, allowance must be made for the re-imbursement of reasonable medical expenses incurred duringthe initial period of disability.12.   In so far as A.H.P. volunteers are concerned Ianticipate no difficulty about substituting the terms nowproposed for those of the existing Policy,  but in the caseof Auxiliary Firemen I am advised that objection may beraised by men already enrolled,,   The terms already offeredunder the Policy scheme with a range of substantial lumpsuras have been a definite factor in recruitment, and while have no doubt that the revised terms proposed arereasonable, and taking the long view possibly better thanthose available under the Policy, I propose, in order toavoid criticism or misunderstanding, that Firemen alreadyenrolled should be given the option of retaining theirexisting terms if they so desire.13.   In submitting these proposals I must bring to thenotice of my colleagues the possible repercussions of therates I- propose on other compensation rates payable for peace-time  injuries in the Services and under Worlmien&apos;sCompensati on,
     The compensation rates payable in peace to  members  ofthe armed forces of the Crown (regular or auxiliary)  are insome respects less favourable than those which I am nowrecommending for application to A.P.P. personnel,  and mycolleagues will no doubt desire to have these differencesexamined.   I am advised, however,  that an assimilation  ofthe services&apos; code to that which I am now proposing wouldnot cost more than  80,000 a year.    This is, o:? course,very considerably less than the premium payments to whichI have referred in paragraph 4 above, and I suggest thatthe justification and necessity of any such assimilationshould be left for interdepartmental settlement in theusual way.   I understand that it is not anticipated tha.there need be any repercussion upon the war rates ofcompensation for the armed forces,  except that the lump sum payments on death, particularly to firemen,  might provoke a claim for some modification of these rates.14.   The comparison with Workmen&apos;s Compensation assumesimportance as this is now under review and there will be pressure to improve the rates available under the Act.The maximum rate payable for total disability is 30/- a  week,and the more favourable rates I propose for compensation to injured volunteers with family responsibilities will  no doubt be quoted in support of any attack on Workmen&apos;compensation rates.   In my view, however, the differencecan properly be defended or. the grounds that the Workmanruns certain risks at his occupation as part of hisjob for which he is being paid.   The A.H.P. volunteer orAuxiliary Fireman on the other hand is coming forward andin his own time and without pay is submitting himself to additional risks that he would not otherwise undergoin order to  assist the cause of national defence.   Heis especially entitled,  therefore, to generous treatment.
         15.   There remains one further point which calls for         consideration.   It appears probable that an employee taking         training during working hours in connection with A.R.P,         precautions at his place of work would  have a claim in case         of injury to compensation under the Workmen&apos;s Compensation         Act.    It is possible that a claim might lie even in a case         where the training was taken outside working hours and off         the employer&apos;s premises, if taken at the request of, or by         the direction of the employer.    It  is  clearly desirable to         avoid,  if possible, any likelihood of double entitlement         to compensation,         16.   As it is the Government1s intention to impose a         statutory duty upon employers to make suitable provision for         the protection of their workpeople, and as part of that         provision will ential the training of a number of their         employees in A.R.P., it would seem reasonable that compensa-         tion for any injuries incurred in such  training should be         taken over by the Government.   This would necessitate         legislation to extinguish the right  to  claim in such cases         under the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act and to substitute         Government Compensation.   This might be dealt with by an         appropriate clause in the forthcoming Bill,   It is clear         that if Government Compensation were to be substituted         in these cases for Workmen&apos;s Compensation, the maximum         payment in case of death could not be less than  600, being         the maximum available under,the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act.         17.   Schedules are attached as Appendices for convenience         of reference showing the terms at present in force under         the Insurance Policy Schemes as compared with those I have         suggested.                                          (Intd.)  J.A.10th February, 1939.
Compensation.A.R.P. Volunteers,Present Policy Terms.Proposed Terms.   Compensation for bodily injurycaused solely &quot;by  violent  accidentalexternal and visible means whilst the insured as a  volunteer traineeunder the Home Office Anti-GasTraining Soheme is in attendance fortraining.   Death or disablement directlyattributable to Air Raid Precautionstraining.Death .........____..........  500Total and irrecoverable loss   of sight in both eyes ...  500Loss of two limbs, above   wrist or ankle ..........  500Loss of one limb and one   eye..................... 500Total and irrecoverable loss   of sight in one eye .....  250Loss of one limb...........Temporary total disablement 250   3a week for 52weeksonly.Death (a)  600 payable to widow with            dependent child or children:             400 to widow without            dependent child.      (b)  300 payable in respeot of            motherless dependent child            or children.      (o) Compensation to other relatives             wholly or mainly dependent,             if no payment under (a) or             (b) up to a maximum of  300.Total Disablement.   3 a week for 26             weeks and thereafter 30/-             a week for a single man,             35/- a week for a man with             wife, 40/- a week for a             man with wife and one child:             with 3/- a week for each             additional dependent child             up to a maximum of 49/-             a week.          Permanent partial disablement             Proportionate rates:             disablement to be assessed             on the degree of physical             incapacity and a percentage             scale applied to the rates             shown above other than the              3 a week.          Reimbursement of reasonable             medical fees.Compensation for Women at 2/3rds above rates.
   Compensation.Auxiliary Firemen.Present Policy Scheme.Proposed Terras.Bodily injury caused solely by violentaccidental and visible means  whilst in attendance for training................   Death.........................  1000   Total and irrecoverable loss of     sight in both eyes .........   1000   Total loss of both hands or     both feet, or of one hand and     one foot..................    1000   Total loss of one hand or one     foot and total loss of sight     in one eye ...............      500Total loss of one hand or one  foot ....................Total disablement from  following occupation ....Permanent total and absolute  disablement ............. 500    3 a week  to a limit of52 weeks. 100 perannum for aperiod not .exceeding 10years afterone year, at 3 a week.   Death or disablement directly   attributable to Auxiliary Fire   Service training.Death  (a)  1000payable to widow           with dependent child or           children:  700 to           widow without dependent           child,       (b)  500 payable in respect           of motherless dependent           child or children,       (c) Compensation to other           relatives wholly or           mainly dependent, if no           payment under (a) or (b)           up to a maximum of  500.Total disablement  3 a week for 26           weeks, and thereafter           30/- a week for a single           man, 35/- a week for a           man with wife, 40/- a           week for a man with wife           and one child:  with 3/-           a week for each additional           dependent child up to a           maximum of 49/- a week.Some limited allowance for  permanent partial disability.Reimbursement of reasonable  medical fees.Permanent partialdisablement proportionaterates: disablement to heassessed on the degreeof physical incapacityand a percentage scaleapplied to the ratesshown above other thanthe  3 a week.Reimbursement of reasonable medical fees.

</content>
</cab>
