<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/283/0 images: 160-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1939.SECRET.dp. m (39).CABINET.CONGRESS AND THE INDIAN STATES.POSSIBILITIES OF  RESIGNATION  OF CONGRESS  MINISTRIES  IN  BRITISH                        INDIAN PROVINCES.              Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.      DEVELOPMENT  OF  CONGRESS INSPIRED  AGITATION  IN THE  STATES.    UNDER  the  provisions  of the  Government  of  India  Act,  1935,  theLegislature in the proposed Federation of India will be so composed that it willbe impossible  for  the Congress Party to secure an absolute majority in either house unless they can capture a substantial number of the seats allotted either tothe Moslem community or to the Indian States.  As there is no possibility of theirsecuring many Moslem seats, the Congress are, by the organisation of agitation,bringing pressure to bear upon  the Rulers of the Indian States to agree thattheir  representatives shall be chosen by election  instead of by nomination.  TheAct itself is silent as to the method of selection, but it was quite clear at the timeof the Joint Committee  that the great majority of  States intended to nominatetheir  representatives and would accept no other solution.    The recent trend of events suggests that while the right wing of the Congresscondemn the federal provisions of the Act equally with the left wing, they wouldbe willing  to enter the Federation if they were satisfied that they could secure amajority in the Federal Legislature, their belief being apparently that they could make it very difficult, if not impossible, in such circumstances for the Governor-General to exercise the special powers vested in him by the Government of india act.  Hence the concerted agitation for the introduction of responsible govern-ment  in the States which is a disconcerting feature of the present situation, the expectation being that with  the representative government once established, theelection  instead of the  nomination of  States&apos;  representatives  in  the federal legislature would necessarily follow.  The more extreme elements in the  party on  the  other  hand  are  more  concerned to make  Federation of the type con-templated  an impossibility.    2.  A certain  number of States at present possesses representative institu-tionsof varying  degrees and types,  but  their  functions  are generally purelyadvisory.   Under pressure from the Congress, however, some Rulers have already expressed  their  intention, however  reluctantly,  of introducing  more  advancedforms of representative  government.   The agitation has  for the most part been based ostensibly on local grievances, but even  when these have been  redressedit has in many cases continued with responsible government as its  overt object.At first groups of persons from British India  invaded the States to encourageagitation,  but there  has very  recently been some  tendency on the part of theCongress Working Committee to discourage  such invasions and to recommendthat agitation should be confined to the subjects of the States themselves.  Butthis has not prevented individual Congress leaders from visiting certain states to direct the agitation.       [18643  I                                                      jjCopy No.
     J  Trouble started-m Mysore,  where following a riot in April  1938 the Dewan reached an agreement with Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel, one of Mr.  Gandhi&apos;s chief  lieutenants, and  a committee including local Congress sympathisers was set  up to consider constitutional  advance  in the State and is still sitting Agitation then developed in a number of small States in the Deccan, which, as they are much interspersed with British territory, were in a specially vulnerable position,  and have now, generally  speaking, accepted in  principle the  necessity of going some considerable way  towards meeting  Congress  demands in  the development of representative institutions.  One of the worse affected areas has been the Orissa States, where, owing to the backward character of the population, agitation has been accompanied by, no little  violence.  The  situation here was brought to a  head  by the murder in Ranpur by a mob on the 5th January of Major Bazalgette,  the Political Agent in charge of these States.   The incident was deeply deplored in the Indian  press, including Congress newspapers, whose regret, however, was not uninspired by the realisation of the adverse effect of the incident on their own cause.   A substantial body of troops is now quartered in the  affected area.   In Nandgaon, a small State surrounded by territory of  the Central Provinces,  agitation  has developed out of a mill strike, and troops have also had to be sent to this State.  In Rajkot, a small State in Western India, the Ruler, who is  of very poor quality, reached an agreement with Vallabhbhai Patel on the 25th December behind the back of his Dewan (an ex-I.C.S. officer who has since resigned), conceding much of  the Congress demands at the time.  He has since fallen out with Patel and agitation in his State has  recommenced. He has been promised the support  of the Paramount Power in resisting  improper pressure.   There has also  been agitation in Hyderabad, organised  by Hindu communal bodies with  some assistance  from  Congress,  against the Moslem dynasty. . Owing to increasing symptoms of its communal character the Congress Working  Committee have recently  discouraged civil disobedience in this  case. In Travancore, agitation against a  Brahmin Dewan has been carried  out by  the State Congress, which is largely a Christian organisation.  There are threats of trouble in many other States. v:  -  4.  The  attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government  towards the question of constitutional  reform in the  States was  defined by me in  a speech on  the 27th May, 1938, and was  further  elucidated in answers  given to  questions in  the House of Commons  on the 21st February, 1938, and the 16th December, 1938, and in a speech made by the Viceroy in Calcutta on the 19th December.  Copies of these pronouncements are attached.  The policy which we have adopted is, briefly stated, that while the Paramount Power will not stand in the way of the intro- duction of changes  in the form  of  Government in the States, the  nature of the changes is a matter  for the Rulers themselves;  and further that, while  the Rulerswill be required to remedy misgovernment where found to exist, they will be given the protection to which they are entitled under their treaties against violence and disorder.  In  pursuance of this policy the Political Department in India have received instructions to urge on Rulers generally prompt redress of administrative and  fiscal  grievances in the States.     5.  The Congress have now directed their attention to Rajputana, the strong-hold of the States.  A Praja Mandal, in effect a Congress Party, was formed in Jaipur with Jamnalal Bajaj, a Jaipur subject and a member of the Congress Working  Committee, as Chairman.  As elsewhere,  it  professes to exist  for economic  as well as  political objects, and it recently attempted  to  usurp inconnection with famine relief measures some of the functions of the  State Govern-ment.:  The Jaipur Government have already declined to recognise the Mandaland  have  issued a warning to its members.   They have  also banned JamnalalBajaj from.Jaipur.  Jamnalal Bajaj entered the State in defiance of this ban on the  1st February and again on the 7th  February.   On  each  occasion he  was arrested and  deported to British India.  Mr. Gandhi has made a number of statements supporting his lieutenant  in his action  and indicating that he maymake an all-India issue, of the Jaipur case.   The Maharaja of Jaipur has  for some years employed as his Dewan a retired officer of the Indian Political Serviceand  it would  appear from these statements that Mr.  Gandhi may take the line that this Dewan, being a European British officer, is really the agent of the crown representative, who can and should instruct him to lift the ban on JamnalalBajaj.  There is, of course, no substance in any such contention.
    6.  The Viceroy  considers that he must advise States, particularly Jaipurand Rajkot, who are known to be under improper pressure from Congress, to stand firm and that he must promise them any necessary support, even at the risk of theCongress Working Committee  calling out Congress Provincial Ministries as a protest and of the consequent necessity of applying the breakdown  clause of theGovernment of India Act in the Provinces affected.  I have informed the Viceroythat he may count on my support in this attitude.   I am indeed in full agreementwith him that the results of a  Congress success in Jaipur would be that Rulersgenerally would assume that the Paramount Power could no longer be relied onto support  them and that&apos;their  safest course was to secure the best terms possible from the Congress while it was  possible to do so.   One result of this  would almost certainly be that, in the event of a war, the States would become a liability insteadof an asset.    7.  The  general  grounds which justify the  policy which we  are pursuingin regard  to Congress agitation in the States are broadly as follows.  It  is a fundamental part of the relationship between the Paramount Power and theStates that it shall protect them against internal disorder or external aggression.It follows  from this  that it has a  corresponding  right which it has frequentlyexercised in the past  (as in Alwar and Nabha) to intervene in States to  preventoppression. But this right has not been interpreted in the past as  requiring the paramount Power to call  upon the  Rulers  to  keep pace with constitutional changes in British India.  In regard to the form  of their government they havebeen treated  as  sovereign Rulers.   Conditions necessarily vary greatly betweenState and  State and methods  of  government  suitable to one State would notsuit all.  Some of those which have been subjected to most pressure are largelyinhabited  by aboriginals  and,  if they were part  of  British India, would havebeen scheduled under the  Government of India Act as excluded areas under the personal administration  of Provincial Governors.  Others  of them, such  asMysore and Baroda, are among the most advanced States, politically and adminis-tratively, in  India.   The recently  declared policy of the Paramount Power  tobe neutral  on the question of constitutional advance in the States freely initiated by Rulers, does not affect its obligation to prevent improper pressure being broughtto bear upon them by other agencies external to the States to change their formof government.                       PROBABLE ACTION OF CONGRESS.    8.  No considered appreciation has yet reached me from  the Viceroy of theeffects of a conflict over the States on the constitutional  position in the BritishIndian  provinces. The three  questions that  have to be answered are :     (1)  whether Gandhi is likely to call out the Provincial Governments in the           Congress   Provinces unless  pressure is put  on Jaipur  to meet his           wishes,    (2)  whether they will obey,    (3)  whether the  position is  likely to be  affected by the  recent re-election           of S. C. Bose (the left-wing leader) as President of the Congress Party           in opposition  to Mr.  Gandhi&apos;s candidate.    9.  Indications as to (1) above are in the main to be drawn from the variousstatements that  have been made  by Mr.  Gandhi  himself  and  the working committee in the past month or two.   These  have shown a certain variation  oftendency.   On the 3rd December Mr. Gandhi  in his own paper Harijan warned the Paramount  Power of the serious consequences of any interference with the intentions  of States Rulers to  grant responsible government to their people.  Aweek  later another article endorsed the view  that outsiders should keep out  ofthe satyagraha movements in Rajkot and Hyderabad and this was followed  bya  resolution  of  the Working  Committee drafted by  Mr. Gandhi-expressing&quot; regret at the attempt of the Rulers to call in the help of the British government against their own people,&quot; claiming on behalf of Congress  a right  to protect the States&apos; people against forces  lent by the British and asserting its right and duty to guide the people of the States, while at  the  same time maintaining the inadvisability of  other than States&apos; people taking part in civil disobediencemovements in the States.   The article of the  3rd December advised the Britishthat if they did not accept its  warning &quot; they will precipitate a first-class crisis.whose magnitude it is difficult to  foretell.&quot;      [18643]                                                    B 2
    10.  Further statements in Mr. Gandhi&apos;s own paper and elsewhere appearedduring January.  Those immediately following the murder of Major Bazalgettewere mainly confined to expressions of sympathy, but more recently there appearedfresh evidences of an intention to join issue with the Paramount Power.  Articleson Rajkot on the  7th January  and on Jaipur on the 14th January sought toencourage resentment against British officials in the States, and  finally, afterthe intimation that  Jamnalal Bajaj  would take  up the challenge  of Jaipur atthe beginning  of February, a personal letter from  Mr. Gandhi  was receivedby Lord Linlithgow which, while characteristically vague, leaves little doubt aboutthe strength of his views as to the legitimacy of agitation in States for responsible government.  .  11.  From all that has been said, coupled with the fact that Jamnalal Bajajhas now made his challenge to the Jaipur authorities, and, more important still,Mrs. Gandhi has gone  to Rajkot to  offer Satyagraha and has been arrested, itis clear  that  there  is  a  substantial risk  that  Mr.  Gandhi and  the working committee intend  to  press this conflict  to  the  extent  of withdrawing  theirMinistries, however  illogical such a course of action might be.    12.  The Viceroy has obtained the opinions of the provincial Governors as tothe readiness of the Congress Ministries to obey such a summons.  The Governorsare agreed that Ministers would obey however reluctantly though one  or twoof them discount the likelihood of the contingency arising.  The Governors of theCentral Provinces and Assam have not yet replied.    13.  It remains to  consider  the possible effect of the re-election of S. C. Boseto the  Presidency of the Congress, and in particular  the possibility of a  conflict between  Mr.  Gandhi and the  right wing Congress men at present in control of congress on  the one hand and  the left wing element under Bose  on the other.On the one hand, it  is possible that Mr. Gandhi and  the right wing of Congressmay seize the opportunity to launch  a fight with the British on an issue whichmay serve to  stave off  a  split in the ranks of the party.   On the other hand,they may be deterred by the consideration that Congress, divided on other issues,must be at a disadvantage in such a conflict. -    14.  However that may be, the conclusions arrived at by myself and theViceroj&apos; as explained in this Memorandum  may be summed up as follows :     (1) We are bound by our treaty obligations to the States to support them.     (2) If we failed to support the Rulers now a land-slide would be inevitable,           the Rulers seeking to make their peace with the Congress while there           is time.     (3) We cannot  allow ourselves to be influenced by  the resignation of the           Governments on a matter  with which, under the Government of India           Act, they have no concern.  Moreover, from a purely tactical point of           view, I  am  disposed to  think that the present issue is advantageous           from  the British point  of view, assuming  that  conflict  with the           Congress is inevitable sooner or later, for  the following  reasons :-           (a) If Ministries resign upon this ground, there  are likely to  be now,                 as there were in  1937, reactions in the Provinces among those                 who  are  more closely  concerned with  provincial than with                 all-India interests.           (b) The Moslem League, owing to their fears of Congress domination,                 are tending to support the cause of the States.           (c) The  murder  of Major  Bazalgette  has  aroused considerable                 sympathy both in India and here,  and has detracted seriously                  from the claims of the Congress that they are pursuing  a policy                  of non-violence.     I shall  be glad to know, therefore, whether  I  have the agreement of my colleagues in the policy which the Viceroy and I are pursuing.February 9, 1939.
APPENDIX.         Speech by the Secretary of State for India oh May 27, 1938.    I CAN understand the views of those who will represent the Provinces inthe Federation as  a  result of election, that some element of popular choice, as distinct from  nomination, should enter into the Selection of  the States&apos; repre-sentatives.  Well, that is for the Princes themselves to decide.  There is nothing in the Act to  prevent  it; nor will the Paramount Power be found standing inthe way of any Prince who seeks to temper the rigid autocracy of bygone  dayswith a more liberal system.  REPLY TO A QUESTION IN  THE HOUSE OF COMMONS ON FEBRUARY 21, 1938.                                 Question.    2.  Captain Heilgers asked the Under-Secretary of State for India whether his attention has been drawn to the public  statement of the Dewan of Travancoreto the effect that the power of-the ruler of an Indian State to grant measures of responsible government is restricted by the necessity of obtaining the  explicitconsent of the Paramount  Power; and  what  is the policy of His  Majesty&apos;sGovernment in this matter?                                  Answer.    Earl Winterton: I have seen a report of the statement.  It is not the policyof the Paramount Power in ordinary circumstances to intervene in the internal administration of  full-powered States. In particular, I can assure my hon. andgallant Friend that the Paramount Power would certainly not obstruct proposalsfor constitutional advance initiated by the Ruler.  The consent of the ParamountPower has not been required before such advances have been approved by variousPrinces, nor, so far as I  am aware,  has  it been sought in such matters.  the paramount  Power would  in ordinary circumstances confine itself to tenderingadvice when consulted.      REPLY TO  A  NON-ORAL QUESTION IN  THE HOUSE OF COMMONS ON                            DECEMBER 16, 1938.                                 Question.    Sir  John  Wardlaw-Milne, To  ask  the  Under-Secretary  of  State  forIndia in what way  the attitude of His  Majesty&apos;s Government towards constitu-tional reform in Indian States has recently been modified; and what is the policyof His Majesty&apos;s Government towards  the present agitation in various indian states.                                 Answer.    His  Majesty&apos;s Government adhere fully to  the Statement made by my NobleFriend the Member for Horsham in his reply on  the 21st February last on thissubject.  The Paramount Power  will not obstruct proposals for constitutional advance  initiated by Rulers.   But His Majesty&apos;s  Government have no intentionof bringing any form of  pressure to  bear upon them  to initiate constitutional changes.  It rests with the Rulers themselves to decide what form of government they should adopt in the diverse conditions of Indian States.    With  regard to the  second  part of the question, the  obligations of  the paramount Power to the States extend to protecting Rulers against violence and disorder  and to  advising and assisting Rulers  in remedying such  legitimategrievances  of their subjects as may be found to exist.
EXTRACT  FROM  VICEROY&apos;S  SPEECH TO  ASSOCIATED CHAMBER OF COMMERCE  IN:                         INDIA, DECEMBER&apos; 19, 1938.     &quot;The decision whether or not to accede to the federation of India falls tobe taken  at  a time  when  the minds of many rulers are preoccupied with  thequestion  of  determining the extent to which ideas,  germinated in  different conditions and  arising from wholly  different  circumstances,  are capable  ofassimilation  with the background of  their traditions and responsibilities.     &quot; I realise the difficulty of that problem none the less great because, whilethe advice and  assistance  of the Paramount Power is always available to  the rulers, it must rest with the rulers themselves to decide  what form of government they should adopt in the diverse  conditions of the Indian States.     &quot; And as the Secretary of State again made clear in the last few days, whilethe Paramount  Power will not obstruct  proposals for  constitutional advanceinitiated by  the rulers, His Majesty&apos;s Government has no intention of bringingany form of pressure to bear upon them to initiate constitutional changes. I haveno need to remind you of the close and  active interest which so many rulers havealready displayed in this question.  But in a field in  which, for historical andother reasons, such wide differences  in  conditions exist,  generalisations  aredangerous and misleading.              Collaboration and Participation of  States necessary.     &quot;The nature of any internal adjustment, the checks and balances appro-appropriately to be applied,  cannot wisely in all circumstances be  the same, and  thefullest weight must be given to all relevant factors by those on whom responsibilitydirectly falls.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
