<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 22-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. 7AR C7QINET.G.T. 808U-ITY OP CONTROL OF RAILWAY FACILITIES[ IN AMERICA.(Copy of letter dated 22nd.May, I917 from Ministerof Munitions to the Secretary, War Cabinet).Dear Sir Maurice Hahkey,Before replying to Mr*Lalfour1s telegramof Hay 17th. I shall be glad if you will have the enclosedmemorandum considered by the Cabinet as soon as possible.The matter is urgent and would only taks a few minutes.The Shipping Controller is interested.Yours sincerely,&apos;  (Sgd)    C. ADM SON.
ENCLOSURE 1.With reference to Hr..Bt\lfourTs Cable to the War Cabinet ofHay 17th. I Fish to submit the following remarks for theconsideration of the War Cabinet :-I regard it as essential that all British organisa-tions in America should be placed under the control of aman of Ex-cabinet rank of considerable standing and withadministrative experience.     He would be responsible forthe general direction end co-ordination of ail our differentagencies and in a position to negotiate effectively withthe ^nerican Government end the allied representatives inthe United States, always, of course, being in communicationwith out Ambassador.In principle I a.r;ree y^ith Mr. Be If our that thereshould be unity of control of all rt.il feeilities end thatthe traffic organisation should not leave a gap between rail-ways and ships.     I regret, however, that I am not satisfiedthat Captain Guthric is the right man to be at the heed ofthis organisation, though presumably competent to deal withthe snipping side.     I have found that llr. Jap;.&quot;)1 s orgenisetio;.using Wr.I:-err, hag proved competent to handle Inlandjjrensport and therefore I an not desirous of risking achange of control on Railway irensport.     I am prepared,however, to see some big or men placed in charge both ofthe internal railway transport anf. the shipping transport,so that any existing gap nay bo closed.     This bigger manwould, of course, report to the Minister in charge ofour affairs in America.     as a further part of a completedscheme of organisation,, I would link up the Wupply and ,Inspection Branches of the Ministry organisation under asenior officer who v/ould be the chief representative ofthe Ministry in the United States.,(Sgd)    0. AD&quot; 13017.Ministry of Munitions,Whitehall &quot;lace, 3.W..Hay 2 nd. 1917.
Deeypher of telegram from Sir C.Spring Rice (VaaHinfftonL May i?th,1917Following from Hr.Balfour:-One of the most pressing matters whichc all for decisionis organisation of Allied traffic with the United states by landand sea,iiatry of United States into the. war gives them right tointervene;    and if they are driven to take matter up by?ourdeficionoies I do not think matters will be improved end in aJlprobability subject will be approached from side cf rail ways ardtoo little from side of ships.Our traffic organisation should :-(l) Avoid any hiatus betwern Railways and steamers..(2) Avoid any competition between Allies for rail facilities,aud these enls can be attained without delay by creatinga traffic e^eoutivo consisting of Captain thvLhrio,chairman nominated by His Modesty1 s Ocve:;?jme:at and onedelegate eao:i for Drench and Italian interestso     Inaddition Mrt.Kerr would strengthen this executive bodyby his special knowledge of [? munitions) trafficrequirements.Fact that Gubhrie as representative of Ministry of Slippingalready controls movements of bulk of tonnage and already routeswhole of allied grain cn behalf of Wheat Executive will mska iteasy for him. as Chairman of Traffic Executive to oc-c/rdin&amp;ts landand sea traffic without disturbing direct control of Ministry cfShipping over British ships *Traffic Executive should take instructions about priorityof cargo from Departments to wham ships have been allocated andshould assume responsibility far routing cargo c:a rails to sea-beard either by direct arrangements with Bailways or-by use ofany Railway Executive created hereaIt seems to be generally agreed that United Control shouldbe introduced into all the traffic of Allies whether on thoContinent ef America or in transport from America to .eiur *;pe butthere is   &quot;difference of opinion as to hands in which UnitedControl should be placed *     Ministry of Munitions appears tothink land transport should be divorced from sea transp -rt andthat control of former should be assigned to Munitions of WarOrganisation in  Tew Xork*     The alternative suggestion is thatit should be assigned to Traffic Executive with C-utLrie as  ,Chairman eOn the whole I am in favo-UTa of the latte^lacu     Ministrycf Munitions Office in Hew Yoik&apos;fa&quot;t present nothing to do withshipping cad though railway traffic arrangements connects:! withrunitions are difficr.lt and complicated, the amount cf munitionstransported is many times, less than supply cf wheat and disparityin ton mileage is even more marked^      here are oVvious adveitaresin maintaining un.brcken connection between sea and land transportpartly because great land distances C7er which wheat has to becarried would make perfect co-ordination between lend and seatranspcit difficult unless one authority was responsible for bebhbut still more because it would be easier to induce allies to cornsinto a sysuam^/pf single control if they have to deal w ith. anorganisation/wnich they are already familiar in connectio^withtheir shipments of wheat 0     Prench have already accepted trafficexecutive scheme and I anticipate Italians will also agree *Above is for consideration of War Cabinet.
Decypher of telegram from Sir CSpring Rice (Washingtonh. May 17th^l917following from Mr.Balfour:-One of the most pressing matters whichcall for decisionis organisation of Allied traffic with the United States by leadand sea.iintry of United States into the. war gives them right tointervene;   and if they are driven to take matter up &quot;by ourdeficiencies I do not think matters will be improved and in all-crobability subject will be approached from side cf railways andtoo little from side of ships.Our traffic organisation should :-(l) AVoid any hiatus between Railways and steamers..(2) Avoid any competition between Allies for rail facilities,and these enis can be attained without delay by creatinga traffic exevutivo consisting of Captain ChvLhrio,chairman nominated by His Ma.]estyTs teever?jment and onedelegate each for French and Italian interests.     Inaddition Mr tKerr would strengthen this executive bodyby his special knowledge of T? munitions) trafficrequirements.Pact that GubLrie as representative of Ministry of Shippingalready controls movements of bulk of tonnage and already routeswhole of allied grain cn behalf of Wheat Executive will -neks iteasy for him as Chairman of (traffic Executive to co-ordinate landand sea traffic without disturbing direct control cf Ministry cfShipping over British ships-Traffic Executive should take instructions about priorityof cargo from Departments to wham ships have been allocated andshould assume responsibility for routing cargo on rails to sea-board either by direct arrangements with Railways or by use ofany Railway Executive created here.It seems to be generally agreed that United Control shouldbo introduced into all the traffic of Allies whether on thyContinent ef America or in transport from America to .&amp;urope butthere is  &quot;difference of opinion as to hands in wliich UnitedControl should be placed *     Ministry of Munitions appears tothink land transport should be divorced from sea transport andthat control of former should be assigned to Munitions of WarOrganisation in Hew York.     fX&apos;he alternative suggestion is thatit should be assigned to Traffic Executive with  uthrie as  xChairman cOn the whole I am in favo-ivji, of the latter/plan^     Ministryof Munitions Office in lev/ Yoi^fsTt present nothing to do withshipping cad though railway traffic arrangements connected withmunitions are difficr.lt and complicated, the amount cf munitionstransported is many times- less than supply cf wheat and disparityin ton mileage is even more id arks d*     There are obvious advsataresin maintaining unbroken connection between sea and laud transportpartly t-eeause great land distances ever which wheat has to becarried would make perfect co-ordination between land and seatransport difficult unless one authority was responsible for bothbut still more because it would be easier to induce allies to cornsinto a sysuem^Qf single control if they have to deal w it&amp; morganisation/wnich. they are already familiar in conneetior&apos;with,    their shipments of wheats     French have already accepted trafficexecutive scheme and I anticipate Italians will also agree *

</content>
</cab>
