<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 26-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MEMORANDUM \vy/r:,^ U-T .On May 1st, 1917, Lord J)erb^^svma(m^uB^&amp;^iM^-at which the Minister of Munitions, A.&amp;., M,G.O.,D,C*IaG,S., D*C,G,S,France, D, of Recruiting, Lt*ColonelSterm and Sir Eustace dlEyncourt were present, to discussthe formation, of a Tank Committee to deal with the questionof Tani design, equipment of Tanks and of Tank cfews, andanti-Tank expedients, eto.This Committee, it was suggested, shouldconsist of a President, and of two representatives-ofthe Ministry of Munitions, one from the War Office, andone from the Heavy Branoh.     The President to he anofficer not below the rank of Major-General with recentfighting experience in France,As Director General of the Meohanical WarfareSupply Department since October 1st, 1916, Chairman ofthe Committee of Tank Supply, and Director of the TankSupply Department from February 12th, i916, and asSecretary of the -tiandship Committee of the Admiraltyfrom April, 1915* I have been responsible for theconstruction of every tank produced, and consider that Ihave greater experience than anyone else in the questionof Mechanical Warfare,The Military Authorities, who have not grown up   -with this new development, and who do not know the reasonsfor the different advantages and disadvantages whichgo to make up a Tank, are disregarding more and moreexpert opinion.
For instance; the original Tanks, Mark 1.,were fitted with the Hotchkiss Machine Gun, and theemployment of this gun was only decided on after veryexhaustive investigation and considerationjxf the&apos;specialcircumstances of Tank warfare.On the 23rd November, 1916, at a specialMeeting, the Military Authorities decided that theHotchkiss Machine Gun be abandoned and the Lewis Gunbe substituted.     This decision was reached against theadvice of M.W.S.D.At a series of meetings again held by theMilitary, and reported on by a Committee on the 6thMay, 1917, it was decided that the Lewis Gun wasuseless in a Tank and that the Hotohkiss gun was theonly gun that could be used.     The result is thatonce more a change has to be made, but too late tomake the alteration as it should &quot;be made, and thisyear&apos;s Tanks will carry converted Lewis gun loopholesand Hotchkiss ammunition in racks and boxes providedfor Lewis guns.Originally, it was considered by the M.W.S.D.that Male and Female Tanks in equal numbers was thebest arrangement.     In the winter of 1916-17, the militaryexperts decided on the proportion of 1 Male to 2 Female&apos;.Last week they again changed their ideas to 3 Males to2 Females, and there are insufficient 6 pdr. guns forthis purpose.In consultation with the expert advice ofMechanical Warfare, it was decided by the MilitaryAuthorities that 100 Tanks in France and 100 Tanks inEngland were necessary for training purposes.    Onthis decision, Tanks were manufactured with mild steel------- . &apos;plates instead of armour plates, without the improvements
required for fighting.     This decision was onlyarrived at after very full discussion and after thequestion of this large number of Tanks necessary fortraining purposes had been very severely criticisedby the Prime Minister and Sir Eustace d*Eyncourt, butthe Military Authorities stated that it was absolutelynecessary to have this number of training Tanks.Shortly after this, the Military Authorities decidedto use 60 of these training Tanks for fighting purposes.The reason given for using these praotioemachines was that the output of machines was late.The Military Authorities, though crying out for an earlydelivery of Tanks, have never given the M.W.S.D, theassistance they required.      At the same moment thatthe Director General of the M.W.3.D. was oalled before theWar Cabinet on March 22nd to answer for the delay of onemonth in the delivery of Tanks, the War Office had madean agreement with the Ministry of Munitions fquoted below)dated the 16th March that the only two munitions whichthe Army required most urgently were aeroplanes and guns-&quot;It will be understood that the new system is baaed on the exemption of occupations; any generalreservation of the labour engaged in engineer-ing shops on the manufacture of any particularmunitions would import into the scheme almostconfusing and undesirable features.    The facthowever, remains that the manufacture of thetwo munitions whioh the Army requires mosturgently at the present moment, viz:- aero-planes and guns, necessitates the employmentof a great number of men and youths whowill not come under the schedule.     Thisapplies particularly to the aeroplane industry.&quot;
&quot;On October 27th, 1916, a letter-ms dispatched&quot;from the Minister of Munitions to the Secretary&quot;of the War Office from whioh the following&quot;paragraphs are extracted -*As reagrds the labour required to oarry outlthis programme, I am to state that it will( *be necessary for th9 manufacturers to employfabout 3,000 additional hands of whom 1,000 to11,400 ma/ he women,     The detailed arrange-&quot;menbs for supplying this labour are still*under- oo?j.sideration and I am to say that it&quot;will only be possible to obtain the number!of man required with the assistance of the,Army Oounail.*I am directed to state that Mr. Montagu!feelvj himself unable to hold out any hope of1 meeting the large programmes that are being&quot;put before him unless he can secure the support8not only of the Adjutant General, but also*of the Recruiting Officers throughout the1country, in protecting the labour staff of1 firms manufacturing very urgent war material1,&quot;At a mooting with Sir Douglas Haig, the Minister&quot;of Munitions. General Whigham, General Davidson,&quot;and Sir Uostace d&apos;EyncourT, on 23rd November, 1916,&quot;I s^ato^.quite clearly that to produce the Tanks&quot;according to my proposed Programme, I should require&quot;about 2,000 workmen.&quot;Instead of getting these men after repeated,&quot;continual, and continuous demands, men are being&quot;taken from the Works, and only 275 out of the&quot;2,000 have been supplied.&quot;Figures are enclosed of labour required.&quot;The Military Authorities, being aware ofthe Commander-in-Chief1 s demand, had not put thisDepartment in a protected category, and it is only afterrepeated demands to General Butler, and a visit toSir Douglas Haig last month (April 24th) at Amiens,that the Mechanical Warfare Supply Department nowappears on the sase list ?/ith Guns and Aeroplanes andis thus protected.The withdrawal of these Tanks for fightingpurposes has resulted in a lack of trained men, and great-----I here quote from ^ JLemorsno^20th February, 1917 -
delay in training the men, on which the whole successof Mechanical Warfare depends, has resulted.The lack of training has also been due to ashortage of essential Spare Parts; a Schedule was laiddown &quot;by the Military Authorities in January on a muchreduced scale to that suggested by the, M.W.S.B. andtwo months1 later certain categories were multiplied byI quote from my letter to the Minister ofMunitions on March l tn, 1917 -&quot;As Director General of the Department which has&quot;been responsible for the design and which has&quot;produced every Tank, I have persistently opposed&quot;the premature employment of Tanks this year.    Also,&quot;the employment? of praotioeuTariks, i.e*, Mark I, II,&quot;and III. in action this year.\x x x&quot;I consider it more than unwise to use Practice^Tanks in action under any oiroumstanoes.    They&quot;have all the faults that necessitated the design of&quot;last year being altered to the present design of Mark^IV.     In addition the training of the men is being&quot;delayed by this action.    Their failure will undoubted-&quot;ly ruin the confidence of the troops in the fixture&quot;of Mechanical Warfare.&quot;For the sake of 60 machines, the whole future&quot;of thousands of Tanks will be most unjustifiably&quot;prejudiced.&quot;I wish also to point out that even when Mark IV.&quot;machines are delivered, taking Machanioal Warfare&quot;as an enterprise, it is a most uneconomical&quot;expenditure of our resources to use them before&quot;we have large numbers, and the necessary central&quot;Workshops ready in operation.&quot;As the War proceeds and our losses in men&quot;accumulate, necessity will force us more and more&quot;into labour saving devices, which will take their&quot;place in warfare as they havo in commerce.&quot;All care should be taken to foster the development&quot;of this new weapon, with the greatest caution.&quot;However excellent the design of a ship, without a&quot;sudder she will be wrecked.    I believe Mechanical&quot;Warfare, without prudence, will share a like fate&quot;.The Military Authorities again disregardedTechnical advice, at a Meeting on Spare Parts at the
Ministry of Munitions, in the Ministerfayibom, at whichthe M.G.O., Sir Eustace d,Eyneourt, General Anley.Colonel Searle and Mr. Percy Martin were present,(April 3rd, 1917).At this Meetingj which had been called as aresult of oomplaints to the War Council, the MilitaryAuthorities laid down that they required the same numherof 9paa?e Parts for Training Machines per 100 as forFighting Machines per 100.I pointed out to them that a Fighting Machinewas, oompared with a Training Machine, a projectile,and that after going into action, it would hardlyrequire any Spare Parts; in other words, that TrainingTanks would require Spare Parts, hut Fighting Machineswould require spare Fighting Machines.The technioal side was overruled, and SpareParts were ordered in quantities which are overtaxingthe whole Steel Castings capacity of this country.The technical advice that these maohines wereworth 200 or 300$ more on dry ground than on wet groundwas also disregarded.I explained that the wear necessitating thelarge number of Spares was due to wet winter weather(namely, Mud), and would be largely reduced by summerweather, and mudguards, which were &quot;being fitted.     Thisadvice was unheeded.     The date of this Meeting wasApril 3rd.A letter dated May 10th, from the Heavy Branch,France, states that all estimates for Spares for FightingTanks, estimated on March 10th and confirmed at theMeeting on 3rd April above mentioned, are to he halved,except the 6 Steel Castings which were demanded in
enormous -goantltlefl.     %h&amp;8&amp; -djmaM&amp;. M^-&amp;Q$2m&amp;$^ inthe ease of 4 of tham3o-a/6th, and in the oase of2 of them to V4th.The total weight of the demand ofApril 3rd, covering 1,600 machines over a period of8 months, was 10,600 tons; the amended estimate of May10th for the same number of machines over the sameperiod is 3,400 tons.The advioe that Tanks in quantity areessential to the success of an action in MechanicalWarfare has also been disregarded, *The preparations being made by the Ministryof Munitions should result in the shipment of between40,000 and 50,000 tons of Tanks during the fightingseason this year.    The Military Authorities haveprovided a single Central Workshop - one centre forthe reoeption of this mighty host! - this in againsttechnical advice&quot;.The Central Workshop at the Iront which weunderstood was to be used for running repairs in nowbeing used for the reconstruction of new types ofmachines such as Supply Tanks and Signalling Tanks,General Anley was appointed General incommand of the Tanks in England and the MechanicalWarfare Supply Department made arrangements for hisoffices to be next door to the M.W.S.D.It was arranged that general demands fromFranoe for Spares, Tank Stores, eto,, from the TankCorps should oomo direot through the General to theM.W.S.D., and be shipped direct by the organisationof the K.W,S.D, which ships Tanks and Tank Storesunder control of its own officers and men to the TankHeadquarters in France.    Now, it is proposed to divertthis through all sorts ef channels in the War Office,
Instances can &quot;be quoted &quot; y which the time taken inreceiving a demand and fulfilling it under the newregime means endless delay.The present suggestion to put MechanicalWarfare on the above basis at the War Office is,in myopinion,ill-considered and fatal to the suooess andprogress of Mechanical Warfare.It is proposed that two members of the Ministryof Munitions,a member of the War Office,and a memberof the Heavy Section should meet under th.e. Presidencyof a General not below the rank of a Major Beneral.Major General Capper has now been appointedAdministrative Commander of all the Tank Forces,and is,I believe,on Sir Douglas HaigTs Staff,and also Chairmanof the TankuCommittee,As far as I can gather,the Committee have nofurther&apos; Charter than the document   attacked,but Majorgeneral Capper called a meeting on* the 15th inst.of$ir Eustace d&apos;Eyncourt,Major Sir John Keen representing^he M.G.O., and myself (Lieut,Col.Stern).I wish once more to put forward that,in myopinion,this Committee,to be successful,must be puton a proper footing,and ,1 consider it essential thatthe Chairman,Major Genoral Capper,must be a member ofthe Army Council.and that the members of the Committeeshould devote their entire time to Mechanical Warfareand be responsible to the Chairman for the differentbranches which go to make up Mechanical Warfare,viz:-PERSONNEL -There should be a member responsible to the Chairmanfor complete knowledge of requirements and studygenerally of personnel for Tanks both in Pranoeand England with a liaison.-with French Tanks,
Another member should study the Question of Tacticsin oo-operation with the TanJr Force in ,Franoe and the^-^Tank Force in England,and hate complex informationready for the Committee,with a liaison with FrenchTanks.SUPPLY &amp; DESIGN-All knowledge of supply and design should be concentratedin Lieut.-Colonel Stern and Sir Eustace d^yncourtrepresenting the Ministry of Munitions.      TheMechanical Warfare Supply Department are in liaisonwith the French Department on Tanks design andsfcPP1^ to consist   .The Committee/of 5 members, 3 to beappointed by the Army Council to devote their entiretime to Mechanical Warfare; the Chairman to be amember of the Army Council;the Z members from theMinistry of Munitions,representing Supply and Design,to be appointed by the Minister of Munitions subjectto the approval of the Army Council.In this way,the Chairman of the Committeewould have a permanent organisation with first-handinformation on the Personnel,Tactics,Manufacture andDesign of Tanks,and,as a Member of the Army Council,would be in a position to furnish the Army Council withthe latest information on all these points wheneverrequired.This Committee should be the recognisedauthority for submitting recommendations as to theTactical employment of Tanks and other M.W.Stores andshould advise on the Numbers,Training and Equipment ofCrews,and on anti-Tank expedients.    The Committeeshould be empowered to give final decisions (subjectonly to approval by the Secretary of State for War andthe Minister of Munitions),on all matters appertainingto design and equipment of Tanks (whether for Fighting,
&amp;igttaaiin&amp;r uri-^ other purposes);Transport ana Storage of M.W.Storea, epairs,includingCentral and Mobile Workshops; Spare Parts and any-special Stores and Inspection.The Mechanical Warfare Supply Department havehitherto carried out the experiments,Design.Construction.Inspection,Storage and Transportation.     Their Contractand Finance Sections have been under the Director Generalsubject to the supervision of the heads of those Departmentsin the Ministry of Munitions,who have their representatives inthis Department.This system has proved entirely successful andno faults have been found &quot;by the Finance and ContractsBranches of the Ministry of Munitions except that it differsfrom the procedure in other Departments,namely,that thelocal control of Contracts and Finance Departments,thoughsupervised by the Ministry of Munitions,is directly underthe Director General of the Mechaaioal Warfare SupplyDepartmenti      The systems adopted by this Department areused in the most up-to-date and successful businesses inthe world and have been approved by the different authoritiesof the Ministry of MunitionsiThe question of Transportation,Storage andInspection as above, should be left to the discretion ofthis Committee to decide.My reasons for stating this are that MechanicalWarfare is in a process of great expansion and developmentwith violent and continual changes, and it would he fatalto try and impose on this new enterprise the hard and fastrules governing standard Army Stores,      Of course, it isunderstood that the formation of this Committee and thepowers given to it are a temporary measure for this andnext year&apos;s production.
If these re^oimaeBAatlons are approved, Isee every hope     oexrying out the big programme whioiu. ison order this year, and tho programme which has &quot;beenforeshadowed for next year, but unless the new organiza-tion is formed on these lines, with the flexibilitysuggested, I see np possibility of earring out eitherthis or next yearTs programme.18.5,17.
l2l/Stores/4164. f J CRETMINUTES OF CONFERENCE ON TANKSheld at the War Office on 1st May 1917,Present:-   Secretary of State for..War.Minister of MunitionsAdjutant-General.Master-General of the Ordnance,Deputy Chief of the Imperial General Staff,Deputy Chief of the General Staff,France,Director of Recruiting,lieutenant-Colonel Stern (D.G.M.W.S.D.)Sir Eustace D,Bynoourt.&apos;-:1.   A Committee will &quot;be formed to deal with the question ofTank design, equipment of Tanks, and Tank crews,and anti-Tankexpedients.2.   This Committee to consist of a President, and of tworepresentatives of the Ministry of Munitions, one from the WarOffice, and one from the Heavy Branch. , The president to &quot;be anofficer not &quot;below the rank of Major-General with recent fightingexperience in France,3,   All recommendations and suggestions in regard to thematters referred to in paragraph 1 and other cognate questionswill be referred to this Committee,     The functions of theCommittee. will be to formulate definite specifications andproposals based on the recommendations submitted to it and onits own research.     These specifications so far as the designof the Tank as a fighting machine is concerned, will then bepassed to the Design branch of the Mechanical Warfare Departmentof the Ministry of Munitions to carry.out...   The latter willsubmit its designs to the Committee for final approval beforemanufacture is proceeded with.   Field trials of any Tank ofnew or improved design.will also be carried out under theorders of the Committee.
4.      tfhe question was raised as to whether the tanksshould not he handed over complete to the Army in Englandin the same manner as guns, instead of &quot;being transportedto France by the Ministry of Munitions and there takenover by the Military.    Dr. Addison stated that he wasprepared to agree to the principle that they should hetaken over by the Army in England and transported toFrance under War Office arrangements, hut suggestedthat the matter should he discussed in detail by theTank Committee before a final decision was given.This was agreed to.

</content>
</cab>
