<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 57-65</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Before the War the World1s metal market was largely-controlled &quot;by a group of German metal companies engagedfor producers.     fhese companies were closely connected bystock control, the inter-ownership of stock, inter-lockingdirectorates or joint syndicates and their relations wereof such a nature as to lead to a common policy in respectalike of purchase and sale of metals.     The most importantof these concerns is the Metallgesellschaft of Frankfurt onMain, with which are closely connected H.E.Merton &amp; Co. inthe United Kingdom with its subsidiary the Merton Metallurgi-cal Co. and the American Metal Company in the United States.These in their turn combined with certain German metal-lurigical and financial interests to found in 1910 theMetallbank and Metallurgische Gesellschaft.of   Frankfurt onMain with a capital of  2,000,000&apos;.     This last named organisa-tion either directly or through its constituent concernshad by the outbreak of war established er acquired control-ling or other financial interests in metal dealing, miningor working companies or chemical companies in Germany, Austria,the United Kingdom, France, Belgium, Switzerland, Holland,Spain, Australia, Africa, Mexico, and Italy.     Distinct fromthe Metallgesellschaft group of companies but closely associatedwith the same interests and with aeach other in various syndicatesand combinations ware Beer, Sondheimer &amp; Co. of Frankfurt,with interests in companies in Germany, Austria, Italy, Belgium,France, and the United States;    and Aron Hirsch &amp; Co., withsubsidiary companies in Germany, the United States andAustralia.This control of the non-ferrous metal trade of theprimarily in buying metals or in acting as selling agentsby German or German controlled interests has been a
cause of grave embarrassment to the Allied Governments duringthe War, and the question of the &quot;best means of preventingthe re-establishment of that control has been occupying theattention of the Board of Trade for some time hack.   Thematter has been discussed on more than one occasion with theFrench Government, and quite recently the Imperial War Gon-ference passed a Resolution declaring that it &quot;would welcomeappropriate measures for the purpose of freeing the Empireand the Allied countries from their previous dependence onGerman controlled organisations with respect to non-ferrousmetals and ores&quot;.It is, however, the unanimous opinion of all the expertswho have been consulted that in view of the widespread con-nections, highly developed organisation and great financialresources of the German group, it would be almost impossiblefor any new Imperial or Allied organisation to secure a firmfooting in the metal markets of the. Allied countries and ofthe World unless drastic steps are taken to prevent the re-vival within Allied territories of the operations either adirect of indirect of the German interests.   The Frenchand Belgian Governments have expressed their willingnessto take the necessary restrictive measures in their owncountries, and the Resolution of the Imperial War Confer-ence quoted above shews that the dominions are in sympathywith the same policy.   The Non-Ferrous Metal Industry Billhas been drafted to give effect to this policy within theUnited Kingdom.
- 3 -4The Bill provides in Clause I that no company, firmor individual should engage in the business of extracting,smelting, dressing, refining, or dealing by way of whole-sale trade in metal or metallic ore, to which the Billapplies, except under licence which shall he renewableannually.     The Bill applies to Zinc, Copper, Tin, Lead,Nickel and Aluminium and provision is made for itsextension to other non-ferrous metals by order of theBoard of Trade.Clause I, sub-section (2)   provides, that the Boardof Trade shall not grant a licence to a Company or Firmto which the conditions in the schedule apply, unless theyare of opinion that for some special reason the grant ofa licence is expedient.     Any company or firm to whichthe conditions in the schedule do not apply will beentitled to the licence.     The conditions are so framedas to cover businesses controlled ,or managed to anysubstantial extent by persons who are or have been enemysubjects, and thus cover the case of a business controlledby naturalised British subjects of German origin.     Theyalso cover the case of close enemy association at the dateof the introduction of the Bill through any shareholdingin some neutral company.Clause I, sub-section (5) gives a right of appealto the Court on the question whether the conditions inthe schedule apply in fact to any particular firm orcompany.     No right of appeal is given from the refusalof the Board of Trade to grant a licence if the conditionsin the schedule apply.By Clause VI the Bill is to continue in force duringthe War, and for five years afterwards.
[7 Geo. 5.] Non-Ferrous Metal Industry. 1DRAFTOP AB I L LTORegulate temporarily the business of extracting, smelting, ad. 1917.dressing, refining, and   dealing in   certain   non-ferrousmetals and metallic ores.TVE it enacted by the K:ing&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andJJ with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual andTemporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled,and by the authority of the same, as follows : on5       1. (1)-It shall not be lawful for any company, firm, or prohibitiindividual after the expiration of three months from the passing *gaj.nns* .of this Act, or such longer period as the Board of Trade may in certaiuany particular case allow, to engage in the business of extracting, metals withsmelting, dressing, refining, or  dealing by way of wholesale outa lcencu10 trade in metal or metallic ore [or product] to which this Actapplies, unless licensed to do so by .the Board of Trade :Provided that the purchase of metal by persons for thepurposes of their trade shall not be deemed-to be dealing insuch metal by way of wholesale trade where the trade carried15 on by the purchaser is not primarily the trade of dealing inmetals.(2) In the case of a company, firm, or individual withrespect to which any of the conditions set forth in the Scheduleto this Act apply, no licence shall be granted unless the Board20 of Trade are of opinion that for any special reason the grantof a licence is expedient, but save as aforesaid any company,firm, or individual engaged or proposing to engage in suchbusiness as aforesaid shall on making application in the pre-scribed manner, and on furnishing such information and allowing25 inspection of such books and documents as may be reasonablyrequired, and on payment of the prescribed fee, be entitled to alicence under this Act.
2 ^Nbn-Fert^ous Metal Industry.. [7 Geo. 5.JA.D. 1917.        (3) A licence under this Act, unless suspended or revoked,shall remain in force until the day of followingthe date of issue of the licence, hut shall he renewableannually, and the same provisions shall apply to the renewal ofthe licence as apply to the.grant of a licence. 5(4) The Board of Trade, if satisfied that any company,firm, or individual to whom a licence has been granted underthis Act [is or] has become subject to any of the conditionsset forth in the Schedule to this Act, may revoke or suspendthe licence. 10(5) If any question arises between the Board of Trade andany company, firm, or individual,, as to whether or not any ofthe conditions set forth in the Schedule to this Act apply inrespect of the company, firm, or individual, the question shallin manner provided by rules of court be referred by the Board 15of Trade to the High Court, and the decision of the HighCourt shall be final, and no appeal therefrom shall lie to anyother court.(6) Where at the expiration of such three months or atany time when a licence expires, any such question stands 20referred to the High Court, the Board of Trade shall, onapplication being made for the purpose, extend the said periodof three months as respects that company, firm, or individual,or as the case may be, the duration of. the licence, for suchperiod as may be necessary to allow the question to be deter- 25mined by the High Court.2. The Board of Trade shall have power at any time torequire any person able to give information with respect to theconstitution, control or management of any company, firm orindividual which has applied for the grant of a licence, or to 30which a licence has been granted under this Act, to furnishsuch information within such time as the Board may direct, andany person appointed by the Board in that behalf shall beentitled to inspect any books and documents belonging to orunder the control of such company, firm or individual. ggOffences. 3.  (1) If any person carries on the business of extracting,- smelting, dressing, refining, or dealing in any. metal or metallicore [or product] in contravention of this Act without a licence,he shall [on an information being laid by or with the consentof the Board of Trade] be liable on summary conviction toPower torequireinformationand inspec-tion ofdocuments.
f 7 Geo -51 Non-SFerrous Metal Itulustm. n 3imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term not        1917.exceeding three months, or to a tine of one hundred pounds, orto both such imprisonment and fine.(2) If any person refuses or neglects to furnish any informa-5 tion which under this Act is required to be furnished within thetime within which it is to be furnished, or knowingly furnishesany information required to be furnished under this Act whichis false in any material particular, or having custody of any bookor document which a person is authorised to inspect under this10 Act, refuses or wilfully neglects to produce the book or docu-ment for inspection, or forges or fraudulently alters or uses orpermits to be fraudulently used any licence issued under thisAct, he shall be liable on summary conviction to imprisonmentwith or without hard labour for a term not exceeding three15 months or to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, or to bothsuch imprisonment and fine.. -(3; Where the person guilty of an offence under this Actis a company, every director, manager, secretary, and otherofficer of the company who is knowingly a party to the default,20 shall also be guilty of the like offence, and liable to the likepunishment.4. The Board of Trade may make rules (subject in respect Rules,of fees to the approval of the Treasury), for prescribing any-thing which, under this Act, is to be prescribed, and generally25 for carrying this Act into effect.5. The metals and ores to which this Act applies are zinc, Metals orcopper, tin, lead, nickel, aluminium, and any other non-ferrous oreft0metals and ores to which this Act may be applied by order of applies^01the Board of Trade.30       6.-(1) This Act may be cited as the Non-Eerrous Metal Short titleIndustry Act, 1917. and duration.(2) This Act shall continue in force only during thecontinuance of the present war and for a period of five yearsafter the termination thereof.68 A 2
4 Non-Ferrous Metal Industry. [7 Geo. 5.] .IF. ^--wc-o^ .^vv/ f c- ,03/D ta.d. 1917. SCHEDULE.Conditions,1. That any director of the company or any partner of the firm,or the individual or any manager or other principal officer employedby-the company, firm, or individual, is a person who is or has &quot;been 5an enemy, or who was at any time before the fourth day of Augustnineteen hundred and fourteen the subject of a State which subsequentlybecame an enemy State: -2. That in the case of a company, any capital of the company isor was at any time after the day of nineteen 10hundred and seventeen held by or on behalf of an- enemy.3. That the company, firm, or individual is or was at any timeafter the .    day of   - . nineteen hundred and seventeenparty.to any agreement, arrangement or understanding, which enables;[or enabled] an enemy to  influence the policy or conduct of the 15business.4. That the company, firm, or individual is or was at any timeafter the day of nineteen hundred and seventeeninterested directly or indirectly to the extent of one-fifth or more ofthe capital in any undertaking whether or not in the United Kingdom,  0engaged in business of a kind to- which this Act applies,,.in whichenemies are also interested directly or indirectly to the. extent ofone-fifth or more of the capital!5. That the company, firm, or individual is or was at &quot;any timeafter the , day of nineteen nundred and seventeen 25directly or indirectly controlled by a company, firm, or individual; towhom a licence under this Act would be refused.6, That the company, firm,, or individual, is by any means what-ever subject to enemy influence or association.For the purposes of this Schedule The expression &quot; enemy&quot; means a subject of an enemy Stateand an enemy controlled corporation.The expression &quot;enemy State &quot; means any State with which HisMajesty is at the passing of this Act, or has after the passingof this Act, become&apos; at war.30
[7 Geo. 5.]Non-Ferrous Metal Industry.5The  expression  &quot;enemy controlled   corporation&quot;  means  any  A.D. 1917.corporation (a) where the majority of the directors or the personsoccupying the position of directors by whatever name called,5 are subjects of such a State as aforesaid; or(b) where the majority of the voting power is in the handsof persons who are subjects of such a State as aforesaid, orwho exercise their voting powers directly or indirectly onbehalf of persons who are subjects of such a State as10 aforesaid ; or(e) where the control is by any means whatever in thehands of persons who are subjects of such a State asaforesaid; or(d) where the executive is an enemy controlled company15 or where the majority of the executive are appointed by anenemy controlled company.The expression &quot;capital&quot; in relation to a company means anyshares or other securities issued by the company which carryany voting power with respect to the management of thecompany.20
JSTon-Ferrous MetalIndustry.DE APT1   OP ABILLTo regulate temporarily the businessof extracting, smelting, dressing,refining, and dealing in certain non-ferrous metals and metallic ores..LXII. (3.)7th May 1917.

</content>
</cab>
