<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 189-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Decipher.   Sir G. Barclay (Jassy)May 18th. 1917.D.   12.45 p.m..May 18th 1917.R..      4.50 p.m.. May 22nd 1917.Following for Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff from General Candolles..In order to assist in placing communicationsbetween Roumania and Russia In fit condition forstrenuous military operations there was undertakensome months ago construction of three new junctionrailways linking up Roumania with Bessarabia viz, fromDangeni Northwards and from Umgheni Northward and fromBarlat Eastward.   In view of surplus rolling stockof Roumanian gauge and shortage of that of Russiangauge best policy would obviously be to lay as muchas possible of these three junction lines withformer gauge.   Unfortunately inverse policy has beenso far insisted on by Russian head-quarters but Iam still contesting point in respect of portions offirst and third of them.I have personally gone over first pf these newjunction lines and am sending officer to visit othertwo as to state of which no reliable information isprocurable.   Work is proceeding but slowly on allthree of them and none can be ready before Octobereven should rails and sleepers be delivered in timewhich is more than doubtful.   Total Russian outputof rails no?; represents less than 300 kilometres oftrack a month.     Even should enough of this smalloutput be spared fo? Roumania and Bessarabia or ifimportations through Vladivostock should increase it iscertain that delivery here would be slow and irregularon account of bad operation of Russian railways.
ItOn Danube there has also been built across outlet ofLake Brateshul embanked rail connection between Renl andG-alatz.   Although still unfinished it is already in usebut is exposed to enemy artillery whilst Russian approachline from Benderi to Reni is of small traffic capacitywhich would only be partially corrected by proposed spurconnection towards Ismail.     In this region internationalcommunications will not be placed on a really sound footinguntil Danube below Galatz again becomes freely utilizableby Allies.In Roumania the operation of carts and automobileswhich are by no means numerous and the building of roadsare badly handled so that for any substantial offensivetowards Wallachia important stocks of rai(ls and otherrailway materials would be quite indispensable for immediateuse in conquered territory as also heavy stocks of wood fuellocal coal and oil being very limited in quantity and allproceeding from a district still liable to be cut off byenemy whilst to import adequate fuel supplies from Russiawould merely congest (?approach) railways unless of courseDanube route were previously made available.These rails we can not hwever expect to receive andaccumulation of adequate stocks of wood fuel even if wesucceed in giving greater impetus to use of Decauvilleline will be rendered almost impossible by prevailingshortage of cartage from forests which is intensified bycurrent demands for sleepers and construction timber.
It Is in fact this shortage of cartage and lack ofcertain incidental imported materials that trill constitutechief problem of the future in Roumanian Railway systemas it exists today.Traffic congestion around Jassy is being nowgradually corrected and was partly the outcome of overcrowding into that neighbourhood of excessive garrisonsand other organisations, which over crowding incidentallyfostered the late panic as to insufficiency of immediatefood supplies.The working of Roumanian locomotive trafficDepartments still leaves much to be desired and isengaging our special attention although owing to innatereluctance of Roumanians to push through comprehensiveprogrammes it will not be easy to bring about rapidimprovement.   So uninviting is the prospect that certainRussian railway officials are beginning to display sometendency towards wishing to entrust Roumanian railways todirect care of my mission.   In this they are no doubtinfluenced by general situation prevalent in Russia andI am of opinion that at any rate for some time yet weshould not depart from my present plan of limiting ourselvesto tendering of unofficial advice.   See my telegram ofMay 3rd,

</content>
</cab>
