<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 342-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Re-port to the Cabinet.26th May, 1917.General        I.    A mission composed of officers of the ItalianPolicy. Aeronautical Service has been in London this week and has hada Conference with the Air Board at which various questions, andchiefly that of the; standardisation of aeronautical material,have been discussed.   Facilities have been given to theItalian officers for visiting Aircraft Factories and forinterviewing representatives of the Various Government depart-ments with which they desire to confer.II.     There has been in the past a free interchange ofinformation between the Aeronautical Authorities in thisCountry and in France ^hieh has been of mutual benefit to thetwo countries.   u&quot;hen the Government of H. Ribot recently cameinto office, with M. Daniel Vincent as Under-Secretary forAviation, there was created in Paris, under the direction ofM. Flandin, a Bureau Interallied for the purpose of bringingtogether for the benefit of all the Allies the latest availableinformation on the progress of aeronautics, designs of aircraft,aero-engines, their accessories, the development of aerialtactics, etc   The Air Board were invited to participate in thisscheme and to nominate a delegate, but no definite reply wassent for the time being.M. Flandin. who recently came to London to seo theAir Board, is evidently a man of considerable energy and forceof oharacter Who is credited with the intention of making Parisin future a sort of International Headquarters of aeronautics.Tho Air Board have now been requested to communicateto the Bureau Interallied technical information such as theyhave hitherto furnished only to the Service Technique of theFrench Ministry of V/ar.   The proposal that this information,sometimes of a highly secret character and likely to prove ofgroat value to the enemy if it came into his hands, should beplaced at the disposal of all and sundry of the Allies, of thecharacter and trustworthiness of whose representatives inParis the Board have no knowledge, is looked upon withconsiderable- distrust by the Haval and Military Authoritiesand by the Board.   A reply has accordingly been sent to theeffect that while the Board are prepared to place at thedisposal of the Bureau Interallied such information as theymay think suitable, it must bo understood that the informationfurnished to the French Government is to be treated as striotlyconfidential and not imparted to any other Government withoutexpress authorisation in writing.    In the absence of such anunderstanding the free inter-communication which has hithertoexisted between the Aviation Authorities of the two countriesr*ili be inevitably and regrettably restricted.
Sup-ply.   The deliveries of engines and aeroplanes have &quot;beenas follows:-Total fore r*eek to 19thTotal for May to dateTotal for April 1917Total for April 1916Engines,166555675202Aeroplanes.262719804202The output of aircraft and more particularly ofengines hai been most seriously affected during this monthby the strikes and labour unrest.(Signed) H.P. HaHVEY,Secretary to the Air Board,

</content>
</cab>
