<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 392-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Memorandum of the 19th instant that the Tribunals are working&quot;badly and that bO% of them are failing in their work at thepresent moment.   As the ICinister responsible for supervisingTribunals in England and Wales I have no hesitation in sayingthat their work has been on the whole very well performed,though naturally among 1,800 bodies there must bo some who areopen to criticism.    I ba.se my opinion not only on generalinformation obtained from my Inspectors and other sources butalso from special enquiries which I have caused to be made.2.     Recent statistics obtained by me indicate that thetotal number of the exemptions of men under 51 years of agewhich had to be reviewed under the recent general directionwas about 40,000; and of this number only 13,000 were fit forgeneral service; even this number will now have been reducedby the review.On the other hand, the total number of fit men under31 years of age now in civil life in Sr.-&quot;land and Wales isprobably not less than 500,000, and as less than Z% of thesehave been exempted by Tribunals in cases where they haveunfettered jurisdiction, it is absurd to attribute the diffi-culty of finding men to the action of Tribunals.The small number of men holding Tribunal exemptionsin cases in which Tribunals have unfettered jurisdiction is aneloquent testimony to the thoroughness with which they havedone their work.   In the 13,000 are included employers,pivotal men not in certified occupations, proprietors of &quot;oneman&quot; businesses and cases of hardship,In several big towns the number of men known to be fitfor general service whose cases had to be reviewed was under 10.3.     The statistics indicate that the total number of menk
hOMing&apos; Tribunal exemptions in England and Wales pf all ages andall medic3.1 categories is about G0O,OO0.    The total number of men5f military age still remaining in civil life is estimated to besome 3,500,000.These 500,000 include men holding temporary exemptionsand men who have been exempted only until substitutes are foundfor them.    The large majority of the 600,000 are in agriculture(which, by Government diroction, is in a privileged position) orin certified occupations, or in a low medical category.4.     The conclusions to be drawn frcm these statistics areconfirmed by enquiries into criticisms of individual cases whichappeared recently in certain newspapers.    Investigation showedthat in very few cases was there any ground for dissatisfactionwith the Tribunal.5.     It is obvious that a certain lack cf uniformity willbe found among the large numbers of Local Tribunals.   It was to*meet this point, among other reasons, that the MilitaryRepresentative was given an unrestricted right of appeal to theAppeal Tribunal.   Lord Derby himself states that &quot;most AppealTribunals are very geed::.    The members of Appeal Tribunals areappointed by the Crown.6.     It was clearly pointed out in the recent report made tothe War Cabinet by the Committee over which I presided that fityoung men of military age are now to be found in large numbersonly in the protected industries; and it is by the judiciouscombing out of these indtistries that the Army can obtain a largenumber of young reoruits.It was estimated in the report, and the figures nowobtained and quoted above amply show, that the number of fit youngmen exempted by Tribunals is exceedingly small; and in my opinionthe Tribunals as a whole arc undoubtedly entitled to the gratitudeof the Government for the thorough way in which they have performeda very difficult and invidious task.R.24th May. 193 7

</content>
</cab>
