<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 430-432</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
to    Director of Mi lit ary Inl^te^efji^^v/     f/Petregrad,^/7^;UL S7th May, 1017.fro proclamations fron Kerenskt natch occupy 8 oolumns arepublished by tho Frees Sureau. 376fhe 1st heided 8 Order to all of tho Amy and Fleet&quot; affirmsthat It is impossible to drive tho enemy back if wo &amp;tm&amp; still andthat there can bo no salvation without aiseiplino.fhe m&amp; is a declaration of tho righto of tho soldiers andcontains nothing now except in paragraph IS which lays down that tho*awarding of punishments and tho interim control are the province ofthe f elected committees, tout that appointments operations andtraining Mist bo loft to tho command.    Keren ski has boon wellreceived by a conference of tho elect deputies of the south WesternFront.     It is statod by a Battalion Coriander from tho 17th Coppothat the Companies in his Division are about 1B0 strong.    Therehas boon no desertion from tho trenches but owing to sickness thostrength is falling rapidly.    His men are absolutely without boots&apos;notwithstanding ho considers an offensive impossible as thetransport drivers and depot battalions in roar have deserted.the average monthly transport of coal from tho DOH basinfor tho tot Quarter of 1917 foil from 1.790,000 tons of 191(6 to1,589,000 tons.   Tho output of coal in April as compared with thecorresponding month in 1916 foil by 20.St per cent, and of coke by4.8 per cent.    In tho first Quarter of tho year tho production ofiron has fallen by 17.6 per cent.The output of factories has decreased by 40 per centchiefly owing to the S hours day, the refusal of tho men to workovertime and the lack of skilled labour to furnish additional shifts.On an average 4Q per cent of too Engineers have boon expelled by thomen.   Tnere is no limit to tho demands of tho son.   In certain metalworks of tho Bon region which in 1016, allotted 18,000,000 roublesto DIVIDEND the men asked for increased pay amounting 840,000,000.thoi/
From Brigadier-General KnoKTo    Director of Military intelligence.Petrograd,S3th May. 1917,     I1133.        The Assistant Minister of War, colonel Yakubovich,told me today that ha estimated the number of deserters beforerevolution at 8 million, and  the figure has since doubled.      &apos;The last day fixed for their rejoining is todayand a considerable (1 group undecipherable) he thought over100,000 were returning.Keren ski is at Odessa today.    He took SO agitators iwith him to the front, soldiers and workmen.    These willremain with units and attack with them.    At the earliestKeren ski Is not expected back before June 2nd.General Manikovskl gave me an illustration todayof Kerensklvs influence.    He had told a deputation from oneof the divisions that all parleying with enemy mast cease *The deputation returned to the front and passed on the order.  IThe next day 11 men tried to  cross to the Herman trenches;but were stopped by fire.     Subsequently they were tried bysoldiers, courtraartialled and sentenced to be flogged betweenthe trenches.    Borne of them had to go to hospital and one ofthem has since died.   Many Russian officers implore me to getthe Japanese to send a single division which would besufficient they say to restore order.\ If -\. U
*me masters offered to give up all tho profits but theoffer was refused.    Hie  socialistic organ PBAWA gives itsdefinition of the tera mwithout annexation&quot;   Germany suet giveup Aleaee Lorraine, Austria Serbia all Poland and Little RussiaTerritory.    England mist hand over Ireland, India and Egypt,mir&amp;ey AJMlIAjftasela Finland Poland Turkestan Little Russia etc. hat this idea oan only be attained by general revolution isacknowledged.

</content>
</cab>
