<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/14/0 images: 433-437</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.379KEPOBT BY MAJOR C. THORN HILL, Assistant Military Attache.Subject : EFFECTS OF RUSSIAN REVOLUTION.British Embassy, Petrograd,4th May, 1917.1. Operations. No operations may be expected on this front for at least twomonths. General Gurko, Commanding &quot;Western Front, thinks it will be possible toundertake an offensive on the front of the Tenth Army about 1st July, but told me thiscould only take place if internal affairs did not meantime change for the worse andhinder the reorganization and the re-establishment of discipline.Judging by the present deplorable state of the Army, it is difficult to see howdiscipline can be re-established in the short space of two months.2. Soldiers&apos; Committees. The Army has now become a series of armeddebating societies in which questions of internal politics and army reform have verylargely eclipsed the question of the prosecution of the war and the common interestsof the Allies.When the news of the revolution reached the troops at the front and details of theself-administration introduced in dep6t units of the Petrograd garrison became known,a general upheaval took place. Army, corps, divisional, regimental, battalion andcompany committees were elected by the men all along the front, and a certain numberof officers were arrested or forced to leave their appointments in consequence of votesof &quot; want of confidence &quot; by the men. In some armies the changes were accompaniedby acts of violence, but in the Third, Tenth and Second Armies there was no case in theunits actually at the front where an officer was murdered. The men of the newlyformed 168th Division killed three of their officers near Mogilev before the division tookits place in the front line.3. Discipline. All authority is in the hands of the mens representative committees,and to-day the Commander-in-Chief for all practical purposes is the Petrograd Councilof Workingmen and Soldier Deputies, whose resolutions carry far more weight thanany military order by Alexeyev or Commanders at the front. Officers cannot givepunishments and are reduced on relying on their powers of oratory to uphold theirposition and maintain the semblance of discipline.4. Minsk Conference. A conference of representatives elected by each of the threearmies of this front assembled at Minsk on 20th April, and its sittings continued dailyup to 30th April. The results of the conference were disappointing. The generalopinion of officers, including the Commander-in-Chief, General Gurko, was that it was awaste of time and in some ways directly harmful as emphasizing the mens completepredominance and the helplessness of the officers.The workmen assumed control of the proceedings from the first day when theelections to the &quot; Presidium &quot; took place. Not a single officer was chosen to sit on thisPresiding Committee, and a Minsk working-man was elected to the chair. The directionof a conference with a majority of military delegates should naturally have been in thehands of the Staff of the front, but as political organization and platform oratory haveonly lately become necessary military subjects tor officers (there is now a PoliticalSection of the Headquarters Staff), it is not surprising that the workmen, with asocialist organization of years, should have easily swept aside their amateur efforts.The Conference opened with a speech from M. Rodzianko, the President of theDuma, who was followed by the Secretary for Finland, M. Rodichev, and anotherMember of the Duma. General Gurko was invited to speak next by the chairman. Itwas an edifying spectacle, and typical of the present conditions, to see the Commander-in-Chief of a Front invited to address his own men not by a soldier, but by aworking-man.All four speakers were well received. The first three appealed for support of theProvisional Government, and two of them gave an outline of the causes of the warand the reason the Allies are continuing the struggle. This might seem superfluous inany other allied country, but it is very necessary here, where 75 per cent, of the mendo not know what they are fighting for.General Gurko made a strong speech, during the course of which he asked the menwhether they would attack when ordered to.   He said, &quot; Will not that Army that(b341)   15  5/17  h&amp;S  4587 woi3
under the tyranny of the old regime so bravely defended its mother country, at timeswith bare hands when rifles and munitions failed, will not that Army, now that freedomhas been won, go forward against the enemy when called upon ?&quot; The delegatesshouted in reply, &quot; We will go forward &quot; ; but there is no guarantee that they will be ableto persuade the men to agree in face of the propaganda for a &quot; strictly defensive war,&quot;which is daily gaining ground and which is much more to the liking of the majority.5. Resolutions of the Conference.-Hhe following are the most interesting of theresolutions passed by the Conference(a.) That the designation &quot;officer&quot; be done away with, the various ranks in futureto be named &quot; soldier,&quot; &quot; soldier non-commissioned officer,&quot; &quot; soldierlieutenant,&quot; &quot; soldier captain,&quot; &amp;c.(h.) That a selected committee of the men&apos;s representatives be present when anyscheme for military operations is under discussion, and that this committeebe also empowered to discuss events at the conclusion of the operations.(c.) That, though officers are in no case to be elected by the men, nevertheless,every officer be given a certificate by the representative committee of theunit he commands or serves in. Such certificate to accompany him whenappointed to a new post, where it will be read by the men&apos;s committee. Inthe event of such certificate being unfavourable to the officer, an enquiry isto be instituted and, if necessary, the officer to be removed from his post.6. Removal of Officers. In the Third Army, one divisional commander and fouror five junior officers were obliged by the men to leave. No officers were arrested.The XVth Corps announced that it intended to maintain a strictly defensive attitude,and would not undertake any offensive. The XXXVth and XXth Corps passedresolutions that they would attack when the men considered the concentration ofartillery and munitions sufficient to ensure success. General Kvetsinski, Commanderof the Third Army, told me this would dislocate the plans for the proposed offensive onthe front of the Tenth Army, according to which the XXth Corps was to attack with theobject of pinning the enemy to his positions and securing the right flank of the TenthArmy. The minimum of artillery would be left with the XXth Corps in this case, butwhen the men became aware of the transfer of batteries they would probably refuse toattack. Kvetsinski considers it advisable to adopt the resolution of the rnens delegatesat Minsk and allow their representatives to assist at discussions of plans for offensiveoperations.In the Tenth Army, one corps commander (Ilnd Caucasus Corps) and two divisionalcommanders were driven away. One of the divisional commanders refused the honourwhen subsequently requested to return by the men, who apologised for their vote of&quot; want of confidence.&quot;General Beneskul who took over command of the Ilnd Caucasus Corps by therequest of the men was found shot three days later. He was stated to have committedsuicide, but there seems to be some doubt as to the facts. The total number of officersdriven away in this army was about 15. In many cases there was a good, deal to besaid on the side of the men, at any rate, as far as junior officers were concerned.In the Second Army, one divisional commander (42nd Division), one colonel and19 officers were removed. The Divisional Commander, Yelshen, was appointed to thecommand of the XXth Corps. His disagreement with the men of his division appearsto have been the result of a misunderstanding. The colonel and 19 officers of the31st Siberian Regiment were arrested entirely owing to their own stupidity. During aconversation in mess someone remarked that the position of officers was impossible inthe Russian Army, and the best course would be to go over and join the German Army.Two officers were also seen to kiss the Imperial monogram on their sword hilts. Whenthe men heard of these doings they arrested their officers on the ground that they weretraitors to Russia and the Revolution.7. Parleying with the enemy. All along the front the men are crossing to theenemy&apos;s trenches to discuss conditions of peace, under the delusion that the Germansare prepared to overthrow the Monarchy and institute a republic. Every advantage isnaturally taken by the enemy of the ignorance of the mass of the Russian soldiers, andplacards of &quot; Down with the Kaiser &quot; and &quot; Down with the war &quot; are hoisted from theenemy trenches. The Russian soldier goes across to meet the Germans withoutremoving the number on his shoulder straps-so that dispositions are given away.The German returns the visit with a camera, and a great portion of the Russian firstline is now known to the enemy.
Six men of the Second Army who crossed to the enemy were taken to Woyrsch&apos;sHeadquarters at Slonim. After an absence of ten days they returned to the Russianlines on 23rd April, having been thoroughly cross-examined and primed with peacepropaganda,In the Tenth Army a telephone wire attached to a rocket was fired into thetrenches of the 31st Division j and the Chief of Staff of the division had a conversationwith a German officer lasting half-an-hour.On the fronts of the Tenth and Second Armies Russian gunners have several timesopened fire on parties of men crossing to the German lines. Such incidents wereimmediately followed up by proclamations thrown into the Russian trenches in whichthe men were urged to stop the war which was all due to England, and to seek out theEnglish agents at work in the rear who forced the Russian gunners to kill their ownmen. The Russian infantry threatened to kill their gunners if they opened fire on themin future.On 17th April on the front of the Tenth Army a company left its trenches toparley with the enemy, and was driven back at the point of the revolver by two youngensigns of the neigbouring regiment. When the men returned they threatened tosearch out and bomb one of the offending officers in his dug-out at night. His ownmen made no protest and the officer spent the night in fear of his life, sitting up withhis revolver in his hand and a guard at the door of his dug-out. No attempt on hislife was made, but the incident is interesting as throwing light on the attitude of theRussian soldier towards his officer. One can hardly imagine the men of a Britishregiment similarly placed allowing a threat to murder one of their officers to passunnoticed.On 20th April the commander of the 83rd German Division sent a letter to theGeneral Officer Commanding 75th Russian Division under a flag of truce in which heproposed the latter should come over with his division and join him. The two divisionswould then proceed to France to fight the English and French, following the precedentof Yorke in 1812 who deserted with his corps to the Russians in East Russia andfought against his late allies^ the French.The Germans, well informed no doubt as to the trouble between officers and men,direct the fire of their artillery on headquarters of regiments, divisions and corps, topersuade the Russian soldier their quarrel is not with him but with his officers who areforcing him to continue the war.To encourage the idea now current that the Germans are ready to conclude peace,firing has been reduced to a minimum. Formerly on the whole Western Front thecasualties were from 80 to 100 per diem. For the week ending 1st May, these droppedto 30 to 40 daily.On the front of the Special Army, where the lines are closer together, thecasualties were seldom less than 100 daily. Returns for the same period show 1 killedand 12 wounded, or 2 killed and 16 wounded, as the daily casualties.Desertions. Gurko estimates the desertions from the Western Front at 17 per cent.The number of deserters from units actually at the front never reached seriousproportions according to him. I saw returns in the Second Army which showed a totalof 80 deserters for the week ending 14th April. March companies on their way upfrom depots to reinforce units at the front sometimes arrived 40 per cent, to 50 per cent,short. Deserters are now gradually returning. A great deal of the trouble was dueto an order which was ambigiously worded granting an amnesty to deserters up to1st June. This was taken to mean that anyone absenting himself without leave in theinterval would not be punished.A number of officers of the newly formed 168th Division who protested againstdesertion were arrested by the men. The division was at that time near Mogilev andconsiderable disorder occurred in it. The men broke into a spirit distillery near thebarracks and when drunk killed three of their officers. Later, when ordered to proceedto the front, the men of one of the regiments refused to go and opened fire on those oftheir comrades who had already entrained. Firing continued all day and it was nottill the following morning that sufficient order was restored to enable the first echelonto be despatched.Polish Aemy.9. There is a movement on foot among the Poles serving in the Russian ranks, ofwhom there are 800,000, to form a separate Polish Army under their own officers. Thematter was discussed at the meeting of the Polish Army. delegates at Minsk at thebeginning of May, when it was decided to send a petition to the Stavka.(4587)
Autonomy for White Russia.10. The inhabitants of White Russia are agitating for autonomy and have heldconferences in Minsk to discuss details preparatory to submitting their demands to theGovernment.Opinions of All Ranks on the Situation.11. Corps and Divisional Commanders optimistic. Corps and Divisional Com-manders of all three armies told me they were confident that any offensive of theenemy would be repulsed, but the Officer Commanding, 20th Grenadier Regiment, saidthat for the first time during the war he was unable to answer for his men, and wasconvinced that they would run in the event of a German attack. A non-commissionedofficer of the same regiment, on the other hand, said that he was ready to answer withhis head that his comrades would defend their trenches to the last.General Gurko said that the worst of the trouble was over in his opinion, butevery other officer with whom I conversed considers that it is only now in process ofpassing, Gurko said, &quot; I blame the Higher Command for its weakness in followingbehind the wave of the revolution, instead of leading it and setting a definite limit toits demands.&quot;12. Pro-war propaganda. General Kvetsinski, commanding Third Army, thinksthat order will be established in two months sufficient to permit of an offensive, unlessunforeseen developments in the internal situation delay the work of reconstruction.He considers no time should be lost in launching a pro-war propaganda amongst thetroops, and has asked the Commander-in-Chief to send out suitable men for thepurpose.General Kiselevski, commanding the Tenth Army, is, of the senior officers, the mostoptimistic as to the future, but I could not discover any special foundation for thisoptimism.General Veselovski, commanding the Second Army, is of opinion the present difficultieswill gradually be overcome and the Army will be stronger than before, but how andwhen this desired end is to be attained he was unable to say. He considersreorganization is proceeding fairly satisfactory. The best stimulant would be asuccessful offensive by the Russians on any part of the front.13. Officers depressed but anxious to continue the war. Officers generally, thoughconsiderably depressed, are anxious to continue the war to the end. With more menof character in the officer class the situation could very soon be got in hand butunfortunately such men are conspicuous by their absence. There are many who aredoing their best to establish order on a new basis but they have a very difficult task,and at present all efforts seem to be ineffectual. Fully 90 per cent, of officers aremonarchists at heart and out of all sympathy with the republican views of the majority ofthe men&apos;s representatives.14. Strong man wanted. The only hope, of which there are no signs at present, isin the appearance of a strong man, whether War Minister or Commander-in-Chief, whowill force the various elements to unite by enforcing discipline and so re-establishthe normal relation of superior and subordinate and with it the lost prestige of theofficer class.15. Ignorance. After 2^ years of war it is a melancholy fact that 75 per cent, ofRussian soldiers have no idea of what they are fighting for. When on this subjectRussian officers often tell the following anecdote as an illustration of the mentality ofthe average soldier. The spirits of three Allied soldiers killed in action met andjourneyed to Heaven together. When they appeared at St. Peters wicket he askedwhy they had gone out to face death on the battlefield.   They replied severally, theEnglishman: &quot;To beat the - Germans!&quot; the Frenchman: &quot;For France andliberty!&quot; and the Russian :-&quot; Ne mogu znat, Vashe Sviatost!&quot; &quot; I cannot know, yourHoliness!&quot;16. Absence of patriotism. Patriotism, collective or individual, is a thing unknown.The Russian realizes vaguely that he is &quot; defending his country,&quot; because the phrase hasbeen drummed into him since the war began and he sees the enemy in occupation ofRussian soil, but unless his own little bit of Russia is threatened or invaded, this doesnot cause him any concern, and the peasant would far prefer to be sitting at home.The men elected to the various committees are mostly chosen from the moreintelligent non-commissioned officers and soldiers, but many of these also are pitifullyignorant. The complaint of the intelligent non-commissioned officer and soldier is thesame as that of the officer.   They say the unenlightened mass of the men realizes the
force of their argument while they are actually speaking to them, and they all agree asto the need for continuing the war; but a few minutqs later a red-hot revolutionary orextremist will receive the same attention and the same applause, though advocating cheexact opposite, and the words of the one who speaks last will have the most effect.Conclusion.17. Disastrous influence of agitators. It is obvious that agitators are the cause ofthree-fourths of tbe trouble at the front to-day. In a nation of 80 per cent, ofilliterates, the agitator has naturally an easy task, and until the danger is cut off at itssource and agitators are forbidden to the area of the active army, no improvement canbe expected.It is next to impossible to counteract their influence once they get amongst thetroops since they belong to the same class as the men and have their completeconfidence. Those who speak against them are usually of the upper class and, asRussia is in the throes of a social revolution, these people are at once howled down asanti-revolutionaries, bourgeois or agents provocateurs.The decline of the influence and prestige of officers is solely to be ascribed to themischievous activities of these agitators who have so prejudiced relations betweenofficers and men to the detriment of the former that the men now readily accept asgospel the most fantastic stories and construe the simplest act into an attempt attreachery.An officer of the Guard Jaeger Regiment told me a certain division when orderedto move in support to another position refused to obey because the men suspectedtheir front was being purposely weakened.In another instance, also in the Guards, an order was given to prepare deep widetrenches in expectation of an attack by German &quot; tanks.&quot; The men thought this wasbeing done to provide ready made cover for the enemy and refused to carry outthe work.19. Russian Army an armed hand of peasants. The cavalry and artillery are ina better state than the infantry) but taken as a whole the Russian Army to-day is anarmed band of ignorant peasants out of control of its officers and directed by a smallpercentage of literate non-commissioned officers and men who are liable to be deposedshould they act counter to the wishes of the mass.20. Letter of protest. Mr. Purishkevitch, the well-known member of the Duma,strongly attacks in an open letter the &quot; Bolshevik&quot; or &quot; Majority&quot; section of theSocialist Party which, shouting loudest, is doing the most harm in the army to-day.The whole Russian Press was obliged to refuse publication of the letter owing tothe refusal of all printers&apos; workmen throughout Russia to set up the type, acting underorders of the Petrograd Socialist and Labour Organization.The passing of the letter for publication by the men&apos;s Committee of the TenthArmy, where I gave it to the Quartermaster-General on 23rd April, almost caused amutiny. The men proceeded to depose their committee and published a leaflet to warnall soldiers that the letter was an attempt to cause a split between the workmen andsoldiers.I have the honour to be, &amp;c,C. THORNHILL, Major,Assistant Military Attache.

</content>
</cab>
