<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/104 images: 608-617</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Government.i SECRET.wpjirao) SOU.i aogi November, 19k0.&quot;WAR CABINET.TRADE RELATIONS WITH EIRE.Copy No.K rMemorandum by. the Secretary of State forDominion&apos;Affairs.At their meeting on the 19th August (Conclusion Nell inNo.33o(k1)) the War/Cabinet authorised the conclusion -of a comprehensive;-, agreement; with Eire on trade matters, on the basisoutlined in a&apos; draft agreement which was before the Cabinet. -   this draft agreement--included provision for a payment to Eire in respectof .fat cattle imported from her of  500,000 a year, -  It also included-certain undertakings on the part of Eire in connexion withtrans-shipment arid storage facilities in Eire ports.    Theagreement was to run&quot;for twelve months only.-    &apos;&apos; -I &quot;circulate the reply of the.Eire Government to theseproposals,.1  Briefly, the Eire reply&quot;rejects the proposal thattrans-shipment and storage&apos; facilities&apos; should be provided in Eireports. &apos; It is&apos;understood that the&quot; reason is that. Eire regards them as incompatible with..-neutrality and. fears that they, would-lead to immediate German,attacks on the ports concerned if not on Eire as awhole..    The Eire&apos;reply also seeks certain assurances, which were not previously offered, in regard to the provision and insurance ofshipping for Eire trade and the rates to be paid for&apos; that shipping.Whilst apparently accepting the offer of, 500,000 in settlement of claims for increased prices for-Eire products in 1940, ..it asks,thatit. &quot;be linked with the. purchase of dairy produce and bacon and notwith fat cattle.   As regards- future years&apos;, the reply.rejects thesuggestion of compensatory&apos;payments and asks for either preciselyor approximately-the United Kingdom prices for all Eire-productssold to this country. . -The Eire reply has been &apos; discussed -at a meeting of , theUnited Kingdom Ministers principally concerned, at which.Sir John Maffey was also present, and it has&apos;been agreed that it isnot possible to accept the Eire request for the United Kingdom price for all her primary products, or her request for guarantees as- tothe provision of and the rates to be paid for - shipping..-   .     -&quot;It appeared to the- -Ministers; concerned that&apos;in present   -&apos;circumstances the possible alternatives&apos; open to us are&apos;as follows:-(l)    to. inform.Eire that, as she is unable to accept the clauses -relating to the;provision of trans-shipment and storage facilities:in Eire ports, and as we are unable, to go furthertowards meeting the Eire request for higher&quot;prices for herprimary, products, or to give the guarantees asked for asregards, shipping, if appears that&apos; there is.no longer-any basis for. agreement, and that the:discussions had bettercome to an end. &quot;&apos;.(2)    to agree to drop, the -trans-shipment and storage proposals  -and to offer, to. sign -the. agreement submitted to them on26th August, including the offer of  500,000, otherwiseunchanged. .The argument in support of the former alternative is thwhen the matter was first, considered by the War Cabinet, the offe,of  500,000.. to- the eire authorities was thought only to be justifas a quid pro quo for the trans-shipment and storage facilities.Eire has now declined these, we should not agree to give her themoney without receiving some tangible concession in return.In support of the second alternative, it is pointed outthat the Minister of Shipping no longer attaches the same importance as hitherto to the trans-shipment and storage proposals.    Althoughchanged circumstances may arise in the future in which the use ofthese
these facilities would he of value, they could not.be usedimmediately, even if they were now. obtained, since^all the small craft available are already being used for.the same purpose inUnited Kingdom ports, and since it might be dangerous to have anaccumulation of shipping in ports5; Where anti-aircraft and anti-submarine protection could not be provided..- We should in fact loselittle or nothing by making this concession, though it could be &apos;represented to the Eire Government as a- considerable gesture onour part, and has therefore a material&apos;value as a. bargaining counter.&apos;-&apos;- Secondly,, there&apos; is some advantage in not depressingfarming in Eire, both from the &quot;nearby larder.&quot; aspect and becausefrom the trading point, of view it is desirable to maintain the -complementary character of the economics of the two countries.Indeed, when the discussions with Eire first started, the offer of 500,000 was introduced as a measure of compensation for theadmittedly low prices offered to Eire for her dairy produce .andbacon.    Thirdly, it is urged that it is undesirable to incur the unfavourable reactions which would-result in Eire from insistingupon the , from- our point of viewcomparatively minor. trans-shipmentand storage proposals,.particularly&apos;a&quot;$ a&apos;time when developmentson major political issues between-the two countries may occur.The Minister, of Pood, however, points out that the valueof the .&quot;nearby larder&quot; depends to a &apos; great,extent on whether Eire --agricultural exports to the United Kingdom are produced from-  -  -feeding stuffs grown in 13ire or from feeding stuffs imported from overseas.    To the extent&apos;that Eire is dependent upon imported supplies of feeding, stuffs, to create an exportable surplus shecannot properly be regarded as a nearby larder.    The feeding stuffsmight just as well come to the United Kingdom and be used for -producing bacon, eggs, etc.    The&apos; ilinister of Agriculture considersthat in view of the anticipated shortage of feeding stuffs hereour previous need f or Irish store- cattle hajs, been considerably -reduced.    Moreover, Eire. tia.&amp; no other market; for her products. &quot;.&apos; Thereis therefore :no need.to bribe&quot; her, at all-events&apos; at this-stage.:   - &apos;   Some of my colleagues are in favour of course (l) -above.While- I fully recognise&apos; that strong arguments may be adduced infavour of either, course, I have personally.-been, driven to theconclusion-that the.second is the wiser..   In my&apos;view, there is-noquestion of a., bribe.    We are &apos; faced, at\ this moment, with thepossibilityindeed ,the, probability, of. a major clash.with Eireover the use .of the Irish, portsr :- I;-t is to my mind of the first importance that JL-t should..be made as clear -as may be toMr;  de Valera that we are actuated-by no general animosity against their-,;and- that -if we&apos; are&apos; obliged to ;occupy the&apos;ports,,, this is apractical strategic measure, essential for winning the war, victory in which is as essential for the-liberty and security of.Eire as itis for our own. . To show ourselves willing to.continue&apos; these negotiations at the present juncture seems to offer the best chance-of so convincing&quot; him, and I-&apos;feel that it should not beneglected..    I feel too that ,the- argument of the nearly larder hasa. certain added force, at*&apos;a time when our shipping position is soprecarious.    -:,        . -     &apos;. If : this course&apos; is &quot;adopted, the communication to the eire government-would&quot; indicate ;that, as-&apos;regards &apos; the payment of the sumif  500,-000,.-although&apos;we cannot agree that this money should be^efini-tely; linked with&apos;; dairy produce:and. bacon, we would beprepared to consider&quot; &apos;&apos;al^U^a&apos;tiVd-*-&apos;sugg-es.^ibhs from, the Eire &apos; side- ast&apos;o the purposes-:-to.-which it. should be applied in Eire.    We shouldbf&apos;&apos;:cburse make- It clear&apos; that;.the&quot;agreement is for one year only,and that- it muat_.be&quot;&quot;open^tef:VeviBX.on in the light of changed circumstances,;,, &apos;. \.&apos;        &apos;&quot;\ &apos;\    -.     1.&quot; , &apos;. .-.     : CRAKBORNE.0        &apos;  bth November, 19h0.
BO 4Memorandum in reply to the Draft Heads of Agreement furnished tothe High Commissioner for Ireland on ,24th August., 1940.SECTION A,1. The Irish Government regret that they are unable toagree to the proposals for the provision of facilities fortranshipment and storage which they consider impracticableunder existing conditions.2. If the Irish Government are to accept the restrictionproposed under Head A.1,  it is considered that the Ministryof Shipping should undertake to provide tonnage for an agreedshipping programme in respect of Irish import and export tradeand that freights and insurance- should not be higher thanthose applicable in respect of British trade.     In thisconnection,  it is suggested that provision should be made forthe granting of facilities for the insurance, through the british war Risks Office, of ships chartered for Irish trade and forcargoes or consignments to or from Ireland...3. The agreement should include an undertaking on behalf ofthe United Kingdom Governme. t to provide the necessary foreign exchange for reasonable requirements of Eire.4. . The agreement should also include a provision that theUnited Kingdom Government will facilitate the supply of reasonable Irish requirements in respect of fertilizers, farmand garden seeds,  agricultural machinery, steel billets andsheets, motor spirit, coal etc.5. The Irish Government are prepared in principle to agreeto the proposals in Section A.-.of the draft Heads apart from&apos;.-,para-graphs 3 and 4 of that Section.SECTION B. .&quot;   - -   &apos;6.GENERAL.The prices being paid by the -Ministry of Food for manyclasses of agricultural commodities exported from Eire are having.a depressing effect on output and are militatingseriously against the efforts which the Government are makingto ensure increased production,  or even to maintain normalproduction,  during the war emergency period.     Costs ofproduction have advanced considerably so that in the case ofmany commodities the farmers&apos; margin of profit has been eliminatedor becomeso narrow as to render production not worth while.Under existing circumstances farmers will be obliged to contract their output as the. only means of obviating losses andthey will be thrown back on a subsistence -form..of agriculturewhich will leave little surplus available for export purposes.Fundamental changes of this.nature would have far-reachingrepercussions on the economic structure and policy of thecountry and would profoundly affect the industrial position aswell as the Import trade.7* ADJUSTMENT IN RESPECT OF YEAR 1940.The method suggested in paragraph B.3 of the British DraftHeads
Heads of Agreement for distributing a sum of  500,000 to producers of fat cattle is open to the objection that it would be impossibleto devise administrative arrangements which would ensure that thebenefits would be passed on to the producers.    The payment of sucha sum was originally proposed as a recompense for the uneconomicprice being offered for Eire dairy products.      In the circumstances which now exist and having regard to the lapse of time since&apos;these proposals were first discussed,  it is considered that thesum of  500,000 should be paid over to be utilised for thepurpose of bringing the returns from dairy products supplied to&apos;the Ministry of Pood in 1940 up   to an economic level and alsoto utilise some portion of it in bringing the price of theadditional bacon already supplied at 95/- per cwt. up to 133/6d.per cwt.      By this means it would be possible to ensure that the producers most adversely affected by low prices paid in 1940 would obtain the benefit of the additional payment of  500,000.As regards future arrangements, however, the onlysatisfactory course is to fix economic prices-for the variousproducts in respect of the year 1941 so as to obviate the questionof further additional compensatory payments.8.DAIRY produce the pre-war price obtained for butter by creameries inNorthern Ireland was the same as that obtained by creameriesin Eire.     The cost of producing milk and its manufacture intodairy produce in Northern Ireland are no greater than those in eire.     The prices for milk and butter have been substantiallyraised in Great Britain and Northern Ireland to cofripensatefor the increased costs of production under present conditions.The price for milk delivered to Northern Ireland creameries,including additional payments recently announced,  is equivalentto butter prices of 166/Sd. per cwt. for period April to June,  188/4d.- for July and 199/2d.  for August and September.     The lastmentioned price would provide about 8a. per gallon for milkdelivered to these creameries.     The offer of 126/- per cwt.ex quay (equivalent to about 4-gd. per gallon for milk delivered to creameries) for Eire butter produced under the same conditions is entirely inadequate.The lowest price at which milk production for manufacturecan be maintained in hire is 6d. per gallon. This is equivalentto a creamery butter price of 163/- per cwt. ex quay.The following is a revised table of quantities and pricesproposed for Eire dairy products&apos;to be sold to the Ministry of food in the year 1941.      (The prices are for delivery ex.quayGreat Britain or ex railway station Belfast).Commodity
&quot;Commodity____Quantity_______price_cwt.Ireamery Butter 320^000 163/- ner cwt.farm Butter - Table    - 4, 00C 154/- &quot; &quot; &apos;   &quot;Manufacturing 3,000 135/-    &quot;      &quot;Iheddar Cheese 40,000 106/-    &quot;      &quot;    (in bulk)londensed Milk Per case ofs.    doFull Cream - Sweetened) 37,500 48 x if pints       26. 6.) 96 x 7        &quot; 29,10o) o .. .Unsweetened ) 48 x 2 23. 0.fsiam ... ) 48 x 2-5 20:  8.142,000  48 x 1- 17:  1.848 x if 13:   8.Juried Milk - Whole 7,000 110/- per cwt.9. pat cattle.The increased prices fixed by the Ministry of Food forBritish produced fat cattle as from 15th July,  1940,  theextension of which to cattle exported from Eire has been refused, widen still further the gap between the prices paid for British cattle of the classes eligible for subsidy andfor cattle of like classes exported from Eire and introduce a gap which had not hitherto existed between the prices ofother classes of fat cattle produced in the United kingdomand exported from Eire.      This further differentiation in price was made without any recognition of increasing costs ofproduction in Eire through causes over which the country hasno control.    It constitutes, moreover,  a departure from theprinciple which was indicated to Irish representatives atdiscussions in regard to the arrangements for taking overfat cattle from Eire by the Ministry of Pood to the effect thatthe prices which would be paid for fat cattle exported from eire to the United Kingdom would, be the same as those paid forBritish animals of like cpuality, less the amount of theBritish subsidy then being paid in the case of those classesof cattle eligible for subsidy.The agreement should provide that the dead weight price to be paid for first quality steers, heifers and cow-heifersimported from Eire shall not be lower than the price ofBritish home-bred cattle of similar quality by more than the equivalent of 5/- per cwt. live weight and that in the case of animals in other grades the price shall be the equivalent ofthe price of home-bred animals-10 o SHEEP.It was made clear at discussions regarding the purchase ofsheep by the Ministry of Pood that the prices to be paid forsheep
sheep and lambs exported from riire for slaughter would be thesame as those paid to British producers for animals of likequality and this principle was accepted3      This position was maintained up to 15th July,  1940s      As from that date new prices were announced by the Ministry of Pood for all classes of Britishsheep but the extension of the new prices to sheep from Eire wasrefusedoThe Agreement should provide that the position which existedup to 15th July, 1940, should be restored,,11. LIVE PIGS.The Air-is try of rood agreed to purchase live pigs exported from hire at the same prices per score, dead weight, as - thoseprescribed by the Ministry and operating on 15th January,  1940.&apos;The prices for British-produced pigs were stepped-up twice, on20th May,  1940, and again on 1st July,  1940.   Neither of these increases was made applicable to pigs from Eire but when theprice of British pigs was recently stepped down the Ministryintimated that it was intended to reduce the price of certainclasses of Eire pigs below the level operating on 15th January,1940The agreement should provide that prices paid for live pigsshould be on the same level as those fixed from time to time forBritish-produced pigs, the nurnbex^s for 1941 to be agreed inadvance *12, B AC 01!.In January, 1940, the Ministry of rood agreed to purchase the surplus bacon available for export from rare to the Unitedkingdom at an agreed price (133/6d. per cwt. for Wiltshire sides).This price was on a parity with the price of British-producedbacon which,  in turn, was related to the prices fixed for pigsin Great Britain.     The surplus was estimated at 500,000 cwts.for the year commencing from the date the arrangement came intooperation, and no indication was given by the Ministry duringthe discussions which then took place that bacon in excess of theestimated surplus would not be covered by the arrangement.In early summer it became evident that supplies of bacon inexcess of 500,000 cwts. per annum would be available0     TheMinistry of&apos; Food refused to accept any increased quantity ofbacon except at the reduced price of 95/- per cwt.The price agreed to last January is bareljr economic havingregard to the cost of feeding and other actual increases infarming costs.      It is entirely uneconomic to produce bacon inSire at 95/- x^er cwt.The agreement should provide that an annual quota of600,000 cwt. be fixed to cover the shipment of bacon from Eire,the purchase price for the whole quota to be the ex factory pricefixed from time to time for bacon cured in England.13.  PREbSEP MEATS.The agreement should provide that the prices to be paid for dressed meats - beef, mutton and lamb and fresh pork -delivered
9 fi ^0 Jodelivered to the Wholesale Meat Associations at the nearest ports in Great Britain should he related to thecorresponding dead weight prices agreed to for live animals.14. LARD,Practically the entire surplus of lard and other animalfats produced in Lire was marketed in Great Britain and NorthernIreland prior to January,  1940.      The importation of lard intothe United Kingdom was prohibited as from 20th January,  1940, andconsequently Lire producers have been excluded from any outlet for surplus lard and other fats since that date.The agreement should provide that a quota to cover the shipment of 30,000 cwt. of lard should be fixed at a price tobe agreed upon from time to time and that licences for theimportation of other surplus animal fats in agreed quantitiesand at agreed prices should be granted..The price arrangement for eggs suggested in the DraftSchedule, that is,  &quot;on a parity with other&apos; imported eggs&quot; ismuch too vague to be acceptable.     Eggs exported from Eire tothe United Kingdom are now the only unstored eggs imported into that country and are of similar quality to British and NorthernIreland produced eggs.     The prices agreed to for our eggs shouldbe the same as, or be closely related to, those fixed from timeto time for British home-produced eggs.16. POTATOES.The arrangement for the purchase of seed potatoes from Lireshould provide for the purchase by the Ministry of i-ood of thesurplus seed crop of varieties acceptable tothe Ministry at prices to be agreed upon and that the Ministry would endeavourto accept not less than 10,000 tons of wane potatoes at agreedprice s.17. FLAX.The price to be paid for flax produced in Sire should bethe same as that paid to Northern Ireland producers.5-




</content>
</cab>
