<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/7/28 images: 402-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property op his britannic majestvs goyejrnmentTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.198S EG R E ToV.P.(40)148 V(/ISO 0.0.S. (40)329)COPY NO. ^ war CABINEToARUBAAND CURACAOs    PROTECTION OP OIL REFINERIESIN THE EVENT OF A GERMAN - INVASION OF HOLLAND.Report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee.Sicrni f icaji c e,The Dujtch &quot;le^t Indian Islands of Aruba and Curacaoare of great strategic importance on account of the largeoil refineries which deal with the bulk of the output ofVenezuelan oil, the supply&apos; of Y/hich is of vital importanceto our war efforta       The degree of importance of this source.of supply would be considerably increased in theevent of the Mediterranean route being closed,,H0M, Consul at Willemstad has reported that the localDutch Authorities at Curacao are alive to the possibilityof the security of the Islands being threatened in the eventof a German invasion of Holland. Rumours are currentlocally that Venezuela has designs on Curacao in that event.Defence precautions are stated to have been re-doubled.Forms of Attack^2. The security of the oil refineries in the DutchWest Indies might be threatened by;-(a) Sabotage^(b) Bombardment raid by armed merchant vessel orsubmarinea(c) Attack by raiding parties from similar craft.

Sabotage.,3. In the light of their recent activities in scandinavia it seems possible that the Germans may have prepared a comprehensive scheme for immediate sabotageeither through the medium of employees in the refineriesor by the crews of German ships lying in the harboursThere is also a possibility of internal disturbances beingfomented   by local pro-German elements,,      It is understoodthat the danger is realised by the American element,,especially at Aruba,  and that anti-sabotage precautionshave been taken,h. The only action that we can take in advance to avert this danger is to warn the Dutch Government to beon their guard0        In the event of a German invasion of holland taking place it would he very advisable to occupy the Islands without loss of time in order to safeguard our     important interests.     A further advantage of so doing would be that it would enable us to seize theGerman merchant shipping sheltering in the islands.Bombardment raid by armed merchant vessels or submarine.5. All the refineries, being situated on the coast,are vulnerable to bombardment from the sea.        Thetwo installations in Aruba, which island is devoid of defences, are particularly exposed, though their Americanownership might perhaps he some safeguard.       The refineryin Curacao^ which is owned by Anglo-Dutch interests, is somewhat less exposed, being situated inside the harbourof Willemstad, which is believed to have    some modern7,5-inch coast defence guns although there is some

2 godoubt whether they have yet been mounted.        There arealso 2 Dutch submarine ines and a gunnery instruction,ship stationed at Willemstad, the presence of which,would afford some protection.Si&apos;    &apos; &apos; The fact that the Islands are situated inthe American neutrality zone nakes attack by german regular ^aval surfac e forces unlikely.    Thecover provided by the existing Allied forces in theCarribean , would also afford some protection.     Attack,by disguised raider or submarine remains a possibility,however, against which the only certain defence wouldbe the installation cf coast defence guns, which--wouldtake some time.       Local submarine patrols would be aiuseful safeguard and these could probably be provided bythe two Dutch submarines on the station.Attack by raiding parties.7. We do hot feel that this is a likely eventuality,but   there is the chance of a raider evading our       ipatrols.    A small garrison in each Island would   suffice to guard against this threat, as well as the dangei?   of sabotage.   The Dutch are believed to have a few marines&apos;In Curacao, but Allied control would be ne^ss&apos;sary to; d,,ensure that proper precautions, are taken.Allied Action.8, We consider that energetic Allied&apos; action toensure the security of the oil refineries in Curacooand Aruba in the event of a German invasion Of Hollandis highly desirable, and that. such..action should include

occupation by Allied troops, which, the British ambassador in Washington considers would be unlikely to offend American -susceptibilities in such circumstances..  Certain preliminarysteps have already been taken on the initiative of theAdmiralty.force (a) available.9. The equivalent of three regular infantry companies couldh6 made, available at once from Kingston for service in Curacaowithout prejudicing the present internal situation inJamaica.    They should, however, be replaced as soon as ispossible either by raising new local forces or byreinforcements    from overseas,10. The French would be prepared to send a small detach-ment from the Garrison of Martinique,  and for administrativereasons it would be a convenient division of responsibilityfor the British to occupy Curacao and the French Aruba.The French High Command has agreed to these arrangements, butthe concurrence of the French Government has not yet beenreceived.Co-operation with U.S.A.11. We agree with the suggestion by the british ambassador in Washington concerning the participation of-theU.S.A., and we accordingly suggest that an invitation to theU.S* Government to share in the control of the IslandsBhouid be made concurrently with our occupation, but thatno previous warning of our intention should be given.R e c pmmenda t i ons.12. We recommend that:-(a)    early action should be taken through diplomatic channels to ensure that the Dutch Government arealive to the importance of guarding against sabotageto the oil refineries,.-4-

(to)Tn the event of a German invasion of Hollandlocal French and British forces should immediately occupy the Islands of Aruha andCuracao respectively.(e)The agreement of the French Government to theproposed action should he obtained.(d) The general control of the operations should be vested in the Commander-in-Chief America and west Indies Stations.(e) The Admiralty should be responsible for initiatingthe operations when the occasion arises.(f) Concurrently with the occupation of the Islands,but not before, a formal invitation to the U.S.A.Government to share in the occupation of the islands be made.(Signed)DUDLEY POUND.11J.G.  DILL .(For C. I. G.S. )ttR.E.C. PEIRS2(For C. A.S. )Cabinet War Room.5-




</content>
</cab>
