<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/54/0 images: 80-83</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DO((.. i/IENT IS THE PROPERTYOF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY-*S GOVERNMENT)confidential. (52) 262 COPY NO.25th JULY, 1952.CABINETPRIVILEGES AND IMMUNITIES for international ORGANISATIONSMemorandum by the Lord chancellor at the meeting of the Cabinet on the 24th June, 1952 (C.C.(52) 62ndConclusions, Minute 6), the Attorney-General and I were asked to considerwhether &quot;the Government are committed by agreements to which they are partiesto accord the prescribed privileges and immunities to the organisations listed in Annex III to the Foreign Secretary&apos;s paper C. (52) 191&quot;   The Attorney-General is submitting a separate paper.   The organisations referred to are asfollows: -(a) Specialised Agencies of the United NationsUniversal Postal UnionInternational TelecommunicationsUnionWorld Health OrganisationWorld Meteorological OrganisationMaritime Consultative OrganisationInternational Trade Organisation(b)   Other OrganisationsNorth Atlantic Treaty OrganisationEuropean Payments UnionInternational Wheat CouncilCustoms Co-operation council. At common law representatives of foreign sovereign States, and membersof their official staffs, are entitled to diplomatic privileges and immunities.   it follows that representatives of foreign States on the international organisationsunder consideration, and their personal staffs, are already entitled to substantialprivileges and immunities in this country.   This is an important fact because,as I show, some of the international conventions and agreements, to which we area party, have the effect, not of increasing but of diminishing, the scope of the privileges to which some of the individuals affected would be entitled at common law.   Sufficient weight does not appear to have been given to this considerationby those who have opposed the making of the relevant Orders in Council.   Noris it always remembered that diplomatic privileges and immunities are rights,not of the individuals concerned, but of the foreign State itself which can andusually does waive them.3,    The Specialised Agencies of the United nations the International Convention on Privileges and Immunities for the specialised Agencies of the United Nations was adopted by the General Assembly
United Nations on the 21st December, 1947. Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment took the initiative in this matter.   The object of theConvention wasto unify and limit the privileges and immunities to which the specialised agencies, representatives of States thereon, and various officials were to beentitled.   Its effect was in some respects to diminish the scale of privilegesto which the individual would otherwise be entitled at common law.   Forexample, theConvention provides, in its standard clauses, that immunity fromlegal process is only to be available in respect of acts done in an officialcapacity; there is no such limitation at common law for diplomatic representatives.   On the other hand the Convention went further than the common law in proposing to confer privileges on the organisations themselves andtheir officials,4, The Convention of 1947 is not an easy document to construe.   Itspecifies a number of organisations which are declared to beSpecialisedAgencies, and provides for others to be added later on.   No State is bound to accord to any Agency the specified privileges and immunities unless and until it has adhered to the Convention in respect of that Agency.On one view the terms of the Convention (and in particular Section 43)have the effect of preserving complete freedom of action to an individual state to decide whether or not to adhere to the Convention in respect of any Agency,even if it is a member of that Agency.   The other, and in my opinion the right,view is that the provisions of the Convention relating to accession oughtproperly to be regarded as machinery, and that any country which is a partyto the Convention - as the United Kingdom is - is committed to the applicationof it to any Specialised Agency of which it is a member, and from which itderives all the benefits of membership.   This view, moreover, is consistent with the action which has already been taken by Her Majesty&apos;s Government,because we have now adhered to the Convention in respect of a number of specialised Agencies mentioned in the Convention.5. Moreover, besides being &quot;committed&quot; as a party to the convention of 1947 to grant privileges and immunities to all those Specialised agencies of which we are members, we may be also bound by the terms of the agreements which set them up:  and many of these agreements themselves expressly providefor the grant of privileges, although often in rather general terras. 3Wcreferto various instances below. ^6. r$R* now consider the case of each of the Specialised Agencies&apos; in turn:-(1) The Universal Postal Union    We have not acceded to the Convention of1947 in respect of this Agency, nor have we been parties to any separate agreement conferring privileges and immunities upon it.   But we are already under an obligation at common law to accord diplomatic privileges and immunities to the representatives of Member States (and their staffs) on this body, and although it may be argued that, as we have been a member of thisinternational organisation for upwards of seventy years, it is unnecessary tomake special provision for it, it is one of the Specialised Agencies  specifically mentioned in the Convention and, for the reasons mentioned in paragraph 4of this Opinion, I consider that we are committed to accede to the convention in respect of it, and to pass the necessary Order in Council to enable us to doso.   The result will be to reduce the degree of privilege to those alreadyentitled to it but to confer privilege on some who would not otherwise enjoy it.(2) The International Telecommunications Union The position here is precisely the same as it is in respect of the Universal Postal Union.
koOThe World Health Organisation   We have already acceded to the convention7 in respect of this Specialised Agency.   It has a separate annex to theConventionj modifying the standard clauses, and we have already accepted oneamendment to that annex.   Tv/o Orders in Council have already been made forthis purpose.   Her Majesty&apos;s Government are now asked to accord privilegesnot only to the members of the organisation, but to associate members.   Theseare defined in Article 8 of the agreement setting up the organisation as&quot;territories or groups of territories which are not responsible for the conductof their international relations&quot;.   Having regard to our adherence to theConvention of 1947 in respect of the organisation, it would clearly be unreasonable to refuse the grant of privileges to these associate members.(4)   The World Meteorological Organisation Her Majesty&apos;s Government have ratified the agreement setting up this organisation.  Article 27 provides that theorganisation, representatives of members on it, and officials, shall enjoy suchprivileges and immunities as are &quot;necessary for the exercise of their functions&quot;and as shall be defined in a separate agreement.   An annex to the Convention of1947 defining the privileges for this organisation has been prepared and depositedwith the Secretary-General of the United Nations, in accordance with theprocedure laid down by the Convention of 1947.   In my view we are committed,by the terms of the agreement, to give effect to the annex defining theirprivileges and immunities.(5)   The Maritime Consultative Organisation.   Her Majesty&apos;s Government have ratified the agreement setting up this organisation.   Article 50 of the agreementprovides that the privileges and immunities of the organisation shall be governed by the Convention of 1947, and Article 51 provides that, until it accedes to theConvention in respect of the organisation, each Member State on the organisationundertakes to apply the provisions of Appendix II to the agreement.   This Appendixprovides for the grant of such privileges and immunities as are necessary for theindependent exercise of functions in connection with the organisation, and thatin applying the provisions of the Appendix the Member States &quot;shall take intoaccount as far as possible the standard clauses of the Convention&quot;.   There is inmy view a binding obligation to apply the provisions of the Appendix to theagreement until we accede to the Convention in respect of the organisation.(6) The International Trade Organisation I now understand that this organisation will probably never be set up, and I make no observations about it.7,    Other. organisations the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation   Her Majesty&apos;s Government have signed, but have not ratified, the agreement on the Status of the North atlantic treaty Organisation, National Representatives and International Staffs, of the20th September, 1951.   This agreement, for which express Cabinet authority was given when the last Government was in power, accords greater privilegesthan is usual under an agreement to which Her Majesty&apos;s Government are parties.The agreement was based upon a draft supplied by the British Delegation, and theChairman of the body concerned with the drafting was British.There is some authority for the view that by signing an agreementa State places itself under no binding duty to ratify it.   But, as Oppenheim pointsout (6th Edition, Volume I, p. 818), a State which has created for itself a reputationfor arbitrarily refusing or delaying ratification may, in practice, find itscontractual capacity somewhat impaired.   In fact it is not the practice ofHer Majesty&apos;s Government to sign international agreements which they do not intend to ratify.   In this instance, there are obvious political reasons why it wouldbe manifestly impossible to disregard our signature and go back upon theagreement.
The European Payments Union   This body has been in existence for thepasl two years and Her Majesty&apos;s Government have been fully participatingmembers,   The agreement setting up the organisation has not been ratified by Her Maj. ity&apos;s Government, but Her Majesty&apos;s Government has signeda Protocol of Provisional Application which provides that the parties to the protocol shall apply the agreement provisionally as if it had been effective from 1st July, 1950.   Under the terms of the agreement the privilegesaccorded to the organisation relate to such matters as financial transactions and facilities in respect of communications and do not confer any privileges and immunities upon individuals. In my view we are bound to accord the limitedprivileges prescribed for the organisation.(3) The International Wheat Council   Again, Her Majesty&apos;s Government have ratified the agreement setting up this organisation, the headquarters of whichare in London.   The agreement provides for very limited priviloges andhaving ratified the agreement we are bound to accord them.(4)   The Customs Co-operation Council   We have signed the agreement settingup this organisation, but we have not yet ratified it.   The privileges and immunities to be accorded to the Council are set out in detail in an annex.   Inmy opinion, for the reasons mentioned in relation to the North atlantic treaty Organisation agreement, we are &quot;committed&quot; to its ratification.Simonds.Lord Chancellor^ Office, S.W.125th July, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
