<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/54/0 images: 131-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1952Copy No.   ggCABINETBOARDING EDUCATION FOR CHILDREN OF SERVICE PARENTS PROPOSALS FOR FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE ;Memorandum by the Minister of defence for some time the Defence Departments have been studying the problems of affording some assistance to Service parents in order to ensure that their childrenget suitable education.2. The special difficulty facing Service parents arises mainly from theirfrequent moves from one station to another as a result of which their children&apos;sschooling is seriously interrupted; children may attend as many as three or fourschools before reaching secondary school age (11 plus), and this alone makes it very difficult for them to attain the qualifying standard for &quot; grammar school&quot;education. Changes of home after that age are even more disturbing to the educational progress of the children. The normal way to avoid handicapping thechildren in this way is to send them to boarding school, and the high and increasingcost of doing so places many married officers of the middle ranks in serious financial difficulties and constitutes a powerful incentive to leave the Forces,especially for the most highly-qualified officers, who can find well-paid posts incivil life.3. Thus, both on educational grounds and in order to keep in the services the men of most value to them, it is of great importance to find a solution to theproblem.4. After discussion with my Service colleagues, we came to the conclusionthat there was a strong case for granting a measure of financial assistance towardsthe education of the children of those Service parents who have been subject tofrequent posting in the course of their duties, and who are likely to continue to besubject to similar moves. I therefore proposed to the Chancellor of the exchequer that tax-free educational allowances should be granted to Service parents, whereverserving, at rates corresponding to those authorised for Civil Servants requiredto serve abroad. These annual grants are:  50 a year for the first child,  75 forthe second and each subsequent child in the family, and  25 for each child (afterthe first) living with a guardian or sent to boarding school under local EducationAuthority arrangements. The awards would be limited to cases where the Serviceparent has been frequently moved or is liable to constant posting.5. The Chancellor has not been able to accept these proposals on the grounds that Service parents have always been liable to frequent moves and that this factor has been taken into account in determining the 1950 pay increases. He doesnot admit the validity of the suggested analogy with the Civil Servant becausethe latter&apos;s remuneration does not contain a specific disturbance element. Further,he claims that the income tax reliefs which Service officers will enjoy under his budget proposals increase their ability to meet these special expenses. I have examined these objections with the Service Ministers and we feel that we mustpress for this decision to be reconsidered.6. Owing largely to the requirements of the Cold War, members of theForces are, in fact, liable to more frequent posting than was previously the case.confidential. (52) 2788th August, 195242732
This disadvantage, which has now become intensified, prevents the child of Serviceparents from enjoying as good educational advantages as the child of nearly allother parents. The grants proposed would be some help in putting the Servicechild on- an equality with other children. lAll H ?G iy; J7. It is our view, as my predecessor, Mr. Shinwell, expressly informed The&quot;then Chancellor in a letter of 9th August, 1951, that the 1950 pay increases shouldnot be regarded as a bar to the improvement of particular aspects of Service con--ditions from time to time if sufficiently good reasons can be shown. The amountof money involved in financing these grants would be more than repaid by retainingfor the State the services of many valuable officers in the middle ranks who, mainly because of the difficulty of providing for the education of their children, are finding the attraction of more settled, and perhaps more remunerative, employment out-side too strong for them.8, As regards the analogy with the Civil Service, we do not agree that the&quot; disturbance element,&quot; which is in any case incapable of evaluation, has everprovided compensation for the particular disability in relation to the education of children which is inseparable from present conditions of mobility.9. We cannot regard the Budget reliefs afforded to the taxpayer generally which were designed to offset the reduction of food subsidies and other cost-of-living changes-as haying any relevance to the grant of educational assistance to service parents in need of it.10. We are not seeking to put the Service parent in a privileged position at the taxpayer^ expense as regards his children&apos;s education, in comparison withthe civilian parent. But we are satisfied that if the children of Service parents areto enjoy broadly equivalent educational opportunities to those of civilian parentsthey should be able to benefit from unbroken education at boarding school. Forthis reason we are asking for a measure of financial assistance for Service parentswho are finding this an increasingly heavy burden to carry. I and my Servicecolleagues feel therefore that they must press for the introduction of the schemeof educational grants outlined in paragraph 4 above.A.Ministry of Defence, S.W. 1,8th August,&apos; 1952.

</content>
</cab>
