<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/54/0 images: 251-251</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
LEGISLATIVE programme memorandum by the Minister of supply at their meeting on 8th July, 1952, (C. C.(52) 66th Conclusions, Ivinute 1 )the Cabinet approved the Parliamentary time-table proposed by thePrime Minister.    In accordance with this time-table the transport bill and the Iron and Steel Bill were to be introduced early in the new session, and were to be proceeded with concurrently.    It was estimated that this would enable the Transport Bill to become lawby the middle of March, and the Iron and Steel Bill by the end of April.2.   The revised legislative programme since proposed by theLord Privy Seal (C. (52) 261) provides only two days for the Iron andSteel Bill before Christmas and does not contemplate that it will necessarily be completed until the House rises in August.3.   I am much concerned about the effects of this possible postpone-ment.4.   It is most important that the Iron and Steel Bill should be passedas soon as possible, for the reasons set out in my memorandum c.(52) 149, of 5th May, namely:-(a) to end the present state of uncertainty and lack of responsible leadership in the industry;(b) to give time for a substantial part of the nationalised companies to be returned to privateenterprise and for the new supervisory organisa-tion to prove its worth before another GeneralElection.5.   Moreover, since this matter was last considered by the Cabinet,the White Paper on steel has been published and has been well received in most quarters.    The advantage of going ahead with theBill before the effects of these favourable reactions   have worn off is,I submit, a further argument against postponement.6.   I. trust, therefore, that the time-table approved by the Cabinet inJ&apos;uly will be adhered to.    If, however, it should be found that, for reasons not then foreseen, the two Bills cannot be proceeded withconcurrently, I would ask that the desirability of taking the committee stage of the Iron and Steel Bill first should be considered..D.S..COPY NO,Ministry of Supply.8TH SEPTEMBER, 1952.S E C RET--&quot;C.(52) 2938TH SEPTEMBER, 1952CABINET

</content>
</cab>
