<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/2/0 images: 26-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1945.SECRET.CM. (45)51st Conclusions.Copy No.CABINET 51 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 8th November, 1945, at 10-45 a.m.&apos;PresentThe Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Stansgate,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply and of aircraft production (Item 4).Sir Hartley Shawcross, K.C., M.P.,Attorney General (Item 5).Mr. G. Buchanan, M.P., Joint Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State forScotland (Items 5-6).The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Minister of State (Items 1-3).The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury(Items 1 and 2).General Sir Ronald Adam, Bt.,Adjutant-General to the Forces(Item 5).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.[30868]b
CABINET 51 (45).minute no.Contents.Subject.1      ParliamentNational Insurance (Industrial Injuries) Bill.Business in House of Commons.2      Leakage of information      United Nations OrganisationLocation of Headquarters.4      Atomic EnergyInternational Control.5      Man-PowerRelease of Doctors from the Armed Forces.6      The Communist PartyAttitude of Departments towards Organisations influenced or controlled by the Party.Page231231231233233234
1. The Lord Privy Seal reported the results of a meeting which he and the Minister of National Insurance had held theprevious afternoon with the group of Government supportersinterested in the National Insurance (Industrial Injuries) Bill.This meeting had discussed the situation created by the action takenby those Members earlier in the day in carrying an amendmentagainst the Government in Standing Committee on that Bill. after a prolonged discussion the meeting had passed a resolution in favourof the bill&apos;s being passed into law, and had agreed that they wouldnot press to a Division the remaining amendments of which theyhad given notice. They had further agreed that, if the Oppositiondeclined to agree that any of these amendments should, after discussion, be withdrawn, they would vote with the Government ina Division.Business in The Lord President informed the Cabinet of the business whichHouse of it was proposed to take in the House of Commons during the commons.       following week.The Cabinet were also informed that a further Debate onforeign affairs was planned for the 21st and 22nd November. Itwas pointed out that, if the Prime Minister had not by then returnedto this country, it might be more convenient that this Debate shouldbe postponed, as there would otherwise be a demand for yet anotherDebate on foreign affairs after his return. The Lord Presidentundertook to keep this point in mind in arranging parliamentary business for the week beginning the 19th November.Parliament.national insurance(industrial injuries)Bill.(previous reference erence:CM. (45) 39thConclusions,Minute 1.)Leakage of 2.   The Prime Minister said that Mr. Churchill was asking aInformation. Question that afternoon, by private notice, about the premature disclosure in the Press of information of the governments intentions in respect of a national hospital service. There had beenother recent occasions on which the Press appeared to have obtainedconfidential information on matters under discussion by the cabinet or its Committees; and he was seriously concerned about theseapparent leakages of information.After a short discussion the Prime Minister undertook to circulate a note stressing the need for discretion in relation to matters under discussion by the Cabinet or its Committees.UnitedNationsOrganisation.Location ofHeadquarters.(previous reference:C.M.(45)38thConclusions,Minute 5.)3. At their meeting on the 4th October the Cabinet had agreedto discuss further the choice of site for the headquarters of theUnited Nations Organisation. The Cabinet how had before them amemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(CP. (45) 259) recommending that in the Preparatory CommissionHis Majesty&apos;s Government should continue to support the view thatthe headquarters of the United Nations Organisation should be inEurope.The Foreign Secretary said that, although the UnitedStates Government could not openly oppose the decision reached by the Executive Committee of the PreparatoryCommission in favour of a site in the United States, they werenot likely to be displeased if this decision was reversed in thePreparatory Commission. There could be no criticism of ourconduct if we pressed strongly the desirability of a European sie and, indeed, if we failed to do this we should weaken our positionin the eyes of European countries who looked to us for leadership.Support for a site in Europe would not compel us to advocateGeneva.[30868]b 2
In discussion the following points were made : (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he still thought there would be advantages in the choice of a site in the UnitedStates from the point of view of enlisting the support and interestof the United States in the United Nations Organisation. In any event, he would be strongly opposed to the selection of Geneva,which was associated with the failure of the League of Nations andwas not likely to be acceptable to the Soviet Government.(b) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that of theDominion Governments only Australia pressed strongly for a site inthe United States. The Canadian Government, on balance,favoured Europe, though they would oppose the selection of Geneva.South Africa was strongly in favour of a site in Europe, whileNew Zealand had not expressed any definite view.(c) The Minister of Education said that the location of the headquarters of the United Nations Educational and cultural organisation was being discussed at the Conference now being heldin London and it would be necessary for His Majesty&apos;s Governmentto indicate their views on this matter. There was considerable support for a French proposal that the headquarters of this organisation should be in Paris. The Minister asked for authorityto support this suggestion, even though it was likely that the head-quarters of the United Nations Organisation would be establishedelsewhere in Europe : there was much to be said for not concen-trating in one city the headquarters of all the various international organisations which were being set up.(d) The Minister of State said that, while there might be something to be said for a separate location for the United nations educational and Cultural Organisation, it should be the generalaim to bring together in one place the headquarters of the various international bodies connected with the United Nations Organisa-tion. This would reduce the risk that different parts of theOrganisation would pursue inconsistent policies : it would make it easier to provide common services more economically and efficiently: and it would make for better reporting of theproceedings through the Press and radio. The fact that the head-quarters were located together need not preclude the holding of conferences in different countries from time to time.(e) Attention was drawn to the danger that the success of theUnited Nations Organisation might be prejudiced through theestablishment of an excessive number of international bodies, and itwas suggested that a comprehensive report should be submitted tothe Cabinet on the number and functions of the various bodies whichhad been or were to be established.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the representatives of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment on the Preparatory Commission should press thearguments in favour of locating in Europe the head-quarters of the United Nations Organisation, but shouldnot press the claims of Geneva.(2) Agreed that, if it became necessary to state on behalf ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government a view regarding the location of the headquarters of the United Nations educational and Cultural Organisation, no objection need be raised to a proposal that the headquarters of this organisation should be established in Paris for the time being.(3) Invited the Minister of State to submit a report givingdetails of the various international bodies which were already in existence or were to be established inconnection with the United Nations Organisation,together with information as to the steps which werebeing taken to prevent duplication among them. (SeeCM. (45) 49th Conclusions, Minute 6.)
atomic energy.international control.4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the PrimeMinister (CP. (45) 272) indicating the line which he proposed totake in his forthcoming discussions with President Truman andMr. Mackenzie King about the international control of atomic energy.A record of the discussion and of the conclusions reached is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of Cabinet Conclusions.5. The Cabinet had before them a report by the HomeSecretary and the Attorney-General (CP. (45) 267) on the releaseof doctors from the Armed Forces.The Prime Minister recalled that he had asked the HomeSecretary and the Attorney-General to examine the possibility ofincreasing the number of doctors to be released from the armed forces in 1945 beyond the 4,500 releases which had been planned.He had been greatly concerned at the disparity between the ratio of doctors to the civil population and the ratio of doctors to personnel in the Armed Forces, and he was convinced that, now the war was over, there was no justification for the retention of such largenumbers of doctors in the Forces.The Home Secretary said that it was proposed in the reportthat the doctors in the Services should be reduced by the end of1945 to a number giving a ratio of two doctors per thousand. Thiswould involve a net release of 7,745 in the period from the 18th june to the 31st December, and would, in his view, leave the Services withenough doctors to provide an adequate medical service even afterallowance was made for a higher ratio in the Far East. Therelease proposed fell short by 1,125 doctors of the minimum demandmade by the Minister of Health and the Secretary of State forScotland and, including&apos;all doctors serving the civil population, didno more than bring the ratio for the civil population up to one doctorper thousand. There was a tendency for doctors released from theForces not to revert to general practice and it was doubtful whetherthe ratio of general practitioners to civil population would riseabove -47 per thousand. In order to achieve the releases proposedit would be necessary to depart to some extent from the principlesof demobilisation by age and length of service and, in order to ensurethat the right kind of doctors were released and that they shouldpractise in the places where the need was greatest, the number of releases in Class B should be increased.Points in discussion were : (a) The First Lord of the Admiralty said that in the years1929-33, when rigid economy was being practised in the armed forces, the ratio of doctors to personnel had never fallen belowfour per thousand. He had not been able to work out the full implications of the proposals made by the Home Secretary and the attorney-General, but he believed that if 1,265 doctors were released from the Royal Navy it would not be possible to maintain areasonable minimum standard of medical attention.(b) The Secretary of State for War said that he also had been unable to give full consideration to these proposals. He felt,however, that if the Army had to surrender 5,600 doctors there wasa grave risk that occupational troops in Germany would sufferseriously from the epidemics which were likely to arise during thewinter.(c) The Secretary of State for Air said that he was prepared toaccept the proposal for the release of 880 doctors from the RoyalAir Force. The proportion of doctors to personnel was alreadylower in the Royal Air Force than in the other two Services, despite the fact that there was a high accident rate in the R.A.F.Man-Power.Release of doctors fromthe armed forces.(previous reference:L.P.(45)25thMeeting,Minute 3.)
(d) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that he fully supported the proposals made in the report, in view of the dangerous situation which had arisen owing to the shortage of doctors for the civilian population. There was good reason to believethat the services of doctors were wastefully used in the Forces, andthere was a strong case for an investigation designed to lead to amore scientific employment of the doctors available to the Forces.(e) The Minister of Health stressed the importance of taking steps to ensure that the proposals made in CP. (45) 267 werepromptly implemented. Progress reports should be submitted at frequent intervals showing the numbers released.The Cabinet-(1) Approved the following net releases of doctors from the armed Forces in the period from 18th June to31st December : Royal Navy       ...      ....      1,265Army      .........      5,600R.A.F.......... 880Total      ......      7,745(2) Agreed that figures showing the progress made with therelease of doctors from the Armed Forces should beincluded in the fortnightly statistical reports on theprogress of demobilisation which the Minister of Labourand National Service had undertaken to supply to thePrime Minister.The 6.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeCommunist     Secretary (CP. (45) 242).Party. The Cabinet were informed that it had been decided in 1942Attitude of that organisations materially influenced or controlled by a politicalDepartments party, or run to serve the interests of a political party, should nottowards be given official support, and that Ministers should consult the HomeOrganisations Secretary when any occasion arose which seemed likely to comeinfluenced or within this decision. The only organisations which had, in fact,controlled by come within the terms of the Cabinet decision had been thosethe Party. influenced or controlled by the Communist Party. The question for(Previous decision was whether the policy laid down by the War Cabinet in reference:      1942 should be maintained.W.M.(42)72nd Lord President said that in his experience it had been conclusions,     convenient for Ministers or Departments to seek advice from them mute 9.)      Home Secretary when they were asked to lend their support toorganisations about which there was some doubt.  It was, of course,always open to any Minister who disagreed with the advice given tosubmit the matter to the Prime Minister or to the Cabinet.The Cabinet-Agreed to maintain the existing practice by which ministers and Departments sought the advice of the HomeSecretary when asked to give support or assistance toorganisations likely to be under the influence or control ofthe Communist Party.Cabinet Offi.ce, S.W. 1,8th November, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
