<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/3/0 images: 13-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M. 38(45). 3rd April, 1945. (11.30. a.m.) Post-war Trade: Views of Mr. Baruch. P.M. Optimism of Baruch, readiness to offer facilities to float our import requirements: confidence in world boom condns. J.A. Credits will be offered: diffy. will be to refuse those whose terms are not satisfactory. World Organisation. P.M. Will Doms. object to multiple vote? D.O. They don’t like it: but will register their protest.. P.M. If there is a row, I ought to be there. D.O. Prob. Thursdy p.m. when F.O. giving genl. picture of foreign pol. P.M. Russians mayn’t go because Lublin Poles not to be asked. Even so, wd. be disposed to go ahead. There will be 40 odd States there. Unless events here side-track it. D.O. Shd. we go on with Yalta compromise on voting if Russia doesn’t attend? It was based on assumptn tht. great Powers wd. pay the game. Diff. to defend the veto if it is apparent tht. Russia can’t be relied on. P.M. Agree don’t like it: but we must face the facts, includg. R.’s power. Change of atmosphere since Yalta – suggests tht. Stalin is not in supreme control. We don’t suffer from giving fuller repn to small nations: ques is wtr. it is worth makg. that concession to get R. in. D.O. But we shall have tied our hands – by giving her a veto. P.M. What alternative – unless you are prepared to fight against Russia. We have bn. able to save nothing in the Balkans except Greece: R. is fastening own types of Govt. in all other countries, includg. now Vienna. Czechoslovakia: Poland: Yugoslavia. D.O. Agree we can’t slam the door. Wd. it be wiser to postpone the Confce. M.A.P. But on merits believe compromise is sound &amp; realistic – fr. our angle too. P.M. To indicate no confce w’out R. wd. increase her sense of self-importance.

M.A.P. Most unfortunate to postpone S. Fr. on tht. a/c. P.M. Agree: another matter if collapse of G. made postponement inevitable. International Aspects of Colonial Policy. P.M. Agenda for S.F. was to be world organn . Territl trusteeship to be mentioned but no business to be done of that. C.O. Must be some discn in U.S. before S.F. U.S. intend to raise it there, &amp; do some business there. P.M. Our answer shd. be: ready to have same relations to a parent body as we had with L/N. L.P. But want to be rid of some hampering restns . C.O. Now propose to drop earlier scheme: accept continuance of mandates: but seek to remove some limiting restns . E.g. tht. we can’t have fortified base ina Mandated territory: wh. we breached on loss of Singapore: tht. we give unrestricted field to mission schools: they must fit in to the agreed plan for education. J.A. We had to stop Missionaries going into N. Nigeria. C.O. Modifns wd. need discn in detail. At S. Fr. do us more than accept in principle continuance of system &amp; reserve its detailed discn for later mtg. P.M. All we have promised to discuss – a) territories taken from enemy b) L/N. mandates c) territories wishing to put themselves in trust. L.P. Fear that U.S. might suggest that all existing colonial dependencies should come under “trust” condns. Cad. “Voluntarily” means the will of the sovereign power, not that of the Dependency. Ch. That shd. be made clear. And anyway it will provoke agitation. P.M. Not much to fear: the world organisation wd. make a mess of it. Cad. Nothing to prevent such agitation, whatever to say in the agreement or at S. Fr.

M.A.P. Has bn. agreed at Yalta. c.f. W.P.(45) 208. Cad. And obviously means “placed” by the sovereign power. P.M. That must be made abundantly clear at S. Fr. C.O. Even so, some alarm. Cd. be done w’out provn for it. Providing for it implies tht. it is going to be used. We must therefore either a) say at once we don’t mean to use it or b) leave all Colonies to worry themselves to death over it. P.M. Yalta doesn’t preclude us from raising this sort of ques. (as against W.P. (45) 208). All is open for discussion. J.A. Yalta means: This is to be discussed: and the rest are limiting phrases. Limiting the scope of the matters to be discussed. P.M. Agreed: important so to record it. H.O. Supported C.O. view: power is inherent: needn’t be provided for: if it is, may mislead – for we at least have no intentn to use it. P.M. No reason why you shdn’t raise that suggn in discn. These are only points for discn &amp; nothing to prevent us from submitting that argument. We are perfectly free in the discussion. I do not accept para. 3 of W.P. (45) 208. C.O. Timing. B. repve to go to Washington for talks. Decided not to go until Tuesday: so as to let Doms. have a chance. F.O. now say wanted on 9/4 if there’s to be time. Does D.O. still think such delay is inevitable. D.O. Some Doms. have strong views: their repres will want to consult Govts. C.O. No final decn at W’ton. Main thing to be said (continuance of Mandates) is acceptable to them. D.O. Let C.O. ask them after end of discn with Doms. to-morrow. But if they then ask for time, hard to deny it. Ch. Let them start: telegraph instns to them after arrival. World Organisation. (a) Non-Permanent Membership of Security Council.

D.O. Summarised Memo. Canadian pressure for recognition of “middle Powers”. S. Africa against: Australia will support. Para. 11. plan – assumes no increase in size of Council. Don’t like the plan because it discriminates between Doms. But can’t think of a better. May I put it to the Dom. Confce. M/L. Believe you can’t adjust the voting on so narrow a Council. S. Am. States will hang together &amp; work a majority. Cad. Put this point to AE. who feels v. strongly that smaller is more effective. Also any extension will mean U.S. will try to add Brazil. U.S. &amp; R. will be against any increase. H.O. Solution by informal agreemt. (as in L/N.) that one Dom. will always Have a seat. P.M. Larger Council – wd. mean tht. all business wd. be done behind the scenes between the great Powers. L.P. Hasn’t S. Africa as good a case as Belgium. Latter only justified by includg. coloued populns. M.A.P. U.S. wdn’t agree this list – with only one S. American State in it. P.M. How will this list strike others. 3 “Doms” included. India, they will say, will do what U.K. Govt. say. Foreigners won’t like it: and 2 of our Doms. will be affronted. L.P. Better basis: one Europe: one Asia: Africa: America (N. and Central and S.): Australasia. Agreed: put this basis forward in lieu of para. 11. (b) Obligations of States not represented on Council. D.O. Canadian proposal wd. take all the teeth out of the organisation. Must be rejected. [Agreed. World Organisation: Outstanding Points. a) Guarantee of Territorial Integrity. Cad. Such a provn led to rigidity in L/N. constitution. U.S., R. and ourselves agree on this. Essential if any scope to be left for Treaty revision.

D. Oaks plan made no provn for this: &amp; no repns against its omission. Australia now propose to raise it: &amp; N. Zealand has criticised it. P.M. Indicated some doubts. Cad. Deployed other arguments. b) Guarantee of Political Independence. Cad. As in para. 9. D.O. V. diff. to defend not giving this guarantee. If they press it strongly at Dom. Conf., diff. not to give way. – neither territorial nor political. M.A.P. Do we guarantee pol. integrity of Ukraine? J.A. And what of India? Then, if we agree, we have to define it. [ Agreed: can’t do it. M.A.P. Every Treaty derogates fr. pol. independence. c) Domestic Jurisdiction. Cad. Under L/N. States were under no oblign to submit any domestic issues. This wd. give the new Organisation a right to intervene. d) Control of Enemy Powers. Cad. As in para. 16. The Permanent Members bear the burden. D.O. ? Add review in 5 years.. Approved W.P. 209 as basis for discn with Dom. Govts. Relationship of I.L.O. to new World Organisation. M/L. Labour &amp; employers approve this. [ Agreed.

</content>
</cab>
