<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/3/0 images: 22-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M. 47(45). 20th April, 1945. 1. The Budget. Statement by C/Exchequer. 2. Electoral (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill. H.O. Have informally consulted Party repres – broadly agreed. P.M. Assimilation of L. Govt. franchise has vastly increased e.g. electorate to disadvantage of Conservative Party. Business voter, equally: so arranged that people didn’t exercise their rights. H.O. Had to be a date. B. Gateshead only 5 out of 617. We can’t appeal because confined to those regn. x/ We wd. like to extend time for appeals by people who failed to get on register. – L.O. to advise wtr. this is legal. P.M. Won’t affect no. of seats. H.O. May affect about 6 seats. Don’t object to referring to L.O. This will be a bad register: the next (Oct.) will be better. e.g. London bldg. workers fr. Provinces: won’t have exercised right to vote here as absent voters. Equally evacuated persons will never go back to evacuation areas. Agreed: H.O. to consider x/. P.M. I exclude legn. H.O. It cd. go into this Bill. H.O. (a) Add 25% for first election. B. Wd. prefer to fight this Election on old law. i.e. financial arrangemts. shd. be left over to another Bill. Increased cost of newsprint &amp; printing. H.O. See App. II. The Party Agents think this enough save Lib. Nat who want £50 more for counties. P.M. Spkers’ Confce – 2 years ago. Circs. have changed.

M/L. It was unanimous recommn : why not consult Parties again. P.M. Apathy of voter will be feature of Election. Want to get as many votes as possible. M/L. Don’t want to impose this on the Parties. y/{Consult M.P.’s who served on Spkrs Confce. { &amp; 4 Party Agents. B. Or 4 Chairmen of Parties. H.O. No: why not keep the consultn with Parlt. P.M. Will consult with E.B. Alternative: do nothg. &amp; leave it to pre-war scale. A.S Supported suggn for consultn with Members. [Agreed as at y/. Much pressure fr. all Parties for action on remaining recommns of Sp. Conference. J.A. S.IV. Special Spring reg. Needed only if 2nd Genl. Electn next year and if Oct. Register not good. This will cost £3/4 m. Lot of money: is it necessary? General view: it is worth doing. 3. Release of Candidates from H.M. Forces. P.M. Told P.J. to prepare instns for candidates to return at once. May be a Poll in 80 days from now. Not too much time e.g. in county constituencies with 60/70 villages. No one to come who is in contact with enemy. M/L. Wrote a letter to P.M. on this. Para 4. Army pay &amp; allowces cease after 4 wks. P.M. But can’t be compulsory. Not willing to leave it to dissolution. A.S. Favour day of dissolution. Release at once will cause heartburning – for many of the best won’t wish to leave their jobs. Fairer to bring all out together later on. M/L. Apply to candidates same rule as M.P.’s. When bona fide adopted, can be released f.with. P.M. x/ { The M.P. has a right to come away at once – subj. to mil. necessity. { Appd candidate on same basis as sitting Member .. .. .. Agreed as at x/.

4. Release of Staff for Regn Officers &amp; Returning Officers. H.O. Outside figure 2.000. Applns 110 to date: but more will apply. A.S. Shd. know the extent of liability. M/L. Diffy. for me: everyone is asking for people. Have stood out against release from overseas. Can’t believe they are really experienced in regn - none since 1935. – they are staffs wanted by l.a.’s. H.O. We let the Party organisation have their people. We can’t do less for the official machine. P.M. Must do this. A.S. Exempt S.E.A. Command. – covered by mil. necessity. P.M. x/ With assurances they were employed on regn work. And limit of 1.000 all told – not worth a limit. Agreed: subject to x/ &amp; try to avoid S.E.A. Refer back to War Cab. if necessary to withdraw any from S.E.A. 5. Paper for General Election. P.M. Outraged tht. Cons., with 150 majority over other Parties, was to get only 500 out of 1.800. 1185 : 615 won’t do. We shall have the burden of caretaking: we shd. have a larger share. Preposterous that Liberals shd. have same quantity as Cons. &amp; Labour. Where are his promised 400 candidates? If in the event they run only 200, they can use double quantity of paper for them. Must be proportionate to bona fide candidates. Are co-opve really a Party? H.O. As much so as Nat. Liberals. y/ If Party running enough candidates to run a Govt. they shd. have same quantity. Their existg. membership is irrelevant. Liberals are fighting Cons. &amp; Labour. P.M. No. They are against Cons. &amp; have interest in a deadlock. A.S. We are fighting for ourselves – w’out Allies. P.M. My test = produce your candidates. A.S. Series of discussions – we all accepted.

P.M. I won’t agree. A.S. We shall certainly run 300-400. Accept the criterion of H.O. above. y/ P.M. My criterion wd. be - relate paper to no. of candidates. H.O. Must be 450-500: to justify a claim that they may get a majority. P.M. I will put in nominal list of adopted Cons. candidates: and get Labour: then Liberal must toe the line. Then we will consider. H.O. This is broadly right, subject to verification of Lib. candidates. M/L. Approve this: &amp; let them draw up to propn of candidates approved. Agreed: this is a fair proposition: if it can be worked out. J.A. Or assurance from Parties tht. they won’t issue more than amount correspondg. to no. of candidates running. H.O. This will work: M/L. suggestion wouldn’t. Init. provl . allocn on best estimate give now. But on condn they don’t put into circuln more paper than entitled to on a formula (1 ton p. candidate).

</content>
</cab>
