<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/3/0 images: 80-80</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 62(45). 13th December, 1945. 1. Offices of Profit: Proposed Select Committee. H.M. Sessional Sel. Cttee – so tht. any further cases can be referred to it. Power to sit in Recess. I.O.O. not sure wtr. these have commd offence. Read out proposed t. of r.

P.M. Not to recommend changes in law? H.M. No. Proposed that shd. be left to Govt. initiative. Genl. feeling that law shd. be amended. E.B. Diffy of e.g. M/L. in getting people to serve on such Panels – don’t want to scare people off who are candidates for Election prs. years ahead. J. Devise method of apptmt wh. automatically determines apptmt on election. P.M. Agree this present action must be taken. Also tht. law be amended. Ques: shd. amendmt. be proposed by Govt. or by S. Cttee. A.G. There is a report. Let us consider wtr. we propose legn to give effect to it. Agreed.

[Exit: A.G. and S.G.

[Enter: J. Griff. &amp; Paling 2. National Insurance Scheme. A.G. Summarised proposals in memo. Limited Duration. A.B. Supported J.G. What point in ceasing benefit after 30 wks. if State

has failed to find work or training before then. State is obliged

to maintain: ques. only by what means, benefit or assistance. P.M. What of married women? A.B. Shd. deal with special cases specially, not by general rule. M. women case always raises diffy: but if no job can be offered locally she shd. be treated as havg. fallen out of insurable class and treated as such by Regn. P.M. What Regn? Getting back to “not genuinely seekg. work.” T.W. What of seasonal workers – worst case if any. H’to worked 16 wks. &amp; drew benefit for remainder. If you try to define by Regn you’ll be driven back to Anomalies Act methods.

397

E.W. Continuous benefit wdn’t cost State more. Strongest argument against = take them off the Fund. But cd. be so administered tht. it was tighter on shirker than assistance. Recogn. m. women = crucial diffy. Meet it by makg. marriage a break unless in industry where she wd. normally go on working.

“need”: but ques. whether they are in the employment field.

P.M. A.B. harking back to conditions of depressed areas betwn. the wars.

P.M. Point if diff. – Many women now workg. who wdn’t normally work. Can’t see how Regn proposed by A.B. is diff. fr. “gen. seekg. work”. A.B. Diff. = onus of proof. Exchange must offer work. E.B. Is it just to put on contns the cost of abnormal unemployment? That is the issue. Insurance: shd. be definite contractual basis. Any discretionary adminn shd. be outside Fund &amp; outside Labour Exchange. If abnormal unemplt. occurs, remedy shd. not be on insurance. Pay the same, if you like, but not out of Fund. x/ Arguable that assistance payable to unemployed shd. not be the same as that designed for o.a.p. State and not the Fund must bear the responsibility if abnormal unemplt. occurs. On E.W. argument we don’t want to encourage a marriage break. Policy of maternity grants etc., is to encourage them to go on in emplt. Remedy is in x/: look into that. H.M. Recalled experience of 1931 – degeneracy of U.I. Fund – strongly supported E.B. After 30 wks. new situation arises. Govt. must be forced to look at econ. situation, generally locally &amp; by individual. H.D. Must retain 30 wks. – both for E.B.’s reason: also for financial reason that some, when situation reviewed, will cease to draw fr. any sources. We can’t balance our Budget etc., unless unemplt. for more than 30 wks. is cut to minimum. G.A.I. Consider this – after 30 wks. State to pay, but at insurance rate, subject to needs test. Genuine workman wd. have no diffy. in provg. need. But m. woman wdn’t get away with it. Not pers. Problem now is rather the individual cases such as M. women who are not genuinely in the emplt. market. E.B. Insurance shd. continue on contractual basis – shd. be no ques. of discretion or onus of proof. E.Sh. If full emplt. is our policy – long before 30 weeks State must take positive action. 398

But need shdn’t be introduced after the 30 wks. – only tests re willingness to take work or training. E.B. Those tests must be considered separately – as tests for unemployed class w’in the assistance field. This fight on u. benefit &amp; assistance betwn. the wars has caused national indiscipline in this sphere. – cheating the Fund instead of pride in not claiming. P.M. Let us agree that liability of Insurance Fund shall be limited to 30 wks. y/ That is all we need decide for Bill. Condns of payment after 30 wks. can be considered subsequently &amp; separately. G.H. More diff. than m. women = men between 50/65 who can’t go on working and can’t be moved. Agree Fund shdn’t maintain them. E.B. By alteration of assistance rules in 1941/2 I added 30-40 m. State pensioners not really un-employed at all. Some heavy industries – special scheme w’out age limit. It is invalidity not old age. Can’t define an age – e.g. in coal or steel. J/G. Two separate problems a) m. women. Ques. there [Exit C. Ede is wtr. they satisfy the first condition - [ Jowitt. available for work. Agree on that with W. Paper. Not a 30 wks. problem. Arises in 1st week. Not merely m. women only. b) People who can’t be placed w’in 30 wks. Agree State not Fund shd. carry it. Ques: how shall it be discharged. I must answer that in H/C. on this Bill. Only answer I can give now is Assistance. And remember test of need is in the Act &amp; can’t be changed by Reqn. Sending them to Assistce Bd. will revive v. bitter controversy

E.B. Why not give pledge to consider form in wh. State’s oblign shall be z/ discharged. Separate legn. We aren’t tied to existing law. Assurance in genl. terms. H.M. Don’t say anything to commit this Govt. to abolish test of need – generally. Agreed as at y and z. Statement at z to come to Cabinet. H.D. Pensions. Agree to 26/=. But no giving way to pressure for increases. Say nothg. at this state re special schemes for particular industries. E.B. Don’t want any reference to possibility of Exchequer assistance. But there are existg. schemes – will have to be adjusted. These are prized. Cd. J.G. say we wd. welcome or encourage specl. schemes – wd. be willing to allow State scheme machinery to be used in proper cases.

399

H.D. No objn qua existg. schemes. Don’t want talk about new schemes. Need to keep people longer in industry. E.Sh. Diffy. – existg. pension schemes in mines. Can’t leave it with them. For they are bound to extend. Want it said we wd. look with favour not only existg. but on further schemes so long as don’t involve addl. charge on Exch. H.D. Why say it now? E.B. To avert opposition fr. supporters of special schemes. ?Spk. in terms of special schemes: State willing to help at low cost on admin. machinery. Wd. give encouragemt. to trustees. Agreed. { special schemes, not limited to existing schemes. { Formula to be agreed with C/Exch.

P.L. Inducements. Alarmed at magnitude. Owing to ….. greater longevity. Problem of o.a.p. But also relief because can work to later age. Suppose he remains at work up to 70 because stronger and in favourable industry – then gets 50% more pension. Disparity with less fortunate neighbour. Fear you won’t hold that position. H.D. Inducements stop at 70. Want to get them to go on working. Difference is only 10/= or 20/= for a couple. Deserved well of the State. P.M. Human fortunes. Equally hard luck if a man dies at 61! Agreed: as in memo. P.L. drawing attentn to dangers. Contributions H.M. In W. Paper we contemplated power to vary contributions. Is it possible to include it in this Bill? J.G. V. diff. to work this system. Wd. put Fund off actuarial basis. You wd. have to provide correspondg. contn by Exchequer. H.M. Don’t ask for decn to-day. But want it examined seriously. E.B. I wd. take genl. powers. Agreed: Social Services Cttee to examine &amp; report. [Exit: Griff &amp; Paling. 3. Parliament. H.M. Explained business. A. Hope to get Bldg. Materials Bill thro’ on Thursday – tho’ only recd Bill on Mon. p.m. Managed 2nd rdg. on Tuesd. But amendmts. 400

desired by Dpts. wh. will have to go back to H/C. Cutting it v. fine. H.M. Sorry – but must get the Bill. E.W. Adjournment Day. Ques? W.W. 11-12. Will allow St. Cttees. to sit. 4. Levant States. E.B. Propose to sign Agreemt. to-day. Read it out. Mtg. on 21/12 to agree p’mme of evacuation. Sufft. forces to remain to guarantee security. Fr. m’while will retain forces re-grouped in Lebanon. This shd. end Fr. intrigues in Palestine &amp; Iraq - &amp; with Mufti. And at same time gets independence of Levant States. Best I can do. Propose to sign at 12 noon. Announce in Parlt. 3 p.m. Read out communiqué. J.J.L. We are going to leave a token Force?

E.B. May have to leave none. Depends on discn. Agreed.

5. Motions of Gratitude to War Leaders.

P.M. Saw W.S.C. and A.E. Still v. keen. Asked wtr. we cdn’t take repve figures. Read out terms of Ismay’s drafts. Separate draft for U.S. Commanders. They will table it if we don’t. Awkward to refuse time for U.S. Commrs. But cdn’t debate U.S. and not B. Commrs. Doms. pt. avoided. J.J.L. Omission of mention of anyone connd with Burma will cause diffy. A. Protests fr. Austr. and N.Z. are certain. P.L. And possibly from India. H.M. If we bless, we must do it ourselves. And trouble with own b. benchers. Suggest reasoned reply to W.S.C. askg. him in public interest not to proceed. Letter we cd. publish. If they table none the less, doubt if we shd. give time. E.B. Do C.O.S. want it? P.M. No. 401

A.V.A. Opportunities for Opposition on Service Estimates.

A.B. Undignified to debate relative contns of individuals. [ Exit W.W. Enter Wilmot &amp; Barnes. 6. Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Bill. E.Sh. This has bn. scrutinised by Socialising Ministers.

E.Sh. Directions – general, not related to day-to-day adminn.

Assets under b). Compensn on basis of sale betwn. willing buyer

up to £150 m. [Exit E.B.

H.D. We accept it, subject to further considn of some details. Assets will be transferred to Bd. Divided a) undertakgs. b) ancillary. And sub-division of b). Terms of compensation. For undertakgs., referred to arbitration. No figure suggested by my Dpt. (in spite of refces in Press) – our discns with industry were not negotiations. Thought from outset amount wd. be for a Tribunal. Greene, Cohen &amp; accountant agreed by both parties. Difficulty about t. of r. This now resolved. Vid. C.P.337. Arbitn can now proceed w’out waitg. for passage of Bill. May have come to concln on global figure before Cttee Stage concluded – in wh. event we cd. add it in a new Clause. &amp; seller. Subject to arbitration. Safeguarding public interest. V. diff. Genl. terms may not be effective – may be only façade. Decided in the end to have 2 statutory Consumers Councils. The “industrial” Council will deal with the industry but may represent to Minister. The “domestic” Council has less teeth in it but may be of same value. Coal Commn – to be transferred bodily to Coal Board. M. Welfare Commn. Part of its functions will be taken over by Bd: rest with Commn, but it will come under control of M/F. &amp; P. Will lose its independ. status, wh. has given rise to some diffy. They have bn. doing much wh. shd. be done by a good employer or the l.a. – bldgs. particularly. Much modernisation etc. Therefore Bill provides borrowg. powers Industry must pay its way. Must float the compensn. Some time before valuation complete. Eventually decided – for 2 yrs. fr. resting date (= reasonable interim period) they will receive ½ of profit vice interest to wh. they wd. have bn. entitled on global compensn sum. Expect £7 m. annually, providing for amortisation. Industry is makg. profit of £14 m. approx. Thus even on existg. standards, the industry can more than pay its way - &amp; may even be able to reduce a little the price of coal.

402

Parly. deficit. Was anxious to get short Bill. Cd. have run easily to 200 clauses. To do this have had to include 20 clauses empowerg. Minister to make Regs. There may be Parly. trouble over that. Bill = full of legal definitions. Shall want L.O.O. help.

This = bare skeleton: pivot on wh. re-organisation must turn. Can’t

indicate in Bill how we shall re-organise. Home to do that in my 2nd Readg. speech. P.M. Level of salaries.

E.Sh. Not in the Bill. Arguing that elsewhere. Must have personnel before Bill goes thro’ - &amp; must talk with them re re-organisation. Must have the best men – otherwise this may fail. Chairman, Deputy &amp; 7 Members. Want them all full-time. But want all to be functional e.g. commercial, technician, welfare, labour. Coming to L.P. Cttee to-morrow.

coul. u. wl take over automatically. But subsidiary assets

H.D. Drafting points on finance still under considn.

P.M. Retail distribution? E.Sh. Party Cttee with T.U.C. thought this shd. be p’poned until after dealg. with prodn. Proposg. Bd. shd. do all tht. private enterprise now does – but will expect Bd. to consult me on greater efficiency in distn, tho’ they won’t do it ‘selves. A.V.A. Optional transfer of assets. If owners are to have large options ….. E.Sh. We are takg. main – some of subsidiary assets. All that is part of as under b) above. Cases of doubt e.g. brick-works. We mayn’t want it: but owner mayn’t be able to operate it w’out the mine. Many other diff. cases – bound up with iron &amp; steel works: various farms also: these cases will be subject to arbitn. H.D. Investmt. p’mme of industry. Shd. be positive provn in Bill tht. Bd’s p’mme needs specific approval of Minister. E.Sh. Agree: thought it was provided for. - Cl. 18(2). Agreed H.D. and E.Sh. to consider wtr. more is needed. H.D. On earlier point: want Ty. as well as Minister to be mentioned. E.Sh. Accept Minister’s approval. But want to avoid charge that nationalised industry will be hamstrung by Ty. control. A.V.A. Separate Consumer’s Councils. Will they sit independently?

403

Risk of damnifying domestic consumer to get industrial rates cheaper. Can they meet jointly. E.Sh. Minister can bring them together. And I have power to make Regs. on their procedure.

H.D. Considered separate coal stock or part/ Nat. Debt. We decided on

R.S.C. Better put in the general language of Cl. 20(2). To avoid

A.B. How to amortise compn. Minister has bn. ingenious. But doesn’t para 13 put him in unnecessarily restrictive position? x/ brings him back to formal balance sheet. Stock redeemable. Psych. problem: persuade miners they aren’t workg. to make profits for coal-owners. This will make it look as tho’ they still are doing so. R.S.C. It will be put as a debt to Ty. not to coal-owners. E.Sh. May have disasters leading to loss of revenue. We must explain why. Or fr. our decn to reduce prices. We must lay facts before H/C. second. There are therefore no coal-owners save State. But tho’ you can’t say wh. part of N.D. this is, there is a relationship betwn. Coal Bd. &amp; Ty. We are anxious to avoid any concealed deficits. We must therefore make the position clear – and if there is inefficiency we mustn’t cloak it. A.B. y/ in para. 13 is inconsistent with merger in N. Debt. Agree pay fr. N. Funds. But is intimate relationship necessary? H.D. This is 1st large socialising measure. More to follow. [Return of E.B. Can’t agree to undertake to follow any system wh. fails to show clearly wtr. a natd industry is paying is way or not E.Sh. Anxious to have such a safeguard. A.B. V. weighty arguments on other side. Want to get natd industry away from conceptions of capitalist balance sheet. H.D. says that is necessary for good business. It isn’t – good costing methods may give you the same safeguards. R.S.C. A.B. wdn’t object to Cl. 20(2) but to 20(1)(a), wh. gives direct link with what is requd for compensation. It is the link between earnings and interest on compensation. H.M. Isn’t it bound to be so? psychological diffy. Agreed: examine language.

404

H.M. a) All Regns made subject to neg. resoln. Aren’t there some for

b) This Bill has no provn for compensatg. displaced employees.

wh. no resoln is needed. I agree with that but think attentn shd. be drawn to it. E.Sh. On b) I’m fortified by Rpt. on Gas Industry. Read extract. Posn wd. be Coal Bd. cd. do as it thought right. Bill approved – subject to points raised. [Enter Listowel. 7. Civil Service Leave at Christmas. H.D. Invited E.E.B. to speak on this. E.E.B. Read from Minute. a) Main ques. = shall we go back to full leave in 1946. b) Extra 3 days. 2 diffies (i) repercussions on industrials. (ii) really busy people cdn’t take advantage. I wd. therefore propose, as alternative, promise to extend e.g. to 30 days’ leave for 1946 &amp; suggest extra days at Xmas in anticipation of 1946 leave. H.D. We need to shut up the shop over Xmas. P.M. Better done by Ministers talking to senior officials &amp; setting an example. J.W. Cdn’t confine it to H.Q. Must go to out-stations. Then trouble at once with industrials. V. diff. therefore to close for a week.

P.M. Agree no general rule. Each Minister to consider position of his own senior officials. No public announcement. H.D. And no mtgs of Cab. or its Cttees. Agreed [Enter Winster &amp; Strachey Exit. Lawson. Listowel

8. British Air Services.

P.M. Complained of short notice. H.M. Ditto. But delays in the Dpt. Want more speed. W. Circulated earlier draft – to colleagues mainly interested &amp; later to L.P.’s group. T.W. Why can’t Dakotas be civilianised.

W. Yes – now recognise tht. there is authy to buy them. 405

E.B. Vitally important to get on with this. Cd. Cab. take this first item on Monday - &amp; stand by their decision. P.M. W. Paper – must be presented when? Agreed: consider Monday 11 a.m. E.B. Comments to be commd to W. before Monday. Exit Wilmot. Barnes Winster. 9. Service Pay &amp; Allowances.

Took note with approval.

H.D. Expld posn. P.M. said Cab. shd. consider basic rate. The concept is: build on basic rate equated (with allowances etc.) to Civil wage of 89/= p.w. 406



</content>
</cab>
