<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/3/0 images: 84-84</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 1(46). 1st January, 1946.

1. Moscow Discussions.

E.B. a) Peace Treaties. Arising from brkdown of C.F.M. B.’s proposal for confce accepted in principle – right to discuss &amp; amend - &amp; final revision of texts by 4-3-2. Powers.

in trouble. This pulled U.S. up in their monkey tricks.

accepted India.

Earlier publn of this concordat was due to U.S. political wishes.

others.

Diffy. over Doms. &amp; India. M. suggd 3 Baltic States if India included. Decided to risk aceptg. B. States, wh. put U.S. B talked with Stalin: &amp; M. then w’drew B. States &amp; Awaitg. reply fr. France. U.S. in too much of a hurry &amp; not suff. considerate of U.S. Delegn seemed conscience-stricken re India. Apologised to us for Byrnes.

b) Far Eastern Commn &amp; Allied Council in Tokyo.

There had bn. much prev. consultn between U.S. &amp; Russia.

by wh. one

Obvious tht. we cd. only get 4 Powers on A.C. Clear we cdn’t get separate repn for Australia. Concluded I cdn’t hold up US-R. settlement on this a/c. Therefore urged arrangemt. represented, not Commonwealth, but U.K.

finding diffy. in gettg. Forces for Japan – Evatt may be

India. Aust. &amp; N.Z. But noticeable tht. Austr. have bn. ahead of his publ. opinion. c) Korea. U.S. proposed indep. State in 5 yrs. Two commands are choking economic integrity of the country. Luckily

doesn’t concern us. Agreed to put to U.N.O. 4-power

Good thing to let Austr. be Comm. repve on this trust.

trusteeship, to co-operate in bringing in independent State. d) China. B. put on Agenda w’drawal of R. troops fr. Manchuria: M. countered – w’drawal U.S. troops from N. China. Appeared Ch. Govt. ad invited R. troops to remain, beyond

agreed date. In N. China Comm. Army – U.S. said

mind. U.S. sent in 50.000 marines: &amp; were ready to send

But didn’t want to go until all U.S. out of N. China.

thereby. Document put fwd. suggd Comm. shd. come in

Govt. Embarrassing to discuss w’out China.

500.000: Stalin said 50.000. U.S. said when Chang sent up to disarm Jap. they were stopped by Communists. R didn’t in Ch. by air. Appd R. had agreed with Ch. to be out of Manch. by 3/12. Then suggd put Comm. into Chang’s Govt. &amp; get truce throughout – not only central but local govt. units. I opposed: &amp; at end agreed Comm. shd. be only in central e) Balkans. R. put in Grose Govt. in Rum. King refused to recogn. Grose &amp; they have bn. carrying on unconstitutionally. Tr. 426

at Potsdam made unilateral decln tht. U.S. wd. never recogn. Gr. Govt. or Bulg. Govt. R. have gone on w’out it. Fr. our informn appears Rum. on edge of collapse. A.C.C. being asked now to invite U.S. &amp; U.K. to avert the collapse – tho’ we didn’t strip the country. After long discussions – agreement re Rumania. None re Bulgaria.

havg. included a Bulg. settlement. They then produced that. It

was not acceptable: M. then produced an alternative which,

after discn was accepted.

recognising these Govts. I wanted to get civil avn,

spot.

f) Persia.

When we met to sign &amp; I had signed U.K. &amp; U.S. version – R. not ready: when it arrived M. said delay was due to their I had prev. concluded it wasn’t poss. to delay much longer consulates etc., going – to build up relations. I didn’t therefore object to this settlement. No Balkan Party is pure. We saved posn of King – in Rum. agreemt. Commn is now on the Recognn won’t be long delayed. Long talk with Stalin. Believe R. had started the old

want is to come down at back of Turkey: then they’ll press

70.000 troops in Azerbaijan. St. said need to safeguard Baku

oil – v. sabotage. V. thin. He has no intn of annexing

have never implemd own constitn – hence R. find fertile

Also U.S. attitude wasn’t clear, tho’ on brk. down U.S.

game of pushing their policy by infiltration. What they the Straits issue. I asked our Amb. Tehran up &amp; asked wht. is alternative. R. have Azerb. – no need, if puppet Govt. There is Treaty of 1921: limited by exchange of lrs. (wh. shd. be circulated): under wh. R. can in certain circs. put troops into Persia. Persia soil in Ab. Drafted Persian proposals (in telegrams) for appointmt of local Councils. St. said = basis of settlement if Commn sent in. Persian Govt. not consulted: therefore I inserted “with approval of P. Govt.” U.S. didn’t like that: wanted “concurrence”. I accepted that. But R. wdn’t then carry the discns any further: saying Pers. P.M. had abused Sov. Govt. Final interview – as in telegram. Considered refusing to sign anythg. if no Persian settlement. Decided world opinion wd. be critical of thus losing agreements under a) – e). became alarmed. Byrnes then became more helpful &amp; aligned himself. Have sent proposals to Persia via Bullard: if P. Govt. accepts. I will commt tt e ee Mosc. &amp;

Persian Amb. y’day suggd to me it shd. be put thro’ U.N.O.

Wash. &amp; see if we can re-open on this basis. Doubt if they’ll get much comfort there (veto etc.). Inclined to advise them against this. We want to avoid friction in areas where our interests meet those of R. 427

g) General. Talk with St. Said we didn’t trust them re Tripolitania. I said

He is more concerned re

not a ques. of trust, but competition. He then said he was anxious we shdn’t quit Egypt. I asked for his symp. co-opn in our dealing with Egypt - &amp; he promised it. He welcomed our moves in India – referred to dangers of a separatist movement there – and he hoped India wd. remain in B. Empire. India &amp; Far East than Balkans.

h) Indonesia. Talk with M. &amp; St., both of whom thght we were seekg. to add it to B. Empire. I gave him assurance on this. Spoke, however, of Dutch claims which I said we cdn’t ignore. We were seeking Dutch/Indonesian settlement. This has bn. clarified. i) Greece. Long talk: asked us to w’draw our Forces. I said we were going to see election through &amp; re-establ. econom. posn. Want it to find its political legs. After that Greece was used only as pin-prick. j) Austria. We raised ques. of w’drawal of troops. They countered with charges of supportg. White Guard. – to avoid discn. There are 60.000 troops there. I offered to reduce to 20.000 each. They evaded discn. Same charges re B. Zone in Germany. Had to take stiff line, insistg. on w’drawal of all imputns v. commrs. General Ques. of W’drawal of Troops. My concln: (i) R. is afraid of bringing any more of Red Army back to R. The internal posn in R. is not good. 170.000

towns destroyed. No substantial amount of work going on. Machine highly geared for war: doubt if reconversion can get going as quickly as here. Doubt also wtr. they will be able to enforce labour control so strictly. Reasons: food &amp; discipline: keep them out durg. winter. (ii) They will try for repeat, move in May, for Peace Confce. They will then propose simultan. w’drawal, incldg. Greece &amp; China. k) Atomic Energy. U.S. tabled memo. omittg. substance of para. 8 of W’ton Decln – i.e. the proposal to move by stages. That I regard as vital para. Byrnes said omitted because thght. R wdn’t like it. I prevailed on him to some extent: &amp; he submd addl. para. I refused to sign w’out it. Discn adjourned. Next day R. accepted it. In later discn

(informal) I told St. we must be v. careful over this: &amp; he

Also advantages as well as dangers. Agreed: &amp; Rpts.

agreed. R. wanted whole control in Sec. Council. I said only on security side. Many other aspects. Not limited to atomic energy. 428

to be publd unless Sec. Council (i.e. unanimous agreemt) decide not to publish for security reasons. P.M. Gratitude to For. Secy., who has done v. well. A.B. R. Rule of no flying over R. territory. E.B. Raised this with Stalin. He is adamant. R. are averse to all internatl intercourse. They are suffering gt. economic upheaval &amp; diffy. Will refer to this in H/C.

E.Sh. Posn of France? E.B. I didn’t like 3. Power Mtgs. After next one in W’ton, hope no more. But Fr. does open her mouth v. wide for present weakness. R. has contempt for France. U.S. are not really acceptg. France as 1st cl. Power. E.Sh. But isn’t it to our ultimate advantage to draw more closely to France. Can’t say how. E.B. History of prejudice betwn. W.S.C. and de G. Below him, there is as good an understandg. with France as ever. But diff. to translate it into action. Collapse of Fr. adminve machine. H.D. We set aside £1 m. for Fr. wines. But they are in such a mess we can’t buy it. This = example of the diffies. E.B. And vice bldg. up on small things they will concentrate on e.g. Ruhr. Thus, they now want to start a campaign to break relations with Franco. A.B. This is diversionary – typical Comm. tactics. T.W. China. “Those on our side” – Edgar Snow. – said “Comm.” in in North were not really Comm. but democr. elected structure. Are they really democratic? E.B. Agreed all round tht. in these areas Govt. is better &amp; less corrupt than anywhere else. P.M. Visit of Dutch P.M. etc., Thursday. V. decent men. Van Mook seemed broad minded. Their proposals seemed sound. Compld they were being kept out of p. services etc., in N.E.I. Promised to

investigate. I was encouraged by this talk.

[Enter C.I.G.S and Creech-Jones. 429

2. Palestine. C.J. Telegrams confirm earlier reports on disturbances. 10 k. 11 wounded in 3 major outrages.

Precautionary measures taken earlier now supplemented by searches

High Comm. feels recent Govt. ruling v. genl. search shd.

&amp; arrests. be maintained – for genl. measures wd. destroy chances of Anglo-U.S. Commn. He is also against genl. fines &amp; levies. Favours re-affirming. our deprecn of violence. But no more. Raised ques. of Jewish Agency – as in telegrams. Police observn etc., of leaders wd. discredit moderate opinion. Immigrn. 75.000 under W. Paper are now nearly exhausted. F.O. x/ seekg. acquiescence of Arab States in continuance of present monthly rate, ad interim. C.I.G.S. Enough Force to deal with situation, if it becomes necessary.

E.B. Am in touch with Arab States.

Attitude to J. Agency. Do nothing. Don’t send for them again. If they

Speeding up re-inforcemt. of 1st Divn. – replacemt. of personnel. P.M. Ben Gurion &amp; a.n.other: attitude in not condemning outrages. – v. bad. Humanitarian consn Jews in Europe. A.B. What of the practical suggn of admittg. relatives. C.J. Diffy: we are now as at x/. This supplem. measure wd. complicate those approaches. J. Wd. have liked to see this suggn explored. P.M. Tr. is askg. about actual posn under Quota. E.B. Will consider with C.O. addg. to draft telegrams to Arab States the relatives suggn. If they refuse, we must take our own decision. ‘M’while, we mustn’t let the flow stop. C.O. must see to that. If Arabs complain, their fault for not replying. ask to come, enquire wtr. they are going to help. E.Sh. Shd. be announced that flow hasn’t bn. stopped. E.B. But Jewish Agency decided to boycott the 1.500 a month. This isn’t likely to be connected with attitude of J. Agency. [Exit: C.I.G.S. &amp; Creech-Jones [Enter: Hynd: N. Baker: Barnes

430

3. World Wheat Supplies.

P.M. Avoid discussion of detailed allocns w’in Ldn. Cttee area. Points for decision are in paras. 13-15. T.W. Summarised memo. Suggested reductions. Big cut is in UNRRA. M/F. doubt Italian claim. Pre-war ½ m. tons cpd. with 3m. claim. China: cdn’t be transported, even if available. U.K. stocks worse than ever. Will go below the 700.000 figure appd by Cab. before June – prob. to 550.000. If C.F.B. appd these cuts then wd. be a contingency reserve, fr. which G. &amp; Austria cd. draw. On para. 15 suggest defer until Austr. has replied to approach by M/Food. In para. 12. 600.000 is mis-print for 1.500.000. J.B.H. agreed. Allocns can be considered in detail in light of M/F. report on his W’ton talks. P.M. Work on Summary on p. 7.

Para. 14(ii). Recent telegram suggests Argentine O.K. for 3 months.

P.L. Wd. accept if a) supplies made in first 3 months – to prevent hoarding. b) substantial imports of rice from Siam etc. E.B. Siamese agreemt. now signed. R.S.C. Consumer goods – in hand. P.M. Telegram to present – Agreed. J. Are these facts known? T.W. C.F.B. calculations – 3 already. First, 10m. surplus. Second, July, all square. Third, Sept., 2m. deficit w’out enemy countries or

6m. with them.

Latest Oct. figures = 7m. deficit for half year. U.S. have no control over producer use of wheat. France scrapped all controls before elections – now re-instated, too late and push up their claims for import. We mustn’t suffer on this a/c. P.M. might impress on Fr. need for getting all wheat off their farms.

E.B. On facts: I answered P.Q. &amp; Salter asked for publn of supplies. I said wd. consider – for all food supplies for world as a whole, supply &amp; demand. x/ Think C.F.B. shd. consider publn. Ask M/F. to consider that. Agreed. 431

R.S.C. Can we suggest these drastic cuts – leavg. our own intact – with 2 exporting countries. T.W. We are cuttg. by 80.000 t. And we can’t drop our stocks any lower

than 550.000 in June.

R.S.C. What of extraction rate? We are only consumer country &amp; we suggest heavy cuts on all others. P.M. But we have cut and we have supplied to others. A.B. My advisers are alarmed. Fr. have 90% &amp; rationing. Europe is being reduced to starvation level. T.W. France collects nothg. from farms. A.B. In March we may regret not being sensibly altruistic now. J.B.H. Para. 12. 600.000. Memo. is based on that. Their needs cdn’t be met fr. contingency reserve. Offl. Cttee shd. be allowed to complete their work on the German supply posn. Accept para. 14 on understandg. tht. figures in App. II shdn’t be used until Offls. have examd. P.M. But para. 14(iii) leaves elbow room. J.B.H. But I don’t want G. &amp; A. left to contingency reserve. Want them included with other countries. T.W. Cd. be done on M/F. return. P.M. Agreed. P.L. Appeal for economy re bread. N.B. Yes – to world, not U.K. alone. E.B. might do it at U.N.O. Assembly. Need for more food for Germ. to prevent epidemics. Drastic cut on UNRRA. Poland: ration now said to be too small. Greece: UNRRA adjusts her supply to local supply. Italy: prodn cdn’t be normal because of war: also catastrophic crop failure. P.M. We are facing World deficit. Must be some scaling down. We can’t consider here what the cuts shd. be. N.B. Content with memo. provided these cuts are not considered a proper aim. Better line is to go for more food fr. producg. countries. Appeals. U.S. proposing Joint Mission to Argentine.

432

P.M. Can we not accept para. 14 and 16. Barnes. But see para 11. We must get agreemt. on minimum. This memo. is based on minimum distribn figures. W’out that

I can’t arrange shipping. 433

</content>
</cab>
