<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/3/0 images: 87-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 4(46). 10th January, 1946.

1. London Airport.

Three stages: first will be substantially completed this year.

No estimate of revenue.

A. Summd main points in memo. Need for takg. plenty of land at outset, to avoid limitg. future development. Thus, propose acquisition of Cranford Park. Might be awkward because of height of bldgs if this area isn’t under our control. Difficulties a) Transport. Interruptn with Bath Rd. New road to the north wd. be requd. Other access: Extension of Underground fr. Hounslow West. This is only proposal for near future: later, other facilities will be needed. b) Cost. Land 7.M. Main cost = that of runways. Officials estimates are based on existg. costs. With addl. items of rlway. extension etc., cost is likely to be about £30 m. c) Demolitions etc., Southall Gas Holder. S.W. corner – runway 7 goes beyond boundary into Sludge- works, part of wh. wd. have to be acquired. M/C.A. and Ty. must vet costs in greater detail. Hybrid Bill will be needed. H.D. V. expensive. Beginning to feel that Cab. shd. put a brake on expenditure. Hope therefore that details will be examd with critical eye. Agree we must have 1st rate airport: that this is the place: that we must go fwd. Need however to be sure we are using best. Para. 19. £221/2 m. + ½ m. for b-flying system. Over 7 years. £31/2 m. for Bath Road. £1-2 m. .. rl. access for employees. £10-15 m. .. passenger rlway line improvemt. Not satisfied we need at this stage acquire anythg. n. of Bath Rd. Certainly no need to acquire Cranford Park – sterilisation at most. N. of Bath Rd. – no need for it yet, &amp; no need to assume cost will rise. Recommend therefore go ahead s. of Bath Rd. P.M. Don’t like figures. Up-to-date methods shd. make for lower constn costs. R.A.F. reluctance to use rapid methods of laying runways. A. No basis for that. Unwise to count on it. A.B. No diffy. in sterilising adjacent land. Don’t need Cranford Park for housing.

445

Need for closer supervision of costs because of repercussions on housing in same area. P.M. Estimate of labour requirements? A. No. Evidence is sketchy. Barnes. N. of Bath Road. If we are going to spend these large sums – no

economy if we don’t look ahead to road facilities. Essential we shd. know when the Bath Rd. is ultimately to run. Otherwise our roads to airport will be cut in wrong place. Quick access to Ldn. = only point in having Airport here. Wdn’t meet me to have Bath Rd. in existing site but larger. I’m concerned also with ques. of by-passing Slough &amp; Maidenhead. That’s why I must know where this airport is going to be. E.B. Supported Barnes on this point. Need to see road as a whole. A. H.D.’s suggn also knocks out proved case for 9 runways vice 6. C.E. If we leave land n. of road, we shall pay a lot in compensation. P.M. Why not go further out? W. Inconvenience to passengers - &amp; need for feeder services.

E.B. Thrashed out under Coalition. Never liked it. But settled now &amp; already spent £5 m. And surely unwise to swop horses now. Don’t like leavg. land n. of Bath Rd. Surely we shd. earn interest on the cost of it. Surely you will get some industrial development along the new line of Bath Rd. R.S.C. Need for 9 runways – because congestion at peak hours. H.D. Need all the traffic come to London? P.M. Do you assume large propn of trans-Atlantic traffic will come here? What is to prevent them from coming via Eire or France vice Ldn. E.B. Everyone who built rlway terminal failed to buy enough land. Marshall. Purchase wd. be better &amp; cheaper than T.C.P. control. Latter will involve continual but separate applns for compn. Cheaper to buy &amp; re-let for appd purposes. No objn to this scheme as a whole on planning grounds. Need to give notice of our intentions soon. A.B. a) Under what authy. has expendre already bn. incurred. b) Any real-estate gambling in this land.

446

c) On what are estimates based of cost of land. Drop or rise in cost. W. On c) 1939 values + 40%. On a) requisitioning or Defence acquisition. Barnes. Are we going to make the same mistake here as we’ve always made in past re transport. Land is not main cost. Don’t limit amount of land. T.W. Agreed. There is an airport here: if you scrap this you’ll want as much elsewhere. W. This is best of 50 sites surveyed in belt round London.

R.S.C. Every earlier airport has become out of date because insufficient land taken at outset. Cranford Park – stupid for any kind of development not to acquire this intervening tongue of land. H.D. What is to be done with Heston? T.W. Housing &amp; other development. A.G. Hybrid Bill affectg. many land-owners will run into diffies in Parlt. Unless you get in quickly, it won’t get through Joint Sel. Cttee. in time to pass this Session. P.M. Agreed: proceed with hybrid Bill. But you must be much clearer about costs before you get into Select Cttee. Study must continue. See no harm in acquiring whole area, incldg. Cranford Park. C.E. Why out of revenue? Why not special loan? P.M. Consider that. [Enter N.B. Exeunt. W., Barnes, Marshall.

2. International Trusteeship. A. As in covering memo. Form of announcement. Want authy. to communicate draft to Dom. Govts. Order of commn. a) To Doms. Get their comments before we send to other interested Powers. E.B. Some diffy. with French. Hoped they wd. say the same re their 447

mandates in Africa. Seen Bidault: but he can’t go ahead w’out de G. Told him I cdn’t avoid mentiong. this in my speech on Monday. Halifax confirms we must retain initiative. Stanley asked P.Q. – I gave vague answer, not changing policy of Coaln Govt. We shall have Parly. difficulty. G.H. In spite of risk we must take it. Para. (i)(a) agreed. H.D. Para. (i)(b) – What of effects on Pal. enquiry? E.B. Can’t help that. On other hand, cdn’t negotiate Treaty I want vis-à-vis Egypt. G.H. No promise ever made of J. immigration in Trans-Jordan. Para (i)(b) and (c) agreed. E.B. Para (ii). Cab. shd. be clear Smuts wanted the other. We shall explain to Smuts.

A. Para. (iv). No ref. to negotns with other Powers shd. be included in announcement. E.B. Agreed. Para. (v) Agreed. Agreed. 3. Malayan Constitution. P.M. Para. 13. Amplify? Will look odd. G.H. Will agree a simultaneous statemt. Won’t include Appendix. Agreed.

4. Gas Supplies.

J.J.L. Agreed. Tho’ a) can’t guarantee continuity of personnel. b) don’t like night-shifts – don’t put them on too many. 448

</content>
</cab>
