<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/164/12 images: 223-230</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CP(72) 87 COPY NO   OD3 August 1972CABINETCIVIL SERVICE manpower memorandum by the Lord Privy seal. The Cabinet agreed on 16 March (CM(72) 16th Conclusions,Minute 5) that there must be some increase in Civil Service non-industrialmanpower but that numbers should keep under taut control.    The public expenditure Survey Committee (PESC) forecasts should be used as aflexible guide to planning.2. As foreseen there was a rise in the number of non-industrial civilservants up to the end of March 1972.    But the increases have been cancelled out by the transfer of the Civil Aviation Authority out of the CivilService on 1 April and a technicality of the new Superannuation Act which enables us to cease counting the staff of Trustee Museums and Galleries ascivil servants.    The result is that, taken together with the continuingreduction in industrial employees, there is at present a decrease in thetotal number of civil servants since June 1970:Non-industrial   Industrial     Total1 July 1970 495, 965 205,825      701, 7901 April 1972 496,370 194,013      690, 3831 July 1972 497,130 191.920     689, 0503, I acknowledge that the Cabinet decision in March prevents us fromcarrying out our pre-Election pledge to reduce the number of civil servants and I do not question that decision.    Nevertheless I am concerned aboutincreases in the forecasts of manpower requirements.    The 1972-73Estimates provide for an increase in non-industrial staff to 511, 000 by1 April 1973, but already Departments have put forward strongly supportedbids, not yet accepted, for about 6, 000 more at that date to meet approvedGovernment policies.    The 1971 PESC forecast for 1 April 1974, correctedfor transfers out, was 517,000 but the corresponding 1972 PESC forecast is527,000.4,        Thus the position which emerges is as follows:-Non-industrial   Industrial     Total1 April 1973 511,000 194,000     705, 000(with bids 517, 000) (711, 000)1 April 1974 527,000 191,000      718,000
The prospect is for an increase of some 30, 000 non-industrial civil servants in the next two years and an increase of 16, 000 in the overall total by1 April 1974 compared with 1 July 1970.5. Appendix A tabulates the individual changes put forward by departments and the reasons for change between now and 1974.    Appendix Bis a graph indicating the trend of total numbers since 1951 and up to 1977 onthe basis of the 1972 PESC.    It shows a rate of increase comparable withthat of our predecessors in the mid-1960s, which they largely moderatedtowards the end of their Administration, apart from the artificial increaseof some 15, 000 due to the transfer in of the Department of National savings from the Post Office,    Appendix C is a graph showing the growth of CivilService numbers, and costs related to gross national product (GNP).    the direct co3ts of salaries and superannuation rose from 2.5 per cent of GNPin 1962 to 2.9 per cent of GNP last year; the costs including administrative services rose from 3 per cent to 3. 7 per cent of GNP during the sameperiod.    (The rise includes 0.1 per cent for Selective Employment Tax).6. In trying to contain the increase in Civil Service manpower we are meeting with three basic difficultiesa. Ministers wish to introduce new policies which arepolitically important and which require additional manpower.b. There is an unwillingness to discard old and continuingfunctions the abandonment of which would save manpower.c. The numbers required depend essentially on subjectivejudgments by line management who have no real incentive toreduce staff.It is on these last two areas that we must exert pressure.    It cannot makesense for this Government, above all, to accept that there is no furtherscope for the improvement of efficiency, the elimination of activity, andthe improvement of productivity.7. What therefore is needed is a comprehensive efficiency drive,with a strong bias to reducing manpower, in every Department.    To make this effective it will be necessary to set targets which make due allowance for increases and decreases attributable to forecast expansion orcontraction of work.    The only way to do this is to have a common target for all Departments based on PESC forecasts,8,        I believe that our target should be a reduction of 1 per cent perannum in the total forecast staff requirement of each Department,cumulative over the next three years, beginning with the current year1972-73.    This is not asking for a reduction in overall numbers, merely for a reduction in the forecast rate of growth.    This can be achieved by cutting back on recruitment and the turnover of staff is so large (120, 000people enter and leave the non-industrial Civil Service every year) that itmust be practicable.    I appreciate that it may be too late for some ministers to achieve a reduction of fully 1 per cent in their forecast by april 1973 and this should be accepted provided that the full cumulativereduction of 2 per cent is made by April 1974.    But an early start isessential as a means of bringing about change and achieving the aim.2
9. Success can be achieved only by Ministers putting their full weight behind the programme and insisting on increased efficiencybeing regarded as a political aim which must be attained.    Ministers incharge of Departments will want to consider how best to arrange for all their junior Ministers to take part.    A Minister in each Department,either the Minister in charge or a junior Minister acting with his authority, should regularly comb through the manpower estimates insearch of savings.    A short list of check points is at Appendix D as an indication of some possible lines to follow.    But the essence of thematter will be to convince line managers that Ministers require themto increase productivity and cut out the non-essentials.Civil Service department August 1972
NON-INDUSTRIAL MANPOWERDIFFERENCE BETWEEN 1 4 72 STAFF-IN-POST AND 1972 PESO FORECAST FOR 1 4 741 4 72In post1972 PESCForecastfor 1 4 74ChangesMain Reasons for Changes4 72(in post) to4 73&apos; (as in 72-73Estimates)1 4 73(as in 72-73 Estimates)to 1 4 74 (PESC)Cabinet OfficeHAFF..........Intervention Board forAgricultural Produce ,,.......Chancellor of the Exchequer:Treasury(incl Rates &amp; UKTSD)Customs &amp; Excise ............Inland RevenueInformation ......RHSO .............HIS..............Small DepartmentsCSD................Education &amp; Science:DE3 &amp; tEC..............V k A * Science MuseumsEmployment:DE incl OME ............Environment:EOS.......Ordnance Survey.....Foreign &amp; Commonwealth:PCO.................ODA.................Home Office...........Lord Chancellor:Courts, etc ,..Land Registry ,Public Trustee .......Public Record Office .MPT....................northern Ireland OfficeScotland:Scottish Office ......Scottish CourtsSmall DepartmentsSocial Services:EHSS .......OPCSTrade and Industry:DTI.......ECGDWales.............Small Departments.Defence .....TOTAL58714,6941,09218,60871,9251,3253,20214,4301,6392,9913,20695632,01938,6214,19210,2742,34223,3128,9814,288564322442748,5665271,00374,5542,47017,6951,6179361,242127,674496,37060514,5053501,11426,20673,4831,3273,32314,4401,7153,4503,0761,11734,05641,1504,30010,3652,34526,56210,2924,7685803584869,2336941,05980,6442,72618,0731,9701,0461,351129,76218350227,5981,558212110764591612,0372,5291089133,2501,311480163644667167566,0902563783531101092,08818913074VAT (+6000)Abandonment of plans to establish furtherPAYE A DP Centres(-500)Transfer of Payroll work!to Chessington CC (+100JExpansion of industrial training &amp; industrial relations Act (+1500)Centralised LicensingScheme and RentAssessment Panels(+1400)Prisons, Immigration &amp;Police support (+1700)New Courts Servicef+SOQ),Greater number of transactions (+200)Prisons &amp; Rent Service(+400)Transfer of staff from local authorities (+100]Supplementary benefits(+1600)Expansion of Marriage &amp;Registration division and Legitimation Unit(+100)Rundown of investment grants Organisation(-200)Increased business(+200)526,53130,161EEC work (+200) Cmnd 4564 reductions infunctions (-400)New bodyEEC (+800) VAT (+2000) end of purchase tax (-1800)General increase in workload (+2000)reorganisation of valuation Office records (+50O) 1973Revaluation rundown (-3J0) SurtaxOffice rundown (-200) revised taxexemption arrangements for superannuationcontributions (-200) 1972 Budgetchanges (nil net).Further transfers to Chessington CC(+100) College and PRISM (+100)Employment services (+300) vocational training (+300) occupational safety and health (+200) Benefit work(-200) SET (-200) IR Act (+300)Centralised Licensing Scheme (+800)expansion of research (+200)Prisons Immigration and Policesupport (+1600)Increase in Court business (+300)Extension of registration and increasein applications (+500) Computerisation(-300)Prisons &amp; State Hospitals (+200) RentService, e.c., student awards etc (+100)Local Offices    (+1500) attendance allowance (+700) Newcastle central office &amp; HO (+600) New HI Scheme (+500)Managerial changes (+900)Work resulting from NHS executive councils reorganisation (+100),completion of alphabetical index (+100)1971 Census rundown (-200)1972 Budget Changes (+600)Increased business (+100)Increases in:-MOD Police, BAOR Schoolteachers,Accounts Division, Dockyards,Bicester computer, and Military UnitsWarehouses; and postponement ofrundown of may Belfast; offset bysavings from 5% financial economyexercise
APPENDIX   Bvil   Service Non-Industrial   and   Industrial   Staff   1951  -   1977800 \-,-1-,-10051     52      5 3     5 4     5 5     5 6     5 7     5 8     5 9     6 0     61      6 2     6 3     6 4     6 5     6 6     6 7     6 8     6 9     7 0     71      72      73     74     7 5      76     7 7Year 19-NOTE:   1972-73 Estimates Provision197U-77 PESC Forecasts
APPENDIX 0 ,000700,0002-221-18654,000TotalCivilServicenumbers62&apos;63  70&apos;71Average costof a civilservantPercentage growth of Civil Service numbers and costs related to GNPKEY:Percentage changes in(a) cost of CS as% of GNP(b) total CS numbersCost ofCivilServiceas%of gnp
APPENDIX DEFFICIENCY DRIVE - CHECK POINTSInvolve line-managers in the search for improved efficiency -remember 7 out of 10 posts are not in London.Examine areas of work which have been stable for sometime rather than those affected by current policy or changes.Look at number of top posts;    levels in hierarchy;    scope for amalgamation in divisions and sections.Identify and challenge agreements which automaticallyrelate staff numbers to predetermined levels of activityor hierarchical ratios.Streamline methods;    reduce checking and unnecessarysupervision;    improve selective audit procedures;    eliminateredundant information gathering and dissemination;    cutlength,  volume and circulation of paper.Review inspectorates;    reduce in-house R&amp;D;    close down oramalgamate establishments.V


</content>
</cab>
