<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/274/0 images: 96-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS    DO CUHEHI    IS    THE    PROPERTY   OF HIS    BRITANNIC    M A J E ST Y&apos;S    GOVERNMENT).PUBLIC    CAPITAL    EXPENDITURE.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.In order to enable my colleagues to appreciate more fully the proposals made in the two Reports of the Inter-Departmental Committee  (Cabinet Papers P.C.E,(37)10 and (37)15) I have had a redraft made of the draft circular appended to the First Report in order to bring it more into line with conditions now obtaining, which,  as the Second Report points out, have changed materially since the summer. The redraft, which is appended to this paper,  is necessarily tentative and the final terms of the document may, no doubt, require further consideration by those of my colleagues who are in charge of the other Departments concerned.1.      It is, I think,  clear that,  if the policy of a five-years&apos; programme for local authorities is to be adopted, at all, the programme must include all the activities of the authorities,  including housing, roads, schools, water supply, and so forth.      As regards-housing for slum clearance purposes and,  as I understand, roads, programmes have already been submitted.to the Departments concerned.      These must, I suggest, be incorporated in the general programme of the authority and should not be regarded as necessarily incapable of modification.2.      I have considered carefully the question whether programmes when made should be submitted to my Department, not for approval, but for information,     On the whole, I have reached the conclusion that a direction to submit is necessary.SECRET.CP.7(38) .CAB 1 NET.I may add one or two comments.
In its absence there would be no assurance that the circular was not being disregarded,  and in so far as the object of the proposal is to secure a &quot;pool of works&quot;, the Government would have no answer to its critics if it subsequently appeared that the Departments concerned had no knowledge  as to the extent, or,   indeed, the existence of, the pool.On the other hand, I should make it clear that the scrutiny of these programmes will involve a considerable amount of additional work in my Department, and will necessarily impose some responsibility on the Government, even though there is no question of actual approval or disapproval. In a case where the programme was either obviously inadequate or threatened an intolerable burden on the rates my Department could hardly evade the responsibility of drawing the attention of the local authority to the matters and pressing for modifications.     Moreover,  in so far as the programme will contain proposals falling within the province of other Departments,  it may be that some standing inter-departmental machinery will have to be devised.In connection with the reference on page 4 of the draft circular to contemplated legislation simplifying the procedure for the compulsory purchase of land I should add that I hope to bring before the Cabinet very shortly the question of making permanent a section of the Public Yforks Facilities Act, 1930, which deals with this matter.K.W. 1st January, 1938.
6SAppendix to C ,P. 7 (.38).Draft Circular Letter to Local Authorities in England and Wales.Capital Bx-penditure.Survey of pro spec tive Works.I am directed by the Minister of Health to draw the attention of your Council &quot;Co certain considerations of importance in relation to prospective works involving capital expenditure.The Minister has on previous occasions urged upon local authorities the policy of making every year a survey of their probable capital commitments for at least five years ahead.    It is only by means of such systematic budgeting that authorities can take a reasonably long view and appreciate the cumulative effect of their future liabilities. Under such a system they will also be able to arrange their programme of capital works in an order of priority, which, though necessarily conditioned by considerations of their relative urgency, will have regard to present and anticipated conditions of prices and labour so that they can be carried out with the greatest possible efficiency and economy.The need for this long term approach to questions of capital expenditure, more pe-rticularly in connection with projects involving building work, is accentuated under present conditions not merely in order to secure the smooth progress of local authorities1  operations but as a matter of national economic policy-At the present time the building industry continues to be fully occupied, and any material increase in large-scale operations which might put an undue strain on its resources is to be deprecated.    It is true that in England and Wales the building operations of local authorities form a relatively
small part of the work of the building industry as a whole, and that the activity of the industry depends mainly on the extent to which private enterprise is engaged in the erection of commercial and industrial buildings, houses, shops, etc. Moreover, the probable increase or decrease of this activity cannot be foretold with accuracy from year to year, still less over a long period of time.None the less, by an ordered planning of their prospective capital works on a basis which will admit of review should circumstances make it desirable, local authorities can make a valuable contribution to the stabilisation of the conditions [in the industry][of employment] over a considerable period.   At the same time the adoption of such a policy will enable them to take&quot;the fullest advantage, in the interests of their rate-payers, of periods when the resources of the industry are not unduly strained and conditions are therefore most favourable for the execution of necessary works.For this purpose the first essential is the preparation of a programme, which should be as complete as possible, of the capital works which are likely to be required during the period in view, and the Minister requests that the Local Authority will take this matter into their early consideration. The programme should cover the whole of the capital works which are in contemplation including those, such as housing and roads, for which provisional programmes are already in existence. It should also indicate at what point in the period covered by the programme each item of work is provisionally intended to commence and should furnish a rough estimate of the probable cost. It will, of course, be realised that since the assumption by the Minister of Transport of direct responsibility for trunk roads, work on these roads is removed from the scope of the local authority&apos;s works programmeo
The programme will be compounded of projects emanating from the various Committees of the Council and their advisers.    It is suggested, therefore, that the several Committees should be invited to formulate their proposals and that arrangements should be made for the examination of them by some co-ordinating Committee and their embodiment in a provisional programme to be approved by the Council.The existence of some central co-ordinating machinery will clearly be necessary, as it is often difficult to assess relative degrees of urgency, and the various Committees of the Council may have divergent views on this point.    Co-ordination - either by the Finance Committee or by a Committee specially appointed for the purpose - will therefore be required, to assist the Local Authority to determine whether a particular project should be included in the programme and, if so, what provisional position should be assigned to that project in the programme.In this connection it will be necessary for local authorities to bear in mind the need for discharging such statutory obligations as are placed upon them.Further, a considerable measure of elasticity in the arrangements will be necessary.    It may well be that, over a period of years or in any particular year, circumstances will make it desirable to increase the amount of work to be carried out as compared with that envisaged in the programme, or to diminish it, and it is of primary importance that the execution of an authority&apos;s programme should be capable of acceleration or retardation as circumstances require,,The Minister will be glad to be informed that the Council have taken steps to formulate a programme and to receive as soon as practicable, and in any case within the next six months, a copy of such a programme and of the
provisional timetable at present contemplated for its execution. He will be glad to afford any assistance practicable to the Local Authority in the preparation of the programme and the preliminary work required in order to enable particular schemes to be put in hand with the minimum of delay when the most favourable opportunity arises.It will be appreciated that one of the essential features of the policy outlined is that active preparations should at once be made for such schemes as are likely to require much preliminary work, e.g. in regard to the acquisition of land and the preparation of plans.The acquisition of land is often an essential preliminary, and in many cases the details of specific proposals cannot be settled until it is known that a particular site can be acquired. Upon being satisfied that a scheme is one which may ultimately be approved the Minister will be prepared to sanction loans for the immediate acquisition of land in readiness for the execution of the proposed works at a later date.Legislation is contemplated by the Government to shorten the procedure at present involved in the compulsory acquisition of land by local authorities for a number of purposes so as to assimilate this procedure to that provided by the Public Works Facilities Act, 1930.The preparation of plans is another necessary preliminary which may occupy a considerable time, particularly in the case of the larger schemes.      To enable work on such buildings to be put in hand at comparatively short notice it is essential that the plans should be prepared well in advance, and the Minister would be ready to consider plans submitted to him notwithstanding that immediate execution of the work may not be contemplated.      It should usually be possible to prepare detailed plans and estimates of any projected&quot;scheme sufficiently accurate to avoid the need for substantial revision even if the execution of the scheme is deferred for some time.
The preparation of a comprehensive programme will involve the study toy the Local Authority of the current needs of the district and of the probable lines of future development. This task should not of course be allowed to interfere with the progress of current works, nor should it in general delay works which though not actually begun are urgent and in an advanced stage of preparation.      The.settlement of priority within the programme is a matter which each local authority Will require carefully to consider in the light of their own local conditions. There are, however,  certain general considerations to be borne in mind.      As stated,  the building industry at present continues to be fully occupied:    urgent considerations of national defence make it essential for the Government to carry out their programme of re-armament with all possible expedition and similar considerations apply to that portion of local authorities&apos; prospective works which is concerned with air raids precautions. These considerations in themselves will go far to facilitate the determination of a timetable and they emphasise the advantage of an ordered programme of constructional works in general so arranged that work on previously prepared plans can be started when circumstances are most favourable with the minimum of delay.The Minister desires me to state that the suggestions contained in this circular have been discussed with, and are made with the concurrence of,  the other Departments concerned.      In cases where the programme of the Local Authority includes works which will require the sanction or approval of some Department other than the Ministry of Health,  it will of course be understood that the normal procedure for consultation with that Department in regard to the relevant part of the programme and the preparation of plans should be observed. A copy of the programme submitted to the Minister should also be supplied to that Department.

</content>
</cab>
