<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/274/0 images: 150-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for -the Cabinet.   January 1938.SECRET. Copy No.CP. 14 (38).&apos; ..&quot; ;CABINET.COMMITTEE ON PENT RESTRICTIONS ACTS AND RATINGREVALUATION.REPORT.AT their Meeting on the 15th December, 1937 (Cabinet 47 (37), Conclu-sion 13), the Cabinet agreed that a Cabinet Committee composed of : The Secretary of State for India (in the Chair),The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,The Secretary of State for Scotland,The Minister of Health,The Minister of Labour,The Minister of Transport,The Attorney-General,The Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Health, should be appointed with the following Terms of Reference: &quot; To consider the Reports of the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Rent Restrictions Acts and the matter of the general revaluation for rating purposes which will come into effect on the 1st April, 1939.&quot;2. We have held two Meetings and have had before us the Reports of the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Rent Restrictions Acts (the Ridley Committee), which are attached to this Report as Appendix I, together with a number of memoranda submitted by the Minister of Health and a Memorandum from the Secretary of State for Scotland. We deal first with the Rent Restriction part of our terms of reference and subsequently with the question of the general revaluation for rating purposes.Rent Restriction.3. The present Rent Restrictions Acts expire on the 28th May, 1938, in Scotland, and on the 24th June in England and Wales. In the debate on the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill on the 8th November last an undertaking was given on behalf of the Government that new legislation would be introduced and passed through all its stages before these dates.4. The Ridley Committee produced a Majority Report signed by the Chairman and eleven members, subject to a reservation by two members, and a Minority Report signed by the three representatives of Labour on the Committee. The principal recommendations in the Majority Report are as follows : (A) All houses in the upper range of the present Class B (i.e., with a rateable value in London and Scotland between  35 and  45 and elsewhere between  20 and  35) should be decontrolled when the present Acts expire in the course of this year. The number of houses involved is approximately 450,000.(B) The remaining houses (approximately 650,000) in Class B should be amalgamated with the present Class C, and should, in consequence, no longer be subject to decontrol on the landlord obtaining vacant possession.[16562-1] b
(C) As regards England and Wales (but not as regards Scotland), the new-legislation should provide a scheme for the gradual reduction and eventual termination of control on different dates in different areas based on the percentage of overcrowding in the area, the scheme to be operated without further legislation by Orders to be made by the Minister of Health. The first set of these Orders should be made in 1940, and would aggregate the local government districts into areas for the purposes of the scheme. The Orders would provide that (i) in any control area where the percentage of overcrowding exceeds 4 per cent. (i.e., is above the present average percentage of over-crowding) no change should be made in the number of houses subject to control, and (ii) in any control area where the percentage of over-crowding does not exceed 4 per cent., the upper rateable value limit of the control class should be reduced by  5. The second set of Orders, to be made in 1942, would provide for the gradual cessation of all control by specified reductions in the upper rateable value limit of the control class. These would take place over the periods of years indicated in the Committee&apos;s Report according to the percentage of overcrowding in the different areas. In the least overcrowded areas the final stage would be reached by 1944, in the most crowded by 1950, and in the remainder on intermediate dates. The Report contem-plates, however, that in some areas there might be special factors which would make it desirable to adopt special Orders.5. The reservation to the Majority Report signed by Sir Miles Mitchell and Mr. Graham White. M.P., objects to the use of the overcrowing percentage as a measure of the housing shortage and dissents from the proposed automatic time-table for the determination of control. The Minority Report expresses the view that control of rents should be general and permanent, and that Tenancy Courts should be set up to settle disputes between landlords and tenants.6. We first considered the question of principle raised by the Minority Report, viz., whether the ultimate object of the Government should be to bring rent control to an end or whether control should be envisaged as a desirable permanent measure. It is clear that an indefinite continuance of the present system of control would be indefensible. The present Acts apply only to pre-war houses, which now represent less than 50 per cent, of the total number of houses in Classes B and C in Great Britain, and only 57 per cent, of the total number of houses in Class C (i.e., working-class houses strictly defined). If the views of the Minority Report were to be adopted and control of rents treated as a permanent measure, it would undoubtedly be necessary to bring into the scheme all houses within certain limits of rateable value and to abandon the distinction which is rapidly becoming anomalous between pre-war and post-war houses.7. On this major issue we feel no doubt that the view expressed by the Majority Report &quot; that the restrictions should at once be lifted from any class of property as soon as it can be shown that they are no longer needed in the general interest &quot; is right, and it is to be observed that the earlier Inter-Departmental Committee appointed by the Labour Government in 1930 (the Marley Committee) reached, with one dissentient, precisely the same conclusion. We think it important that in the public statement (to which we refer in a later paragraph) it should be made abundantly clear that the Government take their stand on this principle.8. We are also of opinion that the Government should accept the view adopted both by the Marley Committee and by the Majority Report of the Ridley Committee &quot; that the question of continuing control of any particular class of house must be regarded as dependent on whether the shortage of houses in that class is at an end or is likely to end within a reasonable period.&quot; Further, we consider that the principle of decontrol by area is right and that, broadly speaking, the progress of decontrol in any area should be determined in the light of the housing situation in the area.      -     -9. The detailed proposals contained in the Majority Report for gradual decontrol in England and Wales are, however, a more difficult matter. As already stated, they involve immediate legislation which would empower the Minister of
I Health by Order to secure decontrol by successive stages in the different areas fixed by him for the purpose, the time-table in each area (with possible exceptions) being based on the overcrowding in the area. There are, in our. view, two substantial reasons against accepting this proposal as it stands, notwithstanding that its rejection is likely to create considerable disappointment amongst the house-owning interests. First, it involves legislation which commits the Government for many years ahead on matters in which there is inevitably a large element of uncertainty, including the unknown factor of the future rate of house building. The subject matter of this legislation is one which arouses much popular interest and is notoriously contentious. Any Government action in this sphere is peculiarly liable to misrepresentation. Moreover, if this legislation were passed by the present Government and a Government of a different political complexion assumed office before the date on which the legislation was due to be put into actual operation, it is, to say the least, probable that the legislation would be repealed and would thus have achieved nothing.Secondly, while we recognise that&apos; the overcrowding standard fixed by the Housing Act, 1935, is to some extent a convenient yard-stick with which to measure the scarcity of housing accommodation in an area and thus to determine the rate at which decontrol can properly be allowed to proceed, we do not feel that it would be wise to proceed on the view that this is by any means the only factor to be taken into account. The amount of statutory overcrowding is largely conditioned by the prevalent type of house in the district. The effects of removing control will be mainly influenced by the demand for accommodation, and the chances. of unreasonable increases of rents will be greatest in districts experiencing a great measure of prosperity, producing a great demand for houses, though without increasing in any marked degree statutory overcrowding. This is, no doubt, the reason for the special representations received from Birmingham, and the conditions would be parallel in other assessment centres. It would, therefore, in our view be important to review the procedure for effecting decontrol nearer the time when it had to be applied.10. Our conclusion, therefore, on this point is that the immediate legislation should not deal with the question of future decontrol. On the other hand, we recognise the prime importance of certainty in this matter, both from the point of view of property owners and, though no doubt to a lesser degree, of the tenants themselves, and we consider that if the Government merely intimated that they did not accept this recommendation of the Ridley Report, and thus threw the whole future of rent control once more into the melting pot, a good deal of justifiable criticism and resentment would be aroused. What we propose is that the Government should make a public announcement, which we think might conveniently take the form of a White Paper, setting out their views on rent control and making it clear that, while they do not propose to set up a procedure for gradual decontrol in the forthcoming legislation, they accept the general principle of the recommendation of the Ridley Committee in this respect, but intend (as regards England and Wales) to set up in due course a Committee to examine the exact time and method by which decontrol by areas should be effected. As at present advised we contemplate that this Committee should hold its enquiry in the Autumn of 1941 at the same time that the proposed review of housing finance, &amp;c, will be proceeding, but the exact date will no doubt be governed by future events. The statement would also make it clear that, while the state of overcrowding is an important factor, all considerations bearing on housing should be taken into account in deciding on further decontrol. As regards Scotland we feel no doubt that for the reasons stated in the Ridley Report no decontrol of houses below a rateable value of  35 should at present be contemplated. We attach (Appendix II) for the consideration of the Cabinet a draft Statement on these lines.11. It will be seen from the Statement that we recommend the acceptance of the Ridley proposals as regards Class B houses, i.e., the upper range to be decontrolled and the lower range to be brought within the rather stricter control now applying to Class C. The Majority Report does not state explicitly the reasons for this latter proposal, but we understand that the Committee &quot;were influenced by the fact that under their proposals for future decontrol the continuance of control over the lower range of Class B houses would in any event be short lived and that it would make for administrative simplicity and convenience in the meantime to abolish the distinction between Class B and Class C [16562-1] b 2
and to end a form of decontrol (by vacant possession) which is at best haphazard. It would in our view be very difficult politically to reject this proposal while accepting the proposal to decontrol the upper range of Class B, and we accordingly recommend the acceptance of both proposals.12. The Majority Report also recommend a number of minor amendments of the Rent Restrictions Acts. These are set out and discussed in a paper by the Minister of Health, which we attach as Appendix III; we recommend that they should be accepted. As regards the procedure for levying distress (para-graph 11 of Appendix III) it is to be observed that the subject falls outside the ambit of the Rent Restrictions Acts and that we suggest, subject to the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor, the setting up of a Committee to examine the matter further.Revaluation for Rating Purposes.13. As regards the second half of our Terms of Reference, viz., the question of the impending revaluation for rating purposes, we have considered a Memorandum by the Minister of Health which examines the problem in great detail and suggests various possible courses of action. The Memorandum is attached hereto as Appendix IV. Put very briefly, the position is this : Outside London and one or two provincial areas the third quinquennial valuation under the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, is due in April 1939, and the preliminary work on the revaluation is now beginning and will be in full swing in the coming summer. For the reasons set out in paragraphs 6-14 of the appended paper, it is probable that some Assessment Committees throughout the country, following on the advice of a circular issued by the Central Valuation Committee, will substan-tially increase the gross assessments of houses, and in particular of small houses. Whether or not this will occur generally, or only in isolated areas, cannot be known with any degree of certainty till the autumn of the present year. But if action is to be taken, an early announcement must be made, since otherwise much of the work done in connection with the revaluation may prove useless.14. The four possible courses of action suggested in paragraph 17 of Appendix IV are as follows : I. To leave the law to operate unhindered. II. To legislate to postpone the next valuation, outside London.III. To amend the existing temporary legislation mentioned in para-graph 7 (b) of the Paper, so as to increase the deductions to be made from gross value in assessments of houses and shop properties.IV. In effect, to restore Section 12 (9) of the Rent Restriction Act of 1920,but extending it to cover houses in general.Of these, we unanimously rejected courses II and III, and, in our view, the issue lies between course I and course IV. The general form of the legislation proposed in course IV is indicated on page 8 of the Paper and is as follows :  (a) the gross value of a house belonging to a housing authority must notexceed its rent;(b) the gross value of a house which does not belong to a housing authority,but is of such a type as is provided by the authority, must not exceed such rent as the authority charge for a house of that type;(c) in fixing the gross value of a house not falling under paragraph (a) or (b).regard must be had to the gross values fixed for houses falling under those paragraphs.15. We have reached the conclusion that the introduction of legislation on the lines of course IV is desirable. The actual language of the legislation will call for very careful consideration. We think that, in the absence of some such provision, there is a real risk-rthough the precise extent of the risk cannot as yet be definitely ascertained of an increase in assessments sufficiently marked to create much resentment throughout - the country, and, for the reasons indicated in paragraph 16 of Appendix IV, to give rise to unfortunate reactions on the Government^ housing policy. We recognise that there are objections to introducing into the already complicated system of valuation for rating purposes provisions the effect of which will be to limit still further the resources of local
authorities in terms of rateable value, but we consider that on balance this is to be preferred to the prospect of a substantial increase in the rate burdens of the working class and of the black-coated class immediately above it. We under-stand that the Minister of Health does not regard it as probable that a demand for further Exchequer assistance, based on the ground that the contemplated legislation is a measure of derating, will be seriously pressed by the local authorities. We are agreed that such a demand, if made, would have no. foundation and must be resisted. We recommend accordingly that legislation on these lines should be introduced, and we suggest that it should form part of the Rent Restriction Bill. The repercussions of such legislation on Scotland where the valuation system is rather different would require further consideration.16. The Minister of Health&apos;s Paper also raises the question whether the time is ripe for the appointment of a Royal Commission to consider the whole question of local taxation. The arguments for and against this course are set out in paragraphs 18-20 of Appendix IV. After an examination of these arguments, we have unanimously reached the conclusion that the appointment of such a Commission would in present circumstances serve no useful purpose and should not be entertained. Conclusions and Recommendations.17. Our conclusions and recommendations may be summarised as follows :  Rent Restriction.(1) On the question of principle raised by the Minority Report, viz., whether the ultimate object of the Government should be to bring rent control to an end or whether the contrary should be envisaged as a desirable permanent measure, we feel no doubt that the view expressed by the Majority Report &quot; that the restrictions should at once be lifted from any class of property as soon as it could be shown that they are no longer needed in the general interest &quot; is right. We recommend the Cabinet to approve this conclusion and to make it clear in the public Statement which is to be issued on the subject that the Government take their stand upon this principle.(2) We also recommend the Cabinet to accept the view adopted both by the Mar ley Committee and in the Majority Report of the Ridley Committee &quot; that the question of continuing control of any particular class of house must be regarded as dependent on whether the shortage of houses in that class is at an end or is likely to end within a reason-able period.&quot; Further we consider that the principle of decontrol by area is right and that, broadly speaking, the progress of decontrol in any area should be determined in the light of the housing situation in that area.   We invite the Cabinet to concur in these conclusions.(3) For the reasons set out in paragraph 9 of our Report we are unable to recommend the Cabinet to accept the detailed proposals contained in the Majority Report for gradual decontrol in England and Wales. As regards this aspect of the matter, we endorse the views expressed in the reservation by Sir Miles Mitchell and Mr. Graham White, M.P., on page 53 of the Ridley Report, subject to a qualification as to the time when the further examination of the position should be made. We recommend accordingly that the immediate legislation should not deal with the question of future decontrol, but that the Government should make a public announcement which we recommend should take the form of a White Paper setting out their views on rent control and making it clear that while they do not propose to set up a procedure for gradual decontrol in the forthcoming legislation, they accept the general principle of the recommendation of the Ridley Committee in this respect, but intend (as regards England and Wales) to set up in due course a Committee to examine the exact time and method by which decontrol by areas should be effected. As at present advised, we contemplate that this Committee should hold its enquiry in the Autumn of 1941 at the same time that the proposed review of housing finance, &amp;c, will be proceeding. The Statement should also make it clear that while the state of overcrowding is an important factor, all considera-tions bearing on housing should be taken into account in deciding on future decontrol.
As regards Scotland, we feel no doubt that for the reasons stated in the Ridley Report no decontrol of houses below a rateable value of  35 should at present be contemplated.(4) We recommend the acceptance of the Ridley proposals as regards Class B houses, i.e., the upper range to be decontrolled and the lower range to be brought within the rather stricter control now applying to Class C. It would in our view be very difficult politically to reject the latter proposal while accepting the proposal to decontrol the upper range of Class B, and we accordingly recommend the Cabinet to accept both proposals and embody them in immediate legislation.(5) We recommend the acceptance of a number of minor amendments of the Rent Restrictions Acts set out and discussed in Appendix III to this Report.(6) As regards the procedure for levying distress, we suggest, subject to the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor, the setting up of a Committee to examine the matter further.(7) We attach a draft statement on Government policy on Rent Restriction (Appendix II) embodying the conclusions we have reached. If the Cabinet approve this draft Statement, it will be for consideration whether it would be better to publish its contents as a White Paper or in some other way, such as, for example, by an announcement by the Minister of Health on the Second Reading of the Bill in the House of Commons. We strongly favour the former course, and accordingly recommend the Cabinet to authorise the publication of the Statement as a White Paper.Revaluation for Rating Purposes.(8) For the reasons given in paragraphs 14 and 15 of our Report, we recommend the inclusion in the. Rent Restriction Bill of a provision to give effect to Course IV in paragraph 17 of Appendix IV, i.e., in effect to restore Section 12 (9) of the Rent Restriction Act of 1920, but so extended as to cover houses in general. (9) While it seems improbable that demands for further Exchequer assistance, based on the ground that the contemplated legislation is equivalent to a measure of derating, will be seriously pressed by the Local Authorities, we agree that such a demand, if made, would have no foundation and that it should be resisted.(10) In our view, the appointment in present, circumstances of a Royal Commission to consider the whole question of local taxation would serve no useful purpose, and accordingly we recommend that a Royal Commission for this purpose should not be appointed.(11) If the Cabinet accept our conclusions and recommendations, we recommend that the Minister of Health should be authorised to arrange for the drafting of the necessary legislation and for its-submission in due course to the Home Affairs Committee.Signed on behalf of the Committee :ZETLAND, Chairman.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, January 27, 1938.
Appendix I.Reports nf the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Rent Restrictions Acts. (Cmd.   5621 of 1957).Appendix II.    Draft White Paper.Appendix III.  Minor Amendments recommended in Majority Report of Ridley Committee.(Memorandum by the Minister of Health).Appendix- IV.    Rating and Valuation In England and Wales.(Memorandum by the Minister of Health).
A P P   /V2)/X   I.MINISTRY OF HEALTHReports of the Inter-Departmental Committeeon the rent RESTRICTIONS ACTSPresented by the Minister of Health to Parliament by Command of His Majesty December, 1937LONDONPRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2 ; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2 ; ad    26 Y0rk Streef, Manchester 1 ; 1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Card,fF; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller1937 Price is. od. netCmd. 5621
RENT RESTRICTIONS ACTS COMMITTEEMEMBERS. The Viscount Ridley (Chairman). Councillor Arthur W. Brady. Humphrey R. Brand, Esq., D.L., J.P. Captain V. A. Cazalet, M.C., M.P. R. N. Duke, Esq., D.S.O., M.C.C. Gerald Eve, Esq., P.P.S.I. Sir Francis Fremantle, O.B.E., M.A., M.D., M.P. H. H; George, Esq., M.C. Duncan M. Graham, Esq., M.P.D. S. Macdiarmid, Esq., B.A., LL.B., Advocate (Sheriff-Substitute of Lanarkshire).Alderman Sir Miles E. Mitchell, J.P.F. Montague, Esq., M.P.His Honour Judge Sir Mordaunt Snagge.Mrs. H. B. Tate, J.P., M.P.H. Graham White, Esq., M.P.Miss E. M. R. Russell-Smith (Secretary). Mr. A. C. Sturman (Assistant Secretary).TERMS OF REFERENCE.&apos;&apos; To enquire into and report upon the present working of the Rent Restrictions Acts and to advise what steps should be taken to continue or terminate or amend those Acts.&quot;The estimated gross cost of the preparation of this Report (including the expenses of the Committee) is ^306 4s. id., of which ^41 15s. od. represents the estimated cost of printing and publishing this Report.
CONTENTSMajority Reportpart I. Paragraph    page introduction    ...       ...       ...       ...      ...       ....... 1-8 previous Committees    ...       ...      ... ...      ... 2 1Oral evidence    ...       .......      ... ...      ... 4 2Written evidence         ...       ...      ... ...      ... 5 part II.Summary of the present position under the Acts ...      ... 9-24 5Acts in force      ...       ...       ...      ... ...      ... 10 5Objects of the Acts      ...       ...... ...       ... n 6Position as regards houses in Classes A, B, and C   ... 12 6Registration of decontrolled Class C houses ... ... 13 7Onus of proof of decontrol      ...       ... ...       ... 14 7Sub-tenancies     ...       ...       ...       ... ....... 15 7Limitation of scope of Acts     :..      ... ...      ... 16 8Restrictions on rent     ...       ...      ... ...      ... i7-T9 8Premiums and key money       ...       ... ...       ... 20 9Protection against eviction     ...      ... ...      ... 21 9Alternative accommodation    ...       ... ...       ... 22 10Mortgages...............       ...... 23 10Administration   ...       ...       ...       ... ...       ... 24 11part III.General housing position      ...       ...      ...       ... ... 25-44 11Connection between control and house shortage ... 26 11Marley Committee&apos;s analysis of housing position in1931 ...      ...      ...       ......       ... ...&quot; 28 13Analysis of housing position in 1937 ...       ... ... 29-37 i3Comparison between 1931 and 1937 --- 3^-39 16Approximate rent levels         ...      ...       ... ... 40-42 17Proportion of existing houses still controlled... ... 43 18Effect of post-War increase in supply of houses ... 44 19part IV.Future housing developments ...      ...       ...      ... 45-5q j9Factors influencing future house production...       ... 45 19Shortage..................... 46 20Needs     ............      ......... 47&quot;49 20Demand..................... 50 21part v.Extent of present house shortage      ...      ... ...      ... 5i-56 22Effect of post-War building on shortage      ...... 5x-53 22Evidence of the overcrowding surveys ...      ... 54 23Geographical distribution of overcrowding ...      ... 55-56 2447389 A 1
part VI.                                   Paragraph PagFuture of control       ...      ...      ...      ...       ...      ... 57-79 24Examination of the question of decontrol by areas... 57-61 24Selection of areas         ...      ...      ...       ...      ... 62 25Effect of the overcrowding provisions on the standardof accommodation ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 63 26Methods of varying control by areas ...      ...      ... 64 27Overcrowding as a measure of shortage       ...      ...&apos; 65-66 27Recommendations as to the future of control affectingGreat Britain        ............... 67-70 29Decontrol of upper range of Class B houses ...      ... 68-69 29Safeguards in respect of houses occupied by morethan one family    ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 70 29Scheme for gradual reduction of control in Englandand Wales based on percentage of overcrowding 71-76 30Advantages of scheme ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 77-79 31part VII.Scotland         ..................... 80-87 32Future of control in Scotland ...      ...       ...      ... 80 32Owners&apos;rates in Scotland       ...      ...      ... 81-87 33part VIII.The agricultural population ...      ...      ...       ...      ... 88-91 3692-105 3793 3894-95 3896 3997 4098-99 40100-102 41part IX.Minor amendmentsOnus of proof of decontrol Rent books Sanitary certificates Possession for own occupation ... RegistrationCompounding allowances Period allowed for recovery of overpayments of rent   103 41Procedure for increasing rents after improvements ...   104 42Alternative accommodation    ...       ...       ...       ...   105 42Overcrowding as a ground for possession     ...       ...   105 42part X.Points on which no amendment of the law is recommended...   106-116        43Mortgages.....................107-112        43 &quot;Owner&apos;s right to possession     ...       ...       ...       ...   113-115        45Special Committees appointed by Local Authorities   116 47part XI.Consolidation of the Acts      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...   117-118        48part XII.Miscellaneous ...      ...      .........      ...      ...   119 49Distress.....................119 49Summary of Recommendations       ...      ...      ...      ... 51Reservation to Majority Report............ 53Minority Report    .................. 54
ijRENT RESTRICTIONS ACTS COMMITTEEMAJORITY REPORTMinistry of Health, Whitehall, S.W.i. 6th December, 1937.To the Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood, P.C., M.P., Minister of Health, and the Right Hon. Walter E. Elliot, M.C., M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland.Sirs,1. We were appointed by you on the 27th May, 1937, &quot; to enquire into and report upon the present working of the Rent Restrictions Acts and to advise what steps should be taken to continue or terminate or amend those Acts.&quot; We now have the honour to submit our Report.PART I.INTRODUCTION.2. There have been four earlier Committees of Inquiry into the operation of the Acts, the Hunter Committee of 1919, the Salisbury Committee of 1920, the Onslow Committee of 1922 and the Marley Committee of 1930. The investigations of the Marley Committee, on which six of our number served, were carried out at a comparatively recent date. We have carefully studied the Report of this Committee (Cmd. 3911) and the evidence given before them was available to us. We therefore thought it right to limit the scope of our inquiry so far as possible to circumstances arising since the date of their Report.3. We invited various bodies and persons representing property owners and tenants, or possessing special knowledge or experience of the workings of the Acts, to give oral evidence before us and we invited other bodies and persons to submit written statements. We have had the advantage of the views of County Court Judges on the legal aspects of our inquiry. We also received written statements from a number of bodies and persons who learnt of our inquiry from the Press. In addition over 300 letters and representations were received from various sources, of which 170 were from individual landlords, and 70 from tenants.47389
Oral Evidence.4. The organisations represented before us and the private individuals who gave evidence were: A. Representing Tenants.Organisation. Birmingham      and      DistrictTenants&apos; Federation. Glasgow Labour Party housing association. Moss Side Tenants&apos; ProtectionSociety, Manchester. National Union of agricultural workers. National Union of Scottish MineWorkers. Provan   Housing   Association,Glasgow. War Rents League      ......Witness. Mr. W. C. Woodward.Mr. Andrew Henderson.Mr. A. R. Edwards.Mr. W. Holmes.Mr. A. Sloan.Bailie Jean Mann.Mr. Dan Rider.B. Representing-Property Owners. Central Landowners&apos; AssociationNational Federation of property owners    and    Factors    ofScotland. National Federation of property owners and Ratepayers. Property Owners and FactorsAssociation, Glasgow, Ltd. Property    Owners   ProtectionAssociation.C. Government Departments.Ministry   of   Agriculture   andFisheries. Ministry of Labour      ......D. Local Authorities.London County council the  Lord  Cranworth, M.C.Mr.       R.       Murray MacGregor, B.L.Mr. E. J. Churchman, JP-Mr. H. Miller Fletcher.Mr.     Harold    Griffm, F.S.L, F.A.I., J.P.Mr.   E.   L.   Mitchell,C B E Mr. H.&quot; H. Cook.Mr.     H. F.S.I.Westwood,E. Legal and Technical Societies, Associations, etc.Building Societies Association ...   Mr. G. E. Jackson.Mr.   G.   L.   Vigers,Chartered Surveyors&apos; Institution J    ^^&quot;t^;.   ^ ttt ,Mr. J. A. F. Watson,F.S.I.
Legal and Technical Societies, Associations, etc. cont. Organisation. Witness.Chartered  Surveyors&apos;   Institu-   Mr. A. Lickley Proctor,tion, Scottish Branch. F.S.I.Joint Committee of Legal society-   Mr. Rutherford Fortune, ties in Scotland. S.S.C.Law Society      ......      ...   Mr.   L.   S.   Holmes,LL.M., J.P.F. Private Individuals.Councillor Dudley Appleby, Newcastle-on-Tyne.Mr. A. F. Lovatt, Birmingham.Mr, E. Roberts, Town Clerk, Merthyr Tydfil.Mr. Lewis Silkin, M.P., London.Mr. R. A. Simpson, Edinburgh.Written Evidence.5. The organisations and persons from whom written state-ments of evidence and letters have been received include the following:  Tenants&apos; Associations.East London Tenants&apos; League. St. Helens Tenants&apos; Association.Sparkbrook, Sparkhill and Midland Districts Tenants&apos;Association. West Wales Tenants&apos; Defence Association.Property Owners&apos; Associations.Association of House Factors in Edinburgh and Leith. Freeholders&apos; Society.Liverpool and District Property Owners and Ratepayers Association.Government Departments.Department of Agriculture for Scotland. Department of Health for Scotland. Ministry of Health. Public Trustee Office. Unemployment Assistance Board.Local Authorities.Association of County Councils in Scotland. Association of Municipal Corporations. Convention of Royal Burghs. Urban District Councils Association. Middlesex County Council. Birmingham County Borough Council. Blackburn County Borough Council.47389 A 4
4 rLocal Authorities cont.Lincoln County Borough Council. Smethwick County Borough Council. South Shields County Borough Council. Bermondsey Metropolitan Borough Council. Deptford Metropolitan Borough Council. Fulham Metropolitan Borough Council. Jarrow Borough Council. Wrexham Borough Council. Conisbrough Urban District Council. Dundee Corporation. Edinburgh Corporation. Glasgow Corporation.Other Organisations.Association of County Court Registrars. Auctioneers&apos; and Estate Agents&apos; Institute of the United Kingdom.Bentham Committee for Poor Litigants. Communist Party of Great Britain. Edinburgh and District Trades and Labour Council. Faculty of Procurators in Paisley.Incorporated Society of Auctioneers and Landed PropertyAgents. Land Agents&apos; Society. Land Union.Liverpool Personal Service Society (Inc.). Manchester and Salford Better Housing Council. Manchester and Salford Trades Council. Metropolitan Housing Corporation, Limited. National Association  of Auctioneers,  House Agents,Rating Surveyors and Valuers, Limited. National Council of Labour. National Farmers&apos; Union. National Unemployed Workers&apos; Movement. Sanitary Inspectors Association. Society of Our Lady of Good Counsel. Society of Women Housing Estate Managers. Southwark Housing Association, Limited. Standing  Joint  Committee  of  Industrial  Womens&apos;Organisations. Trades House of Glasgow.Individuals.Town Clerk, Aberdeen. Councillor Griffin, Greenock. Mrs. E. J. Heaton, Petworth. Mr. R. Jackson, Derby. Mr. R. M. Leslie, Aberdeen.
Individuals cont.Councillor Leslie M. Lever, LL.B., Manchester.Mr. W. Miles, Enfield.Mr. Hugh Reid, Motherwell.Mr. J. S. W. Whybrew, Hampstead.Mr. H. Heathcote-Williams, Barrister-at-Law, London.6. The evidence received appears to us to have been fully representative of all the interests concerned and of every aspect of the questions we were appointed to consider.7. Recognising the importance of the statistical aspect of our inquiry and the necessity for presenting the statistical evidence submitted to us in a form giving to the layman an intelligible picture of those aspects of the general housing situation of the country which bear on problems of Rent Restriction, we appointed a Statistical Sub-Committee &quot; to examine and report on (a) the statistics furnished to the Committee by the Ministry of Health in the light of the evidence of the Ministry of Labour and other witnesses, and (6) any other statistical aspects of the Committee&apos;s inquiry, as, e.g. the cost of repairs &quot;. The work of the Sub-Committee has been of the greatest value to us and much of the material prepared by it is incorporated in this Report.8. We have met on 12 days, on eight of which we heard oral evidence by the 26 witnesses who have appeared before us.PART II.SUMMARY OF THE PRESENT POSITION. UNDER THEACTS.9. The history and evolution of the Rent Restrictions Acts is fully and clearly set out in the Report of the Marley Committee (Cmd. 3911) and it seems to us superfluous to recapitulate it in this Report. There have, however, been certain changes in the law following the Marley Report and in order to indicate the background from which our recommendations spring we think it well at the beginning of our Report to give a brief outline of the present position under the Acts.10. The Acts at present in force in whole or in part are:  Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1920.Rent Restrictions (Notices of Increase) Act, 1923. Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions Act, 1923. Prevention of Eviction Act, 1924.Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions Continuation) Act, 1925.
6 oRent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions (Amendment) Act, 1933-Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1935-They expire on the 24th June, 1938, in England and Wales and on the 28th May, 1938, in Scotland.11. The principal objects of the Acts at present in force in relation to the dwellings to which they apply are:  (a) to protect the tenant against his landlord by(i) limiting the rent he can be called on to pay, and (ii) providing him with security of tenure while hepays his rent, and(&amp;) to protect the landlord against his mortgagee by(i) limiting the rate of mortgage interest he can be called on to pay, and(ii) providing against the calling in of the mortgage so long as this interest is paid.12. The Act of 1933 divided controlled houses into three cate-gories usually referred to as Class A, Class B and Class C by reference to rateable value at the 1st April, 1931, in England and Wales, and yearly value in the valuation roll for 1931-2 in Scotland.Class A houses.In the Metropolitan Police District,* over  45. In Scotland, over  45. Elsewhere, over  35.Class B houses.In the Metropolitan Police District, over  20 but not over  45-In Scotland, over  26 5s. but not over  45. Elsewhere, over  13 but not over  35.Class C houses.In the Metropolitan Police District,  20 or under. In Scotland,  26 5s. or under. Elsewhere,  13 or under.Class A houses were decontrolled by the Act of 1933 as from the 29th September, 1933, in England and Wales and as from the 28th November, 1933, in Scotland. The restrictions on mortgages on these houses were continued for six months after the passing of the Act and then ceased to apply.* Throughout this Report reference to the Metropolitan Police District should be read as including also reference to the City of London.
Class B houses are still subject to the provisions of the Acts but become decontrolled on the landlord coming into possession in accordance with the terms of Section 2 of the Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions Act, 1923. The number of houses in Class B subject to control is therefore constantly being reduced.Class C houses which were controlled on the passing of the Act of 1933, he., on the 18th July, 1933, are continued in control by Section 2 of that Act and no longer become decontrolled on the landlord coming into possession. The number of controlled houses in Class C is therefore at present stationary, except for reduction due to demolition, conversion into business premises, etc.13. Registration of decontrolled Class C houses. Every Class C house which was let as a separate dwelling immediately before the 18th July, 1933, and which the landlord claimed had become decontrolled during the period 1923-33 had to be regis-tered within three months of the passing of the Act of 1933, in a register kept by the local housing authority for the purpose and open to public inspection. Any such house not registered in this period is deemed to be a controlled house unless the Court certifies that there was reasonable excuse for the failure to register, and allows registration.14. Onus of Proof of Decontrol. The certificate of registra-tion is evidence of registration but cannot be received as evidence of decontrol. The burden of proof that the house is controlled lies on the tenant, both in the case of Class B houses and of Class C houses registered as decontrolled.15. Sub-Tenancies. A statutory tenant can sub-let part of the premises unless sub-letting is prohibited by the terms of the contractual tenancy on which the statutory tenancy is founded, but he cannot assign or sub-let the whole of the premises, the object of the Acts being to protect an occupying tenant. Where the interest of a tenant is determined any sub-tenant to whom the premises have been lawfully sub-let is deemed to become the tenant of the landlord. A tenant who has lawfully sub-let may charge the sub-tenant an additional 10 per cent, of the net rent of the part sub-let and the landlord, to whom notice of the sub-letting must be given, is entitled to increase the rent of the tenant by 5 per cent, of the net rent of the part sub-let. Where a tenant has charged a sub-tenant a rent in excess of the permitted amount the landlord is entitled to apply to tire Courts for possession. For the purpose of determining the standard rent the Courts have power to apportion the standard rent as between a dwelling-house and any part sub-let and a tenant who knowingly charges a sub-tenant a rent in excess of that appor-tioned to the sub-tenancy is liable to a fine not exceeding  100.
A tenant is required to supply the landlord with particulars of all sub-letting.16. Limitation of scope of Acts. The Acts do not apply to(a) Class A houses.(b) New houses built or bona fide converted into two or more self-contained flats or tenements since the 2nd April, 1919.(c) Houses in Class B and Class C which have become decontrolled, and, in the case of Class C houses, have been registered as decontrolled.(d) Premises used solely for business purposes (but not houses of which part only is used for business purposes).(e) Public houses.(/) Furnished lettings (subject to certain provisions relat-ing to the charging of extortionate rents). (g) Houses in service occupation.17. Restrictions on Rent. Rents of controlled houses are restricted by reference to the &quot; standard rent &quot;, i.e., the rent at which the house was let on the 3rd August, 1914. In any pro-ceedings in which sufficient evidence on this point cannot be obtained the Court has power to determine the standard rent by reference to the standard rents of similar houses in the neighbourhood.18. The permitted increases are:  (a) An increase of 15 per cent, of the net rent, which is the standard rent less the amount of the tenant&apos;s rates where these are paid by the landlord.(&amp;) A further increase of 25 per cent, of the net rent where the landlord is responsible for all repairs.(c) Where the landlord pays the rates, an increase equal to the amount of any increased rates payable by him. In Scotland this increase is not permitted in respect of any increase in owner&apos;s rates after Whitsunday (i.e., 15th May), 1920.(d) An increase of 8 per cent, of expenditure by the land-lord on structural alterations or improvements (6 per cent, on expenditure incurred between the 4th August, 1914, and the 2nd July, 1920). Expenditure since the Act of 1933, on additional or improved fixtures or fittings (not being decorations or repairs) can be deemed expenditure on improvements.(e) An increase in the rent of the whole house of 5 per cent of the net rent of any part sub-let, and an increase of 10 per cent, in the net rent of the part sub-let.An increase of rent in excess of these permitted increases is. irrecoverable from the tenant.
ig. A tenant can apply to the Court for an Order suspending the permitted increases (a) and (b), known together as &quot; the 40 per cent, increase &quot;, if he can satisfy the Court by a certifi-cate of the sanitary authority, or otherwise, that the house is not in a reasonable state of repair, or alternatively, if he has such a certificate, he may withhold the increase and, if sued for pay-ment, may put in the certificate as prima facie evidence that the house is, or was, not in a reasonable state of repair. It is the duty of the sanitary authority to issue a certificate on application if satisfied that the house is not in reasonable repair and the certificate cannot be withheld if a notice requiring the execution of repairs has been issued under the provisions now consolidated in Section 9 of the Housing Act, 1936, or under Section 14 of the Housing (Scotland) Act, 1930.20. Premiums and Key Money. The taking of premiums or key money by landlords in respect of controlled houses is punish-able by a fine not exceeding  100 and since 1920 such payments have been recoverable from the landlord. A tenant of a con-trolled house can be fined for demanding from any person except his landlord a premium for giving up possession.21. Protection against eviction. The landlord can only recover possession of a controlled house by Order of the Court. Before making an Order the Court must be satisfied that it would be reasonable to do so and that suitable alternative accom-modation is available for the tenant, or will be available when the Order takes effect. An Order may, however, be made with-out proof of suitable alternative accommodation if (a) The tenant has not paid his rent or carried out his other obligations as tenant.(&amp;) The tenant or any person residing with him has been guilty of conduct which is a nuisance, or has been convicted of using the premises for immoral or illegal purposes, or by neglect or default is causing the condition of the house to deteriorate.(c) The tenant has given notice to quit in consequence of which the landlord has contracted to sell or let the house.(d) The tenant has without the consent of the landlord assigned or sub-let the whole of the house.    \(e) The house is the subject of an off-licence and the tenant has not conducted the business to the satisfaction of the licensing justices, or the police, or the renewal of the licence has been refused.(/) The house is so overcrowded as to be dangerous to the health of the inmates, and the Court is satisfied that the overcrowding could have been abated by the removal of a lodger or sub-tenant and the tenant has not taken steps to remove the lodger or sub-tenant.
IO(g) The house is reasonably required by the landlord for an employee and either the tenant was formerly employed by the landlord and the house let to him in consequence of his employment, or the house is required for an agricultural worker employed by the landlord.(h) The house is reasonably required by the landlord (except where he became landlord by purchase after the nth July, 1931) for himself, his son or daughter over 18 years of age, or his father or mother, but the Court in such case cannot make an Order if satisfied that greater hardship would be caused by granting the Order than by refusing to grant it.22. Alternative accommodation. A certificate of the housing authority that the authority will provide suitable alternative accommodation for the tenant is conclusive evidence that suit-able alternative accommodation will be available for him. Where no certificate is produced to the Court accommodation is deemed to be suitable if it consists either (a) of a controlled house, or(6) of a house to be let on terms which afford the tenant equivalent security of tenure to a controlled house, and is in the opinion of the Court reasonably suitable to the needs of the tenant and his family as regards proximity to place of work and either(i) the rent and size of the house is similar to the Council houses in the neighbourhood provided by the local authority for persons whose needs are similar to those of the tenant, or(ii) is otherwise reasonably suitable to the means of the tenant and to the needs of himself and his family as regards extent and character.23. Mortgages. The Acts apply to mortgages on controlled houses created before the 2nd July, 1920. The rate of interest may be increased by 1 per cent, subject to an over-riding maximum of per cent. A mortgagee is restricted from calling in his mortgage or enforcing his security so long as the interest is not more than 21 days in arrear, the covenants by the mortgagor are observed and the mortgagor keeps the property in proper repair. These provisions do not apply to mortgages where the principal is repayable by instalments spread over ten years or longer; they do not affect any power of sale possessed by a mortgagee in possession on the 25th March, 1920; nor do they apply where the mortgagor consents to the exercise by the mortgagee of his powers under the mortgage. If the Court is satisfied that a mortgage of leasehold property is seriously diminishing in value it may, under the terms of Section 7 (ii) of the Act of 1920 authorise the mortgagee to call in the mortgage.
24- Administration. The administration of the Acts is not vested in any Government Department, all questions of dispute being settled by the Courts, who have jurisdiction inter aha to decide summarily any question as to the amount of rent, net rent, standard rent, apportionment of standard rent, or per-mitted increase of rent. The local housing authorities are responsible for keeping the register of decontrolled Class C houses. They also have power to set up a Special Committee of the Council to give information for the assistance of landlords and tenants as to their rights and duties under the Acts and as to procedure, and in England and Wales they have power to prosecute for offences.PART 111.GENERAL HOUSING POSITION.25. Much of the evidence given before us was based on two diametrically opposed social principles. Many of the witnesses representing tenants regard the control of rents as a thing desirable in itself and some of them urged the permanent exten-sion of control to all working-class houses, new and old, and advocated the setting up of special Rent Courts to deal with all questions as to rent and tenure arising between land-lords and tenants. Witnesses representing landlords, on the other hand, put forward the view that control should be regarded as a temporary expedient introduced solely to meet the emer-gency created by the War; that, apart altogether from the question of hardship to landlords, its continuance in respect of a diminishing proportion of privately-owned houses created un-justifiable anomalies between different classes of houses which could not otherwise be distinguished; and that it should be terminated at the earliest practicable moment so that normal relations between landlord and tenant might be resumed in respect of all private property. The view which we ourselves have adopted and which forms the basis of our recommenda-tions for the future of control is that taken by our predecessors, the Marley Committee.26. The Marley Committee stressed in their Report the close connection between the control of rents and the general housing situation, and drew attention to the fact that, although the Rent Restrictions Acts were originally emergency measures designed to protect tenants from increases of rent due to the temporary stoppage of building during the War, the ground on which they have since been periodically extended has been that the con-tinued shortage of houses might result in the exaction of scarcity rents if control were removed. The Marley Committee con-cluded &quot; that the question of continuing control of any par-ticular class of house must be regarded as dependent on whether the shortage of houses in that class is at an end or is likely to end within a reasonable period.  The shortage is both a measure
12 Iof the need for control and the main barrier to its removal. While it is not desirable to retain control longer than is necessary we cannot accept the suggestion that, regardless of the shortage, a date must be fixed for final decontrol .... At the same time we fully appreciate that, in imposing control on those who own or have invested their money in house property, Parlia-ment is imposing on one section of property owners restrictions which it is imposing on no other; and, whenever restrictions of this kind are imposed in the general interest, cases of great hardship among the class controlled are bound to occur. We are, therefore, of the opinion that the restrictions should at once be lifted from any class of property as soon as it can be shown that they are no longer needed in the general interest.&quot; With these conclusions we are in full agreement and it follows that the question of rent control cannot be considered independently of the general position of housing throughout the country. On this point we have received valuable evidence from the Ministry of Health and the Department of Health for Scotland (as well as interesting sidelights from some of our witnesses) and we also have had the advantage of two important social documents not in existence at the time of the Marley Committee&apos;s investi-gation, namely the Reports of the Overcrowding Surveys in England and Wales and in Scotland, which for the first time in the history of housing provide a substantially accurate measure of the extent of the housing shortage in every local government area in the three countries.27. To obtain as complete a picture as possible of the general housing position in Great Britain we have attempted to bring up to date the analysis included in the Report of the Marley Committee of the numbers of controlled and decontrolled houses in the various categories. The only statistics available during the Marley Committee&apos;s investigation had not been kept in the categories subsequently adopted by the Committee and for the purposes of comparison the figures included in their Report have accordingly been rearranged and are presented in the new categories, as was done in the statistical memorandum (Cmd. 4208) published by the Minister of Health and the Secretary of State for Scotland in 1932. As we have mentioned already, the Marley Committee divided the various types of houses into three categories by reference to their rateable value in England and Wales or their yearly value in Scotland, namely:  Metropolitan Rest of England Police District.        and Wales. Scotland.Class A     ...   Over  45   ...      Over  35   ... Over ^45Class B     ...    20-^45     ...       13^35  26 5s--^45Class C      ...    20 or under       13 or under  26 5s. or underWhen in this Report we refer to a Class A, Class B or Class C house it is with reference to these categories. Although the classes were related primarily only to controlled houses, we shall
Class A(&quot;Controlled ... ] Not controlled/&quot;Decontrolled 1 New326,000 \ 350,000/[&quot; Controlled...............Class B  A Not control]ed  /Decontrolled 200,000 \ L \New        ...  700,000/f ControlledClass CJNot controlledScotland.f ControlledClass A  jNotcontrolled   ^Decontrolled... 21,000yNumber of Houses. 530,000. 670,000-1,200,0001,350,000 900,0002,250,0004.375-000 1,225,000-5,600,000Number of Houses.45,000- &quot;.;  . 26,000f ControlledClass BClass C^Not controlled  (g^&quot;;;; ^)f ControlledNot controlled/Decontrolled... 88,ooo\\New92,000 /71,000193,000 67,000260,000612,000 180,000702,000.*^ .........Analysis of housing position in 1937.29. In bringing the Marley Committee&apos;s analysis up to date, from 1931 to 1937, we have taken into account the following factors:  (a) The numbers of new houses of each class erected since 1931-47389 A *include in the terms all other houses within the specified limits of rateable value or yearly value and, further, as regards Class C we shall often use the term to include all small houses, new and old (such as those provided by housing authorities) available for the working-class population.Marley Committee&apos;s analysis of housing position in 1931.28. The original analysis made in 1931 by the Marley Com-mittee according to this classification was as follows: &apos; England and Wales.
14 (:(&amp;&apos;)&apos; The number of houses demolished.(c) The number of houses which have become decon-trolled.30. As to (a) we have had evidence from the Ministry of Health and the Department of Health for Scotland.31. As to (b) we have only had evidence as to the number of unfit houses demolished under the slum clearance programmes and have been unable to obtain any accurate information as to the number of houses demolished for industrial re-development, etc. In order to take account of this unknown factor we have estimated that the total number demolished for all purposes other than slum clearance since 1914 is, in England and Wales, about 60,000, and in Scotland, about 10,000.32. As to (c) the decontrol on vacant possession of Class C houses ceased on the passing of the Act of 1933, but it was, of course, in operation between the date of the Marley Report and the date of the Act&apos;. When the Marley Committee examined this problem the percentage of decontrol in pre-War Class C houses was about 12J per cent.; it is now, according to the evidence of the Ministry of Labour, 24 per cent, on average throughout Great Britain, and slightly less, namely, 22 per cent, in Scotland alone. The decontrol on vacant possession of pre-War Class B houses has been continuously in operation since 1923, and the percentage decontrolled may be assumed to amount now to at least 40 per cent. Class A houses were all decontrolled by the Act of 1933.33. On the basis of these assumptions we estimate that the up-to-date analysis of the housing position according to categories is in round figures as follows: England and Wales.Number of Houses.Class A     Not controlled  /Decontrolled......     850,000\New     ...      ...      ...     400,0001,250,000f Controlled.........      -.....     950,0002,950,000fControlled................3,600,000Class C n j   /Decontrolled......   1,200,000uiassc  ^Not controlled  ^New     .........1,500,0006,300,000
I 1534. It will be noted that the 5,000,000 pre-War Class C houses in England and Wales included in the Marley analysis have been reduced by 200,000 to 4,800,000 owing to demolition, and that a much greater proportion of the total number are now decontrolled than was the case at the time of the Marley investigation.   The post-War Class C houses comprise:   Houses erected by local authorities       ...      950,000 Houses erected by private enterprise    ...      550,0001,500,000On the question how many of these 550,000 private enterprise houses are let to tenants, as distinct from those occupied by their owners, we know from the returns which have been obtained since 1934,. that during the three years ending March, 1937, 109,000 (roughly one-third) of the Class C houses erected have been let. Probably, therefore, from 150,000 to 200,000 out of the 550,000 are let.35. In the case of Scotland the percentage of decontrol in pre-War Class C houses is 22 per cent., slightly less than in England. The percentage of decontrol in Class B houses is probably at least 33J per cent, which is the figure we have taken for the following analysis. The statistics supplied by the Department of Health for Scotland, did not classify houses according to values in the valuation roll, but according to the number of apartments they contain. It was therefore neces-sary to make additional assumptions in preparing the table. It has been assumed that all houses erected by the local authori-ties are Class C houses and that one-fifth of the houses erected by private enterprise with State assistance are also Class C houses, the remainder being Class B houses. Houses of more than five rooms erected by private enterprise without State assfst-ance have been treated as Class A houses.Class A     Not controlledScotland./&quot;Decontrolled \NewNumber of Houses. 66,000 7,000f Controlledrin^ T?     ,T ,   1, j   f Decontrolledoiass d 1 Not controlled -I New(&quot;Controlled     ......Class C   lNotcontrolled (g^^73,000150,000 70,000 73,000293,000490,000 140,000 189,000819,00047389A*2
i6 (36. It will be noted that the 700,000 pre-War Class C houses in Scotland included in the Marley analysis have been assumed to be reduced to 630,000 by demolition (there were nearly 60,000 demolitions due to slum clearance). The new houses are almost entirely comprised in the 179,000 houses erected by the local authorities.37. The statistics of new houses erected since 1934 which in England and Wales have been kept according to the categories established by the Marley Committee make it possible in some measure to check the previous estimates. The new figures sug-gest that the Marley Committee rather under-estimated the number of Class C houses erected by private enterprise. At the date of their Report private enterprise had erected 1,100,000 new houses which the Committee apparently allocated roughly as 40,000 Class C, 700,000 Class B, and 350,000 Class A. (They explained that they considered that the operation of Sec-tion 12 (9) of the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1920, had operated to keep down rateable values, and they endeavoured to take account of this.) It seems clear from the later statistics that these proportions were not justified on the basis of rateable values only, but the Committee appear also to have had regard to the assumption then current that very few of the houses being built by private enterprise were for letting.Comparison between 1931 and 1937.38. The following table compares the present position with the position as given in the Marley Report of 1931:  Total Number of Class C houses. Percentage controlled	England and Wales.		Scotland.		1931-5,600,000 Per cent. 78	1937-6,300,000 Per cent. 57	I931-792,000 Per cent. 77	1937-819,000 Per cent. 60Total Number of Class B houses. Percentage controlled	2,250,000 Per cent. 60	2,950,000 Per cent. 32	260,000 Per cent. 74	293,000 Per cent. 50Total Number of houses in Classes A, B, and C. Percentage controlled	9,050,000 Per cent. 69	10,500,000 Per cent. 43	1,123,000 Per cent. 76	1,185,000 Per cent. 5439. Incidentally a comparison of this table with that given in paragraph 28 will show that the proportion of houses in England and Wales in Class B which are now uncontrolled, namely, 68 per cent., exceeds the proportion of uncontrolled houses in Class A, in 1931 when the Marley Committee decided to recom-mend the termination of control in that class, namely, 56 per cent.
Rents.40. We have endeavoured to supplement this broad classifica-tion of houses into categories with an analysis which would show, in similarly broad outline, the rents at present being paid by the working classes. This has appeared to us to be possible so far as England and Wales are concerned. In the first place there is now available a published return (Cmd. 5527) giving the rents charged by local authorities for houses and flats belonging to them. There are also the results of a return (not quite com-plete) obtained by the Ministry of Health giving particulars of the rateable values of privately-owned small houses in most of the local government areas. These returns show that the aver-age of rateable values of privately-owned Class C houses are  s.in the Metropolitan Police District    ...      ...     13 18in County Boroughs    ...      ...      ... -    ...      90in other urban areas    ...      ...      ...      ...      812in rural areas    ...      ...      ...      .;&apos;;      ...      70For each of these rateable values an approximate range of aver-age net rents can be estimated on the assumption that assessments are based on the full net rent.41. The evidence of the Ministry of Labour gave average increases in rent of decontrolled houses as compared with con-trolled houses. As regards privately-owned new houses, in-formation is very incomplete, but is sufficient to show that, in general, the rents charged are considerably higher than the rents of small decontrolled houses. On the basis of this information the following table has been prepared to give a broad general picture of average working-class rents. The rents given are net rents, i.e., they are exclusive of rates, water charges, etc. It should be added as regards London that since the table is based on rateable values, it cannot take account of the rents paid by working-class families occupying parts of houses of a rateable value above  20 (Class B or even Class A houses).Approximate ranges of average net rents of working-class houses inType of House.Greater London.County Boroughs excluding Greater London.Other Urban Districts excluding Greater London. .Rural Districts excluding Greater London.s. d.8 69 o12 613 oto 6to   6 27 6to   7 97 2s. d. 5 10to . 5 107   o to   7   4 6 11s. d. 5   6s. d. 4   6 to   4 10Local authority 9 to    6   o,   6047389
42. The rents of houses belonging to local authorities in urban areas lie between the rents of controlled and decontrolled houses, being nearer to the decontrolled rents. Taking urban areas outside London and combining numbers of houses with rents paid, the general picture is as follows:  Fifty-seven per cent, of working-class houses have an average net rent of about 6s. (Controlled).Nineteen per cent, of working-class houses have an average net rent of about 7s. 6d. (Decontrolled).Sixteen per cent, of working-class houses have an average net rent of about 7s. (Local Authority).Eight per cent, of working-class houses have an average net rent of about (say) 10s. (New private) . On the same assumptions the average net rent for all types would be about 6s. gd. per week.43. In considering what effect any further measure of de-control would be likely to have on the general level of working-class rents, it must be borne in mind that (unless control were extended by Act of Parliament to existing houses which are not at present controlled) the number of controlled houses cannot increase. It is, in fact, steadily diminishing as a result of demolition and the operation of the present provision for decontrol on vacant possession in Class B. Similarly the number of &quot; decontrolled &quot; houses, i.e., houses which have at one time been controlled, can only be increased by. the decontrol of further Class B houses at present controlled. No new houses built since the War can fall into either of these two categories. The percentage of working-class families in urban areas in England and Wales outside London at present kving in con-trolled houses is only 57. The remaining 43 per cent, live in houses which are not at present controlled. The number of &quot; new,&quot; i.e., post-War houses of all classes, is at present being increased at the rate of over 60,000 Council houses and 250,000 private houses annually, and while, for reasons given later in our Report, we think that the output of houses by private enter-prise will not necessarily continue at the present rate, it is obvious that the proportion of controlled houses, and therefore of families living in controlled houses, is being very rapidly reduced, and that it cannot be long before even in Class C houses it will be less than 50 per cent, throughout the greater part of England and Wales. We mention this point because there has been a tendency on the part of some of our witnesses to assume that the great majority of working-class families are at present living in controlled dwellings, whereas, as will be seen from what we have already said, it is much nearer the truth to say that one working-class family out of every two is already living in an uncontrolled house.
I 1944. The explanation of this position is to be found in the statistics supplied to us by the Ministry of Health, as analysed in the tables already given, which show what a large increase in the supply of houses in England and Wales has taken place in the last few years. It has much more than kept pace with the growth of population as is shown by the great reduction in the number of persons per dwelling-house. In England and Wales in 1921 there were 4*67 persons per house, while in September, 1936, there were only 3-64. The corresponding figures for Scotland are 4-45 in 1921 and 3-95 to-day. We are, of course, aware that this is not the whole story, and that the increase in the number of families and the diminution in the number of persons per family must be taken into account in a full analysis. The figures are quoted merely to emphasise the fact that, in England and Wales at any rate, great inroads must have been made on any general housing shortage. There were 5,000,006 Class C houses in 1914 and now there are 6,300,000, an increase of 26 per cent. There were about 1,500,000 Class B houses in 1914 and now there are nearly 3,000,000, an increase of 100 per cent. In the intervening period the population has only risen by 10 per cent. The figures are only intelligible on the assump-tion that a large proportion of the Class B houses are being occupied by persons who were previously living in Class C houses. We assume that for the most part these persons must be the better paid members of the working classes in regular employment who are able to face the habihty of increased rent or repayments to Building Societies.PART IV.FUTURE HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS.45. The erection of houses is, of course, still continuing and they may be expected to be built in large numbers, though not perhaps at the present unprecedented rate, for some years to come. So far as England and Wales are concerned, the Ministry of Health in their evidence distinguished three factors influencing future house production.(1) Actual shortage of accommodation assessed on the . basis of the overcrowding, survey.(2) Needs, arising from a shortage of satisfactory dwell-ings of the right type, e.g., the needs of persons at present fiving in houses which are unfit for habitation or otherwise unsuitable, or from pressure on housing accommodation in a particular locality occasioned by an influx of population.(3) Demand, occasioned by the desire of persons already adequately housed, to have a new house, and by their financial ability to acquire one.47389 A* 4
It was pointed out to us that the houses required under head-ings (i) and (2) fall almost exclusively to be built by the local authorities, while those built under (3) are the production of private enterprise.Shortage.46. According to evidence given by the Ministry of Health, the iotal number of families in England and Wales found to be overcrowded during the overcrowding survey carried out in 1936 under the Act of the previous year was 341,554. It is difficult to estimate exactly the number of new houses which will be required to relieve this overcrowding, as much of it is being relieved by interchanges of tenants or abated by natural changes in the size of families. It has.been suggested that the number may be approximately 60 per cent, of the total number of over-crowded families but in view of the comparatively short experi-ence in administering the statutory provisions relating to over-crowding this figure must be accepted with reserve. On this basis, however, approximately 200,000 houses would be required for the relief of overcrowding and we have taken this figure as representing the actual shortage of accommodation in these two countries. The number of new houses so far com-pleted specifically to meet this shortage is about 2,000, but, in fact, local authorities, even where they are solely engaged in building replacement houses for slum clearance purposes, are in many cases building large houses which are let to over-crowded families while the families from unfit property are housed in the accommodation which the overcrowded families have vacated.Needs.47. The number of houses required to meet present needs, as defined above, cannot be reliably assessed. The aggregate need is made up of the following items: (a) Needs of families occupying houses which are unfit for habitation.(6) Needs of families occupying houses which, while not technically unfit or overcrowded, are otherwise unsuitable.(c) Needs of persons wishing to set up separate homes of their own.(d) Needs of persons wishing to move to another district.(e) Needs of classes of persons of low rent-paying capa-city, e.g. agricultural workers, who are paying more rent than they can afford.48. The number of houses required for slum clearance pur-poses is the only point on which figures are available. The total number of unfit houses included in the revised slum clear-ance programmes of local authorities in England and Wales
is now, we understand, just over 400,000. Just over 230,000 new houses have so far been approved by the Ministry for replacement purposes, of which about 170,000 are completed. It may therefore be assumed that over-150,000 additional houses will be required for slum clearance purposes to complete the revised programmes, and, at the present rate of progress, this number represents between two and three years&apos; output by local authorities. It would appear, however, that the work of slum clearance will not necessarily cease when the present pro-grammes are completed, as each year a further number of old houses will reach the age when they are no longer fit for further habitation.49. In this connection it must be borne in mind that the bulk of the new houses still required both for slum clearance and for the relief of overcrowding will fall to be built by the authorities responsible for the large towns, and we understand that a large number of the smaller local authorities in England and Wales will have completed their programmes within the next 12 months. A certain number have indeed already done so, and when this stage has been reached there will be no longer any actual shortage of accommodation in the area, although there may still be a demand for new houses with post-War amenities.Demand.50. The improvement in the standard of the type of house now being built for the working classes and the general apprecia-tion of the benefits of this better type, coinciding with a period of comparative prosperity, have resulted in tha wholesale demand for a post-War house with modern amenities which is the outstanding feature of the present housing situation. This change of outlook has led to a demand for new houses which has no relation either to shortage or to the needs discussed above, and which may well result in a number of old houses being put out of use as obsolete which will falsify all previous estimates. The demand is clearly dependent on continued pros-perity, but so long as wage rates generally do not decline and there is no great rise in building costs or interest rates there seems no reason why the production of houses by private enter-prise to meet this demand should not continue, though not necessarily on the present scale, until a considerable proportion of pre-War houses have been replaced by a more modern type. The number of houses built by private enterprise has been main-tained at the rate of 250,000 a year since 1934. The following figures published in the monthly issues of the Ministry of Labour Gazette relating to dwelling-houses for which plans were approved during the first eight months of 1937 by the local authorities for 146 large towns in England and Wales afford some evidence for holding that a decline in the rate of building of dwelling-houses is, however, beginning to set in.
	No. of	No. for			houses for	which plans	Increase	Percentage	which plans	were	or	Increase or	were	approved.	Decrease.	Decrease.	approved,	1936.			1937-			January	9.I41	13,534	- 4-393	- 32-46February ...	10,906	14,149	- 3,243	  22-92March      ......	12,429	11,940	4    489	4-   4 - 096April	14,480	13,120	4- 1,360	-r- 10-37May	&quot;,747	i5,709	- 3,962	- 25-22June        ......	11,988	14,099	  2,111	- 14-97July      ......	12,460	13,94s	- 1,488	  10-67August     ......	6,988	10,956	- 3,968	- 36-22PART V.EXTENT OF PRESENT HOUSE SHORTAGE.51. The movement into the new houses built to meet this demand for a modern house must inevitably have had a marked effect in overcoming any shortage of pre-War houses on the same general rent level as the new. This is shown, apart from statistics, by the evidence given us that, in Manchester, for example, there are many empty Class B houses which are now unlettable to the type of tenant who would normally occupy such a house, notwithstanding that the rent asked is below the level of the controlled rent. Even in Scotland, where the housing position is, in general, much worse than in England, witnesses agreed that there was no difficulty in most places in obtaining empty houses (though not necessarily of a desirable type), at rents from about  35 per annum upwards.52. Some of our witnesses have been inclined to press for the continuance of control not only until there is no longer any actual shortage of houses but until there is.a-sufficient supply of good and satisfactory houses available at rents not exceeding the level of controlled rents. We have great sympathy with the feeling underlying this view, namely, that the housing problem cannot be regarded as solved until good and suitable accommodation is available for every one according to his needs and within, his means, but in our view it is not relevant to the question of the. continuance of control. The houses at present controlled were all in existence prior to 1914. Many of them were, in fact, built long before that date, and they necessarily include most of the oldest and least satisfactory houses in the country. Some of them are being demolished as no longer fit for habitation. Naturally, as more houses are provided, the least desirable houses will be vacated firsthand, as pressure on
accommodation relaxes, will remain empty, even although the rents asked are below the controlled level. These empty houses may not be attractive, but they cannot be ignored. Their existence in large numbers would ensure that decontrol could be accomplished without the danger of scarcity rents being exacted, and that is the primary consideration to be borne in mind. Some persons appear to fear that the removal of control from pre-War houses would cause the rents of post-War houses to rise.  We cannot see any ground for such fears.53. The general conclusion which might&apos;be drawn from the various facts is that as regards Class B houses, of which there are now about twice as many as there were at the end of the War, there is not now such a shortage that if control were removed scarcity rents could be exacted. This is almost certainly broadly true, even of Scotland, but it does not immediately follow that all Class B houses, like Class A houses, can in all places and simul-taneously be decontrolled without hardship. Considerations not present in the case of Class A houses are involved. It is not so much that the number of Class B houses is larger than the number of Class A houses as that their tenants are of a lower economic class, shading into the working class at the lower rate-able values. In London, where a large proportion of the work-ing classes are housed in parts of large dwellings originally built for occupation by a single family, it is probably true that the majority of Class B houses are occupied by working-class tenants and sub-tenants. It is therefore hardly sufficient to know that for Great Britain as a whole there is no longer a shortage; it is desirable to ascertain whether or not there are sub-stantial parts of each of the three countries where the general housing conditions are such that complete decontrol of Class B houses would be likely to cause hardship. If it should be found that there are such areas the question will arise whether the rest of each country is to await the amelioration of the conditions in these particular areas or whether the present Acts should be altered to provide for varying degrees of control in different localities. This is a large question of principle which must inevitably arise at the stage of the housing and rent restriction problem which we are now approaching. It was foreseen and discussed by the Onslow Committee in 1923 although it was not then considered opportune to deal with it.54. The Ministry of Health stated in their evidence that there are parts of England and Wales where there is no longer any housing shortage, and as house-building continues the number and extent of these parts must grow. On the other hand, in the inner congested areas of London and some other large cities in England, the pressure on housing accommodation is likely to continue for a considerable time, while this is also true of Scot-land generally.   The recent overcrowding surveys carried out
PART VI.FUTURE OF CONTROL.57. As we have already indicated, we think that the situation is now such that the major question which has to be faced is whether a uniform system of control of prerWar houses should be continued for Great Britain as a whole, notwithstanding the growing number of areas where no housing shortage exists, because it is still necessary in certain congested areas.under the Housing.Acts of 1935 give for the first time compre-hensive information relating to the housing position in every local government area compiled on a fairly uniform basis. The percentage of overcrowding in every area of the three countries is known and could be used as an index of the housing shortage in each area. The survey in England and Wales showed that 341,554 dwellings were overcrowded, representing 3-8 per cent, of the total of working-class dwellings. The average percentages for the different classes of local authority were:  Per cent.Metropolitan Boroughs (and City of London)      7-0 County Boroughs ...      ...      ...      ...      4-2Non-County Boroughs and Urban Districts ... 3-0 Rural Districts    ......      ...      ......      2-g55. The geographical distribution of overcrowding is very-uneven, a large proportion of authorities having a percentage under the averager for their class and the average being raised by a comparatively few cases of very high percentages. Thus Sixty-four per cent, of County Boroughs have percentages not exceeding 4.Sixty-four per cent, of non-County Boroughs and Urban Districts have percentages not exceeding 3.Fifty-eight per cent, of Rural Districts have percentages not exceeding z\.On the other hand there are over 30 local government districts in. England and Wales with a percentage of over 12-5. The worst overcrowding is concentrated in two areas, the East End of London and the North-East Coast.56. In contrast to the position in England and Wales, the survey in Scotland showed that, of the 1,146,534 houses sur-veyed, 22-6 per cent, or over a quarter of a million were over-crowded. This is about six times the rate of overcrowding in England and Wales. It is noteworthy that 75 per cent, of the overcrowded houses were of one and two apartments.
58. If the answer to this question is in the affirmative all we should be justified in recommending on the evidence before us is the decontrol of the upper range of houses in Class B with a rateable value (in 1931) exceeding  35 in London and Scotland and  20 elsewhere. Even in Scotland most witnesses indicated that there is no longer any serious shortage of this type of house. Such a restricted recommendation, however, would imply that the whole position would once again have to be reviewed after a further period before any further steps to terminate control could be taken, and it would be left to yet another Committee in a few years time to conduct an investigation similar to our own. It is already possible to forecast what, in the absence of any un-predictable national crisis, the results of such an investigation must be. The lines on which the housing situation is developing are plain and, assuming that no such crisis occurs, the lapse of a further period can effect no radical alteration. All that can happen is that the shortage will have lessened to an extent ascertainable by reference to the latest overcrowding surveys and an up-to-date analysis of the position then obtaining on the lines of our analyses in paragraphs 33 and 35 might be found to justify a further reduction in the upper limit of rateable value of the controlled classes, but would certainly emphasize more strongly the uneven distribution of shortage throughout England and Wales.59. It appears to us that the stage has now been reached when the possibility of varying degrees of control in different areas must be faced, and we have accordingly considered how a scheme could be framed which would provide for the gradual reduction and eventual termination of control in individual areas in England and Wales over a period of years without further investigation of the general workings of the Acts.60. It is true that certain happenings, such for instance as a major European war, might necessitate the reimposition of a measure of control on houses, but it is equally clear that should such a course become necessary a system of control based on rents charged in 1914 would not adequately meet the case and that some new system applicable to all houses would have to be devised. We feel, however, that it is outside our province to make suggestions for meeting an eventuality of this sort which would call for emergency measures designed to fit the occasion.61. Before going into the details of the scheme which we recommend for the reduction and termination of control, there are certain general observations which appear to be pertinent to any proposal for varying conditions or degrees of control in different areas.62. The first observation is that the areas would have to be chosen carefully to accord with the facts of the local housing situation. This can be illustrated by the case of London. The East End of London is severely overcrowded, and Class C houses
there must obviously remain controlled for some time to come. Other parts of London (e.g. Woolwich and Wandsworth) present very little overcrowding at all, and if those parts could be considered in isolation, the shortage of houses is so small that control could be removed, without undue hardship, in the near future. The essential fact in the housing situation of London is, however, that the different Metropolitan Boroughs, although they are separate housing authorities, cannot be considered in isolation. The people of the East End are so closely packed, that even if all the existing property were removed and the ground covered with new blocks of tall flats, it would be impossible to rehouse them without overcrowding. The only hope of abating the overcrowding in the East End is to encourage the movement of the people into less overcrowded neighbouring areas, and at the same time to secure that any house which becomes uncrowded remains uncrowded. The necessary mobility would be destroyed if control were removed from surrounding uncrowded areas. People would tend to stay in the place where they had a controlled house, and there would be further pressure on the controlled accommodation from people living in the uncontrolled areas adjoining. This suggests that it is necessary to consider London as one unit for purposes of rent restriction, at least so far as Class C houses are con-cerned. There are other parts of England and Wales where the same sort of considerations arise, though perhaps to a lesser extent, and where accordingly it might create difficulties if the unit of area adopted for rent control purposes were the area of the housing authority. For this reason, although in normal cases the area of the housing authority should, in our view, be the unit of area for control purposes, it would be necessary to provide machinery whereby the unit, in appropriate cases, might be an aggregation of housing areas. Where the local community of interest was sufficiently widespread such a unit might reasonably embrace the whole of a county or an even larger area.63. The second observation is that the new legislation against overcrowding has introduced a fundamental change in the hous-ing policy of the country. Housing of the working classes is now quite definitely a public health service. In future it is not to be sufficient that a man has a roof over his head. He must have a certain statutory minimum of accommodation in which he and his family can five in reasonable health and comfort. The corollary to this statutory requirement is, of course, that such accommodation must be available for all families at rents within their means. The duty to see that this is the case is laid on the housing authorities of the three countries. Each will have to see that in their area there is a sufficient pool of low-rented houses of the right types and sizes to meet the needs of their population.   Their own houses form part
of this pool, but in most areas the greater part of the pool consists at the moment of the controlled Class C and lower-rented Class B houses. It appears essential, therefore, that complete decontrol should not take effect in any area unless it is clear that the supply of working-class houses is so ample that no general increase in rents will result.64. The third observation relates to the method by which control can be varied.   At the moment there are two forms of control, that over Class B houses where control ceases on the landlord obtaining vacant possession, and that over Class C houses where control of the house  persists not-withstanding changes in the tenancy.     Extended decontrol could be effected by providing for decontrol on vacant posses-sion in the case of some or all of the Class C houses as and when the housing situation in a particular area improved. There are certain advantages in this method of which the chief is that existing protected tenants are not affected.   The method has the disadvantage, however, that sporadic decontrol is likely to mean attempts to increase rents in the case of individual houses which would not be possible if a substantial number of houses of the same type were simultaneously decontrolled.   It is suggested, therefore, that, on balance, it would be better to provide for the various stages of decontrol in any area by gradually reducing the upper rateable value limits of the houses to remain controlled.   This method would constitute the natural reversal of the process whereby control was originally imposed, the upper limit of rateable value of houses to which, control applied having been raised in stages by successive Acts of Parlia-ment.   The method would have the particular advantage that the cheapest houses of all would remain controlled for the longest time.65. For the purpose of formulating a scheme we have felt justified in assuming that the amount of overcrowding in any area may be taken as a general indication of the amount of the housing shortage in that area. We fully realise that over-crowding as defined by the Housing Acts is not necessarily an exact or comprehensive measure of housing shortage, but it is, in our view, the best available and is, moreover, one which is automatically kept up to date. Every year in every area the Medical Officer of Health has to report to the Minister of Health the position of overcrowding in his district, giving details of the number of families still overcrowded, the number of cases abated, etc. We have accordingly adopted the percentage of overcrowding as the basis of our scheme as being the only con-venient measure by which the shortage can be numerically assessed. By the expression &quot; the percentage of overcrowding &quot; we do not necessarily mean the percentage as returned by
the local authority .for the purposes of the overcrowding survey, as we are aware from what is stated in the report of that survey that the percentage was not calculated on a strictly uniform basis in all areas. We contemplate that it will be necessary for the Minister of Health at his first survey of the country for the purpose of aggregating areas for control purposes under our scheme, to take steps to obtain a reasonably accurate percentage of the overcrowding in working-class houses taken on a uniform basis. Further, while satisfied that such a percentage of overcrowding would normally be a reliable guide to the relative shortage of working-class houses in any area, we can conceive that special circum-stances might exist in a particular area which would not be adequately reflected in this percentage. It is for this reason that in our scheme we recommend that the Minister should take any such special circumstances into account in dealing with the future of control in any particular area. It is generally conceded that the present overcrowding standard is a bare minimum and that a new and more satisfactory statutory standard will be imposed as soon as conditions permit. It is chiefly in order to give time for this contemplated new standard to be introduced that we have suggested in paragraph 72 delay-ing until 1942 the investigation by the Minister which will fix the time-table for the dates for decontrol in the various areas in the country.66. Any such raising of the overcrowding standard would affect the percentages of overcrowding calculated on the old standard, but the new percentages could be used in the same way as the old for differentiating between the housing conditions in different areas. For example, in the scheme we outline later we have selected a figure of 4 per cent, as denoting the degree of shortage which must not be exceeded if any further reduc-tion in the rateable value limit of the controlled class is to be made in 1940. This figure is, in fact, the unit just above the average percentage of overcrowding in England and Wales. The amount of housing shortage in any area in which this per-centage is exceeded is greater than the average. It is con-ceivable that, if the standard of overcrowding were raised, the average percentage of overcrowding in Great Britain would also rise notwithstanding the rate at which overcrowding is being reduced. In such a case the new average would no doubt be substituted for the figure of 4 per cent, appearing in our scheme, and the percentages shown in our time-table be modi-fied on the same scale, without, however, extending the period recommended for the termination of control, unless indeed the new standard was so far above the old standard that a large number of houses would have to be regarded as obsolete as not affording sufficient accommodation for an average family.
Recommendations as to the Future of Control affecting Great Britain.67. In the light of the foregoing observations and founded upon the conclusions which we have drawn from the facts and figures laid before us, we submit the following recommenda-tions which fall naturally into two parts, the first part being applicable to Great Britain as a whole and the second part being applicable only to England and Wales. The housing condi-tions in Scotland are so different that special considerations arise in regard to that country and are discussed in paragraph 80 of this Report.68. As to the first part, we recommend that, subject to the reservation in paragraph 70, houses in Class B with a yearly value or rateable value exceeding  35 (in 1931) in Scotland and in the Metropolitan Police District, and  20 (in 1931) elsewhere should be decontrolled at the expiration of the present Acts, subject to the same conditions as to the continuance for a further six months of the restriction on the right to call in mort-gages, and as to notice to the tenant, etc., as were applicable when Class A houses were decontrolled, and that the remaining controlled houses should continue to.be controlled whether or not the landlord obtains vacant possession in other words, all houses remaining controlled should form one class subject to the same conditions as the present Class C.69. The effect of this recommendation would be to split the number of controlled houses in Class B into two categories. The number of Class B houses in Great Britain at present controlled is 1,100,000. Though no exact estimate can be given of the number of these houses with a yearly value or rateable value between  35 and  45 in Scotland and in the Metropolitan Police District, and between  20 and  35 elsewhere, it can hardly exceed 450,000, and this recommendation therefore involves the proposition that about 450,000 of the larger type should be decontrolled and added to the 2,140,000 uncontrolled houses already in Class B, while the remaining 650,000 are added to Class C.70. We are, however, impressed by the fact that many of the houses with a yearly value or rateable value between  35 and  45 in Scotland and in the Metropolitan Police District and between  20 and  35 elsewhere are occupied by two or more families, and, if the parts were separately assessed, would each constitute two or more Class C houses. This is especially so in London and one or two other large towns. We do not consider that immediate decontrol should apply to such houses, but that the present law providing for decontrol on vacant posses-sion should apply for a further period. We therefore recommend that where such a house is at the date of our Report occupied
30 Iby more than one family so that, within the meaning of the Rent Restrictions Acts, it contains two or more dwelling-houses, then the existing law should continue to apply to that house, but in England and Wales would cease to apply when the Orders of the Minister which we suggest in paragraph 72 have reduced the rateable value limit of control to  20 in the Metropolitan Police District and  15 in the Provinces. When those limits are reached houses with a rateable value as a whole ^between  35&quot; 45 m the Metropolitan Police District and between  20 and ^35 elsewhere occupied by more than one family should be finally decontrolled.Scheme for gradual reduction of control in England and Wales.71. As to the second part of our recommendations which contains the scheme applicable only to England and Wales, we recommend that in 1940 the Minister of Health should consider the general housing situation from the point of view of the natural aggregation of districts based on the degree of shortage, and issue Orders which should set out the districts to be aggre-gated for the purpose of forming one control area, and provide(i) that, if the Minister is satisfied that the percentage of overcrowding in any such control area exceeds 4 per cent., the rateable value limits of controlled houses shall remain unchanged in that area; and(ii) that, if the Minister is satisfied that the percentage of overcrowding in an area is not more than 4 per cent, and is also satisfied that no special considerations arise which render it desirable to retain the limits unchanged, the rate-able value limits for control in that area shall be reduced by  5 as from the earliest practicable date to be fixed by the Order.72. In 1942 the Minister should again consider the housing situation in each area and by Orders provide for the gradual cessation of all control by specified reductions in the rateable value limit of controlled houses to take effect on specified dates in each individual area. In normal cases the rateable value limit would be reduced from  20 to  15,  10 and  5 until all houses were decontrolled. It might happen, however, that ,jn some particular area special considerations exist which make it desirable in the opinion of the Minister to adopt some special basis for the Order either for the area as a whole or for some particular housing authority within a control area. Subject to this point, however, we think that the Orders might proceed on the basis that where there exists in any area in 1942 a per-centage of overcrowding as now calculated, as defined in the first column of the following table, the maximum period for
A31bringing control to an end would be as shown in the second column of the following table:  Maximum Period. 8 years.4 3 2Percentage. Over 4Between 3 and 4 Between 2 and 3 Between 1 and 2 Under 1Should the standard of overcrowding be raised, with a conse-quential rise in the average percentage of overcrowding, the percentages shown in the table could be modified on a corresponding scale as indicated in paragraph 66 above without extending the periods recommended for the termination of control except perhaps at the discretion of the Minister in any particular area.73. It seems to us necessary that if the scheme we recom-mend, or one like it, is adopted, the Statute should itself provide a table of the sort indicated in the preceding paragraph for the guidance of the Minister and local authorities, in order to ensure that, subject to a reasonable elasticity to take account of any exceptional conditions, the date of decontrol should depend solely on the overcrowding percentage used as an index of shortage. The fixing of this date ought not to become a question of local politics.74. Any alteration of limits should be accompanied by safe-guards as to the calling in of mortgages and as to notice to sitting tenants of houses about to be decontrolled on the lines of those adopted when Class A houses were decontrolled.75. The rateable value of a house for the purpose of any Order made by the Minister under this scheme should be the rateable value at the date of the Order.76. All Orders made by the Minister should he on the Table of the House so that Parliamentary supervision of the opera-tion of decontrol might be maintained.Advantages of scheme.77. Among other advantages which we claim for our scheme are, firstly, that all existing controlled Class C houses would remain controlled until after 1942 and the smallest houses would remain protected for the longest time. Secondly, by delaying until 1942 the inquiries which would fix the decontrol stages for the individual areas, time would be afforded to make use of overcrowding percentages based on any revised statutory standard of overcrowding which might be introduced by that date. Thirdly, the scheme should operate to remove or reduce uncertainty as to the future of the Acts.
78. In the past the Acts have been periodically extended for a limited period by the Expiring Laws Continuance Acts without reference to the date by which it might ultimately be found possible to terminate them, and their workings have from time to time been investigated by a Departmental Committee. The public has naturally had no prior indication of the probable outcome of these inquiries, of which there have been no less than five, including our own, in the last 18 years, and the resulting state of uncertainty on a matter which might involve severe hardship for large sections of the community has had an unsettling effect on the minds of landlords and tenants alike which has in no way contributed to the promotion of harmonious relations between them. This uncertainty as to the future of control has also by its effect on values greatly increased the difficulties of owners wishing to dispose of, or to improve, their property.79. If our scheme were adopted the possible future varia-tions of control .and the probable date of termination in each area would be generally known for an appreciable period in advance of any change, and there would be the additional safe-guard against hardship that control would only be removed gradually while the housing shortage was being overcome and the exaction of scarcity rents would not be possible. The direct linking of the continuance of control with the housing position in each area would not only allay any fear of arbitrary action without reference to possible hardship to tenants but might also help to stimulate the erection of houses by private enter-prise in areas with a high degree of overcrowding.PART VII.SCOTLAND.Future of Control in Scotland.80. The housing shortage in Scotland is much more acute than the shortage in England and Wales. The Report of the Scottish Overcrowding Survey which covered all houses with a rateable value not exceeding  45 per annum showed that, out of 1,146,534 houses surveyed, 22-6 per cent, (or over a quarter of a million) were overcrowded. This is about six times the rate of overcrowding in England and Wales. Overcrowding exists in Scotland throughout the whole country. In none of the cities and large burghs, in only a minority of the small burghs, and in only half of the counties (including none of the industrial counties) is the proportion of overcrowded houses less than 10 per cent, of the total number of houses surveyed. The existence of a continued scarcity of houses, except in the upper ranges of Class B, was admitted by all Scottish witnesses who appeared before us.   The Department of Health for Scotland
estimate that the number of houses required to end over-crowding in Scotland is not less than 200,000. At the pre-sent rate of building it will be many years before the percentage of overcrowding in most Scottish districts is reduced to anything comparable to the percentages now obtaining in England and Wales. We do not think it advisable to recommend the exten-sion to Scotland of a scheme for the eventual reduction and termination of control which could not begin to operate for so long a period, and for this reason we have excluded Scotland from the scheme recommended for England and Wales in para-graphs 71-76 above. We believe that the principle underlying this scheme might ultimately be applied to Scotland, but the date by which any further reduction of control would be possible lies so far in the future that further inquiry may be found desir-able before this is done. It was agreed by the majority of those who supplied us with evidence, however, that the shortage relates particularly to the smaller type of house and does not extend to the upper range of Class B, i.e. houses with a yearly value in the valuation roll exceeding  35, and for this reason we have already recommended in paragraph 68 above that these houses should now be decontrolled subject to certain safeguards and reservations; while, as recommended for England and Wrales, all houses with a yearly value not exceeding  35 remaining in con-trol should continue to be controlled whether or not the landlord obtains vacant possession, i.e. all controlled houses would form one class and be subject to the same conditions as the present Class C.Owners&apos; Rates in Scotland.81. A point which has been much stressed by all bodies giving evidence on behalf of Scottish property owners is the hardship imposed on owners of controlled property in Scotland by in-creases in owners&apos; rates since Whitsunday, 1920, which cannot under the Rent Restrictions Acts be passed on to the occupiers. It must be borne in mind, however, that, whereas in England rates have always been a personal charge on the occupier, in Scotland owners&apos; rates, as distinct from occupiers&apos; rates, are a charge on the owner of the land. It does not appear to us possible to remedy the position without alterations affecting the basis of the law of Scotland relating to rating and valuation. This is a subject going far beyond the scope of our enquiry and we accordingly do not make any recommendation; but as the acceptance of our general recommendations would leave control in Scotland to continue for a number of years we think it right to put on record the facts as they have been presented to us.82. The Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1920, allowed a 40 per cent, increase in the net rent (i.e. the rent at the 3rd August, 1914, less occupiers&apos; rates where paid by
the landlord). It also allowed the Scottish owner (Section 2 (i) (b) as read with Section 18 (i) (&amp;)) to increase the rent by the amount of any increase in owners&apos; rates between the 3rd August, 1914, and Whitsunday, 1920, but prevented him from increasing the rent on account of any increase in owners&apos; rates after Whitsunday, 1920. If in August, 1914, a house were rented in England for  35 per annum the permitted increase of 40 per cent, would enable the rent to be raised to  49 per annum. In Scotland a house involving the same capital outlay would be rented (if owners&apos; rates in the district concerned amounted in August, 1914, to 2s. 6d. in the  ) for  40, and an increase up to  56 would be allowed.83. This apparent benefit to the Scottish owner would imme-diately be off-set by the fact that under Scottish valuation law the yearly value of the property in the valuation roll would become  56, and the Scottish owner if the owners&apos; rates re-remained at 2s. 6&quot;d. in the   would be paying  j in rates, reduc-ing his net return to  49, the same as that of the English owner. There was a substantial increase in owners&apos; rates in Scotland after August, 1914, and this was recognized by the provision in the Act of 1920 referred to above. The effect of this provision was to permit a further increase in the rent (and consequently in the yearly value) of the property; and assuming that the owners&apos; rates had risen to 4s. in the   in the year ended Whitsunday, 1920, the permitted rent would be increased by , 3 (is. 6d. x 40) to  59 (and the yearly value would be correspondingly in-creased) . In the following year (the first year the Act of 1920 was in operation), even if there was no increase in the poundage of the owners&apos; rates, the Scottish owners&apos; net return would be  $g less (owners&apos; rates of 59 x 4s. =  u 16s. od.) =  47 4s. od. as compared with the English owners&apos;  49. This deficiency would increase in any year in which the owners&apos; rates exceeded 4s. in the  .84. In many districts owners&apos; rates have increased since Whitsunday, 1920. The average owners&apos; rates in Scotland may be estimated at 2s. 2d. in 1913-4: 3s. 5d. in 1919-20: and 4s. 7d. in 1936-7. Any increase in owners&apos; rates since Whitsunday, 1920, has fallen upon the owners of controlled property, and has further reduced their net return as compared with that of English owners of controlled property. In the current year, however, there is a tendency towards a reduction in owners&apos; rates in many districts. Under the revised arrangements relat-ing to Scottish Block Grants which were recently passed into law, additional Exchequer reliefs are being given to local autho-rities in Scotland, as from the 15th May last, amounting to nearly  x% million per annum; and this substantial measure of additional relief should materially alleviate the burden of rates on both owners and occupiers.
85. It has been represented to the Committee that, owing to increases in owners&apos; rates since 1920, many owners of controlled houses in Scotland are now getting such a small return from their property that they cannot afford to maintain it properly. There may be cases where this is true, but there is no evidence that it applies to any considerable proportion of Scottish owners of controlled property. It must be kept in view that the cost of repair work to-day (even allowing for an appreciable increase in recent months) is substantially less than in 1920 (when an item of 25 per cent, was included in the total permitted rent increase of 40 per cent, in order to meet the increased cost of repairs). It is, however, clear that in many cases the Scottish owner of controlled property, owing to the incidence of owners&apos; rates, gets a smaller net return than the English property owner, and is to this extent not so well able to meet maintenance costs. Any future increases in owners&apos; rates would further reduce the net return of Scottish owners.86. It has been suggested to the Committee that Scottish owners of controlled property should now be allowed to increase rents by the amount of any increase in owners&apos; rates since Whit-sunday, 1920. This would permit considerable increases of rent in many areas (in Glasgow the increase, in the case of a house with a pre-War rent of  25 per annum or 9s. y-^d. per week-would be about 2s. 7d. per week on an existing rent of 14s. 3d. per week or nearly 20 per cent.): and these increases would be permitted at a time when there is a very great scarcity of working-class houses. A proposal was made that Scottish owners of controlled property should be allowed to increase rents by the amount of any increase in owners&apos; rates since Whit-sunday, 1920, but that the yearly value in the valuation roll of the houses in respect of which rents are so increased -should be stabilised at the 1937-8 level. This would permit the increases of rent referred to above, and is also open to the objection that it would exempt owners of controlled houses from increases in the yearly value which they would otherwise incur under the operation of the general valuation law so that in effect it would subsidise owners of controlled property at the expense of owners of other property within the area. An alternative course would be to allow every Scottish owner of controlled property a further permitted increase in his rent (of, say, 10 per cent.), this increase not being specifically related to owners&apos; rates but being granted as a general concession to compensate owners in some measure for increases in owners&apos; rates which they have suffered since 1920 and which they may expect to suffer in the future. This course also is open to the objection that it would mean permitting increases of rent at a time when there is a great scarcity of working-class houses; and it would enable rents to be increased all over Scotland, whereas in certain areas (for example, the cities of Dundee and Aberdeen) there has been
200,000 50,000 250,000no increase in owners&apos; rates since Whitsunday, 1920, and accordingly there is no justification for any increase in the rents of controlled houses.87. In the light of the present scarcity of working-class houses in Scotland we would not feel justified in recommending any course which would permit substantial increases in controlled rents and as already indicated we do not make any recom-mendation on this matter.PART VIII.THE AGRICULTURAL POPULATION.88. It has been represented to us that any further measure of decontrol of Class C houses would add to the existing shortage of accommodation for agricultural workers, a shortage which is believed by the Ministry of Agriculture to be already endanger-ing the maintenance of the supply of agricultural labour. It was stated in evidence that agricultural workers being, in general, unable to afford the rents paid by other sections of the community, the decontrol of Class C houses at present occupied by them would result in their being dispossessed in order that their cottages might be let to industrial workers or &apos;&apos; week-enders &quot; at enhanced rents.89. To gain some idea of the extent of this problem we have sought to discover how the agricultural population are housed at present. The agricultural returns of England and Wales, 1936, published by the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, show that the number of male workers over 21 years of age on hold-ings above an acre in extent, on the 4th June, 1936, was 480,900. This figure does not include pensioners or old people who are no longer employed, or workers who were unemployed on that date. Among the number of male workers over 21, there are many who are unmarried or are living with their parents or as lodgers. This&apos; number would be offset by the number of old people and unemployed workers; and the figure might perhaps be taken as representing approximately the number of potential families. It might therefore be estimated that the agricultural population does not exceed 500,000 families, and on the basis of the estimates given in the report of the Departmental Com-mittee on Tied Cottages of 1931, after making some allowance for the changes which have taken place in the housing situation since that date it would appear that it is reasonable to assume that these 500,000 families are housed approximately as follows:  ;Housed in tied cottages Housed in Council houses ... Housed in ordinary private houses
go. The 200,000 tied cottages and the 50,000 Council houses do not come within the scope of the Rent Restrictions Acts and the problem we have to consider is restricted to such number of the 250,000 private houses as are at present con-trolled. Agricultural workers tend to move from place to place with much greater frequency than urban workers, and it may therefore be assumed that a relatively high proportion of these houses became decontrolled during the operation of the pro-visions for decontrol on vacant possession in the period 1923-33. On this assumption the number of these houses remaining in control may perhaps be put at round about 150,000. In Scot-land it is practically universal for farm workers to be housed in tied cottages to which the Acts do not apply.91. It seems to us that it would not be possible to justify the maintenance of an elaborate system of control solely in respect of so comparatively small a number of houses and that the proper solution to the problem would be found in increasing the number of new houses to be reserved for the use of the agricultural population. The report by the Central Housing Advisory Committee which has recently been published deals with this aspect of the question and recommends that a special Exchequer subsidy should be granted for the erection of houses for the general needs of the agricultural population. The Minister of Health announced in the House of Commons on the 28th October last that he had decided to adopt this recom-mendation and would shortly introduce legislation to carry it into effect. Under the scheme for gradual decontrol which we recommend, cottages occupied by agricultural workers, being of very low rateable value, will be among the last to be decon-trolled, and we do not feel justified in recommending the con-tinuance of control for agricultural cottages after it has been terminated in any particular area for working-class houses generally.PART IX.MINOR AMENDMENTS. 92. In considering the many suggestions made to us for the amendment of the Acts on minor points we have been influenced by the facts that the Acts have now been in operation sub-stantially in their present form for over 20 years and that if our principal necommendation is adopted the day when control will terminate over large areas of the country is now in sight. We have accordingly proceeded on the assumption that at this late stage in their history the present general scheme of the Acts to which everyone has become accustomed should be altered as little as possible, and for this reason we have not adopted various suggestions for amendment which at an earlier stage might have been considered desirable. Our recommendations are limited to points on which amendment is specially urgent or can be made without appreciable alteration of the general scheme.
Onus of Proof of Decontrol.93. In 1936 it was held in the case of Heginbottom v. Watts [1936] 2 K.B. 6 that in case of dispute whether a house claimed by the landlord to be decontrolled is actually decon-trolled the burden of proof that the house is controlled lies on the tenant. This decision reversed the practice which had been generally followed in the administration of the Acts for the previous 16 years and we have had evidence from a large number of responsible and experienced persons that it is operat-ing harshly on tenants involved in these disputes. In general the landlord has far greater opportunities and facilities than the tenant for proving a point such as this, and we consider that the burden of proof in such cases should be placed on the shoulders best able to bear it. We recommend that the necessary statutory amendment be made to transfer the onus of proof to the landlord.Rent Books. -94. It has been strongly represented to us by Tenants&apos; Asso-ciations, and other witnesses with experience of the tenanfs point of view, that tenants are sometimes prevented from making use of their legal remedies against a landlord who has been guilty of an offence under the Acts because they are unable to ascertain his full name and address. Section 4 of the Housing Act, 1936, provides that in the case of any house which is occupied, or is of a type suitable for occupation, by persons of the working classes, the name and address of the landlord, or other person who is directly responsible for keeping the house in all respects reasonably fit for human habitation, shall be inscribed in the rent book, and, where there has been any failure to comply with the provisions of this Section in respect of any house, any person who while the default continues demands or collects any rent in respect of the house shall on summary con-viction be liable to a fine not exceeding 40s. Similarly the regulations made by the Minister of Health and the Secretary of State for Scotland under Section 14 of the Rent Act of 1933 provide for the name and address of the landlord, as well as the name and address of the agent to be inscribed in any rent book used in relation to a controlled dwelling. It was represented that the landlords name and address is frequentlyinserted in some such form as &quot; J. Smith, c/o Messrs.............,of.................................&quot; (Agents).   This form of name and address was insufficient to enable a summons to be served, and the tenant had no means of ascertaining the full name of the landlord. It was accordingly suggested that there should be a definite statutory requirement that the full name and address of the landlord be inserted in rent books. With this suggestion we agree, and we recommend accordingly. We further recom-mend that the full name and address of any agent employed by the landlord should also be required to be inserted in addition to the name and address of the landlord, and that, by leave of the
) 39Court, service of any notice required to be served by the tenant on the landlord shall be deemed to be good service if served at the address of the agent whose name appears in the rent book for the time being.95. It was also pointed out that there is no legal obligation on a landlord to provide a rent book. It appears to us that, in the absence of a rent book, the statutory provisions in the Housing Acts and Rent Restrictions Acts which require the insertion of various notices in a rent book or similar document are to a large extent rendered ineffective, and we suggest that at a convenient opportunity it might well be made a statutory requirement that a rent book should be provided for all working-class houses which are not in service occupation. Sanitary Certificates.96. Many witnesses referred to the difficulties which have arisen, particularly in Glasgow, in issuing sanitary certificates in respect of houses included in the local authority&apos;s programme of slum clearance as being unfit for human habitation, owing to the requirement of Section 18 (1) of the Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions Act, 1923, that the certificate shall specify what works (if any) require to be executed in order to put the dwelling-house into a reasonable state of repair. It was pointed out to us that it was quite impossible to put most of these houses, which were already scheduled for demolition, into a reasonable state of repair, and therefore equally impossible to specify the works required for this purpose. In consequence of this position the local authorities were no longer willing to issue sanitary certificates in respect of such houses and tenants were being deprived of the benefit to which they were entitled under the Acts by being compelled to pay the full rent for houses which were not reasonably fit for habitation. We recommend that Section 18 (1) of the Act of 1923 be amended to omit this requirement to specify works, and that the other consequential amendments thereon be made. In the case of England and Wales this would leave it to the owner, if he wished, to submit to the local authority a list of any works he is prepared to carry out under Section 51 (1) of the Housing Act, 1936. An owner submitting a list of works under this Section is entitled to be informed whether the local authority consider that the house would, after the execution of the works, or of any additional works suggested by them, be in all respects fit for habitation and remain so fit for at least five years. If the local authority grant a certificate to this effect no action to secure the demolition of the house as unfit for habitation can be taken during the period specified in the certificate. There is at present no provision in the Housing (Scotland) Acts corresponding to Section 51 (1) of the Housing Act, 1936, and, if effect is given to our recom-mendation on this point, we think that some similar provision should be enacted for Scotland.
97. Since 1924 an owner wishing to obtain possession of his house for his own occupation, or for his son or daughter over 18 years of age, has been able to obtain possession, without show-ing that alternative accommodation is available for the tenant, unless the Court is satisfied that greater hardship would be caused by granting an order for possession than by refusing it. This privilege has, however, not been open to anyone who became an owner by purchase after a given date, the date inserted in the Act of 1933 being the nth July, 1931, i.e. the date of the Marley Committee&apos;s Report. Since that date a further number of persons have acquired houses for their own occupa-tion in the hope that they might be able to obtain possession at any rate by 1938 when the Acts as they at present stand would expire. We think that the benefit of obtaining possession with-out offering alternative accommodation, except where the Court is satisfied that greater hardship would be caused by granting an order for possession than by refusing to grant it, should be extended on similar terms to owners who acquired their property after July, 1931, and we accordingly recommend that the date of this Report should be substituted for the nth July, 1931.Registration.98. We received a great deal of evidence designed to show that the system of registering Class C houses which had become de-controlled prior to July, 1933, had in practice proved ineffective. It was represented to us that a certain number of houses had been registered as decontrolled although they were in fact con-trolled, and that on the other hand houses which were decon-trolled had not been registered as such. We think that so far as Class C houses are concerned no useful purpose would be served by keeping the registers, which have been in existence since 1933, open for an indefinite period, and we accordingly recom-mend that no further registration of the present Class C houses should be permitted after the expiration of three months from the passing of any amending Act.99. The decontrolled Class B houses in the lower range of rateable values, which will become merged with Class C if our recommendation is adopted, are relatively not very numerous, and we think that the best course is to put them on a similar footing as regards registration to the decontrolled Class C houses. We recommend, therefore,-that they should be required to be registered within three months of the passing of any amend-ing Act, and that thereafter registration should in special cases be allowed with the leave of the Courts during a further nine months but no longer.Possession for own occupation.
Compounding Allowances.ioo. In the case of Strood Estates Company, Limited v. Gregory [1937] 3 All E.R. 656 it was held by the House of Lords in 1936 that the expression in the Act of 1920 &quot; rates chargeable &quot; and &quot; the amount of such rates &quot; refer to the full amount of the rate as assessed, and that where rates are compounded the &quot; net rent &quot; means the standard rent less, not the compounded rate, but the full amount of the rate.1O1. This decision seems in a certain sense to contrast with the earlier decision in Nicholson v. Jackson [1921] 90 L.J. (K.B.) 1121 in which it was held that under Section 2 (&amp;) of the Act of 1920 there can be added to the standard rent only the increase in the rates actually payable after deducting the commission payable to the landlord under the provisions as to compounding. The Marley Committee considered that, in equity, the law as settled by the decision in Nicholson v. Jackson should be altered &quot; so that, whatever the compounding allow-ance might be at any particular moment, it should enure to the benefit of the landlord &quot;. They refrained from making any recommendation to this effect, however, because it would have involved slight adjustments of the rents of about five million houses, and they were not making any other recommendations which involved the recalculation of the permitted increases in rent.102. We are in agreement with the views of the Marley Com-mittee on the equity of altering the law as established by Nicholson v. Jackson; and we also think that if the contrasting principles established by these two decisions are both allowed to stand unaltered throughout the period during which, if our recommendations are adopted, control will continue, they will be a constant source of embarrassment to all concerned with the application of the Acts. We regret to recommend any altera-tion of the law which will involve a general recalculation of rents of houses within the compounding limits but we consider it the lesser of two evils, and we accordingly recommend that the necessary statutory amendment should be made to give the land-lord the benefit of the compounding allowance and thereby obviate the effect of the decision reached in the case of Nicholson v. Jackson.Recovery of Over-Payments of Rent.103. We have been impressed by the evidence given before us that the present limitation on the recovery of over-payments of rent to a period of not more than six months is, in some cases, operating harshly on tenants. The present position is that under Section 8 (2) of the Act of 1923 any sum paid by a tenant which, under Section 14 (i) of the principal Act, is recoverable by the tenant, is recoverable at any time within six months from the date of payment but not afterwards or if made before 31st July,
42 01923, at any time within six months from that date but not after-wards. It has been suggested to us that certain unscrupulous-landlords take advantage of the present law and charge illegal rents in the hope of gaining by this means a sum greater than any they can be called upon to repay. We are aware that the present limitation of recovery of over-payments to a six months period was introduced following the investigations of the Onslow Committee who had had before them evidence of the hardship which, if there is no limit to the period allowed for recovery, may be caused to landlords who have innocently calculated the permitted increase of rent on a basis which may afterwards be shown by a decision by the Courts to be wrong. We think that the situation which preceded the Onslow investigation is un-likely to occur again, but at the same time we are unwilling to suggest any alteration of the law which might possibly operate harshly, more particularly as the landlord is not in a position to recover under-payments of rent from the tenant. While, therefore, we are not prepared to recommend that the&apos; law should revert to the position prior to the Act of 1923, we con-sider that the time limit for recovery of over-payments of rent should be extended to twelve months from the date of payment, and we recommend accordingly.Procedure for increasing rents after improvements.104. The present procedure under Section 7 (2) of the Act of 1933 is said to lead to absurd results, e.g. if works of improve-ment are carried out while the property is vacant the landlord cannot forthwith increase the rent but must proceed by stages, first letting the premises at the old rent, and then serving a notice of increase of rent in respect of the improvements, and reletting the premises. This should be amended.105. We also make the following recommendations for minor amendments made necessary by other legislation subsequent to the Rent and Mortgage Restrictions (Amendment) Act, 1933.(a) Alternative Accommodation.The definition of alternative accommodation should be amended to require that the house offered as alternative accommodation must in addition to other existing require-ments be one in which the tenant and his family can live without being overcrowded within the meaning of the Hous-ing Act, 1936, and the Housing (Scotland) Act, 1935.(b) Overcrowding as a ground for possession.In view of the provisions of Section 65 (1) of the Housing Act, 1936, and Section 8 (1) of the Housing (Scotland) Act, 1935, clause (/) of the First Schedule to the Rent and Mort-gage Interest Restrictions (Amendment) Act, 1933, is no longer necessary and should be repealed.
I 43PART X.POINTS ON WHICH NO AMENDMENT OF THE LAW IS RECOMMENDED.106. There are two points which have been carefully con-sidered in the course of our investigation on which we cannot agree to recommend any alteration of the present law and we therefore confine ourselves to setting out the views held by some of our members. We have not considered it necessary to discuss in detail various other questions such as the adequacy or otherwise of the present allowances for repairs and improve-ments which were fully discussed in the Marley Report and concerning which no substantial alteration has taken place since that date.Mortgages.107. Several of the bodies and persons who have supplied us with evidence, including the Public Trustee, the Law Society and the Joint Committee of Legal Societies in Scotland, have drawn attention to the difficulties which are arising owing to the continuance of the restrictions imposed by the Acts on the right to call in mortgages on controlled property. It was represented that these restrictions are a source of special embarrassment to trustees, who are thereby prevented from winding up their trusts and distributing estates to the beneficiaries. In such cases, not only can the mortgages not be realized, but other funds which ought to be distributed have to be retained to provide for possible expenses in connection with the mortgaged property. It was also represented that the restrictions pressed unduly hardly on the mortgagee whose mortgage is secured by old property now rapidly diminishing in value. These restric-tions have now been in operation since 1915 and a great deal of property which at that date would have been generally accepted as good security has now deteriorated to a very con-siderable extent. The period of the existence of the mortgage may exceed the life of the building. The mortgagee is, how-ever, precluded from calling in the mortgage or requiring it to be reduced in amount except in the case of a mortgage of a leasehold interest, when he may apply to the Court for an order authorising the calling in of the mortgage under Sec-tion 7 (ii) of the Act of 1920.108. In the view of some of our members the principle under-lying the exception made in this Section in the case of the mort-gage of a leasehold interest appears to be that any loss due to the permanent diminution in the value of the security should be borne by the mortgagor, who has entered into a covenant to pay, rather than by the mortgagee.  They think that the reason
44 Iwhy this provision was not originally extended to cover mort-gages of freeholds was that at that time it was contemplated that control would continue for a comparatively short period only, and that on its removal the value of freehold property would rise to a level more than sufficient to cover any temporary diminution 1 due to deterioration in the meantime. This view was no doubt fully justified so long as control was regarded simply as an emergency measure which might be. terminated at any time. The principle laid down by the Marley Committee on which this Committee&apos;s principal recommenda-tion is based is, however, that control of rent must be continued so long as there is a shortage of houses which might result in in the exaction of scarcity rents if control were removed. If this Committee&apos;s general recommendation as to the future of control is adopted, control will continue until there is no longer any possibility of a general rise in rents on its termination, and it follows that mortgaged property which is now diminishing in value is in general unlikely to regain its original value when control comes to an end. Some of us feel that in these circum-stances the principle that loss due to permanent diminution in the value of the security should be borne by the mortgagor should apply, and that the mortgagor would in fact be in a better position to meet this liability at the present time than he would be on the termination of control, by which date the value of his property might have deteriorated still further.109. On this ground certain of our members feel that the scope of Section 7 (ii) of the Act of 1920 should be extended to cover mortgages of freeholds, provided that the Court should have discretion to refuse or modify an order or to permit re-payment by instalments over a period of years in cases where, having regard to all the circumstances, including the question of greater hardship, it considers it reasonable to do so.no. Those of our number who take this view think that such an amendment would go some way to meet the difficulties experienced by trustees. They would not, however, suggest that there should be any general exemption from the restrictions on the right to call in mortgages in favour of trustees whether or not the security is diminishing in value, as they are satisfied that any such general exemption might well create more hard-ship than it would alleviate.in. Others of our members are, however, firmly convinced of the necessity to maintain the general principle that while the landlord is prohibited from raising his rent or otherwise dis-posing of his property in a free market, the mortgagee should be prohibited from calling in, or raising the rate of interest on, his mortgage. In their view the proviso in Section 7 of the Act of 1920 regarding mortgages on leasehold interests was intended to protect mortgagees from diminution in the value
of their securities arising from a special cause the expiry of leases. That consideration does not, however, arise in relation to freehold property or to its Scottish analogy, property held in feu. The landlord and the mortgagee have hitherto been treated on an equal footing by the imposition of control both on rents and on mortgages; and the proposal that mortgagees should now be given a right to call in mortgages on controlled property, whatever conditions and safeguards may be attached to it, would restore to them a freedom which would by statute remain denied to the other party to the original contract. If such a step were taken there appears to be no logical reason why mortgagors on their part should not be allowed to raise their rents, subject to similar safeguards in the way of applica-tion to the Court, and consideration by the Court of questions of greater hardship, etc. Incidentally, it is apprehended that power to call in mortgages would flood the Courts with applica-tions by mortgagees and that in many such cases the Courts would be faced with very difficult decisions on grounds of greater hardship. For these reasons some of our members adhere to the view expressed by the Marley Committee &quot; that those who borrowed on a free security should not be made liable to be compelled to reborrow on a controlled security for the purpose of repaying the loan; in other words .... that the control on a mortgage should continue as long as the rent of the mortgaged property is controlled.&quot;H2. On this point we are almost equally divided and we accordingly do not make any recommendation.Owner&apos;s Right to Possession.113. It has been stnongly urged by certain of our witnesses that the stringent restriction on the right of the landlord to obtain possession of his property, unless he proves the existence of alternative accommodation, is bearing especially hardly on landlords of the type who most deserve encouragement, namely those who are anxious to improve and reconstruct their pro-perty and introduce modern amenities. It has been represented to us that landlords who may be greatly concerned at the con-dition of their property are compelled to watch it deteriorating further from day to day, even to the extent of becoming unfit for habitation, because the necessary works of improvement cannot be carried out while the tenant is in occupation. We are fully alive to the hardships entailed by this position and have carefully considered whether there is any remedy which we could recommend. The only effective remedy which has been suggested is the extension of the grounds on which an owner may obtain possession of his house without offering alternative accommodation, set out in the First Schedule to the Act of 1933, to include cases where the owner requires possession of his house in order to improve his property.
114. In the main, the present position is that the landlord can only get possession without proof of alternative accommodation in the cases of the tenanfs neglect or default, the principle of the Acts being that by his own conduct the tenant may forfeit his right to protection from eviction.   The extension of the grounds for obtaining possession to cover cases where the owner wished to improve his property would mean that a tenant might be evicted without any alternative accommodation being avail-able for him in cases in which he was not at fault.   This course would, we consider, unless the right of the landlord were made subject to strict examination by a competent authority such as the County Court, or in Scotland the Sheriff Court, or the local authority, lead to great hardship on tenants who had committed no fault to justify such treatment.   It is relevant to point out that under the existing law, even where the landlord has the strongest possible grounds for obtaining possession without proof of alternative accommodation, i.e. where he has bought the house for his own occupation, the Court cannot give possession without weighing hardship likely to be caused respectively to the tenant and to the landlord.   It would consequently appear necessary to provide, in connection with any proposal for ex-tending the grounds for obtaining possession in the manner sug-gested, that, in considering an application for possession on this new ground, the Court or other competent authority should take the question of hardship into account.   If this were done the con-cession would probably prove almost worthless in actual practice from the landlords point of view.   The solution to these difficulties is, in our view, to be found by enlisting the sympathy of the local authority for the landlords proposals, and per-suading them to assist him by undertaking to provide accommo-dation for the tenants displaced. Where this is done no difficulties need arise, because a certificate that the housing authority will provide alternative accommodation is conclusive evidence that alternative accommodation will be available.   The houses which the landlord desired to improve would remain subject to control after the improvement, although it would, of course, be open to him to raise the rent by the permitted increase of 8 per cent, on the cost of the improvements.   The pool of accommodation available for the working classes would therefore not be reduced, while the standard of housing in the district would be raised. We think that, in the circumstances, local authorities, to whom the facts of the case were explained would, in general, be found ready to assist in the carrying out of such proposals by every means in their power although we realize that in some areas with a heavy slum clearance programme there would at present be few council houses which could be made available for this purpose.   This position would, however, improve as the slum clearance programme neared completion.   We suggest that the Ministry of Health and the Department of Health for Scotland
I 47might at a convenient opportunity draw attention by circular to the public benefit which may accrue through co-operation between local authorities and property owners to effect improve-ments in these circumstances.115. Complaints have also been made in a number of the letters which we have received of the hardship experienced by landlords of very limited means who are precluded from raising the rent of a house occupied by a tenant in better financial circumstances who, in some cases, may be making money through lettings or through using the house for carrying on his business. We have great sympathy with the feelings of land-lords who find themselves in such a position but the remedy which they claim would amount, in effect, to depriving persons with an income above a certain level of the benefits of control, a course which would cut right across the principles on which all the successive Acts have been based and which, quite apart from any other aspect of the matter, would entail insuperable difficulties of administration.Rent Restrictions Act Committees of Local Authorities.116. Several of our witnesses, particularly those appearing on behalf of tenants&apos; organisations, have referred to the power conferred on local authorities by Section 10 of the Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions (Amendment) Act, 1933, to publish information to landlords and tenants as to their rights and duties under the Acts, and to delegate these powers to a Committee of the authority, either an existing Committee or a special ad hoc Committee. It appears that comparatively few authorities have made any extended use of this power and it was suggested that this was due to the limitation of their powers&apos;-which, as was pointed out in Circular 1348 issued by the Ministry of Health in July, 1933, and in Circular 2777 issued by the Scottish Office in August, 1933, do not extend to giving advice on legal questions arising between individual landlords and tenants. The extension of these powers to include a power to offer legal advice would, in our opinion, be open to the gravest objections, and we cannot therefore recommend it. We feel, however, that the lack of this power does not in fact prevent Committees of local authorities from carrying out most useful work in the remedying of injustices, and this is borne out by the experience of some of the Committees. It must be remembered that local authorities in England and Wales have power to prosecute in the case of the offences created by the Acts, most of which are closely related to permitted rent increases. In considering whether a particular case is one which calls for the exercise of these powers the Committee must necessarily inquire closely into the facts of that case, and it is as a result of inquiries of this sort that it has been possible to arrange for rent adjust-ments and recovery of over-payments. We are, in fact, satisfied
48 1that if a local authority is prepared, in suitable cases, to exercise its powers of prosecution for offences, it will find that it has ample powers in the Acts as they stand for the remedying of abuses. In our opinion there are not enough authorities willing to exercise their powers, and we think that, in any future circular issued from the Ministry of Health and the Scottish Office to local authorities on the subject of the Rent Restrictions Acts, the importance of exercising these powers should be stressed.PART XI.CONSOLIDATION OF RENT RESTRICTIONS ACTS.117. Like our predecessors, the Marley Committee, we have received numerous representations in favour of the consolidation of the various Rent Restrictions Acts now in operation from witnesses representative of all those who have to deal with the Acts in the course of their daily work. The principal argument in favour of consolidation appears to us to lie in the fact that the Acts affect a very large number of people in a matter which is often of supreme importance to them. It is frequently essential for these people, who are almost exclusively members of the working classes, to obtain advice as to their position, but in the present confused state of the statutes it is often very difficult for them to obtain exact information on this point except at a price which they are not in a position to afford.118. If our general recommendation as to the future of control is adopted, control may continue in respect of the smallest and cheapest houses for a period of seven years in most parts of the country, and for a still longer period in the areas where there is a high degree of overcrowding. During this time, however, there should, if the housing position develops as we anticipate, be no occasion for any further amendment of the law&apos;. The present time is therefore particularly opportune for the consolida-tion of the Acts. We know that the recommendation of the Marley Committee in favour of consolidation was not adopted by the Government of the day. We are, however, so impressed by the unhappy results of the present confusion that we cannot contemplate with equanimity the continuance of this state of affairs throughout the years during which, if our major recom-mendation is adopted, control will persist, and we urge that further consideration should be given to the possibility of con-solidation, and further that in any consolidating statute the word-ing of the present Acts should be retained as far as possible. Legal decisions on the interpretation of the existing provisions would thus remain undisturbed.
i 49PART XII.MISCELLANEOUS.Distress.119. Distress for the rent of a controlled house can only be levied with leave of the Court. It is clear from the evidence given before us that the loss of this protection is one of the chief fears associated in the minds of many tenants with decontrol, and it was urged that the protection ought to be extended to houses which have already become decontrolled. It was repre-sented to us that it is a practice among certain owners of un-controlled working-class property to employ as their agents persons who are also registered bailiffs. It was stated that should the tenant fall behind with his rent, even in some cases to the extent of one week only, from whatever cause, the bailiff would enter the house, sometimes by means of a master key, and place a &quot; blue paper &quot; on the table which rendered the tenant liable for a levy fee and bailiffs expenses at the rate of 6s. a day, notwithstanding that no one had been placed in possession and accordingly any expenses would necessarily be very small. If arrears of rent together with these charges are not paid by the tenant within five days, his goods and furniture may be taken away and sold. Cases have been brought to our notice where, owing to the charge for expenses, the tenant has still been in debt, after the sale of his furniture, for as large a sum as was pre-viously owing in rent. A number of our witnesses emphasized the harshness of this procedure, which can change a minor misfor-tune, such for instance as a week&apos;s sickness of the breadwinner, into a major calamity making it almost impossible for the tenant and his family to recover their previous position. The extension of the measure of protection from distress accorded to tenants of controlled houses to houses which have become decontrolled is one of the few forms of re-imposition of control which could be introduced without appreciable hardship to landlords, and the majority of our members feel that there is a strong case for this extension. There could be no logical reason, however, for distinguishing in this particular between houses which have at one time been controlled and other working-class houses; and in-deed any remedy called for should be of a permanent character. The extension of a permanent protection of this nature to all working-class houses is a question going beyond the scope of our terms of reference and is accordingly one on which, apart from placing on record the views of the majority of our members, we do not make a specific recommendation.120. The Committee wish to record their grateful appreciation of the services rendered by their Secretary, Miss E. M. R. Russell-Smith, who has appreciably lightened their task by the ability she has shown in organising the heavy work of collecting,
summarising and presenting the voluminous evidence we have received. The assistance of Mr. A. C. Sturman, who has acted as the Assistant Secretary of the Committee, was also valuable and much appreciated.We have the honour to be, Sirs,Your obedient Servants,(Signed)   RIDLEY (Chairman).HUMPHREY BRAND. VICTOR A. CAZALET. R.  N.  DUKE.C. GERALD  EVE. FRANCIS FREMANTLE. H. H. GEORGE.D. S. MACDIARMID. MILES  E.  MITCHELL.* T.  MORDAUNT SNAGGE. MAVIS TATE.H.  GRAHAM WHITE.*(Signed)   E. M. R. RUSSELL-SMITH (Secretary).* Sir Miles Mitchell and Mr. Graham White signed subject to the reservation on page 53.Mr. Brady, Mr. Graham and Mr. Montague were unable to sign this Report and have submitted a separate Report (p. 54).
SUMMARY OF RECOMMENDATIONS.(a) That houses in the upper range of the present Class B with a rateable value in 1931 exceeding  35 in the Metropolitan Police District and Scotland, and exceeding  20 elsewhere, which con-sist of single dwelling houses within the meaning of the Rent Restrictions Acts, be decontrolled as from the expiration of the Acts at present in force, subject to the same conditions as to the continuance for a further six months of the restriction on the right to call in mortgages and as to notice to the tenant, etc., which were applicable when Class A houses were decontrolled. (Paragraph 68.)(b) That where houses in the upper range of the present Class B with a rateable value in 1931 exceeding  35 in the Metro-politan Police District and Scotland, and exceeding  20 else-where, are occupied by more than one family in such a way as to constitute two or more dwelling-houses within the meaning of the Acts, the existing law should continue to apply, but should cease to apply in England and Wales when the rateable value limit of control has been reduced to  20 in the Metro-politan Police District and  15 elsewhere.   (Paragraph 70.)(c) That houses in the lower range of the present Class B with a rateable value in 1931 of  35 or less in the Metropolitan Police District and Scotland, and of  20 or less elsewhere, be combined with the present Class C and therefore be subject to the same con-dibon applying to Class C houses that they continue to be controlled whether or not the landlord obtains vacant possession. (Paragraph 68.)(d) That in England and Wales the upper limit of rateable value of the new controlled class recommended at (c) above be gradually reduced by areas over a period of years in accordance with the scheme based on the percentage of overcrowding set out in Part VI of this Report.   (Paragraphs 71-76.)(e) That in case of dispute whether a house is controlled the onus be placed on the landlord to prove decontrol. (Para-graph 93.)(/) That a rent book be required to be provided for all working-class houses which are the subject of a contract of tenancy; that the full name and address both of the landlord and of any agent employed be required to be inserted in the rent book; and that by leave of the Court service of any notice required to be served by the tenant on the landlord be deemed to be good service if served at the address of the agent whose name appears in the rent book for the time being.   (Paragraphs 94-95.)(g) That Section 18 (1) of the Rent and Mortgage Interest Re-restrictions Act, 1923, be amended to omit the requirement that
a sanitary certificate issued by the local authority shall specify what works (if any) require to be executed in order to put the dwelling-house into a reasonable state of repair. (Paragraph 96.)(h) That the date of this Report be substituted for the nth July, 1931, in Clause (h) of the First Schedule to the Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions (Amendment) Act, 1933. (Paragraph 97.)(i) That no further registration of decontrolled houses in the present Class C be permitted after the expiration of three months from the passing of any amending Act, and that decontrolled houses in the lower range of the present Class B which will be combined with Class C if our principal recommendation is adopted be required to be registered within three months of the passing of any amending Act and that thereafter registration of these decontrolled Class B houses be allowed in special cases with the leave of the Courts during a further nine months but no longer.   (Paragraphs 98-99.)(;&apos;) That by statutory amendment the effect of the decision in Nicholson v. Jackson, in which it was held that under Section 2 (6) of the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restric-tions) Act, 1920, there can be added to the standard rent only the increase in the rates actually payable after deducting the commission payable to the landlord under the provisions as to compounding, be obviated.   (Paragraph 102.)(k) That the time limit for recovery of over-payments of rent be extended to 12 months from the date of payment. (Para-graph 103.)(I) That the procedure for increasing rents after improve-ments be amended so that where works of improvement are carried out while the property- is vacant the landlord may let at the increased rent forthwith without first letting the premises at the old rent and then serving a notice of increase of rent in respect of the improvements and reletting the premises. (Para-graph 104.)(ra) That the definition of alternative accommodation be amended to require that the house offered as alternative accom-modation must in addition to other existing requirements be one in which the tenant and his family can live without being-overcrowded within the meaning of the Housing Act, 1936, and the Housing (Scotland) Act, 1935.   (Paragraph 105.)(n) That clause (f) of the First Schedule to the Rent and Mort-gage Interest Restrictions (Amendment) Act, 1933 be repealed. (Paragraph 105.)(o) That the Rent Restrictions Acts be consolidated. (Para-graph 118.)
RESERVATION BY ALDERMAN SIR MILES MITCHELL, J.P., AND MR. GRAHAM WHITE, M.P.We regret that we cannot agree to the Report without reservation. There are several matters to which, in order to secure a general measure of agreement, we have assented, but after much hesitation and very careful thought we feel bound to say that we do not approve of the proposals for securing decontrol.We are not here concerned with the principle of control. Parliament has repeatedly taken the question into consideration and has maintained control.This Report recommends that certain control shall still be maintained and with those recommendations we are in general agreement. We would point out, however, that those recom-mendations have been arrived at after much evidence and careful analysis of the position.We feel that to apply the overcrowding standard to measure the problem is wrong. The question is one of hardship, and, all through our many meetings and the listening to and reading of evidence, the question, we venture to say, in the minds of every member of the Committee has been, &quot; if houses were decontrolled would hardship ensue? &quot;, and the clear answer in the recommendations is that there would be serious hardship.We strongly dissent from the proposed automatic time limit. It would work inequitably and disregard hardship in many places.We recommend that the control as suggested should be for a further five years and that as now a full examination of the position should then be made, and when Parliament takes off control finally, we suggest it should be satisfied that the housing position is fully satisfactory.
MINORITY REPORT.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood, P.C., M.P., The Right Hon. Walter E. Elliot, M.C., M.P.Sirs,I. We, the undersigned members of the Rent Restrictions Acts Committee, have given careful consideration to the proposals which prove acceptable to the majority for the gradual decontrol of houses o^er a period, and feel that it is necessary to submit a number of points of disagreement. At the same time, we desire to say that the scheme laid down is preferable to one involving immediate decontrol of Class C or lower Class B houses.2. In the first place, we.do not accept what seems to be the assumption of the Majority Report that a bare sanitary minimum is a suitable standard of working-class housing. It is stated that the Reports of Overcrowding Surveys provide, for the first time in the history of housing, a substantially accurate measure of the extent of the housing shortage. We submit that they do nothing of the kind, and that figures denoting a substantial decrease of official overcrowding can hide an equally substantial increase of bad housing. This has been brought out in written and oral evidence from people closely in touch with housing conditions.3. It is argued that standards of housing are not the concern of the Committee but of Parliament and appropriate adminis-trative authorities. It has been said that the subject is outside the Committee&apos;s Terms of Reference and that Rent Restriction is a matter not of quality but of quantity. We consider this view to be fundamentally wrong. Rent restriction applies at the present time to houses not technically overcrowded. It would be most undesirable if, as a result of decontrol, present tenants were forced to go into dwellings of a less desirable type because of an existent aggregate of mere cubic space conform-able to official requirements.4. A further objection to the scheme of regional decontrol as it stands is in the dangers which might arise from striking an average over given areas. It is no comfort to the tenant of a house coming under the provisions of decontrol to be told that the average of overcrowding over this or that extensive area is only one per cent., especially if because he is not technically overcrowded he does not come into the average himself. It might be a great hardship to have to move to another end of a large combined area if conditions of work are not convenient or costs of travelling are considerable.
5. Superficially, it would appear from the majority Report that no decontrol could take place in any grade of Class C or lower Class B houses so long as any shortage existed. This is not so. While recognising that gradual decontrol on the basis of decline in the need of tenants for protection, even accepting overcrowding statistics as a guide, is less objectionable than any alternative method of decontrol suggested, we must point out that the scheme loses its elasticity in a comparatively few years. A maximum period of control is proposed for each classification according to the percentages of overcrowding in 1942. It is presumed that housing conditions will necessarily and auto-matically improve. But this is by no means certain. A slump in building is possible before long. Owing to rising costs of building materials, working-class housing may become a much less economic proposition than it is at present. Failing huge subsidies from the Government, municipal authorities may find it impossible to finance adequate schemes, and conditions of national stringency may recur in an even intensified form as a consequence of unstable world conditions.6. Our examination of the proposal convinces us that any hard-and-fast fixation of the period of control is undesirable. And in this regard we do not accept the implication that control is, of itself, an evil the ending of which should be a sort of ideal of all right-thinking people. Frankly, we consider that control of some kind is desirable as a permanent feature of the housing service.7. The attitude of mind represented by the commonly-repeated phrase, &quot; Control must come to an end some day &quot; is too apt to bias judgment. We cannot agree that housing is a fit subject of commodity economics, but rather hold the view that, so long as it is left to private enterprise, its management should be subject to public utility principles, modified as may be necessary. We feel that a social service of such extreme import-ance ought to be controlled, the public being protected against extortion and improper treatment.8. If, as property-owners claim, decontrol is not sought for the purpose of putting up rents, but in order to have freedom to keep property in good condition, protected against the bad tenant, or otherwise occupied to the best advantage with perfect justice to everyone, there could be no proper objection to some form of control that would achieve these objects without disturb-ing the security of, or otherwise penalising, the properly-conducted tenant. In respect to the value of property and return upon capital, if injury has been done by control (difficult to calculate unless it is&quot; injurious &quot; to be prevented from taking advantage of public necessities) it was done during the initial stages of control. Owners of ten or more years might have suffered, but speculative buying on a low market has been extensive since.
g. The fact that Class B houses are frequently occupied by** wage-earners forced into them by the shortage of accommodation lower down is recognised by the proposal to raise the Class C limit. The recognition is welcome, as is also the concession that it is undesirable to apply decontrol to Class B houses of the upper category, except on possession, where such houses are occupied by two or more working-class families.10. The decontrol of the upper range of Class B houses in Scotland is based largely, if not altogether, on the evidence of the Corporation of Glasgow. No witness appeared before the Com-mittee to explain why Glasgow Corporation were building non-subsidy houses at a rental of  43 per annum, plus rates, if there were an abundance of houses to let in Glasgow with a valuation of  35 to  45.II. There is still the false supposition that the. receipt of salaries rules the recipients out of consideration. Black-coated workers are, in fact, frequently paid as little as many an artisan although having to keep up a position of greater cost and live in a better type of house. It is all very well to say that there are plenty of upper Class B houses and that rents would not go up on decontrol. Some representatives of landlord interests have admitted that rents will go up &quot; to some extent &quot;, but, in any event, figures that include houses run up on the outskirts of towns for the prospective owner-occupier mislead. Many of these houses are jerry-built and their occupation involves travelling expenses often of no little amount. Not every clerk or salesman is able to buy his own house. We cannot agree that houses in the upper range of Class B should be decontrolled forthwith. We support the proposal as to lower Class B houses that decontrol should not automatically come into force on recovery of possession by the landlord and think that this should apply to all Class B houses.12. Control in some form should be both general and per-manent. In our view this control should take the form of Tenancy Courts (not merely Rent Courts) set up to deal with all cases of dispute, determination of reasonable rent, charges of nuisance, etc. Some formula based on costs, maintenance, history, and surrounding practice would require to be devised in order to settle what is, in any disputed instance at any rate, a fair rent, but this should mean no greater difficulty than the tasks of local assessment and valuation committees. The formal legal atmosphere, so intimidating to the inexperienced or less educated applicant, must be avoided. No good landlord should have anything to fear from such Courts.13. Tied cottages, agricultural and otherwise, should come under the Rent Restrictions Acts. Farmers, in our opinion, ought to be able to handle the problem of labour on farms
Pco-operatively but, in any event, we cannot accept the prin-ciple that change of employment or changes in farm management should entitle farmers to turn agricultural workers out of their cottages without proof of suitable alternative accommodation. Apart from the tyrannical power the tied cottage system uncon-trolled allows certain types of employers to exercise, it does not follow that a dismissed labourer will find another job where there is a cottage available. Naturally, he would desire to adapt himself to new circumstances and would no doubt do so in time, but, in these days of country transport, cycling, etc., the neces-sity for the existence of the tied cottage and therefore the urgency of the question to the farmer must be less than in the past and beyond comparison with the disability of the deprived farm worker. He should have the right of appeal to an inde-pendent Court.^ 14. Local authorities should be charged with the.duty of pro-viding information and advice to landlords and tenants on matters regulated by the Acts. They should be in possession of com-plete information concerning (1) the actuality of control or de-control, (2) sub-tenancies and rents, and (3) controlled rents. This information should be freely available to the public. Local authorities should conduct frequent investigations as to the operation of control, refer cases to the Tenancy Courts, and institute proceedings under the Acts.15. We are impressed by the quantity of evidence coming from all parts of the country alleging wide disregard of the provisions of the existing Acts. Fear of being turned out, operates in favour of the grasping and unscrupulous landlord. Despite narrow obligations to keep working-class houses in repair, com-plaint is frequently the signal for systematic bullying and^un-pleasantness. With decontrol this would be intensified. The tenanfs need of protection (in respect of undoubted rights) affords a strong argument for continuing and, to some degree, re-instituting, control. The only fair test in the matter is the production of alternative accommodation by the landlord or the local authority.16. The right of a tenant to withhold the whole of the 40 per cent, permitted increase, so long as his house is not in a reason-able state of repair and he has a certificate from the local autho-rity to that effect, appears to be rarely exercised. Again, the tenanfs fear of &quot; reprisals &quot; is more often than not responsible. The repairs that a local authority can or will tabulate are meagre enough judged by any standard of good housing but, even so, there would seem to be an enormous number of instances where the increase has been paid over long periods while little or nothing has been done. Moreover, it is not fully appreciated that the 25 per cent, supposed to be appropriated for repairs is upon the whole of the original net rent and takes no account of
(1/38)   (47389r-11)   Wt. 1889-2060   1000   1/38   P. St.   G. 335the amount deemed properly to cover repairs in the first place. Add this on and the 25 per cent, is magnified to a proportion more near 50 per cent, in an enormous number of instances. In any event, the percentage of repair costs and the percentage of rent are not the same thing, a fact that should be noted when considering increased liability in terms of a percentage.17. We urge that the recovery of excess rent paid by the tenant of a controlled house should be subject only to the principle of the Statute of Limitations.18. Distress should not in any circumstances be levied in respect of any house in Class B or Class C, whether controlled or uncontrolled, except by leave of the appropriate Court. The Majority Report emphasises the urgency of this question, and we see no reason why the recommendation of permanent protection should be regarded as beyond the scope of the Committee.19. We do not agree that the benefit of obtaining possession, without offering alternative accommodation on proof of greater hardship, should be extended to owners who acquired their property in the hope that the Acts would expire in 1938. Unless it is argued that such property was acquired actually in order to inflict greater hardship if necessary we fail to see the relevance of the proposed concession. Such acquisition of property was on the face of it speculative and can hardly warrant the infliction of &quot; greater &quot; hardship upon anyone.20. Finally, we desire to record our opinion that acceptance of what are called &quot; working class &quot; standards (in other words, specifically low standards) of housing for the great majority of the population entirely invalidates the figures presented in the Majority Report. We consider that the real housing shortage is much greater than appears from these figures and is not confined to the working class by implication narrowly defined. We point to evidence given by responsible and representative bodies for confirmation of this view.We have the honour to be, Sirs,Your obedient Servants,(Signed.)   ARTHUR W. BRADY.DUNCAN M. GRAHAM. FREDERICK MONTAGUE.
APPENDIX II.Draft White Paper.Government Policy on Rent Restriction.1. THE Government have given careful consideration to the Eeports of the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Rent Restrictions Acts under the chairman-ship of Lord Ridley. The Government believe that, having regard to the exhaustive examination of the position relating to rent restriction made both by this Committee and by the Committee which sat under the chairmanship of Lord Marley in 1930, there is now adequate material for taking the further action hereafter referred to and for formulating future policy.Both Committees refer to the great advances which have been made in housing provision since the War and the later Committee mention, for instance, that since 1914 there has been an increase of some 100 per cent, in the number of Class B houses, which now number nearly three millions. The Ridley Report also shows that the percentage of controlled Class B houses in England and Wales has fallen from 60 per cent, in 1931 to 32 per cent, in 1937, and that of Class C houses from 78 per cent, to 57 per cent.Even in Scotland, where the housing situation is much more difficult than in England and Wales, the Committee indicate that the number of Class B houses has increased by about 33^ per cent, since 1914&quot;; while between 1931 and 1937 the percentages of controlled Class B and Class C houses have fallen from 74 per cent, to 50 per cent, and from 77 per cent, to 60 per cent, respectively.The simple fact that a house was built before the War does not appear to the Government to provide a good ground for the application of a distinctive system of control, and the main issue which is raised by the Majority and Minority Reports is whether there should now be instituted a permanent system of rent control to be applied to all houses whenever erected or whether the partial system of control instituted during the War should be terminated as soon as this can reasonably be done.On this question of major policy the Government agree, without reserve, with the judgment expressed by the Marley Committee with one dissentient and endorsed by the Majority Report of the Ridley Committee that it is desirable that &quot; the restrictions should at once be lifted from any class of property as soon as it can be shown that they are no longer needed in the general interest.&quot;The Government also accept the view similarly expressed by the Mafley Committee and endorsed by the Majority Report of the Ridley Committee that &quot; the question of continuing control of any particular class of house must be regarded as dependent on whether the shortage of houses in that class is at an end or is likely to end within a reasonable period.&quot;2. So far as immediate action is concerned, the Majority Report indicated that any shortage of Class B houses either in England and Wales or in Scotland did not extend to the upper ranges of Class B. The Government, therefore, accept both for England and Wales and for Scotland the recommendations of the Majority Report that (1) Subject to an exception in the case of houses referred to in paragraph 70 of the Report as being houses occupied by two or more families, houses . in Class B with a yearly value or rateable value exceeding  35 (in 1931) in Scotland and in the Metropolitan Police District and  20 (in 1931) elsewhere should be decontrolled at the expiration of the present Acts subject to conditions as to the continuance for a further six months of the restriction on the right to call in mortgages and as to notice to the tenant;(2) the remaining controlled houses in Class B and Class C should form a single class and should be subject to the same conditions of control as now apply to houses in Class C.Legislation dealing, with these points will be introduced in the near future. [16562-2]
3. As regards future decontrol, the Government recognise^ that, as the Ridley Committee point out, there is a marked difference between the housing situation in England and Wales and that in Scotland. In England and Wales the supply of new houses is being maintained at a rate of over \ million a year. Council houses are replacing the smallest type of controlled houses at the rate of 60,000 a year and a number of lower rented nouses are now being built by private enterprise. Moreover, the majority of the Ridley Committee indicate in their Report that in their opinion there are certain areas where there is no longer any actual shortage of accommodation; and there is no doubt that during the next few years a considerable advance in the provision of housing accommodation, particularly for the lower paid workers, will add to the number of these areas.In Scotland, on the other hand, the survey of overcrowding has disclosed that the average percentage of overcrowding is 22-6, which is roughly six times the rate of overcrowding in England and Wales, and that the great majority of the population live in districts in which the percentage of overcrowding exceeds 10. The number of houses required to meet the housing needs of Scotland, including the remedying of overcrowding and the replacement of unfit houses is roughly 250,000. In recent years the supply of houses for letting at a rental of less than  35 has been considerably less than 20,000 a year.4. The Government believe that in the case of all three countries it is in the national interest that decontrol should be effected as soon as there is an adequate supply of housing accommodation; and they agree with the view of the majority of the Ridley Committee that decontrol should be progressive and should be related to areas and determined in the light of local conditions. The exact method and time at which such local decontrol should be brought about in England and Wales are matters which will call for further examination, and the Govern-ment, therefore, propose in due course to set up a Committee to examine these matters. In this examination it is the Governments opinion that, whilst the state of overcrowding in an area must play an important part, all considerations bearing on housing conditions in the area must be taken into account before further decontrol is effected.The Government consider that the question of further decontrol in Scotland must be subject to special consideration, and, while it is hoped to accelerate the building of working class houses in that country, it is clear that the Government would not be justified in initiating any general system of decontrol until conditions have been materially improved.5. The Government accept the minor amendments recommended by the Majority Report and will include them either in the Rent Restriction Bill or in other legislation as may be appropriate.6. The Ridley Committee, while recognising that the matter was not strictly within the scope of their terms of reference, made a number of observations upon the general procedure for levying distress in England and Wales which, in the opinion of the Government, demand careful consideration. The changes envisaged by the Committee would involve an alteration in the general law of landlord and tenant, and the Government propose to set up a Committee to examine the whole question.
[R.R (37) 5x]APPENDIX III.MINOR AMENDMENTS RECOMMENDED IN MAJORITY REPORTOF RIDLEY  COMMITTEE.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.1. Some of the minor amendments recommended in the Majority Report are designed to assist landlords and others tenants. They are set out in detail below.2. The Majority Report recommends that in Court proceedings the onus should be placed on the landlord to prove that the house is decontrolled, and not, as at present, on the tenant to prove that the house is controlled. This amounts to the reversal of the High Court decision of 1936 in the case of Hegin-bottom v. Watts, which, in its turn, reversed the previous practice which had obtained since the inception of the Acts. The decision in Heginbottom v. Watts placed on the tenant an obligation which he was seldom in a position to fulfil and led to much discontent. The landlord, on vwhom it is now suggested that the onus of proof should be placed, is in general in a much better position to know the history of the house. It is suggested that the recommendation in the Majority Report should be accepted.3. The Majority Report recommends that the full name and address of both the landlord and his agent should be inserted in rent books, while, with leave of the Court, service of any notice required to be served on the tenant by the landlord should be deemed to be good service if served at the address of the agent. This amendment is designed to assist tenants wishing to take proceedings against landlords for breaches of the Rent Restrictions Acts. At present, the form of name and address inserted in the Rent Book is frequently insufficient to enable a summons to be served. It is suggested that this recommendation should be accepted. The Majority Report also recommends that Rent Books should be provided for all working-class houses which are not in service occupation. This latter recommendation is to be welcomed on general housing grounds, as the provisions of the Housing Acts requiring the insertion of notices in rent books and similar documents are rendered to a large extent ineffective where there is no rent book, but as it would involve an amendment of the Housing Acts it cannot be dealt with in the new Rent Restrictions Bill, and will have to be the subject of future legislation at an appropriate time.4. The Majority Report recommends that sanitary certificates, issued for the purpose of enabling a tenant to pay a reduced rent for a house not in reasonable repair, should no longer be required to specify the works needed to put a dwelling house into a reasonable state of repair. This recommendation is designed to meet the difficulties which have arisen, particularly in Glasgow, in the case of houses which have got past repair. The Glasgow Corporation feel that, owing to a Sheriff Court decision, they are at present debarred from issuing sanitary certificates in respect of nouses included in their slum clearance programmes as incapable of repair and needing to be demolished. As a result the tenants of these houses are compelled to pay the full rent, and are deprived of the benefit of the provisions in the Rent Restrictions Acts under which a reduced rent may be paid for a house not in reasonable repair. It is suggested that this recommendation should be accepted.5. The Majority Report recommends that the right to apply for an Order for possession of a house required by the owner for his own occupation without proving the existence of alternative accommodation, which is now only enjoyed by owners who acquired their houses before July 1931 (the date of the Marley[16562]
Report), should be extended to owners who acquired their property before the date of the present Committee&apos;s report. A similar extension has been recom-mended by previous Committees and accepted by the Government of the day. It is suggested that this recommendation should be accepted, but it is to be noted that it is opposed in the Minority Report.6. The Majority Report recommends that decontrolled Class B houses in the lower range of rateable values should be registered in the same way as the present decontrolled Class C houses, that there should be no further registration of decontrolled Class C houses after 3 months from amending legislation, and that even for Class B houses the registers should be finally closed within a year of amending legislation. The procedure for the registration of decontrolled houses has not in practice proved as successful as had been hoped and the proper course seems to be to close the registers as soon as possible as recommended by the Majority Report.7. The Majority Report recommends that the benefit of current compounding allowances for rates should go to the landlord. As the law stands (as decided by the House of Lords in Nicholson v. Jackson) in calculating the &quot; permitted increase &apos;&apos; to the standard rent there may be added only the increase in the rates actually payable after deducting the compounding commission payable to the landlord. A note is appended setting out the position in detail. This amendment of the law was advocated in equity by the Marley Committee, though not then recommended in order to avoid widespread alteration of rents. Since the date of the Marley Report there has been another legal decision (Strood Estates Company Limited v. Gregory) in which it was held that in calculating the net rent the full amount of the rate, and not the compounded rate, must be deducted from the Standard rent. There is no conflict between the two decisions, but the Committee regarded the second decision (which was in favour of tenants as against landlords) as adding weight to the case for amending the law as to calculation of permitted increases to counteract the effect of Nicholson v. Jackson. The only objection previously taken had been that it would involve a large number of recalculations, and these were necessary in any case in view of the decision in Strood v. Gregory. It is suggested that this recommendation should be accepted.8. The Majority Report recommends that the period allowed by the Rent Restrictions Acts for recovering over-payments of rent should be extended from the present six months to one year. This amendment was strongly pressed by bodies representing tenants. The principle of extending the period is supported in the Minority Report, which, however, recommends that the period for recovery should be limited only by the Statute of Limitations. It is suggested that the recommendation to extend this period should be adopted, but the precise length of time to be allowed is a matter which may require further consideration.9. Three minor amendments are recommended on page 42 of the Majority Report. They are either consequential on other recent legislation, or designed to effect an improvement in machinery and should be accepted.10. The Majority Report recommends that the Rent Restrictions Acts should be consolidated. This amendment was strongly pressed by the County Court Judges and it is suggested that it should be accepted.11. While the Majority Report makes no specific recommendation on the question of levying distress, it records the view of many members of the Committee that the present procedure leads to great hardship and that the levying of distress might well be made dependent on the leave of the Court. These views are emphasised in the Minority Report, in which a definite recom-mendation is made that distress should only be levied with leave of the Court in any house in Class B or Class C, whether controlled or uncontrolled. The change would involve an alteration of the general law relating to the levying of distress and it would be well to set up a Committee to examine the question, subject to the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor.K. W.January 11, 1938.
&quot; Nicholson v. Jackson.&quot;(Paragraphs 100 to 102 of the Ridley Report.)1. Part of the permitted increase in the rent of a controlled house is the increase on account of rates &quot; payable by the landlord &quot; over the corresponding rates payable by him in 1914. The House of Lords decided in 1921 in the case of Nicholson v. Jackson that &quot;rates payable by the landlord &quot; must be taken to be the net rates payable after deducting any compounding allowance. An example will make the position clear : (1)	In 1914-^	 	s.	d.		Full rates (say) Compounding allowance ...	......      5 ......      1	0 0	0 0	(20%)	Payable by landlord       ... &apos;	......      4	0	0	(2)	In 1925-					Full rates (say) Compounding allowance ...	......      8 ......      1	0 12	0 0	(20%)	Payable by landlord	......      6	8	0	(3)	In 1937-					Full rates (say)    ......... Compounding allowance .	8 ......      1	0 4	0 0	(15%)	Payable by landlord	......      6	16	0	In 1914 the landlord got  5 from his tenant on account of rates, and retained  1 as compensation for payment of rates in advance, risk of losses, &amp;c.In 1925 the. landlord got  5 4-  2 8s. Od. (increase in rates &quot;payable by the landlord &quot; over rates payable by him in 1914), a total of  7 85. 0d., from his tenant. The landlord had to pay the rating authority  6 8s. Od., so that his compensation was still  1 as in 1914 instead of  1 12$. Od. to which he was equitably entitled.In 1937 the landlord got  5 4-  2 16s. 0d., a total of  7 16s. 0d., from his tenant, and had to pay the rating authority  6 16s. Od., so that his compensation was still  1 as in 1914.These examples show that the result of the decision in Nicholson v. Jackson is that in all cases the landlord obtains by way of compounding allowance the same amount as he did in 1914, irrespective of current rates of allowance.2. In 1914 the percentage allowance for compounding was variable in different parts of the country, and varied also as between the different kinds of rate poor rate or general district rate. On average it was somewhere between 20 per cent, and 30 per cent, of the rate levied. This position was altered by the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925. The compounding allowance is fixed at 10 per cent, of the general rate levied, but under later (temporary) enactments this may be increased to not more than 15 per cent. The level of rates has risen considerably, and the net effect of increased rates and lower percentage allowances is to make the actual amounts of compounding allowances now current not very different from those in .1.914. They will, normally, be a. little greater or a little less, so that an alteration of the law to give landlords current compounding allowances in all cases will mean slight increases or decreases in rents charged to tenants. This, however, is subject to an important qualification. There are houses now subject to compounding which were not so subject in 1914 because either, at the earlier date, the local authorities had practised direct collection of rates or because, owing to the alteration in the class of house subject to compounding which was effected by the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, certain houses were brought into compounding for the first time in 1928 or 1929. In these cases the landlord, although having to pay rates in advance, &amp;c, is receiving the same amount for compounding as he did in 1914, viz., nothing at all.  This is clearly inequitable. In these cases the alteration of the law suggested
by the Ridley Committee will give the landlord the current compounding allowance to which he is entitled, and the tenanfs rent will be increased by the same amount.3. The House of Lords decision in the case of the Strood Estates Company (Limited), referred to in paragraph 100 of the Ridley Report, may be exemplified by the figures given in paragraph 1 of this note. If, in 1914, the gross rent of the houses in question was  20, the landlords have been accustomed to say Gross rentRates payable by landlord in 1914 .20 4Net rent16Permitted increase of 40 per cent, on net rent of  16 =  6 8s. Od.The decision means that it is correct to say-Gross rent Full rates . 20 5Net rent15Permitted increase of 40 per cent, on net rent of  15 -  6.
[R.R. (37) 3]APPENDIX IV.RATING AND VALUATION IN ENGLAND AND WALES.Memorandum by the Minister of Health. Introductory.1. Basis of Liability to Rates. Broadly- speaking, local rates in England and Wales (other than land drainage rates, &amp;c.) are still levied on the basis of ability to pay formulated for the poor rate by the Poor Relief Act, 1601. The language of Section 2 of that Act is wide and, in fact, the law is largely judge-made. Ability to pay is now measured by the annual value of real property occupied, the assessment of an ordinary property being determined by making an estimate of the rent at which the property might reasonably be expected to let from year to year in the open market, the tenant paying the rates and taxes but not bearing the cost of repairs or insurance. From a &apos;&apos; gross value &apos;&apos; thus arrived at, a deduction is made in accordance with a statutory scale to ascertain the rateable value.The liability to rates is that of the-occupier of the property. But in respect of properties of small value the rating authority is empowered to rate the owner instead of the occupier, making an allowance of part of the rate if it is paid before a prescribed date.2. Administrative Reforms effected in 1925. The Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, which applies to England and Wales, excluding London, made practically no change in the basis of liability to rates, but effected great reforms in the administrative machinery. The duty of levying the rates and preparing the draft assessments Avas transferred from parish overseers to the borough and district councils. Assessment committees were constituted to determine the assessments and, except in county boroughs where the assessment committee is normally a committee of the borough council alone, these committees operate over areas comprising several rating areas. A county valuation committee was constituted as a special committee of each county council with power to promote uniformity of valuation throughout the county. Administrative machinery, the nature of which is described in paragraph 5 below, was for the first time set up to promote uniformity of valuation throughout England and Wales.3. Quinquennial Revaluation. In addition to placing the duties of assess-ment and rate collection upon larger and more responsible bodies, the Act of 1925, in order to promote fair and uniform assessment, required a complete revaluation every five years.Two such quinquennial valuations have already been made. A third is due to take effect in the country generally, outside London, in April 1939. In a number of areas work on the valuation has already begun, and by April of this year it will be in full swing throughout the country. The new values will be jknown to the public by the autumn, demands will be issued in or shortly after[16434] b
April 1939, and rates based on the new values will be payable before September of that year. In the City of Oxford and parts of the County of Berkshire these processes all take place one year in advance of these dates.As already stated, the Act of 1925 does not extend to London. Under law which has operated since 1869, the next quinquennial valuation in London will not take effect till April 1941.4. Before the Act of 1925 there was undoubtedly a grave lack of uniformity in assessments as between one area and another, a condition as yet only ameliorated. Formerly this was not of any great importance, since each rating area was in the main a self-contained local government unit. But the situation has been wholly transformed by the great post-war expansion of services provided by county councils (including those transferred to them from the minor authorities by the Local Government Act, 1929) and the new system of block grants established by the same Act and based on the needs of the respective areas as measured in part by rateable value per head. It is now of the first importance as a matter of fairness between different areas that assessments should be made strictly in accordance with law, and should thus be on a uniform basis.5. The Central Valuation Committee. It was with this need in view that the legislation of 1925, following provisions which had operated in London since 1869, originally proposed that assessments determined under it should operate both for rates and for income tax under Schedule A. Under this scheme the Board of Inland Revenue would have had important powers in order to secure correct and uniform assessments. These proposals met, however, with strong opposition in Parliament and were withdrawn. As an alternative method of promoting uniformity of assessment throughout the country, provision was made for the constitution of the Central Valuation Committee. This Committee consists of persons nominated by the various Associations of Local Authorities, with a minority of nominees of the Minister of Health. Its function is to &quot; give the Minister such information and make to him such representations in respect [to the operation of the Rating and Valuation Act] as they may consider desirable for promoting uniformity and removing inequalities in the system of valuation.&quot;A further duty imposed on them by the statutory scheme which governs their constitution is to convene conferences &apos;&apos; with a view more particularly to the formulation of principles for the assistance or guidance of rating authorities, assessment committees and county valuation committees.&quot;The Problem.6. Central Valuation Committee&apos;s Circular. In preparation for the new valuation the Central Valuation Committee has issued to local authorities a memorandum dated the 23rd June, 1937, of which a copy is attached. This memorandum is carefully worded and requires to be carefully read. While, in fact, it does no more than call for strict observance of the law, it has caused protest owing to a fear, in part unfounded, of drastic increases in assessments, if its recommendations are observed by the local authorities.7, Before dealing further with this circular, reference should be made to two statutory provisions which have a bearing on the problem: (a) Section 12 (9) of the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1920, provided, in effect, that the assessment of a post-War house which, if it had been erected before the War, would have been subject to the Rent Restrictions Acts should not, in the case of a house erected by a local authority under the Housing, Town Planning, &amp;c, Act, 1919, exceed the rent actually charged, and, in the case of any other house, exceed the rent which would have been charged by the local authority for a similar house erected under the last-mentioned Act. i The circumstances in which this provision became law and was subsequently repealed by the Rent Restriction Act of 1933 are set out in Appendix A.(&amp;) By Section 2 (3) of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1928, provision was made for altering the amounts to be deducted from &quot; gross value &quot;in order to ascertain &quot; rateable value.&quot;   In the case of houses and
buildings whose gross value did not exceed  15 the new amount was 40 per cent, of the gross value, and, in the case of houses and buildings whose gross value fell between  15 and  20, the new amount was  6?lus 30 per cent, of the amount by which the gross value exceeded  15. his provision applied only to the revaluation of 1928, but it has since been re-enacted for subsequent valuations and will, by virtue of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1937, apply to the new assessments to be made in the course of 1938. The history of the legislation dealing with deductions from gross value is stated shortly in Appendix B.8. The Central Valuation Committee&apos;s circular may now be considered in some detail. After calling attention to the respective functions of the Committee, the rating authorities and assessment committees and the county valuation committees, and to the importance of uniform assessments, the circular (pp. 4 and 5) emphasises the duty of arriving at a proper assessment of &quot; gross value&quot; and proceeds to discuss this in terms of (i) pre-War houses;(ii) post-War (other than council) houses; and(iii) council houses.As regards (i), the circular states (p. 6) that in many, possibly most, rating areas gross assessments are based on the &quot; net controlled rents &quot; (i.e., broadly, pre-War rents plus 40 per cent.), but that it has been judicially decided that the rents contemplated in the definition of &quot;gross value&quot; are the rents which might reasonably be expected if the hereditaments were not subject to control under the Rent Restriction Acts.As regards (ii), the circular notes &quot; a tendency to refer to rents of post-War houses, and to rents of decontrolled pre-War nouses as &quot; famine rents,&quot; &quot; scarcity rents,&quot; &quot;abnormal rents,&quot; or &quot;excessive rents,&quot; and states that, while for some few years one or other of these expressions may be justified, the position is changed to-day. &quot;It appears to be a fact that, given in any area an old house or a new house, of approximately the same extent and nature of accommodation, the newer house would command a higher rent than the older. Having regard to the popular preference for the modern type of house, a difference in rental value between pre-War and post-War houses is naturally and reasonably to be expected.&quot;As regards (iii), the circular points out (p. 10) that &quot; gross value &quot; is concerned with a hypothetical rent negotiated by a hypothetical tenant and a hypothetical landlord, and (p. 11) that rents of council houses, owing to the special considerations which determine them, cannot generally be regarded as rents of the kind indicated in the statutory definition of &quot; gross value.&quot;Summing up the situation as regards dwelling houses, the circular (p. 12) states that the Committee are satisfied that the gross assessment of dwelling houses generally in the valuation lists now in force in many parts of the country are not in accord with the statutory definition of &quot; gross value.&quot;9. There is no reason to suppose that the statements as to existing practice contained in the circular are not substantially in accord with facts. There is no doubt that, on any true reading of rating law, the gross value of a house provided by a local authority under the Housing Acts is in many cases in excess of the actual rent, and the true rateable value of many new houses is substantially in excess of the figure at which that value has at present been placed. The root of the difficulty lies in the fact that a modern house is not the same thing as a pre-War house, and that, apart from any question of the variation of the value of money, the amenities afforded by its occupation are greater, and often much greater, than those enjoyed by the occupier of a pre-War house.10.   Hence, two main questions demand consideration : (a) What is likely to be the effect of the circular?(b) If, in the absence of any action by the Government, its effect is likelyto be considerable and as a result assessments are likely to be substantially raised, is it desirable to take action to prevent this, and, if so, what form of action should be taken ?11.   Probable effect of the Circular. Each year there is a normal increase in rateable values clue to new properties coming into rating of about  5,000,000. [16434] b 2
In a revaluation year, in addition to this normal increase there is the increase due to the revaluation of old properties. In the revaluation year of 1929 the total increase was  28,000,000 (13^ per cent, on the existing valuation), and in the revaluation year of 1934 the total increase was  11,000,000 (4 per cent, on existing valuation). In the ordinary course, and disregarding as incalculable the possible effects of conditions of slump or boom, it might have been expected that the revaluation of 1939 would have been on a moderate scale, in which case no problem would have arisen. The new factors in the situation are the Central Valuation Committee&apos;s circular and the change in the law effected by the repeal of Section 12 (9) of the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1920, referred to in paragraph 7 above, although the latter does not appear to have had much effect on the revaluation carried out in London in 1936.12. The Central Valuation Committee have issued similar, though less forceful, memoranda on the occasion of earlier revaluations. These were largely disregarded by the rating and assessment authorities, whose members are naturally sensitive to the pressure which can be exerted by the ratepayers who are their neighbours and electors. Moreover, a rating authority that can keep its valuations down contributes less than it should to county expenditure and obtains or helps its county council to obtain-more than it should from Government grants. They may accordingly be disposed to take a similar course in the coming valuation. But the county councils under the lead of the Central Valuation Committee are realising the importance to themselves of uniformity as between their constituent districts. Some of them have already taken steps in the course of the current valuation period to criticise and secure an alteration of a number of existing valuations, and they would be neglecting their interests as well as failing in their duty if they did not take the opportunity afforded by the new valuation for a more widespread and more thorough attack upon recalcitrant rating authorities. It is already highly probable that action on these lines will be taken in a number of counties, and it is known that certain councils are already applying an educative pressure to the rating authorities.13. Confidential inquiries have been made of a number of valuers in an attempt to appraise the position. As regards six county boroughs in respect of which these inquiries have been made, it is anticipated that three will show an increase in rateable value of not more than 5 per cent, on revaluation; one reports that a general increase of 10 per cent, to 20 per cent, is expected, but that there will be no general increases in small houses; one expects an increase of 25 per cent, in small houses; and one expects an increase of 50 per cent, in the values of post-war subsidy houses and 25 per cent, to 30 per cent, in pre-War working-class houses.As regards the 19 administrative counties in which this confidential information has been sought, the majority expect a general increase in rateable values. The highest figure mentioned is 25 per cent, and it may perhaps be surmised that the average will be in the i&apos;egion of 10 per cent. It is commonly reported that there may be substantial increases in post-War houses. It will be appreciated that no actual figures have yet been considered by the local authorities, except in Berkshire.14. It will be seen from the above that at the present time the materials for an estimate of the probable course of the new revaluation are scanty. It is difficult to say more than that there can be no assurance that the revaluation may not in many areas involve a substantial increase in assessments. This situation will probably continue with but slight improvement till the autumn of 1938. On the other hand, if action is to be taken, it is important that an early announce-ment should be made, since otherwise a large amount of work may be carried out at considerable expense in connection with the revaluation, and may subsequently prove useless.15. Effect of a substantial rise in assessments. If effect is given to the Central Valuation Committee&apos;s recommendations on a largo scale, a substantial rise in assessments will occur and will be most marked in the case of the smaller houses, particularly the smaller post-War houses, which have been erected in hundreds of thousands and are occupied by the rather better-paid members of the working classes, clerks, &amp;c. This is likely to lead to widespread resentment on the part of occupiers, many of whom have to meet Building Society repayments and
will have difficulty in finding money for increased rate charges. This resentment will not be counterbalanced by any satisfaction on the part of those whose propor-tion of the total rate expenditure may be reduced. Their assessments also are likely to go up, though not so much as those of others. If all assessments are simultaneously raised to an equal extent, the effect should be to secure a propor-tionate decrease in rate poundage, the actual burden on each ratepayer being thus left unchanged. Experience shows that this rarely, if ever, happens, and that in practice local authorities are apt to regard increased assessments as a windfall which presents them with an opportunity of increasing their expenditure.16. Rating and Housing Policy. Apart from the probable reaction of a marked rise in assessments on the public mind, the question calls for consideration in relation to general rating and housing policy. From the point of view of rating, there is much to be said for leaving the situation as it stands, in the expectation that the circular will have its intended effect of bringing the practice into closer conformity with the law. The administrative interest in the matter, shared in the main by the county councils, the Ministry of Health and a number of other Government Departments, is strongly on the side of securing uniformity of valuation, and thereby a truer distribution of burdens and of grants. This can best be secured by leaving the existing carefully devised administrative machinery to work unhindered. It will also be appreciated that, as existing services expand, there is a growing need for further rate income, which will be more difficult to meet if assessments are artificially limited for the benefit of any particular class.Again, a large proportion of modern rate expenditure is due to the greatly increased scope of the social services, and it may fairly be contended that this fact, coupled with the increase in working-class incomes, makes it equitable that the contribution of the working-class ratepayer living in a modern house should not be artificially restricted to an amount comparable with that which would have fallen on him under earlier conditions.On the other hand, the housing policy of successive Governments since 1918 has been based on the need for securing houses for the working-classes at rents within their financial capacity, and it has been generally accepted that, for practical purposes, rents in this context mean gross rents, i.e., rents including rates. The whole of the financial arrangements between the Exchequer and the local authorities in post-War housing legislation have proceeded on the footing that the Exchequer subsidy, together with a suitable contribution from the rates, will secure a gross rent suitable to the means of the prospective tenants. Under the pooling arrangements introduced by the Housing Act, 1935, any increase in the assessments of municipal houses would (except in so far as balanced by a reduction of rate poundage) either fall on the occupiers in the shape of an increased gross rent, or would have to be set off by a reduction of the net rent, leaving a debit in the local authorities&apos; housing revenue account to be met from the rates. The probable result of the latter would be a demand from the housing authorities for increased housing grants.It should be added that an increased assessment means not only increased rates. It entails also increased charges for water and sometimes for electricity and gas. Usually it is accompanied by an increase in the assessment under Schedule A for those occupiers (only a proportion of the whole) who are liable to pay income tax.. Possible Courses of Action.17.   The following courses of action are presented for consideration : I. to leave the existing law to operate unhindered; II. to legislate to postpone the next valuation, outside London;III. to amend the existing temporary legislation mentioned  in  para-graph 7 (&amp;), so as to increase the deductions to be made from gross value in assessments of houses and shop properties;IV. in effect, to restore Section 12 (9) of the Rent Restriction Act of 1920,but extending it to cover houses in general.
Before discussing these possible alternatives, it is necessary to refer to another factor, which, though not in itself a matter of urgency, may have a bearing on the selection of the proper course of action. This is the possibility of appointing a Royal Commission to consider the whole question of local taxation.18. Demand for a Royal Commission. In December 1936 the Association of Municipal Coi&apos;porations asked for a Royal Commission or Departmental Committee to consider &quot; the whole system of local taxation.&quot; This request, which was based on the somewhat inadequate ground that there had been no Royal Commission on the subject since 1901, nevertheless received a large measure of support from local authorities and others. No action was taken on the request and it was revived in stronger language- in October 1937, the new approach containing indications that the rating of land and local income tax were among the matters requiring consideration.The request has not been formally supported by any of the other associations of local authorities, but the County Councils Association are known to be concerned at the growing financial difficulties of some of the more rural counties.In addition, there has for some time past been a considerable volume of criticism of the present rating system, which is summarised in Appendix C.19. The subject of local taxation was exhaustively examined by a Royal Commission under the chairmanship of Lord Balfour of Burleigh, which issued its final Report in 1901. In 1914 a Departmental Committee, under the chairmanship of Sir John Kempe, reviewed the recommendations of the Royal Commission in the light of the changes which had taken place since 1901. The Terms of Reference of these two bodies appear in Appendix D. Since that date there have been extensive changes in the financial arrangements between the Government and local authorities, culminating in the abolition of the &apos;&apos; assigned revenues &apos;&apos; and of many of the percentage grants, and their replacement by the block grant, which was effected by the Local Government Act, 1929.The figures in the following table indicate the growth in the income and expenditure of local authorities since 1900 : 	1900-01.	1913-14.	1928-29.	1934-35.	1936-37.	.    	 	 	 	 	(millions.)	(millions.)	(millions.)	(millions.)	(millions.)Total expenditure ...	m	148	406	455	Income 					Government Grants	13	23	89	125	Rates	43	71	166	155	171 (a)Other Income	26	55	157	181	Total Income	82	149	412	461	Valuation for local rates ...	180	212	26S	2S5	299	s.   d.	s.  d.	s.   d.	s. d.	s.   d.   &apos;&apos;Average rate in   ...	5   1	6   9	12   5	10 10	11   6 (a)&apos;(a) Estimated.These figures suggest that a review of local taxation is a matter which it may be difficult to avoid undertaking in the near future, unless some new factor should counter the steady increase of burden. This new factor is not at present in sight. Nor can the burden of local rating be considered in isolation from that of Imperial taxation which is at present, and appears likely to continue, at what would until recently have been considered a war level.20. The question of appointing&apos;a Royal Commission calls for consideration, first on its merits, and secondly, as making it easier to justify any legislation which may be thought desirable to meet the immediate problem. It will probably be agreed that it would be premature and undesirable to reopen at the present time the bargain between the Exchequer and the local authorities effected by the Local Government Act, 1929, and that for this reason the terms of reference of any Royal Commission should be drawn more narrowly than those of the
Commission of 1901 and should, so far as possible, exclude the question of assistance from Imperial taxation to local services.    On merits the advantages and&apos;. disadvantages of a Commission may be summarised as follows : In favour of the appointment of a Commission (1) The demand for a general reconsideration of the rating system is a growing one, and it seems unlikely that an inquiry of some sort can be postponed for more than a few years. If so, there may be advantage in the Government taking action without waiting for further pressure. Moreover, a Commission appointed in the Spring of 1938 might be expected to report in 1940, and this would make it possible to promote any necessary legislation in an early Session of the new Parliament.(2) Even if, as past experience suggests, no fundamental change in the system were recommended, it may fairly be hoped that the Commission would advocate a number of improvements in the present machinery, in particular amendments of the law for securing greater uniformity of valuation and assessment, either on the lines proposed by the original Bill for the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925 (see paragraph 5 above), or at least by making valuation and assessment a function of county councils. Further, it might be expected that useful proposals for clearing up the present situation with regard to railway assessment and rating might be made. In view of the powerful interests involved, it may be doubted whether, in the absence of strong backing from a Royal Commission, legislation on any of these matters is likely to be achieved within any reasonable period of time.Against the appointment of a Commission- (1) In the present state of public opinion it is unlikely that any unanimous report will be achieved. It is fairly certain that the whole subject of taxation of land values and of increment values would be once again canvassed, and probably also that of a local income tax.(2) The derating of agricultural land and partial derating of industrial hereditaments would necessarily come under review and would . probably be subjected to a good deal of criticism.(3) However strictly the terms of reference are drawn, the Commission might reach the conclusion that no system of local taxation can be devised that is adequate to meet the present and prospective burdens of local expenditure and thus inferentially reopen the whole question of Exchequer assistance to local services. In doing so their inquiry would necessarily go to the roots not only of local government finance, but also of the whole local government system.21. Turning now to the four possible courses of action set out in paragraph 17 below : I. The main arguments for and against leaving the law unaltered have been referred to in paragraphs 15 and 16. In favour of this course it may be added that no demand for legislation to deal with the forthcoming revaluation has been made by any local government organisation. Any such legislation might well be regarded by them, therefore, as a sale of their birthright. The pressure for action is political, and a substantial part of this agitation, it must be noted, is conducted by ratepayers&apos; associations, a form of perennial agitation which local councillors have learned very largely to discount.. Moreover, the fact that, as a result of the Central Valuation Committee&apos;s circular, an outcry has been raised so far in advance of the date on which the revaluation would take effect, may not be a disadvantage.II. The proposal to postpone the revaluation, while avoiding some of the immediate political difficulties, would be almost impossible to justify if no Royal Commission is appointed. It would arouse an especial outcry in those areas in which at the instance of the County Valuation Committee concerned assessments have already been increased in anticipation of the revaluation. Notable examples of these, within the knowledge of the Ministry of Health, are Cornwall, Warwick and West Sussex The resentment caused amongst ratepayers by these re-assess-ments has only partially been allayed by the understanding that the principle on
which they have been based will be generally applied throughout the: county concerned in 1939. Further, though the Department have no definite knowledge as to the attitude which the Central Valuation Committee would, adopt towards such a proposal, it seems not unlikely that the proposal would provoke much resentment and might lead to the resignation of many members of the Committee. It is also to be borne in mind that the postponement of the quinquennial revaluation would not in itself prevent rating authorities undertaking (or. in the case of the areas mentioned above, continuing to undertake) individual revaluations. Any rating authority could thus, if it so desired, render nugatory the postponement of the general revaluation so far as concerned its own area, and those authorities who have already increased assessments in individual cases might feel themselves bound as a matter of equity between different ratepayers to carry on the process.III. The third course, that of increasing the deductions to be made from gross value, has the advantage of being a method of approach which is familiar and has in the past been accepted without demur; and it does not nullify the efforts of the Central Valuation Committee to secure true gross values.Moreover, in form the adjustment would give relief to all classes of ordinary property (i.e., all properties except mills, factories, industrial hereditaments and public utility undertakings), though doubtless the relief would be so scaled as to go mostly to the small properties, the owners of which can least afford an increase.On the other hand, it is open to a number of objections :  (a) It may be criticised on the ground that it reopens an issue which was before Parliament as recently as June of last year, when the Bill prolonging the operation of the existing deductions was passed without debate.(b) Existing deductions are founded in theory on the cost of repairs,insurance, &amp;c, and no principle can be invoked for increasing them. Hence, there is scope for interminable argument as to what the amount of the deductions should be.(c) The proposal is not readily distinguishable from derating; and in theabsence of a strong demand for Government action from the Local Government Associations it might well result in a claim being made by them for a compensatory Exchequer grant. It is true that no such claim was made when the existing legislation was passed in 1928, but at that date the block grant system had not been invented.IV. The proposal to restore to the statute book Section 12 (9) of the Rent Restriction Act of 1920 in an amended form, so as to cover dwelling houses of all classes, could most conveniently be effected by inserting a provision either in the Housing (Financial Provisions) Bill, which has been approved by the Cabinet and is to be introduced immediately after the Recess or in the Rent Restriction Bill, preferably in the former, if the somewhat restricted scope of the Bill will permit of this.   The provision would take some such form as follows : (a) the gross value of a house belonging to a housing authority must notexceed its rent (as in Scotland);(b) the gross value of a house which does not belong to a housing authority,but is of such a type as is provided by the authority, must not exceed such rent as the authority charge for a house of that type;(c) In fixing the gross value of a house not falling under paragraph (a)or (6), regard must be had to the gross values fixed for houses falling under those paragraphs.The object of paragraph (c) is to provide a legal basis for the course which assessment authorities would in any event tend to adopt in order to avoid too big a gap between the assessments.of the houses of the villa type, i.e.,, those just outside the limits of working-class houses and those just inside the limits. The paragraph would apply to houses of all sizes, but, in practice, it would operate most effectively in the case of houses of a kind comparable with council houses, but slightly superior in size or in type of accommodation, and its effect would diminish as the size and value of the house increased.
[16434]no one disadvantage of this course is that, while it is practicable to apply the relief to all dwelling houses and thus to avoid the criticism that the working-classes are receiving benefit at the expense of the &apos;&apos; black-coated &apos;&apos; class, it does not appear practicable to apply it to buildings other than dwelling houses. It might, therefore, provoke some outcry on the part of shopkeepers, a class which has, through the National Chamber of Trade, for some time past alleged that an undue share of the local burdens resulting from derating has been transferred to their shoulders. Further, it is possible, though not, it is thought, so likely as in the case of course III, that the Local Government Associations might demand further Exchequer assistance by way of compensation for lost rateable value.Nevertheless, this course appears on the whole to present less parliamentary difficulty than either of courses II or III. It could fairly be represented as an attempt to maintain the status quo, which is in danger of being altered too drastically, in part as a result of the repeal of Section 12 (9) and in part by the more general realisation of the strict legal position with regard to gross value, which has been brought about by the Central Valuation Committee&apos;s circular.22. It is clear that, if it were decided to adopt any one of the courses II, III or IV, a simultaneous announcement of the Governments decision to appoint a Royal Commission to review the whole rating system would make the position easier. Indeed, as already stated, it would be exceedingly difficult to justify course II (postponement of the revaluation) in the absence of such an announce-ment. On the other hand, a case could no doubt be made out for course IV (re-enactment, in widened terms, of Section 12 (9) ) on its merits, and not merely as an interim measure. Such a case would he based on the broad grounds of social policy discussed in paragraph 16 above.(Initialled) K. W.Ministry of Health, S. W. 1, January 1938.
APPENDIX A.Assessment of New Houses.Section 12 (9) of the Rent Restrictions Act, 1920.1. THE Rent restriction Act of 1920 controlled all houses erected before April 1919 which had a rateable value not exceeding  105 in the Metropolitan Police District or  78 elsewhere. The Acts accordingly applied to about 98 per cent, of all houses then existing. Tt was assumed that the statutory restriction on the rents of controlled houses would imply a corresponding restriction on the assessments for rating purposes, and the Government of the day felt that this made it necessary to restrict the assessment of new houses whose rents were unrestricted. Accordingly, the Bill as introduced contained a provision that the rateable value of any new house should be the same as that of a similar house built before the 2nd April, 1919. The actual language of Section 12 (8) of the Bill as introduced was as follows:  &quot; For the purpose of any enactment relating to the assessment of rateable property the rateable value of any such dwelling-house (other than a reconstructed dwelling-house) to which this Act would have applied if it had been erected before the said date, shall be calculated as though this Act applied to the dwelling-house and as though the standard rent were the rent at which a similar dwelling-house would have been let at the date by reference to which the standard rent is calculated.&quot;The provision in this form was severely criticised in the House of Commons on the ground of unintelligibility, and the Government accordingly replaced it by the following provision:  (Section 12 (9) of the Act.)&quot; for the purpose of any enactment relating to rating, the gross estimated rental or gross value of any such house to which this Act would have applied if it had been erected or so reconstructed before the third day of August, nineteen hundred and fourteen, and let at that date, shall not exceed (a) if the house forms part of a housing scheme to which section seven of the Housing,Town Planning, &amp;c, Act, 1919, applies, the rent (exclusive of rates) charged by the local authority in respect of that house; and(b) in any other case the rent (exclusive of rates) which would have been charged by thelocal authority in respect of a similar house forming part of such a scheme as aforesaid.&quot;2. The assumption that restriction of rent implied restriction of assessment was proved to be false in Poplar Union Assessment Committee v. Roberts [(1922) 2 A.C. 93], but nevertheless Section 12 (9) was left on the Statute Book until 1933. By the Kent Restriction Act of 1933 the section was repealed following upon a recommendation of the Marley Committee. In their report the Marley Committee give the following reasons for recommending the repeal:  &quot;The intention of this provision was to ensure that the erection of new houses should not be discouraged by assessing them for rating purposes at their full post-War value. Since 1920 the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, and subsequent Rating Acts have been passed with the object of securing uniformity of valuation between all classes of hereditaments. In view of the provisions of these later Acts it seems clear that the rating provisions of Section 12 (9) are no longer necessary, and in some areas they have caused inconvenience. We have been informed by the Central Valuation Committee, the Committee representative of all local authorities which is specially charged with the duty of promoting uniformity of valuation, that they are of opinion that the provisions of Section 12 (9) as far as they relate to valuation should be repealed or discontinued.Accordingly, we recommend that the rating provisions of Section 12 (9) of the principal Act should be repealed in their application to England and Wales.&quot;3. Section 12 (9) with its specific reference to the Addison Housing Act and its lack of any reference to later Housing Acts was very difficult to administer in practice, and consequently the letter of the law was probably ignored almost everywhere. Nevertheless, it is a fact that in most parts of England and Wales the assessments of controlled houses have been restricted in sympathy with the restriction on rent, and that the assessments on new houses have been kept down below the level warranted by rents actually charged. It may perhaps be mentioned that one of the reasons which led the Marley Committee to recommend the repeal of Section 12 (9) was that they were under the impression that the-occupier of a new house similar to a house erected by a local authority would have a good ground . for appealing against an assessment which was considerably higher than the assessment of the council house on the ground of comparability. In a case decided after their Report (Ladies Hosiery and Underwear, Ltd. v. Assessment Committee for the West Middlesex Assessment Area [(1932) 2 K.B. 679]) and in later cases it has been, in effect, held that an appeal on the grounds of comparability is no longer valid.4. Section 12 (9) of the Rent Restriction Act, 1920, was never repealed so far as Scotland was concerned.   On the contrary, the provision, in so far as it relates to council houses, was
brought up to date and made part of the permanent law of Scotland by being incorporated in the Housing (Scotland) Act, 1985, in the following terms:  .&apos;&quot;For the purposes of any enactment relating to valuation or rating, the gross annual value of any dwelling-house or dwelling to which this section applies shall not exceed the rent (exclusive of occupier&apos;s rates) fixed in pursuance of this section, and no account shall be taken of any rebate from the rent so fixed.&quot;APPENDIX B.Scales of Deduction from Gross Value to obtain Rateable Value.1. THE present scales derive from Section 52 of the Valuation (Metropolis) Act, 1869. That Act, in Section 4, defines &quot; gross value &quot; as -&quot; the annual rent which a tenant might reasonably be expected, taking one year with another, to pay for an hereditament, if the tenant undertook to pay all usual tenanfs rates and taxes: and tithe commutation rent-charge, if any, and if the landlord undertook to bear the cost of the repairs and insurance, and the other expenses, if any, necessary to maintain the hereditament in a state to command that rent.&quot;&quot; Rateable Value &quot; is denned as &quot; the gross value after deducting therefrom the probable annual average cost of the repairs, insurance and other expenses as aforesaid.&quot;In the case of certain properties, including houses, the maximum deduction which might be made for the cost of repairs, insurance, &amp;c, was set out in a table in the Third Schedule to the Act.  For the smallest houses it was 25 per cent., and for the largest 16f per cent.2. Under the Eating&apos; and Valuation Act, 1925, which applies to England and Wales outside the Metropolis, the definition of &quot; gross value &quot; is practically the same as that applicable in London, but the deductions from gross value to rateable value are not specifically related to cost of repairs, &amp;c, and are definitely fixed by a Schedule. The deduction for the smallest houses is 40 per cent, and for the largest is 16f per cent.3. The scale of deductions in the Eating and Valuation Act, 1925, has never yet operated, and the operation of the scale in the Valuation (Metropolis) Act, 1869, has been suspended since 1925. In their place temporary scales have been provided by amending legislation to meet the difficult post-War conditions.4. The Valuation (Metropolis) Act, 1925. This Act suspended the operation of the scale in the 1869 Act during the quinquennial valuation period in London, 1926-1931, and substituted for it two other scales providing for larger deductions.The necessity for the Act arose because prior to the revaluation, which was to take effect in 1926, pre-War values had not been revised, and it was felt that this position could not be allowed to continue. Bents of controlled houses had increased by 40 per cent., and it might be assumed that gross values would normally be increased by 40 per cent. The local authorities in London suggested that such an increase would cause serious injustice unless the scale of deductions was increased. The suggested justification for the increased deduction was the increased cost of repairs. A large part of the 40 per cent, increase of rent was on account of increased cost of repairs, and this, they said, should properly be reflected in the scale of deductions. The position was aggravated because, in London, gross values for assessment purposes were at that time also the gross values for Income Tax purposes.At an interview at which these matters were considered the representatives of the Metropolitan Boroughs admitted that they had no treasonable case on the ground of cost of repairs which in practice had long been divorced from the scale, of deductions and fell back on the ground of expediency. They felt that acute political and social issues would be raised by the strict, application of the law resulting in increased rate burden on the poor. The increases might have reached 2/- per week. Mr. Neville Chamberlain on Second Beading of the Bill explained that it was to prevent increases in the outgoings of controlled tenants.       -5. The Rating and Valuation Aet, 1928. The first valuations in the provinces under the. Eating and Valuation Act, 1925, were to operate in 1928 or in 1929. As soon as the rating, authorities started to prepare their new valuation list, they were confronted with the problem which had arisen in London three or four years earlier, but in an aggravated form. In the provinces there had been no statutory scales of deduction before the passing of the 1925 Act; thft deductions had been left to each assessment committee to determine. Further, the 1925 Act. reduced the compounding allowance to 10 per cent, as against the 25 per cent.-30 per cent, previously enjoyed. Owing to the operation of the Bent Bestrietion Acts a reduction itj. compounding allowances meant an increased burden on tenants, so that tenants were likely to be injuriously affected both by increased assessments and reduced compounding allowances.The Bating and Valuation Act, 1928, met this position by prescribing a new scale of deductions and increasing the permissible compounding allowance from 10 per cent, to 15 per cent. The new scale of deductions was not as generous as that in the Valuation (Metropolis) Act, 1925;[16434] c 2
which it was felt had gone too far. That scale only operated for the one quinquennium 1926-1931, and in the new Act the opportunity was taken of fixing one scale (so far as small houses are concerned) applicable both to London and the provinces.The operation of the 1928 Act has been extended by later Acts, and by an Act of last session it will apply to the revaluation about to take place outside London.APPENDIX C.Summary of the Present Main Currents of Criticism of the System ofLocal Taxation(other than protests against increases in Assessments).(a) CONSIDERABLE publicity was given to some remarks of Lord Kennet in opening a national conference of assessment committees in March 1936. Expressing a purely personal opinion, he said that he had &quot; never been able to convince himself that the whole basis of assessment for rates was not completely out of date and unscientific.....   He would like to substitute for it some more general and generally distributed basis of contribution which would not be a tax on enterprise and development.&quot;(b) In 1931 there began an agitation for the repeal or review of derating, on the grounds that the privilege had been extended by the Courts far beyond the limits intended by Parliament, and. more recently, that it was intended as a measure of economic recovery and no longer necessary on that ground. The agitation began in West Middlesex, and was supported by more than 120 local authorities and assessment committees. In 1936 a renewal of this agitation was endorsed by the Association of Municipal Corporations, and perhaps a dozen Members of Parliament have written either to the Minister of Health or to the Chancellor of the Exchequer in support. Prominence was given to the agitation at the National Conference of Chambers of Trade at Bournemouth in the Summer of 1936.A &quot; snowball &quot; resolution has been passed by many assessment committees in the following terms:  &quot; That we, the Assessment Committee, desire to draw the attention of theMinister of Health to the provisions of the Rating and Valuation (Apportionment) Act, 1928, especially those affecting the derating of industrial hereditaments and which appear to us to have been extended to industries and businesses which were not intended to benefit and far beyond the original intention of Parliament. We further suggest that there is a general desire amongst local authorities for an enquiry into the working of the Act which is, in itself, difficult enough to interpret, but rendered more difficult by an amazing conflict of legal opinion.&quot;(c) On the other hand, there is agitation by particular interests to be given the benefits of derating. The most recent example is that of cold stores, the interests concerned in which have run a well-organised campaign.(d) The question of exempting from rates particular kinds of properties (sewers, hospitals, playing fields, &amp;c.) comes up from time to time. Newcomers to this field are the owners of aerodromes, who want exemption in order to help them in their financial difficulties. Since the report of the Maybury Committee does not recommend a subsidy, it is to be expected that there will be further agitation in this direction. It is still more probable that the government campaign for greater physical fitness will be seized upon to agitate for exempting playing fields and the like. There has already been a foretaste of it.(e) There is discontent with the low level of assessment of rates secured by the railway companies as the result of the House of Lords decision on the Southern Railway case, and some would like to see the Railways (Valuation for Rating) Act, 1930, re-written. Undoubtedly a number of local authorities will be seriously affected, and those hardest hit are those least able to bear it, eg., those in Glamorgan.(/) There is some demand that machinery like that set up for the assessment of railways should be available for the assessment of undertakings extending over a wide area. At present, for example, the Central Valuation Committee are doing what they can to facilitate the assessment of the property occupied by the Central Electricity Board, though the arrangements are not working without difficulty.(g) Apart from the immediate issue on re-valuation, there is much dissatisfaction with the lack of uniformity in valuation; and it is freely said that if the advance made at the next quinquennial re-valuation is not substantial new machinery will have to be evolved.(h) Discontent is as strong as ever with the present arrangement under which Crown properties are not liable to rates, but the Treasury pay a grant in lieu, more particularly in its application to telegraphs and telephones and similar property. The Central Valuation Committee have pressed this matter as strongly as they could, but without avail.(i) There are a number of points of detail in the Rating Acts on which the Central Valuation Committee and other parties have suggested amendments.(j) When the London provisions were dropped from the Bill wliich became the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, the understanding was that legislation would be introduced soon. Negotiations between the authorities concerned have dragged on, but so far without result.(fc) A year or so ago Political and Economic Planning brought out a broadsheet suggesting the derating of all working-class houses.
jl. &apos;*j j..APPENDIX D.THE Terms of Reference of the Royal Commission on Local Taxation were as follows:  &quot; To enquire into the present system under which taxation is raised for local purposes, and to report whether all kinds of real and personal property contribute equitably to such taxation; and, if not, what alterations in the law are desirable in order to secure that result.&quot;The Terms of Reference of the Departmental Committee on Local Taxation were as follows:  &quot; To enquire into the changes which have taken place in the relations between Imperial and local taxation since the Report of the Royal Commission on Local Taxation in 1901; to examine the several proposals made in the Reports of that Commission and to note recommendations on that subject for the consideration of His Majesty&apos;s Government, with a view to the introduction of legislation at an early date.&quot;(?) Undoubtedly derating has proved a serious weakening of the basis of local taxation, and some local authorities are finding difficulty in financing an ever-growing local expenditure. Recently, for example, a special committee was appointed at Manchester as a result of local alarm because the rate had risen to over 15/- The committee reported that a halt must be called at a maximum of 15/6 or otherwise the law of diminishing returns would begin to operate. Since then the rate has reached 15/6, and there is little doubt that it will have to be further increased. The position is similar in Liverpool, while at Sheffield a longstanding policy of stabilising the rate at 16/- has had to be abandoned.(m) In 1936 the London County Council unsuccessfully sought Parliamentary powers to make owners liable for part of the rate in respect of empty properties. Since that date the London County Council have urged the Government to introduce legislation enabling local authorities to Telieve the burden of local expenditure by levying a rate on site values. The report on the Finance Committee upon which this resolution was founded, a long document reviewing the rating system in this country and the attempts to secure powers to levy rates on site values, has attracted considerable attention.
County Valuation Committees. Assessment Committees (outside London).Rating Authorities (outside London) including County Borough Councils.CENTRAL VALUATION   COMMITTEE.New Pubuc Offices,Whitehall,London, S.W.123rd June, 1937.Rating and Valuation Acts, 1925-1932. Preparation of the Third New Valuation Lists.Sir,I am directed by the Central Valuation Committee to refer to their Circular Letter of the 11th January last relative to the use of Returns under section 40 of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, and to forward to you, as therein promised, the enclosed Memorandum on certain other matters connected with the preparation of the third new valuation lists. I have to request that you will be good enough to bring it to the notice of your Authority or Corrunittee.An additional copy is enclosed for the use of the Valuation Officer.It is hoped that your Authority or Committee will authorise the distribution of the Memorandum to the individual members. Additional copies for that purpose may be purchased at the price of 2d. each or 1/10 per dozen (post free) from the Secretary of the Central Valuation Committee at the above address.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,F. J. OGDEN, Secretary to the Committee.The Clerk to the rating Authority, Assessment Committee, or county Valuation Committee.
MEMORANDUM BY THE CENTRAL VALUATION COMMITTEE ON THE PREPARATION OF THE THIRD NEW VALUATION LISTS.\The observations in this Memorandum are to be read in conjunction with the Representations* previously made by the Committee to the Minister of Health and circulated by him to the local authorities.&apos;]It is the duty of the Central Valuation Committee under section 57 of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, and the Scheme^ made under that section &quot; to take all such steps as may appear to them to be useful or expedient &quot; to promote uniformity in the principles and practice of valuation. The Committee have hitherto proceeded by way of inquiry, conference and consultation, and by the giving of advice either in the form of &quot; Representations &quot; made by them to the Minister of Health and issued by him to the local authorities concerned, or, as on the present occasion, by Memoranda and Circular Letters addressed directly to the local authorities. In pursuance of the line of procedure indicated above, the Committee now make the following observations, in the hope that they may be of assistance to the local authorities who are concerned with the preparation of the third new valuation lists under the Act of 1925.The Central Valuation Committee desire to remind all such authorities that  .,(a) a direct and positive statutory duty is imposed by the Act upon rating authorities and assessment committees of making for aach rating area a valuation list which is correct, that is, a list in which every valuation is in accordance with the standard of valuation prescribed by the Act ;(b) general uniformity in the valuation of property for the purpose of rates can be achieved only on the basis of correctness, for it is only where every valuation is correct that true uniformity of valuation will be attained ;(c) it is the duty of the county valuation committee under the Act to take effective steps to secure the correctness of the valuation list for each rating area in the county, and it is the duty of that committee and of the several rating authorities to co-operate in achieving that purpose ;  and* Copies of the Consolidated and Amended Edition of these Representations may be obtained from II.M. Stationery Office, Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C. 2. at the price of One Shilling each.t See Statutory Rules and Orders, 1926, No. 1019 (Price 2d., plus postage l^d.), obtainable from H.M. Stationery Office,
(d) the rating authority and the county valuation committee respectively are empowered by the Act to employ such valuers and officers as may be necessary for the purpose of carrying out their statutory duties.This statement of the duties of local authorities is based on j udicial observations recently made in the Court of Appeal; but it does not contain anything new. The Central Valuation Committee from the first have pointed out that the uniformity of valuation required by the Act can be attained only by a strict adherence to the statutory definitions of value.Local authorities arid ratepayers should realise that the total amount to be collected as rates is neither increased nor decreased by a faulty valuation list and that, consequently, if any assessment is unduly low, whatever advantage or benefit may accrue to any indi-vidual therefrom must be made up by other ratepayers.It is also to be remembered that the greater part of the rates raised in an administrative county is for county expenses. According to the latest figures available (1934-35) those expenses absorbed more than 60 per cent, of the total amount of the rates collected in administrative counties in England and Wales. If, by reason of incorrect assessment, the ratepayers in any rating area within a county make less than their proper contribution to the county rates, then the ratepayers within areas which are correctly assessed contribute more than their proper share.A further and important consideration to be borne in mind is that valuations for rating purposes form part of the bases of allocation of Government Grants, and it follows that as a consequence of incorrect assessments these Grants from national funds may be distributed unfairly.STANDARD OF VALUATION.As already mentioned, the Committee have consistently advised local authorities that true uniformity of valuation can be obtained only by an undeviating adherence to the statutory definitions of value. The obvious reluctance of some local authorities to follow this advice in the past may have resulted from doubt as to its soundness or accuracy. If there was any such doubt it has now been removed, for
the general principle that correctness is the only road to uniformity of valuation has been amply confirmed in recent years by the judgments of the Courts of Law in the cases of Cardiff Archdiocese Trustees v. Pontypridd Assessment Committee (1930), Ladies&apos; Hosiery and Underwear, Ltd., v. West Middlesex Assessment Committee (1932), Lilley &amp; Skinner, Ltd. v. Essex County Valuation Committee (1935) and R. v. Cornwall County Council, etc., ex parte the Mayor, etc., of the Borough of Falmouth (1937). In the face of these judgments it is no longer possible for any local authority to claim that the uniformity of valuation required by the Act has been achieved unless they can also show that it has been achieved on the basis of correctness.From this series of judgments it is clear that in respect of house properties and other ordinary properties the rating authority and their professional advisers should form the best estimate within their power of the &quot; gross value &quot;* and apply that estimate without regard to any consideration other than that it is their statutory duty to make a correct valuation on the basis prescribed by the Act. No local or other difficulties should deter the rating authority from carrying out their positive statutory duty in this matter.A brief note of the effect of some of the judgments referred to above is appended to this Memorandum.fDWELLING-HOUSES. To a very large degree dwelling-houses preponderate in both number and value over all other types of rateable hereditaments. The Central Valuation Committee propose, therefore, to review briefly certain facts relating to the valuation of dwelling-houses in the hope that such a review will assist rating authorities in preparing their third valuation lists, and assessment committees in revising them.Dwelling-houses (excluding &quot;agricultural&quot; dwelling-houses, which are referred to separately in later paragraphs) may for present purposes be considered broadly under three heads, namely : (i) pre-war houses :(ii) post-war houses (other than council houses) ; and(iii) council houses.* &quot;Gross Value&quot; means the rent at which a hereditament might reasonably be expected to let from year to year if the tenant undertook to pay all usual tenanfs rates and taxes, and tithe rent-charge, if any, and if the landlord undertook to bear the cost of the repairs and insurance, and the other expenses, if any, necessary to maintain the hereditament in a state to command that rent.t See page 20
(i) Pre-war houses.The number of pre-war houses in England and Wales in occupation at the present time cannot be stated exactly, but is estimated approxi-mately at 7,000,000. It is further estimated (again only approximately) that of this number two millions and a half have either never been subject to the Rent Restrictions Acts or are not now subject to them ; that four millions and a half are still subject to those Acts, and that of this latter number at least three millions and a half are entered irt the valuation lists as having rateable values not exceeding  13.The information furnished to the Committee indicates that in many, possibly in the majority of, rating areas, the gross assessments-of pre-war houses are based on, or related to, the &quot; net controlled rents.&quot; By &quot; net controlled rent &quot; of any dwelling-house is here meant the &quot; net rent &quot; as defined in the Rent Restrictions Acts increased by 40 per cent., and by such other additions (exclusive of additions in respect of increased rates) as are authorised by the Rent Restrictions-Act, 1920. It should here be remembered that the &quot; net rent &quot; reflects the conditions existing nearly a quarter of a century ago.It was established by the decision of the House of Lords in Poplar Assessment Committee v. Roberts (1922),* that in the case of a hereditament subject to control under the Rent Restrictions Acts, the rent contemplated in the definition of &quot;gross value&quot; set out in section 68 of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, is such a rent as might reasonably be expected for the hereditament if it were not subject to control under the Rent Restrictions Acts.Whether the &quot; net controlled rent &quot; can be accepted to-day as the best evidence of &quot; gross value &quot; depends upon the facts which govern present rental values in any locality. Before the question can be answered it seems necessary to have regard inter alia to consider-ations such as the following : the weight of evidence as to decontrolled rent; whether the 1914 rents were normal; whether there have been such alterations in the character of the locality since 1914 as to cause a general increase or decrease in rental values, e.g., the opening of new roads and new estates, the provision of new transport facilities, the development of local industries, with consequent increase of population, or, on the other hand, trade depression and a stationary or dwindling population ; and whether the demand for, and supply of, houses of a modern tvoe has had any effect on the rental values of pre-war houses.* See Appendix, page 21.
The Committee are of opinion that (a) the whole position in relation to the valuation of pre-war houses requires to be carefully re-examined by each rating authority for its own rating area separately, and by each county valuation, committee for the administrative county ;(b) where, in respect of an appreciable number of houses, the-net de-controlled rents are higher than were the net controlled rents of the same houses, such evidence cannot be ignored in the-ascertainment of gross value ;(c) since &quot;net controlled rents&quot; are, in actual fact, being paid in-, respect of millions of houses, and have been so paid continuously for many years, a controlled house should not be assessed at a. gross value lower than the &quot;net controlled rent&quot;, unless there are facts relating to that house justifying that course. Investigation may show that the rents of some old-type houses are tending to-fall in some cases to a level below the &quot; net controlled rent,&quot; owing, e.g., to, the almost universal preference now being shown: for post-war houses of modern type. On the other hand it may be found that on decontrol practically all rents are increased. In estimating the gross value of pre-war houses regard should be-had to such tendencies where they are shown to exist.The assessments of comparable pre-war houses should not differ from one another on the ground solely that some are controlled and: some are decontrolled.(ii) Post-war houses (other than council houses).In very many areas, if not indeed in all, the assessments of new-houses have been based on an attempted comparison with the-assessments of older houses having somewhat similar accommodation.In view of the paucity of direct rental information concerning; new houses in 1929 and 1934 respectively, such a basis for the first and-second valuation lists is understandable, even though its soundness-may have been open to question.Now, however, the position is clearer. In many parts of the country there is rental evidence concerning new houses ; there are probably-very few areas, if any, where there is not some such evidence close at hand.The Committee have noted a tendency to refer to rents of post-war-houses, and to rents of decontrolled pre-war houses as &quot;famine rents&apos;&apos;,.
&quot;scarcity rents&quot;, &quot;abnormal rents&quot;, or &quot;excessive rents&quot;. For some few years one or other of these expressions may have been justified, owing to the facts that almost all rented houses in existence were occupied by tenants at rents controlled under the Rent Restrictions Acts and that houses to let at uncontrolled rents were really scarce. In these circumstances, a house to let at a rent freely negotiated was unusual, and thus the rental of such a house may at that time have had an element of &quot; scarcity value &quot; about it.To-day the position is changed.The Committee are unable to accept the view that rents current to-day are necessarily &quot;famine&quot;, &quot;scarcity&quot;, &quot;abnormal&quot; or &quot;excessive&quot; -rents, merely because they are higher than the rents permitted under the Rent Restrictions Acts.Many authorities and many valuation officers have been con-sidering what is the relationship (if any) between rental values of pre-war houses and rental values of post-war houses. After enquiring carefully into the matter, the Committee are of opinion that the difference between pre-war houses, taken as a whole and post-war houses, taken as a whole, is such as to justify the use of separate data for the purpose of determining the rents at which they respectively J&quot; might reasonably be expected to let from year to year.&quot;It appears to be a fact that, given in any area an old house and a new house, of approximately the same extent and nature of accom-modation, the newer house will command a higher rent than the older.Having regard to the popular preference for the modern type of house, a difference in rental value between pre-war and post-war houses is natural and reasonably to be expected.In accordance with their statutory duty rating and assessment authorities will doubtless satisfy themselves as to the character, extent and measure of the rental information obtainable in their respective areas. A careful examination and analysis of the infor-mation contained in the Returns obtained under section 40 of the Act of 1925 will be an essential aid to this end.When the evidence has been assembled, examined and analysed, and when the several properties have been inspected and all relevant considerations given their due weight, it is the duty of the rating authorities to prepare their valuation lists in accordance with the facts so ascertained.
It has been suggested in some quarters that, where direct rental Information is absent, recourse can be had to a reasonable commercial rate of interest on recent cost price or present effective capital value. The Committee appreciate that this, the so-called &quot; contractors method,&quot; may have some use as a rough check on the valuation of new dwelling-houses, but they are of opinion that it should be used with caution and they are not prepared to recommend it for general adoption as a basis of assessment.It has also been suggested that the gross value of a house which is being purchased through a Building Society may be deduced from the interest which the purchaser pays to the Society, the contention being that the interest paid by him on the loan, plus an amount representing interest on his original deposit, plus an addition to accord with the statutory difference between gross value and rateable value,, will afford a guide to &quot; the rent at which the hereditament might reasonably be expected to let.&quot; This suggestion is probably prompted by the fact that so many houses, in post-war years particularly, have been purchased through the agency of Building Societies, and of the consequent absence of direct evidence of their rental value. It is, in fact, merely another version of the &quot; contractors method.&quot; It is open to special objection for the following reasons among, others : (a) Building Society rates of interest are below those which would be regarded by investors and other owners as providing, a reasonable rental return from property of this class ; (b) a purchaser through a Building Society takes the risk of a fall in market values ;. and (c) he also takes on the full burden of repairs, maintenance,, decoration, insurance, and depreciation. A tenant does not take these risks and burdens (save that he may sometimes be responsible for some repairs), but pays a rent which is intended to cover them. Furthermore, a tenant wishing to move is more free to do so than is-an owner-occupier purchasing through a Building Society. Conse-quently it may frequently be found that a tenant of a post-war house is willing to pay, by way of rent, a greater sum than he would incur not only by way of payment of interest, with an addition for repairs, but also by way of repayment of capital, if he were buying the house through the agency of a Building Society instead of renting it.There is in fact no infallible ready-reckoner method by which gross value may be determined. Rating authorities and their advisers must apply their experience to ascertained facts, and iu doing so, observe the following principles : 
^1) the real value of the hereditament must be ascertained so far as an estimate can ascertain it; and(2) that value will, like all other values, depend on and be fixed by the economic forces of demand and supply in every case where the hereditament is of a kind to admit of those forces operating.As already suggested in the case of pre-war houses, the Committee are of opinion that the whole position requires to be carefully re-examined by each rating authority for its own area and by each county valuation committee for the administrative county.Whatever method or methods may be adopted, it is clear that ior some houses or types of houses the gross values of owner-occupied houses may, in the absence of rental evidence in the same locality, be arrived at by consideration of the values of similar houses in neigh-bouring localities, due allowances being made for the higher or lower rental values in the one locality as compared with the rental values in the other.(iii) Council houses.The definition of gross value applies alike to houses provided by local authorities and to privately owned houses. Rent actually demanded for houses provided under the Housing Acts affects the actual tenant and the actual landlord, but &quot; gross value &quot; is concerned -with a hypothetical rent negotiated by a hypothetical tenant and a hypothetical landlord.&quot; Rating is a process between an occupier and a rating authority to the determination of which the landlord and the lessee are strangers &quot; (Poplar Assessment Committee v. Roberts).Complaint is sometimes made that council houses are not assessed, :as they should be, on the same basis as privately-owned houses, but are assessed at lower amounts. The Committee have been informed lhat the existing assessments of council houses correspond, generally speaking, to the existing assessments of subsidy houses of a similar Mze and design provided by private enterprise.
It appears, however, to be a common practice in urban areas to assess council houses at a slightly lower amount (usually a pound or two less) than other houses, because tenants are generally willing to pay a somewhat higher rent for a non-council house, either because they dislike to be known as council-house tenants, or because they think that there is less risk of uncongenial neighbours on a private -estate. Where, in fact, tenants generally are willing to pay a greater rent for a non-council house than for a similar council&quot;house, there -clearly is ground for a corresponding difference in assessments. Such a difference has been accepted by Quarter Sessions in several cases.Rents of council houses, owing to the special considerations -which determine them, cannot generally be regarded as rents of the kind indicated in the statutory definition of &quot; gross value.&quot;Agricultural dwelling-houses.Agricultural dwelling-houses which are subject to the provisions of section 72 of the Local Government Act, 1929, comprise (a) farm-houses (i.e., the dwelling-houses of persons who are primarily engaged in directing agricultural operations on the land with which the house is occupied), and (b) farm-cottages (i.e., the dwelling-houses of persons who are employed in agricultural operations on the land with which the cottages are occupied).(a) Farm-houses. In some areas farm-houses are still assessed on the basis of some fixed proportion of the estimated total value of the farm ; and it has been alleged that in following this practice the local authority are acting in accordance with a recommendation of the Central Valuation Committee. The Committee wish to remind local authorities that in paragraph vii of their Resolution No. 77 (printed at page 20 of the Consolidated Edition) they stated definitely that they were advised that section 72 of the Local Government Act, 1929, does not neces--sarily require that the gross value to be placed upon the farm-house should bear a definite relation to the estimated gross annual value of the farm as a whole, and that, even were the section so to require, the relationship would not be capable of being ascertained by the apo^ cation of any arithmetical formula.The Committee are of opinion that where the land farmed includes land other than that held with the house, the local authority, when estimating the gross value of the farm-house, should take into con--sideration the whole of the land farmed and not merely the land held with the house.
(b) Farm-cottagesIn the case of farm-cottages, it appears to be a common practice in some counties to accept as the gross value the amount fixed by an Agricultural Wages Committee as being the value at which the benefit of occupying the cottage is to be reckoned as payment of wages in lieu of payment in cash. The Committee wish to repeat that, as stated in paragraph xi of their Resolution No. 77, they do not think that such an amount is conclusive for the purposes of the valuation list.What the rating authority have to ascertain is the rent at which the cottage might reasonably be expected to let from year to year for the purpose indicated in paragraph (b) of section 72 of the Iyocal Government Act, 1929. When vthe farmer is the rateable occupier of the cottage the rent to be found will be the rent which a farmer, taking the cottage for the purpose of housing his emploj^ee, might reasonably be expected to pay. Where the actual tenant is the rateable occupier, it will be the rent which the employee, who is offered the cottage under the restrictive condition that he may use it only while he is employed, on the farm, might reasonably be expected to pay for it for his own occupation.Dwelling-houses generally.On the information before them the Committee are satisfied that the gross assessments of dwelling-houses generally in the valuation lists now in force in many parts of the country are not in accord with the statutory definition of &quot; gross value.&quot;This position appears to be due, in part, to a doubt as to how far rents which have been negotiated recently can be accepted as the-rents at which houses &quot; might reasonably be expected to let from year to year &quot; under the conditions specified in the statutory definition. The Committee are not prepared to accept the view that, taken as a, whole, rents which have been negotiated recently between owner and occupier cannot be taken into account for valuation purposes merely because they are relatively high as compared with pre-war rents or with &quot; net controlled rents.&quot;There also appears to be an assumption among some local authorities that it is within their discretion to fix gross assessments on whatever rental basis they may consider reasonable, irrespective
of the rents that &quot; might reasonably be expected.&quot;    There is no authority for such an assumption.If a local authority, after careful consideration of all the infor-mation available to them from the Returns obtained under section 40 and from other sources, find that the level of valuation at present prevailing in their area does not conform with the statutory definition, it is their positive duty to make whatever change may be necessary to bring the values in the new valuation list into conformity with the statuteWhatever reluctance there may be to break away from a level of assessment which has, perhaps, been in force for many years, the Committee are bound to point out that if the existing level is incorrect, local authorities must not allow considerations of past practice to deter them from carrying out their duties by correcting it in accordance with the law. They have a greater public responsibility in this matter than ever before.There was a time when rates were very low and a rating authority&apos;s responsibility did not extend beyond its own area : then incorrectness in the valuation list had little or no effect outside that area. To-day the facts are otherwise : great additions have been made to the duties of local authorities, and consequently to their expenses ; rates are higher, and a large proportion of the rates collected in a rating area may be applied in meeting county expenses or other expenses common to the area and to other rating areas ; and the need for building up a standard for the distribution of Government Grants has made national uniformity of valuation on the statutory basis imperative.There seems to be a widespread impression that rating authorities by fixing their assessments below the correct level are acting in the interests of occupiers. On the one hand, owners who are charging decontrolled inclusive rentals much above the restricted rent level may be receiving higher net rentals because of the low tone of valuation ex-isting for local rates. On the other hand, where tenants pay rates direct, some houses are let at high rents because the assessments are low. In other words, low assessments are in many cases subsidisinghigh rents. It is true to some degree that an occupier maysometimes, at the expense of his fellow ratepayers, derive an advantage from an unduly low valuation ; but it is also true that in very many cases this advantage
accrues wholly or partly to the benefit of the owner and not the occupier, for very often the existence of a low valuation is thought by an owner to justify a higher rent or an enhanced sale price, and thus the effect of the under-valuation is merely to disturb the rental or sale price which the property would have commanded in the open market if it had been correctly valued for local rates. If all assessments were at their true and proper level as required by the Act there would be no artificial interference, due to incorrect assessment, with the flow of economic factors towards ensuring that prices and net rents also will be at their true economic level.VALUATION OF PROPERTIES OTHER THANDWELLING-HOUSES.The Committee have not thought it necessary to include in this Memorandum any special recommendations with respect to the valuation of &quot; ordinary properties &quot; other than dwelling-houses, e.g., shops and offices, or of &quot; special properties.&quot; The Committee have been mainly concerned to direct the attention of local authorities to what appears to them to be the most difficult problem of the forth--coming re-valuation, namely, the correct valuation of dwelling-houses, but they are equally concerned with the valuation of other &quot; ordinary properties&quot; and of &quot; special properties,&quot; the correct valuation of which is no less important.The Committee desire to remind rating authorities of the recom-mendations contained in their Resolutions 38 and 68 with respect to the valuation of water, gas, electricity and other extensive public utility undertakings which are situated in more than one rating area. It is understood that those recommendations were widely followed at the preparation of the second valuation lists, and that generally it was found that they worked satisfactorily. Complaints have, however, been made that in some instances the several rating authorities -concerned with the valuation of particular extensive hereditaments did not agree to the appointment of one or more valuers to represent them jointly ; that in other instances there was unwillingness on the part of the occupiers of the hereditament to supply necessary information ; and that, consequently, the occupiers or the rating authorities were put to unnecessary trouble. It is hoped that it will be found possible on this occasion to give effect to the above-mentioned recommendations in every case.
ISThe Committee, in advising rating authorities to give their -closest attention to all types of rateable hereditaments with a view to ensuring their correct assessment in accordance with the law, would further advise that the assessments of those properties which are now embraced either in Part 2 of the valuation lists as &quot; Industrial Hereditaments &quot; or in Part 3 as &quot; Freight-Transport Hereditaments &quot; should be reviewed, not only with respect to the quantum of the valuation, but also in order to ascertain if the circumstances of present -user still warrant the inclusion of the premises in those Parts of the valuation list which entitle them to partial relief from rating.&quot; Agricultural land &quot; and &quot; agricultural buildings &quot; are no longet entered in the valuation lists. It is important that steps should be taken to verify that the present user of all such lands and buildings -justifies the continuance of their exclusion from the lists.ORGANISATION OF THE WORK OF VALUATION.The Committee would again point out that while rating authorities .and assessment committees share the responsibility for bringing about general uniformity, the correlation of assessments throughout an administrative county or between one county and another, or between county and county borough, can be carried out effectively only by the -county valuation committees acting in co-operation with the rating authorities of the rating areas within the administrative counties and the rating authorities of county boroughs.The insufficiency of the provision made by some local authorities for the discharge of their valuation duties is, in the Committee&apos;s opinion, an indication that there are still many rating authorities, and some -county valuation committees, who do not appreciate the vital importance of those duties to the interests of the general body of ratepayers.ORGANISATION IN COUNTIES. As already stated on page 4, the greater part of the rates raised -in an administrative county is now raised to meet county expenses, and consequent^&apos; the county council are specially concerned in securing a fair and equitable distribution of rate charges throughout the county. It is suggested, therefore, that every county valuation committee should endeavour to ensure that the arrangements for the valuation of property in the various rating areas throughout the xounty are satisfactory.
Under the powers given to county valuation committees by sections 18 and 38 of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, it would appear to be competent to a county valuation committee to arrange for the valuation, at the cost wholly or partly of the county, of similar types of property throughout the county and to make those valuations available for use by the rating authorities. This view is confirmed by the decision of the High Court in the case of Coulsdon and Purley U.D.C. v. Surrey County Council (1934) (32 U.G.R. 447).*Every county valuation committee should hold conferences from time to time with the authorities within their own area, and with the county valuation committees of adjoining counties and the rating authorities of adjoining county boroughs.It is understood that at the preparation of the second new lists it was arranged in some counties that groups of typical ordinary properties in various parts of the county should be valued by the valuation officer of the county and the valuation officer of the rating area in consultation. These valuations were intended to serve as a guide to the valuation of other similar properties in the rating area, and in some counties were submitted for examination to the valuation officers of neighbouring rating areas in the county. This plan calls for a large measure of co-operation between the local authorities concerned, but wherever that was forthcoming it was found to give good results and to help particularly towards the building up of the spirit of mutual confidence which is essential if needless and costly friction and litigation are to be avoided. The Committee commend the plan for use in connection with the preparation of the third new lists.It is also understood that in a number of counties the rating officers employed on valuation work hold regular meetings. The close association of the county valuation officer with these meetings has helped to promote smooth working throughout the county.While recommending the holding of such conferences as are-suggested above, the Committee would urge that every endeavour should be made to secure that the conferences are regarded as a means-to an end, and not as the end itself. If any local authorities, as a result of the exchange of information, are led to the conclusion that their valuation lists are more satisfactory than others, they should not assume therefrom that there is no need for them to take any action towards further improving their own lists.* See Appendix, page 22.
16* See Appendix, pages 22 and 23.ORGANISATION IN RATING AREAS. The Central Valuation Committee have been informed that some rating authorities have been reluctant to co-operate with the county valuation committee, although co-operation would save both trouble and expense. For example, it is said that even when specimen cases have been taken by the county valuation committee on appeal to Quarter Sessions, some rating authorities will not apply the decision of Quarter Sessions to exactly similar cases unless separate proposals are made by the county valuation committee in each case. The Central Valuation Committee think that a difficulty of this kind should not arise, but that where it does arise, the county valuation committee should not hestitate to deal with it.On account of the expense, the rating authorities of some areas, where the produce of a penny rate is small, are said to find it difficult to provide effectivety from their existing staff, or by temporary additions to that staff, for the making of a correct valuation list. It is, however, their statutory duty to make such a list, and, looking to the terms of the judgment in the case of Coulsdon aud Purley U.D.C. v. Surrey County Council (already mentioned on page 16 above) it w&apos;ould appear to be practicable, in appropriate cases, for a rating authority and the county valuation committee to co-operate in overcoming any difficulty that the rating authority may experience in meeting at their own expense the whole of the cost of preparing for the rating area a valuation list which shall be correct. Alternatively, there seems no reason why a rating authority should not share the services of a competent valuation officer, with one or more other rating authorities.ASSESSMENT COMMITTEES. The powers and duties of assessment committees under the Rating and Valuation Acts have been considered in recent years in a number of cases before the High Court. Reference may be made in particular to the cases of R. v. North Worcestershire A.C., ex parte Hadley (1929) ; R. v. North-East Surrey A.C., exparte F. W. Woolworth &amp; Co., Ltd. (1933) ; R. v. Salford A.C., ex parte Ogden (1937) ; and Middlesex County Valuation Committee v. West Middlesex A.C. (1937).*In each of these cases one effect of the judgment has been to emphasize the judicial or quasi-judicial nature of an assessment
committee&apos;s functions. A full realisation by the assessment committees-themselves, as well as by ratepayers, rating authorities and county valuation committees of all that is explicitly stated and implied in these judgments would, in the opinion of the Central Valuation Committee, prove of great assistance to the assessment committees in discharging their responsible and difficult duties under the Act.DATES OF PROCEEDINGS.Section 28 of the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925, requires that the new valuation lists shall be approved by the assessment committees not later than the 31st January, 1938 or 1939, as the case may be. Having regard to the widely differing conditions in rating areas and assessment areas, it is not thought practicable to suggest a table of dates of proceedings which could conveniently be operated in every area, but the Committee strongly urge upon every rating authority the desirability of completing their draft lists in such time as will afford the assessment committee ample opportunity for con-sideration. The rating authority should consult the assessment committee on this point at an early date.GENERAL.In making the foregoing observations, the Committee, as already mentioned, have adhered to the course hitherto followed by them, namely, to proceed by way of inquiry, conference and consultation, and by the giving of advice in the form of Representations and Memor-anda.The responsibility for the making of correct valuation lists rests entirely upon local authorities, and the failure of any local authority to discharge faithfully that responsibility necessarily reacts to the disadvantage of some, at least, of the ratepayers in the authority&apos; own area and of ratepayers in other areas. It also exercises a bad influ-ence. The Committee are convinced by the facts brought to their notice that one of the chief causes of the existing lack of correctness and uniformity of valuation is the suspicion that some rating authorities are evading&quot; their statutory duty to make correct valuations, and are under-valuing the properties in their areas with the intention of (i) avoiding payment of a fair share of county expenses ;(ii) obtaining an undue share of Grants distributable by the Ministry of Health and the Board of Education.
If any rating authorities uuder-assess properties, from a desire not to offend their own ratepayers, or to secure an advantage over neighbouring rating areas, or for any other reason, the other rating authorities and the county valuation committee should not hesitate to make the fullest possible use of the powers of objection and proposal given to them in the Act.Good faith and efficiency on the part of all the local authorities concerned in this matter are so important, that if, after the third new lists have been made, the Central Valuation Committee have grounds for believing that there is neglect or evasion of duty in any area, and that the neglect or evasion is not being adequately dealt with by the local authorities primarily concerned, the Committee will consider it their duty to take such further action as will lead to the fulfilment of the purposes for which they were constituted and the proper attain-ment of the objects of the Act.Office of the Centrally aluaiion Committee, New Public Offices,Whitehall,London, S.W.I.23rd fane, 1937.
A. Notes of cases referred to on Page 5.(1) Cardiff Arch-diocese   Trustees v.  Pontypridd  Area  Assessment Committee and Mountain Ash Rating Authority (K.B.D., 1930)Extract from the head-note to the Report at 28 L.G.R. 535.It was contended that a part of a church should be excluded from the valuation list because other churches with similar circum-stances were so excluded. It was held that the contention of unfairness amounted to a claim, not that the Act should be uniformly applied, but that it should be uniformly misapplied. If other buildings had been wrongly excluded the appellants sought to contend that none must be rightly included, but that all must be included in the unfairness. Such a contention could not succeed.(2) Ladies&apos; Hosiery ana Underwear, Ltd. v. Assessment Committee for the West Middlesex Assessment Area (Court of Appeal, 1932).Extract from the head-note to the Report at 30 L.G.R. 369.&quot; Held that quarter sessions were not justified in disregarding the uncontradicted evidence that the assessment was a correct state-ment of the gross value of the appellants&apos; premises according to the statutory- definition and in altering it to an incorrect statement in order to secure uniformity in error.&quot;(3) Lilley &amp; Skinner, Ltd. v. Essex County Valuation Committee (K.B.D., 1935).Extract from the head-note to the Report at 33 L.G.R., 272.&quot; . . . . The Appellants occupied a shop of which the assessment had been increased. They admitted that the increased assessment was not higher than the true value of the property, but contendedAPPENDIX.Notes of Judgments in certain High Court cases.
that it was unlawful to increase the assessment of one class of under-assessed property without at the same time increasing that of all other under-assessed property.Held that the appellants were not entitled to have their assess-ment reduced on the ground that other property had been assessed at less than its true value.&quot;(4) R. v. Cornwall County Council ex parte the Mayor, etc., of the Borough of Falmouth.   (Court of Appeal, 1937.)Extract from the Judgment of Lord Justice Scott as reported in &quot; Rating and Income Tax &quot; of the 27th March, 1937.&quot; It seems to me on the merits of the case the Appellants have not taken sufficient account of the direct statutory duty imposed by section 22 and other effective sections of making a valuation list that is correct, or correcting a valuation list under section 37 of the Act which is incorrect. The duty of making a valuation in accordance with the standard of valuation prescribed by the Act is a positive duty. In my view the argument for the Appellants here assumes that there is an over-riding positive duty modifying the first positive duty laid on the County Valuation Committee, and also on the Assessment Committee, to see that no correction of an existing List is made unless there is uniformity established throughout the whole county. I see no ground for taking that view.&quot;b. Notes of other cases referred to in the Memorandum.(5) Poplar Union Assessment Committee v. Roberts (House of Lords, 1922) Extract from the headnote to the Report in Butter-worth&apos;s Rating Appeals, at page 858.The &quot; gross value &quot; to be arrived at in valuing a hereditament under the Valuation (Metropolis) Act, 1869, is not limited by reason of that hereditament being a dwelling-house within the meaning of the Increase of Rent, etc. (Restrictions) Act, 1920, to the amount of the standard rent plus the permitted increases, and the latter Act does not . , , , affect the system of rating established by the Act of 1869.
(6) R. v. North Worcestershire Assessment Committee, ex parte Hartley (K.B.D. 1929). Extract from the head-note to the Report at 27 L.G.R. 458.Held : That in hearing and determining objections to the valuation list the assessment committee were in a position analogous to that of a court and were bound to act judicially.(7) R. v. Assessment Committee for North East Surrey Assessment Area, ex parte F. W. Woolworth &amp; Co. Ltd. (K.B.D. 1932). Extract from the head-note to the Report at 31 L.G.R. 119.The mere presence of the county valuation officer during the deliberations of an assessment committee on a proposal to amend the valuation list, is sufficient to invalidate the decision, though he takes no part in the discussion and is not consulted by the committee.(8) Coulsdon and Parley Urban District Council v. Surrey County Council (Chancery Divn., 1934). Extract from the head-note to the Report at 32 L.G.R. 447.As the result of a conference held between the county valuation committee of the defendant county council and representatives of the rating authorities of that county, the county valuation committee appointed a special panel of valuers for the purposes of the preparation of a new valuation list for the county to value special classes of property throughout the county on behalf of themselves, with a view of advising such rating authorities as chose to take advantage of their valuation, the payment of such valuers to be met out of the county rate.Held : That the defendants had acted within the scope of their duties and powers under the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925.(9) R. v. Salford City Assessment Committee (ex parte Ogden) (Court of Appeal, 1937).Extract from head-note to Report in &quot; Rating and Income Tax,&quot; of 6th March, 1937.   148. Held :   That an assessment committee is a body performing judicial or quasi-judicial functions, and that the general principles affecting the possibilhy of bias, as exemplified in the case of justices of the peace, should be applied to an assessment committee.
(10) Middlesex County Valuation Committee v. West Middlesex Assess-ment Committee (Court of Appeal, 1937).Extract from the head-note of the Report at 35 L.C.R. 211.Held : That the County Valuation Committee, through their officer, had a general power under section 18 (2) of the Act to attend such meetings and, therefore, the power given to the Assessment Committee by Schedule 1 to the Act of regulating their own proceedings did not include the power of excluding that officer from such meetings. Such power to attend meetings, however, did not enable the County Valuation Committee, through their officer, to be present at the deliberations of the Assessment Committee when they were arriving at a decision.

</content>
</cab>
