<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/274/0 images: 573-588</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  February 1938.SECRET. Copy No.CP. 28 (38).CABINET.QUESTION OF THE TRANSFER TO THE UNION OF THE GOVERN-MENT OF THE HIGH COMMISSION TERRITORIES IN SOUTH AFRICA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.AT the meeting of the Cabinet on the 28th July last (Cabinet 32 (37)) my colleagues approved the general lines of a draft letter which I proposed to send to General Hertzog on the subject of the transfer to the Union of the government of the High Commission Territories in South Africa I now attach for the information of my colleagues a copy of the letter to General Hertzog, in the form in which, after correspondence with Sir William Clark (our High Commissioner), it was finally handed as a draft to the General (Appendix A). I also attach copies of draft letters sent to me by General Hertzog in reply (Appendix B). My letter was given to the General in the form of a draft, in order to avoid possible difficulty if he did not regard it as a suitable basis for further discussion and negotiation, and his replies therefore took the same form. It was subsequently agreed that signed copies of the letters should be exchanged.2. It will be noticed that General Hertzog, in his reply, asserts with considerable emphasis that it was clearly and definitely understood between him and Mr. Thomas in 1935 that it was essential to the success of the policy then agreed (as to which see paragraph 5 of my memorandum CP. 197 (37)), that not only should the officials in the Territories actively discourage agitation against joining the Union, but that they should also be instructed to inculcate in the inhabitants ideas favourable towards transfer. The instructions which Mr. Thomas had, in fact, issued to the High Commissioner in 1935, had received General Hertzog&apos;s concurrence, and were to the effect that the policy should be to discourage agitation against joining the Union and to concentrate on getting everyone, Natives and Europeans alike, to work for the success of such co-operative measures as might be found possible. I made it clear to General Hertzog, when I discussed the question with him during the summer, that I fully accepted this policy, but that it did not seem to me proper to go a step further and issue specific instructions to our officials to use their influence positively to persuade the Natives to agree to transfer.3. After consideration of General Hertzog&apos;s draft letters, I asked Sir William Clark to discuss the matter further with the general, to explain to the general that it seemed clear that he must have derived from his talk with Mr. Thomas an impression which could not be reconciled with the records in the Dominions Office, but to suggest that this divergence of view as to what had taken place in the past should not prevent our now concentrating on the consideration of what practical steps could be taken in the future to continue the policy of [16675] b
co-operation between the two Governments with a view to bringing about a situa-tion in which, if transfer were to become a matter of practical politics, it could be effected with the goodwill of the populations concerned. General Hertzog has agreed to proceed on this basis. I thought it desirable that my inability to accept his interpretation of his talk with Mr. Thomas should be placed on record in reply to the assertions in his letter, and therefore sent him the brief acknowledgment which appears in Appendix C.4. The main practical steps which we contemplate with a view to carrying the policy forward are :- (a) the constitution of a Standing Joint Advisory Conference consisting ofthe Secretary of the Union Native Affairs Department and two other officers of the Union Government together with the Resident Commis-missioners of the High Commission Territories, whose function it will be to study openings for co-operation between the Union Government and the Administrations in matters affecting the development of the Territories and to consider questions of joint concern to the Union and the Territories (such as the marketing of produce, prevention and control of animal diseases, prevention of plague, &amp;c.); and(b) the issue of memoranda by the Union Government setting forth, for theinformation of the inhabitants of the Territories, a clear picture of the terms on which the transfer of the administrations of the Territories to the Union, if decided upon, would take place.5. It is contemplated that the Resident Commissioners would bring these memoranda to the notice of the Native authorities in the Territories and assist them in obtaining any further explanation of the memoranda which they may desire. This action, it is hoped, will serve to indicate to the Union Government that we are fully prepared to act in accordance with the spirit of the 1935 Agreement.6. It is- public knowledge that General Hertzog and I have been in communication together about this question since his visit to England last summer. With a view to making known the results of this exchange of views, and to announcing the agreements reached as a result of it, it is proposed that the general and I should publish a joint statement. The draft of this statement, which has been prepared as a result of consultation between Sir William Clark and the Union authorities, and which is being submitted to the Union Cabinet for their early approval, is attached (Appendix D). It is desirable that this should be issued as soon as possible since questions as to the position are being asked in the House of Commons, and General Hertzog will no doubt also be questioned in the Union Parliament, which has now reassembled. I invite my colleagues&apos; approval to the terms of the proposed statement (subject to further consideration if the Union Cabinet suggest any amendments), and to the publication of the statement soon after it has been agreed.7. The memoranda referred to in paragraph 4 (b) above and in the joint, statement are now in course of preparation by the Union authorities. It is contemplated tha,t these memoranda should be issued by the Union Government at a later date. They will be issued, of course, on the sole responsibility of the Union Government, but informal discussion regarding their terms is taking-place between Union officials and Sir William Clark. I wall circulate the drafts for the Cabinet&apos;s information as soon as I receive them in any approximately final form.8. There still remains the question of the alternative security to be offered by the Union Government in place of Sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule to the South Africa Act. (Section 20 states that the King may disallow any law made by the Governor-General in Council in relation to the Territories after transfer, and Section 25 provides that all Bills to amend or alter the provisions of the Schedule should be reserved for His Majesty&apos;s pleasure.) This point is referred to in my first letter to General Hertzog (Appendix A).   Whatever arrangement
is proposed as a substitute for the safeguards in the Schedule will, of course, require the assent of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom. At present, Sir William Clark has been asked to try to secure Union Ministers&apos; agreement to an undertaking that the Union Government would consult with the United Kingdom Government as to any proposal for any alteration of the terms of the Schedule, and also if any legislation relating to the Territories were proposed involving variation of arrangements agreed between the United Kingdom and Union Governments prior to and in connection with the transfer of any of the Territories.M. M.February 11, 1938.[16675]
APPENDIX A.Draft Letter from Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs to General Hertzog.(Confidential.) Downing Street.I WELCOMED the opportunity whilst you were in London this summer of discussing with you the position regarding the transfer of the South African High Commission Territories. To my mind this is a question of great importance, with regard to which it is desirable, and indeed essential, that there should be constant contact, understanding and confidence between His Majesty&apos;s Governments in the Union of South Africa and in the United Kingdom. I was therefore glad of the frank and friendly discussions which we had, though keenly sorry that you should have felt disappointment at their outcome.You will remember that at the close of our talks I promised to think over very carefully the position as it was left by them, and to communicate with you further after your return to South Africa. The purpose was to see what further practical action we could devise in consultation together to enable the policy agreed upon in 1935 to be given full effect. Since you returned to South Africa the question has been further discussed in your and my public statements, and in the light of these I have included in this letter some account of recent delevop-ments regarding the question, which will, I hope, make clear the attitude which His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom have adopted towards it.I should like at the outset to say that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom entirely accept the view expressed in your speech in London in May 1935 that Section 151 of the South Africa Act, with the Schedule, has a &quot; meaning and intention.&quot; We fully recognise the significance of the Section, and do not seek to minimise it. At the same time the position of the United Kingdom Government is also necessarily governed by the pledges which were given during the passage of the South Africa Bill through the United Kingdom Parliament in 1909, i.e., that transfer should not take place until the wishes of the natives of the Territories had been most carefully considered, and that before such transfer Parliament here should also be given the fullest opportunity of expressing its views.For the purposes of this letter, I do not think it is necessary to go into the past history of this question beyond the agreement which you reached with my predecessor in 1935, which at present governs the situation.In the course of your discussions with him in that year, Mr. J. H. Thomas, then Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, told you that the information available to the Government here indicated that native opinion in the Territories remained strongly opposed to transfer, and that he therefore did not think that the time was ripe for consulting opinion in the Territories with regard to it. You and he then agreed to the policy which was set forth by him on behalf of the United Kingdom Government in the Aide-M^moire of the 15th May. 1935. in the following words :  &quot; The policy of both Governments for the next few years should be directed to bringing about a situation in which, if transfer were to become a matter of practical politics, it could be effected with the full acquiescence of the populations concerned. With this end in view, we feel it important that the closest possible co-operation should be established between the Union Government and the Administrations of the Territories. We realize, of course, that some measure of. co-operation already exists; but we feel that there are many directions in which it could be fruitfully extended. In particular, it appears to us to be an essential condition of the success of such a policy that the native population should feel that the Union Government are working in concert with the local Administrations with a real and generous desire to develop and improve conditions in the Territories.&quot;It has sometimes been^suggested that the United Kingdom Government have failed to play their part in implementing this policy. I should like to recapitulate briefly the steps which the United Kingdom Government have taken to carry it out.   Following immediately on his discussion with you Mr. Thomas
sent a letter to Sir William Clark, the High Commissioner, informing him of the discussion and proposing the lines of action which he and the local Administra-tions in the Territories should adopt for the policy&apos;s achievement. Before that letter was sent it was shown to you, so that there might be an understanding as to the general lines which the local Administrations should adopt. Regarding this. Mr. Thomas wrote in the letter :-&quot; I . . . . promised to, press upon you (the High Commissioner) the desirability of having as comprehensive a scheme of co-operation as possible worked out. I mentioned that T thought it would be very desirable that you should have a further talk with General Hertzog as soon as possible after his return. I added that I was sure that -the right policy, especially in dealing with the chiefs and their followers, was to discourage agitation against joining the Union and concentrate on getting everyone, natives and Europeans alike, to work for the success of such co-operative measures as might be found possible. It seemed to me that this was the best way of creating the right atmosphere.   General Hertzog concurred.&quot;On your return to South Africa, Sir William Clark discussed the matter with you, and subsequently conferred both with the Resident Commissioners of the Territories and with representatives of the Union Government in order to see what co-operative measures were possible. Certain arrangements were made for the extension of the facilities already granted by the Union Government as regards the loan of Union experts on problems affecting the Territories, and other matters.Moreover, when the Union Government generously offered to share the cost of certain important development schemes which we were initiating in the Territories, the High Commissioner, with my approval, accepted the offer on a 50:.50 basis, and the Resident Commissioners were instructed to explain this proposal to the inhabitants of the Territories and to seek their co-operation. Despite the initial opposition of the native authorities, it seemed likely that this co-operation would be secured, when a debate took place, in June 1936, in the Union Parliament, in the course of which things were said which made the natives suspect, quite erroneously, that attached to the Union&apos;s financial offer was some condition regarding the transfer of some or all of the Territories within a set period of years. Although with your concurrence I stated in the House of Commons soon after that there was not and had not at any time been such an agreement, uneasiness regarding the proposal for financial assistance had, unfortunately, been aroused amongst the natives, and in these circumstances you concurred in the abandonment for the time being of the proposal. I very much regretted the breakdown of the policy of co-operation in this very important field. Such a practical example of the Union Government&apos;s readiness to help the populations of the Territories should in time have had a considerable effect in establishing in their minds a more friendly disposition towards the Union, and had the proposals materialised, they might well by now have begun to have that effect.As regards the other suggestions in Mr. Thomas&apos;s letter to the High Commis-sioner, that agitation against joining the Union should be discouraged, I am confident that the High Commissioner and Resident Commissioners have acted in this spirit, as has also the Government here.His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom stand by the policy of bringing about a situation in which, if transfer were to become a matter of practical politics, it could be effected with the full acquiescence of the populations concerned. Parliament here, who are to have the opportunity of considering transfer before it can take place, would not, I feel certain, agree to transfer if after consultation it appeared that such acquiescence could not be secured. The immediate question therefore is what further steps can be taken to give effect to the intentions of the 1935 Agreement.I have given this question careful thought following upon the talks with you and Mr. Havenga, and should like to put to you the following considerations. In the first place, can we do anything more in present circumstances in the way of practical co-operation between the Union Government and the administrations of the Territories in matters of interest and benefit to the inhabitants of the Territories, so that the natives may feel that, in the words of the Aide-Memoire
of 1935, the Union Government are &quot; working in concert with the local adminis-trations with a real and generous desire to develop and improve conditions in the Territories &quot; 1 I appreciate that, in view of the circumstances in which financial co-operation connected with development schemes broke down last year, it is doubtful whether further proposals of this kind could usefully be renewed at present. There are, however, other practical ways in which the Union Govern-ment may be able to show their goodwill towards and readiness to help the Territories, and indeed certain measures such as the loan of technical officers already demonstrate the desire of the Union to assist to this end. I should welcome any further measures of that nature which were practicable, and am asking Sir William Clark to continue in close touch with you and your colleagues and advisers concerning them.Another step which would undoubtedly have the greatest possible favourable influence on opinion in the Territories would be the withdrawal, or relaxation, of the weight and other restrictions (not, of course, including restrictions imposed for purely veterinary reasons) imposed in respect of the entry of cattle from the Territories into the Union. I referred to this in a conversation which I had with Mr. Havenga shortly before he left England, and recognise your difficulties regarding it. But if it were at all possible for the Union Government to give the matter fresh consideration, any further step in that direction could hardly fail to. be regarded by the peoples of the Territories as an act of real goodwill, and it would impress on them the advantages which can be gained from close and friendly relations with the Union authorities.Further, I have been considering whether it would be possible to take steps to remove any misapprehensions which may exist in the local populations&apos; minds, as to their position in the event of transfer. If misunderstandings on this point exist, it is desirable that they should be removed by explanation of the facts, so that there should be a true understanding of the prospects. The question arises, for instance, whether it would not be useful that an outline of the system of administration which the Union would propose to institute based upon the Schedule to the South African Act should be made available to the Native Authorities in the Territories in some simple form, with an indication of how the system would be worked in practice and to what extent, if any, the form of administration to which the natives are now accustomed would be changed as a result of transfer. I know that the Union Government are willing that the principles set out in the Schedule to the South Africa Act should be maintained, and, as you are aware, the United Kingdom Government attach great importance to this. Indeed, they are pledged not to support any proposal for transfer if it involved the impairment of such safeguards for native rights and interests as the Schedule was designed to secure. It would, I think, be helpful if the Union Government could prepare some document on the lines suggested above. Mr. Havenga will remember that in my last talk with him in London regarding the Territories I suggested that this matter should be looked into.The question also arises whether it would be possible in such a document to make available to the Native authorities in the Territories information as to any economic and other advantages which might be expected to result from transfer. Producers in the Territories, Europeans and Natives alike, are largely dependent on the Union market, and on the economic side it would clearly be of importance that they should be aware what would be the position with regard to the marketing of their produce in the Union. It is provided in the Schedule to the South Africa Act that in the event of transfer no differential duties or imposts on the produce of the Territories should be levied. It was then, in fact, contem-plated that after transfer there would be complete freedom of trade between the Territories and the Union of South Africa, subject to veterinary requirements and to the embargo on the sale of intoxicating liquor to natives, and it would seem desirable that the effect of transfer in regard to the present quotas, levies and restrictions, especially in respect of cattle, should be clearly indicated.In the foregoing paragraphs I have referred mainly to natives, but there are also the European inhabitants of the Territories to be considered, especially in Swaziland and the Bechuanaland Protectorate. It would be for consideration whether the document which I.have proposed should not be so drawn as to cover the position of Europeans as well as natives in the event of transfer, so that both sections of the population would be made aware of the prospect.    Or it
might be more convenient for all concerned if the matters affecting the Europeans were dealt with in a separate document.Tt would, no doubt, also be desirable to include in the document or documents mention of the point which Union Ministers have already made known to us through Sir William Clark that the Union Government would be prepared, in the event of transfer, to take over the serving officials in the Territories, including Native officials.I hope that you will agree that the preparation by the Union Government of a document or documents on these points would be useful. The question how best such a document could be made available to the Native Authorities in the Territories would be a matter for further discussion. So far as I am concerned, the object would be, as explained above, to secure a full presentation of the facts.I should, however, mention that there are certain prior points for considera-tion before it would be possible to settle the terms of any such document. In the memorandum which Mr. Thomas handed to General Smuts in July 1933 (which we subsequently published here in the Parliamentary Paper 4948 as an Appendix to the Aide-Memoire of May 1935), it was pointed out that, since the South Africa Act was passed, the Constitutional position had been affected by the passage of the Statute of Westminster, and that there were, in particular, two sections in the Schedule which required special consideration, i.e., Section 20, which states that the King may disallow any law made by the Governor-General in Council by Proclamation for any territory, and Section 25, which provides that all Bills to amend or alter the provisions of the Schedule shall be reserved for the signification of His Majesty&apos;s pleasure. When the South Africa Act was passed, His Majesty would have been advised on such matters after transfer of the Territories by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom. It would be desirable that we should discuss together what form of alternative security for the populations of the Territories on these points could take the place of these provisions. I am ready to discuss this aspect of the problem without delay.I should be glad to receive your observations on the suggestions put forward in this letter, and if you have any other suggestions to make, I shall, of course, be very ready to consider them. I would suggest that the terms of any public announcement as to future policy in regard to this question which it may be possible to make after the present communication between us has been concluded, should be agreed between us. I can assure you that the wish of the United Kingdom-Government is to continue to work in close co-operation with you in this matter, in the hope that it may be settled by friendly agreement in the best interests of all the peoples concerned.APPENDIX B.Draft Letter from General Hertzog to the Secretary of State.Department of External Affairs, Pretoria.1. I AM herewith forwarding my draft reply to your draft letter on the subject of the South African High Commission Territories.2. At one stage it has been suggested that it might be useful if I were to suggest what passages might be omitted from your present draft, and were then to frame my draft reply as an answer to your draft as amended by me.3. Unfortunately, I do not think that this procedure would be sound, for I cannot be certain that the amendments which might be suggested by me to your draft will be acceptable to you, and then my reply would not, so to speak, fit in. Moreover, with regard to the account given by you of the recent developments regarding this question, which commences on page 2 of your draft and concludes on page 7, it is incumbent on me to emphasise that, inasmuch as the undertaking which Mr. Thomas gave me on the 14th May, 1935, viz., that instructions would be given to the officials in the Territories to foster amongst the natives a spirit
of goodwill towards the idea of transfer to the Union, was never carried out, it will become necessary to revise the statement of policy to which I agreed with Mr. Thomas in 1935, unless His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom contemplate taking steps to implement the undertaking given to me by Mr. Thomas.4. As I see it, the fundamental idea underlying your draft letter, as set out in paragraph 2 of page 7, viz., that &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom stand by the policy of bringing about a situation in which, if transfer were to become a matter of practical politics, it could be effected with the full acquiescence of the populations,&quot; becomes fallacious and untenable, because the condition precedent agreed upon between Mr. Thomas and myself has not been fulfilled.5. Similarly. I have grave objections to the second sentence in the same paragraph, viz., &quot; Parliament here, who are to have the opportunity of considering transfer before it can take place, would not, I feel certain, agree to transfer if, after consultation, it appeared that such acquiescence could not be secured.&quot;6. For I have a feeling that you not only somewhat prematurely stress a possibility which may not arise at all, but that, even if it should arise, you overlook the possibility that probably other factors besides the attitude of the inhabitants of the Territories would have to be most carefully considered by the United Kingdom Parliament before arriving at a final decision.7. I am therefore compelled to emphasise that whatever the wording of the undertaking which was originally given to the Parliament at Westminster may be. or whatever its intention ma)&apos; have been, it cannot now be considered appropriate to say what Parliament would or would not do in case the under-taking which was given to Parliament might fail of accomplishment.8. I suggest, therefore, that the better procedure would be if your draft letter were to stand unaltered at this stage and my draft reply were given fully and frankly, as I hereby submit the same.9. At the same time I am forwarding in draft form the documents which you suggest might be prepared in order to inform the natives what form of administration would be applied by the Union and what advantages would result from transfer together with a statement of the disadvantages that would be avoided in future if transfer were not delayed too long.10. I should be failing in my duty if I did not emphasise once more that this question has become a burning one. The impression is gaining ground in the Union that the administrations of the Territories are not serious in their efforts to promote a more friendly spirit amongst the natives towards the idea of transfer. It is felt that if they were, transfer would become a matter of practical politics within a comparatively short time.11&apos;. It is not the wish of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union that anything should be done to jeopardise the friendly relationships which exist between the Union and the United Kingdom. Accordingly I have deemed it fit to set out the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union in detail and candidly. For I feel that it is on this basis only that we shall in the end arrive at useful and profitable results.12. As this question may be raised during the forthcoming session of our Parliament I should appreciate it if you could deal with this matter as soon as you are in a position to/do so with convenience.(Confidential.)Draft Letter from the Prime Minister of the Union of South Africa to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.1. I have read with interest your draft letter on the subject of the transfer of the South African High Commission Territories.2. It is hardly necessary for me to state that I agree whole-heartedly that in this matter there should be the closest contact and understanding between His Majesty VGovernmehtss in the United Kingdom and in the Union of South Africa and would Venture to add that there should also be that complete degree of frankness which is a necessary corollary to genuine confidence and co-operation.
3. It is in this spirit, therefore, that I shall, in the first place, deal with the account which you give of the recent developments regarding this question and which you hope will make clear the attitude wnich His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom have adopted towards it.4. In this connection you refer to the Aide-Memoire of the 15th May, 1935, which purports to embody the policy which Mr. Thomas and I agreed upon at the time.5. Before dealing with the terms of this document in more detail, I desire to state that when I visited Mr. Thomas on the 14th May, 1935, for the purpose of discussing the matter of the Protectorates with him, the document had already been prepared by him.6. I was, however, unaware of this fact. A discussion ensued between Mr. Thomas and myself, in the course of which I emphasised the necessity that the officials in the Territories should be instructed to foster amongst the inhabitants a spirit favourable towards the idea of transfer&apos;, as this seemed to me to be the most important method by which my objective could be attained within a comparatively short period of time. To this Mr. Thomas assented, and, in proof of his agreement with me, produced the document to which I have already referred and read it to me.7. As I had thus obtained from Mr. Thomas an undertaking which seemed to me to be vital to the attainment of my objective, I agreed that &quot; the policy of both Governments for the next few years should be directed to bringing about a situation in which, if transfer were to become a matter of practical politics, it could be effected with the full acquiescence of the populations concerned.&quot;8. Similarly, it is in the light of the same undertaking by Mr. Thomas that the following further statement must be read : &quot; In particular, it appears to us to be an essential condition of such policy that the native population &quot;-should feel that the Union Government are working in concert with the local Administrations with a real and generous desire to develop and improve conditions in the Territories.&quot;9. I desire to state emphatically that it was clearly and definitely under-stood between Mr. Thomas and myself that the most important method by which the &quot; essential condition &quot; of the success of our policy could be achieved was not only that the officials in the Territories should actively discourage agitation against joining the Union, but that they should also be instructed to incidcate in the inhabitants ideas favourable towards transfer.10. This method seemed to me to be a sine qua non in the process of ensuring the &quot; full acquiescence &quot; of the inhabitants concerned.11. It was in the light of this definite understanding between us that I concurred in the letter which Mr. Thomas wrote to Sir William Clark, the High Commissioner, to which you refer in detail on pages 4 and 5 of your draft letter, and in which Mr. Thomas stated that he Avas sure that &quot; the right policy, especially in dealing with the chiefs and their followers, was to discourage agitation against joining the Union and concentrate on getting everyone, Natives and Europeans alike, to work for the success of such co-operative measures as might be found possible. It seemed to me that this was the best way of creating the right atmosphere.   General Hertzog concurred.&quot;12. That this &quot;right policy,to repeat the words of Mr. Thomas, was never fully implemented in the manner agreed upon between Mr. Thomas and myself came to my knowledge comparatively recently, and as a painful surprise to me. You will recall that, in the course of our conversations during the recent Imperial Conference, you admitted to me that no instructions had been or would be issued to British Officials in the Territories to assist in cultivating with the natives under their jurisdiction a spirit favourable to transfer to the Union.13. It is hardly necessary for me to state that, had I anticipated that what was agreed upon between Mr. Thomas and myself to be an &quot; essential condition of the success &apos;&apos; of the policy which we had in mind would never fully be translated into action, I should never have agreed to the use of the phrase &quot;full acquiescence of the populations concerned,&quot; nor, indeed, would I have returned from England in May 1935 with the feeling of satisfaction to which I testified at the time.14. For, as you state on page 2 of your draft letter, during the passage of the South Africa Bill through the United Kingdom Parliament in 1909, no [16675] 1 c
more was undertaken than that transfer should not take place until the wishes of the natives of the Territories had been most carefully considered a proposi-tion which, you will agree, does not necessarily postulate full acquiescence on the part of the inhabitants.15. Be that as it may, I returned from England in May 1935 entirely satisfied in my mind that, if Mr. Thomas&apos;s promise to me were carried out (and I had no reason to believe that this would not happen), the transfer of the Territories would become an accomplished fact within a couple of years.16. I must, therefore, emphasise that inasmuch as the integral part of the policy which was agreed upon between Mr. Thomas and myself has up to the present not been carried out by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, it is surely merely playing with words to suggest that the policy agreed upon between Mr. Thomas and myself has been fully implemented.17. The very essence of the agreement between Mr. Thomas and myself not having been complied with and the &apos;&apos; essential condition of the success &apos;&apos; of the policy which we had in mind not having been car?ied out, how can it seriously be suggested that the United Kingdom Government have fully carried out their part of the policy which was agreed upon between Mr. Thomas and myself ?18. Moreover, if, as you suggest on page 7 of your letter, a serious effort has been made to discourage agitation against joining the Union, I can only record my feeling of regret that these efforts have been so transparently ineffective and barren of positive results.19. In dealing therefore with the suggestions advanced by you and which you consider would assist in practical ways in ensuring the acquiescence of the inhabitants of the High Commission Territories and also the concurrence of the United Kingdom Parliament in the transfer of the Territories in question to the Union, I shall assume that no more is meant by the word &quot; acquiescence &quot; than &quot; goodwill towards the idea of transfer to the Union.&quot;20. Proceeding then on this assumption, I understand your letter to contain the following four main points : In the first place, in order to remove any misapprehensions which may exist in the local populations&apos; minds as to their position in the event of transfer, you suggest the preparation of a document setting forth (a) the system of administration which the Union would propose to instituteand the extent to which, if any, the Union system would differ from the present system;(b) the advantages, economic and other, which might be expected to result to the inhabitants of the Territories from transfer; and(c) the readiness of the Union Government to take over the serving european and Native officials in the Territories.21. In this connection, I should like to say at once that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union of South Africa have never contemplated any other form of administration for the Territories in question than that outlined in the Schedule to the South Africa Act and, apart from the question as to the legal effect of sections 20 and. 25 of the Schedule (which is dealt with by me at a later stage hereof), they likewise do not contemplate a departure from the terms of the said Schedule in future..22. Under section 22 of the Schedule provision is made for the protection of the rights of officers of the public service and, in conformity with the intention-of the said section, the Union Government would be prepared to take over the serving European and Native officials in the Territory.23. I also agree that the preparation of a document on the lines suggested by you.would be a.very useful step indeed, and have already given instructions in this respect.     , .. 24.... With, regard to the point raised by you as to whether a separate document should be made available for Europeans, I feel that, especially in view of the position of Swaziland,- it would be advisable to prepare a further document dealing with the matters more especially affecting the European inhabitants of such territories as are concerned. This document is also in course of preparation, and both documents will be. submitted for your observations in due. course. ;, 25. Perhaps it would be well to indicate here that in the document dealing with the form of administration it would be emphasised that in actual practice,
no change in the existing form of administration will take place, and the only real and substantial change in this respect would be the transfer of the legislative and administrative control at present exercised by His Majesty&apos;s High Commissioner to the Governor-General of the Union.26. In the document the functions of the Commission to be appointed under section 2 of the Schedule would be emphasised.27. I likewise agree that the manner in which the above documents should be made available to the Native Authorities in the Territories would be an appropriate subject for further discussion.28. In this connection the thought occurs to me that at some stage or other, possibly an eai&apos;ly one, or, in any case, at the right moment of time, it might be found important and necessary to give, the inhabitants of the Territories an opportunity of putting such questions or obtaining such further information as they may desire.29. The question whether, in such event, representatives of the Union would be afforded an opportunity of attending pitsos and similar gatherings might become a very vital one, and seems to me to be one which might usefully be borne in mind during all the further stages these discussions may take.30. In the second place, you mention in page 13 of your letter the matter of Sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule to the South Africa Act. You point out that Section 20 states that the King may disallow any law made by the Governor-General in Council by Proclamation for any territory, and that Section 25 provides that all Bills to amend or alter the provisions of the Schedule shall be reserved for the signification of His Majesty&apos;s pleasure. You also mention that when the South Africa Act was passed, His Majesty would have been advised on such matters after transfer of the Territories by His. Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom.31. In this connection you desire that,we should discuss together what form of alternative security for the populations of the Territories on these points could take the place of the above-mentioned provisions of the Schedule, and you emphasise that before it would be possible to settle the terms of the documents mentioned earlier in this letter, this point would have to be considered.32. This aspect of the matter has been very fully considered by His Majesty&apos;.s Government in the Union, for it is bound up very closely not only with the constitutional position of the Union-a matter which is and must always remain of profound importance to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union but also with the fair name of the Government and European population of the Union in relation to their treatment of the native peoples of the Union.33. In the latter regard, it devolves upon me to say that for a very considerable time it has been a matter of profound regret and concern to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union that owing to the prevalence of fundamental misconceptions and tragic ignorance of the real implications of the Union&apos;s policy towards the native peoples of South Africa on the part of a large portion of the electorate and the public Press of the United Kingdom and owing to the systematic dissemination of misleading and prejudiced information by a variety of public bodies and individuals on the same matter both in the United Kingdom and in the Union, there appears to prevail a wholly unjustified view that the inhabitants of the territories in question will not receive fair and equitable treatment from the Union.34. The real fact of the matter is that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union of South Africa and their officials must of necessity have an infinitely better understanding of the natives of South Africa and should likewise be far more capable of dealing with the overwhelming and vital problems occasioned by the presence of a variety of races in South Africa than any other government or body of persons.35. The broad lines of the Union&apos;s Native administrative policy are reflected in the system of government which is applied to the huge native population of the Transkei and it is the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union to continue and extend that system.36. This system coincides in its broad aspects with the system contemplated by the Schedule to the South Africa Act, and as I have already stated, the Union Government intend to adhere to the provisions of the said Schedule.37. I shall now revert to the question raised by you as to what form of alternative security for the populations of the High Commission Territories could take the place of Sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule.[16675] c 2
38. The attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union on this point is the following.39. In the first place, it seems necessary to analyse and determine the true effect that sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule may be considered to have had.40. In this connection it would hardly seem necessary to draw attention to paragraph 22 of the Eeport of the Imperial Conference on the Operation of Dominion Legislation and Merchant Shipping Legislation, 1929, in which it was stated with regard to the right of disallowance by the Crown on the advice of Ministers in the United Kingdom as follows : &quot; This practice did not, however, long survive, for it was realised that under the conditions of self-government the power of disallowance should only be exercised where grave Imperial interests were concerned and that such intervention was improper with regard to legislation of purely domestic concern. In fact the power of disallowance has not been exercised in relation to Canadian legislation since 1873 or to New Zealand legislation since 1867; it has never been exercised in relation to legislation passed by the Parliaments of the Commonwealth of Australia or of the Union of South Africa.&quot;41. Accordingly the Conference agreed that &quot; the present constitutional position is that the power of disallowance can no longer be exercised in relation to Dominion legislation.&quot;42. In only one respect was a reservation made in this connection, viz., the special position in relation to the Colonial Stock Act, 1900.43. It will also be recalled that in paragraph 29 of the said Eeport, the Conference in dealing with the effect of provisions in Dominion Constitutions relating to the reservation of Bills, inter alia, specifically referred to section 25 of the Schedule to the South Africa Act.44. Nevertheless, it was recommended without reservation in paragraph 35 that it was open to those Dominions which desired to abolish provisions in their Constitutions relating to reservation, to do so.&apos;45. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union of South Africa accordingly hold the view that, when regarded in true constitutional perspective, the practical effect of sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule always was and would have been of no importance and, indeed, of negligible value to the inhabitants of the territories in question. Indeed, it was stated in the most explicit terms at the Imperial Conference of 1926, and accepted without question, that the principles contained in the Declaration of 1926 laid clown nothing new in so far as Dominion indepen-dence or freedom was concerned, and that it merely declared the legal position of Dominion freedom as it then already existed and had existed for years. The Statute of Westminster went no further.46. Secondly, regarding it from a purely administrative angle. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union find it difficult to understand how any efficient check or sound judgment could be exercised or formed by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in the United Kingdom in regard to a multiplicity of considerations which would influence the Union Government in coming to a decision upon facts in respect of which no other Government would have a first-hand acquaintance and no real means of forming a sound judgment.47. I am persuaded to think that upon a frank and realistic consideration of the true effect of Sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule, you will agree with me that the only real security upon which the inhabitants of the territories could rely by virtue of, or rather, in spite of, the said sections, would be a security based upon the sense of responsibility towards, and understanding of, the native peoples, which would determine every decision of the Union Government.48. It is my duty to emphasise that it will ever be the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union that their policy and administration relating to the native peoples of South Africa is and must remain a matter &quot; of purely domestic concern &quot; in respect of which it would be inappropriate and even improper, to revive a constitutional theory which never in the Unioris history has had any practical significance &quot;or to attempt to find for it any substitute which might have the semblance of an admission that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union is not completely qualified to fulfil the trust which rests upon them.49. In the third place, you have been good enough to make certain sugges-tions relating to the further extension of practical measures, such as the loan of......tr**?&apos;^\
Union technical officers to the Territories and to the desirability of relaxing the restrictions imposed in respect of the entry of cattle from the Territories into the: Union.50. With regard to the more extended loans of our technical officers and services, it is hardly necessary for me to say that the Union is prepared to do as much as possible in this direction.51. In addition, I would recommend the appointment of a joint advisory committee from among leading officials of the Union Government and the Protectorate Administration to consider and advise upon all necessary improve-ment schemes in the Territories, embracing such economic matters as water conservation and supply, soil erosion, afforestation, stock diseases, roads and transport, trade and so forth. In this way, with the technical and (where required) the financial assistance of the Union Government, surveys and plans of improvement and development could be jointly elaborated by the committee, which might considerably accelerate the rate of progress in the Territories.52. I regret to say, however, that the question of removing or relaxing any restrictions relating to the entry of cattle is a most difficult one and wellnigh impossible of execution, inasmuch as the political repercussions resulting there-from in the Union would be very serious indeed and would much embarrass His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union.53. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union could hope to face the hostility of Union farmers and other difficulties, both economical and political, which: would arise from a relaxation of the present restrictions relating to the entry of cattle, only if such relaxation would follow as a necessary concomitant of actual transfer.54. In other words, Union cattle farmers could be placated in this matter only if the Union Government were placed in a position to use the argument that the relaxation of these restrictions is an exigency arising out of the transfer of the territories, and also the additional argument that, as a result of transfer, the influx of cattle from yet other adjacent territories could be more effectively checked.55. In the fourth place, you are good enough to enquire whether I have any further suggestions to make in connection with this matter.56. Acting on this, I desire to revert once more to a matter which from time to time has caused grave concern and misgivings to His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in the Union, and which has more than once in the past seriously prejudiced the cordial relationships which, on the whole, prevail between His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom and in the Union.57. &apos; I refer to the unfortunate lack of understanding in the United Kingdom of the Union Government&apos;s attitude towards the natives of South Africa and of their sincere desire to ensure a treatment of these people which will at once be fair and just to them (the natives), and at the same time be compatible with the maintenance and preservation of European civilisation in the Union and the whole of South Africa. The agricultural and industrial progress which is proceeding apace in the Union and bringing in its train a multiplicity of new and unforeseen problems, in which both the European and native populations are very vitally concerned, is regarded as a sufficient justification by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union for emphasising the need of finding a method of enlightening and guiding public opinion in the United Kingdom in order to ensure not only a proper understanding of the true constitutional effect of sections 20 and 25 of the Schedule, but also a better appreciation of the Union&apos;s real policy and aims towards the natives in South Africa, and of the stupendous problems which it has to face and solve in this connection.58. If intelligent propaganda seems desirable in the High Commission Territories, it would seem equally desirable that in the United Kingdom the enlightenment of the public mind on a similar or possibly much wider basis should be undertaken. Such a step would be of far-reaching importance, and would-assist still further in ensuring the consolidation of that lasting goodwill between the Union and the United Kingdom for which His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union stand.59. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union would undertake to prepare the necessary literature in this connection, and would further be prepared to send representatives to the United Kingdom to present the cause of the Union, if His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom considered action on such or similar lines desirable.
60. Secondly, under this head, I would suggest the desirability of filling future official vacancies in the Territories after consultation with His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union. I refer to the correspondence which recently passed between us in this connection and would also draw attention to the fact that the post of Resident Commissioner for Bechuanaland, which recently became vacant, has now been filled by the appointment of an official from Nigeria, whereas the vacancy might perhaps have been filled by an official more conversant with South African problems.61. Thirdly, it becomes incumbent upon me to repeat with regret the Union Governments feeling that the efforts of His Majesty&apos;s officials in the Protectorates to discourage the agitation against joining the Union (to which you refer on page 7 of your letter), have so far met with very little success.62. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union feel confident that if every effort were made on the part of officials in the Territories to counteract any attempt to prejudice the minds of the native inhabitants against the Union and actively to do their duty to inculcate friendly feelings on the part of the inhabitants towards the Union and sympathy towards the idea of transfer, positive results would become apparent within a very short time.63. As I have said, it is a matter for regret with the Union Government that, if efforts have actually been made in accordance with the agreement arrived at between Mr. Thomas and myself in 1935 to produce a more friendly disposition on the part of the inhabitants of the Territories, these efforts have been productive of such meagre results.64. I have already referred to the possibility that at some time in the future it may be found necessary to give Union representatives an opportunity of attending pitsos in order to elucidate the Memoranda setting out what the form of administration will be and what advantages to the inhabitants will accrue upon transfer.65. Possibly His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom may be able to suggest a method which would facilitate opportunities for direct contact between the inhabitants of the Territories and Union officials, with a view to creating improved relations between the Union and the Territories.66. In conclusion, I wish once more to emphasise that, in the event of incorporation, the intention of the Schedule to the South Africa Act will be strictly carried out, and this will accordingly also apply in respect of equal trade between the Union and the Territories.67. As a matter of fact, in spite of protestations by Union farmer congresses and organisations for years, the Union Government have, until quite recently, been able to maintain a policy of free trade between the Union and the Territories.68. By the passing of the Marketing Act during the 1936 Parliamentary Session, however, the power of regulating &quot;the marketing of Union agricultural products has been placed in the hands of the Union producers. Boards of Control composed mainly of producers may, under the Act, obtain extensive and far-reaching powers to deal with the Union marketing problems. As is generally known, only the pastoral and agricultural products of the Territories are of any importance. It is conceivable that the representatives of the Union producers on the Boards of Control will not be so sympathetic towards the interests of the Protectorates.69. The Union Government will, in this event, not be able to interfere directly, and it will only be by means of incorporation that the Territories will be assured of equal treatment by the various producers&apos; Boards of &apos; Control. While outside the Union, the Territories must necessarily be looked upon by Union producers as importing countries and treated as such.70. In terms of the Marketing Act, however, Control Boards, which may be established for the different products, may not discriminate between producers in the Union. If, therefore, the Territories were incorporated in the Union, they would receive equal treatment with other areas of the Union.71. In other words, the Territories would be assured of equal trading opportunities in the Union&apos;s markets and no differential treatment would be applied to the Territories.72. - Finally, I agree that a public announcement in due course as to future policy in regard to the matter of transfer, prepared by us jointly, would be advisable.
73. I further cordially agree that close and frank co-operation is the onlv method in which this matter can be settled in the interests of all the peoples concerned.APPENDIX C.Dominions Office, Downing Street, S.W. 1,January 27, 1938.Dear General,THANK you for your letter of the 29th December on the subject of the transfer to the Union of the Government of the South African High Commission Territories. I am glad that you set out your views, as I did in my letter of the 25th September to you, frankly and fully.I do not^ think that we need prolong our correspondence since we have agreed that the discussion should be continued with you by Sir William Clark, and indeed he has already been in touch with you on the subject. I ought, however, to mention as Sir William has, I understand, already explained verbally to you  that it seems clear that you must have derived from your talk with Mr. Thomas in 1935 an impression as to the procedure contemplated in connection with the agreement then reached which is different from that which I get from the relevant documents here. But we have agreed that there is no reason why the divergence of view on this should stand in the way of our reaching agreement as to further practical action. I am glad that you have arranged that memoranda should be prepared for the information of the inhabitants of the Territories, both Native and European, on the lines suggested in my letter of the 25th September, and that your discussions with Sir William Clark are making good progress.With kind regards,Yours sincerely, (Signed) MALCOLM MacDONALD.APPENDIX D.Draft Joint Statement.WE took the opportunity during General Hertzog&apos;s visit to England in May and June last to discuss the situation in regard to the transfer of the Government of the High Commission Territories to the Union, and have since continued our communications on the subject.With regard to the principles involved, His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom entirely accept the view expressed by General Hertzog in a speech in London in May 1935, that Section 151 of the South Africa Act (which deals with the transfer of the Government of the High Commission Territories to the Union) had a meaning and intention.His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom fully recognise the significance of the section and do not seek to minimise it. At the same time the position of the United Kingdom Government is also governed by pledges which were given during the passage of the South Africa Bill through the United Kingdom Parliament in 1909 namely, that the transfer should not take place until the wishes of the natives of the territories had been most carefully, considered, and that before such transfer the fullest opportunity should be given to the United Kingdom Parliament to express its views.Bearing in mind these fundamental conditions, we have been jointly studying what is the best and most practical course to pursue.We have had especially under consideration the progress made with the policy of co-operation adopted two years ago, the aim of which, as set out in the
lfjAide-Memoire of 1935, was to demonstrate to the people of the Territories, that the Union Government are working in concert with the local Administrations with a real and generous desire to develop and improve conditions in the Terri-tories. It seems to us that, putting aside for the moment large financial schemes, there is room for a closer co-operation on lines which have not yet been fully explored. We have therefore agreed to constitute a Standing Joint Advisory Conference consisting of the Secretary for the Native Affairs Department and two other Officers of the Union Government, together with the Resident Commis-sioners of the three High Commission Territories, whose function it will be to study openings for co-operation between the Union Government and the Administration in matters affecting the development of the Territories and to consider any matters of joint concern to the Union and the Territories, such as the marketing of produce, prevention and control of animal diseases, prevention of bubonic plague, &amp;c. The establishment of this Standing Joint Advisory Conference would not, of course, affect the present responsibility of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom for the government of the Territories.It has also seemed to us desirable that the peoples of the Territories should have before them a clear picture of the terms on which transfer of the govern-ment would take place if decided upon. Such terms would naturally follow closery the provisions of the schedule of the South Africa Act, 1909, but it seems to us important that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Union should set them out in a more convenient and more complete form so that the peoples of the Territories may appreciate the conditions under which the Territories wrould be governed, the position in regard to the maintenance of the tribal institutions of the Natives, the economic advantages which the Union Government anticipate would accrue to the peoples of the Territories and any other relevant matters. It has accordingly been arranged that memoranda should be prepared by the Union Government setting forth the terms which they would propose, and that these memoranda should be made available for the information of the Native and European inhabitants of the Territories. We feel that this step will be very helpful in clarifying the whole question.

</content>
</cab>
