<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/178/12 images: 283-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IlIS1 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTi 8C(74) 87 COPY NO31 July 1974CABINETwUNITED KINGDOM CIVIL SERVANTS IN NORTHERN Ireland memorandum by the Lord President of the council. In May I received a deputation from the National Staff Side whorepresent the non-industrial civil servants of the United KingdomGovernment.    The deputation argued strongly for a long-standingclaim (rejected by the previous Administration) for an additionalone week&apos;s annual leave and a special allowance of JU50 a year forall staff serving in Northern Ireland,    The Staff Side said that othergood employers in the Province give their staff additional leave, cashbonuses, or free holidays abroad; that employees of the Governmentare, in virtue of their employment, subject to more stress and straintlian the generality of people in Ulster; and that morale is at a low ebb^because the Government has failed to concede extra annual leave and a cash allowance in recognition of the difficult circumstances in whichemployees have to live and work.    There are some 4, 000 non-industrial civil servants of the United Kingdom Departments serving in Ulster and about 5, 000 industrial civil servants.    The National Staff Side speak only for the former, but it would be right and necessary to give to industrialswhatever is granted to non-industrials.    There are also some 30, 000 staffof the Northern Ireland Civil Service who, I think, would also have to benefit from whatever may be conceded to United Kingdom&apos; civijL servants.2.        I am impressed by the Staff Side arguments and concluded that theGovernments relations with its staff are such that we should make a concession.   I therefore proposed to some of my colleagues that in thecurrent year all full-time non-industrial civil servants of the UnitedKingdom Government should be granted an ex^ra week&apos;s leave and an exgratia payment of  100,    The notional cost of the leave would be about 350, 000, and of the cash payment about  900, 000.    I would justify sucha concession publicly on the grounds that United Kingdom civil servants inNorthern Ireland suffer hardships not experienced by their counterparts in britain.3.        The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland is strongly opposed tomy proposal on grounds of the financial and economic effects of itsrepercussions.   He does not believe that United Kingdom civil servants,
taken as a whole, are a category which are suffering most and he considersthat any concessions to civil servants could not defensibly be refused to allemployees of the public sector (some 110, 000 in total), and that claims would follow across the private sector.4,        I see the force of these arguments but they have to be weighed against the Governments responsibilities towards its employees, thefact that the staff have loyally carried on under difficult circumstances,their feeling that the difficulties confronting them need tangible recognition,and the possibility of industrial action.    Many firms in the Province havemade concessions to their staff, and unless the Government takes some action, we cannot claim to be a good employer.5.        Apart from the general National Staff Side claim there is a departmental claim on the Customs and Excise- Department for an allowance of  300 a year for the 200 or so staff employed at the landboundary posts.    These staff are particularly exposed to the risk of armed incident and have to work in primitive and uncomfortable conditions.Indeed it is perhaps for consideration whether we should continue to expectcivilians to carry out these tasks.   If something special were to be conceded to them it would be virtually impossible to define the circum-stances in such a way that other staff in both the United Kingdom andNorthern Ireland services could not justifiably claim that their circum-stances merited similar special treatment.    If a general concession onthe lines indicated above could be made, I propose the rejection of aspecial concession to the land boundary men.5V -6,v\       I invite my colleagues to consider whether the potentialrepercussions of concessions to United Kingdom civil servants/on the lines of my proposal should be accepted.E S1Privy Council Office31 July 1974


</content>
</cab>
