<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/87/5 images: 48-60</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



CABINET

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet

held at 10 Downing Street on

THURSDAY 22 OCTOBER 1987

at 10.00 am

PRESENT

The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP

Prime Minister

The Rt Hon Viscount Whitelaw

Lord President of the CouncilU V

The Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP ^C^f/Si

Chancellor of the Exchequer /^/a

The Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP J/y^s

Secretary of State for the Home Departm^^/^

The Rt Hon George Younger MP S

Secretary of State for Defence v!

The Rt Hon Tom King MP

Secretary of State for Northern Ireland

The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker MP

Secretary of State for Education and

Science

The Rt Hon John MacGregor MP

Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food

The Rt Hon Paul Channon MP

Secretary of State for Transport

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP

Lord Privy Seal

The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MP

Secretary of State for Foreign and

Commonwealth Affairs

The Rt Hon Lord Havers

Lord Chancellor

The Rt Hon Peter Walker MP

^Secretary of State for Wales

^Tlvk Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP

^^p^etary of State for Employment

ViU/^Aovi Nicholas Ridley MP

Secr  axy of State for the Environment

The R&lt; ^tpSr&gt;Kenneth Clarke QC MP

Chancel^^ojf the Duchy of Lancaster

The Rt Hon Malcolm Rifkind QC MP

Secretary of State for Scotland

The Rt Hon Johnntfoo^e MP

Secretary of St b^/p r\ Social Services

The Rt Hon Cecil PH3e#foon MP

Secretary of State ferrVRri^rgy

The Rt Hon John Major MP

Chief Secretary, Treasury

ALSO PRESENT

The Rt Hon David Waddington QC MP

Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury


SECRETARIAT

Sir Robert Armstrong

Mr C L G Mallaby (Items 3 and 4)

Mr R G Lavelle (Items 3 and 4)

Mr A J Langdon (Items 1 and 2)

Mr S S Mundy (Items 1 and 2)

CONTENTS

Subject

Item			Page

1.	PARLIAMENTAfH^AFFAIRS Autumn Statement		1 1

2.	HOME AFFAIRS //^\\ Share Prices ^^^^^) Storm Damage in SoTfl^Wn and Eastern England Flooding in Wales ^^^^^ Flooding in Northern Ire3^^^^ Prisons Social Security Announcements&apos;^/IsS		1 2 4 4 5 5

3.	FOREIGN AFFAIRS &lt;^/&gt;\		

	Iran/Iraq War and the Threat to Shiwp I^in the	Persian Gulf	5

	Nuclear Arms Control		6

	Japan		6

	Belgium /		6

	Sri Lanka V		6

	Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting		7

	United States of America Trident Nuclear Submarine Programme		8 8

4. 1 |	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS Future Financing 1 Agriculture I ii		k


AFFAIRS &lt;^^\

1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House

of Commons in the following week.

Autumn

Statement

^m^VRIME MINISTER said that all outstanding programmes had now been

^^tfceM in that year&apos;s Public Expenditure Survey.    The way was therefore

cl^frer the Cabinet to consider the outcome and for the preparation of

the Jw p Statement.    In the previous year Ministers&apos; effective

presa^J^tfWons of their programmes at the time of the Autumn Statement

had beeyn/a^key factor in the success of the public expenditure exercise.

It was ^s^ential that Ministers should mount a similarly well prepared

operation^that year.    Equally, it was most important that Ministers

should prevent any leakage of information about the Government&apos;s public

expenditure decisions before they were formally announced. This

requirement wa^gT^en special importance by the current British

Petroleum flotk^ios^^ It was essential that nothing which might have or

be thought to ha^e/SNhaterial bearing on the offer should be said by the

Government until \a\fJ^eV/&lt;hat time.

The Cabinet - /^^\

Took note.

HOME AFFAIRS

Share Prices

2.      THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXqjK# A said that in recent days share

prices throughout the world had qrfflya dramatically.    The collapse had

begun on Wall Street, and had been^rf&amp;kly followed in other countries.

On the London stock market, prices had/fallen by 22 per cent between

Thursday 15 October and Tuesday 20 WMrdEZb, before rallying by the close

of business the previous night to a levVtV/Wi per cent below that of

Thursday 15 October.    Similar falls ha V&quot;peen experienced elsewhere in

the world.    What was striking was not so^much the magnitude of these

corrections, which had been expected by many observers for some time,

but their rapidity.    The initial crash in Wall Street appeared to have

been precipitated by three main factors -

i. There had been a long running bull nuncJy^^bich could not be

sustained indefinitely. \v_&gt;/y&gt;\

ii. There was a growing lack of confidence in^tftp^&amp;aited States

economy where the budget deficit was not being r^jfjja^X sufficiently

quickly and very poor trade figures had been pubrisn*d^the previous

iii. The United States Secretary of the Treasury haa^v^*3^ nwisely

stated the previous weekend that if West Germany did nc*^Tprevent

interest rates from rising, he would be content to see ttre^feftue of

the dollar fall.    When the figures for the United States b\J*pgV\

deficit for the fiscal year ending on 30 September were publis^Je^


they were likely to show a reduction in the deficit of some $60

billion; but this would still leave a deficit of some $160 billion

&gt; which was far too high.    It was clear that an increase in taxation

/\\ to reduce the deficit was the single most important step which

could be taken to restore confidence;  there were some indications

that the President of the United States might now be prepared to

Avyv    move in that direction.

Dc^e^tically,  the slump in share prices was bound to dampen ecoaomic

acti^4k\y.    Unless, however, confidence in the United States economy

co%la ^ d so markedly that it went into recession,  there were no grounds

forvrajj^rn about the British economy which remained very strong. The

fallTwosh^re prices should be kept in perspective:    as things stood the

eventsv^f/the previous few days had done no more than return share

prices cX the levels which had obtained six months earlier.    The Bank of

England was keeping a very close eye on British banking and finance

companies, and were satisfied that there was no reason for alarm.

It was unfortuVata)that the fall in share prices had coincided with the

offer period r&gt;or\ J3ftarnment shares in British Petroleum.    Unless the

Stock Market were( to)recover by the close of the offer period on

Wednesday 28 OctoWjJr^zt was unlikely that the offer would contribute

towards the Governmen^^^objective of widening share ownership.

However,  the offer bf&amp;^^e^x fully underwritten on satisfactory terms

before the Stock Markerx^c Wapse had begun.    There was no truth in

reports in the media tha^3ro^Government was considering extending the

offer period. \S J)

The Cabinet - ^^^)

1.      Took note.

Storm Damage

in Southern

and Eastern

England

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRO^K^? said that hurricane force

winds in the early hours of Friday 16 yctober had caused devastation in

Southern and Eastern England.    There haa been widespread damage to

property and trees, roads and rail lines had been blocked, and

electricity and telephone lines had been brough-t.down on a massive

scale.    Much of the damage had been caused byvfa^ling trees.    Most of

the damage had been suffered by private indiv^4ua**&gt;, a great majority of

whom were protected by insurance.    He had alreawy amnounced that the

existing financial arrangements to assist local^u&amp;po^ities in

emergencies - known as the Bellwin Scheme - would&lt;&amp;^^ ailable in the

areas affected for the purpose of emergency work to^p^oaXr the storm

damage.    Under this scheme,  local authorities were rw^^n^ible for the

first tranche of expenditure and he had set the threshoirjK^jr this at

expenditure equivalent to the product of an exclusive p&amp;anyjjate for

county councils and of 0.15 p for shire districts and the^^^jLValents

for London authorities.    The Government would meet 75 per ^Y^t^f

expenditure incurred over and above the threshold.    As to cfayyyah.

expenditure, prudent local authorities would have insured agal^/M^^.


damage of the kind which had been experienced.    But those which had not

\ done so would no doubt demand that the Government made resources

XV/ailable to them.    The question whether such demands should be met

Aa^uld need to be addressed in due course.    Resources were being provided

&gt;s% f the planting of trees to replace those which had fallen, with

v^ytfa^Lal help being given to Kew Gardens, Wakehurst Place and the Royal

THE &lt; J&gt; |eJARY OF state FOR ENERGY said that about 7 million electricity

consufSflrfJyhad been cut off immediately following the storm,  5i million

of whomAajPbeen reconnected within 24 hours.    About 124,000 consumers

were stO^i without electricity and it was hoped that the vast majority

of these would be reconnected by the following evening.    Engineers had

been brought in from other areas, trebling the normal workforce. An

enormous effort had been made to repair the damage, but work had been

hampered by coji^fhJiing bad weather.    Area boards had sought to keep in

touch with comm^rVies which remained without electricity and were

giving priority~yy&apos;Th\se who were most vulnerable.    Most area boards had

insured against emejp&amp;Artpies of this nature and would be able to absorb

most of the costs ^y^fpO^A&apos;    There was no question of any immediate rise

in electricity prices//x^\

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOJJ^KFENCE said that the Meteorological Office

were very concerned abou^^Kevylamage to their credibility caused by

their failure to predict N^e^fjjil severity of the storm.    He had asked

for a full report from the jJrjQ&amp;ipr General of the Meteorological Office

and had invited Sir Peter Swnar^rfton-Dyer, the Chairman of the

University Grants Committee, a&amp;dyPy&amp;fessor Robert Pearce, the Head of

the Department of Meteorology a/^ReOTing University, to consider the

findings of the report when they w e*vjyailable and to report their

conclusions to him.

In discussion the following main poi^^^^^^e made -

a. Local authorities&apos; expenditure^up to the threshold would count

as part of their total expenditure and would be subject to grant

abatement in the normal way.    This had attracted criticism. But

prudent authorities could be expected to b^5ZS.made contingency

allowances in their budgets for this kinafof( vent.

b. In providing assistance to deal with emergencies, it was vital

for the Government to strike a proper balance-^*ween, on the one

hand, avoiding accusations of parsimony and, OT^Ar^other hand,

being exploited by local authorities seeking Got^wfiMt funds for

projects going beyond emergency repairs. ^^^^

c. If more than one emergency covered by the Bell^imSyheme were

to occur in a single financial year, it would not be str^Srniable to

expect local authorities to meet the first tranche of My^ynJ&amp;ture

on each occasion.    Instead, once local authorities had  ^^f/jW to

I the threshold during the course of a financial year, expena*^f1rte

above that limit on emergency work covered by the Bellwin Sxhertje^

should not attract grant penalties.


THE PRIME MINISTER,  summing up the discussion, said the Cabinet

recognised the efforts which were being made to restore services

following the damage caused by the very high winds in Southern England

.   the previous Friday.    They agreed that the Government should make clear

J that, where in the course of a single financial year a local authority

?^ftad spent up to the threshold under the Bellwin rules, expenditure in

^^remnection with any further emergencies falling within the scheme during

V/aa same financial year should not attract grant penalties.    It was

^Mwjjratant that local authorities&apos;  claims for Government grants should be

pWocPjjNied with all possible urgency.    The Government had been generous

in^makj^Vg financial assistance available to help repair the damage and

had &lt;^ o &lt;J story to tell.

Tl(Z- &lt;rbinet -

2.  ^Invited the Secretary of State for the Environment to be

guided by the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of the discussion.

Flooding in

Wales

THE SECRETARY OF x^gu^FOR WALES said that exceptionally heavy rainfall

over the previous w^e^ejaj^ had resulted in extensive flooding over a

large part of South-Wg^^&amp;ales and localised flooding in North Wales.

He had already announ^Q^tVat Government assistance would be made

available to local authoj^&amp;^fes in accordance with the Bellwin Scheme.

There had been a train gw&amp;aent at Glanrhyd, which had resulted in the

loss of four lives.    ThisN^rjip^Xed to have been caused by the collapse

of a bridge whose foundatiorf^v&gt;iad been undermined by flood water. There

had been reports in the mediS^,LHar British Rail had failed to pass on

flood warnings to the areas wrn&lt;m/ ^oo&amp; to be affected.    If this were

true,  it would be an appalling 4*^oe\ The collapse of the bridge had

led to widespread concern about tfye&lt;cosdition of other bridges, with

local authorites complaining that tK^^had not been able to maintain

their bridges adequately because orvkr^rof resources.

Flooding in

Northern

Ireland

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said that exceptionally

heavy rain over the previous 36 hours had pro/yic&quot;eyi the worst flooding in

Northern Ireland since records had been kept.\VTms-~situation had been

particularly bad in the west of the Province.    ytt ~}jain had now abated,

and the floods had begun to diminish.    The secuA^^O^Arces had done a

magnificent job in helping those worst affected; s^jrae^he flooding was

concentrated in predominantly nationalist areas,  th  / Khuld help to

improve their relations with the minority community. &lt;y/\\V.

The Cabinet - ^/)\

3.      Took note.


previous \^

Reference: /

CC(87) 28.2 \

THE HOME SECRETARY reported on the current problems in the London

I prisons.    The discussion is recorded separately.

Social

Security

Announcements

THE S^^SaRY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES said that he would be making

a stat^raep^on the following Tuesday announcing the level of the annual

upratin^pf social security benefits and also announcing details about

the starring levels for a number of the new arrangements flowing from

the social security review and enacted in the Social Security Act 1986.

Among the controversial points in his announcement would be the

decisions on cl^WNbenef it, the uprating of the previously published

illustrative mlgur^s of the income-related benefits, and the budget for

the Social Fund^^ATMments about assistance for the disabled could also

be expected when \Aji / f&gt;ntents of his announcement had been digested.

The Government couT^^yoduce strong arguments to support all the

decisions.    He would ip%f  icularly wish to point to the effectiveness of

family credit as a me^^^O^ targeting help on poor families in work, and

to the extent to which the^&amp;at majority of disabled people would gain

under the new arrangemen^^^e would ensure that his colleagues were

provided with full briefibX &gt;XAa

The Cabinet -

4.     Took note.

FOREIGN

AFFAIRS

Iran/Iraq War

and the

Threat to

Shipping in

the Persian

Gulf

Previous

Reference:

CC(87) 28.4

3.      THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECR^MP^RY said that the Government had

been supporting the efforts of the UnitfitfL Nations Secretary General,

Mr Perez de Cuellar, to obtain the implementation of Security Council

Resolution 598 on cessation of hostilities between Iran and Iraq. The

Government would also maintain the pressure foP^2Qv arms embargo as a

means of enforcing that Resolution.    The Sovi/^Uiyon continued to delay

work by the permanent members of the Security iSokifjSkK on an enforcement

Resolution.    The Soviet Union was promoting the lmpraiticable idea of a

United Nations naval force in the Gulf.    The chancers* progress on the

basis of Resolution 598 were not good.    The war mig%y%^tinue for a

considerable time. ^s\X\

The United States had responded to an Iranian missile at^Jafrt^Bn a

Kuwaiti tanker carrying the United States flag by attackMSoH

19 October an Iranian oil platform on which military equipmejK^^ad been

installed.    This had been widely recognised as a restrained\g(ex)cjjLon.

The next Iranian action could not be predicted; it might be

terrorism or an attack on United States forces in the Gulf.    It /tterfx

become increasingly difficult for the United States to respond

Iranian actions in ways which would be both restrained and ef fectWe^X?


The situation in the Gulf was more tense than ever before, and future

developments were unpredictable.

Nuclear ArnfeT

Control

Previous

Reference

CC(87) 8.3

FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the United States

^Wcxetary of State, Mr George Shultz, was in Moscow discussing nuclear

/*prfs\control and other matters with the Soviet Foreign Minister,

Mi^E^h^flrd Shevardnadze.    Detailed talks between the United States and

the &amp;mriet Union had not made as much progress on the outstanding

asp^ -s^5f an agreement on intermediate range nuclear forces as had been

hopecOoylJu-t there seemed to be no insuperable problems.    It still seemed

probat&amp;ev^nat the date for a United States/Soviet summit meeting would

be set       the near future;  that meeting might now be in December 1987 or

even January 1988, rather than in November as had earlier been

envisaged.

Japan

Previous

Reference:

CC(87) 12.3

THE FOREIGN AND ob^^5JWEALTH SECRETARY said that the outgoing Prime

Minister of Japan,M^*Vjf^suhiro Nakasone, had designated Mr Noboru

Takeshita to be his vs^^eXsor,  the three candidates for the position

having been unable to^agjree\ on which of them should have it.

Mr Takeshita was a forme^/F^ance Minister.    He was undramatic in style,

but shrewd and an effect^^e ijblitical operator.    He was expected to

follow the policies of MrNiJ^K^^ne.

Belgium

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECtifcw&amp;P said that the coalition

Government of Belgium led by Mr Wid^ ijrd Martens, consisting of the

Flemish and French speaking Christv^S^^emocratic and the Flemish and

French speaking Liberal Parties, had (A&amp;tgned on 19 October. The

principal reason was a long-standing dispute about language matters.

There was also an underlying argument aoout economic management in

Belgium.    A transitional Government, led by Mr Martens and consisting of

the same parties, had been established and miah-t. last some time, until

elections were held. U~l)

Sri Lanka

Previous

Reference:

CC(87) 27.2

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that th^J^kil Tigers&quot;

guerrilla organisation had launched an offensive des^gn^aj^o destroy the

agreement between Sri Lanka and India on the restoratip*J/j f\peace

between the communities in Sri Lanka.    Massacres by the^Tcunil Tigers had

left 200 dead and had caused 10,000 people to flee their\tt jte&amp;. The

President of Sri Lanka, Mr Julius Jayewardene, and the Ind^Tl^p\ace-

keeping force had responded very firmly.    Over 100 Indian rcaej s/ had

been killed and 300 injured.    The agreement between Sri Lanka^^rtJ^ruiia


was the best hope of ending the trouble and the Government would

continue to support it.

Commonwealth

Heads of

Government

Meeting

[ME MINISTER said that the Commonwealth Heads of Government

Mes inV.in Vancouver from 13 to 17 October had passed off on predictable

lines^&apos;The two major issues had been Fiji and South Africa.

There^^^JJfeen a tendency among some members of the Commonwealth to

claim t *t the situation in Fiji was akin to that in South Africa.

Others na}J argued that the situation in Fiji was a new one, that it was

still fluid and that the Commonwealth should not react hastily.    It had

been pointed out that, when the political system in Grenada had been

radically chang 3-^Sut that territory had not become a republic, the

question of CoraWinvealth membership had not arisen.    The reason why

there was now aSr^CrS^ about Fiji was that the Governor-General had

resigned and the W^y/jzjw had become a republic.    She and the Foreign and

Commonwealth SecreT^J  /iad worked to keep open the possibility that

Fiji, although its Caroajjyjwealth membership had lapsed with its change of

status, could re turn S^^Ktr^ Commonwealth if it applied to do so as a

republic.    The Prime MinH^w: of India, Mr Rajiv Gandhi, had been

willing to leave the que^^J^nyppen in this way.    With the lapsing of its

membership of the Commonw^i^tfj/AFiji would lose some development aid,

but the United Kingdom shoupKX^ofar as possible continue to provide

aid, which Fiji would badlyNfee^L/^

The African members of the CommmTpe&apos;awh which in 1986 had declared their

intention to introduce sanctions ag^r^st South Africa had not done so,

for the good reason that the effecxs&gt;^jr the Front Line States would be

catastrophic.    These countries had v a&lt;fi&amp;d at Vancouver by trying to

press others (and in particular BritawrVtA introduce more sanctions.

But many people within South Africa wrte^^a been working for years

against apartheid believed that a healtr\ economy there was the best

mechanism for bringing more power to the blacks.    She had made clear

that the existing British sanctions against South Africa, which were

designed to send a political signal, would staY/^JQiv place, but that they

would not be extended.    She had suggested thatf/Bryish aid for the

education of blacks in South Africa and aid tovOj^EJv&gt;nt Line States

should be mentioned in the communique&quot; on the Heafls ojc) Government

meeting; but this had not been agreed.    Some sma FteHj^mffmbe r s of the

Commonwealth had made clear privately to the BritisyfyQjjd^gation that

they were grateful for British aid but had been unwiQ^fgfVto speak up on

the matter during meetings of the conference.    There ftacrOb^Pejn some

ill-tempered incidents in the margins of the conference^/Jjphers had

been highly critical, in speaking to the press, about theytfJniA^ed Kingdom

and the Prime Minister herself.    The Canadian delegation lva^n &lt;Swbeen

pleased when the British delegation had pointed out that CaMc^&apos;jp^trade

with South Africa had increased in 1986, according to the larVs^/igures

available from the International Monetary Fund.    During the disM^mn,

the Front Line States had at least admitted for the first time tftatAxgy

were not in a position to undertake significant sanctions againstvifou^^


Africa and had recognised that change in South Africa would have to come

|\ from within.    Overall, the discussion of South Africa at the

^Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting had not been as difficult as at

- Xroe previous meeting in 1985 or at the meeting in London in 1986 of the

0 k*|3ds of Government of seven Commonwealth countries.

yj-&apos;arsXHission of Fiji,  it was noted that India might seek to obstruct

any^apM^ication by the republic of Fiji for resumed membership of

the CkJjHmonwealth, unless arrangements were made which in the Indian

GoveSjflS^fr&apos; s view should enable the Indian community in Fiji to

particubap^properly in politics.    New Zealand had introduced sanctions

against ^nj i, but Australia was showing restraint.    There had been no

move to reduce the United Kingdom&apos;s development aid, although some of

the personnel who had been working in Fiji as part of the British aid

programme were no longer there.    The situation in Fiji was reasonably

calm for the t^e-^&gt;^ing.

United States

of America

THE SECRETARY OF STA^^J^jkNORTHERN IRELAND said that, during his visit

earlier that month to^p^Tl^ited States, he had held meetings with the

Chairmen of the Boeing Corporation, General Motors Company and the Ford

Company.    The Chairman o ^B *flsVal Motors had told him that its

performance in 1987 wouldNag^XAjier ior to that of Ford;  this was the

first time that this had happ^rt ^    The Chairman had said that one for

reason was that Ford had inv^^redxtaore in the United Kingdom than

***** ^IL^

General Motors, while General Mqjt^svtad invested more in the Federal

Republic of Germany. The Chairman^aiil that General Motors needed to

invest more in Britain. Ss&apos;

Trident

Nuclear

Submarine

Programme

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that there was no truth in

stories in the press that day which alleged that the missiles for the

United Kingdom Trident submarines would be lea&amp;&lt;rjfc&gt; rom the United

States.    The United Kingdom was purchasing thejraiis^iles from the United

States at a cost of  1 billion.    The warheads Vc2yM^&gt;e permanently in

British hands.    As regards the missiles, there hi^Wdn no change in the

arrangements announced in 1982.    After some seven^y-e  sr in service each

missile would go for refurbishment to the United StVtyf^^nd would be

replaced; the same number of missiles would always bev^tvB\itish

ownership. v y\

The Cabinet - \&lt;

Took note.


COMMUNITY^

AFFAIRS &lt;^

 Future

Financing

4.      THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the meeting on

i 19-20 October of the Foreign Affairs Council had been mainly devoted to

long discussion of future financing.    A positive feature was that the

tfjSmmission was maintaining a robust position on stabilisers:    the French

^^&quot;fte also looking for their adoption for all commodities.    Elsewhere the

^MAJAh Chairman had shown an unhelpful disposition in some cases to look

^^Mmpromises between alternatives put forward by the Commission or

merab^f&quot;^ountries, neither of which would be acceptable to the United

KingderfjJr   The prospects for a conclusion at the December European

Coune^K*8mained in doubt, but the right problems were being addressed

and th^^j^rnment should keep up the pressure for one.

Agriculture

THE MINISTER OF/^5HI CULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that the

Agriculture Council/on 19-20 October had considered stabilisers for

individual comm 3^*e^Sy.    There was still a long way to go and he had

stressed the need{(foj7/urgent progress.    He had made clear that the

European Council wtwl^oe looking for specific mechanisms and that

agreement on frameworlt/^TOuld not suffice.    He would be meeting the

Danish Presidency befOT^rfWe next meeting of the Agriculture Council on

16-17 November, which was^LAely to be a protracted one. The

Agriculture Council had ^^^cons idered the Commission&apos;s proposals for

income aids.    These had a^raJied a wide range of critical comment from

most member countries and atr^p^^ent the likelihood of early agreement

here appeared small. ^^/^7

Cabinet Office

22 October 1987


THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

COPY NO

CABINET

LIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEX

CC(87) 29th Conclusions, Minute 2

Thursday 22 October 1987 at 10.00 am

&gt;risons:

Industrial

iction

 revious

tef erence:

!C(87) 28.2

THE HOME SECREl^Y^&amp;id that more than half the prisons in England and

Wales had now mo\/ad dn to the Fresh Start working and pay arrangements

on which the propNiE^urfJhgement of the prisons depended, but that a

bitter rearguard acviwO^ainst Fresh Start was being fought by the

staff at a few estab](j^l^Qts including Wandsworth and two of the other

big London prisons.    wfe\p iion took the form of refusing to accept

prisoners above a prisonl^/^rtified normal accommodation and there were

now some 1,300 prisoners ^futlnely being held in police cells around the

country.    This representedva^aftger ous diversion of police manpower and

would mean that it would be^ew^lifficult to cope with any major

problem of public order that^jw^jjvy arise.    The Prison Officers&apos;

Association (POA) was a divideMyl^WSn whose national executive committee

had little control over local bRafich A. a few of whom were capable of

creating disproportionate disrupt^fi^ajd of prolonging irresponsible

activity indefinitely since their m^J&amp;er^s did not lose pay thereby. The

Wandsworth staff had,  for example, feS^^iaintaining their action since

the end of July.    The Ministerial Steerolp^Committee on Home and Social

Affairs (H) had earlier that week agreetd^with his proposals that he

should forthwith put the staff on notice^that officers who refused to

accept prisoners at their establishments would be suspended from duty,

and he believed that the situation demanded that he should now take this

step.    Despite the POA&apos;s fragmentation, he wasj^eSsV conscious of the

risks of escalation and he would do everythingA$ps^g_ible to ensure that

the matter was dealt with on a localised basis, WVfKVVhe Government&apos;s

action being seen to be focused exclusively on pR^s^p^\such as

Wandsworth where the staff were behaving quite unaq&lt; ^fably. In

furtherance of that approach, he did not for the presre^^bropose to take

action towards the suspension of facilities for the c^i&amp;c&apos;Oion of POA

subscriptions from pay at source, which H had agreed.    The^xpantingency

plans for prison emergencies had been much improved sinc^^^KeNyncidents

in the previous year and the police, on whom the initial a^n^Zfiteent

burden would fall, would prefer to see the contingency plana^a^^j/ated

rather than to endure the indefinite diversion of police stavfH^Othe

oversight of prisoners in police cells.    If assistance was neoje^&amp;^^fr

beyond1 what the police could provide,  there were back-up arrangej e&apos;nip6\

involving the Armed Forces.    Looking further ahead, he thought it^Xj^N

increasingly clear that a no-disruption arrangement would need to ^P^^^.


imposed on the POA at the appropriate time, though he accepted the view

^ of his H colleagues that this matter should be handled delicately in the

/?meantime.    The immediate question was whether he should proceed towards

&lt;\0^e suspension from duty of staff who were failing to work properly the

^j^rf^lowing week, and he sought the Cabinet&apos;s agreement to his taking that

THIS^ORR PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that H had unanimously agreed

that/^re POA could not be allowed to sabotage the Fresh Start

arraifewirtMts.    The London prisons were, however, a special problem. Not

only wac/^^ey very large establishments under the gaze of the media,

but the^r-^staff had a long history of contumacious behaviour. He

believed^hat it would be dangerous to provoke confrontation with all

the London prisons at the same time, since there must be some doubt

whether the police could cope with that situation.    He greatly welcomed

the Home Secre&amp;fiJ^^ks assurance that the dispute would be handled in a

localised fashfeton,Visolating individual establishments so far as

possible.

THE PRIME MINISTERT^&amp;jmning up a short discussion, said that the

disputes at issue wer/^x&amp;a 1 ones.    The Cabinet agreed that the Home

Secretary should movey?MOTds suspending from duty those prison officers

who were refusing to accejj^^irisoners at their establishments the

following week.    The Hom^ ^v&lt; etary should further discuss the

contingency arrangements ^^r^cfelling on the Armed Forces with the

Secretary of State for Defen^^VsThe Cabinet would wish in due course to

return to the question of ncVdi^p totion arrangements for the POA.

The Cabinet - l^&gt;\

Invited the Home Secretary topjxj eed as the Prime

Minister had indicated in her ^majiStg UP  ^ tne discussion.

X

Cabinet Office

22 October 1987 (^^)



</content>
</cab>
