<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/199/15 images: 440-452</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DoCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(78) 15COPY NO     o a6 February 1978 - .    &quot;&quot;CABINETNORTH SEA DEVELOPMENT FUNDNote by the Secretary of the CabinetI was instructed to arrange for the preparation of a note showing how aNorth Sea Oil Development Fund could be operated assuming ministers decided that there should be one.    I now attach a note prepared by officials of the Treasury, the Scottish Office and the Cabinet Office.Signed JOHN hunt cabinet Office6 February 1978
NORTH SEA DEVELOPMENT FUNDNote by officials at its discussion of the draft White Paper on the Benefits of North SeaQil, on 26 January, tho Cabinet agreed that a note should be prepared to show how a North Sea Development Fund night be operated, and to examine any&quot;technical problems.   This noto has accordingly boon produced by officials in&quot;the Departments mainly concerned (Cabinet Office^ Treasury, Scottish Office),drawing on the discussion in the earlier paper circulated to DVY Committee inOctobor as DVY(77) 16,     The note docs not arguo tho merits, but outlines some alternative possible forms of Fund,2*    Ministers will wish to consider two questions, which this paper attempts to clarify -i. Should tho Fund be wprosentational&quot; (ie simply a matter of bookkeeping, with North Sea revenues notionally hypothecated against selectedexpenditure programmes in toto);    or should it be wadditional&quot;(ie purporting to show additional expenditure made possible by North Seaoil)?ii. Should the Fund be 1 c ompr oh en s i vc1 (ie including all or most of theNorth Sea rovenues) or should it be tselective1 (ic confined to a specificsum, oarmarked out of tho totality of revenues).   In the rest of this paper those options are called the 1largo&apos; and 1snail1 funds,^gdo are not questions which can bo settled without consideration of theteohnical merits.r*    This paper accordingly examines three possible forms of Fund - large/Presentational; large/additional; and small/additional,   A small Fund which^ad no real effect and was purely presentation would seem to have no advantages,is not discussed further.
4*     If a Fund covered mattors to bo devolved under the Scotland and WalesBills, there could be difficulties in the relationship between the Fund andthe blook funds to be paid to the devolved administrations.   Ordinarily, &quot;thoseadministrations will determine the pattern of devolved spending; but theywould not havo this freed on if Fund payments wore earmarked for specificpurposes.A. LARGE/PRESENTATIONAL(i) Objeotivo5o     The objective is to be able to show that the North Soa revenue is beifl spent in accordance with the priorities which are to be set out in the government&apos;s White Paper.   This is &quot;essentially a book-keeping exeroisef wi^no procedurb for determining how public expenditure would have developed the absence of North Sea revenues.   It would show how on one side the totalrevenue for a given year, and on the other side tho items of expenditurepossibly tax reductions) which in the Government1 s view oan bo seen as rtusoSof this rovonuo.   (Any pavmonts related to devolved matters in Scotland ^Wales might havo to be shown as aggregate sums sinoo their application wo^l^not be a matter for the Government.)(ii) legislation.     In principle*no legislation would be necessary, and the Government cotilsimply publish an annual account for a purely notional Fund. Alternative^&apos;there mi^vt bo logislation to make the Fund statutory, and thus give it ooresubstanoof if tho Government and Parliament wore prepared to aocopt the r.s.^^complication of tho Government1s.accounting procedures.   It would bo nooossto spooify what North Sea revenues would be paid into tho Fund and, what for0of expenditure would be admissible as charges against it.   The revenuesmi^it bo paid into account with tho Paymaster General, distinct from the consolidated Fund.   Expenditures from the Fund would similarly bo dea^outside tho traditional Estimatos/National Loans Fund procedures (thoughfid.course still counting as public expenditure).   Parliament would still ^approve expenditure in advance, which points to a procedure for laying ^annually, subject to affirmativo resolution, providing for specified e&amp;o^of expenditure in the financial year ahead (or revised amounts in thocurrent year).   Any surplus in the Fund would automatically bo lent to
Government,- and there could be a provision for surrendering any end-yearsurplus to the Consolidated Fund.   A statutory Fund with revenues assigned&quot;to it would need   an Accounting Officer or Officers:   in the basence ofany new institution, the Accounting Officer for each block of expendituremight be the Permanent Secretary of the Department which has previouslyborne it on its own Vote.(iii) Revenue7*     Government revenue from North Sea oil and gas production will compriseRoyalties, PfiT and Corporation Tax.   Forecasts of the receipts from these&quot;taxes are very sensitive to the assumptions made on the exchange rate,the rate of inflation and the real price of oil.   In the early years, whileproduction is still rising rapidly, there is an additional difficulty offorecasting the timing of receipts since companies will be setting off their development costs against profits.   The following figures (consistent withthe EPR4&quot; article on the North Sea of August 1977) indicate the broad orders of magnitude:  billion at 1976 prices (broadly comparable with1977 Survey prices)Corporation Tax        Petroleum Revenue Tax197819791980198514Royalties11&quot;2&quot;Total1223*Prom the mid-eighties there may well be something of a plateau, with no substantial further increase in total revenue.8.     These three categories of revenue would appear the most natural to define as North Sea revenue, as it would arguably be legitimate to excludeBN0C and BGC profits.   However, it could be argued that royalties shouldbe excluded because of the National Oil Account^ arrangements, and indeed itwould only be possible to include the royalties as a whole if the National^he Treasuryfs monthly ^Economic Progress report published by itsinformation Division.*A11 North Sea royalties and licence fees are payable direotly into this Accountare used, with the Secretary of State for Energy!s consent, to financeExpenditure by DNOC, although^i any surplus is payable to the Consolidated Fund,^e main reason for this arrangement was to secure the agreement of American oil companies to payment on a deferred basis for BNOC*s participation in their oilfields.   In the event this concept of participation has been dropped and the01iginal case for having this special Account no longer exists.
Oil Account arrangements were repealed.    It could also be argued thatcorporation tax (CT) should be excluded.    Since corporation tax is assessedcompany basis, not on a fielcUby-field basis like PRT, it is not possibleaccurately to attribute CT to a company^ North Sea operations.   It is ofcourse possible to make notional calculations, but those could only give an approximate indication.   There would in any case be no possibility ofchannelling &quot;North Sea CT&quot; directly into a Fund;    a transfer would have tobe made from the Consolidated Fund of an amount equal to the CT notionallyattributed to North Sea activities.9. These estimates are based on current rates of CT and PRT. clearly a change in the CT rate could affect receipts, and for PRT it is again open *0the Government, anyway in principle, to change the rate.(iv) Expenditure10. By definition this typo of Fund is not intended to affect the actualtotals of expenditure.   The problem would be to match suitable kinds ofexpenditure, from within the existing public expenditure programme, as clo6e^as possible against the (uncertain) prospective total revenue.11. The main expenditure programmes which have a strong claim to be original^e &apos;in accordance with the White Paper objectives, are as follows -(a)   Regional investment the Fund might cover the following programmes (with figures drawn fronlCmnd 7049) m at 1977 Survcv^^		1977-78	198O-8I	Regional Development grants	380	451(ii)	Selective assistance (under Section 7 of the 1972 Industry Act) .	51	48(iii) Scottish and Welsh Development Agencies		90	100(iv)	Other regional support	22	21(v)	Provision of land and buildings	28    . -	29(vi)	Northern Ireland trade, industry and employment	170	168		741	- 817
There are some other categories of expenditure which might &quot;be included:for example, infrastructure projects in the regions (ports, roads,railways etc) aimed at improving their economic base, although, sincenumerous public authorities are involved, the public expenditurecomplications would bc considerable.   That is not to say, however, thatsuitable projects could not be identified;   for they already are forthe purpose of attracting European Regional Development Fund assistance.More doubtful would be the regional portion of the tourism programme,and it would be going far from industrial objectives to include more general infrastructure spending - eg on housing, or through the urban programme,(b)    General assistance to industryIf the Fund were to have the general purpose,of strengthening theindustrial base, it mi^it cover the following programmes:  million at 1977 Survey prices(i) National Enterprise Board(ii) Selective assistance to individual firms etc(mainly under Section 8of the 1972 Industry Act)(iii) Future industrial support(&quot;the wedge&quot;)And possibly also:(iv) General industrial R a D(v) Technological and industrialsponsorship^Figures arc in money terms and not at constantpricesa(c) general   /ryThere could be a case for including in such a Fund expenditure whichwas concerned with conserving energy or developing new sources or methodsof securing long-term energy supplies.    Some expenditure of this kind is included in the industrial R&amp;D and sponsorship programmes referred toabove;    other possibilities would be expenditure on developing nuclear51977-78 1980-81207* 275*91 1015759 7610 10367 519
capacity and on financing now coal mines, though much of this is in the nationalised industries* investment programmes, rather than financed from the Exchequer.   Deoisions have yet to be taken in a number ofthose areas, but expenditure of the order of  3jg- billion over the next10 years oould be involved, ie  350 million a year.(d)   Labour Market MeasuresThis is another area of expenditure that might be included.   It mightbe possible to provide support only for the Training Services Agency13expenditure on industrial training and re-training, or also cover theexpenditure of the Employment Services Agency on placement and mobilityrincluding its Job Centre Expansion Programme.   Any special employmentmeasures designed to deal with tho high unemployment which is in prospfor the medium-term, such as the Youth Opportunities Programme (YOP)and the Special Temporary Employment Programme (STEP) for adults, orto encourage labour-intensive investment, might also be financedthrough the Fund.   Other initiatives in the field of improving the suppljrof labour to industry (eg tho development of prestigious technologi08!institutions) might also be candidates for inclusion, though this wouldmake it harder to define the precise scope of the Fund.   The relevantPESC provision is as follows  million ^ 197-7 Survey iF1977-78 198081Industrial training(1)(2)Placement and mobilityAnti-unemployment measure s290160354804(3)329172226727(4)Notes:    (1)   This covers the Training Services Agency&apos;expenditure, excluding special measures.(2) This covers all expenditure on employmentservices, including Manpower services commission central administrative expenditure,and Work Experience Programme allowances.(3) Temporary Employment Subsidy, Job ReleaseScheme, Job Creation, special training measures,etc,(4) Youth Opportunities Programme and specialTemporary Employment Programmes only: assumeother measures phased out.6
(v) Taxation12*   One potential use of North Sea revenues is to reduce the level of&quot;taxation.   In principle it would be possible to show a specific taxreduction as a debit item in a non-statutory Fund, or in tho case of a statutory Fund to provide for a transfer into the Consolidated Fund to offset!the loss of revenue from a tax reduction,,   But this mi it be thoughtan unnecessary complication for this presentational kind of Fund,(vi) Technical Problems13. This type of Fund would not purport to identify changes in expenditureresulting from North Sea oil.   But there would bo a problem in that the revenues would vary in size from year to year, and will be rising until about 1985;   the forecast in paragraph 6 is already hi ier, for this year,&quot;than the purely regional spending items in paragraph 10(a), and for nextyear looks like exceeding all the items in (a)-(c).   The aim rrigjit be to adjust the expenditure covered by the Fund from year to year so as to matchexpenditure as closely as possible against tho prospective total revenue. In&quot;the statutory version of the Fund, this would point to having a flexible order-making procedure to adjust the expenditure headings met from the Fund so asto achieve this matching from year to year.   Alternatively, or additionally,it mi  it have to be accepted that thore would be large unspent balances in theFund which would be lent, or surrendered, to the Government.   However this problem was resolved, major changes in Parliamentary acoounting would beRequired, and it cannot be assumed that ir. public Accounts Committee andExpenditure Committee would look: favourably on those changes.B *     LARGE/ADDITIONAL(i) Objective14. The broad intention is to ensure that the North Sea revenue is spentV deliberate Government decisions, separate from the ordinary public expenditure programme and in accordance with stated priorities. ThisRequires that some way is found of defining the course of public expenditurein the absence of the additional revenue via the Fund.7
(ii) Legislation15. This would clearly need to be a statutory Fund, with its ownspecified sources of revenue, procedure for Parliamentary approval ofexpenditure and auditing;,   The crucial question would be the responsibilityfor deciding on expenditure.    One possibility would be a fully institutionsFund, with its own Board and staffj   the Board could include representativeof the regions, the TUC and CBI, and could operate under general Ministerialdirectives and subject to Parliamentary scrutiny.   Alternatively, given thevery large sums involved, Ministers might themselves wish to reach decisionon spending the Fund, and make proposals for Parliamentary approval;   hut togive the Fund a separate reality, it would probably at least bo necessary *0have an Office distinct from existing Departments, running its separateexpenditure programme subject to approval by a Ministerial Committee,In either casoy there would need to be an Accounting Officer prepared to answer to the Public Accounts Committee for all expenditures made fromthe Fund.(iii) Revenue16, As noted in paragraph 7 above, there is a case for excluding royalti06from the Fund revenue, and perhaps also the corporation tax attributable &apos;fc0North Sea operations.   But even if confined to PRT revenue alone, the Fundannual income would build up to more than  800 million by I98O, and . 1200 million by 1985, at present rates.(iv) Expenditure17,.   Given the intention to   make the Fund*s spending &quot;additional&quot; &quot;fco wwould have been spent in tho absence of the revenue, Ministers would to agree on a lower, notional &quot;base-line&quot; for expenditure programmes, -c.the annual totals in the&apos; current Public Expenditure White Paper - onthat the economic assessment on which the White Paper plans are based.full account of North Sea oil.   Tho amount of the neoessary reduction ^programmes would depend on the amount of revenue allocated to the Fund*(v) Taxation-p NoT^18.   Notionally it would bo possible to argue that in the absence 01thoSea revenue, instead of the levels of public expenditure being lowerThistotal of revenue from non-oil taxation would have had to be higher.-hut a180would point to a smaller cut in the public expenditure base-line, DU8
a smaller amount of discretionary spending from the Fund, with the balance&quot;transferred as a prior claim to offset4.the assumed lower revenue in the consolidated Fund.&quot;19.   A more realistic possibility is that Ministers could take the view,as the Fund revenue began to build up, that part should be used to reduce&quot;taxation rather than adding further to total public expenditure. Again&quot;this could be achieved by a transfer to the Consolidated Fund.   A similareffoct would be achieved indirectly, if tho &quot;additional&quot; spending from the*^nd reduced the pressure to expand the corresponding programme within&quot;tho. base-line total, or even caused it to contract, thus allowing lower&quot;taxation (or higher spending elsewhere).vV*)   Toj3hniqal,rpr obi ems20.   Several problems need to be mentioned -(i) The amount of revenue receipts in any year will remain uncertain(depending on oil prices, capital costs, exchange rates etc).   It willbe affected by Government decisions on energy policy (depletion rateseto), taken on other grounds than their impact on the Fund*s revenue.Hence the inflow into tho Fund is likely to be unpredictable andsubject to wide fluctuation.   If in any year it fell short ofexpenditure commitments, there would be a question whether thoseshould be cut back, or alternatively financed from tho Consolidated^Fund, perhaps as a first charge against the oil revenue for later years.(ii) With additional expenditure on this scale, organised more orless independently of spending Ministers, a major difficulty would beto co-ordinate tho activities financed from the Fund with tho spendingprogrammes of departments and with the activities of the not andAgencies.   The problems of management responsibility and accountabilitywould be severe, and here again it cannot be assumed that the relevantselect committees of the House would look favourably on these proposals.(iii) Even the procedures described above would not provide any assurance that additional expenditure/tax cuts had been correctly identified.Setting up a notional &quot;no-North Sea&quot; baseline in the annual public expenditure survey would be a highly artificial - and probably controversialexercise.   The problem is that there is no satisfactory way of
distinguishing what segments of expenditure, or tax reliefs, wouldnot have &quot;been undertaken in the absence of the North Sea - and hence ofisolating genuinely &quot;additional&quot; expenditure or tax reliefs.   As timepasses, this problem would become increasingly difficult. Itwould be increasingly difficult to decide whether new proposals shouldbe financed from the Fund or from &quot;mainstream&quot; programmes.   On theexpenditure side, the genuinely additional projects and items ofexpenditure would tend to be marginal ones.   But it would be temptingon presentational grounds to assign some hi i priority projects to theFund.(iv)   Tho other question is whether this very elaborate change wouldhave any practical effect on the balance of public expenditure programmes.   For regional industrial assistance, the main determinantis the level of business activity, and hence the number of investmentproposals coming from industry itself;   the main instruments aredemand-determined (RDCs) or roactive (selective financial assistance,and the Agencies).   e.c. competition rules constrain the scope for making assistance available on more generous terms.   For industrialassistance, the Department of Industry already has the &quot;wedge&quot; to finance new projects riot yet foreseen in detail.   If it turned out- that the Government was .already doing, or planning to do, as much as could be done cost-effectively in these hi v-priority directions, theestablishment of a large &quot;additional&quot; Fund mi  it not in fact change the balance of expenditure in the manner intended.c. small/additional(i) Objective21. The intention here is to recognise that most of the North Sea revenueswill be needed, either to help finance the Governments expenditure progr&amp;^^in accordance with existing priorities, or to create an improved macro-ecoflclimate by reducing levels of taxation;   but to segregate a relatively smalshare of tho revenue to finance specific additional projects of industrialregional development and of replacement sources of energy.(ii) legislation siati on22. Once again, 1the Fund.   This mi  it specify that  x million a year from the North Seaild ^crevenues should bo paid into the Fund each year. Another possibility woUJ-to provide for a specific sum to bo earmarked over say a five year period&apos;10,CONFIDENTIAL22.   Once again, there would be a case for legislation to give substance ^0
(iii) Revenue23. Since the sum allocated annually would be only a small proportion cfNorth Sea oil revenues, these would not need to be hypothecated;   instead a specific sum would be earmarked.   The Scottish Office, who support this approach, have suggested a figure of the order of  200 million a year.(iv)24. It has been proposed that this sum should be made available for additional expenditure concentrated on the regions, on industry (through theNEB and Agencies), industry-delated infrastructure, and environmental, social and cultural schemes to make depressed industrial areas more attractive toincoming industry.   The organisation for achieving this would need further study;   it is suggested that local authorities would be able to apply&quot;through the relevant Government Department or, in Scotland, through theScottish Executive.25. After devolution, a share might be made available to the devolvedadmini strati ens to bo used on devolved programmes (eg Development Agencies,^oads, airports).   These programmes are to be financed as things stand from&quot;the dovolved administrations&apos; block funds, or by borrowing for capital investment, under arrangements laid down in the Scotland and Wales Bills.Any amount transferred from the Fund would need to be subject to the Assemblyaudit and accounting arrangements.(v) Technical ProblemsDifficulties that nccd&quot;.to bo mentioned are -(i)   Making a share of tho Fund available to the devolvedadministrations (whether under this alternative or the &quot;large11Fund at B above) would run counter to the general approach of theScotland and Wales Bills, that within the limits approved by theHouse of Commons the administrations should determine their ownspending priorities.   To ensure additionally a case-by-case approach,with central approval of individual applications from the devolvedadministrations, would need to bo provided for in the legislationsetting up tho Fund.11
(ii) As with the largo additional Fund, there would be theproblems of trying to decide whether a new proposal should be financed from this Fund or from within a Departments existing programme, by finding savings elsewhere, or from the contingency reserve.   The basic question is how to establish whether a project is truly additional, which entails a clear view on i^hatthe existing programmo is before extra projects are supported bythe Fund.(iii) There would need to be a procedure for allocating a limitedsum among a range of possible uses - regional, industrial assistanceinfrastructure, energy and so on.   This might be done either bysharing out initially, or by reaching Mnisterial decisions on individual proposals.(iv) There would presumably be a single United Kingdom Fund, partsof which might bo. made available (as proposed in paragraph 24)to the Assemblies.   But there would still have to be an AccountingOfficer for the United Kingdom Fund who would be responsible for making disbursements to the Assemblies and fully accountablefor all other expenditure from the Fund.CONCLUSION27.   Ministers will want to consider, in the light of this paper, whetherthey wish to propose a North Sea Development in the White Paper on theBenefits of North Sea Oil;   and if so, which of the throe kinds of Funddiscussed in this paper they wish to put forward.6 February 197812

</content>
</cab>
