<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/243/0 images: 134-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r E  T.Q u216(33)COPY NOsCABINET.negotiations 30r new anglo-soviet trade agreement&quot;. &apos;Despatch from Sir John Simon to Mr. Coote (Moscow).(Circulated    by direction of the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.)Whitehall Gardens * S.W.1. loth September,  1933.
Circulated to the Cabinet by direction ol The Secretary of Scats for Foreign Affairs this document is the property of his britannic majestvs government87RUSSIA. September 4, 1933.CONFIDENTIAL. Section 5.[N 6678/5/38] No. 1.Sir John Simon to Mr. Coote (Moscow).(No. 548.)Sir, Foreign Office, September 4, 1933.THE Soviet Ambassador came to see me this afternoon to talk about negotiations for the new Anglo-Soviet Trade Agreement.2. His Excellency said that the negotiations were meeting with difficulties. He briefly described the proceedings in the special committee which has been set up to discuss the draft of the new agreement, and stated that the main difficulty: now remaining was to find a means of providing for the exception to most-favoured-nation treatment which was necessitated by clause 21 of the Ottawa.: Agreement. The Soviet Government had agreed that this exception to most-favoured-nation treatment must be made. They had proposed that there should be definite quotas on goods not subject to embargo, and that outside these quotas arrangements should be made for goods which were subject to embargo. Under these provisions the Soviet Government would be secured from restrictive action without due notice. The latest Soviet proposal in cases where the necessity for prohibition, under the Ottawa clause, of any class of Soviet goods might arise was that there should be a limit of two months for negotiation, and, if this should fail, a notice of prohibition, to come into force after three months, making a total period of five months in all before any embargo could become effective. They further asked that goods contracted for before prohibition should be excepted from its effects. It was on this point that the greatest difficulty was being experienced in the committee, and the Ambassador said that the British counter-offer of one month&apos;s notice of prohibition without any period for negotiation would render impossible that security for Soviet trade with this country which was of vital importance. The Soviet Government had on their side made considerable concessions which would render the new trade agreement most advantageous to us. On the Soviet side they must have security for their trade.3. I told his Excellency that the matters which he had mentioned were questions with which the Board of Trade had been dealing, and that, as Lhad been on holiday abroad, I had not yet had any opportunity of informing myself of the position. I should be seeing the President of the Board, if not on the following day, then in a very few days, when I would certainly discuss the question with him. I reminded his Excellency that an embargo was a weapon which operated in two directions, and, while I trusted that its use would not arise, we had on our side to make stipulations which would safeguard our own interests.4. On taking his leave M. Maisky once again stressed the necessity of obtaining security for Soviet trade if our commercial relations were to be put on a secure basis as&apos; apart from one of casual trading. I took this opportunity to remind his Excellency that we expected that matters should be made as easy as possible for our&apos; Embassy and consulates in Russia in regard to such questions as &quot; Torgsin,&apos;&quot; &quot; Intourist,&quot; &amp;c. M. Maisky appeared to regard these as minor matters which could be disposed of without difficulty.I am, &amp;c.JOHN SIMON.[917 d-52

</content>
</cab>
