<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/243/0 images: 197-200</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT,.)S E C RE ToTranslation of summary of an Italian Aide-Memo ire commun lea ted-to the French Ambassador in Rome on the 21st September, 19550gThe Italian Government on their side agreed in noting &quot;the very interesting possibilities of material progress implicit in the points of view formulated by the two parties&quot;.    They indicate that &quot;certain points will have to be examined in further detail in connection with the observations which may be put forward by other interested powers, especially by Germany and Great Britain&quot;. They suggest that further progress might be made in the con-versations between delegations at Geneva or in discussions through the diplomatic channel.    They continue with the following detailed observations.1.    Chemical___and Bacteriological Warfare.It only remains to work out in detail the agreement which was already apparent during the Conference,  &quot;particularly in the matter of the necessity of sanctions.    The Italian Government hope that it will be possible to reconcile this agreement with the principles laid down on the subject by other, especially the German and British delegations.&quot;The Aide-Memoire in question is the Italian reply to the French observations on Signor Mussolini&apos;s proposals on the subject of disarmament.    The summary prepared by the French Government was communicated to the British Ministers during the conversations of September. 28nd. See   enclosure in Lord Tyrrell&apos;s despatch No. 1558 of September 25th circulated to the Cabinet.CP. 227-A (35) .C A B I N E T.REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.(bee CP.227  (33).)
mThe right of reprisal &quot;ought not,  in any event,  to include any right of precautionary preparation for its exercise&quot;. 2.      The Italian Government &quot;would find no difficulty in extending their proposal for the prohibition of the bombardment of civil populations - during the first period - to include the prohibition of all bombardment from the air and of bombing aeroplanes, provided that this very important measure of disarmament were accompanied,  in accordance with the principle of the inter-dependence of the three forms of armament, by proportionate reductions in heavy material of war on land and sea.&quot;Since, however,  certain powers have not found it possible, up to the present,  to agree to such reductions either in the case of land or naval war material, the Italian Government have been obliged to confine their proposals in the matter of aviation to the abolition of the bombardment of civil populations.&quot;&quot;The Italian Government naturally agree, in accordance with what has always been their view, that the abolition of bombing-aeroplanes should be contemplated for the second period, taking account of technical necessities and of the principle of inter-dependence . &quot;After recalling that they were in favour of making a beginning with a more substantial measure of real disarmament, the Italian Government confirm their adherence to the principle of the trial period,  &quot;which would make it possible to realise immediately if not such important results at least those which the circumstances of the present moment permit.&quot;&quot;They hope that their attitude v/ill lead at a later date to the more complete results which alone can be regarded as a positive fulfilment of obligations of the Treaties.&quot;This sentence is taken from a text of the aide-memoire provided by the Italian delegation at Geneva.      The text of the French Summary appears to be corrupt.
4.      &quot;The Italian Government confirm the principle of the limitation of armaments at their present level except in so far as final decisions remain to be taken on the question&quot; of the quotas of defensive war material to be allotted to the ex-enemy Powers.      However, the limitation of the manufacture and the purchase of arms should not&apos; stand in the way of programmes of modernisation and replacement, including the modernisation and replacement of fortifications-t i on s.5.        The Italian Government confirm that they do not ask for the extension of the standardisation of the type of armies to overseas forces.      They agree in hoping for a satisfactory solution of the problems concerning police and paramilitary formations and they take note of the inclinations expressed by the French Government on the subject of the Italian point of view concerning pre-military formations.&quot;As regards the numbers of effectives and the length of service,  the Italian Government point out that the ques-tion of the ratio between the French and Italian forces in-cluding certain overseas forces should ultimately be considered in the light of the numbers of effectives which maybe allotted to other States&quot;.6.        The question of a quota of defensive material to be allotted to ex-enemy States (see below),7.        Agreement to postpone negotiations on jfavai questions. 8.        The French amendments dealing with voting in the Permanent Disarmament Commission are being Suudied. 9.        Taking the British plan as a base, the Italian Government are ready on their side to examine the possi-bility of modifying that part  of the plan dealing with supervision of the application of provisions of the Convention (British plan. Articles 69-87), in the direction of giving to the supervision to be carried out on the  spota regular, periodical and automatic character.-3-
10.     No observations on the conditions in which the Disarmament Conference would resume a study of the problem in 1938.The Italian Government express their satisfaction at the spirit of understanding which the two Governments have shown.     They ask the French Government in all frankness and friendship &quot;to consider that although an unbending attitude towards the countries disarmed by treaty might be fully justified in the event of the adoption of effective measures of reduction of war material on the part of the countries which are heavily armed? the postponement of these measures cannot but deprive such an attitude to an appreciable extent of its moral and political basis. These considerations do not in any way detract from the expediency of ruling out high powered weapons - which in the Italian point of view coincide with weapons of a specifically offensive character - seeing that it should remain the final object of all States Without exception to alleviate the burdens and dangers of armaments&quot;.&quot;The Italian Government hope that it may be possible, as soon as the British and German Governments have made known their observations,, to reach, in agreement with the interested parties, final decisions which will take account of the treaties? of considerations of general  security and of the five-power declaration of December 11th, 1932, and which will be capable of being realised in the atmosphere of the Four-Power Pact.&quot;(Intld, ) A.&quot;Wo A. L.

</content>
</cab>
