<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/243/0 images: 402-405</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1933.SECRET. - V/mUV,&apos;.: :;&apos;7&apos;Y :   Qqpyl No.   40CP. 245 (33).231CABINET.THE FUTURE OF THE HOME DEFENCE SCHEME AND THE ROYAL AIR FORCE PROGRAMME FOR 1934.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.1. THE preparation of Air Estimates for 1934 is now in hand, but before any progress can be made I am compelled to ask the Cabinet for early directions on certain matters of policy.2. The Air Ministry has now reached the latter part of a programme of 52 squadrons organised primarily for home defence, but also forming the only source of reinforcement for major overseas emergencies. This programme was first approved in 1923 and has been subsequently endorsed by each successive Government since that date, including the Labour Administrations of 1924 and 1929. I may remind my colleagues that the programme was announced as an initial step only towards remedying the extreme disparity existing between our own and foreign air services; and that since 1923 all the principal Powers have very extensively increased their air strength not least Soviet Russia, of whose immense aerial activity I have been given a striking account by M. Cot, the French Air Minister, who has just paid a personal visit to Moscow. Forty-two of the 52 squadrons envisaged in the 1923 programme have now been formed, but one is about to proceed to Singapore, so that there will only be 41 available in this country; and of these no less than 13 are non-regular. The last occasion on which the date for completion of this programme was specifically considered by the Cabinet was nearly four years ago (vide CP. 355 (29) of December 1929), when the then Labour Government approved a retardation to 1938 instead of 1935, to which year the Air Ministry was at that time working.3.   The subsequent course of events may be summarised as follows : (a) The ruling of December 1929 that the Air Ministry should work to completion of the expansion scheme by 1938, would have involved the formation of 14 new squadrons over a period of eight years, spaced in such a way as to avoid any sharp variations in Air Votes. If the time-table which was prepared to give effect to the decision of 1929 had been adhered to, we should by this time have formed 46 out of the total of 52 squadrons,(b) The Armaments Truce (November 1931 to February 1933)  precluded,however, the formation of any new units in 1932. Moreover, as a further earnest of His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s desire to promote the work of the Disarmament Conference, the standstill was voluntarily extended to the current year in spite of our marked inferiority in air strength as compared with other great Powers,[9193]
(c) No new units &quot;-having thus been formed for the last two years/ accom-&apos; modation exists in excess of the present number of squadrons. -For;,n - &apos; I -;&apos; land has to be taken5 up- and building schemes for new: stations initiated 1 -&apos;/&quot;&apos;   &apos;&apos; four years in advance of the actual formation of the squadrons which &quot;&apos;3 -i;i &apos; are to occupy them.  There is a similar surplus of technical personnel, since these&apos; have to be entered and trained three years ahead.4. Accordingly, vacant accommodation and, broadly speaking, sufficient personnel are now available to add four squadrons to the present uncompleted programme. I now propose that this accommodation should be occupied and the personnel absorbed, firstly, by the formation of two new regular squadrons, and, secondly, by the conversion to their proper operational basis of two squadrons, which, though they have always been reckoned in calculating our first-line strength, in fact exist only on paper, since they are embodied in the Aeroplane and Armament Experimental Establishment at Martlesham Heath, have never been organised or trained as fighting units, and simply could not function in war.5. The construction of works for the additional stations still required to complete the programme up to 52 squadrons is dependent upon a decision as to the date of its completion. I am advised that the full programme could not now be completed by 1938, except by raising the works vote to an inconveniently high level during the next four years. In the first place we should be obliged to have a number of major works schemes in full progress at the same time; secondly, this intensive development at home would coincide with new works commitments overseas. I therefore propose that the date of completion of the present Home Defence Scheme should be deferred until 1940, which will give us a more even load of expenditure over the next few years. I do not contemplate making this date public, for the present at all events.6. So much for Home Defence. The only other addition I propose for the 1934 programme is the formation of one flying boat squadron. We have at present only 7 units of this type, which is one of wide general utility for imperial defence. The Air Ministry has been much criticised in the past for alleged neglect of flying-boats, which has, of course, simply been due to lack of funds. The recent flight of the Italian armada anross the Atlantic has focussed public attention on the potentialities of the flying-boat- and they are certainly very great.7. I have, of course, given very careful consideration both to the political and financial implications of the foregoing proposals. There is, as my colleagues are aware, a strong and by no means extremist body of opinion (I ignore the Daily Mail) which considers that our present position in respect of air power by comparison with that of other nations with far smaller and less widely scattered responsibilities is gravely unsatisfactory, and looks for an acceleration of the Home Defence Scheme approved more than ten years ago for completion &quot; with as little delay as possible,&quot; and a general strengthening of the Air Force as a whole. Having regard to the multiplicity of our Defence responsibilities, the steady technical development of aircraft, the growth of foreign air services, and the unfortunate deterioration of the international situation in so many directions which has taken place in recent years, there is clearly a strong case for such measures.8. There can, I feel satisfied, be no ground for any reasonable body of opinion regarding the proposals in paragraphs 4 to 6 above as otherwise than extremely moderate. Actually they involve the formation of only three new units next year and an addition of under 30 machines to our first-line strength. They are thus comfortably within the figures proposed by the Foreign Office for insertion in the latest draft of the; British Disarmament Convention, and represent, indeed, what many people will regard as a scarcely adequate step towards lessening our present inferiority. I have, indeed, hesitated as to whether it is not my duty to put before my colleagues proposals for a much more substantial increase, which would, I believe, command widespread support both in Parliament and in the country at large. By the proposals contained in White Paper No. 11 of 1932, and by the terms of the subsequent White Paper (Miscellaneous No. 2 of 1933), embodying the British Draft Convention, His Majesty&apos;s Government have explicitly declared their intention to secure for the United Kingdom a one-Power, standard in the air. This has been generally welcomed and I do not, indeed, see how we can set ourselves any other goal.  For I do not think anyone will dispute that air power
is as important to this country and the Empire, in its different; ye^ complementary sphere, as is sea power, and we can no more afford to accept a ppsijbiomof lasting inferiority in the air than we could at sea. Lt is,on.this ground.that His Majesty&apos;s Government have consistently advocated so drastic a policy of, air- disarmament at Geneva; we cannot escape its logical corollary&apos;. We must still hope that this one-Power standard will be; achieved in the main by a reduction of foreign air forces to the British level, rather than by our being compelled to build up to theirs  and it is for this reason that I have thought it wise to confine my proposals for the time being to the very modest measures above outlined. They will give Us a breathing space to see the future course of Disarmament and the intentions of other nations. But I must warn my colleagues that, despite American protesta-tions at Geneva, President Roosevelt has, under the National Recovery Act, recently authorised an increase of something like 200 aircraft in the first-line strength of the United States; whilst in Russia and Japan substantial programmes of air development are in full swing.9. As to the financial aspect, I am advised that the amount to be asked for in Air Estimates 1934 -including provision for the new units included in these proposals need not exceed the present year&apos;s figure by more than  300,000, that is one-fifteenth of the amount added to the Estimates of the other Services this year, when Air Estimates actually underwent a further reduction. I cannot yet pledge myself to an exact figure, but it will be one of that order. The details I shall, of course, discuss with the Chancellor in due course, when the broad policy is settled. I may add that, while I am not as yet in a position to give precise estimates of the course of air expenditure in future years, I am advised that my present proposals, including completion of the expansion scheme to its full total of 52 squadrons, can be carried into effect for an addition of not more than  1,250,000 to the present level of our effective Votes. This full expenditure will not be required for several years and, when it is attained, will still represent a level of Air Estimates some half-million pounds below the corresponding figure for 1925, in striking contrast with air expenditure in France and America, which is, in both countries, already over 100 per cent, higher than eight years ago. The capital expenditure involved on works and equipment for the squadrons which will remain to be formed after 1934 can, I am confident, be found within that sum provided that we are allowed to retard the final completion until 1940. This estimate may appear indeed almost paradoxically low and it would, of course, require upward revision in the event of any marked increase in prices. That I am able (subject to that proviso) to put it forward with reasonable confidence is due partly to the general fall in the price level since 1925, but still more to the continuous and unremitting efforts made by the Air Ministry to secure economies by taking advantage of every new technical development which promises a longer life for machines and engines, and by a policy of bold experiment in the sphere of personnel, entailing far-reaching measures of reorganisation.10.   The success which has attended these efforts and the extreme financial moderation of our air policy may be illustrated by the two following comparative, tables which were furnished to the Estimates Committee this summer and have attracted considerable attention. , .The first table shows the percentage increase or decrease in British, French and American air expenditure since 1925 :  -t- or - of 1933 on 1925. Country. Per cent.Great Britain ... ... ...       -    8France ... ... ... ...       -f- 112United States of America        ... ...       4- 108The second table shows the relation borne by the latest Air Estimates in these countries to their total National Budgets : Percentage of air to total . national expenditure.iCountry. &apos; &apos; &apos; Percent.Great Britain ... :.. &apos;      2-2France ;.     &quot;&apos;- &quot;...    &apos; &quot; ... &apos;   ;&quot; 4-3      &apos;United States of America        &apos; ... &apos; 30
(a) to authorise the formation in 1934 of two new home defence squadrons &apos; y and the conversion to a normal basis of the two &quot; paper &quot; squadrons &apos;&apos;al!f present incorporated in one of our technical establishments-       ;: (6) to reaffirm the Home Defence Scheme of 1923, the date of its completionto 52 squadrons being, however, deferred from 1938 to 1940.; (c) to authorise the formation of one new flying boat squadron in 1934.12. To avoid any possibility of misunderstanding, I should point out that the proposals which I have put forward deal, apart from the one flying boat squadron, only with the completion of the Home Defence Scheme. Any increases required to the strength of the Royal Air Force at overseas stations, such as Singapore, will of course entail additional expenditure. Nor have I taken into account any additional requirements for the Fleet Air Arm in 1934 or subsequent years the cost of which would fall primarily on Navy and not on Air Votes.L.Air Ministry, October 24, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
