<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/8/43 images: 434-447</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  June 1941.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (R) (41) 43.June 23, 1941.WAR CABINET.REPORTS FOR MONTH OF MAY 1941 FOR THE DOMINIONS.INDIA. BURMA, AND THE COLONIES, PROTECTORATES and mandated TERRITORIES.THE DOMINIONS.Report by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.CANADA.1. General Position.DURING May there seems to have been a lull in the campaign in the press,and other quarters, for a speeding-up of the war effort. It is probably becomingno longer necessary. Canadian opinion, perhaps to a greater extent than that ofother Dominions generally, is beginning to grasp the realities of the war, andthe war budget, which was stated in last month&apos;s summary to have staggeredpublic opinion, has received a general welcome, despite an occasional expression of fear of a deficit,- and of the effects on business. There was also some fear of increased centralisation if the Provinces were obliged to give up their powersof taxation; but the general attitude may be summed up by a statement in thepress, which said that &quot; it was not too soon to begin economising at home.&quot;Speeches by the leaders of the Administration, and also a notable speech by air. Purvis, have contributed to make the public more conscious of the gravity ofthe situation, and a new war loan campaign has been launched. Against thislabour troubles continue, and Quebec remains firmly opposed to any suggestions for conscription.Canadians naturally welcomed the news of United States moves in the atlantic at the beginning of the month, and an anxious watch was kept onWashington as the speeches of United States leaders seemed to be graduallymoving towards war. Particular note was paid to the change in the attitude ofthe Saturday Evening Post (the influential United States weekly, hithertoisolationist). Air. roosevelt&apos;s broadcast was received with satisfaction, though there was some disappointment that he did not announce any direct move tosubstantiate his declaration of &quot; undeclared war.&quot; A useful result of the speechAvas that it was interpreted in some quarters as a challenge to Canada to redoubleher efforts. The sinking of the Hood, and Bismarck caused certain quarters tosuggest that Canadian forces might take up their position again in Iceland, andalso even share with the United States in the defence of Greenland.In the field of Empire politics Air. Alenzies&apos; visit perhaps was the most striking event during the month. The Australian Prime Alinister made a very strong impression and it was said that his speeches &quot; revealed great character and high purpose and reflected courage and integrity.&quot; Lord Beaverbrook&apos;appointment in England was hailed as the &apos;&quot;&apos; greatest achievement of anyCanadian in Empire Government,&quot; and considerable interest was also aroused[22631] b
in another piece of news from the United Kingdom : Mr. Eden&apos;s speech wasreceived very favourably, as heralding Anglo-Saxon co-operation, both in peace and war.Most of the remaining interest was taken up by the increasing revelation ofthe collaboration of Vichy with Germany. In the middle of the month two paperscalled for the severing of Canadian relations with the French, even to the taking-over of St. Pierre and Miquelon. The Action Catholique stated that, &quot; if Vichywas for Germany, then the duty of all Canadians was to remain faithful to canada, however painful the consequences to French Canadians.&quot; All the signsare that Canadian Opinion continues to harden in regard to France. Otherwise,there was little independent comment. It might not be out of place to record here that the (Liberal) Winnipeg Free Press, after discussing the ;&apos; Haffner &quot; and&quot; Vansittart &quot; theses about Germany, inclined to the former.2. Naval, Military and A ir A activities.The Canadian Government has been asked to make available accommodation for a number of additional air training establishments which it is jDroposed totransfer from the United Kingdom.3. Economic Activities.Nothing to report.COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.4. General Position.The political situation in Australia continues to revolve around the unsatisfactory relations between the Labour Party and the Government. Theoutlook became even worse towards the beginning of the month, when the twoLabour Members of the Advisory War Council issued a statement attacking theresults of the munitions programme. This action received a very poor press, andit was generally considered that it was a political move, since it was issued onthe eve of the New South Wales elections, in which, in circumstances of greatapathy, the reunited Labour Party secured a smashing victory. There is some criticism that the maximum war effort has not yet been reached, and the Presidentof the Commonwealth Bank has commented on the &apos;&apos; appallingly &apos;&apos; poor response to the recently issued war loan.In these circumstances, it was hoped that the return of Mr. Menzies would bring unity to the &quot;country. It was recognised that his status had been increasedby his visit to the United Kingdom and to the United States, and in the firstspeech he made on his return it was noted that &quot; never before had he spokenwith such depth of feeling, and even passion.&quot; Next day, however, the FederalLabour caucus reaffirmed its refusal to enter the National Government; and onthe day after, the Prime Minister made a major tactical error in making a freshappeal in the House of Representatives, where his speech proved a complete failure, even among his own followers. Observers were greatly disappointedby this failure, since they had hoped that Mr. Menzies might have found thequality of &quot;inspired leadership.&quot; which is the only failing in his armoury.Nevertheless, his position has been subsequently somewhat strengthened by apublic recantation by Sir&apos; Earle Page, formerly a bitter personal enemy. TheParliamentary strength of his Party has also improved with a victory in theBoothby By-election, which gave him back his majority of 1.The general position remains unsatisfactory. Virtually every newspaper inthe Commonwealth is pleading for National unity without the slightest effect on political circles. It seems clear that the Labour Party are afraid of splittingtheir organization from top to bottom by a move in that direction, and that theyare also afraid of assuming power independently.Australian reaction over Crete has been less marked than over Greece, nodoubt owing to the smaller Commonwealth forces involved. German allegationsthat the Anzacs were being used too often in the fighting were countered by thePrime Minister; and on the whole there seems to be full recognition of the need
for sacrifice involved in this &quot;vast delaying action&quot; of the Empire. Forexample, all criticism of the decision to go to Greece is dead. Relations with japan have not been in question during the month, though some objection hasbeen taken to the Japanese inclination to treat Australia as a separate entity,rather than a part of the British Empire. Comment on the other near-AxisPower, France, has hardened during the month. The general attitude now is,that &quot;it is time to take off kid gloves in dealing with traitors.&quot; If there hasbeen a fault in British policy it has been &quot; an excessive solicitude for the formerAlly who forsook her.&quot;5. Naval, Mill tart/ and Air Activities.Australian forces took part in the fighting in Crete.At the end of the month Australian Imperial Force enlistments totalled151,732, of whom 88.353 are serving overseas.6. Economic Activities.Nothing to rejjort.NEW ZEALAND.7. General Position.It may be said that, during May, the war, for the first time, became a domestic issue in New Zealand. This is, of course, due to the role of the NewZealand forces in Crete. There was general satisfaction when it was learned that New Zealand troops were to take the brunt of the Axis attack and thatGeneral Freyburg had been chosen for command. This pride was accompanied bya certain anxiety, which increased as full news of the bitter fighting began toarrive. The end of the operation was received with oalm, but public feeling was greatly affected when detailed casualty lists frdin Greece followed the news of fighting in the island. Nevertheless, the general attitude of the New Zealandpress was that the time gained by the battle of Crete outweighed the lossesinvolved. The Acting Prime Minister, on the 28th May, called on the people to&quot;wake up &quot; and increase their war effort, and certain papers still emphasised that New Zealand had not fully understood the &quot; dark period through which theBritish people wall have to go.&quot;The triennial local elections resulted in a land-slide in favour of - theConservative Opposition. There has been an increase in Government civil expenditure in the last year, and considerable criticism is made of this in thepress (which is almost entirely Conservative). The Dominion states that theGovernment attitude that &quot;war expenditure must not restrict ordinary Stateexpenditure &quot; is indefensible.The impact of the war is shown by the comparative scarcity of reference to new Zealand economic troubles, though considerable satisfaction has been expressed at the United Kingdom decision to buy more New Zealand meat and cheese.New Zealand has been following the course of the war elsewhere with greaterinterest. Mr. Menzies, on his voyage home to Australia, made a speech atAuckland, which made a strong impression on public opinion; and, generally. NewZealand comment has been both vigorous and independent. Thus, on the Atlanticbattle, one paper says that &quot; defeat and victory may turn out to be somewhatrelative terms,&quot; while another states that &quot; the effective reply (to German propa-ganda) is to show that the British people know the kind of world they want tocreate.&quot;   Comment on Vichy has been restrained.A Government Mission is shortly to visit the United States of America.Mr. Fraser, the Prime Minister of New Zealand, reached the Middle Easton his way to the United Kingdom.Nothing to report.[22631]8. Economic Activities.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.9. General Position.As the Parliamentary session ended at the beginning of the month, political activity increased, although this took the form mostly of preparation for thecongress of the Afrikaner Party on the 28th May, and of the Nationalists atBloemfontein on the 3rd June. At the former, Dr. Malairs appeal for unity was&quot;coldly-&apos; turned down, largely owing to the Nationalist association withOssewa Brandwag, which is showing signs of &quot; increasing arrogance.&quot;&apos; Themeeting made no reference to the war, and this was sharply criticised by all other parties. Mr. Havengar was elected Leader and General Hertzog HonoraryLeader. (It may be noted that, earlier in the month, General Hertzog was usedto propagate the canard that the United States was to take over South Africanbases.) The Nationalist Congress is expected to see a &quot;show down&quot; betweenMessrs. Pi row and Strydom, but Dr. Malairs policy is wholly devoted to maintaining an outward parade of unity if at all possible.In these circumstances it seems unlikely that the movement recently started by Members of the University of Potchefstroom to include the Nationalist Party,Ossewa Brandwag, and Reddingsdaad in a united &quot; peophrs front &quot; will have much success. (The last of these organizations is an economic movement designedto &quot; redeem &quot; the poor whites, who are mostly of Dutch origin.)Little activity is reported from the Government side, except the recentbroadcast by General Smuts on the 12th May, in which he stated that the day ofthe small Sovereign States was over, a thesis bitterly attacked by the Opposition.The Nationalists also lost no opportunity of pouring scorn on General Smuts&apos;spromotion to be Field-Marshal, and references to him in the vernacular press arenow preceded by his new rank in English. His announcement of the use of union troops north of Abyssinia has also aroused intense opposition.Comment on foreign affairs, with one important exception, follows the usualParty pattern. Thus, the Trans coaler, after the sinking of the Hood, announcedthat &quot; British Atlantic supremacy hangs by a thread.&quot; The Malanites have madeseveral attempts to discover divisions within the Empire as a result of the Greekcampaign. Much play has also been made with the decision to abandonconscription. In Ulster, oddly enough, however, the Opposition references to theloss of Crete have been most objective, while criticism of the battle has come fromsupporters of the Government.10. Naval, Military and Air Activities.On the 4th May General Smuts announced that Union forces would be sentto Egypt from Abyssinia as soon as they could be released, and certain units havearrived.11. Economic Activities.Nothing to report.NEWFOUNDLAND.12. General Position.Messages from the Prime Minister and other Ministers were sent toNewfoundland during a recruiting week which commenced on the 26th May.The preliminary Estimates for the financial year, commencing the 1st July,1941, indicate that, as a result of a considerable anticipated increase in revenue and of the economies that have been effected, a net suplus of about $$2,000,000is expected. In addition, the sale of War Savings Certificates is expected toproduce $500,000. The Newfoundland Government propose to devote a sum of$1,000,000 to the British war effort, and have suggested that part of this might,be ear-marked for the equipment of an Air Force Unit manned by Newfound-landers. The bulk of the balance of the sum of $2,500,000 expected to accrue in1941-42 will be set aside as a reserve for meeting the problems of post-war resettlement.
The Government of Newfoundland have raised the question of the futurecontrol of the Islands of St. Pierre and Miquelon in the event of some action being necessitated by the attitude of the Vichy Government, and have urgedthat, for administrative and economic reasons, whatever control may be assumedshould be vested in them (rather than in the United States or Canada). It hasbeen explained that, in the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Government, if steps wereto be taken with a view to a change of status of the Islands, they should be ralliedto the Free French Movement, and would, if so taken over, be controlled from theFree French Headquarters in this country. His Majesty&apos;s Government would,however, be in a position under such an arrangement to keep close watch on theinterests of Newfoundland in the Islands.13. Naval, Military and Air Activities.The fifteenth Naval Contingent (151 men) arrived in this country safelyduring May.14. Economic Activities.The Government of Newfoundland have agreed, at the request of the UnitedKingdom, to the suspension for a further year of the general United kingdom import duty of 10 per cent, on certain kinds of white fish, under which theyenjoy preference by virtue of the Ottawa Agreement.Recruitment of a further Contingent of 400 Loggers has begun, and it isexpected that the first batch will sail in June. Newfoundland are also supplyingadditional deck hands and firemen to assist in the manning of the ships to betaken over in the United States.SOUTHERN RHODESIA.15. Naval, Military and Air Activities.Nothing of importance to report.EIRE.16. General Position.The most important matter affecting Anglo-Eire relations which came to thefore during the month of May was the question of applying conscription to northern Ireland. The news that the United Kingdom Government were considering the matter caused Mr. de Valera to summon a special meeting of theBail, at which he said : &quot; If Britain imposes conscription on Northern Ireland, the old unhappyrelations between the two countries will be revived. There can be ho moregrievous attack on any fundamental human right than to force an individualto fight for any country to which he objects to belong.&quot;He stated that he had made representations to the British Government againstthe imposition of conscription. In general his speech was moderate in tone,although he did not fail to harp on the evil of partition and to restate Eire&apos;policy of neutrality. Mr. de Valera was supported in his declaration againstconscription by both Mr. Cosgrave, the Leader of Fianna Fail, and Mr. Norton,the Leader of the Labour Party. Mr. Cosgrave&apos;s speech was, however, studiedlyfriendly to the United Kingdom. A strong declaration against conscription wasalso made by Cardinal MacRory, Archbishop of Armagh and Roman CatholicPrimate of all Ireland, speaking on behalf of himself and all the Roman CatholicBishops in both Eire and Northern Ireland. The Prime Ministers announce-reassessment  in the House of Commons on the 27th May that it would be more troublethan it was worth to enforce conscription on Northern Ireland was received withrelief throughout Eire.In last montlrs summary it was stated that the United States Governmenthad offered to make available to the Eire Government two ships for the carriage of foodstuffs.   It appears, however, that Mr. de Valera resented the tone and
circumstances in which this offer was communicated to him by the United StatesGovernment, and consequently replied that the Eire Government could not accept it, first, because it was deliberately not made through Mr. Aiken, and, secondly,because it was alleged to be subject to certain implied conditions affecting theextent of Eire&apos;s co-operation with Great Britain. Ignoring this response,Mr. Roosevelt published his offer in the United States press, and included in itan offer of a free food consignment. This announcement Avas well received inthe Eire Press, which is of course ignorant of the exchanges between mr. de Valera and the United States authorities. Subsequently an announcement was made in the United States that the Eire Government had accepted the offer.The third important incident in the month was the bombing of Dublin onthe night of the 30th-31st May, when, according to the Eire Governmentsofficial statement, at least twenty-seven people were killed and about eightyinjured, and considerable damage was done to property. The Eire Governmentsstatement added that investigations showed that the bombs dropped were ofGerman origin. The Eire Charge d&apos;Affaires in Berlin was directed to protest inthe strongest terms to the German Government against the violation of Irishterritory, ana! to claim compensation and reparation for the loss of life andinjuries suffered and the damage to property. The Charge d&apos;&quot;Affaires was furtherdirected to ask for definite assurances that the strictest instructions would begiven to prevent the flight of German aircraft over Irish territory and territorial waters. The Irish newspapers did not. on this occasion, try to disguise thegeneral conviction that the bombing was done by the Germans. The loss of life and damage done created great indignation in the Irish Press, and Mr. de valera and other members of his Government and the Leader of the Opposition all paid a visit to the bombed area.Recently it has been announced that a German reply has been received which,while maintaining any damage done was accidental, due possibly to an aircrafthaving lost its way in a high wind, expresses regret and offers to pay compensation.INDIA.Report by the Secretary of State for India.17. Political Situation.(i) Civil Disobedience. The latest reports show a progressive decline in thenumber of persons offering satyagralia and public interest in the movement is saidto be negligible. In some districts the movement is described as being practicallydead. During the month nearly half of the satyagrahis were ignored and theaction taken against organisers in the United Provinces had telling effect.A slight complication has arisen in consequence of a ruling by the LahoreHigh Court that a certain type of offence is not punishable under the Defence ofIndia Rules, and a number of persons arrested have had to be released. Con-sideration is being given to the need for amending the Defence Rules to meet thesituation.By the 1st April the number of persons undergoing imprisonment in con-nexion with the movement had risen to 8,611, in addition to which 249 were under detention. The cumulative total of convictions up to the middle of April was12,891.(ii) A desire to end the political stalemate brought about by Congress andMuslim League tactics appears to be growing among moderate elements.Speeches by the Punjab and Bengal Prime Ministers, both Moslems, urging the setting up of all-party Governments at the centre and in the Provinces to meetthe situation due to the narrowing distance between India and the theatres ofwar have met with a good reception in various quarters. Up to now, however,neither Congress nor the League have made any overtures with a view toco-operation.18. Indian States.(i) The Nizam of Hyderabad and the Nawabs of Bhoyal and Rampur havemade valuable public statements condemning the Iraqi revolt. Some pessimismand increased attention to enemy broadcasts is reported among the intelligentsiain the States as a result of recent war news.
i  1? i m the mills in Indore Sfcate, which led to disturbances, has been settled, the outbreak appears to have been well organised and may be connectedwith similar disturbances in Ahmedabad and Bombay, possibly throughCommunist or enemy-inspired agitators. &quot; a19. Military Affairs.(i) Indian forces in Iraq amounted to a Division of three Brigades withsome divisional troops, base and L. of C. units by the end of May. The Govern-ment of India have agreed to send two more Infantry Brigades in June and an armoured regiment in July.(ii) The Government of India have agreed that the British battalion sent toIraq by air in April may be retained at Habbaniya as long as it is required.(iii) The personnel of three animal transport companies R.I.A.S.C. have now arrived in the United Kingdom.20. Foreign and Frontier Relations.(i) Afghanistan. The British Minister at Kabul had a long conversationwith the Afghan Prime Minister on the 10th May. His Royal Highness&apos;s viewson the general situation in Afghanistan and the attitude of the public towardsthe war were as follows : The Afghan public were not much interested in the warunless it was likely to affect themselves. The Russian menace, which was their chief preoccupation, had receded at any rate for the present and German influencewas hardly a factor in the lives of the general public. German propagandawas strong, but only influenced a comparatively small number. Opinion was,however, likely to be affected by a further advance of the Germans eastwardand by the attitude of Turkey. The Prime Minister did not consider the germans were at present in a position to stir up trouble in Afghanistan and, if they did, hewas confident he could suppress it and them at once. The tribal situation was generally satisfactory.The Prime Minister&apos;s attitude was quiet and undisturbed, and Sir KerrFraser-Tytler feels that the views he expressed are probably a fair estimate of thegeneral situation, though he may be underestimating the unpopularity of himself and his Government.The Government of India have decided to break off their negotiations for thepurchase of Afghan cotton unless the Afghans reduce their prices. The woolnegotiations&apos;with the Afghan Government, which are of more importance fromthe point of view of economic warfare against Germany,,are still going on.(ii) North-West Frontier. The Madda Khel tribe in North Waziristan havebeen giving trouble. A large gang about 1,300 strong was reported on the 23rdMay to have collected between Razwall and Datta Khel with the intention of attacking Datta Khel. According to rumour the Faqir of Ipi, whose where-abouts are uncertain, was proposing to lead this gang in person, but air reconnaissance had not observed any abnormal movement. On the 16th may the Warwickshire Regiment lost five men killed and one wounded in an encounterwith hostiles six miles north of Razmak. The Faqir&apos;s propaganda againstMaliks, Khassadars and all persons in Government Service has been intensified,and has had some effect on Khassadars in one area.In South Waziristan, Sher Ali and other hostiles are reported to be moving-North with a gang of about 200 to join in the proposed attack on Datta Khel.The attitude of the Mahsuds is. however, generally satisfactory except for one section. On the 6th May the South Waziristan Scouts suffered casualties ofthree killed and six wounded in an engagement with hostiles.Outside Waziristan the frontier has remained quiet.(iii) Persian Gulf. Some sympathy with Rashid Ali was noticed in Bahreinand Koweit, probably a sign of the influence of German and Italian wirelesspropaganda. Otherwise there is nothing to report regarding the ArabSheikhdoms.21. Economic.The scheme for the training of Indian workmen in this country is now infull working order. The first batch of trainees arrived during May and were received by Mr. Bevin and Mr. Amery. It is understood that the arrangementsfor looking after the men during their stay here have given complete satisfaction
sand are working well. The second batch of trainees are already on their way;and the Government of India are ready to send more as soon as they hear from us that the experiment is justifying itself and that more are wanted.22. The Roger Mission.The Roger Mission has now completed its task and most of its members have returned to this country. It has made an intensive and comprehensive survey of Indian supply possibilities in terms of the main items of Army equipment,and has presented reports dealing Avith Guns and Carriages, Gun Ammunition,Explosives and Ammunition Filling. Rifles, Small Arms Ammunition, armoured fighting Vehicles and Scientific Instruments. These reports contain specific and detailed recommendations as to the scale of production to be adopted, the locationand erection of factories, the expenditure involved, the requirements of labour,machine tools. &amp;c, and the extent to which assistance will be required from theUnited Kingdom. Taken together they provide a complete survey of India&apos;smaximum productive capacity of the more important munitions and of the action required to translate this industrial potential into actual munitions production.The Mission&apos;s proposals have not been accepted in full as they assumed a degree of assistance from the United Kingdom in the matter of plant and trained personnel which the supply position of this country at the present time did not warrant, but the schemes sanctioned as a result of their labours are designedto provide an additional monthly output in India of the following items :  Small Arms Ammunition        ...       ... 12i million RoundsGun Ammunition :25 Pounder H.E.......... 150,000 Rounds3-7 A.A. H.E..........     20.000 Rounds18 Pounder A.P..........      9,000 Rounds6 Pounder AT..........     25,000 RoundsThey will also aim at a programme of construction of Guns and Carriages atfollowing annual rates : 900 6 Pounder AT. equipment,300-3-7 A.A. liners.124 3-7 Howitzer equipment.The schemes sanctioned also envisage the provision of components to match the output of shell bodies, e.g., fuses, cartridge cases, primers, &amp;c, components ofS.A.A. as well as the explosives necessary for the filling of shells and S.A.A. Thishas meant big expansion in the production of Cordite, T.W.T. and Toluene.The erection of six new factories has been sanctioned and additions will bemade to several already in existence. The construction of a Bren gun factoryunder Czech management has been agreed to in principle, and negotiations arenow being conducted for its erection in Hyderabad. This will provide a substan-tial output of light machine guns.The skilled personnel necessary to this programme of expansion amounts tosome 26 superior and 284 subordinate officers. The provision of such a largenumber presents considerable difficulty at the present time, but all are notrequired at once, and it is hoped to provide the essential minimum at eachstage of development, so as to ensure the smooth progress of the schemes. TheGovernment of India have been asked to enlist the assistance of other eastern group countries in this respect, and they are themselves putting in hand a schemefor training a large number of mechanics.Generally speaking, the Mission has achieved a great deal, and has givensubstantial impetus to the tempo of Indian munitions production which will beof great benefit to the Empire as a whole.23. Finance.Rupee Borrowing. In the report for November was given the yield, up to the23rd November, of the respective war issues.   The following table (in which
Rupees have been converted into sterling at 1*-. Gd. the rupee) gives comparativefigures, and shows the amounts issued since that date :  Difference;::: amountissued betweenTotal to Nov. 23,   Total to May 3,   Nov. 23, 1940, and1940. 1941. May 3, 1941.  million.   million.   million.3 per cent. Defence Loan        22-4 37-6 15-2Interest-free Bonds     ...          1-7 1-8 -defence  Savings   Certi-certificates        ......         1-1 1-9 -8Minting for war pur-poses. The minting, and shipment, of Maria TheresaDollars for use in the Middle East has continued at the rate of about 2.000,000pieces a month. In addition, in recent months large supplies of rupee coinagehave been shipped, where required, to theatres of, operations overseas; and an urgent demand (sponsored by the Treasury and Foreign Office) for Hejazi rivalsfor Ibn Saud is being dealt with. The Government of India&apos;s own immenserecoining operation, designed to conserve silver supplies within the sterling area,is proceeding concurrently.BURMA.Report by the Secretary of State for Burma.24. General.The country generally is quiet.At the instance of the Home Minister, in consultation with the Premier,U Ba Thi, lately Finance Minister, has been detained under the Defence of burma Rules. *In consequence of a disagreement with the Premier, and of his refusal to address his resignation in proper form to the Governor, Ba Hhi was dismissedfrom the Cabinet by the Governor at the beginning of the month. Since then heis alleged to have been endeavouring to persuade influential pongyis (priests) that britain is doomed to defeat and instigating them to secure the freedom of Burmawith the help of Japan.25. Defence and External Relations.Nothing to report.26. Burma-China Road.During April the main Chinese Government agency transported 7,400 tonsinto China, the reduction being due to the extension of the run to Paoshan. TheControl is working smoothly and Control lorries commandeered earlier in Chinaare now beginning to return.THE COLONIAL EMPIRE.Report by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.(Note. In this report &quot; Colonies &quot; is used to cover not only the colonies in the restricted sense, but also protectorates and Mandated Territories,and &quot; Colonial Governors &quot; is used to include High Commissioners andthe British Resident, Zanzibar.)27. Military Affairs.(i) West Africa.An opportunity has been taken to discuss with General Sir George Giffard,General Officer Commanding West Africa, various defence matters of common[22631] c
concern to the civil and military authorities. The problem of improvement in thesecurity services and co-ordination of intelligence work has recently been examined by a special representative sent out from the United Kingdom to WestAfrica, who returned at the end of May.Another problem which is causing some difficulty is the demand for localEuropean man-power for the military forces. The stage has now been reachedwhen it is felt to be impossible to release further European man-power, as the personnel available is already required either for Government services or for themaintenance of essential industries; and it is understood that the militaryauthorities do not intend to make any further calls on local European man-power in West Africa.(ii) West Indies.Arrangements have been made for discussion between the United kingdom military Mission in Washington and the United States authorities of common defence problems which arise in those Colonies where bases have been leased tothe United States. Joint defence plans for the various islands will have to bedrawn up, and discussions between the British Military Mission and the UnitedStates authorities on certain joint principles common to all Colonies will be heldin Washington during June.(iii) East A frica.Proposals have been under consideration (and have been approved since theend of the month under review) for raising pioneer labour units. It is proposedto recruit approximately 6.500 volunteers for service in Africa or the Near East.28. French Colonies.Vichy Consular Representatives.As a reprisal for the expulsion of British Consular representatives from Syriathe following action has been taken : (a) In Palestine all Vichy Consular offices have been closed and the Consularstaffs required to leave the territory. Two Consular officers haveelected to join the Free French movement.(b) Elsewhere in Colonies where there are still Vichy Consular representa-tives, their cypher and censorship privileges have been withdrawn. an exception has, however, been made in the case of the French consular representatives in the Straits Settlements and Hong Kong, in viewof the fact that British Consular representatives are still allowed to function freely in Indo-China.29. Wartime Economic Policy in the Colonies.A circular despatch is being issued summarising various important aspectsof economic policy which should be pursued in the Colonial Empire at the present stage of the war.  The following are the chief points : (a) The contribution to the war effort of the wealthier classes in the Coloniescan be increased by reducing their demands on the productive resources of the Empire and of America, in particular by muchstricter licensing of non-essential imports and by the increase of direct taxation.(b) Should Colonial Governments impose taxation in order to reduce con-sumption without respect to their immediate revenue needs, the resultmay be to create surpluses. If it is decided that these surpluses canbe placed at the disposal of His Majesty&apos;s Government it should be byway of loans free of interest for the period of the war rather than of gifts. The amounts will thus be available to Colonial governments for financing Colonial development after the war.
(c) Our general responsibility for improving the standard of living of theless fortunate classes in the Colonial Empire must not be ignored, evenin present circumstances, and plans of development which can go oneven now without a substantial call upon material and personnel from outside the Colonies should not be held up. This applies particularly to schemes under the Colonial Development and Welfare Act, 1940,and it has been made clear that the Secretary of State and theTreasury will be prepared to consider any such schemes, subject tothe above qualification.30. Import Control.Further instructions have been sent by telegram to the majority of theColonies requesting them to tighten up their import control procedure so as to economise in shipping and productive capacity. This telegram asked for astricter control of imports from non-sterling sources, and also for the first timerequested that imports from sterling sources, including the United Kingdom,should be controlled.Arrangements are now complete whereby all Colonial orders for Unmanufactured-factured or semi-manufactured iron and steel must be passed through the Iron andSteel Control who allocate them either to this country or to the United States(generally to the latter).31. Middle East Supply Centre.This Centre, which has now been set up in Cairo under the chairmanship of Sir Alexander Keown-Boyd, is co-ordinating supply and demand in theEastern Mediterranean, including Malta, Cyprus and Palestine. arrangements have also been made for it to avail itself of the productive capacity of EastAfrica, if need be, and correspondence is now proceeding with a view to bringing the Colony and Protectorate of Aden within ita scope.32. Rubber.The demand from the United States, both for a reserve stock and for current consumption, continues on a very high level, and the permissible exportableamount under the Regulation Scheme for the third quarter of the current year has been maintained at 100 per cent, of the standard figure fixed for the first twoquarters. This represents unrestricted production at the present time. Allrubber for the United Kingdom for stock and manufacturers&apos; needs is nowpurchased by the Rubber Controller.The United States also contemplates centralising all buying in the RubberReserve Company, and negotiations through the United States Embassy as to how this is to be put into effect are proceeding.33. Tin.The quota under the Tin Regulation Scheme remains at 130 per cent, of thestandard tonnages, in order to supply the American demand. Negotiations forthe renewal of the International Tin Agreement, which expires at the end of thecurrent year, are proceeding very slowly.Reports on Particular Colonies.34. East Africa.Both Uganda and Zanzibar have now accepted in principle the imposition ofan excess profits tax.35. West Indies.(i) Recruitment of Seamen.At the instance of the Ministry of War Transport, arrangements are inprogress for the recruitment of West Indian seamen for the Merchant Navy upto a total of 300 men in the first instance.  The agreement would be for a period[22631] d
of twelve months with the option of renewal or repatriation. A hostel is to beset up for their reception while in this country on leave or otherwise.(ii) Munition Workers.Arrangements for bringing to this country further parties of West Indianskilled tradesmen for the munitions industry are proceeding. The men will comefrom Jamaica (mainly) and British Guiana. This is apart from the recruitment of tradesmen for the Army which is also proceeding36. Trinidad.The changes previously announced in the composition of the LegislativeCouncil, involving a substantial reduction in the official membership and anincrease in the elected representatives, were brought into effect on the 16th May.37. Malaya.In the early part of the month strikes, accompanied by methods of intimidate-tion, broke out among Indian rubber workers employed in the district of Klangin the Federated State of Selangor, and later spread to some estates in NegriSembilan. Some 7,000 persons were involved, and it was found necessary to reinforce the police with troops. Two clashes resulted in five fatal casualties torioters, but on the 20th May the High Commissioner was able to report that the resumption of work was practically complete.As wages for Indian estate labourers have never been so high as at present,the High Commissioner reports -that there was no obvious economic justification for the strike, but the district has been subject to propaganda of adherents of theCentral Indian Association of Malaya, which professes sympathy with Congressviews, and one of the men concerned, against whom there was clear evidence ofsubversive propaganda, had been arrested with a view to banishment. The HighCommissioner considered that the cessation of work was intended to secure thisman&apos;s release.  He was deported to India on the 19th May.The High Commissioner is examining grievances put forward by thelabourers.38. Mauritius.The Government of Mauritius has received demands for the raising offurther Pioneer Units for service with the military forces in the Middle East.These demands are being met, and, with a view to possible future demands andto the better organisation of the supply of skilled men, a system of compulsoryregistration is being introduced.The Colony has recently voted a further sum of about  6,000, which, inconjunction with the sum already contributed, will provide a full flight ofSpitfires.39. Malta.During May reports were received from the Malta Government regardingthe effects of the intensive air raids which the Colony experienced during the months of March and April. There were in this period 15 raids by day and 23by night. Considerable damage was done to house property and to importantbuildings. The main street of Valletta suffered severely, but damage wasAvidespread. St. John&apos;s Cathedral, the Law Courts, three banks and the FlorianaCentral Hospital Avere all hit, and 714 houses were demolished or badly damaged.Civilian casualties were light, OAving partly to the extensive eA^acuation of thepopulation from the danger areas and partly to the increasing provision of deepshelters. The civilian casualties during March and April were : killed 78,seriously injured 53. The total civilian casualties from the llth June, 1940, tothe 30th April&quot;, 1941, Avere : killed 274, seriously injured 204. Buildings, whollyor partly destroyed during the same period, numbered 1,901. The GoA^ernor has reported that these intensive raids have hardened the people, who are facing their difficulties with cheerfulness and fortitude. A message of encouragement,addressed to the people of Malta from His Majesty&apos;s Government, was published in the Colony in the third week of May, and was recei\red with great satisfaction.
The King has approved General Sir William Dobbie&apos;s appointment asGovernor of Malta. He has hitherto been administering the Government in anacting capacity.40. Cyprus.The fall of Crete has brought Cyprus within the areas which must beregarded as liable to enemy attack at any time. Active measures are being takento strengthen the civil defence services. On the advice of the Governor, con-siderable dispersion of the population is taking place. Arrangements are beingmade to evacuate (1) the Polish refugees who were accommodated in the Islandlast autumn (about 500 in number); (2) some 600 Jews who have established themselves there; and (3) the wives and families of British officials, and any other british people who wish to leave. These people are being sent, in the firstinstance, to Palestine.The morale of the civil population is low; there have been some strikes, whichare symptomatic rather of a general apprehension and distrust of the Govern-ment than of industrial unrest. The policy which should be followed in regardto the defence of Cyprus has recently been reviewed by the Committee of Defence.41. Gibraltar.Lord Gort succeeded General Sir Clive Liddell as Governor and Commander-in-Chief of Gibraltar on the 14th May.The evacuation of the civil population from Gibraltar is still proceeding,and about 1,250 additional civilians are being sent to this country. Of these, some350 have arrived; 500 are on the high seas; and the balance are expected to leaveGibraltar during June.42. Aden Protectorate.Friction in the Dar-al-Beidha district qa the frontier between the aden protectorate and the Yemen continues owing to the obstructive attitude of theoccupant of a local &quot; fort,&quot; who, although a native of the Protectorate, is apparently receiving a certain amount of local Yemeni support. His diversion of water-courses and his armed defiance of the Protectorate authority haveaggravated a dispute which it was hoped to settle by amicable discussion withthe Yemeni authorities. It is proposed, if necessary, to take air action againstthe recalcitrant &quot; fort.&quot;43. Palestine.Little interest was shown in the Iraq coup cVEtat. Outwardly, the Arabswere, on the whole, calm, but there was a good deal of wild talk, alarm andexpectancy. In some areas it was reported that there had been a certain swingof opinion towards anti-British feeling, but there had been no outward manifes-tations of any change of heart. Baghdad and other Axis broadcasts attempted to incite the Arabs to join in a Holy War against Britain or to avenge allegedwrongs. Certain Arab notables, including the Mufti, broadcast from Baghdad.The Mufti&apos;s broadcast was particularly virulent, and his supporters wereoptimistic about the chance of making trouble; but, as a whole, the Arab popula-tion of Palestine showed no desire to take any overt action.The use of Syrian aerodromes by German aircraft increased the tension, but did not otherwise affect the situation. Kashid Ali&apos;s lack of success was no doubta determining factor. Some felt that Rashid Ali and his associates had &quot; sold &quot;Arab Nationalism by embarking on an ill-timed adventure which might prejudice the Arab cause after the war. The lack of active support in Palestine for thisadventure, and the failure of disaffected elements to profit from our preoceupa-tions in Iraq and Syria may be ascribed to calculated motives rather than to anyabstract loyalty.The Jews showed great uneasiness, which in some areas bordered on panic;but subsequent indications were that the Prime Ministers speech had broughtencouragement and a calmer outlook.Apprehension regarding the future was the dominant feeling in the jewish community, and political groups, while no nearer to unity, have all been pre-
occupied with the question of Jewish self-defence. The Jewish Agency issuedvigorous appeals for Jewish recruitment in the British Forces, but the resultshave not been markedly successful.Recruiting continued to be sluggish, although latterly there was a modestimprovement in the intake of Jews.There was some increase in lawlessness as compared with the past fewmonths, but except for two isolated instances activities of gangs appear to becriminal, and not political. Substantial seizures of arms were made, including a secret Jewish cache of rifles, ammunition and explosives. The police have alsobeen successful against robber bands, notably after an impudent hold-up onNablus Road, when the offenders were arrested on the following day and thestolen property recovered.In Trans-Jordan public opinion was disturbed by German infiltration intoSyria. Movements of British Forces in and through Trans-Jordan did much to restore confidence, and a visit of several days by the Amir Abdullah to NorthernTrans-Jordan further improved matters.Great George Street, S.W. 1,June 23, 1941.

</content>
</cab>
