<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/165/22 images: 305-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PUBLIC EXPENDITURE TO 1976-77Memorandum by the Central Policy Review staff. In July, the Cabinet decided that the rate of growth of public expenditure between 1971-72 and 1976-77 should be restricted to3. 8 per cent per annum, and that the total for public expenditure in1976-77 should therefore not exceed  30, 300 million.2. The Chancellor of the Exchequer^ memorandum on public expenditure to 1976-77 (CP(72) 121) shows that this objective has not been achieved.    While methods may be found to deal with the problems ofpublic presentation in this year&apos;s White Paper, the real problems arestill unresolved.    The whole of the contingency reserve for the next fiveyears is for practical purposes completely mortgaged.    Even if everythingwent well, and there were no pressures for further expenditure, theGovernment would have no room to manoeuvre on public expenditure.3. In fact there will be obvious and growing pressures for increased expenditure, and there will be unforeseen events which may require futher increases.    In other words, the Government is over-committedon public expenditure, and there are serious risks that hasty and painfulcuts may be necessary later in the lifetime of the present Parliament or that the Government will fail to achieve its taxation objectives.4. There is probably little choice but to accept the present situationso far as this year&apos;s White Paper is concerned.    But the longer   theGovernment continues to allow the present over-commitment to run on,the more dangerous the situation will become.5. Between now and next year&apos;s Public Expenditure Survey (PESC)exercise, action must be taken which will reduce the rate of increase in public expenditure to an economically acceptable level, and to re-establish an adequate contingency reserve.    This will require Ministers, bothindividually and collectively, to re-examine priorities, to cut out marginalcommitments, and reduce the future growth rates of selected programmes to a tolerable level.    If this is done, next year&apos;s PESC exercise should bemanageable;  the adjustments could be made discreetly and to choicerather than publicly and arbitrarily;  and the Government would face thenext two years with room to manoeuvre on public expenditure.COPY NO     g cp(72) 12213 November, 1972CABINET
recommend agenda TIONS6. We therefore recommend that:-i.       Ministers should endorse the Chancellor of the exchequers proposals;ii.       action to bring the rate of increase of public expenditure down to an acceptable level and to re-establish an adequate contingency reserve, be put in hand before thenext PESC review.Cabinet Office13 November 19722


</content>
</cab>
