<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/170/19 images: 281-314</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(73) 79 COPY NO 6613 July 1973CABINETCOMPANY LAW REFORM: DRAFT WHITE paper note by the Minister for Trade and Consumer affairs. We have undertaken to introduce a major Companies Bill in the next session;  our proposals are awaited with keen interest.    The matters withwhich we propose that the Bill should deal have been considered in Homeand Social Affairs Committee (HS) and fall into three broad categories:-a. A number of apparent abuses have attracted pubHc attention in recent months: for example, insider dealing; the building upcovertly, of a dominant holding in another company in preparation for a takeover bid;  and exploiting the power of directors to syphonoff profitable activities to their private interests.    It has becomeurgently necessary to strengthen the law in such respects.b. Second, there remain from the Jenkins Committee Reportof 1962 a range of recommendations for which room was not foundin the relatively small Companies Act 1967; most of these retain their validity, and consultations with interested bodies have shownthat there would be support for legislation to deal with them,subject in some instances to modification in the light of experience.c. Third, there is a range of other matters, some of a largelytechnical nature, which have come to the attention of myDepartment in the course of administering the Companies Acts;these are all desirable, though of very varying importance -probably the most important being the late filing of company accounts.2.        A Bill embodying a., most of the rest of Jenkins as in b., and a selection of the more important parts of c., would be a well-balanced and important measure which would satisfy public expectations of a significantadvance in companies legislation.    I am of course conscious of the need to contain the size of the Bill and shall consult the Lord President of theCouncil as drafting proceeds.    I am hopeful, however, that a lot can beachieved by careful drafting and the use of schedules.3.        I propose the early publication of a White Paper, dealing with themost important of the matters to be covered and indicating the broad scopeof the Bill.    The White Paper would also have a &apos;green&apos; second part,dealing with major issues on which there is as yet no consensus of opinion and on which our own views are not yet fully elaborated.    These matters1
include the social responsibility of the company, the rights and duties ofinstitutional shareholders, and most particularly, worker participation,on which we have already proposed to issue a separate Green Paper later to which the White Paper can only be a trailer.    It is highly desirable thatthere should be real public debate on these matters, and that we should beseen to contribute to that debate in the light of our general philosophy.A copy of the last draft of the White paper is attached.4.        In the White Paper, I have sought to set these legislative proposals in the context of our determination to see that the private enterprisesystem operates fairly, openly and effectively; that is, that the law is designed to prevent discerned abuses, to require a high degree ofdisclosure of company affairs as the way of encouraging a sense of socialresponsibility, and to ensure that so far as possible within those statutorylimits individual enterprise is able to adapt quickly and profitably tochanging conditions and opportunities.    It is important to make these pointsclearly, in opposition to the restrictive philosophy held by our political opponents.5.        There are a number of related aspects v/hich I believe can be betterdealt with in the accompanying presentation and Press briefing than in the body of the White Paper - eg. material on why Lonrho and Sir Denis Lowsonare not typical, why tax havens are not readily available to companydirectors, and so on.    I have, however, referred in the present draft tothe need to eliminate abuses as soon as they are identified.6.        The White Paper as redrafted takes account of substantial commentmade by colleagues in HS, and by the Parliamentary Secretary, CivilService Department.    In particular, the Introduction has been strengthenedto set the proposals iu the context of our general economic and socialpolicies; the references to disclosure have been expanded, with an indication of the existing statutory provisions and how they can usefully beextended; a section on international companies has been introduced;  and Ihave introduced specific references to disclosure of high directors&apos; and management salaries, &quot;perks&quot; and the like.    The present version alsotakes account of consultations my officials have had with outside advisersin the City and the legal and accountancy professions.7.        A major concern in preparing a substantial measure of company law reform must be to ensure that it is compatible with our Europeanobligations;  this I have been careful to do.    I am satisfied that none ofthe provisions of the Bill are prejudicial to our policies on harmonisationof company law, or will lead our European Economic Community partnersto suspect that we are ignoring our obligations or their interests;  and Iam arranging for a senior official to discuss the proposals with officials ofthe Commission at the time of publication of the White Paper, as areassurance.2
8. I ask my colleagues to approve the publication of a White Paper assoon as possible on the lines of the attached draft; the date I provisionallyhave in mind is Wednesday 25 July, two days before the Recess.    It wouldbe published on the basis of an arranged Parliamentary Question and theSecretary of State and I intend to give full Press, television and radiobriefing.    In view of the tight timetable it would be helpful to have any comments of substance quickly, in advance of discussion in Cabinet.G HDepartment of Trade and Industry12 July 19733
COMPANY LAW REFORM CONFIDENTIAL DRAFT WHITE PAPERINTRODUCTION1.      Her Majesty&apos;s Government believe that a healthy free enterprise system isessential to the success of our mixed economy, in this setting free enterprise hasfulfilled the British desire for freedom and capacity for responsibility in an increasingly better educated, better informed society.   It has demonstrated aunique capacity for promoting innovation, and a flexibility that responds tomar^s ever-changing demands and potential.   But any system, however good, mustadapt to change.   The rules that govern it must relate to the social and economicconditions of the time.   It remains the continuing task of government to make sure that the impetus of the system continues to be harnessed to the real needsof the nation and to the interests of all its people.2.      In this free enterprise system, it is the limited liability company thatprovides the framework through which the savings of individual citizens arechannelled both directly,and indirectly through institutions such as pensionfunds and banks, into the industry and commerce of the country.   It enablescapital to be accumulated and invested in risk-taking enterprises, which createeconomic expansion, provide jobs and produce goods and services.   As circum-stances alter, this framework needs to be changed. The same is true of many ofour institutions and many of the day to day relationships which have long beentaken for granted.   It applies to the relationship between consumer and supplier,which is why the Government have introduced a new Fair Trading law.   It applies to the relationship between worker and management, which is why the Governmentintroduced a new Industrial Relations law.   It applies to the institution ofthe limited liability-company - which.is why the Government now bring forward proposals for the reform of Company-Law.3.       In formulating these proposals, the Government give specificrecognition to the fact that management and ownership of a companymeans accepting the responsibilities as well as the rewards, and thata company owes a duty to the society of which it forms a part.This means that company directors have a manifest obligation towards all
CONFIDENTIALthose with whom they have dealings - and none more so than towards their employees.   It is for this reason that, in addition to these proposals, theGovernment intend to publish later this year a separate Green Paper whichwill discuss proposals for the closer involvement of employees in companyaffairs.If the system of competitive enterprise is to thrive, it must be open and based upon integrity.   If it is not, it will forfeit public confidence,and it will fail.   This is why the Government attach such importance to theneed to guide the concept of &apos;the company1 into modes of thought and linesof action that correspond with modern needs, producing responsibilitywithout timidity.confidential
confidential      The government will therefore be introducing in the next session ofParliament a new Companies Bill.   The principal reasons for introducing this important measure are as follows;1      Many of the recommendations of the Jenkins Committee that werenot included in the 1967 Act have shown themselves still to bevalid and important,ii      There has been growing appreciation of the need for fullerdisclosure of information by companies both as a spur to efficiency and safeguard against malpractice,iii      The arcangements for uncovering and dealing with commercial crimeand malpractices have proved to be inadequate in a number ofrespects.iv      The existing classification of companies needs to be adapted tothe needs of the present day.-v      Issues of social responsibility, both towards employees in a company and to the community at large, have rightly come muchto the fore in public discussion, and there is a need to consider how far it is desirable and practicable to take account of theseby statutory means.6      Increasingly, this aspect of our national life will be affected bythe developing policies of the e.c., and the Government will seek to influencethat development in ways that   will   contribute to a prosperous Community.A separate section of this paper considers some of the opportunities and problems of e.c. membership.   Commercial practice will have to be flexible and quick in its response to this change of environment, and company lawwill need to be of a kind that enables and indeed encourages that response..7      On some of these matters the Government already have a settled view and their proposals for legislation are firm, though the details of someof the proposals remain to be worked out.   On other matters a reasonableconsensus of opinion does not yet exist: and the Governments purpose is to*   Which reported in June 1962 (Cmnd. 17^9) referred to throughout this paper as * Jenkins1)
CONFIDENTIALstimulate informed debate.    To the extent that this debate results quicklyin a good measure of agreement it may be possible to embody the outcome inthe forthcoming legislation.   This Paper is therefore written in two parts -first describing the more important matters that will appear in the proposed bill, and second, setting out those matters on which there is a need forfurther information and debate.PART ONE - THE COMPANIES BILL8 In recent months, the Department of Trade and Industry have consulteda wide range of representative   bodies on the main matters covered in the irreview of company law.   Paragraphs 10 to 51 below set out only the major points which the Government intend to include in the Bill.    In addition the Bill will include a substantial body of other proposals recommended by the JenkinsCommittee, and will also deal with a number of matters, some of general andsome of largely technical importance which have come to the attention of theDTI on the course of their administration of the Companies Acts.THE JENKINS committee      The last systematic, independent review of Company Law was undertaken by the Jenkins Committee, which reported in June 1962.Some of the Committee&apos;s recommendations wereincorporated in the Companies Act 1967, but much of the Report remains tobe dealt with.   Apart from certain particular matters discussed in separatesections of this paper, the considerations governing the Committee&apos;conclusions have not significantly changed, and the Government therefore consider that one of the main objects of the next Companies Bill shouldbe to enact substantially all the remaining Jenkins recommendations foramendments to the Companies Acts.   Certain of the more important of these recommendations on which the Government will propose legislation - not alwaysin the precise form recommended by Jenkins - are described later in this Paper.DISCLOSURE10 Disclosure of information is an essential part of the working of a free and fair economic system. Obviously there are limits - imposed, for example, by theneed to preserve commercial confidentiality in a competitive situation.   But the confidential
bias must always be towards disclosure, with the burden of proof thrown on those who defend secrecy.   The more people can see what is actually happening,the less likely they are to harbour general suspicions - and the lessopportunity there is for concealing improper or even criminal activities.Openness in company affairs is the first principle in securing responsiblebehaviour.11     The Government already have substantial powers under the existing statutesto require further disclosure in company accounts.   In particular, existing lawrequires full disclosure of the rates at which directors and senior employees are paid.   The figures must include not only cash payment but also all other kinds of reward; and there is power to add to the degree of disclosure in the accountsin this, and other respects.   The Government intend to seek, a similar power inrespect of directors&apos; reports, and then to use these two powers in concert torequire companies to report a much wider range of matters than they now have todo.   Disclosure is the best method of tackling a number of the problems mentionedin the following paragraphs.12    For quoted and large private companies these powers will be used by theGovernment to give shareholders and the public the chance to judge companies1behaviour by social as well as financial criteria.   As possible examples, the directors may be required to report on the performance of their company in regardto the safety and health of the company&apos;s employees, on the number of consumercomplaints and how they were dealt with, on improvements in the workingenvironment, and on the conduct of industrial relations.   The directors will berequired to include in their report certain particulars of their own contracts ofservice; of their other interests; of any dealings they have in the company&apos;sshares; and of transactions by the company and other companies in which theyhave any significant interest.   Most of this information is already requiredto be shown in a publicly   available record.   It is desirable that it shouldbe given in the annual report rather than merely being available to those who can go to examine it.   It may also be desirable to require the directors to disclose more fully than is now the case, details of significant materialCONFIDENTIAL5, 1
acquisitions, realisations and contracts since the previous year.   For smallerprivate companies the same levels of disclosure are not appropriate because there is no element of investment by the general public and the public interest is not involved to the same extent.   For such companies also the burden ofdisclosure is greater and the commercial dangers may be greater.INTERNATIONAL ENTERPRISES13    With the progressive reduction of barriers to international trade and investment, and the increasing scale of modern technology, there has been aconsiderable growth in enterprises or groupings of companies able to seek outcommercial opportunities on an international scale.   These enterprises are astrong force for economic growth at both the national and international levels,but they also raise certain issues for national governments which need to be resolved on an international level.   To this end the Government are involved in pursuing discussions in the appropriate international bodies.l*f    The principle of openness needs to be applied to international enterprisesas to national ones.   In reviewing the general disclosure requirements in theUnited Kingdom, the Government will pay particular attention to the publicinterest in information about the activities of these enterprises, bearing inmind the contribution that they make to the national economy.   The Governmentwill also take account of disclosure requirements in the e.c. and elsewhere,and of any recommendations which may result from the studies being carriedout in the United Kingdom and in various international bodies.   United Kingdomdisclosure requirements are already more extensive than those of most otheradvanced countries.   The Government&apos;s aim is to secure improvements in boththe quality and the comparability of information available in all member countries of the e.c. and of the OECD about the activities of internationalenterprises.
INSIDER DEALINGS15     Unfair profits can on occasion be made in share dealings by the improperuse of confidential, price-sensitive information that is not generallyavailable to the investing public.     This is prima facie most likely to happen in a bid, or expected bid, situation, but in principle it can happenat any time.     The efficient operation of the market as a source of capital,as a measure of industrial success and hence as a means of achieving a desirable and efficient disposition of resources, requires that relevant information should be fairly available, and that all investors should be ableto back their knowledge and judgment rather than that favoured individualsshould be able to take private advantage of confidential information.These requirements have so far been fulfilled by the application of the rules of the Stock Exchange and, in bid situations,   by the Take-Over Panel.Without implying that   malpractice has been widespread, the Government have concluded that it is necessary for the voluntary system to be reinforced by statute so as to ensure, as far as practically possible, that the marketoperates freely on the basis of equality between buyer and seller.     Caremust of course be taken to avoid unduly inhibiting the flexibility of themarket.     But the general desirability of ensuring equality of information to all potential or actual investors, and hence a proper disposition of theresources available to those investors, must have a high priority.     Thesuccessful operation of the system demands a high degree of confidence in fairdealing on the Stock Exchange, and indeed in securities generally, whether ornot publicly quoted.16     Many experienced and responsible organisations have recently given advice on this subject (for instance, Justice, the Take-Over Panel and the stock exchange, and the City of London Solicitors1 Company).     The subject is discussed (in relation only to dealings by directors) in paras 88 and 99 ofJenkins.     In the light of all these considerations, the Government have concluded that in principle insider dealings should be made the subject of a criminal offence. j
17    The object of legislation on insider dealing must be to ensure that anyone who is in possession of information which would be likely, if generally known, to have a materially significant effect on the price of the relevantsecurities refrains from dealing until the material information has properlybeen made generally available.     It is no part of the purpose of legislation toinhibit normal and honest transactions.18    There are two main problems to be resolved in drafting the legislation.The first is the definition of an &quot;insider&quot;.     It is important to avoid anunfairly onerous restriction on normal transactions by people who have no direct relationship with the company or its officers.     The definition should,in the Government&apos;s view, include directors, senior employees and professionaladvisers of a company, together with the near-relations of each of these people.     Secondly there is the question whether an offence is committed byan insider only when he deals with the guilty intent of profiting from insideinformation, or simply when he deals, having inside information at the sametime.     The Governments view is that dealing in a company&apos;s securities byanyone who, by reason of his relationship with the company or with its officers, has information which he knows to be price-sensitive, should be a criminal offence unless he can show that his primary intention in dealing atthat particular time was not to make a profit or avoid a loss.19     There is also the question of civil liability.     An insider deal of thiskind will normally have involved one party in taking unfair advantage overanother, by misusing information relating to a company or companies.     Inprinciple someone who profits unfairly in this way should be liable at law tothe other parties concerned - the person with whom he dealt, and the company in whose securities he dealt or whose information he used in so doing.     Thelaw should therefore confer a civil remedy on persons who can establish that by reason of the misuse   of materially significant information they have suffered an identifiable loss.     Similarly, the law should preserve thepresent liability whereby an insider may be accountable for his profit tothe company. confidential
20    Steps need to be taken in addition to ensure that more knowledge ismade available to shareholders about transactions by directors in the quotedshares of their company.     A director who deals in his company^ shares, isnot obliged by the present requirements of the law to bring such transactionsto the shareholders&apos; attention for some considerable time.     Ss.27-29 of theCompanies Act 1967 require notification within 14 days, and require thecompany to keep a public register of such transactions.     The government propose to require notification to the company within the shortest practicableperiod.     A valuable offer of help in this connexion has been made by the stock exchange, which has undertaken to publish details of such transactions if thelaw is amended to require notice to be given simultaneously there alsc.     Suchdealing is normally wholly innocent, and publicity is the best means of ensuring that it is so.NOMINEE SHAREHOLDINGS.21    There is nothing inherently wrong in the practice of holding sharesthrough nominees, and indeed there are many circumstances in which thepractice is both normal and convenient on commercial or personal grounds.Furthermore, there is a large and complex area of common law and the law oftrusts which would be involved in any attempt to forbid the practice even if that were thought desirable.     The Government recognise that there is a degree of public concern about the subject, and have considered carefullywhat may be the circumstances in which concealment of a beneficial interestin a holding can be undesirable.     They have concluded that there is one areaof commercial activity where new legislation is required.22     Warehousing1 is a situation in which a number of parties act inundisclosed concert, not sufficiently close to bring them within the existing provisions, each acquiring an interest in the equity of a company (below thefigure of 10% which is the threshold&apos; at which notification to the company is required by S.33 of the Companies Act 1967) thus enabling one or more ofthem to acquire by stealth a dominant position in that company.     This is
10CONFIDENTIALusually, though not necessarily, in preparation for a bid which the company to be taken over is by then unable to resist.     The Government intend todeal with this situation in two ways:   first by lowering significantly thethreshold percentage at which an individual holding has to be notified tothe company, and second by requiring such notification to be much quicker.23 The present 10% threshold of notification is too high: it is in generalunlikely that one investor would acquire such a size of holding in the normal course of managing his investments without the deliberate intention of becomingdominant.     Even 5% normally represents a substantial holding in any one company:   the Government propose to reduce the notification figure to atleast that level.     The time allowed for notification (including notification of further changes once the minimum level has been reached) should be theminimum consistent with practical operation.     These requirements shouldmake it almost impossible in practice for a few parties acting in loose buteffective concert to build up a position of strength without revealing thefact.24    A company which has any reason to fear that it may be the subject of abid, or that a Warehousing&apos; situation may be developing, ought to have aright to know the real identity of its owners.   The Government therefore propose to give every company a right reasonably (ie not vexatiously orcapriciously) to demand to know who are the beneficial as opposed to the nominal owners of its shares.   An enquiry which ultimately leads to a nomineeacting for a person overseas, is unlikely to get any further;   but even that information may be inferentially if not directly useful.
PRIVATE INTERESTS OF DIRECTORS25        The present law imposes three separate duties on directors to discloseinterests in the contracts of their company, namely: disclosure at the general meetingsunder the general law (from which the company&apos;s articles may release them);disclosure, under S.199 of the Companies Act 19^8, to the directors;   and disclosureto the general meeting and to the public through the directors&apos; report, under -Ss.l6(l) and 23 of the Companies Act 1967.26        Jenkins considered this problem, and made certain recommendations;   inparticular, that there should be a statutory restatement of the basic   fiduciaryrelationship between a director and his company (ii(a));   that the disclosureprovisions of S.199 should be clarified and strengthened (99(i) and (m));   thatagreements for the management of the company  should be filed with the Registar if a director has an interest (99(n));   and that directors should disclose their interestin resolutions put before the general meeting (h6&quot;J and U68(i)).   The Government agreewith the intention of all these recommendations;   a statutory declaration of a director&apos;s duty, and a strengthening of thedi sclosure requirements in these matters,is desirable.27        Moreover, in certain respects, the combination of a fiduciary duty and ofa duty to disclose may not be enough.   There are some categories of transaction which pose such clear conflicts of interest for directors of companies that they should be forbidden.   The details will require carefulformulations, since it is important not to impose restrictions on normal andwholly innocent transactions.    In these circumstances the Government intend ifpossible to legislate in respect of situations where directors seek to syphonoff profitable business to their private advantage.11
COMPANIES REGISTRATION OFFICE:   FILING OF COMPANY ACCOUNTS28        Limited liability is a substantial privilege which given considerable-personal immunity to those who run companies.   Prompt and full disclosure of accounts, which is the only protection given to creditors, is the very least whichmust be expected in return.   Consequently the present Acts require accounts to belaid before a company in general meeting each year and an annual return to be madeto the Registrar.   The Annual Return must include a copy of the accounts so laidduring the period to which the Return relates.   This is a most important obligation of central importance to the proper working of the capital market and to the main-tenance of normal trading relations.   There is obviously however a massive difficultyin enforcing these provisions over the very large field represented by all limited liability companies.   The position is not improved by the fact that the presentprovisions allow the latest accounts filed with the Registrar to relate, in extremecases, to events nearly 3 years old.   This is not a satisfactory situation.   Further-more, a very sizeable proportion of companies on the register - possibly as many as250,000 - are at any one time late in filing their annual returns or the accountswhich should accompany them.   This essential safeguard of the law must not continueto be disregarded.   The administrative burden and the expense of pursuing thesedefaulters is heavy, at a time when the Registrar is experiencing serious difficultyin coping with the recent unprecedented increase in the rate of formation of newcompanies (many such companies do not trade, since they are held by agents for subsequent sale, or are registered merely to protect a trading name).   penalties for late filing are prescribed (the maximum is  5 for each day of default); however,experience   shows that the average fine imposed varies from about  5 to about  30.The fines actually imposed for annual return offences therefore bear little relationto the potential maximum fine (which may amount to over  1,000 per charge) and varywidely from court to court.29        The Government propose to legislate on this matter in two respects.   First, itis proposed to create a specific obligation to file annual accounts with the registrar, and to prescribe with some strictness the period after the end of the
company&apos;s financial year within which that must be done.   This will substantiallyreduce the time-lag that is at present possible.    Second, the practical inadequacy ofthe present enforcement provisions must be remedied.   New provisions will be made for creating an incentive on directors to file accounts without delay, and for altering the present penalties so that the consequences of delay bear increasingly heavily,and directly, upon those who are responsible - the directors.THE STRUCTURE OF INCORPORATION30        The privilege of limited liability is now available both readily and cheaply.Jenkins recognised (para 20) that the proliferation of very small companies &quot;can anddoes1 lead to abuse, and made some proposals about registration fees (adopted inthe 1967 Act) for checking it.   However, the proliferation has increased in the last decade.   For example, there were 21,500 new applications for registration in thefour months to the end of May 1975 compared with 15,000 in the same period last year,and the number of companies on the Register was at the end of 1972 approximately600,000 compared with 577,000 at the same time a year before, and with 444,000 atthe end of 1962.   In the period 1844-1871, regarded as the great period of companyformation, there were 7,000 incorporations altogether, of which 4,000 survived in1871.   There has been, rightly, increasing emphasis on the degree of public dis-closure required of companies.   But the public interest does not require the same amount of disclosure (involving the same amount  of administration by the company and by the DTI) from the smaller as from the larger company.   There is therefore acase for grading the disclosure requirements, and the administrative effort both by companies themselves and by Government, in relation to the size and status of theindividual company.   These facts call for a reconsideration of the Jenkins con-clusions, and have led to a re-examination of the structure of incorporation.   Thatre-examination has suggested a need for considerable clarification of the status of&quot;public&apos; and &quot;private&apos; companies.   The proliferation problem thus falls to be dealt
CONFIDENTIALv/ith alongside the more important problem of clarifying the implications ofincorporation.31       Despite the Jenkins conclusion (para 67) that there should be no distinctionin the Companies Acts in the treatment of public and private companies, theGovernment believe that there remains a valid and important difference between, atthe one extreme,a company that owes a wide duty to its numerous shareholders, tothe investing public as   potential shareholders, to creditors and indeed to thepublic interest at large, and at the other, a company that owes a duty more narrowlyto its creditors (who might for the most part be its current trading partners) and toa restricted number of members.   This distinction is broadly reflected in the presentclassification of the   public and private company and to some extent in the differentdegrees of disclosure required of companies of differing size.   The present statutorydefinition in S.28 of the Companies Act 19^8 however only specifies three limitingcriteria which in combination mark a private company;   a public company is thus de-fined only by exclusion.   Moreover, the differences betv/een the large public and private companies and between the small public and private companies do not reflect the differences in their economic significance or in their responsibilities.32        The Government propose to redefine the status of a private company in a way which will give statutory effect to existing practice and which will require thatstatus to be made explicit in the company&apos;s title, and also to define explicitlythe term &apos;public company&apos;.    In addition, a public company should be required to havea minimum paid-up capital.   This has two objectives - to correspond to one of theindicia of a public company (in French terms, an S.A., or in German, an A.G. ) whichthe e.c. are proposing to adopt, and to ensure, as the e.c. are seeking to do, thatany company having public status has a reasonable minimum level of resources - on present proposals, 25,000 units of account, approximately  10,000.   It would then bepossible to define disclosure requirements by reference to either the size or thestatus of the company. Jenkins recognised (paragraph 27) that as a protection tocreditors, a minimum level of paid-up capital could be readily evaded and so was largely illusory.   The Government nevertheless believe that there is sufficient value in the provision, partly as a protection and partly as a deterrent to frivolousincorporations^to make legislati^iQr^d^l^j.!! AL
also be desirable to require a mininum paid-up capital for a private company -obviously by comparison low (say,  1,000).   The arguments for that course arefirst, that it would ensure some minimum financial substance as a properqualification for the protection of limited liability, and second, that it wouldsharply discourage the registration of companies which are not going to trade.   Atpresent many companies are registered for &quot;shelf&quot; or name-protection purposes.   Asfar as the Registrar is concerned such companies vanish into limbo.   He is requiredto pursue fruitlessly an organisation with possibly no traceable directors, probablyno correct address, and certainly no intention of answering letters.   The argument against such a change is the possibility that the elimination of the very smallprivate company would have an adverse effect on the economic life of small tradersand small firms with a useful potential for growth.3k        What may be needed is an additional form of incorporation, which does not give lightly the privilege of limited liability (with its attendant need for a significant degree of disclosure) but which does afford the benefits of incorporation(real or apparent) to the small traders to whom they are of value.   The privilege of limited liability is not inseparable from the fact of incorporation, as witness theunlimited company.   Some argue that limited liability is often a myth for the smallman.   His sources of funds are trade debts and borrowing from a bank or finance house.The Report of the Committee of inquiry on Small Firms in 1971* for instance, saidthat bank credit formed the greater part of external finance for small firms.   Ifthe small trader does not have enough tangible assets to reach the fairly low thresh-hold suggested in the preceding paragraph, then it is probable that his creditorswill seek a charge on his personal assets despite his, theoretical, limited liability.On the other hand, the benefits of incorporation may be real - particularly, con-discontinuity of legal personality.   It is not easy to assess whether there would be asizable   legitimate demand for some new &quot;small man form of incorporation whichwould not attract the registration fees and disclosure requirements appropriate to public and private limited companies as newly defined.   It is important to seekevidence about the desirability of providing some additional corporate structure* Cmnd **8llCONFIDENTIAL15
for the small trader before coming to a conclusion on the question of a minimumfigure for private as well as for public companies.   It may well be that themachinery provided by the Partnership Act of i89o, or the Limited Partnership act of 19.07, or the unlimited company, is already sufficient, or could be made so bysuitable amendment.
THE REST OF JENKINS35       As already mentioned, the next Companies Bill will seek to enact most ofthe outstanding Jenkins recommendations insofar as they relate to the CompaniesActs.   Paragraphs 36 to      describe some of the more important of these recommendations which it is proposed to modify in the light of more recent experience,i   DISQUALIFICATION OF DIRECTORS (AMENDMENT TO Sl88 OF THE COMPANIES ACT 19^8 )36       This Section empowers the court to.disqualify a person for a maximum of5 years from being a director, or concerned in the management, of any company,if he is convicted on indictment of any offence connected with the formation,promotion or management of a company, or if, in a winding-up, it appears thatwhile being an officer of the company he has been guilty of an offence under S332(fraudulent trading) or of any fraud or breach of duty to the company.   The Sectionhas been criticised for being too narrow.   Jenkins recommended (para 85 (b)) that itshould be extended to cover persons who have been convicted on indictment of anyoffence involving fraud or dishonesty whether or not in connection with a company,who have been persistently in default in complying with the Companies Acts, or whohave shown themselves when acting as director of a company or otherwise concernedin its management, to have acted in an improper, reckless or incompetent manner inrelation to its affairs.   The Committee acknowledged that it might be difficult todecide in any particular case whether a director had acted so recklessly orincompetently that he should no longer be allowed to remain a director, but they thought that the court should be able to put a stop to the activities of someonewho had, for example, * succeeded in steering a series of companies into insolvency&apos;.They also recommended that, in cases where the person concerned was sentenced to a term of imprisonment for the offence for which he was disqualified, the court shouldhave power to disqualify for 5 years after the end of the term and not onlyconcurrently with it.IT
57      The Government propose to give effect to these recommendations with theexception of the proposal that disqualification should be possible when a personhad been shown to be incompetent (as opposed to being guilty of impropriety orrecklessness).    &quot;Incompetence1 per se is not a matter which can be easily defined in law or readily determined by a court.   A course of conduct leading to disasterin the face of clear warnings, may well be &quot;reckless1 in an identifiable sense, butto allow for disqualification solely on grounds of incompetence would go unwiselyfar.ii   PROTECTION OF MINORITIES (AMENDMENT TO S210 OF THE COMPANIES ACT 19^8)38      This Section allows a member of a company who complains that its affairs arebeing conducted in an oppressive manner, to petition the court for an order;-*ifthe court is satisfied that the complaint is justified, and that to wind up thecompany would be justified on the facts but would be unfair to the oppressed, itmay make any order it thinks fit.   Jenkins (para 200) considered that this Sectionof the Act provided inadequate protection for the interests of minority shareholdersand that the relevant case law had demonstrated as much.   They recommended (para 212)that the court should not be required to be satisfied that the facts were such as tojustify a winding-up order; nor that to wind up the company would unfairly prejudice the oppressed minority.   It should be sufficient to show that the affairs of thecompany were being conducted in a manner unfairly prejudicial, and not necessarilyoppressive, to the minority.   The Section should cover isolated acts falling short of a course of conduct; and the court should be enabled to restrain the commissioner continuance of any act that would suffice to support a petition under the Section.They recommended moreover that the court should be given express power, where itthinks fit, to authorise the bringing of proceedings in the name of the companyagainst a third party on such terms as the court might direct.   They also proposed(para 212 (f) and (g)) that persons such as legal personal representatives, or the trustee in bankruptcy, to whom shares are transmitted in law but who are refusedregistration by the directors should have a right to present a petition or seek an injunction under S210 and, unless a prompt explanation is provided why they should18CONFIDENTIAL
not be registered, to registfJMNi, subject to the priority of pre-emptive rights in regard to the shares.39      The Government propose to accept these recommendations, but with some modification in detail.   In particular, they propose to extend the recommendations in para 212 (f) and (g) to cover persons to whom shares are transferred as well asthose to whom they are transmitted by process cf law (subject, insofar as (g) isconcerned, to the terms of any restriction in the articles of the company).   Further,the directors should be required, if they refuse to register, to serve upon theapplicant within 28 days of application a statement in writing setting out thereasons why it is not in the interests of the company that the applicant should be entered upon the register.   In default of such service, the directors should berequired to register the shares in the applicants name.   If the applicant considersthose reasons open to challenge, it will be open to him to apply to the court forrectification of the register under S116 of the Companies Act 19^8.iii   POWERS TO APPOINT INSPECTORS^0       At present the Secretary of State may appoint an inspector to investigate a company under Sl6*f of the 19^8 Act on the application of a prescribed number ofmembers or of members holding a prescribed number of shares.   Under Sl65(a) theSecretary of State must appoint an inspector upon a special resolution of thecompany concerned or an order of the court to that effect.   Under Sl65(b) theSecretary of State may appoint an inspector if it appears to him that there arecircumstances suggesting intention to defraud creditors, or fraud, misfeasance orother misconduct towards the company or its members, or oppression of a minority,or that the members have not been given all information that they might reasonably expect.   Ssl66-170 as amended by Ss35-k3 of the 1967 Act confer powers oninspectors and contain provisions as to reports, costs of investigations and proceedings resulting from them.19
hi      Certain of the Jenkins recommendations were included in the 196? Act.     Inaddition, they recommended (para 218) that SI65 of the Companies Act 19^8 shouldbe extended to require the Secretary of State to appoint inspectors if requestedto do so by 200 shareholders or holders of 23% of the issued shares of any class,unless he thought the application vexatious or considered that the applicantsalready had enough facts to enable them to take proceedings on their own behalf;that Sl6*f should be repealed; that SI65 powers should be extended to cover the inspection of other companies relevant to a company under investigation; thatcompanies should be required to preserve books and papers from the start of aninspection; and that Ssl68 and I69 should be amended in relatively minor ways.h2      These recommendations raise certain conflicting considerations.   On the onehand, it is essential that action by the Secretary of State should not be seen asa convenient substitute for appeal to the court, which is normally the proper course for an aggrieved individual.   On the other hand, shareholders may by the nature ofthe case be unable to establish the facts on which an action might be based, andthere may then be a public interest in an official inspection to establish thefacts.   Government ought not to try to cushion investors from the results of theirown decisions,   or to seek to intervene in the internal management of companies, bythe appointment of inspectors; however, the power to appoint must extend to all caseswhere there is reason to believe that there has been fraud, misfeasance or improprietyin the conduct of a company&apos;s affairs.   In each case, the Secretary of State has to judge where the public interest lies, and must be scrupulous to see that the powers are not used to support the pursuit of a wholly private interest.^3       Given these considerations, the Government do not propose to amend SI63 inthe way suggested or to repeal Sl6*f; there is still a place for a power (as opposedto an obligation) to appoint inspectors when a body of shareholders seek an investigation.   The cost of an investigation can be very considerable.   Where an appointment is made under SI65 there is no power, nor should there be, to requirethe applicants to contribute to its cost; but where an investigation is started atthe instance of shareholders it is reasonable to have the power to require the20
applicants to contribute to the cost, though the power might not always be used.It should not be mandatory for an appointment to be made and an investigationcarried out at the public expense or at the expense of the company on theapplication of a minority of shareholders.hk    The upper limit of  100 which the applicants under Sl6h may be required togive as security for their contribution to the cost of the investigation should beremoved, and applicants should in appropriate cases be required to give securityreasonably related to the probable cost.A number of other relatively minor amendments to the existing powers are desirable, designed to meet difficulties or criticisms that have emerged with experience.   These will be designed to improve the general operation of the existing powers, but not in ways which would seriously infringe the rights of the citizen.iv   FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE FOR PimCHASE OF OWN SHARES BY A COMPANY(S54 OF THE COMPANIES ACT 19^8)1,5      Jenkins recognised (paras I7O-I83) that the present form of S5*f had proved to bean occasional embarrassment to the honest without always being a serious obstacle to the unscrupulous; but since there had been some flagrant abuses, to the seriousdetriment of, particularly, minority shareholders, they recommended that the Sectionshould be retained and strengthened.   They sought to improve it by a requirement thata *Section 5^&apos; transaction would be unlawful unless (a) it had been approved by aspecial resolution and (b) a declaration of solvency had been filed with the Registrar(Jenkins para 187 (d)).l^y     The Government take the view that S^k fulfils a useful purpose in inhibitingunscrupulous transactions involving the acquisition of a company&apos;s shares withoutreasonable certainty that the buyer can obtain the resources necessary to acquirethem; and they are not convinced that the additional measures suggested by Jenkins-would necessarily be effective. The &quot;declaration of solvency&apos; might well not deterunscrupulous operator.   The suggested 12 months&apos; validity of the declaration would give him ample time to escape its consequences; and anyone advancing funds for a &quot;Section 5^&apos;transaction would be able to rely uncritically on its existence as a defence (forinstance, if charged with assisting in a breach of a director*s fiduciary duty toCONFIDEllVlAL
confidential the Government therefore intend to leave the main principle oi&apos; S5&apos;i intact.   However,they recognise the truth of the Jenkins argument that the present drafting can bean occasional embarrassment to legitimate transactions; tho prohibition is statedin very wide terms.   They are therefore examining whether suitable amendments canbe made to allow &apos;Section 5*f&apos; transactions in suitable circumstances, withoutopening the way for the kind of unscrupulous transaction mentioned above.1+8      The Government accept the intention of the Jenkins recommendations about provisos(b) and (c) of S5*f, that there is a good case for extending the potential benefit ofthe exemption from the general prohibition, to allow a company to assist its employees in buying shares not only in the company and its holding company but also in asubsidary.LIMITED VOTING RIGHTSLq      The practice of issuing equity shares with limited or no voting rights has booncriticized, particularly on the grounds that it deprives their holders, howeverwillingly,, of the power to exercise an influence in their company in proportion totheir holding and enables the favoured shareholders, who may have been the company&apos;sfounders, to maintain their control after their initial capacity to conduct thecompany&apos;s business efficiently has waned.   The Government accept in principle thecase for prohibiting the issue of such shares in future: indeed they are rarelyissued today.   There are however practical problems, especially as it is possibleto ensure that voting power is disproportionately distributed between shares ofdifferent nominal value, and it will be necessary to limit the scope for this practice if voting rights are not to be unreasonably distributed.   Practicalsuggestions for achieving this end will be carefully considered by the Government.NO-PAR-VALUE SHARES50      The Government do not intend to make any changes in relation to shares ofno-par-value.   This matter has been closely examined on previous occasions,particularly by the Gedge Committee (195^) and by Jenkins; both Committees (Gedgewith a dissenting minority) recognised the potentially misleading nature of percentagerelationships of dividends to nominal value of shares, and thought that companies should have the opportunity to avoid such meaningless but colourful calculations byissuing n-p-v shares - whether ordinar^^^ar^j^pn^as recommended by Gedge, or
CONFIDENTIALpreference as well, as recommended by Jenkins.   There is logic in this argument, butthe Government do not think that the practical need is now a strong one.   No noriou::enquirer is likely to be misled by nominal value, particularly nr. public common I.nowadays concentrates on the significant ratios (P/E, dividend cover, earnings pershare, etc).   Even v/ith n-p-v shares it would still be open to anyone so inclined toconstruct a similarly dubious argument by reference to issue price.   The Governmenthave accordingly decided that.legislation on this subject would not bejustified by the potential benefit to be gained from it.OTHER PROPOSALS51      The first half of this Paper does not seek to cover all the matters on which legislation will be proposed; as already explained, there is a range of furthersubjects for inclusion - much of the rest of Jenkins,and desirable changesrevealed by experience of administering the Companies Acts.   What has been donehere is to set out the arguments that have led to the most important proposalswhether on wholly new subjects or on Jenkins recommendations suitably modified inthe light of more recent experience.   These arguments are of course informed by thegeneral considerations in the Introduction.    It may prove undesirable to legislate in the immediate future on the whole list of possible candidates.   It may alsoprove desirable, as a result of public discussion stimulated by the presentpublication, to import matters into the Bill from the second part of this Paper.However the broad scope and main contents of the Bill will now be clear.23CONFIDENTIAL
PART TWO - WIDER CONSIDERATIONS52     This paper now turns to discuss briefly some of the major issues on which therewill eventually need to be decisions, and probably legislation, but on which thefull arguments have not yet been debated in public.   It does not attempt to setout all the relevant considerations, but is intended to stimulate public analysisand debate.     If debate matures a subject to the stage at which broadly acceptable provisions can be included in the forthcoming Companies Bill, theGovernment will take the opportunity of seeking appropriate legislation;    but they expect that many of these matters will qualify for inclusion in subsequent legislation.THE EEC53    The stage upon which future developments in company law will be enacted v/illincreasingly be set by the community of interest that is growing in Europe.   a significant amount of work has already been done in certain fields, and the SummitCommunique in October gave a valuable impetus to further work.   At the same time,two points should be made.   First, even with the best possible will, harmonisationis bound to be a lengthy process.     It will be some years in all probability beforesome of the matters discussed in the first part of this paper can become subjectto effective harmonisation.        It is therefore wholly appropriate that this country should take independent action where an immediate need can be shown.   Some of thematters referred to in this latter part of the paper need to be the subject of wide-ranging debate both in this country and in the Community generally before a basis for common European action can evolve.5*f    Secondly some aspects of the existing harmonisation programme have been thecause of real concern in the British commercial and legal community.   TheGovernment have accordingly taken the initiative with the new Commission and withour partners in Europe, in suggesting a rather different approach to harmonisation.The Government certainly does noc suggest that the detailed and valuable work already done on draft Directives, the European Company Statute, and other topics should be abandoned;    rather, they suggest that this and similar future work should be directed2k
CONFIDENTIALtowards identifying those elements of a common company law which each member state would regard as essential to any system of which it formed a part, and towardssecuring the harmonisation of those elements which could contribute to an early and practical degree of unification, of&apos;the market.55     This is clearly a process that will continue over a number of years.   But theGovernment believe that it offers a prospect of achieving a working common systemreasonably soon.     That is certainly the prime objective.     There is of course diffi-culty in harmonising in detail systems which have developed very differently in the uk and other member countries.     However, the Government believe that the approach which they have been advocating will contribute to the prosperity of the Communityat large, and that the outcome should not involve any serious hindrance to the flexibility and adaptability of the commercial and financial structure of this andother member States.   On the contrary, there are great economic benefits to be gained from early progress in harmonising the essential constitutents of a flexible,open and fair company law.THE PUBLIC EESPONSIBILITr OF THE COMAPNY56    There has been increasing public debate about the duties which a company owesto the wider public interest, and the recent Report of the CBI Committee under LordWatkinson has given added stimulus to the discussions.   The Government have decidedthat certain measures of reform are desirable, and are glad to find that their conclusions are in principle endorsed by the Committee on such points as,  for instance,insider dealing and the filing of annual accounts.57    Statute law has over the years defined and limited the areas and directions in which simple profit may be pursued.   The directors of a company owe a fiduciaryduty to do their best for those whose financial resources they are using;    but inan increasingly complex industrial society this is no longer taken to mean that the aim must be the simple one of immediate profitability.   A board of Directors hasto reconcile several different interests, of which profit is the main but cannotbe the only one.   Any company must behave as a responsible part of the society inwhich it exists, but as for an individual, responsibilities are of two kinds - onespecific and one general.   The law sets limits to the pursuit of profit - be they25
limits on acts affecting the public generally, such as fraudulent dealing,exploiting monopolies or polluting the atmosphere, or domestic matters such asthe proper amount of redundancy payment and the keeping of proper books of account.These are in the main specifically identifiable duties or proscriptions;    and itis for society, through the general body of the law, to alter those limits forall companies if it is thought right that they should be altered.   The other kindof responsibility, a more general and moral kind, is much more difficult to specify and define in terms that can assist any board to decide in any particularsituation just where that responsibility leads them, or that can be translated into law.58     For these wider responsibilities, a Code of Conduct might be appropriate,but to be effective a Code needs some external sanction.   The Watkinson Committeesuggest, for instance, that companies should consider adding to the Memorandum a clause allowing directors to take wider considerations into account when exercising their judgment as directors, and that a Code would set such judgments in a generalframe of reference.     That would no doubt protect the directors against any claimby shareholders seeking compensation for loss caused by directors&apos; actions not taken directly and clearly in the shareholders&apos; interest.     What also needs to beconsidered is whether it would give the positive guidance which a company might feel it needed, or might feel that its competitors needed, if it were to deviate safelyfrom the straightforward most profitable course.     For a Code to be effective inthat area of responsibility which this Paper has described as &apos;social&apos; or &apos;moral&apos; -and since by its nature much of the material cannot be put in specific and precise form - some independent source of judgment may be necessary.     The Take-Over Panelsuggests a precedent, but the Panel has of course the sanctions of the Stock Exchangebehind it, and it is not at present easy to see what counterpart might exist inrelation to the general run of industrial decisions.     It is evident that boards of directors can and do have regard to such matters as the interests of customers,of employees and of the general public, since these matters bear upon the reputation and well-being of the company as well as upon short-term profit.     The26CONFIDENTIAL
The more public disclosure there is of companies1 conduct the more will that be true.     It is however important to set criteria for judging whether in any-particular case they have done so to an acceptable degree.5l)    A useful step forward would be to impose a duty on directors to report tothe shareholders on specific parts of the company&apos;s response to the changingsocial environment.     As indicated above (para 12) the Government intends to use for this purpose the powers which they seek to require additional disclosure indirectors&apos; reports.     Administrative and drafting problems for directors may be involved, but these are matters of legitimate public concern.     There is no lackof informed and interested people (including the employees of a company) to markwhat is said.     And the cumulative effect would have real and increasing value bothin making companies more aware of their duty to and dependence on the community ofwhich they are a part, and in helping the community to appreciate the real extentto which companies individually and collectively are contributing to social progress.THE COMPANY AND ITS EMPLOYEES60    The duty that a company owes to its employees has already been emphasised.The role of the employees in the conduct of the company&apos;s affairs is a matter towhich the Government attach the greatest importance and which they have under urgent examination.     The Government believe that it is in the interests of all concerned,including those who provide the capital, that the employees should have aninfluencing decisions which can closely affect their own interest.appropriate opportunity of / These matters extend beyond the field of company law and have a significant part to play in the improvement of industrial relations.     The debate on this subject is proceeding alongside the debate oncompany law as a whole.     The Government therefore intend to publish later this yeara separate Green Paper on employee participation, discussing proposals for ensuring the closer involvement of employees in company affairs;   decisions about any new legislation which may be needed will be taken only when there has been full opportunity for public debate on the proposals and after consultation with bothif * *sides of industry.27CONFIDENTIAL
THE COMPANY&apos;S RESPONSIBILITY TO ITS SHAREHOLDERS6l    There is increasing public discussion, partly stimulated by developments in Europe, of the value (or otherwise) of some form of &apos;2-tier board&apos;structure, and also of the position of non-executive directors.     The 2-tierboard is represented as a device for bridging the undoubted gap that canexist in the larger company between on the one hand the shareholders and onthe other the executives for whom there is a temptation to become naturallycommitted - and in the main healthily committed - to thinking in terms of&quot;their company.     However, the ability of a 2-tier structure to operate inthis way may in part depend on the structure of the ownership of the company.It can be argued that the 2-tier structure is more suited to a situation wherethe main source of finance was an institution - as is frequently the case insome other European countries - and less suited to one where the company is largely equity-financed by a considerable number of shareholders, as is usuallythe case in this country.   In the latter case, the supervisoryt non-executive board might act not as a bridge but as an additional insulator.     On theother hand, it may be that the authority of a large body of shareholders wouldbe more effective if focussed by the existence of a supervisory board with powers of ultimate control over the management.62     There is no doubt that in many companies the non-executive director canplay a powerful and useful role, partly by his concern for the interests ofthe shareholders and partly by obliging executive members to look beyond their immediate concerns to the longer future and to the wider stage uponwhich the individual company must operate.     In addition, he may have a particularly active role in matters of management and board succession, whereonly the non-executive director can be confident of exercising a detached and impartial judgment.     Without imposing on the non-executive director any specific personal duty to the shareholders, which would reflect adversely bothon the responsibility of the other directors and on the concert of mindswhich the board should represent, there is nonetheless an argument for saying28
that every company over benefit from the presence on theboard of such directors.     Shareholders might reasonably expect to rely onthe non-executive director to be particularly sensitive to their interests,since he should be less committed to the managerial view and hence better able to discharge the &quot;stewardship&apos; function.INSTITUTIONAL SHAREHOLDERS63    An increasingly important part of the shareholding population is nowrepresented by the institutional investors.     The individual member of thepublic still stands behind them, in the person of the investment trust orunit trust investor, the endowment policy-holder, the pension fund beneficiary,and so on, but the immediate rights and responsibilities as members of thecompanies devolve upon the institutions.     These institutional investors shouldbe better informed than the individual, but do not have the same opportunityof selling out when dissatisfied;    the size of their investments compared tothe market-base can often mean that they are effectively locked in.Nevertheless, they do not all and at all times accept the implications, interms of the responsibility which they then properly have to their owninvestors and creditors, for the profitable conduct of the companies in whichthey are investors.     The Governor of the Bank of England has recently hadwelcome success in persuading the major institutional investors to acceptthe logic of their situation, and the responsibilities which unavoidably gowith it.     Many already do so, but there is room for further development inthis direction   - for instance, by increasing use of the appointment ofnon-executive directors with suitable qualifications and experience.Certain practical arguments have been advanced against this course.Some institutions feel that they are investors, and have no special expertisein the management of the companies in which they have invested.     their position may be no different in principle from that of the small individualinvestor, but they have greater resources to assess the performance of thecompanies in which they hold an interest.    They also have greater power topress their criticism of inadequate management and, where it might help toprovide a remedy, to secure the election of able non-executive directors toCONFIDENTIALthe board of such companies.
Despite those possible objections, the position of the institutionalshareholder is increasingly a matter of importance and concern both to industrial management and to the capital markets.     The Government will do all they can to see that the Governors valuable initiative maintainsmomentum, and that any necessary further action is taken.CONCLUSION65    The Limited Liability company has proved itself a most effectiveinstrument for promoting commercial prosperity in a free society.     Like anyinstitution, it must constantly develop and adapt to changing circumstances.That is why the Government will promote early legislation to produce improve-ments in company law, some of major public importance, some of technicalvalue, as set out in the first part of this paper. The Governments general approach is that disclosure of information is the best guarantee of fairdealing and the best antidote to mistrust.     If shareholders, employees,creditors and the public generally are properly informed, innocent activitywill be shown to be so and underhand activity will be inhibited.     Specificgaps in the law require specific legislation which will be introduced:examples are insider dealing, warehousing, the protection of minorities andthe disqualification of unsuitable directors.     The Government will welcomedebate on the wider questions in the second part of this paper, so that thebest and most acceptable ways can be found of improving the relationships between shareholders, employees and the public in a   modern society.     Onlyin this way can the company, the mainstay of free enterprise, remain thesuccessful instrument for prosperity that it has been in the past.30


</content>
</cab>
