<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/28/7 images: 84-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERitfftlENTPrinted for the War Cabinet   August 1942.MOST SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (42) 377.August 25, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the &quot;secrecy of this document war CABINET.SUMMARY   OF    OPERATIONS    OF    BOMBER    COMMAND    for fortnight ENDING 1200 HOURS, SUNDAY, AUGUST 16, 1942.Weather.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.1.THE weather both at home bases and over the target areas has notbeen good, and as a result the weight of attack on Germany has been lighter thanin the previous fortnight.A considerable mining effort -has been made.Operations.2.   Bombing Night-EssenRuhr .......Duisburg.......Le Havre ...Intruders ...Day-Anti-Submarine PatrolsVegesack  ...HagenHamburg ...BremenRuhrStuttgart.......Stuttgart ...Cologne-Ijmuiden  ...Anti-Submarine PatrolsKiel -..      .....Essen ...Hannover ...Kiel ....      .....MannheimMunsterNight-OsnabruckIntruders ...Mainz      ...      ...Intruders ...      .....Mainz      ...      .....Intruders ...Dusseldorf ...[24262]4/ 5 August5/6.6/76/76/73      ,,33344455566      ,,6a77    -- 79/109/1011/1211/1212/1312/1315/1638 aircraft252165    -6      vi--4 v, I&apos;1110211111      ,,111iil20213154101386131
Day-Anti-submarine patrolsCologneKiel ......Frankfurt ...OsnabriickCologneEssenAnti-submarine patrolsConvoy escortAnti-submarine patrolsWiesbadenAnti-shipping patrolsEssenAnti-submarine patrolsMannheimMining.9 August99910101010111212131313144 aircraft111111431717191q I A Q4/5          . 455/6           . 586/7      ,,. 18/9      ,, 129/10      ,, 510/11 52H/12 912/13 913/14 3815/16 9648 mines were laid during the period in the following areas :- Baltic.................. 275Bight and Frisian Islands     ...       ...       ... 216West Coast of France ...      ...       ...       ... 157Special efforts were made on the 8th/9th and 10th/11th August to lay minesahead of the Liitzoiv, known to be returning through the Belts. This was accom-plished in exceptionally severe weather conditions.Operational Achievements.3.   Mainz.Axigust 11/12 and 12/13. Jn two nights, with comparatively small forces,and with no moon to help, Mainz has been severely damaged, and. the centre ofthe city laid in ruins.Mainz has a population of 159,000. It is a commercial centre of importance and its rail and water communications have made it the chief grain distributioncentre for the Rhine-Main area.On the 11th/12th August 154 aircraft attacked the city in clear weather.Crews&apos; reports and night photographs leave no doubt that a great density of H.E..and incendiaries was achieved on and around the aiming-point. This was confirmed by a visual reconnaissance next morning, when a pall of smoke was seentowering up to 15,000 feet over the city.A follow-up attack was made by 138 aircraft on 12th/13th August, when,although layer cloud covered the town, many crews came down to low altitudesto identify and hit the objective. Two excellent night photographs are attached,both taken early in the attack before smoke and fires had become widespread;one shows the dense white smoke of phosphorous incendiaries rising over theaiming point, and the other H.E. bursts near the embankment.   .An area of 135 acres of the central city has been devastated by fire and H.E.;warehouses, silos and railway sheds at the main goods station and at the SouthTown Station have been destroyed; factories have sustained considerable damage,and three military barracks have been gutted and three very seriously damaged.Industrial damage includes a big H.E. incident in the important KalleChemical Works North of the river (photograph attached), a big brewerydemolished, three sheds in the waggon works destroyed and several in the boat-building yard gutted.Many of the most important public buildings have been burned.
The outflow of refugees must have been on the Rostock and lubeck  scale.On the 15th August, four days after the first attack, the station is seen to bepacked with them and the city has already assumed that &quot; dead &quot; appearancecharacteristic of thoroughly blitzed towns.A photograph is attached showing the completeness of the destruction in thecentre of the city.Osnabruck.   (August 9th/10th.)4. A force of 202 aircraft was sent to raid Osnabruck on 9th/10th August.This is a town of nearly a hundred thousand inhabitants and of considerable importance as a railway centre.Though it was dark and somewhat hazy, there was little cloud and a largeproportion of the crews dropped their bombs in the target area. No day photo-graphs have, yet been taken, but night photographs taken during the attack showthat good fires were started.dusseldorf.5. The results of the raid on the 31st July/1st August are dealt with inparagraph 6 below. A further raid was carried out on the 15th/16th August, butit is too early to attempt any assessment of damage. The weather during this operation was much worse than expected.Information concerning Previous Raids.dusseldorf.6. In the last summary it was possible to give only a sketchy impression ofthe results of the heavy attack &quot;on dusseldorf on the 31st July/1st August. close examination of photographs have now revealed that this raid was outstandinglysuccessful and especially remarkable because of the amount and severity of damage done to factories.No less than 24 factories have been either destroyed or seriously damaged;among them are the Schiess-Defries factory (magnetic mines and machine-tools),the De Limon Fluhme Engineering Works, which had its main shops completely destroyed; three steel-tube factories, a worsted mills, the main buildings of acattle-cake factory, seven sheds of a rolling mill, a chemical works and a alcoholplant. Buildings of the Olex Petroleum Company were still burning next day,and a long building at the Petroleum Receiving Depot has been destroyed.Among destroyed dockyard buildings are the Customs House, the Harbour Offices,a timber yard and 18 other sheds and warehouses.   Photographs are attached.Great havoc has been caused in the main business and shopping centre.Photographs show that 250 large buildings have been ruined in this concentratedarea.Stations and railway yards were also hit. The Neuss yard, in particular,suffered 6 hits across the sorting sidings affecting 15 lines and damaging a quantity of rolling-stock. There were 1,000 wagons present and this damage will certainly handicap working and cause congestion elsewhere for some time.Ground sources report that Benz and Hilgers (manufacturers of machinery)and Rheinmetal Borsig (iron and steel works) have both been badly damaged.saarbrucken.7. A detailed study of the photographs of Saarbrucken shows that the damage caused by the attack on the 29th/30th July was even more extensive than was thought. This attack was clearly one of the most successful raids of its scalecarried out.The two chief factories in the city the Eich Dudelinger Iron Works andthe Erhardt and Schmer Engineering Works have been severely damaged (seephotographs). Nearly all the railway sheds of the main station have sustainedsevere damage and the majority of the goods station buildings and railway shopshave been gutted. Other industrial damage includes the complete destructionof three large buildings in the Btirbacher Ore, dump, and three sheds in a cementworks. Part of the brewery and part of the gas works have also been burnt down.In the business centre, an area of 10^ acres which contained large blocks of shops and offices has been devastated. There are many other incidentsthroughout the business and residential districts, including a notable example ofthe blast power of our 4,000-lb. bombs, two of which have wiped out part of a housing estate (see photograph).[24262] b 2
Some of the comments on the saarbrucken raid in the German press are ofinterest.  An editorial in a Ludwigshaven paper on the 2nd August says : &quot; The raid was an agony for the Saar people and they will remember it for ever. To the many happy and elevating days which they experienced, aday of hard trials has now been added. The effect of the raid is still so--strong-ana fresh that it. occupies all our thoughts.&quot;The article goes on to say that clearing-up work was still going on, that allthe victims had not been rescued, and that, besides some 300 dead and wounded,approximately 8,000 to 10,000 people had lost their homes. The article endswith a warning that the attack might be repeated soon.The same paper contained this appeal by the Mayor of saarbrucken :   .&quot; A large proportion of the air raid victims did not make use of theemergency camps. These people have been taken in by their friends. I wish to point out that this is in order as a first measure, but cannot be tolerated for any length of time, as it is bound to cause trouble in thesehomes ; two families in one flat, two wives in one kitchen. All victims should therefore report to the local Party leader. Everybody will be lodged, someof them in Metz .... I cannot find a flat for everybody in our town or in theimmediate vicinity ; everyone must be satisfied with what he gets.&quot;Somewhat paradoxically the same paper remarked that the camps were full.Duisburg.8. A detailed study has now been completed of the photographs of theDuisburg area taken after the raid in the week ending July 26th. These showa considerable number of areas of damage scattered over the whole district ofDuisburg, Hambom and Hamburg.Industrial property has been extensively affected, notably the famousThyssen Steel Works, where several separate sections have been severely damaged,including the Rolling Mills, the centre, of which received a heavy bomb, the SheetMelting Mill, the Steel Strip Mill, and the power house. At least seventeenother industrial plants and factories have also been damaged, in some casesseverely.In the urban and suburban districts destruction by blast and fire has been caused to very large numbers of houses and tenement blocks.On night 6th/7th August a further attack was made by a force of 216aircraft. There was considerable ground haze, and it is believed that this raiddid not add appreciably to the existing damage.Hamburg.9. Further photographs taken recently reveal additional points of damage,chiefly in N.E. Hamburg. In the Barmbeck, Wandsbek and Wintruder districtsthere are approximately 20 incidents, mainly in residential and businessquarters.   Many of the buildings damaged are blocks of flats.In Uhlenhorst, East of the Aussen Alster, about 20 buildings have been gutted.Wilhelmshaven.10. The photograph attached shows destruction on three sides of theBauhafen at Wilhelmshaven, including that in the submarine-building yard and referred to in the last Summary.German Morale.11. A source who in the past has reported rather scathingly of the effectof R.A.F. attacks has stated that the recent mass raids have had a real effecton the morale of the population, and have caused complete chaos to life ingeneral. Apart from damage to industrial plants, industry has been severelydislocated by the chaos in bombed areas. As an example, he states that a textileworks in Cologne received a direct hit by one big bomb. Approximately a month after the raid these works were still idle, as, owing to the general confusion andthe lack of transport, the damage could not be repaired.
The following report was given to the British Legation in Stockholm by areliable source who was in Cologne on the day following the big attack : &quot; Relief services broke down badly. The fire-fighting strength was inadequate, as a considerable number of fire engines had previously beentaken from Cologne and concentrated in the Ruhr area, where an attack was expected. Consequently there was not enough left for Cologne. Theprovision of food also proved inadequate, and when the Ministry of theInterior commission left Cologne after staying two days, this problem was still not satisfactorily settled.Among the refugees met on the road by the Ministry of the Interiorparty were a number of SA and SS officers. When asked why they had notremained at their posts, they gave the answer that they were looking for accommodation for the homeless in the neighbouring towns, an answer whichdoes not always seem to have carried conviction.The spirit of the population is described as &apos;&apos; not at all heroic &apos;&apos; and theMinistry of the Interior cars, as they proceeded slowly and, with difficultythrough the crowds of refugees, were constantly assailed by cries of, &apos;&apos; Youhero, too, what a surprise &quot; ! &quot; This is the bill for London that we arepaying &quot;; &quot; This is revenge for Coventry &quot;; &quot; Thought you said the americans would, never come.&quot;As indicated by some of the insults addressed to the official carsmentioned, above, the population had the idea that American bombers hadtaken part in the raid. As soon as the news spread that it was a purely british raid, there was enormous dismay and widespread whispering of theterrors to come. The spirit of the population is very different from the declarations given by the authorities and the press, and the man-in-the-street. who has quite a good idea of what has happened, in spite of restrictions, is terrified, of the future.On the second day of their stay, the Ministry of the Interior officialsmentioned 2,800 as the number killed. It had by then not been possible toform any estimate of the number wounded, as casualty clearing stations were so over-burdened that they had not been able to keep count.&quot;-Mining.12.   The following results have been reported by a reliable source : 15th June The Danish Esther, of 319 tons, was mined four miles.S.W. of Kielsnor Light, and was beached at Baggenkop,&apos; at thesouth end of the Langeland Belt.20th June The Danish Anna (1,220 tons) was mined and sank at PaludansFlat, at the North end of the Great Belt.24th June The German auxiliary Veser 11, sank off the East Coast ofLangeland.1st July The Danish Polly (803 tons) was mined and beached at LjushageLt., at. the North end of the Great Belt.1st July The Danish TJlla (1,575 tons) was mined and damaged 5 miles north of Hala, off the North-West coast of Denmark.4th July The Danish schooner Minnie was mined and sank in the Northernapproach to the Great Belt.15th July A Danish fishing vessel, R.U. 529, was mined and sank 10 miles south of Baggenkop.5th August A Swedish ship of unknown tonnage struck a mine at 0900hours West of Heligoland. The crew was transhipped to anothervessel and the damaged ship was taken in tow.8th August A Danish ship of 1,200 tons was sunk by a mine North ofWangeroog.The Danish cutter Rita (534 tons) was mined and sank 13 miles N.E. ofSoren, Bogbjerg Deep, off the West Coast of Denmark (date unknown).A..H. M. S.A ugust 25, 1942.
























</content>
</cab>
