<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/8/23 images: 248-255</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO&apos; BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. 123It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.S E C R E T .W.P.(40) 195TAlso Co0oSo ( 40) 420)  copy NO.4TH JUNE, 1940.WAR CABINET .PRODUCTION PRBGRAMHESlReport &quot;by the Chiefs of Staff Committee:,In order to replace the enormous wastage both inArmy and Air Force material incurred in the past few weeks,it is obviously essential to exert the utmost energy in producing the equipment necessary for this summer&apos;campaing.      It may not be too much to say that on thisdepends our ability to avoid losing the war this summer.20 Subject to certain exceptions in the case ofequipments which are of the highest priority of all, thegeneral principle that has been adopted by the production council is to give priority to the production of equipmentthat is  capable of being used against the enemy within thenext three months.      The object of this is  to achieve themaximum productive capacity of the most important items by theend of August,      This short-term production programme is then to be continued until the strategic situation permitsa switch-over to a long-term programme030 It is essential not to lose sight of the fact thatif we are to have a chance of winning the war, we must lookfurther ahead than this summer&apos;s campaign.      While doing all we can to improve our fighting capacity during the nextfew months, we must not mortgage the future altogether.40 Our present programmes are based on a three years&apos;war, and aim at the provision and equipment,  on a high standard, of very large air and land forces in 1942.     Thisis manifestly too far ahead to be acceptable as a programme in present circumstances, and we must now fix a nearertarget date for armament production at which all three services must aim.      Plans for capacity which will matureafter the new target date should be abandoned and the resourcesof labour and material thus released, should be concentrated on capacity which matures earlier.

5, Time does not permit of a decision on the targetdate being deferred for an exhaustive appreciation of thepossible duration of the war on a number of different^hypotheses;    indeed in a situation such as the prime-eaentsuch an&apos;-appreciation is unlikely to be of an-y&quot;value.Each Service, however, will have to examine the repercussions on their own programmes of the new targetdate and adjust their production and training plans to meetthe new conditions.6. It may well be that if the enemy can be held untilthe end of October he will be unable to last out overanother winter.      It would, however, be unwise to make that assumption, and we therefore consider that our long-term programme should be based on attaining maximum production by June 1941,      The acceptance of this date would allow production from capacity completed by thatdate to be available for use before the end of the summercampaign of 1941.      Of course, if the war goes on into 1943,both the scale and the quality of our production will fall short of the scale and the quality which we should have,reached under a programme based on the present target date.But we cannot eat our cake and have it.7. In this connection it has been brought to our notice that the difficulty of finding sufficient skilled labour forthe armament industry would be very greatly eased if anumber of the skilled artificers and apprentices now serving in the Army could be released on a temporary basisto return to industry-.,      The strength of the forces whichwe can put into the field is determined not by man power butby equipment.     It would therefore clearly be uneconomicalto retain with the Array numbers of skilled men who, through lack of equipment, could not be employed at their trade andwould be of far more use in civil life.He commendat ions.8, We recommend therefore:-(a) That the programmes of supply and of theprovision and training of personnel andthe necessary ancillary services shouldbe based on the assumption that we shouldbe prepared to attain our maximum outputby June 1941, subject of course to reasonable latitude in individual cases.

(b) That the Service and Supply Departments, assisted by the Production Council, should base their arrangements on the above assumption, andshould as soon as possible reshape their programmes and present the War Cabinet withan estimate of the forces at which they areaiming by June 1941k      The assumption to beadopted as the basis for this estimate shouldbe that while there will be periods ofintense.activity such as the present, theaverage rate of wastage taken over the whole period should still be that of &quot;sustainedoperations&apos;^( c) That as many skilled men as possible should be temporarily released from the Army to industry, subject to recall to the colours at48 hours&apos; notice.    This matter is beingtaken up by the War Office.(Signed)    C.L.N. NEWALL.DUDLEY POUND.J&quot;.G. DILLoRichmond Terrace, S.W. 1.




</content>
</cab>
