<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/22/0 images: 66-70</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
--------------- /(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret .P..(k7) 29928th Octobers  19U7.COPY NO.CABINETAMENDMENT OF, THE PARLIAMENT ACT,   1911*Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council,the Lord Chancellor and the Home Secretary1. The attached Bill gives effect to the Cabinet&apos;decision of the 20th October (CM. (U7) 81st Conclusions,       rMinute 2)  regarding the amendment of the Parliament Act,  1911.We ask authority for its early introduction in the House ofCommons.2. The Cabinet should be aware of the adjustments whichwill have to be made in the Parliamentary time-table if the .Lords reject this Bill.      In order to secure its passage underthe existing provisions of the Parliament Act,  and subsequently to secure the passage of important Government measures underthe amended provisions of that Act,   the remaining Sessions ofthis Parliament would have to be arranged as follows:-1914.7/14.8 Session - The Parliament Act Amendment Billshould receive a Second Reading in the House of Commons not later than 17th November,  191+7*      Two years must elapsebetween the first Second Reading in the House of Commons andthe final passing of the Bill by that House on the thirdoccasion^    and thereafter the Lords must have a month in which to consider the Bill.      The first Second Reading must thereforebe secured by 17th November,  191+7? in order that the &quot;thirdSession&quot; may be brought to an end by 17th December,  19^+9*The present Session will presumably end by prorogation inJuly,  1948*19U-8 Session - It will be necessary to hold a shortSession in the autumn of 19^4-8 in order to comply with theother requirement of the Parliament Act that the Bill shouldbe passed by the Commons in three successive Sessions.      Thisshort Session would last for about six weeks and might openearly in September,  19U8,  and be prorogued in the followingmonth.      The first few days would be occupied with the debate on the Address and thereafter the Parliament Act amendment bill would be taken in the Commons.      The Session would haveto be continued for a month after the Bill had been sent tothe House of Lords.      If,  however,  the Lords immediatelyrejected the Bill and it was not convenient to take other business it would be possible to adjourn Parliament for aweek or so.
19U-8/h9 Session - This Session would presumablyopen in November, l&quot;9h8, but eould not be ended before december, 19^4-9-     As already indicated, the Parliament ActAmendment Bill could not be sent to the Lords in thatSession until two years after the date of its first SecondReading in the Commons (viz. two years after 17th November,i9kl)  and it could not receive the Royal Assent until just before Christmas, 1.949.      If an important controversial bill were introduced in the 19k8/h9 Session, it should be given a Second Reading in the Commons early in 191+9 so as&apos;to ensurethat in the. following Session it could leave the Commons forthe second time early in 1950..1950 Session - This Session would open in January,1950 and would have to be prorogued in July,. 1950 at latest.Under the amended provisions of the-Parliament Act,  a bill which had been rejected by the Lords in the preceding Sessioncould not leave the Commons for the second time until one year after its first Second Reading, in the Commons, and the Houseof Lords would have to be given one month to consider it before the end of the Session.      It could then receive theRoyal Assent under the amended Parliament Act procedure.        ^H.M.J.J, C-E.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1.28th October, 19U7.-2&apos;
DRAFTof a   &apos;B  I   L   LtoAmend the Parliament Act, 1911.E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and  A.D. 1947.with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and       rTemporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled,and by the authority of the same, as follows : 5 . 1. The Parliament Act, 1911, shall have effect, and shall be SubstitutionI deemed always to have had effect, as if- of references,(a) there had been substituted in subsections (1) and s (4) and one year of section two thereof, for the words &quot; in three successive for referencessessions &quot;, &quot; for the third time &quot;, &quot; in the third of those to three0 sessions&quot;, &quot;in the third session &quot;, and &quot; in the second ^wo^ears^or third session&quot;  respectively,-&quot;the words &quot; in two respectively,successive sessions &quot;, &quot; for the second time &quot;, &quot;jin thesecond of those sessions &quot;, &quot;in the second session ?&apos;,and &quot; in the second ^session &quot; respectively ; and I  - !5 (b) there had been substituted in subsection (1) of the.said section two, for the words &quot; two years have elapsed&quot;the words &quot; one year has elapsed &quot; :Provided that, if a Bill has been rejected for the second time ; %by the House of Lords before the signification of the Royal &amp;0Assent to the Bill for this Act, whether such rejection was inthe same session as that in which the Royal Assent to the Billfor this Act was signified or in an earlier session, the requirement of the said section two that a Bill is to be presented to His Majestyon its rejection for the second time by the House of Lords shallijhave effect in relation to the Bill rejected as a requirement thatit is to be presented to His Majesty as soon as the Royal assent to the Bill for this Act has been signified, and, notwithstanding15-1ii Geo. 6. Parliament.
Parliament.ir Geo. 6.a.d. 1947.   that such rejection was in an earlier session, the Royal Assent-       to the Bill rejected may be signified in the session in which theRoyal Assent to the Bill for this Act was signified.Short title,        2. (1) This Act may be cited as the Parliar. ent Act, 1947.construction and citation. (2) This Act and the Parliament Act, 1911, shall be construed as one and may be cited together as the Parliament Acts, 1911and 1947, and accordingly subsection (1) of section four of the parliament Act, 1911 (which specifies the words of enactment to beinserted in a Bill presented to His Majesty under that Act) shallhave effect with the substitution of the words &quot; the Parliament]Acts, 1911 and 1947 &quot; for the words &quot; the Parliament Act, 1911&quot;.


</content>
</cab>
