<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/22/0 images: 98-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1947SECRETCP. (47) 30613ifA November, 1947CABINETCRIMINAL JUSTICE BILL : CAPITAL PUNISHMENT&apos;.&apos;. Memorandum by the Home Secretary. AT their meeting on 3rd November (CM. (47) 84th Conclusions, Minute 1)the Cabinet invited me to submit a further memorandum on this subject. Themain questions for consideration may be summarised, I think, as follows : T. Are murders likely to be more frequent if the death penalty is abolishedthan they otherwise would be?II. Does the alternative penalty entail disadvantages to which weightmust be given in balancing the considerations for and against capital punishment? ;-. o ,;. ^III. -Are present-day circumstances such that legislation for the abolition- of the death penalty ought.to be avoided at this juncture?IV. What repercussions will the abolition of the death penalty for crimestried by the civil courts of Great Britain have on the imposition of death sentences in the British Zone of Germany, in the colonial territories, and by Courts-Martial ?I. The Deterrent Effect of Death Sentences2. Those who are opposed to a change of the law represent that by annexingthe death penalty to the crime of murder society marks its special horror ofthis crime and imbues the minds of its members from their youth upward withthe feeling that this crime is to be avoided above all others. They contend thatthe abolition of this penalty would necessarily impair the protection given tosociety by the existing law. On the other side it is pointed out that similararguments have been advanced in the past for the retention of the death penalty for: other crimes, and that in countries where the death penalty has been abolished,abolition has not been followed by any increase in the number of murders. Sofar as can be judged from the evidence collected by the Select Committee of 1930,*there are no reliable figures showing that in any country which has abolished the death penalty there has been subsequently any significant increase in the numberof murders. It is retorted that the incidence of crimes of violence is liable tobe affected by other changes than changes in the criminal law and statistics ofmurders are liable to be misleading without full information as to local circum-stances. Conditions vary from country to country and it is arguable that theexperience of one country does not prove that the experience of another country would be similar.3. In the United States some States after abolishing the death penaltyrestored it again, but whether such changes were due to practical experience orto variations of mood is disputable. In any case arguments as to the effect ofthe death penalty in the Lnited States are liable to be vitiated by the fact thata murderer has many chances of escaping conviction or if convicted of escapingexecution. .^; 4. As mentioned in my memorandum of 8th July (OP. (47) 200) the view is held by many experienced police and prison officers that criminals in thiscountry would be more likely to use lethal weapons if the penalty for murderwere imprisonment rather than death.* A note on this Select Committee is given in the Appendix to this Memorandum.34511Copy No. ^&apos;  
II.-The A Itemative Penalty\ *-&apos; - 5. If the death penalty were abolished it would be possible either toisubstitute a fixed penalty of imprisonment for life or to give the Judge discretion to pass sentence of any term up to imprisonment for life. The Select committee recommended the first course and said that the life sentence should be interpretedand administered in the same way as the sentence to which a reprieved murdereris subject at present. This course seems preferable. There are some reprievedmurderers whom it is right to release on licence after very short periods, of imprisonment (for example, a mother who kills an imbecile child from mercifulmotives), and it would be undesirable in such cases for a court publicly to passa sentence of imprisonment for a few months or for a year or two, and therebyto create the impression that the taking of human life may in certain circumstances be no graver a crime than theft.6. If, when the jury returns a verdict of murder, the Judge has no option but to pass a sentence of imprisonment for life, it will rest with the HomeSecretary to decide when the prisoner shall be released on licence. In manycases of murder detention would no doubt be necessary for at least ten years.In some cases longer detention would be requisite, and there may from timeto time be murderers who can never be released. For purposes of prison adminis-tratibn it is essential that the cases where the prisoner is never released shouldbe exceptional and that there should be maintained amongst those serving lifesentences a general hope of release and consequent incentive to good behaviour.Moreover, experience shows that imprisonment for more than about ten years is liable to have so deleterious an effect on the prisoner that longer detentionshould be avoided whenever possible.7. The conditions under which murderers would serve their life sentencesmust be no, more rigorous than those applied to other long-sentence prisoners.The longer the period of detention the greater is the need for creating in the prison conditions which will keep alive the prisoner^ mental interests and socialinstincts.8. It has been suggested that in some countries where capital punishmenthas been abolished the alternative is the imprisonment of murderers under morerigorous conditions than are applicable to other prisoners, but from the informa-tion collected by the Select Committee it appears that this suggestion is unfounded.The evidence given to the Select Committee showed that in Norway and Belgiumit was the practice to keep in solitary confinement prisoners (whether sentencedfor murder or for other crimes) who had not a criminal record, but this methodwas adopted for reformative purposes and for protecting such prisoners fromcontamination by other prisoners.III. Present-Day Circumstances   &apos;9. A large section of the public has no strong opinion on this subject andis liable to be influenced by the circumstances of the time. There are circum-stances which at the present time are likely to influence this section of publicopinion against the abolition of the death penalty.10. Most police forces are much below strength and the police have todeal with a greatly increased volume of crime. In 1946 the crimes of feloniouswounding and malicious wounding known to the police numbered 3,009, against,990 in 1938; cases of robbery with violence numbered 921 in 1946, against287 in 1938, and, cases of rape 251 in 1946, against 99 in 1938. The numberof persons tried in 1946 at Assizes and Quarter Sessions for burglary, housebreaking and shop breaking was 8,537, against an annual average of 3,339 inthe period 1935 to 1939. The police will feel that their task in combating crimewill be made harder if the death penalty is abolished. They believe that it isa far stronger deterrent than imprisonment against the use of firearms, by. criminals engaged in felonious enterprises. Whether this belief is or is notmistaken, it is firmly held by experienced officers and is shared by many membersof the public.11, Many people may be, and probably are, inclined to think that warexperiences, and especially the experiences of young men trained in the Com-mandos, have weakened the sense of the sanctity of human life. The same personspossibly feel that the danger of murderous activities is greater to-day than itwas before the war. No certain inference can be drawn from the statistics of murder, because the comparatively small figures are liable to be affected by
numerous casual factors. For what they are worth, bearing that consideration in mind, it can be stated that murders known to the police (excluding murdersof infants under one year.of age) numbered 97 in 1938 and 136 in 1946. Attempts,threats or conspiracies to murder numbered 94 in 1938 and 199 in 1946.12. The statistics given above correspond with the generally accepted viewof present day circumstances. They probably make little impression on theconvinced people at both ends of this controversy., Their impact on the minds of those holding the middle opinion can be assessed by each of my colleagues for himself.IV- Repercussions13. Any clause inserted in the Criminal Justice Bill will apply only to GreatBritain. (Any amendment of the law in Northern Ireland would be a matter forthe Northern Ireland Parliament.) If, however, capital punishment is abolishedin Great Britain it will be necessary for the Government to consider the questionof death sentences in the British Zone in Germany,and in other areas wheremilitary government is being exercised. .: 14. Death sentences in the British Zone in Germany are imposed not only,for murder but for war crimes and for a number of offences against the securityof the Occupation. , I understand that there may be an average of ten to twentyexecutions a month. In addition to sentences passed by the German courts, deathsentences may be passed by the Control Commission courts, which deal mainly with offences against the security of the Occupation, and by the Military Courtsset up by Royal Warrant, which deal mainly with war crimes. In view of the;recent abolition of the death/penalty in Soviet Russia, the first Russian military government Court dealing publicly with the trial of war criminals a few,weeks ago felt it right to abstain from imposing the death penalty on any of the con-victed persons before it.15. A position somewhat similar to that in the British Zone in Germanyexists in Austria and in other areas, for example, the Italian Colonies and theFar East, where military government is now being exercised.16. Consideration will also have to be given to the position in the colonial territories, particularly territories such as Nigeria, Uganda and Tanganyika,where a substantial number, of death sentences are executed each year. Thequestion is no doubt primarily one for the local legislatures, but if the death sentence is abolished in this country, the Government will be pressed to secure sofar as possible a similar change in the laws of the Colonial Territories.17. The question of death sentences imposed by Courts-Martial will also require attention. The death sentence for desertion in the field and cowardice inthe face of the enemy was abolished in 1930, but the Army Act still provides forthe imposition, of the death penalty as the maximum punishment (a) for certain military offences, and (b) for crimes punishable by death under the ordinary civillaw (i.e., treason and murder) when such crimes have to be tried by Court-Martialin areas overseas outside the jurisdiction of the civil courts.(a) The military offences for which the death penalty can be imposed include certain offences which can only obtain in time of war, such as treacherouslygiving intelligence to the enemy or treacherously making known a watchwordor countersign to persons not entitled to receive it, and also the offences of causingor conspiring to cause mutiny or sedition, etc., which may occur in time of peaceas well as in time of war. Five men are, I understand, at the present time undersentence of death for mutiny which included murder of officers and occurred on christmas Island during the war.The Select Committee confined their recommendation for legislation to &apos;&apos; casestried by civil courts.&quot; The question whether the death penalty should be retained for certain military offences tried by Courts-Martial stands on a different footing,and the War Office suggest that if the House of Commons were to decide in favourof the abolition of capital punishment, the Government should make it clear thatthe question of retaining the death penalty for certain, military offences wouldhave to be examined as a separate issue.(b) As regards, however, cases of treason and murder tried by Courts-Martialin areas overseas, the question will arise whether it is justifiable to maintain the death penalty if it is abolished for these offences when tried by civil courts in thiscountry. Recently a soldier in Germany was convicted by Court-Martial of the murder of a German woman and the sentence of death was executed.   On the one
persons. j c. E.Home Office, S.W. 1,13^ November, 1947.appendix the Select Committee of 1930On 30th October, 1929, a Private Members&apos; Motion was moved by Mr. W. J.Brown that &quot; in the opinion of this House capital punishment for civil crimesshould be abolished.&quot;    An amendment was put down by Sir Herbert Samuel(now Lord Samuel) asking for the appointment of a Select Committee.   TheHome Secretary, Mr. Clynes, suggested that the amendment should be accepted.He said : &quot; We are wandering partly in the region of opinion and partly in the region of disputed fact: ....   During the last hundred years this subject hasbeen debated in the House of Commons on, I believe, eighteen occasions ... .Some of the greatest humanitarians and parliamentarians have spoken in thesedebates, and no one can rise from any long reading of these discussions without having some doubt as to whether the abolition of Capital Punishment for the worst cases of murder can safely be enacted.   There are some cases of murderthat are so horrible that if the murderer were allowed to live the whole conscienceof the community might be provoked.&quot;   He also referred to possible difficultiesif a murderer escaped from prison or murdered a warder.   Mr. W. J. Brownaccepted the amendment, which was carried without a division.v   The Select Committee was composed of seven Labour Members, six Con-servatiye and two Liberal.    The Rev. James Barr, a Labour Member, wasappointed to the Chair;   The Committee finished taking evidence by the end ofJuly 1930, and in November a Draft Report was submitted to the Committee bythe Chairman.   At the next meeting on 2nd December Sir Gervais Rentoul,a Conservative Member, proposed an adjournment &quot;in order that those of theCommittee, who held, views opposed to those embodied in the Draft Report pro-posed by the Chairman, might prepare and bring in an alternative Draft Reportafter the Christmas adjournment of the House.&quot;  He intimated that if the Com-mittee should decide not to adjourn, he and other Members of the Committeewould withdraw and take no further part in the proceedings.   At this meetingone Liberal Member was absent owing to illness and one Labour Member was absent. The six Conservative Members voted for the adjournment, the five labour members and one Liberal Member voted against, and thereupon the Chairmandeclared himself with the Noes.  The Conservative Members left the room, andat the two subsequent meetings, attended only by the seven Labour members and one Liberal, the Draft Report of the Chairman was adopted with a fewminor amendments.The Report made in December 1930 recommended:-&quot;That a Bill be introduced and passed into law during the present session, providing for the Abolition of the Death Penalty for an experi-mental period of five years incases tried by Civil Courts in time of peace. . . .&quot;In regard to the penalty that should be substituted for the sentence of Death in the cases referred, we recommend that it be the Penalty nowattached to reprieved murderers, interpreted and administered in the same way as at present.&quot;On 29th January, 1931, a Parliamentary Question was addressed to the PrimeMinister enquiring &quot; whether he proposes to take the opinion of the House on the.report of the Select Committee oil Capital Punishment; and if not what stepshe will recommend the House to take with a view to amending the law.&quot;Mr. Clynes replied : &quot;The Government do not propose at present to take any action concerning the report of the Select Committee.&quot;


</content>
</cab>
