<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/22/0 images: 151-154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S EC RET C.P. (1+7)  31J4--: -26TH NOVEMBER,  19U7..       . MOTION ON JOURNALISTSMemorandum by the Lord President of the Council: At their meeting on 25th November,   (CM. (hi) 90thConclusions, Minute 3) the Cabinet invited me to revise, inthe; light of the discussion,  the terms of the Motion relatingto the conduct of:journalists at present on-the Order-paper of the House of Commons and to submit a revised draft- forconsideration on 27th November,  i 91+7. &apos;2. As at present drafted, the Motion reads:-&quot;That,  if in any case hereafter a Member shallhave been found guilty;by: this House of corruptlyaccepting payment for the disclosure and publicationof confidential information about matters to be   .proceeded with in Parliament,  any person responsiblefor offering such payment shall incur the gravedispleasure of this House;    and if such person shallbe the representative of a newspaper or of a pressagency, that person -and any other representative ofthe same newspaper or agency shall,  if the Housethink fit, be  excluded from the precincts of this house,  until this House snail otherwise determine.&quot;3.&apos; During arid&quot; since the Debate of 30th October, 19U7,exception has been taken to the&apos; terms of this Motion,particularly to the latter part,  qn the grounds that:--(a) It cast a slur upon an honourable body of men,/namely,  the Lobby journalists,  in advance of any action that would justify a charge of corruption;(b) That it was too wideand tooautomatic in its effects.1+. On 25th November the Cabinet considered thefollowing amendment: -&quot;Leave out from displeasure of this House&apos;  tothe,end, and add:- &apos;&apos;And may,  if the House think fitbe deprived of any facilities which he -may enjoy within theprecincts of the House for such period as the Housemay determine.1&quot;COPY NO. ^ 1-CABINET(THIS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
It was felt,  however,  that this indication of the penaltieswhich might be imposed would tend to fetter the discretion of the House in dealing with any future cases that might arise and,  so for from acting as a deterrent, might evenencourage potential offenders by revealing the limited nature:of the penalties which could be inflicted.5* Following the Cabinet discussion,  I have been considering various&apos; alternative amendments. &apos; One possibility would be insert after &quot;displeasure of this House&quot;  :-&quot;and shall be subject to such penalties as this house shall think fit to impose.&quot;As to this suggestion, I am advised, however,  that the word&quot;penalties&quot; would not be appropriate as there is, in fact,no penalty in the strict sense that the House of Commonscan impose for the class of offence with which this Motionis seeking to deal.      The object of the Motion is, in fact^a strictly limited one, namely,  to give notice that^theHouse will in future consider taking action againstrepresentatives of Press Agencies and newspapers for offeringbribes to Members in cases where no specific breach of privilege has been committed. &apos;     &apos;6. All that, the House can,  in fatrt., do in such cases,apart from expressing its. grave displepsej, is to withdrawits facilities from the representativeWr representatives ofthe newspaper concerned.      This points either to my originalwording or else to some more general but also more menacingform of words.      I attach importance to the House placingits intentions on record, so that the way maybe clear (as itwas not entirely clear on the last occasion) to take immediate action against the offerer as well as against the recipientof a bribe.      It seems, therefore, that,  in order to coverthis point,  without extending the area of privilege, the choice of words is limited to some.such general expressionsas the following (to be added in place of the words in theoriginal Motion ,after &quot;displeasure of this House&quot;):-&quot;And this House will proceed against him in such manner as it may,  in the circumstances, think fit&quot;,or, alternatively:-.-&quot;And this House will take such action as itmay,  in the circumstances,  think fit.&quot;Or,  a third possibility would be:-Leave out from &quot;incur&quot; and insert -&quot;Such expression of the displeasure of this house as the House may, in the circumstances, thinkappropriate.&quot;7. If my colleagues agree with me in preferring thefirst of &apos;the amendments mentioned in paragraph 6 above,the. amended Motion would then rea&amp;i-&quot;
&quot;That,  if in any case&quot;hereafter a member shall have been found guilty by this House of .corruptly accepting payment for the disclosure and publication of confidential information aboutmatters to be proceeded with in Parliament,  anyperson, responsible for offering such payment shall&apos;incur the grave displeasure of this House;    andthis House will, proceed against him in such manner as it may, in the.circumstances,  think fit.&quot;H.M.Office of&quot; the Lord President of the Council,S. W. 1 .&apos;..26th November, 194-7.\


</content>
</cab>
