<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/22/0 images: 155-158</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret*p.(h7) 31526th November; i9h7cabinetCOMPENSATION FOR REQUISITIONED land memorandum by the Chancellor of tho ExchequerIntroductory1. -The Requisitioned Land and War Works Bill, whichwill he submitted to the Legislation Committee next week,contains provisions extending the period -during which landrequisitioned for military purposes may be retained,  andamending the Requisitioned Land and War Works Act, 19h7 invarious other respects.   Compensation for the requisitioning of land is still tied to 1939 values, and since the 1939standard has now been abandoned, both for war damage payments and for compensation on compulsory acquisition, there is a clear case for taking this opportunity to amend the lav/regarding compensation for requisitioning.    I invite mycolleagues to consider what changes should be made.Rental Compensation2. Rental compensation was originally the market rent .-of the property at the date of requisition, excludingappreciation in value duo to the emergency.    The RequisitionedLand and War Works Act, 19h7 allowed this to be raised asfrom 20th February, 19h7, to either the level ruling on thatdate or the level ruling on 31st&apos; March, 1939,&apos; whichever wasthe lower.   Broadly speaking, therefore, rental compensationis on 1939 values or lower.3* The principle (following what has been done incases of compulsory acquisition) should be to adopt currentvalues, excluding any unreasonable inflation due to scarcity.I propose that, with effect from the passing of the Bill,compensation rentals should be raised (on a claim made bythe owner) to current values, subject to a ceiling of 1939values plus 60. per cent,  the property being assumed of course to be ih the state in which it was when it was requisitioned.In the case of rent-restricted property, the ceiling wouldbe the standard rent.h. The ceiling of &quot;1939 plus 60 per cent&quot; is not a completely logical way of excluding the scarcity, element incurrent values but that could be effected with precisiononly by means of a. complex scheme which would be verydifficult to administer and would be open to&apos; various othercopy no.  &quot;^Jr1HIS document is the property op his britannic majesty&apos;s government)
objections.   The figure for,the addition can be fairlyarrived at by taking the increase in building costs since1939 and applying to it the fall in the yield of money.This can be done only on broad lines and suggests a figureof 50 per cent or 60 per cent.   The rent now asked by building lessors erecting buildings for the Government exceedspre-war rents by about this amount on the average.    It sohappens that 60,per, cent-was the addition made to 1939 values,both for war damage payments on &quot;good&quot; properties and for compulsory acquisition in the case of owner occupiers priorto the Town and Country Planning Act, 19h7, but both these,cases related to buildings only, excluding site.   For thepresent purpose, virhere rent of course includes site value,a case can be made out for 50 per cent only, but I am prepared,if my colleagues agree, to concede 60 per cent.- Terminal Compensation5.    . Terminal compensation is the cost of repairingdamage done during requisition but is subject to a ceiling of the value of the property in.,its original state, excludingappreciation due to the emergency (i.e., again, 1939 valueor lower).   This requires adjustment in two respects.   First,,the 1939 ceiling how bears very hardly on owners whose property has been destroyed or seriously damaged,  since the.present cost of substantial repairs may greatly exceed the1939 value.   Secondly, whon we abandon 1939 value in favourof a current value,  it is illogical to allow an owner to get back his property in its damaged state and, in addition,a sum equal to the current value of the&apos; whole property,including what ho gets back.   If, qs I think we must, wedepart from the 1939 basis, we should take the opportunityof removing this illogical feature.6* . I therefore suggest that the ceiling for terminalcompensation should be the difference between the values - ofthe property in its state (a) at the beginning, and (b) atthe end, of the requisition, both these figures being taken,at current value on the basis adopted for compulsory.. acquisition.7. This provision will apply only in a small minority of cases, and will he operative for cases of derequisitionin/;after the Bill becomes law.    It does not. cure a grievanceon derequisitioning generally which is becoming more acuteowing to the delays suffered by owners in getting their !;repairs done.   The Act is interpreted as requiring terminalcompensation to be assessed by reference to costs of repairat the, date -of derequisitioning:    in fact, the owner cannot&apos;then get. them done and costs often rise substantially before he can - or even before the negotiations for compensation .are concluded.   A small concession is made administrativelyby way of a continuance of rental during a rehabilitationperiod normally&apos; not. exceeding six months, but the ownerwants either a continuation until the repairs are in factdone or a cost of works payment.   The.former would involveconsidering how for the property can be put to reasonableuse without the repairs, and the latter would be not only very expensive inasmuch as it would lead to repair of properties not worth repairing but also impossible to administer
without substantial staff increases.    The point is sureto be pressed, in Parliament, but unless some plan emergesbetter than, we have hitherto thought of, I think we canonly held to the existing position with a promise ofreasonably sympathetic administration.General8. These proposals have been discussed with officials of the Departments mainly interested, and I understand thatthey are acceptable from the point of view of administrativepracticability.summary. I invite my colleagues&apos; approval to the proposals(i)    that rental compensation should be raised to current values, within a ceiling of 1939 valuesplus 60 per cent or, in the case of rentrestricted.property, the standard rent;(ii)    that terminal compensation should be subject toa ceiling of the difference between current&quot;compulsory acquisition&quot; values of the ^.property in its&apos;state (a) at the beginning and(b) at the end of the requisition.R.S.O.Treasury Chambers, S.W..1.,26th November, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
