<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/22/0 images: 165-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENTSECR E TCP. (1+7) 3182ND DECEMBER,  191+copy NOCABINETNEEDS OF THE ARMED FORCES AND MINISTRY OP supply for LAND FOR TRAINING AND OTHER PURPOSESMemorandum by the Minis top of Defence-   .A White Paper giving &quot;details- of the post-war landrequirements of the Services was promised to Parliament earlyin the year and a draft was laid before the Cabinet by thePrime Minister on 27th June (CP, (1+7) 18Z+).At their meeting on 1st July, the Cabinet     0,-.;;:(CM. (h7) 58th Conclusions, Minute L)  : - -  &apos;(2)    Invited the Lord President, in consultation withthe Minister without Portfolio and theChancellor of the Exchequer, to. arrange for thedraft White Paper annexed to CP.(1+7) 184 to be revised on the lines suggested in discussion,and agreed that the revised draft should be circulated to the Cabinet.(3)   Invited the Minister of Town and Country planning to ensure that all interested Departments werenotified in good time of any proposals made bythe Service Departments for the acquisition ofland for training purposes.2. T,he draft White Paper was revised accordingly butit was subsequently agreed, on the suggestion of the lord president, that the actual, requirements of land should be reviewed in the light of the discussions-&quot;then proceeding on-,the future size of the Armed Forces, and that the White *Paper should be withheld until the-review had been carriedout.3. As a result of this review, the War Office.,requirements, which represented about 7/8ths of the total demand, have been reduced by 103,000&apos; acres, the total demand&apos;for training land now being 702,000 acres, as against 805,000acres under the earlier&apos; proposals.U)Approved in principle the proposals in CP. (1+7) 18Z+for the use by the Service Departments and theMinistry of Supply, of land for training andother purposes;-1-
k. At their meeting on 31st October (L.P.(U7) 27thMeeting, Minute 4), the Lord President&apos;s Committee approved the proposed reduction of requirements and invited me to makethe consequential amendments to the White Paper inconsultation with the Minister of Town and Country Planning:also to consult the Lord President on the method of presentation,, before submission to the Cabinet.   This hasnow been done, and the draft attached has been agreed byall concerned.5, -Pressure in Parliament and in the Press for theissue of this White Paper is strong and continuous and it isdesirable that it should be published without further delay.The new Requisitioned Land and War Vi/orks Bill will be issuedduring the next few days, and this provides a further reasonfor immediate publication.    That 3ill extends the powerto retain requisitioned land required for Service purposes and will raise numerous questions which are dealt with inthe White Paper.6. The proposals contained in the Vifhite Paper -were approved in principle by the Cabinet on 1st July,  and I nowinvite the Cabinet(1)    To approve the attached revised draft ofthe Wh;Lte Paper; V(2)    To authorise its immediate publication.A.V.A.MINISTRY OF-DEFENCE, S.W.I.,2nd-December, 1947*
NEEDS OF the armed FORGES FOR LANDFOR TRAINING ANDOTHER PURPOSES
NEEDS OF the armed FORGES FOR LANDFOR TRAINING ANDOTHER PURPOSES
NEEDS OF THE ARMED FORCES FOR LAND FORTRAINING AND OTHER PURPOSESPART I.-introduction.   Land is needed by the Services both for permanent installations -that are part of the national defences, and for training.   The Governmenthave considered the land requirements of- the Service Departments andof the Ministry of Supply f1) from two points of view:   .(a) the size of the total need for land (including sea danger areas relatJ^to such land) in Great Britain, and the effect of that need uponthe public interest, especially in such matters as agriculture,forestry, fisheries, and access by the public for. the purpose ofrecreation; and(6) the distribution of the land requirements (i) between home and overseas;(ii) within Great Britain, between England, Scotland and Wales.Their conclusions on land requirements are set but below.2. It. will be recalled that on 15th November, 1946, the Prime Ministergave an undertaking, that public local inquiries would be held when desiredin all cases involving the acquisition of land and the procedure for holdingthese inquiries is set out in Part IX. The. scope of the inquiries has,however, been extended (subject to security considerations) to cover changes of use of existing Service Department land, proposals to acquire trainingrights and cases where existing user was begun during the war and thereis strong objection to its continuance.PART II.-LAND NEEDED BY THE SERVICES FOR purposes other THAN TRAINING3.   The needs of the Services for land for permanent installations thatare part of the national defences are as follows :  &apos; . .(a) Boyal Air Force and Boyal Naval airfields.   These have been selected from those in use during the war.(ft) Space for accommodation and storagfe; most of this is already heldby the Services.(c) Sites for anti-aircraft defences and coastal artillery.(d) Sites for radar installations.(e) Ministry of Supply experimental and research establishments, ranges,airfields and trial grounds (in addition to land used jointly with thethree Services).Airfields -4. The R.A.F. airfields in this country are the main bases from whichthis force operates, and upon which it is maintained, trained and accom-accommodated. In the case of Naval Aviation the airfields are an indispensablesupplement to the carrier forces for training, maintenance and disembarkationof front-line squadrons. The airfield plan has been drawn up in the lightof strategical and tactical requirements, and is now being considered in the(&apos;) For the purposes of this paper the Ministry of Supply is treated as a service Department.
light of jthe views of-the interested civil departments and:of the least possibleinterference with amenities. A large number of airfields will be shared withthe Ministry of Civil Aviation or the Ministry of Supply.Living and Recreational Accommodation -.5.   Many more, men have to be accommodated than before the war;while a greater proportion of the Eoyal Navy must now be quartered ashore,&apos;chiefly owing to technical developments during the war.   Many additionalmarried quarters are needed in all three Services as part of the general policyof improving living conditions.   Much of the basic accommodation exists,J^it it needs modernisation and some extension.   Moreover, many barrackspresent without&quot;garages and workshops must be provided with them.The total requirements for land under this head are, however, &quot;small andwill be met as far as-possible by the use of land already held by th.eServices.Storage, .6. The increasing amount and variety of equipment used by theServices have created new demands for storage accommodation. these will be met in the main by the development of existing depots, on whichconsiderable sums of money were spent before or during the war. In afew cases new accommodation will be needed, e.g., for distribution points for supplies and stores near large troop concentrations, or in replacement of properties at present requisitioned for storage purposes.Defensive Installations7. Tf the Forces are to operate successfully in an emergency, certainstatic defences such as Anti-Aircraft and Coast Artillery are needed,together with many scientific and mechanical aids necessary to them,including the radio and radar network. These installations cannot be erected hurriedly, but. must be permanent, though little land is needed for them......Ministry of Supply8. The Ministry of Supply provides the aircraft, weapons, fighting vehicles, ammunition, and most of the other types of equipment and stores,needed by the Army and the Eoyal Air Force; much of the armaments;and ammunition required by the Royal Navy, and aircraft and relatedequipment for Naval- Aviation.The land used by industrial establishments and the storage and housing.- accommodation ancillary thereto falls outside the scope of this Paper, but important land requirements exist for:  (a) experimental  and  research  establishments,   including ranges  and airfields, in connection with design, development and testing ofarmaments,, munitions and aircraft;.,:(b) trial grounds for fighting vehicles.The&apos; rapid advance of scientific knowledge in recent years, and its application to all aspects of attack and defence, has necessitated corres-correspondingly more extensive and specialised facilities for research and experi-mental&apos;work. Thus, increases are necessary in the size of the experimentaland research establishments, and more particularly in the ranges where new-weapons are tested. The number and diversity of character of these establishments has also grown. To some extent, the needs of the Ministryof Supply in respect of its experimental work can be met by using areasheld by the Service Departments for their own purposes, and such joint Use[33917] b 2
has already been arranged with the War Department and the Air Ministry.In other cases the nature of the Ministry of Supply work is such that itmust be carried out separately.While certain experimental and. research work is being carried put over-seas, in the main such work must be done in this oountry within convenientreach of the Headquarters of the Service and Supply Departments, and ofthe main centres of scientific and industrial activity.PART III.-MORE LAND NEEDED FOR TRAINING THAN BEFORETHE WAR9. The problem of Service training has greatly changed since pre-w^^1days. Three new factors have to be considered. The first is the decision taken hy Parliament to continue National Service in peace-time. TheNational Service system, which will after 1st January, 1949, consist of oneyear&apos;s full-time service and six years in the Reserves, will greatly increasetraining requirements. Not only will the turn-over of men doing full-time service.be very much greater than it is under-a long service system, butthe Reserves will be enormously expanded in comparisori with pre-war. -Inorder to reduce their demands for land, the Services intend to carry on training continuously throughout the year, instead of, as formerly, con-concentrating it mainly in the summer months..10. A second factor is the larger space required for manoeuvre and forthe use of modern weapons. On the one hand the proportion of armour toman-power is greater, and there is need to use more tracked vehicles; onthe other hand the enormous increases in range and mobility&apos; arising fromimprovements, that have taken place in the design of existing weapons, andthe - introduction of new ones into all. the Services have also increased theamount of land needed for practice in their use. .11. Thirdly, land must now be set aside where various arms inco-operation can train with live ammunition. This . form of training, triedout during the war and since adopted by the principal powers, accustomstroops to the conditions and sensations of battle and, by creating confidence,has been an important factor in saving life in action.Training for aircrews must also be provided, which involves the dischargeof live bombs, rocket projectiles, and ammunition from aircraft at operational&apos; heights and speeds. These danger areas are at sea wherever possible, but some land areas are essential. -Because of the danger from- unexploded ammunition, the public must at all times be excluded from training areas of this kind, though some limiteduse may be made of them for purposes such as forestry.PART IY.-rTHE LAND NEEDS FOR TRAINING PURPOSES OFEACH BRANCH OF THE SERVICES12. The following paragraphs attempt to show for what purposes landis needed by each Service, in order that all branches of the Armed Forcesmay be trained in peace-time to a standard that will allow weapons to beused at short notice with efficiency. This involves not only constant practice by the men, but also continuous use. of equipment to make sure that itfunctions properly throughout the year. The inadequacy of pre-war training-grounds was found to be a grave handicap. &quot; ;Royal Navy.   13. &apos;The land requirements of the Royal Navy are mainly for navalgunnery, aviation, and the training of Royal Marines.    Naval gunnery
practices are carried out largely at sea, or from sites on shore where thedanger area is mainly at sea but two land areas are necessary for ship toshore firing.Training in naval aviation involves the use of land for live and practicebombing, air to ground firing and rocket projectile firing. The Royal Marinesneed land for weapon training, company and platoon training, Commandotraining, and training in minor demolition.The Army14. Under the basic training organisation which will be introduced early4pi 1948, men will be selected for the various arms and services as a result ofa pre-eniistment interview at the Ministry of Labour. On enlistment, theywill be called up to Basic Training units of the appropriate type. These units will be located in existing barracks and camps. Recruits will spend there aperiod which will vary with the complexity of the training they have to undergo. They will receive sufficient training in basic military matters andin the specialist tasks which they are to perform in the Army, to enable themto be posted to units as trained individuals.At these Basic Training units, land will be required for rifle ranges, fieldfiring, driving, and small-scale tactical exercise areas.-Land is also required for the training of the units of the Regular and territorial Armies in the United Kingdom. &apos;The most important requirementsunder this heading are areas (to which reference &quot;is made in paragraph 11)where units of all arms can train together under realistic conditions. Fivesuch areas are required in order that this essential form of training may be within reasonable reach of units stationed in all parts of the United Kingdom.Finally there are the &apos; requirements of the Army Schools which areresponsible for the drawing up of the tactical doctrine used throughout&apos; theArmy, and for the training of instructors and certain specialists. these requirements differ considerably according to the purpose for which theschool is designed. The School of Infantry, for example, needs a very large area in order satisfactorily to try out modern supporting weapons and theirtactical employment; the Coast Artillery School, on the other hand, requiresonly a very small area as all firing takes place seawards.       -The various categories of training land required are set out. in detail inparagraph 32 of the Paper. It will be seen that more than half the total requirements are heeded for battle training, field firing and artillery ranges.The scope and range of modern weapons make demands of this sizeunavoidable.Royal Air Force15. Apart from the airfields themselves, the Royal Air Force needs landmainly for armament training.In the ease of training in bombing, most of the exercises are done withpractice bombs, but a number of &quot; live &quot; exercises must be included topractice air crews in carrying and dropping full loads, ground crews inarming up, and Station and higher organisations in the supply and handling 4problems involved.Much valuable gunnery training can be given by the use of cin^-cameras,but men must be trained also in the use of their weapons with liveammunition.In spite of the development of weapons and projectiles, which demandlarger training areas than before the war, the Royal Air Force has kept downto the minimum the size of danger areas. The strategic deployment of theRoyal Air Force very largely governs the distribution of the ranges they use,
but in order to avoid interference with civil interests, a distance of as mucn.as 50 miles between the range and the operational station using it has beenaccepted.  . , .   &apos;     :One ground training area and an Anti-aircraft Gunnery School are needed for the R.A.F. Regiment while the Eoyal Air Force requires the use of rifleranges.  As far as possible, these areas will be shared with the Army.&apos;Auxiliary Forces &quot;16. Auxiliary Force units in any of the Services need parade-grounds,week-end camps, local ranges and land for tactical exercises within reasonablyreach of the homes of the officers and men. A fair amount of land is neede^for these purposes, though each piece is small. Annual camp and similartraining is carried out on land used jointly with the Regular Forces, and,theincreased land required is included in their figures. - : .PART Y. THE POSSIBILITY OF  TRAINING OVERSEAS17, In view of the large amount of land inevitably needed, it is natural that the suggestion should be made that training which would cause difficultyif carried out in this country should take place abroad.in the ease of the Regular Army this is, of course, happening at present,since most of the Regular Army is abroad upon occupation duties in Germanyand elsewhere. Therefore, the training of a large part of the Regular army will in fact take place abroad for some time to come. It is necessary, how-eyer, for security reasons that a reasonable proportion of the Regular Army(which alone is available for immediate service) should be stationed at home;training facilities for these units must therefore be provided in the UnitedKingdom. An additional factor to be remembered is that the sending of ahigh proportion of Regular units overseas for training would have a bad effecton recruiting, because it would increase the already long period of service overseas.18. One of the main reasons against training abroad is that&apos; inthe event of war or an emergency, a complete redisposition and reorganisa-tion of the training establishments would be required, because danger to shipping and many other factors would clearly then make it necessaryto carry out training in the United Kingdom. This change woulddisorganise the training machine and drastically lessen our readiness for war at a vital time: Money spent on training facilities would have been wasted,jmd much of the equipment would be out of use. The change-over and the replacement of essential equipment might take many months., In-order to avoid these difficulties, it would be necessary to have shadowschools and training establishments in the United Kingdom. It would theabe necessary to provide and hold complete sets of equipment, to earmarkaccommodation and training areas that could be taken over and to providetraining and administrative staffs ready to operate these establishments. &apos;PART VI.-THE POSSIBILITY OF TRAINING IN SCOTLAND ORNORTHERN IRELAND19. The Government have carefully considered whether a greater propor-tion of training could not be carried.out in remote areas of Scotland andNorthern, Ireland, and the survey of these two -countries referred to in thePrime Minister&apos;s statement of 25th February bus now been carried out..
r 20.- At -first sight the remoter areas of Scotland may. seem to be useful for&quot; training;   In fact theyT are generally unsuitable because:-(a). Some of the areas are interspersed by large and small valleys whichare crossed with difficulty, if at all.   Moreover, the interveningground tends to he deficient in &quot; features    such as are essential. -  for-military, exercises.(b) In other areas the surface is too wet, soft, or broken, to allow theeasypassage and movement of wheeled and tracked vehicles, and even. . in the drier or. firmer parts the . possibilities of manoeuvre are so.... .    limited as to be almost negligible.   Surfaces which are not peatyare usually too steep and rocky.(c) The climate severely limits the seasons within which operations are.   &apos;   , &apos; feasible. ,    v.     &apos;;;;: , , ,&quot;&apos;&quot;&apos;.&apos; Accordingly; the number of areas which are usable at all,&apos; apart fromminor training and this is not the type of training that really gives rise to^difficulty is comparatively small.21. Of Northern Ireland much the same can be said, while there is theadditional difficulty of the sea transport that would he necessary.Land was requisitioned during the war for training purposes, and theServices, have at present approximately&apos;33,000 acres in use there. Experi-ence during that period showed, that there is little scope for armoured: trainingin that country except in isolated foreshore areas, and that the additional land needed for this purpose cannot be found there.22.; The Army must in war be able to fight on any type of land. Ingeneral, therefore, it is desirable to train men and practise the use of equip-irient under varying conditions, but clearly the elementary stages oftraining must be carried out on land which does not. present abnormaldifficulties to those under instruction. In any case training could not beliteited solely to the very bad&apos;conditions which may be encountered from timeto&apos;.time&apos;&apos;in&quot;War, owing to the time lost, the expense incurred by damage tovehicles and-equipment, and the false lessons which such limited^ trainingwould impart.  : -23. Moreover, the administrative difficulties in the way of.using such areas; as are.physically suitable would be serious. The location of the Forcesin this country is largely governed by the position of,existing accommoda-tion; the building of new accommodation, installations and roads in the few physically suitable areas,in Northern Ireland or. the remoter parts ofScotland would be extremely expensive. &apos;&quot;: ..PART YII. THE CHOICE OF TRAINING AREAS WITHINGREAT BRITAIN24; It has been explained that difficulties of national security and trans-port prevent the greater part of training being carried out overseas, whilethe: unsuitability. of the terrain; and the location of existing accommodationmakes it impossible to use Northern Ireland or the remoter parts of scotland as the principal areas.In. the rest of the United Kingdom it is obviously essential to avoid, if atall.possible, the use of good agricultural land&apos;or.that-reserved for forestry, aswell as catchment areas for water supply. -     -The Services have also tried to avoid using common land near large centres of population arid where this has-been unavoidable^ as for example for,thetraining of local members of the auxiliary, forces,-the&apos;Services have, to the
greatest possible extent, provided only for general training without the use of live ammunition or tracked vehicles for cross country running so as tointerfere as little as possible with the public right of access.A strong criticism of the choice made by the Service Departments oftraining areas in England and Wales is that they are unduly concentrated in areas of high recreational ;ind landscape value, and in particular that-they are concentrated in potential National Park areas. It must be borne in mind, however, that the only type of land the use of which for Servicepurposes would not be open to objection on the grounds mentioned above is,broadly speaking, that found in areas of high amenity value. This, and notany disregard by the Services of the need for preserving them, is the reasonin many cases why training is proposed in National Park areas..25. It has been suggested that all Army training should be carried outon land near the main military centres, such as Aldershot, Colchester andGatterick. As explained in Part IV, certain training facilities must existwithin reasonable reach of the centres. where troops under training areaccommodated. If, therefore, all the training necessary has to be givennear the main military centres, it follows that all the troops to be trained mustbe located in these areas. Much money has, however, already been spent in providing^ accommodation in many other parts of the country. To replacethis accommodation by new building in the main military centres wouldmean the loss of large sums, while in any case the land areas available are inadequate. &quot; &apos;26. Care has been taken to reduce the total requirements of the services to; the minimum consistent with efficiency, by arrangement to share areas where this is possible, and a special Inter-Service Committee was estab-lished by the Government for this purpose.27. In some cases, e.g., the practical training area at Stanford, landalready planted with trees or capable of afforestation will be affected. TheGovernment attach great importance to the preservation of the plantationsin these areas and arrangements have been made for their protection. Therewill be close co-operation between the Service Departments and the forestry commission and tb/ Ministry of Agriculture both at Headquarters andlocally, and the Government are satisfied that the needs of the armed forces can-be met with little detriment to existing plantations;In some areas the Service Departments&apos;,proposals involve the acquisitionof land or training rights on land which would probably otherwise have been used for afforestation. In such cases every effort will be made to providesuitable alternative land.PART YIII. THE AMOUNT OF LAND NEEDED BY THE SERVICES28: During the war 11,547,000 acres of land in Great Britain were heldor used by the Services for training purposes; of this area over 10 million acres have already been released. The rest of the land no longer needed willbe given up as soon, as possible. It is, however, necessary first to clear theland of unexploded ammunition of one kind or another, and this is the main reason for delay.29. As already explained, the needs of the Services for land fall into two parts: for training and for other purposes.   For training 702,000 acres.are-
required; for other purposes 325,200 acres. It must be remembered that land shown under various headings in the following figures includes such areas as Salisbury Plain, Catterick and many others, which have long been used for military purposes. The areas already in the ownership of theServices account for some 40 per cent, of the areas required for training.Effect of the Proposal on Public Access30. The public have hitherto had partial or complete access, on a rough^estimate, to about 60 per cent, of the 700,000 acres which are requiredjjjfor training, i.e., to about 420,000 acres. They will retain unfettered rightof access to some 40 per cent, of this latter area, and a substantial right of access to a ;further 40 per cent., subject to conditions prescribed by bye-laws or otherwise and dependent on the Service requirements. The public will,therefore, be completely excluded from only about 20 per cent, of the area towhich: they previously had access. Moreover, further rights of access maybe given over land acquired by tho Services.Effect of the Proposal on Agriculture and Forestry31.&apos; The use for agricultural purposes of most of the land on whichtraining is carried out will still continue. Of the 700,000 acres needed fortraining only about 14 per cent., on a rough estimate, can be classed ascultivable land.. The amount actually lost to agriculture is not likely to exceed 8 per cent, of the total requirement, and only about a quarter of this,i.e., about 14,000 acres, can be classed as good agricultural land. Of theremainder of the 700,000 acres, some is moorland, heathland or forest land,but the larger part is suitable for grazing and the bulk of this will remainavailable for that purpose, subject to the restrictions imposed by the natureof the Service use.32. The land needed for training for the Armed Forces is provisionallyallocated as follows:  ,     \ ^; AcresAdmiralty        ...       ...      .......&apos;.. 20,000Royal Air Force ...      ..&apos;........ -34,000War Office-.                .           ,                . &apos; AcresBattle training and field-firing areas ... 200,000Field artillery ranges     ...      ... &apos;    ... 170,000              &apos; - .&quot;&apos;         Armoured vehicle driver training areas ... 35,000Armoured fighting vehicle and anti-tankartillery ranges ...      ...      ...      ... 50,000Royal   Engineer   training   areas    and .bridging sites   ...      ...      ...      ... 30,000Anti-Aircraft practice camps    ...      ... 5,000Small arms ranges         .......      ... 65,000General training and miscellaneous areas 93,000.648,000702,000As stated in paragraph 29, some 40 per cent, of this land already belongsto the Services. :   . -
- 33. . Ths approximate requirements of land for other purposes, may, be divided as follows (see Part II): - : ^cres,  Eoyal Air Force Airfields       ...      ...      .:.      ... 140,000Admiralty Airfields       ......      ...      ...      ... 22,700Accommodation and storage    ...      ...&quot;    ...      ... 100,000&apos;Anti-aircraft sites and coastal artillery (permanent) ... 2,000Anti-aircraft sites and coastal artillery (building pre-vented)          ......      ...      ...      ...      ..; i&apos;8,00&apos;0Eadar installations       ...   &quot; ...      ...      ...      ... 4,000Ministry of Supply purposes (other than airfields)   ... 32,000   -Ministry of Supply airfields                       ...... 6,500        325,200Much of this land was used for these purposes before the war. ...34.   A chart comparing present and past requirements will be found atthe end. .35. About two-fifths of an R.A.F. airfield is covered by buildings andconcrete; the rest is generally under grass. On, this basis.it is estimatedthat of the 140,000 acres required for E.A.F. airfields, about 80,000 acreswill always be available for such purposes as hay cutting, grass drying oreven grazing. During the interim period of reorganisation when the E.A.F.requirements on airfields will be below normal, every effort will be madeto make the greatest possible agricultural use of this land; arid it is hopedthat some 23,000 of the 80,000 acres will be available for arable farming.. Similarly, of the B.A.F. requirement of 34,000 acres for bombing rangesand training areas, the bulk is already freely available for grazing and about,000 acres have been made available temporarily for arable farming.As far as practicable, similar arrangements will apply to the land usedfor Admiralty airfields.The approximate area of 100,000 acres for storage and accommodation is largely for buildings erected by the Services before the war or during the warand cannot be used for any other purpose. The amount of land; requiredfor new building by the Services is relatively small.It is not possible to give figures of the types of land included in theremaining requirements, because most of them are merely estimates of totaleventual requirements for operational and research and development purposes which have been prepared in connection with forward defence planning andhave not yet been-related to particular locations. These locations will bedetermined by strategic and geographical considerations. AH that can besaid at this stage is that many of the individual areas, e.g., permanent anti-aircraft sites, will be very small and that their use will cause little disturbanceor deprivation to the public interest.The process of selection and acquisition of these areas will be one of close investigation with due regard to the considerations mentioned in paras. 42 and 49. * -36. Areas at sea have been selected with due regard to the safety ofshipping lanes and public rights of navigation. There will,&apos; however, be some interference with inshore fishing interests but figures of the area over which fishery operations will be restricted cannot be given. Local arrange-ments will be made to minimise interference with fishing.37. Where wild moorland or hill country which is a gathering ground for public water supplies is to be used for training, local arrangements willhe made to guard against the risk of damage to dams and other -works, orof pollution of the water. .
r ; 38.: A number of roads will:have to be permanently closed, but alterna-tive. routes for traffic will be provided wherever necessary.Economy in the extent of training areas required can be brought aboutif firing across roads . is allowed and the proposals take account of this expedient. The Government are satisfied that, subject to certain safeguards,it can be authorised without danger to passing traffic. Guns will be keptso far back that no risk will arise to users of the roads nor will the noiseof explosions distract the attention of drivers.39. The Government recognise that to retain the amount of land they feelto be necessary-for the national safety and for the proper training of NationalService men is to ask from the nation a sacrifice both of wealth, in so far asland is used that is of agricultural or other economic value, and also ofrecreation and enjoyment. This sacrifice is, however, lessened in so far asover wide areas the Services only require freedom to move troops for training purposes, in other respects the land being available for agriculture, forestryandpublic: recreation, and the sea for fishing.40. The following statement shows the needs of the Services for trainingland in Great Britain, but not in Northern Ireland: - StatemkntService	Area in acres held before the -war	Area in acres held during the war	Approximate area in acres for future purposes, including present Service estates						England	Wales	Scotland	TotalAdmiralty...... War Office ...      ... Air Ministry . Total   ...	&quot;   3,000 235,0000 14,000	95,000 11,400,0000) 52,000	16,000 473,000 23,000	105,000 2,000	4,000 70,000 9,000	20,000 648,000. 34,000	252,000	11,547,000	512,000 &apos;	107,000	83,000	702,000(&apos;) Includes accommodation.PART IX.-THE PROCEDURE FOR EXAMINING INDIVIDUALPROPOSALS BY SERVICE DEPARTMENTS:. 41. The Services fully- appreciate the growing dependence of the nationupon home agriculture; the vital importance of home-grown timber; the need to maintain unpolluted sources of water; the part, direct and indirect, played by our..fisheries; the recreational Value of the countryside, and their importance as an economic asset. In many eases areas alternative to those areas first proposed have been adopted, or substantial modifications made.This review is continuing, and is one of the main reasons, for the time taken incoming to final conclusions about: Service land requirements. .42. The Government feel it desirable to make sure that both localauthorities and amenity societies have full, opportunity to make ,representa-tions upon, the effect of the proposals: on the public interest they represent.The procedure laid down in the following paragraph will therefore apply with two exceptions.. It. is not considered necessary. to extend the review indetail.to land; owned by- the Services before the war, on which training
Public Local Inquiry45. In cases where substantial objections on grounds of the. publicinterest still remain, then (subject to security considerations) a public local inquiry will be held, after due notice, at a convenient place.. The object of this inquiry will be to hear and report on objections raised on grounds of public interest, national or local.  These will comprise:  (a) Objections raised by local authorities, water supply undertakers,amenity societies and other bodies concerned, on the grounds of,   &apos;        injury to the public interest; and(6) Representations of scientific or archffiological societies against curtail-ment of opportunities for scientific investigation, such as birdwatching, or damage to areas of unique scientific interest.46. The inquiry will be presided over by a person selected by theMinister of Town and Country Planning (or, in the case of areas in Scotland,by the Secretary of State for Scotland), on the basis of his experience andstanding in public affairs. As the inquiry will be of a non-statutory nature,there will be no powers of summoning witnesses .sub pcena, taking evidence is to be continued without change of use or additional buildings erected forpurposes of storage or accommodation, or to small training grounds for theTerritorial Army. Where operational requirements cannot for reasons of secrecy be made the subject of public local enquiry, then stage (c) of theprocedure must be omitted.43.   The procedure will be as follows : (a) Regional consultation by the Ministry of Town and Country Planning,with the local authority and water supply interests, and consulta-tion by the Headquarters of the Ministry of Town and Country.Planning with amenity and scientific societies having no region^, organisation. . Similar consultations with Scottish interests will bearranged by the Department of Health for Scotland.(6) Consideration of proposals by an Inter-Departmental Committee inthe light of objections expressed by any Civil Department and of representations made under (a), and the submission of reports forconsideration by Ministers.&apos; (c) Public local enquiries (subject to consideration of security) into pro-posals to which objection is maintained by the local authorities.water supply undertakers, or amenity or scientific societies on grounds of public interest.Regional Consultations .    ,44. The object of the regional and Headquarters consultations under (a)of the preceding paragraph is to ascertain and, as far as possible, to resolveobjections put forward in each case.As a result of these consultations and after considering the reports of theInter-Departmental Committee, it may be decided.that the Service Depart-ment proposals must be abandoned. In other cases, the contending claimsmay be so evenly balanced that a final decision cannot be reached withouta public local enquiry. There is, however, a large intermediate range ofcases in which either no objection has been taken, from any quarter orthe proposals have been so modified or other action talren that ho substantialopposition remains.   No public local inquiry will be held in such cases.
on oath, or charging expenses on any body or person. An officer representingthe Service will explain generally the nature of the requirements and answer questions of fact which may be put to him at the discretion of the personappointed to hold the inquiry. Suggestions for the use of specific areas inthe same general locality as alternatives to those under enquiry will beadmissible, but not arguments of a general character, such as that therequirements should be met in some other part of the country or abroad,which would re-open in the particular case questions of principle which theGovernment have decided generally on &quot;the grounds stated in earlier para-graphs of this memorandum.2) 47. It is not a purpose of the inquiry to hear individual owners or lesseeson the ground of disadvantage to their personal interests, although they willnot be debarred, merely because of their interest in the land, from making representations as to the effect of the proposal on file public interest. Subjectto this, the question who should be heard in evidence will be a matter for thepresiding officer. The guiding aim will be, on the one hand, to hear- fully allthat can be said as to the effect of the Service Department proposal on thepublic interest, and on the other, to prevent repetition which wouldprolong the inquiry without benefit.48. In the case of some of the proposed training areas, particularlyStanford and the Purbeck tank gunnery school, it has been, or may be,represented that pledges were given that displaced persons would be allowedto return to their homes at the end of the war. The Government acceptthe fact that pledges of this kind were given or understood to.be given, andit will not therefore be necessary to press the point at any public inquiry.At the same time, for reasons given in earlier paragraphs, areas for practicaltraining must be provided and it follows that if an area in respect of whicha pledge was given were surrendered&apos; and a new area taken up, one result would be the eviction of residents in the new area for the benefit of thoseoriginally displaced.If, however, after a public local inquiry, the Government decided that persons displaced from these areas could not be allowed to return to their homes, the &quot;Government would consider what assistance over and above thecompensation provided by the relevant statutes is necessary towards the satisfactory resettlement of those who have not already been able to resettlethemselves.Considerations of Security49. Reference has been made above to the fact that fn some cases;eg., anti-aircraft gun sites, radar stations, airfields, experimental ranges and establishments, security considerations will preclude the holding of a publiclocal inquiry. In such cases, local authorities, amenity societies, and similarbodies representing public interests will have the opportunity of making representations to the Inter-Departmental Committee.Public Local Inquiry upon Use of Land50. Public local inquiries may also be held on occasions when no questionof the acquisition of land arises, either because the Service Departmentalready own the land or because they only need to obtain training rights over it. The point really at issue is whether the use to be made of the landis, or may be, objectionable, and not the acquisition of the land itself. Apublic local inquiry will therefore be held (subject, as stated, to security con-siderations), if on land already held by a Service Department, a new use isproposed, and objected to on grounds of public interest by a body of
responsible opinion; -or. an -existing use, started diiring; the. -War,. is: sirrrihrrLpobjected to; or even in cases, where.training rights only are in questionif-thereis objection to their exercise,Informal Consultations51. There may be other cases in&apos;which informal conferences between representatives of local authorities, amenity societies, and other publicinterests, and the Departments concerned, or a hearing before the Inter-,Departmental Committee, would be more appropriate than the procedure ata public local inquiry. A request for such an informal conference expressed;by .these.interests will readily be met.
FUTURE SERVICE LANDREQUIREMENTS FOR all purposes IN RELATIONTO THE TOTAL AREA OFLAND IN GREAT BRITAINAND TO HOLDINGS BEFORE.AND DURING THE WAR.


</content>
</cab>
