<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/183/24 images: 598-603</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government&apos;.&apos;.:-:.7!77;   77.;&apos;- :&apos;7;7&apos;,- :  -.&apos; &apos; v--..&apos;1C(75) 74 COPY NO        321 July 1975CABINET1975 REPORT FROM THE SELECT COMMITTEE ON THEPARLIAMENTARY COMMISSIONER FOR ADMINISTRATIONNote by the Lord Privy SealMy colleagues will wish to see the attached reply to the Report from theSelect Committee on the Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration,Session 1974, which has been agreed by the members of the legislation committee.    It is to be published as a White Paper on Wednesday 2 July1975.Civil Service department July .1975
CONFIDENTIAL-FINAL REVISE[to be published as Command 6144 by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery office price lip net]Report from the Select Committeeon theParliamentary Commissionerfor AdministrationSession 1974Observations by the Government
Report from the Select Committee on theParliamentary Commissioner for AdministrationSession 1974Observations by the GovernmentINTRODUCTORYThis White Paper contains the Government^ response to a number ofcomments and recommendations in the Select Committee&apos;s Report, Session1974.DELAY IN REPAYMENTS OF TAX2. In paragraph 3 of their Report, the Committee refer again to thequestion of the allowance of interest on delayed repayments of income tax and estate duty and the statement by the Chancellor of the Exchequer on26 March 1974 foreshadowing provisions in his second Finance Bill on thissubject. As the Committee are aware, provisions relating to interest onrepayments of estate duty (and capital transfer tax) were included in that bill. As promised by the Paymaster General on 13 November 1974(Hansard, Vol. 881, No. 16, Col. 538), provisions in relation to income tax and corporation tax are included in the 1975 Spring Finance Bill.REMISSION OF TAX3. The Committee indicate in Paragraph 12 that they will expect theincome limits governing tax remission in cases of official error to be kept under review. The Government will keep these limits under review.REIMBURSEMENT OF AGENTS&apos; FEES4. In paragraph 15 of their Report, the Committee express the viewthat it is unjust to the taxpayer for no allowance to be made where,exceptionally, a serious error on the Inland Revenue&apos;s part compels a tax-payer quite needlessly to incur costs. The Board of Inland Revenue will consider allowing some recompense in the circumstances envisaged in theReport.PENSIONS INCREASES FOR PERSONS LIVING ABROAD5. In paragraph 6 of their Report the Committee propose to keep underreview the decision of successive Governments not to make pensionsincreases available to persons living abroad in countries with which thereare no reciprocal arrangements. The Government has reviewed the matter again in connection with the April 1975 uprating of pensions and its policyremains as explained to the Committee last year.AWARD OF INDUSTRIAL WIDOWS PENSION6. The Government confirm that if further medical evidence were tobecome available about the pathological relationship between pneumo-coniosis and the degeneration of other organs, cases such as that described in paragraph 16 of the Committee&apos;s report would be looked at again. Todate no new evidence of this kind has been produced.
ACCESS BY PRISONERS TO TYPEWRITERS7. In paragraphs 22-24 of their Report the Committee draw attention tothe circumstances in which prisoners might have access to typewriters.Acknowledging the changes would tend to add to the burdens of the prisonstaff, the Committee nonetheless express the hope that the Home Office&apos;sreview of the existing arrangements would result in a considerable discretionbeing given to governors. The Committee also consider that, particularconsideration should be given to prisoners who have already been accepted as a non-security risk by being transferred to an open prison.8. The Home Office are continuing their review. The current instructions are being re-examined and fresh ones will be issued in due course. for reasons explained in the Home Office evidence to the Committee, a changeof present practice is not free from difficulty. There are control as well as security problems involved in permitting wider access and it seems unlikelythat revised arrangements foreseeable within existing resources could resultin any large scale changes. But the Committee&apos;s views will be borne in mind as the review proceeds. In the meantime the existing provision for governorsto seek headquarters&apos; permission to allow the use of a typewriter where the submission of particular typewritten documents is essential eg by prisonersconducting their own case or appeal or studying for academic qualifications,is continuing to operate.LIVING AWAY FROM HOME ALLOWANCES9. In paragraph 27 of their Report, the Committee ask to be kept informed of the progress of the inter-departmental consultation about thevariations in living-away-from-home allowances and express the hope thatthese consultations will lead to the elimination of anomalous discrepancies.Information about the various schemes in operation which make provision,amongst other things, for the payment of living-away-from home allowanceshas been collated and analysed to ascertain the extent and nature of the differences between the schemes. On the basis of this analysis, the issues raised by the Commissioner are being further considered and a report willbe made to the Committee.LOCAL COMMISSIONERS FOR ADMINISTRATION10. In commenting, in paragraph 34, on the change in arrangements fordealing with cases which involved local government and central government(and possibly also concerned the Health Service Commissioner) the Com-mittee hope that the involvement of more than one Commissioner will not result in unco-ordinated and widely differing judgments. The Governmentshare the hope that the provision which has been made for collaborationand consultation between the Commissioners in the preparation and presentation of their reports will ensure that the different aspects of jointcases of this kind are handled in a uniform way, while, preserving the separate independence of the various Commissioners concerned. As theCommittee observed in paragraph 32, the fact that the parliamentary commissioner is an ex officio member of both the English and WelshCommissions should greatly assist consultation between Commissioners.
HEALTH SERVICE COMMISSIONER11. In paragraphs 39-41 of their Report the Committee refer to therecommendation by the Davies Committee set up to consider hospitalcomplaints procedure in England and Wales that investigating panels shouldbe established by the regional health authorities in England and by the welsh office in Wales. The Select Committee call attention to the dangers ofoverlapping and confusion that a multiplicity of avenues and remedies forcomplaints might cause. The Government is still considering the report ofthe Davies Committee which made many important and far reachingrecommendations; no decisions have yet been reached. They agree that it isimportant that complaints procedures should be as simple and easy to under-stand as possible, and will take this into account in reaching decisions on the report of the Davies Committee.12. The Government note that in paragraphs 45-47 of their Report theCommittee draw attention to the wider responsibilities of the Welsh Officeand the Scottish Home and Health Department arising from the absenceof a regional health service tier and that the Committee have invited the health Service Commissioner to report to them in due course on theprocedural points arising out of these difficulties.13. The Government note that in paragraph 49 of their Report theCommittee invite the Health Service Commissioner to include in his annual report summaries of completed cases in some number, including all those where some follow-up might be advisable and on which the Committee might wish to take further evidence because of procedural or other defectsrevealed. In taking any such evidence the Committee will doubtless wishto safeguard the anonymity of individual cases.Printed in England for Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office by Williams Lea, LondonDd. 158766 K32 7/75ISBN 0 10 161440 3


</content>
</cab>
