<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/95/0 images: 317-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential this Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty&apos;3 GovernmentTABLISHMENT OF A BLOCKADE ADVISORY         COMMITTEE.Admiralty memorandum for the Cabinet.21          The Admiralty have had under consideration thevarious questions that may arise consequent on the raising of the Blockade and the dissolution of the Allied BlockadeCommittee.          It would be regrettable if the experiences andlessons gained on the subject of Blockade were to be lostsight of and the whole subject neglected until anotherwar threatens, or the necessity for bringing economic pressure to bear on another Power arises under theconditions contemplated in Article 16 of the Covenant ofthe League of Nations.  It therefore appears desirablethat, with as little delay as possible,  there should beset up a Blockade Advisory Committee which should meetfrom time to time in Peace-time and review the wholequestion of Blockade policy as affecting the variousPowers with which we may find ourselves  likely to be at war in the future.          The matter /has formed the subject for discussion between the Admiralty^and other Offices  concerned, viz;Foreign Office; War Office, 3oard of Trade, Ministry of food, and Department of Overseas Trade,  which Offices,together with the Treasury have expressed concurrence intho following proposal :-     A Standing Blockade Advisory.Committee to be     set up consisting of Representatives of the     above Departments who would meet from time to     time - say six time a year under normal     conditions.          The duties of the Committee would be to prepare a complete list of contraband in the event of war   -:threatening with any country, and to offer advise inregard to the Contraband lists of Belligerents and their effect on this country when neutral. It would be animportant part of their duty to consider what machinery would be necessary for carrying into effect thevarious forms of Blockade policy that might be possiblein likely eventualities, and to advise as to the necessary steps to give effect to any form&quot;of economic pressurethat might be decided upon when the emergency arose.          The Committee could, if and when desired, bebrought into relation with or be superseded by, anygeneral organization set up by the  Cabinet to co-ordinatedepartmental preparation for War.(Intlld)   W.  H.  L.           19.12.19.

</content>
</cab>
