<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/95/0 images: 326-327</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Military Secret.1224 &quot;From  Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India,                              22nd December 1919.         &apos;                                (Received 24th.)    1729 S.  Reference to your No. 4879, dated 12th December.   Raids on Peshawarand  Knrfam Frontier  are  largely work of  Afridi  deserters  from our  regular  andirregular; military forces,  together with younger  Afridis and of  nomad Wazirisencamped in and round Khost, some from  beyond the frontier, and others withoutregular habitat but having close connection with Wana Waziris.    As regards the Afridis, elders are believed to be anxious for peace, but are unableat present  to  control  the irreconcilable elements noted above.   In  view of Afghansituation and lack of transport we  shall not  be able to undertake decisive operations against the Afridis, if they refuse our terms, until Waziristan campaign is over, andall that we  are  prepared to do  is to stop raids  by reinforcing Peshawar and  Kohat&apos;areas and carrying  out a  modified form of  blockade.  Nomad  Waziris and  Wazirsof Khost are under-no control of the Afridis, and they are  probably acting under theinstigation of Afghan frontier officials, though of this we have no positive proof.    In Waziristan, Tochi Wazirs have accepted our terms and have  hitherto  carriedthem out satisfactorily, but they are now showing  disposition to delay handing in of balance of deserters&apos; rifles, and  some further  pressure may  be needed.  Mahsuds were much  shaken  by aerial bombardment,  and  were at first  reported to be on verge of accepting- our terms ;  but our  insistence on  opening of  road  through Shahur Tangi,to which we attach great strategical importance, is for the  present apparently provingstumbling  block, though bulk  of  tribesmen, as apart from  Maliks,  are reported to favour submission.    Our  troops consequently advanced  in  force from  Jandola on18th  December,  and are  encountering stubborn resistance from  Mahsuds, who arebeing assisted by contingents of Wano Wazirs as  (corrupt  group) whole will be dealtwith after  Mahsuds.  They are still being actively encouraged against us by AfghantShah Daula, whom, however  they are reported to  be watching with lively suspicion.     Zhob tribes are settling down rapidly,  comparatively lenient  settlement havingbeen made by Agent  to the Governor-General on advice of strong Jirga of repre-sentative Sardars,  on * basis of  compensation for damage  clone  and return of&apos;Government rifles,  deserters being punished by  light  fines  or  short  terms of imprisonment.     Foregoing  is summary  of the actual situation on frontier,  but  future  hingeslargely on  attitude  of  Afghanistan.  We gauge  this  broadly as follows.  Amir andMahmud Asrzi are dominated by ambition to make-Afghanistan strong  independent state and to enlarge its boundaries, but do not fully realise weakness  of  its resourcesnor its economic dependence on India.   They regard our Pushto-speaking tribes asAfghanistan irredenta, which  they hope  ultimately to worry  us into ceding to them,but at same time we believe they  regard prospects of expansion in Central  Asia as most  immediately  hopeful.   They  aim at  securing  this  if  possible  by friendlyagreement  with Bolsheviks.   Latter appear  anxious  concerning Moscow,  to  havedropped their communistic principles for Central  Asian purposes,  and to be  making-hostility to British  Empire sole condition of their  friendship and support and to beusing pan-Islamism as their main propaganda.   This  policy is  helped by MahmudTarzi&apos;s  anti-British and pan-Islamic leanings.  In order to win over Afghanistan, Bolsheviks are believed willing to make considerable territorial  concessions, but there are signs that Afghans may demand more than Bolsheviks are  prepared to &apos;give  and that  serious friction may result  between them.   Amir&apos;s policy aims at getting as much as possible  out of  Bolsheviks  and  British simultaneously  and at  playing British  off against  Bolsheviks.  He  probably uses threats  of British  alliance  and obstinate Turcomans as bogey to frighten Bolsheviks, just as lie appears to be using threats of  Bolshevik alliance and intrigues of Pathan tribes of North-Eastern Frontier (as)  bogey to frighten us.  In this situation there are undoubtedly two dangers. First, that  the  Bolsheviks may, for the purpose  of diverting Amir&apos;s ambitions  from Central Asia and  embroiling  him with us, induce him  to  join in attach on Persia, which they profess to wish to liberate from British  dominance;  second, that any great development or  success of pan-Islamic movement might sweep  Afghans off their feet and cause them to attack us again  with such aid from Bolsheviks as they can get. If, for instance, recent events in Mesopotamia were to end in Sheriffian party definitely
        joining  anti-British  and pan-Islamic movement  under Turkish suzerainty, and if        announcement of Turkish peace terms wore to cauee great excitement amongst Indian        Moslems, then there might be risk of Afghan attack and of such widespread disorder        on frontier and in Persia.and Mesopotamia that available  troops would have greatest        difficulty  in  coping with  the  situation.   Our military  advisers  are so  seriously        impressed with this danger that they urge us to make immediate demands on Amir        to expel Bolsheviks, and cease  intrigues with  tribes,  and, if  he  refuses,  to  bring        military pressure to bear upon him.  They state that they are at present able to deal        with Afghanistan by itself  before Afridis have committed themselves against us and        while Indian Moslems are quiescent, as they are confident that troops now in Peshawar        neighbourhood could hold that portion of the frontier and that Amir would collapse        under aerial attacks on  Kabul and Jalalabad, &amp;c.   If, however, we miss this present        opportunity of either stopping Afghan  intrigues or disposing  of  Afghanistan by        itself, widespread  (? Afridi) rising and internal disorders may,  they urge, coincide        with or produce next spring or summer open  declaration of Afghan hostility.  Indian        units, already  below pre war standards owing to the  officer difficulty, will, owing to        necessity of granting leave, be below  strength  for many months, and  British units        will not be fit  for frontier service  in hot weather.   Military authorities doubt whether        troops could then deal with situation thus aggravated  at the worst season of the year        from climatic point of view, especially for  aerial operations.  While admitting force        of these arguments, we still  consider that  best  chance  of avoiding trouble  is  to        continue our present policy.  We  hope to have settled Waziristan by the middle of        February.  This, we hope, may bring Afridis to  their senses, and, in the meanwhile,        friction between the Afghans and Bolsheviks, prospect of  which Malleson constantly        alludes  to, may have definitely developed.   Its developments would  almost  certainly        be stopped by our  making sharp demands from Amir now, even if he were ostensibly        to comply with them, and would probably bring about very results which we wish to        avoid, viz., make him definitely join Bolsheviks and pan-Islamic camp next summer.        On the other hand, if things move in contrary direction and Amir  is by middle of        February drifting into obviously more hostile attitude, there should still  be time to .4      force  him to  show his  hand  before  hot  weather sets  in and  before Central  Asian, i      climate admits of Bolsheviks helping him in Afghanistan or  by serious movement in &apos;      Central Asia.   If.we were then driven to hostilities, release of troops from Waziristan        would place us in a better military position, but even then wec&apos;ould not, until autumn,        undertake more than local operations combined with aerial raids.

</content>
</cab>
