<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/95/0 images: 434-472</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SOCIETE DES nations league OF nations conference INTERNATIONALE DU TRAVAIL   INTERNATIONAL LABOUR  CONFERENCEPROJETS DE CONVENTIONS ET RECOMMANDATIONS   ADOPTES PAR LA CONFERENCE A  LA PREMIERE   SESSION ANNUELLE, 29 OCTOBRE-29 NOVEMBRE 1919DRAFT CONVENTIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS  ADOPTED  BY  THE  CONFERENCE  AT  ITS  FIRST  ANNUAL MEETING, 29 OCTOBER 29 NOVEMBER, 1919(TEXTES AUTHENTIQUES)(AUTHENTIC TEXTS)
                 Sunderland House,                       Curzon Street,                                 LONDRES.                                15 Janvier 1920.  Les  pro jets de Convention et de Recommanda-tions  dont  le texte  est  reproduit ci-apres ontete adoptes par la  Conference  Internationale duTravail, au cours de la seance tenue a Washingtonle 28 novembre 1919, a 1&apos;exception du projet deConvention concernant 1&apos;emploi  des femmes avantet apres 1&apos;accouchement; cette derniere convention a ete adoptee au cours de la seance tenue a Washing-ton le 29 novembre 1919.  Les  textes  de  pro jets  de Conventions  et deRecommandations presented  ici sont  des  copiesexactes des textes authentiques par les signaturesdu  President et du  Secretaire General  de la Con-ferencc Internationale du Travail, et deposes entre les  mains du Secretaire General de la Societe desNations.                 Sundeiiand House,                       Curzon Street,                                  LONDON.                             15 January, 1920.  The  Draft  Conventions and Recommendationshere reprinted were adopted by the InternationalLabour Conference at its meeting held in Washing-ton on 28  November,  1919, with  the exceptionof the  Draft  Convention concerning the  employ-ment of women before and after childbirth, whichwas  adopted  at the meeting held in Washington on 29 November,  1919.  The  texts of the Draft Conventions and Recom-mendations as here presented are true copies of the texts  authenticated  by   the  signatures  of  thePresident and the Secretary General of the Inter-national  Labour  Conference and deposited withthe Secretary General of the League of Nations.Secretaire General de la Societe des Nations.          Secretary General of the League of Nations.
PROJETS DE CONVENTION ET RECOMMANDA-  TIONS  ADOPTED  PAR   LA  CONFERENCE  INTERNATIONALE DU TRAVAIL A WASH-  INGTON.                                       Page.Pro jet de Convention tendant a limiter a huit  heures par jour et a quarante-huit heures  par semaine le nombre des heures de travail  dans les etablissements industriels..     ..    3Pro jet de Convention concernant le chomage   12Recommandation concernant le chomage ..   15Recommandation concernant la  reciprocite  de traitement des travailleurs etrangers ..   17Pro jet de Convention concernant 1&apos;emploi des  femmes avant et apres l&apos;accouchement  ..   18Pro jet de Convention concernant  le travail  de huit des femmes........22Recommandation concernant la prevention  du charbon  ..    .........   26Recommandation concernant la  protection  des femmes et des enfants  contre le satur-  nisme        ........     ..    27Recommandation concernant  la creation d&apos;un  Service Public d&apos;Hygiene......29Pro jet de Convention fixant  1&apos;age  minimum  d&apos;admission  des   enfants   aux  travaux  industriels..........30Projet de Convention concernant  le travail  de nuit des enfants dans l&apos;industrie     ..   34Recommandation concernant l&apos;application de  la  Convention  Internationale  adoptee  a  Berne en 1906 sur 1&apos;interdiction dc l&apos;emploi  du phosphore blanc (jaune) dans 1&apos;industrie  des allumettes     ..     ..   &apos;..     ..   38DRAFT  CONVENTIONS AND  RECOMMENDA-  TIONS  ADOPTED  BY THE INTERNATIONAL  LABOUR CONFERENCE AT WASHINGTON.                                       Page.Draft Convention limiting the hours of work  in industrial undertakings to eight  in the  day and forty-eight in the week  ..     ..     draft Convention concerning unemployment   12Recommendation concerning unemployment   15Recommendation concerning  reciprocity of  treatment of foreign workers    ..     ..    17Draft Convention concerning the  employ-  ment of women before and after childbirth   18Draft Convention concerning employment  of women during the night ..    ..     ..    22Recommendation concerning the  prevention  of anthrax   ..    ..    ......26Recommendation concerning  the protection  of women and children against lead poison-  ing   .,     ..    ..    ..    ..     ..    27Recommendation concerning  the establish-  ment of Government Health Services   ..   - 29Draft Convention  fixing the  minimum  age  for  admission  of  children to industrial  employment......&apos; ..     ..    30Draft Convention concerning the night work  of young persons employed in industry  ..    34Recommendation concerning the application  of the  Berne Convention of 1906, on the  prohibition of the use of white phosphorus  in the manufacture of matches   ..     ..    3S
kt 0 JSOCIETE DES nations league OF  nations conference  INTERNATIONALE  DU TRAVAIL    INTERNATIONAL  LABOUR  CONFERENCEPROJET  DE   CONVENTION   TENDANT   A  DRAFT    CONVENTION    LIMITING    THELIMITER  A HUIT  HEURES  PAR  JOURET  A  QUARANTE-HUIT   HEURES  PARSEMAINE LE NOMBRE  DES  HEURES de travail  DANS  LES  ETABLISSEMENTSINDUSTRIELS.HOURS OP WORK IN  INDUSTRIAL UN-DERTAKINGS   TO  EIGHT  IN  THE  day and FORTY-EIGHT IN THE WEEK.  La   Conference  Generate   de   1&apos;Organisation    The  General  Conference of the  InternationalInternationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  des  Labour  Organization of  the League of  Nations/Nations,      Convoquee  a  Washington  par  le  Gou-    vernement  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre 1919,      Apres  avoir  decide   d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions  relatives  a  &quot; 1&apos;application  du    principe de la journee de huit heures ou de    la   semaine  de   quarante-huit   heures,&quot;    question   formant  le  premier  point  de    1&apos;ordre  du  jour  de  la  session de  la  Con-    ference tenue a. Washington, et      Apres avoir decide que ces propositions    seraient redigees  sous forme d&apos;un projet de    convention internationale,adopte  le  Projet  de Convention  ci-apres  aratilier  par   les  Membres   de   1&apos;OrganisationInternationale  du  Travail,   conformement  aux dispositions  de  la Partie  relative  au  Travaildu Traite de Versailles du  29 juin 1919, et duTraite de Saint-Germain du  10 septembre 1919:                 ARTICLE  1.  Pour  1&apos;application de la presente  Convention,seront  considered comme  &quot; etablissements indus-triels &quot;  notamment:  (a) Les  mines, carrieres   et  industries   ex-tractives de toute nature ;  (b) Les industries dans  lesquelles des  produitssont  manufactures,  modifies,  nettoyes,  repa-res, decores,  acheves, prepares  pour la vente,ou  dans lesquelles  les matieres  subissent unetransformation, y  compris  la construction  desnavires,   les   industries    de  demolition  demateriel, ainsi que la  production,  la transformation-tion et la  transmission de  la force motrice engeneral  et de 1&apos;electricite ;  (c) La construction, la  reconstruction,  l&apos;en-tretien,  la  reparation,  la  modification  ou  lademolition   de  tous  batiments   et   edifices,chemins  de  fer,   tramways,    ports,   docks,  (3164)  P1514/83R 1/20  500 D.St. (Gp. 38      Having  been  convened  at  Washington    by the  Government  of  the United States    of America,  on the  29th  day of October,    1919, and      Having  decided  upon  the  adoption  of    certain  proposals  with   regard   to   the    &quot; application of the principle of the 8-hours    day or of  the 48-hours week,&quot;  which is the    first item in  the agenda for the Washington    meeting of the Conference, and      Having  determined that  these  proposals    shall take  the  form of a draft  international    convention,adopts  the following  Draft   Convention  for ratification  by  the Members  of the  Interna-tional  Labour  Organization,  in  accordance withthe Labour Part of the  Treaty of Versailles of28 June, 1919, and of the Treaty of St. Ger-main  of 10 September,  1919:                 ARTICLE 1.  For  the  purpose  of  this  Convention,  the term  &quot; industrial undertaking&quot;  includes  parti-cularly:  (a)  Mines, quarries,  and other works for the extraction of minerals from the earth.  (b)  Industries  in which  articles  are manu-&apos;factured,   altered,   cleaned,   repaired,   orna-mented,  finished, adapted for sale, broken  up on demolished, or in which materials are trans-formed;  including shipbuilding  and the genera-tion,  transformation, and transmission of elec-tricity or motive power of any kind..  (c) Construction,     reconstruction,    mainte-nance,  repair,  alteration,  or demolition of  any building, railway, tramway, harbour, dock, pier,canal,  inland  waterway,  road, tunnel,  bridge,(3)B3
jetees,  canaux,  installations  pour   la  naviga-tion interieure,  routes,  tunnels, ponts,  viaducs,egouts   collecteurs,  egouts   ordinaires,   puits,installations   telegraphiques  ou   telephoniques,installations   electriques,  usines  a   gaz,   dis-tribution  d&apos;eau,  ou  autres  travaux  de  con-struction, ainsi  que  les travaux  de preparationet de fondation precedant les  travaux ci-dessus;  (d)  Le  transport de  personnes  ou  de  mar1chandises par route, voie ferree  ou  voie  d&apos;eau,maritime  ou  interieure,  y  compris  la  manu-tention des marchandises  dans les  docks,  quais,wharfs  et  entrepots, a  1&apos;exception  du  transporta la main.  Les  prescriptions  relatives  au  transport  parmer et par  voie  d&apos;eau interieure  seront  fixeespar une Conference  speciale sur le  travail desmarins et mariniers.  i  Dans  chaque   pays   1&apos;autorite   competentedeterminera   la  ligne  de  demarcation  entrei&apos;industrie,  d&apos;une  part,  le  commerce et  1&apos;agri-culture, d&apos;autre  part.viaduct,  sewer,  drain,   well,   telegraphic  ortelephonic   installation,  electrical   undertaking,gas work, waterwork or other work  of  construc-tion,  as well as  the  preparation for or laying the foundations of any such work or structure.  (d)  Transport  of  passengers  or  goods   byroad,  rail,   sea  or  inland  waterway,  includ-ing  the  handling  of  goods  at  docks,  quays,wharves  or  warehouses,  but  excluding  trans-port by hand.  The  provisions  relative  to  transport by  sea and  on inland waterways shall be  determinedby  a  special  conference  dealing  with  employ-ment at sea and on inland waterways.  The  competent  authority  in  each  country shall  define the line  of  division which  separatesindustry from  commerce and agriculture.                   ARTICLE  2.   Dans   tous   les   etablissements  industriels, publics  ou prives,  ou  dans  leurs dependances, de quelque  nature qu&apos;ils soient,  a 1&apos;exception de  ceux  dans  lesquels  sont   seuls  employes les membres  d&apos;une meme famine, la duree du travail.  du personnel  ne  pourra  exceder  huit heures  par  jour  et  quarante-huit  heures  par semaine,  sauf les  exceptions prevues  ci-apres:   (a) Les  dispositions  de   la   presente  Con- vention  ne sont pas  applicables  aux personnes occupant un  poste  de surveillance ou de direc- tion ou un poste de confiance.   (b) Lorsque en vertu d&apos;une loi ou par  suite de 1&apos;usage ou de  conventions&apos; entre  les  organisa- tions patronales et ouvrieres (ou, a  defaut de telles  organisations, entre les representants des patrons  et des  ouvriers),  la duree  du  travail d&apos;un  ou plusieurs jours de  la semaine est infe- rieure a  huit heures, un  acte de  1&apos;autorite compe- tente ou une convention  entre  les organisations ou representants susmentionnes  des  interesses peut  autoriser le depassement&apos; de  la limite des huit heures les  autres jours  de  la semaine.   Le depassement   preVu par le   present  paragraphe ne pourra jamais  exceder une  heure par  jour.   (c)  Lorsque   les   travaux   s&apos;effectuent   parequipes,  la duree du travail  pourra etre   pro-longee au-dela  de  huit heures  par jour  et dequarante-huit  heures  par  semaine,  a  la  con-dition que la moyenne des  heures  de  travailcalculee  sur  une  periode  de  trois semaines  oumoins  ne  depasse   pas   huit   par  jour  etquarante-huit  par semaine.                   ARTICLE 2.  The  working  hours of  persons employed  inany public or private industrial undertaking  orin  any  branch  thereof,  other  than an under-taking  in  which  only  members  of  the  samefamily  are  employed,  shall  not  exceed  eightin  the   day  and  forty-eight  in  the  week,with  the exceptions hereinafter  provided for.  (a)  The provisions  of  this  Convention  shallnot apply to persons  holding  positions  of super-vision  or  management,  nor  to  persons   em-ployed in a confidential capacity.  (b)  Where by  law,  custom,  or  agreement be-tween  employers&apos;   and  workers&apos;   organizations,or,  where no such organizations  exist,  between employers&apos;  and   workers&apos;  representatives,&apos; thehours of work on one or more days of  the  weekare less  than eight,  the  limit  of eight hoursmay  be  exceeded  on  the remaining   days  ofthe week by the  sanction   of  the competentpublic  authority,   or  by  agreement   betweensuch  organizations  or  representatives  ;   pro-vided, however,  that in  no case under the  pro-visions  of this  paragraph  shall the  daily  limit of  eight  hours be  exceeded  by  more  thanone  hour.  (c)  Where persons are  employed in  shifts  itshall  be  permissible to  employ  persons in ex-cess of  eight hours in any one day and forty-eight  hours  in  any one week,  if  the  average number  of  hours over a period  of three weeksor  less  does not   exceed  eight  per day   and forty-eight per week.
                   ARTICLE 3.   La  limite  des heures  de  travail  prevue  a 1&apos;article  2  pourra  etre depassce en  cas d&apos;acci- dent  survenu ou imminent,  ou en  cas de  tra- vaux d&apos;urgence  a effectuer  aux machines ou  a 1&apos;outillage,  ou en  cas de  force  majeure,  mais uniquement  dans  la  mesure necessaire  pour eviter  qu&apos;une gene  serieuse ne  soit  apportee  a la marche normale de 1&apos;etablissement.                   ARTICLE 4.   La limite  des  heures  de   travail   prevue  a 1&apos;article  2  pourra  etre depassee dans  les  tra- vaux dont  le  fonctionnement continu doit,  en raison  meme  de la   nature  du  travail,   etre assure  par des  equipes successives,  a la condi- tion  que  les  heures  de  travail n&apos;excedent  pas en  moyenne  cinquante-six  par semaine.    Ce regime n&apos;affectera pas les  conges  qui  peuvent etre  assures  aux travailleurs  par les lois natio- nales  en  compensation  de leur jour de  repos hebdomadaire.                   ARTICLE  5.   Dans les  cas exceptionnels ou les limites  fixees a 1&apos;article  2 seraient  reconnues  inapplicables, et  dans  ces  cas  seulement,  des   conventions entre organisations ouvrieres et patronales  pour- ront, si  le Gouvernement,  a  qui  elles  devront etre  communiquees,  transforme  leurs  stipula- tions en  reglements,  etablir sur une  plus longue periode un tableau reglant la duree  journaliere du travail.   La  duree  moyenne  du  travail, calculee  sur le nombre de semaines determine par  le tableau, ne pourra  en aucun  cas  exceder  quarante-huit heures par semaine.                   ARTICLE 6.   Des reglements  de 1&apos;autorite publique deter- mineront  par industrie ou par profession :   (a)  les  derogations  permanentes  qu&apos;il  y aura lieu  d&apos;admettre  pour les  travaux  preparatoires ou complementaires  qui  doivent  etre  neces- sairement   executes  en  dehors   de  la  limite assignee  au travail  general  de  1&apos;etablissement, ou pour  certaines categories de personnes dont le travail est  specialement intermittent ;   (b)  les  derogations  temporaires  qu&apos;il&quot;&quot;y  aura lieu  d&apos;admettre pour  permettre aux  entreprises de  faire  face  a  des  surcroits  de  travail  extra- ordinaires.  Ces  reglements doivent  etre pris  apres con- sultation  des  organisations  patronales  et  ou- vrieres  interessees,  la  ou  il  en  existe.    Ils determineront  le  nombre  maximum   d&apos;heuressupplementaires  qui  peuvent  etre   autoriseesdans  chaque cas.   Le taux du salaire pour  cesheures supplementaires  sera majore d&apos;au moins25 pour cent par rapport au salaire normal.                   ARTICLE 3.   The  limit of hours  of  work prescribed  in  Ar- ticle 2  may be  exceeded  in  case of  accident, actual  or threatened,  or  in case of urgent work to be done  to machinery or plant, or in case of &quot; force  majeure,&quot; but only so  far  as  may  be necessary  to  avoid  serious  interference with the ordinary working of the undertaking.                   ARTICLE 4.   The  limit of hours  of  work prescribed  in  Ar- ticle 2 may also  be exceeded in those processes which are  required  by reason of the nature of the process  to be carried on continuously by  a succession  of  shifts,  subject  to the  condition that the working hours  shall  not exceed fifty- six  in  the week  on the  average.  Such regula- tion of the hours of work shall  in no  case affect any  rest  days  which  may  be  secured by  the national  law to  the workers in such processes in compensation for the weekly rest day.                   ARTICLE 5.   In exceptional  cases  where  it  is  recognized that  the  provisions  of  Article  2  cannot  be applied,  but only  in such  cases,  agreements between   workers&apos;   and   employers&apos;   organiza- tions concerning  the daily limit  of work over  a longer period of  time  may be given the force of regulations,  if the Government,  to  which  these agreements  shall  be   submitted,  so   decides.   The  average  number  of hours  worked  per week,  over  the  number  of weeks covered  by any  such  agreement  shall  not exceed  forty- eight.                   ARTICLE 6.   Regulations  made by  public  authority  shall determine for industrial undertakings :   (a) The permanent  exceptions  that may  be allowed   in  preparatory  or   complementary work  which  must  necessarily   be carried  on outside  the  limits  laid  down  for  the general working  of  an  establishment,   or  for certain classes  of  workers  whose  work is   essentially intermittent.   (b)  The  temporary  exceptions that  may  be allowed,  so  that  establishments  may  deal with exceptional cases of pressure of work.  These  regulations  shall  be made  only   afterconsultation  with the  organizations of  employ-ers and  workers  concerned, if any  such organi-zations  exist.  These  regulations  shall  fix  themaximum  of  additional hours in each  instance,and  the rate of  pay for  overtime  shall not  beless than one and  one-quarter times the regularrate.
                   ARTICLE 7.   Chaque   Gouvernement   communiquera   au Bureau  International du Travail:   (a)  une  liste  des  travaux  classes  comme ayant  un  fonctionnement  necessairement  con- tinu dans le sens de 1&apos;article 4 ;   (b)  des  renseignements  complets  sur  la pra- tique des accords prevus a 1&apos;article 5 ;   (c) des  renseignements complets  sur les&apos;  dis- positions  reglementaires  prises  en  vertu  de 1&apos;article  6 et leur application.   Le  Bureau  International   du  Travail  pre- sentera chaque annee un rapport a ce sujet  a la Conference   Generale  de  1&apos;Organisation  Inter- nationale du Travail.                   ARTICLE 8. .  En  vue  de  faciliter  1&apos;application  des  dis- positions   de   la   presente  convention,  chaque patron devra:   (a) faire   connaitre   au   moyen   d&apos;affiches apposees  d&apos;une  maniere  apparente  dans  son etablissement ou  en tout autre lieu  convenable, ou  selon  tout  autre  mode  approuve   par le Gouvernement,   les   heures   auxquelles   com- mence  et  finit  le  travail,  ou,  si  le  travail s&apos;effectue  par  equipes,  les  heures  auxquelles commence  et  finit  le tour de chaque equipe. Les  heures  seront  fixees  de  facon a ne  pas depasser  les  limites  prevues  par  la  presente convention, et, une  fois  notifiees, ne  pourront eTre modifiees  que  selon le mode et  la  forme d&apos;avis  approuves par le Gouvernement;   (b) faire  connaitre,  de  la  meme  facon,   les repos  accordes  pendant  la  duree du travail et consideres comme  ne faisant  pas  partie  des heures de travail;   (c) inscrire  sur  un  registre,  selon  le  mode approuve par  la  legislation de  chaque pays  ou par  un   reglement  de  1&apos;autorite  competente, toutes  les heures supplementaires  effectuees  en vertu  des articles 3  et  6  de  la  presente  Con- vention.  Sera  considere  comme illegal  le  fait  d&apos;em-ployer   une  personne en   dehors  des  heuresfixees  en vertu du paragraphe  (a),  ou pendantles heures fixees en vertu du paragraphe (b).                  ARTICLE 9.  L&apos;application  de  la presente  convention  auJapon  comport era  les modifications  et  condi-tions suivantes :   (a) Seront   consideres   comme   &quot;  etablisse-ments industriels,&quot; notamment        les  etablissements  enumeres  au  para-    graphe  a  de  1&apos;article  ler; &apos; &apos;    les  etablissements  enumeres  au  para-    graphe  b  de  1&apos;article ler,  sils  occupent  au    moins dix  personnes;                 ARTICLE 7.   Each  Government  shall communicate  to the International Labour Office:   (a) A  list of the processes which  are  classed as  being  necessarily  continuous  in  character under Article  4 ;   (b) Full information  as  to  working  of the agreements mentioned in Article 5 ; and   (c)  Full information  concerning  the  regula- tions made under Article 6 and their application.   The International  Labour  Office   shall  make an annual  report  thereon  to the General  Con- ference of  the International Labour Organiza- tion.                   ARTICLE 8.  In  order  to  facilitate the  enforcement  of the provisions  of  this  Convention,  every  employer shall  be  required:  (a)  To  notify, by means  of  the  posting  of notices in conspicuous places in  the works  or other suitable  place,  or  by  such  other method as  may  be  approved by the  Government, the hours  at  which  work  begins  and  ends,  and where work is  carried on by  shifts, the hours at which each  shift  begins  and  ends.   These hours shall be  so  fixed that the duration of the work  shall not exceed the limits  prescribed by this  Convention,   and when  so  notified  they shall  not be  changed  except with such notice and in such manner as may be approved  by the Government.  (b)  To  notify  in  the  same  way   such  restintervals  accorded  during  the  period  of  work as  are  not  reckoned as  part  of  the working hours.  (c)  To  keep  a record in the  form  prescribed by  law  or regulation in  each country  of alladditional  hours worked  in  pursuance of  Arti-cles 3 and 6 of this Convention.  It shall be made an offense against the law to employ any  person outside the  hours fixed inaccordance with paragraph  (a), or during the in-tervals fixed  in accordance with paragraph (b).                  ARTICLE  9.  In  the  application  of  this   Convention  to japan the  following  modifications  and  condi-tions  shall obtain :  (a)  The  term   &quot; industrial  undertaking &quot; in-cludes particularly       The  undertakings  enumerated  in  para-    graph (a) of Article 1 ;      The  undertakings  enumerated  in  para-    graph   (b)   of  Article  1,  provided  there    are at least ten workers  employed;
       les  etablissernents  enumeres  au   para-    graphe c de 1&apos;article  ler,  sous  reserve que    ces  etablissements  soient  compris  dans  la    definition   des   &quot; fabriques&quot;   donnee  par    1&apos;autorite  competente;       les  etablissements  enumeres  au   para-    graphe d de  1&apos;article ler, sauf  le  transport    de  personnes  ou  de  marchandises  par    route,  la  manutention  des  marchandises    dans les  docks,  quais,  wharfs et entrepots,    ainsi que le transport a la  main;  et,       sans  egard  au  nombre  des  personnes    occupees,   ceux   des   etablissements   in-    dustriels   enumeres  aux    paragraphes   b    et c  de 1&apos;article  Pr que 1&apos;autorite  compe-    tente  pourrait  declarer  tres dangereux ou    comportant des travaux insalubres.  (b)  La  duree  effective du travail de  toutepersonne  agee  d&apos;au  moins  15  ans,  employeedans   un  etablissement  industriel,  public  ouprive,  ou  dans  ses  dependances,  ne depasserapas   cinquante-sept  heures  par  semaine,  saufdans  l&apos;industrie de  la  soie   grege, ou  la dureemaximum  de  travail  pourra etre  de  soixanteheures par semaine.  (c)  La  duree  effective  du travail ne  pourraen  aucun  cas   depasser quarante-huit   heurespar  semaine, ni  pour les enfants  de moins dequinze ans occupes dans les etablissements in-dustriels,   publics  ou   prives,   ou   dans  leursdependances,  ni  pour les   personnes  occupeesaux  travaux  souterrains  dans  les  mines,  quelque soit leur age.  (d)  La  limitation  des  heures  de  travail  peut etre  modifiee dans  les conditions prevues  auxarticles 2,  3,  4  et 5 de la  presente Convention,sans  toutefois  que  le  rapport   entre  la dureede la  prolongation  accordee et  la  duree de  lasemaine   normale   puisse  etre   superieur  aurapport  resultant  des   dispositions  des  ditsarticles.  (e)  Une  periode de   repos  hebdomadaire  devingt-quatre  heures  consecutives sera accordeea  tous   les  travailleurs  sans  distinction  decategorie.  (/)  Les  dispositions  de  la legislation  indus-trielle  du  Japon qui  en  limitent  1&apos;applicationaux   etablissements   ou  sont   employees  au moins quinze   personnes,  seront  modifiees defacon  a   ce  que  cette  legislation  s&apos;appliquedesormais  aux   etablissements   ou   sont  em-ployees  au  moins  dix  personnes.  (g)  Les   dispositions   des  paragraphes   ci-dessus du present article entreront en  vigueurau plus  tard le ler juillet  1922  ;  toutefois,  les dispositions   contenues   a   1&apos;article  4,   tellesqu&apos;elles  sont   modifiees  par  le  paragraphe  ddu  present  article,   entreront   en  vigueur auplus tard le ler juillet 1923.      The  undertakings  enumerated   in  para-    graph (c)  of  Article 1, in so  far  as  these    undertakings   shall  be  defined  as  &quot; fac-    tories &quot; by the competent authority;      The  undertakings  enumerated   in  para-    graph id)   of  Article  1,   except   transport    of  passengers  or goods  by  road, handling    of  goods  at  docks,  quays,  wharves,  and    warehouses,  and  transport by  hand;  and,      Regardless   of  the  number of  persons    employed,   such  of  the   undertakings  enu-    merated  in  paragraphs   (b)  and  (c)  of    Article  1 as may  be declared by  the  com-    petent   authority  either  to  be  highly    dangerous  or to  involve unhealthy processes.  (b)  The  actual  working  hours  of  persons of fifteen  years of age or  over  in any  public or private   industrial   undertaking,   or   in   anybranch   thereof,  shall   not  exceed   fifty-sevenin  the  week,   except   that   in   the  raw-silkindustry  the limit may  be sixty  hours  in  theweek.  (c)  The  actual  working  hours  of  persons under fifteen  years  of  age  in  any  public  or private   industrial   undertaking,   or   in   anybranch  thereof, and of all miners  of  whateverage engaged in underground work  in the mines,shall  in  no  case exceed forty-eight in  the  week.  (d)  The  limit  of   hours of  work  may  be modified  under the  conditions provided for in articles  2, 3, 4, and 5 of this Convention,  butin no case shall the length of such modificationbear  to the length  of the basic  week a pro-portion   greater than that  which obtains  inthose Articles.  (e)  A   weekly  rest  period  of  twenty-fourconsecutive   hours   shall  be  allowed  to   allclasses of workers.  (/)  The provision  in Japanese   factory  legis-lation limiting its  application  to places employ-ing fifteen  or   more persons  shall  be amended so  that such  legislation  shall apply  to  placesemploying ten  or more persons.  (g)  The  provisions  of the  above paragraphs of this   Article shall  be  brought  into  operationnot  later than  1  July,  1922, except that theprovisions of  Article  4 as  modified  by  para-graph (d) of this  Article shall be brought  intooperation not later than 1 July, 1923.
  (//) La limite de quinze ans prevue an paragraphec du present article  sera  portee  a seize  ans leIer juillet 1925 au plus tard.                  ARTICLE 10.  Dans  Uncle  britannique,  le  principe  de  lasemaine  de  soixante heures  sera adopte - pourtous  les  travailleurs occupes  dans  les  indus-tries  actuellement  visees  par la  legislation  in-dustrielle  dont   le   Gouvernement   de  1&apos;Indeassure 1&apos;application, ainsi  que dans  les  mines etdans  les  categories de  travaux de  chemins defer   qui   seront   enumerees  a  cet  effet   par1&apos;autorite   competente.     Cette   autorite,  nepourra autoriser des modifications  a  la  limiteci-dessus  mentionnee  qu&apos;en  tenant  compte  des dispositions  contenues  dans  les articles 6 et 7de la presente Convention.   1  Les  autres prescriptions  de la  presente Con-vention  ne  s&apos;appliqueront  pas a 1&apos;Inde, maisune  limitation plus etroite des heures de  travaildevra  etre   examinee   lors   d&apos;une   prochainesession de  la Conference Generale.                  ARTICLE 11.  Les  dispositions  de  la  presente  convention ne s&apos;appliqueront ni  a la  Chine,  ni  a la Perse,ni  au  Siam,  mais  la limitation de  la  duree dutravail dans  ces pays  devra  etre examinee  lorsd&apos;une   prochaine  session  de  la   ConferenceGenerale.                  ARTICLE 12.  Pour  1&apos;application  de   la  presente  Conven-tion a la  Grece, la  date  a laquelle  ces disposi-tions  entreront  en   vigueur,   conformement  a1&apos;article  19,  pourra etre reportee  au  ler juillet1923,  pour   les  etablissements  industriels  ci-apres:       (1) Fabriques de sulfure de carbone,       (2) Fabriques d&apos;acides,       (3) Tanneries,       (4) Papeteries,       (5) Imprimeries,       (6) Scieries,       (7) Entrepots   de   tabac   et   etablisse-             ments   ou  se fait  la  preparation             du tabac,       (8) Travaux   a.  ciel  ouvert  dans   les             mines,       (9) Fonderies,      (10) Fabriques de chaux,      (11) Teintureries,   -   (12) Verreries  (souffleurs),      (13) Usines a gaz  (chauffeurs),      (14) Chargement   et   chargement    de              marchandises;et  au plus  tard  au  ler  juillet  1924,   pour lesetablissements industriels ci-apres:  (h)  The  age  of  fifteen  prescribed  in  para-graph  (c)  of this Article shall  be  raised,  not later than 1 July, 1925, to sixteen.                  ARTICLE 10.  In  British India  the  principle  of a sixty-hour  week  shall  be  adopted for  all workers inthe industries at  present covered  by the  fac-tory  acts  administered by the  Government ofIndia, in mines,  and in  such  branches  of  rail-way work as shall be specified for this  purpose by  the  competent  authority.   Any  modifica-tion of this limitation made  by  the competent authority shall  be subject  to  the provisions ofArticles 6 and 7  of this Convention.   In other respects  the provisions  of this Convention  shallnot  apply   to   India,  but further  provisionslimiting  the  hours  of work in  India shall  beconsidered at a  future meeting  of the  general conference.                  ARTICLE 11.  The provisions of this  Convention  shall  notapply  to China,  Persia,  and  Siam, but  provi-sions  limiting  the  hours  of  work  in  thesecountries shall be considered  at a  future  meet-ing of the General Conference.                  ARTICLE 12.  In  the   application  of  this  Convention  to greece,  the date at  which  its  provisions  shallbe  brought into operation in  accordance  with article 19  may  be extended to not later  than  July,  1923, in the  case of the  following in-dustrial  undertakings:       (1) Carbon-bisulphide works,       (2) Acids works,       (3) Tanneries,       (4) Paper mills,       (5) Printing works,       (6) Sawmills,       (7) Warehouses   for  the  handling   and             preparation of tobacco,       (8) Surface mining,       (9) Foundries,      (10) Lime works,      (11) Dye works,      (12) Glassworks (blowers),      (13) Gas works (firemen),      (14) Loading     and    unloading    mer-             chandise;and to not later than 1  July,  1924, in the  caseof the following  industrial undertakings :
   (1)  Industries  m^caniques :   construction de  machines,  fabrication   de  coffres-forts, balances,  lits,  pointes,  plomb  de  chasse, fonderies  de fer et de  bronze, ferblanterie, ateliers    d&apos;etamage, fabriques   dappareils hydrauliques;   (2)  Industries   du   batiment:   fours  a chaux,  fabriques  de  ciment,  de  platre, tuileries,    briqueteries    et    fabriques   de dalles, poteries, scieries  de  marbre, travaux de terrassement et de construction ;   (3)  Industries  textiles:   filatures  et  tis- sages de toutes sortes, sauf les teintureries;   (4)  Industries de 1&apos;alimentation : minoteries, boulangeries, fabriques de pates alimentaires, fabriques  de vins,  d&apos;alcools  et de  boissons, huileries,   brasseries,  fabriques de  glace et d&apos;eaux gazeuses,  fabriques  de produits  de confiserie  et  de chocolat,  fabriques de sau- cissons et de conserves, abattoirs et boucheries ;   (5) Industries chimiques :  fabriques de cou- leurs  synthetiques,  verreries  (sauf  les souf- fleurs), fabriques d&apos;essence de terebenthine et de tartre,  fabriques d&apos;oxygene et de produits pharmaceutiques,  fabriques  d&apos;huile de  lin, fabriques  de  glycerine,  fabriques  de carbure de calcium, usines a. gaz (sauf les chauffeurs);   (6) Industries du cuir :  fabriques  de chaus- sures,  fabriques d&apos;articles  en  cuir;   (7) Industries du papier et de rimprimerie : fabriques d&apos;enveloppes, de registres,  de boites, de sacs, ateliers de reliure, de lithographie et de zincographie ;   (8) Industries du vetement:  ateliers de cou- ture et de lingerie, ateliers   de pressage, fa- briques de couvertures de lits, de fleurs artifi- cielles, de  plumes et de  passementeries, fa- briques de  chapeaux et de parapluies ;   (9) Industries  du bois :  menuiserie, tonnel- lerie, charronnerie,  fabriques de meubles et de chaises,  ateliers d&apos;encadrement, fabriques de brosses et  de balais;   (10)  Industries electriques:  usines de pro- duction de  courant,  ateliers  d&apos;installations electriques;   (11)  Transports  par terre :   employes dechemins  de  fer  et  de tramways,  chauffeurs,cochers, et charretiers.   (1)  Mechanical    industries:      Machine shops   for   engines,   safes,  scales,   beds, tacks,   shells   (sporting),   iron   foundries, bronze  foundries,  tin  shops,  plating  shops, manufactories of hydraulic  apparatus ;   (2)  Constructional    industries:     Lime- kilns,    cement  works,  plasterers&apos;   shops, tile   yards,   manufactories  of  bricks  and pavements,  potteries,  marble  yards,   exca- vating and building  work;   (3)  Textile  industries:     Spinning   and weaving  mills  of   all kinds,   except  dye works;   (4)  Food  industries:  Flour  and   grist- mills,  bakeries, macaroni  factories,   manu- factories  of   wines,   alcohol,   and  drinks, oil works, breweries,  manufactories   of  ice and  carbonated  drinks,  manufactories   of confectioners&apos;    products   and   chocolate, manufactories  of  sausages   and  preserves, slaughterhouses, and butcher shops ;   (5) Chemical  industries :    Manufactories of  synthetic   colors, glassworks (except the blowers),   manufactories   of   essence   of turpentine  and   tartar,   manufactories   of oxygen and pharmaceutical products,  manu- factories  of   flaxseed  oil,  manufactories  of glycerine,  manufactories  of  calcium  car- bide, gas works (except the firemen);   (6) Leather   industries:   Shoe  factories, manufactories of  leather  goods ;   (7) Paper    and   printing    industries: Manufactories of  envelopes,  record   books, boxes,   bags,   bookbinding,   lithographing, and  zinc-engraving  shops ;   (8) Clothing  industries:   Clothing   shops, underwear  and trimmings,  workshops for pressing,   workshops   for   bed   coverings, artificial  flowers,  feathers,   and  trimmings, hat and  umbrella factories ;   (9) Woodworking   industries:     Joiners&apos; shops,   coopers&apos;   sheds,   wagon  factories, manufactories   of    furniture   and   chairs, picture-framing  establishments,  brush  and broom factories ;   (10)  Electrical industries:  Power  houses, shops for electrical  installations ;   (11)  Transportation   by   land:     Em-ployees  on railroads and street  cars, fire-men, drivers, and carters.                  ARTICLE 13.  Pour 1&apos;application de la presente  convention a la  Roumanie, la date  a laquelle ses disposi-tions   entreront  en  vigueur,  conformement  a1&apos;article  19, pourra etre  portee  au  ler juillet1924.                  ARTICLE 13.  In  the   application  of  this   Convention  to roumania  the  date  at  which  its  provisions shall  be  brought  into  operation in  accordancewith  Article  19 may be extended  to not  later than  1 July, 1924.
                  ARTICLE 14.  Les  dispositions  de  la presente  Conventionpeuvent  etre  suspendues  dans  tout  pays  parordre  du Gouvernement,  en  cas de  guerre ouen   cas   d&apos;evenements  presentant  un  dangerpour la  securite nationale.                  ARTICLE 15.  Les   ratification:   officielles  de  la  presenteConvention,   dans  les   conditions   prevues  ala  Partie   XIII  du  Traite  de Versailles  du28   juin  1919,  et  du   Traite   de  St.-Germaindu   10  septembre  1919, seront   communiqueesau  Secretaire General de  la Societe des Nationset par lui enregistrees.                  ARTICLE 16.  Tout Membre  de  1&apos;Organisation internationale du  Travail  qui  ratifie  la presente  Conventions&apos;engage a  1&apos;appliquer a  celles  de  ses  coloniesou possessions ou  a ceux de ses protectorats quine  se  gouvernent pas  pleinement eux-memes,sous les reserves  suivantes :  (a) Que  les  dispositions  de la  Convention nesoient  pas  rendues  inapplicables par  les  con-ditions locales;  (b) Que  les  modifications qui  seraient  neces-saires  pour  adapter   la  convention  aux  condi-tions  locales  puissent   etre   introduites  danscelle-ci.  Chaque  Membre  devra  notiner  au   bureau international du  Travail  sa  decision  en ce quiconcerne chacune de  ses colonies ou  possessionsou  chacun de  ses protectorats  ne se gouvernantpas  pleinement  eux-memes.                  ARTICLE 17.  Aussitot  que les  ratifications  de deux Mem-bres  de  1&apos;Organisation  Internationale  du  Tra-vail  auront   ete  enregistrees   au   Secretariat,le Secretaire  General  de la Societe des Nationsnotifiera ce  fait  a tous les Membres  de 1&apos;Orga-nisation Internationale du  Travail.                  ARTICLE 18.  La  presente Convention entrera en vigueur ala date  ou  cette notification  aura  ete  effectueepar  le  Secretaire General de  la  Societe  desNations;   elle  ne liera  que   les  Membres  quiauront fait  enregistrer  leur  ratification au Se-cretariat.    Par  la suite,  la presente  Conventionentrera  en  vigueur  au  regard  de  tout autre memre  a.   la  date  ou  la ratification  de  ceMembre aura ete enregistree au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 19.  Tout Membre  qui  ratifie la presente  Conven-tion  s&apos;engage  a  appliquer ses  dispositions auplus tard le ler juillet 1921,  et a prendre  tellesmesures   qui  seront   necessaires  pour  rendreeffectives ces dispositions.                  ARTICLE 14.  The  operation  of  the  provisions   of   thisConvention  may be  suspended  in any country by  the  Government  in   the  event  of war orother   emergency   endangering   the   nationalsafety.                  ARTICLE 15.  The  formal  ratifications  of  this  Convention,under  the  conditions  set  forth in Part XIII ofthe Treaty  of  Versailles  of 28 June,  1919,  andof the Treaty  of St.  Germain of  10. September,1919,  shall  be  communicated to  the  secretary general  of  the League  of Nations  for  registra-tion.                  ARTICLE 16.  Each Member of the International Labour Organ-ization  which ratifies this Convention engages toapply it to its colonies, protectorates and possessionswhich are not fully self-governing :         t  (a)  Except  where  owing  to  the  local condi-tions its provisions are inapplicable ; or  (b)  Subject  to such modifications as  may benecessary to adapt its  provisions to  local  con-ditions.  Each  Member  shall  notify  to  the  Interna-tional  Labour  Office  the  action taken  in respectof each of  its  colonies,  protectorates,  and  pos-sessions which  are  not fully self-governing.               &apos;   ARTICLE 17.  As  soon  as  the ratifications of two MembersOf the International  Labour  Organization  havebeen  registered with  the  Secretariat,  the  Secre-tary General of  the  League of Nations shall sonotify  all   the  Members  of  the  InternationalLabour Organization.                  ARTICLE 18.&apos;  This  Convention shall  come into  force at thedate  on  which such notification is  issued bythe Secretary General of the League of Nations,and  it shall  then be binding only  upon those members  which have registered  their ratifica-tions  with   the  Secretariat.    Thereafter   thisConvention  will  come into force  for  any other member at  the  date on  which  its ratificationis registered with the Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 19.  Each  Member which  ratifies  this  Conventionagrees  to   bring  its  provisions  into  operationnot  later   than  1  July,  1921,  and  to   take such  action as may  be  necessary  to  make these provisions effective.
                  ARTICLE 20.  Tout&apos; Membre  ayant  ratine  la  presente Con-vention peut la  denoncer a  1&apos;expiration d&apos;une periode de dix annees  apres  la date de  la mise en  vigueur  initiale  de la Convention,  par  unacte  communique au  Secretaire   General   dela  Societe des  Nations  et  par  lui  enregistre.La  denonciation  ne  prendra  effet  qu&apos;une annee apres avoir ete enregistree  au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 21.  Le  Conseil  d&apos;Administration  du Bureau Inter-national du Travail devra, au moins une  fois pardix annees,  presenter a la  Conference Generateun  rapport sur 1&apos;application de  la  presente Con-vention et decidera  d&apos;inscrire a  1&apos;ordre du jour de  la, Conference la  question  de  la  revisionou de la modification  de la dite Convention.                  ARTICLE 22.  Les  textes  francais et  anglais de la presenteConvention feront foi 1&apos;un et 1&apos;autre.                  ARTICLE 20.  A Member  which has  ratified this Conventionmay  denounce  it  after  the  expiration  of tenyears from the  date  on  which the Conventionfirst  comes  into force,  by an  act  communi-cated to  the Secretary  General of the  Leagueof  Nations   for  registration.   Such  denunciation-tion shall  not take  effect until one  year afterthe date on  which it  is registered with the Sec-retariat.                  ARTICLE 21.  At  least once in  ten  years  the  governing body of the  International  Labour  Office shall present  to the  General Conference  a  report onthe working  of this  Convention, and  shall  con-sider  the desirability  of  placing on the  agenda of  the  Conference the  question of its  revisionor modification.                    &apos;                  ARTICLE 22.  The French and English  texts  of  this Con-vention shall both be  authentic.
PROJET  DE CONVENTION CONCERNANT  LE                 CHOMAGE.  La   Conference  Generale  de  1&apos;OrganisationInternationale  du  Travail de  la  Societe  desNations,      Convoquee  a  Washington  par  le  Gou-    vernement  des Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre  1919,           I      Apres  avoir  decide  d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions   &quot; relatives  aux   moyens  de    prevenir le  chomage  et  de remedier  a  ses    consequences,&quot;  question  formant  le  deu-    xieme  point de 1&apos;ordre du  jour de la Con-    ference tenue a Washington, et      Apres avoir decide que  ces  propositions    seraient redigees sous forme d&apos;un projet  de    convention internationale,adopte  le  Projet  de  Convention  ci-apres  aratifier par  les Membres  de  1&apos;Organisation  In-ternationale du  Travail,  conformement   aux dispositions  de  la  Partie  relative  au  Travaildu  Traite  de  Versailles  du  28  juin  1919,  et du  Traite  de  Saint-Germain  du  10 septembre1919:DRAFT CONVENTION CONCERNING         UNEMPLOYMENT.  The  General  Conference  of  the  InternationalLabour Organization of the League of Nations,      Having  been  convened  at  Washington    by  the  Government of the United  States    of America, on  the 29th day  of  October,    1919, and      Having  decided  upon  the  adoption  of    certain  proposals  with  regard  to  the    &quot; question   of   preventing  or   providing    against   unemployment,&quot;   which  is  the    second item  in the agenda for the Washing-    ton meeting of the Conference, and      Having  determined that these proposals    shall take the  form of a draft international    convention,adopts the following  Draft Convention for  rati-fication  by  the  Members  of  the  InternationalLabour  Organization,  in  accordance  with  theLabour  Part  of  the  Treaty of Versailles of  28June, 1919,  and of the  Treaty of St.  Germainof 10 September, 1919:                 ARTICLE 1.  Chaque Membre  ratifiant  la presente Con-vention communiquera au  Bureau  international du  Travail  a des  intervalles  aussi  courts quepossible  et  qui  ne devront pas depasser troismois, toute   information  disponible,  statistiqueou  autre, concernant  le  chomage,  y  compristous renseignements sur  les mesures prises  oua prendre en vue de lutter contre le chomage.Toutes les fois  que ce sera possible les  infor-mations  devront  etre  recueillies de  telle  faconque  communication  puisse en  etre  faite dansles  trois  mois suivant la  fin  de la periode alaquelle elles  se rapportent.      &apos;          ARTICLE 2.  Chaque Membre  ratifiant  la presente Con-vention devra etablir  un  systeme  de  bureauxpublics  de  placement  gratuities  place  sous  lecontrole d&apos;une autorite centrale.   Des  Comitesqui  devront  comprendre des repfesentants  despatrons  et   des  ouvriers  seront  nommes   et                 ARTICLE 1.  Each  Member which  ratifies  this  convention shall communicate  to the International LabourOffice, at intervals as short  as possible and  notexceeding  three  months,  all available  informa-tion, statistical or otherwise, concerning  unem-ployment,  including  reports  on measures  takenor  contemplated  to  combat   unemployment.Whenever  practicable, the information  shall bemade available  for  such  communication  not later than  three months  after  the end of  theperiod to which it relates.                 ARTICLE 2.  Each   Member  which   ratifies  this  Conven-tion  shall establish  a system  of  free  publicemployment  agencies  under   the   control  ofa  central authority.  Committees,  which  shall include  representatives  of  employers  and  ofworkers,  shall  be  appointed   to   advise  on
consulted pour tout  ce  qui  concerne  le  fonc-tionnement de ces bureaux.   Lorsque   coexistent   des  bureaux  gratuitspublics  et  prives,  des  mesures  devront etreprises pour  coordonner  les  operations  de  cesbureaux sur un plan national.   Le  fonctionnement   des   differents   systemesnationaux  sera  coordonne  par  le  Bureau  In-ternational  du Travail,  d&apos;accord  avec  les paysinteresses.                   ARTICLE  3.   Les Membres de 1&apos;Organisation internationale du Travail  qui  ratifieront  la  presente  Conven-tion  et  qui ont  etabli un  systeme  d&apos;assurancecontre  le ch&amp;mage,  devront,  dans  les  condi-tions  arretees d&apos;un  commun  accord entre  les membres interesses,  prendre  des  arrangementspermettant   a  des travailleurs  ressortissant  al&apos;un  de  ces  Membres   et  travaillant   sur  leterrltoire d&apos;un autre  de recevoir  des  indemnity-nites  d&apos;assurance  egales  a  celles  touchees parles  travailleurs   ressortissant  a  ce  deuxiemeMembre.                   ARTICLE  4.   Les ratifications omcielles de la presente Con-vention,  dans  les  conditions prevues  a la  PartieXIII du Traite  de Versailles du 28 juin  1919,et  du Traite  de  St.-Germain du 10  septembre1919,  seront  communiquees au   Secretaire Ge-neral de la Societe des Nations et par lui enre-gistrees.                   ARTICLE  5.   Tout Membre de 1&apos;Organisation internationale du Travail  qui  ratine la  presente  Conventions&apos;engage  a 1&apos;appliquer  a celles de ses colonies oupossessions  ou a ceux de  ses protectorats qui nese gouvernent pas pleinement eux-memes, sous lesreserves  suivantes:   (a) Que  les  dispositions de la  Convention nesoient pas  rendues inapplicables  par  les  condi-tions locales;   (&amp;) Que  les  modifications  qui  seraient  neces-saires  pour  adapter  la  Convention  aux  condi-tions  locales  puissent  etre  introduites  danscelle-ci.   Chaque  Membre devra  notifier  au  bureau international du  Travail  sa decision en ce quiconcerne chacune  de ses  colonies  ou possessionsou chacun de  ses protectorats ne se gouvernantpas pleinement eux-memes.                  ARTICLE 6.  Aussitot  que les ratifications  de  trois  Mem-bres  de  1&apos;Organisation Internationale  du Tra-vail auront  ete  enregistrees  au  Secretariat,  leSecretaire  General de  la Societe des  Nationsnotifiera  ce  fait a. tous les Membres de 1&apos;Organi-sation Internationale du Travail.matters  concerning  the carrying  on  of theseagencies.  Where  both public and  private  free  employ-ment  agencies  exist, steps  shall  be taken  tocoordinate the  operations  of such  agencies  ona national scale.&apos;  The operations  of  the various  national sys-tems shall be coordinated  by  the  InternationalLabour Office  in  agreement  with the  countries concerned.                   ARTICLE 3.  The  Members  of  the  International   LabourOrganization  which ratify  this  Convention andwhich  have  established systems  of insurance against unemployment  shall, upon  terms being agreed between  the  Members  concerned, make arrangements   whereby   workers  belonging  toone  Member  and  working  in  the  territory  of another  shall  be  admitted  to  the  same ratesof  benefit  of such  insurance  as  those  whichobtain for the workers belonging to  the latter.                   ARTICLE 4.  The  formal  ratifications  of this Convention,under the conditions  set forth in  Part  XIII  ofthe Treaty of  Versailles of 28 June,  1919,  andof the  Treaty  of  St.  Germain of  10 September,1919,  shall be  communicated to  the secretary general  of the League of Nations  for  registra-tion.                   ARTICLE 5.  Each  Member   of  the  International   LabourOrganization which ratifies  this Convention en-gages  to  apply it to  its colonies, protectorates and possessions which are not fully  self-governing :  (a)  Except where owing to the local conditionsits provisions are inapplicable ; or  (b)  Subject  to such modifications as  may benecessary  to adapt its provisions  to  local  con-ditions.  Each  Member  shall  notify to  the  Interna-tional Labour Office the action taken  in respectof each of its  colonies, protectorates and  pos-sessions which are not fully self-governing.                   ARTICLE 6.  As  soon as  the ratifications of three Membersof the International  Labour  Organization  havebeen  registered  with  the Secretariat,  the Secre-tary  General of the  League  of Nations  shall  sonotify  all  the Members  of the  InternationalLabour Organization.
                   ARTICLE  7.  La presente  Convention  entrera  en  vigueura la date ou cette notification aura ete  effectueepar  le   Secretaire  General  de   la  Societe  desNations;  elle  ne  liera  que  les  Membres  quiauront   fait  enregistrer  leur   ratification  auSecretariat.    Par  la  suite,  cette  Conventionentrera   en  vigueur  au  regard  de  tout  autre memre  a  la  date  ou  la ratification  de ,ceMembre  aura ete enregistree au  Secretariat.                   ARTICLE  8.  Tout  Membre  qui ratine  la  presente Conven-tion s&apos;engage  a  appliquer  ses  dispositions auplus  tard  le  ler  juillet   1921   et  a   prendretelles mesures qui  seront necessaires pour rendreeffectives ces dispositions.                   ARTICLE  9. I  Tout  Membre  ayant  ratine  la presente  Con-vention  peut la  denoncer  a  1&apos;expiration  d&apos;une periode  de  dix annees apres la  date de  la  mise en  vigueur  initiale  de  la  Convention,  par unacte communique  au  Secretaire General de  laSociete  des Nations  et  par lui  enregistre.    Ladenonciation  ne   prendra   effet   qu&apos;une  annee apres avoir  ete enregistree au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 10.  Le  Conseil   d&apos;Administration   du   bureau international  du  Travail devra,   au moins unefois  par dix annees,  presenter  a  la ConferenceGenerale  un   rapport sur  1&apos;application  de  lapresente Convention  et  decidera  s&apos;il  y  a lieudlnscrire a 1&apos;ordre  du  jour de la Conferencela question de la revision ou de  la modificationde la dite Convention.  -                  ARTICLE 11.  Les  textes  francais et  anglais  de la presenteConvention feront foi 1&apos;un et 1&apos;autre.                   ARTICLE  7.  This  Convention shall come into force  at  thedate  on  which  such  notification  is  issued  bythe Secretary General of the  League of Nations,but  it  shall then  be  binding only  upon  those members  which  have  registered  their ratifica-tions   with  the   Secretariat.    Thereafter  thisConvention will  come into  force for  any  other member at  the  date  on which  its  ratificationis registered  with the Secretariat.                   ARTICLE  8.  Each Member which ratifies  this Conventionagrees  to bring  its  provisions into  operationnot  later  than 1  July,  1921,  and   to  take such action as may be necessary to make these provisions effective.                   ARTICLE  9.  A  Member which has ratified  this Conventionmay  denounce  it  after the  expiration of  tenyears from the  date  on  which  the Conventionfirst  comes into force,  by an act communicated tothe Secretary General  of the  League  of nations for   registration.  Such denunciation   shall  not take  effect  until  one  year after  the  date  onwhich it is registered with the Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 10.  At  least  once  in  ten years the  governing body of  the International  Labour Office shall present to  the  General Conference a  report onthe working of this  Convention, and shall con-sider  the  desirability  of placing on the agenda of the  Conference the question of  its revisionor modification.                  ARTICLE 11.  The French and English  texts  of this Con-vention shall both be authentic.
SOCIETE DES NATIONS                                                     LEAGUE OF NATIONS              CONFERENCE INTERNATIONALE DU  TRAVAIL                  INTERNATIONAL  LABOUR  CONFERENCERECOMMANDATION  CONCERNANT  LE              CHOMAGE.  La   Conference  Generale   de  1&apos;OrganisationInternationale  du  Travail  de  la Societe  desNations,      Convoquee  a  Washington  par  le  Gou-    vernement  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre  1919,      Apres  avoir  decide  d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions   &quot;relatives   aux  moyens  de    prevenir le chomage et  de remedier a  ses    consequences,&quot;  question  formant  le  deu-    xieme point  de  1&apos;ordre du jour de la Confe-    rence tenue a Washington, et      Apres avoir  decide de  rediger  ces propo-    sitions sous forme  de recommandation,RECOMMENDATION  CONCERNING        UNEMPLOYMENT.  The  General Conference of the InternationalLabour Organization of the League of Nations,      Having  been  convened  at   Washington    by the Government of the United States of    America on the 29th day of October, 1919,    and      Having decided upon the  adoption of  cer-    tain  proposals with  regard  to  the  &quot; ques-    tion  of  preventing  or  providing  against    unemployment,&quot;  which is the  second item    in the agenda for  the  Washington meeting    of the Conference, and      Having  determined that  these proposals    shall take the  form  of a recommendation,adopte  la  Recommandation  ci-apres qui  serasoumise a 1&apos;examen des Membres  de 1&apos;Organisa-tion  Internationale  du  Travail en  vue  de  luifaire porter effet sous forme de loi nationale ouautrement,  conformement  aux dispositions  dela Partie relative au Travail  du  Traite de Ver-sailles  du 28 juin  1919, et du Traite de Saint-Germain du 10 septembre 1919 :adopts the  following  Recommendation,  to  besubmitted to the  Members  of  the  InternationalLabour  Organization  for  consideration  with  aview  to  effect  being  given to it by  nationallegislation or otherwise,  in  accordance with theLabour Part of the  Treaty of Versailles of 28June, 1919,  and of the  Treaty of St.  Germainof 10 September,  1919:I.I.  La   Conference  Generale  recommande  quechaque   Membre   de  1&apos;Organisation   Interna-tionale  du  Travail  prenne  des  mesures  pourinterdire  la  creation  de  bureaux de placementpayants   ou  d&apos;entreprises   commerciales   deplacement.  En  ce qui concerne les bureaux deja  existantsla Conference recommande  que leur fonctionne-ment  soit   subordonne  a  1&apos;octroi  de  licencesdelivrees  par le  Gouvernement  et  que  toutesmesures  soient  prises ann de   les  supprimerdes que possible.  The  General  Conference   recommends  that each  Member  of  the  International  LabourOrganization  take  measures   to  prohibit  theestablishment  of  employment  agencies  whichcharge fees or which carry on  their  business forprofit.  Where such  agencies  already  exist,  itis  further recommended that  they be  permitted to  operate  only  under Government  licenses,and  that  all practicable  measures  be taken to abolish such agencies as soon as possible.                     II.  La   Conference  Generale   recommande  auxMembres  de  1&apos;Organisation   Internationale  duTravail  que le recrutement  collectif  de  travail-leurs dans un  pays, en vue de leur emploi dans un autre,  ne puisse avoir lieu qu&apos;apres  ententeentre  les  pays interesses  et  apres  consultationdes patrons et des ouvriers  appartenant, danschaque pays, aux industries interessees.                     II.  The  General  Conference  recommends  to theMembers of the International Labour  Organiza-tion  that the recruiting  of bodies of workers inone  country with a  view to their employmentin another country. should  be  permitted only by  mutual  agreement  between  the  countries concerned  and  after  consultation  with  em-ployers  and workers  in each  country  in theindustries  concerned.(15)
                     III.  La   Conference   Generale   recommande  quechaque   Membre   de   l&apos;Organisation   Interna-tionale du Travail  organise  un systeme  effectifd&apos;assurance  contre  le  ch6mage, soit  au  moyend&apos;une  institution   du   Gouvernement,  soit &apos;  enaccordant  des  subventions   du  Gouvernementaux  associations  dont  les statuts  prevoient  enfaveur  de  leurs  membres  le paiement d&apos;in-demnites  de chomage.                      IV.  La  Conference  Generale   recommande  quechaque   Membre  de 1&apos;Organisation   Interna-tionale  du  Travail coordonne 1&apos;execution  des travaux  entrepris pour  le compte de  1&apos;autoritepublique,  et  reserve  autant  que possible   cestravaux  pour les periodes de chomage et pour les   regions  particulierement  affectees  par  cephenomene.                     III.  The   General   Conference   recommends   that each Member of  the  International Labour  Or-ganization  establish  an effective  system of  un-employment  insurance,  either  through  a  Gov-ernment  system  or  through   a  system   ofGovernment  subventions  to  associations whoserules  provide for the  payment  of  benefits  totheir unemployed members,                     IV.  The   General   Conference   recommends   that each Member of the  International  Labour  Or-ganization    coordinate  the   execution  of   allwork    undertaken  under   public    authority,with a view to  reserving  such work  as far aspracticable  for  periods  of  unemployment  andfor districts most affected by  it.
RECOMMANDATION     CONCERNANT     LA   RECIPROCITY  DE   TRAITEMENT   DES   TRAVAILLEURS ETRANGERS.RECOMMENDATION    CONCERNING    RECI-   PROCITY  OF  TREATMENT  OF  FOREIGN   WORKERS.  La Conference  Generale de  1&apos;Organisation  In-ternationale  du  Travail  de  la   Societe   desNations,      Convoquee a  Washington  par  le  Gou-    vernement des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre  1919,      Apres  avoir  decide   d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions  &quot; relatives   aux   moyens  de    prevenir le  chomage et  de  remedier  a  ses    consequences,&quot;   question   formant  le deu-    xieme point  de  1&apos;ordre  du  jour  de  la  ses-    sion  de la  Conference  tenue  a Washing-    tion, et      Apres avoir  decide  de rediger ces  pro-    positions sous forme de  recommandation,  The  General Conference  of the InternationalLabour Organization of the League of Nations,      Having  been  convened  at  Washington    by the  Government of  the United States    of America  on the 29th  day  of October,    1919, and      Having  decided  upon  the  adoption  of    certain proposals with  regard to the &quot; ques-    tion of preventing  or providing  against  un-    employment,&quot;  which is the secofid item in    the agenda for the Washington meeting of    the Conference, and      Having  determined  that  these  proposals    shall take the form of  a recommendation,adopte la  Recommandation  ci-apres qui  serasoumise  a.  1&apos;examen des  Membres  de  1&apos;Organi-sation Internationale du Travail  en vue  de luifaire porter effet sous forme de loi  nationale ouautrement,  conformement  aux  dispositions dela  Partie  relative au Travail   du Traite de versailles  du 28  juin  1919,  et  du Traite deSaint-Germain du  10 septembre 1919 :  La Conference   Generale   recommande  quechaque   Membre   de   1&apos;Organisation  Interna-tionale du Travail assure,  sur  la base  de  lareciprocity,  dans  les  conditions  arretees  d&apos;uncommun  accord entre  les pays  interesses,  auxtravailleurs etrangers  occupes  sur son  territoireet a leurs families, le  benefice des lois etregle-ments  de  protection   ouvriere,  ainsi  que  lajouissance du droit dissociation reconnu  dansles  limites  de la  legalite  a. ses propres travail-leurs.adopts  the following  Recommendation  to  besubmitted to the  Members  of the InternationalLabour Organization  for  consideration  with  aview  to effect  being given  to  it  by nationallegislation or otherwise, in  accordance with theLabour Part of the  Treaty of Versailles of  28June, 1919,  and of the Treaty  of  St. Germainof 10 September, 1919 :  The  General  Conference recommends  that each Member of  the International  Labour  Or-ganization  shall,  on  condition  of   reciprocityand  upon   terms  to  be agreed  between   thecountries concerned,  admit  the  foreign work-ers  (together  with  their  families)  employedwithin  its territory, to the benefit of its  laws and  regulations for  the protection  of its  ownworkers,  as well  as  to the  right  of  lawfulorganization as enjoyed by its  own workers.
PROJET   DE   CONVENTION  CONCERNANT  DRAFT   CONVENTION   CONCERNING   THE   L&apos;EMPLOI  DES   FEMMES   AVANT   ET     EMPLOYMENT   OF   WOMEN   BEFORE   APRES L&apos;ACCOUCHEMENT.                     AND  AFTER  CHILDBIRTH.   La  Conference  Generale   de  reorganisation Internationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  des Nations,       Convoquee  a  Washington  par  le  Gou-     vernement  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le     29 octobre 1919,       Apres   avoir  decide   d&apos;adopter  diverses     propositions   relatives  a  &quot; 1&apos;emploi  des     femmes:   avant  ou  apres  1&apos;accouchement     (y  compris la question  de  1&apos;indemnite de     maternite),&quot;   question  comprise  dans   le     troisieme  point  de 1&apos;ordre  du  jour  de  la     session de la  Conference  tenue  a Washing-     ton, et       Apres  avoir  decide  que  ces  propositions     seraient redigees  sous forme d&apos;un projet de     convention internationale, adopte  le Projet  de  Convention   ci-apres  a ratifier  par les Membres  de  1&apos;Organisation In- ternationale  du   Travail,   conformement   aux dispositions de la  Partie relative au  Travail du Traite de Versailles  du  28  juin  1919 et  du Traite  de  Saint-Germain  du   10  septembre 1919:                  ARTICLE 1.  Pour 1&apos;application  de  la   presente  Conven- tion,  seront  considered  comme  &quot;  etablissements industriels &quot; notamment:  (a) Les   mines,  carrieres   et  industries  ex- tractives de toute nature :  (b) Les  industries  dans  lesquelles  des  pro-duits  sont  manufactures,  modifies,  nettoyes, repares,  decores,  acheves,   prepares  pour   la vente,  ou dans  lesquelles les  matieres  subis-sent une transformation ; y compris  la construc-tion des  navires,  les industries  de  demolitionde  materiel,  ainsi  que  la production, la  trans-formation et  la transmission de la force motriceen general et de 1&apos;electricite;  (c) La  construction,  la  reconstruction,  l&apos;en- tretien, la  reparation,  la modification ou  lademolition  de  tous   batiments   et  edifices,chemins de  fer, tramways, ports,  docks, jetees,canaux,  installations   pour  la  navigation  in- terieure,  routes, tunnels, ponts,  viaducs, egouts collecteurs,  egouts  ordinaires,  puits,  installa-  The General Conference of the InternationalLabour Organization of the League of  Nations,      Having  been convened  at  Washington    by  the Government  of  the United  States    of America on  the 29th day  of  October,    1919, and      Having  decided  upon  the adoption  of    certain proposals with regard to  &quot; women&apos;s    employment,  before  and after   childbirth,    including  the  question  of maternity bene-    fit,&quot;  which is part  of the third item in the    agenda for the Washington  meeting of the    Conference, and      Having determined that  these  proposals    shall take the form of a draft international    convention,adopts  the  following   Draft  Convention  for ratification  by the Members  of the InternationalLabour  Organization, in  accordance  with  theLabour  Part, of the Treaty  of Versailles  of  28June, 1919, and of  the Treaty  of St.  Germainof 10 September,  1919:                 ARTICLE 1.  For the purpose of this Convention, the term&quot; industrial undertaking &quot; includes particularly:  (a) Mines, quarries, and other  works for the extraction of  minerals from the earth.  (b) Industries  in   which  articles  are manu-factured,    altered,   cleaned,  repaired,   orna-mented,  finished,  adapted for&apos; sale,  broken up on demolished,  or in which  materials  are  trans-formed ;  including shipbuilding and the genera-tion, transformation, and  transmission  of  elec-tricity or motive power  of any kind.  (c) Construction,    reconstruction,    maintc-nance,  repair, alteration,  or  demolition of any building, railway, tramway,  harbor,  dock,  pier,canal,  inland waterway,  road,  tunnel, bridge,viaduct, sewer, drain,  well,  telegraphic or  tele-phonic  installation,   electrical  undertaking,  gaswork, water  work, or  other  work  of  construe-
 lions  telegraphiques  ou  telephoniques,  instal- lations  elcctriques,  usines  a  gaz,  distribution d&apos;eau  ou  autres  travaux de  construction,  ainsi que les travaux  de  preparation  et de  fonda- tion precedant les travaux ci-dessus ;   (d) Le  transport de  personnes  ou  de  mar- marchandises  par  route, voie ferree  ou voie d&apos;eau, maritime  ou interieure, y  compris  la manuten- tion  des   marchandises  dans  les  docks,  quais, wharfs  et  entrepots, a  l&apos;exception  du transport a la main.   Pour 1&apos;application cle la presente Convention, sera  considere  comme  &quot; etablissement  commer- cial&quot;  tout lieu consacre  a la vente  des  mar- marchandises ou a  toute operation commerciale.   Dans  chaque   pays,  1&apos;autorite   competente determinera  la   ligne  de  demarcation   entre 1 Industrie  et  le  commerce d&apos;une  part,  1&apos;agri- culture, d&apos;autre part.                   ARTICLE 2.   Pour 1&apos;application de la presente Convention, le  terme  &quot; femme&quot; designe  toute  personne du sexe  feminin, quel  que soit son  age ou  sa na- tionalite,  mariee ou non, et le terme &quot; enfant &quot; designe tout enfant, legitime ou non.                   ARTICLE 3.   Dans  tous les   etablissements  industriels ou commerciaux, publics ou  prives,  ou  dans  leurs dependances,  a  1&apos;exception  des  etablissements ou  sont   seuls  employes  les membres  d&apos;une merae famille, une femme   (a) ne sera  pas  autorisee  a. travailler  pen- dant  une  periode  de   six  semaines apres  ses couches;   (b)  aura  le droit de  quitter son  travail,  sur production  d&apos;un   certificat   medical  declarant que ses  couches  se  produiront  probablement dans un delai de six semaines ;   (c)  recevra,  pendant  toute la  periode  ou elle  demeurera absente,  en  vertu  des  para- graphes (a) et  (b),  une  indemnite  suffisante  pour son  entretien et  celui  de  son enfant  dans de bonnes  conditions  d&apos;hygiene;  ladite  indemnite, dont  le montant  exact sera fixe par 1&apos;autorite competente  dans   chaque  pays,  sera  prelevee sur les  fonds  publics  ou sera fournie par unsysteme d&apos;assurance.   Elle aura droit, en outre, aux  soins  gcatuits  d&apos;un   medecin  ou  d&apos;une sage-femme.   Aucune  erreur,  de  la  part  du medecin ou  de la sage-femme,  dans  1&apos;estima-tion de la date  de  1&apos;accouchement,  ne pourraempecher   une   femme   de  recevoir 1&apos;indemnite a  laquelle  elle  a droit a compter de la date ducertificat   medical  jusqu&apos;a   celle   a  laquelle1&apos;aCcouchement se  produira ;   (d)  aura  droit dans tous les  cas, si elle  allaiteson enfant, a deux repos d&apos;une demi-heure pourlui permettre 1&apos;allaitement.tion, as well as the preparation for or laying  the foundation of  any such work or structure.   (d) Transport of passengers  or  goods by road,rail,  sea,   or inland  waterway,  including  the handling  of goods  at  docks,  quays,  wharves,and  warehouses,  but   excluding  transport  byhand.   For the purpose of this Convention,  the term&quot; commercial  undertaking&quot;  includes any place where articles  are sold  or  where  commerce iscarried on.   The  competent  authority  in  each  country shall define the line  of  division which  separatesindustry and  commerce  from  agriculture.                  ARTICLE 2.   For  the  purpose   of this   Convention,  the term  &quot; woman&quot;  signifies  any  female  person,irrespective   of   age  or  nationality,  whethermarried  or  unmarried,  and the  term  &quot; child&quot;signifies   any   child   whether  legitimate   orillegitimate.                  ARTICLE 3.   In any public  or  private industrial or com-mercial undertaking,  or in any branch thereof,other  than an  undertaking  in  which onlymembers  of the same  family  are  employed, a woman    (a) Shall  not  be  permitted  to  work  duringthe six weeks following her confinement.   (b) Shall  have the  right to  leave  her work if she  produces  a  medical  certificate  stating thather   confinement   will  probably  take   place within six weeks.   (c) Shall,  while  she is absent from  her workin  pursuance  of  paragraphs   (a)  and  (b),  bepaid benefits sufficient  for the full  and healthymaintenance of  herself and  her child,  providedeither  out of  public  funds  or by  means of asystem  of  insurance,   the  exact   amount   ofwhich  shall be  determined  by  the  competent authority  in each  country, and as an additionalbenefit shall be entitled to  free  attendance  bya  doctor or certified midwife.     No mistake ofthe  medical adviser  in  estimating  the date ofconfinement  shall  preclude   a  woman  fromreceiving  these  benefits  from   the  date  of  themedical certificate up   to  the date on  whichthe confinement  actually takes  place.   (d) Shall  in any case, if  she  is  nursing  herchild, be allowed half an hour twice  a day duringher working hours for this purpose.
                   ARTICLE 4.   Au cas ou une femmc  s&apos;absente de son travail,en vertu des  paragraphes  (a)  et  (b)  de 1&apos;arti-cle 3 de la present Convention, ou  en demeureeloignee pendant  une  periode  plus  longuc,   ala  suite  d&apos;une  nialadie  attestee  par  certificatmedical comme resultant de sa  grosscsse ou deses couches, et qui la met dans 1&apos;incapacite dereprendre  son travail,  il  sera  illegal  pour sonpatron,  jusqu&apos;a ce que  son absence  ait atteintune duree  maximum  fixee par l&apos;autorite  com-competente  de  chaque  pays,  dc  lui  signifier sonconge   durant  ladite  absence,  ou  a  une  datetelle  que le delai  de  preavis  expirerait pendantque dure 1&apos;absence sus-mentionnee.                   ARTICLE 5.   Les   ratifications  ofncielles   de  la  presenteConvention,  dans  les  conditions  prevues  a  laPartie  XIII   du  Traite  de   Versailles  du  28juin  1919,  et du  Traite de St.-Germain du 10septembre   1919,   seront   communiquees   au secretaire  General de  la  Societe  des  Nationset  par  lui  enregistrees.                   ARTICLE 6.   Tout Membre  de l&apos;Organisation  internationale du Travail  qui  ratifie  la  presente  Conventions&apos;engage a 1&apos;appliquer a  celles de ses colonies oupossessions ou a ceux de ses protectorats qui nese  gouvernent pas pleinement  eux-memes, sousles reserves suivantes:   (a) Que   les  dispositions  de  la  convention ne soient pas  rendues  inapplicables par les con-ditions  locales  ;   (b) Que  les  modifications qui seraient neces-saires  pour  adapter la  Convention  aux condi-tions  locales  puissent  etre   introduites  danscelle-ci.   Chaque  Membre devra  notifier  au  bureau international  du Travail sa decision  en ce qui-concerne  chacune  de  ses  colonies  ou  posses-sions  ou  chacun  de   ses protectorats ne  segouvernant  pas pleinement eux-memes.                   ARTICLE 7.   Aussitot   que   les    ratifications  de  deux membres  de   1&apos;Organisation   Internationale  duTravail  auront ete enregistrees. au  Secretariat,le Secretaire General  de la Societe des  Nationsnotifiera ce fait a  tous les Membres de  1&apos;Organi--sation Internationale du Travail.                   ARTICLE 8.   La presente Convention entrera  en vigueur  a.1a  date ou cette  notification  aura  ete  effectueepar le  Secretaire  General de  la Societe desNations; elle  ne  liera  que  les  Membres quiauront   fait   enregistrer  leur  ratification  auSecretariat.     Par  la  suite, la presente Conven-tion entrera en vigueur  au regard  de tout  autre memre  a   la date  ou la  ratification de  ceMembre aura ete enregistree au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 4.  Where a  woman  is absent  from her work inaccordance with  paragraphs (a) or  (&amp;)  of  Article3  of  this  Convention, or  remains absent  from her work for a longer  period as a result of illnessmedically certified  to  arise out of  pregnancy orconfinement  and  rendering her unfit  for work,it  shall not  be  lawful,  until her  absence  shallhave  exceeded a maximum  period to be  fixed by  the competent  authority in  each country,for her employer to give her  notice of dismissalduring such  absence,  nor to give  her  notice ofdismissal at  such a time that the notice wouldexpire during such absence.                  ARTICLE 5.  -  The formal  ratifications  of  this Convention,under  the  conditions  set forth in Part XIII ofthe Treaty  of Versailles-1 of 28 June,  1919,  andof  the Treaty  of St.  Germain of  10 September,1919,   shall  be communicated to  the  secretary general of the League  of  Nations for registra-tion.                  ARTICLE 6.  Each  Member of  the  International LabourOrganization which ratifies this Convention engagesto   apply  it  to  its colonies,  protectorates,  andpossessions which  are not  fully  self-governing:  (a)  Except  where,  owing  to  the  local  con-ditions, its  provisions are  inapplicable;  or  (b)  Subject to  such modifications as may  benecessary  to adapt its provisions  to  local  con-ditions.  Each Member shall  notify  to  the Interna-tional  Labour  Office the action taken in respectof  each of its colonies, protectorates, and pos-sessions which  are not fully self-governing.                  ARTICLE 7.  As  soon as  the  ratifications of two Membersof   the International  Labour  Organization  havebeen  registered with  the Secretariat,  the Secre-tary General of  the League  of Nations shall sonotify all  the  Members   of  the  InternationalLabour Organization.                  ARTICLE 8.  This Convention shall come into force  at thedate  on which  such  notification  is  issued  bythe Secretary General of the League of Nations,but it shall then  be binding only upon those members  which  have registered  their  ratifica-tions   with  the  Secretariat.    Thereafter  thisConvention  will  come into force  for  any other member  at  the  date on   which  its  ratificationis registered with the Secretariat.
                  ARTICLE 9.  Tout  Membre  qui  ratifie  la  presente  Con-vention  s&apos;engage  a appliquer  ses  dispositionsau  plus tard le  ler juillet  1922,  et  a prendrctelles   mesures   qui   seront   necessaires   pourrendre effectives ces  dispositions.                  ARTICLE 10.  Tout Membre ayant ratine  la  presente Con-vention  peut la  denoncer a  1&apos;expiration  d&apos;une periode de dix  annees  apres  la date de la mise en  vigueur  initialc   de la Convention, par  unacte communique au  Secretaire  General  de  laSociete des Nations et par lui enregistre.    Ladenonciation  ne  prendra  effet  qu&apos;une  annee apres avoir ete enregistree au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 11.  Le  Conseil d&apos;Administration  du Bureau   In-ternational  du  Travail  devra, au  moins  unefois  par dix annees,  presenter a  la ConferenceGenerale  un rapport  sur  1&apos;application  de   lapresente  Convention   et  decidera  d&apos;inscrirc  a1&apos;ordre  du jour  de  la Conference  la question dela revision ou de  la modification de la  dite Con-vention.                  ARTICLE 12.  Les  textes francais  et anglais de  la presenteConvention feront  foi 1&apos;un et 1&apos;autre.                   ARTICLE 9.  Each  Member which ratifies this  Conventionagrees  to bring  its  provisions  into  operationnot  later than  1  July, 1922, and  to take suchaction as may be  necessary  to make these pro-visions effective.                  ARTICLE 10.  A  Member which  has  ratified  this  Conven-tion  may denounce  it after the  expiration  often  years from  the date  on which the Conven-tion first comes into force, by an  act communi-cated to the Secretary General  of  the  Leagueof  Nations 1  for  registration.   Such   denunciation-tion shall not take  effect until  one  year afterthe  date on which  it is  registered  with  the secretariat.                  ARTICLE 11.  At least   once   in   10  years  the   governing body of  the International   Labour  Office shall present  to the  General Conference a report  onthe  working  of  this  Convention,  and shall con-sider the desirability of placing  on  the  agenda of the Conference the question of its revision  or modification.                  ARTICLE  12.   ..  The French  and  English  texts  of  this  Con-vention shall both be authentic.
PROJET  DE  CONVENTION  CONCERNANT  LE  TRAVAIL DE NUIT  DES  PEMMES.DRAFT   CONVENTION   CONCERNING   EM-   PLOYMENT  OF   WOMEN  DURING   THE   NIGHT.  La Conference  Generale  de  reorganisation In-ternationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  desNations,      Convoquee a Washington  par le  Gou-    vernement  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre 1919,      Apres  avoir  decide d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions  relatives   a  &quot;1&apos;emploi  des    femmes  pendant la nuit,&quot;  question  com-    prise  dans  le troisieme point de  1&apos;ordre du    jour de la  session de la Conference tenue  a    Washington,  et      Apres  avoir  decide  que ces propositions    seraient redigees sous forme d&apos;un projet de    convention  internationale,adopte  le  Projet   de   Convention  ci-apres  aratifier  par  les  Membres   de  reorganisationInternationale du  Travail,  conformement  aux dispositions de  la Partie relative  au  Travail duTraite  de  Versailles du 28  juin  1919,  et duTraite   de Saint-Germain   du  10   septembre1919:  The General Conference of the InternationalLabour Organization of the League of Nations,       Having  been  convened  at   Washington    by the Government  of  the United  States    of America,  on the  29th  clay  of October,    1919, and       Having  decided  upon  the adoption  of    certain  proposals with regard to &quot; women&apos;s    employment:  during the night,&quot; which is    part  of  the third item in the agenda  for the    Washington  meeting  of  the   Conference,    and       Having determined that  these  proposals    shall take the form of a draft international    convention,adopts  the  following  Draft  Convention  for ratification by the Members  of the InternationalLabour Organization,  in  accordance with  theLabour Part of  the Treaty  of  Versailles  of  28June,   1919,  and  of  the Treaty  of St.. Germainof 10  September,  1919 :                 ARTICLE 1.  Pour  1&apos;application  de la presente Convention,seront   considered comme  &quot; etablissements  iri-dustriels &quot; notamment:  (a) Les  mines,  carrieres et  industries  ex-tractives de toute nature ;  (b) Les  industries   dans lesquelles  des  pro-                                                 ,o               ARTICLE 1.                                                 For   the  purpose  of  this  Convention,  the                                               term   &quot; industrial undertaking&quot; includes  par-                                               ticularly :                                                 (a)  Mines,  quarries,  and other works for the                                               extraction of minerals  from the  earth;                                                 (b) Industries  in  which  articles  are manufac-duits   sont   manufactures,  modifies,  nettoyes,  tured,   altered,  cleaned,  repaired,  ornamented,repares,  decores,  acheves,   prepares  pour  la  finished, adapted for sale,  broken  up or demol-vente,  ou dans lesquelles les  matieres subissent  ished,  or  in which  materials are transformed;une transformation;   y compris la construction  including   shipbuilding,   and  the   generation,des navires,  les   industries  de  demolition  de  transformation,  and transmission  of electricitymateriel, ainsi  que  la  production, la transfer-  or motive  power of any kind ;mation  et  la  transmission de  la  force motriceen general et de relectricite ;  (c) La construction,  la  reconstruction,  Ten-    (c) Construction,    reconstruction,    mainte-tretien,  la reparation,  la modification,  ou  la  nance,   repair, alteration,  or&apos; demolition of anydemolition   de  tous   batiments   et  edifices,  building, railway,  tramway, harbor,  dock,  pier,chemins de fer,  tramways, ports,  docks, jetees,  canal,  inland  waterway,  road,  tunnel,  bridge,canaux,  installations  pour  la  navigation   in-  viaduct, sewer,  drain,  well, telegraphic or tele-terieure,  routes,  tunnels, ponts,  viaducs, egouts  phonic  installation,  electrical undertaking,  gascollecteurs,  egouts  ordinaires,   puits,  instal-  work,  waterwork, or  other  work of construe-
lations  telegraphiques  ou  telephoniques, instal-lations  electriques,  usines  a  gaz,  distributiond&apos;eau,   ou   autres   travaux   de  construction,ainsi  que  les  travaux  de  preparation ct  dcfondation precedant les travaux ci-dessus.  Dans  chaque  pays   1&apos;autorite  competentedeterminera   la   ligne  de   demarcation   entre1&apos;industrie,  d&apos;une  part,  le commerce  et  1&apos;agri-culture, d&apos;au.tre part.                  ARTICLE  2.  Pour 1&apos;application  cle la  presente Convention,le  terme   &quot; nuit&quot;  signifie   une  periode  d&apos;au moins   onze  heures  consecutives,  comprenant1&apos;intervalle  ecoule entre  dix  heures du soir etcinq heures  du matin.  Dans  les  pays  ou aucun  reglement  publicne  s&apos;applique  a  1&apos;emploi  des  femmes  pendant la  nuit  dans  les   etablissements  industriels,le  terme   &quot; nuit&quot;   pourra   provisoirement,  etpendant   une   periode    maximum  de   troisannees, designer,  a la discretion du  Gouverne-ment,   une  periode  de  dix  heures seulement,laquelle comprendra   1&apos;intervalle  ecoule   entredix heures du soir et cinq heures du matin.                  ARTICLE  3.  Les  femmes, sans distinction  d&apos;age,  ne  pour-ront etre employees pendant la nuit dans aucunetablissement   industriel,   public   ou    prive,ni  dans aucune dependance  d&apos;un  de  ces  etab-lissements,  a  1&apos;exception  des  etablissements ousont  seuls  employes  les  membres  d&apos;une   meme famille.                   ARTICLE 4.  L&apos;article 3  ne sera pas applique:   (a) En cas de force majeure,  lorsque  dans uneentreprise  se produit une interruption  d&apos;exploi-tation  impossible a  prevoir et  n&apos;ayant  pas uncaractere periodique ;   (b) Dans le cas ou le  travail s&apos;applique soit a des  matieres  premieres,  soit a  des matieres en  elaboration, qui  seraient  susceptibles  d&apos;alte-ration  tres  rapide,  lorsque  cela est  necessairepour  sauver  ces  matieres  d&apos;une  perte   inevitably- table.                   ARTICLE 5.  Dans 1&apos;Inde  et   au  Siam,   1&apos;application  de 1&apos;article 3  cle la  presente  Convention  pourra etre  suspendue  par  le  Gouvernement  sauf en ce   qui  concerne  les  manufactures   (factories) telles  qu&apos;elles sont  definies par  la loi  nationale. Notification  de  chacune  des  industries exemp- tees  sera  faite  au  Bureau   International  du Travail.                   ARTICLE 6.   Dans les  etablissements  industriels  soumis  a.1&apos;influence des saisons, et dans  tous les cas oudes  circonstances  exceptionnelles   1&apos;exigent,  lation, as well as the preparation for or laying the foundations of  any such work or structure.  The  competent  authority  in  each  country shall  define the line  of  division which  separatesindustry from commerce and agriculture.                  ARTICLE 2.  For the purpose of this  Convention,  the term&quot; night&quot; signifies  a  rjeriod  of at  least  elevenconsecutive  hours,  including  the   interval be-tween ten o&apos;clock in the evening and five o&apos;clockin the  morning.  In   those   countries  where   no  Governmentregulation as yet applies to  the employment  ofwomen  in  industrial  undertakings  during the&apos;night, the term &quot; night&quot; may  provisionally, andfor a maximum  period  of three  years,  be de-clared by the Government  to signify a period  of only  ten hours, including  the interval betweenten  o&apos;clock  in  the  evening  and five o&apos;clock  inthe morning.                   ARTICLE 3.  Women without distinction  of  age  shall notbe  employed during  the night in any  public  or private industrial undertaking,  or  in any branchthereof,  other  than  an undertaking  in  which only   members   of  the  same   family  are  em-ployed.                   ARTICLE 4.   Article 3 shall not  apply:   (a) In cases  of force majeure,   when  in any undertaking   there  occurs   an interruption  ofwork  which  it  was  impossible to  foresee, andwhich is not  of a recurring character.   (b) In  cases  where the  work has to do  withraw  materials  or  materials  in course  of  treat-ment  which  are  subject to  rapid  deterioration,when such night work  is  necessary  to preserve,the said materials from certain loss.                   ARTICLE 5.   In  India and Siam,  the application of  Article3  of  this Convention may  be  suspended by theGovernment  in respect  to  any industrial  under-taking,  except  factories as  defined  by the na-tional law.     Notice of every such suspensionshall  be  filed  with the  International  LabourOffice.                   ARTICLE 6.   In   industrial  undertakings  which are  influ-experienced by the seasons and  in all cases where ex-exceptional  circumstances  demand  it,  the  night
durec   de  la  periodc   de  unit  indiquee  a1&apos;article  3  pourra  etre   reduite  a  dix  heurespendant soixante jours par an.                  ARTICLE  7.  Dans les ,pays ou le climat rend le travail dejour  particulierement  penible,   la  periode  denuit peut  etre  plus courte que celle - fixee parles  articles ci-dessus, a la condition qu&apos;un reposcompensateur soit accorde pendant le jour.                  ARTICLE  8.  Les   ratifications   officielles   de  la  presenteConvention,  dans les  conditions  prevues  a laPartie  XIII  du Traite de Versailles  du 28 juin1919, et du Traite de Saint-Germain du 10 sep-tembre  1919,  seront  communiquees  au  Secre-taire General de  la Societe des  Nations et par lui  enregistrees.                  ARTICLE  9.  Tout  Membre de  1&apos;Organisation internationale du  Travail  qui  ratine  la  presente  Conventions&apos;engage a  1&apos;appliquer a  celles de  ses  coloniesou  possessions  ou  a  ceux  de  ses  protectoratsqui ne se gouvernent pas  pleinement  eux-memes,sous les reserves suivantes :  (a) Que  les dispositions de la Convention nesoient  pas  rendues inapplicables  par  les  con-ditions locales:  (b) Que  les  modifications  qui  seraient ne-cessaires pour adapter la Convention  aux  con-ditions  locales  puissent   etre  introduites danscelle-ci.  Chaque  Membre  devra  notifier  au   bureau international  du  Travail  sa  decision   en  ce qui  concerne chacune de ses colonies  ou  pos-sessions  ou  chacun de   ses protectorats  ne segouvernant pas pleinement eux-memes.                  ARTICLE  10.  Aussitot   que   les   ratifications   de   deux membres   de  1&apos;Organisation  Internationale  duTravail auront  ete enregistrees  au  Secretariat,le Secretaire  General  de  la Societe des Nationsnotifiera  ce  fait  a  tous  les   Membres  de1&apos;Organisation Internationale du Travail.                  ARTICLE  11.  La  presente  Convention  entrera  en vigueura la date ou  cette notification aura ete  effectueepar le Secretaire  General  de  la  Societe desNations ;  elle ne liera que les Membres qui aurontfait  enregistrer  leur  ratification  au  Secre-tariat.     Par  la suite,  la presente Conventionentrera  en  vigueur  au  regard de  tout  autre memre,  a  la  date  ou  la  ratification  de ceMembre aura ete enregistree au Secretariat.period may  be reduced to ten  hours on  sixtydays  of the year.                   ARTICLE 7.  In  countries  where  the  climate  renders  work by  day  particularly trying  to  the  health,  the night period may  be  shorter  than prescribed inthe above articles, provided  that  compensatoryrest is accorded during the day.                   ARTICLE 8.  The formal  ratifications  of this  Convention,under the conditions set forth in  Part  XIII  ofthe Treaty of Versailles of 28  June, 1919, and ofthe Treaty  of  St. Germain  of  10  September,1919,   shall be  communicated to  the secretary general  of the  League of  Nations for  regis-tration.                   ARTICLE 9.  Each Member of the International Labour  Orga^nization which ratifies this Convention engages  toapply it to its colonies, protectorates and possessionswhich are not fully self-governing :  (a)  Except  where owing  to  the local   con-ditions its provisions are inapplicable ; or  (b)  Subject to such  modifications  as  may  benecessary to  adapt its provisions  to local con-ditions.  Each  Member  shall  notify to  the  Interna-tional Labour Office the action taken in respectof each  of its  colonies, protectorates  and pos-sessions which are not fully self-governing.                  ARTICLE 10.  As  soon as  the  ratifications of two Membersof the International  Labour Organization  havebeen  registered with the  Secretariat,  the  Sec-retary General  of  the League of Nations shallso notify all  the  Members  of  the InternationalLabour Organization.                  ARTICLE 11.  This Convention shall  come  into  force at  thedate on  which such notification is issued by  theSecretary  General of  the  League  of  Nations,but  it shall  then  be  binding only  upon  those members  which  have  registered  their  ratifi-cations   with   the  Secretariat.  Thereafter  thisConvention will come  into  force  for  any  other member  at the date on  which its ratification isregistered with the Secretariat.           ,
                  ARTICLE  12.  Tout  Membre  qui ratine  la presente  Con-vention  s&apos;engage  a  appliquer  ses  dispositionsau  plus  tard  le  ler juillet 1922,  et  a prendretelles  mesures   qui  seront   necessaircs   pourrendre effectives ces dispositions.                  ARTICLE  13.       0  Tout  Membre  ayant  ratifie  la  presente Con-vention peut la  denoncer  a  Texpiration  d&apos;une periode de dix annees  apres  la date de la mise en  vigueur  initiale   de  la Convention, par  unacte  communique  au  Secretaire   General  dela  Societe des  Nations et  par  lui  enregistre.La  denonciation  ne  prendra  effet  qu&apos;une  annee apres avoir ete enregistree au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE  14.  Le Conseil d&apos;Administration  du Bureau  In-ternational  du  Travail  devra,  au  moins  unefois par dix  annees,  presenter  a  la  ConferenceGenerale un  rapport sur 1&apos;application de la pre-sente Convention  et  decidera  s&apos;il  y a lieu d&apos;in-scrire  a 1&apos;ordre  du  jour  de  la  Conference,  laquestion de  la revision  ou  de la modification dela dite Convention.                  ARTICLE  15.  Les textes francais et anglais de la presenteConvention feront foi l&apos;un et 1&apos;autre,                  ARTICLE 12.  Each  Member  which  ratifies  this  Conven-tion agrees to  bring  its  provisions into opera-tion not  later than 1  July, 1922, and to take such action as may be  necessary  to make  these provisions effective.                  ARTICLE 13.  A Member  which  has  ratified  this  Conven-tion may denounce  it  after  the  expiration  often years  from the date  on which  the Conven-tion first comes into force,  by an act communi-cated to the Secretary General of the League ofNations   for   registration.   Such  denunciationshall  not  take effect until one  year  after  thedate  on  which  it is  registered   with the  Sec-retariat.                  ARTICLE 14.  At  least once  in   ten  years,   the  governing body  of the  International Labour Office  shall present  to  the General Conference  a report onthe working of this  Convention,  and shall con-sider  the  desirability  of placing  on  the agenda of  the  Conference the  question   of its revisionor modification.                  ARTICLE  15.  The French and  English  texts  of  this  Con-vention shall both be authentic.
RECOMMANDATION  CONCERNANT  LA     PREVENTION DU CHARBON.  La   Conference  Generale   de   1&apos;OrganisationInternationale  du  Travail  de la  Societe  desNations,      Convoquee  a  Washington   par  le  Gou-    vernemcnt  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre 1919,      Apres  avoir  decide   d&apos;adopter   diverses    propositions  relatives  a &quot; 1&apos;emploi  des feni-    mes dans  les travaux insalubres,&quot; question    comprise  dans  le troisieme point de 1&apos;ordre    du  jour  de  la  session  de  la  Conference    tenue a Washington, et      Apres avoir  decide  que ces propositions    seraient   redigees  sous  forme de recom-    mandation,RECOMMENDATION  CONCERNING THE     PREVENTION OP ANTHRAX.  The  General Conference  of the InternationalLabour Organization-of  the  League of Nations,      Having  been  convened  at  Washington    by the  Government of  the  United  States    of  America on  the  29th day  of October,    1919, and      Having  decided  upon  the adoption  of    certain   proposals  with  regard  to   &quot; wo-    men&apos;s  employment:  unhealthy  processes,&quot;    which  is part of the  third  item in the    agenda   for  the Washington  meeting  of    the Conference;  and      Having determined that these proposals    shall  take  the form of a recommendation,adopte la  Recommandation  ci-apres,  qui  sera adopts  the  following  Recommendation,  to  besoumise a  1&apos;examen  des  Membres  de 1&apos;Organi- submitted to the Members  of  the  Internationalsation  Internationale  du Travail, en vue de lui Labour&apos;  Organization  for  consideration  with afaire porter effet sous forme  de  loi nationale ou view  to effect  being given to it  by  nationalautrement,  conformement  aux  dispositions de legislation or otherwise, in  accordance with thela  Partie   relative au Travail  du  Traite de Labour Part of  the  Treaty of Versailles  of  28Versailles  du 28  juin  1919,  et du  Traite de June,  1919,  and the Treaty of St.  Germain ofSaint-Germain du 10 septembre 1919 :            10 September, 1919 :  La   Conference  Generale   recommande   auxMembres  de  1&apos;Organisation   Internationale  duTravail   de  prendre  des  mesures  en   vued&apos;assurer,  soit  dans  le   pays  d&apos;origine,  soit,au  cas ou  cela ne serait  pas possible,  au portde  debarquement, la  disinfection  des  lainessuspectes de contenir  des spores charbonneuses.  The  General  Conference recommends to  theMembers  of the International Labour  Organi-zation  that  arrangements  should  be  made  forthe disinfection of wool  infected with anthraxspores, either  in  the  country  exporting suchwool or if  that is  not practicable at  the  port of entry in the country importing such wool.
RECOMMANDATION     CONCERNANT     LA   PROTECTION DES FEMMES  ET  DES  EN-   FANTS  CONTRE  LE  SATURNISME.  La  Conference   Generale  de  1&apos;OrganisationInternationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe desNations,RECOMMENDATION     CONCERNING     THE   PROTECTION OF  WOMEN AND CHILDREN   AGAINST LEAD POISONING.  The  General  Conference of the  InternationalLabour Organization  of the League of  Nations,     Convoquee a  Washington  par  le  Gou-    vernement  des  Etats-Unis d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre 1919,     Apres  avoir  decide  d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions  relatives  a  1&apos;  &quot; emploi  des    femmes  et  des  enfants  dans   les travaux    insalubres,&quot;  question  comprise  dans  les    troisieme et quatrieme  points de 1&apos;ordre du    jour de  la  session  de  la  Conference tenue    a Washington, et     Apres  avoir decide que  ces  propositions    seraient  redigees  sous  forme  de  recom-    mandation,adopte  la  Recommandation ci-apres,  qui  serasoumise a  1&apos;examen des Membres de 1&apos;Organisa-tion  Internationale du  Travail en  vue de  luifaire porter effet sous forme de loi nationale ouautrement,  conformement  aux dispositions  dela  Partie  relative  au  Travail  du  Traite  de versailles   du 28  juin  1919, et du Traite deSt--Germain du 10 septembre 1919 :  La  Conference Generale  recommande  auxMembres   de  l&apos;Organisation  Internationale  duTravail qu&apos;en raison des dangers que presententpour les femmes au  point de  vuede la mater-nite  certaines  operations industrielles  et dansle  but de  permettre  aux enfants de se develop-per physiquement, 1&apos;emploi  des  femmes et  desjeunes gens  au-dessous  de  dix-huit  ans soit in-terdit dans les travaux enumeres ci-apres :  (a) Dans le  travail  aux  fours  ou  s&apos;opere  lareduction des minerals de zinc et de plomb.  (b) Dans la manipulation,  le traitement  would  reduction  des cendres  contenant du plombet dans le desargentage du plomb.  (c) Dans la fusion en grand du plomb ou  duvieux zinc.  (d) Dans la  fabrication de la  soudure ou desalliages  contenant  plus de dix pour cent  deplomb.                                           (      Having  been  convened  at  Washington    by the Government of the United States of  &apos;  America on the 29th  day of October, 1919,    and      Having  decided  upon  the  adoption  of    certain proposals with regard to  &quot; women&apos;s    and   children&apos;s  employment:   unhealthy    processes,&quot; which is part of the  third and    fourth items in the agenda  for the Wash-    ington meeting of the Conference, and      Having  determined  that  these  proposals    shall take the  form  of  a recommendation,adopts the  following Recommendation,  to   besubmitted to the Members of the  InternationalLabour  Organization for  consideration with  aview  to  effect  being given  to it  by  nationallegislation or otherwise, in accordance with  theLabour Part of the Treaty of Versailles  of  28June, 1919, and of  the Treaty of St. Germain of10 September, 1919  :  The General  Conference recommends  to  theMembers of  the International Labour  Organiza-tion that in view of the danger involved to the function  of  maternity and to the  physical  de-velopment   of  children,   women,  and   youngpersons  under  the  age  of  eighteen  years  be excluded  from employment  in the  followingprocesses:  (a) In  furnace work  in the reduction  of zincor lead ores.  (b) In   the  manipulation,   treatment, .  or reduction of ashes containing lead, and in thedesilverizing of lead.  (c) In  melting lead  or  old zinc on a large scale.  (d) In  the  manufacture  of solder  or  alloyscontaining more than ten per cent, of lead.
   (e) Dans  la  fabrication  de  la litharge,  dumassicot, du minium,  de la ceruse, du  mine-orange, ou du sulfate, du chromate ou du silicatede plomb (frite).   (/) Dans  les  operations  de  melange  et  detartinage dans  la fabrication  ou  la  reparationd&apos;accumulateurs electriques.   (g) Dans  le nettoyage  des  ateliers ou sonteffectues les travaux enumeres ci-dessus.   La  Conference  recommande,   en  outre,  queTemploi  des  femmes  et  des  jeunes gens  au-dessous  de dix-huit  ans  aux  travaux  ou  Tonutilise des sels  de plomb ne soit  autorise qu&apos;ala   condition  que  Ton  prenne  les  mesuressuivantes:   (a) Ventilation   localised,   de   maniere  a.  ceque   soient  dissipees,  des  leur  formation,  lespoussieres et vapeurs.   (&amp;) Proprete des d&apos;outils et des ateliers.   (c) Avis  donne  a   1&apos;autorite   publique   detous  les  cas  de  saturnisme,   et  attributiond&apos;indemnites aux personnes intoxiquees.   (d) Examen  medical  periodique des  person-nes  employees aux travaux  enumeres  plus haut.   (e) Installation,  dans  des  conditions  satisfai-santes,  de vestiaires,  lavabos, et  refectoires, etfourniture de  vetements  protecteurs speciaux.   (/) Interdiction d&apos;introduire des aliments  oudes boissons dans les ateliers.   La  Conference  rccommande,   d&apos;autre   part,que,  dans les industries  ou il  est possible  deremplacer les  sels  solubles   de  plomb par  dessubstances non-toxiques,  1&apos;emploi  desdits  selssolubles  de plomb  soit 1&apos;objet  d&apos;une reglemen-tation plus severe.   En ce  qui concerne la presente Recommanda-tion, un  sel  de  plomb sera considere  commesoluble  s&apos;il contient plus  de cinq pour  cent  deson  poids en  plomb metallique soluble dans unesolution aqueuse d&apos;acide chlorhydrique a  0&apos;25%d&apos;acide.  (e)  In the  manufacture  of  litharge,  massicot,red lead, white  lead, orange  lead,  or  sulphate,chromatc or silicate (frit) of lead.  (/) In mixing and pasting in the manufactureor repair of electric accumulators.  (g)  In the  cleaning of  workrooms where theabove processes are carried on.  It  is further recommended  that  the  employ-ment  of women and young persons under theage  of  eighteen  years  in processes involving the use of  lead compounds be  permitted onlysubject to the following conditions :  (a)  Locally   applied  exhaust   ventilation,  soas to  remove  dust  and  fumes  at  the  point of origin.  (b)  Cleanliness of tools and workrooms.  (c)  Notification   to  Government  authorities of all cases  of lead  poisoning,  and  compensationtherefor.  (d)  Periodic  medical examination of  the per-sons employed in such processes.  (e)  Provision of sufficient and suitable  cloak-room,   washing,   and  mess-room   accommoda-tion, and of  special protective clothing.  (/)  Prohibition of bringing  food  or drink intowork  rooms.  It is further recommended  that  in industries where soluble  lead  compounds can be  replaced by non-toxic substances,  the use of soluble leadcompounds should be strictly regulated.  For the  purpose  of this Recommendation,  a lead compound should be  considered as solubleif  it  contains  more ,than  five  per cent,  of itsweight  (estimated  as metallic lead) soluble ina quarter of one  per cent, solution of hydro-chloric acid.
RECOMMANDATION   CREATION   D&apos;UN   D&apos;HYGIENE.CONCERNANT    LA  RECOMMENDATION     CONCERNING    THE SERVICE    PUBLIC     ESTABLISHMENT    OP    GOVERNMENT                         HEALTH  SERVICES.  La  Conference   Generale  de  reorganisation    The General  Conference of the  InternationalInternationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  des  Labour Organization  of  the  League of Nations,Nations,  Convoquee  a  Washington  par  le  Gou-vernement  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le29 octobre 1919,  Apres  avoir  decide  d&apos;adopter  diverscspropositions   relatives   a  &quot; 1&apos;emploi   desfemmes   dans  les   travaux   insalubres,&quot;question  comprise  dans le  troisieme pointde 1&apos;ordre du jour  de la session de la  Con-ference tenue a. Washington, et  Apres  avoir decide que ces  propositionsseraient redigees sous  forme  d&apos;une  recom-mandation,  Having  been  convened  at  Washingtonby  the  Government  of  the&apos; United Statesof x\merica  on the 29th  day  of October,1919, and  Having  decided  upon  the  adoption  ofcertain proposals with regard to  &quot; women&apos;semployment:  unhealthy  processes,&quot; whichis  part  of  the third  item in  the  agenda for  the  Washington meeting of the  Confer-ence, and  Having determined  that  these  proposalsshall take the form  of  a recommendation,adopte la Recommandation  ci-apres,  qui serasoumise  a. 1&apos;examen des  Membres  de  1&apos;Organi-sation Internationale du Travail,  en vue de luifaire porter effet sous  forme de loi  nationale ouautrement,  conformement  aux  dispositions dela Partie relative  au Travail du Traite de Ver-sailles du 28  juin 1919, et  du Traite  de  Saint-Germain du 10 septembre 1919 :  La  Conference  Generale   recommande  quechaque  Membre  de   1&apos;Organisation Internatio-nale du  Travail etablisse aussitot que possible s&apos;il ne l&apos;a deja fait non seulement un systemeassurant  une   inspection  efficace  des  usines  etateliers,   mais,  en  outre,  un service   publicspecialement  charge  de  sauvegarder  la  santedes ouvriers,  et qui se mettra en  rapport avec le Bureau International du Travail.adopts the  following  Recommendation,  to -besubmitted  to the  Members of the &quot;InternationalLabour  Organization  for  consideration  with  aview to effect being given  to it by  national legis-lation  or  otherwise,   in  accordance  with  theLabour Part of the  Treaty of Versailles of 28 June,1919,  and  the Treaty of St. Germain of 10 Sep-tember,  1919:  The  General  Conference  recommends  that each Member of  the  International Labour  Or-ganization which has not  already done so should establish as  soon as possible,  not  only a systemof efficient factory inspection, but also  in addi-tion thereto a  Government  service especiallycharged with the  duty  of  safeguarding  the health of  the workers, which will  keep in touchwith the International  Labour Office.(29)
PROJET  DE  CONVENTION  FIXANT  L&apos;AGE   DRAFT  CONVENTION  FIXING   THE  MINI-   MINIMUM    D&apos;ADMISSION DES  ENFANTS      MUM AGE FOR ADMISSION OF CHILDREN   AUX TRAVAUX INDUSTRIELS.                  TO INDUSTRIAL EMPLOYMENT.   La  Conference  Generale  de  1&apos;Organisation Internationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  des Nations,       Convoquee  a.  Washington  par  le  Gou-     vernement   des   Etats-Unis   d&apos;Amerique,     le 29 octobre 1919,       Apres  avoir   decide  d&apos;adopter  diverses     propositions   relatives   a  &quot; 1&apos;emploi   des     enfants :  age d&apos;admission au travail,&quot;  ques-     tion comprise  dans  le quatrieme point de     1&apos;ordre  du jour de la  session  de la  Confe-     rence tenue a Washington, et       Apres avoir decide  que  ces  propositions     seraient  redigees  sous  forme  d&apos;un  projet,     de convention Internationale,adopte  le   Projet   de  Convention  ci-apres  aratifier  par les Membres  de  1&apos;Organisation  In-ternationale  du   Travail,   conformement   aux dispositions de la Partie relative au  Travail duTraite de  Versailles  du 28 juin  1919, et  duTraite de Saint-Germain  du 10 septembre 1919 :                  ARTICLE  1.  Pour 1&apos;application de la  presente  Convention,seront  consideres   comme   &quot; etablissements  in-dustriels &quot; notamment:  (a) Les  mines,   carrieres  et   industries   ex-tractives de toute nature ;  (b) Les   industries  dans   lesquelles  des  pro-duits  sont  manufactures,  modifies,  nettoyes,repares,  decores,  acheves,  prepares  pour  lavente,  ou  dans  lesquelles  les  matieres  subis-sent  une  transformation;   y compris  la  con-struction des  navires, les  industries  de demo-addition  de materiel,  ainsi que la production, latransformation  et  la  transmission  de la  forcemotrice en general et de 1&apos;electricite ;  (c) La construction, la  reconstruction,  l&apos;en-tretien,  la  reparation,  la   modification  ou  lademolition  de  tous batiments  et  edifices,  che-mins  de fer,  tramways,   ports,  docks,  jetees,canaux,  installations  pour  la  navigation   in-terieure, routes, tunnels,  ponts,  viaducs,  egoutscollecteurs,   egouts  ordinaires,   puits, installa-   The General  Conference of  the  International Labour Organization  of  the  League of  Nations,       Having  been  convened  by  the  Govern-     ment of the  United States  of America at     Washington, on  the  29th  day  of  October,     1919, and       Having  decided  upon  the  adoption of     certain  proposals with regard to the &quot; em-     ployment  of  children:  minimum  age of     employment,&quot; which  is  part of  the  fourth     item  in the  agenda  for  the  Washington     meeting of the Conference, and       Having  determined  that these proposals     shall  take  the form  of a draft  international     convention, adopts  the  following   Draft   Convention   for ratification by  the Members of  the  International Labour Organization,  in  accordance with  the Labour Part of the Treaty of Versailles  of 28 June,  1919,  and  of  the  Treaty  of St.  Ger- main of 10 September, 1919 :                  ARTICLE 1.  For  the purpose of this Convention, the term &quot; industrial  undertaking &quot; includes  particularly :   (a) Mines,  quarries and  other  works for the extraction of minerals from the earth.   (b) Industries in  which  articles  are  manu- factured,   altered,  cleaned,   repaired,  orna- mented,  finished,  adapted for  sale,  broken  up or demolished,  or  in  which  materials are trans- formed ;   including shipbuilding,  and the gen- eration,  transformation,   and  transmission  of electricity and motive power of any kind.  (c) Construction,    reconstruction,   mainten- ance, repair, alteration,  or  demolition of  any building, railway,  tramway,  harbor, dock, pier, canal,  inland  waterway,  road,  tunnel,  bridge, viaduct,  sewer, drain, well,  telegraphic  or tele-phonic installation,  electrical undertaking,  gaswork,  water  work, or other work  of construe-(30)
 tions  telegraphiques  on   telephoniques,  instal- lations  electriques,  usines  a  gaz,  distribution d&apos;eau, ou autres travaux  de  construction, ainsi que  les  travaux  de  preparation  et  de  fonda- tion precedant les travaux ci-dessus;   (d) Le transport  de  personnes  ou   de  mar- chandiscs par route,  voie  ferree ou  voie d&apos;eau, y  compris   la  manutention  des  -merchandises dans les docks,  quais, wharfs  et  entrepots,  a 1&apos;exception du transport  a la main.   Dans   chaque   pays,  1&apos;autorite  competente determinera   la  ligne  de  demarcation  entre l&apos;industrie,  d&apos;une  part, le  commerce  et 1&apos;agri- culture,  d&apos;autre part.                   ARTICLE  2.   Les enfants  de  moins  de  quatorze  ans  ne peuvent  etre  employes ou  travailler   dans  les etablissements  industriels,  publics  ou prives, ou  dans leurs  dependances,   a 1&apos;exception  de ceux  dans  lesquels  sont  seuls  employes  les membres d&apos;une meme famine.-                   ARTICLE  3.   Les  dispositions de  1&apos;article  2  ne  s&apos;appli- queront  pas  au  travail  des  enfants   dans  les ecoles professionnelles,  a.  la  condition  que  ce travail  soit  approuve et surveille  par  1&apos;autorite publique.                   ARTICLE  4.   Dans  le   but  de  permettre  le  controle  de 1&apos;application. des  dispositions   de  la   presente Convention,  tout   chef d&apos;etablissement  indus- triel  devra  tenir  un  registre  d&apos;inscription  de toutes les personnes de moins  de seize ans em- ployees  par  lui avec  1&apos;indication de  la date  de leur naissance.                   ARTICLE 5.   En  ce qui concerne  1&apos;application  de  la pre- sente  Convention  au  Japon,  les  modifications ci-apres a 1 &quot;article 2 sont autorisees :   (a) Les enfants de plus  de douze ans  pourrontetre admis au  travail s&apos;ils ont acheve   leur ins-truction  primaire ; &apos;  (b) En ce  qui   concerne  les  enfants  entredouze et  quatorze  ans  deja  au  travail,  des dispositions transitoires pourront etre adoptees.   La  disposition   de  la  loi  japonaise actuelle qui admet les  enfants de  moins de douze ans acertains  travaux faciles  et  legers sera rapportee.                   ARTICLE 6.   Les dispositions  de  1&apos;article  2  ne  s&apos;appli-queront  pas  a l&apos;Inde,  mais  dans  1&apos;Inde  lesenfants  de  moins  de douze ans ne  seront pasoccupes:tion, as well as the preparation for or laying the foundations of any such work or structure.   (d) Transport of passengers or goods by roador   rail   or  inland   waterway,  including  the handling of goods at docks,  quays,  wharves, and warehouses, but excluding transport by hand.   The  competent  authority  in  each  country shall define the  line  of division  which  sepa-rates industry from  commerce  and  agriculture.                  ARTICLE 2.   Children under the age of fourteen years shallnot  be  employed  or  work  in  any  public  or private  industrial   undertaking,   or  in   anybranch  thereof,  other  than  an  undertaking inwhich  only  members   of   the  same  familyare employed.                  ARTICLE 3.   The provisions of Article 2 shall  not apply towork  done  by  children  in  technical  schools,provided  that  such  work  is  approved   andsupervised by public authority.                  ARTICLE 4.   In order  to  facilitate the  enforcement  of theprovisions  of this  Convention,  every  employer in an industrial undertaking shall  be requiredto keep a register of all persons under the age ofsixteen  years  employed  by him,  and of  the dates of their births.                  ARTICLE 5.  In  connection  with  the  application  of  thisConvention to  Japan,  the  following  modifica-tions of Article 2 may be made :  (a)  Children  over  twelve years of age may beadmitted  into  employment if they  have finishedthe course in the elementary school;  (b) As  regards  children between  the  ages of twelve  and fourteen  already employed,  transi-tional regulations may be made.  The  provision  in  the  present  Japanese  lawadmitting  children  under the   age of  twelve years  to  certain  light  and  easy  employmentsshall be repealed.                  ARTICLE 6.  The  provisions of  Article 2 shall  not  apply toIndia,  but in  India  children  under  twelve yearsof age shall not be employed,
  (a)  Dans   les   manufactures   employant  laforce  motrice  et occupant plus de dix  personnes;  (b)  Dans  les  mines,   carrieres et  industriesextractives de toute nature ;  (c)  Dans le transport par voie ferree de passagers,de marchandises, et de services postaux, et dans la manipulation des marchandises clans les docks,quais et wharfs,  a 1&apos;exception du transport a lamain.                  ARTICLE 7.   .  Les ratifications  officielles  cle la presente Con-vention,  dans les  conditions prevues a  la PartieXIII  du  Traite  de Versailles du 28 juin  1919,et du Traite de  Saint-Germain du 10  septembre1919, seront  communiquees  au  Secretaire  Ge-neral  de la  Societe  des Nations  et  par  luienregistrees.                  ARTICLE 8.  Tout  Membre  de 1&apos;Organisation internationale du  Travail  qui  ratifie  la presente Conventions&apos;engage a  1&apos;appliquer a  celles   de  ses coloniesou possessions ou a ceux  de ses protectorats quine  se  gouvernent  pas   pleinement  eux-memes,sous les reserves suivantes :  (a)  Que les  dispositions de la Convention nesoient pas rendues inapplicables par  les condi-tions locales,  (b)  Que les  modifications qui  seraient  neces-saires  pour  adapter la  Convention aux condi-tions   locales  puissent   etre  introduites  danscelle-ci.  Chaque  Membre devra  notifier  au  bureau international  du Travail  sa  decision  en ce quiconcerne chacune de ses  colonies ou possessionsou chacun de  ses protectorats ne se gouvernantpas pleinement eux-memes.                   ARTICLE 9.  Aussitot que les ratifications de deux membres de   1&apos;Organisation  Internationale   du   Travailauront  ete   enregistrees  au  Secretariat, le  Se-cretaire  General  de la Societe des Nations noti-fiera  ce fait a  tous les  Membres de 1&apos;Organisa-tion Internationale du Travail.                  ARTICLE 10.  La presente  Convention entrera en  vigueur a.la date  ou  cette notification aura ete  effectueepar  le  Secretaire  General de la  Societe des Na-tions;  elle  ne liera que  les Membres qui aurontfait  enregistrer leur  ratification au  Secretariat.Par  la suite, cette  Convention entrera  en vigueurau regard de tout  autre  Membre a la  date  ou laratification  de  ce  Membre  aura  ete  enregistreeau Secretariat.  (a)  In  manufactories  working  with   powerand employing more than ten persons ;  (b)  In mines,  quarries, and other  works  forthe extraction of minerals from the earth ;  (r)  In the  transport  of  passengers  or  goods,or mails, by  rail,  or in the  handling of goodsat  clocks,   quays,   and  wharves,  but   exclud-ing transport by hand.                  ARTICLE 7.  The formal  ratifications  of  this  Convention,under  the  conditions set forth in Part  XIII ofthe Treaty of  Versailles  of 28 June,  1919,  andof the Treaty  of  St. Germain of  10 September,1919,  shall be  communicated to  the secretary general  of the  League  of  Nations  for  regis-tration.                  ARTICLE 8.  Each  Member  of the  International  LabourOrganization which ratifies this Convention engagesto apply it to its  colonies, protectorates,  andpossessions  which are  not  fully  self-governing:  (a)  Except  where  owing  to  the  local  condi-tions its  provisions are inapplicable ;  or  (b)  Subject  to such  modifications as  ma)&apos; benecessary to adapt  its  provisions to  local  con-ditions.  Each  Member  shall  notify  to  the  Interna-tional  Labour  Office  the  action  taken in  re-spect to each  of  its colonies, protectorates,  andpossessions  which  are  not fully  self-governing.                  ARTICLE 9.  As  soon as  the  ratifications of two Membersof the  International Labour Organization  havebeen  registered with  the  Secretariat,  the  Sec-retary General  of  the League of Nations  shallso notify all  the  members  of  the InternationalLabour Organization.                  ARTICLE 10.  This  Convention shall  come  into force at thedate on which such notification is issued by theSecretary  General  of  the  League  of  Nations,but  it  shall  then  be binding  only upon  those members which have registered  their  ratifica-tions  with the Secretariat.  Thereafter this Con-vention will come into force  for any other Mem-ber at  the date on which its ratification is reg-istered with the Secretariat.
                  ARTICLE  11.  Tout  Membre  qui  ratifie  la  presente  Conven-tion s&apos;engage  a  appliquer  ses  dispositions  au                  ARTICLE  11.  Each Member which ratifies  this  Conventionagrees to  bring its provisions  into operation notplus tard le ler  juillet 1922 et a prendre  telles  later than  1   July,  1922,  and  to  take  such                                                 action as  may  be necessary to make these pro-                                                 visions effective.mesures  qui  seront  necessaires  pour  rendreeffectives ces dispositions.                  ARTICLE 12.  Tout  Membre ayant ratifie la presente  Con-vention  peut  la  denoncer  a 1&apos;expiration  d&apos;une periode  de  dix annees apres la date de la mise en vigueur  initiale de la Convention, par un actecommunique   au   Secretaire  General   de  laSociete des Nations et par  lui  enregistre.  Ladenonciation  ne  prendra  effet   qu&apos;une   annee apres avoir  ete enregistree  au Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 13.  Le  Conseil  d&apos;Administration  du  Bureau  In-ternational  du Travail devra, au moins  une foispar  dix annees,   presenter  a   la   ConferenceGenerale  un   rapport  sur  Implication  de  lapresente  Convention  et  decidera s&apos;il y a lieud&apos;inscrire a  1&apos;ordre  du jour de la Conference  laquestion de la revision ou de la  modification dela dite Convention.                  ARTICLE 12.  A Member  which has ratified this Conventionmay  denounce  it  after  the  expiration  of tenyears from the  date  on  which the Conventionfirst comes into  force, by  an act  communicatedto the Secretary General  of the League  of Na-tions for  registration. Such  denunciation  shallnot take effect until one year after the date onwhich it is registered with the Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 13.  At least once  in  ten  years, the  governing body  of   the  International  Labour Office shall present to  the  General Conference  a report onthe  working of this  Convention, and shall  con-sider the desirability  of  placing on  the  agenda of the  Conference the  question of its revisionor modification.                  ARTICLE 14.  Les  textes  francais et  anglais de  la  presenteConvention feront foi 1&apos;un et 1&apos;autre.                  ARTICLE 14.  The French and English  texts  of  this  Con-vention shall both be authentic.-3164)F
PROJET   DE    CONVENTION   CONCERNANT  DRAFT   CONVENTION   CONCERNING   THE   LE  TRAVAIL  DE  NUIT  DES  ENFANTS     NIGHT WORK  OF  YOUNG PERSONS EM-   DANS  L&apos;INDUSTRIE.                           PLOYED IN INDUSTRY.  La  Conference Generale de  l&apos;Organisation In-ternationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  desNations,      Convoquee  a.  Washington  par le  Gou-    vernement  des  Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,  le    29 octobre 1919.      Apres  avoir   decide  d&apos;adopter  diverses    propositions relatives a  &quot; 1&apos;emploi  des en-    fants:   pendant  la nuit,&quot;   question  com-    prise  dans le quatrieme  point  de  1&apos;ordre    du jour de la session de la Conference tenue    a Washington, et      Apres  avoir decide  que ces propositions    scraient  redigees  sous  forme  d&apos;un  projet    de convention internationale,adopte  le   Projet   de  Convention   ci-apres  aratifier  par  les  Membres   de   1&apos;OrganisationInternationale  du Travail,  conformement  aux dispositions de  la   Partie   relative  au  Travaildu  Traite  de Versailles du  28 juin 1919, et duTraite de  Saint-Germain du 10  septembre  1919.                 ARTICLE 1.  Pour  1&apos;application  de la presente  Convention,seront  considered  comme   &quot;  etablissements  in-dustriels &quot;  notamment:  (a)  Les   mines,  carrieres   et  industries  ex-tractives de toute nature.  (b)  Les   industries  dans  lesquelles  des  pro-duits   sont  manufactures,  modifies,  nettoyes,repares,  decores,  acheves,  prepares  pour  lavente, ou  dans  lesquelles les  matieres subissentune transformation;  y  compris  la constructiondes  navires,  les  industries  de   demolition  demateriel,  ainsi que  la production,  la  transformation-mation  et  la transmission  de la force  motriceen general  et de l&apos;electricite.  (c)  La  construction,  la  reconstruction,  l&apos;en-tretien,  la reparation,  la  modification,  ou  lademolition   de   tous  batiments  et   edifices,chemins de  fer, tramways, ports, docks, jetees,canaux,  installations  pour la  navigation  inte-rieure,  routes, tunnels, ponts,   viaducs,  egoutscollecteurs,  egouts  ordinaires,   puits,   installa-tions telegraphiques  ou telephoniques,  installa-tions  electriques,  usines   a  gaz,   distributiond&apos;eau,  ou  autres travaux  de construction, ainsique les travaux  de  preparation  et de fondation precedant  les travaux ci-dessus.                                            (34)  The  General  Conference  of the InternationalLabour Organization of the League of  Nations,      Having  been  convened  by the  Govern-    ment  of  the United States  of America at    Washington,  on the 29th  day of  October,    1919, and      Having  decided  upon  the  adoption of    certain proposals with  regard to  the &quot; em-    ployment  of children:  during the  night,&quot;    which  is  part  of the fourth item in the    agenda for  the  Washington meeting of the    Conference, and      Having  determined  that  these  proposals    shall  take the  form of a draft international    convention,adopts  the  following   Draft   Convention  for ratification  by   the  Members   of  the  Inter-national  Labour  Organization,  in   accordancewith  the  Labour Part of  the  Treaty  of  Ver-sailles of 28 June, 1919, and of the Treaty of St.Germain of 10  September, 1919 :                 ARTICLE 1.  For  the purpose  of this  Convention,  the term&quot; industrial  undertaking &quot;  includes particularly :  (a)  Mines, quarries,  and other works for  the extraction of minerals from  the earth.  (b)  Industries  in  which  articles are  manufac-tured,  altered,  cleaned,  repaired, ornamented,finished,   adapted   for  sale,  broken   up,   ordemolished,  or  in   which  materials  are trans-formed ;  including  shipbuilding,  and  the gener-ation,   transformation,  and  transmission   ofelectricity or motive power  of any kind.  (c)  Construction,    reconstruction,    mainten-ance,  repair,  alteration, or  demolition of any building,   railway,   tramway,   harbor,   dock,pier,   canal,  inland  waterway,  road,  tunnel,bridge,  viaduct,  sewer,  drain, well,  telegraphicor   telephonic   installation,   electrical  under-taking, gas work, waterwork,  or  other work of construction  as well as the preparation for  orlaying  the  foundations  of any such  work  orstructure.
   (d) Le  transport  de  personnes  ou de  mar- marchandises  par  route,  voie  ferree,  ou  eau,  y compris la manutention des  marchandises dans les docks, quais,  wharfs et entrepots, a  1&apos;excep- tion du transport a la main.   Dans   chaque   pays,   l&apos;autorite  competente determinera   la  ligne   de  demarcation  entre 1&apos;industrie,  d&apos;une  part,  le  commerce  et 1&apos;agri- culture,  d&apos;autre part.                   ARTICLE 2.   II est interdit d&apos;employer  pendant  la nuit les enfants  de  moins de  dix-huit  ans  dans  les etablissements   industriels,  publics  ou  prives, ou  dans   leurs  dependances,  a. 1&apos;exception  de ceux  dans  lesquels  sont  seuls   employes  les membres  d&apos;une meme  famille,  sauf dans les  cas prevus  ci-apres.   L&apos;interdiction  du  travail de  nuit ne  s&apos;appli- quera pas aux enfan,ts  au-dessus de seize  ans  qui sont  employes,  dans  les  industries  enumerees ci-apres,  a  des travaux  qui,  en raison  de  leur nature,  doivent  necessairement  etre  continues jour et  nuit:   (a) Usines de fer et d&apos;acier;  travaux  ou Ton fait  emploi des fours  a  reverbere  ou a  regene- ration,  et galvanisation de la  t61e  et du fil de fer (excepte les ateliers de decapage).   (b) Verreries.   (c) Papeteries.   (d) Sucreries ou Ton  traite le sucre brut.   (e) Reduction du minerai d&apos;or.                   ARTICLE 3. &apos;  Pour 1&apos;application  de la presente  Convention,le terme &quot; nuit &quot; signifie une periode d&apos;au moins onze  heures  consecutives,  comprenant  1&apos;inter- valle ecoule  entre dix  heures du  soir  et cinq heures du matin.   Dans les mines de charbon et de  lignite, une derogation pourra etre prevue  en  ce qui con- concerne la  periode  de repos visee au paragraphe precedent, lorsque  1&apos;intervalle  entre les  deuxperiodes  de   travail  comporte   ordinairementquinze  heures,  mais  jamais lorsque  cet inter-valle comporte moins de treize heures.   Lorsque la  legislation   du  pays  interdit  letravail  de  nuit a tout  le  personnel  dans  laboulangerie,. on  pourra  substituer,  dans  cetteIndustrie,  la  periode  comprise entre  neuf heuresdu soir et quatre heures du  matin,  a la  periode de dix heures du soir a cinq heures du matin.   Dans les pays tropicaux ou le travail est sus-pendu pendant  un certain temps  a*u milieu dela journee,  la  periode  de  repos  de nuit pourra etre inferieure  a  onze  heures,  pourvu  qu&apos;unrepos  compensateur  soit  accorde   pendant  le jour.  id)  Transport of passengers or goods by roador rail, including the handling of goods at  docks,quays, wharves,  and  warehouses,  but  excludingtransport by  hand.  The  competent   authority  in  each  country shall  define the line of division which separatesindustry from commerce and agriculture.                   ARTICLE 2.  Young  persons  under eighteen  years  of ageshall  not  be employed  during  the night  in any public or  private  industrial  undertaking, or inany branch  thereof, other than  an undertaking in which  only members of the same family areemployed,  except as hereinafter provided for.  Young  persons over  the  age of sixteen maybe  employed during the night in  the  followingindustrial  undertakings  on  wofik  which  byreason of the nature of the  process,  is requiredto be carried on continuously day and night:  (a)  Manufacture  of  iron  and steel;  processesin  which  reverberatory  or  regenerative  fur-naces are  used,  and galvanizing  of sheet metalor wire (except the pickling process).  (b)  Glass works.  (c)  Manufacture of paper.  (d)  Manufacture  of raw sugar.  (e)  Gold mining  reduction work.                   ARTICLE 3.  For the  purpose of  this  Convention,  the term&quot; night&quot; signifies a period of at least  eleven con-consectutive  hours,  including the  interval betweenten o&apos;clock in the evening and  five o&apos;clock inthe morning.  In  coal and lignite mines work  may be carriedon  in the intorval between  ten  o&apos;clock  in the evening and  five o&apos;clock in  the  morning, if an interval  of ordinarily fifteen  hours,  and  in  no case  of less  than  thirteen  hours,  separates  twoperiods of work.  Where night  work in the  baking  industry  is prohibited  for all workers, the interval betweennine  o&apos;clock  in  the evening and  four o&apos;clock inthe morning may  be  substituted  in  the  bakingindustry  for  the interval between ten o&apos;clock inthe evening and  five o&apos;clock in the morning.  In  those tropical countries in  which  work  issuspended  during  the   middle  of the  day, the night period  may  be  shorter  than eleven hoursif compensatory  rest is accorded during the day,
                  ARTICLE 4.  Les dispositions des articles 2 et 3 ne  s&apos;appli-queront pas  au travail de  nuit des  enfants agesde  seize a  dix-huit  ans  lorsqu&apos;un cas de  forcemajeure qui  ne pouvait etre prevu  ou empeche,et qui ne presente  pas  un  caractere periodique,met obstacle  au fonctionnement  normal  d&apos;unetablissement industriel.                  ARTICLE 5.  En ce  qui  concerne  1&apos;application  de  la pre-sente Convention au Japon, jusqu&apos;au  ler juillet1925, 1&apos;article  2 ne  s&apos;appliquera  qu&apos;aux  enfantsages de moins de quinze ans, et,  a partir de  la date  susmentionnee, ledit  article 2 ne  s&apos;appli-quera  qu&apos;aux  enfants ages  de moins de  seizeans.                  ARTICLE 6.  En ce  qui  concerne  1&apos;application de  la  pre-sente Convention a  l&apos;nde, le  terme &quot; etablisse-ment  industriel&quot;  comprendra   seulement   les&quot; fabriques&quot;  definies   commes   telle  dans   la&quot; Loi des  fabriques&quot;  de  1&apos;Inde  [Indian factoryact),  et  1&apos;article  2  ne  s&apos;appliquera  pas  auxenfants  du   sexe  masculin  ages  de  plus   dequatorze ans.                   ARTICLE 7.  Lorsque, en raison de circonstances  particulie-rement graves, 1&apos;interet  public 1&apos;exigera, 1&apos;inter-diction du travail de nuit pourra etre suspendue parune decision de  1&apos;autorite  publique,  en ce  quiconcerne les  enfants ages de seize a. dix-huit ans.                   ARTICLE 8.  Les  ratifications  officielles   de  la  presenteConvention,  dans les conditions prevues  a  laPar tie XIII du Traite  de Versailles du  28 juin1919,  et  du  Traite  de  St.  Germain  du   10septembre   1919,   seront  communiquees   au secretaire  General   de  la  Societe  des  Nationset  par  lui enregistrees.                   ARTICLE 9.  Tout Membre de  1&apos;Organisation internationale du  Travail  qui  ratifie  la presente  Conventions&apos;engage a. 1&apos;appliquer a  celles  de ses  colonies oupossessions ou a ceux de ses protectorats qui ne segouvernent  pas  pleinement eux-memes,  sous  lesreserves suivantes :   (a) Que les dispositions de  la  Convention  nesoient pas  rendues  inapplicables  par  les condi-tions locales ;   (b) Que les modifications qui  seraient  neces-saires pour  adapter la  Convention aux condi-tions  locales   puissent   etre  introduces   danscelle-ci.                  ARTICLE 4.  The provisions  of Article  2 and 3 shall notapply  to  the night work of young persons be-tween  the ages  of sixteen and eighteen years incases of emergencies which could not  have beencontrolled  or  foreseen,  which  are not  of  a peri-odical  character,  and  which  interfere with thenormal working of  the industrial undertaking.                  ARTICLE 5.  In  the application   of  this  Convention  to japan, until 1 July, 1925, Article  2 shall  apply only  to   young persons  under  fifteen years ofage  and  thereafter  it shall apply only to youngpersons under sixteen years of age.                  ARTICLE 6.  In the application of this Convention to India,the  term  &quot; industrial  undertaking&quot;  shall  in-clude only &quot; factories &quot;  as defined in the IndianFactory  Act, and Article 2  shall not  apply tomale young persons  over fourteen years of age.                  ARTICLE 7.  The prohibition  of night  work  may be  sus-pended by  the Government, for young personsbetween the ages of sixteen  and eighteen  years,when  in  case  of serious  emergency the  publicinterest demands it.                  ARTICLE 8.  The  formal  ratifications  of  this Convention,under  the conditions set forth in  Part XIII  ofthe Treaty  of  Versailles  of 28  June,  1919,  andof the Treaty  of St. Germain  of  10 September,1919,  shall  be  communicated  to   the  secretary general  of  the  League of  Nations  for  regis-tration.                  ARTICLE 9.  Each Member of the IntcrnationalLabour Organi-zation which ratifies this Convention engages  toapply it to its colonies, protectorates and possessionswhich are not fully self-governing :  (a) Except where  owing  to  the  local  condi-tions its provisions are inapplicable ; or  (6) Subject  to such  modifications  as may  benecessary  to  adapt  its   provisions  to &apos;  localconditions.
   Chaque  Membre  devra  notifier  au  bureau international du  Travail  sa decision en ce  quiconcerne chacune cle  ses  colonies ou possessionsou chacun de  ses  protectorats ne se gouvernantpas pleinement eux-memes.                  ARTICLE 10.   Aussitot  que les ratifications  de  deux  Mem-.bres  de reorganisation Internationale  du  Tra-vail auront  ete  enregistrees  au  Secretariat, leSecretaire  General  de  la  Societe  des  Nationsnotifiera ce  fait a  tous les Membres de 1&apos;Orga-nisation Internationale du Travail.                  ARTICLE 11.   La  presente Convention  entrera  en  vigueura la  date  ou cette notification aura  ete  efiec-tuee  par  le  Secretaire  General  de  la societe des Nations;  elle ne liera  que les  Membres quiauront  fait   enregistrer   leur  ratification   auSecretariat.  Par  la suite, la presente Conventionentrera  en  vigueur  au  regard  de tout  autre memre, a la  date  ou la  ratification de ce  Mem-bre aura ete enregistree au Secretariat.                   ARTICLE  12.   Tout Membre qui  ratifie la presente  Conven-tion  s&apos;engage  a  appliquer ses  dispositions  auplus tard  le ler juillet  1922  et  a. prendre tellesmesures  qui   seront  necessaires   pour  rendreeffectives  ces  dispositions.                   ARTICLE  13.   Tout  Membre  ayant ratifie la  presente  Con-vention peut  la  denoncer  a  1&apos;expiration  d&apos;une&apos; periode de dix annecs apres  la date de la mise en vigueur  initiale de  la  Convention,  par  unacte  communique  au Secretaire  General  de laSociete  des Nations  ct  par  lui  enregistre.   Ladenonciation  ne   prendra  effet qu&apos;une  annee apres  avoir  ete enrcgistree  au Secretariat.                   ARTICLE  14.   Le   Conseil   d&apos;Administration    du  Bureau International  du  Travail  devra,  au moins  une fois par  dix  annecs,  presenter  a la. ConferenceGenerale  un  rapport  sur  1&apos;application  de la presente  Convention et  decidera  s&apos;il  y a  lieu d&apos;inscrire  a. 1&apos;ordre du jour de la  Conference la question de la revision  ou  de  la  modificationde la  dite Convention.                   ARTICLE  15.  . Les  textes  francais et anglais de  la  presenteConvention  feront  foi 1&apos;un  et 1&apos;autre.  Each  Member  shall  notify  to  the  Interna-tional  Labour  Office the action taken in respectof  each   of   its  colonies,  protectorates  andpossessions which are not fully self-governing.                  ARTICLE 10.  As soon as the ratifications of two  Members ofthe International Labour Organization have been registered  with  the  Secretariat  the  secretary general of the League of Nations shall so notifyall  the  Members  of  the  International  LabourOrganization.                  ARTICLE 11.  This  Convention shall come  into force  at  thedate  on  which  such  notification  is issued  bythe Secretary General of the League  of Nations,and it shall  then be  binding only  upon those members  which have  registered their  ratifica-tions  with the Secretariat.  Thereafter this Con-vention  will   come  into  force  for   any  other member at  the date  on  which  its   ratificationis registered with the Secretariat.                  ARTICLE 12.  Each  Member which  ratifies  this  Conventionagrees  to bring  its  provisions  into  operationnot later  than 1  July,  1922,  and to take suchaction  as may be&apos;  necessary  to  make  these provisions effective.                  ARTICLE 13.  A Member  which has ratified  this Conventionmay  denounce it after  the   expiration  of  tenyears  from the  date on which  the  Conventionfirst comes into force, by an  act communicatedto  the  Secretary  General  of  the   League  ofNations  for   registration.   Such denunciationshall  not  take effect  until one  year  after  thedate  on  which it  is  registered  with the Secre-tariat.                  ARTICLE 14.  At   least once  in  ten  years  the governing body  of  the  International Labour  Office shall present  to the General  Conference a  report  onthe  working  of  this  Convention,   and shall consider   the  desirability  of   placing   on  theagenda  of. the Conference the  question of  itsrevision or modification.                  ARTICLE  15.  The  French and English  texts  of  this  Con-vention shall  both be authentic.
RECOMMANDATION  CONCERNANT  L&apos;APPLI-   RECOMMENDATION  CONCERNING  THE  AP-CATION  DE  LA  CONVENTION  INTERNA-TIONALE ADOPTEE A  BERNE  EN  1906SUR L&apos;INTERDICTION  DE L&apos;EMPLOI  DUPHOSPHORE  BLANC (JAUNE) DANS L&apos;IN-DUSTRIE DES ALLUMETTES.   La  Conference  Generale  de  1&apos;Organisation Internationale  du  Travail  de  la  Societe  des Nations,      Convoquee  a  Washington  par  le  Gou-    vernement  des  Etats-Unis cFAmerique, le    29 octobre 1919,      Apres avoir decide  d&apos;adopter  une  pro-    position relative a .1&apos; &quot; extension et applica-    tion de la  Convention Internationale adoptee    a Berne en 1906 sur 1&apos;interdiction de 1&apos;emploi    du phosphore blanc  (jaune) dans 1&apos;industrie    des allumettes,&quot;  question comprise dans le    cinquieme  point  de  l&apos;ordre du jour cle la    session de  la conference tenue  a  Washington,    et      Apres avoir decide que cette  proposition    serait  redigee sous forme de recommandation, adopte la Recommandation ci-apres,  qui  sera soumise a 1&apos;examen des Membres de l&apos;Organi- sation Internationale  du  Travail,  en  vue  de lui faire porter effet sous forme de  koi nationale ou autrement,  conformement  aux  dispositions de la Partie relative au  Travail du Traite de Ver- sailles du  28 juin 1919,  et du Traite de Saint- Germain du 10  septembre 1919 :  La  Conference  Generale  recommande  quechaque  Membre  de  1&apos;Organisation   Internatio-nale  adhere s&apos;il ne l&apos;a deja fait a. la Conven-tion Internationale adoptee  a Berne  en 1906 sur l&apos;interdiction de  1&apos;emploi du phosphore  blanc (jaune) dans 1 Industrie des allumettes.PLICATION OF THE BERNE convention of  1906, ON THE PROHIBITION OF  THEUSE OF WHITE  PHOSPHORUS  IN  THEMANUFACTURE OF MATCHES.  The  General  Conference  of  the  International Labour Organization of the League of  Nations,      Having  been  convened  at  Washington    by  the  Government of the United  States    of  America on the 29th  clay of October, 1919,    and      Having  decided  upon  the  adoption  of    a  proposal  with  regard to the &quot; extension    and  application of the International Con-    vention  adopted at Berne  in  1906  on  the    prohibition  of the use  of white phosphorus    in  the  manufacture of  matches,&quot; which is    part of the fifth item in the agenda for the    Washington meeting of the Conference, and      Having determined that this proposal shall    take the form of a recommendation, adopts   the  following  Recommendation,  to  be submitted to  the  Members  of  the  International Labour  Organization  for  consideration  with a view to effect being given to it by national legis- lation  or otherwise,  in accordance with  the Labour  Part of the Treaty of  Versailles  of  28 June, 1919, and the Treaty of St.  Germain  of 10 September, 1919:  The   General   Conference recommends  that each  Member  of  the International   Labour Organization,  which has not already  done so, should  adhere  to  the  International Conventionadopted at Berne  in 1906 on the prohibition of the  use  of  white phosphorus  in  the  manufac- ture of  matches.(38)Oit              CONFERENCE  INTERNATIONALE DU  TRAVAIL                  INTERNATIONAL LABOUR  CONFERENCE

</content>
</cab>
