<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/35 images: 560-569</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,THTo DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S^ GOVERNMENT)(R)(UO)35SECRET Copy No.W A R        CABINETPROPAGANDA:    APPRECIATION OF ACTION taken and ITS EFFECTFifth Report submitted by the Minister ofInformation covering the period December1st 1939 to mid January 19hOPrevious Report   W.P.   (R)(39) 101J.C.W.R.January 24th, 19^0

HO M BTRK REGIONSSome machinery was needed to deal with local aspectsof home propaganda and to keep the Ministry in touch withmovements of public opinion.     Originally the organisation wasto he linked with that of the political parties, hut this was abandoned in October.      Political parties have since &quot;stoodoff&quot; and only this week have signals once again been exchanged.Meantime 11 Regional Information Officers have &quot;been appointed(for the Civil Defence Regions) who, with the assistance of asmall staff, will act as local organising agencies of theMinistry.     Their main task is to present the national war effort by every available medium of local publicity and tokeep people in good heart.      If local committees are advisable,they will be set up.    Sir Arthur Willert and Dame Rachel Crowdyhave been appointed to visit the Regions for co-ordination andliaison.. ARTISTSWith the co-operation of the Service Departments,an Artists&apos; Advisory Committee, under the chairmanship ofSir Kenneth Clark is at work.      It will advise on the selection of artists for the recording of the war.broadcasting the Broadcasting service was improved by the openingon 18th December of the transmitter station at Start Point;it operates on 3U2 metres (London Regional), and, by means ofa special aerial which does not give D.P. assistance to theenemy, transmits in the evenings a second programme withspecial appeal to the B.E.P.       This programme is receivablealso over a large part of this country.      In those areas wherethe B.B.C. Home Service on hi+9 or 391 metres is poorlyreceived, the transmission on 3h-2 metres may help, hut wherethe former service is well received, 3^-2 metres may not he asatisfactory alternative.     Other improvements are:    in theEast Midlands the conversion of the old long-wave transmitterat Daventry to work on 391 metres, and in Aberdeen theoperation of a low-power transmitter on the same wavelength.A proper service of alternatives is still impracticable, but the better the Home Service can be heard, the less listeningto Hamburg and Bremen.SPECIAL SUBJECTSThe last Report mentioned publicity on Anti-Gossip,Rationing, Evacuation, etc.     Work on them continues,GENERALarticles,There has been a steady increase in the despatch of news items, documents, and photographs.      In the lastweek of December over 100,000 copies of 30 separate publications*ere sent to Press Attaches and Consulates for distribution,-he Blue Book and two Command papers on Germany have &quot;beentranslated into the main European languages and Hungarian,Yiddish, Hebrew and Russian translations are in hand.    80,000copies of the White Paper, Germany No.2, are being distributed

- 2 --Dy the French authorities to elementary school teachers.     Asummary of British and German broadcasts about the Graf Sneeis being produced.     Arrangements to give extensive distribu-tion to the Blue Book on the Russian negotiations have ofcourse been cancelled.     Work has been done on the presentation of the British case for contraband control.      25,000 copies ofa pamphlet in Dutch will be distributed in Holland and FlemishBelgium.      Professor Brierley broadcast on January 8th on theGerman export blockade and a print of his talk is to be givenwide circulation in neutral countries.      To help the continentalpress the Ministry has borne half the cost of press calls tothe Continent since January 1st.france,000 copies of a bulletin prepared by the PressAttache are distributed to newspapers and prominent people.French newspapers carry more and more British news andphotographs.     gome-of the Oxford Pamphlets are to be published in translation.      French news is not, however, nearly so wellor so largely presented in Britain, and steps are being takento remedy this.SPAlfr?The Press Attache&apos;s daily bulletin-   has a circulation of 2,000.ITALYDuring the first three months the Press Attache was unable to issue communiq.ues direct to the Italian press, but had to leave them at the Ministry of Popular Culture.    InDecember Signor Gayda asked for material direct.      An improve-ment may follow from an agreement by Stefan! to take.Reuters&apos;  service.BELGIUM7,500 pamphlets are issued weekly from Brussels andAntwerp.     Many articles sent from the Ministry are published.Five times as many British articles as German appear in thepress.THE NETHERLANDSSome Dutch papers have become openly anti-Germanbecause of neutral sinkings.     Articles are sent from theMinistry in Dutch, all of which appear in I+ or 5 Netherlandsnewspapers, and a bi-weekly bulletin prepared by the Press-Attache is sent to 2+5 provincial newspapers.      British pictures! predominate and news of British origin occupies three times the space of German.SCANDINAVIA AND THE BALTIC states the predominance of news from British and Frenchagencies over German is shov/n by the following analysis of aweek&apos;s newspapers:NEWS AGENCIES: Reuter       1505 inches&apos;Havas 796       &quot;D.N.B. 819        &quot;ARTICLES: British     11+62. inchesFrench 235       11

PICTURES:BritishFrenchGerman582 inches256       &quot;295       &quot;Soandinavian journalists have visited the Weymouth contraband control base.      The Norwegian &quot;Norges Handels og Sj5fartstidende&quot;in a Jubilee issue, had 7 articles supplied hy the Ministry.    Inthe Baltic States numbers of Oxford Pamphlets, White Papers, andphotographs have been supplied, but activities here are necessarily restricted.MIDDLE east the Ministry has sent to its 21 posts in this areaabove 500 articles (an average of four copies of each) and5,000 photographs, the latter partly for the press and partly for village display.LATIN AMERICA120 articles and 61+0 photographs were sent to eachof 20 Missions.      German propaganda is extensive and heavily subsided.      It holds the field in regions like South Chile,where there are large German colonies, but on the whole latin american opinion is pro-Ally.Export blockade and the resultant.damage and delayhas naturally produced some ill feeling, notably among theScandinavians,  the Belgians and the Dutch, hut the influence of the Graf Spee victory is still obvious in increasedconfidence in British strength at sea.      There is, however, theusual tendency on the part of some countries, particularlyFrance, to require assurance that we are taking the warsufficiently seriously.      For instance, protests have beenreceived against photographs showing British soldiers dancingand playing games, and there is a damand for scenes suggesting the discipline and sacrifices of war and above all for picturesindicating military strength and massive armament.g     E M P I R EAir Mail passage rates on editorial matter to pressdestinations on routes previously served by the Empire AirKail Scheme are to ha halved.      Additions to the large body oimaterial sent to various Empire destinations are:    a weeklycommentary on international events and the progress of the war,to U3 Information Officers in colonial territories;    a seriesof documents called &quot;Matters of Fact&quot;;    5 films chosen ordesigned for display to African native audiences through cinemavans or otherwise.      A scheme is in hand for the regular supply to overseas empire countries of large-scale reproductions oftopical photographs suitable for shops and public buildings.S * PiThe period of this Report was. dominated hy         gSfQ  story which gave a dramatic and ^ch-neededcorrectivene American impression that there was nothing doing.      me&apos;eekly confidential reports on the tendency of Americancorrespondents in London (supplied by the Chief Censor) showthat the bulk of American despatches are accurate and not-nfriendly.      The York Times of December 7th Panted an active and sympathetic account of the Censorshipwhichdid*ch to correct prevailing misconceptions.     Apart from the

- h -Graf Spee interlude and the story of Finland&apos;s defence,  theperiod under review is marked hy:(a)   A decline in American interest in theWar as a whole.(h)   A parallel decline in open support forthe Allies.(c)    No compensating gain &quot;by Germany.This is due to present land passivity and still more to the growing domestic political preoccupations.JjfllOUS relations the Ministry issues bulletins as under:(a) A Catholic Newsletter for foreign use, 3*600 copiesbeing sent to editors of religious newspapers, Bishops,Missionaries and other selected persons in the Empireand neutral countries;(b) A Spanish and Portuguese edition for still widercirculation in Spain, Portugal and Latin America.(c) For English Catholic newspapers;(d) For European Protestant Press and Church leaders in neutral countries;(e) A Home Press Bulletin for Protestant religious papers.Plans have been made for visitation between leadersof Churches in the British Isles and those of Prance and manyneutral lands.     A series of press articles has been written by prominent people in British religious life, and widedistribution to the Protestant religious press in neutral countries is arranged.      Cardinal Hinsley&apos;s broadcast &quot;TheSword of the Spirit&quot; is being reprinted and 250,000 copieswill be distributed at home.      A summary of the PapalEncyclical, as broadcast by Father Martindale, has been givenwide circulation in neutral countries.     A series of messagesof interest to members of the Orthodox Church has been supplied to the B.B.C. for use in Balkan, Greek and Polish broadcasts.Similar arrangements have been made for German broadcasts.-oOo------------


</content>
</cab>
