<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/138 images: 800-805</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Intld.) W.S.C.30th December, lgjjC.DOCUMENT IS-THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)^S.C.R E T.(G)(UO) 338. COPY NO,Note by the Prime Minister.I circulate herewith Minutes on theOrganisation of Civil Committees, and the Study of post-War Problemso

ORGANISATION OF CIVIL COMMITTEES.1.      In order to grip more closely the work of adjustingand carrying out the import programmes, an ImportExecutive will he- established consisting of theprincipal consumers of imported materials, namely:the three Supply Ministers (the Minister of aircraft production, the First Lord of the Admiralty and theMinister of Supply) - the Minister of Food, and thePresident of the Board of Trade.2.     The Lmport Executive will carry out the generalpolicy laid down by the War Cabinet.    The Executivewill have subordinated to it, in all matters affectingtheir work, the Ministers of Shipping and Transport,with appeal to the War Cabinet in case of difference, andthe Department of Merchant Shipbuilding and Repairs atthe Admiralty.    The policy of the Executive will beput into effect through these two Ministries and thisDepartment,3.     A Production Executive will be set v:gf consistingof the three Supply Ministers, and the Minister ofLabour, to give effect to the general policy of the WarCabinet.    The functions of this Executive will includeallocation of available resources of raw materials,productive capacity, labour, etc. and the establishmentof priorities, where necessary.    The Executive will ofcourse make arrangements to meet the necessary requirementsOf other Departments, especially Agriculture, whoseMinisters are not members of the Executive.4,     Both these Executives, which will report direct to the War Cabinet, will of course be entitled to invite any other Minister to assist in their deliberations.5*     Both Executives will require a Secretariat, and as their work is closely linked, it may be convenient tohave a Joint Secretariat.6*     These two Executives will take over the work ofthe Production Council, and most of the work of theEconomic Policy Committee.7e The Civil Defence Committee will continue as atpresent under the Chairmanship of the Home secretary and Minister of Home Security.8.    - The Home Policy and Food Policy Committees   willcontinue under the Chairmanship of the Lord PrivySealsq The Lord president&apos;s Committee, &quot;The SteeringOommitteeM, will  continue, and will comprise, under theChairmanship of the Lord President of the Council, the

Chairmen of the Import and Production Executives,  theChairman of the Home Policy and Pood Policy committees,the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Minister ofLabour, and the Minister without Portfolio, who willtake charge of the study of post-war problems,(See separate minute)a     To this Committee the largerissues of Economic Policy will be referred by theWar Cabinets    This Committee will concert the work ofthe above Committees, will deal with any differencesnot requiring Cabinet decisions, and will also dealdirectly with any residual matters, and with specialquestions which arise from time to time*(intia.) W. S.C.50th December. .1940.,STUDY. OF POST-WAP PROBLEMS.Provision must now be made for the study of post-war problems.    It is unnecessary to set up agrandiose Ministry of Reconstruction, but one minister will be put in charge of the work, acting with   aCommittee of Ministers,-    This Minister will be theMinister without Portfolio.,    A small staff of 5 or 6 willbe appointed, whose functions will be analytic andselective.    They will, under instructions, obtain andsift practical reconstruction plans, to be giveneffect to In (say) the 3 years after the war.    these plans should be worked out - (a) in the Departments and(b) by organisations such as Chatham House; and shortstatements of principle will be presented to the ministerial committee     Detailed implications will be worked out afterwards,.    The services of Junior and other ministers will be utilised in this matter.    The generalaim will be to obtain a body of practical proposalswhich will command broadly the  support of the main elements in all the political parties.(Intld.) W.S.O.50th December, 1940*


</content>
</cab>
