<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/9/44 images: 456-465</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. Copy No. 1 5W.P. (40) 264,July 18, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR GABINET.INVASION.Note by the Prime Minister.I CIRCULATE herewith, for the information of my colleagues, a minute bymyself dated July 10, together with a note by the First Sea Lord dated July 12reviewing the possibilities of large scale raids or invasions.W. S. C.10, downing  Street, S.W.1,July 18, 1940.[21528a]this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  July, 1940.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1940.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.INVASION.Minute by the Prime Minister.O-in-O, Home Forces,C.I.G.S.,General Ismay, 10 downing  Street, Whitehall.I FIND it very difficult to visualise the kind of invasion all along the coastby troops carried in small craft, and even in boats. I have not seen any seriousevidence of large masses of this class of craft being assembled, and, except in very narrow waters, it would be a most hazardous and even suicidal operation to commit a large army to the accidents of the sea in the teeth of our verynumerous armed patrolling forces. The Admiralty have over 1,000 armedpatrolling vessels, of which two or three hundred are always at sea, the wholebeing well manned by competent seafaring men. A surprise crossing should beimpossible, and in the broader parts of the North Sea the invaders should be an easy prey, as part of their voyage would be made by daylight. Behind thesepatrolling craft are the flotillas of destroyers, of which 40 destroyers are nowdisposed between the Humber and Portsmouth, the bulk being in the narrowestwaters. The greater part of these are at sea every night, and rest in the clay.They would therefore probably encounter the enemy vessels in transit during the night, but also could reach any landing point or points on the front mentioned intwro or three hours. They could immediately break up the landing craft, interruptthe landing, and fire upon the landed troops, who, however lightly equipped,would have to have some proportion of ammunition and equipment carried on tothe beaches from their boats. The Flotillas would, however, need strong air support from our fighter aircraft during their intervention from dawn onwards.The provision of the Air fighter escort for our destroyers after daybreak isessential to their most powerful intervention on the beaches.2. You should see the Commander-in-Chief&apos;s (Home Fleet) reply to thequestion put to him by the desire of the Cabinet, i.e., what happens if the enemycover the passage of their invading army with their, heavy warships. The answer is that, as far as we know at present, they have ho heavy ships not under longrepair except those at Trondheim, which are closely watched by our very largelysuperior forces. When the Nelson and Barham are worked up after refit in afew days&apos; time (the 13th and 16th), it would be easily possible to make two forcesof British heavy ships, either of which would be sufficiently strong, thus thedanger of a Northern outbreak could be contained, and at the same time a dartT21528] bSECRET.W.P. (40) 264.July 18, 1940.
to the South by the Trondheim ,ships could be rapidly countered. Moreover, the cruisers in the Thames and Humber are themselves strong enough, with theflotillas, to attack effectively any light cruisers with which the enemy could coveran invasion. I feel, therefore, that it will be very difficult for the enemy to placelarge well-equipped bodies of troops on the East Coast of England, whether informed bodies or flung piecemeal on the beaches as they get across. even greater difficulties would attend expeditions in larger vessels seeking to break out to the northward. It may further be added that at present there are no signs ofany assemblies of ships.or small craft, except perhaps in Baltic ports, which are sufficient to cause anxiety. Frequent reconnaissance by.the Air and the constantwatching by our submarines should give timely warning, and our minefields arean additional obstruction.3. Even more unlikely is it that the South coast would be attacked. we know that no great mass of shipping exists in the French ports, and that thenumbers of small boats there are not great. The Dover barrage is beingreplenished and extended to the French shore; This measure is of the utmostconsequence, and the Admiralty are being asked to press it forward constantlyand rapidly. They do not think that any important vessels, warships ortransports, have come through the Straits of Dover. Therefore, I find it difficultto believe that the South coast is in serious danger at the present time. Of course,a small raid might be made upon Ireland from Brest. But this also would be dangerous to the raiders while at sea.4. The main danger is from the Dutch and German harbours, which bearprincipally upon the coast from Dover to the Wash. As the nights lengthen this danger zone will extend northwards, but then, again, the weather becomes adverseand the &quot; fishing-boat invasion &quot; far more difficult. Moreover, with cloud, theenemy Air support may be lacking at the moment of his impact.5. I hope, therefore, relying on the above reasoning, which should be checkedwith the Admiralty, that you will be able to bring an ever larger proportion ofyour formed Divisions back from the coast into support or reserve, so that their training may proceed in the highest forms of offensive warfare and counter-attack, and that the coast, as it becomes fortified, will be increasingly confidedto troops other than those of the formed Divisions, and also to the Home Guard,I am sure you will be in agreement with this view in principle, and the only question open would be the speed of the transformation. Here, too, I hope weshall be agreed that the utmost speed shall rule.6. Air-borne attack is not dealt with in this note. It does not alter its^conclusions.w. s. c.July 10, 1940.INVASION.Note by the First Sea Lord.IN reviewing the possibilities of large-scale raids or invasion to-day, we haveto take into account the characteristics of the Hitler regime, under wmich themost careful detailed preparations are made for any operation it is desired toundertake, and complete disregard of losses is to be expected if this will facilitate the attainment of the object. We cannot therefore assume either that specialcraft will not have been&apos; provided or that past military rales as to what is practicable and what is impracticable will be allowed to govern the actionundertaken.With our present naval superiority, if we were to rule out the effect of air action, the prospects of sustaining an invasion, which needs a line of supply,would clearly be nil, If, therefore, an invasion is undertaken by Germany, wemust assume that she expects to counter both our air and our naval forces by theuse of her superior air power.We have to assume, therefore, that when undertaking a heavy raid oiinvasion large numbers of German air forces will be concentrated on our warships in the narrow seas in an endeavour to prevent them operating against the invading
forces. In the areas where dive bomber attack is possible we must expect consider -able losses among our naval forces from this source.The initial landing of a considerable number of enemy is, however, quite adifferent matter from maintaining a line of communication and, taking intoaccount thick weather and darkngss, it will never be possible for the admiralty to guarantee that such forces may not: be landed in considerable numbers.In the hundred years since invasion of this country Avas last seriously talkedabout the Channel and North Sea have become very much narrower because ofthe greatly increased speed of the craft that might be employed, and the crossingof these waters by large numbers of high speed small boats is now quite a practicable matter. The whole crossing can be undertaken in many places in thedark hours.In order to try and arrive at some idea of the numbers that might be landed,it is necessary to review the various sections of the European coast line now inpossession of the enemy.Bay of Biscay forts.Owing to distance and weather conditions, invasion from these ports wouldhave to be staged in moderately large ships. Given air reconnaissance over the ports, the assembly of a concentration of such ships should be detected, but thesouth Biscay ports are at present outside the range of our reconnaissance.An expedition could therefore to-day be assembled and sailed from, say,Bordeaux unobserved. Once detected, such an expedition would be verysusceptible to naval counter measures, but if suitable -weather was chosen or our naval forces had been temporarily driven away by bomber attack, a determinedenemy should be able to land some part of such an expedition on our southerncoast.  A figure of ten to. twenty thousand may be hazarded.French Channel ports from Brest to Cape Gris Nez.Our air reconnaissance of these harbours is good, and their nature and layoutis such that the enemy could not hope to conceal preparations for an invasionon any substantial scale, whether in big ships or small craft; The use of big-ships, in any case, appears improbable from these ports.&quot;The distances concerned are, however, comparatively short, and by usingsmall craft, and, again, given suitable weather, it might be possible for a forceup to, say, 5,000 men to be landed.Cape Griz Nez to Terschelling.There are innumerable harbours and stretches of canal on this coast wheresmall craft can be readily hidden and where it would be very difficult to detectthem by air reconnaissance. Given good organisation, a large concentration ofsuch craft could be effected unseen.This appears, consequently, the most suitable area for fast small craft, andit is assumed that this is the area in which they will be used. The enemy maywell have prepared a considerable number of these fast craft, and it is not impossible that,, say, 400 of these vessels, each capable of holding 40 men, may bein readiness.Such an exepedition would, of course, have to choose its weather, but, if itchose well, we could not rely on receiving any warning whatever from our air reconnaissance of its approach. The first thing that would be known of a coming-attack would be contact with our naval patrols. With an enemy steaming30 knots, this would only occur when he was 20 minutes or so distant from hisselected beach.Under these circumstances the likelihood of our destroyers being able to get to. the spot in time to take any considerable toll is not great. The coastal patrolsthemselves, being slow and of weak armament, could not be expected to stop morethan, say, 20 per cent, of such a force. Thus it may be, say, 12,000 enemy soldierscould be landed under these conditions. These men, however, like all otherscoming in small boats, could only be armed with portable weapons.Enemy coasts North of Terschelling.This coast is at such a distance from this country that the use of small craftis most unlikely, and the ships selected would probably be moderate-sized oneswith as high a speed as possible. About 50 such ships, with speeds from 15 to20 knots, are probably available to the enemy, and each could carry between 1,000and 2,000 men, total capacity 75,000 men.[215281 b 2
Our air reconnaissance is reasonably good in this area to-day, but the expedition would probably be assembled in the Kiel area or the Kattegat and thencome out via the Kiel Canal or the Skagerr&amp;k.In suitable weather it is again possible that such an expedition would notbe detected until it arrived quite close to our shores and could run themselvesashore on selected beaches from the Southwold area to, say, Rosyth.We ought to take a considerable toll of such ships while they were unloading,but, in the weather conditions envisaged, 50,000 men might very well get ashoretogether with a proportion of tanks, for the landing of which it must be assumed that proper provision, similar, perhaps, to our own motor landing craft, hasbeen made.In 1917 a Committee on Invasion decided that, although an absoluteguarantee could not be given against the arrival of one convoy, maximum size32 ships, subsequent convoys would fail to reach our shores and his expeditionwould be a failure. Therefore, the maximum force with which the land forces would have to deal would be limited to one convoy, that is 30,000 men, with a strictly limited proportion of transport and artillery.It will be seen that we now put this figure at 50,000 for the following reasons: (a) Hitler&apos;s driving power.(b) A larger number of fast ships available.(c) Danish ports as well as German ports are available.(d) As the Danish Islands are in German hands an expedition can pass through the Kattegat without being reported.Norivegian Coast.In view of the presence of the Home Fleet at Scapa and/or Rosyth, it doesnot seem probable that the enemy would be likely to use- large ships starting from Norwegian ports to land a force on the East Coast of Scotland.It is, however, by no means unlikely that he would employ a very largenumber of small craft, such as are available in Norway, for bringing over his troops. Such forces might take the Faroes, the Shetlands, and perhaps Iceland,and they might even try and land of our West Coast. The chances of their gettingashore will again depend mainly on the weather conditions, and, while our forces would take a heavy toll of anything met, in suitable weather 10,000 men mightwell succeed in getting ashore.-General.With the enemy in occupation of such a great extent of European coast, hecan approach our shores at almost any point. The chances of his getting con-siderable numbers of men ashore depend almost entirely on weather conditions.In the calm misty weather that sometimes prevails for days on end in these-areas, large numbers of vessels might start from the enemy shores without beingseen and might reach these coasts without it being possible to intercept them.Arriving as they would in thick weather, their landfalls would be unlikely tobe accurate, but there are so many places on our coast where landing is possiblethai, this might not be of vital importance.From the review given above, it appears probable that a total of some100,000* men might reach these shores without being intercepted by naval forces.These men would no doubt be sufficiently equipped to keep them going for somedays, and possibly weeks, but, as mentioned above, the maintenance of their lineof supply, unless the German air force had overcome both our air force and ournavy, seems practically impossible.It must be assumed, therefore, that if the enemy undertook this operationunder these conditions he would do so in the hope that he could make a quickrush on London, living on the country as he went, and force our Governmentto capitulate.d. p.July 12, 1940.* South coast from Bay of Biscay ports ...       ...       ...       ... ... 20,000South coast from Channel ports...       ...       ...       ...       ... ... 5,000East coast from Dutch and Belgian ports      ...       ...       ... ... 12,000East coast from German ports   ...       ...       ...       ...       ... ... 50,000Shetlands, Iceland and coast of Scotland from Norwegian ports ... 10,00097,000
Further Minute by the Prime Minister.THE chiefs of Staff and Home Defence should consider these papers. TheFirst Sea Lord&apos;s Memorandum may be taken as a working basis, although I personally believe that the Admiralty will in fact be better than their word, andthat the invaders&apos; losses in transit would further reduce the scale of attack, yet the preparations of the land forces should be such as to make assurance doublysure. Indeed, for the land forces the scale of attack might well be doubled,namely, 200,000 men distributed as suggested by the First Sea Lord. Our HomeArmy is already at a strength when it should be able to deal with such an invasion, and its strength is rapidly increasing.I should be very glad if our plans to meet invasion on shore could be reviewedon this basis so that the Cabinet may be informed of any modifications. Itshould be borne in mind that, although the heaviest attack would seem likely to fall in the North, yet the sovereign importance of London and the narrowness ofthe seas in this quarter make the South the theatre where the greatest precautionmust be taken.W. S. 0.10 Downing Street, Whitehall.July 15, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
