<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/195/8 images: 89-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 33 COPY NO22 March 1977CABINETDIRECT ELECTIONS TO THE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department. In accordance with the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on 17 March (CM(77) llthConclusions), I have revised the draft White Paper on direct elections.     the annexes have also been revised in the light of discussion and to bring them into line with the text of the White Paper itself.2. There are two substantive changes that I should bring to mycolleagues1 attention.    The first relates to the reference to the electoralsystem for Northern Ireland.    I think it would be right for this to bebrought forward into the discussion of options as paragraph 24.Paragraph 27 can then deal with the particular situation if a simple majoritysystem is used in Great Britain.    Secondly, I have deleted from Annex Bthe example showing how seats might be allocated under a regional ListSystem.    The example was somewhat complex and might be misleading inthat it focused attention on one particular variant of the system.    Aparallel example for a Single Transferable Vote system in Annex C would beeven more cumbersome, and I do not think that it is necessary to go intothis sort of detail in the White Paper.3. The Cabinet agreed that the White Paper should be published earlyin April.    Mr Roger Sims MP has put down a Question about the white paper for Oral Answer on Thursday 31 March.    It would, therefore, be helpful if it could be published that day.    To achieve that timetable, thefinal text of the White Paper and annexes needs to be with the printers inthe course of Friday 25 March.    It will therefore be necessary for me toreceive any comments on the revised drafts by close of business onThursday 24 March.M RHome Office22 March 1977
DRAFT OF 21 MARCH 1977WHITE PAPER on direct ELECTIONS TO THE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLYList of contents the BACKGROUND Paras. 1-part I : THE CONSTITUTIONAL ISSUESThe Electoral System Paras. 8-20Compulsory Dual Mandate Paras. 21-22Options Paras. 23-24pART II.: RESPONSE TO THE SELECT COMMITTEE(1)    SIMPLE MAJORITY SYSTEMAllocation of Seats Para. 26Determination of Constituencies   Paras. 27-31Franchise Para. 32Disqualification Para. 33Conduct of Elections Para. 34-Deposits Para. 35Nominations Para. 36Returning Officers Para. 37Election Expenses Limits Para. 38By-Elections Para. 39Broadcasting Para. 4-0Finance Para. 4-other Matters Para. 4-2(2)   LIST SYSTEM -  Paras. 4-3-46(3)   SINGLE TRANSFERABLE VOTE Paras. 4-7-50(4-)    COMPULSORY DUAL MANDATE Para. 51ANNEX A : Electoral Systems to be used in other Member StatesAKB*X B : List system a %Ex C : Single Transferable Vote^^EX D : Compulsory Dual Mandate
BRAFT of 21 March 1977WHITE PAPER ON DIRECT ELECTIONS TOTHE EUROPEAN assembly the BACKGROUND-    The United Kingdom became a member of the European community in 1973 and our membership was endorsed by the referendum of 1975--Tills fundamental decision has implications for the relationship    .between our form of government and the institutions of theCommunity.2. &apos;   The European Community was established in 1958 by the cominginto force of the Treaty of Rome.   Article 138(3) of the TreatyProvides for the introduction of a system of elections to theEuropean Assembly on the basis of &quot;direct universal suffrage in !accordance with a uniform procedure for all member States&quot;.    However, :fQr the past 19 years, members of the European Assembly have beendominated by national Parliaments from among their members in jaccordance with Article 138(1).5-     The European Assembly is very different from the Westminster        j?arliaaient since it has no independent legislative functions and a-&quot;    government is not formed from its members.   As Article 137 of the^treaty 0f Rome explains, it has only &quot;advisory and supervisory jPowers&quot;.   However, it does have certain limited powers in relationto the Community budget and it has the power to dismiss the whole       . j0f *he European Commission.    The present nominated Assembly consists   i0f 198 members of whom  36 represent the United Kingdom,lien it is      .!Erectly elected, the Assembly.will have 410 members, 81 of them^ the United Kingdom.CONHDENTlAjL
*    Direct elections have increasingly been seen as anlaPortant means of strengthening democratic participation in Community affairs.   A Green Paper on direct elections**0 the European Assembly (Cmnd. 6399) was presented toPar.Uament in^February 1976. . -.*.   Following a debate in the House of Commons in-March 1976, a Select^&quot;unittee jvas appointed &quot;to consider proposals for Direct Elections to the^uropean Assembly and arrangements requiring action by Parliament and by the^Uropean Community following the Government^ commitment to proceed to such..,Actions11.   The Select Committee have produced three reports.   The Governmentindebted to the Committee for their recommendations on the many issueslnvolved.   The Committee&apos;s reports have been of great assistance to theGovernment in their consideration of these difficult matters.oAgreement was reached between all member States onSeptember 1976 on the text of a Council Decision onl3?ect elections (published as Cmnd. 6623).   This Agreement/s down that, subject to its provisions, the&quot;Gctoral procedures for these first direct electionssllouidbe governed by the national provisions of each: *-u0er State. . The substantive provisions of the Agreementnot come into force until all member States haveConiPleted their respective constitutional requirements.5 Preamble to the Decision records the agreed intention
01&quot; member States that the first direct elections to theEuropean Assembly should be held in the period Hay/June1978.   In recognition, however, of the possibility that so&amp;e member States might have difficulty in completing the necessary legislative and other preparatory stages.iu that timescale, no binding date for first electionswas set.   The Agreement provides for the Council, acting \.unanimously after consulting the Assembly, to determine the date of the first elections at a later stage.   Her-ajesty&apos;3 Government has undertaken to use its best endeavours &apos; -to be ready for elections by Hay/June 1972 and The Queen1sSpeech of November 1976 contained a commitment to introduce the necessary legislation in the current Session ofParliament.7,    There are fundamental constitutional issues involvedin direct elections to the European Assembly.    It is theview of the Government that before legislation is introductedthere should be a dob&amp;ts in Parliament and in the country in vhich all aspects ofthe matter are considered.   The purpose of this White Paper is to        :put the issues involved before the Parliament and the people of - ;the.United Kingdom. :
part i:  the constitutional issuesthe electoral system3-      The electoral system to be used for direct elections to theEuropean Assembly presents a most difficult issue.    The uk hasa distinctive electoral system which has developed gradually0ver the last one and a half centuries and which is different from that of any other e.c. Member State.    It has stood the test of^me and it is well understood by the electorate at large and bytue political Parties.9&apos;      With, certain limited exceptions, all local and national.Sections in the UK have always been on the basis of the simple majority (first-Past-the-post) electoral system.   The concept of the constituencyis a fundamental part of our traditional electoral practice and at both local and national level each person elected has owed asPecial allegiance to a distinct and comparatively small electorate.Ttis local power base has not been without significance in theHo^se of Commons itself, where the individual Member of Parliament0ften plays a distinctive part in influencing the policies of the^ernment and of his Party.   The advantage of the single memberCoristituency is that the elector votes for a particular candidatein the clear knowledge that the candidate who obtains most votes   .i1-1-! be elected and will act as his Member.Furthermore, the careful and objective drawing of constituencyaries by statutory   Boundaries Commi s si or s, independent of the5Grnment of the day, with the right of electors toallenge proposed boundaries and confidential
CONFIDENTIALwith the necessity for subsequent approval by Parliament,has become an essential part of our democratic process.11.     All these traditional practices are basic to the westminster type of Parliamentary democracy.   They should not changed or curtailed for direct elections to the european assembly except after the most careful consideration ofthe present and future implications of such a step.12.     Another relevant factor is the growth of party organisations alongside the development of our democraticinstitutions and reflecting the nature of these institutions.The structure of Party organisations has been developed atconstituency, regional and national level, with Party conferencesPlaying a significant role.   Within the Party system, the selection of candidates tends to be de-centralized and exercised by theiocal constituency.   Whatever form of electoral practice emerges,Party organisation and selection of candidates will both beaffected by a move to direct elections to the European Assembly.13.     Our partners in the E.E.C., with their different historicaltraditions, have developed different electoral systems.Most of them use some form of proportional representation for national elections;    and, for elections to the european assembly, it seems likely that, apart from the republic of Ireland (whore it is proposed to use the single transferable vote system of election), all other member States will useS0Rie form of list system.    (Details of the systems used ore*Pected to be used by the other members of the E.E.C. are givenltl Annex A.)   Thus, if we use our traditional single majority system for
the first direct elections to the European Assembly, therewill he significant differences between our procedure andthat of the other 8 countries who will be electing members to the same Assembly.14.   There are other considerations, which result from someof the inherent characteristics of the existing Britishsystem.   One of these characteristics is the tendency forswings in electoral opinion to be magnified in terms ofSoats won or lost.    This is regarded by many as an advantage in the context of Westminster elections wherea Government is being elected.    In the context of Europeansections, however,   &apos;it&apos; might be regarded as a less desirableMature.    This would be especially so if, as some studieshave suggested, the relatively small number of Assemblyconstituencies (81 as compared vriih635 WestminsterConstituencies) further magnified   the effect with a -     .    .fi*al result in terms of seats which was quite disproportionateto votes cast.   There is the further point that, particularly ifAssembly elections fell mid-way between General.Elections toVestminster, there could be a wide divergence between theGlance of power at Westminster and the Party composition0f the United Kingdom members of the European Assembly.    In one respect,Siven the advisory nature of the European Assembly, this^Sht not be a matter of much concern; but in a developingNation   it could lead to friction between the Government   ^    ;at Westminster and the U.K. representatives in the directly electedSuropean Assembly or even between the Government and the Assembly itselfl5*   It would be possible to  resolve some of these problems byopting a system of. -* - %*i0IN ua 1 l*IN OAL
Proportional representation for elections to the european assembly.    Since the European Assembly does not constitute a legislature or provide a government, and since its membersdo not have the same constituency responsibilities as aWestminster M.P., proportional representation for theEuropean Assembly might not be open to the same objectionsas proportional representation for the Westminster Parliament.A different institution might warrant a different form of election.^-   A list system could be devised based on the whole0? the United Kingdom or Great Britain; or on separatelists for their constituent parts; or England could be sub-dividedinto regions or constituencies, each being allocated a number ofMembers on the basis of electorate.   The adoption of a listSystem would bring us into line with the majority of our EuropeanPartners and would ensure that the allocation of seats was moreProportional to the votes cast for the competing Parties.   ItWQuld also have advantages in the speed with which it could be bought into operation, since there would-not be more than abouta dozen regions and even if Boundary Commission procedures werePessary they would be less elaborate than would be required toaeiine 81 new constituencies.    (Annex B shows how a regionallist system might work in practice.)1?-   To abandon our traditional method in this way would be a%0or constitutional innovation, the consequences of which are^difficult to foresee.    It would mean the absence of the sort ofCoilstituency link with which we are familiar and could lead toges in Party organisations, including giving the central or
regional Party organisations a bigger role in nominating candidates,^-e electorate might take time to become accustomed to the new system and might be confused by the existence of separateprocedures for national and European elections, althoughthe Northern Ireland electorate have coped with a similarsituation since 1973.   Furthermore, there might have to be yetMother change if in accordance with the Treaty of Rome, thereis,in due course,a move to put European elections on a commonDasis and a different system is then adopted.   This would be amatter for all Community governments and their respective Parliaments1s-   Besides the simple majority and list systems, a thirdPossible electoral system is the single transferable vote, whichis another form of proportional representation.   It has alreadybeen used for local government, Convention and Assembly electionsir* Northern Ireland.    Such a system involves multi-member con-sbituencies and the elector votes for as many candidates as hewart &apos;ishes in order of preference.   This system gives maximum influence to the elector, who is able to express a preference between theAfferent candidates of the Party of his choice as well as between^candidates of other Parties.   Such a system would retain theincept of the constituency, but geographically such constituencies^only be larger than single member European constituencies in asiBlPle majority system of election and much larger than the WestminsterCo^stituencies used in our General Elections.   The United Kingdom&apos;s81 seats might be allocated to about a dozen constituencies each^turning between 3 and 10 members, depending on size ofdoctorate.    (See Annex C for further details of this system.)
Another problem is the relationship between Assembly members andWestmin ^ted Kingdom are members of the House of Commons or the House ofrds.   Assembly members who were not also members of the Westminstera:c&apos;liament would tend to be out of touch with developments atestminster and might regard themselves as owing a primary allegiance to -pEuropean rather than National Parties.kuch problems could be overcome if all Assembly members had to beers of the House of Commons - the compulsory dual mandate.    but would in turn create serious practical difficulties.   The strainPerforming the double task could be very great.   As Parliament isGently organised its work would be hindered by the absence of81 to,s at the European Assembly, and changes might be necessary in theSements of the business.    In addition it would be necessary to19.   However, STV like the list system, would involve fundamentaldepartures from our traditional electoral practice and, would againaean that we were using different electoral systems for national and European elections.    It too might require some kind of boundaryProcedure, but this again would be less complex that that necessary if we were to use the simple majority system.20 -   Whatever electoral system were used, it would be important toensure a democratic procedure for the selection of candidatesaQd to involve the constituency party organisations in this procedure to the fullest possible, extent.GoMPULSORY DUAL MANDATE21.tster MPsited
Provide for the situation where an Assembly member subsequently lostMs Westminister seat at a national election which did not coincide with elections to the Assembly.   Moreover, following direct electionstfce dual mandate concept might be much more difficult to operatethan hitherto.   At present the United Kingdom sends 36 delegates,some of whom come from the House of Lords; but after direct elections*e shall send 81 members, all of whom would have to come from theHouse of Commons under a compulsory dual mandate system.   Futher-^re, when the European Assembly is directly elected    and the0verwhelming majority of its members do not sit in a nationalIeSislature, the Assembly is likely to have a more intensive schemeof business which pays little regard to the times of sittings ofthe&quot;let?ue various national legislatures.    (See Annex D for further;a-ils of the compulsory dual mandate.)
CONFIDENTIALil$ptiqns^3.   As the preceding paragraphs show, the United Kingdom faces adumber of difficult problems in its approach to direct elections to the European Assembly, some of which are not shared by our^*E.C. partners.    The Government is aware of the importantinstitutional issues involved.    It is also conscious of thedesirability Of making major constitutional changes unless theybave a \\&apos;ide measure of support.    There appear to be four main^ssibilities: to stick to our traditional simple majority electoralAstern; to change to a list system of proportional representation,^obably on a regional basis; to change to S.T.V.; or to retain theSlInple majority system as far as possible but to combine this with compulsory dual mandate.    Each of these possibilities has someattractions; but each also presents serious difficulties.    before coming to a conclusion on this, the Government wishes to listen0 the views expressed in Parliament and elsewhere.^   Whatever electoral system is used in the rest of the United-&quot;-ngdom for. direct elections to the European Assembly, the&apos; 0v&amp;rnment considers that the special circumstances of Northern^land would make it appropriate for direct elections there to be conducted by a system of proportional representation.
PART II:    RESPONSE TO THE SELECT COMMITTEE(1)    SIMPLE MAJORITY SYSTEM25.     The Select Committee on Direct Elections to theEuropean Assembly recommended that the first electionshe conducted on our normal first-past-the-post electoralsystem.    If this is to be the basis of these elections,then the Government will wish to see the following arrange-ttents on the particular points on which theSelect Committee has made recommendations in its second and Third Reports.. COM F1 DENTS AL
CONFIDENTIALAllocation of Seats26.    It will be necessary to decide upon the allocation of our 81seats among the component narts of the United Kingdom.    It wouldbe possible to base the allocation of seats directly in accordancewith the size of the electorate in each of the component partsin accordance with current representation at Westminster, orin other ways.    For the first elections, bearing in mind,among other things, the special circumstances of Northern Ireland,the Government proposes accepting the Select Committee&apos;recommendation on the allocation of seats.   This would giveEngland 66 seats, Scotland 8, Wales 4 and Northern Ireland 3-    for subsequent elections, the allocation of seats and the determinationQf boundaries (which is dealt with below) could be referred to a speaker&apos;s Conference on Electoral Law.^termination of Constituencies2?.   The Government would agree with the Select Committee&apos;srecommendations that the European Assembly constituencies should be formed by grouping existing Parliamentary constituencies and thatthe number of electors in each of the European Assembly constituenciesnould be approximately equal (with some exceptions for geographicalreasons).    Northern Ireland would, however, form a single EuropeanConstituency.    As explained above the Government considers that thesPecial circumstances of Northern Ireland would make it appropriate for direct elections there to be conducted by a system of proportional representation: /if the rest of the United Kingdom usesthe simple majority system, S.T.V. would be used in Northern Ireland?
The procedures for the determination of V/estrainster&apos; onconstituencies are laid down in the House of Commons (RedistributeQf Seats) &quot;Acts 1949 and 1953. These procedures make provision for^presentations to be made to the Boundary Commissions about theirprovisional recommendations and for local inquiries to be held; ifnscessary, two rounds of representations and local inquiries may takePlace.29.&apos;    The Select Committee have recommended that the European AssemblyCoristituencies should be determined on the basis of recommendations from theanentary Boundary Commissions, using as far as possible similar proceduresthose employed by the Commissions in the reviews of Parliamentary constituency0Undaries.   The Government shares the view that it would be desirable for thearliamentary Boundary Commissions to be asked to make recommendations en thermination of the boundaries for European Assembly constituencies.   Thee^ct Committee believed that some curtailment of these full procedures would^e necessary for elections to be held in May/June 1978 and recommended that theUlng procedures should be followed, but with provision for one round only of 1QCal representations and inquiries.   The Government accept that some curtail-Qf the full Parliamentary constituency review procedures will be necessaryLne first elections if they are to be held in May/June 1978, although  it mightaPpropriate for the full procedures to be followed for subsequent elections.Par];,tobedeterIn the Government&apos;s view, for the first elections a choicehave to ha made between the following three options:A.   Boundary Commission recommendations following one round of representations and local inquiries, or
B.   Boundary Commission recommendations following one round of representations but no local inquiries, orG.    Boundary Commission recommendations with no representationsor local inquiries.^n evidence to the Select Committee, the Boundary CommissionsSuSgested that from the time of-Royal Assent to the relevant legislationUP to the submission of their reports, Option A would take a minimum0  30 weeks, Option B a minimum of 18 weeks and Option C a minimum of&apos; weeks.    Bearing in mind that some 6 months will be needed to select   :andidates and prepare for the elections, the Boundary Commissionsneed to complete their work by the end of 1977 if elections areto be held in Hay/June 1978.*1*     The Government considers that it would be unsatisfactory forue^e to be no provision for either representations or local inquiries i^ therefore finds Option C unattractive.    On the other hand, theres. insufficient time to be at all sure of implementing Option A.^lt:n some reluctance, the Government therefore inclines in favour of^Ption B for the first elections, since this would .at least provide -     -0lfie opportunity for the political parties and other interested-Les to express a view on the Commissions&apos; provisional recommendations.;The Government agrees with the Select Committee that the^hise for European Assembly elections should in general be thesasie -as for United Kingdom Parliamentary elections with the addition0&quot; oPeers.   The Committee recommended that the franchise should benaed to certain United Kingdom nationals
CONFIDENTIAL16resident overseas;   but the Government does not consider that this important extension, which would have obvious relevance to the franchise for Westminster, should be made without prior considerationDy a Speaker&apos;s Conference.disqualification33.     The Government proposes accepting the Select Committee&apos;recommendation on disqualification.   This would mean that (unless there were a compulsory dual mandate) the rules governing disqualifica-tion of candidates for Westminster elections would be applied with theEdification that peers and all clergymen would be allowed to standxor election to the European Assembly.   Members of the Westminster-srliament would not be disqualified from election to the european assembly.Go&apos;aduct of ElectionsThe Government accepts the Select Committee&apos;s recommendationhat in general normal United Kingdom Parliamentary electoral law should apply to the conduct of European Assembly elections.    This&apos;;ould cover the present arrangements for absent voting by post or proxyand the arrangements for service voting.^PositsThe Select Committee,recommended that the deposit should beSet at  150 for each Parliamentary constituency contained in theStir-^0Pean Assembly constituency.   This would mean that for an Assembly&quot;0nstituency containing 5 Parliamentary constituencies the deposit&apos;Quld be  750, while for one containing 10 Parliamentary constituenciesitwould be  1500.    The Government takes the view that it would be^-Gferable for a fixed and rather lower deposit to be set and proposesth.e^    sum of  500 irrespective of the size of the Assemblyu 0QstitUenc y concerned.   A deposit of this size would deter frivolaceidature  without unreasonably inhibiting genuine candidates.CONFIDENTIAL
Nominations35.      The Select Committee recommended that nominations should be accompanied by the signatures of ten per Westminster constituencyo-t those eligible to vote in the European Assembly constituency.   The  &apos;Government considers that the number of nominations required for european Assembly elections should be greater than that requiredfor a Westminster election, but does not consider that the increase should be in proportion.   The Government therefore proposes that,^ the simple majority   is   adopted, nominations should be accompanied by the signature of a fixed number of electors in eachEuropean Assembly constituency and proposes that this number shouldbe set at about 50.Returning Officers3?.      The Select Committee recommended that in England and Wales the^turning officer should be appointed by the Chief Executive for theCouuty (including metropolitan counties and the Greater London Council)iri which the European Assembly constituency (or the larger part of it)is situated.   In Scotland, they recommended that the returning officersUould be appointed by the Secretary of State from among those^Pointed&quot;to act as returning officers at regional or islands councilActions.    In Northern Ireland, they recommended that the returning0i&apos;officer should be the Chief Electoral Officer for Northern Ireland.The Government accepts the&quot;recommendations in relation to Scotland^ Northern Ireland, but considers that, it would be more appropriateEngland and Wales for the Secretary of State to appoint the&quot;tu^ning officers from among the returning officers for the relevant^Uamentary constituencies (the sheriff of the country or the^or of the borough or the chairman of the district council).    They&quot;0l*ld be required to delegate most of their duties to an acting6t^ning officer. ^flAg &apos; &apos;
Election Expenses Limits38.      The Government proposes, as recommeded by the Select Committee,to consult the political parties on an appropr.io.te formula for limiting candidates&apos; election expenses.    The Government would propose&quot;that there should be a free   postal&apos;delivery of candidates1 electionaddresses on the same basis as for Parliamentary elections.%-ElectionsThe Select Committee recommended that the machinery for filling  !Assembly vacancies should be set in motion by means of a writ movedln- the House of Commons.   The Government does not consider that the proc--Qure would be entirely appropriate, since unless there js a compulsory dual mandate%*ibers of the Assembly may not be members of the House of Commons. The Government;accepts that arrangements will need to be made to ensure that therela no clash between Westminster and European Assembly by-elections and :ls at present considering how best to deal with this. -broadcasting the Select Committee pointed out that broadcasting raisesSocial problems in relation to direct elections.   The GovernmentAccepts the Select Committee&apos;s recommendation that the full^Plications of this should be examined through the existing^chinery for the provision of part political broadcasts.^QanceThe Government considers that the cost of administering-^european Assembly elections ( (estimated to be at least  10 million)s^0Uld be met out of the Consolidated Pund.    The GovernmentQQt yet formed a view on
whether candidates should receive any reimbursement of theirexpenses from central funds.   This matter is being considered in the context of the Government&apos;s consideration of therecommendations made by the Committee on Financial Aid to?political Parties (Crand 6601).Other Hatters*2.    There are other matters (such as the arrangements for electoralroaris4-pn-h-.or. nr,h fn. th* avoidance of double voting, the countingof votes and the declaration&apos; of results) that will need to be covered.   The Government agreees with the Select Committee that  -ese matters should be conducted in accordance with normalfilamentary electoral law and practice.    It will, however, be^cessary to make certain adaptations to fit the circumstances of^ropean Assembly elections.    .
CONFIDENTIAL20(2):    LIST SYSTEM43.    If the electoral system used in the first direct electionswere a regional list system of the kind outlined in Annex Brather than the simple majority system, then the Governmentwould have to make a different response to some of therecommendations of the Select Committee.44-.    The Bill could specify the regions to be adopted and thenumber of seats to be allocated to each region.    These regionsmight be the economic planning regions, which are well known.Alternatively, some form of Boundary Commission procedure mightbe desirable, especially if such recognised regions were to besub-divided.4-5.    It may be that a regional list system would call for adifferent view on the appropriate value of the deposit and numberof nominations and on the appointment of Returning Officers.If the list system were used, it would probably be unnecessary to hold by-elections.4-6.   All other arrangements (including allocation of seats amongthe component parts of the U.K., candidature and franchise) wouldhe the same as for the simple majority system.
(3):    SINGLE TRANSFERABLE VOTE47.    If the electoral system used in the first direct electionswere a single transferable vote system of the kind outlined in Annex 0 rather than the simple majority system, then theGovernment would have to make a different response to someof the recommendations of the Select Committee.4-8.   As with the list system, the Bill could specify the constituencies-uencies to be adopted and the number of seats to be allocated to each constituency.    These constituencies might be based on well established regions such as the economic planning regions.Alternatively, some form of Boundary Commission proceduremight be desirable, especially if such recognised regions were tohe.jab -divided to make STV constituencies.4-9.    It may be that the use of STV would call for a differentview on the appropriate value of the deposit and number of nominationand on the appointment of Returning Officers.    If STV were usedit would probably be necessary to hold by-elections.50.   As with the list system, all other arrangements would bethe same as for the simple majority system.
.(4):    COMPULSORY DUAL MANDATE51.    If there were a compulsory dual mandate the Government&apos;sresponse to the recommendations of the Select Committee (whichenvisaged an optional dual mandate) would depend on the electoralsystem used.    Since the essential feature of the compulsory dualmandate is that all UK members of the European Assembly would haveto be members of the House of Commons, the rules governingdisqualification of candidates for Westminster elections would beapplied without the modification (proposed by the Select Committee)that peers and all clergymen would be allowed to stand for election to the Assembly.    Depending on the electoral system adopted,appropriate arrangements would need to be made for fillingvacancies in the event of a member of the House of Commons, whowas also a member of the Assembly, losing his seat at Westminster.
DlHECT ELECTIONS:    ELECTOR A]- SYSTEMS IN THE OTHER MEMBER STATESBELGIUMThe Chamber of Representatives has 212 Members elected from 30constituencies which return between 3 and 32 seats in eachconstituency.    The political parties present lists of candidatesm each constituency (with separate lists jf substitutes to fillcasual vacancies).   The elector may vote either for the list or fora Particular candidate on that list.    The votes cast for aParticular candidate count as a vote for the list of which he is aMember.   List votes and candidates votes are added together in eachCQnstituency to find the total number of votes cast and the number&quot;Qf votes cast is divided by the number of seats in the constituencyto find the electoral devisor and each party&apos;s constituency total is then divided by this devisor to find the number of seats which it hasv&apos;Qn,   Votes for a list go to the candidates in the order their namesappear on the list, but personal votes go to the candidates concerned and niay result in lower candidates being elected over the heads ofthose above.The last election, held in 197h, returned three national partiesdivided into independent Flemish and Francophone wings), three(smaller) regionalist parties, a small splinter group and a smallGommUnist party.^UlgjLt Elections;    Discussion is continuing about the arrangements0r direct elections.    It seems likely that there will be some formof party list system but without the separate list for substitutes.DenmarkThe Folketimr is a single chamber Parliament with 179 seats,ehmurk uses a list system of considerable complexity.    The endSult is however simple.    Each party obtaining more than 2 per cent the total vote is represented in the Folketing in almost exact^portion to the votes it received at the election./135 of the
135 of the Folketing seats are divided between constituenciesaccording to the distribution of population.    These &quot;constituency&quot;seats will be filled in accordance with the number of votes receivedby each party in each constituency.    Parties present lists ineach constituency,    Electors may vote for a list or for an individualcandidate whose prospects of election are advanced by the size ofbis personal vote.    A further kO &quot;supplementary&quot; seats will be allotted in such a way as to give each party a total number of seatscorresponding to its share of the national vote provided this is atleast 2 per cent.    In addition, the Faroes and Greenland each have 2seats.Sj^lgjct Elections:     The Government are consulting the Folketing marketcommittee about the main features of a Bill which would provide forSections based on a list system, with the whole of Denmark forming0ne constituency and Greenland a separate constituency with one seat.^ &quot;the time of signature of the direct elections instrument the danish government obtained the concurrence of the Council of Ministers toWo reservations, to permit a compulsory dual mandate and thecoincidence    of European and their national elections.    No decision^as yet been taken on whether either or both of these reservationsShould apply.italy the Italian Chamber of Deputies consists of 630 members electedCm 32 constituencies with fixed boundaries which return from*Q 52 members depending on the population of the constituency at thedevious census.    Each party presents a &quot;list of candidates.   TheVo&quot;ter indicates his preference among parties by crossing out his^arty&apos;s symbol on the ballot paper.   He may also express a preference for UP to 3 candidates of the party he has chosen (or U if his constituency is electing 16 or more deputies).   He identifies theseGandidates by name or by their numbers on the party list.   The list^ es are added up to find each party&apos;s total vote in the constituency.ese totals are divided by the electoral quotient for the constituency&amp;nci seats allocated accordingly.    Remainders are transferred to a/national poolJ
national pool from which unassigned seats are distributed.    (A party has to elect at least one candidate in one constituency and pollat least 300,000 votes altogether to participate in this distribution.)The Italian Senate has 315 Members elected by regions,     The^gions elect from 1 to 1.8 senators depending on their population(though there is a bias in favour of the smaller regions).   TheMinimum age for voting for the senate is 25, as against 18 for theCamber, and the minimum age for candidates is UO, as against 25 forthe Chamber    The voting method, and remainder system, are similar^ those used for the Chamber.   In the Senate there are also 5 lifeMembers appointed by the President of the Republic, and formerResidents of the Republic (2 at present) are ex-officio life Members.Party allegience in Italy has been remarkably consistent overrne last 30 years with overall swings rarely exceeding 3.5 per cent^tU the regional and national elections of the last two years.There are currently 6 main parties having more than 10 seats in theChamber, 5 in the Senate, plus a few splinter groups.^ect Elections;    Discussion of the electoral arrangements is still at an early stage among the parties, although a ratification bill hasal*eady been passed in the Chamber of Deputies.    It appears, however,t0 be common ground that the country will be divided into constituenciesResponding to the present regions,  each with its own party lists^ electing a number of representatives depending on population orSi2e of electorate, and the electoral rules should be modelled months-ose for the Chamber.lljxemb0urgThe Chamber of Deputies consists of 59 Members elected by a systemQf Proportional representation.    For domestic elections the countryis divided into four constituencies each returning at present 6-2h^ers on the basis of one Member per 5,500 inhabitants.   lists ofCa^idateS cannot contain more names than there are seats in theC0^tituency.    He may vote for a list (in which case it counts as onevote * ,.j 4. ii*rH or he may cast his votese for each candidate on that list; 01 nc     j/individually
- k -individually giving up to two votes for the same candidate and, ifhe wishes, spreading his votes over more than one list.    All votes^e then added together to give a grand total for each list.    Seatsare awarded to lists    on the basis of these totals, and the numberof votes cast for each candidate determines which of them are thendeclared elected.    On resignation or death a deputy1s seat isautomatically awarded to the unsuccessful candidate on the same listwho polled the next highest   personal vote.   There are at presentfive political groups represented in the Luxembourg Chamber of Deputies.Parget Elections;    A working party of politicians and civil servantshas been established and the government will take its report intoconsideration when drafting enabling legislation.    The proportional^presentation system will be retained but the question of whether to divide Luxembourg&apos;s six members between two or more constituenciesQn to have a single national list remains to be decided.NETHERLANDSThe lower House contains 150 Members.    These are in effectelected from the whole country as one constituency, but there are]8 voting districts.    Any 25 electors within a voting district maynominate a list of candidates.   The voter selects one of the listsand marks one only of the candidates on it.    The votes cast forcandidates of the same party are added up to find the party&apos;s totalvalid vote.    Each party is allotted seats in proportion to its nationaltotal of votes on the basis of an electoral quota.    Candidates whoseVQtes equal or exceed the quota are elected.    Each candidate&apos;a surplusvotes over the quota are transferred to the next candidate on the sameiist.   unused votes from all lists are allocated in accordance with* complex formula to the parties which have obtained the most votesPen seat.    No party may participate in the share-out of seats unlessU has in its total vote reached the electoral quota-(ie the totalnumber of valid votes divided by the number of seats).   This lowthneshold (0.672 of the total vote) has resulted in a good many minorUnties being represented (the last elections held in 1972 produced^  gt. Elections:     The Bill to be presented to Parliament later in the/year
year is likely on present forecasts to provide for a list system basedon a single national constituency, similar to that used in nationalelections, but the country will not be divided up into voting districts and the threshold will be higher.
- 6 -THE FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF germany the Bundestag has 496 seats (not including therepresentatives of West Berlin who can vote only on proceduralissues).     After the war, elections were held in the american and French zones on the basis of proportional representation,Dut in the British zone a compromise was adopted between theProportional and the first-past-the-post system.   It is thismixed system which is now used throughout the Federal Republic.There are 248 single member constituencies and 248 furtherseats filled from lists put forward by the parties in the Individuallender.     The voter has two votes.   The first vote is cast foran individual candidate in a constituency (as in a Westminsterelection) and the second for a party list.     The 496 seats aredivided among the parties in proportion to the number of secondvotes they receive.    248 are filled by the candidates directly elected by the first vote, and the remainder of each party&apos;sentitlement filled from the lists.    (Occasionally a party winsttore constituency seats than its total entitlement, in which case it keeps its extra seats and the total number of seats inthe Bundestag is increased accordingly.)     Constituencycandidates are chosen by the Party organisations in the constituencies, or by groups of electors:    list nominations areaH made by the parties.   If the candidate wins both on a landparty district and an irdividual seat, he takes the individual seatand his name is removed from the party list.   The voter may splithis vote by voting for a candidate of a different party fromthe one whose list he favours.It is the second vote for the party list which decidesth-e composition in terms of parties of the Bundestag as a whole.in order to participate in the share-out of the 248 indirectlySeated seats, a party must first secure either,.at least 5 per cent0f the total second vote, or, what is in practice more difficult,three seats in the direct constituency   elections.   &apos;xhe FDP forStance, who won 39 seats in the 1976 elections, have not won aCo*stituency   seat on the first vote since 1961 but they haveal,&quot;ays qualified for representation by containing more than 5 per cent0f the total vote.    As a result of the 3 per cent .,/ threshold
threshold the large parties are slighly over represented.Since the 1957 election no party has obtained an overallma,priority of seats and government has been by coalition of twoof the three party groupings represented in the Bundestag.Direct Elections:    The parties are currently being consulted on a preliminary draft, which provides for elections011 the basis of Federal lists with a five per cent qualifyinghurdle.   There is no provision for individual constituency^Presentation.   A draft Bill will be introduced into the bundestag shortly.TH  REPUBLIC OP IRELANDThe Dail has 1A4 seats with 42 constituencies each with*&apos; 4 or 5 seats elected by single transferable vote.   Mostcandidates are selected by parties but there are always a numberQf independents.    To be elected a candidate has to reach a quota0 Pone vote more than a quarter of the total valid votes in athree-seat constituency, one more than one-fifth in a four - seatConstituency and one more than one-sixth in a five - seatConstituency (thisis known as the Droop formula).   The elector&quot;0tes by numbering in the order of his preference as many of^e candidates as he wishes.   The voter is thereby indicatingv,flere hi? &quot;support should go:if the candidate of his first choice has secured morethan enough votes for election, or^        in his first choice is eliminated during the count.The votes which would not be used to elect anyoneeither because he already has sufficient, or because he has been eliminated during the count are thenredistributed amongst other candidates in accordancewith the preferences expressed by the voters.   Whenthe surplus votes have been added or &quot;transferred&quot;to the remaining candidates&apos; original first preferencevotes, any candidate whose total vote (ie first preferencevote plus transferred votes) now exceeds the quota isdeclared elected and his surplus over the quota/re-examined
- 8 -re-examined for second or third preferences andtransferred to the relevant candidates.   proportional representation was first used in pre-partitionIreland in 1919 to encourage participation of the protestant minority. - There are at present three parties in the Dail plus three independents.Direct Elections:    The Irish Government have announcedthat the draft legislation under preparation will provide for election by the STV system based on four regional constituencies,and have published the boundaries of the four constituenciesproposed.france the National Assembly is elected on a two ballot systemfrotn single member constituencies, 473 in Metropolitan Franceand 17 overseas.   As in British elections, the voter votesdirectly for the candidate of his choice.   The votes cast inle first ballot are counted and if no candidate has securedan absolute majority over all his opponents those candidatesVvh-o received at least 12 1/2   per cent of the electoral rollre permitted to go forward to the second ballot one week later.ae second ballot is final and a candidate may be elected^ a simple or absolute majority,    -he French two ballot system,llce the British first-past-the-post system, can produce   alsProportion between votes and seats.The procedure for Presidential elections differs in twosPeots.     The second ballot takes place two weeks after thelrst:    and for that ballot, only the two leading candidatestake part.Direct Elections:    The French Foreign Minister has^licly stated that the Government will propose elections by0Portional representation on a national list system.
DIRECT ELECTIONS TO THE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLYLIST SYSTEMIntroduction1.     In essence, the list system of election is simple; but overthe years sophisticated variations have been developed in different countries.    The primary purpose of a list system is to ensure that-total seats won by a political party are proportionate to total -votes cast for that party.    The main variations in the systemrelate to the exactness of this proportionality and the extent tov&apos;hich an elector can vote for named candidates as well as (orinstead of) a political party.2.     One possibility is that the electoral area could be the wholeUnited Kingdom and the ballot paper could list only the political parties.    The votes for each party would be totalled nationally andthe 81 United Kingdom seats would be allocated to each partyaccording to a formula.    In principle, a party obtaining 25 per centQf the total votes cast should be allocated 25 per cent of the seats(either 20 or 21 seats depending on -the formula).    In this system,the individuals to take these seats would be drawn from the(published) list of candidates drawn up by the political party inthe order listed there.    Electors would have no direct say in thischoice.    Each political party could draw support from all parts ofthe United Kingdom; for example, supporters of the Scottish,Northern, Irish or Welsh Nationalist parties living in London couldvote for the nationalist party of their choice.^LjteRional List System3- A regional list system might be preferable to a national listAstern, and would allow some of the virtues of the simple majorityAstern to be retained.    Regional feeling and identification is a
recognisable factor in England, and many of the issues discussed inthe European Assembly have as much significance for a region in-&quot;gland as for European constituency.    With a regional list of candidates, individual candidates are more likely to be known tothe voter than with a national list.    There would also appear to beTiore scope for involving existing Westminster constituencyorganisations in the selection process.    The following paragraphsdeal only with a regional list system.Effect oral areas the United Kingdom would be divided into a number of electoralareas:    Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland would each constitute a separate area; England could be divided on the basis of existingeconomic planning regions, but the G.L.C. area might be separated from the South East planning region and East Anglia combined withbhe East Midlands.    The number of seats for each region would be allocated on the basis of electorate.    As an example the seats mightbe allocated under this system as follows -Region	SeatsScotland	8V/ales	4Northern Ireland	3South-East England (excluding Greater London)	14Greater London	10South-West England	6East Anglia and East Midlands	8West Midlands	north-West England	9Yorkshire and Humberside	7Northern England	5&quot;^lag Procedure5* The ballot paper in a regional list system might show the names^ alphabetical order) or individual candidates with their party
affiliations, if any.    This procedure would enable the elector toexpress preferences between individual candidates as well as betweenparties.    Individual identification of the votes with a particularcandidate is one of the strengths of the simple majority system that can be retained in a regional list system.   The ballot paper would contain more names than is usual at Parliamentary elections.In the North-West England region for example, with 9 seats, therettight be 3 parties putting forward 9 candidates each, with 3 other parties putting forward say 2 candidates each.    The ballot paper would thus contain 33 names.Candidates6.    The parties would have to develop procedures for selectingtheir candidates.    Some form of registration of political partiessight be necessary if the list system used party rather thanindividual candidate names.    Independent candidates could be permitted to stand for election provided that they had nominationsfrom the prescribed number of electors.^omiiiation and deposit  .?-     Suitable provision would be needed for nomination.    Therequirements might have to be more stringent than for parliamentarySections, especially if it were thought inappropriate to require a deposit on the grounds that candidates would sometimes be elected on the basis of the aggregate votes cast for members of their partyfather than the votes cast for,them personally.^Ld-term vacancies8-     It should normally be possible to fill vacancies, withoutElding by-elections, by allotting the seat to the candidate whosecured the next highest total of votes for his party in the region.no such candidate remained, then it might be sufficient to permit the party t0 wh0m the retiring member belongs to co-opt a successor.CostA list system would probably cost much the same to run as a*Ple majority system.    The main administrative costs in both would
relate to postage and to polling and. counting arrangements.Inf ormation10.   A lint system would be new to the United. Kingdom and therewould he need to be a reasonable period of time for the political parties, candidates and electors to learn about the workings of thenew system.    Information and training would also probably be needed for the local authority staffs who would be responsible for conducting the poll and the count.    This factor would have to betaken into account in the timetable for election.Counting and Allocation of Seats11.    Each elector rould have one vote which he would cast for anamed candidate.    The total votes cast for all the candidates ofeach party would be calculated, and the parties would be allowedseats in proportion to their total share of the poll.    Thus, in a4-seat region, a party gaining   of the total votes would be allocated 1 seat.    This scat would go to the named candidateof that party who had received the most individual votes.    It wouldbe necessary to devise a formula for allocating the odd seatsremaining after the first allocation; a number of different formulasare used in other countries.
ANNEX CSINGLE TRANSFERABLE VOTE (STY)introduction.     The single transferable vote (STV) system of proportional representation involves the use of multi-member constituencies.    In thissystem, account is taken not only of the voter&apos;s first choice of a candidate but also of his second and subsequent preferences.    The votermarks on his ballot paper his order of preference (1, 2, 3, etc) for allthe candidates named on the ballot paper.    By doing so, he is indicatingwhere his support should go if -either the candidate of his first choice has already secured enoughvotes for election,or his first choice is eliminated because he has secured too fewvotes to stand for any chance of election.2-     The STV system is used in the Republic of Ireland, AustraliaElections to fee Senate) and in local elections in Northern Ireland.Such matters as the exact means of calculating the electoral quota and procedure for redistributing surplus and other votes may vary according to the precise system selected.    Constituencies always returnat least three members. lectprai Areas3*     For European Assembly elections, Wales and Northern Ireland coulde*ch constitute a single constituency; Scotland would comprise one orfcv&apos;o.   ln England, the constituencies could be formed on the basis of theeconomic planning regions (although some modifications would probablyW to be made to the South East economic planning region, whoseelcctorate would entitled it to about 2A members).-^iog procedure as with our system of parliamentary elections, the ballot paperV&apos;0uld list candidates in alphabetical order (with their partyfiliations, if any).   The voter would then mark the names of theCa*candidates in his order of preference (i.e. 1, 2, 3, etc, for as many as he wishes, up to the limit of the number of names appearing0tl the ballot paper).J
5.     The arrangements for the selection of candidates would be similarto those under a simple majority system.    Independent candidates wouldbe permitted to stand provided that they were nominated by the prescribednumber of electors and could meet the necessary deposit.Nomination and deposit6.     Suitable provision would be needed for nomination and deposit.    Inthe Republic of Ireland, a candidate loses his deposit if he fails tosecure $ of the quota at any stage.    In the Northern Ireland assembly and Convention   elections, the deposit was lost if the candidate did not secure i of the quota at any stage.Mid-term vacancies7.     Vacancies arising between general elections may be filled in one ofthree ways.   The first involves a by-election using the STV system as described above.    The member thus elected is elected with an absolutemajority of votes.   Alternatively, the ballot papers cast at the generalelection for the retiring member may be re-examined and allocated tothe other candidates in accordance with the next available preferences ofthe voters.   Or the vacancy could be filled by co-option from the partyrepresented by the retiring member.cost. STV would probably cost much the same to run as a simple majoritysystem. The main administrative costs in both would relate to postageand to polling and counting arrangements.- Information9.     STV would be new to the UK outside Northern Ireland, and therewould need to be a reasonable period of time for the political parties,candidates and electors to learn about the workings of the new system.&apos;Information and training would also probably be needed for the localauthority staffs who would be responsible for conducting the poll andthe count.    This factor would have to be taken into account in the timetable for the election.
 gating and allocation of seats&apos;0.   The returning officer determines the number of valid firstPreference votes cast for each candidate.    An electoral quota is established by first dividing the number of valid ballot papers by thelumber of members to be elected plus one.    One is then added to produce the quota.    Anyone whose total of valid first preference votes exceeds the quota is declared elected.If vacancies remain, the number of votes by which an electedCandidate has exceeded the quota is transferred to the candidates whohave not yet been declared elected.    The transfer is made in accordanceV;ith the second or (if the candidate of the voter&apos;s next choice hasalready exceeded the quota) subsequent preferences shown on the ballot papers.    For this purpose all the ballot papers cast for a successfulcandidate are examined in order to determine the proportions in whichais surplus votes should be transferred to the as yet unelectedcandidates.cL%   If a transfer of surplus votes brings the total of votes cast forether candidates above the electoral quota, they in turn are declaredelected.    Their&quot; surplus votes are then, if vacancies remain, trans-*erred to the remaining candidates.    The transfer is made according tothe proportion of next preferences shown by the transferred ballot papers which brought them up to or over the quota (i.e.    the candidates10rlginal first preference votes are not taken into account).J&apos;   If, after all surpluses of successful candidates have beentransferred, there reamin vacancies but none of the remaining candidates. ^ Up to or over the quota, the candidate who at that stage has the-Qwest vote is eliminated.   His votes are transferred to the rerr*training^elected candidates in accordance with the next available preferencesshovjn.   Anyone who is brought up to or over the quota after theeliBiination of the lowest candidate is declared elected and his surplus,ifany, is transferred as described in paragraph 11 above.    If no-one is&quot;^cught up to the quota, the candidate with the next lowest total ofQtes is excluded and his votes transferred.    The process of trans-rring surpluses or eliminating the lowest candidate as appropriate Is^tinned until all the vacant seats are filled.
14.   Recounts may be demanded of each stage of the count as described in the preceding paragraphs.    The request for a recount must be madealter the completion of the stage whose recount is demanded but beforethe commencement of the next stage.   No recount is permitted of thecount as a whole in Northern Ireland elections.15.   The actual mechanics of the STV count are similar to those used ina U.K. parliamentary election:    votes are sorted according to thevoters&apos; preferences and the preferences thus sorted are counted.    But&quot;this sorting and counting takes place several times during theProceedings rather than just once (or twice or more if there arerecounts).
ANNEX DA compulsory dual niandateIntroductionA compulsory dual mandate can in principle be operated with anyelectoral system.    It would mean that membership of the House ofCommons would be an essential condition for membership of theEuropean Assembly.AdvantagesA compulsory dual mandate would ensure that United Kingdom Assemblymembers had as their primary base their position at Westminster andin their Westminster constituencies; it would minimise the risk ofdivergences between Assembly members and other Westminster members ofthe same party; and it would discourage the development in britain of European parties with federalist aims which might undermine theposition of our national parties.DisadvantagesA compulsory dual mandate would impose considerable strain on Assemblymembers.   They would be less able to play their full roles at westminster and in the Assembly than other members of either body,particularly if they represented remote constituencies.   SinceWestminster elections and Assembly elections would not normally coincideproblems would arise when MPs lost their seats at Westminster and were thus disqualified from membership of the Assembly.Practical considerationsApart from possible changes in the arrangement of parliamentary business^changes in voting arrangements would be needed.   one possibility would be to introduce proxy voting.   At Westminster thiswould involve formal recognition that Assembly members&apos; votes were bein
cast, without their having participated in debates and would disturblong established conventions.    It might be a less significant innovation in anewly elected Assembly although other member States which were not operatinga compulsory dual mandate might not feel the need for such a procedure.   Analternative possibility would be automatic pairing at Westminster of Assemblymembers.general a dual mandate combined with pur traditional electoral system would requirecandidates from the House of Commons to stand for each of the 81 seats.   this might be difficult especially for the party forming the Government which alsoftas to provide Ministers.   Under a system of multi-member consituencies there&apos;tVould be greater flexibility in finding sufficient candidates to fill the 81Seats.   Assembly members who lost their Westminster seats would be disqualifiedand would need to be replaced by selection from a list or by holding by-elections,depending on the choice of electoral system.   Both Assembly and nationalelections would be likely to result in significant changes in United kingdom representation in the Assembly.


</content>
</cab>
