<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/46/0 images: 6-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SEP(67) 8th Meeting, Item 1MONDAY, 26th JUNE, 1967Economic Outlook to 1972(SEP(67) 41)NO CIRCULATION RECORDThis note records part of the discussion on the above item whichis not referred to in the minutes of the meeting.THE LORD PRESIDENT said that, if the maximum growth rate which was consistent with stability in the balance of payments was theaverage of 3j per cent per annum postulated in the report by the medium Term Assessment Committee annexed to SEP(67) 41, theGovernment could not escape the dilemma of being compelled either to restrict personal consumption to a degree which would be unacceptableor to reduce expenditure on social services in a way which would be inconsistent with the Governments philosophy and with their politicalcommitments.    The only way of escaping from this dilemma was tosecure a higher growth rate.    This meant that we must devise policies to secure an increase in exports and a reduction in imports.    There wasno sign that existing policies were likely to achieve this; and we should therefore re-examine the desirability of more drastic changes in policy.He was not arguing that a change in the parity of the pound wasnecessarily the right solution;  he was only suggesting that a thorough examination of this question was desirable before economic strategy forthe medium-term was settled.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE said he did notbelieve that devaluation would solve the problem.    Nevertheless, he agreed with the Lord President that existing policies seemed unlikely to ensure satisfactory economic progress: it seemed more probablethat they would compel us to run the economy at a level of demand whichwould entail under-use of resources, high unemployment and low investment.Some new departure in policy might therefore be needed;  and quantitativerestriction of imports was a possibility.    He did not advocate that thisshould necessarily be considered now; but it should be re-examined before long unless some evidence was forthcoming that existing policies would lead to a more acceptable economic prospect than at present seemed likely.In discussion, it was pointed out that the Cabinet had discussed thequestion of parity as recently as the meeting at Chequers on 30th April.No useful purpose would be served by reverting to this issue, particularlyin view of the risks which could arise if it were reopened and this became known.    There were no conclusive grounds for thinking that devaluationwould make possible a higher growth rate and hence a more rapid increasein personal consumption and public expenditure.    Moreover, devaluationcould only achieve the desired effects on. the balance of payments if it were accompanied by a considerable measure of deflation, including highertaxation.    It would therefore entail a real reduction in the standard of living,which would be resented by public opinion.    The extent of the benefit to our exports which might accrue from devaluation was problematic, since manyexporters might simply absorb the increased profits instead of reducingprices and expanding sales abroad.-1-
A recent poll of informed opinion showed that, while a majorityof economists were in favour of a change in parity, the greater number ofbankers and industrialists were equally opposed to it.     So were the general public, on grounds that it was domestically painful to devalue the currency:even if the issue was imperfectly understood, the conclusions reached inthat respect were sound enough.    In any case, a decision to change theparity could only be taken in the light of international considerations, in circumstances in which the credibility of the Governments action wouldbe accepted, and not simply on the grounds of thestate of the domesticeconomy.28th June, 1967

</content>
</cab>
