<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/46/0 images: 115-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TOP SECRET -   Iv t (LCC(67) 5Sarf ConclusionsThursday, 20th JulyThis note records a discussion which took place after theconclusion of the Cabinet&apos;s main business and is not recorded in thecirculated Conclusions.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that some 70 ofthe Governments supporters in the House of Commons had signed amanifesto, which had been published that day, proposing in effect adevaluation of sterling.    This could have serious repercussions on international confidence in the parity;  and it was therefore essentialthat the Government themselves should not be thought to be associatedin anyway with the signatories of the manifesto.     Otherwise, devaluationmight become inevitable;  and a decision which, if it were ever taken,should be an act of considered and deliberate policy would be forced onthe Government at a time and in circumstances which might be whollyinappropriate.    He himself did not accept that devaluation representedany solution to our present economic difficulties;  and he was not preparedto be a party to it.    Moreover, whatever views his colleagues mightprivately hold on the possible merits of devaluation, it was essential,if the Government were to retain their freedom of decision, that theyshould consistently maintain in public that the Government were resolved to maintain the present parity.In discussion there was general agreement that Ministers should follow the course indicated by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and should ensure that their junior Ministers and Parliamentary Private Secretariesdid likewise.    At the same time, Ministers should avoid inflating theimportance of the manifesto which had been published that day.    It mustbe deemed to have been prompted largely by apprehensions on the partof the Governments supporters that the current review of public expenditure would result in drastic reductions in expenditure on the social services;  and it would therefore help to reduce the chances of furtherdamaging statements on devaluation if an early opportunity could be foundto allay these apprehensions.     It would also be particularly important to seek to steady opinion on the question of devaluation during the forthcoming debate on the economic situation;  and^since this debate would be founded on an Opposition Motion of &quot;no confidence&quot;/arrangements should be madeto remind the Governments supporters of their overriding duty in such circumstances.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said theChancellor of the Exchequer was clearly right to take a robust line inaffirming that the Government were resolved to maintain the existingparity of sterling.    It was essential that all Ministers should followthis lead and should ensure that their junior Ministers did likewise.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinisters summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1.20th July, 1967

</content>
</cab>
