<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/1/31 images: 516-527</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
l-fsH flOCOMBHT IS THai jfMurJSMTx;.yjr HIS,BRITANNIC&apos; raiidisSxrs BOyERNMBNT     Sj^nTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document..P.  (59) 51.COPY NO. .WAR CABINET.SUPPLY OF ARMAMENTS TO POLAND.Note by the Secretary.By direction of the Prime Minister, I circulate herewith for consideration by the War Cabinet, theattached Report by the Deputy Chiefs of Staff Sub-committee dealing with the Supply of Armaments to Poland(Paper No. D.C.O. S*   (59) 16),(Signed)    E.E.  BRIDGES.Secretary.Richmond Terrace, S. W. I.,15th September, 1939.

gnu-- r ----- -OCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT--TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AMD KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.2Ki1-(59)16.COPY NO.WAR CABINET,DEPUTY CHIEFS OF STAFF SUB-COMMITTEEOT^HfTCHIEFS OF STAFF COMMITTEE.SUPPLY OF ARMAMENTS TO POLAND.REPORTuAt the Meeting of the War- Cabinet36  on 15th Septemberit was suggested that there was little hope of Poland being able to hold even a strip of their country guarding the PolishRoumanian Frontier,  and therefore, that it was futile tocontinue to despatch war stores to here      On the other hand,it was pointed out that if the Poles did manage to holdout in this corner of their country, the psychological effect of stopping war consignments (for some of which she has already paid) would be deplorable.2. It was accordingly agreed that, as a matter of urgency:-&quot;The Deputy Chiefs of Staff should consider,inconsultation with the Foreign Office, what action should be taken as regards variousconsignments of war stores which are already on their way - or about to be despatched - to poland.&quot;In pursuance of this wo submit the following report.Nature and P re sent JPqsition^OfJar Stores en route to,or about to be&apos; despatched t&apos;o, Polando3* The present position is as follows:-(a)  s.s. LASSELLPresent Position.    Now in the Mediterranean,and is due to reach Istanbul at 0700 hours on the19th September^* (War Cabinet (39) I6th Meeting).

15 Modern Fighters, including14 &quot;Hurricanes&quot; and1 &quot;Spitfire&quot;,7 &quot;Battles&quot; (Bomber aircraft).6,000 tons of bombs.2f million rounds of ammunition.150 Parachutes.112 Browning Machine Guns (for Fighter aircraft).Mechanical transport - including 9 Prime Moversand 21 Trailers.(b) s.s.  CL.A1:::&apos;   MENZIES-Present Position.   Now loading at Ellesmere port and due to sail on Sunday, 17th September.Cargo.15 &quot;Battles&quot;5,000 Hotchkiss Machine Guns.15 million rounds of small arm ammunitionSome ammunition in Turkey.Detecting Inst ruments *500,000 Civilian gas masks.(c) s.s. ROBUR   VIII..Present Position.    On her way from Methil, Firthof Forth to Mersey where she is due to arrive onMonday, 18th September.     After loading,  she willbe ready to sail - at earliest - on Wednesday 20thSeptember.Cargo.14 &quot;Battles&quot;.Such overflow of stores, other than aircraft,as cannot be shipped by the s.s.   Clan  fvlenzies.

Possibilities of diversion.4.     It will be seen that none of the consignments forPoland has yet left this country, with the exception ofthose now in the S.S. Lassell and that the latter is not due to reach Istanbul until the morning of the 19thSeptember.      It is, therefore, clear that it will bepossible, if desired, to stop or divert all or any of theconsignments destined for Poland before they reachIstanbul or Constanza.5.     The decision to do this should, we suggest, betaken ad hoc in each case on its merits by the Chiefs ofStaff in the light of the situation in Poland;,    asfollows?&quot;S.S. Lassell on the 18th September.S.S. Clan Menzies.     The position to be reviewedon the 26th September.S.S. Robur VIII. The position to be reviewed onthe 28th September.6.      In deciding, if they do, that these consignmentsshould be diverted, the Chiefs of Staff will, at thesame, time, have to consider the destinations to whichthey will have to be sent instead. In considering.this pointwe propose that the Chiefs of Staff should again judgeeach case on its merits, taking into account theinternational situation at the time, the position of theship, and the nature of the consignment which shecarriesi    and we tentatively suggest alternatives in thefollowing order of priority:-(i)    failing Poland consignments should go to Turkey(ii)    failing Turkey &quot; &quot;       &quot;    &quot; Greece(iii)    failing Greece &quot; &quot;       &quot;    &quot; Rumaniaor Egypt*

Aircraft to be Flown to Poland.7.      In addition to the stores which are being, or are due to be5 sent to Poland by sea, we would draw attentionto a proposal which is on foot that twenty &quot;Battles&quot; shouldhe flosnfron. this country to France with a view to their being taken delivery of in that country by Polish pilotswho will then fly them direct to Poland.,8.     We suggest that the Chiefs of Staff should beinformed by the Air Ministry as seon as information is received that the Polish pilots are on -choir way to takedelivery of thir;* aircraft,  so that they way,,then decide whether the situation is such.as Cojustify the release of these aircraft to Poland.Consignments &quot;jto Rumania -9, Although we have not been specifically asked toconsider the question of war stores now on order forRumania, we would draw attention to the fact thatS.S. Bardale begins loading at Birkenhead, to-morrowmorning, the 16th September, with the following storesdestined for Rumania12 &quot;Hurricanes&quot;,470 tons of bombs,  detonators,  and small-arm aiiimuni t ion *350 tons of aircraft s/pare parts.,She will be ready to sail on the 18th September.10.    We recommend that the position of this consignmentshould he similarly reviewed by the Chiefs of Staff on the27th September,(Signed)      R.F. ADAMR.E.O. PEIRSE.DUNDAS.(for D.CJ.S.)Note:      The Deputy Chiefs of Staff have not had anopportunity of seeing this Report in its final form.     They have authorised their signatures tobe appended subject to any amendments which theymay wish to make,Terrace, S.W.1.September,  1939.. -4-




</content>
</cab>
