<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/279/0 images: 212-227</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fllS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) C R E T.[\ 222     (58). COPY NO. Ac*PCABINET. GERMAN AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY. Memorandum &quot;by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Committee of Imperial Defence at their 333rd Meeting held on 6th October, 1938, had under consideration a note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Industrial Intelligence in Foreign Countries,  covering a Memorandum prepared in collaboration bstween the Air Ministry and the Department of Overseas Trade,  on the German aircraft industry (C.I.D. Paper No. 1472-B).2. The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed %-&quot;(a)    that the Memorandum on the German aircraft industry (C.I.D. Paper No. 1472-B), together with the above minutes, should be remitted to the Cabinet, concurrently with the Memorandum&quot;1&quot;now being prepared in the Air Ministry on the relative air strengths, existing and prospective, of this country and certain other Powers, and on the measures recommended to improve our own position.(b)    that, in forwarding the Memorandum on theGerman aircraft industry, the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence should draw the attention of the Cabinet to the view of the Committee of Imperial Defence that this country could not be regarded as safe until the Royal Air Force and the anti-aircraft defences had been increased, and our passive defence arrangements had been substantially improved&quot;.3. ,I accordingly circulate herewith, for the information of my colleagues, a copy of the Memorandum (Enclosure No. l)&quot;^^/C.P. 818(38)7 -1-
and the relevant extract from the Minutes of the 333rd Meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence (Enclosure No.4.      In this connection, I would draw the attention of my colleagues to my memorandum on measures to accelerate defence preparationsv   (CP. 219(38)).(Intd.)    T. 17. II, I.richmond Terrace, S. W. 1., 14th October, 1938.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   September 1938. SECRET. * &apos;     Copy NIk   148COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.GERMAN AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY. (Previous C.I.D. Paper No. 1407-B.)Note by the Secretary.THE accompanying Note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Industrial Intelligence in Foreign Countries, covering a memorandum on the German Aircraft Industry, which has been prepared in collaboration between the Air Ministry (Intelligence) and the Department of Overseas Trade (Industrial Intelligence Centre), is circulated to the Committee of Imperial Defence by direction of the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.2. This memorandum, which is in continuation of C.I.D. Paper No. 1407-B, brings the position up to date on the 22nd August, 1938.(Signed)      H. L. ISMAY.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1, September 19, 1938.ANNEX.Note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Industrial Intelligence in ForeignCountries.THE accompanying memorandum on the German Aircraft Industry which has been prepared in collaboration between the Air Ministry (Intelligence) and the Department of Overseas Trade (Industrial Intelligence Centre), and is based on information available up to the 22nd August, 1938, is submitted to the Committee of Imperial Defence for information.4 (Signed)      T. St. QUINTIN HILL,Chairman.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1, September 15, 1938.[17908]b
[F.C.I. 123.][I.C.F./148, dated 22.8.38.]ENCLOSURE  TO ANNEX.German Aircraft Industry.Memorandum prepared in collaboration between the Air Ministry (Intelligence) and the Department of Overseas Trade (Industrial Intelligence Centre).1, Estimated Output in June 1938 compared with January 1938.Our last report estimated the rate of output of the German aircraft industry at the end of December 1937 at:  About    500   air-frames per month. .  About 1,010   aero-engines per month.On the basis of the information received during the last seven months, the tables of output of the twenty-eight factories in Germany producing complete aircraft and the fifteen factories producing aero-engines have been brought up to date as at the 1st July, 1938, and are attached as Appendices I and II. From these it appears that the rate of output at the end of June 1938 may be estimated at: About    595 air-frames per month. About 1,210 aero-engines per month.Of this total, military types (including trainers) appear to comprise about 550 and purely civil types about 45.Attached as Appendix III is a graph illustrating the progress of the output of the German aircraft industry since this series of reports first appeared in 1933.2. Labour Employed.Our last report estimated the number of hands employed on production in the aircraft industry on the 1st January, 1938, at:  On air-frames   ...      ...       ...      ...   about 62,950On aero-engines...      ...       ...      ...   about 26,050Total    .........   about 89,000In the intervening period some information has been received which fills gaps in our knowledge of the labour employed at a number of factories. Our present estimates as at the 1st July, 1938, which are therefore more complete and, it is believed, more accurate than any given before, are :  On air-frames.............   about 103,750On aero-engines        ...       ...      ...   about   29,000Total    .........   about 132,7503. Increase in Output.To some extent the increase over the last estimate of air-frame production is a statistical one, since, as explained at the time, the last estimate did not include, owing to insufficient information, the output of two important new factories, which were believed to be already delivering complete aircraft of military type. The estimated output of these factories is, however, included in the present figure.There has, none the less, been a genuine increase in output during the six months under review. A number of old-established factories have increased their output, and a number of new ones have been able to show some production for the first time.Several assembly factories which have come into production during the. last six months have not yet reached full production, and we may expect to see in consequence a still further increase in output during the second half of the year.
4. Reorganisation of the Industry.A scheme has now been put into force in Germany by which the number of firms permitted to design military types was restricted, all other firms being allocated as sub-contractors to one or other of the designing firms, limited to seven* in number. Each of these controls one or more &quot;constellations&quot; of factories, organised on sinrilar lines, comprising a central design and adminis-trative office, various sub-factories for the production of major components, sub-contractors for minor components, a central assembly factory and aerodrome and a school for the training of mechanics.This arrangement appears to be resulting, as it was presumably intended to do, first in increased output and, secondly, in a reduction in the number of types manufactured. The two principal bomber types now in production are, for example, being turned out complete by no less than ten different factories. Even Junkers and Dornier are manufacturing a type designed by Ffeinkel.5. Effect of the Anschluss.German intentions regarding the four or five small factories comprising the aircraft industry in the Ostmark are not yet known, but it is probable that for the time being they will all be confined to the manufacture of components, and will have little effect on the total output of the Reich.6. Government Ownership of the Aircraft Industry.Although formal nationalisation of the aircraft industry does not seem to be part of present policy, the Government seems, in fact, to be acquiring a progressively greater control over it. The capital of only two major firms is now reported to be privately-owned, that of the remaining firms being Govern-ment-owned. New factories seem for the most part to be erected with Govern-ment capital, and are merely managed and operated by the company to whom they nominally belong. The degree of control which the Government is able to exercise is seen from the enforcement of the arrangement mentioned in paragraph 4 above.7. Conclusions.From the above it may be concluded that: (a) The approximate rate of output at the beginning of July 1938 was : 595 air-frames per month, 1,210 aero-engines per month,of which about 550 were of military types, including trainers, and on the production of which about 132,750 hands were employed, this figure probably including designing staffs and some proportion of apprentices.(6) Since certain new assembly factories have not yet come into full produc-tion, a further increase in output is to be expected in the course of the next six months. The former Austrian aircraft industry is, however, unlikely to make much contribution to the total output for some time.(c) The most important factor affecting output since our last report has been a scheme for the organisation of the industry, restricting design to seven firms only, all others being allocated to one or other of them as sub-contractors. This measure seems to be resulting in an increased output and a reduction in the number of types produced.* Viz., Junkers, Dornier, B.F.W., Arado, Heinkel, Focke-Wulf and Henschel. These, with the addition of Blohm und Voss, will also design all civil types.[17908]
APPENDIX I.Principal German Aircraft Factories.Name of Firm.	Location of Factory.	Estimated Personnel July 1,1938.	Product.	Estimated Monthly Rate of Output July 1, 1938.	Remarks.Ago    Flugzeugwei-ke,    formerly Apparatebau G.m.b.H. (sub-sidiary of Ludwig Loewe A.G. of Berlin)	Oschersleben     a.d. Bode	2,000	B.F.W. single-seater fighters; own light twin-engined passenger type (Ao. 192)	15 (Bf. 109).......	May be undertaking manufacture of com-components of Bf. 110.Allgemeine Transport Anlage Ges.-Assembly Factory.........	Leipzig-Mockau   ...	5,000	Assembly of Heinkel bomber type      ......	25 (He. 111).	Arado Flugzeugwerke G.m.b.H.  Parent Works     ...... Subsidiary Factory       ...     i.. Subsidiary Factory       ...... Subsidiary Factory       ....., i Subsidiary Factory       ......	Brandenburg    a.d. Havel Babelsberg (ex Nowawes) near Berlin Rathenow   ...... Anklam Wittenberg......	4,000 800 ? 1,500 1,600	Design and construction of own type trainer and reconnaissance types (sea and land planes).   B.F.W. fighter type Components for parent works ?......... No information.   Believed still under con-struction Components for BrandeDburg factory...... Components (fuselages and centre sections) of Heinkel (He. Ill) and Arado (Ar. 95) types	10 (Ar. 95). 15 trainers. 10 (Bf. 109).	Baehmann Flugzeugwerke......	Ribnitz	250	Repairs and components of Heinkel aircraft ...	...	Factory is leased from Heinkel-Werke, by whom it was built.Bayerisclie Flugzeugwerke  A.G. (Messerschmitt)  Parent Factory    ......	Augsburg   ......	4,000	Own civil and fighter types.........	10 (Bf. 108). 15 (Bf. 109). 10 (Bf. 110).	Subsidiary, Factory (Bayerisclie Flugzeugwerke    Regenshurg G.m.b.H.)	Regensburg......	1,500	Believed intended  for production of own fighter type (Bf. 110)	Negligible......	A new factory believed coming into full production in the near future.
Blohm und Voss, Abteilung Flug-zeugbau  Parent Works (ex  Hamburger Reisniiihlen A.G.)Subsidiary Factory     *-...Assembly Factory......Subsidiary FactoryBucket&apos; Flugzeugbau G.m.b.H.Dornier Metallbauten G.m.b.H.-Parent Works      ......Subsidiary FactorySubsidiary FactorySubsidiary Factory Assembly Factory...Subsidiary Factory Assembly Factory...Subsidiary    Factory   (Leicht-metallbau G.m.b.H.) Assembly Factory......Subsidiary    Factory   (Leicht-metallbau-Lubeck)Erla MascliinenwerkErnst Heinkel-Flugzeugwerke-Assembly Works......Subsidiary FactorySubsidiary Factory Subsidiary FactoryHamburg    (Worth-damm)Hamburg (Osthalle, Blohm und Voss yard)Wenzendorf...      ...Finken warderBerlin-liangsdorf ..Maiizell,        near FriedriclishafeuLowenthal.....Rickenbach,    nearLindau Pfronten-Weissbach Allmansweiler, nearFriedricjishaienRavensburg......Oberpf affenhofen,near       Aubing,Munich Neuaubing,     nearMunich Wismar      .....LiibeckLeipzig-Hei terbl ick (3 factories)Marieuehe,     nearRostock Rostock   (Bleicher-str.)Rostock (Wcrftstr.) Rostock      (Horst-wesselstr.)6001,000700 Nil1,0004,000Included abovo 300 ?1,000500150 2,5003001,0006,000Included aboveIncluded above Included aboveAssembly of own multi-engined civil types. Components and assembly of major com-components of Dornier bomber type for Wenzendorf factoryAir-frame components    ............Storage and assembly of components supplied by Hamburg factories See Remarks       ............Own type single-engined trainersAssembly of own type seaplanes and flying boats; experimental and development work on all typesWings for Manzell and Allmansweiler fac-toriesComponents, light metal sheet........,Undercarriages    ..............Construction and assembly of own type land planes UndercarriagesAssembly of twin-engined bombers    ...Components for Oberpfaffenhofen factoryAssembly of Heinkel type twin-engined bombers. Conversion of Do. 23 to twin-engined trainersFuselages for Wismar factory   ...      .....B.F.W. fighter type.   Light civil aircraft of own typeAssembly of military and civil types of own designMetal work and metal components of aircraftWoodwork and wings for assembly works Light construction and fitting........2 (Ha. 139, 140, 142)15 (Do. 17).15 (&quot; Jungmann &quot; and &quot;Jung-meister &quot;).12 (Do. 18, 24, 26, 28).10 (Do. 17)5 (Do. 17).16 (He. 111)...5 (Bf. 109). 6 (E. 5).32 (He. 112,270,116).Owued  by   well-known   shipbuilding   firm, Blohm und Voss.Under construction.    May be intended for assembly.May be preparing for production in series of new dive bomber (Do. 19).Appears to be supplied by two separate com-ponent factories in Wismar.
Name of Firm.    *&quot;	Location of Factory.	Estimated Personnel July I, 1938.	Product.	Estimated Monthly Rate of Output July 1, 1938.	Remarks.Ernst   Heinkel    Flugzeugwerke (contd.)  Subsidiary Factory      ......	Berlin - Reinicken-dorf Oranienburg - Anna-hof (2 factories) Warnemiinde       ...	300	Seaplane floats     ...............		Assembly   Factory   (Heinkel-Werke G.m.b.H.) Assembly Factory   (ex Arado Flugzeugwerke) Subsidiary   Factory   (part   of &quot;Neptun&quot; Sehiflswerft)		7,000 4,000	Construction and assembly of raulti-engined bombers Assembly of seaplanes    ...........	30 (He. 111). 15 (He. 114).		Rostock     ......	j	Wing construction for Wamemunde factory ...		Fieseler Flugzeugbau G.m.b.H. ...	Kassel-Bettenhausen (3 factories)	4,000	Own type communication and training aircraft and B.F.W. fighter type	25 (F. 156, 97). 20 (Bf. 109).	Flugzeugbau Klemtn Focke-Wulf   Flugz-eugbau G.m.b.H.-Parent Works     ......... Subsidiary Factory       ...... Subsidiary Factory (ex Albatros Werke)	Sindelflngen   (Bob-lingen) Bremen (3 factories) Bremen-Hastedt   ... Berlin- Johannisthal	500 5,000 Included above 800	Light aircraft      ...      ............ Design and construction of own type single and twin-engined trainer aircraft and uiulti-engined passenger monoplane. B.F.W. fighter type Major components for assembly at Bremen  ... Repair and overhaul only        .........	10. 2 (&quot;Condor&quot;) 25 (Fw. 44, 56, 58) 10 (Bf. 109) Nil.	Believed doing experimental work on the new fighter and bomber types.Gothaer Waggonfabrik A.G. (sub-\   sidiary    of    Orenstein    vind Koppel A.G. of Berlin)-Parent Works     ...... Assembly Factory (Bayeriscne Waggon-u. Flugzeugwerke) Subsidiary Factory (Gotha -Ilnienauer Flugzeugbau G.m.b.H.)	Gotha        ...... Furth        ...... lmenau     ......	2,500 1,000 1	Assembly of B.F.W. fighter type, own type single and twin-engined trainers and Focke-Wulf trainers Assembly of own type trainers......... Components for Gotha and/or Furth factories	10 trainers (Go. 145, 146, 149, Fw. 58) 15 (Bf. 110) 8 trainers.	Aircraft section of railway engineering shops.Henschel   Flugzeugwerke   A.G. (subsidiary of Henschel und Sohn G.m.b.H. of Kassel)  Parent Works     ......... Subsidiary Factory       ......	Schonefeld ... Berlin-Johannisthal	6,000 1,500	Reported as making all jigs for the. aircraft industry.   Dornier type bomber aircraft Development and repair work. Production of own type reconnaissance aircraft	35 (Do. 17). 10 ,(Hs. 126)......	May be preparing for manufacture of Hs, 124
Junkers Plugzeug- und Motoren-werke A.G. (see also Appendix II)-Parent Works      ......... &quot; Deutsche Eeiohsbahn Anlage &quot; Branch                 -c-	Dessau...... South end of Dessau	10,000 Included above	Design, development, repair and modification of all types of civil and service aircraft. Assembly of own multi-engined types. Also aero-engines (see Appendix II) Components for Junker aircraft and engines...	50(Ju.52, 86, 87,88. 90)	Makes complete aircraft and assembles from large sections and components made else-where.Assembly Factory......... Subsidiary Factory       ...... Assembly Factory......... Subsidiary Factory       ...... Subsidiary Faotory       ...... Repair Factory.........	Aschersleben Halberstadt...... Bernburg   ...... Leopoldshall Ochzensoll,      near Hamburg. Leipzig-Mockau   ...	5,000 5,000 1,500 ? 250 y	Assembly of Heinkel multi-engined bomber ... Major components for assembly at Aschersle-ben factory Believed intended for assembly of Heinkel multi-engined bomber Major components for Aschersleben and Bern-burg factories Believed intended for assembly of Junkers types seaplanes (Ju. 34) Repairs     ......     ......     ......	15 (He. 111). 5 (He. Ill)...... Nil    ..	Factory is not yet in full production. t A new factory not yet in production.Miag (Miihlen Industrie A.G.)   ...	Dresden   (Werk Sporbitz)	500	? Components of B.F.W. lighter type......	...	Aircraft section of the Dresden branch of this engineering firm, whose main works are at Brunswick.   May be preparing to manu-faeture a B.F.W. type (Bf. 110) complete.Siebel Flugzeugwerke Halle K.G. (formerly Flugzeugwerk Halle G.m.b.H.)	Halle...   &apos;......	1,500	Own type 2-engined passenger monoplane. Dornier type bomber aircraft	2 (Fh. 104). 8 (Do. 17).	Weser Flugzeugbau G.m.b.H. (ex Rohrbach   Metallflugzeugbau G.m.b.H.)-Parent Works     ......	Bremen (Industrie-hafen)	5,000	Components and assembly of major components for Einswarden and Deichshausen-Lemwerder factories	-	Company was promoted by shipbuilding firm of   Deschimag,   owners   of  A.G.   Weser yard.\  Subsidiary Factory       ..... Subsidiary Factory       ..... Subsidiary Factory (ex Deutsche Linoleumwerke)	. Einswarden ... . Deichshausen-Lemwerder Delmonhorst	1,500 1,000 1	Assembly of Junkers and Dornier types sea-planes and repair work Assembly of Junkers types land planes and repair work Components, including tail units       .....	30(Ju.34)..... 12 (Do. 18) 30 (Do. 34).	ex Frerichswerit shipyard. May be closing down.
Name of Firm.Location of Factory.Argus Motoren G.m.b.H. ..Bayerische Motorenwerke A.G. ...Engine Works (B.M.W. Flug-motorenbau G.m.b.H. Engine Factory (Flugmotoren-fabrik Eisenach G.m.b.H. (for-merly Dixi Werke)\Brandenburgisehe   Motorenwerke G.m.b.H.      (subsidiary     of Siemens und Halske) Engine Works (Flumowerke) Subsidiary Factory       ......Daimler Benz A.G. ... Engine WorksSubsidiary Factory       ....... Engine Works.........Development Works     ......HenschelFlugmotorenbau G-m.b.H. (subsidiary of Henschel und Sohn G.m.b.H.) Engine Works     .........Hirth Motoren G.m.b.H  Engine Works     ...     ......Development Works (Hirth Motor-enbau Waltersdorf G.m.b.H.)Berlin dorfMunichReinicken-Eisenaeli   (2   fac-tories)Spandau BasdorfBerlin-MarienfeldeMannheim.....Genshagen,      nearLudwigsfolde Stuttgart - Unter-tiirkheimKassel-AltenbaunaStuttgart - Zuffen-hausen Waltersdorf, Berlin-TeltowAPPENDIX II.Principal German Aero-Engine Factories.Estimated Personnel July 1, 1938.	Product (Aero-Engines only).	Estimated Monthly Rate of Output July 1, 1938.	---1--- Remarks.2,500	Aero-engines of 150 h.p. to 250 h.p.   ...	60	Well-known motor engine works.	...		Firm also makes motor cycles and automobile parts4,500	Air-cooled engines of 500 h.p. and over	200	2,500	Air-cooled engines only............	200	Owned by well-known machine and tool manu-facturers.2,500	Radial air-cooled engines of 100 to 900 h.p. ... Under construction       ............	100 Nil	2,500 500 2,000	DB. 600 and 601 aero-engines  ...... Diesel airship engines    ......     ...... DB. 600 and 601 aero-engines   ...	120 Negligible. 100	Well-known motor car manufacturers. Believed not yet in full production.?	Components of aero-engines.    Development work	Nil.	Aero-engine development section of a large automobile factory. Owned by the well-known locomotive builders. (See also Appendix I.)750	Factory under   construction,  intended for Daimler Benz aero-engines	20	Some aero-engine work going on at Kassel-Mittelfeld pending completion of new factory.700	Aero-engines from 80 to 240 h.p.	25	Specialises in built-up crankshafts.1,000	Development work on  engines of larger capacity	25	A new factory which is believed to have recently begun production.
Humbolclt Deutz Mntorcn G.ra.b.H. Junkers Plugzeug und Motoren-i i       werke A.G. (see also Appen-M      dix I)-(2   Engine Works     ......... O    Development Works IS Engine Works     ......... Subsidiary Factory       ...... Subsidiary Factory       ...... Mitteldeutsche      Motorenwerke A.G.   (subsidiary   of   Auto Union A.G.) Engine Works    .........	Hamburg    ......	250	Believed going into production of aoro-engines, probably under licence	Nil	Branch of the well-known motor car manu-facturers.   Factory not yet producing.	Kfithen      ...... Dessau Magdeburg...... Schonebeck ...... Allach, near Munich Tauclia, near Leipzig	3,000 1,100 2,500 1 1,500	Water-cooled petrol engines (Jumo 211) M;iinly development work on petrol injection and Diesel engines Water-cooled petrol engines (Jumo 210) ? Components      ............... See Remarks............... Junkers water-cooled petrol engines (Jumo 210) B.M.W. aero-engines under licence    ......	120 .25 100 Nil 30	Engaged in development work for Kothen and Magdeburg factories. Factory is being greatly extended. Believed intended for aero-engine manufacture. A new  factory of which  few  details are available. Owned by well-known motor car combine. Has recently started production of complete aero-engines.Niedersacksische    Motorenwerke G.m.b.H.     (subsidiary      of Biissing-N.A.G.) Engine Works     .........	Querum, near Bruns-wick	1,200		25	f Belongs to firm of motor vehicle manufacturers.Pomiuersche Motorenbau G.m.b.IT. (subsidiary of Stoewer Werke A.G.) Engine Works     ......... Subsidiary Factory       ......	Stettin-Neutorney... Arnimswalde	2,000	B.M.W. engines (? B.M.W. VI) under licence... Under construction       ............	60	Subsidiary of firm of motor car manufacturers. CPoto
SECRET

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   October 1938.SECRET. Copy No. -- -                                                                       . * &apos;&quot;&quot;COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the Minutes of the 333rd Meeting, held on October 6, 1938.7T 7f Tv **v(9) GERMAN AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY.(OLD. Paper No. 1472-B.)(Previous -Reference : C.I.D. Minutes of the 316th Meeting, Minute 3.)THE COMMITTEE had under consideration ia note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Industrial Intelligence in Foreign Countries, covering a Memorandum prepared in collaboration between the Air Ministry (intelligence) and the Department of Overseas Trade (Industrial Intelligence Centre) on the German aircraft industry.   (OLD. Paper No. 1472-B.)SIR KINGSLEY WOOD suggested that the Memorandum should be referred to the Cabinet for consideration concurrently with the Memorandum now being prepared in the Air Ministry on the relative strengths, existing and prospective,, of this country and certain other Powers and the measures recommended to improve our own position.In the ensuing discussion reference was made to the fact that, under the scheme for the reorganization of the German industry, the number of types of aircraft had been reduced to seven.In reply to questions as to whether Germany was working on a one-shift basis, Mr. MORTON explained that at the period dealt with in the Memorandum the German industry was working, statistically speaking, on a one-shift basis of about a ten-hour day, but these arrangements had been speeded up in August, and by the date of the crisis the industry was working at an average of a sixteen-hour day. &apos; . , &apos;    - ,  \Mr. St, QTJINTIN HILL said that the Memorandum prepared in July and giving an estimate of the output of the German aircraft industry as on the 1st of that month was now out of date. Recent information indicated that the rate of output given on the 1st July as about 550 aircraft of military types had been substantially increased.SIR ROBERT VANSITTART remarked that the French now estimated the monthly output at about 800.In reply to questions by Mr. Hore-Belisha, Mr. MORTON said it was pro-visionally estimated that a rate of output up to perhaps 750 aircraft per month might have been reached in Germany at the date of the crisis. The position had been considered as a matter of urgency by the Industrial Intelligence. Centre last week, and it had been agreed with the Air Staff that in three months from the outbreak of war the German monthly output might reach 1,100 aircraft. The principal difficulty of further expansion would be the shortage of skilled and semi-skilled labour.[18034-9]
,............Mr. HORE-BELISHA considered that we should aim at a similar output.SIR SAMUEL HOARE suggested that this was a point which would have to be considered by the Cabinet in connection with the Memorandum of the Secretary of Sta^e for Air. &apos;SIR ROGER BACKHOUSE considered that as an essential corollary we should, speed up measures to provide an adequate anti-aircraft defence.Mr. HORE-BELISHA agreed, but pointed out that the capacity at present available for gun manufacture was fully taken up. To increase the output it would be necessary to control industry and to face the political and national problems involved. He proposed to deal with this question in the Report to be prepared by the War Office on the measures taken during the recent crisis. Increased capacity for A.A. gun production could, however, only be obtained, under the present system, at the expense of some other requirement. He considered that a more far-reaching industrial organization would have to be created if any real advance were to be made.SIR WARREN FISHER pointed out that if we withstood the first blow of war, it would be necessary that we should be in a position to outlast our enemies; if our export trade was ruined, this might not be possible. This point should be borne in mind in connection with the problem of industrial mobilisation.SIR KINGSLEY WOOD considered that the strength of our air force should be such as to provide a deterrent to possible enemies.SIR SAMUEL HOARE asked whether more detailed talks should not be held with the French to see whether we could not come to an agreement with the French Air Staff as to a provisional number of bomber aircraft which could be considered as an effective deterrent. In his opinion the events of the last fortnight would result in a demand from the country for an anti-aircraft organization of a much increased scope, not only as regards its size, but the number of guns, personnel, &amp;c. He was glad to hear the Secretary of State for War, would take this question up in his report.SIR KINGSLEY WOOD said that so far as aircraft production was concerned, arrangements had been made with big engineering firms to undertake aircraft production and agreement reached with five or six big firms. The chief difficulty had been that of labour, and the Air Ministry had now adopted the policy of taking the work to the men by the extended use of sub-contracting. This had increased numbers employed in the industry by about 10 per cent.Mr. HORE-BELISHA considered that even with these measures we could not approximate to German aircraft production.SIR KINGSLEY WOOD&apos;S view was that our air force should be built up to a strength sufficient to protect this country and to act as a deterrent to possible enemies, so that, whatever the strength of the German air force, Germany itself would risk destruction if they attacked us.SIR SAMUEL HOARE again stressed the necessity for heart to heart talks with the French, in view of the state of their Air Force as revealed in the last few weeks.SIR KINGSLEY WOOD said that the Chief of the Air Staff was proceeding tb France at the end of the week for this very purpose.SIR THOMAS INSKIP, summarising the discussion, suggested that the Memorandum on the German aircraft industry, together with a copy of the Minutes, should be remitted to the Cabinet for consideration concurrently with the Memorandum now being prepared in the Air Ministry to which the Secretary of State for Air had referred. In addition the Cabinet should be informed of the view of the Committee of Imperial Defence that the position of this country could not be regarded as safe until the strength of the Royal Air Force and the anti-aircraft defences as a whole had been substantially increased.
162X uRichmond Terrace, S.W. 1, October 6, 1938.Conclusions. The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed : (a) That the Memorandum on the German aircraft industry (C.I.D. PaperNo. 1472-B), together with the above minutes, should be remitted to the Cabinet, concurrently with the Memorandum now being&apos;prepared in the Air &quot;&quot;&quot;Ministry on the relative air strengths, existing and prospective, of this country and certain other Powers, and on the measures recommended to improve our own position.(b) That, in forwarding the Memorandum on the German aircraft industry,the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence should draw the attention of the Cabinet to the view of the Committee of Imperial Defence that this country could not be regarded as safe until the Royal Air Force and the anti-aircraft defences had been increased, and our passive defence arrangements had been substantially improved.-At. At, JZ. JL. Jl.&quot;7V TV &quot;A&quot; &quot;VV TV &quot;A-

</content>
</cab>
