<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/279/0 images: 278-279</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1938.SECRET.Copy No.CP. 227 (38).CABINET.CENTRAL EUROPE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.MY colleagues will perhaps be interested to see the following extract of a personal letter from Sir P. Loraine, His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Angora, about the reaction in Turkey to the part played by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the recent crisis.Extract from letter, dated October S7, from Sir P. Loraine to Viscount Halifax.You will already have received my telegram(1) reporting the reactions of the Turkish Government to the attitude and action of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and in particular of the Prime Minister, in the grave crisis of which the Czechoslovak question was the occasion. I do hope that this report gave you some satisfaction.The Opposition and even friends of the Government at home have reproached the Government with weakness and irresolution. No responsible person in Turkey with whom I have had speech since my return here takes that view. Very much the contrary. There is eloquent and ungrudging admiration of the role England has played. The whole credit for preventing war, for saving the peace of the world, for reaching an honourable settlement in a matter of which circumstances had prejudged the issue, is given to England and to the Prime Minister. I have been too busy to see many other people but Turks; but I can tell you that a similar view is held by the Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs, the Yugoslav Minister and the Hungarian Minister; and the new Italian Ambassador, whose acquaintance I have only just made, praised the Prime Minister&apos;s action with every appearance of real sincerity.I feel very definitely that in this corner of the world not only has England, lost no friends, she has also gained in moral stature.H.Foreign Office, October 14, 1938.P) See Annex.10094   [18073]
ANNEX.Sir P. Loraine to Viscount Halifax. (No. 82.   Confidential.)(Telegraphic.) Istanbul, October 3, 1938.i WAS able to have some conversation yesterday with the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs about recent crisis and its solution at Munich.I am happy to tell you, in the first place, that the Turkish Government are more than ever confirmed in their attitude of friendship towards, faith in, and close and loyal collaboration with His Majesty&apos;s Government.Dr. Aras, and he tells me that his views are shared by Ataturk and Celal Bayar, has the deepest admiration for the Prime Minister&apos;s courageous action and his unflinching and successful efforts not merely to avoid war but also to build a real peace. In his opinion, the United Kingdom has emerged really victorious from the crisis; for the Prime Minister&apos;s action has not merely made British will to peace prevail, but has preserved both Germany and France from probable disaster, and has saved Signor Mussolini by offering him the role of peacemaker and opportunity of steering away an unpopular war which the mass of Italians shrunk from and dreaded. He is, moreover, impressed with profound wisdom and skill with which the Prime Minister found means to associate the three other great Western Powers with his work of peace, and has ended what was in essence a trial of strength and will between England and Germany, not merely without arousing antagonism between the two countries, but actually by creating a far better feeling and clearer understanding between them. In his Excellency&apos;s opinion hope of peace in Europe depends on some real Anglo-German understanding, and to that the Prime Minister has opened the road.But for the Prime Ministers handling and had there been left in any quarter a sense of defeat or discomfiture, Dr. Aras reiterated, for his own part, that Herr Hitler would barely have given Europe a respite till the spring of 1939. He now looks forward to a &quot; peace l&apos;entremise &quot; of two or three years which may be possible to turn to good account in direction of consolidating peace; but about this he cannot yet be optimistic.He expects that Italy will now see whether England will make it worth her while, by means of a loan, to renounce another winter campaign in Spain which, anyway, Italy does not want; and he thinks that Germany may show an inclina-tion to connect her colonial ambitions with British financial assistance.He strongly criticises Poland and attributes her peremptory action vis-a-vis Czechoslovakia mainly to an outburst of temper at not being Included in invitation to Munich, which is likely to recoil on her own head.

</content>
</cab>
