<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/156/14 images: 153-185</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ government cp(71) 3922 March 1971PUBLIC EXPENDITURE FORECASTSMemorandum by the Chief Secretaryj, treasury, The Cabinet invited me to circulate a memorandum indicating the changes in the public expenditure forecasts since the publication of cmnd 4578, with particular reference to the investment expenditureof the nationalised industries (CM(71) 15th Conclusions, Minute 9)*COPY NO y *CABINETCMND 45782, Table I of the Annex lists the main groups of programmes(excluding only social security * debt interest and shortfall) as wepublished them in Cmnd 4578, converted to the price basis of thenew 1971 Survey.    The totals for these programmes ares  million at 1971 Survey prices1971-72   1972-73   1973-74   1974-75Nationalised industries&apos; capitalexpenditure (before shortfall)Other capital expenditureCurrent expenditure, includingcontingency reserve (exclusive of social security provision)Total for Table 1 programmes,764 1,791 ls8?4 2,0134,019 4,044 3,943 3,9585,783 5,835 5,817 5,97111,272 &quot;11,371 11.659, 1L 67417,055 17,206 17,476 17,845CHANGES SINCE CMND 45783. Table 2 of the Annex shows present provisional estimates of the changes from Cmnd 4578. The amounts are approximate and subject to officials&apos; discussions, which are now beginning in the usual way between
Departments and the Treasury in order to establish agreed estimates ofthe cost of existing policies for the 1971 Survey^    The total increases fromCmnd 4578 are;Nationalised industries capitalexpenditureOther capital expenditureCurrent expenditure total Table 2 changesRolls-Royce RB 211Total changes  million at 1971 Survey prices1971-72   1972-73   1973-74   1974-75+213	+2T5	+280	-J-340+110	+170	+160	+155-i-325	*44 5	-HL40	f495-25	+30	*5	-25-f300	*475	*445	+470-i-110	+60	-10	-5+410        +S35        +4S5        *465NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES AND NATIONAL LOANS FUND4, One important aspect of the problem created by the nationalisedindustries1 proposals is that their calls on the National Loans Fund (NLF),which are already inflated by cost increases, and in particular by the deterioration in the British Steel Corporation^ financial position, willbe greatly increased unless by raising their prices they are enabled toincrease their self-financing ratio.    The extent of this increase will bemade clear in the V/hite Paper which I present to Parliament on BudgetDay.    A copy is included with this note.,,    Table 2 of this White Papershows how close different public corporations have come to their statutoryborrowing limits - whether increased by Order or not*    Table 1 shows thetotal increase in calls on the NLF, which can be summarised!&quot;  millionEstimate for 1970-71 536Provisional outturn 1970-71 704Estimate for 1971-72 1,005If it were necessary to provide for the whole of the additional capitalexpenditure by nationalised industries shown in Table 2 of the annex to this memorandum for 1971*72 (via  115 million for steel and  100 million for the other industries) the call on the NLF for that year would be correspondingly increased.
THE CONTINGENCY RESERVE AND POSSIBLE SAVINGS5, The increases in public expenditure summarised in paragraph above must be considered in relation to the contingency reserve provided in Cmnd 4573 s  million1971-721972-731973-741974-75Contingency Reserve(excluding provisionfor social security)100200260300Total net changes to be charged tothe contingency reserve (nationalised industries&apos; componentin brackets)300 (215)475 (275)445 (280)470 (340)Net ContingencyReserveremaining(Deficit (-))-200-275-185-170It will be seen that the Contingency Reserve is heavily overdrawn throughoutthe period; if the S.B 211 is continued the deficits rise to over  300 million in 1971-72 and in 1972-73.    We shall need to recreate a substantial positivereserve for each year of the period060 In anticipation of this need, and in accordance with the instructions given to me by the Cabinet in. approving the public expenditure programmes for Cmnd 4578 (CM(70) 47th Conclusions. Minute 3), I have been seeking,with colleaguesg further savings in the existing investment programmes ofthe nationalised industries,,    I regret that we have not been able to findanything material; nor do I think it possible to make more than marginalsavings in public expenditure, without major changes in the programmesconcerned and in the methods of financing them.conclusion. We shall, therefore, face some substantial issues of policy when we come to consider the 1971 Survey report, v/hich should be ready earlyhi June.    It is ail the more important meanwhile to avoid adding to our difficulties by accepting new commitments.M V treasury Chambers SW122 March 1971
ANNEXTABLE 1:   Public expenditure programmes (other than social security and debt interest): provisional estimates:1971-72 - 1974-75  million at 1971 Survey prices1971-72   1972-73   1973-74    1974-75Defence and external relations	2,966	2,913	2,959	2,997Commerce and industry	1,773	1,448	1,200	1,034Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure	1,764	1,791	1,874	2,013Transport and miscellaneous local	3,971	4,157	4,292	4,411services				Social services (other than social security)	5,379	5,555	5&apos;, 718	5,886Other services	1,102	1,142	1,173	1,204Contingency reserve (excluding provision for social security)	100	200	260	300Total for these programmes 17,055     17,206    17,476      17,845
TABLE 2:    Changes since Cmnd 4578 in public expenditure programmes (otiier than social security and debt interest):   provisional estimates:    1971-72 - 1974-75  million at 1971 Survey prices		1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-1.	Defence and external relations	. - -	-   5	-	-2,	Commerce and industry a..   Rolls-Royce51					i.    42m launching aid for RB.211 (net)	- 13	-   7	*   3	*  4	ii*   Acquisition of assets	-f?70	- -	-	-	iiie   Working capital for new company	+715	+715		+715	bOther	* 40	* 25	* 35	* 253.	Nationalised industries					a.   Steel (as proposed by the . British Steel Corporation subject to the review announced by the Secretary of State)	+115	+160	+190	+250	b.   Other	+100	+115	* 90	* 90k.	Transport and miscellaneous local services					a.     Housing/	* 35	-f-165	+130	+130	b,     Other	- 40	- 10	-   5	-   55.	Social services (other than social security)	- 20	-   5	- 25	- 50	Other services	-   5	+ 10	* 10	4- 10Total net changes (rounded)		300	475	445	470at   If the RB.211 is continued on the basis of the offer. of19 March to Lockheeds there would be further additional expenditure of approximately+110      * So      - io      - 5/   Item 4(a), expenditure on housing, appears larger thanin Cmnd 4578 partly because savings to the supplementary benefits Commission on payments in respect of rent, whichin Cmnd 4578 were credited to housing, will henceforthbe credited to social security.
LOANS FROM THENATIONAL LOANS FUND1971-72
CONTENTSIntroductionPART It     LOANS FROM THE NATIONAL LOANS FUNDLoans to the Nationalised IndustriesLoans to Other Public CorporationsLoans to Local and Harbour AuthoritiesLoans to Private SectorLending ..&apos;J.-:,l.in Central Govetiwr. &apos;it able 1     Summary of Loans from The National loans Fund: Actual orEstimated Issues and Receipts 1S6S-69 to 1971-72PART II:   NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES: BORROWING POWERS and financing OF CAPITAL REQUIREMENTSBorrowing PowersTable 2    Nationalised Industries: Borrowing PowersTable 3    Nationalised Industries: Borrowing Outstanding on31 March 1971Financing of Capital RequirementsTable 4    Nationalised Industries: Financing of Capital RequirementsI. National Coal board. Electricity Council and Boards (in England and Wales)3. North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board4. South of Scotland Electricity board. Gas Council and Boards6, British Steel Corporation7, Post Office8. British Overseas Airways Corporation9. British European Airways Corporation10. British Airports AuthorityII. British Railways Board12. London Transport Board13* British Transport Docks Board14* British Waterways Board15. Transport Holding Company16. National Freight Corporation17* National Bus Company18. Scottish Transport GroupPage
LOANS FROM THE NATIONAL LOANS MJND1971-72INTRODUCTION1.   This White Paper gives details of Government lending from the National loans fund, and of the financing of the nationalised industries capital requirements&apos;2.   It continues the series of annual White Papers which started in 1961 under the title &quot;Government Expenditure  slow the Line&quot;, and appeared, subsequently as&quot;Loans from the Consolidated Fund&quot;.   In 1968, following the establishment of theNational Loans Fund, the current title was adopted.3.   The presentation is similar to that used in last year&apos;s White Paper (Cmnd 4333)except that in Table 4 financing by internal sources, and by capital receipts are shown separately.PAST 1:   LOANS FROM THE NATIONAL LOANS FUND4.   The figures of gross issues, receipts and net issues for the years 1968-69 to1971-72 are shown in Table 1, pageLOANS TO NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES5*   The nationalised industries borrow from the National Loans Fund to financethat part of their approved investment programmes which cannot be met from internal sources - mainly depreciation - or other external borrowing, includingborrowing abroad.   In last year&apos;s White Paper (Cmnd 4333) it was estimated thatthe industries would need to borrow  536 million from the National Loans Fund.Final outturn figures are not yet available but it is now expected that the indust-ries&apos; borrowing requirements will amount to  704 million.   The reason for this increase is that,&apos; in common with many large private sector firms, nationalised industries have experienced a deterioration in their financial position duringthe present financial year, because of rising costs.   While charges have had tobe increased for most of the industries it is likely to be difficult for theindustries to increase the proportion of investment financed from internalresources in the coming financial year.6. As last year an allowance for shortfall has been made in the overall borrowingforecast for the coming financial year.   This allowance ( 225 million) takes accountof uncertain factors such as a likely shortfall on fixed investment,, thepossibility that,the industries may be able to borrow more extensively abroad and the effect of increased charges now under consideration.
7.    The financing forecasts, leading to estimates of required borrowing, are consistent with figures provided by the industries themselves.   It should alsobe noted that the industries forecasts are subject to special difficultiesthis year.   In common with private industry the postal strike has meant thatcertain industries have been forced to increase temporary borrowing to cover a loss of revenue.   The forecasts for 1970-71 and 1971-72 reflect this.1a
LOANS TO OTHER. PUBLIC CORTORATIONSNew Towns: Development Colorations and Commission3.    The total net issues for the New Town Development Corporations and forthe Commission for the Hew Towns were  846 million by 31 March, 1971( 625 million in respect of 21 New Towns in England,  32 million in respectof 2 New Towns in Wales and  189 million in respect of 5 New Towns in Scotland).One New Town, the Central Lancashire New Town, was designated during the year.Scottish Special Housing Association9.  The Scottish Special Housing Association is a company limited by guaranteewhich is wholly financed by the Government.    It is empowered by various Housing(Scotland) Acts to build houses to let where need is greatest.   It also acts asan agent in Scotland for the Housing Corporation and in some circumstances for local authorities.   Net issues to the Association were  158 million by31 March 1971, out of a total of  230 million authorised by various Housing(Scotland) Acts and by Order.Housing Corporation10.   The Housing Corporation, established under the Housing Act, 1964, lendsmoney to housing societies (which provide houses for letting at cost rents oron a basis of co-ownership) to the extent of at least one-third of their needs.Issues for this purpose from the National Loans Fund are currently limited to 75 million, but this sum may be increased to  100 million by Order subject to affirmative Resolution of the House of Commons.   Repayments by the Corporationbegin within 5 years of the date of each advance and are spread over 40 years.Covent Garden Market Authority11.   The issues to the Covent Garden Market Authority are to enable them tomeet interest charges on existing loans and expenditure on site works programmedto start in 1971? in connection with the move of the market to Nine Elms.Sugar Board12.  The issues to the Sugar Board are annual totals of short term loans tocover the deficits arising between the purchase of Commonwealth sugar, etc. andthe receipt of surcharge income; and loans to the British Sugar Corporation underSection 21 of the Sugar Act 1956 and monies repaid by the Corporation.
Industrial j&amp;eorganisation Corporation13.   The Industrial Reorganisation Corporation is to be wound up under theIndustry Bill now before Parliament.    There will be no further transactions withthe National Loans Fund.   The Corporation&apos;s outstanding commitments will bemet by the Government directly from votes and its liability to repay itsborrowings from the National Loans Fund will be formally extinguished.   the proceeds of realisation of its investments will be credited to the consolidate fund.LOANS TO LOCAL AND HARBOUR AUTHORITIESLocal Authorities14.    In 1970/71 local authorities were able to raise from the Public WorksLoan Board, at Government, credit rates, up to 4O7&amp; (S0fs in the lessprosperous regions) of their actual capital payments during the year lesscapital receipts, Central Government capital grants, and any other CentralGovernment loans.   Authorities whose quota, calculated on capital&apos;expenditure,was less than  400,000 were entitled to draw up to  400,000.   The grossissues were originally estimated to be  915 million ( 735 million net).   Thelatest estimate is  845 million gross ( 660 million net) mainly becausedrawings in the last quarter have been at a lower rate.15&apos;    For 1971-72 authorities&apos; percentage access to theBoard will    remain at 40 per cent (50 per cent for authorities in the lessprosperous regions) of their reckonable capital payments.   Authorities whosequota calculated in this way is less than  400,000 will be entitled to draw upto that amount.   The Board will continue to act as a lender of last resortand the arrangements for reallocating undrawn quotas will bp continued.Harbour Authorities16.   The Secretary of State for the Environment is empowered by the HarboursAct 1964 and the Ports and Harbours Act 1966 to make loans to harbourauthorities for the development of harbour facilities.confidential
17&apos;   The previously exisLing staLutory limit of x.100 million on loans (together,vlth port modernisation grants) imposed by the Harbours Act 1364? was repealedby the Harbours (Amendment) Act 1970.   This Act provided for a new limit of 75 million on loans (but not grants) made after the passing of the Act.This limit may be increased to  12) million by resolution of the House of Commons.18.   Following the change of Government in Jane 1970* the revised loan arrange-ments envisaged last year, as proposed under the Forts Silly were noL proceededni th.LOANS TO PRIVATE SECTORBritish Nuclear Fuels Ltd and the Radiochemical Centre Ltd19*    The Atomic Energy Act 1971 empowers the Secret-cry of State for Trade andIndustry with the approval of the Treasury to make loans to British NuclearFuels Ltd and the Radio chemical Centre Ltd up to  50 million and  5 million respectively.    These limits may be increased by order up to  75 million and 7 million respectively.   No advances are expected to be made in 1971-72.Shipbuilding Industry Board .20.    The Shipbuilding Industry Act 1967 empowers the Shipbuilding industry board, with the approval of the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry, tomake loans to shipbuilding undertakings and marine engine manufacturers up toa total of  32.5 million to help them to carry out. the reorganisation andrationalisation of the industry recommended by the Geddes Committee.Ship Credit Scheme21.   This Scheme, authorised by the Shipbuilding Credit Act, 1964 made available 55 million for loans to United Kingdom shipowners for the construction ofvessels in the United Kingdom,   The last payment under the Scheme was made in1966 and there will be no further advances.Building Societies22.   Loans made to approved Building Societies under the House Purchase and housing Act, 1959. are now being repaid.   No new loans are being made at present.
Housing Associations23*   Loans to Housing Associations to encourage the provision of unsubsidisedhousing for letting (under Section. 7 of the Housing Act, 1961, and Section 23of the Housing (Financial Provisions; (Scotland) Act, 1968), amount to 0.1 million in 1971-72.   Repayments by Housing Associations are made by annuityover a period of 60 years in respect of completed schemes.LIMBING WITHIN CENTRAL GOVERITIJEMTPurchase of US Military Aircraft24.   Advances from the National Loans Fund are made under the Military Aircraft(Loans) Act, 1966, to the Ministry of Aviation Supply&apos;s Vote (Class IV,17:Purchase of United States Aircraft) to offset money provided by Parliament towardsthe purchase of Phantom and Hercules aircraft and associated equioment.   The amount and timing of these advances correspond with the instalments of credit, in dollars,made available by the US Government to the National Loans Fund to assist with thepurchase.   The advances reduce the Vote to a token sum,but this procedure enablesParliament to retain control over the cost of the programme financed by UnitedStates credit.25.   The advances are repaid, together with interest and other charges on theUS credits, to the National Loans Fund by the Ministry of Defence, on whose behalfthe aircraft are being purchased, and by the Ministry of Aviation Supply as regardsresearch and development costs.   Thus the full cost of the transactions is borne by those Departments and falls within the Defence Budget.   The Treasury in turn repaysthe US credits from the National Loans Fund.Married Quarters for the Armed Forces26.   The power to make loans under the Armed Forces (Housing Loans) Acts, 1949*1958 and 1965, ceased with the expiration of the Acts on 31 March, 1968, butrepayments of outstanding loans will continue until 2028,Town and Country Planning Compensation27.   The power to make payments of compensation under Parts I and V of the Townand Country Planning Act, 1954, and the Town and Country Planning (Scotland) Act,1954* out of issues from the Consolidated Fund ceased with effect from 1 April,1968, with the passing of the National Loans Act, 1968.   Repayment of past issuesfrom that Fund by way of annuities financed from the Votes of the Department ofthe Environment, the Scottish Development Department and the Welsh Office willcontinue until 1976 for England and Wales and until 1980 for Scotland.
Redundancy Fund28.   Under the Redundancy Payments Act 1965 advances may be made to the redundancy Fund if at any time the demands on that Fund temporarily outrun itsincome.   The amount of advances that may be outstanding at any one time isstatutorily limited to  8 million.   As forecast in last year&apos;s White Paper(Cmnd 4333) all advances outstanding at the beginning of the year were clearedduring 1970-71* and it is not expected that there will be any advances outstandingon 31 March 1971*   It is estimated that, if any advances are needed temporarilyduring 1971-72, these will be cleared during that year, and there will be nooutstanding advances at the end of it.Land Commission29.   The Land Acquisition and Management Fund was established under the land commission Act, 1967* for financing the Land Commission^ acquisition, management and disposal of land.   The Fund itself is financed by loans from the national loans Fund.   The Land Commission (Dissolution) Bill provides for the Fund to bewound up on a day to be appointed and for the Land Commission^ liability inrespect of suras advanced from the National Loans Fund to be extinguished.   Thus,no estimate is made of transactions in 1971/72; instead, provision has been madefor the remaining expenditure in the 1971/72 Estimates of the Department of the environment (Class VI,16) and the Scottish Development Department (Class VI, 3)*while receipts from sales, etc will be paid into the Consolidated Fund as ExtraReceipts,30.   It is estimated that the liability which will be extinguished will be  11.5m,including interest accumulated since the last interest payment was made.   On theother hand, receipts from sales, etc payable into the Consolidated Fund over aperiod should amount to about  8.5 million.Northern Ireland Exchequer31,   It is estimated that the Northern Ireland Government will have borrowed 62.2 million (net) in 1970-71 under the Miscellaneous Financial ProvisionsAct 195O (as amended by Section 57 of the Finance Act 1969) and under Section 35of the Finance Act 1970, which replaced the previous statutory authority forlending to Northern Ireland during the year.   This sum exceeded the amount forecast in paragraph 27 of last year&apos;s white Paper (Cmnd 4333) because of increased lendingby the Northern Ireland Government to the Electricity Board for Northern Ireland,and because of increased expenditure by that Government itself.   It is expectedthat by 31 March 1971  43 million will have been advanced to the Northern Ireland
Exchequer under Section 35 of the Finance Act 1970; the limit of  50 million inthat Section can be raised on not more than three occasions by statutory instrument, and subject to approval by the House of Commons of the necessaryinstrument it is expected that some  74 million will be lent to the NorthernIreland Exchequer in 1971-72.
O ONFI DEWT IALTABLE 1 *SUMMARY OF LOANS FROM THE NATIONAL LOANS FUND - ACTUAL OR ESTIMATED ISSUES AND RECEIPTS 1968-69 TO 1971-72  Million		ISSUES				RECEIPTS				NET	ISSUES														1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated	1971-72 Estimate	1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated	19 7H2 Estimate	1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated	1971-72 Estimate			Outturn				Outturn				Outturn	LOANS 10 NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES /												National Coal Board	2,4.6	17.3	22.2	72.3	24.3	28.4	68.6	40.3	20.3	-11.1	-46.4	32.electricity Council and Boards North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board	294.0 12.2	425.0 9.2	357.0 22.5	360.0 17.*	129.5 7.2	141.1 7.7	170.0 8.2	184.0 9.0	164.5 5.0	283.9 1.5	187.0 14.3	176.0 8.1South of Scotland Electricity Board	48.0	50.5	59.0	64.2	13.5	15.5	17.6	20.0	34.5	35.0	41.4	44.2Gas Council and Boards	240.0	203.0	187.0	363.1	34.2	44.9	53.8	62.6	205.8	158.1	133.2	300.british Steel Corporation	15.0	50.0	65.0	315.0	33.5	18.8	22.0	26.0	-18.5	31.2	43.0	289.0Post Office ^	271-6	271-6	297-6	305.6	31.6	31.6	31.6	31.6	240.0	240.0	266.0	274-british Overseas Airways Corporation	-		- -	-	2^8	2.8	16.9	-	-2.8	-2.8	-16.9	-British European Airways Corporation	53.0	-	60.0	64.O	23.4	18.2	18.9	27.0	29.6	-18.2	41.1	37.british Airports Authority	3.0	1.0	-	5.0	0.1	0.2	0.3	0.3	2.9	0.8	-0.3	4.7British Railways Board	-	-	29.0	55iO	-	15.0	14.0	14.0	-	-15.0	15.0	41.london Transport Board	21.0	11.0	-	-	-	-	-	-	21.0	11.0	-	-British Transport Bocks Board	8.5	9.7	7.3	11.3	-	-	-	-	8.5	9.7	7.3	11.british Waterways Board	0.4 i.....-	0.7 j	0.2 1            ______	0.5		0.2	-	-	0.4	0.5	0.2	0.5* The grouping of the items in ftis table follows the classification by sector used in the statistics of national income and expenditure./- See notes to Table 4-f Issues and receipts for 1968-69 and 1969-70 have been revised to inolude advances of  31.6 million renewed in eaoh year.
confidential table 1 continued  Million	ISSUES				RECEIPTS				BET ISSUES				Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 Estimate	19&apos;o&quot;8-^9 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 Estimate	1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 EstimateTransport Holding Company	14.0	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	14.0	-	-	-national Freight Corporation	-	10.0	15.0	10.0	-	-	-	-	-	10.0	15.0	10.0National Bus Company	-	-	2f.O	2.0	-	-	-	-	-	-	4.0	2.scottish Transport Group	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-		Deduction for shortfall (see para 6)	-		-	-225-0	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-225.0Total loans to nationalised industries	1025.3	1059-0	1125.8	1420.1	300.1	324-4	421-9	415-8	725.2	734.6	703.9	1005.3LQAHS TO OTHER PUBLIC COBPOHATIONS												Hew Tonne Development Corporations and Commission	80.8	99.7	110.5	127.8	2.1	2.8	3.3	2.6	78.7	96.9	107.2	125.2Scottish Special Housing Association	11.7	13A	15-0	15.0	0.7	1.0	1.0	0.8	11.0	12.4	14.0	14.2												
COHFIDEHTIALTABLE 1 continued&amp; iiUlfll		ISSUES			RECEIPTS				BET ISSUES				1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 Estimate	I96W9 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 Estimate	1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Eat lasted	1971-72 Bet lastsHoming Corporation	12.0	13.1	9.1	12.6	-	-		0.1	12.0	T3.t	9.1	12.5Cownt Garden Karket Authority	0.3	2.1	3.5	5.3	-	-		mm	0.3	2.1	3.5	5.3Sugar Board	12.0	6.0	7.0	11.0	14.2	5.6	2.5	16.0	-2.2	0.4	4.5	-5.0Industrial Reorganisation Corporation	20.9	33.1	36.5	m.		10.0	15.9		20.9	23.1	20.6	Total loans to other public corporations	137.7	167.4	1ST.6	171.7	17.0	19-4	22.7	19.5	120.7	148.0	159.9	152.2LOADS TO LOCAL AND tmnmiia AUTHORITIES Looal Authorities Harbour authorities	597.1	676.6 20.2	845.0 17.0	1070.0 25.0	128.0 0.2	151.4 0.1	105.0 0.1	210.0 0.2	469,1 9,2	525.2 20.1	660*0 t6.Q	860.0 2A.8Total loans to local and harbour authorities	606.5	696.8	862.0	1095.0	126.2	151-5	185-1	210.2	478.3	545.3	676.9	88V. 8L04B3 TO PRIVATE SECTOR Shipbuilding Industry Board	5.9	3.6	2.6	5.0	-	-	-	0.1	5 *9	3.6	2.6	4.9Ship Credit Scheme	-	-	-		6.2	6.5	9.9	4.3	-6.2	-6.5	-9.9	-V,
confidential table 1 continued  million	ISSUES				RECEIPTS				NET ISSUES				1968-69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 Estimate	1968^09 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 Estimate	1968^69 Outturn	1969-70 Outturn	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 EstimateHousing Associations	1.2	0.4	0.2	0.1	-	-	0.1	0.1	1.2	0.4	0.1	-Building Societies	-	-	-	-	3.4	3.1	3-3	3.6	-3.4	-3.1	-3.3	-3.6Total loans to private sector	7.1	4.0	2.8	5.1	9.6	9-6	13.3	8.1	-2.5	-5.6	-10.5	-3.0LEHDIBG WITHIN CEHTHAL GOVEEHMENT												Advances to Votest Purchase of US Military Aircraft	110.5	29.6	10.0	6.5	38.5	32.4	39.9	40.5	72.0	-2.8	-29.9	-34.0Harried Quarters for Armed Forces	-	-	-	-	1.1	0.3	0.3	0.3	-1.1	-0.3	-0.3	-0.3Town and Country Planning Compensation	-	-	-	-	3.2	3.3	3.5	3.7	-3.2	-3.3	-3.5	-3.7Total advances to Votes	110.5	29.6	10.0	6.5	42.8	36.0	43.7	44.5	67.7	-6.4	-33.7	-38.0Sedundsnoy Fund	17.8	3.8	1.6	-	11.0	17.8	5.4	-	6.8	-14.0	- 3.8	-Idmri Camilla9Ion	4.2	3.3	3.0	-	-	-	- -   -	-	4.2	3.3	3.0	-Horthem Ireland Exchequer	23.0	35.0	63.O	75-0	0.5	0.6	0.8	1.0	22.5	34.4	62.2	74*0Total lending within Central Government	155.5	71.7	77.6	81.5	54.3	54.1  j	A9.9	45.5	101.2	17.3	27.7	36.grand TOTAL	1932.1	1898.9	224.9.8	2773.4	509.2	559.3	692.9	698.1	1422.9	1439.6	1556.9	2075.3
PART II.   NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES: BORROWING POWERSBorrowing,   including public dividend capital by the nationalised industries is limited by legislation.   Table 2 sets out the current limits and the amounts estimated tobe outstanding at 31 March, 1971.   Table 3 analyses the content of the latter.TABLE nationalised Industries: Borrowing Powers  millionNationalised Industry	Existing Statutory Limit	Increase Permissible by Order	Estimated Amount Outstanding at 31 March, 1971	Relevant Statute(i)	(ii)	(iii)	(iv)	(v)National Coal Board	900	50	644	Coal Industry Act, 1967Electricity Council and Boards	4,400	**	4,052	Electricity and Gas Act 1963North of Scotland Hydro-) Electric Board             ) South of Scotland Else- ) tricity Board              )	700	100	664	Electricity (Scotland) Act, 1969Gas Council and Boards	2,100	300	1,696	Gas and Electricity Act, 1968British Steel Corporation	500	150	366	Iron and Steel Act, 1969Post Office	2,300	500	2,270	Post Office Act, 1969British Overseas Airways Corporation	250	130	118	Air Corporations Act, 1971British European Airways Corporation	200	30	151	Air Corporations Act, 1969British Airports Authority	70	-	58	Airports Authority Act, 1965British Railways Board	550	150	395	Transport Act, 1968British Transport Docks Board British Waterways Board	160 12	mm	118 8	Transport Act, 196S Transport Act, 1968Transport Holding Company	100	-	2	Transport Act, 1962 as amended by Transport Holding Company Act, 1968National Freight Corporation	200	100	135	Transport Act, 1968National Bus Company	130	-	102	Transport Act, 1968Scottish Transport Group	50	-	23	Transport Act, 1968
Notes to Table 2(a) The limits shown in Col (ii) can be increased by amounts not exceedingthose shown in Col (iii) by an Order made by the responsible Minister. TheOrder is subject to Affirmative Resolution procedure.(b) The amounts in Col (iv) show the borrowings by the industries whichcount against the borrowing limits in Col (ii).   They include a total of 1,214 million in respect of outstanding stock issued before the introductionof the system of Government advances in 1956.(c) The Iron and Steel Act, 1969, substituted for the commencing capital debt of the British Steel Corporation under the Iron and Steel Act, 1967, debt of 134 million and public dividend capital of  700 million,.   The statutory limitrelates to new capital and applies not only to borrowings but also to additional public dividend capital subscribed from the Consolidated. Fund.(d) The Air Corporations Act 1966 provided for an element of public dividendcapital in B0AC&apos;s capital structure.  The statutory limit for BOAC applies notonly to borrowings but also to the Corporations public dividend capital (exceptthat created by the conversion of reserves).   The figure in Col (iv) accordinglyincludes public dividend capital amounting to  35 million.(e) The figures for the Transport Holding Company in Col (iv) of Table 2 andin Table 3 differ to the extent of the Company&apos;s commencing capital debt, this latter figure being excluded from the statutory borrowing limit under Section 29(11) and (18) of the Transport Act, 1962, as amended by Section 1 of theTransport Holding Company Act, 1968.(f) The figures for the National Freight Corporation, the National Bus company and the Scottish Transport Group in Col (iv) include provisional estimates ofthe commencing capital debts of these bodies, which are in the course of being determined under Schedule 2 to the Transport Act, 1968.
confidential table 3Nationalised Industries: Analysis of amounts outstanding againststatutory financing limits at 31 March 1971  millionf Gross Nationalised Industry     ^^f1&quot; J     ! ment iAdvances		Bepay-ments :	Net Govern- ! ment Advances I	l Borrowing j by Stock ! Issues j	f Temp-   ; Foreign temporary   jCurrency Borrowing! Borrowing i		! i PDCi	TotalNational Coal Board	800	136 ;	644	i j				 1.1.Electricity Council and				i				Boards	4,334	984	3,350   I	620   !	49	33	- I	4,052North of Scotland Hydro-   ;								Electric Board	244	60	184	71	2	3   ;		260South of Scotland Elec-		i	i					tricity Board	492	102 j	390   !	-	8	6	d i	404Gas Council and Boards	1,483	223 I	1,260	283	69	84	- j	1,696British Steel Corporation I	305	74 !	231		135		- I	366Post Office*	2,503	316 !	2,18 7	-	75	8	- !	2,270British Overseas Airways		&apos;  &apos; 1 1						Corporation	31	31 I	-	-	-	83	351	118British European Airways							i i	Corporation	192	48	144		-	7	- i	151British Airports							I	Authority	59	1	58	-	-	-	-:	58British Railways Board	394	29	365		30		-;	395British Transport Docks								Board	117	-	117		1	I	an :	118British Waterways Board	7	-	7		1	-            I	-:	8Transport Holding				I j		I	I	Company /	5	-	5	-	2	-	-i	7National Freight						I		Corporation p   6	124	-	124	t	11		-j	135National Bus Company ^	100	-	100	-	2	-	-j	102Scottish Transport							i	Group ^	21	-	21	-	2	-            j	-i j i	23Total	11,211	I 2,024	9,177	974 i	387	224	35	10,807* A reduction of  11 million will be necessary to take account of the transfer of buildings and other assets now used,by the Department of Hational Savings.   The figures arerevised to include advances of  31.6 renewed in each of the nine years 1961-62 to1969-70, in addition to the repayment of the same amount in 1970-71./   See Note (e) to Table 2/  These figures include provisional estimates of the commencing capital debts of theTransport Holding Company, the National Freight Corporation, the National Bus company and the Scottish Transport Group which are in the course of being determined, takingaecount of transfers effected under the Transport Act 1968.   The borrowings of theTransport Holding Company between 1 January 1963 and 31 December 1968 are included in thecommencing capital debts of the successor bodies.fi  At 31 March 1971, the National Freight Corporation had  0.5 million of foreign currencyborrowing outstanding, as approved by the Secretary of State for the Environment.
PART III   NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES: FINANCING OF CAPITAL REQUIREMENTS29.   The following table shows for each nationalised industry how its capitalexpenditure has been financed in the years 1968-69 and 1969-70, and how it isexpected to be financed in 1970-71 and in 1971-72.   Figures for the financing ofcapital requirements are expressed at outturn prices for 1968-69 aid 1969-70, and estimated outturn prices for 1970-7&quot;) and 1971-72,   Footnotes to the tablesexplain points of interests   Fixed investment comprises total expenditureon fixed assets in the United Kingdom; capital receipts include capitalcontributions by consumers and investment grants.TABLE 4Nationalised Industries: Financing of Capital Requirements1.    National Coal Board   million	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	i 1971-72 Estimat eFixed investment	58.8	59.4	74.5	85.other investment	2.5	2.6	3.0	4.0Changes in working capital	-9.6	-55.5	-25.5	-22.0Total capital requirements	5l7	6.5	52.0	67.OFinanced by:				Internal resources	49.2	37.3	58.0	35.capital receipts	0.9	1.7	-	-Borrowing:				National Loans Fund*	1.6	-32.5	-6,0	32.0Total finance	51.7	6.5	52.0	67.O* These figures do not correspond to those given in Table 1, which do not include Ways and Means Advances in 1968-69 and 1969-70^and because of technical adjustments.
LB2.    Electricity Council and Boards (in England and Wales)   million	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment&apos; Other investment                          ; Changes in working capital	^92.9 46.2	405.4 45.4	380.0 80.0	400.0 ko,total capital requirements	539.1	450.8	460.0	^40.0Financed by:                / Internal resources  * Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	353.0 32.3 164.5 - 10.7	327.5 21.1 - 181.7	230.0 20.0 187.0 23.0 11	283.0 17.0 176.0   . - 36.0Total finance	539.1	450.8	^60.0	440.0includes nuclear fuel /Less debt redemption in respect of certain vested assets : ^ 200 million British Electricity 4^ Stock 1967-69 was redeemed.   Provision for this is included in NLF borrowing. t  21.1 million borrowed in Germany 11  12.0 million borrowed in Germany 3.   North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board                                        million				1968-69		1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment Other investment Capitalised interest Changes in working capital	8.7 -1.2	10.3 mm 0.8	12.6 0.1 0.3	14.9 0.2Total capital requirements	9.9	11.1	13.0	15.1Financed by: Internal resources Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	5.4 0.9 5.0 -   1,4	5.9 2.4 1.5 , 1.3 *	a.? 2.1 14.3 j - 10.3 *	7.6 1.2 8.1 -   1.8Total finance	9.9	11.1	13.0	15a/  3.1 million  borrowed -in Luxembourg^  7.8 million of the Board&apos;6 3% Stock 1968-70 was redeemed.  Provision for thisis included in the NLF borrowing.
k.   South of Scotland Electricity Board   million&apos;  1968-69		1969-70         1970-71 j Estimated i Outturn		1971-72 estimate fixed investment * Other investment Changes in working capital	61.0 4.1	60.1 -   2.9	68.6 -    0,9	69.9 4.0Total capital requirements	56.9	57.2	67.7	73.9Financed by: Internal resources Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	20.8 4.3 34.5 -     2.7	21.2 4.8 35.0^	&apos;   19.1 7.8 41.4 0.6	22.3 7.2 44.2 0.2Total finance	56.9	57.2	67.7	73.9* Includes nuclear fuel /  15 million of &quot;the Board&apos;a stock was redeemed.   Provision for this is included in NLF borrowing. t  6.3 million borrowed in Germany. 5.   Gas Council and Boards                                                               million					1968-69 ! 1969-70		1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment Other investment* Capitalised interest           , Changes in working capital	222.4  !     198.7 9.8 j      3.0 2.8    j           3.3 47.0 I     73.3		203.8 3.7 3.2 103 .9	225.2 5.3 0.9 99.4Total capital requirements	282.0	278.3	314 .6	330.8Financed by:              , Internal resources Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	76.0 205.8 0.2	83.2 1.0 158.1 . 36.0*	82.2 1.8 97 .4&apos;v	102.4Total finance	282.0	278.3	314.6	330.8* Includes loans to North Sea subsidiary/ Includes costs of appliance conversion to natural gas Less debt redemption in respect of certain vested assetst  30.3 million borrowed in Germany//  52,5 million borrowed in Switzerland.H In 1971-72    72.1 million British Gas 3i% Guaranteed Stock xs due forredemption.   Provision for this is included in NLF borrowing
6.   British Steel Corporation   million......&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;v&quot;&quot; &apos;v f	&apos;    1968-69	1969-70         1970-71 Estimated Outturn		1971-72 estimate fixed investment Other investment Changes in working capital	68.0 21.8 45.5	81.1 29.1 27.1	130.0 4.0 29.0	205.0 45.0Total capital requirements	135.3	137.3	163.0	250.0Financed by: Internal resources Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	79.5 32.1 -   18.5 42.2	91.3 30.3 31.2 -   15.5	66.0 24.O 43.0 30,0	- 34.0* 40.0 289.0* - 45.0Total finance	135.3	137.3	163.O	250.0*Takes no account of a price increase proposal received from the Corporation before publication. 7.   Post Office                                                                                   million				;    1968-69 I		1969-70    I    1970-71 j  Estimated Outturn		1971-72 estimate fixed investment                        i     351*7 Other investment                                   7*0 Changes in working capital                 44.3		390.1*          444.0 5.6              3.0 24,1              22.0		554.0 3.0 - 10.0Total capital requirements J     403.0		419.8	469.0	547.0Financed by: Internal resources Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	162.8 0.2 240.0	178.1 1.7 240.0^	- , 187.O 8.0 266.0 , 8.0*	269.0 1.0 274.0 3.0/Total finance	403.0	419.8	469.0	547.0*Department of National Savings requirements are included only up to30th September 1969./ A reduction of about  11 million will be necessary to take accountof the transfer of buildings and other assets now used by the Department ofNational Savings.&apos; Foreign currency borrowing.
8.    British Overseas Airways Corporation   million&quot;	1968-69	1969-70  ! 1970-71		1971-72			Estimated	Estimate			Outturn	Fixed investment	39.1	41.8	79.2	75.other investment	2.1	2.0	2.9	8.5Capitalised interest	mm	mm	0.5	1.0Changes in working capital	8.7	4.5	9.8	-   5.3- -Total capital requirements	49.9	48.3	92.4	79.7Financed by:				Internal resources	38.3	30.1	57.9	52.capital receipts	0,1	1.1	1.9	0.4Borrowing:	- 2.8			National Loans Fund		-   2.8	- 16.9	-Other	14.3	19.9*	49.5*	27.3*Total finance	^9.9	48.3	92.4	79.7* Overseas hank loans				9*    British European Airways Corporation			  million		1968-69	1969-70	i.......... 1970-71	1971-72			Estimated	Estimate			Outturn	Fixed investment	48.8	21.3	35.4	51.other investment	3.3	0.1	0.8	1.0Capitalised interest	1.6	1.3	0.9	1.0Changes in working capital	2.1	1.3	5.0	4.2Total capital requirements	55.8	24.0	42.1	57.6Financed by:				Internal resources	20.2	25.9	15.6	20,1Capital receipts	0.3	0.3	0.4	0.5Borrowing:	28.5 /	- 17.2 /		National Loans Fund			41.1	37.other	6.8*	15.0	- 15.0	total finance	55.8	24,0	42.1	57.6* Overseas bank loan/ The figures in this table for 1968-69 and 1969-70 differ from those in Table 1 becauseof retrospective adjustments made in BEA&apos;s outstanding liabilities to theNational Loans Fund under the Air Corporations Act 1969*
10.   British Airports Authority   million	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71	f :      1971-72			Estimated	Estimate			Outturn	Fixed investment	11.9	9.3	10.5	14.changes in working capital	0.1	2.2	-   1.7	0.6Total capital requirements	12.0	11.5	8.8	15.1Financed by:				Internal resources	8.6	11.7	9.1	10.capital receipts	-	-	-	-Borrowing:				National Loans Fund	2.9	0.8	-  0.3	4.other	0.5	-    1.0	-	-Total finance	12.0	11.5	8.8	15.111.     British Railways Board			  million		1968-69	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72*			Estimated	Estimate			Outturn	Fixed investment	82.8	74.3	91.8	100.other investment	0.2	10.3	8.0/	10.0/Changes in working capital	10.8	-   15.2	4.0	8.0Total capital requirements	93.8	69.4	103.8	118.0Financed by:              . Internal resources^					85.7	81.6	72.8	71.capital receipts	2.6	2.3	3.5	9.0Borrowing:		J	6	National Loans Fund	-	- 15.0*	15.0*	41.0*Other	5.5	0.5	12.5	-   3.0Total finance	93.8	69.4	103.8	118.0* Subject to review in the light of Government&apos;s consideration of the Board1s firstCorporate Plan./ Includes Board1s share C*9 per cent) of the financing of the investment ofFreightliners Ltd.^ Repayment of  15 million of commencing capital debt.jrf Net borrowing after  14 million repayment and refinancing of commencingcapital debt.
\j Wu- xfJMVXX Ail12.   London Transport Board   million	1968-69	1969-70*	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment Interest&apos; Changes in working capital	26.1 4.1 -0.1	13.3 0.2 9.8	-	-Total capital requirements	30.1	23.3	-	-Financed by Internal resources)/ Capital receipts   ) Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	11.6 21 .0 -2.5	10.2 11.0 2.1	-	-Total finance	30.1	23.3	-	-*From 1 January 1970, most of the Board1 s functions were transferred to theLondon Transport Executive which is responsible to the Greater London Council.The National Bus Company became responsible for the remainder (the Londoncountry buses),/interest chargeable to capital account under Section 18(5) of the transport act, 1962,/Mainly capital receipts ^infrastructure and new bus grants) and provisions for depreciation and amortisation charged to revenue and therefore included in therevenue deficit financed up to J1 December 1968 from Votes under Section 22 ofthe Transport Act 1962 as applied to the London Transport Board by Section 1 ofthe Transport Finances Act, 1966 and to 31 December 1969 under Section 19(8) ofthe Transport (London) Act 1969.13.   British Transport Docks Board   million	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment	14.9	12.8	12.0	13.other investment	0.3	-	0.4	4.6Interest*	0.7	1.4	0.1	0.changes in working capital	-0.6	1.7	1.8	0.6Total capital requirements	15.3	15.9	14.3	19.1Financed by:				Internal resources	4.5	3.5	3.8	5.capital receipts	2.3	3.3	2.8	1.9Borrowing:				National Loans Fund	8.5	9-7	7.3	11.other	-	- 0.6	0J+	-Total finance	15.3	15.9	14.3	19.1*Estimate of interest chargeable to capital account under Section 18(5) of theTransport Act 1962 (subject to the consent of Secretary of State for the environment)*
14.   British Waterways Board   million	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment	0.7	0.7	0.8	0.changes in working capital	-0.2	0.5	-0.1	0.1Total capital requirements	0.5	1.0	0.7	0.9Financed by:				Internal resources*	0.2	0.3	0.3	0.capital receipts	-    -	-	-	-Borrowing:				National Loans Fund	0.4	0.5	0.2	0.other	-0.1	0.2	0.2	-Total finance	0.5	1.0	0.7	0.9*  After taking account of grant under Section 43 of the Transport Act 1968,and also provision for depreciation and amortization.15.   Transport Holding Company   million	1968-69*	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment Other investment Changes in working ca^ical	20.2 5.7 7.3	0.3 0.7 -0.3	0.8 0.9 -0.3	0.4 0.1 0.6Total capital requirements	33.2	0.7	1.4	1.1Financed by: Internal resources Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	j 21.0 14.0 -1.8	0.4 0.1 0.2/	-0.2 0.1 1.5/	1.1 0.2 -0.2/Total finance	33.2	0.7	1.4	1.1*0n 1 January 1969 most of the activities of the Transport Holding company were transferred under the Transport Act 1968 to the National!. freight corporation, the National Bus Company and the Scottish Transport Group/ 0.1 million borrowed overseasf 0.3 million borrowed overseasp 0.2 million borrowed overseas
TABLE IV.   Nationalised Industries:Financing of Capital Requirements (continued)16.   National Freight Corporation   million	1968-69*	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment^ Other investment Changes in working capital	2.4 0.4 3.2	25.7 0.3 8.2	26.0 2.5 1.7	29.3 4.9Total capital requirements	6.0	34.2	30.2	34.2Financed by:              . Internal resources?&quot; Capital receipts Borrowing: National Loans Fund Other	j   2.6 3.4	13.3 3.9 10.0 7.0	13.7 0.5 15.0 1.0	22.5 1.7 10.0Total finance	6.0	34.2	30.2	34.2*The Corporation commenced business on 1 January 1969includes 100 per cent of the investment in Preightliners Ltd, 49 per cent ofwhich is financed by the British Railways Board.^After taking account of grant under Section 5 of the Transport Act 1968 andthe British Railways Board share of the financing of freight liners Ltd,17.   National Bus Company   million	1968-69*	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment	2.3	9.4	13.9	14.other investment	-	0.2	-0.7	-Changes in working capital	-1.4	-2.6	2.0	4.6Total capital requirements	0.9	7.0	15.2	19.4Financed by:				Internal resources	1.1	9.9	1.4	10.capital receipts	0,2	2.0	2.4	2.7Borrowing:				National Loans Fund	-	-	4.0	2.other	-0.4	-4.9	7.4	3.8Total finance	0.9	7.0	15.2	19.4*The Company commenced business on 1 January 1969
18.   Scottish Transport Croup   million	1968-69*	1969-70	1970-71 Estimated Outturn	1971-72 estimate fixed investment	0.2	3.5	3.5	3.other investment	-	0.6	-	Changes in working capital	-	1.7	-0.4	-0.6Total capital requirements	0.2	5.8	3.1	3..1Financed by:				Internal resources	0.2	2.1	2.8	3.capital receipts	-	1.9	0.4	0.7Borrowing:				National Loans Fund Other/	-	-	-	-	-	1.8	-0.1	-1.0Total finance	0.2	5.3	3.1	3.1*The Group commenced business on 1 January 1969/Mainly bank borrowing


</content>
</cab>
