<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/13/1 images: 14-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.MOST SECRET.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.copy NO.operations in NORWAY.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 108thConclusions,Minute 3.)Statement bythe PrimeMinister inthe Hou. . ofCommons.W.M.   (40) 109th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 34Confidential Annex.(1st May, 1940.)THE PRIME MINISTER said that he would shortly have to make a full statement on the situationin Norway in the House of Commons.The following were the main points in a discussion which ensued regarding what should beincluded in this statement:(i)    The withdrawal from central Norway wasstrategically imperative.      If we had continued to operate in that theatrewe should probably have had to put ina force of some 50,000 to 60,000 troops and conducted a campaign in an area inwhich we could not have maintained airequality.(ii)   The maintenance of such a force throughports over which the enemy had great air superiority would have imposed a strain onthe Navy and thereby impaired its mobilityto an extent which would only have been justified if great results could have beenobtained.(^v)    The same objections did not apply to NorthNorway and Narvik, which would not be exposed to the same scale of air attack andwould be easier to protect.(vi)   To the question why we had sent an expeditionto Norway at all, the reply should be thatwe had been obliged to answer an appeal forassistance from the Norwegians.     Owing tothe need for speed, we had done this with small forces;    and had the advance of theGermans been less rapid, these small forces might have served a very useful purpose incontaining much larger German forces.(vii)   Whilst it had been impossible to foreseethe course of events, we could point to thefollowing favourable factors:-(a) the tangible and irrefutable fact thatwe had succeeded in destroying half theGerman Navy:(b) that we had induced the Germans to sendsome 8 or 9 Divisions into Norway:1 -

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS government most SECRET.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.copy NO.W.M.   (40)  109th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 3iConfidential Annex.(1st May, 1940.)operations in NORWAY.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 108thConclusions,Minute 3.)Statement bythe PrimeMinister inTHE PRIME MINISTER said that he would shortly have to make a full statement on the situationin Norway in the House of Commons.The following were the main points in a discussion which ensued regarding what should beincluded in this statement:( i)    The withdra^a^l-^fj^ro^Clar^strategically imperative. . .1-1*&apos;we had continued to operate in that theatre,we should probably have had to put ina force of some 50,000 to 60,000 troops.The maintenance of sea communications forthis force would have tied down the NavyBy retaining a large force in CentralNorway we should have been pursuing thevery course which the Germans wished usto adopt.We were withdrawing from Central Norwayto fight in North Norway.The same objections did not apply to NorthNorway and Narvik,which would not be exposed to the same scale of air attack andwould be easier to protect.To the question why we had sent an expeditionto Norway at all, the reply should be thatwe had been obliged to answer an appeal forassistance from the Norwegians.     Owing tothe need for speed, we had done this with small forces;    and had the advance of theGermans been less rapid, these small forces might have served a very useful purpose incontaining much larger German forces.(vii)   Whilst it had been impossible to foreseethe course of events, we could point to thefollowing favourable factors:-(a) the tangible and irrefutable fact thatwe had succeeded in destroying half theGerman Navy:(b) that we had induced the Germans to sendsome 8 or 9 Divisions into Norway:(lii)(vi)- 1 -

(c) That in going into Norway the Germans hadimposed upon themselves an act of self-blockade &quot;by losing the Norwegian corridorof territorial waters for their ore traffic:(d) That it had given us the opportunity ofseiz:&quot;. ng N arvik-(viij) We had had to deal with a country which had refused our offers of help.     When eventuallyNorway had appealed to us for help,  the germans had succeeded in taking possession of all the aerodromes, which had enabled them to achieve an overwhelming superiority in the air.( vill*)    The Territorial Army forces which had formed thefirst contingent sent to Norway had been despatchedwith the object of seizing bases at Andalsnesand Namsos,      It was only after their arrivalthat our hand had been forced &quot;by the NorwegianCommander-: n-Chief, who had stated that unless these troops were sent into the front line tohelp $he Norwegian troops, the latter wouldsurrender,THE PRIME MINISTER said that one of the main points upon which discussion might centre, and upon which,therefore, the War Cabinet would have to decide the line tobe taken, were the step:s which we had taken - in advance ofthe German invasion- to prepare forces for Norway.     be referred to the statements made by Herr von Ricbentrop inhis recent speech.      Our forces had been prepared in viewof the probability that assistance by us to Finland, oraction in Norwegian territorial waters, might provoke aGerman invasion of Southern Norwajr.      Our forces had been intended to forestall the Germans at Bergen, Trondhjemand Stavanger - since if the Germans had got there first, itwould have been very difficult- to push them out - but the e ssenceof our plan had been that we should not set foot on Norwegiansoil unless invited by the Norwegians, or until the germans had first committed a hostile act against Norway.     Thiswas quite clear from the instructions to the Commander of&quot;Stratford&quot; Force&apos;(Enclosure II to W.P. (40) 122).     Itmight well be that the document which Herr von Ribbentrop hadin his possession was an order based on these instructions.

The War Cabinet would have to decide whetheror not to disclose to the House of Commons the contents of these instructions.    He felt it would be best to do so, since they showed that, on the onehand, we had made full preparations for the eventuality, and, on the other, that we had had no intention of violating Norwegian soil until theGermans had done so first.      In this way a completeanswer would impliedly be furnished to von Ribbentrop.There was considerable discussion on thispoint, and various incidents were recalled to show thatit had only been on account of the German treachery to norway that our carefully laid plans had beenforestalled.It was generally agreed that it would be best that the Prime Minister, in making his statement in the House on the operations in Norway, should,without going into unnecessary detail, disclose the plans which had been made,  and the orders whichhad been issued.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that it wouldbe desirable that he should make a statement inParliament that week, probably on Thursday.    The debate would probably take place in the ensuing week.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR informed1heWar Cabinet that at 8 p.m. on the previous night, theDirector of Military Operations had been rung up byone of the General Managers of Reuter&apos;s to say that theirLobby Correspondent had received &quot;from a person inauthority&quot; information that we intended to withdraw from norway,    The General Manager had given instructions

that this news was on no account to &quot;be reported,,The Lobby Correspondent had refused to divulge thename of his informant.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that according tothw Minister of Information our intention towithdraw f.voa Central Norway was already known toscores of people, *THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY felt thatit was inevitable that people were drawing their owninference ass to our? withdraw/a?^cThe War Cabinet took note of theahove statement^

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to   Jfensure the secrecy of this document.MOST SECREToGERMANY.possible intentions.(previous reference:W.M.  (40) 108thConclusions,Minute 8.)COPY NO.   ( ;W.M.(40)  109th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 9.Sonfidential Annex.(1st May,    1940).THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said that inview of the exceptionally large number of mine-laying air-raids the previous evening, orders had been issued forthe action to be taken in the event of a German attackon Belgium or the Netherlands to be held at 12 hoursAction if Holland notice instead of 24Q    As regards the defence of the Belgium is invaded. coast, we must rely for this mainly on aircraft.    More^Reference- than ever, he felt that we should have at least oneW.M. (40) 97th      highly trained Division in this country available to conclusions,Minute 8.) meet a German landing..Invasion of GreatBritain:    Pr*e-cautionarymeasures.(previous reference:W.M.  (40) 108thConclusions,Minute 4.)Air action if holland or belgium is invaded.(previous reference:W.M.  (40) 102ndConclusions,Minute 1.)THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that hehad taken preliminary steps to recall to this country therest of the 5th Division;    the final orders would beissued the following day,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that aGerman attack on Texel at once raised the questionwhether we should bomb targets in the Ruhr, since ithad been agreed with the French that we should attack the oil targets in Germany if the Netherlands wereinvaded by Germany,,    A German attack on Texel would alsocall for a revision of the policy governing our air operations in Scandinavia0    The number of long range bombers at our disposal was not such that we could afford to sustain continuous losses ov to have large numbers of aircraft continually under repair.

The Secretary of State added that it nowlooked as though the Germans contemplated making aseaborne raid on the Netherland   Islands, ratherthan a land invasion across the flooded areas.From their point of view this would he a far more satisfactory operation.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said thatin any previous war we should have been able to seizeTexel;    but, in view of the development of the air arm, it was not desirable to expose.war ships tocontinual air attack in this manner.    This objectiondid not apply, however, to the use of submarines.The most effective answer to a German attack on Texelwould be an immediate air attack by ourselves onthe Ruhr.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that we should at once inform the Netherland Government of thereport we had received, and inquire whether they had any reason to anticipate a German attack and what measures they proposed to take.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he would at once make the inquiries suggested.In the meanwhile, however, it would, he thought,be right for us to assume that such action by theGermans would constitute an invasion of theNetherlands, and would thus free our hands to attack the Ruhr.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed, and added thatthis was fully understood by the French Government.It would, however, be of advantage if the Chiefs ofStaff were no?; once more to examine the action tobe taken.

r13The War Cabinet:-(i) Invited the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to instruct HisMajesty&apos;s Minister, The Hague,  toinform the Netherland Government ofthe report which we had received of a threatened attack &quot;by germany on the Netherland   Islands from Texeleastwards;    to inquire whether theyhad any reason to anticipate suchan attack;    and what measures they propose to take to meet it.(ii) Agreed that an attack by Germany on the netherland Islands would constitute&quot;a German aggression against Holland&quot;(Resolution IV of the 8th Meetingof the Supreme War Council), and thatin the event of a German attack onthe Netherland Islands, the Royal AirForce would be free immediately toattack marshalling yards and oil refineries in the Ruhr.(iii)    Invited the Chiefs of Staffs Committeeto examine in the light of (ii) what action should be taken in the eventof a German attack on the NetherlandIslands.




</content>
</cab>
