<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/60/0 images: 117-130</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HISDOCUMSNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT)EC RET. COPY NO,CABINET    8 (29).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10Downing Street, S.W*1.,  on Wednesday,February 20th, 1929, at 11.50 a.m.AGENDA.1. MILITARY CONTRIBUTIONS OF COLONIAL AND OTHER GOVERNMENTS(Reference Cabinet 60 (27), Conclusion 5).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Wer,CP. 34 (29)    -   already circulated.2. RECQMMENDATIONS, OF COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRS,The Police Magistrates Superannuation(Amendment) Bill.The Industrial Assurance and Friendly SocietiesBill.(Reference H.A. 2nd Conclusions (29)circulated herewith).3. FOREIGN AFFAIRS - if required.4.  CHINA.__REDUCTION IN THE BRITISH FORCES.(Reference Cabinet 52 (28), Conclusion 8).Memorandum by tho Chancellor of the Exchequer,CP. 41 (29)    -    already circulated.(Signed)  M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.February 19th,  1929.
.-TTg^DOCUMEftT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAIN: IC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .C RET. Copy No.CABINET    8  (29) .CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street,  S.W.1.,  on WEDNESDAY,February 20th,  1^29, at 11.^0 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon.  Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P.,  Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.he Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C.B.,Lord Privy Seal.he Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P.,  Secretary of Statefor Home Affairs.fhe Right H0n.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bt. ,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.Ifghe Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.B.E.,C.M.G. ,M.?., Secretaryof State for Air.She Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.&amp;.e Right Hon.W.E.  Guinness, D.S.0.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.&apos;-The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P., Minister ofLabour.The Right Hon.Lord Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Ri^ht Hon.W.S.  Churchill,  C.H.,M.P.,Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion Affaiand Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.The Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Most Hon.The Marquess of LondonderryK.G. ,M.V.O., first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Lord Cushendun, Chancellorof the Duchy ofLancas ter.Sir M.P.A. Hankey,  G.C.B....................... Secretary,
THE POLICE i.The Cabinet bad under consideration a Memo-randum by the Home Secretary (Pa per H.A.-4 (29))covering the draft Police Magistrates Superannuation(Amendment) Bill, together with the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C.2nd. Conclusions (29^, Para.l).In accordance with the latter recommendation the Cabinet agreed  On the assumption that nochange will be made in the presentage limits for compulsory retire-ment in the case of MetropolitanPolice Magistrates^ to authorisethe introdtiction forthwith in theHouse of Cohens of the PoliceMagistrates Superannuation (Amend-rrent) Bill in the for- of the draft annexed to H.A.-4 (29), on theunderstanding that the further progress c&quot;&apos; the Bill must dependon its being treated as uncontro-versisl.MAGISTRATESS UPPRANMJA TI ON(MF-NDMENT)BILL.-1-
1MB industrial assurance and friendly SOCI-E1TIES BILL.(&quot;previous reference:Cabinet 6(28), Con-elusions 8,Appendix,and 14.)2. The Cabinet had before there a Memorandumby the Financial Secretary to the Treasury (paper.A.-3 (29)) covering the draft industrial assurance and Friendly Societies Bill, and an explanatory Memorandum by the Industrial AssuranceCommissioner, together with the recommendation ofthe Committee of Rome Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 2nd.Conclusions (29), Para.2).In accordance with the latter recommendation the Cabinet agreed  To approve the Industrial Assuranceand Friendly Societies Bill in theform of the draft annexed to H.A.-3v29)9 subject to any drafting orether minor alterations which maybe found necessary or desirable,on the understanding -(&amp;) that the Bill will not beintroduced in the House ofCommons until definiteassurances have been receivedfrom the Labour and LiberalOppositions and also fromthe Companies and Societiesinterested that, so far asthey respectively are con-cemedft its provisions willbe accepted without qualifi-cation?    and(b) that its further progressnrcst depend on its be ingtreated as wholly uncontro-versial.
3.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairscommented to the Cabinet on Sir Fame&apos; Howard&apos;sstatement to the Press in America to the effectthat0 now that the 15 Cruiser Bill had become law, it was likely that a further effort wouldbe made before long to reach agreement betweenthe principal Naval Powers for the limitation ofnaval armaments.   Sir Austen Chamberlain believedthat the origin of this incident was a statement the himself had made to the American Press Corres-coorespondents in London at a private luncheon, as theresult of which one Correspondent had sent hiseditor a private communication to the effect that conversations would probably be resumed at anearly date.   This had been shown to Sir EsmeHoward, who, wishing to avoid any appearance ofrudeness by making no comment, had issued thestatement referred to.   What Sir Esm  had said wasnot particularly indiscreet, but it did not perhapssufficiently emphasize that conversations werenot likely to take place immediately, in spite ofhis reference to the fact that the English Elec-tion would probably postpone discussion for sememonths.    Consequently Sir Austen Chamberlain had thought it right to issue a statement to theeffect that the situation had not changed since he informed the House of Commons on February 6ththat His Majesty&apos;s Government were engaged incareful examination or all questions concerningour relations with America and the naval conditions-of the two countries.Sir Austen Chamberlain added that on theprevious day he had had a conversation with the
f 18American Ambassador, who had referred to a phrase-used by the Prime Minister in his speech at theDinner in connection with the British IndustriesPair expressing the hope that if any nation wishedto quarrel the other nations of the world would say &quot;Move on&quot;.   This had corresponded with MrHoughtonTs own thought, and he had asked if thePrime Minister&apos; e intention had been that, if war broke out( all neutrals should place an embargo on the supply of arms to both belligerents until it had been determined which was the aggressor.Sir Austen Chamberlain had indicated that thePrime Minister had probably not intended so muchas that0   This episode, however, illustrated thedesire in America for some kind of sanction for breaches of the peace.Sir Austen Chamberlain had taken this oppcrtu-nity to tell the Ambassador   what, of course, healready knew   that the Government were examiningall these questions relating to Anglo-american relations;    that the Arbitration Treaty was mixedup with the question of Belligerent Rights at Sea,as was the Naval question generally.   Thissubject of Belligerent Rights went back to theroots of our history and required most carefulconsideration, as well as consultation with theDominions.   Mr Houghton had then volunteered thestatement that he could understand that theGovernment might not want to discuss these mattersimmediately before the General Election, and had expressed the belief that Mr Hoover would not bein any great hurry ^  In this way. Sir austen chamberlain explained, he had prepared the way:-4-
f 19for what he understood to be the desire of theCabinet, - to keep open the question of discussions with America on Anglo-American problems beforethe Election.5-
I.MILITARY CON-IR-rBUTlONSIf COLONIALOTHERWBBNMBNTS .(previous^Reference:iCabinet 601(27), Con-jclusion 5.)1204. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for War (Paper C0P.-34 (29))setting out the present position with regard tothe proposals for increased military contributions by Colonial and other Governments contained in theReport (Paper C.P.-298 (27)) of Lord Peel&apos;s Com-mittee, approved by the Cabinet at their Meetingon December 7, 1927.&apos;As stated in the Memorandum in question it hasnot so far been found possible to reach an agreed settlement in the cases of Ceylon, Malta, Bermuda,Jamaica and the Sudan.   In the case of the straits settlements discussions are still proceeding betweenthe War Office and the Colonial Office.     Thegarrison of Sierra Leone has been reduced to asmall care-and-maintenanoe party, the cost ofwhich will be borne by Colonial funds, and theChannel Islands have been Informed that in futureno payments in respect of the cost of the channel islands Militia will be made from Army funds.After hearing statements from the Secretary ofState for War and the Secretary of State for theColonies, the Cabinet agreed   $(a) To take note that the Secretary tfof State for the Colonies was prepared to put further pressure on the rich Colony of Ceylon toincrease its contribution:(b) That the question of payment bythe Sudan of the extra cost ofmaintaining an Air Force S&apos;quadronin that country instead of at. ho: we should be considered as soon asthe conversations on the subjectbetween the Foreign Office andthe Treasury are completed  conversations which the Secretary. of State for Foreign Affairs under-took to expedite as far as possible:(c) That the Secretary of State for theColonies should make a progress reporton the question as affecting the variousColCnies not later than July, 1929.
CHINA.FutureBrxtishGarrisonsin.(previous reference:Cabinet 52(28), Con-elusion 8.)5. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer (Paper CP.-41 (29)urging that complete effect should now be givento the proposal made in November, 1928, &quot;by theSecretary of State for War (Paper C0P.-353 (28))for the reduction of the then total number of8 British Battalions in China to 6, pointing outthat, notwithstanding the views of the british authorities in China   a Battalion had in fact been withdrawn on December 23rd last, and asking for a further reduction in view of the fact thatthere does not appear to have been any recentworsening of the position, and of the burden whichShanghai still imposes on the British Exchequer.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that the British Ministerat Peking was strongly opposed to any reductionin the present garrison;    that the Naval Commander-in-Chief did not regard it as safe;   and that theGeneral Officer Command lng-in-Chief held the same opinion, although he had expressed it rather lessstrongly than the other two.   In these circum-stances he thought the time had not yet come fora further reduction.The Secretary of State for &quot;r&apos;ar did not wish topress for a further reduction at present, as he did not think the situation had materially improvedsince the last reduction *   Moreover, to bring bscka further Battalion would involving taking upa special troopship, undertaking the voyage duringthe hot season, and separating the men of tfe&amp;^^^^vBattalion from their wives, who would have toremain at ^ong-Kongft/Any^C/^w^-^^&apos;^//^J^^yr/U-i ^In these circumstances the proposalfor a reduction of the garrison of hong-Kong was not pressed.
6. The Cabinet had -under consideration thesituation arising out of what had occurred in theHouse of Commons on the previous evening in Gommit-tee of Supply in connection with a motion for a supplementary Estimate not exceeding  70,000 fora grant in aid for compensation to the IrishLoyalists.   After the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs had brought forward a supplementary estimate, with a full explanation of the reasonsfor it, strong opposition had been raised fromthe back benches on the Government side of theHouse which the Chancellor of the Exchequer hadnot succeeded in allaying, and eventually, afterconsultation with his colleagues, the PrimeMinister had moved to report progress &quot;with aview to re-examining the whole situation in thelight of the debates which have taken place&quot;.There was unanimous agreement that the statements made by the Government speakers in the course ofthe Debate had been in full accord with thepreviotis decisions of the Cabinet^ and the membersof the Cabinet who had conferred on the emergencywith the Prime Minister in the ^Touse of Commons onthe previous evening all agreed that the sugges-tions in the Press that there had been any differ-ence o&quot;&quot; opinion between the Prime Minister andany of his colleagues were wholly without founda-tion.   On the contrary, in a very difficult Parlia-menta.ry situation they had been in full accordthroughout.In the course of the discussion various proposals for dealing with the situation weremade, e.g.:-
(i) That the Government, while not themselves admitting that thiswas a debt of honour,  should recognise frankly that many oftheir supporters in the Houseof Commons regarded it as such,and should agree to pay the Wood-Renton recommendations in full,which might involve an additional expenditure of from  350,000 to 500,000:(ii) That the Government should standby their previous decision:should make it clear, by refer-ence to their previous communi-cations to the House of Commons,that this could not be regardedas a debt of honour:    and shouldmake the question one of confidence and put on the Government Whips:(iii) That the Government should announcethatB in deference to the opinion,      of the House of Commons, they would&quot; Commission, but should add that since the House of Commons were now virtually insisting that theWood-Renton Commission^ proceed-ings should be treated as equiva-rlent to those of a judicial insteadof an advisory body, as had been intended, future awards, includingthe 40 per cent, which had not been paid in respect of some of theseawards, would be treated on a judicial basis, but that the treasury would claim the right to be repre-sented by Counsel in order to ensurethat the grants in respect of the outstanding claims are not excessive:(Sy) That the Government should explain the true position with regard to the so-calleddebt of honour and should state that, in deference to the views expressed in theHouse of Commons,  they were willing thatany claimant who did not receive the full amount awarded by the Wood-RentonCommission should have the right eitherto accept payment on the Government basis(i.e.,  1,000 in full and 60 por cent,of the balance) or to  claim that It shouldbe referred to a judicial tribunal todetermine the amount to which he wouldhave been legally entitled under the Irishlav; at the date of the Treaty;    such tribunal should determine the amount due on this basis&apos;(I.e., the debt of honour basis) and thisdecision would finall;/ bind both parties and determine the amount to be paid whethergreater or less than the figure ascertainedIn accordance with the Wood-Rentonrecommendations.
(i) That the Government, while notthemselves1 admitting that thiswas a debt of honour, should recognise frankly that many oftheir supporters in the Houseof Commons regarded it as such,and should agree to pay the Wood-Renton recommendations in full,which might involve an additional expenditure of from  350,000 to 500,000:(ii) That the Government should standby their previous decision;should make it clear, by refer-ence to their previous communi-cations to the House of Commons,that this could not be regardedas a debt of honour:    and shouldmake the question one of confidence and put on the Government Whips:(iii) That the Government should announcethatB in deference to the opinionof the House of Commons, they would pay/rrnr o l the awards alreadyrecommended by the Wood-RentonCommission, but should add that since the House of Commons were now virtually insisting that theWood-Renton Commission&apos;s proceed-ings should be treated as egulva-lent to those of a judicial insteadof an advisory body, as had been intended^ future awards, includingthe 40 per cent. which had not been paid in respect of some of theseawards, would be treated on a judicial basis, but that the treasury would claim the right to be repre-sented by Counsel in order to ensurethat the grants in respect of the outstanding claims are not excessive:that, in deference to the^piniun^of the House of Commons, Jihey would pay in full the awards ^alreadyrecommended by the Wp-da-RentonCommission, but that if any claimantthought that legaKLy he was entitledto a higher awar^d than had beenrecomaended as^an ex gratia grantby the Wood-Kenton Commission and paid by the^Government, lie shouldbe entitled to appeal to a Judicialtribune^ on the understanding thathis claim would be contested bythe ^Treasury and that he might perhaps receive less than the
At the conclusion of a long discussion thePrime Minister asked the Chancellor of theExchequer to consider whether, having special regard to the strong feelings expressed in theHouse of Commons, the beet course would not bethe first, and whetherQ from a Parliamentary-point of view, it would not be advisable for mr Churchill himself to announce the change in policy.    The Prime Minister added that if mr- Churchill, after consideration of the question in all its bearings, came to the conclusion thatsome course similar to the third and fourth,referred to above was preferable, he himself would support him.The subject was adjourned untilthe next Meeting of the Cabinet.
NEXT MF.&quot;mING 7.   In vie&quot;&apos; of the Prime Minister&apos;s publicOP THE CABINET.engagement at Manchester on the followingWednesday, the Cabinet agreed -To meet on Tuesday afternoon at&amp;-3G p0ir.., in the Prime Minister&apos;room at the House of Commons.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,February 20,  1929.-11-

</content>
</cab>
