<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/63/19 images: 268-279</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NOCM(78) 19thConclusions75CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 18 MAY 1978at 10. 30 am present the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp prime minister the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon David Owen mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for the Environment^&quot;he Rt Hon Bruce Millan mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Albert Booth mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Edmund Dell mp secretary of State for Trade*&quot;he Rt Hon John Silkin MPblister of Agriculture, Fisheriesa^d Food^he Rt Hon William Rodgers MPcretary of State for TransportSeThe Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for the Home department the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Education and science and Paymaster GeneralThe Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon David Ennals mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Joel Barnett mp chief Secretary, treasury the Rt Hon Roy Hattersley mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Stanley Orme mp minister for Social security the Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster i
ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Michael Cocks mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat sir John HtfntMr W I Mclndoe (Item 1)Sir Clive Rose (Items 2 and 3)Mr M D M Franklin (Items 2 and 3)Mr P Le Cheminant (Items 4 and 5)Mr P Mountfield (Item 5)Mr D E R Faulkner (Item 1)Mr C H Wilson (Item 4)contents subject parliamentary AFFAIRSEuropean Economic Community Document onLiner ConferencesFOREIGN AFFAIRSZaireSoviet PoliciesRelations with TurkeyZambiaBotswanaCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSCommon Agricultural Policy Price-fixingINDUSTRIAL DEMOCRACY:  DRAFT WHITE PAPERKMOS SEMICONDUCTORS LIMITEDii
J^LIAMENTARY     1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.:,ropean Economic    THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TRADE said that the European^munity Economic Community (e.c.) document R/3245/77 on Liner^ment on Liner     Conferences, which was the subject of a Motion to be debated on&quot;Terences Wednesday, 24 May, proposed that Member States should becomecontracting parties to the United Nations Code Convention on tliii:subject.    The e.c. proposals and the United Nations1 Conventionwere not acceptable in their present form, and the Governmentwould have to decide whether to press for the e.c. proposals to be modified, or to oppose them outright.    One possibility which wou.itprotect the United Kingdom&apos;s interest would be to exempt theOrganisation for Economic Co-operation and Development countriefrom the application of the Code, but the e.c. were unlikely to agrcTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thaiGovernments policy would need to be further considered by the ministerial Committee on European Questions in the first instance,but the issue was an important one, and nothing which damaged our interest should be accepted without reference to the Cabinet.The Cabinet -Took note.1
[0*EIGN^AIRS*ire2. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat the Katargcpe incursion into Shaba had created a dangerous situation with particular risks for the safety of the European expatriatesin Kolwezi, who included 400 French and 24 British and Commonwealthsubjects.    The 3elgi2.na had plans to fly in a force with a view to securing the airfield and they hoped then to be able to bring out theexpatriates in civilian aircraft.    The Prime Minister had agreed onthe previous day to a contingency request from the Belgians to beallowed to stage through Ascension Island on the understanding that thiswould be for the purpose of evacuation and not for intervention in thdispute.    It was however now unlikely that they would want to use tl sroute.    As regards the 24 British expatriates the men had beenrounded up by the invading forces and their dependents confined to thoilhouses.    It might therefore be difficult to get them to the airport.The Americans had no intention of using force except possibly in orderto assist in securing evacuation of their nationals and other expatria*-So far no help on the spot had been asked for from us and the action wabest left to the Belgians.    But we should be ready to consider giving any help which might be required to assist the mounting of the Belgianoperation.The Cabinet -1.Took notePolicies       In a general discussion of Soviet policies, it was pointed out that thesituation in Africa was becoming increasingly complicated and that theRussians were taking every opportunity to exploit the political andeconomic instability which existed in a number of African countries.President Kaunda during his recent visit to London had expressed hieconcern about the situation;  and had given as an example his feeling that President Neto of Angola was unable to get rid of the Russians andCubans who had been in his country since the time of the civil war.One problem was the difficulty of getting agreement on any form ofaction from the United Nations.    This applied particularly to Namibia,where the Western proposal was sound and had been agreed by theSouth Africans but was strongly opposed by the South West AfricaPeople&apos;s Organisations (SWAPO).    SWAPO1 s intransigence was being encouraged by the Russians who were annoyed about the way in whichthe United Nations Interim Foi co in the Lebanon had been set up and claimed that it had been pushed through without their being properlyconsulted.    It was true that the Soviet Union had had some rebuffs inthe Horn and even in Angola, and they had given some assuranceswhich they had maintained, for example that they would not enterSomalia.    Nor had they gone into Eritrea.    But the fact that the Cubanswere able to secure the border with Somalia had freed Ethiopian forces for the Eritrean action.    The Soviet Union was able to use Cuba as asurrogate, but no similar option was open to the United States. Althoughthe Russians exercised caution in the face of firm opposition from theUnited States the situation was a frustrating one for President Carter,2
The time might soon come when, despite their understandablereluctance, the United States might need to involve themselves more directly in peace-keeping operations.    There was a case for greater co-ordination of the Western response to Soviet activities in Africa,and for considering whether we ought not to adopt a more positivelyinterventionist policy.In further discussion it was questioned whether Mr Brezhnev was fullycommitted to the policy of detente.    It was suggested that he wassincere in wanting to achieve nuclear disarmament.    Herr Schmidthad told the Prime Minister that his impression from the recent talkin Bonn was that Mr Brezhnev was anxious to have an early meeting with president Carter.    But in return for their support for his policies ckarms control, Mr Brezhnev might have given his military estab)ishn-.7n:considerable freedom over military expenditure which, accordirr to tAmerican intelligence authorities, was running at about 13 per come.. ofthe gross national product.    Whatever might be Mr Brezhnev&apos;s attiti -to detente, however, the Soviet Union gave the impression of continuallyinfringing the Helsinki agreement.    The prison sentence on Orlov rvasdue to be announced that day and this had made it inappropriate for u:; - jgo ahead with the planned signature of an agreement on sporting contaThere had even been some suggestion that the holding of the Olymp: cGames in Moscow in 1980 should be reconsidered, which was a muchmore serious issue.    So far as we were concerned, the Anglo-Sov&apos; lJoint Commission was due to meet in London from 23-25 May and thequestion of human rights v/ould have to be raised by Ministers withMr Kirillin, the leader of the Soviet team, to whom our views on theOrlov case should be made clear.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the rewere many worrying features about Soviet policies in a number of fieldsHe was not in favour of reacting by means of political gestures whi&apos;-!.were devoid of substance and had no positive purpose.    This was notthe way to deal with a great power like the Soviet Union.    It was muchmore important to stand firm on the tilings that mattered and to workseriously for agreement on lowering the nuclear threshhold, reducingnuclear weapons and arms control generally.    It would be valuable forthe Cabinet to have a wider discussion about Soviet policies and how weshould react to them.    As a basis for this the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary should circulate a paper covering inter aliaSoviet policy in Africa and on detente and human rights.The Cabinet -2.       Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion and invited the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to proceed accordingly.3
rations with THE PRIME MINISTER said that he and the Foreign and Commonwealth&apos;r*ey Secretary had seen Prime Minister Ecevit of Turkey on 15 May. this had been a cordial meeting at which discussion had been mainly aboutCyprus, on which he had urged Mr Ecevit to show more flexibility.Mr Ecevit had stressed the difficulty in which Turkey war. placed by her reliance on the United States for arms supplies, which were nowcut off owing to the Congressional attitude towards the embargo, andhad expressed the hope that the United Kingdom, France and germany would provide arms in the future.    The Prime Minister had said thaithis would need to be discussed in more detail.    Since then it hadbeen reported that Mr Ecevit had come out in opposition to a staterof solidarity with the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation at the Surwhich did not auger well for President Carter&apos;s hopes for a decla m-rtlbia THE PRIME MINISTER said that at his meeting with him on 15 Ma-.he had found President Kaunda of Zambia optimistic about future developments over Rhodesia, possibly unjustifiably so. ThePresident was generally in agreement with the line we were taking ananxious that we should push ahead with our plans for all-Party talks.Our ability to offer him further aid of  15 million had helped to create a favourable atmosphere for the meeting.8*ana THE PRIME MINISTER said that at his meeting on 17 May with president Seretse Khama of Botswana the main problem discussedhad concerned the death of Nicholas Love.    A draft statement hadbeen agreed with President Khama which would be used with the press and in reply to Parliamentary Questions.    This took the line that OiePrime Minister had expressed deep concern over the incidentinvolving the tragic death of Nicholas Love;  that President Khama had expressed his regret and assured the Prime Minister that he was satisfied that Mr Love had not been involved in any illegal or subvc siveactivities;  and that a report on the police investigations in Botswanahad been submitted to the Botswana Attorney General, who would ensure that criminal proceedings were instituted against anyone shown to have acted improperly.    The statement would end by recording taatthe Prime Minister was glad that the good name of Nicholas Love hadbeen vindicated and had welcomed President Khama&apos;s assurance thatnormal Botswana legal procedure would be followed.    The PrimeMinister said he thought that this statement would be accepted as satisfactory by Mr Love&apos;s parents and others who had expressed concern over the case.The Cabinst -3.       Took note.4
J^munity&apos;fairs^culturalfey Price-;Jetence:pit) 16thfusions,^te 33. THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOODsaid that the long discussions over Europeer. Economic Communityagricultural prices were completed last week with an average increaseof 2,\ per cent, the lowest increase since our accession to the communities.    It represented a reduction in real terms. Afterdifficult negotiations, he had secured the continuation of the milk marketing Boards without time limit, and had resisted proposals whichwould have put their operations at risk whenever there was a change the green rates.   We had gained  26 million on the butter subsidy andavoided a reduction in the autumn of this year.    Strong Danishopposition had made it impossible to secure more than a limitedreduction in the monetary compensatory amounts (MRCA&apos;s) on pigme-;The continuation of beef premia in the United Kingdom had been ass 5although the possibility of an increase in the contribution from Communiifunds would have to be taken up again later.    We had also secured usefulfinancial contributions from the Community for the construction of Cshiiijboats and a modification in the calculation of MRCA&apos;s which would as., tour exports of biscuits and confectionery.    While it had been possible&apos;,delay agreement on two of the proposals for improving the structureMediterranean agriculture, the agreed measures to assist French andItalian Mediterranean producers were nevertheless very substantial.THE CHIEF SECRETARY, TREASURY, said that officials were stillexamining the budgetary consequences.    It was clear that there would be some claim on this year&apos;s contingency reserve and the new proposalsfor the Mediterranean area represented a significant liability for thefuture.    Despite the success in holding down prices, our contribution tothe Community budget would continue to rise.    We secured no effec;help from the Germans in trying to hold down the cost of the common agricultural Policy (CAP).THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said that theCabinet congratulated the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food on what he had achieved.    However, the budgetary consequences ofthe CAP remained a matter of concern.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister1 summing up.5
I^STRIALjJtoOCRACY:^T WHITE^ERevious&apos;erence:&apos;(?8) 17thfusions,cute 44. The Cabinet considered a note by the Secretary of State for education and Science and Paymaster General (CP(78) 58) which hadattached at Annex C a revised draft of the White Paper on industrial democracy, and at Annex A a note setting out a number of amendments which had been proposed.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE and paymaster GENERAL said that the text of the White Paperattached at Annex C to CP(78) 58 took account of the amendments ofa purely drafting nature which had been suggested by Cabinet colleagues on the version of the White Paper which she had circulated in theprevious week.    Some of the amendments proposed had not been incorporated as she considered that they required prior considerationby Cabinet.    These were set out in Annex A.In discussion of the amendments proposed in Annex A to CP(78) 58 it wajagreed that, in paragraph 1 of the White Paper, &quot;characterised&quot;should be changed to &quot;marked&quot;;  that paragraph 12 should be leftunchanged except that in the fifth sentence &quot;could delay&quot; should bereplaced by &quot;would be able to delay&quot;;  that the heading to paragraph 13should be amended to read &quot;What would happen if companies do notcomply with their statutory obligation?&quot;;  that the first sentence to paragraph 22 should be replaced by the sentence proposed in Annex Aby the Secretary of State for Employment;  that the last sentence ofparagraph 26 should be deleted and the replacement sentence set oui. in annex A inserted at the end of the fifth sentence in that paragraph;that paragraph 32 should be amended to include a sentence to read&quot;The Government does not exclude parity as an ultimate outcome&quot; andthat any consequential amendments should also be made; that paragraph 37 be left unamended;  and that the amendments proposedin Annex A to paragraph 57 should be accepted.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that,subject to the amendments agreed in discussion, the Cabinet nowapproved the White Paper.    Publication date should be Tuesday23 May.    He would make a statement in the House of Commons on that day and would also take the lead at a Press Conference. Hewould like the Secretaries of State for Employment, Trade and education and Science to attend the Conference.    The Secretary ofState for Trade should arrange for copies of the White Paper to besent in confidence to the Trade Union Congress and the confederation of British Industries shortly before the time of publication.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister and in-rited theSecretary of State for Trade to be guided accordingly.
5. The Cabinet had before it a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Industry (CP(78) 59) proposing that the national enterprise Board (not) should be authorised to invest  50 million in a new company, KMOS Semiconductors Limited, to manufacturesilicon chip micro- circuits in the United Kingdom.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that recentrapid developments in electronics technology had producedcomponents which combined many thousands of different functic -very cheaply into a single very small &quot;chip&quot; of silicon. Thesr.chips were capable of a very wide range of application withinindustry, both in consumer goods, consumer durables and heavy plant.    These developments would have very big industrand social consequences.    The United Kingdom could not star.Aaside from the development of this technology.    The question was whether it should develop a manufacturing capability of it.:own.    The not had received a proposal from a group of large.American businessmen who wished to set up a company in thiscountry to manufacture &quot;standard1 (as opposed to &quot;special&quot;)silicon chips.    It would involve an investment of  50 million by the not, while the &quot;founders group&quot; of businessmen wouldmake a small personal investment.    In exchange, they would receive very large rewards if the project were successful.The aim was to reach a turnover of  140 million, or 10 per cent of the relevant world market, by 1982.    The not, aftercommissioning reports from leading consultants, unanimously agreed to support the proposal.    There were other potentialdevelopments in the same field.    The General Electric Comp;Limited (G.C) in conjunction with the American companyFairchild and the International Telephone and TelegraphCompany Limited (ITT) were also considering investment inthe United Kingdom, though probably on a smaller sfale, andalso requiring Government support.    These proposals were ata very early stage, and the KMOS scheme was the only fully developed project available.    In his view it would be a mistake to reject the first large original new venture proposed by theNEB, which was entirely consistent with the role theGovernment had always planned for it.    A majority of the ministerial Committee on Economic and Industrial Policy had supported the proposal at their meeting the previous week, andsome of the Ministers concerned had since met Sir Leslie MurphyChairman of the not, for discussion of the details of the plan.In discussion, there was general agreement that the UnitedKingdom must develop the domestic manufacture of silicon chips.It could not afford to be left behind by its competitors. however the social implications of the new technology were enormous.Many hundreds of thousands of jobs might be at stake.    In Jheoffice sector alone, which was one of the few remaining growthareas of employment, as many as 90 per cent of existingemployment could be lost in some sectors.    The Government^toossemiconductorsLimited7
had a responsibility to start thinking about these problems,and the Prime Minister had already arranged for theSecretary of the Cabinet to let him have a report on how this could best be arranged.In discussion of the KMOS proposal, it was first stressed thatan early decision was needed if the project were to be able totake advantage of market developments in the early 1980s.It was also essential to secure the services of certain individuals who could not remain available indefinitely.It was next argued that the roles of the not and of Ministersneeded clarification.    The Government had established theNEB, in contrast to the old style of public ownership throughstate corporations, in order to fill a vacuum in private sectorrisk taking.    The KMOS proposal was precisely the kind ofventure which the not was designed to undertake.    The NEBand its Chairman had put their own reputations at stake on thisscheme.    Ministers were not good at taking entrepreneurialdecisions.    They should be content to accept the not&apos;s judgment,on the argument that one does not keep a dog and bark oneself.On the other hand, it was argued that the not, impressed bythe imaginative proposahof KMOS, had acted impulsively, andwere now seeking to force Ministers into an early decision.They were under a statutory obligation to consult Ministersabout investments on this scale.    It was for Ministers to takepolitical judgment about such matters.    For example, thedecisions to support the development of nuclear energy, or the rb 211 aero-engina,    had been political decisions not commercialones.    A similar political judgment was needed here, and itturned on the need to establish a British presence in the micro-electronics market.    Such a &quot;make British&quot; policy was a necessarycomplement to the &quot;Buy British&quot; initiative recently taken by theGovernment.    In any case, the issue having been laid before theCabinet, Ministers could not evade a decision.In further discussion it was suggested that the material availableto Ministers did not permit a full evaluation of such an ambitiousproposal.    It was a mistake to be too impressed by consultants&quot;reports, which were inevitably slanted to give the requiredresult.    The not forecast a very rapid expansion of sales, toa turnover of  140 million by 1982.    This was not necessarilyincredible, given the circumstances of the particular industry,but the risks were high.    It was not clear why the &quot;foundersgroup&quot; had chosen to develop in the United Kingdom.    The Americanmarket might be saturated, but there were alternative locationsin Europe and Japan.    Against this, there was probably no other government which would be prepared to venture  50 million on similar terms.    The scale of investment proposed wasdisturbing.    Although  25 million out of the total  50 million8
would be committed at once, this was too much for the designstage alone.    Yet if the project were already at a stage whereit was right to commit funds to manufacturing investment,then it was likely that other competitors were also in a positionto start investing.    It was unlikely that a new venture couldcompete on equal terms with major established companies.In further discussion of the alternative means of developing a united Kingdom manufacturing capacity, it was pointed outthat the sector working party (SWT?) concerned had recentlychanged its appraisal of the appropriate strategy.    They were now recommending the establishment of a British manufacturinc;capacity for &quot;standard&quot; as well as &quot;special&quot; chips.    But the SWwhich included representatives of most of the main potentialrivals, did not know about the KMOS proposal.    Nor did the NEBhave details of the possible developments by other companies,although it knew of these in general terms.    Indeed, these companies had not formulated precise plans yet.    If the probler::of commercial confidentiality could be overcome, it would be right to ask not to evaluate these alternative proposals. Inany case, the Secretary of State for Industry should discussthose plans himself with the companies concerned so that theCabinet could compare them with the KJvIOS scheme.    In theabsence of planning agreements, existing knowledge of their plans within Government was necessarily fragmentary.    It wasnot certain that other companies would wish to go ahead. G.C,who would in any case resist co-operation with not, were knownto be seeking an agreement with Fairchild, but Fairchild&apos;srecord in recent years was not very successful.   ITT had amanufacturing capacity in the United Kingdom.    But there wererisks in encouraging developments by foreign based multi-nationals, particularly if they did not have Research andDevelopment facilities here.    However, the KMOS proposalsdid not represent a totally new technology.    Essentially theyconcerned the development of existing discoveries to a newlevel of sophistication.    This was the sort of thing better leftto large companies with considerable resources.In discussion of the proposed financial arrangements, it was argued that there was a case for high rewards for highly-valuedscarce skills.    But the scale of these in the present proposal was unprecedented and could be highly embarrassing to theGovernment.    The &quot;founders group&quot; would eventually hold30 per cent of the equity in the company for an investment of only  87, 000;  no individual would contribute more than  15, 000.These particular terms had probably been designed to securethe most favourable treatment under United States tax law.No United Kingdom company could match these terms, or indeed would bo allowed to.    A deal of this kind would createproblems for the not in respect of its other subsidiaries. it
was inconsistent with the Governments own egalitarianphilosophy, and with the particular stance it was adoptingon the present Finance Bill.    However, it was also argued that the Cabinet should concentrate on the problems of wealthcreation, leaving normal United Kingdom taxation to deal withthe distribution of profits when they arose.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussrion,  said thatthe Cabinet wished to support the development of a UnitedKingdom manufacturing capacity for silicon chips but was divided on the merits of the KMOS proposal.    In thesecircumstances they must rely heavily on the advice of the responsible Minister provided he had access to all the relevant information.    Before asking the Cabinet to take a final decisionon the KMOS proposal the Secretary of State for Industry should therefore have early discussion with those electronics companiewhether British or foreign owned, who were known to be interested in establishing manufacturing capacity for siliconchips in the United Kingdom.    He should seek to establish thescale - of their plans and the extent of Government supportthey would seek.    In the light of this he should give his views to the Cabinet which would resume its discussion of the KMOSproposal at its next meeting.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister1 6summing up of their discussion and invited theSecretary of State for Industry to proceed accordingly.Cabinet Office18 May 197810

</content>
</cab>
