<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/100/0 images: 28-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT).S3QRET. CABINET,      . &apos;M0.P.-8Q4. THE ADRIATIC QUESTION.Note from American. Ambassador, forwarding President Wilson7s Reply to French and British Prime ministers Memorandum of 26th February, 1920 (Paper No.CP.746).No.169.The American Ambassador presents his compliments to His Majesty&apos;s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and with reference to Mr.Davisfe communication No.163 of March 5, and 167 of March 6, *19SO, has the honour to state that the United States Government will release for publication on Monday morning next the President1s latest note on the A&amp;ri-atic question.London,6th March, 19EO.
LONDON,--March 6, 1920.No .167. My Lord:-.With reference to my Note 163 of yesterday, I have the honour to inform Your Lordship that I am now in receipt of a telegraphic communication from my Government transmitting a corrected version of the Presidents Note on the Adriatic question, a copy of which I enclose herewith.It appears that there were several very serious errors in transmitting yesterday&apos;s message from Washington.1 am also sending an identic copy of the corrected version to Monsieur Cambon.I have the honour to be,with the highest consideration My Lord, Your most obedient,  ( humble servant, (Sgd)    JOHN W. DAVISThe Right HonourableEarl Curzon of Kedleston, K.G., &amp;c ., &amp;c.., &amp;c.,The Foreign Office.
&quot; The Ere s i dent. ^eBirea^to-crri^eesJh^^ and cordial interest in the response of the Frenchjaiid^ British Prime Ministers received on February 27.     He notes with satisfaction their unaltered desire to reach &quot;an equitable solution in conformity alike with the principles of the Peace Conf sren-ce and of the legitimate though conflicting aspirations of the Italian and Jugo-Glav peoples&quot;.     He further welcomes their expressed intention regarding certain essential points &apos;to urge upon the Governments interested that they should bring their desires into line with the American point of view&apos;.The President is surprised, however, that they should find in the statement of his owri willingness to leave to the joffint agreement of Italy and Jugo-Slavi; *&apos;:.:3 settlement of &apos;their common frontiers in the Piume region&apos;, the ground for suggesting the withdrawal of the Joint Memorandum of jDecember 9* In this he could not possibly join.     The Memorandum represents deliberate and disinterested judgment after months of earnest discussion.     It constituted more than a more exchange of views;   it was a        i statement of principles&apos;and a recapitulation of the chief points upon which agreement had been reached. There was thus afforded a summary review of these points of agreement of the French, British and American Governments and the Memorandum should remain as it was intended to be the basis of reference representing the combined opinion of these Governments.
In referring to the Tcomon^fronl7ie:r^^ region1 the President ha a in mind the express desire of&quot;the tvo interested Governments to abandon the project of the Free State of Fiume as defined in the memorandum of December 9.   If, as he understands, the Government of Italy and the Government of the Serb-Croat-Slovene State prefer to abandon the so-callea. buffer state containing an overwhelming majority of Jugo-Slavs, and desire to limit the proposed Free State to the corpus separatum of Fiume, placing the sovereignty in the League of Nations without either Italian or Jugo-Slav control, then the Government of the United^ States is prepared to accept this proposal and is willing under such circumstances to leave the determination.of the common frontier to Italy and Jugo-Slavia. In this connection the President desires to reiterate that he would gladly  ,       approve a mutual agreement between the Italian and Jugo-Slav Governments reached without prejudice to the territ-orial or other interests of any third nation.   But Albanian questions should not be included in the proposed joint discussion of Italy and Jugo-Slavia and the President must reaffirm that he cannot possibly approve any plan which assigns to Jugo-Slavia in the northern districts of Albania territorial compensation for what she is deprived of elsewhere.   Concerning the economic outlets for Jugo-Slavia in the region of Scutari, suggested in the note under reply, the President desires to refer to the memorandum of December 9 as making adequate provisions to meet the needs of Jugo-Slavia,Regarding the character ana applicability of the Treaty . of London the President is led to speak with less reserve on account of the frank observations of the i-rench and British Prime Ministers.   He is unable to find in the Exigencies of military strategy&apos; sufficient warrant for exercising secrecy with a
Government which was intimately associate &amp; ,withMxliex^ of the Treaty of London in the gigantic task of defending human freedom and which-was being called upon for unlimited assistance and for untold treasure.     The definite and well accepted policy of the American Government throughout its participation in the deliberations of the Peace Conference was that it did not consider itself bound by secret treaties of which it had previously not know the existence.   Where the provisions of such treaties were just and reasonable the United States was willing to respect them.   But the French and British Prime Ministers will of course not expect the Govern-ment of the United States to approve the execution of the terms of the Treaty of London except insofar as that Government may be convinced that these terms are intrinsically just and are consistent with the maintenance of peace ^and settled order in Southeastern Europe.     The absence of an American representative, v;ith plenary powers is to be regretted and may have been a source of inconvenience but the President can recall several instances where decisions in the bupreme Council were delayed while the British and French representatives sought the views of their Governments and he is convinced that time would have been saved and many misunderstandings avoided if before actual decisions had been reached and communicated to the Italians and Jugo-Slav delegations this Government had been given.sufficient indication of the fact that the British and French Governments intended radically to depart from the memorandum of December 9.In conclusion the President desires to express his concurrence in the views of the British and French Irirae Minister-? that a speedy settlement of the Adriatic question is of urgent importance.     But he cannot accept aH just the implied suggestion of his responsibility for the failure to reachxa solution.   He
has merely adhered.to the provisions of a settlement which the French and British Governments recognised as equitable in the joint memorandum of December 9 and has declined to approve a new settlement negotiated without the knowledge or approval of the American Government which was unacceptable to one of the interested Governments and which in his opinion was in direct contradiction of the principles for the defence of:which America entered the war.   These views he has fully explained in his note of February 10th, and he. ventures to express the earnest hope that the Allied Governments will not find it necessary to decide on a cour;   * &apos;.JLch the American Government ina ccordance with its reiterated statement, will be unable to follow.&quot;-6-

</content>
</cab>
