<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/100/0 images: 238-241</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DISABILITY PENSIONS COM IT TEE.Interim Report-on. Disability Pensions inpresent, war cases .-   1.   The Committee was set up by a decision of the Finance Committee of the Cabinet (Eighteenth Meeting., Conclusion l) to consider the Admiralty proposals in regard to Disability Pensions.. The Committee have agreed to    the following recommendations as regards present war cases., to take effect as from 1st April 1919* 2,    Definition of Present Tar cases.These are defined as covering the oases of(a) men discharged with disability during the course of the war, and(b) men discharged after the war on account of disabilities recognised by the Ministry/of Pensions as attributable to service in the present war.3&apos;   %basic rate of. pension for men discharged during, the war for disabilities not attributable to service-.The following rates are &quot;recommended:-Continuous Service Men only.. Continuous Service Men, Non Continuous Service MenX, and Royal Marines.The Admiralty will add the usual additions for rank, ete. according to the new service scale.ARMY.There is no rate for less than 14 years service The other daily rates set out above, viz: over 14 years l/6;    over l6 years, l/9:    over 18 years, 2/-:overx   This is a technical Navy tern and refers to certain special classes such as- officerh* stewards and nooks.Over 10 years&quot; 16 &quot; &quot;18 &quot; 11   20     &quot;NAVY. l/- a day. l/6 a day.) l/9 a day ) 2/-. a day J 2/6 a day )
Vta Admiralty and wiJLl^WMtofr^^imHXj^tl^for rank, etc., go in the new service scale. 1The Committee put foward the above recommendation as the best which they can frame in all the circumstances: .it does not neoessarily imply the adoption of a eiiilar principle for post-war cases.     It is olear that no solution can bo devised whioh would be completely satisfao-tory to all the Departments concerned.     That reoommended above has the practical advantage that it will obviate the administrative inconvenience and delay which would result from the recalculation of numerous existing disable-ment allowances.5.    Attributable cases where no permanent disablement pens ion has&apos; been&quot;&quot;awaj-d ed .fa) In oases of temporary disablement the -service allowances set out in.paragraph 4 above will be paid in addition to disablement pension.     When the disability is ended and the disablement pension withdrawn the man will revert to the rate set out in paragraph 1 above.     The conditions of entitlement will be the same as those set out in paragraph 3.(b) Men with an attributable disability of less-than ZQffo will receive service allowance under paragraph 3 above together with a gratuity under the Pensions Warrant based on disablement alone.6.     gratuities in respedt of service.The Admiralty proposal as to gratuities for less than 10 years&apos; service was considered bdt, after explanation of what was done by the Ministry of Pensions, It appeared that in the majority of oases thejnen were better off than if they received the proposed service gratuity but lost the service element in their gratuity from the Ministry of Pensions.     If cases arise where the men would be worse off it may possibly be neoessary for the Ministry of Pensions to reconsider the service allowanoe now given for less then10 years/
over 80 years, 2/6: will apply to tire following classes of so Idlers :-(a) re-engaged men,(b) men re-enlisted to complete a term of service v/hich, with former service, makes a total of at least 2,1 years.(e) men who have had the above periods of continuous colour service although.they may. not have re-engaged.A minimum of 10 years colour service will he required in all cases to qualify for the new rates, .The v7ar office will add the usual additions for rank according to the new service scale.4.        lioale of service allowance in addition to Disablement Pension in attributable cases.It is recommended that the full disability pension should be paid and in addition the following service allowances to the classes described in Paragraph 3;veekly hate Old hates for recommended.     comparison.Army, navy.Over 10 years(Navy only)	v-	-	3/6Over 14 years.	.0/-	4/8	3/6&quot;15     &quot;	8/-		4/8&quot;   16	&apos;     9/-	5/3	4/8&quot;   17     &quot;	9/-	5/6f	4/8&quot;   18     &quot;	10/-	-   .5/10 .	5/3&quot;   19     &quot;	10/-	6/5	5/3n    go      n	11/-		5/3&quot;   21     &quot; (Navy only).	11/-	-	5/3The
(Sgd.) STAKE,BY BKDWINM T.I).   .JA1P&apos;S&quot; P. PHILLIPS&quot; W. SMGTjJR&quot; J.A. SMITHVJhitehall Gardens, g ,w. l. 12th March, 1920.10 years&apos; service.   The War Office are not in favour of either gratuity or allowance for men under 14 years&apos; service.7.   with the possible exception of a few minor points, which can be settlec by discussion between the Department the above recommendations, if approved, dispose of the question referred to the Committee so far as concerns present war cases.   The Committee will now proceed to consider post war cases.(Chairman). (War Office). (Admiralty). (Treasury). (Ministry of pensions (Air /Force).P.?/. Leith Ross   (Secretary).

</content>
</cab>
