<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/100/0 images: 318-321</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
11 ft A ,   r\ &apos; ,L   *11&apos; ^  &apos;(r&apos;&apos;\il&quot; iOOCbVLWi&apos; lij Tlir P^OPioTY OP MIS &quot;:RITAi :niC &apos;iAJ? f&apos;;TY&apos;B GO^mmSHT.).^&quot; :    263&apos;SEC T( J T,&quot; CABINET* 1G.F, 875* yINTOXICATING LIQUOR (tUGULATIOi?) BILL,Memorandum by the ^resident, aoarrl of Education *1*        It is desirable that the Cabinet&apos;s decision on the Government Llmior Bill should be taken before the debate on the Private .&quot; ember &apos;s Sill for ..elsh Temperance, which stands first on mhe t.rder Paper for Friday, the 2Gtty!:arch,    Some member of the Government must speak and will be seriously embarrassed if the Government Bill is still in the air,2.j       The main purpose of the Uolsh Bill is to provide for local option for no-licences or for reduced licences, without compensation, after a time limit of six years.     It follows generally the Scottish Act of 1913, but it attaches far more drastic results to a &quot;no-licence&quot; resolution and in a &quot;no-licence&quot; area cuts off every source cf supply of dm ink (including hotels, restaurants and clubs), except the private house cellar, which could be kept replenished from sources of supply outside the area,    The killing of the&apos;-working men&apos;s club and the sparing of the private cellar amounts to class legislation, such as the Government cannot support.r3,       Temperance advocates ought now to concentrate on measures which can be put in force at once, and \t%th more advantage to sobriety than is offered by these heroic aspirations.    This shoul be the main line for the Government in the debate.    But it is impossible to work it out effectively, and shew where and how the Vfelsh mill would prejudice the more sober measures which the  &apos; Government have in mind, unless the leading principles of the Governments Bill have been defir tely settled beforehand.4.      -The summary of the Government Bill submitted to theiCabinet by the Minister of Pensions, though not entirely accuratein
n some matters of detail, mo Jf in r-eneral be accepted.    Ho uraws attention pointedly to the controversial character of many .pf the provisionsj but that has been recognised from the first, an&apos;&apos;; has to be faced,,-5. -       I agreo with the   Inister of Pensions that the local Option and trie Ttate Purchase Clauses of the Licensing Bill will inevitably arouse tho opposition of the Trade.     Per contra the Public house Improvement Clauses will excite antagonism in T emp e r aiic e circles.6.-       It is only necessary to deal with the four difficulties mentioned at the bottom of page 4 of the i enorandum submitted by ths minister of Pensions 1. Clubs.&apos;It is recognised, of course, that the principle of equality of treatment between clubs and licensed premises will encounter formidable opposition from the clubs;   but Sir Li. &quot;Worthington 5&apos;vans agrees that the principle is necessary and that the opposition must be faced,^L^J,0,Ca&quot;LTl?f^vSyoct of the Local Option Clauses is the reduction of redundant licences., a reform acknowledged to be necessary not only by Temperance enthusiasts but by enlightened members of the Trade and, as the Minister of Pensions points out, this object could be more effectually attained by the provisions contained in the Alternative Clauses for an all-round increase in the compensation levy a-    I have no special affection for Local Option myself and on the merits should prefer a system under which reduction could be carried out simultaneously and on a concerted plan throughout the country*    On the other hand, the alternative is more severe to the Trade than the Local Option Clauses of the Bill and is likely, at the same time, to be a great deal more attractive to *the*.advocates of Temperance.     Local Option^ in some form or other, is an item In all Temperance programmes.   To the argument that the limitation of local option to reduction of licences contained in the Government Bill, with no option forprohibition
prohibition, is illogical, it may be replied, that the principleof trie &quot;&quot;-ill is that compensation it to be paid for the extinction of licences and that if Local Option were extended to prohibition, the sources from which compensation la derived would be, entirely cut off.     It would, therefore, i..:c cuite impossible to extend the -present Local Option 3chene so as to include prohibition, without abandoning the fundamental principle adopted in the &apos;0ill that the houses which are left pay compensation for those which are suppressed. I do not therefore see any difficulty in resisting amendments to introduce local option for prohibition.I am also doubtful whother if tho Local Option Clauses were dropped, the Government could proceed with the Public House Im-S provement Clauses without running the risl: of being charged with 1tohaving brought in a Bill unduly favourable/the interests of the Trade.   &apos;3, tote m^Qii^m -spO- h-.n-,aei^n^.   .fl&quot;1 -)lJ &apos; 1   &apos;M   &quot;       &apos;     &apos;    &apos;     W ill&quot;--LlLIJfJ-     IIIIU  U. ...    MM     Ull   ISir L. fcth^t^^vanff1  &apos; oolnt that the Bill makes no provision for payment for the property taken over by the State is based on a misapprehension.    It had been considered that the Acquisition of Land (Assessment of Compensation) Act, 1919, subject to any supplementary or modifying provisions made In a Provisional Order, would ipso facto, and without express inclusion, apply to the assessment of the purchase price.     If thought desirable, ffor^   making this application express could be easily found,    But the insertion of such words would pKewise the hostility of the Labour r-arty and others, who hold that no departure from the Summer Committee terms of purchase or: pre-war profits should he made;   it may be wiser to ta?e the sense of the House, before insisting expressly on tho Act of 1919. 4. General.. The main point, however, raised in the Memorandum is whether the Bill should be restricted to the very narrow object of continuing, fdr a short period, the powers exercised by the Liquor Control Board or whether it should attempt to deal with the following three matters
(a) the reduction or redxri&amp;ant licences.(b) the Improvement of public housesj(c) the ortcnriion, on demand, of State Purchase areas. My general view is that the Government would find very great support in the Country for each of those three reforms.   The support, It is true, uoulA not corse from the same quarter in each case.   The TraOe would oppose (a) and (c) and favour (b); the Temperance Interest would favour (a) and (c) ami oppose (b); tho Extremists on either side would oppose all the Bill, but I believe that the moderate opinion of the Country vould rally round the Government in its endeavour to secure those three main objects.   It should also be remember-ed that even the moat limited Bill will arouse oontrovreray. We cannot escape a fight with the Clubs over the regulation of hours question, and in view of the large number of Members of the House who are now keenly interested in the Carlisle experiment and desirous of seeing it extended, there would be general disappointment if there were nothing in the Bill to show that the Government were willing to test the advantages of State Purchase in other parts of the Country.   Whatever we do we must excite some controversy.   I think that in this case, with an electorate now to a large extent consisting of women, a moderate dose of valour will prove to be the better part of discretion.(intldi)   H.F.Board of Education,16th March, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
