<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/100/0 images: 432-436</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THIS PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITAiTSTC HAJESTT&apos;1 3 ^OT^Km^JSB CRST,Copy No&quot;.t, .P. 896.CABINET. TREATY OP PEACE WITH TURKEY.MISCELLANEOUS ARTICLES.Copy, of letter from Sir M. Harikey,, to President,jyra.fi i ng Commit t s a, *(Ciroulated for information), v J2 Whitehall Gardens,London, S.W,1*18th March, 1920.Sir,I am directed by Mr. Lloyd George to enclose herewith Draft Articles for insertion either in the Political or Miscellaneous ehapters in the Treaty of Peaae with Turkey dealing with various miscellaneous matters including Archaeology in Turkey;   the disposal and return of Archives; the cessation, inter alia, of the authority of the Sheik-ul-Islamat over ceded or transferred territories;   access to the Turkish Department of Wakfs;   and Amnesty.All the above were approved by the Conference of Ambassadors and Poreign Ministers now meeting in London.I&quot;am directed, however, to call the attention of the Drafting Committee to the fact that tSie Draft Clauses regarding Antiquities in Turkey which were the work of expert archaeologists were approved in principle, but the Conference expressed a desire that the Drafting Committee should examine them with a view to the detection of any legal flaws. .I am to request that the Drafting Committee will take the necessary steps to include Articles based on these drafts in the Treaty of Peace with Turkey.I amSir,President,Driuting Comm.i11ee.Your obedient Servant,(Sigrtd)   K. ?. A. Hankey.
LGKiORANDUL&apos;1 BY BRITISH DELEGATION FOR SUBMISSION TO THE COUNCIL OF FOREIGN MINISTERS AND AMBASSADORS,The British Delegation propose the following draftarticles for insertion either in the Political or Lligcellaneouschapters of the Treaty of Peace with Turkey:Nos. 1 and 2 deal with Archaeology in Turkey;No. 3 deals with the disposal and return of archives.No.4 deals with the cessation, inter alia, of the authority ofthe Sheik-ul-Islamat over ceded or transferred territories.No.5   deals with TQK-^ey&apos; s connection with the Hedjaz Railway, No.6   deals with access to the Turkish Department of Wakfa. No. 7   deals with Aaaaesty, &apos;The Turkish Government will, within twelve monthsjfrom the coming into force of the present Treaty abrogate the existing law of antiquities and take steps to enact, and will thereafter execute, a new Law of Antiquities on the basis of the instructions contained in the Annex hereto,      The terms of the said Law shall be submitte/d to the Financial Commission for approval before being submitted to the Turkish Parliament.      In executing this law the Turkish Government shall observe complete equality towards al -nations.Annex.TV r:  &quot;Antiquity&quot; means and construction on any product of human activity-earlier -than tne year 1700,2,     Any person who, having;.disco,yered. an antiquity without being furnished with the authorisation contemplated in Article 5 below, reports the same to an officer of the Ministry of Public Instruction shall be recompensed according to the value of the object.     The principle to be adopted should be to proceed $y.- encouragement rathei-than - by threat.&quot; &apos;&apos; &quot;*1 v&apos;&apos;x Thio is the qualified Turkish Department. .
3.     Ho antiquity may &quot;be sold except to the aboveMinistry;     but if this Department renounces the acquisitionof any antiquity that antiquity may then be freely sold.No antiquity may leave the country without an export licencefrom the said Hinistry. y4.     Any person who maliciously or negligently destroys ordamages an ancient object or structure shall become liable toa penalty to be fined,5.     Ho clearing of ground or digging with the object of finding antiquities shall be permitted, under penalty of fine, except to persons authorised, by the above Ministry. 6.     Equitable terms for expropriation, temporary or permanent, of lands which might be of historical or archaeological interest shall be fixed.7,     Authorisation to excavate shall only be granted to persons who show sufficient quarantees of archaeological experience,, The Turkish Government shall not in granting these authorisations, act in such a way as to eliminate scholars of any nation without good grounds,8.     The proceeds of excavations may be divided between the excavato??/and the Ministry of Public Instruction in a proportion fixed by this Liinistry.   If division seems impossible, for scientific reasons, the excavator shall receive a fair indemnity in lieu of a part of the find,All objects of. religious, archaeological, or artistic interest which have been removed since (1st August, 1914) from any of the territories which now cease to form a part of the Turkish dominions will within (12) months from the coming into force of the present Treaty be restored by the Turkish Government to the Government of the territory from which such objects were removed
If any such   objects have passed into private ownership, the Turkish Government will take the necessary steps by expropriation or otherwise to enable them to fulfil their obligations under this ArticleLists of the objects to be restored under this Article will be furnished to the Turkish Government by the Governments concerned within (6) months fib in the corning into force of the present treaty1&quot;.&apos;Turkey will hand over without delay to the Governments concerned archives, registers, plans,- title-deeds and documents of every kind belonging to the civil, military,&apos;financial,  judicial or other forms of administration in the transferred territories.     If any one of theae documents, archives, registers, title-deeds or plans is missing, it shall be restored by Turkey upon the demands of the G o ve rn me at e o n c e rn e d.In case the archives, registers, plans, title-deeds.or documents referred to in the preceding paragraph, exclusive of those of a military character, concern equally the administrations in Turkey, and cannot therefore be handed over without inconvenience to such administrations, Turkey undertakes, subject to reciprocity, to give access thereto to the Governments concerned&quot;.No authority shall be exercised by any functionary of the Sultan 02 tho Turkish Government in any territory which in ac cor ranee with the terms of t.- e present Treaty ceases to form part of Turkey, or of which the existing status is recognised
recognised by Turkey under the present Treaty&quot;.&quot;5. The Turkish Government abandons whatever rights itpossesses over the Hedjaa railway, an6 accepts such arrangements as shall be made for its working, and for the distribution of the property belonging to or used in connection with the railway, by the Governments concerned. In any such arrangements the special position of the railway from the religious point of view shall be fully recognised and safeguarded&quot;.&quot;6. The Turkish Government undertakes, subject toreciprocity, to afford to the Governments exercising authority over territory severed from Turkey under the present Treaty access to all archives and documents relating to the administration of   Wakfs in such territory, or to particular tfakfs, wherever situated, in which persons or institutions established in such territory are interested&quot;.&quot;7, Without prejudice to the provisions of chapter.......(Penalties) no inhabitant of Turkey shall be disturbed or molested, under any pretext whatever, on account of any political or military action taken by him, or any assistance of any kind given by him to the Allied Powers, or their nationals, between August 1st, 1914 and the coming into force of the present Treaty;   all sentenoesp&amp;ssed against any inhabitant of Turkey for the above reasons shall be completely annulled and any proceedings already instituted shall be stopped&quot;.

</content>
</cab>
