<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/167/4 images: 144-166</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT(? PCP(73) 4 COPY NO16 January 1973CABINETBAHAMAS INDEPENDENCE CONFERENCE 1972Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign and CommonwealthAffairsI circulate for the information of the Cabinet the draft of a White paper i propose xo publish giving the agreed report on the Bahamas IndependenceConference held in London last month.    My statement to the House on21 December (a copy of which is attached) summarised the main resultsof this conference.    Agreement was reached on the substance of a future constitution and I undertook to recommend to Parliament the passage of aBill to provide for the Bahamas to become independent on 10 July 1973.The new constitution will includo safeguards ensuring the rule of law, therights and freedoms of the individual, and the maintenance of theconstitution, and provisions for the acquisition of Bahamas catieapjahip&quot;at the time of independence.    Unless I hear to the contrary from mycolleagues I propose to publish the White Paper on 18 January.A D-foreign and Commonwealth Office16 January 1973
EXTRACT FROM HANSARD, Volume 848, No 38Dated THURSDAY 21 DECEMBER 1972BahamasMr Michael McNair-Wilson asked the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs if he will make a statement on the Bahamasindependence conference.Sir Alec Douglas-Home:  The Bahamas Jidependence conference was successfully concluded yesterday at Malborough House having been openedby myself on 12 December.    The plenary sessions were under thechairmanship of my right hon Friend the Minister of State and my hon,Friend the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs,,    A White Paper containing the report of the conference will belaid before Parliament as soon as possible.After full discussions in which all sides had opportunity to explain theirviews, the conference agreed on die substance of a constitution appropriate to the Commonwealth of the Bahamas as an independent sovereign state.Throughout their deliberations the conference had in mind their responsibility for ensuring that decisions were taken in the best interestsof all the people of the Bahamas, whatever their race, colour or creed.Particular attention was paid to the need to provide constitutionalsafeguards ensuring the rule of law, protection of the rights and freedomsof the individual, the independence of the judiciary, the impartiality ofthe public service and the maintenance of the constitution itself.The Bahamas delegation to the conference expressed the wish that onindependence the country should remain a monarchy and indicated that theGovernment of the Bahamas would apply for membership of the Common-wealth.    Her Maj estyrs Government in the United Kingdom have undertaken to sponsor the Bahamas application for Commonwealth membership and touse their best endeavours to facilitate applications by the Bahamas for membership of the United Nations and other international bodies.The Bahamas Government agreed that on independence diplomatic relationswould be established between our two countries by the setting up of HighCommissions in London and Nassau.The present bicameral form of legislature will be retained.The life of a Parliament will be limited to five years from the date of its first sitting after any dissolution.
The Prime Minister will preside over a Cabinet consisting of not lessthan eight other Ministers of whom one will be the Attorney-General.    Inhis responsibility for public prosecutions the Attorney-General will actentirely on his own responsibility and aot be subject to the direction or control of any other person or authority.There will be a Supreme Court presided over by the Chief Justice and alsoa Court of Appeal.    Provision will be made in the constitution for appealsto the Judicial Committee of Her Majesty:s Privy council or to such other courts as may be prescribed by the Bahamas Parliament.Responsibility for the public service, police and judicial service will lie with independent executive commissions as atpresent0Provisions were also agreed to safeguard the position of past and presentmembers of Her MajestyTs Overseas Civil Service in the Bahamas inrespect of pensions and other matters.Satisfactory arrangements were also agreed for safeguarding theconstitution.    The more important provisions of the constitution may be amended only if there have been affirmative votes carried by each Houseof the legislature by a three-quarters majority followed by approval ofthe amendments by simple majority in a referendum.    Certain other provisions mey be amended by a similar process, except tnat the majorityrequired in the legislature will be two-thirds.The Bahamas Government proposed, and it was agreed, that citizenship of the Bahamas 3hould be automatically acquired at the time of independence by:a0 Every person who, having been born in the BahamaSjis a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies.b. Every person born outside the Bahamas who, on the dayof independence, is a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies,if his father, having been born in the Bahamas, becomes or would, but for his deaths have become a citizen of the Bahamas;and that after independence citizenship should be automaticallyavailable to:c. Every person born in the Bahamas of a Bahamian parent.d. Every person born outside the Bahamas after independence whose father was born in, and is a citizen of,the Bahamas.
Particular consideration was given to the position of persons whoimmediately before the independence of the Bahamas are citizens of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies solely by reason of their connection with the bahamas as compared with citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonieswho have qualifying ancestral connections with the United Kingdom or aremaining United Kingdom dependency at the time of Bahamaeindependence.It was agreed that at the time of independence Bahamas citizenship wouldbe extended automatically to all citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies who acquired that status by naturalisation or registration in the bahamas, with the exception of:a. persons who have dual nationality;b. those registered persons who are not ordinarily resident in the Bahamas at the end of 197?-;c. persons registering after the end of 1972;d. naturalised persons who indicate that they do not wishto accept Bahamas citizenship.The Government of the Bahamas indicated that they would assume alltreaty obligations and rights pr jviously undertaken by Her MajestyssGovernment on their behalf, on the understanding that within a reasonable time the new State would review in detail such treaty obligations with aview to their continuation or termination.Her Majesty&apos;s Government indicated that it would be prepared torecommend to Parliament the passage of the necessary legislation toprovide for the independence of the Bahamas on the desired date of10 July 1973.    The British Government undertook that before that datethey would be ready to discuss with the Bahamas Government futuredefence and financial arrangements.
CONFIDENTIA L-FINAL REVISE[to be published as Command 5196 by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery office price I3\p net]Miscellaneous No. 4 (1973)Report ofThe BahamasIndependence Conference1972
ContentsReport of conference i. Introduction.....................II. The Constitution    ..................III.   Other Matters        ..................AnnexesA. List of those attending the Conference   .........B. Speeches by the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs, the Prime Minister of theCommonwealth of the Bahamas and the Leader of theOpposition in the Bahamas at the Opening Session   ...137472
REPORT OF THE BAHAMAS INDEPENDENCECONFERENCE HELD IN MARLBOROUGH HOUSE,LONDON, IN DECEMBER 1972I.  INTRODUCTIONAs a result of the decisions taken at the Bahamas constitutional conference in London in September 1968 (the report of which was published as Cmnd. 3791) a new constitution was conferred on the Bahamas andcame into force by Order in Council in April 1969.2. That conference agreed that changes should be made in the Bahamas(Constitution) Order in Council 1963 so as to give the Government of the bahamas an advanced constitution as the final step towards independence.The Bahamas thus became fully self-governing internally, the Governorbeing responsible only for defence, external affairs and internal security, andin respect of the last two subjects some powers were entrusted to the bahamas Ministers.3. On 8 March, 1972, the Bahamas Government laid before theLegislature a Green Paper outlining its proposals for an independent commonwealth of the Bahama Islands. Subsequently, in September 1972, ageneral election was held in which the Progressive Liberal Party (PLP)won 30 of the 38 seats in the House of Assembly, the Free NationalMovement (FNM) winning the remaining eight.4. On 18 October the Prime Minister, the Hon. L. O. Pindling.presented to the Bahamas Parliament a White Paper on Independence forthe Commonwealth of the Bahamas. After a debate in both Houses of theLegislature a Resolution was passed on 2 November, without a dissentingvote, expressing the desire of the people of the Bahamas to proceed to independence in 1973 and requesting that Her Majesty&apos;s Government in theUnited Kingdom be requested to convene an independence conference to implement their wish.5. The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairsaccordingly invited the Government and Opposition to send delegates to anindependence conference in London.6. The conference met at Marlborough House and held 10 plenarysessions between 12 and 20 December, 1972. The list of delegates and officials who took part in the conference is at annex A. The Secretary ofState for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, the Right Hon. Sir AlecDouglas-Home, presided at the opening session, while the plenary sessionswere conducted under the chairmanship of the Right Hon. Lord Balniel, m p,and Mr. Anthony Kershaw, mp. The texts of the speeches at the openingsession are at annex B.137472n*2
7. In deciding upon the substance of the provisions to be includedin the independence constitution reference was made to the Bahama Islands(Constitution) Order 1969, a draft constitution prepared by the BahamasGovernment representatives, and a memorandum commenting on the BahamasGovernment proposals prepared by the Opposition representatives led byMr. K. G. L. Isaacs.8. After full discussion in which all sides had opportunity to explaintheir views, the conference agreed to the substance of a constitutionappropriate to the Commonwealth of the Bahamas, as an independentsovereign State.9. Throughout their deliberations the conference had in mind their responsibility for ensuring that decisions were taken in the best interestsof all the people of the Bahamas, whatever their race, colour or creed.Particular attention was paid to the need to provide constitutional safeguardsensuring the rule of law, protection of the rights and freedoms of theindividual, the independence of the judiciary, the impartiality of the publicservice and the maintenance of the constitution itself. To this end theconference agreed that the following provisions should be made in theindependence constitution.II.  THE CONSTITUTION10. The constitution will be the supreme law of the Commonwealth ofthe Bahamas and will prevail over any other law.Governor-General11. There will be a Governor-General who will be appointed by the queen and will hold office during Her Majesty&apos;s pleasure.Fundamental Rights12. The constitution will include provisions safeguarding the fundamentalfreedoms of the individual regardless of race, place of origin, political opinion,colour, creed or sex. These fundamental freedoms will include the right tolife, liberty, security of the person and protection from arbitrary arrest;protection from discrimination; the enjoyment of property and the protectionof law; the freedom of conscience, freedom of movement, freedom of expression and assembly, and respect for private and family life. Theright to freedom of movement will include the right to leave the Bahamassubject only to restrictions imposed by law in the interests of defence, public safety, public order, public morality, public health or the public interest, orof securing compliance with any international obligation of the Bahamas.As an exception from the provision giving protection against arbitrarydetention only non-citizens will be liable to be restricted to or excluded froma particular area and only in circumstances of unlawful entry into the Bahamasand for the purpose of their expulsion, extradition or other lawful removal from the Bahamas.** It was agreed between the Bahamas Government and Opposition delegates that thereshould be party political broadcasts on matters of public interest during the period between general elections. The Bahamas Government agreed to amend the rules governing political broadcasts to allow for the allocation of time for such party political broadcasts.
13. All fundamental rights will be subject to enforcement by theSupreme Court. Provision will be made to permit, subject to safeguards,derogation from certain fundamental freedoms in time of war or during anemergency.14. The period during which a proclamation for a state of emergencycan remain in force without being extended by a vote of a majority in theHouse of Assembly will be limited to six months. There will be provisionunder which laws made before independence, and laws made after independence which re-enact existing laws or which vary such laws withoutincluding new elements, will not be challengeable under the provisionssafeguarding Fundamental Rights, but regulations and orders made after independence, or executive acts done under such laws after independence,will not be so exempt from challenge.Parliament15. The present bicameral form of legislature, with a House of assembly and a Senate, will be retained.16. The Senate will consist of nine members appointed by theGovernor-General on the advice of the Prime Minister, four members appointed by the Governor-General on the advice of the Leader of theOpposition and three members appointed by the Governor-General on theadvice of the Prime Minister after consultation with the Leader of theOpposition. The appointment of these last three members will be made withthe purpose of securing that the political balance of the Senate reflects thatof the House of Assembly at the time.17. The House of Assembly will initially consist of 38 members, butthis number may be increased by an Order approved by the House following a recommendation from the Constituencies Commission. If the number ofmembers is increased the quorum in the House will be adjusted accordingly.18. The President and Vice-President of the Senate and the speaker and Deputy Speaker of the House of Assembly will be elected respectivelyby the Senate and the House of Assembly from within their ownmembership.19. Parliament will be prorogued or dissolved by the Governor-general on the advice of the Prime Minister, provided that if the Prime minister has lost the support of the majority of the House of Assembly the Governor-General will dissolve Parliament if no successor can otherwise be found.In any event Parliament will not continue for more than five years from thedate of its first sitting after any dissolution. In times of war howeverParliament itself may extend its life for a period not exceeding 12 monthsat a time up to a maximum of two years.Disqualification from membership of Parliament20. No person will be qualified to remain a senator or a member of theHouse of Assembly if, inter alia, he knowingly becomes interested in any government contract unless he has disclosed such interest to the Senate, or
House of Assembly respectively, and been exempted from disqualificationby the Senate or House. If, however, he is not so exempted, there willbe a right of appeal to the Supreme Court, which may exempt him on being satisfied that he was unaware of his interest in a contract and actedreasonably.Delimitation of constituencies21. There will be a Constituencies Commission which will at intervals of not more than five years review the number and boundaries of the constituencies into which the Bahamas is divided and if necessary make recommendations to the Governor-General. Orders giving effect to such recommendations will require the approval in draft by the House of assembly. Parliament may make provision for a right to challenge in theSupreme Court the recommendations of the Commission on the grounds thatthe Commission has departed from the principles laid down by theconstitution for such a review.The ExecutivePrime Minister and Cabinet22. The Governor-General will appoint as Prime Minister the person from the House of Assembly who, in his judgment, is best able to command the support of the majority of the members of that House. There will be aCabinet consisting of the Prime Minister and not less than eight other ministers (of whom two will be the Attorney-General and the Minister ofFinance). Ministers and Parliamentary Secretaries will be appointed bythe Governor-General acting on the advice of the Prime Minister from among the Senators and members of the House of Assembly.The Leader of the Opposition23. There will be a Leader of the Opposition who will be the personwhom the Governor-General considers to be the member of the House of assembly best able to command the support of the majority of those membersof the House who do not support the Government; or, if there is no such person, that member of the House who in his judgment commands thesupport of the largest single group of such members who are prepared tosupport one leader. In the event of there being no Leader of the Oppositionbecause no person is both qualified and willing to accept appointment, then the requirement that in certain cases the Prime Minister must consult the leader of the Opposition before advising the Governor-General, will notapply, and the Governor-General will in those cases act on the advice of thePrime Minister.A attorney-General24. The Attorney-General will be responsible for public prosecutions.In the execution of this duty he will act entirely on his own responsibility and will not be subject to the direction or control of any other person or authority.
The Judiciary25. There will be a Supreme Court consisting of the Chief justice and such number of other justices as may be prescribed by Parliament.The Chief Justice will be appointed by the Governor-General on therecommendation of the Prime Minister after consultation with the leader of the Opposition.26. There will also be a Court of Appeal for the Bahamas consistingof a President, the Chief Justice and such number of Justices of Appealas may be prescribed by Parliament. Provision will be made for appeals from the Court of Appeal to the Judicial Committee of Her Majesty&apos;privy Council; or to such other court as may be prescribed by Parliament.27. The constitution will include provisions under which Parliamentmay give effect to arrangements for a Court of Appeal shared betweenthe Bahamas and one or more other Commonwealth country.The Public Service28. There will be Commissions responsible for the Public Service,Police, and Judiciary similar to those existing at present. Each will advise the Governor-General on appointments within its sphere and onthe exercise of disciplinary conUol. A Public Service Board of Appealwill be constituted to which an officer may appeal against removal fromoffice or any penalty imposed upon him by way of disciplinary control.The definition of Public Service will be such as to permit exclusion of employees in such organisations as the Department of Tourism.Pensions29. The terms of reference of the Public Service Board of Appealwill also provide for a right of appeal against any decision to withhold,reduce or suspend any pensions benefits or against any disciplinarydecision which might affect such benefits. Pensions benefits of HMOCSofficers will be freely remittable from the Bahamas to their country of residence, subject only to reasonable exchange control regulations.Finance30. The authority for expenditure from public funds will be anAppropriation or Supplementary Appropriation law. The House of assembly will have power to authorise expenditure for the period fromthe beginning of the financial year until the passing of the AppropriationBill. Where at any time the Appropriation Bill in respect of any financialyear has not come into operation by the beginning of that financial year,the Minister for Finance may to such extent and subject to such conditionsas may be prescribed by Parliament issue a warrant for the payment outof the Consolidated Fund the necessary monies for the continuance ofthe public service.31. Parliament may by law provide for the establishment of aContingencies Fund and authorise the Minister for Finance to make advances from that Fund when there is an unforeseen need for expenditure for which no provision has been made by an Appropriation Act.
32. The cost of administering the public debt of the Bahamas,including redemption, will be charged on the Consolidated Fund.Compensation of HMOCS Officers33. Provision will be made to preserve the regulations as to compensation to HMOCS officers as a result of constitutional changes,and to provide for appropriate modifications to these regulations.Amendments of the Constitution34. Those provisions of the constitution relating to the legal force ofthe . constitution, citizenship, the protection of fundamental rights andfreedoms, the establishment of Parliament, its sessions, prorogation anddissolution, the appointment of senators, the determination of membership of the House of Assembly, the power to make laws, alterations to theconstitution, the executive authority, the cabinet and the Supreme andAppeals Courts shall be specially entrenched and may be amended only ifthere have been affirmative votes carried by each House of the Legislatureby a three-quarters majority followed by approval of the amendments bya simple majority of the electorate in a referendum.35. Those provisions relating to the. establishment of the office of governor-General and the exercise of : his functions, the qualifications,disqualification and tenure of office of senators and members of the Houseof Assembly, the Public Service and Finance shall be entrenched and maybe amended only if there have been affirmative votes carried by each Houseof the Legislature by a two-thirds majority followed by approval of the amendments by a simple majority of the electorate in a referendum.36. The other provisions of the constitution may be amended by a simple majority vote in each House of the Legislature.Citizenship37. The Bahamas Government proposed, and it was agreed, thatcitizenship of the Bahamas should be automatically acquired at the timeof independence by:(a) Every person who, having been born in the Bahamas, is a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies;.............(b) Every person born outside the Bahamas who, on the day of independence, is a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies, if his father, having been born in the Bahamas, becomes or would,but for his death, have become a citizen of the Bahamas;and that after independence citizenship should be automatically acquired by:(c) Every person born in the Bahamas after independence of a Bahamianparent;(d) Every person born outside the Bahamas after independence whosefather was born in and is a citizen of the Bahamas.38. Particular consideration was given to the position of persons whoimmediately before the independence of the Bahamas are citizens of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies solely by reason of their connection with
the Bahamas as compared with the citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies who have, qualifying ancestral connections with the UnitedKingdom or a remaining United Kingdom dependency at the time ofBahamas independence.39. It was finally agreed that at the time of independence Bahamascitizenship would also be extended automatically to . all citizens of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies who acquired that status by naturalisationor registration in the Bahamas, with the exception of:(a) persons who have dual nationality;(b) those registered persons who are not ordinarily resident in the bahamas at the end of 1972;- (c) persons registering after the end of 1972; and&quot;(d) naturalised persons who indicate that they do not wish to acceptBahamas citizenship.III.  OTHER MATTERSTreaty Succession40. The Government of the Bahamas indicated that on independencethey would assume all treaty obligations and rights previously undertaken by the United Kingdom Government in relation to the Bahamas, on theunderstanding that they will wish within a reasonable time to review indetail such treaty obligations with a view to their continuation ordiscontinuation.Commonwealth Membership41. The Bahamas Government signified its intention of makingapplication for entry into the Commonwealth. The British government undertook to sponsor the Bahamas application. The British government also agreed to use their best endeavours to facilitate the applications by the bahamas for membership of the United Nations and other international bodies.Diplomatic Relations42. The Governments of the Bahamas and the United Kingdom agreedthat on independence diplomatic relations would be established betweenthe Government of the Commonwealth of the Bahamas and the UnitedKingdom Government and that High Commissions would be opened inLondon and Nassau.Financial and Defence Matters43. The Governments of the Bahamas and the United Kingdom agreedthat before the date of independence there should be discussions betweenthe Governments of the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth of the bahamas concerning financial and defence matters.
Honours44. The Government of the Bahamas agreed that until further noticeBahamian citizens will remain eligible for United Kingdom honours followingindependence.Imperial Lighthouse Service in the Bahamas45. It was agreed that the Government of the Bahamas would assumeownership of and administrative responsibility for the lights and propertiesof the Imperial Lighthouse Service in the Bahamas from the date of independence.Date of Independence46. The British Government representatives confirmed the BritishGovernment^ readiness to recommend to the United Kingdom parliament the passage of the necessary legislation to provide for the independence of the new state, to be known as the Commonwealth of the Bahamas, onthe desired date of 10 July, 1973.
Signed at Marlborough House, London, this twentieth day ofDecember, 1972.UNITED KINGDOMLord Balniel, Minister of state. KershawBAHAMASL. O. Pindling, Prime MinisterGovernmentOppositionK. G. L. Isaacs, Leader of theOppositionM. B. ButlerA. D. HannaC. E. FrancisN. S. SolomonA. A. FoulkesO. A. TurnquestC. T. MaynardA. L. RokerP. L. Adderley, Leader of the Government in the Senate and Ministerof StateP. BethelH. BowenC. ArmbristerG. A. SmithG. D. M. CollettGOVERNOR AND COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF, BAHAMASSir John Warburton PaulSECRETARY-GENERALR. Butters
ANNEX ALIST OF THOSE ATTENDING THE CONFERENCEUNITED KINGDOMThe Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, kt, m p, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Balniel, m p, Minister of State for foreign and Commonwealth affairs mr. A. Kershaw, m c, mp, Parliamentary Under-Secretary for foreign and Commonwealth AffairsOfficialsSir Duncan Watson, kcmgMr. D. A. Scott, cmgMr. C. S. roberts mr. A. R. Rushford, cmgMr. A. M. Greenwood, mcMr. C. G. MortlockMr. J. H. FawcettCOMMONWEALTH OF THE BAHAMASSir John Warburton Paul, gcmg,obe,mc, Governor and Commander-in-ChiefBahamas GovernmentThe Hon. L. O. Pindling, m p, Prime minister the Hon. M. B. Butler, m p, Minister without portfolio the Hon. A. D. Hanna, m p, Deputy Prime Minister and Ministerfor Home AffairsThe Hon. C. E. Francis, mp, Minister for Finance and development the Hon. C. T. Maynard, m p, Minister for Tourism and aviation the Hon. A. L. Roker, mp, Minister for HealthSenator, the Hon. P. L. Adderley, Leader of the Government inthe Senate and Minister of StateMr. P. Bethel, mp mr. H. Bowen, mp mr. C. Armbrister, m pMr. G. A. Smith, m p
Bahamas OppositionMr. K. G. L. Isaacs, c b e, q c, m p, Leader of the OppositionSenator the Hon. O. A. Turnquest, Leader of the Opposition inthe SenateMr. N. S. Solomon, m pSenator the Hon. A. A. FoulkesAdvisersUnited kingdom mr. E. R. HargreavesMr. C. O. adams mr. W. M. LeeMr. B. DaviesMr. A. ParkinsonMiss D. E. WrightMiss K. J. HimsworthBahamas GovernmentMr. G. D. M. Collett, qc, Attorney-GeneralMr. R. L. Wood, Financial secretary mr. T. B. Donaldson, Chairman of the Monetary AuthorityMr. E. T. Strachan, Acting Deputy Permanent Secretary, Ministry of external affairs mr. A. Cox, Director of the BudgetBahamas OppositionMr. E. Dupuch, cbe, qcSir Arthur Grattan-Bellew, cmgSecretariatMr. R. Butters, Secretary-GeneralMr. P. Rogan, Assistant Secretary-General
ANNEX BSPEECH BY THE RIGHT HON. Sir ALEC DOUGLAS-HOME, kt,m p, SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AND COMMON-WEALTH AFFAIRS, AT THE OPENING SESSION ON12 DECEMBER, 1972Your Excellency, Honourable Prime Minister, Honourable Leader ofthe Opposition, Senators and Honourable Members of the House of assembly of the Commonwealth of the Bahamas: May I on behalf ofthe British Government welcome you all to London and thank you all for accepting our invitation to come for this conference, so important forthe destiny of your country.It is particularly appropriate that we should be meeting here in thishistoric Marlborough House. It was here in 1968 that the constitutiongranting self-government to the Bahamas was moulded. The conferencestarting today is therefore the continuation of that process, the bringingof the Commonwealth of the Bahamas to independence and full sovereignty.It has long been the declared and sincere policy of successive british governments to lead the dependent territories of what was once theBritish Empire to independent status. Then they can stand on their ownfeet and be counted among the free sovereign nations in their own right.The policy really started with Lord Durham&apos;s great report on the affairs of British North America in the 1830&apos;s. From this report emergedthe philosophy of granting self-government to dependent territories and encouraging them along the way to full independence. This philosophyhas remained at the heart of our constitutional efforts.The most recent territories to have achieved independence have beenTonga and Fiji in 1970, but no fewer than 36 overseas territories for which britain was formerly responsible have attained full sovereign independence.Their population totals some 900 million people. Leaving aside the associated States in the West Indies, there remain now only 18 dependent territories for which the United Kingdom continues to be responsible.They have a population of something over 5 million people. The secondlargest is the Bahamas which enjoys the most advanced form of constitution short of full independence.I want to repeat the well-known policy of Her Majesty&apos;s government towards the future of the remaining dependent territories. Our guiding principle is to respond to the wishes of the peoples concerned. It is notour intention to delay independence for those territories who want it; noris it our wish to impose it on those who do not.You, Mr. Prime Minister, have recently held an election in the Bahamasat which early independence was the main issue. You won this electionwith a large majority and 60 per cent of the popular vote was in favourof the policy of independence. Furthermore, Honourable Leader of theOpposition, your party was not against the principle of independence,
though you favoured its coming at a somewhat slower pace. So there is this identity of interest between you, and a resolution in favour of independence has passed through your legislature without a dissentingvote. I therefore trust that this conference may produce the full agreement on constitutional arrangements which will serve the Bahama Islands,guaranteeing the future stability of the new state and the democratic rightsof its peoples.Mr. Prime Minister, your legislature has, even in advance of thisindependence conference, passed a resolution that the Bahamas should seek to become a member of the Commonwealth. I understand that thisis the first time that a territory on the threshold of independence has passed such a resolution in advance even of preparing its independenceconstitution.Your Excellency, Honourable Gentlemen, I have no wish at this stage,at this formal opening of your independence conference, to touch on thebusiness which will be proper to the conference itself, but I am confident that your deliberations under the chairmanship of the Minister of State,Lord Balniel, will be fruitful and that from this meeting will emerge anindependence constitution which will fulfil the hopes and desires of thepeople of the Bahamas. So these are our hopes, and I wish you very wellin the conference which lies ahead.I would like, if I may, to invite Mr. Pindling and Mr. Isaacs to makea few remarks to us at this opening stage.SPEECH BY THE HON. L. O. PINDLING, mp, PRIME MINISTEROF THE COMMONWEALTH OF THE BAHAMAS, AT THEOPENING SESSION ON 12 DECEMBER, 1972Your Excellency the Governor, the Right Hon. Secretary of State, theRight Hon. Chairman of the conference, the Hon. Father of our emergingnation, my Hon. Deputy Prime Minister, the Hon. Leader of theOpposition, distinguished delegates to this conference, ladies andgentlemen: some 480 years have gone by since Christopher Columbuslanded on the island of San Salvador and the Bahamian archipelago ofislands, rocks and cays lost their sovereignty in man&apos;s ancient andunrelenting quest for possessions and riches. Some 325 years have goneby since one of those islands, the one known as Eleuthera, attempted tore-establish her sovereignty in a political entity separate and apart fromthe remainder of the islands in the archipelago but the attempt failed.The quest may be just as unrelenting today, but nevertheless, we theofficial delegates to this historic conference and the true representativesof the Bahamian people have been singled out by those same people tobe the instruments through which and by which that long lost sovereigntywould be regained.  We are happy to be here on such an occasion.Mr. Secretary of State, the national delegation of the Bahamas to this conference comprises both Government and Opposition representatives, and,on their behalf, I should like, firstly, to thank Her Majesty&apos;s Government
for so readily agreeing to host this conference at relatively short notice and,secondly, to thank you for your very kind words of welcome. We deem ita signal honour that you. personally were able to convene this openingsession of our conference. I have little doubt that this conference, underthe capable chairmanship of the Right Hon. Minister of State, will be fair,fruitful and without rancour. I am reinforced in this view by reason of thefact that every single delegate to this conference believes in the principleof independence, a point to which you, Sir, have already referred.Standing now, therefore, at the daybreak of freedom, our islands havinggraduated from all the schools of constitutional, economic and socialphilosophies, we seek to pledge ourselves and our countrymen to thereconstruction of our land so that no man or woman or child shall everagain be slave or bondsman and we seek to enshrine in our and their heartsthe indivisible unity of our nation to be.SPEECH BY Mr. K. G. L. ISAACS, cbe,qc,mp, LEADER OF THEOPPOSITION IN THE BAHAMAS, AT THE OPENING session on 12 DECEMBER, 1972Right Hon. Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs,Your Excellency, Hon. Prime Minister, distinguished delegates, ladies andgentlemen: I would like, first of all, on behalf of my delegation, to thankthe Right Hon. Secretary of State for the courtesies extended to us since our arrival in London to attend this historic conference. I would like alsoto express our gratitude to the officers of the Bahamas Government whohave assisted us since our arrival.  To all of you our sincere thanks.I have stated that this is an historic occasion. It is an important eventin the life of the Commonwealth of Nations and it is perhaps the mostimportant event so far in the life and development of the Commonwealth ofthe Bahama Islands.Though far-fiung and small, the Bahamas has been able to develop amodel of the British parliamentary system of democracy which is one ofthe most treasured possessions of our people. Indeed, the BahamasParliament ranks among the most ancient in the Commonwealth and, welike to think, amongst the most honourable as well.By contrast with some territories, our progress has been steady and orderly. We have managed on occasion,, however, to generate enoughpolitical heat to demonstrate the vitality of Bahamian life and intenseinterest which many of our people hold in the public affairs of their country.As I am sure all of us here are aware, the Free National Movement hasthe support of 40 per cent of the Bahamians who voted in the recentelections, a 40 per cent who feel that independence for our Commonwealthat this time is both unnecessary and unwise. Nevertheless, we recognise the necessity for a responsible opposition realistically to accept thedeclaration of a majority of the Bahamian electorate, albeit only amarginal not an overwhelming majority.
If independence for the Bahamas is indeed now at hand, then we saythat there is a grave responsibility for each of our delegations so to co-operate in a spirit of give and take that the Bahamian people will therebygain as much as possible. Let us proceed mindful of the fact that thefuture of a great little country and a fine people will be influenced for goodor for ill by what we do here in this conference hall over the days ahead.That is why we of the Opposition are here today. We intend to play a vigorous part in the drafting of a fair and just independence constitution for the Bahamas. We are fully committed to carry out our functions asenergetically as possible within the framework of the constitution. we hope that our participation will contribute to peace and prosperity underthe present administration. Nevertheless, as we contemplate the onerousburdens which fall upon the Government let me hasten to assure the PrimeMinister and his colleagues that we will take the first constitutionalopportunity to relieve them of those burdens.Right Hon. Secretary of State, distinguished delegates, in spite of ourups and downs over the centuries, we in the Bahamas have enjoyed agood fortune which is almost legendary. I hope it is an omen of furthergood fortune that we have come together to perform this great task in the advent of the holiday season. At least, I hope that the Yuletide will inspireus to work out our problems in a spirit of mutual affection and respect.More important, it is my further hope that our affection and respect forour people will lead us to produce for them the gift of a strong anddemocratic constitution which will stand the test of time and which willwithstand the attacks of any would-be tyrants.Then, when we have finished our work, as much as we are enjoying ourstay in this great city, we would like to express our gratitude to our Englishfriends for their hospitality and to wish them a merry Christmas as wereturn to our own islands in the sun.20902-7   3137472  Dd. 2507S0  K      1/73



</content>
</cab>
