<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 8-9</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.P.(56) 202COPY NO18th August, 1956.CABINETSALE OF SHIPS TO TURKEYMemorandum by the First Lord of the admiralty the Turkish Government wish to buy:-1448DIDO Class Cruiser&apos;M&apos; Class DestroyersBATTLE Class DestroyersBAY Class FrigatesThey have sent Admiral Arnom to this country with authority to purchaseall these ships, to make arrangements for their refits, and to buy thenecessary stores and spares.2.      There are two difficulties about this:   one is the availability of destroyers, and the other is the possible financial risk of the wholetransaction.3.      The cruiser and the frigates are available, and there is no othercustomer for them, but we have no BATTLE Class destroyers to spare:the only destroyers we now have for sale are four &apos;M&apos; Class and three&apos;Z&apos; Class.     Moreover although we have not yet received firm orderswe know that the Spanish Government are interested in buying threecruisers and twelve destroyers, and the Peruvian Government two &apos;Z&apos;Class destroyers.    An immediate decision is needed about makingdestroyers available to the Turks because, apart from the embarrassmentof not being able to give a definite answer to a purchasing mission in thiscountry, we may at any moment receive a firm order from the Spanishor Peruvian Government.4.      Admiral Arnom says that unless we can provide at least the four&apos;M&apos; Class destroyers his Government may not want anything.    On theother hand he understands that we may not be able to release all or anyof the three &apos;Z&apos; Class destroyers because of our possible commitments to other countries.    He has asked that the refit contracts should beplacedona Government-to-Government basis because the Turks havenot the experience or the staff to deal directly with contractors.5.      As for the financial aspect of this transaction, the size of theTurkish requirement and the undertaking to pay in cash are both un-expected.     It is particularly surprising that the Turks in their present financial position can contemplate this sort of expenditure without asking for credit. If we let the Turks have 1 DIDO, 4 &apos;M&apos;s and 8 BAYS, thetotal purchase price for the hulls &apos;as lying&apos;, even at the depreciated
original cost - which on political grounds I would propose to allow -would be over  if millions.     Refit costs would hardly be less than 5 millions, and the cost of first outfits of stores would be about lif millions.     With base spares, the total bill would not fall far short of  10 millions.     The sale of three &apos;Z&apos;s to Turkey would add another 2 millions or so to this figure.     Turkish financial officers will be joiningAdmiral Arnom&apos;s staff shortly and we may learn more then about wherethe money is to come from.6.      If the Turkish financial position were sounder I imagine therewould be no hesitation in agreeing that the Tirks should have all of theships they ask for.    On political and strategic grounds we should want tosell to Turkey rather than to Spain or Peru;   and if the Turks were thefirst to place their orders we should be entitled to follow the commercialpractice of &quot;first come first served&quot;.    However, we must weigh thefinancial risk against the political and strategic advantages.7.      I suggest that we ought to allow most weight to the political and strategic considerations and offer the Turks the 4 &apos;M&apos; Class destroyers in addition to the cruiser and the 8 frigates.     I would propose to let thePeruvians have two of the &apos;Z&apos;s , and reserve the third to offer to theTurks later on if the Spaniards did not want her.     (The Spaniards are more interested in cruisers than destroyers, so it is unlikely that the sales to Turkey would be a very serious disappointment to them).8.       The Turks would be required to pay immediately the &quot;as lying&apos;costs of the vessels.    I think it would be possible to place all the refitwork with suitable contractors, but whether contractors would be preparedto run the risk of Turkish contracts remains to be seen.    I would not wishto agree to making Government-to-Government contracts if the Turks canmanage without it.    I should in any case have to offer Admiralty help,particularly overseeing and inspection services (for the usual charge)although this would mean a further burden on Admiralty staffs.9.      I therefore seek the approval of the Cabinet to proceed on the lines proposed above, with the understanding that if we run into paymentdifficulties with the Turks the question will have to be rec nsidered.C.Admiralty, 5.W.I.17th August, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
