<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 24-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1956SECRETCP. (56) 20811th September, 1956CABINETPLAN GMemorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerSince the papers on Plan G and allied subjects (summarised in Annex I)are lengthy and complicated, I thought it might be useful to try to set out what it is all about.2. We have to make two decisions. First, is this a good plan for the British economy? Will it bring us strength in the long run, even though the risks may be great in the short run? Can the British economy survive alone, insulated andprotected from European competition? Will it be able to maintain its exportsto Europe, which are 25 per cent, of the whole? Equally important, can it maintain its exports to other countries against the competition of European countries, eitherindividually, as now, or in a unified Europe largely under German domination?Can we enter into a new structure and at the same time maintain the advantages of the Commonwealth, our preferences and all the rest? Can we retain them,even if we keep out?  This is the first problem, economic and material.3. Then there is the second question. Is this politically sound? Can weretain the leadership of the Commonwealth world and at the same time seize the leadership of Europe? Would it help us to create a new period of British strengthand power, or should we be foolishly throwing away what we have? Would itbring us promise for the future, or is it an abdication and betrayal of our past?These are the questions which the Government has to settle about the plan itself.4. Next there comes the set of questions related to the politics of the plan.Will our Party accept it both in the House of Commons and in the country? can we swing from the old policy of insular protection to the new policy of wider free trade areas from the policies of a world of unemployment to the policies of a world of full employment? Can we combine in a common policy the Common-wealth wing and the European wing? Can we hold the agricultural constituencies,even if agriculture is excluded, in view of the concessions we may have to make to the Commonwealth?5. For myself, I do not think this can be done only on a material and economic basis.  It will require an emotional and idealistic theme.6. Then can we stand for what will happen? Everything that goes wrongwill be counted against the new policy, even if it would have gone wrong anyway.The trouble with our economy at the moment is it is not as competitive as it oughtto be. Will our employers and trade unions be prepared to stand the pressure which, of course, will help to make them competitive, and so defend full employment and the standard of living, but will also cause considerable discomfort and evensuffering? It will be no answer that these things would have come to us anyway.They will all be attributed to these new plans.Copy No. g g
7. Can we get the Commonwealth to see that the strength of Europe, onthe basis of a single market of 240 million people should create a new source of wealth and thereby an increased rate of investment overseas? Can we get theUnited States to take the same view, or will they raise difficulties about tariffdiscrimination against United States goods?8. These are the questions which we have to consider in reaching a decision.Unfortunately, there are some other distractions which make it difficult for us togive the matter our full attention. In the circumstances, I can hardly ask the Cabinetto do more than give general approval to this line of approach, and allow thePresident and me to explain to the Commonwealth Finance Ministers the way inwhich our minds are working. We do not wish to say that we have reached final conclusions; but we would like to explain these ideas and try to get their sympathy and interest. In order to prepare their minds, I propose to send a letter to commonwealth Finance Ministers in advance; a draft is annexed (Annex II) whichhas been sent to our High Commissioners for despatch when they have receivedfurther instructions after the Cabinet meeting.9. Of course, the Commonwealth countries will wish to bargain if we retain the preferences. But we are in for this anyway, as the recent Australian negotiationhas shown. In the long run it may be easier to make bargains of this kind on thebasis of a big policy; for the people of the old Dominions, like those of the mother country, are temperamentally attracted to that curious mixture of materialism andidealism which has made the English character almost unintelligible to anyforeigner.H. M.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,11th September, 1956.
ANNEX I summary OF PLAN GI. Reference is made here to the following papers :  CP. (56) 191-Interim Report by Officials.E.P. (56) 70-Supplementary Report by Officials.E.P. (56) 75 Note by the Chairman of the Economic steering committee.Description of the Plan2. The United Kingdom would enter a partial free trade area with theCustoms Union of the Messina Six (Benelux, France, Germany, Italy) and all other.E.E.C. countries that wished to join (probably Norway, Sweden, Denmark,Switzerland, Austria).  -3. The area would probably not include either our own dependent territoriesor those of the European countries; this must remain undecided, however, until we know the Europeans&apos; views about this; our own Colonial territories are being consulted about their possible interest.4. The free trade area would cover all commodities without exception exceptfoodstuffs (defined broadly to include processed food products, feeding-stuffs,drink and tobacco). The exclusion of foodstuffs is an essential condition on whichwe should insist without qualification, both in the interests of home agricultural policy and in the interests of the Commonwealth.5. Within the free trade area, tariffs (except revenue tariffs in the strictestsense), protective quotas and other protective devices (e.g., export taxes andcontrols, export subsidies) would be reduced and ultimately abolished in defined and timed stages over a period of about a decade.6. We should retain our existing freedom of action in our tariffs on importsfrom the rest of the world, subject to our commitments in G.A.T.T. and elsewhere:this is the essential difference between a free trade area and a Customs Union.There would be no change in our present obligations regarding free entry of commonwealth goods, and of course we should be under no commitment to discriminate in Europe&apos;s favour against the Commonwealth.7. We should insist that there should be no discrimination by the MessinaSix in each others&apos; favour and against us. This implies the same time-table fortariff reduction throughout the whole free trade area.8. We should retain the right to impose quotas in balance-of-paymentsemergencies. The area would be working under the present G.A.T.T. andO.E.E.C. rules unless it were decided that stricter rules should be applied withinthe area.  (This would probably suit us.)9. We should continue to make progress in relaxing and removing quota restrictions on imports from Canada and the United States. This would not be part of the Plan vis-a-vis Europe, but apart from such direct economic advantagesas might be involved, this action would probably be necessary to secure north american support.10. The Plan would be consistent with the collective approach to freer tradeand currencies; and it would be framed and presented in a manner that would reduce as far as possible the risk that it might be interpreted as envisaging thecreation of an inward-looking and restrictive regional discriminatory bloc.II. The international management of the free trade area would be conducted in O.E.E.C. by a &quot; Managing Board &quot; (at Ministerial and official level), consistingonly of the Members of the area, operating under Article 14 of the O.E.E.C.Constitution. This Article enables a group to proceed without the positive assent of non-Members of the group (provided they do not dissent).12. This machinery could, it is thought, be developed in O.E.E.C. on an inter-Governmental basis without the establishment of supra-national authorities.
Liaison would be necessary with the Messina authorities, but no &quot; special relationship &quot; outside the O.E.E.C.13. Some form of Parliamentary institution would probably prove necessary,perhaps by the development of a suitable link between the O.E.E.C. and the Councilof Europe.The Impact upon the United Kingdom14. The papers by officials analyse this in considerable detail. In E.P. (56) 70,this is done under three heads:  I. Effect of Dismantling Industrial Protection (paragraphs 5-29).II. Effect of the Plan on Sterling and its Compatibility with the Broad Linesof External Economic Policy since the War (paragraphs 30-51).III. Will the Plan Lead us Towards Closer Economic and Political Integrationwith Europe?   (Paragraphs 52-75.)The report is tightly drafted, and necessarily covers a large number of separateaspects : it does not lend itself to summary. The following notes do no more thanindicate the treatment.15. Dismantling Industrial, Protection. Part I of the Report begins by setting out the broad economic advantages which could be expected to flow froma free market with a population of 240 million people-and particularly from a closer association with an area which is in a period of strong economic expansion.The opportunities would be great; but the United Kingdom&apos;s ability to takeadvantage of them would depend upon her competitive power.16. This leads to a discussion of the general impact on internal economic policy and full employment (paragraphs 14-18). These considerations are crucial,and are emphasised strongly by the Chairman of the Steering Committee inE.P. (56) 75. The economy would be increasingly influenced by external factors;internal policies, by management and labour as well as by the Government, wouldhave to be more quickly responsive to change; without protection, we should haveto rely more upon them. It is made clear that Plan G would not represent a difference in kind from the situation that confronts the economy to an increasing extent in any case. But there are new elements introduced by the Plan, some ofwhich might be favourable and some unfavourable in their effect:  (a) the timed commitment to the schedule for removal of protection (both forus and for others);(b) the impossibility of shielding by tariff or quota particular firms and industries from European competition (we should still be fully protected against the United States and Japan);(c) if our economy gets out of line so that we are unable to compete bothabroad and in the United Kingdom market, the reaction comes muchmore directly on the economy (in loss of business and unemployment)and not only, as tends to happen now, on the gold reserves: this may help to make adjustment prompter and more effective, but this cannotbe assumed;(d) the external competition would provide  a spur to check sluggishmanagement and restrictive labour practices the point of greatestdanger in the full employment economy.17. The analysis of special industrial problems (paragraphs 19-23) suggeststhat the industrial gains and losses would be spread widely, both industrially andgeographically. There would be particular problems^perhaps a large number in individual localities and firms with long-standing protection that would be particularly difficult. But it is not thought that in the aggregate the industrialadjustments required would present great difficulty. Considerable importance isattached to whether the economy is expanding at the time when the adjustmentshave to be met over the ten-year period the general expectation of the report isthat the Plan would help economic expansion.18. The report suggests that it would not be necessary to consider significantchanges in our agricultural policy (paragraphs 28 and 29). The Chairman of theEconomic Steering Committee indicates that there is at present no incompatibilitybetween Plan G and the lines of policy advocated for British agriculture and the
Australian trade talks: if, however, serious pressures were put on us to makeagricultural concessions in Plan G there would be little room to do so; and Plan Gwould become difficult to negotiate if it were proposed either to increase the levelof protection to British agriculture or to allow output to rise significantly at thepresent level of protection.19. Sterling and External Economic Policy. Part II considers the impactupon sterling and the relationship with existing external economic policy. the considerations about internal economic policy and competitive power discussed inPart 1 affect the strength of sterling decisively; if the United Kingdom economy isable to take advantage of its opportunities under the Plan, the balance of payments should benefit, sterling should be strengthened, and the confidence of holders of sterling balances maintained, this leading towards convertibility. The reportshows (paragraphs 35-40) the interlocking of the internal and external prospects atthis point.20. The report goes on (paragraphs 41-44 and 50) to show the importance forthe future of sterling and for the successful floating of Plan G of avoiding, both in substance and in presentation, the development of Plan G into a regionaldiscriminatory bloc. If it were allowed to grow this way, grave consequences couldfollow for our trade with the American Continent, our position in the I.M.F. andthe GA.T.T. (and our drawing rights and tariff agreements), and the confidence ofthe big holders of sterling balances. It is concluded (paragraph 51) that if wemoved into Plan G within the framework of existing policies, determined to make and keep the United Kingdom economy competitive, accepting that we must continue to remove dollar discrimination and be prepared, at the right time, toaccept the consequences of sterling convertibility, Plan G should be acceptable andnegotiable and should strengthen rather than weaken sterling.21. Integration with Europe. Part III considers the institutional problems and seeks to assess whether the United Kingdom would, over the years, beinexorably drawn closer to Europe and away from the Commonwealth. Thepossible pressures for &quot; harmonisation &quot; of policies are discussed in turn exchange rate policy (paragraphs 47-49) and internal economic and monetary policy(paragraph 56) are not deemed suitable for supra-national authorities even by theMessina Six; discussion may centre on the French proposals for measures toequalise costs (paragraph 57) and on action on monopolies and restrictive practices in international trade (paragraphs 58-59). The conclusion (paragraphs 67-69) isthat we see no reason for supra-national institutions to manage the free trade area,and consider that the institutions of O.E.E.C. could be appropriately developed to handle the new problems.22. The report considers that freedom of capital and labour would not belikely to be an immediate issue. It is thought that the questions would rise as amatter of administration applications for investment in Europe rather than asa matter of negotiation; and that it is premature, especially in view of ourinsufficiency of savings, to take up a definite attitude in advance. The possibilityis mentioned of a two-way flow greater flow of capital to Europe from here beingmatched by greater European investment here and (via London) in theCommonwealth (paragraphs 61-66).23. This section of the report concludes with some considerations on the moreintangible question whether the closer association with Europe would lead to a weakening of the links with the Commonwealth and the United States(paragraphs 71-75). Here the report sees potential dangers and advantages, butpoints out various political and economic factors which would be likely to preventthe balance from being tilted too far towards Europe.The European Background and Likely Reaction24. Plan G falls to be considered at a time when the Messina Powers are engaged on drafting a Treaty which will embody the provisions of a common market. In the last year, they have done a great deal of work on this project.There are many points still to be resolved, but the structure is beginning to emergeof a Customs Union to be created by stages in 12-15 years, with far-reachingprovisions for &quot; harmonisation,&quot; and a governing structure including a Council ofMinisters,.a controlling and supervisory European Commission, a Court of justice and a Parliamentary Assembly. ,
25. Whether the Common Market will ever come into force it is impossibleto say. It is widely believed that France will never agree to the final irrevocablesteps. On the other hand, it is at least possible that the others will offer such greatconcessions to France to persuade her to accede that at any rate the first steps towards the Customs Union will be taken. The dominant ideas behind the projecthave shown themselves tenacious.26.   The sponsors advocate the Common Market for two major reasons:  (a) To secure for Western Europe the advantages of a large free market,comparable in size with the United States and USSR, in order to provide more economic opportunity and to generate more economic strength;(b) To  tie  Germany into  Western  institutions  while  there  is  still  a western-minded Government in Germany.27. In the earlier stages of the Messina enterprise, there was hostility betweenthe Six and O.E.E.C. the Six regarded O.E.E.C. as a hindrance to the work they wished to do, and the other members of the O.E.E.C. feared that the Six wouldbuild a discriminatory group that would in fact disrupt the wider Europeaneconomy and render nugatory the achievements of O.E.E.C. particularly theE.P.U. and the liberalisation of trade.28. O.E.E.C. Special Working Party. In recent months, a serious attempthas been made on both sides to reconcile the two concepts of Europeandevelopment. This resulted in the O.E.E.C. Ministerial Council resolution at themeeting at the end of July, which set up a Special Working Party to&quot;study the possible forms and methods of association, on a multilateral basis,between the proposed Customs Union and Member countries not taking parttherein. As a possible method of association the Special Working Party shall take into account the creation of a free trade area which would include theCustoms Union and such Member countries.&quot;This Special Working Party, under the chairmanship of Baron Snoy (Belgium),will meet on 24th September, and is due to report by 31st December.29. It will of course be necessary for the United Kingdom representative onthe Special Working Party to have instructions on the attitude to be adopted. Thefirst phase of the work will be technical in character, but the essential policyconsiderations will begin to emerge early in November.30. Countries&apos; Likely Reactions. Her Majesty&apos;s Representatives in thecountries listed in paragraph 2 above have been asked to state their views on whatwould be the reaction to Plan G of the countries to which they are accredited.The replies are analysed in detail in Appendix B to the officials&apos; supplementary report (pages 25-28); these are summarised further in paragraphs 88-95 of thereport itself.31. The advice is that Plan G would, in general, be well received in europe and that, subject to the position of France, the Plan would be acceptable to mostEuropean countries without major modification. It is thought that Plan G wouldbe a strengthening of Western Europe and of O.E.E.C., and that it could be satisfactorily negotiated provided that the United Kingdom laid down absolutelyclearly the conditions governing the Plan, and refused to depart from them,consistently underlining the difference between this and the Customs Union.32. The real risk in Europe is that of frustration through the equivocation ofFrance, and the report urges strongly (paragraph 95) that it would be dangerous to embark publicly upon Plan G without the determination, if need be, to forceFrance into the Plan by being prepared in the last resort to go ahead with the othercountries and without France.Attitude of the United States33. The advice of Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington(paragraphs 96-98 of the supplementary report and its Appendix B) is that he would expect the Plan to be tolerated, and that we should get United States acquiescence in the G.A.T.T. waivers, &amp;c. but that the United States attitude would be likely to fall short of &quot; positive support.&quot; He would not regard this as necessarilypreventing the introduction of the scheme if on other grounds it is thought desirable.
34. The importance of our attitude to discrimination against United Statesgoods and services is stressed. The report concludes that the crucial points appearto be the extent to which Plan G can be presented to United States opinion as:  (i) the only practical course towards European unity, the Messina customs union being in danger of frustration, and any wider move being ruled out by our own Commonwealth and world-wide associations;(ii) a step towards world-wide reduction of barriers to trade and payments,and not a new discriminatory &quot; two-world &quot; regional bloc.The Impact upon the Commonwealth35. The interim report of officials set out in some detail the effect of Plan Gupon the independent Commonwealth (paragraphs 46-49 of CP. (56) 191); theviews of United Kingdom High Commissioners were sought; these are analysedin Appendix A of the supplementary report, and discussed further inparagraphs 77-86.36. The report was unable to give much guidance on the broad political-economic implications of Plan G for the Commonwealth or of the commonwealth countries&apos; likely attitude to these, wider questions. It must be true that if the effectof the Plan upon the United Kingdom economy is favourable, and if the Planwere to result in the strengthening of the Western European economy as a whole,the effect upon other Commonwealth countries could hardly fail to be favourable.Apprehensions that the United Kingdom was diverting its interest to Europe could hardly carry much weight outside Australia and the English-speaking people ofSouth Africa. On the other hand, the Commonwealth countries would be unlikely to see for themselves new expanding prospects under the Plan.37. The views of Canada have a different emphasis from the sterling commonwealth, and it is clear from the United Kingdom representative^ dispatchthat the dominating consideration for Canada will be the removal of quotadiscrimination against Canadian goods, and that the Canadians will probablystart with the expectation that we have reverted to the policy of regional blocs.38. The other countries would seem likely, according to the high commissioners, to think primarily in terms of their export prospects. The exclusion of foodstuffs from the free trade area safeguards the great bulk of Commonwealthexports to the United Kingdom. The field in which commercially valuablepreferences against European competitors would be lost over a 10-year period would be small in the case of Canada, about 10 per cent, of her exports to UnitedKingdom, in Australia about 2-3 per cent., in India probably less (a long list of guaranteed preferences, but the effective competitor is Japan), and for the others,the amount of trade involved is insignificant.39. But many countries have hopes of developing exports of manufacturedgoods to the United Kingdom, which would be frustrated to some extent by the lossof preference vis-a-vis Europe; and none of the Commonwealth countries are sosatisfied with their present trading agreements with the United Kingdom that theywould be eager to handle the problem smoothly and with a true sense of proportion.It is very difficult to say in advance what the practical impact is likely to be. Thescale of diversion of Commonwealth exports is so small that it could properly be compensated by minor adjustment in the preference which the United Kingdomenjoys in Commonwealth markets. But the desire in some quarters to modifyand indeed abolish preference is so strong that much more damaging resultsmight follow.Conclusion40. To sum up, on the one hand are the potential advantages, both economicand political, in the strengthening of Western Europe and in the creation of neweconomic opportunities on a substantial scale. And side by side with the opportunities are the risks of a timed commitment to a more exposed economy and the uncertainties about the ability of Government, management and labour todevelop the internal policies needed to seize these opportunities.41. After these basic considerations have been weighed, there are the shorter-term problems of the Commonwealth reaction and the particular questionof the Commonwealth preferences, the danger of creating ill-feeling and mistrustparticularly in Canada but also in United States, and the risk that the equivocationof France will frustrate this, as it has frustrated other schemes. But these are matters in which presentation is all-important.
ANNEX ii draft LETTER FROM THE CHANCELLOR OF THE exchequer to COMMONWEALTH FINANCE ministers am looking forward with pleasure to the prospect of meeting you at the endof this month at the Fund and Bank Meetings in Washington. There is a matterof importance to us which I want to discuss at the Meeting of commonwealth finance Ministers on 29th September and oh which I think it right to give yousome prior notice. [An alternative first paragraph will be needed in cases wherethe Finance Minister is not going to Washington.]2. There is, we believe, much force in the widely-held view that so long asEurope consists of a number of separate national economies these cannot providea large enough market to be a satisfactory base for modern industry, technicallyequipped and adequately developed to compete with the mass production potential of the United States and the USSR. We have necessarily great sympathy for thepresent efforts Of the Messina Powers who are at this moment planning to form a customs Union among themselves. But because of our interests outside Europe,and in particular our close links with the Commonwealth, the United Kingdomitself could not in any circumstances join such a Customs Union; to do so wouldmean giving up our own tariff and our external trading arrangements.3. We are therefore, as the Foreign Secretary explained to the commonwealth prime Ministers this summer, faced with a dilemma. If the Messina customs union is formed with us outside it, it would tend to be a narrow regional bloc,dominated by Germany, and our exports to Europe might be squeezed out; europe would be divided and our economic, and indeed political, position there might be gravely threatened. On the other hand, if we stand entirely aloof, a movementcalculated not only to benefit Europe economically but to revive it politically, maycollapse. We have therefore been giving further thought to how we might be associated with this movement without in any way weakening our association withthe Commonwealth.4. It appears to us that perhaps the right course might be to seek, togetherwith other countries in Western Europe, particularly Scandinavia, to be associatedwith the Customs Union in a Free Trade Area over the whole field of trade exceptfood. Broadly, this would mean that over a period of, say, ten years we and theother members would undertake reciprocally to reduce and finally abolish ourtariffs on imports of raw materials and manufactured goods from one anotherwithin the Free Trade Area; but we should retain our present freedom to maintainor alter our tariffs against other countries. We should also retain the right toimpose non-protective revenue duties. But such arrangements would, so far as weare concerned, be quite inappropriate for agricultural products, and we shouldmake it an unqualified condition that food, including manufactured foods, feeding-stuffs, drink and tobacco, should be excluded from the scope of the area. Thisexclusion would not only enable us to continue our existing agricultural policy, but would also safeguard the existing preferential advantages enjoyed by the great bulkof Commonwealth exports to the United Kingdom. We would not expect the free trade Area to include the dependent territories of any of the members, but thiswould remain uncertain until we found out European reactions to our main proposals, and their views on this question; in the meantime, we are consulting ourown Colonial territories on their possible interest.5. Arrangements of this kind could, we believe, be of great positive advantage to the Commonwealth as a whole. A politically stable and economicallydeveloping Europe should provide an expanding market for Commonwealthproducts, even though they themselves were not members of the Area. Moreover,a powerful economic unit should be able to provide capital for investment in theCommonwealth on a scale greater than the United Kingdom alone could hope tomake available. For the United Kingdom itself a market of 240 million people would present us with very great opportunities. Clearly, we should not be ableto take advantage of them unless our industry were on its toes and able to competeeffectively, in particular with German industry. But my colleagues and I are determined that we can and should meet such a challenge. Indeed, we must meetit, whatever our trading arrangements.
6. Such a move, therefore, given the necessary policies to ensure its success,-would strengthen United Kingdom industry and give it both the need and theopportunity to be more thoroughly competitive not only in Europe but also in commonwealth and other foreign markets. In so far as these arrangementsstrengthened the United Kingdom economy, they would also strengthen sterling and broaden its use as an international currency. They could not, in our view, beregarded as a reversal of the policy we have hammered out together in successiveCommonwealth meetings. On the contrary we would regard them as entirelyconsistent with, and of assistance to, the objects of the collective approach to freertrade and payments, and to convertibility. The whole Free Trade Area would beso large, and have so considerable extra-European interests, that there would beno danger of it developing into an inward-looking regional group. It would remainessential for us to pursue, and to press others to pursue, a policy of non-discrimina-tion in the removal of quota restrictions; and as regards tariffs, though we shouldprogressively be removing our tariffs towards Europe, we should not be requiredto raise them against others. The general framework of the G.A.T.T., in whichreductions of tariffs can be negotiated on a world-wide basis, would remain centralto our commercial policy.. It is fundamental to our conception that the Free trade area in Europe should be created by the removal of trade barriers between its members, and not by the introduction of new barriers against the trade of othercountries.7. Through the exclusion of all foodstuffs from the scope of the Free trade area, an essential condition on which we should insist without qualification, weshould be free to continue the present advantages in this important sector which other Commonwealth countries at present enjoy. For all other goods, the UnitedKingdom would be moving progressively towards according European goods thefree entry treatment which the Commonwealth countries already enjoy in theUnited Kingdom market; and some consequential adjustments in some of our trade agreements with other Commonwealth countries would need consideration.But apart from this, we ourselves would wish to carry on with these agreements,and the preferences provided by our tariff against imports from foreign countries outside the Free Trade Area would not be affected.[Canada only]8. If a Free Trade Area on these lines came into being, the preponderantpart of Canadian exports to the United Kingdom would be unaffected. The UnitedKingdom would, of course, aim to continue the progress which we have madein recent years in reducing and removing quota restrictions on imports from canada. In tariffs, the United Kingdom would be free to maintain free entrywhere at present that exists. Food would be unaffected; on raw materials and manufactures, Canada would by the end of the ten-year period have lost her present preferences against European producers, though her preferences againstsupplies from the rest of the world, including the United States, would be unaffected.[Australia only]8. If a Free Trade Area on these lines came into being, only a very small proportion of Australia^ present exports to the United Kingdom would be affectedin any way. You would continue to enjoy preferential treatment againstnon-European countries such as the United States and Japan, not only on thosemanufactured goods that you are now sending to the United Kingdom but also onany new export lines that you may develop in the future. I would hope that, ifwe can succeed in finding a satisfactory basis for agreement in our trade talks withMr. McEwen, no difficulty of a major character should arise as a result of our association with Europe in a Free Trade Area.[India only]8. Most of India&apos;s important exports to the United Kingdom would beunaffected if a Free Trade Area on these lines came into being, since there is no corresponding European production. In the remaining field we should still be freeunder the proposals to maintain the existing free entry of manufactures from Indiainto the United Kingdom, including textiles. This present free entry gives india a preference over Japan, her most formidable competitor.
[Ceylon -only]8. I do not think that Ceylon&apos;s exports to the United Kingdom would beaffected if a Free Trade Area on these lines came into being, since there is noEuropean produce competing with them.9. The President of the Board of Trade is arranging to join me in Washingtonat the end of September, and he and I will elaborate these ideas to you when wemeet. I must emphasise that we have not yet taken our decisions on thesefar-reaching questions; they are not decisions which we could take until we hadbeen able to consult the Commonwealth and indeed we are still examining how we might expect them to affect our own economy. Moreover, though we expect that proposals of this kind would be well received in Europe, we do not knowwhether all those parts of the proposals to which we would attach the greatest importance would be acceptable; we cannot be sure whether arrangements for a free Trade Area acceptable to us could be negotiated. Not until a much later date should we be in a position to consider with you the detailed arrangements that such proposals might involve. But I hope that, when we have been able todiscuss together the broad lines of our ideas, you will be able to give some indicationhow they strike you.

</content>
</cab>
