<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 97-100</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1956CONFIDENTIALCP. (56) 21220th September, 1956CABINETWAR pensions memorandum by the Minister of Pensions and National Insurance1. In CP. (56) 64 I set out the then position in respect to War Pensions claims and my proposals for dealing with them were approved by the Cabinet on 8th March (CM. (56) 20th Conclusions).2. Since then the absolute and relative position of disabled war pensionershas not improved, and public opinion, both inside and outside our Party, isconcerned both at the general position of war pensioners and particularly withrespect to certain categories.3. The basic rate of war pensions in cases of 100 per cent, disability (67s. 6d.)now has a purchasing power less than that which it had in 1938 or 1946. To restorethose purchasing powers it would be necessary to raise the basic rate in respect of100 per cent, disability to something between Sis. 9d. and 102s. and to between70s. 5d. and 74s. 3d. respectively, according to which index is used. In addition the rise in wages which has taken place has resulted in a deterioration in the relative position of the severely injured pensioner, who cannot, as a result of his injury,obtain as remunerative employment as the undisabled man. The increase inpension required to re-establish the same relative position of pension to average level of wages would have to be over  1 a week to restore the value of even thelower rate of pension in 1939, and about 10s. to restore the relative position towhat it was in 1946.4. In normal circumstances there would therefore be a strong case, apartfrom any other adjustments, for a substantial increase in the basic rate of warpensions. This is what the British Legion, the largest and most responsible of theex-Service organisations, requests. But increases of this sort are expensive itwould cost approximately a million pounds a year for each shilling increase in the basic rate and in the present economic circumstances it does not seem right to propose additional burdens on the Exchequer of this order.5. This attitude will not be popular with the ex-Service organisations or withpart of our own Party, but should nevertheless in my view, for economy reasons,be maintained.6. However, if it is to be maintained it becomes the more important toconsider the points at which hardship is greatest and on which public opinion feelsthe strongest.7.   There are two such points:  (a) the ageing war pensioner of the First War with a substantial disability;(b) the very serious cases of disability of all ages.The Ageing War Pensioner8. The problem of the ageing war pensioners is one which is only now fullyemerging. We are just at the point at which the average age of the First Warpensioner is 65. The British Limbless Ex-Servicemen&apos;s Association, with thesupport of an All-Party Committee of Members of Parliament, has been pressing50541Copy No.     \
for some years for some special provision to be made to deal with the increasinghardship which they maintain old age brings to the sufferers from amputation.The details of this claim and a reference to the difficult medical issues involved are contained in paragraphs 14-20 of CP. (56) 64. A motion now stands on theOrder Paper in the names of members of all parties, in the following terms:  &quot; 1914-18 WAR DISABILITY PENSIONERS: That this House,mindful of the great services rendered to the nation by those who lost theirlimbs or suffered other grievous wounds in the 1914-18 War, and seized of thefact that advancing age has aggravated the disabilities they sustained during their war service, calls upon the Government to make some additional provision, beyond that provided for by the basic disability pension assessments,to compensate them for their increased disabilities and loss of activities and amenities, and therefore, in view of the fact- that the average age of these1914-18 war disability pensioners is now sixty-five years, urges theGovernment to take immediate action to aid them in their remaining years.&quot;The All-Party Committee have told me that the fullest possible pressure will beapplied when the House reassembles in the Autumn. A large number of localauthorities have associated themselves with the case of these men and my colleagues may remember the unhappy scenes involving severely injured men which tookplace near the Cenotaph in connection with B.L.E.S.M.A. demonstration last november.9. In the light of the Cabinefs decisions on my earlier paper, I have heldnumerous discussions with a number of leaders of the medical profession, in orderto attempt to ascertain whether a means could be found of improving assessmentsfor the severely disabled as they become older. While the medical men concerned have maintained that there is a case for improving pension provision for the olderseriously disabled pensioners, there has not emerged any feasible method of doing this by means of increasing the actual assessments of their disabilities except ina strictly limited type of case mentioned by Sir Russell Brain. These medicalviews, with their strong expression of sympathy with the claims of the olderpensioners, will have to be published before long.10. A number of the doctors with whom I have discussed this question havebeen impressed with the substantial number of medical conditions which canunder the existing arrangements give rise to increased assessments, and have recommended that greater publicity be given to them. I propose to follow this advice. Sir Russell Brain, the President of the Royal College of Physicians, inaddition to recommendations covered by existing provisions, has recommendedthat provision be made for increasing assessments in certain amputation caseswhere there is subsequent impairment of function of the surviving limb. the limited extension I have in mind to meet Sir Russell Brain&apos;s recommendations would involve a small adjustment of existing practice at small cost. I am anxiouswherever it is possible to accept the views of the leaders of the medical professionI have consulted, and details of the application of this recommendation are beingworked out by my Department. Apart from this, however, I have come to theconclusion that the only practicable and sound method of dealing with the caseof the ageing War pensioner is by means of a specific allowance.11. I do not think that B.L.E.S.M.A.&apos;s original proposals to confine additional provision to amputation cases is sound or just. Other serious disabilities, e.g.,blindness or head wounds, could equally be said to be &quot;harder to bear &quot; with increased age. On the other hand, the less serious disabilities are not really inthe same category, and I think that the line of demarcation should be an assessment of 40 per cent, disability which covers all but an insignificant minority of amputation cases.12. In seeking to find a method of doing something for the ageing wardisabled, I have sought to avoid any method which would involve repercussions on the Industrial Injuries Scheme. Provision for industrial injuries is closely related to the main scheme of National Insurance, and I think that changes in thebenefits paid under the Industrial Injuries Scheme should only be made, with due adjustments in contributions, when the time comes for changes in national insurance rates. For this reason I have come to the view that the right approach to an improvement in the War Pensions scheme for the ageing war pensioner isthrough a new allowance analogous to the comforts allowance which was introduced into that scheme a few years ago, and for which there is no counterpartin industrial injuries.
13. At Appendix I of this paper I set out details of a scheme for an ageallowance.14. As my colleagues will see, I suggest that the relevant age should be 65.B.L.E.S.M.A. have suggested 55, but I think it would be better to concentrate on those disabled pensioners who have reached what is both now the average age off first War pensioners and the accepted minimum age of eligibility for retirement pension.Tfee Seriously Disabled15. The comforts allowance also seems to me to provide the right methodof dealing with Class (b) in paragraph 7 above, the very seriously disabled. Sir IanFraser, the President of the British Legion, raised their case on the Adjournmenton 31st July, and there have been a number of distressing, if not wholly accuratereports in the press, which have aroused much public feeling, on the position of very seriously disabled men. The Comforts Allowance was introduced in 1951at a rate of 10s. a week to help to deal with these cases. It is paid automaticallyto those totally disabled pensioners who receive both the unemployabilitysupplement and constant attendance allowance. It is also granted to certainpensioners suffering from multiple injuries of exceptional severity who are receivingconstant attendance allowance above the minimum rate of 15s. but who are notunemployable.16. I propose that the 1951 figure of 10s. should be increased to  1. Thiswill go to the really serious case of war disability involving men the vast majorityof whom cannot work and require to be continually looked after. In fact the reallytragic cases.17. I would also propose that the comforts allowance, though at a lower rateof 10^., should be paid to those disability pensioners who are receiving theunemployability supplement only and to those 100 per cent, pensioners receiving a constant attendance allowance at the lowest rate of 15s. but who do not at presentqualify for the comforts allowance. These are all the very serious cases and men whose relative position to their fellow countrymen has deteriorated by reason ofthe increase in wages which, ex hypothesi, they cannot earn. And although intheir case it would be more logical therefore to make improvements by way of anincrease in the unemployability supplement, or constant attendance allowance, Ido not propose this because such a change would have a direct repercussion on industrial injuries, where similar provisions are made.Conclusion18. Appendix II contains, a balanced plan to deal with the two problems ofthe more seriously injured ageing War pensioner and of the really bad disabilitycase regardless of age. After some thought I have not included proposals for improving the position of the ageing War widow, although there is some demandfor this, particularly from War Pensions Committees. The plan of course is verysmall in scope and cost, compared with the demands of the British Legion whichrun into many millions of pounds. And although it may be criticised on thegrounds that it does more to meet the claims of B.L.E.S.M.A. than it does of thelarger and more responsible British Legion, I have ascertained privately that sir Ian Fraser would welcome proposals on these lines to deal with the ageing aswell as his own proposal for the very severely disabled cases. The cost is relativelymodest and the money is concentrated on the points where hardship and public concern are most acute. I realise the difficulties of any increase in expenditure inpresent circumstances. But a figure of this order can clearly be considered againstthe background of the steady reduction which is taking place in the number of war pensioners now living. At 31st December, 1955, the number of pensioners had sunk from over a million in 1951, and over 900,000 in December 1954, to 871,000.The rate of decrease is greatest among the 1914-18 war pensioners.19. The Chancellor has seen this paper and has asked me to say that he feelshe cannot accept these proposals.J. A. B.-C.Ministry of Pensions and national Insurance, W.C.2.20th September, 1956.
Appendix IOUTLINE OF A SCHEME FOR AN AGE ALLOWANCEThe qualifying age should be 65 for all war-disabled pensioners, and themaximum allowance should be 15s. a week for pensioners assessed at 100 per cent.For lower assessments down to and including 40 per cent, there would be threelower rates corresponding to broad bands of assessment. The following table shows the scale proposed.  About 56,400 pensioners would benefit:  Degree of DisablementPer cent.100908070605040Weekly Age Allowances.   d.15   010  07 65   0The cost is estimated at  1,090,000 in the first full year, rising to about  1  million in ten years&apos; time, thereafter declining.Appendix ii summary OF PROPOSED IMPROVEMENTSNumber of     Cost in FirstBeneficiaries       Full Year1. Age allowance as in Appendix I     ... 56,400 1,090,0002. Increase in existing Comforts Allow-ance to 20s. a week......... 7,800 200,0003. Extension of Comforts Allowance at10s. a week to all pensioners in receiptof Unemployability Supplement onlyor Constant Attendance Allowanceat the minimum rate and notat   present   eligible   for   ComfortsAllowance     ............ 12,500 310,000Total Cost in first full year......... 1,600,000

</content>
</cab>
