<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 101-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
if)Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1956SECRET Copy No.   5 9CP. (56) 21321st September, 1956 ;!,CABINETUNEMPLOYMENT BENEFITMemorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service andthe Minister of Pensions and National Insurance1. On 28th June (CM. (56) 46th Conclusions) we were invited to work outchanges in the unemployment benefit rules for short-time workers with a viewto further consideration by the Cabinet.2. Unemployment benefit has always been available to assist workers whohave been reduced to short-time working, particularly during a general recessionof trade, and we are agreed that, if action is to be taken, the right course is to dealwith the obvious abuses and not to.attempt to withdraw benefit from short-timeworkers in general.3. The insurance scheme assumes a six-day working week and pays benefit for each day at one-sixth of the weekly rate. Under present rules a five-day weekworker losing one day&apos;s work a week can receive benefit not only for his idle daybut also for Saturday; this is the main abuse we should try to remedy.4. For practical reasons, it is necessary that the insurance scheme should provide a daily rate of the same proportion of the weekly rate at present one-sixth for all claimants alike and for unemployment benefit, sickness benefit and industrial injury benefit. It would be possible to devise more equitableunemployment benefit rules for five-day workers if benefit were paid to them at one-fifth of the weekly rate. We have, therefore, considered whether it wouldnot be justifiable to-day to put the insurance benefits on to a five-day week (thatis, ignoring Saturday in the same way as Sunday) and to require that, beforebenefit is payable, there should be two days of unemployment or sickness in thefive days Monday to Friday, instead of two days in the six days Monday toSaturday. The effect would be that the five-day worker losing one-day&apos;s work aweek would not receive benefit. If two days were lost he could receive two-fifths of his weekly benefit rate.5. We do not favour this course, which seems premature at a time when largenumbers of workers are still working on Saturday; it might easily give theimpression that there is something wrong about Saturday working and that ordinarySaturday work should always be specially remunerated. It would enable a fullweek&apos;s unemployment benefit to be paid to a man who had been unemployed inthe first five days of the week even though he worked at high wages from Saturday morning all through the week-end.6. In our view the present abuse could best and most easily be remedied inthe following way:  (a) paying no benefit in any calendar week unless the worker is unemployed in that week for two days on which he normally works; and(b) paying no benefit for a day on which the worker does not normally workunless he is wholly unemployed in that week.50543
7. The effect of these rules would be to deny benefit to a short-time workerwho normally works a five-day week but has been reduced to a four-day week(he can now get benefit for two days a week); to give a five-day worker reduced toa three-day working week benefit for two days, amounting to two-sjxths of the weekly rate (he can now get three sixths), and to give benefit for Saturday to a five-day worker only where he has lost a full week&apos;s work. The position whereguaranteed week agreements are in operation is discussed in paragraph 10.8. It is not possible to form an estimate of the possible saving on unemploy-ment benefit that might result from the proposed rules except on arbitraryassumptions, but assuming that short-time. working continues at its present level,the potential saving might be of the order of  2 millions a year. On the other hand,adoption of these rules, or any others with similar effect, would represent a significant restriction on the benefit rights of five-day workers who are subject toshort-time working and would be strongly opposed by the Trade Union movement.Technically it would be possible to make the change by amending regulations.These, however, must under the National Insurance Act be submitted to and reported on by the National Insurance Advisory Committee involving in thenormal course about six months&apos; delay. Further, that Committee reported on thisquestion as recently as November 1955 when, after hearing evidence from bothsides of industry, they indicated that opinion among them was divided as towhether any change in the rules should be made and did not recommend any departure from the existing provisions.9. We consider, therefore, that if a change is to be made the better course is, after consultation with both sides of industry, to proceed by way of amending legislation to be introduced as early as possible next session. The provisionallegislative programme already contains a National Insurance Bill.&quot; Guaranteed Week &quot; Agreements10. The fundamental test of whether unemployment benefit is payable for a given day is whether or not, in the view of the adjudicating authorities, the claimantis unemployed and is available to accept work on that day. The position can thus be affected by the existence of industrial agreements which guarantee a certainamount of employment or wages in lieu in each week. The adjudicatingauthorities must take into account the exact terms of such an agreement betweenthe workman and his employer in deciding whether, on a given day, the workmanis unemployed and free of his obligation to work for that employer. Some ingenuityhas been spent in drafting agreements which will secure the maximum unemploy-ment benefit for those participating in them when short time is worked, though these devices, as a recent decision by the National Insurance Commissioners hasshown, are not always successful. Given the principle of availability, which seemsto us sound, we do not see how the adjudicating authorities can be prevented fromconsidering everything which is relevant to a claimants obligations on a day forwhich he claims to be unemployed. Admittedly it might be possible, at the costof some disturbance, to lay down that certain types of agreement negativedavailability for an entire week even though the adjudicating authorities had previously held the contrary. Even so, the adjudicating authorities would be left with the task of deciding which agreements did, and which did not, fall within anyban which could be devised, and the position, from that point of view, wouldbe no more satisfactory that it is at present, when some agreements permit benefit,and others do not. We have come to the conclusion, therefore, that there is no practicable method of altogether avoiding the situation in which title to benefitsometimes turn on narrow points in the construction of an agreement. The proposals in paragraph 6, if adopted, might, however, be expected to lessen the present difficulties considerably since the five-day a week worker with a guarantee ofemployment or wages in lieu, for four days or more, would no longer be able toget benefit while on short time.I. M.J. A. B.-C.20th September, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
