<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 154-158</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP.(56) 22?5th October, 1956;THE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON the prorogation OF parliament note by the Lord Privy seal i circulate herewith, for the consideration ofthe Cabinet, a draft of The Queen&apos;s Speech on the prorogation of Parliament.R.A.D.COPY NO.^3CABINETOffice of the Lord Privy Seal, S.W.1.5th October, 1956.
SECRETDRAFTTHE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON the prorogation OF parliament my LORDS ant MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF commons.      I shall always retain the happiest recollections of the visit which I paid with My Pear Husband to the Federation of nigeria and of the loyal welcome accorded to us there.    We alsorecall with pleasure our visits to the Kingdoms of Norway and sweden and the gracious reception extended to us by the peoples ofthose countries.    The warmth of the regard shown by My peoples of East Africa and Mauritius to My Dear Sister during her recent visit has been a source of great satisfaction to Me.2.       I have also been very happy to welcome to this country thePresident of our oldest ally, Portugal,, and the King of Iraq, with whom we are so closely associated in the Bagdad Fact.3.      My Government have continued to give whole-hearted support to the United Nations.      /  Paragraph to be inserted here on the suez situation.    This willhavetobe produced shortly before the speech is made as thejwording will be determined by the state of thesituation at that time /.      They have maintained their efforts in theDisarmament Commission to achieve an international agreement onconventional and nuclear disarmament, and have emphasised the needfor agreed limitation of nuclear test explosions.4,      My Ministers have welcomed the efforts to strengthen non-military co-operation within the North Atlantic Treaty Organisationand the establishment by Western European Union of the Arms ControlAgency.    In the framework of these agreements My Government havereaffirmed the community of interest between the British and Frenchpeoples.5.      My Ministers have maintained close co-operation with theUnited States Government on the many important international issues which have arisen during the year.6.      The visit of the Soviet leaders provided My Government withan important opportunity for personal contacts and an exchange of viewson a wide range of international problems.7.      My Government have welcomed the accession of Pakistan andIran to the Bagdad Pact / and the further association of the UnitedStates Government with many of its activities /.6.      I am happy to inform you that My relations with the Sultan ofMorocco and the Bey of Tunis have been drawn closer by the exchangeof Ambassadors.9.      The Prime Ministers of the Commonwealth met in london at the end of June.    Their wide-ranging discussions were prompted bytheir desire to promote the common interests of My peoples.    My
-I- ii t)Government have continued to support the purposes of the ColomboPlan and have increased their provision for technical assistance.10.    My Ministers have been gravely concerned at the unhappysituation in Cyprus.    In the face of violence and provocationMy Forces have shown exemplary steadiness and forbearance.My Government have taken a fresh initiative by appointing a commissioner to make recommendations for a new and liberalConstitution for the Island.11. I was deeply grieved at the loss of life and great devastationfrom a disastrous hurricane suffered by several of My West Indianterritories.     I am glad to know that with the aid of assistance from my Government in the United Kingdom, from others of My Governments,from foreign countries and public appeals they have since made good progress towards recovery.12.    An Act was passed conferring on Me powers to provide for aBritish Caribbean Federation.    It was agreed at a Conference with a delegation from the Federation of Malaya that a new Constitutionproviding for full self-government and independence within theCommonwealth should be introduced by August, 1957, if possible.An Order in Council has been made providing for an elected majority in the Legislative Assembly of Sarawak.13.    My Government have continued to maintain My Forces in readiness to fulfil their national and international responsibilities.The pay and conditions of service of members of the Services onregular engagements have been improved.    Plans have been developed for using My Forces in support of the local civil defence services.MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS14.    I thank you for the provision which you have made for thepublic services.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS15.    It has been the constant concern of My Ministers to maintainfull employment, to encourage savings by vigorous and imaginativeincentives and to preserve the strength and stability of the economy.16.    In order to stimulate competitive enterprise an Act has been passed to provide for the registration of restrictive trading agreements and their judicial examination by a special court, and to prohibit the collective enforcement of resale price conditions.*       17.    The law relating to copyright and related matters has been revised.18.    The price guarantees and grants determined by My ministers have provided valuable support for the agricultural industry.Farmers and workers have faced with courage and determinationthe difficulties caused by the bad weather this year.x      Bill not yet enacted
19.    Further help has been given to agriculture in the hill farming and livestock rearing areas.20.    Further financial assistance has been given to the fishing industry.21.    An Act has been passed to safeguard the health and providefor the safety and welfare of those employed in agriculture and forestry.22.    My Ministers have ended the Government purchase of imported bacon and have arranged for the import of sugar for home consumption to be returned to private trading.     I have given My assent to an Act to carry out the Governmenfs obligations under theCommonwealth Sugar Agreement.23.    Measures have been enacted to introduce new arrangementsfor financing agricultural research and to amend the constitutionof the Department of Scientific and Industrial Research.24.     The Government have announced a five-year plan for extending technical education.    An Act has also been passedamending the schemes of superannuation for teachers.x 25.    The law relating to education in Scotland has been amended.26.    My Government have been much concerned with the problemof traffic on the roads and legislation has been passed to improve itsregulation and to promote road safety.27.    New criminal courts have been set up in Liverpool and manchester and legislation has been enacted to make further reformsin the administration of justice.    The system of legal aid has been extended to proceedings in the county courts in England and wales and the jurisdiction of these courts has been increased.28.     The law relating to rating and valuation in England and wales has been amended.    Legislation has also been passed to amend thelaw of valuation and rating in Scotland and to provide a new basis forthe payment of equalisation grant to Scottish local authorities for an interim period.29.    Legislation has been enacted to abate the evils of airpollution.31.    The structure of the housing subsidies in England and wales has been modified so as to encourage the building of houses to replaceslums and to relieve the congestion of our cities.    The compensation payable to certain owner-occupiers and businesses affected by slum clearance has been improved.31. An Act has been passed to provide for the establishmentof a General Dental Council.x     Bill not yet enacted
32.    The pensions of retired members of the public services have been increased.     Family allowances have been extended,improvements have been made in the war pensions and national insurance benefits of widows with children, the earnings rules for insurance pensioners have been relaxed, and provision has beenmade for those receiving workmen&apos;s compensation who are totallydisabled.     The national assistance scales have been raised.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS34.    I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.

</content>
</cab>
