<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 177-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret. 1.(56) 2325th October, 1956OPEN - CAST MINING COM F EN SAT IONMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer in C.p.(56) 194 the Committee of Ministers who, under my chairmanship, made recommendations on open-cast mining, invited theCabinet to agree, as part of the proposals, that more generouscompensation should be paid both to landlords and tenants.   The cabinet approved these proposals in principle (CM,(56) 55th Conclusions,Minute 5).2.   The details which have now been worked out are in brief -(i) Compensation to occupiers to be improved as follows -(a) The extra-statutory supplementary rental compensation to be increased to three times the statutory rentalcompensation (four times for small holdings).   Theearlier report had recommended increases of two andthree-fold respectively.(b) The special hardship payments should be continued and made rather more generous.(ii) Compensation to landowners to be improved as follows -(a) The variable extra-statutory rehabilitation allowance, nowpaid in about half the cases, to be paid in all cases at a flat rate equal to one year&apos;s rental compensation (twoyears in special cases).   The benefit, as now, to be passed to the tenants,(b) A new rehabilitation allowance equal to three years&apos;rental compensation to be paid to and retained by thelandowner.(iii) The agreed Code of Restoration to be improved to providefor the reinstatement of stone walls if the landlord wishes.The Government should offer to consider other suggestions for improving the Code.(iv) The announcement of improvements to be made at an earlydate.   Payment of improved compensation should, ifpossible, take effect from the date of its announcement, but should not in any event be made retrospective beyond10th May, 1956.COPY NO.&quot;51CABINET
(v)  The agricultural organisations to be told in confidence of the government&apos;s proposals, coupled with the offer to considersuggestions for improving the Code of Restoration.3.   The cost of the proposals, to be borne by the National Coal)3oard, will be about  300,000 a year.4.   We feel that these improvements will go a long way to meet the complaints of both landowners and tenants, and will help to reduce theopposition to open-cast mining.5.   Nevertheless, it must be realised that the adoption of the above proposals will leave little latitude for further financial concessionsas a sweetener if and when any semi-permanent legislation becomes necessary.   This, however, is a risk we shall have to take,6.   New arrangements following legislation would have introduced asystem of compensation more closely related to losses actuallysuffered by individuals.   The present proposals do not profess to relate compensation to losses with exactitude, and they involve an increasing reliance on extra-statutory payments, which is likely to attract the notice of the Public Accounts Committee.   Nevertheless weare satisfied that our compensation proposals would at least offerrough and ready justice to most claimants, and we think that they arethe best that can be devised within the framework of the present system.7.   Most of us consider that, on grounds of both principle &amp;ndexpediency, payment of the improved compensation should take effect from the date on which these arrangements are announced.   If howeverthere is strong pressure from the agricultural organisations thatpayments should be retrospective, we hope that it should not benecessary to go back beyond 10th May, 1956, the date on which it was announced that improvements in compensation were under consideration.The Minister of Agriculture however would prefer to have a margin left for negotiation with a view to ensuring that agreement is clinched on the broad issues, since the objective is to secure the goodwill of theagricultural interests in connection with the new open-cast programme.We invite the views of our colleagues on this point.8.   We accordingly invite our colleagues to agree -(1) That the Minister of Fuel and Power should at an early dateannounce in the House the terms of compensation set out inparagraph 2.(Z)  That if possible the improvements in compensation should take effect from the date of announcement; but that if retro-spection is inevitable, the date should be fixed not earlier than10th May, 1956, unless the Cabinet consider it desirable toauthorise a margin for negotiation.I-I.M.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.5th October, 1956

</content>
</cab>
