<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 194-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COPY NO.  OxsX&quot;The Government recognise that each annual review by its nature can afford assurance for only a comparatively short time ahead and that, if longer term assurances could be made more effective, this would help the industry in its forward planning.   Accordingly they will consider whether anypracticable methods of providing such assurances of support for the industry can be devised&quot;.2. It would not be easy to offer nothing at this stage, but wehad hoped that in return for a &quot;package deal&quot;, consisting of long-term assurances together with a system of capital grants for farmimprovements, we should obtain the agreement of the Farmers1 unions to doing away with a very large part of the more objectionable features of the negotiations which the annual review has come to impose on us.3. ! rom preliminary talks which officials have had with the farmers&apos; Unions we now learn that our hopes will be disappointed.4. A possible system of long-term assurances, under whichthe Government would undertake not to reduce the value of the guarantees,both individually and in total, below certain percentages of thoseoperating in the previous year, has been worked out and the points still at issue are set out below, together with certain outstanding questions ona system of capital grants.     But the Farmers&apos; Unions are adamant thatthe whole machinery of the annual review must be retained.5. Before, therefore, we look at the details of the schemes,I suggest that we ought to consider whether it is in fact worth while to continue our attempt to honour the pledge given in the White Paper,If all the giving has to be done by the Government.6. The proposals for long-term assurances mean in effect thatthe Government would undertake not to decrease the total value of the guarantees below 97 per cent of those operating in the current year,after giving full credit for any cost increases incurred since thelast review.     The farmers would give absolutely nothing in return,for the full machinery of the annual review would continue to operate,SECRETCP.(56) 23S17th October, 1956.CABINETLONG TERM ASSURANCES FOR AGRICULTURENote by the Chancellor of the exchequer in our consideration of long-term assurances to agriculturewe have been carrying out an undertaking given in paragraph 36 of theWhite Paper issued after the 1956 Annual Review (Cmd. 9721). In this it was stated that -
under which they would still be able to put forward as relevant factorsall the matters over which there is now such extensive wrangling.Their demands could be pitched as high as they wished, while theGovernment would have to start from a base which, to constitute any sort of assurance now to the industry, would leave them restrictedroom for bargaining.7. We should be achieving this at the cost of the scheme for capital grants, a main purpose of which was to gain something forus which would be to our advantage;  whereas in fact we should betying our hands as I have described, not only for one year aheadbut for four years at a time.     It would be virtually impossible insuch circumstances to make any alteration in Part I of the agriculture act which might later seem desirable if we could work out an agricultural policy more to our liking and better suited to the country&apos;sneeds.8. On the other hand the proposals also offer agriculturesome solid comfort, and in later years we should be able to take some credit at annual reviews for the scheme of capital grants.     Wemay well get increased production and a measure of increased efficiency;   but the price will be high and there will be no correspondingcontribution to it from the Farmers&apos; Unions.9. The first question is, therefore, whether we should proceed at all in the matter;   if we do, there are certain points of detail tobe settled, which are discussed in the separate memorandum(C.F.(56) 237 ) circulated jointly by the Minister of Agricultureand myself.H.M.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.16th October, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
