<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/83/0 images: 219-222</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2II7fed tJ  SCOPY NO.DRAFT STATEMENTGOVERNMENT EXPENDITURE:   ECONOMIESWith your permission, Mr. Speaker, and that of the House, Iwould like to make a further statement about economies in government expenditure.2.       The Government set out to achieve savings of  100 millions in thiscurrent year on services provided in the original Estimates as published.On 26th June I made an interim announcement of savings amounting to 76 millions,of which  36-1 millions was on the Defence programme, 14 millions on defence expenditure by Civil Departments and 25^ millions on other Civil Estimates.! secret.P.(56) 24722nd October, 1956CABINETGOVERNMENT EXPENDITURE:   ECONOMIESNote by the Chancellor of the exchequer circulate the draft of a statement on Government expenditure,which I propose to make on Thursday, 25th October.2.       I must remind the Cabinet that the decisions announced in this statement still leave us   6-f millions short of the  100 millionssavings which we have undertaken to secure.   All contributions will begratefully received.   Bis dat qui cito dabH.M.Treasury Chambers, S.W.I.22nd October, 1956
PAIR6(103.       I have now to announce that further savings have been decided on bythe Government amounting to  17^ millions.    Of this,  9 millions is onthe Defence programme and  8^ millions on the Civil Estimates.   I willcirculate details of these further savings in the Official Report.   Advancecopies will be available in the Vote Office immediately.4.       With these further savings the total so far achieved towards the 100 millions is  93.^ millions.   I will make a further statement laterabout the balance.   Among the items in the present instalment, I needcomment on only two.5.       First, it is proposed to increase, as from 1st December 1956the charge for National Health Service prescriptions.   Instead of Is. perform it will be Is. per item.   The average cost of prescriptions is about5s. per item.   The saving will be       million this year and  5 millions ina full year.6.       Secondly, it is nroposed to make a seasonal increase, from 7jd.to 8d. a pint, in the retail price of milk as from 1st January 1957 for theremainder of the winter.   The net saving this year will be  4^ millions.The charges for school and welfare milk will not be affected by this change.7.       I would remind the House that all these decisions about government expenditure ignore, on the one hand, additional necessary-expenditure not provided for in the original Estimates; and that, on theother hand, they do not take credit for underspending on those Estimatesduring the year apart from those deliberately planned.   As regards theadditional expenditure, Civil Supplementary Estimates were presented inJuly amounting to some  15 millions, excluding Post Office expenditure tobe covered by self-balancing revenue.   On defence, additional expenditure is being incurred by the Services in connection with the Suez Canal crisis,but it is not yet possible to estimate how much this will amount to duringthe year.-2-
Following are the details:-ECONOMIES IN GOVERIMENT EXPENDITURE:    EFFECTS on estimates. 1956-57(Additional to those reported on 26th June, 1956Hansard, Cols. 275-280)I.DEFENCEVote No.Title of VoteReduction 000NotesNAVYESTIMATES8. Ill10Shipbuilding, Repairs, 1*725Maintenance, etc:   ContractWorkWorks, Buildings and Repairs 75at Home and Abroad _^Total 1,800Mainly revision of re-fitprogramme.Review of major works.ARMYESTIMATES1Pay, etc. of ArmyCiviliansStoresWorks, Buildings andLandsTotal8001,7502505005,300Manpower adjustment.Reduction in requirementsof civilian labour inGermany.Reduction in purchases of accommodation stores inGermany.Curtailment of certainworks services.AIRESTIMATES56Pay, etc. of the AirForceCiviliansMovementsSuppliesAircraft and StoresTOTAL FOR DEFENCEESTIMATESTotal1,870550250 )500 )7303,9009,000Mainly reduction in R.A.F.manpower requirements.Reduction in civilian man-power requirements at homeand abroad.Mainly reductions consequent on lower personnel strength.Reduction in equipmentre quirerne nt s.
. Class and1 Vote No. Title of Vote Reduction Notes 000II. 2IV.114v.41011VIII.212Foreign Office grants and ServicesColonial ServicesMinistry of education department of education for ScotlandMinistry of HealthNational Health Services,England and Wales-ditto-Department of Health forScotlandNational Health Service,ScotlandAgricultural and FoodServicesDepartment of agriculture for Scotland750 Reduction in loan to Jordanon re-phasing the develop-ment programme.1,250 Reduction in loan to Kenya( 1 million) and miscellaneousservices.4 130 Increase in subsidy on school milk consequent on increasein retail price.4    10 - ditto -4- 2(10 Increase in subsidy on welfare milk consequent onincrease in retail price. -700 Increase from 1st December,1956, in charge forprescriptions from Is. a fox-xr.to Is. an item.500 Reductions in stocks of hospital supplies.4   40 Increase in subsidy on welfare milk consequent onincrease in retail price.50 Increase in charge forprescriptions as above.4,760 )       Seasonal increase in the) maximum retail prices of allgrades of milk by -gd. a pintfrom 1st January, 1957.330All Votes250Various Civil DefenceServicesTOTAL FOR CIVIL ESTIMATESTOTAL:    DEFENCE AND CIVIL2508,25017,250Reduction by 5 per cent, asfrom 1st November, 1956^ ofthe average monthly provision,for Travelling and subsistence AllowancesMiscellaneous \, includingequipment, railways and ports).

</content>
</cab>
