<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/61/49 images: 450-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1945.SECRET.W.P. (45) 94.10th February, 1945SUMMARY OF OPERATIONS OF BOMBER COMMAND FOR four weeks ENDING 28th JANUARY, 1945.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.A. A detailed summary of operations is appended.B, Results of Operations,1. Oil Targets.A large number of attacks were made on oil plants during the period.Photographs taken on the 21st January covering the northern half of the Leuna(Merseburg) plant show that the double attack made on the 14th/15th January-caused damage of varying severity to almost all the important installations.There was no sign of productive activity at the plant. Extensive damage wasinflicted in the attack made on the Benzol plant at Castrop Rauxel on the3rd January using the G.H. navigational aid. Some 18 buildings in the Benzoldistillery, in the colliery complex and in the sections for naphthalene andanthracene treatment suffered particularly badly.Photographs show that on the 16th/ 17th January very heavy fresh damage was caused at the Briix synthetic oil plant, especially to the power station, coolingtower, organic sulphur removal plant and pump houses. Photographic cover ofPolitz showed the plant to be inactive, though until better quality cover becomes available it is not possible to assess the exact extent of the damage. No cover has yet been obtained of Zeitz, but night photographs suggest a most promisingattack. Wanne-Eickel does not appear to have been further damaged, but hadnot yet resumed production when photographed. The R. Muser, Forsetzung andBruckhausen benzol plants were also attacked.2. German Towns.Two attacks, made on Hanover on the 5th/6th January, caused newdevastation at many points north of the main station, an area not previouslydamaged. Two locomotive depots, the A.F.V. assembly plant of Hanomag,aircraft repair works, other engineering works and factories were all seriously damaged. Considerable damage was also inflicted on the landing ground, hangars and barracks. Print No. 1 shows the success of the attack made on Nurembergon the 2nd/3rd January. The destruction extends south and east of the old townthrough the main railway station and through many blocks south-west of thestation.   .The Iso octane plant at the Ludwigshafen chemical works was virtuallydestroyed on the 2nd January and other vital installations were heavily damaged,among them the nitrogen and methanol plant. Numbers of subsidiary buildings in the plant were also either destroyed or damaged. Magdeburg and Munichwere also attacked by large forces and Mosquitoes bombed Berlin on six nights.3. Transportation Targets.As photographs had shown that the Dortmund-Ems Canal at Ladbergenand. the Mittelland Canal at Gravenhorst had been repaired, forces were despatched to attack them both again. The attack on the Mittelland Canal was an outstanding success, as Print No. 2 shows, and the Canal was once more[29217]Copy No./WAR CABINET.
rendered useless. Extensive damage was inflicted on the western arm of theDortmund-Ems Canal, and south of the Glane aqueduct a breach 180 feet widewas made, through which the water poured, causing widespread flooding in theGlane valley (see Print No. 3).Many attacks were made on marshalling yards at Vohwinkel, Osterfeld,Ludwigshafen, Hanover, Krefeld, saarbrucken and Neuss. The full extent ofthe damage achieved in these is difficult to assess, since in many cases photographsobtained several days after attacks show that considerable clearance and repair work has already been undertaken.       ,4. Results of Previous Attacks. &apos;Prints Nos. 4 to 11 show the results of recent attacks on Giessen, Ulm,Koblenz. Bonn, Solingen, Dusseldorf, Saarbruckeh and Kaiserslautern.C. Sea Mining.Mines were laid during the period in the Eastern Baltic to increase theconfusion caused to all types of seaborne traffic in the vicinity of Gdynia, Danzigand Swinemiinde and to interfere with U-boat training. The &quot;Heligoland Bight,Oslo Fiord, the Kattegat, Kiel Bay and Flensburg Fiord were also mined, andswept channels were closed for varying periods off Oslo, Moss, Horten, Drammenand Sandefiord.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, 10th February, 1945.APPENDIX.Summary of Operations.aircraft date. Target.       &apos; DespatchedDec. 31 Vohwinkel, marshalling yard       ... ...       .... 155Oslo, Gestapo HQ.............      ... 12Dec. 31/Jan. 1     Osterfeld, marshalling yard        ... ...       ... 166Oslo Fiord, shipping ...       ...      .... ...       ... 28Berlin......      ......      ... ...      ... 73Jan.   1 Dortmund-Ems Canal at Ladbergen ...       ... 1041/2 Dortmund/Ministerstein     ...       ... ...       ... 139Gravenhorst-Mittelland Canal      ... ...       ... 157Vohwinkel, marshalling yard        ... ....      ... 146Hanau ...       ...      ...       ... ...       ... 28Hanover        ...       ...       ...       ... ...       ... 272/3 Nuremberg.........       ... ...       ... 521Ludwigshafen, chemical works     ... ...      ... 389Berlin ...       ...       ......       ... ...... 533 Castrop Rauxel, benzol plant       ... ...       ... 49Dortmund Hansa, Benzol plant    ... ...       ... 504/5 Berlin .......      ...      ... ...      ... 66Roy an, enemy troop concentrations ...;      ... 3545 Ludwigshafen-, marshalling yard  ... ...      ... 1605/6 Hanover        .........      ... ...... 664Berlin.........      ...      .... ...... 69Houffalize, troop concentrations    ... ...       ...   . 1406/7 Hanau ...      ...      ......- ...... 486Neuss, marshalling yard     ...       ... ...       ... 147Kassel............       ......... 207/8. Munich ..,      ......... ....      ... 654Hanover        ...       ...       ...       ...: ...       ... 5410/11 Hanover        ......      ...... ...... 5011 Krefeld/Uerdingen, marshalling yard ...       ... 15212 Bergen, U-boat pens and shipping ...       ... 3313 Saarbrticken, marshalling yard     ... ...       ... 158.   13/14 Saarbrucken, marshalling yard     ... ...       ... 276Politz, synthetic oil plant  ...      ... ....      ... 225
aircraft date. Target. . Despatched.Jan. 14               saarbrucken, marshalling yard ...      .... 13414/15           Grevenbroich, marshalling yard   .., ...       ... 151Merseburg (Leuna), synthetic oil plant ...      ... 587Dulmen, G.A.F. fuel plant...... ...      ... 115Berlin           ................... 8315               R. Muser, benzol plant       ...      ... ...      ... 63Forsetzung, benzol plant    ...       ... ...       ... 8216/17          Magdeburg     ...      ...&quot;     ........,      ... 371Zeitz, synthetic oil plant   ...       ... ...       ....   - 328Briix, synthetic oil plant    ...... ...       ... 237Wanne-Eickel, synthetic oil plant ... ...      ... 13817/18          Magdeburg     ...      ..,      ......      ....., 7218/19           Sterkrade/Holten, synthetic oil plant ...       ... 5621/22          Kassel...............      ...... 7622/23           Bruckhausen, benzol plant  ...       ... ....      ... 302Gelsenkirchen          ...       ...       ... ...       ... 152Hanover         ...       ...       ...       ... ....      ... 48In addition, 235 aircraft were despatched on small raids on German townsand other targets, 1,461 aircraft were employed in bomber support operations and 747 mines were laid during the period.


























</content>
</cab>
