<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/35/0 images: 110-114</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET   -THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1961C.C. (61) Copy No.    3 516th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, 23rd March, 1961, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right. Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Harold WAtkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills,Paymaster-GeneralThe Right &quot;Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the following were also present:Sir Edward Boyle, M.P., FinancialSecretary, treasury the Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury sir Frederick Hoyer Millar, ForeignOfficeSecretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. F. A. bishop mr. M. Reed
ContentsSouth-East Asia Treaty OrganisationLaos
1 r^&apos;-j *CC. 16 (61)South-East *The Cabinet were informed of the latest military developmentsAsia Treaty jn Laos.  The Pathet Lao offensive, consisting of five or six battalionsOrganisation supported by artillery and backed by large reserves, with the aid ofLaos Soviet arms and equipment and stiffened by technicians from North(Previous Vietnam, was forcing the Laotian Government troops to retire.   the reference: morale and leadership of the Government troops was poor and itCC. (61) 15th was likely that the Pathet Lao forces would capture Luang Prabang.Conclusions, If no special steps were taken the military situation would be boundMinute l) to deteriorate still further.The Foreign Secretary said that, faced with this prospect, theUnited States Government had now agreed that a further effort should be made to secure a political settlement with the object ofestablishing a genuinely neutral Laos. Accordingly, with the UnitedStates agreement, he had on the previous day proposed to the soviet foreign Minister that, as co-chairmen of the Geneva Conference,they should call for a cease-fire in Laos; that the international commission should then proceed to Laos to verify that a cease-firehad become effective; and that when the Commission had reportedthat a cease-fire had been achieved, an international conference ofthe sort proposed by Prince Sihanouk should be convened to workout a settlement which would provide for the neutrality of Laos.I/,: The initial Soviet reaction to this proposal had been reasonablyfavourable, but a formal reply had not yet been received. It was likely, that the President of the United States would announce, at a press conference that evening, his desire for a political settlement onthese lines and would express his hope that the Soviet Governmentwould agree; but he would probably make it clear that, failing15 agreement, the United States Government would take such measures as were necessary to prevent Laos from falling completely underCommunist influence. The United States Government were in factconsidering a number of alternative plans to meet the situation whichwould arise if the Soviet Government would not co-operate in seeking a political settlement. They hoped that some limited area in Laoscould be. retained under the control of the Laotian Government ifBut, if this werenot sufficient, they would be ready to intervene overtly and they had made operational plans to do so. The United States governmenth oped that any such overt intervention would be taken as a resultof a decision to that effect by the South-East Asia treaty organisation, but if necessary they would be prepared to interveneon their own account. In any event they would hope for, and indeedexpect, the material and moral backing of the United Kingdom%\.. Government, though they would not need our direct military support.Their operational plans did not involve the use of nuclear weapons.. The objective of military intervention by the United States would belimited to securing a perimeter of about 50 miles around Vientiane,so as to enable the King and Government of Laos to remain onLaotian soil, and to encourage the neighbouring countries to standv firm against Communist infiltration.We had already explained fully to the United States authorities the disadvantages and risks which limited intervention would entail,from both the military and the international point of view. But it seemed clear that the United States Government, while recognising the force of these considerations, were resolved if necessary to use force to hold part of Laos for the Laotian Government. It wastherefore necessary to consider whether we should seek further to discourage this intervention, and whether we should if the need arosem support it.p co cm. . cc Gj!y-    I I j CG;Or Q Q* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.SECRET
(OZcSECRETThe Minister of Defence said that his conversations with theUnited States Secretary for Defense confirmed this analysis of thesituation. The United States military authorities believed that their plan could be implemented with conventional weapons. We couldnot claim, from the technical point of view, that the limited militaryobjective of the United States plan was not feasible. We could, ofcourse, continue to point out the grave international repercussions of United States intervention. But if we failed to support the UnitedStates Government, once they had finally decided upon intervention,our chances of future co-operation with the new administration would be prejudiced.In discussion, doubts were expressed about the extent to whichthe United States authorities had considered the developments whichmight follow, on their intervention. It was by no means unlikelythat the Soviet Union would respond with massive support throughNorth Vietnam, and the military situation inside a perimeter aroundVientiane might become extremely difficult. Thailand would undoubtedly be involved, especially if bombers were used by bothsides, and the area of conflict might be greatly extended. If hostilitiescontinued, it was most unlikely that the Soviet Union would participate in a conference and there could be no hope of a political settlement. Meanwhile, there would be strong international criticism of the United States, especially in the United Nations. CertainCommonwealth countries, especially Malaya and India, were likelyto be critical of the United States action. In this connexion, therewould be great advantage if any intervention could take place on theinitiative of the United States alone, rather than as the result of adecision by the South-East Asia Treaty Organisation.The Cabinet agreed, on the other hand, that the consequences of abandoning Laos to Communist influence might be disastrous. Itwould then become much more difficult to preserve the integrity ofthe neighbouring States, including Thailand. Moreover, the UnitedStates Government, if they felt unable to count on any support fromtheir allies,&apos; might decide to relinquish their interests in defending thewhole area. In this connexion it had to be remembered that itmight soon be necessary to secure the support of the United states in resisting aggression against Western New Guinea. In view of ourclose relations with Australia and New Zealand it was not open tous to abandon all interest in South-East Asia.It was pointed out that recent developments showed aconsiderable hardening in the Soviet Union&apos;s policy towards theWest. In these circumstances it was desirable that the new UnitedStates Administration should : show firmness and determination.Although our direct military assistance was not needed, our moral support, especially in explaining the position to commonwealth countries, could be of value to the United States, and it wasunthinkable that, in the last resort, it should be withheld. Whilethe disadvantages and dangers of intervention were great, theconsequences of yielding to Soviet pressure were likely to be evenworse.The Prime Minister said that it was the general view of theCabinet that we should continue to point out to the United StatesGovernment the disadvantages and risks of overt intervention inLaos, but that we should make it clear that if the present proposalsfor a political settlement were rejected by the Soviet Union we wouldbe prepared in the last resort to support the action which the UnitedStates Government might feel obliged to take. It would be preferable for any such action to be taken on the initiative of the United Statesand not as a result of a decision by the South-East Asia treaty organisation. In this connexion, it would be helpful if theCommonwealth Secretary were to warn the Prime Minister of malaya, who was in London, of the deteriorating situation in Laos,and to seek to ascertain what his attitude would be if interventionbecame necessary.
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,24th March, 1961.SF^ETCC. 16 (61)Although our views had not formally been sought, there were strong arguments for making our position clear to the United StatesGovernment without delay. For this purpose he would arrange fora draft message which he might send to the President of the UnitedStates to be prepared for consideration by the Cabinet at a meetinglater that night, when the terms of the Presidents announcement ofhis policy would be known.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion of this question later that night.

</content>
</cab>
