<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/35/0 images: 209-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1961C.C. (61) Copy No.SIst conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, on tuesday, 13th June, 1961, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 1-7)The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills, Pay-master-GeneralThe Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations (Items 1-8)The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the following were also present:The Right Hon. John Profumo, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Items 6-7)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary, Trea-!    suryField-Marshal Sir Francis Festing,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Item 7)Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. F. A. bishop mr. M. Reed
Urn       ,    IContentsMinuteNo.123SubjectSouth-East Asia Treaty OrganisationLaosParliament       ......Education        ......Public Schools4     Portugal ......5      Middle East     ......Kuwait6      GermanyDefence Facilities in the United7     Cameroons       ......8     West Indies      ......9     Education        ......Teachers&apos; Salaries10     Suez Finance Company11      Civil Aviation   ......Airport Policy12     Europe   ........Kingdom
SoQth-east asia treaty organisation laos(previous reference:C.C. (61) 29thConclusions,Minute 2)1. The Lord Privy Heal said that, following agreement betweenthe Foreign Secretary and the Soviet Foreign Minister on the termsof a further message to the parties in Laos about violations of thecease-fire, it had been possible to reconvene the Geneva Conferenceon the preceding day. It was clear that the Chinese representatives were unwilling to accept the concept of international control whichthe Western allies thought necessary to preserve neutrality in Laos.The representatives of Thailand had withdrawn from the Conferenceon the ground that it would fail to ensure the independence andneutrality of Laos. Meanwhile, however, the three Laotian princeswere discussing in Zurich the possibility of forming a Governmentin which all the factions in Laos would be represented.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.Parliament 2.  The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Education(previous reference:C.C. (61) 30thConclusions,Minute 3)PublicSchools3. The Minister of Education said that there was to be a debate on 16th June on a motion by a Government supporter calling attention to &quot; the need for a broader-based entry of boys to publis schools&quot; and seeking Government support for a plan under whicha proportion of places in the public schools would be reserved forboys selected by the State whose fees would be paid by theExchequer. This proposal had been considered and rejected by theGovernment in the past, and he proposed that he should continue to resist it.Discussion showed that there was general agreement in theCabinet that this proposal should continue to be resisted. If therewere any difficulty in defeating this motion, it could be talked out.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Education to resist the private member&apos;s motion on 16th June calling for government support for a plan for a broader-based entry to publis schools.Portugal(previous reference:C.C. (61) 30thConclusions,Minute 8)4. The Minister of Defence recalled that, at their meeting on 6th June, the Cabinet had agreed that the military exercises whichwere to be held jointly with the Portuguese Army in Portugal inJuly should be postponed. A statement attributed in the Press that day to a spokesman of the Ministry of Defence, denying rumours,that the exercise was to be cancelled, was misleading and would betaken up with the newspaper concerned. He hoped, however, thatthe Cabinet would be willing to reconsider their decision. any reduction in the limited opportunities for realistic training overseasmust add to the difficulty of recruiting to the Army. While it hadnot been possible to persuade the Portuguese Government that their troops should not participate in the exercise at all, their numberswould be reduced to the minimum and it would be made clear thatthe exercise was of a routine nature and not related to the situationin Angola.Discussion showed that some misgiving was still felt in theCabinet about this proposal.  Anti-Portuguese feeling was growing
secret )MiddleEastKuwait(previous reference:CC. (61) 20thConclusions,Minute 4)in different parts of Africa and this military exercise could not fail to accentuate our difficulties in dealing with African nationalism andits supporters. On the other hand, cancellation of the exercise wouldinjure our relations with Portugal at a delicate time. It would alsoappear that the Government had given way to pressure. If, however,the exercise were not cancelled, an opportunity should be taken tomake it clear that it had no connexion with the question of portuguese colonial policy, which was in any case quite different from our own.Summing up the discussion The Prime Minister said that, inview of the considerations now advanced by the Minister of Defence,the balance of advantage seemed to lie on the side of proceeding with the exercise. It should, however, be made clear to publicopinion, both in this country and abroad, that the nature and purposeof the exercise was limited and that it had no implications on our policy towards the emergent African nations.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the Anglo-Portuguese joint military exerciseshould not be postponed.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence, in consultation with theCommonwealth Secretary and the Lord Privy Seal, toarrange for a statement to be made on the lines indicated by the Prime Minister.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the lord privy Seal (C. (61) 77) about future relations between the UnitedKingdom and Kuwait.The Lord Privy Seal recalled that, at their meeting on 13th April,the Cabinet had agreed to accept the wish of the Ruler of Kuwaitthat the Exclusive Agreement of 1899 should be replaced by a new agreement. The Ruler was offered the choice of two alternatives an exchange of notes which would abrogate the Agreement of 1899but would be accompanied by an oral and unpublished assurance that Her Majesty&apos;s Government recognised their continuingobligation to assist in maintaining the independence of Kuwait, oran exchange of notes which would state in terms that abrogation ofthe Agreement of 1899 did not affect that continuing obligation.The Ruler, in agreement with the leading members of his family,had preferred the latter form. He had proposed, moreover, that itshould be expressed in the terms &quot; nothing shall affect the readiness of Her Majesty&apos;s Government to assist the Government of Kuwait,if the latter request such assistance&quot;. This formula, which was designed to avert criticism from other Arab States, was less specificthan was customary in instruments constituting a defencecommitment, but the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf had been unable to secure the Ruler&apos;s agreement to more precise terms. Itwas intended that the exchange of notes shouH be signed on 19thJune and followed by an immediate announcement. The agreement would not affect the right of the Ruler to appiy for membership ofthe United Nations Organisation (an application which we had undertaken to sponsor) or to join the Arab League (which he wasnot thought to be contemplating at present).In addition the Ruler had proposed that the title of the PoliticalAgent in Kuwait should be changed to Consul-General. This mightbe accepted, but the Consul-General would remain responsible tothe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Governmentshould view with caution any proposals for a more advanced formof diplomatic representation in Kuwait.The Cabinet Approved the proposal in C. (61) 77 and the proposed change in the title of the Political Agent in Kuwait.
Germany(previous reference:C.C. (61) 30thConclusions,Minute 7)defence facilities inthe UnitedKingdom(previous reference:C.C. (61) 12thConclusions,Minute. 6)SECRET59250-13 b 36. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Defence (C. (61) 76) about the provision of defence facilities in the United Kingdom for the Federal German Forces.The Minister of Defence recalled that, at their meeting on 16thFebruary, the Cabinet had authorised him to offer certain defence facilities in the United Kingdom for the Federal German forces on the understanding that the offer did not finally commit theGovernment. Subsequent discussions had shown that, in order to fulfil their commitments to the North Atlantic Alliance, the german forces required certain storage facilities, with which we could provide them, and facilities for tank-firing training (as distinct from tankmanoeuvres), which could be provided at the castle martin range inSouth Wales. There was no difficulty about the former, but someopposition to the latter must be expected both in Parliament andfrom certain sections of public opinion. He therefore proposed that,as a first step, arrangements should be made for a visit toCastlemartin in September by one German tank regiment on an experimental basis and that, if the experiment were successful, weshould accept additional regiments as might be later agreed. Weshould, however, try to avoid any definite long-term commitment.Legal and practical considerations would make it impossible for theGerman units to function satisfactorily in this country unless the visiting Forces Act, 1952, and the Application of Law Order were extended to them, and at their meeting on 14th March the cabinet had agreed that the necessary orders should be made.Discussion showed that there was general agreement in theCabinet that facilities should be provided for the Federal german forces on the basis proposed by the Minister of Defence. Theorders under the Visiting Forces Act would, however, requireaffirmative resolutions in both Houses and the present congestion of Parliamentary business would make it difficult to find time for the debates before the summer recess. Two alternatives should thereforebe considered: either the visit of the German tank regiment mightbe postponed until October, in order that the debates might be heldin the resumed session after the recess; or it might be possible to devise some means by which a relatively small unit could be enabled to function for a limited time and on an experimental basis withoutthe cover of the Visiting Forces Act. Each of these alternatives was,however, likely to present serious difficulty and it was agreed thatif, on further examination, neither proved practicable, it would benecessary to make the orders before the recess.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that defence facilities should be provided for theFederal German Forces on the lines proposed inC. (61)76.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence to give further considerationto the possibility of postponing the first visit of a german armoured regiment to castle martin until October.(3) Invited the Home Secretary, in consultation with the Ministerof Defence, to give further consideration to the possibilityof this unit&apos;s functioning without the cover of the visiting forces Act and the Application of Law Order.(4) Agreed that, if neither of the alternatives referred to in conclusions (2) and (3) above proved practicable, thenecessary orders under the Visiting Forces Act shouldbe made and debated before the summer recess.
Cameroons(previous reference:C.C. (61) 15thConclusions,Minute 5)7.  The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the PrimeMinister (C. (61) 79) about the future of the Southern Cameroons.The Prime Minister said that there was a serious danger thatsubversive forces in the Southern Cameroons, organised by chinese communists, would launch a campaign of terrorism when theterritory became independent on 1st October and, in conformitywith the result of the United Nations plebiscite, entered into some form of federation with the Cameroun Republic. Unless internal security could&quot; be preserved, the administrative personnel, the greatmajority of whom were British, would leave the country, as would the representatives of British commercial interests there. It had therefore been suggested that the battalion of United kingdom troops at present stationed in the Southern Cameroons should beallowed to remain, after 1st October, in order to maintain internal security during the transitional period while the proposed federation was established and to allow time for an adequate local securityforce to be recruited and trained. It was also suggested that weshould establish an Aid Mission, consisting in effect of the existingadministrative personnel, who would be invited to remain under the aegis of the new Department of Technical Co-operation. these measures would be additional to our continuing to finance the budgetdeficit of the territory, including the cost of maintaining the locallyrecruited security force. In default of action on these lines, we mightwell be held to blame if there were a breakdown of administration in the Southern Cameroons and perhaps in the neighbouringCameroun Republic, leading to the emergence of a Communist-dominated regime in this area which would be particularly dangerous to Nigeria.There were, however, strong financial and military arguments against accepting these commitments. The cost of the proposed measures would amount to nearly  2 millions a year, and anyaddition to our oversea expenditure was particularly unwelcome atpresent. The responsibility for ensuring stability in the southern Cameroons ought to be undertaken by the United Nations, and wehad already stated publicly that the United Kingdom forces wouldbe withdrawn when our trusteeship came to an end. There couldbe no question of leaving the battalion unless both the Prime Ministerof the Southern Cameroons, Mr. Foncha, and the Prime Ministerof the Cameroun Republic, Mr. Ahidjo, agreed to request it; but even then there was no precedent for putting British troops underthe command of a foreign Government in time of peace, and wewould be likely in any case to be criticised for maintaining a military force in the territory. There was also a danger that relationsbetween Mr. Foncha and Mr. Ahidjo would deteriorate, and thatour troops might become involved in a personal struggle for power.Moreover, if terrorism broke out on an extensive scale, a singlebattalion would be inadequate and would have to be reinforced;and this, in the light of our other commitments, would be extremelydifficult.United Kingdom representatives were to discuss the future ofthe territory at a meeting later that week with Mr. Foncha andMr. Ahidjo, at which it was hoped that French military representatives would also be present. It was therefore necessaryto decide whether to withdraw the United Kingdom battalion on1st October and to confine our assistance to such modest financial support as we could afford, or to undertake these substantial additional responsibilities for the security and administration of theterritory for some further time.In discussion the following points were made:(a) British investment in the territory amounted to nearly 20 millions; nevertheless these interests were not enough to warrant
CC. 31 (61)the continued deployment of British forces after 1st October. Themain issue was whether we could afford the risk of the dangerousgrowth of Communist influence in this area.(b) The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that conditionsin the territory would make it necessary to relieve United kingdom troops every six months. It was very doubtful whether a localsecurity force could be recruited and trained in a short time. Therewas no doubt that a single battalion would be inadequate to maintainorder if serious terrorism broke out, and in that event it would benecessary to send two further battalions to reinforce it. In view oftheir interests- in the Cameroun Republic, it would be greatlypreferable that the French should accept the responsibility for security, including the training of a local force.(c) Even if the current Army recruiting objective were realised,it would not be possible to reinforce a battalion in the southern Cameroons without losing our capacity to meet other military commitments which ought to have priority. For example, it wouldbe of greater importance to provide reinforcements for Zanzibar.(d) It was very desirable that the training of a local security force should be undertaken by the French authorities, on behalf of theCameroun Republic. Although the French maintained that theycould not accept additional commitments, they might be persuaded to undertake responsibility for security in the Southern Cameroonsif they thought that we would in any case withdraw when ourtrusteeship came to an end.(e) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that if it were necessaryto undertake further commitments in the Southern Cameroons,offsetting reductions would have to be made in oversea expenditureelsewhere. Nevertheless, he would agree that some modestcontribution, up to million, might be afforded as a final measureof assistance to the territory upon becoming independent.The Prime Minister, summing up, said that it was the general view of the Cabinet that, on balance, it would not be justifiable toundertake the additional commitment which would be involved if a united Kingdom battalion were retained in the Southern Cameroonsafter independence. The United Kingdom representatives at themeeting with Mr. Foncha and Mr. Ahidjo should conduct their discussions on the basis that it was our intention to withdraw theUnited Kingdom battalion after 1st October. They should seek toascertain what measures were contemplated by Mr. Foncha andMr. Ahidjo for the maintenance of the administration and of internal security, and how far they were agreed about future arrangementsfor the territory and its association with the Cameroun Republic.They could indicate that we would be prepared to provide financialassistance amounting to    million to the territory during the first year after independence, either to enable our expatriate officers tocontinue in the administration or to support the budget. It was tobe hoped that, in the face of this attitude, the French authorities would realise that there was no alternative but for them to acceptfuture responsibility for security in the Cameroons, as well as in theCameroun Republic.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the United Kingdom battalion in the southern Cameroons should be withdrawn after 1st October, andthat our support for the territory should thereafter belimited to financial assistance of not more than    million.(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to formulate instructions for theUnited Kingdom representatives at the meeting with thePrime Minister of the Southern Cameroons and the PrimeMinister of the Cameroun Republic on the lines indicated by the Prime Minister.
In awEducation 9.  The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the teachers&apos; Minister of Education (C. (61) 78) about the machinery for the salaries settlement of teachers&apos; salaries.(previous reference: The Minister of Education said that, since the Cabinefs lastCC. (61) 30th discussion on 6th June, it had been agreed between the ChancellorConclusions. 0f the Exchequer, the Secretary of State for Scotland, the MinisterMinute 3) Gf Labour and himself that the English teachers should be given anincrease equivalent to an increase of 16  per cent, in the total cost of salaries as from 1st January, 1962, as recommended by the burnham committee, and that the Scottish teachers should be given a 14 percent, increase as from 1st July, 1961. The first decision was not tobe announced at least until after the National Union of Teachershad considered the recommendation on 17th June, but the Secretaryof State for &quot;Scotland proposed to announce the Scottish settlementthat day. It was by now generally expected that the Governmentwould press for some change in the machinery for the settlement of teachers&apos; salaries and, in agreement with the Secretary of State, theMinister proposed that in future the views of the responsible ministers should be made known to, and taken into consideration by, both sidesat an early stage of the negotiations. He also proposed that legislation should be introduced to give the Government power in England andWales, as they already had in Scotland, to amend as well as to acceptor reject a negotiated agreement. These proposals could be defendedboth on the ground that the Exchequer bore more than half the costof teachers&apos; salaries and in the interest of the education service itself.They were, however, likely to excite opposition both from the localauthorities and from the teachers, and the Minister would thereforeprefer, rather than announce a definite Government decision, to seek to work out with both sides changes in the machinery on the lineshe had proposed.Discussion showed that there was general support in the cabinet for these proposals. They must, however, be expected to revive theclaim of the National Association of Schoolmasters to be represented on the teachers&apos; panel of the Burnham Committee and more serious to stimulate a strong demand for some form of arbitration. this must be resisted by all possible means; for, if it were conceded, theGovernment might well find themselves in a position even less satisfactory than the present.In further discussion it was suggested that an attempt should bemade to synchronise future negotiations on teachers&apos; salaries inEngland and Wales and in Scotland. As against this it was argued that, as the salary structure in the two countries was not directlycomparable, there might be positive advantage in keeping the 8. The Colonial Secretary said that the West Indies conference had resolved the problem of the transfer of matters from the reservelist, which particularly affected Jamaica; but it was possible that itmight break down on the issue of freedom of movement between the islands, with which was linked the question of financial assistancefrom the United Kingdom. The United States Government had agreat interest in the establishment of a successful federation, andmight in due course be prepared to provide financial assistance. Itmight be possible to reach agreement on the basis of sending a surveyteam to study a number of development projects for the smallerislands for which financial assistance might be considered. It might,however, be necessary to take an early decision about the level offinancial assistance, and he would in that event consult the Chancellorof the Exchequer.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Colonial Secretary.West Indies(previous reference:CC. (60) 57thConclusions,Minute 2)
SuezFinanceCompany(previous reference:C.C. (60) 62ndConclusions.Minute 11)10. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (61) 74) about the disposal of the government&apos;s holding in the Suez Finance Company.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had now given further consideration to the financial advantages and disadvantages of an early sale of the Governmenfs holding and to the method ofits disposal. The Company&apos;s interests in Saharan oil and in theChannel Tunnel Study Group were comparatively small and toospeculative to justify deferring a sale on that account, and there alsoseemed little doubt now that the Egyptian Government would meet their compensation liabilities. In view, however, of some recentsigns of renewed pressure for an increase in the compensation fundprovided by the Anglo-Egyptian settlement for former owners ofproperty in Egypt, he proposed to give further consideration to the exact timing of the disposal of the Governmenfs holding.As regards the method of disposal, although a block deal witha syndicate would have some obvious advantages, it would benecessary to have regard to the interests of other British shareholdersin increasing their holdings in the Company, and to the special interests of a number of banking and other concerns, includingRothschilds. On balance, it seemed best to dispose of the holdinggradually through the market, by selling blocks when there was an active interest in the shares. Subject to further consideration of the timing, he proposed, as a preliminary step, to consult the management of the company, and as a matter of courtesy to inform the FrenchGovernment and the Bank of France. If these consultations were satisfactory, it would then be desirable to make an announcement inParliament of the Governmenfs intention to dispose of their holding and immediately before such an announcement to inform certainprivate interests which were already aware of the possibility of asale.Discussion showed that the Cabinet agreed in principle that theGovernment should dispose of their holding in the Suez FinanceCompany. Some doubts were expressed, however, about the advisability of selling this asset in London; it might be preferable inpresent circumstances to obtain foreign currency through a sale inParis with the object of benefiting the reserves. It was also suggestedthat consideration would need to be given to the proposal to disclose the Governmenfs intention to the French Government, the Bank ofFrance and certain private interests, in order to avoid anticipatingthe announcement to Parliament and to avoid giving any unfairadvantage to the interests in question.The Cabinet (1) Agreed in principle that the Governmenfs shareholding inthe Suez Finance Company should be sold.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to give furtherconsideration to the timing and method of disposal of thisshareholding.C.C. 31 (61)settlements separate in time. It was agreed that this aspect of thequestion should be further considered.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C. (61) 78.(2) Invited the Minister of Education to give furtherconsideration, in consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Secretary of State for Scotland, tothe question of synchronising future negotiations onteachers&apos; salaries in England and Wales and in Scotland.
11. The Minister of Aviation said that the Economic PolicyCommittee had approved his proposals for changes in theGovernments policy on civil airports. His main proposals were thatthe en route technical services covering the country as a whole andthose related to the operations at individual airports should remainin the hands of the Government, but that their cost should in future be recovered from the airline operators. The ownership and management of the main international airports should be transferredto a new independent statutory body, v/hile that of the provincialairports should be de-centralised wherever possible by transfer tolocal authorities, who might in certain circumstances be givenassistance from the Exchequer. These proposals would relieve theMinister from Parliamentary control over the day-to-day management of, and accounting for, the airports and would accord with recommendations on the London group of airports shortly expected from the Select Committee on Estimates; and they would enlist the enthusiasm of local authorities in operating their own airports and reduce the total cost to the Exchequer. The Minister proposed thatthey should be set out in a White Paper which he hoped to be ableto present to Parliament before the summer recess.Discussion showed that there was general agreement in theCabinet with the substance of these proposals. Since, however, itwas most unlikely that time could be found in the following sessionfor the necessary legislation, it might be preferable to postponepublication of a White Paper. If the Select Committee&apos;s report made it desirable to give some early indication of the governments intentions, this might be effected by a less detailed statement beforethe recess.The Cabinet (1) Endorsed the decision of the Economic Policy Committee to approve the proposals of the Minister of Aviation for anew policy on civil airports.(2) Invited the Minister of Aviation to circulate a draft statementof the Governmenfs policy for civil airports and, in due course, a draft White Paper setting out the proposals indetail.12. The Prime Minister said that he proposed to announce inthe House of Commons that day that arrangements were being madefor the Commonwealth Secretary and two other senior Ministers tomake separate journeys covering all the other independent commonwealth countries to discuss the problems of the relationship between the United Kingdom and the European economic community and the possible arrangements which might meet theneeds of the other Commonwealth countries and the other membersof the European Free Trade Association. It was hoped that thesevisits might begin towards the end of the month.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Prime Minister.CivilAviation(previous reference:C.C. (60) 27thConclusions,Minute 4)AirportPolicyEurope(previous reference:C.C. (61) 29thConclusions,Minute 5)

</content>
</cab>
