<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/35/0 images: 231-235</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC majesty&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  June 1961C.C. (61)34th conclusions copy No. 48CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, on tuesday, 20th June, 1961, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the    Right    Hon.    Lord    Mills,Paymaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food also present:The Right Hon. martin.P.,     parliamentary treasury redmayne,Secretary,Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. F. A. bishop mr. M. Reed
contents minute no. Subject page 1     National Theatre      ..................      32     Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland      .........       4Northern Rhodesia3     Foreign Affairs.....................       5Soviet UnionLaos
national theatre(previous reference:C.C. (61) 11thConclusions,Minute 5)1. The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that at their last discussion of proposals for a National Theatre the Cabinet had decided that the most realistic course would be to concentrate ongiving as much direct assistance as possible to provincial theatresand increasing the subventions to the Old Vic and the RoyalShakespeare Memorial Theatre. New proposals had now been put before him by the London County Council (L.C.C.). Their offer was that, if the Government would provide towards the cost ofbuilding a new National Theatre the  1 million approved byParliament in the National Theatre Act of 1949, they would themselves contribute from the rates whatever additional sum was required. The building of the theatre would be undertaken by theJoint Council for the National Theatre, under the chairmanship ofLord Chandos, in co-operation with Sadler&apos;s Wells (which was atpresent receiving an Exchequer subvention of  170,000 a year inrespect of its London activities), the Old Vic and the RoyalShakespeare Memorial Theatre (whose annual subventions theChancellor was prepared to increase to  130,000 and  100,000respectively, to cover their activities other than provincial touring,which would be provided for separately). If the National Theatrerequired additional assistance from public funds above this totalof  400,000 a year, it would have to be provided from other sources,including possibly the L.C.C. It was most desirable that all thethree institutions should join in the National Theatre scheme, andhe would do his best to bring this about. If, however, one of them should decide not to participate, it would receive its subventiondirect and the Exchequer contribution to the National Theatreitself would be correspondingly reduced. These proposals were known to be broadly acceptable to the Chairman of the Joint Counciland the Chairman of the Arts Council. It would not be easy for theGovernment to reject them, since they accorded with the authorityalready given by Parliament.In discussion it was recognised that it would be difficult torefuse this offer, especially as the scheme would not affect the amountof direct Exchequer assistance available for theatres in the provinces.On the other hand, an Exchequer contribution on the scale proposedto a National Theatre in London would increase the difficulty of resisting demands on behalf of similar projects which had alreadybeen put forward for Edinburgh and Cardiff and might be expectedalso from some of the large provincial cities in England. Nor was it certain that demands for additional Exchequer contributions tomeet continuing deficits in the National Theatre could be resisted.Several Ministers expressed doubts whether a substantial increase in Government expenditure on the arts was compatible withthe general concern about the current economic situation and themeasures that might be necessary to correct it.Summing up, the Prime Minister said that the balance ofopinion in the Cabinet was in favour of accepting the L.C.C.&apos;proposal. But the economic situation made it inopportune to give any definite undertaking to that effect or to make any announcementof the Government^ indentions. The best course would thereforebe to invite the Joint Council for the National Theatre, inco-operation with Sadlefs Wells, the Old Vic and the RoyalShakespeare Memorial Theatre, to formulate and submit to theChancellor a scheme on the lines proposed. These tactics would ensure some considerable delay before it became necessary for theGovernment to undertake a definite commitment.The Cabinet Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to ask the joint council for the National Theatre, in co-operation with
Federationof RhodesiaandNyasaiandNorthernRhodesia(previous reference:C.C. (61) 33rdConclusions)2. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of theconstitutional proposals for Northern Rhodesia, on the basis of adraft message from the Prime Minister to the Prime Minister of theFederation, Sir Roy Welensky, circulated by the commonwealth secretary.The draft message informed Sir Roy Welensky that his proposalfor a sixty/forty ratio between the upper and lower rolls in votingfor national seats had been rejected by the other parties and that,since it was outside the spirit and framework of the White Paper ofFebruary 1961, it could not be adopted in the absence of a generalmeasure of acquiescence. The message set out the modifications which could be made to the proposals contained in the White Paper,and explained in particular the significance of basing the qualifyingminimum on races instead of rolls. It also invited Sir Roy Welenskyto put forward any ideas he wished for a middle roll scheme.In discussion the following points were made:(a) It was suggested that the proposal for a qualifying minimum of 12^ per cent, of the votes cast by each race, or 400 votes from each race, could be criticised on the ground that it was unreasonable to expect a European candidate to obtain so large a proportion of african votes. The minimum might be reduced to 10 per cent., or300 votes from each race. It was argued, on the other hand, thatthe qualifying minimum gave a considerable advantage to Europeancandidates, and that to reduce it would virtually eliminate themulti-racial concept on which voting for national seats was based.There was general agreement that, although the possibility of considering a reduction in the qualifying minimum at a later stageshould not be excluded, this should not be suggested at the presenttime.(b) The Foreign Secretary said that, although the proposal for asixty/forty ratio should be rejected, the possibility of a furthermodification, such as some form of a middle roll, based on the concept of the equalisation of races rather than rolls, should not be ruled out. In present international circumstances we should seek to retain the greatest measure of support from the federation government and their European supporters.The Lord Chancellor pointed out that, although the white paper had favoured the method of equalising the upper and lowerrolls for the election of national candidates, it had also stated thatthe Government would be prepared to consider other proposalswhich would secure their objectives of substantially increased Africanrepresentation and a non-racial political approach.There was general agreement that the Government could notrefuse to examine any reasonable proposals, whether for a middleroll or some other scheme, which Sir Roy Weiensky might putforward.(c) It was suggested that the message should first explain the modifications to the White Paper proposals which we were preparedto make, and that this should be followed by an explanation of the rejection of the proposal for a sixty/forty ratio. Since the possibilityof further modifications ought not at this stage to be excluded, itwould &quot;be preferable not to restate our intention to maintain theprinciple of equalisation of the rolls, as proposed in the White Paper.Sadler&apos;s Wells, the Old Vic and the Royal ShakespeareMemorial Theatre, to submit a scheme for a National    Theatre designed to implement the offer made by theLondon County Council.
Foreign 3.   The Foreign Secretary said that evidence was accumulatingAffairs from many spheres of international relations that the policy of theSoviet Union    Soviet Government was no longer directed to the possibility of(Previous       serious negotiation with the West.  For example, their insistenceReference:      on tripartite administration of any control organisation had broughtC.C. (60) 43rd   the Nuclear Tests Conference to a standstill, and they had made it conclusions,    clear that they would regard any system of inspection as espionageMinute 2)       unless it was accompanied by total disarmament.  Nor was there any sign of a serious desire on the part of Mr. Khrushchev tonegotiate on Berlin; the expectation was that he would proceed to sign a separate peace treaty with East Germany in the followingOctober.Laos No progress was being made in the Geneva Conference on(Previous Laos, and failing an agreement between the three Laotian princes atReference: Zurich, which seemed unlikely to come about, hostilities might wellC.C. (61) 31st recommence. In that event, it would hardly be possible to avoidConclusions. military intervention by the South-East Asia Treaty OrganisationMinute 1) jn order to prevent the whole country being over-run by the PathetLao.The Cabinet-Took note of these statements by the Foreign Secretary.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,20th June, 1961.In further discussion a number of drafting amendments to theproposed message to Sir Roy Welensky were approved.The Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for hismessage, as approved in their discussion, to be sent to thePrime  Minister of the Federation of Rhodesia and nyasaland forthwith.

</content>
</cab>
