<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/35/0 images: 290-294</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. July 1961C.C. (61) Copy No. 48*       A       Cfc      *43rd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W.1, onMonday, 24fh July, 1961, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C.. Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education  . ,The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Paymaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture, Fish-eries and food the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir.Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of HomeSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.Minister of Housing and Local Government  and  Minister  for  welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Peter ThorneycroftM.P.. Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald MaudlingM.P., President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Edward Heath. M.P.Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Ernest Marples. M.P.Minister of transport the following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter, The Right Hon   J. Enoch Powell,M.P..   Minister   of   Pensions   and M.P., Minister of HealthNational insurance the Right Hon. Richard Wood, M.P.. The Right Hon. Reginald Bevins, M.P.,Minister of Power Postmaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P.,      Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. F. A. bishop mr. M. reed DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT
ContentsEconomic Situation
EconomicSituation(previous reference:CC. (61) 41stConclusions,Minute 4)CC. 43 (61)The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the economic situation.They had before them a further memorandum by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer (C. (61) 112) about the second economic regulator,which would impose a surcharge on employers&apos; contributions underthe National Insurance scheme.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in his statement in theHouse of Commons on the following day, he would try to explain insimple terms the balance of payments difficulties and the need forremedial action. He would bring out the fact that in 1960-61personal incomes had increased by  1,365 millions, while production had increased by only  500- 600 millions. Since the latter should cover not only the increase in consumption, but also the needs ofpublic and private investment, together with any increase in exports,it was clearly necessary to apply some considerable restriction to home demand. For the longer-term he would announce that he intended,in the next Finance Bill, to oring forward specific proposals for taxingprofits on short-term investment, whether in stocks or in land. this announcement might help to create a more favourable climate ofopinion in which to appeal for a pause in increases in wages and profits. He would also refer to the control of private investment in thenon-sterling area, and to the need to secure reasonable remittancesfrom investments overseas. He would make it clear that theGovernment intended to keep future public expenditure under control,but the terms of this part of his statement had not yet been finally agreed with the Ministers concerned. As regards oversea aid, he now accepted that it might not be practicable to prescribe a ceiling, but hewould make it clear that the present level of aid could not be increasedby any substantial amount in the future. He would appeal to industryto become more competitive, for example by abolishing restrictive practices, but he did not propose to imply that legislation for thispurpose might be introduced. In this connexion he could refer tothe valuable effects of the reduction in tariffs which it was hoped wouldresult from the current negotiations under the General Agreement on tariffs and Trade.As regards short-term measures, the Governor of the Bankof England was ready to call for an increase in the banks&apos;special deposits scheme, and for restraint in the grant of credit by the clearing banks and other institutions. Bank rate would be raised.The first economic regulator, which increased customs duties and purchase tax, would be brought into operation at the full rate of 10 percent, at midnight on the following day. Application would at once bemade for a substantial drawing and standby credit from theInternational Monetary Fund; and. in view of the measures whichwere to be announced, it was hoped that this application would be successful.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that his advisers weredoubtful whether these measures would W suihcient to restore confidence in sterling. The additional measures which might be takenwere:(i) to apply the second economic regulator&apos;, which provided for ;&apos;isurcharge on employers&apos; contributions under the National Insurancescheme;(ii) to introduce a further restriction on hire purchase facilities;and(iii) to include in his statement an announcement thatthe Government would only agree to increases in teachers&apos; salaries inEngland and Wales of a lower cost than those already offered by thelocal education authorities.In discussion the following points were made:(a) It was argued that, as the Government had secured the powerto use the second economic regulator, it would be unreasonable to refrain from using it in the present emergency.  It would not only serve
to reduce consumption, but it would help employers to resistunjustifiable wage claims. On the other it was argued that the surchange would be unselective in its incidence and would be generally regarded, abroad as well as at home, as an unnecessary addition to industrial costs. Its use might thus appear to be inconsistent withthe Government^ efforts to make industry more competitive and,since it would be resented by both employers and workers, it wouldnot help to achieve a national approach to our economic problems.On balance, therefore, it would be inadvisable to use this secondregulator.(/)) Further restrictions on hire-purchase would seriously affectthose industries which would in any case suffer from the imposition ofthe first economic regulator. Despite the pressures in the economy,there was evidence that several industries, including some which had made a substantial effort to increase exports, were faced with theprospect of a decline in demand in the near future. There was accordingly general agreement that further restrictions on hire-purchase should be neither imposed nor threatened.(c) The Cabinet were in general agreement with the proposal thatthe Government should withhold agreement to the increase inteachers&quot; salaries which had already been offered by the localeducation authorities, and that the cost of the increase in England andWales should be restricted to  42 millions. There were arguments forpresenting this decision in the context of the need to reduce public expenditure, rather than the need to control wages in the public sector.It seemed best for the announcement about teachers&apos; salaries to beincluded in the statement to be made by the Chancellor of theExchequer. In that event the Minister of Education would explain the decision to representatives of the local education authorities and ofthe teachers on 26th July.((/) In appealing for restraint in wages and profits, the Chancellorof the Exchequer would indicate that, where an offer had been madein response to a wage demand, the ordinary processes of wagenegotiation should continue to be pursued. It was possible that the processes of arbitration, if they were allowed to continue, would resultin some wage awards in the public sector which would make it difficult for the Government to maintain that they had played their part in enforcing a pause. Even so. it would not be possible for theGovernment to announce that they would refrain from honouringfuture arbitration awards.ie) The measures which the Chancellor of the Exchequer had itin mind to announce might be thought to be sufficient to meet theimmediate situation, by effecting a substantial reduction in futuredemand, on the assumption that a reasonable degree of success couldbe achieved in securing a pause m wages and profits, and in containingfuture public expenditure. There was general agreement that the degree of success in achieving wage restraint would be decisive for thefuture of the economy.(/) The statement to be made by the Chancellor of the exchequer would make it clear that, if the credit restrictions and the representa-tions to be made by the Governor of the Bank of England were notsuccessful in discouraging excessive lending for building purposes, theGovernment would not hesitate to introduce other measures. By this it was intended to imply that legislation to control building might beintroduced, if necessary, in the autumn.Summing up the discussion the Prime Minister said that thebalance of opinion in the Cabinet was clearly against introducing, atleast for the time being, the surcharge on employers&apos; contributions orfurther controls on hire purchase. It did not seem that these measures were necessary for the immediate purpose of securing assistance fromthe International Monetary Fund, and they might prejudice theGovernments longer-term aim to restore the soundness of the economy,which depended on their success in inducing wage restraint and keeping
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,25th July, 1961.down production costs. In presenting the plan as a whole, reference might be made to the recent deterioration in the international politicalsituation, and the external factors leading to our present difficulties should be emphasised. This would make it easier to obtain theco-operation of all sections of the community. Given this co-operation,and determination on the part of the Government to restrict public expenditure to the minimum, it should be possible to overcome thecurrent economic difficulties.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that neither the surcharge on employers&apos; contributions to the National Insurance scheme, nor further controls onhire purchase, should be introduced for the time being.(2) Agreed that the increase in teachers&apos; salaries recently offered by the local education authorities in England and wales should not be approved; and invited the Chancellor of theExchequer to announce this decision in terms to be agreed with the Secretary of State for Scotland, the Minister ofEducation and the Minister of Labour.

</content>
</cab>
