<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/10/3 images: 66-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT33Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)283rd Conclusions.Copy No-     f?3tOTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 283 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;$Room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Wednesday, November 6, 1940, at12 noon.Present :The Eight Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Eight Hon. C. E. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Eight Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Eight Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Eight Hon. Sir John Anderson,.M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Eight Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Aircraft Production.The Eight Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and Minister ofNational Service.The following were also present :The Eight Hon. Viscount Cranborne,M.P., Secretary of State forDominion affair rs.The Eight Hon. Lord Eeith, Ministerof Works and Buildings and first commissioner of Works (Items and 9).The Eight Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.The Eight Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty(Items 1 to 3).The Eight Hon. E. H. Cross, M.P.,Minister of Shipping (Item 7).The Eight Hon. W. S. Morrison, K.C.,M.P., Postmaster-General (Items and 9).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1 to 7).Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1 to 6).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.[21899]b
\YAR CABINET 283 (40).Contents.minute no.                                        Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations................      17Air Operations.Naval Operations Attack on convoy by a German raider.Military Operations Italy-Greece.Crete.Assistance to Greece.Attitude of Bulgaria.Egypt.German troops in Italy.2      Munitions Production ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      18Decline in output.3      United States of America      ....      ........      ....      ....      18Presidential election.Financial co-operation.Defence plans.4      France    ................................      19Relations with the Vichy Government.5      France    ................................      19General de Gaulle&apos;s movements.-6      Tangier   ...............................      19The International Zone: Attitude of Spain.7       Shipping................................      20Placing of orders for merchant ships in the United States ofAmerica.8      Government Departments : Protected Accommodation   ....      20Faraday Building.&apos;9      Parliament        ....       ....       ....       ....       ....       ....       ....      21Alternative accommodation.
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 282ndConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.naval operations.Attack onConvoy by aGerman raider.MilitaryOperations:Italy-Greece.Crete.Assistance to greece.1.   The Chief of the Air Staff reported that the aircraftcasualties during the previous twenty-four hours had been : Our own 6 aircraft (3 pilots safe).Enemy 6 Fighters destroyed.2 Fighters probable.2 Fighters damaged.Some 250 enemy aircraft had operated over this country duringthe previous day and some 225 (most of which had had London as their objective) during the previous night. One interception hadbeen made during the night by a Hurricane, acting in co-operationwith searchlights, but the enemy aircraft had not been brought down.The previous night&apos;s bombing operations over Germany hadbeen successful. It had not been possible to send bombers from thiscountry to Northern Italy, but 6 bombers from Malta had taken part in a successful attack on Brindisi. Full reports were not yet available, but it was feared that 2 of the bombers had crashed onlanding.The First Sea Lord reported that an 8-knot Convoy of 38 ships had been attacked in mid-Atlantic on the previous evening by aGerman raider, reported to be of the Graf Spee class. The first report of shelling of the ships in convoy had come in at 7-55 p.m.,and the last report at 9-47 p.m.The Navy was now faced with two difficult problems : (a) the more effective protection of the other convoys now at sea, or about to put to sea.(b) the measures to be taken to deal with the raider herself.The First Sea Lord informed the War Cabinet of the measureswhich had been taken to deal with both problems. These measures are recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.The Prime Minister said that the situation was much moreunfavourable than at the time when the Graf Spee had broken out into the Atlantic. We were now maintaining a large Fleet in theMediterranean, and we no longer had the French as allies.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that the greek army was now mobilised, but that concentration would not becompleted for eight days. The main Greek forces were in theFiorina sector. It looked as though an Italian force had penetratedbetween the Epirus sector and the Pindus detachment, thrusting inthe direction of Phourka, Vovousa and Metsovo. A hundred italian prisoners had been taken, and it looked as though part, at any rate,of this force had been cut off.Our Military Attaches in Greece gave an encouraging accountof the temper of the Greek Army. The morale of the Italian forcesseemed to be low, judging from the prisoners taken. This was confirmed by reports of the Italian pilots captured at Salonika.The CJ-reek Government had asked, as a matter of urgency, thatthe Greek Division in Crete should be sent to the mainland. these troops would need to be replaced. One light and one heavy A.A.Regiment and a Field Company had left for Crete on the previous day.   A second British Battalion was standing by, ready to leave.The Prime Minister said that a telegram had been receivedfrom the Secretary of State for War (A.E. 58) saying that he andthe British Commanders in the Middle East agreed to the measures proposed, with the additional risks involved in the Western Desert,which must be accepted in view of the political commitment to aidGreece.[21899] b 2
Attitude of The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that GeneralBulgaria. Metaxas was most anxious that Bulgaria should be pressed to.give an assurance that she would not attack Greece, thus enabling Greek forces on the Thracian frontier to be transferred to the Albanianfront.The Foreign Secretary said that he would renew the representa-tions which he had already made in this matter to the Bulgarianand Turkish Governments.Egypt. There were indications that the Italian advance in the western desert might be resumed. The dispositions were similar to those at the time of the last advance, which had taken place five days before the full moon. This looked as though we might expect anattack about the 9th November.German Troops At least one German Division, with tropical equipment, wasin Italy. reported to be at Foggia, in South Italy.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.munitions production.Decline in output.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 273rdConclusions,Minute 4.)2. The Prime Minister said that there had been a considerabledecline in the output of munitions in the last two months. Inparticular, the Tank programme was seriously in arrear. Thisfalling off was largely, but not, he thought, wholly, attributable to.the effect of air raids.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that if hecould be told in which of the factories it was essential to speed upproduction, he might be able to afford help by provision of additional labour, and possibly in other ways. Perhaps he might discuss thematter with the Minister of Supply.The War Cabinet approved this suggestion.United Statesof America.presidential election.Pinancialco-operation.(previous reference:W.M. (40)232ndConclusions,Minute 3.)Defence plans.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 273rdConclusions,Minute 7.)3. The War Cabinet were informed that the latest informa-tion was that President Roosevelt would be re-elected by a large majority.   The election might turn out to be a democratic landslide.The Chancellor of the Exchequer reminded his colleagues that sir Frederick Phillips, Under Secretary of the Treasury, had visited the United States in the summer. It had then been arranged that, if President Roosevelt was re-elected, he should again visit theUnited States, arriving about the 1st December. It was proposedthat Sir Frederick should leave in about ten days&apos; or a fortnight&apos;s time, in order to arrive on the date named. Lord Lothian&apos;s view was that, although America would be prepared to give us financialassistance, the conditions imposed would not be easy.The War Cabinet agreed that Sir Frederick Phillipsshould proceed to the United States as proposed.The War Cabinet were informed that our Assistant naval attache in Washington had been shown certain United States naval defence plans, in strict confidence (telegram No. 2490 H romWashington).Discussion ensued whether the information so obtained shouldbe communicated to the Dominions. It was pointed out that theinformation was hypothetical and had been communicated to usvery informally, and in the circumstances the War Cabinet decidedthat we were not called upon to transmit it to the Dominions.1 Cq^
35France.Relations withthe &quot;vichy government.(previous references:W.M. (40) 282ndConclusions,Minutes 3and 4.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thought that difficulties with the Vichy Government might arise in three ways.First, out of the blockade. This was not a very serious difficulty.Secondly, from an attempt by the French to bring the Jean Bartand the Richelieu into Toulon. This had been dealt with in the warning which Sir Samuel Hoare had given to the FrenchGovernment. The third likely source of trouble would be a Frenchexpedition to attack the French colonies which had declared forGeneral de Gaulle. There were indications that a force was being concentrated at Dakar, possibly for this purpose.The Foreign Secretary suggested that we should warn the vichy Government that if they attempted to send such an expedi-tion we should, of course, resist it, and our forces would come intoconflict which we wished to avoid.The Prime Minister thought that it would be a good thing tosend a warning on these lines. We might, however, go ratherfurther and add that we had no intention of launching anotherattack on Dakar; making it clear that if, for example, the port fellunder German domination and our intentions changed, we wouldgive them due notice. In exchange for this declaration of our intention not to attack Dakar we should invite the Vichy Govern-ment to refrain from action against the colonies which had declaredfor General de Gaulle.The War Cabinet :-Invited the Foreign Secretary to draft a telegram toSir Samuel Hoare, for the approval of the Prime Minister,on the lines suggested above.France.General de gaulle&apos;smovements.5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to atelegram from General Spears at Duala, dated the 29th October(1600/29 cipher 29/10), indicating that General de Gaulle proposedto return to London towards the end of November and re-establishhis headquarters there. It had been suggested that a reply shouldbe sent indicating that, while we would welcome General de Gaulle&apos; return here for a visit, we doubted the wisdom of his returning toestablish his headquarters here.The Prime Minister said that on the whole he thought that thebest course was to leave things to develop for a few days beforesending a message on the lines proposed.The War Cabinet concurred in this suggestion.Tangier.The Inter-national Zone:attitude of spain.6. The Foreign Secretary drew attention to the telegrams from Tangier reporting action by the Spanish representative whichlooked like the beginnings of a Spanish coup. Our Ambassador in madrid had reported a talk which he had had with the SpanishMinister for Foreign Affairs (Telegrams 956 and 957 fromMadrid). Sir Samuel Hoare had said that we were anxious to avoid a situation which would embroil Spain with Great Britain and theUnited States, at the moment when the economic negotiations werebeing resumed. Senor Suner had said that when the war had started, Tangier had been in reality a French protectorate, and thatwith the collapse of France and the entry of Italy into the war theposition had become dangerous and intolerable. He had, however,responded very warmly to a suggestion that we should endeavourto reach agreement on the matter, and had asked that discussion should start at once.A reply had been despatched (No. 997 to Madrid), pointing outthat we were entitled to protest to the Spanish Government on theaction which their representative at Tangier had taken in seeking to modify the institutions of the international regime without
notice. A formal protest should be put on record, but at the sametime Sir Samuel should intimate that we were willing to startdiscussions with the Spanish Government on the position ofTangier, making it plain that we recognised Spain&apos;s special interests there, and that the object of the discussions would be toreach an understanding about the best way to regularise theposition.The War Cabinet took note with approval of the action taken.Shipping.Placing of ordersfor merchant ships in theUnited Statesof America.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 254thConclusions,Minute 9.)7. The War Cabinet had before them a joint Memorandum bythe First Lord of the Admiralty and the Minister of Shipping(W.P. (40) 433).The Minister of Shipping said that on the. 19th September theWar Cabinet had decided that orders should be placed in the UnitedStates for the construction of 30 ships, each of 10,000 dead-weighttons, and that the construction of a further 30 ships should beconsidered in November if either increased losses or increased demands on shipping made this necessary. He now asked the WarCabinet to approve the placing of this second order. Betterconditions regarding price and delivery would be obtained if theorder was placed at once.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he could not oppose this request, although the rise of 25 per cent, in the total estimateof the cost was disturbing. He asked, however, that the treasury should be consulted in advance if there was any likelihood of thepresent estimate being exceeded. He also suggested that the ships should be of a standardised simple type.Doubt was expressed as to whether the order for the 60 vesselswas on a large enough scale, and whether it should not be increased.The Minister of Shipping said that a Meeting was being held that afternoon, as a result of which it might be necessary to ask the WarCabinet for sanction to place further shipbuilding orders in theStates and. Canada.Reference was made to the figures of shipping losses and gainsgiven in the weekly resume issued under the auspices of the Chiefsof Staff. It was suggested that these figures, by including the shipstransferred to us from Danish, French and other flags, gave a toofavourable picture of the balance of gains and losses. The Ministerof Shipping said that he had this point under consideration.The War Cabinet:-(a) Approved the proposal contained in the joint Memorandumby the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Minister ofShipping, for the placing of orders for the building offurther ships in the United States and Canada.(b) Agreed that the Treasury should be consulted in advanceshould the estimated cost of these vessels appear likelyto be exceeded.GovernmentDepartments:protected accommodation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 275thConclusions.Minute 2.)FaradayBuilding.8. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by thePostmaster-General (W.P. (40) 414 Revise) about the proposal that two floors of Faraday Building should be given up by the general post Office and used for special purposes.The P ostmaster-General said that if, as was now suggested,two floors of the Faraday Building were taken for non-Post Office,purposes, the Post Office would have to go without : (a) reserve accommodation for trunk purposes should FaradayNorth Building be put out of action; and(b) reserve accommodation for a City automatic exchangeshould such an exchange be put out of action.
In his opinion it was of the first importance that this alternative accommodation should be available in order to ensure the mainten-ance of essential communications. Further, owing to the cablesystem it was impossible for him to find alternative accommodationelsewhere. Should, however, the War Cabinet decide to accept therisk, then he would ask that the two floors to be surrendered by thePost Office should be not the ground and the first floor but the first and the second floors.The Minister of A aircraft Production outlined his proposals0 for alternative accommodation to house essential Government staffs.This covered the taking over of accommodation in Faraday House,Curzon House, and the B.B.C. Offices. As regards Faraday House,he had reduced his requirements now to two floors. As for thedormitory accommodation for the staff, under his (the Minister of aircraft Production^) proposals this would be increased ratherthan decreased, and Post Office employees would not suffer.Referring to the suggestion that part of the B.B.C.&apos;s premisesshould be taken over, the Minister said that before any action wastaken he would submit his proposals to the War Cabinet.The War Cabinet-(a) Agreed in principle that two floors of Faraday House shouldbe taken over from the Post Office for the purpose ofproviding alternative accommodation for essentialGovernment staffs.(b) Invited the Minister of Aircraft Production, the Ministerof Works and Buildings and the Postmaster-General to consult as to the detailed arrangements.Parliament.Alternativeaccom modation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 279thConclusions,Minute 8.)9. The Prime Minister said that such good progress had beenmade in providing an alternative meeting place for the Houses ofParliament in Church House, that it would be possible for theHouse of Commons to meet there on the following afternoon. the accommodation for the House of Lords would take a little longer to complete. He therefore proposed to suggest to the House that thisaccommodation should be given a trial immediately.The War Cabinet agreed to the Prime Ministers proposal.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,November 6, 1940.

1J9 1DEPARllvIENTAL (SECDecypher.Mr. Butler (Washington).31st October, 1940.D.R.1.18 a.m.3.10 p.m.1st November, 1%0.1st November, 1%0.No. 2490.MOST SECRET.Captain Clarke has &quot;been shown by Plans Division of navy department privately and unofficially their appreciation ofthe policy the United States Navy should adopt in the eventof America entering the war.   It was understood that apjjreciationreflected generally Admiral Stark&apos;s view and would be represented by him to higher authority.Document was lengthy and interruptions during cursoryperusal precluded a thorough absorption of the contents.The review of present situation was gloomy and conclusion reached was that British programme without considerable combatantaid from American Navy was impossible.   Appreciation anticipatedultimate completion of Axis control in Mediterranean and argued that this would largely nullify British blockade.   Argumentfollowed that very considerable direct Naval, Military and Airassistance in European area must be given to the British toensure victory, and that at the same time a flow of material assistance must not be affected.Appreciation then contended that the conduct of a fullyoffensive war by the United States against Japan would involve thewhole of American Naval and industrial resources, and that withthe adoption of such a forward plan, United States Navy will be unable to provide the minimum assistance in the Atlantic and europe necessary to prevent a British defeat.   Consequently any idea of conducting simultaneously an offensive war against japan and satisfactory assistance in Europe must be abandoned.Appreciation recommended that every political expediencyshould be adopted by the United States and the United Kingdom to preclude a conflict with Japan until the war had been won in theWest.Should however Japan take advantage of America&apos;s preoccupationin the event of her giving military assistance to Great Britain,and the war in the Far East be forced upon America and the Allies,the appreciation proposed that America should conduct a strictlydefensive war against Japan.   Dispositions to this end were notdetailed but it appeared that Naval Staff envisage the maintenanceof a reasonable fleet in Mid-Pacific with a possible co-ordinationreinforcement by submarines and perhaps cruisers&apos;of the Dutch andBritish strengths in Malaya(?) and the acceptance of loss of the philippines and Borneo and even ultimately Netherlands East indies and Singapore.In general a war in the Par East should be relegated tosecond place and ultimate eviction of Japan deferred until asatisfactory conclusion to European war was certain.A fuller version of the foregoing was dispatched to theAdmiralty in sea bag which left this week.   Captain Clarke is anxious to emphasise that he cannot be sure that) the above viewswill necessarily be those held finally or put forward officially,but insofar as it is practicably summarised in an appreciation of this nature, foregoing appears to be considered the view of plans Division.




</content>
</cab>
