<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/13/0 images: 326-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1946.The circulation of this paper has famn strictly limited.   It is issuedx^f^it^,.......for the persona! use of .....%3*n-?. :.y\iJyf.Vr?H^/^. .\\TOP SECRET. Copy. No,CP. (46) 393.22nd October, 1946.CABINET.LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1946-47 SESSION.Joint Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council and theLord Privy Seal.AT their meeting on the 15th July (CM. (46) 68th Conclusions) theCabinet approved the list of Bills annexed to CP. (46) 268 as a provisional programme for the guidance of Departments in the preparation of legislation,pending the formulation of a final Programme concurrently with the preparationof The King&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament. In doing so the cabinet recognised that there were in the provisional Programme more Bills than theGovernment were likely to find time for in the 1946-47 Session, and that theinclusion of a Bill in the provisional Programme could not guarantee it a placein the final Programme.2. Reports have since been obtained from Departments on the progress made with the preparation of the legislation included in the provisional Pro-gramme and the Programme has been reviewed both by the Legislation Committee(H.P.C. (46) 25th Meeting) in consultation with the Ministers responsible for the bills proposed for inclusion, and by the Future Legislation Committee, who have carefully considered the points raised at the meeting of the legislation committee. We now submit to the Cabinet for consideration concurrently withthe draft of The King&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament the programme set out in Groups I to V of the Annex to this memorandum.3. Our proposals involve drastic pruning of the provisional programme and the postponement to a later Session of a number of Bills which Ministers had hoped to introduce in 1946-47. We are convinced, however, that there are over-whelming reasons for lightening the Programme to the extent that we suggest,and it is obviously impossible to achieve this unless our colleagues are willingto accept the sacrifice of at least some of the legislative projects which they hadin mind for the 1946-47 Session.4. In drawing up the Programme we have had in mind that the 1946-47Session will necessarily be shorter than the current Session. In the first place,whereas last year the Debate on the Address was concluded in August and parliament was able to begin the ordinary business of the Session on the9th October, this year the Debate on the Address will not begin until the12th November. - Secondly, we believe that there would be very great advantages in reverting to the former practice of bringing the Session to an end before the summer Recess. Lastly, we feel that it would be wise to provide for some relaxation of the pressure on Government supporters, though, as indicated inparagraph 6 below, no very great relief will be possible if the Programme whichwe propose is to be carried out.5. It will be observed that we recommend the omission from the Programmeof all the Bills in Group VI of the Annex. These include certain importantmeasures such as the Criminal Justice Bill, the Agricultural Policy (Scotland)[32570] &apos;
Bill, the Rating and Valuation Bill and the Poor Law (National Assistance) Bill,which the Ministers concerned would naturally like to see included in next session&apos;s Programme. We propose these omissions regretfully and we suggestthat it should be understood that, in the absence of unforeseen developments, thefour Bills mentioned should have first priority in the 1947-48 Session, which, if our proposal for ending the 1946-47 Session in Axigust is accepted, will beginconsiderably earlier than the 1946-47 Session.6. We should warn the Cabinet that the Programme which we proposeallows very little time indeed for contingencies. If, therefore, after the Sessionhas begun, we find that we must embark on any major legislation not at presentforeseen, some of the Bills now included in the Programme will inevitably haveto be abandoned. We shall also have to restrict the Christmas Recess to four weeks, and probably to keep Parliament in session until the 8th August.Moreover, the Programme will allow very little relaxation of the heavy pressure which this Session&apos;s Programme of legislation has imposed on Ministers and government supporters in Parliament.7. The attempt to carry through a Programme such as we propose beforethe Summer Recess will fail if we do not time the introduction of Bills and arrange their distribution between the two Houses in such a way as to mitigateto the greatest possible extent the inevitable congestion of business in the Houseof Lords towards the end of the Session. Por this purpose it will be essentialto introduce as many Bills as possible in the House of Lords, to get before christmas the Second Readings of as many major Bills as possible and tointroduce any major Bills which cannot be read a second time before Christmassoon enough to enable their Second Readings to be taken by the beginning of* February at the very latest.8.   We invite the Cabinet: (1) to approve Groups I to V of the Annex to this memorandum as theLegislative Programme for the 1946-47 Session, and(2) to authorise the Legislation Committee to keep the Programme under constant review.H. M.A. G.22nd October, 1946.
ANNEX.LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME-1946-47 SESSION.I. Essential Bills.TreasuryDepartment.War Office and Air ministry ministry of Civil AviationTreasuryScottish&apos; Office-  Bill.Finance.Isle of Man Customs.Expiring Laws Continuance.Public Works Loans.Northern Ireland Reinsurance.Pensions (Increase).Ministry of Defence.Army and Air Force (Annual).Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention).II.-Major Bills.Ministry of Agriculture and fisheries and Scottish office ministry of Town and Country Plan-ning and Scottish office ministry of Transport ...Ministry of Agriculture and fisheries ministry of Fuel and Power  ...Board of Trade ...Exchange Control.National Health Service (Scotland).Local   Government   (Scotland)   Con-solidation;Agricultural Wages.Town and Country Planning (Develop-ment Rights).Town and Country Planning (Develop-ment Rights (Scotland).Inland Transport.Agricultural Policy.Electricity Nationalisation.Companies Acts Amendment.III. Medium-Sized Bills.Ministry of food board of Trade ..TreasuryHome office home Office and Scottish office home Office, Scottish Office, Ministryof Education and Ministry of health ministry of WorksTreasuryCivic Restaurants.Raw Cotton Buying Commission.Industrial Organisation.Employment Policy (Statistics).Redistribution.Fire Service.Superannuation.Public Offices (Site).Polish Forces.IV. Minor Bills.admirality ministry of Transport ...Treasury ...AdmiraltyHome Office       ....Ministry of Agriculture and fisheries and Scottish office colonial Office   ...Burma office scottish office ministry of WorksMinistry of Education ...Ministry of Health     .........Control OfficeGreenwich Hospital.Road Traffic (Driving Licences).Trafalgar Estates.Trustee Savings Banks.Royal Marines.Isle of Man Harbour.Superannuation of Probation Officers.Northern Ireland (Miscellaneous Pro-visions).Forestry.Malta (Financial Settlement).Government of Burma (MiscellaneousAmendments).Public Records (Scotland).Duke of Wellington^ Estate.Education Act (Amendment).County Councils Association.Detention   of   Persons   sentenced   inGermany.
V. Bills to be Introduced (if time permits).Department. Bill.Ministry of food ministry of transport ministry of labour ministry of health ministry of Agriculture and FisheriesLord ChancellorMilk (Heat Treatment).Motorways.Training and Employment.Radio-Active Substances.Sea Fish Industry.Crown Proceedings.VI. Bills to be Omitted fMinistry of Agriculture and FisheriesHome office ministry of Health, Scottish Office and ministry of National InsuranceMinistry of HealthScottish office treasury ...Home Office)m the 1946-47 Programme.River Boards.Criminal Justice.Poor Law (National Assistance).Rating and Valuation.Block Grant.Agricultural Policy (Scotland).Water Rating (Scotland).War Damage (Public Utility Under-takings).Acquisition of Land (Compensation).Nationality of Married Women.



</content>
</cab>
