<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/13/0 images: 338-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/ Y / ODOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).23.P.CU6) 596SECRET----- . COPY NO22nd October,  1946.cabinet british POOD SUPPLIESNECESSITY FOR NEW APPROACH TO UNITED STATES government memorandum by the Minister of food. The British food outlook for 1947 is gravelydisappointing.2. In spite of bumper harvests in North America it is likely that wheat shortages will be experienced in India,  the western zones of Germany and certain of our Colonial possessions.      and unless urgent representations are made to the United StatesGovernment the food situation of the United Kingdom may very well deteriorate instead of improving in the new year.      It maybe impossible to remove bread rationing ,during the whole of thiscrop year - and even then we may be faced with the necessity of failing to meet the needs of our colonies or of cutting our ownbread ration.3. Serious shortage of fats will be experienced and it maybe difficult for the United Kingdom to maintain its presentreduced fats and soap rations unless the United StatesGovernment revises its present policy,1;.. In spite of the recently concluded meat contract withthe Argentine we shall be unable to continue our existingcarcase meat ration.      It will be necessary further to supplement that ration with canned corned beef.PRESENT UNITED STATES POLICY5. A major contribution to this state of affairs is thepolicy of the United States Government.      Notwithstanding thefact that food consumption in the U.S.A.  is now 15% in excessof pre-war levels no attempt is being made to limit domestic consumption to help less fortunate countries.      Moreover thefood which is being exported from the U.S.A.  is being consigned to areas of special American interests or to markets which thatcountry is anxious to re-establish or develop.      Food exports from the U. S. ....   (in spite of the existence of the I.E.P.C.)  orenot being directed to the countries most in need of them.CEREALS6. I have submitted to the Cabinet a separate paper(CP, (46) 392)  on tho supplies of wheat to the Western Zones ofGermany,  during the fourth quarter of 1946.      In - allocating itsexports of cereals for this period the U.3.A.  is supplying425,000 tons to    the United States Zone and only 140,000 tons to the-British Zone which has substantially greaterrequirements.

7t During the same period the TJ. S.proposes to supply390,000 tons to oapan, 120,000 tons to Italy and only 59,000tons to India.8- For the United Kingdom itself only 16,000 tons of wheathove &quot;been allocated by the U.S.A.      I shall have to submit a third paper on the forward wheat and. flour position in the &apos;United Kingdom and the possibility of wi theirawin g, &quot;b r ea d rationing... at an early dote.      A decision on this depends upon the longerrather than the shorter term position.      But the^United Statesallocation to the United Kingdom for the fourth quarter of 1946is an indication of the attitude of that country to our needs.9* It is already clear that on the basis of our presentexpectations of wheat imports during the 1946-7 crop year i cannot, at present, recommend the withdrawal of bread rationing.I have appealed to Canada for an extra 40 million bushels(1,100,000 tons) of wheat over and above the 160 million bushels (4,286,000 tons)  provided in the contract.      I havealso asked the U.S.A.  to allocate from their own production26 million bushels (700,000 tons) of wheat to the United Kingdom.If I could obtain promises of these quantities - and ifArgentine supplies are not disappointing - I should be ableto end. bread rationing before Christmas.10. It will not be easy to obtain extra wheat from Canada,but I think that if the matter were pressed and an appeal madeto western farmers to place more of this year1s crop on themarket some additional supplies would be forthcoming.      So faras the United States Government is concerned there is little likelihood, of the much needed supplies being provided unless a personal appeal is made at a very high level.11. I am endeavouring-to purchase the maximum quantitiesof wheat in Argentina.      I am assuming that I shall obtain18,500,000 bushels (500,000 tons)  of wheat and 50,000 tonsof flour.      I have as yet no assurance that this quantityWill be obtained and I understand that the argentine isnegotiating separate agreements to supply other countries,notably Brazil,  on a substantial scale.      If,  however,  I amable to obtain the quantity mentioned from Argentina and also31 million bushels (836,000 tons) from the United States and canada combined. I could discontinue bread, rationing although I should have to    obtain some form of restriction on offtakeof flour.      I do not regard it as impossible to obtain an extra 31 million bushels from the United States and/orCanada during the current crop year.      If we do not obtainour expectations from Argentina our requirements from north america would be correspondingly increased.      It will,however, only be achieved by the most energetic representationof our needs at the highest quarters.

&quot;12* The difficulty of obtaining such extra quantities is emphasised by the first estimate I have received, from washington for the 1946/7 world balance sheet of cerealsfor human consumption..     This shows an estimated deficit of anything from 185 million to 2b0 million bushels(5 million to 7 million tons).      We shall,  therefore,have to put up a stern fight in all supplying countries to ensure that our own requirements are met.RICE13* The wheat and flour requirements of India andthe British Colonies in the Par East v/ould. be materially reduced if additional supplies of rice wereavailable.      It is estimated that 1,500,000 tons of riceare still available in Siarn.      During the past twelvemonths 345,000 tons hove been exported from that country.This is far short of the quantity which, might have beenobtained.     Progress in, procuring the maximum quantityhas been hampered by disagreement between the UnitedKingdom and United States Governments on the price to   bepaid for the rice and other matters of policy.      The U.S./&apos;:.wished to pay a price much in excess of the price we regarded as reasonable or in parity with the price we arepaying in Burma.      Sir Harold Sanderson, my Director office,  is at present on his way to Washington to endeavourto reach agreement on these matters with the UnitedStates Government.      I hope that this will result insubstantially increased supplies of rice being forthcoming from Siam,14* Nevertheless,   even if success attends these efforts, world, supplies of rice will still fall far-short of total needs.      In the years immediately preceding the outbreak of the war the average annual exports office from the three chief Asiatic exporting countries were as followsBurmaSiarnFrench Indo China3,000,000 tons1,300,000 tons1,300,000 tons5,600,000 tons

It will be a considerable time before production will be suffiently restored to enable exports on this scale to be resumed.      This means that the demand for other cereals (wheat,and (course) grains)  in Far Eastern countries will be abnormalfor some lime to come.      I see little chance of restoring riceto the diet of our own people in the near future.      The UnitedStates- on the other hand,  which is a large rice producer,   issuffering no shortage of this foodstuff.OILS AND FATS15* The oils and fats position has steadily deterioratedsince the end of  the war.      The quantities of lard which theUnited States are prepared to export have decreased;    the liberated Far Eastern territories,  with the exception of the philippines,  are at present claimant countries for fats ratherthan producers of it;    and many months were wasted this yearlargely as a result of United States procrastination in securingsupplies from the Argentine.      Indian export of groundnuts has ceased and is unlikely to be resumed.      Following the trypartite discussions referred to in paragraph 17 below, we reduced our stocks during 1945 by 307?000 tons&quot;as a result of abating ourclaims for imports during that year considerably below the quantities required to maintain our rate of consumption.      During1946, we did not receive the total quantities allocated to us bythe Combined Food Board with the result that imports continuedto fell short of our consumption requirements, even after theimposition of cuts and our stocks will,  therefore, have fallen by the end of this year by a further 120,000 tons.16* We cannot continue this procedure.      We are submitting to the I.E.F.C.  a request for an allocation for 1947 sufficientto cover our usings at the existing level of reduced consumption.It is far from certain that  the necessary quantity will be allocated to us.      Much depends on the attitude and requirementsof the U.S.A.17* We estimate that during 1946, U.S.A.  consumption offats was 99 per cent,  of their pre-war figure.      In the  same year,United Kingdom consumption was 77 per cent,  of pre-war.      Arecently published report by the United States Department ofAgriculture refers to substantially increased imports of oils and fats into the U.S.A.  in 1947 and smaller exports from thatcountry.      In spite of their large indigenous production,   theU.S.A; are demanding a substantial share of Argentine linseedoil together with their usual substantial share of the exportable surplus of Belgian Congo palm oil.      They have a strong claim tothe latter on the ground that it is indispensable to their steelindustry.      In 1946 U.S.A. usage of linseed oil was 109 per cent,of pre-war; . ours was under 69 per cent.      For 1947 they aredemanding 500,000 tons of Argentine linseed oil or half thetotal supply.      Such of&apos; the linseed oil as is supplied to theU.S.A. from the Argentine will be at the expense of the UnitedKingdom and other needy claimants.      If the U.S.A, would agreeto parity of consumption with ..the United Kingdom or least to live on its own production and not import any oils and fats,  itwould materially help us and also other countries.      Such aresult,  if achievable at all,  could only be obtained by anappeal at the highest level.

MEAT AND BACON18, Our recently concluded contract with. Argentina willprobably provide us with some 260,000 tons of carcase meat during1947.      In programming our requirements for that year, we hadbudgeted for 1-09,000 tons from the U.S.A.      This quantity,  inaddition to our home supplies and our imports from the rest ofSouth America, Canada,  the Southern Dominions, Denmark,  etc.   isnecessary if we are to maintain our 1/Ud.  ration throughoutthe year.19. Unless some new approach is made,  there is little likelihood of our obtaining  the 109,000 tons of meat from theU.S.A.      Indeed,  there is still outstanding to us the 26,000tons of meat included in the pipe line at the end of Lend-lease.And the Americans actually objected when we reminded them ofthis.      Recent control and price policy in the U.3.A. has impededthe flow of meat and any supplies obtainable in future in the open market will be at a very high price.    - It is unlikely thatwe shall be able to secure a satisfactory arrangement with theU.S,A.  regarding our meat supplies without a full review at ahigh level.20. As regards bacon,  although we  shall get a moderateincrease in shipments from Denmark next year,. Canadian shipmentsare tending to diminish and we shall need 49,000 tons from theUnited States to maintain the 3 oz.  ration.      This is more thandouble what we shall have received from that quarter this year,but without it there seems little prospect of avoiding areduction of the bacon ration to a level which will be lower than ever before.PREVIOUS REPRESENTATIONS TO UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT21, In the spring of 1945 the Cabinet sent Mr, Lytteltonand Colonel- Llewellin to Washington to engage in tripartite adiscussions with the United States and Canadian Governments onthe world food position in regard to foodstuffs in short supply -mainly meat,  sugar,  cereals and fats.      A series of agreementswas reached, which operated to the end of 1945*22. In 1946 Sir Ben Smith and later the Lord Presidentpaid visits to Washington to discuss the cereal position withthe United States and Canadian Governments.RECOMMENDATIONS23.    (a)    WheatMr. Clinton Anderson,  the United States Secretary for agriculture appealed to me personally not to introduce bread rationing in the United Kingdom.      He pointed to the prospectivebounteous harvests (and especially that of the U.S.A.  itself)as grounds for avoiding such a step.      Now is the time to ask forthe assistance his intervention implied.Our minimum requirements are that the United Statesmakes available to the United Kingdom at least 31 million bushels(836,000 tons) between now and the 30th September, 1947*      &apos;Thi aamount will be required in addition to all the supplies&apos; of wheatnow thought to be available for the United Kingdom from canada and the Argentine.      To safeguard ourselves against shortfallsfrom Canada or Argentina, we should endeavour to obtain a largerquantity from the U.S.A.  taking-has our target the 40,000,000

bushels (1,100s000 tons)  I asked Canada to provide.(b) Fats. &apos; Our appeal to the United States must be that they shall reduce their consumption to the same level as the UnitedKingdom.      If they are unwilling to accept this formula theyshould be pressed at least to  refrain from importing fats add to live upon their own indigenous production.(c) MeatWe should press the United States to make availableto us 109,000 tons of meat during 1947. This is necessary tomaintain our 1/4d. meat rallon.(d) BaconWe should press the United States to make availableto us 49,000 tons of bacon during 1947* This is necessary tomaintain our 3 oz. bacon ration.(e) RiceWe require U.S.A.   agreement on price and procurementpolicy in Siam if the maximum quantity of rice is to be obtainedfrom that country.24. I suggest that so soon as the Congressional elections in the U.S.A. are over a full tripartite review should takeplace in Washington with the U.S.A. and Canada of the worldposition of cereals  (including rice) fats and meat.Preparations for such a discussion should be put in hand forthwithboth here and in Washington and it would be desirable to consultour representatives in Washington as to the timing and characterof the talks.      They must not be unduly delayed,  as we must knowour position before the end of the year.      Unless some change inthe U.S.A.  attitude is secured,  I feel that our position in1947 will be even worse than it has been during the early partof 1946.J.S.Ministry of .b&apos;ood,  S.W. 1.,22nd October, 1946.

bushels (1,100,000 tons) I asked Canada to provide.(b) Fats&apos;Our appeal to the United States must be that they shall reduce their consumption to the same- level as the UnitedKingdom.      If /they are unwilling to accept this formula theyshould be pressed at least to refrain from importing fats andto live upon their own indigenous production.(c) MeatWe should press the United States to make availableto us 109,000 tons of meat during 1947. This is necessary tomaintain our 1/4d. meat ration.(d) BaconWe should press the United States to make availableto us 49,000 tons of bacon during 1947. This is necessary tomaintain our 3 oz.  bacon ration.(e)    RiceWe require U.S.A.  agreement on price and procurementpolicy in Slam if the maximum quantity of rice is to be obtainedfrom that country.24. I suggest that so soon as the Congressional elections in the U.S.A.  are over a full tripartite  review should takeplace in Washington with the U.S.A.  and Canada of  the worldposition of cereals (including rice) fats and meat.Preparations for such a discussion should be put in hand forthwithboth here and in Washington and it would be desirable to consultour representatives in Washington as to the timing and characterof the talks.      They must not be unduly delayed,  as we must knowour position before the end of the year.      Unless some change inthe U.S.A.  attitude is secured,  I feel that our position in1947 will be even worse than it has been during the early partof 1946.J.S.Ministry of Food, S.W. 1.,22nd October, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
