<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/13/0 images: 372-376</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT&apos; &apos;    181Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1946.SECRET.CP. (46) 400.29th October, 1946.CABINET.THE kings SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OF PARLIAMENT.Note by the Prime Minister.I circulate herewith, for the information of my colleagues, a revised draftof The King&apos;s Speech on the Prorogation of Parliament, which has been prepared in the light of the discussion at the meeting of the Cabinet on the 24th October(CM. (46) 90th Conclusions, Minute 2).C. R. A.10, Downing Street, S.W.1,29th October, 1946.Copy No.&apos;   2 9[32571a]

Draft of The King&apos;s Speech on the Prorogation of Parliament.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons :When I opened this Session, the first of a new Parliament, there was in all our hearts a deep thankfulness to Almighty God for our deliverance from thewar and an urgent desire to do everything in our power to repair the ravageswhich it had caused, both at home and abroad. A notable beginning has beenmade with this task.2. My Government have taken a leading part in formulating treaties ofpeace with Italy, Roumania, Bulgaria, Hungary and Finland. The conferenceof My Allies convened in Paris to consider the draft treaties and to submit recommendations on them to the Council of Foreign Ministers has concluded itslabours. I have welcomed the thorough discussion which has given an opportunityfor a full expression of views by My Dominion Governments and My many gallantAllies and has enabled the general belief to be expressed that the treaties^ shouldbe based not on vengeance but on justice. I hope that these peace treaties will soon be signed and will substantially contribute to the rehabilitation of adevastated continent.3. It gave Me great pleasure to welcome to this country the delegates to theinaugural session of the General Assembly of the United Nations. My Govern-ment have given every possible help and support to the United nations organisation, its Economic and Social Council and Security Council, and the many international bodies which are to be associated with it. Representatives ofthe United Kingdom have shared fully in the work of the International LabourOrganisation.4. My Government have accepted membership of the International monetary fund and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, and itit My hope that these institutions will help to bring greater security and a betterstandard of life to the peoples of the world. It is a source of gratification toMe that the Chancellor of the Exchequer has been selected as Chairman for thecoming year of the Board of Governors of the Fund and of the Bank.5. Financial agreements have been concluded with the Government of theUnited States and with My Government in Canada, under which substantialcredits have been extended to My Government to assist them in overcoming thedifficulties of transition from war and in moving towards a freer and more stablesystem of international trade. Important economic agreements have also beenmade with various countries.6. In defeated Germany and also in Austria My Forces of occupation and civil authorities, co-operating with those of My Allies, have continued tocarry out with great devotion and diligence the tasks of restoring orderedgovernment, repatriating displaced persons, preventing famine and disease, and finally eliminating Nazism. I welcome the progress which has been made towardsthe restoration of the freedom and independence of Austria and the close co-operation which is being established with My United States Allies as a step towards the treatment of Germany as an economic whole; and I trust that it maybe possible to lighten the heavy financial burden which the present state ofGermany imposes on the people of the United Kingdom.7. The trial of major German war criminals at Nuremberg has been carried through with dignity and impartiality, and in full accordance with the bestjudicial traditions. The proceedings were a signal example of inter-allied co-operation and the principles laid down by the Court, which represent animportant development in international law, will, I earnestly hope, prove a lastingdeterrent against aggression.8. One of the first concerns of My Government on the surrender of japan was the repatriation of all My subjects who had been held captive by theJapanese. We give thanks to Almighty God for their safe return after theirmany sufferings.9. In Japan British Commonwealth Forces are making their contribution towards the work which is being undertaken under the direction of the supreme commander of the Allied Powers for the restoration of a peaceful and productiveway of life in that country.
10. In other parts of the world My Forces are playing their part in helpinga return to. the conditions of peace; and many members of them have been engaged,both overseas and at home, on the difficult and dangerous task of mine clearance.11. It gave Me special pleasure to welcome the Prime Ministers and other ministers of the self-governing members of the British Commonwealth to thiscountry in April and May for discussion with My Ministers in the UnitedKingdom on many important matters. These discussions contributed greatly tothe elucidation of many problems and to a mutual understanding of the issues involved. Discussions have also taken place in London with representatives ofother parts of the Commonwealth on other matters of common concern, includingscientific collaboration and commercial policy.12. My Government have given their most earnest attention to the affairs of India, where changes of unparalleled importance are taking place. The visit of three of My Ministers to India earlier this year has resulted in the election of a Constituent Assembly to frame a constitution for India on the basis of thestatement made by My Government on the 16th May last. Provision has alsobeen made for associating the Indian States with this work.Pending the completion of the work of the Constituent Assembly, an interim government has been formed which is representative of all important elements in British India. I pray that India will prosper under their guidance and will achieve through the deliberations of the Constituent Assembly that freedomwhich it has long been the policv of My Ministers and Parliament to promote.13. In Burma the Governor has reconstituted his Executive Council on a broader basis and with a wider authority which will enable the principal political parties to make their contribution to the economic and political reconstruction of their country.14. In Newfoundland a National Convention has been elected to make recommendations with a view to a subsequent referendum as to the future formof the Government of the Island, and it is My earnest hope that they will be successful in achieving their object.15 I have made an Order in Council providing for a new constitution in ceylon under which responsibility for the internal affairs of the island will pass to a Parliament of Ceylon. I congratulate My people in Ceylon on thisachievement and extend to them My best wishes for the future.16. During the past Session the territories of North Borneo and Sarawakhave come under My sovereignty. I have been glad to extend a warm welcome to their inhabitants and to assure them that it will be the constant care of my government to promote their welfare.Members of the House of Commons :17. I thank you for the provision which you have made for expenditure on reconstruction and other public services.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons :18. Despite the heavy responsibilities of My Armed Forces, no fewer than four million men and women have been released from them since June, 1945.During the same period the transfer of two and a half million workers from war to peace-time production has been smoothly effected without giving rise toany large measure of unemployment in the country as a whole. Good progress has also been made with the rehabilitation of disabled persons and their resettle-ment in employment.19. Controls imposed during the war over labour, materials and other resources have been relaxed, wherever the removal of restrictions could be carriedout without damage to the national interest; and arrangements have been madefor regular consultation with a National Joint Advisory Council, representingorganisations of employers and workers.20. At home there has been an increasing flow of consumer goods and asubstantial advance has been made towards that great increase in exports whichis necessary to secure and pay for the imports of raw materials and other commodities which we need from abroad. The Exhibition of Industrial Designwhich I opened in September is an impressive sign of the achievements of ourmanufacturers and designers.
21. In the face of a continuing and most serious world shortage of food, my ministers have been concerned to maintain the essential supplies of My peoples and also, so far as lies in their power, to help in preventing the spread of famineoverseas. In accordance with the policy of ensuring that the necessaries of lifeare fairly distributed, My Government have been obliged to continue and even to extend the rationing of the main foodstuffs.22. Farmers and agricultural workers have made great efforts to maintain a high level of food production in the United Kingdom. They have had to contendwith exceptionally adverse weather conditions during the harvest months and my sympathy goes out to them in the difficulties which they have had to face.23. The repair of war damage to schools and colleges and the return of teachers from war service have helped towards the rebuilding of our educationalservice. Improved arrangements for granting assistance to students at universities-ties will make it easier for young men and women to continue their education.Milk has been made available free for all attending school; and facilities for children to have meals at school are still increasing rapidly. The provision of milk and vitamin supplements for mothers and young children has also been continued with good results.24. The financial credit of My Government has been fully maintained. Inthe course of the Session rates of interest for both short-term and long-termborrowing have been substantially reduced. This policy has lightened the burdenof the national debt and has assisted the finance of capital expenditure for reconstruction incurred by My Government and by local authorities.25. I have given My assent to a large number of important measures duringthe Session.26. A measure has been passed to nationalise the coal-mining industry.Thereby it has become possible to set in hand the re-organisation of this greatindustry which is one of the foundations of our country&apos;s strength and prosperity.27. I have also given My assent to legislation to nationalise the Bank ofEngland, to regulate the borrowing and the raising of money and the issue of securities, to enable guarantees to be given for loans for industrial reconstructionor development, and to substitute cupro-nickel for silver in the coinage.28. Provision has been made for a National Health Service in Englandand Wales; for the creation of a national scheme of insurance against industrial injuries in place of the present system of workmen&apos;s compensation, and for theexpansion and improvement of the existing schemes of social insurance. A systemof family allowances and the higher rates of old age pension under the newsocial insurance scheme have been brought into operation.29. I have given My assent to legislation to finance the production of houses by My Government and to subsidise house building by local authorities. I havealso assented to a measure to control the rents of furnished houses.30. Legislation has been passed to improve the procedure for the acquisitionof land for public purposes and to provide for the creation of new towns tohelp in securing a properly balanced distribution of the population.31. Acts have been passed to improve the efficiency of the police services,to increase the productive capacity of hill farming areas and to assist fishermenin obtaining boats and gear for the white fishing industry.32. I have assented to legislation to secure the development of air transport services under public control, to bring overseas telegraph and wireless services under public ownership, and to facilitate the provision of nationally ownedair ports.33. A measure has been passed to promote and control the developmentof atomic energy.34. My Government have welcomed the proposal of the Pilgrims Society to erect in the gardens of Grosvenor Square a memorial to that great and far-sightedstatesman, the late President Roosevelt, and by a measure to which I have givenMy assent they have undertaken the duty of maintaining the statue and thegardens.35. I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon us in thecompletion of the arduous tasks that lie ahead.

</content>
</cab>
