<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 30-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His-Britannic Majestys Government.]Printed for the. War Cabinet.   January 1018.SECRET.&apos; 13WAR CABINET, 314.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onFriday, January 4, l&apos;.)18, at 5 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl  Cukzon   ofKedlkston, KG., CCS I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Mtlner,G.C.B.. G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P.Lieutenant-General    the Right lion.J. C. Smuts. K.C.The following were also present : The Right Hon. Lord It. Cecil, K.C., \ The Right Hon. W. Long, XL P., SecretaryXI.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.Mr. Philip Kerr.of State for the colonies the Hon. Sir Edward Kemp, K.C.M.G.,Minister of the Overseas Military forces from Canada and the United Kingdom.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.War Aims.1. With reference to War Cabinet 313, Minute 1, the WarCabinet resumed their discussion on war aims. The PrimeMinister said that he had seen M. Albert Thomas that morning,and had shown him his rough draft of the statement he proposedto make on the morrow to the trade unionists. M. Thomas had said that this would suit France.The Prime Minister said that he had arranged to show thedraft, as approved by the War Cabinet, to Mr. Asquith and LordGrey on the morrow. If the War Cabinet agreed he proposed tostate in his speech that he had recently had the opportunity to consult the Leader of the Opposition and the Leaders of Labour,and that he had consulted such representatives of the Dominionsas were available, and that what he said might be taken as representing the views of the nation.This was agreed to.The Statement. 2. The Prime Minister then proceeded to read the statement which he proposed to make, which was based partly on lord robert CeciPs (G.T.-3181), and partly on General Smuts&apos; draft(G.T.-3180).Subject to certain amendments the new draft was approved,and is reproduced in the Appendix.
The Principle of 3. With reference to War Cabinet 313, Minute 3, it wasSelf-Determination, agreed that the passage dealing with the principle of self-deter-mination of races should be modified so as to apply, not to allraces indiscriminately, but merely to the settlement of the NewEurope.4. Some discussion took place as to a passage in which thePrime Minister proposed, as agreed by the War Cabinet (WarCabinet 312, Minute 8), to notify the Russian Bolsheviks that ifthey had not taken the responsibility of entering into negotiationswith the enemy by themselves, we should have stood by the Russiandemocracy, as we intended to stand by the French democracy.The Prime Minister gave as his reasons for including this state-ment that it was necessary to give warning to the Bolsheviks thatwe did not any longer consider ourselves bound to fight on in russian interests, so that there should be no misunderstandingon the subject in the future; also, that he wished to give a hintto the enemy in the same direction. Against this it was urgedthat the statement would be somewhat discouraging to our friends in Russia, who still wished to fight on in the interests of the Alliesas a whole.It was pointed out that the prevention of Courland and lithuania falling into the hands of the Germans was an import-ant Allied interest, since if this occurred the Baltic would become more than ever a German lake. For many years past one of thegreatest dangers to peace had been the desire of Russia to reachopen water. If the Baltic were entirely under German control,the Black Sea exits practically subject to Turkish control, andVladivostock very possibly in the hands of the Japanese, russia would have no outlet except in the Arctic Ocean. It wasimpossible to imagine that^ this vast amorphous nation, when itrecovered from its present prostration, would be content withthese conditions, and Russian lack of access to the ocean might prove a constant source of future wars. In fact, a settlement onthese lines was not consistent with a just and durable peace.The Prime Minister undertook to  find a form of words which would meet both points of view.Austria. 5. There was some  discussion as to the  manner in whichAustria should be alluded to in the statement. After referring to the legitimate claims of Italy, Serbia, and Roumania, thePrime Minister had proposed to insert a phrase indicating that,subject to the fulfilment of our war aims in regard to thesecountries, we considered the existence of a strong Austria to bedesirable. His, main object was to give a clear indication to austria that we did not wish to destroy her, and to make herpeople lukewarm in the war, thus deterring her from using herstrength actively against us. Against this it was urged that our allies on the borders of Austria-Hungary might be discouraged.It was decided To include some milder phrase than that used in the original draft in the sense that, subject to the fulfilment of the legitimate claims of our Allies, we felt that Austria-Hungary should be in a position to exercise a powerfulinfluence in South-East Europe.
Eoumania.6. With reference to War Cabinet 313, Minute 3. there was some further discussion as to the manner in which Roumaniashould be alluded to in the statement. Eventually, it was decidedthat A suitable reference should be made to the Balkans as awhole, indicating that the boundaries of all balkan states should be settled cn an ethnographical basis, and full reparation made to Serbia and Roumania for damage done in Serbian and Roumanian territory.The labour situation:12i per cent.Bonus Dilemma7. With reference to War Cabinet 310, Mr. Barnes statedthat the labour situation arising out of the 12i per cent, increase to certain time-workers was daily becoming more threatening.Telegrams from all cpaarters continued to pour in. This situation was proving one of the main obstacles to the success of thenegotiations of the Minister of National Service with the trade unionists. In the absence of some decision from the War cabinet as to a statement of Government policy on the subject, the WarCabinet Committee on Labour found itself unable to cope withthe situation. Eveiy day, however, the position was changing,and the composition of a suitable statement became more com-plicated.   He urged that the matter should not be postponed.The Prime Minister asked Mr. Barnes to formulate thepolicy he proposed with precision, and to bring it before the WarCabinet at an early date.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.January 4, 1918.
APPENDIX.WHEN the Government invite organised Labour in this country to assist themto maintain the might of their armies in the field, its representatives are entitledto ask that any misgivings and doubts which any of them may have about the pur-pose to which this precious strength is to be applied should be definitely cleared,and what is true of organised labour is equally true of all citizens in this country without regard to grade or avocation.When men by the million are being called upon to suffer and die and vastpopulations are being subjected to the sufferings and privations of war on a scaleunprecedented in the history of the world, they are entitled to know for what causeor causes they are making the sacrifice. It is only the clearest, greatest, and justestof causes that can justify the continuance even for one day of this unsjiieakableagony of the nations. And we ought to be able to state clearly and definitely notonly the principles for which we are fighting but also their definite and concreteapplication to the war map of the world.We have arrived at the most critical hour in this terrible conflict, and before any Government takes the fateful decision as to the conditions under which it oughteither to terminate or continue the struggle, it ought to be satisfied that theconscience of the nation is behind these conditions, for nothing else can sustain the effort which is necessary to achieve a righteous end to this war. I have thereforeduring the last few days taken special pains to ascertain the view and the attitudeof representative men of all sections of thought and opinion in the country. Lastweek I had the privilege not merely of perusing the declared war aims of the LabourParty, but also of discussing in detail with the Labour leaders the meaning and intention of that declaration. I have also had an opportunity of discussing thissame momentous question with Mr. Asquith and Viscount Gre3&quot;. Had it not beenthat the Nationalist leaders are in Ireland engaged in endeavouring to solve thetangled problem of Irish self-government, I should have been happy to exchangeviews with them, but Mr. Redmond, speaking on their behalf, has, with his usuallucidity and force, in many of his speeches, made clear what his ideas are as to theobject and purpose of the war. I have also had the opportunity of consulting cer-tain representatives of the Great Dominions Overseas.I am glad to be able to say as a result of all these discussions that althoughthe Government are alone responsible for the actual language I propose using, thereis national agreement as to the character and purpose of our waT aims and peace conditions, and in what I say to you to-day, and through you to the world, I canventure to claim that I am speaking not merely the mind of the Government but ofthe nation and of the Empire as a whole.We may begin by clearing away some misunderstandings and stating what weare not fighting for. We are not fighting a war of aggression against the Germanpeople. Their leaders have persuaded them that they are fighting a war of self-defence against a league of rival nations bent on the destruction of Germany. Thatis not so. &quot;The destruction or disruption of Germany or the German people has never been a war aim with us from the first day of this war to this day. Most reluctantlyand, indeed, quite unprepared for the dreadful ordeal we were forced to join in this war in self-defence, in defence of the violated public law of Europe, and in vindi-cation of the most solemn treaty obligations on which the public system of Europerested, and on which Germany had ruthlessly trampled in her invasion of Belgium.We had to join in the struggle or stand aside and see Europe go under and bruteforce triumph over public right and international justice. It was only the realisa-tion of that dreadful alternative that forced the British people into the war. Andfrom that original attitude they have never swerved. They have never aimed at the break up of the German peoples or the disintegration of their State or country.Germany has occupied - great position in the world. It is not our wish or inten-tion to question or destroy that position for the future, but rather to turn her asidefrom hopes and schemes of military domination and to see her devote all herstrength to the great beneficent ta,risks of the world. Nor are we fighting to destroyAustria-Hungary or to derive Turkey of its capital, or of the rich and renownedlands of Asia Minor and Thrace, which are predominantly Turkish in race.Nor did we enter this war merely to alter or destroy the Imperial constitutionof Germany, much as we consider that military autocratic constitution a dangerous
5WG 314anachronism in the twentieth century. Our point of view is that the adoption of a really democratic constitution by Germany would be the most convincing evidencethat in her the old spirit of military domination had indeed died in this war, andwould make it much easier for us to conclude a broad democratic peace with her.But, after all, that is a question for the German people to decide.It is now more than a year since the President of the United States, thenneutral, addressed to the belligerents a suggestion that each side should stateclearly the aims for which they were fighting. We and our Allies responded by the note of the 10th January, 1917.To the Presidents appeal the Central Empires made no reply, and in spite ofmany adjurations, both from their opponents and from neutrals, they have main-tained a complete silence as to the objects for which they ai&apos;e fighting. Even on socrucial a matter as their intention with regard to Belgium they have uniformlydeclined to give any trustworthy indication.On the 25th December last, however, Count Czernin, speaking on behalf ofAustria-Hungary and her Allies, did make a pronouncement of a kind. It is indeeddeplorably vague. We are told that &quot; it is not the intention &quot; of the Central Powers&quot; to appropriate forcibly &quot; and occupied territories or &quot; to rob of its independence &quot;any nation which has lost its &quot; political independence &quot; during the war. It is cbviousthat almost any scheme of conquest and annexation could be perpetrated withinthe literal interpretation of such a pledge.Does it mean that Belgium, Serbia, Montenegro, and Roumania will be as independent and as free to direct their own destinies as the Germans or any othernation? Or does it mean that all manner of interferences and restrictions, politicaland economic, incompatible with the status and dignity of a freed self-respectingpeople, are to be imposed? If this is the intention then there will be one kind of independence for a great nation and an inferior kind cf independence for a smallnation. We must know what is meant, for equality of right among nations, smallas well as great, is one of the fundamental issues this country and her Allies are fighting to establish in this war. Reparation for the wanton damage inflicted onBelgian towns and villages and their inhabitants is emphatically repudiated. Therest of the so-called &quot;offer &quot; of the Central Powers is almost entirely a refusal ofall concessions. All suggestions about the autonomy of subject nationalities areruled out of the peace terms altogether. The question whether any form of self-government is to be given to Arabs, Armenians, or Syrians is declared to be entirely,a matter for the Sublime Porte. A pious wish for the protection of minorities &quot; inso far as it is practically realisable &quot; is the nearest approach to liberty which theCentral statesmen venture to make.On one point only are they perfectly clear and definite. Under no circumstances will the &quot; German demand &quot; for the restoration of the&quot;whole of Germany&apos;s coloniesbe departed from. All principles of self-determination, or, as our earlier phrasegoes, government by consent of the governed, here vanish into thin air.It is impossible to believe that any edifice of permanent peace could be erectedon such a foundation as this. Mere lip service to the formula of no annexations andno indemnities or the right of self-determination is useless. Before any negotiationscan even, be begun, the Central Powers must realise the essential facts of thesituation.The days of the Treaty of Vienna are long past, W e can no longer submit thefuture of European civilisation to the arbitrary decisions of a few negotiatorsstriving to secure by chicanery or persuasion the interests of this or that dynasty ornation. The settlement of the new Europe must be based on such grounds of reasonand justice as will give some promise of stability. Therefore it is that we feel thatgovernment with the consent of the governed must be the basis of any territorialsettlement in this war. For that reason also, unless treaties be upheld, unless everynation is prepared at whatever sacrifice to honour the national signature, it isobvious that no Treaty of Peace can be worth the paper on which it is written.The first requirement, therefore, always put forward by the British Governmentand their Allies, has been the complete restoration, political, territorial, andeconomic, of the independence of Belgium and such reparation as can be made forthe devastation of its towns and provinces. This is no demand for war indemnity,such as that imoosed on France by Germany in 1871. It is not an attempt to shiftthe cost of warlike operations from one belligerent to another, which may or maynot be defensible. It is no more and no less than ?.n insistence that before therecan be any hope for a stable peace, this great breai h of the public law of Europe
must be repudiated, and, so far as possible, repaired. Reparation means recognition.Unless international right is recognised by insistence on payment for injury donein defiance of its canons it can never be a reality. Next comes the restoration ofSerbia, Montenegro, and the occupied parts of France, Italy, and Roumania. Thecomplete withdrawal of the alien armies and the reparation for injustice dene is a fundamental condition of permanent peace.We mean to stand by the French democracy to the death in the demand they make for a reconsideration of the great wrong- of 1871, when, without any regardto the wishes of the population, two French provinces were torn from the side ofFrance and incorporated in the German Empire. This sore has poisoned the peace of Europe for half a century, and until it is cured healthy conditions will nothave been restored. There can be no better illustration of the folly and wickednessof using a transient military success to violate national right.I will not attempt to deal with the question of the Russian territories now inGerman occupation. The Russian policy since the Revolution has passed sorapidly through so many phases that it is difficult to speak without some suspension of judgment as to what the situation will be when the iinal terms of European peacecome to be discussed. Russia accepted war with all its horrors because, true toher traditional guardianship of the weaker communities of her race, she stepped into protect Serbia from a plot against her independence. It is this honourablesacrifice which not merely brought Russia into the war, but France as well. France,true to the conditions of her treaty with Russia, stood by her Ally in a quarrel whichwas not her own. Her chivalrous respect for her treaty led to the wanton invasion of Belgium; and the treaty obligations of Great Britain to that little land broughtus into the war.The present rulers of Russia are now engaged, without any reference to thecountries whom Russia brought into the war, in separate negotiations with their common enemy. I am indulging in no reproaches; I am merely stating factswith a view to making it clear why Britain caunot be held accountable for decisions taken in her absence, and concerning which she has not been consulted or her aidinvoked. No one who knows Prussia and her designs upon Russia can for a momentdoubt her ultimate intention. Whatever phrases she may use to delude Russia., shedoes net mean to surrender oneof the fair provinces or cities of Russia now occupiedby her forces. Under one name or another and the name hardly matters theseRussian provinces will henceforth be in reality part of the dominions of Prussia.They will be ruled by the Prussian sworcl in the interests of Prussian autocracy,and the rest of the people of Russia will be partly enticed by specious phrases andpartly bullied by the threat of continued war against an impotent army into acondition of complete economic and ultimate political enslavement to Germany.We all deplore the prospect. The democracy of this country mean to stand to thelast by the democracies of France and Italy and all our other Allies. We shall beproud to fight to the end side by side by the new democracy of Russia, so willAmerica and so will France and Italy. But if the present rulers of Russia take action which is independent of their Allies we have, no means of intervening to arrest the catastrophe which is assuredly befalling their country. Russia can onlybe saved by her own people.We believe, however, that an independent Poland, comprising all thosegenuinely Polish elements who desire to form part of it, is an urgent necessity forthe stability of Western Europe.Similarly, though we agree with President Wilson that the break up ofAustria-Hungary is no part of our war aims, we feel that, unless genuine self-government on true democratic principles is granted to those Austro-Hungariannationalities who have long desired it, it is impossible to hope for the removal ofthose causes of unrest in that part of Europe which have so long threatened its general peace.     .On the same grounds we regard as vital the satisfaction of the legitimateclaims of the Italians for union with those of their own race and tongue. We alsomean to press that justice be done to men of Roumanian blood and speech in theirlegitimate aspirations. If these conditions are fulfilled Austria-Hungary wouldbecome a Power whose strength would conduce to the permanent peace and freedomof Europe, instead of being merely an instrument to the pernicious militaryautocracy of Prussia that uset the resources of its allies for the furtherance of itsown sinister purposes.Outside Europe we believe Vhat the same principles should be applied.   While
we do not challenge the maintenance of the Turkish Empire in the homelands ofthe Turkish race with its capital at Constantinople  the passage between theMediterranean and the Black Sea being internationalized and neutralized Arabia,Armenia, Mesopotamia, Syria, and Palestine are in our judgment entitled to a recognition of their separate national conditions.What the exact form of that recognition in each particular case should be neednot here be discussed, beyond stating that it would be impossible to restore to their former sovereignty the territories to which I have already referred.Much has been said about the arrangements we have entered into with our allies on this and on other subjects. I can only say that as new circumstances,like the Russian collapse and the separate Russian negotiations have changed theconditions under which those arrangements were made, we are, and always havebeen, perfectly ready to discuss them with our Allies.With regard to the German colonies, I have repeatedly declared that they are held at the disposal of a Conference whose decision must have primary regard tothe wishes and interests of the native inhabitants of such colonies. None of those territories are inhabited by Europeans. The governing consideration, therefore, inall these cases must be that the inhabitants should be placed under the control ofan administration acceptable to themselves, one of whose main purposes will be toprevent their exploitation for the benefit of European capitalists or Governments.The natives live in their various tribal organisations under chiefs and councils whoare competent to consult and speak for their tribes and members, and thus to repre-sent their wishes and interests in regard to their disposal.The general principle of national self-determination is therefore as applicablein their case as in those of occupied European territories. The German declaration,that the natives of the German colonies have, through their military fidelity in thewar, shown their attachment and resolve under all circumstances to remain withGermany, is applicable not to the German colonies generally, but only to one ofthem, and in that case (German East Africa) the German authorities secured theattachment, not of the native population as a whole, which is, and remains, pro-foundly anti-German, but only of a small warlike class from whom their Askaris, orsoldiers, were selected. These they attached to themselves by conferring on them a highly privileged position as against the bulk of the native population, which enabled these Askaris to assume a lordly and oppressive superiority over the rest ofthe natives. By this and other means they secured the attachment of a very smalland insignificant minority whose interests were directly opposed to those of the restof the population, and for whom they have no right to speak. The German treat-ment of their native populations in their colonies has been such as amply to justify their fear of submitting the future of those colonies to the wishes of the nativesthemselves.Finally, there must be reparation, for injuries done in violation of internationallaw. The Peace Conference must not forget our seamen and the services they have rendered to, and the outrages they have suffered for. the common cause of freedom.One omission we notice in the proposal of the Central Powers, which seems tous especially regrettable. It is desirable, and indeed essential, that the settlementafter this war shall be one which does not in itself bear the seed of future Avar. But-that is not enough. However wisely and well we may make territorial and other arrangements, there will still be many - subjects of international controversy.Some, indeed, are inevitable.The economic conditions at the end of the war will be in the highest degreedifficult. Owing to.the diversion of human effort to warlike pursuits, there mustfollow a world-shortage of raw materials, which will increase the longer the warlasts, and it is inevitable that those countries which have control of the raw materialswill desire to help themselves and their friends first.Apart from this, whatever settlement is made will be suitable only to thecircumstances under which it is made, and, as those circumstances change, changesin the settlement will be called for.So long as the possibility of dispute between nations continues, that is to sav,so long as men and women are dominated by passioned ambition and war is the only means of settling a dispute, all nations must live under the burden not only of having from time, to time to engage in it, but of being compelled to prepare for its possible outbreak. The crushing weight of modern armaments, the increasing evil,of compulsory military service, the vast waste of wealth and effort involved inwarlike preparation, these are blots on our civilisation of which every thinkingindividual must be ashamed.
Eor: these and other similar reasons, we are confident that a great attemptmust be made to establish by some international organisation an alternative to war as a,means of settling international disputes. After all, war is a relic of barbarism,and,&apos; just as law has succeeded violence as the means of settling disputes between individuals, so we believe that it is destined ultimately to take the place of war inthe settlement of controversies between nations.If, then, we are asked what we are fighting for, we reply, as we have oftenreplied We are fighting for a just and a lasting peace and we believe that beforepermanent peace can be hoped for three conditions must be fulfilled.First, the sanctity of treaties must be re-established; secondly, a territorialsettlement must be secured based on the right of self-determination or the consentof the governed; and, lastly, we must seek by the creation of some international organisation to limit the burden of armaments and diminish the probability of war.On these conditions the British Empire would welcome peace, to secure those conditions its peoples are prepared to make even greater sacrifices than those theyhave yet endured.January 4, 1918.o

</content>
</cab>
