<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 38-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1918.SECRET.&quot;    JLOWAR CABINET,  315.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on saturday, January 5, 1918, at 4 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount milner g.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonam Law, M.P.The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Lieutenant - General    the    Right    Hon.j. C. Smuts, K.C.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.R.The following we the Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions.Slit Stephenson Kent, K.C.B., Ministryof Munitions.Mr. U. Wolff, Ministry of Munitions.Mr. C. S. Hurst, Ministry of Munitions.Mr. G. Campkell, Ministry of Munitions.Mr. J. C. Spencer, Admiralty ShipyardLabour Department.Mr. G. M. Hodgson.i also present: The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour.Sir D. J. Shackleton, K.C.B., Secretary,Ministry of Labour.Sir G. R, Askwh, K.C., K.C.B., chief industrial Commissioner.The Right Hon. Sir A. H. Stanley, M.P.,President, Board of Trade.Mr. G. Calthrop, Coal Controller.The Right Hon. Sir Auckland Geddes,K.C.B., M.P., Minister of NationalService.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain C. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.[1365 315]B
The labour situation:12  per cent. BonusDilemma.,1/1. With reference to War Cabinet 314, Minute 7, Mr. Barnesstated that the Labour situation arising out of the grant of 12^-per cent, increase to certain time-workers was daily becoming moretroublesome. The latest menace was a threat by the electrical trades Union to call their men out that day unless they were granted an advance of 12^ per cent, on their time rates. A strike had been for the moment averted by Sir George Askwith under-taking to meet the men on Monday. About one-seventh of theelectricians were already covered by the recent increase. Theelectricians employed by the Ministry of Munitions, by publicutility companies, by the municipal corporations, and hospitalswere all making common cause. He (Mr. Barnes) had called the attention of the Chancellor of the Exchequer to the seriousness of the departure involved in the Government granting a subventionin aid of wages to private industries. He had also urged the WarCabinet (War Cabinet 310, Minute 1) to issue a proclamation inthe most public manner declaring that the Government would go&quot; so far and no further &quot; in their concessions. Every day&apos;s delaymeant heavier burdens on the Governments back. He was stillin favour of issuing a proclamation. It would be possible in the proclamation to indicate limits Within which the negotiations forthe extension of the 12^ per cent, should operate; trade eon-ferences&apos; could then be summoned, and the matter be dealt with indetail.Mr. Bonar Law said that the suggestion to subvent the wages of private industries directly was a most dangerous one, for once the workpeople got the notion that they were dealing with theTreasury and not with employers there would be no end to their demands, and future strikes would be against the Government.The urgent case of the electricians might be met by an undertaking -ing that, in cases where the power did not already exist, theGovernment would obtain authority from Parliament for the raising of prices to the consumers.Mr. Churchill urged the War Cabinet to consider theproblem before them as a whole. It had been proposedfortnight ago to extend the 12^shape of an advance of 7s. to workers in the munition trades,had proposed to pay 7s. over top rateserror, for although special treatment was required for some piece-workers, an indiscriminate bonus would be very unfortunate. Itwas necessary to speed up the application of the original decision tothe persons embraced by it, and to make agreements with as manytrades as possible. In that way a barrier could be erectedbetween specific trades and the industrial world generally and alandslide blocked. An overtop advance was not practicable; theright policy was to plough through the difficulties in detail day by day, and by trade agreements limit the range of application ofthe 12^- per cent, bonus. The Labour Co-Ordinating committee set up by the War Cabinet had no administrative machinery togive effect to its findings. Negotiations to be effective had to becarried out in the places and with the people affected. On Tues-day last the War Cabinet (No. 310) had restored his adminis-trative authority, and a conference had been held with the steel trade, in which some thirty strikes were threatening. In that trade, which was very well organised, there was the best chanceof a model agreement. They found the Union animated by good-will and definitely opposed to the wholesale extension to piece-workers of the bonus, and agreeable to the merging in the bonusof the advances already granted. An agreement had been con-cluded with the Steel Trade on the previous day, and the proposals had that day been put to a mass meeting of steel makers inSheffield the most disaffected centre and the men had been ordered to resume work on Monday. In the saime area the shop stewards had called a meeting in favour of a general strike; thataper  cent, bonuses  in  thethe &quot;whole  of   the piece-The   Sheffield employersHe considered that a great
meeting was proceeding at that moment, but such telephonicreports as had come to nand indicated that the men were well inhand. A trade agreement had thus been reached, and if we threwthe leaders over now we could not expect them to stand by theGovernment in future. He was certain that the only sound policy was to go on lighting inch by inch for trade agreements, and infact, they were not very far from the settlement of the mainmunition trades, given reasonable time. These were the tradeschiefly affected by the impending comb-out. With regard to theelectricians, Mr. Churchill&apos;s view was that the advance should beextended to those who had not already received it, and as to therailways, it might be possible for them to be handled by theRailway Executive without upsetting the miners.The Chancellor of the Exchequer referred to a suggestion made to the Prime Minister by a deputation of employers, thatthey would not mind the Government taking the whole of theirexcess profits if more satisfactory arrangements were made asto depreciation. The depreciation at present allowed for somekinds of machinery was, thev alleged, ridiculously inadeonate.The suggestion, Mr. Bonar Law stated, was most plausible onthe surface, but it was really very complicated, and it might involve the employers really paying 50 per cent, excess profitinstead of 100 per cent. What the employers really wanted wasa valuation of their stocks at pre-war -prices. Such a subterfugewould be unmasked in the House of Commons and could not easily be defended. It had to be remembered that the excess profits taxwas a tax on all businesses, whether their prosperity was speciallydue to the war or not, and in view of the present value of money,the 20 per cent, left hardly secured more than pre-war profits. Theemployers were endeavouring to influence the Minister of Recon-struction, and a. suggestion had been made that the 20 per cent,might be put into reserve fcr the development of businesses afterthe war.Sir Albert Stanley stated he found the employers more willingthan he had anticipated to make some sacrifice for the sake ofindustrial peace.Sir Auckland Geddes stated that he regarded the matterprimarily from the point of view of man-power. He did notthink there was anv hone of industrial peace until either the 12^per cent, bonus was withdrawn or extended over the whole field of men emnloved by or on behalf of the Government, The TradeUnion leadQrs knew that the demand fcr increases was largelyuniustifiable, but thev had no shadow of control over the rank and file, lie favoured the issue of a Proclamation by the Government,admitting that an error of iudgment had been made, that theincrease had been er^nt^d -in ord^r to remedv an admitted anomaly,that it had been ^&apos;tend0d hevond its legitimate sphere, that theGovernment w-^uld *Q iustice done, and would not allowprivileged positions to hQ sQt up in certain trades, and some machinery would hp provided for dealing, trade by trade, with thesituation which had arisen. The country was suffering from amultiplicity of Government Authorities issuing decisions, and theresult was a nerfect tant?lp of wages agreements and of protectionsfrom rpcrniting. In the Proclamation the Government ought toemphasise three points 1. War Aims,2. Profiteering,3. Food Prices,or rather two points, in view of the Prime Ministers speech that morning, viz. 1. Profiteering,2. Food Prices,
which, were contributing to the prevailing unsettlement.    TheMinistry of Munitions, though it covered a wide field, did not cover anything like the whole field; there were, e.g., the railwaysand coal mines. Other piece-workers were going back on to timerates and were doing less work per man than they were doing amonth ago. He was anxious to check the growing strength of the rank and file movement, and by means of a Proclamation make itclear that the extension of the 121 Per cent, to an industry was not due to the power of the local leaders.Mr. G. H. Roberts did not believe that a universal applicationof the 1.2J- per cent, could be resisted. It had become an obsessionamong the workers. The premium bonus men were not yet in, butsoon would be, and they would be followed by the piece-workers.The utmost that seemed possible was to confine the advance to121 per cent. The position of the Ministry of Munitions was acomparatively easy one, but their trades naturally affected allother trades throughout the country. The position could be settled by negotiating trade by trade, but probably they would be forcedto deal with the railways, and possibly with the agricultural labourers.Mr. Churchill stated that he agreed substantially with theline taken by Mr. Barnes. He did not want to extend an invita-tion to fresh trades to come forward. The agricultural labourerswere not coming forward. After all, there was a special case forthe munition workers who were about to be combed out; it was desirable to increase the attractive power of the munitions trades in view of the comb-out,The War Cabinet were generally agreed (a.) On the desirability of issuing a Proclamationsubstantially on the lines indicated by Mr. Barnes, andappointed the following Committee of Ministers, inconsultation with their advisers, to draft the Proclama-tion for consideration by the War Cabinet on Monday afternoon next: Mr. Barnes.Mr. Churchill.Sir Albert Stanley.Sir Auckland Geckles.    iMr. G. IT. Roberts.(&amp;.) Mr. Bonar Law undertook to circulate a Memorandumdealing with excess profits from the point of view of treasury and the Inland Revenue.(c.) Sir George Askwith was empowered to settle the difficulty with the electricians and their authorities, and, ifnecessary, to say that the Government would allow thecompanies and authorities concerned to raise their prices by Act of Parliament where required, and would assist with loans.Wai-Aims: 2. With reference to War Cabinet 314, Minute 1, the Prime,Prime Minister^ Minister informed the War Cabinet that he had shown the draft statement. statement of War Aims, as approved by the War Cabinet, to Mr.Asquith and Lord Grey that morning. It had been consideredline by line and certain alterations, chiefly verbal, and none of substance, had been made in the draft.The War Cabinet decided (a.) That the Prime Ministers statement should be tele-graphed verbatim to foreign countries, as well as tothe Dominions, as arranged by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.
5WG 315(6.) That a telegram should be sent by the Foreign Officeto the British Ambassador, Washington, directinghim to notify the United States Governmentfor the personal information of the President,that for the last week or two the PrimeMinister and the War Cabinet have been in negotia-tion with the trades in regard to the release ofthe Government from certain pledges made earlier inthe war, such release being indispensable to thedevelopment of our man-power for military purposes.The negotiations had reached a point at which successturned mainly on the immediate publication of astatement on War Aims by the Government. after consulting the leaders of the Opposition and the Labourleaders, the Prime Minister made an important national statement of War Aims to the TradesUnionist Conference that morning. The british ambassador should explain that there was nottime to consult our Allies in regard to the text of thestatement, which, however, they would find to be inaccordance with President Wilson&apos;s declarations.The Secretary was instructed to take the necessary action.Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,January 6, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
