<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 50-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Bifsotor of Military Operation^[This Document is the Property of Kis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Gobi net.   January I 018.SKCRET.WAR CABINET, 317.idtfthufcf 0/ a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Monday, January 7, 1918, at 3*30 p.m.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Sir Edward  Gaksou,K.C., M.P.The following were also present :-The Bight Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister oE Munitions.Sir Stephenson Kent, K.C.B., Ministryof Munitions.Mr. U. F. Wolff, Ministry of Munitions.Mr. C. S. Hurst, Ministry of Munitions.Mr. G. Calthrof, Coal Controller.Mr.   R.  H.   Fox,   Admiralty   ShipyardLabour Department.Mr. G. M. Hodgson.The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour.Sir D. j. Shackleton, K.C.B., Secretary,Ministry of Labour.The ilight Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President, Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes,K.C.B.&quot;, M.P., Minister of NationalService.Sir Alan Anderson&apos;, K B.E., Con-troller, Admiralty.Mr. j. C. Sfenoek, Admiralty ShipyardLabour Department.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, JLC.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain E. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.The Labour Sttua-tion :i 12  per cent, bonusdilemma.1. With reference to War Cabinet 315, Minute ij, the WarCabinet had before them a draft proclamation prepared by Mr.Barnes (G.T.-3241), and a General Formula for time-workers andfor piece-workers, which had been considered by the committee ofMinisters, but upon which it had not been possible to agree (G.T.-3241 A); and also the draft heads of a proclamation, to which theCommittee as a whole had agreed (G.T.- 3241 B).Mr. Barnes said that the Committee was divided on the ques-tion whether piece-workers should, otr should not, be included inthe General Formula.[1365 -337]
Mr. Churchill said lie could not agree to the whole of theGeneral Formula dealing with time-workers. A series of demands, backed by threats of strikes, were reaching the Depart-ments. Each Department was racing against the others in anattempt to reach a solution. It was impossible in such a situation to reach a settlement which would finally arrest the disturbancecaused by the 12^ per cent, bonus. The Government should declareits policy, and then entrust one Minister with full authority tocarry it out.Mr. Barnes urged that the important decision required fromthe Cabinet was whether premium bonus workers and piece-workers were to receive advances corresponding more or less to the advances granted to the time-workers. It was not so material which Department gave effect to the decision.Mr. Guy Calthrop and Sir David Shackleton said they were agreed as to the General Formula for time-workers.Sir A Ibert Stanley said the difficulty was that the GeneralFormula for time-workers did raise the question of how far the12-^ per cent, advance should go. The moment, for example, the advance was extended to any of the railway workers, it might be demanded by all, and although the Railway Executive might hope to confine the advance to men working on the construction orrepair of carriages, engines, or waggons, the view taken by Mr.J. H. Thomas was that it would be impossible so to confine it. Fie(Sir A. Stanley) thought that while each Department should negotiate in detail, no Department should grant advances withoutthe approval of some one co-ordinating authority. He was againstgranting the 12-\ per cent, to all time-workers, and against issuinga proclamation.Sir Auckland Geddes said he thought that the Committee setup by the Cabinet for the co-ordination of Labour Disputes shouldbe superseded by one authority like the Minister of Labour, who could be represented at negotiations.Sir Alan Anderson and Mr. Guy Calthvcyp concurred in thisview.Mr. Churchill said that he did not disagree with the proposedmachinery, but he was most strongly against the granting of all-round advances to piece-workers, which he believed the Ministerof Labour was ready to grant. To do so would be to squanderpublic treasure, and to bring the Government back to the originalposition where an attempt was made to redress the grievances ofthe skilled time-workers. The right policy, in his opinion, was to conclude special trade agreements, and to include therein certain limited classes of piece-workers.The attention of the War Cabinet was called to the hardshipon piece-workers who were unable to work full time for lack ofmaterial, as had been the case in Belfast shipyards, whose claims were now being considered by the Committee on Production.Sir Alan Anderson said that the grant of 12^ per cent, hadupset the class of workers which it was most desirable toencourage. Unless some encouragement were given to the piece-workers, it would be impossible to obtain an increased output. Itwas easy to over-rate the importance of the money-cost in com-parison with the goodwill and the productive energy of the men.The proposed 7s. was a compromise, and was really less thanthe full equivalent of the 12^ per cent. He thought a settlement could be made at that figure now (7s.), if it were made quickly.
WG 317Mr. G. II. Roberts was prepared to endorse the GeneralFormula as if the settlement were not made now, the Governmentwould be forced to concede the 12-Jf per cent, all round.A suggestion was made that agreement might be reached onthe following lines (a.) Each Department should negotiate and settle with itsown workmen.(&amp;.) buck settlement should be limited by the maximum rateslaid down in the General Formula (G.T.-3241 A).(c.) Such settlement should not be concluded without the assent of the Ministry of Labour.(d.) The Ministry of Labour should be represented at thenegotiations.(e.) The Co-ordinating Committee on Labour Disputeswould thus give place to the Ministry of Labour, and where Cabinet intervention was required. Mr. Barneswould act for the War Cabinet, and would only bringmatters before the War Cabinet at his discretion, andin cases of special urgency or difficulty.Mr. Churchill urged that if the principle of wholesale exten-sion of advances to piece-workers were conceded, it would beimpossible for his Department to carry on negotiations, and hewould prefer that the whole of the negotiations and theresponsibility for them should be transferred to the Ministry ofLabour. His statutory powers in this regard could be transferredby a short Bill.The opinion was expressed on the other hand, that there wasa provision in the Munitions of War Acts, by which the Ministerof Munitions could delegate powers.Sir David Shackieton said he advocated the restoration of theCommittee on Production to its original position as a Court ofAppeal. It had experience and knowledge, and its personnelcould be strengthened if required by a rush of work, in order to expedite its decisions. The essential condition for its success and rapid working was that its decisons should be loyally supported byall the Departments concerned, and that they should strenuouslyoppose all attempts to upset the determinations reached by theCommittee. The Ministry of Labour had never approved the granting of an advance, in cases of a strike, without first insisting on the men resuming&apos; work. If that condition were not fulfilled,the Government should be prepared to face a strike. With regardto the advance of 1.21 Per cent, the Committee on Production, inorder to be consistent with its previous decisions, could not refuseto grant it, to time-workers, and if a settlement could be concluded with the premium bonus men and the piece-workers, on the basis of  s.. it would be a gain of nearly 2s. %d. to the Government.The War Cabinet decided that (1.) All applications for an increase in war advances andwage disputes arising therefrom shall be referred for decision to the Ministry of Labour, who may referthem to the Committee on Production.The Ministry of Labour will have discretion toask the Department concerned to carry on any necessarynegotiations, but the final decision will in all cases rest with the Ministry of Labour.(2.) In deciding all claims for 12^ per cent, bonus or its equivalent the adjudicating authority shall work with-
in the limits and on the lines laid down by thefollowing formula: General Formula for Maximum Concession for theSettlement of the 12-i per cent. Question.(i.) To plain time-workers included in the concession (a.) To workers who have received not more than20.?. war advance- the equivalent of 12\ percent, on earnings.(?;.) To /workers who have received over 20s. waradvance sufficient to produce an equivalentto the 20.*. plus the 12^ per cent, on earnings;that is to say, that in the case of workers whohave received war advances in excess of 20s.such excess shall merge in the 12i per cent,on earnings.(c.) Workmen who have received the equivalent of20s. war advance plus 12-1 per cent, on earnings, or more, are not affected by this settlement,(ii.) To premium bonus workers included in the con-cession 7s. on existing war advances.(iii.) To piece-workers included in the concession 7s.on existing war advances, or its equivalent inpiece rates.(iv.) Any settlement under (ii) or (iii) shall be on the clear understanding that no one shall by thereceipt of this concession in addition to previouswar advances receive more than 12-J per cent, onhis present earnings, or 27s. as a total waradvance, whichever is the less.(v.) In all cases where war advances have been givenotherwise than by the Committee on production or similar award, application must be made through the usual channel and readjustment canbe made within the above limits.(3.) The co-ordinating Committee on Labour Disputes shouldbe replaced by the Ministry of Labour after dealingwith any outstanding business.(4.) Mr. Barnes should have Pull powers to decide on behalfof the War Cabinet in cases referred to him by theMinistry of Labour, bringing to the War Cabinet athis discretion only cases of extreme urgency ordifficulty.(5.) No proclamation should for the present be made, but when a suitable opportunity occurred the PrimeMinister might make a public statement on the generallabour policy of the Government.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 7, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
