<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 54-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet,   January 1918.28?.CKET.WAR CABINET, 318.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Tuesday, January 8, 1918, at Ll&apos;30 a.si.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right  Hon.  the Earl   Ourzon of   The Right Hon. G. N:. Barnes, M.P.Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E. ; Lieuteuant.Geaeral the Right Hon. J. C.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milnerj      Smuts, K.C.G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Box ah Haw. M.P.The Right  Hon. Sir Edward Carbon,K.c., M.P.The Right Hen. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for AIinut.es 5 to 13).The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby,KG., G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War (for Minutes -r) to 1.4).Major-General F. B. Maurice, K.C.M.G.,C.B.. Director of Military Operations for minutes 5 to 1 3).The Right Hon. W. S. churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions for Minutes 10and 13).Sir Arthur McDougalDuckham. K.G.B., ,Ministry of Munitions (for Minute 13).The Right Hon \V. Long, M.P., Secretary ,of State for the Colonies (for Minutes4 and 10)&apos;.The Right Hon. R. E. Prothero, M.V.O., jM.P., President, Board of Agricultureand Fisheries (for Minute 4).The Right Hon. Lord Rothermere,President, Air Board (for Minutes 1and 2).The Right Hon. Lord Rhondda, FoodController (for Minute 4\Mr. U. F. Wixtour, C.B., C.M.G., Secre-tary, Ministry of Food (for Minute 4).     &apos;rhe following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 5 to 13).Vice-Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, K.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff (for MinutesO  LU   LOf.Sin Leo G. Chiozza Money, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Shipping(for Minute 4).Commander the Hon. Sir Lionel Fletcher,R.N.R.,   Ministry   of   Shipping    (for minute 4).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, K.C., M.P..Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minutes 10 and 14).The Right Hon. Sir A. Mond, Bart.,M.P., First Commissioner of Works (for minute I).Sir Lionel Earle, K.C.B., C.M.G.,Secretary, R.M. Office of Works (for minute 1).Sir A. Durrant, M.V.O., H.M. Office ofWorks (for Minute 1).The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, LL.D.,M.P., President. Board of Education (forAlinute 1).Sir F. Kenyon, K.C.B. (for Minute 1).The Most Rev. His Grace the archbishop of Canterbury (iot Minute I).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistaiit Secretary.Captain C. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary,
The british museum :Acquisition for AirMinistry.1. With reference to War Cabinet 309, Minute 2, the WarCabinet, at the request of Lord Curzon, re-examined the decisionof the acquisition of the British Museum for occupation by theAir Ministry.The Secretarypointed out that the decision of the WarCabinet, after the last discussion on this subject, had leaked outimmediately after the meeting. Sir Alfred Mond had addressed aremonstrance to him on this occurrence.Sir Alfred Mond said that, on the day following the dis-cussion. hehad been besieged by newspaper reporters.The Archbishop of Canterbury said that the decision to use the British Museum as the offices of the Air Ministry appearedto have been reached on insufficient information, and on a mis-understanding of the facts. It had been erroneously supposedthat all the space required by the Air Ministry would be available:that the changes could be made without interfering with the library; and that the time occupied in removal would not belengthy. He protested that to treat the Museum in the wayproposed- namely, by removing its collections for the sake of accommodating a War Department in the vacated space wouldgive a most mischievous impression, and would be permanently&apos;discreditable to England. Many of the treasures were in any case to be placed in even greater security than the present basementaffords, but the proposal now made went very much further, andthis further proposal he characterised as an outrage against theculture of the country, unless there was no other buildingavailable.Sir Frederic Kenyon. the Director and Principal Librarian ofthe British Museum, said that he had been informed by the Officeof Works that it would take two months before the receptacles forthe collections would be ready for use: it would be three weeks before the packing-cases began to be received, and in the meantimeno progress could be made. It would be several months before thecollections could be packed and removed. The work would haveto be done by expert packers, for it would be impossible to put inanurgedordinary firm of furniture removers.   Sir Frederic Kenyonthe following points in regard to the unsuitability of thesmokingBritish Museum being used as a Public Department, &amp;c.never been allowed)f tlrooms: if partin the Museum; all the rooms were gang-e collections remained there, the Museumofficials must continue to have access to them. Upon being askedas to whether he could suggest any other building that could betaken over for the Offices of the Air&apos;Ministry, Sir Frederic Kenyonsaid a suggestion had been made that the Bethlehem Hospital,more commonly known as the Bedlam Lunatic Asylum, should beused; but the War Cabinet felt, that this would hardly be suitable accommodation.The First Commissioner of Works recapitulated the circum-stances in which be had given his original advice to take over theBritish Museum. The Air Ministry had asked for 190,000 square feet, and had said.that the large galleries of the British Museumwere exactly what they wanted. It was estimated that the british museum could be sufficiently cleared in from two to three months,without great disturbance. Since then a new and important factorhad arisen. The Air Ministry&apos;s demands for space had beenreduced from 190,000 square feet to 87,000 square feet. This newfigure was a much more manageable proposition, and he thoughtthat the matter should now be reconsidered.The Prime Minister stated that the War Cabinet concurred inthe view expressed by the Archbishop and Sir Frederic Kenyon,and had only reached their previous decision because they wereadvised that there was no other suitable accommodation available.The interests of the Air Ministry were absolutely vital to our national  safety, and time was of the essence of the problem.
Now, however,reduction of time reduction in the requirements of the air the First  Commissioner of Works shouldthe  question  of  taking over the british  . ne v. ar t aDine(a.) In view of ministry,reconsiderMuseum.(b.) In this reconsideration he should not be debarred fromutilising some of the accommodation of the british museum, preferably for the housing of a non-combatant Department, if by these means accommoda-lion would be rearranged.(c.) Lord Curzon should announce this decision in the Houseof Lords when the question was raised on the followingdav.Danger fromBombs.2. The Air Minister drew the attention of the War Cabinetto the danger from bombs which threatened tit present in theBritish Museum. Sir Sidney Coivin had advised the Trusteestwo years ago to remove the treasures.The War Cabinet decided, in view of the fact that the enemvwidently dropping bombs indiscriminately, that The Secretary should draw the attention of the Trustees of theBritish Museum to the great danger which was beingrun.I (issolufcion of AirOrganisationCommittee.3. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by general smuts (Paper G.T.-3197), in which he pointed out that the AirOrganisation Committee had been appointed by the Cabinet (WarCabinet 223, Minute 12) to undertake the preliminary work of theestablishment of the Air Ministry. As most of the  subjects withwhich the Committee had dealt had been settled in agreement withthe Departments concerned, and as the consideration of theremaining questions might now be left to the Air Council.General Smuts recommended that the Air Organisation Com-mittee might now be dissolved.hear   Cabinet, approvednedissolution of  the AirOrganisation Commit! ee.Transatlantic Fish 4. With reference to War Cabinet 217, Minute lij, the war supplies. Cabinet had before them a Report of the Committee on Trans-Atlantic Fish Supplies (Paper G.T.-3177), which Committee hadbeen appointed to examine and report upon Memorandum by Mr.Prothero on the desirability of the British Government securingsupplies of frozen fish from Newfoundland and Canadian com-panies, at an agreed price and subject to inspection, for the periodof the war, and for a year or eighteen months afterwards.Mr. Prothero said that the Committee reported in favour ofthe scheme. There appeared, however, to be some difficulty in thematter of finance. A suggestion had been made that payment insix months might be arranged, but the Treasury had taken theview that this arrangement -would not be satisfactory to them.Mr. Wintour said that he had just seen Sir Edward Morris,who thought that the difficulty could be overcome by the newfoundland Government themselves providing the necessaryfinance in the shape of a permanent loan. A draft telegram tothe Newfoundland Government had been prepared, in conjunctionwith Sir Edward Morris, in the following sense &quot; For some considerable time negotiations have been inprogress between the British Government and EasternCanada and Newfoundland for fresh fish frozen to be sent towas clear that a new factor had arisen in the1.1 r Ministry&apos;s requirements,lecided that 
5. Questioned as to the report of an intended German landing in England, and the concentration of troops for that purpose inHolstein. the Director of Military Operations expressed theopinion that the troops in Holstein were there in depots for ordinary training and not for the purpose suggested. Thesedepots, moreover, had been drawn on to reinforce the western front.6. In reply to a question as to the number of aeroplanes at general Allenby&apos;s disposal, the Director of Military Operationsstated that Genera.! Allenby had four squadrons and unquestionable-able superiority in the air over the Turks. Bombing raids ontheir communications were of frequent &quot;occurrence.The Secretary of State for War stated that a, fifth squadronfor Egypt was in preparation, and old maehines had been replaced by new ones.7. It was suggested that the Admiralty might co-operate use-fully in this activity by the employment of seaplanes, with a base in Cyprus. There was great advantage in harrying the Turks,and, if possible, in damaging their scanty and irreplaceablerolling-stock.General Smuts pointed out that Mudros, which was a more suitable seaplane base than Cyprus, had been selected as a base for operations of this kind, though with a different objective.He added that, in view of the policy of bombing on the WesternBritain. The British Government would be very glad toobtain additional supplies of frozen fish from Newfoundland,and would be prepared to enter into a contract for as muchfish as Newfoundland can supply, and as they can provideshipping for. The only difficulty up to the present has been one of exchange, but it is suggested that this difficulty mightbe overcome if the Newfoundland Government were willing to finance the operations for the period of the war and for areasonable time afterwards, to be agreed upon by mutual con-sent. Et would be necessary to this purpose that the New-foundland Government should furnish credits from whichpayment may be made in Newfoundland for all fish deliveredunder the contract; the British Government in their turnguaranteeing repayment after the war to the new found land government,&quot;If the above cable were approved by the War Cabinet, he,Sir Edward Morris, would himself cable to the new found land government urging them to accept the solution proposed, on theunderstanding that the British Government in their turn would,within the ecuivalent amount, provide sterling for Newfoundland&apos;s sterling debt obligations in London.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would have noobjection to this arrangement being carried out. As regardsCanada, it was hoped that Lord Reading, on his forthcomingMission to the United States, would be able to facilitate matters.The War Cabinet decided that- A telegram in the above sense should be sent by the ColonialOffice to the Newfoundland Government.In this connection the Prime Minister pointed out that, if theenemy refused to treat our statement of War Aims as a, basis for negotiation, the war might be a very long one. In these circum-stances food would become an important factor in the situation,and all questions of this kind ought to be examined with thegreatest care, with a view to doing all that could be done to supply the people with essential foods.
front, the suggestion must be governed by the number of Handley-Page machines that could be spared from that area.The War Cabinet decided that The Air Policy Committee should re-examine the possibilityof utilising the seaplanes from Cyprus or elsewhere for operations against the Turkish communications in Syriaand Palestine.8. With regard to the question as to the replacement of oldby new aeroplanes in Mesopotamia, the Director of MilitaryOperations stated that the particular type of machine asked forby General Marshall was not available, but that modern machines were being sent out, and that the Air Force in that area was being raised to three squadrons.Submarines. 9. The First Sea Lord stated that the British S.S. &quot;Braeneil&quot;reported having, on the 7th instant, rammed an enemy submarine.y which could be regarded as sunk.Dardanelles 10. With reference to War Cabinet 293, Minute 14, the WarCommission: Cabinet had before them the following documents: stion of Publi- (a.) The Second Report of the Dardanelles Commission,cation of Second (&amp;.) A Memorandum by Mr. Churchill (Paper G.T.-2433-Report. Reference War Cabinet 2s2. Minute 3).:q y (c.) Observations bv the Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Paper G.T.&apos;-3078).(d.) Observations by the Foreign Office (Paper G.T.-3079).((?.) A Memorandum by the Naval Staff (Paper G.T.-3170).The Secretary of State for War, speaking after discussionwith the Chief of the imperial General Staff, strongly urged thattlie Report should not be published, as it would give most valuableinformation to the enemy.This view coincided with that of the Admiralty,the Secretary of State for the Colonies stated that feeling in the self-governing Dominions was altogether against the publi-cation of these Reports, as had been shown in the case of thepublication of the First Report and of the Report of the Mesopo-tamia Commission.The Minister of Munitions stated that if, for public reasons,it was inadvisable to publish the Report, he would raise no oppo-sition on personal grounds. But he made a strong appeal for the rehabilitation of Sir Ian Hamilton, in particular with referenceto charges which the Report clearly showed to be unfounded. Hehad been unemployed for two years, with a stigma on him. some action should be taken, either by the publication of the truth or bysome recognition, to vindicate him.It was asked if Sir Ian Hamilton could not be employed inthe Home Forces.The Secretary of State for War stated that, at the moment,in view of his rank and seniority in the Service, this appeared tobe difficult.The suggestion was then made that he might be employed ona Mission.The War Cabinet decided that-(a.) It was not in the public interest to publish the Reportfor the present,(b.) The Secretary of  State for  War should consider the^ possibility of employing General Sir Ian Hamilton.German overtures 11. Sir Edward Carson brought to the notice of the war to Spain: Cabinet a Paper (G.T.-3171) which he had written in connectionPropaganda. with  German   overtures  to  Spain,  and  mentioned  that  theaccompanying document  had recently&quot;   been   handed   by   M.11365-3181 C
CTemenceau to Lord Milner. It appeared, as regards propaganda in Spain, that M. Clemenceau had mentioned the possibility ofthe French and English combining, or at any rate working more closely together in this matter.The War Cabinet took note of the statement as regards theGerman overtures, and, as far as propaganda was concerned,requested Sir Edward Carson to consider the matter and to deal with itas he thought fit.Tim Position of 12. The War Cabinet had,under consideration the ReportHolland. of the Northern Neutral Committee (Paper G.-186) in relationto Holland.The Naval and Military Representatives that were present at the meeting explained that, under the existing arrangements,a certain number of officers and men of both Services were lockedO^f&apos; / - Up jn England although their services were urgently required fory       other purposes.v^S^&apos;- The War   Cabinet  accepted   the  recommendations of theCommittee, and, as regards the embargo placed on officers and menof the Navy and Army, requested The First Lord and the Secretary of State for War tofurnish a Joint Report on the subject, setting out any proposals which they may have to offer as to the retentionin future of only a. nucleus force in the United kingdom for the service under consideration.Tants for American 13. The War Cabinet had under consideration an AgreementGovernment, &amp;c.      (Appendix) between the British Government and the American/ ,   Government concerning the joint production of 1,500 or more&apos;r    tanks, under which Great Britain had to provide plates, track-,3     ^ -  shoes and - rollers, guns, machine-guns, and ammunition, and in,/ &apos;     &apos;       return the American Government guaranteed to replace the steel^ provided by the British Government for armour-plate in theform of ship-plates on or about the date of delivery of armour-plate to the factory, on the basis of ton per ton.Sir Eric Geddes was informed  that the  execution of theAgreement entirely depended on the Americans supplying at theproper dates an equivalent amount of ship-plates, so that thereshould be no interference with the shipbuilding programme.The War Cabinet endorsed the Agreement.Defence of the 14. With reference to War Cabinet 253, Minute 5, the WarRealm (Acquisition Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Secretary ofof Laud) Bill. State for War (Paper G.T.-3207) dealing with the large increasein the value of land in the immediate neighbourhood of land aquired by the Government for the erection of works for war purposes.The Secretary of State for War explained the desirabilityof securing this increased value, for the State, and submitted thedraft of a Clause to give the necessary powers, which might beinserted in the Bill to amend the Defence of the Realm (Acqui-sition of Land) Act.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) The proposed additional Clause should be provisionallyapproved.(b.) The Secretary should circulate to the War Cabinet acopy of the Bill as thus amended.2. Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 8, 1918.
WC 318      ^APPENDIX.He/ids of an Agreement between the British Government and theAmerican Government concerning the Joint Productionof 1,500, or more, Tanks.WHEREAS it is considered desirable by the American andBritish Governments to co-operate in the use of their respectiveresources for the production of the war machines known as the tanks:And whereas the British Minister of Munitions (on behalf ofthe British Government) has appointed Lieutenant Colonel A. G.Stern, CM. G., and the Comma nder-in-( fief. American ExpeditionaryForce ion behalf of the American Government), lias appointedMajor .1. A. Drain, US R., as Commissioners, to investigate thepossibilities of such joint production, and these Commissioners havemade a joint recommendation to their respective Governments;It is hereby agreed as follows :--The above-mentioned Commissioners are authorised bv theirrespective Governments Factory. L To build a factory in France, the cost of which is to be defrayed in equal parts by the British and American Governments.The factory to be of sufficient capacity to produce 300 completedTanks per month and capable of extension to at least 1,200 amonth.The construction materials for the factory to be obtained inFrance and in England.The unskilled labour for the erection of tiie factory to besupplied by the British Government, and to be Irish, Chinese, orPortuguese, or such other as may from time to time be available.Skilled labour to be supplied by the American or British Govern-menls, as the Commissioners may elect.Production. -. To arrange for the production of, and to produce. 1.500 Tanksduring the year 1918, or as many more as may be required and authorised by the respective Governments, and to arrange for theprovision of the components for these Tanks in the United Statesand Great Britain substantially as follows : In the United States : Engines complete, with starter andclutch, radiator, fan and piping, silencer, electric lighting, dynamoand battery, propeller shaft, complete transmission, including maingear box, brakes, roller sprockets, gear shifting and brake control,track links and pins, rear track sprockets, bub and shafts, front idlerhub and shafts, track roller, track spindles and bushings.In Great Britain : Bullet and bomb-proof plates, structuralmembers, track shoes and rollers, guns, machine guns and mountings,ammunition racks and ammunition.Priority. o. The respective Governments undertake to give the necessarypriority in respect of material, labour, shipping, and other require-ments to enable the programme to be carried out in the mcstexpeditious manner.Allocation uf 4. It is understood that the Tanks produced by the factory areTanks. to be allocated between the United States,   France, and   GreatBritain according to a determination to be reached later between these three Governments, provided that the first 600 Tanks producedshall be allocated to the United States, and provided further thatthe United States and Great Britain shall each take one-half of the tanks not taken by France, unless unequal allocation between themshall be subsequently agreed upon.
Prica of Tanks.Finance.Replacement ofSteel.5. The price which shall be charged to France, the UnitedStates, and Great Britain, should there be an unequal allocationbetween the United States and Great Britain, shall be 5,0007,. perTank, which price shall be subject to adjustment at the close of theoperations occurring under this Agreement and the liquidation of allassets upon a basis of actual cost, such actual cost to include nocharge for overhead by either Government.G. The capital necessary to cany on this programme is to besupplied in equal jwrts by the American and British Governments.Expenditure in France will,British Government.Materials purchasedBritish government\ment.Materials purchased in the Unitedpaid for by the American Government.An adjustment of the accounts will be made every six months.7. It is further agreed that the American Government will replace the steel provided by the British Government for armour-plate. The replacement to be made in the form of ship-plates on or about the date of delivery of armour-plate to the factory and to beon the basis of ton per ton, the necessary allowance for difference in value to be made in the adjustment of the accounts..   December 20, 1917.in the first instance, be paid by theGreat Britain will be paid for by theStates of America will beyy)9

</content>
</cab>
