<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 66-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
D.M.O.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Vrintcd for the War Cabinet.   January 19J 8.sfcret;WAR CABINET, 320.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Friday, January 11, 1918, at 11 &quot;30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right lion,  the Earl  Cuezon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the \7iscount Milister,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bon a p. Law, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The Right Hon. Sir Edward Carsox,K.C, M.P.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minute 1).The Right. Hon. the Earl of Derby,K.G., G.O.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War (for Minutes 1 to 10).The Right Hon. H. W. Forster, M.P.,Financial Secretary, War Office (for minute 8).Major-General Sir R. D. Which am,K.C.B., D.S.O., Deputy Chief of theImperial General Staff (for Minutes 2to 5).Major-General Sir F. B. Maurice,K.C.M.G., C.B., Director of MilitaryOperations (for Minutes I to 9).Major-General R. Hutchison, D.S.O.,Director of Organisation, War Office(for Minute 11).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minutes 9 to 1.1).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade (for minutes 11, 13, and 14).The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 6 to 10).The Right Hon. T. j. Macnamara, LL. D.,M.P., Financial Secretary, Admiralty(for Minute s).Vice-Admiral Sir H. F. Oliver, KGB.,K.C.M.G., M.V.O., Deputy Chief of theNaval Stall (for Minutes 1 to 9).The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., Minister of National Service (for minute 11).jor P. Lloyd Greame, Secretary,Ministry of National Service (for minute 11).Mr. E. F.  Wise, Ministry of Food (for minute 14).Mr. A. Mansfield, C.B.E., Ministry ofFood (for Minute 14).Sir D. J. Shaoeleton, K.C.B., Secretary,Ministry of Labour (for Minute 11).Colonel    F.   J.Minute 14).Byrne,   C.M.G.   (forLieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.365-820]B
Newspaper I. THE attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to the head-Indiscretions, lines in the &quot; Evening News &quot; of the previous day, &quot; U-Boats -Serious Situation,&quot; &quot;More Food Cargoes Lost,&quot; and similar headlinesto articles in this and other recent editions of newspapers in thisvein.It was pointed out that these headlines and articles would formthe finest possible propaganda for the enemy. At the present time,when the war had become a struggle between nations, the saidarticles were highly detrimental.The Prime Minister stated that he had already spoken to the editor of the &quot;Times,&quot; and bad asked him to make representations to Lord Northcliffe on the subject.The Secretary of State for War stated that he had been in communication with the Hulton group of newspapers.It was suggested that a special report might be drawn up, for communication to the press, giving typical extracts from the british press as reproduced in Germany. Against this it was pointed outthat the result would show that all the British newspapers were equally quoted in the German press.It was stated that speeches and questions, especially supple-mentary questions, in Parliament were often the best propaganda,for enemy purposes.In this connection attention was drawn to the proclamation,published in the &quot;Herald&quot; of 12th January, by M. Litvinoff, the 0representative in this country of the Russian Bolsheviks Commissaryfor Foreign Affairs. It was pointed out that if this proclamation hadbeen published in the form of a leaflet it would have been stopped,and it was inconsistent to allow propaganda by newspaper andto prohibit it by pamphlet. On the other hand, the suggestion wasmade that the old policy of not attempting to suppress articles of thiskind was the better one, since suppression merely served to drive the trouble underground and rendered it in reality more formidable. Itwas also suggested that if the &quot; Herald &quot; was to be prosecuted the&quot; Evening News &quot; and &quot; Evening Standard,&quot; wdiose headlines were much more harmful to the mor,:I of the nation, ought to be treated in a like manner.The &quot;War Cabinet felt that the issue of a circular on the subject would not be of much use, as the newspapers had received so manycirculars that they did not always pay attention to them.The War Cabinet agreed that -(a.) The best plan would be for the Prime Minister to see the proprietors or editors of the offending newspapers andappeal to them to adopt an attitude more consistent withthe public interest.(&amp;.) As regards any action to be taken against the &quot; Herald,&quot;the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should- see Mr. Barnes and the Home Secretary.Transfer of EnemyDivisions.2. The Director of Military Operations stated that two more german divisions had been brought over from the Russian front, andthat two divisions, previously thought to be on the Western front,had now been identified there. It was also thought that two divisions from the Italian front were now on the Western front, thusmaking a total of 161 certain, and 163 possible, German divisionsopposing the Franco-British forces in France. The total number of enemy divisions moved from Russia to the Western front since october 1917 was 27, but this number did not include the divisionsy   brought over to Italy.EnemyConcentration.3. The Director of Military Operations drew attention to thefact that there was an enemy concentration on the Cambrai-Rheims
front, 18 divisions being held in reserve on this sector. general maurice stated that there was no evidence of an enemy attack beingimminent, and his personal opinion was that the Germans would notbe ready before February. This view was borne out by the factthat the 1.8 German divisions were distributed over a considerablearea belaud the line.German 4. General Maurice stated that up to the present the GermansCommander-in- had not bad a supreme Commander-in-Chief on the Western front,Chief on the . but the recent rumours of the appointment of such an officer (Field-Western Front. y   Marshal von Woyrsch) were not improbable.Palestine and 5. The Director of Military Operations reported that the ArabsArabia. had made further attacks on the Hejaz  Railway with good results.He also informed the War Cabinet that aeroplanes from GeneralS  Allenby&apos;s force had bombed the railway east of Jericho.The Black Sea The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff stated that, accordingFleet. to   the   report of a Russian officer  who  had just  returned   fromSevastopol, 52 officers, including Admiral Xovitski, were murderedy   in the recent disturbances in the Black Sea fleet.Loss of H.M.S. The  Deputy  Chief of the Naval  Staff stated   that   the destroyer destroyer &quot; Racoon &quot; ran aground on the 9th instant on Lough Point&quot;Racoon.&quot; Islands, and a Liter report stated that she had evidently foundered.Soldiers&apos; and g. The War Cabinet had before them the Third Report of theSailors1 Pay- Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Pay Committee (Paper G.-138).The  War  Cabinet, after some discussion and explanation of points of detail by Sir Edward Carson, accepted the recommendations contained in the Report, and instructed Dr. Macnamara and Mr. H. W. Forster to prepare a statement,based on the Report, for publication in the press on they following morning.Air Raids.Provision of CoversGeneral Defensiveand OffensivePolicy.f6^9. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for War, covering a Resolution from theinhabitants of Sbeerness asking for the provision of cover andindemnity from Air Raids (Paper G.T.-3263).In this connection the War Cabinet discussed the possibility ofan enemy attack on London on a grand scale, not merely by a forceof 20 or 30 machines, but by, say, 500 machines, which might result in a conflagration with which the Fire Brigade might be unableto cope. They also discussed the possibility of a direct attackon the Admiralty or other Government buildings in the sameneighbourhood.General Smuts said that these questions had been considered byhis Committee. The prevailing opinion, however, was that, thoughattacks must be expected, nevertheless, taking all the evidence available into account, it did not seem likely that an attack on a really big scale, such as that suggested, would be made.Lord Derby said that General Trenchard had expressed similarviews.Oii the other hand, it was stated that Admiral Mark Kerr held that a big attack was probable.320] B 2
As regards bomb-proof shelters, the attention of the WarCabinet was drawn to a previous discussion on the subject (WarCabinet 2S8, Minute 18) on 3uth November, when it had beendecided not to proceed further with bomb-proof shelters, but toauthorise the local authorities to provide splinter-proof shelters.The War Cabinet further discussed the possibility of increasing our air offensive against Germany. It appeared that our raids intothe enemy&apos;s country had had a very useful effect, both there and here, and the opinion was expressed that these raids should, ifpossible, be continued and increased.Attention was also called to the slow rate at which the Americans&apos;h were rendering assistance in the supply of aeroplanes.    Until july 1) y 4 - it  would be  necessary for % us   to   provide  the Americans with, &apos; / machines.The War Cabinet were of opinion that the question raised inthe memorandum by the Secretary of State for War could not be^        disposed of without fuller information on these wider aspects of the^ &apos;   .       question.   They therefore decided -(a.) To request the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief, Homeft- ) S- Defences, to furnish a report on the defences of London/ fo- against an enemy air raid on a big scale ;y^^. (b.) To request the Air Minister to furnish a report on the out-(Jr^y^ put of machines, with a view to increased offensive against German towns ; f )(c.) To consider Lord Derby&apos;s memorandum (Paper G.T.-3263)in regard to shelters, when the reports referred to in (a)and (6) have been received.Requisitioning of farm Lands for naval and military purposes.-7H10. The Prime Minister said that he had been informed thatvaluable arable land had been taken over by the Services, especially on the East Coast. A good many complaints ban been received from farmers. In view of the vital importance of increasing the home-grown food supply, it was essential that valuable arable land shouldnot be taken over by the Admiralty, War Office, Ministry ofMunitions, or the Air Ministry.Lord Derby agreed that there had been complaints but hethought, since Sir Howard Frank had been appointed Director-Generalof Lands, the grievances had ceased to exist.The War Cabinet decided To pass the following resolution, which should be shown first tothe First Lord of the Admiralty and the Air Ministry fortheir concurrence in its precise terms : &quot; In view of the serious position of the country&apos;s food supply and the necessity of making the best possible use ofland which is capable of producing food, it is decided thatno lands shall be taken over by the Admiralty, the WarOffice, the Ministry of Munitions, or the Air Ministry forpurposes connected with the war without the consent and approval of the Director-General of Lands. If, however, heis unable to approve and the Government department concerned still consider that it is essential for military or naval exigencies that the land should be taken, the mattershall then be referred to a Cabinet Committee for decision.&quot;Restriction ofNon-essential industries.11. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by SirAuckland Geddes (Paper GT.-3L54) and a Memorandum byDr. Addison (Paper G.T.-3272) in regard to the restriction of non-essential industries.
Sir Auckland Geddeswarthat he had had conversations withthe President of the Board of Trade and the -Minister of Labour onthe proposals submitted in bis Memorandum, and that they were inentire agreement as to the action which should be taken. Therewere two questions : firstly, the restriction of new businesses, and secondly, the restriction  of existing businesses.    To restrict newmsinesssadd)Opuliiv inovito restrict existing businesseswould entail a certain degree of hardship, it was proposed that clause (A) of the Draft Regulations should read &quot;To prohibit or restrict persons from establishing any newretail business, or a new branch of anv existing retail business,without a licence from the Minister of National Service.&quot;The War Cabinet approved this proposal.With regard to existing businesses, it was proposed to dealwith any- particular industry as occasion arises, in consultation withthe Board of Trade and the Ministry of Labour and other Govern -ment Departments concerned. In any case where the GovernmentDepartments concerned were agreed that it was desirable to restrict the manufacture or sale of goods in order to secure the transference of labour to essential industries, the President of the Board of trade would arrange that he and the Minister of National Service should meet representatives of the trade (employers aud workmen). Indefault of a satisfactory arrangement being arrived at fby voluntary-operation, the matter should be referred to the War Cabinet.The War Cabinet approved this proposal.Imperial andLocal Defence inIreland.y?1^Q12. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theAdmiralty (Paper G.T.-3208), and a Memorandum by the chief secretary for Ireland (Paper G.T.-3269), in regard to the imperial and Local Defence of Ireland.In his Memorandum, Mr. Duke, pointed out that, in his opinion,it was likely that a frank discussion of the problems of defence withthe Sub-Committee of the Convention by capable officers would leadto their making a very useful report to the Convention, and to agreement in the Convention upon reasonable conclusions.Lord Derby said that General Callwell had given evidence onbehalf of the War Office.The War Cabinet decided that There was no objection to a representative of the Admiraltygiving evidence before the Sub-Committee of the IrishConvention.Unemploymentdue to Eestrictionof Industries.13. The President of the Board of Trade drew the attention ofthe War Cabinet, to the probability of unemployment from now on,owing to the closing down of industries and the restriction of rawmaterials. He instanced the fact that there were to-day about30,000 cotton operatives out of employment. Either the Govern-ment should take some action or the unemployed would be driven to the workhouse. His Department had no authority at present forspending money in administering relief, but he suggested that aCommittee of Ministers should be appointed to submit a scheme.Sir Auckland Geddes agreed that there would be some unem-ployment where industries were restricted, but he did not think thatit would be on a large scale, owing to the general shortage of labour.Th.- Secretary stated that the restriction of non-essential industries had been agreed to in principle by the Cabinet Committeeon Man-Power, and bad been referred, for the preparation of a detailed scheme, to the Minister of National Service, in consultationwith the Government Departments concerned.
When an industry was cdosed there was always a small residuum oflabour unemployable elsewhere, but it was mostly female labour.The War Cabinet decided that A Committee composed of- The President of the Board of Trade (Chairman),The Minister of National Service,The Minister of Labour,Colonel Byrne (Secretary),should be appointed to consider the question and submit ascheme.14. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by thePresident of the Board of Trade, dealing with the position of thelinoleum and oilcloth industry in relation to shortage of linseed-oil,and of other materials, especially cork (Paper G.T.-3283), togetherwith a Note by the Secretary of the &quot;War Priorities Committee(Paper G.T.-3258).Sir Albert Stanley stated that no substitute for linseed-oil hadbeen found, and that the linoleum manufacturers would have to close down their works if their stocks were requisitioned and notreplenished. It was regrettable that no adequate warning had beengiven by the Ministry of Food of their intention to commandeerstocks. He would be prepared to forgo some tonnage assigned tocotton rather than subject the linoleum industry to such sudden anddrastic treatment as was proposed.Mr. Wise, of the Ministry of Food, stated that the linoleummanufacturers had known for some months that the situation was becoming increasingly serious. Durum- the last month the situation had, in fact, become much more grave because of the decision to cutclown imports during 1918, and because of the difhcultj&apos;&apos; of theTreasury in financing shipments of linseed from the Argentine and elsewhere. In view of the general shortage of oils and fats, theMinistry of Food had found it necessary to limit the use of vegetableoils to the two most essential needs, viz., the production of margarineand glycerine. It had also to be borne in mind that the consumptionof oil for edible purposes had greatly increased.General Smuts stated that the position had been discussed bythe War Priorities Committee, and while he himself was inclined to leave in the hands of the manufacturers the G.0OO tons oflinseed oil requisitioned by the Food Controller, which they had in stock, the Committee were of opinion that the oil situation Avas sobad that there was no alternative but to face the closing down ofthe linoleum trade.The &quot;War Cabinet decided that (a.) The 6,000 tons of linseed oil now in possession of the manufacturers should be rationed among them, prioritybeing given to Government requirements, and consumptionspread over a. period.(b.) The President of the Board of Trade should place himself in communication with the Shipping Controller in regardto the possibility of arranging for further shipments atthe expense of cotton or some import other than food.(c.) The President of the Board of Trade should inform the manufacturers of the above decisions.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 11, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
