<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 114-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]53Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1918.SECRET.13WAR CABINET, 328.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,oh Tuesday, January 22, 1918, at 11*30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Blockade.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby,KG., G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War.General Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.Lieutenant-General Sir J. S. Cowans,G.C.M.G., K.C.B., M.V.O., Quarter-Master-General to the Forces (for minutes 16 and 17).Lieutenant-General Sir C. F.N. Macready,K.C.B., K.O.M.G., Adjutant-General tothe Forces (for Minute 19).Major-General   A.   S.   Collard,   C.B.,Deputy    Controller,   Admiralty    (for minute 19).Mr. Andrew Weir, Surveyor-General ofSupply, War Office  (for  Minutes 16and 17).The Right Hon W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies (for Minute 18).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave^ M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minute 18).Rear-Admiral G. P. W. Hope, C.B.,deputy First Sea Lord (for Minutes 13and 14).Sir Alan Anderson, K.B.E., Con-troller, Admiralty (for Minute 19).The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Shipping Controller (for Minutes 16 and17).Mr. Graeme Thomson, C.B., Director of transports (for Minutes 16 and 17).Sir Lynden Macassey, K.C., K.B.E.,admiralty Shipyard Labour Department(for Minute 19).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minute 18).Mr. C. F. Rey, Ministry of Labour (for minute 19).The   Right Hon.  Sir A.   C.  Geddes,K.C.B.,   M.P.,  Minister   of  National&quot; Service (for Minute 19).Major P. Lloyd Greame, Ministry ofNational Service (for Minute 19).Sir E. Wyldbore Smith, Chairman,Commission internationale de RavitaiUe-ment (for Minutes 16 and 17).Sir J. F. Beale, K B.E., Secretary, wheat commission (for Minutes 16 and 17).Lieuteuant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, C.M.G., Acting Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Obmsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain E. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.
Salonica. 1. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that theenemy had made a strong attack on the Greek positions west ofthe Vardar, after a heavy preliminary bombardment, and that the^^attack had been everywhere vigorously repulsed with loss.Training of 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff informed theAmerican Troops. ^ar Cabinet that, according to a French report from New York,the training of American infantry had not yet passed beyondindividual firing instruction. The training of the artillery was still very much behindhand. There was a noticeable lack of discipline. 145 British officers and 140 N.C.O.&apos;s were employed as instructors, and 50 more officers and N.C.O.&apos;s were under ordersv^for the same purpose.3. With reference to War Cabinet 323, Minute 3, theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs raised the question of thedespatch of American troops to the Western front.It was stated that, in the opinion of those best qualified toknow, a private message from the Prime Minister to thePresident of the United States would be opportune on the subjectof despatching American troops by battalions.The War Cabinet decided that The Chief of the Imperial General Staff should draft aprivate message from the Prime Minister to thePresident of the United States, appealing to him toadopt the British view of the form in which Americacould best assist the Allied cause.American military co-operation-operation.3.The Western 4. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported thatFront. the French Military Attache in Madrid had been told by theKing of Spain that the Germans, after considerable discussion,y   had finally decided to make a big attack on the Western front.Transfer of german troops.      -&quot;3/&quot;5 /5. With reference to War Cabinet 326, Minute 2, the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff stated that another enemy division from the Bukowina had been identified at La Bassee, making anascertained total of 168 on the Western Front, and perhaps fromi/ 170 to 175.Eoumania.6. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported thatthe Roumanian Army was securing its hold on the railway com-municatiens in Bessarabia, but that the Ukrainians were notshowing a favourable disposition towards the Roumanians.It was pointed out that the news of the withdrawal ofGerman troops from the Bukowina suggested that theRoumanian Army should be able to hold out against any forcesat present opposed to them. The Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff agreed that this appeared to be so.The Caucasus. **&apos; ^e Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that therewere 41 British officers and 70 N.C 0.&apos;s at Baghdad about to start for the Caucasus. He also stated that he had inspectedcertain officers and N.C.O.&apos;s about to start for that area from england.Russian officers were alsoleavingEngland for the-Caucasus, and General Baratoff hoped to raise a force to co-operate with General Marshall.
3 WG 328The Italian Trout. 8. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that another sector on the Piave front was to be occupied by British^/troops.Italian Labour for 9- With reference to War Cabinet 324, Minute 4, the chief the Western Front,   of the Imperial General Staff stated that the Italian Governmentjf^1        were despatching the men secured by General Foch for work in/&apos; /rj France, and that 15,000 had started. &quot; 25,000 were to be employed at work on aircraft.General Cadorna. 10. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that,according to the French Ambassador in Rome, General Cadornawould be recalled from Versailles as an enquiry into his conductof the operations was about, to begin. In this connection it wassuggested that the Prime Minister should telegraph to SignorOrlando asking him to allow General Cadorna to remain at versailles for the forthcoming meeting of the Supreme AVarCouncil.The War Cabinet decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should telegraph to the British Ambassador in Rome, urging that if general Cadorna were to be recalled before the meetingof the Supreme War Council there should be some otherfully accredited Italian representative appointed in his place.italy&apos;s War Aims. 11. The Secretary^ of State for Foreign Affairs informed theWar Cabinet that the Marquis Imperiali had expressed to him thegreat disappointment caused in Italy by the scanty reference inthe Prime Ministers recent speech to Italy&apos;s war aims. Therewa,s to be, on the 27th instant, a meeting, either in Turin or Milan,to promote the war enthusiasm of the nation, and someencouraging message from England on that occasion would be helpful.The War Cabinet decided that The best method of meeting this object would be for theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs to draft a message of encouragement from the Prime Minister to Signory/S Orlando, to be read at that meeting.Provision for Lady 12. With   reference   to War Cabinet 279, Minute 5, theMaude. Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that he anticipated opposition in Parliament to the granting to General Maude&apos;s widow of25,000Z. in addition to the pension of 500Z. a year to which she was entitled.. As&apos;    L- It was pointed out that the pension was hers of right and could not be reduced, and it seemed that the Government waspledged to her in the matter of the grant.Some doubt was expressed on the latter point, and the Secre-tary of State for War agreed to inform the Chancellor of theExchequer whether, in his communication to Lady Maude, hehad committed the Government to any definite sum.It was agreed that this subject should be brought again beforethe War Cabinet.The &quot; Goeben &quot; and 13. The Deputy First Sea Lord read a full telegraphic reporttc Breslau.&quot;     ,      0f the events connected  with the sortie of the.&quot; Goeben &quot; andy , &quot;S7&quot;?      &quot; Breslau &quot; on the morning of the 20th January.   The bulk of,t^&apos; &apos;   s/i      this information had been communicated to the Press.   prisoners from the &quot; Breslau &quot; expressed intense dislike to the Turks, and
they had anticipated being sent back to Germany on the con-clusion of the raid, which had been intended as a demonstrationagainst the Islands in order to hearten the Turks, whose moralwas very low. The &quot; Breslau &quot; had been struck by no less than from six to eight mines. The damage to the &quot; Goeben &quot; had been caused by one mine. The mines into which these ships had runwere British mines of early type. The &quot; Goeben &quot; had grounded ona spit of sand, and the damage to her appeared serious. Fog had prevented operations by aircraft against the &quot;Goeben&quot; duringthe forenoon of Monday, the 21st January. At that time the&quot; Goeben &quot; was still in the same position. Heavy smoke was stillcoming from her funnels, which seemed to indicate that she was able to use her steam. The size of the hole would decide whethershe could be re-floated or not. Even if re-floated, she was not likely to be of much use, as she could not be docked atConstantinople for substantial repair. The two British destroyersengaged had done very fine work.The War Cabinet decided that -The information derived from the prisoners concerning the1/ moral of the Turks should not be published.Hong Kong. 14. The Deputy First Sea Lord also read a despatch fromthe Rear-Admiral at Hong Kong, stating that the Captain of theRussian ship &quot; Orel&quot; had sent him the following information: ^y (a.) Ships will probably be unable to meet their obligationsn 3 &quot; ^ * here on account of lack of credit.(b.) ITe may want  to send  about 100 men of Maximalisttendencies back to Russia.(c.) He dare not in any case go back to Vladivostock with hismidshipmen on board, as they would be murdered.(d.) He may offer to place his ships and services of those officers and men who elect to remain in them at thedisposal of British Government for such service asmay be required of them.The Deputy First Sea Lord stated that the Rear-Admiral at hong Kong had consulted with the Governor, who concurred withhim in the desirability of requesting instructions in case any of- the above eventualities arose.   The relations on board betweenofficers and men were not entirely satisfactory.Military service bill:Negotiations withthe amalgamated society of engineers.15. A letter was read from Mr. Wardle, M.P., addressed fromthe Labour Party Conference at Nottingham, to Mr. Barnes,suggesting that the Prime Minister should address a meeting ofthe delegates of the Amalgamated Society of Engineers who weremeeting in London to discuss their attitude towards the MilitaryService Bill.Mr. Barnes said that he was endeavouring to get into touchwith Mr. Brownlie, of the Amalgamated Society of Engineers,who was in charge of the delegates, and would communicate withthe Prime Minister as soon as he had obtained further information regarding the attitude of the delegates. He strongly recommendedthat the Prime Minister should not offer to attend the meeting,but thought that if an invitation was issued to the Prime minister the matter should be carefully considered, in consultation with.Sir Auckland Geddes.Greece:Supplies for.
Government were not carrying out their part of the bargain inregard to supplies to Greece.Referring to Table (B) of the Memorandum, as regards thesupply of artillery, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff saidthat it had been agreed that the nine batteries &quot; de pieces longues &quot;should be supplied by the French; of the nine batteries of howitzersreferred to in the Memorandum, 12 guns had been sent, eight were now going from France, and, of the remainder, sixteen were&quot;5 awaiting shipping at Woolwich./ a - Mr. Graeme Thomson said that the Ministry of Shippingcould arrange to take everything that was offering in thisrespect. As regards the hospitals, these had been shipped.The wagons referred to had not been shipped because the Greekshad not yet selected which pattern of lorries they wanted. Itwas clear that some misunderstanding had arisen among theDepartments concerned as to the supply of rolling stock which hadnot been shipped to Greece. In this connection telegrams from lord Granville (Nos. 52 and 64) were read, from which itappeared that the pretext given by M. Venizelos as to why theGreek Army could not even be partially mobilised was becauseof the failure of the British Government to supply the railwaytransport which had been promised.With reference to our undertaking to ship 282,000 tons ofwheat up to the end of June next, it was not clear whether thewheat and oats for the embodied troops were to be regarded asan additional amount. In view of the great importance ofequipping the Greek army so that they may be mobilised to with-stand an attack which might be made by the enemy at any time on the Salonica front, the War Cabinet requested Lord Milner to examine the list of supplies item by item, andto see what could be done to accelerate shipment.Lord Milner undertook to call a meeting the same afternoon,at which the War Office should be represented, when hewould examine the question and draft a message for thePrime Minister to send in reply to M. Clemenceau. acopy of which should be sent by the Foreign Office toLord Granville, to be shown to M. Venizelos.Supply of Oats to 17. With reference to WTar Cabinet 273. Minute 18, the Warthe Italian Army.     Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by Sir E. WyldboreSmith (Paper G.T.-3372) on the subject of Oats for Italy.It was pointed out in the Memorandum that for the first,G/   quarter of this year, and particularly in the months of January/  ^ /s     an(^ February, the situation had become acute.     The monthlylyJj       1   &apos;   requirements of the Italian army, based on a very low ration, was60,000 tons. As against this figure the estimated arrivals (military)during   January,  February, and   March, amounted to 20,000,15,000, and 42,000 tons respectively.   In view of the fact that theoats situation in this country and in France was relatively much better than in Italy, Sir E. Wyldbore Smith suggested that someof the floating cargoes of oats en route to this country should be diverted to Italy, and that representations should be made to theFrench Government with a view to their taking similar action.The Quartermaster-General said that it woidd be possibleto divert one floating cargo, namely, that of the S.S. &quot; Henley,&quot;amounting to 4,650 tons, now en route to Salonica, but that itwould not be possible to spare any cargoes en route to the british army in France, because the reserves there were down to 11 dayson the 18th. January, and the situation was critical.These considerations gave rise to the question as to whetherthe British ration of oats should not be reduced.   It appearedujv&quot;  / Lp-      that whereas the Italian ration averaged 3 lbs. per horse, and
the French ration 7 lbs., the British ration was 12 lbs. these were average amounts for light and draught horses. If theBritish average was reduced from 12 lbs. to 10 lbs., namely, one-sixth, the saving on the present consumption of 86,500 tons per month would be tantamount to a reduction of about 14,000 tons per month. When last year the ration of oats was cut down byone-half, the mortality amongst horses went up from 2 per cent,to 5 per cent.The Shipping Controller suggested that the large amount of oats said to be available in Ireland, which had been estimated at about 300,000 tons were not yet forthcoming.Sir John Beale pointed out, however, that owing to theirfailure to obtain maize, the Irish had been feeding oats to pigs,and it was impossible to buy any except small quantities for seedpurposes. The difficulty of obtaining supplies in Ireland was increased by the lack of transport and threshing facilities.The War Cabinet were of opinion that the whole question ofthe supply and distribution of oats for both civil and military pur-poses, including the ration for horses, required further considera-tion, and, in view of the relative stocks in the Allied countries,directed The Secretary to place the question on the Agenda Paper forthe next Paris Conference.In the meantime they dicided that (a.) The Shipping Controller should divert the steamship&quot; Henley &quot; to Italy;(b.) The Secretary of State for War should make arrange-ments to supply a further 10,000 tons of oats to italy as soon as possible;(c.) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should makerepresentation to the French Government with a viewto their also sending assistance to Italy by the diversion of a cargo or cargoes of oats. ,18. With reference to War Cabinet 322, Minute 18, the WarCabinet had before them the following documents: Memorandum by Sir George Cave (Paper G.T.-3329).Memorandum by Mr. G. H. Roberts (Paper G.T.-3360).Note by Mr. Long (Paper G.T.-3379).Foreign Office telegrams Paris No. 84, of the 17th January, 1918.Rome No. 46, of the 17th January, 1918.Washington No. 243, of the 17th January, 1918.Sir George Cave called attention to a leaflet printed for theBritish Socialist Party for circulation to the Labour Party at theNottingham Conference. The leaflet was a clear breach of theregulations; it had been seized by the police, and a prosecutionwas under consideration. Copies of &quot; The Call,&quot; containing thesubstance of the leaflet, had also been seized. It was evident thatthe presence of M. Litvinoff was being exploited in the interests ofpacifism, and it was desirable to come to some decision as to thetreatment to be meted out to him by the Government.Lord Robert Cecil said that, in his view, one of two coursesshoulc! be adopted: complete freedom of speech, or drastic all-round repression. He believed free speech to be the wiser policy.To suppress small newspapers only gave them and theirteachings a tremendous advertisement. As to M. Litvinoff,he ought to be dealt with in the light of the Government&apos;s generalpolicy towards the Bolsheviks.   To drive him out of the country
Man-Power:Supply of labour in Shipyards.-2-.01 f*ISIdis,-19. The War Cabinet had before them the following docu-ments: Memorandum by the Admiralty on Labour for Merchant Ship-building (Paper G.T.-3408).Draft Report of the Cabinet Committee on Man-Power(Paper G.-185).Sir Alan Anderson called attention to paragraph 47 of theDraft Report on Man-Power, and urged that a decision should bereached at once (without prejudice to a decision on the rest of theReport) with regard to the release of 20,000 skilled men from thearmy for shipbuilding. It was now some three months since steelbegan to arrive in the quantity required, and it was becoming moreand more obvious that the limiting factor in carrying out the ship-building programme was this supply of skilled men. More un-skilled men than could ha properly be absorbed were at presentarriving at the shipyards, and the bad effect of such a momentarysurplus on the minds of the employers and of the men ought not tobe overlooked.General Maciready said that it was impossible, until the cardindex for the whole army had been completed, to say what numberof skilled men was likely to be available. Further, it must be borne in mind that at the moment the infantry was short by over 100,000men, and that during the first sixteen days of January freshrecruits had numbered only 8,300, of whom two-thirds were boysof eighteen. He doubted whether 20,000 skilled men for ship-building could be found.On the other hand, it was pointed out that the position of thearmy in France was likely to be improved in view of arrangements now in progress with the United States Government.Sir Auckland Geddes said it was impossible to give any satisfactory estimate of the number of skilled men available athome and in France. Many were probably not fit for general ser-vice. He had asked the War Office to make preparations for therelease of skilled men from the Home army, and a War cabinet decision was now required.would be tantamount to a declaration of war against tbeBolsheviks. On the other hand, he could be repatriated, like anyother Ambassador, as a person not liked by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment. He had discussed the matter with Sir George Buchanan,who, on the whole, rather assented to the view that the longer adecision was postponed the better.Mr. G. II. Roberts said he agreed with the course taken in theparticular instance by the Home Secretary. There was no doubtthat the propaganda of the British Socialistic Party, backed inthis case by the Independent Labour Party, was tending to under-rnine the moral of the people. He agreed that the house-to housedistribution of leaflets was a most damaging method of pro-paganda. But he would like to lay stress, not on the need forrepression, but on the great need for a counter-offensive, especiallyin the columns of the smaller provincial papers.The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the action which wTas being taken by theHome Secretary, who should, if possible, seize themachinery of the offending press;(b.) That efforts should be made to supply the local news-papers with material on the lines indicated in theMemorandum of the Minister of Labour;(c.) That no action should be taken for the moment in respectto M. Litvinoff.
The War Cabinet decided that The 20,000 men for shipbuilding now asked for should be released from the forces at home and overseas, from all categories, but excluding officers and warrant officers.20. With reference to War Cabinet 327 and to telegrams No.1494A, dated the 17th January, 1918, and No. 2143, of last year,the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was authorised to send the following telegram to Mr. Lindley for Major Keyes: &quot; The Government are so anxious to give immediatefinancial assistance to our friends that if the advance can be utilised immediately to assist them, and on the understandingthat the unnamed financier is P  , the Government willsanction the proposal. You see therefore that we are pre-pared to take this course entirely on your advice.&quot;2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W&apos;.,January 22, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
