<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 122-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
n    sttttt vt*i-ji-- V[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]        57Printed for ike War Cabinet.   January 1918.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 329,Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on tuesday, January 23, 1918, at 10-30 a.k.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).Thr- Rmht Hon   the Earl Curzon of j The Right Hon.  the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. George N. Barnes, M.PThe Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right, Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Blockade (for minutes to 13).The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes 5 to 13).Major-General Sir G. M. W. Macdonogh,K.C.M.G, C.B., Director of military intelligence (for Minutes 5 to 13).Brigadier-General A. W. F. Knox,Military Attache to the Russian Embassy(for Minute 5 to 13).Rear-Admiral G. P. W. Hope, C.B.,Deputy First Sea Lord (for minutes to 11).Mr. W. A. S. Hewins, M.P., Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies (for minute 4).The Right Hon. Lord Rhondda, FoodController (for Minute 3).Mr. Andrew Uthwatt, Ministry of Food(for Minute 3).Mr. G. J. Wardle, M.P., parliamentary secretary to the Board of Trade (for minutes 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Sir A. H. Stanley, M.P.,President, Board of Trade (for minutes, 2, and 4).The Right Hon. Str George Cave, K.C.,M.P.,   Secretary  of  State  for  HomeAffairs (for Minutes 3 and 12).Sir Evan Davies Jones, Bart., Board ofTrade (for Minute 4).The Right Hon. G. ft. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minutes 1 and 2).Sir  David Shackleton,  K.C.B.,  Per-mament Secretary, Ministry of Labour(for Minutes 1 and 2).The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 1and 2).Sir L. Wortiungton Evans, Bart., M.P.,Parliamentary  Secretary,   Ministry  ofMunitions (for Minute 4).Mr. F. G. Kellaway, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Munitions (for minutes 1 and 2).The  Right  Hon.   Sir A.   C.K.C.B.,   M.P.,   Minister  ofService (for Minutes 1 and 2).Sir Stephenson Kent, K.C.B..of Munitions (for Minutes 1 and 2).Sir Lynden Macassey, K.B.E.,  K.C.,Admiralty Shipyard Labour Department(for Minutes 1 and 2).Sir T. Munro, Ministry of Munitions (for minutes 1 and 2).Mr. Noel E. Peck (for Minutes 1 and 2).Geddes,NationalMinistryLieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, C.M.G., Acting Secretary.Captain E. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.
1. With reference to War Cabinet 326, Minute 3, the WarCabinet had before them a memorandum by the Minister ofMunitions, together with the views of certain officers of his department (Paper G.T.-34.17), conveying the following suggestion as an alternative to the action proposed by the Committee on production Piece-work prices and premium bonus-time allowances,which do not enable the men concerned to earn amountsreasonably in excess of those earned by time-workers inreceipt of the 12^ per cent, bonus, shall be revised.&apos;&apos;Mr. Churchill recalled the discussion which had taken place at the War Cabinet on the 7th January, 1918 (War Cabinet 317,Minute 1). It was not then known what view would be taken bythe trade union leaders. Since then, the Trade Union AdvisoryCommittee had passed a resolution in favour of extending the12-g per cent, over the time-workers, against a uniform advance to all piece-workers, but favouring the revision of low piece-rates.The Ministry of Labour had been impressed by this resolution,and had made a public statement of the policy which they intendedto follow. It was with surprise, therefore, that he (Mr. Churchill)had read the decision of the War Cabinet on Monday last (WarCabinet 326, Minute 3) agreeing to an increase of 1\ Per cent, topiece-workers generally. That was a very serious decision, and a reversal of the policy announced to the public. It would cost thecountry between 30 and 35 million pounds, and would immediatelyreact, not only on time-workers, but on women workers, whoalways shared in piece-work advances. It was important that theCabinet should remember that shipyard labour, which it wasspecially desired to appease, was a small fraction of the totalnumber of workers affected by the decision. Whereas only some900,000 were being given the advance of 12i per cent., the exten-sion to piece-workers would raise the number to over 3,000,000.There was no general demand for the advance which the cabinet was now offering; the leaders were against it, and large numbersof men who would receive it did not deserve it. He recommended the Cabinet to adhere to the policy which had been publicly announced, and to deal witrT&quot; special cases as they arose, andparticularly to make an attempt to revise low piece-rates. Thegeneral labour position was infinitely more manageable than itwas five weeks ago, and with care, patience, and the provisionof. the necessary machinery, a gradual solution of the present difficulties could be achieved. There was a further reason why the Cabinet should not grant an advance at the moment; theGovernment was on the eve of serious trouble with the labour move-ment in connection with the Military Service Bill. The presentgrant should be kept in hand as a means of mollification later on.Mr. Barnes reminded the War Cabinet that they hadentrusted the Ministry of labour with power to settle with thepiece-workers within the limits of 7s. The 7J bonus now proposed was roughly the equivalent of 7s. It was quite true that the TradeUnion Advisory Committee had adopted the resolution referred toby Mr. Churchill, and if that policy had been pursued at first asolution might have been reached; but difficulties had accumulatedwith each day&apos;s delay, and cases had come up so rapidly that theCommittee on Production had decided it to be impossible to dealwith them except by some general overhead advance. The positionin Belfast was particularly serious. A strike had only been pre-vented by Sir George Gibb promising that his award would bemade immediately, but the Committee on Production was rightlyunwilling to issue its award without knowing whether it was toapply generally or not. The men on the Clyde and Tyne wouldcertainly demand to share in any award made to Belfast. Pie(Mr. Barnes) would not object to a limit being placed so that themost highly paid men should not share in the advance, but aThe labour situation :7-i per cent. Bonusto Piece-workers.
decision must be taken at once, otherwise the Committee on production would be overwhelmed.Sir Lynden Macassey pointed cut that the award to the time-workers was having a bad effect on the production of the piece-workers, who were now reverting to time-work, and men who were engaged on new shipbuilding construction were reverting torepairs. Examples were quoted of men who did specific jobs onthe premium bonus rates in 28-1- hours who were now on time-ratestaking 56f hours.Mr. G. H. Roberts emphasised the importance of bringing theworkmen back to payment by results, in the interest of increased output, and, in reply to a question whether the grant of 1\ percent, would do this, he stated that the employers whom he had&quot; con-suited were of that opinion. The employers believed that it was better to settle on a basis of 1\ per cent, now, with men&apos;s goodwill, than to be forced later to concede 12-i- per cent, in an atmosphere-phere of ill will. It was true that the Tracle Union Advisory Com-mittee had passed the resolution referred to, but it was significant that they had completely failed to restrain their unions fromdemanding 121 Per cent- The leaders, in fact, had little or noinfluence on the situation. The cases to be dealt with were sonumerous that a general formula was indispensable. The advance in the form of 7-o- per cent, was preferable to a money advance,because the men were accustomed to a percentage system, and weresuspicious that the 75. was some subterfuge. He was certain thatif the advance wras not immediately conceded there would be sucha serious upheaval that the Government vvould be forced to grant the 12^ per cent., and would have to do so to men irritated by delay.Sir Auckland Geddes said that he adhered to the views he had expressed at previous meetings, viz., that the decision should beleft to the Ministry of Labour, and that, sooner or later, the 12-^per cent, w^ould have to be conceded all round. Employers were most anxious to have to deal with one Government Department,and if the Ministry of Labour had not the necessary machinery,then the Ministry of Munitions should contribute some of its staff to the Ministry of Labour. The policy proposed by Mr. Churchillwrould have been preferable had there been time for negotiation,but there was no time available.Sir Stephenson Kent was convinced that a general grant, even of 12-^ per cent., would not bring peace, but rather wrould initiatea new series of demands, because the disabilities of the time-workers and the low piece-rate w-orkers would still be unremedied.It wras the man working on low7 piece rates who was reverting totime rates. The Ministry of Munitions had found it possible toarrive at a settlement, with the steel trade in a Joint Conference ofEmployers and Trade Unionists lasting two days. Given goodwill there should be no insuperable difficulty in adjusting lowpiece rates. He wished it: were possible to get right away from the12^ per cent., formula.Sir David Shackieton pointed out that it was quite impracticable-able, at a time like the present, to attempt a revision of piece rates:they involved complicated questions of materials, machinery, andmen, and would mean negotiations running into many months.Mr. Kellaway believed that the recommendation of theMinistry of Labour did not remove the hindrance to increased production.The War Cabinet, in coming to a decision, had in mind their previous decision to entrust the problems under consideration tothe Ministry of Labour. They were also impressed with thesupreme urgency of increasing the output of tonnage, even at greatfinancial cost to the nation.The War Cabinet confirmed the decision arrived at at themeeting held on Monday, the 21st January, 1918 (WarCabinet 326, Minute 3).
Mr. Churchill believed the decision was one whichwould not only not lead to an increase of output, but would unsettle the time-workers throughout the wholemunitions industry.Strike of Sheet- 2. Mr. G. E. Roberts called the attention of the War CabinetMetal Workers.       to a dispute which had been going on for some time in the London^ area in regard to the establishing of a district rate for sheet-metalL .33 workers of Is. Id. per hour.   This claim had been put to arbitra-^/r Of. tion on no less than six occasions, and in each case it had been held that the claim was not established. He had received on the previous day a deputation representing the officials of the union and themen. If the demand of the men were conceded, the total waradvance which they would obtain would amount to 40s. per week asagainst 27s. M. (including the 12^ per cent.) received by the engineers on plain time-work. Some forty-four firms had, in every case without the consent of the Government, paid the Is. Id., ormore. Some three firms in aircraft manufacture were refusing tomake the concession, and in their refusal were supported by theGovernment Departments concerned and the Employers&apos; Associa-tion. The amount in dispute was not very large, but the principle involved was very serious, for if the new rate were conceded forthis industry, similar claims would follow from the general engineering and shipbuilding industries, and a new cycle of advances would be started, creating a similar disturbance ito thatset up by the 12-1 Per cent, bonus. He had informed the repre-sentatives of the men that he had no power to grant their demandfor a Is. Id. per hour rate, but he had undertaken that, in so faras their demand for a war bonus and the 12^ per cent, were con-cerned, he would expedite a settlement of any outstanding claims.Lie intended to refer the question of the 121 Per cent, to the Com-mittee on Production as soon as the strike terminated.Sir Stephenson Kent represented the views of Sir WilliamWeir, the Director-General of Aircraft Production. The limit of output at present in the aircraft industry, so far as themanufacture of aeroplanes was concerned, was the output of thesheet metal working departments, and this applied verydefinitely to the output of large bombing machines. At thepresent rate of output the London Aircraft Factories wereturning out approximately 180 machines per week, and every week the sheet-metal workers were out on strike this number of machines was lost. Next, some of the London aircraft builderssupplied metal fittings for many aircraft firms all over thecountry, and this represented a further loss of some 50 machinesper week. Next, a large number of radiators were made in the .a)London district by sheet-metal workers, and the influence of this might easily represent the loss of an additional 50 machines perweek. Accordingly, the continuance of the strike meant the lossof approximately 280 machines per week, including a number ofthe most valuable machines for the early spring campaign. Inhis view they were not warranted in incurring such a- loss of out-put by withholding 2d. an hour from a few firms. On the otherhand, in view of the recent interruptions of work in various branches of the aircraft and engineering industries, he would beprepared to face a strike of two or three weeks&apos; duration if sucha course would guarantee a settled labour atmosphere for thefuture.In reply to a question it was stated not to be possible toobtain the necessary sheet metal from France, owing to the labour required on the material, the varieties of design, &amp;c.The War Cabinet took note of the situation, but came to no decision.
Food Control:InadequatePenalties for offences.3. The War Cabinet approved the action proposed by theFood Controller to deal with offences against the Food ControlOrders, as set forth in Paper G.T.-3384, viz.: That a short Bill should be introduced under which offendersshould, in addition to being liable to the Criminal JLaw,become debtors to the Crown in respect of the amount, ordouble the amount, of any excess price charged by themabove the fixed minimum price.CEconomic &amp; flxe War Cabinet had before them Interim Report No. 8Offensive: 01 tue Economic Offensive Committee, dealing with a scheme forBritish Dye the development of the British dye industry (Paper G.-187).Industry. Sir Albert Stanley summarised the recommendations set forth in the Report, and stated that, broadly, the object was to give theBoard of Trade, in dealing with the dye industry, powers similarto those enjoyed by the Ministry of Munitions in relation to industries controlled by that Department. It was desiredto make this country as independent as possible of supplies from Germany. To do this it would be necessary that financial advances should be made to private firms engaged in thedye trade, with the object of promoting developments and extensions. These advances might be in the form of grants orloans. The Board of Trade should retain powers to regulate suchdevelopments and extensions; to limit profits: to decide the kindsand quantities of dyestuffs to be manufactured; to regulate bylicence the import of dyestuffs after the war; and to secure priority for materials and labour, and to provide for the exemption ofchemists and chemical engineers from military service, as set outin the memorandum of the Board of Trade. It was an essentialaccompaniment to any scheme adopted that some effective assur-ance should be given that the importation of dyes into thiscountry should be prohibited except under licence for a consider-able period after the war. The powers already exercised by theBoard of Trade to restrict the importation of a commodity as awhole (so long as they do not discriminate between the countries of origin) do not depend on emergency legislation, but on the CustomsConsolidation Act, and will -therefore continue after the warwithout further legislation. In reply to a question whether, ifthe recommendations now put forward were adopted, this country could be made completely independent of German dyestuffs, SirAlbert Stanley said that it was a question of degree, and that itwas desirable to make as much progress as possible during thewar.Sir Evan Jones believed that, if the authority now asked forwere given by the War Cabinet, it would be possible in a few years&apos;time to make the industry self-supporting, and the country to allintents and purposes independent of the German supply. the class of dye in use before the war was to a considerable extentdevoted to what might be called &quot;luxury trades.&quot; That classwas not likely to be so much in demand after the war. It was important that this country should have ample plant and suitableorganisation to produce dyes for which there would be a big world-market. There was reason to think that the dyes which were nowbeing accumulated in Germany would not be in such generaldemand after the war as before. At any rate, we ought to be ina position to compete, but without obtaining the powers now asked for we would not be in such a position.The War Cabinet considered the difficulty of giving, without legislation, the assurance asked for to private firms an assurancewhich would lead them to invest large sums of money whichmight be repudiated by subsequent Governments.
The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the recommendations set forth in the InterimReport.(b.) That a statement should be made by the Leader of theHouse in explanation of the policy adopted.Greece: 5. With  reference to War Cabinet 328, Minute 16, theSupplies for. discussion of the question of furnishing supplies to Greece was resumed in the light of &quot;the information furnished by Lord Milner&apos;s-^w-^Sr/. enquiries.^ Lord Milner pointed out that everything that Greece had- asked for, with the exception of rolling-stock, and 36 tractors, thesupply of which had been dependent on Treasury consent, had^ either been already shipped to that country or was in readiness toQ go.   Last November the wheat requirements for the whole of(?5 % Greece were gone into, and a compact was drawn up to supply282,000 tons of wheat between that date and the end of June.Lord Milner stated that, previous to the above agreement, we had ?. undertaken, in August and September, to supply, if possible, 5,000tons of wheat per month for military requirements. The questionnow arose as to whether this 5,000 tons per month was includedin the 282,000 tons before mentioned, or not. Lord Milner saidthat the latter allotment ought to cover the needs of the army aswell as those of the civilian population. In answer to a question,Lord Milner said that not only was the supply of the 282,000 tonsactually being met out of the Allied pool, but that Greece hadpriority over our other Allies. M. Venizelos was said to be satisfied with this arrangement.The War Cabinet decided that Lord Milner should draft a telegram, for the approval of thePrime Minister, to be sent to M. Clemenceau, stating thatthe British Government had gone into the question of supplying 5,000 tons of wheat per month to Greece overand above the 282,000 tons which it was agreed to supplybetween November 1917 and the end of June 1918, and considered that the military requirements were includedin the total amount to be so supplied.Oat Eation forBritish Army.IP-it. The Secretary of State for War informed the War Cabinetthat he had issued orders for the oat ration for horses of all british forces everywhere to be reduced by 2 lb. This reduction wouldmean a saving of half a million tons of shipping. Lord Derbyrequested, therefore, that this matter should not be brought up atthe forthcoming meeting of the Supreme War Council at versailles.nation  for troops at Home.7. The Secretary of State for War stated that he proposed,subject to the approval of the jL^edical authorities, that the scale of rations of troops stationed at home should be modified forthwithso as to embrace two classes: (a.) Troops under training or otherwise in preparation for service overseas, and mobile formations actually em-ployed in home defence;(p.) All other troops at home.In the case of (a) the present home service scale of rationswill be maintained. In the case of (b) the following reductions to be made at once: from 12 oz. to 8 oz.from 2 oz. to 1 oz.from 2 oz. to 1 oz.MeatSugarBaconTea
This reduction, if carried out, would mean a saving of 2,000 tons of meat per month.500 tons of sugar per month.500 tons of bacon per month.60 tons of tea per month.The War Cabinet requested The Secretary of State for War to make the suggested reduc-tions after consultation with the medical authorities.Artillery from 8. The Secretary of State for War read a telegram which M.JRussm Armies for Clemenceau had received from General Berthelot, to the effect thatuse in Koumama. gle pfoumanian General Staff were studying the question of form-ing three new divisions to replace the Russian divisions whichwere being withdrawn from the Roumanian front. The telegramstated that General Tscherbatscheff was prepared to give thenecessary artillery to these new divisions by withdrawing it fromthe Russian divisions, if the Allies approved. M. Clemenceau had informed the Secretary of State for war that he was sending thenecessary authorisation to General Berthelot, and asked that theBritish Government should do the same.The War Cabinet considered that the man on the spot shouldbe trusted, and approved the suggestion that materialshould be taken over from the Russian divisions that hadbeen withdrawn on the Roumanian front, and hesupplied to the Roumanian army. Russia being credited,p/toj/ g - and Roumania being debited, with the value of the same./ -j&apos;^ and requested i/The Secretary of State for War to  communicate to M.Clemenceau the War Cabinefs decision.The Italian Front.9. The Director of Military Intelligence stated that, accord-ing to information received from prisoners, an attack on the lineheld by the French near Astico might be expected during the firstfortnight in February.Serbians from 10. The Director of  Military Intelligence stated that aEussia at Salonica.   number of Serbians had arrived at Salonica from Russia, and,/were already incorporated in the Serbian army.CThe &quot; Goeben &quot;and &quot; Breslau.&quot;11. With reference to War Cabinet 328, Minute 13,the Deputy Chief - of the Naval Staff informed the WarCabinet that the air attacks on the &quot; Goeben &quot; were still being continued, and it was known that a certain number of direct hitshad been obtained. The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff read atelegram from Vienna (through Geneva) which stated that the&quot; Goeben &quot; may be considered as lost, but that efforts were beingmade to save the bigger gunsi, whilst the ammunition had been thrown overboard. The question was asked whether news of the disaster to the &quot; Goeben &quot; and the &quot; Breslau &quot; had reachedConstantinople, andThe Director of Military Intelligence was instructed to takethe necessary steps for the news to be spread in constantinople.Kussia :Anglo-EussianMilitary ServiceAgreement.[1366^9]12. The War Cabinet had before them a Paper by Mr. Balfouron the subject of the conscription of Russian subjects in thiscountry (Paper G.T.-3411).D
Mr. Balfour explained the difficulty which had arisen in theworking of the convention agreed between His Majesty,&apos;s Govern-ment and the late Russian Government. Under the Act of Parlia-ment upon which the convention was founded, power was given,without appeal, to the Ambassadors in both countries to grantexemptions from military service. M. Litvinoff, the representa-tive of the Bolshevik Government, would undoubtedly exempt allthe East End Jews from military service, if he could. This would create an intolerable position in the East End, where these RussianJews were making large sums of money by supplanting Britishshopkeepers who had been called up for military service.General Macdonogh stated, that there were about 25,000 ofthese Russians of military age in this country, of whom only about ,000 had so far been called up. From the counter-espionagepoint of view, it was most desirable that these aliens should be either got into the army, interned, or deported to Russia. Themajority of them were Jews. He had accordingly seen Dr.Weizmann, the President of the English Zionist Federation, whohad expressed the opinion that it was important that the Jewishregiment, to which these Russian Jews were usually sent, shouldbe despatched to Palestine at the earliest possible date. orders had accordingly been given to the regiment, which was nowstationed at Plymouth, to prepare for service overseas, and trans-port was being awaited. He feared that a majority of the remain-ing East End Jews cared very little for Zionism, and were onlyanxious to make profits. Under the convention an option wasgiven to these aliens either to serve in the British army or else toreturn to Russia. The tonnage difficulty prevented the latteralternative being made use of in practice, and this fact was knownto a good many of the aliens.Lord Derby stated that there had been some trouble in theJewish regiment at Plymouth, but on being addressed by theirCommanding Officer, Colonel Paterson, who had a greathold over them, they wrere unanimous in desiring to proceed to palestine to fight. He hoped that the Government would remainfirm, and continue to enforce the Military Service Acts in regardto these Russians. Rather than allow them to remain in the EastEnd, he thought that, failing their being got into the army, themost practical suggestion would be to send them to a concentra-tion camp at Aberdeen or Hull, to await transport to Russia, andthat they should be made to understand distinctly that they wouldnot be allowed to return to this country.The War Cabinet decided that The Military Service Acts should continue to be applied to russian subjects in this country, and that, in the eventof it being impossible to get all of them into the army,they should be sent to camps, as suggested by Lord Derby,and be made to understand that their return would not be permitted.The working out of this decision was to be left to an Inter-Departmental Committee, to be arranged by Lord Derby, consist-ing of representatives of The War Office,The Foreign Office,The Home Office,The Ministry of national Service.13. The War Cabinet had before them the question of a date for the next meeting of the Supreme War Cuncil at Versailles.After consultation as to a date which would give time for therepresentatives of Italy to be present, it was agreed that Wednesday-
day, the 30th January, would be a suitable date, and the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs was requested to Send a telegram to Paris suggesting that the next meeting ofthe Supreme War Council should be held at Versailleson Wednesday, the 30th January, 1918.With reference to subjects that might be considered at themeeting of the Council, it was decided that (1.) The Prime Minister and Lord Milner represent theBritish Cabinet at that Council, and that full powersbe given them to decide all questions relating to (a.) The extension of the British front, and(&amp;.) The disposition and  command of the general reserve on the Allied Western front.(2.) In view of the statement produced by the Secretary of;;y. State for War, the supply and distribution of oatsshould not be submitted to the Supreme War Council.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 23, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
