<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 198-203</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Director of Military Operations.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for.the War Cabinet.   February 1918.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 342.Minutes of a, Meeting of the War Cabinet held, at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Monday, February 11, 1918, at 12 noon.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon.  the  Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.O.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, CM.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Rear-Admiral S. R. I^remantle, C.B.,M.V.O., Depxttv Chief of the naval staff /for Minutes 11 to 13).The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C., j The Right Hon. Sir Gordon Hewart,K.C,M.P., Minister of Blockade. M.P., Solicitor-General (for Minute 16).The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,G.O.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar.Major-Gcneral Sir G. M. W. Macdonogh,K.C.M.G., CP.., Director of military intelligence (for Minutes i to 10, 14, 16).Sir E. Cook, Press Bureau (for Minute16).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.The western front :Transfer of german divisions.3^.1. WITH reference to War Cabinet 340, Minute 2, theDirector of Military Intelligence informed the War Cabinet that another German Division had been identified on the Western Front,making a total of 175 Divisions now on that Front, 63 of which arein reserve.The Prime Minister requested-The   Director of MilitaryCabinet with informationDivisions(a) In the line,(b) In reserve,on the Western Front.Intelligence toshowing thefurnishnumberthe war of Allied
German General 2. The Director of Military Intelligence stated that there wereHeadquarters. indications that the German General  Headquarters were   being i/ &quot;  re-established at Spa, near Liege.3. With reference to War Cabinet 340, Minute tf, and inregard to the points most likely to form the object of a german attack, the Director of Military Intelligence stated that, so far aspresent indications went, the most likely point was just east ofRheims, though it might take place anywhere between Arras andthe Argonne.The Italian Front. 4. The Director of Military Intelligence reported that GeneralFayolle had handed over the command of the French troops in italy to General Maistre, who formerly commanded the Sixth Frenchy  Army at Malmaison.Possible german attack.Greece. 5. The Director of Military Intelligence stated that a telegram had been received stating that the attitude of King Alexander, inregard to the - recent mutinies, had been   most correct, and that     M. Venizelos was dealing with the matter with a firm hand.The Hejaz. - 6. With reference to War Cabinet 340, Minute 1, the Directorof Military Intelligence reported the receipt of further information regarding&quot; the Arab victories at Seil-el-Hasas and El Mezra. Inregard to the former, the Arabs appeared to have achieved an over-whelming victory, the whole of the Turkish force, which numberedabout 800 men, being either killed or captured, with the exceptiony   of 1 officer and 25 men.7. The Director of Military Intelligence reported that, on the31st January, a Turkish train had been blown up by the Arabsbetween Abu Naam and Antar, about 100 miles north of Medina.Subsequent attacks had been made or: Turkish posts in the vicinityy    with good results.:  7&quot; \$)Palestine. 8. The Director of Military Intelligence reported   that  thestandard gauge railway from El Kantara, on the Suez Canal, had reached Ramleh. However, construction had been delayed owing towashouts on the wadis on either side of the town of Gaza. Use wasbeing made of the Turkish 1 &quot;05-metre gauge railway from BeitHanun, some 10 miles north of Gaza, to a junction station on theold French Jaffa-Jerusalem railway, and trains were now being runthrough to Jerusalem. Supplies were now being landed from thesea at Nahr-el-Sukereir, whence a new British railway connectedy    with the main standard gauge railway.Eoumahia. 9. The Director of Military Intelligence reported the receipt, bythe Chief of the Imperial General Staff, of a telegram from GeneralBallard, to the effect that he had seen General Averescu, theCommander-in-Chief of the Roumanian Army, on the 7th February,who had given him to understand that, in the event of GeneralAverescu being concerned in the making of peace terms betweenRoumania and the Central Powers, every effort would be made toprevent guns, munitions, &amp;c, from being handed over to the Central
Powers. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff thought that anyreply to this telegram should be sent by the Foreign Office to sir george Barclay.The Cossacks. 10. The Director of Military Intelligence reported the receipt ofa telegram from General de Candolle, at Rostov-on-Don, stating thatthe situation at that place was becoming increasingly precarious,owing to  the spread of Bolshevism, and that it was likely that/    General Alexeieff would be compelled to retire to Ekaterinodar.Assassination ofRussian Com-mander-in-Chiefat Murmansk.If. The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff reported that he hadreceived a telegram from Murmansk which stated that AdmiralKetlinsky, the Russian Commander-in-Chief at Murmansk, had been shot by two sailors in the street on the 10th February, and had diedshortly afterwards. No further details were known at present, butthe situation was quiet.Cossack Conference &apos; 12. The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff reported that he hadatIma&quot;- received a message &quot;from H.M.S. &quot;Suffolk,&quot; at Vladivostock, which stated that the result of the Cossack Conference at Iman was highlysatisfactory. A resolution, condemning Bolshevik policy andrepudiating attempts to make a separate peace, was carried by42, votes to 4. Die message from H.M.S. &quot; Suffolk &quot; also stated that financial and material assistance was urgently required from theAllies in order to enable the Cossacks to organise a force to establishorder in Eastern Siberia, and that enquiries were being made by theCossacks as to whether the Allies were prepared to give such^      assistance.Submarines. 13. The Deputy  Chief of the Naval Staff reported that a successful attack had been made on an enemy submarine N.W. of cape Grisnez on the 8th February.   Two other attacks on the same date had also been made by destroyers on enemy submarines in the. &apos; Bristol Channel, but it was doubtful if they were successful.Visit of Bolshevik 14. With reference to War Cabinet 34.1, Minute 11, the WarDelegates to Cabinet  had before them telegram No.  358 from Mr. Lindley,..ng an . .  Petrograd, containing a recommendation   by Mr. Lockhart   that,  5 - M. Petroff should be allowed to pay a visit of short duration to^ V/0&apos;     England.The War Cabinet also had before them a memorandum by theHome Office (Paper G.T.-3587) pointing out the undesirability of allowing a Bolshevik agent, who had been interned in this countryfor an offence against the Defence of the Realm Regulations, being allowed to return to England.General Macdonogh stated that his Counter-Espionage Depart-ment felt strongly that it would be a grave danger to allow M. Petroffto return to this country.In this connection attention was drawn to an article in the&quot;Woolwich Pioneer&quot; by M. Litvinoff, given under his official seal,inciting the munition workers at Woolwich to revolution.General Macdonogh informed the Cabinet that he had beeninformed that M. Litvinoff had been endeavouring to tamper withthe discipline of British troops, notably Russian-Canadians.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs undertook to see Mr. Leeper, who acts as the informal agent of communica-tion between the Foreign  Office and M. Litvinoff, with[1365-342] B 2
regard to the actual or implied breach of diplomatic usagerevealed by the issue of such a manifesto by M. Litvinoff.The War Cabinet decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should send a telegram to Mr. Lindley, at Petrograd, informing him of the reasons why His Maiesty&apos;s Government were unwilling to allowM. Petroffto visit this country,and instructed The Home Secretary to warn newspapers that they would be guilty of a breach of the Defence of the Realm Regulationsif they published similar revolutionary propaganda issuedby M. &quot;Litvinoff.In regard to the visit of M. Kameneff, it was understood that avise had already been granted by the British Representatives at petrograd to M. kamenoffs passport to visit this country, and thatthe French Government had agreed to permit M. Kameneff to visitFrance, but intended to keep him under strict surveillance.The War Cabinet decided that It was impracticable to refuse permission to M. Kameneff to visit this country ;and requested The Home Office to keep M. Kameneff under close observation.International 15. The War Cabinet had  before them a Memorandum by labour Conference.   Mr.  Barnes on the subject of a proposed International LabourConference (Paper G.T.-3.554).It was pointed out that, until the Inter-Allied Labour Conference,which was to meet in Paris this week, had come to a definite decision regarding the place and character * of the proposed Intex*-national Labour Conference, it was desirable that the Cabinet shouldhave a free hand, so as to be able to consider the case made outupon its merits, without previous consultation with the AlliedGovernments.The War Cabinet decided that The matter should again be discussed as soon as the results ofthe Inter-Allied Labour Conference had been received.&quot; The MorniDgPost&quot; :Article byLieut.-Col.Repington.16. The attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to an article byLieutenant-Colonel Repington, which had appeared in that morning&apos;sissue of the &quot; Morning Post.&quot; The article in question dealt with questions of military strategy, and with the discussions and conclusions reached at the last meeting of the Supreme WarCouncil at Versailles, and more especially with the creation of aGeneral Reserve. The article appeared to give valuable military information to the enemy, and constituted a definite breach of regulation 18 of the Defence of the Realm Regulations, and also adefiance of the decision of the War Cabinet (War Cabinet 338,Minute 3) as to the undesirability of any reference being made inBritish newspapers regarding the formation or command of aGeneral Inter-Allied Reserve.Lord Derby stated that the article in question was clearly of amost mischievous character. He believed that it had been written from Paris, and that it was clear that Colonel Repingtonhad become acquainted with information of a secret and confidential
character, which had now been made public by the Editor of &quot; the morning Post.&quot;The Director of Military Intelligence stated that he understood the article in question had been, submitted to the Press Bureau onthe previous evening. The Press Bureau had communicated withhim, and Sir Edward Cook had informed him that he had told the editor that the article infringed Regulation 18 under the Defenceof the Realm Act, and ignored the special request issued to the presson the 4th February (Press Bureau, Serial D 621).Sir Edward Cook read to the War Cabinet portions of the article in its original form as first submitted to the Press Bureau, fie had endeavoured to censor it, but its whole character was such thatamendment was practically impossible. He had accordingly returnedit to Mr. Gwynne with a letter conveying the warning abovedescribed. In spite of this fact, the article had appeared in a slightly amended form.The Prime Minister pointed out that this was not the first occasion on which Colonel Repington had written articles for publicationwhich were of the utmost military value to the enemy. Further,in connection with the Cabinet enquiries regarding the Man-power situation, Colonel Repington had written articles, published by the&quot;Morning Post,&quot; containing figures regarding our strength and reserves; and also an article damaging to British interests had beensent by him for publication in America. These articles, togetherwith those by Mr. Lovat Fraser in the &quot; Daily Mail,&quot; had beensubmitted to the Public Prosecutor, who had expressed the viewthat Colonel Repington&apos;s articles constituted a breach of theRegulations, but that it wras doubtful whether it would be desirablethat a prosecution should be undertaken.It was pointed out that the most effective way of dealing withnewspapers which published matter which gave information to theenemy was by the seizure of the printing-press rather than by a prosecution, which was dilatory. Press machinery had been seizedin the case of the Glasgow &quot; Forward &quot; and &quot; The Globe,&quot; and thispolicy could be put into effect by any competent military authority.The War Cabinet requested The Solicitor-General to consult with the Director of public prosecutions, and to submit recommendations at a special meeting of the War Cabinet to be held that afternoon at p.m.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,Februarij 11, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
