<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 238-243</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   February J 918.1141x5)SECRET.WAR  CABINET,   350.Minutes of a&apos; Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onWednesday, February 20, 1918, at 11-30 am.Present :The Right Hon. A. Bonak Law, M.P. (in the, Chair).The Right Hon.  the Earl   Curzon- of j The Right Hon. (1. N. Barnes, M.P.Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.OI.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Mtlnek, IG.C.B., G.C.M.G. IoThe following were also present: The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M., M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(for Minutes 1 to 6).The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby. K.G.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes I to 7).General Sir H. II. Wilson, Iv.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff (for minutes 1 to 7).Major-General Sir W. T. Furze, K.G.B.,D.S.O., Master-General of the Ordnance(for Minute 9).Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, .K.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff.Rear-Admiral Lionel Halsey, C.B.,C.M.G., Third Sea Lord of the Admiralty(for Minutes 11 and 12).Sir Alan G. Anderson, K.B.E., Controller,the Admiralty (for Minutes 11 and 12).disclosure W. Guy Grankt, Director-Generalof Movements and Railways (for minute 7).The Right Hon. T. J. Macnamara, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary to the Admiralty(for Minutes 11 and L2).The Right Hon. Sir Joseph Maclay, Bt.,M.P., Shipping Controller (for minutes and 9).The Right Hon. Lord Rhondda, FoodController (for Minute 9).Mr. U. F. Wintouh, C.B., C.M.G., Perina-nent Secretary, Ministry of Food (for minute 9).The Right Hon. Austen Chamberlain,M.P. (for Minute 9).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minutes 8 and 9).Sir L. Worthington Evans, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary to the Ministry ofMunitions (for Minutes S and 9).Mr. W. T. Layton, C.B.E., Ministry ofMunitions (for Minutes S and 9).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary,Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain E. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.[1365-350]B
Turkish advance in the Caucasus.1. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that theTurks were pushing along the Black Sea littoral, and had takenTrebizond.Salonica.2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that,whereas it had been estimated latterly that the Germans hadthree divisions on the Salonica front, it was now believed thattheir forces were reduced to one and a half or one and two-thirdsdivisions. The result of this was a numerical equality betweenthe two sides on that front.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointed out that,if there was truth in the many rumours that Roumania has an understanding with the enemy, and in the story, published in thepress that day, that the Bolsheviks had made peace with Germany,very large numbers of Austrians and Germans would be released for operations on the Balkan front.General Wilson stated that this question had been examined at Versailles. The railways limited the numbers that could bebrought to the Balkan front, but there was little doubt that sufficient troops could be brought to bear to drive the Allies outof their present line if the Bulgarians were disposed to fight. Theresult of the Versailles enquiry, however, had been to establish the belief that the Allies, even if they lost SaJonica, would be able to deny Old Greece to the enemy.Palestine.3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported thatGeneral Allenby had advanced four or five miles eastwards, andwas established on the summit of the hills which sloped towardsthe Jordan and the Dead Sea. This movement might be considered as a prelude to further operations.Bussia: japanese intervention.-3I4. With reference to War Cabinet 346, Minute 9, the WarCabinet had a short discussion on the question of the proposedJapanese action in Siberia, in regard to which a number ofimportant memoranda and telegrams had been circulated.It was pointed out that the situation was changing from da)-to day, and that it was difficult to take a decision at the moment.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs gave a. brief account of the present position. It was no longer a question of bringing help to the Cossacks by means of Japanese intervention,as it was now clear that the Cossacks no longer existed as an efficient fighting force. There were two principal theories uponthe subject of Japanese action: one was the French, which saw in japan the only means of countering German influence in Russia;the other was the American, which, apart from jealousy andsuspicion of Japanese enterprises, considered the Japs as the-worst possible agents of the Allies in Russia.The War Cabinet agreed that the question should be brought up at an early date, when the Prime Minister was ableto attetid the meeting.The western front: possible german Attack.5. With reference to War Cabinet 347, Minute 2, the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff, in reply to a question, stated thatthe General Sta,ff had no information to confirm the rumours ofan imminent German attack on the Western front.
3WG 350Poison Gas.s6,A ir Raids on london : Use of&quot;Gas Bombs.6. With reference to War Cabinet 336, Minute 6, attention was drawn to the rumours of a new and deadly poison gas whichthe Germans had in store for their offensive. It was also statedthat the composition of this gas had been communicated through a neutral country. The formula had been given, and it was-con-si dered that our masks were more likely to be proof against itthan those used by the Germans, as their masks were inferior toours, and that from this it might be inferred that the enemy wouldnot risk the use of a gas against which they could not protect theirown troops in case it were blown back upon them by the wind.it was also pointed out that the use of gas bombs on london had been mentioned as a possibility.The Secretary informed the War Cabinet that expert opinionhad been consulted earlier in the war, and was divided on the sub-ject of the probable efficacy of such a form of attack.The War Cabinet decided that It was desirable that they should hear at an early date theviews of General Thuillier on these questions.Italian Labour forthe Western Front.7. With reference to War Cabinet 328, Minute 9, the WarCabinet had before them a Memorandum bv Lord Milner (paper g.T.-3590).The Secretary of State for War pointed out that we had undertaken a great deal, of extra work behind the front. Heinstanced salvage, and the cultivation of land placed at our dis-posal by the French Government. The value of Italian labourwas that it would enable us to dispense with the importation of chinese coolies. Each coolie saved would give us an Americansoldier. Labour must be found,-and it could not be got in England.The French had given us 3,000 or 4.000 of the Italian labourersthey had secured.Questioned as to the expected report on the utilisation oflabour in France, Lord Derby stated that Sir E. Pearson would shortly have a report ready.Sir Guy Garnet pointed out that we should not rely on theFrench to pass on to us their surplus of Italian workmen, as the type of men we required was of the category of the semi-skilled.We should endeavour to select the men allotted to us.The War Cabinet therefore decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should send atelegram from the Prime Minister to Signor Orlando,in the form drafted by Lord Milner and appended tohis Memorandum (Paper G.T.-3590). with the additionthat, if the Italian Government agreed in principle, wewould  at  once  send someone  to make(Appendix).The selection of the for War.arrangementsagent was left to the Secretary of StateSupply of Raw-Materials froruSpain.&quot;5[1365-350]8. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinistry of Munitions (Paper G.T.-3501) and a Memorandumby the Ministry of Shipping (Paper G.T.-3632), in regard to thesupply of raw materials from Spain.Sir L. Worthington Evans stated that the shortage of coalrequired by the mines and railways in Spain was very acute. TheRio Tinto Company, which is the largest producer of pyrites,would be obliged to close down in about two weeks unless steps were taken to improve the position. Before the war, outwardfreights from Cardiff to Huelva were about 4s. Qd. per ton; nowthey were over 400s.; but, in spite of this rise, shipping was notattracted. In fact there was to-day no market, except in thetechnical sense, because, while there was competition in demandB 2
there was no competition in supply. The Rio Tinto Company saythat they cannot afford to pay 400s. per ton, and they therefore ask for a subsidy from the Government in order to enable themto carry on their business. This company maintain that theycannot ask America to pay more, because of their standing con-tracts in America, which would have to be broken thereby.Sir Joseph Mac-lay said that, while Spain wanted coal, sherefused to send her own tonnage to convey it. Spain will notsend a single ship, if she can avoid it, because she hopes to induceus to send our British ships into the trade and so enable her to employ her tonnage in safe waters. &apos; Sir Joseph Maclay further pointed out that if we were to. give special accommodation to an english company, like the Rio Tinto, there would, in his opinion,be trouble with the Spanish Government, who would plead for equal treatment for Spanish interests. He advised the Govern-ment to remain firm and not to give special facilities, because inthis way our pressure would, before long, bring the Spanish ratesdown and their vessels into the trade.In this connection the Chancellor of the Exchequer drew theattention of the War Cabinet to a telegram from Sir, A.Hardinge, Madrid, No. 200, dated the 19th February, to the effectthat the German Ambassador at Madrid had given a verbalmessage to the Spanish Minister for Foreign Affairs that theGermans would reluctantly torpedo any Spanish ship tradingdirectly or indirectly with the Allies. The Chancellor of theExchequer pointed out that the question was whether we should place British ships in the trade or not.) Owing to the fact that the Foreign Office were not repre-sented, the War Cabinet asked Lord Milner to decide the question later in the day, in con-sultation with Lord Robert Cecil, Sir Joseph Maclay,and Sir L. Worthington Evans.Munitions Budget 9. The War Cabinet had before them two Memoranda byfor 1918: Steel. Mr. Churchill (Papers G.T.-3034 and G.T.-3481), and aMemorandum by Mr. Chamberlain (Paper G.T.-3126), in regardto the Munitions Budget of 1918 and the placing of orders inexcess of tonnage allocated.On the 15th February (War Cabinet 347, Minutes 11 and13) the War Cabinet, in adopting the Report of the restriction of Imports Committee, agreed &quot; that the Munitions Budget shouldbe sanctioned on the reduced basis of 10,000,000 tons import, andthat the Department should have authority to place orderssufficiently in excess of this amount to make sure that every advantage may be taken of the accidents of shipment,&quot;Mr. Chamberlain said that he was afraid of advising theCabinet to spend dollars on goods for which there might be notonnage available. If there were resources in excess of our needs,then it would be a wise and proper course to place our orders inexcess of available tonnage. But this was not the case. Theposition as regards the Inter-Ally Council was different. It was never certain that the assurances of Mr. Crosby in the matterof credits would receive the approval of the United States Govern-ment. As regards food, the difficulties were not so great in finding dollars, because orders were for &quot; spot &quot; purchases, placedand delivered within a few weeks. The munitions programme,however, was more difficult, and Mr. Crosby wanted theprogramme of actual commitments to be kept separate from what were proposals rather than commitments.Sir L. Worthington Evans said that when Mr. Churchillagreed to the reduction (War Cabinet 347, Minute 11) in imports,he asked for authority to order goods in excess of tonnagebecause his experience had shown him that actual shipping
Inter-Ally Council: 10. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum fromPurchases and Mr. Crosby to the Prime Minister (Paper G.T.-3616) in whichFinance. Mr. Crosby asked that instructions might be given to the various departments to &quot; reply to enquiries made on behalf of the council for information concerning stocks.&quot;The War Cabinet instructed The Secretary to circulate copies of Mr. Crosby&apos;s Memo-randum to the Departments concerned, with the request that the wishes of Mr. Crosby in this respect should bemet. as far as possible.The Naval Pro- 11. With reference to War Cabinet 325, Minute 2, the Wargramme for 1919.     Cabinet had under  consideration an Admiralty Memorandum(Paper G.T.-3553) dealing with the proposed programme of war-ship and auxiliary construction for 1919, from the point of viewof steel and wages, the latter giving an indication of the man-. power required for the carrying out of the programme as com-H8b pared with that for pervious programmes.The Admiralty Controller drew attention to the WarCabinet ruling as set out in War Cabinet 347, Minute 11, underwhich the Admiralty were authorised to carry out their existing programme, on the basis of 2,100,000 tons, without alteration.Sir Alan Anderson mentioned that, out of the total amount ofsteel required for the 1919 programme, only 90,000 tons was required for shipbuilding other than cargo vessels, or vessels to beemployed either directly or indirectly for the protection of tradeagainst submarine attack, and that most of that amount would berequired for light cruisers. He added that of the total Admiraltyrequirements of steel during 1918 not more than 10,000 tons wouldbe expended in vessels which would not complete before the end of1919. He further mentioned that it was not proposed to expendany steel during 1918 on the battle cruiser included inProgramme A.The War Cabinet approved &quot; Warship Programme A.&quot;Acquisition of the chilean Battleship&quot; AlmiranteCochrane.&quot;12. The War Cabinet had under consideration a proposal bythe Admiralty (Paper G.T.-3607) for the acquisition of the battleship &quot; Almirante Cochrane,&quot; which was now building atfacilities were greater than those estimated. For instance, inJanuary last the estimated shipping allocated was 40,000 tons,whereas 75,000 tons were actually lifted. In ordering now whatwas contemplated to be ordered later on, no addition was beingmade, in the long run, to the programme. The amount in disputewas the difference between 270,000 tons asked for by the Ministryof Munitions, and 90,000 tons authorised by the American Board,or a balance of 180,000 tons. Tn the event of there being a break-down in tonnage for American shipments, the Ministry ofMunitions could divert other tonnage allocated to them, e.g., forcarrying iron ore which had not been paid for, to fetch the steel from America.Lord Rhondda urged that in no case should the food positionbe affected by the question of dollar credits. Every estimatefurnished by the Wheat Commission showed that the cerealposition grew worse and worse. If, for want of grain, the ships were obliged to bring meat, then the dollar value of the cargoeswould become greater.The War Cabinet decided To authorise  the Ministry of Munitions to place further orders up to 180,000 tons of steel.
Elswick for the Chilean Government, for the purpose of convertingher into a seaplane carrier, the total cost of acquiring and com-completing the vessel being approximately 3,000,0007.The Third Sea Lord pointed out that the -ChileanAuthorities had been approached and the Chilean minister had stated that his Government were willing to transfer the ship in consideration of the Admiralty supplying them with someaeroplanes during the next 12 or 18 months. He wished that thesupply of such should not be deferred until after the end of thewar. He added that the Chilean Government do not, however,make the transfer of the &quot;Almirante Cochrane &quot; conditional upon compliance with this request.The War Cabinet approved the acquisition of the &quot;AlmiranteCochrane.&apos;&apos;2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W&apos;.,February 20, 1918.APPENDIX.Telegram from Prime Minister to Signor Orlando,THERE is a question of great urgency which I wished to bring before yournotice during our recent conferences, but the number of important matters which wehad to discuss did not leave time for it. I refer to the shortage of military labour forthe great amount of work which has still to be done in strengthening our defensivelines in Northern France. As you know, the British troops have been engaged in very heavy and continuous lighting on that front for months past. They are threatened with a heavy attack by the enemy in the near future, and under thesecircumstances it is not possible to detach as large a number for work behind thelines as is urgently required to make the necessary preparations. I would thereforemake a very earnest appeal to you to assist us during the next few months with as many labour battalions as you can possibly spare. I am aware that you are alreadygenerously assisting the French for a similar purpose. Our need is no less greatthan theirs, and, having regard to the exceptional efforts we are being called upon tomake, and gladly make to the extreme extent of our powers, to assist Italy insupplying her imperative wants in grain and coal, I feel justified in begging you tohelp us in respect of our no less urgent want of labour. We should, of course, beprepared to pay whatever you consider right in the way of wages, and to makeample provision for their rations and all other requirements. If, as we hope, you agree to the principle we will at once send someone to Italy to arrange about details.The matter is very pressing, and I hope you majT be able to give if early andfavourable consideration.February 20, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
