<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 250-255</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;vfr6&apos;6io&apos;v of MiHtarylDperaEionsr[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majssty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   February 1918.SKCUKT.13WAR CABINET, 352.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Friday, February 22, 1918, at 12*30/?.m.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the   Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG, G.C.S.L, G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. G. ,\\ Barnes, M.P.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (for Minutes 1 to 7)., \     The Right Hon. the   Earl oe Derby,v* KG, G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War (for Minutes 5 to 7).General Sin IT. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief  of  the Imperial   General   Staff(for Minutes I to 7).Lieutenant-General Sir C. P. N. Mace k ad y.K.C.B., K.C.M.G., Adjutant-General tothe Forces (for Minutes 9, 10, and 11).Brigadier-General B. E. W. Childs,C.M.G., Director of: Personal Supplies(for Minute 10).Sir Sam Fay, Director of Movements (for minute 9).The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies (for Minutes 1to 10).Mr.  W.  A.  S.  Hewins,  M.P.,   Under--lS&quot; Secretary of State for the Colonies (for minute 10).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade (for minute 9).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, KG, M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minutes 10 to 12).Mr.  J.  Lamb,   C.B.,   Assistant  Under-Secretary of  State   for Scotland   (for minutes 10 and 11).Rear-Admiral G. P. W. Hope, C.B.,Deputy First Sea Lord (for Minutes 1fo 8). &quot;The  Right  Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart,Shipping Controller (for Minute 9).Sir A. Norman Hill, Ministry of Shipping(for Minute 9).The Right Hon. T. J. Macnamara, LL.D.,M.P.,   Financial   Secretary,   Admiralty(for Minute II).Mr. E. P. Thursfield, Law Department,Admiralty (for Minute 10).Surgeon-General  J.   P. McNabb, deputy director-General   of   the   Navy   (for minute 10).The Right Hon. W. Hayes Fisher, M.P.,President, Local Government Board (for minutes 10 and 11).Mr. I. G. Gibbon, Local GovernmentBoard (for Minute 10 and 11).The Right Hon. A. H. Illinoworth, M.P.,Postmaster-General (for Minute 12).Sir Horace 0. Monro, K.C.B., permanent secretary, Local Government Board (for minutes 10 and 11).The   Right Hon.  Sir  A.  C.  Geddes,K.C.B.,   M.P.,   Minister   of   NationalService (for Minute 9).Major P. Lloyd Greame, M.C., Secretary,Ministry   of    National    Service    (for minute&quot; 9).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Colonel W. Dally. Jones, C.M.G., Acting Secretary.Captain E. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain the HonAW. Ormsby Gore, Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burois, Assistant Secretary.[1365-852]B
Palestine1. THE Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that our troops had captured Jericho on the 21st instant and that cavalrypatrols now covered the town northward and as far eastward as theRiver Jordan.   The enemy had retired to a position east of the&apos; Jordan, which was now in flood.East Africa. 2. The Chief of the Imperial  General  Staff  reported   thatGeneral von Lettovvhacl fallen back into Portuguese conn try withoutlighting.   General Wilson said that the nature of this country was absolutely unknown, and he thought it possible that von Lettow&apos;sw &apos; force misht now be starved out.Bussia.3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that Minskhad been taken by the Germans.British Division. 4. With reference to War Cabinet 351, Minute 10, the Chief ofErontf       n the Imperial General General Staff stated that he had received a&apos;     &apos; telegram from General Plumer, dated the 21st instant, which stated&quot; / that General Diaz was rather perturbed about the withdrawal oftwo British divisions from Italy. General Wilson said that atelegram had already beeu sent to General Alfieri expressing regretfor the manner in which these two divisions were ordered away from Italy, and saying that they would form part of the allied general Reserve in France. He thought that this statement wouldsatisfv General Diaz.3..The Western Front: 5. With reference to War Cabinet 345, Minute 2, the Chief of transfer of the Imperial General Staff reported that one more German divisionGerman Divisions, y had arrived on the Western front, making a total of 179.British Superiority. 6. In reply to a question, the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff stated that, as regards heavy guns and aeroplanes, we were ina superiority to the Germans on the Western front, but he feared that by May our superiority in heavy guns would be lost.The War Cabinet instructed- G35Japan:Propaganda.,The Chief of the Imperial General Staff to prepare a comparativeestimate of the numbers of men and guns possessed by theGermans and the Allies on the Western front.7. The attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to telegramNo. 154, dated 19th February, PUS, in which a request was madeby Sir C. Greene, at Tokio, that information regarding the general attitude in this country towards the war might be furnished him inorder to counteract the impression which was gaining ground in japan that Great Britain was at her last gasp, Sir C. Greenesuggested that Commander Josiah Wedgwood, who was due toarrive in Tokyo on the 25th instant, should explain the real situation by means of an interview whilst he was in Japan, in order to try and dispel the unfortunate impression which the Japanese had gained.It was suggested that perhaps Commander Wedgwood wouldnot be a very suitable person for this purpose.The War Cabinet requested The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to send a telegram to Sir 0. Greene, giving him very full information asregards the situation in this country, which would enablethe Ambassador to counteract the impression in Japanthat England is suffering from war-weariness.
WC 352Submarines.8.The Deputy First Sea Lord reported as followsinstant, the steamshipsubmarine, which she(a.) In. the Mediterranean, on the 20th&quot; Eleric&quot; sighted and fired at aclaims to have hit.(6.) On the 21st instant the Italian transport &quot; Memfi,&quot; with750 troops on board, was attacked by a submarine whichfired two torpedoes, both of which missed.   The escort&apos;: Ginocchio &quot; towed a mine which exploded and broughty great quantities of bubbles and wreckage to the surface.Transport Workers&apos;Battalions.i 39. With reference to War Cabinet 287, Afinute 3, the WarCabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Ministry of Shipping(Paper G.T.-3534) and a letter from the Port and Transit ExecutiveCoin committee (Paper G.T.-3500), from which it, appeared that therewere two questions for consideration : (a.) Whether the strength of the battalions should be increasedby 5,000 men.(b.) Whether the War Office should nominate representatives to serve on the local committees.Sir Norman Hill outlined the general position as regards the(\ .      present strength of the battalions.    The total strength was about10,300 men. Of these there were nominally some 750 kept at head-quarters, and 750 off duty for hospital or other reasons, leaving a balance of about 8,800 men for work at the ports, on thr- railways,and on the canals. The development of the convoy system had led,by the arrival of ships in batches, to far more spasmodic andfluctuating work at the ports than was the case in peace time. Asa result, many demands were made upon the Port and TransitCommittee which could not be met. One of the best results of theformation of the Transport Workers Battalions had been the. extrastimulus to greater exertion on the part of civilian labour. Thesebattalions had succeeded where the Dockers&apos; Battalions had failed,because the latter had been regarded with suspicion by the civiliani lockers.Sir Joseph Maclay said that he attached the greatest value r,othe work of the Transport Workers&apos; Battalions, and strongly urged,in view of the convoy system of arrivals at the ports, the need for increasing the battalions by 5,000 men.The Adjutant-General said that the War Office did not take&apos;&apos;(S- the same view of the matter as Sir Norman Hill.   Men in thesebattalions formed part of the Home Defence Force, but the Field-Marshal Commanding could not regard them as being of any use as soldiers in the event of an invasion. In such a case they wouldbe required to clear traffic away to the West, and could not be relied upon to light. They were, therefore, not a military potentialasset.On the other hand, it was pointed out that, if an invasion tookplace, traffic would certainly have to be cleared westward, and asthe work could only be doue by soldiers the Transport Workers&apos;Battalions would be very useful.As regards the appointment of War Office representatives toserve on the local committees. Sir Norman Hill referred to the workof the battalions in private sidings and on railway premises in theBradford and Sheffield areas. In both these areas the experimenthad been completely successful. By the employment of a very limited number of men from the battalions, blocks had been avoidedand the flow of traffic maintained. In view of this success atSheffield and Bradford, the War Office had been asked to nomi-nate representatives to serve on the loeal committees. Represen-tatives of the Railway Executive Committee and of the NationalUnion of Railwaymen had been appointed for each local committee,
but the War Office had declined to appoint its representatives. Ata Lull meeting of the Port and Transit Executive Committee recently,the representatives of labour said that they attached the- greatest importance to both, the increase of numbers by 5,000, and. the nomi-nation of War Office representatives.The Adjutant-General said that, in the opinion of the WarOffice, it was no part of the duties of a soldier to give an opinion onthe efficiency or otherwise of civilian labour, but that, in order tomake the scheme a success and satisfy the wishes of Labour, theWar Office would agree to nominate representatives to act under instructions from the Army Council, and so enable the work to beextended to railways outside the Bradford and Sheffield areas.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) The strength of the Transport Workers&apos; Battalions shouldbe increased by 5,000 men ;(b.) The War Office should nominate representatives to serve on the local Committees.Veneral Diseases. 10. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (Paper G-.T.-3,598), asking for^o&apos; 7 ,    the sanction of the War Cabinet to a new Regulation under the. r       Defence of the Realm Act, making it an offence for a woman suffer-&apos; ing from venereal disease&apos; in a communicable form to have sexualintercourse with any member of His Majesty&apos;s forces.Mr. Long stated that the matter arose out of a recommendationof the Imperial War Conference, .1917 (Resolution No. 24), and that*the Dominion Governments were very anxious that steps should betaken to stop the spread of venereal infection among their troops inthis country. The Royal Commission on Venereal Diseases proved that in a number of cases it would be possible to identify the women who constituted the chief danger, many of whom did not belong tothe professional prostitute class. At present, there was no means ofdealing with tliem.It was pointed out to the War Cabinet that objection to the regulation might be raised in Parliament on the ground that the penalties imposed applied only to women and not to men. It mightbe possible that a demand would be put forward that the offenceshould be made reciprocal to both sexes. The difficulty was that itwas not possible to deal with the male civilian population by meansof the Defence of the Realm A(;t. The Army took the view that itwas undesirable to differentiate between the soldier and the civilian.If the Regulation were to apply to male persons, it should thereforeapply to the civilian as well as to the soldier or sailor.The Adjutant-General pointed out that it was an offence underthe Army Act for a soldier to conceal, venereal disease, and that,once it was established that he had venereal disease, he was kept in hospital until cured.Mr. Long pointed out that, in the case of syphilis, there was aninfective period between the; time when the man contracted the disease and the time when the disease could be definitely diagnosed.It was during this period that the disease was spread. He addedthat there was a strong feeling outside the Army that the Regulationshould be applied to male as well as female persons.The War Cabinet approved the Regulation and requested The Secretary of State for War to give the question of its extension to include male persons in the armed forces of. the Crown his further consideration, in the event of thequestion being raised in Parliament.
Representation ofthe People Act:Qualifying Period.11. With reference to War Cabinet 339, Minute 8, the WarCabinet had before them a Memorandum by the President of theLocal Government Board (Paper G.T.-3675).The proposal contained therein was approved.Payment ofConscientiousObjectors in theEmploy of thePost Office.12. With reference to War Cabinet 298, Minute 18, the WarCabinet had before them a Memorandum by Mr. Barnes (paper g.T.-3476).The War Cabinet decided that No change should be made in the present procedure.(Initialled) A B L2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,February 22, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
