<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 286-289</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JIMLiJocmnent ^ the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]      137Printed for the War Cabinet.   March 1918.SECRET. . ,--- i       % LIWAR CABINET, 358.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Monday, March 4, 1918, at 12 noon.The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. -1. C.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, CM.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forAVar.General Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B.,K.C.M.G., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, K.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. S. Amery, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain E. Abraham, Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.The Western Front: 1. WITH reference to War Cabinet 357, Minute 2, the Chief of possible German the Imperial General Staff reported that the Germans appeared toAttack. be concentrating at two places on the Western front, viz. : (a.) As already reported, opposite the Arras-Peronne front,where 35 divisions were concentrated as compared with(q/z , a previous 9 divisions,i 3  / (b.) In front of the French, opposite the Soissons-Rheims front.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that the totalnumber of German divisions on the Western front was now 183.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff did not attach special importance to the German raid on the Portuguese front, reported in last Saturday&apos;s communique.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to ascertain^yZ/ whether the counter-attack mentioned in the communique(w *      / had been made by British or Portuguese troops.[1365-358]
2. With reference to War Cabinet 357, Minute 3. the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff reported that the Executive Committeefor the Control of Reserves was meeting that afternoon at Versaillesto settle the question of the transfer of divisions from the Italian tothe Western front.Poland. 3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported the receiptof information that the Poles had crossed the frontier and had placed themselves under the orders of the Regency Council, which   was tantamount to joining the enemy.The Italian Front:Withdrawal ofBritish Divisions.Russia:Japanese Inter-vention.y4. With reference to War Cabinet 35-1, Minute 6, the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs stated that the United States had agreedto Japanese intervention in Siberia, subject to the proviso that they,in accordance with their usual custom, would not subscribe to ajoint declaration of the Allies, although they would subsequentlymake a declaration of their own, supporting the Allied policy.Mr. Balfour said that he had drafted a telegram to Tokyo, statingthat the United States of America had consented, and that the nextmove was with Japan. He had also drafted his idea of the sort ofproclamation the Allies should make. The telegram, he hoped,would be sent that afternoon.Loss of steamship&quot; Calgariari.&quot;5. The First Sea Lord reported that the &quot;Calgarian&quot; was torpedoed on the 1st March, about 8 miles North-West of RathlinIsland, and that only 49 men were missing out of a total of 600 ony   board.Stornoway TownHall.y(.5. The First Sea Lord reported that Stornoway Town Hall hadbeen completely gutted by fire on the ;2nd instant, but that it was hoped that all the important documents of the naval office establishedthere had been saved.Submarines.7) Ay-7. The First Sea Lord stated that the &quot; Rutherglen &quot; reportedthat she had rammed a submarine 12 miles South of Holyhead onthe 2nd instant.   It was feared that this submarine might have beenj  one of our own out on patrol.Murmansk,yyyy18. The First Sea Lord read a telegram from the Rear-admiral commanding at Murmansk, which stated that the local Soviet hadreceived a telegram from M. Trotzki, saying that peace negotiations had apparently broken off and that measures were being taken todefend Petrograd to the last drop of blood, it was the duty of theSoviet to do everything they could to defend the Murman line, andordering them to co-operate with Allied Missions in everything.The local Soviet communicated this telegram to the french representative and the Rear-Admiral at Murmansk, and suggestedthat the executive command of the armed forces under the supreme command of the Council of WorkmeiPs and Soldiers&apos; Deputiesshould be vested in three persons, one of whom would be appointedby the Council, and the other two would be British and Frenchofficers. The Soviet also asked that the British and French should provide armed force, equipment, and stores for the defence ofMurmansk as far as possible. Before the receipt of this telegram the Admiralty had decided to reinforce the Rear-admiral commanding &quot;at Murmansk with a cruiser. The French had undertaken to do the same, and Admiral Sims had made a similarproposal to his Government for consideration.
v to any Russian forces against the Germans.Bombing of Open 9- With reference to War Cabinet 353, Minute 7, the WarTowns. Cabinet had a further short discussion on the subject of air raids onopen towns.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs stated that he had.y &quot;j^CTl - replied to the communication received from the Spanish ambassador in the sense that Great Britain had always deprecated this form of warfare, and were quite prepared to consider any proposals theGermans had to make on the subject.It was suggested that a public declaration should be made, as itwas easily possible to show that the Germans were the first to startraiding open towns.   Some doubt being expressed on this point The Secretary was instructed to investigate the matter, with the aid of the Historical Section of the Committee of ImperialDefence, and to report to the War Cabinet at an early date.Leakage of 10. The attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to the factInformation. t]iat tjie &quot;Manchester Guardian&quot; had published information which,/ though incorrect in detail, was substantially similar to that contained -zo-&apos;- in &quot;War Cabinet 353, Minute 7.   The Spanish Minister had corn-plained to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs of this leakage.Belief of Higher ] 1.  The Secretary of State for War stated that tiie ArmyCommand. Council wished to establish a flow of promotion in the British Expe-ditionary Force. It was felt that it would be very hard, in the eventof certain commanders being removed from their posts without any reason being assigned for removing them except to help promotion,that they should suddenly be reduced from full to half-pay.Lord Derby said that it was proposed shortly to bring home eightcorps commanders, now in France. Two commands at home would shortly become vacant. He asked the authorisation of the WarCabinet to retain all eight officers on full pay for three months athome, after which they should then revert to half-pay if not againrequired to hold commands in France, or at home.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was in agreementwith this proposal, but, as it involved a departure from the usual&apos; Treasury practice, he had thought it necessary to obtain WarCabinet sanction.The War Cabinet agreed to this proposal.3 WG 358The Secretary of State for War read a letter from the french military Attache on this subject.The first Sea Lord then read a draft of the instructions he proposed to send to the Rear-Admiral at Murmansk, which statedthat it was impossible to send troops to reinforce the garrison at murmansk, but that one cruiser from Great Britain, one from france, and possibly one from iimerica, were on their way to that port. The Admiral was not to undertake operations against theBolsheviks except in a case of extreme urgency, and the Rear-Admiral was requested to state what, in his view, would constitutesuch a case.The War Cabinet decided that -The Admiralty should inform the Rear-Admiral that we cannotsend land forces ; that naval reinforcements are coming;and that he should be authorised to land the troops if, inhis judgment, any useful assistance could be given by them
12. With, reference to the transport of six American divisions toFrance, the Secretary of State for War stated that he was in com-munication with Lord Reading on this subject, and would be glad ifthe War Cabinet would postpone its discussion until he had receivedfurther particulars from Lord Reading.2, Whitehall Oar dens, S.W.,.,   March 4, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
