<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/5/0 images: 366-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.printed for the War Cabinet.   March .1.918.14WAR CABINET, 370.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S. W.,on Friday, March 22, J 918, at 11-30 a.m.The  Right Hon.   the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the &quot;Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.PLieutenant-General the Right Hon. 0. 0.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (for Minutes 1 to 19).The Right Ffon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes 1 to 19).General Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B.,D.S.O., Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff (for Minutes 1 to 19).The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D., M.P.,Minister of Reconstruction (for Minutes20 and 21).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minutes 20 and21).Sir D. J. Shackleton, K.C.B., Secretary,Ministry of Labour (for Minutes 20 and21).Admiral Sir R. E. Wbmyss, K.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff (for Minutes20 and 21).The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Gbddbs,K.C.B., M.P., Minister for -NationalService (for Minutes 20 and 21).Major P. Lloyd Greame, M.C., Secretary,Ministry&apos; of National Service (for minutes 20 and 21).Mr. F. G. Kellaway, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Munitions (for minutes 20 and 21).Sir Stephenson Kent, K.C.B., Ministryof Munitions (for Minutes 20 and 21).The Right Hon. A. H. Illtngworth, M.P.,Postmaster-General (for Minute 20).Sir T. L. Heath, K.C.B., K.C.V.O., joint permanent Secretary. Treasury (for minute 20).    -Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Wilson, C.M.G., D.S.0.,M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F1. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.[1365-370]B
The Western Front:German Attack.y1. WITH reference to War Cabinet 369, Minute 1, the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff reported that prisoners from seventeenGerman divisions which had taken part in the attack had beenobtained. In the course of the discussion some doubt was expressed as to whether these were additional to some twenty other divisions which had been identified. General Wilson said that the germans had a large number of divisions in reserve, and that it might reasonably be expected that a roulemenl would start that night oron the following day. The attack had been on a front of from80 to 85 kilom., from the Scarpe to the Oise, and General Wilsonsaid that, as far as he could ascertain, the whole of the front had fallen back from the outpost line to the battle position. The battleposition consisted of a series of posts, villages, &amp;c, which were at a distance varying from a few hundred to a few thousand yards inrear of the original front line trenches. He pointed out that the battle zoue was very strongly defended, and that, except in places where the front line and the battle line were 4,000 to 5,000 yardsapart, there were very few guns in position. He consequentlyhoped that the losses in guns were not very heavy; In certainplaces, which were not yet very clearly defined, the enemy appearedto have made lodgments in the battle zone, although there wasno information that these lodgments were of any depth. general wilson also stated that there was a very large amount of wireprotection in the battle zone. Reports had been received givinginformation that the enemy casualties were very heavy, but noparticulars had yet been received as regards our own casualties.No information was yet available to enable a definite judgment tobe formed as to bur own position, as the reports must necessarily,at present, be of a very conflicting character. Information receivedup to now, however, gave no cause for anxiety.information byLiaison Officer.suggested that a service of liaison2. The Prime Ministerofficers should be established, between General Headquarters andthe Chief of the Imperial. General Staff, in order- that the WarCabinet might receive more detailed information as to the course ofevents.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to consultG eneral Trenchard, with a Anew to a liaison officer reportingto General Wilson daily.&apos;German general headquarters.3 Tire Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that theGerman General Headquarters had been definitely located at Spa.Transfer of Britishand french divisions from italian to FrenchFront.4. With reference to War Cabinet 366, Minute 11 (4) (6), theChief of tfie Imperial General Staff reported that he had received atelegram from General Rawlinson with reference to the transfer ofAllied divisions to France from Italy. General Rawlinson, GeneralBliss, and General Foch all considered that now was an opportune moment to transfer two Italian, two French, and one british division, which would be the second British division transferred,from the Italian front to France. General Giardino was of opinionthat the two Italian divisions should be transferred now, and thatthe cpaestion of the transfer of the French and British divisions should be considered at a later date. M. Clemenceau had advised thetransfer of all five divisions. The Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff advised the War Cabinet that the two Italian divisions shouldbe brought to France at once, followed by the two French, and finally the British, divisions. His object in bringing the Italiansfirst was to avoid a controversy with the Italian Government. TheItalian divisions, on arrival in France, would be able to relieve two british or French divisions in the line.
The War Cabinet agreed with the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff that two Italian, two French, and one british divisions should be withdrawn in that order, and instructed The Chief of the Imperial General Staff to notify the supreme war Council at Versailles to that effect.Allied general reserve.3-Zeppelin going to egypt,5. With reference to War Cabinet 306, Minute 11 (a), the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff said that the Executive War board had decided that the Italian quota to the General Reserve should consist of four divisions.6. With reference to War Cabinet 368, Minute 5, the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff reported that a Zeppelin had been seenthree miles north of Port Said, lie was of opinion that the basefrom which it operated was in Macedonia.Camouflage.7. With reference to War Cabinet 366, Minute 2, the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff stated that he had seen Mr. Solomon onthe subject of German camouflage, but that he did not consider thatMr. SolomoiFs information was correct.Man-Power :Comparison ofBritish andGerman Strengtli3.-3 C.8. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to lay before the War Cabinet a paper giving details as regards thestrength of the British and German forces and their reserves ofman-power, and also stating the prospects of the belligerents in theevent of the present attack on the Western front continuing for afew days more at its present intensity. He was of opinion that the attack would develop into a long-drawn battle deliberately intended for a trial of strength, in order that a decisive result might be arrived at.Miners.3.9. The Prime Minister stated that a miners&apos; deputation had visited him on the previous day with reference to the comb-out, he informed the War Cabinet that he had considered it his duty to speak very plainly to the deputation which he had received, and heannounced that he had just received news that the Miners&apos; executive had decided to accept the comb-out after hearing an explanation of the military situation from the Director of Military Operations.Congestion in french Ports and railways.10. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff, referring to a discussion which had taken place at a meeting of the Supreme WarCouncil in regard to the state of congestion in the French ports,stated that General Nash had verified the information which he had given, but which M. Clemenceau had refused to believe. this information had been communicated to M. Clemenceau, and it wouldbe found necessary to modify the whole of the programme whichhad been proposed for the landing of United States troops.Zeppelin Raids on great Britain.--i^.-Q-/LI. With reference to War Cabinet. 368, Minute 9, the Secretaryof State for War reported that the aeroplane squadrons for thedefence of the East Coast had been increased by 140 machines. Onthe occasion of the first of the recent Zeppelin raids, the machines had been unable to go up owing to fog. On the occasion of thesecond raid they had driven off the enemy without bringing onedown.
Bombardment of dunkirk, and a naval Engagement.12. The First Sea Lord reported that a force oil Germantorpedo-boat destroyers bombarded Dunkirk on the morning of the2J st instant, and withdi-evv at once. Two British and three Frenchdestroyers slipped cable aud chased, but apparently fell in with another division of torpedo-boat, destroyers and engaged them.One large German destroyer was hit by a torpedo, and onerammed by a British destroyer, which was afterwards torpedoed,but arrived safely in harbour. Two other German destroyers were stated to have been torpedoed aud sunk, and anothertorpedo-boat had been sunk by gunfire. Survivors were picked up, also papers containing valuable information as to the attack.Our casualties were not heavy.Bombardment ofOstend.Submarines.13. The First Sea Lord reported that Ostend was bombarded&quot;by H.M.S. &quot; Terror&quot; on 21st March, with satisfactory results.14. The First Sea Lord stated that a British airship, operating from Flamborough Head, had bombed an enemy submarine, andthat one bomb was observed to have struck her stern.Shipping Losses.Norway:german submarines in territorial Waters15. Attention was drawn to the very serious losses bysubmarines during the last few days, particularly in the Medi-terranean.The First Sea Lord indicated the steps which were being-taken by the Admiralty to deal with the situation in these waters.16. The First Sea Lord stated that the British Consul atStavauger had reported that when three British steamships wereeastward bound under a Norwegian escort, a periscope was observedinside territorial waters, and that a fishing boat reported thepresence of a German submarine. The British Consul apprehendedthat the Germans intend torpedoing ships inside territorial waters,even in the presence of a Norwegian escort, by way of retaliationfor the capture of German vessels by the British on the norwegian coast.Eemoval of Storesfrom Vladivostock.Set:17. With reference to War Cabinet 369, Minute S, the Firsta i^orustated that the Commanding Officer of H.M.S. &quot; Suffolk,at vladivostock, had reported that a satisfactory reply had beenreceived from the Inspector of Artillery with reference to the Alliedprotest against 45,000 rounds of 3-inch shell of Allied stores being^handed over, and that no Allied munitions would be sent away for^   the present.Russian Black SeaFleet.18. With reference to War Cabinet 369, Minute 7, the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs asked what information had reached theAdmiralty with reference to the Russian Black Sea Fleet.Attention was drawn to telegram No. 71, from Helsingfors,stating that the Russian Admiralty had instructed the Commanders-in-Chief of the Baltic and Black Sea Fleets to destroy the Fleets.It was stated that there was apparently no reason why theBolskeviks should give up or destroy any ships in the Black Sea,and the War Cabinet felt that the attitude which would be taken bythe Bolsheviks as regards these Fleets would be a test as to the sincerity of the Bolsheviks&apos; announced intentions.The War Cabinet decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should communicate with Mr. Lockhart in this sense, and should ask him for
19. The First Sea Lord stated that the aggregate strength ofthe Allied Fleets in the Mediterranean was already sufficient to dealwith any increment of strength which the enemy might derive froma possible acquisition of the Russian Black Sea Fleet, althoughfresh dispositions of their forces would be necessary. The french had already agreed to the proposed redistribution of force, shouldthe emergency arise, and the Admiralty was in communication with&quot;the Italian Ministry of Marine on the subject.Conciliation and arbitration Board:Equal Remunera-tipn of Men andWomen.20. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum (paper g-.T.-3960) by the Conciliation and Arbitration Board for Govern-ment employees on the question of remuneration of men and womenengaged on similar duties.Sir Thomas Heath stated that the Board had now before themtwo claims (from the Postmen&apos;s Federation and the NationalFederation of Women Civil Servants respectively) which were, ineffect, claims for the recognition in the Civil Service of the principlethat women should be paid the same remuneration as men engaged on similar duties. Sir Thomas Heath was of opinion that these claims involved an important, question of policy, and therefore felloutside the terms of reference of the Conciliation and arbitration board.Mr. Illingworth concurred in the opinion expressed by sir thomas Heath, and added that, in the Post Office, what sometimesappeared to be similar duties performed by men and women werenot proved on investigation to be so.The War Cabinet agreed that the matter involved a question ofprinciple,&apos; and was therefore not within the competence, of the Board of Conciliation and Arbitration to settle.12J per cent. 21. With reference to War Cabinet 317, Minute 1, Mr. Barnes^onus- called attention to applications which were being received in con-nection with the 12l per cent, bonus from local authorities andothers who were being pressed to make the grant of the bonus totheir employees retrospective. The result of conceding this demandmight be to force the local authorities to raise their rates and to force contractors to re-open accounts for undertakings which hadbeen completed. lie had discussed the matter with the Minister ofLabour, and it was proposed to send a letter to the Committee on production advising that awards should not be ante-dated further-back than the date of application, or some such similar date whichwhich may be determined by the particular circumstances of thecase.Mr. Roberts did not think such a decision was likely to lead to serious industrial trouble, unless there were sympathetic strikes.In the case of the shipyards the granting of the bonus had alreadybeen arranged.Sir David Shackleton thought there would be trouble with local authorities and public utility Companies. There were three classes of cases affected : ya.) Companies now controlled under the penal part of the munitions of War Act, &amp;.g., gas-works.(b.) Cases which could be proclaimed if the Ministry ofMunitions thought a strike could not be risked.such information as to the Black Sea and Baltic Fleets asthe Admiralty might think desirable.The First Sea Lord was asked to communicate the Admiralty^y wishes to Mr. Balfour.
(e.) Small companies and undertakings in the smaller townsand boroughs, which could be left to light their ownbattles.In the first and second groups, applications for the bonus wouldbe made, and if the Government advised the companies not to resistlest there should be a strike, there would be danger of collusionbetween the companies and their employees. The fact was suchcases were never contemplated in the original award. They werenot definitely concerned with munitions of war, and could make no claim on the ground of the higher cost of living : they were simplytrying to take advantage of an award granted in quite another heldof employment.Sir Stephenson Kent thought that, on the whole, the date of application was as convenient a stopping-place as any that could be suggested.The War Cabinet authorised  The Ministry of Labour to advise the Committee on Productionthat the lines indicated by Mr. Barnes, viz., that, as thelocal authority employees were not entitled to be coveredwhen the original orders were issued, it would be desirable for the Committee not to ante-date an award further backthan the date of application, or some similar date whichmay be determined by the particular circumstances of thecase.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,March 22, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
