<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/22/24 images: 206-217</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO 8E KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KfcV.ifSECRET.W.P*(42)94.&quot;(Also CCS. (42)  128)21ST FEBRUARY,  1942.WAR CABINET.FAR EAST APPRECIATION.COPY NO.Report by the Chiefs of StaffOn 15th February we were invited by the War Cabinet&quot;to prepare an appreciation of the situation in the Far Eastin the light of recent events.JAPANESE INTENTIONS.2. Japan is pressing her offensive with the greatestvigour in order to take full advantage of her present superior-ity.      Her -immediate objects appear to be to complete herconquest of the Philippines, Sumatra and Java, and to exploither invasion of Burma, which would threaten Chinese ability tocontinue fighting,      She may also assault Port Darwin and ceylon.3. Japan must realise that the defeat of Germany would very seriously prejudice her chances of ultimate victory.      HerStrategy therefore is likely to be biased towards helpingGermany insofar as that is compatible with her own requirements,1+, Once Japan has effectively breached the Malayan Barrier,she has a clear run into the Indian Ocean, where we aredangerously weak in all respects.      By attacks on Ceylon andIndia, Japan could raise overwhelming internal security problems in India and induce instability in Indian forces in all theatres of war.     By the occupation of Ceylon, Japan would prevent us from reinforcing Burma and achieve a position suitablefor building up a serious threat to our Indian Oceancommunications.      This would go far towards meeting bothJapanese requirements, would help her offensive against Burma and provide relief to Germany by threatening India and the middle east.5. To the east, New Caledonia, and Fiji are stepping stonesto Australia and New Zealand.      The conquest of these islands would gravely compromise American ability to build up forces inthose Dominions and to sieze advanced bases for naval actiontowards the A.E.D.A.  area.6. To sum up, in the near future we may expect to see;-In the A.B.D.A.   area.(a^  Java attacked by greatly superior forces.(hS Port Darwin attacked.(c) Seizure of advanced bases in the Andamans andNicobars.x W.M. (1+2) 21st Conclusions.

In the Indian Theatre.(d.)    An extension of the attack on Burma.le)    Naval attack on our sea communications.(f) Serious threat to Ceylon.(g) Threat of raids on the East Coast of India.In the Pacific.(h) An increased threat to Fiji and New Caledonia.OBJECT.7. Our immediate object is to stabilise the situation soas to ensure the security of bases and points vital to ourprosecution of the war in the Middle and Far East and to oureventual return to the offensive against Japan.BROAD STRATEGY. &apos;8. The basis of our general strategy lies in the safety ofour sea communications for which secure naval and air bases are essential.We must therefore make certain of our main basesi.e, Burma, India, Ceylon, Australia and New Zealand.Assistance from Russia..9. Offensive submarine and air activity from Siberia in theimmediate future would he of great assistance.      In presentcircumstances we have not pressed Russia for this, lest itshould reduce her ability to resist Germany&apos;s spring offensive in the west.Naval Situation.10.       There is no naval base available from which a singlecombined fleet could cover both the Pacific and Indian Ocean..  Thus the strategy in these two Oceans must be dealtwith separately.For the defence of Indian Ocean sea communications, weare building up our Eastern fleet.     At present there is nosecure base in the Indian Ocean.Thus we must:-(a.)    Secure Ceylon.. (b)    Develop Adda Atoll,(c)    Develop additional bases for reconnaissance and striking forces.11.       In the Pacific it is essential to build up a superiorUnited States Fleet.      The Pacific fleet may approach paritywith the Japanese by mid April.     Ultimately a base furtherwestward than Hawaii is needed to exert a real threat to japanese communications. -In the meantime, an energetic raiding policy against japanese communications would influence Japanese operations inthe present theatre of war.British opinion is that an extension of this policy toinclude raids against Japan itself would have a far reachingdiversionary effect.      This would have to be an Americanresponsibility but they do not consider that it is a practical proposition at present.      The Americans are, however,  consideringthe oat   lishment of a naval 1-as.b in Now a on land with a view toadvancing northward, while still holding Hawaii.

The Malayan Barrier.12. With the enemy in Sumatra and the Islands to theEast and West of Java,  it will he very difficult to getshipping to either B.atavia or Sourabaya.    These are theonly good ports in Java,    We are therefore unable to reinforce the - island on such a scale that we couldanticipate holding the island for long.    Nor could weprovide adequate reinforcements in time.If we attempt to reinforce.orce Java our forces would be destroyed piecemeal leaving us without resources to providefor the minimum security of our essential main bases.Thus, our sound policy strategically is to withholdmajor reinforcements from Java and to concentrate onholding Burma,&apos; Ceylon.     India, Australia and New Zealand.13. It is of the utmost importance that the enemyshould not acquire gains cheaply.The East Indies should be defended with the utmostresolution by all forces at present in the area,    Everyday gained is of importance.Burma.140 Burma is the eastern outpost of the defence ofIndia, the only supply line to China,- whose resistance wemust maintain., and a base for future offensive operations.In view of the imminent threat to Rangoon, our policy must be to reinforce Burma strongly and rapidly.Ceylon.15o The loss of Ceylon would imperil the whole british war effort in the Middle and Par East, owing to its position in relation to our sea communications.Immediate measures are being taken to provide the island with adequate defences, particularly air forces,anti-aircraft guns and increased R.D0F.NIndia,160 The maintenance of India&apos;s war effort dependsboth on security against external attack and on thepreservation of internal security and morale0For both reasons additional land and air forces must be sent to India as soon as possible,,Australia.17, Port Darwin is principally of value while weretain any hold on the Malayan Barrier, but is notstrategically essential for the eventual offensive,,    Theremainder of Australia,  in particular the East and SouthWest, will be one of the main bases from which the offensive against Japan will eventually be launched,,.Australia is insecure at present but as we have not theforces available, u.S. must be largely responsible for reinforcing this area.    One U. S, Division is due to leave for Australia early in March.Thus the Australian Divisions serving outside theJapanese war area should be moved to Australia,   though itmay be necessary to use part of the force in Burma,pending the arrival there of other reinforcementso

New Zealand, Fiji and New Caledonia.18. Before invading New Zealand, Japan would &quot;be likelyto seize Fiji and New Caledonia, two points essential tothe American reinforcement route and which the americans are assisting to defend.The threat to New Zealand is not immediate but stepsmust be taken to improve her defences in vie?/ of thepossible loss of Fiji and New Caledonia, and her importance as a channel of communications to the U, S.A.  and as a base for future action.Reinforcement of Far &quot;^ast.19, It is clear from the foregoing that considerablereinforcements will be essential if we are to stabilise the Far East Theatre.    Shortage of shipping and the time factor compel us to find them.at the expense of the middle east.We must accept great risks in the Middle East, forthe security of which we must largely depend on the -successful resistance of Russia in the Ukraine and upon afavourable situation in Turkey.Shipping Situation^20. The shipping situation is very grave and, unlessways and means of increasing our shipping resources and of using these resources to the greater advantage of our war effort can be discovered, we shall be unable to move theforces&quot; overseas demanded by our strategic requirements.    Infact our strategy must be governed in 1942 and probably in1943 largely by shipping.To move overseas from England the land and airforces necessary to replace the formations in the middle east and give additional strength in the Far East, we mustexploit our shipping resources to the utmost and ifnecessary incur a temporary reduction in our import programme.Policy.21.       Thus our policy in the near future must bet-(a) to provide for the safety of our sea communicationsby building up our Eastern fleet and by securingthe bases necessary to its use:(b) to withhold major reinforcements from Java butdefend the island with the available forces withthe utmost resolution:(c) to provide reinforcements as quickly as possibleto secure the essential points vital to thecontinuance of the struggle against Japan,namely Burma, Ceylon, Australia and India:(d) to accept risks in the Middle East to stabilise the Far East:(e) to exploit our shipping resources to the utmostin the interests of our strategy.

22.        The United States of America should undertake(f) offensive operations against Japanese seac omrauni cations.(g) the protection of the essential air and naval bases in the air reinforcement route across the pacific.(h) the concentration of air and land, forces inAustralia,,(i) the building,!- up of a strong Pacific fleet.(j) the reinforcement of the garrisons of Fiji andNew Caledonia,  and the improvement of NewZealand&apos;s defences in view of the possible lossof Fiji and New Caledonia, and her importance as a channel of communications to the U.S.A*and as a base for future action.(Signed) DUDLEY POUND.C, PORTAL.A.F. BROOKE.Great George Street, S.W.121ST FEBRUARY, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
