<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/8/6 images: 110-119</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1940.SECRET. Copy No. J. 9W.M. (40)194th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 194 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, July 5, 1940, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,   The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,M.P., Lord President of the Council.      Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty(Items 1-9).The   Right   Hon.   Sir   archibald sinclair,  Bt.,  M.P.,   Secretary ofState for Air (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary  of  State  for  DominionAffairs (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. L. C. M. S. Amery,M.P., Secretary of State for Indiaand Burma (Item 1).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-9).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary- of State for War(Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister&quot; ofHome Security.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Lloyd, Secretaryof State for the Colonies (Item 1).Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-9).Lieutenant-General R. H. Haining,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff (Items 1-9).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Lieut.-Col. V. Dykes, R.E.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21510]b
WAR CABINET 494 (40).Contents.minute no.                                         Subject. page 1      The Far East..................      ...      41Japanese demand for closing of the Burma Road.2      Eire      ........................      43Action  against  enemy  vessels  and   aircraft  in  Eire  territorial waters.3      The United States of America      ...      ...      ...       ...      43Supply of destroyers.Policy towards Eire.4      Home Defence ...       ...      ...       ...      ...      ...      ...      43Imminence of a German invasion of Great Britain.5      U.S.S.R..........................      43Anglo-Soviet relations.6      France  ...       ....      ...       ...       ...      ...      ...       ...      44Anglo-French relations.7      France  ...      ....      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      44The French fleet,8      France  ...      .......      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      44Shipping bound for French colonial possessions.9      Operation reports      ...       ...       ...      ...      ...        ..      44.   Air.Military.10      Communist propaganda       ...       ...       ...      ...       ...      44
1.   The War Cabinet had before them the following Papers :  Memoranda bv the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsW.P. (40) 234 and&quot; 248).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Burma(W.P. (40) 242).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (W.P. (40) 246).Report by the Chiefs of Staff (W.P. (40) 249).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the main question was whether we should agree to the Japanese demand thatwe should close the Burma Road. After giving full weight to the considerations urged by the Chiefs of Staff, he still felt that weshould decline to agree to this demand. The advantages which weshould gain by agreeing to this demand would be insecure. Further,they would be obtained at the cost of betraying Chiang Kai-shek,and of unfortunate political repercussions in the United States, inRussia, and in this country. The Secretary of State referred to themilitary measures which it would be open to the Japanese to takeagainst us in the event of war. They might attack Hong Kong,but it seemed to him very doubtful whether they would take onthe formidable proposition of attacking Singapore, or would starton some big adventure against the British Empire. He believedthat there was a big element of bluff in their attitude. In thisconnection he drew attention to the account of a visit by theJapanese Ambassador to the Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState (Despatch No. 279 to Tokyo of the 4th July).To sum up, the Foreign Secretary thought that in the longrun we should lose less by standing up to Japanese blackmail thanby relinquishing our principles.In discussion, attention was drawn to the view, strongly expressed by Sir Robert Craigie and by our Military Attache in tokyo, that the Japanese were set on the closing of the Burma road and that a refusal would be highly dangerous. It was only natural that the Japanese, who were anxious to finish off the war in China,should be irritated by our action in keeping open a channel ofsupply to China.The proposal to ration traffic over the road was agreed to be impracticable, in the light of the difficulties referred to by theSecretary of State for Burma. While the volume of traffic carried over the road might not be very substantial, it included certaingoods, e.g., oil and lorries, which China could not obtain by anyother route. Materials were also imported for an aircraft factory in China not far from the Burma border.The effect on public opinion was next dealt with. Ifacquiescence in this demand was followed by still further demands from Japan, it would be difficult to defend our action against the severe criticism which would be aroused in this country. On theother hand, it was pointed out that it was the duty of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to do what was right for the safety of the Empire,without too much regard for public opinion.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs drew attention tothe telegrams from the Governments of Australia, South africa and New Zealand, concurring in the reply proposed by the foreign secretary. He was not, however, entirely satisfied that the Common-wealth Government might not have viewed the matter differently if,at the time of sending their reply, they had been fully aware ofour difficulties with France, culminating in the operations off Oran,and of the anxieties of the Chiefs of Staff as set out in their Paper.It was argued that the effect on Russia of yielding to Japanesedemands would be particularly unfortunate at a time when it seemed that there was a chance of our relations with that countryimproving.[21510] b 2
This led to discussion of the probable attitude of the UnitedStates.The Prime Minister said that while acceptance by this country of Japan&apos;s demands might have a bad effect on public opinion inother countries, it looked as though the whole burden of the standwhich it was suggested that we should take in this matter on behalfof China would fall on this country, which was already fully occupied in a military sense. He thought that the responsibilityfor the decision should be placed where it ought to lie, namely, withthe United States. They should be asked flatly whether they wouldtake any action whatever if, for example, Japan were to makelodgments in the Dutch East Indies. In the present state of affairshe did not think that we ought to incur Japanese hostility for reasons mainly of prestige.This point of view was shared by the Lord President of theCouncil, who drew attention to the interview which Lord Lothianhad had with Mr. Sumner Welles and Mr. Hornbeck (telegramNo. 1216 from Washington). Mr. Welles had favoured an attemptto arrive at an agreed settlement in the Far East.Discussion then turned on the action which Japan would take if we refused to close the Burma Road. Instead of taking military action against the Road, she might use our refusal as a pretext to goto war with us and make capital out of our difficulties. Even ifthe Japanese did not make a direct attack on Singapore, the actionof their Fleet would put us in the most serious difficulties. Notonly would they attack our trade in Eastern waters, but Australiaand New Zealand would be put in peril. These Dominions had always been told that there was no danger of large-scale invasion of their territories, and on this assurance they had denuded them-selves of troops. The difficulties we should have to face in pro-tecting our trade against Japanese action would be further increasedby the danger of French bases being used by the enemy against us.The general view of the War Cabinet was that the militarysituation did not justify us in taking action which might involve us in war with Japan. If, however, we had to acquiesce in thedemand for the closure of the Road, it would be better to do soon the basis suggested in the last paragraph of telegram No. 1216from Washington, in which the President was reported as sayingthat he disliked making an agreement based on the idea of appease-ment, and would rather yield under protest to force majeure than to sign away rights as the French had done.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he stilllooked with disfavour on a settlement on these lines, since he believed that it was probably a question of bluff rather than of force majeure. He would therefore like to try his hand at draftinga telegram to Sir Robert Craigie which would enable him to sound the Japanese Government&apos;s attitude in regard to their demand forthe closing of the Road, without committing himself to acquiescence in this demand.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, in thelight of the discussion which had taken place, to prepare the following drafts : (i) A   telegram   to   His   Majesty&apos;s   Ambassador   in washington instructing him to explain to president roosevelt that, unless we received a clear assurance of American support, we should be compelled to bowto force majeure and to accede to the Japanesedemand for the closing of the Burma Road.(ii) A telegram to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Tokyoinstructing him to gain as much time as possible
in exploring with the Japanese the reasons fortheir demands for the closing of the Burma road and the possibility of reaching a settlement withoutfull acceptance of this demand, but permitting him,in the last resort, to accede to these demands asimposed on us by force majeure.Eire.Action against enemy vessels and aircraft in eire territorial waters.2. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChiefs of Staff (W.P. (40) 245) regarding the issue of instructions on the subject of military action in Eire Territorial Waters.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said thatMr. Walsh had some weeks ago informed Sir John Maffey that the eire Government would turn a blind eye to any such action by our forces, provided our activities were conducted in such a way as notto excite comment.The War Cabinet-Approved the policy suggested by the Chiefs of Staff, viz. :(a) Enemy warships and aircraft of every description,including transports and troop-carrying craft,should be attacked by warships and aircraft when-ever found in Eire Territorial Waters.(b) If suspicious vessels are seen in Eire territorial waters, warships and aircraft may enter to investigate.United States of       3.   The Prime Minister said that, subject to the War Cabinet&apos;sAmerica. approval, he proposed to send a personal telegram to PresidentSupply of Roosevelt making a further strong appeal for the United states destroyers. to supply us with a number of destroyers.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 154thConclusions,Minute 9.)Policy towards In the telegram he also proposed to mention to the PresidentEire. the possibility that it might be necessary for us, in the near future,(Previous and in order to forestall German action, to make a change in our reference: policy towards Eire.W.M. (40) 191st rp,    w     n , -    .n    ,   . The War Cabinet Conclusions,Minute 11.) Approved of the despatch of the proposed telegram fromthe Prime Minister to President Roosevelt.Home Defence. 4.   The War Cabinet took note of a Report by the JointImminence of a Intelligence   Sub-Committee   (W.P.   (40)   244)   relating  to  theimminence of a German invasion of Great Britain. -german invasion ofGreat Britain.U.S.S.R. 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that heAnglo-Soviet would be glad if the War Cabinet could discuss at an early date therelations. recent telegrams that had been received from Sir Stafford Cripps(Previous regarding his interview with M. Stalin.Reference:W.M. (40) 192ndConclusions,Minute 7.)
Fl,anoe. 6.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theAnglo-French previous evening M. Cambon, the French Charge d&apos;Affaires, hadrelations. made a personal statement to him to the effect that the situationbetween the French and British Governments was so grave that itwas impossible to foretell what decision his Government would cometo. He had added an energetic protest regarding our action againstthe French Fleet. That morning M. Cambon had made a furthercall and had stated that he was resigning his post as Charged&apos;Affaires, as he feared he might have to make a communication on behalf of his Government which, after having lived in thiscountry for over twenty-five years, he would not wish to make.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.France.The french fleet.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 193rdConclusions,Minute 8.)7. The War Cabinet were given the latest information inregard to the French Fleet and the position at Dakar.The discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.France. 8.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs suggested that shipping bound the loreign Office, the Admiralty and the Ministry of shipping for French should consult together with a view to lifting the ban on shippingcolonial under Allied control bound for such French Colonial possessions aspossessions. we had reasonable grounds for thinking were friendly to us.Reference: The War Cabinet agreed to this suggestion.W.M. (40) 179thConclusions,Minute 4.)OperationReports.Air.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 192ndConclusions,Minute 2.)9. The War Cabinet were given the following information to supplement that contained in Cabinet War Room RecordNo. 306:-The Chief of the Air Staff said that a further attack had beencarried out on the Scharnhorsi, which now had a definite list.An attack had been carried out against aircraft near Gibraltarby three French fighter aircraft of the Curtiss type.- One had been shot down for certain, and one other unconfirmed.There was a report that Gibraltar had been bombed that morning, but no details were available.Military. The Secretary of State for War said that Italian forces had(Previous succeeded in taking a post at Kassala, held by a Company of the reference: Sudan Defence Force. It had been expected ever since Italy cameW.M. (40) 189th into the war that an attack in force would be made against this conclusions,        post.Minute 2.) The War Cabinet took note of this information.communist propaganda.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 193rdConclusions,Minute 2.)10. The War Cabinet resumed consideration of this question,and again had before them the Memorandum by the Home Secretary(W.P. (G.) (40) 171).The following points were made in discussion :  (1) The Secretary of State for the Home Department and minister of Home Security said that, looking at thematter simply from the point of view of public order, itwas his duty to stop the distribution of these leaflets.
If he did this, but did not also suppress the daily worker, he was open to a charge of inconsistency, sincethe leaflets contained, in a concentrated form, thematerial which appeared in the Daily Worker.(2) The arguments which had been put forward at the WarCabinet on the previous day against the suppression ofany newspaper at this juncture were again referred to.Public opinion was, at the moment, very sensitive in thematter of free speech. This was probably due, first, tothe example of France, where rigid censorship had been followed by collapse; and, secondly, to the proposalswhich had recently been made for tightening up the censorship in this country.(3) The people of this country expected that even-handedjustice should be done. If the Daily Worker wassuppressed, was there not el CclSG for taking further actionagainst other organisations or individuals suspected ofFifth Column activities?The Home Secretary said that he had taken actionagainst all the organisations with Fascist leanings.(4) While it was true that articles highly critical of theGovernments war effort appeared in certain other papers, the fact remained that the Daily Worker wasthe only paper which never published anything infavour either of the Government or of the effectiveprosecution of the war.(5) The Home Secretary said that the opinion of his expertadvisers was against taking action against Communistsas such at the present time. The view taken was thatit was better to leave them to be dealt with under the criminal law.   This view met with approval.The War Cabinet-(i) Authorised the Home Secretary to take action to stop thedistribution of the leaflet entitled &apos;&apos; The People mustAct,&quot; and to institute proceedings against persons concerned in its distribution,(ii) Decided that a preliminary warning should be given to the daily Worker, but that for the moment an Order shouldnot be made prohibiting the printing, publication ordistribution of this paper.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,July 5, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
