<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/43/43 images: 356-367</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1944.SECRET.Copy No. 52W.M. (44)127th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 127 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, 25th September, 1944, at 5-30 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.the right hon.Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P.,   Secretary of  State  for  theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Lord   Woolton,The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon Sir. James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 11). .Mr. Duncan Sandys, M.P., Joint Par-liamentary Secretary, Ministry ofSupply (Item 5).Mr. P. J. Noel Baker, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of war transport (Items 9-11).Vice-Admiral Sir E. Neville Syfret,Vice-Chief   of Naval  Staff  (items-6).1Marshal of the Royal Air Force sir charles F. A. Portal, Chief of theAir Staff (Items 1-6).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Major-General E. I. C. Jacob.Mr. L. F. Burgis..The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel . the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Items 9-11).The . Right Hon Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. the Earl of Selborne,Minister of Economic Warfare(Hems 6-11).The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint     Parliamentary     Secretary,Treasury (Item 11).Mr. Ernest Thurtle, M.P., Parlia-mentary    Secretary,    Ministry   ofInformation (Item 5).Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(Items 1-10).Field-Marshal Sir Alan Brooke, Chiefof the Imperial General Staff (items ).[28375-3]this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENT
WAR CABINET 127 (44).Contents.minute no. Subject. Page  \1      Naval, Military and Air Operations ....       ....       ....       81Air Operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean.China.Naval Operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean.Russia.Military Operations:Northern France and Holland.Italy.Russia.2      Production........................      ....      81Importation of timber from Russia.8 &apos;     Foreign Affairs ..       ................ ......      82Bulgaria.Russia and Poland.4      Attacks by Flying-bombs and Rockets     ....      .........      82Casualties and damage.5      Future Scale of Attack by Flying-bombs and Rockets  ....      82Question of publicity as to rocket attacks.6      Siam.........    - ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    . 83Proposed S.O.B. operations.7      Enemy Assets and Looted Property ....      ....      ....      848      Finance of Relief in the Military Period ....    t ....      .....    849      Suez Canal ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      8510    - Civil Air Transport    ........................      85International Air Conference.11    - Parliament      ............................      87Prolongation of the life of the United Kingdom Parliament andof the House of Commons of Northern Ireland.f-
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 123rdConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Home Theatre.mediterranean china.naval operations.Home Theatre.MediterraneanRussia.MilitaryOperations.northern france and holland.Italy.Russia.1.&quot; The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of theprevious week.Bomber Command had made 2,600 sorties and dropped9,360 tons of bombs, 6,000 of t-hem on Germany. It was now believedthat in the attack on the Tirpitz on the 15th September a hit hadbeen obtained in the fore part of the ship with a 12,000-lb. bomb.United States heavy bombers had flown 2,800 sorties, dropping4,470 tons of bombs. 650 sorties had been flown carrying supplies to the Army in France and Holland. 110 aircraft had taken supplies to Warsaw, two of which had been lost. In all, 40 British and36 United States bombers had been lost during the week.The Allied Expeditionary Air Force, whose losses amountedto 91. aircraft, had flown 7,460 sorties. 5,173 sorties had been flownin the Airborne Operations and their subsequent support, 3,139being by powered aircraft and 2,034 by gliders. Losses in poweredaircraft had been 146. The total lift had been some 22,000 men and2,600 tons of stores and equipment. The weather had beenunfavourable, but on the whole the air part of the operation had been successful.Coastal Command had sunk 2 submarines and possibly damaged3 others.*&apos; 10,900 sorties had been flown and 8,700 tons of bombs dropped.Forty-eight enemy aircraft had been destroyed as against 57 Allied.Attacks had been made against shipping in the Formosa area.It was claimed that 1 transport, 7 freighters and a tanker had been sunk and 197 small vessels damaged.There had been no shipping losses from enemy action duringthe previous week.On the night of the 18th September H.M.S. Stayner had sunk3 E-boats north of the Straits of Dover, taking 67 prisoners. Havrehad been cleared of mines. At Ostend a small,number of ships could now be berthed.A U-boat had been destroyed near Crete. It was thought thatthere were only 2 U-boats left in the Mediterranean.A convoy of 33 ships had arrived in Russian ports without loss.The main operations during the previous week had been thethrust to link up with the airborne troops dropped on the17th September. This had been achieved so far .as concerned thetwo. United States Airborne Divisions. But one brigade of theBritish Airborne Division dropped at Arnhem had been definitelylost. Some contact had been made with the other brigade of the division and further efforts to this end were in progress. further to the south the Germans had twice pushed into the corridor,interfering with our communications, but the. position had. been-established.The Canadians had now reached the banks of the Scheldt atAntwerp. Contrary&quot; to reports, Belfort still remained in german hands. Generally speaking, enemy resistance was stiffening, but themain Allied difficulty was still the supply situation.In the Adriatic sector considerable progress had been made andour troops had captured Rimini and were now moving into open country. In the centre the American forces had cleared the maincrest of the Apennines and were approaching the Bologna-Rimini road. -Progress had been made in the north and Tallinn had been cleared.- Minor progress had been made on the Hungarian-Czechq-Slovakian frontier. The Russians had also made a pronouncedthrust to the west in the neighbourhood of Arad.The War Cabinet-Took note of these statements.Production. 2.   In connection with the preceding item, the question wasImportation of raised whether an endeavour ought not to be made to ensure thatTimber from ships returning from Russian ports carried cargoes of timber.  ThisRussia, might mean some delay in the turn-round of ships, but, having[28375-^3] b 2
regard to our urgent need to build up stocks of timber, this mightwell have to be faced.The War Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Production, in consultation withthe Minister of War Transport, to enquire into thismatter.Foreign Affairs.Bulgaria.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 111thConclusions,.Minute 6.)Russia and poland.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 123rdConclusions,Minute 9.)3. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theterms for the Bulgarian Armistice were being settled by theEuropean Advisory Council. The Russians and the United states had agreed that the Bulgarians should be told that before discussions could be concluded they must withdraw their troops from greece and Yugoslavia. It had also been agreed that the terms of thearmistice should be presented at Ankara.The question whether a representative of General Wilsonshould sign the armistice, as well as a Russian General, had not yetbeen settled.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs gave details of an interview which the British and American Ambassadors had had with&apos; Marshal Stalin, at which the decisions of the QuebecConference had been communicated to the Marshal. Marshal stalin had made certain observations regarding the situation at Warsaw.His attitude towards the Poles now seemed more favourable, but thepopulation of Warsaw was in sore straits and very short of food.The War Cabinet-Requested the Chiefs of Staff to suggest to the UnitedStates Air Command that they should consider under-taking a further flight to Warsaw, dropping mainly food supplies.The Secretary of State for Foreign-Affairs said that he had seen M. Raczkiewicz, the Polish President, who was still consideringthe unanimous decision of the Polish Cabinet that GeneralSosnkowski should be removed from his post. It remained uncertain whether the Polish President would comply with this request. but . Mikolajczyk, who had stated he would resign if the Presidentdid not accept his Cabinefs recommendation, had agreed to holdhis hand for the moment. General Anders had stated that GeneralSosnkowski&apos;s retention, or otherwise, was a matter of indifferenceto the Polish Army.Attacks by flying bombs and Rockets.Casualties and damage.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 122ndConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The War Cabinet was informed that two rockets had been launched (on the 18th September), of which one had fallen in theLondon area.   Since then none had fallen in this country.During the week 83 flying bombs had been launched from aircraft, of which 11 had reached the London area. Two enemy aircraft launching flying bombs had been destroyed the previous night.The War Cabinet-Took note of this statement.Future scale of Attack by flying bombs and Rockets.Question of publicity as torocket attacks.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 123rdConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Report by the Chiefsof Staff (W.P. (44) 534) on the future scale of attack by flying bombs and rockets. The Chiefs of. Staff stated in their Report that the attack by flying bombs might persist for some considerable time onan average of about 20 launchings a night, of which 4 might reach the London defence region. There had been no rocket firings fora week, but the possibility of attack could not be entirely ruled outuntil the whole of Holland West of the line running North and Souththrough Eindhoven had been overrun. The Chiefs of Staff recom-mended that there should be no public statement on the rocketfirings, and suggested that the matter might be reviewed in aweek&apos;s time.
83w.m. 127 (44).     180The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security said that,while he had no strong views on the matter, he thought that on thewhole it might be best to make a statement in Parliament. It was nearly three weeks since the attacks started, though there had beena lull for a week. Parliament was, about to meet, and it was probable that the Germans must by now have received some infor-mation about the fall of the rockets. If the War Cabinet wisheda statement to be made, it could be done as a special statement at theend of Questions, or else the Prime Minister might deal with thematter in his forthcoming speech. He thought it would be quiteeasy to restrain the Press from giving details which might be ofassistance to the enemy.The Minister of Aircraft Production thought that, as theGermans had said nothing about the attacks, it would be far better for us also to remain silent. There was no particular demand for publicity, and we ought to avoid anything which might give theGermans encouragement.The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Information, con-firmed that there was no particular demand for publicity. He saidthat, if it were decided to make an announcement, there should beno difficulty in restraining the Press.The view of the War Cabinet was that it would be best to leavewell alone and say nothings at any rate until we could definitely saythat no further threat existed.It was pointed out that statements might soon be published inthe American Press, as people crossing the Atlantic would tell the story; but it was thought that, if approached, the american authorities would co-operate to maintain secrecy.The War Cabinet-(1) Took note of the estimate of the future scale of attack madeby the Chiefs of Staff.(2) Agreed that no public statement about the rocket attacksshould be made for the time being, and that it shouldbe suggested to the Prime Minister that, if he wishedto refer in his forthcoming speech to the attacks on london, he should confine himself to a statementindicating the scale of attack now being experiencedfrom both rocket and flying bomb, without making ,specific reference to the rocket.(3) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to approach the AmericanChiefs of Staff with the suggestion that they should take steps to restrain publicity in America.Slam. 6.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theProposed Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (44) 514), to which wasS.O.E. annexed a copy of a letter from Admiral Mountbatten regardingoperations.        operations which he desired S.O.E. to conduct in Siam.It was explained that up to the present it had not been possibleto conduct successful operations in Siam, but that S.O.E. now had reason to expect assistance from the Regent and the new PrimeMinister. Although there was a risk that contacts between S.O.E.and the Regent and Government of Siam might be misconstrued ascommitting His Majesty&apos;s Government in some way to them, it was felt that in view of the militar^ advantages there would be noobjection to the proposal provided that it was made clear in anydealings with the Siamese that our only interest was the defeat of japan and the expulsion of the Japanese from Siamese territory,and that no political commitment was involved as regards theultimate regime and organisation of Siam.The Minister of Economic Warfare strongly supported theproposal made in W.P. (44) 514, and confirmed that complete liaisonhad been established with the United States Forces on this matter.[28375-3] b 3
The Secretary of State for India supported the proposal, and paid tribute to the efficiency of the organisation which S.O.E. had.built up for operations in the Balkans.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposal that S.O.E. should undertakeoperations in Siam on the lines proposed in W.P. (44) 514.Enemy Assets 7.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theand Looted Chancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (44) 533), to which wasProperty. appended a resolution passed by the Bretton Woods Conference onthe subj ect of the transfer and concealment of enemy assets, andespecially of looted property, in neutral countries.The War Cabinet-Endorsed the proposal made by the Chancellor of theExchequer in W.P. (44) 533, and agreed that the ForeignOffice should arrange for action to be taken accordingly.Finance of relief in theMilitary Period.(previous reference:W.M.(44)125tLConclusions,Minute 5.)8. At their meeting on the 22nd September the War cabinet had agreed that, before reaching a decision on the proposals in the telegram dated the 19th September from the Minister of State(No. 10 Relief), they should have before them a memorandum setting out the considerations in favour of these proposals and dealing withthe points which had been raised in discussion.The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (44) 543).The Memorandum explained that there appeared no escape from our sharing in the expenditure on relief in the military period and that, in so far as the total expenditure depended on the courseof military operations, and on the extent to which it was possible to recover the costs from the countries in which the military operations were carried out, it was not possible to put any definite limit on thetotal commitment. While it was unfortunate that so muchexpenditure had had to be incurred in Italy, from which we couldnot at present recover the costs, this was an inevitable result of thecourse which military operations had taken.With regard to the scale on which supplies were made availablein the military period, we might well argue that if for humanitarian-tarian, political or other reasons, the United States desired to raisethe scale above the standard necessary for the prevention of disease and unrest, they should pay the additional cost. The main question,however, was whether we should accept a commitment to meet25 per cent, of the cost of relief in the military period with thestipulation that the situation should be reviewed shonM the totalcost reach $450 million. This would mean the definite acceptanceof a liability of Up to roughly  281 million.It would be impracticable to earmark any part of our contribu-tion for use in Greece or Yugoslavia, since expenditure had to be incurred wherever operations took place, and the course of opera-tions might well lead to greater expenditure being incurred in Italythan in Greece or Yugoslavia. On the other hand, every effort wouldbe made to ensure that U.N.R.R.A. would operate in Greece and yugoslavia as soon as possible after our Forces had entered them.The Memorandum accordingly suggested that in all the circum-stances the Minister of State should be authorised to conclude thenegotiations on the terms which he suggested.Against the settlement proposed, it was recalled that when thequestion of the procurement of supplies for relief in the liberated areas had/been raised earlier in the year, the very modest standard-of relief proposed had been criticised On the ground that it might affect adversely the standards of consumption in this country
9. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (44) 507) proposing that a Ministerial Committee should be set up to formulate our policy in regard to the issues involved&apos;.&quot;She War Cabinet-Approved this proposal, and invited the Prime Ministerto settle the composition of the Committee.10. The War Cabinet had before them Memoranda by theSecretary of State for Air (W.P. (44) 530) and by the Lord privy seal (W.P. (44) 540) about the forthcoming International Con-ference on Civil Air Transport, due to begin in Washington on the1st November.The first question discussed was our attitude to the Americaninvitation to the Conference.The Secretary of State for Air reminded the War Cabinet thatat the Anglo-American discussions in London in April last it hadSuez Canal.(previous reference erence  :W.M. (43) 151stConclusions,Minute 6.)Civil air transport.international air Conference.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 123rdConclusions,Minute 12.)(W.M. (44) 30th Conclusions, Minute 2). If it was now proposedthat we should share the cost of a more lavish standard of relief fora former enemy the Government would have great difficulty in defending the position, particularly if the scale of relief granted in italy were to lead to some curtailment of the scale given in greece and Yugoslavia. There was little evidence that the Italians were really trying to help themselves, and there was a danger ofpauperising them. $150 million had already been spent in Italyand it was idle to suppose that as we gained control of the Norththe total expenditure would not soon exceed the total of $450 million.On the other hand, it was argued that the settlement nowproposed represented a great improvement on the original proposal,and that, so far as concerned relief in the military period on a scalesufficient to prevent disease and unrest, our obligation wasinescapable.In further discussion, the question was raised whether we couldnot limit to some extent our commitments by suggesting that thefigure at which the situation would have to be reviewed afreshshould be $400 million instead of $450 million and by stipulatingthat our acceptance of a liability for 25 per cent, of the totalexpenditure was on the clear understanding that nothing beyondexpenditure on supplies necessary in the interest of militaryoperations for the prevention of disease and unrest should bebrought into account. The effect of this would be to require theUnited States Government to pay the whole cost of any supplies ona higher scale which they might choose to provide for political reasons. While it was not certain that we could stand out for this principle consistently with the general policy towards Italy, anattempt to secure acceptance of it was worth making.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would favour thiscourse. *The War Cabinet Agreed that the Minister of State should&apos; be instructed tocontinue negotiations on the basis (a) that the United Kingdom contribution should belimited to 25 per cent.;(&amp;) that there should be a review of the whole situationwhen the total irrecoverable expenditure reached$400 million; and(c) that our acceptance of a liability for 25 per cent, ofthe total expenditure was on the clear understandingthat nothing should be brought into account beyondexpenditure on supplies necessary in the interest ofmilitary operations for the prevention of disease and unrest.
been agreed that we should go forward to a full international conference as soon as possible. We had made it clear that thiswould be on the basis of the recommendations of the Balfour Sub-Committee formulated at the time of the Commonwealth discussions.This had been accepted by Mr. Berle.At a later date Mr, Berle had apparently abandoned any ideaof an International Conference, arid proposed that we and theUnited States, so far as possible on a non-exclusive basis, should move out on the civil air routes of the world. We had made it clearthat we could not acquiesce in this position and had offered to callan International Conference ourselves in London. In the result,the United States had changed their attitude and had issuedinvitations to a full International Conference without further reference to us. In the circumstances, he (the Secretary of Statefor Air) thought that it would be extremely difficult for us now tosay that we were not prepared to attend the proposed conference.The Americans had not issued a formal agenda for theconference, but had issued a full statement which included a listof objectives. From this it was clear that they hoped that bydealing, in the first instance, with interim operating rights theywould avoid discussion of the proposal put forward by the UnitedKingdom and endorsed by the Commonwealth countries for theestablishment of an international authority with executive powers.In the Secretary of State for Air&apos;s view, we must make it clear thatwe had not changed our views and intended to press for thediscussion of this project at the conference.Closely connected with this was a second question, namely, theproposals for a further Commonwealth discussion on civil aviationbefore the proposed International Conference.The War Cabinet were informed that, in the first instance, ithad been proposed that this should take place in London. It had become clear, however, that Canada would not attend a conferencein London, the ground put forward being that their officers wouldnot have time to go to London before the proposed- international conference. New Zealand had then proposed that the conference should take place in Ottawa. A week ago we had telegraphed to canada supporting that suggestion. Canada had not yet replied,but it was thought that South Africa would be willing to send representatives to Ottawa.The latest development was that a telegram had been receivedfrom Australia pressing for a conference at Canberra before any international conference. took place.Tlie Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that, muchas he liked the Australian line of approach, he felt in the circum-stances it was impracticable to fix up a conference in Canberra inthe time available. He thought that Canada would not go toCanberra and that the best prospect would be to concentrate onbringing about a conference at Ottawa ten days or a fortnight beforethe International Conference on the 1st November.The Lord Privy Seal explained the reasons why he thought thatwe should endorse Australia^ pronosal for a commonwealth meeting at Canberra and should ask the United States to postpone -the international conference. In his view there was not sufficient time to work out a scheme for Empire air routes between now andthe 1st November, and Ottawa was not the most favourable place inwhich to make the attempt. It was of the utmost importance thatwe should not go to the conference until an Empire policy had been worked out. ,The general view of the War Cabinet was that we could hardlytake the line that we would not now accept the invitation to theinternational conference in the United States. At the same time,there could be no question of agreeing to attend the conference ifthere was to be no discussion of the scheme which we favoured for aninternational authority with effective powers to regulate both thetechnical and economic aspects of post-war international air trans-port.   We should therefore accept the invitation to attend the
conference, but should make it clear that it was our intention as ithad always been to raise the question of the orderly developmentof post-war civil air transport under the control of an international authority with executive powers.Discussion then turned on the arrangements for a Common-wealth meeting prior to the international conference. The general view of the War Cabinet was that we should concentrate on bringing about the proposed conference at Ottawa, and making it fully effective, and that if necessary we should bring strong pressure tobear on the Canadian Government to agree to this course.The War Cabinets conclusions were as follows : (1) The United States invitation to the proposed international conference on civil air transport in Washington inNovember should be accepted on the understandingreferred to at &quot; X &quot; above, and subject also to (b) of theMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Air(W.P. (44) 530).(2) Every endeavour should be made to secure an effectiveCommonwealth conference in October in Canada, with strong delegations from this country and the Dominions.(3) A decision was deferred on the question whether a white paper should be presented to Parliament .in the nearfuture, outlining the policy which we advocated for thefuture development of air transport until a draft white paper had been prepared by the Secretary of State forAir and considered by the War Cabinet.(4) In reply to a Question by Mr. Ronald Tree, M.P., on thefollowing day, the Secretary of State for Air should state that he was not at present in a position to giveanswers to the points raised.11. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary and Minister of Home Security (W.P. (44) 528) onthe prolongation of Parliament.The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security explainedthat the Prolongation of Parliament Act, 1943, expired on the25th November, and that legislation to prolong Parliament for afurther period must be passed before that date. Although it would no doubt be argued that at the present stage of the war a prolongation-tion for six months would be sufficient, his view was that the right course was to prolong Parliament for a further year. This, ofcourse, would not preclude a dissolution at any time. It would alsobe desirable to empower the House of Commons of Northern ireland to prolong its life, if it chose to do so. This would be justified onthe ground that Northern Ireland was equally involved in the war.The War Cabinet-Authorised the Home Secretary and Minister of home security to proceed with legislation prolonging parliament for a further year from the 25th November, and empower-ing the House of Commons of Northern Ireland to prolongits life for a corresponding period.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,25*A September, 1944.Parliament.Prolongation ofthe life of theUnited kingdom parliament andof the House ofCommons ofNorthernIreland.(previous reference:W.M. (42)91stConclusions,Minute 10.)




</content>
</cab>
