<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/255/0 images: 266-273</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1935.SECRET. Copy No.CP. 129 (35).CABINET.AIR PACT AND AIR LIMITATION AGREEMENT.Memorandum for the Cabinet by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs andthe Secretary of State for Air.THE Cabinet have asked us to circulate for their consideration a joint memorandum on the Air Pact and Air Limitation Agreement.2. A review of the position made as the result of the Cabinet decision of the 5th June that the &quot; Air Pact and Air Limitation should be taken up as a separate question and no longer linked up with a general -settlement&apos;&apos; showed that, while the Italian and German Governments were unlikely to make any objection, the French Government were still withholding their consent to such a procedure.3. In these circumstances we felt that the first step must be a determined effort on the part of His Majesty&apos;s Government to secure French agreement at least to the immediate opening of negotiations between the five Locarno Powers on both the Air Pact and an Air Limitation Agreement, leaving aside for the present the difficult question of the conditions in which such pact and agreement should be ultimately concluded. It was decided for this purpose to take advantage of a visit which Mr. Eden was about to make to Paris in connection with the naval negotiations; and to ask him to try to clear up the point. It was further decided that if the French Government agreed to the opening of negotiations, Mr. Eden should (i) give them a list of some questions on which it seemed to us that the five Powers must, preferably through the diplo-matic channel, define their views and, if possible, reach agreement before work could usefully be begun upon a common draft either of the Air Pact or of the Limitation Agreement, and (ii) inform them that we should now seek the formal agreement also of the Belgian, German and Italian Governments to the opening of the negotiations through the diplomatic channel in the first instance, and-provided those Governments agree ask them, as well as the French Government, for their views on the list of questions.4.   These questions seem to us to be as follows :  General.(a) Is there to be one instrument embodying Air Pact, Limitation Agreement and prohibition of indiscriminate bombing, or are there to be separate instruments \Air Pact.(6) Which of the proposed signatories are to give guarantees, and which are to receive them?(c) What are the circumstances in which the guarantees will operate?(d) Are the guarantees to apply to territory only or to fleets and mercantile marines on the high seas ?8001   [11754] b
(e) Are Powers other than the five Powers in any way to be approached in connection with the Pact ?(/) Is the Pact to be supplemented by bilateral agreements ?TAmitation Agreement.(g) To what category or categories of air power and strength is limitation to apply ? -(h) Is it accepted that limitation shall be on a basis of parity in each category? And if any of the parties is not to enjoy parity, what is to be the relation of its strength to that of the other parties?(i) What is to be included in the term &quot;Metropolitan first-line strength&quot;?(N.B. It will be observed that the foregoing questions do not include that of supervision, but for this see paragraph 6 below.)5. The following are our recommendations to the Cabinet as to the view which we consider His Majesty&apos;s Government should take on these questions :  Question (a). There should be two separate instruments embodying respec-tively the Air Pact and the Agreement on Limitation of Air Strengths. It would not be desirable to embody in the Air Pact, which should be an agreement of a permanent nature, an agreement relating to air strengths, which may at a later date be subject to revision and even reduction, and which may one day fall under the authority of the Permanent Disarmament Commission.It would be desirable that the two agreements should enter into force simul-taneously. We regard both the pact and limitation as very desirable; but of the two, we consider limitation the more important. If the conclusion of an air pact in advance of a limitation agreement precluded or prejudiced the conclusion of a limitation agreement, we think this would be a strong and indeed conclusive reason for deferring the conclusion of the pact. If, however, as we have reason to believe, in the case of France at any rate, the existence of an air pact would facilitate agreement on limitation, there would be no objection to concluding the air pact in advance of the limitation agreement. If, in the course of the nego-tiations, it were found that the conclusion of an air pact were possible, but that the conclusion of a limitation agreement were either impossible or indefinitely postponed, then we are clearly of opinion that we ought to go for the conclusion of the air pact, in order that we may get one positive objective at any rate in our negotiations.We do not abandon hope of the conclusion at a later date of a separate instrument to lay down the rules of aerial warfare. But apart from the fact that the record of past attempts to arrive at international agreement in this matter is not encouraging, it is hardly one which could be dealt with by the five Powers independently of other countries. The negotiation of such an instrument will in any case involve long discussions. In these circumstances we recommend that for the time being our efforts in this matter should be confined to the referencet made to it in the preamble to the British draft of the Air Pact.Question (b). This question can only be finally elucidated by each State indicating the guarantees which it is disposed to give and those which it desires to receive. It is certainly not the intention that every signatory of the Air Pact should guarantee every other signatory against air attack by any other signatory. V   As far as the United Kingdom is concerned, we recommend that (i) we should only guarantee France and Belgium against Germany, andGermany against France and Belgium;(ii) we should require for ourselves a guarantee from France and Belgium .   against Germany, and from Germany against France and Belgium;(hi) we should admit a guarantee of Germany by France and Belgium .:     -     &apos; against us, and a guarantee of France and Belgium by Germany -&apos; against us;(iv) we should give no guarantee to Italy, and we should not require a .i s.-&apos; guarantee from her; we should not guarantee any Power against her; or agree that she should guarantee any Power against us.f This, reads as follows: &quot;Anxious in particular&apos; to safeguard the civil populations of their &quot;cbuntrfes^SEigainstHhe/damger^of indiscriminate attacks from the air, which they recognise to be contrary t6&apos;tli&apos;6&quot;Law! b&apos;f Nat&apos;i&apos;6n&apos;s/&apos;&apos; jmli tflsi-tb,x&amp;m bflJOih: &amp;Vf ;totpq g.nl3 00 l.iIOfl&apos;VO-&apos;T;Woi.l
Question (c). The question of the circumstances in which the guarantees should operate was discussed, in relation to the position as between Germany and Belgium and Germany and France, at the recent secret meeting of the British, Belgian, French and Italian jurists at Geneva. As the result of this discussion it appears that the substantial question which will arise is likely to be whether the guarantees are to operate where there has been an air attack in violation of Article 2 of the Treaty of Locarno (see Annex), or whether, in addition,: it. should be necessary that this violation should constitute an act of &quot; unprovoked aggression.&quot;      .In view of the fact that the case in contemplation is really an instance Of that provided for in Article 4 (3) of Locarno (see Annex), in which the element of unprovoked aggression appears, we recommend that we should endeavour to secure the insertion of the provision respecting &quot;unprovoked aggression.&quot; If strong resistance is encountered on this point from the French or some other Power, the matter could be reconsidered.It will be realized that in any event we must retain the right-&quot;to decide whether the circumstances in which the guarantee is to operate have arisen&apos;; - the present question is as to how these circumstances are to be defined in, the.,Pact. Once this point has been settled in regard to the position as between, Germany and Belgium and Germany and France, a similar solution could be adopted as regards the other guarantees to be given under the Pact. .., v-Question (d). In our opinion a deliberate air attack against the ships of any of the parties to the Pact could only be an act of war; and it is for this reason that we recommend that the Air Pact (though confined to Europe) should cover such a case of unprovoked aggression outside as well as inside territorial waters&apos;. Otherwise we should be deprived of the assistance of the other parties&apos; to the Pact in such an eventuality. -     &apos;We think the better course to be not to provide for this eventuality in specific terms, but to employ a general expression which would cover the case of a deliberate air attack upon ships (or aircraft) outside territorial waters.      :Question (e). The Power whom we and, it is understood, also the; French have in mind in connection with this question is Holland. .....,  ,r;.Our information is that Holland would not necessarily be averse, from participation, if invited; and, though we do not know that the French actually contemplate inviting Holland to be a party to the Pact, we understand that they have given thought to the possibility of asking Holland not to hinder or even in certain circumstances assist (as by allowing flying over their territory) operations undertaken in pursuance of the Air Pact. ;;    -The strategic advantages and disadvantages of Dutch participation in the Pact are discussed in the Chiefs of Staff report of the 20th June (C.O.S. .381). In the time at our disposal we have not been able to give adequate consideration to this report; and we would propose to circulate our view^s on.it to the Cabinet at a later date. ;Question (/). Bilateral agreements might be of three kinds : - &apos;     &apos;(1) Bilateral military agreements between two of the parties for the applica-tion of the Pact, i.e.; operational plans, administrative arrangements, &amp;c.; and the French have already communicated skeleton drafts of such an agreement.We do not consider that the effective value of the Air Pact as a deterrent against aggression is dependent upon the conclusion of bi-lateral agreements for its application, though a bi-lateral agreement between ourselves and France in the matter, for example, of an allocation of aerodromes in Northern France, would be of material assistance to attacks by our bombing squadrons on Germany. As between Belgium and this country, such an agreement might also be useful for the assistance which it would give us of the Belgian warning service. On the other hand, if we conclude a bi-lateral agreement with France only, it would have the appearance of discriminating against Germany, while it is difficult to contemplate that we should concurrently enter into separate bi-lateral agreements,- one of co-operation with France against Germany and another of co-operation with Germany against France. The German Government have already taken up position against bi-lateral military agreements.We recommend that, ,.f or the time, being, and if further, pressed by the French Government on this point, we should maintain that we.must first secure at.least [11754] b 2
an agreed draft of the Pact. The question whether any machinery for rendering it effective is necessary or desirable can be considered subsequently.(2) Bi-lateral agreements in which certain Powers, viz., Italy and the United Kingdom, would, vis-a-vis of one another, contract out of the general guarantee given under the Pact. At this stage it is impossible to say whether any agreement on this point supplementary to the general instrument will be required or will be possible.(3) Bi-lateral agreements under which any two Powers would give to one another pending the entry into force of the general Pact, the guarantees which will be subsequently provided by it. The French Government actually asked us for such a bilateral agreement at the time of the London meeting, and such agree-ments are provided for in the French draft.If such a proposal is repeated, we do not think such an agreement possible at the present stage, though the situation might change if the general negotiation became impossible owing either to German or French obstruction. As a matter of fact; the agreement to conclude such an arrangement would diminish the pressure which we Can bring to bear on France and Germany in the matter of the general air pact and of air limitation.Question (g). We recommend that limitation should be applied to the following categories of aircraft:  (i) Numbers of first line military aircraft (including shore-based naval aircraft)&apos; maintained in commission in combatant units for the operation of which pilots are available without measures of mobilisation.(ii) Numbers of military aircraft additional to those in category (i) which may be held for reserves, training or any other purposes.Category (i) will include the forces which are maintained in a condition of more or less immediate readiness as regards equipment and personnel, for active operations, and would therefore provide the best practical index of the initial striking capacity of an air force. It covers broadly the same meaning as the term &quot; rifle strength &quot; as applied to standing armies. This category would cover only military aircraft in combatant units, and would not include military aircraft held in units maintained exclusively for training or other non-combatant purposes. It is, however, necessary that these aircraft (as also the numbers of military aircraft held as reserves) should also be limited, as otherwise training establishments might be. so organised as to render nugatory the limitation imposed.Category (ii) therefore includes the numbers of military aircraft which may be held for reserves, training or any other purpose. The maximum number permissible under category (ii) would probably have to be negotiated on the basis of a uniform ratio to numbers allowed under category (i).We also recommend a limitation on the number of military pilots. The record of Geneva discussions shows the extreme complexity of any proposal for the limitation of effectives; but the absence of any provision for that purpose would be widely criticised and might work definitely to the advantage of Germany as compared with France or Great Britain by reason of the amenability of the German people to militarization.Questions (h) and (i) We recommend that the air forces of Great Britain, France, Germany and Italy should be on a basis of metropolitan parity in each of the categories of limitation, and that the Belgian Government should be asked to formulate its own proposals for a percentage of strength to that of the four Great Powers. The principle of parity as between those Powers was the basis of the British Draft Convention in 1933 and affords the best starting point for negotiations. Metro-politan parity as a basis of limitation would be in general accord with recent Ministerial declarations of policy. If confined to the above-mentioned categories it would;not in itself provide true equality of air strength; but the essence of an agreement which has any hope of acceptance is simplicity, and for that reason it is necessary to disregard, for the present purpose, such factors as relative vulnerability, manufacturing capacity, potentialities for rapid expansion, &amp;c, and to take our own measures to see that we, are not outstripped by other Powers in such matters.
On this basis of limitation the aircraft in overseas squadrons would not: be included in the parity figure, and we recommend that aircraft provided for operation from aircraft carriers and other ships of war should also be excluded from the agreement. The five Powers, however, should be asked mutually to agree that aircraft held for this latter purpose should be limited in proportion to the number of ships of war respectively&apos; maintained by them and fitted for the operation of aircraft. ,On these assumptions the limitation would cover for Great Britain all first line aircraft in the United Kingdom, and for Germany all first line aircraft: in: that country. As regards France, it is to be remembered that Herr Hitler in the Berlin conversations declared that he would accept nothing short of parity with French metropolitan air forces, including those stationed in North Africa. His point of view was not altogether unreasonable in view of the. fact that squadrons held in North Africa can be moved by air at short notice to French metropolitan territory. On the other hand, it is obvious that the French would object strongly to including their North African air forces on the same basis as those stationed in France itself, and there is indeed no evidence that France is yet prepared to accept parity of metropolitan air forces as between Germany and herself even if those in North Africa were excluded. On this point it will be essential to obtain the French views.Until those views are obtained it is hardly practical to discuss anj-..actual figures for the basis of limitation. The present actual first line strength of French air forces at home and in North Africa as estimated by the Air Ministry could not be put higher than 1,500 aircraft, but until some discussions with the French have taken place, it is hardly possible again to take this aspect of the matter any further. It will be remembered that information has been received that Germany intends to build to a first line strength of 2,000 aircraft, which is apparently her estimate of the present French strength.6. There remains the question of supervision. The methods hitherto evolved have all postulated the existence of a central international supervisory organ. The British Draft Convention of March 1933 proposed to entrust the task of supervision of the execution of the convention to the Permanent Disarmament Commission, giving it the power to conduct local investigations in certain circumstances. In December 1933 a Committee of the Disarmament Conference elaborated this proposal, largely at the instigation of the French Government, into a system of permanent and automatic supervision with periodical local inspections to be conducted by regional committees of the Permanent Disarma-ment Commission. His Majesty&apos;s Government are not committed to acceptance of this particular system, but they are committed by their memorandum of the 29th January, 1934, &quot; if general agreement is reached on all other (disarmament) issues to agree to the application of a system of permanent and automatic supervision to come into force with the obligations of the Convention.&quot;The draft proposals put forward by the United States Government in November 1934 for the control of Arms Manufacture and Trade provided for permanent and automatic supervision with a restricted and fairly anodyne system of local inspections. His Majesty&apos;s Government have decided not to accept such a system of supervision in connection with a restricted convention of this kind and have put forward a simpler system of documentary supervision at Geneva. They have, however, reiterated their willingness to accept permanent and automatic supervision with local inspections as part of a general limitation convention.It may be confidently expected that the French will make their concurrence in an Air Limitation agreement conditional upon the inclusion of provisions for permanent and automatic supervision with local inspections. Moreover, the German Chancellor, during the Berlin conversations with Sir John Simon and Mr. Eden, said that he was ready to accept the principle of permanent; and automatic supervision in connection with an arms limitation agreement.But the present aim is a limitation agreement confined to air armaments and to five Powers, and we recommend that an attempt should be made to come to some arrangement whereby a modified form of supervision should be exercised in connection with an Air Limitation agreement pending the constitution of \ an international supervisory organ which . would. eventually, assume, * the jjtaski)of
watching over the execution of the agreement. This modified form of supervision might be as follows : (i) The observance of the measures of air limitation now proposed should be vouched for by full and regular exchange of information between . . the five Powers in regard to the distribution, organisation and estab-lishments (both in material and in personnel) of their respective air forces. It may be observed that we have already published extensive information on these subjects and it should not be difficult to arrive at a uniform basis for exchange of information between the five Powers.(ii) Each of the five Powers should undertake to afford full facilities for investigations by the Air Attaches (or other officers) of the other parties to the Pact in order to satisfy themselves on the above points.Summary.7. While reserving the necessary latitude for our. negotiators, the general, procedure which we recommend that the Cabinet should approve is as follows : (1) Provided the French Government agree to the opening of negotiations between the five Locarno Powers on both the Air Pact and an Air Limitation Agreement, we should at once seek the formal agreement also of the Belgian, German and Italian Governments to the opening of negotiations and ask them as well as the French Government for their views on the list of questions contained in paragraph 4 above.(2) The view of His Majesty&apos;s Government on these questions should be as follows : (a) The Air Pact and the Agreement on Limitation of Air Strengths should.be embodied in separate agreements which should if possible enter into force simultaneously; and any attempt to go beyond the reference in the preamble to the British draft of the Air Pact to indiscriminate bombing should be reserved to a later date.(b) Belgium, France and Germany should be the only countries which should give us, receive from us and give against us guarantees under the-Air Pact.(c) We should endeavour to secure that the guarantees under the Air Pactwill operate where there has been an air attack in violation of Article 2 of the Treaty of Locarno, provided that this violation constitutes &quot; unprovoked aggression &quot;; if this proves impossible the matter could be reconsidered, though we could not cede the right ourselves to decide whether the circumstances in which the guarantee-operates have arisen.(d) The Air Pact should cover unprovoked aggression outside as well as.inside territorial waters.(e) The question of the possible inclusion of other Powers (notably Holland)-in the Pact is reserved for further consideration.(/) If we are urged to supplement the Pact by bi-lateral agreements of a technical nature, we must maintain that we must first secure at least an agreed draft of the Pact; the necessity for machinery for rendering it effective can be considered subsequently; we should refuse to agree to conclude with any Power a bi-lateral agreement to bring into force, pending the conclusion of the general Pact, the guarantees to be provided by it.(g) Limitation of aircraft should primarily be applied to numbers of aircraft in commission in combatant units, with a correlative limitation (i) on numbers of military aircraft in reseiwe or held for training or other&apos; purposes, and (ii) on numbers of military pilots.(h) and (i) The area in which limitation would operate should be themetropolitan territories of the United Kingdom, Belgium, France,.
Germany and Italy,&apos; it being for further consideration whether the North African territories of France and Italy should be regarded as part of the metropolitan territories of these countries; aircraft provided for operation from ships of war should be separately limited by regard to the size of the fleets of the Contracting Powers.(3) Pending the constitution of an international supervisory organ, we should attempt to secure the agreement of the five Powers to a modified form of supervision comprising full and regular exchange of information in regard to the distribution, organisation and establishments of the respective air forces, and an undertaking to afford full facilities for investigations by the Air Attaches of the parties to the Pact to satisfy themselves on these points.S. H. P. C.-L.June 21, 1935.
ANNEX.&apos; Treaty of Locarno (Extract).Article 2.Germany and Belgium, and also Germany and France, mutually undertake that they will in no case attack or invade each other or resort to war against each other.This stipulation shall not, however, apply in the case of 1. The exercise of the right of legitimate defence, that is to say, resistance to a violation of the undertaking contained in the previous paragraph or to a flagrant breach of articles 42 or 43 of the said Treaty of Versailles, if such breach constitutes an unprovoked act of aggression and by reason of the assembly of armed forces in the demilitarised zone immediate action is necessary.2. Action in pursuance of article 16 of the Covenant of the League of Nations.3. Action as the result of a decision taken by the Assembly or by the Council of the League of Nations or in pursuance of article 15, paragraph 7, of the Covenant of the League of Nations, provided that in this last event the action is directed against a State which was the first to attack.Article 4.1. If one of the high contracting parties alleges that a violation of article 2 of the present treaty or a breach of articles 42 or 43 of the Treaty of Versailles has been or is being committed, it shall bring the question at once before the Council of the League of Nations.2. As soon as the Council of the League of Nations is satisfied that such violation or breach has been committed, it will notify its finding without delay to the Powers signatory of the present treaty, who severally agree that in such case they will each of them come immediately to the assistance of the Power against whom the act complained of is directed.3. In case of a flagrant violation of article 2 of the present treaty or of a flagrant breach of articles 42 or 43 of the Treaty of Versailles by one of the high contracting parties, each of the other contracting parties hereby undertakes immediately to come to the help of the party against whom such a violation or breach has been directed as soon as the said Power has been able to satisfy itself that this violation constitutes an unprovoked act of aggression, and that by reason either of the crossing of the frontier or of the outbreak of hostilities or of the assembly of armed forces in the demilitarised zone immediate action is necessary. Nevertheless, the Council of the League of Nations, which will be seized of the question in accordance with the first paragraph of this article, will issue its findings, and the high contracting parties undertake to act in accordance with the recommendations of the Council, provided that they are concurred in by all the members other than the representatives of the parties which have engaged in hostilities.o

</content>
</cab>
