<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/1/0 images: 7-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(42) 64th Meeting 18th May 1942 

I. Naval, Military &amp; Air Operations. 

C.A.S Bomber. 170 sorties – weather bad – mining only 

Fighter. 12 : 8 : 16 for loss 9 (8 pilots). Weather again limiting. 

Coastal. Brunt. 500 sorties 18 lost. Shot down 5. Bombed 14 merchant ships. 

Main opn. v. Prinz Eugen. Found Sunday – picked up &amp; attacked 9pm by 27 Beaufonts. Possible 4 prob.2 hits. No certain report. Lost 7 Beaufonts &amp; some others. 

[Enemy 18 : 8 : 17. Ours totalling 40. Home Theatre losses for week] 

C.N.S Long wireless signal soon after attack – prob. Means damage. Reports not complete. 

Malta. Sp. Serviceability decreasg. rapidly – next re-inforcement. much needed. 

46 : 22 : 46 for loss {in air 8 : 11. } 

{on ground 2 : 6} 

Change in enemy tactics – fighters + few bombers – to wear us down, but these results show heavy loss to them. 

Report that 2 Fr. Aircraft had shot down off Algiers a Catalina preceding the carrier re-inforcing Malta. 

Egypt. Convoy JU.52. (14 – 20) intercepted. More than ½ destroyed &amp; the rest damaged. Full, but fear full of Italians only! 

Burma. A.V.G now gone China : ours to India. Dropping supplies to our troops &amp; bombg. their aerodromes. 

Pacific. 19 : 8 : 10 for loss 6 : 12 

Eastern Front 21/3 – 13/5. 

{Estimate of losses} Germ. claim 1932 admit 551. Losses of 

{of Aircraft. } Russ “ 1844 “ 206. aircraft. 

If claims right German mendacity factor = 3 times Russian. 

If losses “ Russian “ “ “ German. 

C.N.S. Shipping losses 32 ships sunk. 170.000 tons. 

2 belated 15.000 

Overdue 16.000 

Total 202.000 “ 

30 

Most in W. Atlantic. But 7 in returning (? Russian) convoy. 

U.S.Convoys. K.West – Hampton Rds. Convoy started 15 or 17/5 as planned. 

Caribbean – originally planned for 15/7 may come in on 15/6. 

U.S. have lent us 70 tankers – balance of earlier promise of 100 – prob = 90 by now. 

Queen Mary arrived with 9.500 Americans – in the Clyde, for tran-shipment to N.Ireland. 

Ital. attack on Alexandria with “human torpedoes” failed. 

C.I.G.S. Burma. Our forces are withdrawing over border into Assam. 

x/Remnants of 2 Chinese Divns. also moving into Assam. 

Bulk of Chinese forces now back in China – but elements still holding out much further south. Japs operating well inside China. 

S/S. India. Telegram fr. Assam indicates Chinese at x/ are rabble, tending to loot. Suggested disarming them. 

P.M. consult F.O. about this. 6 – 8.000 B. and 25 – 30.000 Indian are still with Alexander’s force. 

C.A.S A.V.G we think have gone to China. We have nothg. now in Burma and can only bomb over the mountains fr. India. 

Madagascar. 

F.O. – do we go on cleaning up when S.Africans arrive? 

P.M. Depends how long it will take. Don’t want to lock up for too long troops wh. might be going on to India, or M/East. Political negotiation may give us the guarantees we need. Choice to be made when Union Brigade arrives in Madagascar. 

Russia. Kerch offensive has pushed Russians back with fairly heavy losses. 

Kharkov. Russian attempt to widen base of salient to get K. To-day looks tho’ they are carrying on. G forced to throw in a fresh Armoured Divn. 

Otherwise no indications still of major offensive – this (Kerch) is not the beginning of a major push, wh. now cd. not start until 15/6/42. 

II Convoy to Russia. 

31 

P.M. 22 out of 25 got thro’ – but that. Does not reflect true risk. Convoy at 8 knots will be 6 – 7 days w’in range of air attack fr. Norway – because ice still further south &amp; no longer poss. to go N. of Bear Island. 

Lost Edinburgh one convoy &amp; Trinidad the next. 

Next convoy now due – and C.N.S. believe more may be lost than get through. 

The G. air reconnaissance is v. good in this area. Not only was Trinidad spotted &amp; sunk. But the covering force of cruises also spotted tho’ none hit. 

Ques is therefore whtr. to suspend until July – i.e. missing two convoys. We shd. have to inform Russians &amp; Roosevelt. 

C.N.S Suggest put to Stalin the slender chances of an 8 knot convoy movg. within range not only of JU.88 but also JU87 &amp; ask whtr. he wd prefer to lose a lot more now or wait 6 weeks and get much more through. 

C.A.S. G. have 100 Bombers there, of which 70 are long range, &amp; v. fine reconnaissance. Only chance of getting much through is bad weather. 

C.N.S. Weather prospects – on average of last 14 years – in 2 months much inferior weather. But Trinidad was sunk when visibility at sea level was poor. 

M/L. Cd convoys be enlarged after July? 

C.N.S. Yes. But diff. to make up the full loss - &amp; limits to what Archangel can take. 

L.P.S. Ask Stalin whtr. in desperate need - &amp; if so will he tell us what &amp; we will try to run a convoy in. 

M/W.T. Maisky saw me to-day &amp; urged need for trucks as well. 

F.O. We must decide - &amp; put all risks to Stalin even if we decide to send it. 

C.N.S. By end May 102 ships will be piled up waiting. We might in July put up the convoy to 50. 

F.O. We had grave doubts about the last, but 22 out of 25 got through. It may be difficult to persuade Americans &amp; Russians that we are wise. 

L.P.S. &amp; M/L. Suggested putting facts to Stalin before convoy sails. 

P.M. Not much time. Our duty is to fight our way through &amp; get as much as we can to those who are fighting this fearful battle against the German Army. 

1st Lord There is the risk to our naval strength, as well as poss. loss of merchant ships. 

32 

C.N.S. If we are going to do this, we are inclined to put in 35 in the convoy. 

L.P.S. Try to get as speedy a convoy as possible. 

M/W.T. We have selected the ships already &amp; its difficult to change them now. 

L.P. Send this convoy – tell Stalin all about it &amp; say if losses heavy in May we may have to defer the June convoy until July. 

M/Prod. Agreed. 

P.M. Press Stalin at the same time to send up his heavy bombers to help. 

Agreed. Send Convoy : tell Stalin we are comg. but explain risks urge him to send his bombers to attack their aerodromes : &amp; put the warning suggested by L.P. 

III Defence Arrangements in W. Africa. 

C. Govrs’ Conference in W. Africa lately modified by giving Chairman over-riding powers. But even so not satisfy. Govrs. &amp; G.O.C.’s often in disagreement &amp; no one person to decide. Agree therefore with C.O.S. recommendt. Draft Directive – not to exercise operational over Services. Service man – so as not to prejudge post-war question of closer union of W. or E. African Colonies. He wd. live at Lagos. Exact machinery to be worked out after arrival. 

L.P.S. Support need for co-ordination. But it is essential a job of civil co-ordination. Feel strongly therefore need is for a good civilian. 

M/P. Agree with this – and in so far as necessary to co-ordinate Services more difficult still for a Service man. 

P.M. Some minor M/State – who cd. co-ordinate relations with Belgiums, U.S. dir? 

M/W.T. Support suggn for co-ordination, of wh. v. great need. 

Agreed – shd. be civil, not military, man. 

+/P.M. But shd. there not also be a centralised military command. 

S/S. War. I believe it shd. be military man with [latent] operational control, as Layton has in Ceylon. 

C.I.G.S. Agreed with P.M. at x/ , whatever decision about the other man. 

F.O. Two quite separate jobs, both of wh. shd. be filled. 

First Lord. Wd. like military man because of diffy. Of findg. Civilian impervious 

33 

to trade interests.



</content>
</cab>
