<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/1/0 images: 10-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M. (42)72nd Meeting 8th June 1942 

Foreign Affairs 

AE. a) Reminder about need for F.O. to see in advance draft speeches on foreign affairs – particularly now we are getting nearer the point when post-war posn is being envisaged. 

Wohner’s speech in H/Lords Debate unfavourably noticed by P.M. – who asked Cranborne to keep an eye on him. 

P.M. Military matters (not concerned only write his own rpt.) – Ministers outside War Cabinet can &amp; shd. consult Ismay. 

Secretary to prepare a Minute for circulation. 

A.E. b) Talk with Sikorski – v. pleased with new Russian Treaty. Asked to meet Molotov on return. V. good thing that he should. 

M/L. Capini (Polish Minister/Trade) tells me that morale of Russian Army is being well maintained by regular arrival of our convoy supplies – less well impressed with American performance. 

P.M. Appreciation of Russian chances by J.I.C. cd. be circulated to War Cab. (but not sent out of country) with covering note by C.I.G.S. warning readers tht. this is slightly optimistic. 

A.E. c) Negotiations betwn. Turkey &amp; Germany: Not good. need watching. Perhaps try to get Molotov to talk with Turkish Ambassador. 

d) Tibet – telegrams. Purely political. 

P.M. Essential to give China something to keep them in good heart. 

Yugoslav Army Crisis. 

A.E. Military people in M/East incline too much to military view &amp; pay insufficient attention to our political diffces here. 

Amery. These offrs. were associated with Simovitch &amp; the decision to capitulate. They carry no conviction among their countrymen. They have got support fr. M/East mainly because made friends with our military there. 

A.E. Right course is to ship them home. 

C.I.G.S. 1200 men have upset the whole of the M/East. Clear the lot out. 

A.E. Handed round copies of draft telegram. 

41 

P.M. Too submissive. Civil power pre-dominates. The Govt. has the right to appoint their C.in.C &amp; we must accept view tht. he must be obeyed. Our offrs. had no right to encourage the dissident elements. 

L.P.S. Some of these offrs. are bad lots – 2 were in Russia &amp; suspected of espionage. 

W.O. see para 4 of Tel. 1147 from M/State. “Get Yugoslav Govt. to accept a reasonable solution or I will ship the lot home”. 

C.I.G.S. Then transfer them to some quieter Front. eg. India or S. Africa. 

A.E. Why? There is no trouble over those who are actually in the field. 

P.M. Telegraph more shortly and more strongly – saying that these 300 men are to be sent to this country at once. 

[There is no principle to be followed except to support the national Govt.] 

Agreed. 

Policy in Madagascar. 

P.M. Turns out tht. Barnett hasn’t got Annet’s authy. V. difft. pair of shoes. 

A.E. Three courses - a) stay put &amp; let Vichy Govt. stew. 

No more troops. But Smuts against &amp; insecure. 

b) capture the whole Island. Advantages obvious. Disadvantage – troops needed, long campaign. 

c) make terms with Vichy man in Madagascar. 

Tell Smuts what has happened, put alternative to him, &amp; let Platt Sturges &amp; Smuts get together and make proposals. 

Meantime Barnett shd. carry no message back. 

P.M. Let Platt go to M and discuss with Sturges. Then both go on to see Smuts. 

Bruce. Hasn’t Smuts indicated tht. he wdn’t have this plan even if it were backed up by the Govr. 

P.M. Not since he saw my further explanation. 

42 

P.M. Smuts diffy – his advisers were against sending the Brigatz. 

Tell whole story to Smuts – it isn’t fr. Govr therefore will do no more – we will send P &amp; S to talk it over with you. Had it come from Govr it had the basis of something wh. wd. have bn satisfy. in view of our anxiety to free our troops. 

C.I.G.S. Mayn’t the Govr. be behind this? 

A.E. Too thin, esp. if Smuts is hostile. 

W.O. Remember Platt favours doing a deal at Jibuti. He may be inclined therefore to favour finding a modus vivendi in Madagascar.



</content>
</cab>
