<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/1/0 images: 18-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(42) 88th Meeting 8th July 1942. 

Shipping Debate. 

L.P.S. If these Votes are down you can’t say talk on losses is out of order. Ques whtr. or not Govt. will answer is immaterial. You can’t answer in public. Nec. therefore to warn House at outset tht. if they talk on this we’ll go into Secret Session. Even then, shd. we give the losses? 

P.M. I wdn’t mind giving them a picture, in Secret. 

I don’t distrust H/Commons. 

K.W. Indiscretions – this may reach the enemy. 

P.M. Much smaller risk. Real trouble is publn. in Press. 

A.E. No indication tht. anything has got out thro’ Secret Sessions. 

P.M. Don’t take too low a view of H/Commons. 

L.P.S. View of you can’t have this in public. Apart fr. other things, it wd. not be poss. in public to give any explann. of U.S. posn. wh. might be interpreted in U.S. as criticism. 

P.M. What you are really discussing is American affair – their losses &amp; their potential gains fr. bldg. 

A.V.A. Ditto with shipbldg – wh. I wd. debate anywhere if allowed to give the figures. 

I have a v. good case – but am not allowed to make it in public. 

P.M. Wd. risk full disclosure rather than have criticism in public &amp; answer in Secret. 

Ch.Whip. Labour Party have asked for debate in public – but they haven’t asked for losses. 

L.P.S. Genl. dislike of Secret Sessions. Labour Party have asked for it; and a general feeling in H/Commons against Secret discussions. 

M/L. People thinkg. now we have bn. giving too much information – endangering the lives of our men. 

P.M. Say “we will not take this in public” : &amp; if they protest X/ [move into Secret Session and say why.] 

K.W. Unfortunate public effect. 

72 

P.M. Two or three newspapers will write what they wd. write anyway. 

Cannot be discussed satisfy. or thoroughly except in Secret. If House desires will move into S. Session to explain reasons. 

L.P. Cdn’t the reasons for not holdg. it in public be stated in public. You can’t give all the reasons – but surely you can say enough to satisfy the House. 

Agreed – withdraw X/ above. 

L.P.S. I will draft statement on business &amp; show it to P.M. tomorrow am. 

A.V.A. If we talk abt. bldg,. how much can we say about naval programme? 

P.M. Show the figures give globular results – “in every category we had replaced our losses”. 

P.M. Let L.P.S. explain reasons why we hold it in secret. Then let Sir A. Salter open. 

Salter. Difficult for me. H/C has complained before of not havg. genl. background. stated at outset, Wd. resent opening speech by person known to have bn. out of the House for 15 months. 

Genl. feeling tht. First Lord shd. open. 

P.M. Well. L.P.S. on Procedure 

First Ld. open on merits. 

Salter to wind up. 

73



</content>
</cab>
