<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/1/0 images: 44-44</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(42)142nd Meeting. 19th October 1942.

Smuts Address to Parliament.

P.M. All arrangements made.

M/I. Any objn. to announcg. prev. day on B.B.C. – so tht. S.Africa can hear?

P.M. Unwise (C.A.S. agreed). Better to make records and relay later.

M/I. It is being relayed – and no one will know in advance.

Agreed – better relay record later to S. Africa. No announcement before 1p.m. news and no summary in earlier news bulletins.

P.M. Accommodation – to be restricted to B. Commonwealth visitors. i.e. exclude Diplomatic Corps.

Commonwealth Trade Union Conference.

S/Doms. Citrine wants conf. with U.K. + 4 Doms. T.U.’s. Sometime in April.

Small nos. fr. all parts of Empire.

Smuts. We have approved : a good thing.

Agreed.

Man Power: Lowering Age to 18. for call-up to Services.

L.P. Last Proclamation affected all who had reached 18 at date.

Instead of waiting another 6 months we propose another Procln. after 3 months concerning all who became 18 between 30/6 and 22/10.

Further suggn. – amend law so as to enable preliminaries to be got over before 18 is reached. Machinery proposal : but may be criticised.

L.P.S. Care needed in drafting Bill to make it clear tht. we aren’t calling up boys of 17.

W.O. Hitherto we have allowed voluntary enlistment 6 months below compulsory age.

May we now enlist volunteers at 17½? Yes.

Agreed.

American Technical Mission to India. 164

L.S.A. Attentn. to para 4 of final recommdion. in para 9.

R.Mudaliar. Some recommdns. can’t be implemented because of some bottlenecks.

V. cautious abt. wh. can be adopted w’out interfering with existg. programmes.

Read extract fr. report fr. Indian M/Supply. Risk of going too fast and getting involved in larger projects wh. will be embarrassing.

x/ No pressure fr. here in G/India merely because U.S. have recommended.

W.O. Endorse x/. U.S. tendency to intervene industrially in spheres hitherto ours’.

Took note with approval.

Strike in Belfast.

P.M. Losing a Stirling a day.

M.A.P. Cttee has bn. set up : sitting today. Meanwhile boiler-makers H &amp; W have gone back. Mtg. strikers due this p.m. Total now out 8.000 miners 900 boiler-makers.

H.O. By 5 p.m. little development – slight trickle back to work. Hope more may return tomorrow.

K.W. M/L. Strong views – no action wh. wd. weaken T.U. influence. Stand aside.

Leggett. When Enquiry set up, feared large extension of strike. Felt Court wd. help to stop that. Impression now tht. position is improving.

P.M. Disgrace to N. Ireland – hope Govt. feel it.

Weakness there – no conscription in N.Ireland.

L.P. We have in N.I. departed fr. policy to wh. we have adhered in Tyneside strike.

Took note.

</content>
</cab>
