<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/12/14 images: 120-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT ^Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1940.SECRET Copy No.   0W.P. (40) 384.(Also CCS. (40) 762.)September 25, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to /ensure the secrecy of this document, jWAR CABINET.ORGANISATION OF ALLIED NAVAL, ARMY AND air contingents.Ninth Weekly Report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee.IN accordance with the Prime Ministers instructions, we submit thefollowing report on the Organisation of Allied Naval, Army and air contingents.(Signed) C. L. N. NEW ALL.DUDLEY POUND.J. G. DILL.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,September 25, 1940.A-FRENCH.(i) Navy.Free French Naval Force.Number of Frenchmen who have joined Free French Naval Force up tothe 10th September : 120 Officers.40 Aspirants.2,012 Ratings.Total   ...   2,172Increase on figure last reported 293.2. The small flow of volunteers to transfer from the Royal Navy to theFree French Naval Force continues.   These transfers are being encouraged.3. The minesweeper Chevreuil, previously in commission in the Royal Navy,has now been commissioned by the Free French Force. The policy of turning overas many as possible of the French ships commissioned by us to the Free french navy, as and when Admiral Muselier can man them, is in abeyance in the caseof vessels operating, until the strategic situation changes. 2X760 J &quot;r
4. Morale. Reports continue to indicate that active employment will leadto improvement in discipline and morale.French Ships taken over by the Royal Navy.5.   The following French officers and men are now in the Royal Navy:  29 Officers.598 Ratings.Total   ...     6276. Morale and Discipline continue to be fairly good and are tending toimprove.The dislike for the wearing of the French Tricolour with the White Ensignis again reported. Some men in the French submarine chasers have gone so faras to put in a request to their Commanding Officers for the Tricolour to be hauleddown. They feel this connects them in some way with the Free French Force.They are being told that this is a misconception of the facts and that the flyingof the Tricolour is merely an indication that the ships remain French.French Officers and Men awaiting Repatriation in Camps.7. Welfare work in the camps, such as the provision of recreational gearand of additional canteens, is reported to be having a beneficial effect on morale.Volunteers for harvest work have fallen off very considerably as a result of a recent decision of the military authorities to appropriate a part of the pay as a set-off against food and transport charges.8. The process of segregating undesirables continues; the men are being concentrated in Arrowe Park Camp together with recovered deserters.9. The newspaper France continues to be popular, but some recent articlesof extreme left-wing tendency are reported to have had an adverse influence on recruiting and morale.   This has been pointed out to de Gaulle&apos;s Headquarters.(ii) Army.Farnborough.10.   Strength. Foreign Legion :Officers, 7;O.Rs., 81.Other Units :Officers, 41;O.Rs., 679.Equipment. A further issue of LMG&apos;s was made during the week, alsoone 75 m.m. gun which now brings the Battery up to four-gun strength.Web equipment has been issued to all ranks.Training. One British P.T. Sergeant and two British Signal Instructorshave been attached.Morale. Excellent.Seamarts Hospital. 25, Gordon Street, W.C.1.11.   Strength. Officers. N.C.Os. O.Rs.Armee de Terre ...... 22 40 137Air Force       ......... 14 8 16Marine............ 2 10 16538 58 318Morale. Good.
White City.12. The French wounded left this camp on the 17th September forembarkation on the hospital ships Canada and Sphynx. French woundedhave also been evacuated from military and civil hospitals for repatriation inthese ships.(iii) Air Force.13. The proposal to form a Free French Training Centre for all free french Flying personnel in this country has had to be abandoned as the Frenchcannot find the required number of operational flying instructors.14. Admiral Muselier however, on behalf of General de Gaulle, and ColonelWouters, on behalf of the Belgian authorities, have agreed to a suggestion whichis being actively examined that a small flying training school should be established in the near future, at which some 40 selected French pupil pilots and a small number of Belgian pupil pilots should be trained under French Elementary FlyingInstructors and Belgian (E.A.F.V.E.) Secondary Flying Instructors; the latterinstructors in due course to give operational flying instruction. This scheme,like the earlier scheme, will necessitate the provision by the R.A.F. of all material and maintenance personnel.15. It is also proposed that as soon as possible all other Free Frenchpersonnel (except the Headquarters Staff) should gradually be concentrated, onthe Station selected for the Flying Training School, and then be given suchinstruction in ground duties as can be arranged, pending a decision as to whetheror not they can be received and trained in Canada. In this matter General de gaulle has approached the Canadian authorities in London directly. All free french personnel at the Centre and School should, it is agreed, receive systematicinstruction in the English language.16. In the meantime it is hoped to send to R.A.F. Squadrons a few free french pilots who have.passed through O.T.U.&apos;s and to send others to a fighterO.T.U. &quot;B. POLES.(i) Navy.17.   Morale and discipline continue to be excellent.18.   The destroyer Nerissa is being given to the Polish Navy to man.(ii) Army.19. Strength-Officers, 3,631; other ranks, 13,321.Equipment. Issued during the week : Motor Cycles        .......      ......... 8Oars, 2-str. utility...       ...       ...       ...       ... 2Trucks, 15 cwt., 4-whld., G.S.......... 4Lorries, 30 cwt., G.S............. 220.   Accommodation. Winter. &apos;Polish H.Q. have been asked to decide on their billeting plans in theFife-Angus Sector as soon as possible, in order that arrangements to supplementexisting accommodation by means of Nyssen huts may be put in hand withoutdelay.21. Employment. (a) On the 11th instant General Lord Gort inspected thePolish troops at Biggar, Crawford and Douglas, and the Polish Supply depot at Abington.(b) On the 14th instant General Sikorski was accompanied on a visit to theSouth Coast Defences between Brighton and Bognor Regis by Brigadier Burrows,commanding the Sector.22.   Training. General Zajac, who will probably be given the 4th CadreBrigade, is doing 14 days attachment to H.Q., 5th Division.   The work of the[21760] B 2
British Training Cadres in the Polish Camps is progressing favourably, andLiaison attachments to Infantry and Artillery of the 5th Division have beenarranged for 4 Field and 9 Junior officers.The attachment of Polish officers to 3rd Cavalry Training Regiment hasbeen extended.At a recent meeting of the Wireless Telegraphy Board with TechnicalRepresentatives of the Polish General Staff it was decided to place the latter intouch with British experts, to examine various innovations in wireless equipment for which the Poles are responsible.23. On the 17th September the Polish Staff Course visited the R.M.C.,Camberley, saw a demonstration of a Division at war strength at Aldershot,visited the Tank Corps Training Centre, and the Staff College, Camberley, wherethey were addressed by the Commandant.24. Welfare. English classes have been in full swing, and forty teachershave been visiting the camps daily from Glasgow, their bus fares being paid bythe British Council.A special grant has been made by the War Office of  250 for sportsequipment, and 100 sets of football kit and 100 footballs have been issued.(iii) Air Force.25. Nos. 300 and 301 Bomber Squadrons are now taking part in operations of the Bomber Command. So far they have been employed mainly on attacks against the French Channel ports. Nos. 304 and 305 Bomber Squadronscontinue their training at Bramcote, while the reserve crews for the four bomber squadrons are being trained at Hucknall and Benson.26. Nos. 302 and 303 Fighter Squadrons, particularly the latter, have been heavily engaged in air operations during the past week. No. 303 Squadron iscredited with over 70 aircraft shot down. The British Commanding Officersreport that the morale of the Polish pilots is excellent and their bravery muchabove the average. Both Squadrons have had casualties amounting altogetherto 7 pilots killed and 11 missing. Nos. 306, 307 and 308 Fighter Squadronscontinue their training at Air Force Stations and will probably be operationallyfit within three weeks.27. The selection of Polish pilots for non-operational flying dutiescontinues. Already nearly 300 have been earmarked. Similarly, the selection of ground personnel for employment in British units and establishments continues.28. It has been decided to despatch a Polish Section, comprising 52 pilots,to operate on the ferry service between Takoradi and Egypt. These pilots willbe formed into a composite Polish unit within the British establishment.29. Excellent reports continue to be received by all R.A.F. StationCommanders who have Poles on their Stations. They state that their work isexcellent and their morale and discipline good.G. DUTCH.(i) Navy.30. Morale and discipline continue to be very satisfactory, except for thematter mentioned in the following paragraph.31. It is reported by the Nore Command that the Dutch Admiralty haveissued an order forbidding officers and men to correspond with Holland, whichthey have been doing through Switzerland and other channels. This has causedsome resentment.   The matter is being investigated.(ii) Army.32.   Strength.-Porthcawl:  54 Officers, 1,073 ORs.Ruperra Castle, Cardiff : 19 Officers, 479 O.Rs.
Training. Progress has been made with preliminary training of recruits,and company training for that portion of the Battalion not employed on defenceduties. The Battalion carried out an all-day combined exercise with the5th London Infantry Brigade.Welfare. Satisfactory.Morale. Continues high.(iii) Air Force.33. A request has been made by Air Civil Administration for the releaseof 4 pilots and 2 ground mechanics previously employed by K.L.M. who are now serving with Coastal Command. These are wanted for operation with a sectionof the service United Kingdom-West Africa-Khartoum-Cairo, on whichDouglas D.C.&apos;s are being used. Coastal Command and the Netherlands NavalMission are considering this request.D. CZECHS.(i) Army.34. Strength. Cholmondeley : 670 officers, 2,537 O.Rs. Sutton Coldfield :539 O.Rs.Training :Testing of motor transport drivers has been continued and 100 men have obtained driving licences. The training of the Field Battery has commenced and infantry units have made good progress. Firing on thirty yard range started on the 11th September.(ii) Air Force.35. No. 310 Fighter Squadron continues to do good work and has now26 German aircraft shot down to its credit. The Commanding Officer,Major Hess, who has led the Squadron so successfully had a narrow escape fromdeath when he was forced to&apos;bafe out at only 400 feet. No. 312 Fighter Squadronhas formed with one Flight at Duxford but is still short of skilled personnel for the second Flight.36. No. 311 Bomber Squadron has been in action and carried out successfulbombing operations in the Brussels37.   The morale in the service units is high.38. There are approximately 70 experienced fighter pilots at the Czecho-Slovak Depot who will be absorbed into O.T.U.&apos;s at a rate which will ensurethat the service Squadrons are maintained at full strength.39. In order to obtain more skilled airmen the Czechoslovak Army isreleasing skilled mechanics for the Czechoslovak Air Force who are capable of passing the Royal Air Force trade classification tests. It is hoped in this mannerto make up deficiencies in skilled personnel.E. NORWEGIANS.(i) Navy.40. Morale and discipline continues to be fairly good. It has been notedthat courses of instruction in our shore establishments result in marked improve-raent in the bearing and behaviour of officers and men.(ii) Army.41.   Strength.-^ officers, 1,213 O.Rs., 4 nurses.Training. Company training schemes are being carried out. Defenceduties on local aerodrome.Morale. Remains very satisfactory.
(iii) Air Force.42. The Norwegian Naval and Military Missions have asked if they canbe supplied with 5 Curtiss P. 40&apos;s in Canada in order that they may converttheir pilots and ground crews to this type before they come to the UnitedKingdom, where they are to be equipped with this type. This request is beingconsidered.F. BELGIANS.(i) Army.43.   Strength. 42 Officers, 748 ORs., 5 nurses.Reorganization. The organization of the second active company is nowcomplete.Employment. Recruit and company training.Pioneer company constructing defences at Tenby.Welfare. Satisfactory.Morale. Good.(ii) Air Force.44. There is nothing further to report except that P/O Doutrepont was shot down and killed by enemy action on the 15th September, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
