<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/38/35 images: 336-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. COPY NO;----                                      WAR CABINET 7^w.P.(u3) 285.J^h^June, 19U3. POST-WAR SHIPPING POLICY.PROPOSED DEBATE IN THE HOUSE OF COMMONS.Memorandum by the Minister of War Transport.It is proposed that on the points expected to bo raised theGovernment Spokesman should take the following line:-1 .     General object of H.M. Governments policy.(l)     This country must continue to serve the world with a large and efficient mercantile marine.(ii)    H8M. Government will be prepared to collaborate with other likeminded Governments in establishing conditions under which theshipping of the world can be efficiently and economically carried on.2.      Pre-war policy.(i)     The experience of this and every other country showed thatprosperity for shipping is not to be attained by measures in theshipping field alone.      The basic difficulties faced by our shipping in the inter-war years were not the fault of either shipowners orof Government shipping policyB      The root of the trouble lay in theinstability of international trade, periods of strong demand for ships alternating with long periods of depression.      Shippingsubsidies aggravated the difficulties*(.ii)    H.M. Government, in defence of the British merchant fleetrultimately resorted to subsidies themselves;    but they backed allefforts to bring about a measure of stability on the basis of&quot;international collaboration in the shipping industry.3.     Policy in the post-war worlds(i) The main hope of a prosperous merchant fleet must lie in theexpansion of world commerce.     As a shipping nation we must welcome the indications at the Hot Springs Food Conference of the sense ofresponsibility among the United Nations for establishing conditionsof world trade after the war under which international trade canflourish,(ii) As against our competitors, we must rely primarily upon the ability of our ships and their personnel to give to the world the efficient and economic services required.(If it should be claimed that the Disposal Scheme by makingGovernment built ships available to shipowners for deferred purchasehas prejudiced the issue of public ownership this should be denied,^hat issue will, of course, be settled by Parliament when the time&apos; -craes, - and nothing in the Whit^P^p^.. will in any way hamper thefull freedom of Parliament to &quot;male he decisions which it thinksright.     Those owners who have lost ships in the service of thecountry and who take up replacements under the scheme are therebyin no different position from those who have not lost their ships.On the other hand, the issue would have been prejudiced if theGovernment had elected to retain the ships built during the war to replace losses).

(iii) After the war is over in Europe, arrangements for the controland use of shipping will need to he&apos; continued for a time.    It is notpossible at present to say what form those arrangements will takebut they will require a high degree of collaboration between allthe United Nations, comparable to that achieved during the war.The necessity for such collaboration has already been recognised by the United Nations in such instruments as the resolutions adopted at the St. James!s Palace Conference in 1941 and again inthe recommendations of the Pood Conference which recently tookplace in the United States.British shipping will he ready to do its part in a scheme whichdistributes the common shipping tasks fairly among all the united nations;    and H.M. Government intend to seek such a scheme throughdiscussion with other Maritime powers of the United Nations.(iv) After the interim period, some of the shipping problems whichwere recognised before the war will again have to be faced, but therewill also be new problems.    For instance those resulting from thedevelopment of civil air transport.    It cannot be expected thatthese problems will be solved by quoting old shibboleths but on theother, hand there is no reason to suppose that sound shippingprinciples will prove to be inapplicable in the future.    In a peaceful and prosperous world there will be great demand for shipping, great opportunities for efficient shipping communities,and heavy responsibilities upon the shipping powers of the world to make sure that their policies serve the general interest oftraders and consumers.In all these respects H.M. Government intends to play a leading part? but are not prepared, in present circumstances, to definetheir policy on particular issues, nor, in advance of opportunityto discuss with the Dominion or other interested Governments, to commit themselves to a specific course of action to attain the objectives defined.(Note.    The attitude of the U.S.A.  in regard to shipping in thepost-war world is of vital importance, as the present possessor of.the largest merchant fleet and building facilities.    There is reasonto suppose that the United States is aware of the limitations ontheir shipping aspirations imposed by their high capital and operational costs;    but the whole question wants quiet discussionwith responsible Americans before we can be committed to anyparticular line of policy.)U-       Employment at Sea.Reference will be made by the Government speakers to various matters affecting employment at sea, on which no point arises for reference to the Cabinet.L.U[ NISTRY OP WAR TRANSPORT,I 1     30TH JUNE,  19U-3.






</content>
</cab>
