<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/48/19 images: 188-193</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.........&amp;kb JI&amp;!^:..,...:........  /TOP secret copy No.W.M. (Uh) 170TH CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 6Confidential Annex(18th December, 19kk - 12 Noon)FOREIGN AFFAIRSPoland(previous reference:w.M.(UU) 169thConclusions)THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs informed the War Cabinet of the latest developments in connection with Poland.At their meeting on 16th December (W.M.(4U)169th Conclusions) the War Cabinet had approved thedespatch by the Prime Minister of a telegram .to president Roosevelt inviting him to carry out at oncehis proposal to send a message to Premier Stalinsuggesting that he postpone any positive action on thePolish question until the three leaders could get together, and adding that nothing but good could comefrom the publication of the four- points in the presidents letter of 17th November to M. Mikolajczyk,outlining American policy in regard to Poland.The President had accepted the Prime Ministersuggestion, and the Foreign Secretary read to the. ,Vfeir Cabinet the text of his telegram No. 675 to PremStalin, v/hich was wholly satisfactory from our pointof view.During the night, however, we had received from washington the text of the statement which the state department now proposed to issue.     That statement was not on the lines which the President had indicatedin his telegram to. Premier Stalin, and did not meetthe case adequately so far as we were concerned.      Inparticular, it did not express approval of animmediate     settlement by mutual agreement and omittedany reference to compensation from Germany to Poland&apos;for the transfer to the U.S-S.R. of the area east ofthe Curzon Line.     Moreover, the reference which it contained to the facilitation of transfers to and fromPolish territories of national minorities in connectionwith the new frontiers of the Polish State wasequivocally worded, and was open to the constructionthat we had in mind only transfers e.g. of Poles fromthe Ukraine.     There was some risk that the statement as framed might be read as disclosing disagreementbetv/een the Three Great Powers.     - -The Foreign Secretary read to the Wa*r Cabinetthe terms of a drafting amendment which Lord Halifaxhad suggested, but the general sense of the War Cabinet.was that, while an improvement, it did not fully meetthe case.

The/State Department proposed to make/theirannouncement at 5 p.m. this evening.     He proposedto urge as strongly as possible the replacement ofparagraph 2 of their draft statement by -paragraph 2of the statement contained in the,-tele gram from&apos;President Roosevelt to Premier.Stalin, which ran asfollows:-&quot;(2) In regard to the question of futurefrontiers of Poland, the JJnited States, althoughconsidering it desirable that territorial questionsawait the general post-war settlement, recognizesthat a settlement before that time is in the  &quot;interest of the common war effort and thereforewould have no objection if the territorial questions involved in the Polish situation, including theproposed compensation from Germany,, were settled by mutual agreement between the^ parties&apos; directly concerned.&quot; sThe suggestion was also made, and met withthe full support of the War Cabinet, that, in the &apos;    - -event of its proving impossible to secure amendmentof the U.S. statement on the above lines, we should at any rate try to secure the amendment of theequivocal sentence about transfers of population,so as to make it clear that the movement of populationcontemplated was between Poland and Russia,,     THEFOREIGN SECRETARY said that he would do his best to .secure an amendment of this nature.The War Cabinet -Approved the course of action proposedby the Foreign Secretary,Offices of- the War Cabinet, S.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
