<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/10/8 images: 84-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT,^ THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 -GOVERNMENT,TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that sijecial care may he takento ensure the secrecy of this document.C R E t20th,  19^ COPY NO.gAg&amp;L POLICY IN THE EVENT OF,,WAR WITH SPAIN,Note h;y First Lord of the Admiralty,,I circulate the attached telegram for thermation of my colleagues.i ii:ralty, s.w. i,ruly 20th?19UO.

OUT.DATE:  15.7.40.! FROM: Admiralty.Following is outline plan for war with Spain,A. It is in ended to maintain force &quot;based on Gibraltarfor control of Straits as long as naval base can be used.Composition of this force depends on circumstances at the timebut will for the present consist of Force H.B. As soon as possible after the outbreak of waroperations against Vigo, Cadiz and Ferrol will be carried out.Separate signal will follow on these operations.C. Plans are now being prepared and forces detailed forseizing Azores and Cape Verde Islands, and it is intended todo this as soon as possible after outbreak of war.   Risk ofrupture of relations with Portugal will be accepted as it isanticipated that in any case Portugal will be overrun by Spainmid military&apos;assistance to defend her is beyond our resources.D. Seizure of Canaries is too great an undertaking atpresent but offensive operations against these islands are contemplated.E. If Gibraltar becomes untenable, Gibraltar force willprobably be moved partly to Freetown and partly to UnitedKingdom depending on circumstances.    13th Destroyer Flotillawill probably be based on Azores as soon as these Islands havebeen seized.F. Offensive minelaying off ports of North Ifest Spainwill be carried out as opportunity permits under Admiraltyorders.,     A stock of magnetic mines is being sent to Gibraltarnow and an appreciation on general mining policy against Spainis being forwarded to Commander in Chief, Western Approaches,Can CMediterranean and F.O.C.N.A.  for guidance in framingoperations0G. No changes in present station limits are contemplatedand   F.CCN.A. will remain at Gibraltar with the title of ViceAdmiral Gibraltar.     As soon as a base is established in the azores another Flag Officer with his flag flying on shore inthe Azores will be appointed as F.0.C.N.A* 1826/15.ME S S A G E.MOST.....SECRET.TO: C.in home Fleet 63C. in CNore 888Cin Ctortsmouth 392Cin C,Western Approaches 2+89Cin CMediterranean 106.Coin Co South Atlantic 635F.O.C. N.A.  692C.in C.China 150Cin CAmerica and west Indies 265Coin CEast Indies 491V.A. Force H 40NAVAL CYPHER D




</content>
</cab>
