<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/9/0 images: 10-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF  HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1947SECRET Copy No.  4CM. (37)2nd conclusions cabinet 2 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, Qth January, 1947, at 2-30 p.m.Present: 1The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison.Secretary  of  State  for  dominion the Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.RightThe Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P.,  Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T. Williams,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Hall, FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.The Right Hon. Sir HartlevShawcross, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.Mr. J. B. Hynd, M.P., Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster.Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.[32993-2]Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.
CABINET 2 (^7)Minute: - Subject: pQg^1      Peace Treaties ....      ....      ....      .... &apos;    ...       ....      ....      11Italy.Balkan States and Finland.2      Germany....      ....      ....      ....      .... .....     ....      11Preparations for Meeting of Foreign Ministers in Moscow.Socialisation of Ruhr Industries.3      Austria .... .    ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      13.,Peace Treaty.4      Spain     ............      ....       .... ....      ....      13.5.     France   ....      ....      .........   .....      ....      ....      ....      14Economic Co-operation.8      United Nations....      ....      ....      ....      ....       ....      ....      15Use of Veto.7      Albania ....      ....      .........................      16Freedom of Passage in the Corfu Channel.8      Egypt......     ....      ........      ....      .... 169      Publication of Cabinet Business     ....      ....       ....      ....      16
peace treaties.(previous reference:G.M.(47)lstConclusions,Minute 1.)Italy.Balkan Statesand Finland.1.   The  Cabinet discussed the report which the Foreign-Secretary had made at their meeting on 2nd Ja,january on the peace treaties with Italy, Bulgaria, Hungary, Roumania and Finland.The First Lord of the Admiralty reported that no decision had yet been taken to use for target practice the battleship which wasto be allotted to us under the plan for the dispersal of the italian fleet. This decision could not be taken until the vessel had beenreceived and examined. He undertook to consult the foreign secretary and the Prime Minister before approving any recommen-dation that it should be used for target practice.It was asked whether the conclusion of these Treaties wouldenable us to develop our trade with Finland. In particular, would it be easier for us in future to obtain timber from that country?The Cabinet were informed that much would depend on our ability to supply the goods or credits that Finland needed. the signature of the Treaty and the settlement of the reparations issueshould, however, create more stable conditions which would afford a better prospect of re-establishing our trading connections.This applied equally to the Balkan States. They were not anxious to remain dependent on the Soviet economy; and the signa-ture of the Treaties would give us good opportunities for re-openingour trade with Soutb-Eastern Europe. Surveys would at once beundertaken to assess the long-term possibilities of this trade.There were also prospects of reviving trade with Yugoslavia.From the point of view of foreign exchange, it would be preferable to buy timber from Yugoslavia than from Sweden. -The cabinet were informed that the Ministry of Food were sending a repre-sentative to explore the possibilities of obtaining further food supplies from Yugoslavia.In further discussion it was said that many of these countries would wish to buy from us, in return for their exports, capital goods including heavy electrical equipment; and our own require-ments for such equipment were so urgent that we could ill afford to spare more of it for export. It was pointed out that, without increasing the total quantity allocated for export, much could bedone by influencing the direction of those exports so as to securethe maximum advantage to our balance of trade.The Cabinet Agreed that, in the light of the Economic Survey for 1947now under consideration by Ministers, the OverseasEconomic Policy Committee should review the prospects of reviving British trade with Italy, Yugoslavia, the balkan States and Finland, following the conclusion ofPeace Treaties with those countries.Gemiany.preparations for, Meetingof foreign ministers in moscow.(previous reference:CM. (47) 1stConclusions,Minute 2.)32993-2. The Cabinet discussed the report which the Foreign Secre-tary had made at their meeting on 2nd January on the preparations to be made for the discussion of Germany at the forthcoming meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers in Moscow.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster referred to thepossibility that the Soviet Government would press their demandfor reparations from current production in Germany in return forsome concessions in the direction of treating Germany as aneconomic unit. Fie hoped that we should be slow to accept any proposals for taking reparations from current production, since this was bound to impose a further substantial delay on Germany&apos;industrial recovery. He himself hoped that in the Moscowdiscussions opportunity might be taken to reduce, rather thanincrease, the burden imposed by reparations on the German economy.He was preparing, for consideration by Ministers, an appreciation of the cost of existing reparations policy. In illustration of this,-2 b 2
he said that 30,000 men would be occupied for two years indismantling the industrial plants already earmarked for reparation deliveries.The Cabinet agreed that, in the light of the proposals for theeconomic fusion of the British and United. States Zones and other changes which had taken place in Germany since the PotsdamConference, the Departments directly concerned should collaborate:in preparing an up-to-date appreciation of reparations policy forconsideration by Ministers before the Moscow meeting.Other points made in discussion were : -(a) No precise information was available of the amount ofindustrial plant and equipment which had been removed by theSoviet authorities from Eastern Germany.(6). &quot;We ourselves had removed very little industrial equipment from Germany. We had, however, obtained a considerable amountof valuable information about German patents and industrialprocesses; and steps were being taken to make this information available to British industry. We had also brought to this country a number of specially-skilled German technicians.(c) The Foreign Secretary had agreed to discuss with DominionHigh Commissioners means of keeping Dominion Governments intouch with the progress of the preparations for the Moscow meeting.He was anxious that their views should be ascertained at an early stage in the formulation of policy, even though further and moreformal consultations might be required with these and other interested Governments after the Moscow meeting.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for officials ofthe Foreign Office, Treasury, Board of Trade andControl Office to undertake a review of reparationspolicy for submission to Ministers as part of the generalbrief for the British Delegation at the forthcoming meeting of Foreign Ministers in Moscow.The Cabinet&apos;s attention was drawn to a news report that theGovernment had decided to delay the appointment of Germancustodians for the principal industries of the Ruhr.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster recalled that theUnited States authorities had indicated that they would raise noobjection to a policy of socialising the principal Ruhr industriesif the initiative for such a policy came from the Germans, TheBritish Element in the Control Commission for Germany had repre-sented to him that, in view of this, there might be advantages intaking informal soundings to see whether some of the political leaders in Germany would be ready to make public declarationsaccepting the principle of public ownership for these industries.It seemed that some information about these representations had become known to the Press. In fact there need be no delay inproceeding with the appointment of custodians. A list of candi-dates for appointment was now available for consideration by theCabinet.In discussion the view was expressed that it would be adyan-tageous if the Government could, without delay, announce some definite action in pursuance of their policy for socialising theprincipal industries of the Ruhr.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, andreport to the Cabinet whether steps could not now betaken to proceed with the appointment of Germancustodians for the principal Ruhr industries.socialisation of ruhr industries.(previous reference:CM. (46) 105thConclusions,Minute 2.)
13cm. (my 2.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster to reportto the Prime Minister the results of the enquiries whichhe had instituted with a view to ascertaining howinformation had reached the Press about the represen-tations made to him in this matter by his advisers inGermany.Austria.Peace Treaty.(previous reference erence:CM. (47) 1stConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Home Secretary asked whether, in the forthcoming discussion of the pea.ce settlement for Austria, it would be our policy to seek to create an Austria which would be a viable economic unit.Austria&apos;s difficulties after the last war had arisen mainly fromthe fact that the territory left to her by the Peace Treaties hadnot been sufficient to support the large industrial area of Vienna.The Foreign Secretary said that he could not ask that the new treaty should confer any territorial advantage on Austria. her economic difficulties after the last war had, however, arisen largely from the fact that she was surrounded by a ring of high-tariffcountries, and it was certainly his policy to avoid the re-creationof those tariff barriers. Thus, he had already mentioned in theCabinet&apos;s discussion on 2nd January his view that we should press for a right of cabotage to be conceded to riparian States on the danube. He already saw indications of a movement towardseconomic co-operation, rather than competition, between the coun-tries of the Danube Basin. And, in connection with the inter-national regime to be established at Trieste, agreements were tobe concluded about railway facilities over an area stretching from south Poland to the Adriatic. The agreement with Italy over theSouth Tyrol should also assist the Austrian economy. Finally, therewere signs that the Soviet Government might in future adopt amore benevolent attitude towards proposals for promoting inter-national economic co-operation in this area.The Cabinet-Took note with approval of the Foreign Secretary&apos;sstatement.Spain. 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the(Previous Foreign Secretary (CP. (47) 2) on the implications for this countryReferences: of imposing economic sanctions against Spain. This showed the cm. (46) 104th serious effects on our economy of an interruption of our trade with conclusions, Spain. It pointed out that the effect of such sanctions could notMinute l, and be rapid unless they were universally applied, and there seemedCM. (47) 1st little prospect that all countries would co-operate in imposing them.Conclusions, They would probably impair our long-term commercial relationsMinute 4.)&apos; with Spain; and. the burden of enforcing them would fall verylargely on us.The Cabinet were informed that to patrol the 1,800 miles of spanish coast 26 naval craft would be required in addition toR.A.F. assistance.In discussion there was general agreement about the impor-tance to our economy of the supplies which we drew from Spain,particularly of fertilisers and iron ore. From the long-term pointof view, there was also a large potential market for us in supplyingSpain&apos;s need for machinery, &amp;c, for her own economic development.From the angle of our own economic interests, it was clear that wecould ill afford to impose economic sanctions on Spain.The view was, however, expressed that these arguments appliedwith special force if sanctions were not applied by all countries.If they could be universally applied and produced quick results,a regime might be established in Spain which would be well disposed to us and this might be to our long-term commercial advantage.
On the other hand it was argued that, if the existing regime wereoverthrown by sanctions, it was uncertain what type of government might be establishment in its place and the feelings of the Spanishpeople might have been alienated by our action.x The political arguments were similarly open to challenge. Ithad been said that the imposition of sanctions would tend tostrengthen public support for the Franco regime in Spain. On theother hand, Spanish national pride had not rejected the externalinterventions which had brought Franco to power.There was no doubt that the most effective economic sanctionwould be the deprivation of oil supplies. This, however, could notbe made effective without the full co-operation of the United StatesGovernment, and there was no assurance that this would be forth-coming.The overriding question for the United Nations as a whole was,however, whether it would be expedient to apply economic sanctionsfor the purpose of precipitating a change in the conduct of a country&apos;s internal affairs. If it could be said that the existingpolitical regime in Spain constituted a danger to world peace, all members of the United Nations would be under an obligation underthe Charter to co-operate in imposing sanctions. In fact, however,it could not be maintained that the present situation in Spainconstituted a danger to world peace; and we should be well advised to make that our main ground for resisting the application of sanctions to Spain.The Cabinet were informed that, as a result of the resolution passed by the Assembly regarding the withdrawal of diplomatic representatives from Spain, this question was not likely to beraised again in the United Nations for some little time. It wasagreed that we should not ourselves take any initiative in raisingin the United Nations the possibility of applying economic sanctionsto Spain.The Cabinet-Took note that, if the question of imposing economic sanctions against Spain were raised again in international discussions, the Foreign Secretary would seek the Cabinet&apos;approval for the line to be taken on behalf of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in those discussions.France. 5.   The Cabinet were informed that M. Blum, the PrimeEconomic Minister of France, had sent a member of his Government to LondonCo-operation, to impress upon British Ministers France&apos;s urgent need for coal,(Previous an(* to suggest that he might come to London to discuss this reference- question, either in isolation or against a broader economic andC.M.(46)82nd   political background.Conclusions, The President of the Board of Trade said that there was reasonMinute l.) to believe that the French Government were anxious to discuss the integration of the British and French economies, in the light ofthe Monnet Plan for the economic reconstruction of France. he hoped that we might avoid early discussion of these general issueswith members of the French Government. It would be embarrassingfor us to embark on this before we had taken decisions on our own economic plans; and in any event it would be preferable that thesematters should not be discussed between members of the two Govern-ments until the ground had been prepared by detailed discussion between officials.The Foreign Secretary said that it was important on political grounds that we should not return a wholly discouraging reply toM. Blum&apos;s overtures. The Prime Minister had already sent him a message to the effect that we had no coal to spare for France andthat in present circumstances it would be^ very difficult to allocateany more coal to them from the Ruhr.   But,having thus warned
him not to expect too much from his visit, we should not seek toprevent him from coming here to discuss the position if he wishedto do so. M. Blum&apos;s political position was precarious; and it might cause him grave political embarrassment if his approach to uswere rejected. We should do anything we could to strengthen theposition of his Government; for France was now at the cross-roads and; if his Government could survive for a reasonable time, thiswould be very valuable not only for France but for the whole futureof social democracy in Europe. A readiness to discuss his difficul-ties need not commit us to any offer of economic assistance. Itmight be, however, that in. the course of the discussions some means1might be found by which we could help France without detriment to our own interests. We need not be drawn into premature discus-sioii of the Monnet Plan or of schemes for integrating the Britishand the French economies. Nor need these conversations cut acrossthe detailed discussions by officials on the Anglo-French Committee,which periodically considered economic and financial questions ofcommon interest and was to hold its next meeting in the following week. In personal discussions of the kind contemplated we mightbe able to give some assurances which would satisfy the FrenchGovernment of our desire to see the French economy firmly re-established. We could, in particular, make it clear that we had no intention of integrating our economy with the German economy, atthe expense of French industry.Discussion showed that it was the general view of the Cabinetthat it should be possible to hold discussions with M. Blum on thebasis contemplated by the Foreign Secretary, without being drawn into detailed discussion of the Monnet Plan and the integration ofthe French and British economies. It was agreed that it would be preferable if these latter discussions could be postponed for a timeand initiated in the first instance between officials of the twoGovernments.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister, after consultation withthe Foreign Secretary, would arrange for a further message to be sent to the Prime Minister of Franceindicating his willingness to discuss France&apos;s economic difficulties on the basis which had been suggested bv theForeign Secretary in the course of the Cabinefs discussion.UnitedUse of Veto.(previous reference:CM. (47) 1stConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the use of the vetoin the proceedings of the United Nations.The Foreign Secretary said that it now seemed likely that theSoviet Government would not insist on the full exercise of the rightsof veto to which, on a literal interpretation of the Charter, the fiveGreat Powers were entitled. The Soviet Delegation had been unwilling to fall in with his suggestion at New York that theGreat Powers should agree among themselves on a code of practiceaccording to which their right of veto would be exercised. Therewere, however, indications that it might come to be accepted inpractice that abstention from voting would not be regarded as anexercise of the veto. If that became accepts. 0s a matter of usage,it might be possible at a later stage to amend the Charteraccordingly.In general he felt sure that it was wiser to allow such changes of procedure to come about by the evolution of a common practicethan to press for immediate amendment of the Charter.In the same way, he did not favour direct attempts to persuade the member States to accept a surrender of their sovereignty tothe United Nations.   In course of time, however, they would become
parties to a number of international agreements, e.g., on the controlof atomic energy, disarmament and economic questions, which wouldeach involve some limitation of their sovereign powers.There was general agreement with the views expressed by theForeign Secretary.Albania. 7.   The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that theFreedom of Albanian Government had returned an unsatisfactory reply to thePasage in the Note from His Majesty&apos;s Government about the laying of minesCorfu Channel, in the Corfu Channel. He was therefore proposing to bring the(Previous matter before the Security Council. He had taken the precautionReference - o:^ informing the other Great Powers of this intention.CM. (46) 93rd The Lord Chancellor asked that every effort should be made to conclusions,     ensure that the case Which we presented to the Security CouncilMinute 4.)      was as fully documented as possible.   He had been surprised tofind that no enquiries had. been made with a view to obtainingevidence from persons in Corfu who might have witnessed the laying of the mines.The Foreign Secretary and The First Lord of the Admiraltyundertook to see that all possible steps were taken to obtain thefullest evidence in support of our case.The Cabinet Authorised the Foreign Secretary to present to the security council the complaint against the Albanian Governmentin respect of the mining of the Corfu Channel.Egypt. 8.   The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that no means(Previous       had yet been found of overcoming the difficulty which had arisenReference:      over the Sudan Protocol to the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty.    the cm. (46) 104th Egyptian Government were seeking to persuade him to agree to a conclusions,     proposal Which would in effect deprive the Sudanese, when at someMinute I.)      future date they were ready for self-government, of their right ofself-determination.  He had no alternative but to resist this, eventhough the result was a breakdown of the negotiations for theTreaty.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Foreign Secretary&apos;sstatement.Publication 9.   The Lord President said that his attention had been calledof Cabinet to the publication in the B.B.C. news bulletins of reports of theBusiness. business Which had been or was about to be transacted by theCabinet. It had been represented to him that, as it was widelythought abroad that the B.B.C. News was officially authorised bythe Government, they might be asked not to include these specula-tions in their bulletins. He feh% however, that it would be difficultto ask the B.B.C. to refrain from using material which was providedby the news agencies and was published in the Press.There was general agreement with this view. Ministersthought it unfortunate, however, that so many reports should bepublished about the business which had been or was to be consideredby the Cabinet. The Prime Minister said that, while most of theseseemed to be based on speculation, it was important that all con-cerned should realise that no information about the Cabinet&apos;sAgenda should be given to the Press.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,6thJanuary, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
