<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/9/0 images: 41-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IB&apos; THE PKOPERTY \ OF. HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY/S GOYERMKEMT2Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1947SECRETC.M. (4716th conclusions cabinet 6 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Wednesday, 15th January, 1947, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of  State  for theouiuiiies.The Right Hon. E. Shin well, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Be van, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.Lord Pakenham, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for War.Admiral of the Fleet, Sir John H. D.Cunningham, First Sea Lord and chief of Naval Staff (Items 1-3).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.Marshal of the Royal Air Force lord tedder,   Chief  of  the Air  Staff(Items 1-3).Field-Marshal Viscount montgomery of Alamein, Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (Items 1-3).secretariat sir Norman Brook.Lieut.General Sir Leslie Hollis.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[33062^1]
cm...6 (47)Contents:Minute No. Subject page 1      Road Haulage Strike........................ 392      Palestine        ............................. 39Use of Armed Forces.3      Palestine ............      ................      40Military Implications of Future Policy.4      Palestine        ............................      40Political Implications of Future Policy.
39cm. 6 (47)Road HaulageStrike.(previous reference:CM. (47) 5thConclusions,Minute 1.)1. The Minister of Labour informed the Cabinet of the latest developments in the strike of road transport workers. A joint industrial Council for the industry had been established; the strikers&apos; Committee was meeting that morning; and there were some signs that a fairly early resumption of work was possible.Meanwhile, however, the strike was spreading in the london the Prime Minister said that he had been informed that, ifthe strike continued, there was a possibility that by the end ofthe weeknewspapers would cease publication for lack of neWs-print. He understood that the Ministerial Committee on industrial Emergencies, over which he had asked the HomeSecretary to preside, was meeting that afternoon, and he would beglad if they would consider the newsprint position.Palestine.Use of armed forces.(previous reference:CM. (46) 94thConclusions,Minute 4.)2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for the Colonies (CP. (47) 3) on the use of troops for themaintenance of law and order in Palestine.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that the con-tinuance of terrorism in Palestine made it necessary to considerthe issue of a further directive to the High Commissioner on thismatter. The primary responsibility for the maintenance of lawand order must remain with the police, who were being strengthenedand reorganised, but it was necessary that the assistance of themilitary should also be available. At present the military were only used to a limited degree. It was the policy in employing themthat there should be as little interference as possible with the life of the civil population, that military action should always havea definite objective against an illegal organisation and that it should only be taken on reliable information. It was now proposed tobroaden the terms of the directive to the High Commissioner as tothe circumstances in which the military might be used.   Thus, itshould be possible for them to institute searches at any time in anypart of the country, whether or not they had definite evidence, andthey should be free to maintain and increase the number of patrolsin dangerousThe Cabinet were therefore invited to approve the draftdirective annexed to CP. (47) 3, which had been prepared in con-sultation with the High Commissioner, and was endorsed by theSecretary of State for War.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that he favoured the issue of a fresh directive in these terms. The final respon-sibility for authorising the use of the military would remain withthe High Commissioner as head of the civil Government, and he hoped that the High Commissioner would enable the military totake full of the greater latitude which this new directivewould permit. In the last few weeks searches in Palestine,instituted without specific evidence but on general suspicion, hadbeen very effective; a number of suspected terrorists had been arrested and a quantity of arms and documents had been obtained.He was satisfied that, if the powers given under the proposeddirective were fully used and the military authorities were enabled to keep the initiative against the terrorists, they would be able tobring terrorism under control and to restore the confidence of theJewish community in the Government.In discussion there was general agreement with the view thai-more vigorous action should be taken against the terrorists; thatthis would be welcomed by the law-abiding elements of the popula-tion; and that leniency towards the terrorists would not strengthen the influence of the Jewish Agency.
The Cabinet-Agreed that a revised directive in the terms of the draft attached to CP. (47) 3 should be issued to the High Com-missioner for Palestine regarding the employment of the armed forces in suppression of terrorism.Palestine. 3.   The Cabinet discussed with the Chiefs of Staff the miiitary(Previous implications of various alternative solutions of the constitutionalReference:      question in Palestine.o.M.(46)i0ist        The  Cabinefs  discussion  is  recorded  in  the  Secretary&apos;conclusions,     Standard File of Cabinet Conclusions.Minute 2.)MilitaryImplicationsof future policy.Palestine.(previous reference:CM. (46) 101stConclusions,Minute 2.)PoliticalImplicationsof future policy.4. The Cabinet had before them memoranda on Palestine bythe Foreign Secretary (CP. (47) 28 and 30) and discussed thepolitical implications of future policy in Palestine.The Cabinefs discussion is recorded in the Secretary&apos;standard File of Cabinet Conclusions.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,15th January, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
