<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/9/0 images: 108-113</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT   IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF   HIS  BRITANNJC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT     printed for the Cabinet.  February 1947SECRETCodv No.CM. (47)18th ConclusionsGABIKET 10- (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, &amp;th February, 1.947, at 11 a.m.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,.M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right how. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.Mr. J. B Hynd, M.P., Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.jVp\-fftrpn fitSir Norman Brook.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[33260 2]
CABINET 16 (47),Contents.minute no.Subject. page 1      Coal       ... ....      .... ....     1032      Distribution of Industry      ....      ....      ....      ........     103Industrial Development in Lancashire.3      Germany....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     104:     Socialisation of. Basic Industries.4      Foreign Affairs.............      ....      ....      ....      ....     105&apos;.Anglo-Soviet Treaty.
Coal.(previous reference:C,M.(4&apos;;).3rdConclusions.)1. The Cabinet discussed the coal situation. The following were among the points raised : (a) Reference was made to the closing down of the AustinMotor Works owing to shortage of coal. It was pointed out thatthe object of the scheme approved by the Cabinet on 7th Januarywas to create a reserve of coal from which special deliveries couldbe made by the Regional Fuel Allocation Committees to meet casesof exceptional difficulty. If, therefore, the Austin Motor Workshad a stronger claim than other firms in the Region, supplies couldbe made to them from this reserve.(b) Enough lorries were now available to prevent further coalbeing put on the ground at open-cast workings and pitheads. bad weather had, however, delayed progress in removing the accumulatedstocks on the ground.(c) Electricity cuts and the lowering of gas pressure inevitablycaused annoyance to the public. Could it not be made more clearthat this was not due to shortage of coal but to lack of plant?Everything possible should be done to secure the manufacture and delivery of the additional generating plant required; otherwise thesituation next winter would be even more serious.The Minister of Fuel and power  said that he was consideringsteps to reduce the domestic consumption of electricity, which was70 per cent, above the pre-war level. He would shortly be submittinga memorandum on this question to the Lord Presidents Committee.(d) The Minister of Fuel and Power reported that the man-power employed in the coal-mining industry had increased from691,000 to 695,000 since the beginning of the year.Ministers agreed that the National Coal Board should be invitedto concentrate their attention on the problem of securing that theavailable labour was employed where it could be used most effectively.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that he was meeting theBoard and would impress this point upon them.(e) It was likely that there might be pressure for a debate inthe House of Commons on the coal situation. Such a debate mightbe useful in making the facts more widely known to the public.The Cabinet Took note of the position.2. In the course of the discussion recorded in the preceding minute the question was raised whether there had not been too great a development of light industries in the Lancashire area.Development During the war a large amount of munitions production had beenin located in Lancashire and North Cheshire, because these areas wereLancashire. less vulnerable to air attack and it had been the policy to draw offinto munitions labour from the textile industries. Many of thenew factories thus established there were now being used for various kinds of light engineering production for the civilian market. this development accentuated the difficulties both of providing sufficientcoal for industrial use in this area and of rebuilding the labour force of the textile industries. Should not this situation be con-sidered by the Distribution of Industry Committee ?The Chancellor of the exchequer said that, apart from Mersey-side and a small area round St. Helens, there was no unemployment problem in Lancashire; and no positive action had been taken onbehalf of the Government to promote industrial development in therest of this area. He would, however, arrange for his Committeeto consider the points which had been raised in the Cabinet&apos;discussion.Distributionof Industry.Industrial[33260-2]
The Cabinet-Took note that the Distribution of Industry Committee!would consider where an excessive development of light!industries was taking place in Lancashire and North!Cheshire; and, if so, what steps could be taken to correctthis tendency.Germany.socialisation of basic industries.(previous reference:-C.M.(47)2ndConclusions,Minute 2.)3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ForeignfSecretary (CP. (47) 37) on the socialisation of the basic industries in the British Zone of Germany.Discussion turned mainly on the question whether thecustodians for the industries in each Land should be drawn fromthat Land only or from the British Zone as a whole. The importanceof this point lay in its relation to the question whether the industries should eventually be controlled by Land Governments or by a centralGovernment of Germany.The Foreign Secretary was strongly of the opinion that theindustries should be placed under the Land Government for thereasons given in Annex A to CP. (47) 37. It was true that agreat concentration of power would thereby be placed in the handsof the North Rhine-Westphalia Land and it could be argued thatthis would give that Land undue influence over the rest of Germany.Equally, however, it could be argued that it would be easier toretain international control over the Government of a single Land!than over a central German Government. The Foreign secretary thought this a strong argument in favour of placing the industries under the Land Governments. He asked that no action should betaken, before the forthcoming meeting of Foreign Ministers in moscow, which might imply that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentfavoured the centralisation of power in Germany, for that would immediately arouse the opposition of the Governments of Franceand probably of other Western European Powers. He was, there-fore, opposed to the appointment at this juncture of one body ofcustodians for the whole of each socialised industry throughout theBritish Zone. He favoured the appointment of separate bodies ofcustodians for each industry in each Land.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster favoured the appoint- jment of custodians drawn from all parts of the British Zone.He reminded the Cabinet that the Government of the North Rhine-Westphalia Land was dominated by Conservative influences. Togive great power to it would be to weaken those progressive elements in Germany whose influence it was to our interest to strengthen.He also argued that the placing of the industries under a central german Government would make for greater efficiency in the con-duct of those industries. A very large part of Germany&apos;s industrialpotential would have been destroyed and with what was left itwould be difficult to prevent large-scale unemployment and to provide sufficient exports to pay for her essential imports. If this wasnot possible, she might remain a charge on the United kingdom excequer. It was, therefore, to our interest to ensure that theindustries left to Germany were operated as efficiently as possible.The Chancellor of the Duchy said that he recognised fcuCistrength of the arguments against taking action in the direction]which he favoured in advance of the Moscow meeting. He suggested,&apos;however, that no action should be taken, such as the appointment jof different custodians for each Land, which would commit us to ideciding this issue in the contrary sense.Finally, he said that it was not clear why, if the foreign secretary favoured the appointment in the case of each industry of separate custodians for each Land, he was ready to agree to asingle Advisory Committee for that industry for the whole Zone.The Advisory Committees would be composed of persons with know-ledge of the industries, and they were likely to have a much more effective influence over the conduct of the industries than thecustodians.
105cm. 16 (myThe Foreign Secretary said that the custodians would be inthe nature of trustees and would symbolise our intention to transferownership of the industries. The appointment for an industry ofa single body of custodians for the whole Zone would thus imply an intention to transfer ownership to a central Government, whereas the appointment of a single Advisory Committee, even though ithad a more effective voice in the conduct of the industry, would carry no such implication. The Advisory Committee would, at thesame time, maintain contact between the branches of the industryin the different Lands.The Cabinet were impressed by the strength of the arguments advanced by the Foreign Secretary, They did not consider that theappointment of different custodians in each Land for each industryneed necessarily affect the efficiency of that industry. They agreedthat Germany must be enabled to export so as to pay for her imports and to prevent continued expense to the United Kingdom. Butthere was room for German exports as well as British and, ifoccasionally there was some competition between them, this-, mustwithin limits be faced; our major interest was in an expandingworld economy.The Cabinet&apos;s conclusions were as follows: (1) Socialisation should be applied to the coal, iron and steel,heavy engineering, and chemical industries in the british zone.(2) Pending transfer to public ownership, custodians on behalfof the German people should be appointed at once forthe coal and iron and steel industries in each Land inwhich industries were situated.(3) A German Advisory Committee should be established atonce in respect of the coal industry throughout theBritish Zone. A similar Committee should beestablished in respect of the iron and steel industry.These Committees would, in the first instance, be purelyadvisory, but in the course of time it might be possibleto devolve upon them certain executive functions.(4) In the heavy engineering and chemical industries, the first step should be for the Commander-in-Chief to assumecontrol, and the appointment of custodians and theestablishment of Advisory Committees should be post-poned until it had been possible to define more clearly the undertakings within these industries to be coveredby public ownership.The Commander-in-Chief should as soon as possible make an announcement to the Land Governments on theappointment of custodians to the coal and iron and steel industries. The announcement should be in the termsof Annex C to CP. (47) 37.(6) A decision on the exact form which socialisation and public ownership should ultimately take should be postponed until after the Council of Foreign Ministers had met in moscow. Meanwhile, no steps should be taken whichwould imply that ownership of these industries would eventually be vested in a central German Government.(5)foreignAffairs.isle-SovietTi-treaty.(previous reference:CM. (47) lothConclusions.)4. The Foreign Secretary read to the Cabinet the reply whichhe received from the United States Secretary of State about the revision of the Anglo-Soviet Treaty.The Cabinet agreed that there was nothing in this reply whichcalled for any modification of the decisions which they had taken on this question at their meeting on the previous day.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,4tth February, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
