<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/9/0 images: 114-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fffllS DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF   HIS - BRITANNIC &apos; MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1947SECRET17th conclusions copy&apos;No.  44GfijtttKTiBT 41 7fi7Y&apos;I  CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 6th February, 1947, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P., ; The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,Secretary  of   State   for   Foreign j    M.P  Lord Priw SealAffairs. &apos; J    &apos;  &apos;The Right Hon. Hugh Balton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State forThe Right Hon A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P..Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland (item).The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister    of    AgricultureFisheries.CA,11 KiThe following were also present:The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply (item 3).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.Mr. R. J. Taylor, M.P., Lord Commis-sioner, Treasury (Items 1-2)The Right Horn Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 3).The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Works (Item 3).Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary to theTreasury.Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.[33260-3]b
CABINET 17 (47)Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Death of Miss Ellen Wilkinson      ....      ....      .... 1092      Parliament      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    109Business in the,House of Commons.3;     Coal      ............      ....      ....       ...      ....      ....    109Note on;the Movement of Coal by Rail. ... ...        ...       112
Death of. ,1.   The Prime Minister said that all members of the CabinetMiss Ellen must have been deeply grieved to hear that the Minister of Educa-Milkinson.      tion had died that morning.   By her death Ministers had lost avalued colleague and a staunch friend.Tributes would be paid to her memory in the House of commons that afternoon.The Cabinet&apos;s proceedings were suspended for a few momentsas a mark of respect to Miss Wilkinson&apos;s memory.Parliament.Business inthe House ofCommons.2.   The Acting Chief Whip informed the Cabinet of thethe House of Commons in the following week. - ..... ,On 10th and 11th February a number of Civil supplementary estimates would be taken. Those relating to the Ministries of CivilAviation, Health and Transport would be discussed on 10th february-arv; and those relating to the British Broadcasting Corporation,tit r\ xi ^ ^__A   J-l__tne xaome v^mce auu wcOn 12th February the Home Secretary would move the SecondReading of the Polish Resettlement Bill: the Parliamentary Secre-tary to the Ministry of Labour would reply to. the debate. TheSecond Reading of the Tsle of Man Harbours Bill would also betaken; and the House would be invited to consider a Lords&apos; amend-ment to the House of Commons (Redistribution of Seats) Bill.On 13th February the President of the Board of Trade wouldmove the Second Reading of the Industrial Organisation Bill.On 14th February the Second Reading of the Naval Forces(Enforcement of Maintenance Liabilities) Btll would be taken. TheHouse would also be asked to dispose of the Committee and remain-ing stages of the Appellate Jurisdiction Bill, the Births and DeathsRegistration Bill and the County Councils Association Expenses(Amendment) Bill.Coal.(previous reference:CM (47) 16thConclusions,Minute 1.)3.   The Cabinet had before themMinister of Fuel and Power (CP. (4recent severe weather on coal supplies.7^a50)memorandum by theon the effect of theThe Minister of Fuel and Power informed the Cabinet of themain difficulties which had arisen. Ships loaded with coal for theSouth had been held up in North-East Coast ports by gales, whileships which had discharged coal in London and the South had been unable to start back to the North-East: Frost had immobilised themachinery for handling coal in the docks at Cardiff and Barry,and in Northumberland, Durham and Yorkshire the transport ofcoal by rail had been seriously interrupted. In parts of the countryminers had been unable to get to their work owing to the snowand the resulting absenteeism was as high as 50 per cent, at somepits. The production of open-cast coal was completely stopped and coal stocked on the ground could not be moved. Everything possiblewas being done to bring coal to the London area bv rail, and hehad been able to obtain assistance from the Services in movingcoal and clearing collieries blocked with snow. Power stations inthe London area depended very largely on seaborne coal from theNorth-East Coast and from South Wales and, though there were signs that the shipping position was improving, there was a risk that a very serious situation would arise early in the following week. The Central Electricity Board had suggested to him thatin the London, South-East, North-West and Midlands areas all supplies of electricity to industrial consumers should be cut off com-pletely, and that supplies to domestic consumers should be cut from a.m. to 12 noon and from 2 p.m. to 4 p.m., similar cuts beingmade in supplies to theatres and cinemas. He had felt that ftwould be wrong to impose these drastic cuts until the results were[33260-3] B 2
known of the emergency, action which, was being taken to bringmore coal to London, but he had arranged for detailed plans tobe made ready to be put into force at once should a serious emergencyarise early in the following week. These plans would not necessarily follow those proposed by the Central Electricity Board. In parti-cular, he thought it might be possible to avoid such severe cutsif coal supplies were concentrated on the more efficient power stations. As a further measure to relieve the position in Londonhe had proposed to the Minister of Transport that a certain amountof coal which was now being exported for bunkers should be diverted to home consumption. He had already issued a statement to thepress about the situation and would continue to bear in mind theThe Minister of Transport said that, so far as concerned trans-port of coal by sea, 30 of the 57 ships held up in North-East coast ports had sailed on the previous day and 24 more were due to sailthat day. There would be congestion in the unloading of coalin the South and it was most important that everything should bedone to speed up unloading during the next few days. He under-stood that 30 coal ships which had been held up in the South bygales had now been able to leave for the North-East Coast and thatfive had already reached the Tyne. He was arranging to have deep-sea tonnage available to pick up coal from North-East Coast ports;but, in view of the general shipping shortage, he was unwilling to divert this tonnage until he was sure that cargoes would come forward to the ports. Though there had been difficulties in SouthWales ports, it was misleading to suggest that there had been acomplete stoppage of coal shipments.With regard to the movement of coal by rail, the Minister ofTransport gave figures showing that liftings of coal had been main-tained, coal in transit had not increased and the amount of coalbrought to London and the South by rail had, in fact, risen duringthe period of severe weather. (A note of the information given bythe Minister of Transport is annexed to the minutes.)The Minister of Transport added that he would consider sym-pathetically the proposal that coal should be diverted from exportfor bunkers to home consumption. He had arranged for its implications-tions to be examined by his officials.The President of the Board of Trade said that, according tohis latest information, about 120 factories in the North-West region and from 30 to 40 in the Midlands were working short time owingto the shortage of coal supplies. These figures did not, however,take full account of the effects of the recent severe weather, and since most factories had no stocks there was bound to be a seriousinterruption of industrial production during the next week or two.This would have a most adverse effect on the export drive. Hothought the time had come for Ministers to consider whether thewhole of the coal shortage should continue to be met by cuts on industry while no restrictions were put on domestic consumption.The Minister of Supply pointed out that the present scheme forthe allocation of coal to industry left manv firms with just underthe minimum amount which they needed to enable them to operate.He suggested that it would be more profitable to concentrate supplies on certain firms, even though this meant cutting off all supplies to others.The Cabinet first discussed what steps should be taken tomeet the immediate difficulties caused by the shortage of fuel. Therewas general agreement that the extent to which the movement ofcoal had been maintained during the recent severe weather reflectedgreat credit on all those concerned with the movement of coal by rail or by sea, and it was suggested that the Prime Minister migMissue a statement expressing appreciation of what had been done.So far as concerned the maintenance of electricity supplies inLondon, no drastic cuts in supplies to industry and to domestic consumers should be made for the present, but the Minister of
Fuel and Power should press on with the preparation of plans tomeet any emergency which might develop in the next tew daysWith regard to the allocation of coal to industry, it was felt thatRegional Officers should be given a wider discretion m operating theexisting scheme, so that supplies might be concentrated on the more essential factories and, within such industries as brickmaxung, onthe most economic producers. It was also worth considering whetherthe reserve pool maintained for granting emergency supplies to particular firms should not be increased by reducing the basic per-centage allocations. , , ,The Cabinet then discussed the further prospects for coal supplies,   xiie j-uiiuwing puinuo iiwc iiiia,^ .(a) Inougn it wouiu uc iiicii.pcu.ici.Kj ^ uuj;uov imwiu^ub juthe supply of coal or of gas and electricity to domestic consumersat the present time, it was desirable that plans should be made to restrict ^the domestic consumption of fuel from, say, 1st April.(b) Consideration should also be given to the need for initiatingat that time a publicity campaign, making full use of broadcasting,to convince the public of the need for fuel economy.(c) The possibility of introducing double summer-time duringthe coming summer and maintaining summer-time during the f follow-ing winter should be considered.The Minister of A qricultiire and Fisheries said that any such proposal would excite strong opposition from the farming industry;and, if on full consideration it were decided that it would be inthe general interest to adopt such a course, he would wish to havean opportunity of explaining the position to representatives of theindustry before any announcement was made.The Home Secretary said that he understood that any such proposal would entail legislation.The Cabinet-(1) Took note that the Prime Minister would issue a statementexpressing appreciation of the work done by all con-cerned with the transport of coal by rail and by seaduring the recent severe weather.(2) Agreed that the proposals of the Central Electricity board to cut supplies of electricity to industrial consumers andto ration supplies to domestic consumers as summarised in paragraph 3 of CP. (47) 50 should not be accepted,but that the Minister of Fuel and Power should prepare plans to deal with any emergency that might arise inthe next few days through the interruption of coal supplies because of adverse weather conditions.(3) Took note that the Minister of Transport would consideras a matter of urgency whether it would be possible to divert bunker coal to home consumption.(4) Invited the Service Ministers to arrange for the Services togive all possible assistance in connexion with the move-ment of coal and the clearance of snow from collieriesduring the present adverse weather conditions.(5) Agreed that the present scheme for the allocation of coal to industry should be reviewed with a view to intro-ducmg greater flexibility, particularly at the regional level.(6) Invited the Minister of Fuel and Power to submit to theLord Presidents Committee proposals for securingeconomies in the domestic consumption of fuel.(7) Invited the Lord Presidents Committee to consider thesuggestion that in order to economise fuel double summer-time should be introduced in the coming summer andsummer-time should be continued in the following winter.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,6th February, 1947.
UNIQUE OJN TPE&apos;H0VEMBNT OF COAL BY RAIL1. The movement of coal has been substantially maintained throughout thepresent bad weather, at the cost of stringent embargoes on other traffic andenergetic measures by the railway companies to keep routes clear. On 6th february-ary all important routes on the L.M.S. and L.N.E. were iclear, although somebranch lines were still blocked. The Woodhead twin tunnel has been reopenedin its entirety The tunnel blocked with snow has been cleared, and the engineershave temporarily abandoned work on the other tunnel so that both lines areavailable.2. In the week beginning 3rd February only five collieries have been stoppedowing to railway difficulties, and the stoppage has amounted to only 30 hours inall. The number of collieries access to which by rail has been blocked by snowis 12.   . .;3. The following figures show how the movement of coal by rail has been maintained in the main areas affected by the severe weather :  &apos;(a) Coal lifted(i) Wagons lifted on L.M.S. in Warwickshire, Lancashire andStaffordshire coalfieldsDate Number of Wagons29th January       ...      ...      ...      5,3224th February      ...      ...      ...      4,3495th February      .........      5,356(ii) Wagons lifted on L.M.S. and L.N.E. in the Midland (Amahgamated) District: *Date Number of WagonsL.M.S.    L.N.E.3rd February    ......      8,486        -4th February    ......      3,991      3,9595th February    ...      ...      7,401      6,873(b) Coal in TransitIt is estimated that coal in transit is only about 220,000 tons abovethe winter normal and is thus at the same level as on 11th January.The number of coal trains in the hands of the L.M.S. has decreasedsince the beginning of the week.Wagons in transit on the Midland section of the L.M.S.: * Date Number of Wagons29th January .........     11,1914th February .........      8,4565th February ......       ...      8,419(c) Deliveries of Coal(i) Coal wagons shunted in Toten Yard (which brings coal fromthe Midland (Amalgamated) District to London) Date Number of Wagons29th January       ......       ...       1,9074th rebruary      ...       ...       ...       1,4895th February      ...       ......      1,766(ii) Wagons on hand at L.M.S. Midland -depots in London :-Date Number of Wagons29th January       ...      ... ...      1,9644th February ... ...      2^4535th February      ...... ...      2,492(iii) Wagons handed over to the Southern Railway : Date Number of Wagons29th January ... ... ...       1,6264th February ... ... ...      2,3255th February ... ... ...      2^335
tt\    &apos; 11 wn iriti   winfrom South. Wales to London with coal for power stations :-Date3rd February4th February5th FebruaryNumber of Trains141316(v) Movement of wagons at Brimsdown which serves Londbn power stations : Number of wagons Number of wagonsDate in sidings at      cleared in previous6 a.m. 24 hours29th January30th January31st January1st February3rd February4th February5th February35891091541941862388338114912081181054. At the end of January the railways made further cuts in passenger services, releasing eight long-distance locomotives in addition to cancelling many local trains. Temporary cuts are also being made from day to day to meet thepresent position.


</content>
</cab>
