<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/9/0 images: 129-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
s  DOCUMENT   IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF   HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1947SECRETG&amp;pf !Ntt.gnat v*&quot;*-* \- - /jjjf 19th conclusions cabinet 19 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,Monday, 10th February, 1947, at il-80Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister, (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest &apos;jbevin/ M.r.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. E. ShinwEll, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.xne x&amp;ignt non. Arthur ureejnwoud,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scr,t-ln:ndThe Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. AneuRin Bevan, M.P..Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also present:LI. The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,r*&quot;    Minister of Supply.fHfThe Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.The-Right Horn Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport.The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S, Murrie.Coal[33260-5]Contents.SubjectPage122
Goal.(previous reference:CM. (47) 18thConclusions,Minute 1.)The Minister of Fuel and Power informed the Cabinet of thelatest developments in the fuel situation. The movement of coal was being impeded by further falls of snow in the North and bygales and fog; and a specially serious position was developing inthe North-East and East Midlands, where there was a big accumu-lation of loaded coal wagons. Though the temperature had risenin the South and South-East over the week-end, the latest forecastsuggested that further cold weather was to be expected. Withregard to power stations in the London area, his aim was to keepin operation the eight most efficient units, which used a total of18,000 tons of coal a day. The stocks at these stations varied from3J to 10 days&apos; supply, and it was most important that stocks atthose stations which were running on a very small margin shouldbe built up as soon as possible. Preliminary returns showed thatafter 9 o&apos;clock that morning the rate of electricity consumptionhad been reduced from 2-6 million kilowatts to 900,000 kilowattsin the London and South-Eastern area, from 1 - 5 million kilowattsto 850,000 kilowatts in the North-Eastern area and from 1-6 millionkilowatts to 600,000 kilowatts in the North-Western area.  He wasweilintexperience would be needed before a final conclusion could bereached. To a large extent the scheme depended on voluntary-operation by -industry and by domestic consumers, since; it wasoften impossible to cut off supplies at source without affectingessential consumers. On the whole it seemed likely that industry would co-operate in carrying out the scheme, though the Ministryof Fuel and Power were being faced with a very large number of claims for exemption, many of which would have to be rejected.The Prime Minister said that later in the day he would have to answer a Private Notice Question by the Leader of the opposition in the following terms : To ask the Prime Minister whether he has any further statement to make on the action of the Government in imposingcuts in electrical power.Thereafter, the Opposition might seek to move the adjournment inorder to discuss the fuel situation and it was possible that, either as an alternative to this or in addition, they would give notice oftheir intention to move a Vote of Censure.In discussion the following points were made :-(a) It had been agreed that electricity should be supplied forthe production of daily and weekly newspapers, but a final decisionhad still to be taken about periodicals.It was the view of the Cabinet that the publication of thepolitical weeklies should continue, but that the possibility of sus-pending publication of magazines and. picture papers might be explored with the Trade and Periodical Press Committee.(&amp;) Theatres and cinemas could continue to open after 4 p.m.put steps should be taken to stop greyhound racing altogether.(c) The National Coal Board had represented that at many pitsproduction would stop unless exceptional measures were taken tomove loaded wagons, particularly in. the North-East and EastMidlands. The Board had suggested that for the next three daysall long-distance night expresses should be cancelled in order to clear the lines for the movement of coal.The Minister of Transport said that priority was already being given to the transport of coal and that the Railway Executive Com-mittee were under instructions to curtail passenger serviceswherever this was necessary. He was not satisfied that the indis-criminate cancellation of express services would have the effect ofincreasing the quantity of coal moved by rail.It was the view of the Cabinet that during the present emergency any possible action that would help in the movementof coal by rail should be taken, irrespective of any inconvenience
to other interests. This should be made clear to the Railway Execu-tive Committee. Arrangements should also be made for the Ministryof Transport to be represented on the emergency committee set upby the Ministry of Fuel and Power to deal with the present crisis.(d) It was suggested that arrangements should be made for persons thrown out of work because of the electricity cuts to helpin clearing snow from collieries, railways and roads.(e) The assistance of the Navy should be enlisted in bringingcoal ships up the Thames and in getting them out of North-east coast ports during the present adverse weather.(/) It had been decided that factories which produced theirquestion was raised whether this decision should apply to WoolwichArsenal, which was partly engaged in the production of coal wagonsbut was situated near other factories which would have to close.It was agreed that production at Woolwich Arsenal should continue.(g) Special care should be taken to ensure that the public were kept fully informed of the facts of the situation, the measures whichthe Government were taking to meet it, and the need for all sectionsof the community to co-operate in overcoming it. Though theGovernment would have to meet political criticism, it was desirablethat a factual and objective statement should first be made and-J-V*of i finci 1   nnritnn y a t q v r   sTlO nlcl   \^   pSQRSlfels   t)S   ]!?SSOI*VOCi   &quot;pQ^&apos;   Sill)-sequent Parliamentary debate.It was therefore agreed that the statement to be made by thePrime Minister that afternoon in reply to a Private Notice question in the House of Commons should be mainly factual in character.The British Broadcasting Corporation should be asked to includethe full text of this statement in their news bulletins. In addition,the Prime Minister should himself make a broadcast address afterthe 9 o&apos;clock news that evening, inviting the co-operation of thepublic in overcoming the present crisis. The British broadcasting corporation should announce on the 1 o&apos;clock news that this broad-cast was to be made ^ and this announcement, coupled with the factthat the tone of the broadcast would be above political controversy,should have the effect of forestalling anv criticism that by his broad-cast the Prime Minister was anticipating Parliamentary debate the Cabinefs conclusions were as follows : (1) The Ministry of Fuel and Power and the Central Office ofInformation should discuss with the Trade andPeriodical Press Committee, and report to the PrimeMinister, how far electricity should be supplied for theproduction of periodicals.(2) The Minister of Fuel and Power should take steps to prevent any use of electricity by greyhound racing tracks.(3) The Minister of Transport should give directions to theRailway Executive Committee that during the present emergency all possible steps must be taken to move coalirrespective of any inconvenience to other railway users.(4) The Minister of Labour and National Service, in consulta-tion with the Ministers of Fuel and Power and Trans-port, should arrange for persons thrown out of employ-ment as a result of the electricity cuts to help in clearing-snow from the collieries, roads and railways.(5) The First Lord of the Admiralty should arrange for theRoyal Navy to give airy assistance in their power in bringing coal ships up the Thames or getting them outof North-East Coast ports.(6) The Prime Minister would give a short factual statement in reply to the Question teTbe addressed to him that after-noon by Private Notice, and would broadcast after the9 o&apos;clock news inviting the co-operation of the public in overcoming the present crisis.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,- 10th February, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
