<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/9/0 images: 271-279</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fttlS DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  April 1947SECRETCM. (47)87th CoiiuluSlOiiSCopy No. 4QCABINET 37 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,ivn. ThaivQ/1n.n!   17th  4 vwil   IQd.7   fit 11  n. m.Present:The Right Son. G. R. Attlee. ZvLP., Prime ^Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.me   JXigJUL  XlOn.   U.    W jSBTVVUUJJ,   1tJ..X .,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries(Items 1-7).The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P., I TheRight Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 5-8).        i     Minister of Transport (Items 5-8).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P., j The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Minister of Food. !     Minister of State (Items 1-7).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-2).Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mi\ S. E. V. Luke.[33524-1]
LtllTL-lltSNo.1234678Contents.SUOjgCZ.parliamentary in the House of Commons.Civil Aviation ....Civil A.aircraft irls^iiirsizisrivS.India     ....      ....      ....Viscount Waveii.Anglo-Soviet Treaty ....Maintenance of Essential Supplies and Services in anEmergency   ....Food     ................Wheat Supplies.International &quot;Wheat ConferenceParliamentLegislative Programme for the 1947-48 Session.Iron and Steel Nationalisation Bill and Gas Nationalisation Bill.257257257257258259260260
Parliament.Business inthe House ofCommons.1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be takenin. the House of Commons in the following week.On 21st April the Report Stage and Third Reading of theNational Health Service (Scotland) Bill would be taken.On 22nd April the Report Stage of the Budget Resolutionswould be commenced.On 23rd April the Report Stage of tihe Budget Resolutionswould be concluded. Thereafter, the House would be invited to approve the Clearing Office (Spain) Amendment Order and ImportDuties Orders and a new financial resolution relating to theTransport BilL If time allowed, the House would also complete the adjourned debate on the Public Offices (Site) Bill.On 24th April there would be a- debate on the production ofBritish Types of Civil Aircraft, on the motion to go into Committeeof Supply. The Government spokesmen in this debate would bethe Minister of Supply and the Parliamentary Secretary to theMinistry of Civil Aviation. The House would also be invited to approve tihe Biscuits (Charges) (Amendment) Order.On 25th April the Report Stage and Third Reading of the statistics of Trade Bill would be taken.Civil Aviation.Civil Aircraft(previous reference reference.:CM. (46) 77thConclusions,Minute 3.)2. In the course of the discussion recorded in the preceding minute the Cabinet were informed that there was a conflict of view between the Ministry of Civil Aviation and the Ministry of Supplyabout the desire of the former to obtain from the United States,for the use of the British Airways Corporations, a further numberof Constellation aircraft to be fitted with British engines. Itwas important that this conflict should be resolved before the debate in the House of Commons on 24th April.The Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs tbhold an early meeting of the Civil Aviation Committee,together with the Chancellor of the Exchequer; and, ifthe issue could not be resolved by the Committee, to bring it to the Cabinet before the debate on 24tJh Aoril.ViscountWavell,(previous reference:CM. (47) 34thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet of the termsof the reply which he had received to his letter conveying theCabinet&apos;s appreciation of Viscount Wavell&apos;s services as viceroy of India.Inglo-SovletTreaty.(previous reference:CM. (47)29thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Prime Minister recalled that at their meeting on18th March the Cabinet had authorised the Foreign Secretary tonegotiate an Anglo-Soviet Treaty going as far as, but no further than, the Anglo-French TreatRussians had proposed that the Articles requiring each of theParties to give military assistance to the other if attacked byGermany should also apply if the attack were made by another state associated with Germany. In the form proposed by theRussians, this clearly went too far; but the Foreign Secretary had suggested that their wishes might be met in part by providing that military support would be afforded also against any other power which might join with Germany in an armed attack in Europe on either Party. The Foreign Office had, however, drawn attention tothe importance of limiting any such provision to action taken by a european State in Europe; and had suggested that, if any suchextension was to be offered, the following formula should be used :&apos;&apos; In the case of an armed attack by Germany this support and[33524-1] b 2
assistance will be afforded in Europe also against any other state which may take part with Germany in such an attack in Europe.&quot;In the course of a preliminary discussion it was pointed outthat there were risks in offering even this formula. Thus, if anon-European Power were able to use a European base from which to launch an attack on the Soviet Union, and Germany subsequentlyjoined in that attack, should we not be pledged by this formula to support the Soviet Union against that Power I It was also important to keep in mind the effect on French opinion of concludingan Anglo-Soviet Treaty containing promises of military assistance which went beyond those included in the Anglo-French Treaty.It was clear that the Cabinet should have a further opportunityof discussing this proposal when they had been able to study the texts suggested and had received the views of the Chiefs of Staff.The Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for theForeign Office to prepare a paper containing the text ofthe various proposals for extension of&quot; the military clauses of the draft Anglo-Soviet Treaty and setting out the viewsof the Chief s of Staff and the other considerations involved;and agreed to resume their discussion when this paper was available.Maintenance 5.   The Home Secretary recalled that the Industrial Emer-of Essential     gencies Committee was at present responsible only for the main-Supplies and    tenance of essential supplies and services in an emergency arisingServices in an   from an industrial dispute; and, because its scope was thusEmergency.     restricted, the Cabinet had hitherto considered that its planning(Previous       work should be confined to senior officials in Whitehall and shouldReferenee:       not extend to departmental staffs in the Regions.   Experience of cm. (46)22nd   the dislocation caused by the recent heavy snows and subsequentConclusions,     flooding had suggested that the scope of the organisation should be minute 6.)      extended so as to cover the maintenance of essential supplies and services in any emergency, whether it arose from an industrial dispute or from other causes.  If its scope were thus extended, therewould be less difficulty in authorising the preparation of plans, notmerely at the centre, but also in the Regions.   Recent experience had shown that effective plans could not be made unless chief constables and departmental staffs in the Regions were consulted in advance and a skeleton organisation was brought into beingwhich could be rapidly expanded in a time of actual emergency.In discussion it was recalled that when the Cabinet hadimposed, on 6th March, 1946, the restriction which had hithertoprecluded any such preparations in the Regions, they had been influenced by the political risks of its becoming known, at a timewhen they were about to introduce legislation repealing the TradeDisputes Act, that they were preparing what might have been represented as a strike-breaking organisation. If the scope of theorganisation were extended so as to cover all emergencies, whatever their cause, there was much less risk of its being so represented particularly in the light of the events of the recent winter. Therewas therefore generaf agreement that the scope of the organisation should be extended on the lines proposed by the Home secretary and that the restriction precluding preparations at the regional level should be removed.The Cabinet then considered whether there should be any public announcement of this decision. It was agreed that this turnedlargely on the nature of the preparations to be made and the extentto which these must become known locally. The best course wouldbe for the Ministerial Committee to consider what action should betaken in the Regions and, in the light of that, to submit to theCabinet their considered recommendations on the question whether any public announcement was required and if so what form itshould take.
The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the scope of the Industrial Emergencies Com-mittee should be extended so as to cover the maintenanceof essential supplies and services in any emergency,whether it arose from an industrial dispute or fromother causes; and that the Committee might authoriseconsultation with Chief Constables and departmentalstaffs in the Regions for the purpose of preparing plans for maintaining essential supplies and services in suchemergencies.(2) Took note that the Jfrime Minister would reconstitute theIndustrial Emergencies Committee for this purpose.(3) Invited the Home Secretary to convene aniVUrVof the Committee, as so reconstituted, to consider and recommend to the Cabinet whether any public announce-ment should be made regarding the Governments plans for maintaining essential supplies and services in anemergency and, if so, what form that announcement should take.Food. 6.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theWheat Minister of Food (CP. (47) 122) recommending that the extractionSuooiies. rate of flour should be increased from 85 per cent, to 90 per cent./-Previous fQr a period of six weeks beginning on 20th April.Beierenee: The Minister of Food said that, as a result of the low shipmentsC.M.(47)30th of wheat from Canada during the winter, United Kingdom stocksConclusions, of wheat and flour would fall to about 5 -1 weeks&apos; supply by the minute 5.) end of April. He had made urgent representations to the canadian minister of Trade and Commerce, whose reply had been reasonably satisfactory; but, even if the revised programme were maintained,there would be no more than 6-7 weeks&apos; supply in stock at theend of May and between 8 and 9 weeks&apos; supply at the end of June.Precautionary measures should, in his view, be taken to safeguard the distribution of flour during these difficult weeks; but in thelight of the latest information from Canada it should be enoughto increase the extraction rate for four rather than six weeks as suggested in CP. (47) 122. He was advised that this was thebest means of securing an immediate saving of wheat; the bakerswere carrying heavy stocks at present and if the extraction ratewere raised they would reduce their current demands for flour.The animal feeding-stuffs ration would be maintained.The Minister of A griculture said that an increase in the extraction-tion rate would be bound to shake the confidence of farmers in the ability of the Government to maintain the ration of animal feeding-stuffs. This would certainly reduce the effect of his appeal to farmers to breed more .pigs and poultry.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The estimates of stocks had been based on an average weekly off-take of flour of 100,000 tons. What saving was beingsecured by the bread rationing scheme?The Minister of Food said that bread rationing was savingonly about 3,000 tons a week.   The scheme provided for a weekly consumption of 95,500 tons, but there was a weekly leakage of about ,500-5,000 tons. Substantial additional staff would be needed toprevent this leakage. He thought that the Cabinet should consider,later in the summer, the future of the bread rationing scheme :stocks should then have reached about 11 weeks&apos; supply.(o) The average weekly off-take of flour, since the inceptionof the rationing scheme, had been about 90,000 tons a week; inMarch, however, there had been a sharp rise to 106,000 tons. Thiswas probably due to the weather conditions, and to stocking forEaster. Was it necessary to assume that demand would be main-tained at this level?(e) The most effective method of dealing with the presentsituation would be to reduce the weekly off-take of flour, at least
to the level covered by the rationing scheme. ; Would it not bepossible to persuade the millers to restrict supplies of flour to thebakers to this extent by means of a general percentage reduction?If the situation were explained both to the bakers and to the public generally, and a clear indication given of the need for strict economyduring the difficult period ahead, it should be possible to secure areduction in weekly off-take which would make an increase in the extraction rate unnecessary.The Minister of Food said that, if he were unable to secure theco-operation of the millers in reducing the weekly off-take of flour,he would have to bring the matter before the Cabinet again.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that no immediate increase should be made in the extraction rate of flour.(2) Invited the Minister of Food to discuss with representativesof the millers means of securing a substantial reductionin the weekly off-take of flour.(3) Invited the Minister of Food to consider whether, as partof the measures contemplated in Conclusion (2) above.tihe bakers and the public generally should be warnedof the difficulties of the immediate situation and of theneed for economy in the use of flour over the next fewmonths.International 7.   The Minister of Food said that the Overseas EconomicWheat Policy  Committee on  15th April had authorised the UnitedConference. Kingdom Delegation to tihe International Wheat Conference tomake certain concessions in an effort to secure agreement. the delegation had also been authorised to support certain proposalsfor the determination of price ranges from year to year. Theseproposals had not received any support in the Conference, andhad been strongly opposed by the exporting countries. The attitudeof the latter had, indeed, considerably hardened since the Com-mittee&apos;s meeting on 15th April, and they had now reverted to their original proposals. In these circumstances the Minister felt thatthere would be no justification for further concessions by HisMajesty&apos;s Government and he suggested that the United kingdom delegation should be instructed accordingly. That would notnecessarily mean that the Conference would break down; it mightbe adjourned for a time; and, after the American harvest, discus-sions might be resumed in conditions more favourable to the importing countries.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Food to inform the UnitedKingdom Delegation to the International Wheat Con-ference that no further modifications could be made inthe instructions already given to them.8. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Ministerof Supply (CP. (47) 123) and the Minister of Fuel and Power(CP. (47) 124) on the nationalisation of the iron and steel industryand the gas industry respectively.The Prime Minister recalled that, when tihe Cabinet had considered on 20th March the proposals in CP. (47) 79 for legisla-tion in the 1947-48 Session, they had not decided which of theseC.M.(47)30th two nationalisation Bills should be included in the Programme.Conclusions, This point should now be settled : the detailed schemes outlinedMinute 4.) in the two memoranda could be examined later.Iron and Steel The Cabinet agreed that, in view of the heavy pressure onNationalisation Parliamentary time, it would not be possible to pass more thanBill and Gas one&apos; of these two Bills in the next Session. Opinion was, however,Nationalisation divided on the question which of the two Bills should be chosenBill- for inclusion in the programme.Parliament.Legislativefor the 1947-48 Session.(Previous&quot;Reference:
From the point of view of the Parliamentary timetable it was recognised that there were strong arguments in fayour of proceeding with the Gas Bill. &quot;This would be the third of the Bills fornationalising the fuel industries and would have many features in common with its two predecessors which Parliament would already have approved; it would follow in the main the recommendationsof the Heywortlh Committee, which had been appointed by the coalition Government; and it was not likely to provoke muchcoiiLruversy m irttxuiiaiiitjiit. public oucci basis, uu uuiw namj., wav^snew ground and raised difficult and complex issues; it would bekeenly opposed by the industry; and it would arouse bitter contro-ygT-gy iti Parliament: In particular, it might become an issuebetween&apos; the two Houses of Parliament.In other respects, however, the arguments were more evenly balanced. In favour of the Gas Bill, it was urged that the industry should not be kept any longer in the state of suspense created bythe publication * of the Heywortlh Report: this was alreadypreventing necessary development in the industry. Special difficul-ties were likely to arise in South Wales where, without theamalgamations which would follow from nationalisation, itwould prove difficult to provide sufficient supplies of gasfor the development areas. Nationalisation of the gas indusrty was also necessary in order to secure the co-ordinated fuel policy which had been one of the aims^ of the Labour Party&apos;programme for many years past. In the Economic Survey for 1947(Cmd. 7046) the Government had put oh record their view that the fuel industries were basic to our economy; and they would be opento criticism if, having nationalised the coal and electricity indus-tries, they now delayed the nationalisation of the gas industry.Such delay could also be represented as giving electricity an advantage over gas. Moreover, there were no major questions ofpolicy to be settled in respect of this Bill. It might, however, be some weeks before final conclusions could be reached on the detailsof a nationalisation scheme for the steel industry; for some Ministersfelt doubtful about the scheme outlined in CP. (47) 123, whichbad not yet been considered by the Cabinet. If a Steel Bill wereto be passed in the next Session, it was essential that it should beintroduced early in the autumn of 1947. The Cabinet were assured that the Bill could be ready for introduction at that time if earlyapproval were given to the scheme outlined in CP. (47) 123; but some Ministers feared that there would be delay in finally deter-mining the policy, with the result that the Bill might not be ready for introduction until later in the Session. Even if the Bill could beready for the beginning of the Session, it was arguable that by pro-ceedmg with this measure at the present time the Government wouldbe imposing an undue burden on Parliament, on Ministers- and onthe administrative machine, all of which were showing signs ofstrain. This was undoubtedly the most difficult nationalisationproject which the Government had yet entertained; and there was much to be said for postponing it until further experience had been gained in the operation of socialised industries.In favour of the Steel Bill, it was urged that, as a matter ofParliamentary tactics, it would be preferable to proceed first withthe more difficult and controversial of the two Bills. It was truethat the Steel Bill might become an issue between the two houses of Parliament; but some Ministers thought that, on political grounds, this would not be unwelcome. And, if it was thought thatthis Bill could not be passed without recourse to the parliament act, this would be a conclusive argument in favour of introducing the Bill at the opening of the third Session .of the present Parlia-ment. Arguments based on the undesirability of keeping theindustries in a state of suspense applied even more strongly to steelthan to gas. For no one seriously doubted that the gas industry would be nationalised, if not next Session, then in some laterSession. But in respect of the steel industry the uncertainty wasnot when, but whether, the industry would be nationalised. Doubtson this point were beginning to develop even within the Labour
Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,17th April, 1947.Party; and it would be salutary that these doubts should be deter-mined by the Cabinets reaching a definite decision and proceedingwithout delay to put it into effect. To defer a decision would beto invite a re-opening of political controversy on this issue. TheCabinet should recognise that, if this Bill was not introduced inthe coming Session, it was unlikely to be introduced in the lifetime of the present Parliament. The Minister of Supply said that,meanwhile, it was essential to our industrial recovery that we should secure the greatest possible increase in the output of steel and themost rapid reorganisation of the industry. It was arguable that,in both these respects, progress might be delayed either by con-tinuing uncertainty about the ultimate status of the industry orby the effect on the existing management of a decision to proceedwith nationalisation. It might be, however, that such progress would be less likely to be delayed if the Government decided toproceed at once with legislation on the lines proposed in CP. (47)123. Further, to the extent that reorganisation proceeded underprivate enterprise, it was likely to provoke criticism from Govern-ment supporters, who would resent such an extension of privatemonopoly. Thus, the Steel Board were already initiating a 50 million scheme for the development of the tinplate industry inSouth Wales; and the workers in that industry would be concerned to know when it was to be brought under public control.Finally, it was pointed out that there should be no difficultyin defending a decision to postpone the Gas Bill on the groundthat the Minister of Fuel and Power and his Department neededa respite from legislation in order to concentrate their attentionon administrative problems connected with the fuel crisis and the bringing into operation of the Acts nationalising the coal and electricity industries.The Prime Minister said that, after this full discussion, itwas clear that the preponderant view of the Cabinet was in favourof including the Steel Bill, rather than the Gas Bill, in the Legisla-tive Programme for the 1947-48 Session.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that an Iron and Steel Industry NationalisationBill should be included in the Legislative programme for the 1947-48 Session; and that the Gas IndustryNationalisation Bill should be deferred until a subse-quent Session.(2) Agreed to discuss at an early meeting the scheme for the nationalisation of the Iron and Steel Industry outlined in CP. (47) 123.


</content>
</cab>
