<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/254/0 images: 450-462</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. **It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.MOST SECRET.CABINET.Note by the Secretary.CP,  72(35). Copy No.   ^fThe prime Minister has instructed me to circulate to the Cabinet the attached memorandum prepared by Sir Claud Schuster as the result of Inter-departmental discussions on the general question of the procedure to be adopted in the various contingencies which might arise, necessitating emergency action for the performance of the duties of the Sovereign^2c      Attached to the memorandum is a draft Regency Bill prepared after taking the opinion of the Law Officers of the Crown.3.      Attention is called to the secrecy of these papers.(Signed) M0 P. A. HANKSYSecretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, SoW.  1, 28th March,  1955.
*i &amp; X1. It will be remembered that, before the lastImperial Conference, an Interdepartmental Committee examined the general cuestion of the procedure to be adopted in the various contingencies which might arise necessitating emergency action for the performance of the duties of the Sovereign. 2. The contingencies discussed were:-(l) Minority of the heir to the throne on the demise of the Crown,(2) Absence of the heir to the throne on the demise of the Crown.(3) Total incapacity of the Sovereign.(4) Partial incapacity of the Sovereign.(5) Absence of the Sovereign.3. The Report of the Interdepartmental Committeewill be found among the Imperial Conference Papers marked p. (B)  (30) 7.4. This Report was circulated to the Cabinetbut was not furnished to any but the United Kingdom representatives,  though some of the matters to which It relates were mentioned at e. meeting of the Prime Ministers and Heads of Delegations held on the 10th November,  1930.   (P. M. (30) 21.)5. It was not at that time deemed expedient tofollow up the matter.6. Since then the passage of the Statute of westminster and recent legislation in the Union of South Africa have increased the difficulties which would
*5t e$ si &amp; &amp;arise upon the happening of any of the contingenciesdescribed above.      Furthermore it is understood that theKing has expressed a wish that these problems should beconsidered afresh so that, while he is in his presentgood state of health,  such action - whether legislative or otherwise - as may be thought desirable, may be takento provide against the happening of any such event,7. Accordingly, an Interdepartmental Commi.committee,presided over by Sir Maurice Hankey,  has again consideredthe matter.      In the course of their deliberations it became apparent that certain legal and constitutional questions arose upon which it was desirable to take theOpinion of the Law Officers.      A Case was accordinglysubmitted to the Lav/ Officers who,  so far as is material to the present question, advised, as follows:-&quot;The general conclusion we have formed as to the proper treatment of the issues raised In these questions is that there is a very great advantage in deciding to make the necessary arrangements by Statute.      If our view expressed above is correct35 the provisions of such a Statute would only be valid quoad a Dominion which has adopted the Statute if the assent of that Dominion had been obtained and was declared in accordance with section 4 of the Statute of Westminster.      On the other hand, any legislation ought in our opinion carefully to guard the &apos; Prerogative,  and it would not, we think, be difficult to do this by a Preamble suitably framed.      It is much easier to undertake this task when there is time and Oppdr-tunity,  as there happily is at the present time, than to await the arrival of an emergency when it may be impossible to avoid resort to the Royal Prerogative and even to some of the fictions which have been necessary in the past&apos;5.k   We ourselves take the view that in so far as the functions of the Crown are exercised quoad a Dominion any legislation by the Imperial Parliament as to the way in which those functions should be exercised in certain events would come within the reach of section 4 of the Statute of Westminster, and even apart from section 4 we are of opinion that it would no longer be constitutionally proper to pass such legislation in the Imperial parliament without the assent of the Dominions.      It need hardly be said that so far as any functions are concerned, which in no way concern the Dominions the Imperial Parliament is quite unfettered.
** ^ ^*3 i-j &amp;a Bill has been prepared by the Parliamentary Counsel, a copy of which is attached.(a) The Sovereign is authorised by Letters Patent to nominate a Regent to act either in the case of the minority of his successor (up to the age of 18), or in the event of he himself becoming incapable through illness.(b) The person to be so nominated may, at the will of the Sovereign, be the Royal Consort,  the Mother of the heir to the throne, or any person in the line of succession tothe Crown, being in any ease a British subject of full age, resident in the United Kingdom and capable under the Act of Settlement of succeeding.(c) The Sovereign is also authorised, if he desires to do so, by reason of his absence or impending absence from the United. kingdom or by reason of any illness or other like cause, by Letters Patent to delegate to Counsellors of State any such functions as he may choose.      The persons so chosen must be persons capable of holding the Regency.(d) Provision is also made for the case of a Sovereign who succeeds when of full agebut is at his accession absent from the United9.The proposals of the Bill are as follows:-Kingdom.In that case,  four persons of full aige and present in the UnitedKingdom who are next in the line of succession or any two of them, shall
exerci.sethe Royal functions until trie Sovereignisable to do so.This replaces the LordsJustices Act, 1837, which both by reasonof effluxion of time and by reason of someof its provisions both in spirit and in letterhaving become hopelessly obsolete.The LawOfficershave advised thahat this Act ought tobe repealed.10.It may be thought desirable to discuss withsuch of the Dominions representatives who are in this country on. the occasion of His Majesty&apos;s Jubilee,  the questions which arise In this matter.      It is,   therefore, desirable in the first place that the Bill in its broad outlines should be placed before the Cabinet and further provision made In the matter.House of Lords7th March 1935.
ti 6 wSECRET.DRAFTof aB  I  L  LTOMake provision for a Regency in the event of a.d. 1935. the Sovereign being on iris Accession under the age of eighteen years and in the event of the incapacity of the Sovereign through illness, for the performance of certain of the royal functions in the name and on behalf of the Sovereign in certain other events, and for purposes connected with the matters aforesaid.WHEREAS Your Majesty, by Your Majesty&apos;s Royal Message to both Houses of Parliament, has been pleased to recommend that provision should be made for the appointment of a Regent in the event of the 5 Sovereign being on his Accession under the age of eighteen years or in the event of the incapacity of the Sovereign through illness and for the performance of certain of the royal functions in the name and on behalf of the Sovereign in certain other events :10 Now therefore, we, Your Majesty&apos;s most dutiful and loyal subjects, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons, in Parliament assembled, do most humbly beseech Your Majesty that it be enacted, and be it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,15 by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and  Temporal,  and the  Commons,  in  this  present73-4 A
A.D. 1935. Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same,        as follows : Regency during the infancy of the sovereign.of the Sovereign1. (1) If the Sovereign is at his accession under the age of eighteen years, then, until he attains that age, the royal functions shall be performed  in  the 5 name and on behalf of the Sovereign by a Regent.(2) The Regent shall, during the period of any such Regency, be the guardian of the person and property of the Sovereign.Regency 2. (1) If the following persons or any three or 10during total more of them, that is to say, the Royal Consort, that incapacity person, being of full age and resident in the United Kingdom, who is next in the line of succession to the Crown, the Lord Chancellor, the Speaker of the House of Commons, the Lord Chief Justice of England and 15 &quot;the Master of the Rolls, are satisfied on the evidence of His Majesty&apos;s physicians or otherwise that the Sovereign has become by reason of infirmity of mind or body incapable for the time being of performing his royal functions, and by writing under their hands 20 so declare, then, until it is declared in like manner that His Majesty has so far recovered his health as to warrant the termination of the, Regency, the royal functions shall be performed in the name arid on behalf of His Majesty by a Regent. 25(2) A declaration under this section shall be made to the Privy Council, and the Council shall forthwith cause it to be communicated to the Governors-General of His Majesty&apos;s Doriririions and to the Governor-General of India. 30Selection 3. (1) The Sovereign may by Letters Patent underof Regent, the Great Seal nominate the Royal Consort, the Mother of the Heir to the Throne, or any person in the line of succession to the Crown to become Regent in the event of a Regency becoming necessary under this Act during 35 that Sovereigns life or on his demise, and may in like riianrier revoke or vary any such nomination.A nomination under this subsection may include alternative nominations to take effect in the event of &apos;the failure of the principal nomination. 40(2) If, on a Regency becoming necessary under the provisions of this Act? such a nomination as aforesaid
9 9ftfa this in force, then, subject to the provisions of this A.D. 1935. section, that nomination shall determine the person to be Regent and if no such nomination is in force or if the nomination for any reason cannot take effect, then 5 that person who is next in the line of succession to the Crown and is not disqualified under this section shall become Regent.(3) A person shall not be qualified to become or be Regent, unless he is a British subject of full age and 10 resident in the United Kingdom, and would, under section two of the Act of Settlement, be capable of possessing the Crown if he had succeeded thereto; and section three of the Act of Settlement shall apply in the case of a Regent as it applies in the case of a Sovereign.15 (4) If any person who would at the commencement of a Regency have become Regent but for the fact that he was not then of full age becomes of full age during the Regency, he shall, if he is not disqualified under this section from being Regent, thereupon become Regent.20        4.-(1.) If during a Regency the Regent dies or Death, ceases to be. qualified under this Act to be Regent, that&apos;- incapacity, person shall become Regent in his stead who would have become Regent if the events necessitating the Regency had occurred at the time of the death or25 cbisqualification.(2) If the following persons or any three or more of them, that is to say, the wife or husband of the Regent, or, if the Regent has no wife or husband, that person, being of full age and resident in the United Kingdom,30 who is next in the fine of succession to the Crown, the Lord Chancellor, the Speaker of the House of Commons, the Lord Chief Justice of England, and the Master of the Rolls, are satisfied on the evidence of physicians or otherwise that the Regent has become by reason of35 infirmity of mind or body incapable for the time being of performing his functions as Regent, and by writing under their hands so declare, then, until it is declared in like manner that the Regent has so far recovered his health as to warrant his resumption of the Regency,40 that person shall be Regent who would have become Regent if the Regent had died.73 A 2
A.D. 1935.Oaths to be taken by, and limita-tions of power of, Regent.Absence of Sovereign from(3) A declaration under subsection (2) of this section shall be made to the Privy Council, and the Council shall forthwith cause it to be communicated to the Governors-General of His Majesty&apos;s Dominions and to the Governor-General of India. 5 -(4) If within seven days from the date on which a person would otherwise become Regent under this Act and before he enters upon his functions as Regent, he declares in writing his unwillingness to become Regent and notifies the Privy Council within that period that 10 he has made that declaration, the provisions of this Act shall have effect as if that person were disqualified from becoming Regent on that occasion.5. (1) Every Regent shall, before he acts in or enters upon his office, take and subscribe before the 15 Privy Council the oaths set out in the Schedule to this Act and the Privy Council are empowered and required to administer those oaths and to enter them in the Council Books.(2) A Regent shall not have power to give the 20 Royal Assent to any Bill for changing the order of succession to the Crown or to any Bill for repealing or altering an Act of the fifth year of the reign of Queen Anne made in Scotland entitled &quot; An Act for Securing &quot; the Protestant Religion and Presbyterian Church 25 &quot; Government.&quot;(3) A Regent shall not have power to make, vary or revoke any nomination of a Regent.6. (1) If any Sovereign who has attained the ager^l\ i Qf eighteen years or any Regent is at his accession or 30 United ,-,      ___________________,     r  , i. .   no_________   -i______j\_____   j i.Kingdom hisaccession,at the commencement of the Regency absent from the United Kingdom, the four persons of full age and present in the United Kingdom who are next in the fine of succession to the Crown, or any two of them, shall, until the Sovereign is able to assume the royal functions, 35 or the Regent is able to assume the Regency, as the case may be, have power in the name and on behalf of the Sovereign to exercise such of the royal functions as may be immediately necessary to be exercised but shall have no power to dissolve Parliament or to grant any rank, 40 title or dignity of the peerage.(2) The   Lords   Justices   Act,   1837,   is   hereby repealed.
7. (1) The   Sovereign  may, if at any time by A.D. 1935. reason of his absence or impending absence from the        United Kingdom or by reason of any illness or other power&apos;.oflike cause he considers it desirable so to do, by Letters (je2egate5 Patent under the Great Seal delegate, subject to such functions tolimitations and conditions, if any, as he thinks fit, all Counsellorsor any of the royal functions to such persons as he of State, thinks fit, being persons capable under this Act of being nominated to and being Regent, and may in 10 like manner revoke or vary any such delegation.(2) Any functions delegated by the Sovereign under the provisions of this section shall be exercised jointly by the persons to whom they are delegated, or by such number of them as may be specified in the Letters 15 Patent, under the style and title of Counsellors of State.(3) The provisions of this section shall apply in relation to a Regent as they apply in relation to the Sovereign with the substitution for the reference to the royal functions of a reference to such of the royal functions 20 as are exercisable by a Regent.(4) Any delegation to Counsellors of State under this section shall cease and determine on the death of the Sovereign or the occurrence of any events neces-sitating a Regency or a change of Regent.25        8. In this Act, save as otherwise expressly provided, Interpreta-the expression &quot; royal functions &quot; includes all powers tion-and authorities belonging to the Crown, whether by virtue of His Majesty&apos;s prerogative or of any statute, together with the receiving of any homage required to be30 done to His Majesty.9. This Act may be cited as the Regency Act, Short title. 1935.
A.D.1935. SCHEDULE.Oaths to be taken by the Regent.1. I swear that I will be faithful and bear true allegiance to [here insert the name of the Sovereign] his heirs and successors according to law.   So help me God. &quot; 52. ,1 swear that I will truly and faithfully execute the office of Regent, and that I will govern according to the laws, customs and statutes of the Realm, and will in all things to the utmost of my power and ability consult and maintain the safety, honour and dignity of [here insert the name of the Sovereign] and the 10 Avelfare of his people.   So help me God.3. I swear that I will inviolably maintain and preserve the Settlement of the true Protestant religion, with the govern-ment, discipline, rights and privileges of the Church of Scotland as established by law.   So help me God. 15

SECRET.Regency Bill.DRAFTOF ABILLTo make provision for a Regency in the event of the Sovereign being on his Accession under the age of eighteen years, and in the event of the incapacity of the Sovereign through illness, for the performance of certain of the royal functions in the name and on behalf of the Sovereign in certain other events, and for purposes connected with the matters aforesaid,CCCLXIV.-A.  (4.)29th March 1935.73-4

</content>
</cab>
