<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/33/12 images: 78-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
... ^       Printed fop the War Cabinet. rJanuary^m ii ,   .TOvBB&apos; KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY;It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the saereoy of this document war CABINET 12 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Wednesday, January20, 1943, at 5;30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right. Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Ringsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State: for India and secretary of State for Burma(Item 6).The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War:The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State forScotland (Item 4).The Right Hon. Sir, Stafford Cripps,- K.G., M.P,, - Minister of - Aircraft -V -ProductiMtPi&quot; .;:The Right Hon. R S Hudson, M.P.,&apos; Mb&apos;&amp; &apos;,&apos; of.    Agriculture- andFisheries (Mem 4).Captain R. A. Pilkington, M.P., CivilThe Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel the Right Hon.. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Item 6).The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt.; M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Item 8).The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Ministerof Health (liem 4).The Right Hon^ Lord Portal, Ministerof Works and Planning (Item 4).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadqgan,Permanent TJnder-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (/^ 1-^2).
WAR CABINET&apos; 12 (18).Contents.Minute       Ii,.^,        i Subject.1     French;Horfch Airioa ........General de Gaulle and General Giraud.2     Air Policy       ....&apos;     1       Targets in France./Regulation 18b ....-. Correspondence of persons detained.4   - Building Programmes....War Office.Air Ministry.Admiralty.;-Ministry of Supply.Ministry of Aircraft Production.Ministry of War Transport.Housing-Future control of Building Programmes.General.      ;5      The Womeh&apos;s services      The Colonies   ....      ....Future Colonial Policy.7.     Air Raids.Casualties and Damage:.      -       j Reports in the Press.;8     Tank Production&quot;9      Casablanca Conference
0 discussion is recorded in(5aulie andGeneral Qnsaa.(Previous -   ,Reference:W.M. (43) 11th&apos;Conclusions.)JUr Policy.  ,Targets inFrance.(previous reference:.W.M,(43) 6ffiConclusions,Minute. 2.). Correspondenceof personsdetained.ConcmsMs;ry&apos;s Standard File of2. Reference was made to the Conclusion on this matterreached by the War ^Cabinet on the 11th January.A record of the discussion and of the Conclusions reached is,contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.1 -    -,f/i3. The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat Sir Barry Domvile, Who was detained under Regulation 18b,wished to have a letter delivered to The Times for publication inthat newspaper. Detained persons were allowed to submit petitionsto the Home Secretary and to Write letters to Members of Parlia-ment, but hitherto they had not been allowed to send letters for publication in the Press. He thought that this privilege could notbe permitted, since it could be used by detained persons as a meansof conducting&quot; propaganda. Refusal to allow a letter to be delivered to a newspaper for publication therein might well, however, be thesubject of controversy in Parliament.The War Cabinet-Endorsed the views of the Home Secretary and Minister ofHome Security.building programmes.(previous reference:W.M., (42) 170thConclusions,Minute 1.)War Office4. On the 17th December, 1942, the War Cabinet had invited the Minister of Production to review air Departmental building programmes&apos;with a view to adjusting requirements to the reducedlabour force which would result from the withdrawal of 225,000 menfrom the building industry during 1943.The War Cabinet now had before them the recommendations made by the Minister of Production as a result of this review(W;P. (43) 23) and a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air(W.P. (43) 35) on the proposals affecting the Air Ministry building programme. rThe proposals of the Minister of Production for the use of ourbuilding resources over the next three months were put forward inthe form of suggested/labour strengths.^for the various Depart-mehtal&apos; programmes. These were intended to serve as a measureof the; work to &apos;be undertaken by each Department and of the labour force Which it should be, possible to make available for it.&apos; It was,however, an.essential part of the proposals that the available supplyof labour should be treated by the minister of Labour and NationalService as a single; pool, which he wOtild be free, to distributejx) thebest effect in&apos; manning the programme as a whole within the approved limits.  . - /The War Cabinet disctissed these proposals under the various(43)23: &apos;     &apos;ilding progranuhe proposed; for the War Office?s of United StateslivingcttdasAtout; in W.Prne reducecti bun
.       SpcrMary,,ofy,S^dt^.far.J%an78&amp;fath&amp;t-faproposed for milling storage&amp;000 .less;.th neee^rytdcarry outthe ap^^ however, prepared: to accept the risks involved in working with this reducthe understanding that, within the reduced limits noSr^i^^e^ft^&apos;labour would be made a in the places where it was&apos;fm&apos;osturgently required.. - The. War Cabinet-, .&apos;\ , &apos;J&apos;&apos;   *,(1) Agreed that in present circumstances it was reasonable toaccept the. risks. InvolvedI in; working to the* reducedprogramme now proposed forthe provision Of accom-modation for UnitedStates forces. -Air Ministry. The Minister of Production pointed out, in his Memorandum,that the building programme of the Air Ministry provided for theconstruction of 635 airfields by the spring of 1944, as comparedwith a previous programme of 669. - In-view of the recent modification of the programme of aircraft production in 1943, hesuggested that; a much larger reduction in the airfield programme was prima facie reasonable. He therefore suggested that the airfield programme for 1944 should be further examined in the lightof the latest available information as to the probable expansion ofthe R.A.F. and the arrivals of.United States-air forces in thiscountry. In the meantime, he recommended that labour should be concentrated on the most urgent works, and suggested an immediatereduction in the labour force from the present level of 120,000 to110,000 at the end of January and 90,000 at the end of March.The Secretary of State for Air, in his Memorandum, claimed that a reduction of the order suggested would involve a sacrificeequivalent, to new airfields capable of providing for nearly20. squadrons.. In spite of the recent cuts in the planned expansionof the R.A.F., strenuous efforts were being made to avoid a reductionin its striking power, and these efforts would be defeated if essentialairfields were hot provided., . Points made in discussion were (a) The figures quoted in W.P. (43) 35 gave only a general indication of the effect of reducing the labour force engaged.inairfield construction. It had not been possible to make any more precise calculations, in terms of loss of squadrons, since the latestprogramme of aircraft production in this country in 1944 had notbeen available.The Minister of Aircraft Production said that this programme was how completed, and the data were now available for a more detailed computation of the number of squadrons that might be equipped in 1944.(6) It was suggested that some of the contractors engaged inairfield construction were more extravagant than others in their useof labour. It was recognised that some of; the1 larger contractorswere more efficient in their use of labour: but it had been foundnecessary, when the &quot;Bolero &quot; programme was launched, to intro-duce a system of pooling in order to ensure that full use was madeof the smaller firms. I &apos;-&apos;y      -TheMinisterq^ consider, inconsultation.whether anyin the useconstruction.The War cabinet-(2) Invited thei   ihister of. Prpduetipn and the Secretary ofState for Air to give further (a&amp;siSeratipn to the labour
of aircraft production in&apos; &apos;ttus country during 1944, and to report in a week -s timewhether the reductions proposed in W.P. (43) 23 could:be&apos;accep1N^Admiralty. The Civil lord of the Admiralty said-/that the labour forceactually employed on Admiralty building work was In fact less than- the -28,000. mentioned in Annex I-of W.pivotal(43) 23*&apos; and that thenumbers - suggested for February to \ March)&apos; were less than were required. The Admiralty accepted tie proposals put forward byy,-the;Minister^Bf Production, On the uhderstanding that this wpulabe definitely allowed for by the:Minister of Production in futurereviews covering the rest of the year 1943.The War Cabinet- &apos;   &apos;   &apos;&apos;(3) Approved the proposed increase in the building labour forceengaged on Admiralty work, subject to the point raisedby the Civil Lord.Ministry of The labour force proposed for the building programmes of theSupply. Ministry of Supply, the Ministry of Aircraft Production and theMinistry of       Ministry of War Transport had been agreed with the MinistersAircraft concerned.Production.,Ministry of The Minister of Aircraft Production pointed out that hisWar Transport, labour force was at present 5,500 below the figure given in Annex Ito W.P. (43) 23. The Minister of Production agreed that therewas rib intention of preventing the Department from bringing thenumbers up to the figure given in Annex I.Housing. (a) The Secnetdry of State for Scotland said that he was anxiousto complete, a number of half-finished houses in areas where theshortage of living accommodation was acute. He regarded this as having, in some areas, a higher priority than the repair of housesdamaged by air attack.It was agreed that, within the limits proposed, labour allotted .for the repair of damaged houses might be diverted to the comple-tion of new houses on which work haa been suspended when theywere more than half-finished.(b) The Chancellor of the E-exchequer asked that the Depart-ments should consult the War-Damage Commission before determination-ing which of the houses damaged by air attack should be selected for repair.TheMinister of H; faith and the Secretary of State for Scotlandundertook to arrange fpr the War Damage Commission to be broughtinto consultation on this point.(c) Th$Minister of Health and the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries asked that, although work Could not start until afterApril,. authority should be given now for the construction of a specified number:of view cottagesi in rural areas. Unless it was&apos;ikhbwn what hiuriber of -cottages hereto be constructed, it would beimpossible to begin the preliminary steps, e.g., negotiations with local authorities aBul the-selectioii- of sites; .The War Cabinet--&apos;(4)Agrebd that these prelm^^on the basis that a total of - 3,000 cottages were, ifpossible, to be constructed in rural areas.   Even if itjve Impossible-to;-proceed: thisyear with&apos; so-large;kits j&amp;eliMiri&amp;tfv woiS ^ojzM msb Is
be. constricted&apos;CtUrmg/1948i&apos; &apos;&apos;&apos;,rr&apos;:&quot;&apos;Z &apos;Futwe Control       -It^.^^^&apos;;^;^ view of:aw&apos;j^uction\6cm^pia^ in the. -pi Building ...  labour&apos; force of the; building industry, it-would be, necessary that-.Programmes.    strict control should-continue to beexercised over the undertaking ofnew building projects. &apos;     -,       ; .-, The Civil Lord of the Admiralty enquired what was meant hythe phrase,,new projects.&quot; &apos; , /- -It was explained that it was contemplated that there should bea scrutiny of all mewl works/over ^ before they arestarted, froni the-point of view of ^ensuringrthat-lhey can be startedwithin the labour force approved by the War Cabinet; the methodto be adopted to resolve any disputes under this procedure could bediscussed further between the Ministers concerned. *The War Cabinet-/ ,(5) Approved the proposals in paragraphs 9-12 of W.P. (43) 23for the future control of the Government building programmes. -:General. It was pointed out that until a settlement had been reached of the Air Ministry building programme, no final decision could bereached on the distribution of building labour as a whole.The War Cabinet, however  \ &apos;  &quot;(6) Agreed that Departments should proceed meanwhile on thebasis of the proposals in (43)23 subject to thepoints recorded above. The absolute ban on new buildingwhich had been imposed during the recent review by theMinister of Production would now be lifted; andprojects for new building would be communicated underthe normal procedure to the Ministry of Works and planning, who would deal with them in the light of thegeneral scheme outlined in W.P.&apos;(43) 23.W.M (42) iisth mittee might include the mii^^^.mm^^^Conclusions,     were to be continued after the war as an integral partiS\L AhEdMinute 4.)       Forces of the Crown, and whether the personnel of Se WomSServices could be utilised for post-war reconstruction in EutopTA ^Agreed that a Committee comprising representatives Ofthe Departments concerned (including the Ministrv ofLabotira^ffie tern^s of reference. ^These woildfrelate to the futureof-the Women&apos;^ Services of the three Defence ServSe^SMsh&apos;of?the^The. Colonies.-,Future colonial policy,(previout!Reference:vConclusions, -0Minute 1.)   Q6. The War Cabinethadbefore them a Joint Memorandum, bythe Deputy Prime Minister, the Secretary&apos; of State for Foreign$$airs, the Lord Privy Seal ;and the Secretary of State for theColonies (W .P. (43), 33) . raiclosiyjg a revised draft of the JomtDeclaration which;- it was proposed,&quot;should form a basis for$Sj^sibn betweenigi^ Majesty^^bassadpr^in Washington andL-.iv.:. T^is,reyigiliMp^to meet points raised by His Maje^y-s Ambassador, Washington,
and by the Dominion Governments, telegrams from which wereannexed&apos;^ The revised draft had not been ajnlll^^ Govern-:&apos;:-jj^$!--fMcG--M&amp; policy&apos; oh which fpaese; suggestions were based had&apos;,:    already been considered by the War; Cabinet and&apos; had been rejected.The Secretary of State for the Colonies explained that the mainalterationrwas^hat Paragraphs of the previous draft of the Declara--;.-tion had been divided into two paragraphs,: and the wording-y&apos;1 .somewhat amended. ,&apos;,&apos;; i    .: ; The advisability of including any reference jto the atlantic charter in the draft Declaration was questioned. -It was pointedout, however, that the reference to the Atlantic Charter only con-cerned &quot; the establishment in the future of a wider and permanentsystem of^neral security.&quot; Moreover, the instructions to lord halifax would, contain a paragraph warning hm that he must beith ; on his guard against any attempt to apply Article 3 of the atlantic charter to the Colonies.The War Cabinet-Approved the revised draft Declaration, and agreed that,when the Prime Minister&apos;s concurrence had been obtained,the following action should be taken : (a) The draft Declaration should be sent to His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Washington, with instructions thathe should discuss the matter with Mr. Hullinformally on the basis of the revised draft.(6) The Dominions Secretary should inform the high commissioners of the Dominions of the action taken,and should also send telegrams of explanation to theDominion Prime Ministers.Air Raids.Casualties and damage.Reports in thePress.(previous references: -W.M. (41) 32ndConclusions,Minute 3; andWI. (42) 119thConclusions,Minute 3.)7. The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat in the course of the daylight raid on London that morning a bomb had hit a school in Catford. According to his information,the Censor at the Ministry of Information had passed a report that24 children in the school had been killed. This was contrary to the ruling that no figures in respect of any one incident when the casulties were in excess of 12 should be given.Later information had now been received to the effect that30 children had been killed and that there were many more bodies which had not yet been recovered. In view of the partial disclosurealready made, it&apos;seemed, desirable that in this case the full factsshould now be published.The War Cabinet-Agreed with the Home Secretary&apos;s view, and endorsed the ruling that the Censorship authorities should not releasefigures of casualties amounting to more than 12 in any oneincident without the authority of the Ministry of home security.Tanh..Production.8. The War Cabinet were informed that it had been decided,at a Meeting of the Defence Committee on the 11th August, 1942,*that the capacity of the Vauxhall group should be switched to themanufacture of the Cromwell series of tanks at the expiry of theorder for 3,500 A. 22 tanks. .Owihg to a change in circumstances, set out in a joint memorandum by the Secretary of State for War and the Ministerof Supply (DO. (43) 2), it was now clear that the Vauxhall group would hot be able to produce Cromwell tanks until the early days* DO. (42) 16th meeting.
of; 1944. If the present decision.was adhered to, and no furtherA. 22 tanks were manufactured on the expiry of the present order,there would be a gap of four or five months. In the circumstances,it was proposed that a continuation order should be given for afurther 500 A. 22 tanks of the latest type, embodying all the most recent improvements.In discussion, some anxiety was expressed that it was not found possible for the Vauxhall group to start production of Cromwelltanks until the early days.of 1944. It was explained, however, that&apos;the plan now proposed was calculated to ensure the most efficient use of the firm&apos;s capacity and the maximum ultimate rate ofproduction.The War Cabinet-(1) Approved the proposal that a further order for 500 A. 22tanks of the latest type, should be placed with theVauxhall group.(2) Took note that the tank situation as a whole would bediscussed at a Meeting of the Defence Committee at anearly date.9. The War Cabinet considered certain telegrams received-from the Prime Minister at Casablanca.A record of the discussion and of the Conclusions reachedis contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions. (7.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,January 20, 1943./r&apos;*.&apos;.&quot;&quot;V-rv.-:;:.. :-.



</content>
</cab>
