<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/35/0 images: 46-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2.      The increases of charges and the dates of their applicationto individual subscribers proposed in the Bill are all such as could be obtained by action in accordance with the terms of theagreement, and the reply to any criticism would therefore bethat the breach of contract was purely technical and of no sub-stance, and need cause no damage to the subscriber.3*      Procedure by legislation has the strong practical advan-tage of a great saving of labour.      Some three million agree-ments are concerned and,  if the increases of charge are not provided for by legislation, the only alternative will be togive to each subscriber notice terminating his present agree-ment and to ask him to sign a fresh agreement.      There are various forms of contract concerned:(a) about three quarters of a million made before 1st October, 193k, requiring three months&apos;notice;(b) about two million taken since 1st October, 1934,whose initial terms have expired and can be terminated at one month&apos;s notice;    and(c) about a quarter of a million whose initial termswill expire at varying dates up to 6th April, 1950.lu      The forms necessary to terminate existing agreements and provide new ones could not be prepared, printed, filled in anddistributed in time for the Budget increases to eome into effecton 1st October;    1st April, 1950 would be the earliest date.Many subscribers would be annoyed by having to enter into freshagreements;    many would not reply and this would lead to anuncertain position at the date when the notice expired.      Long-standing subscribers such as large firms with elaborateinstallations would be put to much work in checking details oftheir apparatus which are at present recorded in numerousagreements and correspondence.      The additional work thrownupon the Post Office is estimated to be of the order of 25,000man weeks, requiring the recruitment and training of additional staff and the renting of additional accommodation.(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS britannic MAJESTY1S GOVERNMEM1)secret. P. (k10)  115 COPY NO. 31I17TH MAY,  19*4-9CABINETTELEGRAPH bill memorandum by the Postmaster general at this morning&apos;s meeting of the Legislation Committee(H. P. C. (k-9) 16th Meeting, Minute 3) fears were expressed that by raising the rental charges for telephone service by Act ofParliament, as is proposed in the Telegraph Bill, a copy ofwhich is annexed, to H. P. C. (k-9) 46, the Government might becharged with breaking contracts, inasmuch as notice of termin-ation of agreement was not to be given to each individualsubscriber.      The increase in local call fees does not call forany action under the agreements.      It will be made by StatutoryRegulation as from 1st July next.

5.      These disadvantages .and difficulties could be avoided bythe legislation proposed and the sending out of a simplenotification - not requiring a reply - of the Budgetaryincreases to- every subscriber in uniform terms unrelated tothe provisions of his particular agreement.6.     Legislation is in any case required to absolve the HullCorporation from payment of the present surcharges to thePostmaster General as is required under the 1940 Act, and toallow the new charges to be retained in full by the Corporation.The Corporation have been informed that this will be done.7.      I hope that my colleagues will agree that the Bill should proceed.      In that case it is important that the notificationreferred to above should go out well before the end of June inorder that no subscriber can complain that he has had shorternotification (in-general terms) than the period of legalnotice he is entitled to under his agreement - in many casesthis is three months.      I shall be glad to receive authorityfor its distribution as soon as the Bill has received its second Reading in the Commons.W. P.General Post Office, E.C. 1.i?TH MAY, 1949.




</content>
</cab>
