<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/35/0 images: 160-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETp-m^) iaa copy ho. 3/2QTH june,  19H9cabinetMOUNT BATTEN ESTATE bill memorandum by the Lord chancellor in view of the controversy which is likely to arise onnf-n:&quot;-&quot;: Heading of the Mountbatten Estate Bill in the Houseoi Coinmono, I have been asked by the Lord President of the Councilto circulate a memorandum so that the Cabinet may consider what attitude should be taken towards the Bill by the&apos; Government.2*  &apos; The Bill has passed the House of Lords and is due for second Reading in the Commons shortly.      Mr.  Conolly Gage,Sir John Mellor, Captain John Crowder, Mr. Walker Smith,Mr. Hollis and Lieutenant-Commander Gurney Braithwaite havethe following notice of a Motion on the order paper:-&quot;To oppose the Second Reading on the ground that theBill seeks to make, for an individual, an amendmentof the lav/ which, if justifiable, should be made by public Act for the benefit of all whom it may concern.&quot;There has also been some pressure from Married Women&apos;s societies and in the Press for general legislation.3. The object of the Bill is to enable CountessMountbatten of Burma to secure the removal of the restraintupon anticipation which is attached - so long as she remainsmarried - to a life interest to which she is entitled incertain income from the estate of her late grandfather,Sir Ernest Joseph Cassel, who died in 1921.      This incomeamounts to  110,000 a year gross.      After allowing for variouscharitable covenants and charges and deduction of tax, the net annual income at the present day is  h,500.      This compares with a net annual income of  2+0,000 in 1939.h. Restraints upon anticipation were invented in theeighteenth century to enable a person settling property on a married woman to protect it from the &quot;Kicks and Kisses&quot; of her husband.      A restraint enables a married woman to receive theyearly income of the estate from the trustees as it falls due,but to prevent her from &quot;anticipating&quot; the future income by,&quot;for example, raising money upon it for the benefit of her husband or his or her creditors.5. The Law Reform (Married Y/omen and Tort Peasors) Act,&quot;1935, was the culmination of a series of Acts to put marriedwomen in exactly the same position as regards their property asunmarried women.      This Act abolished the device of restraintsupon anticipation in the future, but did not affect restraintsimposed by settlements executed before 1936, or restraintsimposed by the wills, whenever executed, of testators dyingbefore 31st December, 19h7-   &apos;  There was some pressure at thetime, particularly from the Married Women&apos;s Societies, for thetotal abolition of restraints, in the past and in the future.But in 1935 there v/as still some force in the argument thatrestraints upon anticipation did operate for the benefit of married women, and the pressure for making the Bill retro-spective was resisted.-1-

6. The effect of removing the restraint upon anticipationwhich is imposed on the life interest of Countess Mountbattenwould be to enable her, in a variety of ways, to raise a capital sum available for her immediate use.      For example,  she could obtain a capital sum from an insurance company, by assigning tothem the whole or part of her future income from the estate -the company effecting an insurance on her life.     Furthermore,as soon as both Countess Mountbatten&apos;s children, who areentitled to an interest in the estate of her grandfather afterher death, attain full age (which will be next year) it would be-open to Countess Mountbatten and her children by mutual agreement to distribute both the capital and the income of the estateamongst themselves in any way they wished.     The adoption of either of these expedients would result in a saving of incometax and surtax to Countess Mountbatten, and there would also bea contingent saving of estate duty on her death.      I willmention these matters more fully later.7* The procedure on Personal Bills in the House of Lordshas always been of a quasi-Judicial nature.      Until a few yearsago it was the practice for the Lord Chancellor to refer theBill to two Judges of the Chancery Division for their opinion asto its propriety and expediency.     On receipt of a favourablereport the Bill was formally introduced by the Lord chancellor and usually passed without debate.      Occasionally a SecondReading was refused on the ground that the Bill was not in thepublic interest - e. g. because it ought to be carried out by ageneral amendment of the lav/ and not by a Personal Bill.      thus a Personal Bill to enable a man to marry his divorced brother &apos;swife was refused on this ground.3. Under the present procedure (in force since 1945) the petition for a Personal Bill (which is invariably introduced inthe House of Lords) is referred to a Special Personal BillsCommittee, mainly composed of Judges, before whom the promoters of the Bill may be represented by Counsel.     The points on whichthis Committee must be satisfied may be summarised as follows:-(a) that the objects of the proposed Bill are not in conflict with public policy;(b) that the benefits to be conferred are peculiar to thepetitioner and that, therefore, the interests ofthe general public are not affected;(c) that the consent of all persons principally concernedin the consequences of the Bill can be obtained and-that the interests of infants affected are safe-guarded;(d) that the objects to be obtained can only be achieved by means of a Personal Bill and not by any other instrument or form of enactment.9, If the Committee is satisfied on all the points mentioned the Chairman of Committees signs a copy of the bill and the Report of the Committee is made to the House.      The oillmay then be presented and read a first time.      Under the new procedure there is rarely,, if ever, any discussion of the billin the House.10 In -bhe House of Commons the procedure on a PersonalBill is identical with that on a Private Bill.      After a^formalintroduction and First Reading the Chairman of Ways and Meansmoves the Second Reading, and, in normal circumstances, the Billis thereupon referred to an Unopposed Bills Committee.      TheChairman may, however, in an appropriate case   treat the Bxll   ^as an opposed Bill and it will then be considered by the Oppo^-d

Bills Committee, whose members are appointed by the Committee of selection.      In the case of this Bill a Debate will arise whenthe Chairman moves the Second Reading and the Government will havean opportunity of intervening to indicate their views.11&quot; I confess that I think there is some justification for the argument put forward by the supporters of the Motionopposing a Second Heading, which is that if it is right toremove a restraint on anticipation for one person, restraintsshould be removed altogether for the benefit of all who may be concerned, and that the abolition which was effected by the LowReform (Married Women and Tort Feosors) i,ct, 1935, should nowbe made complete and retrospective.      In 1935 Parliament resistedthe pressure to abolish restraints retrospectively on the ground,apart from the general objections to retrospective legislation,that it would contravene the intentions of testators and othersettlors.      Since 1935 the economic x^osition has altered con-siderably and it is inevitable, with the present incidence oftaxation, that restraints on anticipation must operate to the disadvantage of married women.     They are in fact an anachronism,since it is inconceivable that any settlor or testator in, say,the year 1921, would have imposed a restraint had he known whatits financial effect would be on the beneficiaries today.12. In the Second Reading Debate in the Commons there willbe, as it seems to rae, two courses open to the Government.      Wemay either(1)   Admit the validity of the arguments of the supporters of the Motion and express our readiness to supportor introduce legislation to abolish those restraintsstill existing in all instances, in which cose Ithink that our support of the present Bill shouldnot be withheld, or(2)    Oppose the arguments for general legislation, in which case it would be logical to oppose the SecondReading of this Bill.13. It would, in my opinion, be wise to take the firstcourse and not the second.The arguments for general legislation are very strong -(a) They are consistent with the attitude of this Govern-rnent regarding married women, and women in general,as being in a position in no way inferior to thatof men.(b) As the law now stands, men and women alike, -with the sole exception of the class of married women stillsubject to the restraint in question, are free todeal with their income as they like.      If they havenot immediate control of their capital, they canraise capital (amongst other ways) by selling partof their income to an Insurance Company.      Theeffect of the general legislation in question wouldbe merely to put this diminishing class of marriedwomen in the same position as all other men andwomen, married or unmarried.(c) Per reasons stated above (in paragraph 11 ) it is nolonger reasonable to preserve these restraints in deference to the supposed wishes of the settlers.

/.       The objections to opposing the Personal Bill now inquestion are as follows:-(i)   The Personal Bill procedure is in its nature quasi-nudicial.      The Committee is constituted with&apos;a strong judicial flavour.      The Committee whichconsidered this Bill consisted of five persons, ofwhom four were lawyers     the Lord Chairman of committees (Lord Drogheda), Lord Hailsham, LordSimonds and Lord Uthwatt,      The fifth was LordKershaw, a Labour Peer.      This Committee, byreporting in favour of the Bill, must be taken tohave been satisfied, amongst other things, that itwas.not contrary to the public interest and that itwas not open to objection on the ground that therelief sought was not proper to bo granted except bya general Act.(ii) On the recommendation of that Committee, I formallyintroduced the Bill and moved the Second Heading.If the Bill was open to objection on political orany other grounds by the Conservative Party or theLabour Party, that was on occasion on which somethingmight have been said.      In fact it passed unchallengedby any member of any Party.(iii) Such being the procedure of the Lords on a PersonalBill, the practice of the -House of Commons intreating a Personal Bill which has been unchallengedin the Lords as an unopposed Bill becomesintelligible.      It would create a new precedent ifthe Commons were to oppose the Bill.1h. In deciding the attitude to be taken by the Government,it is, I think, relevant to consider the financial aspectvis-a-vis the Exchequer, which is incidental to the removal ofrestraints upon anticipation.      This aspect of the matter hasbeen raised recently in the public Press and will no doubtenter into the Second Reading Debate in the Commons.15. I have explained already that on removal of a restraintit is open to the married woman to raise a capital sum on her future income from the estate or to agree with the otherbeneficiaries under the settlement, who are of full age, forthe disposition between her and them of the capital and income in any way they choose.      Any such arrangement would result ina saving of income tax and surtax to the married woman and itmight also reduce or altogether destroy the contingent interestof the Exchequer in estate duties leviable on the interest ofthe married woman at her death.      Although this aspect of thematter is primarily one for the Chancellor of the Exchequer,I question whether it raises a consideration which shouldinfluence the Government&apos;s policy either towards the Bill ortowards final legislation to abolish restraints.      The extentto which private individuals,should be allowed to.deal freelywith their own property should, I feel, depend, upon considera-tions of public policy rather than on fiscal considerations.Ho one is bound so to arrange his affairs as to attract the maximum amount of tax;    and in considering what arrangements an individual can properly be allowed to ma^e mregard to his own property the advantage or disadvantage tothe revenue of those arrangements should surely not oe arelevant or at least not a governing consideration.      Theexistence of a restraint on anticipation, which is designeapurely for the protection of a married woman, is fortuitous so-h-

far as the Exchequer is concerned.      My colleagues may thinkthat to take advantage of restraints in this way would heunjust, and undesirable in view of the far-reaching effects on policy.      Moreover, a restraint upon anticipation is adevice of a temporary nature;    it operates only during the marriage of a woman, and on the death or divorce of her&quot;husband she is placed in the same position with.regard to her future income as an unmarried woman.      She may raise capitalupon it or come to an agreement with the other beneficiariesto obtain a capital sum in the way I have suggested.      Further-more,  I should mention that it is open to any married womanwho is subject to a restraint to ask the Chancery Court toremove the restraint for a specified purpose.      This was infact done by Countess Mountbatten to enable her to provide adowry for her eldest daughter on her marriage.     On any suchapplication the Coxirt would take into consideration only thebenefit which would accrue to the married woman by the removaland would certainly not be influenced against the application by the incidental effect which the removal might have in reducing her liability to tax.      In very large estates such asthe one which forms the subject of the Bill, it is difficult for tho beneficiaries to foresee the occasions or purposes for which it would be desirable to raise capital sums on thesecurity of future income.      So long as the restraint exists,it would be necessary to apply to the Court each time thatthe raising of a capital sum was desired, and this wouldinvolve a number of expensive applications.16. My conclusions are as follows(1) If we are prepared to support the principle of ageneral Bill releasing married women from the-   disability which attaches to them by reason ofrestraints on anticipation we should, I think,support the Mountbatten Estate Bill.(2) If we are not prepared to support such a generalBill we should,  I think, oppose the present Bill,as it does not seem to me right in this case toconfer a favour on one individual which is denied to others.J.House of Lords, S. W.1.20TH JUNE,  19^-9.




</content>
</cab>
