<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/35/0 images: 340-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/-    175PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)OONPIDENTIAL.P.(4?) 1lf2 COPY NO.     3^28TH JUNE. 1949CABINETSUCCESSION TO THE CROWN ACT,1707;    PROPOSEDINDEMNIFYING BILL     &quot;     &apos; &apos;Memorandum bv the Lord President of the Counciland the Home secretary mr. J. B. Hynd, M. P. , who was recently appointed amember of the General Medical Council, has raised the questionwhether, in view of the Succession to the Crown Act, 1707s his appointment might have prejudiced his position as a Member ofParliament.     Because of his doubts on the point he hasrefrained from taking part in any of the proceedings of&apos;theCouncil since it was raised at the first meeting he attended.2. We have consulted the Attorney-General about Mr. Hynd&apos;s position.     He considers that membership of theGeneral Medical Council on the nomination of the Crown doesconstitute the holding of an office of profit under the Crown,It is possible to argue whether the office is &quot;under theCrown&quot; or &quot;from the Crown&quot; or not&apos;within the scope of the act of 1707 at all, but he has no doubt that the better view isthat. Section 24 of the Act applies.The position is not in the Attorney-General&apos;s viewaffected by the fact that Mr, Hynd has not taken any part inthe work of the Council since the question was raised andhas not taken any fee.     The Attorney-General points out, too,that others are affected.  .  Lord Kennet (1926 and 1931),Lord Hacking (1931, 1936, 1941 and 1946) and Mr. J. J, Robert-son, M. P.   (194-6), all of them Members of the House of Commonswhen appointed to the Council, have all held the office .previously.     Lord Kennet and Lord Hacking cannot now be suedfor penalties because the statutory period has elapsed, but mr. Robertson remains liable to the disqualification and penalties of the statute.3. The Attorney-General has also advised that indemni-fication is necessary in the case of Mr. Albert Evans, M,P. ,the senior partner in the firm of Evans Brothers, which, inthe course of the last three years, has entered into a numberof small transactions involving the sale of electrical equip-ment to a value of less than  100 to the Home Office.     Thisfirm was selected to provide the equipment because, of thevarious firms approached, it offered.the earliest deliveries,at competitive prices.4. In the circumstances, it seems to us that there isno alternative to the introduction of an indemnifying Billto cover the cases of Mr.  Hynd, Mr. Robertson and Mr. Evans,and that the Opposition should be consulted, both as regardsthis Bill and the cases of Lord Kennet and Lord Hacking*H. M.J. C. E.28th June. 1949




</content>
</cab>
