<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/78/0 images: 73-82</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document ithe Property ofBOARD OF TRADE,547, WHITEHALL GARDENS,LONDON, S.W.1.the(1)(2)(3)(4)-       GOAL INDU-JTRf Q04iI3&amp;IQN        mmA mm report. I circulate, for the information of my colleagues,attached Memorandum by the Coal Controller. The points requiring Gabinet decision areThe date from which the owners are to ha charged     with the increased wages.The date from ;hich an amended Agreement or new Act     is to become operative.Whether the profits of Ocke Ovens and Bye product     Hants are to be included.Whether any allowance is  to be  made for additional     capital expended on  the mines since 1913.A. 0. GLTOS,15th April, 1919,
ffor the cabinet.               GOAL   IKgJgggC   COMMISSION.                   INTLHIM mm ElffQRT.Memorandum on the interpretation of the Interim Report andon the arrangements necessary to give effect to its recom-raendations as regards the limitation of the profits of the                        Coal Owners.   The Interim Saakey Report provides -(1)     That wages are to he increased by 2/- per day for men   and 1/- per day for hoys, which is equal to &quot;about  30,000,000   per annum.(2)    , That from July 16th next 7 hours is to be substituted   for 8 hours as the&apos; day1 s work  making a reduction of 12f/0t   which is estimated to reduce the output by 10%. this &quot;being   equivalent to a reduction of prof its&quot; &quot;by  13,000,000 for 6   months  on an output of 250,000,000 tons per annum, or at   the rate of  26,000,000 per annum if the reduction in out-   put continue.(3)     That in order partly to meet the  increased cost, the   profits to bo retained by owners are to&quot; be limited to an   average of 14d. per ton of coal raised, which on an output   of 2513 000,000 tons is approximately  15,000,000.  It is   estimated in the Report that the surplus profits over the   Sankey standard, if&quot; the rate of profit for Hie September   quarter of 1918 continues for fee year 1919,will&quot; pro vide    30.000,000 towards the increased cost.  It should &quot;be noted   that tho greater part of t!;e surplus profits would under   the present Finance Acts he collected by the  State  in i&amp;cess   Profits Duty and would therefore to that extent not be paid   by the Owners but by the State.        The effect of the adoption of tba Sankey Report on the   cost to the State is shewn&apos;&quot; in the Appendix to this  memoran-   dum.        In order to carry the recommendations of the report in-   to effect the present1 Goal Mines Control Agreement and Con-    iraation Act,  1918, will havo  to be amended  or a new Knact-   ing Bill passed through Parliament.        It is agreed that the Average Rate of 14d.  per ton is   to be distributed among individual undertakings by reducing   their pre-war standards in tho  same proportion that    15 000,000 bears to the  aggregate Pre-war Profits Standard   of the whole  industry.   The details of the&apos; method of distri-   bution and its  adjustments are  now being discussed with the   Owners and are  nor likely to lead to difficulty.
     The Report itself does not give any definition of&quot;Profits&quot;, hor does it state what the 14d. includes. Itis held by Mr.  Justice Bonkey to include the profits of(Joke Ovens and Bye-Product  Plants, which are excludedfrom the present Coal Mines Agreement, and also to in-clude interest on Loan Capital  and remuneration for Oap-ital Expenditure on the Mines themselves incurred since1913 or previously.     The following important questions arise for decision;-  (1)   -The date from which the Owners are to he charged     with the increased wage.  It is clearly understood     that as far as the men are concerned i&apos;t is to be paid     from January 9th last.  (2)   The date from which the amended Agreement or iSnact-      ingBill, whichever may be adopted, imposing the new      limitation of profits &quot;and the consequential altera-      tions is to&apos;become operative.  (3)   Whether the Profits of Coke Ovens and Bye-Product      Plants are to be included in  the new standard of 14d.      per  ton of coal raised.  (4)   Whether any allowance is to be made for additional      Capital expended on the Mines since 1913.  The 14d,      is based on the average profits of the 5 pre-war      years.(1) fjti      froqifffeigli to Qmm m to ks togsd with          It is  contended by the  Owners -     (a)     That although it was  understood,  so far as the         men were concerned, that any  increased wage  awarded         was to  date  back to January 9th, they were no party         to this Agreement,  and were not consulted.     (b)     That although the Goal Controller can order any         increase of  wage to be paid and charged against         expense it has not  hitherto-been done without a         compensating increase in the  price of coal nor has         it been dona retrospectively for more than a few         weeks.     (c)     That the  Government must themselves pay this         money both for the  arrears and future payments and         get it  back  throu$i the  operations of &quot;the Goal         Mines Agreement, so far at tlx ere are profits avail-         able*      It&apos;has been arranged with the Coal Owners that  the Government will provisionally advance tho money without prejudice as to who  is to be liable for its  eventual pay-jnent.
The question to be settled therefore are:-

(a) Are the Government or the Owners to be liable for its eventual payment as from January 9th last until such date as is imposed or agreed upon the determination of the present Agreement?

(b) Are the Government to continue paying this money weekly in future as required and to treat it as an advance to be re?overed out of any profits in excess of the Standard? or

(c) Will the Government fix a date after which the Owners themselves must find the money and charge it as an expense of the business?

It should be clearly understood that from the date at which the new Standard becomes operative it is immaterial whether the additional wage is payable by the Government or by the Owners. The Owners would, in either case, retain in the aggregate 14d per ton of output.

It is likely, therefore, that if they were relieved of the liability for the extra wage until the new Agreement of Act comes into force they would accept the liability from that time onwards.

(2) The date from which the new Agreement or Act is to come into force.

Under the present Agreement the Owners are entitled to the profits Standard of the Finance (No.2) Act, 1915. Under the Sankey Report this Standard will have to be reduced to the equivalent of the 14d. per ton on the actual output, both being adjusted in accordance with the provisions of the Agreement regulating the guaranteed Standards.

The Owners contend that they are entitled to the benefits of the present Agreement until it is terminated by notice.

The Agreement provides that after a certain date (which has been passed) it can be terminated by the Controller of Coal Mines at any time without notice.

The date of termination cannot be made retrospective except by Agreement or by Act of Parliament.

It is suggested that it would be inequitable to make the Agreement retrospective to the 1st January, the Sankey Report being accepted by the Miners only on April 15th, unless an allowance be made to the Owners for the period from the 1st January to the 15th April of the difference between the Sankey Standard and the guaranteed standard under the Coal Mines Control Agreement. If this be conceded it is believed that the Owners would agree to continue to operate the mines under an amended agreement, pending the decision of the Government on the larger question of nationalisation and control after the Second Report of the Sankey Commission.


In considering this important question it must boborne in mind that at present the Government take all the profits over the Finance Adts Standard (subjectto an allowance of 12$ for additional capital employedin excess of that employed in the., standard period),except fffi of the excess, and that by fixing the dateof the application of the now Standard as 15th Aprul,instead of malting it retrospective to the 1st January,they would only suffor to tho extent, approximately,of the difference between the two Standards for 3-g-months;  which would bo equal to about  3,000,000.Whether the profits of Cojra Ovens and Bye ?roftugtflanls, wMch are part jT^aTToIllery ^ldo^tTlfing,u areto bo in oludod in  hold a * joor&apos;Ton*(c)   The Coal Industry Commission Act brings witin    the terms of reference of the Commission not only    the Coal Industry but any industry commonly carries    on In connection therewith,  or as ancillary or    incidontal thereto.   nr. Shortt stated in tho    House of Commons .in the Committee Stage of tho    Coal Industry Commission Sill as follows:    &quot;The    intention is that in addition to enquiring into    the coaling operations of the industry the Commissi    should also be able to go into the question of    coking ovens and any other bye-products ancillary    to the Coal industry.&quot;       ...&quot;  fixe average 5 year pre-war profits of 1/- per  -ton upon whioh llr. Justice Sankoy based his    standard of 1*-*.,. *jr\ include the profits of such    Coke Cvens and Bye-Product Hants as were then    in operation,  out they were  no*c included in the    estimated profits of  54,000,000 upon which he    based his calculations as to the deficiency.         This question has been  fully discussed between    Lr. Justice Sankey, Sir Robert Home and Sir    Evan Jones. &apos; &apos;j r. Justice Sankey states that ho    meant .&apos;tho Profits of those Coke Cvens and  Bye-    Product Plants whioh are under the same ownership    as tho Coal Lines to be  included as part of tho    profits of coal raised,  but  that this would not    apply ...to those Plants which, although thoy may bo    situated at the  Colliery, would not bo under the&apos;    samo  ownorship.    He agreoe, howover, it would be    just that an allowance should bo made for  interest    on Capital o;.ponded since 1913,  or expended    previously,  but which had not bcoome productive    until after 1913,  on Coke Ovens and Bye-Product    Plants,  as an  addition to the Standard Rate of 146    por ton or its oquivalont as tho case may  be.         The following points should be taken  into    consideration:-      (a)  Coke Ovens and Bye-Product Plants are dealt          with as  a  distinct and separate industry          and are  separately assessed by the Inland          Revenue  both for the purpose of Income  Tax          and Excess Profits Duty.      (b)  The Report states  that the  average standard          Profit of  14distwr ton of  coal  raised  and ii          is  n^t n^nr^nnrf fj0  include t^o profits  of          coke  ovens and  bye  product plants.
(c)  The Collieries havingOoke Ovens would therefore  have     little inducement to continue to work them,  as  they     would still be entitled to aporoximately the same     standard profit per ton of coal raised if  they  stopped     their Coke Ovens.(d)  The great development-of Coke Oven and Bye-rroduct  ilai     during the ;iar was primarily due to the urgent  afar     necessity for these predicts, and their erection and     development were actively encouraged by the  Government     and controlled in the  interests of the&apos;Hat ion.   Their     post-war development is equally important.(e)  The Coke  Ovens are expressly excluded from the Coal     Hines Control Agreement (Confirmation) iict,(f)  Although  the Profits of the Coke Ovens for the 5 pre-     war yearsr  average wore included in the 1/- per  ton     average profit of coal  raised,  they amounted  only     of coal they represented about  6fd per  ton of  coal  raised,     which would be included in the  profits  limited to 14d     per ton.(g)  The Coal  Owners strongly protest  against  their inclusion,     and definitely state  it will kill the industry as far as     they are  oon.cerr.ed-.   They lay special stress on the faoj     that they are definitely excluded from  the  Coal ,rmeH     Control iigreement  by  a  clause in  the Act,  and  point out     that the  Capital invested in the  Coke Ovens is  in tho     case of some Collieries as much,  if not more than,  that     invested  in the Minesj  and furtier, that  only  a small     proportion of the  total number  of Collieries have Coke     Ovens k and that &quot;in consequence  a  very invidious dis-     tinction  will be drawn  against  those Owners who had erected     Coke Oven Plants.     If it is determined that the Colje Ovens and Bye-Products Plantsare to be included pnder the new Agreement the amount of interestto be allowed in consideration of the expenditure of additional capital since 1913, requires to be determined.  Under theFinance Act, 1918 the fate allowed for i&amp;cess Profits Dutypurposes is 9^.Whether any allowance is to be made,for additional, Capitalexpended since 1913,      *-     It is claimed by the owners that interest should be allowedon capital now employed in excess of  that employed in the pre-war period.     In so far as the capital has increased the earning capacity of the undertaking the Coal  Aines Control Agreementprovides for it to be rewarded.  Moreover, in fixing 14d as taestandard of profit as compared with tho pre-war  average of 1/-,;Ir. Justice aankey has taken into account the increase m thecapital employed in tho mines.
      It  should  be  pointed  out  that  capital  invested  in development  should1lead  to increased  output  and so to an  increase  in  the aggregate of  the standards provided for by Mr. Justice Sankey,  but the  owners contend that  the Sankey Standard of Profits is not sufficient to render the introduction  of further capital remunerative either for the purpose, of  maintaining  the existing output of mines or  for new  developments.      As a matter of. fact the Sankey Report is alreadyhaving a marked effect in arresting development.      In regard to  the General question of the sufficiencyof the standard of  14d per  ton of coal raised, as recommended by the  Sankey Report , it is pointed out bythe Owners that the present reduced value of money ascompared with the pre-war value has not been taken intoaccount and that the value of 14d today consequentlybears no relation  to the value  of 14d  before the war.     To place the owners on the same basis of profitin relation to the purchasing powers of money as in thepre-war years it would be necessary to allow 2/- todayfor every If - in 1913.EYAIf D. J0KT.S.Controller of Coal Mines,      15.4.19.(6)
Appendix.      Sankey Interim Report.The Cost to the State.     The Sankey Report estimates  54,000,000 as the profit of the Coal Industry lor 1919.     This figure is arrived at as follows;-          The profits for the quarter ending 30th September,     1916, were estimated as equal to 3/7d, per ton on the  -     actual output of the whole industry,          It was assumed tht;t for the year 1919 the output     would be increased to 264,000,000 tons which ^ould have     the effect of reducing the cost per ton and therefore     increasing the profit&apos;per ton by&apos;6d.          It ms therefore estimated that, assuming the average     selling price of coal (including exported coal) was main-     tained,&apos; the profit of the whole&quot;industry for the year  1919     would be 264,000,000 x (3/7d. * 6d.)-4/1 -  54,000,000.          The 4/ld. per ton is exclusive of the profits of  Coke     Ovens and Bye Product Plants, but inclusive&quot;of the interest     on Loan Capital.          From the  54,000,000 thus arrived at x,he Sankey Report     deducts  9,000,000, equal to an average profit of 8d per     ton over the whole output, for the probable tailing off in     the profits on Coal exported, which niidiu be due  &apos;  either     to a reduction in the quantity exported or to a fall in     the price or to both;  thus bringing the total estimated     profits ior 1919 down to  45,000,000 - out of which it     allows  15,000,000 to be retained by the Owners, leaving      30,000,000 as available towards the cost of the increased     wage and reduced hours, which the report estimates at      43,000,000.          This estimate of  43,000,000 is  Me UP of  30,000,000     for increased      for one year and  13,000.000 for increase&quot;     ed cost ior six months due to reduced output following     the reduction in hours,          It has been estimated that a reduction of I2ir&amp; in the     working hours **ill result in a. reduction of IQ&amp; in the out-     put which, would increase costs and reduce the profits by     about  13,000,000 for 6 months.
     As  the shortened hours  do net come  into operation now  July -  the report estimates as  the oost  for thisyear (i.e. up to Deo. 51st.  1919);-                   *    Increase  cf wages for 1  year----- -  30;000,000.    Less  of output  for six months-  13.0001000.                                            43,000,000.    Less  amount to  &quot;be recovered by           limiting profits  ---------  30,000,000.                    - Deficiency-----  13,000,000.     It must  be carefully noted that this is on the assump-tion that the  eternal profits mad*! in the third quarterof 1918 will  be maintained,  less the 8d per ton allowed for a  falling  off in 1he profits of the Export !Erade.     fhe  Sankey Report speculates&apos; (p.11) on a  decrease inthe estimated  reduction of output, and on savings byeconomies in  production, etc.   As regards the first,although  in course  of tiire seme decrease may be looked for,it is not safe to make any allowance on this account inpresent calculations.   As regards the second, the limitationof Profits to  a fixed rate per ton while it provides an incentive to ir/ reased outputi, gives no inducement to economy in working.    Since Owners can be sure of their equivalent of 14d. per ton profit, even with antiquated methods, and canIn no casetretain more, the  oost of produotion becomesimmaterial, and there is nothing to induce them to expendfurther Capital on  improved methods or even to checkextravagance or waste*    further the same effect will beproduced  in oomnercial transactions.  The price to be obtained for the ooal will be immaterial to the seller.     In order  to arrive at the cost to the State whichwill be involved in the maintenance of the new guaranteedstandard, alter providing- for the oost of the  increased wages and decreased output, the figures for one whole year will be as iclloT/s. assuming the price to the  home consumeris not raised;-     Profit assumed by Sankey Report ---------    45,000,000        Deduct - Increase in wages                    (1 year) ------  30,000,000                Decrease in  output                    (1 year)----- 26.000,000   56,000,000                                       Loss       11,000,000.     Owners Guaranteed Standard--------------- 15,000,000.                           ?otal deficiency       26,000,000.
T^^S^K?11^11 should be provided in the estimate for1919-20 Trill depend on the decision as to the date when thenenf Sankey Standard of Profit is to come into operation.Assuming this date is made retrospective to 1st January soas to coincide approximately with the payment of the increased wages,  the amount should be:-    Increased wages - 9th Jan: 1919 to                     31st Dec: 1919          30,000,000        &quot;       M     1st Jan; 1920 to                     31st Mar: 1920           7,ftJ0,000    Decrease in Output - 1st July 1919 to                        31st Dec: 1919       13,000,006n     ii    tt- 1st Jan: 1920 to 31st Mar: 1920        6,500,000                     &quot;57^000^000*Estimated Profits on basisof September quarter of 1918,for year to 31st Dec, 1919 -  45,000,000Do, on first three monthsf or 1920                   -  11,250,000 56,250,000Less Owners GuaranteedStandard for 1  years      -  18,750,000 37,500,000Amount required to meet deficiency                     19,500,000      If on the other hand it is decided that the Sankey Standard shall not be applied to the owners until some subsequent date, &quot;then for every month it is so deferred approximately  1,000,000 must be added to the Estimate.      These estimates are on,the assumption that the assumed Sankey Profit At the rate of  45,000,000 per annum^will be realised arxl they are subject.to increase or decrease in proportion to any variation in this assumed profit.      The cost J$ the State should be regarded from the point of view that the lack of incentive to economy  will be cumulative in its effect, and it is .not reasonable to expect that the profits will be maintained at the level of 1918.  On the contrary, it should be  coraidered that the maximum profits to be retained.by the Owners will become the maximum prof its of the industry, even if  they would be maintained at that  level.                                   EVAN D. JOKES.

</content>
</cab>
