<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/78/0 images: 88-105</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/2.&apos;^TCA0 vT*X BOARD Off AGRICULTUKB AMD FI3H1SRISS. jjjj^^eJ0% **or weejc en^e(^ 15th April,  191^*ART I.  - ; i&apos;Q0D PRODUCTION&quot; DEPART:MNT *The Weather and-Condition j?f Crops,.. .          The weather for the most part has.been fine withoccasional showers in some districts.   Progress has;b*jenmade withspring cultivation work, and a considerable amount of spring cornhas been drilled.          Crops on the whole look well.   Autumn sewn wheat- has improved under tha influence, of the fine weather, except in thewestern counties, where wheat lo.6ks sickly.,   A low rate of.mortalityamongst ewes and lambs is reported from Yorkshire where the lambingseason is how nearly over,                     Land Division&quot;,- &quot;  &apos;                  (i) Land&apos;Settlement, ..     j\pplieations f*r Small Holdings,-   The fellewing statement is &amp;summary ox a&apos;return obtained by the Board Bhowing the-number, cf&quot;applications received by Local Authorities:-Authority.	Applications from Service or ex-Service men.		Applications from Civilians.		Tttal,. ,:		&quot;No. of Applicants	Acreage	Jtb, of Applicants	i -Acreage	No. of Applicants	Acrta^aY.lottnty Councils	a, troops &apos; 281	165,, 604 11,050 2,673	3,057 450 .14	* 46,258 &apos;.t,48l&apos; &apos; 452	ir,06B 9 s * IIOIO 355 *	213,732-20,631. 3,325England * * * * * lales ....... liunty Bcrei&amp;hs						England and Wales ..... Hal England and Wales , * *							- 9,748	170,427	3,581	68,191	&apos; 13., 329	237,615          The Cornwall County Council have supplied the firstdetailed analysis of the applications for small holdings received b;them up to the 9th April, 1919.   Out of 269. applicants, 15 only havebeen rejected after interview, while 10 have withdrawn their&apos;applications.   The  44 applicants who remain on the books ar*classified as follows:-      &apos;  -                 Interviewed and Approved* 77 have applied for small holdings totalling *. 42   n     M     &quot;  accommodation holdings                              totalling  ....... 21   w     M     w  cottage holdings totalling,  8 no particulars148                 Still to be Interviewed. 96 no particulars2442,754 aeree454 61175it3,4642,4195,883 aoreB,
i    -Land  Settlement through County council..  Buring the weekheliding  puroHasee  cf^Tand &quot;by County Councils under the Small                                                                th*                                                                holding and Allotments Act, 190.6, mainly for the purpose front providing holdings&apos;.for ex-service men, have been approved by.tho Eeardf-Bedfordparish;Acreage , &apos;   Purchase, Erie a             Oakley. Stafford 3-riage awl               Olipp Hill allotments.  &apos;.,             Arlington. Newton Detate             Saintb*ry and iVillersfcy,             Part Saint bury; Estate!.&apos;             St. Stephens (St, Albane)               Ne3ce Fa/auIsle -&apos;ff Ely  flhit tieeey,&apos; Hay&apos;e. Farau   do.       Parsers Dreve, Threekeiihelt           . -             . &apos;  &apos;   Farm  &apos;;:Salep       * We* Jte&amp;l, Land at SoultsnCheshireGloucester.Hert erd9U 51 4:3S&amp;K$r(*et     Cresosmbe. Upper Thrupe Farm.   66tfti$esterl&amp;lvern Links and HallewPart liadreafield Court-  Estate          1.Heiywell $state  ^Afceey Farm  freer Farm . 20X&amp;3 7$- 13, be. perpetuai-  rentcharge, 14,000  1,875  2,300 12,COO.1M.08  1,900 itti,timber at a&quot; ivaluation,.  4,0841,4*96 &apos;:4J300 -2.,0Q0.          ?he  Beard also  approved schemes for the.leasing by tfce  I.....-Sarttt County  .Council  of  31 acres cf land at Charlton i^marshal], tM?14/years  at  ayreht  of   50 per annum, and by the Wilts County CounVy.;tif&apos;yart&apos; ef  engleaze Farm,  eevil,  comprising 17 acres,  for 14 ye art   an annual rent of  35.                                     &apos;  :*   .   . .   Since  the&apos;20 th  Be comber,  1918, the Beard have apprsveji ityafquiattiisn  Vy County  Councils of I0,8$9 acres, of whi*h 0,605 aerffc.aVo, in England and  1,18.6  acres in Wales,.   Tho fallowing otatemeutr&quot;*vshsws the dates  en  which  vacant pessesoion will be obtained:?Possession already obtained  . *.Michaelmas, 1910  .* *..........&apos;f13th&apos; November, 1919&apos;...........Candlemas, 1920 ...............Lady Lay,&apos; 1920 ..**,*..*.*.....6*h * April., 1920 ...............jUchaelmas, 1920  ,..4 *********november, 1920  ...............No information  ...............Acres, 2,&apos;682 3,367   4&apos;36 1,940 1,446   306   139   137          In addition, the Beard have  under cenaideratien pT&amp;pfsali .TyCounty Councils fyr the acquisition of 7$f05?j  aeres,  includi*V3ir*  .aeres irtiieh ths Council propose to  acquire by  the exercise efe,empuJLsory poTrers.   cf this  total,. 74,122 aeres are  in England, and&apos;4,933 acres in Wales.     Coicpulsory, Orders.  Uhe  Isle ff Ely  County Council precise tfjtake an order for the e^aBpuLa^sary aAquialtianjef-. Alley Farm, Itlurrew/ .t&apos;Cmprising 120 acres.
       Offers .of  and &quot;by Tjatii-swnera,   The of fare received direct by th?  Beard in response &apos;U     iPr^eideJacfc^a, appeal to landcwiiers Jt&amp;r laad  ....(?* suitable for &apos;smai.l ; holdings &quot;i&amp;uafaH?  jM, comprising/ approarimatoCLy  .34,000 acres&quot;,  &apos; Tho a;,  are  bditfg .dsalt with. as. iMioat^d- below,   eolined, Ware er after  inspection  61 cf^ers representing&apos;  4,010  Further particulars ro^uirfcd           84    &quot; &apos;  &quot; .,,    w        T.j463  Heforred t.tf Commissioners  for  .             &apos;.V  .   &apos;inspection           40 .   tt         &quot; .      - $.,$40  Referred by C amis si oners  to  County-                    *      - \; -   1 &quot; Councils-as prima  facie.&quot;suitable -. g &apos;   &quot;         M       . ,  906 .mth&amp;ratm     -                        &quot;.g - -           ;*   ,       aoq           The Duchy gf! Lancaster hare -nc,t*ff Aa4- the Board -that 4 farms in/YyrksJairy&apos;comprising &quot;a: total area&apos; yf &quot;X.,7-64 &quot;acres.&apos;and- a farm ;o  340-&apos;acres in Stafford will \fe vacant at/Lady &quot; ay.:&apos;1$&apos;2Q;&amp;nd that.&apos; thby will  give prior consideration tp;au appl-io at%v&amp;.tha $r-ard fsr a . - leaeeof any of them, &apos;  The matter  has  been referred; to the &quot;twt?-. Pistrict: Commissioners concerned,,  &apos;     &quot; .. &apos;   &apos;        &apos;                &apos;    .      .. Set,fl emefntfl adminig^ereU^ty-&apos;&apos;&apos; tfoft ffiardv   The area ^f land myqu^rod fqr^admlni&quot;stiatisn by&quot;Th?^&apos;^aroT^itBerf is 12.., 267 &apos;a/yrssV !pfor^&apos; are  low 119&apos; exV-service .men&quot; Working on the farm .t?^&quot;ttle?C6ntsj  a rui-ther &apos;21&quot; have been accepted as probationers but&apos; have&apos; n^t. ye t - starts works   . fifteen men-of Agricultural  Companies ars  also working on * th^-sottlements,                                                 . &apos;           At Hol^acji and Heath Hill- a,large amciant of&apos; field wark-was carried emt;lasT&quot;week and&apos;-g&apos;ood.progres-s&apos;- is- being&quot;-made by the&apos;&apos; settlers. At Jjemlrrsy also&apos;.pr9gr-qs8 ia being made  with the drilling of spring&apos;-^ra, T^uT thore, is a large amount still tp  he-done. -  Woric ,is-well. forward at. -the. Boabury settlement and all  spring corn- has new- beon-drilledf   &apos;---&apos;  *   &apos;       &apos;&quot;..&apos;-&apos;.                        &apos;&quot;      &apos;--&apos;           ^ PM^^i^n p^saescicn  hat&apos;been/abtaih^d;&apos;&amp;f ian adjoining farm,  01* Hall farm/ recently taken from the Crown^-&apos; :j. The&quot; farm has been  equipped with horses and implements *    Over 150 aar^s have  yet to be  ploughed?&apos;  of this amount it  is prb^sGd t6  fallow   GC: aorss this year,     ,                          ..    - -      &apos;   -\            &apos;. ;(ii.) Work- of Agricultural Executive  Committees,     yetftradjyitlcn nf Tenanciest &apos; The BoOJ-d have during the.past wivek IssiKvl an Order determining the tenancy on  account  of bad farming of a  farm (75  acres)  at Hatfield in: the  es Ri.di^. .   The Order will however- ??c  held in suspense bjr the Sx^VuHvVrc^o^itte-e while-an effort is. made &quot;to come tn a voluntary arrange nt-&apos;-as&apos;.&apos; it - la stated by the tenant, that the1 pfmer&apos; contemplates  dividing the farm  and allowing him to retain half the - holding,, in which case&apos;the  Ccmmitt^e  think n* might be able to farm the land adequately., -    &apos;. &apos; &apos;f&quot;            -  (iii) -Provision ef Alistmente,           Th* - Somerset Agricultural Executivo Committee has  bsen Authtrised  t^ take possession of 3^  acres r:f-land  at ^cfltlury-suK- &quot;endip and  ^f H acres at High Littlflti,n and ta let .thea&apos; to  thfi
Parish Councils concerned .for the purpose of providing allotments.          The Board are- informed by one of their Inspectors that the.Borough of Stoke-cn-Trent with a population  in 1911 of 235,.000. has   fprovided 9,024 allotments out of an area of  409 acres, that is to say&quot;one allotment to every 26 persons.          As a result of representations put forward to the owners  &apos;concerned &quot;by one of the Board1s-Inspectors the Ely Urban DistriotCourieil have-acquired a 1-f acre field which  will provide 2?allotments.                                                    *                *          The general embargo laid by the Treasury on the raising ofleans by Local Authorities having been removed, it is hoped thatloans will now.be available to enable Local  Authorities to purchaseland in suitable oases for allotments but the high rate of interest which will&apos;be charged, by the Public Works Loan Commissioners willmake it very difficult for the Local Allotments Authorities topurchase land for this&apos;purpose and&apos; to let- it at rents which will he-sufficient to ,cever -their outgoings, and at. the fcame time&apos; be .&apos;reasonable from the point of view of the cultivator.                            - *  v,                       Commercial Pivlsion.     $mall,Holdings Equipment.       Type, Plane.  14 type plans of Cottages suitable for variouselasse-s of e*pa.i!L holdings have now been prepared.   They eemprisei.**   Type A.I.  Single.Bungalow Cottage.- (3 bedrooms).   Type 3. Single. Cottage: s with 3 bedrooms.                        . v.   Type lB.3.  Single 5 rc*om cottage. L plan  with low Out building.:     &quot;  &apos;B,4.    &quot;    &quot;   ,r     &quot;     I plan  self contained.     &quot;  B,5..    &quot;    &quot;   &quot;     &quot;     L plan  self contained,     M  B..6..-   H    &quot;   &quot;     M     Rectangular plan- self contained      (experimental cottage with Concrete block construction).    ye ;C Single Cottages with  4 bedrooms.   -,fpe. C,l. Single CD tt age ,.4 bedrooms, no  dairy.        0.2.    &quot;      &quot;          &quot;      with dairy.Type D. Double Cottagos.Type .B.-1, 6 Room Cottage, L,plan, L&apos;ath in  Scullery,  &quot;  1,2, 6 Room, L plan., ixont entrance.-   Bath  in  v7ash*heust&apos;,&apos;  H  D.4; Square plan. 4 bedrooms, front entrance.  *  j\5.- G Roo&quot;i. cite enrra-noe. L plan.           - - &quot;  B.6. 6 Room, L plan, nont entrance.;&apos; &quot;  D..7, 6 Room, Rectangvla.1 plan with back  addition.  H  L.8. Squaie plan, 4 bedrooms. side entranoe. 1          All drawings show superficial areas of rooms, oubitalcontents cf the building and the suitable aspect.
f       iianuetl %t Small Holdings Equipment.  Part 1*          A manual of requirements atid instructions  for the guidance of,County Councils in the equipment of small holdings hasbeen prepared and a preliminary edition is being printed forimmediate circulation to the Councils,   This will include  the .14 type designs for Cottages enumerated above   A second part ofthe manual will deal with the Parmsteading and Outbuildings,  forirhieh type designs are how in preparation,     Fertilisers  The deliveries*6f Sulphate M Ammonia and BasisSla  continue to be heavy.   The duantity of Sulphate of Ammonia  sent from the Works in the ten months June 1918 4 liarch 1919 was 214,000&apos;tons as compared with 189,000 tottfc in the s4me period last  year,  whilethe deliveries of Basic Slag in ike same period wre 466,000 toneagainst 405,000 tons.           The arrangements for next season are now  being discussed.The Basic Slafc Makers have accepted tho Board1s proposals that thisfertiliser should ^e sold en similar terms to thosa  now ruling subjectto an advance of 2/- per ton.   Sulphate of Ammonia  presents greater difficulties as the effect of the withdrawal of the  subsidy at the  endof itay would be to raise&quot;the price to  20 per ton.   By allowingliberal export, however, it may be possible to arrange a.price1 up.to september next for sale to farmers of  17 per ton, leaving  the price for the remainder of the season to be settled later.   In the case  ofSuperphosphate the removal of the subsidy will probably make itnecessary to arrange district prices at an average level of  7, 10s,or  8 per ton*                      &apos;          The Orders limiting the sale of Potash and Blast  FurnaceFlue Dust except by licence are to be withdrawn as from, the end ofthiB month,     deeding Stuffs.  The withdrawal it the Maximum Prices  of FeedingStuffs Order will remove all restrictions on the oale of Compound  ,ftakos.   It is doubtful if it will be possible to substitutevoluntary action for this control and legislation will probably benecessary.   This question will be discussed with the Scottish and Irish Departments,     Liquid Kanure Tanks.  A pamphlet has been issued giving adviceas to methods of construction and offering the aesistanoe of theBoard1s expert.     Binder Twine.  All control has torn removed from the sale of hempand this may possibly lead to a further fall in Binier Twine prices.With a view to preventing unemployment in the Binder Twine  trade  theImport Restrictions Department are endeavouring to reduce theiicportation of American Binder Twine,     karketing.  Several I*&apos;ruit and Vegetable Societies have beenvisitccTaad an endeavour is being made to put them on a morebusinesslike footing.   A circular has been issued pointing out thatthe guarantee given by the Pood Production Department against lossmust not be used to cover losses arising from the sole ofagricultural requirements.
      1art&apos;,;Diseaoe, otf Potat.ees.   A Conference held en the 9th inst.., over which Dr * &quot;rEeet?le presided, resulted in a. very useful, disoyssion a,nd aoverai valuable suggestions were made1 for&apos; further research wnrk, in connection with the disease. -  Sir Arthur- Beccawon, &apos;1 .P.who attended in the afternoon, intimated that the Board wag prepared to&quot; make the necessary provision for research work and. steps are&apos; r being taken to fprmulate a scheme,                   .   &apos;       .      Seed Oats. .  The following ports have now been eleared:-  Leith, Boston, Liverpool, Bristol and &quot;Vest HartlepoOl.   &quot;Final shipments are being made from King1 s Lynn and Stockton;.                  &apos;    -  .     ; Testing of Seeds Order, 1916.   The.&apos; beneficial -results .ef the Order are very noticeable in-connection with the seeds sold by the smaller agricultural co-operative, societies&apos;.   The so -societies are,/ on the, whole, keenly desirous of improving&apos; their &apos;seed ..trade, but ao&quot; in- many cases the managers.1 knowledge of seeds is very limited they,.&apos;. have been hitherto entirely in the hands of the merchants from whf m they purchased,their bulks.   They now&apos; have a means of checking the quality of the seeds purchased and are giving detailed particular to their members.                    -                           &quot;                          Horticultural Division. puit -Section.          ; &apos;                           i    .   &apos;  -     Th. land at pwwnt 1, in a: poor state .* fertility&quot;, Wil $uch &amp;f it can he made, suitable for market garden crops including&apos; strawberries and raspberries, while the Aye sham Park. Station is well suited for.both market garden, and all kinds of fruit cultivation:  . - particularly &apos;of plums and apples.      pornv/all has decided to take steps to establish a demonstration. orchard irfeach of the Sducatienal Subdivisions of the county, &apos;   v &apos; The prospects  of fruit in the Tamar Valley are as follows:.-. Gooseberries and raspberries good, strawberries fair, top frui$ excellent.       -...           -                 * -*      &quot;       *&apos;           At Huntingdon the North Hunts  Fruit Growers&apos; Association have&apos;made proposals  to provide land fer  a demonstration fruit  plot, and arrangements have been made for a meeting between the Local f. Education Authority  and the Association  to discuss the matter.      Standardisation of fruit -packages.  - Enquiries are being  made regarding present dimensions  and  capacities  of  the various  types  of packages  in use.                                       ,      French, Sprayingj Machines-I   Enquiry shows  that there are  in  this country &quot;at&quot; The pre sent^time  large  stocks-of  knapsack machines, bbtjh of the Varoaor-el&apos;and  English  makes,  sufficient to meet all  probable demands  for  some  time, and  it has  therefore  been decided to inform the Department of  Import Restrictions:that the  Board does  not recommend the  granting at  the present  time of applications  ta import French machines.      Standardisation of  insecticides  and&apos;fungicides.   A meeting  has; beon arranged&quot; for.next week  between representatives  of  the, Technical, Cccaercial and Horticultural Divisions,  -&apos;:he  Government Chemists,  and the  Chamber  of Horticulture  w&apos;th a view to  standardising  these for the  spraying  of  fruit  trees  otc.,  the  object being  to  secure that -the  preparations  put on  the  market shall    effective.Sml\  Live  St*cft.       Foreign  Sggs.  The  question of  the marking  *f foreign eggs  imported  into this country  was considered by the poultry Advisory                                        6 .
Committee but the general opinion was that until the organisation of the poultry industry in this country is more advanced, it would be inadvisable to press for the marking of eggs.

Poultry Institute. The sub-committee of the Poultry Advisory Committee has submitted a scheme for the formation of a Poultry Institute, which the Advisory Committee have recommended for the Board&apos;s consideration.

A visit has been paid to St. Dunstan&apos;s to inspect the equipment and obtain information on the training given in poultry keeping. Sir Arthur Pearson explained that the training at St. Dunstan&apos;s was mainly theoretical, more practical instruction being given at the poultry farm belonging to the Institute at King&apos;s Langley, the inspection of which is being carried out. This will be reported on as soon as possible.

The breeding pens and large laying house which were formerly used are being removed to King&apos;s Langley as the results with live stock at St. Dunstan&apos;s have not apparently given satisfaction. The training consists of a six weeks&apos; course of lectures and demonstrations, a course of carpentry, a month&apos;s practical work at King&apos;s Langley and a final six weeks&apos; theory. Wives or relatives of the soldiers may also receive two months&apos; training on a poultry farm. These pupils are being trained by Miss Rawson, Meopham, Kent. It is understood that 130 men have been started in this way, and several instances were given of satisfactory development following.

Instructor and Advice.

Wales. An inspection of about 300 acres of small holdings at Bishopston on the Gower peninsula about 6 miles from Swansea has been carried out. The methods of cultivation are unscientific and out of an intensive nature; the growers are satisfied if they obtain the ordinary rotation, but it must be allowed that they appear to be prosperous, many being already freeholders. Land is at a prohibition price, a plot recently sold in the neighbourhood fetching £200 an acre.

Technical and Cultivation Division.

Technical Section. (1) Inspection of Land. A farm of about 100 acres in East Suffolk has been inspected in connection with an application by the Agricultural Executive Committee for authority to enter into possession. It is in very poor condition, ? acres, at one time arable, being now let with the remaining pasture for grazing (one field for mowing) at an average rent of about 30/- per acre. The proposal of the Executive Committee is to take possessions of the land, clear and improve it, and let it for grazing purposes, the estimated outlay being approximately £400. This course would add greatly to the value of the farm, but slagging would produce little effect till the summer of 1921, and if the Committee&apos;s tenure lasts only for two years after the declaration of peace it would be necessary for them to ensure that there was a reasonable prospect of being able to recover from the owner the value of the improvement.

(2) Dry Spraying for Charlack. In many districts such as the Yorkshire Wolds, the Downs, and other parts of England, difficulty is experienced in spraying charlock owing to shortage of water and to the fact that no satisfactory form of dry spraying has hitherto proved satisfactory generally. The matter was brought to the notice of the University of Leeds, who have agreed to test various forms of dry sprays in order to meet the needs of farmers in the Wolds and to obviate the necessity for carting water, and it is hoped to find some effective remedy in time for this season&apos;s operations.


Tractor Section// *:&apos;During  the week ended 8*th ult.  1,279. tractors .  -  which were in  eemmission in England  ploughed ever 6,100 acres and  cultivated 2,300 acres showing en; average at re age per  tractor of 4.7$  ploughed and 1,S0&apos; cultivated, respectively.   These  figures are  slightly better than those for. the&apos; preceding week, cultivating.  showing a considerable v.-increase *ver the preceding week.   Tfts;  highest acreage was done in Shropshire, where 20  tractors averaged  over 16 acres  of ploughing and.3&apos;.of.  cultivating.    The largest  amount of cultivating&apos; was done in East Anglia and the,Southern  Counties.   The majority of the Counties whore,the  now contract,  scheme is in operation are at the top. of the list ae regards acreage  per tractor.   Juat, over one^third. of the. tractors&apos;in  the Counties  were in commission, and  these were idle on account  of  adverse  weather conditions for almost half the: time ..&apos; &apos; - .            Inhales over  1,000 acres&apos;  were ploughed and  180 cultivates.  by 178 tractors, giving.an average of 6.04 acres  ploughed.and one&apos;.&apos; &apos;,  acre cultivated per tractor respectively&apos;.   The amount /of work dene  &apos;  was more than  double that of the preceding week,  and the; tractors.  were idle for  one quarter&apos; of the .time erf account  of the bad -weather  The largest amount of work was done  in Angleseyv   Carnarvon, working  on the new contract scheme, wao at the head of the  list with; an &apos;. .,  average of 11.17 acres of ploughing  per tractor.  -             .            The  proposals  of the Surrey, 2ast Suffolk and Ner^h Biding  Cwaaittees were approved during the  week.   The arrangements in 30&apos;&apos;  .&apos;.&apos;  counties havo  now been settled.   The number of tractors in these  counties to be retained  after Eay is approximately 1,200 out of ft-.,  total of 3,600:  the Ceim-lttees do not in all cases propose, to  retain the tractors until the &quot;end of September;   in Durham the  -,-  proposal is to dispose of the 31 remaining tractors after, the,e&apos;n$ * of June, tho idea being  that farmers should purchase - them for-the  :-  .  harvest.   In  all other  cases where  tractors are  being retained :the v  Committees consider that they&apos;, chouid themselves be responsible for  a oertain amount of tho  harvest work.- -              ;.leehanlcal section.   For  a considerable times past.the ,tectaHcal  experts have been visiting the counties inspecting Hnd^ra and&apos;  advising an to repairs required to put: them inord^r -for the1 cemjag  harvest.   In  some&apos; counties&apos; the-.looal of ficlals, appeared. t$ &quot;have V  very little knowledge of tho handling of *tno&apos;ee machines?&apos;            1th the liquidation of the Sracter &quot;SchOfcte. and. tfce  reduction in the number  of iooal officials, the Coraoitt^eo.are &apos;  making increased use of  the technical -experts, who are in a position  in many ways to replace  the tractor  Representative  without adding  itaterially to  their normal duties.                         - - -;Requirements and Disposal  Section..   During the week  ended the&apos;l&apos;2th-  April returns  of sales have been, received from Kent, Devwa,  Pembroke, Cambridge, Essex, Bucks, Gloucester,Montgomery / Lance,  Leicester, ITorthante, West Sussex, Vf&amp;at Riding ana Glamorgan.            The  following  have boon disposed of:-                       610 tractors                       745 tractor ploughs                       463 miscellaneous tractor implements                       417 binders                     2,101 horse ploughs                       415 drills                       603 carts, and lorries   .^                     1,569 harrows and cultivators/                       923 rollers and pressers.      ^  Ovor ,5176,754&apos;;  has beer, remitted as tho result of  tho  sales.
Up to date 219 sales have been held for which ? returns are to hand. Twenty-nine further sales have been arranged and negotiations are proceeding with Holland, Devon, Derby, Isle of Ely, Dorset and Herts as to fixing up auctions and auctioneers.

In addition, purchase of implements etc. have been made for the Land Drainage Section, and machinery and implements have been provided for the Land Division in connection with their farming schemes.

Horse Section. The total number of horses sold to date is 4,500 at an average price of over £62 per horse. It is satisfactory to report that 180 horses sent to Hertfordshire have realised within £3 of their original cost. Over 200 horses have been sold in the West Riding at an average of £95.

The sale of surplus harness in the various counties is proving entirely satisfactory, and arrangements have been made for the disposal of new harness in London, and other big centres.

The Department have offered 300 sets of harness to the Scottish Board as the collars were made in the North and are more likely to realise 3000 prices there than in England.

The Department are also in communication with the Irish Board with reference to the disposal of shop-soiled and second-hand harness.

Steam Tackle. During the past week 282 acres were ploughed, 625 acres were cultivated, 202 acres were harrowed and 76 acres ? grained.

Labour Division.

Training of ex-Service Men. Additional men have been sent to the Training Centre at Brentwood during the week, bringing the number of men at this Centre up to 94. The first batch of men will be available for issue at the end of the week and arrangements are being made to find them suitable employment.

A leaflet describing the scheme for training and ? placing men in employment has now been issued and will be circulated through the Employment Exchange. As a quarter of a million ex-Service men are unemployed, the scheme should be a means of recruitment of agricultural labour apart from the immediate object of providing opportunities for ex-Service men expressing a wish to take up an open-air life.

Demobilisation. The number of agriculturists demobilised during the seven days ended 9th April was 11,440 making the total number of such men released up to that date 197,035.

Soldier Labour. The number of men remaining in the Agricultural Companies at the end of the week was 23,766, a total of 4?, 285 having been demobilised since January last. The Army Council Instruction recalling these men to military duty was issued on the 11th inst., so that the majority will be lost by the end of the month.

Civilian Labour. A Conference has been held with the Ministry of Labour during the week. That Ministry is unable to find civilian substitutes to replace the skilled soldiers who are being withdrawn from the land, as the number of skilled agriculturists registered at Employment Exchanges in England and Wales as unemployed is negligible, and such men are quickly absorbed. A scheme for utilising on the land for unskilled seasonal work, men with no experience of agriculture, was discussed.

 
?. Assistance with the formation of School Boy Camps for harvest work is being given to Schools who desire to visit again the districts in which they have worked previously, and who apply for the Board&apos;s help with the camp arrangements and for railway facilities.

Women&apos;s Branch.

The position of women labour this week is difficult. The farmers are not yet willing to state the number of women they will require; averse as they always are to do so, their disinclination is strengthened at the present time because of the unsettled state of labour and the recent rise in the scale of agricultural wages. A larger number of women are appearing before the Selection Boards than can, at the moment, be absorbed, though it is equally true that the supply of ? and horsewomen is still well below the demand. It is to be hoped that the farmers will take stock of their available ? labour in the immediate future and make known their demands for women labour, in order that the women may be ready when they are required.

The housing question is presenting many difficulties. During the War, women were often bill?tted with the wives of men serving with the forces; the men having now returned, such accomodation is closed in many areas. Farmers must now realise that if they wish for large numbers of imported women, they must as in the fruit and hop districts provide special accommodation. Thus, in the Holland Division of Lincoln where a request for 400 women&apos;s on July 1st has been made, farmers haven been told that they must be responsible for finding accommodation.

A final test of Land Army girls has recently been carried out at the University Farm, Reading. A very high standard of efficiency was shown.

?, tractor work, the women continue to show great skill. One woman who has done a year&apos;s satisfactory work has been offered the permanent post of tractor demonstrator to Messs. George Heath and Company, the firm for which she has been working. All the ten women who have been trained in tractor work in Somerset are now in employment with different farmers. The value of their work is proved by the fact that application has been made for a further number to be sent for training immediately.

Women&apos;s Institutes. A successful Women&apos;s Institute School was held during the week at Wye College. 36 women were in resid? at the College during the course, and others attended from neighbouring Institutes. Six working women attended, those travelling and maintenance expenses were paid by the Board. The majority of those present at this School paid their own expenses, thus showing the interest taken in the movement.

14 new Institutes were started during the week, making a total of 997.


PART. IIiLr. PTE DEF/IRTI^KTS.  Animals Division.           The number ef outbreaks cf Swine ^ejve  confirmed was 26 and the reports of suspected cases 1&apos;25.  &quot; Tvo&quot;&quot;outbreaks of Anttoax have been confirmed and S3 reports received.    There have been 5&quot;&quot;aa&quot;sOs of Sheop-Scab reported and one case of Glandora.           There have been 13 reports of  suspected eases of Rabies and 7 more outbreaks have been confirmed,  namely .5 in Glamorgan^&quot;&quot; one in Konmouth and one in Surrey,   Tho last cane occurred in a dog owned at baling that was killed near Byfleet.   In connection with this case an Ord^r is beir^ prepared prohibiting movement out of an area comprising tho counties of London,  Middlesex, Surrey (with the exception of a small part) and parts of  the counties cf Herts, Bucks, Berks and Hants.                                          1 .                           Rats Order, 1918.            The Orders of the Ministry, of Food and the Local Government Board amending the above Order&apos;have at last been issued. The amendments enable County Councils to delegate their powers to Agricultural Executive Committees, make  the Port Sanitary Authorities and the. City of London separate Local Authorities and allsw, subject to the sanction of the County Councils, the.exercise of powers under the Order by the Councils cf any district or Borough within the Administrative County.-  A circular letter explanatory cf the effect of these&apos;Ordors and exhorting these who have up to&apos; the present hung fire, to bestir themselves and take action, has been issued by the Board to all the local Authorities concerned.            The formation of a National Committee on Rat Destruction was announced yesterday in the Press.   This Committeepromoted by Lieutenant A. 7,, Moore, whose activities in the field of vermin destruction are well-known to the Department, has been formed in crd&apos;&apos;&apos;r tc bring about the effective repression of rats and it  is paid that it3 ohief object will, be to render to the Beard the closest possible co-operation, and tc take steps tc  secure the enactment cf a permanent measure.  &apos; The following gentlemen have agreed to. serve on this National Committee:-                            Lord Aberoonway,        Prof.W.V.R,Simpson,                           , Sir Anderson Critchett, Sir Hi Jardine, and                            ,CC1. A. Weigall, M.P.  . Major Harding Ccx.                          Ve t e r i na ry Depart me nt,.      Swine  ever material was examined in 40 reported tutbreaks.   In  29 swine; fever was  found to exist.      Mti?!^ material was examined in 13 reported outbreaks.   In 7  if&apos;these disease was found to exist.      Anti*-swine-feverr serum.   60 c.c. were  issued for distribution.      Ant:-abortion  vaccine .   27,900 e.c.  (558 doses), have been manu-^taiHttrod, put up &quot;in a suitable farm, and despatched for use cn&apos; Infected farms.      Ui 3oellaneoua  aioeciment.    Post mortem examinations were made  on !f specimens.       RabieB.   During the week in question  specimens have been   feeeived from 11 suspected   outbreaks.                                    11. &apos;
0          A auspicious dog which had run from Baling was  killed  just outside the Laboratory on 14th inst. owing to its offensive  manners. The head etc. were examined immediately and rabies was  found to  exist. This case implicates at least Middlesex and Surrey.                           Fisheries Division.                          Administrative Section.      Export, of Herrings.   A Deputation from the  British Herring - Export rs Association was received.   They urg*d  thrtpoints:-           (l)  The Germane to be excluded from British  fish  markets.           (S)  The. prohibition of Aliens from operating oh fish  markets,                   except through British Companies.           (3)  That they might be informed as soon as possible tjhether                   they will be frue to export fresh herrings to  Germany,                   and elsewhere in the coming season.  ,           They were asked to send, in an official  letter explaining their case..   it was promised that in the meantime -unofficial enquiries would be made of the Foreign Office, the Ministry of Fcod, and the Timber Department (with regard te wood for fish boxes).&apos;      Deposit ofiExplosives in the Sea.   The Military Authorities &apos;I desire to dispose of very .large quantitjtes of explosive  material. -  The percentage of ammonium nitrate in some of this material is as much  as $0%, and enquiry is being made as to the possibility of its  use  as  a fertiliser.   It was considered desirable that an experimental deposit Of explosives should be made in a suitable area of the  Thames in order to ascertain to what extent water might be affected by  the deposit,&apos; and with this object a Conference was held between representatives  ofj,&apos;this Department, the Ministry of Munitions, port of London Authority,. and the London County Council.   The River Authorities&apos;were  not  at first inclined tc agree, tc the experiment, but their main objections were explained away.   As, however, some of the representatives  of  the  . Hiver Authorities suggested means by which the Munitions Department could obtain suitable barges and lighters, new in Government hands, perfectly seaworthy and suitable for long journeys at  oea, the Meeting was adjourned until the 28th inst., in order (l)  that  the Ministry  of Hunitions could make some further enquiry as to whether .the  explosives could not be taken out to deeper water, and  (.2) to enable the Chemists of the River Authorities to make seme further laboratory experiments.      Tarry taete in fish.   Complaints have been received as to  the r&apos; currence of a strong taste of tar, carbolic acid,  etc, etc.,  in fish, and the Beard are making some; enquiry in the matter.      International Fishery Research.   Twc officers  cf the Prench Central fisheries Department called tc inspect some  of the Government stock of frozen fish in London with a view^  if found  ..suitable,  to arranging for the export of supplies te Prance.   They also  proposed that the work of the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea should be continued and extended to Korth Atlantic  and Newfoundland waters and even tc Morocco.   ittanco is even disposed to join the Council but  feels difficulty about co-operation witfe Germany.   They I suggested that the Headquarters of the Council should be transferred from Copenhagen to Brussels, apparently feeling that  the Danes were I too subject  to German influence,      Looe Harbour.   A Public Inquiry has been held into the Qu* stions affecting Looe Harbour and the Report of the Inspector thereon is new under consideration.
!          ffishcrnen1 a Registrat ion tand^ Recruiting. Section.;L I^mobift1s---tt;i..jn of ffish..n^ Ve3se 13.    Some  850 steam fishingjpreis&quot; in all1, have how he en reported as demobilised at  ports inpi and and -Tales, distributed as follows,  approximate ly; -                               -  - Trawlers.     rift^re.                 Ulast Coast  ....   410           294                 Couth   &apos;1   ....     2             2                 7est    &apos;*   ....   133   *          4                                     550           300   , Employment *   Enquiry has shown that generally there is very It tie unemployment among fishermen, only one or two ports and only jrtain ratings bo.\ng ever -name d,  - There is, on the other hand, a. jBtinct-shortage of hands elsewhere , and this shortage is net unlikely  be. more marked in the near future.                        1 nto 1 lifT.c.ncp g&amp;vision.            Education Branch.         Tho approval of the Treasury has been obtained to an . Iponditurc cn Agricultural Education and ftesoareh during tho ensuing pve years of 52,000.000.         In connection with the coming reconstruction of agricultural &quot;fucation throughout the country proposals art; now being received,  th from agricultural colleges and from county education authorities,  r providing increased facilities of instruction by means of enlarged  1 id higb^r-Ph-LarSed staffs, and ether methods.   The proposals made in Is&apos;&quot;regard ly the Leicester County Education Committee were put   ;arc&quot;. and examined at a conference held on Friday, 11th inst.   It is satisfactory to find that the Authority fully recognised the  need  3? a progressive policy.         The Counties which have adopted the Beard&apos;s scheme for the istribution of sittings of eggs to small holders have consented to ie prolongation cf tho scheme until 15th Hay, in vie?/ of the lateness f the season generally.       .  The Regulations for Grants in Aid of Agricultural Education Jd-Research have been revised, and are ready for issue in their revised irm.   The most important alterations relate to grants to Local Jthoritieo whose expenditure will now be divided into two classes only:-          (l) salaries and expenses of organisers, which will earn a                , grant of four-fifths, and-          (2) all other approved expenditure, which will earn a grant                 cf two-thirds,           .                        ?r &quot;hiuky lioney&quot; will no longer ^e taken into account;  the Board&apos;s grants  Ilill be a definite proportion of the approved expenditure without - nduction on^this ?.account.         The award of Research Exhibitions has been continued.  iders of unaxpired scholarships are being pressed to continue their sholar ships.         A considerable amount of correspondence continues tc be  reived (a) from parents anxious to obtain an agricultural training or their sons and (b) from applicants ;-for posts as lecturers and tachore in agricultural   &quot;--.subjects.                                13.
     Encouragement of.Oheseemaklng Schoneu  The starting ofnpcrat ions Tor the &apos; 1919&quot; &quot;BO as on has been greatly delayed by&apos;ty*  .winter price of milk being maintained until the end tf April.          Representation?) hare been received from County Education.Authorities to the effect that pending an announcement regarding theprioe for cheese as compared with the price for milk, they werofinding great difficulty in organising classes.   Similarrepresentations have been made,by farmers namely that they do not propose to make cheese unless they can see that by so doing they will obtain a monetary return equal to that whioh can be obtained byselling milk.          Up to the present 16 Counties have started schools thisseason and many more hope to start in May.   A full report of thetrork done during 1918 has been prepared and hae been submitted thisweek.                             t..     Arable Dairy Farming Demonstrations,   With a view to arranging the location of these demonstrations&apos;, visits &quot;of inspection were paidlast week to Yorkshire, and Staffordshire (two centres) and similarinspections are taking place in Dorsetshire and Cornwall.                  Publications Branch.          The number of applications for  ordinary issues ef the leaflets was 405 in response te which 1,770 copies wore despatched.           In addition, 19,470 copies of the leaflets were despatchedte applicants for  supplies in bulk for distribution.          Applications were received for  410 eopieo  sf the,threeBound Volumes of Leaflets, and 173 oepiee of the pamphlet  &quot;How tfiianage an Allotment&quot; were cent out *          The April issue&apos; of the Board1 f  Journal was cent t.* Prosetogether with &quot;Small Holders1 Guide11 No.  IS  (Market  Garden Crops en .Small Holdings).          The usual number of enquiries bearing on Agriculturalmatters was dealt  with by the Branch, together with  correspondencein eenneetion with the &quot;Corn Exchange Stands&quot; taken  ever from theJoint Committee.           No. 37 of the &quot;Weekly Notes&quot; was published on Thursday,April 10th.                 Officers, Training, Branoh,     greo Government Scholarshipe.T otal applications  ions recorded by Board ...................\.. 440                       During week   87                       Previously   663  Dealt with by Departmental Committee  ..**....*....*...... 565      Awarded Scholarships ...............   0      To bo recommended for Scholarships,.   7      Placed on Reserve Lists:-                    Second List ..........   ft                    Third List ...........  17      Refused.........................\ $76      Outstanding for references,)                 interviews, etc.).......  64      Not yet dealt with by Pepaiiimantal. Committee ............ 275*N. t  A lumber cf these oases will, it is expected, be dealt with     during the ensuing week.                              14.
          The announcement in the House of Commons on the 10th inst,that it was proposed to increase the number of Scholarships from 50 to100 has already brought forward requests from one or two unsuccessfulcandidates for their applications to be reconsidered by the DepartmentalCommittee, on tho ground that more Scholarships are now available,     Residential Farm Training.                            Demobilised        Non-Demobilised                              Officers.           &quot;officers.  &quot;* ur2-M -Previously         Previously  week  --u   week.--TotalJferred to 54 County Councils    127       429       81       395      1,032feted training in 24 Counties    29     .63        -        -          P2Jliminary arrangements made      19        79       18        61        177[used                            IS        19       10        19         60thdrawn                           P        13        3         9         36fstanding for interviews etc.       314                366             670       *Pigures are as regards information received        by the Board- during the week.            In order to avoid delay as far as possible in the interviewing  of candidates by County Committees, it has been agreed with the Ministry  of Labour that Committeoo shall arrange interviows direct with candidates  instead of, as has previously beor  ;ho practice, through the local  office of, the Ministry of Labour.            The Head of the Branch attended      j. meeting of one of the  Counties in which applications had not previously been promptly dealt  with.            One or two Counties were unable to arrange for payment of  maintenance allowances due *n the 1st April to Officers who had started  training.   The Board are therefore paying these Officers direct,  pending definite arrangements being made by the Counties tc make such  payments for the future.                        fflax Production Branch.            The output of seed during the week ending the 10th April was  3,946 ewts.  (last week 3,981 cwts).   About 1,930 tons of seed have boon  forwarded to Belfast.   No more seed will be despatched.   Contracts  have been completed fqr about 13,600 acres flax, for 1919.            A Branch Committee has been appointed for the purpose of  considering and reporting on the possibility of deseeding flax on tho  growers premises by the aid of the  new deseeding attachment for thresher,  which has given promising results  en other portable maohinery.                          Live Stook Branoh.                                                During week  Total since  Live Stock Grants.                       ended 12 April.   1,April 1919.       No. of  Grants approved for Boars             2             7          do.            do.      Bulls            15            30          do.            do.      Heavy Horses     26            77          do.            do.   Milk  Reoording       1             2                                                             Total sinoe  Milk Recording Certificates.                               1 Oct. 1918.       No, of  Certificates  issued                 337         3,839          do.  Cows accepted for Registration      214           415                                                             Total since  Horse Breeding.                                            I Nav.1918.       No. of  Stallions acoepted for^Registration  6*         2,198  Expert of Stock.                                   During above week       9 Applications for the Export  of  36 Horses were  approved.       4     do.               do.      286 Cattle       do.       2     do.               do.      836 Pigc         do.       C     do.               do.      131 Poultry      do.      , 1 Application for the Kxport  of 200  Sheep waa approved,
The number of Army mares submitted to the Board&apos;s Inspectors has been only about 1500 up to the present, and of these only 140 have been selected as suitable. As we have received applications for approximately 5,000 mares we have circularised applicants explaining the position, but the refusal of application will probably cause dissatisfaction in many cases. The War Office estimate of 12,000 suitable mares being available was unduly optimistic.

Economic Division.

Statistical Branch. Application has been made to the Treasury for authority to carry out the scheme for collecting, verifying and paying farmers&apos; claims under the Government guarantee of corn prices.

The returns of fish landed show a further increase in quantity during March, the average value per ?. being about the same as last month.

Markets Branch. Certificates have been issued for the export of 3 horses to France; and of 22 cattle to Argentina. 14 Certificates for export of forage to Jersey were also issued.

A full Report on the proceedings of the recent session of the Inter-Allied Agricultural Conference in Paris, has been prepared.

At the request of the French Minister of Agriculture, enquiries are being made relating Agricultural Shows in this country, for guidance in connection with the proposed creation of a permanent official building for shows in France.

Farm Workers&apos; Branch. A dispute has arisen between the employers of agricultural labour and the workers in March, Cambridgeshire. Both sides have agreed to refer the matter to an arbi? to be appointed by the President of the Board of Agriculture, but up to the present they are unable to agree as to the day from which the award shall date.

A conference was held in the President&apos;s room on the 11th inst, between representatives of the National Agricultural Council and the Agricultural Wages Board, on the subject of Conciliation. After some discussion the matter was referred to a sub-committee to prepare a report for further consideration.

Agricultural Wages Board. Meetings of the Administration Committee, Committee on Probationary Workers, Allowances Committee and Committee on "Customary Hours" were held on the 9th, and a meeting of the Selection Committee on the 10th.

The thirty-first meeting of the Wages Board was held on Thursday the 10th April.

After considering protests which had been submitted by District Wages Committee against the procedure adopted  by the Board in issuing a proposal to vary mininum rates for adult male workers before consulting District Wages Committee, and also a request from the Berkshire District Wages Committee asking the Board to call a conference of all District Wages Committee to discuss questions of importance in agriculture on a national basis, the Board decided to conve? a conference of representatives of all District Wages Committee to discuss question relating to the work of the Board and of the District Committees.

The Board adopted a report from the Committee on "Selection" making recommendations with regard to the manner in which District 


 Wages Committees should be consulted on the subject of the filling&apos; ft vacancies emong representative raembcrc on the District Comraitt&amp;es,And decided to &apos;&apos;adopt the recommendation of the S* lection Committee ;;j to appoint per^one to fill the vpoancieo cn certain of the District committee.           Sir Henry Rev presented a report from tho Administration &quot;IOoumittoo dealing with (a) tha application of the Boards new[Overtime Order to Cumberland end Westmorland, (b) questions withfrcgard to tho scope of minimum r^tes;&apos;,  fc) proceedings taken for the enforcement of the &quot;Bo^rd&apos;v Orders and (d) ection taken on complaints&apos;!&apos;eo to non-payment of tha minimum rates.   It was decided to adopt a, unanimous recommendation .of the Cumberland :--nd Westmorland District(Wages Commutes, to modify th-r. Bo- rdTe new Overtime Order in its replication to Cumberland and Westmorland so as to provide that in!Jotfcee where the employ-:r and worker ngr*e to the worker having a.-week&apos;&apos;  holiday on full pay, or p wewk1e work on double pay in each half year, this i&apos;holl be substituted for tho weekly short day, Th&apos;* report of the Committee showed that up to the 5th April the sum of lot  1,575 had be*n paid to workers in arrears of wage** as a result1 of. action tak^n by the b of&quot;.rd&apos;s Inspector-te.           Sir Henry,Rew reported that a conference of representatives ;of employer&apos;ef and workers&apos; organisations had been held, fit the jfifages Board for the purpose of inviting the co-operation of these [organisations in the work of enforcing the Board&apos;e Orders, and that a general agreement had be n r ached with the organisations on both [flideo tc use thsir. best offices in considering eases of dispute [between employers and workers with a view to obviating the necessity Ut the complaints hsving to be deelt with and investigated by the teges Bor*rd.           The Bo; rd appointed committuoe to consider and report upon tho questions (-&quot;;) of the revision of tho minimum rates at present in operation for boys and for female workers, (b) of special-Irates for harvest work, r*nd have at the came time invited the  ibservatione of the various District Wages Committees on the subjects.           During the week 15C cases of oomplaint of non-payment of  the minimum rates were received, the-largest numbsv from a single  county being 23 in the case cf Yorkshire,   Twenty-nine cseee were pent to Inspectors for visit;  enquiries by correspondence were  ift.de in 221 cases and 31 cases wave completed.   Reports were  received from Inspeotort in 43 or-sao. I             Tithe,&apos; w^-ii-a^jy., Copyhold and Survey Branch.           At the recuest of the Anglesey,County Council the Board  isve supplied them with particulars of. the tithe rent charge  ihnrged on lands required or to be acquired by the Council for  fcnll holdings under the Smallholdings and Allotments Act, 1908,  &apos;6 thnt it can be /redeemed.   Th  total area of the titheable lands   iready acquired by the Anglesey County Council is 2,624 pores which  *e charged with tithe rentcharge amounting to  249.   The lands l*e situate in 13 different Parishes,  and before redemption can 1* effected Alter?d Apportionments will be necessary in 11 of these Irishes.           Ihe Bofrd&apos;e report on the City end South London Railway Jill, 1919, has been drafted.   By Section 12 of this Bill powers  jN sought by the City and South London Railway Company to enclose  rapoTarily, for constructional works, 206 square yards of  Ilapham Common in the Metropolitan Borough of Wand3worth, 40  Rue re yards of which it is proposed to acquire permanently for  isubway leading to the Company1s Underground Railway Station..
            t*dnancea Surrey.Maps were despatched as follows:-      tfat Office        7,610      Air MinistTry        107      Admiralty        18,294      Other Services      732.            and Reolffla^pn.                                                          J       K      Washt  KerIfcWg*t  Shore.     Ke decision has yet been f0&amp;.$.ed en the vueatien whether  tlTelend at Preisten which is at present occupied by the Air ministry fcr flying purposes shall be included in the area fcr reclamation or not.   The Parliamentary Secretary is in cemmunieation with General Seely/ cn the subject.           A draft notice-under Regulation %U ef D.O.R.A. tev entry cn the Northern half  of tho  stretch  of fere she re between Oibrcitcr Eeint and the Witham,  for the purpose ef the prcpesed works, has.bea* ribaitted fcr the approval ef the Beard, subject to the, ccheurrence cf the two ether Departments concerned (Beard cf Trade and Duthy of Lancaster).                                 *           Further hutments and plant have been delivered during the week.           Longitudinal levels are being taken as a basis fcr the settlement cf the position cf the prcpesed embankments.      ^fTth (pardi^anshire).    the amended  schedule of Owners it Being examined in the  Branch,           As the result cf an interview with the Secretary cf the Cumbrian Railway, the  Company are about to submit a draft agreement as to the utilisation ef the railway embankment as a sea wnH fc* the protection cf the proposed reolaimable area..                   *      Qrimsc^e (Warwick),   has Branch ie  in tcmmunleatlcn with the ewner ef the area proposed for reelsmatiehV with a view to purchase,       Aaskwell Hill (Somerset).  Ihe Agent etatea that Xord Bath is willing to sell the proposed area en condition the Beard purchase an additional 10 ^ores.   A price ef .216 per acre is suggested by the agent.      Lfsbume  state  (Cardiganshire.. Ihe  joint survey ef this area in conjunction with the Interim Forestry Authority is proceeding.                                           Secretary.                                                         fICth April,  1S19.

</content>
</cab>
