<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/78/0 images: 132-134</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 I HIS DOCUI-MiM &apos;  ,      I.77::- - &quot;   &apos;. :   Kr. (jertv ofF       ^V/Y^H^cmT &quot;HELAilHG TO THE 1V0RI 01* THEIt * T.  **          OP AGRICULTURE! ?0R SOOTED-forr ?l  f ^]3/ ) %s WEBiC e21*ing *6til APRIL, 1919.&quot;TTpROWCTION.1. Milk Supply.      The Board hare issued a circular letter to PistrictAgricultural Executive Committees intimating that, in viewof the altered situation as regards cereal production, theydo not urge that golf courses, public parks and other re::creation grounds in their area should be cultivated thisyear:  They have suggested to&apos;the Committees, however, thatthey should ascertain whether, for the purpose of maintain::i?u$ the milk supply of the district, such ground&apos;should be utilised for&apos;the purpose of grazing milk cows, or youngdairy stock, and, if so, that they should approach the clubor other body and endeavour to effect an arrangement withthem.   The Cor/anittees have also been requested to reportto the Board,without delay, the whole circumstances of anycase in which it ts not found possible to arrive at an amicable arrangement.     A circular letter has also been addressed to the secretaries of Golf Clubs throughout&apos; the country, informing them of the&quot;Board1s proposal in regard to Golf Courses, and asking them, in view&quot;of the neceseityfer&apos; maintaining, and ifpossible increasing,the milk supply of the country, to ac:rquiesce in any arrangement proposed by a Biotriot Axricultur::al Executive Cofflraittee for the grazing.of their courses forthis purposeLABOUR.agricultural Companies.     The Army Council have issued an Instruction, Ho. 251 of11th instant recalling men in Agricultural Companies on a fortnight&apos;e notice.     The intention is to disband these Oouranies - meneligible for demobilisation under Army Order ZIV. being released and those not eligible being recalled to their units for service in the Armies of Occupation.     The Soottiah Office, on the Board18 appeal, made re:^presentations that.this Instruction should be cancelledor the recall of the men postponed until  6th May.&apos;   Thsserepresentations were^ however, unsuccessful;  but furtherappeals have been made by the Board for a postponement ofthe operation of the Order.     The effect of the withdrawal from farms of&quot;men in agricultural Units will, in the Board1s opinion, seriously affect Spring cultivation, and Parmere and District Agricultur::al Executive Committees are protesting vigorously against theimmediate promulgation of the Order.&apos;     The Board are concerned about such of the men affectedby the Order who are on the Pivotal Lists, but who are noteligible for demobilisation under Army Order 217.   L statementgiving particulars of these men is being prepared for eubmis::eion to the !?ar Office, with the request that the men shouldbe/
&quot;be released prior to the expiry of the fortnights notice,  10BILISATI0H of AGRICUIrUEAii WOBEBES.The figures to date are as follows:-                         J!o. of Men    lo. of Men                         applied.ior.    relei-sed.,Aberdeen.............Argyll................Ayr    ...............Banff................BerwickBute.................Caithness........Clackmannan    ....... * * *Dumbarton............Dumfries.............Elgin    ................Fife   ..................Forfar    ...............Ha&amp;dington......-.........Inverness    ..........Kincardine &apos;  ............Kinross    ........ *... a.Kirkcudbright    ........Lanark...............Linlithgow   ............Midlothian   ............Hairn.................Orkney................Peebles...............Perth.................Renfrew   . -,.............Ross..  ..................Roxburgh..............Selkirk   ..........Shetland   .....*........Stirling...............Sutherland.............Wigtown   ......-......1445 413 464 312 265 107 237  35  67 484 270 420&apos; 533 266 536 292  46 221 576 111 327  57 423  94 571 216 342 346  56 287 161 136 275781..22228721.2181 73150 18 43284168241302164303178 30157334 65186 42209 54315114179235 35137 99 80155103916033III.  WAGB3 ?0R ASRIOULgUBAL WORKERS.          &apos; &apos;&quot; The following minimum rates:of wages fixed by tie     District Wages Committee for the areas indicate! have now     come into forceNorthern /
3.108Horthem Counties (lo. I.[  1. Caithness.                                          Bar,week.Male workers &quot;between 18 and 21 yearsof age other than those experienced&apos;workers aftermentioned...........28/-Male workers, including ploughmen,shepherds in charge of a hirsel ofsheep, cattlemen, barnmen and orramenbetween 18 and 21 having net less than3 years experience as such..........        32/-Male workers over 21 years other thanthose experienced workers aftermentioned     30/-Male workers including ploughmen,shep-:herds, in charge of a hirsel of sheep,cattlemen, barnmen and orramen of 21years and over, having not less than3 years1 experience as such.                 36/-IQ1&apos;]5.-   In the case of shepherds and cattlemen, the above*         rates to &quot;be increased by 2/6 per week for first         dog, and 2/- for each additional dog necessarily         kept.          V/J-OJ.J.U..                           &quot;Pp r w^elcKale workers over 21 years of age ...       37/-                                         with an addition                                         of 2/6 per week                                         for each dog which                                         the woikman is re-                                         quired by the con-                                         ditions of his                                         employment, to keep.   3. Orkney.Male workers between 18 and 21 years ofage..................................Per week.     .......................&apos;.......       27/-Male workers over 21 years of age  ....       31/-

</content>
</cab>
