<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/78/0 images: 138-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;Dotument is the  Property of His Britannic Majesl^Jovermm.nOCONFIDENTIAL                      POLITICAL  INTELLIGENCE DEPARTMENT,       .         -                               FOREIGN OFFICE.  April 4th, 1919.                                                        SWITZERLAND /004.MEMORANDUM  HALLON&quot;^^&amp;TROBLEMS  OF  TRANS-ALPINE  RAILWAY TRANSPORT, WITK                SPECIAL  REFERENCE  TO SWITZERLAND.       The  following Memorandum  deals  with various problems  of  trans-Alpine  Railway Transport, particularly with the lines which  pass through Switzerland:        1. There  are numerous problems, political and economic, which are raised in  connection with the  group of trans-Alpine  railways.   Of the lines  already in  existence  the  principal are the Mont  Cenis, the St.  Gotthard,  the Simplon,  the  Brenner, the Lotschberg and the Arlberg.   The projected lines are very numerous.  Almost every  pass in the Eastern Alps, for example, has  had its advocates during  the past thirty or forty years, but the chief plans which have come under discussion  are those which have reference to the Spliigen, the Greina,  the so-called &quot; Adriatic &apos;&apos;  line, the Mont Blanc and the Little St. Bernard.       2. There  are several reasons why the Powers, Great Britain not  least among  them,  though  not directly interested to any considerable  extent,  should turn their  attention  to the trans-Alpine railway system.   All of them have, in the first place,  urgent commercial  and economic interests  to  serve by developing and extending,  where necessary, the  means of transit among  themselves.  The  war,  for  example,  has  brought France and Italy very  close politically;  the rapprochement must be  made  enduring  by  an increased economic  exchange.   Then the political  changes  which have come about, the setting up of new sovereign  states able to develop an  independent economic policy, the  re-drawihg of boundaries these must have a  very  perceptible influence  on the  development of mid-European,  particularly of  trans-Alpine railway traffic.   At a moment, too, when international control seems  likely to  be extended, it  is  particularly  opportune  to  bring  under  review  the  question of these railways which are,  we may say, almost as much international  necessities as the great rivers the Rhine, the  Danube, the Vistula. Is it possible  usefully to apply any analogies here?  One thing is certain, the great increase in  the development of European water  transit, which is bound to take place in  the  years immediately following the conclusion of peace, is intimately connected with  the problems of  railway transport.   The projected improvements  in the Rhine,  for  example,^  will make possible  a very  much larger  British share in  trans-Alpine  traffic it may be possible in a fairly short time for goods to be transported, partly  by water,  partly by land, all the way from London to the Adriatic, via  Rotterdam,  tne Rhine, Basie, Lucerne, the Lake Maggiore, the Po.       3. Finally/there  is the very  important  bearing  these problems  of  railway  transport  must  have  on politics.  League  of  Nations or no League  of  Nations,  international control or no international control, nothing so far as we can see, until  nationalism becomes  extinct,  will  be  able utterly to  prevent international  railways, carriers of national trade, from assisting in the commercial rapprochement  of one country to another, from being a weapon of policy.   French economists, as  will be seen, have complained that Germany used the St. Gotthard as a potent means  to the economic subjugation of Italy.   The Swiss are rebutting this charge  and are  pointing out that  the Convention concerning the St. Gotthard  which Germany  forced on them  put  them into a very undesirable position  of economic servitude.  This is the kind  of political problem with which the trans-Alpine railways confront  us, the kind with which an eventual League of Nations court may at any time be  called  upon to deal. j     4. So far as the  economic enslavement of Switzerland  by means of one-sidedI railway agreement  is  concerned Great Britain&apos;s tradition and  policy are clear.  The  absolute maintenance of Swiss  independence political and economic, has always                         * See Foreign Office Memorandum P.C. 030.      [11301-492                                                        B
                                       * been  an integral part of this country&apos;s  diplomatic heritage.   The  unsatisfactory attitude of a great part  of the Swiss press must not be allowed to obscure the fact to-day.  It is emphatically against Great Britain&apos;s interests,  as it is in evident contradiction to the policy that she has held fast since the days of the  Congress of Vienna, that Switzerland should be drawn exclusively into the economic orbit of any one Power, or  be made to serve  the  commercial  ends of any one country or group of countries.   The trans-Alpine railways of Switzerland  arc thus  at once a potential  economic menace  and,a source of prosperity.  She was, nevertheless, very backward in developing  them.  The reason for this apparent indifference to a vital subject when most other countries were bending their  energies to exploring it, may possibly be found in the peculiar basis of Swiss Government, the cantonal system.  Cantonal  sovereignty, so essential  a  part of  the  Swiss  constitutional development,, was long jealously guarded and restricted by the Federal  Government in the matter of railway building.   A clause in the Federal  Constitution,  indeed, expressly&apos; conceded  to  the individual cantons the right  to  take what  action they felt desirable in regard  to the development of means of communication.  So long as this was  the  case, so  long  as there  was  no central  authority invested with the power of deciding on the railway policy of the country as a whole, so long did the jealousy and competition between the separate cantons act as a check on tendencies to which other  countries,  with  more strongly  centralised governments, rapidly yielded as their progressing industrial and economic demands made themselves felt. It thus came about  that  three  great trans-Alpine railways  were constructed before the  Swiss roused themselves thoroughly to  the task of having  one made through their own territory.  These were the Vienna-Trieste line, through the  Semmering, which was opened in 1854; the Innsbruck-Brenner  Verona railway, which began running in 1867; and the Mont Cenis railway, which was opened to traffic in 1871.     5.  With the  transfer  of Trieste to Italy the trade of the port  will, no doubt, take on an orientation more westerly than Vienna,  and the project of the Adriatic line with Trieste as its termnius, of which more will be said later, will probably receive a  fresh impetus.   The principal problem connected with the Brenner is  the manner in which so important a  line of international traffic, the highway, let us recall,  of the Berlin-Naples express, shall be assured against interruption by insecure political conditions.   With  that  is  closely  connected  the question of  the attachment  of German-Austria,  including  North  Tyrol,  to  the  great  German  Republic, the intolerable strategic menace to Italy. Merely to name this, perhaps ultimately the most serious of all the territorial questions with which Europe is faced, is to indicate sufficiently clearly the bearings of the problem.     6. The Mont Cenis line connects France directly witSh Italy, Paris with Tunis. For  the  time when it was constructed  the  Mont Cenis tunnel was an astonishing engineering feat, accomplished in the face of tremendous technical difficulties and without the very efficient technical aids which were  discovered later. Just  before the work was undertaken, in 1868, a light railway was built over the pass side by side  with the road  constructed between  1803 and  1810.   This precursor of the international railway, it is interesting to recall, was run on the. Fell system and its management was in the hands of English engineers.  Until the completion  of the tunnel it carried the  Indian mail. With the opening of the tunnel to traffic, its work was  done and it dropped into desuetude.     7. The completion of the. Brenner  had acted as  a  spur to the Swiss, and the languishing project  for a St.  Gotthard railway was vigorously revived.  It was in 1851 that the  plan of  making a  railway through the St. Gotthard system was first  proposed, but beyond  the drawing up of vague projects nothing was  done.  The drawbacks, already mentioned of cantonal autonomy in the  matter of railway con- struction  were  one cause; another was  doubtless the vast cost of constructing the tunnel, which might have  well  given the Federal authorities pause even  if the first hindrance had not been effective.  In 1863 a St, Gotthard Union (Vereinigung) was founded to popularise  the project of  the  railway, but matters were  no further advanced until, five or six  years later, Italy and Germany began to show  an interestin the suggestion.  It was to the advantage of both countries to have,  in addition  tothe Brenner line, through  Austrian territory, and the Mont Cenis railway, throughFrench territory, a line passing through a  neutral state.   This point of view waswell  understood by Bismarck-a French writer  called  him &quot;  le veritable  instigateurdu St.  Gothard &quot;-and he expressed it in a speech in  1870 in which he said :-         The North  German  Confederation must be profoundly convinced that     political necessity demands the  construction of a new and rapid means of
     communication between us and Italy; we must have a line which is not subject     to other nations or at least subject only to a neutral country like Switzerland.     Before this plea in its favour, however, the cause of the St. Gotthard railwaywas practically won.  On September 15, 1869, there  had assembled at Berne under,the chairmanship of M. Welti, President of the Swiss Confederation for that year,a &quot; St. Gotthard Conference,&quot; at which the North-German Federation, Wurtemberg,Baden, Italy and Switzerland were represented.  As a result of their deliberationsa Convention, settling the details of financial support, was drawn up between Italyand Switzerland on October  15th.  It  was duly ratified by both countries andformally adhered by the New German Empire on October 28,1871.  In the followingDecember the St. Gotthard Railway Company was founded at Lucerne, in accordancewith the financial provisions  of the Convention, and in August of the following year the construction  of  the  great  St.  Gotthard tunnel was  commenced.   Thisstupendous feat demanded more money than had been estimated and made necessary a supplementary Convention, signed on March  12th, 1878, which had to be drawnup  in  order to  settle  the proportion  each State should contribute towards  theincreased cost.    8.  In 1904 the Swiss Federal  Council cantonal  autonomy  in  the  matter  ofrailway construction had of course been given up when the St. Gotthard scheme was first seriously discussed announced its intention  of  buying  the St.  Gotthardrailway system,  so  cancelling the arrangements  made  between the St. GotthardRailway Company  and Italy and  Germany respectively. *   These two  countries,however, demanded a new  Convention, and a long period of negotiations was enteredupon.  The transfer of the railway  to the Swiss Confederation was  completed  onMay 1st, 1909, and very  soon  afterwards  the terms of the new Convention were published.   They gave  rise in Switzerland  to an immediate chorus  of protest.  Bythem it was agreed that traffic on the St.  Gotthard railway was to be  carried  atthe same rates  as  on  any other of the  Swiss  Federal railways   (Article  7);Switzerland further  undertook to grant to the Italian and German railways  thesame facilities and  advantages as  might be granted  to  other railways outsideSwitzerland  (Article  8).   By Article 2 the Swiss  Federal  Government  pledgeditself not to raise the existing rates of transit for German and Italian goods passingover the  railway so long as the German and Italian railways  did not  raise their rates.    During the years 1909 to 1913 these provisions, being considered an invasion of Swiss sovereign rights as well as a serious disadvantage to Switzerland&apos;s financialand commercial prosperity, were the subject of bitter discussion.  Meetings to protest against them were held, petitions were presented to the Federal Council, and it wasnot until this body brought pressure to bear, and the German Minister had handed in a statement to the effect that the Convention, should it be found really prejudicial to Switzerland,  should be subject to international  arbitration,  that feeling wasallayed and the Convention ratified.    9.  This ratification took place on April 9th,  1913, and  although the railwaybrought great prosperity to those cantons within its sphere, Switzerland as a  whole has never reconciled herself to the  provisions according to which  it is  regulated.During the war, even at the times of German success,  Swiss protests have been heardand scarcely a voice has been raised to  defend  the Convention.  Switzerland, it is pointed out,&apos; has had to  bear the upkeep of  the railway for four  years and will notbe in a position according  to the terms of the Convention properly to recoup herself.This is a claim to which careful attention will need to be given.   The St. Gotthardrailway,  whatever may be the  political  changes  brought  about  at  the  PeaceConference, will remain the shortest and one of the most convenient means of transit,between North Europe and Italy, and it is not in the  interests of Europe as a whole to tolerate  its  exploitation by  any one country.   Certain French  publicists,  inparticular M. Ernest Lemonon, have recently pointed out that  the  St. Gotthardrailway wTas constructed in the interests of Germany and has been of immense  use to her.   This is no doubt true, but whether the proposal to institute what amountsto a bovcott of the  railway in favour of the Mont Cenis or  the Simplon is likelyto be either beneficial or practicable may be doubted.  The real interest of the Alliessurely lies  in developing trans-Alpine traffic as much as possible whether throughSwitzerland or not.  There is by no means an excess of lines.  The use of the railway                             * See Memorandum P.C  030.[1130]-492
  in the future as part of Germany&apos;s dumping  machinery can be prevented by the  provisions of the new Convention.      10.  It should also be borne in mind that the French themselves could find, and  indeed have found, benefit from having a railway line through neutral  territory.  Arguments similar to those which Bismarck used to advocate the building of the  St. Gotthard were employed by French statesmen, chief among them Jules Ferry,  ili urging the construction of a trans-Alpine railway,  which would have  the effect  of attracting Italy more  towards France.  But for  many  years the  results  of  Bismarck&apos;s diplomacy in setting the one country against the other were  a serious  hindrance.   The Simplon was,  oif course,  always  an  obvious  route  to  choose.  Between 1800 and 1807, as everyone knows, Napoleon  built a road over  the Pass,  and the  idea of boring  the Simplon Tunnel arose as early as 185,1.   In 1870 the.  French partisans of the scheme succeeded  in bringing  it before the  Chamber, but  it was; rejected.  And  then came the war.   After 1871 it was taken up again,  obtaining support from Gambetta in 1880 as it had received the help of Jules Ferry  in 1870.   But little progress was achieved.  The St. Gotthard was detracting not  only from the Mont Cenis traffic between 1800-1889 the tonnage through Modane  showed  a decrease of 56 per  cent; but also from that of the port of Marseilles,  which, in spite of the efforts of the Paris-Lyons-Mediterranee Railway, was steadily  losing its trade  to Genoa.   For both political and economic reasons, then,  not much  support  was to be expected from the Italian side, and it was not till November, 1895,  that Italy became a.party to the Simplon project.  Even then the Convention was  between  Italy and Switzerland  only.   France was still debating on the respective . merits of the Mont Blanc and the Little St. Bernard tunnels.   After  the  signature  of the Swiss-Italian Convention the work of the Simplon tunnel went  ahead.  Then  came the prolonged dispute as to where the connection  line  to the tunnel  should be  built.  The canton of Geneva -carried on an extensive agitation in favour of its own   that so-called Faucille project, but was apparently ready to grant only a small  subvention towards the cost.  Eventually the rival line, the Frasne-Vallorbe, costing  less and  benefiting a large number of cantons, was adopted, and the future arrange-  raents of the railway regulated the tunnel had been opened to traffic in  1908 bv  the Franco-Swiss  Convention  of June  1909.  The logical conclusion of the whole  scheme,  the construction of the  Lotschberg tunnel, by  which the Simplon line was  brought  into communication with Berne and Basle, was carried out in 1913.      11.  Although by the Simplon Paris was brought  within 850 kilometres from  Milan, which is  50  less than by the St.  Gotthard route and 99 less than by  the Mont  Cenis, the share of the railway in  transcontinental goods traffic has never  been  satisfactory.  It could,  however, be made  so.   A  few  technical improvements,  particularly on  the Lotschberg, the construction of  not more than 200 additional  kilometres of line, would bring Calais, Boulogne, and  Ostend out of the St.  Gotthard  orbit, and allow the principle of the shortest distance  to have its  natural effect  on  competition.  The  distance, for  example,  between  Milan  and Calais by the St.  Gotthard is  1,114 kilos., by the Lotschberg it is 1,072.  A few statistics will show  the size  of the market which is open to be captured.   In 1912 Italy imported from  Germany and Austria goods  to  the  value of  nearly 1,000,000,000  fr.,  and sold  550,000,000 fr. worth. In France she received goods  to the value of 289,000,000 fr.,  from England 577,000,000 fr. worth, and  from  Belgium  74,000,000.  Numerous  political  and economic causes after the war will  contribute  to transfer the balance  from Germany&apos;s, side to  that of the Allies, but this can only be effectively done  by  the various governments working hand in hand in the elaboration of  a progressive  railway  policy.      12.  On the Mont Cenis there is room for even greater developments than on the  Simplon  system.  There are technical  improvements  to the tunnel and the railway  track, changes to be made in the customs examination, which is more  expeditiously  carried through  on  the Simplon than on the Mont Cenis.  There is finally  the effort  the French  will need to make  to overcome the  disadvantage of distance from a  central point like Lausanne, under  which Marseilles  suffers as compared with  Genoa.   This raises at once the  question of the  great Rhone canalisation project,  and  is an excellent illustration of the  necessity for considering ways of communi- cation policy, what the Germans call &quot; Verkehrspolitik,&quot; as a whole.      13.  This memorandum has dealt with  the history of the St. Gotthard and the  Simplon  respectively, and the problems  which surround them, in some detail, because of their paramount position in international rail-traffic.  It is not possible to leave the subject of trans-Alpine railway without some reference  to the agitation in the
                                       5 East Swiss cantons for a railway which will serve their interests as the St. Gotthard serves those  of the centre and the Simplon those of the west.  There  have been  and are, for  the question is not yet settled several projects, each with its group of eloquent supporters.   A mere glance at the bibliography contained in such a, survey-of the matter as is  given  in  Dr. Hans Schmidlin&apos;s  :&apos; Die  Ostalpenbahnfrage &quot;* is sufficient  to show  how great a literary and controversial activity the discussion has  produced.                                          ,     In 1882 a Swiss engineer named Roller drew up a list of the  Swiss passes most suitable for the railway transit, placing them in order of merit.  His recommenda- tions are : St.  Gotthard,  Spliigen, Bernardino,  Lukmanier,  Albrunn-Grimsel, Simplon-Grimsel.   Of these the  St.   Gotthard and Simplon have  been carried through.  The rest of the list by no means exhausts the possibilities in the Eastern Alps.  There are, in fact, ten proposals for an East-Alpine railway:-         Spliigen.         Greina.         Bernardino.         Septimer (a variety of the Spliigen project).         Lugnezer (a variety of the Greina project).         Adriatic.         Ortler.         Maloja.         Todi (practically a branch of the Spliigen).         Segners (practically a branch of the Greina). This list is  given for the sake  of  historical completeness.   Practically it can be reduced to Greina, Spliigen and Adriatic, or, still further, when we consider that the  Greina,  like the Ortier, would debouch on the overloaded port of Genoa, to the Adriatic and Spliigen lines alone,     14. The Adriatic, with  ail  the  possibilities the redemption of the  subject Italian lands and the liberation of Jugo-Slavia offers  to Allied, commerce, is likely to play  a  very interesting  part  in future European policy.   The transcontinental line towards the Adriatic will probably not be sufficient for dealing adequately with the  great increase in the production of goods for quick transit  which is likely  to come about in the years  following the conclusion of peace.   It is likely, therefore, that the project of an Adriatic line through Switzerland, which the Swiss engineer- Gelpke elaborated in a brochure published in 1910,  will be revived.   If so, it will need to be very carefully considered in Allied countries.  In spite of what has been said, however, the Adriatic line is  less urgent, and  as, at  least  as  projected by Gelpke, it would involve   two long  tunnels before reaching Botzen  en route for Trente, Venice, or Trieste,  it is not very likely to secure priority of attention either- from the  Swiss  Federal authorities or  from the.  various  other  governments who would  otherwise interest themselves in the scheme.  From all points  of view the Splugen project is the more  &quot; actual,&quot;  the nearer adoption.     15. The question arises  first as to who, beside  Switzerland, particularly the canton of  Grisons, would benefit from the Spliigen, and secondly as to who would be prepared to share the cost?  France, it has been noted, is already well supplied for  the  purpose of getting her quick transit  goods through by the Mont Cenis and Simplon-Lotschberg.  Italy, for the purpose of quick transit, export   and  import, is in still  better case with the Brenner, the  Simplon-Lotschberg,  the  St. Gotthard and the Mont Cenis lines.  German-Austria, if she  could  have any  voice in the matter, would probably object to the East Alpine scheme as tending to compete with the  Brenner.  It is  clear that the  South  German  States,  perhaps  also  Alsace- Lorraine to  a certain extent where, of course, French interests re-enter have the greatest interests next to Switzerland herself.  The Splugen line, when completed, would provide the shortest route between the greater  part of South Germany and Milan.  If this is so, the Splugen projecfmay be said  to be on an equality with the St. Gotthard, and the Allied Powers will need to take note of the fact.  A second St. Gotthard Convention, with all its advantages to Germany, a second cheap, quick highway from Germany  into  Northern Italy, and  there would be  a danger  of allowing the peaceful penetration of Italy to begin all over again.   The remedy and the  safeguard to this lie not in hostility to  the project, but in a more just&apos;, more carefully drawn-up,  Convention.     16/For the West the economists and engineers have been scarcely less fertile in suggestions than for the  Centre and East.  When the  Simplon scheme was fighting                              * Orell  Fiissli, Zurich, 1915.
Gfor its life, French experts were considering the Mont Blanc and Little St. Bernardtunnels as possible alternatives.  Then, when the cause  of the  Simplon was won,they began to discuss them as alternative routes.  In 1874 a project for  a MontCenis  railway was actually submitted to the French Chamber, but was rejected.The principal objection was, and  is, on the ground of  oost, estimated by the opponents of the Mont Blanc  scheme and champions of the Little  St. Bernard at400,000,000 fr. A more accurate estimate would  be about 150,000,000.  But this is too great a burden for France to shoulder-the Spliigen, it may be mentioned, would.cost between 50,000,000 and 70,000,000 fr. at ia time when all kinds of more urgentproblems of commercial reconstruction, such as the Rhone canalisation scheme,  are pressing for solution.  The probability, therefore, is that the Mont Blanc or LittleSt. Bernard scheme, whichever issues triumphant from the inevitable year-longcontroversy, will  not become a matter of  immediate importance  for some years.Italy and  France will  rather devote their  energies to improving their means  ofcommunication already existing.     17. Whatever may come in the future, however, the history  of  the  central european Railway policy  in  relation to  the trans-Alpine routes  provides severaluseful suggestions as to the way they should be dealt with.  In the first stage we see the nations and  governments very wary in their dealings with all such plans.Then they become convinced in principle that international  railway  constructionis a matter for governmental initiation and regulation.   Finally, they vie with one another in developing means of communication among themselves  and securing  asmuch of its benefits  as possible.   Perhaps another stage may now be entered upon.It may perhaps have become clear that great international railways such as thosewhich this memorandum has been discussing should really be made to serve the endsof European civilisation as a whole.  This does not mean that any such encroach-ment of national sovereignty as the  appointment of  an  international Commissionregulating the railways should be suggested.  A better plan is that of &quot; delegation &quot;or  &quot;trusteeship,&quot; putting international  highways (railways,  rivers,  and canals)under the care of those nations through which they pass, which  would run them ata just profit and hold the trust for the League of Nations an ideal,  perhaps, but onetowards which the complicated character of modern commercial and political lifeseems  inevitably  to be  tending.    Such  an arrangement  should  not abolishcompletely or do  away with national  interests.  It  would  be a  check  on  the exploitation to which the possession of indispensable means of transit must always be a temptation,  and provide a tribunal for the  impartial settlement of the manyclaims  and grievances to  which  international  means  of  communication seempeculiarly capable of giving rise.o

</content>
</cab>
