<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/78/0 images: 432-435</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                                 99 A                                                                 $ si ft(THIS DOCUMENT IS THF PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)T&quot;        -&quot;......&quot; &quot;............-.......- MKWiLlli.......I.I 1.......-mil    ......................................... ... confidential.   .  /ft          WAR CABINET.G.T. 7178.     f           WOMEN  IN  INDUSTRY.The following summary of the Report of the WarCabinet Committee on Women in&apos; Industry is circu-lated for information.   It will be given to thePress on Friday, May 9th for publication inSaturday&apos;s newspapers.     The War Cabinet Committee on Women in Industry, appointed in September 1918 (War Cabinet 468, Minute 11) have now com-pleted their investigations and presented their Report     The volume consists of the main report signed by theChairman, Mr. (now Lord) Justice Atkin, Miss Janet MoCampbell)M.Dv, Sir Lynden Macassey, Sir William Mackenzie and Sir&apos;Matthew Nathan;  a memorandum by Miss Janet Campbell on the health of Women in Industry;  embodying the results of aspecial investigation by certain members of the Committee,which has been accepted by the majority; a minority reportby Mrs&apos;. Sidney Webb;  and a note by Sir William Mackenzieon certain points of disagreement with his colleagues.     Following on a brief introduction and a summary of theCommittee*fl recommendations comes Part II of the reportdealing with the original reference, namely, the relationwhich should be maintained between the wages of women and menhaving regard to the interests of both as well astthe valueof their work.   Chapters I and II give the history of women&apos;s&apos;employment and wages prior to the war in all the principal industries, trade by trade, and in occupations such acdomestic service, commercial and clerical work, teaching, etc the comparative standards of remuneration for men and women in all these forms of employment in 1886, 1906 and immediate-ly before the war are collated and tabulated, and certain general matter such as the demarcation of men&apos;s and women&apos;work, the relative wages-rates for men and women and the causes thereof, the regulation of employment and wages are set forth as they existed under pre-war conditions.     Chapters III and TV deal with the employment and wages of women during the war.   The employment of women in what were formerly recognised as men&apos;s occupations and theircomparative value in different types of new work are consider-ed and their relative industrial qualities described.
       In dealing with women1s wages during the wan the Committee  describe at SQine lengthnthe various orders of the Ministry of  Munitions in controlled establishments and discuss the effectS of these orders but they also deal with the wages rates in other  occupations, with the general rise in women&apos;s wages as compared  with men&apos;s  and with the regulation of wages by Statutory Orders,  Trade Boards, Joint Industrial Councils, &quot;etc.    War advances  are the subject of some general observations and of a comparison  between what was done here and in foreign countries.       Chapters V and VI deal with the future.   The directions In  which women&apos;s employment may be extended in their interest are  discussed and the methods by which the extension may be brought  about are examined.  The regulation of the conditions under  which married women and of young girls may he employed in industry  is advocated.   The necessity for a women&apos;s subsistence wage based  on the needs of single women is urged and as a corollary the need  for Mothers&apos; Pensions and increased assistance to maternity.  Paragraphs  follow with regard to the application of the subsistence  wage, its effect pn foreign trade and the modification necessary  in the case of young girls.       The various conditions in which the relation of women&apos;s  wages to r.en&apos;s in the future require to he considered are  described,  and the principle of the &quot;rate for the job&quot; and its  effect in excluding women from industry is examined,  The formula  of &quot;equal pay for equal work&quot; meaning &quot;pay in proportion to  efficient output&quot; and the effect of the adoption of this principle  on men and  women workers by its application to industry and to  particular  occupations are fully gone into.       The Committee make a number of recommendations which are to  be found collected on pages 4-7 of? the Report and may be sum-  marised as  follows:-       In regard to the relation of men&apos;s and women&apos;s wages they  propose the adoption of the formula of equal pay for equal work  in the sense that pay should be in proportion to efficient output.  On systems  of payment by results equal pay should be given to men  and women for an equal amount of work done.  On time work the  relative value of work done by women and men Bhduldr.bE. agreed by  employers and employed acting through the usual channels of  negotiation..  Where a woman on time does the whole of the work  of a man whom she replaces she should receive the full manTs  rate.  Where a man!s job is subdivided without simplification of  process and a women is put on to do part only of the job, the  labour cost should be su regulated that the employer does not  gain by cheaper labour and the workers receive proportionate  pay for the value of their Work.  \ here a job is simplified and  a woman is  introduced^ the rate should be determined as if the  job were allocated to less skilled male labour than that employed  before simplification, and tho woman should receive only that  amount less than the unskilled rate by which her work is of less.  value.  The onus of proof  as to the extent  to which the woman&apos;s  work is of  less value than the nan&apos;a  is to rest with the employer.  where * omen are employed doing the same work as men for less  wages, the  jobs should be  considered  as men&apos;s jobs for the pur-  pose of fixing womenss wages.  Special  attention  is drawn  to  the  desirability of regulating the wages  of women in  clerical  and  commercial  occupations in accordance  with the formula of  &apos;equalD pay for equal work.  It is recommended that this  formula  should  he  applied  by the Government to Civil Service Departments  and  other national establish ents and  as  far  as possible  to their  contractors.   Separate  grades of women clerks in the Civil . Service should be  abolished, though discretionary power  to  regulate the proportion of women/
in any branch etc.  should be retained. Special allowancesshoulc be granted lor Government work under speciallyarduous conditions, and this principle should; bo extendedto industry.  Where it is essential to employ men andweauon;of the same grade but vjhere &apos;equal pay for equal work&apos;will not attract the same.grade of man as ocman, it maybe aeeesr::ary to counteract this by tha introduction ofchildren&apos;s allowances.  This requires a special consideration in connection with the payment of teachers to which theGovernment contribute.          The Committee recommend an extension oiwomens enroloyment in suitable directions by trado agreemeivtswhich Should duly protect the interests of men workers.The reform and  extension  of the Factory and Workshops Acts,the strengthening of the  Home.Office Factory MedicalInspectorate and the establishment of a local factoryaedieul service to supervise and co-ordinate the existingmedical authorities are recommended.  Further Ao safeguard the health anu  improve the  efficiency of women/industry the Committee advocate a  statutory minimum wage, representingthe cost of reasonable subsistence below whioh no womanshould be employee in industry.  This wage, with additions to adapt it to  places with  high  cost of living,  should bedetermined in the  first instance by a  specially  .:&apos;-cnrjt:.tutedauthority and be adjusted&apos;  periodically.   A  scale oi wages should be established for girls  2/- a week less  than the .women&apos;s  subsi3tence Wyge  for  each year under  16.,  lower rates may be allowed by a Trade  Board  etc., where theemployment  is in  the nature of  an apprenticeship.   Theadoption of a scheme of mothers&apos; pensions  should be  consideredby the Government  and the entire direct costs  involved by the lying in of women  un*er  thoroughly  satisfactorycondtiions  should be provided by the  tate-          Sir William Mackenzie  in a nove  at  the  eni of  thevolume considers  that in  view of existing  arrangements for determing wages  the establishment of a national woman&apos;s  sub-sistence wage is unnecessary.          Part  III of the Heport is an investigation,required by, a supplementary reference  to  the  Committee,  into certain  charges of breach of  faith broiu.:  fc against  v-JieGovernment by various workers&apos;  organisations  in connectionwith  the payment  of women on men&apos;t5 work during tine  war.   Itwas claimed that  the  Treasury Agreement of March 1915required that the women  employed on war v/ork in substitution of men should     receive  the  same pay  as  the  men they  replacedirrespective of the  degrees of  skill  of  the  men substitutedand  of whether  qqual  work was done and it  &quot;was further  claimed that  the war advances given to  assist  in  meeting the increased cost  of  living  should be  the  same  for  women as for men.   TheCommittee came  to  the conclusion that  the  allegations  of breach of faith have not  been  established.   Their investigation intothis  matter leads-  them  to  make   recommendations that  women&apos;s -interests   should be  adequately represented  by women whenindustrial  questions  aflooting  them  are  discussed,  that  the duecarrying out of the  conditions  of  the  Fair Wages Clause  inGovernment  Contracts   should  bo supervised,.that expert   drafts-manship  should  be available for important  industrial agreementsan 6  that when these  are made under the auspices of  a GovernmentIis^artment   the shorthand notes  should be  communicated to  thepartieu  oouteraod.
9 9 &apos;7          Mrs. Sidney y;ebb&apos;&apos;s minority report records her dissent from her colleagues both in the scope and substance of theirreport and in their conclusions and recommendations.   Mrs *v;,ebb first discusses the principles on which wages have hither-to been determined.   She states that the exclusion of women from the better-*paid posts, professions and crafts has driventhem to compete with each other and with men in the lower grader.,of vocation and that this demarcation has had a detrimentaleffect on character and output both individual&apos; and national,the time has now come to exact the same qualifications from  .women as from men and employ them under the same conditions and on the same rates of pay.   The formula of equal pay for equal work though aiming at a right ideal is too ambiguous. .v*hat is rather required are clearly defined Occupational orStandard Rates for all persons in a like occupational grade,these standards to be enforced but only as minima.  Thereshould be a legal national minimum in respect of weekly wages,rest-time, education, sanitation and subsistence the same for both sexes.   In regard to children some sort of State provisionentirely apart from wages, of which the present MaternityBenefit, Free Schooling and Income Tax constitute only thegem, Is essential.   This question should be investigated by a separate Commission.     The chaos and inequality in wage remuneration produced by the war calls for investigation by a Royal Commissioninto the sharing of the national product among classes,industries and individuals better to secure the ir.?ximum pro-productivity of industry and the maximum personal deve-lopweut of citizens.     Mrs. Tebb examines the charges brought against theGovernment in regard to the Treasury Agreement arid  comes to the conclusion that the pledge it embodies hod beenwholly ignored by some Departments and only tardily andpartially fulfilled by others to the -great loss to  the womenconcerned and that the most flagrant breach was the refusal of the Government to concede to the women concerned thesuccessive advances given to men doing similar work.Whitehall Gardens,

</content>
</cab>
