<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/78/0 images: 498-504</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(55 W , This  DOCUMENT.is t^Prop^lQj,     and MAY, 1919,H&apos;s Grfiarjnjcjoajw^jjLi. ........&quot;^tW^Xr OF  SITPPLY AUD CE1WRAL31ADMIRALTY teAORATTDIM FOR TIE WAR CABINET. HALL                I  hcpo  that tho Cabinet will discuss at an early       date  tho  question cf what  are to be the future powers of       the Ministry cf  Supply..  On the 8th November, 1918, the       War Cabinet decided.          (a)   To create out of  the Ministry of Munitions                a  Ministry of Supply,          (b)   To entrust the Ministry of Supply with the                sale of surplus war stores.          (c)   That the departments concerned should be res-                ponsible for saying what stores vore surplus.          (d)   That no change in supply arrangements should                be made.- until the conclusion of peace.                They therefore requested. -                The Ministry cf Munitions to submit tc the War       Cabinet(1)  A sphere for orfanisirf and naming a  su     department of the  Ministry for the  clisp                                     sub-                                      posal  of surplus war stores;     (2)  A scheme for -                  The scope of a Ministry of Supply;              12) Its functions;              (5) Its organisation.         The time has now come when the actual functions ofthe Ministry of Supply in relation to other departments should be more fully considered, as differences of opinionexist as to the precise effect of the Cabinet decision.         In a Memorandum tc the Cabinet G-.T.70G4, theChancellor of the Exchequer states - &quot;it will be rememberedthat Lord lnchcape&apos;s Committee on Contracts recommended thatthe Ministry of Supply should deal with all Government purchasesexcept feed and highly technical supplies for the Navy.&quot;  Thereis, I. think, a misunderstanding here as to what it was Lord&apos;Inchcape&apos;s committee actually proposed.  The recommendationsof that Committee only deferred tc the period of war and were                                                       . __.net  /
 riot intended to apply to normal  conditions of peace.  This fact is quite clearly indicated  by the following correspondence,          On October 31st the  question was raised by Mr, Pretymon at that time Civil Lord of the Admiralty in the following letter to Lord Inohoape                                       31st October, 1918. Dear Inohoape,          Has your attention been called to the attached report  of the Munitions Ooundil Committee?  If you look at paragraph 3 of Chapter II at the  bottom of page 7 you will see that you and your Treasury Committee arc  quoted as having advocated central buying in peace  time.          Paragraph 2 of  your report states exactly the contrary opinion, and all  the rest of it deals with centralbuying  under war  conditions which was the matter referredto  you.          It seems  to me  a serious matter that.your1 report should  be misquoted in an official document  and you may wish to have it corrected0        *          The point is of some Importance  as  great efforts are still being made by the Ministry to perpetuate its existence as a permanent supply and manufacturing department in peace time.  This would obviously have a  disastrous  effecton private trade and would interfere with the  return to  normalconoiitions and the withdrawal of  Government  interference whichwe are  so anxious to bring about  as soon  as  possible afterthe end of the war.         For you of all people to be quoted  as  a supporterof this policy is no doubt laughable but  it  is &quot;also  dangerous.   .
        I well remember  this point of oan feral buying inpeace time being mentioned when  I gave evidence beforeyour Committee and you  all saying that it was not referredto you  and that you did not consider it a practicalproposal.                         Yours etc.                             (Sgd.) E.G. Protyman.5?o this letter Lord Inchcape replied as follows;-                             7th November 1918.My dear Pretyman,              Please excuse delay in answering your letterof 31st October.   It was never in the mind of theCommittee to suggest setting up a Department for purchasingafter the War.     All we considered was the host meansof co-ordinating the purchase arrangements during the wa^while they run into thousands of millions and there wasa rush  to buy to meet the emergencios with which thevarious Departments were faced.   When things become normal and there is no emergency I am firmly of opinion that each department should,be allowed to look after its own affairs,             I am just  leaving for the Clyde, and mySecretary will si/rn this letter.                         Yours  sincerely,                        (Sgd.) For Lord Inchcape.            It may be that this misunderstanding was in the minds of the Cabinet when they cane to their decisionlast November.    If so, the misunderstanding should nowbe cleared up.
                    (4)o         Paragraph 7 of  the Memorandum to the  cabinet of the Minister of 1-taVtions Ci,T,  7036 states         &quot;The Government has also  decided to develop     the present Ministry of todtions into a  Ministry     of Supply charged with tho  responsibility of     providing, with a few exceptions, the whole of the     supplies&quot;for all the Departments  of Government&quot;.         These words appear to me  to go beyond what wasin fact decided at tho time and  I  am anxious that thematter should again be. considered  by the Cabinet, because,apart from the differences between the Air Ministry and  theMinistry of Munitions, the Admiralty is also involved.         It seems to be  supposed that  the success of theMinistry of  Munitions in purchasing on a hugh  scale for  theArmy during the War is an argument for making  another department responsible for the supplies of the Navy.  the argument is fallacious.   It ignores the fact that the needsof the Army and tho Navy are entirely  different.    The Historyof the Iftnistry of Munitions in fact only proves that at atime when demand enormously exceeded supply the organisationof manufacture -Mid the allocation  of raw materials  under special powers were so essential that  much  else had to be sacrificed to secure them.  During the same period  theAdmiralty carried out all the supply arrangements of  the Navywith complete and conspicuous success.         Meetings have taken place between representatives ofthe Admiralty and the Ministry of  Munitions  to discuss whatfunctions can be transferred to the new Ministry of Supplywithout impairing the responsibility  of the Admiralty for  theefficiency of the Naval  Service.  In tho discussions  whichhave taken place, the Ministry of  Munitions have interpretedtho Cabinet decision  in a sense which the Admiralty do notbelieve to have been  intended and which if acted upon wouldmake it impossible for the Admiralty  to accept responsibilityfor the consequences.
         Briefly stated the Admiralty contention is thatstrategy and supply are so closely interwoven that theefficiency of the Navy would inevitable suffer if they were tobecome dependent upon another Department for the supply ofNaval equipment of all kinds.  They do not believe that the cabinet ever intended that this should be the consequence oftheir decision.  The Admiralty regard tho resolution of theCabinet as having established the principle of a CentralPurchasing Department without determining its scope at themoment, the question of the actual services to be transferredto it being left for further consideration in connection withthe scheme which the Ministry of Munitions was to prepare.         Acting- on this interpretation, they have proposedto the Ministry of Munitions that the Admiralty should retainresponsibility for the supply of ships and their essentialequipment, and have offered to discuss with the Ministry ofMunitions what articles of a general stock naturo required in bulk might be supplied by the Ministry of Supply whether bypurchase or by    manufacture in the Ordnance, or other National-Factories.  Agreement was in fact reached that machine guns,rifles, small arms ammunition, and certain other articlesshould be so supplied and the Admiralty contemplated thediscussion of other supplies on their waits.         The Ministry of Munitions, however, take the view thatthe Cabinet intended, without any consideration of the special conditons of the Admiralty, that all supply should be handedover to them with the exception only of ships and suchtechnical and experimental stores as the Admiralty can makeout a case for exempting from tho general rule.         If such an interpret--tion is insisted upon, agreementcannot be reached as regards the details of carrying it out,  ,The Admiralty do not believe that a dividing line betweendesign and supply, or between technical or experimental and
general articles,  can be drawn in a manner that will adjiitof satisfeatery working between tuo Departments.   Design,manufacture, inspection and the maintenance of  reserves  are sointerlaced in the case of ships and their equipment  that theAdmiralty regard it -s impracticable for a separation to be.effected on the lines desired by the I&amp;nistry of  Munitions,A ship is an infinitely complex arganiss and self containedunit, the complete efficiency of which for fighting  purposesdepends on every detail, and there are many importantdifferences in the circumstances of Naval and Army supplies.         Similarly with regard to oil and fuel. The  design  ofILK.Ships and their machinery is dependent inter alia uponAdmiralty knowledge of world1 s supplies of fuel,  coal and oil,and qualities.  Seagoing experience and information  from manysources are collated for the above purposes, emergency arrangements and forward contracts, etc, are based not only upon estimates of requirements;., but upsn Admiralty knowledge of resources, relative costs, efficiencies etc.  The mobility  ofthe Fleet is absolutely dependent upon efficient arrangementsfor supply of coal and oil at all ports at home and abroad.Reserve stocks ail over the world are based not only uponestimates of requirements, but also conditions of replenishments.Emergencies frequently arise necessitating larger requirementsof the Fleet or variations in places of requirement, orincreases of stock in case of threatened strikes etc.          All these matters of vital concern to the  Admiralty,in  regard to which immediate executive action has to be taken.To  attempt  to control the intricate relations which are involvedthrough the medium of some other department will inevitablyresult in failure to obtain the supplies upon which EJ&apos;, ships are dependent for their  movements.
         The ADMIRALTY HAS IN FACT  HAD EXPERIENCE  IN THE PASTOF THE INEFFICIENCY WHICH &quot;RESULTS FROM  ENTRUSTING SOME OFITS MAIN SUPPLIES TO ANOTHER  DEPARTMENT OF STATE   AT  ONETIME GUNS AND AMMUNITION WERE OBTAINED BY THE WAR  OFFICE for both THE ARRAY AND THE NAVY WITH THE RESULT,  SO FAR  AS THENAVY WdS CONCERNED, THAT WE FAILED TO KEEP  ABREAST  OF progress and &quot;THE GAINS WERE NOT READY IN TIME FOR THE SHIPS.   WITH this experience FROM THE PAST, THE ADMIRALTY COULD NOT  accept responsibility FOR THE EFFICIENCY OF THE NAVY IF A SIMILARSYSTEM WERE TO BE RE-ESTABLISHED,                          (SIGNED)   W. H, LONG,   5, 19.

</content>
</cab>
