<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/219/26 images: 782-818</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

|p&lt;85) 26 j^pvember 1985

COPY NO 32

CABINET

PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEY 1985 ^Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council

At their meeting on 11 July the Cabinet decided   hat the public expenditurelBKfc totals should be  139.1 bil llon_f&quot; J98^lnvUed  143.9 billion for&quot;.1987-88, and  148.2 billion for 1988-89, and the Chief Secrelary, treasury to pursue bilateral discussionso expenditure programmes with the Ministers responsible.    On 3 October the Chief secretary   Treasury reported progress.    The Prime Minister invited   to JrSe ch:i3H\.PMini.teri.l Group on Public    xpen itu (MISC 120) to consideT J^ake recommendations on those iswhich not been resolved by th^hTef Secretary   Treasury and spending Ministers concerned (CC(85) 24th Conclusions, Minute 4; CC(85) 28th Conclusions, Minute 4).

2.     This memorandum sets out ^commendations of  SC &quot;0.    I should like to express my gratitude bolMlthe members of the Group and spending Ministers who have applied before us for the care and thoroughness which they have broufht to the task.

3-     A large number of programmes we^fced in bilateral *   ioM between the Chief Secretary, Treasury and the spending ^ters concerned.    The effects on the Survey bllfcarese    out in Annex A

brief descriptions of the policy i P&quot; J^ &quot; ^&quot;/of programmes to were. however,  left with an unprecedentedlM^e numbe to t p g consider, with aggregate bids above the agrTed^sel ine in the y remaining at some  3.4 billion,  4.7 billion Wd ^ 5.7 bi ion ^spectWely, after allowing for the lower Reserves and large additional asset sales&apos;proposed by the then Chief Secretary, Treasury in July and changes agreed bilaterally between the Chief Secretary, Treasury and spending Ministers. a tf^

In order to assist the Group&apos;s substantive discu%M|^n the Individual programmes, the Chief Secretary, Treasury re#ns^e e Prospects for receipts from asset sales and the size of Xther ^serve it would be prudent to keep in hand.    He also consferfl whether it would be appropriate, in the light of the latest projection ox inflation,  to make some small adjustment to the planning totaJ consistently with the Government&apos;s determination to hold that &quot;tai broadly constant in real terms.    He concluded that the followin^^s, though not without risk, would be possible.


			  billion	

		1986-87	1987-88	1988-89

Reduction in Reserve		0.5	0.25	0

Increase in receipts asset sales	from	0	0.75	0.5

Increase in planning	total	0	0	0.5

5.      1 to report that the Group --made major strides towards

^n^L^fc t,:t::a ^ivizi of the ^ two

years, ana a 1 ttie over  3 billion in the third     Changes in the economic Projections rT^el the social security additional bide by about E0.2 billion   IfcSklion and  0.7 billion in each oi  the thre. years, somewhat reducing the extent of the Group&apos;s task     On the basis of he Group&apos;s proposalfthere^ould be excesses of about  0.1 billion in each the first two years.    However,  the housing programme is still &quot;n*er discussion and^xcesVjkhe order of  1 billion would remain   n each Survey year if the addi#nfl bid by the Secretary of State for the Environment were allowed.    I will report the position &lt;w  j to&quot; e Cabinet.    Since the Group discussed the social security programme it has also become clear that later estimating changes reflecting later assessments of claimant numbers anxlof the rate of take up  [ will add further to our problem^ffcrhaps by as much as Ej billion by third Survey year.    There thus remain difficulties m holding to the agreed public expenditure plannina^^^J-S.

6&apos; recommendations on the ag^^ammes are summarised in

Paragraphs 7-21.    All figures are in  -ji^n U&quot; 6    B         ,llar auestion and further details are provided in AnoAto L.    A particular arises about Scotland which is summarised^gj|ragraph 15.

AGREED PROGRAMMES

P^fence

7*     The Survey baseline is as follows -

18,560 r I8&apos;859 |ft 19,033

The Secretary of State for Defence had proposed the following additions to baseline -

sqs 897 + 422 &apos; 595


In discussion with the Group he accepted that   with the ending of the NATO .commitment to 3 per cent real annual growth, there ne ed *e   ^8^8 f ^further real increase in the defence programme     Intheee c rcumstances  Mje future size of the defence programme should reflect on the one hand

the requirement to maintain a defence capability suffJ ent to meet the

SER cUi 1 f l-   Shin the overall constraint of the agreed aggreg te

provision for public expenditure.    The Group made clear their view that,

following the very substantial real increases of recent years in the

Provision of equipment for the armed forces, itwas now  t

Government unities more towards health, housing and social &quot;ourity,

they saw 4 ong case for reducing the defence programme below bas in,

in order to mak, room for more expenditure in these other areas They

acknowledged, however,  the difficulties the Secretary of State *&gt;r

Defence would face if provision for defence were reduced in cash terms

below thrpe^S| published figures, and they therefore agree   with him

that the progrSKSkuld remain at baseline for the firs,  two years Foi

the third yeS tSpfteed with the Secretary of State    or Defence that

the ? 11 \ vtaA      Survev baseline figure should be maintained,

cue - as yet unpublished - Survey uabeiJ-uc     &amp; , . .    t-v,Dr rntal

but that the costsl|QS^lklands should be contained within that total

Foreign and Commonwealth Office:    Oversea Development Administration

8- MISC 120 and the Foreign and Commonwealth SecretarJ^aroragt^e&apos;Verall recommend the following increase the baseline provision for the overall Programme - fcml

This will accommodate the estimated ^r^se in the Aid and Trade Provision agreed by the Ministerial C^ajke on Expor s (EX(85) 3rd feting,  ltL 1; EX(85) 4th Meeting &quot;^P-   o     he cos    of th. latter will  be me I   during the Survey per^EMktrarisier rrom otner Departments   interested in promoting facility.

JSgJLgy (Departmental Programme)

9- MISC 120 and the Secretary of State for Energy have agreed on savings of  5 miinon per annum from the nuclear research and development Programme which will be found across the whole programme.

P-  artment o  the Environment: Other \J^L

i -    Following discussions with the Group,  the Secretary&lt;0 |te for the Environment and the Chief Secretary, Treasury have fref^O^OE? ^duction8 below baseline  Ln the Department  oi  the Environm^W)  ther&quot; _

- 20 - 20


These figures are net of a substantial increase in receipts from the sale k of new town assets.    The urban programme which is an element m the DOE V&apos;Other&quot; programme is assumed to remain at baseline, pending further discussion, among Ministers of possible Government policy responses  to the ivKent disturbances  in  inner cities.

Education and Science

11. MISC 120 have agreed with the Secretary of State for Education and Science to recommend that the following additions should be made to his Department&apos;s Survey baseline -

Chan^J^reed bilaterally 28.5 23.5 8.0

Scienca^^^iniversities 25 25 25

Local autl^Ji^capital 27 25 25

The changes agree^fcterally primarily reflect spending on  an^tory student awards and,(i  the first two years) expenditure on the -witch transferred from ot^WLrammes to enable universities to increase then -tput of graduates  sjLce and technology.    The other additions will enable the Secretary of#afe for Education and Science to allocate some additional resources to key areas in science and the universities without relaxing the pressure on the latter for greater efficiency; ^d also Provide some greater flexibility in essential local authority capital expenditure.

A tJL_and Libraries

12-    MISC 120 have agreed with the\fi*er of State, Privy Council Office (Minister for the Arts) on the f olll5fg|et additions to the baseline Provision for the arts and libraries ^^^L

These figures include additional provision^^r^te Arts Council of

The Minister of State, Privy Council Office, belj^^^^^slng&apos;from

sufficient to meet the requirements and P?^^&quot;^&quot;^^!^, and

fcne abolition of the Greater London Council and Me ro Co ,

^ maintain the Arts Council&apos;s regional development s rat,gy.

addition in 1986-87 reflects the need to ensure tha   ^ ^e Mini8ter

immediate adverse effects through abolition.     Ln later y^^jfllk

 f State, Privy Council Office expects to be f^^J^O-.the costs

8ubstantial contributions from the successor authorities to^y^

01 the performing arts.


Hg_alth and Personal Social Services

There were large bids for additional expenditure on both the j^^cash-limited parts of the programme  (principally the hospital and Jj^mmunity health services) and  the demand-determined  family practitioner services, which are not at present subject to a cash limit.    They total -

?  i^09 487 870

^      Following a re-examination of these bids the Secretary of State for octal Services has identified further savings that could be made by ntensifying the campaign for increased efficiency in the hospital and community health services; and changes in provision for certain centrally nanced s^tflkces and for family practitioner services administration. se changes yield the following savings on the bids set out above -

159      ^Sfc. 184 270

MISC 120 and th^g^OT^tary of State for Social Services jointly recommend them,    xhe agreed additions to baseline then become -

250 300 600

This will allow an incr^^^^of 2 per cent  in real terms on hospitals and community health services current spending in 1986-87.

Sc^Uand

5.    The Group would like to haue^kcured savings on the Scottish block of the order of - ilf,

reflecting their judgment that public^^ro^e provision in Scotland is now generally too high in relation to comparable provision in England and

es&apos;    For example Scottish local authority rents are 30 per cent lower he 3 proPort-i n  f average earnings than i^JO^charged in England, and

ealth expenditure per head is over 25 per^^t^igher than the English average.    Furthermore it is noteworthy that th^^^pulation of Scotland has the 6n ^ ^ * ^ Per cent relative to England since the underlying base for

Scottish block was set in parallel with a needs assessment based on in     ^ata*    The Secretary of State for Scotland, however, considers that th ^eneral no changes can be made in the overall block provision other n as a result of the application to Scotland of vari^^ms in English ogrammes,  by means of the automatic &quot;formula&quot; which ^M^^tes such rginal changes.    The only other reductions the Secrew A  State for 0 land will contemplate are those which would not be r^Hj^^de tec table


or which could be justified by reference to ParticuJa*-^&quot;&quot;J^ fund circumstances.    He has offered reductions in respect of lower contributions to housing revenue accounts

!k 8-7 20-7 &apos;

^kher with other agreed variations, the overall change, in the Scottish h^Wfcne are -

The Group believe, however, that even after such &quot;^^^^^15! &quot; is unsatisf^ory   and should not be allowed to ^^^f^1 ^iasis There is | Lr case for a fresh assessment of need to serva the for the allocation of public provisions as between England Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland.    The objective would be to &quot;^&quot;^^ baselines foSHPfcrritorial block provisions, and a new ^anism tor adjusting thosXjLines in the light of ^ure econom, c e^ca^ other relevant changes.    The Group recommend that this tres&quot; need be undertakeTlgUme to be taken into account in decisions on 1986 Public Expenditure Survey; the work should be undertaken on a confidential basis w^lfeovernment, but Ministers would need to b ready to explain that the TtJfkat was required to take account of changes over the last decade throughout the United Kingdom and implied no prejudgments about the conclusions.

Electricity Industry

16.    The Survey baseline is as follows -

Following substantial reduction of thtft^tricity supply industry&apos;s initial bids, the Secretary of State fo^Qrgy sought the following changes in the baseline provisions - 42sW

+ 169 - 124 + 568

After re-examination of the scope for f ur ther^avings, and some rephasing of working capital requirements from 1986-87 to 1987-88, and given that, on the latest available evidence, the timetable for construction ot tne Sizewell PWR is likely to slip a year, the Group and the Secretary ot State for Energy have agreed to recommend the following^kanges from the above baseline - Em^U.

+ 31 - 198 V^ k+ 2&quot;

The Chief Secretary, Treasury has agreed that if, contrary expectations, consent was given to the construction of Sizewell before autumn 1987,  any resulting additional expenditure above the ba*s 20L should be met from the Reserve. ^^^W


Water

^fhP Chief Secretary, Treasury 17.    Following discussion with the Group, the cnie ^ and the Secretary of State for the Environment have   g ^ Ihpuld be no increase in the baseline provisio 6 ^ broadly the same

^l s is consistent  with maintaining planned efl8e in domestic charges

Vejls as envisaged  Last year, and an ^eragrecommend that the figures

oJ^ibut 8 per cent next spring.    The Group re efn 0 f the Secretary

should be settled on this basis, while noting al   roblems when the

of State for the Environment at the potential po ^ Return Order in

House of Commons is asked to approve the necessa y       _      , basis December.    They also note that a settlement on tne P P represents fte relaxation of the rate  J erial committee on

industry&apos;^mlancial performance sought by the n) {      la8t year.

Economic IKjL Sub-Committee on Nationalised Industries

Coal and Gas yy^ies

18. Tor the Na^ftlfcoal Board,  the Chief Secretary   Treasury and the Secretary of Statflfcnergy have agreed changes to the

provision of external finance of -

+ 348 + 158 &quot; 2

These figures are provisional, pending the availabilit?  * ^&quot; Business Plan, and this will be made clear in the Autumn Statement.

19. For the British Gas Corporate*, which is due to be P&quot;^^86^11&quot;&apos; autumn,  the Chief Secretary, TrA i*nd the Secretary of St at

Energy have agreed that the baseflKfttgative external f1 &quot;&quot; * ion requirement in 1986-87 of  470 midHJ^hould be revised to  42U ^ to cover the period before privatis^jMukes places.    in 8 orthcoming

not be separately identified in the jfcur^S t a t erne n t or in tne White Paper. ^V^B Social Securitv

20. There are large additional bids stemm\j^y ^&apos;^.^^^ithoT&quot; assumptions and higher take-up of benefits wh h are inevitable wi Policy changes.    Following the Chief Secretary, Treasury s bilateral ^ discussions, and taking account of further revision to the figure

light of the autumn economic forecast, the bids above the Survey baseline totalled -

? 982 + 459 + ^144

21. After a very careful and detailed examination of op^&gt;5i&apos;&apos;^ j^rtner savings,  including possible accelerated  implementation of s e #L f measures in the Social Security Reviews, the Group, with the agreafen o the Secretary of State for Social Services,   recommend the folW^^^ further savings - ^^5^


1986-87	1987-88	1988-89

No uprating of Child Benefit in July 1986, but ^   full uprating in April 1987. &apos;A Further savings in 1988-89. 16 ~ new drive against social security fraud. 25	- 27 30	23 30

Reduction of help with mortgage interest from	*	*

	80	160

Squire employers ^^ke over payment of maternity allowance on the same  asis as Statutory Sick Introduce selective fcWL ^?vision to replace maternlty and death grant. Wfc Adjustment required to t6oU    forln Pr Visi0nal ror the programme.	30 140 25 t	105 170 * 276

T tal Savings                                    n \	i\ 278	764

* Saving already scored in base figures

 al security in l98^8;,^!^ million The total for expenditure on socia      19g7_88 baseline tVK benefits iti calculated by adding to the a^S    \,     er cent upratilK ot       the Retail needed to meet the cost of a full J tiotlS of the c&lt;~2flpLhe baseline.

April. 1988, reelecting the latest p    j      increa8e assunie g_     and wili Pric,   Lndex, rather than the 2i per ce       .gureS are Prov^j&quot;&quot;lLj Lt should be emphasised that the 1V  context of tne^i^Lchanges

depend on decisions still to be taken i flbout the t nn.ng

Security Review, because of public    rtai   y considera^0  in social security arising from the Review    t       ^ pregented to some extent to 1987-88, and both figure provisional in the Autumn Statement.


The agreed changes from baseline on social security are thus

\ + 380

U ? 891 + 181

^^The Group have not yet been able to &lt; ^ I?  j  ^ ~J^ary of State for the Environment on the housing p

The baseline provision for current and capital expenditure net of capital receipts is as follows -

1988-89

1986-8*^ 1987&quot;88

|fl 2,589

 f &lt;?fflte for the Environment In discussion%5i%he Group the Secretary of State tor

Proposed the fiioiog net additions to the baseline

^*j*\. + 892

The Chief Secretary, Treasury sought reductions below baseline of -

^^^^ - 298

- 21 ~ 227

23. Both sets of figures include agreed changes of  104 ^l^;ter0St  123 million and  12 million to meet the unavoidable errec -te changes on housing subsidy aerate funds con&apos;ributxona and Pf -ortg and agreed capital savings  (improvement grants Secretary  25 million,   55 million and  20 million.    The remainder of State for the Environment&apos;s bi^is made up as follows

W% +50 + 50

New provision for rent ^^^A

Renovation of public  sector J^A, . 350

stock + 55(^P^ +

Discussion with the Secretary of State forlkeJ^iromnent is continuing and 1 win report the outcome orally to the CWinet.

LOCAL AUTHORITY CURRENT EXPENDITURE AND THE RESERVE

24. Inevitably a major concern remains about the futurejcourse authority current expenditure.    In general the Government must ^ y ^ indirect means to control this expenditure, and the outcome  1s -dual be influenced also by changes in the political complexion or in 1 authorities.    A major uncertainty remains about whether or wne&quot; authorities might be in a position to call on the additiona^r^ourc ^ held out by the Government for restructuring teachers&apos; pay F0UOW.11 b agreement on teachers&apos; duties and on the better management ot^!B^k in force.    There is a risk, in the present climate, that any figures pu would only be regarded as a challenge to be exceeded; and to glV^*^ White Paper a breakdown between services of an aggregate the Chie^


Secretary, Treasury could accept in advance of negoti^^f^amat authorities would almost certainly show lower exPen^&quot; . j

Policy would indicate on, for example, pojn   P  ona       ex. ^ ^services.    The Chief Secretary, Treasury ^.f J&quot;^r*8re8pon8ible for Jj|cretary of State for the Environment and the M n s P ^ f&lt;&gt;r

the main services that the agreed 1986-87 fxguireswcri Overs&apos; P^)  ho ld be projected  &lt;&gt;^rd unchanged^

^^ing two years, with a clear proviso that r . Rate

P^5v^ion will be determined in the context of*acV^ &quot; rhis \Z Support Grant settlement, and that regard has been had to this in determining the size of the Reserve.    The Reserve has accordngly been increased above the level at which it would otherwise have a too by  0.25 billi     t0.75 billion and  1.0 billion for   he three years

Principal*!* this account&apos; Taki g int  ^ /  4 75 billion, out in paragraph 4 above, the Reserve thus now stands at  4.75 billion,  6.5 billion and  8 billion for the three years.

AUTUMN STATEME^^

The Group urlAand that the Chancellor of the =*fe^ *&quot;&quot;^ar8  give total figures for each programme for each of the three Survey years m his forthcoming }(RlLstatement.    This responds to s&quot;ong Parliamentary preMurfTjkwi&quot; make U Possible   r the 1&apos; Jd as

totals emerging from the 1985 public expenditure round to be presented as a whole.

RECOMMENDATIONS 26-    I invite the Cabinet -

a. subject to my report on the housing programme,  to endorse the agreements reached,  as summar^Sita paragraphs 7-21 above,

b. to agree that a fresh assesV^^f need be undertaken   oa a confidential basis within Governmi||o serve as the basis tor rn allocation of public provision as between England, Scotland, *aies and Northern Ireland. ^C^k.

Pri*y Council Office 6 November 1935


12C:    PROGRAMMES PREVIOUSLY AGREED

		 		secret			

			SCORECARD				

EX	1986-87 1987-88 Baseline     AGREED Baseline 999,999   99,999 999,999 *  FCO-OTHER                   603          38 619				AGREED 99999 43	1968-89 BoHlin* 999,999 635	AGREED 99999 63

		640	10	830	320	850	100

	3.  1BAP/aff CAP	1.277	272	1,304	334	1,337	336

	aff domes^Xjp^ 5. FORESTRY	713	8	699	5	717	3

*		a 53	0	  54	0	56	0

*	6. TRADE/1NDUSTR	Pi*	-13	980	12	1,004	-25

*	7. ECGD ij		200	-43	213	-44	138

*	8. EMPLOYMENT		-74	3,901	-207	3,999	-125

*	9- TRANSPORT		27	1,995	33	2,045	52

	IO.DOE-psa	-120	7	-128	0	-131	0

*	11.LCD	574	21	610	39	625	73

	12.HOME OFFICE	1.061	1ft	1,10*	44	1,131	55

	13.CIVIL SUPER	1,114		L1,226	86	1.257	147

	1*.WALES	1,708	-1	|j^^35	-1	1,779	-4

	15-N.IRELAND	4,464	53		76	4,717	105

	16.CHANCELLOR XS	1,825	163		169	1,888	143

	17.OTHER line let consequences 1	366	170		170	406	205

J	    NAT IND |0. Settled 21.     RMPS &amp; SRP 23. BGC	1,495 309	-4 194	1,265 318 -390	~ -41 390	1,299 326 -400	-459 -50 400

	2* .la REL CURIUKAI	26,032	646	26,301	359	26,959	-323

	25.SPECIAL SALES of ASSETS	-2,250  	2,250	-2,250	-2000	-2,250	-1750

  ?	26.RESERVE 27.3.3 1 increase in 1908-89 2B.lets double counting TOTAL AGREED	6,000   -254	 1,250	7,000 -247	-500	^A^|po 1000  ^ -1627	

		52,509	-1,675	&quot;53&quot;, 724	-533~	56.571	


MISC  120:    PROGRAMMES CONSIDERED BY THE GROUP

	1986-87		1987-88		1988-89	

Baseline M D(1)V\ Pen        4v^\     18 &apos;56  from other d ENErgy s d0e~0ther DEs 848 OAL 3^8 ^   pss ^itorial 4&apos;3    nsequences -,447 Coal 123 Bgc 382 ^Lanmt ,               &apos;    &apos; &apos;-		MISC 120 PROPOSALS 0 21 -4 22 -20 81   \ 31 0 348 50 -1,675	Baseline 18,859 1,317 293 860 3,505 342 15,622 43,553 4,373 -1,487	MISC 120 PROPOSALS 0 29 -11 32 -20 75 9 300 181 0 90 -196 0 158 -533	Baseline 19,033 1,350 300 882 3,593 350 16,012 44,642 4,482 -1,524 15 402 56,574	MISC 120 PROPOSALS 0 37 -11 35 -15 60 12 600 380 -17 170 243 0 -2 -1543

lNG TOTALS  n 139,062 DlTir. EWVIR0^ UGHT BY V1***ENT SECRETARY Plus fu *na^Se8 t6rrit-ial		51 679 140	143,894	195	148,700	-51 892 180


ANNEX B

^^NOTES ON AGREEMENTS REACHED IN BILATERALS

  million

 *^3fr. i +38    +&quot;3 +63

cos-ts lr&gt;cludes increased provision to offset increases in overseas

&apos;   and   for tcrp

is 1h , C SU  external  services.     In  the  last  year  an  extra  20m

compensate for the ending of loan repayments &quot;by Yugoslavia.

oft

+100

The figures  reflect nign&lt;?^J^

Communities.   tB^10*

i.    imp/aw cap ^ irfW        f intervention bt ~

f0Wi^s  f        ff ^creases

flects ^Sher ^l^forecastxtiS lT1 er

The net change  largely  reflec ^ in     c* *

*ue to agricultural a^8** &apos;     ort tor ^ acriieved V

offset hy economy measureb on ^ ^ recent re u

and a once and for  all saving of &quot;^2*^11** recei*- 

,  cereals- l985 ^d Payments for intervened cei             ^ntion  -r ^

   -\ c interne in the forecast  for cereals

f-rom nev EC &quot;butter measures.   jjj^-on

8 Civ

- result ol volume ctonsas 1  ^ prote=

the resources to implement decisi


  million

For^ommission vas settle*a    ^ ^ ^..^ conse^^kand restoration ahsor ^

-13 +12

6.    D/Trade and_lnd^ry_ aeroengi*e projects,

%fT lor  aircrait and ae ^ reduced

. increases  i r industries, Q

The net changes  include m steel   in airCraft

Vlr|-&lt;1^ng    a communications, et;Ung

assistance   to   the ^  urgency   Comm nclaaeB o Be

requirements   for   the ^ uPk        TYie settlement a aeroengine projects and manpo

savings on regional policy- ^^^^   pillion

+200 +21S

7&apos;      |CL f tYie interest support

a9t costs of tne ^ soUg1at

The agreed  olds  cover the higher  ^^^^^^g savings fl. Program and cost escalation ^0,1 cap-

  H and making inci dW^M ty reducing &quot;banks&apos; margins an   mil110&quot;

 -    Employment a_+s and the

 K J- . requirements

ejecting  reduced  req A-^sement  et  savings  have  heen  agreed,   r Bedundancy ^n &apos; Uj^kyears.

abolition oi rebates to employers from ^ {Qr tne ne.        ^ ^

eternity pay will again he kept at 9^ ^ ^ ^^L* ^ese savings are partially offset   y     ^ ^ expansion ol Dillon a year-, for 19&amp;8-89 over half In the Budget.


  million

^^Mu mi | i I

\AT .oml roads,   local capital and

^e^ change  includes  increases  for  nation    ^ programmes and

gross^l^g  costs   offset  by   savings   from transport companies

in^djLon of EFL treatment for local au ^&amp;  ag   a   hole is

( l+0 oill^n^a  year).    The  agreement   on the  pr ^oduce EFL treatment conditional on securing the legislation needed to n for local authority transport companies.

agreed for maintenance,

&gt;- the  first year  increas^Cfcjvision has  been  agr allowance ^ works  and  the  Internat^bjjonference  Centre.       ^ ^ has   also   been   made   for   Parliamentary huildmg Apartments).

  million

&apos;     IgrdChancellor&apos;s Dept + ^Ji^

TJiks    of    legal   aid and -e   agreed   changes    reflect   the    increased nfidential review

-Ministration  of   legal aid by  the  Law SocietlM^ ^gal aid controls will be set up. ?^^^

  million

&apos; ***age deal was agreed with the Home Secretary ref^^^^ ^ prison service, largely because of the growth m ^^^^^ need to maintain the prison building programme.    Bids  for  lPjg.

the ^ n1cn v. accommodated w^Qjg^^

;    Passport and immigration departments will also  oe ^ crimiO^k

Vae agreed provision.    The figures imply worsening arrears on la^ies compensation scheme and no addition to provision for ire ^    The   figures   also  reflect  a   switch  of   resources   from anothe -^gramme for civil defence purposes. 3


  million

-&apos;&apos;fttl Superannuation

VfV .   +,e  cost  of  Paints  to civil

^ fl^Jceflect  higher   forecasts of

service packers and their dependants.

  million

V^.   ,   Development Agency and the

&apos;  reduction, have lli^reed for the Wish partially offset

B alop e t Board  for Inhales.     These  savings  ar pa ^ -teases for housing rSenue account interest payments.

^Pj^   millio11

+ 76 +l05

ip .   CO + |U

gortherp Ireland

TV, iJl^on the hasis  of  the normal

ne Northern Ireland hlock will he  sex^a ^ higher forecast

^Vforinuia arrangements.    The agreed a^jySkrePinterest payments. Costs of social SeCUrity and housing revenue

^jft*   millio11

16.  c, +163 +lU3

^Sgellor&apos;s Departments +XD3

tion of  fraud and

^^islon has  heen made   for  increased work on +he ^standing

4rUg ahuse,  expenditure on computers and staff to re fc^l^er the

Wklog of work in tax offices.    Increases are also nee e ,

^ expenditure costs of life assurance premiums and mor BTOLct

7Uef-   ^ the Rating of Government Proper,;, Department, ^

l0Wer ^recasts of receipts from departments under PRS, an ^ JPJ^

C Sts  f rates paid on hehalf of Crovu occupations and forexgn


^^luding territorial

^^ffig^quences) increases agreed

V\,                            -to-al conseouences of *  provision

Provisi^Kade for the terror                 ^ add^ ^ ^ ^

for  comparable  programmes.            secution Service. prQvision

to cover the cost of the Crown Pro   .    ^ ^ q{ Lords; ^ in

running costs of th^House ofcope yith an antxdP* has also teen allowed for ^taff

IB.   nationalised- jLgchjstrie^B^g- Electricity

^ on EFLs for the tisn Agreement was reached in bila^e-- Brltis Autnority

Boards,   BSC,   Post  Office, ^        t), Civil

Transport Group, British Shipbuilders Jjk

and London Regional Transport.   miHioT1

T9.   bmps &amp; sbps cant Minevorkers

r tne cost of    IP^*   T*nCy Payments Extra provision has teen made to c V6r       shipbuilding *e^&apos;Z^ Pension  Scheme.     The   figures for

Scheme are little changed.  ^

20-   bgc efl

flt  of  British Gas&apos; mi   mse tne benefit oi ^e planning total will  lose ^

^ter 1986-8T when it will he privatise . n1-on^fck

?39  ^


VJk       &apos;                                          the ksG settiemen _^ l9o6-o7,

T^tft^ior X9B6-B, -e agree* -    ^   c S,  level *       ^ ^

fo,  jBNWars  .as  -en   set   at*            ^ ol pro ^ ^er

recogn^  n o;an a^^ ^ ^

to he taken in next years                    ^ the ca=e.      = in schoo

Reserves than would otherwise ^           ^ ^   u^ ^ Qlfered has heen included f^he new v                element5 o (. A mutant not i r &apos;in all three yeg^J^^

on teachers&apos; conditi^R|^^rVlC   million

-2,250 2&apos;

22. Special Sales_cAj^^ ^ suggests

^   !  sales  ol the

X from special DaSeline W

The latest  forecast  of provided f&lt;* ^

that proceeds will he higher

  

n 1,000

23. Reserve ^Ske pr vided ior t0

 6V hillion and  B ^WV^ elsevhere. \    Reserves of   H3&lt; billion, changes, not^

.. ne. estimating,

\ cover contingencies, including million

I 2H.   .33 per cent ijigrease

1 IS 1968-89                                                                       3 3 per^^fS

\ total to increase ty    &apos; raI[m?Ml^

\ Revision is  de for the planning tota^ ^  individual *^

\ 1988-89,  compared with the baseline up

\ 2.5 per cen-t.


Provisions for the Department of Agriculture Fisheries and Food, SC0^SSnd ^ Wel5h  ffiGe  f ASricultural Development are included ln bouW^FF/IBAP baselines and the Scotland and Wales baseline.


							

				secret scorecard		fmillion	

?1		1986	-87	1987-88		1988-89	

		Baseline	agreed	Baseline	agreed       Baseline agreed		

		999,999	99,999	999,999	99999         999,999 99999		

		603	38	619	43	635	63

	2- ec	640	10	830	320	850	100

	3-  1bap/aff cap	1,277	272	1,304	334	1,337	336

	&apos; aff domestic	713	8	699	5	717	3

	5- forestry a #k	53	0	54	0	56	0

	6- trade/1	1,162	-13	980	12	1,004	-25

*	7- ecgd m 8- employment 9- transport		200 -74 27	-43 3,901 1,995	213 -207 33	-44 3,999 2,045	138 -125 52

	10.doe-psa			-128	0	-131	0

	h.lcd 12.home office 13-c1vil super	1,061		610 1,104	39 44	625 1,131	73 55

		1,114	65	1,226	86	1,257	147

	1j*-wales	1,708	-1	1,735	-1	1,779	-4

	15-n-ireland	4,464	53	^4,603	76	4,717	105

	16-chancellor&apos;s 1,825 &quot;-other llnc  ter &apos; consequences 1		163 170		169 170	1,888 406	143 205

	1b nat ind j|- Settled ao:  g s &amp; SRP						

		1,495 309	-4 194.	i.cn		1,299 ... . 326	-459 _ -50 .

				-39^	L^90	-400	400

	1&gt;la rel CURlUKAl 26,032		646	26,301 ^		26,959	-323

	OPE?iAL sales  e assets !3-reservf	-2,250	-2,250	-2,250		-2,250	-1750

	f&quot;J * increase		-1,250	7,000	-500	7,000	1000

	Jn 1988-89						-1627

						1,627	

	55-less double counting	-254		-247		-258	

*  	total agreed						

		52,50?	-1,675	53,724	-533	&quot;5^4-	-1543


			Annex C

	1986/87	1987/88	1988/89

- ej&lt;istlng Survey			

b v^L is:	18560	18859	19033

1. Tf^c

  Secretary of State for Defence initially proposed the following add^ions to baseline:

	^   bid S4^d:	+422	+595	+897

(i) (11) (Ui) (iv) (v)	lnflation adjusVA^ 241 &quot;tra C StS  f 128 A^ Forces Pay Review Body (AFPRfi) &gt;*Jk R **l Dockyards: redun-^f dancy and redundancy costs Dockyards: post- 0 c ntractorisation pension costs *   Ordnance plc 42 6Xternal financing limit 422		430 131 0 \ 595	536 134 0 35 0 705*

		+ 172	+345	+4^fi(W

MTSC 120 and the Secre%fjA 

Following discussions with the Group, n hAoelinTllU

* nn a settlement at baseline MTMk State for Defence reached agreement on a ^ ^ ^g mill|on

the three Survey years ( 18,560 million for 19   -    .       * ]fc

c r iQRft-89 including provj. ^ for 1987-88; and  19,033 million for 1988 m

the Falklands).

1988 89

*Not including  192 million Falklands costs,


^^^^gYgI^PMENT_^MINISTRATION

1986-87 1987-88 1988-89

x&quot;ting Survey baseline is 1296 1317 1350

^    The M^ ^rial Committee on Exports (EX(85)4th Meeting, Item 1) agreed

a soft loan mechanism was desirable to make Aid and Trade Provision (ATP) more f ]_ &apos;v-i

ex        exible and effective; and that decisions on how to meet the public

Su   n ltUre costs shc-^1 be taken in the context of the 1985 Public Expenditure

Qf .ey&quot;   EX COntemP^j^that funds would be diverted from the programmes interested n

^ ^ uePartments in order to minimise the net impact of the

Priority given tb^^^pn the public expenditure planning totals.

s ughthe SeCretary of state^feitreign and Commonwealth Affairs initially Survey lnCreaS6S in the aid pr^p^e of +60, +80 and +95 for the three

an,      years&gt; to maintain the re^^Kue of the bilateral aid programmes, nd also to fin

tne UK . nance the increase in multilateral aid programmes to which

accePted .C0Inmlt:t:ed    After discussion with MISC 120, the Foreign Secretary c sts of InCreaSed Provision of +21, +29 a^^-37.   The ODA element of the total .6        ATP soft loan facility w^wJl financed within the revised

Provision for the aid programme.

The costs of m ^5pL

busines Proposed soft loan facility, assuming additional

and the       ^ milUon in 1986-87 rising to  250 fl^i^k in 1988-89 as~you-       lowing two years, and meeting all additiona^^^ts on a pay-818, are estimated to be:

ECGD 1986-87 1987-88 1988-89

OuA 3   iO. 9

0ther ^ 3 10      ^ 20

this fa  .,    St6d DePartments have been asked to make contributions t&gt;S s faCllity of: W


tJLIL for the ECGD element in the

*^ke of these amounts, after proving for the ^

new facility, will he transferred to the        P representing the rem ^f the agreed increases in the overall axd p a net increJ^.n total public expenditure.

5-     The changes in ODA&apos;s baseline are:

	1986-87	1987-88	1988-89

	1296 21 1317	1317 29 1346	1350 37 1387


 H^ Annex E

lrar~^ARSlENTAL PROGRAMME )

Chief Secretary, Treasury initially sought a reduction in provision ^F^Jfast reactor research of -28,  -55, and -58 in each of the three ^   ~ years.    The Survey baseline for fast reactor is:

103 105 108

6   hief sAtfetary, Treasury subsequently reduced his bid for reduction^J^^0 in each of the Survey years.

e   ecretary^^^^te for Energy had aiready made cuts since 1983 in expenditure on the fast reactor programme of 22 per cent for 985/86, 37 per cent for 1986/87 and 42 per cent for 1988/89. In tl0n&apos; he has obj^gfc^y-ie United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority ) management to v^U%n the basis of a Trading Fund, which will

Int

ensifv t-v&gt;o ~

y tne pressures for a more commercial approach.    Against this

Aground the Secretary of State for Energy did not believe it was

Possible to l.

make the cuts proposei^&gt;y the Chief Secretary, Treasury.

3. Misc

and the Secretary of State for Energy reached agreement on

million per annum for^^PR%)f the Survey years from the W  le range of UKAEA activities. V2\

The costs of ^Si^W

CQn    . extending the Coal Firing SchTO^u^til June 1987 will be

n amed within the Departmental programme.


VmgOTHER

&gt;jU                                                  i2B6^87 1987^88 1988^89

848 &quot;0 882

wfey Baseline

MT4^.20 _20 -20 &quot;15

Recommendation

li)       New Town Asset Sales

fcfm -   the   chief    Secretary have

1. The   secretary    of    State   and   t        ^  ^  ^ q  NeW

agreed  to   increase   the   level   of   receip and

^?2P^k +-h     first   year q&apos;1u

Town   assets,   by K7l.million   in   tne increase

m&apos;U \ c    W1J--L a-i-LU

 40m  in  the two  subsequent years. provision shown

in  gross   expend iture^GPfcput   affecting   the nc above. ^^^^^

Local Environmental Services__(LE^i

1 -will allow capital allocations

2- The recommended       provis^will an ^   ^ get

^   local   authorities   for   the   other   services sufficient .

I! &quot;00  million  for  &quot; e^^T^.  *Y -al

to  minimise   the   risk   of   a   success* *^ allocations authorities on the&apos;basis of previous commitmen s

Win , - 4-vlCJ^^.-85 level-

Ui be no less than 70 per cent of ttlL^H^

Uxi)   Other Envi rnnmp.ntal Services

3- Provision for the large  scale Household Survey ta..been   .      MISC   120   recommends   that   it ^^d ^tte

111   is   subsequently   found   to   be   absolutely necMjrv standpoint of reform of local government finance.

The Urban Programme ^a^U.

4- The    Urban    Programme    has    not    been    considered liJ^C [2 &gt; Pending the outcome of the review of urban policy comm^s^ by the Cabinet.    Provision remains at baseline.


^J^L Annex G F^^nPJLMD SCIENCE

1986-87 1987-88 1988-89

Sur^^ellne 3418 3505 3593

c  cT^^local

authority current)

In their bilateral discussions, the Secretary of State for Education and ScienAtK^i the Chief Secretary, Treasury agreed the following Editions to baseline, in respect of mandatory student awards and (in the first two%^^ of transfers from other programmes to finance the

switch&quot; - the^toS^Lon of extra places in higher education to increase the numb^rjj^raduates and postgraduates in engineering and technology:

+28.5 +23.5 +8.0

The

ese figures also include a reduction of  1 million a year in funding f r the Economic and Social Research Council.

2. The

e   ecretary of State for Education and Science sought the following fUrther Editions above baseline =

UniVersities

Science +47 +49.: +69.5

Veil     h0rityCaPltal +?1 +71

Untary Sch o1 Repairs +8.5 +8.^^ +9.0

3% ^

120 and the Secretary of State for Education and Science reached greement on increased provision of  25 million for tl^tf^versities ^   science taken together in each of the Survey years^ftfck provision st Uld g  some way towards meeting the need for new equi^Qfl^ ^ ^   ating research activity, and stemming the scientific ^fc^L


\4&apos;       MISC 120 and the Secretary of State for Education and Science reached

Oagreement on allocations for local authority capital expenditure in -JL 1986/87 of  300 million.    This corresponded to additional provision Tj^r such expenditure of  27 million in 1986/87, with additions of  25 ^Jmiion for provision in the subsequent two years.    MISC 120 agreed

WOuld be  Pen to the Secretary  f St3te t0 flnd fr m Withln &apos;hese additions, provision in each year for voluntary school repairs to the extent necessary.

UP to anc^^uding 1987/88 fundi-., for the &quot;switch&quot; is shared among interestSA^tments.    The Department of Education and Science had already agr^^fcnrovide  4 million towards the cost of the switch ( 22 million) ^1|8/89.    MISC 120 agreed with the Secretary of State for Education an^CVnce that it would in principle be necessary, if the necessary room could&gt;not be found within the universities Programme, to reduce^rjWion for local authority capital expenditure in 1988-89 by up to  lFmillion to enable the &quot;switch&quot; to be funded.

The impact of these changes on the education and science baseline is as follows: fcCt

Blds already agreed 28.5 23^^\ 8,0

Sciehce and Universities    23 25 vAfc5

L Cal authority capital     27 25

  lk

80.5 73.5

New Ba

Seline 3498.5        3578.5 3651


^^^L^ Annex H

^^ANDj^ibrartes

^^Lk 1985/86       1986/87 1987/88

Th-e ^iJW

survey baseline is 332 342 351

ln their bilateral discussions, the Minister for the Arts and the Chief Secretary, Treasury agreed on changes of -7, -0.5, +4.0 over the three Survey years, to reflect a changed requirement for the new British Lfbrary^uilding and reductions in local authority capital e*penditure^M^

2.       T, ^^^k

  Minister for^fcArts had sought additions of -22, +23 and +23 in

each of the three Survey years.    He had sought additional provision in Aspect of the Arts &amp;uJk (+15, +15, +15), moderating the cost squeeze on the arts (+4^+5, +5) and national museuas and galleries (+3&gt; +3, +3).

3%

120 reached agreement witMinister for the Arts on increased Provision above baseline for the Arts Council of +14, +9 and +8. lnS into account agreements alr%5*^ached between the Chief retary, Treasury and the Minister^^^yie Arts, this agreement represents an addition to baseline of ^J^k5 and ~11 in each  f the tJee Survey years.    In the judgement of^^J^nister for the Arts, ^   s settlement should enable the GovernmeM tJkontain, in relation th        arts  the transitional problems arising froa the abolition of i(_e MetroPolitan Authorities; and, depending on the rate of inflation,

also enable the Arts Council to continue their regional strategv     tu \a

ine Minister for the Arts has assured the  wv that he Will m^kW

n t make a further additional bid in the 1986 pulAjkpenditure

tVey ln resPect of the impact of abolition on the Art^jj^il.

A&gt;       MISC 120 w

th as unable to aceep&apos;   any  increased provision in resrf^^f

 st squeeze on the arts or on the museums and galleries b&apos;fild pr grammes     Th m-

     j-ne Minister for the Arts accepted this position.   ^ |L

5-       Th ^

ihe impact of i-k

f , cnese changes on the Arts and Libraries baseline is as

tollows:


			

a ^5ii^ady agreed	-7	- 0.5	+4

	+ 14	+9	+8

^^^^^^^	+7	+8.5	+ 12

New baseline			

	339	350.5	363


^^W^^RspNAL_S0CIAL SERVICES			Annex I

MISC i204f^ u Recommendation	1986-87 14945 +250	1987-88 15622 +300	1988-89 16012 +600

***** as follow,:			

c^rFaiiviiianciai^^(cFs) (pps   --ctitione^ Pamii/p   mniStrati n V\ Pra itioner ServicesV^L	+157 +13 +80	+196 +14 +90	+374 +21 +205

For the Hrwc

k av^nb, it is expected that efficiency savings of 2 per cent will

made in 1986-87, releasing additional resources of  200 million. er savings will follow in fuXi^kyears.    But there will not be ^ufficient to cover the additional costs of the 1985 pay awards (which ^     u ed a significant element of restructuring), while responding also increased demand through demographi^^r ssure.    The increased Sl0n w111 allow an increase of 2 per cent in real terras in HCHS CUtrent pending in 1986-87.

2*      The add&quot;

itions for the FPS reflect the best estf^PTel of likely demand.

ne net

osts will however be reduced by planned increases in Prescript!

bill an&lt;* &lt;*enta&quot;1&quot; charges, and by further savings on the drugs

^e        ^e Planned Green Paper on primary health care is ^fcected to

a      t0 further control on this expenditure; and MISC 120 has identified Sigaificant savlng fQr 1988_89&lt;


^SOCIAL SECURITY

&gt;q*7/K8 1988/89 1986/87 *9s7/88

Sur^g^eiine (excluding  fi:m lc,cal amhority current expenditure)

x state ior Social Services and the l    In their bilateral discussions, the Secretary of State 10

? etc were needed as

Ch.ei S re r|ELr, agreed that additional administrate cests

follows:

Of.

They further agreed that there were large and unavoidable increases to be met, main &gt;

k j u  hpr take-up of benefits. They

because of changes in economic assumptions and higher xaKe v

c uld not agree, however, on the extent^hich these should be offset by savings

^5^^. .h- h.lateral discussions, and

irom within the social security programme^gT&apos;&quot;6

taking account of both savings previously agr^li ^^ther revision to t &lt; 1

^iKV  u       thP Snrvev baseline totalled

ln the light of the autumn economic forecast, the bids above the

+982

The Group felt it necessary to explore the scope for further policy^justments to

llVt, measures offset part at least of these additions.  They looked both to specie

&lt;;   nl^^^fity Review and ^so to savings already identified within the context of the boC1^ ^

*hich could be brought forward and implemented in earlier years.  They took as an ass^pt)on that the main measures of the Review would be implemented


N*.   The Secretary of State for Social Services has agreed to commit himself to finding ^Jollowing additional level of savings within the social security programme; m1sc ^M^ns with him in recommending them to the Cabinet

^ _91 -278

3-    The main souses of these savings are as follows

(&apos;)  No upratiflSwd benefit in Duly 19s6 but full uprating of child benefit in April 1987.

(&quot;)  A new drive agains^oJLsecurity fraud.

m Additional restrictions from early 19S6 of single payments for particular items ^ supplementary benefit recipientsJftticipation of the eventual abolition of ^ch payments and their replacement  fcscretionary payments from a cash limited social fund in 1988. ^^^^

Negotiations with the building societies to^^restrictions on mortgage ^payments in supplementary benefit cases from a S 1986 instead of from 1988 when the main review meaures are implemented.

^ Deleting provision for the abolition of the retirement P&lt;^^ earning ^ until April 1989.

(V1) A requirement for employers to take over from April 1987 paymeMJ^temity allowance on the same basis as Statutory Sick Pay. f


ft&lt;v ) mtroduction in 1987/88 oi se.ecuve provision to replace maternity and death

*    T^retary of State for Social Services has further agreed that, in order not to prejudice further collective consideration of the measures in the Social Security Review, the figure for the final year of the Survey period which is published following the Autumn Sta^fL should be shown as provisional only and Dependant on the final collective decisionlSLon his Review.  He has agreed to a figure of  45022 being ^own, ie an increaseGLeline of  380 million winch would be sufficient to f.nance a full 31/*% uprating in ti |r in line with the latest projection of the RPI. Since at the time of the AutumnlK^nt, the decision to defer implementation of the main review measures will not bTpublicly known, the same procedure will need to be applied to the second year of the Survey; although the figure for this year is in ^ imal not provisional and this is no fftthan a presentational device.


Annex K

^^pRIgm^SJWLY INDUSTRY

Th^Sk. 1986-87     1987-88 1988-89 Total

^^ing Survey

-1447 -1487 -1524 -4458

1   rp*

e electricity supply industry&apos;s initial bid was for additional Provision of  613 million over the three IFR years.    On 30 September a bid for^^further  466 million was tabled, reflecting a  Late bid

r m the\ t^ry&gt;    This took total extra provision sought to  1079 million over the period.    The increased bid of  466 million included

90 million ^^^e assumption that the Sizewell  pressurised water-reactor (PWR) w^^^p ahead;   130 million to enhance the industry&apos;s ability to endure another coal strike; an extra  55 million to

mPlete the AGR sr^^o^at Heysham and to improve the performance

Sa ety of AGRs mo^rTg%nerally; and additional capital expenditure

quired by the industry largely to meet requests for new supplies which

^        are growing with the economy.   The Secretary of State for ergy offered to secure savinc^^f  603 million against this bid, therefore sought the foll^^Jfchanges in baseline provision:

+ 191 -94 +379 +476

2*        MISC 120 r u

^ reached agreement with the Secretary of State for Energy on

 Howing further general savings on^^e^Unancing requirements 0f ^e electricity industry:

The -50 -50 -70 -170

thi   eCretary of State for Energy also offered - and ttJjSC 120 agreed

ca . W Uld be helpful - to seek rephasing of  50 mi^Jpf^f working

a   requirements from the first to the second IFR year. These   anSes produced the following revised bid:

+91 -94 +309 +306


lt seeraed increasingly doubtful that the Sizewell enquiry report Would be ready by the spring of 1986.   MISC 120 therefore agreed with ^J^W the Secretary of State for Energy that it would be realistic to ^^^ssume that the timetable for the Sizewell would slip a further ^PW3*&quot;*    This did not represent a change in policy on Sizewell, nor a ^p^ion that the project should be deferred by a further year. The ief Secretary, Treasury accepted that if, in the event consent to the construction of Sizewell was given before Autumn 1987 the resulting additional expenditure above baseline should be met from the Resejn^k   The savings resulting from the new working assumption at)out thMykng of sizewell are as follows:

Wm -60 -104 -66 -230

Th ^jjL

6 cuniulative elWajAnroduces changes in baseline as follows:

+w -198 +243 +76

The impact on baseline is:

**&quot;ing baseline _i44? _i524

Ne  baseline ^5KW

ne -1416        -1685 -1281 -4382

XL


Annex L

1986/87 1987/88 1988/89

^PVjsting survey

^^^e is 108 0 0

^ *       ^ (NI)

c        conducted a major review of water strategy last year.    The Sub-

ttee agreed it was important to maintain and strengthen pressures

116 Wat^J^borities for increased efficiency; and that there was ,i strong case

^^W^^reased investment in water services accompanied by ases in rewj^^^urns on assets employed in the industry.    It was gnised that ^^j^^Leveraent of these objectives would require

increases in the real level of water charges over a period

of years.         The S

mill   Cretary  f State f r the Environment bid for an addition of  33

to the EFL in 1986-87.    This was estimated to permit an average increase tn

Water charges of no mor^than 8i per cent for domestic consumers (\ ?fl^

woul Pei&quot; Cent leSS f r oChers) for 1986_87  which in his view

1n. consistent with a capital investment programme for the water

tha iU m3-Hion.    MISC 120 accept this.    Their view was

3 prlce increase of 8\ per clWsZfkd with the improved prospect ext year f

rh., ne general level of inflatTcBi^iter authorities would

bCHl be abl ^i^k.

with an &amp; ^ Undertake an expanding capital investment programme lower     Unchan ed EFL; MISC 120 would have beTiiJ^ared to accept a

increase together with a smaller investment programme. The Secretary Qf

Treas atate for the Environment and the Chief Secretary,

ry have aer  a (t/^ existing s subsequently that there should be AeJ^nge to the

for the     rV6y baseline for all three years.    The SecrefB^fl^ State

for an av   lronment and the Chief Secretary, Treasury also^tatffekto aim

87 to f .   rag6 lnerease in domestic charges of about 8 per ce\kS^ 1986-

take effg 1^^^^. in the - c    m the spring of  1986.    This involves some re^Vftan

&quot;ate of im V^P^ sought l Pr vement in the industry&apos;s financial performanca^^^L

by the u y    ^NI)*    The capital investment that can be undeHalJL

ater indu

need tr, w ustry in 1986-87, consistent with these decisions, will

u oe estimat

a ed in consultation with the water authorities.    But the


ecretary of State for the Environment will be seeking to ensure that it \kjkis not less than  885 million.

5-^Bfks

^|maecretary of State for the Environment notes that an average increase ?&quot;^ppestic water charges of about 8 per cent will require very careful PWsefitation when tne House of Commons is asked to approve the necessary Rate of Return Order after the autumn statement.

The Secretajp^of State for the Environment envisages a White Paper on   ater industry privatisation before Christmas, followed by a Bill in the 986 87 session providing for privatisation based on river basin uthorities (lj^^madly the present structure of the industry). The ^^^^^ ^^^^l

retary of St?^i^d the Chief Secretary, Treasury are agreed that the UPt ^inancial sJfffgcy for water authorities will necessarily have to reviewed as part^Bfc^rther work on privatisation, and that the

results of this will n^^%o be taken account in future public

expenditure decisions.



</content>
</cab>
