<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/116/0 images: 57-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVjBRNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1964CABINETTHE SCHOOL LEAVING AGEMemorandum by the Chief Secretary to the ; Treasury and &quot;Paymaster General      ;-.-.v\,-In his paper CP. (64) 1 the Lord President of the Council reports the viewof the majority of the Education and Research Policy Committee that the school leaving age should be raised to 16 at the turn of the decade. It is recognised in theLord President^ paper that the educational arguments do not all point in one way.In this paper I wish to develop the public expenditure aspects of the proposal.2.   The cost is assessed as follows: .(a) Capital investment of the order of  150 million (of which the building work would total about  115 million). ,(b) Net additional current expenditure of about  45 million a year. (But this estimate takes account of the fact that many of the additional teachersneeded would not be forthcoming initially; as this-position is corrected,the extra annual cost would become greater.).      ;(c) Indirect costs of nearly  20 million a year falling on the Exchequer and up to  13-5 million falling on the National Insurance Fund.(d) Loss of annual production of  150 million.Capital expenditure3. If the leaving age were to be raised &quot; at the turn of the decade &quot;, most, ifnot all, of the capital expenditure would have to fall in the late 1960s. The prospects for public investment in this period were examined in some detail (in relation to theChannel Tunnel) in the Chancellor^ paper E.P.C. (63) 24. This shows that in thenext four years the prospective situation is one of great pressure on resources andshortage of capital, with continuing need for fiscal action to restrain private consumption, and that no real easement can be expected thereafter. Indeed,investment in the late 1960s is rapidly becoming committed by the Government&apos;present decisions on housing, roads, higher education, hospitals, etc. Moreover,these are the very years in which the bulk of the expenditure on the ChannelTunnel would fall, if present plans were accepted; and the same is true of the costof decimalisation, if D-Day were in 1967. The conclusion reached in E.P.C. (63) 24was that public investment would in the aggregate be continuing to increase in1968-69 and 1969-70 at a high rate in relation to the growth in Gross national product.4. The scale of the capital expenditure required for the raising of the school leaving age (about  150 million) can be illustrated by the following alternative ways of allocating that amount of resources in public investment.  150 million (at present prices) is roughly the cost of any of the following:(i) the whole of the Channel Tunnel (i.e., including the.French as well as theUnited.Kingdom share intended to be roughly equal);(ii) the Victoria Line tube and another tube of the same magnitude;(hi) two years&apos; construction of motorways and trunk roads at the present rate;(iv) two new towns of about 50,000 people each;(v) six new universities of about 7,000 each, all with 100 per cent residential accommodation.CP. (64) 108th January, 19643738
confidential- 5. Another way of-considering the problem is to look at the cost in termsof the existing school building programme. This is designed to serve two main objectives, viz., to provide &quot; roofs over heads &quot; for increases and shifts in population and to improve and replace existing schools. The size and distribution of the &quot; roofsover heads &quot; part of the programme is largely dictated by circumstances outsidethe Departments&apos; control, so that any adjustments to the programme to help to accommodate the raising of the leaving age would have to fall on the&quot; improvements &quot; part. In order to raise the leaving age it would be necessary toprovide about 350,000 extra places in England and Wales (as well as about 50,000in Scotland). The current rate of &quot; improvements &quot; in the Ministry of education programme is equivalent to the provision of about 100,000 places a year. The capitalexpenditure for raising the leaving age is thus equal to 3-4 years&apos; building at thecurrent rate of&quot; improvements &apos;\Current expenditure6. The prospects for public expenditure as a whole are just the same as for public investment, indeed the increased public service investment will itself generateextra current expenditure. Thus the pressure on resources is likely to be as great hereas on the capital side.7. The annual cost to public funds of raising the school leaving age is put atsomething of the order of  75 million. This can be compared with the cost of thefollowing services:(i) wage-related sickness and unemployment benefits graduated at 35 per cent of earnings between  9 and  18 per week about  70 million a year(assuming 1963-64 earnings rates, 2\ per cent unemployment and12 months maximum duration of benefit);(ii) an additional 7s. 6d. per week for men and women at 70 about 70 million;(hi) total of next year&apos;s recurrent grants to universities through the university grants Committee just over  75 million (before allowing for Robbins);(iv) five years&apos; increase in hospitals&apos; current expenditure at the agreed annual rate about  70 million.Loss of production8. The effect of raising the school leaving age would be to keep about400,000 15-year-olds in school for an extra year. The loss of annual production onthis account has been roughly estimated at about  150 million, or \ per cent ofthe Gross National Product. In other words, at a time when the national resources are already certain to be heavily committed, we should be imposing a significantcheck on the growth of those resources, equal to about \ per cent of the gross national Product. It is true that the longer period of education might be expectedto result in higher productivity in later years; but this gain is by no means certainand cannot be quantified. Even if some such ultimate counter-balancing gain is assumed, there should be offset against it the earlier loss from the lower educationalstandards (especially in the shortage of teachers) which will be felt for some years.conclusions .   I would draw the following conclusions:(i) We are fast pre-empting the future growth of economic resources ahead,right into the 1970s.(ii) The raising of the school leaving age would represent a very substantialaddition to these commitments, both in the form of capital expenditurein the late 1960s and in continuing cost thereafter.(iii) Moreover, the raising of the age would result in that year in a significantcheck in the rate of growth of national production; nor would it be prudent on other grounds to assume a faster economic growth.J. A. B.-C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,8th January, 1964.

</content>
</cab>
