<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/116/0 images: 59-64</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1964CP. (64) 119th January, 1964CABINETMONOPOLIES, RESTRICTIVE PRACTICES AND RESALE PRICEMAINTENANCEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Industry, Trade, and regional development and President of the Board of trade the modernisation of Britain was the policy on which the present administration was formed just over two and a half months ago. The PrimeMinister elaborated this concept in his speeches during the Kinross by-election.It provided the major theme in The Queen&apos;s Speech. It has been accepted by thecountry as our dominant purpose. It is the criterion by which people judge so many of our policies. It will no doubt figure prominently in the forthcomingelection. It is right in itself. It can be a great electoral asset to us.2. It is abundantly plain that one of the key features in this policy must bea clear statement of the Governmenfs attitude towards Monopolies, Mergers,Restrictive Practices and Resale Price Maintenance.3. As my colleagues know, there have been discussions on a number of occasions during the past two years, both in the Economic Policy Committee andthe Cabinet, on proposals for new legislation dealing with these problems. no decisions have yet been reached.4.  We must now come to a conclusion on these matters.5.   Certain factors have been moving steadily in our favour in this field:(a) There is strong public support for the Governmenfs policy of growth,expansion of the economy and modernisation of the country.(b) There is growing impatience with the continuation of the harmful aspectsof Monopolies, Mergers, Restrictive Practices and Resale price maintenance.(c) There is general agreement about the economic advantages of action inthese fields. Even the political objections to the removal of Resale price maintenance appear to be decreasing.(d) The Consumer Council has come out strongly in opposition to theretention of Resale Price Maintenance.(e) There is now a more general appreciation, demonstrated in the meetingof the National Economic Development Council on the 8th January,of the need to take every action possible to prevent increases in prices and indeed to reduce them.In brief, the political climate for action is more favourable than it has beenhitherto.6.   On the other hand, time is against us for the following reasons:(a) The Governmenfs apparent indecision over a number of years isattracting increasingly adverse comment. This is weakening theposition of the administration and can only be stopped by an effectiveParliamentary statement.Copy No.643745ATHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
(b) The second reading debate of Mr. Stonehouse&apos;s Private Member&apos;s Bill to ^abolish Resale Price Maintenance takes place on the 17th January, fglWe must be able to state our own policy before that debate.(c) The Leader of the Opposition is seeking an early debate on the recently published report of the Monopolies Commission on the supply of electrical equipment for motor vehicles. The history of the Commission^enquiry into that case and their recommendations on it, which includethe abolition of Resale Price Maintenance, underline the weaknesses ofthe existing law on Monopolies and Restrictive Practices. We shall behard put to it to meet the criticism of for example the lengthof time this enquiry took, or our lack of power to implement its recommendations, unless we can. show that we mean to deal with the defects in the law.7. In answer to Parliamentary questions I have promised to make a statementof Government policy soon. Recent developments mean that we must agree now on our policy and on what is to be said in Parliament when it re-assembles.8. I have, therefore, taken the opportunity since coming to the Board ofTrade of looking with a fresh eye at these problems and at the many studies whichhave been made of them. I have set out in the attached annex my own views and proposals. We need only concern ourselves now with the broad issues of policy.If we can get these settled the details can be filled in later.9. I have deliberately brought together proposals for these four specificitems in order to cover as wide a field as possible. This should demonstrate that measures affecting large concerns are being promulgated just as effectively asthose which may impinge on small businesses. I am sure that we must not only be fair but must be seen to be fair.10. I believe these proposals add up to a comprehensive and defensiblepolicy. There is nothing doctrinaire about it and it is based on some years of careful study. It is, in my view, an essential element in our policy of modernisation and promotion of efficiency generally. Its announcement will counter effectively anumber of current well-founded criticisms, and will underline our intention to convert all sectors of the economy to more up-to-date attitudes and methods.11. The preparation and introduction of the legislation foreshadowed here onMonopolies and Restrictive Practices will clearly take time. Legislation in the lifetime of this Parliament is out of the question. But I think that we ought tomake our intentions immediately clear by the publication of a short White paper on Government policy.12. Resale Price Maintenance is a different matter. It is highly topical, itdoes not require a long technical Bill, and if my colleagues accept my generalpolicy recommendation I think we should undertake to introduce legislation this session to make the practice illegal. The promise of Government legislation is,indeed, almost the only defensible ground for blocking Mr. Stonehouse&apos;s Bill.13. Past discussions have revealed some differences of view on the economic aspects of these problems. But even where there has been agreement economicallythere have been differences of view on the political implications of the proposals put forward and these still exist. I am now giving consideration to the points,both economic and political, which were raised by my colleagues at the economic policy Committee&apos;s discussion, and I hope to circulate a further paper on thesebefore the Cabinet meets. We now find ourselves, however, dealing with theproblems at a late stage of this Parliament. It might be more convenient again to defer action on them until a later date. If that were to be done, it would benecessary to set out our policy in an election manifesto and some of these problems would become issues at the election. But even if we wish to deferdecisions again until the manifesto, the events I have listed will not allow us todo so.14. Let us, therefore, seize all the advantage we can from the fact thatthis will be seen as a bold and courageous step fully in accord with our theme ofthe modernisation of Britain.
: 15.   I accordingly seek the agreement of my colleagues to:(i) The-policies and proposals I have set out for dealing with Monopolies,Mergers and&apos; Restrictive Practices in the fields of goods and services.(ii) A statement in Parliament on Wednesday, 15th January, setting out our-    broad policies on these matters, including an announcement that theGovernment will introduce legislation this Session to make the practice,     of Resale Price Maintenance illegal.(hi) The early: publication of a White Paper amplifying my statement toParliament in respect of other measures covered in the Annex to this paper.E. H.Board of Trade, S.W.1,9th January, 1964.AnnexMONOPOLIES, MERGERS AND RESTRICTIVE PRACTICESI am satisfied that the present law needs to be strengthened and extended invarious directions,Monopolies2. I am sure that our present &quot; neutral&quot; and uncommitted approach tomonopoly is fundamentally right. We ought not to introduce into the law anypresumption that monopoly or bigness is in itself bad. Optimum efficiency of operation may demand large plants, costly research and highly developed marketingtechniques. Units must be large enough to raise the necessary capital for takingrisks. Large-scale production may be necessary to compete abroad.3. There are nevertheless occasions where the public and the government need to know how a monopoly is operating in case intervention is necessary. I am satisfied that such inquiries are best carried out by an administrative tribunallike the Monopolies Commission. The changes I propose are intended to makethe Commission more effective, to give it greater authority, and to enable it towork much more quickly than at present.4. First, the Commission should themselves have the responsibility forinstituting inquiries into &quot; monopolies &quot; defined broadly, as at present, as controlof at least one-third of the market. All the difficulties we have had over the years in deciding which &quot; monopolies &quot; to refer to the Commission convince me thatthese investigations should be initiated by an independent body.5. The Government must of course continue to be responsible for deciding whether action should be taken on the findings of the Commission, but their statutory powers should be made more fully effective. Our present powers are quite inadequate. They were originally intended for use principally againstrestrictive trading agreements which now come within the province of the restrictive practices Court. Experience has shown that many of the ways in which theCommission may find that a monopoly is acting against the public interest cannotbe dealt with under these powers. I have, for example, no power to enforce someof the recommendations made by the Commission in their recent report on electricalcomponents for motor cars, or in their report on wallpaper which I shall shortly belaying before Parliament.6. For the extreme but very rare case, we should have powers to compelfirms to divest interests or even to require the break-up of a monopoly, subjectto appropriate Parliamentary safeguards.3745
7.   The Monopolies Commission must also be enabled to work more quickhjfo..Their numbers will need to be enlarged so that they can work in small groups, and^an enlarged and strengthened secretariat will be essential. In short, we should havea new body with a new name.8. In streamlining the Commission and its procedure we should hope to beable to meet the criticism of industry that the Commission, by going into too muchdetail, forces them to spend disproportionate time and money defending their operations over a wide field. We must also try to meet the complaint that industryfrequently feel that they are in the dark about the case they have to meet.Mergers9.   The present law makes no provision for inquiry into mergers or takeoversas such.10. Some mergers are positively beneficial to the economy. Withoutimpairing competition they produce stronger units, economies of scale, bettermanagement and better research. The last thing we should dp is to place anyobstacle (even an investigation) in the way of such mergers or indeed of the vastnumber whose economic effects are neutral.11. There is, however, a minority of mergers which may have harmfuleffects. These are mergers which seem likely to result in a significant reduction of competition in a market of substantial significance.12. I have reached the conclusion that we ought to make it possible for thenew Monopolies Commission to take the initiative to investigate mergers of thepotentially damaging kind which I have mentioned in cases where they would lead to or strengthen monopoly.13. If this were done I would propose that the legislation should give theCommission guidance on the considerations which would help them to decide ina particular case where the public interest lay considerations such as efficiency,technical and technological advance, industrial growth and competitive power in international trade.14. I think that it would be wrong to require a merger to be held up whileit was being investigated. If prior consent to merging were necessary, desirablemergers might well be frustrated. If, however, on the basis of the Commission^report, the Government took the view that no action short of the undoing ofthe merger would safeguard the public interest, this would have to be broughtabout, if necessary by compulsion, and powers to effect this would therefore berequired. The effect of having them might well be that they would never have tobe used.Restrictive Trade Practices15. The present judicial approach to restrictive trade practices is now generally accepted. The Restrictive Trade Practices Act has strengthened the economy by leading to the abandonment of many restrictive practices and thus to more competitive trading conditions. We certainly cannot afford to weaken the Act to meet industry&apos;s desire for some easier grounds of defence, and experience has shown that the Act needs to be amended to deal with certain loopholes whichare bringing it into disrepute.16. The most important of these is the &quot;information agreement&quot; anagreement between firms to exchange information about prices and possibly othermatters. The potentially undesirable character of some information agreements isnow indisputable. The Registrar of Restrictive Trading Agreements has drawn attention to this deficiency in the law in a published Report, and it is emphasisedby the Monopolies Commission^ recommendation in their latest Report that anagreement of this kind between the manufacturers of batteries should be broughtto an end.17. I propose that information agreements should be brought within thescope of the Act and that several other loopholes should be blocked. We shall ofcourse take care not to obstruct harmless or even beneficial exchanges of informationbetween firms.18.  There are a number of other relatively minor respects in which the Actrequires amendment.
JjsrvicesW 19. In a modern economy the services sector becomes increasingly important.It is quite as necessary to keep costs down and do away with wasteful restrictive practices in this field as in the industrial sector. I believe that it is wrong in principlethat there is no legislative provision for monopolies and restrictive practices in thefield of services.20. It would not, however, be right or practicable at the first stage to treatservices in the same way as goods throughout the legislation on restrictive practices and monopolies. Until we have more experience in this field we cannot say whetherrestrictive practices in the supply of services must necessarily be presumed to be contrary to the public interest, or whether the considerations with which the law has provided the Restrictive Practices Court for judging restrictions on the supply ofgoods would be appropriate to services. Before the establishment of the monopolies commission, we were equally in the dark as to the precise effect of restrictive practices in the field of supply of goods, but a series of investigations carried out bythe Commission provided a solid background of factual information in the lightof which it became possible and appropriate to set up the Restrictive Practices Court.21. I think that we should now adopt broadly the same pragmatic approach to services. We should take powers to enable us to refer to the Monopolies commission for investigation particular services or particular restrictive practices in the field of services. Monopoly situations or mergers could also be referred. We should of courseneed powers to deal with any mischief they might find.22. I know that some of my colleagues feel some hesitation about the wisdomor the expediency of embarking on investigations into some services for instance,the professions. But my proposal would avoid this difficulty, because we should keepin our own hands the initiative in instituting inquiries.Resale Price Maintenance23. To give continued sanction to resale price maintenance is incompatible with our general economic policy of encouraging effective competition and keepingcosts and prices down. There are vocal pressure groups who defend the practice.Experience in countries which have got rid of resale price maintenance, and inthe grocery trade here where the practice has largely disappeared, suggests thatthe fears expressed about the consequences of its abolition are unfounded; to forbid the practice would not endanger outlets or services which are meeting a genuine public demand. I discount entirely the argument that resale price maintenance is of value to consumers in upholding a higher standard of service.What resale price maintenance means is that the customer is paying for serviceswhether he wants them or not and whether or not they are supplied.24. Abolition would have obviously beneficial effects. The practice keepsdistributors&apos; margins up to the level required for profitability by those with thehighest costs, and so weakens the incentive to find and apply more efficientmethods of distribution. It must result in a less than fully economic use of resources.Few disinterested authorities question that abolition would lead overall to price reductions. All in all, the economic case for abolition is overwhelming.25. If we are satisfied on this, we should have the courage of our convictions,and make resale price maintenance illegal. This would mean that it would be a statutory offence for a supplier to impose a condition as to resale price whensupplying goods to a distributor. A comprehensive prohibition of this kind would lead to the immediate ending of resale price maintenance, would secure themaximum economic benefit, and would be more defensible than any half-wayhouse.26. We should stand firm against proposals for exceptions. It is natural thattrades committed to the practice of resale price maintenance should fall back, whenit is threatened, on the argument that they are special cases. I do not believe thatthere is any trade to which the general objections to resale price maintenance donot apply. We must therefore resist special pleas and act in the general economic interest of the community.
27. Moreover, on examination the suggestions sometimes made forprocedure for authorising exceptions present almost insuperable problems. TWrarguments from special circumstances are basically so weak that if one tradequalified for special treatment it would be impossible to prevent others fromjumping on the band wagon. The proposal that the Restrictive Practices Court orthe Monopolies Commission should examine requests for exemption means inpractice that the tribunal would have to decide the matter case by case, sincevirtually every trade would apply for exemption. Resale price maintenance would,therefore, effectively continue for an indefinite period.28. Resale price maintenance could be ended by a short though obviouslycontroversial Bill.

</content>
</cab>
