<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/116/0 images: 99-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS (GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. January 1964CP. (64) 24 Copy No.28th January, 1964CABINETBRITISH SUGAR corporation memorandum by Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food have been asked by the Economic Policy-Committee (E.A. (64) 2sp Meeting)to put to my colleagues my proposals for dealing with the difficult problem ofour relations with the British Sugar Corporation (B.S.C.).2. The JB.S.C. is in form a public company set up in 1936 by amalgamation of all the existing beet processing enterprises. But since 1939 it has never operated on an ordinary commercial basis. At present the shareholders get a dividend of  per cent on their original capital of  5 million (which is in practice guaranteedwhatever the trading results of the company), take no commercial risks, and yetare the legal owners of assets worth  17-J million in the books, and with a,currentinsured value of over  60 million. The dividend cannot be increased without theconsent of Ministers. The shareholders were acquiescent until about 1960. since then they have been pressing for higher returns.on their investment. The presentposition is obviously untenable.3. The Labour Government intended nationalisation but never got aroundto it. The present set-up was constructed in great haste in 1956 to enable us todecontrol sugar. Jn 1961 -we considered a -scheme for converting the existingordinary shares into preference shares and transferring the equity into public hands.But this rather smacked of nationalisation, and in any case it was difficult :to finda basis for the conversion acceptable to both the Government and the shareholders.Since 1960 I have had each year to refuse to agree to an increase in the dividend.The shareholders are increasingly restless, and the Board of Directors increasinglyuncomfortable. The time has come when something definite must be done. In fact,we were only able to hold the position with the Board and the shareholders atthe annual meeting last August because the Economic Policy Committee had, agreed in.principle to a reorganisation. I was therefore able to authorise the Chairman ofthe Board to say that the Government andthe Board were working on new financial arrangements which would come into force on 1st April, 1964, and which wouldenable the Government to cease controlling the dividend (E.H (63) 24th Meeting).4. We have now reached agreement on these new arrangements with the Boardof the Corporation. These new financial arrangements are what I am now proposingwe should implement. They would put the B.S.C. on a basis comparable as far aswe can see to that of sugar processing industries operating on a commercial basis.5. Broadly speaking, we have negotiated a formula fixing the price which theCorporation could afford to pay for beet on a commercial basis. The price will be varied with changes in world sugar prices, and to a limited extent with changes inby-product prices and with any general inflation in the United Kingdom. (The first two factors are common form in other countries in contracts for purchasing sugar beet or sugar cane: and some protection against inflation is essential if the formulais not to require constant revision.) Other risks will be borne by the Corporation.These are real and substantial, as can be seen by applying the agreed formula to theresults of the last two years. In 1961-62 the B.S.C. would have made a profit of 1 million; in 1962-63 of  2-3 million. (The &quot; target &quot; figure is about  1-8 million representing about the same rate of profit per unit as Tate and Lyle, the sugarrefiners, make on their output.)3833
6. In future therefore the payments to the B.S.C. will represent onlyJtedifference between this commercial price of beet and the guaranteed price to farnfPswhich they pay on our behalf. In effect they will be taking all or nearly all the risks which would normally be undertaken by a commercial firm processing sugar beet.Their profits will vary with the commercial efficiency with which the enterprise isrun. There will therefore no longer be any reason for Government control, of theirdividends or share structure.7. My main concern was how to defend ourselves against the charge that wewere handing over to shareholders unfettered control over millions of pounds of assets built up since 1939 by public support without any real contribution orrisk-taking by the shareholders. The B.S.C. have now offered to make a capital reconstruction an integral part of the new arrangements. The present capital is  million  1 shares. The published reserves of the B.S.C. are however nearly afurther  10 million. The Board propose that the issued capital should be increasedby 5 million  1 shares; 2\ million would be distributed to existing shareholders asa 1 for 2 bonus issue; a &quot;further 2\ million would be issued free to the statutorySugar Board which (since 1956) has been making payments to the B.S.C. out ofwhich its capital modernisation programme has been financed. The Sugar board would thus acquire 25 per cent of the equity of the B.S.C. (and of course 25 percent of all future profits which would redound to the benefit of consumers). Inaddition, the Treasury have since 1936 had a holding which would represent11 per cent of the enlarged equity capital.8. I believe this will provide us with an adequate defence against any chargeof a &quot; give-away &quot; to shareholders. And in view of the wide degree of government support for all sections of the sugar industry in Britain, I think there can be no real objection to a stake of this order in the B.S.C. being vested in the statutorySugar Board.9. Of course the shares will certainly be valued higher as a true equity than as a virtually fixed interest stock. In 1962 the  1 shares stood at about 25s. (not much over their value as a fixed interest stock). Once shareholders realised thatthe dividend was not fixed (but only controlled by Ministers) the price rose toabout 30s.; and later to 40s. It has now dropped back to 35s. A recent analysisby the Investors Chronicle of the value of the B.S.C. shares on the assumptionthat they made profits of the same scale as we are envisaging in the new arrangements put them at about 50s. (assuming a 10 per cent dividend and a yield of about 4 per cent). If 25 per cent of the equity is to be given to the Sugar board the value of the remaining shares would, on that basis, be under 40s. The Boardof theB.S.C. intend to indicate that the dividend will in fact be 8 per cent in 1964and not more than 9 per cent (depending on results) in 1965. There would therefore be no rational justification for a price much higher than the present one.The B.S.C. financial advisers consider the true value to be below 35s. (All thesefigures are based on the existing shares ignoring the watering of the capital by the bonus issue.)10. The position of the sugar beet growers will not be affected. They willcontinue to be assured of the guaranteed price fixed at the Annual Review. the permitted acreage will also be settled by the Government and the B.S.C. will be under an obligation to buy it at the guaranteed price. The present factory capacity is fully adequate to deal with the amount of home produced sugar for which a market can be found in Britain.11.  By these changes we shall gain the following advantages:(a) we shall dispose of the constant pressure on us from the shareholders andthe Board for higher dividends;(b) we shall end a situation in which every important aspect of the B.S.C.&apos;operations (capital programme, level of profits, dividends, etc.) is determined by the Ministry of Agriculture and the Treasury;(c) we shall encourage the B.S.C. to become as commercially efficient as it isalready technically efficient.12. The procedure would be to tell the B.S.C. that we will approve these arrangements for submission to their shareholders. They intend first to consult the institutional shareholders informally; and then to put them formally to allshareholders. If the shareholders approve I will lay the necessary Statutory Ordersbefore Parliament in March. (In due course we ought to amend the Sugar Act, 1956;but for the moment we can get by without legislation.)
/jgjftj 13. I recognise the difficulties of presentation. But what is the alternative? Ifw&amp; simply tell the Board of the B.S.C. that we cannot accept the scheme because it is too favourable to shareholders, I am quite convinced that the Board (both the.Ministers appointees and the other Directors) will resign. We shall probably find itimpossible to get anyone (certainly anyone of standing) to take it on. The dissidentshareholders will probably succeed in electing their own leaders to the Board, sincethe big investors will not want to take sides in this struggle. Although theGovernment-appointed Chairman would have a veto in the Board of Directors, wehave no veto in shareholders meetings. It is not impossible that a resolution towind up the Company and distribute the assets might be passed in spite of theTreasury votes; and the only thing we could do would be immediate legislation.14. There are certainly big presentational problems in the scheme we have worked out. But to do nothing will equally involve large and real problems.Moreover, every year which passes makes the prospect of any solution short ofstraight nationalisation more difficult as  1 million a year is added to the B.S.C.assets. I am sure that to act now on the lines I propose will be by far the better course even on a short-range view.C. S.Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food,27th January, 1964.

</content>
</cab>
