<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/116/0 images: 119-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL1171(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HSR BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CP. (64) 32 COPY NO.4th February, 1964\CABINETSTATEMENT ON DEFENCE, 1964Memorandum by the Minister of defence i attach, for the approvel of my colleagues, a draft of statement on Defence for 1964.Ministry of Defence, S. W. 14th February, 1964
STATEMENT ON DEFENCE:
/STATEMENT ON DEFENCE


CONFIDENTIAL PROOFSTATEMENT ON DEFENCE1964Presented to Parliament by the Minister of defence by Command of Her majesty february 1964LONDONHER MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY office price     S.   d. net
For the financial year 1964-65 Parliament is being asked to grant for the Defence Services the net sum of as follows: ,   Central Defence Vote ...     ...     ,.j     ...     ...Naval Service..................Army Service   ......      ...      .........Air Force Service      ...............
120STATEMENT ON DEFENCE 1964CONTENTSPageIntroduction  ...      ...      ...Basis of Defence PolicyIndependent British DeterrentNuclear Co-operation in N.A.T.O.Mixed-Manned Force        .;.Arms Across the Sea ...Military Commitments in EuropeMilitary Commitments ElsewhereFinance        ...      ......THE ROYAL NAVYIntroduction.........The Fleet      .........Education      .........Naval Manpower: NumbersAccommodation      ......The Navy and Industrial ManagementStreamlining the Navy&apos;s Shore organisation the Royal Naval Scientific ServicesCivil Staff.........Fleet Activities        .......FinanceAnnex A Strength of the FleetAnnex B H.M. Ships disposed ofTHE ARMYOperations    .........Training        .........Weapons       .........Manpower     .........Works and AccommodationAdministration        ......Finance        .........Annex A Recruiting Results 1960-63
page the ROYAL AIR FORCEIntroduction...............Operational Commands of the Royal Air ForceService ManpowerCadet ForcesCiviliansOrganisationWorks ...MeteorologyFinance...Annex A Defence (Air) Estimates 1964-65Annex B Combined Royal Air Force and Civilian Strengths 1958-64Annex C Strength of the Royal Air Force 1958-64    ......CIVIL defence Statistics 1964-65
INTRODUCTIONCentral Organisation for defence. The year 1964 will see a major development in the organisation for defence: the setting up of a unified Ministry of Defence, with authority and responsibility vested in a single Secretary of State for Defence. The plan was described in a command paper last July (Cmnd. 2097). The arrangementsfor the new organisation are now far advanced, and subject to the passage ofthe necessary legislation it will come into being on 1st April, 1964. TheGovernment believe that it will greatly help the achievement of a unifieddefence policy and the efficient and economical provision of our militaryforces.2. Within the new Defence organisation major Defence policy will be formulated centrally, under the authority of the Secretary of State for defence. In order to achieve an organisation in which Defence, rather thansingle Service, considerations will be paramount, the Naval, General and AirStaffs, together with the Central Defence Staffs, will be incorporated in asingle Defence Staff. It will work in close collaboration with a DefenceScientific Staff and a Defence Secretariat in which staffs of the presentMinistry of Defence and the present Service Departments will be integrated.All these staffs will be accommodated together in the Whitehall MainBuilding. of the unified Ministry. This will facilitate team work betweenmilitary, scientific and civil administrative staffs to achieve balance betweenpolitical, military, scientific, technical, financial, and economic factors in defence planning. The partnership between the staffs concerned will ensurethat all relevant facts on which major decisions must be based are fully andaccurately presented. In particular, under the new organisation the DefenceScientific establishment will be working as a single scientific service, exceptin those cases where their work relates immediately to the requirements of asingle Service.3. The Secretary of State will delegate to the Ministers of Defence forthe Royal Navy, for the Army, and for the Royal Air Force much of his responsibility for the day-to-day management of the Services. Ke will thus be free to devote the time required to major policy questions and the dangers of the over-centralisation of administrative detail will, it is hoped, be avoided. At the same time the central staffs have been strengthened for anew drive, with the staffs responsible for the management of the Services,to rationalise administrative practices wherever possible.BASIS OF DEFENCE policy. In the Statement on Defence for 1962 the basic objectives of Britain&apos;defence policy were described as:  (a) to maintain the security of this country ;(b) to carry out our obligations for the protection of British territoriesoverseas and those to whom we owe a special duty by treaty orotherwise ;5
(c) to make our contribution to the defence of the free world and theprevention of war in accordance with the arrangements we have with individual countries and under collective security treaties.5. The keystone of this policy is the prevention of war. If we ana our allies fail to prevent major war, none of the other objectives can be attained.Nuclear weapons are so devastating that, unless we prevent them from being used, we shall not be able to secure the homeland or carry out our obligations to those who rely on us. Yet, until true disarmament becomes a reality,it is the overwhelming power of these very weapons and the determination of the nations not to proyoke their own destruction that keep the peace.1964 will be the nineteenth year in which this truth has been demonstrated ;and in the present state of the world no other realistic policy is apparent.Early and provident fear, as Burke said, is the mother of safety.INDEPENDENT BRITISH DETERRENT   -6. It is the Governmenfs policy not only to contribute forces to the mainstrategic deterrent, but to maintain an independent British deterrent. Forthe present V-bombers continue to be used for this purpose and, as announced in Cmnd. 1915, their role will in due course be taken over by a force of Polaris submarines.7. Even a small number of Polaris submarines would possess immensedestructive capacity. To suggest that the independent deterrent might be abandoned in the interests of non-dissemination overlooks the fact that ifthere were no power in Europe capable of inflicting unacceptable damage on a potential enemy he might be tempted if not now then perhaps atsome time in the future to attack in the mistaken belief that the UnitedStates would not act unless America herself were attacked. The V-bombersby themselves are, and the Polaris submarines will be, capable of inflictinggreater damage than any potential aggressor would consider acceptable.For this reason the British nuclear forces make a unique contribution to themain deterrent. In keeping these forces the Government is not seeking to pursue and enforce policies independent of its Allies&apos; (though it would beirresponsible to discount all such possibilities in all possible political circum-stances of the future) : it is maintaining a possibly crucial thread in the deterrent fabric.8. The Polaris submarines will be built in British yards and, although the delivery system is American, the nuclear warheads will be British and free from all control by any other power. At Nassau the Government of theTJ.S.A. agreed to make Polaris missiles available &quot; on a continuing basis &quot;.NUCLEAR CO-OPERATION IN N.A.T.O.9. Apart from providing for the continuance of the indepedent Britishdeterrent, the Nassau Agreement recorded the conclusion that the provisionof Polaris missiles to the United Kingdom by the United States &quot; created anopportunity for the development of new and closer arrangements for theorganisation and control of strategic Western defence and that such arrangements in turn could make a major contribution to political cohesionamong the nations of the Alliance &quot;. As a start, it was agreed that some
122part of the nuclear forces already in existence should be subscribed toN.A.T.O.; and we have fulfilled our part of this undertaking by assigningthtfjaj^-bombers to N.A.T.O. The Government have reserved the righttoCfier the use of these forces at discretion if they decide that supremenational interests are at stake. The Polaris submarines, when they becomeoperational, will be assigned in the same way and subject to the samereservation.10. Other developments making for increased cohesion in the Alliancehave been the appointment of Allied officers to a Joint Strategic Targettingand Planning Section at Omaha in the United States, the formation of theN.A.T.O. Nuclear Committee and the appointment of a Nuclear Deputy tothe Supreme Allied Commander, Europe.MIXED-MANNED FORCE11. In the interest of cohesion in N.A.T.O. the United States have also proposed the creation of a mixed-manned force of 25 surface-ships witheight Polaris missiles each. This project is being studied in all its aspects and possible variants by a Working Group in Paris, assisted by Military and LegalSub-Groups. As announced by the Prime Minister on the 1st October, theGovernment decided to take part in these discussions without commitment.The Governments concerned have not yet decided whether to create such a force, but it has been decided to make an experiment in mixed-manning foreighteen months in an American warship. H.M.G. have agreed to participate,again without commitment, in the experiment because the government believe that, if their representatives are to play an effective part in the discus-sions about the creation of the force, some first-hand experience of theprogress of the experiment is needed.ARMS ACROSS THE SEA12. Our nuclear contribution is vital as an insurance for the future indeed, as an assurance that we shall have a future. Our present well-being,and that of our friends throughout the world, depends in large measureupon the skill and efficiency of our conventional forces. The term is not anapt one. As the events of recent months have shown, our forces must beanything but conventional if they are to meet the varied and ever-changingdemands made upon them. The fact that every demand has been met,that there has been a quick and effective response to every challenge, isproof enough that our three fighting Services have broken the conventionalmoulds and transformed themselves into a single swift-moving, flexible,almost infinitely adaptable instrument of defence policy.MILITARY COMMITMENTS IN EUROPE13. A symbol of N.A.T.O.&apos;s unity is the presence of troops of many countries in the area of the Central front, where all countries are makingdetermined efforts to meet requirements, and where continuing progress is made with improving the equipment of the troops. Their readiness to do so and their will to resist have undoubtedly been potent factors in preventing aggression and in changing the climate of the Wesfs relationswith Russia.  The need to maintain and improve the conventional forces
in Europe was emphasised in the statement made by the late president kennedy and Mr. Macmillan after the meetings in the Bahamas.14. A large part of our naval, land and air forces are availabjjf )rthe support of N.A.T.O. In particular we have assigned to KATxCO.the V-bombers and our tactical air forces and earmarked the greater partof our naval forces and maritime air forces for assignment. We have 51,350troops in Germany. We are striving to bring this number up to 55,000as required under the Brussels Treaty, although our efforts are affected bythe continuing commitments in other parts of the world which are referredto below.MILITARY COMMITMENTS ELSEWHERE15. We have said that the keystone of Britain&apos;s defence policy is theprevention of war. In Europe this means, above all, the prevention of nuclear war and insurance against the other types of armed conflict whichmight lead directly to that catastrophe. Further afield the ultimate objective is the same but the emphasis is different because the nature of the immediatethreat, to ourselves and our friends, is different. In Asia and in Africa, in allthe under-developed regions, there are powerful pressures for change, and itis for us both an interest and a responsibility to help it to take place with aminimum of violence. This is in our interest because violence in all its formsis contagious and can quickly threaten the health of our whole society; itis our responsibility because in so many parts of the world formerly depen-dent states look to us for help in establishing themselves and making theirown way in peace.16. Nowhere is this more true than in the Far East, where the threat andactuality of violence are acute and where we deploy very substantial forces.Our interest (with that of our allies) in the stability of South-East Asiaremains; our responsibility, especially for helping Malaysia to establish and consolidate its independence, has made increasing calls upon our resourcesthrough the past year. Throughout the area we can expect no immediatereduction of our commitments. The speed and effectiveness with which wecan meet them have been increased firstly by the build up of our airliftand sealift capacity, and secondly by the creation and development of uni-fied command in the Far East; it will be increased further by the currentchanges in the central organisation for Defence.17. Unification of command is working well in the Middle East. Inno other theatre are our Defence problems more complex. Flexibility inthe deployment and use of limited forces is of paramount importance in an area where political change is continuous and not always predictable. in africa, where we had looked for a steady diminution of our militaryresponsibilities, new demands of a delicate and difficult kind have beenplaced upon us. We are far from journey&apos;s end; the most difficult partis ahead; but one performance so far has given fresh heart to our friendsboth in Africa and elsewhere.18. As. in Africa, so in the more central regions of the Middle East,we can look for no immediate relief from our Defence burdens. We haveobligations, which we shall meet, to our allies in the Central.Treaty Organi-sation; to Kuwait and to other states in the Persian Gulf which desire toretain their associations with us ; and to the South Arabian Federationincluding Aden.
19. When added to the burdens we bear in other parts of the world, thetask of supporting, or standing ready to support, our friends in the Middlear*vii-ar ^ast *s a neavv one&apos; DOth militarily and financially. The ability toresfSad quickly, in sufficient force, over great distances and to cope with harshand testing conditions of climate and terrain is not easily or cheaply main-tained. Despite all the difficulties, however, we intend to maintain it for aslong as circumstances in these areas, and the vital interests of our friends andallies, demand.20. The efficient, rapid and economical use of our forces requirestoday, as never before, that the three Services shall not only be interdependentbut accept interdependence as a natural continuous and essential frame fortheir activities. This acceptance is exemplified by the dramatic events ofrecent weeks. The problems of Malaysia, Cyprus and East Africa couldnot have been handled without a unity of effort unprecedented in what we call, for want of a better term, times of peace. The superb efficiency of RAF Transport Command complemented the resource and adaptabilityof our ground forces; with its skilled use of carrier and commando ship,its rapid deployment of marines, its ability to deliver the soldier to awkwarddestinations and if necessary to stand in for him until he arrives, the Navyhas made an essential contribution to the speed, punch and versatility ofour operations. It is perhaps significant that the three most importantgroups of operations in recent weeks have been commanded by an Admiral,a General and an Air Marshal, and that at times it has been difficult (andunimportant) to remember which was which.Nature of War and Allocation of Resources21. The provision that we make for the strategic deterrent forces andour contribution to N.A.T.O. represent an insurance against direct threats tothe security of this country. As we are continually reminded by events, our other obligations and interests force us to engage in operations in many partsof the world. In recent months our forces have operated, sometimes on aconsiderable scale, in the jungles, swamps and mountains of Borneo, in thedeserts and hills of the South Arabian Federation, in Cyprus, in EastAfrica and in British Guiana. It is reasonable to assume that we mayhave to continue to exercise responsibilities in this way for years to come,whether on our own, or with allies, or perhaps as a contribution to united nations forces.22. British forces are based on voluntary enlistment. In the case of theRoyal Navy and the Royal Air Force, recruitment is already running up toour requirements in most categories, and we have reached 95 per cent, of ourtarget for the Army. Any shortage is more than offset by our ability to rely on Regular professional forces, fully trained in their specific roles,and it is this which has enabled us to meet the varied and difficult demandsplaced on us in recent months.23. Weapons and equipment, ships and aircraft for these operations mustmeet the essential requirements of ruggedness, lightness, ease of maintenance,and suitability for operations in specially harsh and difficult conditions. Insome cases at least what is most suitable for these conditions may differ con-siderably from what is required, for example, for operations in northern europe. Our system of priorities and allocation of money and research effort
must be such as to provide the Services with the best means for the lesserwars that they will probably have to fight as well as for the major wars thatwe hope and expect we shall be able to prevent. jgc ^24. Ninety per cent, of the Defence Budget is spent directly on ccfF.en-tional forces, and this includes large purchases of modern conventional arms of all sorts. Many of these arms are of a complex and necessarily expensivenature. It is vital before finally placing orders to make detailed studies,both as to precise operational requirements and as to technical merit. Itis for these reasons that a detailed project study as to future aircraft is beingcarried out and there will be an announcement on future plans shortly.FINANCEDefence Budget25. To carry out the tasks of our defence policy is making, and willcontinue to make, significant demands on resources; the Defence budget in 1964-65 will amount to [ ]. A projection of the level of defence expenditure (including net expenditure on the Purchasing (Repayment)Services Votes and civil defence) in 1967-68 has been published in cmnd. 2235. Efforts have been, and will continue to be, made to improveforecasting in the especially awkward areas of development and productionexpenditure, for example, by using the processes recommended in the Reporton Management and Control of Research and Development dated 5th July,1961.26. As foreshadowed in Section XIII of Cmnd. 2097, a single volume of estimates is being published for 1964-65, to include.additional information about the Defence budget as a whole. Proposals for further changes in theform of the Defence Estimates for future years are being considered with theEstimates Committee and the Public Accounts Committee.Works Services27. On 1st April, 1963, responsibility for executing requirements for works services for the Service Departments passed from those departments to the Ministry of Public Building and Works and the framework of the new organisation is described in Cmnd. 2233. Funds are now provided on that ministry&apos;s Vote and the amount so allocated is regarded as part of theDefence Budget. Similar action has been taken as a result of the decision that, from 1st April, 1964, the defence works services which the Ministryof Public Building and Works carries out for the Ministry of Aviation andthe Royal Ordnance factories should be a final charge to Ministry of public building and Works Votes instead of being on repayment.Fissile Material28. We have now reached a point where supplies of fissile materialalready available or assured will be sufficient to.maintain our independentnuclear deterrent and to meet all our defence requirements for the foreseeable future. This takes account of the fact that material already embodied inweapons can be returned and used again. Consequently, production of U.235for military purposes at Capenhurst ceased in 1963 and the output of the
plant has been reduced to the minimum level necessary to keep it in pro-duction. Military plutonium production is gradually being brought to anersfSjblf at any time further supplies of fissile material are required fordeiiftce purposes, it will be possible to resume or increase production.There is, therefore, no question of these changes in any way affecting the ability to maintain the independent British deterrent.29. It is, however, necessary to modify the charging arrangements forfissile material supplied to the Defence Departments. The capital costs ofthe facilities for the production of fissile material have been borne on the votes of the Atomic Energy Authority (and previously of the Ministry ofSupply). The Authority were to recover from the Defence Departments their share of these costs by including charges for depreciation and interest in theprices of the fissile material supplied to the Defence Departments year by year. The great bulk of these recoveries would have been completed by1972. From now on, as the remaining deliveries will be small, this financialarrangement will no longer be appropriate. It has therefore, been arranged that the Defence Departments will meet the outstanding Capital liabilitiesby making eight annual payments (including interest on outstanding balances)from the Defence Budget to the Atomic Energy Authority ; thus completing the payments over approximately the same period. These payments willalso take account of certain terminal expenses involved in the closing down of military production. The first of a series of diminishing payments will bemade in 1964-65 and will be [ 37-75m]. The payments will be borne withinthe Defence Budget as a charge to a new Vote to be managed by the Ministryof Aviation.30. It has been further arranged, as part of the new settlement, that,provision having been made for foreseen needs, supplies of uranium ore notneeded on present plans for military purposes should form a nationalstockpile in the custody of the Atomic Energy Authority as the agent of theMinister for Science. This stockpile will be separated from the rest of the ore stocks, needed for civil purposes, which are held by the Authority and shown in their accounts; and will form a reserve available for either civil or military use.

THE ROYAL NAVYINTRODUCTION1. In modern weapons systems, quick action calls for equally quickreaction; the demand is for ever higher speed, faster than the humanhand, eye and brain can manage unaided. Computers and other eiec-tronic devices have to be used. Communications also must be swift,reliable and secure, proof against jamming, the interference of nature and the listening ear of the enemy.2. The warship&apos;s design has to combine the best lay-out for the opera-tion and maintenance of the individual weapon systems, equipments and aircraft, with the best lay-out for the accommodation of the men whowill operate and maintain them and whose living place the ship will befor commissions of up to 2-1 years. The sailors who operate and main-tain the ships and aircraft at sea, the men who design the ships andtheir equipment, and the men who refit the ships in the dockyards are all engaged in the application of some of the most advanced techniquesof modern science. To his pride in membership of a disciplined bodyof men, the sailor now adds his pride in his own technical knowledge and the pleasure of controlling complex mechanisms in operation.THE FLEET3. The strength of the Fleet during the coming year is shown in tabularform in Annex A.  Particulars of ship disposals appear in Annex B.4. All major fleets have a balance of the new and the old. In ourFleet, the escort strength is a good guide to quality. Of the 71 escortsexpected to be in service during the year 49 have been built since the war.The remaining 22 were built during the Second World War, but 20 of these have been modernised or converted since then.5. In the five years ending in December, 1964, the following ships have joined or will join the Fleet:  (a) Modernised or converted1 aircraft carrier.1 commando ship.7 destroyers.7 maintenance and support ships.(b) New2 cruisers.4 guided missile destroyers.24 frigates1 nuclear propelled submarine.14 other submarines.16 other war vessels.
6. New ships under construction or on order on 31st March, 1964 2 guided missile destroyers.2 assault ships.    &quot; ggx,9 frigates. &apos; Q&apos;J4 nuclear submarines (Polaris).2 nuclear submarines.2 conventional submarines.1 helicopter support ship.3 survey/oceanographical ships.2 Fleet Replenishment ships.3 Fleet Replenishment tankers.(Further details are to.be found in Navy Estimates 1964-65,pages     .)Carriers7. Among the modernised ships is H.M.S. Eagle. Like all aircraft carriersshe is a self-contained mobile air base with her own runway, hangar andmaintenance space, navigational aids, ground control, radar and so on.All will be of the latest designs. She will be capable of operating themost modern aircraft, and will have the surface-to-air guided weapon systemSeacat, up-to-date sonar and communication systems, and inertial naviga-tion of a high order of accuracy.8. When the new aircraft carrier joins the Fleet in the early 1970&apos;s,she will incorporate the results of advances in scientific and technicalinvention over the last twenty years which will make her a great deal more formidable even than the modernised Eagle, though her size willbe only marginally greater. The carrier force will continue to form thebackbone of the Navy throughout the 1970&apos;s.9. The Buccaneer Mark 1 now in service in the Fleet is proving tobe a most successful low level strike aircraft, and the programme forthe introduction of the Mark 2, having greater power and range, is going ahead.10. Bullpup, the air-to-surface guided missile now fitted to Buccaneers,Scimitars and Sea Vixens alike, greatly improves the accuracy of high explosive delivery, while reducing the vulnerability of the attacking air-craft to ground defences. Experience to date has shown this to be amost effective weapon.11. Delivery of the Sea Vixen Mark 2 has begun. The carrier trialsof the aircraft will be completed early in 1964 and the first squadron isbeing formed ashore to embark at the completion of the trials. an improved weapon system, incorporating the new Red Top air-to-air missile,is fitted, and the internal fuel capacity has been increased. Red Top isan infra-red, passive homing air-to-air missile with a greatly improvedpotential particularly against high flying and supersonic targets. In the interception role therefore the introduction of the Sea Vixen Mark 2 willmark a significant advance over its predecessor.12. The Wessex Mark 1 in the Commando troop carrying role hasacquitted itself well in the Borneo operations in 1963. The tactical evaluationof the Wessex Mark 5, a twin-engined aircraft designed to replace Whirlwind 7
1in the troop-carrying role, commenced early this year. Every effort has beenmade to develop the sting of this improved version, which will be armedwUh rockets, SS.11 anti-tank missiles and&apos; smoke-screening equipment asvSlfeis machine guns. The first front-line squadron is expected to formduring 1964. In the anti-submarine role, the Wessex is now embarked inthe four guided missile destroyers as well as in operational carriers. TheWasp helicopter forms part of an advanced anti-submarine weapon system for the Leander and Type 81 Tribal class frigates, and a series of successfulgeneral trials under all kinds of sea conditions were completed in 1963,followed by more specialised tactical evaluation.13. With the increasing complexity of aircraft and weapon systemsreliability is growing in importance. Unreliability costs money and affectsoperational efficiency. Increased emphasis is now being placed on designfor reliability and is being written into staff requirements. In conjunctionwith the Ministry of Aviation and the other two Services, progress is beingmade in the collection and dissemination of the results of experience to theaircraft industry and elsewhere.14. H.M.S. Eagle will be the first ship to be fitted with the revolutionaryAction Data Automation system (known familiarly in the Navy as ADA).This will give her command and control facilities in advance of any systemat present known. Sophisticated digital computers enable the system to handle simultaneously a large number of factors affecting the tactical situation.15. The guided missile destroyers will be fitted with an even moreversatile version of ADA, developed from the one fitted in H.M.S. Eagle.This new ADA will first be fitted in the two ships of the class now building(H.M.S. Glamorgan and H.M.S. Fife) and, later, in the four ships alreadywith the Fleet.The Polaris Programme16. The Royal Navy has been given the challenging task of completing the Polaris submarine programme to a very tight time schedule. Since theNassau Agreement was signed, much has been achieved. Two submarineshave been ordered from Vickers-Armstrongs and two from CammellLairds, and work is well in hand at both yards ; the Ministry of public building and Works are busy on the site for the Polaris base on the Gare-loch ; orders have been placed in the U.S.A. for the Polaris equipments, and special &quot; project team&quot; type organisations have been set up in theAdmiralty and Ministry of Aviation to drive the programme through.17. The target is that the first submarine is to be ready to go on patrolin mid 1968 ; three more submarines are to follow so that four submarineswill be operating by the end of the decade. To meet this the training ofthe crews will start soon in the U.S.A., but by the middle of 1966 ourown Polaris Training School will be commissioned the first part of theGareloch base to be completed. Less than a year later the base itself,with communications, stores, workships and a floating dock, will have to be capable of providing support to the first submarine at the beginning ofher sea trials in 1967.18. The complicated task of integrating our production programmerequirements with those of the U.S.N. has almost been completed. Thereis a well-established communication link between the Project Officers on
each side of the Atlantic and the utmost co-operation has been receivedfrom the U.S. authorities.Hunter Killer Submarines 0-&apos;-19. Last year the nuclear powered submarine H.M.S. Dreadnoughtstarted an extensive series of trials at home and abroad, designed to ensurethat we get the best value in the use of the operation of the hunter/killersubmarines. These trials will continue during 1964. Progress has beenstimulating and already the participation by H.M.S. Dreadnought in trialswith surface forces has advanced the development of tactics to counterhostile nuclear propelled submarines.20. A second nuclear powered submarine H.M.S. Valiant which was launched in December and a third hunter/killer nuclear propelled submarineis already under construction.21. The present R.N. building programme for conventional submarinesis nearing completion and two more Oberons are expected to join the Fleetthis year. These submarines are fast, silent, manoeuvrable and are effective against both submarines and surface ships.Frigates22. The introduction of the latest general purpose frigates into service is gathering momentum. The Type 81 Tribal class building programmecompleted at the end of 1963 and the seven ships of this class will be in service together with seven of the Leander class. Nine more Leander classships will be under construction: the ships of this class have a variety of armament and equipment to give a composite anti-submarine, anti-aircraft and aircraft direction capability. In addition they have bunk sleeping,cafeteria messing, full air-conditioning and are fitted with stabilisers.Amphibious Forces23. H.M.S. Bulwark will be in service East of Suez throughout the year.Increased accommodation for embarked troops has been provided inH.M.S. Bulwark, and H.M.S. Albion will be brought up to the same standardduring her refit; she will rejoin the Fleet later in the year.24. In 1961 it was announced that an assault ship of an entirely newdesign was being built. Two of these are being constructed. H.M.S.Fearless has already been launched and H.M.S. Intrepid will be launched in June.25. When these ships come into service they will replace the wartime-built ships of the Amphibious Warfare Squadron. They will increasesignificantly our amphibious capability by their greater speed, improvedcommunications and larger troop carrying capacity and by their ability to landtanks, heavy vehicles and equipment.26. Great technical strides are being made in the design and testing ofH.M. ships themselves. New materials are being evolved. To cope with the growing electric power requirement of the ships, electric generators of much higher capacity are being introduced in the Royal Navy. There have been considerable developments in ultrasonic and radiographic techniques for the examination, for example, of submarine pressure hull welding.
127EDUCATION27. On the lower rungs of the ladder, the year&apos;s work at Junior Train-in^gstabhshments is divided equally between professional, academic and  olal character training. Juniors already take G.C.E. examinations at&quot; O &quot; level and those who wish will be prepared for the Certificate of secondary Education when it is introduced in 1965. For technicians thestandard of naval apprenticeship training is second to none. Apprenticesfollow courses which lead to Ordinary National Certificate in Electrical,Mechanical and Aeronautical Engineering, in parallel with comprehensiveworkshop training in their trades. Other ratings&apos; courses lead to City andGuilds qualifications in a variety of technical subjects.28. Promotion to the Special Duties List of officers is based on pro-fessional competence and personal qualities ; but candidates must alsopass in certain subjects of the Royal Navy Higher Educational Test.Selection for the Upper Yardman course at Dartmouth, where candidateswork for G.C.E. &quot; A &quot; levels, also depends in part upon achieving G.C.E.passes at &quot; O &quot; level standard. In the general training field InstructionalTechnique courses are given to potential instructors, rating and officer,and experiments in the use of Teaching Machines are in progress.29. General List officers enter Dartmouth as cadets and spend their first year almost entirely in professional training, followed by a year at sea as Midshipmen. Under the present scheme of training Seamen and supply Officers then return to Dartmouth for the third year. The syllabusis run on university lines and is designed to prepare officers for professionalspecialist courses. Those who have a bent for foreign languages are fullycatered for. Correspondence classes are arranged for those who areunable to attend conventional courses of instruction.30. Degree and diploma courses in engineering and postgraduate and specialist scientific courses are provided in the Royal Naval Colleges atManadon and Greenwich. In the last few years courses in atomic physicsand nuclear propulsion have been established at Greenwich, where a Jasonnuclear reactor is in full operation. This training given to naval officersand civilians from industry and the dockyards is vital to the. implementation of the Polaris programme.31. The Royal Dockyards, the Dockyard Technical Colleges and theRoyal Naval Colleges at Greenwich and Manadon are making their contri-bution to the supply of trained civilian technologists. Post-graduate train-ing in naval architecture is provided at Greenwich for recruits to the RoyalCorps of Naval Constructors who have previously acquired honours degreesin mechanical engineering or mechanical sciences. Professional training is also provided there for school leaver entrants at age 18-19 and for thebest of the dockyard apprentices, leading to careers in the Royal corps of Naval Constructors and the Royal Naval Engineering Service. At thesame time, the Dockyard Technical Colleges provide courses leading tothe Ordinary and Higher National Certificates, and to the City and GuildsCertificates. In this way the dockyards provide many well trained tech-nicians and craftsmen. Similarly the Dockyard Technical Colleges at singapore and Gibraltar are helping substantially to raise the standard of technical training in these areas.
NAVAL MANPOWER: NUMBERSStrength32. Parliamentary approval is sought for a Vote A strength not ex &apos; ;%ing 103,000 during 1964-65. This figure will provide for the incnL&amp;dentries required to ensure the supply of trained men needed in due course for Polaris and other commitments.Recruiting (Ratings)33. Some 7,250 ratings are expected to be entered in 1963-64. this compares with nearly 6,800 in 1962-63 and 6,250 in 1961-62. provision is made in the 1964-65 Estimates for the recruitment of 8,000 ratings.This target will not be easy to attain but vigorous action will be takenin support of it.34. Royal Marines. Provision is made at present for the recruitment,excluding land ranks, of 800 in the 1964-65 Estimates. The number beingrecruited in 1963-64 is 750.V/.R.N.S. 1964-65 Estimates provide for the recruitment of 1,000. Thenumber of enrolments in 1963-64 is expected to be 900.Re-engagement35. Currently, the rating&apos;s first engagement is for nine years ; for Arti-officers, 12 years. It is of great importance that a high proportion re-engageand thus provide the higher skills in the Navy with the minimum additionaltraining cost. Whether or not men re-engage primarily depends upon their conditions of service, one of the most important of which is whether theycan expect to spend a fair proportion of their time in unity with their families.36. Men completing their first Continuous Service (12-year) engage-mentsare now re-engaging at the rate of about 55 per cent., compared with about&apos;60 per cent, during 1962. Men entered for the 9-year engagement,substituted for the Continuous Service engagement in 1956, will begin tocomplete their service in 1965 ; their probable rate of re-engagement cannotbe forecast but will vitally affect the Navy&apos;s strength thereafter. Re-engagement on completion of 22 years&apos; pensionable service is now at therate of 29 per cent., compared with 20 per cent, in 1962, though the numerical effect of this is not great.Officer entry37. General List. The General List entry continues to rise: 198 cadetsentered Britannia Royal Naval College, Dartmouth, last September, com-pared with 146 in 1961 and 171 in 1962. 105 of the cadets had heldR.N. scholarships or reserved cadetships ; the balance of 93 entered throughthe 1963 cadetship competition. But the entry is still below what is needed and could be bettered but for the continuing failure rate in the G.C.E.&quot;A &quot; level examination among candidates qualified in all other respects for entry. (Many of those who do not quite reach this academic standardenter the Supplementary List.) It is hoped that the annual entry willcontinue to grow: 78 R.N. and R.M. scholarships, and 125 reserved cadet-ships, were awarded in 1963, and the number of applications for both thescholarship and the cadet entry competitions is increasing.

NAVAL MANPOWER: NUMBERSStrength32. Parliamentary approval is sought for a Vote A strength not extf&apos;&quot; \&apos;-ing 103,000 during 1964-65. This figure will provide for the incrlu&amp;dentries required to ensure the supply of trained men needed in due course for Polaris and other commitments.Recruiting (Ratings)33. Some 7,250 ratings are expected to be entered in 1963-64. this compares with nearly 6,800 in 1962-63 and 6,250 in 1961-62. provision is made in the 1964-65 Estimates for the recruitment of 8,000 ratings.This target will not be easy to attain but vigorous action will be takenin support of it.34. Royal Marines. Provision is made at present for the recruitment,excluding land ranks, of 800 in the 1964-65 Estimates. The number beingrecruited in 1963-64 is 750.V/.R.N.S. 1964-65 Estimates provide for the recruitment of 1,000. Thenumber of enrolments in 1963-64 is expected to be 900.Re-engagement35. Currently, the rating&apos;s first engagement is for nine years ; for Arti-officers, 12 years. It is of great importance that a high proportion re-engageand thus provide the higher skills in the Navy with the minimum additionaltraining cost. Whether or not men re-engage primarily depends upon their conditions of service, one of the most important of which is whether theycan expect to spend a fair proportion of their time in unity with their families.36. Men completing their first Continuous Service (12-year) engage-ments are now re-engaging at the rate of about 55 per cent., compared with about 60 per cent, during 1962. Men entered for the 9-year engagement,substituted for the Continuous Service engagement in 1956, will begin tocomplete their service in 1965 ; their probable rate of re-engagement cannotbe forecast but will vitally affect the Navy&apos;s strength thereafter. Re-engagement on completion of 22 years&apos; pensionable service is now at therate of 29 per cent., compared with 20 per cent, in 1962, though the numerical effect of this is not great.Officer entry37. General List. The General List entry continues to rise : 198 cadetsentered Britannia Royal Naval College, Dartmouth, last September, com-pared with 146 in 1961 and 171 in 1962. 105 of the cadets had heldR.N. scholarships or reserved cadetships ; the balance of 93 entered throughthe 1963 cadetship competition. But the entry is still below what is needed and could be bettered but for the continuing failure rate in the G.C.E.&quot; A &quot; level examination among candidates qualified in all other respects for entry. (Many of those who do not quite reach this academic standardenter the Supplementary List.) It is hoped that the annual entry willcontinue to grow: 78 R.N. and R.M. scholarships, and 125 reserved cadet-ships, were awarded in 1963, and the number of applications for both thescholarship and the cadet entry competitions is increasing.

The Royal NavVs warships demand a high standard of technical competence fromthe men who serve in them. Illustrated are the bridge q/&apos;H.M.S. Dido, a LeanderClass frigate, and the machinery control room of the County Class destroyerH.M.S. Devonshire.
Royal Naval Minesweepers are playing a vital role in operations in Sarawak.Illustrated is H.M.S. Woolaston taking supplies up river in the Beluga area.Royal Marine Commandos use local boats for river patrol during Borneooperations. The Royal Marines celebrate their tercentenary in 1964.
The Royal Navy&apos;s warships demand a high standard of technical competence fromthe men who serve in them, illustrated are the bridge of&apos; H.M.S. Dido, a LeanderClass frigate, and the machinery control room of the County Class destroyerH.M.S. Devonshire.
Royal Naval Minesweepers are playing a vital role in operations in Sarawak.Illustrated is H.M.S. Woolaston taking supplies up river in the Beluga area.Royal Marine Commandos  use local boats for river patrol during Borneooperations. The Royal Marines celebrate their tercentenary in 1964.
The aircraft carrier H.M.S. Ark Royal and the guided missile destroyer H.M.S. Devonshire on exercise in the Mediterranean.
38. A small graduate entry to the Seamen specialisation of the GeneralList is being introduced; and it is planned that the first entrants, whoms^include Arts Graduates, should enter Dartmouth in September, 1964.T^p/entry is designed to attract what may be the increasing number of young men wishing to take a university degree before entering the Navy.There will continue to be opportunities for engineering graduates to enter the Engineering Specialisation of the General List.39. Supplementary List. The officer structure of the Navy is dependenton a healthy Supplementary List. The entry into the Supplementary Listof Seaman Officers and Observers continues to be satisfactory, but thereare still insufficient applicants of good calibre for the fixed-wing pilot andhelicopter entries. A number of measures have been taken to deal withthis problem and the associated high rate of failure in training. Fromnext year, 100 flying scholarships on the R.A.F. pattern will be awardedeach year to members of suitable youth organisations with naval connec-tions. Better conditions of service were introduced last year for pro-fessionally qualified electrical engineers, but there is still an urgent needfor more candidates. Under a new form of entry the special engineeringcommission entrants are being trained by the Navy for graduate member-ship of the British Institute of Radio Engineers. The initial response to this scheme has been encouraging.40. Other branches. In 1963 the Royal Marines once again obtainedall the General List entrants required. In order to have more junior officers without restricting the career prospects of the General List, a smallShort Service Commission List is to be introduced by the Corps inSeptember, 1964. Officers will enter on 5-year commissions, which may beextended to 10 years. The Instructor Branch entered 75 officers duringthe year, including 51 graduates. Under a new scheme announced lastyear, the first three ratings have been selected for training in civil colleges,and will take up pensionable careers as Instructor Officers in July, 1964.The Medical Branch is still attracting too few qualified doctors: but thesuccess of the medical cadetship scheme, for which some 50 candidates havebeen accepted, promises well for the future. Entry to the Dental Branchremains satisfactory.ACCOMMODATIONAshore41. Work has already started at many establishments such as H.M.S.Dryad, H.M.S. Excellent and H.M.S. Sultan in the Portsmouth area, theRoyal Naval Air Station at Lossiemouth, and the Infantry Training centre for Royal Marines at Lympstone. These as well as the new buildings which will appear at establishments such as H.M.S. Collingwood at Ports-mouth and H.M.S. Caledonia and H.M.S. Cochrane at Rosyth, will.follow the best standards of modern building.42. In the married quarters field there is continued progress with thebuilding programme. There are now some 8,500 married quarters avail-able and under construction in the United Kingdom and the programme will continue in 1964-65. In addition, furnished accommodation is hiredby the Admiralty for some 4,500 families.
The aircraft carrier H.M.S. Ark Royal and the guided missile destroyer H.M.S. Devonshire on exercise in the Mediterranean.
13038. A small graduate entry to the Seamen specialisation of the GeneralList is being introduced ; and it is planned that the first entrants, whoyoung men wishing to take a university degree before entering the Navy.There will continue to be opportunities for engineering graduates to enter the Engineering Specialisation of the General List.39. Supplementary List. The officer structure of the Navy is dependenton a healthy Supplementary List. The entry into the Supplementary Listof Seaman Officers and Observers continues to be satisfactory, but thereare still insufficient applicants of good calibre for the fixed-wing pilot andhelicopter entries. A number of measures have been taken to deal withthis problem and the associated high rate of failure in training. Fromnext year, 100 flying scholarships on the R.A.F. pattern will be awardedeach year to members of suitable youth organisations with naval connec-tions. Better conditions of service were introduced last year for pro-fessionally qualified electrical engineers, but there is still an urgent needfor more candidates. Under a new form of entry the special engineeringcommission entrants are being trained by the Navy for graduate member-ship of the British Institute of Radio Engineers. The initial response to this scheme has been encouraging.40. Other branches. In 1963 the Royal Marines once again obtainedall the General List entrants required. In order to have more junior officers without restricting the career prospects of the General List, a smallShort Service Commission List is to be introduced by the Corps inSeptember, 1964. Officers will enter on 5-year commissions, which may beextended to 10 years. The Instructor Branch entered 75 officers duringthe year, including 51 graduates. Under a new scheme announced lastyear, the first three ratings have been selected for training in civil colleges,and will take up pensionable careers as Instructor Officers in July, 1964.The Medical Branch is still attracting too few qualified doctors: but thesuccess of the medical cadetship scheme, for which some 50 candidates havebeen accepted, promises well for the future. Entry to the Dental Branchremains satisfactory.41. Work has already started at many establishments such as H.M.S.Dryad, H.M.S. Excellent and H.M.S. Sultan in the Portsmouth area, theRoyal Naval Air Station at Lossiemouth, and the Infantry Training centre for Royal Marines at Lympstone. These as well as the new buildings which will appear at establishments such as H.M.S. Collingwood at Ports-mouth and H.M.S. Caledonia and H.M.S. Cochrane at Rosyth, will follow the best standards of modern building.42. In the married quarters field there is continued progress with thebuilding programme. There are now some 8,500 married quarters avail-able and under construction in the United Kingdom and the programme will continue in 1964-65. In addition, furnished accommodation is hiredby the Admiralty for some 4,500 families.ACCOMMODATIONAshore
Afloat -    ;   .,/ -    ...43. In recent years- the standards of accommodation have beensystematically improved in hew ships joining the Fleet. The older shitf^irebeing improved as opportunity offers. These standards include new fu^sh-ing arrangements; improved kit lockers and coat-stowages, new and brighterdeck coverings, and better bathroom, sick bay and canteen arrangements ;fuller laundry facilities are also provided: All new ships are being fullyair conditioned and considerable extensions are being made to air con-reconditioning facilities in existing ships, particularly, those in service, in the far east.      v &apos;     .   .      ,   . . .        .       ; .,.THE&apos; NAVY. AND INDUSTRIAL; MANAGEMENTShore Organisation and Management44. Management of ;the naval shore organisation is anything but a statictask. The operations and needs of. the Fleet are continuously developing,while the arts of management are themselves rapidly changing. There arenew techniques and tools of management to use. and new forms oforganisa-tion to evolve. ,45. Among more modern techniques Organisation and Methods and work Study are now generally applied in the Naval Service. More recentlyoperational research, which has long been used in the sphere of Fleetoperations, has been applied to management problems.. A particularexample has been the application of statistical methods to the provisioningof stores. Another innovation is that of network analysis and critical pathscheduling. This technique is an advanced type of flow chart which demon-strates the inter-relationship between all the various activities in a particularproject; thus making it easier to expose bottlenecks and to judge the totaleffect of any programme change. About two years ago it was decided toapply this technique (which was used on the U.S.N. Polaris project) to.therefit of H.M.S. Bulwark in Devonport Dockyard. The results of this have led to its application to other suitable work at Portsmouth and ChathamDockyards.46. The experience gained enabled the technique of network analysisto be developed as a means of control for the Polaris project. A specialsection has been set up within the Polaris Executive. Several networks are used covering different areas of the project, and the shipbuilders concernedwith Polaris are required by contract to make their contribution in all stages, of programme planning and evaluation. These field.networks are all co-ordinated by a master network.. The, techniques are. being used ina way which ensures compatibility with the U.S.N. Polaris, project.47. New techniques like those described are to some extent made pos-sible by new tools of management. Prominent among the latter are com-puters, and other data processing machines. Certain important fields arenow, or soon will be, fully covered by these means.48. First, supplies and stores. A central computer (at Copenacre), andother machine installations in the principal store depots in this country,cover the provision, control and accounting for practically all naval stores.Second, civilian pay.  Computers have been used for some years for the
calculation of industrial pay in the Home Dockyards. The Copenacre com-puter is taking on the non-industrial, pay roll for the United Kingdom.TbjHJly, computers at the Royal Dockyards process the cost accounts,WhQjR! are an essential tool for planning and production and for financial control and planning.       ,;49. We are; now planning to advance from such routine tasks, whichhave hitherto been done1 by manual means, and are moving into newspheres, where manual calculations combined with professional judgmenthave necessarily been somewhat rough and incomplete. A few examplesmay be given. Computers have for long been used in our research anddevelopment establishments: more machines will be provided according to need. A new computer has been installed at Bath for ship design calcu-lations: it is hoped by more detailed and precise calculation to achievebetter results, whether in cost or size, or in operational effectiveness of theships so designed.50. Lastly, there are ways in which management itself can be reorganised and modernised with or without new techniques and new tools.The dockyard reorganisation, as an example, is familiar and has been fullyreported in the past.51. It is a feature of the organisation that a substantial amount of design work must be done by staffs at Headquarters in addition to thatdone by industry. The growing complexity of naval material has putsevere strains on the specialist design staffs. It has therefore been foundnecessary to underpin these by forming a new body the Royal NavalEngineering Service to carry out management and other professional tasksin the field of mechanical and electrical engineering. This came intooperation in May, 1963. An energetic and successful recruitment campaignis being conducted to enable the Service to meet the heavy demand placed upon it by the naval programme, including the Polaris submarine.STREAMLINING THE NAVY&apos;S SHORE ORGANISATION52. The streamlining of the shore support of the Navy continues. Over170 closures, reductions and transfers of tasks of shore establishments havebeen effected since 1955. Four Royal Dockyards have been closed and a fifth, transferred to commercial management: two Commands have been abolished: four bases at home have been run down, and. one is being rundown abroad: 9 training establishments have been closed, reduced orabsorbed in other establishments and a similar number of air stations havebeen closed. During 1963, two air stations, one barracks, one trainingestablishment and thirteen minor establishments (mostly stores) have been closed or transferred to other Departments. By reducing overheads in thisway more money and manpower are freed for more important navalpurposes.THE ROYAL NAVAL SCIENTIFIC SERVICE53. Most naval research and development is carried out by the royal naval Scientific Service. The work is done in exDerimental. and designestablishments supported by research contracts with universities and research and development contracts with industry, and calls for high qualityeffort in many scientific disciplines.
54. In the fields of radar and sonar, research is directed towards more advanced techniques to achieve increased range, accuracy and informationcapacity and reliability. The latest high speed digital techniques are usg-^to analyse the data provided. In the communications field new and imp^^dmethods of data transmission and exchange are under study. Researchis also conducted on methods and devices such as shipborne inertial navi-gation systems to meet modern navigational requirements. Research in basic electronics for all three Services is carried out at the Services ElectronicsResearch Laboratory. Masers and lasers, semiconductors and superconduct-ing devices are all under active study, and researches in this field havegiven the lead in this country to the development of the semiconductor laser.55. Officers are recruited into the Royal Naval Scientific Service from theage of 16 upwards, and with qualifications ranging from G.C.E. at &quot; O &quot;level to Honours degrees. Because the wide and varied scope of navalresearch and development programme, entrants are given the fullest possiblechoice of specialisation and the opportunity to acquire national reputationsin their particular fields.CIVIL STAFF56. The advancement of technology and the new systems of organisationand management now being developed require professional staff of thehighest quality. Our current problems call for advanced thinking, as wellas the application of professional knowledge. Additional recruitment hasbecome necessary in the Royal Corps of Naval Constructors, the royal naval Scientific Service, the Royal Naval Engineering Service and the Pro-duction Engineering Service. Recruits to these services can look forward to a wider range of stimulating work and to attractive career prospects.Civilian numbers57. Details will be found in Appendix ...... of the Navy Estimates1964-65.FLEET ACTIVITIES58. The pattern and volume of Fleet activities throughout the world has again been intensive. These show that the men of the Royal Navy havethe opportunity of performing a wide variety of tasks in all parts of theworld ; the farflung extent of the Royal Navy&apos;s activities is emphasised bythe fact that over two-fifths of the personnel afloat are now serving east of Suez.59. Actual operations this year have been no less spectacular thanin the preceding year. Units of the Far East Fleet and in particular the Commando ship H.M.S. Albion have given valuable backing in theBorneo operations. An impressive example was Albioris intervention at45 minutes&apos; notice in response to a guerilla attack in October, 1963.Wessex helicopters from the ship lifted Gurkha troops and positionedthem for a successful ambush. Escorts and minesweepers have maintainedpatrols constantly off the Borneo coast. Thousands of miles away theescorts of the West Indies Squadron have been employed in a successionof minor incidents and episodes in patrols in the Bahamas, off Haiti
132against the possible need to evacuate British and West Indian citizens,during the general strike in British Guiana and in giving help to Tobagoduripig Hurricane Flora which have been a model of versatility andmtiflpky. Recently H.M. Ships have played a vital part in the series of operations in East Africa.60. Throughout the past twelve months the Royal Marines (three hundred years old this year) have been in action all round the world.In the Far East H.Q. 3rd Commando Brigade, 40 and 42 Commandos,with their naval helicopters, have been employed in operations in Sarawak.In the Middle East, 45 Commando were moved at short notice from the aden Protectorate to East Africa where they have played a major partin operations to restore law and order. Forty-one Commando also were flown from the U.K. to Nairobi as reinforcements.61. Nearer home Fishery Protection duties in coastal and northern watershave continued. In May, 1963, a large force of minesweepers, includingR.N.R. units cleared mines laid in the last war off the Dutch and Germancoasts. This operation was the best sort of training; opened the way tothe laying of telephone cables ; and was a joint project with the Dutch andGerman Navies. In the Persian Gulf and Red Sea anti-gun-running patrols were carried out.62. H.M. Ships have played a leading role in many exercises throughoutthe world in co-operation with the navies of the Commonwealth, N.A.T.O.,S.E.A.T.O. and C.E.N.T.O. In the Far East Exercise Sea Serpent was oneof the biggest maritime exercises ever Undertaken by the navies of theS.E.A.T.O. powers. Nearly 60 ships with 14,000 officers and men took part. In the same theatre R.N. submarines with the help of the royal australian Air Force carried out an 18-day exercise simulating all possiblewar-time conditions in the deep water of the station. In the Middle East,Midlink VI, the latest and largest of the annual C.E.N.T.O. naval exercises,deployed 40 warships, 100 aircraft and 25,000 men. East of Suez R.N.aircraft carriers figure prominently in the exercises.63. &quot; H.M. Ships are heavily engaged in carrying out trials of modern equipment and techniques. There were highlights like the trials ofH.M.S. Dreadnought. H.M.S. Porpoise and H.M.S. Grampus carriedout a journey under the Arctic icepack to test equipment sometimesmore than 30 miles under the ice. Deep Diving Trials involving newdiving techniques have been continued from H.M.S. Reclaim during thepast year and a depth of 500 feet has been achieved experimentally. Afurther programme of trials is planned during 1964 from H.M.S. Reclaimtogether with trials in the new wet and dry recompression chamber whichis capable of simulating a depth of 1,000 ft.&quot;64. Both at home and abroad H.M. Ships show the flag during the traditional programme of visits. H.M. Ships were at San Sebastian inAugust, 1963, for the 150th Anniversary celebrations of the liberation ofthe town during the Napoleonic Wars ; and at about the same time at rotterdam for their 150th anniversary. H.M.S. Devonshire the first ofthe Royal Navy&apos;s new guided missile ships, visited Philadelphia in Octoberfor the British Week. Earlier the Dartmouth Training Squadron visited the U.S.A. and Canada including cities in the Great Lakes which have
seldom, if ever, seen snips of the Royal Navy. Over 50,000 people walkedaround the ships. Then there are activities too miscellaneous to capturein any detail. H.M.S. Belfast with eleven coastal minesweepers   ^theR.N.R. Divisions, manned by reservists carried out a programme \^theMediterranean with cadets of the Combined Cadet Force and the SeaCadet Corps on board. In Borneo two Wessex helicopters from H.M.S.Albion rescued the passengers from a Borneo Airway&apos;s aircraft which hadforce-landed in mangrove, swamps. In the Far East the ocean-going tugEncore took the U.S. ex-Liberty ship Vivian in tow when the Americanship was adrift, with badly damaged engine and no propeller.65. A note of this kind can only give a cross-section of the Fleefs life.When a ship comes home at the end of a commission it looks back on a valuable and exacting programme. To take one last example, H.M.S.Caprice commissioned in March, 1962. She first served on the Far EastStation, took part in exercises and visited Australian ports. After a shortrefit in Singapore she went to the Mediterranean to join one of the newstyle escort squadrons, and en route was on duty for a week in the vicinity of the Maldives. After a short spell in the Mediterranean, however, she had to be sent unexpectedly to the West Indies to assist with the eventalready mentioned.FINANCE66. The Estimates which Parliament is being asked to grant the royal navy for 1964-65 show gross expenditure of..............., Appropriations-in-Aid of.............:.... and therefore a net cash requirement of...................This is.................. above the correspondiing figure for 1963-64 (including a Spring Supplementary Estimate of..................).67. The main reason for this increase is the developing momentum of thePolaris programme ; and pay and prices have, increased. The variations are shown in more detail in the Section on Defence Statistics, Annex C, Table 2.
ANNEX A.STRENGTH OF THE FLEETDuring the coming year, the ships of the Fleet and the Royal FleetAuxiliaries which will be available for th&amp; various tasks of the Navy willbe broadly as shown in the following table.  &apos;Type/ClassOperationalor preparing for serviceTrials andTrainingShipsFleet support and RoyalFleet   -Auxiliariespermanentlyallocated toFleet supportReserve or&apos; undergoinglong refitmodernisation,conversion;etc.Aircraft carriersARK ROYALVICTORIOUSCENTAUREAGLE1HERMESCommando ships-2BULWARKALBIONCruisers.-2TIGERLION4BLAKEBELFASTSHEFFIELDGAMBIAEscorts(a) guided missile destroyers(b) other destroyers(c) fleet picketsId) general purpose frigates(leander class) ...(tribal class)(e) anti-aircraft frigates(/) aircraft direction frigatesto) anti-submarine frigates ..Despatch vessels (flag frigate)..Ice patrol ship........Submarines(a) nuclear   ...(b) &apos; A&apos; class...(c) OBERON Class(d) porpoise class(e) &quot;I&quot; class...(/)&apos;E&apos; class...(?) X craft   ...Minesweepers(a) oceanlb) coastal(c) inshore   ...HAMPSHIREDEVONSHIREKENTLONDON945733191111211673521214195221122163765
TypejClassOperationalor preparing for serviceTrials andTrainingShipsFleet support and RoyalFleetAuxiliariespermanentlyallocated toFleet supportReserve orundergoinglongpiofitmode. &apos;ij*)ton,conviimbn,etc.Landing vessels        ...... 7 1   6Coastal patrol craft   .......   5   24Survey vessels.........     12 2Submarine depot ships        .,.     2 1Submarine support ships     ...   -   2Submarine tender     ......     1 -rEscort maintenance ships ...     1 3Mine counter-measures supportships............     3  Mine counter-measures main-tenance ships        ...     ...       2Minesweeper support ship   ...       1Repair ships   ...      ...      ...     \Accommodation ships......     4 3Helicopter support ship      ...     1 --Controlled minelayers         ...     2    - 1Degaussing vessels    ......     3  Mooring, salvage and boomvessels       ......     ...     27 8DG range laying vessel       ... -   1 -Fleet replenishment tankers ...     11 1Fleet attendant tankers       ...   ;  4  Freighting tankers     ......     7  Fleet replenishment ships     ...     2  Armament support ships     ...     3  Store support ships    ......     3  Air/victualling store supportship............     1  Dry cargo freighters  ......     2  Coastal store carriers...... - 2145 49 93 226
134W ANNEX BH.M. Ships disposed of (other than by sale commercially) or approved for disposal by scrapping during 1963-64By sale to Malaysia:H.M.S. Loch Insh (frigate).H.M.S. Hexton    \H.M.S. DilstonH.M.S. Essington )(coastal minesweepers).By ScrappingOne cruiser, one destroyer, nine frigates, five ocean minesweepers,one inshore minesweeper, five submarines, one submarine tender.

THE ARMYOPERATIONSFar East1. During 1963 the main operational task for the Army has been in theBorneo Territories. The Brunei rebellion, which broke out in December,1962, was effectively suppressed by February, 1963. But a new and more serious threat emerged with the growing influence of the Clandestine Com-munist Organisation in Sarawak. In addition an increasing number ofraiding parties from Indonesian Borneo crossed the border into the BritishBorneo territories. To meet these threats a force of five British and Gurkhabattalions were deployed in the Borneo Territories by May, 1963.2. On 16th September, 1963, Sabah, Sarawak and Singapore joined theexisting Federation of Malaya to form Malaysia, and our defence obliga-tions in these territories are now governed by the Anglo-Malayan defence agreement as extended. The British and Gurkha force in the operationalarea had been substantially strengthened by the end of the year, alongsidea growing number of Malaysian units. This increased force is likely to berequired for some time to come.3. Operations have consisted mainly of extensive patrolling of the 1,000mile frontier between Malaysia and Indonesian Borneo. There have beennumerous clashes in which officers and men have been killed and wounded and substantial casualties inflicted on the terrorists. By their operationsBritish and Malaysian forces have succeeded in maintaining overall controlof. the Malaysian side of the border.4. In spite of the Borneo operations the Army has maintained its ability to take part in S.E.A.T.O. operations and so plays its part in ensuringstability in South East Asia.5. Elsewhere in the Far East the Army has had a quiet year. in singapore the task of internal security has been handed over to the Malaysianarmed forces.Cyprus6. In early December, 1963, tension between the two communities onthe island mounted quickly. After a number of minor incidents seriousinter-communal fighting broke out. Following a request by the CommanderBritish Forces Cyprus, reinforcements consisting of Headquarters 16thParachute Brigade, 2nd Regiment Royal Artillery, 1st Battalion the Sher-wood Foresters and 1st Battalion the Parachute Regiment were flown fromthe United Kingdom, and a squadron of the I4th/20th King&apos;s Hussarswas flown from Libya. To restore order the Cyprus Government acceptedthe offer of the Guaranteeing Powers (The United Kingdom, Greece and turkey) to set up a Truce Force under command of the General OfficerCommanding Cyprus District. The British troops belonging to the TruceForce were engaged initially -in patrolling the Neutral Zone, in Nicosia,
and in maintaining the cease fire. Subsequently patrols have been sentto all parts of the island. They have been engaged in supervising theexchange of refugees, taking over road blocks and restoring normal tr^c;providing food for isolated villages, evacuating casualties, and relfpngcommunications.B.A.O.R.7. It has been decided to reorganise B.A.O.R. from seven brigade groupson to a basis of three divisions, each of two brigade groups. This reorganisa-tion will enable additional artillery, engineer and transport units to be madeavailable to B.A.O.R. and thus provide a better balanced force within itstarget strength of 55,000.8. A party of 50 Royal Engineers from B.A.O.R. gave assistance to yugoslavia after the Skopje earthquake by constructing 244 prefabricatedhuts and ancillaries presented jointly by Her Majesty&apos;s Government and the welfare Organisation &quot; War on Want&quot;. The huts are being used as schools,clinics, churches and administrative buildings.Africa9. The 1st Battalion the Gordon Highlanders were sent from Kenya toSwaziland in June, 1963, at the request of the High Commissioner for theSouth Africa High Commission Territories to meet an internal security situation which developed from labour and political unrest in the Territory.The 1st Battalion the Loyal Regiment relieved the Gordon Highlanders inAugust, 1963, and were themselves relieved in December, 1963, by the 1stBattalion the York and Lancaster Regiment.10. On the dissolution of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland atthe end of 1963, Her Majesty&apos;s Government assumed responsibility for defence and internal security in Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland; and a british commander with a small headquarters was established in Lusaka, northern rhodesia.Caribbean11. In April, 1963, a general strike was declared in British Guiana. by july it was feared that disorders, which had been sporadic up to that time,might become widespread, and reinforcements consisting of Headquarters2nd Infantry Brigade and 2nd Greenjackets were sent by air from the UnitedKingdom to reinforce the 2nd Battalion Grenadier Guards. This reinforce-ment. was completed in 72 hours, and demonstrated our ability to reinforceisolated garrisons at short notice.North Africa12. In February, 1963, the Army provided assistance to the victims of theBarce earthquake. The Libyan Government paid particular tribute to the speed with which this assistance was given.TRAININGUnit and Formation Training13. During 1963 the most important factor has been the continuingemphasis on air mobility training.  Formations and units of the&apos; Strategic
136Reserve have taken part in exercises in France, Germany, North Africa,Cyprus, Aden, Canada and Australia.jf1&amp;4. Within Europe the general shortage of training areas has led to aglcSier exchange of training facilities within the N.A.T.O. Alliance. troops from B.A.O.R. have trained in France, Denmark and Norway ; and N.A.T.O.troops, including Germans, Americans, French and Belgians, have trained in the United Kingdom.Assistance to Commonwealth and Foreign Countries15. The Army has continued to give considerable assistance in trainingofficers and soldiers of Commonwealth and certain foreign countries.Many of these come to the United Kingdom for various courses andattachments each year; the demand has been particularly great from the armies of newly independent Commonwealth countries. For our partwe are continuing to second over 1,450 officers and men to assist intraining these armies.Territorial Army16. During the year 2,400 soldiers of 44 Parachute Brigade Group(T.A.) took part in an exercise in Cyprus. A contingent of 200 soldiersfrom the Territorial Army Emergency Reserve who volunteer to serveoverseas up to six months in emergency-were flown out to Hong kong and Singapore for operational training. Other T.A.E.R. men accompanied the 2nd Green Jackets on a training exercise in Libya. Their efficiency,keenness and bearing impressed the Regular Army units to whom they were attached.Adventure Training17. Adventure training is an increasingly important feature of thetraining of the Army ; and a larger number of all ranks is taking part in it.WEAPONS18. The production of new equipment which has been developed overthe last few years is gathering momentum. This is clearly shown by theincrease in the Estimates provision for deliveries of fighting equipment from  80m. last year to  100m. in 1964-65.Mobility19. The Chieftain main battle tank, having successfully completed itstrials, has been ordered and two production lines have been established.First deliveries of the tracked armoured personnel carrier have alreadybeen received and it will start going into service during the summer of1964. The self-propelled 105mm. Abbot close support gun is also in production and will start to come into service during the year. Theintroduction of these three weapons will give the battle group addedmobility. They are being matched by further deliveries of logistic supportvehicles including a number of Stalwart High Mobility Load Carriers.Fire Power20. Chieftain, with its powerful and accurate 120mm. gun, and the105mm. Abbot with its long range and rapid rate of fire, will contribute
to increased fire-power as well as to mobility. In addition, an order has been placed for the M 107 American 175mm. self-propelled heavygun as part of the plan to provide modern artillery support to complera^ntAbbot. During 1964 deliveries will be made at an increasing rate cs -*.egeneral purpose machine gun, 81mm. mortar, and the new anti-tankweapons which will go into service with units during the year.Expansion of Army Aviation21. The Army is entering a period of expansion of Army Aviation inwhich the number of light aircraft and helicopters is to be substantially increased. The present programme for re-equipment with 5-seater Scouthelicopters will be completed in 1964, thus largely standardising the army air Corps on fixed wing Beavers and Scout helicopters.Communications22. By the end of 1964 issue of the new family of radios will have been substantially completed. During the year higher formations will receive more radio relay and terminal equipment, and the strategic network willinaugurate a system of telegraph automatic relay which will speed traffic and save manpower.Other Equipment23. Delivery of the German M2 amphibious bridge is expected duringthe year and a start will be made on the production of assault trackwayspecially developed for rapid laying on soft ground.24. The second and third Logistic Ships will be laid down in 1964.25. The wide field of other equipment includes instruments to aid firecontrol, infra red devices for night driving and fighting, new types of ammuni-tion and mines, and earth-moving vehicles and mechanical lifting aids.26. A new combat and general service sleeping bag is being introduced to replace the blankets now used in the field; first issues will go to unitsof B.A.O.R. and the Strategic Reserve. A new and improved range oftentage has also been developed and will provide lightweight, portableand more easily erected shelters for use in the field. Some of the shelterswill be coming into service in 1964-65.Research and Development27. Apart from their work on the development of the Chieftain andother weapons mentioned above, the Research and Development Establish-ments are undertaking longer-term projects including work on the feasibility of using unguided rockets in the role of surface to surface artillery, withthe advantage over the conventional gun of improved range, mobility andlethality. Work continues on the study of more advanced armoured fighting vehicles, on improving the performance of multi-fuel engines for fighting vehicles and on investigating the potentialities of unconventionalengines.28. Research continues over a wide field for acquiring fundamentalknowledge on which to base the development of future equipment for theArmy.   Extramural research at universities and Research Associations is&apos; encouraged and supported in those fields where suitable facilities exist.
137-MANPOWER&apos;--:&apos;Recruiting: General   - -During 1963 there has been a serious drop in recruiting of OtherR^jjs compared with the two previous years, and at the end of the year the other rank strength of the Army was .151,499 against a requirement of160,000.&apos; .&quot;. . &apos;     &apos; :;30. Our advertising, as a result of-research, lays stress on.the personalexperience of serving soldiers. We believe that the interest of a potentialrecruit is likely to be especially aroused and strengthened by personalcontact with contented serving soldiers: We have therefore formed ArmyYouth Teams whose task it is to make contact with the young people ofthe nation, and to tell them and show them what Army life is like.31.. The Army offers young men a varied and secure career. There areunrivalled opportunities for adventure, travel and sport; and high regardis given to the welfare of them and their families. Above all it offers a worthwhile job with a clear purpose. ,Officers32. The number of United Kingdom cadets entering. the Royal MilitaryAcademy, Sandhurst, in 1963 was 402, compared with 439 in 1962. Therewas a low entry of 139 in January, but a record intake in September of 263entrants, half of whom had two or more &apos; A&apos; levels ; and in January, 1964there was a full entry of 208. The Army Scholarship Scheme continues to attract the number of candidates we require, and Welbeck College is full.33. Applications for short-service commissions continue to fall short of requirements ; 225 were granted in 1962 and only 209 in 1963. Steps arebeing taken which it is hoped will improve the position.34. To replace the Extended Service Commission a new Limited ServiceRegular Commission is being introduced. This commission guaranteesemployment for 16 years, and officers will earn rates of retired pay appro-priate to regular officers. Extensions of service will be offered in suitable cases. Those officers who are not extended beyond the 16 year point willbe able to retire at an age when they have good prospects of resettlement incivil life. It is hoped that the commission will attract those who wish toserve for a longer period than that covered by the short-service commission,and will induce eligible short service officers to extend their Army career.The commission should also provide a worth-while career for those soldierswho may have missed the opportunity of obtaining regular commissions.35. In 1963, 18 university candidates were commissioned into the Regi-ments and Corps which receive officers from Sandhurst, compared with29 in 1962. More graduate officers are needed and certain new schemes are being introduced this year. These provide for up to 20 short service commission officers. a year to be sent to the Royal Military College of science, Shrivenham, to study for a science or engineering degree with aview to being granted permanent commissions ; for 20 young men fromcivilian life to be granted permanent commissions and to study for scienceor engineering degrees at the R.M.C.S. or universities; and for an increasein the number of Sandhurst students who proceed to a degree course at universities.
36. Changes are being introduced in the non-medical officer structure of the Royal Army Medical Corps. At present, these officers serve onquartermaster terms of service, although less than one-quarter are employedon quartermaster duties; others serve as staff, administrative and comy^p;officers. It is proposed to establish three types of non-medical officer^the R.A.M.C.: administrative, technical and quartermaster. The introduc-tion of administrative officers will provide soldiers in the R.A.M.C. withan opportunity of being commissioned at an earlier age ; and technicianswill have greater opportunities of obtaining commissioned rank and at thesame time pursuing their trade. Some non-medical officers will fill postsat present held by medical officers and this will help to relieve our shortageof doctors.Other ranks37. Recruiting during 1963, as has been emphasised above, fell seriouslybelow the high level of 1962. There has, however, been a welcome increasein the strength of certain corps, such as the Royal Corps of Signals. AnnexA on page 38 shows the recruiting results in 1960, 1961, 1962 and 1963.Boys38. The recruitment of boys is continuing satisfactorily and there is atpresent no problem in obtaining enough boys of the required standard.At this time of manpower shortages the boys training scheme makes a mostimportant contribution to the long term strength of the Army. The high quality of the young soldiers passing into the Army from the boys training units makes the contribution particularly important.39. At the end of 1963 there were      apprentices,      junior leaders,junior tradesmen and       junior bandsmen under training; a totalofThe Women&apos;s Services40. We need more candidates of high quality for commissions in theW.R.A.C. Although the other rank strength has slightly declined, mainly because of the high marriage rate, recruiting has been fairly good and hasfurther improved in recent months.41. An initial engagement of four years was introduced for W.R.A.C.and Q.A.R.A.N.C. other ranks on 1st October, 1963. It is hoped thatthis measure will produce greater stability in units, and more potentialnon-commissioned officers.. 42. We can accept many more trained State Registered Nurses forQ.A.R.A.N.C. as officers. Steps which have been taken to improve the opportunities for Q.A.R.A.N.C. nurses (other ranks) to qualify as StateRegistered Nurses (who can be commissioned), or State Enrolled Nursesshould improve the position.The Territorial Army43. Recruiting for the Territorial Army has made steady progress overthe past year and there is every indication that the strength will continueto rise. It is now intended that from 1965 more use will be made of theTerritorial Army for the reinforcement and support of BAOR.   The

36. Changes are being introduced in the non-medical officer structure of the Royal Army Medical Corps. At present, these officers serve onquartermaster terms of service, although less than one-quarter are employedon quartermaster duties; others serve as staff, administrative and comr/1^1-officers. It is proposed to establish three types of non-medical officer lathe R.A.M.C.: administrative, technical and quartermaster. The introduc-tion of administrative officers will provide soldiers in the R.A.M.C. withan opportunity of being commissioned at an earlier age; and technicianswill have greater opportunities of obtaining commissioned rank and at thesame time pursuing their trade. Some non-medical officers will fill postsat present held by medical officers and this will help to relieve our shortageof doctors.Other ranks37. Recruiting during 1963, as has been emphasised above, fell seriouslybelow the high level of 1962. There has, however, been a welcome increasein the strength of certain corps, such as the Royal Corps of Signals. AnnexA on page 38 shows the recruiting results in 1960, 1961, 1962 and 1963.Boys38. The recruitment of boys is continuing satisfactorily and there is atpresent no problem in obtaining enough boys of the required standard.At this time of manpower shortages the boys training scheme makes a mostimportant contribution to the long term strength of the Army. The high quality of the young soldiers passing into the Army from the boys training units makes the contribution particularly important.39. At the end of 1963 there were      apprentices,      junior leaders,junior tradesmen and       junior bandsmen under training ; a totalofThe Women&apos;s Services40. We need more candidates of high quality for commissions in theW.R.A.C. Although the other rank strength has slightly declined, mainly because of the high marriage rate, recruiting has been fairly good and hasfurther improved in recent months.41. An initial engagement of four years was introduced for W.R.A.C.and Q.A.R.A.N.C. other ranks on 1st October, 1963. It is hoped thatthis measure will produce greater stability in units, and more potentialnon-commissioned officers.42. We can accept many more trained State Registered Nurses forQ.A.R.A.N.C. as officers. Steps which have been taken to improve the opportunities for Q.A.R.A.N.C. nurses (other ranks) to qualify as StateRegistered Nurses (who can be commissioned), or State Enrolled Nursesshould improve the position.The Territorial Army43. Recruiting for the Territorial Army has made steady progress overthe past year and there is every indication that the strength will continueto rise. It is now intended that from 1965 more use will be made of theTerritorial Army for the reinforcement and support of BAOR.   The
Junior Leaders skin diving near their camp at Bovington.

An operational patrol in the Brunei Jungle.

Ail operational patrol in the Brunei Jungle.
A Soldier at home with his family in Berlin.
140extended use of the Territorial Army in this role will involve &quot; teeth &quot; armsas well as administrative units, and will increase its relevance to general war.fliM- The Territorial Army Emergency Reserve will continue to provide aVL^ble source of reservists who are available in times of tension andwithout a proclamation. Further steps will be taken to increase its numbers and it is hoped that employers will give every encouragement to suitableyoung men who wish to volunteer.Other Reserve Forces45. The Army Emergency Reserve was reorganised in 1963 into thenumber of units required to back the Strategic Reserve in the event of limited war. Recruiting to the Army Emergency Reserve has been good and establishments should be nearly filled by the end of 1964.46. Under the Navy, Army and Air Force Reserves Acts, 1954 and1959, soldiers who have completed their National Service commitment,or service in lieu, are retained in the Army General Reserve until theage of 45. This reserve is indispensable for bringing the Territorial Armyup to full strength in the event of a general war emergency. The Actsexpire in June, 1964, and legislation has therefore been introduced toprovide for continuing this reserve until 1969. Only a small proportionof the existing Army General reservists will be retained, and nearly amillion will be released from all obligations. The Bill also providesfor a new Long Term Reserve of ex-Regular soldiers which will eventuallytake the place of the Army General Reserve, and for the liability for service in Section A of the Regular Reserve to be extended from one to three years.47. The Combined Cadet Force is being reorganised with the full co-operation and support of the schools concerned. By raising theminimum age and reducing the size of Army sections it is hoped to providebetter facilities and more interesting training for the cadets.WORKS AND ACCOMMODATION48. Progress on Works projects at home during 1963-64 kept verymuch in line with what Was planned when the year&apos;s Estimates were pre-pared. Overseas, some projects were postponed pending a general reviewof long term deployment.At Home49. By the end of 1963-64 it is expected that 37 large projects willhave been completed, including 6 of the Infantry Brigade Depots, andthat 18 further large projects will have started.50. In 1964-65 27 large projects are due to be completed, includingthe very large one at Stanhope Lines, Aldershot, which contains barracksfor the equivalent of four major units. In all, 12 major units will beprovided for, as well as 8 depots, centres and large schools.51. During 1964-65 47 projects are due to start, but only two ofthese are for major units, one of which is the Household Cavalry regiment,at Knightsbridge.  Some of the other projects are however very large,
A Soldier at home with his family in Berlin.
140extended use of the Territorial Army in this role will involve &quot; teeth &quot; armsas well as administrative units, and will increase its relevance to general war.&apos;-*fM. The Territorial Army Emergency Reserve will continue to provide ava^ible source of reservists who are available in times of tension andwithout a proclamation. Further steps will be taken to increase its numbers and it is hoped that employers will give every encouragement to suitableyoung men who wish to volunteer.Other Reserve Forces45. The Army Emergency Reserve was reorganised in 1963 into thenumber of units required to back the Strategic Reserve in the event of limited war. Recruiting to the Army Emergency Reserve has been good and establishments should be nearly filled by the end of 1964.46. Under the Navy, Army and Air Force Reserves Acts, 1954 and1959, soldiers who have completed their National Service commitment,or service in lieu, are retained in the Army General Reserve until theage of 45. This reserve is indispensable for bringing the Territorial Armyup to full strength in the event of a general war emergency. The Actsexpire in June, 1964, and legislation has therefore been introduced toprovide for continuing this reserve until 1969. Only a small proportionof the existing Army General reservists will be retained, and nearly amillion will be released from all obligations. The Bill also providesfor a new Long Term Reserve of ex-Regular soldiers which will eventuallytake the place of the Army General Reserve, and for the liability for service in Section A of the Regular Reserve to be extended from one to three years.47. The Combined Cadet Force is being reorganised with the full co-operation and support of the schools concerned. By raising theminimum age and reducing the size of Army sections it is hoped to providebetter facilities and more interesting training for the cadets.WORKS AND ACCOMMODATION48. Progress on Works projects at home during 1963-64 kept verymuch in line with what was planned when the year&apos;s Estimates were pre-pared. Overseas, some projects were postponed pending a general reviewof long term deployment.At Home49. By the end of 1963-64 it is expected that 37 large projects willhave been completed, including 6 of the Infantry Brigade Depots, andthat 18 further large projects will have started.50. In 1964-65 27 large projects are due to be completed, includingthe very large one at Stanhope Lines, Aldershot, which contains barracksfor the equivalent of four major units. In all, 12 major units will beprovided for, as well as 8 depots, centres and large schools.51. During 1964-65 47 projects are due to start, but only two ofthese are for major units, one of which is the Household Cavalry regiment,at Knightsbridge.  Some of the other projects are however very large,
including the Depot of the Airborne Forces, and ah Army ApprenticesSchool to take 1,000 boys. ... ...52. During the last three years married quarters have been comp^^lat the rate of about 1,200 a year. It is expected that [1,900] new quau3rswill have been started in 1963-64 ; the programme will continue in 1964-65.In addition the Army will continue to make use of hired accommodation.Overseas52. The emphasis in Germany will continue to be on improving thegeneral standard of barracks and on providing additional married accom-modation, N.A.A.F.I. Families Shops, and schools. Work is progressingon the blocks of flats which are being specially built by German con-tractors for hiring to the Army as married quarters, and it is hoped that,000 will be available by March, 1965. This will bring the total of personnel in permanent homes in Germany at that date to 18,000 other ranks and 3,000 Officers. As a temporary measure the number of caravan-type mobile homes are also being provided.54. In the Arabian Peninsula progress has been made on the Armytownship at Little Aden. Work will continue as fast as possible on theprovision of hutted camps for the additional units which will join thegarrison, and on providing better accommodation for the existing garrison.In the Persian Gulf work will continue on the. provision of new living and working accommodation for the British and Arab troops of the TrucialOman Scouts. It is also intended to construct much needed new living accommodation for British troops in Bahrein.55. In the Far East a secondary school will be built in the Common-wealth Brigade cantonment at Terendak Camp, Malacca. Work will con-tinue on .the provision of air-conditiorted sleeping accommodation for theWomen&apos;s Royal Army Corps in Singapore and on the barrack and depotaccommodation improvement programmes. Money has also been pro-vided for several projects in Hong Kong including the Ordnance Depot atKaiTak.56. The re-housing of the Gibraltar garrison will go ahead in newaccommodation at Europa Point at the south end of the Rock, where atpresent new barracks and 74 married quarters are being built. There will beseveral new projects including additional married quarters.]57. In Cyprus the sea-water distillation plant will be completed and work will continue on the L.S.T. jetty. It is expected that 153 married quarters will be under construction at Dhekelia.Disposal of Land58. The Army&apos;s holdings of land and property world-wide are con-stantly being reviewed. In the United Kingdom some 135,500 acres havebeen released since 1957 and further releases of land will take place in1964-65. The rate of release is governed by many factors including the changing requirements and deployment of the Army, the process of clear-ing explosives from the land and the need to decide, in consultation withother Government Departments, on the future use of the land.
UlADMINISTRATIONThe Nye Committeefife:FINANCE60. Parliamentary approval is sought for a net grant of  527,410,000 for services administered by the Army Department: viz. Defence (Army) Estimates............     523,010,000Defence (Royal Ordnance Factories) Estimate   ...        2,400,000Defence (Army) Purchasing (Repayment) ServicesEstimate     ..................        2,000,000527,410,00061. Defence (Army) Estimates 1964-65 show an increase of  37* 1M overthe corresponding figure for 1963-64, mainly on Vote 7, to provide for the increasing deliveries of new fighting equipment, and on Vote 1, to providefor the higher rates of pay resulting from the 1964 pay review. TheDefence (Royal Ordnance Factories) Estimate is  0T5M more than thecorresponding figure for 1963-64. &apos; Vote by Vote comparisons between1964-65 and 1963-64 showing the main courses of variations, are given inthe Section on Defence Statistics, Appendix 3, Tables 3 and 4.62. The Defence (Army) Purchasing (Repayment) Services Estimate1964-65 is  4-OM below the corresponding figure for 1963-64. As explained in the note on page 131 of the Estimates, expenditure from the Vote is repaidby customers when the equipment is delivered and over a period of years the Vote should be approximately in balance.
ANNE5.IRECRUITING RESULTS 1960-63
1429THE ROYAt AIR FORCEINTRODUCTION1. Speed and flexibility are the essence of our defence requirements.2. They are signally demonstrated today by the V-force, the TacticalStrike forces, and the Transport forces. The V-force provides world-widecoverage with its massive conventional as well as nuclear striking power.The Tactical Strike forces, made up today of Canberras and Hunters, canbe brought quickly into action in overseas theatres. The long and mediumrange Transport forces enable ground forces to meet sudden troubleswherever they may occur. These forces, with their wide variety of tacticsand techniques, provide air power fully capable of playing its part in deter-ring aggression in all its forms and of taking part in active operations.3. The world-wide role of the Royal Air Force, taken together withthe constant progress in technology, demands the highest standards from all who serve, both in the air and on the ground. The Service is, and willremain, in the forefront of technical progress.4. The most notable example of such progress is the T.S.R.2 which willmake its first flight shortly. This aircraft promises to be one of the mostpotent and flexible instruments of military power yet devised and should havea long and effective life. Production contracts for fifty T.S.R.2s are being negotiated, covering a number of development aircraft and the initial pro-duotion order.5. Speedy reinforcement around the world is helped by the growingstrength of Transport Command. This will be augmented by the acquisitionof further modern long-range transport aircraft the Belfasts and the V.C.10s.The Belfast strategic freighter successfully made its first flight last month.6. More emphasis is being placed on flight refuelling for use by manytypes of aircraft. It has been decided to increase the size of the R.A.F. flightrefuelling fleet and to replace the Valiant tankers with Victors.7. The re-equipment of the front line and supporting units is going aheadover a wide field. In 1964-65 deliveries to the Royal Air Force of aircraft and missiles are expected to include the types shown in paragraphs 6 and 7.8. Continuing DeliveriesVulcan Mark 2 The latest of the nuclear and conventionally armedmedium bombers.&apos; Blue Steel The air-to-surface nuclear stand-off missile withwhich many of the V-bombers are beingarmed.Firestreak The air-to-air missile with which the Mark 2Lightning fighter aircraft are armed.Bloodhound II The latest version of the Bloodhound surface-to-air missile which is air transportable andwill be used mainly overseas.
The air-to-surface missile with which Canberrastrike aircraft are to be armed.The wire-guided missile with which WhirlwK\&apos;helicopters and s other short-range transptfUcan be armed.The twin-engined Transport helicopter.The basic jet trainer.The advanced jet trainer.A faster version of the Lightning fighter aircraft which has a greater reinforcement range andis a more advanced weapons system.The advanced air-to-air missile with whichMark 3 Lightnings will be armed.The medium range Transport aircraft.The short range Transport and Communicationsaircraft which is replacing part of the existingAnson fleet.10. The complexity of much of this new equipment together with the manyand varied tasks of the Royal Air Force requires a constant search for bettermethods and improved operating techniques. Some examples of the way inWhich these challenges are being met in practice are given below.OPERATIONAL COMMANDS OF THE ROYAL AIR FORCE11. Last year the Royal Air Force provided air support for operations from Borneo to British Guiana, from Swaziland to the Aden Protectorate.In addition, all operational Commands undertook a programme of exercisesdesigned particularly to practise quick reaction and world-wide mobility.Bomber Command12. Bomber Command continues effectively to provide the independentstrategic deterrent of the United Kingdom and contributes to that of theAllies. The Commands ability to react instantly to any threat has been further improved. It has been impressively demonstrated during the year ina series of &quot; no notice &quot; alert and dispersal exercises.13. In May the V-bomber force was assigned to N.A.T.O. in accordancewith the intentions expressed in the Nassau Agreement (Cmnd. 1915). TheSupreme Allied Commander Europe described this as &quot;an important andpowerful addition to the air capability of Allied Command Europe &quot;. TheV-bomber force is now fully integrated into SACEUR&apos;s war organisationand covers a substantial proportion of the co-ordinated targetting plan.14. Re-equipment of the Vulcan 2s and the Victor 2s with Blue Steel is proceeding satisfactorily and will be completed this year. The capacity ofthe V-bombers to survive attack by taking off from widely dispersed baseswithin the minimum warning time available from the Ballistic Missile early warning System has been frequently practised.A.S. 30S.S. 11Wessex Mark 2Jet ProvostGnat9. New DeliveriesLightning Mark 3Red TopH.S.748Beagle 206
1415. The effective equipment for Electronic Counter Measures which itcarries and the ability to operate from widely dispersed bases at home and(f^rseas-armed with weapons that can be released at high or low level leisure, that the V-force will provide a formidable deterrent against general war for years to come. .16. In addition to its nuclear capability, the V-force has a massive con-conventional bombing potential which can back up the tactical air forcesbverseas and which is a deterrent to limited war. Both nuclear andconventional weapons can be dropped with great accuracy from high or low level, by day or night, regardless of weather conditions. Overseas reinforce-ment is regularly practised by detachments to the Near, Middle and Far East.Last year individual V-bombers also made some 400 overseas flights.17. The tanker force provides for refuelling in flight which adds greatly to the mobility of aircraft of the operational Commands. Its use duringthe past year has substantially reduced the time previously taken to mountreinforcement exercises. Valiant tankers have supported many overseasdetachments including that of 3 Vulcans which in July flew non-stop fromthis country to Australia in 18 hours.18. Valiants and Canberras of the Photographic Reconnaissance forcecompleted air surveys of British Honduras and, in the Pacific, of the solomon Islands, Santa Cruz and the New Hebrides. They also surveyedpart of New Guinea, Papua, Uganda and Rhodesia.Fighter Command19. The introduction of the Lightning 2 has been completed. deliveries of the Lightning 3 will begin this year. This aircraft is an improved weaponssystem and has a better ferry range which will enable it to be used tcreinforce all theatres.        .20. The main Home Air Defence exercise in July 1963 tested the command&apos;s ability satisfactorily to come quickly to a war posture without warning. Overseas reinforcement exercises by squadrons were carried outregularly. Thus, Lightnings have been sent for short periods to cyprus and Javelins to Cyprus, Malta and North Africa. In the autumn, a Javelinsquadron took part in Air Defence exercises in India. Refuelling in flightis regularly practised; it was used by the Javelins en route to and from india. Lightnings have been flight refuelled at night.21. Eleven exchange visits have been made during the year with fighter squadrons of N.A.T.O. Air Forces.22. Service trials of Bloodhound 2 have begun and training is proceedingThis Surface-to-Air Missile system can be carried by air and those heldin this country will be available to reinforce those to be deployed overseas.Bloodhound 1 squadrons are being progressively withdrawn ; this has been avery successful weapon system with an exceptionally high rate of service-ability.23. The Ballistic Missile Early Warning Station at Fylingdales is nowoperational. The introduction of radar with greatly improved performanceis proceeding for Air Defence; these radars will also be used for air traffic Control purposes as part of the plan being prepared by the NationalAir Traffic Control Services. Work on the control centre of a fully integrated
air defence and air traffic control organisation has begun at West Draytonwhere the military and civil air traffic controllers will work alongside eachother. &apos; Qn24. Under the joint programme of evaluation of vertical take-off ancTlanding which has been agreed with the United States and German federal republic, a P. 1127 evaluation unit, manned by officers and airmen fromthe three participating countries, will form during the year at West Rayn-ham. This evaluation will give the R.A.F. early logistic and operationalexperience of VTOL, particularly in the field of tactical air support.Coastal Command25. The purpose of the long-range maritime force is to provide constantsurveillance of the ocean areas of importance to the United Kingdom.It must be able to detect, shadow and if necessary, destroy submarines and surface vessels. Shackletons of Coastal Command and Air Forces overseashave practised these roles in a large number of N.A.T.O., C.E.N.T.O.,S.E.A.T.O. and national exercises in areas stretching from the Norwegiansea to the South Atlantic, from Malta to Nova Scotia and from Aden to singapore. The range, endurance and versatility of the Shackleton also makeit suitable for a variety of other tasks. Shackletons have played an important part in air sea rescue operations, and aircraft have been detached from gibraltar to Aden to assist in internal security duties, and from the UnitedKingdom to the Caribbean to maintain surveillance against intrusions.26. The modernisation of the aircraft and their equipment continues andthe present high efficiency of the Shackleton Force will not only be main-tained but improved. - The Shackleton Mark 3 is to be equipped withauxiliary jet engines to improve its take-off performance.27. Since March 1963, aircraft, helicopters, mountain rescue teams and marine craft have been called out for search and rescue operations on[ ] occasions and [ ] people have beenrescued. Search and rescue by helicopter often involves great risk inadverse conditions and depends not only on the skill of the pilot but also on the resource and courage of the crew. Recognition of this was shown lastyear by the award of the George Medal and of the Air Force Medal to two helicopter winch operators.Transport Command and Transport Forces Overseas28. The build-up of the Argosy force is virtually complete. Squadronsare based in the Middle and Far East as well as in the United Kingdom.A version of the Hawker Siddeley 748 will be used for communicationsflying this year. The freighter version of the H.S.748 will follow in 1965and will augment the short-range transport force. In the Far East the medium and short-range force has been reinforced with more Beverleysas well as Belvedere and Whirlwind helicopters. Belvederes are alsodeployed in the Middle East. The Wessex 2 helicopter is now in serviceand the first squadron will be deployed overseas about the end of thisyear.29. Transport Command and the theatre transport forces have continued the support of Malaysian and British troops deployed in Borneo. . In June,troops and equipment were flown to Swaziland ; in July to British Guiana;
144and in December and January to Cyprus. In addition these forces played a major part in the deployment and support of British forces sent toi$k Africa in January at the request of the governments concerned.$$30. Last year Transport Command participated in 113 exercises for all three Services. In the autumn, for the tri-Service exercise TRIPLEX WEST,Britannias, Argosies, Beverleys and Hastings of Transport Command and theNear East Air Force flew some 5,000 men, 280 tons of equipment, togetherwith 280 vehicles and 4 Whirlwind helicopters from England to Libya andback again. Troops were resupplied by air during the exercise in whichGround Attack Hunters, Whirlwinds and Belvederes of No. 38 Group also provided tactical support.31. Route training flights by medium-range aircraft to Germany and theNear and Middle East are being used increasingly for the carriage of priorityfreight. Regular aero-medical evacuation services are maintained to all themain overseas theatres, and 258 flights were made in 1963.R.A.F. Germany32. The Canberra strike squadrons, have satisfactorily maintained thehigher state of readiness called for by SACEUR last year. In addition to training in the low-level nuclear strike role, squadrons have exercised in the conventional interdictor role, both in Germany and in the Mediterranean.33. In the annual AIRCENT competition, Canberra and Hunter squad-rons of the reconnaissance force won the long and short-range day trophiesrespectively. R.A.F. Germany contributes a squadron of Javelin 9s to theAllied Command Europe Mobile Air Force; this is a &quot;fire brigade&quot; forcedesigned to act immediately in an emergency in support of any particularlyvulnerable area. In practice for this role, Javelin 9s took part in a N.A.T.O.mobile force exercise in Norway in the summer.Near East Air Force34. In Cyprus re-equipment of the Canberra strike squadrons with B.15and B.16 aircraft is complete. These aircraft are capable of striking withnuclear and conventional bombs and with rockets; their conventional capa-bility will be further increased by the introduction of the short-range stand-offA.S.30 weapon which will start this year. The force has taken part inC.E.N.T.O., N.A.T.O. and national exercises which have taken aircraft to southern Rhodesia, East Africa, the Persian Gulf, Iran and Pakistan. Forair defence, Hunters have been replaced by Javelins and the control and reporting radars are being re-engineered and modernised. Whirlwind 10helicopters are now used for search and rescue duties.35. In Malta, the photographic reconnaissance force which it assigned toN.A.T.O. has re-equipped with Canberra PR.9 aircraft which have an improved operational capability at high and low level. The Shackletonscontinue to play their full part in the N.A.T.O. maritime role.Air Forces Middle East36. Shackletons and Hunter fighter/ground attack and reconnaissance aircraft have taken part in operations to maintain law and order in the Pro-tectorate and Federation of South Arabia during the year. AdditionalHunters have been provided to strengthen forces permanently deployed in the theatre.   Shackletons have also taken part in anti-smuggling operations in
the Persian Gulf and in, a C.E.N.T.O. maritime exercise from Karachi.Argosies and Twin Pioneers provided transport support for troops deployedin Swaziland. The theatre transport forces have carried over 10,000 tons-effreight during the year, a figure which illustrates ,the importance of.,^-transport in this area of vast distances and poor surface communications.Far East Air Force37. From the start of operations in Borneo, the Far East Air Force has provided tactical air support for the troops deployed there. More helicopters,including additional Belvederes, have been sent to. the area and these, togetherwith Pioneer aircraft, are providing STOL/VTQL airlift for the forwardground forces. Air transport of supplies between Singapore and Borneohas been regularly provided; over 18,000 passengers, 1,500 tons of freightand many vehicles, light aircraft arid helicopters were air-lifted during 1963.38. Air transport and reconnaissance operations have continued in sup-port of internal security operations along the North Malayan border.39. Last November, 299 British Nationals were evacuated from Djakartato Singapore by Argosy and Hastings aircraft.40. The new Air Defence Centre for Singapore is now operational.41. Canberras and Hunters took part in a major S.E.A.T.O. exercise ofair and ground forces in North Thailand in the summer and flew air defence, ninterdictor and close-support missions. Shackletons detached to Butterworthhave taken part in anti-submarine exercises with units of the Far East Fleet.42. V-bombers have made regular detachments to the Far East Air Force.,     ROYAL AIR FORCE REGIMENT43. The RAF. Regiment celebrated its 21st AnniversaryTast year. TheRegimenfs light anti-aircraft and field squadrons deployed overseas provide a highly mobile defensive force and can be rapidly reinforced from a strategic reserve in the United Kingdom. A Regiment parachute squadron is avail-able to support tactical Operations by No. 38 Group in any part of theworld.44. During the year, field squadrons in the Far East have been detachedto Gan, Brunei and Kuching. One field squadron has been converted to lightanti-aircraft duties but will still be available for ground defence and internal security operations if required, arid a second squadron is to be given a lightanti-aircraft capability.45. In December 1963, the R.A.F. Regiment provided the first Britishpatrols to enter the troubled areas in Nicosia and brought out the first reliablereports on. the situation. Their impartiality was respected on all sides andtheir early action was undoubtedly of great help. An additional R.A.F.Regiment squadron was flown out from the United Kingdom and was on patrol in Cyprus within 48 hours of recall from Christmas leave.... TRAINING, .46. Introduction of the Gnat for advanced flying training will becompleted shortly. Due to extensive use of flight simulators, the averagetime for students to :reach solo stage on the Gnat is shorter than it was with the Vampire, despite the Gnat&apos;s higher performance.
47. Improved selection methods and training procedures have resultedin a marked reduction in training failures particularly for navigators andif^^lectronics officers.J&apos;v48. Aircrew have been attached to Vickers and Short Brothers forliaison, conversion and route proving flying on the V.C.10 and Belfast......49. In Technical Training Command ground training arrangements arebeing changed to suit the future needs of the Service. Formal training at training schools has been reduced and more trade training is being given on units. Basic trade training is being redesigned to match the revised organisation of trades to be introduced, as already announced,on 1st April, 1964.50. Some 1,100 officers and men from 35 Commonwealth and foreigncountries have had flying or technical training with the R.A.F. in thepast year.MAINTENANCE COMMAND51. Maintenance Command stores, prepares for issue and distributesworld-wide nearly 500,000 different items of equipment. - It also providesthose overhaul, modification and salvage services which can be most effectively and economically organised centrally within the Royal Air Force.The Command now undertakes all aircraft salvage work west of Suez. Majorservicing of most V-bombers has recently been centralised at one depot;this saves both money and time. Similarly, an increasing amount ofoverhaul work on aircraft such as the Canberra, Hunter, Argosy andVarsity is now being centralised at. the civilian-manned -depot in NorthernIreland. Maintenance Command also provides some of the supply andservicing teams for supporting theRoyal Air Force in emergency operations and exercises overseas.AIR TRAFFIC CONTROL&quot; 52. Three radar Units, which formed part of the Bloodhound 1 system,are being converted to improve air traffic control over the United Kingdom.These will facilitate control of both military and. civilian traffic above25,000 feet, and in certain special areas at lower levels, in the period beforethe new air. traffic control and air defence radar system is ready for operation.53. At the invitation of the Singapore Government a joint Air traffic control Radar Unit is being set up at Singapore Airport to facilitate thecontrol of civil and military aircraft. This unit will use the radar andother installations provided by the Singapore Government.THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE SOVEREIGN BASEAREAS OF AKROTIRI AND DHEKELIA54. Administration of the Sovereign Base Areas has proceeded smoothlyand cordial relations have been maintained with the authorities of theRepublic &quot;of Cyprus. The Administration and the authorities of theRepublic have continued to co-operate closely, through the medium ofthe Joint Consultative Board and its sub-committees, on the measures necessary to give effect to the Declaration of Her Majesty&apos;s Government
(Cmnd. 1093, Appendix O), particularly in regard to the provision of administrative services for the Cypriot population in the Areas.SERVICE MANPOWERStrength and Recruiting55. The strength of the Royal Air Force on 1st April, 1964, includingwomen and boys, but excluding civilians and local forces, Will be 136,100compared with 143,800 on 1st April, 1963. By 1st April, 1965, thestrength is expected to be 132,400. The table and diagram at Annex Bshow the progressive reduction in the combined Service and civilianstrengths since 1958. Annex C shows the Service strength by types of engagement, and indicates the growth of the long-term element amongserving airmen.56. There were no major recruitment problems in 1963, and require-ments were broadly met in all fields. The number of vacancies for adultsin ground trades has, however, been very small for the past year and insome trades a number of airmen have been offered free discharges.Requirements for adults in ground trades will rise substantially later in1964 when entrants of high quality will again be needed.Officers57. Entries of cadets to Cranwell in 1963 were larger than for manyyears. The requirement for direct entry pilots and navigators was fullymet but there was a small deficiency of air electronics officers.58. Ground branches which require professional qualifications still have recruiting difficulty. This is part of a national problem.59. During 1963, the University Air Squadrons provided 40 entrants tothe General Duties branch and 16 entrants to Ground branches. There arenow University Air Squadrons at eighteen Universities, a new squadronhaving been formed at the University of Wales. The squadrons not onlyprovide high quality officers but are most valuable in maintaining liaison between the Universities and the Royal Air Force.University Cadetship Scheme60. The University Cadetship Scheme was successfully launched and22 awards were made. This scheme provides opportunities for those who wish to complete a university course before making a permanent careerin the Royal Air Force General Duties or Technical branches. In bothof these branches there is a need for a number of graduates.Airmen61. There has been no difficulty in getting the small numbers of adultrecruits required. Changes in requirements have resulted in surpluses insome trades and deficiencies in others (mainly ancillary trades) but these have had no serious effect on operational efficiency.62. The new trade structure, which introduces important changes inthe career structure and system of progression in the ground trades, was announced in March, 1963, and will take effect on 1st April, 1964. Thenew arrangements are simpler than those they will replace and are bettersuited to the future.
63. The high quality of youth entrants has been maintained. The aimnow is to provide training more suited to the higher standard of entrantrjfjsx coming forward and to the future technical needs of the Royal Air1&quot;j**fe. Accordingly, the youth entry system will be revised in the autumn of 1964. The new technician, craft and administrative apprenticeshipswill provide a first-class grounding in a variety of trades.Women&apos;s Royal Air Force64. The Women&apos;s Royal Air Force makes a major contribution to thework of the Royal Air Force not only at home but also overseas whereabout a fifth of the W.R.A.F. is now serving. The range of duties carriedout by the W.R.A.F. is steadily widening; for example, the first W.R.A.F.Air Traffic Controllers are in post and W.R.A.F. Air Quartermasters are serving in Transport Command. This variety in the choice of work andthe excellent opportunities for service abroad are no doubt partly responsiblefor the fact that recruitment to the W.R.A.F., both of officers and air-women, has continued to be satisfactory.CADET FORCES65. A large proportion of the best recruits to the Royal Air Forcecontinues to come from the Air Training Corps and the Air Sectionsof the Combined Cadet Force. Over the last five years over 60 per cent,of the officer cadets for the General Duties branch and more than 40 percent, of the officer cadets for the ground branches and of direct entryaircrew, apprentices and boy entrants have come from these sources.66. Last year more than 30,000 passenger flights in R.A.F. aircraft were given to cadets. Three hundred cadets flew to Germany and theFar East, and 60 took part in the International Exchange Scheme with canada, the United States and a number of European countries. Twenty-two thousand cadets attended camps at Royal Air Force Stations in thiscountry.67. Some 2,300 cadets were trained to elementary glider pilot standard,and 5,000 younger cadets were given flights in gliders.CIVILIANS68. The Estimates provide for the employment of the following num-bers of civilians on 1st April, 1964:  Royal Observer Corps (Vote 2).........      ... 78Headquarters (Vote 3)     ...      ......      ......       4,480United Kingdom-based Staff at Outstations at home and overseas (Vote 4)       ......      ...      .....,     46,560Locally-engaged staff overseas (excluding locally-engagedMeteorological staff) (Vote 4).......    ...      ...     21,740Meteorological Office (Vote 4)    .............     3,590Sovereign Base Areas (Vote 9)     ......      ...... 13876,586
Certain staff, mainly at Headquarters, hitherto borne on Air Voteshave been transferred to the Central Vote.  The number so transferred is330.ORGANISATION69. The Royal Air Force uses complicated equipment. Highly skilledmanpower is expensive to train. The effective and economical use of manpower, is,, therefore, of supreme importance. There is well triedmachinery for controlling establishments which combines the specialtalents and aptitudes of both Service and civil staff. There is a continuingprocess of examination of the need for particular tasks and. of the best methods of carrying them out. Work Study pioneered in Service use bythe Royal Air Force, Organisation and Method investigations, studies carriedout at the Central Servicing Development Establishment and by the scientific Adviser and his staff are all directed towards the critical examina-tion of methods of work in the Service and the, evolution of more efficient and more economical practices.70. One of the most effective contributions to economy is the concen-tratipn of units on a smaller number of well-found stations whereveroperational and functional considerations permit. In the last twelve months,much has been done in this direction.&apos; In Bomber Command, the disband-ment of THOR units has not only led to the closure of a number ofsatellite bases, but has released several permanent stations for other uses.One of these, R.A.F. Feltwell, has become the new home of the OfficerCadet Training Unit, allowing the RA.Fi station at Jurby, which is largely in temporary construction, to close. In Fighter Command, a number of stations have been declared surplus, including Horsham St. Faith and Middle-ton St. George. In Coastal Command, new deployment changes make it possible to hand over operational control of Aldergrove, now the main civilairport in Northern Ireland, to the Ministry of Aviation in June, 1964. in technical Training Command, the short-term reduction in recruit intakeshas resulted in the closure of RA.F. Bridgnorth which is mainly of tem-porary construction. Steps such as these have made possible significantsavings in capital and running costs and allowed valuable assets to bereturned to the community.71. A comprehensive review has been undertaken of the number ofcommunication aircraft in the United Kingdom, and reductions have beenmade to enable the transfer of resources to the maintenance Of the frontline. The reorganised force has been put under the control of transport command on a regional basis.72. In the field of management the emphasis for the future must remain on what Lord. Trenchard, in 1922, described as &quot; the expansion of thepower of material and personnel without increasing either&quot;.Automatic Data Processing73. The transfer to automatic data processing equipment of the records of service and the computation of pay of all civilian staff in the UnitedKingdom is virtually complete. Data processing machinery for the integratedsystem to control the supply of equipment is in use at RAF. stations ;the linking of its operations to the central computer will start in 1964.
74. A computer has been ordered for a third automatic data processingsystem to,deal with the Service records of airmen, to maintain their payable,p^ounts centrally, and to provide information for use in the manning ofi^xpkoyal Air Force ; it is hoped that this will start working in 1965.WORKS-75. During the coming year, improvements will be made to the airfield and technical facilities of Coastal Command; work will continue on thenew air defence radar system, and planning will begin on a second transport command base for long-range transport aircraft. Overseas, substantial improvements will be made to the aircraft servicing facilities in the middle east, and work will start on a school extension and other amenity services.In the Far East, work is due to begin on new technical facilities and amenities.76. The improvement of domestic accommodation for single and marriedofficers and airmen is continuing. The married quarter building programme is mainly directed towards providing new accommodation in the UnitedKingdom where, in the coming year, some 1,200 houses for R.A.F. per-sonnel are due to be completed.METEOROLOGY77. Enquiries from industry, commerce and the general public forweather information increased by over 25 per cent., the number for theyear approaching one million. Calls on the Automatic Telephone WeatherService increased at a similar rate and reached eight million.78. Promising results have been obtained from using a computer toproduce a forecast weather map for 24 hours ahead. It is hoped to instala larger and faster machine in 1964.79. Since 1955, the Meteorological Office has experimented with fore-casting the weather for a month ahead in general terms. The issue ofsuch forecasts to the public began in December 1963. The forecasts,together with a review of the normal climate of the month, appear in anew publication &quot; Monthly Weather Survey and Prospects &quot;.80. Further study is being devoted to the world-wide circulation of the atmosphere. This is an important field of research and the primary aimis to understand the mechanism of long-term weather anomalies.81. By agreement with the University of Edinburgh and other academicinterests, the Meteorological Office Observatory at Eskdalemuir, Dum-friesshire, is to become the main national centre for seismological observa-tions. Underground vaults have been constructed to house new standardinstruments, presented by the United States Government, and to provide facilities for research.82. The Meteorological Office is responsible for an experiment to measure the distribution of ozone in the high atmosphere, using the Anglo-Americansatellite UK-2. Integration of the experiment in the satellite was completed on time in October, but the launch has been delayed by difficulties with
the United States &quot; Scout&quot; rocket vehicle. Work has begun in the Brack-nell laboratories on a similar experiment to measure the distribution ofmolecular oxygen in the low ionosphere, to be carried on satellite UK-Jjgx83. The first firings of the 5-inch meteorological rocket, designed? to measure wind and temperature to a height of 200,000 feet, took place fromthe South Uist range in November.84. The Meteorological Office continues to play an important part inthe work of the World Meteorological Organisation. A conference of directors of Commonwealth Meteorological Services was held at Bracknellin May.- FINANCE85. The net total of Defence (Air) Estimates for 1964-65 is  503,800,000.Further details of the financial provision required with the corresponding figures for 1963-64, including a Supplementary Estimate, are given in annex C to the section on Defence Statistics, on page 65.

the United States &quot; Scout&quot; rocket vehicle. Work has begun in the Brack-nell laboratories on a similar experiment to measure the distribution ofmolecular oxygen in the low ionosphere, to be carried on satellite UK-ac--83. The first firings of the 5-inch meteorological rocket, designed? to measure wind and temperature to a height of 200,000 feet, took place fromthe South Uist range in November.84. The Meteorological Office continues to play an important part inthe work of the World Meteorological Organisation. A conference of directors of Commonwealth Meteorological Services was held at Bracknellin May.FINANCE85. The net total of Defence (Air) Estimates for 1964-65 is  503,800,000.Further details of the financial provision required with the corresponding figures for 1963-64, including a Supplementary Estimate, are given in annex C to the section on Defence Statistics, on page 65.


A Victor with Blue Steel.A Belvedere helicopter on an army support mission in eastern Sarawak.

A Victor with Blue Steel.A Belvedere helicopter on an army support mission in eastern Sarawak.

DEFENCE (AIR) ESTIMATES 1964-65cAIN HEADS OF EXPENDITURE (NET)Pensions, &amp;c. ( 15-6m)R.A.F. Personnel (a) ( !75-4m)Personnel^costs 48%Reserve Personnel ( 0-8m)Civilian Personnel (b) ( 50-4m)Petrol and Oil ( 26-8m)Aircraft and Equipment (c) ( 225-4m)Materiel and other^costs 52%Miscellaneous (d) ( 9-4m)Total  503-8 millions(a)  Pay, allowances, movements, clothing, accommodation services, &amp;c. (Vote 1 and partsof Votes 5, 6, 7, 8 and 9).(6)  Pay, allowances, movements, special clothing, &amp;c. (Votes 3 and 4 and parts of Votes 5,7 and 9).(c) Excluding parts of Vote 7 included in Personnel Costs.(d) Freight of stores, telecommunications and miscellaneous minor expenditure (parts of votes 5, 6, 8 and 9).

DEFENCE (AIR) ESTIMATES 1964-65.AIN HEADS OF EXPENDITURE (NET)Pensions, &amp;c. ( 15-6m)RAF. Personnel (a) ( !75-4m)Personnel costs 48%Reserve Personnel ( 0-8m)Civilian Personnel (b) ( 50 -4m)Petrol and Oil ( 26-8m)Aircraft and Equipment (c) ( 225 -4m)Materiel and other,costs 52%Miscellaneous (d) ( 9-4m)Total  503-8 millions(a) Pay, allowances, movements, clothing, accommodation services, &amp;c. (Vote 1 and partsof Votes 5, 6, 7, 8 and 9).(b) Pay, allowances, movements, special clothing, &amp;c. (Votes 3 and 4 and parts of Votes 5,7 and 9).(c) Excluding parts of Vote 7 included in Personnel Costs.id) Freight of stores, telecommunications and miscellaneous minor expenditure (parts of votes 5, 6, 8 and 9).
strengths in thousands at 1ST july	1958	1959	1960	1961	1962	1963	1964 (a)SERVICE-							Royal Air Force	184-9 (70-7%)	171-3 (69-7%)	163-8 (68-8%)	155-5 (67-9%)	148-3 (66-7%)	142-0 (65-5%)	134-1 (64-5%)Local forces en-listed abroad...	1-7 (0-7%)	1-6 (0-6%)	1-1 (0-5%)	1-1 (0-5%)	1-1 (0-5%)	1-1 (0-5%)	11 (0-5%)CIVILIAN (b)-							Non-industrial...	25-6 (9-8%)	26-6 (10-8%)	27-2 (H-4%)	27-6 (12-0%)	28-2 (12-7%)	29-3 (13-5%)	29-8 (14-3%)Industrial	49-2 (18-8%)	46-4 (18-9%)	45-8 (19-3%)	45-0 (19-6%)	44-7 (20-1%)	44-4 (20-5%)	43-0 (20-7%)TOTALS	261-4	245-9	237-9	229-2	222-3	216-8	208-0(a)  Estimated.(b) In order to show a fair comparison, figures prior to 1963 have been adjusted toallow for the transfer of works staff to the Ministry of Public Building and works with effect from 1st April, 1963, and those prior to 1964 to allow for the transferof certain staff to the Ministry of Defence central staffs with effect from 1st April,1964.Notes: (i) Figures in brackets indicate percentages of total personnel.(ii) Figures for civilians exclude those engaged on services for the United states forces and Royal Canadian Air Force in the United Kingdom.COMBINED ROYAL AIR FORCE AND CIVILIANSTRENGTHS, 1958-1964 tl
COMBINED ROYAL AIR FORCE AND CIVILIANSTRENGTHS, 1958-1964
strengths in thousands at 1ST july	1958	1959	1960	1961	1962	1963	1964 (a)OFFICERS 							Royal Air Force Women&apos;s  Royal Air Force and Princess Mary&apos;s Royal Air Force Nursing Service	23-5 (12-7%) 0-8 (0-4%)	21-8 (12-7%) 0-8 (0-5%)	21-7 (13-3%) 0-8 (0-5%)	21-4 (13-8%) 0-7 (0-4%)	20-8 (14-0%) 0-8 (0-5%)	20-7 (14-6%) 0-8 (0-6%)	20-5 (15-3%) 0-8 (0-6%)AIRMEN  AND AIRWOMEN 							Airmen: National Service	38-1 (20-6%)	23-4 (13-7%)	18-2 (11-1%)	11-5 (7-4%)	3-2 (2-2%)	-	-Airwomen	4-0 (2-2%)	4-5 (2-6%)	4-9 (3-0%)	5-2 (3-3%)	6-3 (4-2%)	6-2 (4-4%)	5-1 (3-8%)Airmen on regu-lar engagements of: Under 5 years 5 to 8 years ... 9 years and over	29-9 (16-2%) 19-4 (10-5%) 69-2 (37-4%)	23-3 (13-6%) 18-1 (10-6%) 79-4 (46-3%)	13-8 (8-4%) 16-1 (9-8%) 88-3 (53-9%)	7-7 (5-0%) 14-8 (9-5%) 94-2 (60-6%)	2-4 (1-6%) 14-4 (9-7%) 100-4 (67-8%)	0-6 (0-4%) 12-4 (8-7%) 101-3 (71-3%)	01 (0-1%) 9-2 (6-9%) 98-4 (73-3%)TOTAL PERSONNEL	184-9	171-3	163-8	155-5	148-3	142-0	134-1(a)  Estimated.Note: Figures in brackets indicate percentages of total personnel.STRENGTH OF THE ROYAL AIR FORCE,1958-1964 at
ANNEX C (continued)STRENGTH OF THE ROYAL AIR FORCE, 1958-1964OFFICERSNATIONAL SERVICE AIRMENAIRWOMENAIRMEN (UNDER 5 YEARS)AIRMEN (5-8 YEARS)AIRMEN 0 YEARS &amp; OVER)
CIVIL defence Until general disarmament has been achieved the possibility that nuclear weapons might be used against this country can never be totally excluded.The Government believe this possibility to be remote, but it cannot be ignored. In face of it, the Government have a clear duty to make prepara-tions to mitigate the consequences of nuclear attack for those who wouldsurvive. Within the framework of our defence policy, therefore, civil defence preparations have an essential part to play. These preparations involvealmost every aspect of national life and embrace all measures necessaryto the survival of the community following nuclear attack.2. What could civil defence achieve? The Government have neversought to conceal that a nuclear attack would cause millions of casualties and unimaginable destruction. No one can assess exactly how great the tollwould be: many factors would play their part; but, terrible though the disaster would be, it would be likely that millions would survive. Thosesurvivors would stand in urgent need of the assistance which a civil defence organisation, planned and prepared in advance, could provide. This is the underlying principle of all civil defence preparations. They are not based onany attempt to minimise the effects of nuclear weapons. Civil Defencecould do little to help those within the areas of complete devastation;but, outside those areas, it could reduce the suffering of large numbers ofmen,&quot; women and children, and help them to survive. Civil Defence isnot and never can be a comprehensive insurance against nuclear attack.How effective it would be depends on the premium which we can afford,having regard to other commitments and to our assessment of the likelihood of the disaster. But so long as nuclear attack remains a possibility, it is no more than prudent and humanitarian to take out such insurance as we canagainst its effects.3. Within the limits of our resources, civil defence preparations must be broadly based and realistically planned. The lines on which work should proceed if these objectives are to be attained were laid down in the revised programme of home defence expenditure announced in the report on defence for 1961. In addition to improving the efficiency of the voluntary civil defence and emergency fire services, particular attention has been given within this programme to two main objectives of the Governmenfs plans.These are, first, the preparation of an emergency system of control whichcould provide a framework of administration following a nuclear attack, and secondly, arrangements for the maintenance and restoration of supplies and services essential to the survival of the nation.4. For the emergency system of control, wartime regional seats of Govern-ment have been provided and equipped in England and Wales, and similarcentres in Scotland. Work on improving those controls is going ahead. Fromthe regional seats of government the emergency chain of control extends tolocal authorities. As explained in the report on defence for 1962, discus-sions have been held with local authorities about the arrangements for control within the regions.   In the light of these discussions, changes are
being made in the system of control below regional level, which will hence-forth be based entirely on local authority areas. These changes wouldenahflL &apos;he governmental and administrative resources of the country to beused^more effectively throughout the period when the nation might bestruggling to survive.5. Closely linked with the emergency system of control are emergencyorganisations for essential supplies and services. The aim here is to achieveflexibility in our control arrangements so as to make the best use of survivingresources, and to concentrate expenditure on items of particular importance.Thus, in addition to the organisational plans which have been made, reserves of food, medical supplies and oil have been stockpiled and special measures taken for the continued operation of other essential services such as emergencyports and anchorages and for the safeguarding of water supplies. Sub-stantial sums have also been extended on providing emergency communica-tions and on the maintenance of broadcasting in war.6. In our civil defence preparations, the police, fire and hospital servicesand the Civil Defence Corps and Industrial Civil Defence Units have anessential part to play. Their organisation, training and equipment is animportant part of our peacetime preparations. Our plans rely also on the close support and co-operation of units of the Armed Forces, and in 1964new arrangements will be made to train units of the Territorial Army in emergency fire-fighting techniques. The provision of Royal Observer Corpsposts and headquarters required for the warning and monitoring organisa-tion is nearing completion. The installation of equipment for the more rapid transmission of warnings should be substantially completed in 1964.7. The Government have also reviewed the problem of providing shelteragainst radio-active fall-out. Advice on improvisation of such shelter is contained in Civil Defence Handbook No. 10. In addition, some communalshelter would be necessary for those living in certain types of dwelling witha low protective factor against fall-out, such as prefabricated houses andcaravans. A detailed survey is required to determine the extent of this need, to identify suitable existing accommodation, and to determine whateach shelter would require in the way of adaptation and provisioning. before considering a wider survey, the Government intend first to carry out a pilotsurvey in selected areas of the country to find out the best methods of collecting and analysing the necessary data. Plans have been made for the holding of this pilot survey during 1964.8. In 1964 work will be carried forward on the lines set out above. Forthis purpose [ 25m.] has been provided in the coming financial year. In aconstantly changing situation, the task of civil defence can never be regardedas complete and plans must be kept continually under review. Our generalobjective must be to complete physical preparations as our resources allowand to maintain and improve the state of readiness which has already been achieved. In this the Government will continue to rely on the co-operation and assistance of all those who would have an essential contribution to make to the survival of the nation.
DEFENCE STATISTICS 1964-65Manpower1. An analysis of the active strengths of the three Services is given in annex A, Table 1. The strengths in Table 2 are additional to thosein Table 1 and consist of forces and units enlisted overseas and personnelenlisted into the forces on local service terms.2. In 1964-65 the Armed Forces will need about 47,000 male entrants.This figure includes men who enter upon regular engagements and thosewho enter as boys, apprentices and juniors.3. An analysis of the Volunteer Reserve and Auxiliary Forces and national Service Reserves for the three Services is given in Annex A, Table 3.finance. The estimated cost of the defence programme is:   m.(a) as,estimated for 1963-64 ......      1,837 70(b) as estimated for 1964-65        ......5. The division between Departments for 1963-64 and 1964-65 isshown below:-	 m.		 m.	1963-64		1964-65Ministry of Defence	19-98	Ministry of Defence			(Central)......	25-97Admiralty......	440-96	Ministry of Defence			(Navy)   ......	496-02War Office......	491-03	Ministry of Defence			(Army)  ......	525-41Air Ministry	503-20	Ministry of Defence			(Air)      ......	503-80Ministry of Aviation	230-47	Ministry of Aviation			(including Special			Materials Vote)...	274-96Ministry of Public		Ministry of Public	Building  and		Building  and	Works   ......	146-66	Works   ......	166-34Atomic   Energy		Atomic   Energy	Authority	5-40	Authority	6-80	1,837-70		1,999-30As from 1st April 1964 the Ministry of Public Building and Works willbear the cost of defence works services previously borne on the Ministryof Aviation and Royal Ordnance Factories Votes. This accounts for  8-91m.of the increase in the Ministry of Public Building and Works expenditureon defence.   There are compensating reductions of  7-53m. and  l-28m.
respectively in the Ministry of Aviation and Royal Ordnance Factoriesexpenditure.cw. breakdown of the 1964-65 Estimates is at Annex B and analysesof the major variations between 1963-64 and 1964-65 in respect of Ministryof Defence (Central), (Navy), (Army), (ROFs) and (Air) Votes are at annex C, Tables 1-5 respectively.7. In the Financial year 1964-65  24-lm. will be provided for HomeDefence expenditure by Civil Departments. This compares with  23-01m.in the Estimates for 1963-64. An analysis of the proposed expenditure is given in Annex D.
ANNEX a table 1   Analysis of Active Strengths (Figures in Thousands)	1st April, 1963 (actual)				1st April, 1964 (estimate)				1st April, 21965 (estimate)			-	Royal Navy	Army	R.A.F.	Total	Royal Navy	Army	R.A.F.	Total	Royal Navy	Army	R.A.F.	TotalRegular Adult Males   .........	87.7	170.9	130.4	389.0	89.8	171.7	126.0	387.5	92.1	176.7	123.9	392.7National Service............	-	2.6		2.6	-	-	- -	-	 	 	 	_Women...............	3.5	6.8	7.3	17.6	3.7	6.6	6.1	16.4	3.8	6.8	5.6	16.2Boys      ...............	4.6	10.3	6.1	21.0	4.7	11.6	4.0	20.3	4.9	11.6	2.9	19.4Totals............	95.8	190.6	143.8	430.2	98.2	189.9	136.1	424.2	100.8	195.1	132.4	428.stable 2   Forces Enlisted Outside the United KingdomStrengths at 1st January, 1964Royal Navy...Army......Royal Air ForceTotal2,10027,8001,00030,900
Table 3   Analysis of Volunteer Reserve and Auxiliary Forces and National Service Reserves	Strength at 1st January, 1963				Strength at 1st January, 1964				Normal	Volunteers	Part-Time	Total	Normal	Volunteers	Part-Time	Total	Volunteers	from N.S.	N.S.		Volunteers	from N.S.	N.S.	Royal Navy								Royal Naval Reserve	7,755	1,016	89	8,860	7,180	943	46	8,169Royal Marine Forces Volunteer Reserve...	939	72	27	1,038	979	20	13	1,012Royal Naval Special Reserve     ......	 	 	1,691	1,691	 	 	502	502Women&apos;s Royal Naval Reserve......	995	 	-	995	978	 	 	978Army								Territorial Army   ............	101,234	2,389	53,583	157,206	105,116	1,663	24,703	131,482Women&apos;s Royal Army Corps (T.A.)	4,543	 	 	4,543	4,443	 	 	4,443Queen Alexandra^ Royal Army Nursing								Corps (T.A.)     ............	295	 	 	295	263	 	 	263Army Emergency Reserve......	14,037	551	107,648	122,236	13,763	305	79,267	93,335Women&apos;s Royal Army Corps (A.E.R.) ...	84	 	 	84	88	 	 	88Queen Alexandra^ Royal Army Nursing								Corps (A.E.R.)............	91	 -	 	91	89	 	 	89Royal Air Force								Royal Auxiliary Air Force        ......	340	4	 	344	354	3	 	357Women&apos;s Royal Auxiliary Air Force	130	 	 	130	130	 	 	130Royal Air Force Volunteer Reserve	1,445	18	 	1,463	1,062	3	 	1,065Women&apos;s Royal Air Force Volunteer								Reserve   ...............	42	 	 	42	18	_	_	18Royal Air Force Reserve of Officers (N.S.)								and Class H of the Air Force Reserve...	 	 	34,943	34,943	 	-	21,035	21,035Totals   ............	131,930	4,050	197,981	333,961	134,463	2,937	125,566	262,966
ANNEX BDivision of the Defence Budget under the Principal Headings (v)Financial Year 1964-65(  million)Item1. Pay, &amp;c, of service personnel    ......2. Pay, &amp;c, of Re-serve, territorial and auxiliary forces, and grants for administration,&amp;c.......3. Pay, &amp;c, of Civi-lians      ......4. Movements5, Supplies: (a) Petrol, oil andlubricants   ...(b) Food and ration allowance ...(c)fuel and light...(rf) MiscellaneousItem 5 total. Production and re-search (i)......7. (a) Works, build-ings and land(6) Associated Ex-penditureItem 7 total . Miscellaneouseffective services...9. Non-effectivechargesTotals2 Ministry of Defence												3 Ministry of Aviation			4 Ministry of Public Building and				5 Totals	(a) Central			(A) Navy			(c) Army			(rf) Air						Works					Gross	a in a	Net	Gross	a in a	Net	Gross	a in a	Net	Gross	a in a	Net	Gross	a in a	Net	Gross	a in a	Net	Gross	a in a	Net8-95	-	8-95	90-25	1-78	88-47	167-73	11-12	156-61	144-07	7-57	136-50	1-82	-	1-82	-	-	-	412-82	20-47	392-35			1-32		1-32	19-20	0-23	18-97	1-08	0-27	0-81			_	_	_	 	21-60	0-50	21103-13 0-63	-	3-13 0-63	60-52 11-08	2-25 0-23	58-27 10-85	121-43 28-89	1-55 1-37	119-88 27-52	52-52 15-92	4-10 2-22	48-42 13-70	29-11 3-31	 	29-11 3-31	-	-		266-71 59-83	7-90 3-82	258-81 56-010-01	_	001	16-45	1-73	14-72	6-43	0-68	5-75	28-75	200	26-75	1-32	-	1-32	-	-	-	52-96	4-41	48-550-68	-	0-68	12-87 6-44 0-71	1-71 1-59	11 16 4-85 0-71	28-31 13-29 2-71	4-37 2-77 019	23-94 10-52 2-52	17-90 10-07 1-92	2-26 3-14 0-24	15-64 6-93 1-68	1-27		1-27	-		-	59 08 31-07 6 02	8-34 7-50 0-43	50-74 23-57 5-590-69	-	0-69	36-47 299-06	5-03 25-65	31-44 273-41	50-74 (iv) 206-37	801 (iv) 93-33	42-73 113-04	58-64 254-50	7-64 20-25	51-00 234-25	2-59 (iv) 590-36	(iv) 350-32	2-59 240-04	_	_	_	149-13 (ii) 1,018-84	20-68 (ii) 158-10	128-45 (iii) 867-5412-71	5-19	7-52	10-64	7-39	3-25	21-91	17-68	4-23	8-80	5-67	3-13	4-28	705	D-2-77	159-45 26-23	17-56 1-78	141-89 24-45	217-79 26-23	60-54 1-78	157-25 24-4512-71	5-19	7-52	10-64	7-39	3-25	21-91	17-63	4-23	8-80	5-67	3-13	4-28	7-05	02-77	185-68	19-34	166-34	244-02	62-32	181-705-18	013	5-05	915	2-18	6-97	10-67	3-38	7-29	9-54	9-19	0-35	1-07	0-21	0-86	-	-	-	35-61	15-09	20-52_	_	 	22-09	0-05	22-04	35-46	0-32	35-14	15-79	015	15-64	-	-	-	-	-	-	73-34	0-52	72-8231 -29	5-32	25-97	540-58	44-56	496-02	(iv) 662-40	(iv) 136-99	525-41	560-86	57-06	503-80	(iv) 632-54	(iv) 357-58	274-96	185-68	19-34	166-34	(ii) 2,281-90	(ii) 289-40	(iii) 1,999-30notes:  (i)  Includes the costof development work undertaken by industry under contract, the purchase of stores for research and development establishments, the Ministry oration(ii) to it^Xtk^^UlT^s to the Ministry of Aviation and Defence (Army) Purchasing (Repayment) Services Votes the g.    totalsof columns 2-4 have been reduced by  331-45 million.M includes ?e nce1^^^ Customers carried on the respective Purchasing (Repayment) Services(v) &apos;t^^X^^&quot;V^^^S^ of  23-5 million being the difference between expenditure (including progress payments) and receipts on theMinistry of Aviation and Defence (Army) Purchasing (Repayment) Services Votes.
ANNEX CAnalysis of Major Variations between 1964-65 and 1963-64Table 1 - Defence (Central)ServiceEstimates1964-65 (Net)Estimates andSupplementaryEstimates1963-64 (Net)(a)Increase 4-Decrease -Main Causes of VariationHeadquarters and Outstations:Administrative Services (SubheadsA. 1-4).International DefenceOrganisations :(i) British elements of N.A.T.O.,C.E.N.T.O. and S.E.A.T.O.(Subheads B.1^1).(ii) International     Subscriptions(Subheads C.l-3).o\   (iii) N.A.T.O.  InfrastructureU) (Subhead D.1).(iv) C.E.N.T.O.   Infrastructure(Subhead D.2).Miscellaneous Assistance:(i) Military Training Assistance(Subhead E).(ii) Mutual  Defence  AssistanceAgreement with the UnitedStates of America (Sub-head F).(iii) Scott Polar Research Insti-tute (Subhead G).Totals......... 8,422,0006,356,00033,743,0007,210,000130,00030,00080,0002,00025,973,000 6,992,0005,525,5003,405,5008,119,000500,00036,000120,0002,00024,700,000 -1,430,000-f 830,5004- 337,500- 909,000- 370,000- 6,000- 40,000-f 1,273,000Improved rates of pay, and additional posts arising from re-organisation. Expenditure on equipment and rental of circuits for the Defence Communications Centre and on othertelecommunication requirements. Increased costs of the United Kingdom Central Codifica-tion Authority.Increased number and higher rates of pay of seconded personnel. Increased provision forhirings.Increases in total common expenses of N.A.T.O.Decreased expenditure on projects in the U.K., partly offset by a reduction in related receipts.Reduction due to approaching completion of schemes for military facilities and installations.Decreased expenditure on military training assistance to C.E.N.T.O. Forces.Decrease in the amount due to be paid as the U.K. contribution towards the sterling expensesof the U.S.A.(a) Original Estimate (H.C. 120 of 12th February, 1963)      ...................................................Supplementary Estimate (H.C.      of 10th February, 1964)      ................................................Add Adjustment for purposes of comparison to take account of transfer of functions from the Service Departments (-1- 4,123,000) and to the Cabinet Office (Class I (3)of Civil Estimates) (- 19,000) on 1st April, 1964       ................................................... 19,980,000616,00020,596,0004,104,000 24,700,000
ANNEX c table 2 - Defence (Navy)ServiceEstimate1964-65 (Net)Estimate1963-64 (Net)Increase 4-Decrease-Main Causes of VariationsPay, etc., of the royal navy and royal marines.Royal Naval Reserves ...Navy Department Head-quarters.Research and Develop-ment and other Scien-scientific Services.Medical Services, Educa-tion and Civilians onFleet Services.Naval Stores, Armament,Victualling and other material Supply Ser-vices.H.M. Ships, Aircraft and weapons, New Con-struction and Repairs.Lands and BuildingsMiscellaneous   EffectiveServices.Non-Effective Services ...Additional  married quarters.Total84,222,0001,323,00010,657,00028,025,00014,615,000174,822,000147,660,000962,00011,692,00022,036,0001,00075,286,0001,292,0009,989,60025,873,50013,073,500138,470,000142,700,000*82,300*11,496,70021,687,0001,000-I- 8,936,000+ 31,000+   667,400+ 2,151,500-f- 1,541,5004-36,352,000+ 4,960,000+   879,700-f- 195,300-h   349,000Increases in Naval pay; increased rates of London and LodgingAllowances; increased strengths and higher numbers in the far east; and higher national insurance contributions.Increases in Naval pay.Higher numbers of naval and civilian staff to meet the Polaris pro-gramme; increased pay and national insurance contributions.Increased provision for Research and Development programmes and increased civilian numbers required to meet the programmes;increased pay and national insurance contributions.Increase in Naval and civilian pay and national insurance contribu-tions; increased requirements for medical stores; continuedcivilianisation of naval posts.Increased pay of personnel in Supply Establishments; higher prices,initial provision of electronic etc., equipment for Polaris submarines;increasing cost of maintenance of modern aircraft; increased pro-vision for new Stores Support Ships and Tankers under construction;increased provision and cost of armament stores. Increased numbers to be victualled, and clothed.Increased pay of Dockyard personnel, increase provision for navaland repayment New Construction offset by reduced provision formodernisation, conversions and contract refits; reduced provisionfor the purchase of production aircraft modified by increased provision for additional work on the aircraft conversion programme.Increased provision for purchase of land (mainly for Polaris); greaterprovision for hiring married accommodation; and reduction inreceipts from sales of lands and buildings.Increased provision for telecommunications, postage and travelling expenses partly offset by increased receipts.Increases in Naval pensions and increased numbers of awards andcommutations.496,015,000439,951,600t-1-56,063,400* These figures have been further adjusted to take account of the transfer of the cost of machinery items from Vote 8 to Vote 7.t Adjusted by  1.008m. to take account of the Defence Reorganisation (Cmnd. 2097).
ANNEX c table 3   Defence (Army)Vote	Service	Estimates	Estimates (a)	Increase 4-		1964-65 (Net)	1963-64 (Net)	Decrease-1		 	 	 	Pay, etc., of the Army...	156,610,000	144,242,000	-1-12,368,0002	Reserve  Forces,  Terri-	21,480,000	20,710,000	-f-   770,000	torial Army and Cadet				Forces.			3	Army Department Head-	6,479,000	6,416,150	-f-     62,850	quarters.			4	Civilians at Outstations...	113,400,000	110,820,000	4- 2,580,0005	Movements     ......	27,520,000	27,385,000	4-   135,0006	Supplies.........	42,730,000	41,501,000	-f 1,229,0007	Stores and Equipment...	107,500,000	87,300,000	H-20,200,0008	Lands,   Buildings   and	9,670,000	6,982,000	4- 2,688,000	Works.			9	Miscellaneous   Effective	2,480,000	5,709,000	- 3,229,000	Services.			10	Non-Effective Services ...	35,140,000	34,850,000	4-   290,00011	Additional  Married	1,000	1,000		Quarters.				Total    ......	523,010,000	485,916,150	4-37,093,850Main Causes of VariationMainly higher rates of pay and marriage allowance resulting fromthe 1964 pay review.Increased provision for the Territorial Army.^Higher rates of pay partly offset by lower strengths.Increased expenditure on movement of personnel and stores partly offset by payment of less compensation in 1964-65 for the termina-tion of troopship charter.Increased requirements for heating fuels and higher rates of ration allowance.Mainly increased deliveries of vehicles, weapons and other fightingequipment.Mainly increased provision for the hiring of married quarters at homeand overseas.Increased recoveries for the occupation of married quarters and reduced contribution towards the cost of the South ArabianFederation Regular Army.Higher rates of awards partly offset by fewer retirements and areduction in the numbers of pensioners.(a) As in the Estimates, for purposes of comparison these figures have been adjusted for transfer of  1,514,850 to Defence (Central) Vote.Table 4 - Royal Ordnance FactoriesVote	Service	Estimate 1964-65 (Net)	Estimate (6) 1963-64 (Net)	Increase 4-Decrease -	Main Cause of VariationR.O.F.	Expenses of operating the Royal Ordnance Factories.	  2,400,000	  2,250,000	  4- 150,000	Increased expenditure on plant and materials.(b) As in the Estimates, for purposes of comparison these figures have been adjusted to take account of transfers to Civil Estimates, Class IX, 8 in 1964-65.
ANNEX c table 5 - Defence (Air)			Estimates and			Vote	Service	Estimates	Supplementary	Increase+		Main Causes of Variation		1964-65 (Net)	Estimate (a)	Decrease-					1963-64 (Net)					 	 		 	1	Pay, etc., of the Air Force	136,500,000	125,980,000(6)	-r-10,520,000		Higher rates of pay and allowances resulting from the 1964 Pay review.2	Reserve and  Auxiliary Services.	809,000	849,000	 	40,000	Reduced strength of the paid reserve.3	Air Force Department Headquarters.	4,550,000	4,642,000	 	92,000	Lower average strengths.4	Civilians at Outstations	43,870,000	43,750,000	+	120,000	Increased expenditure as a result of pay awards which were not fully	and the Meteorological					effective in 1963-64, partly offset by increased receipts in respect of	Office.					personnel employed on meteorological services.5	Movements     ......	13,700,000	13,144,000(6)	+	556,000	Reduced provision for receipts for air transportation services, partly offset by lower expenditure on movement of personnel and freight.6	Supplies.........	51,000,000	52,504,000(6)	-	1,504,000	Wider use of cheaper aviation fuel partly offset by higher costs of water and sanitary services.7	Aircraft and Stores	234,250,000	243,060,000(6)		8,810,000	Lower expenditure on airfranies, engines and armament, partly offset by higher expenditure on radio, instruments and other technical equipment.  Receipts from sales of equipment are also expected to be greater.8	Lands,   Buildings   and	3,130,000	2,870,000	+	260,000	Higher expenditure on married quarter hirings and lower receipts	Works.					from the sale of land and buildings, partly offset by lower expendi-ture on land purchases.9	Miscellaneous   Effective	350,000	2,324,000(6)	-	1,974,000	Increased recoveries from the occupation of married quarters and	Services.					hirings.10	Non-Effective Services ...	15,640,000	14,430,000	+	1,210,000	The normal growth of the retired pay and pensions lists, and higher rates of retired pay, pensions and terminal grants.11	Additional  Married Quarters.	1,000	1,000			o	Totals   ......	503,800,000	503,554,000	+	246,000	
25 (a) Original Estimate (H.C. 112 of 8th February, 1962)   &apos;....................................     503,200,000Supplementary Estimate (H.C. of February, 1963)      ..................      ..................        ^0,000505,iOO,000Less functions transferred to Defence (Central) Vote in 1964-65      ..............................        1,600,000503,500,000Plus the net effect of works functions transferred between Civil Estimates (Class IX, Votes 1, 2 and 6) and Air Votes in 1964-65 ... 70,000503,570,000Less functions transferred to Civil Estimates (Class IX, Vote 14) in 1964-65        ........................ 16,000 503,554,000(b) For purposes of comparison, these figures have been adjusted to take account of the transfer of certain services between Votes in 1964-65.Qjrtcm
Home Defence Expenditure by Civil Departments (Net)     $Department	Item	Class and Vote		1964-65 Estimate (  million)Home Departments   ...	Grants to local authorities, pro-duction of equipment and materials, etc.	Class III,	3 4	15.health Departments ...	Grants to local maintenance of medical services including stocks of equipment and materials; emergency hospitals, etc.	Class VI,	16 18	1.housing        ......	Grants to local authorities, etc.; production of equipment and materials.	Class VI,	1 2	1.ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food	Handling, storage, etc., of food stocks; grants to local authori-ties; storage and maintenance of equipment and vehicles, etc.	Class V,	7 8	2.ministry of Power	Oil storage and distribution; grants to gas and electricity industries.	Class IV,	16	0.8Ministry of Transport...	Due functioning of railways and shipping; port facilities.	Class IV,	13	0.5Ministry of Public Build-ing and Works.	Storage and accommodation	Class IX,	2	1.9Board of Trade	Maintenance and turnover of stocks of materials.	Class IV,	2	0.1Various Departments ...	Miscellaneous     ......	Various Votes		0.7		Total		24.1(31325)  Wt. 1031-375   351   1/64  St.S.

Printed and published oyher majesty&apos;s stationery officeTo be purchased from york House, Kingsway, London w.c.2423 Oxford Street, London w.l13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2109 St. Mary Street, Cardiff39 King Street, Manchester 250 Fairfax Street, Bristol 135 Smallbrook, Ringway, Birmingham 580 Chichester Street, Belfast or through any bookseller printed in England

</content>
</cab>
