<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/244/0 images: 7-9</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majestvs governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.  November 1933.SECRET. Gopy No.   43CP. 252 (33). [Amended Version.]CABINET.B.B.C.  COMMENTS ON INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS.1. AT 9-20 p.m. on Saturday, the 14th October, a few hours after Germany had announced her withdrawal from the Disarmament Conference, Mr. Vernon Bartlett, who is now a salaried &quot;commentator of the B.B.C. and before that frequently appeared as a speaker, was announced as coming to the microphone to comment on the news. His intervention immediately followed the news summary, which, although it included a summary of my speech at the Bureau and of the German communication of withdrawal, was necessarily abbreviated and may well have been imperfect; certainly the summary did not convey the full facts set out in the White Paper as to the approval of the United States, Italy and others, for these facts were only known in England after the report of the proceedings in the Bureau became available and the White Paper was published.2. Listeners to Mr. Vernon Bartlett on this occasion derived from his manner as well as from his words the impression that the speaker was in a great state of agitation. He was very successful in conveying this agitation to the millions who listened to him. &quot; Germany &quot; he declared, &quot; is now fast nearing the stage when she would put up active resistance would fight if necessary with fists and pitchforks in defence of what she sincerely believes to be honour and justice.&quot; .... &quot;I take the risk of offending some of you because I am so profoundly convinced that our behaviour during the next few weeks is going to decide theissue between a real peace and another war.....   I beg of you to try to dropyour prejudices and to face up to the facts.....   I am so convinced that weEnglishmen would feel much as they do and act much as they do if we were in. their situation, that my sense of fair play makes me hope that we shall take thislatest step calmly.....The great majority of my listeners want peace and arefed up with politics.....   It is worth swallowing any amount of pride ifpeace is at stake.   Civilisation is more valuable than prestige.There can be no doubt at all of the tremendous effect produced by Mr. Vernon Bartletfs words. Whether his personal opinions at that moment were right or wrong does not seem to me to be the real question. The real question is whether it should be in the power of the B.B.C. to create a panic whenever one of their officials is so overcome with deep and sincere emotion that he has not time to reflect whether the broadcasting of his sentiments will injure or improve inter-national relations. It seems a terrible power to be left in the hands of any corporation not under direct Government control. For if this new instrument can be used at a moment of special anxiety and difficulty to ingeminate peace, it. may equally be used to stir up war feeling or to ferment internal division. Good intentions are not the same as wisdom, and I suppose that not even an exceptionally well-informed person could be confident of expressing himself wisely immediately after hearing a disturbing piece of news.3.   It is a falsehood to assert, as newspapers unfriendly to the Government immediately proceeded to do, that the Foreign Office protested.   We have never protested at all, for the simple reason that when Mr. Bartletfs talk was finished [9221]
it could not be; recalled., Neither is it in the ileast, true- that niy ownbroadcast on Tuesday, the 17th October, had anything to do with Mr. Vernon JBartlett&apos;s talk. It was occasioned by the German Foreign Ministers misleading statement to the foreign press in Berlin. Anyone who heard it or read it will know that there was not any reference to Mr. Bartlett from beginning to end. In fact, the B.B.C., over the week-end, were very hastily arranging a series of talks on disarmament, and proposed that Lord Lloyd, Mr. Lansbury, Lord Cecil, and a member of the Government should take their turn at the microphone on succeeding nights. &apos; All that happened on Monday, the 16th October, was that the B.B.C. were informed that the Prime Minister would be glad if I had an opportunity of explaining the situation in view of Herr von Neuratb/s statement, and the B.B.C. were quite prepared to arrange that the order of their proposed speakers should be varied and that I should go first. There was no compulsion or threatened compulsion, and there is no reason to suppose that the other speakers raised any complaint.4. Two questions now arise. The first is as to whether the above matters are likely to be the topic of question or debate in Parliament, and if so how they should be dealt with. The second is whether there is any step that can be taken to protect the general interest (not the interests of this or any Government) against the danger which this kind of proceeding seems to threaten. As regards the first question, it will be important to bring out, if challenged, that my broad-cast was an answer to Baron von Neurath. Presumably, no House of Commons&apos; critic can maintain the view that this was &apos;&apos; improper interference with the B.B.C.&quot; I doubt the wisdom of criticising what Mr. Bartlett said on the 14th, for it will only add fuel to the flames. The Cabinet had, however, better know the very peculiar circumstances in which Mr. Bartlett let himself go. It is understood that he submitted his manuscript to another official of the B.B.C., but neither he nor anyone else from the B.B.C. office ever came to the Press Depart-ment of the Foreign Office to gather any information on what in fact had occurred. To appreciate the irresponsible character of the pronouncement, it is well to add that on Saturday and Sunday the responsible official at the Foreign Office was visited by between forty and fifty journalists, and every respectable newspaper did its best (1) to be sure that it was fully informed of the facts, and (2) to promote calm and discourage a sense of crisis. It may be assumed that Mr. Vernon Bartlett is quite conscious that his behaviour was irregular, if only because on the next occasion he began by informing his audience that he felt that on the last occasion he had &quot; said a mouthful.&quot; Indeed, the Head of the Foreign Office Press Department has received a letter from Mr. Bartlett, in which he says &quot; I know it was an indiscreet talk.&quot;75. As for the future, I suggest to the Cabinet that it would be best not to act too hastily and to let the immediate hubbub die down. Mr. Vernon Bartlett is not at all likely to offend again in this way, at any rate at present. Any attempt to impose or secure new regulations at the moment will be maliciously misrepresented. But when the situation returns to normal and the subject can be regarded, as it ought to be, as a problem of modern government, without regard; to any particular administration or any particular controversy, it needs to be tackled.&apos; It raises the difficult question of censorship and kindred matters.The recent resolution of the House of Commons on the subject must be kept in mind (see Annex).Until about three months ago the B.B.C. dealt with foreign news by reproducing what was circulated by the news agencies, stating that these bodies were the source and claimed copyright. It has now begun to &quot;brighten the news &quot; by occasionally interspersing phrases or comments which seem appropriate to the announcer or his superiors. The discretion placed in the B.B.C. includes the right to arrange for a series of controversial talks frankly putting different points of view, e.g., about India. A regular commentator on international matters seems to stand in a different position. He presumably has high technical qualifications as a broadcaster, and his personal opinions acquire enormous authority from the fact that listeners know his voice and his name. At the same time, what he says tends to be regarded, at any rate abroad, as having something more than official permission, and the latitude of comment in which he may indulge is at times of great assistance to other countries, who are delighted to put us in the wrong.   Sometimes, moreover, it involves this country in the
apossibility&apos; of trouble with another country. 1 For example, a particularly foolish talk on last New &quot;Year&apos;s Eve, in the course of which listeners were carried round the world, included a passage about Poland which so much annoyed the authorities at Warsaw that Sir John Reith had to go round and apologise to the Polish Ambassador.J. S.Foreign Office, November 1, 1933.ANNEX.Copy of Resolution unanimously adopted by House of Commons, February 22,1933.Mr. EMMOTT : I beg leave to move,&quot; That this House, being satisfied that the British Broadcasting Corporation maintains in general a high standard of service, is of opinion that it would be contrary to the public interest to subject the corporation to any control by Government or by Parliament other than the control already provided for in the charter and the licence of the corporation; that contro-versial matter is rightly not excluded from broadcast programmes, but that the governors should ensure the effective expression of all important opinion relating thereto; and that only by the exercise of the greatest care in the selection of speakers and subjects can the function of the corporation be fulfilled and the high quality of the British broadcasting service be maintained.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
