<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/244/0 images: 112-116</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERKMEKT.)BORE T, .P. S59 ( 55)COPY HO.C A B I N E T.DIS/LRMAMBMT,Hote by the Secretary of State for Air.I circulate for the information of my colleagues a Memorandum which I have received from the Chief of the Air Staff,(Intld. )   L.November 4th, 1933,,
1.      I understand the main object of the Article on bombing in the Foreign Office Draft Plan of November 1st (CP. 255(33)) is to save Europe from the danger of air bombardment.      I understand also that it is not regarded as likely that the Japanese will accept any Convention.      That being so, it is unlikely that the United States will do so either, or at any rate, will not agree to a limitation in numbers of aircraft.      It is hardly possible that the Russians will agree to restrict the number of aircraft in Asiatic Russia while the Japanese are unrestricted.    Consequently, the &quot;principal non-European Powers&quot; will not have accepted the Convention, which will mean the Colonial Allowance will exceed 250 and not be limited. Thus Pranee will be able to maintain unlimited aircraft in Worth Africa, within reach of Europe on one side;    equally Russia will be able to maintain unlimited aircraft in Asia. 2.      Unlimited bombing aircraft can consequently be maintained within reach of Europe by Powers who have signed the Convention and maintain its provisions in peace.      There will, of course, be other anomalies and difficulties.      There is the question of defining &quot;Europe&quot; in such an area as the Mediterranean and its numerous Islands.      Prance and Russia will be able to have within reach of us superior numbers of aircraft to ourselves and the Germans. The American Navy would have unlimited aircraft, but our own in Europe (which presumably includes the Mediterranean Fleet as being based on Malta) will be restricted to such part of the 500 Metropolitan quota as can be allowed in competition with other claims such as Army Co-operation and Home Defence.     Yet the Mediterranean Fleet is now one of our main naval concentrations and from it would come in the first instance the bulk of the naval forces required for a war in the Par East or elsewhere.      India will presumably be restricted in the same way as the Dominions and will-1-
&quot;be liable to attack &quot;by unlimited Soviet aircraft -maln-tained in   Asiatic Russia.      I suggest, therefore, that a practical measure of prohibition of air bombardment will not be obtained by signing a convention for its complete prohibition in Europe or by other reciprocal or regional conventions,3,      In so far as the prohibition of air bombardment and. other qualitative proposals &apos;for air disarmament are concerned there appear to have always been three principal schools of thought amongst the Delegations at Geneva;    those who desire to achieve immediately the complete abolition of military aviation,  coupled with the control or supervision of civil aviation and, in come cases, the creation of international air police forces;    those who wish to prohibit entirely all air bombardment whilst retaining military air forces; and those who are only prepared to accept a prohibition of air bombardment which is subject to certain conditions or&apos; exceptions designed to suit their individual needs. 4.      If we consider the various States who belong to the different schools of thought to which I have just referred, we find that the Italians have stated that they are only prepared to agree to complete prohibition of air bombardment if it is accompanied by analogous reductions of heavy land and naval war material,  viz.   capital ships, heavy guns and tanks.The Japanese have made it clear that they will not accept the prohibition of bombing, unless an agreement was established which would, effectively prevent the use of civil aircraft for military purposes in wartime,  and unless aircraft
carriers and landing-on platforms on -warsnips were abolished.      There is reason to suppose that the U. S. A-might favour a prohibition of air attack on the civil population, in lieu of total prohibition of bombing. Mr. Norman Davis remarked during a conversation between Ministers at Geneva on 31st May, 1933, that &quot;he thought it was a great, pity that v/e have not attempted to achieve the desired result by saying that bombing must be confined to military objectives such as ships, bodies of troops,etc.......... as this would have avoided much of thepresent difficulty&quot;.        The Italians have recently put forward the specific proposal that the difficulty of bombing should be dealt v/ith by a Convention &quot;prohibiting air bombing of civilian populations&quot;  (Rome Telegram No. 270 of the 16th September to the Foreign Office).      The French in reply intimated that they were willing to accept this solution.      Hitler has just expressed the view that bombing behind the battle zone should be entirely prohibited (Telegram No. 232 of 24th October, 1933, to the Foreign Office).5. The case of Germany deserves special mention.Prohibition of air bombardment will do nothing to dissuade Germany from claiming an air force.      On the contrary, she intends to use it as the strongest argument    in support of her claim to be allowed what may then&apos; be termed a &quot;non-aggressive&quot; air force.6. It is impossible to disregard the divergent views which are held by different States on the question of prohibition of air bombardment, nor is it possible to foresee how we can accept the conditions which various States have indicated to be indispensable to their-3-
acceptance of prohibition of air bombardment,      I have shown above that the present proposal for the prohibition of air bombardment will not attain its object,,    On the other hand there appears to be every probability of obtaining the assent of both France and the United States of America to the Italian proposal for a prohibition of air attach on the civil population - in fact France,, as I have pointed out5 has already agreed to  this proposition,, and there are indications that the United States of iimerica would also consider this a convenient solution to the p robl enu7o I  therefore wj sh to urge strongly that we shouldsubstitute the prohibition of air bombardment of centres of civilian population for the latest Foreign Office proposal. This would be in accordance with the Cabinet decision (Cabinet 15 (33)) - taken on 8th March3 1933s to the effect that if our then proposals for air disarmament were rejectedj, we should advocate this alternative piano(Signed) E0L. ELLINGTON,,November 4th 9 1955.-4-

</content>
</cab>
