<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/244/0 images: 124-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT). C R E T..  261 (33). COPY NOo JfiJTCABINET.REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OP ARMAMENTS.-CONCLUSIONS OF MINISTERIAL COMMITTEE ON DISARMAMENT.The attached Draft of Conclusions reached by the Ministerial Committee on Disarmament at its Meeting held this morning in accordance with yesterday&apos;s Cabinet decision (Cabinet 60(33) Conclusion 2), are circulated in connection with Item 2 of tomorrow&apos;s Cabinet Agenda.(Signed) M.P.A.  HANKEY. Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whi teha11 Gar dens, S.W.1. , 7th November,  1933.
DRAFT OF CONCLUSIONS of Ministerial Committee on Disarmament reached at a Meeting held at No. 10, Downing Street, on Tuesday, November 7th, 1933, at 11.0.a.m.I.  PROCEDURE AT GENEVA.(a) that it is undesirable to attempt to negotiate details of a Draft Disarmament Convention until the ground has been prepared by con-versations between the principal Powers concerned, including Germany.      It is essential to avoid the risk either of confronting Germany with conditions which she may reject or emphasising publicly disagreement between the other Powers.(b) that, as a corollary      to (a) above, His Majesty&apos;s Government should not, at this stage, put forward the draft plan for a modified disarmament convention proposed by the Foreign Office (CP.  255(33);;  &quot;and they should endeavour to get the discussion at the Bureau on November &apos;9th of Mr.  Henderson&apos;s modified draft of His Majesty&apos;s Governments Convention of March 16th, 1933, postponed.(c) that, as regards procedure,  the first step should be to consult the French and Italian Governments with a view to getting their support for the proposed adjournment of the Bureau:    it is most important that France should be approached first since she is believed to be the strongest advocate of continuing discussions at the Bureau.The next stage,  if the above conversations are satisfactory, will be to approach the President of the Disarmament Conference.(d) that the reasons for desiring a postponement of the proposed discussion at the Bureau will require very careful consideration.The following points were suggested for the guidance of His Majesty &apos;s Governments Representatives:-(i) a new factor seems to have arisen in the offer made by Baron Von Neurath in his speech on November 6th as reported in &quot;The Times&apos;1.(ii) the disarmament proposals which Mr.  Henderson wishes to bring forward will almost certainly be unacceptable to Germany since they contain the modifications to our Draft Convention which caused her withdrawal from the Conference.(iii)  it is better to recognise  that Germany&apos;s withdrawal has caused a new situation which, in all probabilitjr can best be handled, in the first instance, by exploratory conversations between the prinoipal Powers concerned, including Germany.
(e) that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs accompanied &quot;by Mr. Eden should represent us at Geneva and should endeavour to meet M.  Sarraut on his way.    In the meantime information should at once be sent to the British Ambassador in Parisso that he may prepare the ground.(f) that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should be authorised to take extremely tentative soundings as to the possibility of a meeting of Heads of Governments at some stage, possibly in London.      It being clearly understood, however,   that before any such meeting could be given concrete consideration, its objects must be clearly defined anda plan prepared which would have definite prospects of success.II.  LORD MAYOR&apos;S BANQUET.(g) that the Home Secretary should be asked if he would take the- Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs&apos; place at the Lord Mayor&apos;s Banquet on Thursday, November 9th.III.     DEBATE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS.(h) that with a view to preparing the ground for our proposals at the Bureau, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should refer in his speech to the offer reported to have been made by Baron Von Neurath (Vide I  (d)(i) above.)Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.7th November, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
