<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/244/0 images: 138-236</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).80COPY NO. 4*- OC A B I N E T.THE UNEMPLOYMENT BILL.Note by the Minister, of Labour. (Reference Cabinet 60(35^    Conclusion 5).I circulate for the information of my colleagues a copy of the Unemployment Bill in the form in which it was introduced in the House of Commons on Wednesday, November 8th, 1953,  together with a typed Memorandum prepared in my Department, explaining the various provisions of the Bill.(Intd. )    H.B.C R E T..  265  (35),Ministry of Labour,November 9th,  1933.
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).80COPY NO. 4 6C A B I N E T.THE UNEMPLOYMENT BILL.Note &quot;by the Minister of Labour. (Reference Cabinet 60(55)    Conclusion 3).I circulate for the information of my colleagues a copy of the Unemployment Bill in the form in which it was introduced in the House of Commons on Wednesday, November 8th, 1933, together with a typed Memorandum prepared in my Department, explaining the various provisions of the Bill.(Intd.)    H.B.ORB T..  265 (55).Ministry of Labour,November 9th, 1933.
THE, .. UNEIIPLOYMENT    BILL. 1.     The Bill is the first measure introdut ad in this country deal-ing comprehensively with the whole of the able-bodied industrial unemployed.    It has been framed after very careful examination and consideration of the recommendations made in the Reports of the Royal Commission.It is in two Parts:    Part I relates to the Unemployment Insurance Scheme, and Part II to a new National service of Unemployment Assistance.PART    I.    UNEMPLOYMENT    INSURANCE. 2,      (l) The existing provisions of the unemployment insurance scheme are in the main continued.    There is no change in the rates of contribution or benefit for the present classes of contributors,(2) Persons who have paid 30 contributions in the past two years, may as at present,draw up to 26 weeks of benefit in a benefit year, but there is a new provision enabling additional days of benefit up to a maximum in all of 52 weeks to be drawn by those with good contribution and benefit records in the previous five years.    This will result in the transfer of a substantial number of persons from transitional payments to insurance benefit.(3) The minimum age for entry into insurance is to be lowered to the school-leaving age for the time being in force, and benefit will be payable from the age of 16.      Dependants   benefit      in respect of juveniles between the ages of 14 and 16 will be payable to the parents not only, as at present, wherever the child is receiving full-time instruction at a day school or attending a course of instruction for unemployed juveniles, but also whenever he is unemployed for reasons outside his control.(4) There is to be a wide extension of instruction courses provided by local education authorities, with the assistance of a grant, for juveniles under the age of 18, and attendance of unemployed juveniles at such courses, when available, is in general to be compulsory.
Si(5) The proposals in Part I of the Bill have been framed with careful regard to the importance of establishing the Unemployment Insurance Scheme on a solvent and self-supporting basis,    With the object of providing machinery for securing the continued solvency of the scheme the Bill sets up an Unemplo5rment Insurance Statutory Committee.    It will be the duty of the Committee to report on the financial position of the scheme and to recommend any changes that may be necessary for financial reasons, whether for meeting a deficit or dealing with a surplus;    the Minister is empowered subject to the approval of Parliament,  to bring changes into force to the extent necessary for dealing with a deficit or surplus certified by the committee(6) The statutory committee is to make such proposals as seem to them practicable for a scheme for the insurance of agriculture and to report to the Minister but such a scheme is not to come into force without further legislation.3. The following paragraphs deal rather more fully with some of the chief pointSo4.      Period of benefit.  The existing provision is retainedunder which claimants receive 26 weeks of benefit inthe twelve months following the date of their claims(which is called their benefit year)  provided theyhave paid 30 contributions in the last two years and are otherwise&apos; qualified for benefit,,      They will, however, be
entitled under the provisions of the Bill to additional days of benefit in accordance with the following: rulePersons who have been in insurance for five years will be allowed the additional days of benefit at the rate of six extra days of benefit for every ten contributions paid in the preceding five years,  subject to a deduction of one day of benefit for every five days received in, broadly speaking, five years,,This means that a man who has over the five years paid the full number of contributions, i.e, 260, and has received no benefit, will be entitled to receive benefit for 26 weeks over and above the minimum allowance of 26 weeks, i.e.    52 weeks in all in his benefit. year0 .   The actual amount of additional days of benefit payable in any case will, of course, depend on the claimant&apos;s individual record as regards both contributions paid and benefit received. 5.      Juveniles under age 18.      In any area where the number of unemployed juveniles under 18 is considerable, the Local Education Authority will be under obligation to provide a Junior Instruction Centre, with the assistance of a grant.    Attendance at these centres will be compulsory for all unemployed juveniles over the school-leaving age and under 18 unless there is some good ground for excusing attendance.    In areas where the number of unemployed juveniles. does not justify the opening of centres, arrangements will-be made, so far as is practicable, for the attendance of unemployed juveniles at some form of instruction class.At present the minimum age for entry into unemployment insurance is 16.    Under the Bill such insurance is to begin at the school-leaving age.    In the case of a juvenile above the school-leaving age and under 16 employed in an insured trade an unemploy-ment insurance contribution of 2d.  each is to be paid by the juvenile,  the employer and the Exchequer.      Juveniles under 16 who
continue in whole-time education voluntarily beyond the school-leaving age will receive a free credit of contributions up to a maximum of 20.    Unemployment benefit is to become payable at the age of 16 whereas at present it is not payable at earliest till the age of rather more than 164-.      Employers may be required to notify the discharge of boys and girls from their employment. 6.      Insurance of agriculture.      The Statutory Committee is to make such proposals as seem to ..them practicable for insuring agriculture (including horticulture and forestry) against uneinploy-ment, and to report to the Minister, who is to lay the Report before Parliament.Further legislation will be necessary before such a scheme can be brought into force.7.      Financial provisions.      The Statutory Committee which is to be set up by the Bill will examine the financial condition of the scheme immediately after the close of each calendar year and within two months will make a report to the Minister on the financial condition of the Unemployment Fund.    They will also make a report at any other time if they consider that the Fund is or is likely to become insufficient to discharge its liabilities,.If the Committee at any time report that there is an existing or prospective deficiency or that there is and is likely to continue to be a surplus to an extent greater than is required for working purposes, their report must contain recommendations for the amend-ment of the Acts which will have the effect of restoring the balance of income and expenditure. .The matters on which the Committee may recommend amendments cover a wide range, and include rates of contributions and rates and conditions of benefit and the duration of benefit.    Their report must 1 also give an estimate of the effect which the amendments will have on the financial condition of the Fund.
The Minister must lay the Committee&apos;s report before parliament,  together with the draft of an order either making the amendments recommended by the Committee, or other amendments having substantially the same financial effect.    In the latter case he must give reasons for not adopting the recommendations of the Committee,The report with the draft order will be considered by both Houses of Parliament, and if both Houses pass resolutions approving the proposed amendments an order will be made in the terms of the draft and will thereupon become law.Borrowing by the Fund will not be resumed except that, where the Fund is unable to meet its immediate liabilities, temporary loans may be made by the Exchequer.    If these cannot be repaid out of the ordinary revenue of the Fund., within a limited period, the machinery just described will be set in motion to restore the solvency of the Fund and to provide for the repayment of the loans out of the Fund,Provision is made for the amortisation of the debt outstanding when the Act comes into force by means   of instalments of fixed amount paid out of the Unemployment Fund to cover principal and interest at the rate of 3-g- per cent, per annum.    It is anticipated that under these arrangements the debt will be repaid within a period not exceeding 40 years.PART    II.    UNEMPLOYMENT ASSISTANCE, 8.      This part creates a new Central Authority, the Unemployment Assistance Board, which will take over from the Public Assistance Authorities their present duties in regard to transitional payments and also the administration of out-relief given to able-bodied persons on account of unemployment.
The Board which will consist of not more than five- members, will work through its own local officials, from whose decisions there is power of appeal, in appropriate cases,  to local Appeal Tribunals.The Minister of Labour will be responsible to Parliament for the general policy of the Board.     The Minister will submit to Parliament for approval the Regulations governing the assessment of need by which the Board and its officials will work,  and the application of those regulations to individual cases will be a matter for administration by the Board.This procedure will ensure more uniformity in the assessment of need, while at the same time divesting the Minister of any responsibility for individual decisions.In order that the Board may have the advantage of the help and advice of the persons who have had long experience In this work the Board is empoy/ered to set up Local Advisory Committees.     While these Committees will have no right to intervene in the decisions of the Board and the Appeals Tribunals, there is no doubt that the members of them will be increasingly asked to help in some of the cases that come before the Board.9.     Scope of the Scheme.     The scheme covers all persons between the ages of 16 and 65 whose normal occupation is employment in respect of which contributions are payable under- the Widows1 Orphans&apos;  and Old Age Contributory Pensions Acts, or who can shew that not having had such a normal occupation,  they might have expected to have been so employed but for the industrial circumstances of the district in which they reside, and who are capable of and available for work.The scope is thus much wider than that of Unemployment Insurance. ,Persons who are disqualified from benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts owing to loss of employment by reason of a stoppage of work due to a trade dispute, or v/ho would have been so disqualified if they had been insured contributors,  are excluded
from the &apos;scope of the Board for the period of the disqualificatioruA demarcation of responsibility between the Board and the Local Authorities is necessary, and for soiind administration it must be one that can be tested, by reference to objective facts. The scope of the Contributory Pensions Act is the widest of any of the Acts that could be considered as appropriate for the purpose.10. Finance of the Scheme. Subject to contributions by Local Authorities on account of the liabilities of which they v/ill be relieved the cost of the Scheme will be borne on national funds by the Exchequer.11.    Co-operation with the, Ministry of Labour.     Applicants for assistance will register at the Employment Exchanges in order that they may be kept in touch with opportunities of employment in the same way as other workpeople on insurance benefit..     They will, also in general receive their unemployment allowances at the Exchanges.12.    Assessment of Need.      The Regulations governing the assessment of need have to be approved by Parliament.     The Board, is not bound by the statutory rates of unemployment benefit;    it relieves all the need, other than medical need,  arising in the household of an applicant and takes into account the resources available to the household.     The protection for certain classes of resources conferred by the Determination &apos;of Need Act,  1932, is continued;    this protection relates to sick pay and National Health Insurance benefit,  disability pensions, workmen&apos;s compensation and small savings.
13.    Maintenance of Bmployability.      The Board is given power, in co-operation with the Minister of Labour, to provide courses to enable persons under the Board to regain physical    fitness and so to improve their chances of employment.      It is contemplated that these courses should follow the lines of the present reconditioning schemes of the Ministry of Labour,  the main object of which is to make men fit for manual labour such as is done on public works contracts.      In order that the course may include familiarity with actual working conditions the Board will have power to make appropriate arrangements with Local Authorities for the course to be completed by a limited spell of employment at the customary wages on work for the Authority of a character and under conditions that will complete the training.14*    Provision for cases of special difficulty.      Having regard to the wide scope of the scheme there will be a limited number of cases of special difficulty where the applicant has shown that he cannot be appropriately dealt with by the ordinary procedure described above.      The Board is given power to deal with such cases subject to the due safeguarding of the applicant&apos;s right to state his side of the case.      The Board may order the assistance to be given to a member of the applicant&apos;s household instead of to the applicant himself;    or may order the assistance to be issued otherwise than in cash;    or, where necessary, may require an applicant to attend a work centre specially provided for this purpose;    or, by arrangement with a Local Authority may make the assistance conditional upon the applicant becoming an inmate of a workhouse.      In all these cases the applicant will have a right of appeal to the Appeal Tribunal.
*    . y    There an applicant persistently &quot;breaks the conditions,  or persistently refuses or neglects to maintain himself, the Board may apply to the Appeal&apos;Tribunal for the exclusion of the applicant from their jurisdiction;&apos;   he cannot be properly considered as one of the ordinary industrial unemployed for whom the scheme is designed.      His recourse will then be to the Public Assistance Authorities.     The person concerned and the Local Authority may in such cases appeal to the Appeal Tribunal. 15*    The duties of Local Authorities.    It is a corollary to the scheme that the Local Authorities will no longer have power to give outdoor relief to persons whose needs have been met by the Board, though the duty of giving relief in cases of sudden or urgent necessity will remain upon the Relieving Officers.      The Board will reimburse Local Authorities for any relief so given.The Public Assistance Authorities will retain their existing powers and duties in relation to assistance for the sick, aged and infirm.      They will also be responsible for the medical needs and institutional or clinical treatment of persons who otherwise are under the Boardo16.    Administration.    The administration will be through the officers of the Board, co-operating for certain purposes with the Employment Exchanges.      If and so long as arrangements for this purpose are in force,  investigation into applications may be carried out on behalf of the Board by officers of the Local Authorities. 17.    The effect of the Assistance scheme is that the able-bodied unemployed are removed from the care of the public Assistance Authorities;    they are brought under one central authority - which has wide powers to give them assistance according&apos; to their need, Including the provision of training.    Through its co-operation with the Minister of Labour and the Employment Exchanges the Board will be able to shape its policy on industrial lines and so help as many as possible of the persons under its charge to regain an opportunity of employment.
Unemployment Bill.FINANCIAL MEMORANDUM.1. Part I. of the Bill amends the Unemployment Insurance Acts. Part II. makes provision outside un-employment insurance for assisting and promoting the welfare of able-bodied persons, within the definitions in the Bill, who are unemployed and in need. Part III contains Transitory Provisions relating in the main to the period between the coming into force of Part I and the full operation of Part II. The financial arrange-ments under Part II of the Bill so far as they concern local authorities are under discussion with them and it is not yet possible to give complete information on the finance of this part of the Bill. A revised memo-randum will be issued before the Second Reading of the Bill.Part I.2. The main provisions having financial effect are those concerning persons under eighteen years of age (clauses 1 and 13), the extension (in . certain cases) of the period of benefit (clause 3), and the redemption of the debt of the Unemployment Fund (clause 18). Provision is made, also, for the appointment of an Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee, with important financial duties (clause 17).3. Persons under eighteen. The minimum age for entry into insurance is reduced from 16 years to the school leaving age for the time being in force; contribu-tions at the rate of 2d. each per week will be payable by employer, employed, and Exchequer (clause 1). The additional charge to the Exchequer is estimated to be  253,000 per annum.Provision is made under which there will be a con-siderable increase in the number of Junior Instruction Centres for persons between 14 and 18 years of age provided by local education authorities with the assistance of a grant (clause 13). The additional charge on the Exchequer is estimated to be  850,000 in the first full[Bill 170] a
year, of which 50 per cent, will be repaid out of the Unemployment Fund (clause 15).As a result of lowering the age of entry into insurance insured contributors may become entitled to benefit at the age of 16 years (i.e., 30 weeks earlier than at present).4. Period of Benefit. Clause 3 provides that benefit may be drawn not only for a period of 26 weeks in any benefit year (as at present) but that, subject to certain conditions, benefit in respect of additional days may be paid up to a further period of 26 weeks, to contributors who have been insured for a period of five years; this provision for additional benefit will transfer a considerable number of persons from transitional payments to insurance benefit.5. Redemption of debt. (Clause 18). The balance outstanding at the commencement of the Act of the advances made to the Unemployment Fund by the Treasury, and borrowed by them from the National Debt Commissioners, will be redeemed, both as regards capital and interest, by the payment of the appropriate number of half-yearly instalments of  2,750,000. The rate of interest for this purpose has been agreed at 3J per cent, per annum with a reservation for the continuation of existing rates for unexpired periods of current advances, which in no case exceed five years. The period required to complete the repayment will depend upon the amount (not exceeding, however,  115,000,000) outstanding at the commencement of the Act but will be approximately 40 years.6. Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee.  Clause 17 of the Bill sets up the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee whose duty it will be to report from time to time on the financial position of the scheme and to recommend any changes in the provi-sions of the scheme that may be necessary for financial reasons, whether for meeting a deficit or dealing with a surplus. The Minister is empowered, subject to the approval of Parliament, to bring changes into force to the extent necessary for dealing with a deficit or surplus certified by the Committee. Other duties of the Committee are : (1) to consider and report upon draft Regulationsaffecting the Unemployment Fund proposedby the Minister (clause 19);
(2) to consider and advise upon questions relating to the operation of the Unemployment Insur-ance Acts which are referred to them by the Minister (clause 19 (5) );(3) to make as soon as may be after the passing of the Act such proposals as may seem to them practicable for the insurance of agriculture against unemployment and to report to the Minister (clause 20).7. Other provisions in Part I of the Bill relate to :-(1) Dependants&apos; benefit. Extended provision is made for the payment of dependants&apos; benefit in respect of dependent children between the ages of 14 and 16 (clause 9).(2) Training courses, etc. The Minister is autho-rised to provide training courses for persons who have attained the age of 18 years (clause 13); a grant not exceeding 75 per cent, of the cost in respect of the attendance at such courses of persons in receipt of benefit may be made out of the Unemploy-ment Fund (clause 15). Arrangements may also be made with other bodies providing courses of training, instruction or occupation (clause 13).(3) Men discharged from the Forces. Clause 25 applies to men discharged from H.M. Forces the fuU extension of the period of benefit referred to above in paragraph 4, to which they could have been entitled had they been insured during service. The additional cost of this provision to the Exchequer is estimated at about  300,000 a year.(4) Short Service Constables of Metropolitan Police.  Clause 26 makes corresponding provisions as regards entitlement to benefit in respect of short-service constables of the Metropolitan Police Force upon the completion of their period of service. No cost will arise under this head until after the end of about 10 years.8. A separate White Paper (Cmd. 4447) is being-issued containing a report by the Government Actuary on this Part of the Bill.
Part II.9. The Unemployment Assistance Board, created by Part II. of the Bill, will be responsible for the welfare of the classes of able-bodied unemployed persons covered by this Part of the Bill, mclucbng provision for main-tenance of their fitness for employment and for the grant of assistance to them in accordance with their needs (clause 34).10. The scheme covers all persons between the ages of 16 and 65 whose normal occupation is employment in respect of. which contributions are payable under the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Acts, or who can show that, not having had any re-remunerative occupation, they might have expected to have had insurable employment but for the industrial circumstances of the district in which they reside, and who are capable of and available for work. Persons who are disqualified for benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts owing to having lost employment by reason of a stoppage of work which was due to a trade dispute, or would have been so disqualified if they had been insured contributors, are excluded from the scope of the Board for the period of the disqualification (clause 35).11. The provision now made for the above-mentioned classes consists of transitional payments and the grant of relief on account of unemployment by Public Assistance Authorities. The cost of transitional payments for the twelve months ended 31st October, 1933, was about  51,000,000 excluding cost of administration. As regards &apos; refief now granted by Public Assistance Authorities, the financial arrangement proposed is that the whole responsibility for persons within the scope of the scheme shall be borne by the Unemployment Assistance Fund (clause 43), but, towards that cost, local authorities shall make contributions of a percentage of the cost in a standard year of the service of which they will be relieved (clause 44); this cost will need to be specially determined and clause 44 makes provision for this purpose. These financial arrangements, including any consequential adjustment of the General Exchequer contributions, payable under the Local Government Acts, are at present the subject of discussion with the local authorities.
Part II.9. The Unemployment Assistance Board, created by Part II. of the Bill, will be responsible for the welfare of the classes of able-bodied unemployed persons covered by this Part of the Bill, including provision for main-tenance of their fitness for employment and for the grant of assistance to them in accordance with their needs (clause 34).10. The scheme covers all persons between the ages of 16 and 65 whose normal occupation is employment in respect of. which contributions are payable under the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Acts, or who can show that, not having had any re-remunerative occupation, they might have expected to have had insurable employment but for the industrial circumstances of the district in which they reside, and who are capable of and available for work. Persons who are disqualified for benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts owing to having lost employment by reason of a stoppage of work which was due to a trade dispute, or would have been so disqualified if they had been insured contributors, are excluded from the scope of the Board for the period of the disqualification (clause 35).11. The provision now made for the above-mentioned classes consists of transitional payments and the grant of relief on account of unemployment by Public Assistance Authorities. The cost of transitional payments for the twelve months ended 31st October, 1933, was about  51,000,000 excluding cost of administration. As regards relief now granted by Public Assistance Authorities, the financial arrangement proposed is that the whole responsibility for persons within the scope of the scheme shall be borne by the Unemployment Assistance Fund (clause 43), but, towards that cost, local authorities shall make contributions of a percentage of the cost hi a standard year of the service of which they will be relieved (clause 44); this cost will need to be specially determined and clause 44 makes provision for this purpose. These financial arrangements, including any consequential adjustment of the General Exchequer contributions, payable under the Local Government Acts, are at present the subject of discussion with the local authorities.
Apart from the financial adjustments with the local authorities the cost of assistance under the new scheme will differ from the present expenditure by reason of the transfer to unemployment benefit of certain persons who, under existing legislation, are in receipt of transitional payments and by reason of any change there may be in the level of unemployment or in the conditions governing the grant of unemployment allowances, as compared with existing conditions.12. Training. One of the functions of the Board is to make provision for the improvement and re-establishment of the condition of the persons to whom Part II applies with a view to their being fit for entry into or return to regular employment. In this connection clause 36 provides that the Board may provide and maintain training courses and co-operate for the same purposes with the Minister of Labour or any local authority or other body. It is estimated that a sum of  750,000, additional to the provision now made for training in the Vote for the Ministry of Labour, may be spent by the Board during the first full year after they have completed the necessary arrangements. The clause provides, also, that the Board may make special arrangements with local authorities for the continuance of training and instruction by means of employment for limited periods at customary Avages upon work for the authority of a kind suitable for the purpose, the Board being empowered to contribute towards any additional expenditure incurred by reason of the work being utilised as part of a training course.13. Grant of Allowances. The amount of the allowance to be granted to an applicant is to be determined by reference to his needs, including the needs of any members of the household of which he is a member who are dependent on, or ordinarily supported by him. The needs are to be assessed in accordance with Regula-tions (clause 37) which operate after approval by each House of Parliament (clause 42); the Bill provides that such Regulations shall, in particular, provide that the resources of an applicant taken into account shall include the resources of aU members of the household of which the applicant is a member, due regard being had also to the personal requirements of those members whose resources are taken into account (clause 37). This clause also
provides that the protection of certain resources given by Section 48 of the Poor Law Act, 1930, and the Transi-tional Payments (Determination of Need) Act, 1932, shall be continued and applied to all persons assisted by the Board.Provision is made for the appointment of Advisory Committees for the purpose of securing the advice and assistance of persons having local knowledge and ex-perience of matters affecting the functions of the Board (clause 34). Provision is also made for the appointment of Appeal Tribunals (clauses 35 and 38).Clause 38 provides that the allowances shall be determined by officers of the Board and the necessary organisation will be established for the purpose. In general, applicants will apply at the existing local offices of the Ministry of Labour and receive their cash allowances there (clause 41). Under clause 37, for the purpose of investigating the circumstances of applicants for allowances, the Board may act either through their own officers or through officers of the Minister or of a local authority if and so long as there are arrangements for this purpose.A statement regarding the cost of administration will be included in the revised memorandum.14. Unemployment Assistance Fund. Clause 43 pro-vides for the creation of the Unemployment Assistance Fund. The money required by the Fund to meet its liabilities will be provided from moneys voted by Parlia-ment, apart from the contributions received from the local authorities. From this Fund will be paid all the expenses of the Board, except the salaries of the Board, which will be on the Consolidated Fund (Fifth Schedule), and salaries of officers of the Board and of the Appeal Tribunals, which will be on Votes (clause 46). Clause 45 provides for the recovery from the Fund of costs incurred in connection with the scheme by Government Depart-ments. The result of these provisions will be that the Vote taken for the salaries of officers of the Board and of the Appeal tribunals, and for the grants to the Fund (clause 46), will show the total estimated cost of the scheme to the Exchequer in each year, apart only from the salaries of members of the Board, which will be charged to the Consolidated Fund.
Part III.15. Transitory Provisions. Part II of the Bill as regards the grant of allowances will come into force on the appointed day (clause 37), which, it is anticipated, will not be until after 30th. June, 1934, the date on which the present provision of transitional payments expires. The Bill, therefore, continues transi-tional payments after the 30th June until the appointed day, but gives power to the Minister to transfer the assessment of these payments to the Board at an earlier date (clause 55). The present cost of transitional pay-ments, mcluding administration, is at the rate of about  4,500,000 per month.
Unemployment Bill.ARRANGEMENT OP CLAUSES.Part I.Amendment oe Unemployment Insurance Acts. Insured Persons.Clause.1.   Age for entry into insurance and rate of contribu-tions in respect of persons under sixteen. 2.   Power to enlarge or restrict excepted employments.Benefit.3.   Duration and computation of benefit.4.   Definition of benefit year.5.   Amendments as to meaning of unemployment.6.   Amendments as to third statutory condition.7.   Amendments as to fifth statutory condition.8.   Period of disallowance of benefit in certain cases.9.   Definition of dependent child. 10.   Amendments as to increase of benefit in respect of dependants. 11.   Amendment as to anomalies regulations.Determination of Claims and Questions. 12.   Determination of claims and questions.13.14. 15.Instruction and Training.Provision of authorised courses and other courses of instruction and training. Power to require attendance at authorised courses. Power to make grants out of Unemployment Fundtowards expenses of attendance at authorisedcourses.Power to require notification of discharge from employment of persons under eighteen.[Bill 170] A
Financial Provisions.Clause.17. Establishment of Unemployment Insurance Statu-tory Committee, and duties of Committee as respects Unemployment Fund.18.   Treasury advances to Unemployment Fund.Miscellaneous and General.19. Duties of Unemployment Insurance Statutory Com-mittee as respects regulations and advice.20. Duty of Unemployment Insurance Statutory Com-mittee as to insurance of persons employed in agriculture.21.   Amendments as to arrangements with associations of employed persons. 22.   Amendments as to schemes. 23.   Amendments as to offences.24.   Amendment as to summary recovery of sums due to unemployment Fund. 25.  Amendment of s. 41 of principal Act and applicationof Acts to officers of reserve forces. 26.   Extension of principal Act to short service constablesof the metropolitan police force. 27.   Power of Minister to assist schemes for promotinggreater regularity of employment. 28.   Continuation of 20 &amp; 21 Geo. 5. c. 16. 29.   Minor amendments.30. Payments out of moneys provided by Parliament, &amp;o.31. Interpretation of Part I and construction of references32.   Application of Part I to Scotland.33.   Commencement, extent and citation of Part I.Part II.Unemployment Assistance.34.   Unemployment Assistance  Board  and  advisorycommittees. 35.   Application of Part II of Act. 36.   Provision and maintenance of training courses. 37.   Persons to whom, and circumstances in which,allowances may be granted. 38.   Determination of applications for  allowances  in questions relating thereto.
Clause.39.   Method of dealing with cases of special chfficulty.41.   Issue of allowances.42.   Rules and regulations.43.   Unemployment Assistance Fund.44.   Contributions of local authorities to UnemplojmientAssistance Fund. 45.   Payment to Treasury out of Unemployment fund of expenses of Government departments. 46.   Expenditure out of moneys provided by Parliament. 47.   Penalty for fraudulently obtaining allowance and recovery of over-payments. 48.   Provisions as to allowances paid to persons entitledto old age pensions. 49.   Inspection of documents.50. Superannuation rights of officers of local authorities entering the service of the Unemployment Assistance Board.51.   Modification of enactments and saving.52. Interpretation of Part II and construction of references.53.   Application of Part II to Scotland.54.   Extent and citation of Part II.55.   Transitory provisions. 56.   Short title and repeals. Schedules :First Schedule Provisions subject to  which Regulations may be made.Part I. Making of Regulations. Part II. Reckoning of Credited Contribu-tions.Second   Schedule Unemployment   Insurance Statutory Committee.Part I. Constitution and Proceedings ofCommittee. Part II. Provisions of Unemployment In-surance Acts of which amendments mav be recommended by Committee.40.Part III. &apos;Supplementary.
Third Schedule-Provisions as to publication of Draft Regulations and objections thereto. Fourth Schedule Minor Amendments. Fifth Schedule Constitution and Proceedingsof Unemployment Assistance Board. Sixth Schedule Constitution and Proceedingsof Appeal Tribunals. Seventh Schedule Modification of enactments relating to the relief of the poor.Part I. Provisions applying to England. Part II. Provisions applying to Scotland. Eighth Schedule Repeals.Part I. Enactments repealed as from thecommencement of Part I of this Act. Part II. -Enactments repealed as from the -date appointed under Part II of this Act as the appointed day for the purposes of that Part. -
B&apos; I  L  LtoAmend the Unemployment Insurance Acts, a.d. 1933. 1920 to 1933, and to make further provision for the training and assistance of persons who are capable of, and available for, work but have no work or only part-time or intermittent work; and for purposes connected with the matters aforesaid.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as f ollows : Past I.Amendment of Unemployment Insurance Acts.Insured Persons.1. (1) The minimum age for entry into insurance 10 under the principal Act shall, instead of being the age of sixteen years, be the age (not being less than fourteen yeajrs) when a person attains the age at which under the law for the time being in force his parents cease to be under an obligation to cause him to receive efficient 15 elementary instruction, or to attend school.[Bill 170] A3Age for entry into . insurance and rate of contribu-tions in respect of persons under sixteen.
Power to enlarge orrestrictexceptedemploy-ments.(2) The rates of contribution applicable under the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933, in the case of persons under eighteen years shall apply only as respects persons who have attained the age of sixteen years but are under the age of eighteen years, and the 5 contributions payable under the Unemployment Insur-ance Acts by employed persons and their employers shall, in the case of persons who have not attained the age of sixteen years be at the following rates, that is to say, from the employed person for each week twopence, 10 and from the employer for each week twopence.(3) Subject to, and in accordance with, the provi-sions of Part I of the First Schedule to this Act, the Minister shall, after consultation with the Board of Education, and with the approval of the Treasury, 15 provide by regulations for crediting with contributions any persons who, after attaining the age at which under the law for the time being in force their parents cease to be under an obligation to cause them to receive efficient elementary instruction, have continued to receive whole- 20 time education, and the provisions of Part II of that Schedule shall have effect as to the reckoning of con-tributions so credited.Regulations made under this subsection shall not come into force until the expiration of twelve months 25 after the coming into operation of this section but as from the date on which they come into force shall apply to persons who, having previously (whether before or after the commencement of this Act) attained the age aforesaid, have continued to receive whole time education 30 so long as they so continue.(4) This section shall come into operation on the third day of September, nineteen hundred and thirty-four, or on such earlier date as the Minister may by order direct. 352. (1) Where it appears to the Minister that the terms and conditions of service of, and the nature of the work performed by, any class of persons employed in an excepted employment are so similar to the terms and conditions of service of, and the nature of the work 40 performed by, a class of persons employed in an insurable employment that anomalies result in the operation of the Unemployment Insurance Acts, the Mtnister may, by regulations made with the consent ofPaet I.  cont.
the Treasury, either unconditionally or subject to such AD. 1933.conditions as may be specified in the regulations, either         .&quot;F? a &quot;r/r X(a) provide f ormcluding the class of persons employed    -cont.&apos; in insurable employment among the classes of 5 persons employed in excepted employment; or(6) provide for including the class of persons employed in excepted employment among the classes of persons employed in insurable employment.(2) Section four of the principal Act shall cease 10 to have effect.(3) The Minister may by regulations provide, subject to such exceptions and conditions as he thinks fit, for adding any class of employment to the excepted employments only as respects persons who are in any week employed 15 in that class of employment to such extent (being in the opinion of the Minister inconsiderable) as may be specified in the regulations.Benefit.3. (1) An insured contributor who has attained Duration 20 the age of sixteen years and is unemployed shall, if he and com-proves that the statutory conditions are fulfilled in his Potation of case, and if he is not disqualified under the Unemploy- beneilt-ment Insurance Acts for  the receipt of benefit, be entitled to receive in a benefit year, benefit 25        (a) in respect of periods  not  exceeding  in  the aggregate one hundred and fifty-six days; and(6) if qualified for additional days under the pro-visions of the next following  subsection, in respect of additional days of which the maximum 30 number shall be computed in manner providedby that subsection.(2) The following provisions shall have effect with respect to additional days (a) an insured contributor shall be qualified for 35 additional days if at the beginning of the benefityear five insurance years have elapsed since the beginning of the insurance year in which he first became such a contributor, so, however, that a person shall cease to be so qualified if at the 40 beginning of any benefit year five consecutive
A J). .1933. insurance years have elapsed without contri-butions being paid in respect of him as an insured contributor,  but upon contributions being again so paid shall be treated for the purposes of this paragraph as if he had then 5 first become an insured contributor: (b) the maximum number of additional days in any benefit year shall be computed, in the case of an insured contributor qualified for such days, by reckoning six days for every ten contri- 10 butions paid in respect of him as an insured contributor in respect of the last five years, less one day for every five days in respect of which benefit has been paid to him in respect of the benefit years which ended in the last five 15 years.For the purposes of this paragraph  *(i) the expression &quot;the last five years&quot; means the period of five complete insurance years last preceding the beginning of the benefit 20 year in respect of which the computation of additional days is made;(ii) every two contributions paid in respect of a person as an insured contributor under the age of eighteen years shall be reckoned as 25 one contribution;(iii) fractions of a day shall be disregarded.   t(3) An insured contributor who has in any benefit year exhausted his benefit rights shall not thereafter be entitled to benefit in respect of any day in that benefit 30 year, nor shall he become entitled to benefit in his next benefit year before the Monday next after the end of the calendar week for which there is paid the last of the ten contributions whereof payment is required by the next following section to be proved at the beginning of that 35 benefit year.(4) In calculating contributions for the purposes of the last two foregoing subsections, paragraph (i) of subsec-tion (2) of section five of the Unemployment Insurance Act 1927 (which provides that no account shall be taken of 40 any contributions paid in respect of any person in re-spect of any period during which he was not bona fidePabt I. -cont.
employed) shall apply in like manner as it applies in A.D. 1933. calculating  the  thirty contributions required by the &apos;&apos;     -first statutory condition. -cow/&apos;(5) The Minister may by regulations make pro-5 vision as to the circumstances in which and the extent to which contributions paid in error and sums paid to a person by way of benefit, while he was not entitled thereto are to be taken into account for the purposes of computing benefit under this section.10 (6) After an insured contributor has at the beginning of his benefit year proved that the first statutory con-dition is fulfilled in his case then, subject to and in accordance with regulations made by the Minister, he shall be treated throughout the remainder of that benefit15 year as if that condition continued to be so fulfilled.4. (1) For all the purposes of the Unemployment Definition Insurance Acts, the expression &quot; benefit year&quot; shall of Denent mean, in relation to an insured contributor, the period of * twelve months beginning on the date on which, on an 20 application for benefit, he proves for the first time after the commencement of this Part of this Act (a) that the first statutory condition is fulfilled in his case; and(6) in the case only of an insured contributor who 25 has exhausted his benefit rights in his last pre-ceding benefit year, also that ten contributions have been paid in respect of him since the Sunday last before the last day in respect of which he was entitled to benefit;30 and every subsequent period of twelve months com-mencing on the date on which that contributor on an application for benefit proves the matters aforesaid for the first time after the termination of his last preceding benefit year:35 Provided that, in relation to an insured contributor in whose case a benefit year is current at the commence-ment of this Part of this Act (i) the expression &quot;benefit year&quot; shall, until the expiration of twelve months from the beginning 40 of that benefit year, mean that year, and that
year shall for the purpose of determining his next benefit year be treated as his last preceding benefit year; and(ii) he shall not be deemed to have exhausted his benefit rights in that last preceding benefit 5 year unless he has exhausted such rights both under sub-paragraph (6) of paragraph (1) of Article I of the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931, and under the last foregoing section. 10(2) The definition of &quot; benefit year&quot; contained in subsection (1) of section sixteen of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927, as amended by paragraph (2) of article four of the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931, shall, notwithstanding 15 the repeal thereof by this Act, continue to have effect for the purpose of determining the duration of the benefit year of any insured contributor which is current at the commencement of this Part of this Act.Amend-ments as to meaning of unemploy-ment.5. (1) An insured contributor shall not be deemed 20 for the purpose of the Unemployment Insurance Acts to be unemployed on any day which is recognised as a holiday for his grade or class or shift at the factory, workshop or other premises at which he is employed.(2) An insured contributor who has worked in any 25 calendar week for the number of days or number of shifts which constitute the full week&apos;s work for his grade or class or shift at the factory, workshop or other premises at which he is or was last employed shall not be deemed for the purpose of the Unemploy- 30 ment Insurance Acts to have been unemployed on any day in that calendar week.Amend-ments as to third statutory-condition.6. (1) The following shall be substituted for the third statutory condition for the receipt of benefit by insured contributors-  35&quot; (hi) that he proves that he is capable of, and available for, work but unable to obtain suitable employment.&quot;(2) An insured contributor shall not be deemed to have failed to fulfil the third statutory condition by 40Paet I. - cont.
reason only that he is attending at an authorised course,  A.D. 1933. or  at   a training course  or  course   of  instruction,        approved by the Minister in his case. cont(3) Subsection (1) of section four of the Unemploy-5 ment Insurance Act, 1930, shall (save as respects the remainder of any period of disqualification thereunder current at the commencement of this Act) cease to have effect, and subsection (2) of that section shall have effect as if for the reference therein to that section there were 10 substituted a reference to the third statutory condition.7.-(1) The following shall be substituted for the Amend-fifth statutory condition for the receipt of benefit by ^V^3 as to insured contributors- *&apos; statutory&quot;(v) that, if he has been required by the condition. 15 Minister to attend  at any authorised course,he proves either that he duly attended in accordance with the requirement, or that he had good cause for not so attending.&quot;(2) For the purposes of the fifth statutory condition 20 an insured contributor shall not be deemed to have duly attended an authorised course during any period for which he has been required to discontinue his attendance thereat by reason of his misbehaviour while attending the course, unless he shows that the require-25 ment to discontinue his attendance was in all the circumstances of the case unreasonable.8. (1) Where a claim for benefit by an insured Period ofcontributor is disallowed by the court of referees or the disallow-umpire on the ground  fnceJif.r 0 benefit m30        (a) that the third statutory condition is not fulfilled certainin his case by reason of his failure to prove that cases-he is unable to obtain suitable employment; or(6) that he is disqualified under subsection (2) of section eight of the principal Act for receiving 35 benefit,the court of referees or the umpire shall declare the insured contributor to be disentitled to benefit for a period of six weeks or such shorter period as may be determined by the court of referees or the umpire, as 40 the case may be, being a period beginning as from such date as may be so determined :
A. D. 1933. Provided that, if a previous claim for benefit made by the insured contributor within the last preceding -cowi twelve months has been disallowed on either of the grounds aforesaid this subsection shall, in relation to the claim under consideration, have effect as if the words 5 &quot; six months&quot; were substituted for the words &quot; six weeks.&quot;(2) So much of subsection (2) of section eight of the principal Act as relates to the period of ^qualification, and section ten of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) 10 Act, 1921, shall cease to have effect.Definition 9. (1) For all the purposes of the Unemploymentofdepen- Insurance Acts, the expression &quot;a dependent child&quot; dent child.   means, in relation to a person entitled to benefit, anychild, younger brother, or younger sister, of his who -    15(a) is under the age of fourteen years and is main-tained wholly or mainly by him; or(b) is between the ages of fourteen and sixteen yearsand is maintained wholly or mainly by him and is either  20(i) a person under full time instruction at a. day school; or(ii) a person who is prevented from receiv-ing such instruction by reason of physical or mental infirmity; or 25(c) is a person between the ages of fourteen andsixteen years and is while unemployed main-tained wholly or mainly by him, and is a person in whose case the statutory conditions for the receipt of benefit, as hereinafter adapted 30 for the purposes of this paragraph, are fulfilled (or would be fulfilled, if he were an insured contributor) and who is not disquahfied (or would not be disquahfied if he were an insured contributor) under the Unemployment Insurance 35 Acts for the receipt of benefit.(2) For the purposes of determining whether a per-son is a dependent child by virtue of paragraph (c) of the last foregoing subsection, the statutory conditions shall be construed subject to the following adaptations, 40 that is to say, the first statutory condition shall be deemed to be omitted, and in the second statutory con-
dition the words &quot; has made application for unemploy- a.D. 1933. ment benefit in the prescribed, manner and&quot; and the       words &quot; since the date of the application&quot; shall be Paet I. deemed to be omitted. -^cont.5 (3) In this section the expression &quot; child &quot; includes a stepchild, adopted child (whether adopted under the Adoption of Children Act, 1926, or otherwise), and illegitimate child; the expression &quot;younger brother&quot; includes a younger half-brother and a younger step-10 brother; and the expression &quot; younger sister&quot; includes a younger half-sister and a younger step-sister.10. (1) No increase of benefit shall be payable to Amend -an insured contributor in respect of any person for any ments as to period before the date on which the insured contributor j^^?8^15 makes  application in the  prescribed manner for an respect Gf increase in respect of that person so, however, that dependants, regulations may be made under section thirty-five of the principal Act for authorising some earlier date to be substituted for the date of the application in cases in20 which good cause is shown for the delay in making the application.(2) Where a claim for benefit is made by an insured contributor and another insured contributor receives an increase of benefit in respect of the first-mentioned insured25 contributor for any period between the date when the claim is made and the date when it is allowed, the benefit payable to the first-mentioned insured contributor for that period shall be reduced by the amount of the increase of benefit so received by the second-mentioned insured30 contributor.11. (1) Notwithstanding anything in the Unem- Amend-ployment Insurance (Expiring Enactments) Act, 1933, ment as to section one of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 3) Act, anonialies 1931, shall continue in force, subject to the amendments re&amp;ua lons-35 hereafter specified in this section, until   Parliament otherwise determines.(2) The Minister shall have power to make regula-tions, subject to and in accordance with the provisions of the said section one, for the purpose of removing 40 any anomalies which may arise from time to time in the operation of the Unemployment Insurance Acts in connection with the classes of persons in that section mentioned.
Determina-tion of claims and questions.(3) Paragraph (d) of subsection (2). of the said section one shall have effect as if there were inserted at the end thereof &quot; but not including a married woman &quot; who proves that she has been deserted by, or is &quot; permanently separated from, her husband, or that 5 &quot; ner husband is permanently incapacitated,&quot; and the proviso to the said subsection (2) shall cease to have effect.(4) Section two of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 3) Act, 1931 (which provides for the constitution of 10 an Advisory Committee for the purpose of section one of that Act) shall cease to have effect.Determination of Claims and Questions.12.-(1) The following subsection shall be substi-tuted for subsection (3) of section eight of the Unemploy- 15 ment Insurance Act, 1930: &quot; (3) If the insurance officer is not satisfied that a claim ought to be allowed he may either refer the claim (so far as practicable within fourteen days from the date on which the claim 20 was submitted to him for examination) to the court of referees for their decision or, subject to the provisions of this subsection, himself disallow the claim :Provided that  25(a) the insurance officer shall not himself disallow a claim on any of the follow-ing grounds, namely, (i) that the third statutory con-dition is not fulfilled; 30(ii) that the claimant is disquali-fied by reason of his having lost his employment through his misconduct or left his employment voluntarily without just cause; 35(iii) that the claimant does not fulfil one or more of the additional conditions or terms with respect to the receipt of benefit imposed by regulations made under the Unem- 40 ployment Insurance (No. 3) Act, 1931, or is subject to restrictions onPaet I  cont.
the amount or period of benefit A.D. 1933. imposed by such regulations; and  (6) the insurance officer shall refer to the    _cont.court of referees any question whether 5 the claimant is liable to have deduc-tions made under any of the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance Acts from any benefit to which he is, or may become, entitled.&quot;10 (2) For the purposes of paragraph (6) of subsection (5) of section eight of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930 (which specifies some of the persons at whose instance an appeal shall he from a court of referees) a claimant for benefit shall not, in relation to any15 appeal, be deemed to be a member of any association of employed persons unless he wras a member thereof on the last date on which he was employed before the claim subject to the appeal was made, and has con-tinued to be a member therfore until the date when the20 appeal is made.(3) A court of referees shall record their decisions in writing and shall include in the record of every decision (a) a statement of their findings on questions of 25 fact material to the decision; and(6) in a case where the court grants leave to appeal to the umpire from the decision, a statement of the grounds on which leave to appeal is granted.Instruction and Training.30        13. (1) Every education authority shall, as soon Provision of as may he after the commencement of this Act, take authorised into consideration the number of persons in their area courses and who, having attained the minimum age for entry into courses Qf insurance, have not attained the age of eighteen years instruction35 and are capable of and available for work but have no and work or only part-time or intermittent work, and if, training, having regard to that number they are of opinion that courses of instruction for such persons are necessary in their area or in any part thereof, they shall submit to40 the Minister proposals for the provision of such courses and if the Minister approves the proposals with or with-out modifications the authority shall provide such courses in accordance therewith :
Power torequireattendanceat author -isedcourses.14. (1) If the Minister is satisfied in the case of any applicant for benefit who is unemployed or in the case of any person, who having attained the minimum 40 age for entry into insurance, has not attained the age of eighteen years (whether an insured contributor or not) who is capable of and available for work but has no works.D. 1933. Provided that the Minister shall not approve any - proposals submitted to him under this subsection unless -PartwJ- they are in accord with a scheme made by him with the &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;       consent of the Treasury after consultation with theBoard of Education. 5(2) If it is certified, by the Minister that, having regard to the number of such persons as aforesaid in the area of any education authority, insufficient pro-vision has been made under the last foregoing subsection for courses of instruction in or in any part of the area, 10 and that such courses of instruction as are specified in the certificate are necessary in such localities as are specified therein it shall be the duty of the authority to provide such courses of instruction in those localities within three months from the date of the certificate or such 15 further time as the Minister may allow, and if the authority&apos; fail to do so the Minister may make such order as he thinks necessary or proper for the purpose of compelling the authority to fulfil that duty, and any such order may be enforced by mandamus: 20Provided that any order made by the Minister under this subsection may be varied or revoked by a subsequent order made by him in like manner.(3) The Minister, subject to the approval of the Treasury, may contribute towards the cost of courses of 25 instruction provided under the foregoing provisions of this section, and may himself provide training courses for persons who have attained the age of eighteen years and are capable of and available for work but have no work or only part-time or intermittent work. 30(4) The Minister, subject to the approval of the &quot; Treasury, may also defray, or contribute towards, the cost of training courses, courses of instruction, or courses of occupation, provided by any public authority or other body for persons who are capable of and avail- 35 able for work but have no work or only part-time or intermittent work.
or only part-time or intermittent work, that it would A-.D. 1933. be for his advantage to attend an authorised course    p     . at which he can reasonably be expected to attend, the    -^ nt&apos; Minister may require his attendance at that course in 5 accordance with regulations made by the Minister.(2) If any person under the age of eighteen years whose attendance at an authorised course has been required by the Minister under this section does not duly attend that course, or by reason of his misbehaviour10 while attending the course is required to discontinue his attendance for any period, then proceedings may he taken by or on behalf of the Minister, in the case of a person who has not attained the age of sixteen years, under section forty-five of the Education Act, 1921 (not-15 withstanding that he may be over the age at which an order could otherwise be made under that section) or, in the case of a person who has attained the age of sixteen years under section seventy-eight of that Act, as if the requirement were, respectively, a school attend-20 ance order, or a requirement imposed under the said Act for attendance at a continuation school, and as if proceedings could be taken by or on behalf of the Minister under those sections, and the provisions of that Act shall apply accordingly.25 (3) The regulations made by the Minister under this section may make provision for the establishment of boards of assessors for the purpose of reporting to him as to the advisability of requiring persons to attend an authorised course.30        15. (1) Subject to the provisions of this section the Power to Minister may, with the consent of the Treasury, authorise make grants the payment out of the Unemployment Fund of grants 2?* of . towards expenses incurred in respect of the attendance ment^und at authorised courses of persons who have not attained towards35 the age of eighteen years and of insured contributors in expenses receipt of benefit who have attained that age. of attend-(2) Grants under this section  authorised(a) in respect of attendance at authorised courses, courses-being courses of instruction, shall not exceed 40 fifty per cent.;(6) in respect of attendance at authorised courses, being training courses, shall not exceed seventy-five per cent.;
of any amount which may be paid out of the moneys provided by Parliament in respect of the attendances in question.(3) All sums paid out of the Unemployment Fund under this section shall be paid as an appropriation in aid of moneys provided by Parliament for the expenses of the Minister.Power to 16. The Minister may make regulations requiringrequirejiotifi- employers to notify to the Minister in the prescribed discharge      manner the discharge from their employment of any 10 from employ- person (whether an insured contributor or not) who has persons under attained the minimum age for entry into insurance, but eighteen.      wri0 has not attained the age of eighteen years.Establish-ment of Un-employmenb Insurance Statutory Committee and duties of Com-mittee as respects Unemploy-ment Fund.Financial Provisions.17. (1) There shall be constituted a committee, 15 to be called &quot;the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee &quot; to give advice and assistance to the Minister in connection with the discharge of his functions under the Unemployment Insurance Acts and to perform the duties hereafter specified in this Part of this Act; and the 20 provisions of Part I of the Second Schedule to this Act shall have effect with respect to the constitution and proceedings of the Committee.(2) The Committee shall not later than the end of February in every year make a report to the Minister 25 on the financial condition of the Unemployment Fund on the thirty-first day of December last preceding, and shall also make a report to the Minister on the financial condition of the fund whenever they consider that the fund is or is likely to become, and is likely to continue 30 to be, insufficient to discharge its liabilities, and may make such a report at such other times as they think fit.(3) If the Committee at any time report that the Unemployment fund is or is likely to become, and is likely to continue to be, insufficient to discharge its 35 nubilities, or is and is likely to continue to be more than reasonably sufficient to discharge its liabihties, the report shall contain (a) recommendations for the  amendment,&apos; either generally or in relation to special classes of 40Part I.  cont.
insured contributors, of the provisions of the A.D. 1933. Unemployment Insurance Acts set out in Part II        of the Second Schedule to this Act, being such    Pabt I. amendment as, in the opinion of the Committee &quot;5 is required in order to make the Fund, as the case may be, sufficient or no more than reasonably sufficient to discharge its liabilities; and(b) an estimate of the effect which the amendments recommended will have on the financial con-10 dition of the fund;I t -    &apos;    -and, where the Committee report that the fund is and is likely to continue to be more than reasonably sufficient to discharge its habiHties, the report may contain recom-mendations for the application of any sum towards the 15 discharge of the liabilities mentioned in subsection (2) of the section of this Act next following.(4) The Committee shall give such notice as they consider sufficient of their intention to make a report under this section and shall take into consideration 20 any representations which may be made to them with respect thereto.(5) Within the period of two months after the receipt by the Minister of any report under this section or, if Parliament is not sitting at the expiration of that 25 period then as soon after the expiration thereof as Parlia-ment sits, the Minister shall lay the report before both Houses of Parliament, and in a case where the report contains recommendations for the amendment of the Unemployment Insurance Acts, shall after consultation 30 with the Treasury, lay before both Houses of Parliament (a) the draft of an order making such amendments in the provisions of the Unemployment Insur-ance Acts as are duly recommended in the 35 report, or, if and so far as any amendmentso recommended is not adopted bythe Minister, making such amendments in those provisions (being amendments which the Committee had power to recommend) as will, in his opinion 40 have substantially the  same  effect  on thefinancial condition of the Unemployment Fund as that estimated in the report as being the effect of the amendments recommended; and
A.T). 1933,Part I  cont.Treasury advances to Unemploy-ment Fund.15(6) if and in so far as the amendments proposed in the draft order differ from the amendments recommended in the report, a statement of the reasons for the difference.(6) If each House resolves that the draft of an g order laid before it under this section be approved, the Minister shall make an order in the terms of the draft to take effect on such date as may be specified in the order, and as from that date the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance Acts shall have effect subject to the provisions of the order.(7) So much of the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933, as provides for the variation, otherwise than in accordance with the provisions of this section, of the rates of contributions in force at the commencement of this Act shall cease to have effect.(8) This section shall come into operation on the passing of this Act.18. (1) Section five of the Unemployment Insur-ance Act, 1921 (which provides for advances by the Treasury to the Unemployment Fund of sums amounting to one hundred and fifteen million pounds), shall cease to have effect, except in so far as it provides that the advances made before the commencement of this Act under the said section together with interest thereon shall be charged on and payable out of that fund.(2) Subject as hereinafter provided the liability imposed on the Unemployment Fund by the said section five in respect of the said advances and interest, and the hability incurred by the Treasury to the National Debt Commissioners in respect of the provision of 30 money for the purpose of the said advances, shall be discharged by the payment to the National Debt Commissioners of half-yearly instalments which (except for the last thereof which shall be for the balance of the advances and interest then outstanding) shall be of two 35 million seven hundred and fifty thousand pounds each: the first of the said instalments shall be paid on the thirtieth day of September, nineteen hundred and thirty-four and a subsequent instalment shall be paid on the thirty-first day of March and the thirtieth day of 40 September in eaoh year, and the said instalments shall c*as8 to b* payable when the National Debt Com-2025
missioners certify to the Minister that the amount of the A.p. 1933.advances and interest outstanding immediately before p^Tjthe commencement of this Act, together with interest &quot; cont&apos; thereon at the appropriate rate, has been discharged :5 Provided that nothing in this subsection shall be construed as preventing the application, on the recom-mendation of the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee, of sums out of the fund towards the discharge of the said liabilities in addition to the  instalments10 therein mentioned.In this subsection the &quot; appropriate rate &quot; means, as respects any amount for which a rate of interest has been fixed by the Treasury before the commencement of this Act for any period, that rate for that period, and, as15 respects any such amount after that period and as respects any other amount, the rate of three and one half per cent, per annum.(3) Subject   to  the   provisions of this subsection, the   instalments   aforesaid   shall   be  paid   out   of  the 20 Unemployment Fund :Provided that, where the moneys in the Unemploy-ment Fund are insufficient to pay any instalment falling due or any part thereof, the Treasury shall pay to the National Debt Commissioners out of the Consolidated 25 Fund or the growing produce thereof the sum required to make good the deficiency, and an amount equal to that sum shall be treated as having been temporarily advanced to the Unemployment Fund.(4) The Treasury may under this subsection at any 30 time temporarily advance to the Unemployment Fund out of the Consolidated Fund or the growing produce thereof such sums as may be required from time to time for the purpose of making any payments properly falling to be made out of the Unemployment Fund other than 35 instalments payable under the foregoing provisions of this section and the repayment of any sums treated under the last preceding subsection as having been temporarily advanced to the fund.(5) If at any time it appears to the Minister, after 40 consultation with the Treasury, that the Unemployment Fund is, or will shortly become, insufficient to discharge its liabilities, including the repayment of any advances made under the last two preceding subsections within the time limited by this section in the case of such advances,
A.D. 1933. there shall be advanced to the fund out of moneys provided by PakTi Parliament such sums as appear to the Treasury to be -^cont&apos;    required to enable the fund to discharge its liabilities.(6) Any sums advanced or treated as having been temporarily advanced under this section, together with 5 interest thereon at such rate as may be fixed by the Treasury, shall be charged on the Unemployment Fund and shall be repaid to the Exchequer in such manner as the Treasury may direct out of that fund, and shall be so repaid (a) in the case of a payment treated as having been 10 advanced under subsection (3) of this section, within six months from the date of the payment to the National Debt Commissioners ; (6) in the case of an advance under subsection (4) of this section, before the end of the financial year 15 in which the advance was made ; (c) in the case of an advance under subsection (5) of this section, as to one-third thereof not later than the end of the first financial year next following the financial year in which the advance 20 teas made, and as to two-thirds thereof not later than the end of the second financial year so next following.(7) Whenever any advance is made to the Unem-ployment Fund under this section, the Minister shall 25 forthwith report the fact to the Unemployment Insur-ance Statutory Committee.Miscellaneous and General.19. (1) Before making any regulations under the Unemployment Insurance Acts, except regulations made 30 under the provisions of this Part of this Act relating to instruction and training, the Minister shall submit to the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee a draft of the regulations and the Committee shall forthwith consider the draft and report thereon to the Minister, 35 and the Minister shall not make the regulations until the report of the Committee on the draft thereof has been received and considered by him:Provided that where the Minister certifies that on account of urgency or any special reason any regulations 40 should come into operation without delay, the Minister may, before receiving the report of the Committee on the draft thereof, make the regulations as provisional regulations, so however that no provisional regulationsDuties of Unemploy-ment In-surance Statutory Committee as respects regulations and advice.
shall continue in force for longer than three months after A.D. 1933. the receipt by the Minister of the report. -(2) Throughout the provisions of the Unemploy-    _cant&apos;ment Insurance Acts, except the provisions of sections 5 eighteen and twenty of the principal Act (which relate to special and supplementary schemes) and the enact-ments amending those sections and except the provisions of section eighteen of this Act, references to orders (other than Orders in Council), and special orders required or10 authorised to be made thereunder shall be construed as references to regulations, and any such orders or special orders made before the commencement of this Act under the provisions of the said Acts (with the exceptions afore-said) may be revoked, varied or amended in the same15 manner as if they had been regulations.(3) The provisions of the Third Schedule to this Act shall have effect with respect to the publication of, and objections to, draft regulations laid before the Committee.20 (4) Whenever any regulations (being neither regu-lations made under the provisions of this Part of this Act relating to instruction and training nor provi-sional regulations) are laid before both Houses of Par-liament in pursuance of subsection (3) of section thirty-25 five of the principal Act, the report of the Committee on the draft thereof shall be laid together therewith, and in a case where any report so laid contains recom-mendations for the amendment of the draft, there shall be laid together with the report a statement by the30 Minister showing what effect (if any) has been given to the recommendations, and, if effect has not been given to any recommendation, giving reasons for not adopting it.(5) The Minister may from time to time refer to the Committee for consideration and advice such questions 35 relating to the operation of the Unemployment Insurance Acts as he thinks fit (including questions as to the advisability of amending those Acts).20. (1) The Unemployment Insurance Statutory Duty of Committee shall as soon as may be after the passing of this Unemploy 40 Act make such proposals as may seem to them prac- mentlnsur-ticable   for   the   insurance   against   unemployment ^torv Com of persons  engaged  in  employment  in  agriculture, mittee and shall make a report to the Minister containing the as to in-scheme and any recommendations of the Committee with surance of
A.D. 1933. respect thereto and the report shall be laid before       Parliament. Part I-cont&apos; (2) The Committee shall give such notice as theypersons       consider sufficient  of their intention to  enquire into employed in the matter, aforesaid, and shall take into consideration 5 agriculture. arvv representations submitted to them by persons appearing to them to represent employers or persons employed in agriculture or by any Government depart-ment.(3) In this section the expression &quot;agriculture&quot; 10 includes horticulture and forestry.Amend-ments as to arrange-ments with associations of employed persons.21. Where, in  pursuance  of  a decision of   an insurance officer, court of referees or umpire, any sum by way of provision for unemployment has been paid by a society, body or other association with which  an 15 arrangement has been made under section seventeen of the principal Act to a member of the association, repayment of the sum shall, notwithstanding that the decision is revised on new facts being brought to the knowledge of the insurance officer, court of referees or 20 umpire, be made to the association out of the Unem-ployment Fund, if it is shown that no one concerned with the case on behalf of the association could reasonably have been expected to ascertain the facts on which the decision was revised, and that recovery of the sum 25 has not been practicable.22. A supplementary scheme under section twenty of the principal Act may be submitted by any organisations which appear to the Minister to represent a majority of such of the employers in any industry, 30 and of such of the employees in that industry, as are organised:Provided that the Minister, before approving any supplementary scheme so submitted, shall take steps to ascertain so far as practicable, and shall take into con- 35 sideration, the views of other employers and employees in the industry.Amend- 23.-(1) Subsection (3) of section twenty-two of thements as to principal Act (which provides for the recovery of contri-butions where an employer has been convicted of the 40 offence of failing or neglecting to pay any contributions) shall apply in a case where an employer has been chargedAmend-ments as to schemes.offences.
Part I.  cont.with such an offence and an order has been made under A.D. 1933. subsection (1) of section one of the Probation of Offenders Act, 1907, in the same manner as it applies where an employer has been convicted of such an offence.5       (2) In any case where (a) an employer is convicted of any offence under * section thirteen of the Stamp Duties Manage-ment Act, 1891, as applied by regulations made under section thirty-three of the princi-10 pal Act, or of the offence under subsection (2)of section twenty-two of the principal Act of contravening or not complying with the requirements of the regulations made under that Act, or is charged with any such offence15 and an order is made under subsection (1) ofsection one of the Probation of Offenders Act, 1907; and(6) the evidence on which he is convicted or on which the order is made shows  that the20 employer, for the purpose of paying any con-tribution which he was liable to pay, has affixed to an unemployment book or card any stamp which has been cancelled or defaced in any way whatever, whether it has25 actually been used for the purpose of paymentof a contribution or not;the employer shall be liable to pay to the Unemployment Pund a sum equal to the amount of the contribution in respect of which the stamp was affixed, and on such a30 conviction or on the making of such an order, if notice of intention to do so has been served with the summons or warrant, evidence may be given of the failure or neglect on the part of the employer to pay other con-tributions in respect of the same person during the two35 years preceding the date of the offence, and on proof of such failure or neglect, the employer shall be liable to pay to the Unemployment Pund a sum equal to the total of the contributions which he is so proved to have failed or neglected to pay. Any sum paid by an employer under40 this subsection shall be treated as a payment in satis-faction of the unpaid contributions, and the employed person&apos;s portion of those contributions shall not be recoverable by the employer from the employed person.
Amend-ment as to summary recovery of sums due to Unemploy-ment Fund.(3) The following provisions shall have effect with respect to sums ordered to be paid to the Unemploy-ment Fund under the last foregoing subsection: (a) any sum so ordered to be paid by a court in England shall be recoverable as penalty; 5(6) if the employer, being a company, fails to pay to the Unemployment Fund any sum which the company has been ordered to pay under the last foregoing subsection, that sum or such part thereof as remains unpaid shall be a debt 10 due to the Unemployment Fund jointly and severally from any directors of the company who knew, or could reasonably have been expected to know, of the failure or neglect to pay the contribution or contributions in ques- 15 tion, and may be recovered accordingly as a civil debt.(4) If any person for any purpose whatsoever falsely represents that he or any other person is the person specified in an unemployment book or card as 20 being the person to whom the hook or card was issued, he shall he liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding ten pounds :Provided that nothing in this subsection shall be taken to prejudice the provisions of subsection (1) of 25 section twenty-two of the principal Act.24. (1) Proceedings for the summary recovery as civil debts of sums due to the Unemployment Fund may, notwithstanding anything in any Act to the contrary, be brought at any time within three years from the time 30 when the matter complained of arose.(2) In this and the last foregoing section of this Act and in section twenty-two of the principal Act references to the Unemployment Fund shall be construed as in-cluding references to the seamen&apos;s special fund or any similar fund established by any order or regulations for the time being in force under section thirty-nine of the principal Act.35Amendment of s. 41 of principal Act, and application of Acts to25. (1) The fixed number of contributions for the purposes of section forty-one of the principal Act 40 (which makes special provision with respect to dis-charged seamen, marines, soldiers and airmen) shall, in the case of a man discharged after the commencementPart I. -cont.
of this Act, be a number equal to the number of weeks A.D. 1933.during which he had served in the Forces and for the  purposes of the Unemployment Insurance Acts the ^^ntcontributions credited to him under the said section shall 0fficers of5 be deemed to have been paid in respect of him at the reserverate of one contribution per week over a period ending forces. , with the week in which his discharge takes place :Provided that the said fixed number shall not in the case of any man serving in the Forces at the com-10 mencement of this Act be less than thirty.For the purposes of this subsection any part of a week shall be reckoned as a week.(2) The provisions of the last foregoing subsection shall have effect so as to amend section forty-one of the 15 principal Act in its application to Northern Ireland.(3) Subsection (2) of section forty of the principal Act and subsection (1) of section nine of the Unemploy -ment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1921, shall apply to officers of the naval reserves, regular army reserve of officers,20 supplementary reserve of officers, air force reserve, territorial army, territorial army reserve of officers and auxiliary air force, and to persons given temporary commissions in the naval, land or air forces and to persons given temporary warrants in the Royal Navy or Royal25 Marines, who before training or before being called out on an occasion of great emergency or before being called out for actual military service or embodied or before being commissioned on an occasion of great emergency for   service   during   the   emergency,   were   normally30 employed persons within the meaning of the Un-employment Insurance Acts, in like manner as they apply to men of the reserves and forces mentioned in those subsections.26. (1) For the purpose of qualifying a constable Extension of 35 of the metropolitan police force, who is appointed for a principal fixed period of service, to receive benefit on his discharge Act .to sllorfc from the force on the completion of his period of service, g6^^6 there shall be paid to the Unemployment Fund out of the ^ ^tro-Metropohtan Police Fund by way of employers&apos; and politan 40 employed persons&apos;  contributions in respect of every police force, such constable so discharged from the force, such sum as will, in the opinion of the Treasury, be sufficient to enable him to be credited on his discharge with a number
of contributions equal to the number of weeks during which he has served in the force.For the purposes of this subsection any part of a week shall be reckoned as a week.(2) Every such constable so discharged as afore- 5 said shall, for the purpose of the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance Acts relating to the rights of an insured person with respect to benefit, but not for any other purpose, be treated as if he were on the date of his discharge an insured contributor who ceased 10 to be employed on that date and in respect of whom contributions equal in number to those credited to him under this section had been paid at the rate of one contribution per week over a period ending with the week in which his discharge takes place.(3) The sums to be paid under this section out of the Metropolitan Police Fund shall be calculated in such manner as the Treasury may direct, and shall be paid in such manner and at such dates as may be agreed upon between the Minister and the Secretary of State.1520Power of Minister to assistschemes forpromotinggreaterregularityof employ -ment.27. (1) Where any scheme for promoting greater regularity of employment in any industry is approved by the Minister, the Minister may, in accordance with arrange-ments made by him with the consent of the Treasury, assist the administration of the scheme by attaching 25 officers of the Ministry of Labour to help in the adminis-tration thereof and by such other means as he thinks fit.(2) The Minister may, in accordance with such arrangements as aforesaid, issue on behalf of employers to persons to whom any such scheme applies, sums by 30 way of wages or additional benefits in respect of unem-ployment or compensation for loss of employment; but any arrangements making provisions for the issue of any such sums shall also make provision for paying to the Minister any sums to be so issued by him and any 35 expenses incurred by him which are attributable to the scheme.(3) If an organisation representing employers and an organisation representing workpeople in any industry make to the Minister a joint representation as to any 40 difficulty in the operation of any scheme for promotingPart I.  cont.
greater regularity of employment in the industry, or in making any further schemes for that purpose for the industry, the Minister may appoint a person to hold an inquiry into the circumstances giving rise to the 5 difficulty and to make a report to him with respect thereto.The fee to be paid by the Minister to any person holding such an inquiry as aforesaid shall be such as the Minister may with the consent of the Treasury 10 direct.(4) In this section the expression &quot; industry &quot; has the same meaning as in section eighteen of the principal Act.1528. Notwithstanding anything in the Unemploy-ment Insurance (Expiring Enactments) Act, 1933, the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930, shall, subject to the amendments made therein by any subsequent enactment, including this Act, continue in force until Parliament otherwise deterrnines.Continua-tion of 20 &amp; 21 Geo. 5. c. 16.2025ments.29. The amendments specified in the second column Minor of the Fourth Schedule to this Act, being minor amend- amend-ments of the principal Act and of the enactments amend-ing that Act, shall be made in the provisions of that Act and those enactments specified in the first column of that schedule.30. There shall be defrayed out of moneys provided Payments by Parliament(a)any increase attributable to the passing of this Part of this Act in the sum payable out of moneys 30 provided by Parliament by virtue of subsection(3) of section five, or sections forty or forty-one, of the principal Act, or of section three of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 3) Act, 1931 ;(b) any sum by which any education grants under 35 any other Act are increased by reason of theadditional powers and duties conferred and imposed by this Part of this Act on education authorities ;(c) any expenses incurred by the Minister in carrying 40 this Part of this Act into effect.out of moneys provided by Parliament,Part I.  cont.
A.D. 1933.        31.-(1) In this Part of this Act, unless the con-text otherwise requires, the following expressions have -oowi nieanings hereby respectively assigned, to them, thatInterpreta-   19 to sav&apos; Part 1*and &quot;Authorised course&quot; means a training course or 5construction course of instruction provided under or in pur-of refer- suance of subsection (1), (2) or (3) of sectionences. thirteen of this Act and includes, in relation toinsured contributors who have attained the age of eighteen years, any training course provided 10 under Part II of this Act; &quot; Benefit &quot; means unemployment benefit;&quot; Benefit rights &quot; means, in relation to an insured contributor, his right to receive benefit for the number of days allowed in his case by the 15 provisions of paragraphs (a) and (6) of subsection (1) of section three of this Act, or by the provisions of sub-paragraph (6) of paragraph (1) of Article one of the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931, as the 20 case may be;&quot; Education authority&quot; means a local education authority for the purposes of higher education under the Education Act, 1921;&quot; Excepted Employments &quot; means the employments 25 specified in  Part II  of  the  First Schedule to the principal Act, and any employments included among or added to those employments under section two of this Act;&quot; Insurable employment,&quot; in relation to any person, 30 means such employment as would make him an employed person within the meaning of the principal Act;&quot; Insured contributor&quot; means a person insured under the principal Act; 35&quot; The Minister &quot; means the Minister of Labour;&quot; The principal Act&quot; means the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920;&quot; The Unemployment Insurance Acts &quot; means the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933, 40 and this Part of this Act.
(2) Any reference in this Part of this Act to any A.D. 1933. other enactment or to any provision of any other enact-    -p &quot;*&quot;*&quot;&quot; * ment shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be construed as a reference to that enactment or that &apos;5 provision, as the case may be, as amended by any subsequent enactment, mcluchng this Act32. This Part of this Act in its application to Application Scotland shall have effect  subject  to the following of Part I modifications:- to Scotland.10       (1) A reference to the Scottish Education Depart-- . ment shall be substituted for any reference tothe Board of Education.(2) A reference to efficient education shall be sub-stituted for any reference to efficient elementary 15 instruction.(3) A reference to the Adoption of Children (Scot-land) Act, 1930, shall be substituted for any reference to the Adoption of Children Act, 1926.20       (4) A reference to a complaint shall he substituted for any reference to a summons or warrant.(5) In subsection (2) of section thirteen the words &quot; and any such order may be enforced by &quot; mandamus&quot; shall be omitted;  and it is25 hereby declared with  respect to any order made by the Minister under that subsection that proceedings for the enforcement thereof may be taken at the instance of the Minister under section ninety-one of the Court of Session30 Act, 1868, as amended by any  subsequentenactment.(6) Section fourteen  shall have effect as if for subsection (2) thereof there were substituted the following subsection :  35 &quot; (2) If any person under the age of eighteen years whose attendance at an authorised course has been required by the Minister under this section does not duly attend that course, or by reason of his misbehaviour while 40 -      attending the course is required to discontinuehis attendance for any period, then  ...
AD 1933 (a) *n        case G^ a Person wmo has not.11.   &apos; attained the  age  of sixteen  years,Part I. proceedings may be taken by or on-cont. behalf of the Minister under section four of the Day Industrial Schools 5 (Scotland) Act, 1893 (notwithstanding that such person may be over the age at which an order could otherwise be made under that section) as if the requirement to attend the course were 10 an attendance order and as if proceed-ings could be taken by pv on behalf of the Minister under the said section, and the provisions of the said Act shall apply accordingly; and 15(&amp;) in the case of a person who has attained the age of sixteen years, the provisions of subsection (8) of section fifteen of the Education (Scotland) Act, 1918, shall apply as if the requirement to 20 attend the course were an order by an education authority served upon such person in accordance with that subsection.&quot;(7) Subsection (1) of section twenty-four shall not 25 apply.(8) In subsection (1) of section thirty-one the definition of &quot;Education authority&quot; shall be omitted.Commence. 33. (1) Save as therein otherwise expressly pro- 30ment, vided, this Part of this Act shall come into operationextent and   one month after the passing of this Act. citation ofParti. (2) Save as therein otherwise expressly provided,this Part of this Act shall not extend to Northern Ireland. 35(3) This Part of this Act, together with the First, Second, Third and Fourth Schedules to this Act, may be cited separately as the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1933, and the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1933, and the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 40 to 1933, may be cited together as the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933.
Part II. AD, 1933.Unemployment Assistance. Paet II.34. (1) For the purposes of this Part of this Act Unem-thcre shall be constituted a Board, to be called &quot; the ployment 5 Unemployment Assistance Board,&quot; and the provisions Assistance of the Fifth Schedule to this Act shall have effect with advisory respect to the constitution  and  proceedings  of  the committees. Board.(2) The functions of the Board shall be the assistance 10 of persons to whom this Part of this Act applies who are in need of work and the promotion of their welfare and, in particular, the making of provision for the improve-ment and re-establishment of the condition of such persons with a view to their being in all respects fit for 15 entry into or return to regular employment, and the grant and issue to such persons of unemployment allow-ances (hereinafter referred to as &quot;allowances&quot;) in accordance with the provisions of this Part of this Act.(3) For the purpose of securing the advice and 20 assistance of persons having local knowledge and experience in matters affecting the functions of the Board under this Part of this Act, the Board shall arrange for the establishment of advisory committees for such areas as they think fit, and may pay to 25 members of such committees such travelling and other allowances (including compensation for loss of remunera-tive time) as the Minister may, with the consent of the Treasury, determine.(4) A report on the operation of this Part of this 30 Act shall be made annually by the Board to the Minister who shall lay every such report before Parliament.35. (1) Subject to the provisions of this Part of Application this Act relating to suspension from the application of Part II thereof, this Part of this Act applies to any person of Act. 35 in whose case the followdng qualifications are fulfilled, that is to say : (a) that he has attained the age of sixteen years and is under the age of sixty-five years; and(6) that he is either  40 (i) a  person  whose  normal  occupation  isemployment in respect of which contributions
are payable under the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Acts, 1925 to 1932; or(h) a person who, not having normally been engaged in any remunerative occupation since 5 attaining the age of sixteen years, might reasonably have expected that his normal occupation would have been such employment as aforesaid but for the industrial circumstances of the district in which he resides; and 10hat he is capable of and available for work:Provided that during any period during which a person is disqualified for receiving benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts owing to his having lost employment by reason of a stoppage of work which was 15 due to a trade dispute, or during which he would have been so disquahfied as aforesaid if he had been an insured contributor under those Acts, he shall, notwith-standing that the foregoing qualifications are fulfilled in his case, be deemed not to be a person to whom this 20 Part of this Act applies.(2) Rules made under this Part of this Act may provide that for the purposes of the foregoing qualifica-tions a person shall, in such circumstances as may be specified in the rules, be deemed to be capable of and 25 available for work notwithstanding such periods of occasional sickness or incapacity as may be specified therein.(3) Any question whether a person is or is not a person to whom this Part of this Act applies shall be 30 decided by officers of the Board, but any applicant for an allowance under this Part of this Act or any public assistance authority may appeal from any such decision to the chairman of the appeal tribunal constituted in accordance with the provisions of the Sixth Schedule 35 to this Act, whose decision shall be final:Provided that, if, on consideration of any appeal under this subsection, any dispute or doubt arises as to (a) the question whether any employment is employ -ment in respect of which contributions are 40 payable under the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Acts, 1925 to 1932; or(c) t.Part II.  cont.
Part II.  cont.(6) the  question whether a person is disqualified A.D. 1933. for receiving benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts owing to his having lost employ-ment by reason of a stoppage of work which was 5 due to a trade dispute, or would have been sodisqualified as aforesaid if he had been an insured contributor under those Acts;the first mentioned question shall be referred by the chairman of the appeal tribunal for the decision of the10 Minister of Health in such manner as he may direct, and the second mentioned question shall be referred by the chairman of the appeal tribunal to the insurance officer and be determined by the same persons and in the same manner as if the question had arisen upon a claim for15 benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts.An appeal from a decision of the Minister of Health upon a question referred to him under this subsection shall lie in the same manner as an appeal under section eighty-nine of the National Health Insurance Act, 1924, 20 and the rules of court for regulating such appeals shall apply accordingly and the Minister of Health shall have the same power to refer a question for decision as he has under that section. -(4) Nothing in the last foregoing subsection shall be 25 construed as preventing an officer of the Board or the chairman of the appeal tribunal, on new facts being brought to his knowledge, revising a decision given in any particular case, but, where any such revision is made, the provisions of the last foregoing subsection shall apply 30 in relation thereto in like manner as they applied in relation to the original decision, and the revised decision shall have effect as from the date thereof.36. In  the  exercise   of   the   functions   of   the ProvisionUnemployment Assistance Board under this Part of this and main-35 Act the Board, with the approval of the Minister, may  tenance of17      training(a) provide and maintain framing courses for persons courses.who have attained the age of eighteen years and co-operate  with  the  Minister  or  any local authority or other body in the provision and 40 maintenance of such courses; and(b) make  provision for  the  continuance  of thetraining and instruction afforded in connection with any such training course by entering into. [170] C2
A.D. 1933. agreements   with   local   authorities  whereby  persons to whom this Part of this Act applies,^&quot;-cont may5 as part of such training and instruction,&apos; &quot;&apos; be employed for periods not exceeding threemonths upon work for the authority of such a 5 character as to render them more fit for entry into or return to regular employment and under conditions suitable for that purpose; but any such agreement shall be subject to the approval of the Treasury and shall provide for payment 10 at the expense of the authority of the rates of wages customary in  the  district,  and  may provide for contributions being made by the Board towards any additional expenditure in-curred by the authority by reason of the work 15 being utilised as part of the training course.Persons to 37. (1) Subject to the provisions of this Part ofwhom and   tnis Act an allowance may after the appointed day be circum-       granted thereunder to any person to whom this Part of which allow- this Act applies, if he has proved in accordance with 20 ances may   rules made under this Part of this Act  be granted. ^ ^nafc ne js registered for employment in theprescribed manner and has made applicationfor an allowance in the prescribed manner; and (6) that he has no work or only such part-time or 25intermittent work as not to enable him to earnsufficient for his needs; and(c) that he is in need of an allowance.(2) The amount of any allowance to be granted under this Part of this Act to an applicant shall be 30 determined by reference to his needs, including the needs of any members of the household of which he is a member who are dependent on, or ordinarily supported by, him, not being persons in whose case the qualifi-cations set out in subsection (1) of section thirty-five 35 of this Act are fulfilled.(3) The need of an applicant shall be determined and his needs assessed in accordance with regulations made under this Part of this Act, and such regulations shall in particular provide that the resources of an 40 applicant taken into account shall include the resources of all members of the household of which he is himself a member (due regard being had also to the personal
requirements of those members whose resources are taken A.D. 1933.into account) and shall further provide that in com-  puting all such resources the following provisions shall Part u-be complied with (that is to say):  coni&apos;5 (a) the first five shillings of the applicant&apos;s sick pay from a Friendly Society and the first seven shillings and sixpence of the applicant&apos;s benefit under the National Health Insurance Acts, 1924 to 1932, shall be disregarded:10 (b) any wounds or disability pension and any weekly payment by way of compensation under the enactments relating to workmen&apos;s compensation shall, as respects one-half thereof, be disregarded:(c) all money and investments treated as capital 15 assets shall (i) in so far as the value of all such money and investments considered in the aggregate does not exceed twenty-five pounds, be dis-regarded;20 (ii) in so far as that value exceeds twenty-five pounds but does not exceed three hundred pounds, be treated as equivalent to a weekly income of one shilling for every complete twenty-five pounds:25        (d) in taking into account the value to any person of any interest in the dwelling-house in which he resides, any sum which might be obtained by him by seUing, or borrowing money upon -   the security of, that interest shall be disregarded.30       (4) In this section the expression &quot; needs &quot; does not include medical needs.(5) For the purpose of investigating the circum- . stances of applicants for allowances, the Board may act either through their own officers, or, if and so long as 35 there are in force arrangements made in that behalf by the Board Avith the Minister or any local authority, through such officers of the Minister, or of the authority, as may be provided by any such arrangement.38. (1) All applications for allowances under this Deter-40 Part of this Act and all questions arising in connection initiation of with such applications shall be determined by officers applicationsof the Unemployment Assistance Board. a^c*s [170]                         C 3
(2) In order that an applicant for an allowance may be given an opportunity of becoming fit for entry into or return to regular employment, any such determi-nation granting an allowance may, subject to and in accordance with rules made in that behalf under this 5 Part of this Act, determine that the allowance shall take the form of provision for the maintenance of an applicant at a training course and the issue of payments to him during his training thereat, and, where the needs of any member of the household of which he is a member have 10 been taken into account in determining the amount of the allowance, the issue of payments to such of those members as may be specified in the determination.(3) Where an applicant for an-allowance is dependent on or ordinarily supported by another member of the 15 household who is also an applicant for an allowance, any determination granting an allowance to the first mentioned applicant may, subject to and in accordance with rules made in that behalf under this Part of this Act, determine that the allowance granted to him shall 20 be issued wholly or in part to the second mentioned applicant.(4) Por the purposes of this Part of this Act there shall be constituted appeal tribunals and the provisions of the Sixth Schedule to this Act shall have effect with 25 respect to the constitution and proceedings of such tribunals.(5) If any person to whom this Part of this Act applies is aggrieved by the determination of any officer of the Board upon any application made by him for an 30 allowance under this Part of this Act, he may, subject as hereinafter provided, appeal to the appeal tribunal, and on any such appeal the tribunal may make a deter-mination confirming the determination appealed against or substituting therefor any determination which the 35 officer of the Board might lawfully have made; and any determination of the appeal tribunal shall be final:Provided that, save as provided in the section next following, no appeal under this subsection shall he to the appeal tribunal without the leave of the chairman 40 of the tribunal, so, however, that leave shall not be granted unless it appears to the chairman that the need of the applicant has not been determined or that his needsPart II. -cont. questions relating thereto.
have not been assessed in accordance with the regulations A.D. 1933.made in that behalf under this Part of this Act, or that       there are other special circumstances affecting the case.   Part **-r &amp;  cont.(6) Rules may he made under this Part of this 5 Act-(a) as to the date as from which determinationsmade under this and the next following section by officers of the Board and by appeal tribunals shall have effect, and as to the period for which 10 such determinations shall remain in force;(b) as to the review of such  determinations asaforesaid.39. (1) No application for an allowance shall be Method of dealt with under this section unless, having regard to all dealing with15 the circumstances of the case, and, in particular, to the case? ?f question whether the applicant has failed to avail him- ^^ultv self of opportunities of employment or training and to the question whether there is any necessity for protecting the interests of the applicant or of persons dependent20 upon him, the officer of the Unemployment Assistance Board, or on an appeal, the appeal tribunal, by whom the application is to be determined is of opinion that the application ought to be dealt with under this section as a case of special difficulty:25 Provided that an application shall not he so dealt with by reason only that the applicant has not accepted an offer of employment which would not, in relation to a claim for benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts, have been held to be suitable employment.30 (2) Where the said officer or appeal tribunal, as the case may be, is of opinion that an application ought to dealt with under this section as a case of special difficulty, the officer, or the tribunal, as the case may be, may make one or more of the following determinations, 35 that is to say: (a) that the whole or any part of the allowance granted be issued to such member of the applicants household as may be specified in the determination;40       (b) that the allowance granted be issued otherwise than in cash;(c) that the allowance be granted only upon con-dition that the applicant attends a work centre provided and maintained under this
Suspension from appli-cation of this Part of this Act.section, or, where arrangements in that behalf have been made with a public assistance au-thority, that he attends a work centre or similar place provided and maintained by that authority; 5(d) where arrangements in that behalf have been made with a public assistance authority, that the allowance be granted only upon condition that the applicant becomes an inmate of a workhouse and be payable only by way of 10 payments to the authority in pursuance of the arrangements and payments to a member of his household while he is such an inmate.(3) If an applicant is aggrieved by any such deter-mination as aforesaid made in his case by an officer 15 of the board he may, without leave, appeal to the appeal tribunal.(4) In the exercise of the functions of the Board under this Part of this Act, the Board may provide and maintain work centres for the purpose of affording 20 occupation suitable for applicants whose cases are dealt with under this section, and may make arrange-ments with any public assistance authority for the attendance of applicants whose cases are so dealt with at any work centre or similar place provided and 25 maintained by that authority.40. Upon any application for an allowance, if the officer of the Unemployment Assistance Board by whom the application is to be determined is satisfied that the applicant has persistently refused or neglected to main- 30 tain himself or his family or has persistently contravened conditions attached in accordance with determinations made under the last foregoing section, he may make a special report to the appeal tribunal, and the tribunal may direct that for such period as may be specified in 35 the directions no further application for an allowance made by the applicant shall be considered, and during any period so specified he shall, notwithstanding that the qualifications set out in section thirty-five of this Act are fulfilled in his case, be deemed not to be a person to whom this Part of this Act applies :Provided that (a) no such direction shall be given until an opportunity to be heard has been afforded to the applicant; and40Pakt II. -cont.
(b) if by reason of any such, direction an applicant becomes chargeable to any public assistance authority, that authority may apply to the appeal tribunal for the reconsideration of the case, and upon any such application the tribunal may revoke or vary the direction in such manner as the tribunal thinks proper.Part 11. cont.4-1. (1) An allowance granted under this Part of this Issue of Act shall, in accordance with rules made under this Part allowances.10 of this Act, be issued by officers of the Unemployment Assistance Board, or by arrangement with the Minister by his officers, or by arrangement with an educa-tion authority by. their officers, and, except where the Board with the approval of the Minister otherwise direct,15 at the local offices of the Ministry of Labour or, in the case of allowances issued by officers of education auth-orities, at the offices of the authority.(2) Section six of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1923 (which relates to arrangements with education20 authorities for administration of benefit) shall apply in relation to the issue of allowances under this Part of this Act in like manner as it applies in relation to the administration of benefit under the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933; and any scheme made or25 amended after the passing of this Act under that section and approved after the passing of this Act and any regulations made or amended under that section after the passing of this Act may make provision as to the administration of such allowances as well as to the30 administration of such benefit as aforesaid.42. (1) The Unemployment Assistance Board may Rules and make rules for carrying this Part of this Act into effect regulations, and in particular with respect to all matters with respect to which rules may be made under this Part 35 of this Act, and for prescribing anything which under this Part of this Act is to he prescribed, but no such rules shall have effect until confirmed by the Minister, and any such rules shall, when confirmed, be laid before Parliament.40 (2) The Board shall within four months from the passing of this Act and thereafter from time to time as occasion may require prepare and submit to the Minister draft regulations for the purpose of subsection (3) of
Part II.  cont.A.D. 1933. section thirty-seven of this Act, and the Minister shall consider any draft regulations so submitted to him and shall make draft regulations either in the form of the draft submitted to him or subject to such variations and amendments as he thinks fit : .5Provided that where the Minister makes any draft regulations otherwise than in the form of the draft submitted to him he shall, before making the draft regulations, inform the Board of the variations and amendments which he intends to make and the Board 10 shall report to him thereon and he shall consider their report.(3) Any draft regulations made by the Minister under this section shall be laid before Parliament as soon as may be after they are made, and, if the draft regula- IS tions so laid are made otherwise than in the form of the draft submitted to the Minister, there shall also be laid before Parliament a statement of the Minister&apos;s reasons for, and a copy of the report of the Board on, the variations and amendments made by him. 20(4) If each House resolves that draft regulations made by the Minister under this section be approved, the Minister shall make regulations in the terms of the draft to take effect on such date as may be specified in the regulations. 25Unemploy- 43. (1) There shall, in accordance with regulationsment Assis- made by the Treasury, be established a fund which tance Pund. snavj[ he called the Unemployment Assistance Pund and shall, subject to the provisions of those regulations, be under the control and management of the Unemployment 30 Assistance Board.(2) All sums received by the Board shall be paid into the fund, and all expenses of the Board (mcluding the amount of the allowances issued under this Part of this Act, but not including any salaries or allowances of 35 officers and servants of the Board or any remuneration, salaries or allowances of members, officers and servants of appeal tribunals) shall be defrayed out of the fund.Provided that the total sum paid out of the Pund in any year in respect of the expenses of the Board, other 40 than the aggregate amount of the allowances issued under
this Part of this Act, shall not exceed such sum as may A.D. 1933 on the application of the Board be determined by the        Minister with the consent of the Treasury. Pabt il- cont.(3) The regulations to be made by the Treasury as 5 aforesaid shall make provision with respect to the accounts which are to he kept by the Board, and in particular shall provide that on or before the thirtieth day of November in each year an account shall be prepared  and  transmitted  to   the   Comptroller  and10 Auditor General showing the sums paid into, and the sums issued out of, the fund in the year ending on the preceding tlhrty-first day of March; and the Comptroller and Auditor General shall before the end of January next following examine the account and make a report15 thereon and the account and report shall be laid before Parliament.44. (1) There shall be paid to the Unemployment Contribu-Assistance Board by the council of every county and tions ofcounty boroueh, an annual contribution towards the    X. nn j? ^i    V.      i authorities20 expenses of the -Board. to xjn.(2) The contributions to be paid by any such council employment as aforesaid in each of the five years in the period begin- Assistance ning on the first day of April, nineteen hundred and   un &quot; thirty-four, and ending on the thirty-first day of March, 25 nineteen hundred and thirty-nine, shall be tlrree-fifths of the sum of the two following amounts, that is to say (a) the estimated expenditure (excluding the cost of administration) incurred by the council in the year, ending on the thirty-first day of March,30 nineteen  hundred  and  thirty-three,  on  theprovision of relief which would not have been provided if this Part of this Act had then been in operation; and (&amp;) the difference between the estimated cost of35 administration incurred by the council in thesaid year in connection with the provision of relief and the estimated cost of administration which would have been so incurred but for the relief which would not have been provided if40 this Part of this Act had then been in operation :Provided that (i) such reduction shall be made in the amount of the contributions payable for the year
A.D. 1933. beginning on the first day of April, nineteen- hundred and thirty-four, as, having regard toPast IT. the date fixed for the appointed day, theconL Minister of Health may with the consent ofthe Treasury direct; 5(ii) in cases where the boundary of a council or county borough has (whether before or after the passing of this Act) been altered since the thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and thirty-two, such adjustment shall be 10 made in the amount of the contributions of that council as the Minister of Health may direct.(3) In this  section the  expression  &quot;estimated&quot; means, in relation to any expenditure of, or cost to, a 15 council, estimated by that council to the satisfaction of the Minister of Health in accordance with directions given by him.(4) The contributions to be paid by a council under this section in the years subsequent to the period 20 of five years mentioned in subsection (2) of this section shall be calculated in such manner as Parliament may determine.(5) The contributions payable under this section shall be paid in such instalments payable at such times 25 as the Treasury may direct, and shall be defrayed, in the case of the council of a county, as expenses for general county purposes, and, in the case of the council of a county borough, out of the general rate fund.Payment to 45. -(1) There shall in each year be paid to the 30 Treasury Treasury out of the Unemployment Assistance Fund at out- 01 un- sUch times and in such manner as the Treasury may Asastance1 direct, such amount as the Minister may estimate, in Fund of accordance with directions given by the Treasury, to be expenses of the amount of any expenses of any Government depart- 35 Government ment attributable to the carrying of this Part of this depart-        Act effect-ments.(2) In calculating the said expenses for the purposes of this section, there shall be included (a) such sum as, in the opinion of the Treasury, 40 approximately represents, the amount of the accruing liability in respect of any superannua-
Part II.-cont:&apos;tion allowances, lump sums or gratuities to A.D. 1933 which,   any   officers,   inspectors or servants employed  (whether by the Board or by a Government Department) for the purposes of 5 this Part of this Act, or the legal personalrepresentatives of any such persons, will become entitled under the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1919, in respect of that employment;(b) any capital expenditure inctirred for the purpose 10 of providing premises for the purposes of thisPart of this Act;(c) in respect of the use of any premises belongingto the Crown and used for the purposes of this Part of this Act in respect of which no rent is15 payable by the Board, an amount determinedby the Treasury, with the consent of the Minister, regard being had to the rental value of the premises and to any capital expenditure incurred as aforesaid which has been charged20    - to the Unemployment Assistance Pund :Provided that if, in any case where the amount of any such expenditure as is mentioned in paragraph (b) of this subsection has been charged to the Unemployment Assistance Pund, the premises in respect of which the25 expenditure was incurred are sold or cease to be used for the purposes of this Part of this Act, there shall be deducted from the amount thereafter chargeable to the said Fund under this section such sum as may be deter-mined by the Treasury, with the consent of the Minister,30 to represent the whole or the appropriate proportion of the then value of the premises.46. Inhere shall be paid in each year out of moneys Expendi-provided by Parliament  ture ou* or(a) the salaries and allowances of the officers and vided^y^0 35 servants of the Unemployment Assistance Board Parliament.and the remuneration salaries and allowances of the members, officers and servants of the appeal tribunals constituted under this Part of this Act;40 (b) such contributions to the Unemployment Assistance Fund as the Minister after consultation with the Board may, with the consent of the Treasury,
Penalty for fraudulently obtaining allowance and re-eovery of over-payments.determine to be necessary in order to enable the Fund to defray payments falling to be made i i    therefrom in that year ;(c) any superannuation allowances, lump sums and gratuities payable under the Superannuation Acts, 5 1834 to 1919, by virtue of the provisions of this Part of this Act ;(d) the expenses of any Government department attri-attributable to the carrying of this Part of this Act into effect. 1047. (1) Any person who, for the purpose of obtaining an allowance, either for himself or for any other person, knowingly makes any false statement or false represen-tation, shall be liable on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months.      15(2) If it is found at any time that an applicant for an allowance has, whether fraudulently or other-wise, procured by the non-disclosure or misrepresentation of a material fact any issue by way of an&quot; allowance to himself or any other person in excess of that 20 which would have been made but for the non-disclosure or misrepresentation, a sum equivalent to the excess shall be repaid by him to the Boasd and shall he recoverable by the Board from him summarily as a civil debt, and if, in or in connection with any 25 proceedings for the recovery thereof, any question arises as to the amount of any such excess, the question shall be referred in the prescribed manner to the appeal tribunal and a certificate signed by the clerk of that tribunal, setting forth the decision of the tribunal 30 upon the question, shall be conclusive evidence of the amount of the excess, and any certificate purporting to be signed by the clerk shall be deemed to be so signed unless the contrary is proved.(3) Proceedings under this section before a court 35 of summary jurisdiction may he instituted, prosecuted or conducted on behalf of the Board by any officer authorised in that behalf by a special or general direction of the Board, notwithstanding that he is not of counsel or a solicitor. 40(4) Notwithstanding any provision in any Act pre-scribing the period within which summary proceedings may be commenced, proceedings for an offence underPart II,  cont.
202530Part II.  cont.this section may be commenced at any time within A.D. 1933 three months from the date on which evidence, sufficient in the opinion of the Board to justify a prosecution for the offence, comes to the knowledge 5 of the Board or within twelve months after the commission of the offence, whichever period is the longer.For the purposes of this subsection a certificate signed by the secretary of the Board as to the date on 10 which such evidence as aforesaid came to the knowledge of the Board shall be conclusive evidence thereof.(5) Proceedings for the summary recovery as civil debts of sums due to the Board may, notwithstanding anything in any Act to the contrary, be brought at any 15 time within three years from the time when the matter complained of arose.Provisions as to allow-ance paid to persons en-titled to old age pen-3548. If it appears to the Minister of Health that any sums have been paid to any person by way of an allow-ance in respect of any period subsequent to the date on which an old age pension under the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Act, 1925, com-menced to accrue to that person, the Minister may direct sions. that the sums so paid shall be treated as advances made to that person on account of the old age pension, and accordingly in section twenty-three of the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Act, 1929 (which relates to sickness or other benefit paid to persons entitled to old age pensions), after the words &quot; the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1929,&quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; or by way of an allowance under the Unemployment Assistance Act, 1933,&quot; and after the words &quot; to the Unemployment Fund&quot; there were inserted the words &quot;or to the Unemployment Assistance Fund.&quot;49. Every public assistance authority shall permit Inspection any officer of the Board or any officer through whom the of docu-Board is for the time being acting to inspect and take ments-copies of any documents in the possession or power of the authority which he reasonably requires to inspect in connection with his duties,  and in like manner, the Board shall permit any officer of a public assistance authority to inspect and take copies of any documents
in the possession or power of the Board which he reasonably requires to inspect in connection with his duties.50. (1) Rules may be made by the Treasury after consultation with the Minister of Health with respect to 5 the superannuation rights of persons who, being officers or servants of local authorities with pensionable local authority service, become officers or servants of the Board and such rules may provide (a) that the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1919, 10 shall have effect in relation to such persons subject to modifications in respect of the mini-mum periods of established service which qualify persons for the benefits of those Acts;(6) that on the retirement of such persons from the 15 permanent Civil Service of the State in such circumstances that an annual superannuation or compensation or retiring allowance might be granted to them under the said Acts as modified by the rules, they shall be entitled in respect of 20 their local authority service to receive from the local authority from whose service they retired in order to become officers or servants of the Board such payments by way of annual allowance, lump sum or return of contributions 25 (with or without interest) as may be prescribed by the rules;and the rules may provide for such modifications of the enactments relating to the superannuation of officers and servants of local authorities as may be necessary 30 for giving effect to the rules.(2) In this section the expression &quot; pensionable local authority service &quot; in relation to an officer of a local authority means service which would be taken into account for the purpose of determining whether he would 35 be entitled to any, and if so, what, superannuation allowance on leaving the service of the authority.ol^nfcf1011 51.-(1) The enactments relating to the relief of mentsiC &quot;and Poor shall have effect subject to the provisions set saving.&apos;       out in the Seventh Schedule to this Act. 40Pabt II.  cont.Super-annuation rights of officers of local autbo-rities enter-ing the service of the CJnem-ployment Assistance Board.
(2) Save as in this Part of this Act expressly pro- A.D. 1933.vided, nothing therein shall affect any powers or duties contof any local authority in relation to medical needs or to   1 A1:l 1&apos;&apos;mental or bodily health or to education.5        52. (1) In this Part of this Act, unless the context Interpreta-otherwise requires, the following expressions have the ^on,^T meanings hereby respectively assigned to them, that is J^^^0&quot; to say :  tion of&quot; Appointed day &quot; means such day as His Majesty references. 10 may by Order in Council appoint:&quot; Chairman,&quot; in relation to an appeal tribunal, includes a deputy chairman :&quot; Dwelling-house &quot; includes any yard, garden, out-house and appurtenances belonging thereto :15 &quot;Education Authority&quot; means a local education authority for the purpose of higher education under the Education Act, 1921:&quot; Enactments relating to workmen&apos;s compensation &quot; means the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Acts, 1925 20 . to 1931, and the corresponding enactments inforce in Northern Ireland :&quot; Investments &quot; includes interests in land, except that, in relation to any dwelling-house, it does not include any interest which belongs to a 25 person who is residing therein :&quot; Local authority &quot; means any body having power to levy a rate or to issue a precept to a rating authority; and &quot; rate &quot; and &quot; rating authority &quot; have respectively the same meanings as in the 30 Rating and Valuation Act, 1925 :&quot;Medical needs&quot; means the need of medical or surgical assistance including any need of drugs, medical or surgical appliances or of nursing or similar services :35       &quot; Medical or surgical&quot; includes optical and dental: &quot; Minister &quot; means the Minister of Labour : &quot; The Unemployment Insurance Acts &quot; means the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933:&quot; Wounds or disability pension&quot; means any retired 40 pay or pension to which section sixteen of theFinance Act, 1919, applies. [170j D
A.D. 1933. (2) References in this Part of this Act to &quot; the       appeal tribunal&quot; shall, in relation to any application ^L^nf1&quot;   ^or an auowance, or for a decision that a person is a person to whom this Part of this Act applies, be con-strued as references to the appeal tribunal for the district 5 in which the application was made.(3) Any power conferred by this Part of this Act to provide training courses and work centres shall be construed as including power to acquire land, to con-struct buildings and to provide and maintain plant and 10 equipment for the purposes of such course or centre.(4) Any reference in this Part of this Act to any other enactment or to any provision of any other enact-ment shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be construed as a reference to that enactment or that pro- 15 vision, as the case may he, as amended by any subsequent enactment, including this Act.Application 53. This Part of this Act in its application to of Part II Scotland shall have effect subject to the following to Scotland, modifications:- &quot;      - 20(1) A reference to the Department of Health for Scotland shall be substituted for any reference in section thirty-five to the Minister of Health, and a reference to the Secretary of State shall be substituted for any reference in section 25 forty-four to the said Minister, and in section fifty the reference to the Minister of Health shall include a reference to the Secretary of State.(2) &quot;Public assistance authority&quot; means a local 30 authority which is charged with the adminis-tration of the relief of the poor, and &quot;work-house&quot; means poorhouse.(3) Section forty-four shall have effect as if a refer-ence to a large burgh within the meaning of 35 the Local Government (Scotland) Act, 1929, were substituted for any reference to a county borough, as if references to the fifteenth day of May were substituted for the references to the thirty-first day of March in paragraph (a) of, 40 or proviso (ii) to, subsection (2), and as if for
subsection (5) of the said section there were A.D. 1933.substituted the following subsections:  -Part II.&quot; (5) The contributions payable.under this    -r-cont. section shall  be paid in such instalments 5 payable at such times as the Treasury may direct, and shall be defrayed by the councils concerned in like manner as expenditure for the relief of the poor.(6) For the purposes of  this  section  a10 county  shall  include   any  burgh   situatetherein which is a small burgh within the meaning of the Local Government (Scotland) Act, 1929; and any reference to a county shall, in the case of the counties of Perth and15 Kinross and of the counties of Moray andNairn, be construed as a reference to the combined county of Perth and Kinross or to combined county of Moray and Nairn, as the case may be, and any reference to the council20 of a county shall be construed accordingly.&quot;(4) Subsections (3) and (5) of section forty-seven shall not apply.(5) In subsection (1) of section fifty-two the defini-tion   of   &quot;Education   authority&quot;   shall   be 25 omitted,   and   for   the   definition   of   localauthority   there   shall   be   substituted   the following definition : Local authority&apos; has the same mearring as    in   the  Local Authorities   Loans 30 (Scotland) Act, 1891.&quot;54. (1) This Part of this Act shall not extend to Extent and Northern Ireland. ParflT 0f(2) This Part of this Act, together with the Fifth,   *&quot;* Sixth  and Seventh Schedules to  this Act, may be 35 cited separately as the Unemployment Assistance Act, 1933.Part III. Supplementary. 55. (1) Notwithstanding the repeal by this Act of Transitory 40 any enactment as from the appointed day  provisions.(a) transitional payments in respect of days or periods of unemployment before the appointed
day may be made after the appointed day as if the said enactments had not been repealed;(6) paragraphs 1 to 3 of Article 8 of the Unemploy-ment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931, shall continue to have effect in 5 relation to the year ending on the thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and thirty-five;(c) references to benefit in the following enactments, that is to say, subsection (3) of section seventeen, subsection (1) of section twenty-eight, and the 10 proviso to paragraph (b) of subsection (1) of section forty-seven of the principal Act, sub-section (1) of section fourteen of the Unemploy-ment Insurance Act, 1922, subsection (1) of section nine of the Unemployment Insurance 15 Act, 1923, section seven of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924, subsection (1) of section nine of the Unemployment Insurance Act,  1927,  and section twenty-three of the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory 20 Pensions Act, 1929, shall be deemed to include references to transitional payments.(2) As from the commencement of Part I. of this Act, the reference in paragraph (2) of Article 1 of the said Order to persons who would but for the operation 25 of the precechng paragraph of that Article have been entitled to benefit shall be construed as. including a reference to persons who would have been entitled to benefit if they had not exhausted their benefit rights.(3) Subsection (3) of section five of the Unemploy- 30 ment Insurance Act,   1927,  and  the   definition  of &quot; benefit year&quot; in section sixteen of that Act shall, notwithstanding anything in this Act, continue to have effect in relation to transitional payments.(4) As from such day as the Minister may by order 35 direct (a) the functions of councils and county boroughs under the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931, shall be trans-ferred to the Unemployment Assistance Board, 40 and any question which before the said transfer would have been referred to and determinedPart III.  cont.
by any committee or sub-committee or officer of such, a council as if they were estimating the need of an unemployed able-bodied person who had applied for public assistance, shall be 5 referred to and determined by officers of theBoard in like manner and subject to the same regulations as applications for allowances under Part II of this Act are after the appointed day to be determined under section thirty-eight of 10 this Act by them, and any such determinationshall be subject to the like appeal as a determina-tion under that section;(b) the proviso to paragraph (3) and the proviso to paragraph (4) of Article 1 of the Unemployment 15 Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order,1931 (which restrict the amount of transitional payments to the amount of the benefit which the applicant might have received but for the provisions of the said Order) shall cease to have 20 effect;(c) a public assistance authority shall not orderoutdoor relief to be given to any person whose needs have been taken into account in a deter-mination for the time being in force as to whether 25 &quot; any and, if so, what transitional payments areto be given to any person.(5) In this section the expression &quot; the appointed day &quot; means the date appointed under Part II of this Act as the appointed day for the purposes of that Part.30 (6) Any increase attributable to the passing of this Act in the amounts which are, by virtue of paragraphs 1 and 2 of Article 8 of the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931, to be paid into the Unemployment Fund shall be defrayed out of moneys35 provided by Parliament.(7) Any reference in this section to any other enactment or to any provision of any other enactment shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be con-strued as a reference to that enactment or that provision, 40 as the case may be, as amended by any subsequent enactment, mcluding this Act.Part III.  cont.
AD. 1933. 5go (i) This Act maybe cited as the Unemploy-PaeTih.   ment act&apos; 1933-- cont. (2) The enactments set out in Part I of the EighthShort title Schedule to this Act are hereby repealed to the extent and repeals, specified in the third column of that Schedule as from the 5 commencement of Part I of this Act; and the enactments set out in Part II of the said Schedule are hereby repealed to the extent specified in the third column of that Schedule as from the date appointed under Part II of this Act as the appointed day for the purposes of 10 that Part.
SCHEDULES. a.d. 1933.FIRST SCHEDULE.Provisions as to the crediting oe contributions in respect oe persons continuing education.5 Part I.Making of Regulations.Provisions subject to which Regulations may be made.1. Subject as hereinafter provided, the regulations made under subsection  (3)  of section one of this Act shall not10 provide for persons who, after attaining the age at which under the law for the time being in force their parents cease to be under an obligation to cause them to receive efficient elementary instruction continue to receive whole-time education, being credited with contributions until they have so continued15 for a period of twelve months; and the number of contributions with which a person who has so continued for any period specified in the subjoined table may, under the regulations, be credited shall not exceed the maximum number specified in the said table as respects that period :20 Provided that for the purpose of avoiding anomalies, and, in particular, for the purpose of preventing inequalities between persons who attain the age at which the said obligation ceases during school holidays, the said regulations may make provision for any person being deemed for the purpose of computing the25 beginning of any such period as aforesaid to have attained that age on such date (not being more than three months before or after the date on which he in fact attains or has attained it) as may be prescribed by the regulations.Table.Period for which Education	Maximum Number of continued.	Contributions to be credited.Twelve months or more but not	Ten.exceeding eighteen months.	Eighteen months or more but	Fifteen.not  exceeding   twenty-four	months.	Twenty-four months or more -	Twenty.
AD 1933 Particular matters for Regulations.- 2. The power of making regulations under subsection (3) of1st Sch.    section one of this Act shall (without prejxidice to the generality cont.     thereof) extend in particular to the following matters (a) prescribing the types of education and classes of school g continuance at which shall be reckoned for the purposes of crediting contributions; (6) determining to what extent holidays or other periods of interruption shall be disregarded for the purpose of determining whether a person is continuing to receive 10 whole-time education;(c) prescribing the procedure as to claims in respect ofcontributions so to be credited, including the limitations of time within which such claims must be made;[d) requiring local education authorities, governing bodies, or 15other persons responsible for the management of schools, attendance at which may be reckoned for the purposes of credited contributions, to supply such particulars as to school attendances as may be prescribed.Part II, 20Reckoning oe Credited Contributions.1. For the purposes of determining whether the first statutory condition is fulfilled in the case of any insured contributor (a) any contributions with which he is credited under 25 regulations made under subsection (3) of-section one of this Act shall be deemed to have been - paid in respect of him at the rate of one contribution per week over a period ending with the week in which he ceased to receive whole-time education or in which 30 he attained the age of sixteen years Whichever is the earlier; and for the purposes of paragraph (i) of sub-section (2) of section five of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927, he- shall be deemed to have been , .    bona, fide employed during that period; and 35(6) if the number of contributions actually paid in respect of him before he ceased to receive whole-time education is in excess of the number with which he is so credited as aforesaid, any contributions so paid in respect of weeks before the - beginning of the said 40 period shall be taken into account in so far as they exceed the number credited; but except for the purpose of determining whether the number of con-tributions actually paid in respect of an insured contributor is so in excess as aforesaid no such con- 45 tributions paid in respect of the said period shall be taken into account.
2. For the purpose of  determining whether an insured A.D. 1933.contributor is qualified for additional days, or the maximum       -number of such days, no account shall be taken of credited 1st ScH-contributions. conLSECOND SCHEDULE.Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee,Part IConstitution and Proceedings oe Committee.1. The Committee shall consist of a chairman and not 10 less than three nor more than five other members who shall be appointed by the Minister and shall hold office for a period of five years and be eligible for reappointment from time to time on the expiration of their term of office.2. Of the said members, other than the chairman, there 15 shall be appointed, one after consultation with organisations representative of employers, one after consultation with organisa-tions representative of workers, and one after consultation with the Minister of Labour for Northern Ireland.3. If a member becomes, in the opinion of the Minister, 20 unfit to continue in office or incapable of performing his duties, the Minister shall forthwith declare his office to be vacant, and shall notify the fact in such manner as he thinks fit, and thereupon the office shall become vacant.4. The expenses of the Committee to such an amount as 25 may be approved by the Treasury (including the salaries and expenses of their staff and such salaries or other remuneration paid to all or any of the members as the Minister, with the consent of the Treasury, may determine) shall be paid by the Minister.30        5. The Committee may act notwithstanding any vacancy in their number.6. The Committee may make rules for regulating the pro-cedure (including the quorum) of the Committee.7. The Minister shall furnish the Committee with such 35 information as they may reasonably require for the proper dis-charge of their functions under this Act.
Part II.2nd Soh.  cont.Provisions oe Unemployment Insurance Acts oe which amendments may be recommended by Committee.Provisions of Act.Subject matter.     5Section seven of the principal Act; section five of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1923; subsection (4) of section one of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924, and such of the provisions of the Second Schedule to that Act as amend section seven of the principal Act or section five of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1923 ; section three of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1925; sections five and seven of the Unem-ployment Insurance Act, 1927; subsec-tion (2) of section four and section seven of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930, and such of the provisions of the Second Schedule to that Act as amend section five of the Unemployment In-surance Act, 1927; and sections five, six and seven of this Act.Section eight of the principal Act; section four of the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924, and such of the pro-visions of the Second Schedule to that Act as amend section eight of the prin-cipal Act; section six of the Unemploy -ment Insurance Act, 1927, and section eight and subsections (1) and (2) of section fourteen of this Act.Sections three and four of this Act  -Subsection (1) of section four of the Unem-ployment Insurance Act, 1927, and paragraph (a) of Article two of the Un-employment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 1) Order, 1931, and the Second Schedule to that Order.Statutory conditions for receipt of bene-fit and matters re-lating thereto.101520Disqualifications for 25 benefit.30Duration of benefit and definition of 35 &quot; benefit year.&quot;Rates of benefit.
Provisions of Acts.Subject matter.      A.D. 1933Section one of the Unemployment Insur-Act, 1922; section two of the Unemploy-ment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924; sub-5 section (2) of section four of the Un-employment Insurance Act, 1927; subsection (2) of section two of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930; such of the provisions of the Second10 Schedule to the Unemployment Insur-ance Act, 1930, as amend section one of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1922; paragraph (6) of Article two of the Unemployment    Insurance    (National15 Economy) (No. 1) Order, 1931, and sections nine and ten of this Act.Section forty-one of the principal Act; Part I of the First Schedule to the Unem-ployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924;20 section three of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1925, and such of the provisions of the Fourth Schedule to the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927, as amend Part I of the said First Schedule;25     and section twenty-six of this Act.Subsection (9) of section eight of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930.Paragraph (a) of subsection (1) of section four of the Unemployment Insurance 30 Act, 1925, and Article one of, and the First Schedule to, the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 1) Order, 1931, and subsection (2) of section one of this Act.Increase of benefit in respect of depend-ants.2nd Sou.  cont.Supplemental pro-visions relating to right to benefit.Payment of benefit pending appeals.Rates  of contribu-tions.35 Section one of the Unemployment Insur-   Provisions with res-ance (No. 3) Act, 1931. pect to benefit inthe case of special classes of persons.
A.IX 1933. THIRD SCHEDULE.Provisions as to publication oe draft Regulations and objections thereto.1. When any draft regulations are submitted by the Minister to the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee in pursu- 5 ance of this Act, the Committee shall publish, in such manner as they think best adapted for informing persons affected, notice of the fact and of the place where copies of the draft regulations may be obtained and of the time, which shall not be less than fourteen or more than twenty-eight days, within which any 10 objection made with respect to the draft regulations by or on behalf of persons affected, must be sent to them.2. Every objection shall be in writing and shall state the portions of the draft which are objected to, the specific grounds of objection,  and the omissions,  additions or modifications 15 asked for.3. The Committee shall consider any objection made by or on behalf of any person appearing to them to be affected which is sent to them within the required time.FOURTH SCHEDULE.20Minor Amendments.Enactments to be amended.The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.Section section 3Amendment.25After the word &quot; persons&quot; where that word first occurs there shall be inserted the words &quot; of either sex, whether British subjects or not, being persons.&quot;    30In paragraph (c) of subsection (1) for the words &quot; employment in which does not &quot; make him an employed person within &quot; the meaning of this Act&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; which is not 35 insurable employment.&apos;
Enactments to be amended.Amendment.The Unemployment Insurance    Act, 5     1920 continued.Section 3- cont.1015        Section 5202530354045Section 10Section 12In paragraph (d) of the said subsection (1) for the words &quot; make him an employed person within the meaning of this Act&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; he insurable employment &quot;At the end of subsection (1) there shall be inserted the words &quot; and while holding &quot; such a certificate shall not be entitled &quot; to benefit.&quot;For subsection (5) the following subsection shall be substituted : -&quot; (5) Contributions shall not be pay-able in respect of blind persons in receipt of pensions under the Old Age Pensions  Acts,   1908   to   1924,   as extended by section one of the Blind Persons Act, 1920.&quot; In subsection (7) after the words &quot; liable to be insured under this Act &quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; and in this Act references to the employer&apos;s contri-bution shall be construed as including a   contribution  payable  under  this subsection.&quot;In paragraph (6) of subsection (1) there shall be inserted after the words &quot;is or is not &quot; the words &quot; or was or was not,&quot; and after the word &quot; applies &quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; or applied.&quot; After paragraph (d) of subsection (1) there shall be inserted the following para-graph : -&quot; (e) whether a person was or was not employed in any excepted employ-ment during any period falling within the period of two years mentioned in the first statutory condition.&quot;The  following shall  be substituted for subsection (2) : &quot; (2) Unless the context otherwise requires, any reference in the Unem-ployment Insurance Acts to the umpire1 i4th Scb4 -cont.
A.D. 1933. Enactments to bs-  amended.                          Amendment.4th Sch. _ 1 -cont. The TJnemploymentInsurance     Act1920 continued. 5Section 12 cont. shall include a reference to a deputy-umpire and to a person appointed to act in the place of the umpire or any deputy umpire under regulations made in pursuance of paragraph (d) of sub- 10 section (1) of section thirty-five of this Act.&quot;The proviso to subsection  (3)  shall  be omitted and in lieu thereof there shall be inserted the following subsection:     15 &quot; (4) There shall in each year be paid to the  Treasury out  of   the unemployment fund such amount as the Minister may estimate in accord-ance with  directions  given by the 20 Treasury to be the amount of any expenses of any Government depart-ment  attributable   to  carrying  the Acts relating to unemployment insur-ance into effect: 25&quot; Provided that the sum so paid in any year shall not exceed one-eighth of the receipts paid into the unem-ployment fund on account of income, after deducting, so long as regulations 30 made under this Act provide for the payment of contributions by means of unemployment insurance stamps, any sums which have been refunded on account of any such stamps or on 35 account of contributions paid (whether by stamps or otherwise) in respect of a person under the erroneous belief that the contributions were payable in respect of him under the general 40 provisions of this Act.&quot;Section 17      -   In paragraph (a) of the proviso to sub-section (1) for the words &quot; payable under this Act &quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; for the time being payable.&quot;       45 For subsection (3) the following subsection shall be substituted: &quot; (3) Where any sum is paid to a person under an arrangement under this
Enactments to be amended.Amendment.The Unemployment Insurance     Act, 5     1920 cont.Section 17 cont.10Section 22 15       Section 3320253035Section 47Schedule I, Part I.- The Unemployment Insurance     Act, 1922. 40       Section 145section, so much thereof as represents the amount of benefit which but for the arrangement would have been payable to him, shall be deemed for the purpose of the Unemployment Insurance Acts to have been paid by way of benefit.&quot; In subsection (7) for the words &quot; under this section,&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; for an offence under this Act.&quot; For the words  &quot; the  Commissioners of Inland Revenue &quot; and &quot; the said Commis-sioners,&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; the Postmaster-General,&quot; and the words &quot; with the consent of the Postmaster-General &quot; shall cease to have effect.Eor paragraph (e) of subsection (1) there shall be substituted the following para-graph : &quot;(e) The   expression    &apos; insurance year&apos; means the period beginning on the twenty-seventh Monday in any calendar year and ending  on the Sunday preceding the twenty-seventh Monday in the next calendar year.&apos;&apos; In paragraph (c) for the words &quot; employ -&quot; ment under any local authority or other &quot; public authority &quot; there shall be sub-stituted the words &quot; employment in Great &quot; Britain under any public  or local &quot; authority.&quot;At the end of the proviso to subsection (1) the following words shall be inserted &quot; if &quot; the amount of the wage earned in the &quot; employment or, where there is also &quot; a payment for the performance of &quot; work, the aggregate amount of the &quot; wage so earned and the payment so &quot;made amounts to or exceeds the &quot; amount of the increase of benefit &quot; payable in respect of her.&quot;4th Sch.  cont.
Amendment.The  following subsection shall be sub-stituted for subsection (1): &quot; (1) In any case where an authority has granted outdoorrelief to or onaccount of, or the Unemployment Assistance 10 Board has under the Unemployment Assistance Act, 1933, granted an allow-ance to a person who was not in receipt of benefit, or was in receipt of less than the full amount of benefit to which he 15 was entitled (a) in excess of the amount which would have been granted if that person had been in receipt of benefit or had been in receipt of the full 20 amount of benefit to which he was entitled; or (6) in excess of the amount which would  have been granted if  an insured contributor had  been in 25 receipt of an increase of benefit in respect of that person;then, if a claim by that person for benefit, or for the full amount of benefit to which he was entitled, or a claim in 30 respect of that person for an increase of benefit, for any part of the period during which relief, or as the case may be an allowance has been so granted, is subse-quently allowed, the Minister may treat 35 the benefit allowed. to that person, or the increase of benefit allowed in respect of that person, as the case may be, as reduced by an amount not exceeding such an amount as the authority or, as 40 the case may be, the Board certify to have been so paid in excess for the period for which the benefit or increase of benefit was allowed, and may pay to the authority or, as the case may be, to 45 the Board the amount by which the benefit or increase of benefit is treated as having been reduced as aforesaid :4th Sch.  contThe Unemployment Insurance     Act, 1922-cont. Section 14
0Enactments to be amended.Amendment.The Unemployment Insurance     Act, 5     1922-cont.Section 14- cont.10 The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1923.Section 6 -152025The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) 30    Act, 1924.Section 1354045Section 6Provided that the total charge on the Unemployment Fund shall not be greater than the amount of the benefit or increase of benefit allowed.&quot;In subsection (1), after the words &quot; eighteen years&quot; there shall be in-serted the words &quot;or in connection &quot; with the administration of increase &quot; of benefit claimed in respect of per-&quot; sons between the ages of fourteen &quot; and sixteen years who are dependent &quot; children within the meaning of the .&quot; Unemployment Insurance Acts.&quot;In paragraph (6) of subsection (2), for the words &quot;a scale fixed&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; regulations made &quot;, and the words from &quot; Provided that&quot; to the end of the said subsec-tion (2) shall cease to have effect.A.D. 1933.4th Sch,  com.[170,In subsection (4) for the words &quot; within the meaning of this section&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; for the &quot; purpose of the Unemployment In-&quot; surance Acts.&quot;For the words from &quot; among the expenses &quot; to &quot; expenses therein mentioned,&quot; there shall  be  substituted  the  words   &quot; in &quot; estimating the expenses of Government &quot; Departments for the purposes of sub-&quot; section (4) of section twelve of the &quot; principal Act&quot;; and for the words from &quot; Provided that &quot; to the end of the section there shall be substituted the following words :  &quot;(c) in  respect  of the  use  of any premises belonging to the Crown and used for the purposes of the ActsE
Amendment.The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924- cont.Schedule I, Part I.relating to unemployment insurance in respect of which no rent is payable, an amount determined by the Treasury with the consent of the Minister, regard being had to the rental value of the premises and to any capital expendi-ture incurred as aforesaid which has been charged to the Unemployment Pund:1015Provided that if, in any case where the amount of any such expenditure as is mentioned in paragraph (6) of this section has been charged to the Un-employment Fund, the premises in respect of which the expenditure was 20 incurred are sold or have ceased to be used for the purposes of the Acts relating to unemployment insurance, there shall be deducted from the amount thereafter chargeable to the 25 Unemployment Pund under the said subsection (4) such sum as may be determined by the Treasury, with the consent of the Minister, to represent the whole or the appropriate propor- 30 tion of the then value of the premises.&quot;In paragraph 4 after the words &quot; statutory conditions&quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; (other than the first statutory condition),&quot; and after the word &quot; benefit&quot; 35 there shall be inserted the words &quot; or &quot; is not to be deemed for the purpose of &quot; the Unemployment Insurance Acts to &quot; be unemployed.&quot;In paragraph (5) for the words &quot; makes 40 application for benefit in the prescribed manner: &quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; proves in the prescribed manner that he is continuously unemployed;&quot;In the proviso to the said paragraph (5) for 45 the words &quot; the application &quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; such proof &quot;4th Sohj  cont.
Enactments to be amended.Amendment.The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) 5     Act, 1924- cont. Schedule I, Part I cont.101520 The Widows&apos;, Or-phans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Act, 1925.!25       Section 3930The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927.Section 135-JjoSection 5A.D. 1933.4th Sch.  cont.and for the words &quot; making the applica-tion&quot; there shall he substituted the words &quot; the making thereof.&quot; At the end of paragraph (5) the following paragraph shall be inserted: &quot;6. For the purpose of the second statutory condition, regulations may be made under section thirty-five of the principal Act for authorising some earlier date to be substituted for the date of the application for benefit in cases in which good cause is shown for delay in making the application.&quot;Subsection (1) shall cease to have effect in relation to blind persons in receipt of pensions under the Old Age Pensions Acts, 1908 to 1924, as extended by section one of the Blind Persons Act, 1920.After the word &quot;who&quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; has attained the age of sixteen years and &quot;In subsection (2) there shall be substituted for the words from the beginning of the subsection to the end of paragraph (i) the following words, that is to say : &quot; The following provisions shall have effect in relation to the first and third statutory conditions respectively  (i) in determining whether an in-sured contributor has proved that the first statutory condi-tion is fulfilled in his case, no
Amendment.The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927 cont.Section 5 cont.Section 12The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930.Section section 5Section 6 Section 7Section 13account shall be taken of any contributions paid in respect of him for any period during which h8 was not bona fide employed.&quot;For the words &quot; if the Minister thinks fit or any one of the parties so demands&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; if &quot; the Minister or the person holding the &quot; inquiry, as the case may be, thinks &quot; fit.&quot;15In paragraph (g) of subsection (2) the words from &quot; &apos; regular wage-earning employment&apos;&quot; to &quot;the expression&quot; shall cease to have effect; and for the words &quot; which is less in amount than the &quot; increase in the weekly rate of benefit &quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; if 25 the payment, or, where there is also a wage earned, the aggregate of the payment so made and of the wage so earned is less in amount than the increase in the weekly rate of benefit.&quot; 30The words from the beginning of the section to &quot; officers of employment exchanges &quot; shall cease to have effect.The words &quot; until the expiration of this Act &quot; shall cease to have effect. .For the words &quot; of the employments &quot; specified in Part II of the First &quot; Schedule to the principal Act&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; excepted employment.&quot;For the words &quot; the United Kingdom &quot; in the first, third and fourth places where they occur there shall be substituted the words &quot; Great Britain.&quot;4th Soh.  cont.
Enactments to be amended.The Unemployment Insurance    Act, 1930- conl. Section 1610Section 17 Section 2015The Unemployment Insurance-(No. 3) Act, 1931. Section 320Amendment.A.D. 1933.4th Sch.  cont.In subsection (3) the words &quot; until the expiration of this Act &quot; shall cease to have effect.The words &quot; until the expiration of this Act &quot; shall cease to have effect.In subsection (3) for the word &quot; shall &quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot; are hereby repealed,&quot; and the words from &quot; cease &quot; to the end of the subsection shall cease to have effect.At the end of the section there shall be inserted the words &quot; and, if the removal &quot; is from and to a place in the United &quot; Kingdom, for assisting towards their &quot; re-settlement.&quot;FIFTH  SCHEDULE.25   Constitution and Proceedings oe unemployment assistance Board.1. The Board shall be a body corporate by the name of the Unemployment Assistance Board with a Common Seal and power to hold land without a licence in mortmain, and shall 30 consist of a chairman, a deputy chairman, and not less than one nor more than four other members appointed by His Majesty by warrant under the Sign Manual.2. Every member of the Board shall hold and vacate office in accordance with the terms of his warrant of appointment.35        3. No member of the Board shall be capable of being elected to or of sitting in the House of Commons.4. Any person who has ceased to be a member of the Board shall be eligible for reappointment.5. There shall be paid to the several members of the Board 40 out of the Consolidated Fund or the growing produce thereof such salaries as may be determined by the Treasury at the time of their appointment  respectively,   so,  however, that the[170]        ^ E 3
aggregate amount of the salaries of the members of the Board shall not exceed the sum of twelve thousand pounds per annum.6. The procedure and quorum of the Board shall be such as the Board may from time to time determine.7. The Board shall appoint a secretary and may appoint such other officers and such servants, and there shall be paid to them such salaries and allowances, as the Board may after consultation with the Minister and with the consent of the Treasury determine.8. Every document purporting to be an order or other instrument issued by the Board and to be sealed with the seal of the Board or to be signed by the secretary of the Board or any person authorised to act in that behalf, shall be received in evidence and be deemed to be such an order or instrument without further proof, unless the contrary is shewn.SIXTH SCHEDULE.Constitution and Proceedings of Appeal Tribunals.1. Every appeal tribunal shall consist of a chairman and two other members. 2(12. Each of the said tribunals and the chairman thereof shall have jurisdiction in respect of such district as may be assigned to them by the Unemployment Assistance Board.3. The chairman of every appeal tribunal shall be appointed by the Minister, and of the two other members of an appeal 2ij tribunal, one shall be appointed by the Unemployment Assistance Board from a panel of persons nominated by the Minister to represent work-people, and the other shall be appointed by the Board to represent the Board; and rules made under Part II of this Act shall provide for the formation and periodical revision ;&apos;j of such panels as aforesaid, shall prescribe the manner in which the members of appeal tribunals are to be chosen therefrom and their tenure of office, and shall provide that during any unavoidable absence or incapacity of the chairman a person appointed by the Minister shall act as deputy chairman, and in 3f the case of any unavoidable absence or incapacity of any other member of an appeal tribunal, another person shall be chosen from the same panel to be a member of the tribunal in his stead.4. There shall be paid to the chairman or deputy chairman of an appeal tribunal such remuneration, and to any member 4j of an appeal tribunal such travelling and other allowances5th Schs  cont.
(including compensation for loss of remunerative time) as the A.D. 1933.Board may, after consultation with the Minister and with the       -consent of the Treasury, determine. 6th So.k&quot;5. The Board shall assign to every such tribunal a clerk 5 and such other officers and servants, and there shall be paid to them such salaries and allowances, as the Board may, after consultation with the Minister and with the  consent of the Treasury, determine.6. Rules may be made under Part II of this Act-10 (a) as to the procedure of appeal tribunals and the proce-dure in connection with appeals (whether to a tribunal or to the chairman thereof) and applications for leave to appeal, and as to the time within which such appeals and applications are to be made;15 (b) as to the procedure in connection with applicationsby public assistance authorities for the reconsideration of directions that for a period specified therein no further applications for an allowance made by an applicant shall be considered;20 (c) for enabling appeals and applications to be proceeded with in the absence of any member or members of the tribunal;and in any case where an appeal is proceeded with in accordance with rules made in accordance with sub-paragraph (6) of this 25 paragraph the tribunal shall, notwithstanding anything in this Act, be deemed to be properly constituted, and the chairman or deputy chairman shall, if the number of the members of the tribunal is an even number, have a second or casting vote.SEVENTH SCHEDULE.30     Modification of Enactments relating to the relief of the poor.Part I.PEOvisions applying to england.1. A public assistance authority shall not order outdoor relief 35 to be given (a) to any person who by a decision for the time being in force has been decided to be a person to whom Part II of this Act applies; or
(6) to any person whose needs have been taken into account in a determination for the time being in force under Part II of this Act; or(c) to any person in receipt of unemployment benefit, unless he is a person who by a decision for the time being in 5 force, has been decided not to be a person to whom Part II of this Act applies :Provided that (i) where a person to whom Part II of this Act applies has been granted an allowance subject to conditions 10 attached under paragraph (c) or paragraph (d) of subsection (2) of section thirty-nine of this Act and by reason of his non-compliance with the con-ditions the allowance is not issued, the foregoing provisions of this paragraph shaU, notwithstanding 15 the provisions of section eighteen of the Poor Law Act, 1930, be taken as only prohibiting the giving of outdoor relief to that person himself;(ii) this paragraph shall not apply to the granting of relief in respect of the medical needs of any person or affect 20 any powers or duties under section seventeen of the Poor Law Act, 1930 (which relates to relief in cases of sudden or urgent necessity).2. The Unemployment Assistance Board and any public assistance authority may make arrangements for the reception 25 into any workhouse maintained by the authority of any person to whom an allowance may be granted subject to a condition that he should become an inmate of a workhouse, and any such person shall, in accordance with such arrangements, be received into the workhouse and dealt with therein as if he had been 30 received therein under the enactments relating to the relief of the poor.3. The Unemployment Assistance Board shall pay to any public assistance authority (a) the cost of any outdoor relief (not being relief in respect 35 of medical needs) given to any person to whom Part II of this Act applies, being relief given pending the decision that he is such a person :(6) the cost of any relief under section seventeen of the poor Law Act, 1930 (not being relief in respect of 40 medical needs), given to a person to whom Part II of this Act applies except relief given during any period during which he has failed to comply with any condition attaching to the grant of an aUowance under para-graph (c) or paragraph (d) of subsection (1) of section 45 thirty-nine of this Act:7th Sch.  cont.
7th soh:  r-ont.(c) such sums, in respect of the attendance at any training  A.D. 1933.course or work centre or similar place maintained by the authority  of any person  attending thereat in pursuance of arrangements made under Part II of 5 this Act, as may be provided by the arrangements :(d) such sums, in respect of the maintenance in any work-house maintained by the authority of any person received into the workhouse in pursuance of arrange-ments  under  the last foregoing paragraph  of  this10 schedule, as may be provided by the arrangements :Provided that the amount payable by the Board in respect of any person under subparagraph (a) or subparagraph (6) of this paragraph shall not exceed the amount of the allowances which would have been granted to that person by the Board, 15 and any dispute between the Board and any authority as to the amount of the allowances which would have been granted as aforesaid shall be referred to the appeal tribunal, whose decision shall be final.Paet II.20 Provisions applying to Scotland.1. Outdoor relief shall not be afforded under the poor law (a) to any person who by a decision for the time being in force has been decided to be a person to whom Part II of this Act applies; or25 (b) to any person whose needs have been taken intoaccount in a determination for the time being in force under Part II of this Act; or(c) to any person in receipt of unemployment benefit, unless he is a person who by a decision for the time 30 being in force, has been decided not to be a person to whom Part II of this Act applies :Provided that (i) where a person to whom Part II of this Act applies has been granted an allowance subject to conditions35 attached under paragraph (c) or paragraph (d) of subsection (2) of section thirty-nine of this Act and by reason of his non-compliance with the con-ditions the allowance is not issued, the foregoing provisions of this paragraph shall operate to the40 effect only of prohibiting the affording of outdoorrelief to that person himself;(ii) nothing in this paragraph shall prohibit outdoor relief being afforded otherwise than in money to any person in a case of sudden or urgent necessity;
A.D. 1933. (iii) this paragraph shall not apply to the provision of medical relief.7th Soh.  cont.2. The Unemployment Assistance Board and any poor law authority may make arrangements for the reception into any poorhouse maintained by the authority of any person to whom 5 an allowance may be granted subject to a condition that he should become an inmate of a poorhouse, and any such person shall, in accordance with such arrangements, be received into the poorhouse and dealt with therein as if he had been received therein under the enactments relating to the relief of the poor.     103. The Unemployment Assistance Board shall pay to any poor law authority (a) the cost of any outdoor relief (not being medical relief) afforded to any person to whom Part II of this Act applies, being relief afforded pending the decision that 15 he is such a person;(6) the cost of any outdoor relief (not being medical relief) afforded otherwise than in money in a case of sudden or urgent necessity to a person to whom Part II of this Act applies, except relief afforded during any period 20 during which he has failed to comply with any condition attaching to the grant of an allowance under para-graph (c) or paragraph (d) of subsection (1) of section thirty-nine of this Act:(c) such sums, in respect of the attendance at any training 25 course or work centre maintained by the authority of any person attending thereat in pursuance of arrange-ments made under Part II of this Act, as may be pro-vided by the arrangements :id) such sums, in respect of the maintenance in any poor- 30 house maintained by the authority of any person received into the poorhouse in pursuance of arrange-ments under the last foregoing paragraph of this Part of this Schedule, as may be provided by the arrange-ments: 35Provided that the amount payable by the Board in respect of any person under subparagraph (a) or subparagraph (6) of this paragraph shall not exceed the amomit of the aUowances which would have been granted to that person by the Board, and any dispute between the Board and any authority as to the amount of 40 the allowances which would have been granted as aforesaid shall be referred to the appeal tribunal, whose decision shall be final.4. In this Part of this Schedule any refererfce to a poor law authority shall be construed as including a reference to a com-bination of such authorities. 45
EIGHTH SCHEDULE.Repeals. Part I.Enactments Repealed as from the commencement of Part I of this Act.Session and Chapter, or Year and Number of Order.Short Title.Extent of Repeal.10 &amp; 11 Geo. 5. 10    c. 30.15The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.202511 &amp; 12 Geo. 5. c. 15.30 12 &amp; 13 Geo. 5. o. 7.3513 &amp; 14 Geo. 5. c. 2.4014 &amp; 15 Geo. 5. c. 30.The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1921.The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1922.The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1923.The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924.Section four; in subsection (1) of section seven the words from &quot; provided that a person&quot; to the words &quot; good employers &quot;; in sub-section (2) of section eight the words from &quot; for a period &quot; to the end of the said subsection; section eleven; in subsection (3) of section twelve the words from &quot; Provided that&quot; to the end of the said subsection; sections fifteen and sixteen; section thirty; and in section thirty-three the words &quot; with &quot; the consent of the Post-&quot; master-General.&quot;Sections four and ten.Subsection (2) of section one; sections seven and eight; and in subsection (1) of sec-tion sixteen the definition of &quot; a dependent child &quot; and the definition of &quot; a child.&quot;Section four; in subsection (3) of section six the words from &quot; Provided that &quot; to the end of the said subsection; and subsection (2) of section nine.Subsection (5) of section one; in section three the words &quot; and (iv) &quot; and the words &quot; (iv) that he is genuinely &quot; seeking work but unable &quot; to obtain suitable employ -&quot; ment &quot; ; in subsection (2)
Session and Chapter, or Year and Number of Order.Short Title.14 &amp; 15 Geo. 5. c. 30.15 &amp; 16 Geo. 5. c. 69.17 &amp; 18 Geo. 5. c. 30.20 &amp; 21 Geo. 5. c. 16.The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924-cont.The   Unemployment Insurance Act, 1925.Extent of Repeal.The  Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927.The   Unemployment Insurance Act, 1930.of section seven the words &quot; a recommendation &quot; and 5 the words &quot; or recommenda-tion &quot; and the words from &quot; any question &quot; to the end of the section; and sections eleven and fifteen. 10In paragraph (a) of subsection (1) of section four the words from the beginning of the paragraph to &quot; the extended period,&quot; and all the words in 15 the said section four from the beginning of paragraph (c) of the said subsection (1) to the end of the said section four. 20Section three; paragraphs (6) and (c) of subsection (2) of section four; subsection (3) of section five; sections eight and thirteen; in sub- 25 section (1) of section sixteen the definitions of &quot;benefit year &quot; and &quot;benefit quarter,&quot; and paragraphs 2, 3, 4 and 5 of the Third Schedule.       30Section one; paragraphs (d) and (e) of subsection (2) of section two; subsection (1) of section four; in section five the words from the 35 beginning of the section to &quot; officers of employment ex-changes &quot;; in section six the words &quot; until the expiration of this Act &quot; ; sections 40 nine, fourteen and fifteen; in section seventeen the words &quot; until the expiration of this Act &quot;; section eigh-teen; in subsection (3) of 45 section twenty the words &quot; cease to have effect until the expiration of this Act,&quot; and subsection ^8) of the said section twenty. 508th Sch.  cont.
Session and Chapter, or Year and Number of Order.21 &amp; 22 Geo. 5. 5     c. 8.21 &amp; 22 Geo. 5. c. 25.Statutory Rules JO and Orders, 1931, No. 814.Statutory Rules and Orders, 1931,No.8531521 &amp; 22 Geo. 5. c. 36.202523 &amp; 24 Geo. 5. 30    c. 26.Short Title.Extent of Repeal.The   UnemploymentInsurance Act, 1931. The   UnemploymentInsurance   (No. 2)Act, 1931. The   Unemployment(National Economy)(No. 1) Order, 1931. The   UnemploymentInsurance (national economy) (No.   2)Order, 1931. The   UnemploymentInsurance  (No.  3)Act, 1931.The Unemployment Insurance (Expiring Enactments) Act, 1933.The whole Act.Sections one and three.In Article one the words &quot; until the expiration of the &quot; extended period.&quot;Subparagraph (6) of para-graph (1) of Article one and paragraph (4) of Article eight.In subsection (1) of section one the words &quot; after con-&quot; sultation with the Advi-&quot; sory Committee constitu-&quot; ted for the purposes of &quot; this section &quot;; in sub-section (2) of the said section one the words from &quot; Pro-vided that &quot; to the end of the said subsection, and subsection (6) of that sec-tion; section two; and sub-section (3) of section five.The whole Act.Part II.35 Enactments repealed as from the date appointed under Part II of this Act. as the appointed day for the purposes of that Part.4045Session and Chapter, or Year and Number of Order.	Short Title.	Extent of Repeal.17 &amp; 18 Geo. 5. c. 30. 19 &amp; 20 Geo. 5. c. 19.	The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927. The Unemployment Insurance (Transi-tional Provisions Amendment) Act, 1929.	Section fourteen; and hi sub-section (1) of section sixteen the definition of &quot; benefit year.&quot; The whole Act.Sth Soh.  cont.
Session and Chapter, or Year and Number ol Order.Short Title.Extent of Repeal.20 &amp; 21 Geo. 5.c. 16. 20 &amp; 21 Geo. 5.c. 25.StatutoryRules     and orders, 1931,No. 853. 22 &amp; 23 Geo. 5.c. 19.22 &amp; 23 Geo. 5. c. 54.The Unemployment Insurance Act,1930.The Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1931.The Unemployment Insurance (Na-tional Economy) (No. 2) Order, 1931.The Transitional Payments Prolon-gation (Unemployed Persons) Act, 1932.The Transitional Payments (Deter-mination of Need) Act, 1932.Section sixteen. Section two.The whole Order, except sub-paragraph (6) of paragraph 1 of Article one and para-graph (4) of Article eight.The whole Act.The whole Act.1015208th Soh.  cont.

U nemploymenTrAB   I L  LTo amend the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1933, and to make further provision for the training and assistance of persons who are capable of, and available for, work but have no work or only part-time or intermit-tent work; and for purposes connected with the matters aforesaid.Presented by Sir Henry Betterton,supported byThe Prime Minister, Mr. Chancellor of the Exchequer, Mr. Secretary Thomas, Secretary Sir Godfrey Collins, Sir Hilton Young, Mr. Elliot, Mr. Attorney General and Mr. Hudson.Ordered, by The House of Commons, to be Printed, 8 November 1933.LONDON:PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICETo be purchased directly from H.M. stationery office at the following addresses Adastral House, KIngsway, London, w.C. 2 120, George Street, Edinburgh 2; York Street, Manchester 1 1, St. Andrew^ Crescent, Cardiff; 16, Donegal! Square West, Belfast or through any BooltsellerPrinted by Eyre and Spottlswoode Limited East Harding Street, E.C. 4 Printers to the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty[Price Is. 3d. Net.][Bill 170]

</content>
</cab>
