<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/58/5 images: 38-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet, November, 1944:.lTOP secret the  circulation  of this   paper  has  been strictly   limited.     It   is   issued   for   the personal use of copy No.   36W.P. (44) 655   -16th November, 1944.WAR CABINETPRISONERS OF WAR CAPTURED IN WESTERN EUROPE SINGE6th JUNE, 1944MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR1. At the Meeting of the War Cabinet on 7th November, 1944 (W.M. (44)147th Conclusions, Minute 3), I was invited to submit a report showing how manyGerman prisoners of war had been brought to this country since 6th June, the totalnumber who were now in this country, and what further arrangements were proposedin this matter&quot;.2. The German prisoners of war brought to this country from Western Europesince 6th June, 1944, are 110,000 American-owned and t6o,ooo British-owned. Ofthese there now remain in this country 17,000 American-owned (of whom 4,000 arein hospital, 4,000 are awaiting shipment to the United States, and 9,000 are beingretained to work for the Americans), and 113,000 British-owned.3. By the use of tentage and by overcrowding covered accommodation up to50 per cent, above capacity, we have so far managed to accommodate the British-owned prisoners brought over. Indeed, we shall have on the present basis (even afterabandoning some particularly bad tentage for 6,000, enough room at the end of 1944to accommodate 15,000 more prisoners (captured since 28th October, 1944)/ whom we have undertaken to accept from 21 Army Group, and still show surplus accom-modation for 36,000. But the use of tentage in winter and overcrowding on the scaleadopted are contrary to the Geneva Convention, and may provoke German reprisals.If we revert to proper standards of accommodation, we have already 9,000 too many(or, with the 15,000 expected from 21 Army&apos; Group, a total of 24,000 too many at theend of 1944).4. It is clearly of importance that further large numbers of German prisoners ofwar should not be brought to this country. Accommodation which might otherwise have been converted for them cannot now be made available in view of our commitments to our Allies. We are now required to hold up to eight American divisions at one timetogether with numerous, non-divisional troops, all of whom we had hoped would be despatched direct from America to France. We have, moreover, a potential commitment to train 150,000 Dutch, Belgian and Polish troops in this country. And there will bea further call on our resources here to accommodate a large number of British formationsbrought back from Europe and the Mediterranean preparatory to being sent to theFar East.5. Accordingly, the following measures are being taken to increase the holding ofBritish-owned prisoners of war on the Continent and in North America:  (i) Europe. The French Provisional Government have agreed with S.H.A.E.F.to accept 50,000 prisoners, of which 25,000 would be the British share, assoon as administrative arrangements have been completed, which is unlikelybefore the middle of December. The Belgian and Dutch governments are also being approached by S.H.A.E.F., but owing to local unemploymentit is unlikely that they will require any prisoners for labour.21 Army Group have accommodation for 10,000 prisoners in transitand 50,000 in holding camps, but owing to the difficulties of accommodation and maintenance this figure cannot at present be exceeded.(ii) North America. The Chiefs of Staff Committee have been asked to approach the Combined Chiefs of Staff to agree to the transfer of 50,000 prisoners from the United Kingdom to the United States. The Dominions Office have asked the High Commissioner in Canada to enquire from the canadian government whether they could accommodate an additional 50,000 prisoners.Prisoners sent to North America could be shipped at the rate of 15,000per month, but an increase in this rate might well be necessary if largepockets were captured.
6. We cannot escape the fact that we have entered into an obligation to accept the custody of 50 per cent, of the total captures in Western Europe.It ^ill be seen that the permanent transfer of a large number of future captures tothis country would present a problem of considerable difficulty; in fact, in order to conform with the standards of the Geneva Convention under winter conditions, thenumbers already here should be reduced.I ask my colleagues to take note of the steps which have been taken to secure the accommodation of a considerable number in Europe and North America. I must warnthem that, if these steps should prove unfruitful, a very difficult situation will arise whichcan only be met by increased accommodation in 21 Army Group or the United kingdom or both: in either case additional man-power would be required to build the additional accommodation.    d for guards. .P. J. G.The War Office,ibth November, 1944.(R^.i/t88)   tic   tt/44   W.O.p.   19971



</content>
</cab>
