<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 34-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 :4Mni27Off, 5111,&apos;jr*i)l&apos;ii^&apos;*&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;SECRET.(THIS D0CUM3HT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAiK-IC MAJESTYGOVERHM  NT),A R   CABINET.MINISTRY OF HEALTH BILL AHD POOR LA1./ REFORM. (Note by the Minister of Reconstruction)At the Meeting of the Hone Affairs Committee on July 9th the question was raised as to the necessity of the declaration respecting the Health Services at present admin-istored by tho Poor Law Authorities.I circulate for the information of my colleagues a statement of the expressions of opinion on the subject which have been brought before me in the conduct of negotiations relating to the Bill,C, ADDISON.15-7-18.THE MINISTRY OF HEALTH AWD POOR LAW REFORM.The following expressions of working-class opinion may be referred to as indicating that the representatives of organised Labour regard the adoption by the Government of the principles of Poor Law Reform stated in the Report (Cel.8917) of the Local Government Committee published in January 1910 as a necessary condition of the establishment of a Ministry of Health.On the 11th October, 1917, the Prime Minister received a deputation, introduced by Mr * .J.K. Thomas, which advocated the establishment of a Ministry of Health,     The suggestion made by the Sub-Committee of the Reconstruction Committee on a ministry of Health in May, 1917, that the Poor Law Division of the Local Government Board might remain as it stood within the Ministry of Health, was mentioned to the deputation, and this part of the proceedings is reported in the Manchester Guardian of the 12th October 1917 as follows&quot;Mr. Lloyd George pointed^out that a suggestion had been put forward with reference to the Ministry of Health that by way of a provisional arrangement the Local Government Board should be divided into two branches, one health and the other non-health.     He asked the view of the deputation upon that. Mr. Thomas;   The Local Government Board is connectedwith pauperism, and, speaking for the insured members and also the trade unions, I can say we hate it. VJe are opposed to it, and we will not have it at any price at all.     (Applause.)
oMr. Lloyd Georgej   That is emphatic, and seems to. evoke the sympathy oi those present.     (Laughter)11.As a result of this deputation the Minister of Reconstruction was asked to enter into negotiations with those concerned in order to arrive, if possible, at a substantial moasure of agreement in regard to the terms of a Bill.     He held a conference on the 5th November with representatives of the Approved Societies and Insurance Committees which adminis-ter the National Health Insurance Acts, at which Mr. Thomas was present.     The relevant passage in the notes of the proceedings is as follows&quot;Tho conference then proceeded to discuss the future position of the public health functions which at present form part of the administration of the Poor Law.     Mr. Thomas said that those whom he represented felt that it was imperative to remove the existing anomalies which resulted from the existence of the Poor Lav; system of medical at tend-anoe side by side with the provision made under the National Insurance Acts, or by the public health authorities,The Minister pointed out that the question of the reform of the Poor Law system as a whole stood referred to Sir Donald Maclean&apos;s Committee, and that tho establishment of a Ministry of Health might bo seriously delayed if the Government were to attempt to reform the Poor Law simultaneously;-with the establishment *f the Ministry&quot;.Further conferences were held on various dates between November 1917 and March 1918.   &apos; The question of Poor La-;; Reform was throughout perhaps the most difficult of all the questions discussed.     Until the appearance of the Report of the Local Government Committee in January 1910 it appeared to be insoluble.     On tine Oth November the records show that&quot;Mr. Thomas strongly urged that the represcnta-tives of Health Insurance organizations would be unable to secure any public support for a Bill which gave tho administration of Health Insurance to a Department that was also etneerried with&apos;the adminis-tration of the Poor Law&quot;.It was impossible to move Mr. Thomas or his companions from this position, and tentative suggestions to the effect that the administration of the Poor Law might be conducted in a separate building or through a separate authority on the lines of a Poor Law Board met with small favour at the conferences.As soon as the Lical Government Committees Report appeared, Mr, Thomas and his companions laid it dtwn as an essential condition of their concurrence in a Ministry of Health Bill on the lines proposed that the Govemnent should undertake to give effect to the principles laid down in the Report, and to introduce legislation on those lines as soon as the Parliamentary   -Situation permitted. iIt was a matter of the greatest difficulty to induce Mr. Thomas and his companions to acquiesce in any words which thoy considered so indefinite as those which appear in para-graph I of the First Schedule to the Dill;   and both the Labour Party and members interested in Health Insurance are, certain to press when the Bill is introduced for a declaration of the Government^ Intentions on the lines indicated above.
The Local Government Committee&apos;s Report was published during the sittings of the Labour Party conference at Nottingham, and it was with that Report before them that the conference adopted a resolution in favour of the establishment of a Ministry of Health on the 25th January,     The following extracts from the resolution bear upon the present point:&quot;That this conference declares that the organisation and development of a unified Health Service for the whole community are questions of urgent importance, and that steps should be taken without delay to establish a Ministry of Health based upon Public Health Services, and entirely dissociated frcm any Pocr Lav/ taint&quot;.It further declares;&quot;that the Public Health Acts should be extended so as to include within their scope all those duties now so inadequately provided under the Poor Law, and all further services that are necessary to secure and maintain the health&apos; of the community&quot;.-On the 11th April, 1918, the Minister of Reconstruction received a joint deputation from the Labour Party, and from the Standing Joint Committee of Industrial ,/omen&apos;s Organisations, on the question of a Ministry of Health.     The memorandum sub-mitted by the deputation included the following paragraph;&quot;All medical and health work now dealt with under the Poor Law should be transferred to the Public Authority and in doing this it will be necessary to extend the Public Health Acts and to administer the whole of the services regarding hoalth under these and not under the Poor Law.171th regard to the Poor Law as a whole, It Is our strong conviction that nc satisfactory reform with regard to the health of the community can be made until all such questions are taken wholly out of the hands cf the Poor Law authorities&quot;.This point was dealt with at the deputation by Mr. P.W. Jowett, ! .?. and Mr. Sidney Webb, who laid stress upon the necessity of securing that if the work of the Local Government Board were taken over by the Ministry the transfer should be accom-panied by the abolition of the Poor La?,r.The draft Report on the general policy of the Labour Party on reconstruction issued under the title &quot;Labour and the New Sooial Order&quot; refers to &quot;the urgently called for Ministry of Health&quot; and contains the following statement in regard to thes    The organisations affiliated to the Standing Joint Committee are The Women&apos;s Trade Union League, The 17omen&apos;s Co-operative Guild, The Women !s Labour League, The national Federation of Women Workers, and The Railway Women&apos;a -Guild;
Poor Law in relation both to health, and unemployment;&quot;It is clear that, in the twentieth century, there must be no question of driving the Unemployed to any-thing so obsolete and discredited as either private charity, with its haphazard and ill-considered doles, or the Poor Law. with the futilities and barbarities of its &quot;Stone Yard&quot;, or its &quot;Able-bodied Test iVork-houso&quot;.     Only on the basis of a universal application of the Policy of the National Minimum, affording com-plete security against destitution, in sickness and health; in good times and bad alike, to every&apos;member of the community of whatever age or sex, can any worthy social order be built up&quot;.On the 14th June,. 1918, the Minister of Reconstruction received a deputation from the National Union of Women Workers of Great Britain and Ireland on the subject of the establishment of a Ministry cf Health;   end it was urged upon him by one of the speakers that the Ministry of Health should be formed without delay in the interests of the people;   that&apos;their one great dread was that they should ccme on to the *Poor Law or to the workhouse and that there should be no more Poor Law,This memorandum is limited to a statement of the more important expressions of opinion on this subject which have been brought to the notice of the Ministry of Reconstruction.   But in addition a number of resolutions have been received from Labour bodies in support of the adoption of the Report of the Local Government Committoe, and these resolutions have as a rule suggested that the abolition of the Poor Law and the establishment of a Ministry   of Health, are nece-ssarily connec-ted.

</content>
</cab>
