<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 68-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
u1    it5. DCCLl/iJNT 13 THK PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAMIC MAJESTY&apos;5 GQVER&amp;RCEHT) *WAR CABINET.T. 6124.H  -     RELEASE 6l? iffl BOM IN TKB YEARS 1895, 1896 AKD 1897. Resolution by the War priorities Committee.C/278.The Secretary,War Cabinet.With reference to the Report on the Release of Men born in the years 1895-1899 made by the. War priorities Committee (G.T. 4854) and considered by War Cabinet 451 (Minute 5) of tho 17th June, 1918, the Report cf the Permanent (Labour) sub-Committee on the necessity and practicability of excluding any particular occupation and as to the possibility of producing a measure of elasticity in the case of men born in the years 1897, 1896 and 1895 la attached herewith (W.P. 107) together with a Resolution, which in the light of the sub-Committee&apos;s Report, the War priorities Committee desire to submit for the early con-sideration of the War Cabinet.(Sgd.)   3?. BYRKE,Colonel.Secretsry/War priorities Committee.11, pall Mall, S.W, 1. 15th JUly, 1918.
ENCLOSURE ijj ; Resolution by the War Priorities Committee.&apos;,&apos;The War priorities Committee sitting as a Committee of Ministers, having considered the report of the Labour Sub-Committee on the Release of Men born in tho years 1895, 1896 and 1897, are of opinion that it is inpracticable, consistently with the maintenance of the essential outputofiminitions of war manufactured on tho present scale for our own Forces and those of our Allies., to make any clean cut applicable to tho men of these a^ta, or to&apos; lay down any principle upon which any modification of such a clean cut could be made operative. Thoy therefore approve the Report and instruct the Departments to proceed upon tho lines therein indicated.   Thoy at the same time desire to record their opinion that no clean out in these ; or any older a^cs in practicable, and that no further substan-tial numbers of men of these and older ages can be released&apos; on bloc from oascntial industries, except in the ordinary bourse of release by Departments, without seriously affecting the output oficoy industries.   They accordingly submit that if the War Cabinet decide that any further substantial releases are necessary other than in tht* ordinary cour3u of release by Departments the War Cabinet should state in what respect pro-grammes of production are ts; be curtailed, as it is not possible W fulfil the present programs of production and at tho same time release men on a large scale for the Army.The War -priorities Committee records further its view that the time has now arrived when the War Cabinet must review as a whole the national war effort a3 affecting man-power and munition programmes and including industrial and munitions assistance to our Allies.   Further, the Committee recommend that no noYr or extended programmes involving labour in buildings or production should be authorised by th* War Cabinet without a clear indication of a corresponding reduction elsewhere as there is no longer sufficient man-power to gr; round for all requirementsr
w,rp. 107report m pertotmt (labour)&apos; sub-^omiItSeT,\p On- the 14th.June the&apos;Committee of Ministers consideredI   &apos; a resolution of the Permanent (Labour) Sub-Committee dealing with 4864. the release of men borrt in the years 1895-1899 (W.J?.94&apos;) x and decided that a clean-cut of Grade 1 men! born in the years 1999-1S99 should be made immediately effective, a recommendation which ,   was acepted by the War Cabinet.   The Committee of Ministers further&apos; approved the principle of making the clean-cut effective in the case of Grade 1 men born in the years 1895-1897, but directed the Permanent Labour Sub-Committee to report as early as possible as to the practicability of excluding any particular occupations and as to the possibility of providing a measure of elasticity.The Sub-Committee have investigated the question in detail. They have had prepared for them by the Departments concerned a c&amp;ries of memoranda dealing with particular industries and occupa* tionsj/and they have referred a number of questions for special re-ports by technical representatives of the Admiralty, Ministry Of Munitions, and the Ministry of National aervictej whose reports on all points submitted to them have been practically unanimous.While it is too soon to form a complete estimate of the effect of the clean-cut of men born in the years 1898-1899, there is considerable evidence that1 thewithdrawal of all Grade 1 men of these ages has had an appreciable effect on certain classes of out-put .At the outset of their deliberations the Sub-Committee felt that they were bound by the policy of the Government to safe-guard the development of^shipbuilding,   With regard to Munitions the Sub-Committee were inevitably faced with the position that the ex-tent to which special treatment should be accorded to pivotal men in the munitions industries must depend upon the relative importance of men and munitions.   In the course of their deliberations the War Office representative reported that both the Army Council and the Supreme War Council considered it essential not only to maintain as far as possible the normal output of munitions but also to accelerale and increase the output.of certain special munitions, such as tanks, gun equipment and gas.   The Sub-Committee, has, therefore, assumed that it is their duty to make recommendations which will not only safeguard the shipbuilding programme, but will also enable the Ministry of Munitions to fulfil the requirements of the Military Authorities.The Sub-Committee attempted in the first instanoe to limit the exceptions: from the clean-cut to occupations which stood by themselves and did not&apos;overlap seriously with other occupations&quot;. It soon became clear however, that such a limitation, which would exclude many of the most skilled and vital occupations in engineer? ing would have a.disastrous effect upon production.   They next con* sidered the practicability of fixing a wider list of selected occupations, within which.Departments should have the power to continue protection to pivotal men.   The Sub-Committee assisted by, their technical advisers, drew up a list of,pcoupations.   They then had an exhaustive analysis prepared of a number of industries, in order to see whether it was possible to safeguard the essential&apos; output of those industries by limiting exemptions to the listed . occupations. It was found, as the result of this analysis, that there would still be a number of cases,, comparatively few in number, probably not more than 10 to 15 per cent, but ranging over a.&apos;-wide ;&apos; , field of occupation^ the exclusion of which from special consIdera-tion would have an adverse effect on output out of all proportion to
the numbers of men involved. The Subcommittee therefore came to the conclusion that it was impossible to draw up a limitod list of occupations for special treatment.The Sub-Committee also considered the possibility of call-ing up ,pivotal men for whom special treatment was required&apos; by age groups on successive dates, e.g,, men born in 1897 on 31st August, men born in 1696 on 2let October, men born in 1895 on tho 31st December.   They decided, however, that owing to the special considerations which must apply to different oases, it was im-possible to deal with the problem on these broad lines.The Sub-Committoe accordingly recommend that tho Admiralty and the Ministry of Itoitions should be empowered to deal with the cases in which application for retention of men born in the years 1895 - 1897 has been made in firms or establishments under their respective control on tho merits of each particular case. Thoy further recommend that if a Department considers either that there is a case of victimisation, or that the retention of a particular pivotal man, who has not previously bean specially applied for by his employer, is necessary to obtain essential output, the Department should, have the right to submit such oases for the consideration of the Permanent,Labour Sub-Committee. It is not anticipated that this will materially increase tho number of claims now undor consideration, and the Sub-Committee consider that this measure of elasticity&apos; should be provided.As the bub-Committee recommend that the special cases of men born in the years 1895 to 1897 should be dealt with on their merits, it is not possiblo to state exactly the effect upon recruiting; but the following figures contain the nearest estimate which the Sub-Committee are able to submit.   The Ministry of National Service estimates that tho. total number of Grade 1 men bom in the years 1895 to 1897 engaged on Admiralty or munitions work, including mon employed in Dockyards and Naval ostablish-ments, but excluding men engaged in occupations for which an age limit of 19 is fixed in tho Schedule of Occupations, amounts approximately to 36,000,    The Ministry of-Munitions have under consideration approximately 12,000 to 13,000 claims in respect of those three years,,   Tho Admiralty havo not been able to supply complete corresponding figures, as many of the relevant documents are under consideration in their local offices; but the Admiralty representative thinks it is roasonablo to assume that tho numbor of special applications will be approximately 8,000.Having regard to the fact that all Grade 1 men born in the years 1898 and 1899 have been taken and that tho Minister of National Service is asking the Admiralty and the Ministry of Mbnitions to release all Grade 1 youths as thoy attain military age, tho Sub-Committoe think it is probable that, if tho output asked for by the Naval and . ilitary Authorities is to be secured, protection will have to bo continued in a large proportion of ^hoseoases.(Signed). P.Lloyd Greene. (Chairman.) n Stephenson Kent. .11        David Shackloton.R.SwIiorn. Wo Tr Fur so. JMymovF. J.7;rotteslcy.Secretary.July, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
