<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 138-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Notes of a Moating held in Lord Curzon^s- Room at tho Privy Council Office on Monday, 15th July, 1913 at 4.30.p.m,...   PRESENT:-lord Curzon        (In tho Chair).Mr. Chamberlain. Mr. Balfour.Mr. Montagu. Maj.Gen.Slr G.M.W. MacdonoghLord Islington.. Lord Hardinge.Sir G. Car;.Colonel Leslie Wilson,     (Secretary).LORD CURZON explained that the meeting had been called in accordance with the wishes of the Prime Minister to deal with questions arising out of tho visits&quot; of Dr. Nair and Mr. Tilak to this country.THE SECRETARY 0.? STATE FOR INDIA said that Lord Lamington was asking a question in tho House of Lords on Thursday next. Mr. Tilak had been allowed to come to  England on certain conditions (War Cabinet 428, Minute 11) which ho had accepted but the situation was now complicated by the presence in this country of Dr. Nair.   Dr. Nair has come home for reasons of health receiving permission to do so from the Governor of Madras who had not consulted tho Vioeroy of India on the subject.   Dr. Nair had, while in India, said that if the Homo Rule delegation came homo, he would also go and answer&apos;eny speeches made by Mr. Tilak here.   Mr. Montagu said that he had obtained from Dr. Nair the same undertaking as regards making public speeches which had boon given by Mr. Tilak and now Lord Lamington. Lord Sydenham and others were asking that he should be relieved from that undertaking.   In fact, Lord Sydenham had suggested that Mr. Tilak should also be released from the restrictions he was now under as regards putlic speaking and that both should be treated alike.   Mr. Ma&amp;tegu^ expressed the opinion that both should be allowed to say what they liked, relying on them not to abuse the privilege, and gave three reasons for this proposal:-(a) That one of the reasons for restricting Mr. Tilak?s speech was that he would go to Ireland - but he could not go now as passports were required, and, as a matter of fact, Mr. Montagu was of opinion that Mr. filak^s present attitude towards the war would be one of urging its keen prosecution. :..(b) That, having published the Indian Report and invited criticism, it was difficult to   say that people coming to this country, who were interested in Indian affairs should not be allowed to oritioise.[THIS POOTOffiHI 13 IHB PBOPBRTY Off HIS BRIIAB3I0 MAJBSrlY&apos;3 SOVaSHMEM!)ItSECRET.Tr^*&quot; WAR   CABINET.O.T. 5144.&quot; VISIT TO THIS COUNTRY OF DRtf MIR AND MR. TILAK.
&apos;  , (o)   If Mr. Tilak was allowed to speak frwoy he would realise how little support there me in England for his Home Rule for India IdeaaLORD CUR2OT said that the two cases were very dissimilar;     on the one hand Dr. tfair was a respectable person, while Mr. Tilak had been in prison for seven years for publishing an article alleged to have caused bombs to be thrown, and was known as a dangerous conspirator and as a loader of a very violent Nationalist Home Rule and Anti*Government movement.     Lord Ourzon dealt with the history of tho decision to nut restrictions on Mr. Tilak pointing out that tho War Cabinet, after refusing leave to him to come to England, had only allowed him to do *&apos;o on condition of his not speaking in public,in order thai ho mi^ht tfive evidence in the libel action which ho was bring-ing against Sir Valentine Chirol.     He thought on the wlole that the restrictions, having been imposed,and accepted in both oae^s ou^ht, in both, to be maintained.LORD ISLINGTON urged that &apos;the restrictions might bo removed from, both without any appearance of inconsistency. It was undoubtedly sound to restrain Mr, Tilak when the report on Indian Reforms was unpublished, but it ^ould bo impossible to centihue restraining public criticism on this question.LORD HARDINGE said that ho could not imagine anything more dangerous than to let Mr, Tilak at large.     He was an extremist with un&apos;soun(jL ideas who would preach a very advanced doctrine.- ICR. CHAMBERLAIN was of opinion that if Mr. Tilak was not allowed to speak, Mr. Nair should not be - but pointed Out the difficulty which this course might lead to,&quot;namely that anyone coming from India mi^ht be stopped speaking.SIR GEORGE- CAVE said there was a great deal of difference between allowing Dr. Nair and Mr. Tilak to speak.     The latter had always preached sedition and promoted rebellion in India.   As Mr. Tilak was coining on certain conditions Sir G,Cave considered that he should be held to those conditions.SIR 0t.m.w.macd6nogh, representing the O.I.G.S. said that Sir Henry Wilson considered that to allow Hr.Tilak to speak would be only oausin? trouble and that he would incite to dissatisfaction all over the country.     Sir G. Macdortogh stated that, besides the seven years&apos; Imprisonment Mr. Tilak had undergone, he had been bound over in 1916* in one sum of 8-0,000 rupees and in two&apos;sureties of 10,000 rupees each to be of good behaviour for a year because of speeches of a&apos;Seditious character on Home Rule for India.the SECRETARY 03* st ati! ?0R FOREIGN-AFFAIRS said that his opinion was that we ought to say that this was not the time when wo could tolerate the speeches of a man with such a record as that which Mr. Tilak had.    At the same tine he thought that either both should be allowed to speak or neither.lord ISLINGTON said that -a difficult political situation would be &quot;created, as the Report on Indian Reforms could be discussed in both Houses of Parliament and on public platforms, but an embargo was&apos; to be placed on. Indians who were so personally interested in the question.
SIR G. CAVE said that he would-agree to Dr. Hair being allowed to apeak but not to Mr, Tilak.    He could under-&apos;, stand why restriotions should he imposed on rebels, but could not understand why they should be put on honest men.   It should, however, be made perfectly plain to Dr. $air that he must not attack Mr. Tilak. . ,MR. MOHTAGU said&apos;that he must protest&apos;1&apos;against Sir G. Cave^ statement..   Dr.. Nair1 s name was execrated by hundreds of thousands&apos; of Indians,&apos;THE COMMITTEE decided that &apos;:- &apos;&quot;The restrictions imposed on Dr. JSfair and Mr.. Tilak as regards; taking,part In&apos;propaganda Y/ork&apos;, of,.ar,y:kind&apos; should not be removed in either case.&quot; -LORD CURZON, offered,&apos; in view of the lack of unanimity . which existed among the members of the Committee, to call &apos;. another meeting before Thursday in order further to consider . the question should Mr. Montagu desire.     It was understood, however, that the Secretary of State for India did not think it worth while to&apos; resume the discussion and that Lord Islington&apos; should reply.in the sense approved by the majority.2 T3hitehall Gardens, S.W.1. 16th July, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
