<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 155-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
y&apos;s Government,) &apos;Politioal &quot;1&apos;irtelXigenoo&quot;Department,CONFIDENTIALForeign Office,July 17th, 1918.Sweden, /007.M E M 0 R&quot; A. N D U uonTHE POLITICAL SITUATIOII IK SV/EEDEN.The Stockholm correspondent of the &quot;Frankfurter Seitung&quot;, on the 27th June, writes;-f,0ne gets the decided impression that the position of the Liberal Social-Democratic Ministry is strengthened.     There&apos;werein the days of the Finnish Revolution when the neighbour State asked Sweden for help and the Government in Stockholm was not pre-pared to carry on an active policy, the waves of excitement ran high and a certain dissatisfaction is to-day still apparent in tho^e Swedish circles which were in favour of intervention.     If we examine why, despite this, the present Government not only did not fall but is at present safer in the saddle than at the begin-hingi we naturally find the answer, not in the good results of the Riksdag session, for they would not counterbalance the yielding-up nf proud natibnal dreams, - but in reasons which lie deeper and which are connected with other questions.     The one is the inner political situation, the other closely allied to it, the food &quot;vroblem-As regards domestic affairs, their marked feature in Sweden for the last two years is doubtless an ever-increasing growth of the Socialist movement.     The results of the last elections are the best proof of this.     Numbers tell their tale.     No one can deny that the Left Wing of the Swedish Left is growing rapidly andtiVAes when exactly the opposite seemed to be the case.     Especially
I Ithat its power in the country is rising.     The Liberlals be^-unifced with it and divided authority with Social Democracy, which, as re-gards voting,&apos; has taken from it so many seats.     It   is the spirit of self-preservation which leads the former to do this.     The Right has decided to remain in opposition and that the more because con-ditlons at the present moment render government by it impossible. The proof of this emerge^ clearly when Branting mobilised his working masses against Hammerskjtfld as &quot;HungerskjtJld&quot;,Here comes in the food question.    As is well-known, one of the principal arguments of the Left against the late government of the Right was that the latter, through its obstinacy, had rendered im-possible an understanding with England and America regarding i^oorts into Sweden.     This domestic result of England&apos;s blockade brought into power those parties who, from the beginning of the World War, have sympathised with the Entente.     Now, the anxiety of providing what is necessary for the country has been placed on their shoulders and there is no reason for astonishment when the Right feels no in-clination.to take the burden on itself again.As is well-known, an agreement has been reached in London be-tween the Eden Ministry,and the British Government.     The official Stockholm communique gives exact details about vhat Sweden has to do but as regards England the only prospect held forth is that the im -port of 200,000 tons of essential food will be facilitated.     The Entente does no$ show itself very accomodating to its political friends in Sweden.     The Entente does not consider this necessary .;. and believes that the fortunes of these parties depend on England. If they cannot arrange provision of food-stuffs, then their day is past.     Consequently,  &apos;   England can now take with both hands and give with the little finger only.     This impression is very ^uch i strengthened by what one hears to the effect that the agreement
-3-concluded in London contains, in addition to the conditions nub-lished, also secret ones in which Sweden promises   England no longer to exoort certain froods to fter^any.   For the present the conviction remains that at any rate the Bntente has done far better business than Sweden and the feeling that this is the case is evident also in the Liberal Swedish press&apos;.This is a remarkably frank and, on the whole - leaving out of account the last paragraph - correct appreciation of tho situation in Sweden, though naturally no allusion is made to the developments1in Finland, which have caused general dissatisfaction among the Con-servatives, and in justifying the Finnish policy of the SwedishGovernment, have contributed to strengthening its oosition.

</content>
</cab>
