<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 199-203</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;(this jxouis:tt is tii5, prgpitjy of HIS BlilTAIfNIC MAJESTY,&apos;1 S gov^ilffT;,!G.t.*5163,,1W ah -cab..! .11. ST.THE. FigSIOKT . SITUATION-IN. MACEDONIA.------ - r   -r-       i   &apos; . i     &quot;If  I   ii      mm   &apos;\    - -  -   j   i i     ......i   mi. iin.nu//HLriesurn6 of opinions given by General GuiIIaumat at Seventh s e atti bn ^./. Suprerne v/af.,: Council.(See also 1.0.72, G.T.5109, and Imperial War C abi net 25, Ki nut e 5).At the -present moment the situation inMaaedonia. appears excellent and the fears which were entertained at the end of last year as to the future of the ariiies in Salonika have altogether vanished.German troops, with the exception of some artillery a 5ialist Units have been withdrawn to strengthen the Ger:andspecialist Units have been withdrawn to strengthen the German forces on the Western Front and. one cannot consider the arrival of Bulgarian troops brought back from the Kouraanian Front as compensation for the withdrawal of the German troops.There can be no doubt as to of the Bulgarian army, thus leftthe bad state to itself.of the moralThe operations carried out to the y,:&apos;est of the Lakes, in conjunction with the Italians, against the Austrians have resulted in allaying any anxiety as to a possible offensive in Albania and as to the consequences which such an offensive would have for our naval forces at Corfu.Lastly, the Allied navies have taken precautions which appear amply sufficient to cope with the possibility of offensive action on the part of the Russian naval forces which have fallen into the hands of the Germans,The political situation in Greece, which it is always necessary to watch, has decidedly improved and, if the Greek mobilisation has not been carried out with any great rapidity, &apos; it has nevertheless not been attended with the set-backs which one might have expected.   The Greek army, considerably elated by the initial successes which it has obtained, constitutes at the moment a force from which one- can expect serious efforts, if one uses it soon and in circumstances suitable to its national character and organisation.   These same successes have encouraged the Serbian army, which seems likely torecover from the inertia which has marked not only for reasons of amour-propre, butit in the from fearpast, of seeingthe Greeks occupying, for themselves, territory yfhich it will subsequently be difficult to make them give up.   The arrival of Yugo-Slav reinforcements, and changes in the Serbian General Staff have considerably improved this army.   At the present moment the French and British armies are in a most excellent state both as regards moral   and materiel. Both these armies have diminished in numbers, the one as the result of operations, and the other as tho result of sending troops to reinforce the Front in France.   Both armies are, however, in good condition to carry out any mission whioh may be entrusted to them.The Italian Expeditionary Force is also in splendid condi-tion and the successes which the Arnry Corps of General Ferrero have just achieved in Albania proveb that the situation on this side is likewise favourable.In these circumstances one can hope for very considerable results from an offensive action by the ALlied armies in the East, provided that this action is as complete as possible.
Theso results might &quot;be almost decisive as far as concerns the situation in the Balkans, if the enemy can be kept by . our action on other Fronts from sending reinforcements to the Bulgarian army, which left to itself, has not sufficient strength to resist a well-conductcd offensive by the Allied troops.The ration strength of tho Allied troops may be estimated at about 600,000 men.   It would not appear that that of the Bulgarians can possibly be more than 400,000. Without entering into details one in ay state that approxi-mateiy the sme proportion exists between the fighting forces of the two sides.      Tilth this strength the Bulgarian army holds a front of 450 kilometres.      The importance of the defence of different parts of this front aaries widely, the importance of the East being quite different from that of the West,   In the Eastern sector the Bulgarian army is covering its own frontier and is holding this line at the moment with seven divisions in line.   On the Western side, on the contrary, although seven divisions are also in line here, the Bulgarian army is covering country which it has conquered from Serbia, country which Bulgaria cannot possibly hope to occupy permanently even under tho most favourable conditions in the eventual settlement.   It is evidently this consideration which, led the Germans to intersperse contingents of their troops among the Bulgarian troops fin this part of tho front.    These contingents have since been withdrawn.   Finally, the right of the Bulgarian army rests on the Austrian forces in Albania and any retirement on the part of the latter must in consequence threaten the Bulgarian right wing and would probably compel the withdrawal of part of the Bulgarian forces.it would appear thon that an attack in&apos;foroe on the Bulgarian centre in the district between Lakes Dfiiran and Veles, the principal effort being directed on the Vardar between the stations of Stroumitxa and Gradsko, would have the result of both menacing directly the Bulgarian frontier and making communications with the divisions more to the West very difficult.   The retreat of these latter divisions would soon become necessary, thus freeing the neighbourhood of the lakes and allowing the French troops in the Monastir district, as also eventually the Serbian army, to advance in the direction of Uskub and of Old Serbia.The front of attack under consideration is occupied at the present moment by five Bulgarian divisions.   Given the menace of an attack by the Greek army in the Struma region and also the possibility of an advance by the Italian troops in Albania and by our troops in the region of Monastir it would appear that the enemy would not be able to reinforce the five divisions in question by more than two or three others.   If these reinforcing divisions are taken from the right of the Bulgarian army, Serbia is left open;   if they are taken from the left, the attaok by the Greek army on the line-of the&apos; Struma is assured of success.      Without going into details one may tabulate as follows the possible distribution of forces(a) Attack on the Strums Front againBt Drama, Seres and Demir-Hissar, with a secondary attack concerted With the Fleet against Cavallaj-6 Greek divisions 2 French divisions.(b) principal attack on the line of the Vardar:-
2 British divisions2 Greek tt6 Serbian       tt2 French        *Italian Expeditionary Force,or, in other words, a total of about 12 divisions, allowing for the different strengths of the various contingents.(c)   There would remain to hold the quiet sectors and in general reserve2 British divisions 1 or 2 Greek divisions 3 or 4 French    &quot;It would appear that this total strength of forces would be sufficient for the operations in question.Operations on the Macedonian front must not be regarded in the same light as operations on the French Front.   The hostile troops are not organised to any great depth.   As the result of this, once the front line positions have been carried for which -first stage of the operations one must look mainly to the British French and Italian troops, the Greek and Serbian troopsmay be counted cn to cany out operations of a nature familiar to them in a much intersected country, favourable in consequence to that kind of mountain warfare which they have already several times conducted successfully.From that moment onwards the action of their Allies would mostly consist in assuring their supplies     This business will certainly be difficult, but in consequence of the numerous roads and railways constructed both by us and by the enemy, will be rendered infinitely easier than at the time of the Balkan &quot;War.The Staff of the Allied armies in the East has already commenced the study and preparations for such operations.   The result of this study will be communicated-to the Military Representatives of - the Powers, but even at the present moment one can state that it has been conclusively shown that these operations are not in any way impossible.Undoubtedly it would&apos; be desirable to have more artillery. It would not appear to be impossible, 3ince it is only a question of materiel, to send a hundred modern light field guns to Salonika, but even if it would be impossible to send this assistance, one might get over the lack of artillery by commenc-ing the two operations on the Struma and the Varder in succession and transferring the bulk of the artillery rapidly from one field of operations to the other.To sum up,, a successful offensive by the Allied armies . is quitei possible.    Uo increase is necessary in the number of troops on the spot.     There must be some increase of material, particularly of materials for the construction cf railways, in order to improve communications and spead up the supply cf munitions and food.   It woiud appear eminently desirable that the assistance of America should bo obtained for these purposes. The results of such a successful c fensive would be.to force the Bulgarians to evacuate the terriiuory conquered by them, both in Greece and in part of Old Serbia.   Following on this it
would bo possible for the Serbians to undertake ths reoon-quest of their country, not only by military action, but also by political action.   Theso possible results must undoubtedly be present to the minds of th.* Bulgarian Government, which must also realise that Bulgaria is at present menaced by invasion and that thie invasion can now at last take place under favourable circumstances.   The only way out of thie situation as far as Bulgaria is concerned would be if the Central Empires were in a position to send strong reinforcements.   This can of courses only take place if the situation in the other theatres of war is favourable to them.   In this case, an offensive by the armies in Salonika will at any rate have the result of diminishing the pressure on the other $rents.This offensive must obviously be prepared in such a fashion as to avoid failure, but in ;&apos;a.3fc the same way as on the other Fronts, success cannot be absolutely guaranteed any more than in any other enterprise of wara   One must therefore take into consideration the consequences which might result from an unforseen check.These consequences could not be very serious, bearing in mind the present state of the Bulgarian army.   We are not here speaking only of the condition of its morale, which might change from one day to the next for reasons difficult to foresee, but also of the undoubted war-weariness of this army, which has been in the field for six years on end and which is now tied up in trenches from which it has not moved and which it occupied, one must not forget, after a counter-offensive on our part, that is to say; as the result of a defeat.   One may safely say that it has neither the training nor the capacity for manoeuvring, necessary for a counter offensive 8- All information leads us to believe that the Bulgarian army has had no instruction in open warfare since the commencement of the campaign.   Prisoners taken in the action at Skra-di-Iegen belonged to Units which for the previous 15 months had remained, both officers and men, in the same positions and tho same dug-outs, without ever having been taken out of the line and put in reserve.   Experience on the Western Front makes ua understand how difficult it would be for troops in this condition to revert suddenly to open warfare.The situation is not at all tho same as far as the Allied armies are concerned, except possibly in the case of the Serbian army.   Here, however, efforts are being made at the present moment to remove this cause of inferiority. From all this we may assume that failure in the offensive would not endanger ,in any way the existing situation in Salonika, vhich would remain the same as at present.On the other hand, it is undoubtedly essential to enable both the Greek army and the Serbian army to commence operations aB soon as possible.Every army has its own qualities and defects.   Everyone who knows the Greek army is aware, that, while it is capable of carrying on an energetic offensive for some time, it has not the qualities neogssary for trench warfare of the kind which Wo have carried oh/jSerhap.- $tto long a period on the Western Front.   The remembrance of the useless and prolonged mobilisation ordered by King Constantino two years ago still haunts the memory of the Greek army and the Government of M. Yenezelos cannot continue a similar policy for long without sarious danger.   ?/heh we
o.  5  minduced him to consent to the mobilisation of tho Greek army,,we did so with a tacit understanding that it should be activoly employed.   It would be a great mistake to have agreed to the sacrifices which this mobilisation involves, if no advantage is to be obtained from it. In&quot; oonoJLusioia, it can be said that even all the considerations set forth above have less weight than one simple statement which ought to decide beyond everything else the necessity for an offensive in the East.   We have in the Balkans an army of 600,000 men anC we cannot employ this army in any other theatre of war.   Are we doing right, considering the situation as a whole, to leave this army inactive, seeing what very considerable sacrifices we have to moke for it? Ought we not, on the contrary, to employ it as soon as possible with a view to shortening tho duration of these sacrifices^(Sd.) GUILLAUMAT.ITOTE.The above is a resume of the opinions given atVersailles by General Guillaumat, formerly Commander inChief of the Allied Armies in the East. It has no official character.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., July 19th, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
