<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 238-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
eve-iThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government!32 187Printed for the War Cabinet.  July 1918.SECRET.uNAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION&quot;-No. 60.Week ended 13th July, 1918.NAVAL OPERATIONS.Minelaying operations have been carried out in the Heligoland Bight, in the North North Sea Sea, off the Belgian Coast, and in the northern approaches to the Dover Straits.The weather generally has been unfavourable for flying, but a number of patrols and reconnaissances have been carried out in various areas by R.A.F. machines employed on naval duty.Machines from Dunkirk have, in addition, carried out the following raidsApproximate weight ofDate. Objective. bombsdropped.Flanders Area.Results observed or Remarks.July. 7th &quot;8th-9th9th 13thOstend Docks Bruges Docks...Tons. 1Bruges   Docks,   Ostend   Docks,&quot;] Ostend-Bruges Canal&quot;,  La Bru- I     6^ geoise Works, Ghistelles and Maria [ Aelter Aerodromes       ......JBruges Docks............       ill-Bursts on shed near Bassin de Chasse. Bursts on docks and submarine shelter, and also on merchant ships.Bursts on Bruges Docks and on Maria Aelter Aerodrome.Bursts on railway sidings, on quay and on submarine shelters.Zeebrugge Mole Bruges Docks...1*Total weight13* TonsOne enemy machine was destroyed, and two of our machines escorting the bombing raid on 13th July collided over Zeebrugge and were lost.On 7th July our aircraft carried out an attack on Constantinople, half a ton of bombs Mediter-being dropped.   All our machines returned safely. ranean.On the 7th July the monitors &quot; Earl of Peterborough &quot; and &apos;: Sir Thomas Picton &quot; assisted an Italian force in bombarding enemy works at M^la, with successful results. In this operation British aircraft also co-operated, spotting for the monitors. Further, two machines from Taranto bombed the aerodrome at Tirana, and six from Otranto, working in pairs, attacked Kuchi Bridge on several occasions, the bridge being reported completely destroyed. One enemy machine was driven down and one of our machines was brought down, but was destroyed by the pilot, who, with the observer, was taken prisoner but afterwards rescued.On 9th July one of our Coastal Motor Boats was lost by fire whilst exercising at Casualties Spithead.   One of the crew was burnt severely, but the others escaped injury.ATTACK UPON ENEMY SUBMARINES.During the week under review it is estimated that from 16 to 21 large enemy sub- Submarines marines were operating, included in this number being three &quot; cruisers,&quot; one possibly of a operating, new type. Of the latter, one is homeward bound and the other two are operating on Atlantic routes while apparently on their way to American waters. Most of the remaining large boats have either been working between the south of Ireland and the north of Spain, or have been on passage, but the enemy recommenced operating on&apos;a small scale off the coasts of the Bay of Biscay.The only area in Home Waters where activity has been intense has been the Yorkshire coast.(C 1292)  Wt.50&apos; IIIS   H &amp;
Actions The following Table shows the number of actions between Allied craft and enemywith enemy submarines which are reported to have taken place in all waters during recent weeks, 1 &quot;m 1    &apos; and the nature of the craft which have been engaged ; and also the number of submarines which have been destroyed as the result of such actions : 	Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		June 22nd.		June 29th.		July 6th.		July 13th.	Nature of Craft, &amp;c.									Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.T.B.D. and T.B..........	7		2		5		4	A.P. Vessels     .........	8	 	7	 	3	 	6	Aircraft   ......      ......	3	 	5	 	6	 	6	 Sloops and Patrol Craft	5	1	7		7	 	5	 Merchant Vessels.........	1	 	3		3	 	1	 Special Service Vessels......	1	 	 	 	 	 	 	 Submarines      .........	1	 		 	3	_	1	 Mines     ............	1	1	 	1	 	 	1	 Total	27	2	21	1	27 1-		24	-&quot; Results &quot; indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.MERCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.Number The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all Merchantand ton-     Vessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action :-nage of all vessels sunk.Week Ended1918.				,						June 1st	12	59,425	3	2,172	3	24,969	11	6,059	29	92,625June 8th	8	27,389	&apos;3	3,497	13	43,033*	12*	8,878*	36*	82,797*June 15th	12	42,089	6	6,840	5	10,886	5	5,084	28	64,899June 22nd	2	11,169	2	2,090	2	8,624	4	2,759	10	24,642June 29th	12	60,396	2	1,371	3	9,166	2	311	19	71,244July 6th	6*	25,860*	4*	542*	3*	22,992*	8*	3,555*	21*	52,949*July 13th	5	23,837	1	339	8	24,261	11	3,684	25	52,121* Adjusted.The Table in Appendix i shows the numbers and tonnage of sailings and of losses by enemy action, and the percentage of losses to sailings of all merchant steamships, both British and Foreign, of over 500 tons gross register, and the Table in Appendix II is a summary of those percentages for recent weeks.The tonnage engaged, in Overseas trades which arrived at or left United Kingdom ports in the week under review shows a considerable increase, but the losses also were heavier, making the percentage of losses to sailings 1.23 as against 1.28 last week. In neither week were there any losses in Cross-Channel or Coasting trades, and the percentage, reckoning all United Kingdom trades together, is this week .48 as against .38 in the previous week.Areas The Table in Appendix iii is a comparative statement of all merchant vessels, Iin which    Foreign as well as British, sunk, damaged and unsuccessfully attacked in the last two vessels lost. weeks by enemy craft and by mine, classified according to areas.As regards Home Waters, there has again been considerable enemy activity in the i North Sea, but in the English Channel only one attack was made during the week. There iBritish Vessels.		Allied and Neutral Vessels.		Total.1,600 tons gross and over.	Under 1,600 tons gross.	1,600 tons gross and over.	Under 1,600 tons gross.	All sizes.No.    Tonnage.	No.   Tonnage.	No.   Tonnage.	No.    Tonnage.	No.  Tonnage.Losses of British and Foreign Steamships in Trades.
is, however, a large increase to record in the number of attacks in the Mediterranean winch has this week been the zone of greatest activity. All of the 11 attacks made upon Foreign vessels in this area were successful, but the one British vessel attacked, although damaged, was not sunk.The number of British arid Foreign Merchant Vessels sailing in organised Convoy Vessels which completed their voyages during last week, and the losses sustained whilst in such convoyed. Convoys, compared with corresponding figures for previous periods, are as follows : 	Weekly average		Weekly average		Week ended		Week ended		May, 1918.		June, 1918.		6th July, 1918.		13th July, 19.18.	Convoy.									No. of		No. of		No. of		No. of		ships	No.	ships	No.	ships	No.	ships	No.	convoyed.	lost,	convoyed.	lost.	convoyed.	lost.	convolved.	lost.Atlantic trades 								Homeward       ......	148	1.8	148	1	153	 	166	3Outward.........	134	.2	136	1	98	2	164	 Scandinavia-Methil	100	.6	103	.5	78	 	146	 French coal trade......	364	 	403	.75	411	--	402	1Mediterranean local	207	4.2	222	2.25	246	2	250	2Total   ...     ...     ...	953	6.8	1,012	5.5	986	4	1,128	6The losses in the Mediterranean were one in the Malta-Milo Convoy and one in the Bizerta-Malta Convoy.The number of ships which were convoyed during the week under review constitutes a record.The following statement shows the number and tonnage of British and Foreign Compara-Merchant Vessels sunk by enemy action in each month since the commencement of tive^ state-unrestricted submarine warfare : -	British Merchant		British Fishing		Merchant Vessels		Merchant Vessels		Total		Vessels.		Vessels.		of other Allies.		of Neutrals.		of all Vessels.	Month.											No.	Tonnage	No.	Tonnage,	Np.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1917.			i							February  ...	105	313,486	30	3,478	60  !	84,280	69	135,090	264	536,334March	126	352,309	43	3,586	62	81,151	92	165.225	323	602,271April	170	546,451	41	5,920	82	134,448	122	189,373	415	876,192May......	121	349,419	19	1,448	70	102,960	95	137,957	305	591,784June	122	417,925	21	1,342	79	126,17!	89	139,229	311	684,667July......	98	364,430	18	2,736	72	111,683	56	70,370	244	549,219August	91	329,810	5	242	63	128,489	34	53,018	193	511,559September...	78	196,212	7	245	64	119,086	18	29,941	167	345,484October	85	274,973	5 &apos;	227	53	127,932	30	54,432	173	457,564November ...	64	173,560	3	87	42	87,646	22	34,295	131	295,588December ...	85	253,087	.  5	413	46	86,981	37	54,047	173	394,5281918.										January	57	179,973	10	375	45	87,078	21	35,037	133	302,463February ...	69	226,896	12	686	27	54,904	19	36,374	127	318,860March	82	199,458	10	293	61	94,321	26	51,035	179	345,107April	67	211,165	3	241	30	50,715	13	11,361	113	273,482May......	58	187,555	16	507	33	80,826	18	20,101	125	288,986June	48	158,386	5	493	25	51,949 HHBH	23	38,202	101	249,030ment of monthly losses.As regards British vessels sunk, the June figures are the lowest recorded, both as regards number and tonnage, since the commencement of unrestricted submarine warfare; while as regards World&apos;s tonnage the figures are the lowest in number in any month since July, 1916, and in tonnage since September of that year.(C 1292) A 2
Daily ^ The following Table shows the daily average of World tonnage sunk by enemytonS0f actlon ana 0* British merchant tonnage sunk or damaged by enemy action, or attacked    escaped from attack, for each month since unrestricted submarine warfare commenced, standardized &quot;by taking 100 as the daily average for February, 1917, in each caseMonth.	World Tonnage.	British Tonnage.				Sunk.	Sunk.	Damaged.	Escaped.	Total Attacks.1917.					February      ......	100	100	100	100	100March	101.5	101.5	64.8	95.7	92.9April           ......	152.4	J62.7	70.7	147.3	140.9May            ......	100.1	100.7	44.8	122.3	98.7June            ......	119.7	124.4	99.4	174.0	138.0July .        ......	92.6	105.0	45.7	124.0	101.5August	86.7	95.0	27.7	84.8	79.5September     ......	60.5	58.4	70.7	53.3	58.7October        ......	77.5	79.2	40.5	39.9	58.1November     ......	51.8	51.7	62.3	45.9	51.5December......	66.8	72.9	56.5	&apos; 63.6	66.61918.					January       ......	51.2	51.9	45.4	48.1	49.4February      ......	59.7	72.4	72.4	43.1	61.7March          ......,	58.4	57.5	127.9	68.8	74.0April           ......	47.9	62.9	61.4	73.0	66.3May    .........	48.9	54.0	72.0	51.1	56.1June    .........	43.5	47.1	40.4	37.9	42.6It will be observed that the daily average, both of World tonnage and of British tonnage sunk during June is the lowest yet recorded, as also is the daily average of attacks British vessels during the month.uiDonenemy mines.Enemy The attached diagram shows for each fortnight of the present year the numbers ofminelaying  enemy mines which have been swept up, and also the greatest distance from Zeebrugge in 1918.     (on which port most of the enemy&apos;s minelaying submarines have been based) at which such mines were located.It will be seen that not only has the number of mines laid tended to decrease during the period, but that the tendency for them to be laid nearer and nearer to Zeebrugge is still more marked during the last three months. If the number of minelaying sub-marines available had remained constant, and it had been a definite policy on the part of the enemy to lay mines nearer to the Flanders bases, the number of mines laid should have increased owing to the greater number of trips that could have been made. It may therefore fairly be inferred that the reduction in enemy minelaying activity is principally due to a great diminution in the number of submarines which are available for minelaying, although it is doubtless also partly accounted for by the fact that the utility of Zeebrugge &apos; . as a base has been much restricted.Minelaying. So far as is known no enemy mines have been laid in Home Waters during the week under review, and only two enemy moored mines have been swept up, one of these being accounted for by British minesweepers off Cherbourg. This is the first week for over two years in which no minelaying activity on the part of the enemy has been observed. Fifteen months ago the daily average of enemy mines accounted for was equal to a complete U.C. boatfs cargo.
fro-rrj. zeebrug6e-artas.?oq     liverpool. clyde ^BELFAST.FALfOUTHplymouthPORTSMOUTH\HARWICH ^ UOWESTOFT.oocojamuaryfebrtjaryaprilmayjune
Week Ended.	- Number of Enemy Moored Mines Destroyed.	Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.June 1st        ......	34	Nil	Nil,,  8th       ......	48	Nil	1,, 15th       ......	18	1	Nil22nd      .......	34	1	Nil29th       ......	42	1	NilJuly 6th       ......	21	Nil	Nil13th       ......	2	Nil	NilAlthough no British vessel has this week been sunk by mine, H.M.S. &quot; Botha &quot; (Flotilla-leader) has sustained damage which, it is believed, was caused by a drifting mine.MOVEMENTS OF ENEMY SHIPS.During the week under review six enemy merchant ships arrived at and three sailed Merchant-from Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat.  No enemy ships have entered or left men. Rotterdam.FOREIGN NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. Russia.The local Soviet at Archangel is reported to be at present in a conciliatory mood, but plainly intimates its decision to be guided by Moscow alone, and Rear-Admiral Kemp is of opinion that the occupation of Archangel by the Allies will be opposed. The situation as regards food has become so acute that orders have been given to discharge s.s. &quot; Egba,&quot; whose cargo is to be handed over to the local co-operative society for distribution in Archangel.In the Murmansk district H.M.S. &quot; Attentive &quot; made a successful reconnaissance to Soroka on 7th July. The landing party was well received by the local inhabitants,, who reported that the Bolsheviks had retired in a southerly direction. The railway had been damaged both north and south of Soroka, but it was hoped to be able to repair the section between Soroka and Kem without great difficulty.The situation in Vladivostok is now satisfactory, the control of the town having been taken over by Allied landing parties.Russian small craft at Yeisk are still causing the enemy anxiety in the Sea of Azov.A French source reports that two Russian destroyers arrived at Sevastopol on 25th June. On 6th July the Turks occupied Tuapse, but no further news has been received of the destroyer &quot; Derski,&quot; which arrived there on 18th June from Novorossisk. The destroyer &quot; Kertch,&quot; however, has been sunk off Tuapse by her own crew.Portugal.The majority of the trawlers employed on the Portuguese Coastal Patrol have been withdrawn from service, in order that they may be utilized for adding to the food supply . of the country.Spain.An important decree has been recently promulgated, introducing extensive reforms into the Spanish Navy. The present establishment of officers of all ranks is much in excess of requirements, and measures are being taken to reduce it by granting higher pensions and a step in rank to officers who retire, and by limiting promotion to one-half of the vacancies caused by retirements. The age limit for compulsory retirement, however, still remains very high as compared with the British Navy.Japan.On 12th July the Japanese battleship &quot; Kawachi&quot; was destroyed as the result of an internal explosion, about 600 lives being lost.Naval Staff,mh July, 1918.[Appendices.The following Table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed and British vessels Casualties, sunk: by mine in Home Waters (including the Havre and Cherbourg areas) in recent weeks : 
APPENDIX I.Statement of Numbers and Tonnage of SAILINGS and LOSSES of British and Foreign Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons grossfor the Week ended j3th July, 1918.	Sailings.						Losses.						Percentage of Losses to Sailings.					United Kingdom Trade.	In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		. Total.		No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	i ! No. 1	Tons.	No.	Tons.Overseas	272 197*	968,569 635,956*	265 201*	953,873 764,083*	i ;   537 .   398*	1,922,442 1,400,039*	3 1*	6,220 6,533*	3 3*	17,473 11,385*	6. 4*	23,693 17,918*	1.10 .51*	.64 1.03*	1.13 1.49*	1.83 1.49*	1.12 1.01*	1.23 1.28*Cross-Channel   ...	398 439*	636,948 686,704*	381 467*	598,440 681,167*	779 906*	1,235,388 1,367,871*	 	- 										Coasting...	 	-	 		&apos; 1.007 1,101*	1,808,910 2,008,745*	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 Total of all United Kingdom Trades *	-		 	 	2,323 2,405*	4,966,740 4,776,655*	 	 	 	 	6 4.*	23,693 17,918*		 	 	 	.26 .17*	.48 .38*					Losses on other Trades					......	8 4*	23,989 29,214*			-	-							Total Losses for Week ...				*		14 8*	47,682 47,132*						* Previous week&apos;3 figures adjusted.
APPENDIX II.Statement showing, as regards British and Foreign Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross sailing to and from United Kingdom Ports, the percentage of tonnage sunk by enemy action to tonnage sailing during recent weeks.United Kingdom Trade.		Weekly Average in June.	Week ended 6th July.	Week ended 13th July. *	&quot;In   ...	1.02    &apos;	1.03f	.64Overseas     .........*	Out...	1.49	1.49	1.83	Total	1.27	1.281	1.23	&apos;In   ...	.19	 	 Cross-Channel       ...	Out ...	.61	 	 	^ Total	.39	 	 Coasting     .........	Total	.21		 Total of all United Kingdom Trades...		.66	.38f	.48t Adjusted.i.
APPENDIX III.Statement of the number of jBritislr. and Foreign Merchant Vessels sunk, damaged, or molested during weeks ended _6th and 13th July, 1918, according to Areas._		Sunk.						Damaged, but not Sunk.						Unsuccessfully attacked.						Attacks.	Area.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		Total.			Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended			6th July	13th July	6th July	13th -July	6th July	13th July.	6th July	13th July	6th July	13th July	6th July	13th July	6th July	13th July	6th July	13th July	6th July	13th * J nly	6th July	13th JulyArctic and White Sea	/British... \ Foreign																				Atlantic (Northern) ...	/British... \ Foreign	 	 	1 1	l	1 1	1 ,	 		 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	1 1	1Atlantic (Southern) ...	/British... \ Foreign	1 1	3	2	1	o 1	4 2	 	 	-	 	 	 	]	1	 	 	&apos; 1	1	3 2	5Bay of Biscay	/&quot;British... \ Foreign	 	 - -	 	 	 	 	-  	 		 .	 	 	1	 	 	 	1	 	1	 Gibraltar Azores	/British... \ Foreign	1	I	 	 	1	1	 	 	 	 		 	1	1	 	 	1	1	2	1 1South of Mogador	f British... \ Foreign	 	 																		North Sea    .........	F British... \ Foreign	1		L 6	2	2 6	2 2		 	1	 	1	 	1	2		 	1	2	3 7	4 2English Channel	/British... \ Foreign	1	-	 	 	1	 	o	 		-	3	 	2	1.	1	 	3	. 1	7	1Irish Sea and Bristol Channel	/British... \ Foreign	 	-    ;	 	 	 	-	-	-	-			2	 	 	 	--	 	 	 	2Mediterranean	/British... \ Foreign	2 2	V 3	1	8	o 3	11	1	X	 		1	1	 	- 	 	-  	 		3 3	1 11American Coast	/British... \ Foreign	 		-	   &apos;	-  	2	-	 	 	 	 	&quot;  	 	 	 	----	 	 	 	2Totals    ......	/British... \ Foreign	. 6 o o	5 8	4 8	1 11	10 1]	6 19	4	1	1	2	4 1	3	4 2	5	1	 	5 2	5	19 14	14 1!)
t ATA. Substitute for figures shown in ton for 31st May 1918.(Scandinavian)			8	23,489(Huclva/U.S.A.)	 	 	1	3,842(Medii./Nfdld.)	 	 	2	7,778(Medn./East) -	 	-	1	4,425;./JSTor\vay	 -	 	29	66,160cellaneons (e.g.,	2	8,304	51	227,172icrth cargoes).				o   AS 581J 2

</content>
</cab>
