<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/58/0 images: 349-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel Jones                                                                                     G.T. 5191                                                                                     This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.

AIR MINISTRY.

Report No.2.

FOR THE FORTNIGHT ENDING 15th JULY, 1918.


(For periods as shewn &quot;below)	:               ....							Theatre of V ar	France.	Italy	Sulonika.	Palestine.	Uosopotai-iia	5th Group Dunkirk	Independent Force.	Period of Returns	July 2nd - 15th	July lot-14th	June 24th to July 7ti	June 24th l   to July 7H	June 24th l   to July 7th	July 2nd-15th	July 2nd - 12th	T-i oNo. of IS.A. Brought do&quot;m No. of F..A., driven dovm out of control No. of hostile Kite Billoon:; destroyed No., of our ma&apos;ch i no s mi 3 s ing 1m o. of rounds fired -^t &amp;i ound t?;raets* No.  of Phute-gr?.phs taken4 \:eight of Bonbi dropped.	99	29	3 .	2	-	4	5		- .....  -..... 52	1	1			4			4						-	t-i V. , 00 *	38	3	1	1	-	-			378173	14350	9370	39050	bl5	-	8020		8409	1018	^98	631	44	-	81		220  tonu	l-  ton:?	11 tons	5^ ton:;	140 lbs.	31 -&amp; tons	17 tons	Ho.  of Btia--.cl.ron. in the Field	79 and 2	5	o	4 2/3rd	o	10		i	special duty Fitc.							
SUHKARY OP AlOT-SUBivIARINE OPERATIONS BY R.A.F. NAVAL CCHTHCTTS FOR THE FORTNIGHT EMDItfG JULY 15th 1918.B *HOME STATIONS.No. of Petrols................ 125VNo, of Escorts................ &apos;S75Submarines soon............4*. 11Submarines Bombed............. 8Possible Submarines Bombed.... 8Mines Sighted................. 5Mines Destroyed............... 1Combats....................... 1H.A. Shot down................ 13ritish Machines Sfeot Down 3(ii)    AIR SHIPS.No. erf Patrols................ 2574Ho. of Escorts................ 84Submarines Seen........... sSubmarines Bombed............. *Pos s ible Submarines&apos;........... .2Mines Sighted................ 9Mines Destroyed............... 9
C.

SUMMARY OF OPERATIONS BY THE INDEPENDENT FORCE, R.A.F. FOR THE PERIOD July 2nd - 12th, 1918.

1/2 July

Objectives. Boulay Aerodrome. Mannheim, Oppau Works Soda Fabrik &amp; Railway Line Thionville, Railway works. Treves, Railway Station. Coblenz, Railway sidings and sheds.

Results. All targets successfully attacked. One enemy machine shot down.

5th July

Objectives. Coblenz, Railway Station. Saarbrucken.

Results. At Coblenz observation was difficult owing to clouds. One enemy machine brought down in flames, another was driven down.

6th July

Objectives. Metz-Sablon, Railways.

Result. One enemy machine was driven down.

6/7 July

Objectives. Saarbrucken, Railway Station and Sidings. Metz-Sablon, Railways.

Results. Both targets successfully attacked.

7th July

Objectives. Kaiserslautern, Station and Factories.

Results. One enemy machine was shot down. Two of our machines are missing.

8th July

Objectives. Luxembourg, Railway Station, Workshops &amp; Sidings.

Results. Bursts were observed both in the station and the Workshops.

Objectives. Enemy Aerodrome.

Results. Bombs were observed to burst on the sheds and hangars.
8/9 JulyV11 July12 July12 July (day)Objectives,.   Aerodromes, trains and Soarchllglitg.Results,       All were attacked with good results, twohangars being reported as having been set on fire.Objective Results.Offenburg, Railway Sidings. Some good bursts were observed,Objective. Aerodromes. Results.Two fires broke out, rounds were fired from machine   guns at trains and searchlights.Objective.    Saarburg,- Railway Sidings,
8/9 Jity11 July12 July12 July (day)Objectives,.   Aerodromes, trains and Soarchllghtg.Results.       All were attacked with good results, twohangars &quot;being reported as having been set on fire.Objective     Offenburg, Railway Sidings * Results .       Some good bursts were observed.Objective.    Aerodromes *Results.       Two fires broke out, rounds were fired from machine   guns at trains and searchlights.Objective.    Saarburg,- Hallway Sidings.
D.

SUMMARY OF ENEMY ACTIVITY FOR THE PERIOD ENDING 16TH JULY, 1918.

1. WESTERN FRONT.

(a). Enemy&apos; Attitude.

In the Coastal Sector there has been a marked decrease in enemy aerial activity, which has remained very slight during the past fortnight. This decrease may possibly indicate a withdrawal of machines.

Over the remainder of the Battle Fronts Scout activity has been, on the whole, slight, except in the Sector, River Lys - La Bassoe Canal, where there was a slight increase North of the Canal during the past 7 days.

Reconnaiasance machines have displayed only normal activity, except in the Sector, Houlthurst Forest - River Lys, where there was an increase in the number of machines seen. In the Sector, River Scarpe - Albert, there was a tendency for 2-seater machines to carry out low flights over our trenches at dawn.

Bombing activity very slight by day, and then only ever front lines. Night bombing machines have shown only normal activity, which has been confined to forward areas, with the exception of raids over Hazebrouck, St. Omer, and Bruay - Bethune Areas.

(b). General Situation.

Apart from the general decrease in activity, which was most marked in the Coastal Sector, there is little change to report during the past fortnight. The weather during the last 7 days has been unfavourable, which may possibly account for the slight activity shown during this period. During the period July 1st - July 8th activity continued to be centred in the Morville Sector oin the north, and in the Albert - Somme Area in the south. During the period July 8th - 15th low flying was reported at dawn, and at dusk on portions of the front; this may be the result of our local operations.

Enemy appears to be concentrating machines, for work during bright intervals, in formations of about 15 machines.

(c). Distribution of German Bombing Forces on the Western Front. (Twin Engine and Giant Machines.)

There is further evidence that at least 1 Bombing Squadron the (5th) has been transferred from Tournal to Rheims (Champagne Area). This movement, however, requires definite confirmation before it can be accepted.

Recent photographs show that the Boulay Acrodrome, in Lorraine, is ocoupied by twin-engined machines; at the end of May, twin-engined machines began bombing opposite that front after a period of inactivity (since the departure of the 6th Bombing Squadron for the ? Battle Front at the end of March).

The eight known German Bombing Squadrons have all been identified on the front between the sea and Rheims during June and July, so that it appears probable that an additional bombing Squadron exists.


(a). German Units.1 Pursuit Plight has been  1 dontifled as having moved from Salonica to the Italian Front,(b). Austrian ,Units..The following Austrian Air Forces have boon identified on the Italian Front:-Reconnaissance Machines       492 Pursuit macflittos 208.Tofcal s    700an increase of 36 machines from tho date of the previous report.MESOPOTAMIA!! AJDD SALONIKA FRONTS. No change is reported.AGEAN AM) PALESTINE FRONTS.Reports received during the past fortnight point to an increase of hostile aerial activity on these Fronts.RUSSIAN FR0I*P ,&quot; &apos;   &apos;      11      1    1 &apos;   &apos; &quot; &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; X(a)   German Unitq^German Units have been identified  on this Front as under :-12 Reconnaissance Flights % 6 machines - 72 machines,Total   -&apos;72 machines.2.(d)     Losses in Gorman Machino3*Losses in Gorman Hachincs, according to reports from Prance, have been since 21st March 1918:-1256 machines destroyed, i 492 out of control.Total 2   1748 machinese
(k)   Austrian Units *The etrongth of the Austrian Air Forces on this Front n.rc as follows,:-11 Reconnaissance Companies   % 12 machines s 132 machines.Total s    132 machines.6,   GENERAL INTELLIGENCE *Now Typo of Seaplane.Reports have boon received of a now type of enemy aeroplane, that is a monoplane seaplane fitted with a large 6-cylinder engine, probably a 220 &apos;h.p* Bcnz or Mercedes *   It is armed with one, or possibly two, guns, firing forward * and with a Parabcllum gun fitted aft.Tho speed is about 105 miles por hour.
E r U I P ii E H T,3I KEEK SiTCto 13TK JULY, 19X8-,      : -OUTPUT OF AEROPL/HES., SEAPLn^S, AilD ENQIK3S.- I ! !PARTICULARS SOURCB     AEROPLANES [   SS/PL/.NJ2&amp; .KITGI1TJ3S.1&apos;...............f*............&quot;--(;iutput for W.E.13/7/18. British j     542     :       24 422  .,&apos;French  j       - - 90 &quot;4m FrancoAmerican!      -      , 2 200. Jin morioni j      542     .       26 712   jtotal output for.28    British       16,214 &quot;     679 jXI,167, !ooks ending X3/7/X0   Othera 80 j     &apos; 53 j 5,642  j5 . &apos; &apos; I16,302   !     732 &apos;16,809-j-.-L-;vcragc Weekly Output  British        579   :      24 1     399  &apos;or 28 weeke ending     Others  ! 3   ! -     2 j     201  jU &apos;&apos;7 &quot;18 j_; , .,_. j j582 26 ;    600    !I-u--f.--otal output during    British i   13,554      86T !  11,5361917. Others    !       958   &apos;  113 -   .4,082 &apos;;  14,512   : Q80 1 15*618.......r   - Iir,f ..... ,.t-..-,,......-.rn........,.   jvorngo Weekly Output British i       261 ;    17 222:during 1917. Othere    i        19   ,     &amp; 78 ii i .280   I    19 I       300 I[    ,     : j        IThe oquipmcnt of the following squadron has been completed..108 Squr.dron*11 &quot;. ...     &apos; 1
MACHINES DESPATCHED TO WITS DUiUHG THE FORTNIGHT ENDIKG 15TH JULY.   191S.Home Units 4953,F- 2Weist Wing 34Independent farce 3Italy MEastern Stations 34Mediterranean 36 Grand Fleet andN. Patrols. 33Sundry Foreign Units -TOTAL   s      1,0142 (a)   AIRCRAFT OF VARIOUS  TYPES! RECONSTRUCTED AT REPAIR DEPOTSl Total of aircraft re-constructod at Repair Depots *  232 (TO   AERO.. BHQIMES OF VARIOUS TYPES REPAIRED AT REPAIR-DEPOTS. Total of engineb re-cor.3 true ted at Repair Depots *  29G-
1.    ENGINES.Trails with the Dragonf ly and Liberty engines are being continued and nc serious troubles have arisen.Work cn the first Tiger and Ccn&amp;ar engines is being pushed forward.   The Condor should be running about the beginning cf August, nut a two-cylinder unit is already running and is giving satisfaction..  These two 600 H.P. engines form a very inportant class for the future.Troubles with the Arab ongine are still engaging attention.  It io cne cf the peculiar features cf this engine that these troubles have only now arisen when the engine is in production, and did not make themselves folt whilo tho engine was in the experimental stage.2.    AEROPLANES. .....*****......i&apos; &quot;jp&quot;The second V type Handloy Page machine ia F^tsreeeingl well &quot;and it io anticipated that it will be completed in about a week.Bfcher&apos; large bombcr-s are alsc well forward, particularly the 4-engined Bristol  bembor and the 6-enginoi Tarrant.Ccn3idorable trouble has been experienced with tho Arab engines in the Bristol Fighter machines and a new design r  reinforced engine mounting has beon g^*otct with a vlow ta eliminating trouble j this fe now undor test.Arrangements arc being made to Install the B.K.P. in tho D.H.10. and the necessary drawings are being pushed forward rapidly.The drawings for the installation of the B.H.P. in the Viekera Vimy will be finished this wook.Satisfactory experiments Have been carried out to determine the best methods cf pressing cut engine cowls for machines so as to dispense with skilled labour.  This should effect a very large saving.The. designs for self-sealing tanks are practioally complete for all fighting machines te which they will be fitted.  These tanks give almost a oomplete immunity from fire due to Incendiary bullets,Tho final details in the design of the Salamander Trench Fighter machine are now satisfactory and the machine is being put into production.A great deal of work on metal construction has been done.   The first complete metal construction Avro wing has been sent to the R.A.E. for test.   Several other designs are also On the point of completion and will be tested shortly.TECHNICAL DEPARTMENT.
A conference was held yesterday, 16th July, at which 47 representatives of the various firms interested in metal construction were present, a great deal of information was exchanged and suggested designs for the V Ty e Handley Page spars, struts and longerons were put forward.    The progress of this work is most satisfactory and all the firms concerned are extremely enthusiastic^ It was also decided that metal construction for the present on the Handley Page was to he limited to the above mentioned&quot; parts.3.    3BXP3RI&amp;3HTAL.A navigation flight has been made from Orfordness to Chester over thick clouds, wind being taken, at the commencement of the flight by A.A. bursts. 2 machines left Orfordness following one another at  half-hour intervals.  Chester was made within 10 miles by both machines.  A full report is not yet to hand.

</content>
</cab>
