<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/48/11 images: 94-105</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYJS GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.....dlJs&amp;r..:.....sJSS&amp;attiifc^TOP SECRET Copy No........FOREIGN AFFAIRSPoland.(previous reference:W.M.(4*0 146thConclusions,Minute 5)WfM.(44) 157th conclusions confidential Annex(27th november, 1944 - 5.30 p.m.)The War Cabinet had a general discussion on Foreign Affairs.    The first subject dealt withwas the Polish situation.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs informed the War Cabinet of the latest developmentsarising out of the resignation&apos;of.M. Mikolajczyk.M. Romer had decided to resign-with.,M. Mikolajczyk, who had explained to the foreign secretary that he found it impossible to carry on,because most of his colleagues did hot believe in Russian good faith or that, in those circumstances, negotiations with.Russia would beof any value.    He had taken the line with themthat it was still his duty to try for an accommodation with Russia, and that unless he hadthe authority of his Government to do so, knowingas he did that he would have the full support and goodwill of the United Kingdom and the UnitedStates, he could not continue in office. The necessary-support from hie own people had, however, not beenforthcoming and lie had felt that he had no option but to resign.     He was, however, remaining in officeuntil a new government had been formedtM. Mikolajczyk had been somewhat criticalin conversation of the attitude of the Presidentof Poland who had not, he felt, given him the full support to which he was entitled.    Under an engage-ment which the President had contracted to the lateGeneral Sikbrski, he was bound to consult thecountry through the Underground Movement in Polandbefore appointing a new Prime Minister.    this he had not done before sending for M. Kwapinski.M. Mikolajczyk did.not at this stage knowwhether M. Kwapinski would be able to form agovernment or not, or whether M. Stancwyzk wouldbe prepared to serve under .him, though strong pressure,would certainly be put on him to do soin the interests of unity.   When asked whether,if M. Kwapinski failed to form a government, he waiS&apos;himself likely to be sent for, and whether hisposition would not then be greatly strengthened by-what had happened, M. Mikolajczyk had expresseddoubt as to whether he could accept power in all thecircumstances from the present President, andwhether the Russians would be prepared to negotiate with him if he were invited to accept office bythe present President. It remained, to be seen howmatters would work out.THE SECRETARY OF ST..TE FOR FOREIGN affairs had informed M. Mikolapczyk that if-M. Kwapinskishould succeed in forming a government, the relations

of His Majesty1s Government with him would not be thesame relations of intimate collaboration as they had&apos; been with M. Mikolajczyk.      M. Kwapinski would not be ableto look for&apos; our support to the same extent and that wouldbe made clear to him. He felt himself grave doubt as to theeffect on the Polish situation of a government underM. Kwapinski&apos;s leadership.     The position was complicated by the very large numbers of Poles who had been liberatedor were awaiting liberation in vi/estern Germany, and bythe substantial military force which was already fighting on the side of the Allies in Western Europe and whichwas likely shortly to receive considerable accretion from switzerland and Prance.The Foreign Secretary added that he thought it very unlikely that M. Mikolajczyk would want to go intoPoland.     Pending the formation of another government hehad asked us to continue deliveries to Poland and certain other facilities which we had been giving to the PolishGovernment.       We were arranging to do this.     He had also informed the Foreign Secretary that M. Vitos, theElder Statesman of Poland, was now available to come out.Nothing could be better from all points of view thanthat M. Vitos should come to this country, and allpossible efforts were being made to arrange for him todo so.      The Lublin Government, which he did not thinkthat M. Mikolajczyk would be prepared to join in thepresent circumstances, had published a statement to theeffect that they would warmly welcome M. Mikolajczykif he were to come to Lublin.      There had been no commentas yet from the Russian side,THE PRIME MINISTER said that we should do everything possible to make things easy materially forM. Mikolajczyk and M. Romer.     As regards relations withthe Kwapinski Government, he entirely agreed with theline which the Foreign Secretary had taken.      Therewould, of course, be no question of breaking offrelations with the Polish Government in London, whenformed, since we recognised it as the - spokesman ofPoland.     But we should adopt an attitude of completedetachment and of frigidity and leave them to look after their own affairs.      The less we had to do withthem in the way of active relations, the better.The War Cabinet -Took note of these statements.Spain(previous reference:lf.M. ikk) 52ndConclusions,Minute 3)The War Cabinet next considered our policy towardsSpain, and had before them -(i) two memoranda by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (W. P.(hh) 665 j    andV/. P. (kk) 691) to which was attached a copyof a letter from General Franco to the duke of Alba.(ii) a note by the Lord President of the Counciland Deputy prime Minister (W,P.(i+h) 652);    and(iii) a memorandum by the Minister of economic warfare (W.P.(kh) 651) on Policy towards Spain.

- THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR.FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidthat, so far as he could judge, the view of the ordinary-Spaniard was that if the Franco regime persisted therewas bound to be an ex jlosion before very long.     the ambassador, in communicating General Franco&apos;s letter,had been very outspoken and had made it clear that, inhis view, the letter left it open to us to reply toGeneral Franco in terms which would make perfectly clear the view we took of him and of his regime.He would like to, see evolution of theSpanish Government as an insurance against therevolution, which was inevitable if Franco continued onthe lines he had so far followed.      In the light of this situation, what should our policy be?THE PRIME MINISTER said that there was greatclanger in interfering in the internal affairs of othercountries.      Our traditional policy had been to refrain from doing so.      It seemed likely that General Francomight have been encouraged to write his present letterby a misinterpretation of the remarks which he (thePrime Minister) had made in his speech in the House on2hth. May.       That speech had, of course., been intendedas a tribute to Spain and not to General Franco, to the evil features of whose regime he was only too fully alive.As, hoxvever, General Franco had given him the opportunity,he suggested for the consideration of the War Cabinetthat he should reply to General Franco in terras designedto disabuse him of any illusions that we needed his helpor that we were anxious to work hand in hand with Spainunder his government.      The opportunity could be takento bring out that Spain, who had not adopted a trulyneutral attitude during the war, would not be represented at the Peace Conference,     He was at the same time very anxious to avoid active intervention in the domestic policy of a proud and sensitive people well able to resist intervention, and thought that our wise coursewould be to send a rough reply to General Franco and leave him and his government to &quot;stew in their own juice&quot;,while refraining from any active steps to encourage the overthrow of that government.In the discussion that followed the followingpoints were made:-(a) THE L0,:Jj PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL expressed his entire agreement with the action proposed by thePrime Minister.    He had accepted in his paper W. P.(Uh)622that in view of Spanish xenophobia it was probablyimpossible to take overt action to change the situation,but that short of that there was much that could be done,and we should, especially in the economic field, work with the United States and France to deny facilities tothe present regime.(b) THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER pointed out,on the other hand,  that Spain was at the moment one ofour best customers;    important imports came from Spainwho bought extensively frosi us, and was prepared tohold sterling.     We should be careful not to take any action which might result to our-economic detriment.

(c) No suggestion had been made for the negotiation of a special Treaty of Commerce, whichwould indeed be likely to be highly offensive to publicopinion in this country.     Arrangements to govern theordinary exchange of goods were another matter.(d) THE MINISTER OF LABOUR AND-NATIONAL SERVICEsuggested that in any communication addressed tox&apos; General Franco, attention should be given to possible reactions on the Left as well as on the Right, shouldits contents become public knowledge.      It would beI very undesirable to encourage the Left Wing to thinkthat they had more support in this country than mightbe the case, and so perhaps to provoke them to unwise  &apos;and precipitate action.After further discussion, the War Cabinet -(1) Agreed to the Prime Minister&apos;s suggestionthat he should write to General Francoon the lines proposed by him, and that thedraft of this letter should first beconsidered by the War Cabinet.    (TheForeign Secretary undertook to prepare a first draft for the Prime Minister&apos;consideration). , -(2) Invited the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs to send the text of General Franco&apos;sletter and of the Prime Minister&apos;s reply,when approved by the War Cabinet, to theAmerican Secretary of Stato for information and with a view to securing his support.Western Bloc. .  THE PRIME MINISTER said that he thought thatthere would be advantage in an early discussionof the so-called Western bloc which appeared to beI attracting Increasing attention.    It was important that there should be no misunderstanding of our attitude, and in particular that General de Gaulleshould not be in a position to suggest in Moscowthat we had made overtures to him,to join a Westernbloc which he had rejected.    He (the Prime Minister)was very doubtful himself as to the soundness orpracticability of a Western bloc.     In his judgementthe only real safeguard was agreement between thethree Great Powers within the framework of the world organisation,     He felt himself that Russia was ready and anxious to work in with us.     No immediateI threat of war lay ahead of us once the present war was over, and we should be careful of assumingcommitments, consequent on the formation of a Westernbloc, that might impose a very heavy military burdenupon us.     He had himself at one time hoped that a european regional arrangement might be possible, but now felt doubtful as to whether it could be realised,though once the World Organisation had been broughtinto being there was nothing against a specialEuropean group.THE SECRETARY OF STATE&apos;FOR FOREIGN affairs said that nothing more had ever been contemplatedthan a special group based on the proximity ofcertain States to us; on the fact that we, the French,^ ( the Belgians and the Dutch were all great Colonial&apos;&apos; ! powers with common interests in that field;, and finally on the fact that Premier Stalin had himself in 1941 favoured an arrangement of this nature.

He, the Secretary of State, had told MonsieurBidault during the Paris^discussions that our first objective iri present circumstances was a world Organisation combined with our alliance withRussia.     He did not feel that there-could be anyquestion of any misrepresentation in Moscow by theFrench of our, attitude0     In any event the PrimeMinister&apos;s personal telegram to Premier StalinNo, 2183/4 and the parallel telegram which he had himself sent to Monsieur Mdlotov should sufficientlyprotect the position.The War Cabinet, took note of these statements, &apos; . \Offices of the War Cabinet, S,W,1C




</content>
</cab>
