<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/29/8 images: 48-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(^^--?2-^!L-LTHE property 0F HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S.GOVERNMENT)TO BE KEPT UNDER LOOK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document //MOST SECRET.  - COPY NO._ &quot;W.M.   (42) 11th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 5.Confidential Annex.&quot;?,    (27th January, 1942, 6.0 p.m.),3E FAR EAST. THE WAR CABINET had before them a telegram(JOHCU 21) from the Prime Minister of Australia to the.    .. . Prime Minister, dated 24th January, 1942 (W.P.(42) 34)..     7&quot; .   n The following are the main points in this telegramura-cegxoajL        which set out the views of an emergency meeting of the.equxrements.     Australian War Cabinet, which had been held on 23rd January.Part I.      Malaya.On the basis of reports from the G.O.C. ofthe Australian and Imperial Forces in Malaya,doubts were expressed&quot;as to the suitability ofIndian troops for the type of warfare now inprogress in Malaya.Sir Earle Page had reported that the DefenseCommittee (Operations) had been considering theevacuation of Malaya and Singapore,      The evacuation of Singapore would be regarded in Australia and elsewhere as an inexcusable betrayalsEven in an emergency, any diversion of reinforcements from Malaya should be towards theNetherlands East Indies and not towards Burma.Part II.     The Pacific,The importance of Port Moresby was stressed,and a request made that a number of submarinesmight be allotted to that base.Emphasis was laid on the desirability ofco-operation between the United States and australian Naval forces.Part III.     Aircraft.Requests were put forward for the immediateallotment to the R.A.A.F. of considerablereinforcements of aircraft from this countryand from the U.S.A*

THE PRIME MINISTER said   that a very depressingreport had been received from General Wavell, indicating -that it looked as though Singapore might only be able tohold out for a few weeks .    In this event we should have toconsider whether we might not have to send to Burma someof the reinforcements destined for Malaya.   It had5 therefore,been necessary for the Defence Committee to consider what our action should be if we were unable to hold the fortress.But he thought that Sir Earle Page had unintentionallymisled the Australian Government when he had reported tothem that the Defence Committee had considered theevacuation of Singapore.   The decision reached at theMeeting had been that the Battle of Johore and.the defenceof Singapore Island should be given the highest priority.Further, the orders issued to General Wavell had been thatthe battle should be fought out, if need be, in the ruins of singapore.The account given by Sir Earle Page to hisGovernment was, therefore, incomplete.   Clearly no decision could have been taken on such a grave matter without full consultation with the Dominions .   Proceedings at theDefence Committee would be gravely hampered if an incom-plete discussion, which formed, no part of the Conclusionsof the Meeting, was to be reported to the DominionGovernments.The Prime Minister added that he did not proposeto answer the telegram, but to refer it to the Chiefs ofStaff.SIR EARLE PAGE said that his telegram to theAustralian Prime Minister had been a factual statement ofthe position disclosed to   the Defence Committee (Opera-tions), together with his own observations.   He conceivedthat he was&apos; within hi?    rights in despatching such a .telegram.   In sending this telegram he had also had inmind that he could, use this as an instance to reinforce the view which he had already laid before the australian government, that it was in their interest that the ParEastern Council should be established in London, and notin Washington.Turning to the passage in the part of the telegram which dealt with the reinforcement of the pacific, Sir Barle Page said that it had undoubtedly beenin Mr Curt in&apos;s mind, in drafting his telegram, that sincethe beginning of the war Australia had never been unwilling to send her Imperial Forces overseas.   In doing so she haddenuded herself to a dangerous extent.THE PRIME MINISTER said   that it went without saying that the Australian troops and. air squadronsserving overseas must move homewards to the defence oftheir own country, now that danger threatened it.   Buteffect could only be given to this process very gradually.All the available shipping was mortgaged for   essentialmilitary movements.In reply to a question, SIR EARLE PAGE said thatthe Australian Government had. accepted President Rooseveltsoffer to send a large- force of American troops toAustralia.  ,

Reference was also made to   the movement ofUnited States troops to New Caledonia.THE MINISTER OP SUPPLY thought that it would beof, advantage if the Australian Government could be informedthat this movement of troops had been made possible by our having surrendered the use of ships which had been promised to us for other purpose es .SIR EARLE PAGE referred to the need for sendingfighter aircraft to Australia.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this  country and theUnited States were sending a steady flow of aircraft tothe Pa cifi c the at re.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF said that over 300fighters and 300   aircraft of other types were being sent by the United States to Australia for onward despatch to the Pacific theatre.   By far the quickest me&amp;icdcf obtainingfighter aircraft for Australia would be if some part ofthese reinforcements could be retained in Australia.The War Cabinet:-(l) Asked the Chiefs of Staff to report within two days on:-(a) The reserves of men and materialsavailable in Australia for the defenceof that country:(b) The v&apos;ays and means of despatchingearly reinforcements for Australia.(2) Instructed the War Office and Air ministry to prepare a Note setting out the steps which had already been taken to arrange forthe despatch of British and U.S. troops andair forces to the Far East.(3) Took note   that the Prime Minister andthe Minister of Supply were in consultationregarding the possibility of making available to Australia reinforcements ofarmo ur e d fight in g v ehi cl es .reat George Street, S.W.I.




</content>
</cab>
