<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/32/28 images: 234-237</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1942.MOST SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (42) 598.December 17, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND  key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.THE BOMBING OF ITALY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.THE War Cabinet will wish to be informed of the plans that are being madefor conducting the bombing offensive on Italy from this country and fromMediterranean bases.2.   It is necessary to maintain the flexibility of our bomber force so that it -can be switched at any time to targets in Germany.  As much as possible of the bombing of Italy must therefore be conducted from bases in this country.   Home-based bombers can only cover the northern part of the country; their effortsmust therefore be supplemented by aircraft based in North Africa.3.   The proposed plan, to which complete effect cannot be given until theenemy bridgehead in Tunisia has been seized, is as follows : .(i) The heavy bombers of Bomber Command based in this country will usuallyoperate against targets in Northern Italy whenever weather permits;but no opportunity of attacking important German targets in favour-able weather conditions will be missed.(ii) The heavy and medium bomber squadrons at present in Middle Eastwill concentrate against targets in Southern Italy from bases in theBenghazi area, using Malta as an advanced base to the extent thatthe supply position and the primary needs of the local fighter defencesallow.(iii) The effort of the American heavy and medium bomber groups in north africa which will be available for the attack on targets in Italy may be supplemented by Wellington squadrons of Bomber Command detachedperiodically to North Africa to the extent that airfield capacity andmaintenance facilities allow. It is unlikely that at first more than two Squadrons could be accommodated in North Africa for thispurpose, but the number might later be built up to four.4. With these dispositions, all important Italian towns will have beenbrought within the range of effective attack. It is estimated that it will bepossible to drop some 4,000 tons of bombs a month, an amount comparable withthe average weight of attack delivered on Germany in the months before NorthItaly was made the main target of our heavy bombers. Of the total of&apos;4,000 tonsa month, about 2,000 would be delivered by aircraft of Bomber Command.5. During the winter, large-scale operations are severely limited by weather both at the bases and over the target. Except during spells of unusuallygood winter weather, it would be imprudent to count upon more than four or five nights a month as suitable for large-scale raids. Since the weather is more likely to be suitable in Northern Italy than in Germany, the great majority of the[24778]&apos; -
good nights will be taken up with operations against Italian targets andcomparatively few will be available for bombing Germany. It seems possible,therefore, that the effort on Germany may not be more than between 500 and1,000 tons a month. Every advantage will be taken of good weather to improveon these figures. On the other hand, the important sea mining effort of bomber command would be unaffected and it should be possible to continue to lay minesat the rate of about 1,000 a month. So long as Italy remains the main targetthe monthly effort of Bomber Command, leaving out of account the U.S.A.A.C.and British bombers based in Africa, will be of the order of : Italy: 2,000 tons.Germany: 500/1,000 tons.Sea mining : 1,000 mines.The weight of attack should increase towards the Spring as the strength of bomber Command increases and the weather improves.December 17, 1942.A. EL M. S.



</content>
</cab>
