<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/169/11 images: 139-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(73) 51 COPY NO      n004 April 1973CABINETHOUSING POLICY: DRAFT WHITE paper note by the Secretary of State for scotland i attach a draft White Paper on Scottish Housing Policy which, subject tothe views of my colleagues, I propose to publish simultaneously with theWhite Paper relating to England and Wales, a draft of which has been circulated under cover of the Note by the Secretary of State for the environment, CP(73) 50.    As in the English draft, the passage on mortgage funds in this draft remains to be completed.G scottish Office4 April 1973
HOMES FOR PEOPLE SCOTTI&amp;H HOUSING POLICY IN THE 19/70&apos;sDEVELOPING POLICIES1.   After coming into office La June 1970, the Governmentlaunched a new campaign, extending over a broad front, to overcome Scotland&apos;s persistent housing problems.   the initial measures, designed to create a new financial frame-work - without which previous efforts had achieved only-partial success - were outlined in the White Paper &quot;the reform of Housing Finance in Scotland&quot; (Cmnd 4727* July 1971).By July 1972, these proposals had been given legislativeforce in the Housing (Financial Provisions) (Scotland) Act 1972.2.   The 1972 Act is the essential framework, but in theGovernments view it is only the first step towards success.The main elements of the Governments strategic policiesremain those described in the opening paragraphs of Cmnd 4727:the drive for building more new public sector houses wherever they are needed, a more intensive assault on the remainingslums, and the encouragement of home ownership, the building ofnew private houses, house improvement and environmentalimprovement.3*   There is a growing recognition that many long-standingattitudes and assumptions on housing have begun to change.Inoome per head in Scotland is now not far below the average for the United Kingdom as a whole, and is roughly equivalentto the levels prevailing in several regions of England.    most people in Scotland no longer need^. or wish, to regard a lowrent as the main criterion of an acceptable house.    There is less belief in the special virtue of any particular form of tenure, and wider acceptance that housing needs differ at different stages of life.    There is also a much more strongly-held desire to improve the quality of houses (and theirsurroundings), whatever the type of tenure.   There are increasing signs that personal preference, not just housingneed, is a significant factor in the decisions taken by manyfamilies about their home, and it will remain a main objective of the Government to enable them to enjoy as wide a choice as possible.1 .
h.   All these signs are evidence of a completely new attitude to the provision and choice of houses for Scottish families.The main purpose of this White Paper is to establish firmlythe lines on v/hich future action, based on this new attitude,can successfully implement these policies.   The current needin Scottish circumstances is not, in the main, new policies,but the energetic implementation of those already devised bythe Government, with each agency carrying out to the full itsown part of the task, and with local authorities identifyingthe priority needs in their areas and creating the conditions for them to be met.   The Government continue to believe thatthe aspirations of Scottish families to live in decent housescan be met in an acceptable time only by encouraging allagencies to provide new houses, and to modernise the olderones wherever this is appropriate.   But they will also continueto build upon the traditional foundation of Scottish housingpolicies - the local authorities - and will help these authorities to develop their role in response to the needs andwishes of Scottish families.A WIDER ROLE FOR LOCAL AUTHORITIES5.   The Government see a great need to widen the role of localauthorities.   Not only must they press forward v/ith vigour andspeed the building of new houses where these are required, theimprovement of older houses, and the clearance of slums; butit is a cardinal part of their responsibility to assess housing needs comprehensively, using modern techniques for the purpose.Some of today&apos;s problems have arisen from the absence in thepast of the necessary information and skills upon which to baseinformed decisions about the location, quantity, design and formof tenure of housing developments and the social provision -shops, schools, employment opportunities, recreational facilities - v/hich should be an integral part of them.   Localauthorities are now being encouraged to make good the presentdeficiencies.   They are also being encouraged to considerparticularly how to identify the requirements in their areas ofthose with special needs - such as the elderly, the handicapped,the one-parent family, the single person; and, once the needsof each group have been assessed, to consider how they could best be met - by new building or by adaptation or conversion,by the housing authority or by private development, by building for sale or for letting, by sheltered housing or by including an increased proportion of small houses in general housing2.
developments.    For the future, when they have assessed allhousing needs in their areas, the Government look to themto adopt policies which will ensure that these needs are met in the most appropriate ways.    Such policies must be devised in collaboration with neighbouring authorities where necessary, since often the demand for and supply of houses in an area transcends local authorities1 boundaries.HOUSING MANAGEMENT6.   One area in which local authorities can make effective and relatively quick progress lies in the management of their ownhouses.   Fortunately the days are gone when families wereglad to be offered &quot;housing&quot; on almost any terms and, because a local authority house was cheap to the tenant, he was prepared to accept what the council allocated him - in termsof location, h-ouse-type, amenity, maintenance and conditionsof let.   In many places these attitudes have disappeared, and authorities are developing a highly professional housingmanagement service which seeks to identify &quot;customer preference&quot;and then sets out to satisfy it.   Management advice given by theScottish Housing Advisory Committee in reports published duringthe last decade is being more widely followed.   Local policiesrequiring residential qualification for admission to waitinglists are gradually, if too slowly, being replaced by morehumane and realistic arrangements.   The better calibre andtraining of management staff in &quot;house letting departments&quot;should soon enable these departments to function increasingly as fully developed housing management departments, where tenantswill find sympathetic consideration of their difficulties.More thought needs to be given to the methods and frequency of rent collection, and to the early identification of rentarrears and the prevention, so far as possible, of evictionsresulting from the building up of arrears.   In improving these and the many other aspects of housing management, close consultation with the social work department is essential, andthe Secretary of State proposes to set up a Committee to considerthe links between housing and social work services following the reform of local government.   Great advantages can also be gained from arrangements for a positive part to be played in housing management by tenants of council houses, whoseconvenience demands sympathetic attention and reasonable flex-responsibility; there must be full consultation with tenants, forexample, on the planning of schemes of modernisation which may affect improvements already carried out by tenants at their own3.
expense.    In these respects, if all local authorities achievedthe standards of the best, the circumstances in which a largeproportion of Scottish people live would be transformed.   Thisis a major challenge, and the extent to which it is met in thenext few years will be the standard by which very many tenantswill judge their public landlords.    Increased expenditure onsuch mangement activities is now for the first time eligiblefor Government subsidy, and the Government expect localauthorities to take full advantage of this help.NEW HOUSE BUILDING7.    In furtherance of well-considered local assessments of need,and of the strategies for meeting them, the Government intend to do everything within their power to facilitate the provisionof new houses when and where they are required - to replaceslums, to provide for new households (whether for families, orfor the elderly and the disabled and others in special need),and to provide for industrial expansion.   In building thesehouses the local authorities themselves, the Scottish special housing Association the New Town Development Corporations,housing associations and societies, and the private buildingindustry will all be encouraged to play their appropriate parts.Local authorities and housing associations also have animportant part to play in providing hostel and similar accommodation,to respond to the needs of single people who are otherwisehomeless, and the Government intend to take an early opportunityof introducing legislation to enable more effective help to begiven for the provision of accommodation of this nature.8.    In the public sector, the new subsidy system has set the scenewithin which this part can most effectively be played, no longerat the risk of denying resources to the other important relatedfunctions such as slum clearance, the improvement of houses andtheir environs, and proper maintenance.   The Act of 1972 has provided for directing financial help from the Government to the&quot;&apos;councils whose housing problems are most acute, so that these authorities have every encouragement to drive ahead.Indiscriminate building, even by such authorities, is no morejustifiable than it ever was.   But the Government have set noupper limits on programmes, and it is for such authorities to formulate the plans to meet the needs, and to press ahead withmaximum urgency.   The more flexible arrangements recently adoptedin the housing indicative costs system take account of localconditions and will assist local authorities in the cost planning of their housing schemes.
9.    In the private sector, during the last year or two therelease of pent-up demand for new houses to buy has evokeda strong response from the house-building industry, whichhas had two record years, in which completions (at morethan 11,000 houses a year) were some kO% above the previoushighest level.   Although two out of every three new houses built in 1972 were completed by housing authorities, thesustained output of private housebuilders throughout the yearpromises well for the immediate future.   To ensure that people&apos;s wishes and expectations are not disappointed, it is imperative to foster continued confidence among prospectivepurchasers, and among builders, that both land and financewill remain sufficiently available to sustain an increasingvolume of new building.   The evidence suggests that despite the sharp upward movement of house prices in recent years,over the longer term the rise in house prices has no morethan matched rising incomes, and that more people than ever before have been buying houses;   but it is clearly necessaryto stabilise prices if demand and supply are to go on rising.10. Land.   Although there are some areas where local demand is greater than can be met without some movement of population,the availability of land has not been a critical limitation on the provision of housing for owner occupation in Scotland.There is no need to fear that it will become a crucial factor in the foreseeable future.   Scotland is not in general congested,and the latest assessments of availability of land for private housing suggest that there should be no significant shortage in this decade.   In these circumstances, it is important thatthere should be no short-sighted measures to zone and developland where development must be at a significant cost to thequality of the environment.   It is important to exploit thecountry&apos;s high quality environment, not only for the benefitsit will give to Scots living in Scotland, but also because itmay help to retain or attract those who have a large contributionto make to the economic life of the country.11. But a large and regular house building output depends on anample bank of land available for building, to ensure that pre-planning can proceed smoothly.   The Government will therefore continue to assist and encourage local planning authorities toincrease their annual rate of zoning and servicing land for private house building, so as to ensure that the total reserveis always more than the five years supply which these authorities have already been called on to maintain.    Improved5.
arrangements for recording and reviewing the amount of landzoned for development are to be introduced, and there will beregular consultations with local planning authorities and thebuilders to identify any difficulties about bringing this landon to the market and getting it developed.   The Governmentwill also pursue their policy of facilitating the release ofGovernment and other publicly owned land which could be usedfor housing.12. The Government expect house builders to respond tomaintenance of the conditions for confident expansion byplanning and building to meet the rising demand.   The Governmentare themselves stimulating by legislative measures the more rapid use of planning permission and the quicker development ofland zoned for housing.   Under the Town and Country Planning(Scotland) Act 1969 planning permissions, in general, lapseafter five years if not used.   The Government now intend topromote early legislation to introduce a charge designed to discourage the hoarding of land with planning permission, andto encourage landowners, whether builders or not, to ensurethat land with planning permission is developed quickly tomeet social needs.   The proposals for Scotland - which are onthe same lines as is proposed for England and Wales, in&quot;Widening the Choice - Housing Policy in the 1970s&apos; (Cmnd       ),paragraphs are summarised in Annex        .   They will be thesubject of consultations with the Scottish local authority associations and with the house building industry.13. Finance.   Confidence in the continuing availability of funds for house purchase, mainly from the building societies but also from other institutions including local authorities, is essential for both prospective purchaser and builder.   This is especially the case in Scotland.   There has been growing evidence,particularly in 1972 and despite rising prices, that first-time purchasers are coming forward in increasing numbers; and itis to be expected that a high proportion of house purchases inthe coming year will be made by people entering home ownershipfor the first time, with neither resources of liquid capitalnor the proceeds from the sale of a previous house to help them.6.
/The Governments proposals to maintain the flow of funds are/J   /The Government is carrying on consultations with the building societies in Scotland about the creation ofarrangements to secure stability in the flow of mortgage fundswhich are of special importance to Scotland, and such arrangements should greatly help- the sustained expansion ofprivate housebuilding for sale//   In addition, to complementlending by the building societies, the Government areencouraging local authorities to lend for house purchase toborrowers in specified categories, including tenants buyingtheir own council houses: no limit is imposed by the Governmenton the total funds which local authorities may lend in this way.And the option mortgage scheme, increasingly popular in the last12 months or so, demonstrates that there is a considerable demandfor home ownership among people in the lower income groups.Contributions by developers.    One possible source of delay in private house building would be that the financial demands ofproviding services to the land to be developed conflicted withother urgent local requirements for infrastructure investment.There is already provision under planning legislation foragreements whereby developers may contribute towards the cost of services, but these are not widely made.   The Government will therefore consult with the local authority associations and thehouse building industry about v/hether fresh arrangements mightbe introduced for developers to contribute towards the cost of services provided by public authorities in connection with thedevelopment of land with planning permission.15* Other measures.   Measures have already been taken to ensurethat, in allocating land, local planning authorities respond fully to the needs of the housebuilding industry.   The implementation of the Sewerage (Scotland) Act in May should also help thebuilder to build as well as possible at the keenest pricecompatible with value for money.16. The Government are confident that the private house-buildingindustry will respond to the needs and challenges which theGovernments policies are helping to create.    In particular,builders are recognising the growing opportunities for building atthe lower end of the price-scale, for the increasing number of families whose main hope of home-ownership lies there.   In this,they will be aided by recent improvements in productivity onScottish building sites, which the Government are helping to promote.7.
HOME OWNERSHIP17* Home ownership is a form of tenure v/hich is increasingly-desired by a widening range of people in Scotland.    TheGovernment will continue to encourage and help the private house-building industry to play its part.   But local authoritiescan and should do more in this direction, wherever practicable:they should make their own houses available for sale to sittingtenants v/ho wish to buy them, on the attractive terms which havebeen available to all local authorities to offer for over a year;and they should not hesitate, v/here appropriate, to seek theSecretary of state&apos;s consent to sell houses to persons who arenot sitting tenants, or exceptionally to build new houses for sale.This movement towards permitting council tenants to enjoy greater freedom of choice and the greater responsibility of owning theirown homes, which many of them would not contemplate leavingdespite their lack of legal security of tenure, is developing insome areas.   But in others the councils have failed to recognise the strength of the growing tide of public opinion in this matter.Admittedly the sale of only a few houses can give rise to management problems in relation to those that remain, but these have been overcome by authorities which have gone forwardenergetically.   The Scottish New Towns are giving a lead, with some3,000 sales so far and strong tenant demand for more progress.This is a lead which local authorities cannot afford to ignore ifthey are to shape the future of their communities as the residentsthemselves want them to be,HOUSES FOR ECONOMIC EXPANSION18. The availability of desirable housing is a key requirement inrelation to the measures which the Government are taking to expandand consolidate the Scottish economy.    Scotland is poised on aneconomic springboard and the imminent forward leap can bring greatbenefits to the whole country, not only to the areas in which the major new industrial developments are taking place.   Movement oflabour to these areas is both inevitable and essential if theindustrial   projects are -co expand and succeed.   But workers will,not move unless they know that they will be able to obtainsatisfactory houses, providing the kind of accommodation andenvironment in which they wish to bring up their families.8.
19* The Government are confident that local authorities willrecognise the importance of this element of housing need, andwill be prepared to allocate a reasonable proportion of their houses to incoming workers needed to promote economic expansion.Some of these incoming families will wish to buy their ownhouses, and here again local authorities will be able to assistby ensuring an adequate supply of serviced land to enableprivate builders to meet this demand.20o The Government recognise, however, that in some areas thenumbers of houses that may be needed for new industry will be beyond the resources of the local authorities, and they areprepared in these circumstances to authorise the Scottish special housing Association to build houses for incoming workers wherever the need arises.   As a measure of the importance which the government attach to this aspect of the housing programme, the association has already been authorised to build 15*000 houses for completionover the next four years.   This programme is already higher thanit has been for any comparable period since the 1950&apos;s; and itwill be expanded further, particularly to meet housing needs in theareas of oil-related developments.SUBSTANDARD HOUSING21. There are still some 190,000 houses in Scotland which fail tomeet the present statutory tolerable standard and must be dealtwith in one way or another - by closure and demolition, or byimprovement.   The Housing (Scotland) Act 1969 set the framework for action on houses of this kind; the Housing (financial provisions) (Scotland) Act 1972 provided for the first timedirect financial help from the Government towards the cost of slum clearance.    The clearance of unfit houses is already proceeding atan accelerating pace - no fewer than 20,000 were demolished orclosed in 1971* with nearly as many in 1972.   This momentum mustbe maintained.   A renewed drive to deal with Scotland&apos;s remainingsub-standard houses is in the forefront of the governments plans: either by clearing away old houses which are below thetolerable standard, and building new houses to replace them; or byrenovating old houses, wherever this is possible, so that peoplecan continue to live in the same neighbourhoods and communities.9.
22. This is a priority task.    It is intolerable that housesrecognised as substandard a generation ago should still be in use.   The Government will be urging local authorities to reviseand implement the plans drawn up under the 1969 Act, and to proceedto deal with all substandard houses in the shortest possibleperiod.   Furthermore, the Scottish Special Housing Association isbeing authorised to add to its approved building programme an element for assisting local authorities with the provision of replacement houses where slum clearance could not go ahead quicklyenough otherwise.23* Then there are many houses which, while not below the statutory&quot;tolerable&quot; standard, are not up to full modern standards.    It isessential that as many as possible of these should be improved,whether they are in private or in public ownership.   The measures taken from 1 969 onwards, including in particular the raising ofthe grant levels by the 1969 Act and the introduction for a periodof the special, higher grants and Government contributions underthe Housing Act 1971* have already substantially increased thevolume of improvement work in Scotland, from a total of just under15*000 houses in grant applications approved in 1969 to nearly50,000 in 1972.   The Government will continue to support and encourage action to improve substandard houses and poor housingenvironment.   To help in this, they are considering now whetherthe improvement grant scheme in Scotland can be made more effective and will be bringing proposals forward later this year for achieving this.   Meanwhile the Housing (Amendment) Act 1973 has provided for the extension of the 1971 Act so that its provisionsnow apply to work completed before 23 June 1974*24* The drive to improve the quality of housing must not stop atthe house itself.   There is a growing conviction that, particularlyin urban areas, much of the discontent felt, and many of thesocial difficulties encountered, spring from the poor environmentalquality of these areas and their lack of social facilities.    Thebenefits that should accrue from better housing will accrue onlypartly, if at all, when tno houses are in bleak surroundings, andwhen community facilities are sparse or non-existent.   Housingpolicies cannot be pursued in isolation.   They must be part of a wider programme for the physical and social development and well-being of the areas concerned.10.
25. Recognising the need to give special emphasis to this aspect of development, the Government have made financial assistance for it available on an unprecedented scale.   Grant for work onimproving the environment of houses, introduced by the 1969 Act,has been made more attractive by the doubling of the amount ofaualifying expenditure per house and, where the 1971 Act(as extended by the 1973 Act) applies, by the higher proportionof cost provided for under that Act.   Provision for expenditureon the rehabilitation of derelict land has been increased, and special programmes of environmental improvement providing grantof more than  13m have been initiated.   These programmes arebeing particularly concentrated on selected areas of WestCentral Scotland, including the City of Glasgow, where the need to improve environmental quality is especially acute.    TheGovernment will continue to give every encouragement to this very important aspect of improving living conditions.HOUSING ASSOCIATIONS26. The Government believe that the time has come for a majorexpansion in the activities of housing associations and housingsocieties, both in new building and in improvement.   While many more people want to own their own homes, there is still a continuing large demand for housing to rent.   At the same time,however, particularly in towns, the supply of rented houses isdwindling rapidly for those who do not regard council houses as their first choice.    Owners of private houses can help by improving them and keeping them available for renting, and every encouragement will be given to this: but the Government believethat a third source of supply is necessary and that this can best come from housing associations, which have a traditionalrole and expertise in this field. ,27. The Housing Corporation (under a new Chairman), assisted bythe Scottish Special Housing Association (which already providesservices for the Corporation in Scotland), will expand itsrole in Scotland in stimulating action by housing associations and housing societies to improve houses, to build houses forrenting, and to build houses under co-ownership schemes.    its powers to obtain funds for this purpose, and to make loans more widely available, were extended for the country as a v/hole bythe Housing Finance Act, 1972.    The activities of housing associations should also be stimulated by the provision in theHousing (Financial Provisions) (Scotland) Act 1972 for new formsof help for house building and improvement by housing associationsby way of subsidies directly related to the cost of the building11.
or improvement -work and the income likely to be obtained fromthe houses. What is now needed is primarily that the associations and societies, under energetic and professional management, should regard themselves not just as providers for special needs (althoughmuch of their most successful work in Scotland may continue to lie in this area) but as major contributors to the renting market and,through co-ownership, to home-ownership.CONCLUSION2S.   The Government are resolved to press vigorously ahead v/ith the wide range of housing policies, aimed at getting rid as quickly as possible of substandard housing conditions and providing, notjust a decent home for every household, but a growing opportunityfor choice and a steadily rising standard of quality.   To this end,the Government believe that the policies already in operation,together with those now projected, will enable all agencies and formsof tenure to play their part.*29.   Local Housing authorities will continue to have the key role in promoting oetter and more varied housing.   They should set out their general objectives - not only for new building, but for all their main functions - for longer periods than has been usualhitherto;   plans should if possible be drawn up for 5-10 years ahead,in consultation with the other agencies concerned, and should be kept under periodical review.   They have wide responsibilities - for the assessment of housing need for new building where appropriate, forvigorous slum clearance and improvement programmes, for the fosteringof housing association work, and for modernising their own housingstock.    They have already been given Government subsidy for the first time to help people with rent rebates.   Also, for the first time,they have been given powers (supported by subsidy) to help private tenants with rent allowances (and, under the recently enactedFurnished Lettings (Rent Allowances) Act 1973 this help will beavailable in future to priority categories of tenants of furnished accomodation).   These measures are evidence of the Governmentsconcern for the private tenant and the role of the local authority in relation to the private tenant, which is shown also in theGovernments drive for more improvement of older houses and its extension of the fair rent system, in replacement of outmoded rent control provisions.    In addition, there is subsidy for slum clearance operations:   there is subsidy for rising housing expenditure, v/hether arising from new building, management, repairs,re-financing of capital debt or changes in interest rates:   and thereis subsidy for improvement schemes.   In all these activities, theGovernment offer councils full support, financial and otherwise.Z30.   As a result of the measures described in this White Paper, public expenditure on housing in Scotland is likely to increase abovepreviously forecast levels by some  25m over the next five years.This v/ill be achieved by a redirection of resources, without acorresponding increase in total public expenditure.    It demonstratesthe Governments determination that resources should be madeavailable as necessary for accelerating the solution of Scotland&apos;sremaining housing problems^/
31.    If all agencies, public and private, play their full part,there is every prospect in the 1970&apos;s of making unprecedentedprogress towards satisfying Scotland&apos;s housing requirements.    Theconditions are being created in which nobody need go without areasonable home for lack of means, and most can enjoy a fair choice of sound, attractive houses.   The tide has now turned, and theGovernment intend to keep it flowing.13.
annex the LAND HOARDING CIIARGE1.    The Governments measuroc to cccure more planning permissionsfor housing development will go a long way towards remedying theshortage of building land, and so removing the occasion forwindfall profits based on scarcity values.   But they will be frustrated if land speculators can with impunity continue tohoard land with planning permission.2.    The Government have therefore decided, as the Chancellorof the Exchequer announced in his Budget statement, to promote early legislation to introduce a land hoarding charge.    The purpose ofthis charge is to ensure that land v/ith planning permission for housing is developed promptly, and to penalise the speculativehoarding of such land.    The following paragraphs set out the mainoutlines of the charge, about which the Government will now holdurgent consultations with the local authority associations and thehousebuilding industry.3.    The charge will be levied for failure to complete developmentwithin a specified period from the grant of planning permission.Legislation will prescribe a normal completion period of h years from the grant of outline permission or 3 years from the grant of full permission where no outline application was made in the firstinstance.   Local planning authorities will be empowered to authoriselonger completion periods on application where this seems reasonable in the light of the particular circumstances;    the legislation willset out the kinds of considerations to which authorities may haveregard.    These will include the size of the development, itsrelationship to programmes for services, and the general state of thehousing market.   Authorities will also be empowered to extend theperiod if this is justified by any change in circumstances, inparticular those outside the developer&apos;s control, including any delay in approval of detailed plans following a grant of outline permission.h*   Where land is already subject to planning permission on the dateof this White Paper, the normal completion period will be h years fromthat date if the permission is in outline only, and 3 years from thatdate where detailed plans have already been approved or detailedp3rmission already exists.In considering applications for extending the period, local planning authorities will be required to have regard to any time that has elapsed between the grant of permission and the date of theWhite Paper.5.   The charge will be levied on the full market value of the propertyZpn the day after which the relevant planning permission is granted/or, in the case of land withpermission granted before the date ofthe White Paper, the value /on the date of the White Paper/.   Thisvalue will be assessed by the District Valuer, subject to appeal tothe Lands Tribunal for Scotland.   The charge will accrue from the endof the completion period by reference to a fixed percentage of thatvalue for each year&apos;s delay, the charge to be levied for the actual1.CONFIDENTIAL
year of completion being based on the proportion of that year v/hichhas elapsed before completion.    The charge will be due and payable for the first time either on the date of completion or on the expiry of a year from the end of the completion period, whichever is theearlier, and on the same day in each subsequent year during whichthe delay continues until the completion date.    Interest will be payable for any period of delay in payment after the due date.6.    The Governments present intention is that the charge should beat a rate of /2Q]p for each full year of delay.   A final decisionon the rate will be taken in the light of the circumstances prevailing when the legislation is introduced.   But, on the basis ofan annual rate of /2Q%/ a person who had three years in which tocomplete development and was allowed no extension of the period wouldbecome liable to the charge if, on the first day of the fourth year,the development was incomplete.    The amount of the charge would increase day by day until at the end of the fourth year it would be/20/o7 of the value at the beginning of the first year, at the end ofthe fifth year it would be ^4+0^7 of that value and so on.   Where partof the land is completely developed, the charge would apply only to do  much of the site as had not been completely developed.7.    The charge v/ill not be deductible for tax purposes, ie it willnot be treated either as a trading expense for builders anddevelopers or as an addition to cost for those liable to capital gains tax.8.    The charge will be computed on the basi- of the District Valuer&apos;svaluation, it v/ill be collected by the Inland Revenue and paid intothe Consolidated Fund.9.    The charge will not apply to(1)    Cases where the planning permission is for the improvementor conversion of an existing structure, v/hether or notthis involves the creation of new dwellings, or for theextension of an existing structure involving the creationof not more than 2 dwellings.(2)   Plots of land for v/hich there is planning permission onthe date of this White Paper for the construction of notmore than two additional new dwellings.(3)   Land which is the subject of a mixed permission for housing and some other materially different fcrm cfdevelopment, if the local planning authority considersthat housing is not the predominant form of development.10.   To prevent evasion, the charge will be secured on the propertyitself.   Ordinarily the person chargeable will be the owner or the holder of some other relevant interest in the property such as along leaseholder.   To safeguard the position of owners of land whoare opposed to the development of this land, the existing planninglav/ will be amended to provide that the written consent of the ownerwill in general be necessary before an application for planning permission for housing could be valid.   If the owner withholds thatconsent, the local planning authority will be able to resort to proceedings for compulsory purchase with a view to reselling the 2and2.
for development, just as it can now do wliere an owner is ixnwillingto sell land which is ripe for development.    The Secretary of state will be ready to support compulsory purchase if the land is urgently needed for housing and is otherwise unlikely to be forthcoming for this purpose in the immediate future.   planning permission obtained before the date of the White Paper by a person other than the owner will not be exercisable if the owner canestablish that he had objected to the grant of the permission.    Inthat case no compensation would be payable.11. Every permission for housing development which might attract the charge will include a specified completion period, which would,normally, unless the local planning authority determined a longer period, be the one prescribed in the proposed legislation.    Thisspecified completion period will go with the planning permission andbe subject to the right of appeal to the Secretary of State who would determine it on the basis of the parties&apos; written representations.Similarly, any application for an extension of a period incorporated in an existing permission would also be subject to appeal to theSecretary of State.12. All planning permissions are now subject to time limits.    Thenormal time limit for starting to implement a permission is 5 years.A planning permission for housing existing on the date of the white paper which might attract the charge v/ill remain valid for afurther period which v/ill be specified in the legislation unless thelocal planning authority considered that the permission should not remain valid.3.


</content>
</cab>
