<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/35/30 images: 208-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAIi CABTHET 120 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,.S.W. X, on Monday, .306fr August, 1943, ctf 5&apos;30 &apos;p,m;Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Oliver &apos; Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon; Ernest Bevin, M.P.,.Minister of Labour and NationalService.&apos;The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary pf State for theHome Department and1 Minister ofHome Security;The- Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador to theUnited States of America.The following the Right Horn S. %.,Bmjmr.B^m*sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Crepps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton,Minister of Food (Item&apos; 5).The Right Hon. Harcourt Johnstone,M.P., Secretary, Department of overseas Trade (Item 5).Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles FA.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.laisopjEeieslijThe - R^ht Hon. Sir Kjng^ley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Item 5).The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.Sir Orme Sargent, . Deputy Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Vice-Admiral Sir Neville Syfret,Vice-Chief of Naval Staff.Lieutenant-General A. E. Nye, Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr, Norman Brqok.Brigadier L. C. Hollis.Mr. .L. F. BuRGis.&quot;260151
mmMinute23456WAR CAJ&amp;INfET^lSSQ (4Jf),Contents.Naval, &quot;Military ami1 Air Operations..y.vAv\v\Air operations. -Home theatre.Mediterranean.Pacific.&apos; China.&quot;Naval operations:t&apos;.\ Shipping losses.U-boat sinkings.Military operations:&apos;. r       Russia.JRussian and German losses. &apos;-;Air,PplicyTargets in France.Quebec ConferenceItaly     ....      .1.ShippingInternal transportation in India.Yemeni Encroachment in the Aden Protectorate249250260250250251u,
and MsOparatJans. - i&apos;(Previous   -y :&apos;Bef erence:WM. (43) 118thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Home i Theatre-;Mediterranean.&apos;Pacific.China.naval operations.Shipping Losses.U-boat Sinkings.li The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events Of thet-previous week. -Owing1 to weather conditions Bomber Command had onlycarried-out two major attacks, against Berlin and Nurembergi &apos; The-)damage done had not yet been assessed. Our bombers had destroyed16 enemy night-fighters in these two attacks. Coastal Command had had yet another poor week, only sighting one U-boat.Our losses had been 95 bombers, 16 fighters and 10 sCoastaUCommand aircraft. Enemy losses had been 43 aircraft.XJnited States aircraft had attacked, among other targets, the-^ it at Villacoublay and claimed to have destroyed 23 enemy,aircraft during the week.Allied aircraft had attacked enemy communications and airfields. Foggia had also been attacked. 211 enemy aircraft were claimed to nave been destroyed, 56 probably destroyed and54 damaged. Allied losses amounted to 50 aircraft.In the Pacific the United States Army Air Force claimed69 enemy aircraft destroyed, 11 probably destroyed and 38 damagedfOr the loss of 5 aircraft.The destruction of 71 Japanese, aircraft had been claimed bythe Americans.Shipping losses (confirmed) from enemy action during theprevious week amounted to 14,400 tons.MilitaryOperations.Bussia.Bussian andGerman Losses.The U-boat situation in the Bay of Biscay had taken an unfavourable turn owing to new measures adopted by the enemy.Nevertheless, 17 German, 1 Italian and 3 Japanese U-boats had been sunk during the month.Around Smolensk the Germans were offering a stiff resistance to the Russian advance. North of. Briansk the Russians wereapproaching the. Viazma-Briansk railway. South of Briansk,Sevsk had been captured. Further to&apos; the south the Russians had reached a point 30 miles N.N.W, of Poltava. The Germans wereCounter-attacking fiercely in this area. In the Middle Donetz therehad been hard fighting. A News Agency had reported the evacuation of Taganrog by the Germans. In general, the week had been asatisfactory one for the Russians, who had consolidated all theiradvances and repulsed enemy counter-attacks.The Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that theprevious week the War Cabinet had asked him to prepare a com-paratiVe statement showing the total German and Russian claims of men. and material destroyed and captured on the Russian frontsince the beginning of hostilities. The Russians claimed that theGerman losses up to June 1943 had been 6^ million killed and captured. This figure: took no account of men who had ceased to beemployable in the army on account of wounds and sickness. Ifallowance was made.for this factor, the total of German casualtiespermanently lost to the army claimed by the Russians up to June ofthis year was about 16 million.The War Office had endeavoured to arrive at an estimate of thetotal German losses to date, and their provisional estimate was that.between 4^ and 4f million men had been permanently lost to theGerman Army.As Regards material, the Russians claimed 60,000 guns capturedand 48;O0O tanks destroyed.It Was more difficult to assess the German claim of Russianlosses, but in November 1941 Hitler had put forward the figure of8-10 million. The German wireless, early in 1942, claimed that theRussian losses amounted to 12 million, and in September 1942iRibbetitrOp-had stated that the Russian losses, had been 14 millionwith 5  million prisoners. \;,IKeTe ;was noi doubt that the claims of both sides wereexaggerated. &apos;.&apos; -  .The WarCabihefr---Took note of ^hese statements..[26015]&apos;B 2
[(-Previous .Reference;:W.M. (43) 56thConclusions,.Minute .2;)Ouebeo2.   The War Cabinet had a sh^of a target in France. , - ;  r,f The discussion and , the conclusion reached are recorded-inthe Secretary?s Standard Filei of . ^S-ar Cabinet Conclusions.3.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Chiefmqe.       of the A ir Staff gave the War Cabinet a brief account of the main political and military agreements reached in the Anglo-Americanconversations at Quebec.(Previous :Reference:W.M. (43) 119thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The War Cabinet were informed of the latest developments&apos;of the Italian position. &apos;.: ,The discussion is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File ofWar Cabinet Conclusions.Shipping.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 57thConclusions,Minute 5.)Internal &apos;Transportationin India.5. The&apos; War Cabinet considered the Sixth Report of theShipping Committee (W.P. (43) 376).In their Fifth Report the Shipping Committee had recom-mended that, until it became possible to frame a closer estimate of probable imports in the second half of 1943, the Ministry of war transport should endeavour to secure to the Ministry of Food an import for the year of 10-5 million tons, the balance of the importbeing left to the Ministry of Production. They had, however,recommended that, of a total import of 26 million tons, 11 million tons should be regarded as the proper share of the Ministry of Food.It now seemed likely that a total import of 26 million tons wouldbe realised and that any short fall in availability of cargoes wouldbe in raw materials. The Committee therefore recommended, inparagraph 13 of their Report, that the Ministry of War transport should &quot;now endeavour to secure the full share of 11 million tons.tothe Ministry of Food, provided that that Ministry could make available cargoes of type and provenance broadly in accordance withthe import programme:The Minister of Production and the Minister of Food concurred in this recommendation.The Minister of War Transport said that, in view of military commitments discussed at the recent Conference at Quebec, therewould be greater difficulty in finding shipping for the import programme during the last three months of 1943. This need not, hethought, prevent us from achieving a total import of 25- - to26 million tons. In 1944 the posititon should be easier- and in his recent discussions with the United States authorities he had stakedout a provisional claim for shipping sufficient for an import of12  million tons in the first half of 1944. He believed, however, thatan even larger volume of shipping could be; made available for thepurpqses Of our import programme;, and he urged that no time be lost in making an estimate of our import requirements for the wholeof the year 1944.; This estimate would then be communicated to theUnited States authorities.In paragraph 14 of the Report it was recommended that areliable estimate should be made of the internal transportationposition in India, and the effect of increased military activities onthe availability of supplies at Indian ports, v
V; The War Cabinet were informed that the Indian railways hadalready received a good deal of help through the supply of equip-ment, and that the United States Government had co-operated mproviding this assistance. The United States authorities were unlikely, however, to provide further help until an enquiry had beenmade into the operational efficiency of the Indian railways. TheMinister of War Transport was satisfied that such an enquiry wouldbe helpful, and that it would be advantageous if United .Statesexperts were associated with it.The War Cabinet-(1) Took note of the estimates given in W.P. (43) 376 for totalimports in 1943 and in the first half of 1944.(2) Endorsed the proposal, in paragraph 13 of the Report, that -the Ministry of War Transport should endeavour to-secure to the Ministry of Food an import of 11 million tons during 1943.(3) Invited the Minister of War Transport, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for India, to arrange for an enquiry to be made into the internal transportationposition in India, as recommended in paragraph 14 ofthe Report. United States experts should be associatedwith this enquiry.YemeniEncroachmentIn the aden protectorate.6. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (W.P. (43) 377) reporting thata Yemeni detachment had encroached on the territory of the aden protectorate on the eastern side of the peninsula of Sheikh-Said.Written protests to the Imam had produced no result, and theGovernor had now asked for authority to threaten the use of force,and in the last resort to use force, to Compel the withdrawal of the imam&apos;s troops.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he was satisfied that this encroachment was deliberate and that, if it werenot checked, it would spread. He recommended that the governor should be given the authority for which he asked. If it became necessary to use force, it was contemplated that action would betaken by the Royal Air Force alone, would be preceded by airdemonstration and warning, and would not extend beyond the boundary of the Aden Protectorate.,In discussion, it was suggested that the Chiefs of Staff shouldbe given an opportunity to advise what would be the most effective means of applying force if it became necessary to use it.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed in principle that the Governor of Aden should beauthorised to threaten, and in the last resort apply, force to secure the withdrawal of the Imam&apos;s troops from theterritory of the Aden Protectorate. *(2) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to Consider and report how force could be most effectively applied, if it became necessaryto use it for this purpose: Further reference should bemade to the War Cabinet if it was proposed to take military action against objectives outside the Protec-torate.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,30thAugust, 1943.




</content>
</cab>
