<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/66/8 images: 54-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;^,GOVERNMENT eyrjPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1945.SECRET. Copy No ^CP. (45) 8.1st June, 1945.CABINET.FUTURE ORGANISATION OF COALMINING INDUSTRY.Memorandum by the Minister of Fuel and Power.1. I announced in the House of Commons on the 29th May (see Annex I)the Government^ policy for the future organisation of the coalmining industry.2. In view of the agreed necessity, in the national interest, of beginningthe reorganisation of our coalmines as soon as possible, I now ask that Parlia-mentary Counsel shall be instructed to start drafting a Bill for preliminary consideration.3. I do not anticipate that this Bill need be a lengthy one, and it shouldbe possible, I hope, to introduce it soon after the new Parliament meets, if thepresent Government is returned.4. I attach, as Annex II, the outline of the scheme which would form thebasis of the instructions to Parliamentary Counsel.G. Ll. G.Ministry of Fuel and Power, Millbank, S.W. 1.1st June, 1945.ANNEX I.(Extract from Hansard, 29th May; cols. 87-88.)MAJOR LLOYD GEORGE : The Government consider that the working,treatment, and disposal of coal should continue to be conducted by private enter-prise, provided these are planned in accordance with the national need andconducted with the maximum efficiency.   Coal is to-day owned by the State.It is, further, a wasting asset; some qualities are wasting far more rapidly than we like to think.   Therefore, it is right that it should be conducted in accordancewith the national need and with the maximum efficiency.   War-time measures are not necessarily suited to peace-time conditions and a new practical startis needed.   The position cannot be remedied by mere change of ownership. Thatoffers no solution.   The Government have, therefore, decided that a centralauthority, appointed by the Minister of Fuel and Power and subject to his general direction, should be set up to insist that the necessary measures are taken andto provide such help and guidance as are useful.   The measures to which I refercentre upon the proper development and efficient conduct of operations in eachcoalfield according to the best modern practice.   In so far as the grouping oramalgamating of collieries is necessary for this object it will be carried through,voluntarily if possible, but otherwise by compulsion.   We do not propose amal-gamation for amalgamation^ sake, for in this diversified industry, whereconditions vary widely, there are often to be found highly efficient undertakings which aie sometimes not large.    In such cases amalgamation would only be proposed if there were clear advantages to the nation and to the industry.   Themaking and the carrying out of these plans will be undertaken by the industry itself.   The duty of the central authority will be to satisfy itself that the scope and the effect of the plans conform to the national requirements, and it will have powers of enforcement in reserve.   The policy will preserve the incentives of free enterprise while safeguarding the industry from political interference inits day-to-day management.   It will also provide the necessary sanctions for making sure that the essential improvements recommended in the Reid report are carried through.[29996]
ANNEX IEOutline of Scheme.1. A suitably constituted whole-time central Authority (to be known asthe National Coal Board) with a regional organisation to be set up, the membersthereof to be appointed by the Minister of Fuel and Power. This Authority,which would replace the Coal Commission, to be subject to the general directions of the Minister. The Authority would consist of a Chairman and four members,of whom one would be an industrialist, one a mining technician, one a formerwage-earner in the coalmining industry, and one an accountant.2. The fee simple in coal and mines of coal to be transferred from the coal commission to the Authority.3.   The Authority shall-(a) Secure, voluntarily if possible, but otherwise compulsorily by order ofthat Authority, the grouping and amalgamation of colliery under-takings necessary to secure the proper planning and efficient conductof coalmining operations in a coalfield. There shall be no appeal froman Order of the Authority, but, in the absence of agreement, thefinancial provisions of an amalgamation shall be determined by a^Tribunal specially appointed by the Lord Chancellor.(b) Require each amalgamated undertaking to submit broad plans for theworking of coal in lease (including closures of pits and seams, newsinkings and reorganisation work) and for the production of the coalestimated as likely to be required from that undertaking.(c) Determine, in consultation with the undertaking, any modifications tothe plans necessary in the national interest or to increase efficiency of production.id) Ensure that the coal is worked as agreed or determined.Sanction.4. A lease held by a component unit of an amalgamated undertaking to be surrendered, and a new lease on the same terms to be granted to the amalgamatedundertaking, save that it shall be an express condition of such new lease thatthe requirements of the Authority shall be carried out by the undertaking.Breach of this condition to give a right of re-entry or forfeiture to the Authority.Advisory Bodies.5. Pit Production Committees should continue and the executive head ofthe Authority;s organisation in each Region should be assisted by a smalladvisory board on which both management and labour would be represented.Finance of Reorganisation.6. Many amalgamated undertakings will be able themselves to financeschemes of reorganisation undertaken in accordance with the recommendationsof the Reid Report. AVhere this is not possible, however, such schemes of reorganisation cannot be delayed without impairment of the national interest.The necessary financial assistance, on suitable terms, should then be providedfor schemes which have been approved by the Authority. In such cases more detailed supervision by the Authority will be required.Effect on Coal Mines Act, 1930.7. Any necessary regulation of output and fixation of maximum selling-prices should be carried out by the Authority and no longer by the Central Councilof Colliery Owners and District Executive Boards as provided by the Coal mines act. 1930.(Note. No reference is made in the above proposals to wages or todiscipline. It is recommended that wages and conditions should continueto be agreed between the colliery owners and mineworkers, and failing agreement determined by the existing Conciliation machinery. It isanticipated also that in order to restore proper discipline to the pits themanagement should resume the right to dismiss or to suspend workmen.)



</content>
</cab>
