<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/1 images: 26-44</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1971CM (71) Copy No.1st conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 5 January, 1971,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,mp, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon, q c,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, m p,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Da vies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry and President of the Boardof trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. John Peyton, mp,Minister for Transport Industries(Item 6)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, chief secretary, Treasury (Items 6-9)The Right Hon. Norman Wylie, qc,m p, Lord Advocate (Item 1)Sir Geoffrey Howe, q c, m p, Solicitor-General (Items 1-5)
Secretariat :Sir Burke trend sir Robin hooper mr. P. E. thornton mr. N. F. cairncross mr. P. J. hudson mr. B. G. tucker mr. T. D. 0*LearyMiss S. W. fogarty mr. G. F. KearMr. J. F. MayneContentsSubject,Accident at Ibrox Park   ............Oversea Affairs     ......     .........Floods in MalaysiaTrials of Basque Guerillas in SpainTrials of Jews in the Soviet UnionMiddle EastChinaImmigration Bill    ...............Sale of Arms to South Africa.........Rhodesia       .........     .........Channel Tunnel     ...............The Speaker&apos;s Pension.........Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Pay Review BodyImproved Expenditure Decisions by Government
CM 1 (71)confidential. The Lord Advocate said that, in accordance with the normal procedure in Scotland, the Procurator Fiscal had held a preliminaryinquiry into the accident at the Ibrox Park Football Stadium in glasgow on 2 January. It fell to him on consideration of theProcurator FiscaFs report, which he expected to receive very shortly,to decide whether a fatal accident inquiry should be held to ascertain the cause of the deaths of those involved in the accident. In this case it was almost certain that he would decide to institute such an inquiry, which would be held by the Sheriff of Lanarkshire, sittingwith a jury. It would be advisable for one of the Law Officers topresent the evidence. The findings of the inquiry would beavailable in about two months and the inquiry would be able to assign responsibility for the accident and to make general recommendations.*The Home Secretary said that before the accident theGovernment had already taken action aimed at improved safety of football grounds generally; in the summer of 1970 he had seenrepresentatives of the Football Association, primarily in relation tohooliganism; they had told him of the measures being taken byclubs following the report of Sir John Lang&apos;s inquiry, and he had sent a questionnaire direct to the main football clubs makingsearching inquiries about safety and was now receiving the replies.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that he also was receiving replies to a questionnaire he had sent to football clubsin Scotland at the same time as the Home Secretary&apos;s. He had visited the Ibrox Park Stadium and seen some of the injured in hospital,and had received preliminary reports of the origins of the accident.The accident had engendered general concern about the safety offootball stadia, and it was important that this wider problem of safety measures should be pursued separately from the inquirydealing with this particular accident at Ibrox Park.The Prime Minister, summing up a short discussion, said thata fatal accident inquiry would deal only with the accident at IbroxPark; it was necessary to consider at once what action should betaken to secure higher standards of safety at football groundsgenerally. Such action might include long-term measures, involving,for example, structural alterations to football stadia, and alsoimmediate measures such as stricter police control of crowds leaving a stadium. The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the environment (Mr. Eldon Griffiths) was arranging for all clubs to be
asked immediately to re-examine their safety precautions. He would arrange for a small group of Ministers, under the chairmanship ofthe Home Secretary, to consider urgently what general action was required in both the long and the short term, including the questionwhether an independent general inquiry into safety should be set up.When the Lord Advocate had reached and announced his decisionon the setting up of a fatal accident inquiry, the Home secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland should make it known thatgeneral steps had already been taken with the Football associations and the clubs with a view to improving safety at football groundsthroughout the country, and that further urgent consideration wasbeing given to the problem.The Cabinet Took note with approval of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.secret oversea AffairsFloods inMalaysiaTrials ofBasqueGuerillasin SpainTrials of jews in the SovietUnion2. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that heavyrains in Malaysia had resulted in extensive flooding, as a result ofwhich some 30,000 people had been rendered homeless. He was considering urgently, in consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer and other Ministers concerned, what action we could usefully take for the relief of distress.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that a Spanishmilitary court had passed sentences of death on 6 members of aBasque nationalist movement. We had been under heavy pressure from the British Council of Churches, the Trades Union Congress,and Mr. Denis Healey to intervene on behalf of these prisoners but had judged it wise to do so only at the last moment and then inguarded terms. In the event the Head of the Spanish State,General Franco, had commuted the death sentences, and it was likely that our restraint would pay dividends in terms of Anglo-Spanish relations. Now that the death sentences had beencommuted, there would be no objection to proceeding with theproposed visit to Spain of the Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState, Department of Trade and Industry, Mr. Anthony Grant, whichhad been postponed pending the outcome of the trials.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that he had made an appeal through the Soviet Ambassador for clemency in thecase of the Soviet Jews who were on trial in the Soviet Union on
Middle east previous reference :CM (70) 36thConclusions,Minute 4charges of hi-jacking. The Ambassador had expressed resentmentat our intervention and had professed surprise at our solicitude for persons who, in the view of the Soviet Government, had been guilty of the kind of acts of violence against civil aircraft which the BritishGovernment were concerned to suppress. The growing hostilitytowards the Jews in the Soviet Union was a matter for concern. Weshould have to keep up the pressure on the Soviet Government,although the Soviet Foreign Minister, Mr. Gromyko, had beenunresponsive when the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary had raised the matter with him during Mr. Gromyko&apos;s visit to London.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the mission of the Special Representative of the United Nations&apos; Secretary-General, Dr. Jarring, had now been resumed. The United arab republic (UAR) were insisting on the priority of withdrawal byIsrael from the occupied territories, w&apos;hile the Israelis gave first priority to the renewal of the cease-fire after its current period ofvalidity expired on 5 February, and no progress had yet been made.So far as the cease-fire was concerned, the UAR Government, whoseinternal position was not a strong one, might feel impelled to makea demonstration of belligerence when the cease-fire expired: butthe morale of the UAR forces was low, and they were unlikely totake any major action. It might be easier to assess UAR intentionsafter he had seen the UAR Foreign Minister, Dr. Mahmoud Riad,who would be arriving in London that day. Dr. Jarring himself wasnot sanguine about his prospects of success. He alleged that the Israelies insisted on his confining himself to the role of a go-betweenand did not wish him to act as an independent negotiator. TheForeign and Commonwealth Secretary intended to speak to theUnited Nations Secretary-General, U Thant, with a view toencouraging U Thant to try to induce Dr. Jarring to adopt a more constructive attitude. He would also try to enlist the support of theUnited States and France for his representations. But Dr. Jarringwas not a very dynamic character, and the procedures he had adopted left much to be desired: for instance, no records had been kept of his conversations with the contending parties.China The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the lastBritish prisoner detained in the Chinese People&apos;s Republic,Mr. Johnston, had now been released. This betokened a moreforthcoming attitude on the part of the Chinese Government. Thelatter had recently expressed interest in the purchase of VC 10aircraft: but the numbers available had not been sufficient to meet
CONFIDENTIALImmigrationBillPreviousReference:CM (70) 4tnConclusions,Minute 63. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (CP (70) 126) summarising the main provisions of theproposed Immigration Bill and drawing attention to particular points of difficulty.The Home Secretary said that the chief problem in preparing the Bill was to abide by, the clear undertaking in the election manifesto to establish a &quot; new single system of control over allimmigration from overseas&quot;. This the Bill would effectively achieve,although within the single system of control it would be necessary,for practical reasons, to apply more stringent criteria for admission to Commonwealth citizens than to aliens in order to prevent aresurgence of &quot; New&quot; Commonwealth immigration. Such aresurgence would inflame community relations in Britain; the successof our policies aimed at improving community relations was basicallydependent on the Governments maintaining firm and demonstrablecontrol over the admission of immigrants.The Cabinet then considered the detailed problems outlined inthe Home Secretary&apos;s memorandum.In discussion it was agreed that the future control mechanism for commonwealth immigrants should be based on criteria of skill andusefulness rather than on a flat numerical quota system, althoughprovision would be made for the^application of quotas if these should prove necessary. The operation of more stringent criteriaagainst prospective Commonwealth immigrants (which would effectively exclude the unskilled) than those applied to aliens would lead to charges of discrimination; but given the propensity of&quot; New &quot; Commonwealth immigrants, in contrast to aliens, to settlepermanently and to bring in their dependants, this safeguard wasboth necessary and defensible. It would however be desirable tohave an early study of the &quot; open-door &quot; philosophy on which our policy on the admission of aliens for employment had hitherto been based. It was questionable whether, given over 600,000unemployed in this country, it remained an acceptable proposition that certain sectors of the economy, notably catering, shouldtheir requirements, and the Chinese had now placed an order in theSoviet Union.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.
continue to recruit substantial numbers of aliens. The removal or at least reduction of this anomaly would also serve to answercharges of discrimination against Commonwealth citizens under thenew control system. There was a need for a factual study ofthe occupations for which aliens were recruited, coupled with an analysis of the degree to which United Kingdom unemployed couldreplace them.The Secretary of State for Social Services said that he welcomed the special provision that was being made to keep doctors outsidethe future control system for immigrants, but he would urge thatimmigrant dentists should be similarly exempted and that bothCommonwealth doctors and dentists should be exempt from the requirement for police registration.The Home Secretary agreed to consider this.The Cabinet discussed the possibility, examined in paragraphs15-19 of the Home Secretary&apos;s paper, of exempting fromimmigration restrictions Commonwealth citizens who could show adirect ancestral link deriving from a United Kingdom-born parent orgrandparent. It was agreed that, although such a concession wouldprobably attract some criticism as being discriminatory in favourof the &quot; white &quot; Commonwealth, it was defensible as being a clearreflection of our unique relationship with the &quot; old &quot; commonwealth countries. Very substantial numbers of New Zealanders andAustralians and a smaller proportion of Canadians would benefit,and our diplomatic representatives in Canberra and Wellington had indicated that this concession would greatly moderate the criticism of our immigration policies being voiced in those countries.In this connection, some support was expressed for the viewthat all citizens of the &quot; old &quot; Commonwealth countries and notmerely those with one United Kingdom-born grandparent, shouldbe exempted from our immigration controls. After discussion,however, it was agreed that although such a concession would be welcome in the &quot; old &quot; Commonwealth and in this country, it wouldbe difficult to defend against charges that we were discriminatingagainst the &quot;new&quot; Commonwealth and giving to nationals of the&quot; old &quot; a special status which it could be argued was contrary tothe concept of the Commonwealth as a multi-racial institution. Itwould be difficult to find any criterion e.g. the retention by thecountry concerned of The Queen as Head of State which wouldhave the effect of securing in practice unrestricted entry to theUnited Kingdom for nationals of the &quot;old&quot; commonwealth countries with which we had especially close ties, while at the sametime achieving our objective of setting limits to immigration from
the other countries of the Commonwealth. It was noted, however,that even the concession on grandparental connection would be insufficient to exempt the descendants of the earlier colonists in the&quot; old&quot; Commonwealth from our immigration restrictions, eventhough their origins might be purely British. However, for thepurposes of visits to and study in this country the privilege they atpresent enjoyed would be preserved.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said he was concerned lest the interpretation of the new immigration restrictions should adversely affect Gibraltarians to whom assurances had beengiven that they would not lose their present privilege as regardsentry to the United Kingdom. The number of persons concernedwas minimal and this was a matter on which, uniquely, all theGibraltarian political parties were united.The Home Secretary agreed to give special consideration to theposition of Gibraltarians in the light of the assurances which hadbeen given to them.It was agreed that unlike aliens, Commonwealth students shouldcontinue in the future to be exempted from police registration, andthat this exemption should extend to Commonwealth student nursesand post-graduate students. In future, however, Commonwealthstudents who forsook their studies and took up employment would thereby lose the right to remain in the country and would becomeliable for deportation.The Cabinet discussed the desirability of any change in the votingrights of immigrants. It was noted that the Government was under no obligation to make a change in voting rights but was, on thecontrary, specifically committed to preserving the franchise givento Irish (Republican) citizens in the United Kingdom and to maintaining the voting rights of those Commonwealth citizens whowere already settled in this country. The Cabinet agreed that itwould be unwise to seek to modify ^the franchise now accorded to commonwealth immigrants: to maintain it would serve to underlineour relationship with the Commonwealth and answer, at least inpart, charges of discrimination against the Commonwealth arisingfrom other aspects of the new immigration controls.The Prime Minister, summing up, said the Cabinet agreed ingeneral with the Home Secretary&apos;s proposals for the ImmigrationBill. The Home Secretary should now arrange for the completionof the drafting of legislation taking account of the views expressedby the Cabinet on the adoption of criteria rather than numericalquotas for the admission of Commonwealth immigrants, the
SECRETSale of arms to SouthAfricaPreviousReference:CM (70) 42ndConclusions,Minute 2*4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary (CP (71) 1) giving the text of an under-taking by the South African Government not to use arms supplies forpurposes other than maritime defence, together with a note by thePrime Minister (CP (70) 122) covering the reports of two official working Parties on certain aspects of the same problem. The first report considered proposals which we might put forward duringthe Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; Conference at Singapore for discussions on defence problems in the Indian Ocean. The secondexamined contingency plans for the protection of our interests if* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.SECRETintroduction of a concession on grounds of ancestral connectionwhich would broadly benefit the &quot; old &quot; Commonwealth, and the exclusion of Commonwealth students from the requirement to register with the police. No action should be taken to circumscribethe voting rights of Commonwealth citizens. The Home secretary had also undertaken to consider certain concessions to immigrantdentists and doctors and the possibility of making special arrangements for Gibraltarians in keeping with the Ministerialassurances given to them. The Home Secretary would also discuss further with the Chancellor of the Exchequer the question ofassistance towards repatriation expenses for those commonwealth immigrants who wished to return home. The Secretary for employment should initiate a study of the employment of aliens, onthe lines which the Cabinet had discussed, and report his conclusions to the Cabinet. As to the timing of the introduction ofthe Bill, this should not be earlier than the end of January, therebyproviding an opportunity to reconsider the matter if necessary inthe light of the outcome of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos;Meeting at Singapore.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^summing up.(2) Invited the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for employment to proceed as indicated in the PrimeMinister^ summing up.
some members broke away after the Singapore Conference and perhaps also took retaliatory action against us.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the form ofpublic assurance now agreed with the South African Government(set out in paragraph 2 of CP (71) 1) following the cabinets discussion of the subject on 1 December went as far as it was realisticto expect the South African Government to go in reassuring their neighbours that they had no aggressive intentions.The Prime Minister said that the reports of the two official working Parties circulated as CP (70) 122 had been discussed indetail by the Defence and Oversea Policy Committee on theprevious day. The first report showed that there might be advantage in making it clear, during the course of the Singapore Conference,that we would be ready to take part in bilateral discussions on security in the Indian Ocean area with any other commonwealth country and that, if proposals were put forward for discussions on a broader, multilateral, basis we should be prepared to consider themconstructively. The original suggestion for consultations on defence problems in the area emanated from the Governments of kenya and Nigeria; and action on the lines proposed might well be ofinterest to those Governments, as well as influencing them to viewless unfavourably the Governments intentions in the matter of arms supplies to South Africa.On the report on contingency plans, also circulated withCP (70) 122, the Prime Minister said that the Defence and overseas policy Committee had taken decisions on a number of detailedmatters, and that the Cabinet would probably wish to concentrate on the salient points which had emerged from that discussion. Thefirst of these concerned Commonwealth countries which decided to register objection to our action in selling arms to South Africa simplyby leaving the Commonwealth, while taking no other retaliatory action. It was proposed that, while we should do nothing to mitigate the natural consequences of withdrawal from the Commonwealth, weshould take no deliberate retaliatory action against the State orStates concerned. The Committee had also discussed the ways inwhich it would be appropriate to respond to positive measures taken against our interests in the contingencies envisaged. They had agreedthat a great deal would depend on the circumstances of each individual action and that decisions on the measures required,whether in the economic or other fields, could most appropriately betaken at the time. A small Committee of Ministers (under thePrime Ministers chairmanship) was therefore being set up for thepurpose of reaching these decisions speedily. The same Committee
would also be available, when necessary, to deal with problems arising on measures to ensure the safety of British nationals overseas,including evacuation plans, where these required interdepartmentalaction.In discussion, there was general agreement with the conclusions reached by the Defence and Oversea Policy Committee as reported by the Prime Minister. The following additional points were made:(a) The Defence and Oversea Policy Committee&apos;s discussion had shown that, if an announcement of the Governments policy was tobe made very shortly after the end of the Singapore conference it might be necessary to put certain precautionary moves of naval units in hand during the period of the Prime Minister^ absence.The co-ordination of these and other moves could most effectivelybe ensured if the Committee referred to by the Prime Minister metunder the Home Secretary&apos;s chairmanship, as necessary, for thepurpose of issuing the instructions required.(b) The contingency study in CP (70) 122 presented a sombrepicture, since it examined a wide range of possible reactions whichhad potentially far-reaching political implications. There were indications that some African countries would wish to avoid amutually damaging series of counter-measures; but in Zambia and uganda in particular emotions were still running high.(c) The same study (in paragraph 38) referred to possible massexpulsions of Asians with United Kingdom passports from certainEast African countries. Transport limitations would probablyprevent any problem created in this way from building up very quickly; but the possibility could not be excluded that these Asians,as well as our own nationals, might be harassed in the countries inwhich they were at present residing.id) At the Singapore Conference, it would be important to avoidimplying that our attitude was liable to change under pressure. Onthe other hand, the Prime Minister and Foreign and commonwealth secretary would make it clear that our decision would not be announced until after their return to this country, when a statement would be made to Parliament. It would be desirable for the cabinet&apos;s final decision on the terms of this statement to be made inthe light of the conclusions about the likely reactions of the other commonwealth countries reached by the Prime Minister andForeign and Commonwealth Secretary at Singapore.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet welcomed the terms of the South African undertaking
which the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary had reported in cp (71) 1. They took note of the reports of the Working Partiescirculated with CP (70) 122 and approved, subject to the point madein discussion in regard to precautionary moves of naval units, themethod by which the Defence and Oversea Policy Committeeintended to deal with the various contingencies which might arise.Together with the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary, he would seek so to conduct the discussions in Singapore that the procedure and timetable for the announcement of our intentions referred toin discussion could be maintained.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.SECRETRhodesiaPreviousReference:CM (70) 39thConclusions,Minute 2*5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary (CP (71) 2) to which was annexed a proposed reply to a communication dated 21 December, 1970,addressed by the representative in South Africa of the illegal regimeto Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Pretoria.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the replyby the leader of the illegal regime, Mr. Ian Smith, to our initialcommunication enquiring whether there was a basis for the resumption of discussions had been negative in tone. His further communication of 21 December, though it rejected the idea ofresuming talks at the point at which they had been broken off inHMS Fearless, and maintained the regime&apos;s insistence that the starting point for future discussions must be based on the illegal1969 Constitution and the acceptance of Rhodesia as a &quot; sovereignindependent republic &quot;, nevertheless afforded a basis on which thedialogue could be continued. Given the desirability of doing soat least until the Commonwealth Conference in Singapore was over,there appeared to be advantage in replying to Mr. Smith, providedthat we could be reasonably sure that to do so would not provokean announcement by him that he considered that there was no pointin continuing the exchanges. The draft reply annexed to his memorandum, to which he now sought his colleagues&apos; approval, was designed to avoid this risk.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said that before any progress on the substance of the problem could be* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.SECRET
confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for the Environment (CP (70) 123) about the Channel Tunnel.The Secretary of State for the Environment said that the ministerial Committee on Economic Policy (EPC) had consideredthe proposal for a rail Channel Tunnel. They had accepted, in thelight of all the preliminary work which had been done jointly withthe French but subject to the outcome of the final studies, that arail tunnel was feasible and economic, that no alternative form offixed link was practicable, and that the tunnel was preferable tocontinued reliance on sea and air transport alone. There were noplanning difficulties. However, the financing proposals which had emerged from negotiations between the previous Administration,the French Government and a private consortium and which hadbeen largely accepted by the French Government were notattractive. In particular, at least 85 per cent of the constructionfinance raised by the consortium would be guaranteed by the twoachieved, it would be necessary to have a genuine exchange of views with the regime in Rhodesia. For this purpose something more would be required than exchanges in writing. In regard to the replyto the regime&apos;s communication, the Cabinet agreed that the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary&apos;s draft was in general well calculated to achieve our short-term objective of keeping the dialogue withMr. Smith going, thus enabling us to avoid controversy at the singapore Conference on the ground that exchanges with the regimewere still in progress. The last sentence of the draft, however,which pointed the contrast between, on the one hand, the regime&apos;sconcept of parity between Africans and Europeans and, on theother, the principle of unimpeded progress towards majority ruleto which we were committed, raised issues which should be avoidedat this stage, and should in consequence be omitted.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to arrangefor the despatch by Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador inPretoria to the representative of the regime in SouthAfrica of a communication on the lines of his draft, asamended in discussion.
Governments, and the private capital at risk would be very small.It was desirable to reduce the share of the public sector if this were possible. There was, however, a serious risk that if the financial discussions were to be re-opened completely the project would fallthrough with adverse repercussions on Anglo-French relations. it seemed likely that only a small increase in the degree of privateparticipation could be negotiated at this relatively late stage in discussions which had lasted some years. In the circumstances, theMinister for Transport Industries might discuss the position withthe French Government on the basis that the British Governmentendorsed the concept of a rail Channel Tunnel in principle, that we wished to start the final studies now and were prepared, if necessary,to cover all or most of the costs of the first stage, but that we wishedto give further consideration to the financing proposals before reaching joint decisions on those submitted or on the part to be played in the project by the present private group. No commitmentwould be undertaken at this stage to construct the tunnel nor,indeed, to carry the studies beyond the end of the first stage andany proposed agreement would be considered in consultation withthe Law Officers to ensure that the Government were not socommitted.In discussion the following points were made (a) If a fixed link were to be provided, it should be the railtunnel. However, even though all the existing evidence indicated that the growth of crossed-channel traffic could be catered for more cheaply and satisfactorily in that way than by the development of sea and air transport, it would be wrong to commit the government at this stage to going ahead with the project even if the outcome ofthe final studies were satisfactory.(b) Unless a decision were taken quickly to go ahead with thefinal studies, a season&apos;s work would be lost and the project mightbe jeopardised.(c) Provided that we were prepared to embark on the studiesimmediately (and to meet the costs of the first stage if the consortiumwere unwilling to do so before the conclusion of a full financingagreement) it was reasonable to explain to the French Governmentthat the new Administration wished to review the arrangements for financing the British share of the cost in the light of their general policies.id) It was suggested, however, that the French Government who attached considerable importance to the project were likely tomisunderstand an approach on these lines unless it included an assurance of our commitment in principle to the project.   In
particular, it was undesirable to tell them specifically, as EPC had proposed, that our intention to proceed depended on agreement onsatisfactory financing proposals.(e) The private financial interests who had been working on the project for some four years were becoming impatient for a decision.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that stage 1 of the final studies should be put inhand as soon as possible. They were not, however, prepared at thisstage to endorse the existing financing proposals. If in thecircumstances the private interests were not prepared to finance the studies, we should be prepared to provide up to  500,000 to meetthe cost of stage 1. The French Government should be informed of our willingness to proceed urgently in this way, but that we wished to give further consideration to the financing of the british share of the cost of the studies as a whole and of construction.There was no need to refer specifically to our commitment inprinciple to the tunnel project; this had been made clear in 1964.If it proved necessary he would be prepared to write to PresidentPompidou on these lines. The Minister for Transport industries should then explore urgently with the French Government andsubsequently with the consortium the scope for improving the financing proposals, and should report the outcome to EPC. In themeantime there should be no public statement, but the position might be explained in confidence to the consortium as soon as the approach had been made to the French Government. It was essential that any agreement made in respect of stage 1 of the studiesshould not commit the Government, explicitly or implicitly, vis-a-viseither the French Government or the consortium, to proceed withthe later studies or to construction of the tunnel.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for the Environment and theMinister for Transport Industries (i) to consider, in consultation with the Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster, how the governments position might best be explained to the French onthe lines indicated in the summing up of thediscussion;(ii) to explore the possibilities for reducing the degreeof public involvement in the project and to
bring the existing financing proposals and anyalternatives before EPC as soon as possible;(iii) to ensure, in consultation with the Law Officers, thatany agreement in respect of the final studiesinvolved no commitment, explicit or implied, toproceed beyond the first stage or to constructionof the tunnel.confidential the Speakers        7.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ChancellorPension        of the Exchequer (CP (70) 121) on the provision of a pension for mr. Speaker King.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, when the previousSpeaker died in office in 1965, provision was made by Bill for thepayment of a pension of  1,667 a year for his widow. This followed the principle first introduced in 1959 of providing a widow&apos;s pension at the rate of one-third of the Speakers own pension, which was assumed in 1965 to be  5,000 a year. The Speakers salary had not changed since that date. The Acts fixing the pensions for the PrimeMinister, the Lord Chancellor and the Higher Judiciary prescribedone-third of the husband&apos;s pension as the rate for a widow&apos;s pension.He accordingly proposed that a Bill should be introduced a few days after the Election of the new Speaker to provide a pension of  5,000a year for Mr. Speaker King and a contingent widow&apos;s pension of 1,667 a year in the event of his wife surviving him. Although no specific commitment had been entered upon, the salary and pension of the Speaker would no doubt be considered as part of theforthcoming review of the remuneration of Ministers and Membersof Parliament. Any new level of pension that might be establishedwould apply to Speakers retiring thereafter, but not to Mr. SpeakerKing. His pension would, however, come within the scope of thePensions (Increase) Bill to be introduced later in the current Session.The Cabinet-Approved the proposal in CP (70) 121 for the introductionof a Bill to provide a pension of  5,000 for Mr. SpeakerKing and a contingent widow&apos;s pension of  1,667.
CM 1 (71)confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Home Department (CP (70) 125) about the secretariatfor the three new review bodies to be set up on pay in the public sector.The Home Secretary said that the Government had announced on 2 November in the House of Commons that the new review bodieson top salaries in the public sector, Armed Forces&apos; pay and doctors&apos;and dentists&apos; pay were to have a degree of common membership and a common secretariat which would be provided by the proposedOffice of Manpower Economics (OME). The representatives of the doctors and dentists were prepared to accept the principle of somecommon membership and a common secretariat. However, theysuspected that the OME would be under Government influence andthat an OME secretary would therefore impair their review body&apos;independence, to which they attached &quot;the greatest importance.They suggested that, instead, the secretary of the review bodiesshould be drawn from the Cabinet Office, and argued that this wouldenable them to secure acceptance by their members of the rest ofthe Governmenfs proposals. The Secretary of State for social services had recommended the Ministerial Steering Committee on pay Negotiations to agree to the professions&apos; request, arguing that,provided a Cabinet Office secretary would in practice maintainclose links with the OME, the change would be only a formality,and that refusing the concession would lead to a crisis in relationswith the doctors and dentists in the National Health Service.However, the Committee thought that the medical and dentalprofessions would, undoubtedly claim the concession to be one of substance and that accordingly the Governmenfs resolve in carrying through their announced policies would be called in question.Moreover, Members of Parliament, whose pay was to be consideredby another of the review bodies, would see a Cabinet Office secretary as a threat to the review body&apos;s independence, rather than a guarantee of it; and in practice the review of Armed Forces&apos; pay would need the special skill and experience which the OME would inherit fromthe National Board for Prices and Incomes. The Committee had concluded that, while maintaining the undertaking that the findings ofthe new review bodies would not be referred to any other outside body and that the Government would accept the recommendations unless there were clear and compelling reasons to the contrary, they shouldreject the two professions&apos; requests for a Cabinet Office secretary and adhere to their publicly announced intentions. He invited theCabinet to endorse these conclusions.
The Secretary of State for Social Services said that he hadcommended the proposal for a Cabinet Office secretary solely as adevice to help secure the acceptance in general by the medical profession of the arrangements for the new review bodies. If theGovernment rejected it, there was likely to be public dispute with the doctors. However, he was grateful to the Secretary of State for employment for agreeing to make a concession in the industrial relations Bill on the status of bodies such as the British medical association and the Royal College of Nursing, since that would avoid provoking the medical profession on two issues at the sametime.The Prime Minister, summing up a short discussion, said that,for the reasons advanced by the Ministerial Steering Committee on pay Negotiations and because making the concession requested bythe medical profession would contrast unfavourably with theGovernments firm line on the terms of reference for the Court of inquiry into the electricity ,supply pay dispute, the Cabinet agreedto maintain their previous decision that the secretary of the newpay review bodies should be drawn from the OME. Proposals forthe composition of the review bodies should be formulated quickly and submitted to him by telegram during his forthcoming journeyoverseas.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Employment, inconsultation with the other Ministers concerned, to submit to the Prime Minister at an early date proposals for the composition of the new public sector pay review bodies.CONFIDENTIALImprovedExpenditureDecisions byGovernmentPreviousReference:CM (70) 38thConclusions,Minute 39. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Lord privy seal (CP (70) 124) on Improved Expenditure Decisions by government.The Lord Privy Seal said that further study of the implications of introducing a programme analysis and review (PAR) system,particularly in terms of its demands on manpower, had been carriedout by a group of senior officials, under Treasury chairmanship.Their report which was attached to his paper had been seen and endorsed by Permanent Secretaries.  The report made it clear that
the PAR system would have to be selective in its approach: in1971 each main spending Department would review one or two important programmes, and, in the case of the very largeDepartments, one or two programmes for each policy areacovered by the Department. The timetable for 1971 had been worked out and should be compatible with the PESC timetable.The extra load on Ministers would be reduced to a minimum bythe selectivity of the system and because systematic review underPAR would replace ad hoc reviews which became necessary fromtime to time in the absence of PAR. The demands on Civil service manpower, some in particularly scarce categories, had been broadlycalculated as less than 100 in the first year. This price was worthpaying for the advantages gained. Work should start immediately ifthe programme for 1971 was to be put into effect.The Prime Minister, summing up a. short discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed to introduce a selective programme analysis and review system as now proposed, and an appropriate announcementcould be made. The selectivity of the system made it easier tointroduce. The extra manpower involved was small, and, onceintroduced, the system should more than pay for itself. Many ofthe details of the system would have to be worked out as it was introduced; in particular acceptable ways of balancing proposed increases in expenditure with offsetting reductions within the framework of the latest PESC decisions would no doubt emerge inpractice. Departments should co-operate to the full in developing the system as complementary to PESC and as a valuable aid to mcfrerational decisions on the competing claims of programmes withinthe total of public expenditure. Ministers would wish to considercollectively, where this was appropriate, the results of reviews.The Cabinet-CD Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to arrange for the Civil service department, the Treasury and the Cabinet Office to enterinto discussions with Departments in order to introduce a programme analysis and review system as soon aspossible.(3) Invited the Lord Privy Seal, in consultation with the lord president, to make an appropriate public announcement about the introduction of the new system.Cabinet Office,5 January, 1971.

</content>
</cab>
