<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/67/28 images: 178-185</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET Copy No.O.P. (45) 78(Also G.O.S. (45) 143)12th July, 1945CABINETWEEKLY RESUME(No. 306)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 5th July to0700 12th July,1945[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room
NAVAL SITUATION.Continental Ports.1.   The port of Wilhelmshaven is now open to routine shipping.A thousand ships have completed repairs at Antwerp since the port wasliberated in spite of heavy and persistent attacks by rockets and flying bombs.An exceptionally large volume of shipping and supply traffic has also beenhandled in the port.The repatriation by sea of German personnel from Norway began on the8th.   It is estimated that in 20 days, 10,000 men will have been moved.On the 9th, a large ammunition dump blew up at Dunkirk, causing consider-able damage in the centre of the port and many casualties.On the 7th, for the first time since the liberation of the port, a liberty shipwith a French crew entered La Rochelle. The cargo consisted of 7,800 tons ofsteel, building timber, cotton, paper and tobacco.South Atlantic.2. On the 9th, the Brazilian light cruiser Bahia blew up and sank N.E. ofRecife after probably hitting a mine. Over 100 of the crew reached the island of Fernando Noronha and others were rescued by British, U.S. and Brazilianships.On the 10th, a German 700-ton U-boat arrived at Mar del Plata (S. ofBuenos Aires).Mediterranean.3. On the 10th, a new quay, built at Salonika by the Royal Engineers was handed over to the Greek authorities. This quay, 300 yards long, is the largestever built at Salonika, and enables large ships to discharge without the use oflighters.East Indies.4. During minesweeping operations which commenced on the 5th, H.M.ships Nigeria (cruiser) Roebuck, Vigilant and Eskimo (destroyers) and aircraft from H.M. ships Ameer and Emperor (assault carriers) attacked Car Nicobar andNancowrie. Airfields and batteries were the main target and a number of small craft were also damaged. Six of our aircraft were lost but five of the pilotswere rescued. On the 11th, 24 Hellcats were flown off to attack installations atKota Raja in Northern Sumatra. One enemy aircraft was destroyed in combat.One Hellcat was lost but the pilot was saved.5. During recent patrols in the Malacca Strait H.M. S/M Trident shelledan airfield S.E. of Sabang and sank a junk and a landing craft, and H.M. S/MVivid sank a junk.Pacific.6. U.S. submarines operating in the Pacific have sunk two ships, twosubmarine chasers and four small craft. In the Arctic Circle they have sunk large cargo ship, a coaster and three small craft. In the Java Sea a submarine chaser and five small craft were sunk. In Japanese waters a smallcargo ship, two small tankers and nine small craft were sunk, a cargo ship was probably sunk and a large cargo ship and submarine chaser were damaged.During June, Allied aircraft have sunk or damaged 164,800 tons of Japaneseshipping. During the first six months of the year, 2,282,000 tons of enemy shipping has been sunk or seriously damaged.Since operations first began on Okinawa U.S. naval aircraft have sunk159 ships totalling 145,000 tons and have damaged 194 ships totalling 138,888tons.   They have also destroyed or damaged 70 enemy aircraft.Japan.7.   On the 10th and 11th, over a thousand U.S. carrier-borne aircraft attacked enemy installations in the Tokyo area and destroyed or damaged152 enemy aircraft.
Borneo.8. Throughout the week Australian forces in the Balikpapan area havebeen supported by heavy bombardments from Allied warships and attacks bycarrier-borne aircraft.New Guinea.9. Light craft, carrying a shore raiding party, have made daylight raids on enemy island outposts in the western Halmaheras. With the co-operationof aircraft, several warehouses and small craft were destroyed.Solomon Islands.10. On the 7th, an R.A.N. frigate shelled enemy positions on Sohana island in the Buka Passage.Minesweeping.11. In the Oslo, Stavanger, Bergen, Trondheim and Tromso areas 711,000mines have been destroyed, which represents a little over 50 per cent, of the totalmines laid in these areas.During the week 112 German mines have been destroyed in Home waters and 244 in the Mediterranean and off the Burma coast.In Home Waters, 309 British mines have been destroyed.Of the mines destroyed during the week-, 111 were dealt with by Germanminesweepers operating under British control.On the 5th, operations were started to clear the enemy minefield off CarNicobar.   In five days 167 mines have so far been destroyed.MILITARY SITUATION.Western Europe.12. The withdrawal of Anglo-American forces from those parts of the agreed Russian zone where the cessation of hostilities had found them, was com-pleted on the 4th.Agreement as to the limits of the French zone of occupation has been reached,and the necessary redeployment began on the 6th.The Quadripartite occupation of Berlin has now begun, British and U.S.contingents completing their arrival in the capital on the 4th and 5th respectively.A French contingent which arrived on the 4th is being accommodated in theBritish sector.Burma.13. During the week, parties of Japanese which crossed the Sittang River allbut surrounded a detachment of our troops in a village 3 miles N.W. of Makpalin.Our troops have been forced to withdraw temporarily and the Japanese have occupied the village.Further slight progress has been made along the Mawchi Road where leadingelements of our forces are in contact. Patrols have also penetrated to a distance of 23 miles S.W. of Kalaw.Japanese casualties for the week have amounted to 741 killed and 35prisoners-of-war.Pacific.Philippines.14. Luzon. U.S. troops continue to encounter stiff opposition S.E. ofKiangan.In the area south and east of Cervantes Filipino guerrillas have capturedseveral more small towns.The enemy is withdrawing to flanking positions between the roads leadingS.W. and S.E. from Bontoc to ground most suitable for a final stand.15. Mindanao. U.S. troops landed unopposed at the N.W. corner ofSarangani Bay on the 9th. Guerrilla forces are reported to be moving overlandfrom the western shore of the Davao Gulf.[30221] B 2
Borneo.16. Brunei Bay. Australian troops have continued their drive up theBeaufort-Jesselton railway and on the 9th reached Bongawan after overcomingopposition in the early stages of the advance.&apos;  The town of Kuidang S.E. of Tutong was occupied on the 8th.In the Miri area several enemy counter-attacks have been repulsed.17. Balikpapan.- Further landings by Australian troops have been madeon the west of Balikpapan Bay at Penadjam. on the 5th, and Djinabora onthe 9th, completing their control of Balikpapan Bay. Small advances have beenmade north and N.E. of Balikpapan and determined opposition has been met at Manggar.By the 10th, Australian troops had completed the occupation of thePandansari oil refineries.Bougainville.18. The Japanese launched a heavy attack against the Australians holdingthe line of the Mivo River, 16 miles west of Buin, and the Australians have been forced to withdraw to the west bank of the river.On the east coast of the island, native guerrillas are reported to have captured3 villages S.W. of Kieta.AIR SITUATION.South-East Asia.19. In the week ended dusk on the 9th, Allied aircraft flew 805 sorties. Inaddition, Dakota transport aircraft flew 1,896 sorties, carrying 3,948 tons and1,049 men, while light transport aircraft flew 154 sorties.   One aircraft is missing.The Tactical Air Force attacked enemy targets in South Burma, includingcommunications, troop concentrations and gun positions. Nine Liberators laidsea-mines and attacked shipping in the Gulf of Siam; several coasters were sunk or damaged.China,20. Small forces of Liberators bombed targets in the Canton area, including two armament plants.Japan.21. On two nights of the week, a total of 1,050 Super Fortresses (2 missing)bombed 5 urban areas and an oil refinery in Honshu and 3 urban areas in Shikoku,dropping 7,143 tons of bombs with good results. According to preliminary reports,4 other urban areas and another oil refinery in Honshu were bombed later inthe week by about 500 Super Fortresses and observed results were good. In allthese attacks, fighter opposition was slight and A.A. fire moderate.Mustangs carried out successful sweeps over the western and southern coastsof Kyushu; 7 enemy aircraft were destroyed.Pacific.22. In Formosa, attacks were made by a total of 364 Liberators and 49Mitchells on a variety of targets, including 9 airfields and an alcohol factory.Targets on Mako Island (Pescadores) and on Koto Island (off the S.E. coast of formosa) were bombed by 16 Liberators and 34 Mitchells respectively.In the Philippines, Allied aircraft, mainly fighter-bombers, flew nearly 1,000sorties in support of troops on Luzon and Mindanao.In the Balikpapan area of Borneo, Liberators and Mitchells providedsupport for land operations, dropping 330 tons of bombs; heavy damage wasinflicted on troop concentrations, stores and equipment. Support was also givento troops in North-West Borneo. Airfields in the north-western and southernparts of the island and shipyards at Samarinda (N. of Balikpapan) were success-fully attacked by small forces of Liberators. In anti-shipping operations,6 coasters were sunk and 12 others were damaged or set on fire.Airfields and other targets in the Celebes and in Java were attacked by liberators and Catalinas, which flew 90 sorties. Off the coasts, at least5 schooners were sunk or damaged.
APPENDIX V.Casualties to H.M. and Allied Auxiliary vessels and to Naval Personnel.8th July. French A/S trawler La Nantaise sunk in collision in the Straitof Dover; 14 survivors, 11 missing.10th July. M/S trawler Kurd mined and sunk off the Lizard; 11 survivors.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 10 killed.Ratings : 24 killed.APPENDIX YI.Imports under Departmental Programmes.(Thousand tons.)--	Non-Tanker Imports.^1)			Tanker Imports. (*)	Ministry of Food.	Ministry of Supply.	Total.(2)	1945-January February March ... April May     ............ Total, January to May(4) ... June (estimated)   ...	801 805 938 874 998	900 877 922 911 982	1,841 1,830 2,013 1,926 2,130	1,480 1,097 1,544 1,598 2,109	4,398(6)	4,574(&quot;)     ;       9,705		7,788(&apos;)	1,357	1,190               2,667 i		2,104(l) Excluding imports from Eire. The monthly figures of imports given in this table representthe estimated weights of the commodities included in the Trade and Navigation accounts for each month and are unadjusted for small revisions subsequently made in the cumulative totals given in the accounts for later months.(&apos;) Including munitions and miscellaneous imports under the Ministry of production programme, and imports of munitions on Canadian Government account.(&quot;) Petroleum products, molasses, unrefined whale oil, industrial alcohol and acetone.&apos;*) Adjusted for revisions.(6) Excluding about 95,000 tons of cereals and oilseeds under the Ministry of Food programme shipped direct to Europe, but including about 29,000 tons of foodstuffs destined for continental relief which have been brought temporarily to this country.(*) Including about 7,200 tons of timber as a replacement of supplies handed over.to the UnitedStates Army.(&apos;) Excluding about 760,000 tons shipped direct to Europe.In the Wewak and Manokwari areas of New Guinea, Beauforts and Kitty-hawks flew 270 sorties against troop concentrations and other targets; in Bougain-ville, Corsairs flew 460 sorties in support of land operations; and in New Britainand New Ireland Mitchells and Corsairs flew 260 sorties against a variety of targets, mainly in the Rabaul and Kavieng areas.




</content>
</cab>
