<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/31/8 images: 100-105</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MOST SECRET -EG MAJESTY&apos;S, GOVE^ :i^-^iJ.!Zn:i-AJVK. A NO KEY;&apos;:is requested thaupedal cut e may be taken to insure the secrecy of this document.* - -  -COPY NO o.W,Mc(48) 96th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 4.QConfidential Annex.(27th July, 1942, 5830 psm,)SUPPLIES TO RUSSIA.(previous reference:WqM.(42) 95thConclusions^Minute 2.)THE FIRST SEA LORD   said that the position regarding convoy P.Q.17 was as follows:-10 ships had reached Archangel.1 was still on the way01 was unaccounted for.21 had been sunk.If the ship still in passage reached portsafely, the convoy would have delivered to Russia164 tanks, 896 vehicles of various kinds, 87   &apos;aircraft, in addition to general cargoes ofconsiderable size.THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out thatpractically one-third of the convoy had reachedArchangelo     This was better than we had atone time expected.     There was much to be said forattempting to run a further convoy to North russian September.     By that time, the Germans mighthave withdrawn their naval forces from North Norway.There would be great political advantage if wecould tell the Russians that this was our p lan.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRSstrongly favoured the despatch of a convoy inSeptember*THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said thata number of loaded ships were being held up in iceland.     The crews of these ships were givingtrouble, and the position would certainly deteriorateif they were left there until September.   It was forconsideration whether the ships should not bebrought to this country.THE PRIME MINISTER said that 6$ Vf themerchant seamen in Convoy PoQ.17 had lost their lives.     The remainder were in North Russia, and,after what they had gone through, it seemed unfair to call.upon them to make the return journey until there was more darkness in Northern waters.m
N
. &apos; The suggestion was made that it might bedesirable to ifly out to North Russia one or twodelegates of the Seamen^ Union?The War Cabinet:-(1) Invited the First. Lord of the Admiralty,- in consultation with the Secretary o  Stfor Air, to consider whether arrahgemehtscould be made for a convoy to sailto North Russia in September:(2) Asked the Allied Supplies Executive toconsider what action should be taken asregards -(a) the loaded ships now being held upin Iceland;   and(b) the crews of the vessels of &quot;P.Q.17now in North Russia,Great George Street, .S.*W*1*\
\



</content>
</cab>
