<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/6/6 images: 74-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1940.SECRET. CoPy No*W.P. (G.) (SO) 106.April 15, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.TRADE  NEGOTIATIONS  WITH  THE   SOVIET   GOVERNMENT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.MY colleagues will remember that the War Cabinet decided on the29th March that I should explore the possibility of resuming trade negotiationswith the Soviet Government on the lines which I described to the Cabinet. I now circulate a memorandum, which has been drafted in consultation with the Boardof Trade and the Ministry of Economic Warfare, and which I would proposeto hand to the Soviet Ambassador in reply to his memorandum of the 27th March.I consider it desirable for political reasons that His Majesty&apos;s Government should,in present circumstances show their willingness to respond to the advance madeby the Soviet Government and to discuss trade matters with the latter, eventhough I realise that these discussions may not have very satisfactory results.H..April 15, 1940.Memorandum.His Majesty&apos;s Government have had under consideration the suggestionrecently put forward by the Soviet Government that trade negotiations might be resumed between Great Britain and the Soviet Union.It will be realised that at the present time it is of paramount importance for His Majesty&apos;s Government so to adapt their economic policy as best to furthertheir war effort. Any trade agreement concluded with a neutral government therefore must be related to present war conditions. In particular, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would wish to be reassured as to the amount of Soviet goods goingto Germany and as to the destination of goods imported into the Soviet Unionfrom abroad i.e., that these were not destined for Germany, but for use in theUnion itself.His Majesty&apos;s Government would be glad to learn what concrete proposalsfor a trade agreement the Soviet Government would be prepared to make, havingregard to the foregoing considerations.10985   [21151]


</content>
</cab>
