<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/224/0 images: 5-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(TEIS. DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT).CABINET.BLCRLT. ,C.P. 2bfc( 31 ) . LONDON PASSENG^ TRANSPORT DILL. Copy No.ftMemorandum &quot;by, the Minister of. Trar.sport.I find it necessary to consult my colleagues on animportant question which has arisen in connection with the London Passenger Transport Bill and the financing of the expenditure of the Underground Group.The settlement with the Underground group provides for the acquisition of their undertakings by an exchange of stocks and the Bill fixes the amounts of the Board&apos;s stock to be issued in exchange for the existing stocks of the Companies.      At the time the agreement was made it was anticipated that the Bill would pass into law during this year ana that the Underground undertakings would become the property of the Board on the 1st January next.     No provision was therefore made to cover additional capital issues by the Companies before the transfer.In July last the Companies stated that further borrowings would be necessary to the extent of nearly  2 millions to finance expenditure to be incurred by the London General Omnibus Company, the District Railway and the tramway companies up to the end of 1931 *      They then agreed that it was inadvisable to make further capital issued before the passing of the Bill and a scheme of temporary financing was approved by the late Minister of Transport.In the middle of October, however, Lord Ashfield, after consulting his bankers, intimated to me that owing to the change in the financial situation and uncertainty as to the passage of the Bill it might no longer be possible, consistently with the interests of his shareholders, to finance the expenditure to which the Companies are already committed without a new capital issue at a very early date, as it would be unsound in present circumstances to incur
liabilities in the shape of temporary borrowings from the banks, He therefore desired to be in a position, if a favourable opportunity offers, to Issue new stock for part at least of the sura required in the immediate future.&apos;Before any such issue could be made, it is necessary to determine the amount and anture of the stock of the new Board which would, in the event of the London Passenger Transport Bill becoming law, be issued in substitution for the new stock of the companies.In discussion with Lord Ashfield,  it appeared that only in the case of the London General Omnibus Company, whose capital account, is already heavily overspent, will any new capital issue be required this year and that an issue of  500,000 will meet their requirements up to January next.    He, therefore proposes that the London General Omnibus Company should, If practicable, issue  500,000 b% cumulative income debenture stock and that the Government should undertake to amend the Bill so as to increase the amount of the Board&apos;s stock to be issued as consideration for the transfer of the Company1s undertaking by a corresponding amount of &quot;B&quot; transport stock, which -will beissued in exchange for the existing 5% debentures of the Company under the terms of the Bill.   The &quot;B&quot; stock carries trustee status.    The railway expenditure of the group can be met for the present from the proceeds of the debenture stock issued by the London Electric Railway Company in 1930.The London General Omnibus Company have been financing a large programme of replacement of their fleet, extensions of garages, etc., out of their reserves and current revenues, but have now exhausted these resources and borrowing is necessary to liquidate some part of the funds locked up in the business. It was originally contemplated that the Transport Board would either meet this expenditure itself or take over the debt
incurred on it by the Company.      If Lord Ashfield&apos;s present proposal is agreed to the Board will to that extent be relieved of tho necessity of finding cash and issue a correspondingly greater amount of stock as consideration for the transfer of the undertaking.      Provided that the Company can raise the money on terms not materially less favourable than those on which the Board could have raised it, the latter would not be prejudiced and may even benefit by being relieved of the necessity for going on the market for fresh capital at the outset.It will be appreciated that under existing circumstances neither the Company nor, if it were in existence, the Board could expect to issue even prior charge stock except at a substantial discount and it is doubtful if the Board could, until, it has had an opportunity of realising economies and establishing its credit, raise money on appreciably better terms than the Company could do.If the Board required to raise new capital for its omnibus business it would, under the terms of the Bill, unless the Minister with the approval of the Treasury otherwise consented, have to raise at least one-third of the amount by &quot;C&quot; stock, which is not a trustee security and is being issued generally in exchange for the existing equity stocks.      It is, however, doubtful whether at the outset the Board would raise any considerable proportion of its requirements by &quot;C&quot; stock.The other parties which would be affected by Lord Ashfield&apos;s proposal are the Metropolitan Railway and Messrs. Tillings, both of whan are to be paid a substantial part of the consideration for the transfer of their undertakings in &quot;C&quot; stock.      Theso parties, with whom no agreement as to the amount of the consideration has been reached, may allege that an increase in the amount of &quot;B&quot; stock to be issued to the Underground group will tend to depress the &quot;C&quot; stock which they will have to take in part payment.    A sufficient answer is contained in the directions given to the Arbitration Tribunal in Clause 14 of the
1tl- J+ -Bill to avard a consideration equivalent to the value of theundertaking concerned, and to secure that the standard of consideration is fair and equitable as between the variousundertakings, including the Underground group.     Had theadditional capital been raised by the London General OmnibusCompany prior to the settlement, as it might well have been, theconsideration of the London General Omnibus Company under theorigins! agreement would have been increased in the manner nowproposed.      The amendment of the terns can therefore fairly berepresented as a natural and unavoidable result of the delay Inthe passing of the Bill and as not involving any weakening ofthe financial structure of the Board.     uir William McLintockhas fully considered the circumstances of the case and, assuming that the advice Lord Ashfield has received as regards the futuretrend of money market conditions is sound, he advises as follows:(i)    That he is satisfied that, in order to fulfil itscommitments and carry out its normal programme of replacements, the London General Omnibus Company will require to raise the proposed  500,000 in the near future and Lord Ashfleld&apos;s proposal to raise the money by the issue of Debentures is a sound and proper one; ---------(ii)    that the new stock can only be issued if an undertaking is given by the Government to amend the Bill so as to provide for the issue by the Board of transport stock in exchange;(iii)    that, If the London General Omnibus Company make a further issue of       income debenture stock as proposed, an exchange of a corresponding nominal amount of % &quot;3&quot; transport stock would be a proper arrangement, this being the rate of exchange already agreed In respect of the existing 5   income debentures of the Company;(iv)    that, in his opinion, the proposed issue of debenture stock by the London General Omnibus Company on reasonable terms In lieu of temporarily borrowing the required amount should not materially affect the financial position or the prospects of the Board.It should be added that In the event of it being necessary to postpone the date of transfer of the London GeneralOmnibus Company undertaking to the Board from the 1st January
next to the 1st April the Company might find it necessary to raise a further  250,000 to  350,000 and if the appointed day were further deferred until, say, the 1st July, the total amount which would require to be raised is estimated by the Company at about  1,000,000.I accordingly seek authority to inform Lord Ashfield that the Government will do its best to secure amendment of the Bill, if it is proceeded with,  so as to provide for the issue oftransport &quot;3&quot; stock up to the nominal amount of  500,000 ini------- .&apos; ,r:;;&apos;,.m.........exchange for the additional omnibus debenture stock to be issued under his proposal, provided that the terms upon which the stockis to be issued are approved by the Minister after consultationwith the Treasury and Sir Villiam MoLintock.The question well illustrates the position which, as Iinformed the Cabinet last month, was bound to arise as a result   ;lof the delay in passing the Bill.      It would, however, be1unreasonable to leave important commercial interests, who have     to take day-to-day decisions vitally affecting the interests of     IItheir shareholders, in a state of uncertainty longer than isIinevitable.      It must also be embarrassing to the Governmenti Ito have to be parties to decisions taken by the companies with respect to their financial or cc-Eiaercial operations, though itfis obvious that the Government must be consulted in matters which I1may affect and even prejudice the contemplated Board.     I hope,i therefore, that the Cabinet will give authority to put down at an early date the necessary motion in the name of a ilinister of the Crown to enable consideration of the Bill to be resumed^The &quot;appointed day&quot; for the transfer of the principal undertakings was fixed originally to take place on the    1st of January next and if adherence to that date were possible v/e could avoid some difficult queations which will otherwise arise.   I
The Cabinet may, therefore, wish to consider the desirability of making p^^ogress with the Bill before Christmas if that course is compatible with the general arrangements and time-table of the Government.(Intd,)    P,J,P.50th October, l?^lo

</content>
</cab>
