<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/224/0 images: 11-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)SECRET .CP.  267 (31) . COPY NO,CABINET.COMMITTEE ON THE KING&apos;S SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF PARLIAMENT.REPORT.1. At their meeting on October 29th,  1931 (Cabinet72 (31) Conclusion 3)  the Cabinet agreed that a Committee composed of -The Lord Chancellor The Home Secretary and The Minister of health should meet -(a) to prepare a first draft cf the King&apos;s Speech on the lines indicated at the meeting, for consideration by the Cabinet;    and(b) to make suggestions as to the Mover and Seconder of the Address, both in the House of Lords and in the House of Commons.2. The Committee submit for the consideration of theCabinet the draft of the King&apos;s Speech on the opening ofParliament set out in the   Appendix hereto.    special attention is directed to the paragraph in square brackets onpage 3 of the draft relative to a proposal of the canadian government that the Economic Conference should be convenedat Ottawa as soon as possible.      The Secretary of State forDominion Affairs has circulated a Memorandum (Paper CP.268 (31))  on this question,  to the Cabinet.
3, The Committee suggest that the Mover andSeconder of the Address in the House of Lords should he th^Ea^^oj^^ and thatthe Mover and Seconder of the Address in the House of Commons should he Mr. Geoffrey Lloyd and a member of the National Labour party to be nominated by the Prime Minister.Signed of behalf of the Committe SANKEY Chairman.V^hitehall Gardens, S.TV.1. 2nd November, 1931.  &apos;
I/ftAPPENDIX.DRAFT OF THE. KING&apos;8 SPEECH ON THE OSENING OF PARLIAMENT,  NOVEMBER 10th,  1951,(as approved by the Cabinet Committee for submission to theCabinet)MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS:My relations with foreign Poworn continue to befriendly.My Government will pursue the policy of promoting peace and good-will and will continue their active interest in the work of the League of Nations.    Particularly, they are giving close attention tc the preparations for the approaching Disarmament Conference, the successful result of which would, I am convinced, produce great and universal benefit.serious financial and economic situation of the ^orld^^^1&quot;-^ They will do their utmost in co-operation with other Governments, and in the spirit of mutual helpfulness, to find ways for restoring the volume cf international trade.The Indian Round Table Conference continues its deliberations and a Conference with Representatives of Burma will very shortly assemble.    It is My earnest prayer that saxzQ&amp;s&amp;^s&amp;S&amp;^PQ^^In conformity with the undertaking given to the Rep-representatives of My Dominions in 1930, a measure will,be: laid before you to give statutory effect to certain of the Declarations and Resolutions of the. Imperial Conferences of 1926 and 1930.    This measure is deaigned to make   -
clear the powers of Dominion Parliaments and to promote the spirit of free cO-co-operation amongst Members of the British Commonwealth of Nationa. MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS:The Estimates for the public services will be laid before you in due course. MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS:The Nation has recently endorsed those measures for securing economy and balancing the National Budget which constituted the first essential steps in the solution of the financial and e economic problems with which the country &apos;Sinr!H^ confronted.-   JIt wilKjfc&amp;at ti,e.....neces.sarv^o.,.tai^e. further - measuresto secure QamsmBSgLe, financial; stability and to avoid any recurrence of recent troubles.Tc^H^feafflid My Ministers.. invited; the Nation to empower them to adopt a policy which will isoSSSjr re-establish confidence in/ st-e-**4ingA     They also asked for authority to frame plans for ensuring a favourable balance of trade. In this connection, they indicated their view that mutual economic arrangements with the Dominions should be the subject of the fullest and moot
careful consideration.They,  thereforinvited the Nation to give themunfettered discretion to consider every proposal likelyto he of assistance in these matters.My Ministers have now received from the Nationa clear and emphatic Mandate to that effect../&quot;My Government have, received from the Governmentof lily Dominion of Canada, a proposal that the Economic\     Conference,which was adjourned in 1930, should he convenedat Qttajaja as soon as possible.    This invitation will&apos; &quot;beex-atsiiftedJby My MinisterMin the most sympathetic spiritf-a.nd-wi-th..^an ..eanne;.it,.des-ii*e to come to some mutually advantageous arrangement with the Governments of My Dominions*/These important problems are already under detailed examination by My Government.     Decisions will be taken and applied with the least possible delay, and in d-gre course any legislation that may be required will be submitted to parliament.And I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rent upon your deliberations.2nd November,   1931.t-3t

</content>
</cab>
