<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/224/0 images: 321-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mMIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT). B C R E  T.I circulate for the information of my colleagues the attached records of my conversations on November 17th,  in Paris with M. Laval,   the French Prime Minister, and Herr von Bulow, the Permanent Under Secretary of State at the German Foreign Office.P, 886(51).CABINET.REPARATIONS, WAR DEBTS AND COMMERCIAL DEBTS.Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign(intld.)    J.S.Foreign Office, S.V,1, , November 19th, 1931.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.GERMANY. November 18, 1931.CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1.[C 8568/172/62] No. 1.Sir John Simon to Sir R. Vansittart. (Received November 18.) (No. 139.)SIR JOHN SIMON at Paris presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit to him a memorandum recording an interview with M. Laval.British Delegation,Paris, November 17, 1931.Enclosure in No. 1.Record of an Interview between Sir John Simon and M. Laval,November 17, 1931.THIS morning I paid a visit to the French Premier for the purpose of making his acquaintance and laying the foundation for our future relations.M. Laval spoke very freely to me in the course of nearly an hour&apos;s interview. He impressed me strongly as a man of directness and solidity of mind, with whom it was possible to pursue a subject consecutively in a way which Englishmen understand.He began by referring to our recent elections, and expressed warm admiration for the courage of Mr. MacDonald, emphasising that the Prime Minister had, notwithstanding all his relations with the international Socialist movement, put country before party and shown great boldness in the action he had taken in the present difficult situation in England.M. Laval then opened out on the general subject of the European financial situation. I made it clear that, so far as I was concerned, our conversation was of a preliminary character, as I was returning to London on Thursday, and that I appreciated the opportunity of being able to place the British Government in possession of the views of M. Laval, so that if I returned to Paris we could resume the subject.M. Laval then proceeded to give an account of his visit to Washington, and he expounded the communique which had been issued as the result of his con-versations with President Hoover. He emphasised that, while they had not attempted to define the terms and conditions of the new arrangement, it was understood that this arrangement would apply only during the period of depression. Then it was announced that the initiative should be taken by the European Powers and this really meant Germany that was why on his return to Paris he had at once sent for the German Ambassador and proposed that the German Government should as soon as possible take the initiative in asking for the special consultative committee to be set up. I said that I understood that the position was that Germany would ask the experts to subject to a new examination the capacity of Germany to pay, and that M. Laval would note that His Majesty&apos;s Government had hitherto left the negotiations on this point of procedure entirely in the hands of the French and German Governments and had not made any effort to intervene. M. Laval expressed his thanks for this attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government. His only object in the conversations which had been proceeding was to induce Germany to take the initiative for a fresh examination. Germany had been anxious to give to the experts&apos; committee a wider mandate than that provided for in the Young plan so that the private debts of G ermany could be definitely included in the terms of reference. To that M. Laval said the French Government were unable to agree. A full examination, in his view, was, in fact, provided for by article 120 of the Yroung plan, so that the point was really covered. At the same time he emphasised that the experts [302 s-1]
were bound to regard themselves as within the framework of the Young plan. He believed that the question of short-term credits might be examined simultaneously between the bankers interested and their German debtors. When the experts&apos; committee had made their report, there would naturally be a conference of Governments that was the moment when they would have to envisage all the measures of adaptation for Germany in respect of the payment of reparations and of short-term debts. I emphasised the importance which British opinion attached to taking into full account the commercial obligations of Germany, and asked whether I rightly understood that what he said amounted to this : that, while the French Government could not agree to the experts being specifically empowered to consider the position as regards short-term debts, they would yet, in his view, be enabled by the terms of reference under article 120 to consider the capacity of payment by Germany.During the interview M. Laval communicated by telephone with M. Flandin and afterwards dictated textually a short explanation of the situation the effect of which is reproduced above.In the. course of the interview M. Laval, referring to the American attitude, said that the position was that President Hoover would make his contribution as regards debts, while France would make hers under the head of reparations should that be found to be necessary.I enquired what was M. Laval&apos;s idea as to the date of the summoning of the conference. He said that as regards France he would try to answer the question although he would be a little premature. The 7th December was the date when President Hoover might be expected to seek the approval of Congress, and M. Laval hoped that the conference of Governments could be summoned between that date and the end of the year. The French Government wished to neglect nothing which would prevent the collapse of Germany. The first countries to be affected would be Great Britain and America, but the repercussions on France could not be long delayed. I observed that time was short and that it was of absolutely vital importance that the demands to be made on Germany should not press too heavily upon her, since if there were any failure on the part of Germany to pay her private and commercial debts, that would, in its turn, react on any payments of reparations which might have been agreed to.M. Laval said that while France in the recent negotiations in connexion with the Hoover moratorium had reserved her position as regards unconditional reparations, she had agreed that money transferred on account of reparations should be re-lent to the railways. France was very touchy on the matter of the connexion of reparations and short-term credits. He had insisted on the priority of the annuities, and he must be very careful in this respect. He suggested that if the Experts Committee were to decide that certain of the reparations could be paid, France might assist by a portion being placed at the disposal of the Bank for International Settlements for re-lending to German municipalities and others in order thereby to assist them in meeting short-term debts, and that thereby the position of the short-term creditors could be eased, namely, the British and American bankers. On such a plan he thought that French public opinion could be brought to agree. M. Laval emphasised once again that he must be very strict as regards the Young plan, since were he to agree to allow the experts to go beyond the provisions of that instrument, he would immediately lose all his influence.M. Laval said that while the past was past, and he did not wish to level any reproach against the bankers, he did still suggest that they had been over lavish in their method of lending to Germany and that even Chancellor Briining had admitted that this was the case. He added that he was to be called upon to make a speech in the Chamber either to-night or to-morrow, and he sent for his notes of his speech, a large portion of which he read over to me. He explained that it was necessary for him to appear very stiff as regards Germany to meet the requirements of the situation in the French Chamber. The extracts he read to me included a stern reference to the spendthrift expenditure of Germany in various fields of her economic life during the past few years, but emphasised the desire of France to assist in finding a solution.M. Laval said, that His Maiesty&apos;s Government might rest assured that the French Government would exert their every effort for a complete examination of the position before the end of the year so that the conference might be held, and he hoped it would result in placing Germany on her feet.
I told him that I was likely to see Herr von Btilow later in the day and asked if he had any suggestion to make in that connexion. He replied that he would be grateful for anything which I could do to assist in a conclusion being reached as regards the application of Germany for the appointment of the experts committee. He was under the impression that a formula should be found within forty-eight hours. Chancellor Bruning had been correctitude itself throughout the whole affair. The draft letter first proposed was unacceptable to the French Government, but he (M. Laval) had agreed that no reply should be returned in the hope that a formula might be agreed between the two Governments for the invitation to be issued by the German Government in terms which would involve no reply from France. I understood him to say that it had been agreed that if any point of difficulty about the terms of the letter was outstanding, he, M. Laval, should act as arbitrator presumably between M. Flandin and the German Ambassador.In view of what had been said, I reverted to the question of Germany&apos;s private debts and said that M. Laval would appreciate the strength of public opinion in England as to the necessity of this being provided for. The British people had made an immense effort to restore stability to the   and this was of great importance to others besides ourselves. It followed that any failure in respect of Germany&apos;s obligations to British creditors would only tend to undo the good that had been done by weakening our own financial position.I thanked M. Laval for the very full and frank exposition which he had given and said I should be glad to report what he had said to the Prime Minister and my colleagues, and that if I had to return to Paris in connexion with the League of Nations I should be glad to see M. Laval again. He said he would be at my disposal at any time to do anything in complete agreement with His Majesty&apos;s Government and observed that as regards His Ma.jesty&apos;s Government, France had no precautions to take of any kind, although in the case of Germany the position was slightly different. He was, in particular, pleased to feel that there was a really strong Government in England with which the French Government had to deal.Throughout the interview I was careful to say nothing which would in any way commit His Majesty&apos;s Government, but, as I have said above, I stressed strongly the urgencj&apos;&apos; of getting the experts committee appointed and of securing an examination over the whole field.I asked whether his idea was that the committee should be composed of the same experts as before. He replied that that depended on the choice of the nominators.   France wanted a member from Yugoslavia.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOYERNMENTc- ---------GERMANY. November 18, 1931.CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2.[C 8569/172/62] No. 1.Sir John Simon to Sir R. Vansittart. (Received November 18.) (No. 140.)SIR JOHN SIMON, at Paris, presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the (honour to transmit to him a memorandum recording an interview with Herr von Bulow.British Delegation,Paris, November 17, 1931.Enclosure in No. 1Record of Conversation between Sir John Simon and Plerr von BulowNovember 17, 1931.THIS afternoon Herr von Buiow, the Permanent Under-Secretary of State of the German Foreign Office, called to see me. He is in Paris ostensibly in connexion with the meeting of the Council of the League of Nations on the Manchurian affair, but is spending nearly all his time on the Franco-German negotiation for the application about to be made by Germany to the Bank of International Settlements for the setting up of the special advisory committee. He mentioned a number of interesting points, some of which may add to previous information. He said that he expected that the proposed letter of application would be settled and delivered on Thursday or Friday this Aveek. M. Flandin had been very difficult to satisfy on a number of points, but anything now outstanding was not very important. According to the present draft, there would be no reference to short-term credits save in a concluding paragraph, which it was intended should say that the committee would have to bear the situation which these created in mind. The earlier part of the latter would include a recital of the whole series of temporary arrangements that had to be made. The application for the appointment of a committee would, of course, be made under the second alternative in article 119 of the Young plan. The difficulty was to agree to the phraseology under article 120, Avhicn, while it would satisfy the French as being &quot; within the framework&quot; of the plan, at the same time was sufficiently wide to include the examination of what really mattered. A strict limitation to the conditional annuities (compare article 135) would be useless. I mentioned M. Laval&apos;s observation to me in the morning that he might have to arbitrate before the final terms were settled. Herr von Bulow smiled and conveyed that Flandin in such a case would get his way.Herr von Bulow scouted the idea that there could be any funding of the short-term credits, or that there could be advances from the Bank of International Settlements to municipalities, &amp;c. (see my note of my interview with M Laval). He observed that if Germany&apos;s credit justified it many of her short-term creditors would wish to renew their credits; in other cases they might agree to become participants in the concerns they had helped to finance.I asked him when he thought the conference which would follow the report of the committee might be expected to take place. He said that, (however quickly the committee got to work, the report could not be available before a date some way on in December, and that he thought it would be undesirable for the conference to meet for a few days before Christmas and then adjourn, since a break of that sort led to a hardening of opinion. He had asked M. Laval where he thought it would be convenient for the conference to meet, and gathered that the French Government favoured French soil, but outside Paris. M. Flandin had suggested Cannes, but he thought this rather inaccessible.    There were[302 s-2]
objections to Belgium or Holland, and he wondered whether there was any place in. Northern France sufficiently well provided with hotels. For himself, he would have thought Baden-Baden, or one of the Rhine towns, as a good suggestion. It would be a long business, and Ministers of State could not be away from their offices continuously. ......As to the personnel of the advisory committee, he expressed the strongest admiration for Sir &quot;Walter Layton&apos;s work. He knew all about it, and knew how to express the conclusions. It would save a great deal of time if he served again. As for Mr. Wiggins, he pointed out to me that article 129 of the Young plan says that the United States nominee should be ordinarily resident in Europe or in a position to be in prompt attendance in the event of a committee being called. As far as he knew, Mr. Wiggins has as yet made no move to cross the Atlantic. He confirmed what M. Laval had told me, that the French wanted a Yugoslav on the body. I observed that on this matter of procedure, which was now under discussion between France and Germany, the British Government had not yet intervened, and I called attention to Mr. Baldwin&apos;s speech. He said that the German Government appreciated our action in the matter and were grateful for our reserve.

</content>
</cab>
