<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/59/0 images: 136-138</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tjhen the Ministry of Health BUI was last considered&quot;by the Home Affairs Committee % undertook to circulate a note with regard to the prcpeoel to provide 1a the Bill for the constitution of a Consultative Coiamitteo, and the Secretary for Scotland and the President of the Board of Education promised to supply me with information as to Advisory Committees of whioh they had experience.Of the two examples supplied by the Secretary for Scotland the first is that of an Advisory Committee on Agricultural Questions.   Thie body Is not appointed by Statute and le a perfectly legitisu is example of an Advisory Cowmittee con fisting of persons possessing spatial experience to advise On questions in which that experience is especially valuable 1The second example la muoh nearer the Consultative Council under the Ministry of Health Bill.   It is baaed upon section 4 of the Board of Education Act, 1690*  The Scottish Advisory Council is ts consist, to the extant of not lass than two-thirds, of representatives of bodies interested in education.   It la appointed for the purpose of advising the  Scottish $due at ion Bepartment on matters referred to it by the Department.   So far the elaues follows the precedent of the Act of 189ft1 but it goes on to say *The pepartment shall take into e$nsideration any advice or representation submitted to than by the Advisory Council&quot;.   X am not sure of the exact significance of these words but they seam to m to contain elements of danger if they are to be oonstrued as giving to the Advisory Council the power of initiating proposals and submitting them for the consideration of the $apartment*   Given a reasonable Council there would be no difficulty created by the words, out if the Council wished to raise difficulty and press a particular policy they could no doubt force any sort of proposals upon the Department end create trouble if they were negatived.8*  Bftfc&amp; ft Other examples of Consultative end Advisory CocDittees are those appointed under the Board of  duoat1en * the nearest example to that now under consideration is that of the Consultative Committee under Section 4 of the Board of Education Act. 1690, referred to in the preceding p*re* graph.  This ie a Standing Committee, the members of whioh ere appointed for six years and then retire unless re-appointed*   Xte duty (apart from the framing of Regulations for a register of teachers, whioh was referred to in the Section) is to advise the Board of Education on matters referred to it by the Board.   Mine references have been made to the Committee up to the present time and after prolonged consideration reports have been made by the Committee whioh have been useful in paving the way for action by the Department although action cannot always be taken at once.
Other Advisory Committees under the Board of Education are -(a) The Victoria and Albert Museum Advisory Counoil,(b) The Science Museum Advisory Council,(c) The Standing Committee of Advioe for Educationin Art,, W   The Advisory Gommittee on the dlBtrlbuticn of&apos;:i&apos; Exchequer Grants toi Universities and&apos; University Collegea,W   The Secondary School Examination Council,1 I understand that these are not Statutory bodies.Statutory authority is not in the least required for the appointment of an Advisory Committee.   All that la needed is the authority of the Treasury to the defraying of any necssBary expenditure incurred by the Committee.   In the main the advantage of an Advisory Committee is to give advice upon a particular subject which requires a certain amount of expaxt knowledge whioh the Committee may be expected to supply.   Where the jurisdiction of the Department is limited to a single subjeot, such as education, even though that subjeot is a wide one, there is some reason for having an Advisory Committee cf educationalists to oon aider and report upon particular problems that may arise fcr solution.   Where, however, a Department deals with a range of subjeotb bo wide as that which will lie before a Minister of Health and Local Government, the Advisory Committee would seem to be much less useful.   The problems that would have to be solved will be of very varied character, some of them of a medical or scientific kind, others adminiatra-tlye, others financial.   It would be far better to refer these subjects to Committees specially chosen for the purpose than to a&quot;m,ixed body of doctors, insurance experts, local government representatives, and so on.     In my view the existence of a Standing Consultative Council would tend to restrict the Minister&apos;s freedom of choice in the selection of the personnel bp&apos;expert Committees which he might from time to time desire to appoint to advise him on specific questions.The Insurance Commission have had some experience of a i&amp;ixed Advisory Committee of stuaewhat the same character appointed under Section 58 of the National Insurance Act, 1911, JChia was an Advisory Committee &quot;for the purpoee of giving the &quot;insurance Commissioners advice and assistance in connection&quot;with the making and altering of Regulations......of duly&quot;qualified medical practitioners ...... and of such other&quot;persons as the Commissioners may appoint of whom two at least &quot;shall be women&quot;. It is to bo noted that the Bill proposes to repeal that Section and do away with the Advisory Committee,The precedents of the Board of Education Aot, 1899, or.of the Scottish Education Bill now before Parliament do not seem to be at all conclusive evidence of the necessity or advantage of appointing a statutory Consultative Council.   If, however, it is decided that it is necessary to insert in the Bill any provision on this subject, I think the terms of the *lause should be -
8&quot;It $hall be lawful far tin KtnUttl [by OrdtrJ to ftetatoltb mi AAfltory tContultaUTt] OHVftittf [Cot^oU] Uv iuMaing him en any *MUr relating %t pubiie health which he may think fit tp rtCer t* t.na,*17. H4VS0 1X00*Local Go moment Board. Whitehall. fitwa.ann mrt -me.

</content>
</cab>
