<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/59/0 images: 254-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A C \jM     \)$f ItifEhiB Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government]CONFIDENTIAL, Political Intelligence Department,&quot;TiTT^no ima-T&quot; FOREIGN OFFICE.[July 23, 1918.]Bulgaria /001.MEMORANDUMON     -THE CHANGE OF GOVERNMENT IN BULGARIA.THE change of Government in Bulgaria was not only natural, but inevitable, and has been recognised as imminent for some time.&apos;:!:&apos; The only question has always been, what was the most favourable moment lor the change from the point of view of Bulgarian policy ? To make this clear it is necessary to recall the constitution of parties in the present Sabrauiye and their relations to the only real political force in Bulgaria, Tsar Ferdinand.Parties in the Sabraniye.Ferdinand during his thirty-three years&apos; rule over Bulgaria has learnt to perfection the art of manipulating all parties and politicians just as he likes.* He is aided in this by the fact that most of the so-called &quot; parties&quot; with the exception of certain groups, to be discussed later are merely cliques bound together by common interests, and hardly distinguished from one another by any real difference of political principle. The disasters brought on the country by its treacherous policy during the Balkan wars of 1912-13 were astutely laid by Ferdinand to the account of Messrs. Geshov and Danev, his successive Prime Ministers, who have since then been at his mercy. Bulgaria&apos;s defeat at the hands of Serbia and Greece was followed by the dismissal of Danev, and on 17 July, 1913, Ferdinand called to power the veteran leader of the so-called National Liberals, Racloslavov, whose long political career had been distin-guished by neither honesty nor ability. At his Tsar&apos;s orders Radoslavov signed the Treaty of Bucarest of August 1913, and promptly set himself the task of intriguing for its undoing. The elections for the new Sabraniye only took place seven months later (March 1914), and Ferdinand secured for his obsequious Premier a majority sufficient to enable him to carry on the Government of the country, but not sufficient for him to presume on his strength. The recent introduction of proportional representa-tion further made a completely Ministerial Sabraniye, like that controlled by the Malinov Government of 1908-11, out of the question.Radoslavov s Supporters. .Radoslavov&apos;s own- party, the National Liberals, had in the new Sabraniye a strength of 93 deputies out of a total of 243. To provide him with the necessary majority Ferdinand negotiated a reconciliation between Radoslavov and the notoriously corrupt leader of the Young Liberal party, Tonchev, who in return for the support of his party (10 deputies) obtained the post of Minister of Finance for himself in the new Cabinet, and that of Minister of Commerce for his supporter, Bakalov. Even this was not sufficient for a majority, and the Stambolovist party (26 deputies) most opportunist of all Bulgarian parties were therefore won over by the offer of three portfolios  Foreign Affairs, Railways, and Public Works-to Genadiyev, his friend Apostolov, and Dobri Petkov respectively. Armed with a total strength of 129 out of 243 deputies, Radoslavov felt he could defy all criticism.The Opposition.As against him was a large minority of Opposition deputies, numbering altogether 114. They were divided according to party labels into eight factions: these were respectively the National or People&apos;s party (10 deputies), led by Geshov, the Democrats* A full discussion of its probability and meaning may be found in the Weekly Report on Bulgaria XVII (October 19), published by the Intelligence Bureau of the Department of Information.[367-29] B
2(31 deputies), under Malinov, the Progressives (2 deputies, constituting the remains of the Tsankovist party, of which Dr. Danev was the head), the Radicals (5 deputies), the &quot; Narrow Socialists&quot; (11 deputies), the &quot; Broad Socialists&quot; (9 deputies), and 1 Indepen-deflt Socialist. A better division of these Opposition groups would be into three categories those of the party politicians, those of parties with clear but opportunist programmes, and, finally, the doctrinaires.   They may be taken in turn : 1. The first group includes the Nationalists, the Democrats, and the Progressives. The Nationalists, who at the election of March 1914 only came back with a strength of ten deputies, are the followers of M. Geshov, whose last period of office in Bulgaria came to an end in May L913, when the Balkan League, of which M. Geshov professed himself an enthusiastic supporter, was . threatened with disruption owing to the intransigeance of the Bulgarian military party. M. Geshov, whose connections and sympathies have always professedly, and probably actually, been with England and America, found himself hardly persona grata with Bulgaria&apos;s new friends in Austria and Germany. During the last four years in Bulgaria he has been under a cloud. J3oth he and Dr. Danev, who succeeded him as Prime Minister, but had to resign in July 1913 after the crushing defeats inflicted on Bulgaria by Serbia and Greece, were made by Ferdinand into scapegoats for the indignation of the defeated nation. A Parliamentary Commission of Inquiry was appointed to examine their misdeeds, and by this means it was hoped to keep them in check. The Democrat party, originally founded in the &apos;80&apos;s by the great Independence leader, Karavelov, now under the leadership of M. Malinov, Prime Minister 1908-11, possessed a strength of thirty-one deputies, and also the advantage of not having been held responsible, like Geshov and Danev, for the disasters which had befallen the country. All three parties, moreover, and especially Dr. Danev, had always stood as the champions of a Russian orientation for Bulgarian policy. That Bulgaria should take sides with the Entente Powers was their announced programme from August 1914 until September 1915, with, of course, a reservation that she should only do so if her Nationalist aspirations were satisfied. It must again be emphasised that .the following of all these three politicians was largely a personal following, and that their strength rested not on any clearly defined programme, but on the hopes of aspirants to office that by. support of them and by favour of Tsar Ferdinand their desires might one day again be attained.2. The Broad Socialists, who numbered nine, unlike the parties mentioned above, propounded definite doctrines as to legislative reform and a Socialist organi-sation of the community. Their leader is Dr. Sakyzov, and other prominent leaders of the party are Sakarov, Yanulov, Asen Tsankov, and Dzhidrov. They are nicknamed by their opponents &quot; Socialist patriots,&quot; for in hours of crisis, while theoretically opposed to war, they have never failed to support the Government in its use of any means to secure Bulgaria&apos;s national pro-gramme. Thoroughly opportunist, they would be content to co-operate with any party which could promise them either a share of their gains or help in achieving what they want. Their natural affinities are with the Majority Socialists in Germany, and it is thither ,that they look chiefly for support.   Their organ is the &quot; Narod&quot; (the &quot; Nation &quot;).3. As distinguished from these two groups is the group of real Opposition parties. The Agrarian party (forty-five deputies) was led by Stamboliski, and other prominent members of the party were Dragiyev, Omarchevski, and Radolov. Few of them possess any marked ability or political sense, but they are representative of the feeling of the peasants, who form the great majority of the population of Bulgaria, and of the latter&apos;s discontent with all the political cliques that exploit the country. While intensely particularist and so Nationalist, objecting to foreign interference, they are not Jingo in their outlook, nor have they any dreams of Bulgarian expansion and predominance in the Balkans. Their organ is the &quot; Zemledelsko Zname &quot; (the &quot; Agrarian Standard &quot;). A smaller party was that of the Radicals (five deputies), led by Tsanov, Fadenhecht, and Kosturkov, who, with a less definite programme than the Socialists, comprise a group of sincere and honest reformers. Last of all come the Narrow Socialists, as they are called^ a group of eleven deputies, convinced Zimmerwaldians.   Their programme is as intransigent
as that of the Russian Bolsheviks. They refuse all co-operation with &quot;bourgeois&quot; parties, and their organ, the &quot;Rabotnicheski Vestnik&quot; (the &quot;Labour Messenger&quot;), denounces capitalists, bourgeois, and Imperialists in the conventional language of the doctrinaire Socialist. At the same time they are too honest and too sensible to indulge in hair-brained schemes for the overthrow of the order of the world.The Opposition Parties and the War.All these three groups of Opposition parties were opposed in name at least to the intervention of Bulgaria on the side of the Central Powers, and their opposition had to be reckoned with. As a matter of fact, representatives of all of them waited on Ferdinand at the time of Bulgarias mobilisation, 23 September, 1913, to record their protest against the proposed intervention in the war. The way in winch they were respectively treated is a good index of their varying character. Geshov and Danev, over whose heads hangs the sword of Damocles of the Parliamentary Commission mentioned above, stopped their protest against intervention once they saw that it was determined on. Danev relapsed into silence in the Sabraniye. His paper, &quot; Balgariya,&quot; ceased to appear, and he himself accepted a professorship in Sofia University. Since then he has remained a silent figure in Bulgaria, careful not publicly to disavow his former Russophilism, but at the same time to keep on good terms with the Central Powers by visits to Vienna and by discreet behaviour. Geshov and his followers, among whom the chief are the ex-Minister, Todorov, and the brothers Vazov. and whose organ is the &quot; Mir,&quot; promptly switched round to abuse of the Entente Powers for having ignored Bulgarias just demands. The &quot; Mir &quot; was filled with columns of abuse of England, France, and Russia, especially the French, who were denounced as barbarians for invading Bulgaria. The &quot;Mir&quot; became an extreme organ of Bulgarian Chauvinism, and has since then exceeded even the Government press in its territorial demands. M. Geshov has paid frequent visits to Austria and, in his capacity of President of the Bulgarian Red Cross, has welcomed many an official German visitor to Sofia. Meanwhile his agents in Switzerland and his followers in America have not failed to keep open the door of reconciliation with the Entente Powers. Similarly with Malinov and his Democrat party : Malinov seems to have received an assurance from Ferdinand at the time of Bulgaria&apos;s intervention that if his career as Leader of the Opposition during the coming critical period were a discreet one, he would eventually find himself recalled to power in order to serve his country if circumstances made it advisable for Ferdinand to have recourse to him. (The moment has only recently arrived.) No steps were therefore taken against any of the members of these three Opposition parties, though from time to time, as Geshov, Danev, and their followers have become restive at the duration of the war and their continued exclusion from power, it has been necessary to bring them to order again by a threat that the Parliamentary Commission of Inquiry would be summoned to meet unless they behaved themselves. Malinov has played to perfection the part of His Majesty&apos;s Leader of the Opposition.Mention should be made of the part played during the first year of the war by a section of the Stambolovist party. We have seen that three members of this party held office in the Radoslavov Government, two of them, Genadiyev and Apostolov, and their friends having inclined, at least in appearance, to the side of the Entente Powers before Bulgarias intervention, Once intervention was an accomplished fact it was necessary to restrain their activities, and before long Genadiyev was deprived of his portfolio and put under arrest. From this ignominious position he was during 1916 released by the good offices of the German military attache, but in the course of last summer it was again found that he was becoming too dangerous, and he and six of his followers were once again arrested and deprived of their seats in Parliament, where they were replaced by followers of Radoslavov. At the same time Apostolov, who till then had been allowed his post as Minister of Railways, was dismissed and replaced by a member of the rival Germanophil group of the Stambolovist party, Koznichki, an associate of Petkov, Minister of Public Works. Apostolov and three of his followers promptly seceded from the Stambolovist party, which by these various exclusions and secessions was now reduced to twenty-four.With the Broad Socialists the Government seems at once to have come to an arrangement, and they have in fact proved most efficient agents of Bulgarian and German propaganda. Their chance of serving their country came in the ;-ummer of 1917, when Socialist delegations were invited to Stockholm to place their views before[367-29] B 2
4the Dutch-Scandinavian Committee. Six deputies of the Broad Socialist party went to Stockholm where they surprised their neutral colleagues by putting forward unrestricted demands to annexations on all sides, not only Macedonia, Greek and Serbian, but Dobrogea, and especially the Morava Valley, or at least part of it, the N ego tin district, thus providing for territorial contact with Austria-Hungary. Their organ, the &quot; Narod,&quot; was frank enough to say early in 1916 : &quot; In the Balkan Peninsula one nation must have the hegemony; perhaps this role is reserved for Bulgaria.&quot; It appears that quite recently, early this year, there has been some change in the attitude of the Broad Socialists ; possibly they consider that the moment has come for a new orientation of Bulgarian policy. Two of their leaders, Dzhidrov and Sakarov, are said to have been imprisoned last February by the Radoslavov Government, and there are signs of restiveness in their organ, the &quot; Narod.&quot; But whatever attitude they now take up. it must not be forgotten that they are both Opportunist (and therefore untrustworthy) and extremely Jingo, and that they have repeatedly denounced the idea of any Balkan federation.With the more resolute Opposition parties the Government adopted a different method. The leader of the Agrarians, M. Stamboliski, who had threatened King Ferdinand with the loss of his head should he drag Bulgaria into the war, was promptly sent to prison, where he has since remained. His party split into two groups his own followers numbering twenty-eight, and Dragiyev&apos;s group numbering seventeen. Their lack of able leaders has prevented them from making much of a case in Parliament, but everything goes to show that they have done all in their power to prevent the prolongation of the war. They have been accused right and left by the Government of sowing dissension and unrest in the army, where their paper, the &quot; Zemledelsko Zname,&quot; has latterly been forbidden to circulate. During the last few months their revolutionary activity has been openly protested against by the official press. Their leaders and agents are working, for the overthrow of Ferdinand and the restoration of peace, and a fair settlement of the Balkan question in agreement with Bulgaria&apos;s neighbours. Probably the small Radical group of five deputies are largely of this way of thinking, though they are more intellectual in their outlook and less representative of the feeling of the average peasant. The new Malinov Government has found it advisable to conciliate the small Radical party by inviting two members of it, Fadenhecht and Kosturkov, to take office. Lastly the Narrow Socialists, who denounced Bulgaria&apos;s &quot;intervention in the war and declared thattie demand for Macedonia was merely &quot;a cloak to cover imperialist designs,&quot; have throughout the war been perfectly logical and consistent in their attitude. They have invariably refused to vote the war credits, in which opposition the Agrarians have occasionally joined them. They have declared themselves in favour of a Balkan federation and an autonomous Macedonia, Their one idea is the overthrow of the existing regime in Bulgaria and the constitution of a purely Socialist State. If their opinions are doctrinaire and their political capacity not over great, they are none the less valuable adjuncts to the Entente cause, for they continue to excite the populace against its present rulers, and furnish a nucleus of agitation round which the vague discontents of the Agrarians can group themselves.It is impossible to go into too great detail as to the respective attitudes of all these parties during the two and a-half years since Bulgaria&apos;s intervention. The broad lines of Bulgarian policy seem to be these : the rulers of Bulgaria, Ferdinand and the party politicians who depend for their power entirely on his choice and support, saw that their one chance of creating a Great Bulgaria at the expense of their neighbours lay with the Central Powers. The Entente Powers were already in alliance with Serbia and in close relations with Greece, and were therefore not likely to abandon these allies. Moreover, the principle of Nationality, which could only be triumphant through the victory of the Entente Powers, militates against a Great Bulgaria. Even if Bulgaria incorporated the mixed populations of Macedonia, she would be a much smaller State than a Jugo-Slavia or a Greater Roumania only about half the size. Bulgarian Jingoes therefore viewed with horror the prospect of the Ententes victory. There can be no doubt that ever since the Treaty of Bucarest in 1913 Ferdinand and his followers had only been waiting for the chance of achieving their dream with the help of the Central Empires. On the other hand, there was no wish in Bulgaria for a complete victory of the Germanic Powers, While this might secure for Bulgaria all her territorial aims, it would leave her merely the vassal of Germany. But it was believed that such a complete victory was not likely to occur. The German and Russian autocracies must eventually come to terms in the interests of each. Bulgaria, linked to Germany by political and economic bonds, could at any moment appeal to the Slavophil and Orthodox sympathies of Russia, who would further see in her a valuable counterweight to German predominance
I0in the Balkans. This was the idea of Geshov, Malinov, and others in withdrawing their opposition to the alliance, namely, that they were not abandoning their Russo-philism, but that friendship with both Russia and Germany would eventually be found possible, and that Bulgaria as the &quot;friend &quot; of both Powers might play one against the other and thereby enhance her importance in the Near East. Such a view was often vented by the Geshov and Malinov press during 1916, The Russian revolution, while it seemed to bring peace nearer, frightened -these politicians with the prospect of a real German predominance in the Balkans. Henceforth they must look elsewhere than to Russia for the counterweight to Germany. Their attitude towards the Entente Powers has since then been more and more conciliatory. Above all they hoped to find in the United States their chief benefactor. !n the past America has done much for Bulgaria through educational and philanthropic institutions, chief among which is the famous Ptobert College at Constantinople, where many Bulgarian politicians, especially those of Geshov&apos;s and Malinov&apos;s party, have studied. America&apos;s intervention in the war horrified these Bulgarians, but they were promptly reassured by the fact that President Wilson did not break off diplomatic relations with Bulgaria. On this fact they based great hopes. They imagined that all their military activity in this war, their occupation and devastation of Serbian, Greek, and Roumanian territory, and the regime of terror they have practised there will be forgiven and forgotten. At any moment, they think, they can secure the pardon and support of the Entente Powers by merely asking for it. There is of course no intention of breaking with Central Europe, but astute, Bulgarian politicians Avould be perfectly content to make a so-called &quot;separate peace &quot; with the Entente Powers and America, should the latter allow them to retain their territorial annexations.As long ago as last October a &quot; revolution&quot; was prophesied in Bulgaria, and Malinov&apos;s accession to power rumoured. Such a revolution might come about in two ways: (1) There might indeed be a genuine revolution. As we have seen there is an ever-increasing body of discontent among the Bulgarian peasants and soldiers, to whom the war seems interminable, and who have little interest in international political ventures. Such a revolution would be an indispensable and important step towards the beginning of the solution of the Balkan question. But (2) the revolution which Tsar Ferdinand has lately manoeuvred is of a very different character. He has called Malinov to power in order to keep in his own hands the direction of this new orientation. The immediate occasion for this change came from the Treaty of Bucarest, signed on 7 May. Bulgarian dingoes were disgusted to find that instead of Bulgaria at once securing the whole Dobrogea (to which indeed on racial grounds they have no real claim, for they are in a minority of 14 per cent, in northern and central Dobrogea, where the Roumanian population is 55 per cent., but which by hundreds of articles and pamphlets they have hastened to claim as historically Bulgarian, and have sought to turn into a purely Bulgarian country by the usual methods of expropriation, educational propaganda, and forced naturalisation), her German allies only ceded her the southern part of it up to Trajan&apos;s Wall, and placed the rest of the province under a condominium of the four allied Powers, reserving the question of its cession to Bulgaria until Bulgaria had given satisfaction to Turkey and Germany. The satisfaction to Germany was economic. Bulgaria had to take over into her permanent National Debt two milliards of francs, which Germany had allowed her in the form of munitions and war material, and which the Bulgarians had hitherto reckoned as a gift. This concession Radoslavov succeeded in forcing from the Sabraniye, but on the question of retroceding to Turkey the territory on the right bank of the Maritsa, which Bulgaria had been granted as a preliminary to her intervention, Bulgarian opinion was and remains obstinate. The Bulgarian press was permitted by the Government to indulge in loud recriminations against Turkey&apos;s Jingo demands and Germany&apos;s ill-concealed support of them. Ferdinand promptly saw that the moment had come for his coup. He turned to the Petkovist section of the Government bloc. On 27 May the two Petkovist Ministers, Petkov and Koznichki, had an audience of the Tsar, and on 30 May they handed in their resignations. For sixteen days R,adoslavov still remained in office, repeatedly seeing the Tsar, but on the 15th he abandoned his resistance and resigned. Everything goes to show that the matter was finally arranged to Radoslavov&apos;s own satisfaction, and that his services will be employed elsewhere and duly recompensed. Ferdinand saw in turn Vachev, President of the Sabraniye, and the two Opposition leaders, Geshov and Malinov, on 11 June. On 16 June he entrusted Maliuov with the formation of a new Government which Malinov was able to announce on the 21st. The Opposition papers talked volubly of a &quot; coalition,&quot; but Malinov&apos;s followers were presumably unwilling to share the sweets of office with their
rivals. The new Cabinet, apart from the two Radicals, Fadenhecht and Kosturkov, who become Ministers of Justice and Public Instruction respectively, is composed wholly of Democrats. Malinov, Prime Minister, holds the portfolios of Foreign Affairs and of Cults; Takev and Lyapchev, who were Ministers of the Interior and Finance respec-tively in Malinov&apos;s 1908-11 Government, hold the same posts in the new Cabinet. Three professors, Danailov, Mushanov, and Mollov, all members of the party, become Ministers of Commerce, Public Works, and Railways respectively. General S. Savov, (not the same as the Commander-in-chief during the Balkan wars), formerly Cham-berlain to the King, is the new Minister of War, and the portfolio of Agriculture is given to Madzharov.Agents have recorded various opinions of these new Ministers, given before they came to office Mushanov, Takev, Lyapchev, and others. A point common to them all in these confidential conversations is that they insist that they have no intention of breaking with Ferdinand, but that they consider that it is perfectly possible for Bulgaria at any moment to reach an agreement with the Entente Powers, and that the British and American Governments and peoples are at any moment ready to welcome them back to the fold. M. Mushanov, for instance, according to an agent with whom he conversed, &quot; seemed to be complacently persuaded of England&apos;s unlimited patience, in spite of all Bulgaria may do.&quot; Similar views are expressed by the rest. They are, in fact, intent on a double game. As it appears to them the Avar will end in a draw; but as regards the Near East it appears to these people that Germany will be victorious. There can be no question, therefore, of breaking with her. Territorial and political connections with the Central Powers are indispensable to Bulgaria in the role she wishes to assume of chief State in the Balkans. On the other hand. Ferdinand and his new Government have no wish to place themselves wholly in the power of Germany, and they calculate that the best means of stopping this is to come to terms, but their own terms, in time with the Western Powers. - The appointment of a Malinov Government, as viewed from this aspect, meant a significant hint to Germany that she could not afford to disregard Bulgarian demands or favour Turkey at Bulgaria&apos;s expense. Possibly the pressure thus exerted on Germany may have the desired result of making Germany more conciliatory to the Bulgarian point of view over the Dobrogean question and the Maritza Valley. At the same time the Malinov Government, even if it succeeds in its policy, would not be wholly iimcceptable to Germany. Supposing that the Entente Powers were willing to accept the terms proposed by Malinov, ie., the recognition of the present territorial status of Bulgaria and the consequent abandonment of any future offensive from Saloniki, the Central Powers would at least attain their object of preventing any further activity of the Entente in the Balkans, and securing a permanent connection with the East through Bulgaria. Moreover, Ferdinand presumably hopes that the appointment of the Malinov Government and the pose of opposition to Germany which it adopts may have some effect in conciliating the intense irritation prevailing among the peasants and soldiers. In this he may or may not succeed. So far the real democratic parties, the Agrarians and Socialists, have been rather non-committal in their attitude. They refused to form part of the Government, but at the same time they expressed their willingness to support it in the Sabraniye. They are obviously holding their hand in order to see how the Government makes good its promises, and in what way its overtures will be regarded by the Entente Powers. Any recognition by the Entente Powers of the standpoint of the Malinov Government would consequently he to play into the hands of a force in Bulgaria which wall never willingly accept a fair and complete settlement of the Balkan question. The elements of unrest in Bulgaria would thereupon throw in their lot with the Government to which they are at present not particularly favourably disposed. A firm attitude towards the Malinov Government, on the other hand, and a reminder to it that the Entente Powers can have no dealings with a State which supports and imitates the methods of Prussia, would provide the revolutionary party in Bulgaria with the strongest arguments and power of action. The Malinov Government itself rather than allow the power in the country to pass into the hands of the Agrarian and Socialist parties would probably be forced to bid against them with the Entente, or, failing to do so (should it refuse to break its connection with Ferdinand and Germany), would eventually be overthrown. The Entente Powers are, therefore, in the happy position of eventually being able to enforce their views by one means or the other. There is, therefore, every hope that, clever as Ferdinand&apos;s action may have appeared to him, it wili, in fact, provide us with an opportunity of using still further pressure on the Bulgarian nation. Propaganda conducted on these lines wall have an increasing effect-and all advices state that it has already had considerable effect on the mass of the Bulgarian people.o

</content>
</cab>
