<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/59/0 images: 299-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Col. Dally Jones                                                                              G.T. 5269                                                                                     THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

SECRET

I submit for the consideration of my colleagues a Memorandum on the Post War Supply of Superphosphate and Phosphate Rock, prepared by the Branch in my Department which deals with Agricultural questions.

The Memorandum raises questions of policy on which decisions appear to be required.               C. ADDISON.
Memorandum on the Post !7ar Supply of Superphosphate required for Agricultural Purposes in this Country.1,     FINDINGS OP KE,SH0E5?TTS COMI/II^E.It appears from the report of Ilr. Short tls Committee on the Post Nar position of the sulphuric acid and fertilizers trades which was first received in this Department on October 24th 1917, that(a) The post war supply of sulphuric acid is likely to exceed by say 350,000 tons the requirements in this country.(b) The agricultural requirements of the United Kingdom both for superphosphate and basic slag(in the treatment of the former of which siu.phuric acid Is required), will be greatly increased, owing to additional cultivation.(c) Additional super-phosphate factories will be required.(d) An adequate supply of phosphate rock should be guaranteed by State action.2* LORD BALFOUR?S PROPOSAL.On June 10th, Lord Balfour of Burleigh, forwarded a supplementary memorandum which had been prepared by Mr A.R.Dickinson on the means of producing superphosphate in which it wan urged that tho Imperial Government should in view of their predominating requirements retain control of the deposits in the Pacific Islands, especially Nauru Island.     The arguments adduced in support of this view were that-(a) Most of the high gro.de phosphate rock which wastreated in this country before the war was imported from non-British sources, the best phosphate rock being obtained from Ocean and Nauru Island in the
-  Pacific, and from Christmas Island in the Indian Ocean.(b) Before the war ITauru Island was in German possess! but the large deposits there were and are being worked. 07 the Pacific Phosphate Company under-a concession from the German Government -     (Lord Balfour Is Chairman of this Company and Mr Dickinson is a Joint Managing Director).(c) In view of the requirements of British agriculture it would appear undesirable that the Imperial Government - should relinquish their control over the Pacific Island deposits In favour of the Governments of Australia and New Zealand.(d) Granted tho necessary transport facilities, the Pacific Island phosphate, being of a higher grade than North African rock, would provide the cheapest raw material for tho manufacture of superphosphate&apos;.    (It was also urged that largo stocks of high grade phosphate rock should bo accumulated In this country.)3* CRITICISM OF LORD 3ALF0TJRTS PROPOSAL.The desirability of retaining Imperial control over the deposit in Nauru Island would appear to depend upon the relative post war advantage in view of shipping restrictions? of the Nauru deposits.The matter was accordingly referred to the Explosives Acid Department of tho Ministry of Munitions, who stated on June 29th -(a) That the capacity of the North African supply appears to be greatly in excess of the present working of the rock, and should be adequate for/the
217the requirements of both Prance and the United Kingdom,(b) The Pacific Island deposits are by no means the only ones available for the supply of phosphate:, which is for example contained in the extensive guano deposits In Peru, St.Pierve and Canada.    There are also the last Anglian Coprolite deposits which although probably not very extensive can be treated with sulphuric acid., like phosphate rock, for the production of superphosphate.(c) Per a considerable period after the war it Is thought that restriction of tonnage will render the ITorth African supply by far the most valuable to the United Kingdom,4. IilFORMATIOM FuKKISZND BY EXPLOSIVES AC IP DEFT. Upon enquiry, the Explosives Acid Department stated that -(a) Existing stocks of phosphate rock.The approximate amount of untreated phosphate rock In this country, was at the end of Kay about 90,000 tons equivalent to the amount that could be treated to the end of July.     (The correspond-ing figure for June 1917 was 52,000 tons),(k) Shipping tonnage required.The importation of phosphate rock depends however upon the amount of shipping placed at the disposal of the Ministry of Munitions for this purpose.     The shipping allocated hitherto has amounted to 300,000 tons per annum.     As some 40,000 or 50,000 tons Mas been imported monthly, the shipping allowance for this year is already/ practically
218practically exhausted.     As 500,000 tons of phosphate rook are now required for agricultural purposes alone and could he treated in the existing superphosphate factories, while in addition some 50,.000 tons aremade by the Ministry of Munitions to the Ministry of Shipping with a view to securing a further allocation of tonnage. (c)   Phosphate Rock required..High grade phosphate rock when treated with sulphuric acid produces superphosphate in the proportion of about 5 tons of phosphate rock to 9 tons of superphosphate.     It has been estimated by Sir T.S,Middleton that, in view of the increased area of land in the United Kingdom which will be under cultivation at the end of the war, some 1,367,000 tons of superphosphate (representing say three quarters of a million tons of phosphate rock as against say 410,000 tons required in 1913, or an increase of 340 or 356,000 tons) would be required for agricultural purposes.Sir Charles Fielding&apos;s estimate Is larger than the above figure by about 150,000 to 160,000 tons of phosphate rock per annum (i.e,, an Increase of half a million tons on pre-war requirements). In the opinion of the Fxplosives Aoid Department these estimates are probably excessive. (^^   Sources of Supply.At the. present time phosphate rock Is principally obtained from the French deposits in North Africa.     Ac already stated It isneeded for other purposes, representations have been
understood that those deposits are veryextensive and that the supply greatly exceedstho present working of the rock.     In theopinion of the Explosivos Acid Department these depos-its alone should he adequate in the post-war periodprovided that labour is available&apos;, for meeting theagricultural requirements both of this countryand of Prance.It is, however, urgently desirable that immediate action should be taken by the Government to secure from this source guarantees of a supply -which will be adequate for the estimated post war requirements (say 750,000 tons).     It will also be necessary to guarantee a sufficient allocation of tonnage for the importation of this quantity of rock.While the North African rock will doubtless be the most important source of tho raw material required for the manufacture of superphosphate, other sources of supply should not be ignored. - There is for example as already noted the important deposit of coprolite in East Anglia, which while it may not be very extensive is now being worked with success at Trumpington near Cambridge.    The initial expense of working this deposit is however very considerable, and there is some doubt whether the venture will prove commercially advantageous in the pest war period, when the present cost of, and restrictions upon, shipping facilities have decreased. (e) Output of Superphosphate, FactoAt the present time it is understood that there are some 80 superphosphate factories in this country whose capacity may be about 11 to/ 12,000
9 9 n12,000 tons of phosphate rock per week, or approximately 550,000 tons per annum.It has been suggested, that tho sulphuric acid plant at Avonmouth leased to MrvTllden Smith, and the Speltor Factory at Irving Scotland would provide suitable centres for the manufacture of superphosphate if new factories were built in connection with those at present existing there.     It is thought that such new factories might bo capable of an output whioh would be adequate for the increased post war demand for superphosphates in this country for agricultural purposes.It would accordingly appear that, beyond tho two factories proposed no new superphosphate factories need be erected to meet the requirements in this country,(f) AcidIt appears to be generally agreed that the output of sulphuric acid will considerably exceed any post war requirements for the manufacture of superphosphate and sulphate of ammonia,(g) Basic SlagSir T JT. Middle ton estimated that an additional supply of basic slag to the extent of 629,000 tons could with advantage be used in the post war period for agricultural purposes.     There has been some doubt as to whether the supply of suitable raw slag in this country would.be sufficient to meet these requirements.It is however understood from the Explosives &quot;Acid Department that there is at the present time a considerable increase in the output of raw slag, and that they consider that the agricultural requirements for this material will in all/probability
9 9 1probability bo mot by the supply. (h) Af;;rioultural Demand.Tho section of tho Explosives Acid Department which deals with the supply of fertilizers aro working in close touch with the Pood Production Department., and they consider that if the latter arc able by propaganda work to maintain and increase the present demand among cultivators for artificial manures, this country should absorb all the superphosphate which, in view of continued transport and labour restrictions, is likely to be manufactured in the post war period.5&apos;   RBC QMMBHDATIQHS. It would appear from the information obtained that provided an adequate supply of phosphate rock is guaranteed.-(a) The existing factories, with the two new factories proposed to be erected at Avonmouth and Irving, should bo sufficient to manufacture all the superphosphate Y;hioh is likely to be required by British agriculture,(b) That the agricultural demand, If adequately stimulated by propaganda work is likely to absorb tho superphosphate so manufactured.In order however to secure this desirable result from the efforts now being made by the Explosives Acid Department, It is recommended that -(a)   Steps should be immediately takon by the Board of Trade to guarantee the post-war supply of phosphate rock to t?ac extent of say 750,000 tons per annum, (b) An adequate supply of labour for the/ manufacture
0 9 nW hi k/manufacture of superphosphate and of shipping tonnage for its transport should ho guaranteed. (c)The propaganda work of tho Food Production Department, to stimulate the use of super-phosphate by agriculturalists should be main-tainod and extended.With regard to the suggestion made in Lord Balfour&apos;s Memorandum affecting the retention of Nauru Island, it is dear that the possibility of imports therefrom will depend primarily upon shipping facilities as to which, as the Committee is aware, tho Chipping Controller is disposed to take a more sanguine view than is commonly entertained, should tho iar continue ever next year.It is clear, however, that (1) we shall require greatly augmented supplies of phosphate rock and (2) whilst the North Africa sources are most convenient, it might be undesirable to leave ourselvos so greatly dependent upon this source of supply.     It is therefore suggested that the Economic Defence Committee would be justified in recommending that the continuation of Imperial control over these Islands is of importance from the point of view of securing adequate and alternative source of supply of phosphate rock.The Foreign Office and the Colonial Office will doubtless furnish the Committee with their views as to how this matter affects their interests and as to whether, in the event of Imperial control being continued, it would be preferable that it should be exercised from home or through&apos;the New Zealand or Australian Governments./Further
9 9 9Further It is suggested that the Board of Trade in negotiating for scouring out post-war supplied of phosphate rock should consult Sir Charles Fielding!s Committee (which is mentioned below) as to what arrangements might best be mado with the Companies at present responsible for the develop-ment of thed eposits in tho Island of Hauru. Board of Agriculture Committee.It may be noted that the   Board are setting up a Committee upon whioh this Department will be represented under the Chairmanship of Sir Charles Fielding, to consider more closely the agricultural aspect of tho position with regard to the supply of fertilizers.     Tho proposed terms of reference are-&quot;To consider and advise upon tho recommendations made by the (Mr.Shortt &apos;,s) Committee in their agricultural bearing.1!C. Acldi s on. 31.7.13.

</content>
</cab>
