<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/59/0 images: 328-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Hiis $W*U*wit is Nife Property of,jaiiiltii. *       . .EIGHTEENTH REPORT BY THE BOARD OF TRADE ON IMPORTS AND INDUSTRY IN KEIATION TO SHIPPING.EHAl3MQ Report la divided into two parts, (%) a brief account of imports, exports, entrances, and clearances, shipping losses, employment of ships and new construction in the first half of 1918 and in the last month for which figures are availableo (2) a discussion of oertain stocks of materials in relation to the imports of January/June, 1918.A. H.. S31ANISY.Board of Trade,30 th July, 1918.The imports for the half year ended 30th June as oom-pared with the corresponding period in 1913 and 1917 were   * as follows:-Tons.1913. &quot;^917. 1918.Jan-June 25,440,000       19,423,000        17,200,000Thus the 1918 figure falls short of the 1917 figure by some    200,000 tonB or U$f.and of the 1913 figure by 8,240,000 tons or 32$. in October 191V Sir Alfred Watson and Mr. Elderton estimated th*t, exclusive of timber, the imports of the first six months of 19li would fall below those of the first six months of 1917 by 3,726,000 tons.   2?he actual   ... decline, allowance being made for oertain classes of imports which were not recorded in the Trade Returns prior to July 1917, seems to have been only some 2,500,000 tons.   There has thus been a subst-antial improvement on the estimate, and there is evory probability that Sir Alfred Watson^ and Mr. Eldertonia forecast of a total import for the year of   8 million tons short of the import of 193-7 will be considerably exceeded.In June total imports into the United Kingdom amounted to 2,700,000 tons which is 20$ below the figure for June 1917 and 44$ below that of June 1913.For particular Imports the follcving points may be noted On the first six months of 1918 as compared with 1917, wheat and flouj? were       lower, meat 31$ up, and timber 23$ up. Raw wool was down 36$ and raw cotton 3$, raw jute was down no less than 53$.   In June 1918 imports of grain and flour were down by 46$ as compared with June, 1917, but imports of meat were up by 43$.   Eor a number of important commodities com-parison with the early months of 1917 is impossible beoause Government-owned goods (except food) were excluded from the returns before July, 1917.
11w 1 wExports show a larger proportionate falling off than imports.    The weight of all exports of British producemd manufactures was only 1,930.000 tons in the first half of  &apos; 1918 compared with 2,794,000 tons in tho first half of 1917, and 5,800,000 tons in the first half of 1913.    The    * per cent age decline is thus 14$ on 1917 and 58$ on 1913. For tho six months ending (Jime the tonnage of-all manufact^ ures exported was&apos;down 3i$ as compared with 1917, that of coal was down 15$,    As comearod with the, first six months, of 1913 manufactures Were down&quot; 67$. cOal 55$ and the total weight of exports of all kinds 58$.   Tojbal exports in June amounted to 3,000,000 tons, which is 22$ below the figure for June, 1917. ,5* The comparative position as regards entrances andclearances of&quot;vessels with cargo during the half year is indicated in the following statement:-** ...       ......jfa trances. Qlearance.3;.Bri-tisn *    Jtoign.     gotal    MtM  Ipieign,  IplalrJune&apos;1913 15ily-Dec.1913 17-June 1917 9;285 2;383      II;673       7:947      4:661  12:608y-Decl917 9;514 2 031      11 545       8 963      4 488  13 451rJune 1918 9 383 1 778      11 161       7 193      3 921  11 1147;882      23;134      19;290    13:606 32;896 040 8 890      25 930      20 811     14 112  34 923DOR *5?*3QQ 11 rj-QAU A Ul &quot;l     1$? AOIt should be stated that the figures for the first half of 1917 are not fully comparable, since they exclude the tonnage of certain requisitioned vessels included in later figures. Compared with i913, entrances&apos;of British and Foreign&quot; vessels show a decline of 52 per cent* and clearance of 66 per cent. As the tonnage of imports declined only 32 per cent, and that of exports 58 per cent, the loading factor is 40 per cent.   \ better for imports and 24 per cent, better for exports.6.    &apos;    &quot;In June, British entrances with cargo amounted to1,642,000 net tons, that is 1$ less than in June 1917.*   In . May tnere had been a percentage increase of .5% on 1917. *British clearances were 1,226,000 tons - 24$ less*than in June 1917, compared with a decrease of 26$*in Ifay. Foreign entrances amounted to 256,000 tons. 26$ less than in June 1917,- as against a decrease Of 35$ in&quot;the previous month - and foreign clearances to 638,000 tons, 24$ lessthari -in June 1917.    As against 1913 the loading factor is 27$ greater and against 1917 16$ less.7. The position as regards tonnage during the halfyears shows on the whole a marked improvement compared with the estimates for 1918.    New building is greater and losses   -are smaller, but losses still exceed gains. %(2)
gains and losses of British Vessels of 500, tone,, grossaril over.British built brought into serviceGross tons.Jim * June, 191? -*r 1917 -Jan-June, 1918375,000 -618,000 776,000Total Gains inol,purchases and vessels requisitioned abroad,etc.589,000 1,057,000 1,142,000loss through War and Marine Risks2,206,000 1,750,000 1,360,000Net in-crease or Deorease . in Tonnage,- 1,617,000- 693,000 218,000Though destruction   still exceeds building the net loss of tonnage during the first half of 1918 has been comparatively trifling when compared with the figure for the first half of 1917 and has been les*s than l/3 of the net loss during the second,,half of 1917,   It may be noted that Sir Alfred Watson and Mr Elderton in their foreOast of last October allowed for a net decline of nearly 1,000,000 tons during the first half of the present yw. The actual net loss of tonnage would of course have approached much nearer to this estimate had it not been for the addition to the British register of vessels pur-chased or requisitioned abroad.8.4 In June total losses of British Shipping of over 500-0,1* amounted to 192,000 gross tons of which 174,000 tons were due to war risk ,   The figure coincides very nearly with the Admiralty forecast made seven months ago that from June onwards 185,000 tons would be a reasonable expectation for total monthly losses.   War losses during the preceding five months were at the rate of 198,000 tons per month.   In June the new vessels over 500 tons built in British yards and brought into Service . amounted to 139,000 tons.   The grand total of gains amounted to 162,000 tons,9, The average of world war losses (to British, Allied andNeutrals combined), over the first six months of 1918 amount to 895,000 tons a month.   War losses of the Allies&apos;(other than British) in June were 52,000 tons as against 81,000 in May&apos;and 51,000 in April, ahd of neutrals 38,000 tons as against 20,000 tons in May and 11,000 in April. , . - -10. On May 31st - the figure for June 30th is not yet avail-able - as compared with April 30th, the employment of the -British Mercantile steam fleet over 500 tons had changed asfollows J-Vessels repairing and surveying Launched but not completed Total cf the above Army and Navy Colonies(Russia Allies (II.&amp;.A.(Other Permanently abroad OilersRemainder available for British trade other than oilersTotal ready for uaeGRAND TOTAL(3)1,000 tons at May 31st,1,075-396Change since! April,1.471 2,856498 36205 1,806 i;i67 1,0876; 353112 62kamfT174 287 46 16 12 25 6 21f   7714.00815,47938
fit It. thus appears that during May the total. TOBM &amp; age7for service decreased by-212,000 tons. - 6* *The table below gives the absolute and the percentage increases and decreases of vessel^ over&quot; 500 tons that have taken place between May 31st, 1917 and May 31st, 1913 in the several employments o :-1T0Q0 Tons PercentageBepairing and Surveying........ &quot; i 627        ^140Launched but not completed.....   f. 95        f 31Total.............. &quot;fm        &quot;4%&quot;Army and Navy.................. -1,227 * 30Colonies.,..................... - 407 -.45(Russia............... 7 195 - o4Allies...[D.S.A................ t 205            -(Other................ -   75 -  4Permanently abroad,............ 7 113 7  9Oilers......................... / 101 i 10Remainder available forU.K. trade other than oilers... - 233 -  0Total ready for use.,..	.  -1,944	- 12	.   &quot;* 1,222	- 7It will be noted that owing&apos; to the increase innot . tervessels undergoing repair and in vessels launched but 1 completed, a reduction of 7$ in the total on the regisi has meant a reduction of tonnage fit for service of as much as 12$.    But, owing principally to a large reduction in the vessels in the service ofthe&apos;Army and wavy, the tonnage available for British trade appears to have fallen off only 233,000 tons or 3$,    In consequence, however, of (l) uncertainty in the figure for vessels permanently abroad, on account of the change made in January in the method of classification, and (2) the fact that up to May 1918 a vessel was: classed under the service to which it was allocated, irrespective of the actual date of entry into that service, no great stress can be laid on this figure.    to the more, it must be remembered that in May 1917. when our comparison begins the tonnage of vessels available for United Kingdom trade was already enormously diminished below the figure for normal times.The following table shows the position of Britishshipbuilding as reported during the week ending 27th June, 1918:-ffloss asUnder Con- Launched   Total - struction but not     under con-on stocks completed  structionStandard ships........&apos;.. 647.000 117,000     764,000Other Merchant vessels... 406,000 206,000     612,000Oilers................... 257,000 43,000     300,0001^310*000 366^000^^1^676^000(4)
The tonnage under construction on stocks included 95 overseas barges totalling 43,000 tons.    Of the tonnage of &quot;other merchant vessels&quot;, 94,000 tons are ships for carrying meat and fruit.Stocks in relation to importsThe fact that imports for the 6 months have been heavier than was anticipated at the end of 1917 has left the stock position in certain esses more favourable than had been feared&apos;.    But this is not true all along the line, as thefollowing notes show:-limber    Imports have been continuously feeavy as compared with anticipations and, in the case of sawn wood and&quot;mahogany etc, as compared v,ith last year.January-June   January-June   January-June 1916 1917 1913Tons Tons TonsPitwood..............-1,108^000 &apos;       572*000 428^*000Other hewn wood......    105,000 21,000 24,000Softool, savvn, etc,, 1,200,000 469,000 826,000Mahogany 3co-    55,000 27,000 613,000(&amp;L?iteod  The good imports and increased home productionnave mam Gained satisfactory stocks.(b) Bof twod, .3H\yn. eto.r Stock figures are available for May 31st.    They are as follows:-TonsHome grown timber held by Merchants (England andWales only)...   18,000i;i95,000The rate of consumption is estimated at 240-250j000 tons a month.    The June imports were 103.000 tons, which, together with home production at its present level, should supply the greater part of the montlVs needs.    On these figures stock;? at June 30th would be over 4i months&apos; supply.ic) Mahogany etc. Heavy imports reflect the war demand. Stocks remain light.Cotton  Imports les*: re-exports were about 850,000 tons in 1913which was much less than in the previous year] and 675,000 tons in 1917 when imports were supplemented out of stocks.   If present expectations are realised imports in 1918 will probably be about 625,000 tons (there are now&quot;no re-exports).   Stocks of American are not much more now than a two months&apos; supply. Other stocks are adequate.    In the American Section, only 50 per cent of machinery is working and the veek has had lo be cut down to 4 days - though there is some relaxation where Government work is considerable.    This drastic curtailment of production was necessitated by the very low level to which it was intended until recently to bring imports for,the rest of the year.    Recently, however, it has been passible to arrange for an increase of the expected imports with the result that the necessity of yet further curtailing production has been averted and the outlook has been improved.(5)
246Wool.   The imports for the *ux months were 128,000 tons-as! ! compared with 201,000 tons in 1917 and 200,000 tons in I9f h The 1918 import, however, was enough for about 22 weeks&apos;      / consumption, so that stocks have not been dangerously rednj^w There is now 4-5 months&apos; stock in hand.fia%.   Imports of flax and tow have been very small (3,000! tons only for the six months).    The ordinary importing season is now beginning but prospeots in Russia remain un-1 certain.    Stocks have been husbanded by the W.O.O.D. and ft greatly increased production in the United Kingdom has been arranged.    But unless at least 20,000 tons can be extracted from Hussia in the next few months, the situation in 1918-19 v will be very difficult. jtorn.  Net hnports have been greater than those of 1917 T43j&quot;000 as against 40,000 tons).    The proportion of Italijan hemp, whioh is an effective substitute for coarse flax, ha*3 *; been increased from 6,000 to 11,000 tons;   there is a iargja . increase in Manila, and the relatively useless East Indianj.^., material has not been shipped.Jute. Stocks had been run down to 2-3 months1 supply on \ January 1st. By the end of June they were almost exhausted, &apos;*s the import for the six months was only 50.000 tons, whifle *he supply desired by the W.0.CD. was 16,000 tons a month! 96,000 tons), and the amount actually consumed not very ! men less. The danger point for this year however, is * Relieved to be passed, as supplies are now (July) arriving1 freely and good shipments continue.farinaceous products for textile industries. Supplies of &apos; farina are adeouate, but those of corn starch are very low indeed and prompt shipments from America are essential.Bosin.   Imports were altogether inadequate.    In February, when the rosin control was set up, it was estimated that, 0ven with, a reduced consumption, 5,000 tons 0 month were  . Required.    The import for 6 months has been&quot;11.000 tons. ?here was, however, at tho end of June still, at least ) months1 stock in hand and shipments are now coming forward.Rubber.   Shipments are being greatly curtailed.   The net import for the six months was, however, 15,000, and thefross imoort 25,000 tons.    Estimates &apos; cf   . requirements&apos; or the year are not exact but approximate to 30,000 tons. Further arrivals may be expected and stocks are large. The only danger from the point of view of supply is that off a possible snortage of one particular class 01 rubber (Parja).Paper and Paper Materials.    The import for the six monthshas not been&quot;much less than in 1917. 11January-June 1918      January-June 1917J Paper 60,000 tons 76,000 tons.     NMaterials. 19 8 , 000   11 220,000   &quot; \Stocks are inconsiderable.    If the reduction of 250,000 ttms^
ii i   247on 1917, contemplated  or the year, is applied the po^-&apos; ition will become aovcte mJxi2y*^^ But as theFebruary Recommendation of a reduction of 7^000^-000  , ,-fco-ns in total imports for the year was based on assump* tions as to a reduction in importing capacity which have not so far been approximately realised, this strict application may not be necbssary.Oils and ffats.(a) Hon Mineral Oils and gats.     The stocks of Oil anjd Fat (including the oil equival-ont of Seeds, Nuts and ; Kernels) at various dates during the last months were estimated as followsSept.30th. .   Pec .31st..    March,31st.    June 30tL.Tons,  330,000 245,000     205,000 235,00bIn the Autumn of 1917 stocks were deliberately drawn on, but it will be noticed that taken en bloc  they have been kept up satisfactorily in 19157&quot; There is, howevfer, a very small stock of linseed oil, and a bad tutlouk- far linseed imports, which has serious reactions on che paint, printing ink, waterproof, linoleum and other trades/(b) Mineral Oils.    The stock position is much better than it was six months ago and very much better than it Vas a I year ago.    As Kerosene consumption is seasonal the latter comparison is the more interesting.End of June 1917, End of Deo.1917. End of June &quot;&quot; &quot;&quot; &apos;- Bis, (AverT!age of 4 weeks to Ml 6,Motor Snirit 53,000 tons. 75,000 tons lOTToSOTons. Kerosene 63,000 &quot; 73,000  rt       95,000Gas Oil.&apos; 10,000 11 9^000 &quot;        16,000Fuel Oils 23,000 &quot; 12,000  &quot; 6,000The motor spirit stock is enough for over 3  months? present consumption (civil and military), that of Kerosene for about 3f months&apos; summer consumption. Mineral oil stocks in the aggregate hare never been better since this eries of reports started.s Exclusive of Admiralty Stocks.
2iSTable 1. TOTAL IMPORTS.	Imports     000 tons.1917  May June July August September October November December	3,647 / 3,390 / 3,421 . 3,303 2,868 2,886 2,944 2,3041918   January February Marcii April May June Total      (6 months)	2,730 2,559 2,772 3,087 3,354 2,700 17,202TOTAL   1917	37,230TOTAL 1916	46.390TOTAL 1912	54,549/ Including an allowance  or Government ownedgoods.TABLE II.GROSS TOMAGE OF M3HCHANT SHIPPING LOST BY JBHESMY A0TI0H IN 1.000 GROSS TONS..British		Allied/	ifeutre!	Totar1914	241	18	44	303&apos;1915	860	,317	204	1,2811916	1,238	536	575	2,3491917	3,725	1,268	1,190	6,1831918    January	180	87	35	302February	227	55	36	318March	199	04.	51	344April	211	51	11	273May	187	81	20	288June	158	52	38	248Total (6 months)	1,162	420	191	1,773TOTAL	7,226	2,459	2,204	11,869/ U.S.A. Losses included among Allied as from the beginning of April, 1917.(8)
TABLU III.Imports In 1.000 tons.1918.,   m.--sjy fe-$ change in 1918JuneJan/JunoJuneJan/JuneJime&apos; Jan/JunePood etc. rain and Hour(eat ther flood, Drink&quot; &amp; Tobacco.TOTAL.Raw Materials.iron Ore ther Metallic Ores ood and timber lotton oolOther TextileMaterials llineral Oils Oil Seeds etc. Sides and Skins Paper Kate rials iiigcellaneous5?0G?A1-.Manufactures andj MiscellaneousGHAHD TOTAL.5E9124262 915562 125185 37 SO11 380 153 926513,5186851,6295,6323,144 7971,366 356 128109 2,281 732 45 198 4331,5592262,7009,5891,70117,202-46 /43-19-34/17 x / 6 /16 -41xX/26 -18 -43 xx-24 /31-10-17- 0x/23- 3 -36X -14 -31 -10xxx-47 /17-49-43-14-85 - 5 -23-54 /183m-18 -77 -44-42-59&quot;k-x-32 /18-43-32-23 -10 -66 -22 -57-69 /180 -33 -41 -66 -39-28-49-32Comparison with the early months.of 1917 is impossible &apos; because Government owned goods (except food) were ex-cluded from the Trade uoturns before July.(9)
TABLE IVEXPORTS IN 1918 COMPARED V;ITH 1917 AMD 1913.. 2 5 0Exports in 1918.$ increase or deceease mi 1917fo increase or decrease on 1913r Poodcoo1r Oresr Textiles Seedss&amp; Hansonsu&amp; Steel r Metals 8ry etc. tncal ineryonr Textiles relicals etc.hersrllesaneous1ik Unclagg. &apos;1 Weight 1 Value    June Tons6 monthsendedJune502 - 15 39,737 63540,8892,558,004 8513,165 278- 61 628 151 530 28.7204,520&apos;213 188;291 4.921197,94516,553,218 5,028 ! 45 22,430 2,535 &apos;480 23,498 2,786 5,430 168.&amp;84June6 months ended June^68 ^89 /25 -36/21-I-30 -25 00 28 175 -68 -45 -62 -81 -332,592,388  16,784,154153 3 2 117 12655 640 044 248 855 879 495 40,460 5,331 &quot;219 4,379 1,277 54,193 220 10; 326 3; 295 1,959 51.038364,513 4,6533,002,443 45,026,231818 21 118102 20 3337 37 124 6283 1 52 16 162671,930- 2118,933 246,832208032 327 532 432 757 962 434 115 201 859 115540569 546 035-30-3049 ^30 47hi-60- 8 -41- 6 ^55 -20- 6 -62- 2 -10 -6 -43195 561855649725 /3-88 ^84 ^22 -25-26145 ^60 -80 /49 -68 ^58 ^63 -55 -77 -15-15-33 -32 -32 -38 728 /17 -52 -13 -38 41 -46 ^31 45 -69 -B3 -,37 /24^31w&quot;22rl4- 2June^.98 *86 ^66 -49-72-59 &apos;-32 -100 ^32 ^84 - 6 ^57 49 -68 -65-60^63 -72 -67 -44 -73-78 ^42 ^57 -54 ^39 -37 -46 -83 ^82 ^67 -54 -49^62 /13r59 /56 monthsendedJune^98 ^.74 -68 -28-734^55-99.6 2--81 -87 -71 -78-56-67 i ^75 j -71  I-44   ;-73 &apos; ^92   i;^75 :-47 -49 -57 -43 -54 -61 -82 ^67 -81 .47 -71^67 -41r5&amp;- 4(10)
In 1.000 gross tons.,.	Yes	sels 1,600 G.T. and over.            I         Yesse				Is of 500 G.T. and over, less than 1,600 G.T.			Consequent net increase or decrease in Total Tonnage.	Gains British built brought into service	Total gams including purchased&apos; and requi-sitioned abroad seized etc.	War Bisk.	Total-inclu-ding marine risk and sold	Gains British built brought into service	Total gains including purchased&apos; and requi-sitioned abroad &quot;seized etc.	Ytfar Eisk.	r Total    &quot; . including marine risk and sol  abroad.	April &amp;ay June July August *   fieptember t   e3ctober Movember Beeember fotal in 1917	73^ 100^ 45^ 83 91 77 117 131 105	107 * 185 * 96^ 170 166 102 187        i 174 130	515 329 398 334 309 175 252 160 i     226 1	552 362 412 356 354 181 .   288 185 282	6 -1* 4* 2 1 1 4 2 4	11-7* 9 &quot; 33 18 34 16 17	22 18 10 9 13 11 17 13 12	27 21 15 9 16 19 22 21	^323 -186 -171 - 80 -:$s ^16 Jf)^ .	968      1     1.493           3.450			3.789	25*   :	153^	165	167 * 1         -2.310X	Total January February March April May June	62 108 156 106 193 .   139	75 ioa 257 229 236 I        158	183 215 182 205 151 ,    161	222 244 203 218 182 175  .	2 2 3 3 2	11 7 27 23 7 4	5 10 16 9 16 , 13	13 27 24 14 21 17	-149 -156 4 57 ih20 4-40 - 30x  This total in not quite complete owing to lack of details of gains and marine and other losses in Februaryoand March 1917 of vessels of 500-1600 tx. T.Ht Approximate only.INSCUT!
2 5 23 71.Ml MM SHIPPING- ElJBg IN 1.Q0Q TOUS.....	BRITISH.	FORE I ON.	TOTAL.1^91^7.			June. July. August. September. October. November. December. January 1918. February. March. April. May. June.	&apos; 1,656. 1,880. 1,688, 1,568. 1,502. 1,484. 1,392. 1,429. 1,362, 1 554. 1,694. 1 702. 1,642.	348. 416. 349. 316. 330. 327. 293. 315. 327. 308. 258. 256.	2,004. 2 296. 2 037. 1 883, 1 832. 1 811. 1 685, 1 743; 1 677. 1 881. 2 002. 1 960. 1 898.TABLE VII.SHIPPING CLEAMCES IN 1,000 TGHSJune.July.August.September.October.November.December.January 1918.February.March.April.May.June.BRITISH.FORSIGf.1ii: i: i: r i i i i;619.	839.676.	802.644.	893.573.	770.487.	716.240.	698.343.	619.125.	644.138.	600.231.	703.206.	643.267.	693.226.	638.TOTAL.2,458. 2,478. 2,537. 2,343. 2,203. 1,928; 1,962. 1,769. 1,738. 1,934. 1,849. 1,960. 1,864.f 12 )

</content>
</cab>
