<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/29/0 images: 115-120</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  document&apos;is   the property of his  britannicrMAj[est^s  governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1948I SECRET Copy No. 31CP. (48) 2013rd August, 1948CABINETLORD HENDERSON&apos;S VISIT  TO THE RUHRNote by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues a note by Lord Henderson,Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, on his recent visit to the Ruhr.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W. 1.3rd August, 1948.NOTE BY THE PARLIAMENTARY UNDER-SECRETARY OF STATEFOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS (LORD HENDERSON) ON VISIT TOTHE RUHR, 12th-17th JULY, 1948The following is a summary of the main conclusions which I reached duringmy visit to the Ruhr from the 12th to 17th July. They are set forth at greaterlength in the annexed memorandum. I would draw attention more especially to that part of it which deals with the question of the ownership of heavy industries, because it appears to be the one major matter of long-term policyin which there is disagreement with our American Allies.A. German Government for Western GermanyThere appears to be amongst leaders and representatives of the main non-Communist parties a large measure of agreement regarding the need for theearly establishment of a German Government for Western Germany. The attitudeof party leaders is. however, coloured by anxiety not to lay themselves open tolater charges that they have contributed to the division of Germany. They arealso watching events in Berlin with considerable anxiety.B. Currency ReformGeneral approval of currency reform was expressed by all types of Germanrepresentatives I met during my visit. The effect of the reform upon Germanmorale and productivity has been most satisfactory. There are, of course,criticisms. Holders of very small savings and certain classes of wage-earnersfeel they have been hardly treated. Local government authorities are for thetime being without credits and are having difficulties in maintaining housing programmes. Certain governmental contracts have been cancelled and localauthorities experience great difficulties in meeting their social obligations such aspensions to war-widows and assistance to refugees.35715 b
20C. HousingMy visit to the Ruhr served to confirm the impression I had received inBerlin : that lack of living accommodation is the greatest single deterrent to production, the greatest menace to public health and the most destructive socialfactor in Germany to-day.D. Ownership of Heavy IndustriesGerman Trades Union representatives, the British officials connected withthe control of the steel industry and British and United States members of theCoal Control Group all agreed that continued uncertainty about the ownership of the two industries is having an adverse effect upon production.Tears were expressed, particularly in Trades Union circles, that delay willbe exploited on behalf of the private Owners.(Signed) HENDERSON.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,27th July, 1948.ANNEXA. G-erman Government for Western Germany1. There appears to be amongst the leaders and representatives of thepolitical parties a large measure of agreement regarding the need for the earlyestablishment of an independent Government for Western Germany. This view was summarised by Dr. Arnold, Minister-President of Land North Rhine-Westphalia, who informed me that his Cabinet had that same day (12th July)unanimously approved the counter-proposals agreed upon by the Ministers-Presi-dent at Coblenz in reply to the three documents handed to them by the military governors on 1st July. He was optimistic that, if these counter-proposals were accepted, rapid progress would be made towards reaching the objects embodied in the London recommendations even if things were called by different names.He fully accepted the necessity for the establishment of fully recogniseddemocratic institutions as the preliminary to the granting of greater freedom and internal responsibility and as a safeguard against pressure and propaganda fromthe Soviet.2. I am convinced that two important considerations are influencing theGerman mind in this matter : (a) They are most anxious to avoid laying themselves open to the charge that action on their part contributed to the division of Germany or has theappearance of involving their acceptance of a divided Germany. Theywill do nothing which is. calculated to prejudice the restoration of a united Germany, under a responsible German Government. .(b) They are watching developments in Berlin with close scrutiny and con-siderable anxiety. While fully approving Western Allied policy andexpressing whole-hearted admiration of the joint efforts of the RoyalAir Eorce and the United States Air Eorce, they are not certain about Western Allied intentions in what they recogniseto be a difficult situation. They would view with alarm thefuture of democratic forces in Berlin and Western Germanyafter a Western Allied withdrawal from Berlin. The Nazi black terrorwould be paralleled by a Communist Red terror. Until the Berlinissue is settled in favour of the Western Allies, they will be very reluctant to commit themselves too deeply, and, bearing in mind what happened to the democratic leaders who signed the Versailles Treaty,they will be careful not to run the risk of reprisals in the future for&quot;treachery to Germany.&quot;3.   These are the principal reasons, I am convinced, for the counter-proposals which have been put forward.  I believe they are genuine in their desire
for a Western German Government which does not close the door to a Governmentfor a re-united Germany in the future, but an essential support for their politicaland moral courage is unimpaired confidence in the Western Allies. This wouldbe badly shaken if we were to weaken over the Berlin issue.B. Currency Reform4. The introduction of the new currency has had the effect of filling shopwindows with supplies of consumer goods which have in the past been hoardedor sold only on the black market. This development has had an immediate effect upon German morale : workers have become &quot; wage conscious.&quot; The money theyearn has now a real purchasing value and wages have became a powerful incentive to production effort. Avoidable absenteeism has begun to decline and &quot; hidden &quot;labour is being tempted back into employment. In the first fourteen days afterthe reform 1,600 new workers went into the steel industry. The fact that moneyhas started flowing back into the banking system rather more swiftly than hadbeen expected is an indication of public confidence. In the past week, the inflowhas been at the rate of 20-30 million DM a day and although in June arrange-ments had been made with the trade union leaders for wages to be paid, ifnecessary, in instalments, it is now hoped that there will be no difficulty in meetingwage payments up to and including 1st August. There has consequently been lessunemployment than had been feared, though nervousness on this score has not yetbeen wholly allayed.5. Strong criticism was expressed of particular aspects of the measuresadopted. Firstly, large numbers of persons of slender means, with less thanRM 600 in the Savings Bank, have lost all except the per capita issues ofDM 60. Secondly, resentment has been caused by the fact that persons who drewtheir June wages in advance on 1st June received nothing but RM while thosewho received payment after 20th June received wages for the whole of the month in the new currency. More serious criticism arises from the fact that localauthorities have lost the whole of their accumulated credits, including those ear-marked for housing projects, school reconstruction and the development of social services. The Land Government is in similar straits and it is likely to be at leastanother month before any substantial revenue from taxation is available. Whileeffecting the most stringent economies, the Land, in order to avoid large-scaleunemployment, is permitting projects such as road development, which involvelarge wage payments, to continue as before. It will not, however, be possible to finance building programmes on the scale previously intended. As an interim measure a sum of DM 3 million has been made available for housing in LandNorth Rhine-Westphalia, but this is, of course, far from adequate. The LandGovernment feels, in particular, that it is unreasonable for them to be expectedto finance the whole of the miners&apos; housing project.6. On the industrial side the supply of credit is not a matter of serious concern as far as the consumer goods industries are concerned, since the sale ofsuch goods rapidly provides the necessary liquid funds. The situation is moredifficult in the heavy industries whose products involve a long-term turnover,and where credit requirements are correspondingly large. The situation at presentvaries from place to place. Many employers in dusseldorf are already seekingpermission to discharge men. Upon the solution of this problem depends thequestion whether large-scale unemployment will develop. A number of factors,amongst which are the high interest rates and charges for borrowing (whichtogether may total as much as 10-12 per cent.), and the uncertainty regarding thecapital-levy, have resulted in only a small demand for credit to date.7. In spite of the rigid control of circulation credit, prices are alreadytending to rise owing to the eagerness with which wages are being spent onconsumer goods. The good effects of the reform will, in fact, only be able to bemaintained if consumer goods continue to be available.C. HousingQ.,i 0f a pre-war total of 1,250,000 Dwelling Units in the Ruhr, onlydoo,000 remained undamaged in May 1945. 620,000 (i.e., 50 per cent.) were damaged in greater or lesser degree. The remaining 280,000 were totally destroyed,bmce that time rather less than half the damaged houses (230.000) have beenrepaired 330,000 remaining still to be undertaken. Progress has recently been at the rate of about 500 houses repaired each week. The Ruhr population is35715 -  B 2
now substantially of the same size as it was before the war. but only half thepre-war accommodation is available and the density -per Dwelling Unit is double the pre-war figure. In dusseldorf itself, for example, there was before the waran average of 1 - 01 persons to a room : the density is now 2 - 6 to a room. Further-more, many of the rooms inhabited are most unsuitable. I myself visited a cellardwelling of a type still inhabited by no less than 3,500 people in Dusseldorfalone. Some people still live in air raid shelters and very large numbers arein emergency accommodation in barracks, factories, camps, &amp;c. Adults andchildren are herded together in undesirable proximity and conditions are likelyto spread any contagious disease.9. In the coal mining industry, Trades Union officials such as AugustSchmidt, President of the Mineworkers&apos; Union, mine managers and British and united States officials of the Coal Control Group emphasised that housing&quot; wasthe limiting factor on the recruitment of mine-labour. 200,000 new men havebeen attracted to the industry by the incentives we have offered, but there is an overall shortage of- 173,000 dwelling units for miners and their families. Ahigh proportion of the new labour is at present accommodated in camps and inmost cases without their families. Since labour has been attracted from farafield, many of the miners&apos; dependants are still in the Soviet Zone, where, sincecurrency reform, they can no longer receive remittances.10. To meet this situation, local authorities have embarked upon building programmes. In the coal industry there is a eentraUy-administered plan forthe construction during the next four years of 43,250 houses a year. progress has, however, been hampered by shortage of labour, as it has been for a longtime, since even before the war wages in the building trade were low in comparisonwith those in the iron and steel industries. Materials have been lacking andin particular wood, most of which comes from the United States Zone. It isgenerally expected that with the reformed currency both the raw material andthe labour position will improve rapidly. The present difficulties in the wayof the housing programme are therefore almost entirely financial, and althoughtoken credits have been made available by the Land Government, a majority of projects are at a standstill. In the last budgetary year a sum of EM.320 million was made available for the miners&apos; and the general housing programme. Theminers&apos; housing project alone needs credits of DM.12 million a month. Thefinancial experts agree that if inflation is to be avoided it will not be possibleto finance building projects by grants from the Land on anything like this scale.D. Ownership of Heavy Industries11. Both American and British officials of the Coal Control expressed theview that the taking of an early decision either to nationalise the heavy industries or to return them to some form of private ownership was, from a productionpoint of view, more important than the character of the settlement- itself. Thisis interesting in that it demonstrates that the Americans who are in close contact with the mining industry can have little sympathy with the official United States-view that a decision ought to be deferred for 4-5 years.12. I heard considerable misgivings expressed on the score of United Statesdesigns in the Ruhr. The visit of the United States Commission of enquiry into the Steel Industry, in which American commercial steel interests are pre-ponderant, has undoubtedly alarmed German Trades Union opinion. I found,however, that these misgivings were fully shared by the British staff with whom myparty came into contact.13. The British Controller of the North German Iron and Steel Control,who is well qualified to judge the situation, expects the United States Commissionto recommend a substantial investment of American capital in the Ruhr steelindustry. He expects that the Commission will suggest that this development should be made more palatable to German opinion by United States backing fora termination of the reparations and dismantling programme. German arguments that continued dismantling will restrict Germany&apos;s contribution to western european economic recovery fit into the pattern of American policy.14. United States officials in the United Kingdom-United States CoalControl Group made their disapproval of our decartelisation policy in that industry (not   yet carried out) abundantly clear. In its most mild form, theirattitude is that the &quot; horizontal&quot; organisation of industry is inefficient by
comparison with &quot;vertical &quot; organisation. Their attitude to the deeartelisationwhich we have already carried out in the steel industry is certainly eqnallyhostile.15. I found a most unrealistic and out-of-date attitude of mind towardsGerman Trade Unionism among some of the United States officials drawn from american heavy industry whom I met in the Coal Group. It is inappropriate for Western Europe with its much older trade union traditions and practices.The United States Joint Chairman of the Coal Group spoke fervently of the needfor ousting the Works Councils from German Industry as a method of eliminatingCommunist influence. Communist influence in the Councils is a genuine problem,but the Councils are bodies which are of very long standing in Germany and theyare deeply rooted in the traditions of German organised labour. The way to-counter Communist influence in established Trade Union machinery would beby encouraging the strengthening of democratic Trade Unions, recognising thatthey have a proper part to play in industrial and economic planning, and enabling them to carry out the recognised functions of democratic working-class organi-sations. I gathered, however, that there was a tendency for Works councils to intrude into what is the recognised area of responsibility of the Trade Unions(e.g., wage negotiations) and that the latter, for some reason or other, are notresisting this usurpation of function. This seemed to me to be a reflection noton the Works Councils but on the Trade Unions. It may be that the Trade union leaders are activated by political and tactical considerations and that they are notprepared to come into conflict with &quot; militant &quot; members until they have a firmernational policy basis upon which to fight the Communists in the industrial field.16. We have had evidence in the past that strongly suggests the americans are playing for time on the assumption that delay will be to the advantage of theprivate enterprise solutions they favour. I am convinced from my observationsthat this is an extremely dangerous line from the standpoint of both economic-recovery and political stability in Western Germany. I had ample evidence ofthe firm attitude of the Trade Unions against the revival of the old indnstrialcombines and in favour of the public ownership of the basic industries. Thisis an important factor in post-war German life, and one which Allied policy should not seek to frustrate. We have had recent evidence, if such were required,in token strikes arising from the Reusch case, of the present sensitivity of organised labour to the question of ownership of heavy industry.17. The difference of position between the British and the Americans on theissue of ownership is well known among the Germans, both management and workers, in the heavy industries. If the organised workers became convincedthat the present policy of leaving the question of ownership for future determina-tion was of the nature of the &quot; stalling &quot; tactic, the result would be, I believe,serious industrial unsettlement and the creation of conditions which would playright into the hands of the Communists. The prolongation of uncertainty aboutthe right of the German people to settle the question of future ownership bysome form of democratic process is not without dangerous political and industrialpossibilities.


</content>
</cab>
