<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/29/0 images: 165-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT     ^The circulation- of this paper has been strictly limited.  -It is issued for the personal use of.....^        W^vvrstA/vv $f^TOP SECRET Copy No.   ^[CP. (U8) 2072UTH AUGUST.  1 9h8CABINETPALESTINEMemorandum hy the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe resolution adopted by the Security Council on the15th July provides for the continuance of a truce in Palestineuntil a final- political settlement is reached.    The truce,however, is not being fully observed by either side,  and isin constant danger of breaking down.2.        In these circumstances it is imperative that progressshould be made tov/ards a political settlement before thetemporary and precarious stability created by the truce isdestroyed.   When the General Assembly decided on the M+tYi Maythat a Mediator&apos;should be appointed, it was hoped that hewould succeed by negotiation with Arabs and Jews in arriving at a solution in which they would both acquiesce.    But the suggestions which Count Eernadotte subsequently put forwardwere not accepted by either party even as a basis for negotiation.3*.      It has been suggested that gres.ter progress would bemade by means of direct discussion between the Arabs and Jewsthemselves, and the Jewish leaders have publicly proposedthis procedure.    They cannot have supposed, however,  thattheir gesture would have more than a propaganda value, since it is evidently impossible for the two parties to agree uponthe preliminary conditions for direct negotiation.    No Arableader could in present circumstances enter into negotiationswith &quot;the Foreign-Minister of the State of Israel&quot;;    andMr. Shertok for his part would refuse to negotiate under anyother title.h.       There remains only one way in which the foundations of a lasting settlement might be laid during the truce and in whicha breakdown of the latter might consequently be prevented.The United Nations, acting either through the Security council or through the General Assembly, might authorise the Mediatorto put a settlement into effect, and might declare that theuse of force by either party to frustrate this settlement would be regarded as a breach of the truce calling for theimposition of sanctions under Chapter VII of the United nations charter.5.        It is true that the Assembly has already, in itsresolution of the 29th November, 19h7, recommended one political settlement in Palestine.    Subsequently, however, on the1hth May, 19h8, the Assembly terminated the work of theCommission which had been charged with executing its earlierresolution, and established in its place a Mediator with instructions to seek a peaceful settlement.    The United nations have thus recognised the failure of their first attempt to arrive
at a solution, and subsequent events nave confirmed their judgment.    Any new proposals for a peaceful settlement, ifthey are to be realistic, must conform generally with thesituation which no?/ exists in practice in Palestine.    Theexisting situation.differs in the following major respects from the solution recommended by the general Assembly -last november:-(a) the parts of Galilee which were then awarded tothe Arabs have been overman o- Jewish forces;(b) the Egyptian army are holding a line which cutsoff from the Jewish State the whole of thesouthern area (loosely nncwn as the Negeb)awarded to it last November;(c) the Arabs have abandoned the port of Jaffa.;(d) Jerusalem has been partitioned, its eastern half( including the Old 01%-) &quot;being in Arab hands and its western half In Jowls?.6.        In their main outlines, and particularly &quot;by indicating the possibility that the Negeb might &quot;be exchanged for western and central&apos;Galilee, Count BernadotteJs recent suggestionstook account of the military situation,   It say therefore beassumed that he would be prepared to sponsor new proposals ona similarly realistic basis.7.       Count Bernadotte has now asked for the views both ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government and of the United States Governmenton this problem.    Preliminary discussions &quot;between the ForeignOffice and the State Department have shown that the latter are favourably disposed towards a settlement on the lines indicated both by the military situation and hy the MediatorTsprevious suggestions.    The procedure hy which such asettlement might be brought into effect has also been discussed,but in this field agreement has not yet &quot;been reached.8.       Annex A below contains suggestions for the procedure tobe followed in working for a settlement of the kind envisaged in this paper.    Annex B presents the main onillnes of such asettlement.9.       My recommendations are the following:-(i)    that a settlement should be sought by stabilising theexisting de facto situation in Palestine on thelines of Annex Bj(ii)    that discussions with the United States Governmentshould continue on the basis of Annexes A and Bwith a view to agreement upon the details of&quot; sucha settlement,  and to the expression of joint anglo-American views to the Mediator in response to his enquiry;(iii)    that,  if agreement is reached &quot;both, with the UnitedStates Government and with the Mediator on proposals of the kind described, in Annex B,  theinfluence of His Majesty1 s &quot;Government should beused to obtain support for -them froa othermembers of the United Nations.15.3.Foreign Office, S.W.1.20th AUGUST,  &quot;19h8.
-  mANNEX .\A*SUGGESTED procedure in response to his enquiry the Mediator would fee advised by His Majesty &apos;s Government and the United States Qovoxsmsntto make a recommendation to the Security Council on the linesof the draft attached (Annex &apos;B&apos;).2.     Reference.of the whole question for discussion by theGeneral Assembly would much bettor be avoided.    Tike security council can properly deal with the Mediator&apos;s recommendation as a matter affecting international peace and security.    Theeffect of the Security Council endorsing the Mediator-5srecommendation and communicating to all parties as proposedtherein would be to enable the Mediator, to carry but &quot;he taskentrusted to him by the Assembly., of seeking a peaceful solution of the Palestine question.3.      The suggestion has been made that when the Mediator hasmade his recommendation,  statements .approving It should feemade by His Majesty&apos;a Government and the United StatesGovernment who would show that they were deternised, ti cavethese recommendations put into effect by the appropriate oesns.The Jewish authorities and the Trans Jordan Government wouldthen be induced to negotiate within the general framework ofthe recommendations in order to work out a detailed settlement,particularly with regard to the exact position of the frontier.It does not appear to His Majesty&apos;s Government that any suchprocedure is practicable.    It is a cardinal point of the approach to the problem put forward by British representatives in informal discussions with the State Department that neitherparty in Palestine is at all likely to make any positive act of acceptance of the kind of settlement to be proposed toy theMediator, but that both parties might well acquiesce ir it Ifit -were put into effect with sufficient determination.His Majesty&apos;s Government strongly maintain this view and hold,therefore, that it would be useless to ask representatives of either party to negotiate on the execution of the Mediatorsrecommendations,    They would both have objections of principle to doing so.    In particular the suggestion that TransJordanmight be singled out from the Arab States to take part la such negotiations seems particularly dangerous.    The positiveacceptance of any such scheme by Trans Jordan at an early stage would not predispose acceptance of it by other Arab States but would merely serve to make Trans Jordan&apos;s already difficult situation almost intolerable.h.      It is therefore suggested that when the Mediator has made his recommendations the Security Council should be asked to endorse them and to issue the necessary instructions.His Majesty1s.Government and the United States Government would explain the situation fully to the Arab and -Jewish authorities on the basis of the Mediator&apos;s report,  but before this was published,  and would make every possible effort to ensure thatthey would acquiesce in the adoption of the Mediator&apos;3recommendations.&apos;  The two Governments would show that theywere quite determined   that these recommendations should be putinto effect in the shortest possible time and that they wouild -not support any attempt to modify or infringe them.
5.      If it was impossible to obtain the necessary majority inthe Security Council or the proposals.were vetoed there, itwould probably be necessary to take the matter to the assembly in the hope that they would recommend the adoption of theMediator&apos;s proposals and ask the Security Council to take thenecessary action to see that they were put into effect,  but itwould be far better not to have the question discussed in theAssembly until the Security Council had already taken its decision and the necessary measures were being put into effect
ANNEX BOUTLINE OF settlement the most convenient way to present our ideas on thekind of settlement which we should wish to see is in the formin which they would appear if the Mediator agreed to sponsorthem.      In that event he might present a report to the;United Nations on the following lines.2.     The report might begin with a short historical passagerecounting the Mediator1s efforts to maintain the truce andthe various difficulties which he had experienced owing toattempts by both sides to gain advantages for themselves bythe importation of war material and fighting personnel andby military action and owing to the absence of any force withwhich the Mediator could prevent such action.     The Mediatorcould then give his opinion of the relative culpability ofeach side in these matters,3,      The Mediator would no doubt wish to add that in hisattempt to reach a peaceful solution, as he was instructedto do by the Assembly Resolution of 14th May, he has beenthwarted by the entirely incompatible claims of both sides,by the difficulty of bringing them together on any common ground and by the entirely unrealistic picture of thesituation which public opinion on both sides has been allowedto obtain, thus making it more difficult for the leaders toaccept any reasonable compromise.4.      The Mediator might then say that further progress towards a settlement cannot be expected by negotiation between the two parties.      The Jews will only negotiate on the basis, of prioracceptance of the existence of a Jewish state;  the Arabs refuseto recognise the existence of this state and maintain that tonegotiate with its representatives would give away the wholebasis of their position before the negotiations had begun.On the other hand, some success has been achieved, except ina few particularly contentious localities such as Jerusalemand its western approaches, in practical steps to delimit theareas held and administered by either side.     The agreementof local commanders on each side has been obtained to an exactdefinition of a line of this character extending over X kilo-metres.     This process has resulted in a growth of respect forthe status, quo in such areas and has made It easier for united Nations observers to carry out their functions,5.      In spite of this, the continued breaches of the truceand cease-fire make it clear that international peace and security will continue to be endangered by the situation inPalestine unless.a settlement on the following lines isimmediately adopted. - .6.     No further attempt should be. made to negotiate with thetwo parties about the general principles on which a peaceful solution should be reached, but a permanent frontier line should be laid down on the ground as quickly as possible.Failure to respect this line would be regarded as a breach ofthe truce.      The frontier line should be laid down on theground by.a United Nations representative;  the Mediator mightexpress his willingness to assume responsibility for this task.In discharging it he v/ould put into effect the general principles set out below, and would consult appropriate
representatives of &quot;both parties in the&apos; areas concerned.He would also take account of administrative conveniencesand communicationsa      His decision on the location of the&quot;boundary would &quot;be final.7.      Subject to the arrangements mentioned below in regardto Jerusalem and Haifa, the Arab and Jewish authoritiesshall have complete independence on their respective sides of the boundary line.      The provisions of the security council Truce Resolutions -of 29th May and 15th July wouldbe maintained until the Security Council, acting in thelight of advice from the Mediator, decided to terminate them.For a period of six months after the boundary had been laiddown, observers would be maintained on the frontier to ensurethat the Security Council received early and impartial reports on any attempt or alleged attempt.by either side to infringethe boundary,8.     Developing his earlier suggestions, the Mediator might then lay down the following general principles on which the boundary should be drawn.      The division between Arab and jewish areas &quot;should follow very generally the lines now heldby tho forces of either side.      As compared with the boundaryproposed, by the United&apos;Nations Assembly on 29th November, 1947,the Jews would gain Western Galilee and Jaffa.      The Arabswould gain the Negeb, i.e.  the whole area in SouthernPalestine south of the latitude of El Majdel, which theAssembly allotted to the Jews.      This area is larger inextent than the Jewish gain in Western Galilee, but is atpresent very considerably less productive,9.   .   The municipal area of Jerusalem should be a&apos;fullyautonomous unit under neither Arab nor Jewish sovereignty.It would be governed by a Governor responsible to theUnited Nations but appointed in such a way as to avoid a deadlock of the kind which has prevented the establishmentof a Governor in Trieste.     The Governor would be assisted by a force of international police responsible to him.     Aline should be demarcated on the ground in Jerusalem betweenthe existing Arab and Jewish areas,  each of which would have its district municipal administration.      Both municipalbodies would be subject to the overriding authority of theUnited Nations Governor, who -would have powers both of vetoand of initiative.      It would be hoped that after a certaintime the two bodies would fuse into one municipal authority.Meanwhile necessary common services would be operated by special arrangements to be made b&apos;:/ the Governor.     TheGovernor would have special responsibility with regard to therights of the Christian communities and to the preservation of the Holy Places, together with access thereto.10.    There would not be a corridor of Jewish territory-joining Jerusalem to the coast but the United Nations governor would make the necessary arrangements with the Arab and jewish authorities to ensure transit facilities for therequirements of the authorities and all the inhabitants of jerusalem.      Failure by either party to enter into reasonablearrangements or to respect them when they had been made would bo reported to the Security Council.11.    At Haifa a free port should be established covering asufficient part of the port area including the oil dock and the oil refineries and pipeline terminals.      Goods would be
imported and exported through this area on behalf of theJewish authorities and the authorities of the Arab countrieswithout interference and without, payment of customs duties.Agreed facilities would be given for the movement of sealedtrains and road transport on determined routes between thefree port and neighbouring Arab territories       The Arab&apos;authorities would place no obstacle in the delivery of oilby pipeline to the free port.     Any infraction of these arrangements would be dealt with by the Security Oouncil.Pending agreement between the Arab and Jewish authoritiesabout the operation of the ijort and the transit facilities,the free port would be governed &quot;by a United Nations PortCommissioner responsible to the United Nations and havingat his disposal an international police force.      In theabsence of agreement between the Arab and Jewish authorities the Commissioner would demarcate the boundary of the freeport area.     The administration of the free port during thisperiod would bo carried out by a port authority set up by theCommissioner and responsible to him.      The Port commissioner would make every effort to bring about as quickly as possibleagreed arrangements for the operation of the free port andthe failure of either side to agree to reasonable arrangements in this regard..12.    Both parties should have access to Lydda airport.13,    In relation to the Arab areas the Mediator might pointout that it is unlikely that agreement would easily bereached by the- Arab Governments and the representatives of theArabs of Palestine on the disposal of these areas.      It isnecessary, therefore, that the general principles on whichthey should be disposed of must bo laid down by the united nations.      In November, 1947, the General Assembly recommendedthat the Arab areas should form a separate Palostinian arab state.      But this recommendation was bound up with the proposal,since shown to bo impracticable, for an Economic Union ofthe whole of Palestine.  . Without such a Union,  the Arabareas do not form a viable administrative or economic unitby themselves.      It would not &quot;be a permanent solution to setup an independent Aral- state covering this territory.      Theterritory should therefore bo incorporated in Trans Jordan,subject to any frontier rectification which may be desired by the Egyptian Government.   - The Mediator might declare hisreadiness to make the necessary arrangements, after consultationwith the Governments of Egypt and Trans Jordan,     If it -were decided to modify the southern frontier, its new demarcationshould be supervised- by the Mediator.14.    The Mediator might then ask the Security Council to endorse the above recommendations as the only means of ensuring international peace and. security.      They should inform all parties concerned:-(l)  that they should give the Mediator  (or others inauthority charged with demarcating boundaries) all possible assistance in carrying out this task;(2)  that they should respect the United Nations areasin Jerusalem and Haifa and make all necessary arrangements with the United Nations authorities responsible for them;and- &apos; .(o)  that any attempt made during the truce to infringethe new boundaries, once they&apos;were laid down, would be treated .transit facilities.
by the Security Council as a breach of the truce andwould he dealt with under Chapter VII of the United nations charter.15.    The Mediator would presumably include in his recommendations some action as to the Arab refugees.The nature of this recommendation will depend largely on the investigations which he is making into thenumbers of refugees and the proportion of them who wishto move back to the Jewish areas.      Subject to this,the recommendrition might be to the effect that as part ofthe boundary settlement,  the Jewish authorities shouldbe made to allow refugees to come hack or to give themcompensation for the property which they have left behind.The Mediator would report to the Security Council if theJews refused to enter into arrangements which he consideredreasonable.


</content>
</cab>
