<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/29/0 images: 251-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is   the property of  his  britannic  majesty&apos;8  goyernmentPrinted for the Cabinet. September 1948 &apos;       198SECRET Copy No.-1-&quot;&quot; J ICP. (48) 2199th September, 1948CABINETCOMPENSATION TO MINISTERS OE THE CROWN INJURED ORKILLED ON DUTYMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the existing arrangements for providing for the dependants of ministers of the Crown who are killed or injured in the course of their duties cover onlythe risks of travel by air, and need in any event to be reviewed by the Government.I should be glad to know the views of my colleagues on this somewhat personalmatter.  Two points require decision :  (a) Should the State provide compensation when a Minister is killed orinjured on duty?(b) If so, in what form?Should Compensation be Provided f2. No compensation at all was provided up to the 1939 war. Up to then,the family of a &quot;Minister killed or injured on duty depended on his privatefortune or the support of friends and relatives. In the last war, however, withthe greatly increased risks attending air travel, civil servants were allowedto charge to public funds the cost of premiums to insure them, whilst travellingon duty by air, for a sum equal to two years&apos; salary. By analogy this practicewas extended to Ministers. Since the war, this precedent has been followedat least in one case of a Minister making a journey by air. Risks other thanflying risks have not been provided for at all in the case of Ministers.3.   The arguments against giving any compensation are : (a) It might be said that Ministers are provided with a salary sufficient toenable them to insure against such accidents. To provide for compensation out of public funds would be an unjustified supplemen-tation of Ministers&apos; remuneration. (It will be noted that this argument has little force in any event for junior Ministers.)(b) If Ministers are to receive compensation, there may be a demand forthe extension of the practice to cover Members of Parliament.4.   The counter-arguments are : 1(a) Ministers are servants of the State. The State, like any other employer,should cover them as an addition to salary against risks inherent intheir employment.(&amp;) The position of Ministers as servants of the State differentiates themcompletely from private Members.What Form should Compensation take f5.   The choice lies between (a) continuing the war-time practice of taking out premiums with privatecornnanies! nrcompanies; or(6) extending, the Injury Warrant provisions (which are at present confined to civil servants) to cover the case of Ministers as well.35869a
Benefit -provided under these two Systems6. (a) Under the war-time practice, the legal personal representative ofa Minister killed whilst flying on duty would be paid.a sum.equalto his salary for two years.. JSIo doubt for small additional premiumsall Ministers could be insured to cover injury or death in the course- .      of duty, whether arising from air travel or from any other cause.(b) The Injury Warrant provisions would include the following benefits:--(i) A Minister inj used in the course of duty whose capacity to earnhad been totally destroyed would receive a pension of one-thirdof his pay. If the accident proved fatal within seven years,one of the following would apply : (ii) The widow of a Minister killed when flying on duty would receive a pension of one-quarter of his pay together with one-twenty-fourth of his pay for each child up to six.(iii) The widow of a Minister killed on duty in other circumstances would receive a pension of one-sixth of his pay, together with one-forty-eighth of his pay for each child up to six.The Case far and against Continuing the War-time Practice7. The war-time practice is simple, ensures a reasonable amount of com-pensation for death or injury while travelling by air and could be extended tocover other risks. It could be continued without legislation and would not belikely to be the subject of special attention in Parliament. In this way thedanger of a demand from private Members for similar provision would bereduced. (It is clear that special Parliamentary notice is unlikely if all thatis done is to continue, as at present, to cover air travel risk. But it is doubtfulwhether such a limited arrangement could be regarded as a satisfactory solution.Certainly a difficult situation would arise if a Minister with no large privatemeans should be killed on duty in, e.g., a motor smash, and no provision couldbe made for his dependants save by ad hoc personal legislation.)On the other hand, it is undoubtedly wrong that the State, which in almost every other field carries its own risks, should, in this particular matter, pay for the risk to be carried by private companies. If at any time the practicebecame known, it might be alleged that the only reason why it had been adoptedwas the desire to avoid drawing public attention to it.The Case for and against Extending the Injury Warrant Provisions to Ministers8. The extension of the Injury Warrant provisions to Ministers wouldgive Ministers automatic cover without the necessity of taking out insurancepolicies from time to time. These provisions would also secure a reasonablebenefit.   The objections to this course are : (a) The Injury Warrants are part of the general superannuation code for civil servants. It may be argued that it is inappropriate to applya practice introduced for the benefit of civil servants to cover thecase of Ministers who otherwise are not provided for anywhere inthe superannuation code.(6) This course would involve legislation. An early opportunity can be found for this legislation in the Civil Service Superannuation Bill to beincluded in the programme for next Session, but, in the process, acertain amount of public interest in the matter would be inevitableConclusion9.   I think therefore that my colleagues should decide : (a) whether compensation should be provided; and(b) if so, whether this compensation should be ensured by continuing thewar-time practice of taking out insurance policies or&apos; by extending the injury Warrant to cover Ministers as well as civil servants.If it is felt that insurance policies should be continued, the further pointarises whether the risks covered should be extended to injury or death in thecourse of duty generally and not only while on a journey&quot;by air.R. S. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,9th September, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
