<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/29/0 images: 254-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (U8)  2209th. September, 19k8.EIRE AND THE BRITISH commonwealth memorandum by the Secretary of State for CommonwealthRelations1. On 17th August I circulated to my colleagues amemorandum (CP. (U8) 205) with regard to certain statements which had been made by Eire Ministers on the subject of Eire&apos;srelationship with the Commonwealth.      In that memorandum Iraised the question whether, in view of a statement byMr. Costello that Eire is no longer a Member of the Commonwealthit would be right for us to renew the invitation to him toattend the October meeting of commonwealth  /ealth Prime Ministers.2. Since my memorandum was circulated, there have beendevelopments which I think it right to bring to the immediatenotice of my colleagues.3. . Agreement having been reached with all overseaCommonwealth Prime Ministers that there should be a meetingof Prime Ministers in London in October, our Representative in -Eire was instructed at the end of last week to sound eire ministers informally (Mr. Costello is at present in Canada)with a view to ascertaining whether it would be an embarrassment to Mr. Gostello to receive an invitation to the meeting.      Itwas hoped that the view of Mr.- Costello might be obtainedspeedily, since it is important that, when the announcement ofthe forthcoming Commonwealth Prime ministers meeting is made(and we ought to make it at the beginning of next v/eek), bothwe and the Government of Eire should be in a position to answerenquiries whether or not Eire will be represented.k. Lord Rugby duly raised this question with the EireMinister for External Affairs (Mr. MacBride).    Lord Rugbyunderstood that Mr. MacBride would summon a special meeting ofthe Eire Cabinet to consider the matter and would let us have their reply by Saturday of this week.5* Meanwhile, Mr. Costello in Canada made some remarksat a press conference, of which my colleagues have no doubtseen reports in the press.     Although we have no exact text ofwhat he said, the consensus of the reports received shows that      he told the assembled press conference that Eire was preparing to repeal the External Relations Act of 1936, which he described as &quot;full of inaccuracies and infirmities11.      (As explained in CP. (b-8) 205, the termination of this Act wouldin fact remove the last formal link between Eire and theCommonwealth).     Mr. Gbstello added that whether Ireland was-   &quot;a Member of the Commonwealth&quot; was just a phrase;    it was thepractical association that counted.      I understand that in factCOPY NOGABINET
the whole drift of his remarks at the conference showed that what he has in mind is &quot;association with the Commonwealth&quot;,instead of formal Membership of the Commonwealth.6. It so happened that when the reports of Mr. Costello&apos;sstatement appeared in the press on 8th September I was myselfin Dublin, and Lord Rugby had previously arranged for me tomeet Mr. MacBride at lunch.     Mr. MacBrid.e told me that the eire Government had decided to repeal the External relations act, which they regarded as anomalous and as out of accord with the realities of the situation:    but it was equally their desire to have the most friendly possible relations with theUnited Kingdom and the other countries of the Commonwealth.Mr. MacBride then raised the question of the October meeting,and said that he thought his Cabinet would decide that eire ministers should attend,  provided that it was clear that Eirewas not represented as a Member of the British Commonwealthbut as a country associated with the Commonwealth.      He also said that the Government of Eire, if they were represented atthe meeting, would expect to discuss the question of Partition.Mr. MacBride went on to say that the Government of Eire, beforeagreeing to be represented at the meeting, would expect these points to be accepted and made clear in an exchange of lettersbetween the two Governments, which might subsequently bepublished.7. Clearly this statement of the Eire Government&apos;intention raises grave problems both for this country and forthe Commonwealth.     Y/e shall have tc- think of the longer term problem - the relationship of Eire to the Commonwealth aftershe has severed this lost formal link.      But the urgent problem is the question of Eire&apos;s presence or otherwise at the forthcomingPrime Ministers&apos; meeting,  and In particular the question whether&apos;&apos;we can, either of ourselves or in consultation with other commonwealth Governments, agree to an exchange of letters inwhich Eire would impose,  and we would accept, conditionsattaching to her presence.8. On this problem Lord Rugby!s view would be,  Iunderstand, that we ought seriously to consider taking the risk.The link in the External Relations Act Is tenuous;    the realityis the close geographical, financial, economic and culturalrelationship between Eire and the United Kingdom.      Would it not be well, for the sake of the substance of that relationship,to accept the removal of the shadow?     If so, could we not bring ourselves to alloy; Eire to come to the October meeting,even though she came explicitly as a country which did not regard herself as a Member of the British Commonwealth, but asa country associated with the Commonwealth?9. As I see the position (and I have had less time toconsider it than I would wish) there are conflictingconsiderations which may be briefly set out as follows:-In favour.     The whole historical development of theCommonwealth is based on reasonable compromise andon a willingness to discard forms in favour of substance.Against.,     Whatever our decision may be on the longer term problem, we can hardly decide so important an issue in a matter of days before we have to announceto the world that there will be a Prime Ministers&apos;meeting in October.      If we accepted Eire&apos;s firstcondition, we should, in fact, be pre-judging the
question of &quot;two tier&quot; association &quot;between countriesin o Commonwealth of British Nations and associated powers.      This question has already been gone Intoat great length and ministers views have so far beenagainst it.      No doubt it will come up daring thePrime Ministers&apos; meeting;   bat there Is everyindication that the question will need, most careful handling,  and we know that some Members of theCommonwealth are averse from any such idea.     Wecould not accept the Sire condition without prejudicing the position;    and we should most certainly have to consult the other Governments before we did so.      Itwould be embarrassing to all concerned to ask Indiaand Pakistan for their views on this point at thepresent stage.10. As regards Partition, there seesi to use to be serious objections to a discussion in a full conference with all thePrime Ministers.      Indeed, I do not believe that therepresentatives of the old Dominions would agree to discusswhat in the past they have always regarded as a domesticBritish Isles question.      But if we did agree to discuss it,the door would then be open for the ventilation at themeeting of other disputes between Members of the Commonwealth.So far it has been agreed that there should be no discussion in the full meetings of such questions, e.g. the troublesbetween India and Pakistan and the troubles between India,Pakistan and South Africa.     We have already explained to thePrime Minister.of Pakistan that such questions cannot beraised and Dr. Malan has stipulated that South Africa will only be represented if there is no question of discussingher dispute with India and Pakistan.11. I am sorry to have tc circulate this paper at suchshort notice,  and I would&quot;ask for my colleagues&apos; indulgence,and for an expression of their views st tomorrow!s Cabinet.My own tentative conclusion is this:-(1)    We should proceed with the Issue of oar announcementof the Commonwealth Prime ministers meeting andshould say in answer to any enquiries about the attendance of Eire that we are not yet in aposition to say whether or not Eire will be there.(2)    We should await the reply from Sire (which i hope will not be conveyed in the form or a writtendocument)  and should then consider urgently the implications of what is said on attendance at thePrime Ministers&apos; meeting.      There will &quot;be time forthis and for consultation with other commonwealth governments,  if that should prove necessary.It may be, for instance, that the reply will beso worded that, as host Government, we may feel able to take our own decision and aerely notifyother Commonwealth Governments of what we are doing.(3)    We should consider at greater leisure the questionof the effect on our relationship with Sire ofwhat is said in that reply, ana the announcedintention of the Eire Government to repeal the external Relations Act.      This does not press sostrongly, and it may well be that It- Is the sort of topic which we shall have to discuss with theother Commonwealth-Prime Ministers in October.
(h)    If it were to be decided that Eire should notbe represented at the Prime Ministers&apos; meeting,and that she cannot be fitted into the presentpattern of the Commonwealth,  even with any modifications which may result from the Octobermeeting, our general policy should nevertheless be warmly to welcome Eire&apos;s desire for close relations and to do nothing now to prevent hermembership of any new type of Commonwealthorganisation which might emerge in the future.P. J.H.-B.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W.19th September,  19U8.


</content>
</cab>
