<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/79/0 images: 105-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 THIS DOGUMBNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)I E ORE T.COPY NO.CABINET    21 (54) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.  10, downing street,  S.W.I.,  on WEDNESDAY,  16th MAY, 1934,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS    -    (if required).2. jRTP^ncsrnxbN and limitation dp armaments - (if renuired.2A.     PROPOSED EUROPEAN CONVENTION AGAINST AIR BOMBARDMENT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs. 101]CP.  137 (34)    -   already circulated.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.CP.  138 (34)    -   already circulated.4.    PROPOSED RESTRICTION ON SaLE OF AERONAUTICAL material to GERMANY.(Reference Cabinet 7 (34) Conclusion l).Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs and the Secretary of State for Air.CP. 136 (34)    -    circulated herewith.5.    LICENSING AND SUMMER TIME.(Reference Cabinet 19 (34) Conclusion 7).Memorandum by the Home Secretary?CP. 135 (34)    -    already circulated..6.    UNEMPLOYMENT BILL:     DATE OF OPERATION OF unemployment assistance BOARD.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.CP.  134 (34)    -    already circulated.7.     TITHE RENT CHARGE.(Reference Cabinet 20 (34) Conclusion 8).Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.CP.  124 (34)    -    already circulated.
[IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYTS GOVERNMENT)E C R E T.COPY NO.CABINET    81  (54).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street,  S..W.1. ,  on WEDNESDAY,  16th MAY, 1934,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.I1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS(if required).\2.    REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS    -    (if required,(Reference Cabinet 20 (34) Conclusion 3).3.     IMPERIAL DEFENCE POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 20 (34) Conclusion 4).4.    PROPOSED RESTRICTION ON SaLB OF AERONAUTICAL material to GERMANY.(Reference Cabinet 7 (34) Conclusion l).Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs and the Secretary of State for Air.CP.  136 (34)    -    circulated herewith.5&apos;     LICENSING AND SUMMER TIME.(Reference Cabinet 19 (34) Conclusion 7).Memorandum by the Home Secretary?CP.  135 (34)    -   already circulated..6.    UNEMPLOYMENT BILL:    DATE OF OPERATION OF unemployment assistance BOaRD.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.CP.  134 (34)    -   already circulated.7.     TITHE RENT CHARGE.(Reference Cabinet 20 (34) Conclusion 8).Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.CP.  124 (34)    -   already circulated.
8. CONCLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.10th Conclusions (34) of the Home Affairs Committee,To be circulated.1.    Merchandise Marks  (Trade Descriptions) Bill.Memorandum by the President of theBoard of Trade, covering draft Bill.H.A.  30 (34)    -   already circulated.2.    Statutory Salaries_(Restoration) Bill.Memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer, covering draft Bill.H.a.  31 (34)    -   already circulated.3.    Trustee Savings Banks (Special Investments)Bill.Memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer, covering draft Bill.H.A.  32 (34)    -   already circulated.4.    Administration of Justice  (Appeals) Bill.Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor,covering draft Bill.H.A.  33 (34)    -    already circulated.TO TAKE NOTE OF:9.-LIBERIA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.CP.  133 (34)    -   already circulated.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HaNKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.I Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.,14th May,  1934,
fcglg DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).B E C R B T. COPY NO.CABINET    21 (34).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,16th MAY, 1934, at 11.0 a.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon.  J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (in the Chair).IJDbe Right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P. ,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt., D.S.O.,M.P., Secretary of State for home Affairs.Che Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.She Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt. , G.G.S.I. ,G.B.E. , C.M.G., M.P. , Secretary:;j    of State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E., M.C., M.P., Secretary of!)    State for the Colonies.the Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton-Young,I    G. B.E. , D.S.O. , D.S.C., M.P. ,I   Minister of Health.Ihe Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres Mensell,G.B.E., M.P., First Lord ofI    the Admiralty.the Right Ron.I   Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andm   Fisheries.jMajor The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M,P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,K.C.V.O.,  O.B.E.,  K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry, .K.G., M.V.O., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Walter Runeiman, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K. G. ,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Presidentof the Board of Education.The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt., C.B.E.,M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Postmaster-General.polone! Sir Maurice Hankey, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O.,  ......    Secretary.
imperial defence policy.Report ofthe DefenceRequirementsCommittee.(previous reference:Cabinet 20(34), Con-clusion 4.)1. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs reported that the Ministerial Committee, on Disarma-ment had held, a number of meetings on the Report ofthe Defence Requirements Committee and had made agood deal of progress.
REDUCTION and limitation of armaments.Proposed.EuropeanConventionagainst air bombardment.(previous reference:Cabinet 20(34), Oon-clusion 2.)F.R.2. The Cabinet had before them the following documents on the subject of a proposed EuropeanConvention against Air Bombardment:-A Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (CP.-137 (34)) proposing,in view of the urgent situation which will arise if on and after May 29th (the dateof the meeting of the General Commission ofthe Disarmament Conference.)  it is manifestthat general disarmament, agreement is impos-sible, a Convention to be signed by theStates of Europe undertaking not to dropbombs from the air on one another&apos;s territory,whether in peace or in war.   He would lim.itthe proposal to Europe,  in order to savedelay and to enable the Convention to be negotiated outside the machinery of Geneva.Only in this way could Germany be broughtinto conference, and. it was essential thatshe should be a party .   He would add to theConvention a sanction that if any partyviolated the agreement the other signatorieswould, undertake to employ their air forces to vindicate the Convention and to restrain the wrongdoer.   Annexed to C.P.-137 (34)was a Memorandum by the parliamentary secretary, Foreign Office, working out inmore detail some of the ideas contained inthe Secretary of Staters Memorandum:A Memorandum by the Secretary of State forAir (CP.-138 (34)) pointing out the disastrous consequences that would follow the adoption of the above proposal and the anomalies of its application:    that itcould not stand the test of war:    and thatthe sanctions behind it could never be putinto operation.   The Secretary of Statedescribed the proposal as impracticableand detrimental to our essential interests:that it would do nothing to facilitate thelimitation of air armaments, and would not afford to the civil population any protec-tion against aerial bombardment, but on thecontrary would inevitably expose them tothe full effects of unrestricted bombardmentby air forces upon whose size and potential-it ies no limit was proposed.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said,that a decision on this matter was urgent from two points of view.    Firstly, because the Lord Presidentof the Council had. declared in the House of Commons,on behalf of the Government, that if the DisarmamentConference were to fail we should aim. at the promotion of an Air Convention, at any rate for Europe.   Conse-quently the Government would be pressed, on this question
Secondly, because the Disarmament Conference wasevidently on its last legs.    It was clear from thelatest telegrams from the Lord Privy Seal, at Geneva,that Prance was not going to put forward any new proposals.   Within the next few weeks, therefore,  anew situation must arise.   Public opinion would recognise that the Government had been very patientand had made great efforts, but would ask what was thepresent position.   Anything we put forward should belimited to Europe.   That was a sentiment - that hethought was shared by the French themselves.   Anyproposal must also be one which, would enable Germanyto be brought into the discussions.    For these reasonssomething must be done.   His own forecast was thatthe Geneva Conference would not end abruptly.   perhaps the whole question of Disarmament would be passed tothe Council of the League.   As soon as the UnitedKingdom Delegates returned, therefore, the next step would have to be decided.    He thought there was a replyto the various points made by the Secretary of Statefor Air, but at any rate the whole subject ought to bediscussed in detail.The Secretary of State for Air said he had a lot tosay on the subject, when the right opportunity arrived.He regretted that he had been obliged to disagree with most proposals of this character, which, on examination in detail, had. proved impracticable.The Prime Minister thought, it was essential thatthe subject should be discussed in greater detail than was possible in the time available to the full Cabinet.The Cabinet agreed  
Ministerial Committee wished to consult him.NOTE:   The time of the Meeting was originally fixed, for 11 a.mbut this was changed afterthe Cabinet Meeting to 11-3a .m.)
SALE OFAERONAUTICALMATERIAL TOGERMANY.^proposedRestrict ionon.(previous reference:Cabinet 7(34), Con-elusion 1.)3. The Cabinet had before them a Joint Memorandumby the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theSecretary of State for Air (C..P.-136 (34)) on thequestion of restriction on the sale of aeronauticalmaterial to Germany.   The Memorandum recalled that under the Cabinet decision of July 2ft, 1933 (Cabinet49 (33), Conclusion 4) certain Governments were informedthat His Majesty&apos;s Government were ready, should, those governments be prepared to take corresponding action,to request British aircraft and engineering manufactur-ers not to conclude any agreement for the sale of aircraft or engines or of the manufacturing rightstherein to the German Government direct, or to any german Ministry or public authority, and particularly the Police, unless they had received a categoricalwritten assurance from the German Government that thematerial or rights in question would not be used forany purpose forbidden by the Paris Air Agreement of1926.   The majority o^ the Governments approached had intimated their agreement with the procedure proposed,but the United States and Italian Governments had declined to accept it.    On the other hond,, a French note of November 27th suggested an extension of the scopeof the procedure originally proposed, and an agreement on a closer definition of the characteristics of the engines, etc,, the export of which to Germany theGovernments concerned would agree to prevent.    It wasplain that the United States and Italian governments would not agree to this suggestion either:    and theAir Ministry also opposed it.    In the circumstances it seemed useless to continue the attempt to negotiateany special agreement on the subject, and the only course still open appeared to be to inform theGovernments previously consulted that, as it had been impossible to secure general approval of the proposals
11put forward last year, His Majesty&apos;s Government, sofar as the export of aircraft and aeronautical material to Germany was concerned, intend simply to continue todo all in their power to ensure that no breaches ofthe relevant international instruments occur, and thatthey feel sure that the other Governments concerned will act similarly *In the course of discussion it was suggested thatsome means ought to be found to let the general publicknow the large amounts of war material that were being sent to Germany by other countries;    for example, theUnited States of America and Sweden.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointedout that the buying by Germany of engines capable ofbeing used in civil aviation was not a breach either of the Treaty of Versailles or of the Paris Air Agree-ment.   There were, of course, many parts of aircraft-that could be used either for military or civil machines.The Prime Minister thought it important that the story of what we had proposed and how we had beenthwarted by other countries should be published.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs saidhis idea was to start a statement with the story ofour efforts to stop the supply of arms to Bolivia andParaguay and to build up on that basis.Tn this connection the President of the Board ofTrade invited attention to an Answer he had. given inthe House of Commons on May 15th (Parliamentary Debates,Vol. 889, No.94, Cols. 1617-1618), when he had shownthat our exports of war material to the belligerent-countries had been so small as to enable us to repudiate    1&quot;any responsibility whatever for hostilities betweenBolivia and Paraguay&quot;.
The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should be author-is ed to proceed as proposed in his  -Memorandum, namely, not to continuethe attempt to negotiate any special agreement on the subject, but to informthe Governments previously consultedthat, as it had been impossible tosecure general approval of the pro-posals put forward last year, HisMajesty&apos;s Government, so far as theexport of aircraft and aeronauticalmaterial to Germany was concerned,intend simply to continue to do allin their power to ensure that nobreaches of the relevant international agreements occur, and that they feel sure that the other Governmentsconcerned will act similarly:(b) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should make a state-ment in Parliament, on the lines indicated in the discussion at theCabinet, to justify the action ofthe British Government in thismatter:(c) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for Air,should select the most appropriate moment at which to take the aboveaction.
LICENSING :EXTENSION OFPERMIT&quot;1 EHFOURS.previous reference:Cabinet 19(34), C on-clusion 7.)F.R.(3k)ID,ill4. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Home Secretary fG.P.-135 (34)) stating that theCourt of Appeal had upheld the decision of the HighCourt in the case of Rex v, Sussex Licensing Justices,,ex parte .?ubbt declaring invalid an Order by the licensing Justices for the Steyning Division extending the night closing hour to 10-30 p.m. during summertime, on the ground that any such Order could, only bemade for the whole of the year.   The Memorandumexplained that the granting of late night extensionfor the summer months only had a useful and. appropriateapplication to such places as holiday resorts, whichmight not require the later hour during the winter &quot;months, and that its abolition would give rise towidespread dissatisfaction.   The Home Secretary thereforeashed authority to introduce a Dill at as ear 13/ a date as could be arranged and to announce the government&apos;s decision before the Recess.   The effect of the proposed bill would be to amend the Licensing Act, 1921, so as -(i)  to provide for the validation of theSteyning Order and of all similarOrders at present in force which extendor vary the permitted hours for part ofthe year only ,    and(ii) to enable Licensing Justices to make such Orders in the future.There would, also be a provision limiting the duration of the Act to the end of 19 35,  after which it couldbe extended, if necessary,    under the Expiring   LawsC ont inuanc e proc e dur e .After a short discussion the Cabinet agreed - To approve the proposals of the HomeSecretary as set forth in CP.-135 (34)and summarised, above, subject to -(i) the omission, from, the Bill ofthe Clause proposed in paragraph  of CP.-1.35 (34) authorisingLicensing Justices to fix amorning opening hour earlier than the normal limit of 11 a ..m.:(ii) the omission of the provisionproposed in paragraph 8 of cp.-135 (34) to limit the duration of the Act.-r-
BILL.ate of Opera-tion of theUnemploymentAssistanceBoard.(previous reference:Cabinet 69(33), Con-cIrs ion 1.)f-.fi.a &amp; gw 7*5. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Labour (C,P,-134 (34)) on the subject ofthe date of operation of the Unemployment assistance board, set up under the Unemployment Bill.    In his memorandum the Minister stated that it was anticipatedthat the Bill would receive the Royal Assent at theend of June and. that the Unemployment Assistance board would be appointed early in July.    The Board would notbe taking over the work until two Appointed. Days, thefirst Appointed Day being the date from which the Boardtook back from the Public Assistance Authorities theduty of administering transitional payments, and thesecond. Appointed Day the date from which the unemployed,persons now on Poor Relief would be transferred to theBoard.    It was from, this second day that the financialrelief to local Authorities contemplated by the bill would come into operation, and the Local authorities were therefore pressing for the Appointed Days to befixed as early as possible.   Having regard to all the considerations put forward in his Memorandum, theMinister of Labour believed that it would be preferable to make the first Appointed Day fall somewhere in thesecond week in January, and the second. Appointed Dayeight weeks later.The Minister of Labour made a statement to theCabinet on the lines of his Memorandum, explaining,among other things, the technical difficulties in theway of fixing the Appointed Days any earlier than hehad proposed.In the course of discussion it was suggested thatif the second Appointed Day were deferred, until march the local Authorities would feel aggrieved, and would increase the pressure (of which there- was alreadysome indication) to be indemnified for the additional cost that would fall upon them.
The difficulties of the Minister of Labour were fully recognised, but it was suggested, that it mightnot be impossible to fix an earlier date than thatat present proposed.   It was true that the localAuthorities would not be in session in August andthe first half of September, but it was suggestedthat negotiations could be carried on with the officials.The Prime Minister summed up the discussion tothe effect that the Cabinet were in agreement thatthe Minister of Labour should   hasten the procedureso far as was compatible with administrativeatefficiency.   He thought that/the time of the municipal Elections the impression would be bad ifit could be represented that the Local authorities were being left to face the winter without theadvantages of the new Unemployment Assistanceorganisation. -The First Commissioner of Works appealed to theMinister of Labour to let him know as soon aspossible if the Appointed Days were advanced, asthe provision of the necessary office acconmodationinvolved considerable difficulty.On the suggestion of the Minister of Labour theCabinet agreed  That the Minister of Labour should discuss the matter with theChancellor of the Exchequer, theMinister of Health and the first commissioner of Works, and make adefinite proposal to the Cabinet.
ft(Previous (34)) on the position relative to the Tithe Bill,Reference:Cabinet SO briefly summarised at the head of the Conclusion recorded(34), 0 on-clusion 8.)        in the margin.    At the previous Meeting no decision had^een taken, owln? to the unavoidable absence of theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries made astatement to the Cabinet in which he discussed fourpossible courses:    (l) to proceed with the Bill withoutannouncing an enquiry;    (2) to proceed with the bill and at the same time to announce an enquiry but withoutincluding a time limit in the Bill;     (3)  to proceed withthe Bill and to announce an enquiry but to include atime limit in the Bill;    (4) to drop the Bill.      Thefirst proposal was not practical.      The second proposal had been received with some favour by the Cabinet.The third proposal had been fairly strongly pressed on the ground that the passage of the Bill could not besecured without the inclusion of a time limit.      the argument against the time limit was strong;    namely,that a big change in law was involved and it would bedifficult to defend it if limited to only two years.He said that the Bill included everything that was withinthe range of action by the Department,      The reason hehad in the past opposed an enquiry was that sooner or later it would raise questions involving the Treasury.The scheme of the Bill was tosecure alleviation both to tithe payers and tithe owners.      If money was owedand justly owed there ought to be legal means forsecuring payment.-    The case of the tithe payer wasthat it was not justly owed.      Consequently, either some form of compensation or some form of resistancehad to be contemplated.      To proceed with the Bill aswell as with an enquiry would get rid of most of the-11-THE TITHE 6.      The Cabinet again had before them a Memorandum&quot;Ly the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries (C.P.-134
immediate difficulties but the ultimate difficultiesresulting from the case against tithe would remain.He had been struck by the small smount of supportgiven to the Church of England in the controversy.The ordinary farmer and the ordinary Member ofParliament suggested that the Church ought to be deprived of tithe.      That could not be done withoutconsidering the position in which the Church was left.      He was opposed to a time limit which wouldinvolve the Government in difficulties when it came to an end.        He thought the alternatives were eitherto go forward with the Bill and with the enquiryor to drop the Bill and have an enquiry.        he agreed with the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s proposal that he should be consulted both as to the termsof reference and the personnel of an enquiry.The Secretary of State for War as Leader ofthe House of Lords, informed the Cabinet Committeethat the Central Landowners Association refusedto compromise.      He recalled that there was a motiondown in the House of Lords by Lord Strachie thatthe question should be sent to a Select Committee.In the course of the discussion misgivingswere expressed as to the Bill and there was some support for the view that it should be dropped ifmeans could be found without undue loss of prestige.The Lord Chancellor, after reviewing thequestion, suggested that there was much to be said for trying to work out a plan for the redemptionof tithe even if it involved some loss to the Churchwhich the Church itself might have to make good ashad been done in Wales.        His own experience inChurch patronage showed that benefices dependenton tithe were not popular with the clergy, partly owing to the difficulty of collecting the tithe andpartly to the friction it created with parishioners.-12-
The suggestion was made that if the bill were allowed to go to a Select Committee of theHouse of Lords and prior to its formation the by a Royal CommissionGovernment were to announce an enquiry/with a wideterms of reference, it was by no means improbable that the Select Committee would advise that therewas no advantage in proceeding with the Bill untilthe Royal Commission&apos;s enquiry had been completed.^ The Cabinet agreed -i   (a)    That there was no objection to theproposal that the Tithe Bill should bereferred to a Select Committee of theHouse of Lords.(b) That at the same time an announcement should be made in the House of Lordsthat a Royal Commission was to be setup to enquire into the whole question of the with a wide terms of reference,(c) That the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries should discuss the terms ofreference and the personnel of theCommittee with the Chancellor of theExchequer and other Departmentsconcerned,(d) That the Royal Commission should beset up as soon as possible.   ,
COMMITTEE OPHOME AFFAIRS,Procedure of,(previous reference:Cabinet 5 (34Conclusion 137.    During the discussion of Bills submittedby the Committee of Home Affairs the Prime minister pointed out two defects in the present procedure:(l)  that there was a tendency to bring Billsbefore the Committee on subjects which had not been previously submitted to the Cabinet;     (2) that theParliamentary Secretary to the Treasury wasfrequently not present to advise the Committeeon the parliamentary aspects of these Bills.The Cabinet were informed that owing to the many preoccupations of the Parliamentary Secretaryto the Treasury he was sometimes unable to be present.The Cabinet agreed -(a) That Bills should not be brought&quot;before the Committee of Home Affairswithout prior approval of theprinciples embodied in the Bill by theCabinet.(b) To take note that the Prime minister would consult the parliamentary secretary to the Treasury about hisattendance or representation at theCommittee of Home Affairs.
T&quot;HE MERCHANDISEMARKS (TRADEDESCRIPTIONS)Bill.3(previous ousRef reference e:Cabinet 7(87), Con-elusion 1 &amp;Appendix.)8*     The Cabinet had under consideration a Memorandumby the President of the Hoard of Trade (H..A.-30 (34))covering the draft Merchandise Marks (Trade De-scrip-tions) Bill, which was designed to amend, the merchant-dise Marks Act, 1887, -    so as  to enable Orders inCouncil to be made assigning statutory meanings totrade terms in relation to any class or description of goods:    together with the following recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 10thConclusions (34), Minute 1) :-&quot;To authorise the introduction forth-with. in the House of Commons of theMerchandise Marks (Trade Descriptions)Bill in the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-30 (34), subject- to any drafting or other minor alterations that might be found, necessary or desirable, on the understanding thatit might not be possible, owing tothe state of Parliamentary business,to proceed beyond, the First ReadingStage of the Bill in the present session,&quot;Some doubts were expressed at the Cabinetabout this Bill and attention was drawn to thefollowing passage in the Memorandum by the Presidentof the Board of Trade,(H.A, 30 (34) 6 (d))  -&quot;There will probably be considerable opposition from the fancy goods trades.      Theyare interested in such a wide variety of goodsthat they would be affected by a large numberof applications and would probably find itnecessary to appear at a correspondingly largenumber of enquiries,&quot;Experience showed that in cases of this kindopponents were often vociferous while the friends of the Bill remained silent.      The cumulative effectof departmental Bills of this kind was disadvantageousto the Government.The Cabinet agreed -(a) That the President of the Board of trade should consult the Parliamentary Secretaryto the Treasury about the prospects of the Bill in the House of Commons andreport to the Prime Minister.(b) That the subject should be placed on theAgenda at the next meeting of the Cabinet.
9.  The Cabinet had under consideration a Memo-ran dura by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (H.A.-31(34)) covering the draft Statutory Salaries (Res tor a-tion) Bill, which sought to give effect to theannouncement made in the course of the Budget speech on April 17th last that one-half of the salary exitsmade under the emergency arrangements of October 1,1931, should, be restored as from July 1,  1934:together with the following recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 10thC onelus ions (34), minute e 2):-&quot;To authorise the introduction forth-with in the House of Commons of theStatutory Salaries (Restoration)Bill in the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-31 (34), subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that might be found necessary or desirable irable.&quot;The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs asset forth above.
THE TRUSTEESAVINGS BANKS(SPECIAL IN-VESTMENTS)BILL.previous reference:Cabinet  36(S0),  Con-clusion 2.)10.   The Cabinet had under consideration a Memo-ran dum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (H.A.-32(34)) covering the draft Trustee Savings Banks(Special Investments) Bill, which was designed toextend the powers now possessed, by Trustee savings banks in connection with the investment of moneysreceived in the Special Investment Department ofthose banks:    together with the following recommen&amp;ation of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.010th Conclusions (34), Minute 3):-&apos;&quot;To authorise the introduction forth-with in the House of Lords of the trustee Savings Banks fSpecialInvestments) Bill in the form ofthe draft annexed to H.A.-32 (34),subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that might befound necessary or desirable,&quot;The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs asset forth above.
ADMINISTRATIONfrOF JUS&quot;ICE(APPEALS)  BILL11.  TheCabinet had under consideration a Memorandumby the Lord Chancellor (H.A.-33 (3.4)) covering thedraft Administration of Justice (Appeals) Bill, which(previous reference:Cabinet 35(33), Con-elusion 10.)was designed to reduce the number of appeals inlitigation.After drawing attention to the views expressedby the Solicitor-General on the subject of the appoint-ment of additional Judges, the Committee of HomeAffairs/made the following recommendation to theCabinet (H.A.C. 10th Conclusions (34), Minute 4):-&quot;To authorise the introduction forthwith in the Hou.se of Lords  of the Administra-tion of Justice (Appeals) Bill in theform of the draft annexed to H.A.-33 (34),subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that might be found, necessary or d e s ir ab 1 e .&quot;The Cabinet agreed -(a) To approve the recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs as set forth above.(b) To agree with the Lord Chancellor thatthe question of increasing the number of judges should not be considered untilevery effort had b een made, such as thatincluded in the present Bill, to effecteconomy in litigation.had
LIBERIA. 12.    The Cabinet took note of a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs  (CP.-133 (34))containing a record of some conclusions reached in theForeign Office as to the line which should be taken on the subject of Liberia, at the approaching meetingof the Council of the League of Nations.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.,16th May,  1934.-19-

</content>
</cab>
