<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/79/0 images: 200-219</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^DOCUMENT IS the PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT) j. &amp;^fljjl. E T. COPY NO.0&apos; CABINET    85  (34).Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at No.  10, downing street,  S.W.I., on TUESDAY,  19th JUNE, 1934,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS    -    (if required).2.    REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.(Reference Cabinet 23 (34) Conclusion l).3*    IMPERIAL DEFENCE POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 23 (34) Conclusion 2).4*    FOREIGN DEBTS CLEARING OFFICES AND import restrictions  (REPRISALS)  BILL.(Reference Cabinet 24 (34) Conclusion 11).Joint Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequerand the President of the Board of Trade, coweringdraft Bill.CP.  163 (34)    -    circulated herewith.5.    THE MEAT SITUATION:    IMMEDIATE OPENING OF NEGOTIATIONSWITH,THE DOMINIONS AND FOREIGN COUNTRIES.(Reference Cabinet 70 (33) Conclusion 10).Statement to be made by the Lord President of the&apos;Council as Chairman of the Produce Markets supply committee.6-    PUBLIG ORDER     -    (if ready).(Reference Cabinet 24 (34) Conclusion 1).7*    PROCEDURE OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS:    REPORT OF THESELECT COMMITTEE (1932).Memorandum by the Prime Minister.CP. 159 (34)    -   already circulated.8.    CONCLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.Additional Itern. n   &amp;I HiTRADE AGREEMENT WITH FRANCE,(Reference Cabinet 14 (34) Conclusion 11).Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.CP.   165 (34)    -    circulated herewith,Gardens, H,A.  37 (34)    -   already circulated,L      S.Yv.1. , (Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,1QJune, 1934. Secretary to the Cabinet.
IjOCUMENT IS TUB PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT) $J)JL E T,use-COPY NO.CABINET    25  (34)Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.  10, downing street, S.W.I., on TUESDAY, 19th JUNE, 1934,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS    -    (if required)2.    REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.(Reference Cabinet 23 (34) Conclusion l).3.     IMPERIAL DEFENCE POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 23 (34) Conclusion 2).4*    FOREIGN DEBTS CLEARING OFFICES AND import restrictions  (REPRISALS) BILL.(Reference Cabinet 24 (34) Conclusion 11).Joint Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequerand the President of the Board of Trade, covering draft Bill.CP.  163 (34)    -    circulated herewith,5.    THE, MEAT SITUATION:    IMMEDIATE OPENING OF NEGOTIATIONSWITH THE DOMINIONS.AND FOREIGN COUNTRIES.(Reference Cabinet 70 (33) Conclusion 10).Statement to be made by the Lord President ^f the&apos; *&apos;\Council as Chairman of the Produce Markets supply committee.6.    PUBLIG ORDER(If ready).(Reference Cabinet 24 (34) Conclusion 1).7.    PROCEDURE OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS:    REPORT OF THESELECT COMMITTEE (1932).Memorandum by the Prime Minister.CP. 159 (34)    -   already circulated.-te^ll Gardens,e, 1934.8.    CONCLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.13th Conclusions (34) of the Home Affairs Committee,To be circulated.Colonial Stock Bill.(Reference Cabinet 24 (34) Conclusion 10).Memorandum by the Financial Secretary tothe Treasury, covering draft Bill.H.A.  37 (34)    -   already circulated.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.
j pr^ntmknt is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s government).IeXT. copy no.CABINET    85  (54).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.1., on TUESDAY,19th JUNE, 1934,  at 11.0 a.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M,P.,Prime Minister,        (in the Chair).pie Right Hon.^Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,lord President of the Council.lie Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt., D.S.O.,Bm.P, , Secretary of State forfcome Affairs.[he Right Hon.iThe Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.the Right Hon.Hj,H.  Thomas , M.P. ,[   Secretary of State for Dominion!   Affairs.n111 Most Hon..;The Marquess of Londonderry,p.G, , M.V.O., Secretary ofIB tat e for Air.he Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton-Young,p.B.E. , D.S.O. , D.S.C. , M.P.,Minister of Health.&apos;he Right Hon.Sir Bolton iiiyres Monsell,,G.B.E. , M.P, , First Lord ofthe Admiralty.he Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt. , C.B.E.j   M.p, , Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.i.,K.C.V.O., O.B.E., K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E., M.C, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies,The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,C.M.G., M.P., Secretary.of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P. ,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.Major The Right Hon.V/. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., first commissioner of Works,The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley 7/ood, M.P. ,Postmaster-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:Captain The Right Hon.H.D. Margeeson, M.C., M. P,,Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury &amp; Chief Whip.(For Conclusion 8).Sir Maurice Hankey, G..C.B. , O.C.M.G. , G.G.V.O.,  ......    Secretary.
GERMANY.politicalSituati onin.Herr vonPapen&apos;sSpeech.(previous reference:Cabinet 13(33). Con-elus ion 1.1. The Secretary&apos; of State for Foreign affairs drew the attention of the Cabinet to a speech recentlydelivered in Germany by Herr von Papen, the Vice-President of the German Reich,    In effect this amountedto a denunciation of Herr Hitler&apos;s policy.    It hadbeen known for some time that he intended to deliversuch a speech.    The important question, however, was how far he had the support of the President, Marshalvon Hindenberg.    Herr von Papen had been one of thosewho had helped Herr Hitler to attain his position,and had assumed that he and his colleagues would be consulted.    To a great extent, however, they had beenshelved.    Even now Herr Hitler was known to besuppressing the publication of the speech in Germany,   .In some quarters the speech was represented as arevolt of the Junkers against the National Socialists,His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Berlin thought that the speech was a signal for a criticism of Herr Hitler,as the result of which Herr von Papen and. the Generalsof the Reichswehr would come back to power.   The effectof any such change on ourselves would not necessarily be good.    For example, it was unlikely that it would bring disarmament any nearer.    He thought that theFrench would use the episode to say how right theyhad been in forecasting that Herr Hitler was not veryfirmly established.
liEAGUE OP NA^IOWSSSEMBLY,ffnited Yingdomreepresentationfit.(Previous$Reference:Cabinet 451(33), Con-Hclusion B.)FX2.   The Cabinet had a short discussion as to who should be the United Kingdom representatives at theforthcoming Meeting of the Assembly of the League ofNa tions in S eptemb er.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was authorised to arrange for a Delegation as follows:-DELEGATES.The .Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Lord Privy Seal.,&quot;Viscount Cecil of Chelwood (provisional andsubject to furtherc onsiderat ion,)SUBSTITUTE DELEGATFS.Mis s Hors brugh, M.P.,Mr W.E.Beckett, C.M.G. (Foreign Office),A. Treasury Representative,Mr G,H .Shakespeare. M.P.,And one other,Discretion was left to the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to arrange with the Prime Ministerand other Ministers concerned for the final completionof the list.
iEAGUE OP nations assembly .United KingdomRepresentationat.(previous reference:Cabinet 45(33), Con-clusion 8.)FX3.   The Cabinet had a short discussion as to who should be the United Kingdom representatives at theforthcoming Meeting of the Assembly of the League ofNations In September.^he Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was authorised to arrange for a Delegation as follows:-DELEGATES .The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,^he Lord Privy Seal,Viscount Cecil of Chelwood (provisional ands ub j ec t t o furtherc ons iderat. ion.)SUBSTITUTE DELEGATFS.Mis s K ors trugh, M. P,,Mr W.E.Beckett, G.M..G. (Foreign Office),A Treasury Representative,Mr G,H .Shakespeare, M.P.,And one other.Discretion was left to the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to arrange with the Prime Ministerand other Ministers concerned for the final completionof the list,
5. The Cabinet had. before them a Memorandum bythe President of the Board of Trade (G.P..-165 (34))asking Cabinet authority for signature of a short termTrade Agreement with Prance, which, subject to approval by the two Governments and to the necessary formalitiesbeing completed in time, it was intended to bring intoforce on July 1st, provisionally and pending ratifica-tion.    After reviewing the difficult circumstancesattending the negotiations, the President summarised in his Memorandum the salient points of the proposed agreement, the value of which, was that it restoredtrade to a full most-favoured-nation basis and should at least tend to stabilise the existing volume of trade the President of the Board, of Trade made a statement to the Cabinet on the subject of the negotiations..The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention tothe following passage in paragraph 11 of CP.-165 (34):-&quot;In the event, however, of a * gravevariation&apos;  in the rate of exchangebetween the currencies of the twocountries it can be terminated atone month&apos;s not ic e&quot; .He asked what was intended by the term &quot;gravevariation&quot;?    He pointed, out that a small variation of,say, 5 per cent, might easily be brought about by further manipulations of the exchanges in America,and. it might be necessary to choose between our having to uphold the value of the Pound as against the Dollaror losing a valuable Agreement.The President of the Board of Trade, after deserib-ing the negotiations on this point, said that thisvague phrase had been used deliberately and had notbeen defined.    He had understood, however, in thecourse of the conversations that the French had intheir mind something of the nature of 35 per cent.The Chancellor of the Exchequer was satisfied withthis explanation.
There was some discussion as to whether it mightbe advisable to place on record with the FrenchGovernment, by means of a letter, our view that the term &quot;grave variation&quot; signified &quot;not less  than 85per cent.&quot;    It was pointed out, however, that even a20 per cent, variation might, in certain circumstances,prove very inconvenient, and that the French mightwrite a reply containing a different interpretationinvolving the reopening of these difficult riegotia-tions .   The real safeguard was that neither sidewished, to see the new Agreement fail.On the whole, therefore, it was felt to be better to take no action.The Cabinet authorised the signature of the snort-term Agreement with Francedescribed by the President of the Boardof Trade in C .P,-165 (34),
IMPERIALDEFENCE( POLICY, -Defence Re-quirements,(&quot;previous reference cabinet 23(34). con-elusion 2 .)f-.fi.4.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer reported thathis proposals on Defence Requirements would be sent the same evening to the Ministers at the head of theDefence Departments and would be ready for circulation to the Ministerial Committee on Disarmament on the morrow, Wednesday, June 20th.The Ministers at the head of the Defence Departmentsasked that they might be given sufficient time toexamine the new proposals before they were discussed,by the Ministerial Committee.The Cabinet agreed  That the Ministerial Committee on disarmament should, meet on Monday next, June 25th, at 10 Downing Street,at 11 a.m.
l&amp;ERMAN DEBT 5. The Cabinet had. before them a Joint MemorandumNEGOTIATIONS.by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the PresidentIbbts Clearingloffices and of the Board of Trade (C.P.-163 (34)) statin^ thatirpjport restriction-It ions Reprisals      in accordance with the decision of the Cabinet atBill.the Meeting referred to in the margin, the German(Previous Government had been informed that His Majesty&apos;sI Reference:[Cabinet 24 Government intended shortly to propose legislation; (54), Con-I elusion 11.) which would enable them to set up an Anglo-GermanSl+yZjauA Clearing Office, but that they would be prepared toj.jfjMdi^n-, Tefr-ain -from the exercise of these powers if asatisfactory agreement ensuring fair treatment toBritish bondholders and British commerce could be negotiated before July 1st,Attached to the Memorandum was a Draft Bill, ingeneral terms, prepared on the instructions of thePresident of the Board of Trade in consultation withthe various Departments concerned, giving to theGovernment power (l) to set up a Clearing office in cases where payments due to this country were-   withheld as the result of debt defaults, or transfersuspensions, or exchange restrictions:    and (2) toimpose quantitative import restrictions as a reprisalagainst foreign import restrictions which are discrim-inatory against this country.    The Ministers did not recommend any widespread use of these powers, and thought that for the present their use should, be refused except in the special case of Germany.    Ifthe Cabinet approved the Bill it was proposed thatit should be introduced during the present week and.receive a Second Reading, and passed through all stages in both Houses of Parliament.in the week beginning June 25th.    It should then be possibleto set up an Anglo-German Clearing Office on July 1st,or shortly afterwards.  if no satisfactory agreement had been reached with the German Government in themeantime. -6-
The Lord Chancellor informed the Cabinet that the attorney-General and the Solicitor-General weremeeting Departmental representatives the same after-noon to examine the Bill from the legal point ofview,   He anticipated that that examination need not interfere with the Parliamentary programme proposed.This examination would obviate the necessity for aMeeting of the Committee of Home Affairs.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said thatwhile he realised that the Bill was necessary, m.p.. /\ r&amp;&quot;h(Zk)*&apos;       might have a most damaging effect on Colonial tradeunless the Clearing Office were operated so as tosafeguard this .    At present the Colonies had a largefavourable trade balance with Germany.   The GermanGovernment had announced their intention of discrim-inating in their purchases of raw materials in favourof country.es that bought from Germany,   The effect ofsuch action would be most serious on Colonial trade,and particularly on the West African Colonies.   Therehad. been a serious fall in prices of oil seeds andnuts and of cocoa, and a drop in sales.    The United.States had recently imposed prohibitive duties.    if germany were to cut down substantially her. purchases from the West A.african Colonies there would be a doubledisadvantage.   Budget deficits would arise, and therewould be a reduction in the purehasing power of these colonies just at a time when a quota and. drasticduties had been put on against Japan, and when we most needed their purchasing power.   Power existed underthe Bill as drafted, to deal with balances In the clearing Office as we pleased.    It was essential, ifColonial trade were threatened, that we should use this power to retain balances in the Clearing office in order to compel Germany to maintain her purchases from the Colonies .
The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that asthe Bill would confer the powers required to take theaction desired in certain contingencies by theSecretary of State for the Colonies, it would be unnecessary to take a decision on the point at themoment.    If the circumstances apprehended by theSecretary of State should arise, he would be able to consult the Chancellor of the Exchequer and thePresident of the Board of Trade with a view to a recommendation to the Cabinet,    if necessary.The Secretary of State for the Colonies accepted,this suggest ion.The Secretary of State for the Colonies pointed,out that in Clause 1 (5) f i) of the Bill, after thewords &quot;British subjects&quot; (page 3, line 14) it wasnecessary to insert &quot;or to British protected persons&quot;.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs raiseda question as to whether the &quot;persons&quot; mentioned in clause 1 (l)  of the Bill were the same as thosereferred to in.Clause 1 (5)  (i).   Was it deliberate,he asked, that on page 3, line 14, the debts to be discharged, were debts to &quot;British subjects&quot; (whichwould include British subjects who were not residentor carrying on business in the United Kingdom) whereason page 1, line 8, the condition which brings into play the Order is failure to pay debts to &quot;personsordinarily resident or carrying on business in theUnited Kingdom&quot; ?    He also asked whether it wasnecessary to define the classes of debts in Clause1 (5) (1):    e,g., were we to protect gambling debts?The Lord.. Chancellor suggested that these points should be looked into by the Law Officers the same afternoon.
The Cabinet agreed  (a) mo approve the Debts Clearing offices and. import Restrictions Reprisals bill and the programme proposed by theChancellor of the Exchequer for its passage through all the stages ofboth Bouses of Parliament in the week beginning June 25th   as set forth inC.P.-163 (54), subject to -(i) such alterations in the Bill asthe Attorney-General and theSolieit or-General might deem necessary, their considerationto include the various points referred to by the Secretaryof state for Foreign affairs and the suggestion of theSecretary of State for theColonies as to page 5, line 14:(ii) any drafting or other minor .alterations that might be foundnecessary or desirable:(b) That, in view of the specia1 examination by the Law Officers, the Bill need notbe sent to the Committee of Rome Affairs:(c) That if the Bill should have the damagingeffects on Colonial trade apprehended bythe Secretary of State for the Colonies,the latter should have the right tobring to the notice of the Chancellorof the exchequer and the President ofthe Board of Trade the safeguardingsuggestions referred, to above, witha view to appropriate action beingtaken and, if necessary, referenceto the Cabinet,9-
6.      The Lord President of the Council, as chairman of the Produce Markets Supply Committee, reported that the Cabinet Committee had been givingclose consideration to the meat supply situationin the United Kingdom market.      Undertakings given at Ottawa concerning the quantitative regulationof meat imports from Dominion sources end on the30th of this month (June, 1934).     After that date the Government, while under an obligation to theDominions to continue the regulation of foreignmeat imports,  is at liberty, under the terms ofthe Agreement,  to regulate Dominion meat imports,The Produce Markets Supply Committee is proceeding on the assumption that a statement of theGovernment&apos;s intentions will have to be made beforethe House rises for the summer recess.      TheCommittee recommends the Cabinet to authorise theopening forthwith of discussions with theGovernments of the Dominions and foreign countries concerned with the supply of meat to the UnitedKingdom market, at which the meat supply situationcan be fully explored, in the light of thetermination of part of the Ottawa Agreements atthe end of this month.      It is proposed that thediscussions should be opened on the widest possible basis, envisaging, if necessary, the modificationof our powers of compulsory quantitative regulation,in return for powers to raise a levy on overseasmeat imports.      Specific proposals will be putforward to the Cabinet at a later stage afterpreliminary exploration of the position in thelight of the reactions of the Dominions andArgentina.      In the meantime, the Committee,
realising that negotiations of the kind envisagedabove, will necessarily take some considerable time,has arranged for the Departments concerned toexamine in detail schemes to deal with thepractical questions which will arise, includinginterim measures which could if necessary be ptitinto operation to hold the position pending the outcome of the negotiations.The Secretary of State for DominionAffairs added that this was a procedure agreed by the Cabinet Committee.The Cabinet approved the proposals of theLord President of the Council as setforth above.
public ORDER.PoliticalUniforms....Iwearing of.(^previous reference:^Cabinet 24 (34)conclusion 1),7.      The Home Secretary sail that as it would noton Public Orderhe possible to pass legislation/in this part of the session he would like time for careful considerationof the whole question before submitting his proposals to the Cabinet.      His proposals therefore would not beready for consideration at the next regular weekly meeting.Some discussion took place in regard to theforthcoming meetings of the Fascists at Newcastleand later at the White City.The Home Secretary thought it was not very probable that the meeting at Newcastle would be held.The Cabinet instructed the Secretary tocontinue the subject on the Agenda paper.
PROCEDURE of the HOUSE OFCOMMONS.Report ofSelect Com-mittee (1932) .(previous reference:Cabinet 33(30), Con-clusion  6 .)8.    The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by thePrime Minister (CP,-159 (34)) circulating some notesprepared by the Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury on the recommendations contained, in theReport of the Select Committee on Procedure of theHouse of Commons (H.C. Paper Ho.129 of 1932), andsubmitting for the consideration of his colleagueshis own recommendations in the form of a draft answer to a Parliamentary Question and a statement to be circulated in the Official Report.   Attached, to theMemorandum was a copy of the Report of the SelectCommittee .The Cabinet discussed at some length therecommendations contained on pages 16 to 20 of theMemorandum under the following heads -Estimates Committee,Chairmen of Standing Committees,Financial Resolutions,Questions,Guillotine,Closure,Standing Orders,Departmental Rules and Orders,Sitting of Standing Committees duringthe Sitting of the House,Private Members&apos; Rights,Church of England Assembly (Powers) Act.The Cabinet approved the proposals under allheads subject to the following exceptionsand comments:-Estimates Committee,(1)    The Standing Orders shouldh e amended in order to allow of the reports of theEstimates and    Public     Accounts Committeesbeing considered on not more than twoof the twenty supply days and if theHouse of Commons do desire,(2)    That the question of procedure should beconsidered by the Postmaster-General,the Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury and a representative of theTreasury.Financial Resolutions.(3)    To drop the proposal under the headingFinancial Resolutions on page 17 of cp,  159 (34).
That the Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury should draft the necessary amendments to the Standing Orders and discuss them with the Opposition Whips.That half a day should he given fordiscussion of the above amendmentsby the House of Commons, but that thereshould be no question of putting on theGovernment tfhips as the question was one for the. House of Commons itself.-14-
t-HE COLONIAL 9,    The Cabinet had under consideration a MemorandumSTOCK HILL.by the Financial Secretary to the Treasury (FLA.-37(Previous (34)), covering the draft Colonial Stock Bill, which reference:Cabinet 24 was brought forward with the ob ieet of providing.( 34) , C on-clusion 10.)      as respects Dominion Stocks, an alternative to thethird of the conditions prescribed, by the treasury under Section 2 of the Colonial Stock Act, 1900,requiring that the Dominion or Colonial Government-desiring that its Stock issue should qualify fortrustee status should place on record a formalexpression of opinion that any legislation of that dominion or Colony appearing to the Imperial Govern-ment to alter or infringe the rights of a Stockholdercould properly be disallowed:    together with thefollowing recommendation of the Committee of HomeAffairs thereon (.H..A.C. 13th Conclusions (34)):-&quot;To authorise the introduction in theHouse of Commons forthwith, as a mattero-f urgency, of the Colonial Stock Bill,in the form of the draft annexed with.A.-37 (34), subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that mightbe found necessary or desirable.&quot;The Cabinet approved the above recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs.
THE NAVALCONFERENCE1935.UnitedKingdomDelegation at.(previous reference:Cabinet 9 (54)Conclusion 15).10, The Prime Minister instructed the Secretaryto place on the Agenda paper of the next meeting;of the Cabinet the question of the composition ofthe United Kingdom&apos;s delegation at the naval conference, 1935.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,19th June, 1954.-16-

</content>
</cab>
