<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/25 images: 286-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted far the War Cabinet.   April 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)80th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 80 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, April 3, 1940, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Lieutenant-General H. R. S. Massy,Deputy Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (Items 1-7).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[21097]
WAR CABINET 80 (40).Contents.MinuteSo. Subject. page 1      Publicity regarding operations      ...      ...      ...       ...     209B.B.C. news bulletins.Press reports.2      The Air Situation     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     209Enemy activity.Western Front.3      The Naval Situation..................     209Enemy air activity.German ships in the Adriatic and Black Seas.4      The Military Situation        ... ...      ...      ...     2105      Supreme War Council: 6th Meeting       ...      ...      ...     210Royal Marine operation.Proposed operation in Norwegian territorial waters.6      United States of America    ...      ...      ...       ...       ...     211Anglo-American relations.7      Germany ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ...       ...     211State of opinion.8      Naval Prize Money and Prize Bounty      ...       ...       ...     211
PublicityRegardingOperations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 79thConclusions,Minute 1.)B.B.C. news bulletins.Press reports.1. The Prime Minister said that he had noticed a great improvement in the tone of the B.B.C. News Bulletin on the previous evening. War News items in the morning&apos;s papers were alsopresented in a much more satisfactory manner than of late.The Secretary of State for Air added that he had instructed the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief in France to do his utmost to publish early bulletins of aerial engagements, in order to forestallGerman reports. He had suggested that immediate communiquesmight, if necessary, be in general terms, a further confirmatorybulletin being published later.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 79thConclusions,Minute 1.)Enemy activity.Western Front.2. The Secretary of State for Air said that there had been considerable enemy activity off the East Coast on the previous day.Enemy aircraft had attacked four convoys in the Orkney area without result, and an abortive raid by a number of aircraft onScapa had also taken place.Our fighters had intercepted three Heinkels off Yarmouth, oneof which had been forced down on to the sea. According to theGerman report, one of the other Heinkels had rescued its crew.In a fighter engagement in France, two Messerschmitts hadbeen damaged, and had possibly been destroyed. One of ourHurricanes had been shot down, but the pilot had landed safely byparachute.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 79thConclusions,Minute 2.)Enemy airactivitv.German ships inthe Adriatic and black Seas.3. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the raid onScapa (see previous Minute) had been a half-hearted affair. five or six aircraft bad crossed the Flow, but had sheered off on being very heavily engaged by the ships&apos; and shore batteries; one enemy aircraft was thought to have been damaged.H.M.S. Leith had attacked a good contact off Land&apos;s End, butthe results were not yet known.In reply to a question by the Prime Minister, the Chief ofNaval Staff said that we had a device in our mine-sweeping gear to counter the cutting device fitted to the mooring wires of Germanmines.Referring to a question which had been asked at the previous meeting, the First Lord of the Admiralty said that there were28 German ships at Trieste which were expected shortly atDubrovnik. The ships intended to load up with bauxite and other raw materials at Dubrovnik, which they would take back to Trieste.From there the materials would go to Germany in the wagonswhich had brought coal to Italy. A number of German ships atIstanbul were also expected at Constanza. In both cases theGerman ships could make the voyage entirely in territorial waters.[21097]
The Military 4.   The Secretary of State for War said that there was nothingSituation. of importance to report from the Western Jjront.(Previous The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Reference:W.M. (40) 79thConclusions, &apos;Minute 3.)5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that no reply bad yet been received from the French Government on thesubject of the Royal Marine Operation. A member of the ForeignOffice staff had, however, had a long conversation the previous evening with a member of the French Embassy, whose views mightbe summarised as follows : The decision of the French War Committee was most fortunate and the key to the French attitude was to be foundin the attitude of M. Daladier, who was deeply influenced bythe weakness of the French Air Force. When the project ofthe Royal Marine Operation had first been broached,M. Daladier had regarded it as a dangerous toy, but not oneto be taken seriously. Later, when we had pressed thisproposal, he had become irritated, fearing serious Germanreprisals on the French aircraft factories. Political reasonsprobably also entered into the picture, but M. Daladier was asick man, and must not be judged too harshly.Perhaps the only chance of breaking down M. Daladier&apos;sopposition would be for the Prime Minister to send him a personal message which would gratify him and might perhapsreassure him. M. Reynaud, it was felt, would not be likely to object to an unconventional step of this kind, since, if nothingwere done, he would be in grave difficulties when he met the senate on the following Tuesday (the 9th April).The Foreign Secretary suggested that our Ambassador in Parisshould at once be instructed to see M. Reynaud and ascertain whether he concurred in such a message being sent.The Prime Minister agreed that it was worth making anattempt on these lines. The general picture regarding the situationwithin the French Government disclosed by the Foreign Secretarycoincided exactly with his own conclusions on this subject.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theDepartment of the Foreign Office dealing with the United StatesPress thought that the effect on public opinion of the Narvikoperation, if carried out separately, would be bad; but that thereshould be no great difficulty if it were combined with the royal marine Operation. He added that the Minister of economic warfare had expressed the hope that, if the former project onlywere to be carried out, it might be possible for us first to secure from the Norwegians the tankers we required.The Prime Minister attached great importance to the psychological effect of the Royal Marine Operation if carried outsoon after the meeting of the Supreme War Council. We should,therefore, do everything possible to secure French concurrence.A discussion then took place as to the action to be taken inregard to the Royal Marine Operation and the Operation in norwegian Territorial Waters on the assumption that the final reply of the French Government was (a) favourable (&amp;) unfavourable inregard to the first-named Operation.Particulars of this discussion, and of the conclusion reached by the War Cabinet, are recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard file of War Cabinet conclusions.Supreme WarCouncil: 6thMeeting.Royal marine operation.proposed operation in norwegian territorial waters.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 79thConclusions,Minute 4.)
United States ofAmerica.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 29thConclusions,Minute 6.)Anglo-american relations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 44thConclusions,Minute 7.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto Telegram No. 1019 (Arfar), dated 2nd April, 1940, from HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador, Washington, containing a message for sir frederick Leith-Ross from Mr. Ashton-Gwatkin, who was atpresent in the United States for the purpose of discussing with theAdministration various questions relating to economic warfare.Mr. Ashton-Gwatkin reported a great change in the State Depart-ment;- only a month or two ago the lawyers had exercised adetermining influence, but now the State Department had put asidelegalistic arguments, and the situation was developing rapidly inour favour.The First Lord of the Admiralty drew attention to a telegram in which the Ministry of Economic Warfare, when dealing with arecalcitrant United States ship, had threatened to bring her intoKirkwall for examination. No orders have been issued by theAdmiralty on this subject, but, if the unsatisfactory conditionscontinued, it might be necessary to take this action.The Secretary of State for War suggested that, if action wastaken to interfere with traffic in Norwegian Territorial Waters,the United States Government might extend the belligerent zoneto the whole of the Scandinavian coast. This would be greatly toour advantage.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.Germany. 7    The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs gave the WarState of Cabinet particulars of information received from a secret sourceopinion. regarding the present conditions and state of opinion in Hamburg(Previous and the adjoining region.     Particulars of this information areReference: contained in the Secretary&apos;s  Standard  File of War  cabinet.M. (39) 97th Conclusions.Conclusions,Minute 8.) ---Naval Prize 8.   The War Cabinet had before them a Paper by the FirstMoney and , Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (G.) (40) 85) setting out a proposalPrize Bounty. that the King should be moved to make a proclamation grantingPrize Money and Prize Bounty to the officers and men of the naval forces, and a Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer(W.P. (G.) (40) 91) setting out arguments against the adoption ofthis course.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, much as he regrettedit, he could not agree with the arguments or the conclusions putforward by the First Lord of the Admiralty. For example, hecould not agree with the statement that &quot; prize money is not public money,&quot; which would mean in effect that captured ships and their cargoes became automatically the private property of the captors.This result did not, however, follow automatically, but had alwaysrequired a special grant. Thus, a few weeks after the beginningof the war of 1914, the Lords Commissioners of the Admiraltyrepresented that the Proclamation issued by Queen Victoria in 1900,laying down the conditions for the distribution of the proceeds ofprizes, required modification to bring them into accord with modern conditions, and as they intended to set up a system of prize bountiesand gratuities instead of the system of distributing prize moneydescribed in that Proclamation, they asked for its cancellation. HisMajesty approved, and the Lords Commissioners were asked to give directions accordingly (Order in Council (1914) 1301, dated28th August, 1914).Similarly section 1 (1) of the Naval Prize Act, passed on 8th August, 1918, began as follows: &quot;If His Majesty is pleasedby Proclamation or Order in Council to make a grant of prize moneyout of the proceeds, &amp;c.,&amp;c.&quot;   This showed that Parliament clearly
regarded the proceeds of prizes as public money, out of which agrant could or could not be made.It was true that the Navy&apos;s claim for prize money was basedon ancient practice, but the Army also had been entitled to the proceeds of booty captured in war until the Ashanti Campaign of1874. He had not been able to discover that the question of navalprize money had been discussed in the War Cabinet during the last war until 24th April, 1918, when they had discussed a draft of theBill which he had already mentioned. In December 1918, thequestion had arisen whether the officers and men of the Navy should share in the war gratuities which were being paid to the services generally. It had been argued on one side that it was unfair thatthe Navy should receive a gratuity as well as prize money, and onthe other side that it would be a breach of faith to deprive them of the gratuity, when it had never been suggested that this wouldbe the consequence of allowing them to receive prize money. Thelatter view had prevailed, but he himself regarded it as mostobjectionable that the Navy had in this way been allowed first toreceive prize money, and then to share in war gratuities on thesame basis as the other Services.He appreciated that it was very difficult to interfere with along established practice. Surely, however, it was right now to takethe line that the members of all the Services received fair rates of payment and were not entitled to any perquisites. It would be particularly difficult to justify a distinction between the Navy andthe Air Force, or on the other hand to devise a scheme for awardingprize money to those members of the Air Force who were concernedin the capture of enemy ships. Could it seriously be argued thatextra payment was deserved for an operation of this character, andnot for taking part in the bombing of Sylt?Prize bounty for the capture or destruction of an enemy ship of war was equally difficult to reconcile with modern conditions.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he agreed with thegreater part of the arguments put forward by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer. These arguments should, however, have been usedin 1918. At that date, with a full knowledge of all the losses whichthe Army had suffered, the Government had decided that PrizeMoney and Prize Bounty should be awarded, and as a result theNavy now regarded it as their established right. There was something specially attractive in the prospect of an award ofuncertain amount, and it would be taken very much amiss in theNavy if this were denied them. He did not think that the other services need complain, as they would not be put in any worse position than they had been in the last war, and he would thereforeurge that we should adhere to the procedure adopted in 1918.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence agreed that, if anychange were to have been made, this should have been done in 1918.It was very difficult to make such a change during the course of awar, more particularly as the men now serving in the Navy knewvery well what had been done in 1918, and many of them had served in the last war. It was not a matter of comparing the present day with the distant past, but rather with a deliberate decision madein our generation. The sailors had been very badly paid in1914-18, and had therefore attached special importance to additional payments of this character. It was true that there wasa very strong case against the continued award of prize money, andhe agreed on the moral issue with the Chancellor, but the men inthe Navy would not appreciate the arguments and would be left with a strong sense of grievance. The financial issue was not agreat one.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the minister without Portfolio agreed that the arguments against the con-tinuance of prize money were very strong, and that the change
might well have been made in 1918. Nevertheless, they did notthink it was desirable to deprive the Navy to-day, in the middle ofa war, of something which they had been led to expect as a right.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he would be satisfied with an announcement that this was the last war in which prizemoney and prize bounty would be paid.The Secretary of State for War asked whether it was necessaryto make any public announcement at the present time, seeing thatduring the last war the decision had not been taken until 1918. Atthe end of the war it might well be quite out of the question to payenormous sums in gratuities, &amp;c. If so, the position could be betterexplained against the background of the circumstances prevailing at that time. If it were decided to award prize money, he wouldhave to claim that the Army should be treated in the same way asthe Navy, i.e., that they should be entitled to a share, if theycontributed to the capture of an enemy vessel.The Secretary of State for Air said that he would similarlywish to claim that the members of the Royal Air Force should beentitled to share in the award of prize money in appropriate cases.The Prime Minister said that he fully appreciated that sailorsregarded prize money and prize bounty very seriously, and that itwas very difficult to abolish such an old-established practice. Onthe other hand, he regarded it as entirely out of harmony with present conditions, more particularly in view of the developmentof the Royal Air Force, and he thought that it would be against thesentiment of the country as a whole to allow special privileges toone of the three Services when the members of all alike were riskingtheir lives. He suggested that the matter should be considered inconnection with war gratuities to be paid at the end of the war.There would then be less ground for complaints in the Navy if itcould be argued that the gratuities which they were receiving took account of the fact that they were giving up their claim to prizemoney and bounty. If no announcement were made now, the navy would no doubt expect to receive prize money and prize bounty.But at the end of the war, when it was known what the prize funds would amount to and what the general conditions were, an offercould probably be made which could be represented as the mostequitable basis in all the circumstances for giving them that rewardfor their services which the country would wish them to have. Itwas very probable that in the circumstances then prevailing therewould be general agreement as to the right course to adopt.The War Cabinet agreed (i) That no immediate announcement should be made as to thegrant of prize money and prize bounty to officers andmen of the Naval Forces,(ii) That the decision in regard to such grants should, ifpossible, be deferred for consideration at the end of thewar in connection with the consideration of. gratuitiesin respect of war service generally.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,April 3, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
