<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/25/0 images: 245-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;(.T1.11b., Document j^..tlie^J^:cyqf)Ttx^QX. JIlp,. pritannioMai es c7 &apos;* s. Government&quot;..,)S E 0 R F TPT1IAL COPT No.CABINET 35  (211.CE NCI US TONS of a Meeting held in Mr Char;1: erlain&apos;s Boom,Honse of Commons, S.W. 1,  on MONDAY, MAY       1921, at-15 p.m.PRESENT:-The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain,M.P*, lord Privy Seal.?he Right Hon. E.  Shortt,  K &apos;CP,MeP. ,  Secretary of State for home Affairs.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill,MaP.,  Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. F.S. Montagu,  M.P.Secretary o^ State for India.The Right Hon. Lord Lee of Fare-ham,  G-.BiE.,K.0.BFirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir A. Griffith-Boecawen, M.P., Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries...&apos;i&apos;ho Right Hon. Co Addison, M.P.The Right Konr AeJ0 balfour,   0 TviM.PV, Lord President of&apos;theCouncil.The Right Hon. Sir Robert HornG.B.E., E,, C. , M. P. , Ch ancel 1o f the E x c h e que r.The Right Bon. Sir l, worthington evans, Part,,, M. P...,  Sec retaryof State for War.The Right Hon. K.A.L. Fisher, M,president of the Board ofEducation.;The Right Hon. Sir Eric Geddes,G.C.3,,G.E.E.,M.P., MinisterOf Transport.,The Right Hon. P, Munro, K,Ce,;M;secretary for Scotland.The, note 11 ow i n e were a Ps c p r e s en t: -Admiral of the Fleet Earl Beatty,O.M. ,G.C.B, ,.G.C.V.O.,D..S..O. ,First Sea Lord and. Chie-f ofthe Naval Staff.Mr Thomas Jones  ,............  Principal Assistant secretary mr R^^oworth ..,.............. . *.....Assistant Secretary
SAL OPIS PORTRAILWAYERS TO   -LE COAL.INDUSTRIAL     (1) With-rel^erorvo^to-aablnot 34 (SI), Conclusion 1, thoPrime Minister stated that, ina^much-.A&amp;-heen unable to be present at the Cabinet held that forenoen^ -and in view of the gravity of the conclusions reached, hehad summoned a further meeting so that the position mightagain be reviewed.&quot;*The Minister of Transport informed the Cabinet thathe had that afternoon ceen Mr Cramp, the Industrial Secretaryof the National Union of Railwaymen, and Mir Robert Williams,the General Secretary of the Transport Workers&apos; Federation, -and had announced to them t*he policy of the Government^ as agreed by the Cabinet that morning.    Mr Cramp had stated thathis Union did not abject to move coal destined for publicutility purposes, but they refused to move &quot;black-leg&quot; coal which had been handled by volunteer labour.    Mr Williams had stated that his Union objected to handling all foreign import-ed coal, as discrimination between coal for public utilityand for commercial pairpooes was not practicable.    His Exsqu-tive would be meeting on the following day, and he had nodoubt that this view v-ould be confirmed and the strike beextended to all ports.The Minister of Transport further informed the Cabinetthat the Caledonian Railway Company were asking for instruc-tions as to the attitude they should take up in view of the refusal of their employees to handle tho   cargo of Cardiffseaborne coal which had arrived in Glasgow.    It was beingunloaded by volunteer labour, and in consequence drivers,signalmen, wagon-cleaners and examiners were refusing tocarry out their normal duties.    The Caledonian RailwayCompany had ao far suspended three men by booking them off.If this policy of suspension were adhered to and supportedby the Government, tho probability was that a strike wouldbecome general over the railways within 48 hours.In thd view of the Minister of Transport it was clear from the attitude of Mr Cramp and Mr Williams, and from
the action taken by the men in Glasgow and elsewhere,   thatthe country might very quickly find itself menaced by whatwas in effect, if not exactly in form, a Triple TlliBncnstrike,  and all the - resources of the Gc^ ornment would berequired to meet it.The Cabinet briefly reviewed the position of thefood and coal stocks, and the preparations  for their dis-tribution made by the responsible Departments.The Cabinet agreed  (a) ^o reaf-firw the conclusion of the cabinet held that morning (Cabinet M (21), Con-elusion 1),  to resist the challenge tothe community involved in the refuealto    handle seaborne home and foreigncoal:(b) To take steps to make plain, through thePress, that all imported coal is for Gov-ernment order and for public utility pur-poses, and that any private coal which maybe en route to this country will be cbrr-mandeered by the Government for publicuse t(c) To inform the Caledonian Railway Company,through the Minister of Transport,   thatit would be supported by the Governmentin its action in suspending railwaymenwho refused to carry out their duties&quot;(d) To delay setting in motion the machineryof the Supply and Transport Committeepending the decision of the Transport-Workers&apos;  Executive on the following day:(e) To accept the offer cf the Chancellorof the Exchequer to assist for the presentthe President cf the Board of Trade inconnection with the Strike, as Mi  Baldwinand Sir Philip Lloyd-Grease would been gaged for some days in the T:cu.se ofCommons with the  Safeguarding ofIndustries Bill.
(2)   With reference to Cabinet 34 (21), Conclusion 3,\t.he Cabinet were informed &quot;by the Secretary of State for Varand the First Sea lord of tho results of the enquiries whichhad b^en made of Lord Cavan in regard to  the disturbancesat Aldershot and       the local measures which had been takento prevent their recurrence.The Secretary of State for War stated that with refer-en*e to the other Commands he would be in a better positionto report after he had met the General Officers Commanding,whom he had summoned to a Conference in London on the foliar--ing day.The Cabinet considered how far the legitimate griey-ances of the-men could bo met by making the grant of leavewith pay to the; Reservists general (and not 20 per cent, ae aipresent),  subject to recall at 48 hours;    and the question ofd^mobilisine; fke Reservists was also examined.It was pointed out that the reports cf the discipline of the Defence Force were very satisfactory., and that itmight he desirable to reopen ret-raiting if the Strike were extended.The Cabinet agreed  To postpone the question of the Reservistsand the Be fere e Force until the following day.
(5) The following draft announc-ement, prepared by mr balfour, was referred to the Chancellor of the Exchequer(who had been celled away) -for consideration as indicating the lines of a suitable announcement to  the public in theevent of the Strike spreading&quot;.-&quot;The strikere are not content with paralysingthe trade of the country;    they also refusei     to allow coal to be landed and carried even for the purpose of maintaining the life oft he c o irmoin i t y *The result will be that our population willbe deprived of light and water,,  that thera 11.7a y  service Will be utterly diaorgan-iced,  that  food will bo scarce,  and that 4through the dislocation of the \eewagosystem; disease will spread through thecommunity.The (kmsxnraent, in those circumstances, areresolved to commandeer., for purposes ofpublic utility, all the coal they can bring into ports;-, and call on ail loyal citizens,,whether engaged on the railways or not, to aid them in the task&quot;.&amp;, Whitehall Gardens , S .W. 1,May 9,  19:21.

</content>
</cab>
