<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/25/0 images: 250-256</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(.Thja JDoou.ment Iel th\e...^P;r^per tj : of HjLs BritannicMsJesta,,Gpyer rime h t . )g   ,P ^,RJ1 - FINAL COPY No. fiCABINET 26  (21) .CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, DonningStreet j .S.W.L,  on TUESDAY, MAY 1C, 1921,  at 11-SC a.in. present:-The Prime Minister (in the Chair)*The Right Hon.. A., Chamberlain, Mil?,Lord Privy Seal..Hie Right Hon.. Sir Robert Home,G.P.F. ,E.C. ,M.P.,. Chancellorof the Exchequer..The Right Hon. The Earl Curzon of kedleston^ K.G. , G.G..S. I. ,G.C..I.E.,,. Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.,The Right Hon. E,S* Montagu,.. M. P. ,Secretary of State for &quot;India,,Tile Right flc-:i. --Lord Lee ot*; Fareham,GvEoE, ,E.C..B., First Lord ofthe Admiralty..Hie Right Hon.. Sir Alfred Mond,Bart.,M.P,, Minister of Health,Hie Right Hon.. Sir A. Griffith-Bos cawen;- M..P..:,&apos;- Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries..The Right Hon., A,J. Balfour, 0CM.M.P. , Lord President of/the council.The Right Hon. E.  Shortt, K.Cw,M^ffSecretary of State for HomeAffairs.,&apos;.The Right Hon.,. W. S,  Churchill, M&apos;-,P.Secretary of State for. theColonies.The Right Hon. Sir L, worthington evans , Bart. , M. P.&apos;, S ec retaryof State for War.,The Right Hon., S.  Baldwin,  M.P. ,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon.. H./.L. Fisher, M,P..,President of the Board of Blueation.The Right Hon. T.J. Macnamara, M.-P,Minister of Labour.The Right HoruC . Addis on,, M.P.The following were also present:-Sir B..P. Blackett, K.0..B. v Treasury,(For C onc lus ions 1 &amp; 2 .)Lieut.-Colonel Sir K.P.A,Hankey, G.C.B,, secretary mr TTiomas Jones .... Principal Assistant     Secretary
(1) With--reference- to Cabinet 33 (21), Appendix I,  theCabinet had before them - telegram No s202, dated May 9, 1921,&quot;from lord Filmarnoek, the British-Charge&quot; d;Affaires at Berlin,recounting a conversation with Dr. Stresemann, who was appar-ently contemplating accepting the post of Chancellor ofGermany with, a desire to accept the ultimatum of the Allies,but wished for certain explanations of and assurance on thesubject of Reparations before making his decision (Appendix&apos; T).After considering the views of Lord d&apos;Abernon, as ex-pressed in his telegram Bo,204-, of May 9,  1921, which wasreceived during the meeting,  the Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should reply at once tc theBritish Ambassadord^iP%TeuXFa.rlous points raised by Dr* Stresemann, in the follow--ing sense:-(1)On the first point, as to the inter-pretation of tho phrase&quot; or to enableany Allied Power to proceed with therestoration or development of itsindustrial or economic life&quot;,  in thelast paragraph of the Protocol ofMa y 5,   1921   (Pa pe r G,P--2 9 09),  itshould be  explained that the intention,was to enable the Allied Powers to re-ceive payments in kind by Germany forother purposes than reparation ofactual war damage;    that no right is claimed of demanding particular arti-clea which, have already been mahufac-tured, but only of placing orders on commercial lines in Germany for such articles to be manufactured and deliver-ered, and  the value to be credited to german reparation account;    that thiswas inserted at our suggestion;    thatit was in no sense- intended to injureGerman industries, but rather to makepayment easier to the debtor by intro-ducing a more flexible method.    Moreover,that if was contemplated that recourse to this method should be kept withinnarrow and reasonable limits,  and that,if ne ces a ary, d ef inite&apos; as sur ances onthis subject would be sought by us fromthe other Allied Powers;    that any such orders must of course receive the prior approval of the Reparation Commission.(2)On the second point it should be explainedthat the - intention of the British Govern-;-ment was to retain the German Reparation(Recovery) Act, 1921,. in operation, inorder to enable them to exercise the option of collecting sums due for re-paration in the United Kingdom insteadof in Germany,  should thoy co elesvre)t-hvb ne increase in the total burden on
- Germany &quot;wetild thereby be involved;    thatit wan not their intention to collect morethan the 26 per cent, contemplated in para-graph 4 of the Schedule of Payments attachedto the Protocol  (Paper 0.P..-29P3);    thatthe above explanation related only to thepolicy cf the British Government towardsreparations from Germany, and did not af-feet their freedom as regards the generalfiscal policy which they might find it&apos;necessary to adopt towards all natiensirrespective of reparation..(s)l.&apos;3n the third paint it Bhculd be ctated that.,in the opinion of the British Government, the sanctions imposed en March 8th, especially those involving the occupation of 3-useeldr.rf,rJulBhurp/ and lAfhrort,, and the Rhine Customs,Might to be cancelled in the event of Germanyaccepting the ultimatum,  and that the BritishGovernment weuld eomrrunicate this opinion tothe French Government,(4)On tho fourth point, without prior consult?tion with the Allies no aesuranoe of thenature ashed, for in regard to Upper Silos itcould be given, but that in our discussions with our Allies we should r egypt-rt the pointof view adopted by the British Represonia-tive tm the Upper Silesis-n Commission, end should bear in&quot;mind the industrial interesiof Germany.(b)  That the Secretary cf State for Foreign affairs should eemmaixioate immediately to the French andItalian Governments the nature of the interpre-tatiun given by the British Government to thefirst and third points raised by Dr Stresemannand referred to in (a)  (I) and (S).Later in the Meeting a message was received from the german ambassador asking for an immediate interview with the Prime Minis-ter.    After the Prime Minister had seen him, ho reported r,o theCabinet that the German Ambassador had asked him the very guea-determination  contained in Lord Kilmarnock&apos;s telegram, and he had repliedon the lines already approved by the Cabinet and recorded above*In addition,,  the German Ambassador had asked whether Clause  34of the Treaty of Versailles,  giving the Reparation Comiais eicndiswreti^n to extend the date and modify the form of payments., vasstill applicable?    The Prime Minister had replied that thai was par&apos;,of the Treaty and wan still applicable.    He had warned the Amboa-aador,  however, that.once the bonds proposed in the ultimatum were issued and distributed among neutrals, the credit of Germany waul abe involved,    If any request was than made by Germany for a post--penement or reduction cf her liabilities, the Reparation Occ-mis--sion would have to take the issue cf the bonds rnto very carefulaccount,    That, ho had pointed out* was the  &quot;nly degree to whichArticle SS4 -was affect d by the ultimatum, -and the Gorman Arch ass a-dor had appreciated the point. A second point raised by tho &apos;German Ambassador had been in regard to the difficulty in whichthe German Government was placed in securing the disarmament cfBavaria,  and he had asked whether, if the German Government gaveevery evidence that it was doing its best, the application of the sanctions would be withheld.    The Prime Minister had replied byrecalling that at Spa and els^wh^re, so long as Germany had given      iunmistakable evidence that she was doing her best, the letter ofthe Treaty of Versai;ll&amp;a -had not been rigidly insisted on.
&quot;Finally,  the German Ambassador had suggested that the GermanGovernment might possibly accept the ultimatum on the assumo-tion that Germany would be permitted&apos;to retain the industrialparts of Upper Silesia.    The Prime Minister,, however,  had wam-ed him most seriously against such a course, which would playinto the hands of the more extreme elements among the Allies,(A.&apos;, fuller &apos;tteMerah&apos;dum&apos; of-the Prime Ministerysrepp rt to the Cab inet has&apos; been ro n d e f or the.inJkii&apos;ratiion^ofl.the Secretary&apos; of f hate&quot; for&quot;&quot;Foreign Affairs.&apos;)(2)  In the course of the preceding discussion the at ten--tion of the Cabin-1 was called to telegram No.94, dated May 9,.1921,  from Colonel Percival,  the British representative Onthe Upper Silesian Plebiscite Commission, indicating thatcertain French officers were not adopting a strictly impartialattitude.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed the Cabinet that he had already made representations to theFrench Government in this connection,While emphatic views were expressed that it might benecessary within the next fe&quot;  days to make strong rep resent a-tions to the French Government in regard to the importance of deciding the disposition of Upper Silesia with the strictestfairness and impartiality., the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs advised the Cabinet that imi:. &quot;diate action :J.&apos;ouli be premature and ill-advised.(3) With reference to Cabinet 35 (21),- Conclusion 2, theCabrn^t were informed that no reports lad been received that morning or disturbances by reservists in any quarter,(4) The  Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs in regard to telegrams(No. 303 of May 6, 1921,. and No.304 and No.305 of May 6,. 1921)from the British Ambassador at  &quot;ashington -(Sir Auckland G&apos;-ddesin regard to proposals made to the African Government  for american Relief in Ireland (Paper C.P.-2921).The Cabinet agreed   ..To approve the draft telegram attachedto Lord Curzon&apos;s Memorandum.,, in which,the American proposals are- emphaticallyrejected on the ground that there is notthe smallest need for relief in Ireland.-3-
(5) With reference to Cabinet 45 (20), Conclusion 2, theCabinet had before then.the following documents in regard to imperial Wireless Communications:-Letter from India Office to Secretary,Cabinet (Paper 0 * P,-2081),Letter from Air Ministry to Secretary,Cabinet (Paper CP,--2211),Memorandum bv the Secretary of State forIndn a (Laper&quot; G. p.-2808) ,Note by the Secretary, Cabinet  (paper cp.-2876)..The Cabinet referred the question backto the Sub-Committee of the Committeeof Imperial Defence, with full author-ity to decide.(6) Th^ Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Safeguarding of Industries Bill,in viflw of its importance and its  finan-cial aspects, should remain for discus-sion on the Floor of the House, and thatthe Railway Bill should be sent upstairsto Committee:(h) That Mr Henderson&apos;s motion on Old age pensions, which raised the question of granting Pensions without any deductionson account of private.means, should be opposed and that the Whips shorld beput on:(c)  That the Chancellor of the Exchequer andthe Minister of Health should confer asto which of the.ru should speak for theGovernment on the Old Age Pensions.motion.(7)  The Cabinet toofooote of  (i) Conclusions o^ a Confer-nee held onMav 2, 1921, at 12-30 p.m.   (paper cp.-2898, Revise)   Refusal of Transport &quot;workers to handle Coal.(Append1 x IT )(ii) Relief at the Cost of the Rates inColliery Districts   Memorandum bythe Minister of Health (Paper CP.-2907).(Appendix. Ixl,)Whit ehall Ga rde ns , S. W. 1,May 10,  1921.
appendix      i,flo.  2Q2?   froir. LORD EILMARNQCK    at, Per-lindated PLAY 9.  1921.Doctor Stresemann has  just been to see me.    Although he d;dnot expressly say so he is evidentlj   contemplating assumingoffree as Chancellor.    He told me that party leaders cf parties-oxmxng Government were practically united in thinkin- that n ^rmanvshould accept terms of Allies and hoped to be able to&apos;&apos;persuade  &quot;  &quot;their party Co^mitteea to approve this policy but their finald^efsion T&quot;n-t d^r^d on clearing up of following points about which . there was ronsi d^rahie obscure ty.1. Authentic information was required as to interpretation ofprotocol delivered to Germany by Reparations Commission as regardspassage dealing with alteration of paragraph 19 annexe 2 of part Sof Treaty of Versailles.    Phrase at end of first sentence of oom-munication of Reparations Commission runs &quot;or to enable any AlliedPower to proceed with restoration or development of industry orlife&quot;.    Question is whether this applies only to restoration of damage caused by war or whether it means  that any Allied power could at any time require Germany to deliver any goods necessaryfor development of its industry or economic life.&apos;   Latter inter-pretation would mean that any Allied Power e.g.  Italian or Serbiancould four years hence demand delivery by Germany of 20 ships or1,000 agricultural instruments.    Such a provision would paralyseGerman industry to such an extent that its acceptance would beimpossible.2. With regard to section 9 of conditions notified to germany by Reparations Commission, explanations are ashed for as to whetherit is intention that German reparation (recovery) act 1921 shall remain in force indefinitely or whether condition notified in thissection is merely intended to cover period of transition until actin quests on can he repealed.    It is understood that German Ambassadors-dor in London has received some comrunication from Mr Lloyd Georgeon this question but exact purport is not known.    Anxiety existsas to whether,  in the case of England, German indi.io.try would beburdened to a greater extent  than the 26$ now imposed.3.  Would sanctions imposed on bar eh Sth, especially thoseinvolving occupation of Dusseldorf, Duisburg and Ruhrort etc andRhine Custurns be cancelled in event of Germany accepting terms ofultimatum?    Stresemann pointed out that such acceptance involvedvery heavy responsibility and would rr.eet with strong opposition and unless Government which resumed responsibility were able topoint to some definite alleviation which had been gained theywould not be able to obtain majority in Reichstag.4.  Stresemann said that morning papers reported Pri.ti.sh and.Italian representatives on Upper Silk sian Plebiscite commission had r-ported in favour of Pleas and Rybnik and a part of Eattowitzdistrict being given to Poland, and the remainder of plebiscitearea being allotted to Germany.    French representative on theother hand was reported to wish allotment o&quot;: whole of industrial area to Poland.    He recognised however regretfully that in &quot;lew oflarge Polish majorities in districts said to be allotted to Polandir p-r-i-Msh and Italian reports those areas must be regarded^ astost &quot;^o t^rmanv * * she retained greater part of industrial     ^^istr-icts ^e thought that by a great effort (group undecipherable,tri fnt-  (?succeed in)  fulfilling economic conditions imposed by allied ultimatum.    If therefore he ;vere assured that Britxshand Italian Governments would stand by proposals of their repre--sentatives  (as reported in the press) he would be ready to assut)responsibility for the carrying out of economic ooncutaonsWithout industrial area however Gen. an industry wouxd oee
handlcapped that it would not be capable of assuming those obli-sations.    &quot;furthermore any Government which accepted&quot;Allied terms and then was ^aeed with loss of region in question could not last fortnight.    Before deciding advisability as to whether it wouldbe possible for him to form a Government capable of carrying through acceptance of Allied terms,  he would greatly appreciatesome fore of private assurance to the effect that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would not allow any solution of the question otherthan that founded on report already made by British representa-tive on Plebiscite Commission.Stresemann spoke with great earnestness and moderation in athoroughly businesslike spirit, and I am convinced that, if hecould be reassured on above points he is persuaded that he can secure acceptance of our terms.It is of the utmost importance that I should receive an answer at the   earliest possible moment, as the question forming a Government can scarcely be delayed beyond tomorrow.

</content>
</cab>
