<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/1/13 images: 218-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.188COPY NO.WAR CABINET3NAVAL.  MILITARY AND AIP SITUATION-APPRECIATION BY THE CHIEFS OP STAFF COMMITTEE.Note by the^Sejcrejt^ary;.By direction of the Prime Minister, I circulateherwitli, for consideration by the War Cabinet, theattached weekly Resume (No. l) by the Chiefs of staff committee dealing with the Naval, Military and Air Situationup to 12 noon, 7th September, 1939.    (paper No. C. 0.S.(39)18),(Signed)    3. E. BRIDGE S.Secretary..Richmond Terrace, S.W.I8th September,  19390

^DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT      j ^TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO.WAR    CABINET,CHIEFS OP STAFF COMMITTEE.WEEKLY RESUME (NO.  l) OF THE NAVAL, MILITARY ANDAIR SITUATION UP TO IS NOON, 7th SEPTEMBER.REPORT.The accompanying Joint Naval, Military and AirForce appreciation of the situation as at 12 noon on the7th September is circulated in accordance with therecommendation contained in Paper No. W.P.(G.) (39) 3, and approved by the War Cabinet on the 7th September, (PaperNo. W.M.(39) 7th Conclusions, Minuted 17.3.        We should be glad of instructions as to whether,   theform and substance of this Appreciation meets the requirementsof the War Cabinet.(Signed)    C-.L. NEVif ALL.DUDLEY POUND.S.  IRONSIDE.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.8th September, 1939.

WEEKLY RESUME jNO a a.) OF THE NAVAL MILITARYAND AIR SITUATION. %OM^THE OUTBRpK. OFHOSTILITIES IN&apos;POLAND TO&apos;IS NOON*      *      &quot; 7JM. .lssPTEMBERff 1959 ov Alj S xTUATlQN...,General.1. The Royal Navy has been fully engaged in its task of securing sea communications, escorting military andair reinforcements, giving protection to British and Alliedshipping, and in interrupting the Enemy&apos;s seaborne trade.2. The entire Fleet has taken up War Dispositions as modified to meet the naval  situation which has devolped in the opening days of the war.    The necessary patrolshave been established,3. Three Polish Destroyers made a timely passage fromthe Baltic to the North Sea, gind will, in due course, make a valuable addition to our Destroyer strength.40 Progress is being made with the fitting out of linersas Armed Merchant Cruisers.,5. The French Fleet have taken up their dispositions as agreed in the Allied war plans.Attacks upon Enemy Submarines.6. Since war broke out,  there has been very littleactivity by German submarines in the North Sea and no shipping has been sunk there,,    Mines have been laid by a submarine, inone instance, in this area.

Ill70 In the-Atlaniijj^ ^and coast of the british isles, German submarines have definitely made their presenceknown as far South as the coast of Portugal. There are alsoreports of German submarines in the Caribbean probably basedon Curacao.8, There is no reliable information of submarines havingpassed through the Channel, but a steamer is reported to havebeen blown up off Shoreham in the afternoon of 6th September.No details yet received.    This may have been due either to a submarine or to a mine laid by a submarine. enemy submarines are reported and have been attacked in the WesternChannel.9.        A number of attacks have been delivered upon enemy submarines but detailed reports, which would enable a definiteopinion as to their success to be given, have not yet beenreceived.10.       List of British and Foreign Merchant Vessels sunk bythe enemy up to a.m. 6th September, 1959.Type	Name	Flag.	Gross Tonnage	Date       Where	By        Hows,s, s.s. s,s. s.s.	ASHEN IA BOSNIA ROYAL SCEPTRE RIO CLARO.	Br. Br. Br. Br.	13581 2401 4853 4000	3/9    off Ireland 5/9    off Spain off Bay of 5/9         Biscay. 6/9   off Spain	s/m.     Torp. s/m.     Gun. s/m.       ? s/m.       ?

Enemy Merchant Shipping and Losses.11.       On 1st September German merchant ships were generallyerdered to leave British, Colonial and French ports and make for home or the nearest neutral ports0    Those neutral portsmost in favour are Brazilian and Spanish ports, especially the Canary Islands and Vigo, and also Italian ports in theMedit&amp;jpjpanean and Red Sea.18.       In the Far East, Dutch East Indian ports and Japaneseports are being used.    A number of German ships are still onthe high seas, probably making for such refuge as is practicable.13.       Bremen is probably at Murmansk, North Russia, hut she has also been reported at Vera Cruz and making for Mar DelPlata.14.      Enemy Mercantile Losses.Ship	Tonnage	Date	Position		How dealt with.Olinda Carl Friten J.Molkenbuar Inn	4576 6594 5294 2867	5/9 5/9 5/9 6/9	off River Plate off River Plate off Norway near Para          1	AJAX AJAX JERSEY TEPTUNE	Sunk.. Sunk. Captured while sinking Captured and sunk?Convoys.15. The convoy system is being commenced on certain routes.Elsewhere the controlled routing system is in force.

X i. 3Enemy Mines.16.       The Germans have declared a mined area in theNorth Sea, and there is evidence that laying hascommenced.Mines have also been reported in the Southern partof the North Sea and definitely located off the NorthForelands.17.       The Germans have also broadcast the limits ofmined areas in the eastern North Sea and the entrancesof the Baltic.Movements of Enemy Warships - German Main Units.18.       On 1st September, the disposition of the Germanunits appeared to be as follows:-battle cruiser   &quot;Gneisenau&quot;&quot;Scharnhorst&quot;Armoured Ships &quot;Deutschland&quot;&quot;Scheer&quot;Cruisers&quot;Graf Spee&quot;&quot;Hipper&quot;&quot;Blucher&quot;&quot;Nurhberg&quot;&quot;Leipzig&quot;&quot;Koenigsburg&quot;&quot;Koln&quot;&quot;Emden&quot;neighbourhoodofW/havenBalticitMouth of the ElbeWilhelmshaven

19.       The information received concerning the subsequentmovements of these vessels is very scanty, but it wouldappear that no vessels have left German territorial waters except two cruisers possibly &quot;Koln&quot; and &quot;Konigsherg&quot;accompanied by two destroyers which were sighted about60 miles N.W.  of Horn?s Reef at-0715, 6th September,returning to Germany.,    It is possible this force was employed in covering minelaying activities in that area.Light Forces.20.       On 1st September, the German Destroyer Flotillasare believed to have been divided evenly between theBaltic and North Sea ports.    It is probable that themajority are now stationed at North Sea ports.The Torpedo Boat Flotillas are still believed to bein the Baltic.Other Warships.21.       The old battleship &quot;Schleswig-Holstein&quot; hasbeen in the vicinity of Danzig since 25th August;    she has been engaged in bombarding Gdynia.The old battleship &quot;Schlesien&quot; is believed tohave been based at Wilhelmshaven since 1st September,Raiders.28.       No reports have yet been received of any Germanraider activities.

MILITARY SITUATION.FRANCE.23. French troops are reported to he in contact withthe forward elements of the Siegfried Line in the Saar,hut no further details are yet available.POLAND.24.       The German forces crossed the Polish frontiers at.55 a.m.  on 1st September.      The first moves came fromPomerania into the Corridor, from German Silesia into and North of Polish Silesia, and from Moravia andSlovakia across the Carpathians.      A further move from east Prussia South and Westward soon became apparent.From the outset the Poles were at a grave disadvantage in that they had only some 30 infantry divisions withwhich to face the initial heavy German concentrationsagainst them;    they have few mechanized units, their transport is largely horsed, and their air defenceinadequate.25.        By 4th September the Polish Corridor was to ailintents and purposes in German occupation, so that east prussia could be easily rei and as a result the drive on Warsaw increased in strength.26.        It was early apparent that the German attack fromSilesia was being made in great strength and withmechanized formations, with the result that the Poleshad to fall hack rapidly, and must have lost fairlyheavily both in casualties and in prisoners.

27.        No efforts to advance nee were made by the germans in the Poznan Salient.      The movement with which thePoles were faced was a pincer movement from East Prussiaand from Silesia,28.        The progress of the two arms of the pincers fromreports received up to mid-day 7th September is asfollows I -(a) North (German Fifth Group).The Polish forces are resisting the german attacks some miles North of Warsaw.      While the attacks appear to be held up for the moment N.W.of Warsaw there are indications that the mainGerman drive may be designed to pass East ofthe Capital-.(&quot;D) South (German Fir Ft and Second Groups).In the South the Poles are holding theGermans on the line Sxeradz - Piotrkow South ofLodz and there is a report of a Polish counter-attack near Piotrkow., &quot;but the Germans claim the capture of Kielce,, although the Poles havenot yet admitted it.      This drive is veryserious for not only does it bring the german forces very close to &quot;one Polish. industrial area S,E,   of Warsaw but also&apos;, in conjunctionwith the attack from East Prussia, there maybe grave danger of all Polish forces in thePoznan Salient being completely surrounded.South of the attack on Kielce  the situationis still obscure.      The Germans have claimedCracow and there is little doubt that thispocket must go before long.

11 *yi. -1 /29.        The main cause of the great difficulties with,which the Polish armies have been faced has been the overwhelming German air superiority.      Polish railwayshave &quot;been heavily attacked, a considerable proportionof their war industries have been put out of action,and their meagre air force has been reduced to a stateof impotence.Nevertheless the last official reports statedthat the morale of the Polish Army remained high.GERMANY.30.        German divisions on 7th September have been identified as followsWestern Frontier,. 24 divisions.Central Germany. 18 divisions.Eastern Frontier. 54 divisions.Grand Total - 96 divisions.In addition further reserve and Landv/ehr divisionshave probably been formed.Eastern Front.51.        It is believed that the German forces operating on the Eastern Front are divided into five groups andthat the taskg of these groups are as follows:-First Grmro.To oc cupy 0rac ow.Second Group (motorized, group).To attack junction of Polish Second and ThirdArmies and to advance from Eadomsko to Warsaw.

Third, and Fourth Groups.These have cut off the Corridor and are now reported to he mopping up the isolated polish forces.Fifth Group.This group advanced from East Prussia.Western Front.52.        Latest information is that areas of Aachen andOsnatorlick are heing reinforced hy German troops and a newreserve division has heen identified opposite the dutch frontier.      An unconfirmed report stated that trooptrains filled with mechanized troops, etc., were seen on 5th September in the neighbourhood of Berlin movingfrom East to West.      There is no confirmation, however,that these troops are being moved from the Eastern Front.U.S.8.R.33.        There have been rumours ever since the German-Soviet non-aggression pact was signed on 22nd Augustthat a military pact was also contemplated.      CertainSoviet Officers have gone to Berlin but there is no confirmation yet that a military pact will be concluded.The reports of Soviet military concentrations on herWestern frontiers are not conclusive and appear, atpresent, to be no more than is reasonable under thepresent circumstances.      There are few signs that theSoviet is yet likely to abandon the policy of leetingother nations fight, while she waits to reap thebenefits later.

34.        The partial withdrawal of Japanese troops fromthe vicinity of Hong Kong, together with other localindications, suggests that the Japanese do not at presentcontemplate any major operations against Hong Kong.35.       Japan has, however, &quot;been quick to take advantageof the European war situation, and has presented demands to Great Britain and other countries involved in thepresent European conflict to withdraw troops fromregions under Japanese control.      Japan has also asked usto stop helping the Chinese.AIR SITUATION.Strength, of German Air Force.36.        The estimated strength of the German Air force on the 1st September was as follows.&apos;-1750 long range &quot;bombers (858 in North west germany)580 short range bombers ,1215 fighters670 reconnaissance and Army Co-operation305 Coastal and ship borne.Total 432037.        Apart from the aircraft listed above, which are all of modern types, Germany had available about 1,000troop transport airoraft,  of which it is estimated that500 are in troop transport units.      She also had available a considerable number of aircraft of obsolescent typesincluding aircraft taken over from the Czech Air Force.Reports have been received that Germany is formingreserve squadrons out of these second line aircraft,but no confirmation can be obtained of the number of

nosg.uad.rons to be formed.. The reserves of modern aircraftbehind the first line units are estimated, at 100%.German Operations in Poland.38.        German air attacks have so far been directed against aerodromes, aircraft and engine factories, and rail communications, as well as against the polish forces.      Casualties to civilians have &quot;been causedmainly by bombs falling in the vicinity of the objectivesaimed at.      There is no confirmation of the reports from Polish sources that the Germans are using mustardgas bombs.      Although the aircraft factories and the flying training schools must be regarded as now out ofaction,  the alternative aerodromes which had beenprepared for use by the operational squadrons were well concealed, and it is understood that they have notyet been located and. attacked.      The Polish Air Forceconsisted,  on the outbreak of war,  of 494 aircraft ofwhich only some 30 bombers were of modern types.      TheGerman Air Force has therefore been able to obtain acomplete ascendency and is now in a position to concentrate almost entirely in support of land operations.British Air Operatipns.39.        An attack against German warships was carried outon 4th September,  1939, by two squadrons of Wellingtonsand two squadrons of Blenheims,      The results reportedwere - two hits with 500 lb, bombs on a warship in theS chillig-Roads, and one hit on the side of the lockalongside a warship at the entrance to the Kiel Canal.

101tj the attack was carried out at a low altitude in the face of considerable opposition by fighters and A.A.fire.      Seven of our aircraft failed to return.40.        In addition flights over Western Germany havebeen carried out each night in order to distributepropaganda pamphlets.      Opposition has been slight,and has been confined to spasmodic A.A.  fire.      Nofighters have been encountered and it is estimatedthat some 9,000,000 pamphlets have dropped in Germany.




</content>
</cab>
