<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/32 images: 158-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
g DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERWifflNT.SET.     ,Copy No.WAR CABINET.r^ XkA )32.March 1941.REPLACSJIiJRT OP BRITISH AND ALLIED TONNAGE.Memorandum by the Minister of Shipping.ALLIED LOSSES.1. I am being pressed by our allies to allow them to build ships inU.K. yards to replace some of their losses.     I consider that we should allow them to do so under a scheme which, will provide a fair allocationboth between the different Allies and between our Allies and ourselves.Such a scheme is desirable for the following reasons(a) Our Allies cannot build in their own yards.(b) We have monopolised available building facilities not only inour own yards (including Canada and Hong Kong) but also inthe U.S.A., the only foreign source available.(c) We have similarly bought practically all useful existing ships-offered for sale abroad.(d) Wo have all the. seized French and Danish shipping under our flagand all the captured enemy shipping except for that seized bythe Dutch.(e) It is in our interests that new building in our yards should be financed out of the sterling funds due to the Allies from theWar Risks Insurance Office in respect of vessels lost.(f) The allocation of allied orders to British yards during the warwill retain or develop a connection which may be of value tothe Industry after the war.2. The governing principle, I suggest, should be to use the facilities available in such a.way as to secure as soon as practicable after the -war that each of us should have about the same proportion of the total tonnageas we possessed on the outbreak of war.     In working out this principle weshould take into account all losses and also all accretions from all sources.     Allowance for the age of vessels lost could be made by allocationsamong the second-hand ships purchased.3* The post-war situation is too uncertain to attempt to do more thansecure agreement on very general principleso     Once such agreement has been secured the inanediate problem of allowing the Allies to place contractsnow, would become more tractable.    On this I propose that we should offer to the Allies a proportion of new ships building in thi3 country and abroad and also of secondhand ships purchased, subject to the following conditions:-(a) That a proportion of the secondhand ships bought and of new ships built abroad (such ships cost more than those built in the U.K.) should be taken by the Allies;   if an Allyrefuses to take such ships in replacement, the proposed allocation in United Kingdom yards should not be increased and might be decreased.(b) The price would be what we paid ourselves, except that, since theinsurance received is in sterling, we can hardly demand dollarsin full in respect of our dollar payments.     But in view of thefact that Allied Shipowners generally have had a substantial part of their tonnage free for general trading at high rates(paid largely in dollars) we should try to obtain payment in dollars as to one-half for &quot;dollar&quot; ships.     The proportion,
might, however, &quot;be altered in special cases and sterlingaccepted where there have been no free ships,(c) All vessels so sold or built should remain under British flag forduration of the war;   this will no doubt be resisted by the Alliesand we might have to give way, but in any ease the ships wouldbe requisitioned at British rates except for any additionnecessary to correspond with actual extra charges.(d) All vessels built to be of the type we require and to conform toour specification.4* If these conditions are accepted, I would propose to allocate to theAllies up to about one quarter of the &quot;building facilities available to usin 194-1, including (subject to U.So consent) those in the U.S.A., plus asuitable allocation of secondhand ships;   this would be subject toabatement to the extent that existing British vessels have been, or maybe, sold to the Allies.     This proportion is much less favourable to theAllies than it may appear at first sight.     On figures of net losses theAllies would be entitled to a very much higher proportion than this,and it must be remembered that no orders now placed by Allies would be delivered until 1942, that is for the first 2^ years of the war theoutput of British yards would have gone splely to British owners.LOSSES OF BRITISH OWNERS.5. Our own yards are building in part on owners account and in parton Government account.     British owners are allowed to place orders for ships of the types and specifications we require;   the vessels whenbuilt come under requisition for the duration of the war.     government building absorbs the remaining facilities.     Many owners are reluctant to place orders in view of the high and uncertain price they would haveto pay.     (They, receive insurance on a lower basis of valuation thanAllied owners and the hire paid for their ships is much less).Consequently, in fact, though not as a matter of policy, we are buildingmore ships on Government account than on private account, and many ownerswho would like to use the insurance moneys payable in respect of lossare holding back.6. The shipping industry is pressing me strongly to sanction the sale to owners of ships ordered by the Government, in replacement of vesselslost.     There would be increased feeling on the part of British owners thatthey were being unjustly treated if we put into operation a large scalescheme for replacement of Allied ships, while still withholding permission to British owners to buy Government ships.     The general considerations infavour of permitting these sales to British owners are set out in papersW.P. (G)(40)216 and W.P. (G)(40)266.7.  s the Minister of Labour and other Ministers pointed out in theWar Cabinet on the 4th March (W.M. (41) 23rd Conclusions) shipowners areworried about the post-war position.    The Cabinet accordingly agreedthat the question of the sale of vessels ordered by the Government toshipowners who had lost vessels during the war should again beconsidered by them.     I accordingly now seek approval for the sale atcost of Government built ships to U.K. owners who wish to buy them in replacement of vessels lost during the war.R.H.C.Ministry of Shipping,8th March 1941.

</content>
</cab>
