<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/53/13 images: 88-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1944.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of...........................................TOP SECRET. / Copy No.W.P. (44) 413.26th July, 1944.WAR CABINET./&quot; CROSSBOW &quot; SECURITY.SPECIAL MEASURES FOR &quot; big ben.&quot;Report by the Chiefs of Staff.WE have considered the annexed note by Sir Findlater Stewart who, inconsultation with all the interested Departments, has been considering the specialsecurity measures which will be necessary should long-range rocket attack on london begin, to prevent information on the fall of shot reaching the enemy.2.   Sir Findlater Stewart puts forward two alternative schemes (i) A scheme which aims at denying information to the enemy for as long aspossible, including such information as would filter through to him byslow channels.   Even this somewhat drastic plan cannot guaranteesuccess for more than ten days to a fortnight.(ii) A scheme which would be designed to prevent information reaching theenemy for 48 hours, but would not attempt to block the many slowchannels through which news would certainly reach him in about weeks. This plan is less drastic than (i) above, but it must be emphasised that its adoption would render useless any attempt to tighten up after the 48 hours had elapsed, since the information theenemy required would by then be on its way to him through the manyslow channels left unblocked.3. If the first alternative were put into effect, the idea would be to decide atthe end of 48 hours whether to prolong the measures, and if so for how long.4. The measures to be taken under the two schemes are set out in Appen-dices I and II respectively of Sir Findlater Stewart&apos;s note. Under the firstscheme travel and communications of all kinds to destinations outside GreatBritain have to be completely stopped except for operational or urgent Govern-ment business. The restrictions required would be more stringent than those proposed for &quot; Overlord &quot; security purposes and would include, of course, the suspension of diplomatic mail and telegrams other than American and Russian.The second scheme is much less drastic and would simply involve holding upcommunications and travel for 48 hours.5. We are not entirely convinced that the information which the enemymight derive from communications with this country would be of sufficient value to justify the very drastic steps necessary under the first scheme. Nevertheless,we feel that on balance it would be wrong to deny ourselves the option to take any measures which might mitigate the accuracy or severity of the attack. Wetherefore recommend that the first alternative scheme should be put into force if and when the time comes. It can always be abandoned after 48 hours if there is any doubt ahout its necessity or value.6. All the necessary measures have been agreed with the Departments, andall that is necessary is a decision on the policy.(Signed) A. F. BROOKE.C. PORTAL.ANDREW CUNNINGHAM.&apos;    r b[27892]
ANNEX.Note by Sir Findlater Stewart.I have recently been discussing with Departments the special security measures which will be necessary should the enemy launch &quot; big ben &quot; attack against this country. The Air Staff have now decided that, so far as flying bombs are concerned, they are prepared to rely on the existing censorship arrangements.But in the case of &apos;&apos; big ben &quot;&apos; they feel that the type of information which theenemy will require is more easily communicated than in the case of flying bombs.So many of the latter are launched against this country that he could not possiblyexpect to discover where each one fell, and to get information about the meancentre of distribution would involve a difficult piece of technical investigationrequiring the fullest information; on the other hand, the number of long-rangerockets he would be able to launch would be relatively small, and the effect of eachone would be much greater, so that it would be a relatively simple matter to discover precisely where each one had fallen.With this in mind, the Air Staff are most anxious to prevent the leakage tothe enemy of any information about the effect of his fire, and in particular aboutthe fall of shot, for a period of at least 48 hours after the &quot; big ben &quot; attack hasstarted. They feel that the enemy will have great difficulty in carrying outphotographic reconnaissance of the likely target area, and they hope that it willbe possible to jam his wireless equipment for the tracking and plotting of theprojectiles; it is therefore the more important to close down on his third and onlyremaining means of obtaining information i.e., from the ground reports of eyewitnesses. With this object they have asked for special security arrangements,to be put into effect as soon as the fall of the first long-range rocket is confirmed,closing for at least 48 hours all possible channels through which information onthe subject could leak to the enemy; this would give time for consideration of thefuture security requirements in the light of the way the attack developed, and towards the end of the 48 hours the position could be reviewed, and the specialsecurity measures extended for a further period, or modified as necessary.The Air Staff wish it to be clearly understood that there is no particularvirtue in the period of 48 hours for which they are asking in the first instance;the only object of fixing a limited period is to provide an interval, as short aspossible, during which the Air Staff can judge the manner in which the situationis likely to develop, and decide, before its expiry, what their future security requirements will be. It is unlikely that the Air Staff will feel themselves ableto dispense with the special measures at the end of the period, and they will veryprobably ask for them to be continued as long as possible; so much depends onthe success of our counter measures against the enemy&apos;s projectors, and this in turn will be very much affected by the weather conditions prevailing at the time.In view of this, it is clear that the Air Ministry&apos;s objective would not besecured simply by taking steps to prevent any information from reaching theenemy within 48 hours of the first attack. It would be a relatively simple matter to secure this, since most channels through which information can leak to theenemy take longer than 48 hours, and therefore no steps need be taken to closethem. It would be necessary to stop travel by air to all countries which couldbe reached within 48 hours, and from which information could quickly pass tothe enemy (these countries are Spain, Portugal, Tangier, Gibraltar, Turkey,Sweden and Switzerland); telegrams and air mails to these destinations wouldalso have to be held up, and, in the case of telegrams, South America wouldhave to be added to the list. Communications and travel on operational mattersor in connexion with the business of Government Departments could be exempted,provided warnings were issued to all personnel concerned against any mentionin communications or by official travellers of the effects of the &apos;: big ben &quot; attack.But if we are to stop all channels of leakage from Great Britain for a preliminary period, on the understanding that it may be necessary to continuethe measures beyond the 48 hours, we have got to close the slower channels also as soon as the attack starts. This will mean that travel to, and communications with, all other destinations, including Ireland, must be completely stopped,except again for travel and communications connected with operational mattersor with urgent Government business. While it might be possible to do this for48 hours (though in some cases even this short period of complete closure would cause very considerable inconvenience e.g., ships engaged on the short sea trafficwith Ireland would have to be held up for 48 hours, and all outgoing aircraft
other than operational aircraft would have to be grounded, for a similar period),it is clear from my discussions with Departments that it would be impossible tohold these very drastic restrictions for more than a few days. The restrictionsrequired would be more stringent than those imposed for &apos;&apos; Overlord &apos;&apos; securitypurposes; it would be useless, for example, merely to restrict overseas travel,since in this case we are aiming at preventing any leakage of information aboutisolated incidents, which will very quickly become known to a large number of people, and the only way to do this is to prevent anyone at all from leaving thecountry. By forcing us to take such very drastic steps, the enemy would achieve a very considerable victory; by shooting off one long-range rocket, which mightwell do no particular damage, he would, to a large extent, isolate this country from the outside world, and his propaganda about the rocket would be left witha free field. The problem for consideration is whether the importance whichthe Air Staff attach to measures of this kind is sufficient to justify the veryserious consequences if the restrictions are prolonged much beyond the initial period of 48 hours. If it is decided that we cannot accept these consequences,many of the restrictions which will otherwise be necessary need not be imposedat all, since, as pointed out above, the channels through which information canreach the enemy within 48 hours are relatively few. The alternatives aretherefore : (1) To devise a scheme by means of which Great Britain could be sealedfor a period of perhaps a week or ten days (however drastic themeasures taken, one could not guarantee their success for a much longer period), to put this scheme into effect as soon as &quot; big ben &quot;attack starts, and to consider its continuation at the end of 48 hours.(2) To devise a scheme which would prevent any information reaching theenemy within 48 hours.If the Chiefs of Staff and the War Cabinet feel we can decide here and nowagainst any prolongation of the first scheme beyond the initial 48 hours, themore limited scheme under (2) would achieve very nearly the same result atrelatively little inconvenience.I attach at Appendices I and II summaries of the procedure to be followedby Departments according as the War Cabinet decide to seal the country as soonas &quot;big ben&quot; attack starts, or simply to aim at preventing any information about the attack reaching the enemy within 48 hours; both of these have been circulated and agreed with Departments,* and, as soon as we have a decisionon the general question raised in this report, one or other of them will become the operational orders on the security side for meeting the attack.(Signed) S. F. STEWART.Home Defence Executive,Norfolk House, St. James&apos;s Square, S.W. 1.12th July, 1944.* The Foreign Office would wish all diplomatic mail and telegrams of the United Statesand Soviet Ambassadors, and the Allied Governments resident in this country, to be passedwithout delay under whichever of the alternative procedures may be adopted. They point outthat the Allied Governments here have no reason to send out of this country any information about &quot; big ben &quot; attack. They would, however, ask the Foreign Ministers of these Governments,and the United States and Soviet Ambassadors, to make themselves personally responsible for ensuring that no such information was sent. Quite apart from the political objections to anattempt to hold up the telegrams of the Soviet Embassy, any action taken would probably be quite ineffective, since the Embassy possesses a private wireless transmitter.APPENDIX I.Procedure for Implementing Special &quot; big ben &quot; Security Measures.(This procedure will be followed should the War Cabinet decide that wemust stop any information on the subject of &quot; big ben &quot; leaving thecountry as soon as the attack starts.)Some of the measures listed below will be taken as soon as the Chiefs ofStaff decide &quot; big ben &quot; attack is imminent; these are marked with an asterisk.The remainder will be taken as soon as the Ministry of Home Security haveconfirmed that the attack has started.[27892] b 2
Admiralty will * (1) request the Allied Naval Authorities in this country to make no referenceto the attack in any wireless or cable communications sent by their headquarters or ships, whether in cypher or en clair;(2) delay the sailing of any Allied naval ships which are due to leave GreatBritain, except when such sailing is necessary for operational reasons;(3) stop all outward travel from Great Britain by naval personnel, eitherto Ireland or overseas, except for travel which is necessary for operational reasons;(4) delay the sailing from Great Britain of ships engaged on the short seatraffic between this country and Ireland;(5) hold up naval mail to naval personnel other than those stationed inEmpire countries (except Canada and Gibraltar).Air Ministry will (1) hold up any R.A.F., A.T.A. or civil aircraft due to leave Great Britain,other than R.A.F. and B.O.A.C. aircraft flying to North Americaand aircraft engaged on operations or required as reinforcements;* (2) arrange for all R.A.F. air crews, when being briefed for operations overenemy-occupied territory, to be warned not to mention the attack inany way if they should be shot down and captured by the enemy;(3) stop all travel from Great Britain by R.A.F. personnel, either to Irelandor overseas, except travel which is necessary for operational reasons;(4) hold up mail to R.A.F. personnel other than those stationed in empire countries (except Canada and Gibraltar).Dominions Office will * request the High Commissioners for the overseas Dominions not to makeany reference to the attack in their outgoing communications, whetherby bag or by cable, and whether in cypher or en clair.General Post Office will (1) arrange, in conjunction with Postal and Telegraph Censorship, for alloutgoing mail and telegrams (except to Empire destinations otherthan Canada and Gibraltar) to be held up, including all diplomaticmail and telegrams, but excluding communications sent by Govern-ment Departments on official business and Press communicationscensored by the Press Censorship;(2) arrange, in conjunction with the Ministry of Information, for theinvigilation of the operators of the private newspaper telegraph andteleprinter lines to Ireland, if this is not already in operation;(3) ensure that telephone operators, in accordance with advice received from local censors, inform diplomatic callers, including the HighCommissioner, that until further notice no language other thanEnglish may be used in conversation with Northern Ireland and Eire,if this is not already in operation.Home Office will (1) delay all out-going civilian travellers, including all diplomatic travellers,to overseas destinations, including Northern Ireland, except forGovernment servants on important official business;* (2) arrange for Immigration Control to warn outgoing official travellers atthe ports not to make any reference to the attack in conversation once they have left;* (3) arrange for the Police and Fire Service to be warned against any reference to the attack in communications passing over their wirelessnetwork.India Office will * ask the High Commissioner for India not to make any reference to the attack in his outgoing communications.
Ministry of Information will t (1) issue a Private and Confidential letter to editors forbidding, until further notice, the publication of any reports of explosions or bombingincidents resulting from enemy attacks;* (2) arrange, in conjunction with the General Post Office, for the invigilationof the operators of the private newspaper telegraph and teleprinterlines to Ireland, if this is not already in operation;t (3) warn the managers of the Press offices and agencies which have privatelines to Ireland that no messages, not excepting service messages ofa routine type, may be sent unless they have been passed by the censor.Postal and Telegraph Censorship will arrange, in conjunction with the General Post Office, for ail out-going mailand telegrams (except to Empire destinations other than Canada and gibraltar) to be held up, including all diplomatic mail and telegrams,but excluding communications sent by Government Departments on official business and Press communications censored by the press censorship.War Office will &apos;* (1) request the Allied Military Missions to make no mention of the attack in their outgoing communications, whether by bag, cable or wireless,and whether in cypher or en clair, and to pass this request on to theirAir Authorities;(2) stop all outgoing travel by military personnel, either to Ireland or over-seas except travel which is necessary for operational reasons;* (3) arrange with United States and Canadian authorities to hold up militarymail from troops in this country;(4) hold up mail to troops other than those stationed in Empire countries(except Canada and Gibraltar).Panel on Security Arrangements in Government Departments will * (1) warn all Government Departments against any mention of the attack in their outgoing communications;* (2) ask all Government Departments to ensure that members of their staffsleaving the country on official business are warned not to make any reference to the attack in conversation once they have left.Ministry of War Transport will * arrange for the Railway Companies to warn their staffs against any referenceto the attack in communications sent over their wireless network.I.S.R.B. will-(1) stop outgoing travel by personnel under their control, except in caseswhere it is operationally necessary for the personnel in question toleave;(2) warn any personnel leaving for enemy-occupied territory that, ifcaptured, they should make no reference of any kind to the attack.S.H.A .E.F. will-(1) hold up any United States aircraft due to leave Great Britain, otherthan aircraft engaged on operations, or on the service to north america, and aircraft required as reinforcements;* (2) arrange for all United States air crews, when being briefed for opera-tions over enemy-occupied territory, to be warned not to mention the attack in any way if they should be shot down and captured by theenemy;(3) stop outward travel from Great Britain, either to Ireland or overseas, bypersonnel under their control, including all United States service personnel, except in cases where it is operationally necessary for the personnel in question to leave;t The Ministry of Information will take this action, on the advice of the Ministry of home security, as soon as a &quot; big ben &quot; incident is suspected. ?
(4) warn any personnel leaving for operational theatres in which they mightbe captured by the enemy that, if captured, they should make no reference of any kind to the attack;* (5) request United States military headquarters in this country (e.g.,E.T.O.U.S.A.) to make no reference to the attack in their outgoingcommunications, whether by mail, cable or wireless, and whether incypher or en clair.APPENDIX II.Procedure for Implementing Special &quot;big ben&quot; Security Measures.(This procedure will be followed should the War Cabinet decide that the aim should be simply to prevent any information reaching the enemy within48 hours of the start of &apos;&apos; big ben &apos;&apos; attack.)Note. The destinations to which travel by air and air mail must be held up are :-Sweden. Turkey.Switzerland. Tangier.Spain. Gibraltar.Portugal.The destinations to which telegrams must be delayed are those listedand, in addition, South and Central America, Vatican City and spanish morocco.Some of the measures listed below will be taken as soon as the Chiefs ofStaff decide &quot; big ben &quot; attack is imminent; these are marked with an asterisk.The remainder will be taken as soon as the Ministry of Home Security haveconfirmed that the attack has started.A dmiralty will * (1) request the Allied Naval Authorities in this country to make no reference to the attack in any wireless or cable communications sent by their Headquarters or ships, whether in cypher or en clair;(2) hold up naval air mail to naval personnel in Normandy or in any of thecountries listed above.Air Ministry will (1) hold up any R.A.F. or civil aircraft due to leave Great Britain for thedestinations listed above, other than aircraft engaged on operations or required as reinforcements;* (2) arrange for all R.A.F. air crews, when being briefed for operations overenemy-occupied territory, to be warned not to mention the attack inany way if they should be shot down and captured by the enemy;(3) hold up air mail to R.A.F. personnel in Normandy or in any of thecountries listed above.General Post Office will arrange, in conjunction with Postal and Telegraph Censorship, for alloutgoing air mail and telegrams to the destinations listed above to beheld up, including all diplomatic and mail and telegrams, but excluding communications sent by Government Departments on officialbusiness and Press communications censored by the Press Censorship.Ministry of Information will 1t issue a Private and Confidential letter to editors, forbidding until further notice the publication of any reports of explosions or bombingincidents resulting from enemy attacks.Home Office will * arrange for the Police and Fire Service to be warned against any referenceto the attack in communications passing over their wireless net-work.f The Ministry of Information will take this action, on the advice of the Ministry of home security, as soon as a &quot; big ben &quot; incident is suspected.
Postal and Telegraph Censorship will arrange, in conjunction with the General Post Office, for all outgoing airmail and telegrams to the destinations listed above to be held up,-including all diplomatic mail and telegrams, but excluding communica-tions sent by Government Departments on official business and Presscommunications censored by the Press Censorship.War Office will-* (1) request the Allied Military Missions to make no mention of the attack in any wireless or cable communications thev send, whether in cypheror en clair, and to pass this request on to their Air Authorities;(2) hold up air mail to troops in Normandy or in any of the countries listedabove;(3) arrange with United States and Canadian authorities to hold up air mailfrom Great Britain to United States and Canadian personnel inNormandy and. Canadian personnel in Gibraltar.Panel on Security Arrangements in Government Departments will * warn all Government Departments against any mention of the attack inoutgoing air mail or telegrams to the destinations listed above.Ministry of War Transport will * arrange for the Railway Companies to warn their staffs against any referenceto the attack in communications sent over their wireless network.I.S.R.B. will-. warn any personnel leaving for enemy-occupied territory that, if captured,they should make no reference of any kind to the attack.S.H.A.E.F. will-(1) hold up any United States aircraft due to leave Great Britain for thedestinations listed above, other than aircraft engaged on operations or required as reinforcements;* (2) arrange for all United States air crews, when being briefed for operations over enemy-occupied territory, to be warned not to mention the attack in any way if they should be shot down and captured by the enemy;(3) warn any personnel leaving for operational theatres in which they mightbe captured by the enemy that, if captured, they should make no reference of any kind to the attack;(4) request United States military headquarters in  this country  (e.g.,E.T.O.U.S.A.) to make no reference to the attack in out-going air mailor telegrams to the destinations listed above.




</content>
</cab>
