<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/20/0 images: 179-182</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP   HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1947SECRET Copy No.CP. (47) 205 ^ ^17th July, 1947CABINETSTATUTE LAW REFORM  &apos;.. , ,  ...  ,Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor , tTHE present chaotic condition of the Statute Book is a public scandal: itis urgently necessary to set about reducing it to order, by a systematic programmeof consolidation and codification Bills, In the past the, difficulty, has, not beenthe pressure on Parliamentary time the existing procedure ensures that suchBills, need not occupy any appreciable time on the floor of either House-but&apos;thefact that Parliamentary Counsel and the Departments, concerned; have been toooccupied with work on current legislation. A scheme designed to get over, this difficulty was prepared at my, request by the, First Parliamentary Counsel ratherover a year; ago. . Its most important proposals were(a) There should be established in the Office of Parliamentary Counsel aseparate branch devoting its whole time to consolidation, andcodification. ,. .   : ,v(5) The Statute Law Committee, which has hitherto been responsible for this and other aspects of statute law reform, should be strengthened bythe addition of members of both Houses of Parliament, of the legal profession and perhaps of academic lawyers, and should be specificallycharged with the general superintendence of consolidation andcodification, including the preparation of. a long-term plan and itsrevision from time to time. , 1(c) Arrangements should be made for the recommendations of the Committeeto be considered in connection with the legislative programme, sotJhat it could be decided, in the light of the burden placed on Depart-ments by the programme of new legislation, what consolidation Bills1       could be introduced in each session.2. I submitted a scheme (HP.C. (46) 25) embodying these proposals tothe Legislation Committee on 12th March, 1946; it was accepted in principle on22nd March (H.P.C. (46) 10th Meeting) and I was invited to report: it to theCabinet, after conferring with the Lord President and the Minister without portfolio (then Lord Privy Seal) on the precise reconstitution of the statute law Committee. On consideration, however, my colleagues and I came,to theconclusion that it would be best to defer reaching a final, decision, or making any public announcement of the proposed changes until the summer of this year,when it was expected that a number of consolidation Bills, which were then in preparation, would be ready for introduction. This expectation has beenfulfilled; Bills to consolidate the Companies Acts, the Agricultural Holdings Acts,the Agricultural Wages Acts and the National Service Acts are in an advancedstate of preparation and should be ready for introduction next session. The time is therefore ripe, in my view, for the proposed changes to be finally settled andpublicly announced.3.   The first step is to set up the new consolidation branch in parliamentary counsel&apos;s Office.  I propose that it should be headed by Sir Granville Ram, whois shortly due to retire from the position of First Parliamentary Counsel.   Thisarrangement has been approved by the Treasury and is acceptable to Sir Granville33932
* Ram himself; and in my opinion we should seize the opportunity to secure his services for this purpose, thus giving an impetus to the whole&apos;project in its early stages.4. The second step is to reconstitute the Statute Law Committee. Thepresent; composition is given in Annex I. The proposals to which the-. lord president, the Minister without Portfolio and I have agreed are set out ir.Annex II. It will be seen that it is proposed that the Committee should includethree Peers and three members of the House of Commons. I hope that theCabinet will approve the general lines of these proposals, leaving the precisecomposition of the Committee to be settled by myself, in consultation with theLord President and the Minister without Portfolio. Invitations to serve on!the Committee should, I suggest, be issued, as at present, by myself as Chairman5. The terms of reference of the Committee should, I suggest, be asfollows : &quot; To consider the steps necessary to bring the Statute Book up to date by consolidations, revision or otherwise, and to superintend the publication and indexing of statutes, revised statutes and statutory instruments.&quot;The recommendations of the Committee would be referred by me as necessaryto the Legislation Committee or the Future Legislation Committee so that the consolidation programme may be fitted in with the programme of new legislation. If the Cabinet accept these proposals, I am convinced that it will bepossible to surmount the main difficulties which have hitherto hindered theprogress of consolidation. I should, however, mention to the Cabinet anotherproposal which is contained in the scheme approved in principle by the legislation committee. This was that legislation should be introduced to facilitate thepreparation of consolidation and codification Bills, by enabling corrections and minor improvements of the law to be made by Order in Council subject to affirmative resolution. . ......7. The case for this proposal is that consolidation is frequently held upbecause of the existence of minor obscurities and discrepancies in the statutes tobe consolidated; in present circumstances these must either be. reproduced in the consolidation Bill or the preparation of the Bill must be held up until amending legislation has been passed by Parliament. This difficulty would be met if theMinister concerned had power to make the necessary amendments, by Order inCouncil. While I think there is a case for this proposal, it is not needed inconnection with the consolidation Bills referred to in paragraph 2 above and i suggest that we defer raising it until we are in a position to convince Parliamentof its necessity by showing that urgently needed consolidation measures are held up for lack of it.8.   To sum up, I recommend : (a) The establishment of a separate consolidation. branch in the Office ofParliamentary Counsel to be headed by Sir Granville Ram.(b) The reconstitution of the Statute Law. Committee on the lines suggestedin paragraph 4 above..      (c) The announcement of the proposals in Parliament before the Summeri; Recess.. :.-&apos;v-:-&apos;House of Lords, S.W.1,17th July, 1947.
:   ANNEX I1. The Statute Law Committee was first appointed by Lord Cairns in 1868&quot; to make the necessary arrangements and to superintend the work of preparingan edition of Statutes Revised &quot; and in 1870 the preparation and publication ofthe first edition of the Chronological Table and Index to the Statutes was placed under the direction of the Committee.2.   The following are at present members of the Committee :-The Lord Chancellor (Chairman).Lord Justice Somervell.Sir Cecil Carr.Sir Frederick Liddell.Lord Schuster.Sir E. G. H. Cox (of Messrs. Dyson,Bell and Co.).Sir Alexander Maxwell.Lieut.-Colonel Sir Norman Scorgie.Sir Granville Ram.3.   The Committee is responsible for the following publications: The Chronological Table and Index to the Statutes.The Annual Volume of the Statutes.A Table Showing the Effect of Legislation.The Annual Volume of Statutory Rules and Orders.The Triennial Index to the Statutory Rules and Orders.        ^The Index to the Local and Private Acts of the Session.In addition, the Committee makes recommendations on the work of consolida-tion of the Statutes and on the publication of new editions of Revised Statutesas required, and under the direction of the Committee a new subject index oflocal legislation is in course of preparation.4. The staff of the Committee at present consists of Mr. A. de J. Careywho is described as &quot;Editor of Revised Statutes, Statutory Rules and Orders,&amp;c,&quot; and who is in fact registrar of Statutory Rules and Orders, and three clerks.ANNEX IISuggested New Composition for the Statute Law CommitteeLord Chancellor, Chairman.Sir Granville Ram, Deputy Chairman.Members Attorney-General.Lord Advocate.Three Peers (including one Law Lord).Three Members of the House of Commons.Counsel to the Lord Chairman of Committees.Counsel to Mr. Speaker.First Parliamentary Counsel.Permanent Secretary, Treasury, or representative.Permanent Under-Secretary of State, Home Office.Permanent Secretary, Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department.Secretary of the Cabinet, or representative.King&apos;s Printer of Acts of Parliament.A Solicitor.Sir Alan Barlow.Sir Maurice Gwyer.Mr. J. G. Archibald (of Messrs.Parker, Garrett and Co.).Sir M. Millar Graig.Sir William Graham-Harrison.Sir John Maude.Mr. E. H. Keeling, M.P.Sir Albert Napier.


</content>
</cab>
