<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/20/0 images: 384-394</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BKITTANIC MAJESTY&apos; S * GOVERNMENT)S. B C R E TCP. (U7)2uU.2STH AUGUST.  1QJU7.COPY NO.269CABINET. THE CONTROL OF ENGAGEMENT order memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service.     A memorandum (J.C.C.208) explaining the present position regarding control of engagement and the proposed new order and containing a. draft of its operative provisions wasconsidered by the Joint Consultative Committee at their meeting on Wednesday, 13th August.    A copy of the memorandum is attached (Annex).2.     The Trades Union Council, who were favourably disposed towards the proposed new Order,  asked for, and were-given,a, number of assurances, particularly with regard to allowing appeals against directions issued in accordancewith the Prime Minister&apos;s statement in the House that:-&quot;In order to avoid workers remaining unemployed or taking other unessential work instead of acceptingessential employment for which they are submittedunder the Control of Engagement scheme, it will benecessary to resume to a limited extent the use ofpowers of direction.   This is not a resumption ofthe general powers of direction, but an essentialsupporting measure to enable the control of engage-ment to be effectively exercised.&quot;They also asked for, and were given, an assurance that thepower of direction would only be used where necessary inthose cases where a person seeking employment through an employment Exchange refuses to accept each one of anumber of essential jobs offered, and that this did not involve an extension of* the use of directions beyond what is atpresent being done in coalmining, agriculture and building.3*      I intervened and told the Committee that so far as  Iwas concerned there was no question of the immediate use ofthe power of direction in connection with the proposed new order.    The intention was to operate the Order on a basis ofpersuasion and only in the event of this proving to be a failure would it be necessary to consider introducingdirections.    I based this on the public announcement of theTrades Union Council that:-&quot;the General Council approves the re-introduction of control of Engagement Order.    As a first step theGeneral Council directs attention to the primaryneed for transference of labour from unessential and non-productive employment of those industries which-are vital to the economic stability of the country.
If it is found that the application of a Control of engagement Order does not produce the results required &apos;the General Council.will be prepared to discuss with- &quot;the Government further -measures including direction. of labour which may be necessary to deal with our.  national difficulties.&quot;   -I argued that the passage in the Prime Minister&apos;s speech didnot imply that direction would be immediately ordered.    I said that it referred to resumption &quot;to a limited extent&quot;and therefore the limited extent of the Order should besubject to consideration,,4,      I ought to s.ay that my Department place a somewhat different interpretation on tho Trade Union Council&apos;announcement. . They take the view that the Trades union council know that the Order can only be effective if directionis used to a limited extent and that the .announcement means that the General Council will be prepared to^discuss quite -different measures from Control of Engagement, includingindustrial conscription, if the proposed Order, with directions.fails,    I do not accept this interpretation.5,     Following my intervention, members of the Trade union side of the Committee expressed varying views and thenwithdrew for private consultation.    On return the TradeUnion representatives said that -(l)   They were bound by the decision of the TradesUnion Council as publicly announced;(2) they agreed with the provisions of the proposedControl of Engagement Order as set out in the Appendix tothe memorandum JeG,0,208;(3)    they agreed that the Order should first be operated on a basis of persuasion and that compulsion should only beadopted if evidence could be produced that the Order wasfailing;(4)    such evidence j, if forthcoming, would overcome the hostility to direction which would arise if it was imposedwithout evidence of its absolute necessity^(5)    the evidence would provide a more satisfactory guideas to the extent to which direction should apply.6,      In reply to a question as to when the General council would, if desired, be in a position to give further considera--tion to the question of direction, the Trade Union repre-sentatives said that Congress, which was meeting on 1st Septemberwould be/ informed of the action already taken and that theGeneral Council, which would be meeting in the week precedingCongress, would readily give consideration at any time to anyfurther communication addressed to them on this matter.    i accordingly sent to the Trades Union Council on 15th Augusta letter in the terms set&apos; out in -Appendix II,7,      I wish to&apos;place on record that I share the views as expressed above.    It is my opinion that before we announce that the use of direction of labour is to be resumed we mustnot only show the need but set out clearly -the scope, extent and operation of the. use of the power of direction - we havenot only to carry the Trade Unions with us but also tosatisfy public opinion.
G. A. I.MINISTRY OP LABOUR AND NATIONAL SERVICE,S.W.1, 7th August, 1947.8.     My Department do not share my view.    They approach thequestion from the point of view of making the proposed Controlof Engagement Order effective.    Their views on^this issueare set out in the following paragraphs.9.     They state quite definitely that without the power of direction in the background and its limited use as stated by the Prime Minister, the Order will be ineffective.    Theyhave had much experience of this measure during the war andthis shows quite clearly that the Order, which in any case is not a particularly effective instrument when used by itself, cannot be made to work without sanctions.    Evenduring the war very large numbers of workers made every excuse for not taking the essential war jobs and it was only becausethey knew that they would if necessary be directed into these jobs if they refused them that they accepted.    Theimportant point is not the one or two cases a week in whichdirections are issued, but the knowledge by the mass of thepeople that direction is in the background and will be usedif necessary.    The Regional Controllers and Exchange- Managersare unanimous in their view that without direction in the background control of engagement is almost useless.10,    The loss of Unemployment Insurance benefit is not an effective sanction.    The decision to grant benefit rests with the Statutory Authorities and it is far from certainthat the Umpire would disallow a claim for UnemploymentInsurance benefit-for refusing a number of essential jobs,if a less essential job suitable for.the man is available.Essentiality is not the determining factory in decidingsuitability.    But even if Unemployment Insurance benefit werewithheld, the person concerned would only be disqualifiedfor six weeks and during that period could obtain Assistance -the ultimate test for which is need - and, if the familywere large enough, might get more on Assistance than onUnemployment Insurance benefit.11.    I have set out the position at length so that mycolleagues should be fully informed on this important issue.
MINISTRY   OF   .MBOUR   AND   NATIONAL   SERVICE, -   . . JOINT CONSULT AT IVE OOSKITTEEProposed OontrdL. of. Kngagement- order,     The vieus of the Joint Consultative Committee are invited on theproposals contained in the attached draft of the operative provisions of a- -Control of Engagement Order,     The authority for this Order is Re.re:v,eRegulation 5SA wldoh is in, operation by virtue of the-Supplier and Services(Transitional Powers) Act, 1545, . the. purposes, of which are. hying exteniedtoy the Supplies and Services (Transitional rowers) Bill, 1947.2.     Tho present position as to control of engagement is as follows -(a) AgricultureAgricultural workers cannot he engaged outside of agricultureotherwise than through Enployrient Exchanges except in coalmining.Farmers ai-e free to engage any worker except a coalminor wi chcut going-through the Employment Exchanges.(&quot;b) CoalminersCoalminers cannot bo engaged outside the Coalmining industryotherwise than &quot;by submission through the Employment Exchanges.     Theyare freo to engage or he engaged at any pit in coalmining.     Men who -are not already coalminors may also take employment in the coal mineswithout going through the Employment Exchanges.(c) Building and Civil EngineeringAll engagements in the Building and Civil Engineering industries have to &apos;be made through the Employment Exchanges.The proposed Order leaves this position as it is by re-enacting the relevant provisions of the earlier Orders.- 3.     The general effect of the changes proposed in this Order will &apos;be to restore as from 1st October, 1947, the position/which existed under theControl of Engagement Order, 19h7 (S.-R. A 0. (l&apos;M-5) No, 579), i.e. it provides that employers may nob engage or seek to engage employees, withcertain exceptions, otherwise than ttrorgh the Ministry of labour and national Service or an Employment Agency approved for the purpose.     It Isproposed&apos; that .the age limits should bo confined, to men who have reached theage of 1B but not reached the age of 51 and to women.who have reached the agof 18 but have not reached the age of 41 *The Prime Minister made it clear that these changes are of a temporal&quot;&apos;nature until there&apos;has been sufficient improvement in tho economic cohdlir&apos;of the country.     It is suggested therefore that the Order at this stage begiven a reasonably short duration and that It should expire on31st December, 194&amp;.     Should It be necessary tc extend the Order beyond the/date, there would of course bo further consultations.4.     ExceptionsTho principal exceptions proposed are similar to those which were in thi&apos;wor time Orders.     They arc as follows -&apos;  (a) Ex-Service men and women during the period of their demobilisationleavePledges were given that during that period men and women should be free to select their own employment and it is not possible to go bfclc or those pledges.
This was in the earlier Orders but it is for consideration whether theage of 15 should now be substituted for 14 in view of the raising of theschool leaving age.C c ) Part time employment, i.e. employment whether with,pjne^jar jaareemployera for not more than 30 hours weekly in all(^) Employment of a casual nature/otherwise than for the employer1s trade or^usiness(e) Employment in a managerial capacityThis has been held to include salaried officials in executive chargeof departments and to include superintendents and head foremen in chargeof other foremen.     It does not include foremen and charge-hands or anyworker in receipt of hourly rates of pay or piece rates.(f) Employment in a professional, administrative or executive capacityThis was in general excluded from the earlier Orders though certainscarcity occupations were specially included.     It is not proposed onthis occasion to &apos;bring any engagements. in this capacity exceptionallywithin the scope of the Order.(g) Dock labour and Merchant HavyThere is no point in including engagement in those industries withinthe terms of this Order as special joint arrangements governing allengagement in these industries are already in operation.5.     The Order reproduces the old provision which enables approved agencies tosubmit workers for employment.     Approved agencies have to carry on this workin accordance with arrangements approved by the Minister and in accordancewith such directions as he may&apos;give.6.     PermitsThe old provision under which the Ministry could give a permit to theindividual to obtain his own employment is reproduced.     This is occasionallynecessary in special cases where suitable employment is more likely to &quot;befound quickly &quot;by that means.7.     Exemptions for employersThe old provision under which the Ministry can give a Certificate of exemption to an employer in respect of specified employment is reproduced.This was found to be of use on occasion.8.     AdvertisementsThe prohibition of employers seeking to engage workers carries with it a prohibition of advertisement, for workers unless the employment or the workeris excepted from the scope of the Order.9.     DirectionsThe Prime Minister made it clear that there would have to be some use ofpowers of direction, not with a view to re-introducing any general directionof labour, but with a view to making the Control of Engagement Ordereffective by providing for the case whei&quot;e a worker unreasonably refuses to go into any essential job for which he or she is submitted.     This does not require any new Statutory Order as the power already exists under defence Regulation 58A(l).     All that is involved is the issue of furtherguidance to National Service Officers as to the exercise of their powers under the Regulation.     It is proposed that this guidance should be to theeffect that worlcera subject to the Control of Engagement Order should be
8th August, 194711given ,as wide a choice as possible amongst avaiJjjiablG jobs in the most urgent categories.     In the last resort if he-&quot;effeshe3 having been,given full opportunity and a reasonable range of selection, still insists either ontaking unessential work or on taking no work at all, a direction should beissued to take the most important and suitable employment available.     TheProtection of the Control of Employment (Directed Persons) Order(S.R. &amp; 0.(1943) No1. 651) will remain in operation to ensure that properconditions are observed in any work to.which a worker is directed.Failure to obey a direction would involve liability to prosecution for an offence the penalty for which is, on summary conviction, a fine notexceeding  100 or imprisonment not exceeding -ape months or both such fine,and imprisonment.      &apos; , Mjgz
Control of engagement.Provisions asto re-engage-ment.ExceptedEmploy merits,3..Order -(a) no person shall seek to engage or engage any person for employment otherwise than by notifying to a local office or Iapproved employment agency particulars of the vacancy to be filled;(b) no person shall engage any person for employment unless that person has been submitted to him by a looal offioe or an approvedemployment agency;(c) a person seeking employment shall obtain his employment by making application to a local offioe&apos;or an approved employmentagency, and by means of a submission to an employer by a. local office or that approved employment agenoy and not otherwise.4.     The provisions of Article 3 hereof shall not apply to.thore-engagement, of a person by an employer if the re-engagement occurs -(a) immediately following the end of a period of sickness if the engagement with that employer was terminated by reason of suchsickness, and, in the case of an.employer carrying on a building or civil engineering contracting undertaking, is for work on the site at which that person was working immediately before tho engagementwas terminated;   or(b) on his resumption of work on the termination of any stoppage of work due to a trade dispute where he ceased to be employedowing to such stoppage;   or(c) within a period of not more than fourteen consecutive daysfollowing the day on which he was last employed by that employer,unless that employer is a person oarrying on a building or oivilengineering contracting undertaking,5.     The provisions of Article 3 hereof shall not apply to any of-the following employments, that is to say -(a) employment in agriculture, inoluding horticulture and forestry;(b) employment in the coalmining industry;   or(c) er.ployr.ient in timber production, not being employment inagriculture, if the person to be engaged or seeking employment isa member of the Women&apos;s Land Army;   or(d) employment as a registered dock worker under the Dock Vforkers(Regulation of Employment) Order, 1947*    or(e) employment as a master or member of the crow of a ship towhioh the provision of the Merchant Shipping Acts 1894 - 1940 appljl(f) employment as a fisherman or as a master or member of the crew of a fishing boat to which tho provisions of the MerchantShipping Acts, 1894 to 1940 apply;   or(g) whole-time employment in any of the Women1s Servicesspecified in the Schedule hereto;   or(h) part-time employment, that is to say, employment whetherj^pthone or more than one employer that involves- not more than thirtyhours&apos; service weekly in all;   orDraft of Operative Provisions of ProposedControl&apos; of&quot; &quot;Er^geiiEnt**^rder.Subject to the provisions hereinafter contained in this
274(i) employment without remuneration!   or(j) employment as a member of a Police force within the meaning&apos; of the Police Pensions Aot, 1921;   or(k) employment in a managerial capacity;   or(1) employment in a professional,, administrative or executive capacity.6. The provisions of Article 3 of this Order shall not apply to Exceptedthe engagement or employment of any person in any of the following  . Persons,ciroumstances, that is to say -(a) if he is not a person between the relevant ages;   or(b) if, being a woman, she has living with her a child of hersunder the age of fifteen years;   or(o) if die is a person whose employment is of a casual nature and whois employed otherwise than for the purpose of the employor&apos;s trade or business;   or(d) if he is certified by a local authority as defined by the blind Persons Acts, 1920 and 1938, to be registered as a blindperson under arrangements made by the authority under thoseActs;   or(e) if he is the holder of a permit issued by or on behalf of theMinister and for the time being in force, exempting him from the   ^-provisions of this Order in respect of the employment specified ordescribed in the permit;   or(f) if the person seeking to engage or employ him is the holderof an oxemption certificate issued by or on behalf of the Ministerand for the time being in force, exempting the holder from theprovisions of this Order in respect of the employment specifiedor described in the certificate, but subject to any conditions that .may be set out therein, and subject to compliance with those conditions;   or(g) if he is a person belonging to any of the classes of personsspecified or described in paragraph (f) of sub-section (1) ofsection eleven of the National Service (Armed Forces) Act, 1939(whioh relates to persons of unsound mind and persons who arcmentally defective), or, in Scotland, to any of the classes ofpersons specified or described in that paragraph as modified andadapted in the application of that Act to Scotland by seotiontwenty-two thereof;   or(h) if he is an alien who is subject to any condition or restrictionimposed upon him under or by virtue of the provisions of the AliensOrder, 1920 (as amended) or any Order made thereunder whereby hemay not enter into any employment in Great Britain without theconsent or permission of the Minister or of the Ministry of Labourand National Servioe.7,     The provisions of Article 3 of this Order shall apply to a Specialerson whose normal employment is in the coaLiiining industry, or whose Provisionsurrent unemployment book issued under the provisions of the as to coal&quot;Employment Insurance Aots, 1935 to 1944 bears the industry letters 8a,   mining,here the employment for which the person is to be engaged or whichseeks to obtain is employment outside the coalmining industry,Ihethcr or not the employment is one of the excepted employmentsontainod in Artiole 5 (other than paragraph (b)).
Saving as toRe ihs tat ementin CivilEmploymentAct, 19^-4.7 and 8 Ceo.6. c, 15.Order notto apply to members ofthe aimedforces ofthe Crown,   -8.     Nothing in this Order shall prejudice or affect any ,rights oonferred or obligations imposed by or under the Reinstatementin Civil Employment Act. 1944, or the enforcement or fulfilment of ary&apos;such rights and obligations.9*     The provisions of Article 3 shall not apply to the engagementor employment of a person who is a member of the armed- forces of thoCrown-, or who is a woman in any of the services specified in theSchedule, rot being a work.a - whose enrolment or ether undertaking toserve was for part-time service only or for service without remunera^and(a) is in receipt,, as such member or as a woman in any suchseroijo, of pay other than half pay, reserve pay orretired pay   or(b) is oh leave on temporary release granted upon compassionate grounds.Dated this day of1947.Minister of Labour and National Service.SCHEDULE.- Definitions^(1) &quot;Approved employment agency&quot; means any establishment organisation which affords facilities for placing persons inemployment, and is carried on by any person in accordance with arrangements approved by -the Minister (whother before or after $comuo-aooment of this Order), and in, accordar-jo.with such directions (if any) as may be given by the Minister -in respect!the operation of the arrangements j(2)&quot;.&quot;?jrson between the relevant ages&quot; means a person who hasattained the age of eighteen years and who, being a man, has notattained tho age of fifty-one years, or being a, woman, has notattai::-;d iho ago of forty-one years,, or such other age lower thatthe said filfty-one yoar-r-;., or forty-one years as the Minister rfljfrom time to time by Order direct. &apos; .H.q.151-350 H.Q.)
APPENDIX II15th August, 1947.Dear Vincent,You will remember that at the meeting of the Joint-Consultative Committee on Wednesday, 13 frJAugustJ discussion took place about the use of the power of direction in ordero enable the Control of Engagement Order to be effectivelyexercised.    At the close of the meeting I asked if theGeneral Council could give further consideration to thequestion of direction of labour in the present economiccrisis and was informed that, while the representativespresent were bound by the General Council&apos;s decision, anyfurther communication on the subject would-have attention.In view of the near.approach of Congress, I am now askingif the General Council will at once give further considerationto the question of the use of direction in connection withthe Control of Engagement Order.    The proposal of the Governmentis that, while there should be no general resumption of theuse of the power of direction, it should be used&apos; if necessaryin those cases where a person seeking employment through theEmployment Exchanges refuses to accept one of a number of essential jobs offered.    It is anticipated that this would happen in only a small minority of cases;    workers so directedwould be allowed, if they wished, to appeal to an appealboard.     We are proposing to carry on using the old appealboards, but I am prepared to discuss this with you if youwish to do so,-If there is any further information you would like aboutthe Governments proposal, I should be happy to let you have it.Yours sincerely,(Signed)    G.A,  ISAACS.Vincent Tewson, Esq.,&apos; C. B,E, ,M, C, ,Trades Union Congress,Transport House,Smith Square, S.W, 1.


</content>
</cab>
