<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/8/14 images: 188-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  July 1940.SECRET. Copy No. 42W.M. (40)202nd Conclusions.TO BE KEPTJJNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 202 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Saturday, July 13, 1940, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Lord President of theCouncil (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. R. H. Cross, M.P.,Minister of Shipping (Items 2and 3).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Economic Warfare(Items 3 and 4).Mr. W. Strang, Foreign Office.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.
WAR CABINET 202 (40).contents minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      France........................      99Proposed agreement with General de Gaulle.2      France........................       99French ships in British ports, and British and Allied ships in &apos;French ports.3      Contraband Control   ...       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     100Application to the Iberian Peninsula.4      France.........................     101Application  of  contraband  control to   certain  French  colonial territories.Application of enemy export control.5      Foreign Information ...       ...       ...      ...      ...      ...     102Far East.Boumania.Belgian and Polish gold.
1. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the Secretary(W.P. (G.) (40) 181) covering a Memorandum by the Chairman ofthe French Forces Sub-Committee, with which were enclosed (a) adraft agreement proposed by General de Gaulle, dealing with therates of pay, conditions of service, &amp;o, of the volunteers joininghis forces; (b) the draft of a letter from the Prime Minister toGeneral de Gaulle, covering an alternative form of agreement.In discussion, the following points were raised : (i) The rates of pay of General de Gaulle&apos;s forces had alreadybeen dealt with in an interim report by the french forces Sub-Committee, which had been approved by theMinisters concerned. The personnel in question would receive pay on a basis to be agreed separately between general de Gaulle and the Departments concerned.Such rates would apply for so long as his forces foughtunder British direction,(ii) The intention was that, generally speaking, Europeanpersonnel should receive pay at basic British rates.Different arrangements would have to be made for non-European and native troops.(iii) The Lord President of the Council said that he feltanxious about the concluding words of the letter whichit was suggested the Prime Minister should write toGeneral de Gaulle. These Words gave a guarantee thatafter victory had been gained by the Allied army wewould restore the independence and territorial integrity of France and of the French Empire. This was a very big undertaking.The War Cabinet-(a) Put on record the view that it was unnecessary for thiscountry to guarantee to restore the independence and territorial integrity of France and of the French Empire.(6) Deferred further consideration of the draft letter and agreement until a full meeting of the War Cabinet.France. 2.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFrench ships in  Minister of Shipping (W.P. (G.) (40) 180).British ports,and British and French Merchant Vessels detained in British Ports.Allied ships in There were 81 ships in United Kingdom ports and 35 inFrencli ports. British-controlled ports overseas. The immediate action required was to free the United Kingdom ports, as far as possible, of idleFrench ships and disaffected French crews. In particular, the congestion at F^almouth, where ships were subject to the risk of heavy air attack, must be relieved. Some of the vessels concerned had valuable cargoes on board. The Admiralty had already takencertain action to move these ships, by force if necessary, to thedischarging ports.The present position did not permit of delay, and accordingly the War Cabinet (a) Authorised the Minister of Shipping to requisition, underthe Defence Regulations, all French merchant ships inUnited Kingdom ports, and to place them under theBritish Flag. The Minister of Shipping should consult with the Chancellor of the Exchequer regarding themethod of requisitioning.(&amp;) Authorised the Minister of Shipping to consider, in consul-tation with the Secretaries of State for Dominion Affairs,India, Burma, and the Colonies, similar action in regardto all French merchant ships in British ports overseas.France.Proposed agree-ment withGeneral de gaulle.
(c) Agreed that any vessels so requisitioned could not be operated under the control of General de Gaulle, andthat we could recognise no claim by him to the earnings of such vessels.(d) Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Ministerof Shipping, in consultation, to decide what measures should be adopted in the case of smaller French craft,tugs, pilot-boats and fishing vessels, now in UnitedKingdom harbours.British and Allied, Ships in French Ports.Thirty-one British and 54 Allied vessels were detained in ports in France and French Possessions. The aggregate tonnage of these vessels was 270,000 tons, as compared with 484,000 tons of Frenchmerchant vessels detained in British ports. A certain number ofexchanges of British and French ships had been arranged locallyalready.The War Cabinet-(d) Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Ministerof Shipping, in consultation with the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs, to negotiate with the Agent of theFrench Government in London for an exchange ofFrench merchant ships in British ports against british merchant ships in French ports, on a ton-for-ton basis.These negotiations should cover the release of Polishships.Crews of Ships.( ) Authorised the First Lord of the Admiralty and theMinister of Shipping to make arrangements to employin the British Merchant Service French seamen atpresent in United Kingdom ports who volunteered.Such employment should, if possible, be linked withGeneral de gaulle&apos;s organisation. The terms of serviceof those who volunteered to serve in the british merchant Service should be settled by the Minister, inconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(jjjfr Authorised the Minister of Home Security to repatriateFrench seamen who wished to return to France.(\$ Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Ministerof Shipping to ensure that the return to this country ofthe crews of British and Allied ships in French portsis taken up as part of the negotiations at (d).Contraband 3.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theControl. Minister of Economic Warfare (WP. (40) 259) on the applicationApplication to    of Contraband Control to the Iberian Peninsula.the Ibenan Minister of Economic Warfare summarised his proposalsPeninsula. &amp;s follows .^(1) An approach should be made to the Spanish Governmenton the lines that we were forced to apply the blockade tothe whole Western seaboard of Europe; that we desired that Spain should not suffer from the blockade; and thatwe would therefore arrange for the passage through ourcontrols of reasonable quantities of goods required forSpain&apos;s consumption, and would also give everyassistance to Spain to obtain such supplies.(2) We should make such pre-emptive purchases in Spain and portugal as might be practicable.(3) In order to make our Contraband Control more effective,ships&apos; navicerts should be made compulsory, and allun-navicerted ships be treated as blockade-runners tobe seized in prize.
The following were the main points made in discussion : (a) The First Lord of the Admiralty supported the proposalto make ships&apos; navicerts compulsory. The admiralty would like ia few days to work out a plan to make effective the scheme of Contraband Control now proposed.The Minister of Shipping thought that we should be ableso to arrange matters that only in the case of the most valuable cargoes would it be worth while to attempt to run the blockade.The Minister said that to achieve the control of worldshipping it would be necessary to charter further ships.At the moment our policy was to allow freights to drop.If we chartered further neutral shipping we should probably be able to lift cargoes in distant ports whereprices of commodities might be more favourable to us.The saving so effected might offset the rise in freightswhich would follow the chartering of additional ships.(d) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he agreed inprinciple with the policy of pre-emption proposed inparagraph 7, subject to inter-departmental discussion in regard to particular proposals.(e) The Permanent  Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs said that the Foreign Office saw no objectionto the proposals, subject to their being presented on thelines proposed by our Ambassadors at Madrid andLisbon.(/) The Lord Privy Seal thought that Germany might prefer the Iberian Peninsula to be neutral, in the hope thatit would provide a gap in our Contraband Control.The Lord President of the Council agreed, and thoughtthat a rigid application of Contraband Control to theIberian Peninsula might have the effect of forcing Spaininto the war against us. This aspect of the matter would have to be watched.The War Cabinet-(1) Approved in principle the proposals of the Minister for economic Warfare in his Memorandum WP. (40) 259,summarised above, subject to any observations whichmight be offered by the President of the Board of Trade.(2) Took note that the Admiralty would require a few days to prepare a plan to make effective the measures of contraband Control now proposed.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs inconsultation with the Minister for Economic Warfare tomake the necessary communications to the Spanish andPortuguese Governments.(&amp;)(o)France.Application ofContrabandcontrol tocertain french colonial Terri-tories.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 181stConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister for Economic Warfare (W.P. (40) 260) proposing (i) That Contraband Control should now be applied to all ships, whether French or neutral, bound for ports in french Morocco, Algeria and Tunis, and that all goodsdestined for such ports should be regarded as liable toseizure.(ii) That ships from ports in these territories or in continentalFrance should be subjected to Enemy Export Control,and that goods of French origin or ownership shouldbe liable to seizure.
In discussion it was agreed that Contraband Control shouldbe applied to all ships bound for French Morocco, Algeria andTunis.Application of The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsEnemy Export said that the Foreign Office felt some difficulty in applying enemy control. Export Control to goods coming from unoccupied France.   while there might be practical difficulties in distinguishing between goodscoming from occupied and unoccupied France, from the political point of view there was some difficulty in treating unoccupied france as enemy occupied territory, while we were still indiplomatic relations with France.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed that Contraband Control should now be applied toall ships, whether French or neutral, bound for ports in french Morocco, Algeria and Tunis, and that all goodsdestined for such ports should be regarded as liable toseizure.(2) Deferred a decision on the question whether ships fromports in French Morocco, Algeria, Tunis or in Con-continental France should be subjected to Enemy export control.foreign information.Far East.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 200thConclusions,Minute 13.)Roumania.Belgian and polish Gold.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 200thConclusions,Minute 6.)5.   The War Cabinet were given the following information : Sir Robert Craigie&apos;s discussions with Mr. Arita on the burma road question had been satisfactory (telegram No. 1220 fromTokyo).Roumania had decided to leave the League of Nations. Thiswas of no account in itself, but it showed the complete subservienceof Roumania to Germany.The War Cabinet were given the latest information as to theposition. Details are recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,July 13, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
