<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/191/7 images: 62-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cp(76) 5722 July 1976CABINETTHE BRITISH AID PROGRAMME IN 1975Note by the Minister for Overseas development - I am circulating for the information of my colleagues the attachedadvance copy of &quot;The British Aid Programme in 1975&quot;,    This is an annualpublication and will appear in the Command Series on 28 July,2.        The paper, which gives a detailed account of our aid programme in1975, was prepared for presentation to the Development assistance committee of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development.REPMinistry of Overseas Development22 July 1976i &apos;        -.-   t  ,   *COPY NO81confidential
MINISTRY OF OVERSEAS development the British aid programme in 1975 Text of United Kingdom memorandum to the Development Assistance Committeeof the Organisation for economic co-operation and DevelopmentPresented to Parliament by the Minister for Overseas development by Command of Her MajestyLONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICESOp net.6544
PREFACE1. The 1976 United Kingdom Memorandum to the Development assistance committee (D AC) of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and DeveJop-ment is the seventh such Memorandum to be published with the object of pro-vidiog additional information about United Kingdom development assistanceactivities. The Memorandum covers activities in the calendar year 1975 withspecial reference to aspects which the DAC regards as immediately relevant toits purposes. Because the Memorandum has been provided primarily for purposesof international discussion, figures are expressed in dollars as well as Ueriing( I^*2-2217).2. The Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development,established by a Convention in Paris in December I960, is the principal forum for consultations at both Ministerial Had official levels on economic issues ofcommon internet to members, who comprise most of the European and otherdeveloped countries. Its work embraces broad aspects of the world economy andits aims include the promotion of policies contributing to sound economic expansion in non-member countries in the process of economic development.3. The Development Assistance Committee is one of the specialist oomaii-committees set up by OECD to achieve its abas. It is concerned with the volume and effectiveness of resources made available to less developed countries. Membersperiodically review together the amount and the nature of their contributions to aid programmes, bilateral and multilateral, and consult on other relevantaspects of their development assistance policies. The Memorandum nowpublished is the current contribution by the United Kingdom to this process ofreview.4.  Participating in the wort of the DAC are:Australia, Austria, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, Ger-many, Italy, Japan, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Sweden,Switzerland, the United Kingdom, the United States and the Commissionof the Europe&amp;n. Economic Communities.5.  The term &quot;official development assistance&apos;&apos; used in die Memorandumrefers to grants or loans:-undertaken by the official sector; with promotion of economic development and welfare as main objectives; on concessional financial terms (if a loan, a grant element of at least25 per cent).6.  A detailed statistical account of United Kingdom aid it provided in theannual publication &quot;British Aid Statistics&quot;.
CONTENTSPageINTRODUCTION.....................     ...       lChapter IVOLUME AND TERMS PERFORMANCE     ......      ...        ia. Volumeb. Terms and ConditionsChapter IIDISTRIBUTION OF OFFICIAL DEVELOPMENT ASSIS-TANCE...........................      6a. Allocation of Bilateral ODAb. Allocation of Multilateral ODAc. Technical Co-operationd. Commonwealth Development CorporationChapter IIIPRIVATE SECTOR   .....................     13a. Private Investmentb. Investment Protectionc. Investment Insuranced. Export Credits Guarantee DepartmentChapter IVSOCIAL ASPECTS OF DEVELOPMENT        .........      15a. Aid to the Poorer Sectionsb. Integration of Women in the Development Processc. Food Production, Security and AidChapter VINDUSTRIAL AND TECHNOLOGICAL CO-OPERATION ... 24Chapter vi the AID RELATIONSHIP...............     ...     25Chapter VIIJOINT CO-OPERATIVE VENTURES    ......... 26Chapter VIIICOMPREHENSIVE APPROACH TO DEVELOPMENT 27a. Initiatives in Development Co-Operation beyond Official De^velopment Assistanceb. Role of Aid Administrations in the Formulation of DevelopmentCo-operation Policiesc. Changes in Public and Parliamentary AttitudesAnnexSCIENTIFIC ESTABLISHMENTS UNDERTAKING RE-SEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT ON BEHALF  OF DE-VELOPING COUNTRIES   ...     ......
IntroductionI. United Kingdom official development assistance in 197$ was $863m( 3S8m) net and $959m ( 432m; gross compared with $722m ( 309m) act and$824m ( 352m) respectively in 1974. In both years the net amounts were 0-38per cent of the gross national product (GNP),2. The 1975 Memorandum stressed that it was a central objective of theUnited Kingdom aid policy to give a greater emphasis to rural developmentThis was confirmed by the presentation to Parliament by the Minister of Over-seas Development in October 1975 of a White Paper &quot;The Changing Emphasis inBritish Aid Policy: More Help for the Poorest&quot;. (Cmnd 6270). When this major policy statement was subsequently debated in both Houses of Parliament it received support from all parties.3. The United Kingdom has decided that it will no longer use the term &quot;tech-mcal assistance&quot; and that it should be replaced by &quot;technical co-operation&quot;.
I.  VOLUME AND TERMS PERFORMANCEa. Volume4. The United Kingdom has accepted the United Nations target that the developed countries should transfer to the developing countries a combinedtotal of official and private flows amounting to not less than 1 per cent of theirgross national product each year. In addition the United Kingdom has accepted in principle the second United Nations target that the developed countries should provide not less than 0-7 per cent of their gross national product by wayof net official development assistance. The United Kingdom will seek in the years ahead to move towards the target but the rate at which it does so must be governed by the pace of its economic recovery and by the other calls on its re-sources.5. The United Kingdom&apos;s performance against the 0-7 per cent target was0-38 per cent in 1975, the same level as in 1974. Its likely performance against theI per cent target is not yet known because estimates of private investment are notyet available. In any case it has been found that the estimates for net private investment for individual years cannot be used to deduce trends for forecastingsince the various elements which make up the total figure fluctuate considerablyand independently from year to year.Disbursements6. Gross disbursements in 1975 of official development assistance (which includes the bulk of investments of the Commonwealth Development Corpora-tion (CDC) as well as various transactions not encompassed in the aid pro-gramme) amounted to $959m ( 432m) compared with $824m ( 352m) in 1974.After deducting repayments of principal on past loans net official developmentassistance totalled $863m ( 388m) in 1975 compared with $722m ( 309m) in1974.7.  The table below shows the breakdown of disbursements by type: DisbursementsA. Gross Official Development Assist-ance (ODA)Bilateral:Financial grants       ......Financial loans.........Technical co-operationTotal bilateral.........Multilateral:Financial aid   .........Technical co-operationTotal multilateral      ......Total gross ODA     ......B. Other official Flows (OOF)Bilateral grants.........CDC investment (not qualifyingas ODA)        .........Total gross OOF      ......Official Flows (A&amp;B) grossRepayments of principalOfficial Flows net    .........Official Development Assistance net 722	1974			1975	tm	 m	%	Sm	 m	%112	48	14	153	69	16321	137	39	296	133	31179	76	21	214	96	22612	261	74	663	298	69182	78	22	234	105	2430	13	4	62	28	7212	91	26	296	133	31824	352	100%	959	432	100%56	24		16	7	24	11		16	7	80	35		31	14	904	387		990	446	102	44		97	44	802	343		893	402	722	309		863	388	4 and (92m ( 41m) in 1975.					
Commitments8. The United Kingdom aid programme is controlled on a disbursementbasis and commitments are entered into and discharged at a rate intended togive rise to the approved level of disbursements. Disbursements forecasts atereviewed during the course of each financial year and steps are taken to controlcommitments and their discharge according to whether the forecasts are high orlow. Methods of improving forecasting are continually being sought in order to achieve the fullest disbursement of the approved programme. la order to allowgreater flexibility in managing the aid programme, the Ministry of overseas development (ODM)may carry over up to $22-22nt( lflm) of cw-eapeflditureand up to $11-IIm ( 5m) (with the possibility of a further $ll-all ( $m))under-expenditure from one year to the next9. Fluctuations in the rate of annual disbursements to particular countries donot necessarily result from changes in policy towards them: annual disburse-ment levels are dependent on many factors and may vary from year to yew.    ,Prospects/or 1976 Onwards -\ &apos;:   &apos; -10. The planned level of the aid programme for the 1976/77miancjalyear is$1,146m ( 515-8m) net and 31,243m ( 559-3m) gross. Thereafter (he aid pro-gramme is planned to grow by 16-5 percent by 1979/80, subject to revision in &amp;eannual public expenditure survey. Because the United Kingdom does not pobfishforecasts of gross national product, it cannot make projections of performanceagainst the United Nations targets.Aid and the Effects of Inflation11. The annual White Papers on Public Expenditure indicate plannedlevels for the net aid programme over a five year period as part of the planning of the public expenditure programme as a whole. The planning figures are on a constant price basis and are rolled forward each year by revaluation based onestimated price changes in the year concerned for Che economic categoriesrelevant to the pro gramme. The United Kingdom system, therefore, has abuilt in adjustment for price changes Co the forward planning figures. Thefigures themselves are of course subject to changes ia policy. .b. Terms and CoadWsa.Terms of Aid Disbursed in 197512. Of the total of gross official development assistance amounting to$959m ( 432m) in 1975, *662m ( 29Sai) or 69 per cent was in grant form(including technical co-operation and contributions to multilateral agencies)&apos;$216m ( 97m), or 23 per cent, took the form of loans on interest-free terms;$38m ( 17m) or 4 per cent related to loans provided at fixed concessionary ratesof interest; $44,000 ( 2Q,Q0Q)or less than 0-005per cent related to disbursementsfrom earlier loans at market rates of interest (bat including loans with interestwaivers for an initial period); and $43m ( I9m) or 4 par cent was in the fonn of overseas investment by the CDC. Overall the weighted average granf etement ofgovcnuHont-to-government loans disbursed in 1975, omitting flows through theCDC, was 72-19 per cent
Terms of Aid Committed in 197513. The total value of new commitments of official development assistancein 1975 was $1,340m ( 603m), of which $1,226m ( 552m) or 92 per cent was ingrant form (including technical co-operation for which commitments are taken to be the same as disbursements and contributions to multilateralagencies) and $113m ( 51m) was in loans. Of the total value of new officialdevelopment assistance loan commitments entered into during the year, 66 percent was interest-free and 34 per cent carried an initial grace period for capitalrepayments. The weighted average grant elements of official developmentassistance loans was 65 per cent. The grant element of total commitments,including grants, was $1,299m ( 585m) or 96-9 per cent of the commitments.The DAC Recommendations on Financial Terms and Conditions14. The United Kingdom complied in 1975 with the overall terms targetcontained in the DAC Terms Recommendations by attaining an average grantelement of 96-9 per cent (against the target of at least 84 per cent) in its totalofficial development assistance commitments. The United Kingdom also com-plied with the special target set in the Recommendation for Aid to the LeastDeveloped Countries, by providing official development assistance commitmentswith an average grant element of at least 86 per cent to each least developedcountry over the three-year period 1973 to 1975.Criteria for Appropriate Terms and Conditions15. It is the policy of the United Kingdom to adapt the terms of bilateralaid to suit the economic circumstances of the recipient country, taking especiallyinto account income per head as well as its balance of payments prospects. Theterms of aid extended to the recipient country by other donor countries are alsotaken into account. This policy conforms to the DAC Recommendation on financial Terms and Conditions in relating the terms of aid on a case-by-casebasis to the circumstances of each developing country or group of countries. Thepolicy has been followed regularly by the United Kingdom in consortia andconsultative group discussions of the aid to be given to individual countries.As part of its policy of improving the quality of aid to the poorest developing countries, the United Kingdom&apos;s development assistance commitments tosuch countries (which are taken for this purpose to be those shown in the 1974edition of the World Bank Atlas as having a per capita GNP of less than $200in 1972) are now normally on grant terms, except where the country&apos;8 economic prospects are such as to make this an inappropriate concession.Analysis of Refinancing and Consolidation Operations16. The major *refinancing&apos; operation in the aid programme in 1975 was adebt refinancing grant to India amounting to $24-9m ( 11 -2m) to reimburse theIndian Government for certain repayments of capital and interest made on anumber of aid loan agreements dating from 1958 to 1968. Thi9 refinancing wasmade available to the Indian Government as the United Kingdom&apos;s contribu-tion towards a multilateral debt relief scheme, sponsored by the Aid IndiaConsortium, which is designed to alleviate the burden of debt servicing on theIndian balance of payments arising from the terms of past aid loans. The effect of
the scheme is to release the equivalent amount of free foreign exchange whichcan then be applied to the purchase of essential imports and it is considered to be one of the most useful ways in which donors can herp the development of thatcountry. The refinancing was made available on grant terms in pursuance of theUnited Kingdom policy of improving the quality of aid to the poorest countries .Procurement Policy17.  Whilst the extent of procurement in a donor country which may resortfrom the tying practices of that country is not roily revealed by statistics ofcontractually tied aid, the proportion of United Kingdom bilateral aid commit-ments fully tied to United Kingdom goods and services in 1975 was 42 per cent(excluding technical co-operation and aid for compensation and pensions,where expenditure as between sterling and local currencies cannot be cieariyidentified). In addition to the procurement from this fully bed aid, further pro-procurement in the United Kingdom arises from the considerable amount of bilateral financial aid tied to United Kingdom or local goods and services, the proportions of which are not always laid down in advance in specific terms. The.estimated percentage of further procurement in the United Kingdom whidi re-results from such aid was 18 per cent, giving an estimated total 60 per cent of bilateral aid effectively tied to United Kingdom procurement, without regardto any further procurement which may result from untied aid,18. Although United Kingdom bilateral aid is normally tied to the purchaseof British goods and services, the United Kingdom is ready to consider untyinga limited part of its financial aid for meeting the local costs of projects in n-exceptional cases where this is judged appropriate. At present some local&apos;costfinance for projects is available to 25 independent countries. For the UnitedKingdom I^pendettcies, the circumstances require a greater proportion of the aid to be devoted to focal costs or to local procurement Overall, therefore,^theUtdttd Kingdom aid programme continues to provide flexibility in the treatmentof local costs. For a number of countries, particularly the Dependencies, the west indian Associated States and independent countries in Southern Africa, waiversof procurement restrictions have been granted to allow procurement of 3p*rtntricategories of goods from third countries in the light of the paricu^arqnn-stances which apply. To facilitate the administration and use or tied aid, someforeign content, up to a maximum of 20%, may be permitted. Budgetary aid,of which the United Kingdom provided $20m ( 9m) in 1975, by its naturecannot be tied formally to overseas procurement; however, the arrangements with the recipient countries are that offshore procurement supported by thisbudgetary aid will be from the United Kingdom, except where this would be clearly uneconomic.19. As an additional measure to help the poorest countries, the UnitedKingdom now unties its official development assistance loan commitments forprocurement in developing countries with a per capita GNP of less Ann taoOj Ifthe recipient country wishes such an arrangement to be made. This measure,which was available from the second half of1975, should provide an opportunityfor the poorest developing countries to increase their export earnings and Costimulate inter-developing country trade. &apos;
20. The United Kingdom continued to provide its financial contributions tomultilateral institutions on procurement conditions in conformity with theunderstanding reached by all DAC member countries at the DAC High LevelMeeting in October 1973; that is, free for procurement in those countries thatare members or associate members of those institutions and if developed countries are recognised under arrangements made in the institutions con-cerned as significant contributors.n.  DISTRIBUTION OF OFFICIAL DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCEa. Allocation of Bilateral ODA21. There has been growing international agreement that scarce concess-ional aid resources ought to be concentrated increasingly on the poorest countries and the United Kingdom is adapting its aid policies to give help to the poorest countries and the poorest people within these countries.22. The overall change in emphasis of the United Kingdoms policies topoverty oriented programmes will be a gradual process and will inevitably take some time to become fully effective. It is, however, intended that the share ofUnited Kingdom bilateral aid disbursements to the poorest countries (that is,those with a GNP of under $200 per capita in 1972) will be at least a* great as their share of the population of the developing countries as a whole; in 1974that intention was achieved, but in 1975 the phasing of disbursements to Indiaand Kenya in particular led to a temporary reduction in the share going to thepoorest23. The table below shows the distribution of gross bilateral official de-velopment assistance for certain categories of recipients for 1974 and 1975: % %of gross Population     of totalSm   im   bilateral millions     populationODA (1972)       ofLDCsLeast Developed Countries          1974 100   43       18(LLDO) 227             12^                                        1975 115    52      20Mott Seriously Affected Countries 1974 321 137 59(MSA&apos;i)                               M 1,197 651975 294 133 51Under 1200 m 1972 (mcludes some 1974 362 155 66LLTXTi and/or MSA&apos;l) 1 189 641975 329 148 57b. Allocation of Multilateral ODA24. A major part of the United KingdonTs new aid strategy is to promotesituations in which British concessional funds can stimulate matching contri-butions from other governments and to encourage the deployment of such aidthrough both multilateral and bilateral channels towards the poorest countries.As a consequence of this it is the policy of the United Kingdom to support ahigh level of replenishment for the International Development Association
(IDA) and to participate in the International Fund for Agricultural Develop-ment (1FAD); and it is to be expected that as a result the proportion of mul-tilateral aid in the total aid programme will rise slightly over the next four years.The table below shows the distribution of gross multilateral official devefop-ment assistance for 1974 and 1975:-UN agencies   .........World Bank group    ......Regional development banksEEC funds     .........Other   ......     ......c Technical Co-operation1974 1975tm	 m	tm	 m46	20	88	40115	49	146	6611	4	14	636	16	41	184	2	7	3Recruitment of Operational Personnel and Advisers25.  During 1975 bilateral appointments made under the auspices ofODMto advisory and operational postt under various bilateral technical co-operationarrangements totalled 2,253 (compared with 2,197 in 1974). This figure includes,for the Education Sector, 44 school teachers and 79 teacher trainers. TheTechnical Education and Training Organisation for Overseas Countries(TETOC) made 70 operational appointments (72 in 1974), and the british council 201 operational appointments (210 in 1974). In other sectors the CrownAgents for Oversea Governments and Administrations made, on behalf of ODM,238 operational appointments (200 in 1974). Appointments to international organisations, including the United Nations, were 231 (210 in 1974).26. A shortage of suitable candidates in some disciplines continues. Thereare many reasons for this and remedial measures include the following: more frequent reviews of terms and conditions of service to keep up to date with inflation; an extension of the Home Base Scheme to other non-governmentpublic sector institutions to enable more people to be seconded; improvedfacilities for in-service training to enable experts to keep up to date in theirprofessions; a review of pre-service training schemes; better ways of identifyinglikely candidates from amongst people with previous aid service overseas; and consideration of an effective system for according priority treatment to requests for key personnel.The Future Supply of Operational Staff27. The schemes under which salary supplements and other benefits are paid to operational personnel employed by overseas governments and other institutions have been extended in all but a few countries for five years from31 March 1976 when the previous Agreements ended. Manpower reviews areundertaken annually with developing countries to ensure that expatriate man-power is provided on the basis of a country*s developmental needs.Use of Consultants28. Through their work overseas, both commercially and under aid arrange-ments, British consultants continue to play an important part in helping to formulate development programmes and projects. Ia 1975 technical co-operation
expenditure in respect of the services of consultants and other organisations inundertaking feasibility investigations and in the provision of other kinds of management, operational and advisory services was $12-3m ( 5*521 m). Theprincipal fields covered were irrigation and water supplies, agriculture, mining,oil and minerals, transportation, roads and power.29. Seventy-nine new feasibility and pre-investment studies were commi-ssioned during the year at an estimated cost of $7-3m ( 3-299m) compared with104 new assignments in 1974 with an estimated cost of $5-8m ( 2-6m), In addition56 other assignments were initiated totalling some $4-Om ( 1784m) comparedwith 43 valued at $l-2m ( 500,000) in the previous year.30. The Government^ White Paper &quot;More Help for the Poorest&quot; notedthat consultants could put together multi-purpose teams to help promote rural development. This has been imaginatively demonstrated with the commissioningin 1975 of a firm to carry out an integrated rural development programme in theSudan. The programme covers some 27,000 sq km in South Darfur and will takeat least four years to complete. It is concerned primarily with the sustainedimprovement of agricultural production in a semi-arid area and focuses attentionon the needs of stockholders and cultivators who rely on small-scale livestockand rain-fed crop enterprises for their livelihood. (See also paragraphs 57 and 91).Volmteers31. As in 1974 the four Member Societies of the British Volunteer Pro-gramme, namely the Catholic Institute for International Relations (CUR),International Voluntary Service (IVS), United Nations Association (UNA) and voluntary Service Overseas (VSO), continued to recruit volunteers for service overseas in response to requests from developing countries. Official government financial support totalling $2-lm ( 926,000) was provided. The British Councilcontinued to act as Overseas Arm for the administration of the programme inmany countries, but in a few countries a move was made towards a Societyappointing its own representative. The British Volunteer Programme Counciland Secretariat continued its co-ordinating role.32. The number of graduate and similarly qualified volunteers in post at31 December 1975 was 1,300 compared with the 1974 figure of 1,212. The cadetprogramme is now defunct except in the Falkland Islands where there is still asmall demand for semi-qualified young people.33. About half of the volunteers are teachers while the rest are engagedmainly in nursing, agriculture, engineering and community development. demand is continuing to increase for technical volunteers rather than for secondary school teachers, (other than in the fields of English, mathematics, science andvocational subjects) and also for older and more experienced people. Like ODM,the Societies are also attempting to improve living conditions in the poorestsectors by increasing the number of volunteers in the field of rural development.Training34. During 1975 some 14,800 students and trainees followed courses in theUnited Kingdom under bilateral arrangements as part of the aid programme
at a cost of more than $35m ( 15m), Over 74,000 man months were devoted to different forms of education or training in academic, professional, technical andvocational subjects. The principal fields of study were agriculture, education,engineering, medical science, natural sciences and social sciences.35. Consultations with overseas governments, with the object of ensuring that requests for training in the United Kingdom are related as closely aspossible to the overall manpower requirements of the countries concerned,continue on an annual basis. An important objective is to build up trainingcapability within the countries concerned. For some kinds of training, coursesprovided in a third country in the developing world have advantages overtraining in a developed country. Increased attention is therefore being given tosupport for third country alternatives. In accordance with the United Kingdom&apos;srevised aid strategy, the ODM*s technical co-operation programmes will placegreater emphasis on the needs of primary and non-formal education, and ondeveloping vocational skills.Research and Development36. The United Kingdom has a long tradition of scientific and technicalwork on problems of specific concern to the developing countries, notably istropical health and agriculture. Facilities for investigating these problems havebeen built up at home and overseas, and while the long-term aim is to helpdeveloping countries to assume the main responsibility for such investigations,the shortage of expertise and resources overseas means that the United kingdom will continue to pay a major role for some time to come.37.  During 1975 the ODM financed research and development to support a slightly increased programme investigating the economic and social problems ofthe developing countries. $21 -1m ( 9-5m) was spent in all, most of it on problemsof global and regional import rather than those confined to a single country. Partof the work consists of research into the major scourges (mainly plant, animaland human diseases) that afflict the tropics and sub-tropics. The remainder isconcerned essentially with adapting existing technologies to the circumstancesof countries which are tropical and under-developed. The emphasis is on thelabour-intensive rather than the labour-saving and the simple rather than thecomplicated. Above all, special priority is now given to research of directrelevance to the attack on individual poverty-and in particular rural poverty in the developing countries. The greater part of the expenditure goes on re-search in the field of renewable natural resources (agriculture, livestock pro-duction and health, pest control, fisheries and forestry), and there are also majoroutlays on medical, economic and social research (including population prob-lems), and research connected with water resources and road and buildingconstruction. A fuller account of the ODM research and development activitiesis contained in the Ministry&apos;; &quot;Report on Research and Development 1975&quot;,published by Her Majest/s Stationery Office.38.  The ODM supports research and development programmes in, or onbehalf of, developing countries in four main ways: (0) by direct grants to support scientific staff and provide equipment and facilities to investigate scientific and technical problems (paragraph 39refers);
(ft) by work carried out by the ODM&apos;s Special Units (paragraph 40 refers);(c) by annual financial contributions to International Research Centres(paragraph 41 refers); and(d) through annual grants to a number of British institutes and centres(paragraph 42 refers).39. Research connected with renewable natural resources continues to be a major field of effort. For example, in Jamaica a team of British scientists is carrying out research to identify an unknown pathogen (Lethal Yellowing)which kills coconut trees in Jamaica and elsewhere. In the Forestry ResearchInstitute of Nigeria and at the Institute of Terrestrial Ecology Edinburgh,collaborative teams are carrying out research into the vegetative propagationand regular seed supplies of obeche, one of the most important hardwoodsof West Africa, and in Kenya a team is collaborating with the Kenya Vet-erinary Authorities to study the effect of a wide-scale compulsory vaccinationcampaign against Foot and Mouth Disease. The ODM also makes use of facilities in many British universities, some of which it has itself helped to enlarge. TheODM has built and maintains a Tsetse Research Laboratory at the university of Bristol which breeds tsetse flies for supply to institutions in the UnitedKingdom and overseas engaged on trypanosomiasis research, and itselfundertakes research directed towards the control of trypanosomiasis. AtReading University research is being carried out in collaboration with theInternational Institute of Tropical Agriculture in Nigeria on the physiology of grain legumes and a long-term study is being carried out at the University ofSussex and in The Gambia on aspects of mosquito behaviour relevant to the transmission of disease and the control of vectors. A research project has been commisioned from Strathclyde University on the costs and benefits of using&quot;Intermediate Technology&quot; techniques in connection with various types ofproduction and distribution processes in developing countries. This projecthas brought out some preliminary findings of considerable interest and con-sideration is now being given to how best advantage can be taken of the newknowledge.40. Funds continued to be provided in 1975 to maintain a number of scientific and technical organisations specialising exclusively in the problems of developing countries. Total support amounted to $14-Om ( 6-3m) of which about $5-6m ( 2-5m) was devoted to research and development. Of these institutions, the Tropical Products Institute, the Centre for Overseas PestResearch (both of which have substantial research programmes), the LandResources Division, and the Directorate of Overseas Surveys are all functionalcomponents of ODM. These establishments carry out advisory and technicalsurvey work for developing countries in addition to their research programmes.Brief descriptions of the organisations are given in an Annex.41. The growing international dimension is particularly noteworthy.There have been a number of productive initiatives led by various international institutions for the purpose of mobilising scientific and technical resources on a world-wide or regional basis to tackle problems which require a wider base thana single donor country can provide. The most notable is the Consultative group on International Agricultural Research, which is backed by the World Bank,
the United Nations Development programme (UNDP), the United NationsFood and Agriculture Organisation (FAO), and various national donorsincluding the United Kingdom, and works in full co-operation with the de-veloping countries. The Group supports nine internationally-run agricultural research centres in Asia, Africa and Latin America whose work is directed to specific food crops, the development of appropriate farming systems and thecountering of livestock and animal health problems. Of the $21-lm ( 9.5m)which was spent on research and development, $2-7m (fl-2m) went to thesecentres. A comparable international programme in the field of human healthis now in prospect under the auspices of the World Bank, the United NationsWorld Health Organisation (WHO) and UNDP, directed at six major tropicaldiseases. The United Kingdom is closely involved in ai! these programmes, notmerely as a contributor, but as a prominent partner in their planning and execution. ODM has also welcomed the increased international interest and the wider view of the problems of nutrition which is being taken and which derives from the recent World Food Conference. Considerable support has always beengiven, both direct and indirect, in this field and to strengthen its capabilities theODM has recently appointed a Nutrition Adviser.42. In addition to the activities of the ODM Scientific Units mentioned inparagraph 40, annual grants are made to a number of scientific organisations,some of which are part of other United Kingdom Government Departments, toenable them to undertake research and development work, on behalf of the developing countries. These institutions are also described in the Annex, andtheir work includes the fields of road construction, building materials and construction, the development of water resources, geological mapping andinvestigations, tropical veterinary medicine, the development of simple agri-cultural machinery, tropical forestry and research in intermediate technology.d. Commonwealth Development Corporation (CDC)43. It was announced in 1975 that, as a result of discussions between theODM and the CDC, the latter had decided overthe next five years that itwouldincreasingly seek to place its new commitments into the poorer countries,and into renewable natural resource projects that is to say, in agriculture,forestry and fisheries-benefiting people living in rural areas. During 1975 new commitments to such projects amounted to $27-0m ( 12-17m) or nearly 55 percent of total new commitments of S49-5m( 22-27m). Advances to the CDC forthese projects continued to carry a concessionary element44. Since the 1975 United Kingdom Memorandum was submitted to theDAC the CDC has been authorised to operate in the Sudan under the arrange-ments introduced in 1969 whereby it may extend its area of operations to in-dividual non-Commonwealth countries, subject to the consent of the UnitedKingdom Government in each case. The CDC has now been authorised to operate in a total of 10 non-Commonwealth countries.IH. PRIVATE SECTORa. Private Investment45. The United Kingdom is a large scale investor in the developing world and the contribution of net private investment to the Sow of resources from the
United Kingdom to developing countries over the last few years has been considerable.46. The Government announced in March 1976 that it proposed to revive thePre-Investment Studies Scheme which was in operation from 1972 to 1974.This will provide funds to underwrite up to one-half of the cost of pre-investmentstudies, subject to a maximum of $111,000 ( 50,000), in respect of development to which the host governments attach priority.b. Investment Protection47. The United Kingdom seeks where ever possible to conclude bilateral agreements with other countries for the reciprocal protection of investments andbelieves that such agreements help to secure fair treatment of private investmentoverseas. Since December 1974 agreements have been signed with Singapore,Egypt, Korea and Indonesia. Negotiations are continuing with other countries.c. Investment Insurance48. The Export Credits Guarantee Department (ECGD) continues to insurenew investment from the United Kingdom against the non-commercial risks ofwar, expropriation and restrictions on remittances. By the end of 1975 ECGDhad concluded 76 insurance agreements worth $69-9m ( 31-46m). These related to 32 projects in Africa, 7 in Central America, 7 in South America, 16 in the far east, 11 in the Middle East, 2 in Europe and 1 in Oceania.d. Export Credits Guarantee Department49. The net amount of credit in excess of 180 days in length extended to the developing countries in 1975 is provisionally estimated to be $415-7m ( 187-lm),compared with a net total of $336-6m ( 151-5m) in 1974. The provisional total net value of credit extended to all countries was $1,180m ( 531m) in 1975; netcredit to developing countries represents 35 per cent of this total.50. The most significant changes in ECGD facilities during the year werethe introduction of a limited scheme to protect exporters against exeptional and unpredictable increases in costs on major capital goods contracts; a schemeto facilitate the provision of working capital for large export contracts for whichECGD is also providing basic cover; cover by ECGD of various forms of bondsdemanded of British suppliers by overseas buyers; and a scheme to insuremembers of a consortium contracting overseas against losses they may sustainas a consequence of the insolvency of a fellow consortium member. The interestrate for business on credit in excess of 5 years remained a minimum of 71 percent per annum, for business between 2 and 5 years it remained at a mini-mum of 7 per cent and for business below 2 years it was still $ per cent above the relevant bank&apos;s base rate.51. ECGD continued to take part during the year in discussion between certain countries aimed at reaching a consensus on guidelines for determining themaximum lengths of credit and minimum interest rates for different groups of markets.
52.  Whilst there are normally no direct consultations on debt servicingbetween ECGD and the authorities of the importing countries, ECGD controls the volume of officially supported export credit to developing countries byassessing the situation of the recipient country based, inter alia, on the overallamount of external debt to be serviced, and it is a standard ECGD requirement that any regulation of the recipient country (such as prior approval registration of credits) must be complied with. ECGD may also stipulate that a guarantee of payment and/or sterling availability should be obtained from the CentralFinancing Authorities of the importing country to ensure that proper provision is made for payment of the contract. In addition, projects worth over $4-44m( 2m) in a limited number of developing countries are assessed as to their viabi-tity and developmental value before ECGD cover is agreed. However, debt man-encouragement  is primarily the responsibility of the borrower.IV.  SOCIAL ASPECTS OF DEVELOPMENTa. Aid to the Poorer SectionsAssistance to the Rural Poor53. The White Paper on Overseas Development had as its sub-tide &quot;MoreHelp for the Poorest&quot;. The major objectives of United Kingdom aid policy isto ensure that more of its aid directly benefits not only the poorest countries butthe poorest people in those countries. Since most of the poor live in the rural areas the United Kingdom&apos;s main task is to find schemes which help the poorby promoting rural development.54.  This policy was commented on in some detail in the 1975 United King-dom Memorandum to the DAC but briefly, rural development is interpreted as astrategy designed to improve both the economic and social life of the rural poor.It should not be thought of as merely another term for increased agricultural production. Whilst it is obviously of major importance to raise the incomes offanners and ensure that there is enough food for everyone, the appropriate and related development of education, health, housing, water and power supply,marketing and communication is also necessary. Very often the successfulintroduction of one input or the solution of one problem will depend on or affectanother. Farmers will have no incentive to increase their production if they areunable to sell their products because of inaccessible markets or poor marketingfacilities, or if the supply of necessary inputs and basic economic goods areneglected. Dl-health is hardly conducive to increased production, and widespreadmalnutrition in turn makes the rural population especially vulnerable to disease.The United Kingdom thus believes that any rural development project, either by itself or in conjunction with other inputs, should aim to improve both the incomes and the welfare of the lower income groups.55. The United Kingdom is keen to assist countries to increase the volumeand improve the quality of agricultural output. But raising agricultural produc-tion or productivity is of limited value if it is only a small number of fanners whobenefit. The aim should therefore be to design projects so that as large a
number as possible of the poorer farmers are included. It is also vital to maintain a balance between the often conflicting goals of increased production and in-creased employment This means that capital intensive schemes will often beless suitable than labour intensive ones, even though such a choice may result in less than optimum production. If, through improved farming methods, a largenumber of farmers are able not only to grow enough food to feed the local community but are also able to produce cash crops and food surpluses, the consequent increase in local resources will enable farmers to continue creatingwealth as well as producing enough food, and the community to establish and support the social and other services needed for a genuine improvement in itsstandard of living.56. The United Kingdom has been willing to provide assistance to rural development in a number of different ways, including assistance for inte-grated rural development projects consisting of a number of inputs in a numberof sectors designed collectively to improve the standard of living in one area.Such projects are based on the principle of the interdependence of all sectorsin any one area. They ensure that development of one particular sector is notcarried out in isolation from activities in other sectors, a haphazard and piecemealapproach which can lead to unforeseen side-effects and an exaggeration ofexisting distortions in the distribution of income, employment and services. Suchprojects are not always easy to identify and organise and the United Kingdom istherefore also prepared to support projects dealing with one sector only.However, even in these cases the aim will be to place the project concerned in the context of the development of the rural area as a whole; and it is hoped that itwill be possible in a number of cases to extend such projects later by addinginputs in other sectors. For instance, projects designed to increase output inthe agricultural, forestry and fisheries sectors, once established, could be ex-panded by setting up multi-purpose rural training and service centres, con-structing rural clinics, schools and feeder roads, improving water and powersupplies, reinforcing credit and marketing facilities to cover a wider range ofinputs and crops, and developing small-scale processing industries. Equallyvalid are projects which form part of a wider operation in which other inputsare being provided either by other donors or by the government concerned.57. Some examples can be given to illustrate the different types of rural development projects that the United Kingdom is currently undertaking. In theSudan&apos;s South Darfur Province the United Kingdom is helping to mount an inte-grated rural development project (United Kingdom contribution $l-864m( 839,000)). The initial four-year phase of the project began twelve months agowith work starting on the setting-up of three demonstration farms. The maintasks of these farms are to advise, test and demonstrate improved crop tech-techniques and livestock husbandry. The objective of the project is to lay the found-ations for a long term- programme to reverse the trend of declining farm and livestock productivity in the area, by reorganising land use and tenure in in-habited areas, by controlled development of an area of-land of substantialagricultural potential which is largely uninhabited, by improving agriculturalpractices generally in the area through research, extension and ancillary servicesand by extending the area of flood irrigation. If successful, the project will allowsignificant increases in the incomes of the rural population, in contrast to thepresently projected declines in average income. The project is the first of its
kind in the Sudan, and the results will be of potential benefit in planning thedevelopment of other areas in the savannah zone. It is also of interest in thatArab funds are financing a major part of the off-shore costs. (See paragraph 91.)58.  The United Kingdom has financed a study of the resources of part of ethiopia&apos;s Tigrai Province and a report on soil conservation and rehabilitationrequirements and development prospects will soon be presented to the ethiopian government. The study cost about $l-62m ( 730,000) with a farther $0-56m( 250,000) provided for pilot projects started during the investigation. The re-port recommends a long-term development programme for the Province with theobject of preventing soil erosion and raising the productive potential and welfare of the population who are presently suffering from extreme poverty and theconsequences of recent drought and famine. In another part of Ethiopia,WoIIo Province, the United Kingdom is involved in the construction, at a cost of$3-67m ( l-65m), of three feeder roads principally designed to provide easieraccess to local markets.59. In Botswana the United Kingdom is financing a dryland farming projectwhich it is estimated will cost $0-67m ( 300,000) during the period 1975-78.Phase I of the project was designed to carry out research into new fanningmethods and tools suitable for dryland fanning. Under Phase II research is beingextended and as a result of work already completed, an evaluation of farmingsystems is being carried out and an integrated farm project is being established.60.  In 1974, the United Kingdom began to co-operate with the Governmentof the Yemen Arab Republic in a 2j year study of the land and water resourcesof two distinct areas-one in the Montane plains and the other, the Wadi Rima,nearer the coast at a cost of about $2-89m ( l-3m). The study will provide the basic technical and socio-economic information and analysis required to enablespecific proposals for agricultural and social development in these areas to beput forward. A number of possible projects for early implementation have been identified already, one of them being the establishment of an AgriculturalImprovement Centre. Such a centre would facilitate investigation of, and experi-mentation with, more productive farming systems. This would mean examiningnew crops and varieties, water-use, socio-economic responses to variousagricultural innovations and more cost-effective ways of responding to the needsof the rural population for extension. The training of extension staff at the centrewould make it easier both to conduct such research and transmit the results to thelocal fanners.61. An example of a proposal to extend a project to include other inputs isprovided by a project in Eastern Nepal, where the United Kingdom has financeda design and costing survey of a road along the main growth corridor into the hills. Simultaneously with the construction of the road, which will be financed from United Kingdom capital aid, it is proposed that the United Kingdom should establish a technical co-operation project covering project identification and aresources survey, to help the Nepalese Government in its aim of exploiting to thefull the agricultural potential of the area north of the road. Help will also be offered in social services, particularly in the improvement of medical services and family planning.
62. It was recognised from the start that it would take time for the UnitedKingdom to change the emphasis of its aid programme in accordance with thenew strategy. There are a number of reasons for this. In the first place, the iden-tificationof sound rural development projects is not always easy and the fact that other bilateral donors and international aid agencies are simultaneously placinggreater emphasis on the rural sector increases the problem. Secondly, the prob-lems of working up and implementing rural development projects are numerousand complex. Thirdly, the time scale for the implementation of projects of thiskind is likely to be long.63. As regards identification of projects the United Kingdom is lookinginto ways of more effectively deploying its existing resources so as to helpstimulate more proposals from developing countries and to expedite and improvedetailed project preparation and appraisal. It is also examining ways in which itmight make further use of the expertise of British consultants and also co-operate more closely with multilateral organisations for the same purpose.The working up and implementation stages are expected to put a strain on the limited manpower resources available within both the United Kingdom and the recipient countries. Difficulties exist in recruiting technical co-operation expertsfor work in often remote rural areas and the developing country governmentsalso have problems in finding enough suitably qualified counterpart staff. Theseare all matters which it will be necessary to keep under constant review and withthis end in mind the ODM&apos;s Steering Group on Rural Development which was setup early in 1975 has recently been reconstituted with a more limited membership and with revised terms of reference which require it &quot;to keep under review the implementation of the proposals concerning the changing emphasis in Britishaid policies in so far as they relate to schemes for helping the poorer sections ofthe population in developing countries, particularly those in the rural areas&quot;.Urban Development64. The main emphasis of the United Kingdom&apos;s aid strategy is on rural development since it is in the rural areas where most of the poor of the ThirdWorld live. There are, however, urban poor as well as rural poor and the UnitedKingdom remains ready to consider any proposals aimed at helping these people also and of alleviating the growing problems of unemployment andunderemployment which exist in the towns.65. A matter of particular concern to the urban poor on which the ODMhas issued a position paper, is the provision of housing. Financial resources are completely inadequate for the purpose of resolving by traditional and conven-tional methods the housing needs (as well as many of the other urban require-ments) of the poor countries, and it is the United Kingdom&apos;s view that if any immediate impact is to be made on a reasonably equitable basis in reaching the poorest income groups the answer lies in adopting a combination of &quot;site and services&quot; schemes, and the improvement and upgrading of existing informal&quot;squatter settlements&quot;. The &quot;site and services&quot; approach minimises labour costs,first by ensuring that participants in each scheme contribute their own labour tothe construction of housing and, second, by permitting construction standardsdetermined by the resources, skills and initiatives of individual families, providednecessary standards of health and safety essential in the interests of the whole community are maintained. Schemes can range from the provision of land
with defined boundaries within which people can build their own houses, tothe provision of floor slabs, service cores and possibly a single room which canbe expanded as and when opportunity occurs. But the less government has toput into each scheme, the larger will be the number of people who wflj benefit from the limited resources available; and the more each household puts in, (hegreater the number of households that will benefit.66. The ODM has made it known that the United Kingdom h ready toconsider assisting developing countries in the implementation of site and servicesschemes through:(a) providing advice under technical co-operation, at national or locallevels (although the amount of expertise which can be offered in this field is limited);(6) financing pilot schemes in selected areas (that is, where there is sufficient support, both local and central, to indicate a reasonable chanceof long term effective schemes being undertaken); and,(c) providing financial aid for definitive schemes in appropriate cases.Population Policy67. The need to give high priority to aid for population matters is now well established and generally understood and its importance, together with that of the relationship between population and other development, is recognised in the newaid strategy and in the recent Cabinet Office discussion paper on Future WorldTrends.68. The considerable upsurge in demands for assistance provides clear evidence that governments in the Third World are increasingly concerned withpopulation questions and there is little doubt that the events of World Pop-ulation Year played a major part in focusing attention on the vital importance which population change has on development Moreover the aim of universalresponsible parenthood and the recognition of die right of all persons to be ableto control their own fertility are now generally accepted by the internationalcommunity, and the United Kingdom stands firmly behind its pledge to dowhatever it can to assist with programmes intended to achieve the impteawn-tation of the World Population Plan of Action.69.  Consistent wkh this policy and as a result of several initiatives, theproportion of the aid programme spent on population nutters has risen from about 0-5 per cent in 1973/74 to overO-8 per cent in 1975/76. This isexpected torise still further as programmes are implemented in response to an increasing number of bilateral requests. The importance of the role of the multilateralagencies is recognised and the United Kingdom has increased its aid to theUnited Natrons Fund for Population Activities (UNFPA) from $2-22m ( la)in 1974-75 to $4-44m ( 2m) in 1976-77 and to the InCeraaiional PlannedParenthood Federation from *1 -56m ( 700,000) in 1974-75 to $3-33m( l-5m)ia1976-77. The United Kingdom has also actively helped to develop the multi-bilateral system for joint funding of population projects which the UNFPA areunable to support wholly for lack of sufficient funds.
Private Non-Prqfit Bodies70. As anticipated in the 1975 United Kingdom Memorandum, a schemefor the part funding of development projects undertaken overseas by voluntaryagencies came into operation in May 1975. Projects valued between $6,600( 3,000) and $110,000 ( 50,000) are eligible for support on a 50/50 basis.$1-1 lm ( 500,000) was provided for the first year&apos;s expenditure but the schemegot off to a slow start and only 16 projects were submitted for consideration dur-ing the 7 months to December 1975. Eight were approved with a total valueof just over $358,000 ( 161,000). They were concerned with community health,co-operatives, animal health, village betterment, technical training and watersupply. Separate provision has also been made for specific support for popula-tion activities undertaken by the voluntary agencies in the context of familyhealth and welfare programmes and expenditure on this during the year wasin the region of $351,000 ( 158,000). Assistance for this type of activity can begiven (and usually is given) on a 100 per cent basis.71. The agencies themselves, including church and missionary societies,spent an estimated $53-3m ( 24m) on their overseas work in 1975. It is estimatedthat about 75 per cent of the money was provided by about 10 per cent of the215 agencies concerned. Their funds were spent mainly on emergency relief,health and education in over 70 developing countries.b. Integration of Women in the Development Process72. At the United Nations International Women&apos;s Year Conference inMexico City, 1975, the United Kingdom (having previously made a contribution of $22,000 ( 10,000) to the International Women*s Year Voluntary Fund for the promotion of the Year&apos;s activities), offered a special contribution of $l-33m( 600,000) payable in three equal annual instalments to help projects that willprimarily benefit rural women in countries with a GNP per capita of less than$400. It is hoped that as much as possible of this United Kingdom grant will be allocated through UN Regional Commissions for projects at grass roots level,particularly through the Economic Commission for Africa where an ongoingwomen&apos;s development programme is already under way.73. ODM employs the service of a consultant specially engaged to promote the role of women in the development process, who maintains liaison with theUN Regional Commissions and with others concerned in this field. The ODMis also carrying out an examination of how the position and needs of womencan best be taken into account in the context of project appraisals and formula-tion. Of the activities being supported in other fields of particular relevance to women, mention should be made of the training facilities in nutrition, etc,tailored for overseas needs that are available in Britain under the technical co-operation programme; the increased contribution which the United kingdom is making towards family planning in furtherance of the World Plan of Actionagreed at Bucharest in 1974; and the increased support which is being providedfor the United Nations Children&apos;s Fund (UNICEF) as an effective means of reaching the least privileged of all groups mothers and children in poorcountries.
c Food Production, Security and AM74.  in general the aim of the United Kingdom&apos;s aid in the agriculturalsector is to assist developing countries to improve the quantity and quality ofproduction of both food and cash earning commodities. The United Kingdomrecognises in particular that the food problem in developing countries is one fargrave concern and the steadily rising proportion of imports of cereals by devel-oping  countries as a percentage of their total consumption requirements is an indication that substantial food aid will be needed for some years to come. Butthe United Kingdom also recognises thepossible disadvantage of food aid in thatit could in certain situations depress local producer prices for food crops andthus adversely affect local food production. While the need for assistance isacknowledged, it is essential that this is accompanied by a real commitment bythe governments of developing countries to a programme of increased foodproduction through agricultural development. Food aid is not a desirablealternative to this, nor to better protection against crop losses in the held and instore, production planning and more equitable systems of food distribution.Distribution within a country depends very much on the efficiency of the localdistribution system and is thus primarily a matter for the local government.However, the United Kingdom is prepared to offer assistance when asked, forexample, in cases where food aid is for stocks, technical co-operation can beprovided to strengthen local management.Food Security75. The United Kingdom gives support to the FAO food security assistanceprogramme and has indicated to FAO its wish to receive copies of the individualcountry reports on fbod security ia order to consider offering bilateral technical co-operation. In 1975 the United Kingdom supplied and paid for an engineerfor the Nigeria mission and will be providing two experts for the Tanzaniamission in 1976.76. The United Kingdom is also very active in helping to reduce the lossesarising in the transport and stocking of crops. ODM*s Tropical ProductsInstitute is concerned with post-harvest handling, processing, quality controland storage.Fertilisers77.  The United Kingdom is well aware of the important contribution which fertilizers can make to increasing food production in the developing countries and its policies attempt to ensure that these countries obtain thefertilizer supplies they seed at a price which the small farmers can afford. TheUnited Kingdom is also prepared to assist developing countries, wherever possible, to improve or establish their own sources of fertilizer supply.The United Kingdom recognises the need in the short-term to ensurethat developing countries obtain the supplies of fertilizer they require,but is not well placed to be able to make any significant impression on this short-term supply situation because it has to import muchof the raw material required for fertilizer manufacture. However, theUnited Kingdom has supported the FAO/Intemational Fertilner SupplyScheme from its establishment and has been one of the major contributors.The United Kingdom contributed 25,000 tonnes in the United Kingdom financial
year 1974-75 and a further 100,000 tonnes of compound fertilizer to the mostneedy countries during the financial year 1975-76. In addition, fertilizers were provided on a bilateral basis. As in the past, the United Kingdom is also willingto consider providing capital aid and technical co-operation on a bilateral basisto developing countries to enable them to improve the output of their existingplants or to construct new ones.Crop Protection78. In many countries the overall food losses from pests now amount tosome 30 per cent and immediate savings of up to 10 percent can be expected fromsimple schemes of pesticide application, suitable for small farmers. The UnitedKingdom is well qualified to provide the necessary training and technical co-operation through ODM&apos;s Centre for Overseas Pest Research and the TropicalProducts Institute.Food Aid79. Although the United Kingdom still has basic reservations about thedevelopmental value of food aid, it recognises that a need for food aid exists for the time being, as reflected in the resolutions of the World Food Conference.To this end, the United Kingdom has supported within the e.c. a two-yearextension of the Food^id Convention and, although it has not so far proved possible to secure agreement for an increase in the eec&apos;s Cereals Programmean increase in the eec&apos;s Dairy Products Programmes for 1976 and 1977 of145,000 metric tons of dried skimmed milk has been approved, which will cost the United Kingdom $6-6m ( 3m). The United Kingdom is fully aware of the health hazards inherent in the use of dried skimmed milk and has played a leading role in the e.c. to ensure that all possible precautions are taken toavoid them.80. The United Kingdom aims where possible to link the provision of food aid directly with appropriate developmental projects to secure the maximumbeneficial return, with the ultimate hope of rendering food aid unnecessary.There will however always be natural and man-made disasters requiring emer-gency response. The e.c. has, on these occasions, been able to contribute food aid quickly and efficiently. The United Kingdom itself has undertaken emer-gency action bilaterally. Two recent examples are the supply of grain to Nigerand dried skimmed milk to Portugal for Angolan refugees. It is the agreed policy of the e.c. to support the creation of an internationally coordinatedsystem of nationally held stocks from which emergency aid may be supplied in times of shortage, but which will primarily serve the purpose of stabilizingmarkets and prices.81. The United Kingdom has consistently voiced the view within the EECthat the distribution of food aid should be concentrated as far as possible on theneediest countries; of her own bilateral programme nearly 70 per cent is being sent to developing countries in this category whilst the remainder is being given tothe World Food Programme whose policy is to concentrate its aid on the leastdeveloped countries. At the same time, the United Kingdom is conscious of theneed to ensure that local market prices are not depressed as a result of an influx of food aid, and that the maximum nutritional value is obtained from the foodprovided.
82. During 1975 the United Kingdom contributed an estimated $2S-2m( 12-7m) to the e.c. Cereals and Dairy Products Programmes and spent$22-9m ( 103m) on national actions contained within the Community CerealsProgramme.World Food Programme (WFP)83. The United Kingdom has promised the WFP a total of $9-6m ( 4-325m)in commodities and cash for the two calendar year period 1977-78, subject to parliamentary approval. One third will be in cash and two thirds in commodities.This represents an increase of 30 per cent over the previous regular UnitedKingdom pledge. The United kingdom&apos;s  regular pledge for 1975-76 was$7-4m ( 3&apos;325m) but this was supplemented during 1975 by a contribution of$Mm ( 500,000) to assist the Programme to meet increasing costs and by afurther special contribution of $110m ( 5m) in cash to be used for the benefit ofBangladesh. The United Kingdom has supported the WFP since its inception andregards it as being more successful than any other organisation in the difficult task of using food as an instrument of economic and soda! development.Other Assistance84. The United Kingdom is assisting in the promotion of the seed industryin developing countries by the training of technical personnel in the technology of seed production and is also assisting in the improvement of root and vegeta-tively propagated crops under its technical co-operation programme. TheUnited Kingdom also assists in many other areas relevant to food productionincluding disease and weed control, mechanization, soil and water conservation reclamation and the livestock industry.V.  INDUSTRIAL AND TECHNOLOGICAL CO-OPERATION85.  In accordance with the changing emphasis in the United Kingdom aidpolicy as outlined in the 1975 White Paper, industrial co-operation is given acomparatively low priority, although the increasing attention now given torural development naturally extends to the promotion of mdustries-^jarticulariysma]]-sca]eones-within the agricultural sector. Nevertheless the United kingdom has a few industrial co-operation agreements with developing countries and theseare nearly all with Middle East countries. Through its contribution to the EECsFourth European Development Fund the United Kingdom will also be promoting-ting industrial development in the 46 African Caribbean and Pacific signatoryStates to the Lome Convention. An overall objective of the United Kingdom^internal regional and industrial policy is to encourage the transfer of productionand workers out of unprofitable sectors into expanding sectors of industry whichare internationally competitive both in relation to developing and developedcountry production and, as a member of the United Nations Industrial Develop-ment Organisation (UNIDO) the United Kingdom encourages the efforts of that organisation to deliver technical co-operation to developing countries&apos; industries in an effective manner.
86. In tire field of technological co-operation priority is given to natural resources and poverty orientated projects which include technology relevant toagro-industries, agricultural engineering, transport, building, water supply andsanitation, and intermediate technology for small scale industries. The ODMScientific Units provide assistance within these fields.VI. THE AID RELATIONSHIP87. The keynote of the United Kingdom^ aid policy is partnership with the recipient government and its agencies. This is achieved by a close and continuousdialogue with the recipient government through the British diplomatic mission,where aid is an integral part of their duties, and by frequent visits from membersof the team of specialist advisers employed by ODM and based either in thefive regional Development Divisions or at Headquarters. The United Kingdomalso welcomes opportunities to consult and cooperate with other aid agencies,for example, as a member of Aid Groups. The Commonwealth ministerial meeting in Food Production and Rural Development held in March 1975demonstrated another valuable form of cooperation.88. In order to arrive at a mutually acceptable aid programme the recipientgovernment outlines its development policies and priorities with a brief assess-ment of the development potential and prospects by main sectors, identifyingthe main constraints that nave to be overcome. These requirements are considered in tbe light of the amounts and types of aid provided by international agencies,other bilateral donors and by the United Kingdom. This information is evaluatedand a mutually agreed programme and financial limit is achieved where possible.89. The United Kingdom Governments aid policy has increasinglyturned in recent years towards recognition of the criteria of poverty and need asthe principal one which should govern the distribution of concessional aid.Parallel to the emphasis on the poorest countries in the distribution of UnitedKingdom aid, increasing priority is being given to poverty focused programmes of rural development. This change in emphasis requires even closer co-operation and consultation between United Kingdom officials and those of the recipientgovernment on project identification, preparation and implementation.VII.  JOINT CO-OPERATIVE VENTURES90. The OPEC countries have established themselves as a significant group of donors providing between them multilateral and bilateral aid flows amountingto some 15 per cent of estimated net financial flows to developing countries. TheUnited Kingdom has established close working relationships on co-operation injoint ventures with the Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development(AFESD), the Kuwait Fund for Arab Economic Development (KFAED) andthe Abu Dhabi Fund for Arab Economic Development (ADFAED) and has also
initialed discussions on co-operation with other Funds including the IslamicDevelopment Bank (IDB) and the Saudi Development Fund (SDF). This co-operation has consisted of exchanges of information, periodic visits, regularliaison meetings, provision of experts and joint appraisal of projects. Both ODMand the Funds concerned are acquiring a better understanding of their respectiveaid philosophies and procedures which it is hoped will lead to increasing practicalco-operation in future.91. Discussions took place during 1975, first with the AFESD and sub-sequently with the Abu Dhabi Fund, about finance for an integrated rural development project in South Darfur in the Sudan. Agreement has been reached between the Sudanese Government, ODM and the Abu Dhabi Fund under whichthe Fund will finance the off-shore costs of the project up to $3-75m ( l-7m),the Sudanese Government will meet the remaining capital costs of approximately$3-25m ( l-5m) and the United Kingdom finance the continuing work of the consultants at a cost of $l-7m ( 800,000).92. There have also been discussions with the Jordan Government and theArab Fund on a joint appraisal by the United Kingdom Government and theArab Fund of a possible water supply and distribution project for the developingport and town of Aqaba. Other countries where possibilities for co-operationwith Arab aid funds are actively being discussed include Egypt and the YemenArab Republic (provision of experts for an Arab Fund financed electricityproject and co-operation in a livestock project).93.   Discussions were initiated with the Arab Fund on co-operation infeasibility studies for inter-country projects in the Arab region.94.  The United Kingdom has also joined its e.c. partners in discussions with Arab countries on Euro-Arab co-operation.95. The 1975 United Kingdom Memorandum noted the large increase inthe demand by the oil rich states for technical expertise of all kinds. The ODM&apos;srole in relation to the intensive and continuing negotiations between the UnitedKingdom and several Middle East Governments includes the provision of pro-fessional advice, the co-ordination of information and the identification ofBritish sources of supply or assistance, and of responsibilities for further action so far as this lies with Government Departments and associated organ-isations.VIII.  COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH TO DEVELOPMENTa. Initiatives in Development co-operation beyond Official Development AssistanceTariff Matters96. The United Kingdom has continued to work within the e.c. for im-improvements to the Community&apos;s Generalised Scheme of Preferences (GSP).In March 1975 the Council of Ministers agreed a resolution committing the
Community to further progressive improvements in the GSP, particularly for thebenefit of the poorest beneficiaries, and this approach was evident in the im-improvements agreed for the 1976 scheme at the end of 1975. The Communityhas also announced its willingness to continue its Scheme after 1981. TheUnited Kingdom also hopes that real progress will be made in the multilateral trade Negotiations in Geneva. The e.c. Directives for these negotiations take full account of the references in the 1973 Ministerial Declaration at Tokyo forspecial measures in favour of developing countries, in particular for the pooreramongst them.Commodity Questions97. The United Kingdom fully recognises the importance of commoditytrade in the development co-operation context and the need to promote measuresof stability.98. At the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting held in Kingstonin April/May 1975 the United Kingdom recognised the need to aim for a moreequitable pattern of economic relationships between the developed and the developing world and proposed an overall approach to international commoditytrade which would embody the following general commitments.(a) the interdependence of producers and consumers and the desirabilityof conducting trade in commodities in accordance with equitable arrange-ments worked out in agreement between producers and consumers shouldbe recognised;(b) producer countries should undertake to maintain adequate and securesupplies to consumer countries;(c) consumer countries for their part should undertake to improve access to markets for those items of primary production of interest to developingproducers;(d) the principle should be established that commodity prices should beequitable to consumers and remunerative to efficient producers and at a level which would encourage long-term equilibrium between productionand consumption;(e) in particular the need to expand the total production of essential foodstuffs should be recognised;(f) the efficient development, production and marketing of commodities the diversification and efficient processing of commodities in de-veloping countries should be encouraged.99. The United Nations Seventh Special Session in New York in September1975 took the international discussion of commodity questions a step further and these issues will figure prominently within the Raw Materials Commissionof the Conference on International Economic Co-operation (CIEC) as well asat UNCTAD IV in Nairobi in May 1976. The United Kingdom continues to hope that it may be possible to reach a consensus on international guidelines for trade in commodities which could be complemented by appropriate specificarrangements negotiated on a case-by-case basis for individual commodities.
100. The United Kingdom is also participating in the on-going work in international fora concerned with commodity trade GATT, FAO andUNCTAD. In so far as individual commodities are concerned, the UnitedKingdom played a full part in the negotiations which led to new international agreements for coffee, cocoa and tin in 1975 and continues to participate in thediscussions on grains within the International Wheat Council and the Multi-lateral Trade Negotiations. The United Kingdom has also recently submitted proposals for a possible international agreement on tea to the FAO Inter-governmental Group concerned with this commodity.Restructuring of Industry101. The United Kingdom accepts that countries should pursue domesticpolicies which, while taking into account social and economic constraints, en-courage their industries which are less competitive internationally to move intomore viable lines of production. Industry in the United Kingdom makes its ownadjustment decisions as part of a continuing process of adaptation to changedmarket conditions. The Government takes steps to assist this process in thelight of the United Kingdom^ economic circumstances and there are generousdepreciation allowances for tax purposes on a national level, and a generoussytem of regional incentives exists to encourage the developmentof newindustriesin the Assisted Areas to replace jobs lost in declining industries. Selectivefinancial assistance can also be given throughout the country and is used tohelp particular sectors of industry on a national basis. It is very much part of theUnited Kingdom^ Industrial Strategy to encourage firms to move out of lessviable lines in favour of new investment in profit-making activities.Developing Countries Import Opportunities Office (DCIOO)102. DCIOO was established in December 1973 within the London Chamberof Commerce and Industry and is financed by ODM. It provides information and advice to help developing countries expand their exports to the UnitedKingdom and it handled over 2,200 enquiries in its first full year of operation upto March 1975. The Office works in close liaison with the European Commissionand the ODM&apos;s Tropical Products Institute and has established good contacts with the GATT/UNCTAD International Trade Centre in Geneva, and withother national import promotion agencies, for example, the Centre for the promotion of Imports from Developing Countries (CBI) in Rotterdam.b. Role of Aid Administrations in the Formulation of Development Co-operationPolicies103.  Plans were made (and implemented in early 1976) to reorganise thework of ODM to take account of the latest changing needs. Two groups con-cerned in the main respectively with bilateral aid and multilateral aid werecreated, each under a Deputy Secretary. This involved some adjustment inresponsibilities between departments, of which the most important were:-(a) the centralisation in Development Co-ordination Department ofresponsibility for all aspects of relations with the IBRD, IDA, IFCand IMF and general policy towards Regional Development Banks;
(b) the centralisation in Aid, Trade and Commodities Department, anew department, of all work relating to UNCTAD, the consumer/producer dialogue, and trade and commodity policy generally,(c) the centralisation in FAO Department of responsibility for FAO,UNICEF, World Food Council, WFP, 1FAD, The Consultative group on Food Production and Investment and Renewable Natural Resources;(d) the centralisation in United Nations Department of responsibilitiescovering the UN Development System viewed as a whole, includingUNDP, UNIDO and UNESCO.c. Changes in Public and ParHamentary Attitudes104. There were no perceptible shifts in public or Parliamentary attitudesin 1975 during a period of increasing preoccupation with domestic problems.The enthusiastic work of non-Government agencies continued undiminished.105. All-party support was forthcoming for the major policy statement, theWhite Paper, &quot;More Aid for the Poorest&quot; which was subsequently debated in bothHouses of Parliament. The decision to continue the aid programme and toprovide for a 4 per cent per year growth in real terms over the coming years wasmade public on the occasion of the publication of the Governments annual expenditure Survey published in January 1976 (Cnand. 6393). It attracted littleattention in the face of the many projected cuts in public expenditure thenannounced.106. The House of Commons Select Committee on Overseas Developmentcarried out an enquiry into &quot;The World Food Crisis and Third WorldDevelopment: Implications for UK Policy&quot;. In addition to taking formal oraland written evidence it visited Canada and the United States in July 1975 andKenya, Tanzania and Ghana in November-December 1975. The Select Comm-ittee&apos;s Report, represents the result of more than a year*s work, was published inMarch 1976. Its conclusion was clear. There was a &quot;food crisis&quot; of appallingdimensions, which could be solved only by a concerted new strategy by all aiddonors and by recipient countries themselves. The Select Committee consid-ered that the United Kingdom had a particularly important role to play in thisstrategy and endorsed the emphasis on rural development in the aid programme as set out in the Governments White Paper.107. In the wake of the World Food Conference, non-government organ-isations made concerted efforts to call attention to the new obligations on all governments to tackle threatened world food shortages. These were backed bywidespread campaigns for self-denial in domestic consumption.108. About 1,500 letters on the subject of aid were received by ODM in1975 of which less than 200 were critical or opposed to aid. 4,500 separate re-quests from individuals, groups or school classes were received asking for development literature. Parallel inquiries on a rather larger scale were receivedby the Voluntary Committee on Overseas Aid and Development (VCOAD)which meets requests with its own literature, the publications of the subscribing
organisations and those of ODM. The Ministry&apos;s newspaper carried a summaryof the White Paper &quot;More Aid for the Poorest&quot; as a supplement. 5,000 copieswere distributed over and above the normal circulation of about 10,000.109. The main information activitiy continued to be with press and tele-vision. During the year, 260 general press notices and 110 specialist ones were issued. Monitoring of press clippings shows that virtually every one finds its way into print, at home or abroad. Television and radio interest was lively, andnot, as in 1974, overwhelmingly on account of the number of disaster situations.Assistance was provided to programmes on the work in specialist areas; and,for example, on the Lome Convention. Several opportunities occurred for mem-bers of the allied professional services, for example, pest control, tropicalproducts, geological surveys, land resources, to assist with, or participate in,television and radio programmes. ODM is now supporting a plan to have the2 hours film &quot;Five Minutes to Midnight&quot;, which was shown on BBC television,shown in communities throughout the country.110. The Ministry&apos;s publication programme has in general been kept tofairly specific targets and in response to specific demands. A publication &quot;AnIntroduction to the Aid Programme&quot; was prepared to answer points made inletters over the previous year and was sent initially to all persons wbo had written to ODM during the six-months prior to its publication date. Otherpublications during 1975 included a third edition of &quot;A Guide to Sources ofMaterial&quot; in use particularly by school teachers. A new series of illustratedfold-outs for schools, describing individual developing countries, their achieve-ments and problems, together with an account of the aid they get, is provingpopular. So far six of these &quot;country studies&quot; have been issued.111. Week-end conferences and meetings in many different parts of thecountry testify to a persistent &quot;grass roots movement&quot;. These have often been addressed by Ministers or ODM staff. The main issues in the past year haverelated to world economic order. The Overseas Development Institute main-tained a regular schedule of lunch-time discussion meetings which were alwayswell attended.Ministry of Overseas Development,London
ANNEXSCIENTIFIC ESTABLISHMENTS UNDERTAKING RESEARCH ANDDEVELOPMENT ON BEHALF OF DEVELOPING COUNTRIESODhTS Special Units1. Tropical Products Institute. Concerned with agricultural, animal, fisheries,and forest products at the harvest stage and after. It carries out research and development on the use, handling, processing, quality control, pre-servation and storage of harvested natural resources and their residues,usually at the request of overseas countries and often in collaboration with overseas institutions.2. Centre for Overseas Pest Research. The Centre carries out research anddevelopment in the control of insect, rodent and bird pests through itsthree divisions (biology, ecology and chemical control), often in collabora-tion with overseas institutions.3. Land Resoutces Division. The Division is concerned with land use. Its maintask is assessing land resources and planning the development of agricultureand forestry. Its work in fields such as agronomy, animal husbandry andsoil physics involves some research.4. Directorate of Overseas Surveys. Assists overseas governments in the field of mapping, a basic necessity for alt planning and national development.Units of Other UK Government Departments5. Overseas Unit of the Transport and Road Research Laboratory. Carries outresearch into road construction and transport planning in developing countries.6. Overseas Division of the Building Research Establishment. Carries outresearch into building materials and methods for use in developing countries,with particular reference to low-cost housing.7. Overseas Unit of the Hydraulics Research Station. Carries out research intothe engineering aspects of the control and management of surface waterresources in developing countries.8. Overseas Division of the institute of Geological Sciences. Undertakesgeological mapping and investigations to strengthen the infrastructure of developing countries.9. Institute of Hydrology. The Institute is concerned with the study of thenatural water cycle, that is, the measurement and behaviour of surface waterresulting from rainfall and the effects of run-off, evaporation etc.
Other Institutions10. Centre for Tropical Veterinary Medicine. Carries out research into certain aspects of tropical animal health.11. Overseas Department of the National Institute of Agricultural Engineering.Is engaged on research and development on a wide&apos; range of simpleagricultural machinery for use in developing countries.12. Industrial Liaison Unit of the Intermediate Technology Development Group.Essentially a technical information centre whose purpose is to assist small-scale industries overseas but also carries out some research (for example, onproducing glassware and candles by simple means).13. Commonwealth Forestry Institute. The Institute carries out research intobiological, silvicultural and economic problems in tropical forestry, in-cluding work on pest and disease control.Printed in Engltod fat Her Mijetfy&apos;s Stationery Office by McCorquodalo Printers LUHM 7729 Dd 193853 K20 7/76

</content>
</cab>
