<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/29/0 images: 62-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel d(Thlt Document la the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government)WEHKLl submit for the information of the War Cabinet a Memorandumby the Commissioner of Police showing the dispositions made and to be made in connection with Air-raids in the Metropolitan PoliceDistrict.HOME OFFICE,WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 17th October.GEO. CAVE,DISPOSITIONS LIAL::.- AND ABOUT TO BE MADE IN CONNECTION WITH AIR RAIDSThe area affected is about 700 square miles with a population of l\ millions.   The more densely populated portion of this- is the Administrative County, 120 square miles in extent, with a population of 4-jg- millions;   but outside this area on the east, in the County of Essex, there is a very densely populated tract which includes East Ham and West Ham, Canning Town, Plaistow, Forest Gate, IlfOrd, Leyton, Leytonstone, Lea Bridge Road, Walthamstow, and to the north, in the County of Middlesex, St. Ann&apos;s Road, Edmonton, Tottenham, Hornsey, Wood Green, etc.   Conditions there are much the same as in the Administrative County, and arrangement for dealing with the result of air raids have to be on a similar scale.    To&apos; the west and south the agglomerations of houses are fewer and the density of population less.    The arrangements which have been made and which are working satisfactorily may be briefly set out.The whole district is divided into Police Station areas, ofst        which there are about 200.    Each of these can assemble its own&apos;sonnel organisation of persons competent to render First Aid, and abulan-wheeled and hand litters for the conveyance of casualties, and at most of them motor vehioles are also available, v Divisional Stations, of which there are 21, have been eroupedrtaid   and at a certain number of them so selected as to be central for es     the purpose, Air Raid Relief parties assemble with personnel for
HospitalsTimely notice needed to secure assemblingfirst aid, motor ambulances, etc., which can be indented on by adjoining stations if they need assistance in dealing with J casualties. This is further supplemented by a central reserve at New Scotland Yard constituted on the same lines.The necessary arrangements have been made with all hospit receiving casualties, so that there may be a satisfactory dist bution of cases, and with the Royal Society of Medicine for tfc supply of additional surgeons if needed.This considerable agency is unpaid and can be assembled t full strength if sufficient notice is given. In practice it e be said that we need time to get together the full personnel aofpersonnel.   witn less time the assembling is partial only.   But hitherto ij has always proved adequate for dealing with the situation.Police I wish to point out that no reserve of regular Police exijRegular andSpecial. at Police Stations. When it is necessary to have a considerall number of men for any particular emergency the time of which be foreseen, this is provided for by suspending the weekly lei which, with the Force at full strength, would yield 3,000 men the occasion of these Air Raids, which cannot be foreseen, tfc: reserve is not available and such arrangements as may be pose: for collecting the men off duty have to be relied on. In pea&apos; time we had in section houses some 5,000 single men, some of could always be found there. Most of these men have been draj to the Army, Navy or Dockyards, so thiB source of help has di appeared.The Special Constabulary, of whom we have 20,000, are me who in the day time are occupied in earning their living and are able to give only a certain portion of their leisure time to police work.   They have to be called up from their homes * there is a sudden emergency and this of course requires soms
little time.    Unless therefore we get at least from 2Q minutes to 30 minutes notice and there is no interruption of railway,, tram and omnibus services, we cannot get toL t.;.. the personnel of the First Aid parties, Air Raid Relief parties or Police regular and special, in sufficient number to be of effeotive use and we need twice as much time to assemble them in full strength.If an Air Raid were to take place without any warn-ing we should find ourselves without personnel to deal with the consequences.     But this is an improbable&apos;contingency and I refer to it only to make good the point that timely notice is needed to ensure the functioning, of our machineryThe Local Authorities have been requested formally, by letter on three different dates, to keep available a small emergency corps of workmen with the necessary appli-ances and material for exploring the debris when houses are partially demolished and persons buried in the ruins.   Many have made this provision, which has been supplemented by the creation of an Engineer Section under the London Command, whose services are available and can be and have been requisitioned.Lord Cowdray has called attention to the very dis-turbing effect upon the minds of the tens of thousands of persons who after a raid come to view the localities damaged by bombs, when they are permitted to see in their nakedness the gutted houses with their contents strewed about the ruins.     These spectators doubtless on reaching :iome do- not minimise the horror of what they have witnessed in talking to neighbours.     The general effect is that alarm and a tendency to panic are unnecessarily engendered.
It is proposed, if the suggestion is approved, torequire the Local Authorities to forthwith place hoardings^up to a height of 12 feet to screen from the street thedamage done.     Half-inch hoards would be sufficient andhome grown and unseasoned timber could be employed, andif this work   were thus decentralised, the burden placedupon any single local authority would not he too heavy.The Timber Controller would doubtless assist.Measures for In connection with these raids the possibility ofdealing withfires. fires breaking out almost simultaneously in more thanone locality cannot be ignored.     The arrangements made for dealing with outbreaks of fire are as follow.To render the Fire Brigades of the Metropolitan area more effective they have been brigaded under the Chief of the London County Council Fire Brigade, who is now in a position so to dispose of their pooled resources that fires occurring in any part of the area oan be promptl and effectively dealt with.Along the river hank there are great Oil Storage Depots..     If the reservoirs there were struck, the con-tents might escape as a burning flood on to adjoining ground or into the river to the danger of shipping. Powers have been   taken to regulate such depots and con-taining walls have now been raised round all such Reservoirs, 30 that if their oontents were set alight they would burn in situ within the limits of the ,contain-ing walls.Powers have heen also taken to regulate the storage of celluloid,Dissemination The Police are dependent for warning upon theof public -warning. Military.     The first warning they get is &quot;Readiness&quot;       9by day, &quot;Field Marshall Warning&quot; by night, which, is anintimation
intimation that hostile aircraft are approaching or havereached the coast or ar.3. known to be over the land.This warning is treated confidentially and is issued onlyto put the superior   officers of Police on the alert sothat they may have some messengers available to call upthe Constabulary and also the air raid relief parties.The next message received is &quot;Field Marshal&apos;sOrder - Take Air Raid Action&quot; on receipt of which stepsare taken to mobilise the whole, personnel, the membersof which on receiving the summons proceed to theirallotted stations.     This warning is not intended forthe public whom, however, it reaches through variouschannels.     This would be followed by the &quot;Take Cover&quot;message which is at once communicated to the public inthe day time by the discharge of sound signals fromselected centres;   at night by the circulation throughthe streets of Illuminated fascias with the inscription&quot;Take Cover&quot;.     These are carried by motor cars, motorcycles and also by the constabulary, regular and special,on foot and pedal cycles.     They call attention to theirpassage through the streets by ringing their cycle bells,blowing their whistles and calling out.     Those in motorvehicles sound their horns or a bell provided for thethepurpose. This method of publishing/warning is becoming quite effective.When the Military consider that the raiders are on their way home the message &quot;All Clear&quot; is given to the Police and by them to the   public by the same Agency as the &quot;Take Cover&quot;, with this difference that bugles will be used in communicating the &quot;All Clear&quot; to discriminate it from the &quot;Take Cover&quot; .     The Mayors in conference have greatly approved this modification in detail and we are now endeavouring to secure the service of 450 Buglers to give effect to it.
The whole district as divided into Police Station areas has been surveyed by the Police with a view to securing all the air raid shelter accommodation that is available.In many parts, even in working class neighbourhoods the proportion of shelter to population is quite adequate but in others, mostly occupied by working class people who live in small flimsily built houses of one or at the most two-storeys, with few if any railway arches or public buildings of solidity, there is not only an in-adequate amount of shelter but real difficulty in aug-menting it.The problem is one for which a solution has to be found and as a preliminary step it is proposed to obtain powers to compel any person owning or controlling pre-mises which would be suitable as Air Raid Shelters to make them available for public use.Where the problem cannot be solved in this way, it is hoped that existing buildings may be strengthened in various ways so as to render them suitable for shelter purposes.The Institute of Surveyors are appointing a Committ of six of their members, men eminent in their profession, as an Advisory Committee to the Commissioner of Police, who will inspect all the buildings now registered as shelters and report upon their suitability and will further, having been given the necessary power of entry by the Regulation above referred to, be able to enter premises not now available but which prima facie appear to be suitable and will after inspection report upon the accommodation they contain.It is thought that the creation of this Advisory Committee, who will set about their enquiry Immediately, will ^ive much satisfaction to the public.Without
Without going into details I may say that the amount of shelter now available provides for nearly a million people and that the various premises which provide this accomodation exhibit on the issue of the &quot;Take Cover&quot; warning a placard with the printed inscription&quot; &quot;Air Raid Shelter&quot; which Is obtainable at all Police Stations.On the occasion of an air raid Police, regular and special, are sent to regulate the admission of the crov/ds who seek refuge in the better known shelters, so that no disorder may occur there or casualties result from over-crowding.Palaces. In this connection I desire to call attention to theinsecurity of the two principal Royal Palaces.It is a source of grave anxiety to me that none of the rooms in the Wing of Buckingham Palace personally occupied by  heir Ma je sties are adequately secured not only against damage but against actual demolition by a well-directed bomb from an aeroplane.     At present there is only one storey between Their MajestiesT apartments and the roof, and this floor and the roof are constructed of old and inflammable timber.The structure erected on the roof some little time back was calculated to ,give protection against&apos; our own shell fire and incendiary bombs as distinguished from high explosive bombs.     It is of little value afainst bombs of the character lately dropped on London.     Moreover parallel with the North-facing windows of Their Majesties rooms there runs a broad balcony with concrete platform upon which a bomb would probably detonate, causing com-plete devastation in rooms immediately adjacent.Marlborough House, where Queen Alexandra is residing, is equally insecure.Plans
Plans have been prepared for a scheme which would give very.substantial protection in both instances, and I have already made a submission to His Majesty and Queli Alexandra on the subject, but without success.     I may add that the protection to be givon would not be apparent from outside and would inconvenience Their Majesties only to the extent of requiring the evacuation of a very few rooms..*        16.10.17.

</content>
</cab>
