<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/29/0 images: 70-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
No.545/21,GCopy No,. 12S&apos;&apos; E ORE T.Chief of the Imperial General Staff, War Office, London,   S, W.I enclose a Summary of information concerning the allied forces on this front for the month of September, together v/ith a sketch map showing approximate dispositions of all troops in this theatre.(sgd) Geo, F, Milne,G.H.Q.Salonika.8th October, 1917.Li eutenant-General, Commanding-in-Chief,&apos; British Salonika Force.
SUMMARY of OPERATIONS for SEPTEMBER,1917 *No. 545/21.G.   pqo 6British Force,During the past month patrol actions and small raids-have been frequent.     On the 12th Corps front harassing fire-and destructive bembardments have been carried out almost/daily by the heavy artillery.     The formation of a R.A, Headquarters for Counter Battery work promises to add materially to the effectiveness of these bombardments.     On the more open 16th Corps front, cavalry and infantry patrol encounters occur daily, and many ambushes have been laid with varying success,yy r-&apos;.-7*. y &quot;.,- y   yy        \.r y, yy.  X jiji: yy .-,,v   - - - -^y &apos;-yy- y^ \ y -      -fiy yy .:*&quot;-  : - . - &apos;.st-:;&apos;      &apos;!/        :S-       .&apos;y :y   y&apos;- y.The enemy1 s patrols have shewn themselves somewhat more-active.     On one occasion they attempted a raid in some strength against our position near the old DOVA TEPE forts, and wore repulsed only after a sharp hand to hand encounter. On this occasion the Bulgars attacked according to their latest methods as taught in the &quot;storming schools&quot; and were equipped with German pattern steel helmets, rifle and bayonet, pistols, daggers, and a very superior pattern of wirecutter. It was satisfactory to note that our troops proved themselves very much superior with the bayonet.The relief of the 10th Division was completed about the middle ef the month, and their embarkation proceeded smoothly. They have now all left.Aviation.Raids carried out by our aeroplanes have been frequent and very successful and have caused considerable damage to/enemy
enomy oamps, dumps and. gun positions.     On many occasions also our pilots have &quot;been able to descend to low altitudes and engage with machine guns parties of hostile troops.Go-operation &quot;between the Royal Flying Corps and the artillery in the above mentioned destructive bombardments has been good.Other Forces.On September 8th, the French began an offensive operation between Lakes MALIK end OHRLDA, with the object of securing their left flank and ensuring the safety of the KORICA - SANTI (JUABANIA road.This oporation met with complete success, the French advance being rapid and not heavily opposed, and on the 11th September thoy occupied the line UDUKIbTA - Hill 1704 - Hill 1057 - OSNAD -DESMIRAT - ERASIOSTI which they still hold.     About 400 prisoners, three mountain guns, and some machine guns wore captured during this operation.     On September 22nd, a small mixed column of French and Albanian troops operating from the above line made a very successful raid on GOLIX, bringing-b&amp;oJr 440 Austrian prisoners.On September 7th, the enemy attacked and captured some 200 metres of the Russian front line trenches between Lakes OHRIDA and PRESPA, and have since succeeded in maintaining their hold upon them, in spite of counter-attacks.Administration.The labour question remains acute, as always, on account of the constant work -which is required to maintain oommunicatjLons in this country.     I hove decided to organise the P.B. men into &quot;Employment Companies&quot; and the formation of these units is/being
\being carried out..     It is hoped that the 4,000 Turkish prisoners which are being sent from Egypt will arrive shortly-.The organisation of the Itea-Bralo- route is in hand.It is proposed to establish a Rest Camp at either end (l.,e,. Itea and Bralo) to accommodate 25 officers,, 10 nursing-sisters,, and l.,000 other ranks..    Troops going to and fro will be conveyed from Itea to Bralo and vice versa in seated lorries, which have been sent for that purpose..Owing to the fact that rolling stock is very limited on the Greek railways and the gradients very steep It is impracticable to convey daily more than 500 all ranks from Itea to Bralo and vice versa,.     This is the ruling factor as regards the accommodation provided at the Rest Camps.Wells have been sunk and all will be ready by 15th October, 1917..     Lorries have been provided specially for the conveyance of malls and it is understood that the first mail from England by this route will leave London on October 1st. Letters from this end were first despatched by thi/s route on the 27th September, 1917.*Health of Troops..Malaria has been more prevalent than in August, but in spite of this the general hralth has been distinctly better than last year, and the loss of efficiency from disease very appreciably less.The admissions of other ranks to hospitals and Casualty Clearing Stations for all diseases have been 13.5 % of strength against 17,5 % in September 1916.     The majority of Oasos are still recurrent malaria, and -dysentery and diarrhoea continue to be rare.Equipment, for the completion of the summer scheme of hospital .accommodation (26,246 beds) is now available in the/country.
country. There were 26,216 beds equipped in generaland stationary hospitals, at tho end of September, 2,310of those being reserve beds in use.G.H.Q., (Sd) Geo. F. Milne.Salonika.8th October,1917hicutenant-Gonoral,Commanding-in-Chicf. British Salonika Force.

</content>
</cab>
