<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/29/0 images: 116-118</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Bommml Is t^a^Fropertyjof^ Hid Britannic Majesty&apos;* Cov-f&quot;*v*ntl /5  QABD JOT, AfiRJJi^5^^.4^*Report; -for, yeeir.?i&amp;?jl J^th^Octob^r, ,1,9X7,&apos; StatIf tjxalJ3rttnch.Tabulation of the returns of produce of hay and corn is proceedings    the returns should he available in a fortnight.Returns of the produce of hops have been received and published.     The yield has been abundant, 13 cwts. per acre;   and although the acreage is 16,946 acres only (less than half that of 1914) the total yield is 220,719 cwts. or more than 2/3rds the production of 1916.The quantity of fish landed during September was 344.-000 cwts. the lowest of any September, and 60,000 cwts 3.ess than August,$ork has been done in preparation for a census of stocks of potatoes to be taken eaoh month for the Pood Controller;    also in preparation for a census of labour required on farms after the war.Small Holding,, Colonies,.At Patrington the building of cottages is proceeding, the position now is -4 pairs are occupied. 2 pairs are ready for occupation.; 4 pairs are nearly completed,. 5 pairs are roofed.Arrangements will be made in the spring for the erection of the remaining 8 pairs of cottages,,     The Conscientious Objectors, whose work has been very unsatisfactory, will be got rid of without delayaBeans are being drilled and the land prepared for wheat.Sundry repairs and work on the new road are also in progress.     86 men have been employed.Cottage building is also in progress at Hclbeach.     Rather more labour has been available, 37 men being now employed.     Vacant possession of this Estate- has now been obtained.Negotiations for the acquisition of a site for the Welsh Colony are in progress,FiSHSRjCE 8 JDI VISION.Administrative, Section.The means suggested for preventing flooding in the valleys of the Risers Avon and Stour, Hants, have been considered so far as they affect fish passes.further proposals are under consideration regarding the raising of Pcwick Weir in the River Teme in order to secure a reduction of coal in the generation of electrical energy for Worcester.,
* Arrangements are Toeing made for opening a part af StartBay to trawlers.Endeavour is being made to secure such concessions with regard to Insurance and Income Tax as will induce the Belgian fishing boats to use English instead of French ports as their base.Permits Section.50 permits have been issued far commercial and amateurfishing.Reports of the loss of two fishing vessels by submarine attack have been received and communicated to the Admiralty,Fishermen?? Registration and Recruitlng^ection, Fishermen and Naval Service.As a result of the representations of the Board   Captain Parker, RfNs agreed early in the week to grant a short postponement .... to Grimsby calls pending a decision on the situation.The President received on the 16th October a deputation of Grimsby trawler owners, whtu explained in detail the very serious shortage of men at their port, stating that further calls would inevitably result in laying up productive steam trawlers.     Captain Parker, who was present on this occasion, announced that, he had been able to make arrangements by which it was hoped, in virtue of the dilution of the crews of the minesweepers by seamen other than fishermen and by various other ways, to reduce the total remaining palls for Great Britain for the rest of the year to something like 200 men.     He also held out hopes that the Admiralty might agree to protect from call the skippers and engineers of vessels fishing under Admiralty supervision;   the owners on their part, while expressing grave doubts as to the existence of a suitable supply of untrained labour for the vessels, undertook to dilute, as far as possible, with any raw material which could be suggested to them.     They will be informed of the men enrolled in the Special Fishing Reserve by Captain Parker, and of various fishermen, probably, out of employment, by this Department,Captain Parker mentioned that he had received a despatch from the Mediterranean, to which area seamen other than fishermen had been drafted for minesweeping, expressing the opinion of the writer that fishermen were mere efficient than the men sent and requesting to be provided with fishermen in their place.Fishermen, Fish grade and Military Service.Repeated and   energetic representations have been made to the Ministry of National Service and the proper sections of the War Office in support of applications for the release of men for the East Coast herring fishery,     So far these representations have not been attended with success,     The Ministry of National Service has been advised that the fishery is of unusual abundance, but will V,probably be of short duration, and that to be effective any provision of labour must be immediate.
Fish Pood Section.An officer has &quot;been visiting Billingsgate with a view to putting pilchards on the fresh fish market,- and has submitted the names of five firms who will do their best to effect sales,     Similar arrangements are being made in country districts, and the fish will; be despatched by Cornish firms, any loss incurred to be borne by the Fish Food Grant..There being a great shortage of sacks for carrying wood turnings, the Army Contracts Department supplied 3,000 sacks, which: have been despatched to a firm at Tottenham, and it is hoped by this means to supply sufficient turnings.     They ares being sent daily to the Committee!s Agent on the east coast; the sacks should at the end of the season entail no loss to the Fish Food Committee.The work at Lowestoft and Yarmouth is so heavy that another officer has been appointed to assist at Yarmouth during the herring season,    A man has been appointed to carry out repairs to the fishing fleets at these ports, the local firms being over full of work.Motor Loan Section.Four more installations have been oompleted.The boats engaged in the herring fishery are still making very good catches.So pleased were two skippers on the south coast in whose boats the Committee have installed   &quot;Gleniffer engines that they each paid up  100 towards the cost.     One of them informed the Committee*s representative that in a months working since the completion of the installation he had earned  200.Freshwater FishSection.Y/ork has begun on the experimental eel trap at Sewley Pon&amp;, Beaulieu.In other Branches the business has proceeded on normal lines as indicated in previous reports.Secretary,19th October, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
