<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/29/0 images: 405-408</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Italy.To Sir William Robertson,War Office,    London.     24th October, 1917.469. 1I have forwarded to-day memorandum from Cadorna to you. He points out in it that his anticipations of an Austro-German offensive are coming true and confirms soundness of his decision, of September 18th, to renounce then any further Italian offensive. He states that present enemy offensive is being developed along the whole Isonzo front from Plezzo to the sea with a preponderate effort between the Plezzo basin and the Tolmino bridge-head,both included.   The enemy&apos;s principal objectives would be heads theof/valleys of the Matisone and Judrio in order to turn from the north the Italian defences on Julian front.     This morning the enemy&apos;s offensive began.   Cadorna points out that the 14th German army of nine divisions is on this front and that there are now 676 Austro-German battalions (equivalent to 900 Italian battalions) facing him to which he can oppose 844 only.    He points out Austrian divisions have more field artillery than the Italian divisions and that the enemy has now greatly increased heavy artillery including at least 100 German batteries.   Cadorna adds that he deplores the decision of the Allied higher commands to withdraw from Italy a great part of the artillery which was on the Italian (? front) at the end of August in spite of his request, that it might be left here, as in the actions which are about to take place there are at stake not only the fortunes of Italy, but also those cf the whole Entente.       He concludes by saying for his part he awaits the development of events with complete confidence and perfect serenity.
(This Document Is the Property &amp;fHis Britannic Majesty&apos;9 Covf rnment)S E?   p   T7   p   rp-ll    vj    ja   juj     x .eneral Delme Radcliffe, Italy.Operations..;:ieo^     c. ic. i. a. sWar Office.25.10.17.Handed in 4.45 a.m.490.Situation at midnight. 3rd Army front.     Austrians bombarded at intervals during daywind.and rain produced little effect.     There was no infantry attack and prisoners state that action on the Bainsizza Plateau and on the Carso.was to be demonstrative only.     An Austrian officer prisoner of Serbian nationality just captured on Carso told me this evening that it has been common talk amongst officers of his regiment during last four days that Mackensen is in command of Austro-German offensive against Italy and that he has ten German divisions under him, while BordeviCj  in command on the Carso, and Koevess, in the Trentino, are under his orders. 2nd Army front.     I have as yet no information as to what occurred on Bainsizza Plateau except that the bombardment all along the front seems to have been heavy.     However, on the left flank the 4th Army Corps seems to have been pushed back and all the Italian first line position on the left bank of the Isonzo above Tolmino appears to be in the enemy&apos;s hands;    enemy advanced in two main directions south and north of Monte Nero taking Monte Rosso Sleme Plezzo Vrsic Monte Mrzli and I believe Caporetto. Precise information is difficult to obtain and most of it was j derived from probably unreliable fugitives.     2nd Army command had lost touch with H.Q. 4th Army Corps.     I was informed that the Polovnik and Stol ridges are still in Italian hands.     Ridge on the right bank of the Isonzo between the Natisone River and the angle of the Isonzo is said to be still in Italian hands.     The27thvery heavily and at times with gas shell which however owing to
27th Corps south and west of Tolmino was said to be holding its positions well, whilst 7th Corps has been moved on to ridge to cover rear and left flank of 27th Corps.       28th and 14th Corps are also being moved up to cover this flank.     It appears enemy has been gradually concentrating during last month opposite Italian 4th Army Corps and unmasked a large number of batteries this morning the presence of which had not been suspected before.Owing to difficulty of removing it, Italians appear to have lost considerable part of their artillery posted about Monte Nero.     It is probable that Italians have lost large quantities of material and supplies and I saw large fires at several points to-night.       The enemy bombardment in the early morning on the front of 4th Army Corps was very severe and the gas shell caused much damage especially on the low ground, Italian masks being said to give very little protection. To-night fire is still heavy.     Although only one Italian Corps so far has been seriously affected, situation appears to be serious to-night.     Italian troops are in sufficient numerical strength to check the enemy if the difficult nature of the ground and the confusion admit of their strength being proper-ly applied.       It is now known that three German divisions are in front line near Tolmino,     Comando Supremo can, if necessary, bring four or five more divisions from other parts of the front to reinforce troops on the Isonzo.     Weather is clear and fine to-night.
His Britannic ^iajesty&apos;s Government)(Thi^ Document is. ins PropertyOperations.- - &apos;t i.....m.r --. .SEC R . E T..&apos; --^C&amp;P&amp;h&apos; 1* General Delme-^Radcllf f e, Italy %TO G.I.G.S., War Office.25.10.1917,492.       9 a,mV   25th.This morning Cadorna told me that, in his opinion, the situation is serious,   He says that Intrigues in the obuntry to undermine the loyalty of the people must have had their affect on the troops, who yesterday, in some cases., abandoned positions which they ought not to have lost,   He has now ordered counter-attack for the recovery of Monte Jeza, which was taken by the enemy last night.5rd Army would be entirely compromised if the enemy makes further1 progress from the north.   HO has ordered 2nd Army to withdrawfrom Bainsizza Plateau and has prepared orders for the retirementjof the whole army to the line of Tagliamento River, so that this withdrawal may be carried out with as little difficulty as possible-,iIn case it should become necessary.    He says that 4th Army Corps-may be considered as no longer existing.(map 1/100,000) was taken by the enemy last night and recovered by counter-attack this morning.     Monte Jeza still in enemy^ hands.Italians hold head of valley of the Natisone south of Creda, and they also hold the ridge on the right bank of the Isonzo from Monte Matajur as far.as Sagradan.     Thence line bends south.and passes over Monte Xum and Globocak to Ronzina.    , Further rein-forcements have been brought up to support troops holding thisline, who command approaches leading into- valleys of the Natis-one and Judrio rivers.He says that the position of the west of 2nd Army and ofThis&apos; morning I received information that the GlobocakItalian line now rests on the Polovnik ridge and, crossing, I over Stol ridge, passes west of Creda and rests on Monte Mia.

</content>
</cab>
