<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/29/0 images: 414-426</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r^^v-vrcfoRiA 8240. Hi$ BBOARD OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES.BOARD OF AFOOD PRODUCTION DEPARTMENT,72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. (1).24th October, 1917.Sir,I beg to submit the following Report on the work of theFood Production Department for the week ended 23rd October:-The feather.The weather reports from various parts of the countryreceived from the Departments District Commissioners, are depressing reading.     In a few districts there was less rain last week than during the preceding week, but in most counties the work of ploughing and cleaning the land was again seriously hampered.     This is the third wet autumn in succession, and the stubbles are, speaking generally, in a very dirty condition.   This untimely spell of wet weather may have a serious effect on the harvest next year, for should rain continue the area sown with autumn wheat must be reduced;   the land in many parts is at present too wet to permit of drilling wheat.Durham.     The Longnewton estate has been inspected by the Committee^ Executive Officer in conjunction with the agenfc of the owner, Lord Londonderry, in order to select grass land for ploughing up.     Lord Londonderry&apos;s agent strongly objected to the tenants offering to plough up only inferior grass land which would not yield good results as arable, and insisted on the better grass land being V-ploughed whenever this was likely to make good arable land.     One hundred and forty acres were selected for ploughing up on this estate.LOCAL ORGANISATION DIVISION.Work of Agricultural Executive Committees.
Essex.   The Committee are making arrangements to withdraw from possession of several farms upon whioh they had entered in the early part of the year, and on which they have grown croos this year, or which they have got into condition for proper cultivation for the 1918 crop.     In each case the withdrawal will be effected in favour of a new owner or tenant.Kent.   The Committee have arranged with the owner for the breaking up of 45 acres of grass land in Quex Park.Lincolnshire (Holland).   The Committee have been authorised to tave possession of a farm of 191 acres at Amber Hill which is stated to be very foul, and to have been badly managed by an idle tenant farmer.Lincolnshire (Kesteven), The Committee are issuing a general order to plough out all clover and grass seeds sown In 1915-16. Surrey.   The Committee have been authorised to ta-s possession and arrange for the cultivation of four acres of Broad Street Common in Worplesdon in addition to about seven acres of this large Common which are now being cultivated under arrangements made by the Committee.Sussex East.   The Committee, ^ho are already cultivating 393 acres of a building estate known as Peacehaven (Anz-ac^on-Seax, have now been authorised to take possession of 35 acres which they had allowed the building owner to.retain,     He has proved quite incapable of managing it and the land is very foul.     The Committee have also been authorised to take possession of 60 acres of land at Friar&apos;s Bay belonging to the same owner which is in a similar condition, and of 10 acres of uncropped land at Rottingdean for letting to allotment holders, as well as of a neglected farm of 85 acres at South Heighton 28 acres of which are entirely derelict. Flintshire.       The Committee at one time proposed to direct the Chester Gol  Club to plough up 72 acres of their course at Sealand. The land has been inspected by the Departments District Commissioner t-ho found that it could not be suitably cultivated without giving&quot;f 2-
rise to heavy claims for compensation.     An arrangement has been provisionally made by which cattle as well as sheep will be grazed on the links and the tenant of the grazing will plough up 40 extra acres in consideration of being able to graze his cattle on the course instead of on his own land;   the arrangement now awaits the agreement of the council of the club.Drainage of Lands.   The Bedfordshire Committee are taking action with regard to the Starston and Shillington Brooks, the Cumberland Committee with regard to the Rockcliff Beck and the Surrey Committee with regard to the River H&apos;ey.Breaches of the Defence of the Realm Regulations.   A farmer at Halesowen In Worcestershire has been fined  10 for failure to comply with a notice served upon him in July to cut and burn the weeds and other rubbish on 7 acres of his 60 acre farm.     The defence was lack of labour, and the defendant offered in Court to do the work In a fortnight:   but the weeds had already seeded.The Redruth Brewery Company in Cornwall have been prosecuted for failure to comply with notices served upon them on 23rd March and 1st May, 1917, respectively, directing them to plant a field owned by them with spring corn or potatoes for 1917.     The Company pleaded guilty and urged that their non-compliance was due to negligence, and that they had in respect of other lands been material contributors to the food supply.     They were fined 10 guineas.Damage by Game,   Action with regard to pheasants is reported from Derbyshire and East Suffolk, and with regard to rabbits from Cumberland, where the Committee have taken action with regard to rabbits on the Bishop of Carlisle&apos;s land at Rose Castle;   from Kesteven, where the destruction of a gorse has been ordered at Ingoldsby, and also from Herefordshire and the North Riding. Determination of Tenancies.   During the week 13 Orders have been made authorising landlords to determine tenancies&apos;on account of bad
farming in respect of 1,507 acres* and 3 Orders have been made by the Board determining the tenancies of 311 acres. Cultivation of Lands Order, 1917, (No.2).   Reports from 1,093 districts have now been received, showing that 199,571 applications were made for plots, and 130,636 plots have been provided under the Cultivation of Lands Order, 1917, (No.2).     The total area of the plots so provided is 13,282 acres.In February last the Board delegated powers under Regulation 2L to the Parish Council of Hornchurch.     The Council now report that 244 applicants were supplied with plots containing in the aggregate a little over 15 acres, and 53 of the plots have since been converted into permanent allotments by agreement with the landowner.     A further result of the Order Is that a. considerable area of other land previously lying idle has been put. into cultivation with a view to preventing the Council entering into possession under their powers,The Board&apos;s District Commissioner for North Fales states that the Carnarvonshire Education Committee recently reported that the total area of school gardens under cultivation in the county before the war was 22,000 square yards;    in the year 1915-16 the area increased to 31,420 square yards;   and in 1916-17 the area was 53,646 square yards.The Fidland and Great Northern Railways Joint Committee report that, following the Departments appeal, the Committee&apos;s spare lands were cultivated, with the result that about 350 tons of potatoes and 50 tons of other foodstuffs have been added to the nation&apos;s resources by the energy and co-operation of the Inspectors and platelayers employed by the Committee.     They actually dug 60 acres of land for which ploughs were not available,,
HORTICULTURAL DIVISION.v *68-demonstrations in fruit bottling and vegetable drying have been given during the week.     4 Home Canners and 64,608 three pound cans have been sold and demonstrations given daily at the offices of this Department.Small Canning Stations.     Arrangements have been made for Instal-ling small canning stations in association with the pulping stations already in occupation by the Department.     The purpose of the stations is to demonstrate the usefulness of the Rome Canner as a means of preserving considerable quantities of fruit, and for this purpose 6 Home Canners will be used simultaneously in each station.     Two stations at Cheltenham and Bridgwater are already at work.     They are being operated by instructors trained by the Department, with the assistance of local female labour. Fruit Pulping.     Pulping of damsons is still being carried on at Bewdley, Newport and Cambridge, and the apple pulping at Bridgwater, Marston Magna and Maidston^ the last named station being supplied with Somersetshire apples.Drying Stations.     Installations of drying stations at Pershore, Cheltenham and Formby are in progress.TECHNICAL DIVISION. Inspection of Land.    (1) An inspection has been made of Eaton Park in Rutland, at the request of the Agricultural Executive Committee.     The owner is not willing to plough up any of the park, which extends to 900 acres and Includes some 400 acres of dry free working soil quite suitable for cultivation.     At present this is producing practically nothing, being under extremely poor grass and overrun with rabbits and deer.     There are certain difficulties to be overcome, but after discussing these thoroughly with the agent, an area of about 250 acres was roughly marked out for plough-ing during the winter months.     The owner will probably offer no objection to this area being cultivated, though he is not willing to
e\ ^1 nundertake the work himself.     Another area of 150-200 acres is only slightly less suited for cultivation, and may be dealt with after the first one has been taken in hand, but owing to difficulties of obtaining fencing it seems likely to be left till next year sAn area of about 90 acres in the same ownership and adjoining the park was also examined.     It had been down in grass for at least 20 years.     About half had been let to an adjoining tenant and this had already been ploughed by the Departments tractors, which had done---good work.     The remainder was being kept in hand and about half was being ploughed by a privately owned Mogul tractor with a three-furrow Howard plough.     This was doing remarkably good work, the furrows being as straight and well laid as anything which could be done by horses *     The secret evidently lay in the selection of the ploughman, who is well known as one of the best ploughmen in the county,,        ,The present intention of the occupiers of the newly-ploughed land is to sow.the whole with spring oats, but as the lard was in first-rate condition for sowing, it was suggested that half should be sown down with wheat at once.   The Committee will endeavour to persuade the tenant to take this course,(2)   A visit has been paid tcstwo estates in Essex, comprising about 600 acres, which during the past 20 years or so have been allowed to go out of cultivation in favour of game.When the Agricultural Executive Committee took action some-months ago, most, of the fields were much overgrown with thorns, scrub and small self-sown trees.     Several fields b.s.ve been cleared, partly by traction engines and partly by mattocks in the hands of German prisoners, and the problem that has now arisen is how best*to restore the land to its former usefulness.     Mole-draining and slagging will convert some of the fields into useful pastures: others, in addition to mole-draining will have to undergo a course of cropping.     For 1918 the alternatives appear to be potatoes or summer fallowing followed by winter corn,fry.;;:.C-i       ..... i - i. i
Basic Slag.    An enquiry .ia &quot;being made into the agricultural value of the low grade basic slags which have aocumulated In the neighbourhood of steel works, but have net hitherto keen used;   the; evidence indicates that these slags are worth using under present conditions.   At the same time wider scope is being given to the enquiry.    It seems that certain changes now in progress in the steel making industry,, will tend to diminish the output of the rich basic slags to which agriculturists have become aoeustomed, containing 40$&apos; of phosphate, most of which is soluble in citric acidj and instead to produce a much lower grade slag containing only 20 - o0% Of phosphate, only part of which is soluble in citric acid.   As this change would be considerably to the disadvantage of the farmerj serious consideration is being given to methods by which its effects might be mitigated. Nitre^cake sulphate of ammonia.   An experimental enquiry has just been concluded into the agricultural effects of replacing some of the sulphuric acid used in the manufacture of sulphate of ammonia by nitre-cake.   The material investigated had had 20% of its sulphuric acid replaced by nitre-cake, and contained only 20% of ammonia instead of the usual 24-g ,    The resulting fertiliser is in fully as good condition as the best samples of commercial sulphate of ammonia:    it is dry, powdery and keeps well,   &quot;Then applied to crops it gave precisely the same returns as ordinary sulphate of ammonia containing the same amount of nitrogen. Further, when mixed with superphosphate and left for several months it showed no tendency to cake.    It can therefore be regarded as equal in all respects to ordinary sulphate of ammonia, and if the difficulties inherent in its manufacture can be overcome the farmer will not suffer by having it, while the advantage to the country will be considerable.Potash in wool.   An enquiry is being made into the amount of potash in certain unwashed wools.    It is well known that wool
a i 0contains a certain amount of pttash which is washed out during the scouring processes preliminary to spinning.   There is no means of ascertaining precisely how much potash is lost to the country In this way, owing to the paucity of analytical data, but it must be considerable.   A number of analyses are therefore being made of ,the amounts of pitash present in typical wools which are being supplied by ah important firm in the West Riding of Yorkshire. Effeat of cyanides and sulphocyanldes on plant growth.   In view of the circumstance that flue dust, the new potassic fertiliser, is liable to contain cyanides and sulphocyanides, an experimental enquiry is being undertaken to ascertain the effects of these substanoes on germination and early seedling growth.LABOUR DIVISION.Supply of Horses in charge of Ploughmen -   The Departments scheme for the supply of horses in charge of ploughmen to assist farmers to bring additional land under cultivation came under review during the week, and it has been decided that, in order to get this scheme properly taken up and organised, it will be necessary to appoint an officer In each County who will be able to devote his whole time to this work.   His duties will be mainly to organise the gang system, i.e. the system by which horses and men are stationed by the Committees in central villages and let out daily to the neighbouring farmers.   In addition he will inspect the horses let out to farmers for periods of one month or longer, and see that they are being properly cared for.   The experience of the scheme so far gained shews that such an appointment in each County is essential in order to get more horses rapidly taken up, and for the maintenance of the horses in good condition.   Gangs must also be organised in each District or farmers will experience difficulty in ploughing up the additional area of arable land required. Treasury sanction in the matter is being sought. Soldier Labour -   The weekly returns received from Commandants of
*1 r*Distribution centre&apos;s are not quite complete, but they she?/ that 11,549 &quot;so-called&quot; skilled and 13,652 unskilled men for the 1918 programme are attached to the Depots.     Of these 9,865 of the skilled men and 11,190 of the Unskilled ar^e out on farms.     At several of the Centres the demands of the Executive Committees for men have not been met, and the ii.rar Office have been asked to make further men available at once.The number of men sent out for training as tractor drivers and ploughmen is 991, and in addition 169 men have been supplied for work with steam ploughing or threshing tackle. Horses - Orders for the issue of 165 horses have been sent out during the ?/eek, making a total of 2,970 horses to date. Prisoners of War - Two new schemes for the employment of batches of prisoners of war have been sent to the War Office during the week.Agricultural Workers and Aerodromes - In connection with the paragraph in last week&apos;s report as to agricultural workers being taken on by contractors engaged in tho construction of new aerodromes, the Director of Fortifications and Works states that he is unable to issue instructions that agricultural workers should not be taken on, but at the same time the contractors are doing their best not to displace agricultural labour.     This reply cannot be considered a satisfactory one, in view of the enquiries made into certain individual cases brought to the Department&apos;s notice.Women&apos;s Branch. The number of women accounted for as members of the Land Army is 6,633, as follows:-In Instruction Centres.........     698On Farm Work        .........     ... 5,734Waiting for references and to beplaced in Training   Centres...     ...       48Waiting for employment in Depots     ... .    47Waiting in their own homes     ......     108
The Inspector for Staffordshire records satisfaction with the progress of the rcork in that County.     a good class of recruit is enrolling for land work, and there is never the slightest difficulty in placing them;   there are now ten vacancies which cannot be filled.It is reported from Pembroke that the Group Leader there has achieved excellent results;   she has formed gangs in villages where few women have worked before;   she has helped the farmers during the hay and corn harvest, and is now helping them with threshing and potato lifting.     More work such as this could be accomplished if a sufficient number of equally competent leaders were forthcoming.MECHANICAL CULTIVATION DIVISION.The following statement shows the position as regards theprovision of tractors purchased or ordered by the DepartmentConsigned to Agricultural Executive Committees up to and including13th October     .........................    1,496Additional tractors consigned duringthe week   .......................        85On offer to counties....................       100Consigned to Scotland (92) andIreland (45).................,........       137Available for forward allocation (approx).        251,841SUPPLIES DIVISION. Approved Agents.   During the past week 11 counties have been visited by Inspectors from the Department with satisfactory results as to the appointment of Approved Agents.     There are still some 18 counties from whom final lists of Approved Agents havo not yet been received, but all of these, with the possible exception of Westmorland, are now preparing lists.
9 0 1The number of Approved Agents appointed to date is 506 and the storage provided by them is 14,000 tons.     Satisfactory replies to the circular of October 4th, enquiring as to the quantity of Sulphate of Ammonia in store, have been received from a large number of Approved Agents, though in several cases difficulty has been experienced by Agents in obtaining the quantity which they had undertaken to store.Basic Slag,     Although most of the basic slag makers have fully sold their normal production, an arrangement has just been made -whereby an additional 50 tons a week of 20% slag have now been made available and will be sold through Approved Agents.     Other negotiations in the same direction are proceeding. Lime.     A very promising supply of waste carbonate of lime from a munition factory has been cut off during the v/eek owing to a change in the method of manufacture, and there seems little prospect of increased quantities being obtained from similar sources. Fortunately, however, the output by lime makers is generally about 50/o greater than last year, and the unfulfilled orders in the hands of makers are not exceptionally large.     The contract for the production of ground carbonate of lime at Stoneycombe in Devonshire, with machinery provided by the Department, has now been signed, and it is hoped supplies will be available early in the New Year.Potash.     Negotiations are proceeding with three firms who will act as wholesale sellers of blast furnace flue dust on terms approved by the Department.     It has been proposed to the firms to pool the output at their disposal and to establish an approximate equalised carriage rate.     It is hoped to issue full particulars to farmers within the next fortnight.
o o *Binder Twine.   The arrangements with the makers, are now practically complete and it is proposed to issue a notice to farmers urging them to place their orders at once.   The price arranged is 115/- per cwt.   This is a substantial incfease over last year, but this is due to heavy cost of importing the hemp from which the twine is made.Seed Wheat - Arrangements are being made for the disposal of the remaining stocks of the 1916 wheat.   The demand for seed has declined but millers are willing in most cases to give satisfactory prices for these parcels.Sales of seed wheat of the 1917 crop amount to 1,362quarters.Seed Potatoes - The Seed Potatoes Order has not yet been issued, and the inconvenience caused to the Trade is being keenly felt.The Departments scheme for the distribution of seed potatoes through Agricultural Executive Committees is now ready for issue, and-Committees have been requested to forward their orders not later than the 15th December.   The scheme provides both for the distribution of seed potatoes by the Committee direct or through &quot;approved seed potato dealers&quot; in each County.Purchases   of English supplies of immune &apos;seedr havenow reached the following figures:-King George V. ... 1,072 tonsGreat Scot ... l,722j   &quot;Lochar       ... ... 147     &quot;Templar     ... ... 183j-   &quot;5,124fThe latest advice from Scotland is even more favourable in regard to the quantity of the Seed1 of these four varieties available than was reported previously.   It is estimated that the Department may be able to obtain 6,000 tons from that source. Arrangements are being made to secure stocks of ordinary &apos;seed&apos; both in Scotland and Ireland.
0 OUnder the Immune Varieties Order, licences have been issued for the release for consumption of 12,584j tons of potatoes/ and when purchases of &quot;seed&apos; are completed, it is proposed to approach the Ministry of Food with a view to securing a general licence for the use of these varieties for consumption^ while retaining the prohibition in regard to the sale of 5seed&apos; which will then be sold only under licence.I am,Sir,Your obedient Servant,Director-General.It. Hon. Rowland E. Prother0, M.P. President of the Board of Agricultureand Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
