<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/32 images: 306-319</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
frinted for the War Cabinet.  May 1940.SECRET. Copy No. 43W.M. (40)137th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 137 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, May 24, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,M.P., Lord President of the Council. Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax, The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Secretary   of   State   for   Foreign Minister without Portfolio.Affairs.The following were also present:The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Major-General A. E. Percival,Assistant Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (Items 1 and 2).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Group Captain W. Elliot.Mr. L. F. Burgis.Mr. G. N. Flemming.Mr. E. P. Donaldson.[21336]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
WAR CABINET 137 (40).MinuteSo.134569101112Contents.Subject.The Western Front    ...       ...       ...Progress of operations.Co-ordination of command in North France and Belgium.Information for the public.The Western Front (contd.) .........Air operations.Bomber Command.Fighter Command.Page239241ce.K.F.Force.Advanced Air Striking ForAir Component of the B.&quot;Awards for the Royal AirRoyal Air Force resourcesThe Naval Situation   ...U-boat activity.Norway ...Progress of operations.The King of the BelgiansItaly     ...      ......Possible plan for blocking the Suez Canal.Italy     .........French proposal for another approach by President Roosevelt to signor Mussolini.United States of AmericaProposed reply by the Prime Minister to an American enquireiInvasion of Great BritainInformation from Rome.Communication Centres       ...Alleged sabotage plans.Invasion of Great BritainSecurity measures:   control of aliens.Invasion of Great BritainSecurity measures:  arming of the police.242242242243243243244244245247
The Prime Minister suggested that the 3-7-inchNaval guns, which had proved so useful at Andalsnes,might come in useful again, and that steps should betaken to have them in readiness.Dunkirk.(5) Considerable numbers of French troops were in Dunkirk;but no English troops had as yet been sent there, withthe exception of certain small units sent back to this area from the B.E.F. The port was functioning quitewell. One supply ship had been unloaded on the previous day. An ammunition ship was due to arrive therethat day.(6) The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that he waswaiting to receive a report from General McNaughtenon his return from Dunkirk, in order to decide whether-to send the Canadians to that place. It was possible thatDunkirk already contained as mairy troops as it could hold.Report by Sir R. Keyes.(7) The Prime Minister said he had that morning spoken toSir Roger Keyes, who had reported that two french divisions under General Fagaldes including the division which had been at Walcheren were now on the left of the Belgians. The Belgians had endeavoured to21336] b 2The Western 1.   The War Cabinet was given the following information onFront. the position : Progress of operations.        Boulogne.(Previous (1) The Prime Minister said that Boulogne had been evacuatedReference: on the previous night.   1,000 men had been got away,W.M. (40) 136th but 200 had been left behind.Conclusions.) (2) Our destroyers taking part in the operations at Boulognethe previous day had suffered a certain amount of damage from bombing, and machine-gun and battery fire. Theyhad been fired at by some twenty German field-guns north of the harbour. The destroyers had replied, and believedthey had succeeded in putting seven of these guns outof action.Calais.(3) We had the following troops in Calais : 1 Tank Regiment, including cruiser and light tanks;2 Rifle Battalions, the majority of whose equipment had now been landed; and1 Battalion of Queen Victoria Rifles.These were holding a position through the town,which was being shelled. The tanks had had an engage-ment with German tanks on the previous afternoonwhich had resulted in a stalemate. Their instructions had been to try to clear the forward roads, but this theyhad been unable to do, and in consequence the food convoy from Calais had failed to get through to St. Omer.(4) As regards the Naval 12-pounder guns which were being prepared for use at Calais, the First Lord of theAdmiralty said that mountings were being improvised,and that all possible steps were being taken to accelerate the necessary work. It was hoped to have six of the gunsready by the following afternoon, i.e., they might reachCalais in the evening.
persuade these Divisions to go down and occupy theGravelines line, but, on hearing that the German tanks were in the vicinity, the French had turned back.Sir Roger Keyes had said that communications wereop311 between Ostend and the British ExpeditionaryForce, and that it would be perfectly feasible to sendsupplies along this route.Supply Position.(8) The Secretary of State for War read a telegram from lord Gort as to the supply position.The Secretary of State added that the Quarter-master-General had received reports from Dunkirkindicating that the supply situation was a little betterthan that described by Lord Gort. It might be, there-fore, that supplies were already on their way to theB.E.F. about which Lord Gort had been in ignoranceat the time when he had sent his message.(Previous Blocking of Zeebrugge and Ostend : Operation Lyster.Reference: (9) The First Sea Lord said that the blocking of Zeebrugge,W.M. (40) 135th but not of Ostend, would take place that evening.Conclusions,Minute l.)        German Movements.(10) Air reports indicated that there had been a definite haltthat morning in the movement of the German armoured divisions. This might be due to lack of petrol or tothe need for repairs, as otherwise there was no reason why these forces should not push on Northwards throughCassel.Visit of General Bill to B.E.F.(11) Sir Roger Keyes had asked that General Dill should goat once to General Gort&apos;s headquarters. It was agreedthat this should be done.(Later in the meeting the Prime Minister sawGeneral Dill before his departure.)Co-ordination of        The Prime Minister said that he had been considering whetherCommand in it would not be advisable to suggest to General Weygand thatNorth Prance General Dill might be appointed to co-ordinate the British, Frenchand Belgium. and Belgian operations in the North of France.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that it might beas well to await further developments before making such aproposal. General Georges had complete confidence in general blanchard, but if it was found that General Blanchard was unequalto the task, we might then make a protest. One of the difficultiesin appointing an English General as a co-coordinator was that,although British troops would work under anybody, the Frenchalways worked best under a French General.The War Cabinet agreed to await the report of General Dill,before pursuing this suggestion further.Information for The Minister of Information said that he was being asked bythe public. the French Minister of Information to see that no public mentionwas made of any of the places reached by German troops, on theground that many of these detached units were unable tocommunicate with the German High Command. The minister thought that he must comply with this request, and suggested theissue of a statement explaining why information was beingwithheld.
The western front (con-tinued).Air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 135thConclusions,Minute 1.)bomber command.fighter command.2. The Chief of the Air Staff said that at 6 p.m. the previous day 3 Blenheims had attacked a Fort at Boulogne, which was saidto have been entered by an enemy tank. No tank had been seen,but as a result of the bombing dust had been seen rising from the fort. During this operation our aircraft had been heavily firedat by English destroyers, and it was feared that 2 Hurricanes andone Blenheim had been shot down.During the day there had been 28 sorties and 3 of our aircraft were missing.During the previous night a heavy bomber force had carriedout 122 sorties. One of our aircraft was known to have crashed onreturn, and 3 were still missing.Troops and communications had been attacked at a number of key points and hits obtained on the marshalling yard at Givet. Therailway junction at Beaumont had been hit and set on fire.A successful attack had been made on a column of 200 largelorries near Givet and a column of troops and motor transport onthe Doullens-Arras road. These attacks had been carried out by46 Wellingtons.Twenty-three Whitleys had attacked communications atAvegnes, Maubeuge, Beriaimont, Bavai and La Capelle. They had obtained hits on cross-roads north of the Maubeuge railway junction at Beriaimont, and on another railway line.Forty-six Hampdens had attacked communications atEmmerich, Coblenz, Cologne and elsewhere. Hits had been obtained on a railway station, and a bridge at Deldrop had been seriously damaged. Heavy traffic had been reported on canals and alsonumerous road columns in the area Maastricht-Roermond-Turnhout-Di est-Hasselt.At 10 - 30 a.m. that morning 24 Blenheims had left to attackenemy columns in the Arras area and in the Foret de Boulogne.Enemy activity off our coasts had been reduced the previous day. During the previous night some 6 aircraft had been detectedin the Dunkerque-Dieppe areas.During the previous day 29 patrols of an average strength of12 aircraft had been operating in the Boulogne-Calais-Dunkerquearea. Virtually continuous protection had been afforded throughoutthe day. In addition, other fighter squadrons had accompaniedbomber squadrons to the same area, and one squadron had escorted9 civil transport aircraft carrying rations to Merville. this squadron had shot down 2 Me. 109s. One of our fighters had beendisabled, but the pilot had escaped.In discussion, it was agreed that it would be necessary tocomply with this request in general, but that the grounds for the withholding of information should be stated to be military necessityrather than any special request of the French High Command.The Minister of Information then said that it was obviousthat the German High Command must be aware that they had takenBoulogne. Air reconnaissance alone would make this clear to them.From the point of view of public morale he thought that it wasobjectionable to withhold news of the loss of Boulogne.The War Cabinet :-(i) Took note of the above statement.(ii) Agreed that as a general rule no public mention shouldbe made of places reached by German troops, and thatthis course should be justified on the ground of military necessity.(iii) Agreed that this rule would not justify withholding the news of the occupation by German forces of Boulogne.
At about 6 p.m. on the previous evening a Spitfire squadron hadencountered near Boulogne 60 to 80 enemy aircraft, includingMe. 110, Ju. 88, Ju. 87 and Do. 18. A heavy fight had ensued. our total casualties had been the loss of 3 Spitfires, and another hadcrashed on landing, as against 12 enemy machines confirmed, and14 others probably shot down. The provisional figures of total enemy losses in the fighting during the previous day with our fighter squadrons were 23 shot down for certain and 26 probable.Advanced Air The Advanced Air Striking Force had attacked columns andStriking Force,   troops on the roads the previous day and had lost no machines.Air Component The Air Component of the B.E.F. working from England had of the B.B.F.     lost one machine.Awards for the The Chief of the Air Staff, in reply to a question by the PrimeRoyal Air Force. Minister, said that steps were being taken to issue an immediatelist of awards for distinguished service by the Royal Air force during the present operations.Royal An- Force        In answer to a question by the Prime Minister, the Chief of resources. fjie ^?;r Staff said that the resources of the Royal Air Force werebeing heavily strained as a result of the present operations, and theCommander-in-Chief of the Fighter Command was concerned aboutthe position.Hurricanes were delivered from the factories at the rate ofabout forty a week. These machines went to the Air Storage Units.Delivery of Hurricanes from these units was being received insatisfactory numbers at the present time.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The Naval 3.   The Chief of the Naval Staff said that U-boats wereSituation. reported to be operating south of the latitude of Cromer.   Two, on-boat activity, perhaps three, were also in the Western Approaches, and one off(Previous the south-west coast of Norway.Reference: The War Cabinet took note of this statement.W.M. (40) 135thConclusions,Minute 2.)Norway.Progress of operations.(previous reference:. . ( ) 34th that afternoon, and report again to the War Cabinet.   It wouldMhmte^^T&apos;      always be possible to recall H.M.S. Glorious if it was decided to&apos; retain the Hurricanes in this country.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.4. The First Sea Lord said that H.M.S. Glorious, with a squadron of Hurricanes on board, was leaving that day for Narvik.Some doubt was expressed as to whether it was desirable tosend these Hurricanes to Norway in present circumstances.The Prime Minister said that he would examine the question the King of the 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed the belgians. War Cabinet of a message which he had received from the Belgian(Previous Minister as to the movements of the King of the Belgians.Reference: A record of the discussion, and of the Conclusions reached, revise.M. (40) 133rd contained in  the  Secretary&apos;s  Standard  File of  War  cabinet conclusions, Conclusions.Minute 2.)
1 55JL t? v&apos;for anotherapproach byPresidentRoosevelt to signor mussolini.&quot;X&apos;Italy. 7.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionFrench proposal to telegram No. 262 DIPP, dated the 23rd May, from His Majesty&apos;ambassador, Paris, setting out a suggestion by the French Govern-ment that President Roosevelt should be asked to make anotherapproach to Signor Mussolini : &quot; Their idea is to get President Roosevelt to ask signor mussolini what his reasons are for being on the brink of entering the war against the Allies. If Signor Mussolini recitedhis grievances, the United States Ambassador in Rome wouldthen say that the President would be prepared to communicate the Italian claims to the Allied Governments or some other words which would at least have a delaying action.&quot;We had to give our views on this proposal, and, though he didnot think that much would come of it, the Foreign Secretarysuggested that we should reply that we fully endorsed the suggestion of another approach by President Roosevelt, and had no objectionto the line suggested at &quot;X&quot; above, provided it was quite clearthat President Roosevelt were acting on his own responsibility.We might suggest at the same time that it would be useful ifPresident Roosevelt could convey to Signor Mussolini the sense of the last two paragraphs of the statement which the PrimeMinister had proposed to make and had then cancelled; viz., thatthe Allies were ready to consider reasonable Italian claims at theend of the war, and would welcome Italy at a Peace Conference on equal teirns with the belligerents, and that the United States were willing to guarantee that the Allies should carry out these under-takings so long as Italy and the United States of America did not become engaged in the war on opposite sides.The War Cabinet agreed that a reply should be made onthese lines.United States of 8.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionAmerica. to a telegram No. 793 from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Washington,Proposed reply dated the 22nd May, suggesting that the Prime Minister shouldby the Prime send a reply for publication to an arranged question from a minister to an prominent American citizen.   The reply should make clear that,American whatever might be the outcome of the present battle, the Allies hadenquirer.Italy. 6.   The Chief of Naval Staff informed the War Cabinet thatPossible plan for it was not yet known whether the Italian aircraft carrierblocking the Maraglia had unloaded her aircraft before arriving at PortSuez Canal. Said. The Commander-in-Chief in the Mediterranean had(Previous been informed that he had full authority to take steps for a reference:        temporary blocking of the Canal if he thought it advisable, but on W.M. (40) 135th his present information he was inclined to let the Maraglia passConclusions,      through the Canal.   It was not contemplated that any furtherMinute 4.)        instructions should be given to the Commander-in-Chief.   It was true that there were some naval units which we particularly wishedto pass through the Canal, but the passage of these ships was not itself of paramount importance.   The main considerations thatwe had to bear in mind were that we wanted to avoid any risk ofthe Canal being blocked and to avoid provoking Italy into cominginto the war.  The advantage of arranging for a temporary blockagewould be that it would give us time to look into the situation without causing Italy any provocation.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.
every intention of continuing the fight, but that their capacity inthe next weeks and months would be greatly increased if they could obtain additional supplies of war materials of every kind.The Foreign Secretary suggested that he should supply thePrime Minister with material for a reply on the lines suggested.The War Cabinet approved this suggestion.Invasion ofGreat Britain.information from Borne.9. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto telegram No. 630 from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Rome,reporting that talk was current in German circles that Herr hitler was determined on the invasion of the United Kingdom. It wassuggested that the British authorities were &quot; asleep and undulyconfident in the British command of the sea.&quot; Various dates and places were mentioned.The War Cabinet took note of this information.CommunicationCentres.Allegedsabotage plans.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 133rdConclusions,Minute 8.)10. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew theattention of the War Cabinet to telegram No. 796, dated the23rd May. 1940, from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington,reporting that the United States War Department had reliable information that a complete disruption of all important communi-cation centres throughout the United Kingdom was expected in thenear future. It was added that complete plans of all exchanges, &amp;c,had been in the possession of saboteurs for some months.The Secretary of State for the Home Department and Ministerfor Home Security said that it might very well be true that plans for sabotage were in existence, but that all possible steps were beingtaken to increase the protection of vulnerable points of special importance, which included trunk telephone exchanges.Instructions had already been given for the removal of aliensfrom key positions in factories and public utilities, apart fromexceptional cases in which they could be proved to be thoroughlyreliable.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs enquired whethersteps were being taken to provide protection for telephone exchanges and similar buildings in the provinces as well as those in London.The Secretary of State for the Home Department replied thatthe position was under constant review by the Home defence executive and the Sub-Committee on Vulnerable Points, but that,until the new Local Defence Volunteers was fully organised, theprotection of all vulnerable points was likely to be hampered by shortage of personnel. At the same time, all key points were underpolice protection, and instructions had been sent by the Home Officeto local authorities to ensure that buildings under their control wereguarded. In the case of undertakings, such as water works, in private ownership, the responsibility rested upon the owners them-selves, although every effort would be made to furnish protection inappropriate cases.
156Jl. o \jInvasion ofGreat Britain.security measures:Control of aliens.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 128thConclusions,Minute 3.)[21336]11. The Lord President of the Council said that the informalCommittee, over which he presided, had considered, the previous evening, a request made by the War Office for the internment ofall enemy aliens and the imposition of severe restrictions uponneutral aliens. The Home Secretary had represented that anattempt to intern all enemy aliens forthwith would cause a break-down of the machinery and would not be effective, since the danger to be apprehended from neutral aliens was quite as serious as thedanger from enemy aliens.   It was, however, proposed : (a) To intern all German and Austrian women in Category B,between the ages of 16 and 60, and detain them in the isle of Man;(b) To impose special restrictions on all other aliens in thepopulation, subject to the grant in exceptional cases of exemption by the local Chief Officer of Police; and(c) To impose an obligation on every householder to report tothe police, and not merely to record, particulars of anyalien who spends a night in his house.The Lord President suggested that the Home Secretary should beauthorised to proceed with these proposals without prejudice toany further measures which might be desirable in the light offurther developments.He had been gravely disturbed by the reports received fromthe War Office authorities as to the conditions in the camps in whichGermans were interned. Freedom of movement, inter-communica-tion with persons outside, and the use of wireless sets were permitted, and no steps had been taken to &quot; cover &quot; the interneesby the introduction of agents. If the position was as it had been described, action should be taken at once to remedy it.The Secretary of State for the Home Department explainedthat the special restrictions to be imposed on all aliens, unlessspecially exempted, under (&amp;) above, would require all aliens tosleep at their recorded addresses. Any wilful breach of this require-ment would result in the internment of the offender. Power wouldbe taken under the Defence Regulations to intern any alien whose activities appeared to call for such measures. The power of exemption, to which reference had been made, would be exercisedprincipally in relation to persons employed in useful productivework, the conditions of whose employment made it necessary forthem to be away from their homes during the night. He had consulted the Commissioner of Police about giving notice beforeintroducing these measures, and he thought that it would benecessary to give about a week&apos;s notice.These restrictions would automatically prevent aliens fromundertaking duties as A.R.P. wardens, unless they were known tobe reliable. Steps had already been taken to remove all aliens fromresponsible positions in the A.R.P. Services, although some werebeing retained in subordinate posts. He suggested that some marginshould be allowed for reasonable discretion on the part of the police authorities in granting exemptions in cases where, for example,aliens had been long resident in this country, had acquired foreignnationality by marriage, and had had no recent communication with enemy territory.The Home Secretary emphasised that it was important tocontrol any person who might conceivably be a cause of danger, andthat the alien refugees now reaching this country fell within this category even more than the persons of enemy nationality now at large after the scrutiny which had been carried out. He sharedto the full the Lord Presidents views as to the need for immediatelytightening up the conditions necessary for internment of aliens,which were admittedly unsatisfactory. It was essential that theMilitary authorities should recognise that arrangements made for
prisoner of war camps were totally unsuitable for detaininginternees and suspects. Very special precautions were necessaryfor the latter, as experience in Ireland and India had proved.Segregation should be imposed, all forms of inter-communicationprohibited, and the intelligence arrangements for discovering anyconcerted activities to attempt acts of sabotage or to co-operate with possible airborne landings should be at once improved.In the discussion which followed, the following points weremade : The Prime Minister said that his view on this matter had greatly hardened since the events of the last few weeks. He thoughtit would be better to employ no Germans in any position ofresponsibility. The proper method by which Germans opposed tothe Nazi regime could contribute to the common cause was by workin the factories or fields of this country, or, best of all. underdiscipline in the Pioneer Corps. The German technique in theoccupation of the Low Countries had shown the weaknesses towhich we were exposed, and he was strongly in favour of removingall internees out of the United Kingdom.The Secretary of State for War said that the Adjutant-General&apos;s Department had been instructed to make a full investiga-tion as soon as possible, but he understood that General Kell had represented that he was insufficiently provided with funds toundertake the necessary security measures for watching internees.The War Cabinet agreed &apos;(1) To approve the following proposals of the Home Secretary,without prejudice to more severe measures later, shouldthese prove necessary, in the light of developments :  (a) to  intern  all  German  and Austrian  women  in category B, between the ages of 16 and 60, anddetain them in the Isle of Man;(b) to subject all other aliens to special restrictionsprohibiting them from possessing or controllingany motor vehicle or any bicycle, and requiringthem to be at their registered place of residencebetween 10 p.m. and 8 a.m., subject to the grantof exemptions by Chief Officers of Police, in thecase of special categories of persons, including those whose employment required them to work at night;(c) to impose an obligation on every householder toreport to the police the name, nationality and address of any alien who spends a night in his house, together with the date of arrival, the dateof departure and the proposed destination.(2) To invite the Lord President of the Council to convene ameeting, comprising representatives of the Home Office,the three Service Department and the Security Service,to investigate the conditions under which aliens aredetained in internment camps and to report to the WarCabinet on any measures necessary to rectify the positiondisclosed in the preceding discussion.
1 MInvasion ofGreat Britain.security measures.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 137thConclusions,Minute 11.)Arming of thepolice.12. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary (W.P. (G.) (40) 134) seeking authority to arm thepolice for certain purposes (enumerated in paragraph 4 of theMemorandum), so far as the arms available to them permitted.The Home Secretary said that, as would be seen from the Papernow under consideration, there was very great scope for arming thepolice. An additional 12,000 rifles and 10,000 revolvers would berequired to enable the police to undertake the special tasks referredto in paragraph 4 of his Memorandum, and he feared that it wouldnot be possible to meet this demand for some time to come. Theissue of arms on this scale would enable many more than thecorresponding number of police officers to be armed, as the rifles and revolvers would be held in police stations and issued in relays.This would enable a large proportion of the police, whose peace-timestrength amounted to some 60,000 men, to undertake the tasksrequired.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs suggested that anappeal should be made to private individuals to hand in any armsthey might hold, so that they might be distributed and used to thebest advantage in an emergency.The Home Secretary replied that arms had already been collected from all aliens and from rifle clubs, and that persons whoalready possessed revolvers would be unlikely to respond to anappeal to surrender them. Some of the weapons were trophies ofthe last war* and were of foreign manufacture, for which noammunition was available. The majority of such weapons were inthe hands of responsible people who had obtained permits and were anxious to retain them for their own defence.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposal of the Home Secretary to take stepsimmediately to arm the Police so far as the arms availablepermitted to enable them to carry out the functionsreferred to in paragraph 4 of his Memorandum(W.P. (G.) (40) 134).Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,May 24, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
