<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/50/0 images: 360-373</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)..S E C R E T.C A B I K E T   45 (25).MEETING OP THE CABINET to be held at 10, Downing Street,S.W.1,, on Thursday, August 13th, 1925, at 3.0 p,m,A G S N DA,FOREIGN AFFAIRS .. SECURITY g THE. PROPOSED PACT.Reference Cabinet 43 (25) Conclusion 2).CHINA  (IF REQUIRED).THE USE OF THE SEVERN ESTUARY AS A SOURCE OF electrical power.Reference Oabinet 44 (25) Conclusion 4 (a).Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty onthe hydrographic investigation to be made by theAdmiralty,CP. 395 (25) to be circulated.4.      UNEMPLOYMENT - LABOUR REQUIREMENTS FOR ROYAL AIRFORCE t-ifORKS IN A GRICULTURXE DISTRICTS.Reference Cabinet 44 (25) Conclusion 5,Report of Inter-Departmental Committee,C,P. 39 6 (25) to be circulated).(Signed)     M.P.A. BANKEY,Secretary, cabinet, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.August 10th, 1925.
[^DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. )IS E C R E T.COPY NO.CABINET   45 (251.CONCIUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10,  Downing Street, S.W.I., on THURSDAY,AUGUST 13TH, 1925, at 3.0p.m.P R E S E N T:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P., rime Minister (In the Chair)TheRight Hon.Austen Chamberlain, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.Right Hon.W.S.Churchill, C.H..M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for India,fPhe Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,k.G.,G.C.V.O.,C.B.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bart. ,G.B.E. ,M.P., Secretary,of State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart.,C.M.G..M.P., Secretary of&apos;State for Axr.The Right Hon.Lord Eiistace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.jPhe Right Hon. x     The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland, Bart., Viscount Cecil of Chelwood,M.P., Minister of. Labour. k.C, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Sir Douglas Hogg,k.C.,M.P., Attorney-General.x   present for part of Items 1 and 2 only.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT :-Colonel G. R. Lane-Fox, M.P.,Mines ^Department, Board of Trade.(For Items 7 &amp; 8.)^ M. P. A. Hankey, G.C.B.....................------...... Secretary.
FOREIGNAFFAIRS.WiltSecurity.The ProposedPact.(previous reference:Cabinet 43(25), Con-Nelusion 2.)1-    The Cabinet had before them the following documents in regard to the proposed Pact of Security:A French draft reply to the GenanNote of July 20, 1925., containingamendments introduced as the resultof the conversations between Mr.Chamberlain and M. Briand (paper cp. -398 (25)):A draft of the proposed Treaty of mutual Guarantee, including the amendments provisionally agreedupon by Mr Chamberlain and&apos;&quot;M&apos;. Briandon &apos;August- 12, 1925 (Paper CP.-399Notes of a Conversation which tookplace at the Foreign Office onAugust 11, 1925, at Noon^ between representatives of Great Britainand France (Paper CP.-400 (25)).In the course of a full verbal report to theCabinet in regard to the recent negotiations, the secretary of State for Foreign Affairs emphasized thefollowing points:-The very friendly and easy atmosphere in whichthe conversations had taken place.That M. Briand had himself urged that it was of the greatest importance not to give any appearance of confronting Germany with a cut-and-dried plan, andthat for this reason the draft Pact in CP.-399 (25)must be regarded merely as a tentative draft andaabasis for discussion.The importance of the last sentence of theFrench draft reply, inviting the German Government toenter into negotiations, which had been added at Mr.chamberlain&apos;s suggestion.That as regards the next stage, the best plan would be an informal and unostentatious meeting ofBritish, French and German jurists., in England., atwhich the draft Pact could be explained to, and dls-cussed with, a German jurist as a preliminary to later
eonversaiionasaetweenlllveBriand, Dr.hStresemann.j ofOteit. VaMe velde-&apos; - ma?-- tfte1 Be ere t airy- of - S t at e for   &apos; :    -foreign Affairs.The importance of the last sentence ofSection II of the French draft reply to the german note of July 20, 1925 (CP. -398 (25)), which had been added at Mr Chamberlain&apos;s suggestion, and whichwould give a clear indication of the intention ofFrance to follow up a successful issue to thepresent negotiations by the initiation of a processof general disarmament as provided for in theCovenant.The explanation in Section III (page 4 of cp.-398 (25)) of the operation of the guarantee,which should be useful in reconciling the GermanGovernment to the French guarantee to the treaties with States on the East of Germany.Also the&apos; following words in the fourthparagraph of Section III of the draft:-&quot;In this connection an examination   .might be made whether some.means could not be found of safeguarding the impartiality of the decisionscome to without diminishing theimmediate and efficacious opera-tion of the guarantee itself,which had &quot;been taken from M. Briand!s despatch tothe French Ambassador and inserted at Mr.Chamberlain&apos;suggestion in order to show that this point was open for discussion with the Germans.That he had felt justified in agreeing tothe draft reply in CP.-398 (25.) without referenceto the Cabinet.^ but that in the case of the draft treaty of &quot;Mutual Guarantee (CP.-399 (25)) hehad not gone beyond undertaking to recommend it tothe Cabinet.That in discussing the draft Treaty of mutual guarantee, his object had been to see that itconformed to the general Treaty position in Europe
and that any alteration in that position must beagreed to by all the nations concerned or be inaccordance with Article XIX of the Covenant.That as regards limitrophe nations? everydispute should go to arbitration (viz. , arbitration in legal matters and compulsory conciliation in political matters);   this did not involve GreatBritain in sending every dispute to.arbitration,..since she was not a limitrophe State.That when an arbitral decision had been given and one of the parties did not give effect to it, appeel&apos;could be made by the other party to the League ofNations to decide what, action should be taken.That only in one case could force legitimatelycome into play, viz., where one of the parties hadrecourse to force and, thereby created imminent danger to the other.That the discussion on this point had turnedon the use of the French phrase &quot;acts hostile&quot;;   asshown in the Notes of the Meeting on the afternoon of August 1.1th, Mr Chamberlain had elicited from theFrench Legal Adviser that,under Article 44 of theTreaty of Versailles, any violation (however trivial)of Articles 42 and 43 would be treated as a hostileact.    After Mr Chamberlain had insisted that theBritish Government could not bring the. guarantee intooperation in frivolous cases, M. Briand had agreed and had -suggested that consultation might be necessarybetween the parties; . and eventually the followingprovision had been agreed to:-(Article 4 (3)).    In case of a manifestviolation&apos; by one of the High Contract-ing Parties of article 2 of the presenttreaty or of articles 42, 43 or 180 ofthe Treaty of Versailles, if the other contracting Parties are- agreed that -suchviolation constitutes an unprovokedact of aggression, and that by reasonof the outbreak of hostilities or ofthe assembly of armed forces in the-3-
^ &amp; Kdemilitarised sons immediate action is necessary, the said partiesseverally agree that they will eachof them come immediatel?/ to theassistance of the Power against whomthe act complained of is direoted.Nevertheless, the Council of theLeague of Nations, which is to heseized of the question in accordancewith the first paragraph of thisarticle , will issue &quot;its findings ,and the High Contracting Partieswin act in accordance therewith.BThat after considerable discussion on thesubject of the duration of the proposed Treaty, ithad been agreed to provide that it should remain inforce until the Council of the League , acting on therequest of at least two of the High ContractingParties, and voting, if need be, by a majority,decides that the League of Nations ensures sufficientprotection to the High Contracting Parties (Article 8).The original British proposal had been that this procedure should take place at the request of one ofthe contracting parties.That the British Government would not ratify the Treaty until it--was satisfied that its position the proposed under the Treaty was not prejudiced by/Treatiesrelating to States East of Germany.In further explanation of&quot;the way the guaranteewould operate, Mr.Chamberlain took a case where theGermans had crossed the Polish frontier In violation of the Treaty;   Prance, in fulfilment of her guarantee to the Treaties with st&amp;tes East of Germany, had entered the Rhine Provinces.    The French troops had then been, driven backhand. Germany had invadedFrance.    In such a case the British guarantee wouldnot be involved, and Great Britain would have noobligations beyond those involved under the Covenantand would be free to determine her.course of action.
After some discussion, the Cabinet agreed(a) To congratulate the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs on xhesuccessful issue of this stage of thenegotiations:(b) To approve, the assent which theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs&apos; had already given totheFrenoh draft reply to the-german note of July 20, 192 6, as set forth in CP.-398 (25):(e) To authorise the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to inform M.Briandthat the Oabinet had considered theproposed Treaty of Mutual guarantee in CP.-399 (25) and had agreed thathe should proceed with the &quot;negptia-tions on that basis:(d) To invite the attention of the ForeignOffice to certain errors of translation(which, it was recognised, were due .to the short time available for this work) in the draft Treaty of mutual guarantee (CP.-399 (25)) , includingnotably in Articles 2 and 4 thetranslation of the word &quot;flagrante&quot;as &quot;manifest&quot;:(e) In regard to a note received by theSecretary from the Admiral try, drawing. -attention to the expression in Article5 (2) of the proposed Treaty of mutual guarantee (C.P.-3.99 (25)) &quot;resorts to force&quot; instead of /&quot;resorts to war&quot; ,as employed in the Covenant, to take note that the former phrase had beenadopted deliberately and after carefulconsideration by the jurists.
CHINA. 2. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs made a short statement to the Cabinet in recard toprevious-Reference: the present position in China, which did not show muchCabinet 39(25), Con- .       improvement and might become more serious at anyelusions 5. )moment.    It was hoped, however, very shortly tobring about the inquiry into the Shanghai disturbancesand to obtain a declaration of the general policyof the Powers.    The United States of America were inclined to think that separate declarations might benecessary, but the Secretary of State was working fora ^oint declaration.    If this policy succeeded, itwould be possible to proceed shortly after to carry:out the Washington resolutions, which contemplated,first, a Tariff Conference to enable the Chinese-  Customs Tariffs to be raised, and, seoondj an inquiryby the Powers concerned Into the conditions of extra-territorial it y and the circumstances in which It might eventually, be abolished.Some discussion took place in regard to theBritish representation at Conferences dealing with theabove questions, and the matter was left in the handsof tho Secretary of State, who undertook, while conform-ing to the procedure adopted by other Powers in theappointment of their representatives, to give carefulconsideration to the views expressed at this Meetingof the Cabinet. .Attention was drawn to a suggestion which hadbeen made by the Governor of Hong-Kong for givingsome financial support to the anti-Coimrunist elements&apos; in Canton, ana the Cabinet were informed that theBritish Charge&apos; d!Affaires at Pekin, the Consul-general at Canton, and the Secretaries of State for,ForeignAffairs and the Colonies, had all been opposed to theproposal, which had therefore.not been adopted.
THE industrial situation.Dispute inthe Woollenjndust ry.[(previous reference:Cabinet 39(25) 5 Con-elusion 2.)3. The Minister of Labour had -to&quot; Leave the Cabinetduring the preceding disoussion as he was engaged in negotiations in connection with the dispute in the woollen industry.   He informed his colleagues thatthe operatives had offered to accept an Inquiry and tobe bound by the results.    The masters had acceptedthe Inquiry andhad also agreed to be bound by theresults. but had stipulated that the wage reductionsthey had proposed should take effect before the inquiry met.    This had preoipitated a strike, and theonly point now remaining was to induce the masters to waive this stipulation.
4. The Cabinet had before them a. Memo rand urn bythe First Lord of the Admiralty stating that theAclmiralty can arrange for the next stage of the investigation into the Severn Barrage Scheme to becarried out by the Admiralty Hydro graphic Service,on the basis suggested by the Cabinet, i.e., bypostponing other survey work, so that, althoughthe Admiralty would be recouped for their expendi-ture from funds allotted to the Severn Barrageinquiry, no additional State expenditure would be involved (Paper CP.-395 (25)).- /    The Cabinet agreed  That the Admiralty should proceedwith the above investigation.
5.The Cabinet had before them the Report of an inter-Departmental Committee, as requested at their previous Meeting, in regard to Labour requirements for Royal Air Force Works in Agricultural Districts(Paper CP.-396 (25)).The Cabinet agreed  That , as the general opinion of theCabinet at the previous Meeting hadbeen in favour of the principle ofnot recruiting agricultural labour for aerodrome work, a conditionshould be inserted in the contracts of the four aerodromes referred toin the Report of the Inter-DepartmentalCommittee requiring the contractornot to take on a man last employedin Agriculture without the consentof the Employment Sxohange.
6. The Seoretary of State for War drew theattention of the Cabinet to the recent distributionof posters,addressed to soldiers, which had beenfound affixed outside barracks at Knightsbridge,Manchester, Salford, Aldershot, and on the back ofan Order Board in a sentry-box at Buckingham Palace.After the Attorney-General had given a legalopinion, the Cabinet agreed -That, as the name of the printer wasnot stated on the posters, the best plan would be to proceed on the basisof a prosecution under the NewspapersAct if the authors or printers couldbe discovered.    This would not prevent a later decision to prosecute forsedition if sufficient evidence couldbe obtained.
0 4 &amp;THE COALu INDUSTRY.(previous reference:Cabinet 44(25), Con-elusion 1.)7. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that lord Grey had declined the Chairmanship of the CoalInquiry, mainly on grounds of physical disability.Various suggestions were made as to a suitableChairman * and the Prime Minister informed hiscolleagues that he would take them into consideration in discussing the matter with the Ministers concerned the same evening.The Cabinet were informed that the following terms of Reference had been accepted by both partiesto the dispute: -&quot;To inquire into and report upon theeconomic position of the Coal Industryand the conditions affecting it, andto make any lecoEMisndations^ for theimprovement thereof.&quot;The Cabinet were informed that the minersobjected to a Commission which did not includepersons with technical - knowledge of the details ofthe coal industry, but that the mine-owners would &apos;object to the Commission.if it did include such persons.The Cabinet agreed  -- -That if      .representatives of theminers and mine-owners were included -. in the Commission^it would inevitably-lead to Minority Reports, which would cause complications. . Consequently theprevious Intention to constitute theCommission of unbiassed persons withexpert assessors should be adhered to.
SUPPLY AND 8. A discussion took -place in regard to theTRANSPORTORGANISATION.     Supply and Transport organisation, and great strewas laid on the importance of utilising the next(previous reference: few months to briiK this organisation up to theCabinet 44(25),. Con- highest possible point of efficiency,elusion 2.)The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State for india should be added to the Supply andTransport Committee:(b) That, in order to assist the Cabinetin giving effect to the decisionrecorded in Cabinet 43 (25)   Con-clusiOn 3 (b), the Attorney-rGeneralshould prepare a Memorandum forthe Cabinet in regard to the legal powers possessed by the Governmentfor dealing with an attempt by trades union too hold up the essential services of the country in order to gain their objects, and as to the- legislative measures which might betaken to strengthen those powers,either in anticipation of or on the occurrence of an emergency.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,August 13, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
