<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/21/0 images: 63-64</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                  ^^4*o   5Department of Agriculture  and Technical Instruction for Ireland.                   FOOD PRODUCTION  SCHEMES.  IRELAND,W^HAU^J^^noj-andiom prepared  in  compliance  with Chief Secretary&apos;s                         Minute of  17th March,  1917Week ended 25th July, 1917  The  following is  a  brief  statement on the work carried out by theDepartment  during the past  week in furtherance of increased FoodProduction  in Ireland in 1917,  and in connection with tho organisation9f euppllos of roquisitoB for tillage and harvest operations in 1918:-          Administration,of Compulsory  Tillage  Regulation   Nothing material has  occurred  in connection  with tho administrationof tho  Compulsory Tillage Regulation since the  date of last wook&apos;ereport,   The  total number of  cases  in which the Departmontlisvn decidedto oxeroiso thoir power  cf entry  on lands stood at 421 on that dato.                 Loano  for Agricultural  Implements  The  number  of  applications  for  loans  for accricultural implementsreceived by tho  Department during the week was       The total valuoof machinery  ordered  to  date  under the  Scheme is  73,157.                      \v, ^Sftp age*  f&quot;grain, ^  The  Department are proparimg  exhaustive  lists  of  storage  accommodationavailable  at  Irish Porte,  and also  lists of stores  throughout bnocountry, in anticipation of  Government  requirements in this direction.                            Corn  Sacks.   The Department  have  purchased  a  quantity of  corn sacks,  and aroholding them in reserve for  special emergencies which may&apos;arise inconnection with the  provision of  seeds for the  1918 crop etc.                         Spraying  of PotatoosThe spraying season  is now woll advanced,  and  there  is  ample  evidenceof tho ^UGcese  of  the Department&apos;s spraying  propaganda.   This appliesparticularly to socond spraying which  is now in  full Towing, and^is                                                              beingS5/7/.7
(being carried out far more generally than in previous years.  The supplyof spraying materials and machines is adequate for requirements.  Thoreis every prospect of an abundant potato crop.                       Harvesting operationsArrangements aro bming made to provide instruction in counties re-quiring same, in the use of binders and other harvesting machinery,many farmers having purchasod such machinery for the first time thisyear ^     Demonetisations in the uso of self binders and other harvestingmachinery for the instructors employed under the tillage scheme in thevarious counties are also being arranged,.  Special attention will begiven to the use of types of machinos imported during the present year,which were not in general U30 hitherto.                         Saving of FIa.-a Seed   Under the Flax Seod (Ireland) Order, 1917, recently issued, growersOf flax in Ireland in 1917 aro required to dry,, stack and savein such manner as may be prescribed by the Department, one-eighth oftheir crop for soed purposes; and it is prescribed in the Order thatnc person shall, without a permit issued by the Department,, sell, offerfor sale, purchase, make payment for or take delivery, whethu- forscutching or otheruiso, of any flax grown in Ireland during the 1917sea&amp;on unless he has made or obtained, as the case may be, adeclaration to the effect that one-eighth of the crop has been savodfor soed purposes,    The Department aro taking the necessary steps to put the Order inforce.                    Transit  of Farming Requisites   The arrangements  for the  conveyance from Dublin.  Rosslare andWaterford of consignments of farming requisites which arrived at thePor\io during the week were satisfactory.   As compared with previousweek-o there was, howe^or, a  substantial reduction in the volume ofthe traffic passing.   It is roportod that shipments to the Port of Cork were affected bya threatened strike  cf dock  labourers.   Representations were received relative to the convoyanco of bindersfrom Liverpool,  binder twine from Dundoo, hay-making machines fromttewark-on-Eront  and  machinery paifts from Hull.  Action was taken ineach case.                  Maintenance ofLive Stock  During the period  from 10th to 83rd July, inclusive, 915 applications*or licences to  slaughter or export under the Order relating tobreeding sows were received, and 657 licences wore issued.

</content>
</cab>
