<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/21/0 images: 68-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
NAVAL  WEEKLY APPRECIATION,  9.   With the exception of the submarine  attack on trade  there have been no  operationsof importance during the week.                        SUBMARINE  ATTACK ON TRADE.    THE following  table compares  the tonnage  and number  of  British shipsentering and  clearing  to  and from  the  United Kingdom, with  the  number  andtonnage of ships  sunk  by submarines or  mines whilst on passage to and from theUnited Kingdom during the same period on certain specified routes&apos;.  Commissionedvessels and troopships are not included : [649-9]
STATEMENT of Numbers and Tonnage of Sailings and Losses of British Merchant Steamships To and From United Kingdom of Over 500 Tons.                                              Gross Register for Week to July 21, 1917.	Routes United Kingdom (To and From).									Other Routes.	Grand Total.	Cross Channel Ports.	New York and North thereof.	South of New-York and West Indies, &amp;c.	Gibraltar.	Dukar, St. Vincent, and West. Africa.	The Hay (Brest- . Gorutiiia).	Portugal and Spain, West of Gibraltar.	North Sea Ports and Russia.	Total.		SAILINGS. In Numbers Tons Out Numbers Tons Totals .. ^ LOSSES. In Numbers Tons Out Numbers Tons .. . Totals.. PERCENTAGE OF NUMBERS LOST. out.&apos;.&apos; !! Total PERCENTAGE OK TONNAGE LOST. In -. Out.. Total	172 &apos; 337,154 239 453,821	38 222,908 37 211,411	28 133,566 17 91,364	21 67,317 29 114,093	27 145,383 25 135,054	13 27.506 14 27,776	1 2,549 4 8,172	15 37,308 19 , 30,772	315 973.691 384 1,072,463			411 790,975	75 434,319	45 224,920	50 181,410	52 280,437	27 55,282	5 10,721	34 68,080	699 2,046,154			2 2,690	2 6,746 I 3,738	1 4,456 1 4,916	7 23,182 1 5,842	1 3,924 1 3,242	1 3,146	* * 1 2,935	* * * *	12 41,454 7 23,363			2 2,690	3 10,484	2 9,372	8 29.024	2 7,106	1 3,14 6	1 2,935	* *	19 64,817	5 22,245	24 87,062	&quot;-83	5-26 2-70	3-57 5-88	33 3 3-44	3-7 4-0	7-7 * *	25* 0		3-81 1-82			-48	4-0	4-44	16-0	3-84	3-7	20-0		2-72			-59	3-02 1-76	3-33 5 - 38	34-43 5-12	2-69 2-40	11-43	35- 91	* *	4-25 2-17			-34	2 41	4 16	16-0	2-55	5-69	27-37		3-16		
NUMBER of Ships sunk by Submarines and Mines during each of the last four Weeks.Week ending-^-	British Ships.		Allied and Neutral Vessels.	Over 1,600 tons.	Under 1,600 tons.	June 22.. .. July 15.. July 8.. .. July 1..	21 13 14 15	3 4 3 5	13 23 33 29     The losses have risen during the week to twenty-one large ships compared withan average of fourteen during the previous three weeks.  We are therefore back agaiuto the very heavy average loss experienced during June.  They were distributed asfollows :  South and West of Ireland, 8 ; Channel, 6; North and West of  Scotland, 5 ;Bay of Biscay, 2 ; Mediterranean, 3.     The number of large submarines out during the week varied between 20 and 23 ;of these, 11 or 12 appear to have  been operating to the Westward of the BritishIslands, and 5 on the South-West of Ireland  approach routes.  Reports have  beenreceived of the sinking of three steamers and two sailing-vessels to the Southward ofthe  Azores on the 20th July.   There are probably two  submarines  working inthis area.    During the week, three  North-Atlantic convoys, two from the United States  andone from Canada, totalling 310,80(5 gross tons, have arrived ;  one of these convoys raninto a fog in the North Channel, and, after the ships had been dispersed to their partsby the senior officer,  one ran ashore and one was in  collision.   One convoy  wascomposed entirely of ships bound for the West  Coast of England, so that it  could bebrought in  by the North of Ireland route, thus avoiding the  dangerous Channel  andSouth of Ireland areas.   Since the first deep-water convoy arrived on  the 24th May,a total of 732,000 gross tons have been brought in under this  system, without the  lossof a single ship by enemy action.  There are now 128 ships under  convoy  in the NorthAtlantic,  and the system is in operation for all 8 to 12 knot ships in that area.  Out often homeward-hound  ships sunk in  the vicinity of  the United  Kingdom during  theweek, five were from Gibraltar or Spanish ports.  For the four-weeks ending 1st July,the percentage of sinkings on this route was no  less than 23 per cent.,  whereas for theoutward trade on the same route it was only 4 per cent.  Most of the sinkings on theinward voyage occur to the south of  Ireland,  and  if another route could be  found forthis very valuable trade this high rate of loss  might be reduced.  &apos;    The  armed merchant-cruiser &quot;  Otway &quot;  of the 10th Cruiser Squadron  has beensunk by submarine attack in the vicinity of the  Butt of  Lewis.    Twenty-five engagements with enemy submarines have been  reported during theweek, but it is improbable that any of these resulted in  the destruction  of a submarine.    The  enemy&apos;s  submarine minelayers have been  active  during  the week;   128moored mines were swept up.                               Minor Operations.    The machines of the Royal Naval Air Service have carried  out several raids from ^Dunkirk on places of military importance during the week.    Deep mines have been laid in the vicinity of Beachy Head.                       Erratum.   In Appreciation No. 8.    The neutral tonnage  placed at the disposal of the Allies by the new agreementswas stated  to be 3&apos;2  million tons, and it was compared with  the  5*9 million tonsemployed in the trade of the United Kingdom.    The comparison  was misleading,because the former figure was deadweight tonnage and the latter gross.  A deadweighttonnage of  3-2  million tons would approximately correspond  to a gross tonnage  of21 million tons.[649-9]
                       SUMMARY OF NAVAL INTELLIGENCE.                      Movements of German Merchant Ships.    To and from Norwegian ports :  Arrived, 7.   Sailed, 2.    To and from Rotterdam :  Arrived, none.  Left, 2.    Dutch press states that the  two German  ships which were driven ashore offEgmont and  set on fire by British destroyers have been towed into Ymuiden muchdamaged.   Movements of German Merchant Ships Trading letween Oxelosund and Germany.                                                           Left.     Arrived.        During the week ending  June  2        ...       ...    9         8                                      9        ......   11         7                                    16        ...       ...    7         6  .  During three weeks under review (27th May-lGth June) total amount  of iron oreexported from Oxelosund to Germany, 83,239  tons ; total amount of coal importedfrom Germany, 9,783 tons.    Emden, Hamburg, Lubeck, Stettin are given as chief  ports of discharge for theiron ore in Germany.    It is reported on  reliable authority that interference with, the iron ore traffic fromLulea  and  Oxelosund  to   Germany is  almost  impossible  without  infringementof territorial waters.                              THE  GREEK  FLEET.    The Greek fleet has been restored to Greece  by the French.    The destroyers will  perform  escort duties   in the Mediterranean.  The torpedoboats will carry out  patrol duties and short distance work in the iEgean.    It is interesting to note that two of the destroyers built in  Germany in 1912 areconsidered to be  not worth running, while  four destroyers built  by Laird at the  sametime are efficient.   Originally the British  boats were compared very unfavourably tothe German boats.AIR RAIDS ON CONSTANTINOPLE.    The advisability of continuing air raids on  Constantinople has been urged fromseveral reliable quarters.    It has been pointed out by an authority on  Turkish affairs  that  air raids onConstantinople, apart from material damage, have the following effects :     1. The Turks  are sure to be greatly impressed by German raids on London, and          such an impression would be greatly nullified by the discovery that we are          also able to undertake such measures, and that  the  Germans are unable to          afford them adequate protection against  such raids over their capital.    2. The Turkish Government is certain to worry the Germans for A.A. guns and          aircraft, and these demands will probably be acceded to in time, in order          to  keep the Turks  in good temper.  This would  immobilise guns  and          aircraft which,  otherwise, would  probably be used in Mesopotamia or          Palestine.    3. The Turkish official in  Constantinople is just the  sort of person  who takes          great care of his skin, and  constant, bombing might have  the effect of          causing &quot;  war weariness &quot; among Government officials, a state of mind          unlikely to be caused by our victories in distant theatres of war.    A Foreign Office telegram  from Washington states that Mr. Elkus, late AmericanAmbassador at Constantinople,  is of  the opinion that these air raids constitute anexcellent form of offensive against Turkey.    The late Greek Minister at Constantinople told  the British Minister at Berne a few
days ago, that there has never been so much discontent among the population as now.This seems a reason for an immediate repetition of the raid.   It is not often that theTurkish people show discontent and  when they do, it is well to seize the opportunityand bring the war as near to them as possible.    In view of .the  above  considerations, further long distance offensive measures arebeino- considered by the  Vice-Admiral, Commanding Eastern Mediterranean.                                Am INTELLIGENCE.1.  General Information.    (a.) It is  reported that a  new type of &quot; Ago &quot; seaplane is now in existence, withtwo Mercedes  six-cjdinder engines of 260 h.p. each.  It is said to carry three aviators,two aerial torpedoes, in position for firing, four spare torpedoes, three machine guns,150 gallons of  petrol, and a number of bombs.    (b.) The  attached  list gives an estimate of German aircraft  units on  the 11thJuly, 1917 :-   v 7Sector of Front.	Bombing Flights.	Fighting-Flight Si	Protective Flights.	Recon-naissance Flights.	Artillery Flights.	Total Units.	Total Machines.Flanders Artois Uise-Aisne Champagne .. Mouse Lorraine Alsace West Front Russia liouinania Macedonia Fast Front Totals	7 1 6 5 1	10 9 9 2 3 4 3 %	5 4 3 1 1 4 3	11 5 10 5 6 3 5	21 11 17 7 11 2 7	54 30 45 20 21 14 18	456 288 378 141 162 132 144	20	40	21	45	76	202	1,704	1 3 -	1		24 3 6	11 1 2	36 4 12	216 24 84	4	1		33	14	52	324&apos;	24	41	21	78	90	254	2,028Naval Staff,    July 25, 191,7.o

</content>
</cab>
