<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/21/0 images: 178-179</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
, CAB/A/p^T  ^    A \\ SPECIAL WORK OF THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT BOARD.   1                    For Week ending July 27th, 1917.     1,   Further conferences have been held with theMinistry of Food on the subject of.the scheme adopted forsecuring the better control of the distribution and pricesof essential food stuffs, and the President has given hisapproval to a Circular bringing the  scheme to the noticeof the ilooal Authorities whose co-operation is required andurging them to undertake with energy the duties allotted tothem under the scheme.2.          The President is issuing a Circular to LocalAuthorities informing them,  as  authorised by the War Cabinet,that the Government recognise that it will be necessary toafford substantial financial assistance from public fundsto those local authorities who  are prepared to carry throughwithout delay, at the conclusion of the war, a programme ofhousing for the v^orking classes approved by the LocalGovernment Board;   and requesting them to answer byOctober 15th a Series of Questions to show the presentposition in the matter of housing in their areas, theanticipated need for houses after the war, and the measures
taken or proposed&apos;to be taken to meet the need.          An expert Committee has been appointed toconsider questions of building construction in connectionwith the provision of dwellings for the working classesin England and Wales and report upon methods of securingeconomy and despatch invthe provision of such dwellings.     3.-   A Circular and Memorandum have been issued toLocal and Appeal Tribunals informing them of the newpowers conferred on County Agricultural ExecutiveCommittees for securing the retention of the necessarymen on the land, and explaining the effect of the newarrangements on the procedure of Tribunals in dealingwith&apos; applications for exemption from military serviceof men covered-by the arrangements.Local -Government Board,     27th July, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
