<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/21/0 images: 675-676</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAR CABINET.                MTSMITT AND CHILI) WEIJ^J3IJ .                Memorandum by Six Edwin Cornwall.                                                 me          With reference  to the communication sentAto by theWar Cabinet  on 20th July,  enclosing  a  Memorandum from Dr. Ad.dJ.sonon the Maternity and Child Welfare Bill as drafted  and submittedby the Local Government Board, I have  given careful considerationto the subject and now desire  to submit the following observationsthereon :-     1.   In view of the  many  questions arising out of theproposals for the  establishment of a new Ministry totaka overthe whole of the Health services of  the Country, it isdesirable that an effort  should be made to pass a Maternity andChild Welfare Bill without waiting until an agreement has beenarrived at with regard to the  larger measure.     2,   The Maternity and Child Welfare  Bill should be insuch a form  as not to prejudice the  establishment of a NationalHealth Ministry, or to afford  any reason for postponing thefull consideration of that subject.     3.   Conferences have been held with representatives ofInsurance Committees and  Approved Societies of various types,with a view  to formulating proposals which might be embodied in aBill to be passed during  the present Session.   As  a result Ihave prepared the following draft of a Bill for consideration asan alternative to thai of the  Local  Government Board, in order togive an indication of- the lines upon which the existing Healthorganisations could be best brought  into use for the new purposes.This draft would,  of^course, require more  detailed  considerationif its principles were accepted.DRAFT.     1.    (l)   Any Local Authority in England and Wales,  and anyInsurance Committee,  may make  such arrangements as they thinkfit and  as may be  sanctioned by the Local Government Boardand the  Insurance  Commissioners,  for attending to the health ofexpectant mothers  and nursing  mothers and of  children who havenot attained the age  of five years and are not being educated inschools  recognised by the Board of Education.          (2)   In  this Act the expression &quot;Local Authority&quot; meansthe Council of any County or County Borough or of any UrbanDistrict with a population exceeding       ,  or Sorough with apopulation exceeding     2.    Any powers  of a Local Authority under this Act shallbe exercised in such  manner as the Authority  direct by aCommittee, which shall include women and representatives of theInsurance Committee of the area,  selected by  that Committee asrepresenting insured  persons,  and may also include, if it isthought  fit, other persons who are not members of the Authority.The number of representatives  of the Insurance Committee on anyCommittee appointed under this section shall  be not less than ene-third of the total membership  of such Committee.   Any suchCommittee shall held  office for such period,  not exceeding threeyears, as the Authority may determine.
    3.   (l)   It shall be the duty of every Local Authority te makerovision for  Maternity and Child Welfare to such an exfcatit as maye prescribed  by Regulations made by the Local Government Boardith the concurrence of the Insurance Commissioners, and the coatf such provision shall be defrayed from monies provided byarliament.         (2)   Any Committee may be empowered by the Authority byhich it is  appointed to make provision beyond the prescribedtandard in  accordance with the scheme adopted by the Authority andpproved by  the Local Government Board and the Insuranceommissioners,  and to incur expenses up to a limit for theime being fixed by the Authority,  and if so empowered, shalleport  any expenditure so incurred to the Authority in suchanner  and at  such times as the Authority may direct.(Signed)   EDWIN CORNWALL.NATIONAL HEALTH iKsnnAMrra      JO INT OOimi Tf lIlT2nd August,  1Q17.

</content>
</cab>
