<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/6/20 images: 232-237</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S E C R E ToV.P. (G)(40-120c1ST MAY,  1940.Note &quot;by the Prime Minister.I have been examining, in consultation with theMinisters in charge of the Service Departments, the existing arrangements for the consideration and decision of defence questions, and I circulate for the information of my colleaguesa Memorandum describing certain modifications which it has beendecided to make in these arrangements forthwith.     the modifications have been agreed to by the three Service Ministers,With the approval of the First Lord of the Admiralty, Major-General ILL. Ismay, C.B., D.S.O., has been appointed to thepost of Senior Staff Officer in charge of the central staffwhich, as indicated in the Memorandum, is to be placed atthe disposal of the First Lord.     Major-General Ismay hasbeen nominated, while serving in this capacity, an additionalmember of the Chiefs of Staff Committee.(Intdo)   No CoWAR CABINET. COPY NO._k5DEFENCE ORGANISATION.10, Downing Street,S.V. 1,

In order to obtain a greater concentration of thedirection of the war, the following modifications of present arrangements will take effect.The First Lord of the Admiralty will continue totake the Chair at all meetings of the Military Co-co-ordination committee at which the Prime Minister does not presidehimself and in the absence of the Prime Minister will actas his deputy at such meetings on all matters delegated tothe Committee &quot;by the War Cabinet.He will be responsible on behalf of the Committee forgiving guidance and directions to the Chiefs of staff committee,and for this purpose it will be open to him to summon that Committee for personal consultation at anytime when he considers it necessary.The   Chiefs of Staff will retain their responsibilityfor giving  their collective views to the Government and,with their respective staffs, will prepare plans to achieveany objectives indicated to them by the First Lord onbehalf of the Military Co-ordination Committee, and willaccompany their plans by such comments as they consider appropriate.The Chiefs of Staff, who will in their individualcapacity remain responsible to their respective Ministers,will at all times keep their Ministers informed of their conclusions.Where time permits,  the plans of the Chiefs ofStaff with their comments and any comments by the FirstLord, will be circulated for approval to the military co-operation-ordination Committee and unless the Military Co-co-ordination committee is authorised by the War Cabinet to take finaldecision, or in the case of disagreement on the military co-operation-ordination Committee, circulated to the War Cabinet.

In urgent cases it may be necessary to omit the submission of plans to a formal meeting of the Committee,but in such cases the First Lord will no doubt findmeans of consulting the Service Ministers informally andin the case of dissent the decision will be referredto the Prime Minister.In order to facilitate the general plan outlined above and to afford a convenient means of maintaining a close liaison between the First Lord and the Chiefsof Staff, the First Lord will be assisted by a suitablecentral staff (distinct from the Admiralty Staff) undera Senior Staff Officer who will be an additional memberof the Chiefs of Staff Committee.


</content>
</cab>
