<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/24/34 images: 340-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ClfyvvC-p^4 t sj/ sfTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  May 1942.MOST SECRET. , Copy No.W.P. (32) 204. /May 14, 1942. /TO BE KEPT UNDER L^jCK AND KEY.It is requested that speciai care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.SUMMARY OF OPERATIONS OF BOMBER COMMAND for fortnight ENDING 1200 HOURS SUNDAY, MAY 10.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Air.Night-Operations.Rostock and Heinkel WorksCologneTrondheim Naval BaseKiel.........Trondheim Naval BaseGennevilliersDay-St. Omer Railway Station ...Hazebrouck Marshalling YardsOstend Power StationLille Power StationSt. Omer Railway Station ...Dunkirk DocksLe Havre DocksFlushing Docks and Oil StorageMorlaix AerodromeAbbeville Marshalling YardsSt. Omer Railway Station ...Calais Silk FactoryNight HamburgStuttgart and Bosch WorksPilsen Skoda WorksStuttgart and Bosch WorksStuttgart and Bosch WorksWarnemunde Aircraft FactoryDay-Dunkirk DocksLe Havre Power StationZeebrugge Power StationLille Power StationCaen Power StationZeebrugge Power StationOstende Power StationDieppe Port Area ...Hazebrouck Marshalling YardsBruges Oil Storage......26/27 April27/28-27/2828/2928/2929/302626272728293030303011May3/44/54/55/66/78/934556778910107 aircraft9242873488666126666666661120577971956666666666This review covers the outstanding points in Bomber Command activitiesfor the fortnight ending Sunday, the lOth May. It will be circulated weekly infuture.
2(1) Mining.The heavy bombers and Wellingtons have now been brought into the miningeffort, and a very great increase in the number of mines laid is resulting.During the fortnight under review 535 mines were laid by aircraft of bomber command in the Baltic, Heligoland Bight, the Belts and off the west coasts of denmark and France. The approaches to the port of Danzig were mined for thefirst time.(2) Minor Raids.&apos;&apos; Freshmen &apos;&apos; have made night attacks against Ostend and Dunkirk Docks,St. Nazaire (twice) and Nantes (three times).Freshmen have also disseminated no less than *1\ million leaflets over all parts of France, including 1^ million on Paris on the night of the 5th/ 6th May.Operational Achievements.Day A attacks.The week ending the 3rd May was notable for the daylight activity ofBoston aircraft of No. 2 Group in conjunction with Fighter Command. Twelveseparate attacks were carried out comprising 78 sorties-the biggest effort since these aircraft began to operate.These operations were primarily designed to force the G.A.F. to give battle,but in addition the Bostons carried out some accurate and useful bombing, inparticular on Hazebrouck marshalling yards, and aircraft shelters at Morlaix.It is of interest that photographs taken the day following the attackon Hazebrouck showed that the marshalling yard at Lille was full to congestion,not less than 3,500 waggons being present.Zeebrugge; The most successful of the daylight raids during week ending the 10th May was that against the Benzol plant and power station at Zeebrugge.The attached photograph taken during the attack shows bombs bursting all along the target the column of smoke throwing long shadows across the canal.Night Attacks.Rostock. The Heinkel Factory-On the attached photograph the majordamage to this factory is shown enclosed within the white lines. A stick of bombs has fallen across the centre of the main assembly shop, and fuselages andunfinished aircraft have been dragged out on to the tarmac. The large area inthe centre of the factory, which includes the machine shop, canteen and oil store,has been burnt out. Among other destroyed buildings are the office block, boiler house, technical school and Gestapo office. The aerodrome is marked as beingunserviceable. It is estimated that 33 per cent, of the German long-range bomber force consists of Heinkel Ills, and it is believed that this factory is the onlyone in North Germany where these aircraft are assembled. Moreover, it producesthe Heinkel 177 (the largest bomber in the G.A.F.), which it is expected will beused to reinforce the Atlantic reconnaissance squadrons.The factory also produces and repairs single-engine fighters and float planes.Gennevilliers. The attack on the night 29th/30th April against the Gnomeand Rhone, Goodrich &amp; Thomson-Houston Factories at Gennevilliers waseffective, although damage was not as extensive as expected in the prevailingconditions. A stick of bombs hit the power station, which was seen to be inactiveon the following day, and photographs show buildings in both factories guttedor damaged.Trondheim (Naval Base). Two determined attacks in the face of heavy flakwere made by forces of heavy bombers operating from an advanced base^ Atpresent adequate photographic reconnaissance has not. been possible, but it isnot believed that any serious damage was caused to naval units,Stuttgart. Ground haze seriously handicapped crews on each of the threeStuttgart raids, and comparatively few of them identified their targets precisely.Our improved methods of navigation cannot be used directly to fix position atthis range.Nevertheless, the attacks were by no means unprofitable, and night photo-graphs confirm that a large percentage of bombs fell on various built-up areas.
On the third night Heilbronn, 25 miles: N,W. of Stuttgart, was attacked.Night photographs show a fire concentration in the centre of the old town,reminiscent, of some of those taken of burning Rostock, but day. photographsare not yet available.. Heilbronn is a city of 45,000 inhabitants and is a centre for rail and river traffic. &apos;.Warnemiinde. The factory at Warnemiinde is producing 60 Me. 109&apos;s amonth. A heavy attack was made on it at very low altitude in the face ofsearchlights and flak, which were known to have been reinforced since thesuccessful attack on the Rostock factory nearby. At the same time, part of theforce attacked the town which houses the factory workers and includes theterminus of the important train ferry service to Denmark.Photos taken next day show disappointing results. Many sticks of bombs have fallen across the two aerodromes, a few hits have been scored on thefactory buildings and there are several incidents of blast and fire damage in thetown,: But there is no evidence of important damage.The night photos prove that nearly all aircraft found and bombed the areaof the target, but the great concentration of searchlights produced such a glarethat our bomb aimers failed to pick up their small targets. These searchlightswere deliberately laid to produce this result, and the special aircraft detailed toshoot them up, although partially successful, could not compete with the numberinvolved. This experience confirms information that the Germans are vastlyincreasing local defences of vital targets at the expense of the defences of the ruhr and the Reich generally.Information regarding Previous Raids.M.A.N. Factory, Augsburg. The attached photograph shows that the mainassembly hall, which turns out submarine diesel engines and covers an area of20,000 square yards, received direct hits causing severe damage. It will be seenthat the whole roof is bleached by fire, and while the full extent of the damagecannot be gauged from the photograph, it is reported by A.A. Berne that thisbuilding is completely destroyed.Cologne. Reconnaissance on the 29th April showed major damage, mainly the result of fire, in the Central city area. - An area 470 yards by 375 yards isalmost completely burnt out (photograph is attached).Two sources have reported that in the month of February there was no rail traffic passing through the main station across the Hohenzollern Bridge. Oneof these sources, who was present in the middle of February, states that at thattime part of the roof of the main station was destroyed and that the reason whyno trains could use this route was that one of the arches on the approach to thebridge had been so weakened as to cause all traffic to be suspended. It isconsidered that this damage was caused in the attacks in December 1941, whenit is known that a train approaching the main station from the East was hit.It is said that in the interval passenger traffic was routed through and from thesouth station. It is not known how long this suspension lasted, but it is note-worthy that in the photographs taken on the 25th March, although the station and bridge appear intact, there is a remarkable lack of rail activity in theneighbourhood of them.Kiel. Photographs show significant points of damage attributable to the raid of the 28th/29th April,   In the Germania (Krupps) shipbuilding; yards twobays of the plate-shaping sheds have been destroyed by a direct hit.   Two mainshops of a wire cable factory have been completely gutted by, fire, and there is evidence of extensive roof repairs to the engine roundhouse in the Die HornMarshalling Yards. . Damage to residential areas is also shown,, :. .....   ...-[It may be recalled that during ;an attack on the Scharnhorst and -Gneisenauon the 25th/26th February a large liner acting as a depot ship to one of the battle cruisers was hit. and burnt out. This ship has now been idehtified as One of the&quot;Monte Olivia&quot; class, of 13,800 tons. She was&quot;reported as having a large part0IVthe ^^aji^^crew^ on ,hoard..at the time she was hit. A photograph isattached showing the, gutted state of&apos;, the ship and the scene b  devastation on thequay alongside which she was moored.
The Matford Works at Poissy. Ground sources have reported that the scale of damage to this factory is as great and possibly greater than that achieved atthe Renault Works. The fact that the works are largely contained in one building of very solid construction no doubt accounts for this.Several of the sources reported that the damage has been so heavy that the plant is unlikely to be repaired for a long time to come. A significant fact isthat all the orders for component parts previously scheduled for Matford havebeen cancelled.German Reaction to the Bombing Offensive.Apart from the effect on the morale of the German people, the outstandingreactions have been the recrudescence of G.A.F. attacks on our towns, and the dispersal of flak defences on the Continent.It is believed that the bombing squadrons in the West have not yet been reinforced from other fronts, and that the new bombing effort is being maintained at the expense of the sea-mining effort, and by the employment of ReserveTraining Units.Sea Mining.In addition to the sinkings by sea-mining by Bomber Command listed inC.O.S. Resume (42) 239, two additional are reported as follows : (i) On the&apos; 13th March, 1942, a German ship of 5,032 tons was mined and sank 13 miles South of Heligoland.(ii) On the 28th March, 1942, a Danish ship of 7,664 tons was mined and sank off the Frisian Isles.There is good reason to suppose that this is by no means the complete list ofrecent sinkings by mines dropped in these operations.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, May 14, 1942.
The Matford Works at Poissy. Ground sources have reported that the scale of damage to this factory is as great and possibly greater than that achieved atthe Renault Works. The fact that the works are largely contained in one building of very solid construction no doubt accounts for this.Several of the sources reported that the damage has been so heavy that the plant is unlikely to be repaired for a long time to come. A significant fact isthat all the orders for component parts previously scheduled for Matford havebeen cancelled.German Reaction to the Bombing Offensive.Apart from the effect on the morale of the German people, the outstandingreactions have been the recrudescence of G.A.F. attacks on our towns, and the dispersal of flak defences on the Continent.It is believed that the bombing squadrons in the West have not yet been reinforced from other fronts, and that the new bombing effort is being maintained at the expense of the sea-mining effort, and by the employment of ReserveTraining Units.Sea Mining.In addition to the sinkings by sea-mining by Bomber Command listed inC.O.S. Resume (42) 239, two additional are reported as follows : (i) On the&apos; 13th March, 1942, a German ship of 5,032 tons was mined and sank 13 miles South of Heligoland.(ii) On the 28th March, 1942, a Danish ship of 7,664 tons was mined and sank off the Frisian Isles.There is good reason to suppose that this is by no means the complete list ofrecent sinkings by mines dropped in these operations.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, May 14, 1942.














</content>
</cab>
