<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/48/0 images: 27-30</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The circulation of this paper has been^ictlwhmited. ^ iIt is issued for the personal use of...^^.......[S...C^nlA... /hut^&apos;TOP secret copy No...cabinet confidential annex cm(72) 15th Conclusions, Minute 1Tuesday 14 March 1972 at 10. 00 amERN THE PRIME MINISTER said that, when it became clear that theID refusal of the Social Democratic and Labour Party in NorthernIreland to participate in any conference eliminated the hope thatU8 an acceptable settlement would emerge from current discussions,ce: it had been necessary for us to take the initiative in constructing) 14th proposals to meet the needs of the situation in Northern Ireland,fcions, The purpose of the initiative which we now had in mind was to5 secure a situation in which the majority and the minority had equalopportunities in the political and social life of the Province.    TheHome Secretary&apos;s proposals were in no sense a surrender to theIrish Republican Army (IRA), whose objective was the immediatereunification of Ireland by force.    The Cabinet had first to considerwhether to take some political initiative or not.    Failure to act now would mean acquiescence in a situation in which terrorism could never be completely eradicated from Northern Ireland, despite the disruption by the Army of the IRA organisation in Belfast; in which large areas of Londonderry would be outside the effective controlof the forces of law and order;  and in which terrorists could operate in the country areas from across the Border in relativesafety.    In addition, the pressure of Parliamentary and publicopinion would increase to a degree which might become intolerablebefore long.    If an initiative was to be taken, it had to be onewhich would be effective in securing our ultimate objective.    a relaxation of internment was perhaps its most important element.It should be possible gradually to release the less dangerouselements among the internees.    But at present internment wascontrolled by the Northern Ireland Government;  and, in order tobe certain of achieving our purpose, we should have to assume responsibility not only for internment but probably also for themaintenance of law and order, in so far as it affected public security.    In addition it would be right to seek to allay the dominant anxiety among the majority community by institutingperiodic referenda on the question of Ulster&apos;s continued membership of the United Kingdom.    It would also be desirable to construct anew economic programme in which the United Kingdom Governmentwould have a more dominant role than had been the case in the past,in order to prevent the mismanagement by the Northern ireland government of financial subventions and to anticipate allegations
that they were used exclusively for the benefit of the majoritycommunity.    The question for the Cabinet was whether so limitedan initiative would secure a willingness by all Parties to participate in political discussions with a view to a settlement and influence the Government of the Irish Republic towards taking more effective measures against the IRA operating from their territory.    If thePrime Minister of Northern Ireland, Mr Faulkner, were to refuseto agree to these measures and were to decide that he could not continue his Administration if they were imposed, the question would arise whether the Cabinet were prepared to accept atemporary period of United Kingdom rule.    How Mr Faulkner would react could not be ascertained without discussion with him;  therewas some hope that he would respond to appeals to his loyalty to theCrown and carry on his Administration.    Moreover, it should beborne in mind that there was a substantial element in the majoritycommunity which would welcome radical measures of reform.Likewise, it would be necessary to try to ascertain the probableresponse of the Government of the Irish Republic.    The current situation had put the Republic in a position of serious economicweakness;  and their Government might well find it in their interestto respond favourably to the kind of limited initiative which wehad in mind.In discussion it was agreed that some political initiative was nowclearly necessary.    It was argued that more radical changes wouldbe preferable to the limited measures which the Prime minister had outlined.    But account had to be taken of the possibility that animmediate move to United Kingdom rule, which might well become a permanency in default of any agreement about the future constitution of Northern Ireland,, would not receive the unanimousendorsement of the Government&apos;s supporters in the House ofCommons;  and in that event the Governments other policies mightbe endangered.    It seemed necessary, therefore, to be content with a more limited objective for the time being.    While it mightassist the Prime Minister in his discussions with Mr Faulkner toknow whether he had the support of his colleagues in proceeding to united Kingdom rule as a temporary measure should Mr Faulknerrefuse to co-operate in a more limited initiative, it seemedpreferable, on balance, that the initial discussion withMr Faulkner should be conducted on the basis of ascertaining hisreaction to the more limited proposal.    When that was known, theCabinet could consider the further measures which might then benecessary.So far as the approach to Mr Faulkner was concerned, the possibility that a refusal on his part to co-operate in a partial transfer of functions to Westminster might lead to the imposition of UnitedKingdom rule was not the only consideration which might influencehim.    Public opinion in Great Britain was becoming increasinglyimpatient about the commitment of such large military forces to2
Northern Ireland,.    There were, indeed, arguments for a progressive withdrawal - at least from the Roman Catholic areas -of troops who were now finding themselves engagsd in an apparentlypermanent police role,,    Although there were also powerfularguments against this course, Mr Faulkner should be left in nodoubt of the extent to which the safety of the Province depended onour maintaining a military presence which we should wish to terminate as soon as possible.    The prospect of additionaleconomic assistance was also a factor which might influenceMr Faulkner.    The Northern Ireland Government had shown themselves incapable of managing the economy of the Provincesatisfactorily;  and if, as was agreed to be desirable, they wereto receive further large subventions, the United KingdomGovernment must not only retain a measure of control over their application but were also entitled to require some reciprocalwillingness on Mr Faulkner&apos;s part to co-operate in measures whichwe judged to be necessary to meet the needs of the politicalsituation.    In short, if the majority community in Northern Irelandattached importance to Ulster1 s continuing membership of theUnited Kingdom, they must be prepared to accept United Kingdomstandards in the administration of the Province.In further discussion it was argued that, although the proposal for&quot;Community Government&quot;, under which certain Cabinet portfolioswould be statutorily assigned to representatives of the minority community, might have some attraction in theory as ensuring a guaranteed role for the minority in the government of the six counties, it was hard to envisage its working satisfactorily inpractice;  and it was unlikely to be acceptable to all the politicalelements involved.    Although direct United Kingdom rule might be criticised as undemocratic by the Protestant faction in NorthernIreland, this criticism could hardly stand if the position of theProvince were assimilated to that of Scotland and Wales.    Indeed,the local, rather than the central, government concept was best suited in the long term to the circumstances of Northern Ireland.It was also agreed that the enlargement of the functions of theUnited Kingdom Government by the addition of responsibility for law and order in the Province would make it desirable that northern Ireland affairs should henceforward be the concern of aseparate Secretary of State.    While legislation to make membership of the IRA unlawful in Great Britain might prove in practice to be incapable of effective enforcement, it should be a valuable element in our political initiative and should attract support from those who might be concerned that we were yielding to the pressure of violence.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the United Kingdom Government should assume responsibility for law and order in Northern Ireland in so far as itaffected public security.    This would include responsibility for internment;  and it was agreed that we should pursue a policy of3TOP SPrRFT
gradually reducing the number of internees.    We should alsoinstitute a system of periodic referenda on Ulster&apos;s continued membership of the United Kingdom;  and we should be prepared toinject substantial additional finance into the Northern Irelandeconomy in order to rehabilitate industry and commerce;  but theUnited Kingdom Government should retain a measure of controlover the manner in which these economic subventions were applied in the Provinces not least because it was in our interests that the economy of the Republic should also be healthy and this considera-tion would need to be borne in mind in considering the measures tobe adopted.    In addition, the legislation necessary for these purposes should provide for membership of the IRA to be unlawfulin Great Britain;  and a separate Secretary of State should beappointed to deal with our enlarged concern in Northern Irelandaffairs.The Cabinet further agreed that he should hold an early meeting with Mr Faulkner, in order to ascertain his reaction to themeasures which had now been approved and to seek to persuade him to co-operate in their implementation.    He would not at that stage give Mr Faulkner any indication of the consequences of a refusal of co-operation on his part;  but he would reportMr Faulkner&apos;s reactions to the Cabinet, who would then have toreach final decisions upon the measures to be adopted, which wouldhave to be communicated to Mr Faulkner.    At an appropriate pointin this process soundings would also be taken in Dublin.The initial meeting with Mr Faulkner might precipitate a situationin which the Government would be obliged to act with great speed.There was therefore advantage in postponing it until the visit of thePresident of the French Republic during the forthcoming weekendhad been completed and the Chancellor of the Exchequer hadopened his Budget on 21 March.    It was desirable, however, thatthe meeting should be announced during the current week;  and thereafter he would inform the Leader of the Opposition about theGovernments intentions.    Meanwhile, the Home Secretary, inconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretaryof State for Trade and Industry, should consider the further measures of economic assistance to Northern Ireland which mightbe put in train and the manner in which the United KingdomGovernment might retain the necessary measure of control overthe use to which further subventions were put.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion and invited theHome Secretary to be guided accordingly.Cabinet Office14 March 19724

</content>
</cab>
