<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/48/0 images: 40-42</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
It is issued for the personal use o:TOP SECRET10Copy No .r..cabinet confidential annex cm(72) 20th Conclusions, Minute 3Thursday 13 April 1972 at 10, 30 amHERN THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said thatND the political situation in the Province was still confused and was likely to remain so for some time.    There were, however, a numberous of signs of a growing desire for peace within the Roman Catholiccnce: community.    There had been numerous informal approaches to2) 19th his own Office;  and two particularly encouraging developmentsueions, had been the widespread advocacy by Roman Catholic priests ofo 3 a cessation of violence (although the influence of the Church was probably less than it had been in the past) and the meetings heldby a group of women in the Andersonstown area of Belfast whowere working to the same end.    In addition, the Social Democraticand Labour party were trying to encourage a move awaf fromviolence, although it was again questionable how strong their influence was in relation to that of the Irish Republican Army(IRA)0    Nevertheless, these favourable trends would take sometime to develop; and it would remain necessary to maintain a careful balance, not going so far in conciliating the Roman Catholiccommunity as to alienate the Protestants.The Protestants themselves had reacted less sharply to theintroduction of direct United Kingdom rule than might havebeen expected,    A number of Unionists had made informalapproaches to his Office;  but he was for the moment confininghis personal contacts with the Unionists to their leader, Mr FaulknerUnionist politicians would probably be prepared to take part in thework of the Advisory Commission if it was confined to members ofthe prorogued Northern Ireland Parliament; but this was out of thequestion.    The level of violence in the Province and the extent towhich the security forces could resume control of certain areas of belfast and Londonderry would strongly influence Unionist attitudes.The Unionists in Northern Ireland tended both to ignore the fact thatthere had, for many years, been little effective control of a numberof predominantly Roman Catholic areas and to underrate theThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.     . *
magnitude of the military operation necessary to restore the rule oflaw completely in those areas.    Mr Faulkner, however, had beenbrought to admit publicly that it would be impossible to mountmilitary operations in those areas without incurring heavy civilian casualties.    Londonderry, where hooliganism was spreading, would present the most difficult problems and would eventually call for a concerted major effort employing all available military, political,and public relations resources.The Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) and the senior echelons of theNorthern Irish Civil Service had remained loyal, although the special branch of the RUC had not concealed some anxieties about the accelerated releBBe of ctprteSn internees.    A number of difficultdecisions regarding internment were in prospect; and, although there was little doubt that a substantial number of those still internedcould safely be released, it was important both for political reasons and in relation to the morale of the RUC that it should not be suggestedthat internment had not been justified in the conditions of 1971.   Kehad authorised the release of further small ncmbers of interi-ees;and he intended to continue with this process as fast as security andpolitical considerations permitted.    But there would inevitablyremain a number of very dangerous individuals whose reloasewould present great difficulty.He had been very favourably impressed by the standard of themilitary personnel whom he had met in the Province; and he had found that the morale of the Ulster Defence Regiment, apart fromone temporary local instance, had been maintained at a high levelthroughout the recent constitutional changes.    The report submittedby the Lord Chief Justice, Lord Widgery, upon the shootings in londonderry on 30 January might present problems of presentation.With very few exceptions it provided a vindication of the Army&apos;conduct in Londonderry on that day;  but for that reason it mightbe represented in some quarters as a biased document.    He would discuss further with the Home Secretary and the Secretary of Statefor Defence the timing and method of its publication.In the course of a brief discussion there was general agreement onthe importance of taking advantage of the opportunity provided bythe recent constitutional changes to move towards politicaldiscussions designed to promote agreement on the future formof government of the Province.    It might perhaps be advisable to concentrate first upon discussions in Northern Ireland withindividuals representing all the main bodies of opinion.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe introduction of direct United Kingdom rule had, in some respects,proceeded more smoothly than might have been feared;  and this
reflected great credit on the Secretaries of State for NorthernIreland and for Defence.    He would give further consideration tothe best means of devising a comprehensive framework of proposals for the long-term constitutional settlemento    Itwould be necessary to take into account not only the relationship between the constituent parts of the United Kingdom but also the relationship between the United Kingdom and the IvIgL Rep^olic,bearing in mind particularly the prospective accession of both countries to the European Communities,    It was to be hoped thatthe leaders of various groups of opinion, both in Ireland and in GreatBritain, would not prejudice the prospects of an agreed solution by taking up intransigent positions.    Future decisions on the releaseof internees would present a particular problem in reconciling thehopes of the Roman Catholic community with the fears of theProtestants.    It would be wise to present further releases asjustified on security grounds rather than as political gestures,but without suggesting that the initial internments had not been justified.    It was also important to maintain an effective public presentation of the Governments policy, particularly in response to any suggestions that the Government were n.o longer concerned about the maintenance of security within the Province.    Theimposition of direct United Kingdom rule had improved theGovernments public standing abroad.    Within the Irish Republic,however, there was still scope for more vigorous action againstthe IRA.    In particular, and despite the political difficulty for theGovernment of the Republic of giving overt instructions to this end,a more rigorous control of the Southern side of the Border wouldmake it easier for us to modify the policy of cratering roads on theNorthern side.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office13 April 1972

</content>
</cab>
