<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/48/0 images: 59-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The circulation of this paper has beenIt is issued for the personal use of top SECRETteen strictly limited.     *       *  .   \8Copy No...CABINETKRTHERNPLANDoviousftference:if(72) 33rdinclusions,Bnute confidential annex cm(72) 34th Conclusions, Minute 5Thursday 6 July 1972 at 10. 30 am the SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND informed the Cabinet that the &quot;ceasefire&quot; proclaimed by the &quot;Provisional&quot; wingof the Irish Republican Army (IRA) was in general being observed,although there had been a number of isolated incidents of shooting.A more serious development was the expansion of the Ulster DefenceAssociation (UDA), whose strength and influence were extendingsteadily throughout the Protestant community.    The Associationundoubtedly commanded a substantial amount of tacit support fromProtestants who would not themselves wish to indulge in violence but still resented the Governments policy towards the minority, whoseconduct over the last three years they regarded as calling forpunishment rather than reconciliation.    The security forces had been tolerant of the erection of barricades by the UDA solong as these were confined to predominantly Protestant areas.On 3 July, however, the Association had threatened to extend thebarricaded areas to include streets containing substantial numbersof Roman Catholics as well as Protestants.    There was good reasonto believe that, if this had been permitted, the leaders of the&quot;Provisional&quot; wing of the IRA would not have been able to enforce the continued maintenance of their &quot;ceasefire&quot;.The Army had therefore been deployed to prevent the extension ofthe areas in question.    More than 1,000 members of the UDA inmarching order had confronted the troops.    He had thereuponauthorised the commanders of the security forces to make clear to the leaders that no extension of the barricaded areas would be permitted;  and, in view of the likely consequences of any attemptof this kind by the UDA, he had agreed that in the last resort thesecurity forces might be ordered to open fire.    This had been avery grave decision; but, if the Cabinet were to rule out entirelythe possible use of firearms against large formations of unarmedbut disciplined persons in similar circumstances, the UDA would extend their barricades in the areas inhabited by Roman Catholics,with incalculable consequences in terms of intersectarian violence.
On the day in question, however, the UDA had finally withdrawn inthe face of the firm stand taken by the security forces, on the basisof an agreement that they might carry out patrols within the ares which they had at present barricaded.    It must be hoped that the incident would have inculcated a greater sense of responsibilityamong their leaders.    But, although the security forces would do their utmost to prevent a repetition of this confrontation, nomoderate Unionist leader was prepared to attempt to control theAssociation or to mobilise moderate opinion against them.    Thepresent leaders of the UDA might therefore be tempted to establish a political organisation, in which event the local government of theProvince might eventually fall under the control of a type of mob rulewhich, though professedly &quot;loyalist&quot; in sentiment, would paradoxi-cally resemble in many respects an extreme left wing regime.    Theprospect might be more hopeful if an individual with an establishedpolitical position, such as the leader of the Democratic unionist party, Dr Paisley, could acquire a measure of control over thepolitical aspirations of the UDA,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatsensitive legal issues could arise when the actions of large gatheringsappeared liable to lead to serious breaches of the peace but were notin themselves unlawful.    There was no dispute that the civil power could call upon military personnel to assist in securing objectivesdeemed necessary for the maintenance of law and order and that,in rendering such assistance, military personnel were entitled touse such force, including the use of firearms in the last resort, as might be necessary for the purpose.    But the degree of force whichmight justifiably be used must be commensurate with the gravity ofthe threat which it was intended to avert.    On this basis the use of firearms would be permissible only if a careful assessment of the likely consequences of the actions of a crowd indicated a substantialrisk of widespread disorder or loss of life and if all alternative means of holding them in check, such as the use of baton roundsor CS riot control agent, had been exhausted.    The Secretary ofState for Northern Ireland and the military authorities should continueto be guided by these principles, which inevitably involved a nicejudgment of the probability that actions not unlawful in themselvesmight precipitate other actions, perhaps by other individuals, likelyto cause bloodshed.    Nevertheless the legal issues, important asthey were, could well be overshadowed by the political repercussions of, on the one hand, the use of firearms by British troops against anunarmed Protestant gathering and, on the other hand, a renewal of terrorism and intersectarian violence such as might well have followed the extension of Protestant barricades to include areasof mixed population.    It was a matter for satisfaction that the firmaction of the Secretary of State and the military authorities on July had persuaded the leaders of the UDA to recoil from an
ultimate confrontation with British troops; and it was to be hopedthat the incident had caused them to reflect carefully upon thepossible consequences of psrovocative actions.    The Secretaryof State for Northern Ireland should continue to do everything possible to encourage a proper sense of responsibility in all sections of the community during the critical period up to, and including, the major Orange marches on 12 July.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion and invited theSecretary of State for Northern Ireland and theSecretary of State for Defence to be guided accordingly.Cabinet Office6 July 1972

</content>
</cab>
