<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/48/0 images: 6-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY OF HER  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has bee^2trictjy lirnijed.It is issued for the personal use of.TOP SECRETCopy No..CABINETCONFIDENTIAL ANNEXCM(71) 40th Conclusions, Minute 2Thursday 22 July, 1971 at 10. 30 amNORTHERNIRELANDeviousReference:CM(71) 38thConclusions,Minute 3THE HOME SECRETARY said that the current situation inNorthern Ireland gave serious cause for concern.    The firmcontrol which the Prime Minister of Northern Ireland,Mr. Faulkner, had seemed hitherto to be able to exert was nowbeing weakened by the effect on the right wing of the UnionistParty of the riots in Londonderry and the recent acts ofterrorism by the Irish Republican Army (IRA).    The increasingboldness and apparent efficiency of their operations were creatingfresh alarm;  and Mr. Faulkner was now making renewed requeststhat the United Kingdom Government should re-affirm theconstitutional position of Northern Ireland and should institutemore drastic military measures.    Reassurance on theconstitutional position could readily be given;  and, as regardsmilitary action, the General Officer Commanding, NorthernIreland, intended shortly to introduce measures which were likelyto demonstrate the Government&apos;s determination to suppressterrorism.    The situation was such, however, that we now hadseriously to contemplate the possibility that we might becompelled to institute direct rule in Northern Ireland ifMr. Faulkner&apos;s administration was unable to retain its authorityand was replaced by a regime whose policies we could not accept.In discussion it was pointed out that the Ulster Unionist Membersof the Parliament at Westminster were becoming increasinglycritical of the lack of firmness, as they saw it, on the part of theUnited Kingdom Government in dealing with the situation; andthere was increasing danger of their persuading more of theGovernment&apos;s supporters to adopt this attitude.    They regardedthe establishment of a full-time unit of the Ulster DefenceRegiment as a particular test of the Government&apos;s determination.In further discussion it was suggested that the institution of directrule should be regarded as a policy of last resort and that beforeit was adopted it might well be right to agree that the NorthernIreland Government should invoke their powers of internment.While it was clear that internment in Northern Ireland would be1TOP SECRET
TOP SECRETmore effective if the Government of the Irish Republic could bepersuaded to adopt a similar policy in the South, the decisionshould not depend solely on the response of the Government ofthe Republic, particularly since the use of internment in theNorth would subject the Prime Minister of the Republic, Mr. Lynch,to increasing political pressure which would not coincide with ourown interests.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theMinisterial Committee on Northern Ireland would shortly meet toconsider the steps needed to deal with the present dangeroussituation in Northern Ireland.    While it was not possible to giveany prior indication to the Government&apos;s supporters in Parliamentof the nature of the immediate military measures to be taken, theHome Secretary would take the opportunity of a meeting of theConservative Members&apos; Defence Committee in the following weekto explain the Government&apos;s position.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.Cabinet Office, SW123 July, 1971TOP SECRET

</content>
</cab>
