<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/2/39 images: 532-583</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9 f* -fW vjf S-ffijR DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTYTS GOVERNMENT.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,It is requested, that special care may be takento ensure tho secrecy oP this document.SECRET. COPY NO,    U-QW.P.(R) (39) 79WAR CABINEToSUPPLY AND PRODUCTION,,THIRD MONTHLY REPORT BY THE MINISTER OF SUPPLYCOVERING THE MONTH OF OCTOBER.1. The value of all orders placed by the Ministryduring the month of October was  AO?669,000, making a totalof approximately  140,000,000 for the period since theoutbreak of War.    Further financial particulars are givenin Part IV below,,PART I,  MUNITIONS STORES.2. Deliveries showed, a general tendency to improveduring October, and for several items very satisfactoryreturns are now being received.For the second month in succession the outp&quot;4-of complete 3o7&quot; and ho 5&quot; A. A.   equipmentstogether has exceeded 80.A good beginning has been made with AO mm. Bofoi-equipments at the Royal Ordnance Factory,Nottingham,The output of liners for the medium A.A.  gunsand spare barrels for the AO mm,  guns hassubstantially increased.During October also a record delivery of Brenlight machine guns was achieved.Four predictors were lost at sea while beingdelivered from America, but otherwise deliveries of these important instruments were satisfactory.Returns from Filling Factories show a steady increase in the deliveries  to service of complete shell,though these are not yet at the level desired..,3-?0 A /3. The

3. The following schemes of major importance, inaddition to those previously reported, have been approved andare being put into operation:-Four new Royal Ordnance Factories for 3*7&quot;A0 Ac  guns    and spare liners, and for barrelsfor UO mm. Bofors guns.Increased capacity, amounting to 175 liners amonth, for 3C7&quot; A0AC gun liners by threefirms.Further extensions of capacity for 25 pdr.,2 pdr, anti-tank, and medium artilleryCarriageseVarious new plant for shell, cartridge cases and fuzes; and a new factory for 12&quot; howitzershell to bo managed by Messrs.  Beardmore.h* Orders Abroad.Canada.      The Special Mission in Canada is now proceeding with orders on a programme amounting to  9 millions sterlingfor shell, guns, carriages, etcsAustralia.    Initial orders for 3*7&quot; A, A.  equipments,complete shell of various calibres,  rifles and small arms ammunition are about to be placed with the australian government.India.    Orders are being placed to keep the IndianOrdnance Factories in full production and this source willprovide substantial quantities of small arms ammunition and complete shell during 19k0oSouth Africae    The resources of South Africa are likelyto be largely taken up with the Union Government*s own requirements, but enquiries are being pursued with a view toadvantage being taken of any surplus capacity.United States.    An initial list of Naval and army requirements of shell,, gun. liners,  etc., has been communicatedto the Special Mission In Canada to permit immediate orders 1being placed in the United States in order to take advantageof any deliveries obtainable during 1940oSpain and italy     Enquiries are being undertaken with aview to obtaining shell from Spain, and explosives,  instruments.-2- /and

and other equipment from Italy..5. Royal Ordnance Factories.It is now clear that ammunition&apos; filling work v/illbe able to comraence at Bridgend and Glascoed during December,Contracts have been placed for building work at the newFilling Factories at Swynnerton and Warrington and preliminary work for two others is proceeding.The new T.N.T.- plant at Pembrey has been startedsatisfactorily:    the first unit should be in full production early in the New Year and the second unit is due for completion in February with full output about April,  19*40,The first T.N.T.  Factory at Irvine has reached a production of 110 tons per week and should reach the full production rate of 300 tons per week next month.Contracts have now been placed for the constructionof the new T. N. T. Factory at Drigg and the R. D, X. factory at Bridgewater. A contract has also been placed for No. 3Unit at Bishopton,Production of cordite at Waltham Abbey is now upto 102 tons per week and it is hoped to reach full output inJanuary, 19*4-0,The forecasts of the needs of the Filling Factoriesfor the year 19h0 have now been received and show a deficit in cordite which, it is hoped,  can be met by the supply ofN/C powder from the United States.Good progress is being maintained at the FuzeFactory at Blackburn,  the Cartridge Case and Shell factory at Birtley and the Gun Factories at Dalmuir and Leeds.    work has commenced on the sites of the Gun Small Arms AmmunitionFactory at Radway Green and the shell plant at Wigan, and withthe reconditioning of the building at Cardonald.6. Machine Tools.15 new firms are undertaking manufacture of machine-x- /tools

tools and. some 30 others have agreed to act as sub-contractorsto increase the output of established makers.    Progress isbeing made with schemes for assistance to firms and in the placing of &quot;over-riding&quot; orders. Designs of two simplifiedtypes of horizontal boring machines have been agreed withmanufacturers and are being put into production.All the machine tools which it has been definitelydecided to withhold from export to Russia have now been allocated.    In order to obtain machine tools for transfer to munitions work, a Press appeal was recently issued asking for idle plant to be reported.7.    Tanks.There has been no material change in the rate ofproduction of tanks since the last report, as therehas been insufficient time for any appreciable effect to be caused by the employment of the large numbers of machine tools already approved.    Many of these, which are common toother armament suppliers, are for long-dated delivery.A further thorough survey of the existing resourceshas been made.    Additional erecting space has been arranged forand will be brought into use as soon as the supply of thenecessary components and assemblies is forthcoming.In this connection additional capacity for thebackv/ard parts is being secured on an increasing basis andthe most significant point is the increase in bullet-proofplate now being received as a result of arrangements madeearly in the year.8,    Anti-Tank Mines.In order to meet an urgent demand from the B.E.P..,a simple improvised type of mine is being produced in quantity on the basis of an initial order of 200,000 to becompleted and dispatched during November and December.9*    Chemical Supplies,,Impregnite.    Arrangements are in hand for the supply/of

4) C*iCi &apos;ii Jof impregnate - a chemical compound required for theimpregnation of clothing for the Army.    Orders have beenplaced for new factories at Messrs. Dickinson &amp; Son,Church, Lanes., and Messrse Hickson &amp; Welsh, Castleford,Yorks, for the production of Impregnite E to a capacity of25 tons per weekcConsiderable progress has been made in arrangementsfor the increased gas effort approved by the Cabinet on consideration of Papers W.P0/39/58o   Plans are in hand foradditions to the factory at Wade and for the full development of the Valley Factory.    Provision is beingmade for a further factory at Fleetwood and at least one more factory, and the sites for these are being considered.Concurrently, the advisability of locating capacity fortoxic material in Canada is also receiving consideration.10. Area Organization.,Negotiations are proceeding in agreement v/with the T.U.C. with a view to setting up local Committees.    Inthe meantime the present nucleus organization is extendingits operations and dealing with a large volume of localenquiries and offers of assistance.PART II. EQUIPMENT AND GENERAL STORES.11. A number of specialists v/ith technical knowledgehave been appointed to take charge of the work of planning the production of the wide variety of stores which fall underthis heading,.    The machine will of necessity take some timeto function smoothly, but it is approaching that stage andresults are being obtained,,12. During the month contact has been established witha number of Trade Associations and Federations and representative advisory panels have been set up where necessary.13.  QENERAL STORES,.Large and urgent demands for unusual or non-standardj- /items

items have been received.    These entail special treatment,as no advance preparation is practicable.    Examples are:-Crepesac bags(for gas contaminated clothing) 1,600,000Nissen huts 5*000U-gallon petrol cans 2,000,000Entrenching tools, French pattern 500,000Anti-freezing mixture 150,000 gallonsHorse shoes 1,000,000Steel racking 2,000 tonsIn the wood-ware section the number of firms anxiousto help is far in excess of requirements.Some difficulty is being experienced in regard tothe sup-ply of ran materials.    A notable example is aluminiumfor mess tins.    Contracts wore about to be placed for 1,000,000mess tins of aluminium when the serious shortage of this material became apparent.    The use of an alternative material(tin plate)  is under consideration and the question of making available supplies of this material is being actively pursuedwith the Iron and Steel Control.The supply of water-bottles is also affected by theshortage, but not to the same degree.Ik,  TEXTILES &amp; CLOTHING.The position in regard to the items referred to in theprevious report is as followsGreatcoats.      The weekly delivery rate has increased beyond the56,000 reported last month and is now in the region of 70,000.The production of material has almost reached 300,000 yards aweek.Ankle Boots.    The weekly production is now in the neighbourhoodof 120,000 pairs.-Battle Dress.  The production of this dress is being well maintained and is in the neighbourhood of 90,000 suits per week.The serge from which the garments are made is coming forward atthe rate of 500,000 yards per week.Rubber Knee Boots.    In addition to the 15,000 pairs per weekallocated to the Army from the industry&apos;s capacity, about70,000 pairs have been requisitioned from stocks in the hands-6- /of

of the wholesale dealers under a Ministry Order to meetimmediate and urgent requirements.Rubber Thigh Boots. . Approximately 10,000 pairs havesimilarly been requisitioned.Leather Jerkins.     Up to 28th October, 58,500 had been delivered.    The initial difficulties in obtaining suppliesof these articles are being overcome and it is expectedthat supplies will shortly come to hand at the rate of20,000 per week.Sheepskin Goats.    As a result of further enquiries, additionalfirms have been found to undertake this work and the numberplaced to contract is now 17,000.Steel Helmets.    These are being completed on behalf of the pool under the Ministry at the rate of over 100,000 per week,of which 50,000 are allocated to the War Office.Blankets     Additional orders have been placed for over1,000,000 and the rate of delivery is being maintained at about 200;000 per week.Ground Sheets.    The rate of delivery is 110,000 per week,and it is hoped that this rate will be increased to 150,000a week shortly.15.    Control of Shirts Order.    In order to meet an urgentrequirement of woollen vests for the Army, efforts were madeto purchase 250,000 from manufacturers&apos;* stocks, but only60,000 could be obtained in this way.    It became necessary,therefore,  to requisition and the Control of Shirts order was issued on i+th October.    These woollen vests are known in the trade as woollen shirts and the term &quot;woollen shirts&quot;was accordingly used in the Order.    Over 120 firms werevisited in the course of four days and the Order produced over200,000 vests.    In order to minimise the interference with civil trade,  each firm visited under the Order was given a formal release from the operation of the Order after its stocks had been inspected and suitable vests taken over.16-. Cotton.

II16. Cotton.    There has been, considerable difficulty in placingcotton orders.    The Cotton Board is fixing prices and1 pendingthe issue of the list - which may not be available until december - trading is difficult because manufacturers willnot commit themselves to fixed prices.The shortage of imports of raw cotton in the summer has helped to create a scarcity.PAPT IIP RAW MATERIALS.17.    The chief cause of anxiety in regard to supplies ofraw materials arises from the. scarcity of shipping.    Thewithdrawal of neutral shipping from many trades, and the closing, or partial closing, of some of the nearer sources of supply (such as those bounding the Baltic) have resultedin a heavy demand on United Kingdom shipping for long voyagG8eFor those materials which are under control, steps have been taken to put into effect the principles laid downby the Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy with regardto prices.    This involves,  in some cases, the averaging of costs of material bought before the war and of material which has subsequently been imported, as a first step towardsbringing the prices of these materials up to full replacementlevel.    Discussions have taken place v/ith a number of industriesnot at present under control in which some disturbance mightbe expected from v/ar conditions, and usually it has beenfound that voluntary arrangments with the industries concerned have been sufficient to enable supplies for essential usesto be maintained and the stability of prices to be preserved^18. Shipping.The general shipping position is, for the present,largely governed by the necessity of shipping cereals, sugar,oilseeds,  etc., to fulfil the Ministry of Pood&apos;s programme,and the approach of the &quot;close&quot; season on the St. Lawrencehas resulted in a number of applications to carry timber/being

hi a jbeing refused, the ships being directed to load grain instead.The effect of this action has been to restrict very considerably the quantity of timber coming to this country.This position has, however, been represented strongly tothe Ministry of Shipping, who state that timber is, where possible, being given almost equal priority with foodstuffs.Two other materials which have been in competition for shipping are iron ore and pyrites from Spain and north africa.    A number of shipowners applying for licences tocarry pyrites have been directed to load, iron ore instead,and the sulphuric acid industry has consequently become short of pyrites in certain localities.    Some preliminary meetingshave been held between the Iron and Steel Control and thepyrites importers, with the hope of arriving at an arrangement whereby the Foreign Ore Chartering Organisation of the Ironand Steel Control could arrange charters for both commodities,and so eliminate some of the competition between thorn,A list of raw materials ranking for priority forliner space has been prepared and forwarded to the Ministryof Shipping,  and is to be circulated by them to all lines.A provisional programme of imports of raw materials during november, December and January has also been prepared for theMinistry of Shipping to enable that Department to plan aheadas far as possible.19. Priorities.Review has been made by the priority organizationsof the probable supplies and requirements of a number ofmaterials and directions have been given regarding theprecedence to be accorded to various requirements includingthe export trade.    Appropriate directions have been givento the Controllers on the subject.20c Iron and steel.A new Order controlling the prices of iron andsteel has been issued. The Order permits an increase in price.    This was necessary to meet the rise in the cost

of imported materials.    Any rise in price involves additional      &apos;costs for coke and wages which are governed by sliding scalesrelated to the price of steel.    The increase in price, so faras it arises directly from material costs, passes, not intothe pockets of the manufacturers, but into a central fundcontrolled by the British Iron and Steel Federation, out ofwhich- the abnormal war-time costs of imports have been met.The prohibition of imports and exports of iron andsteel except under licence, and the future of the duties oniron and steel goods are questions now under&apos;consideration withthe other Departments concerned.Detailed estimates have been placed before theCentral Priority Committee covering probable steel productionand imports and the demands which will be made on the industry during the next 12 months by the Services, by other GovernmentDepartments and by the export trade    Further examination isoeing ma.de of the returns received and their relation to supplies.In anticipation of a shortage or iron and steelscrap, an appeal is being made to local authorities and to smallfirms which do not normally form part of the scrap collectingnachinery,  to collect all scrap which can be disposed ofeconomically.    The results so far are encouraging.21. Tungsten.Sanction has been obtained for a proposal to buy atlong-term contract prices up to a maximum of 10,000 tons forthe first year and,subject to satisfactory terms being agreed,the entire output of tungsten ores from the Empire and. from t-2ioBritish-owned Beralt Company in Portugal, together with supplies from any other available sources,    Negotiations for such contracts are now in progress,22. Molybdenum.Preliminary steps are being taken in co-operationwith the Ministry of Economic Warfare and the French Missionfor the purchase of the Norwegian output of molybdenum.   .,j!n /23. Chrome Ore,

mDiscussions have taken place with the Ministry ofEconomic Warfare regarding a proposal to guarantee theTurkish export of 200,000 tons of chrome ore,2h. Cobalt.The French Mission indicated that they were considering the erection of a refinery to provicfe theircobalt requirements,  and asked if wo would supply Rhodesianore and place an order for cobalt.    After discussion withthe Rhodesian producers, who have arranged for refining inCanada instead of in Belgium during the war, the FrenchMission are being informed that arrangements have alreadybeen made to deal with the Rhodesian ore and that Britishsupplies of cobalt are assured.25. Non-Ferrous Metals.Control of these metals has on the v/hole continuedto work reasonably smoothly having regard to the complexity of the trade and the temporary shortage of supplies ofelectrolytic copper, electrolytic zinc and aluminium. Therecent estimates submitted by Government Departments of their requirements for next year are considerably in excess of previous estimates and the significance of these figures isbeing explored and a revised global estimate is being prepared.The Non-Ferrous Metals Control Order was amendedon 23rd October (i) by removing from the price schedulezinc sulphide, lithepone   and zinc dust;  (ii) by increasingthe maximum prices for zinc oxide (Red Seal quality), zincsheets and boiler plates and adjusting the price of hardspelter;    and (iii) by fixing for the first time maximum prices for various forms of non-ferrous scrap.    arrangements are being made with the trade for the regulation of theprices of zinc sulphide and lithopone on a voluntary basis.During the month the Committee of tho London/Metal

Metal Exchange have adopted proposals for the closing oftheir contracts, and their commatments are now in processof liquidation.    It is expected that the whole processwill be completed early in December and that as a result the Ministry will take possession at controlled prices ofabout 18,000 tons of copper, all but 1,000 tons of whichwill be of blister quality,  15,000 tons of lead and 1+2,000tons of spelter.    The Ministry may under this arrangementbe called upon to supply 5,200 tons of copper (3,800 ofelectrolytic quality), 5,300 tons of lead and 5,800 tonsof spelter,  in order that the members of the Metal Exchangeor their clients may be able to meet their liabilitieswhere delivery of metal is insisted upon.    These stocksv/ill be of valuable assistance to the Controller in meetingthe present very heavy demand by consumers.    discussions on the amount of the commission to be allowed to motalmerchants for distributing Government metals are proceeding.Supplies of aluminium continue to bo inadequate to meet all requirements and the Controller has had to berigid in withholding supplies for non-essential purposes.In order to regulate supplies of aluriiiniurii more advantageouslyit has been decided that the Ministry shall undertake thebulk purchase and distribution of supplies.    Treasury approvalhas recently been given to the Ministry (1)  to purchase theentire output (hO,000 tons)  of the British Aluminium Co.,from their works in this country and Norway,  (2) topurchase 6,000 tons for delivery within the next six months fromthe Swiss Aluminium Co.,  (3)  to purchase 17,500 tonscontracted by the Aluminium Union Ltd., to bo delivered on private account in the United Kingdom and (h)  to negotiate with other Norwegian producers for the purchase of anyaluminium (not likely to exceed h,000 tons) which can bospared after the French demands have been met.    these purchases are in addition to h2,500 tons already purchased

in Canada and the U. S.A.    The Aluminium Control Order is* now in process of revision with a view to vesting in theController the sole responsibility for the purchase and sale of aluminium in the United Kingdom,The Air Ministry have appointed Controllers toregulate the four main branches of the light alloy industry concerned with the manufacture of material for aircraft and theso Controllers are working in close co-operationwith the Ministry&apos;s Aluminium Controller,During the month preliminary discussions havetaken place with representatives of the French MetalMission.    Their most urgent requirements are forelectrolytic zinc and electrolytic copper.    As regardszinc it has been suggested to them that their difficulties might bo partially overcome by putting down a refluxingplant either in this country or in France and proposals are now being formulated.    As regards copper, they havenow arranged for the Copper Cartel (comprising the producers in Rhodesia, Belgian Congo and Chile) to meet a largoproportion of their needs from Katanga and Chile.Various questions relating to non-ferrous metals of lessor importance such as antimony and cadmiumhave been under consideration.    Cadmium is a by-productin zinc manufacture and the principal sources of supply areCanada and Australia.    There is some production in theUnited Kingdom by the Imperial Smelting Corporation.    Thelatter source has boon restricted during the past few monthsowing to plant reconstruction, but the Canadians andAustralians are expediting deliveries and it is fullyexpected that by the end of the year the supply position will be comfortable and thereafter will be adequate to meet all requirements.    Efforts are being made to obtain areduction in price.26. Refractory Materials.As a result of the con..^rences which, took place lastCtl70 /month

9 H %month, with the makers of refractory materials used vorylargely in the iron and steel industry, a voluntary jointCommittee of the refractory brick makers and the &quot;steelmakers (which the Air Ministry have been invited to joinas representing roagnesfom metal makers) has now boon sot upto deal with the problems created by the cutting off ofsupiDlics of Austrian magncsite.    This Committee is nowundertaking the collective purchase of magncsite from other-sources and, provided that shipping facilities are available,there seems a reasonable prospect of their difficultiesbeing resolved.27. Sulphuric Acid: Raw Materials.(a) Pyrites.Discussions on the supply position of pyrites havocontinued with representatives of the French Mission and of theUnited Kingdom pyrites companies and latterly with arepresentative of the Colonial Office on behalf of, the Cyprusinterest.    No groat progress in concerting a general policyis, however, possible until the commercial negotiations between the British and French Governments and the SpanishGovernment are well in hand.(b) Sulphur.Treasiiry authority has been received for expendingup to  350,000 on Italian sulphur and arrangements wore madeto send out an expert to Italy to act for the Ministry,28. Fertilisers.(a) Superphosphate of Lime and. Compound Fertilisers.. ,Owing to the increases  in freight rates of rawmaterials and in other costs, it will be essential very shortly to authorise an increase in the price ofsuperphosphates and compound fertilisers.    The procedure adopted will require a return of costs by Individualmanufacturers v/ith a view to equating increases in costs and prices over the long term.    The Ministry of Agriculture-.:have been consulted and the National Farmers&apos; Union--lit- /informed

informed of what is proposed,(b) Sulphate of ammoniaPrices continue to be held voluntarily.    With aview to clearing the large stocks accumulating at Billinghamand elsewhere the British Sulphate of Ammonia Federation have offered to soil to farmers at the present low autumn pricestheir whole season&apos;s requirementsc    Owing mainly to storagediff difficulties,  the response by farmers has so far been disappointing,,    In view of this and the increasing stockaccumulation, the question of permitting an increase in thepermissible exports was brought under consideration with theBoard of Trade and the Ministry of Agriculture.    The proposals is that the Board of Trade should issue a general licence tothe British Sulphate of Ammonia Federation tc cover an amountlargely in excess of that exported in September and October, ...The interests outside the 3C, S0 As F, , who are represented on anindependent Committee, are to participate in the scheme,29. Mercury.The Control of Mercury Order was issued on 3rdOctober,  This provided for- maximum prices of the moreimportant mercury salts,  for a census of stocks to be taken,and instituted a system of licensing for the manufacture, useor consumption of mercury sulphide red.  This compound, whichis commonly called vermllions consists as to about 86 percent,  of mercury metal.   It is used as a pigment in rubber,printing inks, sealing wax,  toys, etc.,  these being requirements which, with the exception of dental rubber, can hardly he regarded as essential, For the time being the use of vermilion,stocks of 1 ewte,  or less for whatever purpose is being allowed,and licences are also being freely given for the purchase, etc,..,of vermilion to fill export orders for goods containing it.The dental rubber trade is also being kept supplied up to normal home and export requirements, but it is hoped to rationthe former use and the advice of the Medical Research Council

has been, sought on this. Other uses will be severelyrestricted and licences to use mercury for the manufacture ofvermilion, of which there are fairly substantial stocks, willbe granted only in exceptional circumstances.This control is operated from the Ministryheadquarters and a small committee,  elected by the trade,is available for advice.30. Tung Oil.A new demand for this oil, which is imported only from China, has arisen out of the manufacture of gas-proofclothing.  Owing to the delays in the arrivals of ships,  thestock position of the principal maker of these goods, alinoleum firm, became short towards the end of the month and the stoppage of manufacture was threatened. There are believed to be fairly substantial stocks in the hands of the paintmanufacturers (who,  if need be,  could substitute linseed andcertain other oils)  and an Order requiring a census of stockswas accordingly issued (27th October).  The possibility of having to requisition was considered, but fortunately&apos;.a boatcontaining 200 tons, which is a substantial quantity, arrived in London and by arrangement with the trade the whole of thiswas made available to the manufacturer of gas-proof clothing.The position is being v/atched very closely and the ministry is kept informed of individual shipments from China to thiscountry.31.    Calcium Carbide.A request was received, under the voluntaryarrangement fixed between the Board of Trade and the CarbideCommittee before the war,  for permission again to increase theprice of carbide on the ground of increased freights. Therequest was resisted, as it was felt that pre-war stocks heldgenerally by the industry were sufficient to carry the presentprice position for a further period.

32. Molasses.Further progress was made with the discussions withthe United Molasses Co.   regarding proposals to take over their stocks and to employ them as agents for further purchases. Thecompany have agreed to an examination of their books as a preliminary to presenting a case to the Treasury.33.  Timber.(a) Russian Agreement.Shortly after the beginning of the war the Russianscancelled their contracts with timber importers in thiscountry and a large number of steamers, twelve of which were british, were detained in White Sea ports,  loaded or partlyloaded.  In order to secure the release of these ships and the shipment of timber to this country an agreement was concludedon 11th October whereby Great Britain undertook to exchangerubber and tin for Russian timber.Six cargoes have so far arrived in this country andthirteen ships Ixivc recently sailed from  the White Sea.    It is hopedthat a further sixteen can be got away before the close of navigation.(b) Stock Position.Particulars of the stock of timber in this country have now been received and they show that supplies of softwood and pit props are dangerously low. Considerable purchaseshave been made abroad,  chiefly in Western Canada, but shipping difficulties have so far restricted deliveries.3h. Paper.Owing to the increase in cost of paper-making materials and in lesser degree to the increase of working costs,it has been found necessary to issue an Order increasing theprices at which paper may be sold in this country.  In orderthat the immediate increase in price may be as small as possible,all stocks of wood pulp, pulp wood, and esparto in the country,/and

9^?W  8   and further consignments of these materials as they arrive,have been requisitioned. The stocks so taken over are to bere-sold to tho mills at average prices which take intoaccount the estimated cost of further shipments coming tothis country up to tho end of the present year.  It isproposed to take over existing contracts held by mills forthe supply of those materials whore this appears to bedesirable,and purchases in future will be made by tho control on Government account. Imports of all paper-making materialswill bo allowed only under licence.Consideration is now being given to proposals forfurther economy in the consumption of paper and to thointroduction of a rationing scheme.3-5. Hides, Skins and Leather.The Central Purchasing Pool for imported hides isnow operating and supplies arc moving forward regularly. Toprevent tanners from making unreasonable profits from nativehides, for which maximum prices wore fixed at pro-war levels,the riiaoximum prices of native hides were increased toapproximate parity with world prices; the benefit of theincrease will go to the Ministry of Food as soon as they aroready to take over livestock..The supply of upper leather suitable for Servicefootwoar has been placed under control by licence and steps have boon taken to secure adequate supplies for Serviceroquirernonts at reasonable prices.36.  Cotton.Tho Ministry and the Board, of Trade have boon inconsultation with the Cotton Board regarding the form ofcontrol for tho cotton industry. Ponding further, considerationof the wider question involved in regard to the possibleoxerciso of powers provided for under the Cotton Industry(Re-Organisation) Act,  it is proposed that Sir Percy Ashleyshould be appointed Cotton Controller under the Ministry of-18- /Supply

Supply.    This proposal is now being considered by the     tC * JCotton Board.Proposals to purchase certain quantities of egyptian and Turkish cotton in order to deny supplies tothe enemy,and to compensate these countries for the loss ofthe German market, arc under consideration by the ministry and by other Departments concorned037. Rubber.Sir Walrond Sinclair has completed arrangementsfor the formation of a voluntary control for the rubberindustry.    A central &quot;control panel&quot; consists of SirWalrond Sinclair, Sir Charles Beharrell and Sir ThomasPurves.    They will have the assistance of advisory committeesrepresentative of the suppliers of rubber and other raw materials and of the various sections of the Indus tryc    The intention is to watch supplies and prices, and to advise generally asto the capacity and best use of the resources of the industry.In addition to purchases in the East of rubberrequired for the  cotton-rubber barter scheme with the U.S.A. ,substantial quantities of rubber are being bought in theUnited Kingdom to be set off against shipments of timber underthe recent agreement rath the U0 Sc Sc Ru38. Cement.There are still local shortages arising from transport difficulties and only the more urgent requirements can be met.The situation at Glasgow is now understood to be much easier,shipments having been made via the East Coast and sent acrossfrom Leith by rail.There has been a local shortage in the Manchester,area, but large deliveries are now being made    Consent hasbeen given to an increase in price of 2s per ton.39. Asbestos Cement.The output is equal to just over 55 per cent,  of theestimated Government requirements to the end of the year, and toabout 90 per cente  of their estimated requirements for the/first

z gofirst 6 months of 191+0.,    So long as the contingent A.R.P..demands (amounting to 60 per cont0  of the total) do not becomeactual the situation is not serious.    There is no evidence atpresent that control would be of any assistance,    Tho exporttrade and private demands can at present be met only to alimited extent0hO.  GraphitecThe French authorities have, since the beginning ofthe War, refused to export from Madagascar except under licence and licences have been,  and still are, very difficultto obtain.    At the request of the French Mission wo have given them an estimate of requirements for 1939 and 192+0*    A memberof the Mission who is about to visit Paris has promised todo everything possible to facilitate licences^There has been great difficulty in obtainingfreight space from Colombo for Ceylon graphite, which is usedfor foundry work.^* Asbestos, Beeswax, Candelilla Wax, Cork, French Chalk,Gums and Resinsg Turpentine.All these are boing watched.    There is no fundamentalsupply problem, but shipping difficulties create temporaryshortages.    The refusal of export licences is recommended as and when any shortage is threatened, but otherwise there isno reason to discourage the re-export trade in any of these materials.2+2. Mica.A compulsory census of stocks was held and the resultsanalysed.    On 13th October-a conference was held with Servicerepresentatives and the position reviewed.    Close and friendlycontact has been maintained with all sections of the trade.Principles for regulating export licensing have been worked out and are being applied.    The India Office has been consulted informally on the possibility of obtaining co-operation in India.    A second census of stocks is now boing taken.    It isnot necessary at present to suggest any extension of control.&quot;20- /h3o Bristles.

All sections of the trade wore brought together ata conference on 6th October,,    As a result,  a representativeCommittee was formed which moots at the London Chamber ofCommerce with a Chamber of Commerce official as Secretary.The supply position is easier, the re-export trade has been-cstablishod and no complaints arc being received.UU. Wool.The negotiations with tho Australian and NewZealand Governments for tho purchase of their wool clipsreached a stage at which it was possible to announco that agreement had been reached in principle for the purchase tobe made for the duration of the war and one clip year afterwards.The average price on a greasy basis is to be 10o75d (sterling)per lb. ,  representing in tho casrc of Australia an increaseof about 30 per cent0  on last year&apos;s price, and an increaseof 2.3 per cento  011 tho average price of the last threeyears.    In the case of New Zealand,  the bulk of whose clipis of a kind used for military purposes,   the price is tobe 9.83..per lbc  (sterling), being an increase of 33 per cent,on last year and an increase of 5 per centc on the average price over tho last three years,,    Tho approximate cost perannum is  h3 million (sterling)  in the case of Australia and 15 million (sterling)  in the case of New Zealand.,,    discussions are proceeding on detailscAn arrangement has been made with the South african government under which the United Kingdom Government will support the South African market,  if necessary, by purchases of wool up to  3e7 million,  in order to maintain the price level in South Africa up to that at which the Australian cliphas been purchased,    Tho amount is limited to that covered bythe former barter arrangements with Germany,,In the home market steps have been taken to requisitior.stocks of imported merino and crossbred wool at a price*1 -* / ap-pr oxima t e ly

approximately 10 per cent, above the pre-war prices and forthe re-issue to consumers at a price approximately 20 percent, above the pre-war lovel0    This should enable theindustry to carry on until early in the new year, whenprices will again require upward adjustment in the lightof the stock position and the higher prices of the imported wool.As regards home produced wool, stocks owned by merchants have been requisitioned on the same basis asimported wool and discussions are proceeding concerning thearrangements for taking over the wool remaining infa rme rs&apos; hands 02+5. Hemp.Negotiations have been almost completed as aresult of which supplies of sisal will be assured from east Africa at a reasonable price.    The Control is makingpurchases of other hemps abroad, but prices have risen byabout hO per cento    It is hoped that arrangements will be concluded with Italy for the purchase of 25,000 tone ofsoft hemp,  the bulk of which would be used in substitution for flax,2+6. Flax.The supply position remains acute and proposals are under consideration for the expansion of home production.Arrangements have been made for the purchase by theMinistry of this year&apos;s Northern Ireland crop,2+7. Artificial Silk.Approval has been given to an increase of 5per cent,  in artificial silk yarn prices consequent uponincreased &quot;costs of production0PART IV.. FINANCE.1+8. Employment of Outside Accountants.6Following Treasury approval of the employment of civilian firms to audit Controllers&apos; accounts, discussions-22- /are

are proceeding with the President of the Institute ofChartered Accountants in England and Wales, the Chairmanof the Joint Committee of Chartered Accountants of Scotland,and the President of the Society of Incorporated Accountantsand Auditors..   The inclusion of the Association of Certifiedand Corporate Accountants in the arrangements is beingconsidered..1+9. Marine and War Risks 0Discussions are proceeding with the treasury and other Departments concerned on the question of how far the Ministry should insure its cargoes against marine riskand as regards the arrangements for ascertaining theappropriate charges in respect of v/ar risk for the purposeof the Ministry&apos;s trading accounts,50, Requisitioned Ships.Inter-Departmental discussion is also taking placeregarding the financial arrangements to be made between theSupply Departments and the Ministry of Shipping in respectof requisitioned shipping.51. %t\ t Q gdq-qa r tmon t a 1 P inane i al Ad jus tnon t s u.It has been agreed between the Treasury, War Officeand Ministry of Supply that,  in general, financial adjustmentsbetween the War Office and the Ministry should be discontinued.The detailed arrangements to give effect to this agreement are under discussion. ,,52... Retention of Percentage of Contract Price.The practice of retaining a percentage of a contract pricepending investigation of the costs has been modified to theextent that payment is now made in full in those cases v/herethere is a further contract in hand from which recovery ofany overpayment might be secured.

&apos;3. Oasli Payments,Expenditure Total expend-from 3rd Sept. iture from 1stto 28th October.    August to 28thOctober.. .  .,, . .Jotal Cash Payments29,000,00038,000,000tin items of expenditure&quot;included In the above figures:MunitionsExplosivesTanks and Vehicles^Clothing and GeneralStores.Raw Materials.1U,357,0005,839,000h,77U,00019,^89,0008,297,000I+, 880,00055Estimated Amount of Expenditure on Capital Services. RawMaterials and Stores approved during October, 1939.-(1)    by the Treasury 56,000,000(2)    by the Finance Department(subject to coveringTreasury authority).             222,000The principal commitments by Controllers include(a) Purchase of Flax  1,500,000(b) &quot; &quot;   Hemp  1,780,000&quot;   Aluminium                                              8,000,000&quot; &quot;- Wool:-(c)(a)(i) Imported._______....... 20-25,000,000)(ii) Balance of) )Home Clip _________ 6,000,000) 31,000,000(e) Purchase of Tungsten Ores..Other- principal items of expenditure are:-(a) Shadow Factory for production of 12&quot;shell and 3*.7&quot; and other gun barrels.(b) 2 new Royal Ordnance Factories for.7&quot; and other gun barrels,,(c) 2 new Royal Ordnance Factories for -Bofors hO mm. barrels and 2pdr.  guns.(d) Completion of Chorley, Bridgend and   )Glascoed Royal Ordnance Factories. 1,800,000 1,120,000 1,800,000 l,36h,, 000 1,028,000

x (These figures do not represent the total commitments, asthey exclude commitments in respect of items for which specialapproval of the Finance Department or of the Treasury arenot required.)55. Commitments in difficult Foreign Currencies approved by treasury during October, 1939cMunitions.-(a) MaOMzke Tools(b) Others.ExplosivesRaw MaterialsTanks and TransportEquipment &amp; StoresTotalAmericanDollars,,CanadianDollars 180,54942,3754,18043,350132,000336,985   162,680750,0007,500600,000 lo 0,00.0Belgasj Swiss Ij Francs;FrenchFrancs9,586135,630739,4391,655, 8102,000162.0005,41313,410SwedishlKronerNorwegianKroner I&quot; 150,000PA, 9 9913,4101,275*000150,0001,275,0004- May be spent in lira, which is not a difficult currency,,1In addition to the above, special programmes for purchases in the U.S.A0   of machine tools for Royal OrdnanceFactories and Assisted Contracts have been approved, amountingto approximately  5i millions, of which some  3f: millions isin anticipation of services which will require further referenceto the Treasury in due course.    Otherwise the amounts offoreign currency shown above are included in the expenditureshown in the- total in paragraph 54oPART V.   CENTRAL PRIORITY DEPARTMENT.56. Production and Materials Joint Priority Sub-Committeo.Nine meetings have been held during the month ofOctober.    The more important matters discussed includeds-(i)      The supply and demand position with regard to thefollowing raw materials:-

(a)(b)Flax,Iron and Steel.(c)(a)(e)Aluminium.Timber and building materials,in conjunction with the Works and buildings Priority Sub-Committee.Other non-ferrous metals.(ii) Arrangements have been agreed upon with the Dominionsfor the working of the priority system with regard toorders placed in this country by the Dominions, andalso with regard to orders placed in the Dominions.(iii) Applications for Priority Certificates were submitted:-(e.)    by the Air Ministry for the production of light alloys ;(b)    by the Ministry of Supply for the production of machine tools,.In both cases methods of solving the difficulties were agreed upon without the necessity of issuing PriorityCertificates.57. Work has been continued on:-(i) Maintenance of Supply Board Paper No. 392, (allocation of the output of certain firms between GovernmentDepartments. )(ii) Preparation of Generic Code Book,  to provide a rapidmeans of assessing,  in respect of all types of stores,the raw material, labour and capacity required for their production,(iii) Preliminaries in connection with forms and recordsfor allocation of productive capacity.(Inrta^&quot;)   E.L.B.The Adelphi, W. C, 2.13th November, 1939.


</content>
</cab>
