<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/16/0 images: 88-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His $ritannicMajesty&apos;s Government).SECRET.PERSONAL NOTE BY THE SECRETARY OE A DISCUSSIONWITH REGARD TO THE LETTER FROM THE AUSTRIANEMPEROR,  PUBLISHED BY AUTHORITY OE THE FRENCHGOVERNMENT, APRIL 1918.This discussion took place on April 15,1918, as part of War Cabinet Meeting 391.(The Secretary was instructed to make no officialMinutes of the Meeting, &quot;but, for purposes of re-cord, it has been felt advisable to prepare thisPersonal NoteTlThe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs asked the WarCabinet what answer he should give to the following questionwhich was to be put to him that afternoon by Mr. Outhwaite:-&quot;To ask the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairswhether at the time, a year ago, of the refusal of theBritish Government to consider peace negotiations, andin particular the proposals of the Kerensky Government,he was aware that President Poincare was in possessionof a letter from the Emperor Karl of Austria stating thathe would support, by every means and use all his person-al influence with his Allies, the French just claims re-garding Alsace-Lorraine, and affirming that the sovereignty-eignty of Belgium should be restored, as also that ofSerbia with an outlet to the sea provided&quot;In the discussion that ensued the Prime Minister relatedthat he had met M. Ribot at Folkestone, and M. Ribot had shownhim the letter now revealed by M.  Clemenceau.    The Prime minister had made a copy of the letter in pencil which he was asked by M.ribot  to show to no one but the King.    The two Prime ministers had agreed that nothing could be done without consulting theItalians.At St.  Jean de Maurienne, on April 19th, the Prime Minister-had met Baron Sonnino, who flatly declined to negotiate withAustria and regarded the letter as a trick.    The letter, howeveijYwas not a trick, and the Prime Minister read a translation in  .J1.
which the words &quot;just claims&quot; represented the French original&quot;justes revendications!T.    The copy of the original French docu-ment was then read by Mr.  Bonar Law.The War Cabinet then discussed the advisability of publish-ing in this country and in France a facsimile of the originaldocument, with a view to sowing seeds of discord between austria and Germany.    They were, however, of opinion that it would be a mistake to insist too much on an occurrence revealing the EmperorKarl as a traitor to his Allies and a liar to us, as this wouldfinally close any avenue to a separate understanding between theAllies and Austria.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that hethought the best plan would be to return an answer in the House&apos; of Commons in the following sense:-That His Majesty&apos;s Government, after giving careful thought to the matter, considered that it was not inthe public interest to have any public discussion onthe subject.The Minister for Blockade pointed out that, while the answerwould be sufficient for the moment,  it must be anticipated thatthe question would be pressed further at a later date.    The ques-tion might then be asked why, if His Majesty&apos;s Government hadknown of the offer, they had not pursued it.To this it was pointed out the answer was that we had pur-sued it up to the point of Italian refusal to cooperate.    Our-reason,  therefore, was loyalty to our Allies.Another sanswer was that Emperor Karl had been offering whatbelonged not to him but to his Allies.This second point was reinforced by a second letter, datedMay 9th, from Emperor Karl to his brother-in-law, Prince Sixte ofBourbon, a,translation of which, as well as of the first letter,made by fcJao-JUufcteg, had been left by him with the Prime Minister&apos;Secretary.The War Cabinet approved the answerproposed by Mr. Balfour.Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.,April 15,  1918.

</content>
</cab>
