<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/4 images: 42-49</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1943.SECRET./Copy No.   3 3W.P. (43) 304.8th July, 1943.WAR CABINET.REDISTRIBUTION OF PARLIAMENTARY SEATS.Note by the Home Secretary.AT their meeting on the 16th June (W.M. (43) 86th Conclusions, Minute 5),the War Cabinet deferred a decision on the question whether there should belegislation creating permanent redistribution machinery pending considerationof a further memorandum by me. I circulated a memorandum on this question on the 25th June (W.P. (43) 274), but the War Cabinet, at their meeting on the28th June (W.M. (43) 89th Conclusions, Minute 6), decided to remit the proposalsfor preliminary examination by the Ministerial Committee on ElectoralMachinery.2. The Committee have now given careful and detailed consideration to my proposals, and they fully endorse them -in particular, that the Bill dealing withredistribution should include provision for setting up permanent redistributionmachinery on the lines recommended by the Departmental Committee. It was thought that a decision on the question whether or not there should be two separate Bills dealing respectively with electoral registration and redistribution-tion could stand over until more information was available as to probableprogress in preparing the necessary legislation.3. I accordingly now ask the War Cabinet to approve the proposals I madein W.P. (43) 274.4. The Parliamentary Secretary, Department of Overseas Trade, drew theCommittee&apos;s attention to the Motion, to which a number of Members ofParliament have put their names, urging the setting up of a representativeConference to consider the question of electoral reform. He pointed out thatin any debate on this Motion there would undoubtedly be raised the question of proportional representation, which, if accepted, would affect redistribution, and suggested that the Government should not commit itself as regards redistribution-tion until Parliament had been given an opportunity of such a debate. The othermembers of the Committee felt, however, that the Government should press on with the proposals.I made, and that Parliament should be informed at an earlydate of their decision. If it should so happen that at a later stage it were decidedto introduce some measure of proportional representation, a major Bill would clearly be called for, and any amendments (if required) as regards redistributioncould form part of that Bill.5. If my colleagues approve the Cabinet Committee&apos;s recommendation, Iwould propose to make a statement to the House of Commons at an early date on the lines set out in the Appendix.(Initialled)H. M.Home Office, S.W. 1, 8th July, 1943.[257101
APPENDIX.Proposed Parliamentary Statement.SINCE the last distribution of Parliamentary Seats took place in 1918, therehave been large changes in the distribution of population. In some constituenciesthe population has been greatly reduced; in others the population has doubledand in some places even trebled or quadrupled. For the purpose, therefore, ofmaintaining the principle that each vote recorded shall as far as possible commandan equal share of representation in the House of Commons, the case for a schemeof redistribution is established. The Departmental Committee on ElectoralMachinery, which included representatives of the main political parties,recommended that Parliament, when taking the necessary steps to correct themaldistribution now existing, should also make permanent provision for adjustingconstituencies to future changes in the distribution of population. TheGovernment propose to submit to Parliament legislation to give effect to theCommittee&apos;s recommendations. In such legislation it is proposed to set out thegeneral principles on which any scheme of redistribution should be based; toprovide for the appointment of Boundary Commissioners charged with the dutyof preparing schemes when occasion arises for distributing constituencies inaccordance with those principles; and to make provision for the submission ofany such schemes to Parliament for approval. By the passing of such legislation it is hoped to secure that a scheme of redistribution will take effect before the firstpost-war General Election is held. Thereafter there will be in existence a standingbody of Boundary Commissioners, who will keep the state of the constituenciesunder review and will be in a position, when any redistribution is required, toprepare schemes for Parliamentary approval. Under such an arrangementcomplete control over all measures of redistribution will remain with Parliament.2. The proposed legislation will be submitted as early as possible, but itspreparation will take a little time and, having regard to the state of parliamentary business, it will not be practicable to present it till after the Recess.







</content>
</cab>
