<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/150/0 images: 11-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
13 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS government cp(70) 2 COPY NO    g 023 June 1970CABINETMEMBERSHIP OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIES:OPENING STATEMENT FOR 30 JUNENote by the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs. Her Majesty&apos;s Government, together with the Governments of denmark, Norway and the Irish Republic, which have also applied for full membership of the European Communities, have been invited by theEuropean Communities to a meeting in Luxembourg on 30 June to open negotiations.    The meeting will be a short one, and an occasion for formalstatements only.    I attach for approval by my colleagues the draft of thestatement which the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster proposes to makeat the conference In Luxembourg on 30 June.2.        Provisional arrangements have been made by the Community forthe opening of their bilateral negotiations at Ministerial level with theUnited Kingdom formally to start on 21 July.   (The other three candidateswould have to wait until September).   At this opening meeting theUnited Kingdom representative would seek to set the stage for thenegotiations proper, which would begin in the autumn.    During this initial period, after the formal opening and before the negotiations proper, weshould seek, through working parties set up in July, to examine jointly with the Six and in considerable detail, the very complex problems whichwill have to be solved.    During this initial period of study of the problemsit will not be necessary for the United Kingdom to put forward, ortherefore to have decided on, its negotiating objectives? and one advantageof this approach is that by proposing no solutions we exclude none, and canexamine all,    A series of briefs by officials will be put before minister during the coming weeks on the basis of these we can decide on our objectives.3.        We are already being pressed for our agreement to the openingbilateral session on 21 July and will have to give an answer at the latestby the meeting on 30 June.1
4.        I therefore seek the agreement of my colleagues to accept this date for the following reasonsa. It is in our interest to persuade the Community to undertakewith us a joint examination of the problems to be solved.    If wecan agree on a common assessment it will be easier to secure agreement on solutions.    The process of examining the problemswill enable us to try out various possible lines of solution without commitment and make it easier to decide on the solutions we canaim for with reasonable hope of success.b. It is in cur interest that the Community should deal withour negotiations in a buoinesslike manner.    We are proposingon 30 June to make the point that we have waited so long to begin the negotiations that it is in our mutual interest to lose no more time; it could therefore be regarded by the Community asinconsistent to ask for a postponement of the meeting proposed for21 July,c. K we were to seek a postponement of our first bilateralmeeting with the Community until the autumn it would by then have become much more difficult for us to follow the tacticsdescribed above.    The Community would expect us by then tohave decided on and to declare our objectives, and to proposesolutions; a constructive period of joint examination would beharder to interpose in the process of negotiation,5.        The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster is of the same mind.A D-foreign and Commonwealth Office SW123 June 19702
Opening Statement for 30 JuneWhen the signatories of the Treaty of Rome created theEuropean Economic Community they called on the other peoples of Europe to join in their efforts to create an ever closerEuropean union,,   If Britain seemed slow to respond to thiscall, it was because real problems had to be solved if wewere to become full members, and the decision was not for usan easy one.   But successive British Governments have seenclearly the need for Europe to unite.   Sir Winston Churchillsaid twenty-two years ago.-.&quot;We must aim at nothing less than the union of Europe asa whole, and we look forward with confidence to the day when that union will be achieved&quot;.Mr. Macmillan foresaw the grave consequences that would followif division continued in Europe, and said that it would be &quot;a.canker gnawing at the very core of the Western Alliance&quot;,   inOctober 1961, Mr. Heath, opening negotiations with the communities, spoke of&quot;the increasing realisation that, in a world wherepolitical and economic power is becoming concentratedto such a great extent, a larger European unity hasbecome essential.   Faced with the threats we can allsee, Europe must unite or perish&quot;.And the previous British Government proclaimed in July 1967that &quot;unless Europe is united and strengthened she will notbe able to meet the challenge of the world today&quot;,
2.     in July 1961 the British Government answered the callof the signatories of the Treaty of Rome.   The hopes seton that response were disappointed.    In May 1967 the previousBritish Government applied to join the European Communities.Now there is a new Government in Britain and our determina-tion to find ways in which Britain may join with the otherpartners in the Communities as full members on fair terms andour belief in the need for a united and strengthened Europeare unimpaired.   For the reasons have grown stronger.3.     Europe was the cradle of the most potent and embracingcivilisation that the world has seen.    It set the pace andto a large extent the pattern of human progress.   But it hasbeen borne in on each of its component nations that noneacting alone can gain the ends which we desire for our ownpeoples in terms of physical security or economic or socialadvance.   Beyond our frontiers the world is no less dangerous.&apos;It is right that Europe should assume a greater share ofresponsibility for its own defence.   That is our jointconcern.h*     Europe&apos;s political and economic int-ere.sts areinseparable.   Our place in the world will be largelydetermined by the gro?/th of our resources and the pace ofour technological development.   And economic growth and technological development today require that we unite oureconomies and our markets.
5.     A united Europe must, of course,  take full account of the views of its friends and allies inother parts of the world.   But let none of us whoare taking part in these negotiations lose sight ofour common objective of European unity.   And letno-one who is not taking part think it could be in .his interest that we should fail to achieve thatobjective.   For given this base, we can not only hope for, but more effectively work for a closer and morefruitful relationship between Bast and west,   we can do more to promote the growth of international trade.And we can make a fuller European contribution tosolving the problems of less prosperous countries..6.     These are the reasons why we want to join you.We want to prosper with you.   But we do not seekprosperity for Europe alone, any more than you do.We believe with you that Europe still has its contribu-tion to make beyond its own frontiers and we believethat Europe cannot make its full contribution unlessthe Communities are enlarged to include Britain,/7.
7. We warmly welcome the decisions of the Governmentsof Denmark, the Irish Republic and Norway to apply to join the Communities.    We also believe that a number of european countries which do not join the Communities as full members will have a valuable contribution to make to many of our common objectives, and that it will be in the interest of all of us that these countries should find a mutually satisfactoryrelationship with the enlarged Communities.8.        Both Mr Heath in a speech last month and the previousBritish Government have made it clear that we accept the treaties establishing the three European Communities and thedecisions which have flowed from them,    I confirm that this isthe position of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, subject to thepoints to which I now turn.9- The list of questions which we wish to see covered in negotiations remains the same as those put forward by theprevious British Government in July 1967.    For Euratom and theEuropean Coal and Steel Community we seek only a very shorttransitional period. Adaptation to the obligations of theEuropean Economic Community will require more time than that,though here too I hope it can be agreed to move as soon aspossible in each case to full application of the obligations of membership.    We shall need to discuss with you solutionsto our main problem* which must be solved by agreementscertain agricultural policy questions; our contribution to community budgetary expenditure; Commonwealth sugar exports;New Zealand&apos;s special problems; and certain other Commonwealthquest ions.Ao
10. The position which our predecessors took in July1967 was,  of course, subject to developments in theCommunity in the meantime. In the field of Communitybudgetary arrangements, these developments have made theproblems facing our membership more difficult.    As you know,our predecessors had looked forward to Britain&apos;s taking part asa full member in the negotiation of the financial arrangementsfor the period after the end of 1969.    Had we done so, the resulting agreement would no doubt have made fair provisionfor us as it has for each of the existing members of the communities.    But we were not party to your agreement. And thearrangements which must in any case be agreed to enable a new member to take part in the budgetary provisions of theEuropean Communities will constitute one of the crucial elements in the negotiation on which we are embarking.    When theEuropean Commission gave its Opinion on our candidature inSeptember 1967,  it was recognised that the existing financial arrangements would,  if applied to Britain,  &quot;give rise to a problem of balance in sharing of financial burdens&quot;. The newdecisions have for us made that problem of balance more severe.We must together find a solution to this problem which will be fair and sound for the enlarged Community and for all its members.    For unless such a solution is found, the burden onthe United Kingdom would become intolerable and no BritishGovernment could contemplate joining.    Moreover, the basis of stability and confidence, and the community of interest whichwill bo essential to the further development of the communities would be lacking.
11. For the Communities must develop further.I am confident that our ideas for their development are verymuch in line with yours.    As Mr Heath declared a few weeks ago,we share your determination, to go on from what has alreadybeen achieved into new spheres of cooperation beginning witheconomic and monetary matters, but at the same time laying the foundations for a new method of working together inforeign policy&apos; and defence.    In all these problems, he added, we should seek to achieve solutions which areCommunity solutions.    We welcome the moves which you have undertaken towards closer economic and monetary integration.In other aspects of economic union we shall also want to seefurther progress;  in industrial policy, which should be amost important part of the Communities progress; in regional policy, whore we have common problems; and in thefield of technology where we -nre already engaged with you andothers in work on a number of studies, and where so muchmore can be done once the Communities have been enlarged.A?
12.    I have said enough today to show you that,  like their predecessors the British Government is determined to work with you in uniting Europe in new spheres;    in building a Europe whichhas a coherent character of its own.    If the Communities areto develop;    and if we are to find Community solutions to our common problems, we shall need the machinery to take the decisions.That means sharing in the continued development of effectiveinstitutions - effective to carry out the tasks which our jointexperience shows to be necessary.    That has always been our approach to institutional change.    What matters - to you andto us - is that oue objectives are the same, and we no less thanyou, will want the institutions to match those objectives.13.    I have said that,  like the previous Government, we acceptthe Treaties and their objectives.    But it is not simply a question for us of accepting what you have done.    Like you we look to thefuture.   As the Commission recognised in its Opinion of last october,  the accession of the candidate countries will be of great value for the Communities both in their internal development andin the exercise of increased responsibilities in the world,lh.     I have referred to the main points which we wish to see covered in negotiations.    Go far as other matters are concerned,  I would suggest that wherever it is reasonable we should settle them afteroifir entry into the Communities and so in accordance with yourprocedures.    We hope that negotiations can be kept short andconfined to essentials.    I notice that the problems which you have been discussing for the last six months in preparation forthese negotiations are very much the same as were set out by/the
the previous British Government in 1967.    We regard, these problems as common problems for us and for you - how to enable an enlarged Community to function most effectively for the advantageof all.    Our wish is to look together in the spirit of theCommunity for solutions which in the words of the Commission&apos;sOphion of 1969 will ensure the cohesion and the dynamism whichwill be indispensable in an enlarged Community.15.   -After waiting so long,  it is surely in our mutual interestto lose no more time.   We shall be prepared to meet whenever youare ready to meet, as often and as long as you wish.16.   Mr. Chairman, now - at last - we have the opportunity torealise together a Europe which has a coherent character of itsown.   We have the same defence interests;    our politicalinterests are growing every day progressively closer.   As wedevelop new policies together we shall, as I have said,  find itnatural to develop the institutional machinery which we shall need to execute these policies.    But this is not just a matter of economics and politics.    The history and culture of our Continentare the birthright of us all.    We have all contributed to it andwe all share it.     The vision which the founders of the Communitiesset before Europe was a generous vision for Europe as a whole.   Weshare that vision.    Our wish to join you derives from the sentimentwhich, as Europeans, we all share and from the idea we have of thepart which our Continent should play in the world.    If we cantogether succeed in the negotiations now begun &quot;then as SirWinston Churchill said there will be no limit to the happiness,/to
to the prosperity and glory which Europe&apos;s people will enjoy.So let none of us spare any effort in these neogtiations.Inspired by goodwill and united by so many aims and hopes and interests, wc can and must succeed.17.    Mr. Chairman;,, in view of the historic importance of thismeeting I am arranging for the text of ay statement to be made public in.the United Kingdom.


</content>
</cab>
