<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/150/0 images: 39-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNICMAJESTY&apos;S government cp(70) 6 COPY NO    d41 July 1970CABINETTHE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THEOPENING OF parliament note by the Secretary of the CabinetI circulate for the information of the Cabinet acopy of The Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening ofParliament in the form in which it has been approved byThe Queen.Signed   BURKE trend cabinet Office SWl1 July 1970
THE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE OPENING OFPARLIAMENTMy Lords and Members of the House of commons my Husband and I look forward to our visit to Canada on theoccasion of the centenaries of the Northwest Territories and of theProvince of Manitoba.The major international interests of Britain are the maintenanceof peace, the promotion of prosperity, the settlement of disputes byconciliation and agreement, and the encouragement of trade and peaceful exchanges between nations.My Government have welcomed the opening on the 30th of Juneof negotiations for membership of the European Communities. Inthese negotiations they will seek to reach agreement on terms fair to all concerned and will remain in close consultation with our commonwealth and EFTA partners and with the Irish Republic.My Government will work for the maintenance of the defensivestrength of the North Atlantic Alliance and for a genuine reductionof tension in relations between East and West in Europe.My Ministers will take a full part in the meeting of commonwealth Heads of Government in Singapore in January 1971.They will co-operate with our Commonwealth friends in measuresaimed at maintaining peace and stability in Commonwealth countriesin South-East Asia.I My Government will work for a fair and lasting peace in theMiddle East and for a settlement of the conflict in Indo-China.They will consult with leaders in the Gulf on how our common interests in that area may best be served.My Government will make a further effort to find a sensible andjust solution of the Rhodesian problem in accordance with the five principles.In this 25th Anniversary year of the United Nations, whichopens the Second Development Decade, My Government will lendtheir full support to international efforts to strengthen peace, topromote disarmament and to further world economic development.They will pursue an expanding aid programme and will seek agreement on tariff preferences for developing countries.My Government will work for the development and progressof Britain&apos;s dependent territories.A Bill will be placed before you to provide for the independence of Fiji.
My Government will review the role and size of the territorial and Army Volunteer Reserve.My Ministers will support the Northern Ireland Government intheir efforts to promote peace and harmony among all communitieson the basis of equality and freedom from discrimination, and tofurther the prosperity of the Province. I have noted with pride thepatience, skill and fortitude with which My Armed Forces are carrying out their difficult task.Members of the House of CommonsEstimates for the public services will be laid before you.My Lords and Members of the House of commons at home My Government^ first concern will be to strengthen the economy and curb the inflation. Rising production and a steadilygrowing national income must provide the resources for improving the social services and the environment in which we live. The energy and enterprise needed to achieve this will be encouraged by reformingand reducing the burden of taxation, providing new incentives tosaving and liberating industry from unnecessary intervention by government.My Ministers attach the greatest importance to promoting full employment and an effective regional development policy. Theywill stimulate long-term growth in the less prosperous areas by increasing their economic attractions and improving their amenities.My Ministers will start discussions with a view to encouragingagricultural expansion by changes in the present system of financial    isupport. They will promote the efficient development of the fishing industry.The work of the Industrial Training Boards will be reviewed andthe facilities for re-training and for management training improved and extended.A Bill will be introduced to establish a framework of law withinwhich improved industrial relations can develop and a code of practice will be prepared laying down standards for good management and trade union practice.My Government believe that vigorous competition is the bestsafeguard for the consumer. They will carry out a review of company law.My Ministers will pursue a vigorous housing policy with theprincipal aim of improving the position of the homeless and thebadly housed. After consultations with local authorities, housing subsidies will be refashioned so as to give more help to those ingreatest need. Home ownership will be encouraged.
My Government will expand educational opportunities asgrowing resources make this possible, with priority for theimprovement of primary schools. An inquiry will be instituted intoteacher training. Local authorities in Scotland, as in England andWales, will be set free to take effective decisions on the organisationof their schools.Responsibility for primary and secondary education in wales will be assumed by the Secretary of State for Wales.Legislation will be brought forward to provide pensions for persons now over 80 who were too old to enter the present insurancescheme and for certain younger widows and to provide a constantattendance allowance for the very seriously disabled.Legislation will be introduced on Commonwealth immigration.More assistance will be provided for areas of special social need,especially those in which large numbers of immigrants have settled.Effect will be given to the recommendations of the boundary commissions for the redistribution of Parliamentary seats.Proposals will be worked out in full consultation with allconcerned, for local government reform in England, Scotland andWales, associated with a general devolution of power from the centralGovernment. At a later stage plans will be laid before you for giving the Scottish people a greater say in their own affairs.Proposals will be put forward for permitting commercial local radio stations under the general supervision of an independentbroadcasting authority.A Bill will be brought before you to abolish the land commission.My Ministers will intensify the drive to remedy past damage tothe environment and will seek to safeguard the beauty of the Britishcountryside and seashore for the future.Bills will be laid before you to improve the arrangements for theadministration of justice in England and Wales in accordance withthe recommendations of the Royal Commission on Assizes andQuarter Sessions and to improve the organisation of the SheriffCourts in Scotland.My Government will make it their special duty to protect thefreedom of the individual under the law and will examine ways inwhich this may be more effectively safeguarded.Other measures will be laid before you.My Lords and Members of the House of commons I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon your counsels.


</content>
</cab>
