<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/150/0 images: 53-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^S government cp(70)8 COPY NO    541 July 1970CABINETBILL, TO IMPLEMENT PRIORITY social security PLEDGESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Social ServicesMy colleagues will wish to know that I shall be presenting and publishing a Bill on Friday 3 July which will require Royal Assent by24 July.    The Bill will implement our 3 priority Election pledges to give some pension as of right to the over-80s who now get noretirement pension at all.To improve the present situation where a woman who is just over50 when she is widowed gets a pension but a widow just under 50gets nothing.To introduce a constant attendance allowance for the most seriouslydisabled.The last two proposals are the same as proposals made by the previous government,PENSIONS FOR NON-PENSIONERS2.        Retirement pensions will be paid to persons who did not qualifyunder the pre-1948 schemes and who were unable to become insured underthe present scheme because they were over pensionable age at July 1948.Provision will also be made for wives and widows, Including widows whosehusbands would have acquired title had they lived.    There will be a simpleresidence test.    The single rate of pension is to be  3 and the married rate 4 17. 0,    (The very few people in this age group who qualified for modifiedpensions below this rate will be brought up to it).    There may be up to100,000 beneficiaries, and the cost in the first full year would be  7 millionnet of savings in supplementary benefits, thereafter falling rapidly,provided that we can (as we must) resist pressure to extend the new pension to people outside this age group drawing less than the standard pension.    The,cost is to be met from the Exchequer; &apos; The effective date is planned to be4 November 1970, coincident with the forthcoming Supplementary benefit increases.1J
PENSIONS FOR YOUNGER WIDOWS3.        A woman who in future is widowed when between 40 and 50 or whoceases to be entitled to widowed mother *s allowance when between these ageswill qualify for a widowf&amp; pension at a rate which will depend upon her age at the time.    The rate will be stepped down from the standard rate by7 per cent for each year by which her age falls short of 50, ie. the pension will range from 30 per cent if she was 40 to 93 per cent if she was 49.Regulations will apply these provisions to women already widowed who wouldhave met the conditions.    It is estimated that there will be 100,000beneficiaries at an annual cost of  13 million net from the National insurance fund.    The effective date of this proposal has yet to be decided, but it is highly desirable that it should follow as closely as possible after Royal Assent.Administratively this would be practicable in April 1971.ATTENDANCE ALLOWANCE4.        The attendance allowance, designed to be an entirely new benefit for the most severely disabled, will be a weekly allowance of  4 (less for young children) for anybody who is so severely disabled that -a. he requires from another person, in connection with hisbodily functions, frequent attention throughout the day or repeatedattention during the night;   orb. he requires continual supervision from another person inorder to avoid substantial danger to himself or others.The need for attendance must have lasted for six months; it is not intendedto provide for short-term acute or terminal illnesses.    The allowance willbe payable out of the Exchequer subject only to the satisfaction of conditionsas to residence or presence in Great Britain,5.        The question whether anyone needs attendance to the extent requiredwill be determined by the Attendance Allowance Board, a new body to be composed mainly of highly qualified doctors.6.        The total cost of the allowance at the proposed rate of  4 for adults(and  2 a week for young children) is estimated to be of the order of 10 million in the first full year on the basis of 50,000 successful claims.I must emphasise, however, that the figure of 50, 000 successful claims canin the nature of things itself be by no means precise.7.        I hope to be able to start payment of the allowance from the beginningof April 1972.    The timetable necessary to achieve this date is already a verytight one - we have to set up and consult the Attendance Allowance Board and do much other preparatory work and then need time to take on as many as100, 000 claims.    But the timetable can be adhered to given Royal Assent tothe necessary legislation before the summer Recess, and I propose to announce the intended starting date in the House in the course of theproceedings on the Bill.2
PENSIONS FOR YOUNGER WIDOWS3,        A woman who in future is widowed when between 40 and 50 or whoceases to be entitled to widowed rnotherls allowance when between these ageswill qualify for a widowrs pension at a rate which will depend upon her age at the time.    The rate will be stepped down from the standard rate by7 per cent for each year by which her age falls short of 50, ie. the pension will range from 30 per cent if she was 40 to 93 per cent if she was 49.Regulations will apply these provisions to women already widow/ed who wouldhave met the conditions.    It is estimated that there will be 100,000beneficiaries at an annual cost of  13 million net from the National insurance fund.    The effective date of this proposal has yet to be decided, but it is highly desirable that it should follow as closely as possible after Royal Assent,Administratively this would be practicable in April 1971.ATTENDANCE ALLOWANCE4.        The attendance allowance, designed to be an entirely new benefit for the most severely disabled, will be a weekly allowance of  4 (less for young children) for anybody who is so severely disabled that -a. he requires from another person, in connection with hisbodily functions,, frequent attention throughout the day or repeatedattention during the night;   orb. he requires continual supervision from another person inorder to avoid substantial danger to himself or others.The need for attendance mu?t have lasted for six months;  It Is not intendedto provide for short-term acute or terminal illnesses.    The allowance willbe payable out of the Exchequer subject only to the satisfaction of conditionsas to residence or presence in Great Britain,5.        The question whether anyone needs attendance to the extent requiredwill be determined by the Attendance Allowance Board, a new body to be composed mainly of highly qualified doctors.6.        The total cost of the allowance at the proposed rate of  4 for adults(and  2 a week for young children) is estimated to be of the order of 10 million in the first full year on the basis of 50, 000 successful claims.I must emphasise, however, that the figure of 50,000 successful claims canin the nature of things itself be by no means precise.7.        I hope to be able to start payment of the allowance from the beginningof April 1972.    The timetable necessary to achieve this date is already a verytight one - v/e have to set up and consult the Attendance Allowance Board and do much other preparatory work and then need time to take on as many as100, 000 claims.    But the timetable can be adhered to given Royal Assent tothe necessary legislation before the summer Recess, and I propose to announce the intended starting date in the House in the course of theproceedings on the Bill.2
PUBLICITY8.        My colleagues will wish to know that I propose to make ain the House on Friday 3 July to announce these proposals; andis in hand.K department of Health and Social Security SE130 June 1970


</content>
</cab>
