<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/150/0 images: 66-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SALE OF ARMS TO SOUTH africa memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Cabinet will wish to consider the policy we should adopt on thesals of arms to South Africa and the draft statement on this which it isproposed that I should make after Questions on Monday 20 July.2. The draft statement reflects agreement reached with my colleagues in the Defence and Oversea Policy Committee on the terms to be used indefining our future policy and on its general presentation.    Our intentionshave been explained on this general basis in messages sent to commonwealth Heads of Government and to certain other Governments.This policy is consistent with reservations made Li relation to security council Resolutions on arms for South Africa by the previous conservative administration,l3.        Widespread speculation about the prospect of our renewal of armssales to South Africa has already led to expressions of concern and opposition both overseas, particularly in Africa, and domestically.Against this background the following paragraphs summarise the pros andcons of our adopting the policy outlined in the statement, and announcing itearly.THE PROS4,        The following are some of the main arguments in favour of our proposed policy and of proceeding with an early announcement;&quot;Defence interestsa.        As a Party, we have consistently said during all the yearsof opposition that when we were returned to power we would operate the Slmonstown Agreements and license arms for South Africa in the context of external defence.CP(70) 12 COPY NO   5415 July 1970CABINET
SALE OF ARMS TO SOUTH africa memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Cabinet will wish to consider the policy we should adopt on thesale of arms to South Africa and the draft statement on this which it isproposed that I should make after Questions on Monday 20 July.2. The draft statement reflects agreement reached with my colleagues in the Defence and Oversea Policy Committee on the terms to be used indefining our future policy and on its general presentation.    Our Intentionshave been explained on this general basis in messages sent to commonwealth Heads of Government and to certain other Governments.This policy is consistent with reservations made Li relation to security council Resolutions on arms for South Africa by the previous conservative administration,3.        Widespread speculation about the prospect of our renewal of armssales to South Africa has already led to expressions of concern and opposition both overseas, particularly in Africa, and domestically.Against this background the following paragraphs summarise the pros andcons of our adopting the policy outlined in the statement, and announcing itearly.THE PROS4.        The following are some of the main arguments in favour of our proposed policy and of proceeding with an early announcementDefence interestsa. As a Party, we have consistently said during all the yearsof opposition that when we were returned to power we would operate the Simonstown Agreements and license arms for South Airica in the context of external defence.CP(70)12 COPY NO   5415 July 1970CABINET
b. The reason for that attitude has been the increasingencroachment of the communist powers into the Indian Ocean.The Soviet maritime build-up, particularly their submarine fleet,constitutes a latent threat to the continued security of the Caperoute, upon which, more than any other nation, we are dependentin terms of carrying goods and oil.    The existing Russian influence in Aden and Somalia will be much increased when the Suez Canalis open.c. The Chinese have been expanding their influence inTanzania.    In addition to building the TANZAM railway they aretraining Tanzanian forces and building a base for the Tanzaniannavy,    Mauritius has concluded an arrangement for giving facilitiesfor a Soviet fishing fleet.d. To the extent that other West European natioxis are alsodependent on the route, our action in allowing the South Africansthe maritime defence equipment they need is important to western defence as a whole.    NATO does not accept responsibility for thesecurity of allied shipping in the Indian Ocean; and we cannotguarantee safe passage In these seas by ourselves,    TheSouth Africans are the only country in the area equipped to contribute to this task.Evolution in South Africae. From the point of view of peaceful evolution withinSouth /if rica, it is important that South Africa is not furtherisolated.    This could only have the effect of strengthening thosei   most opposed to evolution, of making them less susceptible toexternal pressures and of creating a less favourable climate forthe operation of those economic forces which are most likely toproduce in the long run the kind of change in their social systemall would like to see.Effect on British-South African relationsf. Although there is no hard evidence that the arms embargohas affected our general trade with South Africa, it has affectedgeneral relations and there has always been the risk that this couldreflect on aspects of our trade.    A decision now to maintain the arms embargo without any relaxation would be a bitter disappointmentto white South Africans and would leave cur relations even worse thanthey have been, with consequently greater risk of damage to our economic interests.    Conversely a decision to relax the policy wouldpromote a better climate for these interests, quite apart from the direct benefits from sales of defence equipment coming within theproposed policy.2
3g. To backtrack now, after havkig told commonwealth governments of our intentions, would inevitably be interpreted as giving In to implied threats and would increase pressures onusin the future over other issues.    Delay in announcing our policy would Increase present pressures and the risk of pre-emptiveaction, eg. at the United Nations.THE CONS5.        Arguments against the proposals includeAfrican relationsa. African Governments will see the decision as a deliberatechoice by Her majesty is Government in favour of their most hatedenemy and therefore against themselves.    They will react againstwhat they regard as Britalnfs bringing South Africa back intorespectable company, and giving her encouragement in her present policies,    Theii strong emotions will tend to make it moredifficult for us to work with or influence them in the immediatefuture, and will polarise even more the attitudes north and south ofthe Zambezi,The Commonwealthb. African reactions wi?l be shared La varying degree by anumber of other Commonwealth Governments outside Africa,including Canada.    There have already been inter-Governmentalcommunications on the question, stimulated by Zambia.    At the worst, reactions could be built up to the extent that there might bepressures on some Govei*nments to leave the Commonwealth or -more likely - to boycott the forthcoming meeting of CommonwealthHeads of Government, or to show displeasure otherwise in theCommonwealth context.United Nationsc. Reactions against our policies are likely -to be brought to afocus at the United Nations.    There are already signs of Afro-Asianintentions of promoting a Security Council debate v/ith the aim of passing pre-emptive Resolutions against any weakening of the arms embargo.    The Soviet Union are encouraging these activities.Generally, and at least in the short term, our standing at theUnited Nations will be adversely affected by a change in policy.This will increase our problems over eg. Rhodesia and South WestAfrica.
d. In some cases Afro-Asian reactions may lead to decisions affecting United Kingdom material interests:i. Possible loss of contracts by United Kingdom suppliers.ii. Commercial discrimination against the United Kingdom.Strategice. It is said that the emotional reaction of African governments could make it easier for the Russians and the Chinese to increase their political and military influence, particularly in Tanzania andZambia.    Generally, reactions by extremist Africans denouncingthe British stand will reduce the ability of the more moderateAfrican leaders to hold to reasonably balanced internal and externalpolicies.     In fact the Russians do exactly what they like.f. The United States have informally expressed some concernlest our common interests in Africa should be affected by the considerations mentioned above,    Mr. Rogers has said that theUnited States Government are for the present committed to maintaining the arms embargo.    He will try to recognise thatwe have a special position and problems over oil routes whichAmerica does not have.g. The South African Minister of Defence has suggested a revision of the Simonstown Agreement.    He is primarily concernedwith the continuity of the supply of spares and no doubt interestedin a possible closer association with NATO.ASSESSMENT OF ECONOMIC INTERESTS6. A brief reference is made above to the possible effects of a changein policy on our economic interests.    Recent studies by the AssessmentsStaff confirm earlier conclusions that our stake in Black Africa in termsof trade is about the same as in South Africa.    Direct private investment in Black Africa is rather less than in South Africa and outstanding port-folio investment by United Kingdom residents is only about one-tenth ofthat in South Africa.    This, however, excludes oil investment which, in nigeria alone, substantially exceeds oil investment in South Africa.    Thelarge holdings of sterling balances in Black Africa can, in this assess-ment, be set against the need to take account of our aid expendituresthere.
lYyyy:-R E COMMEND A TIONS7, It is clear that a change of policy even when it is confined to armssupply for the defence routes, will rouse emotions, in particular amongAfrican members and some Asian members of the Commonwealth.    Itis to be hoped that their reactions will be limited to words.    I will reportthe latest indications to Cabinet.8. Against these risks we have to place our consistent and publishedview and our duty to make our own judgment of our own defence interests.9. I therefore invite my colleagues to agree that I should make astatement on 20 July anncuncing our policy on the lines set out in the annex.A D-foreign and Commonwealth Office SV/l15 July 1970
AnnexArms for South AfricaDRAFT STATEMENT TO THE HOUSE OF commons I promised that I would make a statement before theHouse rose on the Government&apos;s attitude to the Simons town.Agreement with South. Africa.2.     The last Conservative government operated the armslicensing system so as to distinguish between those armswhich might be used in civil strife and those which couldbe used for external defence.3.      It was to mark this distinction that the governmentvoted in the United Notions for a ban on arms which couldcontribute to enforcing apartheid while expressly preservingBritain&apos;s right to export arms aooording to tho torma of tho-Charter in relation to external defence^   * jjT ^ ^   cia^kr4.      The government have now re-examined the matter in thelight of present and future strategic needs and have beenin close communication with allies and friends both inside and outside the Commonwealth.5.     HMG&apos;s particular responsibility and concern is for thefree passage of ships in all circumstances on the vital searoutes round southern Africa.    Our own defence intereststherefore require that we should give effect to the purposesof the Simonstown Agreement.   With these considerations inmind, HMG- have decided in future to accept orders for arms from South Africa but only insofar as they are directly related to maritime defence of the sea routes to which Ihave referred.   Applications for licences falling within this definition will be considered.    In so acting, HMGconsider that they will be fulfilling the joint purpose ofthe Simonstown Agreement and serving the security requirements of Britain.6.     HMG have made abundantly clear their fundamentaldisagreement with the racial policies of the South african government.   Under the policy which I have announced,  our/licensing
Annex (contd)licensing arrangements will ensure that arms are notexported which would assist in the enforcement of apartheidor internal repression:      the decision which has been madeis fully in accordance with our obligations under the united nations Charter and with the position adopted in the security council in 1963 and 1964 by the previous conservative administration.

The circulation of this memorandum has been restricted to members of the Cabinet and to ministers in charge of Departments,    Recipients are accordinglyasked to ensure chat the secrecy of its contents is strictly observed.

</content>
</cab>
