<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/57/0 images: 72-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>

Tel. $o. Abbey 3411.AIR MINISTRY^King Charles StreetWhitehall, s.w.1.Ext.17th October, 1940Dear Wilkinson,I understand that you like tohave a record of the variousMeetings of Ministers below theLine.I send you herewith a note ofthe Meeting which my Secretary ofState had with them last Monday.W.D.Wilkinson Esq., D.S.0., M.C.Offices of the War Cabinet,Richmond Terrace,S.W.1.Yours sincerely
Record of Meeting of Ministers below the lineat the Air Ministry of Monday, October 14th 1940The following were presents-Mr. L.G.M.S. Amery.Mr. W*S.Morrison.Mr. Ernest Brown.Lt.Col. Moore-BrabazonLord SimonLord HankeyMr. Geoffrey Lloyd.Mr. Hugh BaitonMr. R.HoCrossMr. H. Ramsbotham.Lord WooItonCaptain Harold Balfour.In attendance: Mr. R.H.MelvilleMr. F.Wood.The Secretary of State for Air dealt with the followingpoints:-1. Fighter Command Operations................................ 1-pihbiAhw* -mm umiiii.....The changed character of present operations.Previously, heavy bomber forces had come over with strongfighter escorts, governed in speed and maneouvreability bybombers.     These had been easily broken up and as a result achange of tactics had been instituted.   Now the Germans come in in large formations consisting mainly of fighters, some ofthe fighters carrying bombs.   A few of the waves consistof fighters with a small number of bombers*   Waves oftencome in at great height.   The Germans turn back except on occasions when they find themselves at a tacticaladvantage, e.g. when our fighters have had insufficientwarning and are unable to gain adequate height.   Mainattack is often preceded by one or more feint attacks whichit may follow as much as an hour later.At over 30,000 feet and indeed less, the Hurricaneis found not a match for the Messerschmidt.   The Spitfireretains its superiority.   More powerful engine is being introduced into the Hurricane which will give it the performance of the present mark of Spitfire.   This willrestore its superiority.2. Bomber operations.Air Staff policy aims at the reduction of theenemy&apos;8 war potential, in consultation with M.E.W., butinevitable diversions, e.g. the heavy weight of the attack onthe Channel ports and more recently the attack on the Germanheavy ships at Wilhelmshaven.     Difficult to get the measureof success against the ships.   For the rest, oil, aircraft factories and special metal factories, marshalling yards areattacked also Berlin where power stations, etc. have beenobjectives.   Alson, on one occasion, the centre of GovernmentsDamage inflicted upon power stations, gas works, etis more likely to effect public morale than indiscriminatebombing of houses.   Bombing of marshalling yards definitely/effective.8
1 I   SIeffective measure, e.g. the traveller who took IS days to get from Holland to Switzerland and was unable to travel viaBerlin or the Rhineland.3. Coastal CommandoRoutine reconnaissance and anti-submarine work. Alsobombing of invasion ports.   Activity of the photographic reconnaissance unit at altitudes over 30,000 feet.4. Production.Considerable fall last month.   This largely due notto damage by bombs but to upset of work through air raid warnings.   Total production last month 1,350 includingtrainers.   Difficult to be sure but over the last four monthswe are probably definitely ahead in production.   Difficult toestimate effect of our bombing against the enemy18 aircraft industry.5. Pilots.Figures show marked improvement:-June 15th      - Establishment 3,750: Deficiency 650Beginning ofOctober        - Establishment 4,360: Deficiency   41During this period we had been suffering casualties at therate of some 400 a month.    But this is, to some extent, a paperrather than an actual improvement.    Certain squadrons,especially those which have been doing the hard fighting have adefinite deficiency of pilots ready to take the air.   System of bringing in fresh pilots from fresh squadrons.Training going up.     May and June,25 per cent, up onprogramme.   August, 50 per cent up.The need to get men into squadrons means that we arepassing them through training organisations faster than wewould like and they have, to some extent, to complete their training in the squadrons.   This is, in fact, in fighter command, a reversion to the old system before operational training units were established.Accelerated progress of Empire Air Training Scheme*Over 100 pilots expected next month instead of 35.   In March350 instead of 250.   The same enthusiasm in Australiaf SouthAfrica and Rhodesia.     General Smuts* offer of pilots.The German pilot position.    So far morale in generalvery good and training good.   Average length of service ofprisoners greater than ours.    Exception to find a pilot notin the German Air Force before the war but some reductionin the standard of crew personnel.6. The weight of the enemy&apos;s attack on this country6Reference to P.M.&apos;s remarks in the House ftf Commons.Amplification of the basis of calculation of the P.M.*s figures^Germans working from advanced bases under some difficulties.They might possibly manage, say, 1,200 sorties a night for a couple of nights.A
Necessity for reinforcing the Middle East fully realised but must be balanced against needl f or maintainingstrength at home.   Nevertheless substantial measures ofreinforcement being undertaken, establishments are being increased, squadrons re-equipped with modern types, andmobile maintenance and servicing units being sent.At present no major operations in progress.Italian quiescent, German reinforcements not inevidence.     Bomber operations directed towards main ports,Tobruk and Benghazi, so as to hinder enemy reinforcements.Q* Comparative British and German strengthscThe R.A.F. shows an increase of 600 aircraftfirst line and reserves, between May and September.Estimated German strength has decreased over the same period by 2,000.Our strength we hope will continue to increase and that of Germany diminish, in particular because of successful bombing attacks on the German aircraft industry.No doubt that better training, specialisation in night flyingand careful planning has resulted in R.A.F. bombing operationsbeing much more effective than the German.9. Night Air Defence.Installation of apparatus to enable fightersto find enemy aircraft at night proceeding rapidly.Still technical difficulties but these should be solved in the fairly near future.     Apparatus installedin old type machines has already operated with some success.     Installation in newer types proceedingsSimilar apparatus designed to assist nightA.A. gunnery also being introduced.


</content>
</cab>
