<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/57/0 images: 84-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
13th September, 1940,Dear Bridges,I enclose a rough note of the proceedings atthe Meeting held here yesterday when the HomeSecretary spoke to Ministers not members of theWar Cabinet about - certain matters connected with civil Defence.As you know, the first question discussed at this Meeting had been raised at the Meetingof the Civil Defence Committee on Wednesday last;and you may like to let Howorth see this part ofthe note.   I imagine that it will not be thought necessary to refer to this matter again at next week&apos;s Meeting of the Civil Defence Committee, butHoworth may wash some reference made to this meeting in order to clear the Minutes of last WednesdaysMeeting. -Sir Edward Bridges,K.C.B., M.C.
Note of Proceedings at a Meeting of Ministers held inthe Home Secretary&apos;s room at the Home Office onThursday, the 12th September, 1940, at 5.45 p.m.PRESENT;The Eight Hon.Sir John Anderson, G.C.B., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Secretary of State for the Home department and Minister of Home Security.I.P.The Right Hon.Viscount Simon, G.C.S.I., G.C.V.O.,O.B.E. ,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Lord Lloyd, G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,D.S.O.Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour &amp;National Service.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M.P.,Secretary of State forScotland.The Right Hon.Sir John Reith, G.C.V.O., G.B.E.,Minister of Transport.CaptainI.P.,        A. U. Ma&apos;, Hudson, M.P.,Civil Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.H. S. Morrison, M.P.,Minister of Supply.Mr. Geoffrey W. Lloyd, M.P.,Secretary for Petroleum.The Right Hon.Lord Woolton,Minister of Food.Air Vice-MarshalW. Sholto Douglas, M.C., D.F.C.Assistant Chief of theAir Staff.Wing CommanderJ. Whitworth Jones,Air Staff.general sir William Bartholomew, G.C.B., C.M.G., D.S.O.Chief of the Operational Staff,Ministry of Home Security.
referred to certain criticisms of our active defences which had beenbrought forward at a meeting of the Civil Defence Committee theprevious day and said that he had arranged for Air/Marshal Sholto-Douglas to be present at this meeting in order to give some information about the arrangements for active defence against air attack.Air Marshal Sholto-Douglas described the arrangements made for defence against night attack.       As regards anti-aircraft gunfire,he said that two changes had recently been made - (a) a large numberof guns had been moved back to London from other parts of the countryand (b) the previous instructions that guns should fire only ataircraft illuminated by searchlight had been withdrawn, and guns were now instructed to fire by sound.      As regards fighters, he explained the reasons why fighter aircraft had not hitherto been allowed to operate within the artillery zone round London;   but he said that ithad now been decided to make in the near future, when weather conditions were favourable, the experiment of allowing fighters to operate overCentral London - particularly over areas where large fires were likelyto attract enemy bombers.        Future policy would be determined in thelight of the success of this experiment.All the Ministers present testified to the excellent moral effectof the anti-aircraft barrage of the previous night.      It was unanimously agreed that, whatever the material results might have been, the psychological effect was most valuable.        The Minister of Laboursaid that, while he appreciated the importance of making the experimentof allowing fighters to operate over London, he hoped that for the nextfew days at any rate this experiment would be deferred so that the barrage might be maintained.        He said that on Wednesday there hadbeen a very real danger of demonstrations by workers in East london to protest against the want of evident defence against the enemy1 attack.      Last night&apos;s barrage had done a great deal to allay thisanxiety among workpeople, and he thought it most important that the barrage should be maintained for several nights in order to ensurethat the people*s confidence in our defences would be maintained.
He also made the point that workpeople would be more willing tocontinue at work during an air-raid if they could hear, from the sound of gunfire, that a vigorous defence was being maintained.The Minister of Labour also referred to the attack on theVickers Works at Weybridge and said that much harm was being doneamong industrial workers by the rumours which were spreading throughoutthe country about this particular attack.        It was being widelyreported that no guns had fired on this occasion either because theguncrews were at lunch or, alternatively, because the officers incharge of the guns were not allowed to fire until they received orders from some central authority.        Air Marshal Sholto-Douglas explained the circumstances in which this particular attack was delivered without warning and said that it was inevitable that on occasion the defences(which could not be kept continuously manned day and night) should betaken by surprise.      He made it clear, however, that there was nofoundation whatsoever for the suggestion that officers in charge of guns had to wait for orders from some central authority before firingat enemy aircraft.The Minister of Labour referred to the suggestion that therewas insufficient co-ordination in our defences.      Air Marshal Sholto-Douglas explained the system of control, and made it clear that theAir Officer Commanding-in-Chief Fighter Command had full operational control over all sections of our active defences, including the anti-aircraft guns.        He also explained that the division of the defence organisation into separate units for administrative purposes (e.g. thedividing line, passing down the middle of the river, between the anti-aircraft batteries on the North side and the South side of the thames) did not operate to disturb the unity of operational control.The Minister of Labour asked whether active steps were beingtaken to train people in industry to operate a system of localobservation which was now intended to supplement the public air-raid warning system.        Sir William Bartholomew said that arrangements were being made to have a cadre of selected people trained under the auspices of Fighter Command so that they, in their turn, might go allover the country to train people appointed to undertake these duties
in the various industrial establishments....      As regards the supplementarywarnings in Government Departments, it was explained in answer to aquestion by Mr. Geoffrey Lloyd that arrangements had been made for theestablishment of a central control at the Ministry of Transport whichwould be responsible for giving supplementary warnings to all GovernmentDepartments.Unexploded bombs.      The Home Secretary explained the difficulties caused by the large number of unexploded bombs in all parts of theMetropolitan District.      He recognised that there was considerable delay in dealing with these bombs, but explained that this was due, not to anydefect in the organisation, but merely to the lack of sufficient numbersof trained personnel.      The Army was responsible for providing bomb-disposal parties:   but the fact was that everyone had underestimated theextent to which delayed action bombs ^e&amp;s^ss^g used and as a resultthere were not nearly enough bomb-disposal parties to cope with thesituation which had now arisen.      He had been in touch with the WarOffice and everything possible was being done to increase the number of trained personnel available, both by drafting into the London districtpersonnel stationed elsewhere in the country and also by expediting thearrangements for training further numbers of men.Fire Services.     The Home Secretary explained the arrangementsfor mutual aid in the Fire Services - both from one brigade to another,from one group of brigades to another and finally from one Region toanother.      On two occasions so far it had been necessary to have recourse to inter-Regional schemes of mutual aid - first for the oilfire in Pembrokeshire and secondly for the large fires in the london docks.      He gave an account of the manner in which   Fire Service haddealt with the recent conflagrations in the London area, and said thatno praise could be too great for the gallantry and devotion of themen in the Fire Services.      During the attacks of the last few daysthere had been each day more than 200 fires requiring action by a fire brigade;   and in spite of this strain on our resources he had receivedreports showing that at the end of each day the services were 100 per cent,efficient for the work which they would be called upon to undertake on
the following day.        He was glad to say that yesterday it had beenpossible to arrange for many of the men who had been fire-fighting inLondon to take some time off for rest and recuperation.SKSl^llill I-IP?&quot;;In reply to a question by Lord Lloyd the Home Secretary saidthat his Department were now considering whether it would be practicable to make some arrangements for heating air-raid sheltersduring the winter months.In response to a request by the Home Secretary, the PostmasterGeneral gave an account of the damage done by the bomb which fellyesterday on the Central Telegraph Office.


</content>
</cab>
