<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/57/0 images: 100-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>

 net^August 1940.Dear Wilkinson.,&quot;Herewith as promised the record of ^Lmeeting between theSecretary of State for Air and ministers outside the War cabinet held on 22nd July 1940.Yours sincerely.W.D. Wilkinson Esq.. , D.S.O. ,   M.C.Cabinet Offices,Whitehall,S.W.I.Tel. No. Abbey 3411. AIR MINISTRY,ext........................ King Charles Street,Whitehall, S.W.I.
RECORD OP MEETING BETWEEN THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR air and MINISTERS OUTSIDE THE WAR CABINETon 22nd July, 1940,__There were present:     The Secretary of State for Air.The Chancellor of the Exchequer.and the majority of the Ministers to whom the invitation hadbeen sent by the Cabinet Office.The meeting was first addressed by the Chancellorof the Exchequer who explained his Budget.The Secretary of State then addressed the meeting and dealt with the following points:-1.       The loss of the greater part of a Blenheim flightin an attack on Brunswick.2.       The ascendancy of our fighter pilots.     The enemyhowever gets through sometimes, particularly wherethere is a good cloud cover and single aircraft areemployed.     Little destruction caused so far and fewcasualties, the greatest number of casualties being at Aberdeen.     Billingham an example of attack on industrial objectives, some loss of productiontemporarily.3.       M.E.110 intact at Earnborough.4.       New types in the German Air Force, the J.U.88,H.E.177, M.E.110, H.E.113.     No reasons to expect that we shall not maintain the present technicalsuperiority.5.       The performance of the Defiants.     Six lost in a surprise attack over the Channel.     Proposal to send them to Scotland where they would not come up against enemy fighters.6.      Enemy weight of attack so far not great but thestrength of his preparations should not be under-estimated.     On the other hand the full strength ofour defences has not been deployed and a strongerattack will meet a stronger defence,7.      We have formed ten more squadrons since May and toincrease our fighter strength quickly without thenecessity for forming squadrons we are increasing thenumber of initial equipment aircraft.8,      The Middle East.     Small forces have achieved much.9.      Training of pilots and crews, the most important task of the Air Ministry.     Previous disappointments, the bad winter and the failure of two types of advancedtrainer.     Loss of five training aerodromes in france and  abandonment of training scheme in Morocco.Trailing in ?/est Country now being interfered with by enemy operations and difficulties also in night flyindue to operational needs increasing.     Need to establ:training schools abroad.     The quality of intake asgood as ever.     Foreign pilots a great help, fourPolish and two Czech squadrons.     Foreigners workingmostly in their own units,
10.   First line strength of. the&apos;R.A.F.. about. hut the operational training units forming very close reserve.Reserves of aircraft are being steadily built up.Reserves of pilots more difficult.     Possibilities ofobtaining pilots from America.     The Empire air training Scheme.11.   Mr. Bevin mentioned that attacks on railways inGermany were lowering the moral of the German railway-men who formed a very important class of labour.Suggested that these attacks should be intensified.12.   Comparison between British and German Air Force.   Isthe gap widening?     Secretary of State stated that theGerman first line showed a slight increase in strengthwith a diminution in reserves.     The gap was beingclosed, but this would be a slow process.     Comparativetotals of first line and reserves given as - British5,000, German 11,000.13.   Mr. Bevin enquired about our strength in the middle east and expressed the view that it.would be a severe bblow to working class morale if we suffered a reversethere.     The S. of S. explained the difficulties ofaugmenting our strength in the Middle East.


</content>
</cab>
