<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/57/0 images: 204-212</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
With the Private Secretary sCompliments.1st Mwrch, 1940.
A meeting of Ministers took piece la the PrimeMinisters room at the House of Commons et 6 p.ia. onFebruary 89th, 1940.There were present:-*?he Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Lord President of the Council.The secretary of State for the Colonies.The Minister of Shipping.The Minister of Agriculture.The Minister of Food.The Minister of Information.The Minister of Labour.The Minister of Transport.The President of the Board of Education.The Secretary for Mines.Mr. r.c. Skrine Stevenson.&quot;ALTEABK.&quot;THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS said thatthe Norwegian Government had suggested to us that we shouldarbitrate on this question.     He had asked the norweigen minister whether Norway had proposed arbitration to germany in the matter of Norwegian ships sunk by German action.LORD HAUFAX*S own feeling was to say to Norway that weobserve) that she had been the victim of German mendacity,and to continue to the effect that we appreciated theNorwegian point of view and we-ew- confident that theyquestion of arbitration other considerations would arise end that it was therefore to be hoped that the Norwegians wouldnot persist with their proposal.     LORD HALIFAX explained the difficulty of entertaining the idea of arbitration Inview of the undesirable precedent It might create in the case of difficulties with other neutral powers arising outof the exercise of our contraband control.l0115/
LORD HALIFAX referred to the fact that the &quot;ALTHARK&quot;had been allowed to go through the defended zone at Bergenwhich is forbidden to ell belligerent warships.     If she hadnot done so she would have hed to go outside territorial waters and we might well have intercepted her there.Moreover the fact that the commander of the Norwegiandestroyer had asked the &quot;ALTMARK&quot; whether she had anyprisoners on board showed that the Norwegians, despite theirprofessed ignorance, hed good reason to believe that the prisoners were there.FINLAND.LORD HALIFAX said that according to the Finnish Miniate?reports of German mediation in the Subso-Finnish confliotbeing accepted by Finland were untrue.     The political position was however obscure.     The Finnish Minister inParis had given the French Government a message of appreciation for allied help and expressing some optimism.At the same time the Finnish Minister for Foreign affairs had informed the French Minister in Helsingfors that theredid not seem to be much left for Finland to do but to seekterms of peace,,     A telegram was being sent to His Majesty&apos;minister at Helsingfors in order to clear up the position.There was no doubt that the Swedeaowere putting pressure onthe Finns to make peace.Lord Device, who had just returned from Finland, had said that the Finns were Sighting a good rear-guard action and that there were no signs of an imminent collapse.Another line ef defence was being prepared behind viborgand the Finns hoped to hold out until it was ready.    Theywere however very tired.     LORD HALIFAX said that accordingto the information in his possession the Hussion consumptionof ammunition wee prodigious and was reported to exceedanything/
anything that had been mm in the last European war.According to Itho Finnish Minister the Hussiaas had alreadyused five million out of their existing stock of fourteenmillion shells.THJ38IA.LORD HALIFAX then told the Ministers something of therecent Russian offer to settle with the Finns.     He saidthat the Soviet Ambassador hed spoken to the parliamentary under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on the instruc-tions of his Government end had said that in their view weshould persuade the Finns to accept the terras now offered(which, incidentally, were much more onerous than thoserefused by Finland before the outbreak of hostilities), andthat if we refrained from doing ao our relations with Bussiswould inevitably deteriorate.     After seeking instructions from the Cabinet, Mr. F.A. Butler had told the soviet ambassador that we were not prepared to pass these terms onto the Finns, whereupon M. Maisky had said that the resultsof this decision would inevitably be unfortunate.    At theseme time instructions had been sent to His Majesty*sMinis^^^^jllelsingfora to tell the Finnish Government thatthis t,. , .     had been made by the Soviet Government and giving him suthe&amp;ty, if asked by the Finns, to inform them of the terms offered.     These instructions had, however,become academic aa the Soviet **H*-ft***&quot;* had made in themeantime a direct approach to Finland.     LORD HALIFAX&apos; Bapproach to us was probably aLOFB HALIFAX referred to Signer Mussolini^ refusal tosupply us with war material.    He said that we had decidedNto stop shipments of German coal to Italy, but were provldilgcredit/
credit for one month to enable Italy to purchase Brltleh ooeland thua tflrtn nriftr &apos; tht fitrtrftintf-18 g1K* ***** mAtm.       \other swongemonta.     At the end of Merehj, however8 Mussoliniwould probably he faced with economic circumstances whichmight oblige him to change his mind to some extent.    Therewas no doubt that gred pressure would be brought to bear on him by financial end industrial interests in Italy.FAR    1A8T.LORD HALIFAX said that we had agreed to the liberation oftwo Japanese ships carrying material from Germany on theunderstanding that In future all requirements of the Ministryof Economic warfare would be fulfilled by the Japanese.There was some little hope that out of this would grow anarrangement whereby we \ould ellow exports of certainmachinery from Germany to Japan in return for the cutting off by Japan of supplies of certain minerals to Germany throughVladivostock.     On the whole there were signs that theJapanese were gravitating slightly towards the Allies.In regard to the question of silver at Tientsin, lord halifax said that the Chinese had made certain counter-proposals which would probsbly be turned down by theJ spenese.UNITED   STATES.LORB HALIFAX referred to the  ndb-French mission whichhad gone to the United States to explain allied commercial policy and! methods of economic warfare.     He said that themain difficulty in our relations with the United Statesremained the inevitable restriction in our purchases ofagricultural supplies, particularly S^s^m&amp;wMslsa^mmmIt was difficult for American farmers, faced with heavyapples and tobacco.losses/
losses, to appreciate that the United States as^aahola worebenefiting from our Increased purchases.LORD HALIFAX said that he had had a conversation withthe United states Charge1 d* Affaires in the course of whichthe letter had said that if the rSles of the two countries were reversed we would inevitably take the seine view as theUnited States do now.     LORD HALIFAX had replied that while this might be the ease if the United States were engaged inaIlocal war nn-thf. Amanieao irmtlncnft, it certainly wouldnot be so if America were fighting for her life as we wereLORD HALIFAX said that Mr. Sumner Welles -woula-be inEngland between the 8th and 10th March.     From Rome he to-going to Berlin and thence to  tfrieh and Paris on his way toLondon.     He would return to Washington via Rome.     a friendly message was sent to him in Home by His Majesty1aGovernment which he seemed to have appreciated.     HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador in Rome had gathered from him thatthere was in his opinion no danger of a rapprochementbetween Rome and Moscow under the aegis of Berlin.     Therewas undoubtedly a danger, LORD HALIFAX thought, that Mr.Sumnar Welles might receive from Hitler a mass of speciousmaterial which might take him in.In answer to a question from the MINISTER OF LABOUR,LORD HALIFAX agreed that Mr. Kennedy fs speeches in theUnited states had not been helpful.aOAMDIWAVlA.In answer to a question from the PHE8IDEHT OF THEBOARD OF KBUOATIOlf, LORD HALIFAX said that Swedish publicopinion/
opinion might bring the Government to give more effectivehelp to Finland, but if the Finns were to collapse nowno one could help them.    According to the Soviet Ambassadorhere Russia would not invade Norway or Sweden, nor wouldshe undertake any adventures in the Balkans.     There were signs, however, that Russia wae nervous about the positionof the Caucasus.TH&quot; LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL end the MINISTER OFTRANSPORT both said that they had heard a good deal of talk about the proposed ski battalion for Finland.     It was8greed thst, though most unfortunate, it was impossible tokeep all our preparations secret.     LORD HALIFAX agreed,that military opinion seemed to be -opttmiatiQ&apos; in regard to finland&apos;s capacity to hold out.     He was personally not toosure about it.     The difficulty was how to help hereffectively if Norway and Sweden would not co-operate.     Itwould scarcely be feasible to declare war on the two lattercountries In order to send troops to Finland.TUB MINISTER OF SHIPPIHO said that the sooner the matte?was cleared up with Norway and Sweden the better it would bre from the point of view of the shipping position which was becoming very difficult.LORD HALIFAX said that there had been some discussion in the Cabinet on the desirability of following up the&quot;ALTMARF&quot; incident by taking some action, such as laying a mine-field, in Norwegian territorial waters.     It had beendecided, however, that on the whole it was better not totake such action^     In enswer to the MINISTER OFAGRICULTURE he said that the Dominion Governments were not altogether in favour of such&apos;-action as it might obstructefforts to bring assistance to Finland.    They were howeverin/
in favour of being geslly vialeat with Norway and Sweden inregard te the letter question, but they did not realisejnae--fc.Se bringing wj  help to Finland through aJtiasMlsScandinavia iai3.fi--aa&apos;%-*^^ ity-THE SECRETARY OF STATB said that it had been possibleto clear op the doubts in regard to the alleged invitationreceived from the King of the Belgians for allied troops had not socially issued such an invitation but that all hehad said to Sir Roger Keyes hed been coloured by his conviction that the following morning would see a german invasion of his country.GERMANY.In answer to a question from the SHHI8T15R OF FOOD,LORD HALIFAX said that we continued to receive reports ofa possible coup d*etat in Germany and that we were perpetu-ally being asked to affirm that we would not take advantageof such a movement inside Germany to invade the country.LORD HALIFAX was very doubtful about the value of such reports but they came from too many quarters to be dismissedaltogether unless of course they were being deliberatelyput out by Germany as a plant.


</content>
</cab>
