<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/166/16 images: 179-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ government cp(72) 141 COPY NO     0 V)5 December 1972CABINETOBSERVATIONS ON THE SECOND AND THIRD REPORTS FROMTHE SELECT COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY,1971-72: DRAFT WHITE paper note by the Secretary of State for Trade and industry. I circulate herewith, for the information of the Cabinet, the final draft of a White Paper giving the Governments reply to the Second and third Reports from the Select Committee on Science and Technology,1971-72.    The text has been approved by the Ministerial Committee on science and Technology.2. The Select Committee reports to which this White Paper relatesconcern respectively:a. The non-reactor research and development activities ofthe United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority,b. The industrial research establishments of the Departmentof Trade and Industry,3. The White Paper is to be published simultaneously (probably on8 December) with the White Paper replying to the First and Fourth reportsof the Select Committee,P w department of Trade and industry December 1972
THE NON-REACTOR RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT ACTIVITIES of the ATOMIC ENERGY AUTHORITYObservations by the Secretary of State for Trade and Industryand the Atomic Energy Authority on the Second Report fromSelect Committee on Science and Technology.    Session 1971-72INTRODUCTION1     In the second of their four reports on matters arisingfrom the Green Paper &apos;A Framework for Government Research andDevelopment&apos;   (Cmnd h8lk) the Committee examined in detail thenon-reactor research and development activities of the UnitedKingdom Atomic Energy Authority  (UKAEA).      Both the Departmentof Trade and Industry and the Authority agree with the SelectCommittee&apos;s conclusion (paragraph 26) that the research establish-ments of the Authority can provide first class supplementaryresearch and development resources closely linked to industrial needs.VOTE ACCOUNTING FOR NON-NUCLEAR WORK UNDER SECTION 4 OF the science AND TECHNOLOGY ACT 1965, AND THE AUTHORITY&apos;S ANNUAL report        The Select Committee recommend (paragraph 9) that thefunding of non-nuclear projects commissioned by GovernmentDepartments should be borne on the appropriate departmentalVote and listed separately in the Authority&apos;s Annual report under departmental headings.3 The Government accepts this recommendation.     TheCommittee will be aware from the evidence given to them,andfrom the Authority&apos;s latest Annual Report, that a substantial part of the non-nuclear work now done by the Authority isalready borne on the appropriate departmental Vote.     This processwill continue and, as the Committee will note, the authority have already made a first step to meet the second half of therecommendation by including a reference to the main sources of
RESTRICTEDreceipts from Government Departments in the table in the annual report setting out non-nuclear expenditure.    Further steps dependon the method of operation of the Requirements Boards  (Section VI ofthe observations on the Select Committee&apos;s Third Report) hut theAuthority will seek to meet the objectives the Committee had in mind.WORK ON REPAYMENT4       The Select Committee recommend ( paragraph&apos; 28)that the authority should make faster progress than that already planned for increasing the amount of work done on a full repayment basis.5       Both the Department and the Authority support this objective and the Authority will seek to improve their performancein this respect.AN INDUSTRIAL ADVISORY committee       The Select Committee recommend ( paragraphs 30 and 31) that theAuthority should set up an Industrial Advisory Committee composedin equal number of the Authority&apos;s staff and industrialists tokeep under review, in cooperation with the departmental Require-ments Boards, the extent and possible scope of nuclear and non-nuclear research and development.7       The Authority Board which itself includes part-time industrialmembers keeps under close review the scope and extent of allAuthority programmes and receives regular and substantial reports from its Authority Research and Development (ARD) Committees on progress on all the non-reactor work as well as on the majorreactor programmes.    The long term programmes, such as fusionresearch and underlying research, are included in this system ofreporting and in addition the Authority do from time to time, whereit appears desirable to supplement the regular arrangements for review, require an ad hoc study and report.8      The non-nuclear programmes, will in future he commissioned and
monitored by Requirement Boards which will offer industrialcriticism.    In the Departments  view delay and duplication wouldresult if a further Advisory Board were set up to review this area.9       The remaining area, of applied nuclear work, representsAuthority involvement with a very wide range of industries wherenuclear technologies can help in matters of research anddevelopment, or in process control and other operational procedures.In this area, as in that of the non-nuclear programme, the AEABoard through its ARD Committees,  exercises close examination of proposed applied nuclear projects bringing in the joint DTI/AEAProgrammes Analysis Unit or the Authority&apos;s Economic and ProgrammesBranch where elements of general national or social benefit are cla-imed (eg radioactive tracers for siltation studies, nuclear radiat-ion detectors); and professional (usually axternal) market surveyswhere industrial benefit is claimed (radiation chemistry, smallPower sources, information storage devices).    In view of the very wide range of industries and public bodies now using nucleartechniques, it is perhaps unlikely that a single IndustrialAdvisory Committee could significantly enrich the Authority&apos;sextensive experience in the fulfilment of their statutory task ofdevelopment and application of nuclear techniques.    accordingly the Authority have concluded that adequate arrangements for thepurposes the Select Committee have in mind already exist and that therefore a Committee on the lines proposed by the SelectCommittee is not required.    The Department agrees with this conclusion.10     The point made in the last sentence of paragraph 29 of theSelect Committee Report is not in fact correct.   If a programme ofwork falls outside the ambit of work already sanctioned by the
Department,  the Authority can seek a new &quot;requirement&quot; from theSecretary of State under Section 4 of the Science and TechnologyAct, 1365*i\CO I illv* B EbE/
THE INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH ESTABLISHMENTSObservations &quot;by the Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry on the Third Report from the Select Committee on science and Technology. Session 1971-72I        introduction       In their Report on the Department of Trade andIndustry&apos;s Industrial Research Establishments (iREs),the Select Committee on Science and Technology have examined the Department&apos;s proposals for applying the &quot;customer/contractor&quot; principle to themanagement of the IREs;    and have made recommendations about the role of the IREs in industrial innovation, andthe ways in which the results of their work may be exploited to the greatest public benefit.     The Depart-ment of Trade and Industry welcomes the Select Committee&apos;contribution to discussion of these important questions.II       REPORTS ON RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT  (Recommendation 1)2        The Select Committee recommend that the department should publish an annual report on all the research anddevelopment activities for which the Secretary of Statefor Trade and Industry is responsible (recommendation l).3 In reply to the Select Committee&apos;s First and FourthReports for 1971-72, published in Cmnd  &quot;      J, theGovernment has accepted that, in future, Depart-ments should publish annual reports on their research and development activities.
III       THE ROLE OP THE INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH ESTABLISHMENTS ANDTHEIR ORG-ANISATIQN(Recommendations 17,18,19,20 and 21)The industrial role of the IREsU        The Select Committee recommend that the industrial research Establishments should continue to provide thosesupporting scientific services and technical facilities which industry cannot or is unlikely to establish on itsown account  (recommendation 18).5 The Department of Trade and Industry considers thatas a general rule, industrial research is best done in industry.     However, there are certain civil R&amp;D func-tions - some of them of a longer term kind or withpotential for wide application in industry, others involving-ing high risk or expensive facilities - which, although they are in the national interest, individual firms are unwilling or unable to undertake themselves.     TheDepartment is confident that the IREs continue to have apart to play in filling this gap by providing supple-mentary research and development resources.Environmental research6 The Select Committee recommend that the industrial research Establishments should devote more attention toexploring the impact of technology on the community andto solving environmental problems  (recommendation 19).7        The Industrial Research Establishments undertakeprogrammes concerned with the effects of technology onthe environment.     Under the customer/contractor
principle, the sponsorship of a proportion of this work is passing to the Department of the Environment(DOE).     The Department of Trade and Industry expectsthat DOE will continue to commission these programmesfrom the DTI Establishments.8        The Department of Trade and Industry exercisesa wide range of safety and regulatory responsibilitiesrelating to the environment, for example oil pollutionat sea and marine safety, and is active where abatementprogrammes affect the industries which it sponsors.The trend is for the IREs to become increasinglyinvolved in this work.    .The Department welcomes theSelect Committee&apos;s timely reminder that those concernedwith research and development should be alive to the impact of their work on the community.Organisation of the Industrial Research Establishments -a Research Establishment Authority9        The Select Committee recommend that the industrial research Establishments, in spite of their close relation-ship with the Government, should be aware of the need to exploit their services for the benefit of the community as a whole .     They should become more competitive andbe given a greater degree of independence (recommenda-tion 17).     To increase their independence, the SelectCommittee propose a statutory Research EstablishmentAuthority comprising initially the National PhysicalLaboratory, the National Engineering Laboratory and theWarren Spring Laboratory (recommendations 20 and 21).
10     The Government has examined the case for a research establishment Authority.    It has concluded that fullerintegration, chiefly through the Requirements Boards, ofthe research and development in these laboratories with thepolicy and executive functions of DTI will be of greaterbenefit, both to the Establishments and to the community, thanthe removal of the IREs to a separate Authority.   special attention will be given to publicity for the work of theRequirements Boards.IV     EXPLOITING THE WORK OF THE INDUSTRIAL research establishments (Recommendations 2.5.4.5 and 6)Transfer of technology11      The Select Committee recommend that the Governmentshould state on what basis they propose that the IREs shouldtransfer their technology to industry(recommendation 6).12       The comments in this section relate primarily to thethree &quot;multipurpose&quot; Establishments - the National PhysicalLaboratory, the National Engineering Laboratory, and theWarren Spring Laboratory.    Some additional information isgiven at Annex.   Technology is transferred through -(a)     Publication and dissemination of information13      The IREs publish a great deal of information on their work and on the skills and facilities available at thelaboratories.    In general, these publications are directed at potential users, and are backed up by library and information services.
b) Personal contact14       Contacts are made at all levels &quot;both directly with industry and at conferences, at meetings of theengineering institutions, at exhibitions and at training courses run by the laboratories.     Firms are encouraged to pay visits and to second staff to the laboratorieson contract work (see also e) below).     The IREs regardpersonal contact as one of the most effective ways of keeping in touch with those they serve.c) Advisory and consultancy services15       These are made available to industry on a fee-paying basis.     The IREs also deal with many day-to-dayenquiries and the advice which they give is itself animportant end-product of their work.     The research and development puts the laboratory in a position to answer enquiries:    the questions in turn are a pointerto what research is wanted.d) Licensing16       Patent rights in inventions whose primary appli-cation is in industry are normally offered, free of charge, to the National Research Development Corporation(NRDC) .      If NRDC accepts assignment of the rights it becomes responsible for any subsequent patent work andmust attempt to secure exploitation;    the costs of this service are borne by NRDC.     Exploitation in industryis usually achieved by means of non-exclusive licensing,but in some cases NRDC may, with the approval of DTI,
grant exclusive rights to exploit.   Arrangements forservicing a licence agreement by the provision of know-howand any other technical assistance are agreed between NRDC,the originating establishment and the licensee,e)     R&amp;D contracts17     The Department looks forward to a progressive increasein research done on contract for industry and others because it puts the cost of the work on the user; because it represents demand for the IEEJfJ services; and because itimproves the prospects of the research being exploited(Select Committee recommendation 4).18     The Select Committee   recommend that contracts with industry, save in the most exceptional circumstances, shouldbe on a fully economic repayment basis.    They further recommendthat the Industrial Research Establishments should call uponthe services of financial consultants to analyse and determine the true costs of industrial contract work (recommendation 5)*19     An IRE contract with an industrial company is normallyon a fully economic repayment basis.    IRE Directors have discretion to vary their charges, taking account of what themarket will bear, in order to maximise net revenue to theExchequer.    They may charge less than the full economic costexceptionally - where wider national interests are at stake,or to promote the use of expensive capital facilities.    TheDepartment of Trade and Industry has at its disposal the servicesof its own professional accountants for analysing anddetermining the true cost of industrial contract work.
(f)     Interchange of scientists and engineers20      Mobility can assist the transfer of technology to industry (see Section VIlj^.21       The Select Committee are critical of the efforts of theIndustrial Research Establishments to exploit their work(paragraphs 59-44. Third Report).22       The Department of Trade and Industry accepts that morecan be done, although the importance of both publication of research results and personal contact in the spread of ideascan be underestimated.   Some IRE research may not lenditself to sale or licensing in industry.   A good example iswork dn the maintenance and improvement of national standards of measurement which is largely disseminated through thepublication of results, through service on standardisingbodies such as BSI committees, and by making available to industry basic standards against which firms can assess the accuracy of the gauges and instruments that they use.Looking to the future23 The Select Committee have asked two pertinent questions.How can we be sure&apos;that the IREs know what the real
needs of industry are?   And, how can the exploitation of theIREs&apos; work be improved?   They consider that scientists and engineers of the IREs are not necessarily the best people tosell their services (recommendation 2); and that the promotion of the services of the Industrial Research Establishmentsshould be a first priority in the work of the RequirementsBoards (recommendation 3).24     The Department of Trade and Industry accepts the generality of these points, and intends to encourage the establishments to develop a more commercial approach toexploitation.   Emphasis will be on the positive steps whichcan be taken to strengthen the marketing and managementskills of the IREs.    The terms on which the IREs undertakecontract research on repayment and joint venture schemeswith industry are under continuing review.V       THE CUSTOMER/CONTRACTOR PRINCIPLE(Recommendations 10 and 11).25     The Select Committee consider that the adoption of the customer/contractor principle is not necessarily the universal answer to the organisation and management ofGovernment research and development.   They hold that whileparticular areas of the work of the Industrial research establishments may be susceptible to this principle, muchof their broad work, for example standards, is not(recommendations 10 and 11).
26     The Government has adopted a wide interpretation of the customer/contractor principle which sees its significance inthe prominence it gives to the user&apos;s voice in the formulation of research requirements.. There is no reason why all IRE programmes, including those on standards,  shouldnot benefit from the application of tlvs broad principle.VI     THE REQUIREMENTS BOARDS (Recommendations 7,12,13,14,15and 16)27     The Select Committee have taken evidence on theDepartment&apos;s plans to establish a series of RequirementsBoards.    At that time the Department&apos;s proposals for the boards were in the formative stage and the Secretary ofState undertook to inform the Committee of the purpose,composition and operation of the Boards when he was readyto set them up.   This statement follows together withcomments on the Select Committee&apos;s recommendations.(a)     Purpose28     The purpose of the Requirements Boards is to implement the customer/contractor principle over a broadsector of the civil R &amp; D which the Department supportsoutside the aerospace and nuclear fields.    They will berequired to operate within policy guidelines laid down bythe Minister for Aerospace and shipping who will chair aCommittee of Requirements Board Chairmen for this purpose(recommendation 16).    These guidelines will reflect theDepartment&apos;s industrial policies in the fields served bythe Boards.
(b)     Composition of the Boards29       The Department is setting up six Requirements Boardswhich should be operational by the end of this year.    the boards are -Standards and Metrology Requirements BoardMaintenance and improvement of standards J&apos;methodsof measurement.Ship and Marine Technology Requirements BoardShipbuilding; shipping; hovercraft; marine technology, includingnavigation and operation of vessels, safety offshoreengineering and underwater technology.Chemical and Mineral Processes and Plant Requirements BoardChemical processes; Minerals separation; metals extraction;process plant.Mechanical Engineering and Machine Tools Requirements BoardDesign and production engineering, and in particular machine tools, including numerical control.Computers. Systems and Electronics Requirements BoardComputers (hardware and software); automation; telecommunications,electronic components and instruments; utilisation of computersand new applications. /Engineering Materials Requirements BoardFerrous, non-ferrous, organic, inorganic and compositematerials for engineering use.
There are a number of residual research and development programmes which do not fit exactly into this pattern.For the time being, they will be commissioned by theDepartments Chief Scientist.The chairmen and members30     The Department has given careful consideration to the selection of the chairmen (recommendation 14).    Three: areindustrialists; two are Civil Servants.    The Chairman ofthe sixth Board will be announced shortly.31     The Departments aim is a balanced membership inwhich both customer (direct or indirect) and contractorinterests will play a. full part in the formulation of requirements.    The Department accepts that there will bean important place on the Boards for members withbusiness experience and knowledge of particular sectors of industry (recommendation 1i5)- The general pattern foreach Board will be: the chairman; six members from industry;two university scientists; and official representatives of DTI
main customer divisions, other Government Departments, and main contractors.(c)     Operation of the Boards32     The Select Committee say that a system of between six and ten Requirements Boards, assisted by panels of experts,seems rather large.    They consider that it will only work effectively if the objectives and responsibilities of eachBoard are clearly defined, and if they operate within the framework of a coherent policy (recommendations 12 and 13).33     The Department of Trade and Industry has tried to giveeach of the Boards a manageable technological or industrial field in which to operate.    The Department&apos;s interests cover-most industrial sectors of the economy and the problem hasbeen so to group the various customer interests that eachRequirement Board is responsible for a sizeable but fairlyhomogeneous programme of work.    Both intramural and extra-mural work is included to permit the Boards to consider,within their own fields, the overall distribution of investment in R &amp; D by the Department.34    The Requirements Boards have a two-fold function inthe technological and industrial fields within which theyoperate -(a)     to help the  Government identify those areas whichwill most benefit from Government supported R&amp;D;
(b)    to determine the objectives and balance of research and development programmes to support departmental policies,within the broad allocation of funds available to them.These are effectively the Requirements Boards&apos; terms ofreference, and the -Department believes they will allow the boards ample scope to look ahead and give full considerationboth to new developments in science and technology(recommendation 15) t and long-term needs (recommendation 7).35      Within their terms of reference and subject to theapproval of the Minister for Aerospace and Shipping, theRequirements Boards will have wide responsibilities forcommissioning research and development at the industrial research Establishments, the UKAEA (non-nuclear), the research Associations now operating in the DTI field, industry,the universities and Research Councils.    In addition to the scrutiny of current programmes, the Boards will consider proposals for new work.    The initiative may come from the boards themselves, from the DTI customer divisions, or theymay be bids for support from potential contractors.    the boards will consider the objectives of these proposals, the relationship to departmental needs, the market possibilitiesand the budget required.    They will be able to endorse, orotherwise, schemes submitted, determine the balance betweencompeting projects, recommend priorities and indicate thepreferred choice of contractor for the work.   The Boards willalso be responsible for the supervision of the progress of the
research and development they have approved, and the measures taken to communicate and exploit the results.   Each board will publish an annual report.36     Not all research and development will be submitted tothe Boards for their approval.   When the Department supportsextramural R&amp;D with the primary objective of providing direct assistance to industry, and the R&amp;D aspect is secondary, theapproval of a Requirements Board will not be necessary.   ?/orkcarried out by the IREs on full repayment will also fall outside the remit of the Boards.    In both cases however, theRequirements Board will be kept generally informed.    TheMinister will also have discretion to withold information from the Boards on the grounds of commercial confidentiality.Support for the BoardsA new Research Requirements Division under the Department&apos;sChief Scientist will provide technical, managerial andfinancial back-up services for the Boards.    Specialistadvice from independent and government experts will beavailable to the Boards when they need it.VII   MOBILITY OP SCIENTIFIC STAFF (Recommendations 8 and 9)38     The Select Committee consider that the problem of mutual exchange of scientists and engineers betweenindustry and the Industrial Research Establishments has adirect bearing on the future role of these Establishments.They recommend that the Department of Trade and industry should set up a working party to report on the possibilitiesof the transfer, and on the relative pay and status of
scientists and engineers employed in government establishments and industry (recommendations 8 and 9).39     Since the Select Committee made their recommendations,the Government has announced in Cmnd 5046 the setting upof a high level task force to study the problems ofinterchange between the Civil Service and the research councils, universities and industry.    The task force is working and will look at, inter alia, questions affectingmobility between the Industrial Research establishments and industry.
ANNEXTRANSFER OP TECHNOLOGY  (SECTION IV OP THE SECRETARY OP STATE&apos;observations ON THE SELECT COMMITTEE&apos;S THIRD REPORT)The following statistics have boon selected to give some indi-cation of the scale on which the three &quot;multipurpose&quot; IREsare involved in the publication of information and direct contact in the transfer of technology.     A large number of firms have made it their business to know of the work of thelaboratories where the laboratories are providing nationalservices and such contacts are particularly close.     Forinnovative work the initiative rests more with the laboratory,though even here many firms keep in close contact through their technical intelligence and information staff.Publication and dissemination of informationLast year the NPL published hGO major technical reports andpapers and in addition make known nationally a great deal ofinformation on physical and chemical data, standards of measurement, and the technical aspects of standards of specification.NEL supplied over 1,000 organisations  (including 700 firms inthe private sector of industry) with a total of 11,000 copies otechnical reports in response to requests for information.NEL has a regular mailing list of 8,000 addresses for distri-bution of technical leaflets.     In a typical year, WSLpublishes about 200 reports, including contributions toscientific and technological journals.     Last year theLaboratory distributed 55,000 items to 2,500 organisations of which UO,000 were leaflets on air pollution work.Personal contactIncluding open days, NPL receives about 6,000 visitors ayear;    NEL 2,000 and WSL about 5,000.     Each Laboratory willgenerally participate in over 20 major exhibitions a year.Last year 900 people, mostly from industry, attended training courses run by NEL.     Staff of all three stations delivermany lectures to professional and other bodies;   at WSL, forexample, the number is about 130 a year.     Furthermore,large numbers of queries are dealt with over the telephone and especially in regard to standards information.      Onerelatively small section of the NPL alone handled about 1,000last year.

</content>
</cab>
