<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/76/0 images: 40-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOC URGENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret.P.(55) 52 COPY NO. 1/025th June, 1955CABINETLEGISLATIVB PROGRAMME;  1955/56 session memorandum by the Lord Privy seal the Cabinet, at their meeting on 2nd June, 1955 agreed thatthe Bills set out in the Annex to C.P.(55) 23 (reproduced as Annex A to thismemorandum) should constitute the main features of the legislative programme for the present session (C.M.(55) 11th Conclusions, Minute 4).All the Bills set out under Item 1 in that Annex (i. e. Bills introduced butnot passed in the 1954/55 session) have now been reintroduced.    Thefollowing further Bills have also been introduced:-Austrian TreatyEuropean Coal and Steel Community - high authority  (Privileges and Immunities)Friendly SocietiesInternational Finance CorporationMiscellaneous Financial Provisions (includingPotato Marketing)\2. My colleagues will remember that, as I pointed out inC.P.(55) 23, the list reproduced in Annex A was not intended to be exhaustive.The Future Legislation Committee have now considered the remainingmeasures proposed by Departments in response to the customary request for suggestions for legislation, and in this memorandum I submit, on theCommittee&apos;s behalf, their recommendations on these other measures.3. The further Bills which the Future Legislation Committee now recommended for inclusion in the programme are shown in Annex B,    Thereare certain further Bills whose inclusion in the programme would become essential in certain circumstances; these are set out in Annex C.    I shouldalso remind the Cabinet that the need may well arise during the sessionfor additional legislation, for example on Colonial Immigration.    Suchcontingencies were provided for in the penultimate paragraph of The Queen!sSpee ch.4. The Future Legislation Committee recognised the importanceof introducing some at least of the session&apos;s major measures at an earlydate.    It was inevitable that the greater part of the time between the firstmeeting of this Parliament and its adjournment for the summer recessshould be occupied with proceedings on Bills introduced but not passedduring the last session.    It is, however, essential that some larger measures-1-
should be introduced before Parliament adjourns for the summer in order toshow that the Government were not unprepared for the Parliamentary positionbrought about by their return to power, and that they intend to proceedresolutely with the programme of legislation promised in The Queen&apos;s Speech.It is necessary to keep in mind in this connection the need to introduce asufficiency of Bills in the House of Lords if the programme is to be completedsmoothly.     It must also be remembered that, in the absence of an autumnProrogation and a Queen&apos;s Speech on the opening of a new session,substantially more time will be available for legislation than is usual atthat time of year, and that this must be used to the best advantage.5. In view of this it is essential to introduce further Bills beforeParliament adjourns.    The Bills which I suggest for such introduction arethe folio wing: -Channel Islands   -  National ServiceClean Airj^eiiois tSDiplomatic ImmunityHealth, Welfare and Safety in Agricultureand ForestryHouse of Commons DisqualificationInventions and Designs   (Defence)Leeward IslandsSugarWaterAs far as can be foreseen at present, time will be availablein the second half of July for Second Reading debates on some of these Bills,if they can be introduced in time.6. The Bills which, I suggest, it should be the aim to have ready for introduction immediately Parliament reassembles in October are asfollowsCopyrightCountervailing and Antidumping DutiesFa m ily A llowanc e sGeneva ConventionsRating and Valuation  (Scotland)If any of these Bills could be introduced formally before Parliament adjourns,this would enable them to be published during the Recess and, therefore, to be.ready to be proceeded with promptly in the autumn.    If other Bills not mentioned in this and the preceding paragraph can be introduced early in the session, that will be all to the good.
T2-7. If this plan is to be carried out, it is clearly essential that ministers responsible for the measures referred to in the two preceding paragraphs should make it their special concern to obtain all necessary policyapproval for their proposals as soon as possible, and in all cases before ministers disperse for the Recess, in order that the Bills may be got ready for introduction by the times suggested.conclusion. On behalf of the Future Legislation Committee, I invitethe Cabinet;-(i) to approve the inclusion in the programme, inaddition to the Bills set out in Annex A,of the further Bills set out in Annex B tothis memorandum;(ii) to note that circumstances may arise in which.it will be necessary to introduce the furtherBills set out in Annex C;(iii) to invite the Ministers responsible for the Billsreferred to in paragraphs 5 and 6 of thismemorandum to make it their specialconcern to ensure that these Bills are gotready for introduction by the times suggested.Gwydyr House, S.W.1.24th June, 1955.
?4(j^prodoction of Annas: to C^. .(55) 23)... .-1.    Bills introduced but not passed in 1954/55 Session -Agriculture (Improvement of Roads)Aliens Employmentx   County Courtsx   Criminal Justice Administration.Food and Drugs (Scotland)German ConventionsPolice (Scotland)x   Ratina and Valuationx   Road Trafficx 2.    Clean Airx 3.     Copyright (to include Copyright and Television ExliibiiingRights Bill)x 4.    Countervailing and Anti-Dumping Duties5.    Dentists6.    Emergency PowersMinor Bills,    These include -WaterInventions and Designs (Defence)Tube Shelters (Hybrid Bill)vr 7.    Family Allowances8.    Gowers Report -- -*e Agriculture and Forestry? Railway Workers9,    House of Commons Disqualification
10.    Hotising Subsidiesx 11.      Local Government Re-organisation12.    ministers Salaries13.    Potato Marketing (? To be included in a MiscellaneousFinancial Provisions Bill)14.    Representation of the People -Register of ElectorsRevised Directive to Boundary Commissioners15.    Sugar16.    Teachers&apos; Superannuation17.    Valuation, Rating and Equalisation Grant (Scotland)&quot;X.s*x    Referred to inThe Queen&apos;s Speech.
Agriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions)Air Corporations (Borrowing Powers)^Airports Licensing^Channel Islands National Service/ Crown LandsDiplomatic Immunity/D.S.I.R. and A.R.C.J7Education  (Scotland)Expiring Laws ContinuanceFinanceGeneva ConventionsHire PurchaseLeeward IslandsLocal Government ElectionsPost Office and Telegraph  (Money)Public Health  (Scotland)Sudan Officials CompensationTown Development (Scotland)Wireless Telegraphy  (Blind Persons Facilities)x   It is suggested that this Bill, whichwas introduced by a Private member in the last session but not proceeded with, should be re-introduced as aGovernment Bill if opportunity offers.
*		ANNEX C Bills which would become essential in	ft		certain circumstances		Department	Subject                            Approx. No.			(in alphabetical                     of clauses order)                               (if known)	Remarks(1)	Colonial Office	British                               Short Caribbean Federation	If the Final Conference of West Indian Plenipotentiary Delegates is held, a short enabling Act will be required to confer powers to establish the Federation by Order in Council.(2)	Scottish Office	Housing Subsidies	If the Scottish V aluation and Rating Bill is passed early enough in the session, it will be desirable to introduce there-after a Bill dealing which housing subsidies in Scotland.(3)	Lav/ Officers \	Mortmain and                       2 Charitable Uses Acts   (Amendment)	Y/ould be required immediately if the House of Lords were to uphold the judgment of the Court of Appeal in More lie Ltd. v. Water worth.(4)	C o m m onwe alth Relations Office	Pakistan                              Short (Consequential Provision)	Will be required as soon as certain constitutional processes have been completed in Pakistan.(5)	Treasury	Public Works Loans	Likely to be required not later than the end of 1956,    I(6)	Post Office ^:jy::-\t&apos;: &apos;0:&apos;.&apos;-::-J: M^V&apos;&apos;.7&apos;:&apos;-&apos;; &apos;V&quot;	Wireless Telegraphy         6 or 7 Act, 1949 (Amendment) Bill	May be required - to resolve doubt about certain provisions whichare at present thesubject of enquiry.

</content>
</cab>
