<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/76/0 images: 97-98</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 1955SECRET Copy No.   cp. (55) 581st July, 1955CABINETREGISTERS OF ELECTORSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs and the Secretary of State for scotland on 2nd June the Cabinet invited us to submit a recommendation aboutlegislation relating to registers of electors (CM. (55) 11th Conclusions, Minute 4).2. Section 5 of the Representation of the People Act, 1948, provided for tworegisters to be published every year, on 15th March and 1st October. This hadbeen recommended in the report of the Departmental Committee on electoral registration dated December 1946 (Cmd. 7004) because of the importance of having a fresh register for Parliamentary elections.3. The first register under the 1948 Act was the autumn register of 1949. Atthe end of that year the Electoral Registers Act, 1949, was passed, which abolishedthe autumn register as an economy measure. The Act, however, provided that persons coming of age after the qualifying date for the spring register and before15th June following (which would have been the qualifying date for the autumnregister) should be entitled to be registered and to vote after 1st October (whenthe autumn register would have come into force).4. Thus from 1950 there has been only one register a year. The date of publication was altered to 15th February by the Electoral Registers Act, 1953, which took effect for the 1955 register.5. There were two registers a year from 1918 to 1926, but the spring registerwas then abolished, also as an economy measure.6. Should the autumn register now be restored? The case for this is that thepresent annual register, prepared with reference to the qualifying date 10th October,is at least a year out of date for a general election held in the autumn or spring 16 months out of date for a February election. (The staleness of the register ismitigated by the provision mentioned in paragraph 3 for persons coming of ageafter the qualifying date, and by the fact that a person who has moved away fromhis qualifying address is entitled to vote by post.) A register published in Octoberwith a qualifying date in June would be 8 months more up to date.7. The case against restoring the autumn register is the substantial costin money and in unproductive labour. The total cost of the present annual registeris about  2,320,000. Two registers a year would cost rather less than twice this sum, but not much less.8. Of the total cost,  2,070,000 is shared equally between the Exchequer andthe local authorities. (The balance of  250,000 is borne in full by the Post Office.)The local authorities would be likely to object to being required to pay half thecost of an autumn register, on the ground that (as explained in paragraph 12 below)it would confer no benefit on them; and they would be able to make out astrong case.9. The Stationery Office say that it would be difficult to find the capacity inthe printing trade to undertake the additional work. There is an acute shortageof labour throughout the industry, and the Stationery Office already find it48289
extremely difficult to place all their requirements. A second register, if practicableat all, would seriously aggravate the difficulty. There is also a shortage of printing paper.10. In most areas the house-to-house canvass for the register starts a month or more before the qualifying date, and preparatory work begins still earlier. Thismeans that work on the spring register would begin during the final stages of thework on an autumn register published in October. This overlap might causedifficulties. Another possible source of difficulty and misunderstanding is that inmany areas the canvass for an autumn register might well begin during the campaign for local government elections conducted on the previous spring register.11. It is hard enough to persuade people to fill in the canvass form once ayear. If they had to do it twice a year, with an interval of only four months, thedifficulty would be much greater.12. A register published in October would have only a short life before the spring register came into force in February, but there would be no point in publishing a register in August or September. Since ordinary local government elections are now. held in April and May, an autumn register would only be usedfor a general election occurring between its publication in October and thefollowing February, besides Parliamentary and local government bye-elections inthe same period. A substantial need for it, therefore, would arise only at considerable intervals.13. It should be understood that it would not be possible to require anautumn register to be prepared ad hoc unless ample notice about ten months were given before the proposed date of publication. An interval of about four months is necessary between the qualifying date and publication, and probablyanother six months would be needed for printing and distributing the canvassforms; for other preparatory work for, and the earlier stages of the canvass; andfor arranging contracts for printing the register.14. The question is whether the occasional need for a fresh register in theautumn is sufficient to outweigh the objections mentioned above. We do notthink so.G. LL.-G.J. S.1st July, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
