<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/76/0 images: 214-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1955SECRET Copy No.   72CP. (55) 8318th July, 1955CABINETREDISTRIBUTION OF seats memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Secretary of  Statefor scotland on 2nd June the Cabinet invited us to submit a recommendation on thequestion whether legislation should be introduced this session about the redistribution of seats (CM. (55) 11th Conclusions, Minute 4).2. We think there is everything to be said for early legislation on this subject,when there is a good prospect that it will be considered in a relatively calmatmosphere not unduly troubled by thoughts of the next general election.3. We think that we should continue to support the principle of redistributionat regular intervals with the object both of correcting gross disparities betweenthe electorates of constituencies and of maintaining an equitable distribution of seats throughout the country. With this in view, and bearing in mind the exceptional nature of the recent redistribution and the undesirability of any radicalamendment of the law which might lead to a general upheaval at the nextredistribution, we do not think that major amendments of the law are eithernecessary or desirable.4. First we think that the interval between general reviews of constituencies(now not less than three nor more than seven years) should be extended to aminimum of 10 years and a maximum of 15 years. This would allow a reasonableinterval, but not too long for gross discrepancies to develop and persist for any great length of time. (Initially, 10 years from 1954 would probably mean that thenext review would take place after two more general elections.)5. Secondly we think that the undue rigidity of the existing provisions of theHouse of Commons (Redistribution of Seats) Act, 1949 can be satisfactorily relaxedsimply by relieving the Boundary Commissions of their obligation under section 2 (1)to bring all constituencies into complete conformity with the rules in the second schedule on the occasion of every general review, and by requiring them insteadonly to recommend changes which appear to them desirable either to give effectto rule 4 (which provides against the dismemberment of local government areas) orto correct major departures from the rules as a whole. This formula should be suffiently flexible on the one hand to avoid giving too much weight tomathematical considerations and on the other to enable the Commissions to alterconstituencies which have grown too large or too small, or to make any adjustment of the distribution of seats over the country as a whole that may be necessaryowing to movements of population. The formula should minimise, although itcannot entirely remove, the painful features of redistribution.6. The Commissions should also still have power, both at general reviewsand whenever the need arises, to recommend adjustments of constituency boundaries following alterations of ward and other local boundaries.7. Consequently section 2 (3), which enables the Commissions to makeoccasional reports about particular constituencies, should be amended in the same way as section 2(1).48415
V8. We think it also desirable in view of recent experience to provide expressstatutory sanction for basing redistribution in England on the electoral quota for england and not on that for Great Britain. This would mean a separate allocation of seats and a separate electoral quota for each country.^ r* 9.  We have considered whether, to meet the demand for more local inquiries&apos; in England, a statutory obligation should be placed on the Boundary commissions to hold inquiries in defined circumstances. It is impossible to define thecircumstances exactly, and we think it would be undesirable that the Commissionsshould be left without any discretion. In our view the most practical plan would beto provide that, before finally recommending any alteration of the boundaries ofa constituency, a Commission must hold a local inquiry, unless (a) no petitionagainst the proposed alteration (or against a revised proposal published by theCommission after considering initial objections) has been made by a local authority or at least 100 electors of the constituency, or (b) in the opinion of the commission the nature of the petitions and the particular circumstances are such that a local inquiry would serve no useful purpose.. There was no complaint that the ScottishBoundary Commission, who have been able to acquire considerable localknowledge, held no inquiries in the course of the recent redistribution, and theformula suggested would leave them due discretion.10. We suggest that we should be authorised to open discussions withrepresentatives of the Labour and. Liberal parties on these lines, with a view to legislation in the course of the present session. We would propose to tell the speaker what is intended before approaching the Opposition.G. LL.-G.J. S.Cabinet Office,18th July, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
