<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/76/0 images: 230-238</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET Copy No. 64CP. (55) 8823rd July, 1955CABINETPROPOSED COMMITTEE OF ENQUIRY ON ADMINISTRATIVETRIBUNALSMemorandum by the Lord ChancellorAfter considering my memorandum, CP. (55) 44, on the proposed enquiry into the working of administrative tribunals, the Cabinet asked for detailed proposals on the terms of reference and composition of the Committee (CM. (55)19th Conclusions, Minute 7).2. At my request, Sir Edward Bridges and a group of Permanent secretaries of a number of Departments whose interests are affected prepared draft termsof reference for my consideration and also suggested to me a number of possiblenames for membership of the Committee. I have had the benefit of a discussion on Sir Edward Bridges&apos; proposals with the Lord President, the Minister of housing and Local Government, the Attorney-General, the Minister of State, scottish office, and the Financial Secretary to the Treasury. They approve the following proposals which are made in the light of our discussion and of the suggestions made by officials.Terms of Reference3. In considering terms of reference our aim has been to give the proposed committee as free a rein as possible consistent with the limitation mentioned inparagraph 3 of CP. (55) 44: namely, that they should not be in a position tocanvass  he desirability of enabling day-to-day decisions of the Executive to be reviewed by some independent authority. I think that this aim would be met by terms of reference as follows:  &quot;To consider and make recommendations on:  (a) The constitution and working of tribunals, other than the ordinary courts of law, constituted under any Act of Parliament by a Minister of theCrown or for the purposes of a Ministers functions.(b) The working of such administrative procedures as include the holding ofan enquiry or hearing by or on behalf of a Minister on an appeal or as the result of objections or representations, and in particular theprocedure for the compulsory purchase of land.&quot;Paragraph (a) covers all the tribunals established for the purpose of determining questions arising in connection with the work of a GovernmentDepartment, e.g., local tribunals and the National Insurance Commissioner underthe National Insurance Act, 1946, the Pensions Appeal tribunals, the agricultural land tribunals, the Traffic Commissioners who grant road service licences andpublic service licences, and the National Health Service tribunal, which dealswith the removal of doctors from lists of general medical practitioners. It wouldalso cover tribunals appointed by a Minister for purposes not closely connectedwith government administration, e.g., the rent tribunals; and tribunals whichare in the nature of specialised courts of law, ,e.g., the Special Commissioners for income tax and the Lands tribunal.  The latter kind of body are not the subject48446Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1955 1
of criticism and controversy, but their exclusion seems unnecessary and might make the terms look unduly restrictive. The paragraph does not cover professionaldisciplinary bodies such as the General Medical Council.Paragraph (b) is mainly concerned with statutory procedures for compulsorilyacquiring land or exercising other government functions affecting land, e.g.,planning control under the Town and Country Planning Act, 1947, thedispossession of farmers under the Agriculture Act, 1947, and trunk road schemes.The words used, however, would cover a number of other functions involving the holding of appeals or enquiries into objections. Examples are directions exceptingroads from the speed limit, the regulation of dock charges, the approval of schemesfor coast protection, the determining of disputes with respect to road charges, andthe stopping up of highways. There are also a number of wide powers conferred on Ministers to hold enquiries for the purposes of their functions, e.g., section 318of the Public Health Act, 1936, and section 93 of the Education Act, 1944. Theterms of reference probably would not bring in the functions to which these general powers relate unless in fact the administrative procedure included the holding ofan enquiry as a fairly normal event.In both paragraphs of the draft terms of reference mentioned above, the phrase &quot; the working of&quot; tribunals and administrative procedures is, in myopinion, wide enough to enable the proposed Committee to deal with the powersof the High Court in relation to these tribunals and procedures.Composition4. I think, and my colleagues with whom I have discussed this matter agree,that the right blend of wisdom and experience would be found in a committee made up as follows:  Lord Radcliffe (Chairman).Lord Balfour of Burleigh.Marquess of Linlithgow.Lord Silkin.John Morrison, M.P.Douglas Johnston, Q.C., M.P. formerly Solicitor-General for scotland in the Labour Government.Roderic Bowen, Q.C. Liberal M.P. for Cardigan.The Hon. Charles Russell, Q.C.Sir Edwin Herbert Vice-President of the Law Society.A member nominated by the Trades Union Congress.A representative of Local Authority interests not a lawyer.A woman associated with the Citizen&apos;s Advice Bureau or similar social work possibly Miss Eileen Younghusband.Professor Kenneth Wheare Gladstone Professor of Government andPublic Administration at Oxford.Sir Geoffrey Stuart King formerly Permanent Secretary to the Ministryof Pensions and National Insurance.Q5. In view of Parliamentary and public interest in this topic I suggest that itwould be desirable to make a further announcement of our intentions as soon aspossible. If the Cabinet approve the proposed terms of reference and decide uponLord Radcliffe for Chairman, I could sound him at once, and, if he accepts, astatement could be made about the terms of reference and the Chairman beforethe Recess.K.House of Lords, S.W. 1,21st July, 1955.
I.We find no single and easy answer to the plight of the 900,000 Arab refugees who formerly lived in the territory that is now Israel, who fled at the time ofthe fighting in 1948 and were barred from returning to their homes and the costof whose maintenance now falls directly on the international community. Butwe do feel that an answer can be found in a combination of measures which,together, would re-establish these uprooted people and offer them hope of anew life.Compensation by the State of Israel is due for the land and buildings belongingto the refugees which are now in ,Israel&apos;s possession. Perhaps Israel cannot,unaided, now make adequate compensation. If so, there might be an internationalloan to Israel of the balance of the sum necessary. The President would recommendsubstantial participation by the United States in such a loan for such a purpose.The money must be used to create more arable land on which the refugeescould make permanent homes and work to produce a self-respecting livelihood.Money alone, however, will not solve the problem. It is no longer possible forIsrael to take back all or most of the refugees. But she might reasonably beasked to find homes for a limited number of those who might choose to return.Large numbers, however, will necessarily remain. Many of these could be settledover a period, of the next few years as a result of projects such as the jordan valley development Plan, the Sinai Project, and as a result of the increasedopportunities provided by the expanding economies of countries of the area. Here,too, outside help might be required.48443 i b 2\Extract from Revised Draft of Possible Public Statement by Mr. Dulleson an Israel-Arab settlement the ARAB-ISRAEL PROBLEMWhat are the principal remaining problems? There are three that stand out above the others.The first is the tragic plight of the 900,000 refugees who formerly lived in theterritory that is now occupied by Israel.The second is the pall of fear that hangs over the Arab and Israel peoplealike. The Arab countries fear that Israel will seek by violent means to expandat their expense. The Israelis fear that the Arabs will gradually marshal superiorforces to be used to drive them into the sea.The third is the lack of fixed permanent boundaries between Israel and itsArab neighbours.There are other important problems. But if these three principal problemscould be dealt with, then the way would be paved for the solution of others.It seems to me that these three problems are capable of solution and surelythere is need.Border clashes take an almost weekly toll of human lives. The sufferings ofthe 900,000 Arab refugees are drawn out almost beyond the point of endurance.The fears which are at work, on each side, lead to a heavy burden of armament,which constitutes a serious drag on economic and social progress. Responsibleleaders are finding it hard to turn their full attention and energies to the positivetask of creating the conditions of stability and healthy growth out of which strongnations could emerge.Serious as the present situation is, there is a danger that, unless it improves,it will get worse. One ill leads to another, and cause and effect are hard to sortput. Both sides suffer greatly from the present situation, and both are anxious for what they would regard as a just and equitable solution. But neither has beenable to find that way. This may be a situation where mutual friends could,through their good offices, serve the common good.The United States, as a friend of both Israelis and Arabs, has given the situationdeep thought and has come to certain conclusions, the expression of which may help men of good will within the area to fresh constructive efforts. I speak in thismatter with the authority of the President.
III.If there is to be a guarantee of borders, it would be normal that there shouldbe a prior agreement upon what the borders are. That is the third major element.The existing lines separating the Arab States from Israel were fixed by the ArmisticeAgreements of 1949. They reflected the status of the fighting at the moment.They were not designed to be permanent frontiers in every respect. They clearlyrequire rectifications and adjustments.For example, there should presumably be an allocation of the presentdemilitarised zones and &quot;no man&apos;s lands &quot; created by the Armistice Agreements.The Arab world, which is now separated by Israel possession of the Negev,understandably desires an unbroken land connexion. This could be provided,without prejudice to any of israels vital interests, by ceding to one or two Arabnations sovereignty over triangular portions of the Negev having little or no economic value and now wholly barren. The Arab triangles could be based on theEgyptian and Jordanian frontiers respectively so that their apexes meet at a pointon an Israeli route to the south. Thus the now divided Arabs would re-establishsovereign contact, while the sovereign connexion of Israel with the port of Eiathwould be maintained.IV.If agreement can be reached on these basic elements refugees, boundaries andthe elimination of fear it. should prove possible to find solutions for other questions, largely economic, and to bring to an end external economic measures,such as blockade, which presently fan the flames of hostility and resentment.It should also be possible to reach agreement on the status of Jerusalem. TheUnited States would give its support to a United Nations review of this problem.ANNEX 2TEXT OF BAGDAD TELEGRAM TO PARIS, No. 44 OF 14th July have been asked to comment on a proposed statement on the Arab-Israelproblem with particular reference to the effect on opinion in Iraq and on theattitude of Iraq towards the Bagdad Pact and the new Anglo-Iraq Agreement. my views are as follows:  2. We are at present engaged firstly in trying to consolidate opinion in Iraqin support of the Pact and of the Agreement and, secondly, in negotiating with the iraqi Government upon outstanding; matters concerning transfer at Habbaniyaand Shaiba and the Anglo-Iraqi Defence Plan. Pakistan has announced that shewill join the Bagdad Pact, but has not yet done so. Staff talks with Persia, whichmight open the way to accession to Persia, are hanging in the balance.3. All this is proceeding reasonably well for the present. But the most damaging criticism which Nuri has so far had to face and which he has up till nowcountered successfully is that the Bagdad Pact conceals an intention on the partof the United Kingdom (and of the United States) to secure agreement with iraq to some compromise solution for Palestine, which would be a betrayal of Arabinterests.\The second principal element which I mentioned is that of fear. The natureof this fear is such that it is not within the capacity of any single country of thearea to take measures to dispel it. President Eisenhower has authorised me tosay that if a solution can be found to the other related problems, he would recommend that the United States enter into formal engagements with the countries concerned to take appropriate action to prevent or thwart any effort by either side to alter by force the boundaries between Israel and its Arab neighbours. I hopethat other countries would be willing to join in such a guarantee, and it might perhaps be sponsored by the United Nations.
4. There could, therefore, hardly be a more unfortunate moment to choose fora public declaration about Palestine. However wise and statesmanlike the substance of the declaration may be, there is a distinct risk that anything which Her, Majesty&apos;sGovernment may say at the present juncture may lead to a reaction, possiblyviolent, in Iraq against the Bagdad Pact and the new Agreement, and to the weakening or fall of Nuri. In that event the whole concept of a Middle east defence organisation would be swept away.5. This risk would be strong if the proposed statement took the form ofa joint Anglo-American Declaration. It would, perhaps, be even stronger if it took the form of an American Declaration containing a sentence to the effect thatit had been discussed with Her Majesty&apos;s Government, who were in agreement.Whatever the facts of the case this would be interpreted in Iraq as indicating thatHer Majesty&apos;s Government had been induced, against their better judgment, toaccept an American proposal.6. Equal risks would not attach to a statement by United States Government(who have not joined the Bagdad Pact) which was followed within say 24 hoursby a statement by Her Majesty&apos;s Government to the effect that the UnitedStates Government had discussed their views with them, that Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment were in general agreement, that the principles outlined are those whichmust govern any attempt to solve the Palestine question by agreement, and perhapsre-state Her Majesty&apos;s Government^ views in their own language.7. This is not to say that the principles contained in the proposed statementare unsound. On the contrary, they are in essence not far from those which anyresponsible Arab Leader admits to be the best that can be done in the circumstances.But the problem is one of timing and presentation. If these proposals had been presented to the Governments concerned confidentially through diplomatic channels, they might have formed the basis of a constructive approach. But to castthem in the form of a public declaration can only retard the prospect of an arab-Israel settlement.8. If, however, for other reasons, it is decided that a statement is necessarythere are certain points which would greatly improve prospects of its reception:  (a) It should be made crystal clear that no Anglo-American Guarantee wouldbe forthcoming except in the event of an agreement on basis of principlesenunciated.(b) It should be made clear that statement does not constitute a plan but an outline of principles; and that no Government is being pressed toaccept them.(c) At least in the case of Iraq it would be of advantage if there could&apos; bemention of the need for a free port at Haifa.(d) Before the issuing of the statement Nuri ought to be assured of futurearms aid.9. To sum up I consider that for Her Majesty&apos;s Government, as a member ofthe Bagdad Pact, to make a joint statement on the lines suggested, or even more so for the United States Government to make a statement saying it has theconcurrence of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, would entail a risk to the survival ofthe Bagdad Pact and of our new Agreement with Iraq, which is difficult to assess,but which might be fatal. This risk would, however, be diminished to a point where it would be a fair one to take if the statement were made by the UnitedStates Government and were followed by a statement by Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment on the lines suggested in paragraph 6 above. Further statement should take account of points at (a), (b) and (c) in paragraphs above.10. If short advance information is to be given to Iraq and other ArabGovernments, this would best be done by the United States Government and not by Her Majesty&apos;s Government as a signatory of the Bagdad Pact.      :i11. I have two final points. Firstly, the risks in Traq would be greatlyincreased if Egypt used the declaration as a weapon to attack Nuri. Secondly, the syrian presidential election is fixed for. 18th August. Would not any statementbe more safely made after it? &apos; : - :    &apos;     *  ^y.^: -       *   *
ANNEX 4DRAFT OF PROPOSED SUPPORTING STATEMENT by her MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe statement of the United States Secretary of State about the Arab-Israelproblem is a very important contribution towards a solution of the most criticaloutstanding problem in the Middle East.2. Her Majesty&apos;s Government share the concern of the United StatesGovernment at the dangerous consequences which may flow from a continuation of present tensions and are ready to play their full part in an effort to bring aboutmore settled relations. . They agree with the analysis which Mr. Dulles has madeof the problems which require to be solved, and believe that the principles outlinedare those which must govern any attempt to solve the Palestine question byagreement.3. Her Majesty&apos;s Government have made it clear on several recent occasionsthat they could not enter into formal engagements to guarantee the frontiers oiIsrael except in the light of a settlement which included a final and agreed definition of those frontiers. Until such a settlement can be reached their obligations mustbe limited to those arising out of the Tripartite Declaration and the Anglo-jordan treaty. We agree in thinking that it should be possible, without detriment to the vital interests of either side, to reach by direct or indirect negotiation a settlement in accordance with instructions given to us last evening by Mr. Dulles andMr. Macmillan, we suggest the following course of procedure on Alpha:  1. Mr. Dulles&apos; statement will be postponed to Thursday, 8th September.2. Attached is a revised draft of Mr. Dulles&apos; statement omitting mention of specific details of the proposed settlement (see Annex 1).3. Mr. Macmillan would make a supporting statement (subject to 4 below)twenty-four hours later. Attached is a suggested draft of such astatement (see Annex 4).4. It will be necessary to await further discussion by the British Cabinet before deciding whether the statements would indicate that Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment had participated fully and from the beginning in theproposals outlined; or whether Mr. Macmillan would merely welcome the Dulles&apos; statement and support it.5. If possible, Mr. Dulles will inform Mr. Macmillan prior to this cabinet discussion (probably around 26th July) concerning (a) what the UnitedStates would be prepared to say to the Iraq Government following theenunciation of the Alpha proposals with respect to eventual UnitedStates adherence to the Turko-Iraq Pact, and (b) whether it would bethe United States Government policy that Iraq be supplied Centuriontanks under Off-Shore Purchase, assuming appropriate timing andpolitical conditions; and whether Nuri might be informed of this and told that delivery of the tanks will depend upon the manner in whichthe Alpha proposals are received by the Iraq Government.6. The United States and United Kingdom Missions in Israel and the arab countries should be informed, on a secret basis, of the proposals for theAlpha statements as soon as Her Majesty&apos;s Government have formulatedits position under paragraph 4 above.Signed FRANCIS H. RUSSELL.C. A. E. SHUCKBURGH.15th July, 1955.
of outstanding issues, including in particular the refugee problem and the frontiers,! in accordance with the broad principles suggested by Mr. Dulles. In that event weshould be ready to guarantee, by treaty or treaties with the parties concerned, any territorial settlement so agreed. The statement that the United States Governmentwould be ready to do likewise is a most important and welcome development whichoffers the prospect of real security to the peoples and States concerned.4. Her Majesty&apos;s Government also welcome the statement that the UnitedStates would be willing to participate in an international loan to assist the State of israel in paying compensation to the Arab refugees. We are ready to make our contribution also.5. These statements should not be regarded in any way as an attempt toexercise coercion upon the Governments or peoples concerned. Nor are immediatereplies expected to the suggestions contained in them. Her Majesty&apos;s government hope, however, that the Governments concerned may be disposed to examinej and discuss in greater detail the advantages which we believe these suggestionscontain.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet:  July 1955SECRET Copy No.    3 0-CP. (55) 8823rd July, 1955CABINETPROPOSED COMMITTEE OF ENQUIRY ON ADMINISTRATIVETRIBUNALSMemorandum by the Lord ChancellorAfter considering my memorandum, CP. (55) 44, on the proposed enquiry into the working of administrative tribunals, the Cabinet asked for detailed proposals on the terms of reference and composition of the Committee (CM. (55)19th Conclusions, Minute 7).2. At my request, Sir Edward Bridges and a group of Permanent secretaries of a number of Departments whose interests are affected prepared draft termsof reference for my consideration and also suggested to me a nurhber of possiblenames for membership of the Committee. I have had the benefit of a discussion on Sir Edward Bridges&apos; proposals with the Lord President, the Minister of housing and Local Government, the Attorney-General, the Minister of State, scottish office, and the Financial Secretary to the Treasury. They approve the following proposals which are made in the light of our discussion and of the suggestions made by officials.Terms of Reference3. In considering terms of reference our aim has been to give the proposed committee as free a rein as possible consistent with the limitation mentioned inparagraph 3 of CP. (55) 44: namely, that they should not be in a position tocanvass the desirability of enabling day-to-day decisions of the Executive to be reviewed by some independent authority. I think that this aim would be met by terms of reference as follows:  &quot; To consider and make recommendations on:  (a) The constitution and working of tribunals, other than the ordinary courts of law, constituted under any Act of Parliament by a Minister of theCrown or for the purposes of a Ministers functions.(b) The working of such administrative procedures as include the holding ofan enquiry or hearing by or on behalf of a Minister on an appeal or as the result of objections or representations, and in particular theprocedure for the compulsory purchase of land.&quot;Paragraph (a) covers all the tribunals established for the purpose of determining questions arising in connection with the work of a GovernmentDepartment, e.g., local tribunals and the National Insurance Commissioner underthe National Insurance Act, 1946, the Pensions Appeal tribunals, the agricultural land tribunals, the Traffic Commissioners who grant road service licences and public service licences, and the National Health Service tribunal, which dealswith the removal of doctors from lists of general medical practitioners. It wouldalso cover tribunals appointed by a Minister for purposes not closely connectedwith government administration, e.g., the rent tribunals; and tribunals whichare in the nature of specialised courts of law, e.g., the Special Commissioners for income tax and the Lands tribunal.  The latter kind of body are not the subject48446   &apos;
of criticism and controversy, but their exclusion seems unnecessary and might make the terms look unduly restrictive. The paragraph does not cover professionaldisciplinary bodies such as the General Medical Council.Paragraph (b) is mainly concerned with statutory procedures for compulsorilyacquiring land or exercising other government functions affecting land, e.g.,planning control under the Town and Country Planning Act, 1947, thedispossession of farmers under the Agriculture Act, 1947, and trunk road schemes.The words used, however, would cover a number of other functions involving the holding of appeals or enquiries into objections. Examples are directions exceptingroads from the speed limit, the regulation of dock charges, the approval of schemesfor coast protection, the determining of disputes with respect to road charges, andthe stopping up of highways. There are also a number of wide powers conferred on Ministers to hold enquiries for the purposes of their functions, e.g., section 318of the Public Health Act, 1936, and section 93 of the Education Act, 1944. Theterms of reference probably would not bring in the functions to which these general powers relate unless in fact the administrative procedure included the holding ofan enquiry as a fairly normal event.In both paragraphs of the draft terms of reference mentioned above, the phrase &quot; the working of&quot; tribunals and administrative procedures is, in myopinion, wide enough to enable the proposed Committee to deal with the powersof the High Court in relation to these tribunals and procedures.Composition4. I think, and my colleagues with whom I have discussed this matter agree,that the right blend of wisdom and experience would be found in a committee made up as follows:  Lord Radcliffe (Chairman).Lord Balfour of Burleigh.Marquess of Linlithgow.Lord Silkin.John Morrison, M.P.Douglas Johnston, Q.C., M.P. formerly Solicitor-General for scotland in the Labour Government.Roderic Bowen, Q.C. Liberal M.P. for Cardigan.The Hon. Charles Russell, Q.C.Sir Edwin Herbert Vice-President of the Law Society.A member nominated by the Trades Union Congress.A representative of Local Authority interests not a lawyer.A woman associated with the Citizen&apos;s Advice Bureau or similar social work possibly Miss Eileen Younghusband.Professor Kenneth Wheare Gladstone Professor of Government andPublic Administration at Oxford.Sir Geoffrey Stuart King formerly Permanent Secretary to the Ministryof Pensions and National Insurance.5. In view of Parliamentary and public interest in this topic I suggest that itwould be desirable to make a further announcement of our intentions as soon aspossible. If the Cabinet approve the proposed terms of reference and decide uponLord Radcliffe for Chairman, I could sound him at once, and, if he accepts, astatement could be made about the terms of reference and the Chairman beforethe Recess.K.House of Lords, S.W. 1,21st July, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
