<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/76/0 images: 335-336</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for theCabinet.  July 1955SECRETCopy No.CP. (55) 9525th July, 1955CABINETLEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME : 1955-56 SESSIONMemorandumm by the Lord Privy SealOn 12th July, the Cabinet, in taking note of my memorandum, CP. (55) 63 onthe state of the legislative programme, invited the Ministers concerned to continue their efforts to ensure that certain Bills were introduced before Parliament rosefor the summer recess (CM. (55) 22nd Conclusions, Minute 7).2. All these Bills have now been introduced in Parliament, or are ready for introduction, with the exception of the Health, Welfare and Safety in AgricultureBill. It is now clear that no further progress can be made with this Bill, whichhas been given preliminary consideration by the Home Affairs Committee, untilagricultural interests have been consulted. It cannot therefore be introduced until after the recess. On the other hand, the Family Allowances Bill is to be brought before the Legislation Committee on 26th July, and appears likely to be ready for introduction before the end of the month. On balance, these Bills should provide sufficient business in the House of Commons for the first two weeks afterParliament reassembles in October. The House of Lords, however, will havevirtually no Bills until they receive some from the House of Commons.3. It is essential to ensure that an even momentum is maintained in preparing and introducing other major Bills in the legislative programme, and invite Ministers concerned to make every effort to ensure that the Bills set out in annex A to this memorandum are ready in time for introduction immediatelyParliament reassembles after the summer recess; and that the further Bills set outin Annex B are ready for introduction as soon as possible thereafter.4. I ask the Cabinet to note that these arrangements may have to be modifiedif it is decided to introduce a Pensions Increase Bill in the autumn, or if theChancellor of the Exchequer should ask for time to be found for a Finance and revenue Bill.H. C.Gwydyr House, S.W.1,22nd July, 1955.48451
ANNEX BBILLS FOR INTRODUCTION AS SOON AS POSSIBLE AFTERPARLIAMENT REASSEMBLES IN OCTOBERAgriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions) or Crown Lands.;  Geneva Conventions (or another major Home Office Bill).Hire Purchase.Housing Subsidies.Teachers&apos; Superannuation.\VBILLS FOR INTRODUCTION WHEN PARLIAMENT REASSEMBLESIN OCTOBERPart I. House of Commons BillsCountervailing and Anti-Dumping Duties.Health, Welfare and Safety in Agriculture.Monopolies.Rating and Valuation (Scotland).Transport (Parliament was informed on 21st July, 1955 that a Bill dealingwith road haulage vehicles would be introduced in the autumn).Part II. House of Lords BillsCopyright.Administration of Justice (or a law Reform Bill, if proposals for legislation on this subject are approved by the Home AffairsCommittee at their meeting on 27th July, 1955).

</content>
</cab>
