<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/9/0 images: 218-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETG.T-557-&apos;&apos;W   IIFAR OA?IrJET184MILITARY SITUATION ON SALONICA EEONT - MARCH 1917,Local Conditionsilo pro bisect of purely military success of a decisive mature this . Summer.1. In order to estimate the point which may bereached by any offensive that will be possible from Salonica this&quot;Summer it is necessary to realise fully 1ocal conditions *The situation may be summed up thus;     The Balkans constitute a theatre of war almost as devoid of communi-cations as the scenes of many of our small wars;    on the other hand, the opposition to he overcome approximates to that of modern war in Europe.Further, European troops are severely handicapped by climate, lack of shelter;  and sickness, as compared with local troops.    As an illustration of the endurance of Balkan troops the following details may be mentionedWhen fighting is in progress, the Serbian soldier carries on his person enough food to keep him going for 5 days,Early in the precent war at the battle of Loznitsa, such of the Serbian wounded as could put foot to the ground, even though snot through the chest or shoulders, had to walm on an average 52 miles before reaching shelter of any kind.     The severely wounded were removed in ox wagons, there being no ambulances available,Troops in the Balkans, and there is little difference as regards endurance between Bulgars and Serbians and Greeks, after marching all day under a hot autumn sun, lie down by the roadside and spend a frosty night without any covering beyond what they themselves carry.     No blankets or overcoats are carried on transport.It is difficult for the less hardy races of Europe to cope with such men as the above in their own countries.Unfortunately the enemy forces in the field are mainly composed of Bulgars, while the Serbians, the only troops we have of the same type, have now only 30.000 infantry with practically no reserves to draw upon..It was entirely due to the magnificent fighting of. the Serbians last Autumn that the French were enabled to occupy Monastir.     They are prepared again to resume the ofiensive,  when called upon, but owing to their small numbers, much cannot be expected from them this Summer.2&apos; An offensive iron Salonica will only be decisivewhen the railway to Constantinople is cut or immediately threatened.     All military opinion at Saloniea is agreed that it will be impossible to reach the railway this Summer, Consequently no decisive success can be looked for in 1917 by purely military means alone.
3.       On the other hand opinions at Salonica agree as to the probability of cur inflicting a severe blow on the Bulgars and perhaps of reaching the line Voles -aStrumnica - Petric.    This advance would,  as a military operation,.-- effect nothing de-oisive, while it would considerably increase our commitments at Salonica.&apos;  The Army would be further from its base,and the flanks would not be so strong-, . for it is improbable that in the new position the left flank could join up with the Italian right flank,  and the right flank would no longer rest on the Sea.Though it is generally agreed,,., however,  that an advance to the line Yeles - Strumica - Petric would not be in itself decisive,   opinions equally agree that it may produce a situation favourable to negotiations-with, a view to detaching Bulgaria f rciii nor allies .4,        This leads to a consideration of --tho pres-ent moral of the Bulgarian Army.    Opinions cn this point differ somewhat cn different parts cf the front; but there seems little doubt that the Bulgars are sick of the war and feel that their country is being ruined during their absence at the front,  in fact,that they are being exploited by the Germans;In Bulgaria peasant proprietorship is univers-al and the peasant - soldiers are closely attached to the soil.   Though they may not be averse to a short campaign at intervals,  if they see a pros-pect cf immediate gain,  their discipline is not good when left under arms for a long period.    In the present war the Bulgarian Army early gained its objective, Laoedonia,  since when it has re-ma.in.ed on the- defensive, has been to some extent beaten and driven -back,  and. is now being insuffici-ently fed.Consequently the moral of the troops is low; as is sufficiently indicated by the fact that a few Germans and Austrian;-! are distributed among even the smallest Bulgarian Units in order to hold them together, while on the Fonastir front the Germans check desertion by &quot;shootcn&quot;&apos; the nearest sentry whenever a Buigar deserts.-The French appear to consider that,  given a second beating;  the Bulgars,  if hard pressed and afforded opportunities to desert,  will do so in large ra bers when the fighting opens out later.Finally,  we should net&apos; lose  sight of the fact that; the Germans are probably experiencing great difficulty in keeping their scratch pack together. -
let of The effect of any offensive that can in presentlat probably circumstances be delivered from Salonica will probably toaporary. only be temporary-and-will ceaso with the arrival of enomy reinforcements or as soon as it is clear that our offensive has come to an end.In order to profit by tho blow wo shall shortly deliver and the situation anticipated to result thorcfrom, tho terms to be offered to Bulgaria must be settled beforehand, and thoy should be commoni-cated to tho Army at Lalonica and mado knownthroughout Bulgaria.this is not done beforehand, the situation may ohango, and tho opportunity to negotiate may lapse without advantage having been taken of it.5.To recapitulate the ar umont up to this &quot;joint:-(a) In tho Balkans, Juuropean armies are much handicapped by local conditions, and wo havo a small proportion of troops suited to tho country, while tho opposition tobo overcome approximates to that of Buropo.(b) Ho dooisivo succoss can be gained this summer by moans of military operations alonoi(c) On the othor hand, a situation favourable to negotiations with Bulgaria will probably bo produced.(d) This situation may only be temporary and in order to profit by itj wo must bo prepared to act quickly, that is, wo must at onco dotormino tho corms to bo offered to Bulgaria.If this is not done, tho Allied forces may nort autumn be holding the lino Teles -Strumnica - Potric and unable to&quot;advance further until tho Spring of 1910, and tho Balonioa expedition will have achieved nothing decisive in 1917.lit of6f If Bulgaria were detached, tho wholo situationin Europe would be changed, for tho through lineof railway&apos;to Constantinople would be irame&amp;iatoly threatened, and only such Gorman and Austrian troops as could bo spared for this front would o mo so the Allios.Tho possibility of negotiating with Bulgaria has already boon dealt with, and it only&apos;remains to sayfranco, Mesopotamiathat tho British succossos in and Sg- pt may incline Bulgaria she would not havo considered ;toaocepx ar ago.conditionsBulgaria7. It will no doubt bo difficult for the Allies toBible terms agreo irjoa torms which Bulgaria will accept; but&quot;       this should not bo impossible.   In the iirsc ^place-Bulgaria- should bo informed that tho Allios do ncc want to crush her, but only dosiro that she should remove her armies and leave them froo to get at our real enemies, the Germans *
18- 4 -Basing the terms on the existing situation, tho Bulgars might retain:-fa)   3. Macedonia, as far &quot;Zest as the -jtruma;(b) &quot;Tho Dobrudja, as far as the former Bulgarian frontier.In cj.sc (a), tho territory was abandoned by Greece to Bulgaria, and in case (b) Bulgaria has recapture territory that formerly belonged to her, Roumania having proved incapable of retaining her Ill-gotten gains of 1913, .(c) The case of the&quot;terms as they affect Serbia presents more difficulty, owing to rash promises already made,   Probably all that can here be offered to Bulgaria amounts to a slight revision in favour of Bulgaria of the Sorbo-Bulgarian frontier as far as this is possible without inflicting any considerable loss on porbia. .(d) Ho proposal&apos; regarding Adrianoplo or Thrace is perhaps desirable at tho moment as these arenow in tho enemy1 s possession, but no doubt an under-taking to support a return to the Enoc - Llidia line would bo welcome to Bulgaria,(c)   In tho present circumstances tho Bulgars would probably accept tho above terms, (a), (b). and (c), &quot;but if not, we have another powerful instrument, money*   Eon days or a fortnightVb cost of tho war to the Allies would place Bulgaria in an o^coilont/ financial situation, and be good business f oi* tho . -liics.&quot;It may bo argued that wo shall loco prestige if we stoop to bribing small nations, but if we win the war there will bo&quot;prestige and to spare for all the Entente countries,- whoroas an inconclusive peace will leave -Wiistrian and Gorman influence paramount in the Balkans.(f)    Tho Bulgar is patriotic and attached to his land-, and the terms offered must make it quite clear to him that by siding with the Entente or deserting, &apos; ho is not leaving his country to bo ruinod.ig) All deserters might be offered free to America and return to Bulgaria at tho endtransport of the rraIt remains to consider some of tho obstacles to the settlement of the&apos; above terms, though none of those obstacles are of real importance,(a)    To deal first^ with borpia.    If Serbia retains Monastir and&quot;&quot;the&quot;oldGr aeco--Verdian frontier to Lako Boiran she should bo well content;    She has no real claim to any part of Macedonia, which - she herself by the uecrot Treaty of March, 1912, renounced in favour of Bulgaria,   Subsequently she obtained it quite illogically as compensation for being turned back from the . driatic and for territory lost by her in/consequence
consequence of the formation on an Independent . Jfoania.During tho present war Serbia, instead of being conciliatory, refused to come to terms with Bulgaria, ana formulated impossible demands by way of componsa-ti on if sho had to give up Macedonia to Bulgaria.If it should, however, prove necessary now to forco Serbia to be conciliatory, wo should not hesitate to do so.     Her misguided action has already cost her Allies and herself sufficiently dear,(b)   Nationalist&quot;Qrooks.   Any claims to eon-si deration put forward by Vonozolists will be amply mot by restoring tho former oorbo-Greck frontier as far East as the btruma, and by tho eventual rostoration of galonica to Greece.   The assistance givon to the&quot;Allies by the Nationalist troops, though praiseworthy, is not sufficient to bo a bar to our using tho&apos;territory oast of tho Struma, relinquished by Greece, to do a deal with Bulgaria,,(o)   Oortain proposals have boon mooted as to the formation of a Jugo - Slav btate, and its advocates may insist on tho inclusion of liacodonia in this State.   The whole subject is, however., very indofinito and any concrete proposals must necessarily include the disposal of Austrian provinces without tho views Of tho inhabitants having been consulted.   Such proposals should not constitute a serious difficulty,(d)   Another point to consider is tho difficulty Bulgaria would experience in detaching herself from her Allies..   Despite tho fact that&apos;tho Germans dominate Sofia at the present time, and that Germans and Austricns are distributed among Bulgarian units and Bulgarian units arc fighting on other fronts, it may safely be left to tho Buigars to find a means of detaching themselves,Balkan countries have experience in such matters,(o)   formerly a desire existed among certain circles and has boon oitprosood in iiussia that Bulgaria must be destroyed,   . Statements made by prominent men in Russia are hot generally considered binding lixo those made in European countries, and tho recont upheaval affords a good opportunity of instituting a policy more in accordance with tho needs of the ml1i t ary situa t i on,Within the limits of a short paper, I have endoavourod to show that iii my opinion - and this opinion is shared by &quot;the C. in C. Salonika Army, and&apos;&apos;all men, English, French and Russian, with experience of Balkan countries, with whom I liavo discussed the question -(a) The Salonika force must fail to achieve decisive results unless Bulgaria is detached,(b) That tho Allies may shortly bo able to inflict a defeat on the Bulgarian army, and that this defeat may temporarily produce a situation favourablo to negotiations.
(c)   That in order to profit by this temporary situation, stops must be taken without delay to determine tho terms to be offered to Bulgaria* ^(&amp;) That in- spito of. obvious difficulties, it is not impossible for the- Allies to agree on such terms.It should never be forgotten that, unless Bulgaria is detached, tho Salonika expedition can novor achieve a decisive success0On the other hand; if Bulgaria is detached tho way to oofia is open to us, unless the. enemy despatches&quot;a largo German or Austrian Army to the Salonika front.(Signed)   E. Aa PLUIKETT, .   It. Col.31st March, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
