<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/9/0 images: 304-304</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
E C R E T. G.T. - 360.CONTROL OF METAL SUPPLIES. (Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Munitions) .The experience of the Ministry rf Munitions fully confirms the statements made in the Memorandum hy the Minis-ter of Blockade (G.T. 891) and is in agreement with the recommendations of the Inter-Departmental Committee.It is clearly of the utmost importance (l) that effective steps should he taken as soon as possible to prevent the transfer of mining leases or rights in rniner-als in the United Kingdom&apos;without licence both during and -after the War, in order to prevent their acquisition by foreigners;    (2) that similar steps should be taken,  so far as the Dominions and other representatives are prepared to agree, with respect to minerals in other parts of the Empire,, and   (3) though this presents much greater difficulties,  that steps should be taken to prevent,  so far as may be practicable, the transfer, without a lioence,  of mining properties in foreign countries owned by British companies or individuals.In connection with (l) the Mines Development Depart-ment recently established by the Ministry of Munitions,  or some similar organisation, would have to be continued, and in connection with (2) an Imperial Mines Bureau would need to be set up in London to oollate information from the Mines Departments of all the Dominions and Colonies in the Empire and to advise on matters of policy.It is recognised, however,  that the foregoing steps oannot be made really effective, unless there were establish-ed a Mining Corporation,  supported by a Metal Bank,   of sufficient strength to deal with the development of mining properties in an effective manner and to prevent their alienation.If such a Mining Corporation were formed,  it might be possible to call on all British ow&amp;ers of foreign mining rights to make a return of their properties and to enact that none should be. transferred after the War without a licence.    Such a licence would no doubt have to be granted in each case, unless the Mining Corporation were prepared    % to buy or place the property.    The administration cf this Act could be taken in hand by the Mines Development Depart-ment administering (l)(Sgd)    C. ADDISON.3rd April, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
