<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/9/0 images: 488-494</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mmm of blockade XHtmiffisBosliaroh gQ * April 5. 1917*QSBMAg SUBHA3IHS j&amp;QQ]yM*She fallowing casualties, due to enei^ activity, wore officially reported in the period Kerch SO * AprilSteamships, 500 tons ftrosg &amp; overs-(a) British   **********.....   64,06? tons gross.(b) Central   *******.....***    9,429     &quot;      &quot;galling, yeseele, 100 tone. fflrpes  &quot;over:-(a) British *************** 418 fb) Hentral   ...............    3,260f? ft64	,405	,69797	,102Total, British .... ^otal, Neutral  ....Grand ?otal   ....On April 1 were reported as captured, probably sunk, by a German raider in the Atlantic, at uncertain dates:-3 British steamships   ....   9,972 tons gross. 4 French steamships    ....   9,676    H     &quot; , 3 British sailing ships ..   4,748    rt 1 Italian sailing ship ,..1,611    &quot; 6,207 tone gross.H*M* Government have now ooERpleted the arrange-ments for exaisining cargoes at Freetown (Sierra Leone) and Kingston (Jaiaaiea).    Bvery day brings further evi. denoe of the valne which neutral shipowners and govern, mento atteoh to the exemption of their ships from call-ing in the united Kingdom.
The Norwegian Government have pretested against the German declaration of a danger gene in the Arctic Ocean.The Dutoh Government, in consequence of German threats, have definitely refuses our demands on the subject of armed rcerohanttaen.    H.M. Government realising the difficulties of Hollands situation, do not propose to take extreme measures.   It 1b evident that the Dutch Government fear a Oensan invasion and are panic -stricken at the prospect.   But all special facilities will he refused to Xtatoh vessels;   and Lord Bobert Cecil hae intlisated that we hold ourselves at liberty to requisition the Dutoh vessels detained In British ports. Hone of these vessels will bo released until regular Dutch sailings to the United Kingdom ere rested.There is some excuse for tho reluctance of Dutoh owners to trade with the United Kingdom.   The Holland Steamship Company, who have been eommendably &quot;bold, have lost five-eighths of their fleet, and have been black-listed by Germany, bo that no new ships oan be completed for them in Dutch yards. he United States Shipping Boara appear anxious to build up en American merchant marine at our expense. They propose to amend the United States Shipping Act of 1916 so that no ship now building for foreign account in the United States oan he launched during tho war, unless she is owned by an American corporation and registered as an American ship.       Further, if such a ship engages in foreign trade she must be officered according to American law, and must ooramenee or end each voyage at an American pert.    We are urging the State Department
to prevent these conditions from i)eing applied to the vessels for which we have already contracted,    A considerable number of these should be completed in the nest few months if no legal difficulties are created. The President of the Shipping Board has a strong dislike to our Statutory Black  let5   and if we with-draw the Mst, his attitude towards us may change ,considerably.fe have appointed Mr. Sparks, tho Hanager of the Cunard Company, to cooperate with tho United States Authorities in all shipping matters.    He will impress on them tho urgent need of tonnage for Allied trades; and will explain how the United states can relieve Groat Britain of a portion of her responsibilities towards the Allies.fhe new Swedish Government are rather unexpeot-eaiy willing to meet us on tho subject of the British ships detained In the Baltic.     hey arc impressed&quot; by our announcement that Swedish vessels cannot be examined at Halifax, or elsewhere, outside the United Kingdom, unless our ships are allowed to escape by the Kogrund Passage.       Accordingly Admiral Mndman Is pre-pared to let these ships go through the Passage In May and June at tho rate of one a day.      He stipulates that they shall sail in ballasts   from which Sir 1. Howard concludes that ho is acting under some arrange-ment with Germany in the matter.      Sir 15. Howard thinks that wo should insist upon the concession being extended to all Allied ships In the Baltic.^he Norwegian Government have not yet signified approval of our scheme for requisitioning Norwegian
ships * although m have agreed to practically all the demands of the mmers.      Sersaany is aware of our negotiations m&amp; is using every possible msans to defeat them - so far, without success.The Spanish Government are willing that a quantity of the Spanish vessels in Atlantic ports should he time-chartered to us and defensively armed* But they insist that some British ships should be earmarked to carry coal from the United kingdom to Spain.    negotiations with the   argots      Cortina are proceeding in London.-    Meanwhile the Spaniitt mining interests are up in arms against the oondi-tions whioh their (Jovomraent havo imposed upon ore-ships.    The whole of the Huelva district appears to bo ^n our side in this question.tei are informing the Banish Government that no facilities will in future be given to cargoes destined for Denmark unless they are e$Tried in Danish bottoms.    M exception will however bo made in favour of Norwegian vessels mkiQh were loaded or loading for Denmark before April 1.jQSTRABAHp. In the week ending April 4 none of the shipmentsreported to tho Contraband Committee were places in the Prise Court.    2he tramp steamers which, as a rule, are used for the contraband trade have teispor-arily desisted from this profitable business. Tnwikn to the navioert system, and to our special agreements with the chief Butch ana Scandinavian shipping lines, the more Important of the Atlantic cargo boats are now seldom founi to be carrying
objectionable cargo.Danish exporters of butter have been surprised and alarmed to find that the supplies ?ttteh th^ forward to the United Kingdom have lately been refused by a number of British importers, on the ground that a glut exists in the United  ingfioga.   A few sore refusals of this kind would wreck the Agri-cultural Prod no e Agreement.      $he D&amp;niEh exporter makes a considerably higher profit on the German than on the British tradeg and we compel him to export to the United Kingdom at hie own risk. So long as heforwards supplies to us at the agreed price, he has a right to expect that he will find a purchaser. H.M. Government are taking steps to ensure the accept-anoe of future Banish supplies as they arrive, and are considering the desirability of establishing (like the Germans) a Purchasing Agency in Copenhagen.Statistics of the Imports of German fuel into Denmark, for the period Jan. 1 - March 15, are now available.       She monthly average is lower than that of 1916;   end it may be inferred that some time must elapse before Denmark can dispense with British coal, even if her new arrangements with the Gossan mines and railways work smoothly.She composition of the new Swedish Ministry is unsatisfactory.    The Premier* lir. Swsrts, repre-sents the same political tendencies as his pre&amp;eces-eors.      She Minister of Foreign Affairs, Admiral Lindmen, was largely responsible for the failure of
a.   $  -the Anglo-Swedish negotiations in 1915.      But the Ministry e&amp;lets &amp;Ponr stafferanee, and would fall at onee if its opponents made common cause against it. Admiral  lntiman realises that he must obtain the release of the Swedish Tassels which we hold as hostages;   that the Swedish lines cannot resume Sailings until we grant them special facilities; and that Sweden must import large cargoes of cereals by May, if she is to avoid a broad famine.    Hence his offers to open the Kogrund Passage, to conclude (subject to some amendments) the Anglo-Swedish Agreement, and to facilitate the insurance of Swedish ships and cargoes boumi for the United Kingdom.   His good-faith may be doubtful;   but so long as Sweden remains short of cereals he will hardly dare to play us false.RHLAgPS. For reasons \$iieh can only be conjecturedthe Semen Government appear to be forcing a quarrel on the Retherlands.      The Dutch Government are al-ways timid, and the danger may be no greater then that in which the Swiss found themselves in June 1916, when Germany threatened a cessation of commercial intercourse, unless certain supplies were released within a fortnight.    2hat ultimatum was resisted and ultimately withdrawn.      But the Butch Government believe that an invasion by Germany is imminent.?J) She United States Government are prepared tocooperate in our bunker policy, so far as is necess-ary to prevent supplies from reaching enemy raiders or submarines, or firms v&amp;ioh are knovn to be assist-
6th April 1917.ttr   ^   ming enemy crafts.      SJhey will not cooperate in our banker policyt or in our Statutory List policy, against any firm who arc not identified with specific enemy activities.I!* Cochin, in spite of his discussions, remains unconvinced of the necessity for purchasing Swiss oattlot      Apart from the cost of the operation, which H.M. Government have offered to share, M. Cochin is in-fluenood by the difficulty of transporting the cattle from Switzerland to Prance.   Ho hopes that he may per-suade the Swiss to limit their sales of es&amp;tle to Germany to .30,000 to 40,000 head, simply in return for a sufficient supply of oil-cake.   But the Allies also require from Switzerland large quantities of condensed milk and timber;   and it remains to be seen whether these supplies will be forthcoming without some more generous offer from our side than M* Oochln proposes to ;imake. 1 he Swiss commercial negotiations with Crermanyiare proceeding.    The Swiss hope to prolong the present Agreement until July 31;   if a new Agreement is necessary, they will demand larger deliveries of coal, iron and steel than they at present receive. In any case the only articles sfeioh Switzerland can      I use this summer for purposes of exchange are dairy produce, condensed milk and chocolate.H.W.C.D. IWar grade Intelligence department.

</content>
</cab>
