<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/9/0 images: 530-532</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/0\ oG,!D.- 393i&amp;R CABINET,vLBIITATION OP:SHIPPING PROFITS....... .&apos;P?&apos;.K.lspn^sy(Memorandum by tlio Shipping Controller)1, &quot;The *,Jar Cabinet has decided:-O)&quot; To make requisition univorssl or as nearly universal as nay bo..(b)   To deal with profits in a manner corresponding mutatis mutandis with that adopted in tho case of the Hallways*This po-licy is understood to moan:-(a) The control by Government, of tho use of mercantile tonnage.(b) The limitation of &quot;the profits earned by suoh tonnage to a suitable pre-war standard.The extension of requisition is dealt with elsewhere, and all that need bo said here is that the intention of the ITar Cabinet to continue the payment of Blue. Book rates for tho use of the vessels docs not create any difficulty in dealing with profits, although it involves some modification in the method of applying the Railway Agreement.&apos;  Suoh modification would, however, have boon necessary in any case&apos;.3. Tho main principles of the Railway Agreement are:-(a) That no payment is made by the Government for services &apos;.    performed for the Government.(b) &apos; fhat the Railway earnings are thrown into a common fundand tho guarantee applies to that common fund and not t( the Railways individually.4. In applying the Agreement to Shipping; the formerprinciple is modified if Blue Book hire is- paid, and the latter principle would probably be unworkable; if not unworkable, it &quot; would at any rate create&apos;a great mass of additional work which, in the national interest, ought tc be avoided in the present stato of the labour market&quot;.5. lor another reason the principle of the RailwayAgreement will.have, to be modified in its application to Shippingi     Railway Capital and Not Revenue are relatively constant-/   hipping Capital and Net Revenuo are about as variable as anything can be.   It follows that if owners are dealt with individually, an&quot; to some extent even if they are compelled to pool, any proposal to guarantee in terms of amotmt, a fixed pre-war standard revenue would at once give rise to an irresistible demand ircmifia^&apos;%uarters for special variations in view of the fluctuations in xhe amount of the Capital enroloyodin/
in tne^ business.     In this connection it oust be remembered! that po value ox tonnage has greater incr^sed d^O -that the value at the moment is ver/uncertain   and fet^ narkoci diminution in values is not unlikelv i^thePurther, tho margin of -orofit in the. tw  X 5    ? ^lq   .  ^ 1,7     .    ^e^iuo oook rates defendsicu^e-i.^ un wiie cos u ui marine m^nnrs r-v-? ,-.i.  - .    -v--. -, -   J-u-0icnc current value of the vessel. 11 aopauds on5, To sum up ohe i ore going, i&apos;c appears necessary:-(a) to deal with owners individually and not with tho industry collectively.(b) to pay Blue Book hire for 8.11 requisitioned vessels and consequently to proceed by way of paying for the use of the vessels and limiting the profits, and notray of nj net revenue7, This method would have the further advantage ofavoiding highly contentious legislation which would be necessary (to prevent an enormous counter-balancing loss of excess profits duty, income tax and super tax) if the principle of not paying for the use of the vessels on Government service were adopted.0. Turning to another aspect of the subject, it has&quot;been argued that in vioi7 of the high profits of the&apos; years 1912. 1913 and 1914,  the pro-war standard to be taken for the present-purpose should be different from and lower than the pre-war&quot; standard adopted for tho purpose of tho excess /profits - duty0 figures showing in general the average percentages of profits in the Shipping Industry for several pro-war years have already been furnished.&quot;In the opinion of the Shipping Controller, the question of the pre-war standard to be-adopted is closely connected with that of the percentage of the profits above that standard to be levied.   A levy of say Buy or 90$ would justify a lower standard than a levy of 100$.9. The following scheme in outline is therefore suggested:-(i) Government control to be secured by the widest possible requisitioning, as already decided,(ii) Blue Book hire to be -aid for requisitioned&apos; vessels and Blue Book freight for. Government stores carried in any vessel not requisitioned.(iii)&apos;&quot;Return of income&quot; to be made representing x pel&quot; centof the difference between the profits of the undertaking and an Individual&apos;pre-war standard profit special to the Shipping Industry, or y per cent of the difference between the actual profits and the individual pro-war standard assessed for the purposes of excess profits duty.(iv) The special pre-war standard to be arrived at by taking the average of the x pre-war years subject where the capital employed in the business has increased or diminished to the same adjustments as are made in simi-lar cases for excess profits duty purposes.   In making these adjustments, the definition of the capital to be as defined for the purpose of income tax and excess profits duty (see note a) *(?)
o -(v)    he soli one to &quot;be expressed, in legislative terns, as an addition to ozooss profits duty, and;tho machinery of that &quot;duty to &quot;be applied.   This is the simplest way of avoiding&apos; tho creation of a special machinery for tho collection of tho levy - a tasi:&quot;which is probably impossible under present conditions, and which oven if attempted, would involve embarrassing demands for tho exemption from military services of a large number of accountants and others,Hoto.s The definition of capital for Inland Pevonuo purposesis roughly as follows:-&quot;Money put into tho business less (a) depreciation at 4f (normally) on first cost, (b) so much of that money as is borrowed on mortgage or debentures, and (c) less debts: and any unpaid purchase money&quot;In the oaso of vessels whose ownership has changed-during the war; depreciation is only allowed on the pre-war value of the vessels.7th April, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
