<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/17/0 images: 149-152</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;SGOVERNMENT)COPY 1^0. cQ^^CABINETSTEVSNAGE,(NEW TOWN) AND PLYMOUTH(/TOWN &quot;Nl3 COUNTRY PLANNING! ORDERSNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister Icirculate herewith a copy of a Minute which hehas received from the Attorney-General on therecent decisions of the Courts on the StevenageNew Town (Designation) Order,  1946 and the City,of Plymouth (City Centre) Declaratory Order,  1946.( S i gne d)    NORMAN BR 0 OKo E 0 R S TC^if^ .47j^6925TH FEBRUARY,  1947Cabinet Office , S.W.1,25TH FSBRTL-by,   1947.
STEVENAGB  (NEW TOWN) AM) PLIMOliTH  (TOmjimCOUNTRY PLANNING&quot;! orders in my view the decisions of Mr. Juntie Horn Collinsin these cases should be appealed:, if necessary to theHouse of Lords, and all possible stupe  should bo taken to expedite the hearings.    I understand that it -nay bo possible -to reach a conclusion in the House of Lords by the end ofMay.      Concurrently with this course steps should bo takento hold a now enquiry into the Stevenage case.1 (a)  In the 3tovenago case the learned Judge held thatthe Minister,  before entering upon the Local Enquiry whichho was required to hold,  had made up his mind that S tovon agowas to be a Now Town, come what might;     that his functionduring the Enquiry and in confirming the Provisional Order thatStevenago should be a New Town was a quasi-judicial one andthat ho foiled to deal with the objection in  relation to water Supply and Sewage disposal in a judicial manner or&apos;&quot;&apos;to preserve an open mind as an honest Judge&quot;,(B) In my view these findings are misconceived.      TheMinister is required under the New Towns Act to reach at least a provisional decision before any question of a public enquiryarises;    the enquiry itself is one into his own proposal andis as to  th.; objections only.    To say that the Ministeroccupies a Judicial capacity in the matter involves almost acontradie a.5  n in terms, since it is- wholly inconsistent with the idea of justice that a man should bo a judge in hisown cans,.;.      The true position under this Act is  that theMinister acts in an  executive and Ministerial capacity,certainly at the point when he makes his final decision andprobably all through.      The purpose of the public Enquiry isto or)able him to investigate fully the grounds of objectionwhich may be advanced and  to enable objectors to canvass theirarguments in public and under the  sanction of public opinion.Considered from a strictly judicial point of view theproceedings are a farce, as was indeed  said  in terms byMr.  Justice Singleton in a closely comparable co.se, and thisis itself o. strong reason for thinking that the Statute neverintended  Ijjhat the Enquiry should be regarded as judicial.    Whorethe State acts on behalf of the Community as a whole  it is really boside the point to talk about natural justice asbetween individuals as the learned. Judge did at some littlelength.2.   (a) In the Plymouth cases the Judge considered that theMinister could only be satisfied on evidence^ which he as a judge was entitled to review, that it. was requisite to include certain promises in an area of war damage to be redeveloped andlaid out as o. whole and that there was no such evidence before him.    He held that the Minister&apos;s function throughout wasqua si-judicial.(B) Assuming that it was open to the High Court toconsider the point at all, there was ? in my opinion,sufficient evidence in one of the Plymouth cases,:, and possibly in both,  to justify the Minister&apos;a decision.    Under the town planning lets there are stronger grounds for regarding certain of the Minister&apos;s functions as-being quasi-ju.di.eial than is thecase under the New Towns Act, but even so I am of the view thatthe ulticisto  decision is probably a Ministerial one and not open to review by the Courts on the ground that there was no orinsufficient evidence to support it.
3.  Although, however,, I have myself little doubt that the3leverage and at least one of the Plymouth decisions were wrong in law, I do not think that the prospects of upsetting them on appeal are more than -slightly in the kinis tor&apos;s favour, and i cannot follow the example of one of my predecessors who (unwiselyas it turned out)  &quot;pledged his professional reputation&quot; on thesuccess of an appeal.    It must, I think, bo recognised that having supported the Executive during the war the Judiciary will now tend to go in the other direction;    indeed this was expresslyanticipated in one of -the war-time decisions of the House ofLords.    Moreover, as was very apparent in the course of theproceeding.? before Mr.  Justice Horn Collins, colic ctivist action by the State runs counter not only to the traditions of Englishlaw but also to those of most English lawyers.    It is clearlyintolerable that questions of administrative policy should beopen to challenge in the Courts whore Ministers have acted in good faith simply on the ground that the evidence publiclyadduced was  insufficient to justify the decisions taken and,   -quite apart from the present cases,  it will be- for consideration whether legislation should not be introduced codifying the lawas to the public enquiries which Ministers are required to hold-under various Statutes and making it clear that the eventualdecisions cannot bo reviewed by the Courts.h.    None the less, I think it essential to appeal thepresent cases.    Hot only would the present decisions be mostembarrassing to us  in subsequent cases,  but it seems to me tobe politically important - particularly if we have later tointroduce legislation - that wo should make it clear at once that we strongly challenge Mr.  Justice Henn Collins&apos;  view ofthe law.5. It is not altogether clear from the judgment whetherthe Judge would have held the Minister to be precluded bybias from confirming the Stevenage Order had it not been forthe inconclusive nature of the Minister&apos; a findings on the-objections in regard to Pater and Sewage.    This being so Iconsider that the Minister should at once  initiate freshproceedings in regard to 8leverage under the Now Towns Act,and I will discuss with him the manner in which such proceedingsshould be conducted.    If these proceedings are,  as they maywell be, successfully challenged in the Courts ,  that factwill stren ;then the case for fresh legislation-.    If, on theother hand.,  th.  eventual Order is upheld it w ill overcome theneed for legislation should the appeal in the present case fail.6.    it should perhaps be added that whilst the Stevenagecase was without precedent, there were various justifiablecriticisms which, in the light of existing decisions, co,uldhave been made of the procedure followed by the Ministry inthe Plymouth case.    Indeed had it not been for the fortunatefact that the main Plymouth case was settled, I have nodoubt that irregularities would have been brought to lightwhich would have resulted in the whole Order being quashed.II. S..LAW OFFICERS&apos; DEPARTMENT2hTH FEBRUARY, 19h7.


</content>
</cab>
