<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/17/0 images: 288-289</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property op his britannic majesty&apos;s government&apos;3E C RE tc.P.(k7) 9316th march, 19U7.copy no,CABINETREVISION OP THE ANGLO-SOVIET TREA&apos;Memorandum by the Prime Minister,The Foreign Secretary has reported by telegram from Moscowthat he has instructed II.M. Ambassador to inform M. Vyshinskythat he is willing to discuss the question of revising theAn-io-Soviet Treaty as soon as the Soviet Government find thisconvenient.    H.M. Ambassador has seen M. Vyshinsky   whoinformed him that the matter was one which Generalissimo Stalmhimself was attending to personally ana verhe mils t therofo rcan answer as soortherefore welcomefor the revisionRecommendation.seek instructions as possible. TheCabinet authorityf the Treaty.closely, and that and would give H.M. AmbassadorForeign Secretary would to proceed with discussionsI recommend thatnegotiate a Treaty, gAnglo-French Treaty,as he may think necesfull discretion as regardsnegotiations.he Foreign Secretary be authorised tooing as far as, but no further than, the giving him full latitude to make variationsary.   We should leave the Foreign Secretaryprocedure and tactics in these considerations.The Cabinet vvorcign Secretary&apos;eadate madeL    tondiwhen he suggestsdate madedead wood out chave any objectprovisions regafuture system of idrafted before thebeing. Stalin alsTreaty would probeadditions.ill recalls enquiry 1that Stalin in reply to thehat reservations he had in mind that the Anglo-Soviet Treaty should be broughtclear that he was thinking of cutting the he Treaty, notably Part I, which ceased tothe:nd of the war with Germany,  and thethe Treaty and ationalicurity which were, of course,United Nations Organization had come intoo  said that the text of the Anglo-Sovietbly demand certeain other amendments and3.Itdate, the expected that, apart from bringing the Treaty up toOUVicUGovernment will ask forthe inclusion in any new bilateralaty ofJlausos s&apos;imilar to the Anglo-FrenchTreatyf m particular as regards action to forestall any renewedthreat of German aggression.    The Anglo-French Treaty v/as draftedwith the possibility of such a Russian demand in mind, and inthe view of the Foreign Office there would be no objection to negotiations for the revision of on this basis.the 19h2 Treaty being conducted10, Downing Street, S.W.1.16TH MARCH,  19h7.


</content>
</cab>
