<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/104/0 images: 24-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
is DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) IC. (61) 46th January, 1961COPY NO.CABINETLAOSNote by the irrime minister have not so far called a meeting of the Cabinet to discuss thesituation in Laos because we have not yet been faced with the need to take any decisions of grave national importance.2.     I am sure however that my colleagues would like to know of thepresent position, and I am therefore circulating a copy of amemorandum on the position which has been prepared by the foreign secretary.H. M.Admiralty House, S.W.1.6th January, 1961.SITUATION IN LAOSMemorandum by the Foreign SecretarymAs we had expected, the Communists in Laos have reacted to theformation of the right-wing Boun Oum Government by launching an all-outattack.    They did not attempt seriously to defend the capital, Vientiane,against the advance of General Phoumi&apos;s forces, but shortly afterwardsthe Pathet Lao recruits, which had been withdrawn into North Vietnam fortraining, returned to attack the northern provinces.    It seems clear thatthe intention is to capture all the northern towns, including probably theroyal capital of Luang Prabang, and to set up a Communist-run area, asin the early stages of their campaigns in North Vietnam and North Korea.The Pathet Lao troops, assisted by Captain Kong Lae and his men, seemto be achieving their object fairly easily.2. It is hard to determine the extent of foreign interference. It istrue, as the Americans allege, that Fvussian &quot;planes have been droppingweapons and supplies, and may already have sent up to 500 tons.    It is-1-
fairly certain that North Vietnamese officers and perhaps specialistsaccompanied the returning Pathet Lao battalions.     They will no doubt be withdrawn at once if any Commission arrives to investigate.3.      The Americans at first showed signs of wanting to seek a militarysolution.    We are convinced that the intervention of forces of the South-East Asia Treaty Organisation would bring in North Vietnamese and chinese &quot;volunteers&quot;.    The Chiefs of Staff have reported that in such a situation the best we could hope for would be a stalemate and there wouldbe everylikelihood of defeat without using nuclear tactical weapons.     Fight-ing would probably extend to Vietnam.4.      We have therefore been looking for possible political solutions,and we want to exhaust these before seriously contemplating intervention.The best one seems to be the return of the International Commission.Under its existing constitution it must work for the integrity and unity ofLaos.    We should probably not get anything as good as this at a resumedGeneva Conference.     Ita first task would have to be to put a stop to thefighting and prevent the further import of arms which are contrary to the geneva agreements.     We have obtained the conditional agreement of theLaotian Government and the Americans to the return of the Commission,5.      The main difficulty at present concerns the status of the Boun GumGovernment.    It now has the backing both of the King and the LaotianAssembly and we are prepared to accept it de facto as a constitutional government.    Mr. Gromyko however considers the rebels to be the legalGovernment, and pretends that Prince Souvanna Phouma is still theirPrime Minister.     The Indians are refusing to take up a position .    all of this will lead to difficulties for the Commission, particularly a.s theBoun Oum Government insists that the Chairmen must get in touch withthem as a first step.6.     I think we can say that the early American enthusiasm for amilitary operation into which the members of the South-East Asia treaty organisation must have been drawn is receding:  that we have a chanceof getting the International Control Commission into Laos, providedIndia will co-operate and Mr. Gromyko will acquiesce.    If the Russiansveto the suggestion world opinion will, I believe, be against them.    Itis likely that we shall have to end up with something like a geneva conference reconvened but we want to avoid any such suggestion now asthe Americans might then run out on their grudging acquiescence in theControl Commission.H.Foreign Office, 3.W.I.6th January, 1961.SEGRET


</content>
</cab>
