<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/104/0 images: 236-254</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
179THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1961C. (61) 38 Copy No.  5617th March, 1961CABINETWHITE PAPER ON THE NATIONALISED industries memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department on 10th March, 1960, the Cabinet agreed that, with the object of bringing about a greater sense of financial responsibility on the part of the nationalisedBoards, the Ministers concerned should discuss with them whether it would bepossible to obtain a clearer understanding of their financial and economicobligations (C.C. (60) 16th Conclusions, Minute 3). Discussions with the boards have accordingly taken place on the basis of the aide-memoire (the Annex toC. (60) 39) which was approved by the Cabinet at that time, and the result is thedraft statement annexed to this paper.2. This statement was approved by the Committee on Nationalised Industriessubstantially in the present form prior to the final round of consultations with the boards. The Committee recommended that it should be published in the formof a White Paper. The central idea is that, without amending the statutory obligations of the nationalised industries, a more satisfactory basis for their operation in the public interest could be achieved if those obligations wereinterpreted more precisely. The suggestion is that specific financial objectivesshould be determined for each industry within a general framework laid down inthe White Paper. Details of the proposed framework and of the procedures to befollowed are set out in paragraphs 19-29 of the draft.3. The only other paragraphs to which I would particularly draw theattention of my colleagues are those dealing with prices and costs (paragraphs30-33). We have all along recognised that, if the nationalised industries acceptclearer financial obligations, it will affect the ways in which we are able to intervene in pricing and social policies. Although a case for complete freedom for the boards could be made out (and the Coal Board have in fact suggested this),Ministers may still on occasion wish to influence price and other policies. Howcould such intervention be reconciled with the aim of giving the Boards greaterfinancial responsibility? The proposal in the draft White Paper is that, if a Boarddecide to modify their own proposals by reason of views expressed by the Minister,it would be open to them to require a written statement of those views, whichcould be published if the Board so desired, and to propose an appropriateadjustment of their financial objectives. The Committee on Nationalised Industriesconsider that this would usually be the best way to deal with these difficulties,which should not in practice prove serious if the arrangements proposed areworked in a way that restricts the freedom of the Boards as little as possible. as for compensation for undertaking uneconomic activities at the instance of theGovernment, it. would be dangerous to depart from the principle that such compensation should take the form of an adjustment of financial objectives andnot an Exchequer subvention. This principle should not, however, preclude thepossibility of exceptional treatment in appropriate cases.4. The nationalised Boards recognise the need for a clearer definition of their financial and economic obligations. Their concern is mainly with the way in whichthe new principles will in practice be applied in fixing the targets for each Board.The Boards of the nationalised fuel and power industries agree about the need for58697
a restatement of financial objectives, but they would prefer that it should not bepublished. In the view of the Nationalised Industries Committee, however, inwhich the Minister of Power concurs, even if it were possible to prevent the new proposals gradually becoming known, it would be undesirable to attempt to concealthem, since much of the value of the White Paper consists in bringing the financialand economic affairs of these Boards more into the open.n 5. The Committee on Nationalised Industries consider, indeed, that therewould be great advantage in proceeding with the publication of this White Paper.It deals with an aspect of economic affairs to which Parliamentary and public attention is being increasingly directed, and it is a matter of great economic importance to establish a sounder financial policy for the nationalised industries.The White Paper, while fully accepting the social obligations of the Boards, make sit plain that it is a matter of public concern that they should also carry out their financial and economic obligations. It should therefore help to bring about a more realistic attitude towards the nationalised industries.6. I ask my colleagues to agree to the publication of the proposed white paper. It would be best for it to appear at the same time as the other mainGovernment statements on the economic situation, and just in advance of the promised pre-Budget White Paper on borrowing by the nationalised industries inthe coming year. This would mean publication at the beginning of next month,when the Paper would be seen as a coherent part of the Government^ economic policies as a whole. As it is concerned with the financial obligations of the nationalised industries generally, I suggest that it would be appropriate for it to be presented to Parliament by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.R. A. B.Home Office, S.W.1,16th March, 1961.
The Financial and EconomicObligations of the nationalised IndustriesPresented to Parliament by the Chancellor of the exchequer by Command of Her majesty march 1961LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office net cmnd.

THE FINANCIAL AND ECONOMIC obligations of THE NATIONALISED INDUSTRIESMore than ten years have elapsed since the passing of the statutes whichbrought a number of industries into public ownership. During that period there has been much general discussion of the operation of these industries.There have been enquiries by the Herbert Committee into the electricity supply industry in England and Wales and by the Fleck Committee into the organi-sation of the National Coal Board. The Government and the British transport commission have received advice on the structure, finance and working of the organisations controlled by the Commission. The Select Committee on nationalised Industries has produced reports on four industries (the North ofScotland Hydro-Electric Board, the National Coal Board, the Air corporations and British Railways), which have done much to increase public knowledge.Until now there has, however, been no general review of the manner in whichthe general principles and, in particular, the economic and financial principles which were established in the nationalising statutes have been applied in practice.Much experience has been gained both by the Government and by the industries themselves during this period, in addition to the evidence provided by public discussion and by these special reports. In the light of this knowledge and experience the Government have considered how these principles might for thefuture most appropriately be applied to the existing nationalised bodies and tothe Post Office with its new status.*2. In the course of this review the Government have consulted the boatds of nationalised industries about the statutory obligations as they stand and theirapplicability for the future. The review has been conducted against the background of the Government^ general policy in relation to nationalised industries. The relevant aspects of this are as follows. First, the task ofgovernment is to ensure that the industries are organised and administeredefficiently and economically to carry out their responsibilities, and that theyare thus enabled to make the maximum contribution towards the economicwell-being of the community as a whole. Second, although the industries haveobligations of a national and non-commercial kind, they are not, and ought not, to be regarded as social services absolved from economic and commercialjustification.3. This review has not been undertaken in any spirit of criticism of the performance of nationalised industries whose role in meeting the needs of thecommunity for power, transport and communications is vital. The per-formance of the industries is affected by many matters which were dealt within the Nationalising Acts their organisation and structure, their relationswith the Government and Parliament, their relations with the workers and withconsumers, and their obligations to the community.   These are all of great* This paper accordingly discusses principles applicable to the National Coal Board, theElectricity Boards, the nationalised transport undertakings, the Gas Boards, the Air Cor-porations and the Post Office....331080 A 2
and continuing importance, but the Government believe that particular con-sideration should be given to the industries&apos; economic and financial basis:because, unless this is sound and practical, their performance and morale are bound to be impaired. The Government consider that the time has now cometo clarify the financial responsibilities of the nationalised industries in order toestablish a firmer foundation for their future operations.The Existing Framework4. The industries, which were subject to the nationalisation measures in theyears 1946 to 1950 had very different histories and differed considerably (as they still do) in their prospects. Their economic strength also differed and they hadto carry varying burdens of non-commercial, and generally unprofitable,obligations. Their economic and financial rights and obligations, as prescribed by the nationalising statutes, followed a fairly standard pattern. This was based on the view that they were neither straightforward commercial concernsnor social services, but a combination of both: and perhaps on the hope thatthe ability to borrow at Government rates would enable them to meet the limited financial obligations prescribed by statute and also to carry out their non-commercial obligations. For a variety of reasons (many of which havebeen outside the control of the undertakings themselves) their financial per-formance has generally fallen short of these hopes.&quot; Paying-their way &quot;5. The undertakings have, in common parlance, been expected to pay their way and most of the nationalising statutes contain a requirement to this effect.Their statutory obligations prescribe that their revenues should, on an averageof good and bad years (or some similar phrase) be not less than sufficient to meet all items properly chargeable to revenue, including depreciation and also theredemption of capital and the provision of reserves. Thus the Acts prescribea minimum performance and not a maximum. Moreover, this performanceis defined in terms of a surplus or deficit which differs from the ordinarydefinition of profit or loss inasmuch as provision is required to be made fromrevenue for all the items mentioned above before a surplus in the statutorysense arises. The undertakings were thus expected to make some profits in theordinary sense of that term in order to accumulate reserves from them.6. It was envisaged that in some years the nationalised undertakings mighthave a surplus and in other years a deficit. This provision was inevitable, forfluctuations in general business conditions were bound to affect their financial results, and there is no equity capital to act as a buffer. But if deficits are inevitable in some years surpluses must be accumulated in good years; and theperiod over which an average of surpluses and deficits is struck must not be unduly prolonged.7. The wording of the Acts implies that the industries should provide out ofrevenue not only for payment of interest on capital but also both for depreci-ation and the redemption of capital. If these requirements were stringentlyinterpreted they would impose upon the industries the responsibility not merely of providing from revenue for the maintenance of their capital assets buteventually of ridding themselves of capital liabilities. In practice, with theagreement of successive Governments, the industries, like their predecessors,have not been required (nor have they sought) to make provision on this scale.
8. Their practice has varied according to their economic strength, theirtraditions and the precise nature of their individual statutory obligations. Ingeneral they calculate the provision for depreciation in their accounts on the historic cost of their assets. Most of the Boards recognise in their reports that,following the practice generally adopted by industrial concerns, it would be prudent to make some additional provision out of revenue to meet the differencewhich emerges when prices rise, between depreciation at historic cost and atreplacement cost and as a reserve against obsolescence.9. The Acts also provide for the building up of general reserves and giveMinisters power to issue directions as to the amounts. Although some of the undertakings show general reserves in their balance sheets these are in somecases entirely obliterated by accumulated deficits on revenue account. Thetotal retained income of all these industries taken together (including supple-mentary depreciation provisions, capital redemption funds and reserves) hasnot been sufficient to provide for the replacement of assets used up in theproduction process, and this is also the case in most of the individual industries&apos;concerned.Financial Performance10. Tables I to III at the end of this paper summarise the financial results achieved in recent years. The balances on revenue account and reserves aregiven in Table I. The results are expressed as gross and net yields on average net assets in Tables II and III. The results vary markedly from industry to industry. This is to be expected. Some of the industries are expanding rapidlywhereas others are contracting: some are exposed to keen competition whereasothers have monopolistic elements in them: moreover the weight of non-commercial obligations varies from industry to industry. For all these reasonsthese financial results cannot by themselves be regarded as indicators of theefficiency of the individual industries. The fact remains, however, that mostof these nationalised undertakings have over the years earned, after depreciationat historic cost, considerably less than 5 per cent, per annum on capital em-ployed.11. Table IV shows the extent to which public corporations depend on the savings of others to finance their investment. In 1959 these corporationsinvested, in round figures,  800 millions, compared with about  480 millions in1954. In the same period their own savings went up only slightly from  190millions to  230 millions and their dependence on savings by the rest of thecommunity thus increased from  280 millions to  560 millions. The pictureis complicated by the special position of the British Transport Commission.But even leaving aside the Commission, the increase in the savings of the othercorporations from 1954 to 1959 ( 106 millions) was only about half the increasein their investment ( 214 millions).The return on public capital12. Comparisons are sometimes drawn between the return on capital in private enterprise and the return in public enterprises. It is suggested that overthe past five or six years the rate of return on capital in private enterprise wasaround 15 per cent.: and this view is supported by the series of figures quoted in Table III.13. The Government believe, however, that simple comparisons of this kind which tend to overlook or understress the differences between these nationalised
undertakings and private enterprise would be misleading. While it is legiti-mate to look for the same rate of return in a publicly owned enterprise which is fully commercial in its nature and is engaged in the same type of business as private enterprise, the main nationalised industries are not in this position.14. Many of the industries are, or are akin to, public utilities, where a lowerreturn on capital employed is traditional, partly because of the absence of riskin the business and partly because the earnings of such utilities are normallysubject to public regulation owing to the advantages of monopoly which theyare believed to enjoy. Although the area of nationalised industry in whichthese conditions exist is continuously shrinking as competition develops, thetradition of low yields and the restraints which go with it are still an important element in the situation. Moreover, the fact of nationalisation has tended to arouse public expectation that the products and services of these industries should be provided cheaply, and the Boards have been continuously subject to pressure from public opinion to keep their own prices down even when costs and prices elsewhere have been rising. In this way they have contributedsubstantially to efforts to stabilise prices and their own financial position, asreflected in the return on their capital, has suffered in consequence. The lower rate of financial return must also be attributed to the onerous national and non-commercial obligations which the Boards are expected to carry. the boards, moreover, are for a variety of reasons unable to adjust the expendituresof their industries as rapidly as other industries can when there is a change in economic conditions: and this is of special importance in relation to those industries which are contracting.15. These considerations readily account for the low return on the capital of the nationalised industries in relation to that on industrial and commercialcapital generally. It would, however, be unwise to ignore the risks of damage tothe nationalised industries themselves and to the economy generally that are inherent in the present situation. If the profitability of capital development is assessed on different (and easier) financial criteria from those adopted in industry generally,, there is a risk that too much of the nation&apos;s savings will be divertedinto the nationalised industries. Again, if the prices of the goods and services which the nationalised industries provide are uneconomically low, demand forthem (and for investment to produce more of them) may be artificially stimu-lated.16. Thus the operation of the nationalised industries with an unduly low rate of return on capital is sooner or later damaging to the economy as a whole.It must result either in higher taxation or in greater borrowing by the exchequer in order to provide for the replacement of their assets and for new development.The figures in Table IV show the scale on which these industries are drawing onthe rest of the economy. For the reasons already indicated, the nationalised industries generally have had to rely more heavily upon the Exchequer than ishealthy, either for themselves or for the economy as a whole. It is important,therefore, that a careful watch should be kept on the financial and other obli-gations of the Boards so as to ensure that a reasonable balance is maintained between them: such balance can readily be disturbed either by the growth ofnon-commercial activities or by a reduced capacity on the part of the industryto bear them.
A New Financial Framework17. In the Government^ view there would be no advantage in altering the basic financial and economic principles which the nationalised undertakings are by their statutes required to observe. If, however, these principles are toprovide a satisfactory basis for their operation in the public interest they need to be interpreted more precisely in the form of financial objectives for the nationalised undertakings generally.18. The main heads under which clarification or re-statement of the obli-gations and relationships envisaged in the nationalising Acts is needed are asfollows:Revenue Account.Capital Account.Prices and Costs.Revenue Account19. The Government consider that the financial objectives of the nationalised undertakings under their Statutes should now in general be interpreted on thefollowing lines: (a) Surpluses on Revenue Account should be at least sufficient to coverdeficits on Revenue Account over a 5-year period: in arriving at thesurpluses and deficits for each year there should be charged againstrevenue the items normally so chargeable (including interest, and depreciation on the historic cost basis.(b) Provision should also be made from revenue for: (i) such an amount as may be necessary to cover the excess of depreciation calculated on replacement cost basis over de-preciation calculated on historic cost as in (a) above.f(ii) adequate allocations to general reserves which will be availableinter alia as a contribution towards their capital development and as a safeguard against premature obsolescence and similarcontingencies.20. It is the Government^ view that in general anything more than a five-year period as the balancing period for the formula in paragraph 19 would be too longfor effectiveness. They propose, inconsultation with each board which hasfinancial autonomy under the Acts, to agree a framework on the above linesfor the next five years as an experimental period, but the operation will be sub-ject to review each year in the light of events inside and outside the industry.This procedure will be applied in all the major nationalised industries,* in-cluding the Post Office.21. The wide differences in the economic conditions of the various national-ised undertakings have been emphasised earlier in this paper. Their earningpower, depreciation provision, and reserve requirements will vary accordingto their prospective commercial, technological and financial development.t The undertakings would not be required specifically to make good now any under-provision (i.e. on account of the difference between the historic cost basis and the replacement cost basis), which has already occurred in years prior to the operation of these new arrange-ments.* It cannot be applied at present to certain parts of the nationalised transport undertaking,e.g. the railways, for which financial proposals have been outlined in Cmnd. 1248 of December,1960.
The criteria in paragraph 19 would be consistent with the general run of theexisting statutory obligations, but they cannot be expressed as one standardformula to be applied to all nationalised undertakings alike.22. Experience has shown, however, a general need for nationalised industries even those which were at one time reckoned to be relatively free from commercial risk to build up adequate reserves to deal with contingencieswhich may affect their capital as well as their revenue accounts. Moreover,there are powerful grounds in the national interest for requiring these under-takings to make a substantial contribution towards the cost of their capital development out of their own earnings, and so reduce their claims upon thenation&apos;s savings and the burden on the Exchequer: this is particularly so for those undertakings which are expanding fast and which have relatively large capital needs. In normal circumstances, the desirable level of reserves shouldbe related to the amount of capital employed in the business.23. It follows from all these considerations that the State, as owner orguarantor of the capital of the nationalised industries (which are investing over 800 millions a year more than half of which comes from the Exchequer),would expect capital employed in this kind of business to earn a higher rate of return than the cost of the money to the Exchequer. In view of the commercialrisks, which experience has shown to be considerable, and thegeneral conditions to be expected during the next few years, this return might be put somewherearound 8 per cent, net after depreciation at historic cost. Some of the undertakings are earning at this rate now, but most of them are significantlybelow.24. The objective for each undertaking will be determined in the light of itsown circumstances, needs and capabilities in relation to the criteria in paragraph19. For some, the objectives may be expressed in terms of progress towards an appropriate level of self-financing of their capital expenditure, concurrently with the provision of suitable contributions to reserve. For others, the objectivemay be in terms of a specified rate of return on capital employed greater,equal to, or less than the 8 per cent, indicated above in accordance with theparticular circumstances.Capital Account25. The existing procedures for discussion and authorisation of matters concerning investment and borrowing will be continued and can be codifiedas follows: * (i) The Government will discuss with the undertaking and approve thegeneral lines of its plans for development and capital expenditure for five years ahead and be ready to agree to long-term commitments as appropriate.(ii) In the light of (i) the Government will each year fix an upper limit on the amounts to be spent on investment by the undertaking duringthe two years ahead.(iii) The Government will approve proposed borrowings on the basis ofan annual reasoned estimate submitted by the undertaking.(iv) The Government will require to be kept informed of the extent towhich the undertaking was proposing to invest new capital in projects which are from the outset expected to yield a relatively low return.26. These requirements flow from the Government^ responsibility to keeppublic sector investment generally within the nation&apos;s resources, as well as from
the Governments role as provider of public capital It would be the Govern-mentS task to satisfy themselves that the procedure within each organisation for scrutinising and approving capital expenditure was effective.27. The existing arrangements under which capital expenditure in excess of the approved ceiling, or borrowing in excess of the estimates, are subject to investigation and discussion between the undertakings and the departments would continue. These procedures fit in with the recent arrangements underwhich Parliament has been given more detailed information about the estimates of investment and Exchequer borrowing and the Governments undertaking to inform Parliament of the reasons for any marked variation between theestimate and the out-turn.28. While the proposed arrangements are adapted to the present system,under which the industries resort to the Exchequer for their long-term capital requirements, the proposed clarification of financial obligations and theimprovement in financial performance would be necessary and desirable in any event. The reasons which caused the Government to discontinue in 1956 theprocedure of borrowing from the market, with the support of a government guarantee, and to withdraw the financing of the transport, gas and electricity industries from the market into thf Exchequer are still valid. While theGovernment recognise the force of the arguments in favour of requiring national-ised bodies to raise money from the market on their own credit, they see nopossibilities of an early move in this direction. They accept the view of theCommittee under the chairmanship of Lord Radcliffe on the Working of the monetary System (Cmnd. 827, paragraph 595) that such unguaranteed borrow-ing is not a realistic alternative, at least for the present. The amounts of moneyneeded are much too large to be raised in the open market without government support and the industries are, of necessity, closely associated in the public mind with the Government, so that it would be difficult for the market to regard them as independent financial concerns. Whatever may be the possibilities forthe future, an improvement in the financial record as contemplated under thepresent proposals would be a prerequisite.29. The procedures in paragraphs 20 to 27 would be applicable as long as thefinancial performance and prospects of the undertaking were satisfactory interms of the new financial framework. In other cases the Government would be bound to take a closer interest. Thus inability or prospective inability tomeet the requirements in paragraph 19 (a) would be regarded as falling so far short of the objectives that the undertaking would be required to proposespecific measures for righting the situation: it would naturally consult theMinister about these and the Minister would expect to be satisfied on various issues, including the financial justification for major investment proposals.Even if the undertaking were fulfilling the requirement in paragraph 19 (a),inability to achieve the objective set for it under paragraph 24, would beregarded as inadequate performance. In this case, the undertaking would be under an obligation to inform the Minister of the general plans for preventing the situation from deteriorating further and for making up the leeway.Prices and Costs30. A clear definition of each BoardS financial obligations inevitably raisesthe question of the extent to which the Boards should have freedom in theirpricing policies. Although the Government have possessed no formal powerto fix prices in the nationalised industries, nationalised undertakings have,.in
fixing their prices, given great weight to considerations of the national interestbrought to their attention.31. Increased prices would not be the only way in which nationalised under-takings could carry out the prescribed financial obligations. For a variety of reasons, such as fructification of investment and reduction of unprofitableactivities, combined with continuing improvements in commercial efficiency,some of the industries will be capable of increased productivity, part of whichshould be available to improve their financial results. The aim of the industriesgenerally will naturally be to secure the necessary additions to their net revenueas far as possible by reductions in costs. The Government recognise, however,that the industries must have freedom to make upward price adjustmentsespecially where their prices are artificially low.32. While recognising the case for greater freedom and flexibility in thepricing policies of nationalised industries the Government must interest them-selves in the prices of these goods and services which are basic to the life of thecommunity and some of which contain a monopolistic element. In additionto the formal arrangements for the representation of consumers&apos; views throughConsultative Councils in the various industries, the existing informal arrange-ments are that the Chairmen of the Boards ascertain in advance the views of theappropriate Ministers when they prepare to make substantial changes in thelevel of their prices. In the Government^ view these arrangements shouldcontinue. If a Board decided to modify their own proposals by reason of views expressed by the Minister it would be open to them to require a written statement of those views, which could be published if the Board so desired,and to propose an appropriate adjustment of their financial objectives where,in their opinion, this modification would significantly impair their ability tomeet them.33. The financial performance of the undertakings is affected not only by thelevel of prices but also by the level of costs. The level of costs may in time be significantly affected by the amount of commercially unprofitable activities which the undertakings are expected to carry on. The scale of these activitieswould be taken into account in fixing the financial standard for each under-taking: if significant additional obligations and acdvities of this kind were subsequently imposed, the Board would once again be entitled to ask for an adjustment of its financial objectives. Apart from this the Board would, unlessits financial performance had fallen short of the accepted standard, have full responsibility for its costs and would have to reckon whether any increases inthese could be reconciled with its other responsibilities and obligations, includingits financial obligations.Conclusion34. The nationalised industries are from their size and nature bound to play a major role in the economic life of the country. They cannot, however, beregarded only as very large commercial concerns which may be judged mainly on their commercial results: all have, although in varying degrees, widerobligations than commercial concerns in the private sector. The object ofthese proposals is to find for each industry or Board a reasonable balance between these two concepts. The Government believe that the closer definitionnow proposed for the financial and economic obligations of the industries should help improve their performance and morale. It should also reduce theoccasion and need for outside intervention in the affairs of the industries and enable them to make the maximum contribution towards their own development and the well-being of the community as a whole. .
Table IBalances on Revenue Account and General Reserves			Yearly results			  million		Unallocated Reserves and Revenue Balances Carried forward at the end of 1959		1953	1954	1955	1956	1957	1958	1959	  million	As a percentage of capital employed at the end of 1959Coal   ..................	0-5	- 3-5	-19-6	12-8	- 5-3	- 3-5	-24-0	- 52	 Gas *............     ...     ...	1-5	1-9	0-8	3-8	2-8	- 1-5	- 2-4	25-5	4-4Electricity (England and Wales)    ...... Electricity (South of Scotland)     ......	j- 13-2	18-8 1	12-2 0-6	11-7 1-2	16-1 0-5	27-3 0-27	26-7 0-1	127-2 2-6	6-5 1-9Electricity (North of Scotland)     ......	001	0-3	- 0-8	- 0-2	-	- 0-1	- 0-03	-  0-8	-British Transport Commission     ......	4-2	-11-9	-30-6	-54-4	-63-5	-89-0	-73-8	-350-6	-British European Airways.........	- 0-8	106	0-61	006	108	0-23	1-7	2-28	4-british Overseas Airways Corporation	- 106	- 0-03	0-85	0-59	- 319	-11-36	- 0-29	- 13-25	-General Post Office............	Up to 1955-56 the Exchequer received any surplus			- 3-1	-t- 2-6	-f 8-7	+20-9	27-2	3-1GOor
Table ITGross income (before depreciation) as a proportion of net assets (after depreciation)Per cent.	1954	1955	1956		1957		1958		1959Manufacturing and distribution ...	20-8	20-9	20	0	19	3	18	3	190Iron and Steel (55 companies)   ...	19-2	22-9	20	6	20	3	17	9	17-national Coal Board     ......	10-3	7-7	14	1	10	9	9	8	8-3Gas Council and Boards......	8-2	8-4	8	7	8	8	7	8	7-8Electricity (B.E.A., C.E.A., E.C.,	1        f	9-9	9	3	9	6	10	6	10-and Boards)     .........	r10-71								South of Scotland Electricity Board	i    I	100	11	4	10	1	9	2	9-north of Scotland Hydro-Electric									and Board)      .........	4-9	3-4	4	8	4	9	5	1	5-british Transport Commission ...	5-1	4-1	2	7	2	4	1	0	2-british European Airways	16-8	17-5	14	7	17	4	13	3	16-7British Overseas Airways Cor-									poration............	12-1	13-2	11	9	6	7	6	4	12-general Post Office       ......	10-8	100	11	6	12	2	12	6	13-2Table IIINet income (after depreciation) as a proportion of net assets (after depreciation)Per cent.	1954	1955	1956	1957	1958	1959Manufacturing and distribution ...	17-5	17-4	16-3	15-5	14-3	14-9Iron and Steel (55 companies)   ...	15-3	190	16-8	16-4	141	13-3 national Coal Board     ......	3-1	0-4	6-8	3-6	2-8	1-6Gas Council and Boards......	3-9	4-0	4-4	4-5	3-4	3-3Electricity (B.E.A., C.E.A., E.C.,	1     r	5-1	4-7	50	5-7	5-and Boards)     .........	r 5&apos;61					South of Scotland Electricity Board	J    I	4-6	5-7	4-4	4-2	4-north of Scotland Hydro-Electric						Board    ............	3-3	1-8	3-2	3-3	3-5	3-9British Transport Commission  ...	2-8	1-9	0-2	-0-6	-2-1	-1-british European Airways	9-3	7-0	4-1	7-8	4-7	8-british Overseas  Airways Cor-						poration............	3-8	4-2	3-4	-0-2	-0-7	3-general Post Office       ......	5-1	4-4	6-9	7-5	80	8-6
Table IVSaving and Investment  million	1954	1955	1956	1957	1958	1959Saving (1)						Persons............	574	852	1,188	1,205 &apos;	1,130	1,254Companies      .........	1,617	1,677	1,822	1,908	1,803	2,060Central Government (2)	167	412	324	472	517	402Local Authorities       ......	117	109	130	161	160	177British Transport Commission...	31	14	-8	-18	-47	-35Coal, Gas and Electricity in-						dustries        .........	128	117	187	165	183	190Air Corporations       ......	6	6	8	7	5	13G.P.O.............	29	32	41	50	59	70Other Public Corporations	39	26	18	14	18	15Total      .........	2,708	3,245	3,710	3,964	3,828	4,146Capital formation						Persons............	546	639	665	662	718	840Companies      .........	1,054	1,456	1,543	1,621	1,397	1,480Central Government   ......	-13	3	96	109	148	157Local Authorities       ......	577	543	574	577	541	569British Transport Commission...	52	66	114	153	157	164Coal, Gas and Electricity in-						dustries        .........	340	414	395	463	479	524Air Corporations       ......	10	19	25	42	39	27G.P.O.............	73	88	101	103	90	86Other Public Corporations	74	111	84	69	53	56Total      .........	2,713	3,339	3,597	3,799	3,622	3,903Excess of saving over capital for-						mation						Persons ...      ...      ...      ^.	28	213	523	543	412	414Companies      .........	563	221	279	287	406	580Central Government   ......	180	409	228	363	369	245Local Authorities       ......	-460	-434	-444	-416	-381	--392British Transport Commission...	- 21	- 52	-122	-171	-204	-199Coal, Gas and Electricity in-						dustries..........	-212	^297	-208	-298	-296	-334Air Corporations       ......	-   4	- 13	- 17	- 35	- 34	- 14G.P.O.............	- 44	- 56	- 60	- 53	- 31	- 16Other Public Corporations	- 35	- 85	- 66	- 55	- 35	- 41Total (3).........	-   5	- 94	113	165	206	243Notes: (1) Gross saving before providing for depreciation and for tax, dividend and interestreserves.(2) This is equal to the surplus on revenue account less taxes on capital plus transfers to capital account.(3) This is equal to net investment abroad less capital transfers from abroad, stock appreci-ation and the residual error.
Notes on Tables I to EETable IThe figures of accumulations at the beginning and end of the period 1953 to1959 include both balances, whether surplus or deficit, on revenue account atthe appropriate date and such of the reserves of the body concerned as werenot allocated to specific contingencies such as liabilities for future taxation orinsurance.       ,Tables II and IIIDefinitionsGross income covers trading profits or trading surplus and other incomebefore deduction of depreciation, provisions for capital redemption, tax,interest and dividends.Net income is equal to gross income minus depreciation. A minus figureindicates a net loss before taking into account interest payable.Net assets cover total assets (excluding discounts on stock issues and, inthe case of the British Transport Commission, the Special Account for revenue deficits) less liabilities of a current nature. The figure used isthe average for the beginning and end of the year.Depreciation covers depreciation as charged in the accounts but excludessupplementary provision. In the case of the British Transport Com-mission, however, it includes an additional amount based on capitalexpenditure charged to revenue. Depreciation is charged at historiccost except in the case of a few companies in the private sector whichcharge it at replacement cost. For the North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board depreciation is reckoned as equivalent to the instalmentspaid to local authorities plus contributions to the redemption fund.   -SourcesManufacturing and distribution: data for the 3,000 companies quoted onthe United Kingdom Stock Exchange have been published by theNational Institute of Economic and Social Research for 1953 and, onthe same basis, by the Board of Trade for the years 1954 to 1957. Thefigures for 1958 and 1959 have been estimated by the Central StatisticalOffice on the basis of material appearing in the &quot; Economist &quot;.Iron and steel: data assembled for 55 companies in this industry by theIron and Steel Holding and Realisation Agency. As a result ofdenationalisation the number of these companies in the private sectorincreases each year while the number remaining in the public sectordiminishes.All other authorities: the annual accounts of the relevant authority.periods for manufacturing and distribution and for iron and steel, 1954 coversaccounts in respect of accounting years ending within the fiscal year1953-54 and similarly for later years. For the Gas Council and Boards,Electricity (B.E.A./C.E.A./E.C.) and Boards and the two airways corporations the figures for 1954 relate to fiscal year ending March, 1955.For the remainder, accounts relate to calendar years. In the case of theSouth of Scotland Electricity Board which came into being on 1st April,1955, the figures for 1955 are shown on an annual basis.
InterpretationParagraphs 13 and 14 of the text indicate some of the qualificationsapplicable to Tables II, III and IV. In addition, in comparing thefigures for the various undertakings inside the nationalised sector andwith industries in the private sector, there are a number of factors to betaken into account including the following: (1) valuation of assets cannot be obtained on a uniform basis. the valuation of fixed assets, investments and stocks, etc., oftendepends on the date (and the price level) at which they werebought and also on subjective factors such as depreciation andrevaluation policies, writing down investments and writing off baddebts according to the attitude to and interpretation of theprinciples of conservative finance by individual managements;(2) there is a wide divergence in the nature of the undertakings, in thenature of their assets, including the length of the fructificationperiod for investment, and in the conditions under which theyoperate; for example most factories benefit from the derating actswhile electricity power stations and gas works do not;(3) accounting practices vary but the consequences of this have so faras possible been eliminated; the adjustments made have not beenfound to affect the results significantly.(31080)  Wt.      -       80 book  3/61   D.L.
Printed and published by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery OfficeTo be purchased from york House, Kingsway, London w.c.2423 Oxford Street, London w.l13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2109 St. Mary Street, Cardiff39 King Street, Manchester 250 Fairfax Street, Bristol 1. Edmund Street, Birmingham &apos;80 Chichester Street, Belfast or through any bookseller printed in England


</content>
</cab>
