<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/104/0 images: 255-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
189THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSOUTH AFRICA-CONSEQUENCES  OF  WITHDRAWAL  FROM  THECOMMONWEALTHMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations we shall clearly now have to negotiate with the South African Governmentacross the board to preserve bilateral interests. Dr. Verwoerd for his part hasalready expressed a desire to maintain good relations and to co-operate with us as in the past.2. Officials have completed a detailed study of the effects on British interestsof South Africa&apos;s withdrawal from the Commonwealth and on varying ways inwhich we might treat her as a foreign country. I hope shortly to circulate a fullermemorandum on this.3. Meanwhile it is clear that the range of interests on both sides is so widethat it would be impossible for us to arrive at a permanent settlement with the UnionGovernment before the Republic is declared and South Africa formally ceases tobe a Commonwealth member on 31st May. Our negotiations will have to cover,among other matters, such major questions as citizenship, preferences, defence andthe future of the High Commission Territories.4. Whatever settlement we reach and whatever the treatment we then decide to afford South Africa, further legislation will certainly be required. This in turnwill need careful preparation.5. Meanwhile in order to hold the position and to allay doubts andspeculation, not least as regards citizenship, I recommend that we should introduce,with a view to its enactment prior to 31st May, a short standstill Bill. I annex adraft. The purpose of this Bill would be to preserve the existing position for aperiod of say 10 months from 31st May. During that time, which would give uselbow room for negotiation, South Africa would continue to be treated under united Kingdom law as though she were still a Commonwealth country. I thinkthat this would be perfectly acceptable to our Commonwealth partners. It iscertainly the most practical way of ensuring that we arrive at a full and sensiblebilateral understanding with South Africa.Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1961C. (61) 3917 th March, 1961Copy No. 32CABINETD. S.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W.1,17 th March, 1961.58703
CONFIDENTIALp    2 Republic of South Africa^ (Consequential Provision)DRAFTOF ABILLTOMake temporary provision as to the operation of the  a.d. 1961law upon the Union of South Africa becorriing are public outside the Commonwealth.WHEREAS, on the thirty-first day of May, nineteenhundred and sixty-one, the Union of South Africa willbecome a Republic under the name of the Republic ofSouth Africa, and cease to be a member of the Commonwealth:Be it therefore enacted by the Queen&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled,and by the authority of the same, as follows: 1-(1) During the period beginning with the thirty-first day Operation ofof May, nineteen hundred and sixty-one, and ending with the existing lawthirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and sixty-two, any to existing law which operates as law of, or of any part of, the ou no.&quot;United Kingdom shall, unless provision to the contrary is madeby an authority having power to alter that law, have the sameoperation in relation to the Republic of South Africa, and to persons and things in any way belonging thereto or connected therewith, as it would have had in relation to the Union of SouthAfrica and persons and things belonging thereto and connected therewith if the Union had not become a Republic and had continued to be a member of the Commonwealth.(2) In this section &quot; existing law &quot; means any Act of parliament or other enactment or instrument whatsoever, and any rule oflaw, which is in force on the said thirty-first day of May, or,having been passed or made before that date, comes into forceafter that date.76-3
2 Republic of South Africa 9 r L!z 2(Consequential Provision)(3) Subsection (1) of this section shall apply in relation to any existing law which operates as law of, or of any part of, SouthernRhodesia or any colony, protectorate or United Kingdom trust territory as it applies in relation to existing law which operatesas law of the United Kingdom, and references in this subsection 1to a colony, a protectorate and a United Kingdom trust territory *shall be construed as if they were references contained in theBritish Nationality Act, 1948:Provided that the said subsection (1) (a) shall not apply in relation to any law passed by thenFederal Legislature of Rhodesia and Nyasaland;(b) shall apply in relation to other law of, or of any part of,Southern Rhodesia so far only as concerns law whichcan be amended neither by a law passed by the Legisla-ture thereof, nor by a law passed by the said Federal 1:Legislature; and(c) shall apply in relation to other law of, or of any part of,Northern Rhodesia or Nyasaland so far only as concernslaw which cannot be amended by a law passed by thesaid Federal Legislature. 2Short title. 2. This Act may be cited as the Republic of South Africa(Consequential Provision) Act, 1961.Republic of South Africa(Consequential Provision)DRAFTOF ABILLTo make temporary provision as to theoperation of the law upon the Union ofSouth Africa becoming a Republic out-side the Commonwealth.LIV-C (3)nth March, 1961


</content>
</cab>
