<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/20/8 images: 128-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted! for the War Cabinet.   November 1941.SECRET.Copy No.W.M. (41)115th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 115 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,S.W.1, on Monday, November 17, 1941, at 5-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Simon, LordChancellor (Items 4-6).The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne.Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secre-tary of State for the Colonies.Captain The Right Hon. H. D.Margesson, M.P., Secretary of Statefor War (Items 2-6).The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somer-vell, M.P., Attorney-General (items and 6).       .The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma (items-4).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[23162-2]
WAR CABINET 115 (41).Contents.minute no.Subject.Page.1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....      ........      ....    157Air Operations.Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations:Libya.Casualties and damage.4      India.............................      .....    158Proposed release of Satyagrahi detenus.5      Regulation 18b................      ............ 160The Duke of Bedford.6      The Press       ............................ 1617      Turkey............      .................... 161Supply of munitions, &amp;c.U.S.S.R.2 Foreign Affairs3      Air Raids157158
(previous reference:W.M. (41) 111thConclusions,Minute 2.)Air Operations.naval operations.shipping losses.MilitaryOperations.Libya.U.S.S.R.Enemy-4k destroyed.1 probable.3 damaged.Our Own 7 fighters.8 bombers.5 Coastal Command aircraft.Overseas Theatre -Enemy^-8 destroyed.1 probable.11 damaged.Our Own-20 destroyed 1 -6 damaged \ ln the air-The weather during the last few days had been unfavourablefor operations. Two good attacks against submarines had beencarried out.Information was given about the loss of the Ark Royal. OneU-boat had been sunk in the Mediterranean and thirty-fourprisoners had been taken off her.During the previous six days 21,000 tons of shipping had beenreported sunk.  This figure included two belated reports.An Italian Mobile Corps had been moved to the area south of tobruk, presumably in support of the two German armoured divisions in the frontier area.On the Murmansk front the Germans appeared to have with-drawn to a winter line; the Russian forces had followed up and.maintained contact. Leningrad was almost, but not quite, cut off.There was little to report on the Kalinin, Central and UkraineSectors. Winter had arrived abnormally early on the CentralSector and in the Crimea. On the Central Sector there were indications that the Germans, having failed to make progress north-wards from Tula, were now starting fresh operations eastwardsfrom the area Tula-Orel.Stubborn Russian resistance and heavy snow falls had prevented the Germans from making any material progress in their attck on Sevastopol. In the eastern Crimea the Germans had entered Kerch.  .The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Foreign Affairs.       2.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs gave thefollowing information:-Persia.-There had been some delay in shipments of wheat to Persia.The War Cabinet were informed that the Lord presidents committee were considering whether any change in organisa-tion was necessary to harmonise the shipping requirements ofthe Import Executive and of the Allied Supplies Executive,and that a report would be made to the War Cabinet.[23162-2] b 2alriirM,llt8,,y h T* CtWi0f 8*&amp; Save the Allowing information in operations.      amPllfication of Cabinet War Room Records Nos 801-806 :-Summary of aircraft losses since the 11th November :-Home Theatre -
Jibuti. The Vichy Governor of Jibuti had made overturesto us. Our policy was to maintain our blockade for a further period of, say, ten days before entering into negotiations. Ifthe Vichy Governor in the meantime threatened to blow up therailway, he should be warned that, in that event, we shouldcontinue the blockade indefinitely.Italy. G.H.Q., Middle East, had reported that they hadproof that Dumini, the assassin of Matteotti, who had been captured by His Majesty&apos;s Forces at Derna, had been shot inApril last while attempting to attack his guards and escape.There was a proposal that Dumini &apos;s death should be announced, on the grounds that this would result in the releasein the United States of papers said to contain proof ofMussoliiii&apos;s complicity in the assassination of Matteotti.In discussion, it was pointed out that to publish the state-ment now, seeing that Dumini was said to have been shot aslong ago as April, might expose us to damaging attacks. Thewhole story required to be carefully sifted before publicationwas agreed to.The Foreign Secretary was invited to telegraph instruc-tions in this sense to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Cairo.Air Raids.Casualties and damage.(previous reference erence:W.M. (41) 108thConclusions,Minute 3.)India.ProposedRelease ofSatyagrahiDetenus.(previous reference:WM. (41) 112thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Minister of Home Security reported a raid on DormanLong and Co.&apos;s Iron Works at Redcar on the 15th November, inwhich nine people had been killed, seventeen seriously wounded and thirty-two slightly wounded.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.4.   The War Cabinet had before them (a) A Memorandum containing telegrams on this matter(W.P. (41) 271).(b) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India(W.P. (41) 273).The Secretary of State for India said that there were two points at issue.On the question of release, there was a good deal to be said fora &apos;&apos; contemptuous &apos;&apos; act of clemency. He had always contemplatedaction on these lines in due course, but had been a little surprisedthat it was proposed to take action in this sense at the present time.After an explanation of the views expressed in the exchange of telegrams before the War Cabinet, the Secretary of State said that,on balance, he favoured release at the present time, on the lines setout in the final telegram from the Government of India, dated the14th November.The other issue involved (which he regarded as the moreimportant) was that the Governor-General&apos;s Council, which had recently been enlarged with a view to strengthening the war effort,had been doing good work. Both the new and the old Indianmembers of the Council and the British members (with somereluctance in some cases) now concurred in the recommendationssubmitted in regard to release. It would be difficult at any time tooverrule the unanimous view of the Council. To do so at the presenttime would be much harder.. The Secretary of State read to the War Cabinet a personal telegram from the Viceroy, expressing the view that, if the WarCabinet was to reject the proposal submitted to them, it would be extremely difficult/if not impossible, to keep the Council together.
The Lord Chancellor said that, on merits, he saw little or no advantage to be gained by the proposal to release the detenus. the justification must, he thought, rest on the fact that it would be unfortunate to have to overrule a decision of the enlarged Viceroy&apos;council on the first occasion when they submitted an importantproposal.Discussion then turned on the Constitutional aspect of thecourse proposed.The Lord President of the Council said that he had been greatly surprised to learn that the Viceroy&apos;s Council, and not theViceroy, were dealing with this matter. Under the Government ofIndia Act, responsibility for law and order and for internal securitybelonged exclusively to the Provinces. The only qualifying pro-vision was that the Governor-General, in the exercise of his special responsibility for the prevention of any grave menace to the peace or tranquillity of India or any part thereof,, could give directions to a Provincial Governor. It would, however, be wholly wrong forthe Viceroy&apos;s Council to interfere with the responsibilities of theProvinces in this matter.It was true that Section 126 (a) had enlarged the powers of theViceroy&apos;s Council in relation to the prosecution of the war. these powers, however, had been conferred on the Council in order thatthey might stimulate the Provinces to further action in connectionwith the war effort. It was surely wrong to use these special powersto interfere with the responsibilities of the Provinces in regard to law and order. To do so might, he thought, have disastrous consequences.The Prime Minister drew attention to the telegrams from the governors of the United Provinces and of Madras, printed in w.P. (41) 271. Great importance must be attached to their views,seeing that the majority of the detenus were in these Provinces.The Prime Minister thought that the proposal before the WarCabinet had its origin in the desire of the Indian members, who had joined the Governor-General&apos;s Executive Council when it had beenexpanded, to show that they exercised some influence over thedecisions of the Government of India. The telegrams before theWar Cabinet showed clearly that some of those who now concurred in the course proposed had been over-persuaded.Attention was drawn, in particular, to the views expressed bythe Governor of the United Provinces in his telegram of the14th November (No. (14) in W.P. (41) 271).Attention was also drawn to the terms of the draft public announcement proposed by the Governor-General set out in para-graph 7 of the Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.The view expressed was that it would be wrong that the Govern-ment of India should make a public announcement containing advice to Provincial Governments as to the course which they should pursuein a matter of law and order. While it was open to the Viceroy togive directions to Provincial Governors on such matters, such directions should be strictly confidential.Summing up the discussion, the Prime Minister said that- thematters at issue were of considerable importance, and he thoughtthat the War Cabinet would be ill-advised to reach a conclusion that night, before the essential points brought out in discussion had been communicated to the Viceroy. This would mean that the spokesmanfor the Government of India would be unable to announce thedecision when Joshi&apos;s motion was debated in the Assembly on thefollowing day. This might cause some Parliamentary inconvenience.But this was not a factor of sufficient importance to warrant a hastydecision on these matters. Delay would also have the advantage of enabling the matter to be further considered at a Meeting of theWar Cabinet attended by the Lord Privy Seal,
Pandit Nehru.^Some discussion followed about the case of Pandit Nehru.General agreement was: expressed with the proposal made by theSecretary of State that the sentences of 16 months&apos; imprisonment on three several counts should be made concurrent and not consecutive.This was not a matter on which an immediate announcement shouldbe made.The Secretary of State for India expressed anxiety as to theeffect on the expanded Governor-General&apos;s Council of the delayproposed in reaching a decision.The War Cabinet agreed as follows r- :(1) The Secretary of State for India was authorised to tele-graph at once, to the Governor-General, informing him that the War Cabinet, while giving sympathetic con-sideration to the Governor-General&apos;s proposals, were unable to reach a decision on the matter in time for anannouncement to be made on the following day. they hoped, however, that it would be possible for anannouncement to be made in the near future. In themeantime, it would be necessary for the government spokesman to play for time in the Assembly on the18th November.(2) The Secretary of State for India, the Lord Privy Seal, theLord President of the Council and the Lord Chancellorwere invited to prepare a carefully-reasoned telegram tothe Governor-General, setting out the points raised in discussion, and, in particular, the Constitutional issuesin regard to the responsibilities of the Provinces for lawand order.Regulation 18 b.The Duke ofBedford.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 110thConclusions,Minute 5.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary (W.P. (41) 267) on the question whether DetentionOrders should be made under Regulation 18b against certain persons carrying on prejudicial propaganda.The Home Secretary said that the question arose out of certainexpressions of opinion by the Duke of Bedford both in privateletters to individuals and in a news-sheet. The Home Secretaryread extracts from some of these leaflets and letters, and said thathe had reached the conclusion that the course pursued amounted toacts prejudicial to the public safety and the defence of the Realm.It would be seen, however, that the Attorney-General expressedsome doubts as to the validity of Detention Orders made under regulation 18b against persons carrying on prejudicial propaganda.The Attorney-General gave his reasons for this opinion (seeAppendix to W.P. (41) 267), and added that he would be willing, toexamine any further material the Home Secretary might furnish.The Prime Minister said that it was necessary in war time to detain certain individuals in safe custody. The case before the WarCabinet was important from the point of view of ensuring thatthere was no ground for suspicion that persons of wealth orposition were more favourably treated in this matter than other people. The conditions of such detention should, however, be mitigated as much as possible, and those detained should be internedrather than imprisoned.The Lord Chancellor saidthat Lord Ponsonby had put down a motion in the House of Lords relating to the Duke of, Bedford. the duke&apos;s activities were thus bound: toxeeehreipublicity.
The Press. 6.   The War Cabinet had before them (1) a Joint Memorandum(Previous by the Foreign Secretary, the Home Secretary and the Minister ofReference: Information (W.P. (41)269) relating to the publication of articlesW.M. (41) lioth in the Press likely to prejudice the relations of His Majesty&apos;conclusions, Government with foreign Powers; and (2) a Memorandum by the minute 3.)       Home Secretary (W.P. (41) 268) on the question of further powersto deal with such articles as that which had appeared in the SundayPictorial on the 26th October, 1941.The War Cabinet-Took note of these Memoranda and agreed that it was unnecessary to take any action in regard to this matter atthe present time.Turkey. 7.   The War Cabinet took note of the decisions reached at a supply ofStaff Conference held on the 12th November.  The Conference hadMunitions, &amp;c.had before it a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign(Previous Affairs (W.P. (41) 265), and had reached the following conclu-Reference: Sions : -W.M. (41) 98th (a) That general approval should be given to the proposalsConclusions, contained in the Memorandum by the Secretary of StateMJnute 6.) for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (41) 265).(6) That the giving of equipment and supplies to Turkey shouldbe governed by the principles proposed in paragraph 9(i) and (ii) of the Memorandum, i.e.: (i) It should be laid down as our definite policy ofassistance to Turkey that, rather than providingspecialised equipment to Turkish formations, weshould provide the necessary formations ourselves,though some trickle of such weapons should con-tinue in order to satisfy Turkish military pride.This principle should be clearly put to the Turks.In order to gild the pill, however (ii) The Turkish General Staff should be informed thata special effort will be made to supply a minimumprogramme of Turkish requirements for infantryequipment, engineering stores and mechanical transport by a given date, of which the Turksshould be informed.   The Allied Supply Execu-tive should be instructed to give effect to this offer,(c) That the financial arrangements for covering Turkishrequisitions in the United States of America should besettled by inter-departmental discussion.Great George Street, SJV.1,November-17, 1941.The War Cabinet (1) Took note that the Attorney-General would examine anyfurther material the Home Secretary could furnish tohim in this case in order to consider (a) Whether a charge, which would have a good prospectof being sustained in a Court of Law, could be framed under Regulation 18b.(b) Whether the case could be dealt with under Regu-lation 2c.(2) Recorded the view that it was undesirable to frame any newRegulation to deal with persons carrying on prejudicialpropaganda.(3) Took note that the Home Secretary would submit a paper in a week&apos;s time about the conditions under which persons were detained under Regulation 18b.




</content>
</cab>
