<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/6/13 images: 150-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mAt the meeting of the War Cabinet held on April 23, it wasagreed that as an interim measure the Press and the B.B.C should not publish news of shipping losses by enemy action for the next three days,and it was left to the Admiralty to bring before the War Cabinet thequestion of withholding from publication in future items of news (such asparticulars of sinkings of ships by enemy action) which might be of value to the enemy.At present news of shipping losses by enemy action is released for publication immediately, except when there is some special reason forwithholding publication.     In addition, the Admiralty issue for publicationon Tuesday in each week a statement giving the numbers of British, allied and Neutral ships lost by enemy action in the seven days ending on thepreceding Sunday, and giving also the name and tonnage of each british ship lost with the date m&amp;m&amp;ssss of loss.For the future, we should propose that publication of losses ofships &quot;by enemy action shall be confined to a weekly statement, seven days in arrear, giving the numbers of British, Allied and Neutral ships lost,with the total tonnage for British ships, but not the name, the tonnage ofeach ship, the date or the cause of loss.Since the usual .weekly statement would have been issued on tuesday, April 30, the change of policy mil need to be announced on or.before that date. .     It is proposed that theannounceme ntSECRET. Copy No.    1 3W.P.(G)(40)113.---- WAR   CABINET.Publication of Shipping Losses.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.

announcement tie made in answer to a question in Parliament and be in thefollowing sense:-&quot;The Allied forces have inflicted very extensive losses on german shipping during the recent operations, but I am unable togive an indication of the total figure, since the enemy has been at pains to suppress all news of his losses.I have reviewed our own policy in this respecti   Promptannouncement of our shipping losses may convey to the enemy valuableintelligence of the efficacy of any particular operation against shipping.In future, news of losses of our shipping will be confined to a weeklystatement, mo.de seven days in arrear, giving the number of ships sunk andtheir total tonnage.   As the House will &quot;be aware, our recent losses havebeen small.&quot;-dmiralty, S.W. 1.April, 26th, 194-0.


</content>
</cab>
