<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/268/0 images: 282-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT 18  THE. PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S  GOV$grg5NT. ) SECRET. CP. 71(37).                                        COPY NO.  jj  &apos;CABINET,COMMITTEE ON THE REPORTS OF THE COMMISSIONERS          FOR THE SPECIAL AREAS&quot;.THE LAST REPORTS OF THE COMMISSIONERS FOR THE    SPECIAL AREAS IN ENGLAND AND WALES              AND SCOTLAND.FURTHER EXPORT1.     Our previous Report (CP. 57(37)) which was adopted bythe Cabinet at their Meeting on 17th February, 1937,(Cabinet 8 (37) Conclusion 6) was concerned with therecommendations contained in the Reports of the Commissionersfor the Special Areas which might require legislation.This Report is concerned with the remaining recommendationsof the Commissioners which are discussed in Parts II and iii of the Report of the Interdepartmental Committee which isattached as Appendix I to Co P. 57(37).       PART II:  PROPOSALS WHICH DO NOT REQUIRE LEGISLATION.             Pages 21 - 26 of Appendix I to CoP- 5 7 (&quot;57&quot;)aMaryport Harbour.2.     The investigations are proceeding, and we are accordingly as yet unable to submit any recommendations.Welsh Smokeless Coal.3.     We concur in the recommendation of the interdepartmental committee, viz. &apos;.-          &quot;That the Government should continue to attempt             to foster the use of this type of coal, but             it is not possible to contemplate legislation             te make its use compulsory for domestic             purposes, particularly in view of the present             difficulty in burning it in the ordinary             open grate. &quot;
     Settlement - Smallholdings.4.     We concur in the recommendation of the Inter-departmental Committee, viz. :-          &quot;that the Government should announce that the             Commissioner has been authorised to proceed             with an extension up to a total of 3,000             families on the understanding that the             results of the experiment generally will he             reviewed in the autumn of 1938.&quot;Cottage Homesteads.5.     We agree that the Scheme is really one more of social improvement-and transference than of land settlement and, on the whole, the Scheme is regarded as one which shouldbe accepted as an experiment.    In the first instance itwould be desirable to begin on a modest scale, and  it hasbeen agreed that 250 families would afford a suitablebeginning.   Arrangements are also being made so that asubstantial, increase in the size of the experiment could bemade without difficulty if the early results seemed tojustify it.       The acceptance of this recommendation has already been announced in the House of Commons.Welsh National Park.6,     We are unable to recommend acceptance of theproposal contained in Paragraph 99 of the interdepartmental committee&apos;s Report.   From the point of view of givingemployment in the Special Areas or even as an improvementof amenities the scheme to provide^a Welsh National Parkwould not in our opinion,., justify the expenditure by theExchequer of a sum which might amount to  100,000.Additional Physical Training.7.     We concur in the recommendation of the Inter-departmental Committee that the provision of physical training facilities for the unemployed in the Special
Areas should he extended, where the need exists.   further developments  will  he co-ordinated so far as necessary withthe national scheme of Physical Training already under con-si deration.Improvement, of finest ructional Cent re s.8.   While we see no objection to reference being made in thecourse of the Debate in general terms to the proposals summarised in Paragraph 107 of the Interdepartmental Committeefs Report,these proposals are still under examination and we are unable tomake any recommendation in regard to them.       PART III;  PROPOSALS REQUIRING FURTHER IjXAMINATI ON,            Pages 27 - 31 of Appendix I &quot;to CP. 57&quot;T37)&quot;-Oil from Coal.9.   The Billingham, Fischer and Low Temperature Carbonisation-processes are all at present under examination.   We are not therefore in a position to submit any recommendation.Cale ium Carb ide .10.  This matter will come before the Cabinet separately (see cp. 55 (37), 60 (37) and 62 (37)).Control of Expansion of Industry in Greater London.11.  Ve concur in the recommendation of the interdepartmental committee that a Royal Commission should be appointed, but wethink that the proposed terms of reference are open to objection, e.g.  as being too limited in scope.   We have invited the Minister of Health and the Secretary of State forScotland to consider draft terms of reference in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer with a view in due course to revised terms of reference being submitted to the  cabinet for approval.
Southwest Durham Improvement Association.       -  -12.     As a result of a survey which has &quot;been carriedout in South-West Durham (see paragraph 138 of the Inter-depart mental Committee&apos;s Report) ah &apos;improvementassociation&apos; will be  set up, with the object of assisting in the industrial rehabilitation of the area.It would be desirable to announce the establishment ofthis body in the course of the second reading debate onthe forthcoming Bill.Summary of Conclusions and Recommendations.13.     Our conclusions and recommendations may besummarised as follows -        We recommend the Cabinet -        (l) To approve the suggestions of the            Inter-DepartmeTitai Committee In            regard to -                Welsh Smokeless Coal                Lend -Settlement - Small holdings                Cottage Homesteads                Additional Physical Training.(S)  As  regards  the cuestion of the    control  of  expansion of Industry    in  Greater  London to approve in    principle the appointment of a Royal    Commission  subject to further con-    sideration  of the proposed terms of    reference,  such terms of reference to    be  submitted to the Cabinet for    approval in due course.(3)  To  reject the proposal of the .    Commissioner relative to the vVelsh    National park,,To take note th t the proposals Inregard, to improvement of InstructionalCentres, Maryport Harbour and oil from Coal are under examination andthat we are not therefore in aposition to make specific recommend-ations in regard, to them in thisReport.(5)  To authorise the  Minister of Labour    to announce  in the  Debate the es-    establishment  of the  South-West Durham    Improvement  associated  sti on0Signed, on behalf of the CommitteeWhitehall  Gardens, S.W.I. 23rd. February,  1937.N. CHAMBERLAIN CHAIRMAN.

</content>
</cab>
