<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/268/0 images: 286-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
          THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.               QUESTION  OP THE REVISION OF THE FAIR WAGES RESOLUTION OF                       THE HOUSE OF COMMONS OF 1QTH MARCH, 1909.SECRET.                                                             &apos; COFI NO.&quot; P. 72(37).                         MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF LABOUR.          1.   Over a long period the General Council of the Trades Union Congress          has &quot;been pressing for an amendment of the Fair Wages Clause used in          Government Contracts.   The present clause is based on a resolution passed          by the House of Commons on 10th March, 1909, and provides, in brief,          that Government contractors shall be required to pay wages and observe hours          of labour not less favourable than those commonly recognised by employers and          Trade Societies (or, in the absence of recognised hours and wages, those          which in practice prevail amongst good employers) in the trade in the          district where the work is carried out.   Other conditions of employment          generally accepted in the district in the trade concerned are required to be          taken into account in considering how far the terms of the Fair Wages Clause        &apos;  are being observed.          2.   The two principal cnanges suggested by the General Council are that -               (a) fair wages and conditions should be those fixed by an agreement,                   national, district or local;               (b) contractors shall observe the Fair Wages Resolution for the  whole of                   their work, and not merely for Government (or Municipal) contracts.          3.   These proposals were examined, by the Fair Wages Advisory Committee          in 1934, and my predecessor replied to the General Council in July, 1934,          in accordance with the Committee&apos;s advice and with the concurrence of          the respective Ministers of the contracting Departments represented on          the Committee.   As regards (a) it was pointed out that the existing          clause is designed to secure conformity with standards of wages and          conditions generally observed in the district concerned, that the present          Fair Wages Clause, as administered,  ensures generally that wages and          conditions recognised in any particular district, either by agreement or
by customary practice, are observed on Government contracts,  and that  afair wages clause is not an appropriate instrument for the enforcement of agreements irrespective of the question whether they are in fact recognisedor put into operation in the particular district.   As regards (b),  itwas stated that the administration of the existing clause already proceedson the basis that firms to which Government contracts are assigned shallbe required to observe the principles of the Fair Wages Resolution ontheir private work.4.   In July, 1935, a deputation from the General Council again urgedme to give effect to the two proposals mentioned above, and I undertook to examine them in consultation with the Departments concerned.    Thequestion was again brought before the Fair Wages Advisory Committee,which took the view that the reply to the General Council&apos;s renewedrepresentations should follow the lines of the earlier reply mentionedabove.5.   Since 1909, there has been a progressive increase in the extent towhich wages and other conditions of employment are settled by voluntarycollective agreements between organisations of employers and workpeople,.and at the present time over a large part of industrs&apos;&apos;, collective bargain-ing is the normal and established method of settling working conditions.Recently Parliament has given its approval to the principle of thestatutory recognition of collective agreements in the Cotton manufacturing industry Act, 1954.   Further, it is laid doivn in the Road Traffic Actsthat, in arriving at decisions as to the observance by licence holders of the provisions of the Acts based on the Fair Wages Clause, theIndustrial Court shall have regard to joint agreements reached in the motor transport industry.6.   I do not think there is any doubt that there is a case for theamendment of the existing Fair Wages Resolution although it may be opento question whether the moment has yet arrived to deal with the matter,which cannot be divorced from the wider question of the compulsoryextension of voluntary agreements and wages regulation in general.   Inthis field the result of the experiment in the Cotton LfenufacturingIndustry still remains to be defined, and it is anticipated that the enquiries of the Committee recently appointed by the Minister of Transport
and myself to examine the present position with regard to the regulation ofwages and conditions of service of persons employed in the Road transport industry (Goods), will throw further light on another aspect of the matter.(7)  There has, however, been no public review of the subject since a Committeeof which Sir George Murray was Chairman, reported in 1908 and provided the basisof the 1909 Resolution.   There is also the consideration that while we have hadnumerous representations from the Trades Union Congress on points of Pair Wagepolicy we have not yet ascertained the views of the employers1 organisations.Clearly no major amendment of the Clause could be made without the employershaving full opportunity of expressing their views on a matter which is ofconsiderable concern to them.  In all the circumstances I have come to theconclusion that a further public review of the position by a Committee isdesirable and when recently I saw Mr. Bevin, the Chairman of the General Councilof the Trades Union Congress, he indicated his personal view that such action would be acceptable.  This is important, as if the Government are not preparedto make any move the General Council intend, I understand,  to take steps with aview to having a new Resolution moved in the House.  This would not be asatisfactory way of dealing with the matter and I think it is desirable toappoint a Committee now and not do so as a result of pressure from theOpposition.(8)  As this, is a matter in which the Treasury is closely concerned,  I put mypersonal view to the Chancellor.   After considering the report of a Conferenceof representatives of Departments concerned, he has expressed his agreement withthe proposal to appoint a Committee and his view that it should be appointedby me.(9)  If my colleagues concur I propose therefore to proceed forthwith with theappointment of a Committee including representatives of the Treasury and the contracting Departments together with representatives of employers&apos;  andworkpeoples1  organisations and an independent Chairman.   The suggested terms ofreference are as follows:-     &quot;To consider the working of the Fair Wages Resolution of theHouse of Commons of the 10th March,  1909,  as embodied in Government contracts and to advise whether any changes are desirable and practicable&quot;.                                  (Intd.)  E.B.26th February, 1957,                                  3.H.Q.1365-70.B.G.

</content>
</cab>
