<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/268/0 images: 400-402</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
  (THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OFHIS  BRITANNIC  MA JEST Y 1 S  GOVERNMENT).                                                  COPY NO.    *f I                         CABINET.                       RENT RESTRICTION.             Memorandum by the Minister of Health.      1.   The present Rent Restriction Acts will expire on the 24th June, 1938,. in England and Wales,... unless some action is taken in the meantime.   Questions have already been addressed to me in the House as to the Government&apos;s intentions in the matter.      2.   I will briefly recall the history of this legislation, which started in 1915 as a purely war measure and has been continued up to the present day by a series of temporary enactments.   The earlier provisions were extended and amplified until,  under the Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act 1920, all but a very small percentage of the houses in the country were controlled by the Acts.   This Act of 1920 is still the basis of the present system of control, the essential features of which are (1) to limit the permitted increase of rent chargeable by landlords to the actual increase in rate charges payable by them over the charges&apos;payable in 1914 together with an amount equal to 40 per cent, of the net rent in 1914;  and (2) to give the bulk of tenants practically complete security of tenure so long as they pay the rent.   Houses erected after April 1919 were never subject to the Acts.      3.   The Act of 1920 represents the high-water mark of control.   In 1923 another Act was passed which extended the period of operation of the Acts for a further two years, but at the same time.provided for the decontrol of individual houses.                           1.C RET.84(37).
Any controlled house which became vacant in the ordinary courseof events  on  or  after the 31st  July 1923 passed out  of thecontrol of the Acts and future  tenants thereof had no protectionunder the Acts.     4.   The Acts were continued in operation by the annual   -Expiring Laws Continuance Acts  until 1933, when the Act at                                -present in force was passed.    This Act divided controlled housesinto three classes according to their rateable value in 1931.The rateable value limits of these classes were:-     Class A, over  35 ( 45 in  the Metropolitan Police District)     Class B, over  13 but not  over  35 (over  20 but not over                         45 in  the Metropolitan Police District)     Class C,  13 or under ( 20 or under in the Metropolitan                        Police  District).The Act of 1933  provided for the immediate decontrol of all houses in Class A.   Individual houses of Class B continued as before tobe decontrolled  as they became  vacant, but no.further decontrolof individual houses in Class C was allowed.     5.   The three principal Acts mentioned have all been passed                         -following an inquiry and report by a Departmental Committee.The 1920 Act followed the report of Lord Salisbury&apos;s Committee,the 1923 Act Lord OnslowTs Committee and the 1933 Act Lord MarleyTsCommittee.   The Marley Committee which reported in 1931 was thefirst Committee to attempt a statistical analysis of the housingposition and to  base their recommendations thereon.     6.  . Since  the date of the Marley Report there has been aconsiderable change in the housing situation.   There has been aboom in private  enterprise building and one and a half millionadditional new houses have already been erected.                                        -          The new overcrowding  legislation is already in forcein many areas and will soon be  in operation throughout the whole country.   If this legislation  is to be successfully enforced theordinary working man must be able to find accommodation in whichhe and his family will not be overcrowded, at a rent within hismeans.                           2.
     7.   There are three possible courses before us,     (a)  to take no action and let the Acts expire in           June 1938,     (b)  to continue the present Acts unchanged for a           further period, or     (c)  to follow precedent and set up a Departmental           Committee to advise oh future action,,The first course seems to me quite impracticable.   Even if thehousing situation plainly justified the general withdrawal ofcontrol, there would almost certainly have to be transitional provisions - there were such provisions in the 1933 Actapplicable to A class houses when they were decontrolled as a class.   The second course is difficult to justify in view ofthe changed housing situation, and in any case is only puttingoff the problem.   Accordingly I propose that we should adoptthe third course and set up a strong Departmental Committee toexamine the whole question of.rent restriction in the light of present day housing conditions.   As any legislation resultingfrom the recommendations of such a Committee must be passed before June 1938 the Committee should be appointed as soon aspossible with a view to a Report being received towards the endof the year.   The terms of reference of the Committee mightbe:-          &quot;to inquire into and report upon the present working          of the Rent Restriction Acts and to advise what steps          should be taken to continue or amend those Acts&quot;c                                 March 3rd. 1937,

</content>
</cab>
