<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/35/21 images: 206-213</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GO vTSRNMBNT)secret.P.(45)121I       24TH MARCH,  1945 COPY   NO.    I&quot;&quot;.-WAR cabinet proposed POOD CONFERENCE.,Note &quot;by the secretary the attached drafts of two telegrams to our ambassador in. Washington, in reply to his telegrams1358 and 1359, were agreed between officers of theTreasury and Foreign Office, after discussion withrepresentatives of the interested Departments.(Signed) E.E, BRIDGES.Offices of the War Cabinet,S.W.I.24TH MARCH, 1943.

TELEGRAM IYour telegram No.  1359. i see my immediately following telegram,1.     Unless you see objection the following should be terms ofthe aideiremoire which you should give to the State Departmentabout the Pood Conference.Begins.2,      I have the honour to refer to the reply of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to the letter from the United States   Charg6d&apos;Affaires of March 10th rela&amp;ting to the proposed food conference in which His Majesty&apos;s Government stated, that theywere carefully considering what positive suggestions they could offer to facilitate the work of the Conference.      While HisMajesty&apos;s Government agree that the consideration of post-warplans by the Food Conference should be divorced from thequestions of the provision of Relief,  they attach importance to avoiding the creation of an impression among the European andother Allied Governments that the problem of Relief is in danger of being relegated to the background.      His Majesty&apos;sGovernment suggest therefore that it would be desirable beforeconvening the Food Conference to consider what steps could betaken to explain the scope of the Food and Relief conferences and to provide measures for connecting the two sets of discussions in order to indicate that the urgent problems of relief were not being ignored g^r^neglected.3,      His Majesty&apos;s government-^assiime that the main object ofthe Food Conference is to examine andt de^in^^l^^o^i^ rangequestions af&quot; foodstuffs and &quot;other essential agriculturalproducjfcSy( taking into account the problems arising from the!uc^6ur;ai modifications which have occurred during the warin their production.    Further it will consider for which of thesematters concerted international policies are required andindicate the procedure by which their study and solution couldbe actively undertaken by appropriate subsequent discussions.4.    - In -defining the scope of the Food Conference His.Majesty&apos;s Government consider it essential that the Termsof Reference for the Conference should be such as toensure that the discussions would be confined to foodstuffs and other essential agricultural products and thatfirwfarr1o&apos;nil31P^ rv --i*-nft Conference should j&amp;uly^hQ^j^s^S^t^es^.pa??^rg---^^---way f**su*siib^i^ij^^related economic and financial, questions which wlTTC be tt&amp;ld--when there has been adequate   /time for the necessary^preparation.

TELEGRAM NO.  III should be glad if, when making to the U.S9 Governmentthe communication contained in my.immediately preceding telegram, you would put before them orally the following views -as to the&apos;best i^rocedure for discussions under Article VII.,you will see that these are not in a form which could appropriately be communicated to other Governments and it isfor this reason that they should not form part of our formalwritten observations on the Pood Conference,     H0M* government believe it to be desirable that the proposed Pood conference should, be recognised as the first step in a general programme which will include the various &quot;Tl^es&apos;^methods of achieving the objectives contemplated in ArticleVII of the Mutual Aid Agreement of February 23, 19420      Inregard to further development oft procedure in the general programme of disrru^rolis^uncteF^rticle VII His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have always believed that the most satisfactory way of making progress would be to reach if possible preliminaryal^e. 0S  ^ &quot;between the United States and the UnT^ed Kingotoiru&apos;&quot;Having&apos;&quot;achieved a measure of agreement&apos; His Majesty*s Govern-ment and the United States Government would then consult theSoviet and the Chinese Governments and subsequently approach the other members of the United Nations0    In any case as partof the machinery for discussion of the several economic questions in separate but related conferences$ His Majesty?s government believe that it would either now or at a somewhat later stage be indispensable to have some small steering or co-co-ordinating committee generally representative of the United Nations.Sucha Committee would facilitate the taking of preliminarysoundings and the carrying out of the preparatory work whichare essential to the successful outcome of InternationalConferenceso  fWe wish to avoid the Pood Conference itselfappointing Committees to deal with these wider questions orinviting the bodies- which will deal with them in due course toreport to the Pood Conference0   We think the Pood conference should confine itself to pointing out the need for thesequestions to be dealt with by the appropriate experts,2, You should also impress upon the UeSs Government thatwe think it essential to avoid raising at this the firstUnited Nations Conference controversial.,..toiiics...-Q.n which theground has not, fegjeji., &quot;prepared by previous discussion,,     There S*?Tvar ous&quot;&quot;riiat$er s in regard to nutrition and foodstuffs onwhich Resolutions could be passed based on the experiencesgained under war conditions and even if aspirations towards &apos;better nutrition must &quot;be of a long-range character it is better to have rather vague&apos; Resolutions than to embark oncontroversial topics03* For your own information.only, we think it essentialto avoid discussion of plans like the Wheat scheme designed tosafeguard the interests of producers and particularly of high cost producerso    Such schemes, whatever may be their merits, are bound to provoke controversy both on the part of consumers andof low cost producers,    Coilon.. is a particular example,,    Interestof American cotton, producors would not be easy to reconcile withthose of cotton consumers, such as the U*K,5 or low cost producerssuch as India and Brazil0    Supply of cotton to U.S.  textile industry at a lower cost than it would be available to our &quot;-owner other textile industries presents obvious danger^4.        Buffer stock schemes require much p^oiliminary thought and discussion before they could usefully be discussed at any general conference.    Method in which, such schc,:.., could be financed, needsconsideration as part of widur q.uestion of international monetaryarrangements *5, It is not proposed to nominate our delegates until we havean answer from you to these two telegrams 0




</content>
</cab>
