<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/55/19 images: 218-234</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NOCC(74) 44thConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 7 NOVEMBER 1974at 10.30 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the Council(Items 1-5)The Rt Hon Lord Elwyn jones lord Chancellor(Items 1 and 2)The Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social Services(items 1-5)The Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for Trade(Items 1-5)The Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary ef State for the Home Department(Items 1-5)The Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for Industry(Items 1-5)The Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for Defence(Items 1-5)The Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food-   geddrs.\   - :The Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy Seal
The Rt Hon Robert Mellish MP The Rt Hen John Silkin mp parliamentary Secretary, Treasury Minister for Planning and local government the FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Samuel Silkin QC MP The Rt Hon Ronald King Murray QC mp attorney General (Item 2) Lord Advocate (Item 2)SECRETARIATl.( &apos;Sir John hunt mr P D Nairne (Items 3 and 5)Mr H FT Smith (Item 3)Mr P Benner (Item 1)Mr J A Hamilton (Items 2,4 and 6)Mr E J G Smith (Item 5)Mr R J 0&apos;Neill (Item 3)Mr R L Baxter (Items 2, 4 and 6)contents item Subject page 1.      PARLIAMENTARY affairs debate on e.c. Documents on Sugar 12.      BILL TO AMEND THE TRADE UNION AND labour relations ACT 1974 23.      FOREIGN AFFAIRSUganda4.      THE PRICE CODE 45.      SUGAR 56.      PAY OF TEACHERS IN SCOTLAND 104ii
parliamentary affairs. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be takenin the House of Commons during the following week.Debate on EECDocuments onSugarIt was noted that there was to be a Debate on 11 November on certain European Economic Community (e.c.) documents on sugar which the Select Committee on European subordinate legislation had recommended should be further considered bythe House.   A large backlog of such recommendations had nowaccumulated, and it was proposed to give priority to the documents on sugar because the House should have an opportunityof expressing a view in advance of the Ministerial meeting at brussels on 18 November at which they were to be considered.It was proposed that the Debate should take place on the basisof a &quot;take note&quot; Motion.    It was argued however that this formof Motion had attracted some criticism on previous occasions,and it therefore might be preferable,   if the content of the documents made this appropriate, for the Government to put down a Motion welcoming or approving them.    On the other hand itwas pointed out that a Resolution was about to be tabled forthe immediate appointment of a Select Committee to examinegenerally the handling of Debates on European secondarylegislation arising from reports by the Scrutiny Committee; andit would be appropriate, pending the Select Committee&apos;s Report,to continue to take Debates on the basis of &quot;take note&quot; Motions.Whatever the form of the Motion, however, past experience showed the importance of advance collective consideration of theattitude to be adopted by the Government spokesman.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, saidthat although a &quot;take note&quot; Motion would probably be right on this occasion, there was a danger that Debates on European secondarylegislation would have an unsatisfactory outcome unless care hadbeen taken to settle the Governments position in advance.    Inview of the sensitivity of the Debate on sugar on 11 November /the Minister of Agriculture should, as the Government spokesman,inform the Prime Minister and other Ministers concerned inadvance of the line he proposed to take.    In addition the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary should ensure that there werearrangements for the necessary consideration by Ministers of theway the Government should handle other forthcoming Debates in either House, arising from reports of the Scrutiny Committee.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval of the Prime Minister &apos;summing up of the discussion and invited the Ministerof Agriculture, Fisheries and Food and the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary to be guided accordingly.. &apos; .    &apos; 0C        K      1
BILL TO amend the TRADEUNION ANDLABOURRELATIONS ACT1974PreviousReference:CC(74) 12thConclusions,Minute 22. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Employment (C(74) 128) about the Bill to amend theTrade Union and Labour Relations Act 1974, and a minute byhim to the Prime Minister, to which was attached a copy of aletter dated 6 November from the General Secretary of theTrades Union Congress (TUC).THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said thatwhen the Opposition amendments to the Act were put through,the original intention had been to deal with them in theEmployment Protection Bill.    However, since it was urgently necessary to amend the legislation before a case could come before the courts, he had proposed a separate amending Bill.He had told the TUC before the Election that when the Act wasamended some safeguard must be provided for the individualagainst arbitrary exclusion or expulsion from union member -ship, but that if the TUC expressed a strong preference for a voluntary system instead of a statutory provision theGovernment would be ready to consider it.    In hie subsequent discussions with the TUC they had not raised the possibility iof a voluntary alternative until his discussion the previousMonday with the Finance and General Purposes Committee.The Committee were confident that their proposal for a voluntary arrangement would be accepted by the general council and, in the circumstances, he had no alternative but toput it to the Government.    The proposal was explained in theletter from the General Secretary of the TUC which he had circulated.    There was to be an independent review committee under an independent chairman with legal qualifications.    Afterensuring that all internal union procedures had been exhaustedthe review committee would discuss each case with the union and the individual concerned in an attempt to resolve thematter by agreement; failing this the review committee wouldmake a recommendation which the union would be expected to observe.    The independent review committee could be inoperation by the New Year.    This was a respectable proposal, which would fulfil without legal sanctions the Government&apos;s aim off protecting civil liberties.    The adoption of such a procedure would force every trade union to bring its internal proceduresup to the standard of the best.    If the Cabinet would accept theproposal, the Bill could go forward quickly without this clause.If they rejected it, the resulting argument with the TUC woulddistract attention from the primary object of amending, the Act.THE PRIME MINISTER said that since the Lord Chancellor,who wished to contribute to the discussion, was obHged at that point to leave the Cabinet, it would be necessary for theCabinet to resume discussion at their next meeting.
The Cabinet  -Agreed td resume discussion of this question at their next meeting.
3. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat President Amin, who was angered by recent reports in theBritish Press that he was afraid of conspiracies against him andhad been implicated in the death of one of his former wives, had informed us that the staff of our High Commission must bereduced to a total of 5 officers.    In retaliation we had requiredthat the Ugandan High Commission in London should be reducedto the same number.    It was possible that President Amin, in his present mood, would take measures against British interests in uganda and require British subjects to leave.    He might, however be restrained from going too far by a desire to avoid unduecriticism from other African leaders with the consequent risk thatthe arrangements to hold the next summit meeting of theOrganisation of African Unity in Uganda might be cancelled.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, saidthat it was an offence to the Commonwealth that one of its membershould follow the racialist policies and the domestic practices ofwhich President Amin was guilty.    President Amin&apos;s presence atthe meeting of Heads of Government, which was to take place inApril, would be an embarrassment.    There was a precedent forthe members of the Commonwealth telling one of their numberthat she was aot welcome. This was not a matter in which it wouldbe prudent for us to take a lead, for if we did so African opinion might rally against us despite the fact that many African countriesdeplored President Amin&apos;s behaviour.    It would however be ofinterest to know of any indication that African members of theCommonwealth were themselves beginning to think along theselines.    The Cabinet noted that contingency plans existed forsupplementing the normal air services from Uganda if there were a forced exodus of British subjects.The Cabinet -)Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister &apos;summing up of their discussion.4. The Cabinet discussed the Price Code.    The discussion is recorded separately.
5. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Minister ofAgriculture, Fisheries and Food (C(74) 117 and 126) on sugar.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD saidthat the arrangements on supply of sugar which had been agreed atthe Council of Ministers (Agriculture) of the European economic community (e.c.) on 21 October were not ideal, but represented the best arrangements obtainable and were within the instructions given to him by the Cabinet.    It would not be right to seek to reopen the agreement.    The world supply situation next year was becoming more difficult, with every expectation of a world shortage of sugar,and prices were already rising very rapidly. .    All practical steps should now be taken to assure our supplies next year, but the factmust be faced that there could well be a shortage of sugar in thiscountry.    He wished to emphasise that the agreement reached atthe Council of Ministers did not discriminate against cane sugar -indeed it would help us to obtain raw cane supplies - and he was intouch with representatives of the sugar refinery workers on this.He would have preferred to have reached a separate agreement with australia, but it was clear that Australia would not be able to offerenough sugar to meet the short-fall in our supplies over the nextnine months.    Furthermore, the Australian Government had made it plain that they were interested only in a long-term agreement,and that either it would have to be concluded with the community as a whole or, if a bilateral arrangement with the United Kingdom,it would have to receive Community endorsement.    It was essentialthat the e.c. commit itself immediately to the import of 1. 4 million tons a year of sugar from the developing Commonwealth, at a price which took account of the fact that the current very high world prices would be a counter-attraction to them.    The future structure of thecane refining industry in the United Kingdom required urgent examination;  its problems had been before Ministers for at least3 years, but so far without resolution.In discussion it was argued that, although the short-term problem was particularly acute, this should not be solved to the detriment of our long-term objectives.    Some of the terms of the agreement reached were a cause for anxiety on this account.    The agreement to allow e.c. production of beet sugar to expand from 10 million tons to 13 million tons annually could effectively prevent continuingaccess by overseas suppliers.    This agreement should not have beenreached without a matching commitment to import 1.4 million tons annually from the developing Commonwealth and an arrangement for imports from Australia being reached at the same time.    We should now insist on both those arrangements; and we should be preparedto go ahead with them unilaterally if the e.c. as a whole would not do so.    Our cane refineries needed Australian raw sugar in additionto the 1.4 million tons to continue economic operation.    The arrange-ments agreed at the Council of Ministers did not guarantee our supplies - their only immediate effect had been to raise the world price.    Unless we received satisfaction on these matters, we should follow the precedent set by West Germany and reject the agreement which had been reached.
It was further argued that this issue touched on an area which wasfundamental to the approach of the Labour Party to the questionof membership of the e.c..    The Commonwealth Sugar agreement had been a most valuable instrument for furthering the interestsof the Commonwealth as a whole;   and it was essential that thereshould be no gap between its termination and the introduction of effective arrangements to import 1. 4 million tons of sugar annuallyfrom the developing Commonwealth.   The assurances on thisgiven by the previous Administration had proved to be completelydefective;  the Government must ensure that the arrangements it made remedied those defects.    Moreover, the Government hadincluded among its renegotiation objectives, the need to preserveaccess for cheaper food supplies from outside the Community.Even if such supplies were not available now, periods of surplusmight return and we should retain the right to take advantage ofthem.    Australian sugar was a particular example of this principle.The Government would be faced with a considerable politicalproblem, when presenting the results of renegotiation, if it couldbe said that we had been anxious to buy sugar from Australia andthey had been anxious to sell it to us, but that the e.c. had prevented it.    The Government had never accepted arrangements which would prevent us importing Australian sugar in the future.It would be a mistake to make arrangements on sugar which pre-judged our continuing membership of the e.c. following renegotiation.We were in a strong position to insist on our objectives on sugar and,if necessary, to block matters which other members of the EECwanted.On the other hand it was pointed out that, in present circumstances,it was advantageous in relation to world supply and demand for beetsugar production in Europe to be expanded, and particularly to thenational advantage for production in the United Kingdom to beincreased.    If world supplies at some future date went into surplus,and the e.c. were party to an international sugar agreement, itsproduction would have to be restricted.    In any case the increasedbeet production in the United Kingdom still left room for1. 4 million tons of sugar from the developing Commonwealth.    Itwas also argued that our traditional Commonwealth suppliers of foodstuffs had diversified into other markets, both because of theway the previous Administration had approached membership ofthe e.c. and also because in many of those other markets higher prices were available.    The clock could not be turned back in this regard.    Australia in particular was seeking other markets forher primary commodities;  she did not feel that we had let herdown over sugar.   We had not asked for continuing special accessfor Australian sugar in our renegotiation demands.6
It was further argued that the dominant factor was our acute needfor sugar next year; the arrangements agreed at the Council ofMinisters were the best opportunity for obtaining our requirements.If these arrangements now disappeared because of Britishobjections, the Government would be faced with a most difficult task in explaining to the public why we had followed a courseleading to a reduction in supplies and an increase in prices.    Inthe circumstances it would be wrong either to turn down theagreement reached or to attach unduly onerous conditions to it.In further discussion the following points were made:-a. At the meeting of the Council of Ministers (ForeignAffairs) on 12-13 November and of the Council of Ministers(Agriculture) on 18-19 November we should seek to obtain a commitment by the e.c. to the import of 1. 4 million tonsof sugar annually from the developing Commonwealth, on a continuing basis; at a price which was realistic in presentcircumstances, which undoubtedly would be above  140 aton - perhaps appreciably above it - and with arrangementsfor the review of prices; and with a provision that the rawcane supplies involved would be allocated to Britishrefineries.    Our Ambassadors in the eight other member states of the e.c. should be instructed straightaway to makeknown the degree of importance which the government attached to this issue.b. Whatever arrangements for sugar supplies were finally agreed we must prepare for the possibility of rationingearly in 1975.    There were already signs of hoarding since it was common knowledge that the price of sugar was boundto rise.    Contingency planning should be put in hand.c. The whole of the cane refining and beet processingindustries needed rationalisation.    The structural problemsof the cane refining industry needed urgent attention.    Thefuture of the industry should be based upon a realisticestimate of raw cane sugar throughput,, although this wouldbe difficult to estimate before the outcome was known ofarrangements for imports from the developing commonwealth and Australia.d. Further thought should be given to the possibility of adeal with Australia either through the medium of the EECor direct.    A possible, variant of this might be a directdeal which would be converted into a Communityarrangement if we remained within the e.c..
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that a fundamental long-term issue had to be considered against the background of an extremely difficult short-term situation.    TheCabinet accepted the agreement on sugar reached at the Council ofMinisters (Agriculture) on 21 October, on the following conditions :-i.     That the e.c. agreed to the import of 1.4 million tonsof sugar annually under Protocol 22 of the Treaty of accession, offering initially a price not less than 140 a ton.ii.     That the raw cane sugar imports would come to theUnited Kingdom for refining...&apos;        .   - -   : I t\;:v        &apos;iii. That the e.c. accepted the principle of continuingarrangements;   and ii ;..//iv. that the possibility of an agreement with australia in the longer run, if one could be reached, should notbe ruled out.The Cabinet would wish to resume its discussion on the longer termposition in the light of progress on these points and any furtherassessment of the Australian attitude.    In reply to any question in the House of Commons, he would take the line that we had everyintention of getting all the Australian sugar we could, either underCommunity arrangements or direct.    In the meantime theSecretary of State for Prices and Consumer Protection and theMinister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food should put in hand a study of the steps required to deal with the likely shortage of sugarin the New Year and report back as soon as possible.    The Secretaryof State for Industry and the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food should examine urgently the question of the future structure of the cane refining industry.The Cabinet -1.    Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.2.    Invited the Foreign and Commonwealth secretary and the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food to proceed accordingly at the meetings of the Councilof Ministers (Foreign Affairs) on 12-13   november and the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) on 18-19 November3.    Invited the Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and Food to put in hand at once, in close consultationwith the Secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection, a study of the steps necessary to deal withthe likely shortage of sugar.
4.    Invited the Secretary of State for Industry andthe Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food toexamine urgently the future structure of the canerefining industry.5. Agreed to resume their discussion of the longer-term sugar position at a subsequent meeting.9
6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Scotland (C(74) 127) about the pay of teachers in Scotland.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND said that he wishedto impress upon his colleagues the gravity of the situation inScotland.    Just before the Election the teachers&apos; side of theScottish Teachers&apos; Salaries Committee had made a claim for an interim payment of 10 per cent pending the report of the committee under Lord Houghton to examine the pay structure and levels of remuneration of non-university teachers in Great Britain.    after consulting his colleagues he had persuaded the management side to turn down the claim, but he had suggested that they might indicate their willingness to make an interim payment immediatelyafter receiving the Houghton Report. &quot; This was conveyed to the teachers but was not accepted.    There were now official 3-daystrikes in some areas, as well as outbursts of strike action byunofficial action groups throughout Scotland,    The demand now wasnot for 10 per cent but for an interim payment of  300 to be madeto every teacher at the end of December.    There was intensivelobbying and protest marches.    There was ill-feeling about theLondon weighting allowances that had recently been increased for teachers in London, and nationalists were asking whether or not he had the power to take decisions on teachers&apos; salaries in Scotland.There was a danger that the militant action groups that had sprungup might take over the official unions and decline to negotiate onthe recommendations of the Houghton Committee.    He thoughtit necessary, therefore, to make arrangements for the payment in December of an interim award, after consulting Lord Houghtonto make sure that the award would net cut across his recommenda-tions.    In order to clear this through the statutory procedures, ,it would be necessary to set in hand the arrangements before thereceipt of the Houghton Report.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCEsaid that any concession to Scottish teachers would have to begiven to teachers in England and Wales.    Teachers&apos; pay hadbeen increased last April and they would receive further increases under threshold agreements up to the end of November; inaddition they would benefit from the recommendations of theHoughton committee, which the Government would allow to bebackdated to 24 May.     The Government could not concede morethan this under pressure from militancy without endangering thesocial contract.    On the other hand he saw no objection toimplementing the Houghton committee recommendations in two stages:  for instance by giving first an immediate interim awardin the form of a lump sum or a percentage, which would be followedby the negotiation of long-term structural changes.    But theimmediate payment could not be made in December.    The processof clearance through the Burnham Committee and the ScottishTeachers1 Salaries Committee, the making of the Order, the
notification to education authorities, and the programming of localauthority computers, would make it impossible for the payments to go through before the end of January,    All this would apply to scotland in the same way as to England and &quot;Wales.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a short discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed mat it would be desirable, if possible, tomake an interim payment immediately after the receipt of theHoughton Report at the end of December in the same way as animmediate payment had been made to nurses on the receipt ofthe Halsbury Report.    It might be possible to achieve this by setting in motion the statutory procedures before the pubHcationof the Report, though it would be necessary to make sure byinformal consultation with Lord Houghton that the payments wouldnot prove incompatible with his Committee1 s recommendations.Any such arrangement would have to apply to England and Walesas well as Scotland.    The Secretary of State for Scotland should therefore consult further with the Secretary of State for education and Science, and also with the Secretary of State for employment and report back to the Cabinet at the pre-Budget meeting onMonday 11 November,The Cabinet -Invited the Secretary of State for Education and science and the Secretary of State for Scotland to consider, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for Employment,whether arrangements could be made for an interimpayment to teachers throughout Great Britain at the endof December, and to report back to the Cabinet on11 November.Cabinet office November 197411
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ government copy NO    g QCABINETCONFIDENTIAL annex cc(74) 44th Conclusions, Minute 4Thursday, 7 November, 1974 at 10.30 am the PRICE THE PRIME MINISTER, said that because of their connection withQjODE the forthcoming Budget the proposals for the review of the PriceCode must be treated as Budget secrets.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR PRICES AND consumer protection said that after discussion in Ministerial Committeesdecisions had been reached on the proposals to be included in the consultative document on the review of the Price Code, though some of the figures had yet to be finally determined.     The main proposals fell into 3 parts.    In the first place the productivitydeduction was now having a more adverse effect on profits thanwhen it was first introduced:  to give the same effect now it wouldbe necessary to reduce the deduction from 50 per cent to 12^ per cent.She proposed to reduce it to about 20 per cent, with taperingarrangements by which the figure would be increased up to 35 per cent for capital-intensive firms and reduced down to 10 per cent for labour-intensive firms.    The productivity deduction would stillmake an inroad on profits, but to offset this her second mainproposal was to introduce a new investment relief.    The investmentrelief was designed to be as selective and accountable as waspossible with the existing economic machinery: it might be possibleto be more selective after the introduction of Planning Agreements.The relief would be related to plans for future investment; itwould be given at a rate of 15 or 20 per cent;  and would coverinvestment in plant, machinery and industrial buildings, but notvehicles, shops or offices.    Firms whose investment fell short ofthe submitted programme would be denied further price increasesuntil the deficit was made good.    She was satisfied that this wasthe most water-tight arrangement that could be made in presentcircumstances.    In the third place she proposed certain adjustments to the safeguard for manufacturers and distributors.    The presentsafeguard for manufacturers against erosion of profits was not usedexcept by firms that were exceptionally well advised;  in order tomake the safeguard more accessible but at the same time morerigorous, she proposed to amend it to deal with erosion of profits
on a product basis but to reduce the level of the safeguard from90 per cent of net profit margins to 65 or 70 per cent.    Thesafeguard for distributors&apos; net profit margins was at 75 per centbut, for technical reasons concerned with gross margin limits,two thirds of distributing firms were already below that level,being unable to make use of the safeguard.    She agreed with theSecretary of State for Trade and the Minister of Agriculture thatthe special problems of distributing firms needed further examination;  she did not propose to reverse the 10 per cent cut in gross margins but would like to see whether something couldbe done to make the net-profit margin safeguard more available.Her proposals for nationalised industries would bring them more into line with the private sector, particularly as regards theminimum safeguard for return on capital.    This change would leave room for price increases, and the responsible ministers would have to decide how far to allow the prices to rise withinthe new limits.    The total effect of her proposals, assuming someunder-claiming of investment relief, was expected to be to increasethe Retail Price Index (RPI) by about 1 per cent.In discussion it was noted that if the effect of the proposals did notexceed an addition of 1 per cent to the RPI, the Trades UnionCongress had stated that they would accept it, albeit reluctantly.It was argued that there was a good case for easing the applicationof the Code to distributors, since even a highly efficient firmlike Marks and Spencer had reported lower profits on a higherturnover.    Distributors would benefit little from the reductionin the productivity deduction; nor would they benefit much fromthe investment relief if it excluded shops and vehicles;  there wastherefore a strong case for adjusting the safeguard on their net profit margins.In further discussion it was argued that it was doubtful whetherthe investment relief would in fact affect investment, which would depend on market prospects; and that it was impossible in anycase for the Government to operate selectively in this field, since it lacked the necessary information.    It was suggested therefore that the investment relief should be linked to a statutory provisionby which firms would be obliged to disclose to the Governmentand to the trades unions the facts on which their applications were based.    In this way the cases could be considered moreselectively and the procedures under the Price Code could be adapted in the direction required for the introduction of planning agreements.    Against this it was argued that it was necessaryto bring more cash at once into the company sector if massunemployment was to be avoided and that the means of doing thisthrough investment relief were as selective as they could be inpresent circumstances.    There might later be a case for
requiring more disclosure of information, but that would be amatter for separate legislation.    The present Act forbade thePrice Commission to disclose the information given to it.Moreover the arrangements for Planning Agreements could not wholly supersede the Price Code since only some firms wouldbe covered;  the Cabinet would have to consider later how thePrice Code should apply to other firms.    Meanwhile the confederation of British Industry had been asked to advise itsmember firms to give more information to the trades unions.aThe Cabinet -Took note of the statement by the Secretary ofState for Prices and Consumer Protection.Cabinet Office8 November 1974


</content>
</cab>
