<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 13-49</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S.DOCUMENT IS THE PROPEHTY OF HIS BRITANSI0 MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.in2KOKETCopy No.P.2  (29)CABINET.TRADEOUTLOOK.Memorandum by the president of the Board of Trade.I circulate, for the information of ray colleagues,reports which I have received from members of my Advisory Council, regarding the trade position and prospects.The Cabinet will see that there is a general feeling of optimism.    I hope this is well-founded, but I am bound to say&apos; that I think the evidence of orders hardly justifies an expectation of so marked and general an improvement.The present position, however, presents eome distinctly good features.Steel production is up, and looks like being maintained^ Shipbuilding is really good;428,000 tons placed on the Clyde, &quot;fear and Tyne in a month. Shipowners have been stimulated at least as much by new design as by the improvement in freights.Non-ferrous metals continue good.    Engineering reports . a restrained optimism based on an increase of exports of 15% compared with 1927.    The motor industry has shown a marked improvement in the last three months.Goal output and exports have increased; but, as I have always warned the Cabinet, this improvement &quot;will not reduce the numbers unemployed:  it will only mean more regular work.The chemical trade is satisfactory, exports showing a marked improvement over 1927; and the outlook is good. In rubber manufactures there has   been an improvement and the
general situation is reported to be satisfactory.The boot trade Is rather better; and fancy lace and artificial silk bear ex post tribute to the Chancellor&apos;a fiscal wisdom.In cotton and wool there is nothing new to report.On the whole, therefore, while less enthusiastic than some of my advisers, I shall be disappointed if the distinct improvement of the last three months is not maintained;   and with luck we should do still better.I should like In conclusion to repeat to my colleagues the tribute which I paid at my Advisory Council, to Sir George Grahame and Sir Miles Lampson for their success-ful conduct of very difficult and important tariff negotiations,P. C-L.Board of Trade,15th January, 1929,
Page.Spanish Customs Tariff............................ 1.China Commercial Treaty ........................... 1Coal.............................................. 2Iron and Steel.................................... 4Non-Ferrous Metals................................ 6Engineering................................... 6Electrical Industry ........................... VCotton.......................................... - . 757ool  ,............................................. 8Hosiery; Boots and Shoes.......................... 9Chemicals      ....................................... 10Rubber............................................ 10Effect of New Duties.............................. 11General Trade..................................... 11Banking............................................ 15Shipping ........................................ 16Railway Traffic................................... 16Employment........................................&apos;     19Australian Trade................................ 20Indian Trade...................................... 20South American Trade  .............................. 21Statistical Data..............................----. Annex.CONFIDENTIAL. THE TRADE OUTLOOK.
SPANISH CUSTOMS TARIFF.CHINA COMMERCIAL TREATY.THE PRESIDENT said that the Spanish tariff was, of  . course, a matter about which we had. all been anxious.    Our Government had selected fifty-seven of the tariff headings which were the most important to our manufacturers, and on these they had concentrated.    The result was that on forty-seven we had got from the Spanish Government all we had asked for, whilst on the remaining ten we had got something distinctly better than the rates which the Spanish had proposed to apply.    The details would be published as soon as practicable.    A. great deal of work had been done by the Treaties Department of the Board of Trade, but the credit mainly rested with our new Ambassador at Madrid,  Sir George Grahame, who had made an extraordinarily good job of it.    He had nothing to fight with - no retaliation to hold out and the result was very satisfactory.    As regards coal, we had put some inquiries to the Spanish Government but had not yet had a reply.With regard to China, we had had a difficult time towards the end of the negotiationsj the Chinese bad declared that they would not give most-favoured-nation terms for our goods, but only for our na.tiona.ls.    They said they had made several treaties in which they had. granted these terms for nationals but not for goods, and that to do more for us    would be derogatory.    It would have been perfectly useless, however,&apos; to us to have a treaty without the usual most-favoured-nation clause applying to our merchandise, and Jie stood firm on our demand for it.    Finally they added a clause conceding what we asked for.    Here again we owed a great debt to our Minister, Sir Miles Lampson.SIR KENNETH STEVART remarked that so far as the immediate future was concerned, the treaty with China would be a very good one.    The course of British diplomacy during the ^last two years had completely changed the state of mind of the Chinese towards us, and we could look forward to 1929 with pleasant anticipations of business.      In the middle of 1925 we had become very unpopular with the Chinese, and business was almost impossible.    But the Chinese had for some time directed their attention to making things unpleasant for the Japanese, and we wore exceedingly popular just now, and our goods very welcome in consequence.One must, however, feel some apprehension in regard to succeeding years when China has full power to impose import duties as she likes.      She might pull herself together and act with discretion in this respect.      Let us hope, she would so do.
COAL.MR. ViTARHAM stated that the position in the coal trade was more encouraging.    The output of coal in the United Kingdom for the week ended December 1st was 4,654,000 tons; it went up to 5,153,000 tons in the week ended December 8th, and 5,350,000-tons in the week ended December 15th.    The out-put for the week ended December 15th was 102.1 per cent, of the March 1925 average weekly basis, as compared with 88,8 per cent, for the week ended December 1st.    No doubt part of this increase was seasonal, due to the colder weather, but the continued strength of the freight market suggested that there was a distinct improvement in the general volume of world trade, which meant a greater demand for coal.    The improved steel position on the East Coast was, of course, giving them considerable hope for the future.The number of persons employed in the industry for the week ended December 15th was 79,6 per cent, calculated on the basis of March 1925,    Unemployment for the month of November was 25.3 per cent, as compared with 25.1 per cent, in October and 9.3 per cent, in March 1926.    The quantity of coal exported from the United Kingdom during November was 4,231,000 tons as against 4,630,000 tons  in October, - a considerable drop - and the value per-ton f.o.b. showed a decrease, being 15s. 6d. as against 15s ,3d. in October,    The decreased export was probably due to the seasonal home demand.    The disappointing factor was that the price had fallen, though he thought it would improve again during the present month.Generally speaking, the outlook for 1929 appeared to be better than it had been for some time past, and this applied to the exporting districts as well, which had had a very serious time during the middle portion of 1928.    He would have the figures for the whole of the past year before the next meeting of the Council and would then know better how the industry stood.LORD GAINFORD&quot;reported a better demand for blast furnace coke in both the Cleveland and. West Coast districts.    Ship-ments of coke had been irregular owing th the serious storms which had prevailed.    The foundry trade was fairly good in the early part of the month, but closed down in the Christmas holidays.With regard, to coal there seemed. to be no improvement in price at the present moment, but they Were looking forward to the effect of the de-rating system to help them during the coming months.   An interesting feature in connection with the export of coal was that, though - as Mr. Warham had pointed out - there had been a decrease in the exports in November as compared with October, yet If November were compared with November 1927 it would be found that there had beenj an increase, of over 100,000 tons.    He did not suggest that one month could be taken to indicate the real tendency of trade, but it was interesting to see how that 100,000 tons was made up.    In analysing the November figures as compared with a year ago, he found that we were exporting 12,000 tons less to Scandinavia,
IfjCOAL (CONTD. )60,000 tons more to Germany, 91,000 tons more to the Netherlands, Belgium and France, and 95,000 tons less to Spain.    Italy was 42,000 tons down, Egypt 39,000 tons down, but the Sudan 13,000 tons up.    South America was 60,000 tons down, Gibraltar 28,000 tons up and Ceylon 10.,000 tons down.    Canada was 9,000 tons down, but the United States of America was 76,000 tons up.    Those figures showed a great deal of variation among the different markets as compared with a year ago.    The particularly interesting feature was that, having set ourselves to improve our export trade, we had obtained an increased trade to a lot of small countries all over the world, and in the month chosen it amounted in the aggregate to 103,000 tons.    On the other hand, the big markets showed ups and downs which practically balanced one another.THE PRESIDENT said he had been very interested in what Mr. Shaw had said about the use of pulverised coal in ships (see section on Shipping) and he \&apos;/ondered whether they had now reached a stage where the case for it could be said to be provedaMR. ALEXANDER SHAW thought he could not say that yet. He ivould like to wait another month or two.    The case for pulverised fuel was certainly proved on shore.LORD GAINFORD referred to his experiences with pulverised coal used to raise power.    They had had the same kind of trouble as had apparently been experienced on board ship, but by experiment and by close attention and alteration to their plant, they were rapidly overcoming those difficulties, and he was sanguine that the difficulties which had been experienced in the initial stages in connection with this kind of coal would be overcome on board ship in the sa.r.e way as they were being overcome on land.MR. WARRAM stated that he had had a large experience at collieries which had been running for two years on pulverised coal, and for a considerable time they had not had a hitch of any sort..    &quot;Where they had hid sixty-four men attending to the boilers they now had nine, and the economy in the coal used vr&amp;s extraordinary.    Boilers could be shut off altogether at the week-end, and in a couple of hours they could be started again.THE PRESIDENT asked if the Mining Association had con-sidered publishing information as to what was being done, largely by coalowners themselves, with pulverised coal.LORD GAINFORD said they were anxious to have a complete case before they made a public statement in regard to-experimental plants.    They had difficulties, in particular with the fine ash, and if these had not been satisfacterily overcome, they would be emphasised by their critics.
COAL. ( CONTD. )THE PRESIDENT thought that there was a balance of argument in favour of publishing what was being done, even if the process was not yet perfected.   Ther-Governrnent had had experience of this in connection with low temperature carbonisation.   They gave publicity to the experiments-made, with the result that instead of its being thought that the Government wore doing nothing, it was realised that they were giving a valuable lead.    It was also realised in this way that processes of this kind could not be perfected at once.&apos; IRON AND STEEL.MR. BOND wrote:-&quot;The slight improvement in the production of pig iron and steel which wa3 recorded in October was continued in November, and pig iron production increased from 543,600 tons to 544^400 tons.  an Increase, when the shorter month is taken into account, of 4 per cent.    Steel production increased from 756,000 tons in October to 762,500 tons in November, Contrary to expectations Imports of iron and steel remained at a high level, although they declined from 261,400 tons to 232,800 tons.    Exports of Iron and steel at 399,400 tons were the highest of any month this year except March when they amounted to &quot;409,300 tons.&apos; Imports of pig Iron amounted to only 3,000 tons, thus indicating that Continental competition In this product has been stemmed, but, although imports of pig iron have been steadily reduced, no great headway is yet apparent in the export figures, which, in the month under review, amounted to 37,800 tons . compared with eaa &apos; average of 32,000 tons in the previous ten months. Exports of pig iron in 1913 averaged nearly 80,000 tons per month, nearly 70 per cent, of which went to European countries.&quot;Except for a slowing down for Christmas and New Year holidays, the rate of production would seem to have been maintained throughout December and there are prospects that it will continue into January,    With regard to the North East Coast Sir AP Dorman stated to his shareholders at their Annual Meeting in December that  1;There are now marked signs of Improvement1&apos;.    This is due to. the more numerous shipbuilding orders which have recently been placed and to the increasing requirements of bridge builders.&quot;Stocks of pig iron have been   steadily dwindling during the month and no difficulty is anticipated in disposing of the accumulations at the furnaces, due to the fact that steel works will be idle for several days, v/hile blast furnaces must by their nature remain in continuous production.    Prices for pig iron remain stable and there are no prospects of any decline.    In the hematite section stocks have so far been reduced, as to justify llessrs^Gjer Mills &amp; Company In,deciding to relight two hematite furnaces early in the New Year. With the resumption of the German steel works Continental makers are more active In this market and can now promise earlier delivery, but as they have so far shown no inclination to cut prices it is understood that not much business has resulted.
CONFIDENTIAL. IRON AND STEEL (OONTD.).&quot;Reports from Scotland state that, generally speaking, order books are in a healthier condition than they were a month ago and that, although the pig iron branch of the industry continues dull with no grounds for expecting a revival in the immediate future, there is a feeling of confidence that the Clyde shipbuilding yards, especially the larger establishments, are likely to be busier during the early months of the year than hitherto.    The export trade continues in a not too promising condition, although the strong efforts to combat Continental competition have proved fairly successful and several large orders have been booked in consequence.    &quot;fhile the prospects for the steel trade are somewhat brighter the prospects for wrought iron are not encouraging.&quot;After a stoppage lasting nearly five weeks, the works in the Ruhr recommenced operations on December 3rd on the conditions prevailing previous to the lock-out.    On December 21st Herr Severing pronounced his award which provides that:(1)    From December 3rd, when work was resumed, toDecember 31st wages are to be fixed in accordance with the arbitration award of October 27th which was declared legally binding by the minister of Labour but rejected by the employers.    The October award granted an hourly increase of 6 pfennig ( d) to time workers and 2 pfennig (^-d) to piece workers.    Herr Severing insists on the observance of these increases during December in order to uphold the prestige of the arbitration system.v.-(2)    From January 1st, 1929, the increases granted by the October award are to be replaced by the new award which provides that all time workers over 21 years of age earning less than 90 (pfennig)  (lid.) per hour are to receive increases varying from 1 pfennig to 3 pfennig per hour:  these increases are to be so arranged that the highest paid workers are to receive the smallest addition and the lowest paid the greatest addition: for example, the previous time rate of 60 pfennig (7^d) is to be increased to 66 pfennig (8d.) whereas the previous rate of 89 pfennig i3 to be increased to 90 pfennig per hour.    The wages of men on niece work are to remain unchanged.(3)    All men who, under the special modifications of the legal eight-hour day, have hitherto been working 60 hours per week are from January 1st, 1929, to work 57 hours per week.    Foundry workmen are to work 52 hours in a six day week.(4)    Either side :;;ay terminate this agreement on September 30th, 1930, provided that two months notice is given and that the dissatisfied party has informed the other side of its intention to give notice.&quot;The award will clearly involve a slight increase in the cost of production, but it is aoubtful whether the iricrease in cost will be reflected in increased prices on the export markets since Germany already suffers severely from the competition of Prance and Belgium.      It is very significant that, although &quot;rationalisation&quot; has proceeded further in Germany than in any other country, this process is not sufficient to overcome the handicap under vhich Germany is suffering from the lower wages paid in Belgium and France. German wages,  though only 75 per cent of those obtaining in
CONFIDENTIAL. IRON AND STEEL (CONTD.).Great Britain, are 50 per cent higher than wages in Belgium and France, and rather than face an increase of about five per cent in wages the ironmasters locked out their men for five Y/eeks&quot; .LORD GAINFORD stated, there had been a reduction in the stocks of pig-iron in the Cleveland district, but there had been no reduction in the price of local iron, and no reduction could be expected in view of the cost of manufacture The quantity of Cleveland foundry pig-iron now being raanu-factured was probably smaller than it had ever been in the history of the trade.    Hematite stocks would be slightly up during December and, with the additional make of two furnaces early in January, the position would be still more unsatisfactory.    Sales were slow and difficult to carry through.    The important feature in connection with the hematite trade was the price of ore, which was now 21/6 as compared with 18/- in previous periods.    In making hematite iron they were now only realising about 70/- for hematite pig, and they ought to be realising about 20/- more for the industry to be in a really flourishing condition.In regard to finished steel, sales had been maintained during December.    In semi-finished steel there had been rather less activity, but the aggregate imports of iron and steel for the month of November were 234,000 tons, whilst the aggregate exports were 442,000 tons.A new development in France was the- construction of three new blast-furnaces and a new steel works, which indicated a disposition on the part of France to compete more keenly with Belgium in the German market.NON-FERROUS METALS.CAPTAIN LYTTELT0N remarked that trade was quite well maintained.    Probably the worst feature was the tinplate industry, and the best was wiredrawing, and copper consumption which had shown a certain expansion towards the end of the year, although that was partly covered by consumers in view of an anticipated rise in prices.    It was, generally, quite a pedestrian industry and was going along quite steadily.ENGINEERING.SIR ERNEST PETTER observed that the trading results for November for engineering were surprisingly favourable having regard to the fact that October was a good month. Production was well maintained, and foreign trade showed a moderate improvement.    There was an appreciable increase in the exports of iron and steel and also of machinery.    On the other hand, the percentage of workpeople returned as unemployed in the engineering industry as a whole, excluding the construction and repair of motor vehicles, rose from 9.7 in October to 10.4 In November.      This was the biggest increase they had had for some time, and it was largely attributable to general engineering.
It was possible now to form some opinion of the year1s trade in engineering.     For the eleven months ended November, the aggregate value of exports of machinery, electrical goods and apparatus and vehicles was  101.9 millions as against  88.8 millions for the corresponding period of 1927, representing an increase of 15 per cent.      The exports of machinery   for the eleven months were 519,144 tons as compared with 469,613 tons for the same period in 1927.     In fact, the exports for the eleven months of this year were in excess of the total for the whole of the year 1927.     This constituted a record for a post-war year, but the exports were still only 81 per cent of the 1913 export rate.     As regards the value of the exports, there had bden a fall from  97.4 per ton in 1927 to  94.8 per ton in 1928.     The import tonnage was practically the same aa last year.     The discrepancy between the value of the import tonnage and the export tonnage continued, the average value of the imports of machinery being so far this yuar  169.8 per ton.     That difference was explained by the fact that a great deal of,the imported machinery consisted of specialised and costly articles, but it was certainly correct to say that a considerable amount of that class of machinery could be made in this country.As to the outlook for 1929, Sir Ernest had used the expression &quot;restrained optimism&quot; a year ago, and he thought those were exactly the right words to use to-day.     We oould look forward, he thought, to a continuance of industrial peace in engineering.     That was a very important point, and if the load factor could only be increased in the works, we could look forward to a better year.THE PRESIDENT asked if Sir 3. Petter oould give some more information as to the home trade and figures of production.SIR ERNEST PETTER replied that it was practically impossible to get any statistics of the home trade.     He did not think any great expansion in the home trade could be looked for until the home industrial conditions generally got better.ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.SIR PHILIP NASH wrote: -&quot;There is nothing particular to report in the electrical industry since I reported a month ago, but the  &apos; feeling I had then as to the future is confirmed, and perhaps stronger than when I was last at the Advisory Council!1COTTON.SIR KENNETH STEWART reported that the past month had, on the whole, been quite normal for the time of the year for cotton goods.     For the Eastern markets there had been a broadening enquiry which had been quite encouraging and seemed19ENGINEERING (CONVD.)
COTTON., (, CONTD) .to indicate that exports for the first few months of 19S9 would he fairly good.      As regards&apos;other parts of    the world there was nothing muoh to relate;    business was generally keeping up and proceeding in accordance with expectations. It was very much as it had bsen for the last three years or so, and the total exports for last year would be much &quot;the same as for the last two years.There was fairly general activity all over the East. China was, of course, always an important market,  and the tariff treaty signed with Great Britain was of great moment. China wa;s ordinarily our second biggest customer for cotton exports.     It lost its place last year to Australia, but was baok this year to its position as the next bigg&amp;st market to India.Our exports of cotton goods had amounted to 6/7,000;000,000 yards per annum before the war and to about 4,000,000,000 yards per annum in the last few years.    &apos; A considerable portion of the difference had been taken from us by the Japanese.      As the Council were aware, Lancashire had taken steps to meet this change and hoped in course of time to be in a position to-face those who had intruded into&apos; a trade she once considered to&quot;be her ewru .A-S, a s^art&quot;,-a committee of all branches of the trade had beenformed, called the Joint Committee of Cotton Trade Organisations, to discuss, the problem, and they were beginning to&apos; come to some conclusions.     One of the steps which were soon found to be absolutely necessary was some sort of consolidation of the mills spinning coarse counts.      A very able report had been issued, and a practical result might take shape in.the near future.     Some such reconstruction on a large scale was required, as might be judged from the fact that the &quot;Manchester Guardian&quot; had been able to give a list of 207 companies with an approximate paid-up capital of nearly  45,000,000, which had paid out in dividends a total of under  200,000&apos;.      V/hat the losses were of those who had not paid dividends it was hard to tell, but they were estimated at&apos;-, not less than an average of  5.000 apiece.     Not more than half-a-dozen reconstructed companies spinning American cotton paid any dividend at all.     Any re-organisation would have as its object not only the financial re-conditioning of trading concerns, but the recovery of trade lost to foreign competitors.     One of the great causes of the loss of Lancashire trade had been that these mills were in such a financial mess that they had got to buy their cotton on terms on which people in.a financial mess had to buy their   raw material, and they were in no position to organise the selling end in a proper way.     The aim would be both to put them in a position to buy their raw material on advantageous terms and to make proper arrangements, for selling their products.     It did not follow in the least that a re-organis-ation was immediately going to send up prices.WOOL.MR. AYKROYD observed that he had not much new to report since the last meeting of the Council, beoause the mills had only run about a fortnight.     Most of them were olosed ten days.     The markets abroad were closed, and to some extent things were in a state of waiting.
rOOL  (CONTD. ).The eleven months figures of our net imports and exports in woollen and worsted yarns, and woollen and worsted tissues were of interest.    In the whole year 1927 our net imports of woollen and worsted yarns were 17,700,000 lbs, and our exports were 51,900,000 lbs.    Our exports were, therefore, three times as much as our net imports.    For the eleven month.3 of 1928 our net imports were 16,300,000 lbs, and our exports were 45,600 ,&apos;000 lbs.    If during the month of December we had kept up the average of the other months it would be found that we had exported slightly less than in 1927 and imported about the same.    With regard to woollen and worsted tissues, in the whole of 1927 our net imports were 35,600,000 square yards and our exports were nearly 171,000,000 square yards.    For the eleven months of 1928 our net imports were 36,300,000 square yards and our exports were 158,000,000 square yards.    This showed that we were maintaining our ground in the export of our manufactured goods, though the imports were at a slightly higher level.    Mr. Aykroyd drew attention to the increase in our exports of woollen and worsted tissues to South America.     He had a business out there, and the figures that he had received by cable on the previous day showed that they had recently done more business there than at any time for the last eight or ten years.Regarding the conditions and prospects of trade generally, in the case of fine goods, that is the merino goods, business was moderately good and firms were fairly well employed. Price3 of raw materials in these commodities had fallen 66., per lb., but in the medium and &quot;the low qualities, they were ^-d a lb.  higher than twelve months ago.   That trade&apos; was exceedingly bad, and there was a good deal of unemployment. It could be concluded from that that, If an easier basis of values could be reached, business would increase.HO o 13RY; BOOT 3 AMD SH053.MR. WALKER observed that Leicester was possibly more fortunate than many towns, owing to the fact that it was not dependent upon one trade.    It had hosiery and boots;    there were about 300 hosiery firms, about 250 boot firms and about 200 other firms.    The total population of Leicester was, roughly, 250,000, with an insured population of&quot; about 110,000 - 65,000 males and 45,000 females.   Out of that insured population the highest figure of unemployment last year was 4,500, and the lowest point reached was 2,300.    But in addition a great deal of unsystematic short-time had been worked last year.    In August probably quite 10,000 people were out of full employment, and for the whole of last year in the staple trades, on an average, not more than three-quarter time was worked.With regard to future prospects, merely judged by unemployment figures,  the position would be bad, because there was double the amount of unemployment in Leicester now than there had been this time last year.    This was probably due to the fact that, owing to shortage of money and the position of the country generally, people were buying a cheaper type
CONFIDENTIAL. HOSIERY; BOOTS AND SHOES. ( CONTD. )of merchandi se, and unfortunately that cheaper type came from abroad, -wand British manufacturers could not compete.   However, compared with six months ago prospects were probably better, -distinctly better aa regards boot manufacture, which had gone through a very bad period;    and no doubt for hosiery also for which 1928 had been a very disappointing year.CHEMICALS,MR. HILL stated that the state of the Industry ha.d been quite fair both as regards volume and price, and unchanged from that of preceding, months.    Taking the eleven months ended November, the Board, of Trade Returns showed an increase since last year in exports of British manufactured chemicals of  2,000,000, but probably the actual volume -was greater than would be indicated by those figures, if falling prices were taken into account.   As far as home trade was concerned, during the period January to November there had clearly been an actual improvement, though it had /been rather slow and not.very obvious.   The overseas chemical trade finished the year- on&apos;the same advanced level ^as had been noted several months in succes si on.A, more comprehensive ,summary of the overseas trade position for the eleven months could be given i^ttllied products such as soap, basis slag, superphosphates and so on were included with the ^recognised chemicals, drugs, dyes and colours. Taking the statistics for the eleven months there was a balance of home-manufactured exports over retained Imports of  14,000,000 in 1928, which compared with  12,000,000&apos; for the eleven months of 1927, and with  11,000,000 for the same period in 1926.    If we considered that the chemical industry during the year had had to cope with depression in the chemical-consuming industries, with the marked exception of the artificial silk industry, the results appeared not to be too bad, and the outlook for 19-29 was distinctly hopeful.ROBBER.MR. JOHNSTON wrote:-&quot;The rubber manufacturing industry has, generally speaking, finished up the year satisfactorily.    The tyre section has been the least favourable branch of the industry, due largely to the expectation of a price reduction announcement on the part of a foreign controlled British factory, and partly owing to the usual seasonal slackness.   At the  same time most factories have continued production at about the normal rate and there has been little or no unemployment, although goods made have been largely for stock.    In the footwear branch of the industry great activity has prevailed   and overtime has been worked in   many departments.   This section of the industry appears to be steadiLy progressing and is in a healthy position.    Employment has been consistently good during the year and there has been practically no seasonal lull.
CONFIDENTIAL. RUBBER (CONTD. )&quot;The general rubber trade has been a little uneven, certain sections having been very active and others quiet, but on the whole the situation has been fully as satisfactory as previous years.    There has been little or no unemployment. Export trade has been fairly good, although exports to Australia and the East are still quiet, but trade with Continental countries is steadily improving.&quot;The general situation of the rubber manufacturing industry may be regarded as satisfactory.&quot;EFFECT OF NEW DUTIES.MR. WALKER, replying to a question he had been asked by Sir Ernest Fetter, referred to the results of the duty on silk goods.    Certainly there had been no increase in price, but on the contrary silk stockings were cheaper now than they were before the introduction of the duty.    There was quite sufficient competition in this country to fight for whatever trade there was.    In 1925.(the year in which the duty was imposed) the Imports of silk and articicial silk-stockings were 1,600,000 dozen pairs.    By 1927 the imports had dropped to a figure of 751,000 dozen pairs.    At the same time it was Interesting to note that the exports had in the same period practically doubled; they had risen from 558,000 dozen pairs in 1925 to 900,000 dozen pairs in 1927, and, as far as Leicester was concerned,  that was undoubtedly a most promising situation. Manufacturers stated definitely that, had. it not have been for the imposition of these duties, there, would have been practically no artificial silk trade worth speaking of.SIR E. FETTER mentioned the striking improvement which had taken place  in the wrought enamelled hollow-ware trade during the five months since June that it had had the benefit of safeguarding.    It had been stated in the House of Commons that the foreign manufacturers were increasing their prices 35 per cent, all-round as the result of that safeguarding. As a matter of fact, for the five months ending November the price of imported wrought iron hollow-ware had dropped  2 per ton, and the importation had dropped very considerably in amount.    On the ether hand, there had been a record exporta-tion for the five months, and the price of the exported British hollow-ware had dropped by  9 a ton.    Sir E. Petter promised to   supply the figures from which he had quoted, with information as to their source.GENERAL TRADE.SIR GILBERT VYLE observed that the information he had been able to gather seemed certainly more optimistic that it had been for some time.   We had the same1 high hopes this time last year, and those had not been fulfilled; but the same feeling of optimism, though perhaps a little more restrained, was present now.
GENERALTPA.DE   (CONTD.)As far as the Midlands went, there was certainly some substance for it.    In the Coventry district there had been a very marked improvement in the motor trade during the past three months, and it was said that the year was opening with a cheerful prospect and a good volume of work assured to the factories for some time ahead.    This applied also to aircraft, air engines, etc.    There had been some reduction in the numbers wholly unemployed and a substantial reduction in those partially employed.    In the Birmingham district a good deal of work was being quietly done.    Perhaps the diversity of trades prevented things being so bad. there as they had been in some other districts.Generally, as he had said, a more hopeful tone was being taken, though there was very little substance in it if one came to examine  it closely, except In a few places like Coventry.   Elsewhere people were living from hand t.o mouth, and this created a certain amount of anxiety, and nervousness about taking risks for the future.LORD EBBISHAM said that the past few weeks had seen a perceptible brightening in the industrial outlook.    There had been definite signs of a revival in activity in several of the major Industries, a revival which appeared to be due to some-thing more than purely seasonal causes.    In particular, mention might be made of the iron and stee]  Industry, coal, shipbuilding, and various important groups of the engineering trade.    In the textile trades also a feeling of greater hope-fulness was apparent,&apos;though- the wool trade had. suffered &quot;from the recent temporary unsettlement of raw material prices.Reports received from the principal foreign markets during the month had been better than for some time past, and the recently concluded commercial treaty with China should mean the beginning of a brighter era in the Far East.    The November returns of our own country1s foreign trade, although not so good as those for the corresponding month of the previous year, had indicated that the improvement recorded in the preceding month was maintained.Generally speaking, the reports from the coal districts indicated that there had been an Increase in activity during the past month,  this riKvement being mainly due to the necessity of completing contracts in hand before the Christmas holidays.    The, conditions in iron   and steel appeared to be unchanged up to the holidays; there was a slight improvement in shipbuilding; a short period of seasonal activity had been experienced in hardware and cutlery; reports from Northampton stated that during the past few weeks boot and shoe manufac-turers were more active than they had been for some time past; raw cotton markets had been slightly firmer during the past month;    raw wool prices continued to be  irregular during December with no definite indication as to the immediate outlook.
C 0335*1 DE3STTIAL.GENERAL TRAPS (CONTD.)With regard to Mr. Holland Martin&apos;s remarks as to the poor clearances in the month of December (see section on Banking), it might be that an improvement in business would not show itself in the bankers&apos; figures until a month or two later. Mr. Holland Martin agreed;    and Lord Ehbisham repeated that the indications received by the federation of British Industries tended to show that November and December were fairly satisfac.-tory from a trading point of view.      The feeling of hopefulness for future months seemed to be based on the idea that orders were more noticeable and in hand.lilt. MITCHELL had a report from Hull in which it was noted that the demand for cattle feeding cakes had been disappointing, the sale of oils good, with a lower level of prices, the home trade in paint quiet, but the export trade better.    Imports of cereals were about the average, fruit imports satisfactory. As regards Nottingham, there was not much improvement in the trade in underwear.     Business in lace in the home market was small, but the high quality and artistic merit of Nottingham goods had again been recognised by overseas buyers, with a consequent increase in the number of orders.      Generally, there was a feeling of optimism throughout this trade, for which there was much justification.     In Liverpool, tanners were firm in their prices, but buyers were coming along very slowly and boot manufacturers continued to complain that orders were on a small scale;    the hide market remained firm, but nearly all the buying at present came from America and the Continent. There was a hopeful feeling that this trade was approaching a more satisfactory condition.     Business in timber during December had been generally quiet.      The wool market had displayed a very firm tone.Retail Trade.SIR WOODMAN BURBIDGE was glad to be able to report that trade for the month  of December in London and the suburbs showed an increase over the corresponding month last year.     The dis-tributing houses repnrtec an increase of from 2 per cent to 8 per cent, which was very good, considering that trade must have been affected by the illness of the Zing.     If times had been normal, the Christmas trade would have shown a very big increase. The furnishing,  fashion and food departments all showed satisfac-tory increases, but the men&apos;s goods were   not as satisfactory as the other sections.      Reports   from the North of England showed that they had been able to hold their own,  except in the mining areas, where trade showed a decrease.     Many houses reported that-the volume of business had been greater, but the bills were smaller.     Trade in the south-west of England showed a little improvement.     The retail stores selling Christmas goods showed an improvement, but the furnishing sections of the different houses showed a decline.With regard to the present year the feeling was fairly optimistic, as trade for 1928 did not come up to expectations. It had shown an increase, but not as much as had been expected.
GENERAL TRADE ,(contd.).Retail Trade (Contd. )The second six months had shown an improvement over the first six months, and therefore they were of opinion that 1929 would he a fairly good year, especially in the better-olass trade, as there was       doubt that the spending power of the public had increased.      A great deal would depend on the date of the general election, and, for the.retail trade generally, it would be more advantageous t^ have it in September than at any other time.Co-operative Wholesale Society.MR. HAYHURST wrote:-&quot;The  .nearness of the Council meeting to the close of the month of December prevents me from stating with any degree of correctness the actual state of our &quot;business for the past month, in comparison &quot;with the month of December, 1927, but I can say that, up to the second portion of the month (for which figures are available), we show substantial progress in every way,, as compared with 1927.     The yearTs trading .has been eminently satisfactory, and when final figures are published, we shall record a very big inorease.     It is* however,&apos; regrettable that two sections of the country, viz., the North East Coast and South Wales, are still in a very poor condition, and whilst, in the unfortunate circumstances obtaining, we have every reason to be pleased with the -business we have done in those particular areas, there is       doubt that a general improvement in the general industrial conditions there would immediately find its reflection in increased sales by our Depots, etc, operating in those districts.&quot;Grocery and Provisions.     The exceedingly brisk demand for Danish butter consequent - upon the approach of Christmas, and also an additional demand from the Continent, hardened the market somewhat, but after the demand for Christmas had been met the market took an easier turn.     Australian and Sew Zealand supplies have been on the short side, with a firm market tendency.      Sugar markets have remained steady during the past week, with prices on the quiet side.     Flour remains practically unchanged.     Wheat rather firmer;    all round a holiday oharacter has remained.     Further firm prioes have held for oommon and medium descriptions of tea, and fine tea has been in request at steady rates.     Russia seemingly has not been buying tea this last year to the same extent as in 1927, but during these last weeks, purchases in Calcutta and in Colombo have been known to be made for Russia.     At the close of the year there is still a weight of tea not sold on hand at home, in excess of twelve months earlier..     The first oost of West African raw cocoa is round about 46&apos;/- f.o.b. for the first quality.     The trouble will be, if prioes do not beoome firmer, that the farmers in West Africa will refuse their crops and may call a stoppage.     At Christmas the sales of chocolata were exceptional and were in advance of 1927&quot;.
GENERAL TRADE IN ..SGOTLAND.MR. MITCHELL reported that there was a rather more hopeful feeling in the ooal trade of Scotland, with an increase in output in December, due partly, no doubt, to seasonal demand, and a small increase in the number employed. Tie output was still somewhat less than in March, when the Owners&apos;  scheme came into operation.    The export trade had recovered somewhat, the amount shipped being considerably in excess of the figures for March, and the prices showing some improvement.   The home consumption was disappointing, being lower than in March.More iron furnaces had been put out of blast, the demand for Scots pig-iron being very poor.   Very little foreign pig-iron was being imported, but large quantities were coming in from the English districts.    The steel works had fared rather better in December than in november and prospects are more favourable for the winter than had been anticipated 3ome months ago, owing to the shipbuilding orders which had been placed.    As was well known, quite a number of shipbuilding orders had been placed during the last two months.BANKING.MR. HOLLAND MARTIN considered that there, was certainly, speaking generally, a slightly more hopeful feeling about. It was difficult to oee why this should be so.    Perhaps it was reflected from the order books, but the orders that had been received did not seem generally to be more than for a month or so ahead.The provincial clearings for the past month, indeed, the whole of the clearings, showed how depressed the month of December had been.    Total clearings were down 6 per cent for the month of December, and the country clearings in London were slightly down, by .3 per cent.    The provincial clearings were, in every single case, down with the exception of those at Newcastle.    Newcastle showed an extraordinary rise, being no less than 29 per cent over the figures of 1927.    It was agreed by the banks that this rise had nothing to do with the general trade position of Newcastle, but was probably connected -with the financial mergers being carried through  . there.    There was no particular improvement in trade on Tyneside, which, of course, had been very -depressed.During the year the provincial clearings had rarely shown increases.    Birmingham had an Increase of 3.5 per cent, Bristol one of 3.1 per cent, Leicester of 1.8 per cent, and Nottingham a slight increase also.    In those particular places there accordingly appeared to be a slight stirring of business, but, speaking generally, for the month of December the figures had been very poor.
SHIPPING.MR. ALEXANDER SHAW mentioned that no later figures of the tonnage under construction, tonnage launched and tonnage -commenced, were yet available than those for the quarter ended 30th September, which he had previously given to the Council&quot;.   There had been a slight upward movement In freights.. Taking 1930 as 100, the index in November, 1923, was 29.17 in comparison with 27.27 in October.    Up till October every month during 1928 had had a lov/er freight figure than the corresponding month in 1927, and, though there had been this slight and very welcome increase during November, those who had been examining the matter at the Ghamber of Shipping were not at all sure that the rise would be maintained. Freightrs might very well fall back again; it depended on the general state of trade.During the month of November alone orders for sixty-four vessels of ^38,000 tons dead weight were placed on the Clyde, Wear and Tyne.    While the slight improvement in freights was one of the causes of this building activity-, there were other considerations which had really more to do with it, technical reasons which would operate increasingly from now during the next year or two.    It was not merely the fact that tonnage was becoming worn out and had to be replaced, if companies were to maintain their services at sea, but there had been very substantial technical advances which shipowners were beginning to look very carefully into. Among these was the pulverised coal question (see also the section on Coal).Along with that there were modifications in boilers, and, although shipowners were rather conservative and wanted to make quite sure before they launched into heavy expense, they were becoming increasingly aware of the advantage of a higher pressure of steam.    With the higher pressure of steam which could be obtained by modified boilers and pulverised coal, a different sort of machinery was required.   Turbines would have to be used, and a type of vessel would be built in a year or t?/o which would very largely render the ordinary reoiprocating-engined vessel obsolete.RAILWAY TRAFFIC.SIR JOSIAH STAMP reported that in the merchandise and livestock receipts of the four railway groups.the comparison of the four weeks ended 23rd December, 1928, with the corresponding period in 1927 showed an appreciably   &quot;better position than did the comparison between the 51 weeks in those years.    The 51 weeks in 1028 were down by just over 6 per cent compared with 1927, whereas the four weeks  vere down by only 4f- per cent, despite the faot that the decrease in the case of the L.N.E.R. group alone was nearly 7$ per cent.    With regard to coal and coke, the improvement in, the later period of the year was very striking, because for 51 weeks there was a decrease of 8.3 per cent in 1928 compared with 1927, while for the four weeks the decrease was only 2.6 per cent on the previous year.
RAILWAY TRAFFIC (CONTD.)In the case of merchandise the receipts for the t7o years were not strictly comparable, owing to changes in the classifications.      Calculations he had made for his Company indicated that the work was now being done at a charge to the trader of about 1-g- to 1^/3  per cent less than on the previous scale of rates, so that the decreases in receipts which he had quoted did not quite accurately measure the decreases in volume of merchandise carried. There was a change in the amount charged, partly in the section and partly in the through mileage and shortest routes, which had come into force since the 1st January, 1928, and a portion of that 6 per cent decrease over the 51 weeks was due not to decreased volume, but to an actual change of conditions.    The only way to obtain strictly comparable figures was to take specimen periods and apply to the 1928 figures the conditions and charges of the previous year and bring them to a common basis in that way.It was interesting to note with regard to the merchandise traffic, so far as his own Company was concerned, that though there had been a certain decrease in tonnage of iu.erchana.ise as a whole, the heavy trades more than accounted for the total decrease, and in the lighter goods - the general trade - there had actually been an improvement.    Despite the fact that there were a much larger number of lorries on the road, there had been an improvement in the railway companies&apos;  tonnage in all trade-s other than the heavy ones.    The heavy traffics alone accounted for their tonnage decrease.The passenger train receipts were down by 2 per cent for the 51 weeks and 4 per cent for the four weeks.    That was&quot; to some extent a question of date and Christmas traffic, but there was also a definite falling away.    The passenger receipts were much more down in the textile and other depressed areas than anywhere else, but the major cause of the decrease was the increased road competition from private cars and buses.    Private cars were probably the more serious factor in 1938, particularly in the summer months.   The large inorease in the number of small cars had taken away the normal holiday receipts.The receipts for all traffics were down 4.8 per cent, for the 51 weeks and 3.9 per cent for the four weeks.    Ther was just that indication that the position was slightly better, but he could not say how long it ;.vas going to hold. In shipbuilding the outlook was perhaps brighter, but for *fts rest his&apos;reports were not so optimistic as acme of those made to the Council.    The de-rating scheme had not been in force sufficiently long to draw a definite conclusion as to its effects.Sir Josiah handed in the following table of traffic receipts from which he had quoted:-
Four Weeks ended 23rd December, 1928.Passenger Train Receipts.L.M.So  o.L.2T.J3. .. G. W.SouthernTotal...........Merchandise, Other Minerals and Live Stock.j )L.M.S.  ..G.W. ____SouthernTotalCoal and Coke.L.M.S.  ..G. W.     ... aSouthernTotalTotal Traffic Receipts -Passenger and Freight. L.M.S.....................L.H.E...........:.........G. W.......................Southern..................?otalFifty-one Weeks ended 23rd December. 1928.1928.	1927&quot;.	Decrease.		1928.     !	1927.    1	Decrease.	Thousand  &apos;s. i				T	houeand  * s.	1	%2,051	2,164	113	5.2	29.211	29,891	680	3.31     1,368	1,422	54	3.8	19,200	19,848	648	3.3909	962	53	5.5	12,766	13,029	263	2^1,194	1,202	8	0.7      i	16.T41	16,816	75	0*55,522	5.750	228	4.0	77,918	79,584	1,666	2.1! i -f 1 i 2,358	2,420	62	2.6	29,447	31,552	2,105	6,71,707	1,850	143	7.7	21,631	22,924	1,293	5.6864	897	33	3.7	11,146	11,682	536	4.6317	330	13	4.0	4,054	4,417	363	8.25,246	5,497	251	4.6	66,278	70,575	4,297	6.1-1,221	1,263	42	3.3	13,207	14,612	1,405	9.61,090	1,118	28	2.5	12,385	13,136	751	6.7499	495	4*	0.8*	5,792	6,366	574	9.0120	133	13	9.8	1,428	1,671	243	14.52,930	3,009	79	2.6	32.818	35,785	2.973	8.35,630	5,847	217	3.7	71,865	76,055	4,190	1 i. 5.54,165	4,390	225	5.1	53,216	55,908	2,692	4.82,272	2,354	82	3.5	29,704	31,t77	1,373	4.41,630	1,664	34	2.0	22,223	22,903	680	3.013,697	-14,255	558	3.9	177,008	185,943	-i   8,935	4.8  ,*   Increase.
EMPLOYMENT.MR. PHILLIPS stated that there had been the usual decrease in the unemployment figures in the weeks immediately before Christmas.    The last figure available was that for 17th December, and the total was then lower by 124,000 than on 26th November. Almost the whole of this decrease had been in the number temporarily stopped, and more than half the decrease occurred in the North of England, while Scotland showed little change. The next figure would be that for 31st December, and It would probably show a large increase over 17th December.    The usual figures of insured persons in employment in each month of the year would be handed in.    The drop in December In the figures of the unemployed should be discounted to some extent, because in November the figure was taken at the end of the month, when firms had probably arranged in many cases that the proportion of their people on short time should be large; whereas on 17th December the miners In the five counties coal scheme, for instance, were very likely largely kept at work.    It would give a clearer comparison if in future the table handed in gave an average figure of employment for the month, instead of one relating to a single day on the month.   Mr, Phillips thought that this change could be made.TABLE HANDED IN BY MR. PHILLIPS. Monthly Statistics of insured persons aged 16 to 64 in employment.-pate .I Estimated j number of insured persons.,1.      1Mq: -;11Jan. . f KFeb.. I liMar-. . iBApr&quot; &apos; \ I May. . jJ une.! July. ; Aug..: [Sept.; fOc t..j Nov..I Dec . . ! _L2.Number of insured persons unemployed (including two months file of lodged books ).3 .Difference be Ween Columns 2 and 3 (to nearest hundred ).4.Estimated number ofInsured persons in employment after deducting from Col.4. 3% per cent, of the numbers in Col2 to allow for sickness&quot;^ and other unrecorded non-employ-men t, exclusive of temporary holidaysInc lud ing persons directly involved In trade disputes .Exclud ing persons d irectly involved in trade disputes. 6.11,590,000 11,599,000 11,608,000 11,617,000 11,626,000 11,629,000 11,636,000 11,643,000 11,650,000 11,658,000 11,666,000 11,674,000	1,227,435  .;	10,362	,600	1,195,131   i	10,403	,900., . t	1,095,858   j	10,512	,100. :	1,093,158   i	10,523	,800	1,123,989   1	10,502	,000	1,225,150   &apos;	10,403	,900t !	1,322,560   1	10,313	,400t i	1,324,311   i	10,318	,7.00i	1,304,390   i	10,345	,600f !	1,356,037   !	10,302	,000f i	1,407,752   !	10,258	,500i* !	1,288,800 i- j	10,385	,2009,957 i   9,997 10,105 10,117 10,095 9,996 I  9,905 i  9-, 911 1  9,937 i  9,a94 i  9,850 !  9,976,000 , 9.00 ,800 ,200 ,100 ,800 ,100 ,200 ,800 ,000 ,200 ,1009,954, 9,992, .10,100, 10,116, 10,092, 9,975, 9,905, 9,910., 9.934, 9^,892, 9,847, 9,974,000 900 800 200 100 300 100 200 800 000 200 100*The sickness rate has been taken at an e not been possible to allow for Seasona f Pr ov is i ona 1 f i gure .estimated annual mean; it has 1 Variation.-0.9-
EMPLOYMENT.MR. PHILLIPS stated that there had been the usual decrease In the unemployment figures in the weeks immediately before Christmas.    The last figure available was that for 17th December, and the total was then lower by 124,000 than on 26th November. Almost the whole of this decrease had been in the number temporarily stopped, and more than half the decrease occurred in the North of England, while Scotland showed little change. The next figure would be that for 31st December, and It would probably show a large increase over 17th December.    The usual figures of insured persons In employment in each month of the year would be handed in.    The drop in December in the figures of the unemployed should be discounted to some extent, because in November the figure was taken at the end of the month, when firms had probably arranged in many cases that the proportion of their people on short time should, be large ; whereas on 17th December the miners In the five counties coal scheme, for instance, were very likely largely kept at work.    It would give a clearer comparison if in future the table handed in gave an average figure of employment for the month, instead of one relating to a single day on the month.   Mr, Phillips thought that this change could be made.TABLE HANDED IN BY MR. PHILLIPS. Monthly Statistics of insured persons aged 16 to 64 in employment.Estimated number of Insured persons In employment after dedticting from Col.4. 3% per cent, of the numbers in Col2 to allow for sickness&quot;&quot; and other unrecorded non-employ-men t, exclusive of temporary holidayst)a ze .I Estimated i number of insured persons.2.Number of insured persons unemployed (inc lud ing two months file of lodged books).3 .Difference be tween Columns 2 and 3 (to nearest hundred ).4.inc lud ing persons directly involved In trade disputes , 5 .11,590,000 11,599,000 11,608,000 11,617,000 11,626,000 11,629,000 11,636,000 11,643,000 11,650,000 11,658,000 11,666,000 11,674,000i  !T !1,227 1,195 1,095 1,093 1,123 1,225 1,322 1,324 1,304 1,356 1,407 1,288,435 ,131 ,858 ,158 ,989 ,150 ,560 ,311 ,390 ,037 ,752 ,800 f10,362 10,403 10,512 10,523 10,502 10,403 10,313 10,318 10,345 10,302 10,258 10,385,600 I,900&apos;,100&apos;,800,000,900,400!,7,00,600,000,500,2009,957 9,997 10,105 10,117 10,095 9,996 9,906 9&quot;, 911 9,937 9,894 9,850 9,976Exclud ing persons d irectly involved In trade disputes.,000 , 9,00 ,300 ,200 ,100 ,800 ,100 ,200 ,800 ,000 ,200 ,1009,954,000 9,992,900 .10,100,800 10,116,200 10,092,100 9,975,800 9,905,100 9,910-,200 9/934,800 9,892,000 9,847,200 9,974,100-&quot;-The sickness rate has been taken at an estimated annual meannot been possible to allow for Seasonal Variation. iPr ovis i ona1 f i gure,it has
G ON FID ENTIAL.AD3TRALIAN TRADE.SIR FREDERICK YOUNG reported that at the close of 1928 the outlook in Australia appeared to be distinctly better than it had been at the end of the preceding year.    From 1st  July to 30th November 2,150,000 bales of wool had been received in store, and of these nearly 1 .,000,000 had been sold.   At the sales in December competition had been keen and sustained, the principal buyers being the United Kingdom, the Continent, and Japan.    Pastoral conditions generally had improved, with useful rains, but important areas in Queensland were still suffering from want of rain, - some localities had done so for three and even four years consecutively.The 19 27-,s8 wheat season ended on 30th November, the total exports of wheat and flour being, in round figures, 51,000,000 bushels and 442,000 tons respectively, compared with 84,000,000 bushels and 487,000 tons respectively for the previous year.    This season&apos;s wheat harvesting was in full swing in New South Wales, and was progressing In the other States with generally good quality and satisfactory yields. The exports of wheat and relative products should be substantially in excess of last year, but of course prices were not quite    so favourable.A market for Australian wheat had developed in India, and at the present moment was also developing in Shanghai, which apparently offered prices markedly above those of London.General trade in the Commonwealth was satisfactory. Imports from July to October had amounted to  47,000 ,,000 compared with  55,000,000 for the same period in the previous year, and exports to  35,000,000 compared with  40,000,000. Bank clearances at all capital cities up to 26th November last, amounted to  2,000,000,000 odd compared with a slightly   larger sum for the previous year.The conference between representatives of employers and employed, reported at the last meeting of the Advisory Council, had opened auspiciously and promised to lead to more peaceful conditions and a better understanding in industrial affairs. It was tending to follow somewhat on the lines of similar conferences in this country.INDIAN TRADE.MR. LINDSAY explained that he had not yet received the final figures for Indian Trade in 1928, but those he had were close enough to show the general trend.   The lesson from these figures was that the return to normal trade was proceeding steadily in India,    The Imports of merchandise were. approximate-ly  190,000,000 and the exports  255,000,000.    The imports of gold and silver were  27,000,000, leaving a net balance of trade in favour of India of  39,000,000.    A comparison with pre-war figures would show the advance which had been made. Pre-war India&apos;s imports of merchandise were on the average about  100,000,000 a year, and the exports about  150r000,000 a year.&apos;    The net imports of gold and. silver were about
INDIAN TRADE ( CONTD. ) 25 .,000^,000 and the balance of trade in favour oi  India was about  28,000,000.    An interesting fact in connection with the pre-war figures was   that the net balance of trade at  23 5,000,000 just about corresponded to the net annual official remittances to this country to pay for various services of debts, pensions, and so on,    The visible trade therefore just balanced and, with regard to the invisible Items, it could be assumed that on the average the amounts due to foreign countries In repayment of debts and in payment of Interest must have corresponded roughly to the amounts re-invested in India-,    By 1928 the total imports had approximately  doubled, the exports had not quite doubled and the balance of trade had risen in India&apos;s favour from  28,000,000 pre-war to  39,000,000 today.    Here again the interesting feature was that that balance corresponded very closely to the annual remittances to the India Office, and this correspondence, occurring in 1928 almost for the first time, was one more sign of the return to normal trade conditions In India.H.M.  Senior.Trade Commissioner, in his last Report, had stated that the British share in India&apos;s import trade, which was 47.7 per cent, in 1926-27 had been maintained in 1927-28, and he anticipated a ri se in that percentage during 1928- 29.THE PRESIDENT observed that Mr. Ainscough had emphasised the importance of British exporters having effective local representation.MR. LINDSAY agreed that that question was very important Indeed,-,    Many firms here stated that they were not getting a proportional share in the increase in India!s trade, owing to so much trade going past the established firms straight to the   bazaars.    This was a natural development during normal conditions, but might give rise to difficulties during a crisisSOUTH&apos;AMERICAN TRADE.MR. HOSE wrote to the following effect:-The latest returns of Argentine foreign trade show similar tendencies to those which characterised the figures for the earlier months of 1928, that is to say, an increase in the total value of exports has been accompanied by a consider-able expansion in that of imports, resulting in a small reduction in the export surplus of merchandise.     Reports of harvesting in Argentina continue satisfactory, the fine cereals  are in good condition, and threshing is becoming general.       The exportable surpluses of wheat and lin3eed have been recently estimated at over 5,000,000 and over 2,000,000 tons, respectively, while the amount of oats likely to become available for shipment is placed at double that of a year ago.      Harvesting of the maize is not due to take place until after February, but the growing crop is stated to be in good condition.     The areas in which the wheat has been destroyed by hail are being ploughed for maize.      So soon as the movement of the crop reaches its maximum, there should bo a general expansion in the volume of business, but for the time being commercial conditions remain somewhat quiot.
SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE (CONTD.)In general,  it appears probable that extensions of the transport systems may be definitely undertaken in many directions in the early future, and that in particular there may be considerable orders forthcoming for the supply of railway materials of all kinds, for the State Railways, and road-making machinery.    Taking all circumstances into * consideration, the outlook for trade in Argentina during 1039 is extremely satisfactory, in view of the definite re-linking of the currency to the gold standard in August, 1^37, the consolidation of the credit situation and the national finances, and the elimination of over-stocking.    Imports during 1928 showed healthy expansion, and it^behoves manu-facturers and exporters to study the present situation with more than usual care so that full advantage may be taken of the wider opportunities which appear likely to offer themselves.General business conditions in Chile during November last were maintained on the satisfactory basis ruling in October, while an improvement was noted in certain lines of merchandise which had previously been selling slo?/ly.    In fact, a slightly more optimistic tendency is still observable, and credit conditions show improvement.   The official returns of Chilean foreign trade for the first nine months of 1928 give the value of imports at the provisional total of 805,800,000 pesos, and that of exports at 1,397,100,000 pesos, showing an export surplus of 591,300,000 pesos,    ordinary revenue during the ten months ended October, 1938, totalled 743,972,080 pesos, while ordinary expenditure amounted to 719,481,218 pesos, resulting in a realised surplus of 34,490,862 pesos.    Daring the past year, several internal loans have been successfully floated in Chile.    Summarising Chilean conditions in 1938, there has been undoubted recovery, owing chiefly to the success of the Government in restoring equilibrium   in the national accounts and rehabilitating the nitrate of soda industry.    In addition, the production of copper in Chile - an. industry which has reached a stage second only in importance to that of the United States - continued to show extensive development, the output during 1928 having been some 30   per cent, greater than in the preceding year.    In regard to the outlook, prospects for the expansion of trade and for a further improvement in Chilean conditions generally appear more favourable than has been the case for two or three years past.Turning to Brazil, I regret to state that the commercial situation there during the past two months has been far from satisfactory.    Owing to restriction of credit by the Bank of Brazil, important Rio de Janeiro firms were reported to be in difficulties, while some failures occurred.    The effect was to spread a nervous tendency in the commercial markets in both Rio de Janeiro and Sao Paulo.   However, the situation has latterly shown improvement, and increased confidence is now observable.    In the Brazilian import markets, the chief consideration at the present time is the possibility of an early increase in the Customs duties on textile manufactures, and, although the general revision of the tariff which was originally contemplated has been postponed, definite consideration has been given to the
CONFIDENTIAL. SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE ( 00MID. )imposition of increases demanded by the local textile industries.    Normally, a period of 90 days would elapse between publication of the new duties and their enforcement, but this might be waived by legislative action.    I mentioned in my last report to the Council that any real recovery in Brazilian affairs would have to be preceded by measures to ensure a consistent financial policy and stable credit    conditions, and to inspire confidence by completing the legal stabilisation of the currency.In Peru a special committee will be appointed by the Government during 19 29 to study a new taxation system as well as the finances of the Republic in general.    It is understood that the work will be entrusted to Professor R. Murray Kaig, of Columbia University, whose appointment would follow closely on that of Mr.    F.  I. Kent, the United States expert who investigated Peruvian banking and currency problems during 1923.    By an agreement between the Peruvian Government and the Peruvian Corporation the latter has yielded its right to further revenue from the guano concession, and it is therefore probable that increased attention will be given in the future by the Administration to   this  source of revenue.    The general trade movement in Peru continues slow.    Approximately 80 per cent, of the cotton crop has already been sold, and in consequence the movement of sugar - which, however, is of secondary importance - is having more influence than usual.Commercial conditions in Colombia are making satisfactory progress.    In Guatemala,the harvesting of the coffee has been adversely affected to some extent by exceptionally wet weather, as a result of which the crop had to be gathered somewhat early.    There has, however, been no improvement in the volume of sales;    buyers generally are holding off and growers are anxious to dispose of stocks. There ha3 been some increase of confidence in the commercial situation of Ecuador, with a greater demand for credit on the part of the better-class firms;    the money rates are steady.    Supplies of coffee have been coming forward in good quantities, and the yield this season appears to have been one of the heaviest in the history of the    country.    Prices are firmly maintained and current quotations in oversea markets provide a fair margin of profit to exporters.    On the other hand, business in cocaa in the local markets remains quiet, and prices abroad show a tendency to decline.    The announcement that arrangements have been made for the payment forthwith of a further coupon of the Guayaquil and Quito Railway indebtedness has been well received, as indicating the good Intentions of the Ecuadorian Government to improve the credit standing of the country overseas.Business in Venezuela is quiet, but stocks of merchandise are low, and the general commercial situation may be considered sound.    Petroleum production continues at a high level, and there appears reason to believe that a revival in trade activity may be anticipated.In common with the other Central American countries, Salvador has been affected by heavy rain, which has caused damage in the coffee-growing areas, and the trade movement . is slow.
Latest Statist!gal Data. (Information received up to date of circulation oflLatest.A month earlier.m1927.Employment: Unemployed on Live Register (incopersons on &quot;short time receiving benefit).........Railway Receipts week ended -Goods Traffic (Gross).........Passenger Traffic (Gross).....Production: Coal output during week ended, Pig Iron output during month,, steel output during monthDecc31st. Wholly un-employed. Others....1,019,600 501,100970,52M380,279!878,420457,8831,520,700ls350f806!1,336,303Jano5th. itDec.29th. December.Crude i Price s: Whole sale Board of Trade Index No,(1913H 100): ;Food........................i December.Materials................ ...1Total.......................I      &quot;United Kingdom TradettNet Imports...................Exports (Domestic Produce).... Vessels laid up,in United Kingdom ports:British......................Foreign,.....*...............Shipping Freights: Chamber of Shipping Index No.(1920 * 100).................Postal Receipts - DailyAverage a*&apos;* 0...................Bank Clearings: Country Cheque and Provincial,week ended a.......,..........Percentages of Advances to Deposits (London Clearing Banks)........................New Capital Issues in Great Britain^(Midland Bank Statement): United Kingdom Purposes..... .Overseas Purposes............iotal.......Money Market:Bank Rate.......Market Rate 3 months1  BankBills.......................Discount (3 months1  treasury bills.)......................December, i?Oct.1st. . it1,668,800 1,250,300Tons. 2.025.000 &apos;540,400 683,100148.2132.7 130,392,372,572 60,394,329Net tons. 412,353 3,036November, ii29.17  .135,19 6  .Jan.5th...107,089,000November,.December.53.617,993,000 6,693.000 .2,023,800) 1,269,500Tons.4,C54 ..100 544.400 762^500148.5 132 0 2 137.996,022,789 63,766,502Net tons.  Juylst. 491,720 4,14627c27  . 138,855 .106,059,000 53.4 .16,961,000 11,009,0001,629,800(1. 1.. 280,200Tons. 3,240,.000 559,103   . 604,900151.0 134.5 140.4 .95, 098, 327 58,833,924Net tons.267,235 5,60427,75  .128,343  .110,973,000(19153.8 .13,615,000 12,747,00024,696,000!      27,970,000Jan, 11th si114^  4.5s,4.26d,4-l-?c  4.8s.4,07d.26,362,000192*8:4-i- - 45/l0/&quot;  4.4s.4,31d, &quot;&quot;Approximate weekly average for December, 1913. t Monthly average for 1913.)tt The figures for 1913 represent the external trade of the British Isles as a Unit trade of Great Britain and Northern Ireland with the Irish Free State is- includ *-* Telegraph and telephone receipts, Savings Bank, and Money and-Postal Order busin $ Excluding direct borrowings by the British Government for national purpose^, sha arising -from the capitalisation of reserve funds and undivided profits,  issues securities previously held in the United Kingdom,  shortrdatod bills sold in antj and loans by municipal and county authorities except in cases where there is a subscription.    The figures are based on the prices of issue.
Latest Statistical Data. I &quot;1 received up to date of circulation of Minutes)it.A month earlier.At corresponding date in -1927.1925.1913.1,019,600 &quot;501,100970,527380,2791878,420457,883016,987 (4th 534,719 (Jan,/26l1,520.,7001,350,8061,336,3031,251,7061,668,800 1,250,300Tons. 2,325.000 &apos;54O,400 683,100148.2 132.7 130.3192,372,572 160,394,329Ne t tons. 412,363 3,03629.17  .135,196  .107,089,00053.617,993,000 6,698.00024,696,000A 1 of4 a/0 45/lS/0 l 4.5s,4.26d. .2,023,800 1,269,500Tons.4,654,100 544.400 762^500148.5 132.2 137.9 .96,022,789 63,765,502Net tonsrl 491,720 4,14627c27  . 138,855 .106,059,000 53.4 .16,961,000 11.009,00027,970,0004-lfo 43/Sf;;  4.8s.4,07d, .1,629,800(1928)1 1,280,200      11Tons.3,240..000 559,10 3   . 604,900151.0 134.5 140.4 .95,098,327 58,833,924llet tons. 267,235 5,60427.75  .128,343  .110,973,000(1928J53.8 .1,888,900(1927) 1,308,800    &quot;Tons. 3,964,800 503,400 606.800163, 0 146,2 152.1 .119,631,436 65,768,661Net tons.556,567 17,79726.07  .120,649  .Nocomparable data, .961,000 858,900Tons, 5,720,000* 855,000t 638,600*Averages for ,1913 a 100. .61,387,105 43,327,674 .13,615*000 12.747,000107500,000( 1927)51.5 .12.270,000 13,132,000,Average for 1913a    23,40 No comparable data. .49,029,000Average for Oct,-Dec, 1913, (Economist z ) 3,452,100 11,953,20026,352,0001928:4i - 45/l6/o  4.4s.4.31d.24,402,00015,405,50043/lS^  4.3s.4.65d.5%1913. t Monthly avenge for 1913.frnal trade of the British Isles as a Unit; In the other figures shown the* tland with the Irish Free State 13- included as external trade. IBs Bank, and Money and Postal Order business are excluded, sh Government for national! purposes, shares Issued to vendors, allotments 3r-ve funds and undivided profits, issues for conversion or redemption of sd Kingdom,  short-dated, bills ,sold. in anticipation of long-term borrowings, critics except in cases where there is a specified limit to the total jti the prices of issue.
BOARD  OF  TRADE  ADVISORY  COUNCIL.Statistical Tables.TABLE A. GENERAL. New Capital Issues, Transport, Eaw Materials, Production, Employment, cfec Year 1927 and January-November, 1928.Part I. Actual Figures.			Monthly Averages.							Year 1928.						Items.	Unit of Measurement.	Jan.-	Apr-	July-	Oct.-	Jan.-	Apr-	July-									Mar.,	June,	Sept.,	Dec,	Mar.,	June,	Sept.,	June.	July.	Aug.	Sept.	Oct.	Nov.			1927.	1927.	1927.	1927.	1928.	1928.	1928,.						1.	New Capital Issues (Midland Bank State-ments)-															(a.) United Kingdom purposes	Thousand  &apos;s	17,828	16,470	7,203	17,179	18,486	20,595	12,406	25,405	24,115	5,529	7,575	29,715	16,961	(4.) Overseas purposes		9,820	9,113	6,852	20,439	15,968	12,489	9,807	15,967	17,705	984	10,731	10,884	11,0092.	Railways Freight Traffic 															(a.) Coal, Coke and Patent Fuel	1  Thousand J 1  ton miles 1	873,563	731,749	778,467	774,031	782,701	659,967	697,561	658,787	659,252	703,779	729,653			(4.) Other Minerals and General Mer-chandise		782,641	798,406	772,969	771,682	757,477	753,788	747,504	760,495	742,578	746,870	753,064		8.	Shipping-Entrances and Clearances with Cargoes in the Foreign Trade 															(a.) Entrances	\ Thousand f	4,634	5,108	5,425	5,029	4,497	5,136	5,316	5,288	5,438	5,352	5,158	5,630	4,804	(b.) Clearances	j    net tons \	4,982	5,360	5,657	5,168	5,036	5,354	5,643	5,699	5,491	5,972	5,466	5,721	5,4874.	Net Imports of Raw Materials 															(a.) Value as declared	Thousand  &apos;s	28,527*	21,395	20,322	23,328	25,301	21,301	19,265	19,376	19,994	19,871	17,931	19,876	24,545	(5.) Value at average prices of 1927 .	)*	30,600*	22,200	18,600	22,200	22,900	20,400	17,100						5.	Postal Receipts Average amount daily   ..	 &apos;s	119,386	122,013	121,657	139,006	125,699	124,852	125,427	124,578	126,354	121,518	128,409	138,855	135,1966.	Employment  &quot; (a.) Estimated   number   of   Insured															Workers in Employment	Thousands	9,857	10,094	10,079	10,038	10,022	10,070	9,918	9,997	9,906	9,911	9,938	9,894	9,850	(b.) Insured Workers Unemployed		1,242	1,029	1,067	1,130	1,173	1,147	1,317	1,225	1,323	1,324	1,304	1,356	1,408* The figures for January-March 1927 include an average of over  2 million in respect of coal and coke, imports of which in 192 7 were practically confined to these months. [18651] B
TABLE A. GENERAL/  (continued).Part II. Index Numbers. Monthly Average op 1927 ^100.					Monthly Averages.							Year 1928.       ,						Items.		-  Unit of Measurement.		Jan.-	Apr-	July-	Oct.-	Jan.-	Apr.-	July-											Mar.,	June,	Sept,	Dec,	Mar.,	June,	Sept.,	June.	July.	Aug.	Sept	Oct.	Nov.					1927.	1927.	1927.	1927.	1928.	1928.	1928.						1.	New Capital Issues (Midland Bank State-ments) 			-												-		(a.) United Kingdom purposes				121-5	112-3	49-1	117-1	126-0	140-4	84-6	173-2	164-4	37-7	51-6	202-6	115-6	(i.) Overseas purposes				85-0	78-9	59-3	176-9	138-2	108-1	84-9	138-2	153-2	8-5	92-9	94-2	95-32.	Railways Freight Traffic 																	(a.) Coal, Coke and Patent Fuel		For units		110-7	92-7	98-6	98-0	99-1	83-6	88-4	83-4	83-5	89-1	92-4			(b.) Other Minerals and General Mer-		of*measure-															chandise    ..         ..		ment on		100-1	102-1	98-8	99-0	96-8	96-1	95-6	97-2	94-9	95-5	96-3		3.	Shipping Entrances and Clearances with		, which the &apos; *   Index   J															cargoes in the foreign trade 																	(a.) Entrances		Numbers		91-8	101-2	107-5	99-6	89-1	101-7	105-3	104-7	107-7	106-0	102-2	111 5	95-1	(6.) Clearances		are based		94-2	101-3	106-9	97-7	95-2	101-2	106-7	107-7	103-8	112-9	103-3	108-1	103-74.	Net Imports of Raw Materials : Volume ..		see Part I		130-8*	94-9	79-5	94-9	97&apos;9	87-3	73-1						5.	Postal Receipts-average amount Daily ..				95-1	97-2	96-9	110-7	100-1	99-5	99-9	99-2	100-7	96-8	102-3	110-6	107-76.	Employment  (a.) Estimated   Number  of   Insured																	Workers in Employment				98-5	100-8	100-6	100-2	100-1	100-6	99-1	99-9	99-0	99-0	99-3	98-8	98-4.	(b.) Insured Workers Unemployed			-	111-2	92-2	95-5	101-2	105-0	102-7	117-9	109-6	118-4	118-5	116-8	121-4	126-0* See Note against Item 4, Page 1.
sIABLE B.-PARTICULAR TRADES.Part I. Actual Figures.Items.	Unit of Measurement.	Monthly Averages.							Year 1928.							Jan.-Mar., &apos;. 1927.	April-June, 1927.	July-Sept., 1927.	Oct.-Dec, 1927.	Jan-Mar., 1928.	April-June, 1928.	July-Sept., 1928.	June.	July.	Aug.	Sept.	Oct.	Nov.1. Coal Mining  (a.) Quantity of saleable coal raised (b.) Unemployment Insured Worker? -Wholly Unemployed Temporarily stopped 2. Iron and Steel Trades  (a.) Crude Steel Output (4.) Unemployment Insured Workers 3. Base Metal Trades  (a.) Copper available for consumption (!) and (2)       ..         .... (4.) Unemployment-Insured Workers . 4. Cotton Trades  (a.) Raw Cotton delivered to Mills (4.) Unemployment-Insured Workers 5. Woollen and Worsted Trades  (a.) Index of Wages Bill. See Part II. (4.) Unemployment Insured  Workers 6. Artificial Silk-Production of Yarn  Home made 7. Natural Silk-Raw and Silk Yarns: Duty Paid deliveries 8. Crude Rubber available for consumption (2) 9. Paper-making Materials  Imports (3) of Wood Pulp  (a.) Chemical .. (b.) Mechanical (i (2 (3 [18651]	Thous. tons Tons Tons Thous. Centals Thousand lbs. Tons ) The figures gh i I.e., Net Impor Total Imports,	22,086 134,175 67,147 835,700 37,973 11,866 4,861 1,602 49,105 26,370 2,586 281 4,038 40,228 59,302 en do nol ts, less ac Re-export	20,620 114,756 106,288 827.300 35,758 - 11,628 3,963 1,345 39,782 23,075 2,897 357 3,933 49,773 62,122 include ii ditions to ;s of wooc	20,420 133,409 196,475 702,400 38,697 11,116 3,797 1,218 54,550 22,431 3,673 304 2,587 46,950 90,701 i the available warehou [ pulp are	20,948 138,399 79,131 667,500 45,409 12,109 3,600 1,249 63,089 17,603 3,796 421 4,375 55,948 71,884 able supp se slocks unimport	21,429 148,670 65,216 728,000 41,095 12,351 3,664 1,377 51,920 18,398 4,291 462 4,700 33,278 40,792 y the me 3r plus re( ant in am	18,951 163,288 85,689 702,100 42,277 12,310 3,676 1,246 61,384 22,155 4,385 403 2,894 38,537 64,939 ;al produc luctions ii )unt.	18,448 179,524 111,283 677,900 46,558 10,594 3,876 1,051 85,352 37,673 4,410 366 3,430 39,057 74,797 ed from i i warehou	18,959 168,966 130,483 709,000 42,097 13,140 3,720 1,209 72,257 28,636 4,866 404 2,760 43,917 90,296 mported o se stocks	18,135 179,386 145,546 666,900 48,186 9,369 3,824 1,139 84,349 36,497 4,822 346 1,899 41,090 65,239 res.	18,360 180,488 115,922 648,300 47,916 11,226 3,741 978 91,285 35,642 4,040 378 3,502 36,133 88,814	18,855 178,699 72,381 718,600 43,573 11,187 4,064 1,035 80,423 40,879 4,369 374 4,890 39,947 70,338	21,110 173,774 106,236 756,000 43,834 12,436 4,041 1,278 72,482 38,148 4,706 408 6,139 39,858 78,560 B	20,641 176,947 105,346 762,500 44,343 14,311 4,168 1,381 69,562 33,901 4,353 419 3,413 53,627 118,972 2OO
TABLE B. PARTICULAR TRADES-(continued).			Monthly Averages.							Year 1928.						Items.	Unit of Measurement.	Jan.-	Apr -	July-	Oct.-	Jan.-	Apr-	July-									Mar.,	June,	Sept.,	Dec,	Mar.,	June,	Sept.,	June.	July.	Aug.	Sept	Oct.	Nov.			1927.	1927.	1927,	1927.	1928.	1928.	1928.						10.	General Engineering 				55,806	57,564										Unemployment Insured Workers		76,820	59,738			55,473	54,821	57,522	54,189	55,349	58,361	58,855	55,366	59,91511.	Electrical Engineering  (a.) BEAMA Index of Production-See Part II.															(J.) Unemployment Insured Workers		4,988	3,946	3,685	3,424	3,667	3,738	4,059	3,823	3,957	4,140	4,081	4,120	4,13412.	Building  -   (a.) Plans  approved   by   146   Local Authorities in Great Britain  Estimated Cost 															(I.) Dwelling Houses	Thousand  &apos;s	3,754	3,329	2,984	3,229	3,232	3,398	3,403	3,626	3,874	2,431	3,904	3,732	3,751(6)	(II.) Other Buildings and addi-															tions and alterations to															existing buildings	n	1,793	2,388	1,923	2,027	2,083	2,326	2,294	2,765	2,617	1,793	2,472	2,402	2,498(6)	(b.) Unemployment Insured Workers 					111,638	114,786	77,023								(I.) Building		95,133	53,343	63,479				85,309	77,869	81,927	82,154	91,845	103,150	117,430	(II.) Public Works Contracting,						33,256									&amp;c. ...		32,528	24,344	24,865	31,185		28,040	29,866	27,603	28,431	29,925	31,241	33,622	36,984The figures relating to shipbuilding, except those for unemployment, are actual aggregates for the quarterly periods, not monthly averages: 13. Shipbuilding in the United Kingdom  (a.) Merchant Vessels under construc-tion at end of Quarter (b.) Vessels commenced during Quarter (c.) Unemployment Insured Workers   Shipbuilding and Marine En-engineering	Thousand Gross Tons ii	1,217 580 78,537	1,390 437 57,338	1,536 370 51,332	1,580 377 48,500	1,441 342 45,346	1,203 279 53,185	1,090 245 61,555	57,820	59,476	59,504	65,686	72,045	71,048Corresponding figures for shipbuilding in other countries are  (a.) Merchant Vessels under construc-tion at end of Quarter (b.) Vessels commenced during Quarter	Thousand Gross Tons ii	1,353 367	1,450 337	1,538 400	1,539 259	1,452 263	1,458 261	1,432 253						
Part II. Index Numbers. Monthly Average of 1927 ^00105-1	98	1	97	2	99	to	102-0		90	2	87-8	90-2	86	CO	87-3	89-7	100-4	98 -2103-0	88	1	102	5	106	4	110-4		125	5	137-9	129-8	137	8	138-6	137-2	133-5	136-059-8	94	7	175	0	70	5	58	1	76	3	99-2	116-2	129	7	103-3	64-5	94-6	93-8110-2	109	1	92	6	88	0	96-0		92	6	89-4	93-5	88	0	85-5	94-8	99-7	100-696-2	90	6	98	1	115	0	104-2		107	1	118-0	106-7	122	1	121-4	110-4	111-1	112-4101-6	99	6	95	2	103	7	105	7	105	4	90-7	112-5	80	2	96-1	95-8	106-5	122-5119-9	97	7	93.	6	88	8	90	4	90	7	95-6	91-7	94	3	92-2	100-2	99-6	102-8118-4	99	4	&apos;    90	0	92	3	101	8	92	0	77-7	89-3	84	2	72-3	76-5	94-4	102-095-1	77	0	105	6	122	2	100	6	118	9	165-3 -	140-0	163	4	176-8	155-8	140-4	134-796-7	101	0	100	2	102	1	101	6	100	3	92-9	97-8	93	6	91-8	93-4	95-9	96-3117-8	103	2	100	3	78	7	82	2	99	1	168-4	.128-0	163	2	159-3	182-7	170-6	151-679-9	89	5	113	5	117	2	132	5	135	4	136-2	150-3	148	9	124-8	134-9	145-3	134-482-5	104	8	89	3	123	4	135	5	118	2	107-4	118-5	101	5	110-9	109-7	119-7	123-0108-2	105	4	69	3	117	2	125	9	77	5	91-9	73-9	50	9	93-8	131-0	164-5	91-483-4	103	2	97	4	116	0	69-0		79	9	81-0	91-1	85	2	74-9	82-8	82-7	111-283-5	87	5	127	7	101	2	57	5	91	5	105-3	127-2	91	9	125-1	99-1	110-6	167-6122-9	95	6	89	3	92	1	88	8	87	8	92-0	86-7	88	6	93-4	94-1	88-6	95-994-7	104	4	109	6	91	2	77	2	70	2	70-2	68-4	64	9	68-4	77 -2	79-8	81-6124-4	98	4	91	9	85	4	91	4	93	2	101-2	95-3	98	7	103-2	101-8	102-7	103-1112-9	100	2	89	8	97	1	97	2	102	2	102-4	109-1	116	5	73-1	117-4	112-3	U2-8(88-2	117	5	94	6	99	7	102-5		114-4		112-9	136-0	128-8		88-2	121-1	118-2	122-9(1. Coal Mining (a.) Quantity of saleable Goal raised .. (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers-Wholly unemployed Temporarily stopped 2. Iron and Steel Trades  (a.) Crude Steel output (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers 3. Base Metal Trades (a.) Copper available for consumption (*) and(z)(i.) Unemployment Insured Workers 4. Cotton Trades (a.) Raw Cotton delivered to Mills   .. (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers 5. Woollen and Worsted Trades (a.) Index of Wages Bill    .. ..     For units(J.) Unemployment Insured Workers    of measure-6. Artificial Silk  ment on production of Yarn  which theHome made      .. .. .. ^   various7. Natural Silk Saw and Silk Yams  IndexDuty paid deliveries .. ..     Numbers8. Crude Rubber available for consumption (2)      are based 9. Paper-making Materials Imports (&apos;) of    see Part 1 Wood Pulp-(a.) Chemical (b.) Mechanical 10. General Engineering Unemployment Insured Workers 11. Electrical Engineering (a.) BEAMA Index of Production (*) .. (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers 12. Building-(a.) Plans approved by 146 Local Au-thorities in Great Britain  Estimated Cost (i.) Dwelling Houses (ii.) Other Buildings and ad-ditions and alterations to existing buildings1 IFor Notes     (&apos;) and (8), see page 3. (*) The figures are derived from those issued by BEAMA, which are calculated to a basis of 100 for the year 1920.(6) These figures exclude particulars of two local authorities from which returns are still outstanding, and may be increased slightly when the latter are received,
		Monthly Averages.							Year 1928.					Items.	Unit of Measurement.	Jan.-Mar., 1927.	Apr-June, 1927.	July-Sept., 1927.	Oct.-Dec, 1927.	Jan.-Mar., 1928.	Apr-June, 1928.	July-Sept. , 1928.	June.	July.	Aug.	Sept.	Oct.	Nov.12. Building (continued). (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers  (i.) Building (ii.) Public works  contracting, &amp;c.  ..	For Units of measure-ment on which the various Index Numbers are based see Part I	117-6 115-2	66-0 86-2	78-5 88-1	138-0 110-4	141-9 117-8	95-2 99-3	105-5 105-8	96-2 97-8	101-3 100-7	101-6 106-0	113-6 110-7	127-5 119-1	145-2 131-0The figures relating to shipbuilding, except those for unemployment,						are for the quarterly periods, not monthly averages: 								13. Shipbuilding in the United Kingdom  (a.) Merchant Vessels under Construc-tion at end of Quarter (b.) Vessels Commenced during Quarter.. (c.) Unemployment Insured Workers, Shipbuilding and MarineEngineer-ing..	See Part I	85-0 131-4 133-3	97-2 99-1 97-3	107-4 83-9 87-1	110-4 85-6 82-3	100-7 77-5 76-9	84-0 63-2 90-2	76-2 55-6 104-5	98-1	100-9	101-0	111-5	122-2	120-6Corresponding figures for shipbuilding in other countries are  (a.) Merchant Vessels under Construction at end of Quarter (b.) Vessels Commenced duringftQuarter	See Part I	92-1 107-7	98-6 98-9	104-6 117-4	104-7 76-0	98-8 77-1	99-2 76-5	97-4 74-2					* *;	TABLE B. PARTICULAR TRADES (continued).



</content>
</cab>
