<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 458-464</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
c&apos;Triia document    is the property of Hia Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government) . RET ..7  (29), CABINET.Betting, Gaming and Lotteries. Memorandum by the Home Secretary.Various   events   of the last few years have aroused a measure of public interest in these matters.      Prom time to time Government action is urgedj    but while some parties call for restrictions, others call for relaxations;    and the question arises whether the air could be cleared by an inquiry0      Many of my colleagues will no doubt have the matter pressed upon their notice and I endeavour in this memorandum to give them a general conspectus of the case.Dealing only with a few of the more important events of recent years,  it will be remembered that before and during the passage of the Racecourse Betting Bill, although the Bill was generally recognised as a means of limiting the evils attendant on racecourse betting and of restricting juvenile betting rather than as an enabling measure,  the Government was constantly reminded that nothing should be done to increase facilities for legal betting..     This attitude towards betting generally was consistent with earlier events,  such as the prohibition of Street Betting in 1906 and of Ready Money Football Betting Advertisements,  Circulars or Coupons in 1920,  the taxation of betting in 1926,  the Betting (Juvenile Messengers)   (Scotland) Act,   1928,  and with other current manifestations of feeling in favour of proposals to prohibit betting with young persons arid to restrict or forbid betting on Dog Races.    So far as actual betting is concerned,  therefore,  it may be said that recently opinion on the whole has favoured restriction rather than relaxation.It does not follow however that this indicates any decline of the gambling instinct.      On the contrary there are in other directions signs that that instinct,  but not in.its most extreme form,  is spreading to new sections of  society,  and these sections are  said at  some points to resent  strongly any interference with
its indulgence.As regards certain matters,  this resentment arouses some sympathy.      Whist Drives have become a regular feature of modern life    and, when they are carried on not for private gain but  simply as a form of social amusement, are harmless enough.      Before the war a decision of the Courts had brought them within a branch of the law which had been passed years before Whist Drives were thought ofj    and when a similar decision was recently given I felt  justified in making generally known /2ay view (which was In accordance with the actual practice which had been adopted by the Metropolitan Police with the approval of my predecessors), that the police need not interfere unless actual harm was being done. There is no reason to doubt that Chief Officers of Police are acting,  and acting reasonably, upon this view and,   so far as whist drives are concerned, there is not likely to be further serious cause for complaint?    but I ought to point out that my pronounce-ment in this matter has already resulted in suggestions that I should make similar pronouncements in respect of other matters in ?rtiich entirely different considerations arise and where any appearance of an attempt on my part to Interfere with the due enforcement of the law would be incompatible with consitiutional propriety.Thus I have been asked to suggest that the police should not interfere with public lotteries conducted for charity.    How the essence of public lotteries consists in the advertising and offering to the public of prizes,  sometimes of great value, distributed according to chance.      No social game is played:    no hours of harmless amusement are afforded;    the instinct appealed to is the gambling instinct;    these objections apply to public lotteries conducted for- charity as well as to other public lotteries;    and even if the risk of downright fraud (which attaches in a very serious degree to all public lotteries conducted others wise than under the most strict and therefore expensive supervision) be less in the case of lotteries for charity, there is always,
first, the possibility that entirely disproportionate sums are lost in advertising and in working expenses;    secondly,  great harm is done to other charitable objects which for one reason or another0cannot be made the subject of appeals to the passion for gambling; thirdly, many of those whose institutions might benefit by lotteries object strongly to lotteries on moral grounds - witness a memorial I received from the Churches in 1924.    Having regard to the absolute legal prohibition and to administrative experience I feel unable without legislation to suggest any discrimination by the police in favour of lotteries conducted for charitable objects and in view of the fate which, on a free vote, befell the Lotteries (War Charities) Bill,  1918,  supported by the then Home Secretary, I doubt whether Parliament would feel  justified in attempting to deal with the matter.As regards minor public lotteries (whether conducted for charity or otherwise)  such as raffles,  draws and lucky dips, there is a general feeling that these might well pass unnoticed on .the principle &quot;de minimis&quot;j    but there are difficulties;    if the Police ought  to interfere with a public lottery properly conducted for a charitable object,  e.g.  for the funds of a hospital, when the prize is a motor car well worth winning, it is,  I fear, clear that on grounds of principle they ought to interfere with a publicly advertised raffle,  conducted entirely for private gain, when the prize  (perhaps a hamper of spirits and wine) may not be worth more than a fraction of the price of the total number of tickets sold.There are of course minor lotteries held almost every day which may occasion doubts whether the elements of publicity are such as to bring them within the category of &quot;public&quot;  lottery. Every one of my colleagues has I am sure opened Bazaars at which raffles have taken place and it would be simple folly to suggest that the Police ought to prosecute in each case.     Last month a draw for Christmas turkeys took place in my own Conservative Association.      All was well until a local labour leader took a
t^eto      Consternation followed - police raids were expected., Swir expectations were not realised;    the Labour Party copied my ticket, had a turkey drawn of their own and all was well.      If I am pressed in the future in the House of Commons I would propose in such cases to reply - either on the de minimis principle,  or where the necessary elements of publicity are lacking, on the ground that the lottery is not a public lottery.During the last few years Syndicates have distributed throughout the country various automatic gaming machines to be set up in licensed houses, refreshment houses,  small Pun Pairs held in premises formerly shops, and so on.      Such machines are regarded by organisations interested in Juvenile Welfare as specially injurious, and for various reasons several types of machines have been held by the Courts to be illegal and Judges have characterised in strong terms the mischief that they do.      It cannot be said that public opinion has been aroused by the consequent disappearance of the machines, and the Cabinet may recall that when a Scottish Court took a different view from the English Courts, Parliament was quick to pass the Gaming Machines (Scotland) Act,  1917, which made such machines illegal in Scotland,,The law took rather longer to-\cope effectively with a development on a much larger scale, namely, the setting up, by so-called Amusement Caterers,  at Shows, Pairs, Exhibitions and so on, of large-scale gambling devices.    These are now in course of being suppressed and, so far as I can judge,  their suppression is not arousing much, opposition^ -exc^rt-Sr-cm.. persons and Syndicates interested financially in a form of gambling which is peculiarly profitable to the promoters and profitless to the public\    a form...^ which I feel sure is never likely to be legalised by Parliament if -the true facts are sufficiently made known.On the other hand again let me be frank with my colleagues. In- July there was a fete in my Division at which 20,000 people attended and I spoke.      I was subsequently told that all of the side shows were frankly illegal!!&quot;.
Lastly,  gambling on football by means of newspaper coupons has been declared illegal.      If I were to judge only by the representations I have received, the suppression of these has aroused no great resentment...    The great newspapers and newspaper Syndicates have not yet approached me,  or otherwise made public an3r desire for a change in the law;    some newspapers have received the decision with delight;    the Incorporated Society of British Advertisers has written to me expressly welcoming the decision of the Courts, as tending to reduce spurious   certified  net sales&apos;  of papers  (bought only for the sake of the coupons, and then thrown away);    and few general correspondents have written to the Home Office in protest.      Moreover, it ought not to be forgotten that when first the mushroom growth of newspaper &apos;competitions&apos; with entrance fees began to spring up, the Joint Select Committee on Lotteries,  etc. recommended that all such competitions should be made illegal in order to strike at the root of the evil. (H..C.275 of 190ft).But there are not wanting signs that sections of the community, viewing the situation rather confusedly as a whole, and not fully aware either of the evils originally attacked by the lav; or of the conclusions reached whenever the law has been reviewed, harbour the beliefs that there is &apos;one law for the rich and another for the poor&apos;, that the  &apos;innocent amusements of the people&apos;  are being interfered with, and that  &apos;the Puritan&apos;  is abroad in the land.    By suggestions that the&quot;law is in inextricable confusion these sections are encouraged to demand that something should be done, or at least that there should be a comprehensive inquiry.    It is not, however, true to say that the law is in a state of inextricable confusion.    The law is fairly clear but public opinion will not tolerate a rigorous enforcement.      A good deal of play has also been made for instance with the absurdity of interfering with ready money betting but not with credit betting.      The distinction is not really absurd.     Ready money betting is said to be   harmful to a far greater number than credit betting but this is only
because more people indulge in it and they are those perhaps who can less afford to lose their money.    Morally there can be no difference.Again,  it has been urged that some sweepstakes  (e.g. the Stock Exchange Sweepstaice and the.Calcutta Sweep) are  &apos; allowed&apos; while others that are similar but smaller are not allowed.    This is not technically so.      The sweepstakes that are interfered with are advertised and open to the public;      i.e. they are public lotteries.      The Stock Exchange and Calcutta Sweeps are not, though    it is of course the fact that in practice anybodj&apos; who wants to buy a ticket in them can easily do so.Similar answers could be found to other criticisms of the law.      As regards nearly all the matters now in question what has really   happened is that those who in one way or another have gained   wealth (whether for themselves or for charity) by appeals to the passion for gambling have sought, with the best legal advice at their command, to outwit and outstrip the law;    but the law, which is harder than human nature,  in the long run has out-witted them.      It is hardly worth while to institute protracted inquiry, if the only probable result is to trace out in&quot; detail^ this contest between the law and the law breakers;    it might    of course be worth while, if it were at all likely that,  as a result of inquiry, the law could be clarified and placed upon a much simpler basis;    but before this end could be reached there would have to be some consensus of opinion.      Is any such concensus of opinion in favour of any particular alteration of the law likely or possible?There has been during my period of office no interference with any real amusement of the people, nor has there been any attempt to institute a new and puritan regime.    This is being gradually made clear to the general public,  I believe,  e.g. by Answers to Questions in the House of Commons.    Moreover, the Judges in general urge stricter and not laxer enforcement of the law. For these&apos; reasons I do not at the moment favour the setting up
17th January,  1929.of an enquiry which must necessarily involve much time and labour and therefore expense;    particularly just now when a partisan and electioneering spirit would undoubted^ manifest itself.    When the Party comes back after the General Election, the prospects of dispassionate inquiry would be more hopeful and,  should the Government then wish it, the Home Secretary of the day might then perhaps institute an inquiry, but it cannot be suggested with any certainty that it would have any useful results.Lastly I would add that, apart from all the moral and debateable issues involved,  there is always the risk, nay the practical certainty,  that any large relaxation of the law against gambling, betting and lotteries would lead to widespread fraud and other abuses of the kinds which originally led to   laws on the subject being passed.      It might however be considered whether it would not be possible and desirable to devise and embody in the existing law a definition of &quot;public lottery&quot; which would dispel any doubts as to the legality of raffles lotteries and the like held at Nonconformist bazaars and similar gatherings,W.J.H.

</content>
</cab>
