<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 466-467</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.copy no.      28cp. 8 (29). &apos;//.&apos;:u cabinet.EQUAL PAY FOR MEN AND WOMEN IN THE CIVIL SERVICE.note by the chancellor of the exchequer.I CIRCULATE, for the information of my colleagues, a memorandum prepared in the Treasury on the subject of Equal Pay for Men and Women in the Civil Service. A good number of enquiries as to the attitude of the Government on this question are already being received, and it is, of course, bound to attract more and more attention the nearer we get to the General Election. .      .vj^ w. s. c.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1, jJanuary 16, 1929.A DEMAND is now being made by Civil Service Staff Associations and by a number of outside Women&apos;s Organisations for the setting up of a Select Committee^ to consider the question of equal pay for men and women in the Civil Service.      :The history of this question is as follows : On the 5th August, 1921, the House of Commons passed three Resolutions, which were accepted by the then Government, regarding the conditions of employ-ment of women in the Civil Service.   The third of these Resolutions was that &apos;&apos; having regard to the present financial condition of the country, the House could not commit itself to the increase in Civil Service salaries involved in the payment of women in all cases at the same rate as men, but that the question of the remuneration of women as compared with men should be reviewed within a period not exceeding three years.&quot;This period had hardly elapsed before the question was again raised in the House of Commons. On the 3rd July, 1924, Mr. Snowden stated, in reply to a question from Lady Astor, thai&quot;the Government, after full consideration, had decided that the state of the country&apos;s finances was still such as to make it impossible to justify the enormous increase in expenditure that would be involved.&quot;Similar pronouncements have been made on various occasions during the term of office of the present Government. On the 5th March, 1925, the Chancellor of the Exchequer gave the following answer on the subject to a question by Major Clifton Brown: &apos;&apos; This question has been reviewed both by the late and the present Govern-ment, with the result that it has been decided that the state of the country&apos;&amp; finances does not admit of the increase of expenditure involved in the application of the principle of equal pay for men and women in the Civil Service.&apos;[18738]&quot; &quot; &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;     &quot;&apos;       11  &quot;-............   - -  -Printed for the Cabinet.  January 1929.
On the 17th November, 1925, in reply to a question from Colonel Day, the Financial Secretary stated that &apos;&apos; the question of the remuneration of women in the Civil Service as compared with men has already been reviewed by the present Government, and the Government is not prepared to set up a special committee of enquiry on the subject.&quot;This decision was reaffirmed so recently as the 23rd March, 1928, in an answer iio Sir Walter de Frece.An estimate, made in 1924, of the cost involved is contained in the following extract from a reply given in the House of Commons on the 29th July, 1924 : .&apos;&apos; The number of women in the Civil Service now employed in the same grades as men is estimated at about 40,000, but it is obvious that the effect of introducing the principle of equal pay could not be confined to these grades, and that consequent adjustments would be inevitable in the pay of women employed in separate grades of the Civil Service, the number of whom is not far short of 40,000. It would also be necessary to allow for the&quot; extension of the principle &apos;to women teachers, and on this basis the cost would be at least  10 millions a year. If, however, the estimate is confined to the Civil Service, the cost, based upon a comparison of the means of the scales in grades in which both men and women are employed, with a moderate allowance for adjusting the pay of other Women Civil Servants, may be put at  3 millions a year in round figures for , . the existing numbers employed without any allowances for increase in the pro-1 portion of women employed in the Civil Service.&quot;uo A new estimate of cost, allowing for the reduction in numbers which has since taken place and for the effect of the fall in the cost of living bonus, would not bring out a figure markedly less than the  10 millions a year previously quoted.A decision to give equal pay to men and women m the Civil Service and the teaching profession could hardly fail to react on industrial wages standards. Furthermore, it must be borne in mind that rates of remuneration for men are related to the normal needs of married persons. It is almost inevitable, if women were given men&apos;s rates of pay, that a new agitation would arise for the grant to married men of marriage allowances.For all these reasons, it is submitted that the demand for a Select Committee to consider and report on the means for giving effect to the principle of equal pay should he firmly resisted on the ground that in the present state of the national finances the Government could not contemplate the heavy additional burden involved in the application of this principle.

</content>
</cab>
