<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 516-518</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE property  OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT) .LDr: confidential . COPY NO t ,J%.20  (29).C A  B I NET.THE IRON AND STEEL INDUSTRY.PROPOSED ENQUIRY BY A ROYAL COMMISSION OR OTHER BODY..Copy of letter from tho General Secretary of the Iron and S*teel Trades ConfeaeratTon to trie &quot;Prime minister(Circulated in accordance with Cabinet 3 (29), Conclusion 9).The Iron and Steel Trades Confederation, Central Office,Swinton House,324 GrayTs Inn Road, London, W.C.1,31st December, 1928 oThe rt. hon,, Stanley Baldwin, McP0, Prime Minister,10 Downing Street, SJ!ul.Dear Sir^The adverse conditions that have operated in the Iron and stool Industry during the past seven years - particularly as regards its heavy sections - have been a. matter of deep concern to this Confederation., both on account of the Immediate effect upon the lives of the workpeople and their dependants, and the future of the industry,.The returns of the Ministry of Labour&quot; indicate the degree of unemployment, Tsat do not cover the extent of short time working of those employed0     Even so, the returns referred to show that for six years and nine months ending September,  1928, while general unemployment has averaged 11^% and unemployment In the coal mining Industry ll/o,  the figure for the iron and steel trades has averaged over 25%It will be recalled that as far back as 1925 this Confederation comrnunioated with the present Government on the matter, since when manufacturing interests have approached the Government with a view to certain sections of the industry being brought within the provisions of the Safeguarding of Industries Act-The Confederation Executive Council are concerned that recent developments tend in the direction of treating the industry as a subject of political controversy rather than from the standpoint of its economic position.     At the same time, they appreciate there are factors of far-reaching importance which reauire to be brought under consideration If legislative proposals in relation to the industry are - contemplated-
On the other hand,  It is their submission that no Government, whatever lt3 political complexion,  can justifiably ignore conditions which bear upon the welfare and stability of a great basic industry.The Confederation Executive Council consider that the first practical step in connection with Government inter-vent ion on behalf of the Industry and which visualises assistance to the industry to deal with its problems, is an ascertainment of the facts by a.body appointed for the purpose, and vhich will approach the matter less from the political view-point and more from the Importance of the industry in the economic life of the country.While It is true a good deal of information Is already available through the Committee on Industry and Trade, and from other sources, this clearly is not sufficient to enable definite conclusions to be arrived at as to the adoption of measures which the circumstances of the industry may demonstrate as requiring to be of a far-reaching character.I am, therefore, instructed to request that the Government shall consider the setting up of a Royal Commission or other competent Committee to make a full and impartial inquiry into the industry and to ascertain as far as possible all the facts with regard to Its present position, with special reference to the nature of the competition in the Home Market, and to make such recommenda-tions whether as regards action by the Industry itself or legislative action as,  in the considered judgment of the appointed body, the circumstances require, due regard being paid to all legitimate interestaeIn particular, the appointed body shall have regard to :-(a) Whether the organisation of the industry, its technical and mechanical equipment, and Its financial policy Is such as to enable it   other things being equal     to justify its position in the economic life of the country and in -,orld trade.(b) Ihat handicaps,  if any, exist with regard to raw materials, transport, and in the marketing of its products *(c) Factors of competition arising from trade restrictions and barriers on the part of Its competitors 0(d) Factors of competition arising from lower standards of wages, hours and labour conditions In competing countrloc,  including non-observance of Inter-national Labour Conventions.(e) Factors of competition arising from subsidies, direct or Indirect, or other similar measures In competing countries in relation to their exports of iron and steel.(f) The cost of unemployment, not only In actual expenditure for the maintenance of the unemployed, but In the waste of skill and loss of morale, and the possibilities of the capitalised value of this or Its equivalent being applied productively as a part of en organised scheme of dealing with the Industry.
The Confederation Executive Council trust that the Government will see. the importance of such a body being set up at the earliest practicable moment. In order to deal with a situation which is becoming increasingly urgent in its character0A copy of this communication is being sent to the employing organisations with which this Confederation has relations, arid in view of the degree of public attention which has been directed to the industry in the House of Commons and elsewhere, and the desirability of avoiding mls-statemcnts, we beg to suggest that a copy thereof be supplied to the Press, and trust to hear that you approve of that course.Yours faithfully. For the Iron and Steel Trades Confederation-(Sgd.)    A.  PUGH,General Secretary.

</content>
</cab>
