<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 542-606</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
government ^ENTiEC RET.,!T5B(g9),. CABINET.THE LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL (CO-ORDINATION OF PASSENGER TRAFFIC7&quot;BILL;&quot; 1958-29.THE LONDON ELECTRIC RAILWAY COMPANY^S (CO-ORDINATION OF&quot;PA&apos;passenger TRAFTiC&quot;)&quot; glLL, 1323-29.Memorandum by the Minister of Transport.la I circulate herewith the Report of the London TrafficAdvisory Committee on the above-mentioned Bills, dated 5thFebruary, 1929.      It is signed by 12 out of the 19 members of theCommittee,     Mr. Frank Pick, Mr. C.W. Matthews and Mr, Angus Scotthave appended a note to the effect that, as they represent the promoters of the Bills, they do not consider they ought to addtheir signatures, but they do not dissent from its terms, and areprepared to recommend the respective Promoters to give effect tothe recommendations contained in the Report in so far as this canbe done under Private Bill Procedure.     Mr, John Cliff, Mr,Alderman Ben Smith, M,P,, and Mr. J.E. Binks, (the two formerrepresenting the Transport and General Workers&apos; Union and thelatter the National Union of Railwaymen) have added a reservationto the effect that they are unable to concur in the specific recommendation in the Report that &quot;in principle the Minister shouldbe advised to assist the passage of these Bills&quot;, on the groundthat they consider the Government should find time for a public&apos;opy      Bill implementing the recommendations in the Committee&apos;s Report of ached)the 27th July, 1927, (commonly known and referred to hereafter as the &quot;Blue Report&quot;,) which envisaged a Common Management and a Common Fund, subject to public control, for all the passenger transport services in the London Traffic Area other than the Main Line suburban railways.      Mr, W.F. Mallender (representing the Independent Omnibus Proprietors) whilst assenting to the present Report adds a reservation to the effect that he dissents from the scheme proposed under the &quot;Blue Report&quot; &quot;as calculated to stifle private enterprise and appropriate the property of the individual without adequate compensation,&quot;
o d 9 a U ft-la.Sir Herbert Walker finds himself unable to sign the Report as the Main Line Railway Companies have decided to oppose the Bills,
My. colleagues will recall that on the 8th August, 1927,I circulated copies of the &quot;Blue Report&quot; with a covering memorandum(C*,P.220/27).     In this memorandum I sought Cabinet authority(i)    To send copies of the Report to each of theTransport agencies concerned, with the request that if they desired to make any representations as to the major principles of the scheme out-lined therein, they should submit them to me by a named date&apos;.(ii)    To make the Report public.I further recommended that the replies of these Transportagencies should be awaited before any decision was arrived at asto legislation.The subsequent history of the negotiations is as follows:-From the replies received from the Transport Agenciesit seemed clear that, with the exception of the-MetropolitanRailway Company and a minority of the omnibus interests, there wasa general approval of the major principles of the scheme of the blue Report.The view of the main line railway companies which, under the proposals of the Report would be excluded from the scheme of the O-common Pool and Common Management but given powers to enter into working agreements with parties to the scheme, was that no scheme of co-ordination of the kind proposed could be complete unless they were parties to it.-    In view of this attitude, negotiations were opened,  at my request, between the Advisory Committee and of the Railway Companies&apos; representatives with a view to ascertaining whether a satisfactory basis could be devised upon which the latter could be parties to the proposed scheme of co-ordination.     These negotiations are still proceeding.In the meantime, in accordance with the Advisory Committee1? recommendation contained in the Blue Report, I addressed communications in May 1928 to the London County Council and the Underground Group of Companies enquiring whether they would be willing to nominate representatives to confer with other interests,
(9 f\c$ :j &apos;:&apos; dand, to confer in the first place, among themselves, with a view to ascertaining what measure of agreement existed or could be reached between them, as the predominant parties in any such scheme.     Negotiations accordingly took place between these parties.     By Cabinet conclusion 4(28) of 1st February 1928 it had been decided that it lvas Impossible to adopt a London Traffic Bill for the coming session and the congestion of the Parliamentary time-table became obvious in the Summer. Whilst therefore these negotiations were proceeding, I felt bound to let it be known that in any event Government time could not be provided for a Public Bill to deal with the matter during the lifetime of the present Parliament.I understand that the London County Council and the Underground Group of Companies proceeded to explore the extent to which it would be possible, under their existing powers, for them to co-ordinate their operations, but were both advised that they had not the necessary powers.     They thereupon, in the late Autumn of 1928, on their own initiative, decided to promote these Bills.4.        SCOPE OF THE BILLS.pies The powers sought by these two Bills may be shortlyashed..summarised as follows :-To confer upon each Gf the parties powers to enter into agreements first with one another and secondly with any other transport agencies wholly or partly within the London Traffic Area.-(a) for the Common Management, maintenance, operation, development, improvement, etc., of their respective undertakings.(b) The allocation and apportionment of traffic, including receipts and expenses.(c) The establishment of a Common Fund and the control, management and application of such a fund.The Bills provide that these agreements shall be subjectto certain safeguards against undue profits and excessive fares,-and also that any agreements entered into shall be laid on the table of both Houses of Parliament.,
v : &quot; $   - .    It,The London Traffic Advisory Committee (with the solitary exception of the representative of the independent omnibus propristors) still consider that the scheme outlined by the Blue Report provides the ultimate solution of the problem and the Committee has been assured as I am told by the representatives of the promoters of the present Bills, that the sole reason why the points referred to above have not been covered in these Bills is that they cannot be dealt with by way of Private Bill legislation.The question which I now desire to submit to the Cabinet is whether, having regard to the fact that some time must elapse before legislation can be introduced on the lines of the comprehensive scheme set out in the Blue Report, It is desirable that enabling powers for a partial measure of co-ordination should be conferred upon the Promoters of these Bills.     In arriving at a decision upon this point I think particular regard must be had to the following considerations(a) There is no Immediate possibility of any Government being in a position to promote a Public Bill dealing with the matter.(b) The London Traffic Advisory Committee recommend that the passage of these Bills should be assisted.(c) In the view of the Committee, in which I concur there is nothing in the broad principles of the Bills which conflicts with the general soheme outlined in the Blue Report.(d) The magnitude of the undertakings owned and operated by the Promoters embracing as they do the L,C.C.tramways the whole of the tube railways, the Metropolitan District Railway and the London General Omnibus Company should be taken into account.     Further, there is a reasonable prospect that a nurnberg if not all the municipally-owned or operated tramways and the company-c-rnec tramways in the area will avail themselves of the powers provided in the Bills to.enter into agreements with the Promoters.   ,,,      - . &apos;     -The essential differences between the scheme set out in the Blue Report and that covered by these Bills are that the Blue Report envisaged a compulsory unification and co-ordination of all the transport agencies other than the main line railways, coupled with the setting up of an effective form of control so as to ensure a programme of expansion and development, proper scales of fares.,  services adequate to the needs of the public and sound financial arrangements for raising additional caoital.
Co-ordination of passenger transport services in the metropolitan area has been continually advocated during the last 25 years but owing to the difficulties of London, local government and for other reasons nothing has been done apart from the combination of the undertakings Included in the Underground group. At the Public Inquiries held by the Advisory Committee in 1925 and 1926 into travelling facilities in the more congested parts of London, It was conclusively shown that there was a clamant need for additional transport facilities, particularly in the form of tube railways and conditions have since become worse.     It seems clear that these urgently needed travelling facilities cannot be provided unless and until some measure of co-ordination is effected,  and all suitable steps which will facilitate the provision of additional facilities, such as new electric railways at the earliest possible date, should,  in my opinion, receive the support of the Government particularly as in any event their-construction must take some years.I may add that since their publication these Ellis have become a political issue.     The London Labour Party and the Labour Party generally have expressed their hostility  o the Bills on the ground that they run counter to their views with regard to municipal trading in transport,  and the nationalisation of transport services.     They also contend that if passed into law the Bills would confer a virtual monopoly on private enterprise by handing over &quot;the people!s trams&quot;, without any adequate form of public control.      fir. Herbert Morrison, the leader of the London Labour Party, has prepared a Memorandum in opposition to the Bills which has been widely published and contains a foreword by Mr. Ramsay MacBonald.The following resolution was passed unanimously at a largely attended meeting of London Unionist Members of Parliament and of Unionist Candidates for London constituencies:-
That this meeting desires to urge upon the Government the necessity of giving facilities for the speedy passage of the Bills dealing with the proposed London traffic scheme (which scheme received the approval of London electors at the London County Council election in March last) in order that new and urgently needed transport services may he provided, the congestion of the streets relieved, cheaper fares and better labour conditions secured, and an opportunity afforded for giving work to the unemployed in London and the depressed areas of the country by the construction of now tube railways and other improvements 0&quot;The same resolution was also passed by the London Municipal Society and National Union of Ratepayers&apos; As sociations.The attitude of the local authorities in the London Traffic Area towards the Bills appears to some extent to depend on the political views of the majority on the respective Councils.    Up to the present, so far as I can ascertain, 10 Councils have passed resolutions or otherwise expressed themselves in favour of the Bills, whilst 8 Councils with Labour     majorities and Soutlrwark have passed resolutions to the contrary effect.    The Metropolitan Boroughs&apos; Standing Joint Committee, comprising representatives of all the 29 Boroughs, including the City of London, have passed a resolution in favour, as also have the authorities represented on the North London Travelling Facilities Committee.    This Committee consists of representatives of all the authorities in the neighbourhood of Finsbury Park, where additional tube railway facilities are probably more urgently needed than in any other district in the Metropolitan   area.I understand that the Second Reading of these Bills 1Arill be taken on the 14th February and I seek the authority of the Cabinet (a) to publish the recent report from my Advisory Committee before that date (b) to inform the House that the Government consider that they should be accorded a Second Reading and sent to a Select Committee.
In that event, there will be a number of questions of importance arising upon the form and the details of the Bills which will require careful consideration in Committee.Ministry of Transport, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,8th February, 192-9.(Intld.)       W.A.
MINISTRY OF TRANSPORT.Report of the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committto the Minister of TransportgivingParticulars of a Scheme for the Co-ordination of Passenger Transport Facilities in the London Traffic Area.LONDON:PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE. To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120, George Street, Edinburgh; lork Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff; 15, Donegall Square West, Belfast; or through any Bookseller.1927.Price id. net.
fMINISTRY OF TRANSPORT.Counties Traffic Advisory Committeeto the Minister of TransportgivingParticulars of a Scheme for the Co-ordination of Passenger Transport Facilities in the London Traffic Area.LONDON:PEINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S stationary OFFICE. To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the &quot;following addresses: Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120, George Street, Edinburgh; York Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff; 15, Donegall Square West, Belfast;, or through any Bookseller.1927.55-124Price 4d. net.
Report of the London and Home Counties Traffic  Advisory  Committee to the Minister of TransportgivingParticulars of a Scheme for the Co-ordination of Passenger Transport Facilities in the London Traffic Area.1. Introductory. During the course of the Inquiries by the Committee as to the travelling facilities to and from areas in the North, North-East, East and South-East of London, it became abundantly clear that additional Railway facilities (includiing particularly the extension of the Underground Railway system in certain districts) were urgently required so as to enable the public to be conveyed to and from their homes with reasonable speed and comfort. The evidence submitted however made it equally clear that, so long as the present competitive methods are pursued, the Railway Companies as a whole are not prepared, or are not (in a position, to raise the capital necessary for substantial schemes of extension or improvement.In their Reports on these Inquiries, the Committee expressed the opinion that some scheme for bringing all forms of public passenger transport under unified management, subject to public control, appeared to offer the only satisfactory and lasting solution to the whole problem of passenger transport in London, as experience has shown that the powers conferred upon the Minister by the London Traffic Act, 1924, are quite inadequate as a means of eliminating the existing wasteful, uneconomic and unnecessary competition between the several transport agencies.On the 19th of April, 1926, the Minister addressed the following minute to the Chairman of the Committee : &quot; I have further considered the Report of the Sub-Committee of the London Traffic Committee on Travelling Facilities in North-East London.&apos;&apos; I desire to express, in the first instance, my appreciation of the services which you and the other members of the Committee have given in holding this laborious Inquiry and in the preparation of the able Report. I have noted the suggestion made by the witness for the General Omnibus and Tube Railway Companies that the solution for the traffic difficulties in London is to be found in the extension of the principle of common management and a common fund. This proposal raises many important and complex issues, the proper examination and elucidation of which was obviously outside the scope of the Committee&apos;s Inquiry. I am, therefore, not in a position to form any opinion on the proposal and should not attempt to do so. I agree, however, with the Sub-Com-mittee that a proposal put forward with such authority ought to be fully and impartially examined. I should be glad, therefore, if the London Traffic Committee would arrange for this or some other Sub-Committee to discuss with the Companies and Municipalities engaged in the opera-tion of transport undertakings in the London Area whether any further co-operation or combined action is possible or desirable.&quot;The Committee have, with the assistance of the Members representing the London County Council and the Underground Groups of Companies on the Committee, carefully examined this subject and have formulated the following scheme which they submit to the Minister for his consideration.2. Outline of Scheme. The scheme provides for the consolidation of the passenger transport services of London with such public control as is required to protect the interests of the community in the matter of : (a) the level of fares,(b) the adequacy of services,(c) development to the limit of available resources.In Order to remove all the sectional financial interests and to ensure that the consolidated services work efficiently and economically, it further provides for the setting up of a Common Fund and a Common Management, to which the64425 - x 2
passenger transport undertakings operating wholly or partly within the London Traffic Area, comprising underground and other local railways, tramway and omnibus undertakings, should be parties.The ownership of the existing undertakings would remain with the present proprietors, whether they be municipalities or private companies, but an excep-tion to this principle or some variation of it may be necessary in the case of the small omnibus proprietors having regard to their numbers and the small interests which they severally represent.So far as the present amalgamated railways are concerned, it is not sug-gested that they should be parties to the scheme in respect of their London Suburban traffic. Complications, both of accounting and operation, would be involved in such a step, as well as a possible conflict of interest. It is, however, desirable that powers should be conferred upon all such Companies to enable them to enter into agreements with parties to the scheme for therouteing, exchange and clearance of traffic; the provision of through services; the leasing and/or working of any of the suburban lines; the pooling of receipts, and other matters of common interest. These powers would be permissive in nature and not compulsory.The Committee feel satisfied that, if the proposals set out in this memoran-dum are accepted, the transport undertakings concerned can be made self-sup-porting without any increase in the general level of fares now prevailing.3. Constitution of the Common Fund. The foundation and assurance of the scheme is the Common Fund.The general basis of the Common Fund is that the balances of the gross revenues of the several undertakings, after meeting their respective revenue liabilities namely, working expenses, provision for depreciation and renewal, rents, interest on loans, debentures,, guaranteed and preference stocks and other prior charges would be pooled and thereafter distributed or applied in accordance with the proposals set out below.By providing for the charges on the fixed interest bearing capital before determining the amounts to be paid into the Common Fund by the several parties, no disturbance need be occasioned in the terms and conditions under which such capital has been (issued. The security and position of such capital would be strengthened, as it is proposed that the Common Fund shall be applied, in the first instance, to meeting the deficiency of any party thereto in the sum required to meet in full its revenue liabilities. Each party, therefore, would have the benefit not only of its own revenues in support of its prior charges, but of the balances of the revenues of the other parties to the scheme.The manner in which municipal loans are to be treated for the purposes of the Common Fund will, however, require further consideration. From a financial standpoint, a municipal loan is on an equality with the debenture or guaranteed stocks of a company. It enjoys the same market standing and affords the same or better security. Further, not only must interest be paid upon these loans, but in addition sums must be set aside annually out of revenue, if sufficient for the purpose, but otherwise out of the rates, for the redemption or repayment of the capital within a definite period of time. It is manifestly impracticable to treat all the loan charges on this capital as a revenue liability, as this would mean that the municipal authorities would have no financial in-terest in the Common Fund beyond its capacity to make good any deficiencies in the sums required to meet their revenue liabilities, including loan charges. Such a preferred burden upon the Common Fund might wholly destroy its value, especially in the initial years.It has been suggested that either the interest on outstanding loans or the sums required to provide for their redemption might be treated as a revenue liability for the purposes of the Common Fund. It may, however, be convenient that the loan capital of the municipalities should be dealt with on an equal footing with the ordinary capital of the companies. As the principal companies likely to enter into the scheme have met their prior charge securities in full for many years with ample and considerable margins, the adoption of the latter course would not involve any appreciable financial risk, Avhile it would serve to increase the share of the municipalities in the divisible balances of the Common Fund. Where a company has hitherto failed to meet its prior charges in full, the extent to which such prior charges should rank as a revenue liability would, in any event, be a subject for negotiation between the parties to any scheme.
These questions and also that of an exact definition of the &quot; revenue liabilities &quot; in the case of each undertaking, whether privately or municipally-owned, can only be settled after ascertainment and complete examination of the capital position and revenue accounts in past years in relation to the results of those years.Some further points need to be mentioned, viz. : (a) Some margin of current revenue must be secured to establish a credit for the raising of additional capital for the purpose of the extension and develop-ment of travelling facilities. It may, therefore, be necessary to seek authority to extend the periods for the repayment of loans raised by the Municipalities and so afford some relief from the heavy charges now falling upon tramways in parti-cular. In the case of the London County Council, this would necessitate applica-tion to H.M. Treasury; as regards the other local Authorities, the matter might be met by Parliament empowering the Minister to extend the periods.(b) For the protection of the parties to the scheme it would be necessary to provide: (1) That no party shall increase in amount its revenue liabilities as they exist at the date of adoption or commencement of the scheme except to such extent as may be agreed by the other parties, or, failing agreement, as shall be determined by arbitration.(2) That the amount which each party may include in its revenue liabilities in respect of reserve for depreciation and renewal shall be such as shall be agreed between the parties or, failing agreement, as shall be determined by arbitration.(3) That no party shall enter into any agreement or arrangement with any transport agency not comprised in the Scheme which would prejudice the contribution of such party to the Common Fund except with the consent of the other parties to the scheme, or, in the case of dispute, with the consent of the Minister of Transport.(ci) To provide for the temporary financing and to facilitate the execution of new works and improvements, it is suggested : (i) that powers should be conferred upon the constituent under-takings to borrow from the banks, on the security of the Common Fund, sums not exceeding  1,000,000 in the aggregate at any one time, for the purposes of capital and extraordinary expenditure incurred by the Common Management.(ii) that the Minister should be empowered to sanction the execution of new works bv any of the constituent undertakings and the acquisition of land required therefor, within the limit of the sum mentioned in (i), in accordance with the precedent contained in Sections 16 and 17 of the Railways Act, 1921.(d) It would also be convenient if some uniform basis were adopted for the calculating of the reserves for depreciation and renewal, e.g., car mileage. If this principle were agreed, the only outstanding question would be the rate per car mile year by year for each form of transport.4. Distribution of the Common Fund. With regard to the distribution of the Common Fund, it is recognised that the various parties to the scheme will be of different degrees of financial strength and security. It might, therefore, be unfair and give rise to complications with the stock and shareholders if the balances available for distribution from the Common Fund were in the first instance to be divided pro rata to the capital of the constituent undertakings so as to equalise the return on such capital. It would seem more fair to select a past year as a standard year and distribute the Common Fund pro rata to the contributions which would have been made to it in such standard year, until the results for such standard years are exceeded. (Some modification of this basis of distribution may be necessary in order to remunerate any capital raised and expended since the standard year). Such an arrangement obviously would not guarantee any party against loss if the results for the standard year are not reached, but it would not introduce any fresh or varied basis of distribution as a further disturbing factor at such a stage. If, when the results for the standard year are exceeded, no party is allowed to benefit while there are other parties receiving a lower return on their capital the proportions in which the Common Fund is distributed would shift progressively until at length, with the growth of the Common Fund, all get an equal return; and thereafter it would be04425 A 3
convenient simply to distribute the Common Fund on a basis which recognises (this equal return as a desirable criterion, that is, pro rata to the dependent capital.Accordingly the Common Fund should in respect of each year be administered and applied as follows : (1) If the revenue of any party for any year is not sufficient to meet its &quot; revenue liabilities &quot; at the close of such year, any such deficiency shall be made good out of the Common Fund.(2) After payment out of the Common Fund of such sum, if. any, as is provided for in (1) above, it shall be divided between the parties in the following proportions : (a) Until the amount available for distribution from the Common Fund exceeds the amount represented by the Standard Year, in the proportion in which the several parties would have paid into the Fund in the Standard Year if this scheme had been in operation in that year, providing that under this distribution no party receives more than a reasonable return upon its capital.(Note. As already stated, provision may require to be made for the remuneration of any capital raised and expended since the Standard Year).(b) To the extent to which the Common Fund exceeds the amount represented by the Standard Year, in such proportions as will tend to raise the percentage return upon the capital ultimately dependent upon the Common Fund (i.e., the ordinary share capital in the case of Companies and all or such portion of the capital municipally-owned upon which the charges do not rank as a revenue liability) until such percentage is alike for all parties.(c) As soon as the percentage return upon the Capital depen-dent upon the Common Fund has reached the same level for all parties, then in the proportions which the capital of such parties bears to the total capital related to the Common Fund, until such distribution shall amount to a reasonable return upon such capital.It is not possible to define precisely what is a reasonable return upon capital, as this will vary from time to time with the price of money in the market. The return must, however, be such as would enable additional ordinary capital to be raised at or about par..(3) Any balance remaining in the Common Fund after payment of a . .   reasonable return upon the capital employed, should be used for any of the following purposes:     . .    .(a) To provide a credit to attract new capital.(b) To carry out improvements to the existing undertakings.(c) To reduce fares and other charges.(of) To provide a general reserve against possible future bad years. ,      . .   .(e) To finance temporarily new capital expenditure.(/) Such other purposes as may be approved by the Minister of Transport.5. Scope of the Common Fund. If the Common Fund is to be equitable and effective it is essential that it should embrace all local passenger transport undertakings operating within the London Traffic Area as defined in the London Traffic Act, 1924. If there is to be a redistribution of gains and losses as between the various undertakings, all must eventually take their fair share.Whilst it is hoped that this will be effected by agreement, such powers must be conferred on the appropriate authority by Parliament as would ensure that all the undertakings concerned become parties to the Common Fund.So far, no attempt has been made to examine the capital, reserve and revenue accounts of the several undertakings, and it is realised that fresh practical con-siderations will arise when negotiations can be opened with the parties. At this stage it is sufficient to record that an equitable basis must be adopted upon which all parties may start within the Common Fund fairly as regards each other.With a Common Fund, the widest facilities for the exchange of traffic become possible without the need for a close check. This would render the ticket and fares systems to be adopted extremely flexible and permit of a choice of routes and services by the public which is not otherwise possible.
Further, one of the conveniences and economies which would result from the establishment of a Common Fund is the cessation of all inter-party accounting for &apos;&apos; through&quot; traffic and the parties to the scheme should, therefore, be empowered to enter into agreements (but without prejudice to the rights of creditors and any persons having a charge on the respective undertakings) to retain all monies which they receive without apportionment, except in so far as they receive monies in respect of through fares, rates and charges attributable to a transport undertaking not a party to the scheme.6. The Common Management. A Common Fund postulates a Common Management.By a Common Management is meant one or more persons (working together if more than one as a single unit) forming an executive actually engaged in the task of maintaining, working, renewing and developing the combined under-takings, and responsible to the proprietors of the several undertakings for the results of his or their management.As the various sectional financial interests would be merged, separate managements would not serve any useful purpose but on the contrary would be a hindrance rather than a help towards prosperity. Considerable economies would result from a common management. It would become possible to reduce the number of the higher adminisrative posts, to consolidate the work of over-haul and repair and so eliminate marginal waste; to obviate inter-party corres-pondence and returns; to purchase supplies upon a large and economical scale; and to standardise plant and equipment. Furthermore substantial economies would result from co-ordination of tram and omnibus services. For these reasons it is most desirable that all the undertakings, parties to the Common Fund, should be under a Common Management.Common Management is not however considered practicable except by agree-ment, but it is expected that agreement would in the main be reached. Should this not be so then it would be necessary to provide adequate safeguards for the protection of the Common Fund against the results of any improvident or ex-travagant operation by any undertaking embraced within it but not covered by the Common Management.The existing staffs whilst continuing to be the employees of the several transport undertakings, would, as opportunity occurred, be consolidated into one organisation as part of this common management, and in so far as any employees were displaced in consequence, provision should be made to afford them reason-able compensation.Each undertaking should be empowered to enter into agreements for the management, Working, equipment, staffing, maintenance and renewal of its pro-perties in conjunction with those of other undertakings parties to the scheme.7. Principles of Management. For the protection both of the public and of the undertakings, certain principles should be laid down to govern the conduct of the Common Management, viz :  .(a) That the combined undertakings shall at all times be maintained in good and efficient working order and condition, and operated as a single system of transport so that adequate travelling facilities are pro-vided for the public.The reserves for depreciation and renewal in respect of each under-taking should be at the disposal of the common management for this purpose. Any dispute as to; the manner in which such reserves are being expended or applied should be referred to arbitration.(b) That the combined undertakings shall at all times be managed and worked so that the earnings shall be sufficient to meet all proper charges against them and provide a reasonable return upon the capital invested.(c) That any general scheme of fares determined shall be applied as far as practicable on a uniform basis throughout the combined under-takings, except where special circumstances affecting the traffic or its distribution, or the cost of operation warrant a differentiation, and the Common Management shall be required to satisfy the Minister as to the reasonableness of any such differentiation. Fares and charges shall be fixed within the governing legal maxima.These principles should govern not only the conduct of the Common Manage-ment, so that if they fail properly to observe them the several undertakings may
intervene for their own protection, but are also intended to be binding upon any arbitrator or other person or body required to decide any matter arising under the scheme.The accounts of the Common Fund and the several undertakings parties to it should be subject to audit by accountants to be appointed for this purpose by agreement or failing agreement by the Minister, such accountants to be members of an incorporated Society of Accountants. The certificates of such accountants should as regards the facts, be final and binding on all parties, and such certificates should state, subject to any comment that may be deemed fitting, whether expenses and charges incurred in respect of each under-taking are reasonable and proper and cause no unfairness as between the several parties. The Common Management should submit to the Minister of Transport an annual report of the operation of the Common Fund and of the several trans-port undertakings covered by it, in such form as the Minister may require.8. Public Control. &quot;With the establishment of a Common Fund and a Common Management, ah effective public control body must be set up to ensure a programme of expansion and development, proper scales of fares, adequate services capable of meeting the needs of the public and sound financial arrange-ments for raising additional capital.The agreements and arrangements made in connection with the Common Fund will inevitably affect the Public, and there may be disputes and differences between the Parties, or with respect to the action of the Common Management, machinery for the settlement of which must be devised.Under the London Traffic Act, 1924, the Minister of Transport, acting with the advice of the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee, is already charged with powers and duties pertinent to the control of London Traffic, and it would therefore seem fitting that such further powers as are required for the purpose of control under this scheme should be added thereto. The Committee, in arriving at this conclusion, have had regard to the wide-spread objection to the setting up of another ad hoc body in London, and to the fact that no existing, local authority has jurisdiction over the whole area. If at a future date Parliament see fit to establish a local authority for Greater London the adoption of the scheme outlined in this Report would not create any obstacle to the transfer of such powers and duties to such authority as Parlia-ment deemed expedient.It is therefore proposed that the Minister should, after consultation with the Committee, settle questions arising with the Common Management, between those engaged in the provision of public transport and the local authorities, and between the proprietors themselves. Many questions thus arising might be of such a character as could be more conveniently dealt with by technical experts and accordingly the Minister should be empowered in such cases to appoint one or more such persons to act as arbitra-tor or referee. Any reference to arbitration in this Report means arbitration by the Minister with the advice of the Committee or by an arbitrator or referee nominated by the Minister.Without derogation of the powers now exercised by the Minister under the London Traffic Act, 1924, or any other Act, additional powers would be required to enable the Minister to deal with questions as to fares and services arising for settlement under the scheme.The London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee now consists of ordinary members representing the central and local governments and of additional members representing specific interests in transport. The additional members representing specific interests should not take part in any vote of the Committee where matters directly affecting the interests which they represent are involved.9. The Local Authorities and Control. In order that the travelling facili-ties to be provided by the several undertakings may, so far as practicable, accord with public needs, provision should be made to enable any local authority within the London Traffic Area to apply to the Minister with respect to any of the following matters: (a) The formulation and revision, from time to time, of a general plan for the development and extension of travelling facilities, the means for carrying such plan into effect and the review of proposals put forward for extension and development with the object of ensuring that these conform with the general plan.
(jb) The consideration of financial questions arising out of any de-velopment, extension or improvement, with the object of ensuring that all additional capital required for such purposes is secured under as advan-tageous conditions as possible.(c) The review of the services furnished by the Common Management so as to ascertain that the provision of travelling facilities is adequate and convenient, having regard to the financial resources available.(d) The determination of a general basis of fares, rates and charges, including the provision, as required, of special fare facilities; for example cheap fares for workmen. Provided always that the fares, rates and charges shall be on such basis as will be sufficient to cover in respect of the combined undertakings not less than the running expenses and ail other expenses of management, maintenance and working, the requisite provision for depreciation and renewal, the fixed interest and other charges in respect of loan, debenture and preferred capital together with a reasonable return in respect of the ordinary capital.The Minister should be required to refer all such applications to the Com-mittee for investigation and if, after considering their advice, it appears to him that some redress or alteration is required, the Minister should be em-powered to make such Order or to give such directions as may be necessary for the purpose and the Common Management and any constituent party shall comply with such Order or directions.Further, it should be provided that any constituent party may at any time make representations to the Minister, that the terms and provisions of the scheme are not being adequately and fairly put into effect, and in such event the Min-ister, after considering the advice of the Committee, shall take such steps as will ensure due and proper observance of the provisions of the scheme.10. Development. The recent Inquiries by the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee into the transport needs of various sectors of London have shown that there is an insistent and justifiable demand for additional rail-way facilities which cannot be met in full because certain of the Eailway Com-panies contend that their financial position, under existing conditions, is not such as would enable them to raise the necessary capital.Given unified management, and efficient operation of the various passenger transport agencies in the London Traffic Area, there is little doubt that the consequent elimination of the present wasteful competition would result in suffi-cient revenue being obtained from the operation of the several undertakings at the present level of fares as to leave, after meeting all legitimate claims and obligations, a margin available to attract fresh capital sufficient to provide for a programme of steady and continuous development of the traffic facilities of the area.It would be the duty of the Common Management, either of its own initiative or by direction of the Minister, to prepare and submit, with all proper informa-tion, plans for improvement and development. Such plans, when approved by the Minister after consultation with the Committee, may be carried out by that constituent party best adapted to the purpose or, in default, by any other party to the scheme securing the necessary powers, it being assumed that, in the first place, existing undertakings would be improved and developed as may be re-quired by the expansion of traffic. The financial terms for the execution of any works must be agreed by the parties or, failing agreement, be settled by the Minister after consultation with the Committee, it being clear that the Min-ister may not require any works to be carried out unless the Common Fund has a margin of resources sufficient to meet the charges likely to fall on it in respect of the additional capital, after allowing for any net revenue to be derived from the new assets.The Common Management should, however, be empowered to carry out such minor works of betterment and improvement as it thinks fit, provided that no fresh powers are required from Parliament or the Central Government, and to charge to revenue or reserve the cost of such works as is properly chargeable thereto.Powers should be conferred upon the local authorities to raise loans for the development of any means of transport comprised in an approved plan.
\Under the proposed operation of the Common Fund, no constituent party undertaking a particular plan of development would secure any direct or special advantage; equally such party would not suffer any direct or special burden. It is intended that once the Common Fund is established the security and terms of future finance would be based upon that Fund and not upon the results of the individual undertakings although the capital issues will continue to be made by the owners of such undertakings.Any* party to the scheme should be quite free to oppose any application made to Parliament or to any Government Department or Commission or Tri-bunal by any of the other parties in respect to any one or more of the under-takings.As it is of the essence of the scheme to provide for the development of traffic facilities within the London Traffic Area, it is equally essential to prevent any traffic facilities being provided which would conflict with the general plan. Only, therefore, where all existing parties to the scheme refuse to undertake developments or to expand services which, in the opinion of the Minister, after considering the advice of the Committee, are desirable, and for which reasonable financial provision can be made under the scheme, should any new transport undertaking, not a party to the scheme, be allowed to provide additional facili-ties in the area. Under the proposed scheme it is unlikely that existing under -takers would fail to provide the necessary developments.So far as railways and tramways are concerned, the necessary powers for development must be secured either from Parliament or from the Central Govern-ment. It may, therefore, be assumed that Parliament, if it grants the powers essential to the establishment of the scheme, would ensure the observance and maintenance of the scheme. So far as omnibuses are concerned, the only powers now available for the protection of the parties are those contained in Section 7 of the London Traffic Act, 1924. These are cumbrous and experimental, and it would appear essential that the Minister should have power, by the control of the licensing of public service vehicles, to take all steps that may be necessary to protect the scheme against disruption or impairment. It should be provided that no additional licences for public service vehicles should be issued by any licensing authority within the London Traffic Area except with the consent of the Minister and on such terms and conditions as he may direct. The Minister of Transport should refer all applications for additional licences to- the Com-mittee for advice and report, and the Committee should be required to give notice of the applications received, to afford opportunity for interested parties to lodge objections and to hear, either by the Committee as a whole or by a Sub-Com-mittee of its members, the case for or against the granting of additional licences.Given these measures of protection, the passenger transport facilities of the area should be developed and expanded in the manner best adapted to meet the needs of the travelling public.11. Period of Operation of Scheme. It will be evident from the outline of the scheme that the period for which it is established must extend over a long term of years even if it should not be permanent. In the first place, alterations may be made in the operation of various undertakings which might, if the scheme were terminated prematurely, be prejudicial to one or more of the parties. In the second place, additional capital would be raised on the security of the Com-mon Fund, which would require to be repaid during the existence of that Fund. In the third place, once a scheme of co-ordination is adopted it would appear a retrograde step to revert to the competitive, unregulated and uneconomic methods now existing. Transport is a public service and must be governed by public considerations.On these grounds the scheme should only be terminated by the substitution of some fresh scheme, which would afford at least equivalent security and protection to both the undertakers and the public, or by the acquisition and amalgamation of all the undertakings by some authority, company or body created by Parlia-ment for the purpose, or by their transfer to municipal or national ownership.It is therefore suggested that provision should be made that the scheme if adopted should continue in operation for a minimum period of 42 years and that it should not be subject to any revision or variation within that period except by general consent of the parties. Any revision or variation agreed by the parties must provide for the compensation, protection and security of all those who may be prejudiced or injured thereby.
12. Government approval of the General Principles 01 the Proposed Scheme. The Committee have not had any formal negotiations with any of the transport undertakers, but from information obtained informally there is every reason to believe that the proposals set out herein provide a basis upon which formal negotiations might be opened with a reasonable prospect of success. It is thought, however, that no useful purpose would be served by attempting to nego-tiate unless the Committee were in a position to indicate the outlines of a scheme, coupled with an assurance that in its main principles it would meet with the approval of the Government, and that if it were generally acceptable to the Local Authorities and Companies concerned, the Government would be prepared either to promote or to support the necessary legislation to enable effect to be given to.it. To open formal negotiations without such assurance from the Government would seriously jeopardise the prospects of any scheme of co-ordination being adopted.The preparation of any detailed scheme, including the ascertainment of the requisite facts and data, would involve the several parties in a considerable amount of time and labour, and it is therefore very doubtful whether they would be pre-pared to undertake the necessary work if there is any risk of the scheme when prepared being summarily rejected.Given Government approval in principle, the scheme could be submitted to the London County Council, the Underground Group of Companies and the Metropolitan Railway Company and, should it prove acceptable to them as the predominant parties, negotiations could then be opened with the other munici-municipalities and companies owning and/or operating passenger transport services either wholly or partly within the London Traffic Area. Negotiations could also be entered into with the Main Line Companies with a view to reaching agree-ment relative to the provisions to be embodied in any Bill to enable any of the constituent parties to the scheme to enter into agreements with these Companies or any of them for the routeing, exchange and clearance of traffic, the provision of through services, the pooling of receipts and also for the leasing and/or work-ing of any of the suburban lines.In conclusion the Committee desire to emphasise their view that this matter is one of extreme urgency, as they feel convinced that no&apos; substantial improve-ment of the travelling facilities in Greater London can be effected until some such scheme as is outlined in this Report can be made effective.The present conditions are rapidly becoming worse and delay can only add to the difficulties of finding a solution, and any formal negotiations with the parties concerned must necessarily take a considerable time. The Committee therefore consider it imperative that they should be authorised to commence them at the earliest possible moment.(Signed)   Henry P. Maybury (Chairman). E. B. Barnard. John Clife. W. G. Davie. A. L. Dixon. Frank Elliott. Henry Jackson. Charles W. Matthews. Henry F. New. Andrew 0&apos;Leary. John Pake man. Frank Pick. Angus N. Scott. Ben Smith. H. S. Turnbull. Joseph H. Turner.j. S. Pool Godsell, (Secretary), 27th July, 1927.Note by Mr. K. E. Chalmers, J.P. I am the representative of the Councils of the Administrative Counties of Kent and Surrey on the Committee.   I was a member of the Sub-Committee
(10/27) (M425r-4Sb)  Wt. 17867-1171  10CO  11/27  H. St. G.71appointed to consider the question of Travelling Facilities in certain areas and a member of the Sub-Committee which enquired into and reported upon the Tra-velling Facilities in North and North-East London. Unfortunately, owing to ill-ness, I have, however, been unable to attend the meetings of the Committee when the subject-matter of this Report was under discussion and, accordingly, I do not consider that I can properly sign it. I have, however, read the whole of the docu-ments circulated to the members of the Committee on this subject and desire to express myself as being in general agreement with the proposals outlined in this Report.(Signed)      Kenneth E. Chalmers.Note by Sir Charles Cleveland, K.C.I.E., K.B.E.Although I am fully conscious that the existing traffic arrangements in London are very unsatisfactory and that important changes are necessary, I regret that I am compelled to record a vote of dissent from the scheme embodied in this Report. I consider that the scheme as planned and described is unsuitable, im-practicable and unfair so far as the omnibus undertakings other than those in-cluded in the Combine are concerned, and I feel certain that they will wish to reserve to themselves the right of protest against the scheme in the further stages through which it must go before it is adopted by the higher authorities.(Signed)      C. R. Cleveland.Note by Sir Herbert Walker.I am not able to sign this report because the Main Line Railway Companies, and the Metropolitan Railway Company whose interests may be seriously involved if the report is given effect to, have not been consulted, and as their representative I am of opinion that they should be left with an entirely free hand to take what steps they may consider necessary to protect their interests when they become aware of the varying recommendations contained in the report.(Signed)      H. A. Walker.

REPORT OF THE LONDON AND HOME COUNTIES TRAFFIC  ADVISORY   COMMITTEE   TO   THE   MINISTEROF  transport in regard toTHE PARLIAMENTARY PRIVATE BILLS PROMOTED BY THE LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL AND THE LONDON ELECTRIC RAILWAY COMPANIES IN THE 1928-29 SESSION OE PARLIA-MENT, intituled The London County Council (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Bill, and the London Electric Railway Companies (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Bill.At our meeting held on the 9th January, 1929, we received the following; Remit from you.&quot; London Traffic. The Minister understands that the members of the Committee have already been supplied with copies of the London County Council (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Bill, 1928, and the London Electric Railway Companies (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Bill, 1928, and he will be glad if the Committee will be so good as to con-sider and report to him upon the proposals contained in these Bills.&quot; We have given careful consideration to this matter, and we have the honour to report as follows : We regard it as essential that any report on these Bills should shortly recapitulate the history of the subject dealt with and in this connection it should be recalled that co-ordination of passenger transport services in the London area in one form or another has been repeatedly urged for about 25 years. Recommendations on this subject were made by the Royal Commission of 1905 and also by the Kennedy-Jones Committee in 1920.More recently the matter was brought prominently to our notice at the Inquiry held in 1925 with respect to the alleged inadequacy of the travelling facilities to and from North and North-East London, at which certain pro-posals were made for a common management of all passenger transport services which appeared to us to present a possible solution of the whole problem of London passenger transport, and we recommended that these proposals should be carefully examined with the least possible delay, and offered to undertake such an examination if you so desired.As a result on the 19th April, 1926, you addressed the following minute to the Chairman of the Committee : &quot;I have further considered the report of the Sub-Committee of the London Traffic Committee on Travelling facilities in London.&quot; I desire to express, in the first instance, my appreciation of the ser-vices which you and the members of the Committee have given in holding this laborious Inquiry, and in the preparation of the able report.&quot; I have noted the suggestion made by the witness for the General Omnibus and Tube Railway Companies that the solution for the traffic difficulties in London is to be found in the extension of the principle of common management and a common fund.*   This proposal raises many* This refers to the Common Fund and Common Management set up by Agreements made under the London Electric Railway Companies Facilities Act, 1915.   The parties to these Agreements are :  City and South London Railway Company.Central London Railway Company. London Electric Railway Company. Metropolitan District Railway Company. London General Omnibus Company, Limited. The preamble to the Act sets out the purposes of the Common Fund as follows : &quot;.....to maintain the requisite services for the convenience of the public andto provide for increased wages and other expenses consequent on the (said) War and toenable further facilities to be afforded.....&quot;The Agreements provide that the working expenses and certain prior charges of the respective Companies shall be met before any distribution of profits. Under this arrangement it has been possible to operate both the Tube Railways and the Omnibuses, both as regards the level of fares and the services provided, as one undertaking with undoubted advantages to the travelling public and the traffic upon the London streets.The Common Fund has also enabled the Companies to improve and extend their Services in a manner which would not otherwise be possible. For example, without the Common Fund and the Common Management it would not have been possible to construct the Edgware and Morden extensions or to modernise the City and South London Tube Railway.3846 A
important and complex issues, the proper examination and elucidation of which was obviously outside the scope of the Committee&apos;s Inquiry. I am therefore not in a position to form any opinion on the proposal, and should not attempt to do so. I agree, however, with the Sub-Committee that a proposal put forward with such authority ought to be fully and impartial-tially examined. I should be glad therefore if the London Traffic Com-mittee would arrange for this or some other Sub-Committee to discuss with the companies and municipalities engaged in the operation of transport undertakings in the London area whether any further co-operation or combined action is possible or desirable.&quot;The subsequent Public Inquiries into travelling facilities to and from East London, and South-East London confirmed our views upon the subject of the desirability of co-ordination, and it may be convenient to quote the first part of the last paragraph of our report on the last of these Inquiries, dated 31st January, 1927, which is as follows : &quot; Unified Control of Local Passenger Transport Services. In pre-vious reports dealing with North and North-East London and East London respectively the Committee expressed the opinion that some scheme for bringing all forms of public passenger transport under unified control appeared to offer the only satisfactory and lasting solution of the whole problem of passenger transport in London.   The evidence adduced at the Inquiry relating to South-East London in our opinion still further emphasises the necessity for such unification.&quot; In accordance with your request of the 19th April, 1926, set out above, we, on the 27th July, 1927, presented to you a report entitled &quot; Report of the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee to the Minister of Transport giving particulars of a scheme for the co-ordination of passenger transport facilities in the London Traffic Area,&quot; which was printed and placed on sale, and is now commonly referred to as &quot; the Blue Report.&quot;In this report, some portions of which will be dealt with in detail later, we put forward a scheme for the co-ordination and consolidation of the passenger transport services of London, with the exception of the Main Line suburban railways (which however, it was considered should be empowered to enter into working agreements with the other transport agencies if they so desired) with such public control as we considered desirable to protect the interests of the community in the matter of (a) level of fares, (&amp;) the adequacy of services, and (c) development to the limit of available resources, and we further recommended that, in order to remove all the sectional financial interests and to ensure that the consolidated services worked efficiently and economically, there should be set up a Common Fund and a Common Management. Our report concluded as follows : &quot; 12. Government approval of the General Principles of the Pro-posed Scheme. The Committee have not had any formal negotiations with any of the transport undertakers, but from information obtained informally there is every reason to believe that the proposals set out herein provide a basis upon which formal negotiations might be opened with a reasonable prospect of success.&quot; It is thought, however, that no useful purpose would be served by attempting to negotiate unless the Committee were in a position to indicate the outlines of a scheme, coupled with an assurance that in its main principles it would meet with the approval of the Government, and that if it were generally acceptable to the Local Authorities and Com-panies concerned, the Government would be prepared either to promote or to support the necessary legislation to enable effect to be given to it. To open formal negotiations without such assurance from the Government would seriously jeopardise the prospects of any scheme of co-ordination being adopted.&quot; The preparation of any detailed scheme, including the ascertain-ment of the requisite facts and data, would involve the several parties in a considerable amount of time and labour, and it is therefore very doubtful whether they would be prepared to undertake the necessary work if there is any risk of the scheme when prepared being summarily rejected.
&quot; Given Government approval in principle, the scheme could be sub-mitted to the London County Council, the Underground Group of Com-panies and the Metropolitan Railway Company, and, should it prove acceptable to them as the predominant parties, negotiations could then be opened with the other municipalities and companies owning and/or operating passenger transport services either wholly or partly within the-London Traffic Area. Negotiations could also be entered into with the Main Line Companies with a view to reaching agreement relative to the provisions to be embodied in any Bill to enable any of the constituent parties to the scheme to enter into agreements with these Companies or any of them for the routeing, exchange and clearance of traffic, the provi-sion of through services, the pooling of receipts and also for the leasing and/or working of any of the suburban lines.&quot; In conclusion the Committee desire to emphasise their view that this matter is one of extreme urgency^ as they feel convinced that no substantial improvement of the travelling facilities in Greater London can be effected until some such scheme as is outlined in this Report can be made effective.&quot; The present conditions are rapidly becoming worse and delay can only add to the difficulties of finding a solution, and any formal negotia-tions with the parties concerned must necessarily take a considerable time. The Committee therefore consider it imperative that they should be authorised to commence them at the earliest possible moment.&quot;In July, 1927, you met the Committee and discussed the report with us. You informed us that you were fully seized of the importance of the matter and the need for urgent action, and stated that you would consider the report and that if you found yourself in agreement with the principles, would submit it to the Government at the earliest possible opportunity.In October, 1927, we were informed that the report had been submitted to the Government and that you had decided to ask the various passenger transport undertakers in the London Traffic Area for their observations on the proposals, in principle.It was reported to us that on the 29th November, 1927, representatives of the Main Line Railway Companies and the Metropolitan Railway Company, at their request, had a conference with you upon this question generally, as a result of which it was arranged that representatives of the Companies should meet the Co-ordination Sub-Committee to consider whether a practical scheme for their inclusion could be devised. The first meeting took place on the 20th December, 1927, when it appeared that the Companies&apos; view was that no form of co-ordination could be satisfactory which did not include their suburban services, but that our proposals as regards a common fund and a common management could not be applied to their undertakings and, as a result of prolonged dis-cussion, the Railway Managers undertook to furnish the Sub-Committee by the 20th January, 1928, with their considered views as to the basis upon which they would be prepared to come into the scheme, and to suggest, in general terms, the form of management which they would propose for dealing with day to day affairs and the constitution of the Committee which could deal with questions-of general policy.A memorandum in accordance with this undertaking and dated 20th January was submitted by the Companies, and a further meeting was held on the 6th February, 1928, when these proposals were discussed at great length. At the conclusion of this meeting the Companies undertook to furnish the Sub-Committee with an exemplification of their proposals which would show what their effect would be.The Companies submitted this exemplification on the 3rd December, 1928. On the 21st December a meeting took place between officers of the Ministry and the representatives of the Railway Companies when this exemplification was discussed and criticised, and it was arranged that the Companies would con-sider these criticisms and furnish their observations thereon. These observations were received on the 18th January, 1929, and the Sub-Committee desire to resume discussions with the Companies at once.3846A a
From the other replies received it became apparent that, with the exception -of. a minority of the omnibus operators, there was general agreement on the principles set out in the &quot; Blue Report.&apos;1In these circumstances and in pursuance of our recommendations in that Report, we understand that you suggested that in the first instance a meeting should take place, between representatives of the London County Council and the Underground Group of Companies as the predominant partae?s (at. any rate apart from the Main Line Railways and the Metropolitan Railway) with a view to ascertaining to what extent agreement could be reached between them, and for this purpose you offered to provide facilities at the Ministry for such a meeting, and also informed the parties that, whilst the Ministry had no desire to be represented at any such discussions, if they so desired, Sir Henry Maybury would act as Chairman at the first meeting to discuss procedure, and he did so at the request of both parties.We have been informed that during the course of these negotiations it was intimated to the promoters, that, having regard to the heavy Government com-niitments in connection with public legislation, it would not be practicable, in any circumstances, for Parliamentary time to be found during the lifetime of the present Parliament for a Government Bill.As a result of this intimation it is understood that the promoters considered to what extent the passenger transport services they provide could be co-ordinated by agreement, but were both advised that they lacked the powers which are now sought in these Bills. By this time it was late in the autumn of 1928, and they accordingly, without reference to the. Ministry, decided to promote the Bills upon which we are now asked to report.We understand that it was lack of time which prevented them from ascer-taining to what extent other transport agencies would have been prepared to join with them in seeking similar powers, or would be prepared to avail them-selves of the powers sought to be conferred upon them to enter into agreements with the promoters with a- view to a complete or more extensive co-ordination scheme than one which embraced only the undertakings of the promoters. We understand, however, that the London County Council took an early opportunity to meet the other local authorities owning or operating transport undertakings in the area to discuss this matter with them, and that negotiations are actively proceeding.Before commenting on these Bills we desire to make it quite clear that we adhere to the scheme outlined in the &quot; Blue Report &quot; as being the proper solu-tion of the London Passenger Transport problem, and desire to recommend that in any event effect should be given to the whole of the recommendations contained in that report at the earliest available opportunity.Dealings with these two Bills we understand that we are asked to report whether, in our opinion, private legislation of this nature is desirable and, if so, what if any amendments to the Bills we consider necessary:In the first place we wish to draw attention to the main points in which the scheme under the Bills differs from the scheme outlined in the &quot; Blue Report,&quot; and, apart from minor points, these may be summarised under the two following heads: (1) the &quot; Blue Report &quot; envisaged all the passenger transport under-takings, with the exception of the Main Line suburban railways, coming at the same time into a co-ordinated scheme with a Common Pool and a Common Management; (2) it provided for Public Control as set out in paragraph 8 of the &quot; Blue Report,&quot; which is as follows : Extract from the Report of the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee to the Minister of Transport. &quot;8. Public Control. With the establishment of a Common Fund and a Common Management, an effective public control body must be set up to ensure a programme of expansion and development, proper scales of fares, adequate services capable of meeting the needs of the public and sound financial arrangements for raising additional capital.The agreements and arrangements made in connection with the Common Fund will inevitably affect the Public, and there may be dis-putes and differences between the Parties, or with respect to the action
of the Common Management, machinery for the settlement of which must be devised.&quot; Under the London Traffic Act, 1924, the Minister of Transport, acting with the advice of the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee, is already charged with powers and duties pertinent to the control of London Traffic, and it would therefore seem fitting that such further powers as are required for the purpose of control under this scheme should be added thereto. The Committee, in arriving at this con-elusion, have had regard to the widespread objection to the setting up of another &apos; ad hoc &apos; body in London, and to the fact that&apos;no existing local authority has jurisdiction over the whole area. If at a future date Parliament see fit to establish a local authority for Greater London the adoption of the scheme outlined in this Report would not create any obstacle to the transfer of such powers and duties to such authority as Parliament deemed expedient.&quot;It is therefore proposed that the Minister should, after consulta-tion with the Committee, settle questions arising with the Common Management, between those engaged in the provision of public transport and the local authorities, and between the proprietors themselves. Many questions thus arising might be of such a character as could be more conveniently dealt with by technical experts and accordingly the Minister should be empowered in such cases to appoint one or more such persons to act as arbitrator or referee. Any reference to arbitration in this Report means arbitration by the Minister with the advice of the Committee or by an arbitrator or referee nominated by the Minister.&quot; Without derogation of the powers now exercised by the Minister under the London Traffic Act, 1924, or any other Act, additional powers would be required to enable the Minister to deal with questions as to fares and services arising for settlement under the scheme.&quot; The London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee now consists of ordinary members representing the central and local govern-ments and of additional members representing specific interests in trans-port. The additional members representing specific interests should not take part in any vote of the Committee where matters directly affecting the interests which they represent are involved.&quot;We understand that the promoters are in agreement with our recommenda-tions on the two points referred to above but they are advised that it is not prac-ticable to give effect to them by private Bill legislation, because, upon the first point, it is obvious that no private promoter could obtain powers to compel other undertakers to enter into agreements with them, though the Bills do in fact confer enabling powers upon the other undertakers to enter into agreement with the two promoters if they are willing to do so.Further, with regard to the second point, we understand that it would not be practicable, under private Bill legislation, to set up public control in the form and with the scope referred to in the &quot; Blue Report &quot; as set out above.The Bills, however, provide for the submission of drafts of any agree-ments made under them to both Houses of Parliament and also give to local authorities the right to &quot; make representations to the Minister with respect to any action taken under any agreement entered into affecting the area or district of such authority and involving &quot;(1)   In the case of the London Electric Railway Companies Bill: &quot; (a) the alteration of the general scheme of fares, rates or charges, or(b) the withdrawal of services, or(c) the order or priority of developments and extensions,&quot; and (2)   In the case of the London County Council Bill :  &quot; (a) the alteration of the general standard of fares, rates or charges, or (b) the withdrawal of services.&quot; It should be noted, however, that in the L.C.C. Bill provision is made for local authorities to &quot;at any time make representations to the Minister with respect to the need for developments or extensions in the area or district of such authority.&quot;3846 A 3
It is thought that these provisions in the Bills may be considered to implement to some extent the intentions of paragraph 8 of the &quot; Blue Report &quot; if regard is had to the more confined scope of the scheme contemplated by the draft Bills.In these circumstances we have examined the matter from the point of view of whether the need for co-ordination is such that, if the whole scheme cannot be given effect to as proposed, it is worth while or desirable to permit of this partial co-ordination as a temporary measure at any rate, without the safe-guards and control in the form and with the scope outlined in the &quot; Blue Report &quot; to which, we understand, effect cannot be given by private bill legislation.In considering this aspect of the problem we think regard should be had to two considerations, (i) the amount of co-ordination which may be effected under these Bills, and (ii) the prospects of obtaining legislation giving effect to the recommendations in the &quot; Blue Report &quot; as a whole, in the near future.As regards the former it is important to note the following data in regard to passengers carried by the transport agencies of the Underground Group and the London County Council trams in relation to the other agencies in the London Traffic area.Taking all omnibus, tramway and railway undertakings, including the Metropolitan Railway and the Main Line suburban railways, the Underground Group and the L.C.C. tramways carry 77 per cent, of the passengers.Taking all omnibus, tramway and railway undertakings, including the Metropolitan Railways but excluding Main Line suburban railways, the Underground Group and the L.C.C. tramways carry 86 per cent, of the passengers.The number of passengers carried is, however, not the only factor which should be taken into consideration in determining the relative importance of the various undertakings as, for example, it does not have regard to the capital invested in the undertakings or to the extent of their operations.The figures do show, however, that, if these undertakings were unified and brought under Common Management and their services and receipts pooled, a considerable measure of co-ordination will have been secured and it might well be that some, if not all, of the otherundertakers, including the Main Line Rail-ways and the Metropolitan Railway Company, will enter into agreements with these two promoters under the powers sought by the Bills.In considering whether the proposed measure of co-ordination contemplated under these Bills should be accepted as a first step, or whether they should be resisted until opportunity is afforded for the introduction of a public measure to give effect to the terms of the &quot; Blue Report,&quot; we must perforce have regard to the importance from the traffic point of view of the two undertakings con-trolled by the promoters of these Bills, and also as to whether legislation of a general character is likely in the near future, which appears to us to be at least problematical. The justification for their promotion is that they will facilitate the early provision of additional through-travelling facilities.In our view these Bills do not contain any provisions which would prevent, so soon as a suitable opportunity arises, the scheme put forward in the &quot; Blue Report &quot; being given effect to and, having regard to the urgency of the problem and on the distinct understanding that the larger scheme should be given effect to so soon as practicable, we consider that, in principle, you should be advised to assist their passage, subject, of course, to such amendments being made as will, so far as is practicable in private Bills, strengthen the safeguards necessary in the interests of the public.In arriving at this conclusion we are actuated by one consideration only, and that is the urgent and pressing need for the provision of additional through-travelling facilities by high-speed electric trains, etc., to the outer areas in accordance with the recommendation contained in the Travelling Facilities Inquiries Reports, and, if some measure of co-ordination to avoid &quot;uneconomic and wasteful competition is effected, the extension of travelling facilities will then be rendered possible.The whole problem is all the more urgent as the traffic conditions, bad though they are at present in certain areas, are rapidly becoming worse, and it must be borne in mind that, &quot;even when a decision is arrived at to provide new facilities
such as tube extensions, it will be necessary to obtain Parliamentary powers to construct them and, even when these are obtained, their construction will necessarily take some years.Upon the details of the Clauses in these Bills we desire to make the f follow-ing observations but, in criticising the promoters&apos; proposals, we wish it to be understood that our observations relate exclusively to the scope and terms of the measures before Parliament. Obviously their operation must depend, very largely upon the nature and terms of any agreements arrived at under them, as to which we have no information.This observation applies of course equally to any agreements which may be made between the promoters or either of them *and the other transport agencies. In this connection, it appears to us that any agreements arrived at between the promoters are likely to determine or at least influence the basis upon which other undertakers, and in particular the local authorities affected, can enter into agreements with them, because, as previously stated, it was lack of time which prevented the other undertakers being more closely consulted, before the Bills were deposited. In our view, provision should be made to ensure that they should be permitted within a reasonable period to enter into agreements with the promoters on a basis not less favourable than the basis embodied in any agreement between the promoters. Indeed the principles of such agreements are fundamental and therefore the following observations are dependent thereon : Clause 4. We desire to draw attention to the fact that under Clause 4 of the Bills it is provided that the draft agreements shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament for a period of 30 days. We feel that, having regard to the importance of these agreements, it would be desirable for you to have an opportunity of considering them before they are laid before Parliament and accordingly suggest that any draft agreements proposed to be made shall be submitted direct to you for your information and that you should, within 14 days after receipt, be required to lay them before Parliament.We note that this provision is not to apply to any agreement with respect to which you certify that it is supplemental or incidental to a valid agreement already subsisting, and that if you shall not within 10 days from the date of the submission to you of such an agreement intimate to the parties submitting it your refusal to grant such a certificate, you shall be deemed, at the expiration of the said period of 10 days, to have granted such a certificate. In our view this period of time is inadequate, and we suggest that it should be extended to at least 14 days and that it should be made clear that the proviso does not apply to any agreement which would vary the basis of the existing agreement as, for example, by the introduction of fresh parties, the alteration of the definition and/or amount of &quot; ranking capital &quot; or of the &quot; reasonable return &quot; of such capital, or the like.Clauses 9 and 10 of the Council&apos;s Bill; 9, 10 and 11 of the Companies&apos; Bill.  We attach the greatest importance to these Clauses and it will be observed that their proposals, with regard to development in particular, differ to such an extent that they cannot easily be reconciled.(a) Development. The London County Council in their Bill appear to have tried, so far as possible, to implement the proposals in the &quot; Blue Report,&quot; but, in our view, the proposals in Clause 10 of the Companies&apos; Bill are to be preferred. It is true that they are not so specific, but it is considered that to make them too definite might defeat the object desired, namely, the early provision of additional facilities. There are good features in both clauses, and we recom-mend that a meeting should be arranged with the representatives of the promoters with a view to the drafting of a new clause for insertion in both Bills embodying these features.In this connection we are of opinion that it should be made clear that repre-sentations to you may be made by the appropriate authority in respect of &apos;&apos; inade-quacy of services &quot; in addition to any representations such authority may make in respect of any action taken by the parties to any agreements entered into under the powers sought and involving &quot; the order or priority of developments
and extensions.&quot; This would ensure the question of inadequate services receiv-ing full consideration, having regard to the resources of the parties to the agree-ments, concurrently with developments and extensions.It is suggested that the parties to any agreements under the Bills should be required to submit to you for consideration by the Committee a comprehensive scheme for traffic development in the whole area to cover say the next five years, and that in conjunction with the Common Management an order of priority should be determined, and that the Common Management should carry out their developments in accordance with that plan as and when practicable.These proposals should be reviewed annually and the Common Management should report the progress they have made and indicate what steps they propose to take in the ensuing year. On such annual review the priority might be varied in the light of any changes in the travelling facilities required.We realise that it is not practicable to insert any provisions which would enable you to compel the promoters or other undertakers entering into the scheme to carry out desired developments, but we are not apprehensive on this point because we are convinced that the undertakers will be only anxious to carry out developments so soon as they are in a position to do so, and pressure of public opinion will be sufficient to ensure their developing their undertakings to the limit of their resources.Further, it is material to bear in mind that no substantial development can be carried out by the undertakers without their obtaining additional powers from Parliament, and any Bills promoted by them for this purpose obviously provide a valuable opportunity for reviewing the manner in which they hav6 exercised their powers and constitute an effective check in the nature of public control of their activities.(b) Appeals to Minister. It is not clear to us why an appeal to you by local authorities, so far as services are concerned, is limited to &quot; withdrawal of services,&quot; which it is assumed means &quot; a total withdrawal of a service,&quot; and it is considered that this provision should be extended to make provision for appeals in the case of reduction in existing services.With regard to appeals relative to the alteration of the general scheme of fares, rates and charges, it is assumed that generally there will be a uniform rate of fare for various stages on the tubes, trams and omnibuses which will work out at approximately so much per mile, and the question whether such a flat rate is excessive or otherwise will immediately be reflected in the financial position of the undertakers.We recommend that the undertakers, if they desire to increase the general level of fares, should, before doing so, be required to satisfy you (after consulta-tion with London Traffic Advisory Committee) that such increase is necessary.(c) London Traffic Advisory Committee.-We observe that Sub-clause 9 of Clause 10 of the CounciFs Bill provides that the additional Members of the London Traffic Advisory Committee shall not take part in the proceedings of that Committee in connection with Clause 10.We feel that this provision goes much further than the recommendation set out in paragraph 8 of the &quot; Blue Report &quot; and that what appears to be an important amendment of the London Traffic Act should not be effected by this private Bill, and accordingly recommend that it be deleted.GENERAL OBSERVATIONS. In conclusion we think that we should draw attention to the increasing tendency there has been in recent years towards amalgamations and co-ordina-tions in transport which have been approved by Parliament when it has been necessary for them to consider this problem.In this connection we would again refer to the Underground Railways Act, 1915, to The Railways Act, 1921, amalgamating the Railways into four main line groups and the Railway Road Transport Bills of last session under which
Os9 0(J i-j wvery extensive and comprehensive agreements are being made between the Rail-way Companies and Passenger Road Transport Agencies, examples of which are the recent reported agreements between the Sheffield Corporation and the Railway Companies operating in that area as to road passenger transport ser-vices and the agreement reached between the Great Western Railway Company and the Omnibus Companies operating in their area for joint workings.(Signed) HENRY P. MAYBURY (Chairman). E. B. BARNARD. W. G. DAVIE.A. L. DIXON. FRANK ELLIOTT. EDWARD J. HOLLAND. HENRY JACKSON.w. f. mallender. JOHN PAKEMAN.B. J. SAMELS.H. S. TURNBULL. JOSEPH H. TURNER.J. S. POOL GODSELL(Secretary).beoervation BY MR.  C.   W.  MATTHEWS, MR.  FRANK PICK,AND MR. A.  N.  SCOTT.We have refrained from signing the Report because we represent upon the Committee the promoters of the Bills under consideration. We do not dissent from the terms of the Report and are prepared to recommend to our respective undertakings the acceptance of the specific amendments included in the Report in so far as they are applicable to the Bills.(Signed) CHARLES W. MATTHEWS. FRANK PICK. ANGUS N. SCOTT.fjora -reservation BY MR. J. E. BINKS,  MR. JOHN CLIFF ANDALDERMAN BEN SMITH, M.P.We desire to state that for the reasons given hereunder we are unable to concur in the recommendations of our colleagues&apos;&apos; that in principle the Minister should be advised to assist the passage of these Bills.&quot;The Promoters of the Bills, in common with the other local authorities con-cerned, have accepted and are presumably still willing to accept the recommenda-tions contained in the Blue Report, namely : (1)   &quot; that an effective public control body must be set up etc.&quot; (as set out in paragraph 8 of the Blue Report).(2)   &quot; that the passenger transport undertakings, with the exception of the &apos; amalgamated railways &apos; should all be brought into the common fund, with its common management.&quot; Further, the Minister of Transport has accepted the Blue Report.   He is a member of the Government which, given the will, has the power to initiate and enact public legislation giving effect to the recommendations in the Report, including the setting up of an effective Public Control Body.For these reasons it appears to us that it is the duty of the Government to promote immediate legislation which will give effect to the principles outlined in the Report.(Signed) J. E. BINKS.JOHN CLIFF. BEN SMITH.
RESERVATION BY MR. W. F. MALLENDER. I regret that I am unable to concur in the recommendations of my colleagues in so far as these recommendations advise the ultimate adoption of the Scheme known as the Blue Report, a scheme which the Association I represent was advised was calculated to stifle private enterprise and appropriate the property of the individual without adequate compensation.In so far as the recommendations are directed to the two Bills before Parlia-ment I generally concur in such recommendations, being of opinion that the Bills as at present framed will be a contribution to the Solution of the London Traffic Problem.The Bills are, however, drawn in such wide and general terms that it is impossible, in my opinion to judge their ultimate effect, and everything must depend upon the agreements which may be made by the Bills.(Signed)   W. F. MALLENDER.fareREOERVATION  BY  SIR  HERBERT  WALKER.As the Main Line Railway Companies have decided to oppose the London County Council (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) and the London Electric Railway Companies&apos; (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Bills, 1928/9, I find myself unable to sign this Report.(Signed) H. A. WALKER.(3846-12)  Wt. T2584  125  2/29 P. St.  Q. 3
19 &amp; 20 George V.Session 1928-9LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL(CO-ORDINATION OF PASSENGER TRAFFIC).ARRANGEMENT OF SECTIONS.Section.Preamble.	Short title        ...........................	1Interpretation   ...	2Agreements with regard to common management and common fund   ...	3Conditions as to validity of agreements	4Principles to govern management of associated undertakings	5Application of common fund ...      ...      ...      ...	6Audit of accounts......................	7Appointment of members of Council and local authorities on certain bodies	coPower to certain authorities to make representations	9Development or extension of associated undertakings     ......	10Compensation to existing officers and servants of the Council   ...	11Settlement of differences       .........      ............	12Saving for existing obligations affecting the undertaking of the Council	13As to payments under this Act	14Schedule.300.   T P. 18-18.   22/1/29
39 oABILLTo empower the London County Council and local authorities and others owning or working railways tramways light railways trolley vehicles or omnibuses within or partly within the London traffic area to enter into agreements with reference to their undertakings ; and for other purposes.&quot;^TTHEREAS  the London County Council (in this Aci, called Preamble.&quot; the Council &quot;) own and operate under statutory powers practically the whole of the tramways in the Administrative County of London (hereinafter referred to as &quot; the County &quot;) :5 And whereas pursuant to arrangements between the Council and other tramway undertakers the Council operate services over other tramways outside the County and certain of such other undertakers operate services over tramways of the Council within the County :And whereas the routes served by the tramways of the Council 10 are to a large extent also served by railways and omnibuses employed in the local transport of passengers within or partly within the London traffic area :And whereas the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee established under the London Traffic Act 1924 with a15 view to facilitating and improving the regulation of traffic in and near London have held a number of inquiries into the question of providing and improving facilities in various districts of London and have made certain recommendations thereon including recommendations as to the desirability in the interests of the travelling public of the adoption20 by the authorities companies bodies and persons engaged in the transport of passengers in the London Traffic Area of a scheme embodying the principles of common management and a common fund :
And whereas it would be in accordance with the said recommenda-tions and is expedient that the Council and such other authorities companies bodies and persons as aforesaid should be empowered to enter into and carry into effect such agreements as are referred to in this Act with a view to the co-ordination of the traffic of the said 5 London Traffic Area and the provision of new and improved facilities :And whereas the purposes aforesaid cannot be attained without the authority of Parliament :MAY IT THEREFORE PLEASE YOUR MAJESTYThat it may be enacted and be it enacted by the King&apos;s Most 10 Excellent Majesty by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament assembled and by the authority of the same as follows :  short title 1.   This Act may be cited as the London County Council(Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Act 1929. 15interpretation. 2.   In this Act unless the subject or context otherwise requires The expression &quot; the Council &quot; means the London County Council ;The expression &quot; local authority &quot; meens the council of any country or of any county or other municipal borough or 20 urban or rural district;The expression &quot; The City Corporation&quot; means the mayor aldermen and commons of the City of London in common council assembled;The expression &quot; the London traffic area &quot; means the London 25 traffic area as constituted from time to time under the London Traffic Act 1924  or any Act amending the same ;The expression &quot; undertaking&quot; where used in relation to the Council means the tramway undertaking of ,the 30 Council as authorised from time to time including all tramways for the time being owned or worked by or leased to them ;
Q 9 1O k4 OThe expression &quot; the associated undertakings&quot; means the undertakings or parts of undertakings with reference to which an agreement entered into under this Act is for the time being in force and the expression  &quot; associated 5 &quot; undertaking &quot; means any one of such undertakings or parts of undertakings ;The expression &quot; common fund &quot; means the common fund established under any agreement entered into under this Act ;10 The expression &quot; ranking capital &quot; means as respects each ofthe associated undertakings such sum or sums as may be determined under a formula contained in the agreement relating to that associated undertaking or specified in such agreement as representing moneys expended on capital15 account upon or in respect or for the purposes of thatassociated undertaking or capital issued or moneys borrowed or otherwise raised or applied for the purpose of such expenditure together with such reserves or other funds moneys shares stocks securities or credits20 (if any) as  may be so specified  or determined  but excluding any shares stocks mortgages debentures debenture stocks or other securities or sums of money or credits on which dividends or interest are or is under the provisions of such agreement to be payable out of the2g receipts and revenues of that associated undertakingbefore ascertaining the amount to be paid into the common fund in respect of that associated undertaking ;The expression &quot; reasonable return &quot; means such rate or rates of interest as may be  30 (a)- determined under any formula for that purposecontained in the agreement entered into under this Act in relation to which the expression is used ; or (b) specified in such agreement as a proper return upon or in respect of the ranking 35 capital;The expression &quot; the Minister&quot; means the Minister of Transport ;The  expression   &quot; the  Advisory  Committee&quot;   means  the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee 40 established under the London Traffic Act 1924 as con-stituted from time to time.
(a) the management maintenance operation running over user 10repair development extension improvement and renewal of the whole or part of their respective undertaldngs including the provision of buildings rolling stock and other equipment the interchange of traffic the fixing (subject to the authorised maximum fares rates and charges if any) collection appor- 15 tionment and distribution of fares rates and charges on traffic and other receipts and revenues of such undertakings or parts of undertakings and the payments to be made to or by and the conditions to be performed by all or any of the parties to the agreement; 20(b) the allocation and apportionment of traffic (including receiptstherefrom and expenses in connection therewith) to from or over any of the undertakings or parts of undertakings to which the agreement relates (which undertakings or parts of undertakings are in this section referred to as &quot;the 25 &quot; undertakings &quot;) ;(c) the establishment of a common fund and the payment into that fund of (i) the whole or part of the balance of the receipts and revenues of each of the undertakings remaining 30 after making or discharging or providing for the making or discharge of such payments liabilities and obligations as may be specified or provided for in the agreement and making such other provision (if any) as may be so specified or provided for ; 35 orAgreements with 3,    (1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any other Actmanagement and     Or in any Order the Council on the one hand and any local authoritycommon fund. tt e . . .      . . . ,.&apos;companjr body or person from time to tune owning or working (whether under statutory powers or not) any railway tramway light railway trolley vehicle or omnibus undertaking established for the 5 time being within or partly within the London traffic area on the other hand may enter into carry into effect va,ry and rescind agree-ments with each &apos;other for and with respect to all or any of the following purposes (that is to say) 
(ii) (a) the whole or part of the balance of the receipts and revenues of each of the undertakings (so far as  such  receipts and revenues  are not payable into any other common fund) remaining after making 5 or discharging or providing for the making or dis-charge of such payments liabilities and obligations as may be specified or provided for in the agreement and making such other provision (if any) as may be so specified or provided for ; and10 (b) (in   any  case   in   which   the   whole   or   partof the receipts and revenues of any of the under-takings is payable into any other common fund) the whole or part of the sums from time to time payable out of such other common fund to such of15 the parties to the agreement as are entitled to receivepayments thereout ;(d) the control management distribution and application of thecommon fund ;(e) the exercise with reference to anjr of the undertakings of any 20 powers  or rights exercisable  otherwise  than under theprovisions of this Act ;(/) the exercise by any board of directors joint committee or other body of all or any of the powers and duties of the parties to the agreement or any of those parties with respect 25 to the undertakings or any of them :(g) the   appointment   of   an   advisory  board  consisting   ofrepresentatives of the said parties or any of them for such purposes as may be provided by the agreement;(h) the leasing or taking on lease of the whole or part of the 30 undertaking of any company body or person not being apartjr to the agreement ; and(i) generally all such matters and things as may be necessaryfor carrying out all or any of the purposes aforesaid.(2) Every such agreement shall either prescribe a formula for 35 determining or shall specify the amount of the ranking capital with reference to each of the undertakings and the reasonable return on such ranking capital but notwithstanding any other provision
Conditions as to validity of agree-ments.of this Act no such agreement shall have any force or effect unless and until the formula prescribed therein for determining the reasonable return or the reasonable return specified therein (as the case may be) shall have received such approval as the Minister shall direct.4. (1) Except as hereinafter provided an agreement entered 5 into under this Act shall not be valid until it shah have been laid before each House of Parliament for a period of thirty days during which that House is sitting and if either such House before the expiration of that period presents an address to His Majesty against the agreement the agreement shall thereupon become null and void. 10 Provided that nothing in this section shall preclude all or any of the parties to an agreement against which an address has been so presented from entering into a new agreement (either with or without the addition of any other party or parties) to which the foregoing provisions of this sub-section shall apply. 15Provided also that the foregoing provisions of this sub-section shall not apply to any agreement entered into under this Act with respect to which the Minister shall certify that it is supplemental or incidental to a valid agreement already subsisting and that if the Minister shall not within ten days from the date of the submission 20 to him of any such agreement intimate to the party or parties sub-mitting the same his refusal to grant such a certificate with reference thereto he shall be deemed at the expiration of the said period of ten days to have granted a certificate with reference to that agreement to the effect hereinbefore mentioned. 25(2) If with reference to any agreement entered into under this Act no such address is presented within either of the said periods of thirty days or the Minister does not within the said period of ten days intimate his refusal to grant his certificate (as the case may be) then as from the date or latest date on which the said periods 30 of thirty days expire or as from the date on which the Minister grants or is pursuant to this section deemed to have granted his certificate with reference to that agreement the agreement shall subject to the provisions of this Act be valid and may be carried into effect.(3) An agreement entered into under this Act to which a 35. company is a party shall not be valid unless and until such agreement shall have been approved by a resolution passed by three-fourths of the votes of the proprietors of such company entitled to vote who are present in person or by proxy at a general meeting of such company specially convened for the purpose. 40*
5.   The associated undertakings shall be managed maintained Prmoipies to govern0 0 management ofoperated repaired extended improved and renewed in accordance associated under-x takings.with the following principles : (a) The associated undertakings shall at all times be maintained 5 in good and efficient working order and condition and be operated as a unified system of transport so that adequate travelling facilities are provided for the public ;(&amp;) When any general scheme of fares rates and charges applicable to the associated undertakings shall be determined such10 scheme shall (subject to the authorised maximum faresrates and charges if any) be applied as far as practicable on a uniform basis with reference to all those undertakings except where special circumstances affecting the traffic or the cost of making provision for the traffic  justify  a15 differentiation ;(c) The associated undertakings shall at all times be so managed and worked and such fares rates and charges shall (subject to the authorised maximum fares rates and charges if any) at all times be charged that the aggregate earnings of 20 the associated undertaldngs shaU so far as practicablebe sufficient to meet all proper charges against them includ-ing adequate provision for depreciation obsolescence or renewal and a reasonable return on or in respect of the ranking capital.25        6.   Every agreement entered into under this Act and providing Application of for the establishment of a common fund shall provide that during the oommon fund-continuance of the agreement any balance which remains in the common fund after (a) paying or making provision for the payment of 30 (i) the expenses in connection with the management ofthe common fund ;  and(ii) any sum or sums representing the amount by which the revenue of the associated undertaldngs or any of them shall be insufficient for making or discharging 35. or providing for the making or discharge of such payments liabilities and obligations as may be specified or provided for in the agreement and the making of such other provision Cif any) as may be so specified or provided for ; and
Appointment of members of Council and local authorities on certain, bodies.(b) paying to the respective parties to the agreement such sums as the said parties may determine not exceeding amounts representing a reasonable return upon the ranking capitalshall be applied in such manner as may be agreed between the parties to the agreement or as (failing such agreement) shall be settled 5 by arbitration in the improvement of the associated undertakings and in maintaining or extending the efficiency and usefulness thereof in the public interest including any one or more of the following purposes (a) the development  or extension of the associated 10 undertakings or any of them or any parts thereof and the making of financial provision for facilitating the  raising   of  additional  capital  or moneys for those purposes ;(b) the reduction of fares and other charges ; 15(c) the provision of a general reserve to meet contin-gencies ;(d) such other purposes as may be approved by the Minister.Audit of accounts 7. (i) The accounts in respect of each associated undertaking 20and of the common fund established under the agreement relating to that undertaking and of any other common fund referred to in the agreement shall be made up at least once in every year and shall be audited by an auditor or auditors to be agreed upon by the parties to that agreement or (in ^case of difference) to be 25 appointed by the Minister and every auditor so agreed upon or appointed shall be a Chartered Accountant or a member of the Society of Incorporated Accountants and Auditors. The auditor or auditors so agreed upon or appointed shall be entitled to require from the said parties to such agreement all such papers books 30 accounts vouchers information and explanations as may be necessary for the performance of his or their duties.(2) It shall not for any purpose be necessary to audit under any other enactment accounts audited under the provisions of this section. 358. (1) The Council and any local authority being a party to any agreement entered into under this Act may pursuant to any provisions to that effect contained in the agreement and subject to such terms and conditions as they may think fit appoint any of their members
9.   (1) For  the  protection of  the public interest the   City Power to certain. , authorities to makeCorporation or any local authority whose area or district is wholly representations. 20 or partly within the London traffic area may at any time make representations to the Minister with respect to any action taken under any agreement entered into under this Act affecting the area or district of such authority and involving (a) the alteration of the general standard of fares rates or 25 charges ; or(b) the withdrawal of servicesand the Minister if he deems fit may thereupon cause an inquiry to be held into the matter by the Advisory Committee.(2) If as a result of any such inquiry the Minister is of opinion 30 that such alteration of the general standard of fares rates or charges or withdrawal of services is unnecessary or undesirable he may prohibit such alteration or withdrawal and effect shall be given to the decision of the Minister by the parties to the agreement but in the absence of any such prohibition such alteration or withdrawal 35 may be carried into effect. Provided that in arriving at his decision the Minister shall be bound by the principles mentioned in the section of this Act of which the marginal note is &quot; Principles to govern management of associated undertakings.&quot;as members of any board of directors or of any joint committee advisory board or other body (whether constituted for the purposes of the agreement or already existing) to which under the terms of the agreement there are entrusted the exercise of any of the 5 powers and duties of the parties to the agreement or any of them or any advisory duties in connection with the carrying out of the agreement.(2) Any member of the Council or of any local authority holding any appointment pursuant to this section and entitled to receive or10 having received any remuneration in respect of such appointment shall not be deemed to hold or to have held an office or place of profit in the gift or disposal of the Council or such local authority if he undertakes to pay and pays or has paid to the Council or such local authority the remuneration (excluding any allowance for or in15 respect of travelling or subsistence expenses) so received by him in respect of the period during which as a member of the Council or of such^local authority he held such appointment.
Development 10.   (1) When and so often as the parties to any agreementof f^oeiated entered into under this Act determine or the Minister by notice inundertakings. writing to the parties to any such agreement requires that the associated undertakings or any of them shall be developed or extended it shall be the duty of the said parties to submit to the Minister 5 proposals for such development or extension accompanied by such plans and information as shall be requisite for the consideration of such proposals.- (2) The City Corporation or any local authority whose area or district is wholly or partly within the London traffic area may 10 at any time make representations to the Minister with respect to the need for developments or extensions in the area or district of such authority and the Minister when making under the preceding sub-section any requirement on the parties to any agreement shall take into consideration any representations so received. 15(3) Such proposals as aforesaid shall not be carried into effect unless and until the same have been approved by the Minister or otherwise than subject to such modifications and conditions (if any) as the Minister in giving his approval may direct or prescribe. Provided that the Minister shall not direct or prescribe any 20 modification or condition which would conflict with any of the principles set forth in the section of this Act of which the marginal note is &quot; Principles to govern management of associated undertakings.&quot;(4) Any of the parties to any such agreement as aforesaid desiring to object to or make representations with reference to any 25 such proposals may do so in writing and any objections or represen-tations so made shall be submitted to the Minister with the said proposals.(5) Before giving his decision upon any proposals submitted to him as aforesaid the Minister shall refer such proposals and any such 30 objections or representations as aforesaid to the Advisory Committee for examination and report and shall take into consideration airy such objections or representations and any report submitted to him by that  Committee,  upon   the   proposals   so   referred   to them.   Provided that before making their report to the Minister upon 35. any such proposals as aforesaid the Advisory Committee shall take such steps as the Minister may direct for affording to any local authority whom he may consider to be affected by such proposals and to the City Corporation in any case in which the Minister may consider that they are so affected an opportunity of making representations 40 with reference thereto and that any representations so made shall be submitted to the Minister by the Advisory Committee with their report.
(6) Any development or extension of an associated undertaking may with the consent of the other parties to the agreement be carried out by the party owning such associated undertaking and if such consent be withheld or refused a question shall be deemed 5 to have arisen between the party owning such undertaking and the party or parties withholding or refusing consent which shall be settled by arbitration.(7) From and after the carrying out of any development or extension of an associated undertaking the associated undertaking10 as so developed or extended shall on such terms and conditions (including terms and conditions in regard to ranking capital and charges on revenue or capital account and otherwise) as may be agreed to by the parties to the agreement or settled by arbitration be deemed to be the associated undertaking included in any such15 agreement and all necessary adjustments and variations shall be made in the agreement.(8) The foregoing provisions of this section shall apply only to proposals developments or extensions involving a continuing or recurring charge on the receipts and revenues of the associated20 undertakings or any of them or a charge on capital account affecting such receipts and revenues and nothing in this section shall require any such approval or consent as aforesaid to the development or extension of an associated undertaking by the owner of that undertaking where such development or extension does not25 involve any such charge.(9) For the purposes of this section the additional members of the Advisory Committee referred to in section 1 of the London Traffic Act 1924 shall not take part in the proceedings of that Committee.11.   (1) Any person (being at the date of the passing of this Compensation to] 30 Act an officer or servant of the Council) whose service under the servants of the Council is terminated in pursuance or hi consequence of any agree-  oun01* ment entered into under this Act shall be entitled to have compensa-tion paid to him by the Council in respect of any direct pecuniary loss (including the loss of any prospective superannuation or other 35 retiring or death allowance or gratuity or of any prospective allowance or gratuity to his widow family or representatives whether payable pursuant to any legal obligation or power of the Council or to the customary practice of the Council) which he may suffer by reason of such termination but the compensation shall not exceed the 40 amount which under the Acts and rules relating to Her Majesty&apos;s
Civil Service which were in operation at the date of the passing of the Local Government Act 1888 was payable to a person on abolition of office.(2) Any person (being at the date of the passing of this Act an officer or servant of the Council)  5(a) whose service under the Council is terminated in pursuance or in consequence of any agreement entered into under this Act; and(&amp;) who at the date of such termination was a contributor to the Superannuation and Provident Fund established 10 by the Council under the provisions of Part IV of the London Council (General Powers) Act 1891 as amended or extended by any other Act; and(c) who is as from the date of such termination of serviceemployed in connection with the associated undertakings ; 15 and(d) whose   employment   in   connection  with  the  associatedundertakings is determined within a period of five years from the date of the termination of his service under the Council or whose salary wages and emoluments in respect 20 of such employment are reduced in amount within such period of five years owing to his services being no longer required or to his duties being diminished or altered and noti on the ground of misconduct ; and(e) who  shall not  have  received  under  the  provisions  of 25sub-section (1) of this section compensation to the maximum amount prescribed by that sub-section shall be entitled to have compensation paid to him by the Council (in addition to any compensation payable to him under the provisions of the said sub-section (1)) in respect of any direct pecuniary loss 30 which he may suffer (in comparison wdth the conditions of his employment in the service of the Council immediately before the termination of such service) by reason of such determination of employment or reduction of salary wages and emoluments. Provided that the total amount of compensation payable by the Council to 35 any officer or servant under the provisions of this section shall not exceed the maximum amount prescribed by sub-section (1) of this section.
[SCHEDULE(3) The provisions contained in the Schedule to this Act shall have effect in regard to the submission and determination of claims for compensation under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of this section and the payment of any compensation which may be awarded.5 (4) Any expenditure incurred for or in connection with the payment of compensation under the provisions of this section shall be defrayed in such manner as shall be provided for in any agreement entered into under this Act.12.   Any question between the parties to any agreement entered Settlement of differences.10 into under this Act which pursuant to that agreement or to this Act is to be settled by arbitration shall be referred to and d etermined by a person to be agreed upon between the parties or failing agreement to be appointed by the Minister and the decision of such person on the question referred to him shall be final and binding upon the parties15 between whom such question arose.13.   Nothing in this Act or in any agreement entered into there- Saving for existing0 0 obligations affectingunder shall exempt the Council from or affect any obligation duty the undertakingr J &amp; J   of the Council.liability or restriction from time to time relating to their undertaking which the Council are required to perform or discharge or to which 20 they are subject under or by virtue of any contract with any local authority company body or person.14.   All costs and expenses of the Council in the execution of As,to payments4- under this Act.this Act (except so far as they may be otherwise provided for by this or any other Act) shall be defrayed as payments for general 25 or special county purposes within the meaning of the Local Govern-ment Act 1888 as the Council may decide and the costs charges and expenses preliminary to and of and incidental to the preparing for obtaining and passing of this Act shall be paid by the Council in like manner.
The SCHEDULE referred to in the foregoing Act.(1) Every person desiring to have compensation paid to him under this Act shall within three months after the date on which his service under the Council is terminated or his employment in connection with the associated undertakings is determined or his salary wages and emoluments in respect of such employment as last aforesaid are reduced in amount (as the case may be) deliver to the Council a claim under his hand setting forth particulars of the direct pecuniary loss which he alleges he has suffered or will suffer by reason of the termination of his service under the Council or of the determination of his employment in connection with the associated undertakings or of the reduc-tion of his salary wages and emoluments in respect of such employment.(2) Such statement of claim shall be submitted to the Council who shall forthwith take the same into consideration and assess the just amount of compensation (if any) and shall forthwith inform the claimant of their decision.(3) If a claimant is aggrieved by the refusal of the Council to grant compensation or by the amount of compensation assessed the claimant may within three months after the decision of the Council is communicated to him require that the matter shall be referred to arbitration and thereupon the matter shall be referred to an arbitrator to be agreed upon between the claimant and the Council or failing such agreement to be appointed on the application of either party by the Minister. The arbitrator so agreed upon or appointed shaU consider the case and determine (a) in any case in which the Council have refused to grant compensation whether any compensation and if so what amount ought to be granted to the claimant or (6) in any case in which the Council have assessed the amount of compensation whether that amount shall be increased and if so to what amount and such determina-tion shall be final.(4) Such compensation may be paid in the form of an annual or other periodical allowance for life or for a stated period or of a lump sum or partly of such an allowance and partly of a lump sum as the Council or (in any case in which on a reference to arbitration under paragraph (3) of this Schedule the arbitrator shall determine that compensation ought to be granted to any person to whom the Council refused to grant compensation) the arbitrator may determine.(5) In assessing or determining compensation regard shall be had to the emoluments which the person claiming such compensation may acquire or might have acquired by accepting other employ-ment offered to him and to any payments to be made to him out of the Superannuation and Provident Fund pursuant to the scheme relating to that fund upon the termination of his service under the Council and to all the other circumstances of the case.

LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL(CO-ORDINATION OF PASSENGER TRAFFIC).ABILLTo empower the London County Council and local authorities and others owning or working railways tramways light railways trolley vehicles or omnibuses within or partly within the London traffic area to enter into agreements with reference to their undertakings ; and for other purposes.[Presented by Sir Cyril Cobb, Lieut.-Colonel Fremantle, Mr. Gates, Lieut.-Colonel Vatjghan-Morgan, Sir Henry Jacksos and Major Salmon.]19 &amp; 20 George V.-Session 1928-9.H. MARTYN HOOKE, The County Hall,Westminster Bridge, S.E. 1, Parliamentary Officer of the Council.DYSON, BELL &amp; Co.,19, Abingdon Street,Westminster, S.W. 1,Parliamentary Agents.Jas. Tkuscott it Son, Ltd., Printers, Suflolk Lane, E.C.4. 300   t.p. 1S-1S.-22/1/29.
19 amd 20 GEORGE V.-SESSION 1928-9.LONDON ELECTRIC RAILWAY COMPANIES (CO-ORDINATION OF PASSENGER TRAFFIC).ARRANGEMENT OF SECTIONS.Preamble.Section.Short title.......... 1Interpretation 2Agreements with regard to common management and commonfund 3Conditions as to validity of agreements         .... 4Principles to govern management of associated undertakings  - 5Application of common fund   -      --      --      -- 6Audit of Accounts   -      --      --      --      -- 7Appointment of members   of   local   authorities  on  certainbodies      -      .      -      -      -      ...      -      - 8Appeal to Minister         -      -              -      -      -      -      - 9Development or extension of associated undertakings      -      - 10Settlement of differences -      -      -      -      -      -      -11As to certain provisions of Act of 1915 and of the agreementthereunder        --------      - 12Saving of powers of Underground Companies   -      -      -      - 13Saving  for  existing  obligations  affecting   undertakings   ofUnderground Companies   -      -      - -      -      -14
ABILLTo empower the City and South London Railway Company the Central London Railway Company the London Electric Railway Company the Metropolitan District Railway Company the London General Omnibus Company Limited and any county council local authority company body or person owning or working railways tramways light rail-ways trolley vehicles or omnibuses within or partly within the London traffic area to enter into agreements with reference to their undertakings; and for other purposes.&quot;YTTHEREAS the City and South London Railway Company the Preamble.* * Central London Railway Company the London Electric Railway Company and the Metropolitan District Railway Company have constructed and are working underground and other railways 5 for carrying and dealing with the passenger traffic of the metropolis and such railways are together with the undertaking of the London General Omnibus Company Limited worked and managed as one passenger transport system with facilities for through and interchange traffic and with a common fund established under powers conferred 10 by the London Electric Railway Companies&apos; Facilities Act 1915 :
9 1 1ABILLTo empower the City and South London Railway Company the Central London Railway Company the London Electric Railway Company the Metropolitan District Railway Company the London General Omnibus Conrpany Limited and any county council local authority company body or person owning or working railways tramways light rail-ways trolley vehicles or omnibuses within or partly within the London traffic area to enter into agreements with reference to their undertakings; and for other purposes.&quot;f 7TTPIEREAS the City and South London Railway Company the Preamble.* &apos; Central London Railway Companjr the London Electric Railway Company and the Metropolitan District Railway Company have constructed and are working underground and other railways 5 for carrying and dealing with the passenger traffic of the metropolis and such railways are together with the undertaking of the London General Omnibus Company Limited worked and managed as one passenger transport system with facilities for through and interchange traffic and with a common fund established under powers conferred 10 by the London Electric Railway Companies&apos; Facilities Act 1915 :
MAY IT THEREFORE PLEASE YOUR MAJESTYThat it may be enacted and be it enacted by the King&apos;s Most Excellent Majesty by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parlia-ment assembled and by the authority of the same as follows :        20Short title.        1.   This Act may be cited as the London&quot; Electric Railway Companies (Co-ordination of Passenger Traffic) Act 1929.2.   In this Act unless the subject or context otherwise requires -The expression &quot; the Minister &quot; means the Minister of Trans-port ; 25The expression &quot; the Advisory Committee&quot; means the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee as constituted from time to time under the London Traffic Act 1924 or any Act amending the same ;The expression &quot; The Underground Companies &quot; means the 30 City and South London Railway Company the CentralInterpre-tation:&apos;And whereas it would be to the public advantage that the transport systems of the above mentioned companies and of any county councils and local authorities companies bodies and persons owning or working railways tramways light railways trolley vehicles or omnibuses within or partly within the London 5 traffic area should be managed and worked in co-ordination with a view to the most efficient and comprehensive means of local passenger services being supplied throughout the London traffic area at fares sufficient to provide from time to time for working expenses efficient maintenance and renewal of the undertakings and 10 a reasonable return on capital:And whereas it is therefore expedient that the provisions herein-after contained should be made :And whereas the purposes aforesaid cannot be attained without the authority of Parliament: 25
London Railway Company the London Electric Railway Company the Metropolitan District Railway Company and the London General Omnibus Company Limited ;The expression &quot; local authority &quot; means the council of any administrative county or of any county or other municipal borough or urban or rural district;The expression &quot; the London traffic area &quot; means the London traffic area as constituted from time to time under the London Traffic Act 1924 or any Act amencling the same ;The expression &quot; the associated undertakings &quot; means the undertakings or parts of undertakings with reference to which an agreement entered into under this Act is for the time being in force and the expression &quot;associated undertaking&quot; means any one of such undertakings or parts of undertakings;The expression &quot; the common fund &quot; means the common fund established under any agreement entered into under this Act;The expression &quot; ranking capital &quot; means as respects each of the associated undertakings such sum or sums as may be determined under any formula or formula contained in any agreement entered into under this Act relating to that associated undertaking or specified in such agreement as representing moneys expended on capital account upon or for the purposes or in respect of that associated undertaking or capital issued or moneys borrowed or otherwise raised or applied on capital account for or in connection with such undertaking together with such reserves funds moneys shares stocks securities or credits (if any) as may be so specified or determined but excluding any shares stocks mortgages debentures debenture stocks or other securities or sums of money or credits on which dividends or interest are or is under the provisions of such agreement to be payable out of the
Agree-ments with regard to common manage-ment and common fund.3. (1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any other Act or in any Order the Underground Companies or any of them on the one hand and any local authority company body or person from time to time owning or working (whether under statutory powers or 15 not) any railway &quot;tramway light railway trolley vehicle or omnibus undertaking established for the time being within or partly within the London traffic area on the other hand may enter into carry into effect vary and rescind agreements with each other for and with respect to all or any of the following purposes (that is to say) : (a) themanagement20maintenance operation running overuser repair development extension improvement and renewal of the whole or part of their respective under-takings including the provision of buildings rolling stock and other equipment the interchange of traffic 25 the fixing (subject to the authorised maximum fares rates and charges if any) collection apportionment and distribution of fares rates and charges on traffic and other receipts and revenues of such undertakings or parts of undertakings and the payments to be made 30 to or by and the conditions to be performed by all or any of the parties to the agreement ;(b) the allocation and apportionment of traffic (including receipts therefrom and expenses in connection there-receipts and revenues of that associated undertaking before ascertaining the amount to be paid into the common fund in respect of that associated undertaking ;The expression &quot; reasonable return&quot; means such rate orrates of interest as may be 5(a) determined under any formula or formulas for thatpurpose contained in any agreement entered into under this Act or(b) specified in such agreement as a reasonable return upon or in respect of the ranking 10 capital included or referred to in such agreement.
with) to from or over any of the undertakings or parts of undertakings to which the agreement relates ;(c) The establishment of a common fund and the paymentinto that fund of(i) the whole or part of the balance of the receipts andrevenues of each of the undertakings or parts of undertakings to which the agreement relates (which undertakings or parts of undertakings are hereafter in this section referred to as &quot; the undertakings&quot;) remaining after making or dis-charging or providing for the making or discharge of such payments liabilities and obligations and making such other provision (if any) as may be specified or provided for in the agreement ; or(ii) (a) the whole or part of the balance of the receipts and revenues of each of the undertakings (so far as such receipts and revenues are not payable into any other common fund) remaining after making or discharging or providing for the making or discharge of such payments liabilities and obhgations and making such other provision (if any) as may be specified or provided for in the agreement and(b) (in any case in which the whole or part of the receipts and revenues of any of the undertakings is payable into any other common fund) the whole or part of the sums from time to time payable out of such other common fund to such of the parties to the agreement as are entitled to receive payments thereout;(d) the control management distribution and application ofthe common fund ;(e) the exercise with reference to any of the undertakings ofany powers or rights exercisable otherwise than under the provisions of this Act;
(f) the exercise by any board of directors joint committeeadvisory board or other body of all or any of the powers and duties of the parties to the agree-ment or any of those parties with respect to the undertakings or any of them; 5(g) the appointment of an advisory board or boards con-sisting of representatives of such parties to and for such purposes of the agreement as may be provided for therein ;(h) the leasing or taking on lease of the whole or part of the 10undertaking of any company body or person in reference to which a common fund is not established under any agreement entered into under this Act and the terms and conditions of such leasing or taking on lease; 15(1) generally all such matters and things as may be necessary for carrying out all or any of the purposes aforesaid.(2) Every such agreement providing for the establishment of a common fund shall either prescribe a formula or formulae for determining or shall specify the amount of the ranking 20 capital and the reasonable return on such ranking capital but notwithstanding any other provision of this Act no such agreement shall have any force or effect unless and until the formula or formula? prescribed therein for determining the reasonable return or the reasonable return specified therein (as the case may be) shall have 25 received such approval as the Minister shall direct.(3) Every such agreement providing for the establishment of a common fund shall also provide that before any balance of the common fund is distributed among the parties to such agreement there shall from time to time be paid out of such common fund to each 30 of the parties to such agreement a reasonable sum of money to be agreed or failing agreement to be determined by arbitration which sum shall be carried by the party to whom such sum is paid to the credit of a special reserve to be used for such purposes of experiment and research in connection with the undertaking of that party or 35 the development and improvement thereof as may be agreed or failing-agreement as may be determined by arbitration.
4. (1) Except as hereinafter provided an agreement entered Conditions into under this Act shall not be valid until it shall have been laid validity of before each House of Parliament for a period of thirty days during agree-which that House is sitting and if either such House before the 5 expiration of that period presents an address to His Majesty against the agreement the agreement shall thereupon become null and void : Provided that nothing in this section shall preclude all or any of the parties to an agreement against which an address has been so presented from entering into   a new agreement (either with or 10 without the addition of any other party or parties) to which the foregoing provisions of this sub-section shall apply.Provided also that the foregoing provisions of this sub-section shall not apply to any agreement entered into under this Act with respect to which the Minister shall certify that it is supplemental15 or incidental to a valid agreement already subsisting and that if the Minister shall not within ten days from the date of the sub-mission to him of any such agreement intimate to the party or parties submitting the same his refusal to grant such a certificate with reference thereto he shall be deemed at the expiration of the20 said period of ten days to have granted a certificate with reference to that agreement to the effect hereinbefore mentioned.(2) If with reference to any agreement entered into under this Act no such address is presented within either of the said periods of thirty days or the Minister does not within the said period of ten25 days intimate his refusal to grant his certificate (as the case may be) then as from the date or latest date on which the said periods of thirty days expire or as from the date on which the Minister grants or is pursuant to this section deemed to have granted his certificate with reference to that agreement the agreement shall subject to the30 provisions of this Act be valid and may be carried into effect.(3) An agreement entered into under this Act shall not be valid unless and until as regards each company party thereto such agreement shall have been approved by a resolution passed by three-fourths of the votes of the proprietors of such company entitled to 35 vote who are present in person or by proxy at a general meeting of such company specially convened for the purpose.
(ii) any sum or sums representing the amount by which the revenue of the associated undertakings or anyPrinciples The associated undertakings shall be managed maintainedmanage-&quot;   operated repaired extended improved and renewed in accordancement of     with the following principles : associatedtaldno-s (A) ^ne associated undertakings shall at all times be main-tained in good and efficient working order and condition   5 and be operated as a co-ordinated system of transport so that adequate travelling facilities are provided for the public ;(b) When any general scheme of fares, rates and chargesapplicable to the associated undertakings shall be 10 determined such scheme shall (subject to the authorised maximum fares rates and charges if any) be applied as far as practicable on a uniform basis with reference to all those undertakings, except where special circum-stances affecting the traffic or the cost of making 15 provision therefor justify a differentiation ;(c) The associated undertakings shall at all times be somanaged and worked and such fares rates and charges shall (subject to the authorised maximum fares rates and charges if any) at all times be charged that the 20 aggregate earnings of the associated undertakings shall so far as practicable be sufficient to meet all proper charges against them, including adequate provision for depreciation obsolescence and renewal and a reasonable return on or in respect of the ranking capital. 25Applica- 6.   Every agreement entered into under this Act and providingtion of  Qr establishment of a common fund shaU provide that during common r 0fund.        the continuance of the agreement any balance which remains in the common fund after(a) paying or discharging or making provision for  30(i) the expenses in connection with the management of the common fund; and
** &apos;&quot;f. r7. (1) The accounts in respect of each associated undertaking Audit of and of the common fund established under the agreement relating accounts to that undertaking and of any other common fund referred to in that agreement shall be made up at least once in every year and30 shall be audited by an auditor or auditors to be agreed upon by the parties to the agreement or (failing such agreement) to be appointed by the Minister. The auditor or auditors so agreed upon or appointed shall be entitled to require from the parties to such agreement all such papers books accounts vouchers information and35 explanations as may be necessary for the performance of his or their duties.of them shall he insufficient for making or dis-charging or providing for the making or discharge of such payments liabilities and obligations and the making of such other provision as is 5 specified or provided for in the agreement; and(b) paying to the respective parties to the agreement such sums as the said parties may determine not exceeding amounts representing a reasonable return upon the ranking capital10 shall be applied in such manner as may be agreed between the parties to the agreement or as (failing agreement) shall be settled by arbitration in the improvement of the associated under-takings and in maintaining or extending the efficiency and usefulness thereof in the public interest including any one or more of the15 following purposes : (a) the development extension or improvement of the associated undertakings or any of them or any parts   thereof   and   the   making of   financial provision for facilitating the raising of additional 20 capital or moneys for those purposes ;(b) the reduction of fares and other charges ;(c) the provision of a general reserve to  meet contin-gencies ;(d) such other purposes as may be approved by the 25 Minister.
Appoint- Any local   authority being  a party to any agreementmembers of entered into under this Act  may pursuant  to  any provisionslocal -to that effect contained in the agreement appoint any of theirauthorities , , . ,on certain   members as members of any board of directors or of any joint 10bodies.      committee advisory board or other body (whether constituted forthe purposes of the agreement or already existing) to which underthe terms of the agreement there are entrusted the exercise of anyof the powers and duties of the parties to the agreement or any ofthem or any advisory duties in connection with the carrying out of 15the agreement and any members of  any   such  local  authorityso appointed may hold office as such appointees without incurringany disability or disqualification.Appeal to 9. (i)  For the protection of the public interest the mayorMinisteraldermen and commons of the City of London in common council 20 assembled or any local authority whose area or district is wholly or partly within the London traffic area may at any time make representations to the Minister with respect to any action taken under any agreement entered into under this Act affecting the area or district of such authority and involving  25(a) the alteration of the general scheme of fares rates  or charges :  or(b) the withdrawal of services ;  or(c) the order or priority of developments and extensions;and the minister if he deems fit may thereupon cause an inquiry 30 to be held into the matter by the Advisory Committee.(2) Every auditor agreed upon or appointed under this section shall be a Chartered Accountant or a member of the Society of Incorporated Accountants and Auditors.(3) It shall not for any purpose be necessary to audit under any other enactment accounts audited under the provisions of this   5 section.
Appoint- Any local   authority being  a party to any agreementmembers of entered into under  this  Act  may pursuant  to   any provisions *0Ctii &apos;t&apos;    ^Q ^^a* effec^ contained in the agreement appoint any of their on certain   members as members of any board of directors or of any joint 10 bodies.      committee advisory board or other body (whether constituted for the purposes of the agreement or already existing) to which under the terms of the agreement there are entrusted the exercise of any of the powers and duties of the parties to the agreement or any of them or any advisory duties in connection with the carrying out of 15 the agreement and any members of  any   such  local  authority so appointed may hold office as such appointees without incurring any disabihty or disqualification.Appeal to 9. (i)  For the protection of the public interest the mayorMinister. alolermen and commons of the City of London in common council 20 assembled or any local authority whose area or district is wholly or partly within the London traffic area may at any time make representations to the Minister with respect to any action taken under any agreement entered into under this Act affecting the area or district of such authority and involving  25(a) the alteration of the general scheme of fares rates or charges :  or(b) the withdrawal of services ;  or(c) the order or priority of developments and extensions;and the Minister if he deems fit may thereupon cause an inquiry 30 to be held into the matter by the Advisory Committee.(2) Every auditor agreed upon or appointed under this section shall be a Chartered Accountant or a member of the Society of Incorporated Accountants and Auditors.(3) It shall not for any purpose be necessary to audit under any other enactment accounts audited under the provisions of this   5 section.
(ii) If as a result of any such inquiry the Minister is of opinion that such alteration of fares rates or charges or withdrawal of services is unnecessary or undesirable he may prohibit such alteration or withdrawal or if as a result of any such inquiry the Minister is of 5 opinion that a certain order or priority of development or extension should be observed then such order or priority shall be observed if such developments or extensions are undertaken : Provided that in arriving at his decision the Minister shall be bound by the principles mentioned in the section of this Act of which the marginal 10 note is &quot; Principles to govern management of associated under-takings.&quot;10. (1) Any development extension or improvement of an Develop-associated undertaking (other than developments or improvements tension to be carried out with the sums of money referred to in sub-section of15 (3) of the section of this Act of  which the marginal note is under^ &quot;Agreements with regard to common management and common takings, fund&quot;) may  with   the  consent  of   the   other  parties  to   the agreement be carried out by the party owning such associated undertaking and if such consent be withheld or refused the party20 owning such undertaking may refer the matter to arbitration.(2) In the event of any such development extension or improvement being carried out the associated undertaking so developed extended or improved shall on such terms and conditions (including terms and conditions in regard to ranking capital and25 charges upon revenue and capital account and otherwise) as may be agreed to by the parties to the agreement or failing agreement determined by arbitration be deemed to be the associated undertaking included in any such agreement and all necessary adjustments shall be made in the agreement and the30 agreement shall be varied accordingly.11. Any question between the parties to any agreement Settlement entered into under this Act which pursuant to that agreement gnCegffer&quot; or to this Act is to be settled by arbitration shall be referred to and determined by a person to be agreed upon between the parties or 35 failing agreement to be appointed by the Minister and the decision of such person on the question referred to him shall be final and binding upon the parties between whom such question arose.
As to certain I provisions of Act of 1915 and of the agreement there-under.12. (i) Nothing in this Act contained or in any agreement entered into under this Act shall prejudice or affect the priority of or security for any of the payments specified or referred to in the first schedule to the London Electric Railway Companies&apos; Facilities Act 1915 (in this section referred to as &quot;the Act of 1915&quot;) or (except as provided in this section) affect any agreement entered into under that Act before the passing of this Act.(ii) Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (b) of section 3 of the Act of 1915 or of any agreement entered into under that Act any agreement entered into under this Act to which agreement 10 the Underground Companies are parties may provide that the whole or part of the balances of the respective revenues of the Underground Companies remaining after providing for the pay-ments or sums specified or provided for in the first schedule to the Act of 1915 or in any agreement entered into under that Act 15 may be paid into the common fund instead of being distributed among the Underground Companies and that the Underground Companies may pay into any common fund constituted under the Act of 1915 such sums as they may receive out of the common fund. 20Saving of powers of Under -ground Companies.13. Each of the Underground Companies may subject to the provisions of any agreement entered into by it under this Act exercise in regard to its undertaking included in any such agreement all the powers rights and privileges vested in or exercisable by it in regard to such undertaking in the same way to the same extent and 25 subject to the same conditions and limitations as it could have clone if this Act had not been passed.Saving for existing obligations affecting under-takings of Under-ground Companies.14. Nothing in this Act or in any agreement entered into thereunder shall exempt the Underground Companies or any of them from any obligation duty liability or restriction relating to their 30 undertaldngs which the Underground Companies or any of them are required to perform or discharge or to which they are subject under or by virtue of any agreement with any local authority company body or person or (except as by this Act provided) any Act of Parliament. 35
London Electric Railway Companies (Co-ordination of      13 Passenger Traffic).15.   AH costs charges and expenses of and incident to the Costs preparing for obtaining and passing of this Act or otherwise in relation thereto shall be paid by the Underground Companies in such propor-tions as may have been or may be agreed between them.
LONDON ELECTRIC RAILWAY COMPANIES (CO-ORDINATION OF PASSENGER TRAFFIC).AB I L LTo empower the  City and South Londo Railway Company the Central Londo Railway Company the London electrical  Railway Company the Metropolitan Di trict   Railway   Company  the Londo General Omnibus Company Limited an any   county   council   local   authorit company  body   or  person  owning working  railways tramways light rai ways trolley vehicles or omnibuses with&apos; or partly within the London traffic ar to enter into agreements with reference- to their undertakings;  and  for oth purposes.[Presented by the Rt. Hon. Sib Robert S. Horn Sir Henry Jackson, Col. K. Vatjghan-Morga and Lt.-Col. J. T. C. Moore-Brabazon.]19 &amp; 20 George V.-Session 1928-9.donald McMillan and mott,Stafford House,14, King William Street, E.C. i, Solicitors to the City and South London Railway Corn-panASHURST, morris, crisp and co.,17, Throgmorton Avenue, E.c. i,Solicitors to the Central London Railway companies-      - ^  : &apos; &apos;BIRCHAM AND co.,Winchester House,Old Broad Street, E.c. 2,Solicitors to the London Electric Railway CompanARTHUR s. CARDEW,Lennox House,Norfolk Street, W.c. 2, Solicitor to the London General Omnibus Company, LimitsBAXTER AND CO.,12, Victoria Street,Westminster, S.W.1,Solicitors to the Metropolitan District Eaihvay company and Parliamentary Agents for the BitWhitehead mobkis limiiki) law ami parliamentary printer?, :js     sli. parliament street, say. 1.XY.

</content>
</cab>
