<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 607-612</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1929.SECRET.CP. 29 (29).CABINET.POLITICAL SURVEY OF IRAQ.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I CIRCULATE, for the information of the Cabinet, a despatch written on the eve of his departure from Baghdad by Sir Henry Dobbs, who has recently relinquished the post of High Commissioner for Iraq, which he has held for a period of over five years. . .During that period much has happened in Iraq. It has been a time of con-siderable political and economic progress. The Treaty machinery which regulates our present relations with the Government of Iraq was accepted by the Iraqi Parliament and the Council of the League of Nations and became effective. The long frontier dispute with Turkey, which at one time seemed likely to lead to open conflict, was satisfactorily settled by the Treaty of Angora, and relations between the two countries were established upon a friendly basis. The agreements concluded with the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd for the preservation of peace on the desert frontier have been less successful; but, with this exception, public security is complete throughout Iraq.On the side of economic development steady progress has also been made. Five years of careful financial administration have not only seen Iraq successfully through the difficult period of post-war trade depression, but have led to the accumulation of a revenue surplus sufficient to extinguish in one transaction the greater part of the public debt inherited from Turkey. Of the natural resources of Iraq, the most important oil has now been proved and is in process of active development. Increasing prosperity, based upon stable government and internal security, has been reflected in a great extension of pump irrigation throughout the country, resulting in the cultivation of large tracts of hitherto barren land. Both imports and exports have shown a progressive increase, pointing to expansion of trade. All this has, moreover, been attained without recourse to public borrowing, an expedient, with which few young States have found themselves able to dispense since the war.There is, of course, a reverse side to the picture. Such rapid development could scarcely have been attained without temporary setbacks and occasional friction. Indeed, at the present moment Iraq is suffering from one of the recurrent periods of political tension. Our policy of ruling without governing in Iraq, of exercising control through an ostensibly independent native Government, is in the nature of an experiment. Iraq is still scarcely more than a geographical expression. The different races which inhabit the country have not yet heen welded into a single Iraqi nation. A Kurd is still primarily a Kurd and only secondarily (if at all to his own mind) an Iraqi. The tribal confederations of the Euphrates admit no natural loyaltjr or allegiance to the Iraq Government. The Kurd still dislikes and despises the Arab, the Christian hates and fears the Moslem, and the Shiah distrusts the Sunni; and until these traditional antagonisms have been subordinated to a spirit of patriotism, the British Representative in Iraq must, as Sir H. Dobbs explains in this despatch, hold the scales even, and to do so must intervene in matters which might otherwise properly be left to the discretion of the native government. In a country such as Iraq, where national consciousness has outstripped administrative experience, such intervention is apt to be resented and to cause political friction. This is unfortunate but inevitable, and I am satisfied that, in order to maintain the present rate of progress, and indeed to ensure the success of our experiment, some measure of British supervision and control tactfully exercised and not unnecessarily paraded will remain necessary for some years to come.February 7, 1929.[18850] copy No.98
^Secret.   A.) The Residency,Sir, Baghdad, December 4, 1928.AS I shall before long leave Iraq, it may be useful that I should place on record some account of the principles which have guided me in my attitude towards the measures and proposals of the Iraq Government, in so far as these principles have involved an apparent departure from or a deA^development of the principles laid down for my guidance in the Duke of Devonshire&apos;s despatch, Confidential B, dated the 20th September, 1923.2. In paragraph 4 of his despatch, the Duke of Devonshire stated that the four most important principles were : (1.) That the interests of foreigners should be adequately protected; (2.) That the financial interests of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government should be safeguarded;(3.) That the best use should be made of the resources of the country; and (4.) That the Administration should conform generally to the traditions and principles of progressive and enlightened government.In view of the employment by Iraq of a number of British officials, His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared to leave the fulfilment of the third and fourth of these principles to the Iraq Administration; and they declared that they did not propose to criticise in detail or to endeavour to influence in detail the financial or administrative arrangements of the Iraq Government, provided that the Treaty and its subsidiary Agreements were duly observed. At the same time they stated (paragraph 6) that they had no desire to hamper or restrict the exercise of a reasonable discretion by the High Commissioner.3. Other duties laid upon the High Commissioner were that he should report to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government all political and constitutional developments in Iraq, so that they might form an opinion of the extent to which she was fitting herself for full membership of the League of Nations; that he should advi.se the Secretary of State for the Colonies from time to time upon the extent to which the Iraq Government were able to provide for local security and on the degree of efficiency attained by the military organisation of Iraq, so as to enable His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government to reduce as rapidly as possible the expenditure imposed upon them in connection with the defence of Iraq; that he should keep His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government informed regarding all financial measures, so that they might assure themselves that Iraq was doing her utmost to pay for her own defence and security and to meet her obligations in connection with the Ottoman Debt; and that he should secure the control by His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government of the foreign relations of Iraq (a control not specifically provided for in the main Anglo-Iraq Treaty, but implied in Article V thereof).4. I have, to the best of my ability, complied with the instructions set forth above; but I must admit that, to any one ignorant of the springs of my actions, I may appear to have interfered in many details and matters, regarding which, under those instructions, I might have merely maintained a watching attitude. Tor instance, I have restrained successive Iraq Cabinets from abrogating the Tribal Disputes Regulation; I have practically vetoed the attempts of the Ministry of Finance to destroy the &quot; muqata&apos;a system &quot; of Amara, or the system under which large tracts of country are leased to semi-feudal tribal chiefs; I have severely criticised and insisted on the modification of rules and laws for the distribution of so-called Government lands, on the ground that they tended to ignore prescriptive tribal rights; I have received and enquired (from the Ministries concerned) into petitions regarding alleged administrative injustice or judicial obliquity and have closely watched and guided the treatment by the Iraq Government of tribal feuds and quarrels. I have, in spite of Section 4 of the Administrative Inspectorate Regulations, opposed the transfer of the headquarters of Administrative Inspectors to Baghdad and insisted that they shall be allotted to and reside in specific districts. I have further, as His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government know, aroused considerable resentment by expressing dissent from the plans of the Iraq Government for conscription. These actions have contributed to cause an impression among many of the Iraqi politicians, and perhaps in other quarters, that I have attempted to keep Iraq too much in leading strings. [5. The apparent deviations from the principles laid down for my guidance can be explained in the one word &quot; security.&quot; I have constantly brought to the notice of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government that the influential politicians of Iraq are
imbued with the ideas of the townsmen, between whom and the countrymen a great gulf is fixed. Even the present Prime Minister, Abdul Muhsin Beg, though of tribal origin, has become by education in Constantinople infected with the townsman&apos;s ideas and nothing is more abhorrent to him than the authority of the Shaikhs or the yielding to tribal custom in the administration of justice. Nor has the working of the representative system done much to restore the balance; for administrative pressure has resulted in the election of townee representatives, even in purely tribal districts. As giving an example of this tendency, I may recall my despatch Secret B, dated the 16th June, 1928, with which I forwarded a report by the Administrative Inspector of Kut to the effect that the &quot;carpet-bagger&quot; delegate of that district was diametrically opposed to his constituents in his advocacy of conscription.6. In most countries such an opposition between town and country, though resulting in an unwarrantable over-representation of the towns, might not be seriously dangerous. It might indeed have beneficial aspects, since the ideas of the town are more civilised than those of the country. Nor is it wise to underestimate the influence which the educated townsman can exert upon the countryman who, however much he professes to despise the townsmen, is easily worked on by their nimbler brains. But Iraq is peculiar in three respects. Firstj the countrymen, including the inhabitants of the villages, are almost all tribal, unlike the cultivators of Egypt or India or even of Persia, with its mass of non-tribal peasants in the centre and a fairly broad tribal fringe. In this respect I doubt whether the conditions of any &quot;other country in the world, even of Afghanistan, resemble those of Iraq. Moreover, as a result of the war and the quantity of rifles and ammunition dispersed during and immediately after it, the country districts are crammed with arms, which have hitherto been only slightly controlled. Secondly, the countrymen throughout the southern half of Iraq are Shiahs and divided by sectarian differences from the ruling Sunni Arab clique in Baghdad; Avhile in the northern half a large proportion are similarly divided from the ruling Arab clique by racial differences, being Kurds, Turcoman or Yezidis. Thus to the natural alienation of the tribal countryman from the townee is added the special alienation either of religion or of race. Thirdly, the prestige and military strength of the Iraq Government are inadequate to cope with any grave opposition from the tribes, without the help of the British forces and of British moral backing. In Persia the name of the Shah, even when borne by a usurper, spreads traditional terror. In Turkey and Nejd the rulers rule by their own personality and strength of conquest. The King of Afghanistan has both tradition and strength on his side. But King Faisal is a foreigner imported by the British and has had no time to strike roots. The Iraq Army has seen only a few trifling hill-skirmishes and has no reputation in the country. There is little affection for or awe of the Crown, no national consciousness outside the schools of Baghdad and Mosul and no respect for the courtiers or for the politicians. The strength of the Administration rests almost solely on the knowledge of British support and control and on the fear inspired by British aeroplanes and armoured cars in the plains and by the Assyrian Levies helped by British aeroplanes in the Kurdish hills. The Police force is indeed efficient and feared, because British control over it has never really been relaxed. If the Royal Air Force were to be withdrawn, but the British alliance and British powers of inspection and remonstrance remained, the Iraq administration (though badly crippled) might survive, because the people would expect the re-entry of British&quot;forces on emergency. If both disappeared, the Govern-ment of Iraq would, I believe, in a few months, either vanish altogether or remain clinging desperately to a strip of territory along the Tigris between Samarra and Kut, the whole of the rest of the country falling away.7. Thus, although the existing state of security is complete and unprecedented, it rests on a precarious base and quite as much on British reputation and British reserve power outside the country as on the British forces actually present. If the already suspicious Shiah or Kurdish tribesmen were to feel that British policy towards them was being dragged at the heels of the anti-tribal Baghdad politicians and that there was no power in the land inclined to notice their complaints, scattered and spasmodic risings would soon begin which, unless quickly suppressed, would result in general disorder. It is unlikely that the Iraq forces, whether military or police, would be mobile enough to deal with such risings, and the Royal Air Force would have to take action to prevent the whole administration collapsing. In the end, British public opinion would be shocked by the sight of British aeroplanes bombing the tribesmen of the Euphrates or Kurdistan to enforce tyrannical or mistaken decrees hatched amid the intrigues of the Baghdad coffee-shops or conceived by citizen pedants.[18850] b 2
8. Against such a misfortune His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government have some guarantee in the last sentence of Article VIII of the Military Agreement, which reads as follows :  -&quot; The Iraq Government shall not be entitled to the assistance of any forces maintained or controlled by His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government against or for the suppression of any external aggression or any civil disturbance or armed rising which shall, in the opinion of the High Commissioner, have been provoked or occasioned by action taken or policy pursued by the Iraq Government contrary to the advice or express wishes of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.&quot;Upon this provision I have based my policy of supervision in administrative, and especially in tribal, affairs. It would evidently be impossible to pursue in such matters the theoretically admirable policy of allowing a child to learn by its mistakes; since the mistakes would involve not only the well-being of thousands of human beings, but also the reputation of the British Government. Nor is it possible merely to utter mild generalities, axioms and warnings, to watch them being disregarded and in the end to&apos; say, when a rising occurs, &quot; I told you so. Now you must get out of the difficulty without my help.&quot; For the rising might destroy the whole land. 1 have, therefore, frequently found myself forced to intervene in details and to nip the beginnings of policies or even of isolated plans of action which I thought likely to create active discontent.9. After this explanation I may perhaps be permitted to dwell upon what I believe to be the most vital points. These are the retention of British Administrative Inspectors in the Provinces (instead of centralizing them in Baghdad); the retention and adequate use of the Tribal Civil and Criminal Disputes Regulation; avoidance of the identification of conscription with British policy; and the maintenance of the special regime in the Kurdish districts, for which the Council of the League of Nations stipulated when awarding to Iraq the Province of Mosul. The dominant Iraqis dislike all four of these policies.10. The Administrative Inspectorate Regulations had been settled before I came to Iraq. Otherwise I should have protested against Section&quot; 4, which runs: &quot; Headquarters of Administrative Inspectors will be Baghdad. They will be detailed for inspection as circumstances demand and as the Ministry of the Interior may deem fit.&quot; To me it is evident, that a British officer living and working in Baghdad and sent out intermittently on roving missions of inspection, now to one district and now to another, could neither intervene early enough to prevent mistakes and injustice, nor have sufficient knowledge of local events and feelings to enable him to report, for the High Commissioner^ information, whether the use of British forces were justified for the suppression of disturbance. The result of the centralization of Administrative Inspectors in Baghdad would be either that the High Commissioner would, when a question of employing British forces arose, have to depend on information derived from the British Special Service or Intelligence Officers working under Air Headquarters, who are imperfectly acquainted with administrative details, or that he would have to refuse to take action before an Administrative Inspector had gone to the spot, made an elaborate enquiry and satisfied himself that the trouble had not been caused by unwise or unjust action on the part of the Iraqi officials. It would be out of the question to allow local Mutasarrifs or Qaimmaqams to invoke the swift and terrible help of the Royal Air Force at their pleasure. It is even now notorious that minor Iraqi officials sometimes, without authority and contrary to orders, threaten the tribesmen with air action and so enforce their orders. But if it were known that Mutasarrifs could, without giving an opportunity to locally-experienced British officials to intervene, first get themselves into difficulty by unjust acts and then suppress the difficulty by British bombs, the tyranny would be complete and justified odium would fall upon the British name.11. On the Tribal Disputes Regulation I have often written. To its operations I ascribe in very large measure the security now reigning in the Provinces. In Turkish times, when the regular judicial courts tried all offences and took no notice of tribal custom, tribesmen who had committed an offence usually refused to give themselves up and all the borders were filled with outlaws. Vendettas never composed, after tribal custom, by blood money or other compensation, increased and put forth branches. The administration could only control the tribal tracts by intriguing to set one chief against another or by licensed assassination. The Tribal Disputes Regulation has changed all this. Tribesmen appear without hesitation before the councils of their own elders to have the question of their guilt judged by
their own customary laws, and they do not complain if the Administration imposes some reasonable additional punishment. But the politicians and lawyers detest this Regulation, which they consider uncivilised, and, had it not been for my opposition, it would long ago have been abolished, with, I believe, results fatal to internal peace.12. As to conscription, the attitude of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government and myself has, in spite of all discussion which has taken place, been constantly misunderstood. I have never denied that Iraq could by conscription obtain the army which many of her politicians desire more cheaply (by about  150,000 per annum) than under the voluntary system. But I have maintained that in the present state of tribal feeling the enforcement of conscription would cause such widespread risings and require such large forces that it would cost far more than the savings which it might theoretically make possible. It is idle to point to Turkey, where the Anatolian peasant is utterly submissive and accustomed to conscription, or to Persia, where a beginning of conscription has just been made in the towns and has caused much resentment, but as yet no rebellion. Iraq, as I have already insisted, is unique in the predominance of her tribes. The Turks when in Iraq could never enforce conscrip-tion except in a few towns and settled villages, and against the Turks the Kurds held no such feelings as they hold against the Arabs. The only results of conscrip-tion in Iraq would be its effective application to a few towns and some tracts along the Tigris, the flight of the able-bodied men from those tracts into the tribal districts and unrest among the tribes, such as was recently caused even in the Basra district by the operations of the Census Law, which were looked on as a prelude to conscription. His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government have informed the Iraq Government that they are at liberty to introduce conscription, if they can put it into effect by their own forces, but that they must not count on the help of British forces to suppress any risings which may ensue. This has aroused much resentment among the politicians, who accuse Great Britain of trying to keep the Iraq Army weak and of inciting the tribes to resist conscription. No other course was, however, open to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.13. The question of the maintenance of a special regime in the Kurdish districts needs no long discussion. It is a clear obligation towards the League of Nations on the part of both the British and Iraq Governments, and no other regime would abate the traditional dislike of the Kurd for the Arab and secure the retention of the Kurdish tracts in Iraq. Even Turkey and Persia, which had at first hoped to suppress the Kurdish spirit by force, have now been compelled to adopt much the same policy as has been followed in Iraq. If the Kurdish tracts were to get out of hand, the Kurds of the foothills would harry all the northern plains and the main line of communications through Kirkuk and Arbil to Mosul would become untenable. The Arab politicians, however, believe that&apos;they could hold the Kurdish hills by their own force, and they have greatly disliked my insistence on the rule that officials in the Kurdish districts shall, where possible, be Kurds. I fear that, if Arab conceit were ever given its head, South Kurdistan would be lost to them for ever, and a grave blow would be struck at the security and prosperity of Iraq. The oil industry, with all its promise, would certainly become impracticable.14. Intervention on the lines sketched above has, of course, its disadvantages. The Iraqi nationalists and extremists are inclined to allege that the policy of the High Commissioner has been to divide and rule, and that he has himself fostered communalism and accentuated the differences between Sunni and Shiah, citizen and tribesman, Arab and Kurd. A similar accusation against the British with regard to Hindu-Moslem differences is a commonplace Indian political argument, and is equally without foundation. This spice of truth, however, does reside in the nationalist argument, that the presence in any country of an impartial power, attempting to hold the scales even and to prevent the violent domination of one section of the people by another, must if so facto retard the attainment of equilibrium (even if it be the equilibrium of chaos). It has been alleged also that the High Commis-sioner in upholding the tribal system has been attempting to bolster up a dangerous anachronism. In this the critics are mistaken. I recognise that the tribal system must and should in the end disintegrate and make way for the more civilised individualistic system. But the disintegration, if it is to be safe, must be automatic and gradual, timed to allow the Government to substitute their own for the tribal machinery. In holding back the Bagdad politicians from their assaults upon the tribal system, I have merely attempted to act as a brake upon the impatience of the East.15. Finally, I feel that I must meet the criticism that I should have left the British officials of the Iraq Government to intervene in matters such as I have
mentioned, and that I ought to have followed more closely the pronouncement of&apos; His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government that, in view of the employment of a number of British officials, they did not propose to influence in detail the administrative arrangements of the Iraq Government. To this my reply is that the British advisory system does not produce a predominant partner. Each of the principal advisers is an expert in his own line, acknowledging subordination only to his own Minister. Thus, if the British Adviser to the Ministry.of Justice dislikes the Tribal Disputes Regulation, the Adviser to the Ministry of the Interior cannot restrain his attacks upon it; nor can the Adviser to the Interior restrain the Adviser to Finance from undermining the tribal tenure of land. The Prime Minister should, of course, hold the balance and come to a decision between the conflicting views of his British experts; but few Iraqis have personality sufficient to do this; and, in the end, where there is a conflict of British expert opinion, it is usually the High Commissioner who has to make the real decision.16. In conclusion, I must apologise for the length of this despatch which has-greatly outgrown the limits which I had intended to set for it.I have, &amp;c.H. DOBBS,High Commissioner for Iraq.The Right Hon. L. C. M. S. Amery, P.C., M.P.. Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, London, S.W. 1.o

</content>
</cab>
