<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/201/0 images: 618-621</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1929,,&apos;&quot;SECRET^&apos;&apos;&apos;r - /V 1 &apos;&quot;; &quot; . &quot;&apos; Copy No. : ,28CP 32 (29).CABINET.ANGLO-AMERICAN RELATIONS.Lord balfour&apos;s Views&apos;. -  Note by the Secretary.I HAVE received from Lord Balfour an expression of his views on Anglo-American relations, with direction to circulate it to the Cabinet.Lord Balfour, in a private covering letter to me, explains the shape which his views take, as follows::-  -&quot;It is in form a private letter to Borden, and even if I think it good enough to send, I shall take care that it remains strictly private unless it meets, . , broadly speaking, the approval of the Cabinet.&quot;(Signed)    -    M. P. A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, .   , February 9, 1929,.My dear Sir Robert,I AM grateful to you for your letter of the 9th January, enclosing the corres-pondence which has taken place between you and Professor Stewart on present Anglo-American relations. To one who, like myself, has been a life-long and very ardent advocate of a full and friendly understanding between the two English-speaking peoples they are not pleasant reading; but they are not on that account less worthy Of careful consideration.They are not pleasant reading in part because, to optimists like myself, they come as a surprise. Would not any ordinary observer, whether optimist or pessimist, have supposed, if ignorant of the issue, that the course of history had been favourable to that sympathetic understanding between the British Empire and the United States of America, which Professor Stewart, not less than you and I, so greatly desire ? They have been recently associated in the world conflict waged, as they both believe, in the interests of freedom and civilisation. Within the last few days they have become associated under American leadership in the International Pact solemnly proscribing war as an instrument of national policy. Seven years ago the British Empire at Washington formally resigned all claims to naval superiority, and gladly furthered a treaty prescribing equality between their fighting fleets. All these movements seemed calculated to foster international amity, and they had behind them one hundred years of unbroken peace (during which it may be observed there was but one fleet in the world which seriously counted), marked by an unexampled use of arbitral methods for dealing with international differences.So much for the historic prelude. What, according to Professor Stewart, is its present-day sequel? He tells us that a &quot;legend&quot; has grown up in the United States that &quot; England is not to be trusted,&quot; that &quot;the English through long-experience are more astute in the diplomatic game than the Americans,&quot; that &quot; English adroitness is often accompanied by a certain duplicity,&quot; and &quot;that the[18856]
attempted-Anglo-French ^agreement-is-cited-by^ Americans as an instance of this.&quot;: This is certainly, to put it mildly, a very deplorable condition of affairs; and the best suggestion (if I understand him rightly) which Professor Stewart can make is that there should be another Conference; that it should be proposed by England, &quot;provided always that the proposal is made in complete good faith and with a candid recognition of the unalterably fixed policy of the Americans to defend their neutral rights in all future contingencies.&quot;I say nothing for the moment about &quot;candour and good faith.&quot; I dome at once to the other pre-requisite of any international Conference which is mentioned by Professor Stewart, namely, &quot; the recognition of the unalterably fixed policy of the Americans &apos; to defend their neutral rights &apos; in all future contingencies.&quot; This condition is not so simple as it looks. That America has ample power to defend its neutral rights whenever it may choose to exercise it I do not for a moment doubt. If, for example, Great Britain was-again involved in a life and death struggle with European nations of equal strength, America, were she to throw her naval power into the scales, would occupy a commanding position. By supposition the British Empire is already straining its resources to the uttermost, and the intervention of a second fleet equal to its own would obviously change the whole situation to Britain&apos;s disadvantage.Such speculations, however, move me but little. I do not question America&apos;^ naval strength. I question only the confident and &quot; candid &quot; prognostications we are asked to make about the uses to which she will put it. I do not myself believe in a new Armageddon. But should it recur, why are we to assume that, while One branch of the English-speaking peoples is fighting for some great cause to the limits of its capacity, the other will be disputing with it over belligerent rights and neutral claims? Even if such a calamity were indeed to befall us, why assume that in that event America would be the neutral and the British Empire the belligerent? T prophesy that they will throughout be on the same side; but even if this forecast is not completely fulfilled, if, for example, during the first two-thirds of the supposed world-war one of the English-speaking peoples will be making all the sacrifices, while the other is making all the money, why regard it as impossible that the first role should be played by America and the second by Britain ? Why may not the unforeseeable accidents of diplomacy, politics and war make the British Empire for some time the sympathetic neutral and America the hard-pressed belligerent ?The truth is that British experience makes me somewhat doubtful about the use in this connection of such expressions as &quot; unalterably.&quot; At the London Conference in 1909 the British Government of the day agreed to a treaty (subject, of course, to ratification) which modified in important respects existing maritime rules of warfare. The treaty came up for discussion before Parliament, and ratification was refused; but the Government, so far as I am aware, never altered its views on the merits of the case till the bitter experiences of war compelled it to alter its. practice. The behaviour of the enemy, and the developments of the naval situation, destroyed, piece by piece, the scheme which had been so laboriously devised. The very Ministers .whe had helped to frame it were the unwilling authors of its destruction. Am I wrong in adding that long before the Great War there were incidents in the history of the United States itself which provide instructive illustrations of the different perspective in which maritime practice presents itself to the same spectators as they change their outlook from that of a belligerent to that of a neutral ?But (it may be asked) is there no right or wrong in this matter? Are the rules of maritime warfare merely a fine name for the practices which suit the strongest Naval Power of the moment ? Assuredly not. The claims of international morality do not lapse at high-water mark, nor even at the 3-mile limit. But I venture to think that the use of such ph the &quot; freedom of the seas &quot; and &quot;neutral rights&quot;is apt, unless we be careful, to create a misleading atmosphere when we are studying the ethics of war. We are apt instinctively to feel that since Peace is good and War is evil, since it is very desirable that men should trade and not at all desirable that men should fight, it must follow that the rights of neutrals are incomparably more worthy of legal protection than the rights of belligerents. Since the ocean belongs to no one, let it be safe for all. If peace on land be unattainable, let us at least secure it at sea. The presumption ought always to be in favour of him who suffers violence, and against him who employs it.But does not this depend wholly on circumstances ? A blockade runner, though belonging to a neutral country, is acting as a belligerent, and whether the side which he is supporting be right or wrong, at least he takes his chances and runs his risk like
-other-belligerents.. But a neutral manufacturer or, merchant who arranges to aid a belligerent by supplying commodities through neutral territory- is or may be doing! exactly the same thing from the point of view; of morality as the; blockade runner, but with much greater safety to himself. : He is a profiteer making money, perhaps legally, out of the blood and tears of one or other of the belligerents. On what general principle should the seas be &quot; free &quot; to him? If I rightly understand the proposal to which (according to Professor Stewart) American public opinion is &quot;unalterably&quot; attached, such &quot;belligerent neutrals&quot; (to coin a phrase), if they happen to be American citizens, are in future to have behind them the whole strength of the American fleet. I do not argue that this is legally wrong or politically inexpedient. I do not argue at all. I only suggest that, though it may be good for American trade, it is not obviously moral. The whole subject, indeed, is difficult and complicated, not, I suspect, to be decided by a simple appeal to abstract ethical principles.I do not think that Professor Stewart would necessarily dissent from this. His view is that there ought to be a Conference, and that Britain ought to ask for it. Such a Conference would, he believes, provide a fitting arena where such problems as these, and others associated with them, could be profitably discussed in a cool and friendly spirit.There is much to be said for this. At a time when the miseries of war are fresh in all men&apos;s recollections, when such novel and heroic measures for promoting peace as the establishment of the League of Nations and the Kellogg Pact have actually been adopted, and the renewal and modification of old arbitration treaties are under -discussion, a fitting opportunity might perhaps be supplied for surveying the whole field of international law and arbitral practice with a view to bringing them up to date.But the task will not prove an easy one, and I hope the British Empire will take no initiative till the difficulties of the scheme have been duly weighed. Our experiences have not been reassuring. The problem of naval disarmament is now (it seems) mixed up in the minds of the American public with the maritime rights of Neutrals; though of all the international problems requiring solution the laws of maritime belligerency ought to be the least pressing, as they certainly are the most dangerous. They are the least pressing because the state of war which they presuppose has just been universally renounced. They are the most dangerous because they raise unnecessarily every sort.of unsolved controversy, historical and technical, they lend themselves to the invention of hard cases and deal with situations which the progress of invention is always in process of rendering obsolete.&quot; Arbitration,&quot; on the other hand, is a subject which rises in importance as war diminishes. But if the American public be in the mood represented by Professor Stewart, is this a safe subject of international debate? I hardly think so. No doubt arbitration, take it all in all, has worked extremely well; largely because it has been used in the main by Nations anxiously desirous of Peace, who grasp at it as a means of honourably securing it. But if its application is to be universal, surely some effort should be made to reduce it to a clear, logical and workable system.English-speaking communities will at once appreciate the sort of difficulty to which the pursuit of this ideal may easily give rise. In recent Treaties reservations have been made by the United States with regard to the Monroe Doctrine, and by the British Empire with regard to a line of communication in the East. Supposing these reservations are accepted, as presumably they will be, who is to explain with authority their scope and significance ? Doubtless the countries which had originally laid them down will claim the right to define them, and this claim also may perhaps be conceded. But will they also claim to be the legal interpreters of their own definitions or to re-define a doctrine if changing circumstances seem, from their point of view, to make a new definition desirable ? And if they did, would the other nations willingly agree ?Arbitration can only be expected to work smoothly when the Nations arbitrating are anxious for a peaceful solution. They can then be trusted to create, if it be not already in existence, an Arbitral Court, qualified not merely by its impartiality, but by its competence, to deal fairly between the parties. In private life there are very commonly two quite different things to be decided firstly, what is the exact point to be submitted for arbitration, secondly, who are to be the arbiters ? How is it possible to avoid dealing with these problems when we are concerned not with individuals but&apos;with Nations ? And how, in the case of nations, are they to be treated ?  Can we hope to constitute a permanent Court of Arbitration, competent to .
deal with every - class&apos;bf.&apos;&apos; ca&amp;^legal?- - nKilitary&apos;, &apos;&quot;-haval,&apos;:&apos; geographical, &amp;c, or to-determine. on what part of a complicated controversy it is qualified to offer a final opinion? Are we to submit to case-made law? If points of difficulty arise (and ,.how can they be avoided?), who is to decide them? Who is to arbitrate about arbitration? -J -   - :i:;:I have said enough (I fear you will think much more than enough) to indicate the difficulty of devising new rules of universal application for preserving peace and conducting war. These are well worth the earnest consideration of serious thinkers. But after reading Professor Stewarfs letter, and after surveying the history of the last two years, can anyone seriously suppose that in the present temper of the American people (as depicted by Professor Stewart) a Conference initiated by Great Britain could at the present moment end in anything but disaster ?

</content>
</cab>
