<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/204/19 images: 219-222</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(?8)u10 COPY NO 8015 November 1978CABINETRHODESIAN SANCTIONS:  FURTHER INQUIRYNote by the Lord Chancellor** I attach a draft report by the group established at Cabinet last week under my chairmanship which we agreed subject to checking the point about aJoint Resolution (see paragraph 3. c. ) with the Clerks of both Houses.This checking has revealed that it is not possible to establish aspecial Commission (or any other unique body) by Joint Resolution. The^ost we could do would be to have a normal joint Select Committee which^uld be constrained by its order of reference to sit in private and publish0nly such of its evidence as was directly relevant to its findings.    It would^ot be possible to control the provision of Cabinet papers in the way suggestedln paragraph 3. f. of the draft report below.If therefore a further inquiry is to meet the objectives set out inParagraph 1 of the draft below, it looks as though the choice lies between:-a. a Special Commission set up by Act of Parliament;b. a Royal Commission composed of Parliamentarians whosereport would be published as a Command paper.E-J^rd Chancellor&apos;s Department15 November 1978
RHODESIAN SANCTIONS:  FURTHER INQUIRYNote by the Lord Chancellor** I was asked, together with the Lord President of the Council, theHome Secretary, the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and the attorney general, to consider how a further inquiry could best be structured within the constraints provisionally identified in the Cabinet&apos;s discussion(CM(78) 38th Conclusions, Minute 5).    We are agreed in believing that theseconstraints mean that a new inquiry should:-a. be Parliamentary in character but deliberately differentiatedfrom an ordinary Select Committee or Joint Committee, both because it will be necessary to produce Cabinet papers to it and inorder to emphasise its unique nature;b. sit under a Chairman who besides being a Parliamentarianwould also be an impartial and experienced legal figure;c. be a small body (to facilitate expeditious working and alsothe production of Cabinet documents) but at the same time be drawn from the main political Parties and both Houses of Parliament;d. have terms of reference which, while inevitably wide-ranging(on the lines of those suggested in CP(78) 91), should also directattention specifically to the main questions which have emerged inthe Parliamentary debates, namely whether Ministers misledParliament or each other and whether they were themselves misledby officials or the oil companies;e. have access to Cabinet and Cabinet Committee papers and alsoDepartmental papers (including those at No 10) relevant to its work;f. be guided by the general rule that Cabinet papers are not made public, but be free exceptionally to publish selected Cabinet documentsor extracts from them if it considers this essential to explain itsfindings;g. if possible avoid, and in any case minimise, the need for legalrepresentation of witnesses;h. conduct its hearings in private:  this will be controversial butwe believe it to be essential if Cabinet papers are to be produced: andif the inquiry is to avoid legal representation of witnesses;i. publish its findings but not its evidence;j. if possible be set up without legislation.1
2* Underlying these points must be a proper concern to allow asearching examination and disclosure of the facts whilst at the same timeprotecting individuals from unfair attack and the integrity of the decision-taking processes necessary for good government.3.        Against this background our specific recommendations are that, ifthere is to be a further inquiry, it should:-a. sit under the chairmanship of Lord Scarman who is a memberof the House of Lords, a Privy Counsellor and a distinguished memberof the Judiciary;b. comprise five other members drawn from either House ofParliament, two to be nominated by the Government, two to be nominated by the Conservative Opposition and one to be nominated by the Liberal Party;c. be called a &quot;Special Commission&quot; to distinguish it from a normal Joint Select Committee but be established by Resolution ofboth Houses of Parliament;d. have the following terms of reference -&quot;Following the report of the Bingham Inquiry, to considerthe part played by those concerned in the development and application of the policy of oil sanctions against Rhodesia,with a view to determining whether Parliament or ministers were misled, intentionally or otherwise, and to report&quot;;e. be serviced by the staff of Parliament;f. be given unrestricted access to relevant Cabinet papers andalso Departmental papers and those at No 10 under a procedurewhereby the Chairman, with the assistance of the Treasury Solicitor,would determine which of them were relevant and needed to be seen by the other members.    It would also fall to the inquiry to determinewhich documents or extracts should be made available to eachwitness;g. conduct its proceedings in private, but publish its full findingsthough not its evidence.    The Commission would be reminded of thegeneral rule that Cabinet papers are not made public but would be free to publish selected Cabinet papers or extracts from them if itconsidered this essential to explain its findings;h. otherwise be free to determine its own procedures includingwhether exceptionally it became necessary to allow a witnessrepresentation by counsel.2
4. In the meantime no waiver should be given from prosecution for offences revealed by the Bingham Report:  but the Attorney General would maintain close contact with the Chairman of the Special Commission incase this should become necessary.e-j15 November 19783

</content>
</cab>
