<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/19/34 images: 376-385</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1941.SECRET. Copy No.W.P.        261-November 8, 1941.IfmTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK and KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.COMMITTEE ON POLICY IN REGARD TO ETHIOPIA.REPORT.1. THE Committee* were appointed, by direction of the Prime Minister,with the following terms of. reference  &apos;&quot; To examine and present to the War Cabinet the issues for decision in regard to Ethiopia, with particular reference to such safeguards as may bethought necessary to meet the military requirements of the General Staff.&quot;General.2. Ethiopia, although it has virtually ceased to be a theatre of war,continues to be a major military commitment. Our principal military interestsin the country are as follows : (a) The security of the main North-South road communications, which formthe best over-land route between Kenya on the one hand and theNile Valley and Red Sea Littoral on the other.(b) The security of the landing grounds and maintenance facilities and thesecurity of the railway .(c) The protection, maintenance and feeding, until evacuated, of some 40,000Italian civilians, who are the responsibility of the G.O.C.-in-C,and many of whom are necessary for the running of the utilityservices and railway. This involves also the security of the road fromBerbera to Addis Ababa.(d) The security of the surrounding territories, such as Eritrea, British andItalian Somalilands and Kenya.3. Certain parts of Ethiopia, which are vital to the preservation of our military communications and in which any outbreak of disorder would prejudicethese communications, are &apos;&apos; reserved areas,&apos;&apos; under direct British military* The Committee consisted of the Lord President of the Council (Chairman); theParliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office; the Financial Secretary, War Office-Mr. G. MacKereth, Foreign Office; Mr. A. J. Dawe, Colonial Office; and BrigadierA. W. S. Mallaby, War Office.[23125] B
control. It is the intention, as the country settles down, that these areas shouldbe restored by degrees to the civil administration. At present they are a directcharge on the British Exchequer and none of the moneys spent on their administration passes through the Emperor&apos;s hands.4. The remainder of the country is under the nominal control of theEmperor, whose main task is to re-establish his authority and to put into operation the machinery of government.5. It is the declared policy* of His Majesty&apos;s Government to assist theEmperor to establish an independent Ethiopia. The Emperor has. howeverasked for, and His Majesty&apos;s Government have agreed to give him, the outsideguidance and assistance which he needs. In view of the disorganised conditionof the country following upon the Italian occupation and the war of liberation, itis clear that a period of transition must elapse before the country can hope tomaintain its independence unaided.The Cabinet&apos;s Instructions.6. With these considerations in mind, the War Cabinet (W.M. 58 (41)conclusions to Item 4) approved on the 9th June, 1941, proposals submitted tothem by the Secretary of State for War as a basis on which Major-General Sir P.Mitchell, British Representative in Ethiopia and Chief Political Officer,Occupied Territories, East Africa, should sound the Emperor with a view toarriving at an understanding with him on the issues involved. These proposals were as follows : (i) The Emperor and Ethiopian authorities to agree to abide in all important matters, internal and external, touching the Government ofthe country, by the advice tendered to them by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment, and to conduct the administration in accordance with the advice of the officers deputed by His Majesty&apos;s Government.(ii) Taxation and expenditure to require the prior approval of HisMajesty&apos;s Governments representative.(iii) Pending further consideration of the judicial system to be applied to foreigners in Ethiopia, jurisdiction over the person, rights orproperty of foreigners to be reserved to special courts presided overby British officers; these courts may, however, administer Ethiopianlaw if the prior consent of His Majesty&apos;s Governments representa-tive has been obtained to the application of that law.(iv) If the Commander-in-Chief notifies the Emperor that for military reasons it is necessary to resume military control of any part of ethiopia,, the Emperor will raise no objection.(v) No armed forces to be raised nor military operations undertaken except as may be agreed by His Majesty&apos;s Governments representative onthe advice of the British Military Mission,(vi) If the foregoing conditions prove acceptable to the Emperor, HisMajesty&apos;s Government might offer to: (a) find such sums as may be necessary to establish the armed forces,administrative and other services immediately needed in ethiopia.(&amp;) Make available expert advisers for the Emperor, his ministers and provincial authorities.(c) Use its best endeavours to re-establish the Ethiopian Governmentand organise its administrative, technical and social service as may be practicable at this stage.(d) Operate the communications necessary for the above to the extent that this is beyond the present capacity of Ethiopians.* See, e.g., reply by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to a question in the Hoof j Commons put by Mr. Mander on the 4th February, 1941.
(e) Examine proposals for a Treaty which the Emperor and the ethiopian Government, when it is in fact established, may wishto make, including a general financial settlement, which wouldtake account of expenditure incurred in the re-conquest of ethiopia.7. In pursuance of these instructions, Sir Philip Mitchell has been able toreach an understanding with the Emperor which has been elaborated into a draft agreement. In general, the draft correctly interprets the instructions given bythe Cabinet, with the important qualification that, in a number of respects,[ Sir Philip Mitchell felt bound to defer to the Emperor&apos;s arguments that completeacceptance by him of the Cabinet instructions would render the status of Ethiopiaindistinguishable from that of a Protectorate.8. On examination of the draft Agreement it appeared that there was room for a difference of opinion as to the practical application of its terms, particu-larly in regard to the degree of control to be exercised by the advisers. Furtherconsideration showed, however, that this difference was not so great as had atfirst sight appeared. There was no difference of opinion as to the nature of theprincipal British objective in Ethiopia, namely, the maintenance of Britishstrategic interests.9. In the view of the War Office the outbreak of disorder on a large scale in Ethiopia would imperil our communications and the War Office have emphasised that this would necessitate, the despatch of further troops to Ethiopia.Serious disorder must therefore be prevented. The more efficient the Ethiopianadministration the less likelihood there is of disorder. His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave therefore a direct interest in building up an Ethiopian administrationcapable of preventing disorder. This, could only be achieved by a measure of central guidance and supervision exercised by His Majesty&apos;s Government.Subject to this guidance the War Office visualised financial assistance to theEmperor of the order of  2,500,000 per annum, less whatever the Ethiopianrevenues might provide. This figure was based on the calculations of the financialadvisers in Ethiopia.10. The view of the Foreign Office on the other band has been that our military interests in Ethiopia can best be safeguarded by avoiding any appearance of exercising close supervision over the Ethiopian administration. They pointedout that the Emperor could only maintain his prestige if the people really believedhim to be the ruler. If they were to lose this belief, his prestige would be under-mined, his authority would collapse and complete disorder would follow. TheForeign Office considered that the Emperor should be able to maintain a sufficiently high standard of military security with an administration controlled by Ethiopians. They advocated financial assistance in the form of a lump sumgrant substantially less in amount than the assistance recommended by the WarOffice, the necessary control being secured by the power to withold grant if the ethiopian administration were conducted on lines not acceptable to His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.11. In considering the points at issue the Committee have taken oral evidence from Lieut.-General Sir William Platt, General Officer Commanding-in-Chief,East Africa.Major-General Sir Philip Mitchell, British Representative in Ethiopia and chief Political Officer, Occupied Territories, East Africa.Brigadier D. A. Sandford, Personal Military and Political Adviser to theEmperor of Ethiopia.Major E. A. Chapman-Andrews, Foreign Office Representative on the middle east Intelligence Centre, Cairo.Brigadier Lord Rennell of Rodd, Controller, Finance and Accounts, PoliticalHeadquarters, East Africa Command.They also had reports from the first four officers.[23125] b 2
Position of A dvisers.12. The Committee were unanimous in the view that it would be incompatible with the Emperor&apos;s independent status that his British advisers should be appointed on terms which gave them any responsibility to the BritishGovernment. They should be completely free to advise in accordance with theirown judgment and in the best interests of Ethiopia, although they should naturallyavoid giving advice which would conflict with wider Imperial interests. No-authority, whether British or Ethiopian, should be empowered to issue orders to them concerning the nature of their advice. They should have access to theBritish representative for consultation and guidance.Being British subjects, it is assumed that the advisers will retain a residualloyalty to His Majesty The King, and that in matters of high policy they willnot advise the Ethiopian authorities in a manner calculated to prejudice vitalBritish interests or obstruct our war effort.So far as advisers may be appointed in the Provinces, they should haveopportunities of conferring together and of seeking guidance as necessary fromthe British advisers at the Centre.Finance.13. The Committee have approached the problem of finance on thefollowing assumptions : (a) It is not the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government to exercise a&quot; civilising &quot; mission in Ethiopia.(&amp;) Ethiopia must eventually become a self-supporting State; His Majesty&apos;sGovernment cannot contemplate any financial commitment in respectof Ethiopia after the war.(c) The Emperor should not be encouraged to establish a system of adminis-tration which he could not continue without external support.(d) If it should prove necessary on purely political grounds to affordtemporary assistance in excess of what could be justified under theforegoing heads, this should be in respect of non-recurring services(e.g., resettlement of patriots).(e) All expenditure in respect of the administration of reserved areas and reserved subjects (railways, certain main roads, tele-communications,the necessary provision for the remaining Italian population, &amp;c.) willbe paid and accounted for direct by Political Headquarters, EastAfrica Command, and will not pass through the EthiopianExchequer.14. In assessing the amount of the subvention, the following considerations are material: (a) The amount must not be so low as to make it too difficult for the Emperorto maintain his authority without resultant disorder.(b) The cost of the Ethiopian Army is bound to be substantially greater now than when settled conditions obtain.(c) During the next two years, which will be critical so far as the Emperor efforts to re-establish his authority are concerned, we should not be tooniggardly in our allocation of funds for the Emperor&apos;s civil list; inparticular, too violent a contrast between the period of the Italianoccupation and the present should be avoided.15. On present information the Committee are not in a position to say,between the limits of the sums proposed by the Foreign Office and the War Officerespectively, what the appropriate amount of the subvention should be. Botndepartments have been asked to review their estimates in the light of the above and other relevant considerations.The Committee do not think that it would be practicable to attempt to fix a lump sum which should be announced to the Emperor as the amount of. theassistance which he might expect to receive over a definite period.
IP QX    j16. It will be necessary, in the Committee&apos;s view, to exercise through a financial Controller a general measure of supervision over the expenditure of exchequer grants-in-aid to the Ethiopian budget. The precise functions of this financial Controller will have to be defined. The Committee consider that thisis a matter for the Foreign Office and the War Office to settle with the Treasury.For their part, the Committee visualise that the position he should hold should,in a sense, be analogous to that of the Controller and Auditor-General in respectof grants-in-aid to local authorities; that is to say, he should satisfy himself that the system of control exercised by the Ethiopian Exchequer through theBritish financial advisers is a sound system, rather than that he should under-take a detailed check of the expenditure himself. It is also for consideration whether the Financial Controller in respect of Exchequer assistance to the ethiopian budget should or should not also act as Financial Adviser in respectof direct British military expenditure in Ethiopia.Resumption of Diplomatic Relations with Ethiopia.17. Our acknowledgement of Ethiopia&apos;s independence carries with it the implication that sooner or later there should be an exchange of diplomatic missions.18. The War Office have held the view that the time is not ripe for theappointment of a diplomatic representative. They preferred that the presentsystem should continue until more settled conditions have stabilised the Emperor&apos;administration on a firmer basis than at present. On the other hand, the Emperoris known to be most anxious to receive a diplomatic representative and the ForeignOffice considered that his position would be much fortified by such an appoint-ment. Moreover, Parliament is likely to take strong objection to any considerable delay. The Committee are of the opinion that a public announcement of our intention to make the appointment should be issued as soon as possible. Asregards the actual date, in the view of the Foreign Office the diplomatic repre-sentative should be appointed as from the date of the signature of the draft agreement. On the other hand, the War Office call attention to the fact that ina Memorandum* agreed between the Minister of State and Sir Philip Mitchell,dated the 20th October, 1941, the Minister of State had expressed an intentionto visit Ethiopia as soon as opportunity offers to examine conditions on the spotwith a view to making a definite recommendation as to the date at which a diplo-matic representative should be appointed. The War Office urge that no definitedate should be communicated to the Emperor until the Minister of State has hadan opportunity to make his report.19. Since the withholding of funds is our principal means of exercisinginfluence upon the Emperor, it will be necessary, after the appointment of a diplomatic representative, that the Foreign Office should consult with the WarOffice before authorising the diplomatic representative to issue or withhold suchfunds.20. An important administrative problem associated with the appointmentof the diplomatic representative ought also to be settled. It relates to the rightof access to the Emperor on the part of the General Officer Commanding-in-Chiefor his representative in Addis Ababa, in the event of a threat, actual or potential,to our military security from outbreaks of disorder in the country. The Com-mittee attach great importance to the War Office view that the General OfficerCommanding-in-Chief or his representative should have direct access to theEmperor in cases where urgent action seems necessary on military grounds. Thisarrangement should be entirely without prejudice to the duties and privileges ofthe diplomatic representative, who should, in every case, be informed immediatelyof any such steps taken by a military Commander. In practice it is felt that nodifficulty would arise, and the Emperor is known to be favourabe to the proposed arrangement.21. In presenting in this Report the main issues, the Committee haverefrained from commenting on a number of important points of detail whichhave been discussed by them and which will have to be settled inter-depart-mentally when the Cabinet have disposed of the main issues.* Paper C.P.E. (41) 3, Annex 7, para. 6.
Summary of Issues.22. The issues as to which the directions of the Cabinet are required arefollows : System of Control and Position of Advisers.(1) Should the proposals approved by the Cabinet on the 9th June, 1941(W.M. 58 (41) Conclusions to Item 4), as a basis for the negotiation of a draft Agreement with the Emperor, be modified so as to makeit clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government do not intend even temporarilyto set up a Protectorate in Ethiopia ?   (Para. 7.)(2) Should our main objective in Ethiopia, viz. the maintenance of Britishstrategic interests, be achieved by :  (a) A detailed system of supervision and control of the Ethiopianeconomy and administration, exercised through British advisershaving responsibility to the British Government as contem-plated by the Cabinet decision of the 9th June; or(b) A  system, of control  in respect of subjects  not  specificallyreserved relying in the main upon the power to withholdthe British grant-in-aid if it appeared that the Ethiopianadministration was being conducted on lines not acceptable to His Majesty&apos;s Government, the British advisers underthis system having&apos; no ultimate responsibility to theBritish Government, but being so selected and circumstancedas to warrant the assumption that they would retain a residualloyalty to His Majesty The King, and that in matters of highpolicy the)&apos; would not give advice in a manner calculated to prejudice vital British interests or obstruct our war effort.(Paras. 9-12.)Finance.(3) Should the amount of the subvention to be paid to the EthiopianExchequer be based on the following assumptions : (a) It is not the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government to exercise ao        &quot; civilising &quot; mission in Ethiopia.(&amp;) Ethiopia must eventually become a self-supporting State; HisMajesty&apos;s Government cannot contemplate any financial com-commitment in respect of Ethiopia after the war.(c) The Emperor should not be encouraged to establish a system ofadministration which he could not continue without externalsupport.(d) If it should prove necessary on purely political grounds to affordtemporary assistance in excess of what could be justified underthe foregoing heads, this should be in respect of non-recurringservices (e.g. re-settlement of patriots).(e) All expenditure in respect of the administration of reserved areas and reserved subjects (railways, certain main roads, tele-communications, the necessary provision for the remainingItalian population, &amp;c.) will be paid and accounted for directby Political Headquarters, East Africa Command, and willnot pass through the Ethiopian Exchequer.(/) The amount must not be so low as to make it too difficult for theEmperor to maintain his authority without resultant disorder.(g) During the next two years, which will be critical so far as theEmperor&apos;s efforts to re-establish his authority are concerned,we should not be too niggardly in our allocation of funds forthe Emperor&apos;s civil list; in particular, too violent a contrastbetween the period of the Italian occupation and the presentshould be avoided.   (Paras. 13 and 14.)(Paras. 13 and 14.)
(4) Should the duty of the Financial Controller be : &apos;(a) To exercise a detailed check upon the expenditure of the Britishgrant-in-aid to the Ethiopian Exchequer; or(b) To do no more, after approval of the Ethiopian budget, thansatisfy himself that the system of control exercised by the ethiopian Exchequer through the British financial advisersis sound?   (Para. 16).Resumption of Diplomatic Relations with Ethiopia.(5) (a) Should a public announcement be made as soon as possible stating the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to appoint a diplomatic representative; and if so,(b) Should any date be fixed now for such appointment, or should a recommendation on this point be awaited from the Minister ofState ?(6) After the appointment of a diplomatic representative, should the GeneralOfficer Commanding-in-Chief in East Africa or his representative at Addis Ababa, have direct access to the Emperor in cases whereurgent action on military grounds seems necessary?   (Paras. 17-20.)Signed on behalf of the Committee :JOHN ANDERSON,Chairman.Great George Street, S.W. 1,November 8, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
