<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/94/9 images: 122-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL



THIS DOCUMENT IS THE IROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



OOPY NO



?8



CABINET



CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet

held at 10 Downing Street on



THURSDAY 28 SEPTEMBER 1989



at 9.30 am



PRESENT



The Rt Hen Margaret Thatcher MP

Prime Minister



Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe

President of the Council



Rt Hon The lord Mackay of CI

Chancellor



Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP

tary of State for Employment



Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP

tary of State for Trade and



lustry



Rt Hon Kenneth Clarke QC MP

retary of State for Health



e Rt Hon Malcolm Rifkind QC MP

tary of State for Scotland



e Rt Hon Jchn Wakeham MP

:retary of State for Energy



Rt Hon Antony Newton MP

tary of State for Social Security



Rt Hon Peter Brooke MP

tary of State for Northern

land



The Rt Hen Nigel Iawson MP

Chancellor of the Exchequer



The Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP

Secretary of State for the Heme

Department



Rt Hon Tan King MP

!tary of State for Defence



Kenneth Baker MP

of the Duchy of Lancaster



The Rt

Secret

and Scii



MacGregor MP

State for Education



The Rt Hen Cecil Parkinson MP

Secretary of St^j^^r Transport



Ihe Rt Hon The

Lord Privy Seal



The Rt Hon Chr:

Secretary of State for



The Rt Hen John Selwyn

Minister of Agriculture,

and Food



MP



ironment



The Rt Hon Norman Lament MP

Chief Secretary, Treasury



!confidential!




confidential



THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT



  Hon David Waddington QC MP

lanentary Secretary, Treasury



The Hon William Waldegrave MP

Minister of State, Foreign and

Ccrnrronwealth Office



SECRETARIAT



Sir Robin Butler

Mr L V Appleyard

Mr D A Hadley

Mr   J C Mawer

Mrs J Bailey



(Items 3 and 4)



(Items 3 and 4)



(Items 1 and 2)



(Items 1 and 2)



1988/89 and 1989/90



of the House of Commons



CONTENTS

Subject



PARLIAMENTARY



Legislati1



Televising

HOME AFFAIRS



National Health Ser^



?



Teachers&apos; Pay for 19

Explosion at Royal Mar;

Industrial Actio! in the

Anglo-Irish Conference

Social Security Improvements

FOREIGN AFFAIRS

Arms Control

Hong Kong



Prime Minister&apos;s Visit to Japan 9-22 Sq



Prime Minister&apos;s Visit to the Soviet Union

22-23 September 1989



Annual Meetings of the International Monetary Fund

World Bank



COMMUNITY AFFAIRS



Assistance to Poland and Hungary

Social Charter



ii



Page



1

1



2

3

3

4

4

5



ICONFIPENflAp




CONFIDENTIAL[



5NTARY



1.     LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL informed the



Cabinet, on a confidential basis, of the proposed date for

the State opening of Parliament.   He said that pressure on

the legislative programmes in the present session and the

next one was very heavy.   A number of major Bills to be

considered in the Parliamentary spillover were facing

substantial amendment: he was, in particular, discussing

^with the Secretary of State for the Environment the



for reducing the number of amendments to the

Government arid Housing Bill.   It would be helpful if

&gt;colleagues with an interest in Bills presently before



would take a very rigorous view of proposals for

and would also ensure that as many

1its to the Bills as possible were tabled by the time



resumed.   Ihe programme for the 1989/90 session

if anything, even heavier than the present me, and

in view of the desirability of starting the fourth session



of the p:

as possib

about the

programme p:

Ministers wi

ensure that

Counsel as qui!

introduced prar



IHE LORD FRIVY SEAL

resuming sitting on 9

Employment Bill, the L

the Self-Governing School

caiplete their passage

due to return to the Lords

and Oatpanies Bills - would,

the subject of considerable

Ihe target for completing the

a very tight one.



Ihe Cabinet -



Parliament as close to the conventional time

was in touch with a number of colleagues

postponement of several items in the

nally agreed by the Cabinet in March,

remaining in the programme should

were delivered to Parliamentary

ible in order that Bills could be

start of the new session.



the House of Lords would



Ihree major Bills - the

kernment and Housing Bill, and

and) Bill had still to

House, and other Bills

Cannons - the Children

returned, have been

in the lower House,

iness was therefore



Took note.



evising of

Proceedings

the House of



10US



erence:

89) 20.1



IHE IORD PRESIDENT OF     COUNCIL said that the

experimental televising of proceedings in the House  J &gt;^

Caramons would begin after the State Opening of the

session,   !here would be a period frcm 17 October whe^

cameras in the Chamber would be functioning but not

would be transmitted, so that the broadcasters could

out any difficulties.   Ihe introduction of cameras would&quot;

mean that Ministers would have to review their

Parliamentary speaking style: in particular it would not be&apos;



1



CONFIDENTIAL


confidential



AFFAIRS



evious

f erence:

1(89 ) 26 .2



good enough for them simply to read out  lengthy

Departmental briefs couched in technical language.   He was

discussing with other interested colleagues what more

general advice could be given to Ministers on this issue,

and what advantage, if any, could be taken, on a basis

agreed between the Parties, of the period between the

return and the State Opening.   He would issue

further guidance to colleagues in due course.



PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said

it was clear that the advent of television would

the style which Ministers adopted in the House,

sion might appear to call for a more impromptu style

were many Parliamentary occasions on which the

precise words used by Ministers were very important.

Ministers should use plain language but should not forfeit

the authority with which they spoke under the pressure of

the new mediym.   Ihe possibility of providing a lectern on

the despatai^bkx should be explored.   Ihe experience of

other Parlwjmejp^. such as the Canadian, might provide seme

helpful les^QrarSVlhe lord President of the Council should

continue his ra  g a&amp;ion of the issues and arrange guidance

to colleagues j^^U^vCcurse.



Took note, with a^^^

summing up of this

the Lord President

the Chancellor of the&quot;

guidance to colleagues



of the Prime Minister&apos;s

their discussion and invited

5il, in consultation with

of Lancaster, to circulate

.course.



2.       IHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR HEALTH said that he had

had a useful meeting the previous day with representatives

of the British Medical Association (EMA).  Although this

was expected to be a routine business meeting, the Chairman

of the EMA had attended.   In the course o:

EMA representatives had accepted his

proposal in the White Paper on the reform  !

Health Service (NHS) to introduce indicative

for general practitioners (GPs) would net

situations where patients had to be refused

drugs.   This was an important breakthrough, since

assurance given was not a new one, and had involved

concession on his part.   Despite initial reluctance

representatives had agreed to the immediate publicat

a joint statement announcing this development. This

be most helpful in presenting the Government&apos;s case

the caning months, and in countering arguments from the

opponents of the NHS reforms that the elderly and sick



!confidential!




!confidential!



I



might suffer as a result of the introduction of indicative

drug budgets.



sion at

Marine

1 of

, Deal



THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE said that

he had announced on the previous day the remit of the

^XOnterim Advisory Committee (IAC) on teachers pay for 1990-

s&gt;yn$   The additional provision of  600 million was

^jxj&amp;iderably more than in previous years and provided

&lt;2J$s590ility f r tackling problems in the educational system

the recruitment and retention of staff. It



an increase in the teachers  pay bill  of just

oveK^7.5%.   Seen in the context of falling inflation and

given the settlement would not take effect until next

April, the remit was a fair one.   Ihe immediate response of



the Natior

of School!!

disappoint

walkout at

further

action would



,mi



don of Teachers and the National Association

s/Uhion of Women Teachers was however



of the latter&apos;s members had staged a

in West Yorkshire the previous day, and

could not be ruled out. Such

ible.



    SECRETARY OF STATE

a serious explosion at

Deal cn the previous Friday

Bandsmen had been killed

seriously.   Ihe number of

high because of the construct!

the barb had exploded.   Ihe exp

Provisional Irish Republican



said that there had been

Marine School of Music in

eh 10 Royal Marine

, 8 of them

had been particularly

rest room in which



the work of the

which had for seme

ign against military



time been trying to step up its



targets in Great Britain.   His predecessor had set in hand

the previous year a major progranme of improvements to the

security of defence establishments, cost ?

million.   The benefits of this had

number of recent incidents in which int

prevented frcm entering Service bases, and

steps to accelerate the programme. Neve

of the security problem was considerable:

2,000 defence installations of widely varying

sensitivity.   He was reviewing security arrange

light of the incident, in particular the employment&lt;

private security firms to help guard establishments.&apos;

would be wrong to conclude frcm what had happened at

that the employment of such firms should cease: there

proper role for adequately vetted and trained civilians

suitable numbers, in support of military personnel, in



!confidential!




!confidential



Bus trial

ion in

tobulance

vice



vious

erence:

89) 28.2



 10-Irish

|ference



vious

terence:

189) 28.2



undertaking routine, low grade security duties.

Nevertheless he was reviewing the present contracts with

these firms and would not hesitate to take immediate action

to terminate contracts if deficiencies emerged. One

worrying feature of the Deal incident had been the failure

of members of the public to report to the police the

presence of three Irishmen in a house close to the

barracks.   He was encouraging station commanders to urge

the local community to be alert at all times to the

^&quot;^otential terrorist threat.



*Y OF STATE FOR        said that the action by

[ance drivers which had begun on 14 September had not

so far been serious and had attracted little publicity.



m



!here were

weekends,

unaff



expected, th

offer over tl

action.   It wa^ij

develop.   He was&apos;

Although the Mana&lt;

continued to urge tl^

improved their origin

Enployees (NOTE) cpnt

refused to negotiate



localised problems, particularly at the

sane areas services were almost

ituation could however deteriorate if, as

Lance officers rejected their 6.5% pay

t few days, and joined in the industrial

t to predict how the dispute would

imistic of a quick settlement,

ide of the NHS Whitley Council

irption of pay talks, and had



, the National Union of Public

press for arbitration and



m



One matter of direct

Lancashire Ambulance Servi

the Conservative Party Conf

considering with the Chancello:

what alternative arrangements



specif ic threat by the

ambulance cover for

Blackpool.   He was

Duchy of Lancaster

made.



    SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN

meeting of the Anglo-Irish Conference

September.   The meeting had been lengthy

Foreign Minister had expressed serious

number of issues, centring on the Ulster Def

(UDR) and recent alleged leaks of information

Republican terrorists from the regiment to Prates

military groups.   Ihe Irish representatives had not

however, asked for the disbandment of the regiment

there had subsequently been ambiguous statements from

Dublin about this.   In reply he had emphasised the

interest of the two governments in improving confidence

the security forces in Northern Ireland particularly wi



!confidential!




lCONFIDENJIALj



the nationalist community, and had set-out the many steps

which the British Government was taking to that end. He

had also made clear that the British Government could not

agree either to the disbandment of the UER or the

withdrawal of plastic baton rounds.   At the Irish

representatives&apos; request, a further conference had been

convened under the terms of the Anglo-Irish Agreement for 5

October: this gave a 3-week hiatus and he was using the



to prepare the British position for that meeting with

frcm the Chief Constable of the Royal Ulster

Lary and the General Officer Occmanding, Northern

He would make sure that the Irish Government knew

of the British position in advance of the

so that they did not build up undue expectations

outcome.   Meanwhile, the inquiry by the Deputy Chief

of Cambridgeshire into the recent alleged leaks

of information from the security forces was making good

progress and_enjoying excellent cooperation frcm the

security



IHE



Minister

Defence Regi

regiment.



FOR DEFENCE said that the Prime

?ks during her visit to the Ulster

done much to boost morale in the



    PRIME MINISTER,

that it had to be

had now been killed

Lapses ih the security

heart of the difficult!

actions of the terrorists

Irish Republic.   This po

discussions at the conf&lt;



up a brief discussion, said

that 180 members of the UER

jrists, 149 of them off duty,

could not be condoned. Ihe

Lster, however, was the

&gt;pf whom found refuge in the

not be overlooked in the



THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SSJCURITY said that three

important improvements in social security arrangements

would shortly ccme into effect.   The pensioners&apos; earnings

rule would be abolished from the follow:

in National Insurance arrangements frcm 5&apos;

mean reductions in contributions for seme

employees; and increases in income support

benefits for pensioners aged 75 or ever or di

be iirplemented cn 9 October.   An advertising

already under way drawing the attention of



to these changes.   He would be writing to Parliamen

colleagues shortly to remind them of the changes, f

which a substantial number of people stood to

considerably.



!confidential!


(confidential



1



The Cabinet -

Took note.



THE MINISTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND OCMCNWEAITH

(MR WAUDBGRAVE) said that the meetings between the

States Secretary of State, Mr James Baker, and the

Foreign Minister, Mr Eduard Shevardnadze, in



and President Bush&apos;s address to the united Nations

Assembly, had enabled the West once again to seize

tiative on arms control.   The American-Soviet



agreement on chemical weapons reached at Wyoming

had been favourable to the Western position and to British



righ



interests,

efforts to.

On stra

the latest

to suggest

Strategic Arms

Space Talks,

claiming the

they interpreted actj

Initiative as a brea

Treaty.   Soviet agrees

was welcome.   The Rossi

about the United States

and Greenland. There

conventional arms control

trying to drive wedges within

Organisation (NATO) on Short



was essential nevertheless not to diminish

a comprehensive multilateral agreement,

control, Mr Shevardnadze had presented

!reposals in a clever but misleading way

Russians were prepared to delink the

ens Talks (START) and the Defence and

was different:   the Russians were

from a START agreement if

under the Strategic Defence

Anti- Ballistic Missile (ABM)

molish the Krasnoyarsk radar

sought pro forma assurances

radars at Fylingdales

progress on



ians were still

rth Atlantic Treaty

lear Forces (SNF),

dnadze had



1W



aircraft and manpower limits.   *^    

signalled that the Russians were lMk ptj for relatively

early signature of an agreement on orawentional arms

control.



THE MINISTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND

that the Minister of State, Mr Francis Maude,

Hong Kong from 17 to 19 September.   The timing  

had been favourable.   There had been a much

atmosphere than in July and press reaction had been

positive.   Mr Maude had benefitted from the growing

of shame in Hong Kong at the discourteous treatment gi*

to the Lord President during his visit.   It was clear

the problem of the Vietnamese boat people remained the

priority for the people of Hong Kong.   The first meeting o:

the Liaison Group with the People&apos;s Republic of China was



!confidential!




CONFIDENTIAL



currently talcing place in London but-was not expected to

result in significant progress.



2 September



THE ERIME MINISTER said that she had visited Japan frcm 19

?^/&lt;teo 22 September.   She had had discussions with the Japanese



y^pe Minister, Mr Kaifu, and other senior Japanese

^?r  ltical figures.    The new Prime Minister serened



, firmly in control and more outward-looking than

ecessors, though perhaps lacking seme of their



The former Prime Minister, Mr Takeshita, whan

also met, was clearly very influential behind the

In her discussions with Mr Kaifu she had taken up

the question of additional seats for British firms on the

Tokyo StockHSxchange.   She had reminded Mr Kaifu that he

was the fdiptl^Japanese Prime Minister with whan she had

found it T^afcgyg^yy to raise this issue.   In reply, Mr Kaifu



had given

to be made

It seemed unl

assurance if he

Exchange would a*

September for lea

listed the many barf

Japanese markets,

open to imports from

these countries would

from Japan.



that the additional seats were likely

in the next six months to one year.

Mr Kaifu would have given this

been confident that the Stock

her speech at a dinner on 19

industrialists she had

still existed to access to

clear that if Japan was not

other countries, then

idling to be open to products

Ihe Japanese rnnercialists had taken this



well. Ihey had listed the TtBaaw^p which had been taken to

increase foreign imports intcWJapdft.   These were very snail



in Japan&apos;s favour

government was

China.   The main

dinner had been

The Japanese had



compared with the enormous

with major European countries,

evidently anxious to resume

speaker at the preceding industrii

the Chinese Prime Minister, Li Peng.&quot;

sent a former Foreign Minister, Mr I to, to Peking where he

had met Chairman Deng Xiaoping. Chairman Dgwi had assured

Mr I to that he wanted a speedy resunption/cf ly?ade between

China and Japan but had tried to play dcwnuhC^caqic

events on Tienanmen Square.



Continuing, the PRIME MINISTER said the Ja

often tried to reduce the effect of concessions

foreign exporters by promoting local counterpart

with lower tax rates.   Ihe case of look-alike

a striking example.   The Japanese were worried that

governments in the European Community were beginning

claim that there was too much Japanese investment in

Britain.   She had told them firmly that they did not

to be deterred frcm investing in Britain. Representatives&apos;&apos;

of the Fujitsu company had argued that unless there was



confidential!


confidential



 



freedom over intellectual property there could not be

progress in international trade.   She had pointed out that

no company would be prepared to do research unless its

patents were properly protected.   She had discovered

subsequently that the Fujitsu ccnpany had exploited certain

important American scientific advances in the computer

industry despite the fact that they had been patented.

There had been a major court case which Fujitsu had lost,

a more positive note, Fujitsu representatives had said

t although Japan was producing many more engineers than

in, Britain already had carputers in every school and

further ahead in this area than Japan.



In KNprief discussion, it was noted that on a recent visit

to Japan the SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND had talked to

senior representatives of fifteen major companies.   All had



;ices



1 Japanese



Les



stressed

the adven

companies

Japanese

Britain were

many restricti

United States

language problems .?

their manufacturing

able to distribute

European Community, a

reduction of external

more cost-effective

goods direct to the

up manufacturing outlets,

balance of payments surpluses&apos;^!

Community countries than did J

practices, which a Social

a serious problem.



rtance of 1992.   Ihey believed that with

Single Market it was essential for Japanese

op manufacturing facilities in Europe,

found that labour Conditions in

than in West Germany,   !here were too

in West Germany, while in the

Hispanic workers created



had now realised that

set up in Britian would be

in the rest of the

At the same time the

after 1992 might mate it

companies to export their

ty rather than to set

had far larger

European



German restrictive

protect, presented



for



ster&apos;s

it to

Soviet

 



23 September



THE PRIME MINISTER said that on her re

had stepped first in Bratsk in Siberia,

first visit by a British Prime Minister to

group of senior Soviet officials who had wel

Bratsk had stressed their support for perestro



Continuing, the PRIME MINISTER said that the wide-:

discussions with President Gorbachev in Moscow had

successful.    Mr Gorbachev seemed to be much more

assured than when he had last visited London.   At the

Nationalities Plenum, just concluded, delegates had

approved a policy of giving greater freedom to the

constituent Republics while insisting they should remain



8



sel



!confidential!




CONFIDENTIAL



part of the Soviet Union and the Warsaw Pact.   At the most

recent Central Committee Plenum Mr Gorbachev had succeeded

in replacing sore of his opponents by appointees much

closer to his own viewpoint.   During the discussions Mr

Gorbachev had explained his new proposals cn strategic arms

control, claiming to have removed the linkage between START

and the AEM Treaty.   She had pointed out that Mr



rbachev ? s proposals did not amount to a delinkage, since

Soviet government would feel entitled to renege from



if they considered that the United States had

died the AEM Treaty.   Mr Gorbachev had also argued that

iling for stationed forces on the North Atlantic

tion (NATO) side must include not only

States forces, but also those of Britian, France,

Bel^im and Canada.   She had told him that this proposal

was not acceptable.   In their discussion cn Short Range

Nuclear Forces (SNF), Mr Gorbachev appeared to accept that



it would

the time

capability

She had

issued after

agreed to begiii

Armed Forces In

United Nations

Shevadnardze, had

elimination of nucl



possible to go down to zero at any rate for

She had made clear that maintaining an SNF

essential element in NATO&apos;s strategy,

that in accordance with the OcWunique

Summit in May, the Alliance had

tiers on SNF when a Conventional



was in place.    Yet at the

Foreign Minister, Mr Eduard

again about the total



ual



ings of



Inter-

icnal



tary



and

Id Bank



Continuing, the ERIME

the question of human ri&lt;

assured her that there were

any one who wanted to leave

the new Emigration law. Mr

Emigration Law was the second

of new legislation.   His top pri!

legislation on property and land



said she had also taken up

Mr Gorbachev.    He had

any problems, since

able to do so under

had said that the

priority on his list

passage of new

p.   Ihe purpose of

farmers as far 61s



this legislation would be to

possible that property leases could hot be taken away frcm

them by subsequent legislation.



IHE CHANCELIOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that duri

to Washington frcm 22 to 27 September, he had at

Annual Meetings of the International Monetary

and the World Bank.   He had had a meeting with the

Japanese Finance Minister, Mr Hashimoto.   Ihe latter&apos;

taken the same line cn additional seats cn the Tokyo

Exchange as Mr Kaifu had with the Prime Minister,

was a contrast between the relative freedom with which

capital goods were imported into Japan and the

restrictions on the import of consumer goods and



confidential!


CONFIDENTIAL



              ?



agricultural products.   ?Ihe Federal Republic of Germany&apos;s

(FRG&apos;s) balance of .payments surpluses with European

Community countries were a major problem, despite ERG

assurances that after 1992 these would simply be regional

differences.



Continuing, the CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that at

the Annual Meetings, there had been a general consensus

i^Smong the major industrialised nations that the world

^^es&amp;pncmy was in reasonably good shape, and that growth was

v^1&gt;1 &gt;1?y to continue with no significant risk of recession.



worldwide problem of increased inflation was

to an end, although the FRG Finance Minister had

that more needed to be dene in this area. The

diflSpalt question of Japan and Britain&apos;s relative quota

rankings had been successfully deferred.   The United States

Administration was divided about hew much importance should

be attachecMSX Congressional pressure against a General

Quota Inc^^sa) Nevertheless the issue of quota ranking

was bound wSy^SS^up substantively before the end of the

year.



OF THE EXCHEQUER said that there

of views in the Group of 7

anply  demonstrated by their



markets.   The general view

issue was less pressing

written off large

ime the United States

e anxiety about Latin

itical reasons, and had

accomodating stance



Continuing,

was a general

countries which

actions in the fore

cn debt this time

since the private

amounts of debt. At

Government expressed

American countries, mainly

put pressure cn the banks

on the provision of new loans



Continuing, the CHANCELLOR OF TtiENSQSQUER said that the

main talking point at the Annual n 4g ngs had been the

urgent need to help Poland and Hungary in their efforts to

establish genuinely democratic political systems and free

market economies.   There was general agreement that the

Western response should be a combination oi^ft&amp;w money and

practical help.   The intervention of the mrog^an

Carmission was creating difficulties with which

was moving ahead with its discussions as rap(

possible.      He had been impressed ty the new&quot;

Finance Minister, Dr Balcercwicz, and the

Professor Trzeciakcwski.   The new Polish

firmly committed to promoting a genuine market ecor

although they had no illusions about the scale of

problems confronting them.



In a brief discussion, the ERIME MINISTER said that

assistance for Poland and Hungary was of the very highest^

priority.   Their efforts to establish democracy and free

market economies itust not be allowed to fail. The



10



!confidential


[confidential



establishment of a Solidarity government had been an

historic mcment but the Poles still had great problems over

food supplies.   It was important to help them to increase

exports by reducing trade restrictions.   By contrast,

Hungary had no difficulties over agricultural production.



The Cabinet -



IHE MINISTER OF STATE FOREIGN AND OCMMDNWEALIH

said that the Commission were following up

satisfactorily the remit given to them to co-ordinate

assistance to Poland and Hungary.   A useful meeting of

representatesss of the 24 countries concerned had been held

on 26 SeptBtb&amp;fc.      The Commission&apos;s proposals for action

ty the Ocmrawp^Nitself were sensible, although the

extension offrch^Jbeneralised Scheme of Preferences to

Poland and Husgjt&amp;vand the involvement of the European

Investment Ban &lt;ara&amp;d seme difficulties for the United

Kingdom,   !here VMM^nevitably be implications for the

1990 Community BLKJge^/)



In a brief discussio^&lt;r

Germany to take crjedi

initiative should be rd

agricultural products

difficult to defend to p:

states, such as France,

in place.    United Kingdom

placed to help East European

severe environmental problems



noted that any attempt by

at had been a United Kingdom

Increased imports of



and Hungary would be

here if other member

,to keep national barriers

was particularly well-

to overcome their



    SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT sa

Ccmmission had now produced its definitiv

Social Charter. It shewed little change f

draft.   No real account had been taken of

of the Madrid Eurcpean Council.   Following di

official level, the Charter would come to the

Affairs Council on 30 October.



In a brief discussion it was noted that seme of the

detailed parts of the text risked having severe adve

effects and it was essential to put the United Kingdom&apos;

points strongly in the discussions.   An important element

in German support for the Charter was a wish to prevent

less prosperous member states from using their lower wage



??



confidential!


confidential



rates and less onerous social security arrangenents to

attract industry.     It would be important to bring home to

such member states that the Charter in its present form

would be against their interests.



?Ihe Cabinet -



Took note.



12



confidential



</content>
</cab>
