<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/57/0 images: 50-52</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
gflQB Docnment is the Property.of His Britannic Majestys Government]CONFIDENTIAL. tPOLITICAL INTELLIGENCE DEPARTMENT, 1 ** FOREIGN OFFICE.G,T-5018(A). 26th. July 1913.FURTHER  NOTES  ON  THE  UNITED  STATES  AND  THEECONOMIC DEFENSIVE.IN the memorandum recently circulated on the above subject the remark was made that &quot; there has been little consideration of economic action against Germany after the war, but there has been a good deal of consideration of a possible preferential system between the Allies.&quot; More recent information indicates that this remark should be modified. The last few weeks seem to have witnessed a considerable increase of interest in the use of the economic weapon as a means of pressure on the Central Empires.On the 18th May an article on &quot;America and the Economic Weapon &quot; appeared in the New York &quot;Nation.&quot; This weekly paper, though a strong supporter of President Wilson, has been chiefly remarkable for an academic liberalism, sometimes verging on pacifism, and its character therefore gives an added importance to the views it now expresses.The article begins by asking, &quot; Have the Allies attached sufficient importance to the economic weapon that they possess ?&quot; It goes on to point out that in any case during the reconstruction period &quot; self-preservation will require the Entente Allies to prevent laissez-faire in their commerce for some time.&quot; It then quotes Dr. Dernburg&apos;s article in the &quot; Neue Freie Presse&quot; about the international economic arrangements necessary to ensure the reconstruction of the Central Powers, and draws attention to &quot; the extreme concern displayed by Germany as to economic arrangements after the war, and the admission, even by her arch-militarists, that the economic situation controls the military situation.&quot; This anxiety, the writer continues, cannot be satisfied by any Mitteleuropa empire. The Allies, however, &quot;have not made use of their economic weapon to compel the acceptance of the principles and readjustments that they deem essential.&quot; The remainder of the article, which bears some marks of semi-official inspiration, must be quoted in full: &quot;To make use of the economic weapon does not mean that Germany will be permitted, as her Chancellor expressed it last July, &apos; by means of an understanding and give and take (&quot; Ausgleich &quot;-) to guarantee the existence of the German Empire upon the Continent and overseas.&apos; Bargaining economic concessions for territory would not spell the defeat of the German philosophy; the terms that the Allies can accept are well nigh absolute. Nor would it be advisable, were it indeed possible, to threaten economic reprisals of a definite character unless the Central Powers agreed to minimum terms by a certain date. This proposal can be approved only on the theory that acceptance would follow, for refusal would commit the Allies to a war after the war that would make impossible their fundamental war aim-the organisation of the world for peace and would justify Germany in her contention that the Allies aimed at her destruction as a commercial Power.&quot; No; the use of the economic weapon can be attempted only by definitely repudiating the Paris resolutions and making it clear to Germany what she can expect during her most difficult period of transition after the conclusion of peace ; to proclaim that if Germany agrees to a settlement that will mean &apos; restitution, reparation, and security for the future,&apos; if she will renounce her reliance on force and her eastern empire and enter a league to preserve peace, there will be no economic blockade enforced against. her; she will get her share of the shipping, foodstuffs,&apos; raw materials, and credit that will require strict apportionment.&quot; In time of war prepare for peace is an altogether valid maxim. The Allies would do well to lay now the foundation for the organ of control that must regulate the problem of supplies after the conclusion of peace; they would thus be safe-guarding their future and would be creating a much more adequate beginning for a real League of Nations than the Inter-Allied War Council, which, it has been said, furnishes the. germ for such a development. These economic arrangements must include concessions for Germany. Something will have to be done in this direction on humanitarian grounds and in order to prevent the abandonment of the inter-nationalism for which the Allies are fighting. More than this, neutral sympathy [367-25 a]
cannot be overlooked. It is with the Allies by reason of Germany&apos;s methods of making war ; it wilt remain so only if the settlement is a fair and just one that promises to be permanent.&quot; To &quot;announce a definite programme of fair treatment for Germany, then, is the proper use of the economic weapon; for no matter what success attends her armies, she cannot win so long as the Allies control the economic situation. To concede in advance the fair treatment that the Allies must grant to a Germany agreeing to a satisfactory peace is merely a development of the diplomacy that Mr. Wilson has been using in his appeal to the German people and Austria-Hungary to break loose from the -military party ; and it might not be without its effect on the reason, if any is left, of the military party itself.&quot;Following on this article, the reported appointment of an &quot; economic repre-sentative &quot; attached to the American Embassy at Kome excited some attention, and on the 6th June the New York &quot; Journal of Commerce &quot; reported it as possibly &quot; the first step in a general policy of more active participation by the United States in preparations of the nations at war with Germany for the after-the-war trade struggle.&quot; The writer of this article remarks that -&quot; Though the recommendations of the Paris Economic Conference never have been formally accepted by the United States, which in the past has viewed with disfavour attempts to interpose artificial obstructions to free commerce, even with former enemies, recent developments in Europe have led to conference here between representatives of the Entente Powers and officials of the State Department and the War Trade Board, which may result in a complete change of the attitude of our Government.&quot;He conjectures that close consultations are about to take place between the United States and the Entente Powers as to the measures to be taken against the &quot; Mitteleuropa menace.&quot;This was followed by two editorials in the same paper on the 7th June and 10 th June. The first of these editorials comments on the report printed in its columns on the previous day, and concludes with the following forecast of Allied policy: &quot; There will be a broad &apos; peace offensive &apos; when the time comes, but its aim will be defensive for the trade of the victorious Allied nations and all the neutrals that choose to join them on equal terms. It will be offensive against the trade of those of Central Europe only so far as that may be necessary to safety and the continuance of peace on just terms.&quot;The editorial of the 10th June returns to the charge in more emphatic language. It begins with the statement that: &quot; There seems to be a lack of co-ordination between the working of the Presidential and the sub-official mind in Washington.&quot; After quoting the Presidents earlier hints of a possible trade war against an unregenerate Germany, which, it says, have never been given their proper value by the officials, it continues : &quot; But now comes a series of dispatches from Washington bearing the marks of official inspiration, in which we are solemnly assured that recent developments in Europe have led to conferences between representatives of the Entente Powers and officials of the State Department and the War Trade Board which may result in a complete change of the attitude of our Government toward the economic boycott of an unregenerate Germany.&quot; It is something to have the officials of the State Department and the War Trade Board finally posted up to date in regard to a somewhat important field of their activity. But, as our readers do not need to be reminded, the necessity of employing economic pressure to bring the German people to reason has, in the councils of the Entente, long passed beyond the stage of controversy. This, be it noted, is without any reference to the Paris resolutions, from which our Government very properly withheld its approval. The statement has been frequently quoted in these columns that a determination to carry out the Paris programme in any event, whatever the enemy&apos;s attitude may be, would make the ability to penalise his commerce after the war a handicap instead of an asset. But a combination of the Allied nations carrying economic peace in one hand and economic war in the other is quite a different matter. To a sincerely pacific German nation, ready to abandon her militarism and to make her
contribution toward the reconciliation of nations, such a combination would properly offer economic peace, and offer it with both hands. Against a Germany which hesitates to make full restoration or to join a general pact of disarmament, and conciliation, it must be prepared to impose a boycott so stiff, so united, so effective, that these hesitations will disappear. The more united and decided the threat of economic war the less risk there is that it will have to be enforced.&quot;The editorial concludes with a declaration that the test of a regenerated Germany must be a complete change in her system of Government.We have here a rather remarkable concurrence between two periodicals widely different in character, outlook, and political affiliations.It is significant that the conservative &quot; Journal of Commerce,&quot; no less than its liberal contemporary, now emphasises the political aspects of the economic problem, and insists on the fixed idea that the Paris resolutions have a political bias which differentiates them from the scheme now advocated.Recent confidential information shows that these articles are not unrepresentative of official opinion in Washington. In fact, the realisation of the economic implications of Germany&apos;s Eastern treaties and of her new alliance with Austria-Hungary has produced a very marked effect on the mind of the Administration. The responsible officials are preparing memoranda on the whole subject for the Presidents personal perusal, and signs are not wanting that, in this as in other matters, the United States will in the end adopt an even more extreme line than our own. But it is important to note that this line will have a definite political direction. In the first place, American officials are proceeding on the assumption that, whatever may,have been the historical origins of the Paris resolutions, the British Government, at any rate, now attaches to them a political meaning different from the idea of revenge with which the American public has commonly identified them. In the second place, with the same logical disregard for difficulties which they have shown during the past year in urging the conversion of more or less informal inter-allied bodies into authoritative joint executives and in promoting the principle of the unified command, they seem ready to link the idea of co-operation in an economic defensive with the broader political idea of a League of Nations and to deepen co-operation into something verging on an internationalisation of resources. No doubt their desires will, in this as in previous spheres of joint action, outrun their own performance. Past experience has shown that their hesitation to partici-pate unreservedly in the international deliberations which they have themselves advocated arises partly out of uncertainty as to the general character of the allied policy of which such deliberations form only one branch. And so, in the third place, any policy which they propose will aim at comprehensiveness and will tend to be definitely linked with the whole problem of war aims and peace terms. For instance, a responsible American, in speaking recently to the writer about the economic defensive, instinctively brought up the question of the French1 colonial tariff system as an obstacle to a satisfactory agreement. The President is fearful of treading on false ground and will wish to survey the whole field. If participation in an allied policy is to be set before Germany&apos;s eyes as the best that peace can offer her, that policy will, in his1 view, need to be sound in all its parts. Piecemeal discussions will leave him hesitant. He will hardly look at the &quot; economic weapon &quot;from an economic standpoint. The haft of the weapon may be economic, but its point will be political.These indications may not be without their immediate importance, since they foreshadow that any eventual discussions with the United States will not merely be concerned with arrangements of temporary commercial convenience but may affect the course of the war and determine our political future.

</content>
</cab>
