<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/57/0 images: 146-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MEMORANDUM BY THE HOME SECRETARY AS TO EXCHANGEOF PRISONERS.When I left the Hague, an agreement had practically been arrived at, except en the following three pointsi-(l)The consideration to be given for the surplus German civilians in the British Empire was still under discussion.(2)We were insisting that repatriated prisoners, should not be employed (a) at the front, (b) on the lines of communication, (c) in occupied territory, or (d) in territory foreign to the country of origin.    As to (a), (b) and (c), there was no difference^     The object of asking (d) was that the Germans should bo prevented from using their repatriated soldiers in Russia, Persia, etc.;   and the Germans were objecting to this condition,(3)British prisoners employed in mines (especially salt mines) having suffered great hardship, we sought to restrict this employment.    The Germans objected, pleading the great need of labour in Germany.(4)The method of transport for German civilians overseas had been almout agreed, after much disoussion as in Annexe A.These questions are dealt with in the telegrams from the delegates, Nos. 2419, 2432 and 2444.I. Terms of Exchange. The numbers of the civilian prisoners in-each country aro approximately as follows:-Male interned German civilians,In the United Kingdom    ...     ...     20,000Overseas.........     ...     10,00030,000Of theBe it is estimated that two-thirds would be willing to be repatriated, say 20,000.Un the other hand, there are in Germany the following male interned British civiliansAt Ruhleben.........     ...     3,300Merchant seamen elsewhere.,     ...     1,200 - ,4,500 Excess 15,500The problem has been, how to deal with this excess, the Germans originally asking &quot;all for all&quot; and the British asking for   an equal number of combatants in Exchange for the excess of civilians.     Both demands were obviously untenable and various compromises had been considered.The Germans now propose to give one British civilian and one British combatant for every four German oivilians, the combatants being taken from the surplus of British -over German combatants interned in Holland and Switzerland. The combatants in Switzerland are about equal.     In Holland there is a surplus
s.mado up as followsSurplus of officers...     ,,,     ... 320Surplus of N.C.0&apos;s ,......2,200Surplus of men interned by Holland(mainly R.N.D. men from Antwerp]      1,3003,820.There aro also a few privates, who would be included.    The Germans proposed to make these up to 1,000 valid men;   and from the figure given in the telegram I assume that they will adhere to this offer.    Even so, the number of British oivllians in Germany and the number of surplus British oombatant prisoners in Holland will probably be less than the numbers required for the proposed exchange; but I presume that the deficiency would be made up from combatants now in Germany,If so, the1 effect of tho present proposal is that for 20,000 German civilians we shall get 5,000 British civilians and 5,000 British combatants - about one-half of the latter being very good material - officers or non-oommissioned officers. On the other hand, the German civilians now in England are (I am told) in good condition, and would form a valuable labour asset for Germany.    Upon the whole, having regard to the earnest desire of the British public for an exchange, I think it would be wise to strike a bargain on these terms.The Germans now insist that all British and German officers now in Holland and Switzerland shall be repatriated - presumably man for man and rank for rank so far as the numbers will go.    This proposal was put forward while I wan at the Hague;   but as the Army Council objeoted we resisted the proposal, and it was not then pressed.    It appears now to have been renewed;   and unless there i3 some strong military objection, I should be disposed to agree to it.    The Germans would only get about 500 officers and we should get a like number of ours.    It is difficult to find employment for our officers in Holland, and it seems to be impossible to let their wives go out to them;   and I formed the opinion that it would be a good thing for them to come home.     If repatriation is still objected, to, some arrangement should certainly be made for leave,II. Restriction on Employment.-From Telegram 2432 it appears that the Germans now claim to employ repatriated combatants as a military force in Russia and elsewhere.    Lord Newton does not attach much importance to this point, but it may be important from a military point of view.*       111* Mines. It appears that on this point an agreement oan be reached, A      IV.   Transport. It appears from telegram 2444 that the Germans now want to alter the terms arranged, with Capt. Kitson, much to our disadvantage.As the Conference may. be sitting on Monday, I have ventured to telegraph my views to the delegates (copy herewith), and now submit them for the consider-ation of the Cabinet,G, CAVE,6th July, 1918.
Hi1. The German Government will provide three suitable passenger ships from those -of their ships that are now sheltering in neutral harbours, viz. two from the Dutch East Indies and one from Teneriffe (as previously suggested). The German Government will be informed three months in advance of the departure of these vessels from the port of sailing.2, These ships to be manned entirely by Dutch crews and to sail under the Dutch flag.The British and German Governments will consult with the Hetherland Government and request the latter to accept the responsibility for these ships sailing under their   -lag, and give an assurance that any regulations for the conduct of these ships are strictly carried out.3. The vessels are as far as possible to keep outside the Barred Zones, A special arrangement will be made for the ship that collects passengers in the Mediterranean.The routes and courses to be steered will be arranged by the British and German Governments and whilst on their voyages these ships are net to be ordered to make any deviations from these routes which are at variance with this agreement.4, Persons taking passage in these steamers will be landed at Rotterdam,5. On each homeward voyage accommodation is to be reserved for fifty British non-combatant passengers.     On each outward voyage from Rotterdam these steamers may be used by as many British non-combatants as can be conveniently conveyed to Rotterdam but in no case shall this number exceed passengersBritish passengers by these vessels may make use of the special ships sailing between Rotterdam and England.6. Accommodation on homeward voyages is to be used to its fullest extent.7. The British Government will appoint one British officer as its represen-tative on each of these ships and also a British wireless operator.     The British officer shall be allowed by this agreement to send er receive messages (in cypher if necessary) by wireless telegraphy and shall have complete control of wireless installation.The ships shall be examined by British officials before the commencement of their first voyage.The ships at Teneriffe to be taken to Gibraltar for examination, coaling and fitting out.The ships in the Dutch East Indies to be sent to Singapore for a likepurpose.For the purposes of examination   whilst on a voyage these ships shall call at Gibraltar for the Mediterranean and at Cape Town for voyages from the East.     The stay for examination purposes shall not exceed one week.8. Expenses arising from these voyages to be borne by the German Government except those arising from the British passengers and British Commissioners and wireless telegraph operators^These latter expenses to be assessed in accordance with current tariffs for neutral shipping.
NETHERLANDS.(108736). MILITARY.Cypher telegram to Sir W. Townley (The Hague)Foreign Office, July 6th, 1918, 6,30 p.m. No. 1622.&apos;---oooOooo  Following for Delegates from Sir George Cave. Your telegrams Ncs.2419, 2432 and 2444.   1Cabinet will not meet until Monday, and as Conference may meet on that day I sond my views in advance.(l) If Germany will give one British combatant and one British civilian for every four German civilians, the first British combatants taken, being those of all ranks now interned in Holland and Switzerland I favour acceptance of that offer.    But I presume that if surplus British combatants in Holland and Switzer-land or British civilians in Germany should be exhausted and there should still be German civilians for exchange, Germany will make up deficiency by British com-batants from Germany,(2) I also favour exchange of officers now in Holland, such exchange not to be made until after repatriation of 15,000 privates on eaoh side and possibly of some civilians.     This would provide inducement to Germany to expedite change.(3) I think you should insist on clause prohibiting employment of repat-riated prisoners for any military purpose in country foreign to country of origin,The British Government will assist with the supply of coal and necessary fittings - at ports of call and fitting eut.9. On the conclusion of this scheme of repatriation these three ships shall be interned in a convenient harbour in the North of Spain subjeot to the consent of the Spanish Government.13. It is understood that from the date of embarkation on board these ships the German prisoners of war shall be regarded as having been turned over to&apos; the charge of the Netherland Government and that on information being received by the British and German Governments of such embarkation the German Government shall forthwith release for internment or repatriation from Germany a corresponding number of British prisoners of war in accordance with the agreement.11, The complement of passengers carried by each ship on eaoh   homeward voyage is to oontain not less than thirty per oent of women and children and a fair proportion of German officers.12, These vessols. shall carry no carge of any description on either their homeward or outward voyages - except baggage and personal effects of prisoners -which shall be placed on board under the supervision of British officers at the port of embarkation and turned over to the charge of the British representative on board,These vessels shall carry no mails or parcels nor any passengers other than those specified in this agreement.22nd June, 1918.
(4) Except as to purchase of ships changes proposed in arrangements for transport from overseas are open to strong objection and I think annexe as approved by Kitson should bo adhered to,(5)l suggest agreement should cease to run on 1st August, 1919, no provision being made for notice to determine or continue agreement after that date.    Will ask Cabinet on Monday to telegraph their views on the above.

</content>
</cab>
