<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/57/0 images: 166-166</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-i EFFORT OF THE SPECIAL wORK OF THE LOCATi GOVERNMENT BOARD &apos;      FOR THi&apos; WEEK ENDED 5th JULY,  1918.1.   Consideration has been given to the maohin. ry for voting by post by absent voterb under the Representation of the People Act, and in particular to the arrangement si for securing tho voter90 declaration of identity duly signed and authonticated when returning the ballot paper to the Returning Officer.2.   A Bill to extend the life of Parliament, including provisions for the further postponement of elect ions of members o,t&apos; Local Authorities, has been introduced in tih-a House of Commons.3.   Amendments to the Lend Drainage Bill md to the Midwlves Bill In which the Local Government Board are oon-cernod have been the subject of communication and negotiations with she Board of Agriculture, and with the Privy Council and representatives of the midwiveo, respectively.4,   The President has accompanied the Minister of National Service in a Conferonce with Members of Parliament and,Chairmen of Appeal Tribunals en the subject of the medical grading of recruit a of the new military agoa.5.   Deputations have been received from the Labour Housing Association and the London County Council on the subject of the Government Scheme of Housing after the War.cThe Board have received from the Royal Institutieu of British Architects the designs of houses for the working classic prewiated or recommended by them as the result of the competition whioh they instituted with the financial assistance of the- Government.     The question of the best method of securing publicity for the designs and any observations the R.I.B.A desire bo offer in regard to. them is under consideration.6.    Communications have been addressed to Boards of ,Guardians with reference to certain modifications in the allowances to British-born wives of interned and repatriated aliens and on the -subject of the effect on such allowances inoases where the husbands interned in Working Garaps are earning substantial wages,7.   An Order ha9 been issued extending the age-limits within which oases of tuberculosis are required to be notified by Medical Officers of Health to the Chief Commissioner of Medical Services at the Ministry of National Service, to correspond with the now military age-limits.

</content>
</cab>
