<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/6/9 images: 108-119</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property op his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.wu/t&quot;COPY No.war cabinetaction in norwegian territorial watersAttitude of His Majesty&apos; governments in Canada,Australia andNew Zealand.&quot;With reference to&apos;w.p. (1+0) 77, I now circulate to my colleagues telegrams which have&quot;been received from the United Kingdom high commissioners in Canada, the Commonwealth ofAustralia and New Zealand on the subject ofaction in Norwegian territorial waters.A.E.MINIONS OFFICE.28th February, 191+0.

CANADAFrom the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Canada,Dated 27th February, 1940.   Received 1,44 a..m., S3th Feb.MOST IMLSBDIAKLNoa405u     Secret,Tour telegram Ho.350.     I got in touch withSkelton this morning and urged him to consult the PrimeMinister by telephone at once and ask for his personal views.     Skelton at length reluctantly agreed to do thishut reminded me that the Prime Minister always foundrequests of this nature for his personal views mostdistasteful.Skelton has just told me that lie duly telephonedthe Prime Minister-     Latter- asked that I should &quot;beInformed that previous messages on this subject from theUnited Kingdom Government had given no indication that his views would be requested., &apos;   It would of course benecessary for him to consult Ms colleagues beforeexpressing any view at all, particularly if there were anylikelihood of a subsequent statement of policy being issued and especially if this were so drawn up as toindicate that Dominion Governments had been consulted.     he regretted that for obvious reasons it would be impossiblefor him to seek hie colleagues advice in the very short time available.I fear 1 can do no more-     Ends.

CYPHER TSLEGHAMQm&amp;Qwm&amp;um of australia the Prise Hiai*te* of the CQianonwealth of Australia.Dated 28th Petunia vy, 191*0*   Received 6*1$       , 27th February^Wo. 63 MOST SECRET.-Reference your telegrams regarding Finland,     Wholescatter fully discussed with ray colleagues.     I think that therehas &quot;been a tendency to lose sight of the major proposal regardingassistance to Finland,,In particular I refer to the decisions of the supreme war Co\tneil at Paris with the main lines of which I agree though in the absence of further information should be strongly opposed the Petsamo proposition.     The more recent and minor proposalregarding Norwegian territorial waters might, if unrelated to finland,, prejudice the unstable position with neutral countries and though it would no doubt give us immediate benefit in relationto Germany,, it would note save in the most indirect sense, tend toprevent Finland from being overrun,.     We feel that a conquest off inland by Russia would be a major disaster and that any proposalswhich bear directly upon helping Finland are to be preferred bothin time and order of importance to the proposals which relate toour special Norwegian territorial waters problem.     It wouldappear that if the Paris proposals were carried out and the scandinavian countries refused cooperation, world opinion wouldthoroughly support us in any attempt we might make to prevent:.?norwegian territorial waters from being used against us*     If on other hand Scandinavian countries cooperated,, assistance to inland could be given much more effectively than by a speculativejjKcu^sion to &quot;P&amp;tmaxo and if the ewasequdnce was that Germanyflociared war on Norway and Sweden automatic result would be that supplies of iron ore to Germany from Sweden would be cut off, she&quot;&apos;o.uld be denied the use of Scandinavian waters, and therefore theQtt result at least for a substantial time ahead would be to herisa&amp;vantage.   We urge therefore that the undoubted attractions ofkQ proposed action In the territorial waters should not be lowed to obscure the originally contemplated major plan providedoat there is not too much delay,   38ndsa

CYPHER TELEGRAM.Prom United Kingdom High Commissioner in Hew Zealand.Dated 18th February, 19/j.Q.IMMEDIATE.No. 89.Previous communications respecting belligerent use of norwegian territorial waters.    They realize the importance and.complexity - of the proposals under contemplation;, and they havegiven this matter what consideration has been possible in the limited time available to them.    While they would be most reluctant to add yet another to the already long and growing listof infractions of the treaty or the legal obligations they fullyshare the view of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United kingdom that one belligerent cannot be expected to observe all laws of warfare at sea while their unscrupulous opponent is left free to commit with impunity and almost without protest?  the mostflagrant breaches.    From the legal and the moral point of view,therefore,  they would have no doubt that the allies are fullyentitled, vis-a-vis Germany, to take what steps lie in their power to put an end to this state of affairs.2.    They are not, however, without doubt as to the justification,vis-a-vis Norway, of steps proposed, and they fear that precedentestablished might be used by Germany and Russia at a later date for a much more serious infraction of neutral rights, for exampleagainst Belgium and Holland.    They cannot ignore the possibilityalso that an incident in the course of the proposed operations(such as a clash with Norwegian naval forces,  the loss of norwegian life or the destruction of a Norwegian ship by emallied mine)  might possibly have  the extreme effect of throwingNorway

Norway and perhaps Sweden also,,  into the arms of Germany and russia.3.    They have some apprehension also as to possible effecton neutral opinion generally.    They attach, as His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom are aware, the utmost importance to friendly sympathy of the United States of America,and they would urge  that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom,  in their consideration of this matter, regard thepossible reactions of the neutrals, and particularly of theUnited States of America, as of paramount and decisive importance.d.    On the whole, however, and subject to the views expressedabove 5  they are inclined to look upon the matter finally from,the point of view of profit and loss.    They realize that HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom are in a much better position than they are to estimate possible results ana to balance possible losses against possible gains, and they aretherefore disposed, with the information at present available tothem, generally to support the policy that it is proposed toadopt if, on consideration of all the factors, His Majesty&apos;aGovernment in the United Kingdom are satisfied that the allieshave, all things considered, more to gain than to lose by adoptingit.    Ends.




</content>
</cab>
