<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/16/35 images: 444-463</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^ .209(JHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).W.P.   (4-3.) 113. a26th May.  1941. COPY NO.    .APPLICATION OP CONSCRIPTION to northern IRELAND.Note &quot;by the Home Secretary and Minister ofHome Security.The Prime Minister on Saturday appointed aCommittee under my Chairmanship, and consisting of:-The Lord President of the Council,The Minister of Labour and National Service,The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,The Attorney-General,to examine the draft of a Bill to extend the NationalService Acts to Northern Ireland, with certain modificationsswithout prejudice to the decision of the War Cabinet onthe major issue of policy involved in such a proposal..I submit the draft of a Bill, which incorporatesthe decisions arrived at at our discussion this morning.(Intld. ) H. M.Home Office, S.W.I.

DRAFTOF ABILLTOProvide for the enlistment of persons who fail.to register under the National Service Acts 1939 to1941;    and to extend those Acts to NorthernI r elan d0Be it enacted etc,PART LEnlistment of persons who fail to register.er to l0-&apos;l)    If it appears to the Minister that any personistsons who    for the time being liable to be called up for service has1 tolister,        failed to comply with any of the requirements of regulations made under subsection ( l)  of section two of the principalAct (which relates tc registration)  then (without prejudice to any proceedings which may be brought against that person for the offence against the principal Act,  andwhether or not such proceedings are brought)  the minister may serve an enlistment notice on that person under section four of the principal Act notwithstanding that he has notbeen medically examined under section three thereof,(2)      If any person upon whom an enlistment noticehas been served under the powers conferred by the last foregoing subsection claims that he is not a person forthe time being liable to be called up for service,  or thathe has not failed to comply with any requirement of thesaid regulations,  or that there is reasonable excuse forhis failure to comply therewith, he may at any time beforethe date on which he is required by the enlistment notice.to present himself in accordance with the requirements of

the notice, make application,  in accordance with rules madeby the Lord Chancellor for the purposes of this section, tohave his claim determined by a court of summary jurisdiction,and when such an application has been duly made the requirementsof the notice shall not have effect until the claim has been so determined.(3)      Upon any application made to a court of summary jurisdiction under this section -(a) if the court determines that the applicant was not atthe time when the enlistment notice was served upon him a person liable under the principal Act to becalled up for service,  or that he has not failed to complywith any requirement of the said regulations, the court shall order that the enlistment notice be cancelled;(b) if the court determines that the applicant was a personso liable as aforesaid and that he has failed to complywith a requirement of the said regulations but that therewas reasonable excuse for his failure to comply therewith,the court may order that the operation of the enlistmentnotice shall be suspended until such time as may be specified in the order and that the notice shall then cease to have effect if the applicant has in the meanwhilecomplied with the requirements of the said regulations.(4)      Where upon any such application the court of summary jurisdiction does not order the enlistment notice served uponthe applicant to be cancelled,  the court shall give such directions, varying the notice by altering the place and time atwhich the applicant is thereby required to present himself, asthe court considers expedient for giving effect to the orderQ(5)      The cancellation,  suspension,  or variation by orderof a court of summary jurisdiction of any enlistment notice servedunder the powers conferred by subsection ( l)   of this section shallbe without prejudice to the validity of anything done while thenotice was in operation,  and where by virtue of an order of sucha court any such enlistment notice ceases to have effect,  the-2-

provisions of the National Service Acts and this Act shallapply to the person upon whom the notice was served as if no enlistment notice had been served upon him.

PART    II. -&apos; Extension of National Service Acts to Northern Ireland.Extension 2.      The National Service Acts, 1939 to 1941 shall of Acts to northern extend to Northern Ireland and accordingly the NationalIreland.Service (Armed. Forces) Acts 1939 and 1940 and theNational Service Act 1941 shall have effect as if for references therein to Great Britain there were substituted references to the United Kingdom.Interpretation 3.-(l)    In this Act the expression &quot;principaland miscellaneousirovieicms Arft&quot; means the National Service (Armed Forces Act 1959as the araei;o&apos;:\rr^.:;-? o::-&amp;yjx&amp;j&amp;z* any reference to the principal Act shall beconstrued as a reference to that Act as amended by any subsequent enactment or by any regulations for thetime being in farce under the Emergency Powers (Defence)Acts 1939 and 1940.(2)   The amendments specified in the Schedule tothis Act (which relate to matters of minor detail)shall be made in the principal Act and the NationalService Act 19410(3)   In the application of the National service acts 1939 to 1941 to Northern Ireland references tothe Summary Jurisdiction Acts shall be construed as references to the Petty Sessions (Ireland) Act, 1851yand any Act amending that Act whether passed before or after the commencement of this Act, and theexpression &quot;summary conviction&quot; means convictionsubject to and in accordance with the said Act of1851 and any such Act amending that Act.(4) Paragraph (d) of subsection (2) and sub-section (4) of section one of the Emergency Powers(Defence) Act 1939 as amended by sLibsection (2) ofsection one of the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act 1940- 4 -

shall have effect as if this Act had been passed before thecommencement of the last mentioned Act.PART IIISupplementary.4.      Any expenses incurred by the Minister or by any department of the Government of the United Kingdom inconsequence of the passing of this Act shall be defrayed outof moneys provided by Parliament.5.      This Act may be cited as the National Service (No. 2)Act 1941 and shall be construed as one with the principal Actand the other enactments construed therewith, and shall beincluded among the Acts which may be cited together as theNational Service Acts,  1939 to 1941.

SCHEDULENational Service (Armed Forces) Act, 1959*- In subsection (11) for the word &quot;two&quot; there shall be substituted the word &quot;three&quot; and after the word &quot;Scotland&quot; there shallbe inserted the words &quot;and one for Northern Ireland&quot;-At the end of subsection (l) there shall be inserted thewords &quot;or,  in the case of persons so employed in NorthernIreland, by the Ministry of Finance and Commerce&quot;There shall be inserted the following section -&quot;Application 22A.    In the application of this Act toto NorthernIreland. Northern Ireland -(a) subsection (3) of secticn six shallhave effect as if for the referenceto the Unemployment Insurance Act1935 there were inserted a referencetoJ(b) subsection (l) of section eleven shallhave effect as if for paragraphs  (f)and (g) thereof the following paragraphswere substituted -&apos;(f)(g)!  .)(c) Part II of the Schedule shall haveeffeet as if for the reference to sectionforty-one of the Unemployment InsuranceAct 1935 there were substituted a reference to section of theAct 19    .At the end of Part I there shall be inserted the words &quot;and,  inthe case of the division for Northern Ireland, by the LcrdChief Justice of Northern Ireland&quot;

NATIONAL SERVICE ACT 1941.In subsection (2) after the word &quot;Parliament&quot; thereshall be inserted the words &quot;or the Parliament ofNorthern Ireland&quot;There shall be inserted the following section -&quot;15A.    In the application of this Act to NorthernIreland -(a)  section three shall have effect as if inparagraph (e)  of subsection (l) for the reference to the police war reserve therewere substituted a reference to; as if in subsection (5) there were substituted for the references to sectionseven of the Societies (Miscellaneous Prov-isions)    Apt 1940 and section three of theCourts (Emergency Powers) Amendment Act 1940respectively references to; as if in subsection (5) for the reference to a chief officer of police there were substituted a reference to a county inspector of the royal ulster Constabulary and for the reference tothe police war reserve there were substituted reference toand as if in subsection (6) the definition of &apos; chief officer of police&apos;  were omitted andfor the definitions of &apos;local authority&apos;  and&apos;the Minister&apos;  there were substituted thefollowing definitions:-&apos;local authority&apos;  means&apos;the Minister&apos;  means

(b) section twelve shall have effect as if, inthe definition of 1 civil defence force&apos;the words &apos;the police war reserve and&apos; wereomitted therefrom, and as if for references to the Minister of Home Security there were substituted references to a Secretary ofState.&quot;0




</content>
</cab>
