<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/5/26 images: 250-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)26th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It Is requested that special care may be taken toensare the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 26 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, January 29, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., ]M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The    Right    Hon.    Winston    S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P.,  Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir Reginald Dorman-Smith, M.P., Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries (Item 1).Mr. A. T. Lennox-Boyd, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary to the Ministry ofFood (Item 1).General  Sir W.  Edmund  Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 2-9).Sir Frederick Leith-Ross, Director-General,    Ministry    of    economic warfare (Item 1).Sir Arnold Overton, Second Secre-tary, Board of Trade (Item 1).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Mr. L. F. Burgis.The Right Hon. Sir Wilfrid Greene,Master of the Rolls (Item 1).Sir Horace  J.  Wilson,  permanent secretary to the Treasury.Admiral  of  the  Fleet  Sir  dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 2-9).Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, deputy chief of the Air Staff (Items 2-9).
WAR CABINET 26 (40).Contents.minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      Italy     ..........................     193Economic relations.2      The Air Situation     ..................     1993      The Naval Situation..................     1994      The Military Situation        ............       ...     199Western front.Finland.5      Weekly Resumes        ...      ...      ...       .......       ...     1996      Scandinavia     ...      ...       ...      ...       ...       ...       ...     2007      Finland.......      ...      ...      ............    200Allied assistance.8      The Far East......      ...............     201Relations with Japan.The case of the Asama Maru.9      Propaganda in Germany      ...       ...       ...       ...       ...     202
1.   The War Cabinet had before them the following papers : (i) Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs and the Minister for Economic Warfare (W.P.(G.) (40) 21);(ii) Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade(W.P. (G.) (40) 26); and(iii) Memorandum by the secretary of State for DominionAffairs (W.P. (G.) (40) 27);on the subject of our Economic relations with Italy.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, as explained in the covering note, the suggestions put forward in theMemorandum initialled by himself and the Minister for economic warfare, represented the best compromise to which departments could be persuaded to agree. Neither he nor the Minister for economic Warfare felt able to recommend these suggestions to theWar Cabinet in their present form. To save time, however, the document had been allowed to go forward.The War Cabinet would remember that the Master of the Rollshad agreed to become the Chairman of the British Delegation onthe Anglo-Italian Joint Standing Committee to handle commercial relations. He had been to Rome in order to handle the negotiations with had covered a variety of points. First, the implications of stopping the export of German sea-borne coal to Italy; secondly,the War Trade Agreement with Italy; thirdly, the purchase ofwar material; and fourthly, the chartering of Italian shipping.The Master of the Rolls had returned from Italy the previous weekand thought that there was little chance of securing the manifoldobjects we desired unless we were prepared to throw into the scalethe sum of  5 million for the purchase of Italian horticulturalproduce. There were numerous objections to this expenditure, suchas the difficult)&apos; in absorbing the goods bought, and the objections raised by the President of the Board of Trade and the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs. He was also anxious as to the effectsuch purchases would have in the United States of America.Broadly speaking there were two courses open : (a) To continue to endeavour to adjust the Departmentaldifferences with a view to agreeing to purchase Italianproduce to a much smaller extent; such a course, hethought, was foredoomed to failure.(5) To see the whole affair in what he regarded as the trueperspective, and to say that we must reach agreement in this matter with Italy.In the last resort we could, he imagined, always say that we would pay for the goods but not take delivery.He himself pleaded strongly for the second course. We couldnot exercise a free choice in this matter. The position was urgent,since the German Delegation was already in Rome and mightanticipate us by purchasing some of the most valuable commodities.The matter was also urgent since the question of stopping theexport of German seaborne coal to Italy was still in abeyance anda decision.on this question would have to be reached very soon.Continuing, the Foreign Secretary said that only one other course had suggested itself to him. That was to omit German coalaltogether from our scheme for seizing German exports. It was true that this would make a big hole in our policy of stoppingGerman exports, but it would enable us to avoid purchasing Italianhorticultural produce which we did not want.The Master of the Rolls said that, apart from the questionof contraband control, the negotiations with Italy had threeobjectives : (i) the stoppage of German coal exports to Italy withoutfriction;Italy.economic relations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 21stConclusions,Minute 11.)
(ii) the obtaining of certain essential war supplies;(iii) the chartering of Italian ships to carry goods to the UnitedKingdom, particularly ore.In order to obtain these objectives it was proposed that we shouldsupply Italy with coal sufficient to make up the German deficiency;that we should make sufficient purchases of essential supplies toenable Italy to pay for the coal, and that we should spend some 5 million gross in freights.In the negotiations the following difficulties had been encountered. First, it was alleged that we could not supply coal to make up the deficiency; secondly, that Italy wished us topurchase  5 million worth of horticultural produce in order toenable her to find a market for what had previously paid for theGerman sea-borne coal; thirdly, Italy had so far refused to sell usany guns (we proposed buying  6 million worth) and had alsorefused, for political reasons, to permit us to charter ships to carryore. If the matter were left where it was, the position was thatour purchases in Italy would be  5 million short of what was required to pay for the coal which Italy would import from us.Further, we should not get the guns or the ships from Italy. TheDuce&apos;s attitude in regard to shipping had been that he would not as yet have Italian ships carrying to this country what Germanyregarded as contraband, i.e., ore from North African Ports,although he did not object to Italian ships coming to this countryin ballast.The Master of the Rolls thought there were three courses opento us : (1) To bring pressure to bear on the Italians by stopping theGerman coal Italy might then be forced to sell usenough of what was wanted in the way of essential supplies.(2) To attempt to carry out the scheme set out in theMemorandum initialled by the Foreign Secretary andthe Minister for Economic Warfare. Under this schemewe should only buy about  2 to  3 million of horticulture-cultural produce, and the scheme would be unattractiveto Italy. It was not necessary to emphasise the socialimportance of horticulture in a country like Italy,where three quarters of the population depended on the soil.(3) To buy  5 million worth of horticultural produce, if theItalians would supply us with guns and would agree tothe shipping proposals. He thought this latter scheme might be sufficiently attractive to the Italians to obtain their assent.As regards shipping, under this scheme as a whole we shouldspend  5 million gross on freights. From this sum there would fall to be deducted various disbursements, eg., for loading and unloading ships, harbour dues, insurance, &amp;c, and also payments for certain ships which would have to be put at Italy&apos;s disposal,as her own tonnage would not suffice if her ships brought cargoesto this country instead of coming here in ballast. The nett receiptsto Italy in respect of freight were not likely to exceed  2-^ million.Assuming that we spent  20 million in Italy, Italy wouldrequire to allocate this sum as follows : Coal..............Arrears on coal accountPurchases in the United KingdomArrears on this accountPayment on financial account  million.12-0-52-5-5-6Total, say ...16-1
This left a balance of  4 million for purchases of rawmaterials, including raw materials for our orders, amounting toabout  2 million. Out of this balance, the Italians had to buy thefollowing commodities from the British Empire :   -Jute   .........      2,000,000Wool......       ...      2,500.000Rubber ......      3,000,000Total     ...       ...      7,500,000 plus something additionalfor tin and oil seeds.Thus, on the figure of  20 million for British purchases in italy and  5 million for freights, the position was alreadyextremely tight. On any lesser figure than  20 million the pro-position became an unattractive one from the Italian point of view.Referring to the proposed purchases of rice and olive oil, thePrim,e Minister asked whether, if the Germans got wind of theproposed deal, they would be prepared to pay the Italians more than ourselves for these two commodities : in that case, there might beno question of our having to purchase them at all.Sir Frederick Leith-Ross said that Germany might do this, but she might deliberately refrain from purchasing in order to putpolitical pressure on Italy. If the Germans offered higher prices for foodstuffs, they would have the more to pay in goods, unless they came to some arrangement for paying for them as part of theagreement for the transfer of the population of the Alto Adige.That agreement was not yet concluded, but it seemed that germany would be entitled to a large credit under it It could not, however, betaken as certain that, because Germany offered higher price thanus, Italy would sell her all her oil and rice. Italy had sold us somehemp, although the price offered by Germany had been higher.Sir Arnold Overton said that the President of the Board ofTrade was concerned at the prospect of favouring any country by taking from it large supplies which would normally come from someother country. In the recent series of telegrams from the UnitedStates of America one of the major points had been the troublecaused by our prohibition of American agricultural produce,particularly tobacco and apples.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries said that, so far ashome-grown vegetables were concerned, there was a prospect of adecrease in demand accompanied by an increase in home-grownsupplies. Unless, therefore, further assistance for the home producer was forthcoming from the Exchequer, the present proposals would create a very awkward situation.Sir Frederick Leith-Ross said that an embarrassing situation would be created if we were to agree to any general exemption ofGerman coal exports by sea to Italy and other countries. At thepresent time, German coal exports to Italy were being allowed, butnormally Germany exported coal to South America. Greece andother countries, and such exports were being stopped. The grantof an exemption in the favour of German coal would be likely to provoke protests from the United States against our stoppingGerman potash, and from the Netherland Government against ourpreventing the export of German goods consigned by that Govern-ment from Rotterdam to their Colonial Administrations.The Parliamentary Secretary of the Ministry of Food said theMinistry of Food could without great difficulty absorb Italian food-stuffs to the value Of  2-^ million. If it was necessary to accept such foodstuffs, the Ministry would prefer rice and olive oil, whichwere more readily stored. In so far as these purchases were pre-emptive, the French would accept purchases up to 40 per cent.
The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that theimport of Italian rice would raise great difficulties. He recalled that when, about a year previously a proposal had been made toreduce the preference on Empire rice, the proposal had met with considerable Australian opposition. Australian, opposition to thepresent proposal in regard to rice would be greatly increased,following on the recent decision to purchase from Turkey driedfruits at the rate of 40,000 tons a year in order to prevent Turkishchrome going to Germany. Normally Australia would have expected this year to export 57,000 tons of dried fruit to thiscountry, and it had been necessary to tell her that this figure would need to be cut by half, thus causing a loss to her export tradevalued at  1^ million. Similar considerations arose in the caseof South Africa, though there the loss to the export trade wassmaller, amounting to  200,000. He had hoped that it would bepossible to reach an arrangement with Australia in the case of driedfruits without cost to the Exchequer, but this would hardly bepossible if the action proposed with regard to Italian rice wastaken. It would be of great assistance to the Dominions Office ifthey could be brought into earlier and closer consultation by otherDepartments when agreements of this kind were being discussed.The Clumcellor of the Exchequer said that the War cabinet were confronted with the choice of two courses of action eachsupported by arguments of great force. It was worth recalling thatwe had made a great effort to secure Italian goodwill by purchases in that country amounting to  20 million; and that we had accordingly sent representatives of the Air Ministry, War Officeand other Departments to Italy to ascertain how this sum couldbe expended for the purchase of commodities which we required.It now appeared, however, that the Italians were either unwillingor unable to supply us with such goods to the amount required,and we were accordingly now being asked to make large purchases of commodities which we did not want. The war threw a greatstrain upon us, and expenditure on non-essentials should be avoidedas far as possible. Moreover, a transaction of this kind created amost undesirable precedent for negotiations with other neutrals.Already, indeed, the tenderness which we had shown for Italiansusceptibilities had led to protests from the United States. Hewas sceptical regarding the Italian claim that they could not find the sterling to pay for coal imported from this country unless we made these purchases. We were in a position to stop the arrival in Italy of German coal, and, since Italy must have coal, it wasa large assumption that she could not pay for it unless we wereto take large quantities of her horticultural produce. His ownfeeling was that this was a case where we should try to obtain a compromise, balancing for this purpose our desire to give italy the least possible ground for complaint, against the greatembarrassment caused to us by these unwanted purchases. He didnot believe that our action in regard to this agreement would seriously affect the attitude of Italy towards the war.The Secretary of State for War said that as regards the gunsproposed to be purchased from Italy (47 mm. anti-tank and 20 mm.anti-aircraft guns), our need was very great; indeed, in a laterphase of the war, the possession of these guns might be of supreme importance.The Prime Minister said that this was a difficult question todecide, since in additon to the measurable factors, there wereimponderable elements, the importance of which was necessarily amatter of opinion. The proposal that we should spend up to 5 million on the purchase of commodities which we did not wantbristled with objections, and had already led to strong protests fromthe Departments concerned, including the Treasury.  At the present
time we were encountering difficulties for varying reasons with japan, the United States, Roumania and other neutrals. It was unfortunate that a belligerent, trying to conduct the war inaccordance with humanitarian principles, should be confronted withendless criticism by neutrals. It was impossible to foretell whetherthe effect in Italy resulting from an agreement satisfactory to theItalian standpoint would repay us for all the difficulties which theagreement now proposed would entail. It might well be that inthe last resort Italy might be able to find the sterling necessary topay for coal from this country; but this was not a question whichcould be disposed of so easily. &quot;We must consider whether, if italy were forced to find the sterling required, she would remain friendly to us. The Master of the Rolls had made it clear that, in his view,the attitude of Italy towards us at the present time was bound upin the success of these negotiations. The Foreign Secretary was,no doubt, much preoccupied by the United States reaction to our policy, and it was striking that, notwithstanding that preoccupa-tion, he was anxious to secure approval for the proposed deal with italy. In these circumstances, he (the Prime Minister) found itdifficult to take an opposite view, and was disposed to think thatat this stage of the war, the goodwill of Italy was so important tous that we should do whatever might be necessary to secure it. once we had secured the agreement proposed, we should, of course,discuss with those concerned how best to deal with the difficulties caused by the unwanted purchases from Italy.The Master of the Rolls said that the proposed agreement,which also covered contraband control, was an integral agreement,and if we failed to secure it, we should be faced with our olddifficulties with the Italian Government on the score of contraband control, with the added complication that we should have refusedan Italian State guarantee.In reply to a question by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, Sir A mold Overton said that our difficulties as regards theUnited States would be greatly eased if we could eliminate thepurchase of apples from the proposed agreement; and the Ministerof Agriculture and Fisheries said that the same was true as regardsthe difficulties of his own Department.The Master of the Rolls agreed that it would be possible to eliminate apples, the cost of which was only  200,000. If he (the master of the Rolls) was now given authority to negotiate anagreement up to a maximum expenditure of  5 million on food-stuffs, &amp;o, he would strongly resist any attempt on the part of theItalians to increase this figure still further. If they were to take such a line, he would advocate our stopping a few ships carryingGerman coal to Italy.The Secretary of State for War said that there were indications that, through fear of Germany, the Italians might try to make ita condition that any guns purchased from Italy should not be usedon the Western Front. Any such attempt should be strongly resisted, since it would deprive the agreement of most of its value.The Secretary of State for Air said that the same suggestion had been raised in the case of Italian aircraft.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was disposed to advise that the Master of the Rolls should be authorised tosecure an agreement, provided that the Italians were prepared tosupply the guns we required and to make available Italian shipping for carrying ore from Morocco to this country. To get such anagreement it would be worth while agreeing to spend up to 5 million as a maximum on the purchase of agricultural produce, &amp;c. (excluding apples), though no doubt the Master ofthe Rolls would do everything possible to settle for a smaller figure.
From the Treasury point of view it was essential that the sterlingdue to Italy for the use of shipping should be available for useonly in the sterling area, and should not be capable of being converted into dollars.The Lord Privy Seal said that, having regard to the difficultieswhich we had experienced in the last war when Italy was our ally,he doubted very much whether they would agree that their shipping should bring ore to this country.The Minister without Portfolio was afraid that we might beheading for a breakdown, if we were to resist an Italian request-that the guns to be supplied should not be used on the western front. Would it not be possible as a last resort to meet the Italianson this point and to agree that the guns should be made availablefor use in Turnkey, Finland and Roumania ?The Secretary of State for War said that he would be strongly opposed to a concession of this sort, since guns were urgently required for our own army.The Master of the Rolls said that on the question of shippingit should be recalled that it was known that the present Italianrefusal was due to a direct veto by Signor Mussolini. he anticipated great difficulty in overcoming these objections.The Prime Minister said that the Italian objections to the useof Italian shipping for the carrying of ore to this country werepurely political, and that, if the general situation were to developfavourably, it might well be that those objections would lose their force. It would be a step in the right direction if the Italians wereto send their ships in ballast to this country to take coal back toItaly.The War Cabinet-Authorised the Master of the Rolls, on his return to Rome,to negotiate with the Italian Government for a generalagreement of outstanding questions on the linessummarised in paragraph 17 of the Joint Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Ministerfor Economic Warfare (W.P. (G.) (40) 21), subject to thefollowing points made in discussion in the War Cabinet,viz. : (a) That the Agreement should provide (i) for the supply by the Italian Government of the guns which we required, without conditions asto the manner of their use.(ii) for the fulfilment of the provisional shipping&apos;arrangements, but without insistence at thisstage on the carriage of iron-ore or sulphur in italian ships to this country.(&amp;) That, as regards the purchase of Italian agricultural and horticultural products, the Master of the Rollsshould endeavour to secure agreement on the basisof our importing additional quantities to the valueof  3^ million, but that he should have authorityto agree upon a higher figure up to a maximum of 5 million if in his judgment this further increasewere necessary to secure the Agreement as a whole.(c) That no additional imports of apples from Italy shouldbe agreed to.
The Air 2.   The Secretary of State for Air said that heavy falls of snow-Situation, and bad visibility had restricted air operations on the previous day.(Previous Most   aerodromes   on   the   East   and   South-East   coasts   were reference: unserviceable on account of snow drifts. Fighters had taken off toW.M. (40) 25th endeavour to intercept two unidentified aircraft off the East coast,Conclusions,      but no contact had been made.Minute l.) From reports which had just been received, it appeared that german bombers were operating at a number of points off the east coast, presumably with the intention of attacking shipping. one enemy bomber had been intercepted by our fighters, but a report ofthe action bad not yet been received.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 25thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the following-ships had been sunk, probably by torpedo : Norwegian steamship Faro (844 tons).Norwegian steamship Hosanger (1,591 tons).Danish steamship England (2,319 tons).had been without warning and in weather whichThesesinkingsgave little chance of survival for any of the crews.A German parachute mine had been salved at Whitstable.Bodies from H.M.S. Exmouth had been washed ashore at Wick.A Report had been received from Red Cross sources that thewhole of the crews of H.M. submarines Starfish and Undine hadbeen saved.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement,The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 25thConclusions,Minute 8.)Western Front.Finland.4. The Secretary of State for War reported that one Germandivision had been moved from the Aachen area to Czecho-Slovakia,and that two new divisions had been identified in Poland. Therehad also been some interchange of German divisions between the saar and the northern part of the Western Front, which had resulted in a net increase of one division opposite the Low Countries.The total number of identified German divisions was now 138, ofwhich 99 were in the west and 39 in the east.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff thought that nosignificance need be attached to the slight increase opposite the low countries. Conditions on the Western Front were very bad, and anattack at the present time would be impracticable.The Secretary of State for War said that the Russian pressurenorth of Lake Ladoga seemed to have relaxed. The Soviet forces had been thrown back at Kollaanjoki, but at Aittojok the fighting-continued. Changes in the Russian High Command had beenreported, which might indicate a renewed attempt to break theFinnish resistance.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Weekly 5.   The War Cabinet took note of Weekly Resume No. 21 by-Resumes, the Chiefs of Staff (W.P. (40) 32).(previous reference:W.M. (40) 20th &apos;Conclusions,Minute 7.)
Scandinavia.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 21stConclusions,Minute 12.)Finland.allied assistance.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 22ndConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The Secretary of State for War said that the Chiefs ofStaff had prepared a further Report (W.P. (40) 35) on the possi-bilities of intervention in Scandinavia, but a fresh development hadtaken place as a result of the receipt of a telegram from Parisgiving M. Leger&apos;s account of General GamelhVs ideas for directAllied intervention in Finland. The Chiefs of Staff had accordinglyarranged for the Allied Military Committee to go to Paris that morning for an exploratory discussion, and proposed, to go them-selves on the ensuing day to discuss the whole matter with general gamelin. In the meantime, the War Cabinet&apos;s consideration of theChiefs of Staff Report on intervention in Scandinavia would be deferred.It was necessary, however, if we were to have our forces read)&apos;to seize any opportunity that might arise, to proceed, at once withraising the necessary base and line-of-communication units. Theformation of these units would be covered almost entirely by theauthority which the War Office already had to raise and equip the32 divisions, but it might be necessary to obtain authority to raisecertain additional units.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Treasury wouldbe ready to discuss this question with the War Office at the earliestpossible moment.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for War to discuss with theChancellor of the Exchequer, as a matter of urgency, the raising of the additional base and line-of-communicationunits referred to in paragraph 24 (c) of W.P. (40) 35.7. In the course of the discussion on the previous item, theFirst Lord of the Admiralty urged that the discussions of the Chiefsof Staff with General Gamelin should be of an exploratory natureonly. The first impression which he had gained from the Chiefs ofStaff report on Allied Assistance to Finland, which had just been circulated to the War Cabinet (W.P. (40) 36), was that the Chiefsof Staff deprecated the particular proposals put forward by general gamelin.The Chief of Naval Staff said that the Chiefs of Staff had notyet reported on the French plan outlined in the telegram reportingM. Leger&apos;s conversation. The account contained in this telegram was altogether too vague, and it was for this reason that the Chiefsof Staff had felt the best course would be to discuss the matterpersonally with General Gamelin. Their discussions would be ofan exploratory nature only, and they would then report to the WarCabinet.The Prim,e Minister observed that events seemed to be leadingthe Allies towards open hostilities with Russia. He was not clear whether the French had in mind the possibility of immediate actionto counter a combined Russian and German drive against the Finns,or whether they were thinking of an expedition in the lessimmediate future, which would give us more time to make prepara-tions. It would certainly be desirable for the Chiefs of Staff toelucidate the French proposals in personal discussions. It mightwell be that Allied assistance to Finland might be the only way of getting a footing in Scandinavia.The War Cabinet agreed That the forthcoming discussions between the Chiefs ofStaff and General Gamelin should be of an exploratorynature only. The Chiefs of Staff would, of course, makeit clear that we appreciated the great potential importanceof the suggestions made by the French authorities.
The Far East.Relations with japan: thecase of theAsama Mam.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 24thConclusions,Minute 7.)(previous reference:W.M. (40) 23rdConclusions,Minute 4.)8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs made a state-ment regarding the negotiations in Tokyo as to the A. sarna Maru.A point had arisen in connection with the Note, consisting ofan exposition of our case in international law, which had now been delivered to the Japanese Government. The Japanese Ministry forForeign Affairs had suggested (Tokyo telegram No. 145) that we might modify the legal tone of the Note by adding some expression of regret for the offence which had unwittingly been caused to japanese national sentiment. The first phrase suggested bySir Robert Craigie had not been altogether acceptable, but there seemed to be nothing objectionable in his second suggestion : &quot; HisMajesty&apos;s Government greatly regrets, however, that the presentincident, occurring as it did so close to the capital, should havearoused such profound resentment in Japan &quot; (Tokyo telegramNo. 151).The general view of the War Cabinet was that there would beno objection to the British Ambassador presenting a note in theabove terms.The Foreign Secretary went on to say that the success of theTokyo conversations might at any moment be endangered by theJapanese putting in a demand for the return of the 21 Germans.Any chance of a general agreement covering the future would thenprobably disappear. At any rate, a very difficult situation wouldbe created. No such demand had so far been presented, and he (theForeign Secretary) was turning over in his mind the expediency ofour being first in the field with an offer. We might make a statement to the effect that we&apos; had not for a moment contemplated, inconnection with the case of the Asama Maru, any setback to ourgrowing friendship with Japan. On the contrary, we had been greatly surprised at the misunderstanding which had occurred. Ifa satisfactory settlement covering the future could be arrived at, wewere prepared at once to release the 21 Germans now in detentionat Hong Kong.He was not at the moment asking for approval to proceed onthe above lines. He had thought it right, however, to look ahead and to expose his mind to the War Cabinet. If.our present line of negotiation i.e., on the basis of the two suggested solutionsapproved by the War Cabinet on the 25th January should be successful, there would, of course, be no need to search for anotheropening.The view was expressed that it would be essential to discoverwhat the Japanese would do with the 21 Germans from the A samaMaru, in the event of our releasing them. If they were allowed to depart to Germany, we should suffer a serious &quot; loss of face.&quot; TheWar Cabinet were reminded that up to the present time Sir robert craigie&apos;s telegrams had not indicated that he took a very seriousor pessimistic view of the present incident. It was unnecessary, forthe present, to reach a decision on the Foreign Secretary&apos;s tentativesuggestion. If, however, we were to be told by the Ambassador thatwe were within measurable distance of war. with Japan, thesituation would be different. In that event it might be our duty toact on the principle of &quot; one war at a time,&quot; and to make the bestterms we could, before the situation got out of hand.The following additional points were made in discussion : (1) If our relations with Japan deteriorated, as a result of thepresent incident, we should be well advised to &quot; fail tofind&quot; any further Japanese ships carrying Germansubjects, until the war in the West had taken a markedturn in our favour.(2) Attention was drawn to the report that the Nippon YusenKaisha Lines had decided in future to refuse Germanpassengers, unless they could produce affidavits attestingtheir non-combatant status. It was pointed out, how-ever, that the condition as to the production of affidavits
(previous reference:W.M. (40) 25thConclusions,Minute 2.)by Germans was, from our point of view, a safeguardof very little value.(3) The view was expressed that we should do well to make themost of the Wing Sang case, which might be of con-siderable use as a means of applying counter-pressure to the Japanese.The War Cabinet :-(i) Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement,(ii) Agreed that there was no objection to a supplementaryNote being handed to the Japanese Government on thelines proposed by Sir Robert Craigie.Propaganda in 9.   The Secretary of State for ^nAffatrs^e^^Germany. ment regarding Nazi views on the ^^JgS^faSjw^rS(Previous leaflet and broadcastpropaganda,-J^-^S^Z^^&apos;References:       the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.W.M. (39) 44thConclusions,Minute 15, andW.M. (40) 19thConclusions,Minute 1.)Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,January 29, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
