<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/5/18 images: 154-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOOUMSMT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  January 1940.SECRET.Copy No.W.M. (40)18th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It Is requested that special care may- be taken toensure theWAR CABINET 18 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday,&apos; January 19, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.Hon. Winston S.M.P., First Lord of theThe RightChurchillAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,President of the Board of Trade(Item 13).The Right Hon. Sir John Gilmour,Bt., M.P., Minister of Shipping(Item 13).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-12).Sir Arthur Robinson, permanent secretary, Ministry of Supply(Item 13).Air Marshal R. E.Chief of the air the Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Minister of Labour and Minister ofNational Service (Item 13).Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-12).Sir Cyril Hurcomb, Director-General,Ministry of Shipping (Item 13).. C. Peirse, DeputyStaff (Items 1-12).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Mr. G. N. Flemming.
WAR CABINET 18 (40).Contents.Minute ;No.                                      Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     ...       ......       ......... 1152      Aircraft Industry      ...       ..,       ...       ...      ...      ... 1153      The Naval Situation ...       ...       ............ 115...... .       &quot; ..............     ,,&apos;&quot;&apos;        German submarine losses.4      The Military Situation        ...      ............     116Western Front.Finland.5      Western Front ...      ...      ...       ...       ...      ...      ...     116; i  , Possible German attack on Belgium.6      German-Soviet Relations      ...      ...       ... ...     116&apos;Report of concessions to Germany in Southern Poland..7      Sbui.lv-Easf.ern Europe ...       ,..     ....      ...     116Possible German intentions.8      Italy     ......      ...      ..;      .....    ...      ...      ...     117Economic relations.9      Scandinavia     ...      ...       ...       ...       ...      ...      ...     117German submarine attacks on Swedish and Norwegian vessels.10      Scandinavia     ...      ...      ...      ...       ...      ...      ...     118General policy.11  .   Finland ...      ......       ...      .........      ...     118Allied assistance. .....12      Preparation of Strategical Plans   ...       ...       ...      ...     118Responsibility of the Chiefs of Staff Committee.13      Anglo-Soviet Negotiations : Summer 1939 ...       ...      ...     118Proposed publication of Blue Book.14      Explosion at Royal Gunpowder Factory, Waltham Abbey     11915      Shipbuilding:   Proposed   increase   in   programme   ofMerchant Shipbuilding ...      ...      ...      ... -     ...     119The present position and the programme proposed.Need for, and practicability of, a programme at the rate of1  million tons per annum.Supply of steel.Supply of labour. . .Question of the Government Authority to be responsible.
Aircraft 2.   The Secretary of State for Air informed the War CabinetIndustry. that he had received a report from the Air Ministry Intelligencewhich indicated the possibility of industrial trouble in the aircraft industry in the near future. He was in close touch with theMinister of Labour on the matter.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The air situation.(previous reference:W.M..(40) 17thConclusions,Minute 3.)The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 17thConclusions,Minute 4.)Germansubmarinelosses.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 15thConclusions,Minute 6.)3. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that there had beena recrudescence of U-boat activity. The Norwegian steamship Enid(1,140 tons), which had been sunk north of the Shetlands on the17th January, had reported that she had seen/a British shiptorpedoed and sunk and, while looking for survivors of this ship,she herself had been attacked. No news of the unknown ship had yet been received.The Swedish steamship Pajala (6,873 tons) had been torpedoed and sunk to the northward of Cape Wrath. The Pajala had beenunder the escort of the armed boarding trawler Northern Duke?which had engaged the U-boat with gunfire and depth charges and claimed to have obtained a direct hit. The trawler had subsequentlyrescued the crew of the Swedish ship.The Greek steamship Asteria (3,313 tons) had been sunk by a mine off the East Coast. Eleven of the crew of 24 had been saved.Five survivors: from the Norwegian steamship Eagerseim(1,590 tons), which had been sunk, probably by a torpedo, off Ushant,had been landed at Vigo.   Fourteen men were missing. : /One of our trawlers was overdue.The First Lord of the Admiralty again referred to the state1ment on the German wireless which referred to an alleged Britishclaim to have sunk 70 German submarines. The announcer had stated that &quot; if we had said 35 this would have been nearer the mark.&apos;&apos; It Was, of course, impossible for us to arrive at definitefigures, but he (the First Lord) put the German submarine lossesat about 40, while the French put them at about 45. His statement in Parliament that new U-boats were being delivered at the rateof about two a week was an over-estimate. This figure might-represent the position in the coming year, but from the beginningof the war up to Christmas 1939 only eight new U-boats had been added to the German submarine strength. It was therefore safe tosay that the German U-boat- strength was now only half what, ithad been at the beginning of the war.1. The Secretary of State for Air said that propaganda leaflets had been dropped over Hamburg, Bremen; Hanover andBrunswick on the night of the 18th-19th January. All our aircraft had returned safely.Two unidentified aircraft had been plotted during the previous night on the East Coast. ,-. -;: - ?In reply to a question, the Deputy Chief of the Air Staff saidthat there was no foundation for the repeated reports in the press of British bombing attacks on the Island of Sylt. It was possiblethat the reports were occasioned by German training activities.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.
The Military ;Situation.Western Front.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 17thConclusions,Minute 5.)Finland.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 16thConclusions,Minute 5.)4. The Secretary of State for War said that one Germaiidivision appeared to have been moved from opposite Luxemburgto the area opposite Holland. The War Office attached no specialsignificance to the movement. iThe War Cabinet were given information as to the move ofthe 50th and 51st Divisions to France.In reply to a request by the First Lord of the Admiralty, theSecretary of State for War undertook to circulate to the WarCabinet a statement analysing the B.E.F. into units and strength,together with a short explanatory memorandum.The Secretary of State for War said that the Finns were reported to have advanced 36 kilometres in the Salla area.In reply to a question by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff confirmed that the murmansk Railway had been cut, but said that he could not say whether the interruption of the railway had been maintained until further reports had been received.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Western Front. 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionPossible to telegram No. 22 from His Majesty&apos;s Representative, Brussels,German attack dated the 18th January, reporting that the British Military Attache&quot;on Belgium. had now received certain information and had been assured that(Previous replies would be given as soon as possible to a further briefReference: questionnaire on Air matters which he had handed in.   The FrenchW.M. (40) 16th Military Attache would put in a French questionnaire on theConclusions, following day.Minute 3.) The War Cabinet took note of this information.German-soviet relations.(previous references:W.M. (39) 98thConclusions,Minute 9, andW.M. (40) 6thConclusions,Minute 6.)Report of concessions toGermany inSouthernPoland.6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto an article in The Times suggesting that the Soviet Governmentwere contemplating making concessions to Germany in the oil-bearing districts of Poland in return for assistance with the campaign against Finland. He has ascertained from The Timesthat they had obtained these reports from the British United PressAgency in Paris, which would not ordinarily be regarded as a veryreliable source, but that currency was also being given to them bythe Quai d&apos;Orsay. Sir Reginald Hoare had also reported fromBucharest that M. Gafencu was inclined to believe the report thatsome concession of this character was contemplated. It had to beaccepted that one result of Russian weakness, as revealed in theFinnish campaign, was likely to be that she would be thrown intothe arms of Germany, who would be able to exact her price for any assistance given.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.South-eastern europe.PossibleGermanintentions.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 120thConclusions,Minute 9.)7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto a report, from the British Military Attache in Budapest, on thepossibilities of German military action in South-Eastern Europe,which was of particular interest in connection with the viewsrecently expressed by Dr. Benes on this matter during his visit toLondon. The main conclusions of the report were that the possi-bilities of a German military threat, and the degree of Hungarianresistance thereto, depended on political rather than on militaryfactors, and that the Attache&quot; was sceptical in regard to reports ofGerman concentrations in Slovakia, Bohemia, Moravia and the
Italy. 8.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs mentioned that economic a number of telegrams which had been received from Rome showedrelations, that our trade negotiations with the Italian Government had(Previous reached a difficult phase.   The Master of the Rolls would arriveReference:        back in London later that day, and more information would thenw.m. (39) 108th be available.   But he thought it wise to refer to a recent telegramConclusions,      from Sir Percy Loraine (No. 63 of the 16th January), the gist of minute 8.)        which was that the situation arising out of these economic problemshad now assumed a political aspect.   The Italians were, in effect,asking us to rely on their assurances in regard to the destinationsof imports which we wished to control, and wanted us to acceptexports of vegetables, &amp;c, which we did not require in exchange forour coal.   Sir Percy Loraine advised that, if we did not accept their proposals, the result might be a general quarrel, with a press campaing against this country, which would clearly be of great advantage to Germany.  It was not possible yet to be at all definite,but he might, in these circumstances, have to propose the acceptance,on political grounds, of Italian proposals, which would involve anotherwise unjustified drain on our exchange resources.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.9. In connection with the report by the First Lord of theAdmiralty on German submarine activity, the Prime Minister drew attention to the repeated and deliberate attacks by german submarines on Swedish and Norwegian vessels. It might, from some points of view, be argued that mines laid near the British coastswere intended to keep all shipping alike from trading with thiscountry, but deliberate attacks by torpedo and shell fire on Swedishand Norwegian vessels, involving considerable loss of life, wereanother matter. He suggested that in our negotiations with theSwedish and Norwegian Governments it should be pointed out tothem that, while they professed to be in fear of being forced into war with Germany, Germany was, in fact, already at war withthem.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed with thissuggestion, and said he would use this argument in his discussions with the representatives of the two Governments. He would alsoenquire how the matter was being treated in the ScandinavianPress.The Secretary of State for War suggested that the point shouldalso be used in connection with our negotiations for charteringshipping. If Swedish and Norwegian ships were already being attacked by the Germans, they could not refuse to charter their ships to us on the ground that this would involve additional risk of attack.On the contrary, ships chartered to us would have the benefits of ourconvoy system.The War Cabinet agreed-To invite the Lord Privy Seal to ask the Minister of Infor-mation to arrange that the widest publicity should begiven in broadcasts from this country, which would bereceived:in Scandinavia, to the treatment of Scandinavianshipping by Germany, detailed information as to */hichshould be obtained from the Admiralty.Scandinavia,Germansubmarineattacks onSwedish andNorwegianvessels.Burgenland.  He gave no information as to Dr. Benes&apos; report that orders had been given for the strengthening of roads and bridgesin Slovakia and for this work to be completed by the 15th February.The War Cabinet took note of this information.  &apos;
Scandinavia.Genera] policy.(previous reference:   .,W.M. (40) 16thConclusions,Minute 9.)10. The War Cabinet had before them the following reports by the Chiefs of Staff Committee :-(i) Paper No. W.P. (40) 23.&apos;   (&quot;ii) Paper&apos; No. W.P. (40) 24.A record of the discussion and of the conclusions reached is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Finland.allied assistance.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 15thConclusions,Minute 11.)Preparation ofStrategicalPlans.Responsibilityof the Chiefs ofStaffCommittee.11. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs reported a conversation which he had had with the French Ambassadorregarding assistance to Finland. A record of the discussion and ofthe conclusions reached is contained in the Secretary&apos;s standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.12. During the discussion on items 10 and 11 reference wasmade to the machinery by which strategical plans should be worked out.The First Lord of the Admiralty urged that, when one particular Service was the predominant partner in an operation,it was desirable that the Staff of that Service should prepare theplan in the first instance so that its integrity might be maintained.The plan could then be elaborated as necessary by the Joint planning committee, so as to ensure that the functions of the other services were taken into account.The Prime Minister thought that the proper course was forthe War Cabinet to remit the preparation of all strategical plans to the Chiefs of Staff, and to leave it to them to decide how thework of planning should be distributed between their respectiveStaffs. In cases where one Service was clearly the predominantpartner, it would, of course, be only reasonable for the originaloutline of the plan to be prepared by the Staff of the Service inquestion, but this was a matter of machinery. The broad principle should be that the responsibility for the preparation of strategicalplans should rest with the Chiefs of Staff in their corporate capacity,and not upon any particular Department.The War Cabinet endorsed the view expressed by thePrime Minister.Anglo-soviet negotiations:Summer, 1939.proposed publication of blue Book.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 17thConclusions,Minute 2.)13. The Prime Minister said that he had mentioned thismatter to the Leader of the Opposition, who, contrary to expecta-tions, had raised some objection to the proposal not to proceed withpublication at this juncture of the proposed Blue Book. It hadbeen arranged that Mr. Attlee should consult with some of themembers of his Party, and should discuss the matter again withthe Prime Minister in the ensuing week.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.
Explosion atRoyal[GunpowderFactory,.   -Waltham&quot;Abbey.14. The Prime Minister said that his colleagues would be aware that there had been a serious explosion at this factory,i-esulting in considerable damage, the loss of five lives, and minorinjuries to 40 men. It was feared that this explosion would resultin a reduction in the output of cordite over two or three months.No evidence was available to support the view that the explosionhad been due. to sabotage, but a Court of Inquiry had been appointed and was how sitting.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Shipbuilding:proposed increase inProgramme ofMerchantShipbuilding.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 122ndConclusions,Minute 2.)The presentposition and theprogrammeproposed.15. The War Cabinet had before them two documents by theLord Privy Seal, (1) a Report proposing an increase in the Govern-menfs programme of merchant shipbuilding (W.P. (G.) (40) 11);(2) a Note on the labour required for an annual programme ofone and a half million gross tons of merchant shipping (W.P. (G.)(40) 13).The Lord Privy Seal said that, as arranged at the Meeting ofthe War Cabinet noted in the margin, he had been engaged incarrying out a general review of our shipping position; and he had come to the conclusion that the most urgent aspect of the question was the size of our shipbuilding programme. There were two other important, but in a sense more complex, aspects, namely, (i) the1possibility of securing relief for our shipping difficulties through a jfurther restriction of imports, and (ii) of reducing the delays dueto convoys and similar causes. The first of these was underconsideration by the Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy,and he also hoped to produce a further Report. The second group of questions was under close discussion between himself and theDepartments concerned, and he hoped to submit a Report on itshortly.The position as regards merchant shipbuilding might besummarised broadly as follows : (a) The present merchant shipbuilding programme.At the present time merchant shipbuilding constructionwas at the rate of 790,000 gross tons per annum, and the actualtarget programme adopted by the Government looked to raising the rate of construction to one million gross tons per annum inthe course of the Spring. He (the Lord Privy Seal) was con-vinced that a programme even of one million gross tons was not sufficient; he was much impressed by the fact that even duringthe present period of comparative inactivity we were alreadyexperiencing difficulties through shortageof shipping; further,it was also necessary to realise the importance of makingpreparations to enable us to deal with the situation whichwould arise, if our shipping needs were greatly increased, e.g.,through new military expeditions, through the need for givinghelp to Allies, &amp;c. The sooner the fact was faced that thepresent target programme of one million tons was inadequate,the less likely they would be to find themselves later in diffi-culties of the kind which had arisen during the last war.The programme which he (the Lord Privy Seal) recom-mended that the Government should adopt was one which wouldaim at merchant shipbuilding reaching the rate of one and a half million gross tons within a period of twelve months. this rate would be sufficient to make good the gross loss.of tonnagedue to enemy action, if in the next twelve months such losses were to continue at the rate sustained in the first four months ofthe war. The increase of our merchant shipping, if carriedsufficiently far, would have the further advantage that it might
enable us to dispense in part with the need for charteringneutral tonnage at very high rates; it might also make it possible for us to re-employ some of our shipping in neutraltrades, thereby giving us additional foreign exchange receipts.He therefore considered that the Government should atonce set themselves to secure an annual output of a rate ofone and a half million gross tons. This was a formidabletarget, but it should be remembered that in .1918 we had had a programme of 3,000,000 gross tons, and though owing to thetermination of the war we did not reach that figure, we hadin fact secured an output at a rate approximately equivalent tothat now proposed. In spite of the present shortage of steel and the difficulties in regard to the supply of labour and tosome extent also of yards, he believed that it would be possiblefor the Departments concerned to achieve a rate of output ofone and a half million gross tons of merchant shipping in aperiod of twelve months. To secure this end, however,immediate action in various directions was necessary.(b) The main difficulties to be overcome.(i) Priority for steel, &amp;c, required for merchant ship-building.Even with the present merchant shipbuilding programme of one million gross tons, the construc-tion of ships was being held up through difficultiesin securing the delivery of steel required. For that programme 750,000 tons of steel was required, while for a programme of one and a half million gross tonsof merchant shipping 1,100,000 tons of steel wouldbe required. To secure this, it would be necessary togive to steel for merchant shipbuilding the same degree of priority as that given to steel for theFighting Services. The quantity of steel involvedwas large, but (as pointed out in paragraph 7 of his-report) the return secured by the employment ofsteel for merchant shipping was very great, sinceevery ton of steel so employed gave nearly four tonsof dead-weight shipping capacity which could carryto this country over twelve tons of goods per annum.(ii) Shipbuilding capacity.It would, he (the Lord Privy Seal) thought, bepossible to secure the necessary shipbuilding capacity for the merchant shipbuilding programmeproposed without causing embarrassment to theAdmiralty. At the present time not all the ship-yards were in use and, in addition, there were thedisused yards, some of which might need to bereopened.(iii) The labour required for the programme proposed.The report of the Committee presided over bythe late Mr. Humbert Wolfe, which had been circulated by the Chancellor of the Exchequer(W.P. (G.) (40) 9), showed the estimated deficiency of labour in relation even to the present programmeof one million gross tons of merchant shipbuilding.As a result of discussion with the Ministry ofShipping and the Ministry of Labour, he (the lord privy Seal) saw no reason to doubt that it wouldbe possible to find the labour for that programme.The only question, therefore, was whether the labourcould be found to secure the increase in the pro-gramme from one million to one and a half million
The need for,and praotica-bility of, a programme atthe rate of one and a half million grosstons per annum.Supply of steel.gross tons of shipping. The Note prepared by theMinistry of Labour, which he had circulated theprevious day as W.P. (G.) (40) 13, showed that thetask was formidable, but not impossible, providedthat certain conditions in regard, for example, todilution and training were secured.(c) The organisation required.If the programme now recommended was to be secured, itwas essential that it should be pushed through with the utmostvigour. He (the Lord Privy Seal) was convinced that for thatpurpose the organisation of the Ministry of Shipping would need to be greatly strengthened. This led to the questionwhether it would be wise at the present stage to revert to theprocedure adopted in the Great War, namely, to combine ina single person responsibility for merchant shipbuilding as wellas for naval construction.The Prime Minister suggested that the War Cabinet should consider, first, whether a merchant shipbuilding programme as great as 1^ million tons Avas (a) required and (b) practicable, and,secondly, if the answers to these questions were in the affirmative,who should be the authority responsible for carrying through that programme.The Minister of Shipping said that, in fact, it had not yetbeen possible to reach an output of the rate of 1 million tons perannum. This was due to various causes, of which the mostimportant was the inadequate priority allotted to the steel for merchant shipbuilding. Other difficulties included (i) the diversion of a number of merchant shipbuilding slips to Naval purposes onthe outbreak of war, and (ii) the shortage of skilled labour. our shipping losses, though less than in the Great War, were neverthe-less considerable. It must be recalled also that we were getting lessassistance from neutrals than during the Great War, e.g., from norway, Greece and the U.S.A. As regards the possibility of purchasing U.S. shipping, no decision had yet been reached by the maritime Commission on the question of flag transfer; without such transfer the transactions provisionally arranged would come to nothing. He agreed that the building of li million gross tons ofmerchant shipping per annum was a programme at which theGovernment should aim.The Secretary of State for War said that, while it was truethat the rate of 1 million tons per annum would not be reached untilthe Spring, there had been no delay in the fulfilment of the Govern-menfs plan in this matter, since it had never been intended thatthat rate should be reached before the Spring of 1940.The Prime Minister said that it appeared that a programmeof this magnitude was required as the cumulative result of a numberof difficulties, including the diversion of merchant yards to Navalpurposes, the delays due to convoys, the fact that neutral shippingwas not forthcoming to the extent anticipated, and generally to ourlack of margin to meet contingencies.Sir Cyril Hurcomb agreed that this was the case, and said thatas soon as the Ministry was within sight of attaining the rate of output of 1 million tons, it would, in any case, have aimed at sercuring a further increase in the rate of output.The President of the Board of Trade said that the key to thedifficulty was to be found in the fact that the Admiralty had occupied berths which had been allocated to merchant shipbuilding,
Supply oflabour.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 17thConclusions,Minute 1.)and that in consequence it had been necessary to allocate additional supplies of steel to the Admiralty. It must be clearly understoodthat the additional quantity of steel now asked for for merchantship building could only be made available at the expense of someother item, e.g., steel for export. Steel for merchant shipbuildinghad always received a high rate of preference. On the whole, therehad been but little complaint from the merchant shipbuilding yards,though steel deliveries were certainly tight; no difficulties at all had arisen where progress orders had been placed sufficiently far ahead. Rather than sacrifice our exports of machinery, &amp;c, whichwould be necessary if the amount of steel required for the merchantship building programme was to be found from home-producedsources, it would, in his view, be wiser to purchase from the UnitedStates the steel required for the merchant shipbuilding programme.From the point of view of the Board of Trade, he would view withgreat apprehension a decision to give the highest priority to steelfor shipbuilding, and he suggested that, before such a decision wastaken, an examination should be carried out to ascertain whetherall the uses of steel at present given the highest degree of prioritywere, in fact, of such importance as to justify their being so treated.The Prime Minister agreed that steps should be taken toexamine both the points raised by the President of the Board ofTrade.The Minister of Labour said that his views as to the supply oflabour required for the proposed programme were set out in thepaper which had been circulated as W.P. (G.) (40) 13. Those views were still provisional, but nevertheless he considered that the prO-gramme, though formidable, was one which could be carried out.In so far as it made increased demands on general engineering, theprogramme would be in competition with the other Service pro-grammes. He regretted that in the short time available it had notbeen possible for him to present the picture the labour demandsimplied in the shipbuilding programme in terms of the statisticsemployed in the Humbert Wolfe report. The latter were calculated on a basis different from those furnished by the ShipbuildingEmployers&apos; Federation.The Minister without Portfolio thought that there could be nodoubt that it was possible to achieve the rate of shipbuildingproposed by the Lord Privy Seal. It should be recalled that between1916 and 1917 merchant shipbuilding had been raised from the rateof 542,000 tons to that of 1,163,000 tons. Further, in the first ten months of 1918, production had amounted to 1,310,000 tons, an output equivalent to approximately 1,500,000 tons in a full year.The bottle-necks in the Great War were the same as those with whichwe were now faced, namely, the provision of steel and the supplyof labour.The Minister of Labour recalled that in October 1918 thenumber of workers in the shipbuilding industry had been 279,500workers (including 9,000 women), whereas in December 1939 thenumber (including 39,000 in the Royal Naval Dockyards) was only169,000. In general, he regarded merchant shipbuilding as formingan integral part of our defence programme as a whole. While notunderestimating the labour difficulties involved, he said that thedemands of the Departments concerned had never in practice keptpace with the figures in the programmes. He could not say whetherit would be possible to reach the rate of production proposed withina period of twelve months, until he had had an opportunity of discussing the matter with both sides of the shipbuilding industry.The Secretary of State for War thought that it would only bepossible to achieve the shipbuilding programme proposed at the
;:-nci cost of reducing some other part of our war effort.   The need toincrease our merchant tonnage was, however, so great that he favoured the adoption of the increased programme proposed.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it would be an immense gain if we could secure an increased output of merchantship building on the scale proposed. Moreover, at the end of the warthe possession by the Government of a substantial fleet of merchant ships would be of great assistance in dealing with the shipowners&apos;claims for compensation for losses sustained during the war. Hewas in favour of the policy proposed, but it must be remembered thatthe demands which it might make on raw materials and labourmight trench on other important claims for instance, those of theRoyal Navy. If the War Cabinet were to decide to work for anannual output of 1-J million tons of merchant shipping, they wouldnot necessarily thereby be taking a decision to starve other important Services. There would be opportunities later foradjusting the competing claims of various parts of the Govem-menfs programme.Question of the The Prime Minister said that it was clear that there wasGovernment general agreement that a, merchant shipbuilding programme of authority to be 1\ million tons per annum was both practicable and desirable. Itresponsible. remained to decide what authority should be responsible forcarrying through such a programme. He thought there was muchto be said for adopting the policy carried out in the last war, bywhich the Admiralty, the principal competitor of merchant ship-building both as regards raw material and labour, was itself made responsible for merchant shipbuilding. That arrangement had hadthe advantage of ensuring that full weight was given to the relativeclaims of Naval construction and merchant shipbuilding. Severalpractical reasons also pointed to the same conclusion. In a numberof yards both merchant and Naval vessels were under construction,and in such cases great advantage could be secured through thetransfer of labour from Naval to merchant shipbuilding, and vice versa, as progress of work in the yards from time to time might require. In favouring a transfer of responsibility for&apos; merchantship building to the Admiralty, he did not question in any way thecompetence of the Ministry of Shipping, but was influenced solely by the advantages to be secured through making a single authorityresponsible for all classes of shipbuilding in .this country. Ifmerchant shipbuilding were to be so transferred, the admiralty would need to strengthen their organisation in order to dischargethese additional responsibilities.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the general view ofthe Naval Staff was that on balance the best course might betransfer responsibility for merchant shipbuilding to the Admiralty.That arrangement had worked satisfactorily in the Great War; ithad secured the best use of the resources available and had,moreover, avoided the possibility of friction. If, therefore, it wasthe general wish of the War &quot;Cabinet, the Admiralty would beprepared to assume this additional responsibility. He supported the Lord Privy SeaTs proposal that our merchant shipbuilding programme should be raised to 1\ million tons, since he regardedmerchant shipbuilding as a most essential factor&apos;in our war effort.The Minister of Shipping said that he would be in no way...     -     . opposed to a transfer from his Department to the Admiralty ofresponsibility   for   merchant   shipbuilding,   provided   that   theAdmiralty recognised the right of his Department to decide the types of merchant ship to be built.The Prime Minister said that he assumed that in this matter the Ministry of Shipping would be the client, whose needs theAdmiralty would supply.
The Lord Privy Seal thought&apos;  hate it was essential that, asregards the labour side of the question,1 the full position should beput before both sides of the shipbuilding industry with the least possible delay.The Minister of Labour agreed that, this was of greatimportance. He hoped that, on the transfer of responsibility for merchant shipbuilding from the Ministry of Shipping to theAdmiralty, the shipyard labour Department of the Admiralty would maintain the closest relations with the Ministry of Labour.The First Lord of the A. dmirulty said that he would prepare a Memorandum setting out the scheme. of organisation which hewould propose to set up on the transfer to the Admiralty ofresponsibility for merchant shipbuilding.The War Cabinet :-(a) approved the proposals set out in paragraph 21 (c) of the report  by the Lord Privy Seal (W.P. (G.) (40) 11),namely, that all possible steps should be taken to ensurethat at the expiry of a period of twelve months fromthe present time, merchant shipbuilding should reach therate of 1,500,000 gross tons per annum;(b) Took note that this programme involved the yearly delivery to the shipbuilding yards of 1,100,000 tons of steel, andthat this could be achieved either by according to the steel required the same degree of priority as that givento steel required for Naval construction, or by arrange-ments being made for steel required for the merchantship building programme to be imported specially fromthe United States;(c) with reference to (6) above, invited the Chancellor of theExchequer to examine, in consultation with theMinisters concerned :  (1) whether, having regard to the important and heavy demands for steel for purposes other than meetingthe requirements of the Fighting Services, thepresent arrangement, by which, in the allocation of steel for particular uses, the highest degree ofpreference is given to all Service uses, is justified,or whether Service demands could, with advantage, be classified in such a way as toensure the highest rate of preference being allo-cated only to the most important Service uses,lower rates of preference being allocated to service uses of less importance;(2) the relative advantages from the point of view ofconserving our resources of foreign exchange and shipping : (i) of giving to steel for shipbuilding the highestrate of preference, with the attendant risk that the supplies of steel required for themanufacture of exports would be therebymuch curtailed;(ii) of securing steel required for merchant ship-building by purchase from the UnitedStates, thereby ensuring that no diminution-tion of our export programme resulted from the increase in the merchant ship-building programme now decided upon :(d) approved in principle the early transfer from the Ministryof Shipping to the Admiralty of the administrative
responsibility for the Government&apos;s merchant ship-building programme, it being understood that, asregards the types of merchant ship to be built, theAdmiralty would meet the requirements of the Ministryof Shipping;(e) took note that the First Lord of the Admiralty proposed to circulate a Memorandum. setting out the form of organisation which he proposed to establish at theAdmiralty on the transfer to that Department of theresponsibility for merchant shipbuilding.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,January 19, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
