<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/235/0 images: 87-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS    EREMITIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).COPY NO.SECRET.CP. 413 (32)                    CABINET.                        INDIA.               Appreciation of the Political Situation     by the Government of India,  dated 25th November 1932.               Circulated for the information of the     Cabinet by the Secretary of State for India.
Confidential  appreciations  of  the  Political Situationin India dated 25th November,1952,  issued  on  the authorityof the  Segretary of State for  India.         During the pact month interest in politicalcircles has concentrated on the Unity Conference atAllahabad, to which a brief reference was made in the lastappreciation.  Great efforts have been made by the CongressPress to represent that the Conference has succeeded in settling various points in dispute between the communities, but this is far from being the case.  a brief review of recent events is necessary to makethe position clear.           The communal decision of His Majesty&apos;sGovernnent was generally well received by the Muslims,the Sikhs were greatly dissatisfied with it and the hindus generally condemned it on the ground that itsacrificed their interests to those of the Muslims.The Hindus were forced by Mr. Gandhi&apos;s fast to make further concessions to the Depressed classes.   Tosafeguard their position and to establish their influence with the Untouchables it became necessary to ,attempt a vigorous campaign for the removal ofuntouchability and there is direct evidence to show thatthis movement was inspired almost entirely by Congress.The campaign soon aroused strong opposition from orthodoxHindus, who criticised the Poona Pact as the work of asmall heterodox minority.  Numerous instances ofthis  &quot;&apos;growing opposition to the campaign might be cited butit is sufficient to note that Malaviya&apos;s attempt to winsupport for it in the Punjab met with little success,                                                    while
while a tour of two Congress leaders, Rajagopalacharia and Rajendra Prasad, in Madras did little exceptevoTce &quot;the opposition of the orthodox.  The congress leaders had thus achieved nothing by the temporarydiversion of their activities to the new campaign;  itsfailure was damaging to their prestige and its continuance might cause a split in their ranks.Their main hope of improving their position lay in securing the release of Gandhi and other leaders.         At this stage it will be convenient to refer tothe policy of the Government in regard to Mr. Gandhi.Civil disobedience which, as he made clear in his letter to the Viceroy of 1st January last is the alternativefor him of armed rebellion, is still his creed.  although he is taking a very active part in the campaign for theremoval of untouchability, there are no signs that heintends to devote himself to this work to the exclusion of his political activities as leader of CivilDisobedience, and he would probably only agree to suspend Civil Disobedience on his own terras.  Thusreasons which made it necessary to arrest Mr. Ganahiin January last still apply with equal force. Government,therefore, have made their position clear;  they have grantedhim, while in jail, full  facilities for carrying on thework of social and religious reform, but they are notprepared to allow him to take part in discussions ofpolitical questions or consolidate iiis position as political leader.         Hindu-Muslim conversations had begunimmediately after the Poona Pact, and there is good reason tobelieve chat one of the chief objects, which theoriginators of these negotiations had in mind, was tosecure the release of Mr. Gandhi;  they hoped to bring                                                pressure
pressure to bear on the Government to modify theirpolicy by showing that a final settlement of outstanding points  in dispute between the communities could only he effected by the intervention of the Hindu leader -a claim which might appear reasonable to those whooverlooked the fact that during 1931 Mr. Gandhi had contributed little or nothing to the solution of this problem.   The conversations between Shaulcat Ali ana Malaviyawhich began in the first week of October in Bombay,led to outspoken opposition from several influentialMuslim leaders who declined the invitation to take partin the conference at Lucknow.         They pointed^out that the Conference would serveno useful purpose since it was not called to discuss any definite proposals by the other side, that the Muslimclaims were well known and that it was for the majoritycommunity to make a definite offer.  The LucknowConference, however, though not representative of Punjaband  Bengal Muslims, resolved to negotiate with Hindusand Sikhs and the Unity Conference opened at Allahabad.At first it appeared likely to end in complete failure;in the end a mere rump of the original Conference, whichwas itself not representative of the main Muslim view, arrivedat an agreement on certain points.  It v?as agreed that Sindshould be separated, subject to certain conditions;   thatin Bengal and the Punjab Muslims should have 51 per/cent, ofthe seats, ana that there should be in all Provincesjoint electorates with reserved seats, but that, for thenext ten years only, a modified form of Mohammed Ali*sformula would be adopted, under which a communal candidatewould have to secure a certain percentage of the                                                  vot es
votes of his own community.   It remains for thisagreement to be ratified, by the communities concerned,  ithas already been condemned by a Conference of leadingMuslims at Delhi who have taken the view that theacceptance of the Muslim demands, such as a majority inthe Punjab and Bengal and the separation of Sind, have    soboery/hedged round with qualifications and conditions asto be valueless.   In regard to Bengal, it is pointed outthat the Muslim representation has been increased at theexpense of the European community, who did not take partin the Conference and whose representation on the BengalCouncil has been reduced by 72 per cent., while, even inthe Punjab, the Muslims, while deprived of the safeguardof separate electorates, have not been grantedrepresentation on a population basis.       The modification of the Mahomed Ali formula hasbeen strongly criticised in that under it the Muslimcandidates will always have to consider the Hindu votersfirst and the Muslims afterwards.   It is not only fromthe Muslim side that resolutions of the Unity Conference                      tilehave been criticised; / Hindu Mahasabha has shown signs of opposition to any further concessions which it regards asanti-National.   The Conference has, however, beenapplauded in the Hindu Nationalist Press as a great step &quot;in the path of National unity and a concerted effort isbeing made to pretend that difficulties have beensurmounted.       Civil disobedience activities continue at a lowebb, but, apart from the manoeuvre to secure a truce toenable them to reorganise, Congress still has its eye on those areas where agitation may prove  fruitful.   Thus,in &quot;tUnited Provinces, though outward manifestation of Congress                                           activity/
activity has been eon fined to petty demonstrations,  thereare signs that preparations are being made for reopeningthe No-rent campaign at the earliest opportunity;   a partial failure cf crops in eastern districts will be usedto the full, if opportunity offers.   Conditions ingeneral have improved:  they have not yet been restored to normal and any relaxation by Government or any loss ofinitiative would lead to a recrudescence cf subversiveactivity.   In the Assembly the Bill to replace the ordinance has been discussed at great length, but it maybe anticipated that it will be accepted as modified bySelect Committee.   The various local Bills to supplement the main Bill have also made encouraging progress and insome cases have already been passed.       The Ottawa agreement met with much ill-informedopposition when first put before the Assembly;  it has there fore been referred to a Committee for detailed examination.   Whether the Assembly will finally accept itis still open to some doubt.   The opposition is almostentirely political and is, in the main, based on the idea that, if the agreement is rejected commercial interests inEngland may be so much impressed as to bring pressure onthe Government to come to terms with Congress.       In the appreciation for August reference was made to burma and it was anticipated that the general electionwould result in a large majority in favour of separationfrom India.   This forecast has proved very wide of the mark, for the election has resulted in the return of 41anti-separationists,  28 separationists and 9 neutrals.The anti-separationis ts appear to be only willing to join the Federation if they are given a free hand to withdrawat any time, but further comment must be deferred till                                               quest ion/
question has been discussed in the newly elected Council.       It is satisfactory to be able to record some slightimprovement in the terrorist situation in Bengal.    Theattempted assassins of Sir Alfred Watson and Mr. Grassbyhave been convicted;  there have been no further seriousoutrages and the presence of troops appears to be  havingthe reassuring effect anticipated.

</content>
</cab>
