<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/235/0 images: 286-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 jjl C R E  T. p.  443.                                            COPY NO:                         C A 3  I N E T.                 CONTROL OP CROWN LANDS COMMITTEE.                         INTERIM REPORT.            At  their meeting on 14th December, 1933  (Cabinet 67(52)       Conclusion  13)  the Cabinet agreed  that a Cabinet Committee       composed of -                 The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries                                             (in the Chair) :                 The Secretary  of State for Home Affairs:                 The Secretary  of State for Air;                 The First Commissioner of Works,  and                 The Financial  Secretary  to the Treasury,       should meet and report to the Cabinet at their next  meeting       if possible,  as to -             (i)  the Government responsibility for the                  administration of Crown  Lands, and            (ii)  the proposed rebuilding  of Carlton                 Gardens and Carlton House Terrace.       By direction of the Lord President of the Council,  the       Attorney-General was  subsequently  added to  the Committee.            We  have also conferred with Mr. A.8.Gaye, the  Permanent       Commissioner&quot;of Crown Lands.            We  have not yet  completed  our examination of  the  question       of future Government  responsibility for the administration of       Crown Lands.  We have, however, reached the following       conclusions on  the  second part  of  our terms of reference,       namely,  the proposed  rebuilding of Carlton  Gardens  and       Carlton  House Terrace.Is           The first  question  is concerned with the letting  ofTON?NS.    the site of No: 4, Carlton Gardens to Messrs. Pinchin,       Johnson  and Company, Limited, a firm of wholesale paint       manufacturers,  for  the  erection of a block  of office       buildings.IS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT.)
     We understand that the present position in regard  tothis matter is as follows:     In J ;.ly last the Commissioners of Crown lands,  withthe consent of the Treasury, granted a building lease of the site of No: 4, Carlton Gardens, to Messrs. Pinchin,  Johnsonand Company.  Subsequently the Commissioners approved thenlans of the proposed new building, and Messrs. Pinchin,-Johnson  and Company entered into a contract with a firm ofbuilding contractors early in Sept-ember for the demolition of the old housej and for  the  erection of the new blockof offices, at a cost of approximately  60,000.  The oldhouse has been demolished, and orders have been placed forall the building materials required for the new house, andmost of the steel work has already been manufactured.     We are advised  that special legislation would be requiredto compel Messrs. Pinchin., Johnson and Company to abandon their project and to release  the Commissioners from  theircontract.  There is no reason  to suppose  that  the firm would agree voluntarily to the cancellation of  the contract;  but even if they  could be induced  to do so, we are assured  that very substantial compensation, amounting  possibly to  50,000might have  to be paid.  Ho allowance has  been  made in this figure for  the profit which a  shrewd bargainer might expect to get when he is asked to  sell  something which the prospective purchaser particularly wants  to have and cannot get elsewhere. Any reduced  future user would also involvethe  loss  to the  Crown Lands Commissioners of a portion  ofthe  improved  ground  rents  of   1,600 per annum  secured bythe  lease.     In  these circumstances we are  unanimously of opinionthat no  attempt  should be  made by  the Government  to  interferewith Messrs,  pinchin,  Johnson&apos;s  lease of  No: 4, Carlton Carder
UTUREOPMEK TRLTON     The position in regard to CarIton House Terrace isthat no decision whatever has been taken concerning thefuture development of the Carlton Rouse Terrace site.  our attention has been drawn to the increasing difficultiesof finding tenants for houses in Carlton Gardens and CarltonHouse Terrace, aid to the serious Iocs to the CrownRevenues involved in the houses remaining untenantedoNotwithstanding these considerations, the Commissioners of Crown Lands have assured us that they do net propose totake any further action in regard to the development ofCarlton Louse Terrace pending a definite conclusion by theCabinet.  In this connection we learn from Kr. Gaye that no more properties on these si fees will come into the market before april, 1333.Our findings may be summarised as follows.  (i)   That  no attempt  should  be  made  by  the       Government  to  interfere with Messrs. Pinchin,       Johnson&apos;s lease  of No.  4,  Carlton  Gardens; (ii)   That  in view of  the fact that no decision       has been taken,  or will be taken in the  near       future  with regard to  the  future development       of Carlton  Rouse Terrace,  this  matter  should       be deferred pending the Cabinet decision on       the question of  future  Government  responsibility      .for the administration  of  the Crown Lands;(ill)   That,  in view  of the constitutional and       technical considerations involved,  the question       of future Government responsibility for  the       administration of Crown Lands needs further       careful and detailed examination.     Y/e hope to be in a position to report to the Cabineton the general question after the Christmas recess.                        Signed on behalf of the Committee,                                 WALTER E. ELLIOT.,                                    Chairman.hitehall Gardens,  S.WVI0 20th December,  1932.

</content>
</cab>
