<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/31/0 images: 6-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTEIRE&apos;S  FUTURE  RELATIONS WITH THE commonwealth memorandum&apos; by the Lord Chancellor and the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations in pursuance of the Cabinefs decision of 13th November (CM. (48) 72ndConclusions) we have held in Paris two sets of discussions about the consequences of the forthcoming repeal of the Eire Executive Authority (External Relations)Act, 1936:-(a) On 14th November, Avith the Prime Minister of New Zealand, the deputy prime Minister of Australia and the Canadian Secretary of Statefor External Affairs; and(b) On 15th-16th November with those Commonwealth representatives andwith the following representatives of the Eire Government: Mr. Sean. r MacBride (Minister for External Affairs), Mr. Patrick McGilligan(Minister of Finance) and Mr. Cecil Lavery (Attorney-General).The results of the earlier meeting were reported to the Cabinet on 15th November.On the second occasion, we held three meetings with the Eire Ministers beginning with an informal discussion after dinner on 15th November, at whichall save New Zealand were represented, and continuing with full and formalmeetings in the morning and afternoon of 16th November. The discussions wereconducted throughout in the most friendly and constructive spirit.Records of both sets of discussions are annexed.2. We began by expounding to the Eire Ministers the legal difficultieswhich we expected to arise, by reason of most-favoured-nation provisions in commercial treaties, if Eire became a foreign State and we and other Common-wealth countries continued to accord to her the special privileges which she nowenjoys in matters of trade and treatment of nationals. In reply, the Eire Ministersmaintained that the repeal of the External Relations Act involved no constitu-tional change : in their view, Eire had ceased to be a member of the Commonwealthsince the adoption of her new constitution at the end of 1937 : at any time duringthe last eleven years her special privileges might have been challenged by a third party on most-favoured-nation grounds, but no such challenge had ever been made : and the likelihood that the position would be challenged in futurewould not be increased by the repeal of the External Relations Act.We pointed out that, while Eire Ministers might now argue that Eire had ceased to be a member of the Commonwealth since the end of 1937, it was publicly announced on 30th December, 1937, that the other Commonwealth governments were &quot; prepared to trqat the new constitution as not affecting a fundamentalalteration in the position of the Irish Free State, in future to be described underthe new constitution as Eire or Ireland, as a Member of the British Common-wealth of Nations.&quot; The Governments of the United Kingdom and other commonwealth countries had been able to take that line because they could argue that through the External Relations Act a link had been preserved betweenEire and the Crown. It might well be that this was a weak link and an unsatis-factory one; but it was this which had justified the other Governments of the printed for the Cabinet.   November 1948SECRETWe 6--.- O copy No. 61.CP. (48) 27217!!/*. November, 1948CABINET
Commonwealth in proceeding throughout this period on the basis that Eireremained a member of the Commonwealth. It was not, therefore, open to those governments to argue now that Eire had ceased to be a member of the Common-wealth since 1937 and that the repeal of the External Relations Act involvedno change in that position.3. The Prime Minister of New Zealand made a strong appeal to the eire ministers that Eire should continue within the Commonwealth. He emphasised the fact that Eire was one of the parent countries of the Commonwealth andstressed the dismay with which her secession would be greeted by Irish peoplethroughout the world. He also referred to the great political difficulties which hersecession would cause to Governments in the United Kingdom, Canada, Australiaand New Zealand which were all well-disposed towards the Eire Governmentand most anxious to help them. Finally., he spoke of the duty of the Common-wealth countries at this time to stand together in resisting the threat of communism and preserving world peace, and urged that there should be noapparent weakening of the Commonwealth group at this critical stage of inter-national affairs. This appeal was fully endorsed by the representatives of theUnited Kingdom, Canada and Australia. In this form, however, it met with no response from the Eire Ministers. They made it clear that there were two points on which their Governments could offer no compromise. First, they were determined to proceed with the repeal of the External Relations Act. Secondly,they were not prepared that Eire should be or become a member of theCommonwealth.4. At the same time, Eire Ministers stressed the desire of their Governmentto continue and to strengthen the close factual relationship between Eire andthe other countries of the Commonwealth. They were anxious to have the mostclose and friendly association with the Governments and peoples of the Common-wealth ; but they preferred to build that practical association on a reciprocalexchange of rights between free and independent peoples, e.g., in such matters as trade preferences and citizenship. Did the Commonwealth countries wish tomaintain that friendly association ? If so, they and Eire could surely find togethermeans of resisting any attempt by third parties to drive a wedge between them on the basis of most-favoured-nation rights.5. The Deputy Prime Minister of Australia suggested that such a meansmight be found through the fact that, even if Eire was not a member of theCommonwealth, she and the Commonwealth countries would not regard one another as &quot; foreign.&quot; It was a fact that an Australian would never think ofhimself as a foreigner in Eire, any more than an Irishman would think ofhimself as a foreigner in Australia. Could not legal expression be given to this fact in a way which would enable Eire and the Commonwealth countries tomaintain that they were not &quot; foreign &quot; to one another and to resist on that basisany claims which might be made by foreign countries on &apos;&apos; most-favoured-nationgrounds ? In the course of the afternoon meeting on 16th November the deputy prime Minister of Australia produced the following formula: &apos;&apos; From the point of view of Ireland, the factual relationship betweenit and the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia and New Zeland is clear.Ireland does not, and, when the External Relations Act, 1936, is repealed,will not, regard the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia or New Zealandor &apos; foreign &apos; countries or treat their peoples as &apos; foreigners.&apos; On the con-trary the fact is that the citizens of Ireland, while resident in the UnitedKingdom, Canada, Australia or New Zealand, are treated by law or practicenot as &quot; foreigners &quot; or aliens but as entitled to the rights and privileges ofnationals or citizens of those nations. Similarly, while in Ireland, the nationals or citizens of the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia or NewZealand are treated not as foreigners or aliens but as entitled to the rightsand privileges of citizens of Ireland. These facts not only negative theview that Ireland and the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia and NewZealand are to be regarded as &apos; foreign &apos; countries; but they also evidencethe fact of a special association which it is the firm desire and intentionof Ireland to maintain and strengthen.&quot;Dr. Evatt&apos;s intention was that a statement on these lines should be made onbehalf of the Eire Government in the course of the debate in the Dail on theSecond Reading of the Bill for the repeal of the External Relations Act.   Mr.
MacBride said at once that, if a solution on those lines proved acceptable to therepresentatives of the other Commonwealth countries, he would be quite ready tomake some such statement in the Dail, though he could not commit himself atthis stao-e to every detail of the language to be used. It was, for example, pointedout (and he agreed) that any such statement ought to cover all the countries &apos;ofthe Commonwealth.6. At this point in the discussions it became evident that the representativesof Canada, Australia and New Zealand were keenly anxious to find a solution onthe lines of maintaining that Eire and the Commonwealth countries were not&quot; foreign &quot; to one another. They argued strongly that this was fully in accordancewith the facts of the situation. And they were doubtful whether a challenge onmost-favoured-nation grounds was likely to be made at any early date, even inrespect of Eire-United Kingdom trade, since the present conditions of world trade tend so largely to obscure the value of trade preferences. The Eire Mini-ministers, for their part, had made it clear that in the last resort they would beprepared to forego the preferences, from which they expected to derive no materialadvantage for some years to come. They attached more importance to the existing arrangements for the treatment of nationals. This is of some relevance, sincethe treaties which define &quot; foreign countries &quot; as countries which are not partsof the British Commonwealth of Nations (and would therefore be most difficultto handle if we wished to continue to give preferential treatment to Eire persons and goods) are in the main concerned with trade and commerce and not with thetreatment of nationals.It thus became clear to us that, if we persisted in the view that Eire mustbe regarded as a foreign country once the External Relations Act was repealed,we should find ourselves alone in maintaining that view. It was plain that canada, Australia and New Zealand, like Eire, wished to follow the contraryview; and they all felt so strongly on this point that it seemed likely that theymight press it to the point of public disagreement with the United KingdomGovernment. This would have been so serious a development that we thought it-right, without committing ourselves to final agreement, to explore the possibilityof devising legal means of supporting the argument that Eire and the Common-wealth countries would not, despite the repeal of the External Relations Act,become &quot; foreign &quot; to one another.7. We therefore argued that, if the relationship between Eire and other commonwealth countries was to be based on a &quot; reciprocal exchange of citizen-ship rights &quot; the exchange must be fully reciprocal and it must be an exchangeof rights. This was not the position as it existed to-day. British subjects were at present aliens in the contemplation of Eire law, but exempted by Order fromthe restrictions applicable to aliens. This was not enough : there must be an exchange of positive citizenship rights, under which British subjects would beno more aliens in Eire than Eire citizens are aliens in the United Kingdom. the eire Ministers then enquired whether it would be enough if, instead of beinggranted exemption from the provisions of the Aliens Order, British subjectswere given positive rights of citizenship by an Order made under Section 23 (2)of the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Act, 1935. This Section provides asfollows : &quot; Whenever the Executive Council is satisfied that, by virtue of thelaw for the time being in force in any country, citizens of Saorstat Eireannenjoy in such country (either absolutely or subject.to compliance with con-ditions) all or any of the rights and privileges of citizens of such country,the Executive Council may by order declare that citizens of such country shall enjoy in Soarstat Eireann such rights and privileges (similar to thoseso conferred by such law on citizens of Saorstat Eireann in such country) asshall be specified in such order, but subject to compliance with such (if any)conditions (similar to the conditions (if any) imposed by such law) as shallbe specified in such order.&quot;We replied that this, though an improvement on the existing position, wouldnot be enough. For it would still be a concession made by grace and favour of the-tire Government, and similar concessions might be made to countries whichwere clearly &quot; foreign &quot; to the Commonwealth countries. What was neededwas a direct statutory provision conferring positive rights of citizenship in
terms comparable to those of section. 3 of the British Nationality Act, 1948. Inthe end the Eire Minister were persuaded that a truereciprocal exchange of citizenship rights &quot; could only be secured by an amendment of their citizenshiplaw according positive rights of citizenship in Eire, to any Commonwealth country which had enacted legislation on the lines of section 3 of the British nationality act, 1948. They undertook to include such provision in a Bill which they in-tended to introduce in the near future to amend and consolidate their CitizenshipAct. For political reasons, however, they were most anxious to avoid giving any impression that this was being done as part of a bargain struck with other commonwealth Governments; and, although they agreed that their intention tointroduce such legislation should be announced in the course of the debates onthe Bill for the repeal of the External Relations Act, they will probably relatethat announcement to the passing of the British Nationality Act and not tothe constitutional position arising from the repeal of the External Relations Act.8. We finally reached the following understandings which, so far as con-cerned the representatives of the United Kingdom and Eire, were expressed asconditional upon the approval of their respective Governments: (i) In their speeches in the Dail on the Bill for the repeal of the external relations Act, the spokesmen of the Eire Government will be careful to avoidsaying anything which would increase the legal and political difficulties which commonwealth Governments will find in explaining the position which will result from this legislation.(ii) For their part, the Commonwealth Governments will refrain from any public statements which would make it more difficult for them to maintain that,despite the repeal of the External Relations Act, Eire is not a foreign country.In the course of the discussions regret had again been expressed at the effectof the Press conference held on behalf of the United Kingdom Government onthe occasion of the meeting at Chequers on 17th October. This had given theimpression that other Commonwealth Governments were attempting to coercethe Eire Government into abandoning their intention to repeal the external relations Act; and, in addition, it had put interested foreign countries on notice that they might have a claim on most-favoured-nation grounds if, after the repeal of the Act, any of the existing concessions to Eire were continued. If we were now to follow the policy of maintaining that Eire was not &quot; foreign,&quot; it would obviously be undesirable to give any further indication of possible weaknesses inthe legal position which we intended to take up.(iii) When the British Nationality Act, 1948, comes into operation on 1stJanuary, 1949, the Eire Government will make an order under section 23 (2) oftheir Citizenship Act providing that, in view of section 3 of our Act, citizens ofthe United Kingdom and Colonies shall enjoy comparable rights and privilegesin Eire. As and when other Commonwealth countries bring into effect legislationcorresponding to section 3 of the British Nationality Act, 1948, the Eire Govern-ment will extend to them, by orders made under section 23 (2) of their CitizenshipAct, corresponding rights of citizenship.(iv) At a later stage, and possibly within the next six months or so, the eire government will undertake a comprehensive revision of their citizenship law;and they will then take the opportunity of making a direct statutory provisionconferring citizenship rights comparable with those conferred by section 3 ofthe British Nationality Act, 1948, on the citizens of all such commonwealth countries as have enacted legislation corresponding to that section.(v) The intention to take the action summarised in sub-paragraphs (iii) and(iv) above will be announced in the course of the debates on the Bill for the repeal of the External Relations Act.(vi) The Eire Government will collaborate with the United KingdomGovernment, and any other interested Commonwealth Government, in resistingany claims which may be made by foreign countries, on most-favoured-nationgrounds, to share the special privileges which Eire and those countries will con-tinue to accord to one another and to one another&apos;s citizens, whether in matters oftrade or in the treatment of nationals.9. We therefore invite the Cabinet to consider (a) whether a policy on thelines indicated above would be in accordance with our interests and without pre-judice to the maintenance of our relationship with other Commonwealth countries and (b) whether it would provide a sufficiently firm basis for resisting any case
which might be brought against us in the International Court on &quot;most-favoured-nation &quot; grounds. If so, we suggest the following action : (i) An early message should be sent to the Eire Government so that theymay be aware of our agreement well in advance of the date (24th November) onwhich the Second Reading of the Bill for the repeal of the External relations act will be moved in the Dail.(ii) The Eire Government should at the same time be asked to let us knowin advance what language they propose to use in moving the Second reading of this Bill, so that Government spokesmen in the United Kingdom may frame,with knowledge of what is to be said in Dublin, the replies which they give tothe enquiries which are likely to be made in the Parliament at &quot;Westminster.(iii) A full explanation of the policy which the United Kingdom government propose to follow in this matter should also be communicated forthwith to other commonwealth Governments, including the Governments of South Africa, India,Pakistan and Ceylon, which have not been represented in the recent discussions.(iv) It would also be expedient to communicate to the Eire Government,at the earliest convenient date, a detailed statement of the treaty provisions underwhich difficulties might at some stage arise, even though we maintain that despite the repeal of the External Relations Act Eire has not become &quot; foreign &quot; to thecountries of the Commonwealth. This might be accompanied by an invitation to the Eire Government to send one of their legal advisers to this country toconfer with ours on the arguments which the two Governments might jointlyuse to rebut any such claim.J.P. J. N.-B.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,17th November, 1948.
ANNEX ANote of Meeting held at the British Embassy, Paris, on Sunday,14th November, 1948, at 11 a.m.Present:United KingdomThe Right. Hon. Viscount Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.Sir Eric Machtig, commonwealth relations Office.Sir Norman Brook, Cabinet Office.Sir Frank Newsam, Home Office.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite, commonwealth relations Office.Sir    John    Rowlatt,    parliamentary counsel Office.Mr. S. L. Holmes, Board of Trade.Mr. L. S. Brass, Home Office.Mr. F. E. Cumming-Bruce, Common-wealth Relations Office.Mr. B. R. Curson, commonwealth relations Office.canada the Hon. L. B. Pearson, Secretary ofState for External Affairs.Mr. Norman Robertson, High Commis-sioner for Canada in London.Mr. G. Riddell.australia the Right Hon. H. V. Evatt, K.C.,Deputy Prime Minister of Australia.The Right Hon. J. A. Beasley, HighCommissioner for Australia inLondon.New zealand the Right Hon. Peter Fraser, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.Mr. A. D.  Mclntosh,  Secretary for external Affairs.LORD JOWITT welcomed the opportunity to discuss again with theCommonwealth representatives the problems raised by the proposed repeal ofthe Eire External Relations Act. Wide issues were raised, not only of Eire&apos;relations with the Commonwealth, but also indirectly of the future relations of India and possibly other countries. While the issues were to a great extentpolitical, difficult legal problems were also involved, and the United KingdomGovernment had, after the closest examination, been unable to find a solutionof these. It was the legal aspect, therefore, that he wished first to discuss. Asa matter of municipal law, the members of the Commonwealth could accord such treatment to Eire as they wished. The difficulties arose in the sphere of inter-national law. The main difficulties concerned trade preferences and citizenshiprights. Could any intermediate position be devised, between the status of commonwealth membership and foreign status, which would stand up to a judg-ment by the International Court ? In the field of trade preferences, an adversedecision by the Court on an appeal by a foreign State against continuation ofpreferential treatment would have the most serious consequences for the UnitedKingdom tariff and trade relations. On the other hand, use of the argument that Eire was not entirely foreign and entitled to special treatment would belikely to give rise to counter-claims by other States, with repercussions possibly even more serious than the end of preferences. In the case of citizenship rights,it had been hoped in London that some formula might be devised on the basisof reciprocal citizenship rights. The two main rights conferred by citizenshipwere the right of entry into a country and the right to share in its Government.There was no difficulty on either score so far as the United Kingdom itself was concerned, but it was clear that reciprocity under these two heads could not beapplied between all other members of the Commonwealth, e.g., between India andSouth Africa.Mr. NOEL BAKER said there seemed to be no chance of dissuading the eire Government from proceeding with the repeal of the External Relations Act.Nor, it appeared, would they be prepared to make any declaration implyingmembership of the Commonwealth. The United Kingdom Government had been anxious to find a way out, and, at the Chequers meeting on 17th October,
Mr. McGilligan had shown interest in the possibility of a declaration that Eireand the Commonwealth countries did not regard one another as foreign countries.But the Eire note received a few days after the meeting significantly omittedto make any reference to this possibility.There followed a detailed discussion of the difficulties in relation to tradepreferences and nationality.Dr. EVATT then summarised his views. He believed that it might bepossible to find a way round the trade preferences difficulties. He also thoughtthat the possibility of a new link based on nationality should be gone intothoroughly. He felt strongly that the communication of a statement on the linesof the proposed draft note to Dublin would have had a bad effect. He urgedthat, just as every effort should be made to find a means of enabling India toremain in the Commonwealth, so no effort should be spared to facilitate a specialassociation for Eire. It would greatly weaken the position of the Commonwealthif Eire and India were to leave the group. In any case, no precipitate action should be taken. Could not a special arrangement be made with Eire, at anyrate for a limited number of years, on the lines of the arrangements between theUnited States and Cuba and the Philippines ? He agreed that the position wouldbe difficult if in fact the arrangement were challenged before the international court, but he did not, for his part, think that it would be challenged. An excellentatmosphere had been generated at the Chequers meeting. He believed that itwould be possible to translate that friendly spirit into practical arrangementsfor co-operation. He agreed that there was no prospect of withdrawal of the repeal Bill. But the communication of a warning on the lines of the proposedUnited Kingdom note would have introduced a note of bitterness into the Dublinparliamentary proceedings which might prejudice the prospects of a constructiveapproach. He considered that the Eire Government^ action was largely due toconsiderations of domestic Eire politics, &quot; to take the gunman out of Irishpolitics &quot; : it was not directed at the realities of Commonwealth co-operation.He accordingly suggested that an effort should be made to have further talks withthe Eire representatives, preferably before the introduction of the Repeal Bill,but if that was not possible, soon after its introduction.Mr. FRASER said that every effort should be made to maintain the practicalstructure of the Commonwealth and, important as the legal problems were, theyshould not be put into the first place. It was primarily a political question. Theinfluence of the Commonwealth must not be weakened. The Eire Governmenthad acted without due thought or consideration of the difficulties for othersbut he thought it would be a great disaster for the Commonwealth if Eire&apos;s association were terminated. The political effects in New Zealand would bevery serious. He must, therefore, be in a position to tell the New Zealand people that, on the one hand, every effort had been made to avert the contingency, and,on the other, that it was absolutely clear that the consequences were inevitable.He believed that, even if nothing but a temporary arrangement could be made,that would help very much. He therefore urged that every effort should be madeto induce the Eire Government to recognise that they must help to solve theproblem; that the other members of the Commonwealth must err on the side ofminimising the consequences; and that, whatever policy should be agreed in thecase of Eire, India should in any case be enabled to remain within the Common-wealth. The problem must be viewed in a long perspective. For instance, thepresent South African Government had extreme constitutional views. After alapse of, say, ten years, South African opinion might have changed and, if,meanwhile, there was no practical secession from the group, extreme action bySouth Africa might be avoided. Similarly in Eire, public opinion in ten orfifteen years might be less extreme.   The door must not therefore be shut.Mr. PEARSON doubted whether the grant of a special position to Eirewould, in fact, be challenged by foreign countries. If a challenge should be made,the fact of Eire&apos;s association since the introduction of the Eire Constitution in1937 provided us with a powerful case. As to the danger that, if a .specialassociation was established with Eire, groups of foreign countries would claim the right to establish arrangements of reciprocal privilege, there was no realanalogy. In the case of Eire we should only be keeping an existing associationgoing. In the other cases, e.g., South or Central America or the Middle East, itwould be a case of the re-establishment of relations long severed. Whether ornot the advice of the Law Officers of the Crown was correct, he saw no advantage in the publication of such views in advance of foreign questioning.
Mr. ROBERTSON suggested that, as Eire was presumably considering theposition in relation to her own trade, it would be useful to hear how the eire government thought they could meet a challenge on most-favoured-nationgrounds. Secondly, he pointed out that the signatories to the Geneva agreement and Havana Charter had extended benefits to non-signatory countries as an interim measure, but there was no understanding yet as to the ultimate position.Possibly, therefore, the signatory countries would have to reconsider all theirexisting trade treaties with non-signatory countries. The problem of future tradewith Eire might, therefore, be only one part of a larger whole. The Canadianposition was that (i) the Canadian authorities did not believe that the maintenanceof the preferences would, in fact, be challenged; (i) if it should be challenged,they were inclined to think that, on the assumption of a genuine desire of the eire Government to find a solution, some way out could be devised, perhapsbuttressed by nationality arrangements; and (iii) in any case there was no pointin declaring defeat in advance.Mr. FRASER endorsed Mr. Robertson&apos;s views.Discussion turned on the reply which might be made in the United kingdom parliament to the question whether Eire was still a member of the Commonwealthafter the repeal of the External Relations Act. Dr. EVATT suggested that anindirect answer could be given. For instance, if it were stated that Eire was nolonger a member of the Commonwealth, it need not be added that she was nowforeign. It might be said that the position was complex and under theconsideration of the various Commonwealth Governments concerned. It was also suggested that, for the time being, the reply could be on the lines that Common-wealth talks were being held on the subject.Mr. NOEL-BAKER, in reply to Dr. Evatt, explained why it had not provedpracticable to resume Commonwealth talks earlier on the subject. The problem was in some ways linked with that of India, and examination of the latter hadbeen held up as Pandit Nehru&apos;s proposals had not been available in London until recently.LORD JOWITT said that it would be of great assistance if the Canadian,Australian and New Zealand Governments would bring their influence to bear onthe Eire Government to ensure that nothing was said in the early stages of debate in the Dail to make the position more difficult.In reply it was stated that the Canadian, Australian and New zealand governments had not yet answered the Eire Government&apos;s aide-memoire on theproposed Repeal. Dr. EVATT suggested that they should now send an answersupporting the United Kingdom request for postponement of the date ofcommencement of the Act in order to allow full opportunity for discussion of thepractical difficulties to which it would give rise. Mr. PEARSON andMr. FRASER indicated their assent.It was agreed that a message should be sent at once to the Eire Governmenton behalf of the Ministers participating in the meeting. A copy of the messagesent is appended.Appendix to Annex a message from Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations to United kingdom representative in Dublin, dated 14th November, 1948Please deliver the following message immediately to Mr. Costello or mr. MacBride in continuation of our aide-memoire of yesterday : &quot; The Lord Chancellor and the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations have to-day discussed the position further with the Prime Ministerof New Zealand, Deputy Prime Minister of Australia and CanadianSecretary of State for External Affairs. It was the unanimous view of all those present that it would be most desirable if, in continuation of the talks at Chequers on 17th October, further discussions could be held withEire Ministers at the earliest possible date and if possible before theintroduction of the Bill for the repeal of the External Relations Act. Theyearnestly hope that the Eire Government will be willing to join in such discussions with representatives of the Governments of Canada, Australia,New Zealand and the United Kingdom either in Paris, London or Dublin.&quot;
ANNEX note of a Meeting held in the Offices of the Eight Hon. H. V. Evattat the Palais de Chaillot, Paris, on Tuesday, 16th November, 1948,at 11 a.m.Present:United KingdomThe Right. Hon. Viscount Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. P. J, Noel-Baker, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.Sir Norman Brook, Cabinet Office.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite, commonwealth relations Office.Mr. S. L. Holmes, Board of Trade.Mr. F. E. Cumming-Bruce, Conmon-wealth Relations Office.canada the Hon. L. B. Pearson, Secretary ofState for External Affairs.Mr. Norman Robertson, High Commis-sioner for Canada in London.Mr. G. Riddell.australia the Right Hon. H. V. Evatt, K.C.,Deputy Prime Minister of Australia.The Right Hon. J. A. Beasley, HighCommissioner for Australia inLondon.New zealand the Right Hon. Peter Fraser, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.Mr. A. D.  Mclntosh,  Secretary for external Affairs.EireMr.   Sean   MacBride,   Minister   for external Affairs.Mr.   P.   McGilligan,   Minister   for finance.Mr. C. Lavery, Attorney-General.Mr. F. Boland, Secretary, external affairs Department.Mr. FRASER, with the support of others present, criticised the arrangementsmade by the United Kingdom authorities for supplying information to the Pressabout the meeting at Chequers on 17th October. He requested that no press conference should be organised in connection with the present series of meetings with Eire representatives.It was agreed not to hold Press conferences for this series of meetings.LORD JOWITT said that relations between the United Kingdom and Eirewere better than at any previous time.  These countries were in a special positionas two of the parent countries of the Commonwealth.   The United KingdomGovernment, for their part, wished to find a link that might make their mutualrelationship closer than that between any two foreign countries.  Their approach was not, therefore, legalistic.  But facts must be faced.   The present relationshipwas defined by section 3 of the Eire External Relations Act of 1936.   This hadbeen followed in 1937 by the new Eire constitution, which described the country as a sovereign, independent, democratic State.   While the result was open toargument, the fact that Eire diplomatic representatives were accredited by TheKing afforded an argument, good or bad, that Eire was within the Commonwealth,for this link did not apply to foreign States.   Now Eire intended to pass aBill repealing that Act, by which Eire would be described as a republic, andits President empowered to act in its external affairs.  Whatever the effects in the municipal law of Commonwealth countries, there were far-reaching repercussions in international law, which arose urgently in the field of the treaty obligations of Commonwealth countries, principally in regard to the treatment of nationals,but also in relation to trade preferences.   While the latter might not be of greatpractical importance to Eire to-day, they might be of great significance in thelong term.   He read out a statement illustrating the United Kingdom treaty obligations (Appendix I). A cogent instance was the recent treaty with Denmark.A practical question that the United Kingdom Government wished, therefore,to ask was whether the Eire Government could propose some form of constitutionallink which could be used in argument to justify discrimination against foreigncountries, e.g., Denmark,
Mr. MacBRIDE said that it was the sincere desire of the Eire Governmentto maintain the closest and friendliest relations with both Britain and other commonwealth countries. There were two reasons for the repeal of the external relations Act. First, it was a flimsy, dishonest and, indeed, derisory instrumentwhich could not be defended on its merits. Secondly, the Eire Governmentbelieved that relations would be built up on a more friendly and constructivebasis of co-operation if the realities of history were recognised and an entirelyfresh start were made on a footing of frank independence. The link with theCrown constituted one of the two remaining principal points of friction. Itshould, therefore, be removed. The other issue was, of course, partition. the eire Government thought that this also should be discussed, and thought itunfortunate that it had not been discussed in the last quarter of a century.But he did not propose that the issue should be raised to-day. As regardsLord JowittVproposals for a new constitutional link, the Eire Government wouldnot wish to remove one objectionable link only to erect another which mightbe a source of friction in the future. On the other hand, they certainly desiredto maintain the present relationships, for instance in the field of trade andnationality. He believed that all the Governments represented at the talks shared the latter wish. Could not agreement be reached on a method of fulfilling thisdesire, taking into account the fact that the Eire Government had irrevocablydecided to repeal the External Relations Act? He urged that all the Common-wealth countries concerned should bend their efforts to build up a case in favourof continuing the grant of reciprocal rights and should refrain from any actionliable to encourage foreign States to hope for a change in the present position.In the view of the Eire Government, Eire had been outside the Commonwealthsince 1937. Eire had, therefore, acquired a strong prescriptive right to continua-tion of the present treatment. Moreover, he did not believe that in fact anyserious challenge would be made. If it was, the Eire Government for their part were confident that they could continue to maintain trade preferences. Thedevelopment of countries from colonial status to full Commonwealth status hadnot prompted claims from foreigners. Why should they make such claims now ?He suggested that the legal position should be discussed in detail on a lateroccasion by exchange of Notes or talks between the Eire Attorney-General andthe Law Officers of the Crown, but meanwhile he wished to draw attentionto two points. First, the Havana Charter and the Geneva Trade and TariffsAgreement adopted in their classifications of States certain groupings referring to countries geographically, or alternatively used a principle of grouping notbased exclusively on common sovereignty. Secondly, the special position of burma was recognised in these instruments. He realised that neverthelessdifficulties might conceivably be met, e.g., with the Argentine. Let commonwealth countries therefore agree to co-operate in resisting any such claims if andwhen they arose. In the meantime, let all agree to maintain the existing tradeand citizenship rights.Mr. FRASER said that, while he had much sympathy with Mr. MacBride&apos;spoint of view, Mr. MacBride was underestimating the difficulties not only forthe United Kingdom but also for other Commonwealth countries. The great interest aroused by the Eire Government&apos;s decision to repeal was illustrated by the reference to the subject in Mr. Churchill&apos;s latest speech. He realised that public opinion in Eire had difficulty in getting away from the past. The fact remained that Commonwealth countries enjoyed a status fully as independentas foreign States, and there were serious issues at stake. It would be a majordisaster if the influence of the Commonwealth in the world were weakened atthe present critical time, and the termination of Eire&apos;s special constitutional asso-ciation with the Commonwealth would be seized On by our enemies and shakethe confidence of our friends in the stability of the group. Difficult political problems faced the New Zealand and other Commonwealth Governments withtheir respective peoples. They would be charged with being parties to the severingof the last link. Again, there was a widespread hope in New Zealand thatthe problem of partition might ultimately be solved and it would be thoughtthat the present step removed any prospect of a solution by agreement. TheUnited Kingdom Government were in a specially difficult position. Some people would be liable to interpret any inevitable consequential steps taken by them as retaliation. Such allegations might give rise to bitterness, and prejudicefriendly relations. He therefore urged that the commencement of the Act shouldbe postponed for as long as possible in order to enable full inter-governmentaldiscussion.   He, for his part, would be prepared to help in any &quot;way that he
could, for instance by visiting Eire to see Mr. de Valera to enlist his co-operation in a constructive approach. He suggested that Mr. Pearson and Dr. Evatt mightbe prepared to be associated with- such an approach. For it seemed essentialthat there should be no competition between the political parties in Eire madvocating a completely foreign relationship.Mr MacBRIDE assured Mr. Eraser that no spokesman of the Eire Govern^ment would say anything in the Dail to exacerbate relations with commonwealth countries.Dr EVATT said that Australia was deeply concerned on account of the large population of Irish descent. Many mistakes had been made in the past. Hethought the use of the term Eire was such a mistake. In the English languagethe term Ireland should be used. He understood from Mr. MacBnde that the eire Government did not regard the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia andNew Zealand as foreign countries. He therefore proposed that they should make their attitude clear by a statement in the Dail which might be used in support ofthe case against any claims from foreign States. He circulated a draft declaration(Appendix II). This deliberately avoided reference to commonwealth membership.Mr. MacBRIDE said that Dr. Evatt&apos;s draft statement seemed to him to be quite acceptable subject to one or two minor alterations; for instance, under the eire Constitution the right to vote was confined to citizens of Eire.LORD JOWITT confirmed that, so far as the United Kingdom was con-cerned, Eire citizens already enjoyed the same rights of entry and employment, &amp;c.as British subjects coming from other parts of the Commonwealth. He liked theidea of a draft statement on the lines proposed by Dr. Evatt, which deservedcareful consideration. But it did not solve the problem. It was necessary to have some legal facade in substitution for the External Relations Act to enable theUnited Kingdom to refrain from treating Eire citizens as aliens after repeal.Mr. NOEL-BAKER referred to the difficulties that the United KingdomGovernment would face in Parliament. It was very questionable whether Paiiia-ment would have passed the Eire provisions of the British Nationality Act oraccepted the recent Eire Trade Agreement except in the knowledge that Eire wasnot foreign.Mr. PEARSON was attracted by Dr. Evatt&apos;s draft statement. He hopedthat it might be strengthened. He said that he did not contemplate any serious difficulty in gaining Parliamentary acceptance in Canada for the continuation of the rights at present enjoyed by Eire trade and citizens. He believed that thefact of Eire&apos;s neutrality in the war and the flimsiness of Eire&apos;s link with theCrown since 1936 created a strong prescriptive right for continuation. Moreover,he doubted whether there would be any serious challenge. On the trade aspect, thecountries most interested were the Argentine and Denmark. He questioned whether the Argentine, in the light of her attitude to the Geneva Agreement,would take the initiative and it seemed that Denmark could be influenced to refrain, on grounds of Western solidarity, from making any challenge in thepresent situation. But it was essential that repeal should be so handled so as notto allow relations between Eire and other Commonwealth countries to deteriorate.It was possible that repeal might be the starting-point for the creation of strongerand more friendly relations; the difficulties might be converted into an oppor-tunity. But he emphasised that no Government should take any step after theintroduction of the Bill that might enlarge the significance of the repeal in the eyes of world public opinion.LORD JOWITT reverted to the legal difficulty. If the United KingdomGovernment were to be asked to break, say, the Danish Treaty, there must be morejustification than Dr. Evatt&apos;s draft afforded to create a legal ease. Could not the hire Government undertake to amend their nationality legislation so that Britishsubjects should no longer be legally aliens in Eire ?Mr. NOEL-BAKER asked what reply could be given in Parliament to thequestion :   Is Eire a member of the Commonwealth I&quot;Mr. MacBRIDE said that Eire was not a. member of the CommonwealthHe suggested that the reply could be that the United Kingdom Government did36158 c 2
not consider that repeal of the External Relations Act made any change in thefactual position of relations between Eire and the United kingdom mr. NOEL-BAKER said that it was not open to the Commonwealth Govern-ments to use this argument, since they had declared in 1937, that it could be saidthat on the basis of the External Relations Act, that the new Eire constitutionhad not affected her membership of the Commonwealth.It was agreed to continue the discussion later in the dayAppendix I to Annex note on Commercial TreatiesFull United Kingdom Commercial Treaties (covering persons and goods)have regularly been in the Head of States form and there are some thirty such documents in force to-day. (It happens that those now in force were negotiatedprior to 1932.) The normal operative clauses in respect of persons and goods aretypified by the following extracts from the United Kingdom-Greece Treatyof 1926:-Persons and ShipsArticle 2. The subject or citizens of either of the two contractingparties shall be entitled to enter, travel and reside in the territories of theother so long as they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulationsapplicable to the entry, travelling and residence of all foreigners.Article 4. The two Contracting parties agree that in all matters, re-lating to commerce, navigation and industry, and the exercise of professionsor occupations, any privilege, favour or immunity which either of the twocontracting parties has actually granted, or may hereafter grant, to the ships and subjects or citizens of any other foreign country shall fog extendedsimultaneously and unconditionally, without request and withont compensa-tion, to the ships and subjects or citizens of the other, it being their intention that the commerce, navigation and industry of each of the two contractingparties shall be placed in all respects on the footing of the most favoured nation.GoodsArticle 7. Articles produced or manufactured in the territories of oneof the two contracting parties, imported into the territories of the other, from whatever place arriving, shall not be subjected to other or higher duties or charges than those paid on the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. Nor shall any prohibition or restric-tion be maintained or imposed on the importation of any article, pro-duced or manufactured in the territories of either of the two contractingparties, into the territories of the other, from whatever place arriving, whichshall not equally extend to the importation of the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country.There is no definition of &quot;foreign country &quot; in such Treaties, but the factthat they are in the Heads of States form (the &quot; Contracting Parties&quot; beingdefined in the Preamble as His Majesty the King and the President of the Hellenic-Republic respectively) together with the antithesis between, e.g., &quot; territories ofone of the two Contracting Parties&quot; and &quot; any ,other fovaign country&quot; inArticle 7 (quoted above), and the terms of Articles mentioning parts of theCommonwealth other than the United Kingdom, are evidence that &quot; foreign &quot; isto be read as meaning &quot; not part of His MajestyY dominions.&quot; Thus Article 30runs as follows : &quot; The stipulations of the present treaty shall not be applicable to Indiaor to any of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s self-governing Dominions, colonies,possessions, or protectorates, unless notice is given by His Britannic Majesty thatthe said stipulations shall apply to any such territory.&quot;
Some of the more important treaties in force and in this form, with provisions in respect of goods similar to those quoted above, are those with : Argentina (1825) ,Hungary (1926)Poland (1923)Portugal (1914)Roumania (1930)Spain (1922 as amended 1927)Switzerland (1855)Turkey (1930)Yugoslavia (1927)None of the above countries are signatories of the Geneva General Agree-ment on Tariffs and Trade.&quot;Most-favoured-nation&quot; agreements concluded by the United Kingdomsince 1932 and still in force happen to be all &quot; trade agreements &quot; dealing only with goods and not with persons, shipping, &amp;c. Their stipulations generallyapply, on our side, only to the United Kingdom; thus for pure convenience theywere cast in inter-governmental and not Heads of States form. In 1937, however,we made a Heads of States Treaty with Siam, but this has lapsed through the war.In the trade agreements concluded since 1932, the operative clauses in respect ofthe treatment of goods (there are none relating to persons or ships) vary in detail,hut the following is an extract from Article 7 of the United Kingdom-DanishCommercial Agreement of 1933 :-&quot; The Contracting Governments agree that, having regard to theprovisions of the above-mentioned treaties of 1660-1 and 1670, UnitedKingdom goods in Denmark and Danish goods in the United kingdom shall enjoy in all respects treatment not less favourable than that enjoyed by goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country.&quot;In an exchange of notes between the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs and the Danish Minister printed with the Agreement, the following passageoccurs : &quot; The expression &apos; foreign country &apos; in relation to the United Kingdommeans a country not being a part of the British Commonwealth of Nationsnor a territory under British protection or suzerainty, nor a mandated territory in respect of which the mandate is exercised by the Government of apart of the British Commonwealth of Nations, and the expression &apos; foreignimports &apos; means imports from foreign countries as so defined.&quot;Other treaties in the governmental form and still in force are those withIceland (1933) and Sweden (1933).(Not all the trade agreements contain general m.f.n. provisions, and in one at least which does contain such provisions Cuba, 1937 &quot; foreign country &quot;is defined in relation to the United Kingdom as &quot; a country not being a territory under the sovereignty, suzerainty, protection or mandate&apos; of His Majesty TheKing&quot; while the Trade Agreement of 1934 with the Soviet Union stipulatedin Article 7 &quot; nothing in this Agreement shall entitle the U.S.S.R, to claim thebenefit of any treatment, preference or privilege which may at any time be in forceexclusively between territories under the sovereignty of His Majesty The Kingor under His Majesty&apos;s. suzerainty, protection or mandate.&quot; A similar provision is made in. Article 2 of the Trade Agreement with Uruguay (1935).)Appendix II to Annex draft DeclarationFrom the point of view of Ireland, the factual relationship between it andthe United Kingdom, Canada, Australia and New Zealand is clear. Ireland doesnot, and, when the External Relations Act, 1936, is repealed will not, regard theUnited Kingdom, Canada, Australia or New Zealand as &quot;foreign &quot; countries
or treat their peoples as &quot; foreigners.&quot; On the contrary, the fact is that the citizens of Ireland, while resident in the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia or new Zealand, are treated by law or practice not as &quot; foreigners &apos;&apos; or aliens butas entitled to the rights and privileges of nationals or citizens of those nations.Similarly, while in Ireland, the nationals or citizens of the United Kingdom,Canada, Australia or New Zealand are treated not as foreigners or aliens butas entitled to the rights and privileges of citizens of Ireland. These facts notonly negative the view that Ireland and the United Kingdom, Canada, Australiaand New Zealand are to be regarded as &quot; foreign &quot; countries; but they alsoevidence the fact of a special association which it is the firm desire and intentionof Ireland to maintain and strengthen.
ANNEX CNote of a Meeting held in the Offices of the Right Hon. H. V. Evattat the Palais de Chaillot, Paris, on Tuesday, 16th November, 1948,at 5 p.m.Present:United KingdomThe Right. Hon. Viscount Jowitt, Lord-Chancellor.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.Sir Norman Brook, Cabinet Office.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite, commonwealth relations Office.Mr. S. L. Holmes, Board of Trade.Mr. F. E. Cumming-Bruce, Common-wealth Relations Office.canada the Hon. L. B. Pearson, Secretary ofState for External Affairs.Mr. Norman Robertson, High Commis-sioner for Canada in London.australia the Right Hon. H. V. Evatt, K.C.,Deputy Prime Minister of Australia.The Right Hon. J. A. Beasley, HighCommissioner for Australia inLondon.New zealand the Right Hon. Peter Fraser, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.Mr. A. D. Mclntosh, Secretary for external Affairs.EireMr. Sean MacBride, Minister for external Affairs.Mr. P. McGilligan, Minister for finance.Mr. C. Lavery, Attorney-General.Mr. F. . Boland, Secretary, external affairs Department.LORD JOWITT referred to the draft statement circulated by Dr. Evatt(Appendix II to Annex B). He said that the interest of the Union of SouthAfrica, India, Pakistan and Ceyion in Commonwealth constitutional changesmust be taken into account. The draft statement referred only to the UnitedKingdom, Canada, Australia and New Zealand as not being &quot;foreign &quot; in the eyes of Eire. Would the Eire Government agree to extend the statement to theother Commonwealth countries ?Mr. MacBRIDE said that the South African Government had already inti-mated to the Eire Government that the repeal of the External Relations Act wouldmake no difference to the relationship between the two countries. As to the newDominions, he quoted the aide-memoire of 20th October, sent after the Chequersmeeting of the Commonwealth Governments represented there. They proposedto address a similar note to the new Dominions after agreement had been reached as a result of the current talks.Discussion then turned to the question whether Eire would amend hernationality law to bring it into line with the British Nationality Act and other similar Commonwealth enactments, so as to grant reciprocal citizenship rights.Lord Jowitt, supported by Dr. Evatt and Mr. Fraser, urged that an amendingAct should be introduced. The issue of exemption orders under the Eire aliens act would not suffice to rectify the legal position for external purposes.Mr. MacBRIDE expressed the personal view that such an amendment should be made. But he emphasised that he could not commit his Government.The timing of such legislation would require careful thought, as it would be mostharmful if the amendment were thought to be part of a bargain made with theCommonwealth Governments.Mr. McGILLIGAN said that, if necessary, the practical rights could be created by specific orders for each Commonwealth country under section 23 (2)of the Citizenship Act. A comprehensive amendment of the Nationality Actcould then be made at a later stage.
Mr. FRASER requested that such an announcement should be made on thesecond reading of the Repeal Bill, and Lord Jowitt emphasised that other commonwealth countries must be in a position to say that their citizens werenot aliens under Eire law : it was not enough to say that they were not be ingtreated as aliens.Mr. MacBRIDE finally said that he thought that the Eire Governmentwould agree to introduce amending legislation and would so arrange action bytemporary orders under section 23 (2) of the Citizenship Act, to ensure that thenecessary rights were accorded without any time interval after the coming intooperation of corresponding legislation in Commonwealth countries.Dr. EVATT expressed the view that grant of citizenship rights in thisway would constitute a group relationship of a special and definite characterof significance for international law.In conclusion it was agreed that the discussion should be recorded as strictlysecret, that the Ministers of the various countries represented at the meetingswould have to seek the views of their Government on the proposals made,and that no information should be given to the Press except that contained in the agreed communique.


</content>
</cab>
