<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/31/0 images: 41-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic ma]esty&apos;s government       28The  circulation  of this  paper has been  strictly limited.     aIt is issued for the personal use of.TOP SECRET Copy No.    IS.Q,.P..(48)  27618TH NOVEMBER.  1948CABINETNATIONAL service memorandum by; the Minister of DefenceArising out of the discussion in Cabinet today I am circulating herewith copies of two reports dealing with the size of the Armed Forces over the next three years and the adjustments of the present National Service legislation which may be entailed.The first of these (Annex A) is a report by the Chiefsof Staff submitted to the&apos;Standing Committee of service ministers on&apos;19th October, and the second (Annex B) is areport by a Working Party, under the Chairmanship of thePermanent Secretary of the Ministry of Defence, reviewing the provisions of the National Service Act.2.     It will be observed from the Chiefs of Staff reportthat they take the view that a period of not loss than twoyears1 National Service would be essential if the armed forces are to improve on their present grave state ofunpreparedness to fight.    Recognising, however, that adoubling of the period of whole time service would be politically and economically unacceptable, they considerthat an extension of the period of National Service from 12months to 18 months to be effective for a period of at least three years from 1st January next has fewest disadvantages.It does, however, entail the running of risks, many of whichmay well be serious and which, in so far as they affect theArmy, are set out in some detail in Appendix II to theChiefs of Staff report.3.      The Working Party report (Annex B) on the NationalService Act is the outcome of a further examination, under-taken following some preliminary consideration of the matteramong the Ministers most immediately affected, of how the product of the National Service Act, on the basis of an 18month period of service, could be adjusted to the manpowerrequirements of the three Services having regard to theprobable ceilings which economic considerations would impose.
4,      The situation in which the Armed. Forces find themselves at the present moment arises largely from the lack of anyrecruiting of regulars in the case of the Army and the AirForce during the-war period, and the rapid run down of skilled&quot; men which has taken place as the regulars and men with war-time experience have been demobilised,&apos; the resulting state of unbalance &quot;was, from the point of view ofthe Services,, most undesirable but had to be accepted in thenational interest.    The position was* however, very muchworsened by the acceleration of the rate of run down which followed from the decisions which the Government had to takeduring the economic crisis in the Summer of 1947,    Moreover,the progressive liquidation of our overseas commitments which was expected when we made our plans for National service has not been realised as fully or as rapidly as any of usthen hoped and in some respects those commitments have been increased.    As the Cabinet are aware, when the tension over berlin became acute, the deficiencies in the Services were so serious that it was necessary to take certain specialemergency measures to strengthen the Armed Forces.    (See thePrime Minister&apos;o memorandum CP. (48) 206 and the discussion in Cabinet on 26th August, 1948),5.      One of the decisions taken last August was to suspendreleases from the Armed Forces for a period of three months.The three months&apos; period will expire on 14th December and,with the provisions of the National Service Act, 1947 (nowconsolidated into the National Service Act, 1948) coming intoeffect on 1st January following, it is a matter of urgent necessity that we take decisions on the future period ofservice for men called up under that Act which will, in turn,bear on the arrangements to be made for the release of men now serving, who were called up under the earlier war-timeprovisions,6.      Our. present situation is very different from that whichthe Government faced in May 1947 when wo decided, under the pressure in parliament, that wo were prepared to accept aperiod of 12 months&apos; National Service in lieu of the 18months&apos; period, which was specified in the Bill as introduced.There is an urgent need for men with the necessary degree oftraining to maintain our overseas and other commitments.With a period of 12 months&apos;  service the National Service man,even &quot;in. the case of the Army, cannot, at the most, give morethan six months effective service.    In the case of the AirForce, the period is even shorter.    It.is essential toinclude National Servicemen in the wider manning of our overseas posts and this can only be done on a longer periodof service than 12 months.&apos;7.     A number of alternative suggestions have been considered.The call-up of a larger number of men would be no help:    thetraining establishments would have to be increased and men would not be available for a sufficient period of effectiveoverseas service.    The possibility of combining long and short periods of National Service has also been considered,but, although this would enable a larger number of national servicemen to be passed through the Services, it would not produce as much &quot;effective&quot; service.
8.      The conslusion which I must now place before mycolleagues and to which I invite their assent is that thepresent difficulties can only be overcome by the adoption ofthe following measures(1) to increase the period of National Service to 18months in order to preserve minimum efficiency in the Forces and to meet commitments over thenext two or three years.&apos;(2)    as a set-off to the increase in the period of whole-time service, to reduce the period of reserve liability -from six to four years.    Theliability for training during this period would remain unchanged at a total of 60 days.&apos;(3)    to control the annual intake, which under theseproposals will exceed the capacity of the forces to accept them, by; -(a) slightly raising the general standard of menaccepted in the Forces;    and(b) by deferring registrations from time to time  -as has already been done once in 1948.&apos;(c.f. Conclusion (2) of the DefenceCommittee minutes of 14th January, 1948.(D,0.(48) 3rd Meeting)).    This deferment ofregistrations will cause a gradual raisingin the age of call-up to between 18 years9 months and 19 years 6 months in 1952.The precise age depends on the extent towhich it proves necessary to reduce theavailable intake..9.     I accordingly invite my colleagues to agree:-(a) that the legislation necessary to give effect tothese decisions should be introduced at once and passed through all its stages before Christmas.In view of the time factor this Bill will be confined in the.main to the above essentialsbut the opportunity will be taken to include some minor details,(b) that, though the Bill will provide that the ISmonths period is a maximum which the government can at discretion reduce by Order in Council, a directive should be issued to the service departments making it clear that, unless thereis some striking change in the international situation, the 18 months period will be retained for the next three years.    This Directive, whichwill be essential for planning purposes, willnot, of course, be published.&apos;A.V.A.18TH NOVEMBER,  1948*
(2/6/48) (B116) Wt. 19954. D98. 60m. 8/48. P. &amp; N. Ltd. G813.this document is the property of his britannic majestvs government/ The  circulation  of this paper has been  strictly limited. &quot;31It is issued for the personal use of......................................................................TOP SECRET Copy No.ANNEX   A Also o.Q;a.r,(4p),,125)i233L0C T0BSRA-1948 .standirid &quot;committee&quot; ftp ;SHJRVfaft!ministers^ZE^^THE^ARMED^ORCES OVER THE NEXT THREE YEARSReport by the Chiefs of staff the Cabinet at their meeting^ on the 26th August set up a working Party to carry out a comprehensive review of theprovisions of the National Service Act, 1948, in order to enablethe manpower needs of the Services to bo met more effectively.The Terms of Reference of this Working Party are attached^.The following survey of the problem, which includes much of themateriel prepared by the Working Party, covers the calendaryears 1949, 1950 and 1951.    Three years seems the longest periodthat is worth considering in this respect, and 1951 is,also asfar *as wo can usefully look in making estimates of voriahlcssuch as regular recruitment.    On the other hand we must be ableto plan ahead for at least this period.2.      The manpower problem of the Services is primarily the lackof trained men to meet current commitments.    The main original purpose of National Service was to build up a reserve of trained men who would be available in the event of war.    But in the changed circumstances of the last 18 months the National Serviceman has become more &quot;and more ..g..su^stituto for /the Regular entrant^This position will continue until such time ns the Services /S^fmeet their current commitments, as conditioned by tno needs of thecountry, wholly or largely &quot;by regular recruitment.3.     In the present situation each Service would, within obviouslimits, get the &quot;best value out of National Service men if itwere given the minimum number of men to serve for the maximum period in short, a form of compulsory regular recruitment. . Thetime and money spent on training,  and the limited use to whicha man can be put in the early part of his Service, account forthe Service&apos;s preference for the slowest possible turnover of manpower....$ CM. (48) 57th Conclusions/ Appendix III
4. There ere three main limitations on the numbers acceptablewhich operate to a different extent in the three Services:(a) The training organisation can only abosrb a certainannual intake, and to increase the size of this organisation in order to absorb a larger intakemerely sends up the total manpower requirement (this applies to all Services, but in the R.A.F.  its effect is in practice overshadowed by (c)).(b) A short period of National Service imposes a restriction on the overseas posting of NationalService man.(c) The Services&apos;  requirements of N.O.Os.  and experiencedmen can only bu met to a small extent by NationalService men, and the extent to which &apos;dilution&apos; by national Service men can take place depends on theperiod of National Service.    In particular, NationalService men arc for- the most part unsuitable for thehigher trades, although this will improve whendeferred apprentices begin to be called up in larger numbers-from 1950 onwards;    but there too the periodof National Service men has an important bearing onthe degree of dilution that can be accepted.5.      In order to meet current and foreseeable commitments overthe next few years,  the three Services require a total strengthof between 815,000 and 830,000 men and women.    (See Appendix I,Table I.)    This wo consider to be the minimum after all possible economies have boon made and all acceptable risks taken.It is estimated that the recent decision to retain NationalService men for an additional period of throe months will resultin a total strength of about 820,000 at 1st January,  1949, ofwhom about 375,000 will be National Service men.    If the periodof full time National Service served by those entering after this date is 12 months,  all the 375,000 must be released during1949.    Assuming an intake of 150,000 National Se:.vice men andthe continuation of regular recruiting at the present somewhatunsatisfactory rate throughout the next year,  the total strengthof the forces on 1st January 1950 will be- about 615,000 (SeeAppendix I, Table 2).    Thus, not only would there be onunprecedented turn-over of personnel during the year, but at theend of it the forces would be left some 200,000 men short oftheir estimated requirements.    Prom this it will be seen that,apart from the other disadvantages of a term of National Serviceof 12 months,  the effect of its introduction next January wouldbe militarily catastrophic.6.      We have been asked by the Minister of Defence to examinethree other possible courses of action, namely:-(a) an increase in the period of full    time NationalService to 15 months;(b) a similar increase to 18 months;  and(c) the postponement of the introduction of the 1948National&quot;Service Act for a period of one or twoyears,  or indefinitely.
Increase in Period of Full-timo National Service to 15 months7.      This course retains most of the defence of the proposedterm of service of 12 months without going any substantialdistance towards meeting the total manpower requirement - itwould make it impossible for the Army to accept a higherNotional Service intake than 110,000 even if preseir^ovurscascommitments are considerable reduced and would leave the Armysome 76,000 short.of requirements on 1st January, 1950, some100,000 short on 1st April,   1950,  and shorter still thereafter. -(See Appendix I,  Table h.)    The first six months of NationalService are spent in basic training.    Nine months of usefulservice is insufficient to justify sending the man to overseastheatres further afield than Europe,  or to give him soa service in the Royal Navy.    Finally, it gives no time to turn the maninto a skilled tradesman or to get much vise from him as ajunior instructor, which is an important consideration.    (Seeparagraph 2.)This course does not therefore offer a solution to theproblem.Increase in Period of Full-time Rational Service to 16 months8*      This is the absolute minimum that would meet the needs ofthe Navy and Air Force, provided some further reduction in theirstate of preparedness for war is accepted.    It would enable theServices to send National Service men to all theatres overseas,expect perhaps the Far East,  and would produce an increasedfeeling of stability within the- Forces.    It would, however,leave the Army some 50,000 men short of requirements - nothingless than a period of two years&apos; National Service will enablethe Army to moot its estimated commitments.    (See Appendix I,Table 5.)    This course would also mean that the first NationalService men will not enter the Territorial Army until July,  1950,instead of in January, 1950.  as at present anticipated.    Thisdelay would have unfortunate effects on Territorial Armyrecruiting unless the gap could bo filled by imposing an obligation of,  say 2 years Territorial Service on all short termmen now in the Forces.9.      If it were decided to adopt this course,  the War Officeestimate that the effects on&apos;the Army would bo generally asfollows:-(a) The garrisons in Germany, the Middle East and Far Eastmust bo considerable reduced.    This will involve serious risks.(b) There must be a general slowing up of administrative services both at homo and abroad involving virtualcessation in the improvement of amenities.    Withoutfurther examination there can be no guarantee that theproposed cuts in administrative services are in factworkable,  especially overseas.    Aftermath tasks in theU.K.  will cease unless civilian labour is forthcoming.(c) The state of efficiency of the training machine willdrop.    If civilian labour is not forthcoming it willbreak down.    This would have a serious effect on the morale of the National Service man,  the state oftraining of the Army,  and the recruiting of theregular soldier.
(a)    Many vital measures to improve the state of- readiness of the Army will have to be broughtto a standstill,(e)    Assistance to the Territorial Army will notbe sufficient to maintain the training and morale of the Territorial Army at.the pitchrequired.A more detailed War Office statement is attached(Appendix II).Postponement of the Introduction of the 1947/48 Act for aPeriod of Years10.    The main objection to this course is that it doesnothing to remove the present instability of the Services andthe serious psychological effect of this instability.    Anotherserious disadvantage would be the effect on the TerritorialArmy.If the introduction of the Act is postponed a year,  theterra of service introduced in January 1950 would still have&quot;do be at least 18 months if the catastrophic effects of a drastic run-down during 1950 (as mentioned in paragraph 5above) arc to be avoided.    This would mean that the firstNational Service men would not enter the Territorial Armyuntil July 1951*.   This delay vrould have most seriouspsychological effects on the Territorial Army as a wholeunless, in addition to their 18 months to 2 years whole time service, a 2/3 year obligation for Territorial Service is imposed on all men called up after 1st January 1947 under thepresent emergency legislation.A postponement of the Act for two years or more (orfor the duration of the emergency) would do little to promotestability and nothing to ease the present manpower planningdifficulties.     It would still further delay the build-up ofthe Territorial Army.11.    For the above reasons we consider that a postponement ofthe introduction of the Act is most undesirable.CONCLUSIONS12.    Our estimated manpower requirement over the next threeyears for all three Services is between 815,000 and 830,000.The needs of the Army cannot bo met with less than a periodof two years&apos; whole-time National Service beginning on1st January 194-9*    The numbers in. the Forces on the basis oftwo years&apos; service arc given in Appendix I Table 6.    Moreovera period of not less than two years&apos; National Service isessential if the Armed. Forces are to improve on their presentgrave state of unpreparedness to fight, a condition largely dueto lack of trained manpower,13*     If we are to assume that two years&apos; National Service is outof the question, we consider that,  of the courses of actionexamined above,  an ,extension of the period of National service from 12 months to 18 months,  to be effective for at least a3 year period from 1st January 1949* has fewest disadvantages.On the assumption that Regular recruiting continues as on recent trends and the annual intake of National Service men is approximately Navy 10,000, Army 130,000, R. A. F.  35,000(approximately), with.a total of 175,000,  it will result in the
scaling down of manpower figures to the following totals:-1 Jan.  50Navy 11+5,000Army 395,000R.A.F,  &apos; 206,000746,00014-    If it is decided to adopt this course (18 months&apos; whole-time National Service) and to accept the effects outlined inparagraphs 8-9 above,  the numbers in the Forces as set out at the end of paragraph 13 above will fall considerably belowthe manpower requirements given in Appendix I, Table 1.    Tothe extent to which an improvement in present rates of Regularrecruiting,  or other measures, enables this gap to bo bridged,we recommend that the resulting higher figures should beaccepted.    In Appendix I, Table 7,  is given&apos; an estimate of thenumbers available for call-up in 1949, 1950 and 1951.15.    Any increase in the term of whole-time service of 12 months,or any delay in introducing the Act, will postpone the entry ofthe first National Service men into the Territorial Army, due atpresent to begin on 1st January,  1951.    This delay will havomost serious psychological effects on the Territorial Army as awhole unless,  in addition to their 18 months to 2 years whole-time service, a 2-3 year obligation for Territorial Service is imposed on all men called up after 1st January, 1947, under thepresent emergency legislation.(Signed) MONTGOMERY OF ALAMEIN..   .. TEDDER,ERASER OF NORTH GAPE.l-..Jafl* .51149,000381,000183,000713,0001 Jan.  52152,000381,000176,000709,000MINISTRY OF DEFENCE, S.W.I.19TH OCTOBER,  1948.
Royal Navy:Army:APPENDIX ,1Total160,600-  1+43,000R.A.F.:(1) National Serviceof 1 year 2 25,000(2) National Serviceof 18 months 218,000(3) National Serviceof 2 years 213,000TOTAL (1 year)        828,600(18 months)    821,600(2 years)      816,600Limitationsof whom 135,000 must he regularmales;  intake of not more than10,000 National Service men ayear.including 12,000 women;  intake of not more than 130,000National Service men a year.of whom not more than 61,000 may&quot;do National Service men.of whom not more than 68,000 mayho National Service men.of whom&apos;not more than 71,000 mayhe National Service men.ible 2.PRESENT PROSPECTSAssumptions:      (1)    regular recruiting at present rate.(2)    reduction to National Service of1 year by the end of 1949.housands/	Estimate a		t 1/1/49         i		Estimate a		t I7I750		Regular	N.S.	r Women	Total 1	Regular	N.S.	rWomen	TotalSavy	119	:   19	8	146	123	10	8	141[Army	177	241	12	430	192	100	11	303;R . A . P .	114	114	15	243	120	38	13	171TOTAL	410	374	35	:   819 -	435	148	32	615L    __,	-----	----	,   1					
^Figures inI thousands?NavyArmyR.A.F.TOTAL171759&apos;Regular119177114410Women8121535171/50Regular123192120435Women8111332Regular[Women1261851171+28o131334;i/3752:Regular129179111419^Women8191542-f The reduction in regular strength is due to the fact that in1950 and later there will he a heayy outflow of regulars,including many on short Service engagements.EFFECT OH ALTERNATIVE MEASURESTABLSJ+.    ASSUMPTIONS(a) National Service 15^ months.(b) Regular recruitment at present rates.(c) Intake of N.S. men the maximum acceptable by the Services(in the case of the Army the number given will not be practicable unless some overseas commitments arc reduced in1949).(d) Rundown on the basis of 2 years&apos;  service for those enteredon or before 1st July,  1947,  reduced by stages to 15 monthsf or those entered between that date and 1st January,  1949. FiguresinThousands/NavyArrayIR.A.P.TOTALN.S.Intake19484100^46150N.S.Intake19491011042162Strength.1/1Z50.N.i1315470237Total144357203704N. S.Intake19501011039159Strength. 1/1/51  .&apos; Total1212949190146327179652N.S.Intake19511011037157Strength.2ZiZ52m.N.S.1212947188Total149327173649TABLE 3.    FURTHER INDICATION OF REGULAR TRENDS1/1/51
I TABLE 5* ^SUM TIOEB( a) National Sorvico of 18 months.(b) Regular recruitment at present rates.(c) Intake of N.S. men the maximum acceptable by the Services.(d) Rundown on the basis of 2 years&apos;  service for those entered on or before 1 July 1947 reduced by stages to 18 months for those entered between that date and 1 January,  1949&apos;*/Figures f    in      -Thousands/	N.S. Intake-	N.S. Intake	Strength		N.S. Intake	Strength - 1Z1/51		N.S. Intake	Strength 2Z1Z.52		1948	1949	:n.s.	Total	1950	N.S.	Total	: 1951	N.S.	TotalNavy Army Ik./., p.	4 100 46	10 130 36	14 192 73	145 395 206	.   10 130 35	15 183 53	149 381 183	10 130 33	15 183 50	152 381 176TOTAL	150	176	279	746	175	251	713	173	248	______ 709kJMiMJz-   assumptions -(a) National Service of 2^^ears.(b) Regular recruitment at present rates.(c) Intake of National Service men the maximum acceptable by theServices.(d) Rundown to 2 years&apos;   service by not Inter than July 1949.--1-- &apos; &apos;  Figures I  in housandj/	&apos; N..S. Intake 1948	N.S. Intake 1949	: Strc -iZ, N.S.	sngth LZ50 : Total	N.S. Intake 1 1950	. str V N.S.	angth 1/51^ Total	&quot;.....*..... in . O I Intake 1951	Str __IL N.S.	ength 1Z52__ TotalNavy JArmy I.A.F.	4 100 46	10 130 32	14 216 78	145 419 211	10 130 29	20 244 61	154 442 191	10 130 28	20 244 57&apos;	157 : 442 183TOTAL	150	172	308 ________.	775	169	325	787	168 .......	331	782I                 .                !  ABLE 7.    NUMBERS AVAILABLE FOR CALL-UP i   ........         ............										feur.es   &apos; fin fousandsT1	L      4* registrations a year			[       3 registrations a year,;			Now registra-tions	Maturing deferments	: Total	New registra-tions  .	Maturing deferments	Total1?49 H950 11951 1	145 140 -   130	25 -65 95	170 205 225	110 105 95	25 65 95 ., ,,. .,. ----------   .	135 170 190 1 li   .1     1-.111... In.-
EFFECT OF 18 MONTHS NATIONAL service note by the War office.      On the invitation, of the Chiefs of Staff the WarOffice has examined methods by which the manpower deficit,resulting from a period of National Service of 18 months from 1 January.1949 would have to be met.2.      The War Office has estimated that the manpowerrequired to meet&apos;its present commitments is 421,000military plus 12,000 A.T.S.  based on an annual NationalService intake of 110,000 or 431,000 men (plus 12,000women) if, as is probable, the National Service intakehas to be increased to 130,000.3.      If it has been necessary by 1 July 1950 to releaseall men with over 18 months Service,  it is estimated on present recruiting forecasts that the strength of theArmy (including A.T.S.) will fall by this date to below392 ,000, leaving a deficit of about 50,000.4-      In general the deficiency being produced by areduction of the length of National Service will fall forthe most part on men with between two years and 18 monthsService.    These are the best trained soldiers,  the majorityof whom would be overseas.5. From the military point of view, the soundest methodof making good this deficiency would be by curtailing our commitments overseas.6.      If these commitments are not reduced the gap couldonly bo bridged by reduction at the expense of thefollowing:(a) The United Kingdom: Base:   i.e.  in theHome Field army the Training organisation the Static organisation the effect will mainly fall on the. Army&apos;s state of readiness and on morale generally including that of theT. A.(b) Overseas Garrisons where the direct effect will be on the Army&apos;s ability to meet itspresent commitments.7.      It has not be en possible to examine the full implications in the time available and the Commanders-in-Chief would have to be consulted before the effects can be
accurately assessed.    The following is a general review ofthe issues involved.Home Field Army8.      There will be two main effects.    Field units otherthan infantry will have to be kept at 30% below      &quot;   .   &apos;  &quot;    ;establishment.    The numbers of infantry units at home willhave to be reduced by very nearly half the planned number.The result of this will be that the Home Field Army willhave inadequate resources available for internal security and for assistance to the Civil Power in the case of&apos;emergencies and strikes.    The assistance to the TerritorialArmy will be far below what was previously planned.    this must have a serious effect on the efficiency and morale ofthe Territorial Army.Training Organisation9-      The Army is likely to have to face the problem oftraining 1.30,000 National Service men.    At present 33 .000  -Military and A.T.S.  are employed in maintaining essentialArmy Schools and in training an intake of 110,000.&apos;   Tomaintain Army Schools and train 130,000, 36,500 Militaryand A.T.S. will be required.    A reduction below this figurecannot be made without lowering the Training efficiency toan extent where it will have severe- effects on theefficiency of the trained output, the morale of theNational Service man and the recuiting of the RegularSoldier.    The only possible way to reduce the numbers ofmilitary is by employing an increased number of civilianson administrative duties in-lieu of soldiers.    This is  -being explored,  but raises manpower difficulties in other directions.Static Organisation .10.      The original estimate was based on the need tocomplete war aftermath tasks,  to increase the degree of readiness and to maintain day to day administration.Improvements, hoped for by an increased employment of civilians recently agreed, have only partiallymaterialised as civilians-have not been forthcomingmainly owing to lack of acconmodation.11.      The effect of cuts will be that:(a.)    If civilians. are not forthcoming,aftermath tasks will cease;(b)    There will be a general slowing upin administration and little improve-ment in the present low state ofpreparedness of the Army.
Overseas Garrisons12.      Proportionate cuts will have to he imposed on the443,000 estimate for Overseas theatres.    They will he ofthe following order, BAOE 8,000 , MELP 3,000, FARELF 2,000,ETA 750.    This can only he done by reducing administrative units and by withdrawing early&apos;in 1949 &quot;teeth&quot; arms,namely four major units from BAOE (including the Para.Brigade),  six major units from MELP,  two major units fromPARELP.13.      Owing to present commitments the  strengths of  .overseas garrisons to-day, particularly of MELP andPARELP,  are above the 443,000 estimate.    This, means thatin fact MELjj1 and PARELP would lose approximately 14,000and 5,000 men respectively in 1949.14.      The reduction of administrative units will have serious effects, especially in MELP.    In MELP, the stateof readiness will be reduced and all improvements to accommodation and other amenities will virtually cease.In all theatres there would be a danger of administrativebreakdown and  a further examination may prove that thelarge cuts involved are impracticable.15.    The withdrawal of &quot;teeth&quot;  arms would bring thesegarrisons below what the Commanders-in-Chiefs have askedfor and what we consider essential if they are to meetoperational commitments and internal security calls.The politidal implications in reducing BAOR by 8,000 menare considerable.    The situation in MELP is unstable.Developments in PARELP are impossible to forecast.Anti-Aircraft Command16.      The War Office does not consider any cuts in A.A.Command possible.    The present calling only just sufficesto maintain 26 regiments in the Active Army.    This allowsonly one Regiment to assist 7t? in the Territorial Army,Furthermore, A.A.Command takes in National Service menafter two weeks and is very economical in Regularsoldiers.    Further dilution is impracticable.    To reduceA.A.Command would make it impossible to take in the fullNational Service intake proposed.Overheads cannot be further cut without slowingup the speed of mobilisation of A.A.Command and without involving risks which would in present circumstancesappear unacceptable.Conclusion17.      The War Office concludes that the effects on theArmy of a reduction to 18 months National Service will be generally as follows:- -
(a) The garrisons in Germany, the Middle East andPar East must he considerably reduced.&apos;   Thiswill involve serious risks.(b) There must be a general slowing up of administrative services both at home andabroad involving virtual cessation in theimprovement of amenities.    Without further examination there can be no guarantee thatthe proposed cuts in administrative services are in fact workable, especially overseas.Aftermath tasks in the U.K. will ceaseunless civilian labour is forthcoming.(c) The state of efficiency of the trainingmachine will drop.    If civilian labour is not forthcoming it will break down.This would have a serious effect on the morale of the National Service man,  thestate of the training of the Army, andthe recruiting of the regular soldier.(.&apos;&amp;)    Many vital measure to improve the stateof readiness of the Army will have to bebrought to a standstill.(e)    Assistance to the Territorial Army willnot be sufficient to maintain thetraining and morale of the TerritorialArmy at the pitch required.
APPENDIX IIIREVIEW OF THE NATIONAL SERVICE ACT 1948TERMS OF REFERENCE OF WORKING PARTY(i) To review the provisions of the National service act, particularly those relative to the lengthof service on the active list, the length of reserveservice and the training obligations associatedwith reserve service, in the light of:(a) the probable manpower requirements of eachof the three Services over the next fewyears;(b) the training required to fit NationalService men to play an effective role in thedefence of the country;    and(c) the general manpower and economic positionof the United&apos; Kingdom, including thesupply of labour for the essential industries and services and arrangementsfor apprenticeship and training.(ii) To report on the broad effect which the adoption ofany recommendations under (i), together with themeasures decided upon by the Government for theimmediate strengthening of the Forces, - would haveupon the total number in the Forces in the financialyear 1949/50 and subsequently;    and upon theirbroad financial implications.- 13 -
(2/6/48) (B116) Wt. 19954. D98. 60m. 8/48. P.&amp;N.Ltd. G813.this document is the property of his britannic majestts governmentThe  circulation  of this  paper has been  strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.......................................................................TOP SECRET Copy No.ANNEXGEN^25h/l(also MISC/P.(h8) 28 (Final)13TH NOVEMBER,  I9I4.8.CABINETSIZE of the ARMED FORCES-IN-THE--YEARSllSll^lS^O^anE^ll^lREVIEW OF NATIONAL SERVICE ACTRoport^hy.....a Working PartyINTP^DUCTION1.      We were instructed to consider certain problems arisingfrom the conclusions reached by Ministers at their Meeting on 5th November, that the period of National Service should inprinciple not be reduced below 18 months.These problems were mainly concerned with reconciling thenumbers of men available for call-up with the numbers whichthe Services could accept on the assumption that their man-power ceilings would be limited by financial considerations.2.      The approximate numbers available for call-up in thethree years 19U9/50, 1950/51 and 1951/52 on present medicalstandards are as follows:-.On the basis of four       On the basis of threere gi s&quot;t rations registrations19h9/50 175,000 lhO,0001950/51 215,000 180,0001951/52 230,000 195,000Totals 620,000 515,000   .RAISING OF MEDICAL STANDARDS3*      About 87,5$ of the men posted to the Forces are in grade I.      Many men are placed in Grade II rather than in grade I because of some minor defect of vision or locomotion,and it would be out of the question to reject every man in grade II.
4*      On tht) other hand the PULHEEMS system of assessment(under which the capacity of recruits under -various headings-,powers of locomotion, hearing, eyesight, etc. is assessedseparately)  is both mote de-tailed and more flexible than theearlier arrangements,  and it would be possible by raisingstandards to reduce the numbers who pass the initial medical examination.     As it is so necessary for the Forces to secureall possible economies in manpower and money, we feel thatthere is every justification for raising medical standardsto the extent necessary to ensure that the Forces cansuitably use those called up for service.      By a modest raising of the standard, which would be welcomed &quot;by the Services,  thenumbers available for call-up would be reduced by about 7%.5.     We have at the same time examined the possibility of reducing the available intake by raising the standards of mental capacity or intelligence.      This is discussed in some detail in Appendix 1,      Although the War Office would wishfor the elimination before call-up of those men who at present,owing to psychiatric grading?., have to be relegated to the pioneer Corps, we conclude that for the reasons given inAppendix 1 it is.not practicable to bring this about atpresent.6.      Our first recommendation is that the standard of entryshould be slightly raised as proposed in paragraph 4 aboveby adjusting the medical gradings in the PULHEEMS classification.DIMENSIONS OF THE PROBLEM7.      On the assumption that the recommendation in paragraph 6is accepted, the uumbers of men available for calling up inthe next three years will be as follows:-.On the basis of four   On the basis of three 2 iSt 2ii2SS &quot;*   &apos; registrations1949/50 165,000   - 130,0001950/51 . 200,000 165,0001951/52 215,000 180,000Total l.h.49 -     580,000 475,000As a result&apos; of their most recent examination of the problem,the Service Departments have concluded that the annual intakewhich they could accept during these years, would be, withslight variations, 175,000 men, divided between the Servicesroughly as follows:-Wavy 10,000Army 120,000R.A.F. &apos; 45,0008.      If this intake were accepted, and the period of NationalService was scaled down steadily to 18 months by 1st July, 1950,(the day when 1949 recruits would begin to be released), it
has been calculated that the total strengths of the three services would be:-Ayerago Average2:s^*k3 SSJZS iimisfi  ^ilSS 1.4*51Navy 145,000 144,000 146,000    147*000 148,000Army 412,000 397,000 386,000   378,000 375,000R.A..F.      233,000 228,000 213,000    212,000 214,000Total     790,000   769,000   745,000   737,000   737,0009m     An important element in the above figures is the Regularcontent of the Services.      This Regular content is dependentnot only on the rate of recruiting but also on the extent to.which men extend., re-engage or continue in the Service.      these factors can only &quot;he forecast on present trends and accordingly the strengths actually achieved may vary either way from those shown above.10.    It will be seen that a total intake of 175,000 is rather more than the number available in 1949/50 on the basis of four -registrations a year (see paragraph 7) but falls short of - thenumbers available     on      this basis in the succeeding twoyears,  the net short-fall over the three years being 55,000.11.    It has however long been realised that there was likelyto be in the years to come a greater number of National Servicemen available than the Services could absorb, mainly owing tomaturing deferments of service.      The whole problem wasconsidered by Ministers last year, when it was decided thatthe best way of dealing with it would be to omit one of thequarterly registrations each year as necessary,  thus reducingthe intake immediately by about 35,000 and raising the averageage of call-up by three months at each omission.      This coursehas already been announced to apply in 1948,  1949 and 1950 anda registration was in fact omitted in 1946, thus raising the ageof call-up from 18 years to 18 years 3 months.12.    if the Services are allowed an intake of 175,000 a year,it will not after all be necessary to drop a registration in1949, but two registrations will have to be dropped in thecourse of the following two years,  thus raising the age ofcall-up to 18 years 9 months by the beginning of 1952.13.    An increase in the age of call-up has advantages from thestandpoints of the Services,  of industry and of the individual.Under the Military Training Act of 1939 call-up was fixed at 20,after careful consideration of the most advantageous age, andit is suggested that on merits it would be a good thing toget back to it.      On the other hand it was strongly argued,during the debates in Parliament on the National Service Actthat the least interruption to civil life would be caused whenthe age of call-up was fixed at 18.      (in fact it would havebeen out of  the question in 1947 to fix the &quot;age of call-up at 20 because if this had been done, as the age of call-up hadbeen reduced to 18 during the war,  for two years no men would- D -
have been available).    in our view no problem arises untilthe age of call-up is approaching 20.    If the intake is of theorder ol 175*000 a year no immediate problem arises:    the &quot;gap&quot;is more than closed by the measure of raising of the age of&apos;call-up already announced.    Even if the average intake were reduced to 135,000 a year,  the age of call-up at thebeginning or 1952 would still be only about 19 years 6 months.The position thereafter is so uncertain that we do not -thinkit profitable.to consider at this juncture, what steps may benecessary in throe years time., It should bo mentioned here that it would be desirableto give an early indication of any changes in the plans foromitting one registration in 1949 and 1950 already announced.Ih,    We have also considered the effect of a reduction&apos;of the intake at least in 1949/50 considerably below the desirablefigure of .175,000 a year,  in case it becomes necessary toreduce the average strength during this year in order toreduce defence expenditure.    To&apos;give an indication of the way in which this method might work we have chosen two arbitraryreductions in average strength over the year which would, ofcourse, prevent the Services carrying out their present commitments and have worked out the. reduction of intake duringthe year that would be necessary to achieve  them.    We have assumed that since the main object of these proposals i-s tomaintain the essential structure of the Services over the nextyear or so,   they will bo allowed if they so desire to retain the pre-1949 entries for as long as possible - i.e.  that aperiod of 18 months National Service will be worked down tosteadily and reached not earlier-, than 1st July, 1950.    Theproblem is not quite the same in each Service,  that of theAir Force in particular is rather special.    In general, however,it can be said that if the period of service were reduced to18 months more rapidly - say by 1st January,  1950 - the lossof these experienced pre-1949 entries in the first half of 1950would reduce the advantage gained by increasing the length ofservice from 12  to 18 months.    The maximum period for whichpre-1949 entries.will be retained should be worked out and announced as soon as possible.15..    Before giving the figures wc are bound to point out one further difficulty, which is inherent in the attempt to produce,in 1949/50,  an average reduction in inanp wer by reducing the intake in that year.&quot; Since wo are starting from a point at1st AprTI, i^97&quot;whieh is not capable of much variation, andattempting to achieve a certain average reduction between thatdate and 1st April, 1950, wo are bound at the end of the period to have gone far below this average, and the reduction ofintake will be much greater - about twice as groat in fact -than the reduction in overage strength seems at first sight  to demand.    The truth is that the full effect of a reduction oxintake in.1949/50 would only ho felt in the following years.    Inorder to maintain the same average - reduction below the figures at present planned in these later years, an increase ol intakeabove the 1/5,000 mark would bo necessary in order to make upfor the pendulum Having swung too far in 1949/50.- h -
are sho!rlrr-nU^o calculations for all Services combinedaic snown m i,ne lollowmg table:-  -Thousands	Strength 1. 4- 49	Intake ^1949/50	Average Strength 1949/50	Consequential strength 1. 4/ 50I	790	175	769	745II	790	108	737	680III	790	41	705	; 615The first line (1) shows the same strengths during 1949/50s those estimated in paragraph 8 to be the totals &quot;&quot;&quot; &quot;three Servicesthat in order under tin-to achieve a s s ump 11 o its t he 11ie  oorais for allmade.    Line II showsboaverage\n average reduction over the year of32,000 to 737,000, it would he necessary to reduce the intakefrom 175,000 to 108,000,  and the consequential strength at1st April, 1950, would he 680,000.    Line III shows thatdouble this average reduction - i.e.  to bring thestrength down to 705,000 - the intake would have to he further reduced to 41,000 and the strength at 1st April, 1950to 615,000.    If these reductions in intake wore to he achieved by droiDping registrations,  it would he necessary to have tworegistrations in the year 1949/50 in the case of Line II, noneat all in the case of Line III:  on the other hand,  as mentionedabove, it would probably be necessary to have four registrationsin 1950/51 to correct the swing of the pendulum.    While thesedrastic reductions on the intakgreat reduction in the ability oftheir commitments,  theyfinancial savings untilduring 1949/50 would cause aI9ithe Services to carry out would not bear their.full effect inthe foil wing year.WAYS AND MEANS17.    Apart from reducing the- numbers available for callrup byomissions of registrations, various other suggestions wore putforward at the meeting of Ministers on 5th November, and we now proceed to examine them.(a):toneion of total reservation18.    It has been suggested that  the surplis of National Servicemen should ho taken up- by applying a schedule of reserved occupations.    There are serious objections to this course.19s    First of all, it is not appropriate to exempt young menof,18.     They do not at this age possess sufficient skill or experience to make them of great value to industry.    the exemption of young men in coal mining and the Merchant Navy and,for the time being,  in agriculture, has been accepted becauseof the obvious importance of these industries and the speciallyarduous and,  in the case of coal mining, unpleasant and dangerous nature of the jobs.    There are a few other of the same type,  such as iron and steel and foundries, whose-.exclusion might on the same grounds be more or less accepted.industries
But these industries would not account for anything comparable with the reductions assumed in paragraph 17.    The exemption of young men m all branches of the iron and stool industry andin all foundries would, in fact, account for only 8,000 men ayear ax most.    it would therefore&apos; bo necessary to p-o muchiurther and include industries with little or no claim to special treatment.    If all the textile industries, pottery,the motor and aircraft industries, shipbuilding and&quot;ship-   .....repairing and electrical engineering wore added to the list&quot; of&quot;excepted industries,  the total reduction in National Serviceintake would still, on the average, be only some 27,000 a year.But clearly, once this wider field of industries is entered,it is almost impossible to draw the line in a way which would produce the right   numerical results and bo acceptable on theground of the special importance of the selected industries.20.    In short, once any further departure is made from theprinciple of universality of service beyond the exclusion ofcoal mining,   the Merchant Navy and agriculture,  it is almost impossible to draw the line convincingly.    If,  on the other hand,only the few more industries which might have stronger claimswore exempted, hardly any impression would be made on theproblem at the expense of running the serious risks involved ina. broach in the principle of universal service.21.   - With its long history of freedom from conscription,  theBritish people cannot be expected to, and does not, in fact,take kindly to the idea of compulsory military service inpeace-time.    It is accepted &quot;because of its universality and ifthis principle were once departed from to any substantial extent,it might he extremely difficult, if not impossible,  to securecontinued acceptance of conscription in peace-time at all.(D)    Exemption of deferred apprentices22.    There is- some, force in the argument that as theirdeferments fall in there is a stronger case for exempting theyoung men whose calling-up has been deferred to enable them tocomplete their studies or apprenticeships;    they will be older,more skilled and more settled in their jobs.    The Ministry ofSupply,  in fact, would be in favour of such a decisionparticularly in so far as it applied to the small number of scientific and experimental graduates who could possibly beconsidered on their individual merits.    On the other hand theServices badly need many of the apprentices as potentialtradesmen;  those.young men were given deferment on personalgrounds irrespective of the importance, in the national interest,of&quot;&quot;tho industry to which they belonged or the career for whichthey were studying,  and there could be no case,  on indsutrialgrounds, for giving exemption to more than - a small proportionof them.    To give exemption to these lads would give rise tograve dissatisfaction,  and it would be regarded as grossly unfair to others to give these young men not only time to complete their studios or apprenticeships but-also to allow them tosettled clown in industry withput the interruption which nearly all other young men have to put up with.    Moreover,  it wouldbe equally unfair to the lads who did not.ask for deferment tocomplete their apprenticeships but did their military servicefirst.
(G)    BaJl-loi23.    This is  the simplest method of limiting numbers to becalled up for the Forces, and has precedents in continental countries.    From present information it is likely that thiscourse will also be adopted in the UeS.A.   (an account of the selective Service Scheme in that country is at Appendix 2).The ballot system would preserve the appearance of universalliability for service, making it a matter of luck who was called up to fulfil that liability.    If the position arose inwhich the numbers available for service far exceed the numbersneeded, a ballot might well be the only practicable solution.Unless such a situation arose, however, public opinion wouldnot,  in our view,  regard wit?-: favour the use of the ballot todetermine the choice between two such extremes as completeexemption from National Service and service in the forces a lengthy period of whole-time service, to be followed byreserve service for a number of years.for(d)    Alternative of long and short National;rvice24.    Another proposal is that National Service should be dividedinto two types,  (l).a short period of about 6 months&apos; full-time service for training followed by a fairly long obligation forreserve service;   and (2)  a long period of perhaps 2 years&apos;  full-time service with no reserve liability,    The decision whether an individual should undertake one type of service or the.other would be decided by ballot.25.    The proposal,  however, has serious objections.    All three services must get the maximum value out of the men in theForces and a scheme of the kind suggested would net serve thisend.    There is a real need for building up a trained reserve,but in present circumstances greater importance must be laid on meeting current tasks.    From this latter point of view the six months&apos; man -would be entirely unproductive- because he v/ould be unable to render any &quot;useful service&quot;.    If the scheme wereto be a reality the proportion of six months&apos; men would have tobe substantial because, without a provision of this kind,  theaverage number of National Service men in the Forces would be greater than under the present proposal to take in a proportion only of the available intake for 18 months.    the consequence would be that the total cost would be increased.Broadly speaking,  therefore,  to the extent to which this proposalachieved it object of absorbing the whole available intake, itwould do so at the expense.of making the Services less efficient and less able to carry out their tasks, possibly atan increase in cost.26.    To be more particular,  if the attempt were made by thisdevice to take in the whole intake in a certain year insteadof something considerably less,  without increasing the total strength of the Forces,  it would be found that the Forces, inso doing, were accepting the full training liability of the extra men and gaining no immediate advantage from them.    In theNavy and R.A.F.  there would only just be time in the period of six months to train the men to an elementary standard;  evenin the Army with such a short period it would not be possibleto post them to perform any useful work at the conclusion oftheir basic training.
The proposal would mean that in future years the reserves would consist entirely of those who had only done six months&apos;full-time service, which would have a v-ery serious effect ontheir operational value.27.    Apart from the military objections to this proposal, itis probable  that the general public would rot regard whole-time service.for two or more years with no reserve liabilityana six months&apos; full-time service with even a long -period of reserve service as fair equivalents, especially as it would,no doubt,- be borne in mind that,  in the event of an emergency,many of the men without reserve liability would,  in fact, be&quot;colled up.    To the extent to which it was their view that thealternative obligations represented unequal liabilities,  the objection to the use of the ballot for the selection of which individual performed which typo of service,&quot; would increase.26.    A variant&apos; of this scheme is that some national Servicemen should do no full-time service at all but merely incur a liability for reserve service, while others die perhaps twoyears&apos;  full-time service.    This avoids the problem of&quot;givingbasic training to the whole intake, but would have a correspondingly adverse effect on the efficiency of the reserves which would consist entirely of men with no full-time servicebehind them.(0)    Roeeal of National Service Act29.    It has been suggested that as from 1st January,  1949, men should continue to be called up under the war-time powers;  thatthe main provisions of the 1947 Act (new incorporated in the1949 Act)  should be repealed or their operation postponed;  thatthe Government should announce that the maximum period of servicwill be two years;   that a reserve liability should be imposed on those leaving the Forces from 1st January 1950 onwards;  thatthis reserve liability should be for a lesser period than six years;   and that the National Service intake should be requiredto accept the same reserve obligations, but be entitled to thesome financial benefits as the Territorial volunteer.    Some ofthese proposa 1 s are in 1:.er-related.30.    The suggestion that men should continue to be called up under the war-time powers could be brought about either byfresh legislation in the&apos; form of a substantial amendment to theNational Service Act,  1948, or by simply postponing the main provisions of this Act so that the emergency powers under which men are now colled up remain in force.    If,  in fact, men areto be called up for 18 months from 1st January,  1949,  thenumbers in the Forces will be the same whatever thelegislation under which action is taken.    Moreover the present act lays down a maximum period of whole-time service notexceeding 12 months and similer phraseology would presumablybemused in any amending Bill,  thus ensuring the necessaryflexibility should the need arise.    In our view when any announcement is made it is desirable in the interests both ofthose called up and of the&quot;Services that an indication should^be given of the Government * s present intentions as regards  ohenext three years,  since those to be called up will want toknow how long they are likely to be called upon to serve.    Thiswill presumably have to be in the form of maximum periods,
unless future strengths can be definitely laid down.Without a measure of stability the Cervices cannoteconomically plan the best use of the available forces.(f)    Build-up of reserves31.    The lengthening of the period of service will mean that National Service men begin to flow into Royal NavalSpecial Reserve, the Territorial Army, and the Air Force Reservefrom 1st July, 1950 instead of 1st January 1950, unless powers were taken toimpose liability for reserve service on those called upin 19h8 who will bo released in the first half of 1950.To take such powers might be regarded as a breach of the contract made with those men, most of whom are already inthe Forces,  and we recommend that the build-up of the reserves should be postponed.    The effect will simply bethat men who under previous plans would have been in reserve in the first half of 1950, will instead remainembodied in this period.(S)    Liability for reserve Bervi.ce32.    The increase in the period of whole-time service will involve a review of the period of reserve liability.There are obvious advantages from the point of view of presentation if the extension of the period of whole-time service carried with it what would ho regarded as a worth-while reduction in the period of reserve liability. There arecertain attractions in such a claim in the case &apos;of the Army, provided thereduction in the total jieriod&apos; of re serve liability was coupled with anincreased training liability which imposed on the National Service men inthe T.A. broadly the same obligations as those undertaken bythe volunteer.    Any such changes will clearly affect thenumber of trained reservists immediately available on mobilisation and it   is for the Naval, Air and General Staffs to advise as to the minimum numbers essential forthis purpose.    We have asked them to do this urgently butwe have.not delayed our report until we receive theirviews.33.    The suggestion that the National Service reservistshould in effect be completely merged with theTerritorial volunteer has certain attractions, but itpresents many difficulties.    The success of the scheme will depend primarily on the increased training liability for the    National Service man in the T.A.    Such increasedtraining liability would .create many problems yet to be examined.    It should be noted, however,  that  the volunteeraccepts such increased liabilities because he knows thathe can discharge them.    The civilian employment of many^ofthe compelled men might preclude.them from discharging thornand in these circumstances it would seem extremely doubtful whether the country would accept such a scale oftraining liability for National Service men in the T.A.Moreover,  the nature of the training liability undertaken by the volunteer would be extremely difficultadministratively to impose by compulsion.    Finally, the
cost of this proposal would he substantial.    We may assume that ultimately there would he of the order of 750,000National Servicemen with a compulsory reserve liability.    ifapproval were obtained for payment to them of training&apos;bounties etc.  at the full rates for volunteers - and theTreasury feel some doubt whether this could be justified -the additional cost would be many millions&quot;&apos;.In view of the stringency of the Defence Budget overthe next few years we feel that such a sum of money could.bebetter expended in other ways.(h)    Training of deferred men.before call-up3h*    It lias also been suggested that apprentices and students who are how deferred from all National Service until theyhave completed their training should be obliged to undergopart-time training during &apos; these years of deferment.    Thiswould moan that some use was made of all fit men.as they reached the age of 18 and would,  to that extent, makeimpact of National Service universal.    It would be hoped that part-time training before call-up would make the men moreuseful to the Services in their subsequent period of full-time National Service.35.    The T.A.  is designed to form in the years to come alarge body of trained men ready to be mobilised&apos; in anemergency-without any delay.    If each unit contained alarge proportion of young men with only the experience of afew drills or a fortnight&apos;s camp behind thorn it would beimpossible to mobilise them without either&apos;throwing the unit into disorder by removing the untrained men.ordelaying its effective mobilisation for a considerable time until the whole unit was trained up to a state fit for service.    Another objection closely related to this isthat the T.A.  as now planned is designed to. give refreshertraining to trained men and not basic training to rawrecruits.    To attempt to combine the two would be a confusedand wasteful procedure.    This proposal does not touch the intake problem but merely transfers part of the burden oftraining from the Regular forces to the T.A.  snd reserve forces.4-    An attempt is being made to prepare amore precise estimate of cost.
OTHER POINTS FOR DECISION36.    We take this opportunity of dealing with two other points which arise from the decision that the period ofNational Service should he held at 18 months for the timebeing, and which call for Ministerial attention.37.    (a) LegislationAny decision involving an increase above 13 months in theliability for full-time service of those called up in 1949will require legislation.     From a political point of view itis highly desirable that this should be enacted before Christmas,but we must enter the warning that to secure this end high priority will have to be given to the matter, in view of the many stages the proposal has yet to go through before Parliament-ary Counsel could be formally invited to start drafting thenecessary amending Bill, and the great interest that the bill would be likely to arouse in Parliament.      We are advised that,from a purely legal point of view, a possible second course wouldbe to announce the decision to increase the period of full-time,service to 18 months and hold the second reading of the bill before Christmas, inserting a retrospective clause to enablethe Bill to be passed next year and yet to cover all thosecalled up from 1st January, 1949.      If, however, it were decidedthat men should continue to be called up under the war-timeNational Service Acts, legislation would be necessary to postponeor repeal the National Service Act, 1948.      This, we understand,could not be made retrospective and if the amending Bill wasnot enacted by the beginning of 1949 it would be impossibleto call men up for more than twelve months&apos;  service until it was.38.    (b) Retention of 18 months serviceWe have been asked how long the period of National Serviceneed be retained at 18 months.      The Chiefs of Staff in theirreport on National Service said that three years was as far ahead as could he foreseen, but that throughout these years the increase in the period of National Service should he maintained.      There is no reason to suppose that any of the major defence considerations that have led to the Services&apos;present demand for 18 months1 National Service will have lost their force by 1952, and it will be a source of stability tothe Services in their planning if they can be assured of theretention of this period at least till then, subject to revision in the light of any striking improvement in theinternational position with conseq.uen.tial effects on the size of the forces aporoval.      The Treasury stress particularly the need for bearing in mind the possibility of a reductionof the period should circumstances permit.CONCLUSIONS39.    We invite the Defence Committee to take note that -(l) to reduce substantially- average strengths In 1949/50a considerable reduction of the intake during that period and consequently of the strengthsat the end of it would be necessary (S 15 - 16);
(2) the Naval, General and Air Staffs are examining the military implications of a change in thetraining liability and a reduction in theperiod of reserve service for National Servicemen (8 32);(3) in order to implement the decision to increaseabove 12 months the liability for full-time service under the National Service Act ofthose called up in 1949 will require legislation which should be passed before christmas.      Otherwise it would have to be retrospective, a course open to obviouspolitical objections (S 37);(4) any decision to call up men under the -war-timeActs from the beginning of 1949 would necessitate the repealing of the present  .National Service Act before the1st January, 1949 (g 37);and to approve the following RECOMMENDATIONS:(5) that the standard of entry to the Armed forces during 1949 should be slightly raised by adjusting the medical gradings in the FULHEEMSclassification (S 6);(6) that the present method of droppingregistrations is the most suitable and opento the least objection and should &quot;be continuedas far as necessary until the age of call-upis approaching 20 (i 13);(7) the maximum period for which pre-1949 entrieswill be retained should be worked out and announced as soon as possible (i 14);(8) that the other- proposals discussed in paragraphs17 - 35 should not at the moment be adopted;(9) that the build-up of reserves should be allowedto start on the 1st July, 1950, instead of on the 1st January, 1950 (S 31);(10) that unless there is a striking improvementin the intemational situation, the periodof full-time National Service should beretained at 18 months as a maximum forthe next three years (I 38).(Signed on behalf of theWorking Party)H.P.MINISTRY OP DEFENCE,  S.W.I.13TH NOVEMBER,  1948.    .
APPENDIX 1RESTRICTION OF INTAKE BY RAISING STANDARDS OPMENTAL CAPACITY OR INTELLIGENCEUnder the Pulheems system of medical classification, aman cannot he accepted for service if there is any doubt about his mental capacity or intelligence.      A man, of those mentalcapacity or intelligence a medical board has any doubt,  can begraded I or II only if his intelligence is confirmed by apsychiatrist.      There is, however, another type of man whothough not so backward or of such low intelligence as to meritreference to a psuchiatrist, is below average.      The Navy have for many years weeded out by selection test all national servicepreferences below their minimum standard of acceptance;    theR.A.F.  are introducing a similar procedure towards the endof this month.      The Army will, therefore, have to continue totake the dullards.      The Army test recruits after entry, andrefer those with very low test scores to a psychiatrist.Some hundreds of men are in consequence discharged monthly .from the Army largely because the capacity of the Pioneer Corpsto absorb such men is limited.     A similar test could beintroduced before entry, and men falling below a certainstandard of intelligence declared unfit for national service.Such a decision would certainly raise the standard of recruitsand would be in the interests of the Army, who do not wish toaccept any man who cannot be turned into an all-purpose soldier,.The test would, however, seem open to objection on thefollowing grounds:(i) It would, cut across the accepted theory of the\miversality of service for men medically fit for service;(ii) The desire to evade national service would puta premium on ignorance, and the more intelligentclasses of the community would bear adisproportionately heavy share of N.S*responsibility.
APPENDIX 2THE U.S.A.   SELECTIVE SERVICE SCHEMEConscription in peacetime in the U.S.A. was effected onthe 24th June, 1948, by the   re-enactment of the dormant war-time Selective Service Act.      It aims at maintaining theServices at a peace-time strength of 2,166,882 (includingregulars).      Provision is made in the Act, however, for exemption from compulsory service of a limited number of men (161,000)subject to them being accepted for voluntary enlistment at theage of 18.8.       CONDITIONS OP SERVICE (VOLUNTEERS)Men accepted as volunteers within the numerical limit of161,000 laid down in the Act (applications are far in excessof the permitted quota) can state a preference for the branchof the forces in which they would like to serve.      They incura liability of 12 months full-time service with the regular forces during which period they will not be sent outside theU.S.A., followed by 6 years in the Enlisted Reserve Corps(see paragraph 3(a)) or 4 years with the organised reserves(see paragraph 3(b)).      The option of which form of reserveservice the volunteer undertakes rests with the militaryauthorities and not with the individual.3.      CONDITIONS OF SERVICE (CONSCRIPTS)Every male resident in the U.S.A.   (with certain exceptions.-see paragraph 7) between the ages of 18 and 26 is liable for service in the regular forces for 21 months.     At the end ofthis full-time period he has the choice of three alternatives;he may elect to:-(a) become a member of the Enlisted Reserve Corpsfor a further period of 5 years.      This involveslittle more than having one&apos;s name on a reservelist with liability to early recall in emergency,-or(b) become a member of an organised reserve component of the armed forces for a consecutive period ofthree years.      Besides early recall in an emergencythis involves attendance at drills, camps,  etc., or(c) serve for a further year with the regulars whichwill give him dispensation from membership of the reserves.4,      INTAKEIt has been estimated that approximately 9,600,000 willregister whereas, the total manpower requirement is only ,166,882 (including regulars).      It follows then that it willbe possible and it is proposed to grant exemptions particularly on hardship and compassionate grounds on a very generous scale.It is &apos;thought probable that the actual method4&quot; of selectionwhich will be adopted will be that used in the last World War.+ The American Military Attache in Londonalthough not able to confirm was of theopinion that intake would be controlled by lot commencing either this or next month. -
On that occasion each State was allocated a certain quota of conscripts;    this quota was further divided among variousregional hoards to decide on matters of individual hardship.Men then found liable to serve were taken in accordance withthe number of their &quot;call-up&quot; papers, these numbers beingallocated by lot.5-.&apos;     EXEMPTIONS AND DEFERMENTS - &apos;Exemption or deferment of service can be granted to thosewho(a.) have served in the last war with honourable dischargefor a period of(i) 90 days active service between 7th December,1941, and 2nd September, 1945, or(ii) 12 months active service between 16thSeptember, 1940, and 24th June, 1948;(b) are members of the organised reserve and those who can. show that they have had no opportunity tojoin an organised reserve but who had at least90 days service between 16th September, 1940,and 24th June, 1948;(c) have served in the armed forces of any country alliedto the U.S.A.  in the last World War beforekind September, 1945;(d) are U.S.A.  Government officials, ministers of religion, conscientious objectors, are employedby certain international organisations; &apos;   .(e) are aliens;(f) are employed in a reserved occupation (agricultural and certain other trades);(g) may suffer hardship or have claims on compassionate grounds,    persons included in this category aremarried men, sole surviving sons, and registrantshaving dependent relatives.


</content>
</cab>
