<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/31/0 images: 78-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limifed.      65It tS issued for the personal use of..../^..M.^^^^if^&apos;0P SECRET Copy No. v2,P. (48) 278-pi NOVEMBER,  1948CABINETEIRE&apos;S FUTURE RELATIONS WITHTHE COMMONWEALTHNote by the Prime Minister .I attach a draft of the statement to be made inParliament tomorrow, revised in the light of the commentsreceived from other Commonwealth Governments (circulated with C. P. (48) 280).The preliminary reports which I have receivedsuggest that there will be no occasion to revise this further in the light of the speech made by Mr. Costelloin the Dail this afternoon in moving the Second reading of the Republic of Ireland Bill.C. R. A.10, Downing Street, S. W. 1.24TH NOVEMBER,  1948.n
DRAFT  statement in 1937 a new Constitution was enacted in Eire in which no reference was made to the Crown.      This, however, left inforce the Eire Executive Authority (External Relations) Act of1936s which authorised His Majesty The King to act on behalf- of.Eire in certain matters within the field of external affairs as and when advised by the Eire Executive Council to do so.      InDecember, 1937, the United Kingdom &quot;Government stated, after con-suit at ion with the Governments of Canada, Australia, Hew Zealand-and South Africa, that they, like those Governments were preparedto treat the new Constitution as not effecting a fundamentalalteration in the position of Eire as a member of the Commonwealth.On 7th September last the Prime Minister of Eire,Mr.  Costello, announced that the Eire Government were preparing to repeal the External Relations Act.      Subsequently, Mr. Costelloconfirmed this intention.As the House is aware,  I took advantage of the presence in London during October of other Commonwealth Ministers toarrange on 17th October for preliminary discussions with eire ministers in order to explore the consequences which would flow from the legislation proposed in Eire.      Representatives ofCanada, Australia and New Zealand, in which there are particularlylarge numbers of people of Irish ancestry, participated in these discussions.Since then the matter has been under constant examina-tion here.      When the Eire Government announced that their RepealBill (to be entitled the &quot;Republic of Ireland Bill&quot;) would beintroduced on 17th November, I thought it.right that the situation should be further discussed with members of the Eire Governmentand with the Prime Minister of New Zealand, the Deputy PrimeMinister of Australia and the Canadian Secretary of State for external Affairs, all of whom were in Paris for the meeting of theGeneral Assembly of the United Nations.      Discussions took place
accordingly in Paris last week.      I should like to take this opportunity of expressing my warm appreciation of the construc-tive part played by Mr.  St.  Laurent, Mr.  fraser, Dr. Evatt andMr.  Pearson in the preliminary discussions.As a result of these discussions the United KingdomGovernment have been able to give the most careful considerationto the relations between the United Kingdom and Eire when theRepublic of Ireland Bill comes into force.      The United KingdomGovernment have also been in touch with the Government ofNorthern Ireland.      The United Kingdom Government recognise with regret that Eire will then no longer be a member of the Common-wealth.      The Eire Government have, however,  stated that they recognise the existence of a specially close relationship betweenEire and the Commonwealth countries and. desire that thisrelationship should be maintained.      These close relations arise from ties of kinship and from traditional and long-establishedeconomic,  social and trade connections based on common interest.The United Kingdom Government, for their part, also recognise the existence of these factual ties, and are at one with the eire Government in desiring that close and friendly relations should continue and be strengthened.Accordingly the United Kingdom Government will not regard the enactment of this legislation by Eire as placing Eirein the category of foreign countries or Eire citizens in the category of foreigners.      The other Governments of the Common-wealth will, We understand, take an early opportunity ofstating their policy in the matter.The position of Eire citizens in the United kingdom will be governed by the British Nationality Act, 19li8.      The eire government have stated that it is their intention to;,bring theirlegislation into line with-that in Commonwealth countries so asto establish by statute that,  in Eire, citizens of commonwealth countries receive comparable treatment.


</content>
</cab>
