<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/31/0 images: 187-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET COPY NO.   1 ICP. (48) 2957TH DECEMBER.   1946CABINETRATES OF PAY.  PENSIONS AND GRATUITIES FOR&apos;  THE PERMANENT WOMEN&apos;S forces memorandum &quot;by the Minister of. defence. . The women&apos;s Services in the Armed Forces havehitherto been on a temporary basis.      The Defence committee decided on 17th May,  1946,  (.D.0.(46) 16th Meeting, Minute 2)that the women&apos;s Services should become a permanent feature of the post-war Forces.      The Army and Air Force (Women1sServices) Act has recently been passed to give effect tothis decision and to enable the A. T. S.   and W.A.A.F.  to be incorporated into the Army and R.A.F,   on the same basis,  asregards discipline,  as men.      It Is,  therefore,  necessaryto settle the rates of pay, pensions and gratuity for womenwithout delay.2. During the late war the women&apos;s Services were paid at about two-thirds of men&apos;s rates - the ratio originallyapproved when the A.T.S.  was established on a non-regularbasis in 1938,     When the new post-war rates of pay for menof the Forces were announced in 1946,  a settlement of the long-term rates for women was held over pending decisions on how the permanent women&apos;s Services were to be organised, and thegeneral conditions of service therein.      As a provisionalmeasure women other ranks were given a flat increase of 8d.a day and officers an increase of ls.0d.  a day.3. The Service Ministers and I have made proposalsfor the permanent code of pay, pensions and gratuities forthe women&apos;s Forces to the Chancellor of the Exchequer, buthe has been unable to accept them.      With his agreement I now submit them to the Cabinet.      They are that the pay ofthese permanent women&apos;s Services should continue to he a fixed ratio of men&apos;s rates,  that the ratio should he increased from two-thirds to four-fifths,  and that the pensions and gratuities of the women&apos;s Services should also be four-fifths of the corresponding men&apos;s rates.There are no retirement pensions for women atpresent:    as for gratuities, the present ratio (for extendedservice) is one-half for officers, and approximately 60^ forother ranks.Particulars cf the rates which would be payable under these proposals are shown in the Appendix to thismemorandum.-1-
Pates of Payu As regards rates of pay a four-fifths ratio isproposed because:-(i)    The post-war pay code for male other ranks was designed to provide broad equality between Service emolumentsand rates of wages for comparable civilian employment.Women in the post-war Services will in general replace menon a one-for-one basis and will be doing virtually the samework as men.      They should in consequence receive a fixedproportion of men&apos;s rates of pay, .and that proportion shouldbe the same as is received by women in the Civil Service orin industry who do the same work as men, viz.  roughly 80%.(iij   Now that the women&apos;s Services have been established on a permanent basis, women will expect a material improve-ment in the two-thirds ratio, which dates from their formationon an auxiliary basis.      The delay of over two years in settling the rates of pay for the women&apos;s Services, and thefact that the Government have in the meanwhile accepted theprinciple of equal pay for women, will have sharpened thisexpectation.(iii)    Unless the new women&apos;s rates show a material improvement and&apos; represent fair remuneration for the dutiesundertaken,  the Services cannot hope to recruit women inthe numbers and of the quality required.5. The Chancellor of the Exchequer has put forward the following reasons for his inability to agree:-(i)   Women in the Forces are non-combatant.      the relationship between their pay and that of Servicemen shouldbe fixed with this difference of liability for combatantduty in mind.(ii)    A four-fifths pay ratio would result in such increases in existing rates, particularly for officers, as would be difficult to reconcile with the Government&apos; s-wagestabilisation policy as set out in the recent White paper on Personal Incomes, Costs and Prices.(iii)    A four-fifths ratio would inevitably lead to equal pay with men if and when the Government decide to implement the accepted equal pay policy in other public services.      Inthe Chancellor s view this would be indefensible.(iv)    For officers of the women&apos;s Services a suitablemeasure of the appropriate rates of pay would be the nationalRushcliffe salary scales for nurses.      A four-fifths ratiowould raise the pay of officers of the women&apos;s Servicesconsiderably above the Rushcliffe scales.&apos;6* The Service Ministers and I cannot accept these arguments for the following reasons(i)    The argument that the pay of the women&apos;s services should reflect their non-combatant status cannot be sustained,since women may be employed, for instance,  in anti-aircraftbatteries, in Fighter Command Operations Rooms and in ferryingoperational aircraft,  and were so employed during the late war.      On the other hand many members of the men&apos;s Services,Cg.  doctors, medical orderlies,  the non-combatant corps,
etc.  receive full men&apos;s rates of pay.      Moreover,  in themajority of duties on which women will he employed,  and onwhich they will he fully interchangeable with men on a one-for-one &quot;basis, a distinction based on a purely contingent liability for combatant service is largely academic.      It isnot,   in any case, possible to establish that any specificelement was included in men&apos;s pay in respect of the liability for combatant service.It should not be thought that,  despite the unrealityof drawing a distinction between men&apos;s and women&apos;s work inthe Services on the grounds that women are non-combatant,such a distinction can be made on other grounds.      The degreeof inter-changeability will be very high.      Women in theR.A.F.  will he required to qualify for promotion by the samestandards as men in the same hranches and trades;    and whenpromoted will have to undertake the full responsibilities ofthe higher ranks.(ii)    The revision of women&apos;s rates now in hand iscomplementary to the revision of men&apos;s rates approved in1946.      It has always been recognised as consequential,  andit would not be justifiable to condition it by reference tothe wage stabilisation policy of the l/l^ite paper on personal incomes, Costs and Prices  (Command 7321).(iii)   Rates for women in the Services have hitherto bornea fixed ratio to those for men, which up to the present hasbeen two-thirds.-     Any departure from the principle of a fixed ratio would be resented by women as a reflection ontheir usefulness and as a breach of faith on the part of theGovernment.      If the ratio is increased to four-fifths itmay, admittedly, be rather more difficult to refuse equal pay when this is given in other branches of the public services.      But it would certainly not commit the Governmentin advance.      The question of equal pay for women in theForces can,  and certainly should, be considered purely onits merits when the time comes.(iv)    The pay of women officers should be related to theduties on which they are employed,  and they will naturallycompare their rates of pay with those of the male officerswhom they are replacing on a one-for-one basis.      To relatetheir remuneration to the rates for nurses,  or indeed to anystandard other than the pay of male members of the Forces,would give rise to a feeling that they are not regarded asan integral part of their own respective Services,  and wouldnot be readily understood by officers,  seeing that their duties bear no resemblance to those of nurses.      This feelingwould be accentuated if the pay of women officers variedwith the pay of civilian nurses and not with that of therest of the Services.Pensions and gratuities7*   ^ Broadly speaking the rates of pensions and gratuities on termination of service to be provided for officers and other ranks of the women&apos;s Services will followwhatever decision is taken on their rates of pay.      TheChancellor considers however that, whatever decision isreached as regards the rates of pay of the women&apos;s Services,an appreciably lower ratio than four-fifths should be appliedto retired pay and retiring gratuities of women officers.He argues that the rates of retired pay for male officers have been fixed to take account of the needs of men retired
in middle lifegenerally with family commitments, and thegrant of pensions at four-fifths of these rates to womenofficers would he over-generous.      He puts forward somewhat similar considerations as affecting retiring gratuities for officers.8. In my opinion,  and that of the Service Ministers,the pensions and gratuities of women officers must hear thesame ratio to those of male officers as does their pay.This would follow the well known analogy of the Civil Serviceand any other arrangement would he extremely difficult tojustify to the women&apos;s Forces or to explain to the House andthe public.      There is no particular element in a maleofficer&apos;s pension which can be applied to family responsi-bilities,  and,  of course, the bachelor gets  the same pensionas the married man.9. For these reasons I ask the Cahinet to agree that -(i)    The pay of the women&apos;s Forces should continue tobe a fixed proportion of the pay of the men&apos;forces.(ii)    The existing,  approximately two-thirds, ratioshould be raised to four-fifths.(iii) &apos; The four-fifths ratio should also apply to thepensions and gratuities of the women&apos;s Forcesboth for officers and other ranks.A.Y.A.linistry of Defence, S.W. 1.7TH DECEMBER,   1948.
APPENDIXWomen&apos;s Service - Other RanksWeekly Rates for Typical RanksNoteThe rates shown in this table are the weekly cashrates payable to women Other Ranks employed on an &quot;all-found.&quot; basis.RankWomen&apos;swartimeWomen&apos;sinterimpayPayposedIncreaseMen&apos;spresentRatesA.C. W. 1. (Trained Private)	23/4	28/-	36/2	8/2	45/6Corporal	30/4	35/-	50/2	15/2	63/-Sergeant	37/4	42/-	67/1	25/1	84/-Plight Sergeant	44-/4	49/-	75/10	26/10	94/6Warrant Officer	5 8/4	63/-	92/2	29/2	115/6These rates are for W.A.A.P&apos;s in Trade G-roup 0 inthe R.A.P.      Thi&quot; is the group in which the majorityof women are employed.      The rates payable to women in the other two Services for similar qualificationsare broadly the same as in the W.A.A.P.
Women&apos;s Service OfficersAnnual Rates (maxima) for each rankNoteThe rates shown in this table are the annualcash rates payable to women officers who also receivefood and accommodation in kind.Rank	Women&apos;s	Women&apos;s	Pay	Increase	Men&apos;s	wartime	inter im	proposed		present	 	pay  	.  	 	Rate  2/Lt. (c)	143	161	190	29	237Lt.     (c)	164	182	219	37	274Capt.(c)	231	.   249	336	87	420Major(c)	353	371	511	140	639Lt. -Col.	408	426	693	267	867(b)					Col.   (b)	552	570	949	.379	1186Brig, (a)	669	687	1124	437	1405Notes(i) The existing rates quoted are those of W.A.A.P.officers, hut Army ranks are given for convenience of reference.      The existing rates in the W.R.N.S.are slightly higher and in the A. T.S.   generallylower than in the W.A.A.P.(ii) (a)    The Director of the W.A.A.P.   draws  151 p. a.additional pay for staff duties in the AirMinistry which would he abolished if thefour-fifths ratio were accepted;    her net increase in pay would thus be  286 p. a.(b) and (c)    Officers of these ranks at the AirMinistry receive additional pay at the ratesof  60 and  45 a year respectively which wouldbe abolished if the four-fifths, ratio were accepted.
Wptnen&apos;s ServicesOfficers&apos; Retired. Pay Rates  (Annual)RankaoorLt.-Col.ColonelBrigadierAge ofCompulsoryretirement43-4947-5250-5552-58Rate -proposed       Men&apos;s rate 380500660720 475625825900Period10 yearsEach year over 10Maximum 19 yearsOfficers GratuitiesAmount proposed . 8001201880Amounts formen 10001502350


</content>
</cab>
