<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/67/0 images: 225-240</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jTTS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT&apos;)j^C R E T.. - Copy No.cabinet.   36  (51 ).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.  10, downing street, S.W.I.,  on WEDNESDAY, July 1st,1931, at 1O.30 a.m.AGENDA.1.      FOREIGN AFFAIRS-     (if required).2.       THE POSITION OF GOVERNMENT BUSINESS.(Reference Cabinet 28 (31)  Conclusion 3).3.      THE MACMILLAN COMMITTEE.Note by the Secretary, covering Report of Committeeon Finance and Industry, together with a memorandum prepared in the Treasury.(CP.  160 (31)    -    circulated herewith).    Iif,      EXPORT CREDITS,(Reference Cabinet 35 (3&quot;0  Conclusion 12).Report of the Cabinet Committee,(CP.  95  O1)    &quot;    already circulated).Note by the President of the Soard of Trade,  coveringextract from a private letter from&apos;a ship-broker.(CP.  161   (31)    -    circulated herewith).&quot;5-...      THE COAL SITUATION.(Reference Cabinet 35 (31) Conclusion 2).C.      RE-ORGANISATION OF THE IRON AND STEEL TRADE.   (if req(Reference Cabinet 35 (31) Conclusion 3).(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.;Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.! 29th Juno, 1 931.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)P. E C R E T. COPY NO.cabinet    36 (51)Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at No.10,Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,July 1st, 1931, at 10.30 a.m.ADDENDUM TO AGENDA.Please add the following ItemjrFUTURE OF SOUTHERN AND NORTHERN RHODESIA.(Reference Cabinet 22(31), Conclusion 10).Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies,.(.C-*P* 162 (31)    r- circulated herewith).(Signed)    M. P. A. HANKEY.Secretary^ Cabinet.,%l Whitehall Gardens, S.-T.1.,30th June, 19 31.
-2-17-(TTgS, PjO^^S^to^^^^^^^&apos;^ JBRITANN IG MAJESTY &apos; 3 GOVERNMENT)S E ORE T. Copy No.CABINET    3JL Hl.-^ CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street^ S.W.1. ,  on WEDNESDAY,.July 1st, 1931, at 10.30 a..m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor, K.C.V.O.,K. C., Lord President ofthe Gouncil.The Right Hon.J.R.  Clynes, M.P.,Secretary of State for home Affairs,The Right Hon.Tom Shaw, C.B.E.,M.P.,Secretary of State forfar,The Right Hon.Arthur Greenwood., M.P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Christopher Addison, M.P..,Minister of Agricu]tureand Fisheries.The Right Hon.W. Graham, M.P.,President of theBoard of Trade.The Right Hon..William Adamson, M.P.,Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.Herbert Morrison, M,Pf,lister f)f Transport.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon,.Lord Passfield,Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.7/. Wedgwood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C.,M.P., Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon.Lord Amulree, G.B.E.,K.C,Secretary of State forAir..The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.H-B. Lees-Smith, M.P.,President of the Boardof Education.The Right Hon.A.V. Alexander, M.P.,First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.The Right Hon.Tf Johnston, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal,THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:-The Right Hon.Thomas Kennedy, M.P.,Chief Whip.-.(For Conclusion 1 ).Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey,  G.C.B.. ,G.C.M.G. ,............... Secretary.
parliamentary business.(previous reference:Cabinet 28(31),  Con-elusion 3.)UNEMPLOYMENTINSURANO E.(previous reference:Cabinet 35(31), Con-elusion 4.)P. R -\COA? MTNESBILL.(previous ousReferences:Cabinet 30(31), Con-elusion 5, and cabinet 35(31)    Con-elusion 2.)HOUSING  (RURALAUTHORITIES)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 35(31), Con-elusion 9.)agricultural marketing BILL(previous reference:Cabinet 13(31), Con-clusion 2.)THE LONDONPASSENGERTRANSPORT- BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 32(31), Con-elusion 19 .)1. The Prime Minister gave the cabinet particulars of the programme he had drawn up fo;adjourning Parliament on Friday, July 31st,which may be summarised as follows:-Time^Availab le:16 full days4 Fridays.SupplyAppropriation ...Unemployment Insurance(No.3) BillCoal Mines Bill  .Rural Housing Bill8 full days .1 full day and1 Friday.3 full days and1 Friday.1 full day(uncertain) .3 full days and1 Friday.Other essential business     1 full day.He was in hopes of being able to make provisionfor the Agricultural Marketing Bill in addition.The Chancellor of the Exchequer gave warning that he would require at least one day for aConversion Bill.^he Minister of Transport laid great stress on the importance of passing the London passenger transport Bill before the Adjournment;    otherwiseLord Ashfield, who had taken considerable risks,would hold himself free from any obligation tocontinue his support.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisherieslaid stress on the importance not only of theAgricultural Marketing Bill but also of theAgricultural Land (Utilisation) Bill.   Unless hecould get this Bill by Michaelmas much work wouldbe thrown away.The Prime Minister explained that the intention was that Parliament should adjourn at the end of
July and meet again early in October in order tocomplete the business of the Session.    It was hoped to begin a new Session before Christmas.Considerable discussion took place as to thepossibility of passing some of the major measures now before Parliament before the Adjournment.    Onesuggestion was that the Unemployment Insurance(No.3) Pill might be postponed until after there-assembly of Parliament, and that if the AdvisoryCommittee were appointed informally and allowed toget to work in anticipation of statutory authority and the Ministry of Labour were to press on withall possible plans and preparations for implement-ing the Bill, not muclh time would be lost.   It was generally recognised, however, that the Governmentcould only postpone this Bill with the assent ofthe other Parties in the House of Commons, asotherwise such postponement would be regarded as a breach of the understanding on which the Unemploy-ment Insurance (No .4) Bill had been passed.AS the result of the discussion the PrimeMinister invited the Parliamentary Secretary tothe Treasury, who was present, to prepare an alter-native programme as a basis for discussion withthe Leaders of the other two Parties for an Adjourn-ment at the end of the first week in August.   TheCabinet felt, hoyjever, that there would probablybe a general desire to adjourn on Friday, July 31st,if this could be arranged.   ,The Cabinet were reminded that an early adjourn-ment was desirable owing to the meeting, of the-Indian Constitutional Committee in September.
The Cabinet.agreed  -To leave it to the Prime Minister,with the assistance of theParliamentary Secretary to theTreasury, to confer with theLeaders and Chief Whips of theother Parties in the House ofCommons with a view to makingthe best arrangement he could forcompleting the Parliamentary pro-gramme before the Adjournment.
REPARATIONS and inter--ALLIEDDEBmS .It -president hoover&apos; proposal.(previous reference:Cabinet 35(31),  Con-elusion 1.)F.R-GERMANY and austria.ProposedCus t omsUnion..(previous reference:Cabinet 32(31), Con-conclusion ion 6 .)F.R.2. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs gave the Cabinet a summary of the latest develop-ments arising out of President Hoover&apos;s proposalfor a postponement for a year of Allied, debts and reparations .   The main difficulty was the french attitude, and the Acting Secretary of State,Washington, had suggested that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should, without the least delay, make representations to Paris in terms as strong aspossible in support of the stand taken by theUnited. States Government .The question was taken up a second time towardsthe end of the Meeting,  after information had beengiven of a further deterioration in the financialposition in Germany, which, if continued, it was recognised must have serious repercussions on london.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that he had spoken on theprevious day very strongly to the German ambassador to the effect that if the German Government wishedto see the present negotiations brought to a success-ful conclusion the best thing they could do would, beto bury or cremate the proposal for an Austro-GermanCustoms Union.   He had also commented on theexpenditure of millions of pounds on &quot;PocketBattleships&quot; at a time when the German financialposition was so serious.    The American proposal for putting pressure on France was more difficult atthe present moment owing to the.fact that the FrenchGovernment had tied their own hands by passingresolutions in the Chamber and Senate.    He could see no way of doing this except at an international conference.
*) 0 ti* &apos;   1 &apos;       *After considerable discussion the cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should sound theGovernments of France, Germanyand Italy, as well as Mr Mellon,the American Secretary to theTreasury, who is at presentnegotiating in Paris,  as towhether,  if invited, they would accept an invitation to attend a Conference in London at the endof the present week:(b) That any questions of detail,for example^ as to whether other powers besides those mentionedshould be invited, should beleft to the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs, in consulta-tion with the Prime Minister andChancellor of the Exchequer as necessary .-5-
991ts  tlFINANCE AND 3.      The Cabinet had before them an advance copyINDUSTRY.  of the Report of a Committee on Finance and Industry,Report of theMacmillan Com-     presided over by Lord Macmillan, which was appointedmitteeF.fc.by the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the 5th Novem-ber., 1929, to enquire into banking, finance and credit, paying regard to the factors, both internal and international, which govern their operation,and to make recommendations calculated to enablethese agencies to promote the development of tradeand commerce and the employment of labour.   TheReport was covered by a Note prepared by the Treasurycalling attention to its main conclusions andrecommendations  (CP .-160 (31)).The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed the Cabinet that the Report would be publishednext week.      The Government would no doubt be pressed to announce their intentions as to theReport, but as it had taken two years to compilethey had a good answer for not making any early announcement.The Cabinet recognised, however-,  that before long it would be necessary for them toconsider their policy in relation to the Report,and it was suggested that a special meeting mightbe necessary for this purpose.The Cabinet agreed  That the Chancellor of the exchequer should arrange for a furthercommentary to be prepared in theTreasury and circulated to theCabinet, with a view to further discussion of the MacMlllan Report.
4..    The Cabinet had before them an InterimReport by the Home Secretary, as Chairman of theCabinet Export Credits Committee (CP.-95 (31))dealing with (A) Heavy engineering material, and(B) Ships ..   As regards heavy, engineering materialthe course which commended itself was that, inagreement with the Advisory Committee, moreelasticity should be introduced into the terms for giving export credits to heavy engineeringmaterial for Russia, and in return the Governmentwould seek to secure as firm an undertaking aspossible from the Russian Soviet representativethat he would cease from his propaganda campaign for an extension of the credit period.   TheChairman of the Advisory Committee was reportedto be not unfavourable and to be sounding themembers of the Committee on this subject,   TheCabinet Committee proposed that if the AdvisoryCommittee agreed with its Chairman the next step should be for the lord Privy Seal to Intimateto the Russian Soviet representative that theExport Credits Committee was prepared to examinesympathetically any proposals for credits uponheavy engineering orders submitted on the basisof not more than 30 months&apos; credit from the dateof order, and that an effort should be made to induce him to accept these terms as final;    after which they proposed to give the Chairman the assurance that the Committee will not. be asked tomake further concessions.   The Committee also recommended that diplomatic conversations shouldbe opened with the German Government in an endeavour to secure a gentleman&apos;s agreement that
Germany would bring her terms roughly into line with those now suggested,  or at any rate would not raise her present terms without consulting theBritish Government.As regards ships the Committee considered thatthe arguments against the use of the Export credits scheme for shipbuilding applied with great force tothe use of the Scheme for the transfer of existingtonnage.    In particular, the risk to the employmentof British tonnage and British seamen now providedby Russian chartering would be made more imminentand would not be offset by the employment whichwould be provided by the construction of ships inthis country.   The Committee&apos;s view was that, forthe time being at any rate, the Government shoulddefinitely decline to recommend to the AdvisoryCommittee any extension of the Scheme to the disposalof existing tonnage.The Cabinet also had before them a Memorandumby the President, of the Board of Trade, covering an extract from a confidential letter received in theBoard of Trade from a ship-broker, illustrating the propaganda efforts of the Russian Soviet, representa-tive (CP.-161 (31)).The Cabinet approved the policy proposed.by the Committee, whichis set forth in CP.  95.(51), and summarised above, and arranged for appropriate action with a view toallaying the feeling aroused bycontinued Russian propaganda.
PHE OGAL 5.     The Cabinet had before them a Report of theSITUATION.Cabinet Committee on the Coal Situation (CP.-163previous (31)) containing a summary of the salient featuresReference:Cabinet 35 of the recent negotiations and submitting to the(31), Con-clusion 2.) Cabinet the following alternative courses off-R. actiont-(l) To let the existing law take itscourse   there can be no question that in the present economic oondi-tion of the industry a 7-hour daycould only be operated with drasticwage reductions in all districts-.These would certainly be rejected by the men and a general stoppageon July 8th would result .(2) To introduce a Bill to extend theoperation of the 7^-hour day, but without spread-over, for 12 months,and also to provide that during thatperiod there should be no reductionin the present rates of wages (exceptin those districts now working the spread-over, In which cases theappropriate reductions would be amatter for local settlement).(3) To introduce a Bill to extend theoperation of the 7-g-hour day, but without spread-over, for a period up to the date of ratification andthe coming into operation of the geneva Convention, but with no otherlimit of time, subject to an under-taking by the Mining Association(in a form accepted by the Miners&apos;Federation) to meet the Miners&apos;, .,Federation nationally before the.expiry of the twelve months guaranteeperiod, and to re-establish the samemachinery as has been in existencerecently for discussing in advancebetween the Mining Association andthe Miners&apos;  Federation the situationwhich will arise on the expiration of the guarantees ..The Committee recommended the Ca-binet toauthorise them to make the best settlement that canbe obtained, and.to arrange for the immediate intro-duction in the Rouse of Commons of any legislation that may be necessary to implement that settlement.
After the Prime Minister had given theCabinet full particulars of the present positionof the negotiations,  the Cabinet agreed --That the Cabinet Committee shouldhave full powers to continue thenegotiations and to make the bestsettlement possible, and to arrangefor the immediate introduction inthe House of Commons of any legislation that might be:.necessaryto implement the settlement reached.
THE IRON ANDSTEEL TRADE.(previous reference:Cabinet 35(31) , Con-clusion 3) -FX6.    The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that,owing to the preoccupations, both of the ministers concerned and the Governor of the Bank of England,it had not yet been possible to pursue the questionof the re-organisation of the Iron and Steel Trade.The subject was continued on.the Agenda.-it-
J.    The Cabinet had before them a Joint Memo-randum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs and the Secretary of State for the Colonies(C.P.-162 (31)) covering a draft of a Statement ofPolicy, which had been agreed with representativesof the Opposition Parties in Parliament, on theFuture of Southern and Northern Rhodesia.    the gist of the Statement was that amalgamation, though not rejected in principle, was premature.    It was proposed that Questions should be asked simultane-ously in both Houses of Parliament on Thursday,July 2nd, and that the text of the draft statement should be read in reply.The Cabinet approved the proposalsof the Secretary of State forthe Dominions and the Secretary ofState for the Colonies,  as setforth in CP.  1 G2 (31) .
FINANCE BILL.W&amp; Tax Clauses,aying Fields.Ipeviousference:cabinet 34fel), Con-fusion 3) *8.      The Cabinet considered the situation thatwas liable to arise on the following day whenthe House of Commons Committee would be discussingamendments proposed by both Parties for the exclusion of playing fields from the operationof the land taxes.      It was suggested that theChancellor of the Exchequer might with advantagesee representatives of the other Parties with aview,  if possible,  to arriving at an accommodation which would be generally acceptable.The Prime Minister said he would try and find time to look into the political aspects of theques tion.whitehall Gardens, S..W.11st July, 1 931.

</content>
</cab>
