<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/9/0 images: 20-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 42(51).				11th June, 1951.



	1.	Japanese Peace Treaty.	[Enter  K.Y.



H.M.	Put our case forcefully to Dulles.  P.M. also saw him.  He can’t

		accept our view on China.  Point of principle with him to give

		J. full sovereignty &amp; not restrict her power to conclude Treaty 

		with China.  But his second point is more decisive:  nothing else

		wd. get thro’ Congress.  ⅔rds majority needed in Senate &amp;

		imposs. to get support of that no. of Republicans.  A most

		diff. situation wd. arise if Congress declined to ratify.

	Can’t find a precedent for course Cab. wished to follow.

	Mustn’t break, save for clear reasons.

	May get some concessions on other points – e.g. Congo Basin, if we

		can yield on this.  Message from Paris tht. they hope to meet us

		on that ques. if we reach agreemt. on the other.



H.S.	Diffces are not worth breaking over.

	Clear tht. U.S. won’t yield.  Not certain Fr. will follow.  But, even so,

		unwise to aggravate misunderstandings with U.S.

	Doubt wtr. in practice terms of Treaty will be decisive on China.

	Believe we may then get our way on Congo Basin ques.  Of more

		immediate pol. &amp; practical importce.



P.M.	D. was quite firm on main point when I saw him.

	We haven’t much option – tho’ I don’t like yielding.



H.G.	Annex:  Formosa:  para. 4.  We don’t want J. to recognise F. as

		belonging to Chiang.  Wd ease our posn if we cd. get it more

		firmly stated that future settlement wd. be “by U.N.” e.g. adding

		“by them”.



G.W.	Also the words “in the same spirit”.  That raises same point.



McN.         	i)	Disingenuous to say tht. with U.S. occupn force in J., J. cd. 			conclude Treaty with Peking.  Nothg. in that.

                 	ii)	Normal to limit sovereignty in a Peace Treaty.

		But I can’t press my point.

		Para. 4:  Don’t like refce to rights of people of F.  Better drop it 		than include these patronising words.



H.D.	We are being pushed off our posn.  Effect will be unfortunate.

		Believe J. will recognise Chiang.

	Para. 4.  No sense in refce to people of F.  This shd. be wholly re-cast.

		Decn by U.N. isn’t v. safe:  S. American satellites of U.S. too

		strong there.  Wd prefer it settled by F/E. Commn group.

	Latest developmt:  R. has asked to be included in Treaty.



P.M.	R. suggn to C.F.M.  We cdn’t accept that.  Brings in France &amp; leaves

		out Doms.

H.D.	No concession on Congo.  If we yield on this ques., must have our way

		on that.



R.R.S.	If J. recognises Chiang, how cd. we defend that position?



H.M.	Why suppose that.  J. has gt. econ. interest in agreemt. with Ch.

		mainland.

	Gt. diffy of J. will be dependence on certain raw materials – iron, 

		coal, oil, rubber, bauxite etc.  Suppliers can influence her 

		therefore.  Welcome continuing U.S. occupn:  better than going 

		Communist.

	On para. 4 I will do my best to meet criticisms, with wh. I sympathise.



H.D.	No refce to wishes of people of F., who are under Chiang’s heel.



E.Sh.	Stop at “U.N.”  Doesn’t even say there tht. U.N. will “settle” it.

	Fact is that U.S. will dominate J. policy for years to come.  We can’t

		avoid that.



H.S.           x/	Amendments pencilled in draft.

	J. won’t recognise Chiang unless U.S. does.  Not much difference.



H.M.	We may not want F. to go to Comm. China.

	Shd. we side-step U.N.?  Who will the signatories be?  We put F. on

		U.N. Agenda.



J.	Not nec. to recognise one authy for Ch. &amp; F.  J. will prob. recogn.

		Peking as Govt. of mainland.  They may recognise Chiang as 

		Authy in F. – for so long as he lasts.  When he goes, it doesn’t

		follow tht. inhabitants wd. join with m’land (?).

	Concede this point to U.S. in return for satisfn on Congo Basin.



	Shipbuilding.



McN.	If we are bargaining, can we get limn of ship-bldg. into Treaty.



H.M.	Don’t believe we can get it in Treaty.  No real risk for many years.



McN.	Content with Cab. Minutes of 7/6.  Means H.M. can’t conclude all

		Treaty on Thursday.



	Japanese Gold.



H.G.	How tough are we to be on this?  Pol., not financial.



P.M.	Press D. hard on Gold &amp; Congo Basin.



H.M.	You won’t get the gold.



H.D.	Point of presentn:  it wd. help us with our public opinion.

H.M.	If we don’t insist on gold (wh. we shdn’t get) we cd. get the other

		financial concessions.



H.G.	We don’t want much of the gold.  The ques. is wtr. it is to be left in

		J. hands.  Better if U.S. took it, on trust pro-tem.



J.G.	Posn of our p.o.w. is more diff. because U.S. have paid theirs.



			Agreed:  Accept Dulles main point, subject to insistence

			               on Congo Basin &amp; pressure for not allowg. J. to

			               retain her gold.

			               Adjust para. 4 of announcement.

						[Exit  K.Y.



	2.	Four Power Meeting.



H.M.	No one agreed with me – on any point.

	U.S. are firm on their line.  Fr. are lookg. for concessions.

	As we can’t agree on a note, we are going to resume talks in Paris.





	3.	Foreign Office Officials.



H.M.	Due to make a statement to-day.  Maclean has done v. well in F.O.

	All we know is tht. they have disappeared.  May be a security aspect.

		But no evidence yet that there is.  Can’t say much to-day.



P.M.	Doubtful moral characters.  Aren’t F.O. a bit easy over this.



R.R.S.	Maclean re-called from Cairo.  Why?



H.M.	Drinking.  Is that enough to sack him.



R.R.S.	Also attempted rape.



H.M.	Burgess was under consn for dismissal.  Re-called from W’ton.



J.	Is the system strict enough.  Shd. people of doubtful moral 

		character be employed in F. Service – either qua representation

		or qua security.



P.M.	What is standard of conduct in F. Service.  Is it high enough?



H.M.	We don’t know, one way or the other, wtr. they may have been

		engaged in espionage.



				[Enter  N.B. &amp; Dr S.

	4.	Supplementary Pensions for Miners.



N.B.	Expounded memo.

J.G.	Hope we can agree with Union on this.



E.S.	Hope we shan’t.  This wd. jeopardise discns in other cases.

		We started this in order to recruit under-ground workers.  We

		make a concession for that reason only.



H.G.	Support M/N.I.  Whole point of this is repercussions.

	I favoured some scheme for mines:  but want it limited to under-

		ground workers.  If it goes beyond that, can’t hold other

		socialised industries.  Thence it will go into private industry.

		And in the end will cause pressure for increase in M/N.I. rates.

		Stand firm.



A.R.	Must be realists.  Once a scheme is put fwd. for one section of 

		industry, the men will demand its extension.  The man

		underground won’t leave his pal outside.  You must choose

		betwn. no scheme or a comprehensive one.

	But, if concessions are to be made, let N.C.B. give them.  Don’t let

		it appear that Union has swung the Govt.



E.Sh.	Can’t divide miners betwn. underground &amp; surface.

	You’ll have to accept this. For N.U.M. will insist on it.

	Better therefore to agree to it now.



T.W.	Trouble is definition of surface worker.  What of coke ovens assocd

		with collieries?  Rlwaymen. on engines at surface?  Collieries

		on N/E. coast where collierymen work the coal down to docks

		&amp; act as rlwaymen &amp; even dockers.

	But if N.U.M. support the surface-men, we shall have trouble.

	Trouble either way.



H.M.	Cost per ton?



N.B.	About another 1d, only.  Out of about 1/=.



H.M.	Sad story.  We knew on S.I.M. tht., if this spreads to other socd

		indies, it will go over all industry.  Means, not only heavy

		addn to on-costs, but also immobility of labour.

	Whole case for this was based on underground miners – in order to

		get the coal.  We told Chairmen of Bds. it wd. be so limited.

		Where do we end?  Heavy costs on industry:  diff. re-actions 

		on N.I. scheme:  immobility of labour.



P.M.	Choice is between going the whole hog or w’drawing the scheme.



H.G.	V. serious consequences of going whole hog.  	



P.M.	Always was gt. danger of it’s spreading.



H.M.	We cd. have pleaded a special case for underground workers.

P.M.	You cd. make same case for “miners” – because of diffy of 

		discriminating.



J.G.	Wd N.C.B. make it condn of recruitment tht. man shd. go below, 

		if requd.



H.M.	Discussions ought to be carried out by Bd., not Minister.



N.B.	We interfered at outset:  wdn’t allow them to discuss, save on

		scheme wh. wd. be acceptable to us.



P.M.	Minister can let N.U.M. talk &amp; then tell them negotns are for the Bd.

		Then he can tell the Bd. to give way.



A.R.	Let the mtg. be informal.



N.B.	I can’t avoid seeing them.  They know we have given directions to Bd.



			Agreed:  N.B. to see them, but alone, not with other

			               Ministers.

				[Enter  N.B. &amp; E.S.

				[Enter  Willey

	5.	International Wheat Agreement.



	Memo. approved.



H.G.	Dollar balance isn’t favourable.

	M/F. to press on with agreemt. with Australia – also rice. 



</content>
</cab>
