<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/82/0 images: 9-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TS;i3 Document is the Prcrrv;&apos;.7 etannic lV.ajeoty&apos;8 Gr/osvi nom.li*W!.Vl*UMlCI*J.*^i*&quot;&apos;..&apos;^&apos;*&apos;&apos;&apos;*l&quot;&apos;t&quot;/IgRESTRICTION OF ALIEH LABOUR. (Circulated by the Home Secretary). ^should be glad if the War Cabinet would decide the question raised  WALL attached memorandum by the Aliens and Nationality Committee on thesubjeot of continuing the existing restrictions on the employment of Aliens.18th June, 1919. E.S.I.....-......................................-------------......--------article&apos;22B of the Aliens Restriction Order provides that no person shall take steps to obtain the services of.aliens or any alien not in the United Kingdom for non-munitions work in the United Kingdom except with the permission,.in writing, of the Minister of Labour.    This provision came into force in October, 1916.    Up to April 1919 the total number of permits granted was 3,054 involving 4,373 persons while the number of persons refused was appraximately 1,190.    The principal occupations entered by aliens in respect of whom permits had been granted were those of teaohers, domestics, clerks, shop assistants and variety artistes.    The grounds on which per-mission has been refused may be summarised as follows(a) That the employer was politically undesirable, e.g. suspected of trading with the enemy.. (b) That the employee was politically undesirable, e.g. suspected -of being a pro-German,(c) That the work was not of importance in the national interest, o.g. a luxury trade.(d), That it was thought that British labour could be suppliedfor the performance of the services required by the employer.On the cessation of hostilities the grounds on whioh it is desirable to refuse permission to enable aliens to enter the country for the purposes ofA&apos;employment have naturally become modified.    The importance of the first three  grounds specified above has diminished, while, from the point of view of the Ministry of Labour in particular, the fourth ground is the main one upon which it is desirable to place a restriction on the immigration of alien employees.    Briefly the main arguments for the continuance of the Article under postwar conditions are:-(l) To prevent aliens taking work when a surplus of unemployedBritish labour is available and (2) To prevent aliens taking work in this country at sweated rates.It will be noticed that the number of persons affected by the Article has been comparatively small during the war but it is clear that under peace conditions the problem will increase greatly in magnitude.    Since the Armis-tieo the huiaber of applications has steadily risen and at present the number of applications for permits amounts to some 300 a week or 15,000 a year, of which rather more than two-thirds are being refused.    About two-thirds of the
r2r .applications relate to men and one-third to women,    Many are for domes-tio servants but large numbers uro received for shop assistants and skilled men.      The experience of the Ministry of Labour shows that there is abundant evidence that if it were known that the restriction imposed by the Article were removed there would be an even larger move-went of alien labour towards this oountry than the numbers involved in tho present applications for permits,    For the next year or more, therefore, drastic restrictions would appear to be necessary to pre-y^nt the labour market being flooded by aliens.    The problem will become acute as soon as shipping facilities from places like Poland are available.    Having regard inter alia to the fact that there ai*e over a million persons unemployed in this country the question 1b how the wholesale entry of alien employees oan be prevented or controlled.    The alternatives appear to be.&quot; -(a) Maintenance of Article 22B in its present or some modifiedform.(b) Revocation of the Article and an attempt to deal with theproblem by means of the powers which immigration officers will exercise under tho new Aliens Restriction Order.To take the latter alternative first, under the new Order Immigra-tion Officers will be able to exclude from this country persons having no definite reason for coming and persons who although looking for employ-ment have no specific work in view, but it will be difficult for them in most cases to refuse admission to any alien who is able to produce satis-faotory evidence that he has a definite job awaiting him and it will be impossible for them satisfactorily to investigate rates of wages or con-ditions of employment.    A considerable loophole would, therefore, be left for the admission of aliens who may bo competing with British un-employed labour and undercutting British rates of wages.    On the other, hand there are admittedly objections to the continuance of the Article, In the first place the continuance of the Article is opon to the general objections which have been raised to the maintenance of Government Oontrol %f Trade and Industry.    There is also the possibility that the Article may be represented as a piece of Class Legislation intended to exclude the working class alien coming to employment in this country, while leaving untouched tho better class business man whose presence here might well be represented as even less in the national interest.    It would, of course, be necessary   - oarefully to guard dgainst the cry that tho Art* icle was being used in any way for the purposes of excluding foreign Trade Union delegates from this country.    On the whole any opposition from Trade Unions is improbable and in fact protests against the admission of alien workers have already been received from the Musicians&apos; Union and the withdrawal of the Article might lead to protests from tho A.S.E. and other Unions in trades in which there is unemployment.    Finally the difficulty arising from the conflict between Article 22B and our Oommor-oial Treaties may be mentioned (tho Legal Advisors of tho Foreign Office are being consulted on this point).
ftAfter a very full consideration of the arguments for and against the continuance of the Artiole the Aliens and Nationality Committee recom-mend that it should be continued for a period of at least  twelve months after the end of the war but they think it would bo advisable to re-draft the Article so as to provide that an alien being desirous of entering the &apos; service of an employer in the United Kingdom shall produce to the Aliens^. Officer at the port of arrival a permit in writing for his engagement issued by the Minister of Labour to the employer&apos; i     This alteration they consider necessary as in its present form the Article lays no obligation on anyone except the prospective employer.    A neoessary corollary of the continuance of the Article will be the maintonanoo of a strict control by the Immigration Officers over all aliens who are not under a contract of service but who seek to enter the United Kingdom with a view to obtaining employment.     The whole question is one of great national importance and having regard to the issues involved the Committee think that the continu-ance of the Article might properly be submitted for a Cabinet decision.

</content>
</cab>
