<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/82/0 images: 34-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.MINISTRY  OF  FOOD.Report for Month ending 15th June 1919./ K PART I. ACTION TAKEN.In connection with the general question of the demobilisation of the Ministry, the question of food prices is of primary importance.The expectation held out by the Prime Minister, in addressing the Joint Industrial Conference, of a decline by the summer of 4s. in the cost of food to the average working-class household has been more than realised. The actual decline from November 1st to June 1st (on the basis of the average working-class budget calculated by Lord Sumner&apos;s Committee on the Cost of Living) is 4s. 9d. per week. There is no reason for doubting that &quot;this saving will be maintained during the next few months.So far there is no ground for anxiety. From -another point of view, however, the position is less satisfactory. The saving of 4s. 9d. per week, on the basis of Lord Sumner&apos;s budget, represents a reduction of only 10 per cent, in the cost of food at the end of the war. Even this saving is largely due to seasonal decreases in the price of milk and eggs. There is no prospect, as matters now stand, of any large further decrease in the cost of food, and in the autumn there is every prospect of an increase. The cost of food next winter, though it will almost certainly be lower than last winter,, will probably be higher than it is at present.The high prices of food&apos; are not solely, or mainly due to shortage of supplies. There is a general depreciation in the value of money owing to the inflation of currency by war credits and other causes, and the cost of production of all articles of food as measured in money is correspondingly increased. Where an article obtains a scarcity value, however, it is possible to restrict the increase in price by means of control, but even here the measure of the restriction is governed by the necessity of obtaining supplies in the open market of the world. It is not anticipated that there will be any general world shortage of foodstuffs during the coming winter, and that being so the principal problem is to provide sufficient shipping to bring the necessary supplies to this country. If supplies are assured, trade competition will generally keep the prices at as low a level as is compatible with world prices.At present the Ministry is faced with various difficulties arising from uncertainty - as to the future of the Department.   On the one hand there is the decision of Sir Auckland Geddes&apos; Committee favouring a policy of progressive and comprehensive decontrol, which would bring the Ministry to an end about November 15th.   This was confirmed by the War Cabinet on May 5th.On the other hand there has been a persistent demand from organised labour for continued control and for the retention, as a minimum, of such measures of control as may be calculated to assure the public that the Government are taking steps to protect the consumer during the coming winter. Of rate this demand has been reflected in influential quarters.While the Ministry is still in this position of difficulty and doubt, the technical members of the staff are returning or pressing for permission to return to their private occupations and the seriousness of the administrative problem arising from the actual and threatened loss of these officials has been emphasized by the recent instruction requiring definite Treasury sanction for each new appointment.The Food Controller has addressed a memorandum to the War Cabinet asking that this state of uncertainty may be resolved at the earliest possible date as he feels that the present state of affairs not only makes it difficult to deal with specific problems, of great urgency, but also lowers the general prestige of the Ministry in the absence of a clear and settled policy.Liquidation Department. As the future of the Ministry is still unsettled, and as the amount of administrative work in regard to the control of food is still considerable^ Sir Auckland Geddes has been advised that the Department cannot be regarded as-a  (33)8265   Pk 16  150  6/19  B &amp; S A
being in a state of liquidation and could not with advantage be transferred either in whole or in part to the proposed Liquidation Department which is to be established for winding up the affairs of the various War Ministries. Sir Auckland Geddes has also been informed, however, that should the administrative responsibility of the Ministry cease, the transference of all liquidation work to the proposed Department will be desirable.Future of the Sugar Commission. In view of the great uncertainty as to future world supplies and prices of sugar, it now appears to be desirable to continue the work of the Sugar Commission to a later date than that previously contemplated, which was the end of the present year. It has been decided accordingly that the Sugar Commission will continue in business and make purchases on the basis of having three months supply of sugar in stock at the end of the financial year, March 31st, 1920. The decision will be reconsidered in the beginning of December 1 next with a view to deciding whether still further purchaBes should be made by the Commission. In this connection it is to be pointed out that after the end of the present year, or at any rate after March next, it is improbable that either the Sugar Commission or private traders will be able to place sugar upon the market at prices -calculated to permit of the maintenance of the present retail price. It will then be necessary, therefore, to raise the retail price of sugar to the public, or to ask the Treasury to incur a financial loss either by reducing the present sugar duty or by consenting to the Sugar Commission having a substantial deficiency when it is wound up.&apos; . De-control of the Flour Mills. -The Royal Commission on AV neat Supplies have recommended that as from 31st December next, the present control of the Milling Industry should be removed and the Flour and Bread (Prices) Order withdrawn. This will enable the Commission to dispense with the staff of one of their adminis-strative branches, and will free an entire trade from the uneconomical management which inevitably results from control with a guaranteed remuneration. The Royal Commission will sell imported wheat to the millers on a scale of prices governed by the relative intrinsic values of the various grades of wheat to the average miller and the scale will be fixed at a level calculated to produce the 9d. loaf under normal -conditions of milling and baking. This will involve the maintenance of a bread subsidy, but the amount will be much less than the present payment. The Cabinet .has been asked to sanction the proposal put forward by the Royal Commission.De-control of Oils and Fats. The announcement of the decision of the War -Cabinet that control of seeds, oils and fats would cease on May 31st coincided with -a considerable relaxation of blockade restrictions. This led not only to a general forward buying of fats on behalf of neutral countries but also to a revival of speculative purchases which resulted in the price of raw materials being needlessly raised by &quot;Something like 50 per cent.The principal manufacturers of margarine thereupon informed the Food Controller that unless the controlled prices were taken off raw material they would be unable to manufacture the requisite amount, and, further, that if the high level of importers&apos; prices continued they could not sell the manufactured product to the trade at the fixed [price of 87s. Id. per cwt. They expressed their willingness to maintain their price to the trade on a strict parity with the price of imports, and offered to fix the wholesale price of an adequate amount of margarine of approved quality at stated intervals in - i   ^advance so that the retail price should not be varied without notice.As the resumption of Government purchase and distribution, as a temporary measure, is not calculated to afford any protection to the consumer commensurate with the cost of setting up the machinery, and the considerable dislocation of trade which the adoption of this course would involve, the Food Controller has accepted the offer of the manufacturers and has also advised them that while he is prepared to give them every assistance in his power, it is incumbent on them so to organise themselves as to be free from any suspicion of profiteering at the expense of the consumer. All Orders controlling price have accordingly been revoked, while a general licensing Order has been issued under which the Ministry retains authority to examine specifications, to restrict the use of materials and products, to make requisitions and to impose standards of quality. In the case of margarine it is proposed to insist on a minimum proportion of animal fats. It has further been decided tp frame an Order restricting dealings in raw materials to persons and firms licensed by the Food Controller; the linseed oil traders have expressed a desire that linseed should be included in the scheduled list oi seeds.
During recent weeks there has been some irregularity in the supply of margarine, but the Shipping Controller has promised to procure increased facilities for the shipment of raw materials, and as the normal manufacturing capacity of the United Kingdom is half as much again as the quantity absorbed by the 5-oz. weekly ration, it is not anticipated that there will be any shortage in the future.Supplies and Distribution.Meat. The long continued drought, unequalled at this season during the last 25 years, has delayed the arrival of grass-fed cattle on the market, and as the stall-fed cattle season is practically at an end, it is anticipated that there will be a shortage of home-killed meat during the next few weeks. Many live stock areas already show a marked decrease in the quantity of stock marketed and it has been decided that in the circumstances butchers&apos; permits shall be honoured in live stock and home-killed meat to the extent of only 25 per cent, of the total quota. This course will probably lead to complaints from the producing areas, but as the home-killed meat will not exceed 25 per cent, of the total supplies for some time the restriction is necessary in order to ensure equitable distribution throughout the country.The original estimates of the consumption of imported meat during the months of March, April, and May were 196,000 tons, while the estimate for June was 70,000 tons, and it was assumed that these quantities would be available. The actual consumption during March, April, and May amounted to only 116,000 tons, but although this was 80,000 tons below the estimate, it reduced the stocks by 23,000 tons in the three months, so that on May 31st they stood at 31,000 tons. The revised estimates furnished by the Board of Trade showed that in the three months, April, . May, and June there would be about 115,000 tons of imported meat available for civilian consumption, and the amount released during April and May has corresponded closely with this estimate of the supplies. It is probable, however, that between 40,000 and 50,000 tons will be required during June, an amount in excess of the estimated monthly quota. It will be necessary, therefore, to supplement supplies by drawing on the War Office stocks, and it has been ascertained that no objection will be raised to this course. It is anticipated, therefore, that the demands for June will be met without difficulty. The situation in the early part of July still leaves room for anxiety and much will depend on the date of arrivals ; by the middle of the month, however, all requirements should be assured.Milk. The supplies throughout the country are uniformly satisfactory.ISlumerous representations have been made on the subject of the prices fixed in the Milk (Summer Prices) Order 1919, but after careful consideration and reference where necessary to the Travelling Commission, the Food Controller is of opinion that no evidence has been produced in justification of any alteration in the prices already fixed. The scheme for the collection of 2d. per gallon on milk exported from the four South-Western counties and on milk used for manufacture of milk products in these counties has been put into operation. The amount thus collected for the period from 1st to 17th May is 17,7001, This sum with the further amounts collected will be utilised for the benefit of the public in the reduction of the price of milk or milk products or in some similar way. The question of the permanent control of the milk trade is still under consideration, and a memorandum in. which a scheme for the establishment of a Central Milk Board is outlined has been placed before the Central Agricultural Advisory Council for their consideration. It is anticipated that this scheme will secure an increased quantitity of milk with an improvement in quality; prevent domination of the trade by private organisations ; effect economies in the wholesale and retail distribution of milk, and equalise distribution in times of shortage.The control over the distribution of condensed milk of which the supplies are now ample ceases on 31st May, except that a maximum retail price is still retained.Butter. In view of the general position of the butter market, it has been decided that no reduction should be made at present in the retail price of butter, which is 2s. Qd. per lb. Practically the whole of the Ministry&apos;s programme for the purchase of butter from the various exporting countries has now been sanctioned by the Treasury, and in addition to the contracts made in Australia, New Zealand and the Argentine purchases totalling 57,500 tons have been arranged for from Ireland, Denmark, Siberia, &amp;c. Owing to a drought in Australia, the production of butter there has dropped from a normal amount of 30,000 tons to about 12,000 tons and as this was aA   K265      &apos; A 2
source of relatively cheap supply, the deficiency will have an adverse effect on the Ministry&apos;s Buying Account as it necessitates the purchase of: dearer butter from other sources.Bacon, Earns and Lard. With the retention of a maximum retail price and the freeing of the various wholesale prices from control, complaints continue to be received from retailers as to the difficulty of selling bacon without loss as a result of the higher prices charged by wholesalers. The Food Controller has received a representative gathering of wholesalers and warned them that in their own and in the National interest, every effort must be made to keep down prices even at some pecuniary sacrifice.The arrivals of bacon during May amounted to almost 40,000 tons, which was little short of the estimate. The Ministry of Shipping have promised to reserve 60,000 tons of shipping for June, viz., 25,000 tons from Canada and 35,000 tons from the United States. The shipments of bacon on Government account are .now completed.Lard, is in short supply and strong demand with rising prices on a free market. It is being bought heavily and arrivals are likely to improve. The Belgian Govern-ment have offered the Ministry sixteen, million lbs. of lard bought from the United States. A difficulty as to the method of payment has arisen, the Americans having asked for payment by dollars in New York whereas H.M. Treasury hold that the price should be set off against the dollar indebtedness of Belgium. It is expected, however, that a satisfactory arrangement will shortly be made.Tea. In spite of increased supplies, prices at the sales have risen during the last three weeks and the demand for tea remains strong. The balance of Ministry tea to be shipped stands at 5,000 tons and although it had been intended to stop shipping on behalf of the Ministry at the end of May and to cancel these contracts, it has been decided in view of the general situation to carry through the purchases in question. Private traders are able to find tonnage for Indian tea, but difficulty is being experienced in bringing supplies from Ceylon and an effort is being made to obtain a special allocation of shipping in this respect.Cocoa. Imports are satisfactory, and manufacturers are increasing their already large stocks. As a result of the revocation of the Raw Cocoa (Prices) Order, cargoes intended for Havre have been diverted to this country, and parcels earmarked for export have been secured by home manufacturers.Potatoes. The hot weather during May has had- an adverse effect on the consumption of potatoes, but it is not anticipated that there will be a very heavy surplus on June 30th. The Ministry has announced that it will be prepared, to pay for any sound potatoes which remain on farms on that date.The American, French, Norwegian, and Swedish Governments have failed to take delivery of the quantities of potatoes which they contracted to buy, and claims for compensation have accordingly been made by the Ministry. The American War Department has agreed to pay 600,0001. in consideration of the cancellation of the balance of their contract, which amounts to about 80,000 tons.Rationing and Distribution.The modified system of rationing which has been in force since May 3rd, has proved successful and no serious shortage or inequality in distribution has been reported in respect of meat, butter or sugar. The special arrangements for allocating increased supplies to holiday resorts have worked smoothly.The Divisional Food Commissioners report a general feeling that the policy of de-control should not be carried out too rapidly. A certain irregularity of supplies in margarine and bacon, following on the de-control of these articles, has led to some apprehension as to the future on the part of the public. The difficulties with regard to bacon are largely due to the high prices charged by wholesalers with the result that retailers, being left with no sufficient margin of profit under the Maximum Retail (Prices) Order, are unwilling to accept supplies. In the case of fish and milk, the irregularity of supplies in certain districts is attributed to transport difficulties.The duties of Lord Granard and of the Food Control Committee for Ireland have been undertaken by Mr. Hugh Barrie, Vice-President of the Irish Department of Technical Instruction and Agriculture.
Orders Under Defence of the Realm Regulations.v The Order dated 27th May 1919, amending the Intoxicating Liquor (Output and Delivery) Order, 1919, increases the total annual output of beer to 26 million standard barrels.The Edible Fats (Standard of Quality) Order, 1919, dated 30th May 1919, con-tinues, with slight modifications, the provisions contained in Orders now revoked, as to the quality of edible fats, and includes margarine.The following are the principal Orders that have been revoked since May 14th :--Sugar (Domestic Preserving) Order, 1918. Cheese (Requisition) Order, 1917. Dutch Cheese (Prices) Order, 1917. Dutch Cheese (Requisition) Order, 1918.Importers (Returns) Order, 1918, except in so far as it relates to cheese.The Maximum Prices Orders relating to margarine, shredded suet, vegetarianbutter, oil and fat compound, seeds, nuts and kernels, oils and fats. The Calves (Sales) Order, 1918, and portions of other Orders relating to calvesand veal.   The revocation of these Orders removes the control from calvesand veal.The Oats (Scotland and Ireland Restriction) Order, 1918.Enforcement of Orders.The total number of prosecutions during the four weeks ended May 31st was 2,541, of which 92 per cent, were successful.Difficulty has been experienced in enforcing the regulation prohibiting the sale of new bread, both Food Control Committees and magistrates being averse to strong action in the matter.PART II.-SUMMARY OF THE FOOD POSITION.Stocks.Owing to the improved rate of arrivals of cereals in May the decrease of stocks in the United Kingdom during the month, viz., 88,000 tons of wheat and 254,000 tons of other cereals, was much less than in April. Stocks o  wheat remaining on 1st June were 280,000 tons less than those held a year before, but stocks of other cereals on the same comparison were 82,000 tons up, owing to larger stocks of oats held this year. Stocks of wheat on 1st June represent over 9^- weeks&apos; supply, or 73 per cent, of our requirements for the remainder of the cereal year. Of the total stocks of wheat and flour within the country on June 1st, inclusive; of estimated stocks in millers&apos; and bakers&apos; hands, and those still on farms, 35 per cent, was returned as held by the Ministry.Of the stocks of meat and provisions in cold stores and importers&apos; warehouses on 1st May and 1st June, stocks of refrigerated meat (82,500 tons) showed a very large increase of 30,600 tons, making total stocks equivalent to 3-g- weeks&apos; total requirements of butcher&apos;s meat. Stocks of canned meats remained at the high level of 31,000 tons, or approximately a pre-war year&apos;s supply. Bacon and hams showed little increase, and stocks on 1st Jane were little more than a third of those of a year before. Stocks of cheese, though still very low, marked a considerable improvement. on the preceding month, and those of butter showed a smaller advance in continuation of a, steady rise which has proceeded for the last few months. With continued small imports of lard, stocks fell by a further 3,300 tons, though the total on 1st June was still equal to that of a year before.Stocks of sugar (285,000 tons) remained satisfactory, even after a decrease of 32,000 tons. The high stocks of tea showed a further slight increase, and additions were also made to the very large quantities of coffee and cocoa held in the United Kingdom which represent about two years&apos; and one year&apos;s supply respectively.Imports.The weekly rate of imports of the principal foods and feeding-stuffs (Table B) which was 158,900 tons for April, continued to rise steadily to the end of May, the receipts for the last week of the month being 241,700*tons, and the weekly averagea 3
for the month 219,200 tons. Although the arrivals for the first week of June (220,600 tons) showed a decrease on the high figure of the preceding week, they fully maintained this average. The rate of improvement was very marked in the case of cereals, the weekly rate for which in April was 75,300 tons-; during May total arrivals in one week reached 154,100 tons, and the average was 125,600 tons, or 67 per cent, above that for April. Arrivals of frozen and preserved meat, with a weekly average of 20,600 tons for May, were almost double those for April, and also double require-ments for the month, but the consequent increase of stocks will all be required during the period of small home supplies in the next two months. Bacon imports fell off at the end of the month to one half of those at the beginning, and the average (8,6u0 tons), taken with tome supplies, barely met current requirements. Sugar arrivals were little below the high figures for April, and the total net imports for the month (199,000 tons) compares favourably even with the pre-war receipts at this season. Up to the end of May butter continued to arrive in relatively satisfactory quantities, and the rate of cheese deliveries showed a marked improvement on preceding months, but both fell away sharply in the first week of June. Arrivals of lard were still only about three-fourths of the average for this year, and were little more than half current requirements. Tea, coffee, and cocoa arrivals show no signs of falling off from the very high level of recent months.Consumption.Butchers&apos;&apos; Meat.-The highest point in the scale of prices of cattle and sheep was reached on 1 st May, and consequently supplies were very large at the beginning of the month, thereafter falling off. Estimated supplies of home-grown butchers&apos; meat reached approximately 20,000 tons in the week ended 10th May, while those for the last week of the month were .15,500 tons. Releases of refrigerated meat after falling from 9,200 tons to 5,900 tons in the first two weeks rose again to 9,600 tons, but the net result was a tendency for total consumption to decrease from the high level of the beginning of the month. The estimated average loeekly consumption by civilians in Great Britain during May was 25,600 tons, of which 8,000 tons, or 31 per cent., was imported meat; this shows a considerable increase on the weekly rate a year before, viz., 15,500 tons, of which 6,100 tons, or 40 per cent., was imported, and it does not Jail very far short of the rates for May in 1916 and 1917, viz., 27,000 tons. The demand for rationed meats in May represented about 78 per cent, of the supply as based on the ration and extra supplies available for butchers and caterers.Flour. Deliveries of flour from mills and releases of flour from imported stocks reached a minimum point during April, while the local emergency stocks accumulated earlier in the year Avere being used. In May they showed a sharp rise to 102,400 tons per week, as compared with 81,800 tons for the preceding month, and 98,500 tons for May 1918. The rate of delivery during the first five months of this year has been about 8 per cent, above that for the corresponding months of last year, thus indicating an increase in consumption.Fish. The following table illustrates supplies of fresh fish during the month. There was again a very large increase in the total landings in spite of. local labour difficulties at the ports, but the quantities received at the large urban markets failed to reflect this increase. The figures suggest that owing either to transport difficulties or other causes, the best possible use is not being made of the present large supplies:- -Fish Supplies in May. 	May 1919.	April 1919.	May 1918.ILK. landings, monthly total   -	64,000	4.5,700	34,200Coastal markets, average weekly supply  -	9,100	7,000	4,200Provincial markets, average weekly supply	2,000	1,700	1,700Billingsgate Market, average weekl)- supply	3,600	3,000	2,300Other Foodstuffs. During May, owing to the non-arrival of expected Australian and New Zealand supplies, the distribution of cheese remained on a 25 per cent, basis. With estimated total supplies of home cheese, this represented about 1,700 tons per week available for consumption within the United Kingdom, as compared with the pre-war weekly quantity of 3^000.   Weekly production of margarine in May reached
7,400 tons in the United Kingdom as compared with 3,800 tons a year before. Owing to the removal of restrictions on its use in baking and other industries, not all of the larger quantity was available for retail sale. The distribution of butter remained on the basis of 2 oz. per head, which was approximately the quantity distributed a year before. Free home supplies at this season are a very important factor, and as there is no reason to believe these are much, if any, below those of a year ago, total supplies of butter and margarine for direct consumption Were probably over 2,000 tons in excess of those of May 1918.Prices.There was a further fall in retail prices during May. The increase since July 1914 on June 1st was 104 per cent, as compared with 107 per cent, a month previously, and 133 per cent, on November 1st, 1918.The chief movements during the month were in imported meat, fish, margarine and potatoes. The official maximum price of imported meat was 2d. lower. Fish fell 10 per cent, but, although 26 per cent, below the price of a year ago, is still 114 per cent, above the pre-war level. Margarine rose 2d. a lb., or 19 per cent., to llfa\ There was a seasonal increase in the price of potatoes amounting to 6 per cent.; they are 21 per cent, dearer than a year ago. 1 Bacon, and eggs showed small fluctuations ; the former was up 1 per cent, the latter down 2 per cent. The other main commodities showed no appreciable change in price.Wholesale prices of cereals in May showed little variation ; after the slight ten-dency to rise in April, British wheat and barley each lost a penny per quarter, but oats showed an increase from 47s. 5d. to 48s. per quarter. There were considerable changes in meat arising from Government action ; home-grown beef advanced from 116s. 8a7. to 119s. per cwt. and mutton from 123s. Sd. to 126s. per cwt., in accordance with the scale of prices to farmers which reached its maximum point in May ; on the other hand the differentiation of home and imported meat prices led to decreases in the latter, beef falling from 116s. Sd. to 100s. 4d. and mutton from 123s. Sd. to 107s. 4a7-. per cwt. Canadian bacon, free from control, rose from 184s. 5d. to .190s. per cwt., and tea in similar circumstances rose from li\d. to Is. per lb. for Indian, and from life/, to Is. 0\d. per lb. for Ceylon tea. There were marked increases in the group of oilseeds and oilseed cake : linseed rose from 597s. 6a7. to 960s. per ton, the average for May being 863s., and the jump in palm kernels was even greater, 920s. per ton being reached in the third week of the month as compared with an average of 516s. 3d. per ton for April. The increases in cake were not; so considerable, Egyptian cottonseed rising from 297s. Qd. to 300s., and palm kernel from 275s. to 283s. per ton.
Table A.-Summary for May.				Stock, June 1st.		Commodity.	Stock, May 1st.		Home Production.					Net Imports.		Quantity.	Number of Weeks&apos; Supply,		Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tous.	Wks.	Days.Wheat (including flour)	1,494,000	-   513,000	 	1,406,000	9	4Barley     -      -     -     -	198,000	38,000	 	146,000	7	3Oats -     -     -          - -	797,000	6,000	 	628,000	16	5 ,Maize.....	72,000	49,000	 	48,000	2	5Rice ------	142,000	* 4,000	 	132,000	26	3Butchers&apos; meat  -     -     -     -	51,900	80,600	75,000	82,500	3	2Bacon and hams       -      -      -	28,800	34,700	6,000	31,200	2	6Lard ------	16,300	4,500	700	13,000	4	2Butter     -      -     -     -	13,000	12,900	10,500	17,700	5	6Margarine -     -     -     -     -	1,700.	 	33,100	3,000	0	3Cheese     -     -     -     -     -	6,000	14,200	6,300	9,000	2	6Sugar      -      -	317,000	199,000	 	285,000	11	4Tea -     -     -	70,500	18,200	 	72,400	24	1Coffee	42,100	6,900		47,600	95	0Cocoa      -     -     -	52,000	11,600	 	58,600	51	0Oilseeds, &amp;c.     -     -     - ... . \-	286,600	59,300	 	204,000	6	6Oilcake and meal      -	64,700	5,700	75,000	96,700	9	5* Re-export.i
									Average Weekly Net Imports* in 1913. 6.	Total Imports,	Article. -1.	Week ending June 7th, 1919. 2,		Week ending May 31st, 1919. 3.		Week ending May 24th, 1919. 4.		Week ending May 17th, 1919. 5.			23 Weeks from Dec:. 29th, 1918 to June 7th, 1919. 7.	Corres-ponding Period. 1918, 8.1. Wheat-2. Wbeatenflour 3. Rice   -4. Beef    (fresh and refrige-rated). 5. Mutton (fresh and refrige-rated). 6. Meat, unenu-merated (re-frigerated and      pre-served). 7. Bacon     and Hams. 8. Lard   -9. Butter -10. Margarine   -11. Cheese 12. Condensed milk. 13. Sugar (refined and      un-refiued). 14. Sugar,glucose	Tons. 63,480 46,275 436 265 3,715 8,242 1,479 852 &apos; 247 3,849 53,998 1,277		Tons. 97,375 18,725 479&apos; 6,434 7,417 5,412 1,587 912 2,454 3,550 51,823 1,469		Tons. , 113.285 27,745 528 15,854 3,431 2,726 8,285 940 3,363 4,900 2,076 34,288 668		Tons. 75,170 24,310 6,649 15,815 8,315 6,699 6,334 1,055 3,121 1,682 1,321 49,231 886		Tons. 101,378 9,712 2,554 8,849 5,125 2,126 5,267 1,629 3,867 1,460 2,137 742 37,333 1,408	Tons. 1,333,250 321,810 66,549 154,146 63,734 94,239 230,695 33,534 46,436 30,093 45,749 727,059 23,239	Tons. 987,570 750,970 239,552 179,632 .48,018 71,337 284,304 55,451 53,306 15,298 36,557 48,191 586,953 14,736Total	184,115		197,637		218,089		200,588		183,587	3,170,533	3,371,87515, Barley -16, Oats   -17. Maize -	4.010 1,100 18,045		14,485 2,965 19,020		10,435 &apos; 2,665		9,840 490 5,135		21,565 17,464 46,450	107,695 74,890 324,880	186,310 102,160 520,985.   Total	23,155		36,470		13,100		15,465		85,479	507,465	809,45518. Tea    -19. Coffee, raw -20. Cocoa, raw -	9,246 1,707 2,376		3,453 1,653 2,469		4,925 1,223 2,117		5,233 1,892 2,007		2,640 319 542	91,772 32,103 67,398	90,772 3,318 10,322Total	13,329		7,575		8,265		9,132		3,501	191,273	104,412Grand Total  -	 20,599		241,682		239,454		225,185		272,567	3,869,271	4,285,742		Net Imports.		*		A verage Monthly Net Imports* in 1913.		Average Monthly Net Imports. *		Total Net Imports. *		Month ending May 31st, 1919.	Month ending April 30th, 1919.		Month ending May 31st, 1918.				5 Months Jan.-May, 1919.	Oorres-ponding Period. 1918.	5 Months Jan.-May, 1919.	Corres-ponding Period, 1918.11 . 21. Oil seeds and nuts   : and kernels. 22. Oilseed cake 23. Oils,    vege-table, refined and   unre-fined. 24. Oi!, fish, train, blubber, aud-sperm. 25. Stearine	Tons. 59,279 5,746 1867 4,836 5,746	Tons. 87,610 &apos;   25,807 9,992 3,990 354		Tons. 96,667 6 9,511 .  4,359 400		10US. 120,314&apos; 29,436 6,690 5,424 304		Tons. 109,833 20,469 10,091 2,725 154	Tons. 95,075 939 5,282 3,364 154	1 ons. 549,190 102,343 50,455 13,627 772	xons. 475,373 4,694 26,412 16,822 769* Imports less re-exports of Foreign aDd Colonial Produce and less exports of British Pioduce of the same kind, -j- Ee-export.Table B. Imports of Principal Food and Feeding Stuffs.
STATISTICS ILLUSTRATING CONSUMPTION.Table C.--(l)-Weekly Consumption of Flour and Butchers&apos; Meat in theUnited Kingdom.[The figures are based upon quantities of imported food-stuffs released for consumption, plus&apos; estimated home production.]	Flour.	Butchers&apos; Meat. &apos;Army demands from U.K. Stocks and Supply :-	Tons.	Tons.May 1919 - -     -     -     -     - &apos;   -     -     -	1,300	1,500For Civilian Consumption : 		Average for 4 weeks ended : 		March 29th.........	99,900	24,900	97,200	26,50012th.....-	93,800	27,70019th.........	89,400	27,700 -26th.........	85,100	25,800May 3rd     -     -.......	86,700	25,60010th    -     -     -.....	91,600	23,60017th - -     -     - ,   -    .-     -           -	97,400	24,80024th    -     -     -      -     -     -     -	102,700	27,40031st     -     -     -     -.....	101,100	27,700(2) Animals Slaughtered in 9,836 Private and Public Slaughterhouses in Great Britain in March 1919, and April 1919.	Cattle.	Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	figs.March 1919.........	170,919	128,294	332,680	129,477	159,728	121,959 .	364,971	118,523Percentage Increase or Decrease : April 1919 compared with March 1919	&quot;6-6 0/0	-4/9 7o		-8&apos;50/c table D. Index Numbers illustrating Changes in the Rate of Consumption of Butchers&apos; Meat by the Civilian Population in the United Kingdom.[The rate of consumption in May 1917 is taken as - 100.]JanuaryFebruaryMarchAprilMav  -June -July -AugustSeptemberOctoberNovemberDecemberHome Fed.1916.1917.119 111 113 100^931898796 109 101 119 121101  921 lOlj1008488 1021 1031 114&quot; I10 9611918.1919.Foreign.Total.1916.19.17.1918.1919.67157&quot;59554341i54641in79&quot; 741 671611 59 671 64^119 135 1611 1361 1441 138i 165&quot; 137 1131 99 124 14814811191 93 951100&quot; 921105116 881 911 901135118 961114119115519011721177&quot; 801 241 481120&quot;214 196 214 20841916.1917.1181113^119&quot;105100 95^ 971101&quot;1091081119124107*96&quot; 100981 100&quot;8690 104 1001, 110&quot; 107 10U1918.73^62Jj66i63458l62701807871701751919.83. 78 88 84^
	June 1st. 1919.	May 1st, 1919.	June 1st, 1918.Article.				Slocks in the United Kinsrdom including estimated Farm Stoeks. &apos;		&quot;Wheat (including flour)  -Barley   -         -        -         -Oats      - . Beans Peas&apos;	Tons. 1,406,000 146,000 628,000 88,000 61,000	Tons. 1,493,000 199.000 797,000 86,000 70,000	Tons. 1,686,000 302,000 298,000 71,000 40,000	Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, &amp;c.		Maize    -         -         -         -Rice (including ground rice and rice flour) drain Meals      -Sugar    ------	* 48,000 132,000 58,000 285,000	72,000 142,000 50,000 317,000	154,000 159,000 55,000 271,000	Stocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and in Importers&apos; and Wholesalers&apos; Warehouses.		Butter   -                            ... Margarine         -         -         -         -      &apos; -Lard     -        -        -        -Cheese   -        -        -Condensed Milk -Meat:-Beef (chilled and frozen) Mutton (chilled and frozen) Bacon and Hams         -               -&apos; -Poultry, Game, and Rabbits Other Meat Fislr  ! -   &apos;     -     -   -    &apos;    -               &apos; -	17,700 3,000 13,000 9,000 32.800 41,900 31,000 31,200 7,400 40,600 -    32,300	13,000 1,700 16,300 6,000 . 26,000 30,000 15,300 28,800 1,600 37,700 33,200	15,400 1,900 13,200 7,900 14,400 41,700 32,700 90,200 14,000 ,   23,600 . 20,900	Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.		Tea      -        -&apos;        -         -        -        -Coffee    -        -         -         -        -    .    -Cocoa    -        -        -        -        -     . -	72,400 47,600 58,500	; 70,500 42,100 52,000	41,500 43,900 -   26,800	Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports and in the hands of Millers, Crushers, and Cake Manufacturers.		Oilseeds, &amp;c.     -        -         -        -        -Oilseed Cake and Meal  -        -         -        -	204,000 96,700	286,600 64,700	.-   213,800 37,800   .Number of Live Stock in Great Britain.-	May 4th, 1919(Kstimated).(j	April 4th, 1919(Estimated).$	i June 4th, 1918	May 4th, 191S(Estimated).$	June 4th, 1917.Dairy Cattle Total Cattle Ewes kept for breeding Total Sheep Sows kept for breeding Total Pigs -	3,060,000 7,320,000 8,900,000 21,000,000 290,000 1,940,000	3,130,000 7,250,000 9,000,000 &apos; 18,500,000 300,000 1,900,000	3,030,000 7,408,000 9.498,000 23,338,000 306,000 1,825,000	2,980.000 7,250,000 9,280,000 22,500.000 270,000 1,750,000	2,907.000 7,437,000 9,899,000 24,043,000 269,000 2,051,0005 Estimates prepared by the Live Stock Committee of the Board of Agriculture.Table E. Stocks of the Principal Foods and Feeding Stuffs in the:   . . United Kingdom.The figures for wheat and flour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, inland warehouses, mills, and bakers&apos; shops, as well as estimated stocks on farms ; those for barley, oats, beans, and peas include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills, in maltsters&apos; hands, and estimated farm stocks ; those for maize, rice, and grain meals include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills.The figures for sugar are stocks in possession of the Sugar Commission ; those for butter, margarine, lard, cheese, condensed milk, meat, and fish include stocks at ports, in cold stores, and in importers&apos; and wholesalers&apos; warehouses.The figures for tea, coffee, and cocoa are stocks remaining in bonded warehouses or entered to be warehoused; and those for oilseeds and oilseed cake include stocks at ports and in the hands of millers, crushers and cake manufacturers.
Table F. Ministerial Stocks in the United Kingdom.Approximate Date,Commodity.						November 1st,	March 1st,	April 1st,	May 1st,	June 1st,	1918.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.Wheat (including flour)	979,100	815,800	576,000	494,000	496,000Oats       -	56,700	104,000	118,000	133,000	127,000Maize     -      -      -	12,000	67.900	28,000	29,000	15,000Rice-     -     -      -	155,000	138,700	139,000	130,000 317,000	105,000Sugar	414,000	230,000	242,000		285,000Butter    -     -	6,600	12,000	13,200	19,500	20,000Lard             -	23,600	23,900	18,900	10,700	6,300Cheese	25,200	9,000	6,000	7,600	10,500Eggs	4,900	300	30	-	 Frozen meat	33,300	54,400	39,000	21,400	31,600Bacon and hams	40,000	44,400	21,000	23,700	9,400Tea -	34,000	51,400	47,500	39,000	32,400Table G-. Percentage Inorease in Retail Food Prices in the United Kingdom, at each of the Undermentioned Dates, as compared with&quot;Normal Prices in July 1914.&quot;Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.)					Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.										Article.																1st Jan.		1st July		1st Jan.	1st July	1st Nov.	1st Jan.	1st Mar.	1st April		1st May		1st June		191&quot;		1917.		1918.	1918.	1918.	1919.	1919.	1919.		1919.		1919.	Beef :-															British-Ribs    -	64-	2	96	1	80-5	84-8	102-7	102-4	83-6	83	8	84	1	84	2Thin flank -	83-	5	132	2	100-9	98-2	126-2	125-9	97-5	97	9	.98	4	98	7Chilled or frozen 															Ribs -    -	85-	4	119	6	116-4	147-9	175-4	175-4	147-9	147	9	147	9	120	3Thin flank    -	101-	2	156	5	137-3	164-7	206-5	206-5	164-7	164	7	164	7	122	9Mutton : 															British-Legs	58-	7	100	0	76-8	85-5	102-3	102-3	84-4	84	6	84	8	85	1Breast	84	2	142	2	92-5	80-8	106-5	106-2	77-6	77	9	78	4	78	7Frozen Legs   -	86	4	134	4	134-0	176-5	205-6	205-6	176-5	176	5	176	5	147	breast	122	0	190	8	161-8	168-5	217-4	217-4	168-5	168	5	168	5	119	7Bacon, streaky *	56	3	76	4	138-7	138-3	141-7	141-1	140-5	137	9	139	3	142	2Fish &apos; -     -     -	131	1	127	1	195-9	189-7	167-4	166-3	158-6	153	5	136	9	114	2Flour   -     -     -	88	5	109	3	51-8	52-1	52-2	52-3	52-2	51	9	51	9	51	8Bread   -	73	3	100	3	54-4	54-5	54-8	54-9	55-0	55	0	55	0	55	2Tea	50	9	73	7	98-2	73-3	73-3	73-3	73-3	64	8	64	7	63	2Sugar, granulated -	170	0	187	7	189-3	240-3	241-3	241-3	241-8	241	8	241	8	242	milk    -     -    1 -	56	6	59	7	99-5	77-3	141-0	153-9	158-0	156	3	84	5	82	2Potatoes	121	7	144	3	37-1 ,	57-1	59-3	57-3	63-9	66	3	72	-3	83	6Margarine	25	0	73	5	65-9	68-8	97-0	68-8	47-6	27	2	38	-4	64	3Butter, fresh -	72	9	64	7	103-4	97-3	106-8	107-4	107-6	107	5	107	-5	106	8Butter, salt   -	70	6	65	3	105-4	102-4	112-3	112-6	112-9	112	7	112	-6	111	cheese, Canadian or															. u.s.*   , -	74	8	108	0	91-2	93-6	130-2	130-3	129-5	106	9	106	-7	106	6Eggs, fresh   -	175	0	95	3	242-1	248-3	412-1	347-2	285-7	206	5	200	-9	194	6* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative, -j- Decniase.

</content>
</cab>
