<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/82/0 images: 121-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
87From Secretary of Stale to Viceroy, Foreign Department,lUh June 1919.Priority A.   Clear the line.Foreign Secret. Your telegram No. 888 S., dated 16th June. Afghanistan. His Majesty&apos;s Government are glad to learn that you find it possible to place favourable interpretation on Amir&apos;s letter. Its general purport appeared to us much more questionable while tone of certain passages, e.g., boast about warlike qualities of Afghans and reference to supposed difficulties of British Government struck us as defiant. Nevertheless we appreciate full force of arguments adduced in your telegram under reply, and we do not propose in all the circumstances of case to insist on resumption of hostilies against advice of Your Excellency&apos;s Government. We trust that your belief in Amir&apos;s realisation of our strength will prove well-founded.Turning to your specific proposals we concur generally in terms of draft letter, to Amir. But question of first of your armistice terms as stated in your telegram No. 793 of 3rd June seems to us to require clearing up. It appears plain that Amir has rejected this demand but it is not equally clear whether Your Excellency intends to, insist on its acceptance. Question of precise distance from our lines to which Afghan troops should be required to withdraw is one that may be left to military authority, but it must in any case be made essential condition that all Afghan troops shall be withdrawn from our side of Durand line. This should be stated plainly in your letter to Amir. You should also make it plain to him that no further modifications of armistice conditions will be permitted. Subject to modifications in above sense your letter may issue at once.I shall be glad to receive very early indication of your views as to final peace terms. Matter is of great importance as whole question of our future relations, both with present Amir and with Afghanistan, is involved.

</content>
</cab>
