<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/82/0 images: 234-234</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A G.T. 7552* Mo Document r&apos;&apos;* ^--^iliHiJalegty&apos;8 Go7eni7^rTt3Viceroy, Foreign Department, 22nd June 1919. (Received 11 p.m.)Clear the line.Your telegram of 19th June. Letter to Amir, amended as directed, issued yesterday.   Text is as follows : &quot;To the Amir of Afghanistan. I have the pleasure to acknowledge the receipt of your friendly letter No. 6, dated 1.1th June 1919, corresponding to 12th Ramzan 1337 Hijra. You say &apos; Your Excellency will see the signal proof of my good intentions in my acceptance in a reasonable manner of your terms for armistice.&apos; At the same time you point out your difficulties in carrying out literally the first and third terms. My friend, I appreciate those difficulties. But you have misunder-stood what was meant by first term. All I demanded was that your regular troops be removed from frontier to a distance of 20 miles from nearest British force. I understand you have given practical effect to this provision except in vicinity of New Chain an where I must ask you to do so at once. Further, I am informed there are still some Afghan troops on our side of frontier notably in vicinity of Peiwar Kotal. These must be immediately withdrawn. So long as a single Afghan regular soldier remains on our side, peace negotiations are out of the question and there can be no alternative but a resumption of hostilities. I said nothing in first term of armistice regarding removal of villagers and tribesmen from their homes. But I must ask you to issue orders against any gatherings of such tribesmen in vicinity of our military forces. Should such gatherings occur and threaten our forces I have authorised my Generals to take the necessary steps to disperse them.&quot;2. As regards third term, what you say regarding your difficulties has been understood by me. Nevertheless my aeroplanes must continue to reconnoitre in order to secure my troops against such hostile gatherings of tribesmen. I look to you to issue strict warning to your people against molesting them and I have every confidence that your orders will be effective. If our aeroplanes are molested they will retaliate.&quot;3. You do not mention fourth term. I assume from this that you have done what is necessary. If not I must ask you to do so without delay. For at a time when peace negotiations between us are pending it is impossible to leave tribes in a state of doubt-and excitement, and it lies with you, whose actions have excited them, to warn (? them) on the (? lines) laid down.&quot;4. Finally, I must make it plain to you that His Majesty&apos;s Government will not allow any further modification of armistice terms. I sincerely hope, therefore, that you will now (? accept) what I have written, and carry out what I have asked, in a spirit of genuine friendliness, for on this must depend initiation of peace negotiations between us. On this understanding I shall be glad to issue orders for reception of delegates you name at Rawal Pindi.&quot; 5. 1 have appointed Sir Hamilton Grant, the Foreign Secretary to the Govern-ment of India, to be chief of British delegation, and, assuming that you accept my conditions, I shall be glad if you will kindly inform him of the full numbers of party you are sending, and the date on which they will reach British lines. Arrangements will then he made for their conveyance to Rawal Pindi. The names of other members of the British delegation will be intimated to you in due course.&quot;6. I also on my part look forward, please God, to a bright future in the re-establishment of friendly relations between two Governments.&quot; (Signed)     Chelmsfoud.&quot;In communique giving resume of both letters emphasis is laid on friendliness of Amir&apos;s reply, fact that he makes no attempt to traverse our indictment of Afghan aggression, his claim that his own action has already achieved practical cessation of hostilities, his plea regarding difficulties in literal fulfilment of our terms, and his acceptance of Rawal Pindi. Passages &quot;May it be known . . . . places of world,&quot; and &quot; Your Excellency will see ... . two Governments,&quot; are quoted verbatim.   Communique runs over all points in Viceroy&apos;s reply.

</content>
</cab>
