<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/82/0 images: 339-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
From Viceroy, Foreign Department, -Hilt June 1.919. (Received 26th, 3 p.m.)Clear the line.933 S. Afghanistan. Your telegram of the 19th June. We regret that His Majesty-s Government have not been able to accord the policy we advocated a more unqualified support.We ourselves did not.formulate our advice without some misgiving.   We agree that, on first reading, certain passages in Amirs letter sound boastful, if not defiant. But careful analysis of letter as a whole in light of correspondence and events that led &apos; up to it, of Afghan psychology and of traditional style affected by Amir, satisfied us that our interpretation is correct.- In weighing probability of Amir&apos;s sincerity (vide our Army Department telegram 8207, dated 17th June), and in judging also of effect of Amir&apos;s overtures and our answer on our prestige, it must be remembered that Amir&apos;s direct overtures were sequel to our twice repeated refusal to accept indirect overtures.While weight of evidence is in favour of Amir&apos;s sincerity we have throughout envisaged possibility of Amir being under the impression that time is not on our side, but on his, and have made our&apos;military preparations accordingly. But if Amir is sincere, he is sincere not because he regards Afghanistan as vanquished, but simply because he realises our strength.We can, of course, vanquish Afghanistan, but only at cost of: prolongation of war with its attendant dangers probable breakdown of stable Government in Afghanistan, thereby opening- Afghan door to Bolshevism, probably necessitating occupation of parts of the country by our troops, and involving inevitable reaction on frontier, and India already gravely perturbed over Turkey&apos;s future.His Majesty&apos;s Government seem to have contemplated possibility of an immediate resumption of hostilities. But such a course would have involved us in a danger which you warned us in your telegram of the 17th May, 2053, and which wo have throughout been most anxious to avoid. Bolshevik propaganda skilfully manipulated from Tashkend is preaching that we are bent upon an aggressive war on one of the few remaining Moslem powers. Had we resumed hostilities after the Amir had fulfilled our demand conveyed through the Afghan Envoy that he should send us copy of his orders to his Generals, after he had induced practical cessation of hostilities, and after he had in the main complied with our terms, we feel that this would have been interpretation placed on our action by the Moslem world.There now seems to be signs of growth of anti-Amanulla faction. Had Amanulla adhered to his war-at-any-cost policy, we should have welcomed these symptoms. As it is, we are impressed with the urgency of making pence with Afghanistan while there is still a stable Government to treat with, and we are not altogether confident that we are still in time. Initiatory negotiations would undoubtedly go far to stabilise that Government. ,We have throughout endeavoured to deal dispassionately with a situation fraught with difficulty. And having placed position fairly and squarely before1&apos; His Majesty&apos;s Government, wo trust that they will now assure us of their unambiguous support. It is impossible to conduct a policy successfully unless .v . there is accord between authority ultimately responsible for it and authority charged with carrying it out.

</content>
</cab>
