<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/82/0 images: 477-478</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(SHIS DOCUTOST. IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT AMI 0 MAJESTV&apos;S GOVE1HMMT),.361SECRET. 0 WAR CABINET.PERSONS IN GQVFRNMl?lft. SFP.V1CF, HOT OF I BRITISH OR KLLTM) ftARF&amp;TAGB.(Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.)My attention has been called to the draft Minutes of the War Cabinet Meeting cn June 26th With reference to the employ-ment In Government offices of persona net being cf British or Allied parentage. /The Minutes state that after some discussion it was decided that the Committee appointed by War Cabinet Minute 577 - (2) under the Chairmanship of the Minister of Labour to con-sider the question cf finding employment for disabled soldiers in Government service should be requested tc examine the cases of persons employed by the Government of whom Lord justice Bankes Committee were unable to report that definite national reason existed for continuing their employment.The War Cabinet appears to have acted under a misapprehension-hension of fact.   The Committee in question was appointed by but is not presided over by the Minister of Labour.The-primary function of that Committee is to determine hew and to what extent people temporarily employed could be got rid of to find employment for disabled soldiers.The persons of foreign parentage in question are not temporary employees at all but people who have been admitted to the permanent civil Service of the State.Much more important is the fact that the Committee is a purely departmental one consisting entirely of departmental tfficials.   sir M. Ramsay of the Treasury iSr Chairman and the other members are Mr. A.W. Watson and Mr. Shearme of the Ministry of Labour, Mr. Tinniswood of the Ministry of Pensions, and Mr. Corcoran of the War office.Even for its original purpose the Committee bo con-stituted was not a very strong one, and it has sought to        f strengthen itself by co-opting Sir Thomas Elliott as an additional member, but even so the Committee is purely departmental and it is quite incompetent to deal with the question whether or not these particular people of alien parentage 3hculd be employed in the Civil Service.   Its findings on such a question could carry no weight at all with the public and I think the Government would be criticised by the public if it announced that it had referred such a question to such a committee.The Bankee&apos; Committee was set up in consequence of a   decision of His Majesty&apos;s Government that no person should&quot; be employed in any Government Office during the present war who had not certain qualifications of birth unless&quot;There was a definite national reason for such employment.   The Com-mittee reported in February but no action was taken in regard* $    War Cabinet Minute 5851.
to any cf the oases which it reported upon.   Now the far is ever and the findings of the Committee which were directed exclusively to a reference which concerned the condition&apos; . of affairs during the continuance of the War have no necessary relevance to the situation which now arises since peace has been signed.A new state if things therefore has arisen and if the Government are if opinion that the continued emplcyment in the public service cf these persons who were not turned out while the VTar was proceeding (and served all the time without any complaint of their conduct) cannot be justified without exceptions then me possible course is to have the fresh situation re-examined by a Committee on their behalf but this Committee should not be a departmental Committee cf Civil servants sitting in judgment on their fellowas but a committee cf Ministers vho must give a ruling,   Personally I can give no support to any proposal now to drive out of the Service men who have been retained in it throughout the t?ar, vTreasury, g,w.2nd July, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
