<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/190/0 images: 107-108</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT.]                   Printed for the Cabinet.  December 1927.SECRET.                                                 COPY NO.  ^0CP.  312  (27).CABINET.  SPECIAL    REPORT   ON    UNEMPLOYMENT.                  No. 152.    November  1927.    THIS Report  gives a  summary  of  the  recently  published returns ofunemployment  in the various industries.  In Table (A) is shown the course ofunemployment during November, while Table (B) gives an analysis of the numberof persons on the registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at the28th November, 1927.(A.) NUMBER OF PERSONS ON THE REGISTERS OF EMPLOYMENT  EXCHANGES IN                          GREAT BRITAIN.	1025.	1926. J 1927. i						INCREASE (H-) OR DECREASE ( ) SINCE OCT. 31,1927.	NOV. 30.	NOV. 29.	OCT. 31.	1 NOV. 7. NOV. 14. 1 NOV. 21.			NOV. 28.	MEN .. ISOYS .. WOMEN GIRLS .. TOTAL..	937,434 29,131 172,582 26,128	1.170,615 36,913 251,371 37,168	SS4,984 33,371 156,617 31,085	884,737 33,452 162,092 31,370	897,050 32,756 165,407 30,522	898,163 32,532 165.S48 29,711	916,845 32,050 167,069 29,266	4- 31,861 - 1,321 4- 10,452 - 1,819	1,165,275	1,496,067	1,106,057	1,111,651	1,125,735	1,126,254	1,145,230	4- 39,173   NOTE (1) : THE ABOVE FIGURES REPRESENT THE NUMBER OF PERSONS REGISTERED AT LOCAL OFFICES AS applicants for EMPLOYMENT.  IN THE MAIN THEY RELATE TO PERSONS WHO HAD CLAIMS TO BENEFIT CURRENT AND WERE NOT ATWORK ON THE DATES GIVEN.   (2) THE FIGURES FOR THE 29TH NOVEMBER, 1926, WERE AFFECTED BY THE DISPUTE IN THE COAL MININGINDUSTRY.   (3) THE LATEST FIGURE AVAILABLE, VIZ., FOR THE WEEK ENDED THE 12TH DECEMBER, 1927, IS GIVEN IN PART (D)OF THIS LTEPORT.(B.) ANALYSIS OF THE NUMBER OF PERSONS ON THE REGISTERS OF EMPLOYMENT       EXCHANGES IN GREAT BRITAIN AT THE 28TH NOVEMBER, 1927.-	MEN.	. BOYS.	WOMEN.	GIRLS.	TOTAL.	INCREASE ( 4-) OR DECREASE (-) AIUCE OCT. 81, 1927WHOLLY UNEMPLOYED TEMPORARY STOPPAGES CASUALS TOTAL	649,703 202,221 64,921	25,232 6,693 125	89,119 77,209 741	24,054 5,191 21	7S8.108 291,314 65,808	4- 35,199 4- 1,977 4- 1,997	916,845	32,050	1.67,069	29,266	1,145,280	4- 39,173[10957]
     The percentage of unemployment (Great Britain) in the insured  industries atthe undermentioned dates was          November  23, 1925   ....       ....       ....       ....  107                     22, 1920   ....       ....       ....       ....  13-3                     21, 1927   ....       ....       ....       ....   9&apos;9 (men only 117)                    (C.) UNEMPLOYMENT IN INSURED INDUSTRIES.     The latest date for which unemployment figures by industries are available is the 21st  November,  1927, at which  date the  percentage unemployed in GreatBritain   and   Northern  Ireland  was  10&quot;0,  as  compared  with  9*5   at   the24th October, 1927, with 13*5  at  the 22nd November, 1920, and with 11*0 at the23rd November, 1925.   The figures at the 21st  November,  1927, in  respect ofindustries  showing appreciable variations in unemployment  during the  month,together with  the increase or decrease  as compared with the  previous month audwith a year ago are given in the table below : Industry. Insured Persons  recorded as  unemployed at Nov. 21, &quot;1927.Increase (-1-) or Decrease (-)     compared witli Oct. 24, 1927.Nov. 22, 1920.&quot;Number.  Per-centaffe.Number.  Per-ceiitasru.Number.  Per-eentage.All Insured Industries   ..      ..I 1,209,686 I   10-0-h 53,418   4-0-5Building       ..      ..      ..   111.7S7 !   13-2Cotton..       ..      ..      ..    09,653 J   12-2Textile Bleaching, Printing-, Dye-  ing, &amp;c.     ..      ..      ..    15,843 i   13-public \v&quot;orks, Contracting, &amp;c.   ..    32,483    19-2Tailoring             . .      ..    18,481     9-2Distributive Trades     ..      ..    82,671 J    5-2Steel Melting  and Iron Puddling  Furnaces, Iron and  Steel  Rolling  Mills aud Forges     ..      ..    41,988 1   21-6llotel,  Boarding  House,  Club  Services     ..      ..      ..;   30,400     9*7Dress and Mantle Making and Mil-  linery       ..      ..      ..     6.412     6*1Coal Mining    ..      ..      .. j.  221,751,   18-5Manufacture of Tin Plates      ..&apos;     6,009,   18-015,787 6,957 3,489 &apos;&apos; 3.314 I 2,950 2,670+  1-9+  1-2+  2-8+  2-04-  1-54-  0-12,549 I  4- 1-32,4062,3391,9722,272-i-  0-74-  2-2-  0-2-  7-1-420,456* !- 3-5*&quot;+   6,018-  40,669-   8,909-   5.471-   9,870-  21,49552,000 3,987- 0-8-  7-7- 3-9- 5-4- 1-7-27-2-  2-0-   1,644  !  -  1-44-110,385*   4-  9-9*-   9,5 S8   -30-5    * The figures for the 22nd November, 1920, were affected by the dispute in the Coal Mining Industryaud in the case of the Coal  Industry itself the unemployment figures were exclusive of persons in theindustry who ceased work on account of the dispute.                               (D.) LATEST FIGURES.     The latest  figure of unemployment  published  is that for the 12th December,giving the total number on the  registers  as 1,125,200.    This is a decrease overthe  position on the 28th November amounting to 20,030, and a decrease over ayear ago of 285,178.                                                ARTHUR STEEL-MAITLAND.Ministry of Labour,         December 20, 1927.

</content>
</cab>
