<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/190/0 images: 293-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
214(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY CF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S GOVERKMS3TO)SECRET.CP, 325 (27),COPY NOs   &apos;^jOCABINET.ITAVAJJ PROGRAMiSELie; mora ndurn by the Firs t Lord jo f the Admiralty.O c*P.505(27).I much regret that the Naval Programme Committee suggest a reduction or one cruiser in 1928,     It is true that in the next three years our cruiser position is not endangered.     If this reduction is made in the number cf cruisers to  be  laid dovm in 1927 and 1928- the Admiralty de3ire t-j place  on record that  this will result in the ultimate number of  orxiisers being below the minimum requirement of 60 under 20  years;  unless in seme subsequent years the deficiency is  made rood by laying down more than throe  cruisers a year.     The building programme Committee of 1925 had this fact  in view -rchen they decided on a steady construction of  three cruisers a year, in -,-rder that the cost of replacement should not fall too heavily on the years after 1931 when the  replacement of Capital Ships is due  to begin.    There  is  another  consideration which seems to  me of  great freight;  and  that  is tho  great  political difficulty of  accelerating  construction apart  from the question of finance.    In  these tines  when disarmament is  constantly under  discussion at Geneva and elsewhere;here,  any marked addition to our  normal  programme  would  excite  comment  and suspicion,  and we  should be  asked against  what Power we were making these  preparations, and  other  awkward  questions. It  is therefore most  improbable that any speeding  up wouldhe really possible.
        Tho effect on U.S.A. of dropping two cruisers in 1927 was not such as to encourage the idea that the dropping of another in 1S 8 will elioic any syrrpathetio response.        If, however, the Cabinet, with those considerations in. their minds, insist on a reduction in. 1928 of one cruiser of tho 1925 prcgi^ammc, tho Admiralty would reluctantly consent, provided that it is at the same time decided to lay down 5 cruisers in 1929-        If the American programme of 25 &quot;A&quot; Glass Cruisers at  tho rato of 5 a yoar i3 to  be carried cut,  all the cruisers we  build in 1928 and 1929  ought to  ha of the same class.        At tho samo  time  the  Admiralty represent most strongly tho urgent  necessity for eonimoncing tho  replacement  of  Sleeps in  1928  with  a  programme of  4  for 1928 and 4 for 1929.        The  whole of our  Sloops will be worn, out and unfit  for further  service in  1936.        It must  &quot;be remosafcered that no loss  than 17 Sloops are now  being employed as  Cruisers,  and  if not  replaced by new Sloops, their duties will  have  to be carried out  by additional  Cruisers  in full  commission^  and additional  expensewill thus bo  incurred.                                          . 0 oB oAdmiralty,  S.W.I.    20th Deoember, 1927.
216    THE accompanying revise  of the Report of the Sub-Committee of theCommittee of Imperial Defence on the Indianisation of the Indian Army is circulated in accordance with the conclusions reached by the Cabinet at its meeting  held  on the 22nd December,  1927 (reference Cabinet  64  (27),Conclusion 3).    The original Report of the Sub-Committee was circulated to the cabinet as Paper No. CP. 320 (27).                                   (Signed)       M. P. A.  HANKEY.    2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.  1,         December 22, 1927.                                                              1692IA

</content>
</cab>
