<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/109/0 images: 19-23</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 o^vv^/^vfe MTIIIEf LOCuMNT IS THF PROPERTY Off HIS .BRITACTIO MAJESTY&apos;S GOTERMMT)cab i tfCc?e I6c2 A *......----- ^[^MMML^^tW^.MINORITY HEPOBT BY SIR G,L. BARSTOW, K.C.B.-3The economic effect of the Bread subsidy has &quot;been to depress the level of money wages, which during the period that it has &quot;been in operation have in an increasing degree been fixed in reference to the cost of living index figures.   That this is so, is admitted in the argument that if the Bread Subsidy is withdrawn,- wages must rise.The Bread subsidy is therefore essentially a gift from the State not to the working man but to the employer, and it has operated to increase the profits of the latter.To remove the &quot;Bread subsidy will consequently by enhancing the price of Bread give rise to demands for wages increases: ancVche objection is naturally taken that this will be a serious danger for industry.This difficulty has to be faced, and the following argu-ments are adduced to show that it is desirable nevertheless to withdraw the subsidy and the sooner it is done the better.In the first place an increase in wages necessary to meet the.cost to the working man of the increased cost of bread would not be very large,   with bread at l/4d, the index figure would go up from 25o to 258, say by 3-J$ representing a 2/- rise on a.6oA wage.This increase may be offset by reductions in the cost of living in other directions.   There are indications that the turn of the tide has come.   The wholesale prices index number (Q     is down (the Times index number has fallen from 329.2 per cent of 1913 at end of April to 3Q7.4 at end of June) freights are&apos; down; there arc signs that retail prices are on the downward move.   It is true, however, that this is stated by the Food
Ministry not to be likely to affect-food pr?cer &apos;dun&apos;Jig the&apos; aex-t-3 months.in any&apos; case various classes of labour are now asking &apos; for increased v/ages.   In some cases these may be justified by cost of living figures, and in these there is little objection to an increase of wage being given.   In other cases&apos; certain   specially favourably placed classes of labour are probably using their power to hold up the community, and these may as well be given - in the nursemaid&apos;s phrase -&quot;something to cry about&quot;.If money v/ages are increased, it is a serious question whether, when prices fall and with prices the amount of employment, they can effectively and without much friction be reduced again.   But it is possible to exaggerate the dif-ficulty of inducing the working classes to accept wage-reductions.   The circumstances are very different from those which prevailed before the war,   We have become accustomed to rapid changes in price levels, and the tradition of stability in wages has been lost.   Moreover, workman have become accustomed to the association -of wages with the indes number of the cost of living, and if the re-action in prices is so serious as to call for a reduction in wages, that index number will quickly be affected.   That the Trade Unions should be entirely prudent and reasonable would not be consistent with the frailties of human nature, but they &amp;ave had to acquiesce in reductions during former trade depressions, and their advantages in bargaining during recent years has sprung from the very fact that their money wages were- below what industry would bear, and that consequently profits have been corres-correspondingly great.   &quot;Employment will not be affected until pro-^ fits are eaten away by costs and when that happens the employer will be in a much 1 stronger position to bargain with the workmen, l^o power can make private employers employ workmen at wages which continuously involve the employers in loss.   If this
situation arises, wages must fall: the only question is whetherthey will fall &quot;by agreement or under the pressure of unemploy-a meremerit.   This is not/dictum of political economy hut a principle which the&quot; working classes understand perfectly well.   The abolition of the Bread subsidy will greatly reduce the burden on the Exchequer and set free a substantial sum for the reduction of the floating Debt.   This will make it easier to deal with short term borrowings by the State and to meet renewals from the money market instead of by borrowing from the Bank of England on ways and Means advances.   The latter course results in inflation of credit, and inflation of credit results in high prices.If the improvement of the Exchequer position resulted in an improvement of the Foreign Exchanges, this would again re-act favourably upon the price of imported wheat,&apos; sugar, etc.Ho section of the community has a greater interest in a fall of price3 than the working classes, to whom it means higher real wages,   when&apos;cost of living rises, the. workman&apos;s wages go up but after the event..   When it falls his wages may fall (if profits fall) but also after the event&apos;.   The with-drawal of the subsidy and consequent enhancement of cost of bread would not mean ail loss to him, even if he got no increase, in wages.It must not be forgotten that the Bread Subsidy affects all alike, rich and poor.   It is clearly uneconomical to pay out of the Exchequer one fourth of the baker&apos;s bill of a millionaire or indeed of any. member of the classes more numerous than is commonly supposed who could economise in other items of expenditure.It appears to be admitted that the Government pledges to farmers will make it&quot; politically impossible to continue the Bread Subsidy after July 1921.   The following arguments are advanced to show that it is better to withdraw it at once
(a) The sooner it is withdrawn, the more money will be saved,   only 8 millions out of the 45 million Budget estimate have been spent up to 1st July.(b) Employment has net yet been affected by the fall in prices and temporary depression.   (&apos;lf it is delayed too long, and unemployment should set in, the political difficulty of withdrawal would be greatly enhanced.(e) it is better for the same reason to withdraw it before the winter, (d) The last increase in the price of bread was accepted with no serious protest, and the present time when all classes are crying for economy is as favourable a moment as is likely ever to occur. Bread no longer occupies the same position relative to other foodstuffs in the working class budget as it did 100 years ago and we can discount the psycho-logical effect accordingly. My recommendation therefore is that the Bread Subsidy should be withdrawn at the earliest date at which it i3 admini strafeSQty possible.   withdrawal of the subsidy does not necessarily involve withdrawal of control, which would require further consideration.The withdrawal of the subsidy could be effected by rais-ing the price of flour to such a figure as would enable bread to be sold at l/4d.It has been suggested that in that event it would be necessary to remove in respect of the British harvest of this year the maximum price (95/-) of home-grown wheat and to, allow the British farmer wosrld prices (This would involve an increase to l/5c in the price of &quot;Bread).-  I do not consider that this would be justifiable or administratively necessary this year although it would probably be necessary to maintain the Flour
Mills control after 31st December next.   But it might be possible to terminate the purchase operations of the wheat Commission allowing purchase by private enterprise to be resumed, the Wheat Commission retaining a general oversight in order to watch the situation..(S/Sd.).   G.L.. BARSTOW.Treasury Chambers, 9th June, 1Q2Q.

</content>
</cab>
