<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/109/0 images: 271-278</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
gib aOCUMEIlT IS THE PROPERTY Off Hit;,,BEIT;J0IQ MA JE&amp;TYT S . 0 VEHEMENT*)VERY URGENT*       ELiskko.   Lelsovpra.   London.Foreign Office, Earl Curzon of Kedleston, July 17th,The Russian Soviet Government is the more pleased to acknowledge the declaration of the British Government on its desire tocontribute to the establishment of general peace in Eastern Europe,as quite recently still at the time -when the complications between russia and $aland were developing which led to the Polish advanceagainst Russia and the&apos; Ufcraiue, the British Government unfortunatelydid not manifest the same desire on contributing to the cause ofPeace in Eastern Europe and as earlier likewise at the time whenSoviet Russia was trying to obtain peace with the Border states the British Government did not support the attainment of this aimand when the Esthonian Government in December of last year it received a warning in the name of the Supreme Council.   The presentohange in the attitude of Great Britain in the question of peace between Soviet Russia and other States is in complete harmony withthe wishes of Soviet Russia whose desire to live in peace with allother States to which reference is made in the last communication of the British Government remains firm and unalterable.   Regarding Poland likewise in sp.ite of the latters wanton aggression against the Soviet Republic, Soviet Russia remains as faithful as before to the principles she has proclaimed so often and to ier earnest desire ofestablishing peaceful relations with all peoples.   The i uestion* however, of cessation of the armed struggle between Russia and Poland will be unfavourably influenced by the fact that on the part of the polish Government there has been no direct declaration to the Soviet Government regarding its wish to conclude Peace,   numerous utterances of the Polish People have come to the knowledge of the Soviet Government in which they express themselves in an extremely bitter sense as to the British Governments political action in this question and information has been likewise published in the Press as to the decision of the Polish Diet to reject the proposal of anCABINET.Copy HO-... RUSSIA   AND   P0IA1Q,Reply   from_Alb sc ow.(Subject to cortection)*
Armistice with -Sovfeet Russia.     The Soviet Government must therefore consider with some caution such proposals so far as they do not come directly from the Government concerned and as long as the danger subsists that the attitude of the^Polish Government will not correspond to the declarations of other Governments which speak in its name.     The necessity of a direct communication from the Polish Government to the Soviet Government in this case is the more urgent as the past attitude of the British Government in the conflict between Poland and Russia can hardly be considered as a reason for assuming the role of mediator between these two Governments.    If at the time when the Polish Republic was preparing its wanton aggression against Russia and the Ukraine the British Government not only made no attempts of hindering this aggression but even left without any answer the communication of the Soviet Government to the Entente Governments in this question and if at the time when the Polish offensive has had as a result military disaster for Pola&amp;d the British Government on the contrary tries to assume the role of mediator in order to suspend the hostilities that have become so disastrous for Poland so the position which results for the British Government from this line of action is such that it deprives it of the role of an impartial third part^ which would alone render possible its mediation between the belligerents.   It is necessary to remind likewise the British Government that it has itself described the state dreated by the adoption by Russia of its Memorandum of July first as a State of Armistice and that it has therefore described! itself in this way as is belligerent waging war against Soviet Russia, a fact that can in no way create a normal basis for the recognition of its role of mediator between Soviet Russia and another belligerent.     Regarding the British Government, the Russian Government has in its answer to the Memorandum of July First made an absolutely conciliatory declaration including the acceptation of all the demands of the British Government.    It has thus shown its anxious desire to remove completely all fiondiets and to obtain definite peace with Great Britain.     It desires likewise to establish peace with Poland and in the attainment of this aim it considers direct negotiations
!     11with Poland without any immixation from outside as necessary as direct negotiations with Groat Britain in its relations with    * latter the proposed mediation for the negotiations with PC and as the reconciliation with Poland which it earnestly derire   can oniy he hampered in such a case in view of the subordinate ; \Jition which Polahdxs interests and fate in comparison with interests foreign to Poland are -occ^ihg in the domain of re&quot;ations between      j Soviet Russia and Third Power.    V/with the frankness0which can alone completely remove all misunderstandings between twcGdvern-ments the Soviet Government ventures to recall to the British Government that when one of its members defended in the House of Commons the help given to Denikin and Koltchak he justified this line of action of the Government by the argument that the struggle of Denilcin and Koltchak against the Soviet Government presumably helps towards the defence of India and of the British interests-tn Asia in general again,t dangers whioh alle.ge&amp;3u$r threaten them. Hot long ago when the Head of the British Government was negotiating with the Head of the Russian frrade Delegation regarding resumption of trade relations^ he referred to the relations between Russia and the numerous other1 States as to, such facts that can hatfe some influx ence upon the commercial relations between Russia and Groat Britain.   The Soviet $fovernment is of the opinion that roconcili^&apos; ation with Poland can oe successfully accomplished only in case tho interests of both parties are taken into consideration seeing &quot;that these interests can easily be reconciled and this aim will be on the contrary extremely hard to attain.if these interests are sub-    .i ordinated to the interests of a- third Power.     The labouring masses of Russia desire full and complete reconciliation with Poland and in order to attain this aim the Soviet Government considers it necessary to removo from the action of reconciliation all that does -:! not belong to the interests and desires of the two peoples and Governments.   In&apos;tho cause of reconciliation with Poland the Soviet Government finds it necessary to consider besides the. interests1
and desires of the Russian Labour/masses only the interests and desires of the Polish labouring masses and it finds it therefore possible to attain peace with Poland only through direct negotiations with Poland. .  It must also point out that it. has already obtained without foreign immixation complete reconciliation with.three neighbouring states and that esthonia ha.a concluded peace with Russia In spite of the warning of tne Supreme Council that the Treaty between Russia and Georgia has been at the moment of the negotiations ations between the head of the Russian Trade Delegation and the head of the British Government a complete surprise for the latter and that the British Government Was deprived of any Information regarding peace between&apos;Russia and Lithuania when in its, ultimatum of July 12th it.pointed.to Lithuania as to one of the border States with which Russia has still to obtain peace.    The Soviet Government thinks that it can with the same success obtain peace with Poland through direct negotiations as it did with three other neighbouring States.The Soviet Government still oonsiders less admissable the interference in the cause of peace between Russia and Poland of the group of Governments called League of Nations whose covenant/
The Russian Government has never received from the so called League of Nations any communication as to its creation and existence and it has never had the opportunity of adopting a &quot;decision about recognition or non-recognition of this Association of States.    When acquainting itself from unofficial press r&apos;eources with the Covenant of the so-called League of Nations the Soviet Government could not leave unnoticed the fact that according to Article seventeen the non-members in case of con-conflict with members of the so-called League can be invited to submit to its decision as if they were members.   The Soviet Government can in no way agree that one group of Powers should assume the role of supreme body over all the States of the world and watching 0Ver the full inviolability of the sovereign rights of the Russian labouring people the Soviet Government absolutely rejects the pretentions of any foreign groups of Powers claiming to assume the role of supreme masters of the fate of other nations. It absolutely rejects therefore every immixatfcn of this associa-tion in the cause of peace between Russia and Poland.Direct negotiation, with Poland are in full harmony with the wishes of the Soviet Government .and it declares therefore that if the Polish Government addresses to Russia the proposal of entering into peace negotiations the Soviet Government will not reject its proposal and will also consider in the most friendly spirit any subsidiary proposal as to an armistice or to some other means meant to facilitate peace negotiations the Soviet Government - expresses also Its willingness to agree to a territorial frontier more favourable for the Polish people than the frontiers indicated by the Supreme Council in December last and proposed once more by the British Government in its ultimatum of July 155th.   The Soviet Government cannot leave without notice the fact that this frontier was elaborated by the Supreme Council in some parts under the pressure of counter revolutionary Russian elements adherents of the Russian capitalist and landed class and that for example as to the region of Kholm the decision of the Supreme Council clearly reflected the., influence of these counter revolutionary elements and followed the races of anti-
Polish, policy of Tzarist and of tho Russian Imperialist&apos; capitalist class in this question.        Soviet Russia in willing in general as to the Peace conditions with Poland to meet the interests and wishes of the Polish people the more fully the more&apos;the Polish people in its internal life will enter a path creating a solid basis for real     fraternal relations between the labouring masses of Poland, Russia, Ukraine, white Russia, and Lithuania and will create guarantees that Poland will cease to be an instrument of aggression and intrigues against the workers and peasants of Soviet Russia and of other countries.As a separate proposal the British Government has nut forth the idea of* an Armistice, between Russia and the mutinous exgeneral , Wrangel,   the Soviet Government however sannot shut its eyes upon the indissoluble connection between the Military Operations of   -Wrangel which were supported by the Entente Powers and the Polish campaign against Russia and Ukraine,   This close connection found its expression in the negotiations and the Military Agreement between Wrangel and the representatives of the Polish Government.- Wrangel s&apos; offensive which coincided with the advance of the Polish Army in the Ukraine was only a subsidiary military manoeuvre aiming at rendering more difficult the struggle of the Russian and Ukrainian troops against the Polish aggressor and at facilitating the latters task. The Army and Administration of Wrangel being .almost completely depriv ed/bf sources of revenue of their own exist almost, entirely with the financial help received from some Entente Powers.   His Military operations arc carried out exclusively with the help of the ^ar material sent by these Bowers.-     This TCar Material is brought to him on British ships or from harbours under British occupation and the proposal itself regarding 7rangel in the British Ultimatum-of July Twelfth in which the British Government decides for Wrangel that he will come to London for&apos;tho discussion of the, fate of his troops, shows with complete evidence that he is only a subordinate agent, of the British Government and partly of its Allies.     The Soveit Government in its wish to obtain peace with the British Government and wishing to meet the latters desires confirm once
-7- -    230 .more- its willingness to guarantee personal safety to the mutinousex-General virangel to all the persons belonging to His Army and tothe refugees under his protection on the condition of immediate and full capitulation and of surrender to the Soviet authorities of all the territory he occupies and of all the war material, &apos;stores buildings, means of GommuniQat ions and so on in. his power:&apos;:on the same terms as it was proposed by the soviet Government withreference to the Northern Government of the ex-General Miller. &apos;The Soviet Government cannot, however, remain indifferent to therepeated attempts of the British Government to,transport the CrimeanPeninsula into an inviolable permanent asylum for the mutinousGeneral and for other mutineers who in fact are the BritishGovernmentTs subordinate agents and thus really to render theCrimean Peninsula a British Dependence..   It is impossible notto mention that at the time when the Archangel and the Mourmansk ........region w*as in the same subordinate position as to Britain, theBritish Authorities ruled there unrestrained and acted as theSupreme Power devastating the whole region, wasting its natural resources and exporting to Britain as much as possible its riches.The bearer of the will and the representative of the Interestsof the Russian Labouring People the Soviet Government cannot remainindifferent to any violation of its vital interests and of theinviolability of its territory and it protests most strongly against the attempt of Great Britain to annex in fact the CrimeanPeninsula.   It must also be pointed out that the present proposal of the British Government is. a violation of its precedent proposals which became an obligation after having been adopted by the Soviet Government regarding cessation of any help:and support to the ex-General Wrangel. . The . Soviet Government is therefore of the opinion that the greatest possible concession on its part a concession v&amp;ichis the outcome of its anxious desire to come to terms with the British Government is its willingness to agree to the capitulation of the ex-General Wrangel and of his troops with the guarantee of their personal safety., The Soviet Government thinks that the proposal of convocation in London of a /
Conforonco of representatives of Russia Poland Lithuania Latvia and Finland is the outcome of insufficient i:nforelation of the British Government as to the relations between the Russian Re-public and her neighbours.   The Peaoe Treaty between Russia and Lithuania was signed on July 12th and the negotiations betv/een Russia and Latvia and Russia and Finland aie being carries on independently without&quot;Foreign interference and their further r ,utinuance on the same lines is the best pledge of their success-ful resultBeing animated with the most earnest desire of putting an end to all oonflicts between Rjh .ia and Great Britain and to the struggle botween them and to obtain definite peace with Great Britain      the Soviet Government rests its hopes upon the Delegation which it sendsto London with additional members witty the purpose of carrying on negotiations with the British Government on the basis of the British mmar andurn of July 1st, and of the reply of the Soviet Government of July 7th in order to obtain a full agreement with Great. Britain.     This aim will be attained the more successfully if all new and strange elements which can only do harm to. the beginning improvement of the relations between Russia and Great,Britain are kept aside.No. 654    Peoples Commissary for Foreign Affairs.TCHITCESRIN.2, Whitehall Gardens,   3.W.I.July 19th, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
