<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/109/0 images: 368-372</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
flu   tP    flt&apos;\\.C&apos;&apos;/! &apos;. I &apos;.Thin Document is t!i^ Property of Lnn;c f:\ )      Government.340 ministry OP HEALTH. WHITEHALL, S.W.1. 21st July, 1920*I am directed to forward herewith the following report on tho work of the Ministry of Health during the month of June.Yours faithfully,ecretaryThe Secretary, The Cabinet.1.  HOUSING.1.   Parliamentary Housing Group?    Two meetings of the Housing Group were held on the 9th and 30th June.    The special points contained in the Minister*s address at the first meeting wore (1) a joint body had been set up to doal with stock issues,, as a result of which conflicting issues would be .avoided, (2) negotiations were taking place with the War Savings Certificates organisation and it was hoped to divert these savings to helping housing finance, (3) the restriction of luxury build-ing was not being satisfactorily effected and steps were being taken to introduce a General Powers Bill to deal with the question at an early date.    The main points of tho minister&apos;s address at tho second meeting wore (1) shortage of labour, (2) progress of local bonds campaign, (3) deoision to extend period within which the subsidy to private builders would be payable, (4) as a result of the Cabinet Committee on the labour question,rdefinite requests had been put forward to employers and employees. The labour question generally was discussed.
been such an improvement in the state of trade, or alteration of general conditions, as to warrant a further increase in rates of wages. Some sections of the industry may be more active thail others but under the agreement of-February, 1917, the Court are required to decide what general alteration in wages, if any, is warranted by the abnormal conditions due to the war; and hence to have regard to the condition of the industry as a whole. It. does not appear to the Court that on such a view the position to-day differs to such a degree from what it was four months ago that the settlement effected by their last decision should be disturbed.9. After careful consideration the Court accordingly find that the claims submitted have not been established.10. This decision shall apply to the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland.11. Applications for special advances in accordance with the second paragraph of clause (1) of the agreement of February, 1917, have still to be considered by the Court.William W. Mackenzie (President).F. H. McLeod.J. McKie Bryce.F. S, Button.d. c. cummings.James Fullerton.G. T. Reid,Secretary,5, Old Palace Yard, S.W.I.14th July, 1920.
Memorandum ok Amusement between the Engineering Employers&apos; Federation and the Unions connected with the Engineering and Foundry Trades arrived at in February, 1917.It is agreed that, having regard to the special circumstances of the war, the following shall be the principles upon which wages changes shall be arranged for the period of the war: (1) That existing agreements or practice under which applications for general alterations in wages are dealt with shall to that extent be suspended until the termination of the war, or for such further period as may be agreed upon by the parties thereto. This shall not refer to agreements or practice whereby the wages of any trades in any district or department rise or fall with the, fluctuations in another district or industry not covered by this agreement.Nor shall it prevent the Unions bringing forward for special consideration at the hearing referred to in paragraph (2) (a) the case of any district in which they claim that the rates of wages are unduly low or that the total amount of war advance is not adequate.On the other hand, the Federation shall be entitled to bring forward for similar consideration any special cases they desire.(2) During such period of suspension, the following procedure shall be observed, provided the consent of the Committee on Production is obtained:  (a) The Committee on Production shall in the months of February, June and October, after hearing parties, consider what general alteration in wages, if any, is warranted by the abnormal conditions then existing and due to the war.(6) The award of the Committee on Production shall be an award under the Munitions of War Acts and shall be of national application to all federated firms in the branch of trade concerned.(c) The first award shall take effect in all districts on first s full pay in April, and the altered rate shall continue until amended by a further award in accordance with provisions hereof. Subsequent awards shall specify the date upon which the alteration awarded shall take effect.The following memorandum was also agreed between the parties:  The Engineering Employers&apos; Federation and the Unions whose signatures are appended hereto recommend to His Majesty&apos;s Goverti-ment that arrangements should be made whereby all employers in the trade or trades affected should be subject to the awards which may be made by the Committee on Production in virtue of the agreement hereto attached.LIST OF TRADE UNION SIGNATORIES TO ABOVE AGREEMENT.Amalgamated Society of Engineers. Steam Engine Makers&apos; Society.Society of Amalgamated Toolmakers, Engineers and Machinists.United Machine Workers&apos; Association.Boilermakers&apos; and Iron and Steel Shipbuilders&apos; Society.United Kingdom Society of Amalgamated Smiths and Strikers.Scientific Instrument Makers&apos; Trade Society.Electrical Trades Union.Shipconstructors&apos; and Shipwrights&apos; Association.National Brassworkers and Metal Mechanics.United Journeymen Brassfounders, Fitters, Turners, &amp;cNational Society of Coppersmiths, Braziers, and Metal Workers.
British Steel Smelters, &amp;c, Association (now incorporated in the Iron andSteel Trades Confederation). National Amalgamated Sheet Metal Workers and Braziers. Amalgamated Society of Carpenters and Joiners. Associated Blacksmiths&apos; and Ironworkers&apos; Society. Amalgamated Society of Woodcutting Machinists. General Ironfitters&apos; Association. General Union of Braziers and Sheet Metal Workers. Scottish Painters&apos; Society.Sheet Iron Workers&apos; and Light Platers&apos; Society.National Amalgamated Society of Operative House and Ship Painters andDecorators. General Union of Carpenters and Joiners. United Kingdom Society of coach makers. London United Brass and General Metal Founders&apos; Union. Amalgamated Union of Cabinet Makers. London and Provincial coach makers&apos; Trade Union. National Amalgamated Furnishing Trades&apos; Association. Amalgamated Society of Wheelwrights, Smiths, and Motor Body Builders. National Union of General Workers. National Amalgamated Union of Labour. Amalgamated Machine Engine and Iron Grinders. Workers&apos; Union.National Amalgamated Union of Enginemen, Firemen, Mechanics and electrical Workers. Dock, Wharf, Riverside and General Workers&apos; Union. Amalgamated Moulders&apos; and Kindred Industries&apos; Association. National Amalgamated Labourers&apos; Union. Winding and General Engineers&apos; Society. Northern United Enginemen&apos;s Association. Amalgamated Society of Gas, Municipal, and General Workers. London Society of Amalgamated Brass Workers. National Union of Operative Heating and Domestic Engineers. Wheelwrights&apos; and coach makers&apos; Operatives&apos; Union (London). Amalgamated Society of Railway Vehicle Builders, Wheelwrights, Car-penters and Mechanics.West of Scotland Brass Turners&apos;, Fitters&apos;, Finishers&apos;, and InstrumentMakers&apos; Society. Gas Fitters&apos; Trade Association.
She attached papers which have ? already been circulated by the Foreign Office, are recirculated as Cabinet Papers - CP. 1653 and CP,1654 re-spettivaly.2, IVkitonall Gardens, S*W. 81st July 1920*

</content>
</cab>
