<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/109/0 images: 464-466</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)SECRET. C-opyJo^C i B I fl. S. B-C.P.-167ii.pCpGJjITIOfl^,^...fflSSJJJ SOYEIufivMT Of ALL DEBTS OWING BY RUSSIAN NATIONALS.Note by the Chancellor *f the Exchequer oovering letter from&apos;The (To fern or of the Bank of England.I ciroulate for consideration, by the Cabinet a letter which I have received from the Governor of the Bank of England, in ragard to the recognition by the Russian Governrasnt of all debts owing by Russian nationalsHlntd.)   A.O.
SOH O.LM^ -*KGM THE GOVERNOR .0? THE BAJTC 02 EfiGUMDw.    37 TO THE. CHil^OELLOR Off THE SIGHS QUER.Bank of England, London, 32..C2. 21st July, 1920.Lear Mr. Chancellor,It is generally understood to be the intention of His Majestyrs Government to encourage the resumption tf trade between Russia and the United Kingdom subject tt oertain conditions, amonst which is believed to be the recognition by the Russian Government of debts due and owing by Russian traders te British merchants and manufacturers.A statement made by Mr. Bonar Law in the House of Commons on the. 14th instant has given rise to the belief that such debts are to be placed in a first category as distinct from other debts.   I am desired, however, to represent to you that traders debts are but one class of the debts owing by Russian Nationals all of which it is felt should be treated equally as regards recognition.   Many of the Russian Banks, for example, oantracted with British Banks debts, which are still outstanding; and every helder of Bonds of the Imperial Russian Government and of Russian Municipalities, Railways and nther undertakings issued in this oountry possesses &apos;%n equally valid obligation^ particularly when regard is had to. the fact that monies raised by such Bends have in many instances heea expended in the construction of Railways and other revenue producing undertakings the income from which is still, as in the past, a source of revenue to the Russian Government.In
In conveying to you this representation, I desire to support the views expressed with an emphatic expression of my opinion that in order not to prejudice particular classes of creditors, it should he ixade a condition of the resumption of the normal trade relations between this country and Russia that all bona fide ascertained and valid debts should be definitely and equally recognised.Although I have reason to believe that you will see to it that the subject of this letter receives, prompt consideration in the proper quarter, I may add that a widely signed memorial in regard to the matter will be laid before you should you deem such a course desirable.Youia sincerely.,(Sgd.) Montagu Herman.The Right honourable the Chancellor of the Exchequer.

</content>
</cab>
