<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/109/0 images: 558-561</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(thi3 DOCroffiW IS THE PROPEHTY Of HIS BRIJANHIC tUBffS GOVERHMEM)&apos; .  i     . . &apos; i..................ni  .   m   .....     , m m ,,,.....,........mn*- iiniinnf k......i m   ,ii......     ..............cp. 1683, QAmim.IREL AN D. - 5im FUTina o? the home rule bill.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.The mooting of the Cabinet Conforenco on Ireland which occupiod most of yesterday dealt witfr two very different, though closely allied, subjects.    The first was the immediate precautions to be adopted in order to restore order in Iroland.   The second was tbftr wider question of the future &apos; fern of Goyernment tote&apos; adopted- in .that Island..     This Paper deals only - with the second of those; subjects..Very strong opinions wero. expressed yesterdcy by some of the official witnesses   who -gave, -evidence before us.,     But, after a night1 s roflection.. I am inclined to the view that the advice given . (e.g. by the 3rown Prosecutor) was bad, and, though expressed by -him. with an almost fiery conviction, was due to.the perverting effects of the atmosphoro of profound discouragement whioh prevails over-the greater part of Ireland,The policy advocated by the Crown Prosecutor.may, for the purposes of my argument,&apos; be summed up as follows:-a, Negotiations are to be opened with the most respectable members of the Sinn Fein organisation.b. The overtures are to come from us, and not from them,C    We are to offer them terms which, injfche Carown Prosecutor1 s view, they would, probably accept. ....... ; . ..d.     These terms include the abandonment of a Parliament for Ulster (which was tp be left, as part of the Unltod Kingdom); and the setting up of what is usally, but most inaceurately, described as Dominion Government in the rest of Ireland,If this scheme were adopted, hopes&quot; were held out that the campaign of outrago and assassination would be brought to an&quot; end, and the Irish question receive its final settlement,-If. I emphatically dissent from all these suggestions, it is not because! have any special!&apos; love for the lines on which our Home Rule
scheme proceeds.   Rightly/wT^hgly&quot;^- perhaps wrongly - I original4$^ suggested quite a different plan to ray colleagues, and one that in many respects resent] es that whioh. is now put before Us by the Crown Prosecutor as the one which Sinn Fein would accept But whet might, or might net, have boon, wisdom&apos; in January would certainly be f611y now;   arid 1 hope it will receive no countenance from the Cabinet0My reasons are as follows-. -1, There is first the general consideration that the Government cannot abandon a measure so elaborate in its structure and se far advanced in its Parliamentary career as the present Home Rule Bill without some discredit;   and that the discredit would amount to disgrace if this course were adopted, not on its merits, but as a concession to those&apos;who worked through organised assassinaticn.   V;hen it became known as, of course, it would be -that the fDag cf truce had been sent by the Imperial Government to the assassins,- not by the assassins to the Imperial Government the disgrace would deepen tc infamyA parliament has been promises to Ulster.   Whether the promise was originally wise or unwise is quite immaterial; it cannot now be withdrawn. But its withdrawal is an essential part of the Siin Fein plan, partly because they think it wuld embitter Ulster against the Government, partly for a deeper motive,They believe that if Ulster once gets a Parliament she will never surrender it, and Ireland will te*eternally dividedo   Whereas if she were administratively cut off from Ireland and-attached for all purposes to Great Britain, &quot;small dificulties and jealousies, petty sources of friction would gradually create even among the Protestants, a powerful party anxious to promote her re-absorotion in the Irish system.:-It has been suggested as a middle bourse&apos; that we might pass the Homofj-./ i&quot;   -,:v&apos;.&apos;.; -;.I - - &apos; - -&apos;\0.0Rule Bill in its present torn,- but accompany it with a statement that we did nc-V regard that form as final, and that when the two Parliament; were established in Ireland we should&quot;be prepared-(further to consider whether the Constitution hi the South and \7est might not, with but brief delays suffer profound- modification
in the direction of (so-called) Dominion Government *I think this a very perilous proposalc Nothing, of course; in this world is final, and it would be folly to suggest that the Home Rule Bill is a perfect example of immutable wisdom. BuVsurely it would also be folly to suggest that it is but a half-way house to some new Utopia?,   This would supply a most powerful motive to continued agitation/&apos; and would deprive the measure of such chance as it still &quot;possesses of settling the Irish question.   Moreover, it has to be observed, as I pointed out yesterday,,,that every addition&apos;to the&apos;powers and privileges given to the Parliament of the South will produce an irresistible demand for the grant of similar powers and privileges to the Parliament of trie-North: and Ulster, however unwilling, will be driven far along the road to separations&apos;One further point I should like to press on the attention of my colleagues/   All through Irish history since the rebellion of 1798 the men who&apos;have been prepared to run most risks and to commit most crimes on behalf of the Ireland of their dreams are the^extremists;   and to them nothing&apos; short of a Irish Republic&apos;&apos; will be really acceptable^ :This party has constantly been crushed, but it has never been destroyed. It has formed an essential element in all the movements for destroying the Union-The leaders of these movements&apos; have first&apos;silently used it and then openly denounced it; and all in turn, after having denounced it, have themselves lost power a:nd prestige.-If then we let it be understood that our Home Rule&apos;Bill its no more than an install ment, we invite further&apos; agitation: we give&apos;the extremists the occasion they seek; and we shall have before :us a long perspective of Home&apos; Rule Amendment Bills to which no term can be assigned except that of complete separation.&quot;Holding this view, I have to admit that&apos; neither the present nor&quot;any other Home&apos;Rule Bill is going&apos;to settle the Irish question. The party&apos; of assassination will&apos;still be there, ready for action under some new alias when^-ever the opportunity occurs,&quot;The most we can hope for is to weaken the chances of an alliance, always
toinporary&apos;&quot;but- ulwayB^orndda^ tham. and- &quot;th^-iao&amp;aratos.&apos;This, cur Homo Rule Bill may perhaps aoccmplish; and it will bo an incalculable gain if in addition v/o can provide a settlement which, however imperfect, will paralyse Irish intrigues in America and the Dominions, and eemmond itself to genoral opinion throughout the world.     But what chancy is there of securing these ond^jif, at tho vory moment wo aro passing our Bill, we proclaim cur own disbelief in its finality?(Initialled)   A:J*3*Privy Council Office, 24tiuJuly 1920,

</content>
</cab>
