<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/37/0 images: 22-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT is THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1963C.C. (63) Copy No.  4 22nd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 3rd January, 1963, at 5 p.m.Present;The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsRight Hon.Lord Dilhorne. LordTheChancellorThe Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P.. Minister of education the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P.. Minister of defence the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell,M.P., Minister of health the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord Carrington,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 1)The Right Hon. Julian Amery, M.P.,Minister of Aviation (Item 1)The    Marquess    of    Lansdowne,Minister of State for Colonial AffairsThe Right Hon. John Profumo, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Item 1)The Right Hon. Hugh Fraser, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air (Item 1)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . J. H. waddell mr. N. J. Abercrombie
ContentsSubjectBahamas Meeting, December 1962Congo Republic        ......
BahamasMeeting,December1962(previous reference :C.C. (62) 76thConclusions)* 1. The Prime Minister said that a current appraisal of the outcome of his discussions with the President of the United states in Nassau in December must be related to the international situation as a whole. There were some grounds for supposing that theprospect of a detente in relations between the West and the soviet union might be improving. The Soviet Government weremomentarily less confident of their standing in the world, morepreoccupied with domestic difficulties and more seriously disturbed by their theoretical dispute with the Chinese Communists than atany time in the last few years. Among the Communist Satellitecountries the beginnings of independence in Poland and the growingweakness of Eastern Germany were additional factors making for agreater measure of flexibility in the foreign relations of the bloc.On the other hand, the Western Alliance was itself showing signsof strain. The intransigence of Germany and the unilateralcharacter of French policy were considerable obstacles in the wayof progress towards international agreement on disarmament andon Berlin. As a result there were symptoms of growing impatienceand anxiety on the part of the United States Government, who feltthat they were being asked to shoulder a heavy burden ofresponsibility and expenditure, while lacking any effective controlover the policies of the alliance as a whole. It was against this background that the Nassau discussions had to be considered.Those discussions, in which he had been joined by the foreign secretary, the Commonwealth Secretary and the Minister of Defence,had covered a wide range of topics; but they had necessarilyconcentrated mainly on the issues arising from the decision of theUnited States Government to abandon development of the airborneballistic missile SKYBOLT for their own forces. Some sections ofpublic opinion in the United Kingdom were disposed to take theview that this decision was intended to compel us finally to surrenderany independent strategic nuclear capability. This was one indication of the current strains in the Western Alliance. The present UnitedStates Administration included hardly any of the men who had been associated with this country in the Second World War; and manyof President Kennedy&apos;s advisers were inclined to indulge an inflatedconception of the material power at the disposal of their Government.The natural reaction of the other members of the alliance, which was perhaps particularly evident in this country, was apt to take theform of suspicion of United States motives and policies.Nevertheless, it was certain that the decision to discontinuedevelopment of SKYBOLT was genuinely based on the fact that theUnited States Government had available, in POLARIS andMINUTEMAN, alternative deterrent systems of proved reliability,which made it unnecessary for them to continue a very expensiveprogramme offering no certain prospect of a real improvement in thedefence of the hemisphere. But the Administration would find itdifficult to explain and defend the decision to their own people: itwould entail writing off a large sum of past investment and it hadalready aroused the hostility of the powerful interests, both militaryand industrial, which had been engaged in the project. It was wholly unrealistic to suppose that the United States Governmentwould expose themselves to immediate political risks of this ordermerely for the purpose of depriving the United KingdomGovernment of an independent nuclear capability several yearshence; and public opinion in this country must be convinced of thefalsity of such a hypothesis.President Kennedy had first suggested that the United Statesand the United Kingdom should share, on a basis of equality, thecost of continuing the development of the weapon and that we should* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.
thereafter place such production orders as we saw fit. But from ourown point of view this would have been an open-ended commitment;and we should have found it difficult to exercise effective controlover development carried out in the United States. He had no doubtthat it would have been wrong to accept this proposal.Before considering alternative deterrent systems, however, hehad felt bound to consider once again whether it was right for thiscountry to seek to continue to make an independent contribution tothe Western strategic nuclear deterrent. The nuclear weapon hadbeen invented originally by British scientists and we had made considerable progress, both before and after the amendment of theMcMahon Act, in its development. But the gradual introduction of soviet defence systems posed new problems; and the elaboration of modern systems of guidance and delivery implied that thedevelopment of an effective deterrent would become progressively more sophisticated and expensive. There was, therefore, littleattraction in a policy of complete independence in this respect.Nevertheless, there were several compelling reasons for seeking to preserve a measure of independence as regards control over ournuclear deterrent.In the first place, the Western Alliance would cease to be a freeassociation if the whole of its advanced scientific and technologicalcapacity in this respect were vested in one member. Second, we ought to ensure that we should always be able to react appropriatelyto a Soviet nuclear threat to this country, even if the United States,for whatever reason, were disinclined to support us. Third, a Sovietnuclear threat, to which there was no United Kingdom counter-threat,would render all our conventional forces ineffectual. Finally, if thiscountry abandoned the attempt to maintain an independent nuclear deterrent, it would be unable to exercise any effective influence in the attempts, which would eventually have to be made, to achieve someinternational agreement to limit nuclear armaments. For all these reasons he and his colleagues had been convinced that the policy ofa United Kingdom strategic nuclear deterrent capability should becontinued; and they had welcomed the Cabinet&apos;s endorsement ofthis view.He had therefore decided to press the United States Governmentto supply us with the seaborne ballistic missile POLARIS, insteadof SKYBOLT. This weapon, which had a high degree ofindestructibility, could be used in a second strike role and wasindependent of fixed installations on land, was particularly well suited to our requirements. The United States Government, however,regarded POLARIS as different in kind from SKYBOLT, particularly as it would extent the effectiveness and credibility of the UnitedKingdom deterrent for an almost indefinite period in the future.Moreover, they were anxious to find some means of sharing with therest of the Western Alliance some of the responsibility involved inthe possession of such weapons and therefore attached considerable importance to their being placed under some form of multilateralcontrol. This concept was not wholly realistic since, even if itcontributed to dissuading Germany from attempting to develop a nuclear capability, it was unlikely to be acceptable to the presentFrench Government. Nevertheless, it was necessary to go some way towards meeting the United States stipulation that the UnitedKingdom must agree to commit POLARIS in some way to the alliance as a condition of United States agreement to supply theweapon. The Prime Minister had insisted, however, that any such arrangement must correspond to the basis on which our forces hadbeen contributed to the Allied Command in France at the beginningof the Second World War, i.e., with the explicit provision that theywould remain subject to the ultimate authority of Her Majesty&apos;ministers in the United Kingdom and could be withdrawn in thelast resort if the supreme interests of the country required it. Thisproposal was eventually accepted by the United States Government
and was incorporated in the joint statement issued at the end of theconference. It would be criticised in this country from two opposingpoints of view, both as derogating from the concept of a whollyindependent national deterrent and as falling short of completeintegration with the rest of the alliance. In fact, however, it represented a realistic compromise, in present circumstances, betweenindependence and interdependence; and if, as might well be the case,the development of a multilateral system proved impossible, our ownsituation would be unchanged, except in so far as we should have acquired, in POLARIS, a more effective weapon than SKYBOLT.In discussion the Cabinet endorsed the Nassau Agreement andcongratulated the Prime Minister and his colleagues on the successful outcome of the discussions. The following main points were made:(a) There was no reason to suppose that the United StatesGovernment would not honour their undertaking to supply us withPOLARIS weapons; and no real possibility of insuring against thisimprobable risk. But it would be desirable, if possible, to secure an earnest of fulfilment in the shape of actual weapons or detaileddesigns, if necessary by some measure of advance payment. Suchan arrangement could be examined in the course of technical discussions between the Royal Navy and the United States Navywhich were due to start in a few days&apos; time.(b) The elimination of SKYBOLT implied that from about 1965until the availability of POLARIS-firing submarines between 1968and 1970 the deterrent power of our nuclear forces would no longer be as effective, and therefore as credible, as we had previouslyassumed. The introduction of the TSR-2 aircraft during this period would help to remedy this deficiency; and other steps might be takento improve the performance of Bomber Command aircraft and theirweapons.(c) The introduction of the POLARIS weapon implied heavy additional expenditure in the latter part of the present decade. Thiswould inevitably involve even more drastic curtailment of otherdefence expenditure than had previously been contemplated, ifdefence was not to absorb an excessive share of national resources.(d) It would be necessary to consider carefully the exactwording of any written undertaking to commit our POLARISweapons to a multilateral force. For the same reason we should avoid any precise definition of the circumstances in which the supremenational interest might require us to withdraw them.(e) Although French policy might make it unrealistic to suppose that any considerable progress towards an effective multilateral force could be realised in the near future, the industrial and technologicalresources of Europe were sufficiently powerful to allow us to assume that the concept might ultimately be practicable. Its implicationsdeserved further study.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the arrangements recorded inthe joint statement of 21st December, 1962, by the PrimeMinister and the President of the United States, on nuclear Defence Systems.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence to examine, as a matter of urgency, further measures to improve the effectiveness of United Kingdom nuclear forces between 1965 and1970.(3) Invited the Minister of Defence to arrange to explore thepossibility of obtaining POLARIS weapons or designsfrom the United States Government in return for advancepayment.
congo republic(previous reference :C.C. (62) 75thConclusions,Minute 6)2. The Foreign Secretary described the confused situationwhich had developed in Katanga. It had been clear before christmas that the United Nations would embark on an active policy to promote a settlement of problems outstanding between the CentralGovernment and Mr. Tshombe, the Prime Minister of Katanga; butevents had moved faster than had been expected. Firing appearedto have been started by the Katangan gendarmerie; the local representatives of the United Nations had seized the opportunity totake control of Elizabethville and Kamina; and it had been reportedthat United Nations forces had that day taken Jadotville, where a power station and other installations were said to have been put outof action by the Katangans. The advance on Jadotville had probably been undertaken against the wishes of Mr. Gardiner, the united nations representative in Leopoldville; and there had also beenmisunderstandings between Mr. Gardiner and the United Nationsauthorities in New York. Mr. Tshombe, who had visited northern rhodesia in the early stages of the fighting and had seen the federal prime Minister, Sir Roy Welensky, and the United Kingdom HighCommissioner in Salisbury, Lord Alport, had returned to Katanga;it had not been possible, however, to persuade him to go back toElisabethville and his present whereabouts were unknown.The Foreign Secretary said that from the outset he had represented to the United Nations the undesirability of using force to secure a political settlement; and he had made every effort tosecure a resumption of discussions between Mr. Tshombe and theCentral Government about the division of Katangan revenues and about future constitutional relations. He still hoped that, withBelgian help and under guarantees of personal safety, Mr. Tshombemight be persuaded to respond to these suggestions; but he did notbelieve that in the next few days there would be scope for anyfurther United Kingdom initiative.In discussion there was general agreement on the inexpediencyof any immediate action directed to rescuing Mr. Tshombe fromthe consequences of his own actions. It was possible that he mightcapitulate and that the Union Miniere might withdraw such support as he had been obtaining from them; and it was important that weshould provide no grounds for subsequent allegations that our ownactions had been directed to hindering such developments. But when parliament reassembled the Government would be liable to be questioned both about the validity of the interpretation by the united nations of the Security Council resolutions in relation to the use of force in the Congo and about our attitude to the situation whichwould arise, in a few months&apos; time, when the finances available tothe United Nations for operations in the Congo would probablybe exhausted. Further consideration would have to be given to thesedifficult issues.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement and of thepoints raised in their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,4th January, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
