<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/37/0 images: 47-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the. Cabinet.   January 1963C.C. (63) Copy No.   4 26th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, onThursday, 24th January, 1963, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P.. Prime minister the Right Hon. The Earl of Homf,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Secretary  of  State for the home department the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenteb,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell, M.P.,Minister of health the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:The Right Hon. Richard Wood, M.P.,Minister of Power (Items 3 and 4)Sir  Peter  Rawlinson,  Q.C.,  M.P.,Solicitor-General (Item 3)The Marquess of Lansdowne,Minister of State for Colonial Affairs(Item 2)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:.Sir Burke trend . A. L. M. gary mr. J. H. waddell this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
contents subject parliament       ............Foreign Affairs............TogoHong KongIndonesiaIndustrial Disputes     ........Electricity IndustryFuel Supplies    ............Federation of Rhodesia and NyasalandHouse of Lords Reform       .....
a oForeign AffairsTogo(previous reference:C.C. (63) 4thConclusions,Minute 3)Hong Kong(previous reference:C.C. (62) 35thConclusions,Minute 6)Indonesia(previous reference:C.C. (63) 3rdConclusions,Minute 2)2. The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that an all-partyGovernment had now taken office in Togo and appeared to haveregained control of the confused situation which had resulted fromthe assassination of President Olympic There was now no reason why we should not recognise the new Government, provided that theGovernment of Nigeria, who had originally been concerned about the relationship between Togo and Ghana, raised no objection.In discussion it was suggested that a change of regime in a foreign country need not necessarily require us to recognise the authorityof the Government afresh. It might be convenient if, for this reason,we could dispense with any act of recognition of the new Government.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider whether it wasnecessary for the United Kingdom Government to extendformal recognition to the new Government of Togo.(2) Agreed that, if the Foreign Secretary was satisfied, in thelight of Conclusion (1), that recognition was necessary and would not be embarrassing to the Government of nigeria, the necessary action for this purpose should betaken.The Foreign Secretary said that the Communist ChineseGovernment had recently challenged our jurisdiction in the city ofKowloon in relation to certain measures of slum clearance which we proposed to undertake. This challenge had no legal foundation; andwe had therefore rejected it, while taking steps to inform theCommunist Chinese Government that, if the redevelopment of thearea was not undertaken, the inhabitants would suffer. We must await their reaction to these representations; but their real motivesfor challenging our authority in Kowloon were obscure. If their action foreshadowed renewed pressure on Hong Kong, it wouldbecome necessary to give urgent consideration to the possibleimplications for the Colony.The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that there were continuing indications of ;an attempt by Indonesia to subvert theBorneo Territories by gradual infiltration. We were thereforeconsulting the Governments of the United States and Australia aboutthe possibility of promoting joint measures to restrain the Indonesian government; and it would be necessary, in addition, to seek to dissuade the Government of the Philippines from supportingIndonesian policies in this area.In discussion there was general agreement that, although the indonesian Government had been temporarily deterred by our success in quelling the rebellion in Brunei, it might well be necessary to take further measures to prevent them from renewing aggression againstBorneo. For this purpose we must seek to agree a policy with theGovernments of the United States, Australia, New Zealand, malaya and, if possible, the Philippines and thereafter make it clear to theGovernment of Indonesia that, unless they abandoned their intentions in relation to Borneo, they would be liable to meet concertedresistance. If a warning of this kind was to be effective, it shouldnot be delayed.The Cabinet (3) Took note of these statements and of the points made in discussion.C.C. 6 (63)Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
IndustrialDisputesElectricityIndustry(previous reference:C.C. (63) 4thConclusions,Minute 1)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C. (63) 7), reviewing the courses of action open to theGovernment in seeking to prevent further interruptions of electricity supplies.The Home Secretary said that, if supplies were reduced by factorsother than industrial action, it would not be possible to mitigate theeffects by making regulations under the Emergency Powers Act of1920 to restrain demand; the Act applied only in relation to industrial action on a scale likely to involve a serious disruption of the economy.Nor would it be possible, in the absence of a strike, to employ troops to maintain output. Nevertheless public opinion would expect theGovernment to take positive action if electricity supplies were inadequate; and he had therefore considered, in consultation withthe other Ministers concerned, the policies which the government might adopt in this event.It would be theoretically possible to revive the powers which had existed in the 1939-45 war to forbid strikes. But even during thewar these powers had been ineffective and it had proved impossibleto enforce legal sanctions against large numbers of workers.Alternatively, the Government might take powers to make anagreement or combination by two or more persons indictable as aconspiracy if it resulted in depriving people of essential services.Here again, however, the practical difficulties, not only of proof butalso of enforcement, would be considerable. As a third possibilitythe Government might enact that in certain essential industries anycontract of service should be deemed to include a requirement thatthe employee should perform work considered by his employer tobe necessary to maintain or restore essential services at any time whenthe supply to the public was in danger. Failure to comply would render the employee liable to dismissal and might also, in certaincircumstances, render him liable to a criminal charge under theprovisions of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875.In addition, measures of a more general kind might be taken,e.g., by promoting greater disclosure of the extent of Communist(activity in essential industries and by seeking to give the workers inthose industries an improved status and a greater sense ofresponsibility and to persuade the unions to take stronger disciplinary action against members responsible for unofficial disruptive activity.Efforts could also be made to improve the relationship between management and workers generally.In discussion the following points were made:(a) There were considerable objections in principle to legislationdesigned to prevent individuals from acting in ways which were notin themselves unlawful, e.g., working to rule. Legislation to makeworkers liable to a criminal charge in certain circumstances would beopen to the further objection that the operation of the criminal law should be certain, speedy and unselective. These criteria could notbe satisfied where large numbers of workers were simultaneouslyinvolved.(h) There would nevertheless be strong pressure in parliament for more positive and immediate action than general measures designed to improve working relations in the industry in the long term.Unless the Government put forward proposals of their own for thispurpose they might find difficulty in rejecting other, probably moreobjectionable, proposals which might be recommended in the context of the Contracts of Employment Bill.(c) The possibility of including special provisions in the contracts of service of workers in essential industries should be studied further.Swedish practice in this respect might repay examination. In any measures of this kind, however, it would be necessary to definecarefully the circumstances in which workers could be contractuallyrequired to carry out the orders given to them as well as the permissible
Fuel Supplies 4.   The Minister of Power said that supplies of coal, gas and(Previous        electricity had been seriously affected by the persistent severe weather.Reference:       The reductions in gas pressure which had been necessary in SouthC.C. (62) 44th   Wales and a number of areas in England were primarily due to theConclusions,    difficulty of moving coking coal in sufficient quantities to meet the minute 9)        increased demand.   Arrangements had been made by the national coal Board for a special freight service to the areas which were mostaffected; and gas supplies in South Wales should now improve.   Butdistribution of house coal was likely to be a continuing source of difficulty; and, notwithstanding the abandonment of the work-to-rulecampaign and of the ban on overtime at the power stations, electricity supplies had had to be reduced over wide areas, particularly inSouth-East England.In discussion there was general agreement that the Governmentshould be ready to make available, at short notice, Service manpower and transport to assist the movement of coal. The public should be fully and promptly informed of any action of this kind which proved to be practicable.The Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Power, in consultation with theMinister of Defence and the Secretary of State for War, toconsider, as a matter of urgency, the use of Service resources to assist the movement of coal.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theLord Chancellor (C. (63) 8), to which was appended the re-draft ofa White Paper refuting the allegation by the Prime Minister of theFederation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Sir Roy Welensky, that our agreement to the withdrawal of Nyasaland from the Federation wasin breach of pledges given by United Kingdom Ministers at theConstitutional Conference in 1953, which had established theFederation.The Lord Chancellor said that, in preparing this re-draft inconsultation with the Minister of Health and the Minister without portfolio, he had been concerned mainly to emphasise that thediscussions in 1953 had been confined to the limited question of theFederationof rhodesia and Nyasaland(previous reference:C.C. (63) 4thConclusions,Minute 5)limits of the orders themselves. It would be wrong to place onworkers a statutory obligation to carry out orders which were in themselves unreasonable.(d) Whether the Government sought additional statutory powers or not, it would be right to take all possible steps to improve relationsbetween management and workers and to encourage the trades unions to exercise more effective control over their members.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary, in consultation with the ministers concerned, to examine further the possibility of enactingthat in certain essential industries any contract of service should be deemed to include a provision requiringemployees to obey orders in times of emergency.(2) Agreed to consider, at a later meeting, the desirability of promoting legislation on the lines indicated inConclusion (1) in relation to the Contracts of employment bill.
ability of the four Governments concerned to amend the federal constitution in the context of the projected review of that Constitutionafter a period of years. It had been agreed in the discussions that no constitutional amendment could be made at the time of that reviewotherwise than by agreement among the four Governments; but inrecent speeches in the Federal Assembly, which were being circulated in the United Kingdom. Sir Roy Welensky had interpreted thisagreement as equivalent to a pledge by the United KingdomGovernment not to amend the Constitution without the agreementof all four oovernments. The White Paper, as now drafted,demonstrated that the record of the Conference would not sustainthis interpretation. Publication of the White Paper might await thereturn of the First Secretary of State from his visit to the FederalTerritories; but it should preferably precede a debate on theFederation which would probably take place in the House of lords on 18th February. Before releasing the text, he proposed to incorporate certain amendments suggested by the First Secretary ofState and to verify confidentially whether Lord Chandos andLord Swinton, who had been the United Kingdom Ministerialrepresentatives at the 1953 Conference, would endorse it.In discussion some doubt was expressed whether uninstructedpublic opinion would regard the White Paper as conclusively refutingSir Roy Welensky&apos;s allegation, particularly in the light of certainremarks by the United Kingdom Ministers in 1953 which, considered in isolation, could be held to imply that the Federal Constitution couldnot be abrogated unless all four Governments agreed. It would therefore be desirable to emphasise even more strongly than in the amended text that the relevant extract from the record of the 1953discussions was related solely to the question whether the proposedprovision for a review of the Constitution, by implying the possibility that the Constitution might be annulled, might impair the Federation^credit. It would also be desirable to avoid any reference to thewithdrawal of Nyasaland from the Federation as a unilateral act of secession on the part of the Territory. The decision to allowNyasaland to withdraw had been taken by the United KingdomGovernment; and the record of the 1953 discussions made it clearthat the Federal representatives themselves had accepted that in thelast resort we were empowered to take such a decision. The federal government might seek to challenge the validity of our action in theappropriate court; but we should have little difficulty in establishingour case.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Lord Chancellor:(a) to confirm with the First Secretary of State that,during his discussions in the Federation of rhodesia and Nyasaland, he had consulted the otherGovernments concerned about the proposed publication of the White Paper;(b) to re-draft the White Paper in the light of their discussion and of certain comments which he hadreceived from the First Secretary of State;(c) to ascertain whether, if the White Paper were thereafterpublished, it would be endorsed by Lord Chandosand Lord Swinton;(d) to consider whether the United Kingdom Governmentcould effectively withstand an attempt by theFederal Government to challenge the legal validity of our action in agreeing in principle thatNyasaland should withdraw from the Federation.(2) Agreed to defer a decision on publication of the White Paperuntil the First Secretary of State had returned from theFederation.
House of lords reform(previous reference:C.C. (61) 74thConclusions,Minute 1)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the lord president and the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (C. (63) 6)about the attitude to be adopted by the Government towards theReport of the Joint Committee on House of Lords Reform (H. L. 23:H. C. 38).The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that a committee under the chairmanship of the Prime Minister, which had consideredthe Report of the Joint Committee on House of Lords Reform, hadtaken the view that debates should be initiated in both Houses ofParliament on Motions &quot; to take note &quot; of the Report. Since therewas room for difference of opinion on most of the recommendations,the Government should maintain an open mind during the debates.It could be made clear, however, that they would be prepared tointroduce legislation if this proved to be the general desire; and, while no promise should be made about the date of introduction of the Bill,it would be desirable that it should become law in time to takepractical effect at, but not before, the next General Election.Subject to the outcome of the debates, it would be desirableto proceed with legislation, since there was little doubt of the public feeling in favour of enabling Peers to stand for election to the Houseof Commons. But, in order to minimise the risk of conflict betweenthe two Houses, the Joint Committee&apos;s recommendations should be presented as an integrated set of proposals, to be accepted as a wholeor not at all; and, apart from minor modifications for purelyadministrative reasons, the legislation should be on the lines of theCommittee&apos;s Report without any amendment on points of substance.In discussion there was general agreement with these views. Thefollowing points were raised:(a) There would be no advantage in seeking to postponediscussion in Parliament. The debates might be arranged during february or early in March and could possibly take place in bothHouses on the same day.(b) If legislation were introduced, it would be preferable that thestatus of Members of both Houses should not be altered before the dissolution of the present Parliament. There should be no need,however, to seek to prevent Peers who wished to surrender theirPeerages from initiating action for that purpose as soon as the Bill hadreceived the Royal Assent.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that debates should be initiated in both Houses ofParliament in February or early March 1963 on Motionsto take note of the Report of the Joint Committee on house of Lords Reform.(2) Invited the Government spokesmen in the debates to be guided by the considerations indicated in C. (63) 6.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,24th January, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
