<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/37/0 images: 244-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  May 1963C.C. (63) Copy No.36th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, onThursday, 30th May, 1963, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and Secretary of -State forthe colonies the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of defence the   Right   Hon.   Ernest   Marples,M.P., Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell,M.P., Minister of health the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the following were also present:The Right Hon. Hugh Fraser, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air (Item 6)Mr. Neil Marten, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Aviation(Item 6)Sir John Hobson, Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Item 4)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . A. L. M. cary miss J. J. nunn this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
contents minute no. subject      North Atlantic Treaty Organisation ...Nuclear Force : Mixed-manned Component2 Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland3 Local Government in scotland Tribunals of Inquiry    .........5 Transport        ............Proposed Fare Increases6     Commercial Policy      .........Air Ministry Computers7     South Africa    ............Export of Arms
2a oComponent(i) We faced the problem of dealing with the growing power and aspirations of the Federal Republic of Germany. We must thereforedecide whether to attempt to contain that power by treating germany as less than a full and responsible member of the North atlantic alliance or whether to further her integration with the Alliance andto strengthen her relationships with other member countries.(ii) It remained a fundamental objective of Western policy toprevent the proliferation of nuclear weapons. At present, however,there seemed little prospect that an international treaty for thispurpose could be negotiated; and the mixed-manned force representedan alternative means to this end.(iii) Political pressure within the Federal Republic for the possession of nuclear forces under German control would continueto grow; and it could not be safely assumed that Germany would notdevelop a nuclear capacity either independently or in association withthe French Government. Discussions with responsible Germanpolitical leaders suggested that German participation in the mixed-manned force would enable such dangerous aspirations to be divertedand contained.(iv) Whether or not the United Kingdom participated in the mixed-manned force, the United States Government had already been assured of sufficient support from other members of the Alliance tomake it probable that it would eventually come into being. If we didnot participate in it, we should be unable to exert any influence ona force which could become an increasingly important element in the nuclear forces of the Alliance; and to that extent we should haverenounced the right to a full share in the formulation of NATO policywhich the possession of an independent national nuclear force had so far secured for us.(v) If we opposed, or refused to support, a project to which theUnited States Government attached great importance, we shouldsubject our relations with them to considerable strain; and they mightlook with less favour than hitherto on our continued possession of anindependent nuclear capability.It should not be assumed that the mixed-manned force wouldhave no military value; the United States Government, after very careful consideration, had reached the opposite conclusion. Moreover,the Supreme Allied Commander, Europe (SACEUR), would in course of time need replacements for the nuclear strike aircraft which at present formed part of the forces assigned to him but wouldbecome increasingly obsolescent. The United States government intended that the mixed-manned force should meet this need; if theforce were not formed, SACEUR would probably be provided insteadwith medium-range ballistic missiles, some of which would be locatedon German soil. This might be potentially more dangerous than thecreation of the mixed-manned force itself.For these reasons, even though we might not at this stage beprepared to commit ourselves definitely to full participation in a mixed-manned force, we should at least agree to join with the UnitedStates authorities in a detailed examination of the military andtechnical aspects of the proposal.C.C. 36 (63)North Atlantic 1. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the ForeignTreaty Secretary (C. (63) 95) and the Minister of Defence (C. (63) 96) on theOrganisation United States proposal to establish a mixed-manned force as part(Previous of the nuclear forces of the North Atlantic Treaty OrganisationReference: (NATO), together with copies of messages on this subject, datedC.C. (63) 34th 20th and 29th May, which the Prime Minister had received fromM^nuteS4)nS&apos;    the President of the United States, President Kennedy.Nuclear Force: The Foreign Secretary said that the Governmenfs attitude to thisMixed-manned proposal should be governed by five major considerations of policy:
The Minister of Defence said that from the military point of view the proposed force would add nothing to the deterrent power of theWest since, so long as its use remained subject to a United Statesveto, it would only be employed in circumstances in which theindependent United States deterrent forces, which were in themselves of overwhelming strength, had already been committed.For the same reasons we did not accept that SACEUR should necessarily be provided with medium-range missiles when his presentbomber forces became obsolete.The justification for the mixed-manned force, therefore, wouldhave to be sought in its alleged political advantages. To the UnitedStates Government themselves it might well appear to offer a meansof obtaining, at European expense, weapons which, under theirpresent strategy, they would otherwise have to acquire from theirown resources. But the attempt to justify it on the ground that itwould prevent Western Germany from acquiring her own nuclear weapons involved an assumption that there was no other means ofanticipating such a development. This assumption, however, wasunsound. If the German Government attempted to manufacture theirown weapons, they would be in breach of Treaty and would thenbe no longer entitled to hold their allies to their correspondingobligations; they would have no means of testing the weapons; andthey would be bound to expect a hostile reaction from the SovietGovernment. Nor did it seem likely that the French Governmentwould agree to supply the German Government with nuclear weapons.Moreover, the mixed-manned force might itself enable theGerman Government eventually to acquire nuclear weapons. TheUnited States Government had said that they intended to maintain a veto on the use of the force indefinitely. But, so long as thisremained the case, the political pressure within Germany for an effective share in a military nuclear capability would remainunsatisfied; and it would be aggravated by the practical experience inthe management of nuclear weapons which participation in the mixed-manned force would have given them. It was no doubt for thisreason that, not only privately but in public, certain re]. ^ntativesof the German Government were already looking for w. J to theday when the United States veto would have been replaced by amajority vote; for this would bring appreciably closer the prospectof effective control by the German Government itself over at least some part of the mixed-manned force.Finally, the Soviet Government would be bound to regard the concept of the force as both alarming and provocative, while theFrench Government, on whom in the last resort the defence of western Europe would so largely depend, had been opposed to the project from the start and, if the rest of the Alliance were now tosupport it, would be further isolated from their allies.In discussion the following main points were made:(a) The German Government already contributed to NATO, ona national basis, nuclear delivery systems whose warheads were subject to a United States veto. From their point of view, therefore,the mixed-manned force would not have any advantage so long as its use was also subject to a United States veto. Their anxiety toparticipate in such a force could only be explained by hope andexpectation that the United States veto might in due course be waived.Moreover, to the extent that their participation in the mixed-manned force made it clear to them that it would make no significant additionto the defence of Europe but at the same time gave them experience in the management of modern nuclear weapons, their determination to obtain effective control over nuclear forces of their own would beincreased rather than diminished.
(b) On the other hand, the concept of the mixed-manned force was consistent with the German approach to political unity inEurope. They had shown themselves genuinely anxious to subordinatenational aspirations to a broader European loyalty; and they were concerned at the revival of Nationalist sentiment in France whichPresident de Gaulle was fostering. It could be argued, therefore, that german participation in the mixed-manned force would not be theprelude to a more determined attempt by the German Governmentto obtain nuclear forces of their own but would be accepted by publicopinion in Germany as a sufficient end in itself.(c) A mixed-manned force consisting of surface ships would increase the risk of nuclear war; its relative vulnerability would place it in the category of forces which would have to be used in a firststrike and in times of tension it would therefore be likely to provoke a pre-emptive attack.(d) It would not be easy to convince public opinion in the UnitedKingdom that the creation of the mixed-manned force and our participation in it would contribute to the maintenance of peace orto the security of the West. There was still apprehension in thiscountry, as in the Soviet Union, that gradual German rearmamentwould increase the risk of war; and the proposed force would be liableto be seen as an unwise and unnecessary concession to german military aspirations.(e) On the other hand, there was considerable uncertainty among our allies about our own nuclear policy, particularly since themovement towards greater interdependence which we had initiatedas a result of the Nassau Agreement appeared to have given place torenewed emphasis on the maintenance of an independent UnitedKingdom deterrent. This impression would be reinforced if were fused to participate in the mixed-manned force.(/) Nevertheless, the financial implications of any UnitedKingdom participation in the force would be serious. defence expenditure had already risen above the target figure previouslyapproved; and further increases were in prospect. Moreover, theUnited States were seeking to persuade us to deploy largerconventional forces in Europe at a time when the GermanGovernment were failing to honour their obligation to contribute tothe cost of our forces already stationed there.(g) If, on further consideration, it were held that the possibledangers inherent in the creation of the mixed-manned forceoutweighed its possible advantages, the right course might be toexplain our doubts frankly to the United States Government and either to seek to prevent the creation of the force or at least to makeit clear that we could not ourselves participate in it. But such a coursewould itself involve an element of risk since, if we were unsuccessfulin persuading the United States Government to abandon theirproject, we should place a severe strain on our relations with themto no good purpose, we should increase the influence of the federal german Government at the expense of our own and our attitude would disappoint our allies in Europe and would thereby fortifyPresident de Gaulle in his attempts to strengthen the position ofFrance in Europe at our expense.(h) It would in any case be desirable to pursue with the UnitedStates military authorities, who would shortly be visiting this country,a more detailed examination of the technical aspects of the proposedforce. Our attitude towards the project would depend, to some extent,on the outcome of this examination.
Federation of rhodesia and nyasaland(previous reference:C.C. (63) 35thConclusions,Minute 5)2. The First Secretary of State informed the Cabinet that, in further discussions with the Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia,Mr. Field, about the terms on which the United Kingdom might beprepared to grant independence to the Colony, he had indicated thatwe should expect the Government of Southern Rhodesia to be readyto enlarge the A Roll franchise, to increase the number of seats inthe Legislature reserved for Africans elected on the B Roll franchiseand to make a public declaration of intention to extend the scope ofnon-discrimination. Mr. Field had little hope of persuading hiscolleagues to endorse action on these lines and had indicated that theGovernment of Southern Rhodesia might be unwilling to offer morethan an enlargement of the B Roll franchise. Nevertheless, he remainedreluctant to contemplate a breach of relations with the UnitedKingdom; and he had clearly been impressed by the most recentmessages from the Governments of other member countries of theCommonwealth, particularly Canada and Australia, which hadforcibly represented to the United Kingdom Government theobjections to granting independence to Southern Rhodesia in theabsence of a substantial measure of constitutional reform. If, however,the Government of Southern Rhodesia ultimately rejected even the limited degree of reform which we had suggested, they would probablyrefuse to take part in the projected conference on the dissolution ofthe Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland and would seek tomaintain, with the support of the Federal Prime Minister, Sir roy welensky, that the Federation remained in existence.In discussion it was suggested that, if the Government ofSouthern Rhodesia maintained their intransigent attitude, we shouldbe faced with great difficulty in enacting legislation to validate thesecession of Nyasaland and, in due course, Northern Rhodesia fromthe Federation since, in the absence of co-operation by the federal government and the Government of Southern Rhodesia, it wouldbe impossible to apportion, otherwise than on an arbitrary basis, theFederation^ assets and liabilities among the constituent Territories;and, if the Federal Government itself purported to remain inexistence, the complexities would be aggravated still further. Theproblem would be liable to be particularly acute in relation to theFederal Debt and the Armed Forces. On the other hand, it wouldbe unwise to take a premature decision to cancel the projectedconference on the dissolution of the Federation; and thearrangements for this conference should stand until the final attitudeof the Government of Southern Rhodesia was clear.It seemed unlikely, however, that public opinion in the Colonywould be prepared to accept the conditions which we had suggestedor to contemplate more than some enlargement of the B Rollfranchise. This, however, would be valueless as a means of increasingAfrican representation in the Legislature if the number of seatsreserved for Africans elected on that franchise remained unchanged.We should therefore continue to press the Government of SouthernRhodesia to accept, in addition, some enlargement of the A Rollfranchise and to declare publicly their intention to extend the scopeof non-discrimination. Even so, it must remain doubtful whether asettlement on this basis would be acceptable to the African members the Cabinet (1) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for theUnited States Government to be informed that the UnitedKingdom Government were not yet in a position to offer a final view on the proposal that they should participate in a mixed-manned force, to be established as part of the nuclear forces of NATO.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion at a later meeting.
LocalGovernmentin Scotland(previous reference:C.C. (63) 29thConclusions,Minute 8)3. The Secretary of State for Scotland reported that, in the lightof the Cabinet&apos;s earlier discussion, he had discussed with seniormembers of the Scottish Unionist Committee the proposals in thedraft White Paper appended to his memorandum of 29th April onthe Structure of Local Government in Scotland (C. (63) 74). They hadendorsed the concept of a reorganisation of Scottish local governmenton the lines indicated in that draft; and he therefore proposed toarrange for the White Paper to be published towards the end of June.The Cabinet-Approved the publication of a White Paper on there organisation of local government in Scotland on the linesof the draft appended to C. (63) 74.Tribunals of inquiry(previous reference:C.C. (63) 26thConclusions,Minute 2)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland (C. (63) 97) on theprocedure of tribunals established under the Tribunals of Inquiry(Evidence) Act, 1921.The Home Secretary said that the main criticisms of suchTribunals related to the inquisitorial nature of the proceedings; thefact that innocent persons might suffer hardship in terms both of damage to their reputations and the heavy expense of legalrepresentation; the procedures adopted by the Tribunals, includingC.C. 36 (63)of the Commonwealth; and it was for consideration, therefore,whether we should seek to enforce a further interval before independence was conceded to the Colony, in which we could claim that the enlargement of the A Roll franchise (if it had been acceptedby the Government of Southern Rhodesia) would gradually secure an increase in African representation in the Legislature. It was perhaps unlikely, however, that this would in fact suffice to satisfy the African members of the Commonwealth; nor was it realistic to hope that it would be accepted by the Government of SouthernRhodesia in the light of their insistence that complete independencefor the Colony must coincide with the dissolution of the Federation.The Cabinet (1) Invited the First Secretary of State to be guided, in the concluding stages of his discussions with the PrimeMinister of Southern Rhodesia, by the considerations which had emerged in their discussion.(2) Took note that the First Secretary of State, in consultationwith the Lord Chancellor, would give further considerationto the scope of the Bill which it would be necessary tointroduce if the Governments of the Federation of rhodesia and Nyasaland and of Southern Rhodesiaeventually refused to participate in the projectedconference on the dissolution of the Federation.(3) Agreed to resume their discussion at a subsequent meeting.
Transport 5.   The Minister of Transport recalled that, as he had informedProposed Fare the Cabinet on 23rd May, the London Transport Board and the increases Railways Board intended to increase fares, with effect from 23rd June,(Previous for road and rail journeys to and from London. The increase, which reference: would be of the order of 10 per cent, would not apply to journeys ofC.C. (63) 34th less than four or more than 40 miles. He had considered whether it conclusions, might extend more widely instead of being concentrated on journeysMinute 10)      Gf intermediate length; but he had concluded that there were strongcommercial arguments in favour of the course which the Boardsproposed to adopt.In discussion it was suggested that social considerations mightpoint in the opposite direction and that an increase in fares confined to journeys of intermediate length might not unreasonably be resentedby travellers on suburban lines.The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Minister of Transport and the other Ministers concerned,to give further consideration to the scope of the increasein fares proposed by the London Transport Board and theRailways Board.the appearance of the Attorney-General as counsel for the Tribunal;and the authority which the Act conferred on a Tribunal to refer tothe High Court cases of alleged refusal to answer questions.It was generally recognised that some of these defects wereinherent in the Tribunal procedure. But they would be reduced ifTribunals were established only when absolutely necessary and their terms of reference were drawn as precisely as possible. It seemedimpracticable, in circumstances where there was a clear need for apublic inquiry, to seek to protect innocent persons by prohibiting thepublication of interim reports of proceedings until the Tribunal hadfinally delivered its findings; but hardship in this respect could be mitigated by the payment of legal costs and it was therefore proposedthat, at a convenient opportunity, the Act should be amended toprovide a statutory basis for the recently adopted practice of payingcosts ex gratia. It had also been suggested during the debate on theReport of the Radcliffe Tribunal that cases of refusal to disclosesources of information should be referred to Parliament; but mostof the speakers had recognised that the powers conferred on a tribunal in this respect were necessary.For these reasons there was no case for an inquiry into theTribunal procedure; indeed, such an inquiry might do harm byimplying that there were grounds for complaint about the procedure adopted by the Radcliffe Tribunal.In discussion it was suggested that, in the light of the public criticism of the procedure of Tribunals of Inquiry which had been expressed after each Tribunal of this nature in recent years, parliament might not be easily persuaded that no modification of that procedure was required. This aspect of the matter should be given furtherconsideration.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion of C. (63) 97 of a later meeting.
commercial policy(previous reference:C.C. (63) 34thConclusions,Minute 6)Air MinistryComputers6.   The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the chief secretary, Treasury (C. (63) 93) and the President of the Boardof Trade (C. (63) 98) about the proposed purchase of electroniccomputers by the Air Ministry.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that the Air Ministryrequired a computer to deal with the pay and personnel records ofthe Royal Air Force and that it was desirable that this machineshould be in operation not later than July 1965. Of the tenders whichhad been obtained from United Kingdom, United States and Frenchfirms, that submitted by the United States firm, the Remington RandCorporation, was the most acceptable on both technical and financial grounds. On the other hand, doubts had been expressed about thepolicy implicit in the purchase of a United States computer; and ithad been suggested that, in order to encourage the domesticcomputer industry, it would be preferable to accept one of the UnitedKingdom tenders, even at the cost of higher expenditure and some delay in bringing the machine into operation.The Air Ministry had a further requirement for a computer for controlling their stores. Associated Electrical Industries Limited(A.E.I.) had failed to execute satisfactorily the contract for thismachine which had been placed with them; and legal proceedings against them were under consideration. It was proposed that areplacement order for this computer should now be placed in theUnited States in order that, if the computer to deal with pay andpersonel records was also to be of United States manufacture, theDepartment might be in a position to realise the maximum economic advantages of interchanging work between the two machines.Moreover, the purchase of United States equipment in both cases would ensure considerable economies, whereas the delay which wouldresult from ordering United Kingdom computers would involveadditional expenditure in respect of administrative costs, amountingto some  250,000 a year in the case of the pay and personnel records and about  2 million a year in the case of the stores records.In discussion there was general agreement that it would bedifficult to present a convincing reason for additional delay andexpenditure on this scale other than a deliberate decision of policy to prefer domestic equipment to foreign. This would be contrary toour interests at a time when we were seeking to persuade the UnitedStates Government to adopt a more liberal trade policy; and it would amount to an implicit admission that the United Kingdom computer industry could not compete effectively with its United Statescounterpart. For these reasons there would be clear advantage in accepting the Remington Rand tender for the computer to deal withthe pay and personnel records. On the other hand, it would beimpolitic to cast unnecessary doubt on the efficiency of the UnitedKingdom computer industry, since we hoped to secure considerableorders for computers from Western Germany. It would therefore bedesirabL to consider further whether, even at the cost of some delay,A.E.I. would be able to complete satisfactorily the manufacture ofthe computer for the control of R.A.F. stores.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the computer for dealing with the pay and personnel records of the Royal Air Force should be purchased in the United States on the basis of the tendersubmitted by the Remington Rand Corporation.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Ministers concerned, to give further considerationto the possibility of reaching a fresh understanding withAssociated Electrical Industries Limited, on the basis of
which the company might be able to completesatisfactorily the manufuacture of a computer for controlling Air Ministry stores.(3) Agreed that, pending the result of the enquiries to beundertaken under Conclusion (2) above, no legal action should be instituted against Associated ElectricalIndustries Limited.South AfricaExport ofArms(previous reference :C.C. (63) 34thConclusions,Minute 7)7. The Home Secretary informed the Cabinet that, inaccordance with their decision on 23rd May, 1963, he had given further consideration, in consultation with the Ministers concerned,to the current request by the South African Government for thesupply of 3,500 Smith and Wesson -38 revolvers which were of lease-lend origin.The South African Government had been informed in July 1961that, although we saw no great difficulty in continuing to supply them with arms and military equipment in general, we should feelunable to make available small arms and small arms ammunition.In June 1962, however, we had exported 1,500 -38 revolvers to SouthAfrica on the grounds that, although it would be possible for themto be used for repressive action, they were primarily weapons ofself-defence and the quantity involved was small. This made it moredifficult for us to reject the current request on political groundswithout implying that we had changed our policy on the export ofarms to South Africa. If the Government of South Africa formed this impression, they might retaliate by reconsidering both the defence facilities which they put at our disposal in Simonstown and the substantial orders for aircraft and defence equipment which they had placed, or intended to place, in the United Kingdom. If, on the otherhand, we agreed to the export of the revolvers in question, we shouldbe liable to incur considerable international embarrassment. In thesecircumstances, the wisest course might be to seek the views of theUnited States Government, whose consent would be required to theexport of arms of lease-lend origin.In discussion, there was general agreement with this proposal.In addition, however, we should make it clear the South african government that, if they maintained their request for the export ofthe revolvers in question, they would be liable to prejudice therelations which we sought to maintain with them; and we should therefore urge them once again to withdraw their proposal.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to make renewed representa-tions to the South African Government that they should withdraw their request for the export of revolvers.(2) Agreed to defer a final decision on the export of revolvers to south Africa until the results of the enquiries to be madeunder Conclusion (1) were known.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,30th May, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
