<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/37/0 images: 276-279</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted ior the Cabinet.   June 1963C.C. (63)41st conclusions copy No.45CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. I, on Monday, 24th June, 1963, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll.M.P., President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P.. Minister of education the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and Secretary of State forthe colonies the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P..Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P.,    Minister    of    Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell, M.P.,Minister of health the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, M.P.,Minister   of   Housing   and   LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne, I Lieutenant-General Sir DenisM.P., Parliamentary Secretary, 0&apos;Connor, Deputy Chief of DefenceTreasury , I    staff secretariat:Sir Burke trend . A. L. M. Gary3521-1
Subject :Kenya
0 r03Kenya(previous reference:C.C. (62) 26thConclusions.Minute 4)The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the colonial secretary (C. (63) 105), to which was appended the draft of a communique announcing that, subject to the necessary steps being completed in time, Kenya would become independent on 12thDecember, 1963.The Colonial Secretary said that, in the light of developments inrecent weeks, there was now a reasonable prospect that a Federationof Kenya, Uganda and Tanganyika would be established. Such a development would be welcome since, apart from its economic advantages, a Federation would tend to reduce the risk of tribaldissension in Kenya and to reinforce the position of other minoritygroups.The three Governments hoped to bring the Federation into beingby the end of the year, in order that it might be represented at theUnited Nations in the 1964 session. If objections on our part delayedthe independence of Kenya and, therefore, the establishment of theFederation beyond the end of 1963, we should incur the odium of appearing to frustrate the Federation and should lose the goodwill of all three countries concerned. For these reasons we must nowcontemplate an earlier date for the attainment of independence byKenya than we had previously envisaged. We should accept12th December, 1963, as the relevant date and should publiclyannounce our intention to take the steps necessary to this end,including a conference to settle the final Constitution of Kenya inSeptember.In discussion the following points were made:(a) So far as possible the safeguards for minorities containedin the present Constitution of Kenya should be preserved.Some concession might have to be made to the view of the kenya African Nationalist Union (KANU), from whose members the present Kenya Government was largely drawn, that the presentsafeguards were unduly restrictive in that they virtually precludedfuture constitutional changes of any kind. But the fact that theConstitutional Conference would have to reach conclusions very rapidly might help to keep changes to a minimum. Moreover,membership of the Federation would itself restrain a future government of Kenya from making arbitrary constitutional changes;and this in turn would tend to strengthen the position of the minorities.The European inhabitants of Kenya would be likely to welcome theestablishment of the Federation as tending to promote greater stability in the area as a whole.(b) The problem of Zanzibar&apos;s nominal sovereignty over the region of Kenya known as the Coastal Strip could probably be solved by an arrangement with the Sultan of Zanzibar under which, subjectto a process of consultation yet to be worked out in detail, sovereigntywould be effectively ceded to the Government of an independentKenya.(c) It would be necessary to enter into consultation with theGovernments of Ethiopia and Somalia in an attempt to find a solution to the problem of the Northern Frontier District before the attainment of independence by Kenya. The establishment of the Federation might also be of value in this context, since the Northern Frontier District,while representing a substantial area of Kenya, would form a lesssignificant part of a Federation of Kenya, Uganda and Tanganyika;and this fact might make it politically less embarrassing for theGovernment of Kenya to accept the secession of the District toSomalia.(d) The acceleration of Kenya&apos;s independence by some sixmonths, which the timetable now proposed by the Colonial Secretaryinvolved, would make it the more important to decide our future military dispositions in Africa and the Middle East. It had always beenenvisaged that, when Kenya became independent, United kingdom troops would be withdrawn over a period. Under the earlier plans
this withdrawal would probably have had to be completed in sixmonths, i.e., by the end of 1964. It might now be possible, however,to extend this period to 12 months, i.e., from the end of 1963 to theend of 1964. It would remain important, however, that the troopswithdrawn from Kenya should be transferred to Aden, where newaccommodation would have to be provided for them. It would alsobe desirable to build up Kenya&apos;s own military forces, a process whichwould take at least 18 months; to ensure that, once the withdrawal ofUnited Kingdom troops had started, it should be brought rapidly to completion; and to negotiate with the Kenya Government satisfactory arrangements for our retention of longer-term military facilities in kenya itself, in particular the continuation of over-flying rights, themaintenance of certain radio stations, the provision of training facilities and the right to establish and make use of leave and rest camps. Thestrength of our negotiating position in these respects would be likelyto depend on the extent to which we should be prepared to provideassistance to the Government of Kenya in connection with the equipment, organisation and training of their own forces.(e) The most serious difficulty to which the proposed acceleration of the timetable would give rise might be in relation to the current negotiations about the future of the Federation of Rhodesia and nyasaland. It would now become difficult, if not impossible, to defer the grant of independence to Nyasaland for as long as would otherwise have been desirable; and this would in turn intensify pressure forcorresponding acceleration in the case of Northern Rhodesia, towhom it might become necessary to concede a self-governingConstitution in the autumn of 1963. The problem of Southern rhodesia would then become even more intractable than at present. further discussions with the Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia,Mr. Winston Field, and with the Prime Minister of the Federation of rhodesia and Nyasaland, Sir Roy Welensky, were due to start in thenext few days. If a public announcement that Kenya was to attainindependence in December 1963 were made on the eve of those discussions, the task of our negotiators would become even moredifficult. It would be helpful, therefore, if the public announcementcould be delayed for at least a week or 10 days, during which wecould inform Mr. Field and Sir Roy Welensky of our revised intentions as regards Kenya, together with the justification of the course whichwe proposed to adopt.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of advantage appeared to lie in arranging for Kenya to attainfull independence in December 1963. But no public announcement to this effect should be made until the First Secretary of State had hadan opportunity of ascertaining the probable reactions of Mr. WinstonField and Sir Roy Welensky. The Government of Kenya could resonably be asked to accept the short delay involved, on the groundthat we required further time in which to assess the implications ofthe redeployment of United Kingdom troops in Kenya on the basisof the revised timetable.The Cabinet (1) Agreed, in principle, that Kenya should be grantedindependence in December 1963.(2) Authorised the Colonial Secretary to make a public statement to this effect in the near future.(3) Agreed to defer a decision on the precise form and timing ofthis statement until the First Secretary of State had beenable to ascertain, and to report to the Cabinet, the reactions of the Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia and the PrimeMinister of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasalandto the Governments decision to accelerate the attainment of independence by Kenya.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,25th June, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
