<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/37/0 images: 361-365</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1963C.C. (63)53rd conclusions copy No.42CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House. S.W. 1, onThursday, 19th September, 1963, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.PThe Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the ExchequerPrime minister the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne, LordChancellorHenry Brooke, M.P.,State  for  the  home the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P.. Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell, M.P..Minister of health the Right hon secretary  of department the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P.. Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:Sir   Peter   Rawlinson,Solicitor-GeneralQ.C..   M.P.,The Right Hon. martin.P.,      parliamentary treasury redmayne,Secretary,Secretariat:3884-2
iContentsMinuteNo. subject      Foreign Affairs......Indonesia2      Lord Denning&apos;s Report
Foreign AffairsIndonesia(previous reference:C.C. (63) 35thConclusions,Minute 2)I. The Foreign Secretary said that on 18th September her majesty&apos;s Embassy at Djakarta had been looted and burned in thecourse of an Indonesian demonstration against the creation of malaysia. The Indonesian police had made little attempt to control the situation, although they had now been reinforced by the army. Hehad protested strongly to the Indonesian Ambassador and hopedduring the course of the day to receive a formal assurance that Britishlives and property would henceforward be protected. Despite thisoutrage, we should avoid, if possible, any rupture of diplomatic relations with Indonesia, particularly since the labour unions whichhad seized control of certain British enterprises had apparently been instructed by the Indonesian Government to relinquish firms whichthey had taken over. Moreover. United Kingdom and United Statesoil companies were due to conclude a new agreement with the indonesian Government during the next few days on comparativelyfavourable terms.In discussion there was general agreement with this view. the indonesian Government should be required, however, to pay fullcompensation for the damage to United Kingdom property; and,although it would be to our advantage to maintain our trade withIndonesia, the extent to which we made export credit facilities available for this purpose should be reviewed.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the statement by the Foreign Secretary.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe other Ministers concerned, to consider whether thelatest developments in Indonesia required us to reconsider the extent of the export credit facilities which we providedfor the promotion of trade with Indonesia.Lord Denning&apos;s *2. The Cabinet discussed the procedure for publishing theReport report which Lord Denning had submitted to the Prime Minister on16th September, in discharge of his enquiry into matters arising fromthe resignation of the former Secretary of State for War. Mr. j. DProfumo.The Prime Minister said that it would clearly be desirable to publish the text of this report in full, subject only to suchamendment or deletion as might be necessary on grounds of national security or of possible prejudice to the pending trial of Miss ChristineKeeler on charges of perjury and conspiracy to prevent the course ofjustice.In discussion there was general agreement with this suggestion.The extent of the amendment required on grounds of security would need further consideration. As regards Miss Keeler, however, she hadalready disclosed publicly so much of the material about herself whichwas contained in Lord Denning&apos;s Report that it was unlikely that its publication could reasonably be held to be liable to prejudice theforthcoming proceedings. Moreover, the report was concerned only with her character and appeared to contain nothing which was relevant to the current charge against her. It would be desirable,however, to verify carefully that it did not include any references to her credibility as a witness which might be held to be prejudicial.Previously recorded as a Confidential Annex.SECRET3884-2
The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that Lord Denning had stated that he regarded his submission of his report to theGovernment as a form of publication which was protected by absoluteprivilege but that no other form of publication would be so protected;and he had suggested that, since the report contained passagesreflecting on certain individuals, its general publication should beauthorised by a Resolution of one of the Houses of Parliament, which,under the Parliamentary Papers Act, 1840, would afford it absoluteprivilege. If the Government accepted Lord Denning&apos;s advice on thispoint, it would be necessary to recall one, or both, of the Houses ofParliament. The alternative would be to publish the report as a command Paper, on the authority of the Government alone. In that event publication would be protected only by qualified privilege.In discussion some support was expressed for Lord Denning&apos;opinion. If the Government ignored it and individuals who regardedthemselves as adversely affected by the report subsequently institutedlegal proceedings, public discussion of the report would be liable tobe inhibited until those proceedings had been settled; and an episodewhich should now be brought to an end as promptly as possiblewould be further protracted. Moreover, the Press might feel that theGovernment were treating them unfairly if they did not afford them the maximum degree of protection in respect of publication of, andcomment on, the report.Against these considerations the following arguments wereadvanced:(a) The protection of absolute privilege afforded by theParliamentary Papers Act, 1840, would extend only to the individualsresponsible for writing and publishing the report. Any subsequentquotation from, or comment on, the published text by the Press wouldbe protected only by qualified privilege, although the degree of suchprotection might be rather greater if the original document itself wasprotected by absolute, rather than by qualified, privilege.(b) Since it would take a little time to prepare and print thereport for publication and it was desirable in the public interest thatit should be published in time for the Party Conferences which were due to take place in the weeks beginning 30th September and 7th October, it would be impracticable to recall the House ofCommons for the purpose of authorising publication. Moreover, theHouse could properly be recalled only in connection with a matterof urgent national importance.(c) A recall of the House of Lords would perhaps be more easilyarranged; but there could be no guarantee that the House would authorise publication without discussion and the Government mightnot find it easy to ensure the necessary majority in any debate whichmight develop.For these reasons the balance of advantage might lie in dispensingwith Parliamentary privilege, publishing the report as a command paper and accepting that, if any of the individuals named in the reportsubsequently took legal action for defamation, an adequate defencecould probably be based on qualified privilege. If so, however, itwould be necessary to explain to Lord Denning the reasons which had led the Government to this conclusion and perhaps to assure him that, if proceedings were instituted against himself, the Governmentwould introduce legislation to indemnify him. It would also benecessary to make it clear to the Press that the protection which wouldbe afforded to them under this procedure would be only marginallyless than the protection which they would enjoy if publication were authorised by Parliament under the Parliamentary Papers Act, 1840.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that hewould now discuss with the Leader of the Opposition, who had read the report, the procedure to be adopted for its publication; and a finaldecision could be taken in the light of the result of this interview.
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,19th September, 1963.(i) Invited the Solicitor-General to consider whether publicationof Lord Denning&apos;s Report would be liable, by casting doubt,on the credibility of Miss Christine Keeler as a witness, to prejudice the forthcoming proceedings against her oncharges of perjury and conspiracy to prevent the courseof justice.(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would discuss with the leader of the Opposition the procedure to be adopted forthe publication of the report.

</content>
</cab>
