<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/23/18 images: 150-163</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOOK AND KEY.it is requested that special care may be taknn toensure the secrecy of this document.7, poGUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJEOTY^S^GOVERNMENT-Jjf^SECRET.1ST APRIL.  1942,WAR CABINET,OPY NO.INDIA,Telegrams exchanged bjetweejijbhe Lord Privy Seal and: the Prime Minister,,

3 be kept under lock and in is requested that special care may be taken&apos;foensure the secrecy of this document.From Viceroy to Secretary of state for *ind?,a*Dated New Delhis  16*50 hours, 1st April. 1948.Received    16.15 hours./ 1st April 19480SECRET    XXX8635,Persona;MinisteroFollowing f om Sir S. Orlpps for the Primeio From all appearances it seems certain that Congress willturn down the proposals. There are a multitude of currents andcross currents but. they are selecting the question of defence as their main platform for opposition,  .S* The Moslem League who are prepared to accept will nodoubt if Congress refuse also find some reasons for refusal aswell as all the other sections of opinion^So There has been an almost unanimous protest fromrepresentatives including the European community as to thecomplete retention of the existing control of defence by H,M.G,(1 should however add that the. Viceroy doubts whether this isrepresentative of the attitude of Europeans in Bengal)*      Thisprotest arises partly from a misunderstanding of the position which I have tried to clarify in successive stages and partly because people feel that the maximum of appeal must be made tothe Indian people by- their leaders if they are to be galvanisedto their defence,  and that unless those leaders can claim somecontrol over their defence of India they cannot males theirappeal effective to the Indian people. -4* Except in the Punjab and the North West Frontier thepresent situation as to morale amongst the Indian and in manycases the Buropean population is deplorable      The Anti-british feeling is running very strong and our prestige is lower than It-has ever been owing to the events in Burma and more particularlyin Singapore,,    - The stories -circulating on all sides as to malaya and Singapore convey an impression of incompetence whichi nd e ed a 1 ar m i ng *is , Unrest is. growing among the population and unemployment is developing in certain centres.,    &apos; The food situation is causing disquiet and refugee problem in view of complaints of discrimination against the Indians, of which the administration is accused, and &quot;v/hich I have asked, the Viceroy to look into Issource of serious intensification of Anti-British feeling.a6,The outlook so far as internal situation goes is exceedingly bad and if we cannot persuade Indian Leaders to come in now and help us we shall&apos; have to resort to suppression whichmay develop to such a scale that it may well get out of hand eventhough we use for this purpose a part of our frail military resources..

f0 i give you this picture so that you. may gudgs as to theimportance-from a Defence point of view of getting indian leaders into job of controlling? encouraging and leading IndianpeopXe6     This cannot toe done under existing circumstances by.any appeaserc.q,,        The present situation as to -Defence Minister is that new words which were drafted by Viceroy were put into paragraph(e) with full consent of Commander-in-chief who consulted withviceroy upon this point without my being presents,9, An explanatory letter- was sent to     In     mrm-&apos;rj^ycontaining following material paragraph&apos;:- &quot;&quot;&quot;It must, he clearly understood that &quot;&quot;final definition of division of responsibilities  ti esbetween- lord. G. and Government of India is as stated inparagraph (e) of document. The Viceroy would be prepared .to iconsult with Indian Leaders on this basis to see whether it 1were possible to designate an Indian to some office connected Iwith Government of India Defence responsibilities without in jany way Impinging upon functions and duties of commander---in&apos;-GhJj!either in his capacity as supreme commander of armed forces in india or as member of Executive Council in charge of Defence&quot;,I10o       1 have consequently, addressed a letter (text in my Jimmediately succeeding-telegram) suggesting interview with      1Congress Leaders with commander-in -Chief*,lla If some adjustment can be so arrived at will you giveae full authority subject to agreement of Cormvahder-&apos;In---chief and Viceroy.,

jnder Lnr.itnay be ta!Co6 sec,&apos;eoy of this document.aott.eci__._feo JPriyjatSeej^^ry c S56,fcJiiLJLgiLJLJP.........JLJL-JL&amp;ilP ,g, RjUE-From        Viceroy to Secretary of State for India,Dated&apos;     New Delhiv  16,30 hours,  1st April 1948,Received 14*30 hours,  1st April 1942.MOST-&apos; IMMSto sfo&quot;ft.DlATEcPersonal-,     Following from Sir S. Orlops forPrime Minister..    Following is text of letterreferred to rn ray immediately preceding telegram,.Begins?    I understand from Hindu press that-difficulties are still in mind of Congress as to question of responsibility for Defence of India,X have done what 1 could to clarify this pointbut as I. think it would be a tragedy if negotiations were to break down upon any misunderstanding of theposition I should like uo suggest that I should askCommander--in-Chief x,o meet yourself^and PanditJawahar- Lai Nehru with myself in order that he mayexplain fuily^fcw you the (? technical) difficultiesof the situation and in order that you may make to aim any suggestions you wish as to division of responsibilities in this sphere of government*TJnf or % unat elySECRET     XXX74

gnfortunat-ely he is at the moment away in Calcuttabut he is expected hack on Saturday next at thelatest (and possibly earlier)-.      If you consider this a helpful suggestion - as I hope you will -I will ask him the moment ha returns whether hewill he prepared to attend such a meeting and I donot anticipate that there will toe any difficulty about it.-, .I am sure you will realise that I do not want to be met with a impasse if there is any reasonableway out.     Ends;,

PRIME MINISTER-TO SIR STAFFORD CRIPPS.Personal and Seoi^et3I cannot give you any authority to compromise on defence without submitting issue both to Cabinet and ministers above the Line-    I will bring your telegrambefore Cabinet tomorrow,    Everyone admires the manner inwhich&apos;you have discharged your difficult mission and the,\ev.&quot; tt\ &apos;effect of our proposals has been most beneficial in theUnited States and in ln?ge circles here.




</content>
</cab>
