<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/19/33 images: 372-375</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOYERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1941. t ^_ lidCopy No.    29TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.SECRET.W.P. (41) 260.November 6, 1941.WAR CABINET.AIR POLICY ATTACK ON FACTORIES IN OCCUPIED FRANCEKNOWN TO BE MANUFACTURING MUNITION SUPPLIES FORTHE ENEMY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air. /1. THE War Cabinet, at their 104th Meeting (Conclusion 2 (b)), asked that proposals should be submitted for the bombing of certain factories in occupied France known to be engaged in the manufacture of munition supplies for the enemy.2. The most important of these factories number four. They manufacture and assemble aircraft, aero engines, tanks and lorries.3. Advantages.(i) Material damage to the factories attacked, which should be considerable,since the defences are likely to be weak.(ii) Moral effect on the workers in other factories, resulting in a generalloss of output for Germany.(iii) Encouragement  to the French  nation  generally   (Frenchmen  have repeatedly asked us to bomb French factories working for Germany).(iv) Possible diversion of A.A. guns to France from Germany.4.   Disadvantages.(i) A limited diversion of bombs from Germany and &quot; Battle of the atlantic &quot; targets, probably on one of the rare occasions of goodweather.(ii) Some bombs will inevitably miss the factory and kill Frenchmen notengaged there. By choosing good weather we should expect to avoidwidespread damage outside the target area.5. I have little doubt that we could undertake successful attacks on the objectives, and that, if they were combined with propaganda, they would havean adverse effect on the German war industry in France.6. The War Cabinet, at their 62nd Meeting on the 23rd June, 1941, gaveapproval to the daylight bombing of factories in Northern France and a numberof successful daylight attacks on factories have been delivered. These werepreceded by the dropping of leaflets and by wireless broadcasts informing thepopulation of occupied France of our intention to bomb factories engaged inthe production of munitions of war for the Germans, and urging them to keep[23119J
away from the factories. I ask the War Cabinet to extend this authority tocover the night bombing of these factories when weather conditions are such that an accurate attack can be expected.7. If this is approved, I propose that at the first suitable opportunity anattack on the heaviest possible scale should be delivered on one of the targetsreferred to in paragraph 2. If successful, the widest possible publicity would begiven to the attack in order to secure the maximum effect on the morale of theFrench workers in other similar factories. After a suitable interval had elapsedthe attack would be repeated on others of these targets. The attacks would bearranged to interfere as little as possible with our main bombing offensive against targets in Germany.5 A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, November 6, 1941.



</content>
</cab>
