<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/229/0 images: 127-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majestvs governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1932.SECRET. Copy No. 9CP. 110 (32).CABINET.DISARMAMENT CONFERENCE.OUR colleagues may like to have the following summary report of the proceedings of the Disarmament Conference since the close of the general discussion, which was reached on the 24th February.2. It must be confessed that the actual progress since that date has been slight. The Bureau of the Conference had already recommended that the Conference should adjourn for the Easter recess on the 19th March, and the time at the disposal of the various Commissions of the Conference was thus short enough in any event. The Far Eastern crisis and the summoning of the Special Assembly, which it necessitated, diverted public interest from the subject of disarmament, and put material difficulties in the way of frequent meetings or of any continuous work.3. It is unnecessary to attempt to pick one&apos;s way through the maze of Bureaux and Commissions, or to give any chronological account of the spasmodic discussions which took place when best they might, but it may be useful to give some idea of the organisation which has been set up and of the programme of work which has been tentatively evolved.4. The comparatively small Bureau of the Conference had as its primary function the planning of the work. In practice the Bureau has developed a diffidence which leads it to submit its conclusions to the General Commission in all cases. This Commission is really the nerve centre of the Conference. As in the case of all the main Commissions of the Conference, every Delegation is represented on it generally by the First Delegate, in name if not in fact.5. The intention is that the General Commission should lead and direct the Conference. It should take all decisions of principle, only referring its decisions to the Technical Commissions for them to work them out in practical detail. It is, in fact, the Conference in Committee. It has the drawback of being unwieldy in size, but it has, of course, the authority which the Bureau seemed to feel it lacked. Later, no doubt, it will have to resolve itself into a smaller body or bodies, but as it has not yet really come to grips with its work, the need for that has not yet made itself felt.6. At its first effective meeting, on the 25th February, the General Commission adopted the following resolution : &apos;: The General Commission resolves to carry on its discussions within the framework of the Draft Disarmament Convention, full liberty being reserved to all Delegations to develop their own proposals in subsequent debate, and to move their amendments in the form of modifications, additions or omissions at the appropriate point.&quot;7. At the same meeting, the General Commission decided to set up Land, Naval, Air and Defence Expenditure Commissions, and, on the proposal of the French Delegation, a Political Commission.6312   [6762] b
8. The next task was to draw up a programme of work, and this was entrusted to Dr. Benes, the rapporteur of the General Commission.9. In view of the resolution quoted above, it was decided that he should draw up a &quot; synoptic table &quot; (familiar words of sinister association to habitues of Geneva), which should show in parallel columns the. articles of the Draft Convention and the various modifications and new suggestions which emerged from the speeches in the opening discussion of the Conference.10. Dr. Benes even went further, for he produced such a table comprising four columns, a copy of which in its final form is enclosed herein (Annex I).11. The first column reproduces the text of the articles of the draft conven-tion. The second shows every suggestion, of no matter what delegation, which can be related to each article. The third is the hybrid offspring which is dignified with the name of &quot;Questions of principle raised.&quot; The fourth, which is discreetly headed &quot;Observations,&quot; suggests, where it can, a decent disposal of the principle thus obtruded on the notice of the Conference.12. From this mass of material Dr. Benes at the same time distilled agenda for the various Commissions, which will be found in Paper Conf. D. 103, copy of which is also enclosed (Annex II).13. Both these documents were approved by the General Commission on the 8th March. From the discussions which then took place, it was clear that the intention was that the General Commission should forthwith begin a discussion of the items appearing on its list, preferably, though not necessarily, in the order in which.they therein appear, and that meanwhile the other Commissions should tackle the questions appearing on their lists which, as will be seen, are described as being capable of being dealt with &quot;without previous discussion by the General Commission.&quot;14. For the sake of appearances all the Technical Commissions were set to work on the two following days, the 9th and 10th March. But on closer inspection it proved that in fact they were always being faced with the questions of principle necessitating reference back to the General Commission, and the work that they have been able to do is really almost negligible. &apos;15. The proceedings of the General Commission or rather the lack of them require rather more elaborate explanation, and for this purpose it is necessary to make some analysis of part of the &quot; synoptic table.&quot;16. The Preparatory Commission, in 1930, recoiled from the task of drafting a Preamble to the Disarmament Convention, and instead inserted an article 1, which is really no more than a preamble, in that it merely engages the parties to &quot; limit and. so far as possible, to reduce their respective armaments as provided in the present Convention.&quot; Dr. Benes could do no less than place this unfortunate text at the head of his column No. 1.17. Having done that, it was difficult for him not to collect against it in the second column all the various propositions concerning the principles of reduction and limitation of armaments. The synoptic table thus began at the very outset by propounding all the most thorny and contentious problems. This did not seem the best way to go about the work; it would not appear to the ordinary man wise to begin a Conference by an acrimonious discussion of principles on which acute divergence was known to exist; it would have seemed better to take the effective articles of the Draft Convention and endeavour to get them into a final form which should approximate as nearly as possible to the different ideals of the various delegations, or at least effect an acceptable compromise between them.18, To understand the agenda of the. General Commission, it is necessary to read it in conjunction not only with the synoptic.table, but also,with the &quot; Survey of Proposals made by various Delegations during the General Discussion &quot; (Annex III).19. The agenda begins with I (a) Definitive reduction under a single convention.&quot; This corresponds to I (a) of the synoptic table &quot; Reduction to an equal limit of peace-time armed forces (land, sea and air) of all countries.
Reduction to be carried out within ten years Turkey.&quot; Reference is there given to page 29 of the survey, where the Turkish proposals will be found in detail. This illustration will show how the three documents should be read together.20. To return to the agenda, I (6) reads &quot; Reduction to the lowest possible level,&apos;&quot; which seems harmless enough, until one traces it back to its origin in the survey, where one finds that it arises from the proposals of the German delegation. The actual page in the survey referred to contains the ominous phrase: &quot; The German delegation wish to make it clear that the German Government cannot accept a Convention unless its provisions are equally applicable to Germany and to other signatory countries.&quot; In this way the innocent phrase quoted at the beginning of this paragraph gives rise to the whole controversy about &quot; equality of treatment.&quot;21. Item I (c), &quot; Reduction to be brought about by stages,&apos;&apos; covers a number of harmless proposals, and should cause little difficulty.22. Item II (a) corresponds to III (a) in the synoptic table a Chinese proposal for the determination of limits of armed forces by reference to certain factors, such as size of territory, population, length of frontiers, &amp;c. an idea which has been discussed often in the past and is unlikely now to afford a ready solution of our difficulties.23. Item IT (b) is a matter of no great importance or difficulty. Item II (c) is the American proposal for determining the limits of effectives by reference to the needs of internal order and national defence.24. With Item III (a) we come to the Italian proposal for the prohibition of certain weapons of war, and III (b) introduces that part of the French plan which prohibits certain material if the latter does not form the subject of an undertaking to place it at the disposal of the League of Nations.25    Item IV raises the whole French theory of security.26. Item V, corresponding to VI in the synoptic table, enables the ex-enemy States to argue again the whole of their case for &quot; equality of treatment.&quot;27. Item VI represents the proposal of the Netherlands : &quot; Limitation and reduction must be applied to the whole of the armed forces immediately mobilisable. Consequently they must embrace : (a) trained reserves, in the first instance by reducing the contingent; (b) the material of the land forces, by the direct method.&quot;28. Items VII and VIII call for no special comment. Item IX is the extremely inconvenient proposal of the Argentine concerning the rules of blockade, which, as you are aware, it is hoped to remove from the agenda of the Conference.29. It will be seen that the foregoing agenda are really a summary of the major points of principle which divide Governments on the subject of Disarmament, and the discussion of them forthwith would not, one would think, be an auspicious prelude to the work of the Conference. Curiously enough, however, the protagonists evinced a morbid desire to engage at once in these apparently fruitless wrangles. Both the French and the Germans seemed to think that Geneva afforded an admirable election platform. It was at first arranged that the German thesis (I (b) or V) should be taken towards the end of last week, on the eve of the German presidential election, and that thereupon a second round should be staged in the following week by the introduction of the French proposals under the guise of item IV. It was said that both sides would be content with emphatic, though not provocative, assertion of their principles, and that neither would insist on a vote. It is not easy to believe that such a discussion could have passed off in an entirely amicable spirit, or that a good deal of heat would not have been engendered in the process. But if we could make the more favourable assumption,1&quot; there may perhaps be something to be said for taking the discussion at the initial stage. For if this were not done, it is true that this very discussion of principle could be raised at almost every successive point in the Draft Convention. From a practical point of view, therefore, it might save time to concentrate the discussion in one debate. Moreover, it may be that, if honour is satisfied by a resounding assertion of principles at the outset, these latter might[6762] b 2
be allowed to rest more in the background, while practical questions are being discussed.30. When M. Tardieu arrived in Geneva a day or two ago, it seemed that the battle might begin. But it has now been postponed until after the recess. The official reason given for this delay is that it would have been inconvenient to have begun a discussion which, owing to the short time now available, would have had to be broken off in the middle for some three weeks. It may be that M. Tardieu reflected that, with a second count in the German presidential election ahead of us, an attack on the German position might not influence favourably the result. Whatever the reason, the matter now stands adjourned until the 11th April, when the General Commission will hold its next meeting.31. The Technical Commissions have, meanwhile, been struggling with a few minor items, but have been unable to achieve much owing to the lack of a lead from the General Commission. The idea of the Bureau, that public opinion would be impressed by getting all the Commissions to work simultaneously in the last week of the session, has defeated its own purpose. The necessary futility of their proceedings in the circumstances has impressed the public in a way that was not anticipated by the Bureau, and the realisation of this fact produced the decision to close down the Conference for the Easter recess a day or two before the time fixed.32. It seems clear that the Conference can now only get down to useful work if the General Commission will meet at once after the resumption and remain in continuous session until such time as it shall have arrived at a sufficient number of decisions to keep the Technical Commissions at work in their proper sphere.33. This discussion by the General Commission will be of real importance. The first part of it, on Chapter A of the agenda, which is shortly surveyed above, raises a number of important points on which we shall probably have to intervene.34. In the first place, there is the German question of &apos;&apos; equality of treat-ment.&quot; The Germans will take this opportunity of restating all their old arguments to show that the Allies are under an obligation to reduce their arma-ments to the state to which German armaments are restricted. The French will not only contest this claim, but will, as appears likely from what M. Tardieu recently said in Paris, seek to show that it is the Germans who are the treaty breakers, and will bring against them accusations of having violated the military clauses of the Treaty of Versailles. This is calculated to give rise to a most acrimonious debate, and our role should presumably be to exercise such moderating influence as may be possible. On the one hand, there has, in the past, been correspondence between His Majesty&quot;s Government and the French Government on the subject of German violations of the Treaty, and we have on occasions admitted to the French that we agreed that certain violations had been committed. If the French now bring these up against the Germans and we remain silent, the former migvht well complain that we were guilty of desertion. We might therefore have to admit that we believed that violations had taken place, though that individually they had not been of sufficient importance to warrant action. If their total cumulative effect were proved to be serious, we should have to join in a remonstrance to the Germans. On the other hand, while rebutting the extreme German claim on legal grounds for &quot; equality of treatment,&quot; we could emphasise Germany&apos;s moral claim and the corresponding moral obligation on the Allies. We do not attempt to outline here the form which our intervention should take : we merely make these suggestions in order to indicate the kind of situation with which we are likely to be faced and the sort of  arguments which should receive consideration.35. On the other side, there is the whole French &quot; security &quot; thesis, on which we must be prepared to state our case. The policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government, of no further commitments, is perfectly clear, and should come as no surprise to the French Delegation. It will remain to be seen how it can best be stated without giving an appearance of simple obstruction at all points. The particular French proposals regarding the institution of a League force are open to very practical criticism : it is difficult to believe that many think them really practic-able, and we cannot help suspecting that they do not have the full confidence of their authors.
36. The Italian proposal for the abolition of certain weapons approaches nearer to reality. There appears to be a growing feeling that the best result that can be looked for from the Conference would be a &quot;qualitative &quot;. limitation., It would have the advantage of being at once practical and probably controllable, and of making an advance towards &quot; equality of treatment.&quot; It would also.avoid-all the difficulties of prestige which are involved in the comparison of figures and in discussions of &quot; parity.&quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government are already committed to some degree of &quot;qualitative &quot; reduction, i.e., abolition of submarines, and we would urge that the question might be carefully examined with a view to seeing what are the furthest limits to which His Majesty&apos;s Government could go in this direction. For instance, many Delegations have advocated the prohibition of tanks. His Majesty&apos;s Government have been unable to subscribe to this, but we venture to hope that the matter may yet receive consideration. His Majesty&apos;s Government have further indicated that they would consider restriction on bombing from the air, and we would urge that this matter should be studied thoroughly with a view to deciding what concrete proposals would be acceptable.37. It is dangerous to venture on prophecy as to the future course of events. We incline to think that the discussion of this Chapter A of the General Corn-mission^ agenda might take a fortnight. After that follows Chapter B, which, as will be seen, is a more practical and methodical review of the successive articles of the Draft Convention in connection with the various modifications which have been proposed. The duration of that discussion is, of course, impossible to fore-cast. It will no doubt be lengthy, and it may be impossible before June to form an estimate of the fate of the Conference. By then, discussions may have given some promise of reaching a convention that could be accepted by all sides; on the other hand we may have reached a point where only a complete change of direction will lead us out of our troubles.(Initialled)      J. S. (Initialled)      L.March 21, 1932.
Official No.: Gonf. D. 102.[Conf. D./Bureau 5(1).]Geneva, March gth, 1932.LEAGUE OF nations conference FOR THE REDUCTION AND LIMITATIONOF ARMAMENTSCoordinating Table of the Draft Convention1 and of the Propositions referred to the General commission Note.   Without prejudice to the reservations made by various delegations in regard to articles of the draft Convention which have not been withdrawn or modified since the opening of the Conference.s.d.n. 3.330 (f.) 2.475 (a.) 3/32. imp. kundig.Series  of  League  of  Nations   PublicationsIX.   DISARMAMENT 1932. IX. 28.
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle I.Agreement to li-mit and, so far as possible, to reduce armaments as pro-vided in the present Convention.I(a) Reduction to an equal limit of peace-time armed forces (land, sea and air) of all countries. Reduction to be carried out within ten years.(Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29, Art. 1.)(b) Reduction to be made at a rate directly proportional to the extent of the armaments of the various countries on a determined date, and to be less drastic in the case of the weakest States. The reduction of armed forces of the States which have contracted alliances or agreements of military assistance among themselves must be based on the total figures of the additional armed forces (by categories of armaments) of these States.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 34-)(c) Reduction of armaments^to the lowest possible level.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 30-)II(a) A permanent Disarmament Corn-mission to make preparations for further progressive disarmament.(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, para. 5.)(b) Idea of reduction by stages. (Czechoslovakia Conf. D.99, p.52 (7).)(c) A permanent organisation to prepare a programme for reduction by stages, the details to be fixed by subse-quent conferences and reduction to be continued under the programme until the principles of Article 8 of the Coven-ant have been carried out in their entirety.(Denmark Conf.D.99, p. 51, para. 6.)(d) If the aims can only be reached by stages, these stages should be spread over as short a period as possible. The Convention should represent a genuine advance to the farther possible limits in this direction and contain peremptory guarantees for the complete realisation of these aims within as short a time as possible.(Hungary Conf.D.99, p. 18 (4).)(e) Fixing of a percentage to serve as a general guide for the reduction, in the course of three years, of the existing level of armaments of countries which are not at present tied in the matter of armaments, subject to adjustments in particular cases. Reduction of military expenditure in a proportion correspond-ing to the reduction in the general level of armaments.(Denmark Conf.D.99, p. 51, para. 3.)Principle of defini-tive reduction under a single Convention.Ditto.Reduction of arma-ments to the lowest possible level.Reduction to be brought about by stages.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Proportional     arB progressive   reductiJ based on the positul of   armaments   at specific date.Effective reductio: from the first stags with peremptory gua-rantees in the first Convention of a com-plete realisation within a specific short delay.First stage: Proporj tional reduction on thil basis of the status quf\ with adjustments particular cases.
Subject of the parts, ihapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle i (continuation).Ill(a) The scale of armaments on land and sea and in the air shall be deter-mined for each country by:i.   Size of the territory.2.   Number of population.3. Length and nature of land frontier and coast-line.4. Facility of communications on land and sea and in the air.5. Degree of security against external aggression.6.   National resources.(China Conf.D.99, p. 50.)(b) Limitation to be effected in such manner as to leave room for rectification of manifest defects in elements.(Japan-Conf.D.94, p. 53.) (Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.)(c) Need for taking due account of the geographical situation and the special conditions of each State in the preparation of plans for the limitation of armaments.(Persia Conf.D.99,- p. 19.)(d) Computation of armed forces on the basis of the effectives necessary for internal order plus a contingent for defence, the former being absolute figures and the latter a relative figure.(U.S.A. Conf.D.99, p. 49.)IV(a) Preliminary examination by the Conference of the question of the prohibition of war materials of a specifically aggressive character.(Italy Conf.D.99, pp. 18 and 33.)(b) Prohibition of certain material if the latter does not form the subject of an undertaking to place it at the disposal of the League of Nations.(France Conf.D.99, p. 24.)VExamination of further reductions subject to measures to be taken to ensure security.(France Conf.D.99, p. 23.) (Belgium Conf.D.99, p. 14.)Criteria for limita-tion or reduction.Taking into consi-deration of all the particular conditions of the different coun-tries.Ditto.Method of compu-tation of the effectives based on the absolute needs for internal or-der and relative needs for national defence.Preliminary discus-sion of the sirnultane-ous application of a quantitative and qua-litative limitation by the absolute prohibi-tion of certain ma-terial.Prohibition of cer-tain material except under certain condi-tions (placing at the disposal of the League of Nations).Reduction subject to measures to be taken in regard to the organisation of peace.
I	2	3	subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	Proposals relating to the heads of column i	Questions of principle raised	ObservationsArticle I (continuation).Enumeration of the Conditions men-tioned above and of the political and Legal Questions connected therewith. ;&quot;A. Political Conditions.i. Placing at the disposal of the League of Nations or of another inter-national authority of certain land and naval material and of civil aviation and bombing aircraft.(France -Conf.D.99, p. 23 (I and II).)The proposals in the matter connected with Part II, &quot; Material &quot;, of the Draft Convention (provisions relating to land, sea and air material) are summarised under the respective chapters.2.   (a) Creation of an international police force to prevent war. (France Conf.D.99, p. 25.)(b) Creation of a first contingent of coercionary forces to repress war and to bring immediate assistance to any State victim of aggression.(France Conf.D.99, P- 25-)(c) Establishment of a land, sea and air force of the League of Nations by a contribution from all the States belong-ing to it, to be fixed for each in propor-tion to the numbers of its.population and to its national resources. Applica-tion of sanctions against signatory States that may refuse to furnish their contingents.(Haiti Conf.D.99, p. 32.)(d) Constitution of an international air police fleet.(Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51-)(e) Creation of an international army for the application of sanctions.(Bulgaria Conf.D.99, p. 15.)3.   Moral Disarmament.(a) Necessity for moral disarma-ment.(Persia Conf.D.99, p. 19.)(b) Abolition of the existing systems and measures calculated to encourage citizens to take up warlike pursuits, and to foster a warlike spirit among them.(China Conf.D.99, p. 50.)Placing at the dispo sal of the League of Nations, or of another international autho-rity, of certain land and naval material and of civil aviation and bombing aircraft.Creation of an in-ternational force.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Should the Gener Commission consider necessary that a detail   ed examination b made of the questiot grouped under th head or of certain those questions, the might be referred in mediately to the Po] tical CommissionDiscussion   on   the adoption of measur to ensure moral di armament.The   questions  ap-pearing under No. (Moral   Disarmament might be referred the    Political   Com mission, which might in its turn, refer it to a special sub-commit tee, in conformity with the Polish delegation request.1 Under this head are collected all proposals relating to this type of question, even when the delegations which subraittc them did not make them a preliminary condition for the reduction of armaments.
-- 5 -			i Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	2 Proposals relating to the heads of column I	3 Questions of principle raised	4 ObservationsArticle I (continuation).	A.   Political Conditions (continuation).		c	(c) Study of draft conventions relat-ing to the following points: i. Prevention and punishment by national law of actions incompatible with satisfactory international rela-tions (incitement of public opinion to warlike sentiments, false reports, etc.). 2. Convening of a conference of journalists and publishers to examine moral disarmament, so far as the Press is concerned, and. more parti-cularly to study the proposals formu-lated in document Conf.D.i6. 3. International undertakings re-lating to the instruction of youth in international matters. 4. Prevention in the sphere of broadcasting, the cinematograph and the stage of abuses which would be dangerous to a good international understanding. (i)   Conclusion of a general con-vention on broadcasting. (it)   Prohibition of films  and of   plays  which  might embitter international   relations,   and, on the other hand, the encourage-ment of films and plays conveying propaganda in favour of peace. (Poland Conf.D.99, p. 27.) (See also Conf.D.16.) (d) Conclusion of international con-ventions   for    the   prevention   and punishment of war propaganda  and all individual acts likely to disturb relations among peoples. (Roumania&apos; Conf.D.99, p. 20.) (e) Approval of the general idea of the Polish proposal. (Spain^ Conf.D.99, p. 21.) B.   Legal Conditions. 1. (a)   General adoption of the sys-tem of justice organised by the League of Nations. Obligation to have recourse only to pacific means. (Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51-) (Spain Conf.D.99, P- 2I0 (b) Compulsory arbitration. (Spain Conf.D.99, P- 21-) (France Conf.D.99, p. 26.) (Portugal Conf.D.99, P- 20-) (c) Compulsory jurisdiction of the Permanent  Court  combined   with   a system of sanctions. (Spain-Conf.D.99, p. 21.) (Haiti Conf.D.99, p. 33.) 2. (a)   Necessity for a system  of mutual assistance. (Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.)	Organisation of in-ternational arbitra-tion. .   . Ditto. Ditto. Mutual assistance.	
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle I (continuation).B.   Legal Conditions (continuation).(b) Conclusion of a general pact of mutual assistance.(Bulgaria Conf.D.99, p. 15.)3. (a) Precise rules to be drawn up in regard to the operation of the sanc-tions for which the Covenant provides.(Denmark-Conf.D.99, P- 51-)(b) Guarantees as to the rapidity of the decision of the authority controlling the international force. Conformity of the action of such authority with inter-national law.(France Conf.D.99, p. 26.)4. Renunciation of the compulsive clauses embodied in the treaties for the benefit of a nation or group of nations, and modifications of the existing inter-national regime.(Haiti Conf.D.99, p. 33.)VI(a) The disarmament laid down in the treaties of peace must be regarded as an indication (model) for the reduc-tion to be applied to all of the Members of the League of Nations.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 30.) (Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.) &apos; (Hungary Conf.D.99, P- J8-)(b) Institution of a single system applicable equally to all States.Legal equality and equal security for all States.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 30-) (Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Bulgaria Conf.D.99, p. 15.) (Hungary Conf.D.99, P-(c) Equality of right between all States and perequation of armed forces at the lowest levels.(Italy-Conf.D.99, p. 18.)(d) General reduction of armaments according to the principles of Article 8 of the Covenant applied to all nations.(Hungary Conf.D.99, p. 18.)VIILimitation and reduction of the whole of the armed forces immediately movable.(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48.)Mutual assistance.Organisation sanctions.Ditto.ofReadaptation of the international regime.The [ disarmament^ laid down in the trea-ties of peace must be regarded as an indi-cation.Uniformity of me-thods of disarmament under the principle of the equality of rights of States.Equality of right between all States and perequation of armed forces at the lowest levels.Application of Ar-ticle 8 to all States.Limitation and re-duction of the whole of the armed forces immediately movable.
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle I (continuation).PART I. PERSONNEL.VIII(rt)   A  regional solution might be necessary in certain cases. (Poland Conf.D.99, P- 20-)(b) From the point of view of the Latin-American continent, the reduction of armaments should be sought by means of regional agreements. The general draft should accordingly possess the necessary elasticity.(Chili Conf.D.99, p. 16.)IX.Establishment of completely de militaires-tarised zones or zones occupied by a limited number of effectives.(Finland Conf.D.99, p. 16.)X.Relative agreement with regard to contraband of war.(Argentine Conf.D.99, p. 53.)1. The personnel of the land forces and the naval personnel to be recruited only by means of voluntary enlistment.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 30&apos; S 1 and P- 31. S 14-)2. Freedom to choose the system of military service.(Bulgaria Conf.D.99, p. 15.)(Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 22.)3. Limitation and reduction of train-ed reserves.(Sweden Conf.D.99, p. 48, g 2 (a).)4. Limitation and reduction of train-ed reserves.(Netherlands Conf.D.99, P- 4-81 S 2 (*)-) 5.   Proportional reduction of trained reserves.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 40- Arts- 3-5 (a) and 8 (b).) 6.   Limitation and reduction of the annual contingent.(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48, g 2(a).)7. Contribution of effectives to the international force.(a) Constitution of a perma-nently available police force made up of contingents furnished by each of the contracting parties in a pro-portion to be determined.(6) Constitution of a coerciona-ry force of a strength varying ac-cording to the regions concerned, made up of contingents determined for each country and constantly available. (France Conf.D.99, p. 25, III (a) and (&amp;).)Regional agreements within   the    frame-work of the general agreement.Demilitarised zones.Limitation of inter-national law regula-tions with regard to blockade.Abolition of com-pulsory service.Freedom to choose the system of military service.Limitation and re-duction of trained reserves.Ditto.Ditto.Limitation and re-duction of the annual contingent.     ;-Creation of an in-ternational force.Principle already appearing in the part relating to Article i.Details left for exami-nation by the Land, Naval and Air Corn-missions.
PART I. PERSONNEL (cont.)Articles 2 and 3: Definition and li-mitation of average effectives daily.Tables relating to Land Armed ForcesTable I. - Maxi-mum land armed forces stationed in the home country.Table II (option-al).   Maximum land armed forces stationed overseas.Table III. - Ma-ximum of the total land armed forces.(In each of the above tables a separately -ate maximum is pro-vided for total effec-tives, officers and regular soldiers.)8. Mutual assistance force in propor-tion to the population and the national resources.(Haiti -Conf.D.99, p. 32, g 1.)9. Constitution of an international police force consisting of an air fleet.(Denmark Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 7.)10. Creation of an international ar-my for the purpose of applying sanctions.(Bulgaria Conf.D.99, P- x5-)11. Demilitarised zones occupied by limited effectives.(Finland Conf.D.99, p. 16.)1. Ascertainment of the most prac-tical course for limiting the number of effectives.(United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54,5 i-)2. Reduction to a maximum equal for all by means of an annual 10 % re-duction of the difference between the actual strength and the maximum fixed.(Turkey Conf.D.99, P- 29- Art. r03. Method of progressive and pro-portional reduction of peace effectives based on a classification of States according to the amount of their arma-ments.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 35 and 39; Arts. 1, 2, 3 and 4 (a).)4. Estimate of and adequate allow-ance for trained reserves.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 30, 5 2.)5. Special conditions for States having a militia system.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 30, $ 3.)1.   Modifications in the tables:Table I.   Maximum home forces.Table II.  - Maximum oversea forces stationed in the home country.Table III.   Maximum forces over-seas.Table IV.   Maximum forces in the several oversea territories.Table V.   Maximum of the total forces.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 4i. Art. 4(6).;2. The number of officers, non-commissioned officers and regular sol-diers to be fixed in each of the above tables by units and corps.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p.4i,Art.4(&amp;).)3. The number of officers to be fixed at the lowest possible figure for all countries alike in terms of a percen-tage, the figure not to be increased.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 30- S 4-)Creation of an ternational force.Ditto.Ditto.Demilitarised zones.Principle already appearing in the part relating to Article 1 Details left for exami-nation by the Land Naval and Air Corn-missions.Ditto.Ditto.The principle already dy appears in the Part relating to Article When the principle has been decided, the ques-tion may be referred to the Land and Air Coin-missions.The principles raised in points (2) and (3) already appear in the Part relating to Article 1. Points 4 and 5, as well as Articles 2 and 3 of the draft Con-vention, can be refer-red immediately to the Land, Naval and Air Commissions, which would submit to the General Commission any questions of prin-ciple they could not dispose of.Tables I, II and III and points 1, 2 and 3 of the draft Convention can be referred to the Land Commission, which will submit to the General Commis-sion any questions of principle it cannot dispose of.
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservati6nsTables relating to Sea Armed Forces.Table VI. - Ma-ximum sea armed forces. (Only total effectives are limited.)Tables relating to Air Armed Forces.Table VIII (option-al).   Maximum air armed forces sta-tioned in the home country.Table IX (option-al).   Maximum air armed forces station-ed overseas.Table X.   Maxi-mum of the total effectives.Formations organised on a Military Basis.Article 4. Definition of form-ations organised on a military basis and of mobilisation.Article 2. Limitation of the average daily effec-tives in the land, sea and air formations organised on a mili-tary basis.1. A percentage of officers and warrant officers to be fixed as a maxi-mum limit.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, $ 15.)1.   Abolition of air forces.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31-      x7 and 19 (a) and (b).)2. The effectives of the military air forces must be reduced in proportion to the decrease in the number of machines in service.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 45. Art. 28.)1. Prohibition of civil bodies or-ganised on a military basis by special-ised instructors drawn from the army and of the military training of the civilian population at the instance of civil associations.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 41, Art.5(b).)2. Police forces, gendarmerie and similar organisations not to be utilised for military purposes.(Germany-Conf.D.99, p. 30, g 5.)3. The strength and armament of police and gendarmerie forces and Customs guards to be fixed by special commissions in accordance with each country&apos;s needs.(Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29, Art. 5.)Prohibition of the maintenance of mili-tary air force per-sonnel.Table VI in the draft Convention and point 1 can be referred to the Naval Commission with instructions to submit to the General Commission any mat-ters of principle on which it may have difn-culty.Principle discussed in connection with the more general question of the abolition of all military aviation. When matters of principle have been decided, Tables VIII, IX and X and point 2 in the draft Convention can be referred to the Air Commission.Articles 2 and 4 of the draft Convention and points 1 to 5 can be referred to the Land, Naval and Air Com-missions, which may, if necessary, submit any questions of principle giving rise to special dif-difficulties to the General Commission. These Commissions ought more especially to examine the following questions:Definition of forma-tions organised on a military basis. Total prohibition of certain formations organised on a military basis.Prohibition of the utilisation of police and similar forces for military purposes.Method of limiting police and similar for-ces by special conven-tion or by average daily effectives.
- IO -I	2	3	subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	Proposals relating to the heads of column i	Questions of principle raised	ObservationsArticle 2 (continuation).Tables relative to Formations organised on a Military BasisTable IV. - Ma-ximum figures for ef-fectives stationed in the home country.Table V. - Maxi-mum figures for ef-fectives stationed overseas.These two tables provide for a sepa-rate limitation of the total number of ef-fectives, officers or officials ranking as officers and regular personnel.Table VII. - Ma-ximum figures for sea formations orga-nised on a military basis. Limitation of the total only.Table XI. - Ma-ximum figures for air effectives station-ed in the home country.. Table XII. - Ma-ximum figures for air effectives stationed overseas.These two tables provide for separate limitation of the to-tal number of effec-tives and of the total number of regular ef-fectives.4. The number of the police forces organised on a military basis, gendar-merie, Customs guards, train guards, forest guards and other armed corps organised for the needs of the Customs preventive service to be determined by Convention.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, p. 40, Art. i, Remark 1.)5.   Police  forces, gendarmerie and similar organisations to be limited. (Germany Conf.D.99, p. 30- Para-5-)1. Proportional and progressive re-duction and limitation of the number of units and corps of each arm and service(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P&apos; 4Q. Art- 4-)Method of limiting! police and similar for-l ces by special conven-l tion or by average! daily effectives.Ditto.Tables IV, V, VII, XI and XII can be referred respectively to the     Land,     Naval and Air Commissions, which may, if neces-sary, submit any ques-f tions  giving  rise   to j special   difficulties  to I the General Commis-[Reduction and limi-tation of the number! of units and corps.This question can be referred to the Land I Commission,which may, if   necessary,   submit any questions of priii-1 ciple   giving   rise   to \ special  difficulties  to the General Commis-
irSubject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsChapter B, Period of Service.Articles 5 to 9 and Table.PART II. MATERIAL.Limitation of the period of service. (Latvia Conf.D.99, P- I8-)1. Prohibition in general terms of material deemed to be of an aggressive character.(Argentine Conf.D.99, p. 13.)(Austria Conf.D.g9, p. 14.)(Belgium Conf.D.99, P- I4-)(China Conf.D.gg, p. 50.)(Denmark-Conf.D.99, P- 51-)(Finland-Conf.D.99, p. 16.)(Haiti Conf.D.99, P- 33-)(Hejaz Conf.D.9g, p. 54.)(Hungary Conf.D.99, p. 17.)(Latvia Conf.D.99, P- x^-)(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48.)(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51.)(Persia Conf.D.99, P- I9-)(Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.)(Spain&apos; Conf.D.99, p. 27.)(Sweden Conf.D.99, p. 48.)(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50.)2. Prohibition of undefined material deemed to be offensive with prohibition of their manufacture, use and training with a view to their use.(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51.)3. Prohibition of certain material of a presumed specifically aggressive cha-racter and referred to in treaty of peace.(Denmark Conf.D.99, p. 51.)(Germany (Conf.D.99, P- 30-)(Hungary Conf.D.99, P- I8-) -4. Contribution of material forming part of the normal armament of the police force contingents, material form-ing part of the normal armament of coercionary forces and heavy artillery and armoured implements by States which possess such material.(France Conf.D.99, p. 25, III (b).)5.   Demilitarised zones.(Finland Conf.D.99, p. 16.)6. Direct limitation of all war mate-rial by a combined system comprising a convention on trade, a convention on private manufacture and an inventory of stocks, the whole controlled by the Permanent Disarmament Commission.(Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.)7.   Limitation on the lines of the treaties of peace.(Hungary Conf.D.99, P- I8. S 3-) 8.   Direct limitation wherever prac-ticable.(Norway Conf.D.99, P- 51. S2-)Absolute prohibi-tion of certain classes of material.Ditto.Ditto.Constitution of an international force.Demilitarised zones.Direct limitation with control of trade and manufacture and controlled inventory of stocks.Direct limitation on the lines of the trea-ties of peace.Possibility of ap-plying different me-thods for the different States.This question can be referred to the Land, Naval and Air Corn-missions with instruc-tions to submit to the General Commission any matters of princi-ple on which they may have difficulty.This principle figures already in the section relative to Article 1.Principle already in-cluded in the part concerning Article I. When the principle has been decided, the ques-tion may be referred to the Land, Naval and Air Commissions.Ditto.When the principle has been decided, the question can be referred to the Land, Naval and Air Commissions.Ditto.
Chapter A. Land Armaments.I. Prohibition of all kinds of heavy artillery.(Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Italy-Conf.D.qq, p. 33.) (Latvia Conf.D.99, p. 18.) (Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, 5 6.)2. Prohibition of mobile heavy ar-tillery.(Spain Conf.Djgq, p. 22.) (Sweden-Conf.D.99, p. 48, fj 2 (c).) (United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p.54, g 2.)3. Prohibition of heavy long-range artillery.(Belgium Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 41, Art. 6.)4.   Prohibition of heavy   artillery above an as yet unspecified calibre. (China Conf.D.99, pi-50. III.) (Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29, Art. 2.)5.   Prohibition of heavy and field artillery above a specified calibre. (Germany Conf.D.99, p. 30, g 6.)6.   Prohibition of mortars and trench mortars above a specified calibre. (Germany-Conf.D.99, p. 31, 5 6.)7.   Prohibition of tanks. (Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (China-Ditto, p. 50, III.) (Germany Ditto, p. 31, g 6.) (Italy-Ditto, p. 33.) (Latvia-Ditto, p. 18.) (Spain Ditto, p. 22.) (Sweden. Ditto, p. 48, g 2.) (Switzerland Ditto, p. 50, g 6.) (Turkey Ditto, p. 29, Art. 2.) (U.S.S.R.-Ditto, p. 41, Art. 6.)8. Prohibition of armoured motor-cars.(Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29, Art. 2.)9. Prohibition of the stocking of heavy high-power artillery except in the case of countries undertaking to place it at the disposal of the League of Nations, in the event of the application of Article 16 of the Covenant.(France Conf.D.99, p. 24.)10. Prohibition of the construction and maintenance of fortresses, field works and works which constitute a direct menace to the neighbouring country and might possibly obstruct measures taken for the prevention of war.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31- S 8.) 11.   Quantitative limitation of land material.(Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.)12. Direct limitation of the whole of land material.(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48, g 2.)Absolute prohibition of certain classes of land material.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto. Ditto. Ditto.Ditto.Prohibition of cer-tain classes of mate-rial except subject to certain conditions.(Certain classes of material to be placed at the disposal of the League of Nations.)Prohibition of cer-tain land fortifications-tions.Quantitative tation.limi-Direct limitation of land material includ-ing stocks.When the principle has been decided, the question can be referred to the Land Commis mission.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.The principle involving-ed in this proposal al-ready figures in the section relative to Ar-ticle 1. On decision of the question of prin-ciple, the matter may be immediatelyreferred to the Land Commis-sion.When the principle has been decided, the question may *be re-ferred to the Land Commission.When the principles have been decided on, points 11 to 16 inclu-sive may be referred to the Land Commission.
188Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsChapter A. Land Armaments (continued).Article io. limitation of ma-terial by budgetary method.Chapter B. Naval Armaments.13. Quantitative limitation by cate-gory, with a uniform percentage for necessary replacements. authorisation-tion of stocks for countries with no arms factories.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, g 7.)14. Limitation in numbers of certain categories defined in proportion to peace effectives and trained reserves.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 41, Arts. 8 and 9.)15. Special restriction of mobile heavy artillery and tanks.(U.S.A.-Cohf.D.99, p. 49, g8.)16. Prohibition against alteration of existing patterns.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 41, Art. 6.)1. Combination of quantitative and budgetary limitation.(Sweden Conf.D.99, p. 48, g 2(6).) (Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, g 3.) (U.S.A. Conf.D.99, p. 49, gg.)1. Abolition of all naval forces the purpose of which is to make war at a distance thus capable of aggressive war and restrict to what is necessary for defence of national coastline.(Yugoslavia Conf.D.99, p. 22.)2.   Limitation of shells and torpedoes and destruction of quantities in excess. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 44, Arts. 18 and 19.)3. Maximum tonnage of various types of vessels to be reduced simul-taneously with a proportional reduction in total tonnage.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31- S 9-)4. No warships in future to exceed 10,000 tons or carry guns exceeding 280 mm. (n&quot;).(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, g 9.)5. No warships in future to exceed 10,000 tons or carry guns exceeding 203 mm. (8&quot;).(Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.)6. When equal limit of land, sea and air forces of all countries is fixed, the building and use of warships carrying guns over y cm. and displacing over z tons to be forbidden. (Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29&apos; Arts. 1 and 2.)7. Consideration of the most prac-tical method of reducing size of war-ships and the maximum calibre of guns carried by them.(United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54, g 4.)Quantitative limi-tation with adjust-ments.Limitation and di-rect reduction of war material.Restrictions relating to certain materials.Principle of direct qualitative limitation.Combination of quantitative and bud-getary limitation.Abolition of aggres-sive naval forces and limitation of forces to strict needs for coast-line defence.Limitation and di-rect reduction of cer-tain material.Method of reduc-tion in naval arma-ments (in accordance with the principles of the London and Was-hington Naval Treaty or otherwise.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.When the principles have been decided on, points ir to 16 inclu-sive may be referred to the Land Commis-sion.Ditto.Ditto.After preliminary discussion in the Ge-neral Commission, this question might be re-ferred to the Land Commission for an opi-nion.The question may form the subject of a preliminary discussion by the General Corn-mission, which could, if necessary, refer it to the Land Commission or Commission on Ex-penditure for an opi-nion.When question of principle settled, refer to Naval Commission.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.f&quot;mpubwmwiiifibiniiihihurn 11 iimiiibiiill 11 hhbiin&apos;biiiiipmmwiiiwmmiiiiibiibiimwiiliwiiin 11111111 &apos;nm ilium i urn u imm nil i in  im &quot;i&quot; mii&quot; iiii phi 1 hi &quot;i&apos;
- 14 -m			i	2	3	subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	Proposals relating to the heads of column i -	Questions of principle raised	ObservationsChapter B. Naval Armaments (continued).	8.   Extension of age-limits of various categories. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16 (a).) 9.   Maximum standard displacement of a war vessel to be fixed at 10,000 me-tric tons. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16 ( ).)	Method  of reduc-tion in naval arma-ments (in accordance with the principles of the London and Wash-ington Naval Treaties or otherwise).	When   question  ol principle settled, refer to Naval Commission.	10.   Existing vessels of over 10,000 tons to be struck off when they reach the specific age-limits, and in any case not later than ... without prejudice to the right of disposal before the expiry of the said time-limit but without right of replacement. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16 (6).)	Ditto.	Ditto.	11.   Maximum calibre of guns moun-ted to be 12&quot; (304.8 mm.). (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16 (c).)	Ditto.	Ditto.	12.   Appliances for carrying aircraft not to be fitted in any warship. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16 (d).)	Ditto.	Ditto.	13. Classes of categories Limita-tions (vide Draft Convention, Table II, Annex to Chapter B of Part II). (See also Article 12.) Maximum standard displacement. Maximum gun-calibre. Age limit. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16 (e).)	Ditto.	Ditto.	14. Inclusion of fuel and reserve feed water for engines and boilers in the calculation of the standard displacement. (See also Annex III, page 17.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 43. Art- l6. Note.)	Ditto.	Ditto.	15. Landing platforms or decks in vessels other than aircraft carriers   prohibition. (Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, Jj 8.)	Ditto.	Ditto.	16. Washington and London Naval Agreements; prolongation of these as soon as they are completed by the ad-herence of France and Italy. (U.S.A.-Conf.D 99, p. 49. % 2.)		Naval Commission.	17. Washington and London Naval Agreements; proportional reductions from figures laid down when all parties to the Washington Agreement have entered this framework. (U.S.A.-Conf D.99, p. 49, g 3.)		Ditto.	18.   Non-floating   material - - limi-tation. (Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31. S x3-)		Ditto.	19. (a)   Coast defence fortifications. (b)   Fortifications controlling na-tural waterways between two open seas. (Germany Conf.D.99, p 31. $ 16.)	Prohibition of cer-tain coastal fortifications-tions.		20. Free and unhampered passage through natural waterways between two open seas. (Germany&apos; Conf.D.99, p. 31, g 16.)	Ditto.	
Chapter B. Naval Armaments (continued).Article it. Limitation of glo-Ibal tonnage.Article 12. Distribution global tonnage [categories.of perArticle 13. Transfer  of Inage between I ;ories.ton-cate-Article 14. Capital ships. Ma-jximum displacement; I maximum    gun-ca-re.Article 13. Aircraft carriers. Maximum displace-mcnt and maximum gun-calibre. Number of guns carried.21. Contributions to an international force. Only Powers undertaking to place them at the disposal of the League of Nations in specified eventualities to have the right to possess:capital ships carryingguns exceeding 8&quot; (203 mm.) or 10,000 (W.T.) tons. Submarines exceeding n tons.(France Conf.D.99, p. 24, II.)22. To provide the League with an organised land, sea and air force.(Haiti Conf.D.99, P- 32. S x-)the23.   Automatic contact mines in open sea   prohibition. (Netherlands--Conf.D.99, P- 48. 86(ft).)1. Proportional and progressive re-duction of tonnage.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, p. 42, Arts. 12, 13 and 14.)2.   Equalisation of forces. (Turkey Conf.D.99, P- 29&apos; Art. i-)1.   Categories.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31. S I2-) 2.   Categories. (U.S.S.R. Conf.99, p. 43, Art. 16, e.)Right of transfer to vary inversely as the ratio of reduction of the respective fleets.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, P- 42&apos; Art- I2. a, b and c.)i.   Abolition.(China Conf.D.99, p. 50, III.)2. Conditional Abolition. (Simul-taneous abolition of capital ships and submarines.)(Italy-Conf.D.99, p. 33.)3. Reduction in size; reduction in gun-calibre.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, II A.) (Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, 8 6.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16.)4.   Extension of age-limit. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. i6s.)5. Undertaking by the non-signa-tories of the Washington and London Treaties not to construct or acquire capital ships above 10,000 tons.(Argentine Conf.D.99, p. 52.)6. Conditional right to possess capi-tal ships exceeding a specified tonnage or gun-calibre.(France-Conf.D.99, p. 24, II.)1.   Abolition.(China-Conf.D.99, p. 50, III.) (Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31&apos; S I0-) (Italy-Conf.D.99, p. 33, 5 2.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 36, Art. 12 D and p. 43, Art. 16 d.)2.   Conditional Abolition. (Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, g 9.)International Force.Ditto.Method of reduction of naval armaments.Ditto.Absolute or condi-tional abolition. Ditto.Application to non-signatories of the prin-ciples of the Lon-don and Washington Naval Treaties.International Force (see No. 21).Abolition of craft carriers.Principle to be dis-cussed under Article 1 of the draft Con-vention. Subsequent discussion in Naval Commission.Ditto.Naval Commission.To be discussed in connection with Arti-cle 1 of the draft Convention. (Soviet and Turkish proposals.)Naval Commission.Ditto.Naval Commission and subsequent refer-ence to General Corn-mission if necessary.Naval Commission.Naval Commission when question of prin-ciple is settled.
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle 15 (contd.).Article 16. Submarines: ma-ximum displacement, maximum   gun - ca-libre.Article ij. General undertaking -ing. (No vessel ex-ceeding limitations prescribed to be acquired by or con-structed by, for or within the jurisdic-tion of any High Contracting Party.)Article 18. Rules for replace-ment.Article ig. Rules re arming merchant vessels.Article 20. Use of war vessels constructed for an-other Power.Article 21. Cession of war ves-sels to another Power.3. Reduction in tonnage allotted by existing treaties.(Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, 5 7.)4. Landing platforms or decks in vessels other than aircraft-carriers.   Prohibition.(Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, jj 8.)1.   Abolition.(Austria^-Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (China-Conf.D.99, p. 50, III.) (Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, g 11.) (United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54, S3-)(U.S.A.-Conf.D.99, p. 49-, g 4.)2. Conditional Abolition (simul-taneous abolition of capital ships and submarines.)(Italy-Conf.D.99, p. 33.)3.   Conditional right to possess sub-marines exceeding a certain tonnage. (France Conf.D.99, p. 25, II.)4.   Reduction in size; reduction in gun-calibre; extension of age-limit. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16(e).)5. Reduction in size; reduction in radius of action.(Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.)1. Contracting Parties not to build or allow to be built on their territories any warship exceeding the prescribed limits.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 44, Art. 17(c).)2. Not to cause new vessels to be constructed in foreign yards over and above the limits laid down for each Contracting State.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 44, Art. 17(d).)Only replacement vessels to be built. Age-limits for replacement. Replaced vessels not to be used for warlike pur-poses.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16, 1st 5 and g (a), and Art. 17(a).)1.   Limitation of arms and aircraft equipment in merchant vessels. (Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, g 10.)2.   Prohibition. (Germany Conf.D.99, p. 17.) (Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 44, Art.i7(e),o handing over or sale of warships to another Power if such Power can use them as warships supernumerary to its prescribed establishment.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 44, Art. 17(6).)Reduction in on-nage allotted by exist-ing treaties.Ditto.Abolition of sub-marines.Ditto.International Force. (See No. 21, page 15.)Naval Commission.Once the principal has been decided tol be sent to Naval Com-FDitto.Naval Commission, Ditto. Ditto.Ditto. Ditto.Ditto.Naval Commission, which will refer to General Commission if necessary.Ditto.Naval Commission.
Subject of the parts, Lapters and articles of 1 the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle 22. Rules re disposal of ivar vessels.Article 23. Hulks or training stablishments.Annex I. Exempt vessels.Annex II. Special vessels.Annex III. Definitions.Article 24. Limitation of na-Ival expenditure.Chapter C. Air Armaments.Rules for disposal.Disarmament of warships; what this comprises. Procedure for striking ves-sels off the establishment and rendering them unfit for warlike purposes.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, P- 42. Art. 14.)1.   Amended definitions.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31. S I2-)2. Standard Displacement. Amended definition.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 43, Art. 16, note.)1. Prohibition of the maintenance of air forces of any kind. Destruction of existing material except those arma-ments which may be reincorporated in the quantities allowed for land and naval forces.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, fj 17.)2. Total prohibition of military aviation-tion, as well as the manufacture, prepare-ration and entraining with regard to military aviation.(Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51. S 2(a)-) (Sweden Conf.D.99, P- 4&amp;, 5 3 (*)-) 3.   Total abolition of military air-craft :(Hejaz Conf.D.99, p. 54, g 2.) (Hungary Conf.D.99, p. 18.)4. Within one year all military diri-gibles (lighter than air) shall be disarmed and placed in a position precluding their utilisation for military purposes. The disarmament of aircraft belonging to the armed forces includes the removal of guns, machine-guns and special applian-ces for the discharge of bombs and other instruments of destruction.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, P- 44. Art. 20.)5. Abolition of military aviation combined with the internationalisation of civil aviation.(Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.)6.   Abolition of air bombing. (Netherlands Conf.D.99, P- 4^07. Practical examination of the whole problem of aerial bombing in its widest sense.(United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54, $5.Abolition of mili-tary aircraft (aero-planes).Ditto.Ditto.Abolition of mili-tary aviation (dirigi-bles).Abolition of mili-tary aviation com-bined with the inter-nationalisation of civil aviation.Abolition of aerial bombing.Naval Commission.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto. Ditto.Naval Commission and Defence Expendi-ture Commission.Refer to the. Air Commission after de-cision of the principle has been taken by the General Commission.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Refer to the Air Commission.
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column chapter C. Air Armaments (continued).Article 25. Limitation of the number   and   total horse-power of aero-planes.Tables annexed: Table I.(a) Total aero-planes of the armed forces.(b) Aeroplanes sta-tioned in the home country (optional).(c) Aeroplanes sta-tioned overseas (op-tional).(d) Aeroplanes in aircraft-carriers.Table II.(a) Total aero-planes of the forces organised on a mili-tary basis.(b) Aeroplanes sta-tioned in the home country (optional).(c) Aeroplanes sta-tioned overseas.8.   Abolition of bombing aircraft.(Austria Conf.D.99, P- *4-) (Belgium Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (China-Conf.D.99, p. 50, III.) (Hungary Conf.D.99, p. 18.) (Italy Conf.D.99, P- 34-) (Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.) (Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, 5 6.)1. Reduction of the peace-time air armed forces of all countries to an equal limit, to be attained within ten years.(Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29, Art. 1.)2. Progressive and proportional re-duction varying according to the num-ber of aircraft in the possession of the States and amounting to as much as 50 per cent of the existing aircraft. The total engine-power of each aeroplane shall not exceed 600 h.p. on the ground. Reserve machines, and engines for these machines, up to a number not exceeding 25 per cent of the total number of aero-planes in service after their reduction, may be maintained in the establishment of the air forces. Destruction of existing material.Tables relating to the maximum armed air forces stationed in the home country, in each colony, dominion or other over-sea possession and total. Supplementary Convention on the limitation to be imposed on the manufacture and trade in war aeroplanes in proportion to the legiti-mate requirements fixed by the maxima.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99. pp. 36 and 44.)3. (a) Grouping of military aero-planes in three categories according to tonnage (aeroplanes and hydroplanes) or to their volume (dirigibles).(b) Conditional on preliminary inter-nationalisation of civil aerial transport (aeroplanes and hydroplanes above a specified tonnage, dirigibles above a certain volume). Military air-machines of the lowest category are placed at the disposal of national air forces. Military air-machines of the intermediary cate-gory are left to the national air forces on condition that the League of Nations can dispose of them in case of the applica-tion of Article 16 of the Covenant. The military air-machines of the highest category are prohibited in military air forces.(France Conf.D.99, p. 23,1, II and III.)Questions of principle raisedObservationsAbolition of aerial bombardment.Reduction of air ar-maments to an equal limit for al! States. Progressive reduction.Progressive and pro-portional reduction on the basis of material existing at a specific date.Internationalisation of civil aviation.Placing at the dis-posal of the League of military air-ma-chines above a certain tonnage or a certain volume.Creation of an inter-national air force.Air Commission ft preliminary examinj tion.The principle raise; in point 1 is ahead found in Article 1.The principle is al-ready found in .\ tide&quot; 1.The principle is al-ready found in Article 1 for decision by the General Commission. Limitation of unladen tonnage, definition 0! that tonnage, and de-tails to be referred to the Air Commission.Th: principle is al-ready found in Article 1 for decision by the General Commission.
- ig -Subject of the parts, I chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle 26.Limitation of the I number, total horse-I power and total vo-llume of dirigibles.Tables annexed:Table III.(a) Total dirigibles of the armed forces.(b) Dirigibles sta-tioned in the home ,-ountry (optional).(c) Dirigibles sta-tioned overseas (op-tional).(d) Dirigibles in aircraft carriers (op-iional).Table IV.(a) Total dirigibles I of the formations or-I stanised on a military &apos;basis.(b) (Optional) Di-rigibles stationed in the home country.(c) (Optional) Di-I rigibles stationed I overseas.Article 27.Horse-power shall be measured accord-ing to the following rales. . . The vo-lume of dirigibles shall be expressed in I cubic metres.Report of the Com-mittee of Experts to fix Rules for the Ad-option of a Standard Horse-Power Mea-iurement for Aero-plane and Dirigible Engines. (Document C 259. M. 115.1931. VIII.)Committee of Ex-perts to fix Rules for the Adoption of a Standard Horse-Power Measurement for Aeroplane and Dirigible Engines. (Document C. 260. M.116.1931.VIII.)Article 28.Civil aviation: re-lations with military aviation.i. Internationalisation of civil air transport under a regime to be organised by the League.(France Conf.D.99, p. 23,1.)Internationalisation of civil aviation: in-ternational air trans-port to be placed at the disposal of the League.To be referred to the Air Commission.To be referred to the Air Commission after the General Commi;-sion has decided re-garding the principle.
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle 28 (continued).2. Internationalisation of civil aviation-tion:(Belgium Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Spain Conf.D.99, P- 22-) 3.   Internationalisation or strict in-ternational control of civil aviation:(Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51. S 2 (&amp;)-) (Sweden Conf.D.99, P- 48, S 3 if))-) 4.   Civil aviation to be under inter-national control:(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, g 4.)5. All arming of civil, aircraft and all fittings enabling them to be armed or to be utilised for war are prohibited.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, g 19.)(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 45. Art. 25.)6. Any instruction and training of any person. in aviation having a military character or a military purpose to be prohibited. Prohibition of any instruc-tion or training of members of the army or navy in civil aviation.(Germany-Conf.D.99, P- 3*. S 19 ) 7. Prohibition of the construction, maintenance, importation or putting into commission of aircraft which is in any way armoured or protected or sup-plied with devices for the reception of warlike armament of any kind, such as guns, machine-guns, torpedoes, bombs, or which are supplied with gunsights or devices for the dropping of bombs and with similar warlike instruments.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 31. 8 I9-) 8.   Prohibition of the maintenance of any relation between the military or naval administration and civil aviation for any military purpose.(Germany Conf.D.99, P- 32- 8 I9-)Trade in and Manufacture of Arms, Ammunition and War Material.1. Prohibition of the trade in arms, except for non-manufacturing States, within the limits of their needs.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 32, g 21.)2. Adoption of agreements, unspeci-fied, relating to the trade in arms.(Czechoslovakia - Conf.D.99, p. 52, S3-)(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 4.) (Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, g 8.)3. Prohibition of the manufacture of material elsewhere than in specified private or State factories. Publicity regarding these factories and limitation of their production through the Govern-ments;(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 32, g 22.)4. Direct limitation of the total quantity of all kinds of war material found on the territory of each High Contracting Party.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 41, Art. 10.)Internationalisation or control of civil aviationDitto.Ditto.Prohibition of the trade in arms.Supervision of the trade in arms.Limitation of the manufacture of arms, ammunition and war material.To be referred to tl Air Commission aft; the General Comin-sion has decided garding the principltjDitto.Ditto.To be referred to Stl Air Commission.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.To be considered at an opportune time by the General Comrnis-sion.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.
Article 28 (continued).PART III.I Article 29.   Limi-tation of total an-nual expenditure.See also Report of the Committee of Experts on Budget-ary Questions (docu-ment C. 182. M. 69. I93I-IX).5. Supervision, unspecified, of the private and Government manufacture of arms.(Czechoslovakia-Conf.D.99,p.52, S3-)(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 4.)(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, g 8.)6. International and national super-vision of private and Government manufacture by a system of licensing and publicity in accordance with the principles in the Mixed Temporary Commission^ report (document A.16. 1924.IX).Incorporation in the Disarmament Convention of the 1925 Convention on the supervision of the trade in arms.(Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.)1. Inexpediency of the limitation of expenditure in view of the abandonment of the gold standard and the resultant changes in purchasing power.(Germany-Conf .D.99, p. 32, g 23, note.)2. Approval of the limitation of the aggregate expenditure allocated to armed forces, together with formations organised on a military basis in the broadest sense of the term.(Poland Conf.D.99, p.19.)3. Examination of the ratios to be established between the expenditure of countries which have had the advantage of an uninterrupted organisation of their defence system and that of countries which have been obliged to build up a national defence system in the last few years.(Poland Conf.D.99, p. 19.)4. In the case where the budgetary limitation is accepted, necessity to provide for the reinforcement of means of defence of countries the least protec-ted and unprovided with fortifications and insufficiently equipped from an industrial point of view.(Persia Conf.D.99, P- I9-)5. Reduction of expenditure propor-tional to the amount of direct reduction;(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 46, Arts. 34 and 35.)6. Reduction of expenses to a pro-portion corresponding to the level of the reduction of general armaments.(Denmark Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 3.)7. Thorough examination of the bud-getary method, more especially with a view to its application in the event of fluctuations in purchasing power.(Sweden Conf.D.99, p 48, g 4.)8. Approval of budgetary limitation as general method in conjunction with direct limitation of certain classes of material.(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, g 3.)9. Approval of the budgetary limi-tation combined with direct limitation constituted by the control of trade and manufacture and by the inventory of stocks.(See Trade and Manufacture of Arms, -      p. 21, g 6. Spain.)Supervision of the private and Govern-ment manufacture of arms, ammunition and war material.Principle of control of trade and of control of manufacture com-bined with inventory of stocks and the whole considered as a system of direct limi-tation. (See p. n.)Is it desirable to reduce and limit ar-maments by budget-ary methods ?Combination of both methods, direct and indirect.To be considered at an opportune time by the General Commis-Ditto.As soon as the ques-tions of principle in preceding columns are resolved, points 2, 3,4, 5, 6, 8 and 9 can be referred to the Expen-diture Commission.Point 7 could be referred immediately to the Expenditure Corn-mission, which in its turn could set up an ad hoc Committee for the examination of this question.
Article 2g (continued).PART IV. EXCHANGE OF INFORMATION.Article 30.Publicity of aver-age daily number of effectives.Tables I to XII.&apos; Article 31. Publicity relating to compulsory prepare-ratory military train-ing.Article 32. Publicity relating to period of service.Article 33. Publicity relating to the annual expen-diture on land and sea material.Article 34. Publicity relating to the building of ves-sels of war.Article 35. Publicity relating to  merchant  ships whose   decks  have been stiffened.Article 36. Publicity relating to military aircraft. Tables I to IV.Article 37. Publicity relating to non-military aviation-tion.110. Limitation both of aggregate ex-penditure and expenditure under parti-cular chapters (including expenditure on aviation).(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 2.)11.   Abolition of secret funds.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 46, Art. 35.)12. Unification of the military bud-get.(U.S.S.R.--Conf.D.99, p. 46, Art. 35.)1. Complete publicity of armaments, in conformity with Article 8 of the Covenant.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 32.)(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48, $ 3.)(Spain Conf.D.99, p. 22.)(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, $ 5.)2. Complete publicity of reduced armaments.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 47, Art. 45.)Complete publicity of armaments, in con-formity with Article 8 of the Covenant.Complete publicity of reduced armaments.Publicitly relating to non-military aviation.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 47-Art- 45-)Points 10, 11 and; may be immediate! referred to the Expe:l diture Commission.Publicity relating to non-military aviation-tion.The principle of p: blicity being governs by Article 8 of the Q venant, the method 1 publicity in the variot spheres could be n ferred to the Speck Commissions as note hereunder.Land, Naval and Ai Commissions.Land Commission.Land, Naval and Ai] Commissions.Land and Naval Commissions and Com! mission on National Defence Expenditure!Naval Commission.Ditto.Air Commission.Ditto.1 See in this connection document C.95.M.47.1032.VIII: Study concerning the Present Situation in regard to Publicity Civil Aviation and Collection of Provisions in Force concerning the Exchange or Publication of Information relating to Civ Aviation.
I	2	3	subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	Proposals relating to the heads of column i	Questions of principle raised	ObservationsArticle 38. Publicity of total annual expenditure.PART V. CHEMICAL ARMS.Article 39.Prohibition of the use of asphyxiating and toxic gases and liquids and bacterio-logical methods of warfare.1. Conversion to other uses of indus-trial undertakings engaged in the prepare-ration of chemical and bacteriological arms.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 45, Art. 32.)2. Prohibition of the manufacture of chemical arms.(Denmark Conf.D.99, p. 51, 5; 5.) (Latvia Conf.D.99, p. 18.)3. Prohibition of the preparation of, and training in the use of, chemical amis.(Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.)(Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51. 5 5-)(Germany Conf.D.gg, p. 32, 5 20.)(Haiti Conf.D.99, P- 33. 5 3-)(Italy-Conf.D.99, p. 34.)(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48, ij 5.)(Sweden Conf.D.99, p. 48, $ 5.)(Turkey Conf.D.99, P- 29. Art. 3.)(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, P- 45- Art- 31-)4. Destruction of all appliances of chemical aggression and bacteriological warfare.(U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 45, Art. 31.)5. Control of the manufacture of chemical products.(Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51. S 5-)6. Prohibition of the preparation and the use of chemical and bacterio-logical arms even in the case of legislation-legitimate defence conditionally on the outlawry of the aggressor and of the application in his case of the sanctions provided for in Art. 16 of the Covenant.(Yugoslavia Conf.D.99, p. 22.)7. Preparation of a more complete system for the prohibition of chemical arms, supplemented by a system of penalties.(Czechoslovakia Conf.D.99,   p. 52,SS 4 and 5.) 8.   Prohibition of the use of chemical and bacteriological arms.(Argentine Conf.D.99, p. 13.) (Austria Conf.D.99, P- I4-) (Bulgaria Conf.D.99, P- x5-) (Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51. 8 5-) (Germany Conf.D.99, p. 32, g 20.) (Haiti-Conf.D.99, p. 33, 53.) (Italy-Conf.D.99, p. 34.) (Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, $ 5.) (Latvia Conf.D.99, P- x&amp;-) (Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48, % 5.) (Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.) (Roumania-Conf.D.99, p. 21.) (Switzerland Conf.D.99, P-50. 57 (a)-) (Turkey Conf.D.99, p. 29, Art. 4.) (United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 45, Art. 33.)9. Prohibition of lethal gases and bEicteriological warfare.(United States of America Conf.D.99, P- 49. 5 6.)Prohibition of the preparation of che-mical and bacteriolo-psychological  arms.Control of manufac-ture.Penalties.Prohibition of the use of chemical and bacteriological arms.Prohibition of the use of lethal gases and bacteriological warfare.Commission on Na-tional Defence Expen-diturc.When decisions on the principles of these questions have been taken, the proposals may be referred to a Commission to be ap-pointed in due course.These proposals could also be referred for an opinion to the Land, Naval and Air Corn-missions prior to any decision on the prin-ciple.
I	&apos; 2 &apos;&apos;	3	subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	Proposals relating to the heads of column i	Questions of principle raised	ObservationsProtection of the Civilian Populationi.   Protection of the civilian popula-tion enunciated in general terms. (Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Belgium Conf.D.99, P-14- S 3-) (Italy Conf.D.99, p. 34.) (Japan-Conf.D.99, P- 53. 5 4-) (Latvia Conf.D.99, p. 18.) (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 41, Art 7.)2. Agreement to exclude foodstuffs from articles which are declared contra-band of war.(Argentine-Conf.D.99, p. 53.)3. Prohibition of bombardment by land artillery by means of shells which contain poison gases or are specifically incendiary.(France Conf.D.99, p. 25, IV.)(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, 57.)4.   Prohibition of bombardment by artillery behind the battle area. (France Conf.D.99, p. 25, IV.)5.   Prohibition of submarines. (United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54, 8 3.)6. Prohibition of the use of automatic contact mines in the open sea.(Netherlands Conf.D.99, p. 48, g 6.)7. Regulation of the use of naval artillery in conformity with the provi-sions of the Hague Convention.(France Conf.D.99, p. 25, IV.)8. Prohibition of the use by naval artillery of projectiles which contain poison gases or are specifically incen-diary.(France Conf.D.99, p. 25, IV.) (Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, 5 7.)9. Total prohibition of the use of missiles of any kind from air machines and of all preparations for this means of warfare.(Germany Conf.D.99, p. 31, 5 18.)10. Prohibition of the bombardment from the air of the civilian population.(Austria-Conf .D.99, p. 14.)(Czechoslovakia Conf.D.99, p. 52,54.)(Haiti-Conf.D.99, P- 33. S 3-)(Japan Conf.D.99, P- 53. 54-)(Netherlands-Conf.D.99, p. 48, g 6.)(Switzerland Conf.D.99, P- 50. 5 7-)(United States of America Conf.D.99, P- 49. 5 5-)11. Prohibition of bombardment from the air behind the battle area or behind a zone of a certain depth along the coast.(France Conf.D.99, p. 25, IV.)12. Prohibition of the use of project-tiles which contain poison gases or are specifically incendiary.(France Conf.D.99, p. 25, IV.)(Switzerland-Conf.D.99, P- 50.$7-)13. Organisation of sanctions in the event of any violation of undertakings relating to the protection of the civilian population.(France Conf.D.99, p. 26, IVe.)Protection of the civilian population.Once decisions have been taken on the question of principle noted, the proposals can be referred to a commission which 1 be indicated in due course.These proposals could also be referred for an opinion to the Land, Naval and Air Cora-missions prior to any decision on the prin-ciple.Sanctions.
Subject of the parts, liapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column part VI. MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS.Chapter A. Permanent Disarmament Commission.Article 40. Creation and mem-icrship of the Per-anent     Disarma-ment Commission.Article 41.Convocation and meeting of Commis-ion.Article 42. Rules of Procedure.Article 43. Quorum.Article 44.Representation of countries not havingmember on tire Commission.Article 45. Voting.Article 46.Consultation of persons.1. Assurances to be provided for with a view to safeguarding each con-tracting party from menaces caused by the armaments of one or more States not party to the Treaty or by the non-observance of treaty obligations on the part of one or more of the contracting parties.(Japan-Conf.D.99, p. 53, g 2.)1.   Creation of a &quot; Permanent Inter-national Commission of Control &quot;.1 (U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, p. 46, Arts. 39, 40, 41, 42 and 46.)2. Creation of an International Com-mission for the Supervision of Arma-ments.1(Austria Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Denmark Conf.D.g9, p. 51, g 4.) (Finland- Conf.D.99, p. 16.) (Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 5.) (Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.) (Switzerland-Conf.D.99, P-50. S 9-)3. Great importance attached to the creation of the Permanent Disarmament Commission.(United Kingdom Conf.D.99, p. 54.)1. Commission to consist of repre-sentatives of all signatory States.(Denmark Conf.D.99, P- 51. 5 4-)2. Representation on the Commission of all the Powers in rotation.(Portugal Conf.D.99, p. 20.)3. Organisation of a Commission representing all signatory States on a possibly larger basis than the League of Nations.(Finland Conf.D.99, p. 16.)Questions of principle raisedObservationsPolitical Commission.Ditto. Ditto. Ditto.Ditto. Ditto.Ditto. Ditto.Ditto. Ditto.On the question of supervision, see end of this chapter.
I	2	3	subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft Convention	Proposals relating to the heads of column i	Questions of principle raised	ObservationsArticle 47. Minority reports.Article 48. Reports, to whom to be communicated, and publication of.Article 4g. Communication of information received.Addition to Chapter A of. Part VI: Jurisdiction of the Permanent Disarmament Commission.1. Proposal to invest the Permanent International Commission of Control with the right to carry out investiga-tions on the spot; proposal for a labour control.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, P- 47. Arts. 43 and 44.)2. Exclusion of personnel belonging to the forces and persons interested in war industries.(U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, P- 47&apos; Art. 42.)3. Attention to be directed to mili-tary preparations of all kinds; prepar-ation for industrial aggression, air aggression, etc.; need for ensuring that the provisions of the Convention cannot be rendered inoperative by some re-adaptation of the system of military organisation.(Poland Conf.D.99, pp. 19 and 20.)4. Prepared to accept a more com-plete supervision than that proposed in the draft Convention. Proposal to extend supervision to the trade in and manufacture of arms. (Czechoslovakia Conf.D.99, p. 52, $ 3.)5. Need for effective international supervision.(Belgium Conf.D.99, p. 14.) (Finland Conf.D.99, p. 16.) (Haiti  Conf.D.99, P- 33-) (Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, g 4.) (Poland Conf.D.99, p. 19.) (Roumania Conf.D.99, p. 20.) (Sweden Conf.D.99, p. 48, $ 6.)6. Urges control equally applicable to all countries.(Germany-Conf.D.99, p. 32, $ 24.)7. Accepts control upon certain con-ditions.(Argentine Conf.D.99, p. 13, $ 2.)8. The Permanent Disarmament Commission to be responsible also for the preparation of further stages in disarmament.1(Norway Conf.D.99, p. 51, 55.)(Switzerland Conf.D.99, p. 50, 5j 9.)Labour control.Exclusion of per-sonnel belonging to the forces and persons interested in war in-dustries.The methods of dis-armament to be uni-form in accordance with the principle of the equality of rights of States.Political Commissior.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.Political, Land anil Air Commissions.Political Commission.Ditto.This question to be discussed in the Gene-ral Commission in con-nection with Article 1.Political Commission.1 See on this subject the Danish proposal II c, page 2.
			(1	- 27 -		. ^ I Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft converted ention	2 Proposals relating to the heads of column 1	3 Questions of principle raised	4 ObservationsChapter B. Derogations.			Article 50. Conditions,   noti-Jcation.			Political Commisson.Chapter C. Procedure regarding Complaints.	i. The repression of infringements of undertakings relative to limitation 0 * armaments should be considered. Ap-plication of Articles 50 and 52 in the case of a grave violation of the Convention or of another undertaking with regard to reduction and limitation of armaments constituting a threat to the national security of one of the High Contracting Parties. (Poland Conf.D.99, p. 19.)		Ditto.Article 31. Violation: concern to all.			Ditto.Article 52. Procedure regard-ing complaints.			D tto.Chapter D. Final Provisions.			Article 55. Maintenance of previous treaties.	1. Provisions of the Treaty of Peace concerning Disarmament to be replaced by the new Convention. (Austria Conf.D.99, p .14.) (Germany  Conf.D.99, p. 30.)	Uniformity of me-thods of disarmament in conformity with the principle of the equal ity of State rights.	The question will be Discussion sed   in   General Commi sion in connec-tion with Article 1.Article 54. Differences    rela-tive to the interpreta-tion or application: arbitral procedure.			Political Commission.Article 55. Ratification and entry into force.	1.   Proposals regarding the ratifica-tion and entry into force of the Convention. (U.S.S.R. Conf.D.99, p. 47, Arts. 47 and 49.)		DittoArticle 56. Measures to be ta-ken for the execution of the Convention. 1	1.   Provision for transitional mea-sures for the adaptation of existing arma-ments to those provided for in the Con-vention. (Germany Conf.D.99, p. 32, g 25.) 2. The reduction of armaments (in so far as immediate reductions are not provided for in previous instruments) to be carried out in two years, the first being devoted to preparatory work and the second to the actual process of re-duction. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 46, Arts. 37 and 38.) 3. Fixing of a time-limit for the rati-fication of the supplementary conven-tions provided for in the Soviet draft. (U.S.S.R.-Conf.D.99, p. 47, Art. 48.)		Ditto.1 The Haitian delegation proposes that the States be recommended to bring the provision of their national constitutions ad the texts of the Covenant (which would stand in need of revision) into harmony with the new principles of the Convention						
Subject of the parts, chapters and articles of the draft conventional proposals relating to the heads of column questions of principle raisedObservationsArticle 57.Duration Convention.of   theArticle 58.Subsequent exami-nation and possible revision of the Con-vention.Article 59.Revision in the event of special cir-cumstances.Article 60. Denunciation.1.   It ought not to be possible to de-nounce but merely revise the Convention. (Spain Conf.D.99, p. 27.)Ditto.1. Interdependence of civil and fnili-tary aviation.(Poland Conf.D.99, p. 19.)See under Article 57.Denunciation or re-vision of the Disarma-ment Convention.Ditto.Ditto.Ditto.General CornmissioDitto.General commission and Ai   Commission.General Commissioi
ANNEX IEGeneva, March 9, 1932.League of Nations : Conference for the Reduction and Limitation ofArmaments.List of Questions referred to the Commissions for Examination.THE following lists have been communicated to the General Commission as annexes to the repeat of the Bureau adopted by the General Commission on the 8th March, 1932 (document Conf.D.101). There will be found, in the order of Commissions and in the order adopted by the draft Convention (a) The articles of the draft Convention and the proposals of the delegationsin connection with these articles; (&amp;) The proposals which do not refer to the articles themselves, but whosecontents relate to the chapters of the draft Convention.The order in which the questions figure in these lists does not in&quot; any way bind the special Commissions as regards their agenda.A summary of all the proposals mentioned above will be found in document Conf.D.102.GENERAL COMMISSION. Discussion of Principle on the following Questions.(A.) Questions referring to Article 1 with the Different Proposals connected with the Principle of the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments.The main questions involved are the following :  I.   The principle of reduction of armaments :  (a) Definitive reduction under a single convention;(b) Reduction to the lowest possible level;(c) Reduction to be brought about by stages.II.       (a) Criteria for limitation or reduction;(b) Taking into consideration of the particular conditions of thedifferent countries;(c) Method of computation of the effectives based on the absoluteneeds for internal order and relative needs for national defence.III. (a) Simultaneous application of a quantitative and qualitativelimitation by the prohibition of certain material or of certain categories of armaments; (b) Prohibition of certain material except under certain con-ditions.IV. Reduction subject to measures to be taken in regard to the organisa-tion of peace : Political Conditions (a) Placing at the disposal of the League of Nations ofcertain material, &amp;c.;(b) Creation of an international force.Juridical Conditions (a) Organisation of arbitration;(b) Mutual assistance;(c) Sanctions;(d) Re-adaptation of the international regime. 16762-1] b
2V.        (a) Disarmament laid down in the Treaties of Peace regarded as an indication;(b) Uniformity of methods of disarmament under the principleof the equality of rights of States;(c) Equality of right between all States and perequation of armed forces at the lowest level;(d) Application of Article 8 to all States.VI.   Limitation and reduction of the whole of the armed forces capable of immediate mobilisation.VII.   Regional agreements within the framework of the general agreement. VIII.   Demilitarised zones.IX.   Limitation of international law regulations with regard to blockade. (The question of moral disarmament is referred to the Political Commission.)(B.) Other Questions to be studied by the General Commission in connection * with the Headings and A articles of the Draft Convention.1.   Part I. Personnel.Proposals raising the following principles :  (a) Abolition of compulsory service;(b) Freedom of choosing the system of service;(c) Limitation and reduction of trained reserves;(d) Limitation and reduction of the annual contingent.2.   Part II. Material.Proposals concerning chiefly (a) Prohibition of certain material;(b) Direct limitation (quantity) in different forms;(c) Application of different methods according to the country.3.   Chapter A. Land Material.(a) Prohibition of certain material;(b) Prohibition of certain fortifications;(c) Direct limitation of quality;(d) Direct limitation of quantity;(e) Article 10 : Limitation of land material by the budgetary method.Proposals aiming at combined direct and indirect limitation.4.   Chapter B. -Naval Material. Proposals aiming notably at (a) Prohibition of certain material;(b) Prohibition of certain fortifications;(c) Fixing of the method of reduction;(d) Direct limitation of certain material (other than the vesselsthemselves).5    Chapter C. Air Armaments.Proposals aiming notably at (a) Abolition of military aviation,(b) Abolition of military aviation combined with an internationalisa-tion of civil aviation;(c) Prohibition of certain material;(d) Internationalisation or supervision of civil aviation.6.   Trade in and manufacture of arms.- Proposals aiming at taking into account in the draft Convention the trade in and manufacture of arms.7,   Part III. Article 29 (Limitation of expenditure).Proposals raising notably the question of the principle of budgetary limitation, the extension of this method, and the question of the combination of the direct and indirect methods.
8.   Part V. Chemical arms (Prohibition of the preparation of chemical arms).Proposals aimed at the introduction of further restrictions in this connection. (&apos;)(a) Prohibition of the preparation of chemical and bacteriologicalarms;(b) Control of manufacture;(c) Sanctions;(d) Prohibition of the use of chemical and bacteriological arms;\e) Prohibition of the use of deadly gases and of bacteriological methods.9.   Protection of the civilian population.   Proposals in this connection.(&apos;) 10.   Article 53 (Maintenance of the previous treaties).    Proposals in this connection.11.   Article 57 (Duration of the Convention).   Proposal in this connection. 12.   Article 58 (Revision).   Proposal in this connection. 13.   Article 59 (Special circumstances).   Proposal in this connection. 14.   Article 60 (Denunciation).   Proposal in this connection.POLITICAL COMMISSION.Questions to be dealt with by the Political Commission without Previous Discussion by the General Commission. 1.   Article 1. Proposals relating to moral disarmament to be found in Article 1 under the sub-head, &quot;A. Political Conditions: 3 Moral Disarmament.&quot; 2.   Part VI. Miscellaneous provisions.   Proposal on the subject. 3.   Chapter A (Permanent Disarmament Commission).    Proposals on the subject.4.   Article 40 (Constitution and composition).   Proposals on the subject. 5.   Article 41 (Convocation and meetings). 6.   Article 42 (Rules of Procedure). 7.   Article 43 (Quorum).8.   Article 44 (Representatives   of   States   not   having   Members   on   the Commission).9.   Article 45 (Votes). 10.   Article 46 (Consultation of individuals). 11.   Article 47 (Minority reports).12.   Article 48 (Communication and publication of reports). 13.   Article 49 (Communication  of  information  received.    Report  of  the Commission).Additions regarding the Powers of the Permanent Disarmament Commission. 14.(a) Supervision.   Proposals on the subject.15.(i) Preparations for further stages of disarmament. Proposals on the subject. 16.   Article 50 (Conditions; notification).17.   Chapter C (Procedure regarding complaints).     Supplementary proposal on the subject.18.   Article 51 (Violation :  matter of general concern). 19.   Article 52 (Procedure in case of complaints). 20.   Article 54 (Disputes :   arbitral procedure).21.   Article 55 (Ratification and entry into force).   Proposal on the subject. 22.   Article 56 (Measures for carrying the Convention into effect).   Proposals on the subject.LAND COMMISSION.Questions to be dealt with without Preliminary Discussion in the GeneralCommission.1.   Articles 2 and 3 (Definition and limitation of average daily effectives,proposals 4 and 5). 2.   Tables I, II and III, and proposals 1, 2 and 3.(!) These proposals might also bo referred to the Land, Naval and Air Commissions for an opinion, before any decision is taken on the principle.[6762-1] b 2
3.   Article 4 (Formations organised on a military basis) and proposals 1 to 5. 4.   Tables IV and V.5.   Proposal regarding reduction in the number of units. 6.   Articles 5 to 9, table and proposal thereon.7.   Article 30 and annexed Tables I to V (Publicity regarding effectives). 8.   Article 31 (Compulsory preparatory military training). 9.   Article 32 (Publicity regarding length of service). 10.   Article 33 (Publicity regarding expenditure on land war material). 11.   Part V (Chemical warfare (whole question) and proposals 1 to 4 of theChapter :  Protection of Civilian Population). 12.   Polish proposal regarding the powers of the Permanent Disarmament Commission.  Page 26 of document Conf.D.102.NAVAL COMMISSION.Questions to be dealt tvith by this Commission withoxit Previous discussion by the General Commission.Part I. Personnel.1.   Articles 2 and 3 and proposals 4 and 5, Table VI (Limitation of NavalEffectives).   Proposal on the subject. 2.   Article 4, Table VII and proposals on the subject. 3.   Chapter B, Articles 5 to 9 and table.   Proposals on the subject.Part II. Material.4.   Chapter B (Naval Armaments).    General proposals of a technical character. (2)5.   Article 12 (Distribution of tonnage by categories).   Proposals on the subject.6.   Article 13 (Transfer).   Proposals on the subject. 7.   Article 14 (Capital ships)       &quot;18.   Article 15 (Aircraft-carriers)   V Certain proposals on the subject.(3). 9.   Article 16 (Submarines) J10.   Article 17  (General  undertaking  regarding  the construction  andpurchases of vessels).   Proposals on the subject. 11.   Article 18 (Rules for replacement).   Proposals on the subject. 12.   Article 19 (Merchant ships).   Proposals on the subject. 13.   Article 20 (Vessels constructed for other Powers).   Proposals on the subject.14.   Article 21 (Transfer of vessels).   Proposals on the subject.15.   Article 22 (Rules for disposal).   Proposals on the subject.16.   Article 23 (Hulks).17.   Annex I(&apos;) (Exempt vessels).18.   Annex II (Special vessels).19.   Annex III (Definitions).   Proposals on the subject.20.   Article 24 (Limitation of expenditure on naval material).Part IV. Exchange of Information.21. Article 30 (Publicity of effectives).22. Article 32 (Publicity regarding length of service).23. Article 33 (Publicity of expenditure on naval material).24. Article 34 (Publicity regarding the construction of vessels).25. Article 35 (Publicity regarding merchant ships).Part V. Chemical Warfare.26.   Chemical warfare (in its entirety), and proposals 1, 2, 5, 6, 7 and 8 of the Chapter : Protection of the Civil Population.(&apos;) These concern more particularly : (a) the prolongation of naval agreements; (4) the limitation of non-floating- material; (c) restriction of the use of mines.(3) The questions of principle raised in connexion with these articles will be examined by the General Commission.(*) The annexes and tables depending directly on the articles are not mentioned.
AIR COMMISSION.This Commission might undertake a preliminary examination of the principle, of the abolition of military aviation (with or without the internationalisation of. civil aviation). .   . &apos;        &apos; .Should the Commission not be in favour of the adoption of this principle, it might examine the following questions :  -      ...1. Articles 2 to 4 and Tables annexed (Limitation of air effectives).Proposals on the subject. 2. Articles 5 to 9 and Table (Length of service).   Proposals on the subject. 3. Article 25 (Limitation of number and total horse-power of aeroplanes).Proposals on the subject. 4. Article 26 (Limitation of number and total horse-power and of total volume of dirigibles).   Proposals on the subject. 5. Article 27 (Measurement of the horse-power and volume of dirigibles).Documents C.259 and 260.1931 (Standard measurements of the horse-power of aeroplane engines). 6. Article 28 (Civil aviation).   Relations with military aviation. 7. Article 30 (Publicity regarding effectives). 8. Article 32 (Publicity regarding length of service). 9. Article 36 (Publicity regarding military aircraft). 10. Article 37 (Publicity regarding civil aviation).   Document C.95.1932. 11. Part V. Chemical Arms : Proposals 1, 2, 9, 10, 11 and 12 of Chapter :Protection of the Civil Population.   Document Conf.D.102. 12. Polish proposals relating to the powers of the Permanent disarmament commission.13. Article 59 (Revision in special circumstances : Interdependence between civil and military aviation).COMMISSION ON NATIONAL DEFENCE EXPENDITURE/Questions to be dealt with by this Commission without Previous Discussion bythe General Commission.1.   Article 29 (Limitation of total annual  expenditure).   Proposals on the subject, more particularly :(a) Continuous study of the budgetary method in considerationof fluctuations in purchasing power; (6) Budgetary limitation relating to total expenditure and to individual chapters; (c) Abolition of secret funds and unification of the militarybudget.2.   Article 33 (Publicity of land and naval expenditure). 3.   Article 36 (Publicity of total expenditure).4.   Examination of the Report of the Committee of Experts on Budgetary Questions (document C.182.1931.IX) :(a) Part of the report concerning publicity;(&amp;) Part of the report concerning limitation, in so far as this part deals with the questions enumerated under 1.
Official No.: Conf. D. 99.&quot; Geneva, February 25th, 1932.LEAGUE   OF   nations conference FOR THE REDUCTION AND LIMITATIONOF ARMAMENTSSurvey of Proposals made by Various Delegations during the General Discussion.This document has been prepared in conformity with the decision taken by the Conference on February 24th, 1932.It comprises a survey, divided into subjects, of the proposals made during the general discussion by thirty-three delegations. The figures given refer to those of the Conference documents in which these proposals are to be found, and also to the document (Conf.D.93) in which extracts from the speeches have been reproduced at the request of the delegations. The figures in paren-theses indicate the numbered paragraphs in certain of those documents.The survey is completed by an alphabetical index in which the references refer to its chapters and sub-chapters.S.d.N. 3380 (F.) 2575 (A.) 10/32. Imp. Kundig.Series  of League of   Nations  PublicationsIX.   DISARMAMENT 1932. IX.25.
LIST OF DELEGATIONS WHOSE PROPOSALS ARE REFERRED TOIN THIS SURVEY.Conf. D.Argentine.............. 92 and 93Austria............... 93Belgium............... 93Brazil...............- 93Bulgaria............... 93Canada............... 93Chile. . ............... 93China................ 88Czechoslovakia............ 91Denmark.............. 9DFinland............... 93France    .....  .......... 56Germany    .............. 79 and 93Haiti  . .........-....... 80Hejaz................ 97Hungary............... 93Italy................. 81 and 93Japan................ 94Latvia................ 93Netherlands............. 84Norway..... .......... 89Persia................ 93Poland............... 76 and 93Portugal    .............. 93Roumania.............. 93Spain................ 74 and 93Sweden.....  ............ 83Switzerland    ............. 86Turkey................. 78 and 93Union of Soviet Socialist Republics   .  . 82 united Kingdom........... 95United States of America....... 85Yugoslavia.............. 93Page 52, 13 14 14 15 15 15 1650 52 51 1623 29, 173254 1733, 18 53 18 48 5i 1927, 19 20 2027, 21 4849 29, 2234 &apos; 54 49 22SURVEYI.   ORGANISATION OF PEACE.A.   Arbitration.Denmark.............. 90 (8)France    ............... 56 (V)Haiti................ 80 (5)Portugal    .............. 935i 2633 20B.   Security.1.   General Proposals.!4Q3Austria...............      nW*\ 14Belgium................           15J 15Bulgaria............... 15Canada................ (last para.)Czechoslovakia............      nn ln\ 51Denmark..............      j  ty 16Finland  . -.............      *6 IV) 26France    ...............        \ ) 17Germany    .............&quot;1 See also Conf.D.87 (new edition of the Draft Convention submitted to the Preparatory Commission), page 30.
- w    100- 3 -B.   Security (continued).i.   General Proposals (continued).Conf. d. PageHaiti................ 8o (i and 5) 32-33Japan................ 94 (2) 53Latvia................ 93 18Persia................ 93 19Poland............... 93 19Portugal    .............. 93 20Roumania.............. 93 20Spain................ 93 21Yugoslavia.............. 93 22Definition of the Aggressor.Belgium............... 93 (6)                                           *5France    ............... 56 (V)                                          26Haiti................ 80 (1)                                           32Roumania.............. 93 203.   Creation of an International Force.15Bulgaria............... 93 52Czechoslovakia............ &apos;   ) ( 51Denmark    .............. jo (7) l6France    ......... 8o (8) 32Haiti................ qo 18Latvia................ 19Poland............... l\ 20Roumania.............. 21Placing at the Disposal of the League of Nations or Other International Authority of Certain Material.France    ...............      56 (I and II) 23-24C.   Moral Disarmament.China................ 88 (II) 50Persia................ 93 19Poland............... 76 (see also Conf.D.16) 27Roumania.............. 93 20Spain................ 93 21D.   Adaptation of Pacts, Treaties and National Laws.Austria............... 93 14Bulgaria............... 93 15Germany    .............. 93 17Haiti................ 80 (4 and 7) 33Poland    ............... 76 (I) and 93 27, 19Roumania.............. 93 20II.   DIRECTIVES AND PRINCIPLES QF A GENERAL ORDER FOR THE reduction and LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.93Austria.............. (I and y) 14. *5Belgium............-  - -   1 15Brazil................ ^ 15Bulgaria............... 16Chile................; ii (I and III) 50Chma.............. 91 (2 and 7) fTCzechoslovakia........... 00  3 and 6) 5*Denmark.............. *   VJ 16Finland..............-
II.  DIRECTIVES AND PRINCIPLES OF A GENERAL ORDER FOR THE REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS (continued).Conf. D. PageFrance    ............... 56 23Germany.............. 79 and 93 20 17Haiti................ 80 (2) 33Hejaz................. 97 54Hungary............... 93 I7Jtaly................. 81 and 93 (1 and 2) 33, 18Japan................ 94 (2 and 3) 53Latvia................ 93 xgNorway............... 89 (1 and 5) 51Persia................ 93 XgPoland............... 93 T9-20Portugal    .............. 93 20Roumania.............. 93 20sPain................. 74 and 93 27, 21Switzerland............. 86 (2) 50Turkey................ 78 (1) and 93 29, 22U. S. S. R............... 82 V 34United Kingdom........... 95 54III.   DRAFT CONVENTION DRAWN UP BY THE PREPARATORY COMMISSION: ATTITUDE OF THE VARIOUS DELEGATIONS.Argentine............- -Belgium...............Canada   ...............Czechoslovakia............Finland   ...............France...............Germany    ..............Hungary...............Italy. . . ........... &quot;... - -Japan................Norway...............Netherlands   .............Poland    ...............Portugal    ..............Sweden...............Switzerland.............United States of America.......93 (1)	1393 (2)	1493	159i (1)	5293	1656	2379 and 93	29. 1793	1793 (2 b)	1894 (1)	5389 (1)	5i84 (1)	4893 (2, 4 and 5)	1993	2083 (1)	4886 (1)	5085 (1).	49IV.  ALTERNATIVE OR COMPLEMENTARY DRAFTS OF CONVENTIONS.France    ...............      56 23Germany    ..............      79 and 93 29, 17U. S. S. R...............      82 and 87 34. 39V.   PERSONNEL.A.   Effectives.Germany    ........&apos;...... 79 (1 to 4, 14 and 15) 30, 31Netherlands............. 84 (2 a) 48Spain................ 93 21Sweden............... 83 (2 a) 48U. S. S. R. . .  ............ 82 and 87 34, 39United Kingdom........... 95 (1) 54United States of America....... 85 (7) 49
B.  Trained Reserves.Conf. D.Germany..............      79 (2)Netherlands.............      84 (2 a)Sweden...............      83 (2 a)U. S. S. R...............      87C. Formations organised on a Military Basis.Germany    .............. 79 (5)Poland    ............... 93Turkey................ 7M5)U. S. S. R. . ............. 87D.   Period of Service. Latvia ^WBWMW^^WIVI.   MATERIAL OF LAND ARMAMENTS.1A.   Indirect Limitation.Spain................ 74Sweden............... 83 (2 and 6)Switzerland.............. 86 (3)United States of America ....... 85 (9)B.   Direct Limitation.Austria   . . . ............ 93Germany..............- 79 (7. 23)Hungary............... 93Netherlands............. 84 (2 6)Norway............... 89 (2)Spain  ................ 74Sweden............... 83 (2 b)Switzerland.............. 86 (3)U.S.S.R. ............... 87United States of America....... 85 (9)C.   Abolition or Limitation of Certain Land Arms.x.   Heavy Artillery.Austria..............-Belgium...............China.......;......- -Germany...............Italy.................Latvia................Netherlands.............Portugal...............Spain................Sweden..............tSwitzerland..............Turkey................U.S.S.R................United Kingdom . ..........United States of America.......2.   Tanks:Austria...............China................93	93	(3)88	(III)79	(6)81	93	84	93	93	83	(2C)86	(6)78	(2 b)87	(2)95	85	(8)93	88	(III)&apos; See also XVI.B.
C.   Abolition or Limitation of Certain Arms (continued).Conf. D. Page2.   Tanks (continued).Germany............... 79 (6) 30-3*Italy.................. 8i 33Latvia................ 93 l8Netherlands............. 84 48Spain................ 93 21Sweden............... 83 (2 c) 48Switzerland............. 86 (6) 50Turkey................ 78 (2 c) 29U.S.S.R................ 87 39United States of America....... 85 (8) 49D.   Land Fortifications.Germany............... 79 (8) 31VII.   MATERIAL OF NAVAL ARMAMENTS.1A.   Abolition or Limitation of Certain Categories of Warships.1.   Warships of all categories.Germany............... 79 (and I2) 3*Spain................ 74 27Turkey................ 78 (2 d) 29U.S.S.R................ 82 and 87 34. 39United Kingdom........... 95 (4) 54Yugoslavia.............. 93 222.   Capital Ships.Argentine.............. 92 (1) and 93 (3) 52&quot;53. *3China.......&apos;........ . 88 (III) 50Germany............... 93 I7Italy................. 81 33Japan................ 94 (6) 53U.S.S.R................ 87 393.   Aircraft-Carriers.China................ 88 (III) 50Germany............... 79 (I0) 3*Italy................. 81 . 33Japan................ 94 (7, 8, 9) 53U.S.S.R................ 82 344.   Submarines.Austria............... 93 I4China................ 88 (III) 50Germany............... 79 31Italy................. 81 33Spain................ 74 27U.S.S.R........:....... 87 39United Kingdom........... 95 (3) 54United States of America....... 85 (4) 40B.   Merchant Vessels.Germany............... 93 ?7Japan................ 94 (I0) 53Spain................ 74 27U.S.S.R................ 87 391 See also XVI.C.
0 9C.   Non-floating Material.Conf. D.Germany...............      79 (13)U.S.S.R................      87D.   Fortifications controlling International Sea Routes.Germany.............&apos; .  .      79 (16)Spain................      93E.   Treaties of Washington and London:   Application and Extension.Japan................      94 (7)United States of America.......      85 (2 and 3)Page31393i 2153 49VIII.   MATERIAL OF AIR ARMAMENTS. 1A.   Military Aviation:   Abolition or Limitation.General Proposals.Denmark............... 90 (2 a)Germany............... 79 (17 and 19)Hejaz................ 97 (2)Spain................ 74Sweden............... 83 (3 a)Turkey................ 78 (2 a)U.S.S.R........:....... 82 and 87Bombing Aircraft.Austria............... 93Belgium............... 93 (3)China................ 88 (III)France................ 56 (I 2)Hungary.............. . 93Italy................. 81Latvia ................ 93Portugal .  .............. 93Roumania...............93Switzerland.............. 86 (6)U.S.S.R................ 875i 31-3254 27 48 29 39. 3414 1450 2417 33 18 20 20 50 39B.   Civil Aviation: Internationalisation or Control.Belgium............... 93 (3) I4Denmark............... 90 (2 b) 51Spain................ 74 27France................ 56 (I 1) 23Sweden............... 83 (3 b) 48Switzerland.............. 86 (4) 50U.S.S.R................ 87 39IX.   EXPENDITURE ON NATIONAL DEFENCE. 2Denmark...............      90 (3) 51Germany...............      79 (23) 32Norway...............      89 (2) 51i See also XVI.D. a See also VI.a.
aIX. EXPENDITURE ON NATIONAL DEFENCE (continued).Conl D. PagePersia................      93 x9Poland................      93 z9Portugal...............      93 2?Sweden................      83 (4) 4^Switzerland..............      86 (3) 50U.S.S.R.................      87 39X.   CHEMICAL AND BACTERIOLOGICAL ARMS.A.   Prohibition of Use.Argentine.............. 93 I3Austria............... 93 I4Belgium............... 93 (3) J4Czechoslovakia............ 91 (4and 5) 52Denmark............... 90 (5) 51Germany............... 79 (20) 32Haiti................ 80 (3) 32Hejaz................ 97 (U 54Italy................. 81 33Japan................ 94 (5) 53Latvia................ 93 18Netherlands............. 84 (5) 4sPortugal............... 93 20Roumania.............. 93 29Sweden............... 83 4sSwitzerland.............. S6 (7 a) 50Turkey................ 78 (3 and 4) 29U.S.S.R. .   . &apos;............. 87 39United Kingdom........... 95 54United States of America....... 85 (6) 49Yugoslavia.............. 93B.   Prohibition of Preparation and (or) of Control of Manufacture of Chemical Products (of Use for War) .03 14Austria............... 00 (O 51Denmark&apos;. 79 (20) 32Germany............... m 18Latvia................   ^ 48Netherlands............. RlM 48SweLden78  3 and 4) 29Turkey............... &apos;   vo 39U.S.S.R................XI.   PUBLICITY (EXCHANGE OF INFORMATION).Germany............... 79 29Netherlands............. 84 (3)                                           48Switzerland.............. 86 (5)                                           50U.S.S.R................ 87 39XII.   SUPERVISION (PERMANENTArgentine.............Austria..............Belgium..............Czechoslovakia...........Denmark..............DISARMAMENT COMMISSION).93 (2) 1393 1493 (4) 1491 (3) 5290 (4) 5i
XII.   SUPERVISION (PERMANENT DISARMAMENT COMMISSION) (continued).Conf. D. PageFinland7Q (24) 32H^ti..............; 89 (4 and 5)                                   51Norway.............. cn 19Poland................ 20Portugal............... 9j 20Roumania.............. 83 (6)                                           48Sweden............... 86 (0)                                           50Switzerland.............. an 39U.S.S.R. .  .............. *7 54United Kingdom...........XIII.   SPECIAL PROVISIONS TO BE INSERTED IN THE CONVENTION.Germany...............      79 (25) 32Spain................      74 27U.S.S.R. .  .  :............      87 39XIV.   TRADE IN ARMS, AMMUNITION AND WAR MATERIAL.Czechoslovakia............      91 (3) 52Germany...............      79 (21) 32Norway...............      89 (4) 51Spain................      74 27Switzerland..............      86 (9) 50XV.   MANUFACTURE OF ARMS, AMMUNITION AND WAR MATERIAL.Czechoslovakia............      91 (3) 52Germany...............      79 (22) 32Norway...............      89 (4) 51Spain................      74 27Switzerland..............      86 (8) 50XVI.   RESTRICTIONS AND INTERDICTIONS OF THE USE OF CERTAIN ARMS AND PROTECTION OF CIVILIAN POPULATIONS.A.  General Proposals.Argentine.............. 93Austria............... 93 . J*Belgium............... 93  3 *4China................ 88  ^ ) *Denmark............... 90 W ^Finland............... 93Haiti................ 80 3 gHejaz................ 97 (3) 54Hungary............... 93 &apos;Italy................. 81 . . iiJapan................ 94 (4) 53Latvia................ 6   / \ aNorway............... 9 3) 3Netherlands............. 84 (4 and 6) 4bPersia................ 93 ^Portugal............... 93Spain................ 74 8Sweden............... f3 fc) \Switzerland.............. 86 (6 and 7) 50U.S.S.R................ 87 JyUnited Kingdom........... 95
i See also VI.D and VII.D.B. Land Armaments.Conf. D. PageFrance................      56 (IV) 25-26Spain................      74 27C. Naval Armaments.Argentine..............      92 (2), 93 (4) 53- 13-14France................      56 (IV) 25-26Netherlands.............      84 (6 6) 48Yugoslavia..............      93 22D.   Air Armaments.Austria...............      93 T3Czechoslovakia............      91 (4 and 5) 52France................      56 (IV) 25-26Germany...............      79 (l8) 3*Haiti................      80 (3) 33Japan................      94 (4)   - 53Latvia................      93Netherlands.............      84 (6 a) 48Roumania..............       93 20Switzerland..............      86 (7 b) 50Turkey................      78 (2-a) 29United Kingdom...........      95 (5) 54United States of America.......      85 (5) 49Yugoslavia . .     ...........      93 22XVII.   ESTABLISHMENT OF DEMILITARISED ZONES.1Finland...............      93 16
I ALPHABETICAL INDEX.(The headings refer to the divisions and subdivisions of the Survey.)Aggressor, Definition of................... LB.2.Air Armaments:Bombing aircraft..................... VIII.A.2Civil aviation: internationalisation or control........ VIII.BMilitary aviation: abolition or limitation.......... VIII.a protection of civil populations............... XVI.DAircraft Carriers..................... VII.A.3Arbitration......................... LAArtillery Heavy:Abolition or limitation................... VLCiPlacing at the disposal of the League............ LB.4Bombardment:Bombing aircraft..................... VIII.A.2See also Protection of civil populations.Capital Ships........................ VII.A.2Chemical and Bacteriological Arms :Manufacture of chemical products, control of......... X.BPreparation, prohibition of................. X.BUse, prohibition of.................... X.a civil Aviation :Internationalisation or control............... I.B.4VIII.BCivilian Populations, Protection of............. XVICommission, Permanent Disarmament............. XIICompulsory Military Service................ V.AContraband......................... XVI (Argentine)Control........................... XIIConventions, Drafts of, see Drafts of Conventions.Demilitarised Zones..................... XVIIDirectives for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments . . IIDisputes, International, Pacific Settlement of........ .I.ADrafts of Conventions :Alternative or complementary drafts............. IVDraft Convention drawn up by the Preparatory Commission:Attitudes of various delegations............ IllSpecial provisions to be inserted in the Convention...... XIIIEffectives.......................... V. AExchange of Information (Publicity)    ............ XIExpenditure on National Defence.............. IXSee also Land armaments: Material: Indirect limitation.Formations organised on a Military Basis.......... V.CFortifications :Controlling international sea routes............. VII.DLand.......................... VI.DInternational Force, Creation of......&apos;........ I.B.land Armaments :Effectives........................ V.AFortifications....................... VI. DMaterial:Abolition or limitation of certain land armaments, see Artillery, Heavy; Tanks.Direct limitation................... VLBIndirect limitation.................. VI.APeriod of service..................... V.DProtection of civilian populations.............. XVI.BPage37 7 7 10 65 37 63 7 984 108to3 2-4 97 57 64 65 5510
Page975 96 3 963 24 7 67310 73 9839 26 6539 53 7986League of Nations : Placing of Certain Material at its Disposal LB.Manufacture of Arms, Ammunition and War Material..... XVSee also -under Chemical and bacteriological arms.Material :Air armaments...................... VIIILand armaments      .................... VIManufacture of     ..................... XVSee also under Chemical arms, etc.Naval armaments..................... VIIPlacing at the disposal of the League............ I.B.4Trade in......................... XIVMerchant Vessels    ..................... VII.BMoral Disarmament    .................... I.CMutual Assistance..................... LBNational Laws, Adaptation of................ I.D.Naval Armaments :Abolition or limitation of certain categories of warships:See under Aircraft carriers, Capital ships, Submarines,Warships of all categories.Effectives........................ V.AFortifications controlling international sea routes....... VII.DMerchant vessels..................... VII.BNon-floating material................... VII.CPlacing at the disposal of the League............ LB.4Protection of civil populations............... XVI.CTreaties of Washington and London: Application and extension . VILEPacific Settlement of International Disputes........ LAPeriod of Service............-.......... V.DPersonnel:See Effectives,Formations organised on a military basis, Period of services, Trained reserves.Principles for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments . . IIProtection of Civilian Populations   ............. XVIPublicity (Exchange of Information)    ............ XIRegional Agreements.................... II (Chile)Restrictions and Interdictions of the Use of Certain Arms . . XVISecurity   . . . ....................... I.BShips :Merchant vessels, see that title.Warships of all categories................. VII.A.iSubmarines......................... VII.A.4Tanks :Abolition or limitation................... VI.C.2Placing at the disposal of the League............ I.B.4Trade in Arms, Ammunition and War Material........ XIVTrained Reserves . . .................... V.BTreaties:Adaptation    ....................... IDWashington and London: application and extension..... VILEUse of Certain Arms, Restriction of............. XVIWarfare, Chemical and Bacteriological........... XWarships of All Categories.................      VII.A.i
EXTRACTS FROM SPEECHES MADE DURING THE GENERAL DISCUSSION BY THE FOLLOWING DELEGATIONS.	Page		Page	.....            13	Italy.........	.....18Austria.......	.   ....            14.		....           18Belgium.......	.....            14		....           19	.....            15		....           I9	.....            15			.....            15		....           20Chile........	......       16			.....            16			.....            17		....             22	.   .   .   .   .            17		M. Bosch (Argentine), February 16th, 1932.. . . The Argentine delegation would naturally be glad if the Conference could agree to abolish in land, naval and air forces all those factors which, by their very nature, are specially destined for aggression, and if this Convention could be supplemented by effective stipulations prohibiting chemical and bacteriological methods of warfare, the use of which is entirely contrary to all social progress.I will now pass to the concrete points which our delegation wishes to submit at the present stage.1. The Argentine delegation accept as a basis of discussion the draft Convention drawn up by the Preparatory Commission.2. The Argentine Republic will support the establishment of a permanent international supervision of armaments in application of any agreements concluded here, provided that this supervision is accepted unanimously and without reservation and is carried out in a practical form and to the extent considered by the Conference to be compatible with the sovereign rights of each State.3. The Argentine Republic proposes that an undertaking should be entered into between countries which did not sign the Washington and London Naval Treaties, not to build or acquire capital ships of more than 10,000 tons, since these armaments have a definitely aggressive charac-ter. Our country, like those States which signed the above-mentioned treaties, considers that, if the naval problem cannot be solved at one stroke, it will in any case be necessary to seek practical and positive solutions which will enable us gradually to draw nearer to the ideal to which we all aspire.4. The Argentine Republic considers that there is one conception, that of contraband of war, of which this Conference should endeavour to lay down at least the essential principles, if it is not possible to define it more fully.The conflagration of 1914-1918 showed that the lives of civilians, the extension of hostilities to distant countries and, what is still more serious, the consequent increase in the number of belligerents, depends on the interpretation given to this conception. The London Declaration of 1909 attempted to cover and solve the complex problem as a whole. Experience has shown that this is impossible. In the frenzy of war this feeble structure, which was too theoretical and complicated was destroyed. The problem must be tackled in its simplest and most elementary form.The war afforded a terrible proof of the fact that no country possesses unlimited and inexperienced-haustible wealth for the support of its population. No country can be sure, if its attempts to conquer its opponents by this means, that the weapon will not be used against it. The spectre of famine would then be bound to arise, there would be the risk of a blockade of essential routes and finally and inevitably unrestricted submarine warfare. The object of this Conference is to reduce and limit armaments and also to mitigate the horrors of war, should this prove unavoidable in spite of our efforts. In accordance with the proposals and views which I have put before you, the Argentine delegation has the honour to propose to the Conference that an international agree-ment should be concluded under which the signatory States would agree never to regard as con-traband of war certain foodstuffs to be mentioned in the Convention.To exclude foodstuffs from articles which are declared contraband is to humanise war in the same way as is done by the prohibition to use bacteria and asphyxiating gases. The Argentine delegation accordingly hopes that this proposal will receive the unanimous support of Powers both great and small, producing and consuming countries alike, of those nations which passedoConf. d.93 Geneva, February 22nd, 1932.
through the war, as well as those which, although neutral, were not spared by the world conna..;) gration, the various effects of which are still weighing, and will continue to weigh, upon the whole world for a long time to come.M. E. Pflugl (Austria), February iyth, 1032.. . . My Government does not wish to express an opinion upon them as yet; it reserves the right to submit during the progress of the work of the Conference any proposals that it may consider advisable. Nevertheless, that Government thinks that it may at once state its agreement with all proposals devised to ensure an effective reduction in the general level of armaments, a reduction carried as far as possible that from the point of view of my country is an essential condition.My Government approves of measures for the supervision of armaments by an international commission; the abolition of aggressive arms of all kinds; the abolition of chemical and bacte-riological warfare and of bombardment from aircraft and of all preparations made in peace time for those purposes; my Government also approves all measures for the most complete protection of the civilian population.. . . Are you to-day going to ask her to perpetuate in a freely signed Convention, and in spite of previous promises and of the equality of rights enjoyed by all Members of the League of Nations are you going to ask her to perpetuate that inequality of rights and security which you would refuse for yourselves ?M. p. Hymans (Belgium), February izih, 1932,. . . 1. It is desirable in the interests of security and of peace that this Conference should lead to an agreement. If after a number of years of discussions, enquiries and preparations, Govern-ments were to leave this Conference divided, irritated by clash and failure, the effect upon the public mind which is already so anxious and disturbed would be very serious indeed. The financial burden which is already very heavy would become yet heavier. The idea of peace itself, the idea of law in international matters would be weakened. We should be taking a very serious retrograde step and we should follow further competitive expansion of armaments, bankruptcy and revolution.. . . 2. The duty which devolves upon all of us is therefore to co-operate in seeking an understanding. The Preparatory Commission has outlined the framework of a draft Convention for the limitation and reduction of armaments. Belgium co-operated in this work. One of its delegates, M. Bourquin, was a Rapporteur of that Commission. It appears to us that that draft is wisely and soundly prepared, and we hope that it will serve as a basis for a general agreement.. . . 3. I desire, however, to draw attention to a number of them which appear to me to open the way towards satisfactory solutions. I refer to the prohibition of the most powerful and deadly offensive weapons, such as bombing aircraft, with the additional corollary of the intei nationalisation of civil aviation. I refer also to the prohibition of certain forms of long-range ordnance, of chemical and bacteriological warfare, and again in the event of disaster to measures to protect the civil population and keep them, as it were, outside the scope of the war, and to circumscribe the battlefields.. . . 4. I refer finally to the organisation for the international control and regulation of armaments.5. I now come to Article 8 of the Covenant, which is our fundamental law in this question. It lays down the method to be followed in settling this problem and closely links up the question of security with the question of armaments. That, after all, is nothing but commonsense. You will never get people to renounce armed defence unless they find equivalent safeguards and protection in the juridical organisation of peace; that is to say, in respect for law, in mutual assistance and in co-operation against unjust aggression. The idea of co-operation lies at the very root of the Covenant of the League.   .Is the effort that has been made during the last ten years enough to create confidence, .however; does it give to those peoples who have great commitments or are particularly exposed the necessary safeguard for their security ?  I do not think it can be argued that it does.Certainly the political and moral condition of the world would be far more stable and far more steady if the peoples had the assurance that in the case of aggression co-operation against the aggressor would operate effectively and swiftly. That, no doubt, is the ideal, an ideal that is still far distant if we look around us and see what is at the present moment the position and what is the mentality of the peoples. But even at this moment there are certain lines on which we could progress, certain steps that we can contemplate in the immediate future;   .   .   .But if a state of security is to be organised, if a feeling of security is to be given that is to say, if confidence is to be inspired can we be content with a mere moral penalty ? No doubt public opinion and world conscience are imposing forces, the full effect of which, we have been able to gauge;   .   .   .One can hardly imagine a State, signatory of the Pact of Paris, passively witnessing a violation of the Pact; one can hardly imagine such a State putting obstacles in the way of a
Cockade organised against the aggressor, or allowing the aggressor State to trade with it or to obtain supplies from it. That argument is a very strong one, and it is worth careful examination. It is based upon the necessity for effective co-operation of all States against that State which is guilty of having violated its undertakings. It is a sound idea; it is the idea which is the basis of the League of Nations.&quot;6. We are ready to examine with the greatest possible care and in the most open-minded spirit any proposal which is calculated to strengthen the authority of the League of Nations and develop common action and make it more effective. We should be making a considerable step forward if, as proposed by the French delegation, we devised a more precise definition of the aggressor.7. It is therefore only stage by stage that we shall advance towards security; consequently disarmament will also come about stage by stage.8. In the present year there are important political questions which will have to be considered. Considerable budgetary d fficulties are being encountered by all States, difficulties which disorganise credit and paralyse initiative.M. de Macedo Soares (Brazil) February gth, 1932.. . . The system of excessive armaments has led to a political classification of nations into-Great Powers and Powers of limited interests. It is therefore the duty of the Powers most concerned to take the initiative and to lay proposals before this plenary assembly, proposals backed by a conscious will and by loyal action on the part of their authors.M. A. Malinoff (Bulgaria), February 18th, 1932.. . . In view of this fortunate change of circumstances, Bulgaria feels herself justified in con-sidering that the great difference between the present conditions and those existing immediately after the Great War removes any necessity for the one-sided disarmament to which she has been subjected. Every fresh problem requires a fresh solution. In the view of Bulgaria, the solution for the present problem is to be found in permanently reinforcing those means placed at the disposal of the world by the Covenant of the League which have not always played a large enough part in the settlement of the differences which have arisen from time to time. Such consolidation can only be obtained by the conclusion of a general pact of mutual assistance or by the creation of an international army for the purpose of applying effective sanctions in the case of a breach of the Covenant.A further essential to this solution is, in the opinion of Bulgaria, the establishment of legal equality and freedom for each country to adopt that method of recruitment which is most suitable to the require-ments of its national defence, the particular circumstances of each country being taken into account.Thus, the edifice which we are striving to construct must rest upon a foundation of equality and equity; these foundations alone are durable ; they alone correspond to the high ideals which inspired the authors of the Covenant of the League of Nations.. . . In, the hope that no less than other States, we will be guaranteed a security worthy of the name, Bulgaria declares that she is ready to bring to the Conference her modest quota of assistance in the great work of ensuring the success of our labours, and that she will accept any Convention founded upon the principles which I have just laid down.Sir George H. Perley (Canada), February 13th, 1932.. . . His Majesty&apos;s Government in Canada is convinced that the time has now come for a general limitation and reduction of armaments, and we believe that, for this purpose, the draft Convention now before the Conference, though it includes details which require further examination, provides a suitable basis for discussion and consideration.... In respect to the organisation of peace, the importance of which we appreciate, we recognise the value of the many agreements that have been made during the last twelve years, and we are convinced that those agreements should already have resulted in a marked reduction of armaments, rather than in the disturbing increases which, in many cases, the published figures show. We think further that this organisation of peace can best be achieved at this time by emphasising the prevention of conflicts, rather than the punishment of aggression; by building up machinery for conciliation, rather than providing for sanctions; by using the League of Nations as a channel through which international public opinion can express itself, rather than by developing it into a super-State.. . . May I repeat, in conclusion, that His Majesty&apos;s Government in Canada will whole-heartedly support any and every constructive proposal for the limitation and reduction of armaments which may be laid before this Conference. We believe that action towards this end should be taken, and taken now.  Further delay would be fatal.
H.E. M. Valdes-Mendeville (Chile), February 20th, 1932.... The Chilian delegation sees in the firm and trusting nature of those relations-which have, at the same time, facilitated the conclusion of international acts of conciliation and arbitration linking up the majority of the American countries one of the most valuable forms of regional security.... And now I would remind you that the Chilian delegation remains faithful to the views which it so often had occasion to express in the Preparatory Commission. While not proposing to recommend one definite system for the Conference as a whole, Chile considers that, from the stand-point of Latin-America, the reduction of armaments should be sought by means of regional agreements or pacts. In advocating these means, I am not departing in any way from Article 8 of the League Covenant. I am, on the contrary, adhering strictly to its terms, for we have to admit that the four conditions laid down in that article the national security, geographical situation and circumstances of each State and, indeed, the means of enforcing international obli-gations exhibit a very different aspect according to the different continents concerned.The system of regional agreements, moreover, is not, in our opinion, such that it cannot be carried out within the framework of a general convention, provided that the existing draft is given the necessary flexibility to enable it to be adapted to the widely varying circumstances existing in the world. The greater the allowance made for this in the Convention, the greater will be its prospect of becoming actually and in practice worldwide; but the effect of the Convention must not be nullified by reservations. ...H.E. the Baron Yrjo-Koskinen (Finland), February iyth, 1932.In offering a few short comments, I wish first to state that my Government is prepared to consider with sincere attention and desire to achieve results any proposal for the limitation and, reduction of armaments. The attitude is, I think, a natural one for a small country which can never successfully base its future on force.. . . Finland, therefore, has always insisted that the action of the League must be real; she has always thrown in her weight in favour of reliable guarantees of safety..- . . As regards armaments in particular, Finland has always been in favour of their regulation and has welcomed in particidar the principle of the prohibition of arms of a purely aggressive character. Finland has already had the honour to take part in the work of the Preparatory Commission from the beginning. We know how difficult the discussions were from which the present draft Convention emerged. That is why we endorse the opinion, which seems to be pre-valent in this Conference, that the draft Convention should, as a first step towards more effective disarmament, be taken as a basis for the Conference^ work.Without desiring just now to enter into the technical details of the draft Convention, I wish to point out that its value will depend in the last resort on the figures of reduction and limitation which each country will insert in its part of the future Convention. In this connection, the greater countries should set an example.Subject to this reservation, my country urges a sincere recognition of the equality of States, a principle which does not by any means exclude the possibility of taking into account inequalities of fact, particularly as regards security.In approaching thus the grave problem of security, I venture to observe that Finland regards as one of the guarantees of security the establishment along the frontier of neighbouring countries of neutral demilitarised zones, or, at any rate, where the proximity of vital centres or the existence of points of territory indispensable for the defence of a country does not permit of this solution, the establishment of zones within which the number of military effectives will be limited. Wherever such zones seem to be necessary and possible as between neighbouring countries, agreements on the subject might usefully be concluded as corollaries to the General Convention on the Limitation and Reduction of Armaments.Security, however, is not always sufficiently guaranteed by the mere fact of multiplying international Conventions. More important than the number of international acts registered with the Secretariat of the League is the manner in which these acts are applied and honoured. Effective international control is therefore a necessary complement to each general agreement concerning disarmament. Consequently my Government is of opinion that this Conference will achieve effective results only by guaranteeing the effective operation of a system of international control of the reductions agreed to, the efficacy of the limitations fixed and, finally, the conscientious observance of the restrictions and prohibitions imposed on certain methods of warfare. Such supervision obviously can only be exercised by an organ endowed with the necessary competency. I also note with satisfaction that this idea of control, suggested by certain associations as powerful as the Inter-Parliamentary Union, has received the support of numerous delegations.In such matters, security is a question of the very greatest importance and Finland has listened with the greatest satisfaction to the proposals put forward by the French delegation. While avoiding for the present any detailed examination, I should like to make a few comments on some of the more general aspects of this proposal.... It is, however, essential for the sttccessfid completion of our great task that this problem shoidd be solved. I quite realise that, as has been, if I understand rightly, suggested in the French
&quot;pfoposal, this solution may involve the entrusting to an international organ, still wider in scope than the League, of certain duties in connection with the application of a Convention which is to be drawn up. Finland is -prepared to support this idea of such a body in so far as it is essential to the success of universal disarmament; she is convinced that, if only the principle, which is political in its nature, is once accepted, it will always be possible to find a formula which will be in perfect harmony with the Covenant of the League.M. Briining (Germany), February 9th, ig32.The German people looks to the present Conference to solve the problem of general disarmament on the basis of equal rights and equal security for all peoples.M. Nadolny (Germany), February 18th, 1932.. . . The proposals that we have thus drawn up cover the whole field of disarmament. They are, therefore, not merely supplementary to the draft Convention prepared by the Preparatory Corn-mission, but they constitute the various components of a complete plan that we desire to see discussed side by side with the draft submitted by the Preparatory Commission.. . . But the German delegation declare here and now that it is also prepared to agree to the complete abolition of capital ships as proposed by Italy, Spain, and other delegations.. It would, in particular, be glad if the Spanish proposal were accepted that is to say, the proposal prohibiting in time of peace the fitting of merchant ships for military use.. The provisions of the Treaty of Peace concerning disarmament should be replaced by the new Convention which we shall be concluding under Article 8 of the Covenant.Note by the Hungarian Delegation.The Hungarian delegation had the honour to state during the general discussion, which is not yet closed, the principles of which it will request the application in regard to the decisions to be taken on points of detail; it has made known its desire that these decisions should be based on the idea of peace and security for all and has stated that it is not attached to any particular formula; it considers that a practical agreement will be reached more easily if the Conference does not begin with general decisions, the scope of which cannot be gauged and which might possibly lead to discord and even to ruptures, which must be avoided at all costs. The Hungarian delegation has refrained from submitting detailed proposals in advance, but reserves the right to do so, in accordance with the principles set forth above, during the special discussion of the various articles and the proposals laid before the Conference by certain delegations.We also have the honour to send you the authentic text of the speech delivered by the first delegate of Hungary which, we would repeat, contains not formal proposals but concrete suggestions that will help to explain our views.Count Albert Apponyi (Hungary), February 13th, 1932.In thus speaking of peace, I am following the recommendation which has been made, because the consolidation of peace cannot be regarded as an isolated problem. It is rather the central star around which all other special problems revolve like planets. Whether we are endeavouring to set up arbitration treaties, whether we are endeavouring to adjust the Covenant to the various Conventions concluded whatever we are doing on these lines the ultimate aim is always the consolidation and firm establishment of peace.It is from this standpoint that I shall therefore consider the modest contribution that our country desires to make to the success of this Conference.Our contribution to the difficult work with which this Conference is faced is to secure a general reduction of armaments in such a way as will meet with the exigencies of the moment and satisfy the demands of public opinion. But, obviously, we cannot renounce the arms that we have not got. We can only, therefore, insist upon the application of the principles whose enforcement is, in our view, necessary for us to secure really satisfactory results ; that is to say, to move towards the ultimate aim in view namely, the general reduction of armaments and the consolidation of peace.What are these principles ? I do not wish to expound theories to you; I simply want to lay before you one or two ideas which should commend themselves to this Conference on their own merits.For us, the general outline of the kind of thing which disarmament was contemplated to be is given in Article 8 of the Covenant. That only applies, it is true, to Members of the League of Nations, but the terms of that clause have been drafted so wisely and so logically that I cannot help feeling those countries that are not members of the League (or as I always prefer to regard them, not yet members of the League) will be prepared to conform with Article 8 of the Covenant..   .   M. Leon Bourgeois, replying, made it perfectly clear that there could not be two kinds of principles in a society if it was to be truly a society of nations.
Therefore the contribution which we can make here is to urge upon all the public and ah^f the Conference to accept loyally and in spirit of fraternity the principle of equality under the terms of Article 8, an equality which no nation worthy of the name would ever renounce.. . . It is true that the programme of the League of Nations Union says equality must be sought by levelling down and not levelling up armaments; we are perfectly prepared to accept that; we have no objection whatever to accept the condition of being able merely to police our country, provided others will do the same. We have no desire to increase our armaments, we wish for equality. If that can be acquired by scaling down armaments, so much the better. We shall welcome progress along those lines to the utmost possible limits.. That is our idea of our contribution to be made to this Conference not by referring to mere formulas but by getting down to the very essence of things. We come into the special work of this Conference with the resolve to go as far along the road of conciliation as the essential principles upon which the dignity and interests of our country depend permit.. . . But after the remarks which I have had the honour to make, it will be obvious that I am diametrically opposed to some parts of that draft, and therefore I have to say that the draft is not acceptable to us as a whole. But the Minister for Foreign Affairs of Sweden has put forward a formula which will enable me not to hamper the work, and which I can accept, at the same time not committing myself to that moral pledge by which I could not abide. He said that he was prepared to accept the draft Convention, not as a basis, but as a framework for our discussions.In conclusion, may I formulate the principles which guide the Hungarian delegation in its participation in the common task of this Conference ?In the first place, we claim the universal application of Article 8 of the Covenant, which proclaims the equal right of all to the minimum of armaments consistent with national safety and the enforcement of international obligations, and prescribes at the same time that, when applying this principle, account shall be taken of the geographical situation and circumstances of each State in accordance with a plan formulated by the Council and accepted by all States.Secondly: We give it as our opinion that the words &quot;lowest point &quot;, used in the text of Article 8, mean the greatest reduction which can be obtained.Thirdly: We consider that these words involve, not merely the reduction of effectives, but also that of war material; the total abolition of offensive weapons, of aeroplanes (particularly bombing planes), on the model of the prohibitions contained in the military clauses of the Treaties of Versailles, Saint-Germain, Neuilly and Trianon.Fourthly: If the aims thus set out can only be reached by stages, we demand that these stages shoidd be spread over as short a period as possible, and that the Convention to be drawn up by this Conference should represent a genuine advance to the furthest possible limits in this direction, and, further, that it should contain definite guarantees for the complete realisation of these aims within as short a time as circumstances permit.M. Grandi (Italy), February ioth, 1932.The Italian delegation begs to call attentionto the following principal points in the statements made by M. Grandi during the plenary meeting on February ioth, 1932.1. Equality of rights between all States and the equalisation of armaments at the lowest levels.2.   Simultaneous application of qualitative limitation and quantitative limitation:(a) As regards qualitative limitation, the Italian delegation, refers to the proposal already presented by it (see document Conf.D.81);(b) As regards quantitative limitation, the Italian delegation accepts as basis of discussion the draft Convention drawn up by the Preparatory Commission.M. Ch. Zarine (Latvia), February 13th, 1932.My country is prepared to support and accede to proposals designed to create a system of mutual assistance which would guarantee its security and independence. We sincerely hope that the present Conference may reach a satisfactory solution of this problem. The Latvian delegation has accordingly noted with special interest the concrete proposals for the creation of an international force under the control and authority of the League of Nations.. . , The Latvian Government considers that every effort should be made to preserve mankind from the horrors of chemical and bacteriological warfare. This can be accomplished only through the complete prohibition of the manufacture and employment of chemical weapons. The French proposal with regard to new rules for the protection of the civilian population has caused us the liveliest satisfaction. The Latvian delegation is, moreover, of opinion that it would be desirable to prohibit the employment of such aggressive instruments of war as bombs dropped from the air, large calibre guns and tanks.We are prepared to support the proposals for the limitation of the period of military service and a general reduction of armed forces within the meaning of Article 8 of the Covenant.
M. Hussein Ala (Persia), February 16th, 1932.. . . There is considerable good and considerable truth in all the arguments submitted. It might be said that the ideal would be the abolition of war by total and general disarmament as proposed by the Delegate of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics; or the equalisation of armed forces as proposed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs of Turkey.... On one point I note with pleasure that we all agree. I refer to the necessity for the protection of civil populations, and the proscription of the use of the most aggressive forms of armaments. That is a step forward upon which the Conference might congratulate itself. In order to emphasise this determination to put a limit to aggression and recognise only legitimate defence, we might at the same time as considering the abolition of the most deadly and offensive weapons also consider the strengthening of the means of defence of the less protected countries, the countries that have no fortifications and are insufficiently equipped from an industrial point of view. The cause of the consolidation of peace would be thereby helped and strengthened. This case must be foreseen if the principle of budgetary limitation is in the long run accepted.. . . Instead of spending our time in discussion as to whether disarmament comes before security, or, vice versa, it would be better for us to harness ourselves to useful and practical work and to agree on the necessity of considering these two ideas side by side.With each step forward in the direction of security should correspond an equivalent in armaments. We shall thus arrive at a gradual consolidation of peace with less risk, and diminish armaments to the minimum provided for by Article 8 of the Covenant. Let us devote ourselves by every means possible to moral disarmament, because, as M. Hymans said so well, &quot; it is the manners and customs of mankind which engender security &quot;, and &quot; the respect for international law must sink deep into the consciousness of peoples &quot;.. . . All we ask is to conform to Article 8 of the Covenant, which provides for the maintenance of national armaments consistent with a minimum of security and with the carrying out of international obligations imposed by common action, taking due account of the geographical situation and the special conditions of each State.M. Zaleski (Poland), February 10th, 1932.. . . For this reason, we have welcomed with real satisfaction the inclusion in the agenda of the French proposals to give the League of Nations an effective executive power, since this would in our opinion make possible an appreciable reduction of armaments.[Poland&apos;s point of view on the draft Convention.]I need only refer to the statements made in the Preparatory Commission.&quot;[Poland&apos;s point of view on the problem of the reduction and limitation of armaments and on security given in the Polish memorandum dated September 14th, 1931 document C.643.M.257,1931, (Conf. D.17).]It is indispensable . . . that this draft (of the Preparatory Commission) should constitute the main basis of discussion..   .   .   We regret that no reference has been made to the &quot; potentiel de guerre &quot;..   .   Let us hope that these omissions (from the draft Convention)  will be at least partially made good by adequate guarantees against aggression.. . . Nor must we lose sight of the necessity of ensuring that the provisions of the Convention cannot be rendered inoperative by some re-adaptation of the systems of military organisation.. Obviously, if any country were to expend an inordinate amount of its formations organised on a military basis an amount even equal, perhaps, to its military expenditure in the strict sense of the term a situation would arise which would necessarily cause some concern.. . . The limitation of the aggregate expenditure on the armed forces and formations organised on a military basis in the widest sense of the term is hence the only effectual limitation possible in the matter of armaments.[Concerning the limitation of expenditure on armaments.]. . . The Conference must carefully survey the whole of this field of the limitation of the expenditure on armaments; for there are a great many questions unsettled, such as the establishment of reasonable proportions between the expenditure of countries which have the advantage of having uninterruptedly and continuously organised their defence system, and whose territory has never been devastated or suffered foreign occupation, and countries which have had to build up their system of national defence during the gravest economic crisis ever knOwn in the history of mankind.. . . The attention of the world and of the whole body of public opinion must be mainly directed towards preparations for war in every sphere: preparation for industrial aggression, preparation for air aggression and so on.
M. Branco (Portugal), February 15th, 1932. . . . We are therefore in favour of compulsory arbitration.. . . We still think that if it were possible to revive and secure the acceptance of the provisions of the latter instrument, a decisive step forward wotdd have been taken towards the organisation of peace.. . . In any case it does not seem to us that in the present sihiation so far as international undertakings are concerned, in view of the fragility of certain legal obligations, in view of the fact that in the event of a conflict any country can refuse to appear before the organisation of international justice, it does not appear to us in those circumstances that the normal operation of collective assistance constitutes an effective guarantee of security. In the circumstances it will be necessary for a system of mutual assistance to be set up by way of reinforcement of the safeguards provided for in the Pacts of general solidarity. These supplementary special guarantees will be necessary so long as that general solidarity which is referred to in the text of the Covenant is merely general in theory and is liable in practice to disastrous instances of default.. . . We are prepared to maintain our armaments within the limits set by figures which we shall have occasion to submit in detail to the Technical Committees, figures which must necessarily be computed in consideration of what I have just said.We accept as the basis of our discussion the Draft Convention prepared by the Preparatory Corn-mission. We approve of the limitation of armaments by way of budgetary reductions ; we are prepared to accept control by a Permanent Commission as proposed by the Preparatory Commission, provided that all the nations concerned have an opportunity of being represented in turn upon that supervisory body.We note with great pleasure that all the previous speakers have undertaken on behalf of their countries to abolish chemical and bacteriological warfare. I need hardly tell you how gladly we associate ourselves with those declarations, especially as there is already in existence a special Protocol on the subject which has been signed by Portugal and a number of other countries.With regard to the suppression of arms which has been termed aggressive, such as long-range artillery, bombing aircraft, etc., we view with every sympathy the proposals that have been made, provided they are accompanied by effective safeguards and guarantees that they will really be put into general effect..  .  . Its armaments have not been renewed or modernised as they will have to be.. . . A number of highly interesting proposals have been put forward during the discussion here. Some of them will require careful consideration, and we shall examine them in the most sympathetic and broad-minded spirit, especially in view of the fact that in the course of my speech I have had occasion to adopt certain of the principles on which they are based.... I am glad to be able to tell you as a definite earnest of our goodwill and sincerity in this matter that the Government of the Portuguese Republic has decided to accede to the General Act of Arbitration.M. Ghika (Roumania), February iyth, ig32.. . . My distinguished colleague, the Polish Minister for Foreign Affairs, has, moreover, clearly proved that organised moral disarmament is an absohdely necessary condition for military disarmament, and he has set out the main lines of his argument in the excellent memorandum he submitted last September. The urgent necessity of such action must be apparent to all. In every country sincere efforts should be made to achieve this purpose by those on whom the education of the young and consequently the future of the nations depends: I refer to the action which must be undertaken by parents, by the schools and by the Church, nay even by the cinemas and newspapers.... In this essential and burning question of moral disarmament I am proud to be able to say that Roumania was the first country to introduce in her Draft Penal Code the offence of war propaganda that propaganda referred to in the Polish memorandum. My country intends to bring her internal law into line with the new international law.. . . In this same spirit the Roumanian representatives at the various Conferences have expressed the desire that international conventions shotdd be concluded for the universal prevention and punishment of war propaganda and all individual acts likely to disturb international relations.. . . Our efforts must also be directed towards the repression of international offences&quot; constituting a breach of the stipulations of the future Convention..   .   .   I am well aware that it will sometimes be a particularly delicate matter to find common solutions for the Members and non-Members of the League.. . . We shall make a genuine effort (to find these common solutions) without thereby being obliged to abandon the principles on which the Covenant is based.In the sphere of mutual assistance but very meagre progress has been recorded since the Covenant of the League.. . &apos; . Possibly in certain cases a solution on a regional basis within the general framework of the Convention will be found the most suitable, according to well-known precedents.
... So much so that, advancing again certain logical projects, the French delegation, through its eloquent and outspoken mouthpiece M. Tardieu, invites us finally to provide the League with that force which it has hitherto lacked.The Roumanian delegation gives to this proposal its warmest welcome and its fullest support; in its opinion, it provides not merely an instrument for the safeguarding and, if necessary, the successful re-establishment of peace through the application of speedy sanctions against violators of the Covenant, but also, a most important fact, a means of endowing the Covenant and the League with the prestige and the armed force which in the last resort are essential to the curbing of any temptation to appeal to arms or undertake aggressive action.... It has given us very great pleasure to listen to the speeches of Sir John Simon, of the Hon. Mr. Gibson, M. Grandi, and to that of M. Tardieu, and to note that their words, whose eloquence equals their wealth of practical wisdom, contain many points of agreement which are of the happiest possible augury, particularly as regards the prohibition of chemical and bacteriological warfare and of the employment of bombing planes against open towns and the civil population. Agreement on this point will have the invaluable advantage of providing, even if only in a limited sense, a criterion by which the aggressor in a given case can be determined, a matter on which at the present time ideas are far too vague.7 am in agreement with the remarks which the head of the Polish delegation made- on the subject of war potentials. This matter is one of primary importance if we compare, on the one hand, the industrial equipment of States well supplied with factories and with the means for the mass production of armaments by the rapid transformation of their factory equipment and, on the other hand, the absence of similar resources in the case of States whose lack of industrial development places them under the handicap of procuring from beyond their frontiers the arms and munitions required for their defence, and places them at the mercy of all the uncertainties of transport and loads them with the burden of heavy payments arising out of the weakness of their national currency.Similarly, I follow the Danish delegation in its opinion that a really effective supervision is indispensable and would be one of the most valuable means of securing disarmament.When furnishing information regarding the state of her armaments, Roumania at the same time made some brief remarks with the object of explaining her position; I should like to remind this Conference of the particular geographical position of my country, and to point out that her armaments bear no relation to her needs and security; the limitation of her future programmes in this respect will depend strictly on the guarantees which may be provided for her and which are involved in the effective application of Article 10 of the Covenant, through the provision of speedy and effective assistance from the other members of the League, and by the respect for treaties and agreements contained in the Part V of these Treaties.M. Zulueta (Spain), February 12th, 1932. .... . . Efforts to palliate the evil by attempting to humanise war will prove useless. I ask pardon of the distinguished speakers who have advocated such methods if I express my doubts as to the desirability of the attempts which they support for the proscription of those arms which are called inhuman. War has its laws as objective as the law of gravitation, and experience has proved that belligerents do not in practice accept any means of humanising war other than those which do not impair the success of military operations. We are also of opinion that there is some danger in combining points of this character with the question of disarmament; for, in the first place, by so doing we are distracting the Conference from its real object, which is not to mitigate but to abolish war, and, in the second place, we are wasting time and invaluable effort when we endeavOur to render war tolerable and, in so doing, weaken the means of disarmament. . . .. . . Now, to abolish war, or, in other words, international anarchy, we must endeavour to create international order. We here assembled are the artisans of that order, and the League of Nations provides the plan. . . .. . . Among those causes are some of a psychological character; these have been dealt with more particularly in the Polish delegation^ memorandum, of which the importance will undoubtedly be recognised by the Conference.  . . .. . . Spain looks forward to the day when this first rough framework of an international city shall be firmly established, take shape and assume its full proportions.Spain would be glad to see a further extension of compulsory arbitration, the juridical settle-ment of disputes, the strict and courageous application of the Convention for preventing war and the Convention on Financial Assistance; in a word, the whole system of mutual aid and goodwill which is the true guarantee of Peace. Instead of fresh texts she would like to see existing texts better remembered, more faithfully complied with and less . . . interpreted. Within this frame-work she would wish other nations to accompany her in a bold scheme of disarmament which would include:On land: Reduction of armaments, personnel and material, to the lowest limits strictly necessary for maintaining order at home, for fulfilling international obligations, and for the service of the League.At sea: The reduction of Navies to the status of coastal gendarmerie, the neutralisation of straits and a contribution by each country to an international Police Fleet.
In the air: The absolute prohibition of all military aviation combined with the inter- i^j nationalisation of commercial aviation.. We also share the opinion of those delegations which have proposed the abolition of arms of a plainly aggressive character. While fully aware of the relative and empirical nature of this distinction, we nevertheless believe that it can be quite easily applied in practice.We therefore propose the abolition of long-range and highly mobile artillery, together with tanks, ships in high-tonnage categories, long-range naval guns and military aeroplanes of every description.We also propose that the fullest information should be published with regard to armaments and military establishments capable of manufacturing them, in pursuance of the last paragraph of Article 8 of the Covenant.Dr. Tevfik Rustu Bey (Turkey), February 15th, 1932.. . . The British delegate in his speech referred to the system of military service. In my country, as in many others, military service is a duty from which no citizen would desire to escape. I merely must point out in this connection that nowadays, when preliminary military training is almost universal, the question of military service is really little more than a matter of form and structure. Therefore it would be essential for the Conference to recognise that each country must have the right to choose that form of military service which is best suited to its special circumstances and to its financial situation.M. Marinkovitch (Yugoslavia), February 16th, 1932.. . . We are compelled to take this fact into account and to distinguish between armaments intended for national defence and armaments which are mainly aggressive in character.. . . We believe it should he possible to a very considerable extent to make this distinction in the case of certain arms for example, in the case of aircraft, which is a new weapon in full course of development and in the case of navies.We reserve the right to consider this possible in greater detail in the competent committees, but we believe we may state at once that in our view it would be possible immediately, without compromising the security of any of the nations represented at the Conference, to abolish all naval forces, the purpose of which is to make war at a distance, and which are consequently capable of being employed for aggressive war, and to restrict them to what is necessary for the defence of the national coast-line.. . . Again the Yugoslav delegation considers it essential to prohibit the preparation and use of chemicals and bacteria in war, even for purposes of legitimate defence. Such forms of warfare, besides being cruel and inhuman in the extreme, are in the nature of war for the purpose of extermination, inasmuch as their chief menace is to the civilian population. Attacking as they do the women and children, they destroy all hope of any possible revival in the future of the belligerent nations. But we believe it to be our duty to say openly that the prohibition of these forms of war will be useless if no provision is made for sanctions.
PROPOSALS OF DELEGATIONSOfficial No.: Conf. D. 56. Geneva, February 5th, 1932.PROPOSALS OF THE FRENCH DELEGATION.The Government of the Republic, conscious of the gravity of the problem to be solved, is convinced that, in accordance with previous work of the League of Nations, the Conference should deal with this problem as a part of general policy.This is ail the more important since it meets at a time of economic and moral tension, at a time of general disturbance and uneasiness, when events emphasise the absolute necessity of a better organisation in a tormented world.The Government of the Republic is anxious to honour the promise contained in its memo-randum of July 15th, 1931, and to reply to the repeated appeals made by the League of Nations, notably in the resolution of the Assembly of 1927.   It intends thus to fulfil a double duty.It assumes that, on the basis of the draft Convention of 1930, action will be taken with the least possible delay.Further, it presents herewith proposals for placing civil aviation and bombing aircraft, and also certain material of land and naval forces, at the disposal of the League of Nations1; for the creation of a preventive and punitive international force; for the political conditions upon which such measures depend; and, lastly, for new rules providing for the protection of civil population.I. Proposals to Place Civil Aviation and Bombing Aircraft at the Disposal of the Leagueof Nations.The Government, of the Republic proposes, in the first place, to the Conference a series of measures dealing with the newest arm of war, now increasing immoderately in size and technique with consequent disorganisation of prices and international competition this war arm whose character is the most specifically offensive and the most threatening to civilians.Bombing machines capable of carrying great loads and having a wide radius of action which enables them to conduct operations far within the territory of. belligerent countries offer the aggressor a particularly cruel weapon for use against non-combatants. It is to such machines that the following provisions refer:1.   Internationalisation of Civil Air Transport under a Regime to be organised by the League.This internationalisation, already studied by certain Governments for economic and financial reasons, would include:(a) The undertaking by the Contracting parties not to permit their nationals to construct (with the exception of orders placed in accordance with the conditions fixed in paragraphs (b), (c) and (d) hereafter) or to employ machines capable of military use. The maximum unladen tonnage of authorised aircraft will be to this end and in accordance with the advice of their experts, limited by the Contracting parties to x tons for aeroplanes, x&apos; for seaplanes and*&quot; cubic metres for dirigibles.(b) The creation of an international civil air transport service entrusted to continental, inter-continental or inter-colonial organisations, to operate air transport under the auspices1 Or, in the case of the accession of States non-members of the League of Nations, of which several have taken part in the work of the Preparatory Commission, at the disposal of the international authority which would be constituted to ensure their co-operation.
of the League of Nations, which alone will have the right to build and to use machines ofi^ greater tonnage than that indicated in the preceding paragraph.(c) The right to create lines between the home country and colonial territories presenting particular interest for one or more of the Contracting parties, provided always that they undertake to bear the costs, if requested to do so by the League of Nations, and that they submit to the League for its approval the number, the type and the unladen tonnage of the machines to be used.(d) The fair distribution, according to their capacity, between the aviation industries of the different countries, of orders for material for international civil aviation, in accordance with conditions to be fixed in an annexed convention.(e) The exclusive, permanent and inalienable right for the League of Nations to requisition all machines for the International Civil Air Service.(/) The guarantee of the Contracting Parties not to place an embargo on machines belonging to the International Civil Air Service and not to sequestrate them, but to facilitate the League&apos;s right of requisition by all means in their power.This internationalisation of civil aviation is the necessary condition of the proposals which follow.2.   Limitation of Bombing Aircraft.The problem to be solved has two aspects of equal importance.On the one hand, it is necessary that, in order to carry out its preventive and, if need be, its punitive action against war, the League of Nations should dispose of a superiority in air strength.On the other hand, it would be inadmissible for a State suffering from an air bombardment, in violation of the rules laid down in Chapter V below, not to retain the full use of all its air strength in order to reply to this flagrant act of aggression.In order to reconcile these two necessities, the Government of the Republic proposes:(a) The contracting parties undertake not to retain, or not to build in the future for their military air forces, machines having an unladen tonnage exceeding a limit to be fixed by the contracting parties in consultation with their experts, at y tons for aeroplanes, y&apos; tons for seaplanes and y&quot; cubic metres for dirigibles.Machines of tonnage above this limit will be set aside for the constitution of an inter-national military air force. Consequently, they will be transferred by those contracting parties who own them when the Convention comes into force, to the League of Nations which will decide where they have to be stationed and will organise the command of the International Air Force.(b) In the military air forces of the different States, two categories must be distinguished:(i) Machines which will be left, in all circumstances, at the disposal of the Military Air Forces, and the unladen tonnage of which will be decided by the contracting parties after consultation with their experts and will not exceed z tons for aeroplanes, z&apos; tons for seaplanes and z&quot; cubic metres for dirigibles;(2) Machines the unladen tonnage of which comes within the limits y and z and which will conform with the rules of paragraph (c) below.(c) The inclusion of aeroplanes, the unladen tonnage of which comes between z and y tons, in the Air Forces they are entitled to possess, is only authorised to those contracting parties who undertake to place them at the disposal of the League in the eventuality of the application of Article 16 of the Covenant and of common action by the League of Nations. These machines will be permanently under the inspection of the League.(d) Any contracting party suffering from an air bombardment in violation of Chapter V below, on the sole condition that it notifies the League of Nations, will be entitled immediately to use all its air forces including those machines earmarked to be at the disposal of the League of Nations. The contracting party will also, if so facto, be freed from its own obligations vis-d-vis the aggressor.The above provisions, while ensuring to the League its superiority of air strength, result in limiting bombing aircraft as regards number, power and use.II. Proposals to place Certain Material of Land and Naval Forces at the Disposalof the League of Nations.The same problem arises in the case of certain land and naval material as arises in the case of bombing aircraft.   The French delegation offers a similar solution   namely :(a) Only those Powers which undertake to place them at the disposal of the League of Nations in the event of the application of Article 16 of the Covenant and of common action by the League shall have the right to possess such materials;
S* (b)   In the case of aggression contrary to the rules laid down in Chapter V of the present proposals, the said Powers, after notifying the League of Nations, will recover the full right to dispose of all such means of defence;(c)   The material coming under the present section includes:Batteries of heavy long-range artillery;Capital ships carrying guns exceeding 8 inches or of a tonnage exceeding 10,000 (W.T.) tons; Submarines with a tonnage exceeding n tons.III. Creation of an International Force.The object of the third French proposal is to set up on behalf of the League of Nations and apart from the measures provided in Chapters i and 2:(i)   An international police force to prevent war;(2) A first contingent of punitive forces to repress war and to bring immediate assistance to any State victim of aggression.(a) The police force will be permanently available with complete freedom of passage to occupy in times of emergency areas where a threat of war has arisen, and to assist the action of commissioners of the League of Nations on the spot, and also to contribute to all conservatory measures within the scope of the Convention to improve the Means of Preventing War and of Article 11 of the League Covenant.This police force will be made up of contingents furnished by each of the contracting parties in a proportion to be determined. France is prepared to contribute a mixed brigade, a light naval division and a mixed group of reconnaissance and fighter aircraft.The League of Nations will arrange for the command of the international police force and will be entitled to inspect its component elements.(&amp;) The first contingent of punitive forces would, in conformity with the undertakings to be assumed by contracting parties, be made up of elements of strength varying according to the regions concerned.These undertakings entered into by States towards the League of Nations would oblige them to come to the help of any State victim of agression with forces of definite strength constantly available. The contracting parties would have the option of increasing this contribution on the recommendation of the Council of the League (Paragraph 2 of Article 16 of the Covenant) or, in the event of aggression, with a view to applying regional conventions of mutual assistance coming within the scope of the Covenant.The undertakings of the various States would differ according to the place of the conflict -a conflict concerning another continent from that to which the State belongs; a conflict concerning the continent to which the State belongs; a conflict in which the aggressor has a common frontier with the contracting State.France is prepared to undertake the following contributions:In the case of a conflict outside Europe: a mixed brigade, a light naval division, a mixed group of aircraft, material for land warfare without -personnel, and munitions;For a conflict in Europe: a division of all arms, a naval division, a mixed group of aircraft, material for land warfare with personnel, and munitions;For a conflict in Europe in which the aggressor has a common frontier with France the contingents provided for in the preceding paragraph and, in addition, forces, the strength of which would be decided in each case in agreement with the League.As far as material for land warfare is concerned, the contracting parties which possess tanks or similar armoured implements, as well as heavy field artillery, undertake to contribute from them to the forces which will be placed at the disposal of the League under the conditions mentioned above.In these various eventualities the undertakings of each State would only become operative if the forces thus placed at any moment at the disposal of the League reached a minimum total to be determined, and if there were equitable proportion between the contributions of the principal States.IV. Protection of Civilian Populations.In addition to the preceding provisions, the Government of the Republic proposes the adoption of the following rules which can be adopted unconditionally:(a) The use by aeroplanes and by land or naval artillery of projectiles which are specifically incendiary or which contain poison gases or bacteria is forbidden, whatever the objective.(b) Any bombardment either from the air or by artillery is forbidden at a distance of more than x kilometres from the front line in land warfare. The only exceptions admitted to this rule concern the bombardment of air bases used by belligerents or of the emplacements of long-range artillery.(c) Along the coast air bombardment is forbidden behind a zone of a depth of x kilo-metres except on air bases and on batteries of artillery.   In this zone of x kilometres air
bombardment is not permitted except under the conditions laid down by Convention IX ofi The Hague for naval artillery acting with or without preliminary warning according to the cases mentioned in Article 2 of the said Convention.(d) The use of naval artillery will continue to be governed by the provisions of Convention IX of The Hague.(e) Any flagrant violation of one of the rules stated in the present chapter will be regarded as prima facie evidence that the State guilty thereof has resorted to war within the meaning of Article 16 of the Covenant of the League of Nations.V. Conditions for the Organisation of Peace.The Government of the Republic is fully aware that the above proposals entail political measures, which alone permit and guarantee their successful operation.It affirms once more that no substantial reduction of armaments can be brought about by empirical and technical means. Whoever desires the end- and the end is essential must also desire the means. There must be a change of method; in future we must seek in common action that security which each nation has hithero endeavoured to obtain from its own force alone.This is the very spirit of the Covenant. We must give vitality to its stipulations, which, ever since we began to discuss their application, have been constantly interpreted along the line of least resistance.The present Conference offers the best opportunity that has ever occurred to make a definite choice between a League of Nations possessing executive authority and a League of Nations paralysed by the uncompromising attitude of national sovereignty. France has made her choice. She suggests that the other nations should make theirs.The measures without which the above proposals would be ineffective and even unthinkable include amongst others compulsory arbitration; definition of the aggressor; guarantees as to the rapidity of the decision of the authority controlling the international force; the bringing of the action of that authority into conformity with international law, which is still insufficiently precise, but the permanent and contractual elements of which result from international treaties and pacts; and the international control of the execution of all agreements concerning armaments.These provisions, in regard to which the French delegation reserves the right to make concrete proposals are an integral part of the enquiries carried out by the League of Nations during the last twelve years.   All the elements of the necessary solution are brought together.Such a solution would be not only an important step towards a general and contractual limitation of armaments and towards their reduction, but also a great advance in the organisation of peace.As the proposed organisation would have to be general, the execution of the undertakings which the various Powers would declare themselves ready to accept will be held in suspense until the ratification of the final Convention by all the contracting parties.The Government of the Republic furnished in its Memorandum of July 15th, 1931, and in the Annexes to that Memorandum precise details of the modification of its armaments and the reduc-tions which it has already brought about of its own accord, in execution of Article 8 of the League Covenant, since it came into force and since the conclusion of the Locarno Agreements.These reductions, which the political conditions based on the existing order of things have rendered possible to France, are a pledge of her determination not only to fix them by treaty, but also, once co-operation has taken the place of isolation, to endeavour to achieve further reductions on the lines of the present proposals and of the fundamental guarantees to peace which these proposals would ensure.Annex.Explanatory Table of Chapter I of the above Proposals.Military Aircraft	Tonnage	Civil AircraftBombing machines capable of carry-ing great loads, set aside for the International Air Force; not allow-ed for national aircraft. Y	Y	International Air Transport Service vNational aircraft placed at the dis-posal of the League in the eventual-ity of the application of Article 16 of the Covenant. T	x	L,- Military aircraft left, in all circum-stances, at the disposal of the con-tracting parties.	-Li y		a           - 0	Private Aircraft.Note.   X, Y and Z to be determined by the Conference.
Geneva, February nth, 1932.PROPOSALS OF THE SPANISH DELEGATION.GENERAL PROVISIONS.The Convention shall be explicitly concluded on the basis of Article 8, and in consequence Article 60 of the Draft Convention shall be either omitted or amended, as, under the terms of the Covenant and in particular Article 8, paragraph 4, the Contracting Parties may not denounce the Convention, but may only propose its revision under paragraph 3.Provisions shall be added to the Convention with a view to rendering the application of Article 8 more effective.LAND ARMAMENTS.1. Abolition of all arms which a majority of the Conference shall deem to be of an aggressive character. Technical criteria, such as calibre, mobility, etc., shall be decided by the Conference after consultation with experts.2. As an additional measure to Article 10 of the Convention, provisions shall be included to provide for:A. The limitation of stocks of material and the establishment and publication of an inventory;B. The incorporation in the Disarmament Convention of:(a) The Convention of 1925 on the supervision of the international trade in arms and ammunition:(b) A Convention to be proposed by the Conference, providing for international and national supervision of the private and State manufacture of arms and ammunition, such manufacture to be subject to a system of licensing and publicity.The principles which will govern this Convention are those formulated in the Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission (document A.16.1924.IX), duly amended by the Minority Report on page 22.NAVAL ARMAMENTS.1. No State may build vessels of over 10,000 tons or capable of carrying guns of over 203 mm. No submersible vessel may have a displacement of more than 1,000 tons or a radius of action greater than that which the Conference may determine as giving the vessel an aggressive character.2. Merchant vessels may not be strengthened for the purpose of being equipped with guns or with other appliances enabling them to be used for war purposes.AVIATION.Complete abolition of military aviation; internationalisation of civil aviation.Official No.: Conf. D. 76.Geneva, February 13th, 1932.PROPOSALS OF THE POLISH DELEGATION WITH REGARD TO THE GRADUAL ATTAINMENT OF MORAL DISARMAMENT.Referring to its memorandum of September 17th, 1931 (document Conf. D. 16), the Polish Government, being convinced of the absolute necessity of achieving moral disarmament in every field of public life controlled by the organs of government, and anxious to facilitate the work of the Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments by creating an atmosphereOfficial No.: Conf. D. 74.
of mutual confidence, has the honour to suggest to the Conference that the following proposals be forthwith brought under consideration:I.   Reforms to be introduced in National Legislation.Inasmuch as the laws in force in the various countries do not take into account the new necessities arising out of the development of international relations, hut confine themselves to protecting purely national interests, the Polish Government proposes that consideration be given to the possibility of adjusting national laws to the present stage of development of international life. The object of such consideration would be to define a class of actions incompatible with satisfactory international relations and dangerous to the peace of the world, such as the inciting of public opinion to warlike sentiments, propaganda aimed at inducing the State to violate inter-national law, and the deliberate spreading of false or distorted reports or forged documents likely to embitter the relations between States.On the basis of the results of this consideration, it would be possible to conclude a first international convention whereby Governments would agree to make the actions so specified punishable offences under their laws.This first step might be followed by others as international ties were drawn closer.II.   Press.Inasmuch as newspapers and periodicals determine the main currents of public opinion, and thereb3&apos; exercise a considerable influence on international life, the Polish Government proposes that a conference be held, as soon as possible, of qualified representatives of journalists&apos; and publishers&apos; professional associations, to consider what steps could be taken to put the idea of moral disarmament into effect so far as the Press is concerned. This conference might further discuss the specific proposals formulated in the Polish memorandum of September 17th, 1931.The results of the proceedings of this conference might afford a basis for concerted action, both by Governments and by professional Press associations.III.   Education.Inasmuch as the future peace of the world depends upon the spirit in which the young are brought up, and the whole effort to organise an international community would be in vain if the young were not taught to look towards peace as the supreme good, the Polish Government proposes that the recommendations and suggestions already adopted should be progressively put into effect by international undertakings. In this connection, attention should be drawn to the desirability of a general revision of school text-books, to the introduction, in educational institutions of every grade, of instruction concerning the League, international co-operation and the life of other peoples, and to the importance of Government encouragement for closer relations between students and teachers in different countries.IV. Broadcasting, the Cinematograph and the Stage.Inasmuch as international opinion is influenced by every kind of public manifestation of thought, such as broadcasting, the cinema and the stage, the Polish Government proposes that steps be taken to prevent, in these directions, abuses which would be dangerous to a good international understanding.As regards broadcasting, the Polish Government is of opinion that considerable progress would be made if a general convention could be concluded on the subject. It should be observed that that part of the broadcasting programmes which deals with international relations is generally reserved for Governments and official news agencies. If Governments would undertake to adhere to the principles of moral disarmament in their exercise of this privilege, they would contribute greatly to the achievement of moral disarmament in this field.Films and plays are generally subject to Government censorship, and the Polish Government therefore proposes that the Governments should undertake to prohibit the exhibition of films and the performance of plays which might embitter international relations, and, on the other hand, to encourage e.g., by exemption from tax films and plays conveying propaganda in favour of peace.V.Needless to say, the realisation of all these ideas in regard to the attitude of Governments to private activities would be entirely valueless if the Governments did not adhere to the fundamen-tal ideas of moral disarmament in their mutual relations. The achievement here contemplated will not be complete unless the international policy of Governments is in harmony with their efforts in the direction of moral disarmament.
Procedure.The Polish Government proposes that the question of moral disarmament be referred to the General Commission, which will doubtless appoint a sub-committee to draft the necessary convention or conventions.Official No.: Conf. D. 78.Geneva, February 15th, 1932.PROPOSALS OF THE TURKISH DELEGATION.Article i.The object of the reduction of armaments is to reduce the peace-time land, sea and air armed forces of all countries to an equal limit.This limit is to be attained within ten years.   Accordingly, armies exceeding a strengthof ............shall annually be reduced by 10 per cent of the amount by which their effectivesexceed the limit so fixed.Article 2.When the above-mentioned limit is fixed, the manufacture and use of the following classes of war material shall be completely forbidden:(a) Military aircraft, together with all air bombardment;(b) Heavy artillery of a calibre exceeding x cm.;(c) Tanks and armoured cars;(d) Warships carrying guns of a calibre exceeding y cm. and having a displacement of more than z tons.Article 3.Gas.   The use of asphyxiating gases and bacteriological weapons being prohibited, all peace-time preparations for their use shall be likewise prohibited.Article 4.All material designed for the projection of the above-mentioned weapons is also prohibited.Article 5.The strength and armament of police and gendarmerie forces and Customs guards shall be fixed by special commissions, and these forces shall not be included in the limits provided for in Article 1.In calculating these forces, the needs of the different countries will, of course, be taken into consideration.Official No.: Conf. D. 79. Geneva, February 18th, 1932.PROPOSALS OF THE GERMAN DELEGATION.When the German Government rejected the draft Convention at the last session of the Preparatory Disarmament Commission, they made it clear that, at the Conference itself, they would do their utmost, in co-operation with the other countries, to help finding the right way to disarmament. It is in this spirit that the German delegation submit the following proposals to the Conference.In drafting these proposals the German delegation started from the fact that Germany and three other countries have already carried through disarmament for some years past under a
regulation which was set up by the same Powers that drafted Article 8 of the Covenant and declared at the same time that the disarmament of the above-mentioned four countries was to be the first step towards general disarmament as provided for in the Covenant. Germany therefore considers her own disarmament as indicative of the course which the disarmament of ail Members of the League will have to follow, having regard to the fundamental equality of rights of all Members of the League which excludes all discrimination in regard to any of them. The principles governing the general reduction and limitation of armaments, which the Conference is called upon to lay down, must be equally applicable to all Members of the League and to all countries associating themselves with the League&apos;s action for disarmament.The defects and omissions of the draft Convention, which have made it unacceptable to the German Government, can be seen from the reservations incorporated in the report of the Preparatory Commission.  A few examples will be sufficient.One of the chief defects of the draft Convention is the insufficient limitation of land material. A mere reduction of expenditure, as provided for in the draft, does neither affect the existing material in service or on stock, nor does it provide a reliable basis for the future limitation of fresh material. The draft Convention enables the countries generally to keep, and even to increase, their heavy offensive armaments. The air armament as such, in particular, is allowed to subsist in the draft. By exempting from reduction and limitation the main part of reserve aircraft and reserve airplane engines the draft even creates the possibility of a competition between the signatory States in the development of these instruments of aggression. As to personnel, the draft Convention allows the various systems of recruitment to be maintained, but in the case of conscript armies it does not include in its provisions the trained reserves on which the strength of such armies rests. Finally, by departing in almost every decisive point from the rules of disarmament imposed upon Germany at the end of the war, while expressly maintaining these same rules for Germany in its general provisions, the draft Convention makes it impossible to reach an acceptable solution of the problem of disarmament.The following proposals, which are not exhaustive but reproduce the opinion of the German Government in its general outline, are intended to carry through an effective reduction and limitation of armaments extending to all important factors of armaments. They include, in particular, measures of fundamental importance in regard to the prevention of an aggression. The proposals are based upon the principle that there can be only one system of disarmament in future which must be equally applicable to all countries; such a system would produce an equitable and effective solution of the problem of disarmament if armament figures to be incorporate-ated in it for all countries were fixed at the lowest possible level. These proposals are furthermore taking into account the necessity to safeguard the national safety of nations as provided for in Article 8 of the Covenant.In submitting these proposals to the Conference, the German delegation wish to make it clear that the German Government cannot accept a Convention unless its provisions are equally applicable to Germany and to other signatory countries.I.   Land Forces.A. Personnel.i. The personnel of the land forces shall generally be recruited only by means of voluntary enlistment.2. Should this solution prove to be unacceptable to the Conference, and should, in conse-quence, the choice of their military system be left to the decision of the countries themselves, it will be necessary, in the case of conscript armies, to make adequate allowance for trained reserves, which are known to constitute the main part of armies in case of war and to include these trained reserves in the general reduction.3. Due regard must be had in any case to the special circumstances of States having a militia system.4. The number of officers should be fixed at the lowest possible figure for all countries alike in terms of a percentage of the total effective strength of the armies, and that figure must not be exceeded.5. Police forces, gendarmerie and similar organisations must be limited and subjected to provisions excluding their utilisation for military purposes.B. Material.6. It shall be generally and absolutely forbidden to maintain and utilise the following cate-gories of arms:(a)   Outside fortresses and field works: guns of more than 77-mm. and howitzers of more than 105-mm.;(&amp;)   In fortresses and field works: guns of more than 150-mm. and howitzers of more than 210-mm.;
(c) Mortars and trench-mortars of every kind of a calibre of more than 150-mm.;(d) Tanks of every kind.7. The armaments allowed under the above regulation shall be fixed for each State both as regards categories and quantities, together with a uniform allowance for replacements. Countries which do not possess armament factories and work-shops of their own can furthermore be authorised to retain certain reserve stocks. Armaments existing beyond the authorised limit must be des-troyed.C.   Fortifications.8. The construction and maintenance of fortresses, field works and works which, owing to their proximity to the frontier, constitute a direct menace to the neighbouring country and might possibly obstruct measures taken for the prevention of war, shall be prohibited. (As regards coast-defence works, see II.C.)II.  Naval Forces.A. Material.9. The maximum tonnage of the various types of vessels shall be reduced simultaneously with a proportional reduction of the total tonnage. No vessel of war shall, in future, exceed 10,000 tons or carry guns of a calibre of more than 280-mm.10. The maintenance of both naval and land air forces being prohibited under Chapter III, the maintenance of aircraft carriers is likewise generally forbidden.11.   Submarines shall be abolished and forbidden.12. The following &quot; definitions &quot; shall apply to all vessels except special ships or vessels exempt from limitation:(a) Capital ships: vessels of war whose displacement exceeds 6,000 tons standard dis-placement or which carry a gun with a calibre exceeding 150-mm.;(6) Cruisers: vessels of war exceeding 800 tons of standard displacement or the calibre of whose guns exceeds 105-mm.;(c) Destroyers: vessels of war whose standard displacement does not exceed 800 tons and the calibre of whose guns does not exceed 105-mm.13. The non-floating material shall be fixed for each country both as regards categories and quantities.B. Personnel.14. The naval personnel shall only be recruited by way of voluntary enlistment. The system of limitation, however, should be adapted to the system to be applied to the personnel of land forces.15. As regards officers and warrant officers, a percentage of the total strength shall be fixed as maximum limit.C.   Fortifications.16. Coast-defence fortifications may, in principle, be maintained in their present extent. Fortifications, however, which control natural waterways between two open seas shall be forbidden, in order to secure to all nations free and unhampered passage through these waterways.III.   Air Forces.17. The maintenance of air forces of any kind is forbidden. The total air force material which has so far been either in service or in reserve or on stock shall be destroyed, except those armaments which are to be incorporated in the quantities allowed for land and naval forces.18. The dropping of bombs or any other objects or materials serving military purposes from aircraft, as well as all preparations to this effect shall be forbidden without any exception.19. With a view to strictly enforcing the prohibition of any military aviation, the following shall, inter alia, be forbidden.(a) Any instruction and training of any person in aviation having a military character or a military purpose.(6)   Any instruction or training of members of the army or navy in civil aviation.(c) The construction, maintenance, importation or putting into commission of aircraft which is in any way armoured or protected or supplied with devices for the reception of warlike armaments of any kind, such as guns, machine-guns, torpedoes, bombs, or which are supplied with gunsights or devices for the dropping of bombs and with similar warlike instruments.
i^d) The maintenance of any relations between the military or naval administration and civil aviation for any military purpose.iv.   General Clauses. a.   Chemical Arms.20. The prohibition of the military utilisation of asphyxiating, poisonous or similar gases and all similar liquids, matters or processes as well as of all other means of bacteriological warfare shall be extended to the preparation of the utilisation of these weapons.B.  Traffic in Arms and Manufacture of Arms.21. The export and import of war armaments and their ammunition as well as of war material shall be strictly prohibited. Countries, however, which are not in a position to manufacture the quantities of arms, war materials and munitions allotted to them shall be given the possibility of importing the necessary quantities from abroad.22. The manufacture of war armaments and munitions as well as of war material shall only be carried out in a limited number of private or State factories or workshops which shall be made public. The Governments undertake to ensure by appropriate measures that the production does not exceed the quantities allowed for their own use and for export to countries without an armament industry.C. Expenditure.23. In conformity with the obligations of the Members of the League embodied in Article 8 of the Covenant, to exchange full and frank information as to the scale of their armaments, this exchange must also extend to expenditure for armaments.Observation.   The German delegation are of opinion that the numerous deviations from the solid basis of the gold standard which have recently occurred are going to bring about such a decisive and unforeseen change in pur-chasing power that, for the time being, the method of financial limitation cannot be used as an effective measure of disarmament. Under the present economic and monetary circumstances, the application of this method would give rise to continual derogations which would seriously interfere with the steady advance of the process of contractual disarmament. Moreover, the establishment of a common plan for the financial limitation would be connected with extraordinary difficulties owing to the great differences which are at present existing in the various countries as to the stocks of material in hand. On the other hand, regard must be had to the fact that any really effective direct disarmament would be automatically accompanied by the indispensable decrease of the heavy financial burdens under which the nations are suffering owing to the exaggerated level of armaments.D.   Control.24. The carrying through and the observation of the disarmament clauses shall be secured by a procedure of control equally applicable to all countries.v.   Transitory Provisions.25. In so far as the realisation of the present proposals necessitates measures of a technical nature or measures of organisation, the Conference shall have to lay down provisions regarding the procedure and the periods which the various States shall have to observe in adjusting their present armaments to the level fixed by the Convention.Official No.: Conf. D. 80.Geneva, February 17th, 1932.proposals by the haitian delegation.The Haitian delegation proposes that all States taking part in the Conference should undertake, in a general convention:1. In accordance with the principles of mutual help which constitute the foundation of the League, to provide the latter, by a contribution from all the States belonging to it, to be fixed for each in proportion to the numbers of its population and to its national resources, with an organised land, sea and air force, and effectives deemed by experts to be adequate to assist or defend peoples who are the victims of aggression, without prejudice to the sanctions already
- 33 -115laid down in Article 16 of the Covenant: aggression to be denned by the League and the aggressor to be determined by the Permanent Court of International Justice;2. To reduce existing armaments and to limit their strength in accordance with the principles contained in the six paragraphs of Article 8, under the conditions laid down in the draft of the Preparatory Commission, the supervision of these measures being left to a special organisation of the League in accordance with the suggestion of H.E. M. Zulueta Escolano, the distinguished head of the Spanish delegation;3. To abolish forthwith chemical and bacterial arms, the bombardment from the air of civilian populations and the use of offensive armaments, and to forbid all methods of war which are cruel to excess and useless, and which generous minds, expressing the universal feeling of the members of this Conference, have condemned in this place. It must at the same time, in our opinion, always be borne in mind that there are no intermediate stages between barbarity and worse things, and that in any case it is essential, with the aid of the coercive police force to be placed at the disposal of the League, to achieve the progressive abolition of all the means of destroying human life and property, except in cases where the international force is itself repressing crimes committed against peace;4. To renounce the compulsive clauses embodied in the treaties for the benefit of one nation or group of nations against defeated nations, inasmuch as the League should be exclusively responsible for the full and complete execution of all the duties deriving from those treaties; for if the world is to be delivered from its present intolerable and dangerous condition there must no longer be one mentality of the victors and another of the vanquished. There must be no victor but peace, and no vanquished but war;5. As a corollary to the preceding Article, to refer to the Permanent Court of International Justice any dispute likely to lead to a rupture between two nations or between one nation and the League of Nations in accordance with the terms of Article 15 as amended; breaches of these undertakings and of the awards of the Permanent Court of International Justice to be followed by penalties enforced by the League;6. To substitute henceforward in relations between organised nations this new regime of international law, in all parts of the world, for the previous regime which tolerates de facto situations created by the forcible action of one nation against another nation and which tolerates &quot; regional understandings &quot; not freely entered into by all the parties and essentially incompatible with Article 10 of the Covenant, to which no exception may hereafter be made either by the Covenant itself or by any individual treaty;7. To recommend the participating States to follow the example of the Spanish Republic and bring into harmony with these new principles of the final Convention ultimately to be concluded the provisions of their national constitutions and the clauses of the Covenant which should be amended according to the customary procedure.8. To bring into operation when necessary, according as the Council of the League of Nations may think fit, the sanctions provided for in Article 16 or any other kind of sanctions, against any State signatory to the Convention which may refuse to furnish its contingent to the international force.Official No.: Conf. D. 81.Geneva, February 19th, 1932.PROPOSAL BY THE ITALIAN DELEGATION RELATING TO THE PROHIBITION OF WAR MATERIAL OF A SPECIFICALLY AGGRESSIVE CHARACTER.Being convinced that the reduction and limitation of armaments contemplated by Article 8 of the Covenant can be greatly facilitated by the simultaneous application of a quantitative and qualitative limitation:The Italian delegation has the honour to propose that the Conference examine first of all the question of prohibiting all war material of a specifically aggressive character.In this connection the Italian delegation would remind the Conference that it has already announced its willingness to accept an organised scheme of qualitative limitation covering:In the Sphere of Naval Armaments:1.   Simultaneous abolition of capital ships and submarines; 2.   Abolition of aircraft-carriers.In the Sphere of Land Armaments:1.   Abolition of heavy artillery of every kind; 2.   Abolition of tanks of every kind.
In the Sphere of Air Armaments: Abolition of bombing aircraft.In Every Sphere:i.   Abolition of aggressive chemical and bacteriological weapons of every kind; 2.   Revision of the laws of war with a view to the more complete and effective protection of the civil population.Official No.: Conf. D. 82.Geneva, February 19th, 1932. PROPOSALS OF THE SOVIET DELEGATION.Note by the Secretary-General:At the request of the President of the Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments, the Secretary-General has the honour to transmit to the delegates to the Conference the following documents:Letter from M. Litvinoff, President of the Delegation of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, with annexes:(a)   Draft Resolution for General, Total and Immediate Disarmament;(6)   Amendments to Draft Convention for the Proportional and  Progressive Reduction of Armaments;(c) Schemes;(d) Explanatory Note.COMMUNICATION FROM M. LITVINOFF, PRESIDENT OF THE SOVIET DELEGATION, TO THE PRESIDENT OF THE CONFERENCE.Geneva; February 18th, 1932.I have the honour to send you herewith the proposals of the Soviet delegation to the Conference for Disarmament.In accordance with my statement of February nth, I have the honour to ask you to put the enclosed draft resolution before the Conference. This resolution, if accepted by the Conference, would enable it to make the draft convention for total and general disarmament advanced by the Soviet delegation at the Preparatory Commission on February 15th, 1928, and at the time sent to all Governments, the basis of its further work.Should the Conference reject this resolution, I would ask you, in accordance with my statement of February nth last, to place before the Conference the draft convention for the proportional and progressive reduction of armaments presented to the Preparatory Commission by the Soviet delegation on March 23rd, 1928.I venture to bring to your notice that, in a resolution of April 19th, 1929, the Preparatory Commission, after consideration of this draft convention, decided to transmit it for the discussion of the Conference now sitting. Taking into consideration the memorandum of the Soviet delegation of December 9th, 1930, and the note to the report of the Preparatory Commission of the same date, I regard the draft convention for the proportional and progressive reduction of armaments as being thus already before the Conference.Realising, however, that the aforesaid draft convention for the reduction of armaments was submitted to the Preparatory Commission four years ago, since when great progress has been made in military technique, and being, moreover, desirous of taking into account certain opinions expressed during the discussion of this draft convention in the Preparatory Commission, the
- 35 -lii Soviet Delegation thinks fit to make certain amendments to its own draft convention, and I have the honour to enclose these amendments herewith.(Signed)   M. Litvinoff.(a)  Draft Resolution.Animated by the firm desire for an effective and solidly organised peace;Actuated by the determination to create genuine security for all States and all peoples by preventing the possibility of future wars;Convinced that the very existence of armaments and the tendency they show constantly to increase inevitably lead to armed international conflicts which tear the workers from their peaceful occupations and bring innumerable calamities in their train;Considering that military expenditure, which imposes an intolerable burden upon the masses of the people, fosters and enhances the economic crisis with all its consequences;Noting that the States which it represents have renounced war as an instrument of national policy;Believing that the only effective means of contributing to the organisation of peace and the establishment of security against war is the general, complete and rapid abolition of all armed forces, setting out from the principle of equality for all;Convinced that the idea of general and complete disarmament answers to the sincere aspira-tions of the masses towards peace:The Conference decides to base its work on the principle of general and complete disarmament.(b) Amendments to the Soviet Draft Convention on the Reduction of Armaments(Conf. D. 87).Article 1 of the draft to be modified as follows:&quot; In accordance with the preamble to the present Convention, the Contracting States, when effecting the progressive and proportional reduction of the effectives or their armed land forces, agree to divide all the Contracting States into the following groups:&quot;&apos; States maintaining in peace time armed land forces:&quot; A.   Of over 200,000 men;&quot; B.   Of 30,000 to 200,000 men;&quot; C.   Of 30,000 men or less.&quot; Remarks.   1. States disarmed as a result of the world war are not included in any of the groups provided for in the present article.&quot; 2. States having contracted alliances or agreements of mutual military assistance in case of armed conflicts shall be classified in the groups provided for in the present article, for the purpose of the reduction of their armaments, on the basis of a figure representing the total land forces of these States added together.&quot;Remarks 1, 2 and 3 of the draft shall be maintained and shall become Remarks 3, 4 and 5 respectively.Article 2 of the draft shall be modified as follows:&quot; The&apos; effectives of the land armed forces shall be reduced:&quot; 1.   For States in Group A, by 50 per cent;&quot; 2. For States in Group B, from o to 50 per cent according to the number of their effectives and to the scale of progressive and proportional reduction attached;&quot; 3.   For States in Group C, the effectives shall be limited to the present level.&quot; Remark.   The effectives of the armed land forces of the States disarmed as a result of the world war are no t included in the above schedule and shall be fixed separately.&quot;Article 12 of the draft shall be modified as follows:&quot; In accordance with the preamble to the present Convention, the Contracting States agree to effect a reduction of their naval forces on the following basis:&quot; A. Countries having a fleet of an aggregate tonnage exceeding 500,000 tons shall reduce it by 50 per cent, such reduction to affect both the aggregate tonnage of the entire fleet and the tonnage of each category, without right of transfer.&quot; B. Countries having a fleet with an aggregate tonnage of 100,000 to 500,000 tons shall reduce it both as regards aggregate tonnage and the tonnage of each of the categories from o per cent to 50 per cent in accordance with the scale of progressive and proportional reduction attached.&quot; These countries shall enjoy a right of transfer from o per cent to 100 per cent in inverse proportion to the ratio of reduction of their respective fleets.
&quot; C. States having a fleet whose aggregate tonnage does not exceed 100,000 tons shall&quot; retain their fleet at the present level with unlimited right of transfer.&quot; D. States having aircraft carriers shall destroy them within a period of six months as from the entry into force of the present Convention &quot;.&quot; Remarks.   1. Standards for the naval armed forces of the States disarmed as a result of the world war are not contained in the above schedule and shall be fixed separately.&quot; 2. States having contracted alliances or agreements of mutual military assistance in the case of armed conflicts shall be classified in the groups provided for in the present article, for the purpose of the reduction of their armaments, on the basis of a tonnage equal to the total tonnage of these States added together &quot;.Article 21 of the draft shall be modified as follows:&quot; In conformity with the preamble to the present Convention, the Contracting States agree, when carrying into effect the progressive and proportional reduction of air armaments, to divide all the Contracting States into the following groups:&quot; States possessing in peace time air armed forces:&quot; E.   Of more than N1 aeroplanes in service;&quot; F.   From 100 to N aeroplanes in service;&quot; G.   Not more than 100 aeroplanes in service.&quot; States in Group E shall reduce their armed air forces by 50 per cent.&quot; States in Group F shall reduce their armed air forces from 50 to o per cent in proportion to the number of aeroplanes in service and according to a scale of progressive and proportional reduction.&quot; States in Group G shall retain their armed air forces at the present level.&quot; This reduction shall apply both to the number of aeroplanes in service and to the total horse-power of these aeroplanes. In estimating this reduction, account shall be taken of the number and total horse-power both of aeroplanes in service in the armed air forces and of aeroplanes in service capable of use for war purposes and employed in formations organised on a military basis.&quot; The total engine-power of each aeroplane shall not exceed 600 h.p. on the ground.&quot; Remark.   States having contracted alliances or agreements of mutual military assistance in case of armed conflicts shall be classified in the groups provided for in the present article, for the purpose of the reduction of their armaments, on the basis of a figure equal to the total number of aeroplanes in service in the armed air forces of these States added together and to the total aggregate engine-power of these aeroplanes &quot;.Article 24 of the draft shall be modified as follows:&quot; When the number of aeroplanes in service is reduced in virtue of Article 21, 22 and 23 of the present Convention, aeroplanes with engines of over 600 h.p. shall be scrapped first.&quot;(c) Scale of Progressive and Proportional Reduction of Armaments. (See Schemes, pages 37 and 38.)1 The figure N will be fixed according to the decision taken by the Conference with regard to the abolition of bombing-machines.


id) Explanatory Note.The principle of progressive and proportional reduction of land, sea or air forces consists in reducing these forces in direct ratio to their size, so that the forces of the countries possessing the most powerful armaments shall be subject to the maximum reduction. For other countries, this reduction will take place in a ratio directly proportional to the size of their armaments. Thus, applying this principle to the reduction of land armies, it is possible and it will be more equitable to prescribe a certain maximum uniform reduction for armies exceeding a given figure. On the other hand, it is possible to exempt from any reduction the smallest armies, i.e., those below another given figure. As regards all the other armies included between these maximum and minimum limits, their reduction should be fixed according to a ratio directly proportional to the effectives of each.  This system will also be applicable to naval and air forces.Official No.: Conf. D. 87.Geneva, February 19th, 1932.Draft Convention on the Reduction of Armaments Submitted by the Delegation of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics to the Preparatory Commission for the Disarmament Conference on March 23rd, 1928.1Considering that the immense growth in armaments and in militarism imposes a general and heavy burden on the peoples of the entire world and lowers the level of their culture and their material well-being ;And considering that the atrocious struggle between the various States for predominance in armaments and the tendency to increase the number of weapons for murderous and destructive military purposes are one of the factors which increase the possibility and the likelihood of armed outbreaks ;And desiring to protect to the fullest possible extent the peaceful population of workers against the immediate dangers which threaten their life and property in the event of the outbreak of armed strife ;The Contracting States have decided, with the object of taking a first serious and genuine step towards general and complete disarmament, to conclude the present Convention by appointing as their representatives.........................who, having communicated to each other their full powers found in good and due form, have agreed as follows:General Provisions.Whereas a comparatively small number of the most powerful States, which aspire to a role of world domination, which expend on land, naval and air armaments a large portion of the national budgets, and which possess, the power at any moment to increase unduly the armaments which support their aggressive policies by availing themselves of highly developed industries, have at their disposal by far the greater proportion of land, naval and air armaments,The Contracting States recognise that the only just course to pursue is that of a progressive reduction of all kinds of armaments as regards their composition and number, this method being the least injurious to the interests of the weakest States, which are economically depen-dent on the stronger, and it is accordingly desirable to take this principle as a basis for the reduction of armaments.CHAPTER I. - ARMED LAND FORCES. Section i.   Effectives. Article 1.In accordance with the Preamble to the present Convention, the Contracting States, when effecting the reduction of the armed land forces, agree to divide all States into the following main groups :(a) Group A : States maintaining armed land forces numbering over 200,000 men serving with the colours in the active army, or having in the cadres of the armed land forces more than 10,000 regular officers or more than 60 regiments of infantry (180 battalions) ;1 Document C.P.D. 117.
(6) Group B : States maintaining armed land forces numbering over 40,000 men serving with the colours in the active army or having in the cadres of the armed forces more than 2,000 regular officers or more than 20 regiments of infantry (60 battalions) ;(c) Group C : all other States maintaining armed forces inferior in number and composi-tion to the figures given for Group B.(d) Group D :  States disarmed after the world war.Remarks.   1. In all the calculations mentioned above, account shall be taken of the total number of the armed land forces maintained by the State in question in the home country, in occupied territories and in the colonies, including military police, military gendarmerie corps and depot guards.The numbers of the police forces organised on a military basis, gendarmerie, Customs guards, train guards, forest guards and other armed corps organised for the needs of the Customs preventive service, for the maintenance of order within the country and the protection of Government and public property shall be determined by means of a special Convention.2. By persons &quot; serving with the colours in the active army &quot; are understood all persons serving permanently in the cadres of the armed forces and all persons serving in the army cadres as conscripts.3. By &quot; officers &quot; (commanders) are understood all persons who have received specific military training and are described as &quot; officers &quot; (commanders) under the military law of the contracting countries.Article 2.Recognising that, among the methods of reducing armed land forces, the simplest and the fairest for all the States concerned, and that which at the same time least affects the system of organising, recruiting and training such forces, consists in applying the same coefficient of reduction to all States in the same group (Article 1 of the present Convention), the Contract-ing States agree to fix the coefficient at the following figures :(a) States in Group A shall reduce their armed land forces by one-half ;(b) States in Group B by one-third ;(c) States in Group C by one-fourth.Remarks.   The proportionate strength of the armed land forces for States in Group D. hall be fixed under special conditions to be determined by the Disarmament CcnferenceeArticle 3.The armed land forces of the Contracting States shall be reduced by applying the coefficients mentioned in Article 2 of the present Convention to the following totals :(a) To the aggregate total of the effectives serving with the colours in the active army, men belonging to the variable militia formations, the territorial formations, the organised reserves and other military formations receiving military training with the colours or elsewhere ; officers, non-commissioned officers and other ranks shall be reckoned separately in each case ;(b) To the number of the organised units and corps of the main categories of field troops in the regular or territorial armies, in the militia forces, in the organised reserves and in other military formations which can be employed immediately without an order for mobilisation or which exist and are recognised in peace-time as cadres of the armed forces in war.Article 4.The number of the effectives and units and the corps of the land forces which the Contracting Parties must not exceed shall be laid down in a supplementary Convention based on the following principles :(a) The coefficients of reduction mentioned in Article 2 of the present Convention shall be applied to the several States according to the group to which they belong (Article 1 of the present Convention) separately in the case of : .(1)   Each category of armed land forces (regular army, territorial militia, organisedreserves, etc.) ;(2) The total number of the armed land forces stationed in the home country, in occupied territories and in the colonies ;(3) The total number of regular officers arid regular non-commissioned officers and officers of the variable effectives;(4)   The number of units and corps of each category of troops.
(b) In accordance with, the foregoing, the following tables shall be annexed to the supplementary Convention. Each table shows, after the reduction of each category of armed forces, the remaining number of units and corps of infantry, field artillery and cayalry which make up the general effectives classified under the headings of officers, non-commissioned officers and voluntarily enlisted other ranks (total number), of the administrative services, civic education service, intendance, chaplains department, etc. :Table    I : Maximum home forces ;Table   II: Maximum oversea forces stationed in the home country;Table III : Maximum forces of dominions and other overseas possessions;Table IV :  Maximum forces of the home country stationed in the several colonies, dominions or other overseas possessions ;Table   V :  Maximum of the total forces of each State.(c) The aforesaid coefficients of reduction used in calculating effectives will be applied to the effectives of the armed forces as shown in the returns on January ist, 1928.Article 5.With the object of limiting the accumulation of trained reserves, the Contracting States agree :(a) To reduce in each class, according to the coefficients of reduction given above, the aggregate number of men who have received military training and of officers who have received military training either with the colours or elsewhere;(6) To pass legislation prohibiting the existence of any civil bodies organised on a military basis by specialised instructors drawn from the army, and the assembly of such bodies for training, as also the military training of the civilian population at the instance of civil associations.Section 2.   Material. Article 6.For the armament of land forces, the existing patterns shown in the tables at January ist, 1928, shall be retained, except tanks and heavy artillery with very long range, which are essentially designed for aggression.Article 7.All implements of war directed primarily against the civilian population which does not directly take part in the armed conflict (military aircraft and chemical weapons) must be destroyed as provided in the special Convention.Article 8.The quantities of arms for the land armies shall be strictly limited according to : (a) &apos; The needs of the army in time of peace ;(i) The number of trained reservists in each year-class, the number of such classes being the same for all countries in any one group (Article 1 of the present Convention) and not exceeding ten classes for countries in Group A, with a subsequent progressive increase of 50 per cent and 100 per cent respectively for Groups B and C.Article 9.The maximum number of weapons allowed for every thousand trained reservists shall be fixed for each country in strict conformity with the normal proportions existing in the principal arms in different countries and for different forms of armament.Article 10.The actual maximum quantities of arms allowed for troops at depots and elsewhere in the territory of the State, which quantities may not be exceeded, shall be fixed on the bases laid down in Articles 8 and 9 of the present Convention, by an additional Convention and by annexed tables according to the list in paragraph (b) of Article 5 of the present Convention.
Each table must contain general summarised figures under the following heads :(i)  Rifles, carbines and pistols :(a) Automatic;(b) Non-automatic.(2)   Machine-guns:(a) Heavy;(b) Light.(3)  Artillery :(a) Light field guns (76-millimetre guns and 122-millimetre howitzers) ;(b) Heavy field guns (105-millimetre guns and 150-millimetre howitzers) ;(c) Heavy guns and howitzers (over 150 millimetres and up to 204 milli-metres) ;(d) Mortars and trench mortars of all patterns;(e) Guns accompanying the infantry:(aa)   Guns and howitzers ;(bb)   Mine-throwers, grenade-throwers and bomb-throwers ; (4)  Armoured cars ;(5)   Spare parts, machinery, gun-carriages and gun-barrels ; (6)   Cartridges (for rifles and pistols) ; (7)   Grenades (hand and rifle) ;(8)   Shells for guns of the calibres and patterns mentioned above; (9)  Armes blanches.Article 11.All arms in the territory of the Contracting States over and above the quantities specified in Article 10 of the present Convention shall be destroyed.CHAPTER II. - NAVAL FORCES.Article 12.In accordance with the principles set forth in the Preamble to the present Convention, the Contracting States agree to effect a reduction of their naval forces on the following basis :(a) Countries which on January 1st, 1928, had a fleet whose aggregate tonnage exceeded 200,000 tons shall reduce their naval forces by one-half, such reduction to affect both the aggregate tonnage of the entire fleet and the tonnage in each of the following classes of warship :Capital ships :Other warships of displacement exceeding 10,000 tons;Light forces ;Submarines.(6) Countries which on January 1st, 1928, had a fleet whose aggregate tonnage was less than 200,000 tons shall reduce their naval forces by one-fourth of the aggregate tonnage of the entire fleet.(c) As soon as the present Convention comes into force, aircraft-carriers shall be struck of the establishment of the navy. Within six months they must be disarmed and so converted as to make it quite impossible for them to be used for warlike purposes.Note.  : The strength of the naval forces of those countries which were disarmed after the war of 1914-1918 shall be fixed in accordance with special principles to be laid down by the Disarmament Conference.Article 13.The maximum specific tonnage which must not be exceeded by the Contracting States shall be fixed in accordance with the above-mentioned principles by a special Convention, to be concluded within three months from the day on which the present Convention comes into force.Article 14.The division of the fleet into vessels which are to be struck off the naval establishment and vessels which are to remain on the establishment, the names of the vessels being given (within the limits of the tonnage allowed under Article 12 of the present Convention), shall, be effected by each Contracting Party.  Within one year from the coming into force of the
9 present Convention, those warships which each Party designates to be struck off the establish-ment of the navy must be disarmed and put into such a condition that they cannot possibly be used for warlike purposes.Note.   The disarmament of warships comprises the removal of the armour, guns and torpedoes, the destruction of special fittings, armoured turrets, conning-towers, fire-control instruments, communications for use in battle, and aircraft-launching devices.Article 15.The procedure for striking vessels off the naval establishment and putting them into such a condition that they cannot possibly be used for warlike purposes shall be fixed by an additional technical agreement which shall be attached to the present Convention, and shall be concluded in accordance with Article 13 of the present Convention.Article 16.The Contracting States agree that, as from the entry into force of the present Convention, warships (both those which are to be constructed in future and those which are now on the -stocks) shall only be constructed to replace vessels of the corresponding classes or categories which have been retained on the establishment of the fleet after the reduction has been effected as provided in Articles 12 and 13.  Such vessels must satisfy the following conditions :(a) Except in case of total loss, no vessel may be replaced until it has reached the age-limit, as specified below :Capital ships...................     )Other warships of over 10,000 tons.........     [    25 years.Cruisers of over 7,000 tons .Cruisers of under 7,000 tonsFlotilla leaders......Torpedo-boat destroyers . . Torpedo-boats.......Submarines.................... 15 years.(5) The maximum standard displacement for a warship shall be fixed at 10,000 metric tons. Vessels of more than 10,000 tons displacement now included in the naval forces shall be struck off when they reach the age-limit specified in paragraph (a) of this article, but in any case not later than . .  . ;(c) The maximum calibre of the guns mounted in warships shall be fixed at 12 inches (304.8 millimetres) ;(d) No warship may be fitted with appliances for the carrying of aircraft ;(e) The maximum limits for vessels by classes and categories are laid down as follows :Age-limit25 years. 25 years. 20 years.20 years.15 years.Note.   The standard displacement of a ship is the displacement of the ship complete, fully manned, with engines and boilers, equipped ready for sea, including all armaments and ammunition, equipment, outfit, provisions and fresh water for crew, miscellaneous stores and implements and supplies of every description that are intended to be carried in war, including fuel and reserve feed water for engines and boilers. The calculation must be made in metric tons.20 years.,              Standard Calibre of guns Class or category of vessel           displacement82&amp; &amp;^&apos; : :)I0&apos;00OtonS ^mmimetres)Cruisers of over 7,000 tons. ^o^millimetres)Cruisers of under 7,000 tons (x^^mulimetres)Flotilla leaders..... .   ,Torpedo-boat destroyers .     1,200 tons 4--he iTorpedo-boats...... &apos;Submarines.........     600 tons ^f^^
Article 17. k)The Contracting States agree to assume the following obligations :(a) Not to use for warlike purposes warships which have been struck off the establishment of the fleet and replaced by new constructions (except in cases which may be specially provided for in supplementary technical Agreements) ;(6) Not to hand over or sell their warships to foreign countries if the latter can use them as warships supernumerary to the establishment laid down for each State by the present Convention ;(c) Not to build or allow to be built in their territories any warships exceeding any of the limits laid down in Article 16 of the present Convention ;(d) Not to cause new vessels to be constructed in foreign yards over and above the limit laid down for each Contracting State ;(e) Not to equip merchant vessels with any apparatus or appliance enabling such vessels to be used for warlike purposes.Article 18.The Contracting States agree to limit the quantity of shells and torpedoes as follows :(a) For guns of calibres from 8 to 12 inches (203.2 to 304.8 millimetres), 200 rounds each;(0) For guns of calibres from 4 to 7.9 inches (101.6 to 200.7 millimetres), 500 rounds each ;(c) For guns of calibres less than 4 inches (101.6 millimetres), 1,000 rounds each ;(d) For each torpedo-tube, two torpedoes.Article 19.All supplies of ammunition and torpedoes over and above the quantities specified in Article 18 must be destroyed.CHAPTER III. - AIR ARMAMENTS. Article 20.Within one year from the entry into force of the present Convention, all military dirigibles (lighter than air) shall be disarmed and placed in a condition precluding their utilisation for military purposes.Note.   The disarmament of aircraft belonging to the armed forces includes the removal of guns, machine-guns and special appliances for the discharge of bombs and other instruments of destruction.Article 21.In conformity with the Preamble to the present Convention, the Contracting States agree, when carrying into effect the reduction of air armaments, to divide all States into the following main groups :(a) Group E : States having more than 200 aeroplanes in service in their armed forces ; (6) Group F : States having from 100 to 200 aeroplanes in service in their armed forces ; (c)   Group G : States having fewer than 100 aeroplanes in service in their armed forces.States in Group E shall reduce their air forces by one-half; States in Group F by one-third, and States in Group G by one-quarter, with a simultaneous reduction of the engine-power of each aeroplane to 400 horse-power on the ground.Article 22.In addition to the standard laid down in Article 21, reserve machines, and engines for these machines, up to a number not exceeding 25 per cent of the total number of aeroplanes in service after their reduction, may be maintained in the establishment of the air forces.Article 23.All other machines, whether in service or in reserve, together with the engines for these machines, in excess of the limits laid down in Articles 21 and 22 of the present Convention shall be destroyed.
Article 24.When applying Articles 21, 22 and 23 of the present Convention, aeroplanes with engines of over 400 horse-power shall be the first to be destroyed.Article 25.All arming of civil aircraft and all fittings enabling them to be armed or to be utilised for war are prohibited.Article 26.With regard to the types of aeroplanes and their armaments, Article 6 of the present Convention shall apply. The armament of military air forces is included in the standards laid down in Article 10 of the present Convention.Article policy.All stocks of air bombs and other instruments of destruction intended to be discharged by aircraft shall be destroyed within three months of the entry into force of the present Convention. It shall henceforth be prohibited to manufacture or retain them in the army or in the reserve of the military air forces.Article 28.The effectives of the military air forces must be reduced in proportion to the decrease in the number of machines in service.Article 29.The precise maximum numbers of machines in service and in reserve, of the engines intended for their use, and of the military air force effectives, classified as officers, pilots and other personnel serving on board aircraft, which must not be exceeded by the Contracting States shall be fixed in conformity with Articles 21 and 28 of the present Convention in a supplementary Convention.To the latter shall be annexed the following tables :Table    I : Maximum armed air forces stationed in the home country ; Table   II : Maximum armed air forces stationed in each colony, dominion or other oversea possession ;Table III : Maximum of all armed air forces.Article 30.With a view to restricting the production of military aeroplanes and the trade therein the Contracting States agree to conclude, within three months from the entry into force of the present Convention, a supplementary Convention on the limitation to be imposed on the manufacture and trade in war aeroplanes in proportion to the legitimate requirements of the new effectives of the military air forces as fixed in the tables indicated in Article 29.CHAPTER IV. - CHEMICAL METHODS OF WARFARE.Article 31.All methods of and appliances for chemical aggression (all asphyxiating gases used for warlike purposes, as well as all appliances for their discharge, such as gas-projectors, pulverisers, balloons, flame-throwers and other devices) and for bacteriological warfare, whether in service with troops or in reserve or in process of manufacture, shall be destroyed within three months of the date of the entry into force of the present Convention.Article 32.The industrial undertakings engaged in or adapted for the production of the means of chemical aggression or bacteriological warfare indicated in Article 31 of the present Convention shall be converted to other uses within one year from the entry into force of the present Convention on the basis of an additional technical agreement.Article 33.The Contracting States undertake, within three months of the entry into force of the present Convention, to ratify the Protocol on the Prohibition of Chemical Warfare signed at Geneva in 1925.
Article 34.The total amounts of the armaments budgets calculated at their true values shall be reduced in proportion to the reduction of land forces in Groups A, B and C, of air forces in Groups E, F and G, and of naval forces as provided for in Articles 12 and 13 of the present Convention. The said reduction in budgets shall also apply to the items of expenditure on personnel (pay, clothing, victualling, quarters) and those relating to orders for implements of war and ammunition and to their upkeep.Article 35.No secret funds intended to disguise extraordinary expenditure on special preparations for war and the strengthening of armaments may be excluded in State budgets.In conformity with the above stipulation, all expenditure on the upkeep of the armed forces of each State shall be brought together in a single chapter of the State budget ; it shall be open to publicity in all respects.Article 36.The reduction of the armaments budgets shall be carried out as from the year 1929 ftari fiassu with the reduction of armed forces and of war material. As from 1930, the maximum figures of these budgets shall be fixed separately for each of the Contracting States. There-after, no increase shall be made in them.CHAPTER VI. - TIME-LIMITS FOR THE EXECUTION OF THE CONVENTION.Article 37.The reduction of land, naval and air armaments in conformity with Articles 2, 5, 11, 21, 22, 23 and 28 of the present Convention shall be carried out by the Contracting States in the course of two years, the first year being devoted to preparatory work and the second to the practical application of all the measures relating to the reduction of armaments.Article 38.All the other measures for the reduction of armaments shall be carried out within the periods provided for in the relevant articles of the present Convention (Articles 20, 27, 31, 32 and 36).CHAPTER VII. - CONTROL. Article 39.Within three months from the date of entry into force of the present Convention, a Permanent International Commission of Control shall be organised, with the following duties :(a) The supervision, control and general co-ordination of the measures relating to the application of the present Convention, and the notification to each State of breaches of the provisions of the present Convention ;(b) The preparation of an agreement concerning the pressure to be brought to bear upon States which may fail to carry out the provisions of the present Convention and of the supplementary Conventions and technical Arrangements completing it ;(c) The selection of the places, the procedure and the technical conditions for the destruction of material, and the preparation of all the necessary supplementary technical Agreements ;(d) The study of questions relating to further reductions of armaments and the preparation of international Agreements relating thereto ;(e) Communication to the Contracting States and the public of information con-cerning progress in the work of reducing armaments.Article 40.The Permanent International Commission of Control shall consist of an equal number of representatives of the legislative bodies and of the trade unions and other workers&apos; organisa-tions of all States participating in the present Convention.The Permanent International Commission of Control will later include representatives of international associations whose aim it is to establish pacific relations between States and which have pursued this aim with success, provided that these organisations express a wish to participate in the work of the Permanent International Commission of Control.CHAPTER V. - ARMAMENTS BUDGETS.
- 47 -i. 2 wArticle 41.The Permanent International Commission of Control shall be assisted by a Permanent International Committee of Experts, consisting of an equal number of military, naval, air and other experts belonging to all the States acceding to the present Convention.The Permanent International Committee of Experts shall act under the orders of the Permanent International Commission of Control.Article 42.The following may not be members of the Permanent International Commission of Control:(a) Professional soldiers and officials of Ministries of War, Marine and Military Aviation ;(b) Owners of and shareholders in military industrial undertakings, owners of and large shareholders in banking and commercial enterprises with interests in military undertakings and the traffic in arms, and higher employees in all these undertakings.Article 43.With a view to ensuring genuine control, the Permanent International Commission of Control shall be entitled to carry out investigations on the spot in the event of reasonable suspicion of a breach of the present Convention and of the subsequent supplementary Agree-ments on the reduction and limitation of armaments, and to appoint for this purpose special commissions of enquiry.Article 44.In enterprises for the production of war material or in enterprises capable of being utilised for the manufacture of armaments, a permanent labour control may be organised by the workers&apos; committees of the factories or by other organs of the trade unions operating in the respective enterprises, with a view to limiting the possibility of breaches of the correspond-ing articles of the present Convention.A similar control shall be set up in the various branches of the chemical industry, of which a list shall be drawn up by the Permanent International Commission of Control.Article 45.The Contracting States undertake to furnish the Permanent International Commission of Control, within the time-limits fixed by it, with full information as to the situation of their armed forces, in accordance with the list and tables prescribed by the present Convention and the subsequent supplementary Agreements on the reduction and limitation of armaments, as well as with particulars of the number of aeroplanes and dirigibles in civil aviation registered as such in the territory of each of the Contracting States.Article 46.The statutes of the Permanent International Commission of Control, the procedure for examining complaints concerning the non-observance of the obligations entered into for the reduction and limitation of armaments, the organisation of the procedure to be followed in local investigations, and the nature of labour control in regard to production (Article 44) shall be settled by means of a supplementary Convention within not more than three months from the date of the entry into force of the present Convention.CHAPTER VIII. - RATIFICATION AND APPLICATION OF THE CONVENTION.Article 47.The present Convention shall enter into force as from the date of its ratification, in conformity with the legislative practice of the Contracting States, by all the States in Groups A and B for the reduction of land armaments, as laid down in Article 1 of the present Convention, or in the first group for the reduction of naval armaments, as laid down in paragraph (a) of Article 12 of the present Convention.Article 48.All subsequent supplementary Conventions to be concluded in consequence of the present Convention shall be signed and ratified within not less than six months from the date of the entry into force of the latter.Article 49.The instruments of ratification shall be drawn up in five copies and shall be deposited in the capital of a State in each of the five continents.The ratification of the present Convention in conformity with the provisions laid down in Article 47 shall be notified to all the Contracting States by.............
Geneva, February 19th, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE SWEDISH DELEGATION.The speech made on February nth by the first delegate of Sweden contained, inter alia, proposals relating to questions now under discussion. These proposals may be summarised as follows:(1) The draft Convention drawn up by the Preparatory Commission will serve as a basis for the work of the Conference.(2)   As regards land forces the following recommendations are made:(a)   Limitation and reduction of effectives, applicable also to trained reserves;(6) Limitation and reduction of material by the direct method, supplemented by the budgetary method;(c) Total prohibition of tanks and mobile heavy artillery and possibly of other war appliances of a primarily offensive character, and hence the prohibition of all manufacture and training in connection with the use of these weapons.(3)   As regards air forces:(a) Total prohibition of military aviation, and manufacture, preparation and training in connection therewith;(b) Internationalisation or strict international control of civil aviation.(4) Thorough examination of the budgetary method, notably with a view to its application in case of fluctuations in the purchasing power of currencies.(5) Study of the possibility of restricting preparations for chemical and bacteriological warfare.(6) EstabUshment of a truly effective international supervision of the application of the proposed convention.The Swedish delegation reserves the right to submit, during the work of the Conference or its committees, as and when necessary, concrete proposals with regard to the above-mentioned problems and any other proposals it may think useful.Official No.: Conf. D. 84.Geneva, February 19th, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE NETHERLANDS DELEGATION.The speech made by the first delegate of the Netherlands on February 15th contained the following suggestions:(1) The draft Convention drawn up by the Preparatory Commission will serve as a basis for the Conference^ work.(2) Limitation and reduction must be applied to the whole of the armed forces immediately mobilisable.   Consequently they must embrace:(a) Trained reserves, in the first instance by reducing the contingent;(b) The material of the land forces, by the direct method.(3) Complete publicity of armaments in accordance with Article 8 of the Covenant, particularly publicity on land, naval and air material.(4)   Prohibition of arms of a specially offensive or exceptionally destructive character.(5) Absolute prohibition of the use of poisonous and harmful gases and of any preparation for chemical warfare.(6) Prohibition of the use of destructive war appliances against the civil population, particularly:(a) Prohibition of air bombardment;(b) Prohibition of the use of automatic contact mines in the open sea.
Geneva, February 19th, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE DELEGATION OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.For the convenience of the Bureau, the delegation of the United States is submitting the suggestions contained in the speech of the Acting Chief Delegate on February 9th, as was stated at that time. These suggestions are not exclusive; nor do they purport to be an all-comprehensive plan. The points enumerated are merely intended to aid in carrying on the purposes of this Conference.(1) The delegation of the United States advocates consideration of the draft Convention as containing the outline of a convenient basis for discussion, while expressing its entire willingness to give full consideration to any supplementary proposals calculated to advance the ends we all seek.(2) The delegation of the United States suggests the possibility of prolonging the existing naval agreements concluded at Washington and London as soon as they are completed by the adherence of France and Italy.(3) The delegation of the United States advocates proportional reductions from the figures laid down in the Washington and London Agreements on naval tonnage as soon as all parties to the Washington Agreement have entered this frame-work.(4)   The delegation of the United States advocates the total abolition of submarines.(5) The delegation of the United States will join in formulating the most effective measures to protect civilian populations against aerial bombing.(6) The delegation of the United States advocates the total abolition of lethal gases and bacteriological warfare.(7) The delegation of the United States advocates the computation of the numbers of the armed forces on the basis of the effectives necessary for the maintenance of internal order plus some suitable contingent for defence. The former are obviously impossible of reduction; the latter is a question of relativity.Note.   The only criterion for such a computation at present existing is to be found in the military forces maintained by the Central Powers in accordance with the treaties of peace, which specify that they were to be exclusively employed in the maintenance of order and policing of frontiers. This would indicate that a study of the ratio of the number of effectives in these countries to the population and territory would give some rough estimate of the number which world opinion has already agreed upon as essential for the purpose of order; and indicate, when applied to other nations, that the remaining existing forces were destined at least for defence, if not for possible aggression, and in the categories for defence and attack, since these numbers must at present be based on comparisons with the similar forces of other States and are thus relative. Therefore stringent reduction may be justifiably sought in accordance with the purpose for which this Conference was called.(8) The delegation of the United States agrees in advocating special restrictions for tanks and heavy mobile guns as arms of peculiarly aggressive character.(9) The delegation of the United States is prepared to consider a limitation of expenditure on material as a complementary method to direct limitation in that it may prove useful to prevent a qualitative race if and when quantitative limitation has been made effective.Official No.: Conf. D. 86.Geneva, February 19th, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE SWISS DELEGATION.In reply to the invitation of the President of the Conference, and in order to facilitate the work of co-ordination, the Swiss delegation has the honour to draw attention below to the concrete suggestions in regard to technical problems put forward by M. Motta in his speech of February 16th.
i. The draft Convention of the Preparatory Commission to be taken as a basis opUD discussion.2.   The present level of armaments to be taken in all cases as the point of departure, and not to be exceeded in the future.3. The system of budgetary limitation to be adopted as a general method, together with direct limitation for certain categories of material, the mode of application of these two methods to land, sea and air armaments being reserved.4.   Civil aviation to be under international control.5.   The fullest publicity to be adopted in regard to armaments.6.   Arms of an essentially aggressive character to be prohibited in pursuance of the Treaty for the Renunciation of War e.g., heavy artillery, tanks and bombing aeroplanes.7.   Certain forms of warfare to be prohibited, viz.:(a) All forms, without exception, of chemical and bacteriological warfare;(b) Bombardment from the air;(c) Incendiary bombs.8.   Agreements to be concluded with regard to the manufacture, whether private or governmental, of arms, munitions and material of war, and to the trade therein.9. A Permanent Disarmament Commission to be set up with the specific object of supervising the execution of the Convention to be concluded,[Jand making the necessary preparations for future disarmament conferences.The above suggestions are obviously not limitative. The Swiss delegation accordingly reserves the right to define their purport or to put forward new suggestions, whether in regard to methods of limitation and prohibitions or in regard to agreements for the settlement of international disputes or generally for the consolidation of the foundations of peace.Official No.: Conf. D. 88.Geneva, February 19th, 1932.PROPOSALS OF THE CHINESE DELEGATION.In view of the fact that the draft Convention for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments has left untouched certain fundamental principles which are essential to the success of the Conference, and in order that certain proposals, put forward by the various delegations at the Preparatory Commission, looking to the solution of some of the most important but difficult problems, may obtain a fair hearing, the Chinese Delegation has the honour to make the following proposals:I. The scale of armaments on land and sea and in the air for each country shall be determinedby:A. Size of the territory,B. Number of population,C. Length and nature of land frontier and coast-line,D. Facility of communications on land and sea and in the air,E. Degree of security against external aggression,F. National resources.II. The existing systems and measures calculated to induce or encourage citizens to take up warlike pursuit and to foster a warlike spirit among them, being conducive to the creation of militarism, shall be abolished.III. The principle of national armament on land and sea and in the air shall be solely for the purpose of carrying out defensive measures at the land frontiers or on the sea coast and not for the purpose of invading and attacking another country. For this reason, the aggressive arms such as bombing aeroplanes, tanks, heavy artillery of a certain calibre, aircraft-carriers, submarines and battleships shall be abolished.
Official No.: Conf. D. 89. Geneva, February 19th, 1932.PROPOSALS PUT FORWARD BY THE NORWEGIAN DELEGATION.1. Extensive reduction of armaments. Acceptance of the draft Convention of the Preparatory Commission as a basis of discussion, subject to such proposals as may subsequently be made for its improvement.2. Limitation of aggregate expenditure as well as expenditure under particular chapters of military budgets, including expenditure on aviation. Direct limitation of effectives and material wherever practicable.3. Prohibition of arms of a specifically offensive character, including arms which are specially dangerous to civilian populations: prohibition of their manufacture and use and of all training with a view to their use.4. Establishment of supervision on as strict and effective lines as possible of the execution of obligations assumed under the Disarmament Convention, including supervision of both private and governmental manufacture of arms and of the trade in arms.5. Establishment of a Permanent Disarmament Commission to supervise the armaments of the several States, and to make preparations for further progressive disarmament.Official No.: Conf. D. 90.Geneva, February 20th, 1932.SUGGESTIONS CONTAINED IN THE SPEECH OF THE FIRST DANISH DELEGATE.1. Prohibition, as proposed by a number of other delegations, of certain weapons of a specifically aggressive character, in view of the fact that these weapons are already prohibited by the Peace Treaties. Prohibition of all manufacture of such weapons and all preparation and training with a view to their use.2. (a) Total prohibition of military aviation and of the manufacture and preparation of military aircraft or training with a view to its use.(b) Internationalisation or rigorous international supervision of civil aviation.3. A percentage to be fixed to serve as a general guide for the reduction in the course of three years of the existing level of armaments of countries which are not at present tied in the matter of armaments, subject to adjustments in particular cases. Reduction of military expenditure in a proportion corresponding to the reduction in the general level of armaments.4. Establishment of a Permanent General Control Commission, consisting of representatives of all the States signing the Disarmament Convention.5. Prohibition of chemical and bacteriological warfare and of all preparation, manufacture or training in the use of such weapons.Organisation of supervision of this prohibition by the establishment of an international cartel of manufacturers of chemical products under the supervision of the Control Commission.6. Preparation by a permanent organisation composed of representatives of all the signatory States of a programme for the reduction of armaments by stages: the details to be fixed by subsequent conferences, and reduction to be continued under the programme until the principles which form the foundation of Article 8 of the Covenant have been carried out in their entirety.7. Establishment and organisation of an international police consisting of an air fleet constantly available for intervention in cases of the violation of international obligations. Rules to be made in regard to the authority which will have the disposal of this international police.8. Steps to be taken to accelerate the general adoption of the system of justice organised by the League of Nations and of the obligation to have recourse only to pacific methods.9. Precise rules to be drawn up in regard to the operation of the sanctions for Which the Covenant provides.
Geneva, February 20th, 1932.SUGGESTIONS CONTAINED IN THE STATEMENT OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK DELEGATION MADE ON FEBRUARY 12th, 1932.1. The Czechoslovak Government accepts as a basis of discussion the draft Convention established by the Preparatory Commission and the principles set forth therein.2. The Czechoslovak Government is of opinion that the future Convention should lay down forthwith the principle of a definite and explicit limitation of armaments.3. It is prepared to adopt supervision of effectives, armaments and the manufacture of, and trade in, arms in a more complete, and effective manner than that proposed in the draft Convention or than that which has in certain cases been in operation up to the present.4. It would favour the establishment of a more complete system for the prohibition of chemical and bacteriological warfare, and is prepared to extend this prohibition to other means of offensive warfare, particularly the bombardment from the air of the civil population, of cities, and particularly of the capitals of countries at war.5.   It is convinced that this last provision should be supplemented by a system of penalties.6. The Czechoslovak delegation regards the French proposals as of great importance, and states that it is prepared to accept them immediately.7. The Czechoslovak Government is of opinion that the Convention might forthwith embody and apply the second fundamental principle of all action for genuine disarmament by stages, i.e., the reduction of armaments.At. the same time, it reasserts its belief in the necessity for a policy of peace and a progressive systematic and scientific organisation of peace with a view to strengthening the authority and - augmenting the powers of the Council of the League.Official No.: Conf. D. 92.Geneva, February 20th, 1932.PROPOSALS BY THE ARGENTINE DELEGATION.In compliance with the President of the Conference^ wish that the delegations which have put forward suggestions during the general discussion should submit them in a definite form, so as to facilitate their consideration, the Argentine Delegation begs to submit the following proposals:1.  Capital Ships.The Argentine Republic proposes that countries not signatories of the Washington and London Treaties should undertake not to build or acquire capital ships of over 10,000 tons (10,160 metric tons), considering such vessels to be of a specifically aggressive type.This proposal refers to the &quot; Capital Ship &quot; type of vessel defined in Part 4, Chapter II, of the Washington Treaty as follows:&quot; A capital ship, in the case of ships hereafter built, is defined as a vessel of war, not an aircraft-carrier, whose displacement exceeds 10,000 tons (10,160 metric tons) standard displacement, or which carries a gun with a calibre exceeding 8 in. (203 mm.).&quot;The contents of the treaty to be concluded, its form and term of validity, will be decided during the discussions on the proposal. It is already obvious, however, that the proposed agree-ment will form a useful and, indeed, essential supplement to the two international treaties which
Official No.: Conf. D. 94.Geneva, February 22nd, 1932.SUGGESTIONS BY THE JAPANESE DELEGATION.1.   Adoption of the draft Convention as the basis of discussion.2. Assurances to be provided for with a view to safeguarding each contracting party from menaces caused by the armaments of one or more States not party to the treaty or by the non-observance of treaty obligations on the part of one or more of the contracting parties.3. Limitation and reduction of land and air armaments to be effected in such manner as to leave room for rectification of apparent defects in elements.4. Prohibition of air bombardment of cities and towns and other methods of attack on civil populations.5.   Prohibition of chemical and bacteriological warfare.6.   Reduction in the unit size of capital ships and the calibre of their guns.7.   Reduction in the tonnage allotted by the existing treaties of aircraft carriers.8. Prohibition of the fitting of aircraft-landing platforms or decks on naval vessels other than aircraft carriers.9. Total abolition of aircraft carriers, provided that agreement is reached on the prohibition indicated in paragraph 8.10.   Limitation of arms and aircraft equipment on merchant vessels.^nave eliminated the danger of naval competition between the countries possessing the largest naval forces. The Argentine Delegation proposes that the other countries, whether they own capital ships or not, should complete this agreement, which would extend to all States the new naval policy of refraining henceforth from building vessels of excessive tonnage. A decisive initial step will thus have been taken towards abolishing the competition in armaments.2.  Foodstuffs.The Argentine Delegation proposes that an international agreement be concluded in which the signatory States shall declare that:(a)   The following foodstuffs shall not be regarded as contraband of war:Cereals; Rice;Flour and bakers&apos; wares;Fresh and preserved meat of all kinds;Milk in all its forms and dairy produce;Eggs;Sugar;Fresh or preserved fish of all kinds;Fresh or preserved vegetables;Fresh and preserved fruits;Potatoes;Coffee;Tea;Cocoa;(6) Neutral vessels carrying exclusively the foodstuffs enumerated in the foregoing article shall have the right of free transit in case of war, and may only be inspected for the purpose of ascertaining whether the above provisions have been complied with.(c) This agreement shall apply to the foodstuffs mentioned in paragraph (a) and to the vessels referred to in paragraph \b), always provided that such foodstuffs or such vessels come from, or are proceeding to, the States signatories of the agreement.(d) The stipulations of this agreement shall not operate in the case of the application of the sanctions provided for under Article 16 of the Covenant of the League of Nations.
Geneva, February 22nd, 1932. PROPOSALS BY THE UNITED KINGDOM DELEGATION.The United Kingdom Delegation, while of opinion that the draft Convention provides the best groundwork on which to proceed, suggests that special attention should be directed to such prohibitions or limitations as will weaken the attack and so remove temptation for aggression, and to methods of warfare which are specially liable to cause injury to non-combatants. In particular it suggests (without attempting to draw up anything in the nature of an exhaustive list) that the following questions should be closely studied, with a view to the adoption of such proposals as may seem practicable:1.   The most practicable course for limiting the number of effectives;2.   The prohibition of mobile land guns above a certain calibre;3.   The abolition (and prohibition) of submarines as a humanitarian measure;4.   Consideration of the most practical method of reducing the size of men-of-war and the maximum calibre of guns carried by them;5.   The practical examination of the whole problem of bombing from the air in its widest possible form.The United Kingdom Delegation attaches great importance to the maintenance of the provisions of the draft Convention relating to gas and bacteriological warfare, and of those providing for the establishment of a Permanent Disarmament Commission.Official No.. Conf. D. 97.Geneva, February 24th, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE HEJAZ DELEGATION.The Government of the Hejaz and Nejd and its Dependencies, which relies for its guidance on the religion of Islam with its fundamental principles of universal peace and brotherly love, while naturally urging total and absolute disarmament and strongly advocating the complete prohibition of aggressive war, welcomes every attempt to bring humanity nearer to this goal, and supports every proposal likely to save mankind from the scourge of war, earnestly hoping that this Conference will achieve a substantial measure of success in that direction. It is encouraged in this hope by the earnest and sincere spirit of the different Governments of the world, so eloquently expressed by their worthy representatives here, and by the unanimity with which the aims and objects of this Conference are enthusiastically supported by the ranlc and file of every nation. It is with pleasure, therefore, that the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd and its Dependencies signifies its assent to the proposals put forward by so many delegates calling on the Conference to bring about:1.   The prohibition of poison gas and all bacteriological war materials; 2.   The prohibition of all military aviation;3.   The prohibition of all war materials of aggressive character on land and sea;4.   The reduction and limitation of all legitimate armaments to the absolute minimum required for national safety.

</content>
</cab>
