<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/229/0 images: 253-254</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1932.SECRET.-CP. 117 (32). Copy No.......Xf..CABINET.Reports by Local Governments on the Political Situation in India.I circulate for the information of my colleagues the latest weekly reports from the Local Governments in India.S. H.India Office, 30th March 1932.Government of India.Delhi reports little change. At the Muslim Conference at Lahore consideration of boycott resolution was deferred for three months in view of the statement of His Majesty&apos;s Government of 19th March. Feeling in favour of boycott was, however, fairly strong, and atmosphere generally was one of uncertainty and suspicion regarding the treatment of Muslim claims. This restlessness, with attendant risks, is likely to continue until the matter is settled, but the statement of 19th and the Lahore Conference have very definitely improved the immediate situation at a critical stage, and have given much, though not permanent, relief from the dangers which threatened to assume acute form.2. Civil disobedience is now definitely on the down grade and, in the absence of unforeseen developments, the improvement, should be progressive. Significant features are the continued decline in convictions in several Provinces, the lack of agitation in rural areas and the failure of Congress to develop new lines. Each week that passes withoxit serious reactions in the North-West Frontier Province increases the prospects of successful launching of dyarchy and the consequent diversion of the interests of the people from subversive to constitutional activities. Prospects there are now distinctly favourable.Bombay.The situation generally is satisfactory. Telegraph wires have been again cut and timber topped culvert burnt in Kanara district, where, however, principal agitator avoiding arrest and secretly organising no-tax campaign has been arrested. Non-payment of land revenue campaign in Bardoli and Valod Mahal (Surat district) is reported to have collapsed and practically all arrears have been paid up. There has been a slight revival of picketing of foreign cloth shops in Karachi. In Bombay city, at conference held by Finance Member, the leading cotton merchants and associations expressed themselves as opposed to hartals in the markets. It is too early to give an opinion on the result. Twenty-six secret organisers of Congress activities who were recently arrested were convicted and sentenced. Picketing continues, but on a reduced scale. Action under Ordinance 2. Section 3: arrests 14, total under detention 184. Section 4 : orders issued 41, total in force 921. Section 21 : Convictions during week 36.Bengal.There has been a general improvement in the situation and a marked decrease in processions and meetings. The movement is now largely confined to homeless boys and low-class women. Section 3, arrests 6. Section 4, orders issued 190. Convictions under ordinary law and Ordinances, 165 against 376 in previous week.Madras.There is nothing new to report. Very little civil disobedience activity, except for sporadic picketing.796      60   3.32
V ...... ......      2      ...... &quot;     . V:    i.North-West Frontier Province.There has been no serious agitation in the Peshawar district during the week^ and no change in other districts. Section 3: arrests, nil; total detained, 2. Section 4: orders during the week, 46; total orders in force, 1,331. The trans-frontier situation shows some improvement. Threats to the Nawab of Dir territory in Jandol continue and some fighting has taken place, but he is confident that he can control the situation and no further air action has been necessary. Agitators continue their efforts to raise the Upper Mohmand, and although they are having no-success at present, situation still requires careful watching.United Provinces.The situation is practically unchanged. A small crowd attempting to celebrate Bhagat Singh Day at Allahabad on 23rd March was dispersed by sowars without casualties. No order under section 3. Eighteen orders under section 4 of Emergency Powers Ordinance. One conviction for defying order under section 4. Total convictions during week under Ordinances, 88 ; under ordinary law, 222 ; total up to date, 7,583; releases, 1,402.Bihar and Orissa.The Province is quiet. There have been no new developments. No fresh orders and no prosecutions under section 4, Emergency Powers Ordinance. Total convictions reported up to 18th March, 5,102.Central Provinces.The Betul district reports a small outbreak of forest satyagraha. Dictator has been arrested and the sitimtion is reported satisfactory. Elsewhere there has been nothing of interest.   Prosecutions, 91) ; convictions, 89.   No extension of Ordinances.Punjab.The Province continues quiet. Trade and communal situation are unchanged.. Political arrests : under ordinary law, 26; under Ordinance, 20. Totals to date 485 and 723, respectively. Detenus under -section 3 now 4. Four fresh orders under section 4.   Total to date 60.   Total prosecutions for infraction of such orders, 12.Assam.There have been no developments during the past week. The improvement in the situation is maintained.Burma.There has been no attempt at civil disobedience movement. No arrests or other-action under Ordinances.Ajmer Merwara.The situation is quiet.   Six arrests under ordinary law.From the Eesident, Mysore.Coorg continues satisfactory, and there is nothing to report. Bangalore.   Nothing to report.

</content>
</cab>
