<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/229/0 images: 316-318</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1932.d secret. . Copy No.    -CP. 127 (32).CABINET.Disarmament Conference, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR.MY colleagues will remember that when the question of Disarmament was before the Cabinet on the 6th April, I entered a caveat to the effect that I must reserve my opinion on a point arising out of a Memorandum by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (D.C. (M) 32 (13) ) until I had seen the draft Minutes of the Disarmament Committee. I have now seen the Minutes and Conclusions, of which Conclusions (c), (d) and (/) bear on the question of air bombing.Of these Conclusions, (c) and (/) record the general support of the Committee to the Memorandum of the Chief of the Imperial General Staff referred to above, and to an Admiralty Memorandum D.C. (M) 32 (14), both of which are favourable to the abolition of air bombing.Taking these two Conclusions together. I must point out to my colleagues that I feel most strongly that, so far as the recommendations concern air bombing, the Committee have acted on information which was incomplete and consequently misleading, and I am gravely concerned at the possible effects upon vital defence interests both at home and abroad. The Cabinet ought clearly not to accept these recommendations without giving the most earnest consideration to the views of the Air Ministry, who speak on this matter with a degree of authority and knowledge which no other Department can claim to possess.Conclusions (c) and (/) are in general terms, but in Conclusion (d) the Committee recommend that we should favour the concrete proposal of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to prohibit the dropping of bombs by one State on the territory or shipping of another Sovereign State.Before the Cabinet comes to a decision on this Conclusion, I must point out to my colleagues the very serious consequences of its adoption upon our air defence interests : (i) The abolition of the bombing squadrons at present comprised in our air defence forces must follow the formal outlawry of their employment; nor could we maintain at home a permanent defensive force of fighting aircraft to meet a form of attack the menace of which we had (on paper) succeeded in removing. If we did so, we should be openly discrediting the reliability of the solemn international agreement on which the outlawry of bombing would be based. Nevertheless, there is complete agreement on all sides (this point is specially emphasised by the C.I.G.S.) that an undertaking to abstain from the bombing of sovereign States would not prevent the resumption of air bombing during war. What would our position be with regard to the defence of London? We should have to rely purely on the small air forces maintained for ancillary duties with the army, which might number 150 their present total is 60. Against this, the French would muster some 1,021, and this number assumes that they, too, would disband all their present bombing squadrons.(ii) As regards civil aircraft capable of immediate conversion to military purposes on the outbreak of wrar, we should be in a still worse position. France has at present about eight times as many regular civil aircraft transport as we have. This discrepancy, owing to geographical factors, is likely to be maintained, and, as civil aviation expands, to increase.[6850]
Our relative positions would be approximately as follows without allowing for increases in civil aircraft:  ^GreatBritain.     France.Regular aircraft        ... ... ...   . 150 1.021Civil aircraft ... ... ...&quot;        ...        35 269Total ... ... ...      185 1.290We should consequently be outnumbered by 7 to 1.Moreover, the aircraft industries of France and Great Britain would be roughly proportionate to their peace-time strength, so that the French industry must have several times the capacity of ours at the outbreak of war. So far from true is it, therefore, that we could contemplate the outbreak of threat of war with the assurance that &quot; we should all start at scratch.&quot;But this is not all.The complete ineffectiveness of the proposal which brings to life an alternative force of equal destructive power, the employment of which would not be possible if regular forces were in being to counter it, and which adds the horrors of indiscriminate bombing in untrained hands can be still more clearly illustrated by the following : The machines remaining to France will be capable of launching 210 tons of bombs on London on the outbreak of war a fraction less than their regular forces are capable of at the present time, but with this difference. London will be without defence, for the Home Defence Fighters will no longer exist and our counter in the form of bombing will be on such a minor scale as to be practically negligible. Further, the initial scale of 210 tons a day would not be subject to much reduction through counter-attacks and after a few days the total weight of bombs dropped on London would be very much greater than it could be with equal regular forces on both sides.I can come to no other conclusion than that being hopelessly outnumbered from the start, and having no prospect but to fall further behind, we should be forced to sue for peace.(iii) For these reasons my service advisers have warned me that the acceptance of the &quot;abolition of bombing of sovereign States&quot; and its imple-mentation in terms of organisation of our air forces would create a disparity of military air forces as between ourselves and France, which would be as marked as that which existed before we started creating the Home Defence Force in 1923  a condition which was generally regarded as wholly unacceptable. The proposal is in short, and in effect, one of unilateral disarmament on our part and on a most drastic scale.2. Turning to the prohibition of bombing against shipping, what would be the position of Singapore or Hong Kong on the outbreak of war with Japan ? The Committee of Imperial Defence have agreed that the Japanese would be likely to use the whole strength of their Navy, including capital ships, for the destruction of Singapore. The reason that such a scale of attack has been admitted is due to the fact that the British Navy cannot arrive in the area for thirty-eight days. Are we then to deny ourselves the use of this powerful air weapon the one and only reinforcement possible to assist in crippling and destroying this hostile fleet, and so undoubtedly lose our Far Eastern Base ?Again, there are our coastal towns, not only in the United Kingdom but all over the world, liable to bombardment from the SGcl, clS they were in actual fact bombarded though fortunately on a small scale in the late war. Due to the reduction in the Navy, these towns are more open to attack than ever before. You cannot have gun defences everywhere. Are we to forsake the only weapon apart from the Navy that, owing to its immense mobility, can offer them protection ?3. I fully realise how difficult it may be to adopt a negative attitude to proposals such as these at the Disarmament Conference, and I do not wish my remarks to be purely destructive in character. I believe intensely that our soundest method of approach to this jn-oblem of air disarmament is by way of quantitative disarmament, and this is the only sound method by which we can maintain security; but in view of the desirability of the British Government adopting a constructive policy, I suggest, as a measure of  &quot;qualitative&quot;
-disarmament, that His Majesty&apos;s Government should instruct the British Delegation to accept, if such an offer appears expedient, the prohibition of the heavy type of bomber. That is a type of aircraft which (1) has the greatest bomb-carrying capacity, (2) unlike the medium bombing aircraft, is to some extent distinguishable in size and type from aircraft employed for reconnaissance and other duties.The logic and reason of this concession are open to criticism, but on political grounds it might have advantages which could be regarded as justifying it. Moreover, it is a concession which would to some extent be in line with the policy advocated by the French of denying to national air forces the right of maintaining the heaviest type of bombing aircraft.Air Ministry, April 8, 1932.L.\*m iiMfcuaiiiniHllTMfUHIlliin

</content>
</cab>
