<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/18/0 images: 248-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ftfIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE   PROPERTY   OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MA.IESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  November 1950SECRETCM. (50)70th conclusions copy No. cabinet 70 (50)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 2nd November, 1950, at 9 45 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C R. Attleb, MThe Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Town and country planning.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland..P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,State for the home the Right hon secretary of department.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlenson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also present:The Right Hon. P. j. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 4).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 4).Sir William(Item 4).The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 4).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-3).Strang, Foreign OfficeSecretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. O. C. Morland.
CABINET 70 (50)contents minute no. Subject page 1     Defence ...     ...     ...     ...     ... ...1172     Parliament...      ...      ......      ...      ...      ...      ...    117Business in the House of Commons. &apos;3     Permanent Economic Powers ...      ...      .........    1174     Economic Affairs.....................    118Man-power.Production.Building.External Trade.Balance of Payments.Prices.Wages.European Recovery Programme.Raw Material Shortages.Increased Cost of Living.Coal-mining Industry.
Defence.(previous reference:CM. (50) 55thConclusions,Minute 3.) &apos;1. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the PrimeMinister (CP. (50) 246) on the Finance of Defence. There had alsobeen circulated to the Cabinet a memorandum on this subject whichhad been submitted to the Defence Committee by the foreign secretary and the Chancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (50) 247), and amemorandum which the Minister of Defence had submitted to theDefence Committee on the size and shape of the Armed Forces in1951-54 (CP. (50) 248).The Prime Minister suggested that it would be more conveninentif the Cabinefs consideration of these papers could be deferred toa later meeting at which the Foreign Secretary and the Minister ofDefence could be present. In reply to a question, he made it clear that nothing which had passed in the recent meeting at Washington of theDefence Ministers of the North Atlantic Treaty Powers had com-mitted the United Kingdom Government to any particular figure ofdefence expenditure during the next three years.The Cabinet-Agreed to defer until a later meeting their consideration of cp. (50) 246, 247 and 248.Parliament. 2.  The Cabinet discussed the arrangements for handling theBusiness in the concluding stages of the Debate on the Address.House of It was agreed that in the debate on the Amendment on HousingCommons.      on 6th November the Government spokesmen should be the Ministerof Health and the Secretary of State for Scotland.The Amendment on general economic problems, which was tobe debated on 7th November, was not confined to the question ofeconomic controls, but referred also to the nationalisation of steel and road haulage. The Cabinet agreed that the Minister of Town and country Planning should be one of the Government spokesmen inthis debate; and invited the Prime Minister to consider whether thesecond Government spokesman should be the Lord President or thePresident of the Board of Trade.The Cabinet were informed of the other business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Permanent 3.  In their consideration of forthcoming business in ParliamentEconomic t the Cabinet had a brief discussion on the content of the EconomicPowers.    * Planning and Full Employment Bill. Some of the current criticism of(Previous&apos; this measure was based on the assumption that it would makeReference: permanent the war-time powers to direct labour.   If it was not in. (50) 69th fact intended that powers of labour control should be included in theConclusions, Bill, there was much to be said for disarming this criticism by makingMinute 5.) an early statement to that effect.In discussion there was general agreement that powers of labourcontrol should not be included in this Bill; and that, if at any timethe Government found it necessary to seek such powers, they should do so in separate legislation.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the Economic Planning and Fuli employment bill should not include powers of labour control.(2) Authorised the Lord Chancellor to make a statement to that effect in the debate in the House of Lords that afternoon.
economic affairs.(previous reference:CM. (50) 51stConclusions,Minute 4.)Man-power.Production.Building.External Trade.Balance ofPayments.Prices.Wages.EuropeanRecoveryProgramme.4. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Chancellor of theExchequer (CP. (50) 245) covering a report on the economic situation.In a general discussion of the report the following points weremade:  The labour supply situation was satisfactory except for thecontinued fall in the numbers employed in coal-mining. It wassuggested that, as increased mechanisation would involve a continuingdecline in the number of coal-face workers in proportion to other workers, the National Coal Board should consider means of providing the latter with incentives to increased productivity.The continued increase in production was satisfactory, but herealso coal was lagging behind the rest of the economy. The high rateof output of motor cars, and the large proportion exported, were particularly notable, though future diversion of the motor car industryto rearmament might prevent a further large increase in production.Production in the engineering industries generally was also threatened by shortages of raw materials: zinc and sheet&apos; and strip steel were already scarce; a shortage of aluminium was likely to develop in1951; and, unless we could secure scrap from Germany, supplies ofgeneral steel would be insufficient to meet requirements.The total value of building and civil engineering work in thefirst half of 1950 was nearly 6 per cent, above the figure for the&quot;corresponding period of 1949. As costs had been stable, nearly all of this represented an increase in the amount of work done.There would probably be an overall balance in visible tradeduring the last quarter of the year, but the present volume of imports was abnormally low and stocks were declining, so that the balancewas unlikely to be maintained Exports had continued to increase and the level of 175 per cent, of 1938 exports might be reached very shortly.It was pointed out that imports would rise substanially onaccount of stockpiling, and that in the course of the next year exports would be increasingly affected by the rearmament programme.The inflow of gold and dollars was continuing, stimulated byrumours of sterling revaluation, and the reserves at the end of the yearmight be startlingly high. It would be necessary to emphasise, in public statements, the need to consider our reserves and liabilities inconjunction. The balance of payments with the dollar area continuedto improve, and that with the sterling area to deteriorate.There was as yet no sign of slackening in the rate of increase of import prices. Discussions had taken place in Washington, and were now taking place in the Organisation for European economic co-operation, on measures to check the rise in prices of raw materials.Wool prices Were likely to rise still further, with a serious effect onthe cost-of-living index. The rate of increase had been as great inrespect of imports from the sterling area as from dollar sources.Retail prices had remained remarkably stable, but it was likely that there would be a rise of not less than four or five points in thecost-of-living index during the. first half of 1951. There would be some time-lag before the effect of wage increases was fully reflected in the index.The period of wage stability was now ending, and a general increase on about the same scale as that of 1946 must be expected.This might represent an average increase of between Is. and 10s. aweek. Owing to the recent policy of stabilisation, these increases would tend to be grudgingly accepted and regarded as overdue; andthere was risk of pressure for a further round of increases after thecurrent round was completed. The point was made that if full employment were maintained, wages could continue to riseindefinitely, with ultimate damage to our export trade.The first settlement under the European Payments Union had shown a higher United Kingdom surplus than had been expected, andwe were likely shortly to pass the point up to which our surplus was transferred to other members of the Union. Germany was heavily in
deficit through excessive imports, and she must be made aware thatshe could not count on further external assistance.The termination of Marshall Aid to the United Kingdom was now under discussion with the Economic Co-operation Administra-tion. There was now no United States intention to make an embarrassing unilateral announcement, but we must be prepared toreceive no further aid under the European Recovery Programme afterthe current half-year.Material The President of the Board of Trade said that shortages of essential raw materials were threatening our production over a wide field. The scarcity of cotton, wood-pulp and sulphur was already being felt. The United States had reduced her exports of cottonwithout consultation with us and without imposing any restriction on domestic use. Representations were being made against this action and against the inequitable allocation of the reduced supplies betweenthe purchasing countries.Care would be needed in explaining to the public the effects ofthe increase in the cost of living. There had been much criticism ofthe cost-of-living index: the true position was that, while the indexaccurately reflected the increased prices, the public were now buyinga wider range of goods and disproportionate attention was attracted by sharp increases in the prices of some household goods,e.g., blankets, which, since they had to be renewed only at longintervals, did not figure largely in the index.mining A discussion followed on wages, man-power and production in theitry. coal-mining industry. It was agreed that a full discussion of these problems should be deferred until a meeting in the following week atwhich the Cabinet were to consider reports from the production committee on the short-term coal supply position, with particular reference to the reduction in exports, and the prospective levei ofproduction in the longer term. The Minister of Fuel and power should also submit for consideration at that meeting a report on thewages position in the industry.The Cabinet (1) Took note of CP. (50) 245 and of the points made in thediscussion.(2) Invited the Minister of Fuel and Power to submit, forconsideration at a meeting in the following week, a reporton wages in the coal-mining industry.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,2nd November, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
