<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 23-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET.                                                   COPY NO.    &apos;CP. 252 (32).                         CABINET.                      SINGAPORE NAVAL BASE.           Memorandum &quot;by the First Lord of the Admiralty.               The Cabinet have now &quot;before them the  recommendations      t/f the Committee of Imperial Defence (CP.  238(52)) on the      report of the Coast Defence Committee on the subject of the  fixed      defences of Singapore.               The C.I.D., which was dealing exclusively with the      question of defences an-d accordingly confined its recommendations      to that side of the question of Singapore,  r^ecommended, with      representatives of the Dominions present, that,  contrary to      the decision made at the Imperial Conference of 1930, we should      proceed now with the first stage of the Singapore defences.               On the subject of the Base itself the Imperial      Conference of 1930 recommended the continuation of the      main contract for the wharves and graving dock but that      expenditure, for completing the equipment of the docks and      the rest of the details of the &quot;truncated&quot;  scheme should,      similarly to the defence works, be deferred, for five years.               The modification of the 1930 decision in regard      to the defences invites reconsideration of the position in      regard to the Base.               While the financial situation may not at      present justify going ahead fully with the &quot;truncated&quot;      scheme, I think the same reasons which govern the decision      as to the defences must be held to justify departure in      principle from the 1930 decision as to the Base.                              1.
            The recommendation as to the defences is foundedupon the impossibility of any longer basing policy upon the&quot;Ten Years No YJar&quot; rule, coupled with the ominous characterof recent events in the Par East,   It must be borne in mind that the essence of our naval strategy in the Par Eastrests on the arrival of our main fleet at Singapore at theearliest possible moment and that for a fleet of this character to operate in Eastern waters the Naval Base at singapore is a vital necessity.            The position under the 1930 ruling is that on completion of the Jackson contract 7fe shall have at Singapore,apart from the Floating Dock, little more than a hole in the earth, the graving dock being incyaparble&quot;of use untilprovision Is made for a caisson, dock pumping plant, power station, etc;  and the wharves being of little or no useowing to lack of power, cranes, capstans, etc.            I need not strees the most unsatisfactory natureof this state of affairs from the defence point of view and its incompatibility with the attitude which the C.I.D.have adopted as to the Par Eastern situations   I must, however,draw attention to the fact that there is evidence alreadythat some of those communities of the Empire, who contributedso largely towards the cost of the Base, are very dissatisfied with the present situation although it is doubtful if they realise as yet how incomplete is the provision for the dockunder the Jackson contract hy itself0    It  is  I  think, noexaggeration to say that we must Reckon with the possibilityof the contributors to the Base, when they realise theposition, considering themselves defrauded and demanding thereturn of their contributions, which ran into millions of pounds.\
        Apart from the financial aspects of this situation,it lias also a political side which must not he ignored,I may mention that the Attorney-General of Australia during his recent visit to London made it clear that his Governmentwas counting on the Base &quot;being made usable in the near future,.        There is another financial side to the question,which is that the non-provision of certain important comple-mentary adjuncts to the graving dock will cause interferencewith the normal progress of the contractors&apos; work and involve us in heavy claims for compensation.   For instance, to keepthe graving dock dry for the eventual installation of machineryit will be necessary to maintain the contractors&apos; dam acrossthe entrance until the caisson has been provided to take its place.   After the contractors are ready to remove the dam weshall be liable for the expense involved in its maintenance.The same applies to pumping plant which the contractors must continue to operate until we provide our own.   And so withother items.   ^ile it is doubtful if some claims can be altogether avoided even by commencing work at once, it is certain that every week&apos;s delay v/ill add to our liability.Moreover extra expense will have ultimately to be incurred whenthe deferred works are undertaken out of their proper sequence.The whole cost of completing the dock with caisson, dockpumping plant and electric generating station amounts to 380,000 spread over 5 years, in the first of which the expend! -ture would be practically limited to preparation of drawings,whilst in the second year it would probably not exceed one-fifth of the total.        I suggest therefore that the Cabinet should couple withthe decision in regard to the defences approval to proceed with    \
the Base, as finance allows.    The  details of expenditure to he left for consideration between the Treasury and theAdmiralty.(INTLD. )  BoEoM.Admiralty, S.W.1.  11th July, 1932.

</content>
</cab>
