<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 74-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY OF  HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.)                         CAB I N B  T.  Secret                                                 Copy No. *j  CP. 263 (32)  HARBOURS. DOCKS AND PIERS  (TEMPORARY INCREASE                    OF CHARGES) ACTS.  1920  to 1931.                 Memorandum by the Minister of Transport.           Before  the war the charging powers of Harbour, Dock and  Pier Undertakings  were regulated by  statutory maximum charges set  out in the various private Acts governing the undertakings; but  the increased cost of labour and materials due to circumstances  arising out  of  the war made the pre-war maximum charges inadequate  in many cases and  in the above-named Acts Parliament empowered the  Minister of  Transport to issue  Orders modifying the permanent  maximum charging powers for periods  not exceeding twelve months.           The enabling Acts were originally expressed to expire  in 1925, but have  been kept in  operation  from year to year by the  Expiring Laws Acts.           When  the continuance  of these Acts and of the somewhat  similar Acts which apply to the charges of tramway and canal &apos;  undertakings was considered by  the Select Committee on Expiring Laws  in 1928 it was  stated that the  Minister of Transport contemplated  *  introducing,  as soon as parliamentary time would allow, permanent  legislation  and pending such legislation  recommended that all these  Acts  should  be  continued in force for a further period of five years.           The Committee, however, recommended that the Acts should  be continued for a further period of three years only, and, under  the Expiring Laws  Continuance Act, 1928,  the temporary Acts were  continued in force until the 31st December, 1931.           In 1931  the continuation of these Acts was again considered  by the Select Committee on Expiring  Laws, and on this occasion the  Committee recommended that the  Acts  relating to Tramway and Canal  Undertakings should be continued for a  further period of three years,  and that those  relating to Harbour,  Dock  and Pier Undertakings should  be continued for a period of one year only.   Effect was given to  this  recommendation by the Expiring  Laws  Act, 1931.
          It now becomes necessary to consider whether theTemporary Acts of 1920 and 1922, which are due to expire at theend of this year, should he further extended.    There are inexistence 17 Orders made under these Acts which will lapse onthe 31st December next unless the operation of the Acts isfurther prolonged.   Two of these relate to the Railway Companies&apos;Scottish Docks and fifteen to other harbours and piers, ten ofwhich are in Scotland, and all of which are small and strugglingconcerns.          In 1930 the Railway Companies promoted legislation withthe object of making permanent the increased charging powersenjoyed in respect of their harbours, docks and piers under theMinister1s orders.   Parliament granted the powers sought inEngland and Wales but the Commissioners under the Scottish PrivateLegislation Procedure rejected the Provisional Orders relating to scotland.   Thereupon, the Minister, after full public enquiries,in 1930 and again in 1931 made orders carrying on the increasedcharging powers at the Railway owned Scottish ports till the endof 1932.    Last Session the Railway Companies again promotedProvisional Orders with respect to their Scottish ports, whichhave again been rejected by the Scottish Commissioners.          A somewhat anomalous position has thus arisen sincethe powers which Parliament has granted in England and Wales havebeen refused in Scotland and I have again been approached by theRailway Companies with the object of a further prolongation oftheir powers in Scotland by the issue of Orders under thetemporary Acts.          The principal opposition to the powers sought by theRailway Companies emanates from the Scottish Coalowners&apos;Association v/ho claim to have been instrumental in securing the rejection of the Railway Companies&apos; proposals by the ScottishCommissioners.   The Coalowners have also approached me with a request  that the Temporary Acts should not be further extended or that, if it is not JJRA^-Locible,  ... account of the position
of the non-railway owned docks and harbours, to allow the Actsto lapse, that they should he continued in a form which would preclude the Railway Companies frpm again availing themselves of their provisions.          I am unable to view with approval either of the coursessuggested by the Coalowners.   On the one hand it would bemanifestly unfair to the owners of the other docks, harbours andpiers to which existing orders under the temporary Acts relate,  toallow those Acts to lapse at short notice and so force them backon to their pre-war powers of charge - a course which wouldprobably result in some cases at least in their being unable tocarry on their undertakings.   On the other hand I am advised thatit would not be possible in an Expiring Laws Act to amend the scopeof the Acts of 1920 and 1922 so as to exclude applications by theRailway Companies.          There is no doubt that legislation to put the charges  at these docks on a permanent footing is overdue.    This has been recognised by the Committee who advise the Minister in dealingwith applications under the Acts and by my predecessors in office;but most of the authorities concerned are in no position to bear the cost of promoting legislation themselves and the pressure on parliamentary time has hitherto precluded the introduction of aGovernment Bill.   In the circumstances I see no alternative tothe inclusion of the temporary  Acts in the Expiring Laws Bill of *this year with a view to their extension for a further year, andI should be glad of the authority of the Cabinet to inform theauthorities concerned that this will be done.          As regards the Railway Companies * Scottich docks, if,as I anticipate, further applications are made to me by theCompanies, I propose to refer them, in accordance with the procedurelaid down in the Acts, to the Rates Advisory Committee, a strong
expert body on which traders, shipping interests and labour are represented in addition to the three permanent members of theRailway Rates Tribunal.  Before this body, the ScottishCoalowners will of course be afforded every opportunity ofstating their case in opposition to the Railway Companies1proposals.   I propose, however, on this occasion to require theRailway Companies, as a condition of proceeding with theapplication, to lodge certain information relating to particularcoal shipping ports which the coalowners have hithertoendeavoured in vain to elicit from the Railway Companies.   this step should go far to meet any reasonable grounds of objectionwhich could be urged against my entertaining further applicationsby the Railway Companies in respect of their Scottish dockcharges.(Intld. )  P. J. P.28th July, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
