<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 209-210</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IIS, DOCUlfflMI, .IS J^JPgQFEKTY OF HIS^PJTAmiC JMAJESTY&apos;S G OVB FITMENT. )E C RET.Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor, (acting for the Secretary of State for Dominion              Affairs.)      As the Minister responsible for our relations with the Irish Free State during the absence of the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, and with the approval of the Prime Minister, I have arranged for the establish- ment of an inter-departmental sub-committee, of which the Financial Secretary to the Treasury has agreed to act as Chairman for the time being, to keep the situation under review, and particularly any retaliatory action taken by the Irish Free State Government, from the point of view especially of countering propaganda by that Government and misrepresentation in the United Kingdom.      The Sub-Committee has already held two meetings. It has arranged for the preparation of weekly reports from the departments interested, raid a statement giving   ) a concise historical account of the financial dispute has been drawn up for publicity purposes.      There is one point on which the Sub-Committee has asked for an authoritative decision.   It has had brought before it a suggestion as to the possible use.p.  278  (52).COPY NO. -xJ^.C AB I N E T.IRISH  SITUATION.
 of &quot;broadcasting as an instrument of counteringpropaganda.   It seems clear that the broadcasting of  any statement of the Government&apos; s case v/ould, so far as theB.B.C. is concerneds have to be regarded as &quot;controversial&quot;and a matter therefore on which they would be bound to observe scrupulous impartiality.   It might accordingly be difficult for the B.B.C. to refuse to give an opportunityto the Opposition in this country to reply, or, as analternative, to allow a spokesman of the Irish Free StateGovernment to present their case (thus securing for thatGovernment a wider publicity than they would otherwise be able to obtain).    The issues involved are clearly a matter for ministerial decision, and I should be glad tohave my colleagues&apos;  views.                        (intl&apos;d&apos;d.)   S.3rd August, 1932.

</content>
</cab>
