<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 242-244</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  August 1932.CONFIDENTIAL.                                       Copy No.    9CP. 282  (32).CABINET.    I CIRCULATE for the information of the Cabinet the accompanying record of a conversation between the Home Secretary and Baron von Rheinbaben, ChiefNaval  Adviser  to  the  German  Delegation at  Geneva,  together with anaccompanying note of a  further  conversation between Captain  Bellairs,  theAdmiralty  expert  at Geneva,  and  Baron  von  Rheinbaben  and  Admiralvon Freyberg.                                                                   J. S.    Foreign Office, August 5, 1932. Foreign Secretary,     Baron von Rheinbaben had said that he would like to see.a member of the British Delegation in order to convey the ideas that the German Delegation had in mind on the subject of the application to Germany of any measures that might be embodied in the Convention for Disarmament.  He came to see me accordingly this afternoon.  He said  that they had been talking  to the French about land armaments and would like to be in communication with the British on the naval aspect.  With regard to the reference in the preamble to the draft resolution to the right of delegations to reserve their attitude on political matters, Mr. Nadolny would be putting forward a suggestion.     Baron von  Rheinbaben  referred to the conversation  of  the 5th July at Lausanne between the Prime Minister and Chancellor von Papen, and said that according to  the German  record of that conversation, the Prime Minister, in answer to a question from the Chancellor as to equality of treatment of all nations, had referred to his previous conversation with Dr. Bruning. The Germans had understood him to say that Germany should be placed in a position to put forward a statement of what she actually meant to do.  &quot; In four or five years&apos; time,&quot; said the Prime Minister, &quot; another Disarmament Conference would be held at which there would be no treaty provisions to limit German freedom; in the meantime a bridge would be built from the clauses of the Treaty of Versailles on one side to complete freedom  on the  other.  The architecture of  the  bridge  had been generally agreed, but the  bridge had not yet been built.&quot;     Baron von Rheinbaben thought that it would be useful if he  were to tell me what the Germans now  had in mincl as to present proposals in  the naval sphere. , They thought it would be a mistake to have any discussion in the Disarmament Conference as to the permissible limits of German armaments,  but he himself thought that the German  Delegation might  make a statement volunteering that their expenditure on armaments might be limited to the figures of recent years.     If the conference did not result in a general measure of world disarmament. Germany would be obliged to ask for a  reconsideration of the armaments that had been forbidden to her in the Treaty of Versailles.  But,  in any case, she,would accept for a period of five years a standard of armaments less, under each head, than that which would be adopted in the convention now being negotiated. While urging the  principle of equality of right and no discrimination  in the naval sphere,  Germany would ask for the &quot; adaptation &quot; of her armaments to the general rules  to be embodied in the convention.  By  this he meant  that, for example, having been allowed  capital  ships of 10,000 tons  in  the Treaty of Versailles,  if  a limit  of, say, 22,000 tons were now to be fixed by  international treaty, Germany would  voluntarily accept  some  figure  between  10.000  and       6493   [7417]
22,000 tons.  As a matter of fact, for financial reasons she would not, in any case,wish to build up to the higher figure.  He mentioned that the German delegation of course welcomed the Hoover proposal to reduce the existing number of battle-ships.  With regard to cruisers, the German Government cordially  approved theBritish proposal for a  reduction in maximum  tonnage  for  new cruisers  to7,000 tons.  Germany is now allowed to have cruisers of 6,000 tons, and if the,000 limit were accepted, would not ask for a  higher  figure.  If, however, itwere  not  to be  accepted, they would  ask  for  authorisation to  build  up  to10,000 tons.  As to the number of cruisers, they now have five and are  entitledto build a  sixth.   In any case,  they do not want to go  much beyond that, andwould accept such a budgetary limitation of expenditure on  armaments in general as would not allow any  considerable addition to their cruiser strength.   Withregard to light cruisers and destroyers,  they would wish to have the same typesas other nations.   As to  submarines,  they  would concur  in the British proposalfor abolition,  but,  if not abolished,  they  would ask to be authorised to  buildsubmarines up  to whatever individual limit of tonnage might be fixed (250 tonsor whatever it might  be), but would accept a global tonnage less  than the figurethat might be inserted in the  treaty.    They would not put  forward any request with reference to  aircraft carriers.    The total tonnage of all units of  the German Navy, including reserve ships,was now fixed  at 144,000 tons.  In order  &quot; to build the bridge &quot; of which  thePrime Minister had spoken, it would be necessary to add some figure to that total;but this need not necessarily correspond to any increase  in the number of  units&quot;that might be .allowed.   It  might be the consequence  of allowable increases  in size.  For example, if the maximum size of German capital  ships was raised from10,000 tons to, say, 17,000, and if two such ships were built, that would mean an addition of 14,000 tons to the  144,000 limit.    With reference to personnel, their present limit was 15,000 men.  but a numberof these had had to be allocated to shore batteries, for which men had been lacking.They would ask for a  total of about 30,000 men.    In  coast defence they would  not suggest any increase of  batteries  as theyhad enough guns, but would ask for a free  hand in the disposition  of  thosebatteries.    This freedom  was  to be regarded  as an essential feature of anyequality of  status, however understood.   The reason they  make  this request isthat while their North Sea coast is more than adequately defended,  they have noguns at Kiel.    With reference to aircraft, if it was  proposed to abolish military aviationaltogether,  they would concur, but if not they would ask for a modest contingent.Incidentally, he mentioned that the prohibition of air bombing should, in their view,  either be complete or should not be  attempted.  They did  not regard the fixing  of zones in  the  neighbourhood of  military operations, in  which  alonebombing should be allowed, as capable of practical enforcement.    As&quot; to the procedure  to be adopted in preparation for the second stage of theconference, Baron von Rheinbaben referred to the proposal in the draft resolutionthat the five Naval Powers should  discuss among  themselves the naval provisions to be inserted in  the  convention.  He put  forward the suggestion that, at some stage in those negotiations, Germany should be invited to take part.  It wouldnot be thought right that she  should be  entirely excluded and afterwards bebrought into a  g;eneral discussion  at the 1&apos;esumed conference, on the same terms as Sweden  or any other of the minor Powers.  Alternatively, a German observermight be asked to be  present during those negotiations.    I  said  that I would convey all these  observations  to  Sir  John Simon.Baron von  Rheinbaben said that of course  they were only made tentatively.  Ifthe Governments desired to  pursue conversations on these matters, they might prove to be useful.  If not, the notes  on which he had based his statements, andthose that  I had made in the course  of the conversation, could just be torn up.If the British Government desired it, perhaps he himself,  who was closely in touchwith naval matters, together with Admiral von Freyberg, might come to Londonthis summer and explain their point of view to  the Admiralty, and afterwardsthey would be ready, if it was thought advisable, to explain matters  also in Paris.                                                                    H.  S.July 15, 1932;
     [NOTE.-The conversation recorded above  took place before Germany&apos;s decision was definite.not to return to the Conference unless a satisfactory solution of the principle of equality  of rights was reached.,.  In, ,a,conveir-! sation  held   between-  Captain   Bellairs,: Baron  von; Rheinbafoen  and Admiral   von  Ereyberg&apos; rafter \Germany  had  taken  her  decision,  the. proposals  contained in the conversation with Sir II. Samuel, were reiterated by the German representatives, and they added a further.statement in respect of the fortification. ,of  Kiel,   Admiral  von Freyberg  recalled that  the, Treaty of  Versailles permitted fortifications  at the Elbe  entrance  to  the canal, but not at the Baltic entrance. Defensive fortifications at Kiel, he continued,  could not prevent  the  free entry into the Baltic Sea which he thought was the original idea of the prohibition.  It was  not,  he said, proposed  in  any way to increase armaments allowed by the. Treaty of Versailles, but power woidd be sought to place such armaments as might be desired.&apos;]                                                      .   .

</content>
</cab>
