<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 245-246</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
    [This document is the Property oi  His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]                      Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1932.SECRET.                                                             QtCP. 283 (32).                                               Copy No......./..                                   CABINET.Reports by Local Governments on the Political  Situation in India.   I circulate for the information of my colleagues the latest weekly reports  from theLocal Governments in India.     INDIA OFFICE,   9th August 1932.Government of India.   Congress activities are sporadic, and there have  been no serious incidents.  the communal situation in the Punjab, which was disquieting owing to the Sikh agitationand its reaction on Mussulmans, shows signs of improvement.Delhi.   Section 3 : arrests, 1;  total detained,  4.   Section 4:  fresh orders,  4 ;  total todate in respect of whom orders are in force, 28; convictions to date for orders, 9.Bombay.   The situation  generally  is  quiet.  Raids  were attempted  on seized Congressbuildings in  six  districts,  but were  easily  frustrated.   Only  one raid, in  theAhmedabad district, was sufficiently determined to necessitate the use of  force by thepolice.  There has been a slight recrudescence of Congress activities in Sholapur andPandharpur.  Picketing in Ahmedabad  is reported to be nominal.  A case of damageby corrosive liquid of  35 cocoanut trees belonging to a toddy licensee occurred at Ankola(Ivanara  district).   Perpetrators  of  the mischief  were  mostly  recently releasedvolunteers.  In. Bombay city the monthly flag  salutation ceremony on 31st July wasprevented  by the  arrest of  38 persons, including the  emergency war  council.Sporadic picketing is being continued, and 20  picketers were  arrested  during  theweek.   Further arrests have been made  of secret Congress organisers.   Ordinance 10.Section 3:  arrests, 22; total  under detention, 88.  Section  4:  orders, 25 ; total inforce, 811.   Section  17:  convictions,  7; total  casualties in Bombay  riots up  tomorning, 5th, 217 killed, 2,713 injured.Bengal.   It is reported from the Tippera district that a mob attacked the police and rescueda prisoner arrested under section 41J of the Indian Penal Code.   One constable wasinjured by a lathi, and the police fired two rounds.  No injuries to villagers have yetbeen  reported.   Section  4:  orders issued,  62;  in force, 193 ;  convictions,  76.Section 3 : arrests, 4.Madras.   Except for a disquieting bomb  incident in  the Southern District Centre, Madura,the situation during the  week has  been the  quietest since the outbreak  of civildisobedience.Central Provinces.   The situation has been quiet except for a few sporadic Congress demonstrations inJubbulpore  and Nagpur and an attempted forest satyagraha in Wardha.   Prosecu-tions, 52 ; convictions, 42 ; fines imposed, 715.      1123   60 8.32
United Provinces.   Raids on Congress buildings, particularly the Swaraj Bhawan, continue.  Freshactivity is reported from three or four districts.   Elsewhere the situation remainsquiet.   Under  section  3,  no orders ;  under section  4,  14 orders  issued.   Oneconviction under section  4 of Ordinance.  Convictions for week under Ordinance, 34;under ordinary-; law, 167;  of  these, about half were at Allahabad.  Total to date,.10,823 ;  releases and apologies, 2,752..........Punjab.   Congress activities have been negligible.   Political  arrests 9, all under  ordinary law.   No action has been  taken  under sections 3 and 4.   Orders in force undersection  4 reduced  to  60.   Total  under  restraint for  infraction remains  31.   the communal situation is   easier.   Provocative  processions  threatened  for  Friday,5th. August, were  abandoned, and  the general tone  of  speeches  and  Press has improved.  These  results have been  accomplished without the restrictive action forwhich the Government was  prepared.North-West  Frontier Province.   Section 3 :  arrests, 1 ; total detained, 5.  Section 4 :  arrests, 25 ; total  orders inforce, 473.  No lashkar  has yet collected and the Upper Mohmands, owing largely tointer-tribal feuds, appear unable to decide on any united action.  In the remainder ofthe Province the situation is normal.Bihar and Orissa.   There is nothing to report.   Total convictions up  to 31st  July,  8,520.  Totalorders in force under section 4, Special  Powers Ordinance,  11.Assam.   There is nothing to report.Ajmer Merwara.   There is nothing to report and no arrests have been made.From the Resident, Mysore.   The weekly report from  Coorg- and Bangalore is the same as last week.

</content>
</cab>
