<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 277-305</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C A B I N E T.SECRET.CP. 286 (52)TRANSPORT POLICY.       mPRAKDUM BY THE MINISTER OF TRANSPORT.        -In CP.52(32) I drew the attention of the Cabinet tocertain questions raised by the railway companies inrepresentations which they had recently made to me.   It may be convenient if I now indicate the general directions in which weare likely to be called upon to frame and apply a definitetransport policy.legislative and other steps have been taken in the field oftransport which may be summarised as follows:-    (l)  Highway administration was largely reformed under theprovisions of the Local Government Act, 1929c   The changes were brought smoothly into operation.    (2)  A progressive and continuous policy of road andbridge improvement and construction has been pursued.   the drastic retrenchment recently necessitated by the financialcrisis, has involved the cancellation or postponement of works to the amount of about  35 millions and haw brought theprogress of improvements for the time being to a standstill.But in spite of this, facilities for transport by road havebeen greatly improved and increased.   One result of the strengthening and widening of the main routes has been toencourage heavy end fast moving commercial traffic, both goods and passenger, over long distances, thus no doubt to someextent aggravating and accelerating the diversion of valuabletraffic from the railways.RECENT DEVELOPMENTS.During the last few years several important
    (3)  On the other hand, the inclusion of the railwaycompanies in the derating scheme of I929 was intended toencourage the movement of the heavy coal and iron and steeltraffics and also of agricultural traffics hy rail.   It will heremembered that the railway companies are not permitted to retainany part of the &quot;benefit of derating for themselves.   They arerequired under rigid statutory provisions to pass on the wholebenefit to specified classes of railway users.   The amount ofthe rebates allowed to traders has been increased as a result ofthe smaller volume of traffic, but the assistance which thescheme might have  afforded to the railways by s timulating theirtraffics has been diminished by the industrial depression.   Thefuture operation of the scheme is somewhat uncertain as the assessment of the railways on the new basis of valuation has still to be determined.         The railways and their users were assisted by the repeal of railway passenger duty in I929, the capital equivalent of the duty being applied to the provision of new facilities and improvements involving an expenditure equivalent to thecapitalised value of the duty.    (if)  Partly with a view to redressing the balance betweenrail and road and partly to meet the increasing costs of thehighways, taxation on the heavier commercial vehicles was tosome extent increased by the Bnadget of 1926, and a new duty onpetrol was imposed in 1928.   At the same time, a rebate of 30per cent, of the vehicle tax was accorded to the heavier classesof vehicle if fitted with pneumatic tyres, a concession which hasbeen of substantial advantage to the owners of such vehicles.    (5)  Powers to operate services by road and subsequentlyby air were granted to the railway companies.   The power to operate services by road has been of great importance and therailway companies have taken full advantage of it on the passenger side to secure substantial interests in a large numberof omnibus cud coach companies.
                       - 3 -    (6)  The Road Traffic Act,  19/?0,  in addition to bringing the law relating to motor vehicles generally up to date,established a comprehensive scheme of regulation of publicservice passenger vehicles.   It also introduced certain new and amended requirements (iee.  as to construction and use of vehicles, the age of drivers and the regulation of drivers&apos;hours of labour in respect of goods vehicles), but stopped short of any effective schome of regulation of goods traffic by road.    (7)  The scheme embodied in the London Passenger transport bill, including the agreement for a pooling scheme between theproposed Board and four amalgamated railway companies, is designed to settle comprehensively the problem of co-ordinationof passenger transport over the wide area embraced within a circlewith a radius of approximately 25 miles from Charing Cross,                      FURTHER PROBLEMS,         Looking to the future, the ground to be consolidatedor marked out for further advance lies in the following maindirections t -    1.   Road Traffic Act, 19^0.  Most of the features of thenew legislation (including, for example, the introduction of ascheme of compulsory third party insurance.) have given rise tofar less trouble in operation than might have been apprehended.The close contact which my Department maintains with the variousroad  transport road other ant erests concerned, and its practice of consulting with them in regard  to the making of regulations,conduce  to smooth working.         Part IV of the Act, which relates to licensing ofpublic service passenger vehicles, has inevitably  given riseto  some  criticisms, but they are diminishing as the Act comes to be better understood and initial difficulties clear away.The value of its protective as well as its restrictive provisionsis being increasingly realised  by  road operateroo
                        - If -         The transfer to 15 &quot;bodies of Commissioners of thefunctions hitherto performed (often most inadequately) hyabout 1,500 separate local licensing authorities has been effected without undue difficulty, if regard be had to the magnitude of the change.   It is, of course, true that certain of the municipal and other bodies, who were themselves interestedin trams and other forms of municipal transport, do not altogether like the loss of the power to license their competitors, which under the old system was open to abuse*         Apart from the inevitable refusals to license services which were not being satisfactorily or regularly conducted; theCommissioners were required, in giving effect to the directions of Parliament, to have regard &quot;to the extent to which theproposed services were necessary or desireble in the publicinterest and &quot;to the needs of the area as a whole in relation to traffic............... end the co-ordination of all forms of passenger transport including transport by rail&quot;.   Some of their decisions were bound to involve refusals of licences tounnecessary or unreasonably competitive services, and it is amatter of common knowledge that during the progress of the Bill3and in the months immediately after its passage before the new system of licensing could be established, a great many newservices were started in the hope of staking out claims for thefuture.   The new Government assumed office at the moment whenthe decisions of the Commissioners were becoming operative and being made the subject of appeal.   It is easy to conduct an agitation in favour of some particular applicant without full knowledge of the circumstances and without  reference to thegeneral position and the results  of sporadic or uneconomiccompetition upon regular services, and it is inevitable that indealing with an enormous number of applications the Commissioners
                       - 5 -must make some mistakes.    It is,  therefore,  not surprising that I have had to deal with some  troublesome- appeals and to answer a good many Parliamentary Questions on the subject.         I took steps, however, at the end of last year toissue a general direction to the Traffic Commissionersreminding them of the importance of giving full considerationto the case of the small man and the legitimate demands of thepublic.   Complaints against the operation of the Act are nowless frequent.   Substantial progress has been made towards abetter co-ordination of passenger  transport and the responsibleorganisations of the motoring industry realise the value of theAct in bringing stability and proper conditions of employmentinto the industry.   The smaller men are also beginning to appreciate the protection they derive from the orderly systemof licensing which has replaced the competitive chaos prevailingon many routes.         In London, special problems arise.   The congestion ofthe streets by motor coaches has been a source of anxiety tothe Commissioner of Police for the Metropolis and for theCity of London.   A Committee of Inquiry, presided over byLord Amulree, has confirmed the necessity of restricting theuse of streets in the central area and has also advised meupon a number of individual appeals from the TrafficCommissioners1 decisions,   I have accepted their advice and,pending the creation of a Passenger Transport Board, no more satisfactory  means of handling a difficult position will beopen to me.    2.    The early passage of the London Passenger transport bill is indeed the only satisfactory means of co-ordinatingpassenger transport  in  the special and complicated area of greater London.   I need  not recapitulate  the arguments infavour of this step or  the reasons which have led me to theconclusion- that  the  scheme is the only practicable  technicalsolution of the problem,  since they have been laid before theCabinet  on other  occasion
    5.   The investment.of the main line railways in omnibusand coach undertakings under the powers which they seoured fiveyears ago, careful administration of Part IV of the road traffic Act, 1950* end the establishment of the london passenger Transport Board xould carry co-ordination of passenger transport as far as need be contemplated at present.         Under the head of careful administration of the road traffic Act, I include a proper enforcement of the legalspeed limits - a matter to which the Home Secretary is givingspecial attention         I also include the proper observance of legalrequirements as to hours of employment of drivers and conductorsand of the Pair Wages Clause, where enforcement is moredifficult,,   It will be necessary to require all drivers oflicensed passenger vehicles to carry way-bills or journeyrecords of an appropriate kind which will show the times oftheir journeys and duties and will be available for production to authorised persons.   Such records are recommended by theRoad-Rail Conference in respect of goods vehicles and, ifexisting powers are found  to be inadequate to cover passenger services, I should propose to seek further powers in relationto this class of  traffic in any further legislation.    If.   Co-ordination of  goods transport.   On assuming office,it was represented to me that at present the legal speed limits for heavy goods vehicles and the legal limitations upon theloads which they  may carry were being widely ignored,,   Heavyvehicles proceeding at high speeds doubtless cause much generalinconvenience through noise and vibration, epart from thequestion of road  damage or public safety.   The traffic commissioners have no jurisdiction over goods vehicles and enforcement of the law must rest entirely with the police,
including the mobile police, and with the highway authorities,I contemplate some simplification of the existing schedule ofspeeds, hut no general relaxation.   Simplification should makeenforcement easier, hut amending regulations will require an affirmative resolution of both Houses of Parliament.        - As regards overloading, the railway companies complainecand still complain that this is frequent, gross and notoriousThere is undoubtedly much ground for thio complaint and inconjunction with the Home Office I have been considering vrhataction can be taken for the better enforcement of the law3         There remained more fundamental issues, namely:-    (a)  whether the incidence of the total burden of motor             taxation and of highway costs is fairly             distributed between the users of the roads and             other interests, between the different classes             of road users inter se and between the heavier             and lighter vehioies&quot;&quot;in each class.    (b)  whether some system of licensing goods vehicles             should be established so that they may be brought             under the same kind of requirement as to quotation             of rates, the avoidance of undue preference, eto*5             as the railway companies         Equitable taxation of commercial road transport inrelation to the use which it makes of and the value it derives from the highway system appeared  to me to lie at the root ofthe reil-*road prohlem, and a just and speedy settlement ofthis question to he on all grounds desirable.         In the hope that I should be able to narrow down the area of controversy, I  decided, as the Cabinet  is aware3 *to set up as a preliminary  step a small Conference consistingof the General Managers of  the  four railway companies and-four representatives of the goods side of motor transport(under the independent chairmanship of Sir Arthur Salter,                                               ^&quot;-&quot;iniwnmi i_________in IIwhom I selected after consulting  the Prime Minister) to explorethese questions.         It will be within the recollection of seme of mycolleagv.es that demands were made by several other interests to
&quot;be included in the Conference.   In the House of LordsLord Lovat pressed a claim for representation of the highway authorities.   The vaz ious orgsnisations of traders (includingthe Federation cf British Industries, the Chambers of Commerce,the National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers and thaMining Association) and other competitive forms of transport,such as the canals and coastwise shipping, had all raised thepoint of special representation, but I was bound to answer thenall by pointing out that, if I included one, I should soenlarge the Conference as to turn it into a kind of TransportParliament from whose deliberations no practical results were likely to follow.   This answer wa3 accepted by all the intereoconcerned, especially in view of my assurance that before any decision was taken all interests would be given the fullestopportunity of expressing their views upon any proposals orfindings vhich the Road-Rail Conference might reach.   I met thpoint of the highway  authorities to their satisfaction, withoutreopening the question of direct representation on  the Committeby inserting a preamble  in  the reference in order to  define itascope and.object.         Regarding the whole matter as urgent, I instructed the Conference to report by the end of July, so  that  there shcube ample time for any further consultations that may be necessaand for full consideration  by tho Cabinet of all  the  issues arising well in  advance  of  the next  session of Parliament,,         The Conference has conformed to  this time-table and presented a moot valuable and unanimous report, which I havepublished and which  I have  sent  to all the representativeassociations of  local authorities,  traders, motor users andtrade unions concerned,  with  a  request that  any  observationsthey may wish to make shall reach me not  later  than theJOth September,          I  annex a  summary  cf ths Report  (Appendix I).
         I propose to discuss at once with the Treasury thescheme of revised taxation of heavy goods vehicles recommendedunanimously by the Conference as just and necessary toestablish a fair basis of competition, and assume that inprinciple this recommendation will commend itself to theChancellor of the Exchequer and to the Government as a whole.         As regards the scheme of licensing of goods vehicles.v/hich is recommended by the Conference and is set out inAppendix II, I should be glad of authority to prepare a Billin framing which I should, of course, have regard to anycriticisms or suggestions made by the interests I have consulted.   I think that the Cabinet might find it easier togive consideration to the proposals if they saw them in the concrete form of a Bill which could be examined in detail by v.the Home Affairs Committee.    5*   Further -pooling of receipts between the railwaycompanies.   I have already contented to an important poolingarrangements covering all the traffic competitive between theLondon, Midland and Scottish and the London and North EasternRailway Companies, in the circumstances explained to theCabinet in CP. 264(32).   I expect to receive a similarapplication for a pooling arrangement between the London,Midland and Scottish and the Great Western Railway Companies-I shall he bound to order an inquiry into any such applicationas in the previous case, but I hope that the proposals will  he found acceptable since, as the Royal Commission on Transportrealised, arrangements of this kind are inevitable if therailway companies are to secure maximum economies and avoid the waste of their diminished resources for giving publicservice,,    64   Highway Expenditure.   It is a question whether thepolicy recently pursued in making grants from the Road Fundhas had sufficient regard to the co-ordination of railway and
                                                       294    I                        - 10 -road transport and has not in. its practical result (though notin intention) gone too far to facilitate and accelerate the transference of heavy long-distance traffic from the railwaysto the roads.   For many years past the highway policy of theMinistry of Transport has unfortunately heen deflected hy thespectre of unemployment, which has led Government afterGovernment to press for the initiation of such road works as can most readily he put in hand, employ the maximum volume oflabour and anticipate, perhaps substantially, traffic needs.         V/hile it cannot fairly be said that the Road Fund hasbeen applied to schemes not possessing real trafficjustification, immediate or prospective, or that there hasbeen a policy of subsidising mere relief works out of theFund, there can be little doubt that the trunk road and similar programmes since 1924 have been a direct encouragmentto long-distance road transport.   I propose to review thevairious purposes to which we make grants, and possibly to give them a scmewnat different order of priority in relation to ageneral economic policy.   Y/e have created recently a verylarge volume of capital assets in the form of drasticallyremodelled and improved main roads.   It may be that we shallhave to devote a larger portion of our resources to themaintenace of our existing roads and their gradual           ,reconditioning, with a view to keeping the whole network ofour minor roads in the most efficient state for the purpose oflocal distribution by motor transport conducted in mechanicalunits of reasonable weight and dimensions.   It may be wise tocall a halt to the provision of routes largely parallel to therailway lines and adapted to taking the very heaviest types of road vehicle.   I propose to consult the highway authoritiesespecially on this aspect of the matter.
                       - 11 -         In this memorandum I have not thought it.....ne-cessary  &quot;to refer to means of transport other than road and rail.That is not to sas^ that there is nothing to consider exceptin regard to rail and road traffic.   There is, for example,the question of the Canals.   But it can hardly he said that either coastwise shipping, or harbours and docks or even the canals, present any equally pressing problems from the pointof view of co-ordination.   (The position of the tramways -Whether municipal or company - as regards competition is reasonably safeguarded by the Road Traffic Act, 1950).                      1 Summary         To sum up, the possible lines of policy for thefurther co-ordination of rail and road traffic appear to be asfollows:-passenger Transport.    1.   Legislation giving effect to the proposals of             the London Passenger Transport Bill.    2.   Adherence to the policy of co-ordinating passenger             road transport laid down in Part IV of the Road             Traffic Act, 1^0, coupled with the efficient             enforcement of the provisions of that Act in             regard to speed limits and conditions of             employment.Goods Transport.    3.   Enforcement of the provisions of the Road Traffic             Act, I93O, in respect of the speeds and loading of             goods vehicles, and of conditions of employment in             connection therewith.        &apos;          :&apos;&quot;-&apos; :                                &apos; .  y -*  I &apos;    4.   The institution of a system of licensing goods vehicles             in accordance with the unanimous recommendation             of the Road-Rail Conference.General.    5.   A revision of the incidence of taxation with a             view to an adjustment which would more closely             relate the share borne by heavy commercial vehicles             to the use which they make of the roads.    6.   Conservation of highway expenditure by restricting             the use of the -unclassified roads to mechanical             units of suitable size and weight.   We cannot             afford to follow the principle of making every roac             suitable for every vehicle.
0 n (*                       - 12 -    7.   So soon as the Road Fund is in a position to make             grants for further improvements and development             of the higlrroy system, a determination of the             prioritsr to he accorded to various types of             scheme, with due regard to the proper functions             of the railways and the roads.    8.   The institution of pooling schemes between the four             amalgamated railway companies, together with the             exploration of further opportunities for economy             including the introduction of high capacity mineral             wagons.         In. conclusion, I may perhaps be allowed toemphasise the importance of viewing our transport problem asa whole.   V/e should, I am sure, be greatly assisted inmaking effective progress in the many directions where, bygeneral admission, action of some kind is required, if wewere able to say that the Government is viewing current problems in the light of consistent transport policy andthat it attaches importance to that branch of its economic policy and its translation into practice.                          (Intd)  P.J.P.22nd August, 1952.
APPENDIX I               SUMMARY OP REPORT                       OP     CONFERENCE ON RAIL AND ROAD TRANSPORT.         The Report of the Conference on Rail and road transport, which received its Terms of Reference from theMinister of Transport on 11th April, 1932, was signed on29th July and published on 17th August.         The Members of the Conference (with the exception ofSir Arthur Salter, K.C.B., the independent Chairman appointedby the MiniBter) represented in equal proportions theinterests immediately concerned in the operation of goodstransport by rail and by road.         The Report makes recommendations which are in allcases unanimous.   The questions covered are:-    (a)  the incidence of highway costs;    (b)  licensing and control;    (c)  certain other matters affecting &quot;division of function             betv/een road and rail.                 PART I;  INTRODUCTORY.         The first part (Paragraphs 3&quot;3&apos;) ) gives a generaldescription of the recent evolution of motor transport;  the transformation of the road system;  and the problem of road       )and rail competition.         The Conference considers that the relative contributions of the different classes of motor vehicles need correction andthat for certain classes of commercial gocos vehicles need to he
f)flO6 &quot;JO increased.   Extravagant expectations must not, however, he entertained as to the  effect of such increased taxation, or of this combined with additional regulations in forcing back traffic  to the railways.   (Paragraph 2j).         The present situation of the railways is in part due to the fact that for many classes of traffic the motor vehicle is both more convenient and essentially more economical than the railways.   In other words, certain services of the railways, essential in the last century, are no longer indispensable and it would be undesirable to attempt to divert traffic back from the) roads and deprive trade and industry of the convenience of the new form of transport.   The railways position is alsp in part due to the general trade depression.   Against these two major causes of loss, the one permanent and the other temporary, the railways must look to their share of a generally increasing total of trade and to the new facilities they can themselves offer to the public;  and for the rest must deal with their losses in the appropriate manner.   (Paragraph 28).         In its recommendations the Conference can only offer an alleviation of one of these principal causes of loss by dealingwith any existing unfairness in the incidence of highway costs and inadequacy of the regulations to protect the public and otherusers of the road against undesirable forms of road traffic by goods vehicles.   (Paragraph 29)*         PART II:  INCIDENCE OF HIGHWAY COSTS.         The Conference is in full agreement as to the main principles which should govern the determination of the chargesupon commercial motor transport.    (Paragraph 3k-)*         The railway representatives ask no more than that this transport should pay its fair share of the cost of the roads they use as their permanent way.    The road representatives do not ask that commercial road transport should pay less than its
                           - 3 -fair share of the cost of the roads or should by so doing attainany other development than that which is economic and in thepublic interest.   (Paragraphs 35-36).         The Conference had to recommend, therefore,  what is thetotal annual sum which is properly to he allotted tomechanically-propelled vehicles as a whole and then what is thejust incidence as between the different classes (Paragraph 37).         At present road users enjoy the very substantial&quot;legacy of the past&quot; in respect of both the road system existingbefore the motor era and of the heavy capital expenditure on thework of transformation during this era.   But it is necessary tomake allowance for the other uses to which the roads  are put hythose who make no payment therefor except through rates andtaxes;  that is, for what is commonly termed the &quot;community use&quot;of the roads.         After long discussion these two factors, each incapable of exact calculation and required on opposite sides of the account? seemed to approximate closely in order of magnitude.It was agreed, therefore, that on the understanding that annualroad expenditure should be calculated as described later (so asto include future expenditure whether out of revenue  or loansbut to exclude any item in respect of the service of past loana)these two items of &quot;community use&quot; on the one hand and &quot;legacyof the past&quot; on the other might fairly be regarded as cancelling;                                                            jeach other.   (Paragraphs 38-50).         After consideration of the accounts of the last fiveyears, the fairest figure to represent annual expenditure as abasis of a scheme of allocation seems to the Conference to be anet figure of  60 millions to allocate among different classesof mechanically-propelled vehicles.   (Paragraphs 51-54).         Seeking criteria of allocation of total costs and notin any sense the actual methods of collecting the sums so determined, the Conference has examined alternative systemsproposed for the purpose.   (Paragraphs 55-56).
         It was suggested, for example, that some 80 percent, of the total contribution required should be obtained by means of a shilling duty a gallon on petrol, other factors&quot;being allowed for in reduced licence duties calculated on theaggregate to produce the remaining 20 per cent.         There would be great advantages in taking petrolconsumption as the main criterion of incidence.   The Conference,however, came to the conclusion that, while an excellent measure for varying use and wear of the roads by different vehicles ofthe same general weight and description, it is a defective measureof varying use and wear by different classes of vehicles, and this to an extent which would not be adequately corrected by the reservation of 20 per cent, of the total contribution forsollection in the form of  graded licence duties representing -a general road franchise.   At the same time petrol consumption was felt to he a useful element in a criterion and has &quot;been employedin the final proposal.   (Paragraphs 59 - 62).         A second basis considered was that of the &quot;ton-mileage&quot;of the different classes of vehicles, that is, a criterion whichdetermines the appropriate contribution to be made by each classby ascertaining on a system of averages tho laden tonnage of the vehicles in the class, multiplying this &quot;by the estimated mileagethey cover in a year, and distributing the total of &amp;6C millionaccording to these results.   (Paragraph 63).         The Conference reached conclusions, agreed without reserve in any case, as to the average distance run, the average ladenweight and petrol consumed, in each class.   These agreed conclusions, combined with the exactly known number of vehicles in each class, haveoenablcd it to work out what would be thedistribution of  60 million on a strict ton-mile basis for eaohclass of vehicles.  (Paragraph 65).
Off 1 X         The Conference consider, however, that a ton-milecriterion would give results which would need some correctionat both ends of the scale and concluded that a system of allocation based equally on ton-mileage and petrol consumption would be the most adequate general formula.   (Paragraphs 68 - 69         The mean of the results given by the &quot;petrolconsumption&quot; criterion and those given by the &quot;ton-mileage&quot;criterion was therefore taken.   The effect of this combinedcriterion would be to allot  23,847,544 to commercial goods vehicles, and  36,152,446 to all other mechanically-propelled vehicles.   (Paragraphs 70 - 72).         On close examination of this combination theConference oame to the conclusion that some further correctionseemed required, and that a somewhat greater allowance should bemade for the speed and unlimited franchise of the road at oneend of the soale than for the extra wear and tear caused by the heavier vehicles, of which a considerable proportion, but by nomeans all, are to be found among the goods vehicles at the otherend of the scale.   (Paragraphs 73 - 74).         In the circumstances, the final conclusion was reached,in full agreement, that the  60 million should be allocated inthe following proportions among mechanically-propelled vehicles      (a)   23^ million to commercial goods vehicles:      (b)   36^ million to all other mechanically-                propelled vehicles.  (Paragraph 75).         This sum - about  2-g- million more than the presentyield of licence and petrol duties from commercial goods vehicles - involves considerable  increases in the contributions to be made by certain classes.   This is inevitable is each class is to bear its fair share of road expenditure.(Paragraph 77).
                      - 5 -         The Conference consider, however, that a ton-milecriterion v/ould give results which would need some correctionat &quot;both ends of the scale and concluded that a system of allocation based equally on ton-mileage and petrol consumption would be the most adequate general formula.   (Paragraphs 68 - 69)         The mean of the results given by the &quot;petrolconsumption&quot; criterion and those given by the &quot;ton-mileage&quot;criterion was therefore taken.   The effect of this combined.criterion v/ould be to allot  23,847,544 to commercial goods vehicles, and  36,152,446 to all other mechanically-propelled vehicles.   (Paragraphs 70 - 72).         On close examination of this combination theConference came to the conclusion that some further correctionseemed required, and that a somewhat greater allowance should bemade for the speed and unlimited franchise of the road at oneend of the scale than for the extra wear and tear caused by the heavier vehicles, of which a considerable proportion, but by nomeans all, are to be found among the goods vehicles at the otherend of the scale.   (Paragraphs 75 - 74).         In the circumstances, the final conclusion was reached,,in full agreement, that the  60 million should be allocated inthe following proportions among mechanically-propelled vehicles:-      (a)   23i- million to commercial goods vehicles:      (b)   36^ million to all other mechanically-                propelled vehicles.  (Paragraph 75).         This sum - about  24 million more than the presentyield of licence and petrol duties from commercial goods vehicles - involves considerable  increases in the contributions to he made by certain classes.   This is inevitable is each class is to bear its fair share of road expenditure.(Paragraph 77).
         The present basis of contribution is in certain respectsobsolete and inadequate.   More than half the contributions madeby the owners of motor vehicles is now in the form of an 8d. pea1gallon petrol duty.   Steam, electric and fuel oil vehicles entirelyescape this duty.   (Paragraph 78).         Another anomaly arises from the fact that the present scale of duties was fixed before the development of the heaviesttype of vehicle in considerable numbers.  The scale rightlyincreases with tonnage - but at present it stops at 5 tons unladen weight.   A 10-ton vehicle pays no more in licence duty thana 5-ton vehicle.   This gives a preferential advantage to justthat type of vehicle which the evidence shows to involvedisproportionately high road expenditure.   (Paragraph 79).         The Conference unanimously recommends new and detailedscales of the licence duties for the different classes ofcommercial goods vehicles.   These duties are substantially thesame for vehicles not exceeding 3 tons unladen weight, but for thereasons indicated above,   are heavily increased for heaviervehicles - especially those which pay no petrol duty and, therefore,make no contribution to road costs except through their licenceduties.   (Paragraph 89).         The proposed licence duty has been worked out for each class of commercial goods vehicles by category and weight so as togive the appropriate total for the class on the assumption that the^present petrol duty is continued.         The effect of this is that, within each class, individualvehicles pay more or less of the total according to distanceactually run to the extent to which petrol duty makes up the total;as regards the balance, raised by licence duty, the vehicle whichdoes more than the average of its class gains, and the vehicleswhich does less, loses.
         In these circumstances the Conference considers thatit is important that the proportion to he obtained by means ofthe petrol duty should remain as high as it is at present.(Paragraph 90).            PART III:  REGULATION AND LICENSING.         The railways are subject to an extensive and oftenmeticulous system of regulation and supervision.   This systemof control is of especial importance in regard to rates.   Ascommon carriers the railways are under obligation to carrygoods at rates which do not discriminate between one person and another.   Similarly, the arrangements as to wages andconditions of service are such as to give very effective protection of the interests of the railway employees.(Paragraph 93)*         It is agreed that the conditions upon whichcompetition should take place ought to be more on an equality.The Conference had, therefore, to consider whether to proceed in the direction of asking for greater liberty for the railwayor, on the other hand of recommending certain public safeguardto be extended to the operation of motor transport service.(Paragraph 9^)*         In general, the Conference considers that to theextent to which a service, whether by road or rail, must beregarded as partaking of the character of a common carrierservice the necessity for some public safeguards arises.(Paragraph 95)*         In the matter of rates where i-t might seem prima facie that the existence of effective competition over thewhole area of the railways&apos; work make the system in force as regards railway rates unnecessary, no fundamental change is recommended.   Capricious discrimination in rates, whileit may in some cases secure extra  receipts and in others
                      - 8 -extra traffic not otherwise obtainable, is no satisfactory-principle for common carriers to work upon, either from thepoint of view of the transport  industry itself or of the tradeand commerce served.   Indeed,  when a common carrier service is organised in large units, the commercial obligation of fairtreatment  towards customers must, in practice, prevent suchdiscrimination.   (Paragraph 9^)*         The same is true as regards wages and conditions ofService.   The less favourable  conditions obtaining over a parjrof the haulage industry are due to the greater number of individuaunits in that industry.   In justice to the employees and alsoin the interests of both of the railways and of those haulierswho are struggling to maintain  satisfactory wage rates andconditions of work, it is of the utmost importance that an end should be put to the abuses in  these respects which have so farattended the organisation of the industry in so many small units.(Paragraph 97).         In addition, the Conference agrees that the public hasa right to be assured that the  vehicles using the public roadsshould be - and should be maintained - in a state of fitness.This necessity has been recognised in the case of public service(passenger) vehicles.  (Paragraph 9$)*         For these reasons, the Conference considersthat some regulation of goods motor vehicles is necessary;and that this regulation can be enforced only through licensing system.    The Conference agrees, withouthesitation, that all such vehicles should be requiredto have licences which are conditional upon the observance of proper conditions as to fair wages and conditions ofservice, and the maintenance of the vehicles in a state offitness.   (Paragraph 99)*
         Any individual at present has an unlimited right to enter the haulage industry, without any regard to the pressure on the roads or  to any existing excess of transport facilities.   This unrestricted liberty is fatal to the organisation of the industry in a form suitable to a  carrier service purporting to serve the public.   On the other hand the Conference was equally impressed with the evil of any system which would prevent trade and industry from securing the form of transport which is best adapted to its ever changing needs at the lowest practicable cost that can be obtained on a salutary basis.   (Paragraph 100).         In these circumstances the Conference agreed upon a scheme which is defined in specific recommendations (Paragraph 101).                       -         The Conference makes a distinction, recognised by theRoyal Commission on Transport, between &quot;hauliers&quot; who, like the railways, convey the goods of others and &quot;ancillary users&quot; who own goods motor vehicles as ancillary to their commercial undertakings.   (Paragraph 102).         The Conference considers that both hauliers and ancillary users should be subject to regulation, enforced through the grant of licences, as regards fair wages and conditions of service and the maintenance of their vehicles in a state of                                                                 Jfitness.   (Paragraph 10*),         In other respects, however, it is considered thathauliers, with the right to carry the goods of the public, should properly be subject to some measure of regulation not applicable to ancillary users.    (Paragraph 10J?).         It is felt that the hauliers enjoying this right shouldbe an enterprise separately constituted as a -bona fide business.Overlapping of financial interests between hauliers and
                                                          61 u ancillary users  is  inevitable in many cases, &quot;but the accounts should he separate  and  the concerns legally separate.   Ancillary users conversely should, as  the counterpart of the freedom they enjoy, he prohibited from carrying any other goods other than their own,  except  as regards vehicles confined  to a radius of 10 miles from their  place of business.   (Paragraphs 106  - 111).         In the  case of hauliers, the Conference thinks that the licensing authority may properly have regard to any such excess in existing  transport facilities as may make the grant of a licence for the full number of vehicles asked for against the public interest.    Any such restriction of the free normal development of transport facilities must be applied with great care;  It must reflect  a general policy adapted to the needs cf different periods;  and it must be developed as a national policy on consideration of all the interests involved, and applied subject  to a convenient and inexpensive machinery of appeal, through  local licensing authorities.    Por this purpose, the Conference recommends the constitution of a permanent Central Advisory Committee to advise the Minister sf Transport as to  the instructions which he should issue to the local licensing  authorities.   (Paragraph 107).         In the  case of ancillary users, however, the Conference recommends that no restriction on these grounds should be imposed.   Subject always to certain conditions, (e.g.,  fair wages and conditions of service,  etc.)  it considers that the industrialist and the trader should remain free to utilise as many motor vehicles as they find their &quot;business requires.   With this safety valve, there is no cause to fear that any form of seml-monspoly which may develop by a large scale organisation of the haulier^industry,  or close relations&quot;between that industry and the railways, will  be against the public Interest,,    (Paragraph 108),
         On the contrary, it would he to the great benefit of allconcerned if the relations between the different sections of thetransport industry became such that they were less concerned withmutual competition than with the organisation of complementaryfunction.   (Paragraph 109).         The Conference then recommends a definite scheme basedupon the fsregoing principles.   (Paragraph 111).         In the introduction of the above system the Conferencepresumes that care would be taken to prevent unnecessarydisturbance and hardship.   It is considered, for example, thatall hauliers already in business, when the Conference wasappointed in March last, should without question receive their first year&apos;s licence for the number (or equivalent tonnago) ofthe vehicles employed by them at the time of the licenceapplication.  (Paragraph 112),         The Conference further recommends that operators shouldbe required to keep such records as will help to secure the dueobservance of the prescribed conditions of maximum weight to bocarried and hours of work;  that the licensing authorities shallhave the right of access to Information as to the rates charged byby an applicant;  and that, while the licensing system proposed should be brought into immediate operation, the  Minister should examine the question of publication and control cf rates, inconsultation with the Central Advisory Committee.   (Paragraphs117 - 119).         In many oases the heavier types of vehicles causeexcessive damage to the roads and involve disproportionateexpense to the highway authorities.   These authorities already possess powers to secure the exclusion of specified types of vehicles from certain roads.   The Conference contemplates thatif the heaviest type of vehicle should be utilised in increasing
 numbers  on classes of  roads which  are  clearly  unsuitable,  a much more  extended use of the powers referred  to may he necessary.    (Paragraph 120).              PART IV;   DIVISION OF FUNCTION AND GENERAL.         The  Conference feels that to  some extent  these questions are covered by the recommendations as  to  the incidence of  highway costs and  licensing control,  and doeo  not consider it practicable to go much further than this  in the direction  of determining and prescribing respective functions.   (Paragraphs 121 - 12^)&apos;           m         The  Conference records its agreement, however, with the Royal Commission  on Transport  (Final Report, Paragraph 267) that it is not  &quot;in the national  interest to encourage further diversion  ef  heavy goods traffic from  the railways to the  roads&quot;, It agrees  in  recommending that  the Minister of Transport should obtain powers to  prohibit by regulation classes of traffic which are borne by  rail and  which, having regard to the character of the commodity and the  distance  to  go, are unsuitable for road haulage, from being transferred in future to the road, and recommends  that he should examine  the question and take the advice of  the  Central Advisory Committee,         The  Conference  conceives  that in the main transport will divide itself between  road  and  rail as the demand of those who   ^ require it, and the facilities  offered by those who provide it, determine.     &quot;The fairer  incidence of costs which we reoommendwill tend to make  the  result more economically sound.    But webelieve that   the best division of function will be obtainedmainly through the  deliberate effort of those engaged in road and rail transport  to  co-ordinate their services and give thepublic the full advantages  of complementary service&quot;.(Paragraphs 127 - 128).
         In conclusion the Conference states that such a comprehensivemeasure of agreement reached has necessarily been arrived at hy a process of give and take, and concessions on both sides.   &quot;It is expressed in a scheme of which each section is an integral and inter---dependent part of the whole.   It must not be assumed that if one partwas rejected we should remain agreed upon the remainder.   Conscious,therefore, that the rejection of one part of our scheme might endanger the whole, we have taken special pains to avoid prejudice to absentinterests.   In view of this necessary interdependence of the varioussubjects  we have dealt with we have tried to avoid any solution whichmight be acceptable to ourselves at the expense of others not represented.   The incidence of highway costs which we recommend, forexample, is not inconsistent with either a reduction, or a continuance,or an increase of the charges now levied on private motorists.  Increase:.in the rates to be levied on the class cf transport represented at ourConference do not prejudice the interests of other road users oreither central or local revenue authorities.   Moreover, our schemedoes not deprive trade and industry of the practical convenienceafforded by the existing liberty of the ancillary user&quot;.  (Paragraph153).         &quot;As regards our specific calculations and assessments, it isobvious that they are in the nature of the ca;3e based to a considerable extent upon an appreciation of the importance of numerous factors uponwhich individual judgment will differ.   Those who examine our proposals primarily from the point of view of any one of the maininterests concerned will doubtless consider that we have given too little or too much weight to specific factors.    But we venture tosuggest that the fact that a Conference, composed as ours is ofrepresentatives of both railway and road transport, has been able tomake unanimous recommendations, gives a strong presumption that,although we may have erred on this point or that, the scheme as awhole may be regarded as affording a fair basis upon which the different sections of the great inland transport Industries can develop&quot;.(Paragraph 1^5).
Appendix II,  111.   With this preface we make the following recommendations:-    A. All ovmers of goods motor vehicles used on public         highways (both hauliers and ancillary users) shall  hold         an operating licence.         Note.- No charge shall be made for this licence;   each                    motor owner paying all that should be                    required of him in the iorm of his ordinary                    revenue licence duty and through the petrol                    duty.    B. The licence shall be conditional upon payment of         reasonable wages and observance of proper conditions  of         service, in respect of the driver, and upon an         undertaking by the owner that the vehicles employed         under the licence are and will be maintained in a         proper condition of fitness.         Note.(i).- If any of  the  vehicles  are found to be                    not so maintained, the licence may be  ax                    once suspended in respect of such vehicles.         Note (ii).- It is contemplated that the proposed  local                    licensing authorities will ascertain and                    publish the local standards of wages,  etc.,                    prevailing;  and will be prepared to                    consider evidence that the rates and                    conditions applied by a particular applicant                    for a licence are below this standard  in                    deciding whether to grant or renew the                    licence.   No attempt has been made to work                    out the precise method for enforcing this                    principle, as this can be done better  by the                    Minister of Transport and Minister of                    Labour,         Note (iii).- As regards fitness, it is not considered                    that prior or periodical examination of                    goods vehicles is necessary;  but that any                    vehicle might be examined and, if found                    unfit, the licence in respect of it should                    be withdrawn or suspended.    C. A plate (differing in colour for hauliers and ancillary         users) shall be affixed to each vehicle,  giving the   )         number of the owner&apos;s licence and an individual number.         This shall (as in the case of public service         (passenger) vehicles now) be  additional to the revenue         licence plate.   In applying  for a licence the         applicant shall attach a list  of the vehicles which  he         desires to be licensed, giving particulars of the         registration numbers, unladen weights and maximum loads         (and these particulars should also appear on the         vehicle).    If a margin of vehicles is required  for         permissible expansion during  the licensing period,  the         requirement shall be stated in the application, and         registration particulars and  other information supplied         as the vehicles are brought into use.
9 0 l  b x     Note.- As appears &quot;below, the statement of the number                of vehicles required hy an ancillary user,                while being utilized for record, would not                be queetioned.D. The licensing authority shall grant the licences     requested by a haulier except where the grant would be     in whole or in part against the public interest on     consideration&apos;of the following factors   (i) any excess in the existing transport^facilities           suitable to meet the public-requirements to be           served by the applicant;  (ii) any actual or prospective congestion or overloading           of the roads; (iii) the licensing authority shall be entitled to call           for and take into consideration particulars of           the convictions registered against the applicant           or his employees for the previous year- in           respedt of offences  in connection with his road           transport vehicles;  or of his bankruptcy;  (iv) the licensing authority shall act subject to such           directions as he may receive from the Minister           Of Transport, who shall be. advised for the           purpose by a new permanent Central Advisory           Committee of appropriate composition to be set           up for the purpose;   (v) he shall publish in a suitable form periodical           statements of applications for new licences with           the date by which any memorandum of objection           must be forwarded to h:u.   He shall consider           lany Memorandum so received and may, at his           discretion, ask for oral evidence in svtpport or           Answer to it.   But he shall not be precluded           from granting temporary interim licences.E. An ancillary user shall be granted freely such licences     as he may request ior the carriage of his own goods,     subject to the conditions specified in B and C but not     in D above.   The holder of an ancillary licence shall after due     notice be prohibited from carying any other goods than     nis own whether ior reward or reciprocal service;     except as regards vehicles confined to a radius of     ^0 miles from his place of business.P. There shall be a right of appeal from the decisions of     the Local Licensing Authorities.     Note.- We consider that the Minister of Transport                should arrange a machinery of appeal on the                advice of the Central Advisory Committee                proposed in &apos;ID&quot; above.   We consider it of                great importance that this should be such                as to avoid delay and in particular legal                expense, the procedure being such., lor                example, aa to wake the employment of                counsel unnecessary and unsuitable.
2??hi hi ht  112.   In the introduction of the above system we presume-that care would be taken to give such notice, to frame theregulations in such a way, and to make such arrangements,  aswill prevent unnecessary disturbance and hardship.    Weconsider, for example, that all hauliers already in business(or ancillary users employing some of their vehicles partly inhaulage operations who apply for a haulier&apos;s licence for suchvehicles) when our Conference was appointed in March lastshould without question receive their first year&apos;s  licence forthe number (or equivalent tonnage) of vehicles employed bythem at the time of the licence application.   Similarly,  weconsider that reasonable notice should be given before the enforcement of the prohibition against ancillary userscarrying the goods of others for reward or reciprocal service.

</content>
</cab>
