<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/232/0 images: 306-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                                            9on      Zii                                                                              b d      t-v     [This document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]                      Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1932.SECRET.CP. 2S7 (32).                                                Copy No.........1......                                   CABINET.Reports by Local Governments on the  Political Situation in India.   I circulate for the information of my colleagues the latest weekly reports from theLocal Governments in India.                                                                        S. H.     INDIA OFFICE,   23rd August 1932.Government  of India.   Following is brief appreciation of the  first reactions to the Communal decision asshown in the Press.   Announcement has aroused interest  unequalled by any  otherpublication  since the Simon Report.  Press of all shades  of opinion has been filledfor days with comments and editorials to  the exclusion of other news.   Movement of opinion on the whole follows the lines anticipated.   The NationalistPress almost unanimously professes intense indignation over the award, but as  these papers are predominantly Hindu, it is difficult  at present to  disentangle the protestsbased on genuine Nationalist feeling from those inspired by Hindu Communalistmotives.   The only important Indian-owned paper, expressing Hindu point of  view,which extends some sort of approval is Justice.   All the other Nationalist papers ranging from Liberal organs, such as Hindu andLeader, to extremist ones, like the Free Press Journal, Bombay Chronicle, HindustanTimes or  Advance express vehement condemnation of the award generally and of themaintenance of separate electorates^in particular, general contention being  that it is expressly designed to disintegrate the Nationalist movement  and perpetuate Communalstrife.  Sikh denunciations are at least as vehement  as the Hindu,  and undoubtedlyrepresent very strong  feelings.  A  number of influential Sikh leaders  in  Simla,including Jogendra Singh and Sundar Singh Majithia, have  signed manifesto which,inter alia, declares that the decision of  His Majesty&apos;s  Government has  shaken theSikhs&apos; faith  in British sense  of justice and fair play,  and there has been some ratherwild talk of  Sikhs endeavouring to secede from  the Punjab.   Another  line is to declare that  they want no change in the  present Constitutionif this is the alternative.  Ujjal Singh and Sampuran Singh  have resigned from  the consultative Committee.   On the other hand, qualified approval of the award has been expressed by a numberof moderate political   leaders, including Sapru,  Patro,  Setalvad, Ali  Imam  andRamaswami  Mudaliyar, who  urge that  unless  the award  is accepted and  worked,  ipending  the spontaneous  Indian  settlement of the Communal problem, introduction.of Constitution that will  function  must  inevitably be  delayed.  This  is important,and  it is possible that those  Hindu leaders who are  more interested in nationalismthan  communalism will, as soon as the first wave of  excitement has spent itself, as awhole come  round to this point of view.   Muslim  reaction to  the award cannot altogether  be  judged from the  Press, forthey are naturally reluctant to declare  themselves openly as satisfied.  But  there seems to be little doubt that Punjab Muslims are  pleased, and  Bengal  Muslims,though protesting and to some extent disappointed, are likely gradually to realise thesolid advantages they have gained.   Muslims in the Provinces, where Hindus are in amajority, generally appear satisfied.   As regards the Depressed  Classes, Rajah has, of course, expressed disapproval,but nothing much has yet been heard from the Ambedkar group.  It should be borne in mind  that Ambedkar has no Press, and there is  probably much more real support for his point of view among the oomumnity than outward signs might indicate.   Protests  hitherto made with regard to the method of representation provided forwomen have been merely incidental.      1148   60  8.32.....II.............i iiiiiiinniiim&quot;iiiniiiiiiiiiKiniiiTnnnri nmn.ui nil&apos; nBrnillllliiililirilllllil liWIMMIwm
    Joshi has expressed himself satisfied so far as labour representation is concerned, though he has protested against retention of separate electorates.    Europeans, Anglo-Indians and Indian Christians generally appear to feel that the award  safeguards  their interests adequately.   Attitude adopted  by English-owned Press generally  has been  distinctly  helpful.   Sensible leading articles and  other comments have been published by the Statesman, Times of India, Civil and Military Gazette, Madras Mail and also  Pioneer, which is  now under Indian  management. Statement by Executive Committee of the Council of European Associations declares that so far as the Communal seats are concerned community has been given satisfactory increase proportionate to increase in the size of the Legislatures, but contends that in apportioning the seats for European commercial and planting interests, same principle has not been followed. Delhi.    There has been some picketing of cloth shops  by Congress and  liquor  shops by the Jamiatul Ulema. and arrests have been made in consequence.  Section 3 : arrests, 2. Total detained, G.  Section 4:  fresh orders, nil.  Total to date in respect of whom orders are in force, 28.   Convictions to date for orders, 9. Bombay.    The districts have been quiet.  Announcement of  Communal Award has so far caused  little excitement.   Agitation  directed from Mysore still continues in Ivanara District.  In  Bombay City Congress  hirelings  made  demonstrations in Courts on 12th, but their activities attracted little attention.   Attempted raids on Secretariat &quot;building on the 18th and 19th were easily frustrated.   The attempt on the 18th was watched by  the  India League Delegation,  accompanied by  Govind, son  of Pandit Malaviya.   Altogether  67 arrests  were  made.   Desultory picketing continued; 22  picketers were  arrested during the week.   Partial hartal  was observed on the 18th  on account of  arrest of  Miss Slade.   Ordinance  10. Section 3:  arrests, 14 ; total  under detention, 78.   Section 4  : orders, 47;  total in force,  857.   Section 17 : convictions, 8.  Two buildings in Sholapur  have been  notified under section 59 and seized. Bengal.    Last week was the quietest since beginning of civil disobedience movement, which, for time being, is practically dead.  Section 3 : arrests, 14.  Section 4: orders issued, 34 ; in  force, 246 ;  convictions, 64.Madras.    The situation remains quiet.   There is nothing important to report. Central Provinces.    The week has been uneventful.  Prosecutions, 9 : convictions, 13.&quot;United Provinces.    Trains  continue to be stopped by Congress volunteers and telegraph  wires cut. Release-of many local political leaders on termination of sentence  is causing renewedactivity in some places.  Little comment, other than journalistic, on Communal Awardhas been  reported  hitherto.  Orders under Ordinance, Section 3, none;  Section  4, 7, with 2 convictions.   Convictions for the week under  Ordinance, 21;  under ordinary law, 82.   Allahabad  again  prominent;  Total  convictions  to date, 11,093.   Releases and apologies, 2,804.Punjab.    Congress remains negligible.   Political  arrests under ordinary  law,  7; under Ordinances, 2.   No fresh  action under sections 3 or 4.  Number  of  persons served under section  4  further reduced  to 53.  Total under restraint for infraction of such orders  remains  31.  Communities  are still  considering  their  attitude  towards Communal Award..  Muslims generally content,  but Sikhs and Hindus contemplate campaign for continuance of existing  regime.  They advocate peaceful and  constitu- tional methods, and communal situation continues easier.
North-West  Frontier Province.   Section 3 : arrests, nil; total detained, 8.  Section 4 :  arrests,  3;  total orders inforce, 458.  With regard to Mohmand  situation, negotiations are now in progress with Afghan Government with a view  to summoning joint jirga to settle presentdispiite between Upper Mohmand and Halimzai.  Chances of dispute being settled by negotiations are now considerably enhanced.Bihar and Orissa.   The situation  is quiet.  One order under section 4, Ordinance, issued.  Total inforce, 4.  Figures from  one district have not been received.  Total convictions up tothe 14th August, 9,152.Assam.   There is nothing to report.Ajmer Merwara.   There have been six arrests in Ajmer  and vicinity, but no trouble elsewhere.From the Resident, Mysore.   The weekly report from Coorg and Bangalore is the same as last week.

</content>
</cab>
