<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/9/6 images: 46-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT &quot;Printed for the War Cabinet.  September 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)244th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 244 (40).Copy^No.  A9CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, September 6, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Lord Privy Seal. Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,    The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister without Portfolio. Minister of Aircraft Production.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War(Items 5 and 6).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Minister of Supply (Items 5and 6).General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff (Items 5and 6).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty(Items 5 and 6).The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade (Item 6).Mr. Ralph Assheton, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofLabour and National Service (Items 5and 6).Air Marshal Sir Richard Peirse,Vice-Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-5).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.[21736]b
WAR CABINET 244 (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Aircraft Production  ...      ...       ...      ...      ...      ...      33Creation of new capacity in U.S.A.2      Honours and Decorations     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      33Proposed award to civilian war workers.3      Royal messages of condolence ...       ..,      ...      ...      334      The Home Guard      ..................      335      Aircraft Production  ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      34Priority for construction of new airfields.6      Priority Policy ......       ............      34Proposed changes of machinery.
1. The War Cabinet had before them the following documents : (1) Memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production inwhich the War Cabinet was invited to choose between two schemes to produce 3,000 and 1,250 aircraft a; monthrespectively (W.P. (40) 354).(2) Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,explaining the financial implications of the Minister of aircraft Production^ proposals (W.P. (40) 355).A record of the discussion is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet (a) Authorised the Minister of Aircraft Production to do his best to obtain capacity in the United States producing3,000 aircraft per month.(&amp;) Agreed that the scheme should be reviewed when the firstheavy dollar payments became due.(c) Invited the Minister of Aircraft Production and theChancellor of the Exchequer to keep the finance of thescheme under constant observation, and in particular totake all practicable steps to persuade the United StatesReconstruction Finance Corporation to put up thecapital expenditure.(d) Took note that every endeavour would be made to persuade the United States authorities to adopt our types, butthat this might, not be consistent with the United StatesReconstruction Finance Corporation bearing the capitalexpenditure involved.Honours andDecorations.Proposed awardto civilian warworkers.2. The War Cabinet-Invited the Prime Minister to consider recommending HisMajesty to grant honours and decorations in connectionwith civilian war work, including the work of the manage-ments and staffs of munitions aaid aircraft factories andthe services of A.R.P. workers of all kinds.Royal Messagesof Condolence.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 97thConclusions,Minute 13.)3.   The War Cabinet-Agreed that consideration should be given to the questionwhether His Majesty should now be advised to extend theRoyal Messages of Condolence to cover the relatives of allpersons killed by enemy action.The home guard.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 226thConclusions,Minute 4.)4.   The War Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister and the Secretary ofState for War were in consultation as to the desirabilityof giving a more regular status to the Home Guard.[21736]Creation of new capacity inU.S.A.
WAR CABINET 244 (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Aircraft Production  ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      33Creation of new capacity in U.S.A.2      Honours and Decorations     ...      ...      ...      ...       ...      33Proposed award to civilian war workers.3      Royal messages of condolence ...      ..,      ...      ...      334      The Home Guard      ..................      335      Aircraft Production  ...      ...       ...      ...      ...      ...      34Priority for construction of new airfields.6      Priority Policy ..................      34Proposed changes of machinery.
1. The War Cabinet had before them the following documents :- (1) Memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production inwhich the War Cabinet was invited to choose between two schemes to produce 3,000 and 1,250 aircraft a monthrespectively (W.P. (40) 354).(2) Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,explaining the financial implications of the Minister of aircraft Production^ proposals (W.P. (40) 355).A record of the discussion is contained in the Secrefcary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet-(a) Authorised the Minister of Aircraft Production to do his best to obtain capacity in the United States producing3,000 aircraft per month.Agreed that the scheme should be reviewed when the firstheavy dollar payments became due.Invited the Minister of Aircraft Production and theChancellor of the Exchequer to keep the finance of thescheme under constant observation, and in particular totake all practicable steps to persuade the United StatesReconstruction Finance Corporation to put up thecapital expenditure.id) Took note that every endeavour would be made to persuade the United States authorities to adopt our types, butthat this might not be consistent with the United StatesReconstruction Finance Corporation bearing the capitalexpenditure involved.(c)Honours andDecorations.Proposed awardto civilian warworkers.2. The War Cabinet-Invited the Prime Minister to consider recommending HisMajesty to grant honours and decorations in connectionwith civilian war work, including the work of the manage-ments and staffs of munitions and aircraft factories andthe services of A.R.P. workers of all kinds.Royal Messagesof Condolence.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 97thConclusions,Minute 13.)The home guard.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 226thConclusions,Minute 4.)3.   The War Cabinet Agreed that consideration should be given to the questionwhether His Majesty should now be advised to extend theRoyal Messages of Condolence to cover the relatives of allpersons killed by enemy action.4.   The War Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister and the Secretary ofState for War were in consultation as to the desirabilityof giving a more regular status to the Home Guard.[21736]b 2Creation of new capacity inU.S.A.
5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum of theMinistry of Aircraft Production (W.P. (40) 353) asking for aspecial priority, higher than &quot; Works and Buildings Priority A,&quot;for the construction of 50 new airfields for the accommodation of aircraft Storage Units.The Minister of Aircraft Production explained that he proposed to construct airfields of a comparatively inexpensive type.They would have no hangars or concrete runways : the aircraft would probably be stored in small garages each taking two aircraft.Many of the new airfields would be in remote parts of this countryand in Scotland and in Northern Ireland. He proposed as soon aspossible to hand back to the Air Ministry a number of the aerodromes now in use by his Department.The Minister of Supply pointed out that the grant of thespecial priority desired by the Minister of Aircraft production would necessarily operate to some extent to defer the completion ofother essential works, for example, filling factories.The Minister of Aircraft Production said that he would gladlyaccept the ruling of the Minister without Portfolio on the priority of any item as to which there was a difference of opinion between departments.The War Cabinet-Gave general approval to the proposals in W.P. (40) 353,subject to the Minister without Portfolio determining any difference of opinion between Departments as to the priority to be given to any Works and Buildings Servicesaffected by this decision.Priority Policy.proposed changes ofmachinery.(previous reference:W.M. (40)229thConclusions.)6. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister without Portfolio (W.P. (G.) (40) 222), setting out a revised plan recommended by the Production Council (the Ministerof Aircraft Production dissenting) for giving effect to prioritypolicy.The Production Council proposed to withdraw the generalpriority direction given to firms, and to issue decisions as topriorities in future to the Priority Committees, the Departments,the Area Boards and the Raw Material Controls for guidance indealing with allocations and in framing programmes. Firms would receive any necessary guidance from the Departments, who wouldbase their instructions on the general priority decisions, and would act within their allocations of materials and manufacturing capacity. Difficulties arising in factories working for more thanone Department would be resolved by Area Boards as far as possible,or by the Priority Committees.The Minister without Portfolio said that the Departmentsconcerned had preferred a scheme on the lines proposed to analternative suggestion made by the Select Committee on national expenditure in their Tenth Report. He outlined the working ofthe scheme proposed.The Minister of Supply said that the stages that should befollowed to give effect to priority were as follows : (1) The broad strategic policy should be settled and the priority of arms to give effect thereto.(2) In the light of this priority, Departments should state their requirements of munitions.(3) These munitions should be broken down into the materialsrequired.Priority for construction ofnew airfields.(previous erence:W.M. (40)239thConclusions,Minute 11.)
(4) The materials required should be compared with theavailable supply, increased as far as practicable.(5) On this comparison, an allocation should be made to departments concerned.Under the present system, Departments scrambled for availablematerials and overstated their demands. This was shown by thevery large demands which had been made for drop forgings andstampings. These demands had, however, now declined, and it seemed that the difficulties in regard to drop forgings and stampingsmight be diminished without great difficulty.Under the present system, all demands for aircraft tended tohave priority over all other needs, including, for example, thespecial types of ammunition required by fighter aircraft. Thisshowed the need for a balanced programme.The Prime Minister pointed out that in several respects thearmy programme was not making satisfactory progress. TheMinister of Supply clearly thought that satisfactory progress couldnot be made under the present arrangements. He (the PrimeMinister) assumed, however, that the present system was onlyresponsible for difficulties in so far as there were clashes betweenthe needs of Departments. The new procedure proposed would notfundamentally alter the position of factories working wholly forthe Ministry of Supply or the Admiralty.The Prime Minister also referred to the very large demands made for production of army vehicles.The Secretary of State for War said that only 5 Divisions had their first line transport complete. The army realised that theywould have to do with make-shift vehicles fox the second linetransport, but if make-shift vehicles were used for first linetransport, the Divisions so equipped could not operate acrosscountry.The Minister of Aircraft Production asked that the present procedure for giving effect to the priority policy should continue inforce for a further fortnight, subject to further considerationthereafter. The aircraft industry was going through a verydifficult time and he was anxious that they should not be disturbedin any way by a change of procedure at this critical juncture.In reply to a suggestion that it would take a fortnight to giveeffect to the new procedure now proposed, the Minister said that, ifthe Cabinet decided in principle to change the present system, thisdecision would become known and the firms in the aircraft industry would be disturbed. The Minister added that, under the systemproposed, powers exercised in regard to priority would be taken away from his Ministry and vested in a Committee. This would destroy the effective control exercised by his Department.The President of the Board of Trade agreed that priorityquestions arose only at the particular points where the programmesoverlapped. The new procedure proposed would, however, showmore clearly where these overlaps occurred, and would limit theirdisturbing effects. At the present time there was considerableconfusion, and the export trade suffered more than would benecessary if matters were conducted in a more orderly way. Thepresent general priority direction had only been intended to cover a period of three months, and was not suitable for a long-term programme.The Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour saidthat the essence of any satisfactory scheme was to secure co-opera-tion between Departments. The only system of priority whichwould work satisfactorily was a system based on allocation. At thepresent time the Minister of Labour was at a loss to know whatinstructions to give to employment exchanges.   He ought to be in
a position to know whether firms were entitled to the priority whichthey claimed. This could not be done under the present system.There was the further point that changes in the priority directioncould be more easily made if the priority direction had not beenbroadcast to a large number of firms.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the Admiraltyfavoured the adoption of a scheme on the lines proposed in theMemorandum by the Minister without Portfolio. At the presenttime, the Admiralty thought that some of the capacity forforgings, &amp;c, which had been laid down on their initiative, andwhich they had now given up to other Departments, was not being used to meet the immediate needs of those Departments.The Prime Minister said that he assumed that the Minister of aircraft Production could not claim that the existing priorityafforded to aircraft was meant to be an unlimited and indefinitepriority. He thought it was important to define the programmes towhich priorities should extend.The Minister of Aircraft Production agreed. The aircraft programme was, in fact, limited by the possibilities of aero-engine production. He had submitted a programme showing the aircraft to be produced month by month. He hoped that his department would be able to achieve the figures there set out, but saw no possibility of exceeding them.The Minister without Portfolio said that he could not acceptthe Minister of Aircraft Production^ view that the scheme nowproposed would vest the exercise of priority powers in a Committee.He thought it was very important that Departments should know what would be left for them when the essential needs of aircraft had been met.The Minister of Aircraft Production said that, provided theexisting system could remain unchanged, he would submitparticulars of his Departments requirements of steel&quot; of all typesfor the ensuing three months.The Prime Minister thought that, while the discussion had beenhelpful towards elucidating the problem, a final decision could notbe reached that morning. He would like rather longer to considerthe matter. He therefore proposed that the Minister of aircraft production^ suggestion that he should submit the particulars ofhis requirements of steel under various heads within the next threemonths should be accepted, and that discussion as to the procedure of priority should be adjourned for a fortnight.The War Cabinet approved this suggestion.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1.September 6, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
