<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/54/33 images: 250-271</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1944.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.   36W.P. (44) 483.3CKA August, 1944.WAR CABINET.RUSSIA IN 1944.Note by the Prime Minister and Minister of Defence.MY colleagues will be interested to see the attached article which was sentto me by the Editor of the Daily Herald.W. S. C.10, Downing Street, S. W. 1,30th August, 1944.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government confidential.FACTS AND  TENDENCIES  IN  WARTIME,  1944.Memorandum by Ronald Matthews,Daily Herald Moscow Correspondent 1942-44.ANGLO-AMERICAN correspondents in Moscow during the war years havebeen able to present a fairly accurate, if second-hand, picture of Russia&apos;s war effort; enough anyhow to convince the outside world that the Soviet army is really fighting and the Soviet people really working for victory. But the strictnessof the Moscow censorship in dealing with almost anything but military storieswhich have already appeared in the Soviet press makes the presentation of agenuinely all-round picture of wartime Russia almost impossible. This memo-randum is an attempt to fill in these gaps in background information. Sincetransmission of some of these facts has been stopped by the censorship on thegrounds that they might be unfavourable propaganda for the regime, the memo-randum may appear as if it were designed to li pan &quot; the U.S.S.R. That is by nomeans its design.I have roughly divided the material into three sections : Facts of daily life(a) Moral and (b) Material, and general tendencies observed in the regime. Ithink it may serve as a unifying thread linking the various facts together if Iindicate in advance the conclusions about the regime to which I have been drawnduring my stay there. These are briefly, that there is in the Soviet Union an increasing trend towards social conservatism, with a revivified family life as oneof its bases, and a parallel trend towards the hardening and perpetuation of theexisting social hierarchy. This trend could already be noticed before the war,but it has been speeded up immensely since 1941. British Conservatives are stillthinking of Russia as a revolutionary country. As usual, they are years out of date in their thinking. I cannot say what Russia&apos;s foreign policy will be afterthe war (though I may hazard a guess later), but internally, and on the base of herexisting property-owning system she is probably to-day the most conservativecountry in Europe and will probably be after the war the only stable State on theContinent. The proviso about her existing property-owning system as a founda-tion for her conservatism is important, since there is no question at all of Russiagoing back on the principle of State ownership (she will be needing a great dealof foreign assistance after the war, but I should be surprised if any concessionswere granted to foreigners) or of the de-collectivisation of the farms, though itseems likely that a high proportion of the peasants would like to go back to private -ownership.Facts of Everyday Life:  (a) Moral.1. It is convenient to start with moral facts, because almost the first thing that strikes a resident foreigner newly arrived in Russia is the atmosphere ofsuspicion and spying which surrounds him. The roots of this attitude, of course,go back very far : those who know pre-revolutionary Russia declare that even then the ordinary Russian tended to regard the foreigner as the South Sea islanderregards objects which are tabu: to regard him, that is to say, as at once admirableand horrible; admirable because of his knowledge of western technique, horriblebecause, perhaps, of his lack of &quot; soul.&quot; Foreign intervention in the Civil War,and the foreign policy towards Russia of the Western Powers in the between-the-wars period were naturally grounds for the confirmation of this attitude. It willbe noted that I talk of a historical &apos;&apos; tendency &apos;&apos; on the part of ordinary russians to regard the foreigner as a tabu object. I do so because the average Russian is naturally so open-hearted and friendly that whatever his prepossessions he wouldprobably mix with foreigners freely if he were allowed. But, apart from a period during the New Economic Policy era in the twenties, and a shorter period, beforethe Purges, in the middle thirties mixing with foreigners has been strictly and effectively discouraged.[27842] B
One does, of course, meet Russians socially in Moscow from time to time; the big official receptions, for instance, give an opportunity for this. And one of themost disheartening experiences for a raw foreigner is to meet a Russian at some such gathering, to invite him out to a meal and to find that, without a word ofexplanation or apology, he simply fails to turn up. He has, of course, been warnedoff. This warning off sometimes goes to the most amazing extremes. Thus about ayear ago the Australian and Soviet Governments decided to establish diplomatic relations and the British Ambassador, on learning the (name of the SovietMinister-designate to Canberra, asked him out to dinner; he was refused permis-sion to come. The girl friends of officers and men of the British Military mission and of members of the Diplomatic Corps are all sooner or later threatened with. arrest and exile if they continue their association, even if, as is quite often thecase, the association is entirely innocent. In some cases these threats have beencarried out. There is no question of sexual morality being the ground of thesewarnings, for when girls marry their foreign boy friends and apply, throughthe Moscow Police Visas Department, for release from Soviet citizenship in orderto be able to accompany their husbands abroad, they are invariably treated to along lecture by the official in charge on the folly and unpatriotism of theirmarriage.My marriage to a Russian girl enabled me to appreciate even more fully the effectiveness of this official discouragement of mixing writh foreigners. Very few of my wife&apos;s friends felt it prudent to continue visiting her after our marriage.Only four of them attended our wedding reception, where there were present suchdangerous persons as the British Ambassador and the heads of the british military Mission. One of these four was dismissed from her post a week later,writh no reason given. Her post was with V.O.K.S., the Society for EncouragingCultural Relations with Foreigners. (It would appear that only the highestofficials of this organisation, the stoutness of whose Cominunist principles is abovesuspicion, are permitted to mix with foreigners at official receptions.)My wife discovered for me a washerwoman who did my shirts better, more quickly and.more cheaply than did the hotel laundry. After three washes shedeclined to do any more &quot; because it drew unfavourable attention to her to haveforeign linen hanging on her line.&quot;It may seem surprising that since foreign correspondents (and&quot;other residentforeigners) live in a social void, as far as Russians are concerned, and have littleopportunity of gaining first-hand information about anything remotely concerningState security, it should be worth the police&apos;s while to spy on them. Yet spiedon they are constantly, their secretary-translators, messengers, chauffeurs and the servants at their hotel being most of them required to submit regular reports tothe police on them. When, before our marriage, my wife first joined me as secretary, she was almost immediately requested by the police to submit regularreports on my activities.Many people had hoped that when the Russians and ourselves became Alliesthis suspicious attitude towards us would cease. There has not been the slightestsign of such a change so far (to February 1944). This suspicion does not onlyaffect social intercourse, it often goes far in minor ways to hamper co-operation in the war effort. When towards the end of the Moscow Conference last yearB.O.A.C. officials in Moscow enquired of officials at the Moscow main airport thelength of the runway, in order to discover whether it was safe for Mr. Eden&apos;sLiberator to take off with a full load of petrol, it was only after the foreign secretary&apos;s direct intervention that, after four days of vain efforts, they succeeded in discovering the figure. As is kown, the establishment of a regular B.O.A.C.Britain-Moscow air line has now (April 1944) been held up for nearly a year,the only real reason, in the opinion of British officials in Moscow, being that theRussians object to foreign, even Allied, pilots flying over their territory. TheBritish Military Mission compiled a list of what they called &apos;&apos; vexatiousrestrictions &quot; on Allied military activities in Russia. There were such things asthe impounding of British merchantmen&apos;s anti-aircraft ammunition when inMurmansk harbour, so that their guns could not fire at hostile aircraft. Therewas last year&apos;s last-moment refusal by the Russians of permission for theestablishment in North Russia of a Hampden and Catalina Wing of the R.A.F.to protect the (as we contended) inadequately-protected final stage of the northernconvoys into port. This refusal, which came after stores for the Wing had alreadybeen landed, led to a month&apos;s-long suspension of the northern convoys. Therewas the extraordinary incident when, a northern convoy having been very heavily attacked and a large number of British seamen lying wounded in Archangelhospital, the Admiralty sent out a special fast hospital ship with doctors,
medicaments and nurses to relieve the pressure on the local Russian medical staff.In the circumstances there was no time to apply for visas the ordinary way and await their arrival in London, so the Russians were asked to treat this as aspecial case and have the visas ready at the port. They did not do so, doctors,nurses and stores were not allowed to land and, after a few days hanging aboutin Archangel, the hospital ship was forced to return.Foreigners in Moscow often ask themselves when this attitude towards them will change. The speculation is complicated by the fact that one does not knowto what extent the isolation of foreigners may not be due to the inertia of theadministrative machine, which, having been told some years back, in entirely different circumstances, to enforce it, and having never received orders to cancelit, mechanically continues to execute a now out-of-date policy. I know that sir Archibald Clark Kerr has at least once mentioned to Stalin his socialdifficulties. And though Stalin assured him : &quot; you can meet who you like.Who would you like to meet?&apos;&quot; I gather he hasn&apos;t found the situation changevery much. Some people maintain that the launching of an effective Second Frontwill radically change the attitude towards Allied nationals : that should soon be seen. I am inclined myself to doubt the probability of such a speedytransformation. I rather think that till the Russians have raised their productivecapacity a good deal further, they will do little to encourage their citizens mixingwith foreigners, from whom they would be bound to learn of the (up to the moment)greater material comforts available in the capitalist countries.All this does not make pleasant writing. But I feel it essential these thingsshould be known to responsible people in the cause of realism. I very muchsympathise with writers in the weekly reviews who look forward, e.g., to asweeping exchange of university students between Britain and the U.S.S..R. Butto look on such a step at the moment as anything more than a dream is grosslyto delude oneself.2. This attitude of suspicion towards foreigners makes the task ofcorrespondents in Moscow difficult in the extreme. It is complicated by thecomplete lack of co-operation shown by the Press Bureau of the Soviet ForeignOffice, to which they are accredited. Since the beginning of the war it has been laid down that correspondents&apos; contacts with Soviet organisations may only bemade through the Press Bureau, and the Press Bureau, even though acorrespondent may harry it with visits and telephone calls, will take days toarrange the simplest interview. Towards the end of last year I became exasperated(as all correspondents do from time to time) at my complete inability to obtainfirst-hand material for feature articles, and had a long talk with M. Palgunov,head of the Press Bureau (who is also head of Tass). He received my complaintswith every sign of apparent sympathy, assured me the position would be rectifiedand suggested that I should submit to the Bureau a programme of interviews andvisits covering a period of some weeks, whose fulfilment in order he would thenarrange. On the 24th December I therefore submitted to him a list of nineteenrequests : I reproduce the first six to show their complete innocuity : (i) Interview with head of 281 school, Moscow, on subjects covered in his recent Izvestiya article about school discipline, &amp;c.(ii) Visit to one of new Suvorov Cadet Schools,(iii) Visit to Moscow People&apos;s Court,(v) Interview with Mayor Pronin on Moscow&apos;s plans for third war winter,(vi) Interview with representative of Planning Department to discussquestion of how far wartime transfer of industry eastwards is likelyto be maintained after war.By the time I left Moscow on the 21st February, only one of my 19 requestshad been fulfilled.I should say that the Press Bureau makes no sort of ideological discriinina-tion between correspondents. The representatives of the Daily Worker or adistinguished friend of Communism, such as Edgar Snow, are treated as badlyas the representative of the most reactionary paper. The Anglo-AmericanCorrespondents&apos; Association has made frequent protests about the Press Bureau&apos;sunco-operativeness, and has asked for such elementary conveniences as theappointment of regular spokesmen of the Foreign Office and the War Office, from whom authoritative interpretation of diplomatic and military events may beobtained. All its representations have been ignored, and from the rapidity ofMr. Palgunov&apos;s progress in his official career &quot;(he is now a regular guest at the[27842] n 2
big Kremlin banquets to distinguished foreign vistors) it is difficult to avoid theconclusion that his unfriendly treatment of the foreign Press meets with theapproval of his superiors.Correspondents often speculate on the reasons for the Press Bureau&apos;s attitudetowards them.  Three main reasons are usually suggested : (i) Distrust of foreigners as such referred to in (1).(ii) Conviction that the story of Russia&apos;s effort sells itself without anypandering to the correspondents (which is probably true as long asthe war goes on).(iii) The fact that, owing to the unwillingness to take responsibility whichinfects the Soviet civil service (not the army), it is safer for PressBureau officials to say no to correspondents&apos; requests than to say yes.3. The last sentence raises the question how far the atmosphere of constraintand fear referred to in (1) is felt by the mass of Russians, who do not have anopportunity of mixing with the dangerous foreigners. I should say it is less feltat the lower levels, but even there the humblest Soviet citizen cannot helprealising that, his life is regulated for him. There are, for instance, the regularwaves of &quot; voluntary contributions &quot; to national defence : the worker knows well that there is no question of dissenting when the party representative comes roundhis shop and tells him that &quot; it has been decided &quot; that everyone shall contributea month&apos;s pay to the army, and will he contribute his share. The worker knowshow spontaneous are the &quot; spontaneous meetings &quot; held in factories and farms allover the country at an hour&apos;s notice, to hail the sentences on the German, accusedin the Kharkov atrocit)r trial, or the triumph of Allied unity at the TeheranConference. On the higher levels, secret arrests and. disappearances are stillcommon. Rather more than a year ago Kapler, the distinguished cinema scenaristof &quot; Lenin in October.&quot; &quot;A Day of War&quot; and &quot;Stalingrad,&quot; and two of his associates were suddenly arrested and vanished. There has been no trial and nonews of them since, though in cinema circles two explanations are being offered :(i) that Kapler&apos;s ideological approach to the Stalingrad film was incorrect (what-ever that means), and (ii) that he, a married man, had been going about rathertoo much with Stalin&apos;s young daughter. During the October 1941 panic in moscow (to which I shall reefer later) the Police archives were among the vastquantities of official documents burned. But it is suggested that this puts thoseunfortunate enough to be suspected by the authorities in a more and not lessunhappy position since, with any exculpatory evidence there may be in theirdossiers destroyed with the rest, the police are free to imagine their past in themost lurid colours.4. The Communist party, whose negative defensive weapon the police is(I call propaganda its positive defensive weapon) has been allowed to grow very considerably since.the war. I say &quot; allowed to grow &quot; not &quot; grown,&quot; because sincethe party.&apos;s seizure of power in Russia, there has been something like a regularprocess of expansion and contraction in its membership; at one time it is regardedas more important to sweep into its ranks a high proportion of those displayingenthusiasm for (say) the war, or the latest Five Year Plan; at another to safe-guard its internal unity by eliminating those members who are not 100 per cent,trustworthy. A very great number of the latest recruits have come from the army.It is interesting that the political officers of the army (shorn now, of course, oftheir executive authority) do not seek to rouse their men&apos;s ardour by anytheoretical exposition of Communist principles, indeed, this is discouraged asbeing dry and pedantic; instead, they preach patriotism to them, and the waris known officially in Russia as &quot; the Great Patriotic War.&quot; It it notable that on civilian party platforms also orators since the war have also shunned doctrinalissues and have concentrated on practical problems.It may be true that a high percentage of Party members to-day are stilldisinterested enthusiasts. % But no one who knows Russia would do anything butlaugh at the assertion (still sometimes made) that Party members are all incor-ruptible. And now that the self-denying ordinance has been removed, under which members of the Party could not receive more than a certain maximum salary,a large number, of people are undoubtedly seeking membership for careeristmotives, since it is impossible to attain high executive position in any enterprisewithout being a member of the Party.5. Since returning to England, I have sometimes been asked: &quot;What ispublic opinion about the regime? &quot;   I can only reply that real public opinion
about the larger issues of State policy is non-existent in Russia, since it is manu-factured and distributed from above. And the process of manufacture anddistribution is astonishingly easy. It will be remembered, to give an example,how Mi. Wendell Willkie jeopardised his political career during and. after his visit to the U.S.S.R. in 1942 by his championship of the Soviet thesis that theAllies were holding up the launching of the Second Front from motives ofpolitical unfriendliness and military poltroonery, and that their leaders must be&quot; prodded&quot; into action. Two or three months ago, in a pronouncement in theUnited States, whose whole tenor was one of extreme friendliness to the U.S.S.R.,he referred in passing to the fact that, in American eyes, there was a problem ofthe future status of the Baltic States and a problem of the future frontiers ofPoland.. For these harmless assertions the Soviet Press came down on him like a ton of bricks, declaring that they were no more a concern of the United Statesthan the status of California was of Russia. And a day or two later, a friend of my wife&apos;s, a very intelligent person and candidate for membership of the Party,came into our hotel room and started a conversation about the next AmericanPresidential elections. She displayed great anxiety as to whether Rooseveltwould win, and explained it by saying : &quot; It would be dreadful if Willkie were elected; he is an enemy of the Soviet Union.&quot;It is, parenthetically, rather difficult for Moscow correspondents to knowhow to report these waves of manufactured opinion or enthusiasm. In the lateautumn of 1942, for instance, a certain collective farmer was reported in the papers as sending a gift of some hundreds of thousands of roubles to Stalin forthe construction of tanks and his letter to the Soviet Premier and Stalin&apos;s replywere printed in full. This lead was immediately followed by a spate of similarcontributions from all over the country, and for some three months of one of themost exciting periods of the war two pages of all the daily papers were filledevery day with the text of the donors&apos; letters to Stalin and Stalin&apos;s acknowlegement-ments, all printed verbatim : the bitterness of the Soviet war correspondents,whose dispatches were cut or held out entirely on account of this interminablesubscription list was considerable. All correspondents in Moscow know whatthe truth about this wave of gifts was. The scarcity of food had led to an enormous rise of prices on the (legal) open market, where the peasants are free to sell the non-State-requisitioned portion of their produce, and as a result a quite disproportionate amount of the country&apos;s money had found its way into their hands. It was essential for the authorities to redress the balance, and soa drive for &quot;voluntary&quot; gifts was launched.This, real, story of the wave of contributions the censorship naturally wouldnot allow to be sent. To have cabled the superficial story, of a spontaneous move-ment of sacrifice, which the censorship did permit, would have presented, a completely false picture of the situation. What was the duty of Moscow corres-coorespondents, then : to cable this distorted story, or to ignore the whole business ?In spite of this regimenting of opinion and action there are uncriticalfriends of the Soviet Union (the Moscow correspondent of the London Timescan, I think, be classified among these) who maintain that the U.S.S.R. is, in some sort of sense, a democracy. They have the very slenderest ground for theirargument. Till the late twenties the Communist Party was itself a democracy;not only were decisions reached by popular vote but they were quite often initiated,from below; now they are almost invariably initiated from above. It is on theseexceptions to the rule of initiative from above that the contenders for theU.S.S.R.&apos;s claim to the title of &quot; democracy &quot; fasten. They argue that if (say)this or that condition of living in an area of the country becomes so intolerableas to rouse widespread popular protest, the local Communist Party will take it up and matters will be rectified. It is quite easy to find examples of this in minormatters of administrative detail, and I am inclined to think that a recent not sominor constitutional change may also be due to pressure from below. All thosewho listened to M. Molotov&apos;s speech on the proposal to give autonomy in thefield of military and. foreign affairs to the constituent republics of the U.S.S.R.were struck by one thing : that at no point in his speech did he give what seemedin the least like a real reason for the step. I know, though, that during theGermans&apos; autumn 1942 advance into the Caucasus their approach was hailedat first with delight by some of the minor nationality groups, who joyfullyanticipated being freed from the dictatorship of Moscow. It is quite true thatafter a few days of German occupation they were clamouring for the Red army to send them in partisan leaders, but it seems quite likely that the earlier reaction,and the state of mind behind it, may have led Moscow to decide on theconstitutional change.
The strict control wielded by the Party and police renders it difficult for anypopular discontent which there&apos; may be with the regime as such to find voiceexcept by anecdotes; fresh ones, usually reflecting on the rigid thinking of thebureaucracy, are constantly being invented. I have been told by Russians who might have had an opportunity of knowing (though there was no way of checkingon it) that a high proportion of the peasants would gladly return to a system of individual small holdings. All I can say with any certainty about their state of mind is that there is undoubtedly considerable feeling among them against thetown workers; during the 1941 exodus from Moscow there were many instances of peasants attacking and looting cars taking Muscovites away to their evacua-tion homes. The older town workers realise that, though their money wages have risen since the N.E.P. period in the twenties (the tolerated partial returnto private enterprise alongside State production), their purchasing power is far less.But the average age of the Russian population is now so low that the vastpercentage of the town workers have never known any other regime than thatthey are now living under. On my way to the railway station of the Moscowsuburb where I spent last summer I fell in one day writh an elderly schoolmasterwho started to talk to me about the Atlantic Charter, and emphasised that whatRussia wanted most of all the Four Freedoms alluded to in it was freedom fromfear. It was, of course, extremely dangerous for him to speak so critically ofthe regime as he went on to do, but I should,think that people who allow them-selves to think of it openly in such critical terms are probably a very small minority, and are to be found mainly among the older generation.It its often asked whether wre shall see in the measurable future a relaxation in the Russian dictatorship. There are those who believe that such a relaxationwill prove possible wdien the U.S.S.R. has, as they put-it, &quot; solved the problem ofproduction &apos;; has, that is, raised its productive capacity to a height when it willbe able not only to maintain defence and heavy industries equal to those of thegreatest other Great Power, but also to supply its workers with consumer goodsin a stream equal to that provided in the Western European countries. Thoughshe has suffered immense war damage, Russia possesses enormous recuperativepowers, and I have heard the period needed to &quot; solve the problem of production &quot;estimated at from twenty-five to as little as ten years. The argument of thosewho expect to see the dictatorship relaxed when the problem of production issolved is, of course, that its main function is to dragoon the Russian worker intokeeping output rising, and that when this function has&quot; been fulfilled to a point where the TJ.S.S.R. is able to afford its citizens a standard of living comparablewdth that of its industrial rivals it will have exhausted its utility.There are, again, those optimists who contend that there may be a relaxation of the dictatorship immediately after the war. Though discipline is very strictin the Red Army to-day, it is generally agreed that there is a very much freerand less constrained atmosphere in it than there is in civil life. And those who take this optimistic view believe that when the demobilised soldiers return totheir homes and farms and factories after the war they will revolt at the ideaof being ordered about again by a nasty little Party boss or a horrid littlepoliceman.Both these views, of course, are mere guesses. And though the first seemsrational enough, anyone will realise that if a regime which had exhausted itsutility invariably climbed out of the saddle, most of the revolutions in historywrould never have happened. The Soviet police is to-day one of the strongestvested interests in the world; if the dictatorship were to be relaxed, the party would still probably maintain a good deal of its function of leadership, but thepolice would inevitably decline vastly in power and prestige. It is difficult to seethem consenting to this; if there were any real danger of it happening, I canquite easily see them unearthing a new &quot; plot &quot; against the regime and launchinga new purge. On the other hand, the leadership of the Party has always beenvery realistic. When the advent of the war saw a great upsurge of religiousfeeling in Russia, they switched off the State-supported anti-religious propa-ganda like an electric light, just as much (I am convinced) for internal reasonsas to impress their Allies. Should there be at any time an upsurge of feeling infavour of democracy, they would probably appear at least to bow to this, too.Though the lack of critical sense among the Russian public would make it easy for them to concede to the people the shadow of power while themselves retaining the substance.6. What has been said in (5) above about the freer atmosphere, in the red army raises the question to what extent there is to-day a contest of opinion
between the various organs of Soviet life, or between any one of them and communist Party, or within the Party itself. It is widely believed that there arecross-currents of opinion within the Party on quite a number of issues, thoughit should be emphasised that there is not the faintest question of any split within it, but merely of such divergences of view as with us, would be fought out openlyat a Labour Party Conference. It is asserted that one of the issues on whichthere is conflict is that of co-operation with the Allies versus isolationism;Stalin is widely credited with tending towards the co-operationist view, while Ihave heard it said that Shcherbakov, Vice-Commissar for War, and one of thecoming younger men on the Politburo, heads the isolationists. It is said that thepublication of the Pravda &quot;separate peace rumour &quot; story was a result of * theisolationists temporarily gaining the upper hand; all I can say for certain about this is that Litvinov, whom one would expect to be consulted about a matter ofthis kind, knew nothing about it beforehand and was as surprised and puzzled asanyone when he saw the report in the paper.Any conflict between the Party and any of the organs of Soviet life thearmy.or the civil service should theoretically prove impossible, since the party is omnipresent; all the big generals, all the heads of the Foreign Office and thegreat factories in fact, all the important executives of the country belong toit. I have heard it contended that some of the generals may be merely formalmembers of the Party, and thence it is sometimes argued abroad that one or more of them may aspire to the position of a General Monk after the war. I should regard this as in the highest degree improbable. If there were no other reason,the Soviet public knows little or nothing from its Press about the personalitiesof its great generals. It sees an occasional photograph of them; it sees their names in the Orders of the Day, in which Stalin thanks them for their latestvictory; it reads the announcement when they are awarded a new decoration.Beyond that it knows, from the newspapers, nothing, as I can testify, havingvainly tried to construct a biography of the late General Vatutin out of my files.There is little doubt, however, that there is some conflict between the variousorgans of Soviet life, and for the moment the police seem to be gaining the upperhand; most of the new appointees to the foreign diplomatic service are drawn from their ranks. I can give an example of the conflict between the police andthe army. In the summer of 1941 a British naval officer friend of mine,Captain F., arrived in Sebastopol as a liaison officer of the British military mission in Russia. His first night in mess he was approached by a political officer named Gusiev (brother of the present Ambassador in London, who alsooriginated with the police) who asked him to describe conditions in the british navy. F. willingly complied, but, when he declared that married ratings in thenavy got marriage allowances in addition to their pay, Gusiev told him he wasa liar, on the grounds that there were no marriage allowances in the Soviet navy,and that he knew conditions in it were better than in ours. There were two other british officers present in the mess that night, one of whom spoke fluent Russian,and in that language he requested Gusiev to withdraw his accusation against F.,who was considerably his superior in rank. Gusiev withdrew the word liar, andthe British officers imagined the incident to be closed.From what happened subsequently, however, it is evident that Gusiev becamefrightened at the language he had used, imagined that F. would put in a reporton him, and therefore decided to get his report to the Political Department of theNavy in first. For when some months later Sir Stafford Cripps had occasion to write a letter to Stalin, complaining of the lack of co-operation between theRussian military authorities and the British Military Mission, Stalin&apos;s replygave, as the last of a number of reasons for this lack of co-operation, that F. andtwo other British officers had been guilty, at Sebastopol, of &quot; anti-Soviet propa-ganda.&quot; Since the other two officers had only been in Sebastopol with F. on one night, he was speedily able to pin down the incident, and he and his colleagueslater left the country, since Sir Stafford was informed that they &apos;&apos; no longerpossessed the confidence of the Russian authorities.&quot;Perhaps the most interesting aspect of the affair, however, was the way. inwhich the Russian naval chief, Admiral Kuznetsov, took it. He informedAdmiral Miles, head of the naval section of the British mission, that &quot;he regretted that he had been deprived of the services of the three most valuablenaval officers in the whole mission through political interference over which hehad absolutely no control.&quot; And when Miles told him what had really happenedat Sebastopol, and informed him that &apos;&apos; Political Officer Gusiev no longerpossessed the confidence of the British authorities,&quot; Kuznetsov promised to look into it, and was able to inform him within a couple of days that Gusiev had been&quot;liquidated.&quot;
Facts of Everyday Life: (b) Material.7. Food shortage and food rationing came down on Russia very much moresuddenly than they did on us &quot;in England. This was, of course, because of theearly overrunning by the German armies of some of the richest food-producingareas in the U.S.S.R., and the impact was accelerated by the enormous reductionof civil, in favour of military, rail transport. The situation did not begin tobecome acute in Moscow, however, till after the panic of- October 1941, when theGermans nearly got into Moscow, and when undoubtedly a great deal of large-scale looting of food and other stores took place. Then quite suddenly Muscovitesfelt their belts tightened. And the situation was made more difficult by the factthat either the ration scales were framed too generously or (possibly owing to theabnormally severe and early winter) transport for a while completely broke down.For there were three months during which, though the ration cards provided for purchases of butter, meat, milk, eggs, tea, sugar, &amp;c, all that the ordinary citizenwas able in fact to buy was black bread.The food situation has fairly steadily improved since those winter months of1941-42, though the bread ration has twice been cut in recent months, probablyowing to the needs of the reconquered areas. The system by no means works outperfectly, and customers are frequently asked to take substitutes for the com-modities to which they are entitled, such as sweet biscuits for sugar, lard forbutter, tinned sausage for fresh meat. Even for children, fresh milk is almost-unobtainable on the ration : I felt myself very lucky when of the 12 litres of freshmilk monthly to which I was entitled (when living out of the hotel) on the diplomatic ration I managed to get two.As I explained in a feature in the Daily Herald (September 1942) there are several different scales of rations, those for Avar workers and manual workers,for white-collar workers and finally, the lowest, for-non-employed dependants.The differences in the food obtained by the various sections of the population are, however, far wider than these scales by themselves would seem to imply.If a citizen wants to be certain of a good choice of food it is very important for him to be registered at a good &quot; closed store.&quot; These shops are run for the benefitof the workers at the factories or other enterprises to which they are attached,and their families. A citizen who is registered at the Stalin Motor Worksstore or the Academy of Science store, in Moscow, will have when he draws hisration, a pretty wide choice of food-stuffs. If there is no shop attached to his placeof employment and he is registered at a neighbourhood store, where he is inscribedsimply because of his place of residence, he will not only have a narrower choicebut is much more likely to find the rationed goods exhausted when he comes to buy them.There are further forms of food privilege also. Those whom the Statedelights to honour such as (to my knowledge) distinguished artists are permitted to buy at their closed stores a certain value of goods each month over and abovethe ration quantity, at ration prices. The value of this will become apparentwhen I refer presently to the colossal expense of shopping at the only alternative to the State-owned stores, the (legal) open market. There are many jokes in moscow about &quot; Kremlin rations &quot; : all I can say about this is that during the black-bread-only months of 1941-42 my wife was invited to a party at the houseof a Commissar whose daughter she knew. At a time when most of Moscowwas on the starvation line every kind of food and drink appeared on the tableand most of the guests were unable to resist cramming their pockets with thedainties to take away.In almost every town or village in Russia there is an open market, licensedby the municipality, where collective farm peasants are permitted to come in and sell, at competitive prices, that portion of their common produce which theyare not required to sell at fixed prices to the State and also the produce of their individual allotments. Before the wrar, when food was plentiful, prices at thesemarkets did not vary much from those in the shops. Once the war started and food shortage began, they were able to ask just what they wanted : in the winter of 1941-42 they would tour the streets of Moscow, exchanging a sack-of potatoesfor a fur coat or a piano (a cottage piano fetched more potatoes than a grand,since it was more portable and fitted, more easily into a peasant hut). When Ivisited the Arbat market in Moscow in April 1943, potatoes and carrots wereselling at 80 roubles a kilog. (against a ration price of less than a rouble), butterat 800 roubles a kilog. (against a ration price of 30 roubles), milk at 75 roublesa litre, appalling cuts of meat at 350-400 roubles a kilog. The official exchange value of the rouble, by the way, is around 22 roubles to the pound sterling; the
privileged diplomatic rate (which correspondents get) 48 roubles to the pound.The price of potatoes on the market has fallen since last autumn to between20 and 30 roubles par kilog. owing to the large-scale cultivation of allotmentsround Moscow last summer by Moscow citizens : the other prices remain much the same.At the Moscow market, most of the customers carry either openly in theirshopping bags or half-concealed under their coats, loaves or chunks of bread.This is because the peasants of the Moscow region, who produce very little wheatbut do not, for all that, get a bread ration, are eager to buy bread, and will accept it at from 120 roubles a kilog. up, according to its quality (against a ration priceof 1-5 to 4 roubles a kilog.) in payment for their produce. Strictly speaking,this barter is not legal, but the police who patrol the market don&apos;t interferevery much with it. My mother-in-law regularly sold bread in the market for meto get milk for my baby son.On the blind side of the peasants&apos; market booths goes on pathetically theforbidden side of the market&apos;s activities. Citizens can be seen selling every kindof goods to get money to buy food. One appallingly thin woman I saw standinghelplessly beside a large tin hip bath : she was willing to accept what she was offered. An older woman was carrying round a toy lorry, another had a jam-jarwith three chocolates and half a dozen lumps of sugar in it, a third a packetof cheap envelopes, two roubles each. A cripple, with one arm round his woodencrutch was with the other hand offering a stainless steel rubber-ferruled invalidstick for sale, another man was walking around with an electric stove (400 roubles),while 300 was being asked for an old pair of galoshes and 350 for a patched pairof boots. Many of those who in the hard winter months of 1941-42 were not willing in this way to sell their household treasures to buy food on the marketsimply died of starvation; two aunts of my wife, who live in a country villaoutside Moscow, died thus.It should be added that the Moscow7 citizen did not have, from October 1941to last summer, the recourse which the Londoner has of eating out at a restaurantto save his rations. In the autumn of 1941 almost all of the restaurants of thecity were turned into closed restaurants, open only to the workers of a particularenterprise. And only the higher officials of an enterprise had the privilege ofeating without handing in their ration coupons. By the beginning of last summerthere was only one open restaurant in the capital, and it was only open todiplomats, foreign correspondents and Russians of above a certain rank in thearmy or other services or holding certain decorations; prices here may be judged from the fact that a simple two-course meal for six guests, with a little vodka,some Russian wine and a little Russian brandy, which I gave here at the endof 1943 cost more than 2,000 roubles. Last summer there were opened, however,some 20 or more new open restaurants in various parts of Moscow. These soldfood at what were described as &quot; competitive prices,&quot; which meant in practicesome four or more times the pre-war price for a meal. They were, however, very well patronised, and there seemed usually to be queues in front of them.Cigarettes and tobacco are rationed in Russia, and the ration has been small&apos;and uncertain. Cigarettes have been more difficult to obtain than tobacco, onaccount of the shortage of paper, and many people roll their own cigarettes, usingoften torn scraps of newspaper for the purpose. The quality of the cigarettesnow being sold is very low; they taste bitter and will only continue burning if one draws continuously at them. Drink is also rationed, and is in very short supply. There are only two bars now7 open in Moscow, one of which sells beer,the other cocktails. There are almost invariably queues in front of their doors.8. The Russian citizen&apos;s ration book contains coupons for clothes, but inpractice, till very recently, he would have been unable to obtain them unless hehad a good closed store attached to his enterprise; and even then in order to beable to buy he would need a recommendation from the head of his department.War-time rationing of clothes has been a much greater hardship to the Russiansthan to us, for they had smaller individual reserves; even before the war certain articles of clothing, such as shoes, were difficult and expensive to get, though this was less so in Moscow, Leningrad and other &quot; Class A &quot; cities, which got apriority in the distribution of consumer goods of which there was any shortage.A Russian who wanted to keep smart to-day and who cannot (as most peoplecannot) shop with some freedom at a good closed store, can only replenish hiswardrobe in three ways. He can buy clothes at one of the Government second-hand shops, he can buy from his acquaintance, or he can get an article of clothing-made for him by an employee of a Government clothing factory working in his[27842] c
spare time. All these three ways of buying clothes are very expensive, the secondtwo particularly so, so the privileged Russian who keeps up appearances mustbe prepared to sell up household possessions to buy clothes, as well as food. Mylate secretary, who has not been able to get a single article of clothing on the ration since the war, told me he had almost denuded his home of furniture to buy food and clothes. Since more men than women have been mobilised for thefront, women&apos;s clothes are in greater demand and more expensive. A mans suitin fair repair will fetch 1,500 or so roubles, a new pair of nien&apos;s shoes up to 1,500.But a new pair of women&apos;s shoes will command 6,000 to 8,000 roubles, the latter being the price charged by the best Government shoemaker in Moscow, working in his spare time.9. These figures raise the question of what are the rates of pay in russia to-day and what the value of the rouble. The range of rates is very large : anunskilled worker will get around 300 roubles a month, a skilled worker at a warfactory will get 1.500 roubles; so did my wife as English teacher at the Academyof Science. One of her friends, who wrote musical accompaniments for filmsoundtracks, got 30,000 roubles a month; artists are very well treated by theSoviet State.What the rouble in which wages are paid really means to-day it is almost impossible to say. The exchange rates, the official of 22 roubles to the poundsterling and the diplomatic of 48. are entirely meaningless; In Teheran it ispossible to buy roubles back at 300 to the pound. I don&apos;t think it is so far fromthe truth to say that there are almost as many different values to the rouble as there are classes of wage-earner. For the man who belongs to a good closed storeand is also allowed to purchase a liberal supply of goods off the ration at rationprices, each rouble he earns is plainly worth more than it is to the man who hasno closed store and is forced to do much of his shopping &quot;in the open market. Theman in the street is fully conscious of this meaninglessness of the rouble. If youwant any small service done for you, such as the carriage of a load of wood to your house for heating, it is almost useless to offer money for it. You will getnothing done unless you offer payment in kind; you will usually be asked for abottle or two bottles of vodka, though I paid for a carriage of a load of wood toour country home last summer with an old shirt. The barber I usually tippedwith cigarettes (my ration was bigger than his); the hotel servants with bread.Whatever the value of the rouble is, it is plain that a very high proportionof the countings currency has since the war found its way into the hands of the peasants, through their open market dealings. If it were allowed to continuethere it might present very considerable problems after the war, when presumablythe purchasing power of the rouble will rise again and peasants with largereserves of money tucked away might be difficult to manage and more reluctant to work than hitherto. On the other hand, the existence of considerable volumesof public savings in the various defence loans would make it difficult for theauthorities to devaluate. Something has been done to extract the money fromthe peasants&apos; hands by the organisation of waves of &quot; voluntary contributions &quot;to the national defence, described in (5). But it must always be more difficult to trace the amount of money in a peasant&apos;s than in a town worker&apos;s hands, and soto be certain that the peasants have been cleaned out of their hoards.10. Housing has ever since the revolution been one of the biggest problemsfacing the Soviet authorities. And, apart from the newly-established industrial centres in the Urals and further east, Moscow has been shorter of housing thanalmost anywhere else : since on account of its being a Class A city, with priority in the supply of- consumer goods and workers who could flock to it. The 1941evacuation did not seem to affect the situation much, and I should say that themoment nearer 90 per cent, than 80 per cent, of Moscow&apos;s population are living in one-room homes. Before her marriage to me my wife, who had a comparativelywell-paid post, was living in a room measuring some 30 by 15 feet, together with her mother, her daughter by her first marriage, a girl friend of the family and(up to the war) a maid. The room was one of three in a ground floor flat, theother two families in the flat occupying one room each and the three sharingbathroom and lavatory accommodation. It is an extraordinary difficult andlengthy task to get new housing accommodation in Moscow, and cases of divorcedcouples continuing to share the same room are not a joke, but a fact of everydaylife. The importance attached to housing may be judged from the fact that theSituations Vacant advertisements in the evening newspaper Veckernaya Moskvato-day none of them refer to the rate of wages offered, but all promise &quot; gooddormitory accommodation&quot; as well as &quot;good closed restaurant.&quot;   In some of
the Urals industrial centres to which industry has been transferred east sincethe war, the standard of living accommodation has fallen from 10 square metresto 3 - 5 square metres per head. To illustrate the greater tightness of housing accommodation in Moscow, I may say that before my wife came to the capital,when she and her first husband&apos;were working in Rostov-on-Don they had nodifficulty in getting a complete flat to themselves.Plainly, altogether apart from the reconstruction of the devastated areas,Russia will have to do an immense amount of building after the war. And shewill have not only to build a great deal of new houses, but to rebuild a very great number of the old. The apartment blocks and other houses built since the revolu-tion have most of them been built in a hurry, their workmanship and materialleaves much to be desired. The Russian climate, with its vast temperature range,varying annually between around 100 degrees Fahrenheit in the summer andminus 30 degrees in the winter, is a great tester of shoddy building. And, as anadditional reason why many of the new houses will have to come down, duringthe hard winter of 1941-42, when fuel was almost unobtainable in Moscow,indoor temperatures in homes fell to 20 degrees Fahrenheit of frost, pipes icedup and burst everywhere, and a great deal of damage was done to the structure of buildings, some of which was only becoming apparent in the autumn of lastyear : one of my colleagues had the walls of his flat collapse then.11. It is a testimony, both to the stamina of the Russian people and to thework of their medical system that, despite lowered resistance due to food shortageand other conditions favourable to the spread of infection, there have been as yet no large epidemics since the war in unoccupied territory. It should not bebelieved, however, that the war-time medical service for civilians comes up to the standards to which we are accustomed in England : of course the demands of thearmy are far greater. Before the war a citizen who fell ill could count on getting a doctor from a clinic to his bedside within the day, and only if he were in a verygreat hurry would he ring up a doctor at his private address, and ask him tocome round for a fee. To-day the delay in attending to cases is much greater.A friend of nry wife&apos;s who became partially paralysed one morning, she believedowing to contact with an industrial chemical, was told on ringing up her works&apos;clinic that it would be two days before a doctor was available to come and seeher. She had therefore to contact a doctor privately and ask him to come roundfor a fee. I should add that even the most distinguished specialists in moscow to-day prefer to take their fees in kind instead of in cash : when my wife hadoccasion to consult a gynaecologist before our child was born she would invariablytake him a bottle of wine as well as a sum of money. It may be interesting thatthis doctor, though one of the most famous in Russia, had not got a car. And itis no fun for a doctor to do his rounds on the terribly overcrowded trams andtrolleybuses (buses have been mobilised as. ambulances and taken off the streetsfor the duration of the war) of Moscow.There is a very great shortage of even quite simple drugs and disinfectantsin the Russian civilian hospitals to-day. When, before the birth of our child,my wife had to go to a clinic for a routine blood test, the blood was drawn offin a syringe with only part of the barrel, there was no disinfectant available tosterilise the needle, not even boiling water (for gas was then cut off during theday time) and my wife had to produce one of her own matches (the clinic hadnone) in order that the needle might be passed through the flame.12. The Soviet State pays, in war time as well as in peace, very considerable attention to the arts. The principal Moscow theatrical companies were evacuated from the capital during the danger period, and it is easier for a competent artistto obtain exemption from military service than for any other class of citizen;there have indeed been cases of artists escaping from their employment to join the army and being brought back. ArtistSj in addition, get considerable privilegesin rations, housing accommodation and so on.The artists respond by doing their work well. &quot; Artists brigades,&quot; sent out to entertain the forces, carry on their work up to within a mile or two of thefront line. And in the packed Moscow theatres to-day (they have all now returned from the evacuation) some of the very best performances of opera, balletand straight acting that it is possible to see in the world are given.It would be a complete error, however, to think of the Russian theatre to-dayas in any sense of the word leading the world. The Moscow Art Theatre, withits magnificent tradition, gives the best performances of Russian classics andsome of the best of Western European classics than can be seen anywhere in the[27842] D
globe. In its interpretation of classical ballet, such as Tchaikovski&apos;s famous&quot; Swan Lake,&quot; the Bolshoi Theatre is unrivalled. But the programmes to-dayare, and have been for some years before the war, absolutely conservative. Theprincipal fresh pieces in this spring&apos;s season of the Moscow Art Theatre, forinstance, are a play by Ostrovski (Russian 19th century), a new translation of&quot;Hamlet,&quot; and a translation of Oscar Wilde&apos;s &quot; An Ideal Husband.&quot; Thenew plays I have seen have all been of the nature of political tracts, which areflat in their characterisation, stereotyped in their method of presentation andwould be intolerably dull were it not for their superb acting. The same is true of opera and ballet; though Stravinski was already becoming famous in western europe before the last war, his ballets never appear in the Moscow repertory.In the cinema, where during the late &quot;twenties and early &apos;thirties Russianfeature films were leading the world, it is only the documentaries that haveanything to teach us now. My wife, whose first husband was a distinguishedcinema cameraman, assures me&apos; that for some years before the war she had not seen a single Soviet feature film of any real merit; the feature films producedsince the wrar have, like the plays, all been in the nature of tracts. In the field ofliterature, the only figure of any eminence remaining now is the pre-revolutionaryAlexei Tolstoy (who is still allowed to keep up his old regime state, with hishousehold of servants headed by a butler); Sholokov, who is drinking himselfstupid, is held now to have shot his bolt. Not a single big and permanent newliterary figure has emerged since the revolution, and not only has there been no war fiction of any real merit, but the total output of fiction, since the war, apartfrom short stories and serials in periodicals, has been negligible.A musician friend of my wife&apos;s expressed before me one day the opinion that soviet Russia to-day had no intelligentsia which could compare with that of theWestern European countries. It had, he said, killed off the old intellectual class,and the repression exercised by the regime (even if you believe that a new intel-lectual class can spring from the ground overnight) had made it impossible for anew one to emerge. For it must be emphasised that the Tsarist regime, for all itsdefects, afforded a latitude to its author critics which would be quite incon-ceivable under the Soviet system.The facts of Soviet artistic life, apart from the superb technique seen in the theatre, make it difficult to resist the conclusion that this judgment of thesterility of Soviet art is largely true.Tendencies in Soviet Russia.13. At the beginning of this memorandum I spoke of the chief trends nowvisible in the Soviet Union being a trend towards social conservatism and towardsthe hardening and perpetuation of the existing social hierarchy. Evidence ofboth these trends is to be found in the field of education.A year or so befuie the war free education at the secondary schools and universities was abolished : only those pupils whose good work earns them freeplaces go free to either. This obviously puts the children of well-paid parents, sofar as higher education is concerned, at the same sort of advantage as they enjoyin England. The mediocre son of a well-paid official will, as in England, go to a secondary school and university at his father&apos;s expense, whereas the no less intel-ligent son of poorer parents will not. I am not denouncing the change : it isprobable that in pre-war Russia there was, as is in all countries which haverapidly expanded their educational facilities, a tendency to the formation of anintellectual proletariat. I am simply stating the fact. But if secondary anduniversity education is, as is widely believed, an economic and social advantage in later life, it can hardly be doubted that this fact makes for the perpetuation of theexisting social hierarchy. At the same time that free secondary and university education was abolished, a system of factory training schools was set up, whereelementary school pupils who did not go on further with their general educationreceived technical training. The training given in these schools has undoubtedly been of the greatest value in facilitating the industrial effort behind Russia&apos;s war effort. But since the trainees tended to be the children of less well-paid parents, itwill be obvious that this too tended to perpetuate the existing hierarchy.The educational change in Russia which has undoubtedly caused mostsensation abroad has been the separation of girls from boys in elementary educa-tion : there are now, not merely separate classes for boys and girls, but separateschools. This change has been discussed for some time before it was introducedlast year, but the reasons given for it in the public press, though they would havedelighted the heart of a conservative English educationalist (the headmaster of a
boys&apos; or the headmistress of a girls&apos; Public School, for instance) did not seemsufficiently convincing to be the real ones. It was argued that girls had a very different mentality from boys and that in teaching any subject to them it wasnecessary to approach it from a rather different angle if they were to get fullbenefit from the teaching. It was argued that girls should have gentler mannersthan boys, and it was easier to inculcate these if they were educated separately from boys. Finally, it was said that, since a girFs and a boy&apos;s physique were very different, they were plainly adapted to different kinds of work in the community,and so a different bias needed to be given to their education. And, in addition,while boys at school needed to receive the elements of preparatory military train-ing, girls needed to be taught the elements of mothercraft and housecraft.I am inclined to think that the last reason, which appeared to be the leaststressed, was really the valid one, that the old Soviet view that all careers shouldbe equally open to all sexes is going by the board, and that the regime is anxiousto see a high proportion of the young women of the rising generation back in thehome. I do not suggest for a moment that this means the end of careers forwomen (though I believe that under the new dispensation they have, for themoment, fewer secondary school places in Moscow). But the increased pro-productivity of Soviet industry will progressively render it less necessary for all women to work outside the &quot;home. And the first twenty-six years of the Sovietregime, with both parents normally working outside the ordinary home, and with little stabilising home influence thus brought to bear on the children, has undoubtedly resulted in the production of a somewhat boorish and unrulyyounger generation.There is no doubt that the heads of the regime wrant to change this. Sovieteducation has seen the most bewildering series of changes in the systems of organising and maintaining order in its schools. But the emphasis is all now onstrict formal discipline and the enforcing of obedience by graded punishments soas to repress selfishness and hooliganism. &quot;A pupil when entering school,&quot;writes one headmistress. &quot; must feel that he or she is going into a holy place.&quot;Pupils are now issued with a code of rules for conduct which is almost identical with that handed out in pre-revolutionary schools. They must greet theirteachers when they meet them in the street, a boy by taking off his cap. a girl bybowing. In the R.S.F.S.R. school-children may not go to cinemas or theatres on school days without permission from the head of the school, and then it is preferable that they should go in an organised body, accompanied by adults.Respect for parents and elders is being inculcated.An interesting change on the literary (as distinct from the scientific) side of secondary education : Latin is now being introduced as a subject. It is alsonotable that the latest geography text-books on, for instance, parts of the BritishEmpire are comparatively objective in their treatment and free from digs at&quot; capitalist exploitation,&quot;14. The U.S.S.R. has already gone a long way from the period when the family was regarded as a bourgeois institution, which should be broken up by thepopularisation of communal feeding, easy divorce, removal of the stigma onillegitimacy and other means. The family is now accepted and growinglyrespected institution, and the next step which will probably be taken to increase its status and influence will be a further tightening up of the divorce laws. Atthe beginning of the Soviet regime, when abortion (now forbidden) was legalised,divorce could be obtained at a registry office on the application of one party to amarriage only, the registry office notifying the other party of the divorce by post,though provision had always to be made for the maintenance of dependent children. Then further legislation made mutual consent necessary, and later thecost of divorce was progressively stepped up, so that a citizenV second divorcerequired the payment of a bigger fee than his first, and his third divorce a stillbigger sum. It was currently reported in Moscow at the time I left that legislation was contemplated taking divorce away from the competence of theregistry office and making it a court affair, as with us. necessitating the proofby the petitioning party of some grounds of incompatibility with the respondent.It was, indeed, widely expected that this legislation would be introduced duringthe last session of the Supreme Soviet.15. The re-establishment of the Orthodox Church was another conserva-tive move by the regime, though it should not be taken for a moment as implying that any of the heads of the regime have become converted to Christianity; Itwas a realistic move, taken, in my opinion (as I suggested earlier), less becauseof any impression it might make on Russians Allies than because of the immense&quot;[27842] n o
wave of religious feeliug which swept the whole country at the beginning of thewar and has persisted ever since. I attended midnight Mass at Moscow Cathedrallast Easter (the curfew was specially lifted for the occasion, as it has been for similar occasions since it was first imposed with the war), and I have never comeso near suffocation in my life; the building, which might have held some 2,000people with comfort was packed with seven or eight thousand. From what i could see there were far more genuine worshippers than curious spectators there,indeed, I saw no sign of irreverence. And the congregation gave the lie to thefrequently made assertion that only old people go to church in Russia nowadays;there were just as many middle-aged and even young people. The service Iattended was, of course, some time before the re-establishment of the Holy Synodand the Patriarchate as the governing body of the Church, and their officiallinking with the Soviet regime.There had been quite a number of indications before the re-establishmentof what was in the wind. Anti-religious propaganda, for instance, had beenswitched off almost as soon as the war began and the Church rallied behind theGovernment. Then the field censors, who early in the war used to excise religiousexpressions from letters between soldiers and their parents, ceased to do so. Nextan article in the Communist party periodical, The Agitators Notebook, replying to a question whether it was proper for soldiers to mock at comrades who prayedin barracks, answered that while an individual expression of opinion on theuselessness of religious observances could be allowed, any kind of organisedmockery was strongly to be discouraged. And ever since the war such representa-tions of priests or religious persons as had occurred in plays and films had beeninvariably sympathetic.It is not quite true to say that before the re-establishment the OrthodoxChurch was either persecuted or free. There had been an earlier period in therevolution when, for instance, priests had been disenfranchised and deprived of rations and when my wife had been expelled from school half a dozen times onthe grounds that her grandfather was a priest. When, the war started the positionroughly wras that : (i) Any body of believers which could provide enough money annually tomaintain the fabric of its church and support its priest could have its church open; the building and its furnishings were the propertyof the State, and if, say, any church vessels were stolen, the congrega-tion had to indemnify the State for their loss.(ii) State-supported and anti-religious propaganda was fairly active, andhad its own newspaper, but children could not receive anti-religiousteaching in classes (though the Marxist instruction they received inschool was at least implicitly anti-religious and the Church could not maintain seminaries to train its priests).(iii) Minor ways of making a church uncomfortable could be and were used,such as forcing it to pay a higher rate for the heating and lightingof its building.(iv) Though priests were full citizens, a member of the Communist party(membership of which has been stated to be essential to obtain any ofthe better posts in the regime) could not be known to practise religion,and any one who had the ill-luck to be accused of a political offencewould know that his religious beliefs would be counted as a blackmark against him.(v) Though in earlier days the Church had been able to print its ownperiodicals, it had of latter years received no paper allotment for thepurpose.The Church has now its own seminaries and its own periodicals again : this raises the interesting point that it is impossible for a totalitarian Socialist Statesuch as the Russian merely to tolerate a movement, such as the Church. It is bound, as soon as the movements&apos; need for physical facilities arises, to someextent to co-operate with it. Thus the Soviet State has had to furnish State-owned buildings for seminaries, State-owned paper for Church periodicals : itmay soon be furnishing the Church with metal for icons, and the Patriarch hasalready been furnished with a motor car for his use by, oddly enough, theCommissariat for War.This co-operation of the State with the Church has been rendered easierbecause, not only has the Church been extremely patriotic since the war beganand priests served as foci of resistance in occupied territory, but back throughRussian territory the Orthodox Church has always, since Peter the Great at least,
been a tool of the Russian State. There is no reason to believe ,that it will be lessobedient to the Soviet regime than it was to the Tsar. A stiffer test of the realityof the new Soviet toleration of religion will come when the Red Army reconquersLithuania, a country where the bulk of the people profess Roman Catholicism, a branch of Christianity which has always been far more refractory to Stateinterference and which is far less likely to consent to be a tool of the regime.Father Braun, priest in charge of Moscow&apos;s only Roman Catholic Church, thatof St. Louis of the French, tells me that since the re-establishment of theOrthodox Church two or three members of his congregation have been arrestedwithout trial, for no discoverable reason except that they do attend the church.16. One more conservative move is becoming apparent in the various branches of the civil service. Under the Tsarist regime all public servants woreuniform, and there was a system of grades in each service which corresponded tothose in each of the others as well as to those in the army and navy. Last year the railwaymen were given a new system of ranks and insignia which corre-sponded with those in the army : then the employees of the Foreign Office were put into uniform, with a similar system of ranks (the head of the Foreign OfficePress Bureau is equivalent in rank to a major-general). It was forecast in moscow when I left that teachers and students would be the next to be put intouniform again. Another step that is forecast for the near future is the changingof the title of the various Commissariats of the Government into Ministries.17. The teaching of history in Russian schools and its presentation to theadult public has changed remarkably in recent years and is still developing. Notonly the literary men and scientists of the Tsarist regime but its generals andstatesmen are being furbished up again as national heroes. Peter the Great isnow venerated as the founder of modern Russia, his tyrannies forgotten, andIvan the Terrible, the frantic Tsar who murdered his own son and died mad, isbeing turned into a hero and whitewashed as having laid the corner-stone ofRussian national unity. I understand that Alexei Tolstoy, who has written athree-decker novel on Peter the Great, is now turning his attention to Ivan.No effort is being spared to turn the young Russian into a conscious nationalist.18. Nowhere are the conservative trends in the Russian regime moreapparent than in the army. For long years before the war the hated title of&quot;officer&quot; with its reactionary associations had been abolished, and the higher grades in the Red Army were known as &quot; commanders.&quot; Now not only has theword officer been reintroduced, but everything is being done to make the officercorps conscious of itself as a body and (to a great degree) self-perpetuating. there introduction of epaulettes to carry insignia of rank becomes more significantwhen it is remembered that during the revolutionary period officers captured bythe revolutionary crowd sometimes had their epaulettes nailed to their shouldersfor them, to such an extent were they regarded as a symbol of tyranny. Thefounding of officers clubs&apos;, open to commissioned ranks only, is another step which restores the p re-revolutionary army set-up; so is the establishment oforders and decorations open to officers only, such as those of Suvorov, Kutuzov,Alexander Nevsky and the Order of Victory (awardable only to generals, it willbe a ruby and diamond star in a platinum setting). Red Army officers to-dayhave batmen again, though it has apparently proved necessary to print elaboratejustifications of this in the Press. At the booking offices of theatres there arenow special officers-only queues, which get first service.There were no doubt a number of sound practical reasons for these varioussteps whose general effect is to create an &quot;artificial gulf between officers and men.just as there was, some years ago, for the consecration in civil life of the &quot; sacredprinciple &quot;of inequality of pay. Most of them were taken after (the institution of the three first officers only, orders immediately after) the lowest ebb in theRed Army&apos;s morale, the second loss of Rostov, in summer 1942, which led to agood number of shootings among the officers concerned and a sweeping reorganisa-tion in the army. But whatever may have been the immediate reasons for thecreation of this artificial gulf, the institution of the Suvorov Cadet Colleges., forthe training of future officers, leaves no doubt that it is intended to make itpermanent. Boys who enter these colleges at the age of eight or nine will, on theconclusion of their seven years&apos; course, have a mentality and outlook entirely different from that of the rankers whom they will command. The regulations governing the conduct of these cadet colleges have been drawn up, under the supervision of experts such as General Ignatiev, former Tsarist military attache in Paris, so as to closely conform to those obtaining in the similar bodies in the oldregime.   And though the colleges are stated to be Open to the sons of officers
and men of the Red Army and. partisans, I forecast that the local selection boardswho appoint boys to them will choose the majority of entrants from among officers&apos;sons. Press comment at the time the colleges were established underlined the satisfaction it would give to an officer father to know that his son was beingthoroughly trained to follow in his footsteps in his own glorious career. Sincethe colleges will have an annual output of 650 cadets, their graduates are goingto act as a very influential leaven in the Red Army of the future.Discipline is very strict in the Red Army to-day. There has recently been adrive to improve soldierly bearing in the rear areas, and there is far more salutingin the streets of Moscow&apos; than in those of London, while I myself in the crowdedunderground have seen a junior obeying the rule which lays down that he shouldrise and offer his seat to a standing senior officer. Discipline among troops onforeign service is so tight that when our military police in Tehran arrest a drunkand disorderly Russian soldier they do not dare to hand him over to the Russianpolice till he has recovered, for fear he might be shot.General Conclusions.19. The Soviet regime to-day, with its great material and military achieve-ments and its virtually complete control of public opinion, is a very strong one.And since it owes its strength far less to the prestige of any personality than tothe firmness, unity and discipline of the Communist Party, I think it would bea grave mistake to believe that Stalin&apos;s death would affect it as Mussolini&apos;sdownfall affected the Fascist Party or Hitler&apos;s would affect the Nazi Party.Roughly, the contrast is that the Italian and. German dictators created their ownParties&quot; while Stalin was created by his (though he exercised ruthlessly everyart he had to stimulate it into the&apos;creative process). And I believe that theCommunist Party&apos;s Politburo (the body that lays down policy) is a body withincomparably more authority and prestige vis-a-vis the head of the Governmentthan the Fascist Grand Council ever had vis-a-vis Mussolini. So I think it wouldbe a very unsafe bet to anticipate that the death of Stalin would, lead to aquarrel over &quot;his successorship which would seriously compromise the regime.The only moment since the war began when any sign of a crack appeared inthe strength&quot; of the regime was during the &quot; October days &quot; of 1941 in Moscow.The Germans were then rapidly approaching the capital, the Government depart-ments and the Diplomatic Corps were evacuated. Work was stopped in the factories, and a number of installations were blown up : the underground was closed. A number of the Moscow police were drafted up to the front; most ofthose who were not, left their posts. For three clays not a word came from theKremlin, and while householders were vigorously scrubbing Communist inscrip-tions off their housefronts. looting of food stores began and scattered anti-Semiticdemonstrations started in the suburbs. The opinion of those who were there atthe time is that if the Germans had cared to drop 500 parachutists over moscow and take over the radio stations, they could have had it for the asking. Militarycaution caused them to delay resumption of their advance till their main forces had come up with their advance groups, and during this period the Russians had time to bring up their reserves of Siberian troops and counter-attack. After threeclays&apos; silence the Kremlin spoke again, and since that time there has been noweakening in its authority. But it came very near indeed to losing it then, and though Allied journalists at the time naturally had to write as if the loss of moscow would make no difference to Soviet resistance, since the Red Army would continue to fight right back to the Urals, there is little doubt that, in fact, the lossof the capital would have turned Russia into a largely passive partner in the warand would have dealt an irreparable blow at the regime.. Strong though the regiriie is, its heads quite plainly suffer from a markedsense of inferiority in face of the Western capitalist Powers. While, in theirpress comment, apparently quite insensitive to the feelings of these nations, theydisplay a fantastic thinness of skin when confronted with the least criticism&apos;fromabroad. This sense of inferiority probably accounts for the extravagant lavish-ness, considering the country&apos;s wartime shortness of supplies, of the entertainmentthey offer to visiting foreign statesmen and. on certain annual occasions, to the diplomatic Corps : Kremlin banquets and Foreign Office receptions on the scaleon which they are given in Moscow are such that, if our authorities were to holdsimilar festivities in London, they would arouse a storm of public indignation.20. I feel that this sense of inferiority among her rulers, combined with the sense of suspicion to which I referred at the beginning of this memorandum are going to make Russia a very tricky country to deal with in the post-war years.
Any prediction of what her post-war internal and external policy are going to be is bound to be the merest speculation, but I will venture a guess. Her internalpolicy will be, I believe, nothing more than progressively to raise the standard ofliving of her population, while maintaining her arms and heavy industries at full strength : the achievement of Communism, the theoretical final aim of the Party,where the reward motive for labour will vanish and it will be &quot; from eachaccording to his capacities, to each according to his needs,&quot; will remain an aimfar beyond the horizon. As far as foreign policy is concerned, I think theU.S.S.R.&apos;s main preoccupation will be the achievement and maintenance of security.This sounds modest enough, but the kind of security which will satisfy adeeply suspicious nation may well have very wide implications. And even if theSoviet Union does not-wish to dominate Central Europe for the sake of domina-tion, she may feel herself forced to do so for the sake of security. Suspicionbreeds suspicion, and such an attempt at domination might well pave the way toa future conflict between Russia and her present Allies. So it is of absolutelyparamount importance that the Western Powers should be able to give Russiaat the end of the war such a sense of security. Though I think it is just as important from all points of view that they should be able to do so without making concessions to her which they feel to be unjustified. Such concessionswould only make for further rankling ill-feeling; nor do I think the Russianswill ever really trust us till we show firmness as well as conciliation in ourdealings with them. I may be wrong, but I cannot help feeling that the effect ofour giving in to them on points on which we feel we are in the right is doublyunfortunate. First, it loses us their respect (the Russians respect and respond to tough bargaining). And, secondly, it may well give them not confidence in us,but a sense that we are&apos; temporarily buying them off, just as the Germans andthey bought each other off in August 1939. It cannot, unhappily, be said thatthe Foreign Office, under Mr. Eden&apos;s guidance, has up to the moment shown any sort of firmness in dealing with the Russians; it w7as the opinion of GeneralMartell, when head of the British Military Mission in Moscow, that we were&quot;licking the Bolshies&apos; boots till we were black in the face.&quot; And, thoughMartell may have been a Blimp in politics, he was undoubtedly a man of con-siderable intelligence, whose judgments cannot be disregarded.21. Those British Conservatives who believe that Russia still is a revolu-tionaiy, and an infectiously revolutionary, country maintain that we should support discredited monarchist or Right-Wing Governments in the occupied countries of Europe lest, on their liberation, a popular movement should takecontrol and fling them straight into the arms of the Soviets. I feel this to be acomplete misreading of. the situation. I think there is a very good case for believing that, the more popular and revolutionary the new Governments ofEurope after the war, the less they will fall under Soviet influence. Theauthoritarian system now prevailing in Russia will have, it seems to me, littleattraction for a people that has newly won its freedom from its class or otheroppressors. To take an example : in Marshal Tito&apos;s army at the moment thereprevails the system of discussion of tactics between officers and men before andafter an operation, long discarded in the Red Army. It is the Bolshevik practiceof the revolution&apos;s early years that is likely to appeal to the revolutionaryGovernments of the liberated countries. And that practice is absolute poison tothe Kremlin to-day.I cannot help feeling that when the influential review War and the working class argued in one of last summer&apos;s issues that one of the reasons why a delaymight lead to an outbreak of revolutions all over the Continent such as that which followed the last war, it was not for a moment indulging in an argumentum adhominem. Far from having its tongue in its cheek as it played on the western powers&apos; nerves, I think it was expressing a fear that is probably very real in moscow ruling circles. The fear, I mean, that the freedom which may be foundunder any new revolutionary regimes in Europe may put dangerous ideas into theregimented masses of Russia. A Germany, for instance, that went Communist inthis way might shift the whole balance of power of world Communism.22. The picture of conditions in Russia which emerges from this memo-randum, a picture of hard-driven though (individually7) extremely humaninsects, might well seem depressing to members of the British Labour Party. Ithink, on the contrary, it should be an inspiring challenge to their Socialistthinking. Too many of the younger, more ardent and hard-working membersof the Labour Party have been content, in recent years, to abdicate any7
initiative in political thinking because they have thought &quot; Russia has shown us the way.&quot; Russia has, indeed, shown us the way, but to a very large extent, itseems to me, she has shown us the way not to go. The attitude we should take tothe Russian system, I feel, should not be a blind defence of aspects of it which our intelligence must know to be indefensible. It should not be an emotionaldespair that the world&apos;s first Socialist Society has degenerated into something verylike a human ant-heap or a human beehive. It should be a firm resolution to go back to the first principles of our creed and so to rethink them that we are capableof building a new Socialist Society which shall be not only as nearly as possibleefficient, but also, which is just as important, as nearly as possible free, and as nearly as possible human.April, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
