<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/242/0 images: 54-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
on.l:       . Printed for the Cabinet,,rBffgpg.l$$3.jjyjjvcii ad ot snuiiivr*-   1 *  &apos; &apos; &apos; - i; oiui widbIbCI M we-ib oi gbjimSECEET. Copy No.CP. 159 (33). .&apos; , .:V,ca(Also D.C. (M) (32) 49.)CABINET.His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Disarmament Conference.I WOULD ask my colleagues to give immediate attention to the annexed Memorandum written by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary for Foreign Affairs.(Initialled)      J. S.Foreign Office, June 15, 1933.His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Disarmament Conference.THE General Commission of the Disarmament Conference has now passed in review, in &quot;First Reading,&quot; the whole of the United Kingdom Draft Convention.This First Reading has revealed more or less clearly the differences between the various principal Delegations. With the exception of the original German objection to the proposal for the standardisation of Continental armies, no amendments of any importance have been withdrawn. If we were to proceed at once to a Second Reading we should be able to do nothing but record the differences by the taking of votes. Such a proceeding would be a futility, &quot;and perhaps a dangerous futility.Agreement upon a Convention is perhaps not yet entirely out of the question, but there is only one possible way to it, and that is by private discussion between the Heads of the principal Governments, with a Ariew to inducing each of them to make some sacrifice for the sake of reaching agreement. It is not inconceivable that, if they were assured of adequate supervision and certain other guarantees, such as are afforded by Our Part I, the French might be induced (partly by suasion and partly by fear of taking the responsibility for ultimately bringing the Conference to naught) to agree to a measure of reduction, with which we might be able to persuade the Germans to content themselves for five years,or so. But it would be folly to suppose that the Bureau of the Conference, meeting, on the 27th June, could possibly prepare a compromise that could go thrpughjhe General Commission at the latter&apos;s session that is timed to begin on the 3yd.July.The Economic Conference has brought together in London many*&apos;pf&apos;t&apos;; h&apos;e principal statesmen of Europe, and it may be that an opportunity will thus present itself for intimate exchanges of views between them, and that in this: manner we might be able to reach a measure of agreement which would give the General Commission something to build upon. Mr. Henderson has come to London in the hope that something of the kind may result.Delegates to the Economic Conference will doubtless be pi^eoccupied with other matters, but I would submit that this is perhaps the last chance for averting complete failure of the Disarmament Conference, and I would urge that, if by any means possible, advantage should be taken of it. M. Daladier and Herr von Neurath are here for a few days only.   Mr. Norman Davis is only[8740]
&quot;waiting to be invited, a1 Suitable Delegate would be sent from Rome if there were prospects of conversations taking place. I would suggest that an effort be made to draw M. Daladier into a conversation on disarmament, with reference to the recent conversations in Paris, and that he should be made to urge his Cabinet to go at least as far as the British Delegates then urged him. Mr. Davis might assist in this he was quite useful in Paris. If we can get the French to make this advance, we should then have to use our influence with the Germans to try to get them to be content with the most that we can get out of the French. An Italian Delegate might assist us in this.If there are no further conversations or if any that might take place should result in failure, a meeting of the Bureau on the 27th June could only have deplorable-able consequences. Here, then, is the alternative : either to organise conversations at once, pleading if necessary with Mr. Henderson for further delay to allow a better chance of this being brought to success, or to await the 27th with calamitous results to the Conference, and, I fear, inevitably to our own position.But and it is a large &quot;but&quot; the possibility of conversations is dependent on our being able to modify our own attitude somewhat principally in regard to supervision. I understand our present position is that we can make no further concession in this direction. I think we should be literally alone in this; I can think of no other Delegation at Geneva that would make any difficulty about making the provisions for supervision more stringent. We may have the best of reasons for our attitude, but we must realise that we should appear as single-handed obstructors.It is also our present instruction to refuse to extend the &quot;no resort to force&quot; declaration from Europe to the world. We are to persist in this despite our acceptance of President Roosevelt&apos;s message which clearly entailed some such commitment. The attitude of the United States has of course been modified by this message : their Delegate will be prepared to accept extension. We shall therefore stand alone in our refusal.Sir William Malkin has prepared a paper on the present position of security in relation to the Convention and in particular to the question of &apos;&apos; the definition of the aggressor.&quot; The French, and indeed the majority of the Conference, set much store by such a definition, and we have already had conversations with the United States Delegates as to whether some arrangement could be arrived at which would give France and her friends a measure of satisfaction without excessive inconvenience to ourselves and the Americans.In respect of budgetary limitation and private manufacture of arms we have to resist proposals which the French and the majority of the Conference would be glad to put into force.We should, moreover, realise the position in which we shall find ourselves if and when the Second Reading is taken. In addition to being unable to contribute anything upon any one of the above points we should then have to produce figures. Those for effectives will be in fact, if not in appearance, above our present figures. Our tank figure, which, I understand, is to be 550, shows, I believe, a large increase. Our Dominion air figures will at least give the British Empire twice as large an air force as any of the great Powers.I need not recall here that in respect of our reservation for bombing in &quot; outlying regions&quot; we stand almost alone.When all these circumstances are taken into account it will be seen how unenviable our position is becoming. If the 27th June dawns without any previous negotiation the search for the victim will begin. It is in an effort to &amp;yoid the British Delegation being cast for this part that this paper has been written, for this is a fate which, in the circumstances of this Conference, can neither be evaded without concessions nor endured without ignominy.r:5 - June 12, 1933.(Initialled)

</content>
</cab>
