<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/242/0 images: 94-96</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1933.SECRET. Copy No.      42CP. 170 (33).CABINET.AT the suggestion of the Secretary of State for Air, I circulate for the information of my colleagues a copy of a note from Herr Nadolny to Lord Londonderry, dated the 2nd June, enclosing a confidential statement of the broad lines of the German position in regard to disarmament, together with a note of acknowledgment from Lord Londonderry to Herr Nadolny, dated the 3rd June.J. S.Foreign Office, June 23, 1933.[W 6558/40/98] No. 1.United Kingdom Delegate to Sir John Simon. (Received June 7.) (No. 171.)THE United Kingdom delegate to the League of Nations presents his compliments, and has the honour to transmit copies of a note from M. Nadolny to Lord Londonderry of the 2nd June, enclosing a confidential statement on the broad lines of the German point of view in the disarmament question, and of a note of acknowledgment from Lord Londonderry to M. Nadolny of the 3rd June.United Kingdom Delegation, Geneva, June 5, 1933,Enclosure 1 in No. 1.Herr Nadolny to Lord Londonderry.Dear Lord Londonderry, Geneva, June 2, 1933.IN pursuance of this afternoon&apos;s conversation, I have much pleasure in enclosing herewith a confidential statement on the broad lines of the German point of view in the disarmament question.I am, &amp;c.NADOLNY.Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Statement of the German Point of View in the Disarmament Question. (Confidential.)ON the basis of the treaties (article 8 of the Covenant and the preamble to Part V of the Versailles Treaty), and as a member of the League of Nations, Germany has the right to claim that, after she herself has disarmed, the disarmament of the other States should be carried through, and that the6934   [8773]
limitations applying to Germany should be adapted to the general system of disarmament. Even in the Versailles Treaty the arms allowed to the German army are not laid down as incapable of change (article 164, section 2).Moreover, under article 8 of the Covenant Germany is entitled to demand that when the limits of armaments are being laid down her need for national security should be considered in the same way as that of the other States.By the agreement of the 11th December, 1932, Germany&apos;s equality of rights is recognised as one of the guiding principles of the Disarmament Conference, and it is further stipulated 1. That the respective limitations of the armaments of all States should belaid down in the coming convention; 2. That the principle of Germany&apos;s equality of rights and that of the otherdisarmed States must be embodied in the convention; 3. That equality of rights is to be granted in a system which would providesecurity for all nations; and 4. That the methods of application of such equality of rights shall bediscussed by the conference.In accordance with this agreement, Germany&apos;s equality of rights must be carried into effect in the conference, and the signatory States are under the obligation to co-operate to this end. Germany holds the view that the system of security mentioned in the agreement should be put into practice chiefly through a just and reasonable settlement of the proportion between the armaments of the different countries. She has, moreover, always declared herself ready to co-operate in the development of security by treaty, but she considers that, in view of what has already been done in this field, the realisation of equality of rights can no longer be denied her.Although in the agreement of the 11th December, 1932, no mention has been made of the realisation of equality of rights by stages, Germany is prepared, in so far as quantities of armaments are concerned, to remain during the period of the first convention below the level to which she would be entitled in relation to the other States if the principles of article 8 were equally applied. As regards qualitative equality, it must be effected by the first convention, since Germany can neither tolerate further discrimination nor recognise it anew in a treaty. She is, however, prepared to take into account the principle of a period of transition. But the smallest consideration of her national security demands that she should he equipped with the same types of weapons as all other States find necessary for the defence of their territory. If, further, a uniform type is introduced for the effectives of all European continental armies, their arms must also be of a uniform type; otherwise the comparability of armies, which it is sought to attain through a standardised organisation of their personnel, would not be achieved.In a spirit of conciliation and co-operation, Germany is willing to declare her agreement with the following points : 1. The insertion of new security clauses in the convention (part I of the British plan), provided that agreement be reached regarding the contents of certain of these clauses.2. The standardiseition of continental armies, that is to say, the transformation-tion of the Reichswehr along the lines of the British proposal within five years, and by methods which take into account the special position of Germany.3. A system of control, provided it be generally and equally applied andrestricted to what is needful and expedient. 4. The renunciation of all aggressive weapons, which are then to be abolished and destroyed by all States within five years. 5. As regards defensive weapons hitherto forbidden to Germany but allowedand fixed by number for the other States, Germany will contentherself for the space of five years with a smaller quantity than she would be entitled to claim under an equal standard for all States. 6. Germany is prepared not to make use until the 31st December, 1936, ofher right to replace her overage capital ships, with the exception ofone keel to be laid down in replacement.
Enclosure 3 in No. 1.Lord Londonderry to Herr Nadolny.Dear Herr Nadolny, June 3, 1933.THANK you for your letter of yesterday, sending me a confidential statement on the broad lines of the German point of view in the disarmament question. I see that this is in accordance generally with what you said to me in our conversation yesterday, and I shall not fail to take note of it.I am, &amp;c.LONDONDERRY.7. Germany accepts the publication of military expenditure; she considers the limitation by treaty of military budgets to be impossible at the present time for technical reasons.8. Germany accepts in the question of manufacture and traffic in arms (a) International publicity.(b) State supervision.(c) A control on the lines of the general stipulations laid down in theBritish plan.However, in the interest of the security for all States and her own defensive needs, Germany cannot abandon the following demands : 1. Abolition and prohibition of aggressive weapons by all States within fixed periods.2. A strength of effectives and such methods of uniformisation which take into account the existence in other countries of fourteen annual levies of trained reserves and of overseas troops which are stationed in the Metropole or in the proximity thereof.3. At least a certain quantity, fixed by treaty, of all those defensive weapons which are permitted to the other States during the period of the convention and which they regard as necessary for their national defence.The above statement is made on the assumption that the British draft convention will not be altered to the disadvantage of Germany.

</content>
</cab>
