<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/242/0 images: 171-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
11x j - &quot;SECRET. Copy No.    ^3CP. 173 (33).CABINET.I CIRCULATE, for the information of my colleagues, a copy of a despatch to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Paris recording my conversation with the French Ambassador on the 23rd June on the subject of disarmament.J. S.Foreign Office, June 27, 1933.[W 7565/40/98]Sir John Simon to Lord Tyrrell (Paris).(No. 1061.)My Lord, Foreign Office, June 26, 1933.THE French Ambassador called to see me on the afternoon of Friday, the 23rd June, to discuss the present state of work at the Disarmament Conference. At my request, Mr. Eden was present at the interview.2. The French Ambassador asked what were the intentions of the British Government as to procedure in the immediate future. He was reminded that when the Bureau adjourned at Geneva three weeks ago it instructed Mr. Henderson to carry on conversations with the heads of delegations. For a variety of reasons these conversations have not taken place, and it would seem that they were at least as necessary now as they were three weeks ago. His Majesty&apos;s Government therefore took the view that the Bureau would act wisely were it to instruct Mr. Henderson to take the steps which now seemed to him proper to initiate these conversations without further delay.3. The French Ambassador said he thought his Government had in view the possibility of the Bureau continuing work on supervision. The French Govern-ment would be better able to state its views about disarmament when they knew whether their amendments to our Chapter on Supervision could be generally accepted. The Ambassador was reminded that the French Government had previously given assurances that once Germany accepted the principle of standardisation for continental European armies the French Government would then be in a position to state their attitude towards the disarmament clauses of the draft convention. As the result of considerable pressure from His Majesty&apos;s Government, Germany had now accepted this principle, but we were still as far as ever from knowing what was the French attitude towards the disarmament clauses. His Majesty&apos;s Government would not be willing, therefore, to enter upon further discussion on supervision until at least the attitude of the principal delegations to the disarmament clauses of the convention had been made clear.4. The Ambassador said he understood the British point of view, and added that the French proposal for discussion on supervision had only been tentative. He would report our views to the French Government and hoped to be in a position to inform me of M. Paul-Boncour&apos;s views on the 26th June, before Mr. Eden left for Geneva.I am, &amp;c.JOHN SIMON.6938   [8778]Printed for the Cabinet. June 1933.

</content>
</cab>
