<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/242/0 images: 182-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1933.SECRET. Copy No.     .4 4CP. 176 (33).CABINET.FUTURE   PROCEDURE   OF   THE   DISARMAMENT   CONFERENCE.Record of a further Conversation with Mr. Henderson.Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.WITH reference to OP. 175 (33), I circulate, for the information of my colleagues, a memorandum prepared at my request by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs giving the record of a further discussion with Mr. Henderson on the future procedure of the Disarmament Conference.J. S.Foreign Office, July 7, 1933.Memorandum by Mr. Eden.Mr. HENDERSON called on me this morning, &quot;on his return from Geneva, for a discussion on the procedure which he proposes to follow in his conversations with various Governments on the subject of disarmament. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Secretary of State for the Dominions were also present.Mr. Henderson explained that on the 3rd July he had received a communica-tion from the French Government expressing regret that they would be unable to begin conversations this week, and suggesting that these might take place next week without making any definite appointment. He had immediately sent a reply to the effect that he would leave London for Paris on Monday and hoped to have his first conversation on Tuesday. He recalled that the 14th July was a French national holiday, and that consequently unless he could make some progress before that date little would be achieved before the week after next. He expressed the hope that, if it should seem advisable, His Majesty&apos;s Government would agree to continue, under his presidency, the conversations begun on the 8th June between the French, British and United States delegations. Sir John Simon and Mr. Thomas indicated our wish to be helpful. I pointed out that, so far as I was concerned, it might be very difficult for me to leave London after next week.A further point that Mr. Henderson mentioned was that it had come to his knowledge that the French Government had the idea that, after his preliminary conversation with them, he should proceed to Rome and Berlin, on what could be no more than visits of courtesy, whilst the French Government continued conversa-tions with His Majesty&apos;s Government, and possibly with representatives of the United States Government. Mr. Henderson could not acquiesce in this procedure. He felt it would make his position impossible; he had been put in charge of the conversations, and they could not be conducted behind his back. Moreover, Italian and German suspicions would be at once aroused.Sir John Simon and Mr. Thomas at once indicated concurrence in this view. As Mr. Henderson had been assured at his previous interview with them, His Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared to assist him in the discharge of the task6955   [8813]
that had been entrusted to him by the General Commission, and they had no intention of setting up rival conversations. It had been agreed that he should preside over these conversations, and they should not, therefore, take place without his participation. 1Some discussion ensued as to the nature and object of the conversations. It was agreed that the next essential step was to induce the French Government to indicate, in a definite manner, what they would be prepared to do in the matter of disarmament. It might be that the French would say that this depended on whether they could obtain a measure of satisfaction on a number of points which they had raised. The French Government had declared on various occasions that in the most favourable circumstances they would be prepared to undertake a &apos;&apos; maximum &apos;&apos; of disarmament, whilst in less favourable circum-stances they would not be able to do more than a &apos;&apos; minimum,&apos;&apos; but at no time had they defined either the maximum or the minimum. It was essential to know what they meant, and His Majesty&apos;s Government, for their part, would not be willing to consider the various conditions put forward by the French Government until they knew what degree of disarmament what prospect of securing a Franco-German agreement acceptance of those conditions was likely to produce.Sir John Simon and Mr. Thomas endorsed Mr. Henderson&apos;s proposal to proceed to Rome and Berlin after his visit to Paris, but they agreed that it might be difficult for him to go to those capitals until he had obtained from the French something that would help to bridge the differences existing between the French and German Governments.Mr. Henderson said that it had occurred to him that, as His Majesty&apos;s Government had submitted the draft convention to the Disarmament Conference, it might be well that a member of the British delegation should accompany him. Mr. Thomas submitted that this might possibly give rise to some suspicion and misunderstanding; it would throw doubt on the Presidents true position as an impartial chairman; it was, therefore, a matter that would have to be very carefully considered.Mr. Henderson said that he quite understood the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government (as set forth above), but at the same time he thought it might be well to warn them at once of certain questions that would certainly be put to them. These were: (1) The extension to the world of the No-Resort-to-Force Declaration; (2) the Definition of Aggression; and (3) Police BombingAs regards (1) and (2), Mr. Henderson was told that we were in semi-official consultation with the United States delegation. Evidently a great deal would depend on what the United States Government would be prepared to do in this respect and on the texts that might be proposed in regard to these two points. If, by his conversations, Mr. Henderson could secure a likely basis for Franco-German agreement, His Majesty&apos;s Government would be prepared to give sympathetic consideration to all these matters, but they were not prepared to make further piecemeal concessions in advance of such a prospective accord.It was understood, therefore, that Mr, Henderson would proceed to Paris on the 10th July in the hope of meeting M. Paul-Boncour and, if possible, M. Daladier on the following day. He would let the Secretary of State know at once if he required any assistance, and the manner in which, in his opinion, it could best be given.A. E.Foreign Office, July 6, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
