<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/242/0 images: 351-352</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1933.SECRET.CP. 198 (33).CABINET.GERMAN REQUEST TO BE ALLOWED TO PURCHASE BRITISH AIRCRAFT FOR POLICE PURPOSES.IN CP. No. 184 (33) the Cabinet was asked to approve a proposal that the French and Italian Governments should be invited to join with us in making enquiries of the German Government as to the meaning of certain public declarations made by German officials respecting the purchase and manufacture of police and military aircraft after the bogus air raid on Berlin. Since that paper was written a new development has occurred.2. On the 15th July the German Air Minister, Herr Goring (Berlin telegram No. 47, Saving, of the 18th July), made to the British Air Attache a communication comprising (a) A request that, as (Herr Goring alleged) the British aircraft industry-had been allowed to sell five police aircraft to Austria, Group Captain Herring would convey to His Majesty&apos;s Government Herr Goring&apos;s desire to purchase twenty-five to fifty similar aircraft for police purposes in Germany. The German need for these machines was urged-an argument, freely used in Germany since the bogus air raid for defence against foreign and Communist propaganda by air; and a reference by Group Captain Herring to the Paris Air Agreement was met by a statement by Herr Goring that he would undertake that &quot; the Police would not fly these aircraft and that the pilots would be civilian members of an Air Sports Society.&quot; This promise is irrelevant, as the Paris Air Agreement states not only that the German police &quot; may not possess aircraft,&quot; but that &quot; no other special air police organisation shall exist in Germany.&quot;(6) An intimation that whether or not the British aircraft industry supplied these aircraft, Germany intended to have them. Herr Goring said that &quot; it would take three or four months to produce suitable police aircraft in Germany. He could not wait so long,&quot; and he added that.&quot; if His Majesty&apos;s Government would not allow the sale to Germany of aircraft similar to those sold to Austria, he would buy them of France.&quot;3. The second part, (&amp;), of Herr Goring&apos;s communication to Group Captain Herring reinforces the necessity for the enquiries of the German Government suggested in CP. No. 184 (33). I submit that, if the Cabinet should decide to take any action, it should be quoted, in connection with those enquiries.4. As regards the first part, (a), of Herr Gdring&apos;s communication, enquiries in London show that the statement that British aircraft have been sold to Austria for police purposes is untrue. No police aircraft have been sold to the Austrian Government with the knowledge or consent of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and Vienna telegrams Nos. 85 and 86 of the 21st and 22nd July report a statement to our Minister by the Political Director of the Austrian Ministry for Foreign Affairs, made after enquiries, that neither the Austrian police nor gendarmerie possess any aeroplanes whatever, British or otherwise.* His Majesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires at Berlin has, on instructions, informed the German Government to* The Austrian Minister confirmed this to me spontaneously yesterday, when protesting against the persistent violation of Austrian sovereignty on the part of Germany by flying over Austrian territory and dropping subversive pamphlets.[8877]Copy No.:45&apos;
that effect and has added that &quot; there can be ho question of the sale of aircraft by British firms to the German Government for purposes forbidden by the Paris Air Agreement.&quot;5. It may be noted here that British Government licences are necessary for the export from this country of aircraft of a military type with armament mounted; and that though the export of civil types of aircraft is not subject to special licence, the Air Ministry think that exporters will comply with advice not to export such types were it known that they were to be used in Germany for police purposes, i.e., for purposes forbidden by the Paris Air Agreement. The Belgian, French and Italian Governments have been informed of Herr Goring&apos;s communication and of the action taken with regard to 2 (a) above; and they have been asked themselves to act similarly if they are approached.July 25, 1933.EOBEET VANSITTART.

</content>
</cab>
