<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/23/0 images: 45-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1948The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of ...........$0.4******.. j^f\r*?f*...........oTOP SECRET Copy No. &quot;CP. (48) 64:tk January, 1948CABINETTHE FIRST AIM OF BRITISH FOREIGN policy memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs it must be recognised that the Soviet Government has formed a solid politicaland economic block behind a line running from the Baltic along the Oder, throughTrieste to the Black Sea. There is no prospect in the immediate future thatwe shall be able to re-establish and maintain normal relations with european countries behind that line. As I have explained in a separate paper thesecountries are dominated by the Communists, although they are only a minority in each country. Indeed we shall be hard put to it to stem the further encroachmentof the Soviet tide. It is not enough to reinforce the physical barriers which stillguard our Western civilisation. We must also organise and consolidate theethical and spiritual forces inherent in this Western civilisation of which weare the chief protagonists. This in my view can only be done by creating some form of union in Western Europe, whether of a formal or informal character,backed by the Americas and the Dominions.The Situation.In another paper I have attempted to give my colleagues a sober and factualaccount of Russian policy. It is clear that from secure entrenchments behind their line the Russians are exerting a constantly increasing pressure whichthreatens the whole fabric of the West. In some Western countries the danger is still latent but in Germany, France, Trieste, Italy and Greece the conflictingforces are already at grips with one another. In each country the issue is stillin doubt and we must act resolutely if we are to prevail. The Soviet Governmenthas based its policy on the expectation that Western Europe will sink into economicchaos and they may be relied upon to place every possible obstacle in the pathof American aid and of Western European recovery. Our course is equally clear.I have done and will continue to do all I can to bring the Marshall Plan tofruition. But essential though it is, progress in the economic field will notin itself suffice to call a halt to the Russian threat. Political and, indeed, spiritualforces must be mobilised in our defence.The Western,UnionI believe therefore that we should seek to form with the backing of the americas and the Dominions a Western democratic system comprising, if possible,Scandinavia, the Low Countries, France, Portugal, Italy and Greece. As soonas circumstances permit we should of course wish also to include Spain andGermany, without whom no Western system can be complete. This may seem a somewhat fanciful conception, but events are moving fast and the sense ofa common danger drives countries to welcome to-morrow solutions which apDearunpractical and unacceptable to-day. Almost all the countries I have listed havebeen nurtured on civil liberties and on the fundamental human rights. The recentproceedings of the Human Rights Commission at Geneva have shown that ofthe eighteen States represented, all except Russia and three satellites were in34751
substantial agreement with the British draft of an International Convention forthe protection of these civil liberties and human rights. Moreover, most western european countries have such recent experience of Nazi rule that they canapprehend directly what is involved in their loss. All in a greater or lesser degree sense the imminence of the Communist peril and are seeking some assurance of salvation. I believe therefore that the moment is ripe for a consilidation of Western Europe. This need not take the shape of a formal alliance, though we have an alliance with France and may conclude one with other countries.It does, however, mean close consultation with each of the Western european countries, beginning with economic questions. We in Britain can no longer standoutside Europe and insist that our problems and position are quite separate fromthose of our European neighbours. Our treaty relations with the various countries might differ, but between all there would be an understanding backed by power,money and resolution and bound together by the common ideals for which theWestern Powers have twice in one generation shed their blood.I am aware that the Soviet Government would react against this policy assavagely as they have done against the Marshall Plan. It would be described asan offensive alliance directed against the Soviet Union. On this point I canonly say that in the situation in which we have been placed by Russian policyhalf measures are useless. If we are to preserve peace and our own safety atthe same time, we can only do so by the mobilisation of such a moral and materialforce as will create confidence and energy on the one side and inspire respect and caution on the other. The alternative is to acquiesce in continued Russianinfiltration and helplessly to witness the piecemeal collapse of one Western bastionafter another.The policy I have outlined will require strong British leadership in orderto secure its acceptance in Europe on one hand and in the Dominions and the americas on the other. Material aid will have to come principally from theUnited States, but the countries of Western Europe which despise the spiritualvalues of America will look to us for political and moral guidance and forassistance in building up a counter attraction to the baleful tenets of communismwithin their borders and in recreating a healthy society wherever it has beenshaken or shattered by the war. I believe that we have the resources with which to perform this task.Provided we can organise a Western European system such as I have outlined above, backed by the power and resources of the Commonwealth and ofthe Americas, it should be possible to develop our own power and influence toequal that of the United States of America and the U.S.S.R. We have the material sources in the Colonial Empire, if we develop them, and by giving a spirituallead now we should be able to carry out our task in a way which will showclearly that we are not subservient to the United States of America or to theSoviet Union.I have already broached the conception of what I called a spiritual unionof the West tentatively to Mr. Marshall and M. Bidault, both of whom seemedto react favourably without of course committing themselves. I now propose,if my colleagues agree, to ventilate the idea in public in my speech in the forth-coming Foreign Affairs Debate and thereafter to pursue it, as occasion demands,with the Governments concerned.E. B.Foreign Office, S. W. 1,4th January, 1948.

NOTEoAttention is drawn to thevery secret nature of the attached memorandum (CP. (U8) 7), the circulation of which has &quot;been strictly limited.Cabinet Office,  S.W.1.5th January, ^^l^.8*

</content>
</cab>
