<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/23/0 images: 220-224</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT J- -   sThe circulation of this paper has been strictly hmited.is paper nas Deen strictly nmixea. ,       A   9personal use of....JL......SECRET       - Copy No,........kl,It is issued for theC.P. (U8) 161 ?TH JANUARY.  19U8.CABINETTHE BASIC PETROL ration memorandum by the Minister of Fuel and power was invited by the Cabinet to submit a memorandumon the possibility of restoring a basic petrol ration(CM. (i+8) 2nd Conclusions, Minute 2).2. The abolition of the basic ration was extremelyunpopular with all those in any way affected by it.      Ithas been followed by a sustained and violent campaign thatshows no sign of abating.     Quito apart from the manymotorists who have to suffer inconvenience and discomfort,there are powerful vested interests who will certainly keepthe agitation olive.      Moreover rationing petrol in peace-time with no basic allowance is on administrative task ofthe utmost difficulty.     Because it involves assessment of individual needs it will probably never be accepted or evenunderstood in the same way as food or clothes rationing.There is certainly therefore a strong political case for restoring some basic ration as soon as possible.      The casewill be even stronger if Marshall Aid becomes available andthe public get the impression that the dollar situation iseesier.3. Nevertheless in view of the sudden changes in policy last summer resulting from the dollar crisis and the subsequent criticism of the Government for vacillation, wemust be absolutely sure of our ground before giving thepublic reason to expect the return of a basic ration.     Toraise hopes and then to disappoint them in this matter wouldbe politically very damaging.k* Three things are needed before we can restore abasic ration.     We must be able to afford the dollars.      Womust be able to obtain the petrol.     We must be able to cope with the administrative problems.5. The Chancellor of the Exchequer will no doubt dealj with the dollar aspect of the problem;    all I need say isI that the direct saving of petrol has been increasing overi the past three months and in December is estimated at onI annual rate of about 880,000 tons, of which about four-fifths] was probably due to the abolition of the basic ration.      AtI the priaea used in making the original estimates in the summerI this quantity of petrol would hove cost us rather more than 8 millions in dollars, but at present prices the cost would
je over  10 millions.      If we restored a basic ration at lessthan its previous level the saving would of course &quot;bejorrespondingly reduced.o. The question whether sufficient petrol can &quot;beobtained is for the greater part of the year likely to &quot;besound up with the acute shortage of tankers.     At present oil supplies are being maintained throughout the world with greatdifficulty and on a hand to mouth basis.      Only by emergencysssistance from the Admiralty have we been able to safeguardoil supplies for industry in this country over the next fewsionths;    and the position thereafter may be equally criticalunless many more American tankers ore in fact put into service on the ocean routes.    , It is, therefore as yet uncertain when wecan build up motor spirit stocks in this country to a point where we could safely contemplate the increased consumptioninvolved in restoring a reduced basic ration.      It could notbe done before June,  unless soles of oil to third countriessere drastically cut - a step which would involve losses offoreign exchange and be politically awkward during the course ofthe, Marshall discussions.7. In the second half of the year the tanker position^should become easier, and it may be possible to import rather[more oil.     But it is by no means certain that even so weshall be able to supply sufficient oil of all kinds to meetrising industrial needs and also to provide a basic petrolration.      The prospect would be a good deal brighter if wecould (a) reduce the amount of petrol issued for commercialtransport and for so-called essential and supplementary allowances,  and (b) get rid of the black market.      The twosteps are related.      For there seems to be little doubt thatthe chief leakage to- the black market takes place throughcommercial transport and certain business users.8. As an essential preliminary to any restoration of abasic ration,  I am therefore setting- up an enquiry into thenature and. extent of the black market and the measures whichshould be taken to check it.      I hope that in consequence weshall be able to reduce the amount of petrol going to goods vehicles, which has shown an increase during the past twoyears from on annual rate of just over 1 million tons in 19h-5to a current rate of about 2 million tons.      A good deal ofthis increase is of course due to greater industrial and commercial activity and the increased registration of goods vehicles, but some of it may well represent a serious leakageto the black market.9. Further, I am not satisfied with the working of the rationing scheme in connection with business and professionalallowances of petrol.     While the total of these allowances(the E.  and S.  allowances) amounts to rather less than one million tons a year and while I doubt if these allowances goto feed the black market to any large extent,  there are certainly some anomalies under the scheme, and an impressionamong the public that the allowances permit an excessive useof private cars.
10i Here too I am accordingly instituting an enquiry(which involves a good deal of statistical research) withview to seeing whether a new and better.system for allowances for business purposes can be evolved and one which willsave petrol in sufficient quantities to make a substantial contribution towards the restoration of a basic ration when this becomes possiblei   This enquiry together with that intothe black market should be completed by the middle of Marchand I would hope by the end of March to report on the matterso that a decision could then be reached in the light of thegeneral oil and dollar situation.ill. Prom the administrative point of view the restorationof the basic ration itself presents few administrative difficulties.   But a recasting of the system on whichsupplementary allowances are granted which might follow theenquiry I have mentioned would be more complicated.   In anycase I should like to have about 2 months notice between thetime of the decision and its coming into effect.12. Meanwhile.it is, I think, most important that nothing should be said or done to encourage the country tobelieve as yet that it may be possible to restore a basicration next summer.   The uncertainties of the&apos;presentsituation are too groat for \is to risk raising hopes whichnay be disappointed.H.T.N.G.Ministry of Fuel and Power, S.W.I.,13th January, 19ho.

N PTEThe attached memorandum(CP. (W) 17) by the lord president of the Council on the interim Report of the Committeeof Enquiry into&apos; the Tudor aircraft is circulated for consideration as an additional item on theAgenda for the meeting of theCabinet, tomorrow. Thursday,15th January,  at 10 a.m.\Cabinet Office, S.W.1.1h-th January, 19h-8.

</content>
</cab>
