<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/23/0 images: 250-252</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
yl61DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT)secret.P.(k8) 2015TH JANUARY. 19*4-8CABINETPARLIAMENT bill memorandum by the Lord Privy seal at the conclusion of the Cabinet race ting at which my memorandum CP. 0+7) 337 was considered (C.H.(4o) 1stConclusions, minute 5; it was arranged that I should submit a draft of the answer that might be given to questions aboutthe willingness of the Government to participate in discussionsconcerning any possible modification of the constitution ofthe existing House of Lords.2. It was agreed that it must be made clear that thepassage of the Bill now before Parliament in its present formor v/ith any agreed amendments thereto was essential in anycaso.3. A desirable objective is to secure, if possible,that the present Bill obtains a Second Reading.   Without this it is difficult to see how any sort of accommodation couldbe arrived at.h. In the Second Reading Debate in the House of Commons,the Prime Minister said that, subject to certain definiteconditions which he mentioned, the Government would be willingto look at proposals for the reform of the Second Chamber(Hansard, Col. 316).5* In c.P.(47)  337 I set out in detail - paragraphU(i) to (v) - v/hat it appeared were the essential conditionsfrom our point of view;    and I think it is fair to say thatthe majority of the Cabinet took the view that the conditionssuggested were reasonable.6. &apos; In this connection I should like to say quitedefinitely that, in my view, apart from securing, if possible,the passage of the Bill nov/ before Parliament this Session,it v/ould be a first class political blunder if we did not make use, if we can, of the present anxiety of the opposition parties, to obtain a more rational composition of the Houseof Lords - always provided, of course, that the conditionswhich Y/e regarded as essential were obtained.COPY NO.10
7. With tho above considerations in mind, I suggestthat an answer to tho Question, which will be put to mo byLord Salisbury (and probably also by Lord Samuel) in theSecond Reading Debate, whether the Government would be willingto consider suggestions for a reform in the composition cfthe present House of Lords, should be as follows:-&quot;The Government have given careful considerationto the Question of the noble Marquess, Lord Salisbury,and to that in similar terms of the noble Viscount,Lord Samuel, of which previous notice has been given.The Government regard the passing of this bill now before the House or with any agreed amendmentsrelating to the powers of the House of Lords, whetherconstituted as at present or in a modified form, as essential.Subject to this, they are willing, withoutprejudice on either side, to discuss the issues raised in the noble Marquess&apos;s Question.&quot;8. I should point out that, amongst the noticesfor &quot;No Day Named&quot; on yesterday&apos;s Notice Paper of the Houseof Lords is a Question in the name of Lord Samuel in thefollowing terms:-&quot;To ask His Majesty&apos;s Government whether theyhave been able to give further consideration,to the advisability of summoning a conferenceof representatives of tho Three Parties inthis House to examine the question of theconstitution of the House of Lords.;lord Samuel has written to me suggesting that he should put this Question down for answer during the week parliament reassembles (i.e. before the 27th January).   I am endeavouringto persuade him to postpone it until the Second Reading Debate.A *House of Lords, S.W.I.,15th January, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
