<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/23/0 images: 256-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY13 GOVERNMENT)[E C R B T COPY NO.^0kV.(kQ) 222qth JANUARY.   19^-8.CABINETSCOTTISH affairs memorandum by the Secretary of State for scotland at their meeting on 11th December (CM. (1+7) 9UthConclusions, Minute k) the Cabinet gave general approval to proposals (CP. (U7) 323) for meeting the demand for agreater measure of Scottish control over Scottish affairs.After &quot;consultation with the Lord President,  I propose, in orderto avoid a lengthy oral statement in the House,  to announcethese proposals in a White Paper,  a proof of which I circulate for the information of my colleagues.      The precise time of presentation would be agreed with the Lord President and theChief Whip.      The terms of reference of the proposed ScottishEconomic Conference have,  as desired by the Cabinet, beenagreed with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.2. I have had confidential discussions with -(a) the Scottish Executive of the Parliamentary LabourParty (the Chairman of which is also the Chairmanof the Highlands panel);(b) the Executive of the Scottish Council of the LabourParty;(c) the General Secretary of the Scottish Trades UnionCongress (who is also the Chairman of the scottish board for Industry);(d) the Chairman and Executive of the Scottish Council(Development and Industry).a result,  I am satisfied that my proposals are acceptableothese bodies.      I have also had discussions withRepresentatives of the Opposition and I have reason to believehat my proposals will not be opposed by the other Parties.A.W.IfottiBh Office, S.W.1.20th January,  1 9U8.
CONFIDENTIALDraftSCOTTISH AFFAIRSGENERAL&quot;i. His Majesty&apos;s Government are conscious, of the widespread desire inScotland that the Scottish people should have increased opportunities of dealing/&quot;&quot;With affairs of purely Scottish concern.   In Parliament members of both Houses&quot; &quot;and of all Parties have made a variety of proposals designed to improve the handling of Scottish affairs ; and both the Prime Minister and the Leader of theOpposition have commended Scottish aspirations.a. The Government are anxious to do everything possible within the framework of the British Constitution and the existing Parliamentary system to meet Scottishdesires, while preserving Scotland&apos;s rights in Parliament. They have accordinglyexamined the existing arrangements for the conduct of legislative and administrativebusiness relating to Scotland with a view to making such changes as are desirable and immediately practicable.3. The aspects so considered by the Government concern Scottish legislation and Scottish Estimates ; economic questions affecting Scotland ; the machineryfor the administration of Government affairs in Scotland ; the direction of the nationalised industries in Scotland ; and an enquiry into these and other questions.4. The results of the Governments examination are set out below.PARLIAMENTARY BUSINESS5. As regards Legislation, the Government recommend that the standing orders of the House of Commons should be amended so as to enable the Housewithout debate to decide, on the motion of a Minister of the Crown and in theabsence of opposition by ten or more Members, to refer a Scottish Bill to theStanding Committee on Scottish Bills for consideration in principle. Where aBill has been so referred the House would, on its return, be authorised to decidewithout debate, and if necessary by a division, to give or not to give it a SecondReading. An amendment of this kind, which (together with that proposed inthe following paragraph) formulates specifically an aspiration of Scottish Membersreiterated over many years, would enable the House of Commons, while retaining the formal act of Second Reading and the normal Report and Third Readingstages, by agreement to remit a purely Scottish Bill for Second Reading debateto the Standing Committee. The proposal accordingly differs in certain materialrespects from that which was considered in 1946 by the Select Committee on procedure. The types of Bill to which, in the Governments view, it would be suitable and convenient to apply the new procedure would be Bills of a technicalnature applying only to Scotland which, though debateable, are not controversialin a Party sense ; certain Bills which make for Scotland provision similar to that already made or proposed for England and Wales ; and Bills of purely Scottishinterest for which time cannot immediately be found under existing arrangements.6. As regards Estimates, the Government have considered the draft of anew Order of the House standing on the Order Paper in the names of Mr Elliotand other Honourable Members. This amendment would enable the House ofCommons without debate to decide, on the motion of a Minister of the Crown,to refer to the Standing Committee on Scottish Bills for consideration on specifieddays the whole or part of the Estimates for which the Secretary of State forScotland is responsible. After such consideration the Estimates would comeformally before the Committee of Supply in the ordinary way. The government propose to accept the amendment in principle with a limitation to six in the
ECONOMIC AFFAIRS8. As regards the economic position of Scotland, the Government proposeto supplement the existing arrangements for the consideration of Scottish questionsby convening a Scottish Economic Conference. The Conference would meetregularly under the Chairmanship of the Secretary of State for the exchange ofinformation on developments and trends in Scottish economic affairs and toconfer with him on questions of economic importance in Scotland. Thoseinvited to attend would include the Chairman and other representatives of theScottish Council (Development and Industry), the Scottish Board for Industry,the Highlands and Islands Panel, astr-the Chairman of the Scottish Tourist Board,and representatives of Government Departments and State-appointed organisations concerned with economic matters, including the nationalised industries. the function of the Conference would be consultative, and the powers and responsi-bilities of the Departments and bodies represented on it would not be affected.Details of the terms of reference and the proposed membership of the conference are set out in Appendix B.9. It is further proposed to publish and present to Parliament an annual review of the main developments and trends in the economic affairs of Scotland.This would supplement and bring up-to-date the information given in the white paper on Industry and Employment in Scotland (Cmd. 7125).MACHINERY     OF     GOVERNMENT     AND     NATIONALISEDINDUSTRIES10. As regards the machinery for the administration of government business in Scotland, there is already a very wide measure of executivedevolution. Not only are the headquarters of the Secretary of State&apos;s ownDepartments situated in Edinburgh but other Ministers who exercise functions in Scotland have in practically all cases established offices in Scotland in chargeof officers to whom a wide measure of executive responsibility has been delegated.This machinery is, of course, kept continually under review in order that it may be adapted as necessary to changing circumstances from time to time. special attention will be given as opportunity offers to the possibilities of further develop-ments in this direction which would lead to greater efficiency.11. As regards the nationalised industries, the new Boards are in course of developing their own organisation within the wide limits of discretion given tothem by Parliament, and the Government will keep under observation the pattern of these arrangements as they are worked out in order to ensure that they are properly related to Scottish needs.number of days which can&apos; be spent by the Scottish Committee on ScottishEstimates. It would be understood that acceptance does not involve the resignation of the days normally given to the discussion of Scottish Estimates in committee of Supply.7. The Government are submitting for the consideration of the House ofCommons a motion providing for the amendment of the Standing Orders^of theHouse to give effect to these proposals. The draft Standing Orders arc set outin Appendix A. They would give more time for the discussion of. Scottish affairsby Scottish Members, while preserving the control of the House over bothLegislation and Estimates ; and they are sufficiently flexible to enable the arrange-ments to be varied according to the importance of the legislation and the stateof the time-table in the House of Commons itself.
THE QUESTION OF A GENERAL ENQUIRY12. In the course of their examination of the various issues dealt with in this white Paper, the Government have given sympathetic consideration to the requests from many quarters for the setting up of a Committee of enquiry into Scottish affairs generally. Suggestions which have been made as to the scope and objects of such an Enquiry are varied and seldom well defined. They ranges-\ over the desirability of further legislative and Parliamentary devolution ; the&apos; facts of the financial relationship between Scotland and other parts of the UnitedKingdom ; Scottish exports and imports and the economic position of Scotlandgenerally; the machinery of Government in Scotland ; and the arrangements in Scotland for the administration of nationalised industries. A Committee ofEnquiry covering all these matters would accordingly be concerned partly withfacts and partly with matters of opinion.13. Essential facts bearing on the economic position, so far as they are reasonably ascertainable, will be published in the Annual Review mentioned above,and elsewhere, as occasion arises. It is essential, however, at this period of crisisto avoid-any material increase in the calls made on the already strained resourcesof industrial, commercial and other interests, of public bodies, and of GovernmentDepartments ; and practical limits must be set to the volume of further statisticsto be collected. It is unlikely, therefore, that even if a Committee were appointed,the factual information which it would be practicable to collect within a measurabletime would be regarded by those who are asking for an Enquiry as sufficient inrange and in detail to provide a basis for reliable and agreed conclusions.14. The matters of opinion into which it is suggested a Committee shouldenquire also cover a wide field and are, of course, acutely controversial. any committee set up to examine them would have to include members from bothsides of the Border and of varying political views ; and such members might wellbe found to have strongly held opinions for and against Scottish nationalism.The possibilities of fundamental disagreement are therefore obvious. It is unlikelythat any Enquiry, however wide its scope, would satisfy the conflicting demands which have been made ; and the time required for detailed investigation of all aspects of the position would in any case mean much delay.15. The Government feel, therefore, that the time is not opportune to set upa formal Committee of Enquiry, and that it is more important to make immediateprogress by concentrating on the practical measures proposed. In their viewthese go a long way to meet the underlying purposes of the great majority of thosewho have asked for an Enquiry.
APPENDIX ADraft Standing Orders relating to Scottish business in the House of Commons(i) A public Bill relating exclusively to Scotland may be proceeded with underthe provisions set out in this Order.(2) A Bill to be proceeded with under this Order shall be laid upon the Tablebefore presentation, or, in the case of a Bill brought from the House of Lords,before first reading, together with a certificate by Mr Speaker that its provisionsrelate exclusively to Scotland, and shall be printed by order of the House.(3) After five clear days, notice of the presentation or, in the case of a Billbrought from the House of Lords, of the first reading of the Bill may be given,and such notice shall indicate that the Bill is to be proceeded with under this order.(4) After the title of the Bill has been read at the Table or, in the case of aBill brought from the House of Lords, after the first reading, a motion, to bedecided without amendment or debate, may be made by a Minister of the Crown,&quot; that the Bill be referred to the Standing Committee on Scottish Bills,&quot; providedthat if the motion shall have been thereupon objected to by not less than tenmembers, it shall pass in the negative.(5) A Bill so referred to the Standing Committee shall be considered in relationto the principle of the Bill and shall be reported without amendment to the house and shall be ordered to be read a second time on a future day.(6) When the order of the day for the second reading of a Bill so reported hasbeen read, a motion to be decided without amendment or debate may be madeby a Minister of the Crown &quot; That the Bill be committed to the Standing Committeeon Scottish Bills.&quot;(7) If such a motion shall have been agreed to, the Bill shall be deemed tohave been read a second time and shall stand committed to the Standing Committeeon Scottish Bills, and shall proceed through its remaining stages according to theordinary practice of the House.(S) A Motion may be made by a Minister of the Crown at the commencementof Public Business to the effect that the Committee of Supply be discharged fromconsidering the Estimates or any part or parts of the Estimates for which theSecretary of State for Scotland is responsible and that such Estimates or part orparts of such Estimates be referred to the Standing Committee on Scottish bills for consideration on not more than six days specified in the Motion. The question on such a Motion shall be decided without amendment or debate.(9) If such Question be agreed to, the Standing Committee shall consider theEstimates referred to them, and shall report only that they have considered thesaid Estimates, which shall again stand referred to the Committee of Supply afterthe last day specified in the Motion.
APPENDIX BSCOTTISH ECONOMIC conference i.   Terms of ReferenceTo meet frbmtime to time for the interchange of information on develop-I     ments and trends in economic affairs and to confer with the Secretary of state on questions of economic importance in Scotland.II.   CompositionChairman.The Secretary of State for Scotland.Members.i. Development, Industry and Commerce generally(a) The Chairman and six other members of the Executive Committee ofthe Scottish Council (Development and Industry)   representingh //it, Industry and Commerce^ Scottish Trades Union Congress, and Localfi Government.(b) The Chairman and two other members of the Scottish Board for industry.(c) The Chairman and two other members of the Advisory Panel on the highlands and Islands.(d) The Chairman of the Scottish Tourist Board.(e) A representative of the Agricultural Advisory Council for Scotland.(/) The Chairman of the Scottish Committee of the Forestry Commission.(g) The Chairman of the Herring Industry Board.3. Nationalised Industries(a) The Chairman of the North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board (who isex officio a member of the British Electricity Authority).(b) The Chairman of the South East and South West Scotland AreaElectricity Boards.(c) The Chairman of the Scottish Division of the National Coal Board.(d) The Chairman of the Scottish Advisory Geeamtttee on Civil Aviation.(e) A representative of the British European Airways Corporation.(/) Appropriate representation of the British Transport Commission andExecutives.3. Government Departments(a) The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Scotland and the secretaries of the Department of Agriculture for Scotland, the Scottish education department, the Department of Health for Scotland and the scottish home Department. it .0 .e*rt?im .&apos;W
(b) The Senior Admiralty Representative in Scotland on civil labour and production. r - -        - --(c) The Scottish. Controller of the Board of Trade (who is also Chairman ofthe- Distribution of Industry Panel and the Export Committee inScotland).(d) The Controller of the Scottish Division of the Ministry of CiviT Aviation(who is also Chairman of the Scottish Aerodromes Board).(e) The Scottish Controller of the Ministry of Labour and National Service.(f) The Scottish Controller of the Ministry of Supply.(g) The Scottish Under-Secretary of the Ministry of Works.. &apos;Representatives of othedLinterests will be invited to attend meetings of theConference as necessary.The full conference will be convened at regular intervals and in addition theSecretary of State will meet particular members from time to time as circumstancesrequire. The conference will not deliberate in public nor will it pass formalresolutions. The secretarial and other work connected with the conference willbe undertaken by the Scottish Home Department. .   --AoiJjBiv/-. Jr/iJ nw -yiiumwij vioatyu- - .nouVtoq&apos;ioO evcv/iiA nroqwi.tic iioieiiiiiiaioD JioqexisiT dtlyaii itifamit&amp; under the. authority of HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE &apos;tltysiiiOMiiV iS^-^B^H^iiPiitbir&amp;SoOTttrf^-jSr --&apos; &apos;rfetWcoS adJ ban uhkUojS ?ot mlsoH lo tssiahsxtaii on) iJosaiixcqM\\u 74725/583-     1/48.     G. 21


</content>
</cab>
