<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/61/0 images: 39-40</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1953SECRET Copy No.C. (53) 16121st May, 1953CABINETSHORTAGE OF MEDICAL OFFICERS IN THE army memorandum by the Secretary of State for WarI am very concerned about the serious shortage of medical officers in theArmy. Now that we have compulsory service a continued deterioration in numbers and quality might well lead to widespread public indignation.background the Royal Army Medical Corps has been in difficulty for some time. Thesituation has recently become acute. It can be traced to two causes. First, theintroduction of a National Health Service which has given better financial rewardsfor doctors and also a more secure and assured career with a pension at the endof it. Second, the introduction of National Service which has resulted in an increasein the population for which the Army is responsible from the pre-war figure of200,000 to 525,000 (or, if women and children are included, to about 760,000).Present position at the moment we are 15 per cent, down in doctors but that is not the worst.There is a much more serious deficiency in specialists and experienced general practitioners. We ought to have 458 specialists and to-day we have 345. we need 73 surgeons and have got 32. 90 per cent, of the doctors doing general practitioner duties are young National Service officers. Such a high proportion is most undesirable and, indeed, has been termed by the Ministry of Health repre-sentative on the Maude Committee as unacceptable in civil practice.When men joined the Army voluntarily it could be argued that they acceptedcertain risks in all directions; but to-day compulsory service places a far greaterobligation on the Government to provide a satisfactory Army Medical Service.Future trendsFor the last four or five years we have been losing Regular doctors steadily.The present deficiency in Regular doctors is some 383 out of an estimated require-ment of 792. The future trend in the shortage of specialists is even worse. Therewere 387 on 1st January, 1952, and we estimate there will be 298 on 1st January,1955, and for the same dates the number of surgeons is likely to go from 58 to 28.Present proposalsA Committee was set up and as a result the following proposals have beenagreed by the Service Departments:  An initial inducement grant of  2,000 (taxed) to an entrant on appointment to a Regular Commission.Three-year short-service commissions.Direct entry to regular commission.Limited increases of pay for majors to brigadiers (and their equivalentranks).44267
The employment of retired officers.Ante-dates of up to seven years for late entrants to permanent or short-service commissions.Increased pay for senior specialists.vThese are acceptable both to the Air Force whose position is less serious thanthe Army&apos;s and also to the Admiralty whose medical service is in a relatively satis-factory state.The long-term problemI do not, however, believe that these recommendations will solve the Army&apos;smore serious problems.Before raising this matter I consulted the Army Medical Advisory Board which includes many eminent doctors such as Lord Webb-Johnson, Lord Moran, sir arthur Porritt, &amp;c. They were unanimous in advising me that these proposals would provide no solution to our present problem and that a more radical examina-tion of the whole matter should at once be carried out so that in the near future wewould be in a position to consider more drastic steps.I am in agreement with their advice but I am placed in something of a dilemmabecause this problem does not arise for the Admiralty and is less acute in theRoyal Air Force. Quite naturally they do not favour a more radical examinationwhich would include their medical service. It is, therefore, a situation in whichinter-service agreement is, by the very nature of the problem, impossible to achieve.1 should be most reluctant to forgo the benefits of the measures described underthe present proposals above. Although I do not think they will solve the Army&apos;difficulties they should undoubtedly help us to hold the position until more radicalsteps are ready for consideration.I therefore recommend that without prejudice to the acceptance of the pro-posals already agreed by the Service Departments, an independent committeeshould be set up (preferably under Lord Waverley whose provisional consent Iobtained some time ago) to enquire into the matter on behalf of all three services or, if that cannot be agreed, on behalf of the Army alone.A. H.War Office,21st May, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
