<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/61/0 images: 65-66</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1953SECRET Copy No.C.(53) 16912th June, 1953CABINETRELATIONS WITH SOUTH africa memorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations circulate for the information of my colleagues a record of a conversation which I have had with Mr. Havenga, the South African Minister of Finance.SWINTON.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,12th June, 1953.65Record of Conversation between the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and the Hon. N. C. Havenga, South African Minister ofFinance, on Wednesday, 10th June, 1953Mr. Havenga came to see me this morning. He said that Dr. Malan and he ought not to leave without our having had some talk about the Protectorates andthe question of Transfer. There was a strong feeling among all their followersthat nothing had happened in forty years, and the prospects of Transfer did notappear to get any better. What was to be the position? Was it to recede further into the background? It was the one question which could embitter relationsbetween our two countries and make our co-operation on other things moredifficult.2. I said that Mr. Havenga was a realist and he must realise that there couldnot be a worse moment to raise this question. As a Government we hadscrupulously maintained the position that South Africa&apos;s internal policy was heraffair. We had maintained that position not only in this country but at the united nations Organisation; Havenga assured me that they fully appreciated that. But,I went on, there was no doubt about what people in this country felt about thenative policy South Africa had adopted. The United Kingdom Government couldnot possibly contemplate Transfer at the present time and even if the Governmentwere prepared to consider it, which they were not, they would not get ten votesin the House of Commons if they proposed it. It was much better to speakfrankly. Havenga said that, being a realist, he appreciated that this was theposition. But what about the future? Was Transfer to be ruled out for ever?I said that the worst possible thing would be to raise it now. If it were raised now,things would be said which must make the whole future more difficult.3. Havenga said that not only his own Party, which had a good majority inParliament, but many of the Opposition were in favour of the policy of Apartheid.While South Africa was firmly determined that political power should rest in thehands of the white men, their policy was to do a great deal for the material advance-ment and prosperity of the natives, and to do their best for them in the native44350
10th June, 1953.reserves. It was not realised here how much they were doing for native welfare. I said that neither of us could prophesy what would happen in the future. If thepolicy of Apartheid succeeded, in the sense that it were proved that the native. population were well treated and prospered under it, public opinion outside Southif Africa, though they would not think this Apartheid the right way, might come tothink better of it in practice.4. Havenga pointed out that the Territories depended a great deal on theUnion. I said that there was close economic co-operation and that the more thatwas developed the better. In a number of ways that was working well to-day,and that was the best means of practical co-operation. Havenga then asked whatwould be the attitude of our local administrators, and how would they advise thenative populations. I said that so far as economic co-operation went they would do all they could to further it, but that I certainly could not instruct ouradministrators to try and influence the Africans in the Territories in favour of transfer.5. In the end, Havenga said that his Government would not raise the questionof Transfer with us at the present time. They must be free to say that they thoughtTransfer was right, aud ought to be conceded, but Malan and he would do their best to avoid a head-on collision. He thought they could do that for the timebeing, but they were old men nearing the end of their course and their successorswould be less realistic. He must emphasise again that while they would do their best to avoid a collision of this kind, the Transfer question was a constant source of friction and was likely to become more so as time went on.6. Havenga then went on to talk very frankly about the Republic. He saidthat this certainly was not an issue at the present time. He did not think it would come in his lifetime. On this Malan and he had full support in their Cabinet. EvenStrydom had agreed that there could be no question of a Republic unless the whitepopulation of the Union expressed a decisive opinion on that specific question.It had not been an issue in the election. It was Havenga&apos;s personal opinion thatif a secret ballot was taken to-day, two-thirds of the white population would vote against a Republic. Havenga added that one of the strongest forces makingAfrikaners inclined to a Republic was the attitude of some of the people in Natalin trying to claim as it were, a special property in the Queen and saying that theCrown would protect them.7. Havenga then said that the least helpful thing over both the Republic andthe Territories was when newspapers wrote that Dr. Malan was going to raisethese issues actively. I assured Havenga that I had done and would continue todo my best with the Press and that I had told them that the surest way of gettingthese &quot;issues raised, which I hoped and believed could lie dormant, was to ventilatethem in the Press here.8.. Havenga also referred with a good deal of unhappiness to a statement which had appeared in the foreign supplement of the Economist that he had said he was in favour of leaving the sterling area. This really was a bit hard. He hadbeen such a staunch partner and had now brought the whole of his Cabinet round tohis point of view. He said he would mention this to the Chancellor. I said wehad all appreciated enormously his loyal and generous support and that this sort of thing was intolerable, but he was an old politician and he would realise that weall of us suffered alike from time to time, and some of us very frequently, undermisrepresentations in the Press.SWINTON.

</content>
</cab>
