<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/61/0 images: 8-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
?fl bSBtHIS document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s  government ^|BfBJ Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1953 &apos;- I&amp;**fe#iSf&amp;tfK^it . B_BJI     SECRET (,                 .Copy No. ^ Q ^|^fl C. (53) 188                                                    il^^ ^flCABINET&apos;: &quot;&apos;^ :_?JJANTARCTICA       Kt i\ taj-.;.&apos;&apos;B_BJ Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and VAwJB_BJ the Secretary of State for the ColoniesBABJ We attach a memorandum prepared by our Departments in consultation with BAB-1B-BJ officials of the Commonwealth Relations Office and the Admiralty oh policy in the BfBflBfBJ Antarctic. B_B_IBfBJ 2.  Hitherto the policy of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, in close consultation BfBaBfBJ I with the Governments of Australia and New Zealand, has been to assert and BfBflBfBJ maintain title to the sectors shown in the map at Annex B (circulated separately) IBfBJ as claimed by the Governments concerned. Recent events in the Falkland Islands HBfBJ Dependencies have forced us to review our position. In pursuance of our policy, IBfBJ Her Majesty&apos;s Government and the Government of the Falkland Islands Dependen- ^BfflBfBJ cies have been spending up to  200,000 a year, in addition to the naval effort ^B_flBfBJ I involved, in support of our title.  Much of what is now being done is ineffective ^BAflBfBJ for this purpose.  It is directed to keeping up a general claim to the area as aBfBJ whole; but we are advised that, as we lack a clear legal title to the whole area, BfBBBfBJ such activities are not, and possibly never can be, sufficient for this purpose in IBfBJ the face of competing claims by countries such as Argentina and Chile, which are BJBfBJ better placed geographically to operate there. The present activities for the main- BflfflI tenance of sovereignty are not moreover, for the most part, those which serve to B_Bfl^^fl increase our knowledge of the territory. I^^fl 3.  The memorandum demonstrates that in existing circumstances our present IBfBJ policy offers us the worst of ail worlds. Despite the outlay of considerable sums of BJBfBJ money, man-power and resources, this policy will not prevent the progressive BJBfBJ deterioration of Her Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s position in Antarctica.  It is likely BJBfBJ to lead to continued friction with Argentina and Chile, and to the possibility of BJBfBJ humiliation at the hands of two minor Powers in a distant quarter of the globe. HBfBJ We are satisfied that this state of affairs must not be allowed to persist. BflfflJ^^fl 4.  The alternatives before us are- ^^^flBJ 1 (a) to make available the necessary resources to ensure that our activities in B_B_JBfBJ Antarctica are on a scale sufficient to maintain our juridical position and BfB_VBfBJ to permit the proper exploration of the territory; or ^BfBJBfBJ (b) to proceed to the orderly reduction of our political and naval commitment BJBfBJ in the area to a scale which we are in a position permanently to meet. BJBfBJ 5.  This is a difficult choice. Expansion will involve calls upon our resources IBfBJ already stretched by our other overseas commitments. Reduction, while it carries BJBfBJ no disadvantages to military strategy, entails the sacrifice of lands which we have flBfBJ proclaimed to be British, and the jettisoning of unexplored potential sources of BJBJ I wealth.  It would be unwelcome to Australia and New Zealand, whose interests ^^^HBfBJ have to be taken into account. ^BfBJBfBJ  r 6.   The choice cannot be delayed. The Antarctic season opening this autumn BfB_flB_BJ is likely to be critical. The challenge to our sovereignty, already acute, will have BfB_flfl been sharpened by the Deception Island incident.  We must begin planning now J^flfflJBfBJ either to advance and consolidate our position, or to retire. BfBffl4444S
LH LIk^k^ka                       7.   It would clearly be preferable, if the resources can be found, to opt boldly k^^kVk^k^k|                for expansion.   This should enable us to gain a clearer view of the economic k^HI potentialities of the sector, and then to decide our policy in fuller knowledge of the k|^Hk^^kfl                facts. This would mean that-k^k^k| t^t    (i) resources should be made available for a thorough air survey of the    -J| k^Hk^^H &quot;Antarctic sector, to be followed by investigation on the ground of the   Hr k^H&apos;&apos;^^&quot;Jv..-.   mineral possibilities of the area;H                      (ii) for a period of at least five years, while the above survey is in progress, k^HI                              the activities of the Falkland Islands Dependencies Survey should be k^kVI                \ &apos; * ? y increased, so as to ensure that our political and legal position in the k^kfl??^??S                              area does not deteriorate and that the leeway lost in recent years is k^kVk^k^H made up;  . ^|??^??V                     (iii) increased help, including specially strengthened ships, would be required k^kflpn|         &quot;from the Royal Navy. ki^H8.  But if we cannot fulfil these requirements, the only practicable alternative k^kflwill be the planned reduction of our Antarctic commitment. In this event, ki^H(i) a decision should be taken now, that we should no longer attempt to k^kV??^??V                             maintain our claim to the whole area, and our future activities should k^kVbe thus determined;(ii) the Governments of Canada, South Africa, New Zealand and particularly k^kVk^^kV                       -t?^ Australia (who have recently decided to establish a permanent base k^kVin their Antarctic territory) should be informed in detail of our pro- k^kVposals-and given an opportunity to comment, should they so wish; k^^kVk^Hkf            $M    (hi) the Foreign Secretary should thereafter be authorised to pursue such of k^kVthe courses listed in paragraph 15 of the attached memorandum as k^kVmay seem appropriate, with a view to securing an eventual settlement k^^kVk^^k^V of the dispute.k^^k^V 9.  In order that the necessary dispositions may be made for the forthcomingk^^k^S Antarctic season, which opens in October, a decision on Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-k^^k^V mentis Antarctic policy must be taken without delay. Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassadorsk^k^H               at Buenos Aires and Santiago are also seeking instructions on how they should ki^Hk^k^H               handle recent approaches from the Argentine and Chilean Governments. ki^H3rd July, &quot;4
&amp; j i        As shown on the map at Annex B, the greater part of the Antarctic continent^-Wl and the adjacent islands is divided into sectors claimed respectively by the UnitedKingdom, Norway, Australia, France and New Zealand;/-&quot; The United Kingdomterritory was annexed to the Crown as the Falkland Islands Dependencies in ^^^H1908:  The Ross Dependency was established by Order in Council in 1923 and^-Wm placed under New Zealand.  The Australian Antarctic territory was defined byOrder in CJbuncil in .1933.  All five countries recognise one another&apos;s claims. TheI        United States Government has hitherto refused to recognise ahy territorial claimsin the Antarctic.   Argentina and Chile have in the last decade laid claim to sectors II of territory which in part overlap the United Kingdom sector, and also partly ^^^Joverlap one another.   With the exception of South Georgia the area has no residentpopulation, and the Antarctic continent is largely covered by an ice-cap as much^-Wm as half a mile thick in places.2. In 1920 His Majesty&apos;s Government informed the Australian and NewZealand Governments that they had come to the conclusion that the whole of theAntarctic should ultimately be included within the British Empire and that a policyof extending and asserting British control should be followed.   British policy inH I the Antarctic was discussed with the Commonwealth Governments at the ImperialConferences of 1926, 1930 and 1937. The Committee on Polar Questions appointedby the latest of these Conferences considered what action could be taken,in thefuture by His Majesty&apos;s Governments to consolidate their title to the territorieswhich they administered, and discussed the possibilities of co-operation in anyscientific or economic activities. Though Australian and New Zealand activities^^Wl on the mainland have so far been meagre, the Australian Government have now^-Wm decided, despite financial stringency, to establish a permanent base in their sector.3. Increasing efforts to explore and develop the resources of the Dependencies IH I         have been made since the latter part of the first World War.   United Kingdom^^Wl activities are now carried on by the Falkland Islands Dependencies Survey (F.I.D.S.),^-Wm which was created in 1943, and is responsible to the Colonial Secretary through the^-Wm Governor of the Falkland Islands. . The Survey maintains bases (of which thereare now six) in the Dependencies, and has carried out meteorological and geologicalI        survey and other valuable work, as well as a limited amount of exploration bysledge. The R.R.S. John Biscoe is maintained for the supply and relief of our bases.The activities of the F.I.D.S. have been confined to the group of islands lying north, tI north-east and west of Grahamland and to certain limited areas of the peninsula. IThe annual cost of the F.I.D.S. activities is about  200,000.  This is provided bylocal revenues, mainly derived from whaling at South Georgia, supplemented byan annual grant of up to  100,000 from United Kingdom funds.4. The strategic value of the Falkland Islands Dependencies has recently Hbeen re-examined by the Chiefs of Staff, whose conclusions are appended. The^^fl Chiefs of Staff considered that the Dependencies as such provide no strategicadvantage to Her Majesty&apos;s Government which we do not already enjoy by reasonof our possession of the Falkland Islands. The only proved economic value of the IDependencies consists in the land-based whaling industry at South Georgia,H   m      export duties on whale and seal oil forming the chief source of the Dependencies&apos;revenue ( 110,000 in 1952-53).  There is a possibility of the resumption of land-based whaling at Deception Island. Small quantities of coal, copper, tin, gold andI silver have been found on the Antarctic continent. Practically nothing, however, HI is known of the extent of these deposits and the existing resources of the F.I.D.S. Hdo not permit of systematic exploration for mineral deposits. If the existence ofsubstantial mineral deposits were confirmed, it is problematical whether, unlessradio-active minerals were found, exploitation would be profitable. BI 5.  Counter-claims to parts of the United Kingdom sector were first seriouslymade by Argentina and Chile during the late war, and the post-war years haveseen progressive and systematic encroachment by both countries who at presentW     maintain seven and three bases respectively on British territory.   Evidence is^-^M available from documents captured at Deception Island of plans to expand theArgentine total to nine bases this year, and steadily increased activity must beexpected in the future.  By reason of their geographical proximity, and of theb
??? ?!amount of resources which they can make available, including their navies and B^Hair forces which have little else to do, Argentina and Chile are much better placedthan Her Majesty&apos;s Government to sustain over a prolonged period a competitivestruggle for possession-,bf the Antarctic sector. Argentina, at any rate, was com-mitted to such a struggle in 1952, when President Peron publicly announced his     a|| B^Hintention of dominating the &quot; Argentine Antarctic&quot; &apos;* in accordance with aprogressive plan.&quot;.6,  As.regards the legal position, the Law Officers advised in 1947 that we had        I B^Hnot a clear&quot;title to the sector as a whole; our declaration of annexation was aunilateral pronouncement and was not followed up by effective occupation ofthe sector as a whole. We have, in their view, a good title to those parts whichwe have effectively occupied and the longer and more continuous the occupation I B^Hthe better the title to them.! As regards other parts of the sector, in so far as ourtitle to them rested wholly on the 1908 Declaration, it would not necessarily be recog-nised by other States, and therefore could be argued to remain res nullius andBJBJ open to the claims of the first effective and theoretically continuous occupier. In        I BJBJshort our title to the whole sector depends essentially on treating it as an indivisiblewhole and inferring that occupation of a part of it is an occupation of the wholeas an entity. In view of the size of the sector, this claim would be highly dubious.BJBJ Consequently, every year sees a strengthening of title by Argentine and Chile to I B^Hthose parts of the whole area which they effectively occupy despite the extensionto them of our 1908 Declaration. We have made several formal offers to refer thematter to the International Court of Justice, but these have been declined andBJBJ there-is ho means of compelling the two countries concerned to have recourse to I B^Hthe Court. While, in these circumstances, the activities of the other two countriesought not, as a matter of law, to count towards the improvement of their claim,our Legal Advisers consider that, in practice, they cannot fail to do so, and theyB^H will certainly have an adverse effect on our own claim to the area as a whole, In I B^Hshort, we are, from the legal point of view, in the position of having a wastingasset. Our legal position is still reasonably strong but will become progressivelyweaker as the years go by unless we can at least match the activities of the othertwo countries by equally great activities of our own in the area. A reference ^^flto the International Court of Justice would have the advantage of determiningthe position once and for all, but it should be noted that it would be mostunlikely to lead to an endorsement of our claims to the whole area. We ought,on the other hand, to succeed in respect of a considerable part of our claim.. 7.  The two Governments have publicly adopted the position that the Britishsector of Antarctica is beyond question respectively Argentine and Chilean territory.Though their respective claims conflict with one another they have repeatedlyBJBJ expressed their intention of pursuing the struggle together against the commonadversary, and there is little doubt that they could, if Her Majesty&apos;s Government B^Hwere once eliminated, reach agreement on a division of the spoils.  Though Chileis the less energetic of the two (her main interest is probably to deny Argentina aB^H monopoly of the Antarctic), there is little practical possibility of driving a wedgebetween the two countries.   The Argentine Government, in particular, recognise I BJBJthat time is on their side, and believe that, given a ten years&apos; continuation of thepresent state of affairs, they will have established effective possession of the sector.BABJ For this reason, Argentina has shown a desire to avoid direct clashes, and hasentered into arrangements renewable annually with Her Majesty&apos;s Government andChile which.restrict naval activity in the Antarctic area. B^HBAPJ                     8.   Chilean and Argentine operations on British territory have led to con- ^^Btinuous friction between Her Majesty&apos;s Government and both Governments. Thisinitially took the form .merely of diplomatic protests. ..It has, however, been ^^Bnecessary from time to time to despatch naval forces to the area and a frigate of the I BJVJBJBJ               America and West Indies station has recently been obliged to spend most Of the ^^BAntarctic summer in the Dependencies. The installation in January 1953 of ^^BArgentine and Chilean buildings within sight of bur base at Deception Islandrepresented the most flagrant case of intrusion yet attempted, and steps were taken ^^BBJBJ               to evict and deport the intruders and to dismantle their huts^  Similar incidents A B^Hmust be expected in future as the Argentine and Chilean programmes expand. wm ^^flSuch incidents react unfavourably upon our otherwise not unsatisfactory relations ^^Bwith the two countries, and the small size of the Naval forces at our disposal locally ^^BBABJ exposes us to the risk of humiliation.
I 9.  Disadvantages of the present position.-The situation which has arisen*^;-|| from the developments described above confers no advantages on Her Majesty&apos;s H*W Government, and carries with it the following disadvantages:- &apos; s/4 ufojithbfcni*JJDr* I^^HJuridically.-We are losing ground to Argentina and Chile, whose claimsare gaining strength at our expense.Politically.-We face the growing risk of incidents, and the-consequentdisturbance of our relations with both countries.ki^H                   Economically.-We are unable to make a systematic exploratiori?r^Jt^e~_ qx] k^k^kaarea, or to ascertain its potentialities.Militarily.-We are obliged to maintain in a remote area naval forces which , k^k^kaII^H             can ill be spared elsewhere.                                 iWii^^VWAi^W^^* l^k^klk^^kV 10.  No course of action open to Her Majesty&apos;s Government will avoid all thek^^kV above disadvantages, but these could be notably reduced, and a consistent arid viableki^H         policy developed, either by increasing or decreasing our present scale of activities ki^kVin theki^H I           11.  Increased activity would enable us--   . ki^kVk^^H (a) to arrest the deterioration in our juridical position by matching the activi-Awfl ties of Argentina and Chile in the area;k^^H (b) to ascertain, after thorough exploration, the economic potentialities of our BBBjk^^kV                      sector, and then to decide our future course in fullerknowledge ofthe facts. k^k^kaIt would, however- k^k^Vk^^kV             (c) entail the certainty of further clashes with Argentina and Chile on the &quot;ABBJki^H id) require increased naval forces and facilities; andk^^H (e) call for greatly increased expenditure of money and resources.12. Decreased activity would in practice involve:-(a) the abandonment of territory which (though, our legal position is weakerthan we admit) we claim to be British, and in which British pioneersk^^H have led the way.*   This would be disagreeable to public opinion inki^H this country (and possibly also in Australia and New Zealand) unlesski^H it could be done without loss of face, and it might whet South American^^fl I appetites for other British territory, in the Western hemisphere (Falklandki^H                      Islands, British Honduras, British Guiana); and ki^kiV(b) giving up unexplored territory whose potential value is unknown and might ^^^flconceivably be great..C$i the other hand, reduced activity would-(c) lessen the possibilities of friction and incidents by providing, at our expense, ^ki^Han outlet for expansion by Argentina and Chile; and k^ki^|(d) save money and resources, and reduce (or remove the need to increase) VffHthe naval commitment. ki^kiS13. In practical terms, a policy of increased activity would mean matching the ^k^^kaArgentine effort in the Islands and on the fringe of Grahamland by maintainingan equal or greater number of bases. Secondly, it would call for an air survey and |i^kiSB^H I      mapping of our whole sector, coupled with surface exploration of those areas k^^k^Soffering any possibility of mineral development.   In terms of resources, these l^k^kVk^^H         a^ivities would require-  j&apos;aj^f ^^^|(i) a large expansion of the staff of the F.I.D.S., which would scarcely be |^k^kVpossible unless substantial help in man-power were forthcoming from k^k^HVffB                      the Services; ^ki^Hk^kS              (ii) a corresponding increase in the United Kingdom contribution towards the ^k^H?fal W      3*m 4ost of the FIDS-;        &apos; .BBBj              , * Proposals have been canvassed (although the finance has not yet been found) for a projected |^Bj^BBBjBBBj            trans-Polar journey to link the United Kingdom and Australian sectors and do scientific work on the B^Bj^BBBj|BBB           ice-cap.                                                                                             .MSr-&apos;-V&apos;&apos;&apos; (-        j , BBBBj
(iii) the purchase of a second ship as well as replacement of the John Biscoe I^k^k (which is nearly worn out);  j|iM 9Mi ^mm\(iv) the payment.of a fee to an air charter company for the air survey;^k^k (v) provision&apos;of special naval and possibly air facilities bythe/Services, ^k^k^kw The additional expenditure, under items (i)-(iv) above would&apos; probably be about   mh ^-M^kM  500,000 a year. J &apos;  v&amp; 114. The success of a policy of reduced activ^y would depend upon our finding       J ^k^kmeans of;J^itujg our Antarctic commitments which were acceptable to publicand Parliamentary opinion here,and a^ the same time; had the effect of satisfying ^k^k^k^k the Argentine and Chilean Goverhmehts.   From the point of view of British ^k^kopinion it is important that we should if possible choose means which would enable ^k^kus to withdraw from parts of our sector in deference to the decision, freely sought,^k^k                 of a responsibly international&apos;body.15. The possibilities appear to be these:- ^k^k(d) Agreed reference by all thfee parties to the International Court of Justice. ^k^kmmm . have&apos; repeatedly urged this course, which is, however, wholly ^k^kunacceptable to the other two.^k^k (b) Unilateral application to the International Court couplecLwith a state- ^k^kment of the United Kingdom case.  This could not compel the other ^k^k^k^k                              parties to accept the Court&apos;s jurisdiction, but might make it more diffi-       I ^k^k. ; &amp;M1for them to refuse.   There is, however, no guarantee that ^k^kadjudication would result.(c) Reference to the Security Council with a view to securing a direction fp\ ^k^kall parties to have recourse to the Court. The procedural difficulties ofI this course are considerable, the results are uncertain and the risks of ^k^kI damage to our general interests in the United Nations are great. ^k^kW^kt (d) Reference to the International Court ex cequo et bono or the appointment^ ^k^k^k^k of an arbitrator/This might be acceptable to Argentina and Chile, ^k^kI and at the same time provide Her Majesty&apos;s Government with the IH appearance of an honourable settlement.  It would, however, involve II the consideration of non-legal factors (including especially geographical II &apos; proximity) which would certainly lessen the chances of a satisfactory ^k^km^mm J$fe*ti: outcome f T Her Majesty&apos;s Government, and might set a precedent ^k^k^kU ,   which would be embarrassing elsewhere. ^k^kH (e) Direct negotiation with the other parties.  According to the latest informa-       I IH tion, there is a Chance that both countries might be willing to negotiateH - a general settlement of the Antarctic dispute.   Such a settlement wouldI ; inyplye &apos;partition of the area and considerable concessions by Her ^k^k^k^k Majesty&apos;s Government. II 16.   Time Factor.-The next Antarctic season opens in October. ArgentinaI and Chile are now licking their wounds after the Deception Island incident and ^kUI we should be prepared for trouble in the autumn unless direct negotiations or inter- m^km^k^k national litigation or arbitration have been initiated meanwhile.  This means thf^ ^k^kW^km a decision on Her Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s future policy should not be delayed. ^k^k
APPENDIX- &apos;&quot;&apos;^^^^^r&apos;&apos;&apos;  &apos; ^|Report by the Chiefs of Staff DAte&gt; 7th&apos;May, 19S3 &apos;|o;^Hi V:Vfl t|f STRATEGIC REQUIREMENTS IN THE ANTARCTIC I ^Introduction1.  We have examined a letter from the Colonial Office in which they requesta reassessment of our strategic requirementstim the Falkland Island Dependencies.We do not consider that the Dependencies can be considered in isolation from theI       Falkland Islands themselves, and our.study accordingly cover&amp;a rather,wider areathan does the Colonial Office request.BJBJ 2.  The map at Annex A (circulated separately) shows the Falkland Islandsand the Dependencies.  That at AnnexBshows this^ area in relation to the restof the Antarctic and to neighbouring land masses.3. When this question was last studied we summarised the requirements as B^Bfollows - B^B(a) to maintain control of the Drake Passage and ;|he approaches -to ,the^^B m.&apos; Magellan Strait; vv.-&quot;,I (&amp;) to maintain an advanced naval base for ships operating on the east coastof South America;(c) to deny to an enemy the use-tofi harbours which would assist him to attackB^| our shipping;W) to maintain a meteorological organisation in the Falkland Islknds and theDependencies:(e) to retain mining rights in case of future discoveries&apos; and&apos; developments.^^B Reassessment of Strategic Importance BAPJH I Naval4. We cannot visualise war between the United Kingdom and any LatinBJBJ American country except Argentina. In the unlikely event of war between Britain BJBJand Argentina we consider that it would be impracticable to attempt to retain theFalkland Islands and Dependencies at the outset of hostilities unless adequateforces were deployed beforehand. Their strategic value need therefore be con-sidered only in the event of war with Russia. BJBJ5. Against this background there is still a requirement for a fuelling base in ^^BI     this part of the world, the existence of which would moreover enable us to maintainsome control of the Drake Passage and the approaches to the Magellan Strait. ^^flThere is also a requirement that we should be able to deny to the enemy the use of ^^flharbours in the Antarctic although we think it extremely unlikely that such use ^^Bwould ever be made. ^^B6. In order to deny to the enemy the use of harbours in the Dependencies it ^^Bis not necessary that they should be, and remain, occupied by us. By making use ^^B?     of air reconnaissance, denial of these harbours can be exercised more effectively ^^BB^H and more economically by naval forces, provided adequate naval forces are avail- B^Hable in the area. ^^B1. The Falkland Islands are a requirement, but we can see no necessity, from BBJthe naval point of view, for Britain to continue to remain in occupation of any of B^Hthe Antarctic Dependencies. ^^B?flfl ?HH^^B 8.  We cannot foresee any requirement for military or civil air facilities in the ^^BDependencies.  The Antarctic is not, like the Arctic, on the shortest great-circle B^|^^B route between highly populated land-masses, since the southern continents are far ^^Btoo remote from it.I Meteorological^^B I 9.  The meteorological facilities in the Falkland Islands and in the Dependen- ^^B^^B cies are maintained by the Colonial Office for purposes of climatological research BAVJ^^B and for the benefit of the local economy-agriculture, fishing and whaling. The
VaVJ resultant weather reports from the area are of value to ships operating in the Drak AV^VJ Passage and to the eastward, but are of little or no importance to the daily operafl^^fl tions of the Royal Air Force or of civil airlines.I 10.  The climatological research may prove of long-term importance to scienc A^ftYAjand for this purpose the retention of the bases in the Argentine Islands and in PorH^^HLockroy is of value.  From a purely military point of view, however, the provisioiHof meteorological facilities in the Dependencies is not important.Political and Economic Considerations11. No account has been taken of:-(a) The possibility of Mineral deposits. II                        (b) The whaling industry in South Georgia which we understand is wortlfl:&apos;|^^|about  3 million per annum to British interests. ?&apos;(c) Political and psychological repercussions to foregoing any of our claims tflpart or all of the Dependencies.Commonwealth Interest12. Though we do not consider that a British withdrawal from any part, oHall, of the Dependencies would affect the strategic value, if any, that AustraliHand New Zealand attach to their sectors of the Antarctic, we think that they shoul JB ?YflVJH be consulted before any decision is taken to forego any part of our claim.VAVJ Conclusion13. We conclude that: -(a) Our strategic needs in the area can be met by the retention of the FalklaniHIslands themselves, and that there are no military requirements in thHDependencies.(b) For climatological research purposes it would be of some value to us tBJJ?JBJ                w^ii retain the bases in the Argentine Islands and Port Lockroy.?????Mb ?* ???????
^Hiei   RIOTED COPY NO.^oCABINETThe two attached maps are the ^-^M^mm, - xes A and B referred to in mmmvfl 3) ?^H101 net Office, S.W. 1.
I it C&amp;bjfft II FALKLAND ISLANDS and DEPENDENCIES. 10 I75  70                                              65&quot;                                             60       West of Greenwich        55  50  ~~ ,&quot;&lt;, - il????1                                       .---,-j--j--1-i-j-r~---i-..._u-j...---1-r_:_g___ 45 4-0 ????1I r *wl ^   ir 1^          i tt---&quot;-1 I^       Usm&quot;&quot;&quot;            *|?^ * j^-^ lL_-&quot;q-5^--                                                          I                                          / / Scaleof Statute Miles H^lHHa ^^sC-#^^rXr^3-^T J^-&apos; l        - _- / / at 60  Latitude?h .......--     l3 2f       V^SCC^ f FALKLAATn     r --P----_ / ?&apos;EdgeofShelf&apos;l&lt;:e &quot;-----Xoastline based onair reconnaissanceHH &quot;^^l^   ^ I    ri ii*i*i i*frtii*ifai*riri*Bi i^iii i ?      I                   ^    ]       ^   ^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^ ^V^l&apos;*&apos;&apos;Hf ^ /J.*.I J\r^^  It&apos; /    f    7     c K\m&gt;n* ^^ ^^sbf/rff^   / / / /\ I? 6 &quot;^p| a f &lt;%&gt;,s *j     r^^V^    /      /      / \5, ?I I ^ .,          /^^M^4, /      /      / II I 1^-4 StFl^cfel.      /       /      / **%&amp;t** II i   1 r U a  w x^Mz s&amp;r&apos;-   /     /     /     7\   J^*Mf ?I ^^^^i^^ &apos; I   /      ^^^&gt;7 &apos; ^l 7 \^^^ ^ II _9 _90 _8S  80     1     75     g    70     3    65    4    60     5    55     6     50     7     45      8     40      0      35      10      30&quot;      11        25        18        20 _15^_ 10  5 ^| ^^^^^^t^^*u*^mg^i Provisional edition to illustrate Colonial Report ^1% *SZg$ ^^
^^^^^| Longttud  30* Wit from Greenwich  ^   ^ 20*        ^   ^  I 10* ^ |    fcfaridran IH* of Qwanwtyh ^  ^  ^  ^ IQ*   ,,,/,, 3 *,   &lt;  ft./  &apos;   H&quot;*?1*^*     fr**, Gf*&lt; &gt;&gt;* *f??????1          s                              ^^^^        \           \                       /           /         ^Ss/&apos;\ *&quot;nc*Edwand                 ^X      so* bbbbbI|X     - \&lt;^A^^NJ?\     \ _a_     /     /     /   ^N&lt;f         /\. ^|BBBBaral    I              ^X           f     geSksia^3      fc \    ^sSnos\^^&apos;^   V            ..            Z^^^tX            /                /         &gt;v           a     &apos;         / BBBBbIbbI!    g/^. o ^|BBBBmI              ^ \   /                   7^      y^irsouthNjrkney     \ ,--V  \        \                  /         /   *      /            /      jC      /                    \    .X&apos;^ ^^^HbbbbbI            ; \/J^FALKLAN.  ^ V\         islands       A   \  \    JUrfr^k^i^ /       ML       /   XXX         -&lt;        &gt;T bbbbIbbbH      * /C#&apos;slands yvX     \r  \ \\^a&amp;&lt;4/   / / X     * mm     I bbHBBBBaVJ                 &apos;   /c^vv X^          /     A X                X            V^V \      ) \ prince*         id   X-X^wX        A     X     /     \                 &lt;S^        \ BBBBflBaVJ                \^&apos;^^X / &apos;\X\ \ VnrHAUT i   /^^LjZr /   \ X&quot; *    \ Bb1/^^^^^^^^^                         \ &apos; bbbbIbbI   ^.........._________u  ^^^^y^c \                   ^s^^^v HbbbH ^r^-^   tSv s\ A    y^USTrmLIANi^5^^ ^ r^^^M bcu^gshausen    /    ^---^  A      X A rj^ii-^^^land LJb *si^ j  sea /  james w     jf      &apos;--^^^X^tX 1  &quot;SER   i\ ZH     fm----------ANTARCTIC    TT--^ ?bJHh lbbbbb!          &apos;  ^^^\        /^^^^/&apos;^/^                                                                    /^^&quot;^   /   : bbbbI |||^ V^^^&amp; Xx//\./   Kl/ / rS&apos; \ W Am^^^^^x^   ^^^x/ /~^:bbbbbI         &apos; \     /^^^ ^\ /////^ ^^///^^^/^^J *l    IP V^^^^^^^^^^wX\                       / bbbbIBBBBBfl                               &gt;.     j/^^                  /^&apos;^lSXv        /           /           T^atapotio - - Ciwi*   \           \           \  ?    ^^^^^s\ BBBBbBBbI           XX      /        /\ / DERfeNDKNCY\     W\       \        XN   . H^^^^^B ^^^^ ^^^^^^^ I ^~~~^\ &apos; ^^^^^^^w ft i. ^^^^ &quot;bbI     f,w^r,? ., t, , , t . , .X^^M.Le,^^     j| ^n^JTi^^y\AN sea JX&gt;   x^^ bbIBBBBBJI                                 Longitude 150* West Frara Greenwich    160*                            170*                           180&apos;                           170*                            160*                   Longttuda 150* But from Greenwich          ? BJJBJJBBV                        I     THE ANTARCTIC HGENERAL MAP SHOWING TERRITORIAL CLAIMS, 1946^--- KEY TO SYMBOLS USED^^Km C=l AREAS CLAIMED TO HAVE BEEN SEEN BY EXPLORERSbritish territory _______ argentine claims 0-0-c^^^|b norwegian territory- norwegian claims 00_00french territory -!_ chilean claims^^^^^Vl                                                                           SHELF ICE .*w&quot;****&apos;*&apos; m ^                 (Northern limit undefined) ^^^H^^^M AZIMUTHAL EQUIDISTANT PROJECTION^^Hn Prepared by the Hydrographic Dep* of the Admiralty, 18^ April    1946. under the Superintendence of Rear-Admiral A. G. N. Wyatt, .Hydrographer.I                                                      I      RESTRICTED D.6479 H

</content>
</cab>
