<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/65/3 images: 34-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECREThOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT[CM(79) 3rddelusionsCOPY NOCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 18 JANUARY 1979at 10. 30 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon James Callaghan MPPrime MinisterIe Rt Hon Michael Foot MPrd President of the CouncilThe Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-JonesLord ChancellorHe Rt Hon Denis Healey MPancellor of the Exchequere Rt Hon David Owen MPBcretary of State for Foreign andBmmonwealth Affairsie Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn MPcretary of State for Energyie Rt Hon Peter Shore MP^cretary of State for the Environmentie Rt Hon Bruce Millan MPicretary of State for ScotlandRt Hon Fred Mulley MPicretary of State for DefenceIie P.t Hon David Ennals MPcretary of State for Social Servicesie Rt Hon Joel Barnett MP&quot;ief Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Merlyn Rees MPSecretary of State for the Home DepartmentThe Rt Hon Shirley Williams MPSecretary of State for Education andScience and Paymaster GeneralThe Rt Hon Eric Varley MPSecretary of State for IndustryThe Rt Hon Roy Mason MPSecretary of State fcr Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon John Morris QC MPSecretary of State for WalesThe Rt Hon Albert Booth MPSecretary of State for EmploymentThe Rt Hon Lord PeartLord Privy SealThe Rt Hon John Silkin MPMinister of Agriculture, Fisheriesand FoodSECRET
SECRETHon Roy Hattersley MP The Rt Hon William Rodgers MP[ry of State for Prices and Secretary of State for Transportier Protection .be Rt Hon Stanley Orme MP The Rt Hon John Smith MPinister for Social Security Secretary of State for TradeThe Rt Hon Harold Lever MPChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENThe if Hon Samuel Silkin QC MP The Rt Hon Michael Cocks MPttorney General   (Items 2 - 5) Parliamentary Secretary, TreasurySECRETARIATSir John HuntMr W I Mclndoe (Item 1)Mr M D M Franklin: (Item 2)Mr p Le Cheminant (Items 3-5)Mr P Mountfield (Items 4 and 5)Mr C A Whitmore (Item 2)Mr D E R Faulkner (Item 1)Mr R M Orton (Item 3)CONTENTSSubject Page1.1 PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSOfficial Information Bill 12.1    COMMUNITY AFFAIRSEurope?n Monetary System and the CommonAgricultural Policy 21fl   SPECIAL EMPLOYMENT MEASURES 3sjH PAYRoad Haulage 6Water 8Local Authorities 9Railways 10W   EUROPEAN ASSEMBLY ELECTIONS 11iiSECRET
CONFIDENTIALMENTARYfairs1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.ition BillTHE HOME SECRETARY said that the Ministerial Group onDisclosure of Official Information (GEN 29) had concluded that theGovernment should not oppose the Official Information Bill when itcame up for Second Reading on 19 January, despite the need for theGovernment to move a money resolution if it was to make progressbeyond Committee Stage.    The Committee Stage would however bedifficult,,    He had seen Mr. Clement Freud, the sponsor of the Bill,who had said that he would accept an explanation of the short-comings of the particular proposals in his Bill and would not beunduly concerned if it did not make progress in its present form.His main concern was to obtain from the Government an admissionthat they were in favour of a statutory right of access to officialdocuments.    As regards official secrets, Mr Freud had said thathe would be willing to accept Government amendments to bring theBill into line with their own proposals in the White Paper on theReform of Section 2 of the Official Secrets Act l9Ht  the problemfor the Government was that extensive amendments would be neededand it would be some time before they could be properly drafted.In discussion, it was pointed out that the important questions werewhat kind of information should be covered by new legislation, andwhat form of access should be given.    The Official Information Billgave the judiciary a wholly unacceptable position in determiningrights of access;  difficulty could already arise in the courts whenthey were unwilling to accept claims of Crown privilege for internaldocuments.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that thequestion of a statutory right of access was not one on which theGovernment could reach a decision in the present Parliament. TheGovernment should therefore seek to prolong discussion of the Bilb,On Second Reading it should be ma.de clear that the Government werein favour of improved access to a wider range of information, butthat they had not yet reached any view on the form of access(whether statutory or otherwise) or on the type of information to be vcovered,    The weaknesses of the individual clauses should beclearly brought out in Committee.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALUNITYRSWSzrv SystemE&apos; CommonturalBUSInce:43rdIisions,s 22. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthe French Government had created a difficult situation by insistingupon precise commitments for the phasing out of monetarycompensatory amounts (MCAs) before they would agree to the entryinto force of the European Monetary System (EMS)0    The questionhad not yet been discussed in the Council of Ministers because theFrench were pursuing bilateral discussions.    We had made it clearthat we could not be excluded from these negotiations merelybecause we would not be applying the exchange rate mechanismunder EMS.    The Commission were holding firm on their intentionto propose no increase in prices under the Common AgriculturalPolicy (CAP) but there was pressure to accept that these priceswould have to be increased in order to compensate for the effectof a reduction in MCAs on prices in Germany,    The MinisterialCommittee on European Questions had had a first discussion andagreed that we would have to consider our attitude to any arrange-ment about MCAs in relation to its effect on prices and hence onthe production of surpluses.    The Committee would be having afurther discussion on tnese issues and also whether or not thereshould be a devaluation of the Green Pound.    If so it wouldprobably be tactically sensible for us to move in uoncert with theFrench and the Italians who had already proposed devaluations intheir Green currencies.In discussion it was noted that the Italians would probably be willingto support us in insisting upon a freeze of CAP prices for productsin surplus provided we would agree with them that Governmentsshould be free to make changes in Green currencies when it suitedthem.    With the link now established over MCAs it could well beMarch before the EMS would be introduced.    In the meantime centralbankers were behaving as if the exchange rate mechanism wasalready in operation.The Cabinet -Took note.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALL 3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofOYMENT      State for Education and Science and Paymaster General (CP(79) 1)URES about a package of special employment measures for 1979-80,,,us THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE ANDjnce: PAYMASTER GENERAL said that the Ministerial Group on Unemploy-35fca ment among    Young People (GEN 27) had substantially agreed asions, package of measures proposed by the Secretary of State for Employmentwhich should reduce unemployment by over 300, 000 in March 1980 fromthe levels it would otherwise reach.    Without a programme for 1979-80on this scale, unemployment was expected to start rising again in thevery near future.    The details of the package was set out in the Annexto her memorandum,    GEN 27 had been unable to reach agreement oncertain aspects of two of the measures in the package, the Job ReleaseScheme (JRS) and the Small Firms Employment Subsidy (SFES). OnJRS, there had been a more or less equal division of view betweenthose who favoured setting the age of eligibility at 63 for men and59 for women, and those who preferred 62 for men and 59 for women,The second alternative had a substantially greater impact on theunemployment register, and was favoured by the Secretary of State forEmployment on those grounds.    There was also a difference of viewas to whether or not if JRS were to be payable for more than two years,which would be the case whichever of the options discussed above wereadopted, it should continue to be free of tax.    The Secretary of Statefor Employment was anxious that it should, to avoid reducing theoverall impact of the scheme.    Other Ministers had argued howeverthat to make a benefit payable for two years non-taxable would set anundesirable precedent with regard to social security benefits. OnSFES, the majority of the Group thought the subsidy should be furtherextended to cover non-manufacturing firms in Intermediate Areas aswellaa in other Assisted Areas and Inner City Partnership Areas. Itwas for consideration however whether such an extension was desirableon grounds of regional policy.    To extend SFES in this way would alsomean that the total cost of the package would exceed the overall limitof  230 million, which Cabinet had set for the package in October.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that his latestassessment of the unemployment prospects waa even more gloomythan that which he had given to GEN 27, and it now appeared that hemight have to announce an increase in the total number of unemployed,next week.    This would exclude any temporary layoffs arising fromthe current industrial situation.    Large redundancies were alsoexpected shortly in for example the shipbuilding and motor carindustries.    Apart from redundancies, the increase in the labour forcewould in itself cause a substantial rise in unemployment.    One of themost effective of the special employment measures, the TemporaryEmployment Subsidy, was now losing its usefulness and was beingphased out.    All these factors made it important that a substantialpackage of special employment measures for 1979-80 should beannounced urgently.    On JRSf, he strongly favoured setting the ages of3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALeligibility at 59 for women and 62 for men,    This would meet thepoints which had been raised by Department of Health and SocialSecurity Ministers about moves towards equalisation of retirementpension age, and would also ensure that the only measure in thepackage which acted on the supply of labour had the maximum effect.He was convinced that if the JRS allowance was made subject to tax,the whole scheme would effectively be wrecked.    To make the allowancetaxable would incur the hostility of the Trades Union Congress (TUC)and would mean that potential beneficiaries would not, as now, be ableto make a quick comparison of the benefits available to them under thescheme and their take home pay.    It seemed absurd to devote substantialstaff resources to taxing JRS allowance, when this would impair tatherthan enhance the effectiveness of the scheme.    On SFES, all thearguments from the point of view of reducing unemployment were clearlyin favour of extending it to non-manufacturing firms in IntermediateAreas.In discussion, it was argued that if the unemployment figures were infact about to start rising again, it was particularly important that theGovernment should be ready immediately with an improved package ofanti-unemployment measures.    Expenditure on the special employmentmeasures was more cost-effective in reducing unemployment thanexpenditure on other public expenditure programmes.    Even thoughcut-backs in public expenditure might eventually be necessary in thelight of the general economic situation, it would be wrong to start atthis stage making cuts in particular programmes without looking atpublic expenditure as a whole.    If it were nevertheless decided toreduce the overall size of the package, the proposed extension of SFEScould be postponed for the moment.    If however it were proposed toexpand JRS on the basis of any of the three options described inCP(79) 1, urgent decisions were needed in view of the fact that legislationwould be required.    To keep JRS on the same basis as it was at presentwould reduce the total effect of the scheme by about a third, and wouldcertainly result in a rise of unemployment.    It was moreoverparticularly important that the schemes run by the Manpower ServicesCommission, with which the TUC were directly concerned, should notbe cut back.On the other hand, it was argued that it would be very unwise to announceany additional public expenditure (even if largely already provided for)at this particular time.    To do so ccjild have an adverse effect onexternal confidence and the gilt-edged market, leading to higherinterest rates and increased unemployment.    Moreover if it becameclear that the rise in average earnings in the present pay round waslikely to be significantly in excess of the assumptions upon which currentpublic expenditure allocations were based, it was quite likely that cutsin public expenditure would be required.    To commit more publicexpenditure to special employment measures now would mean that anylater cuts would be correspondingly larger.    The effect of the specialemployment measures upon unemployment was in any case largely aCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALstatistical one;   real permanent extra jobs were not created.    In anycase it would be better to hold biLck any decision on this package forpossible use in any new discussions with the TUC on the economicsituation.    To make any announcement now about an expandedprogramme of special employment measures would mean that theGovernments position in any such discussions with ihe TUC would beweakened.    At the same time it was argued that it should not beassumed that public expenditure cuts were the only way of respondingto excessive growth of wages.    It was important that other possibleapproaches should not be overlooked.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that themajority view of the Cabinet was that no decision on the package ofspecial employment measures proposed in CP(79) 1 should be takenat present.    It might well be that the future of the special employmentmeasures would be amongst the subjects to be covered in thediscussions with the TUC on wages and the economic outlook generally,which he hoped could be arranged soon.    He would arrange for theCabinet to consider the special employment measures again at theappropriate time.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the summing up of theirdiscussion by the Prime Minister.5CONFIDENTIAL
SECRETsces:1stHions,3 and1(79) 2nd[elusions4. THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Cabinet should resume itsdiscussion of the current industrial situation in the light of recentdevelopments.    In recent meetings with trade onion leaders,including Mr Murray of the Trades Union Congress (TUC), he hadstressed the need for common ground between the Government and theunions, in order to prepare for the coming Election.    There was notmuch time left.    The whole question of the power of trade unions andthe role of the law in reepect of them would play a big part in thecampaign.    It was essential to persuade the unions to adopt a moreco-operative attitude in their own interests.mlage THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Ministers principally concernedhad met the previous evening to discuss a possible declaration of aState of Emergency.    They had agreed that this would not improve thesupply situation immediately, and might actually worsen it by impairingthe co-operation of the trade unions.    He had then discussed thesituation with Mr Len Murray and Mr Moss Evans.    They had agreedthe terms of a draft Code of Practice on picketing which would be putforward in Mr Evans&apos; name.    That draft was now being considered bythe Finance and General Purposes Committee of the union.    The Cabinethad not yet seen the text, but its main purpose was to make it clear thatsecondary picketing was not part of union policy.    Mr Evans had askedfor two or three more days in which to assess the effects of this newdevelopment before the Government decided to introduce a State ofEmergency.In discussion, it was reported that there had been considerableconfusion about the effect of the strike and of picketing.    New arrange-ments had therefore been made for the exchange of information betweenthe union and the Contingencies Unit in the Cabinet Office.    This wouldensure that both sides had an agreed appraisal of the facts, and thatproblems which could not be resolved by the Regional EmergencyCommittees at local level could be settled by the fenion at national levelvery quickly.    On the evidence available, the suppry situation wasdeteriorating slightly.    But it was still better than the level of supplywhich could be maintained with the use of troops alone.    Some picketingcontinued which should, under the terms of the instructions issued by theunion, have ceased.    But union co-operation over the supply of certainessential foodstuffs had improved.In further discussion of a State of Emergency, it was argued that adeclaration would be of very limited effect.    The Army only had about2, 000 trucks available, and could requisition a further 8, 000, but itwould take about 4 days before these could be fully deployed, becauseof the need to train drivers,    For comparison, there were about500, 000 vehicles in the road haulage industry in normal times. Itwould be difficult for the Army to maintain more than a tiny fraction ofthis very complicated distribution network.    The situation was differentfrom that of the recent oil tanker dispute, where distribution was in theSECRET
SECREThands of a few very large companies whose management co-operatedfreely in contingency planning.    The use of troops in the road haulagesituation would almost certainly involve the loss of union co-operation.The militants, like the general public, probably expected Army inter-vention to be very much more effective than it would be in practice.It should be noted that a State of Emergency would not be needed inorder to deploy troops to deal with the water emergency.Against this it was argued that the public impression was that thedistribution of foodstuffs was now entirely in the control of theTransport and General Workers Union (TGWU).    The Governmentshould be prepared to use troops, at least to relieve pressure pointsin those cases where the official union policy of co-operation wasbeing defied.    The psychological effect of doing nothing was verydamaging.    Since it would take 4 days to organise full deployment oftroops, by which time the situation might be desperate, a decision shouldnot be delayed until after the week-end.    If possible, troops should bemoved into position ahead of time before a declaration, so that theycould move into action immediately afterwards.In further discussion, it was suggested that a very high settlement wasinevitable before long.    How long should the Government let the strikecnntinue ?    Had the time come for the Government to let it be knownthat it was prepared ^o see the employers settle at a  65 a week basicrate - a 22 per cent increase in earnings?    The damage caused by acontinued strike might be greater than that which would be broughtabout by renewed inflation.    The Government should not accept theresponsibility of prolonging the present disastrous situation.Against this, it was argued that the Government could not indicate itswillingness to let the strike be settled on such terms and still maintainany pretence of a pay policy.    Fewer than 1 per cent of the companiesaffected had yet settled on the terms demanded by the union. Asettlement in line with the original claim would be very damaging,and would spread very rapidly.    Its impact on the local authority andother public sector negotiations could not be ignored.    It would bemuch better to seek a settlement, itself excessive, which involvedsome reduction in the original claim - say at  62 or  63 a week.The Government was bound to suffer some defeats in the defence of itspay policy, but it would be quite wrong to invite them needlessly. Onepossibility would be to invite the Chairman of the Advisory Concilationand Arbitration Service (ACAS) to see both parties about a resumptionof negotiations on the terms put forward by the Road HaulageAssociation.    But this could not be done until the threat of a pricelimitation order had been lifted.    In any case it was not clear that theTGWU could negotiate centrally or tsubmit the claim to arbitration,when in practice negotiations were conducted by a series of regionalcommittees which were not wholly within the control of the unionleadership,7SECRET
SECRETIn further discussion, it was argued that the time had come towithdraw the proposed Order to limit the prices charged by the roadhaulage industries.    It would only apply to the largest companies,amounting in total to about 10 per cent of the industry.    Its effectwould be to limit the increase in their profits to the going rate ofinflation between September 1977 and September 1978, about 7. 8 percent.    It was not directly related to the size of the likely pay settlement.It was in line with the abortive agreement with the TUC on pay and prices,and with the declared policy of the TGWU itself.    The possibility ofmaking an Order would lapse on Tuesday, 23 January.    But there wasthe serious risk that introduction of the Order would prejudice thechances of the settlement,,    It would be subject to negative resolutionprocedure in both Houses, and the Opposition could be expectedimmediately to press for an early debate.    The Government might wellbe defeated by a combination of its own backbenchers with theOpposition.     It was unlikely that the Order could be carried in theHouse of Lords.    The Government would incur the maximum odiumfor the introduction of the Order, with the minimum effect.    Yet toannounce the withdrawal oi the Order would amount to a hint to theemployers that the Government was prepared to let them settle.This in turn could react upon the local authority and water negotiations.It would be wrong therefore to let the Governments intentions bu knownuntil the last possible moment.    Equally it would be impossible to avoidmaking the Government^ intentions clear at Question Time on Monday,22 January, when the Secretary of State for Prices and ConsumerProtection was first Order,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that theMinisterial Committee on Economic Strategy, Sub-Committee on PayNegotiations (EY(P)) had agreed that he should authorise an offer of upto 11. 9 per cent in the water industry, made up of a combination of abasic pay increase, a productivity scheme, and certain bonus payments.This would not prove sufficient to reach a settlement.    He haddiscussed the situation with the Prime Minister and other Ministersconcerned the previous day, and they had agreed (subject to Cabinetapproval) that the Government could not stand the effects of a sustainedand widespread strike in the water and sewage industry.    They hadtherefore authorised him to seek a settlement on the best terms avail-able.    He had instructed the Chairman of the Water&quot; Council to do soduring the day, and had given him considerable negotiating flexibility.In discussion, it was suggested that the Cabinet had the choice of amajor breakdown in water supply, or accepting another settlement atover 20 per cent.    This would establish a norm for the round of atleast 16-20 per cent.    But the consequences of disruption in water and,more importantly, sewage services was not predictable or containable.The unions realised this and were behaving with a degree of moderationc,The new offer could just about be reconciled with pay policy, on the8SECRET
SECRETassumption that 100 per cf*nt of the benefits of the productivity dealwent to the workforce, thrt there was a 5 per cent increase in basicpay, and that comparability would be introduced from the followingyear.In further discussion, it was reported that 2, 000 people in the North-West Water Authority area were without normal water supplies anddependent on standpipes.    About 1 million were suffering from dis-coloured water supplies, and had been advised to boil all drinkingwater.    This was the result of unofficial action.    Restricted supplieshad been maintained with the co-operation of management,, Troopswere available to move in immediately they were required, to helpwith the erection of standpipes and the delivery of water from tankers.But their use had been postponed until the present round of paynegotiations were concluded.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said thatthere had been a further major development in the course of theprevious day.    The employers&apos; side now thought that they could reachan agreement with the unions for a new pay offer to tan- manualworkers at about 8.8 per centj although their initial offer would besomewhat lower.    This took full account of the underpinning arrange-ments announced by the Prime Minister in the debate on 16 January,,but in addition allowed for the carry-through of this increase to bonusand overtime rates.    It was linked to an offer of comparability studieswhich would be implemented in 1980 and 1981.    It would be a majorsuccess to achieve a settlement well into single figures, particularlyif this could be done before the proposed &quot;day of action&quot; on 22 January.It would require an appropriate adjustment both to the Rate Support Grantand to Cash Limits, of about  20 million in 1978-79 and about 50 million in 1979-80.    This assumed that the Government wouldfinance 61 per cent (the Rate Support Grant percentage for the year)of thj whole cost of the settlement including the carry-through of theunderpinning arrangements into bonus and overtime payments. Thelocal authority share of the additinnal costs would mean about0. 5 per cent increase in the rates.In discussion,  strong support was expressed for a settlement on theselines, although it was recognised that it involved a further modificationof the underpinning arrangements approved by the Cabinet earlier in theweek.    It was noted that a similar offer would have to be made toNational Health Service ancillaries.    It was not thought that the some-what higher offer to the water industry would make it harder to reacha settlement with the local authority manual workers on these lines.9SECRET
SECRETTHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TRANSPORT said that there was nosign of improvement in the railway dispute which was essentially onebetween the Amalgamated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen(ASLEF) and the National Union of Railwaymen(NUR).    The best hopeof an eventual solution lay in the intervention of Mr Len Murray, whohe had asked to talk to the various parties.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that there should be no declaration of a State ofEmergency that day.    He would arrange for the Ministers concernedto review the situation next day in the light of progress on the proposedCode of Practice on secondary picketing.    If there had been noimprovement in the situation by then, Ministers could then authorisean immediate declaration.    He would make this position clear in hisstatement to the House of Commons later that day.   The Cabinet alsoagreed not to introduce an Order to restrict the profits of the roadhaulage Industry.    The Secretary,of State for Prices and ConsumerProtection should announce this decision in answer to Questions in theHouse the following Monday (22 January).    No advance indication of thedecision should be giveiio    He would himself make a statement in theHouse about the outcome of his discussions with Mr Len Murray andMr Moss Evans.    The Home Secretary should follow Jiis with astatement about the industrial situation generally, and about theemergency arrangements made by the Government.    Both statementsshould be repeated in the normal way in the House of Lords. TheCabinet approved the terms of the revised pay offer to manual workersin the water industry.    Whether or not this offer produced an earlysettlement, Cabinet authorised the use of troops to maintain essentialwater supplies in the North-West if the present unofficial industrialaction there continued.    The Home Secretary should make thisintention clear in his statement.    The Cabinet also approved the termsof the revie:ed offer to the local authority manual workers proposed bythe Secretary of State for the Environment,   They agreed that the ratesupport grant and cash limits for 1978-79 and 1979-80 should beincreased to take account both of the increased costs attributable to&quot;underpinning&quot; and to the increased costs attributable to the otherelements in the proposed offer.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the summing up oftheir discussion by the Prime Minister, and invitedthe Ministers concerned to be guided accordingly.10SECRET
CONFIDENTIAL5. THE PRIME MINISTER,  summing up a very brief discussion,said that insufficient time remained to discuss the proposal containedin CP(78) 130 for State Funding of the European Assembly Elections.The Cabinet agreed however, without prejudice to this, that theHome Secretary should lay the regulations for the conduct of theEuropean Assembly Elections on the basis proposed by him in CP(78)129cThe Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.Cabinet Office18 January 197911CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
