<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/37/42 images: 382-387</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet:   June 1943.SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (43) 242.Ihth June, 1943.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY/It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.BURMA.CIVIL ADMINISTRATION IN BURMA IMMEDIATELY AFTERPREOCCUPATION.Joint Memorandum by Secretary of State for Burma and Secretary ofState for War.THE method of civil administration in Burma during its re-conquest andreoccupation has been the subject of discussion between our two Offices, theGovernor of Burma and the Commander-in-Chief, India. The War Cabinet may wish to be informed of the main lines of the agreement which has been reached between all the parties concerned. The arrangements agreed upon are in accord with the general scheme for the administration of liberated territories described in the memorandum by the Lord President of the 1st June (W.P. (43) 226) so faras that scheme affects British territories recovered from the enemy.2. While military requirements must be paramount until Burma ceases tobe either a scene of active operations against the enemy or a base from whichoperations are taking place, it is accepted that civil administration should bere-established as soon as, and in so far as, conditions are such as to enable it to function. It is clearly impossible to attempt to forecast at this stage when andin. what part or parts of Burma such a transfer of authority will be possible. Wecan only be guided by events. A decision on this point will be primarily one forthe General Officer Commanding in Burma, subject to any overriding decision bythe Commander-in-Chief, India (or whatever other authority is in general controlof operations), or by His Majesty&apos;s Government.3. Until conditions are such that transfer from military to&apos;civil administra-tion can be effected, the General Officer Commanding in Burma must be vestedwith full powers of administration, including judicial and. legislative powers.During this operational phase, the Governor will not return to Burma. civil administration will be carried out under the instructions of a Chief Civil AffairsOfficer, who will be solely responsible to the General Officer Commanding, and willhave a staff of Civil Affairs Officers under him. These Civil Affairs Officers,seconded from the various Services and Departments of the Government of Burma,will be commissioned with appropriate ranks in the armed forces and will con-stitute an integral part of the force operating in Burma. They would advise onall matters affecting the civil population, and may be placed in charge of civil affairs in specific areas or attached to moving formations.4. When the operational phase has been concluded either in respect of burma as a whole or of a given area, normal civil administration would be resumed in the area in question, and the Governor would return to Burma.Resumption would be effected with the minimum disturbance, since Civil AffairsOfficers placed in charge of specific areas would merely transfer their allegiance[25570]
from the General Officer Commanding to the Governor, while remaining at theirposts as civilians. The Governor would then have sole responsibility for adminis-tration in that area, though even after the Governors responsibility was extendedto the greater part or the whole of Burma, military administration might berequired in certain areas to safeguard lines of communication.5. Consideration has also been given to the formal and legal aspect of theproposed arrangement. So long as land operations in Burma are on a limited scale, it has been mutually agreed that there should be no public pronouncement,and that de jure executive and legislative authority should rest with the Governor,and de facto executive authority in the parts of Burma under our control with theCommander-in-Chief. But it is contemplated that, when the appropriate time comes, the General Officer Commanding will on his own authority under martial law assume full powers by a proclamation. The text of this proclamation(No 1) is appended to this note. It would be followed by other proclamationssetting up military courts and providing for their procedure. Such courts wouldin practice be conducted by the Civil Affairs Officers. The proclamation will not,of course, confer legal authority upon the General Officer Commanding to doacts for which he would otherwise have no authority, and Acts of Indemnity willbe necessary, as and when military jurisdiction is withdrawn, to legalise actsdone by or with the authority of the General Officer Commanding under the proclamation and orders deriving therefrom.*6. Under the arrangements described above all the Civil Affairs officers would, of course, be British. If troops of Allied nationality, such as Americanor Chinese, - were employed in the operations, it is contemplated that british civil Affairs Officers would be attached to them and administer the areasrecovered by their operations, and be responsible to the Chief Civil AffairsOfficer attached to the General Officer Commanding, possibly through deputy chief Civil Affairs Officers at American or Chinese headquarters. Such anarrangement would obviously be desirable both to safeguard bur political interestsin the British areas recovered from the enemy and in order that our Allies mighthave the advantage of the assistance of Civil Affairs Officers who knew thecountry, the language and the people. It is not anticipated that there wouldbe any difficulty in securing these essential requirements.7. Detailed arrangements for the administration of civil affairs in Burmawould be made in India in accordance with plans described above. These wouldfit quite naturally into any proposals for a Combined Civil Affairs Committeein London which may be adopted on the understanding that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment must retain the right of final decision on civil affairs matters inBritish territories.P. J. G.Burma Office,        - L. S. A.Ibth June, 1943.
Draft Proclamation by G.O.C., Burma.British Military Administration, Burma.   Proclamation No. 1.WHEREAS British and Allied Armed Forces are operating in Burma forthe purpose of evicting the enemy therefrom, of freeing British subjects of the-Crown from enemy domination, of rehabilitating Burma and of restoring thenormal life of its inhabitants;And whereas there has thus arisen a state of affairs necessitating military administration for the time being :Now I (name), General Officer Commanding the British Forces in Burma,hereby proclaim as follows : 1. Jurisdiction. Military administration is hereby established in Burmafor as long as military necessity shall demand.   I have therefore assumed for.myself, and for any successor of mine, full judicial, legislative, administrative and executive responsibility in regard to all territories of Burma occupied from timeto time by the British or Allied Forces in Burma and exclusive jurisdiction overall persons and properties therein.2. Public Order. I will take all steps which I may deem necessary andexpedient for the purpose of establishing and maintaining public order and safety in the said territories, and in so doing I will, as far as military exigenciespermit, respect all laws, customs, rights and properties in the said territories and act in accordance with the laws for the time being in force in Burma. Allrequisitioning of services or of property (other than munitions of war) which. may be necessitated by military exigency will be subject to reasonable compen-sation.3. Courts. All criminal jurisdiction in any part of Burma occupied fromtime to time by the British or Allied Forces, including jurisdiction in respect of matters dealt with in the Penal Code or other penal provisions of the law of burma as well as any penal provision contained.in any Proclamation or Adminis-trative Order published under the authority of myself or any successor of mine,shall vest exclusively in the military courts established by the military administration. No other courts having criminal jurisdiction under the law of burma in any such part shall exercise such jurisdiction so long as thejurisdiction of the military courts hereby established shall continue to operatetherein.All civil proceedings of any description already instituted in any court inany part of Burma occupied from time to time by the British or Allied forces are hereby suspended; and no such proceedings shall be continued, and no civil proceedings of any description shall be instituted in any such court except withthe specific authority, general or particular, of myself or a successor of mine.4. Military Administration and Military Courts. Administrative Ordersissued by myself or a successor of mine, and operative in Burma or some part orparts thereof, will make such provision as may be deemed necessary in relationto the military administration, the conduct of the inhabitants of the territories concerned, and the application therein of the penal law of Burma. They willalso provide for the establishment of the military courts mentioned in para-graph 3 of this Proclamation and for the procedure to be followed therein.&quot;5. Civil Officials. All lawfully established local administrative authorities^ are hereby authorised and required to continue to exercise and discharge theiradministrative duties, powers and functions, subject to such conditions or limita-tions as may be prescribed under the Authority of myself or any successor of mine.6. Restoration of peaceful conditions. In order that their prosperity maybe quickly restored I hereby call upon the people of Burma to preserve order andtranquillity and to go about their normal avocations in good will and without fear.7. Promulgation. This and all subsequent Proclamations, or Administra-trve Orders of the Military Administration will, be displayed at Court Houses,Police Stations and Public Offices or promulgated by any other means commonlyemployed for similar purposes in those parts of Burma which are occupied fromtime to time by the British or Allied Forces operating in that country.




</content>
</cab>
