<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/79/0 images: 26-28</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of...........................TOP SECRET Copy No. AfeCP. (56) 76th January,  1956CABINETTHE ECONOMIC SITUATIONMemcranduir. by the Chancellor of the exchequer my predecessor gave repeated warnings about the dangers of thecontinued inflationary pressure in the economy.     The most recent of these is contained in his memorandum on Overseas Expenditure (C. P. (55) 184) inwhich he pointed out that unless we were able to keep our demands withinbounds, we would be faced with &quot;irreparable damage to our economy ....to sterling, and to the sterling area system, with all that this implies toour position as centre of the Commonwealth and as a leading worldPower&quot; (paragraph 16).2.      We are trying to do more than our resources allow.     The effect ofthis excessive demand shows itself in expanding imports and using at homegoods that we ought to be exporting.    This endangers the balance of payments and consequently the reserves.3.      We have been trying to deal with this situation mainly by monetarymeasures.    Bank Rate has been at 4vj per cent since 24th February,Through the whole of 1955 we have had high interest rates and maintainedcontinuous pressure on the supply of money.    Since July the volume of credit as measured by bank advances has been reduced by 6i per cent.These measures have been supported by the hire purchase restrictions imposed in February and strengthened in July.    Other important measures designed to relieve the situation were the reduction of the housing subsidies,the autumn budget, and the supplementary measures dealing with thecapital expenditure and finance of the local authorities and the capitalexpenditure of the nationalised industries.4,      I must warn my colleagues that the latest indications of the state ofthe economy, as shown by the November and December trade figures, donot show any signs that the pressure is being relieved.    I am concerned for the moment to give the facts;   I shall circulate later my proposals asto remedies.5.      At home, the preliminary figures of unemployment for Decembershow that unemployment in mid-December was about 216, 000.     This is40, 000 below the figure for December, 1954 and is by far the lowestDecember figure since the end of the war.    The Board of Trade hasrecently asked a sample of business firms about their investment plans for 1956, and these, combined with the figures for investment projectedby the Government, local authorities and nationalised industries indicatethat total planned investment for the coming year is about  250 millionsmore than last year (at 1955 prices).
ix6.      Consumers&apos; expenditure is estimated to have increased by nearly 400 millions between 1954 and 1955, and having regard to the currentincreases in wages, we must be prepared for a rise this year of the orderof  300 millions (at 1955 prices).    We cannot hope for an increase in production this year, in the most favourable circumstances, of more than about  500 millions.   These figures, though very rough at this stage,indicate that home demand is likely to do more than absorb this year&apos;sincx-ease in output, which can -nly be done by a further increase in imports and a further diversion of goods from export.7.     It is probable that in 1955 we shall have had a deficit on currentoverall external account, instead of the  250/300 millions surplus whichwe need.     On the above analysis, the position in 1956 will be worse thanin the current year.G.      Preliminary indications of the December trade returns suggestthat the visible deficit will be at best about  75 millions and that it mayeasily reach  100 millions.     These figures compare with about 50 millions for September and October, and about  70 millions for November.     These figures support the view that our position is rettingwo r s e.9.      The gold and dollar reserves at the end of December stood at$2, 120 millions.     They are therefore approaching the critical level,which is between 02, 000 and 01, 500 millions, at which experience showsthat speculation against sterling can be expected.    When this happensthe reserves themselves are in danger of falling so low that confidence in our ability to maintain the value of sterling will be lost.10.    It is clear, therefore, that we are faced with the necessity of taking immediate action over a wide field of a more drastic characterthan has hitherto seemed necessary.     Time is running out.H.M.Treasury Chambers, 5.W.I.5th January, 1956.
6.      Consumers&apos; expenditure is estimated to have increased by nearly 400 millions between 1954 and 1955, and ha.ving regard to the currentincreases in wages, we must be prepared for a rise this year of the orderof  300 millions (at 1955 prices).    We cannot hope for an increase in production this year, in the most favourable circumstances, of more than about  500 millions.   These figures, though very rough at this stage,indicate that home demand is likely to do more than absorb this year&apos;sincrease in output, which can only be done by a further increase in imports and a further diversion of goods from export.7.      It is probable that in 1955 we shall have had a deficit on currentoverall external account, instead of the  Z50/300 millions surplus whichwe need.     On the above analysis, the position in 1956 will be worse thanin the current year.0.      Preliminary indications of the December trade returns suggestthat the visible deficit will be at best about  75 millions and that it mayeasily reach  100 millions.     These figures compare with about 53 millions for September and October, and about  70 millions for November.     These figures support the view that our position is gettingworse.9.      The gold and dollar reserves at the end of December stood at$2, 120 millions.     They are therefore approaching the critical level,which is between 2*2, 000 and $l, 500 millions, at which experience showsthat speculation against sterling can be expected.    When this happensthe reserves themselves are in danger of falling so low that confidence in our ability to maintain the value of sterling will be lost.10.    It is clear, therefore,  that we are faced with the necessity of taking immediate action over a wide field of a more drastic characterthan has hitherto seemed necessary.     Time is running out.H.M.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.5th January, 1956.-2-

</content>
</cab>
