<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/79/0 images: 67-80</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of...........................TOP secret copy No..G...F.Q (56) .1.7  .21st Januarya 1956CABINETTHE ECONOMIC situation memorandum, &quot;by the Chancellor of the exchequer,      In my previous memorandum (CP.  (56) 7) I gave the reasons which led me to think that the Inflationary pressure in the economic system was seriously endangering our position.     So long as inflationcontinues our reserves will he further run down and internal wagesand prices will continue to he forced up.     We must now decide onthe measures we must take to remedy this state of affairs,2*     Public opinion is not only ready for resolute action hut expectsit,,      If we fail now, we shall he discredited as a Government,      Ifwe succeed, it will make all the other things we hope to do duringour present term of office very much easier,3a     What is needed is to take a substantial &quot;block from the load now-pressing on our resources,     I &quot;believe that the measures we havealready taken have &quot;begun to reduce the overload and will &quot;becomeprogressively more effective once it is &quot;believed that we are&apos;serious.This will give us a tide in our favour instead of against usf as itIs now.      But we cannot afford to wait.     Nor need we fear that weshall overdo It,     The methods of reversing a deflation which has gone too far are well known and &quot;because they involve spending or taxconcessions are likely to he only too easy from a political point ofview,k-9     Our measures must satisfy three requirements(a)    They must show that we intend to he firm,(h)    They must take effect quickly.      Steps which will onlyaffect activity in a year&apos;s time are useless in thepresent situation,(c)    The Government must he seen to he making an adequatecontribution in the field over which it has direct or indirect control,5$     I start hy setting out very hriefly the various measures whichI think we should take,     I would hope that decisions could he taken on all these measures in the very near future and that as many aspossible of them could he announced together at an early date.     for reasons which will he evident, not all of them could he so announcedoI deal with the timing of the announcements in the final paragraphof this paper.Credit Policy60     I attach the utmost importance to the continuance of themeasures under this head instituted hy my predecessor.      Indeed, itis necessary that these measures should now he intensified,      I willnot. enlarge further on this subject   here;.    I may have something more to say to my colleagues orally,      I also want to mention theeffect on the credit squeeze of the Government * s &quot;borrowingI,MONETARY AND FINANCIAL MEASURES1/programme,
si Oprogramme, particularly that for the nationalised industries.      (Mysuggestions for reducing the investment programmes of these industries are in paragraphs 15-22).     But the point with which I amimmediately concerned is that the heavy &quot;borrowing programme of these industries - estimated at ahout  275 m. in 1956 - makes it much moredifficult to intensify the credit squeeze and tends to destroy any&quot;belief that the Government will succeed in curbing inflation.      I am therefore convinced that we must find some means of easing thisproDlem.     I am having the whole problem examined urgently and I hope to put specific proposals to my colleagues at a later stage.Hire Purchase7o     The present restrictions have helped to check demand,      Butthey can do more.     I am asking the President of the Board of Tradeto consider additional measures.     First, to take the power tocontrol hire*     Secondly,, to increase the minimum down-paymentsrequired for consumer goods.      I suggest that for motor-cars,radios and television sets the minimum deposit should be raised fromthe present 33i to 50/Sj    for furniture, &quot;bicycles and cookers the deposit should go up from 15% to 20$;o.      Thirdly, to extend thecontrol which is now confined to consumer goods to a representativerange of capital goods.     As a starting point, I suggest that the range should at least include the capital goods which are subjectto hire purchase restrictions up to July 195U - that is motorcoaches, goods vehicles and office furniture and machinery.      But Itnink it is important that hire purchase control should be used toexercise a general check on investment demand just as it does now on consumer demand.     I am therefore asking the President to prepare a comprehensive list, but to discuss the contents with the treasury and other Ministers concerned &quot;before action is taken.Savings8.     What the National Savings Movement really needs is an assurance that inflation will be checked so that money saved deesnot lose its value.      Improved securities and inducements cannottake the place of this assurance.     But I think it is right tosee whether any improvements can be made.      In particular I have in mind the scope for tax inducements and the need to provide themovement with something new to sell to the public.     I am consideringvarious suggestions under this head.9.      One of these is that the Movement might offer to the public apremium bond - not a lottery in which the investor1  loses his stakebut a scheme in which the money saved remains, intact;   but insteadof earning interest, the equivalent of the interest is distributed in money prizes drawn by,lot.     It is not worth spending time and staff on organising such a security unless the National SavingsMovement is prepared to welcome it and make it a success.      I proposeto discuss it with Lerd Mackintosh and go ahead if we can draw upa practical scheme which the Movement will adopt wholeheartedly,but not otherwise.II.      INVESTMENT10.    Much of our troubles are due to the investment boom.     Thoughthe objects of this investment may he admirable, we must go moreslowly in both the public and the private sectors.11.    In the public sector the nationalised industries are planning to do 16% more investment in 1956-57 than in 1955-56, centralgovernment 17;/o more and local authorities 6% more..     Only in housings-taking public and private house -&quot;building together, is any reduction/foreseen,
oforeseen, and that of far too small an amount to offset these massiveincreases.     Our first duty must he to reduce the load which thosesectors of the economy which are directly or indirectly under our control place on our resources,12.   We cannot make any impression on the problem if we regard anypart of these expenditures as sacrosanct, nor if we regard ourselvesas precluded from stretching out programmes which have already received our approval, collectively or individually.     Obviously, itwould he stupid to delay works which have already started..     They .should he pushed aheado     But if we can agree to defer work whichhas not yet started, we can &quot;bring the load which investment isplacing  on  our resources within manageable proportions.13a   The adjustments necessary to do this must, of course, he seen to conform to carefully considered plans.     Postponements must haveregard to the priorities appropriate in each case and the programmesmust he properly rephased.      This is particularly necessary on theBritish Transport Commipsion&apos;s programme which is referred to inparagraphs 15 and 16 and which seems to me to require quite radicalreconsideration.114*    1 ask my colleagues to accept these broad principles.NATIONALISED industries british Transport Commission15*    The investment of the railways is planned to increase from 6k million in 1955 to  9h million in 1956.     I know that therailways have been held back, and that they have been encouraged to.go ahead with a modernisation plan.      But this is more than can be managed - probably far more than they will be able to do,      Ipropose that at least  20 million of this work be deferred until next year.16.    The investment of the 3,T.C. in other fields is planned toincrease by  17 million - a 100% increase.     Most of this is for replacement of the British Road Services fleet.     I propose that atleast  10 million of this be deferred.National Coal Board17.   This investment is planned to increase from nearly  100 million in 1955 by a further  7 million,     We have never previously sought toreduce the N.C.B.    investment, but this year I think we should askfor some contribution,     I propose that  7 million of this investment should be considered for deferment, if practicable.Central Bile ctricity Authority180    Investment in distribution is planned for  72 million, almost the same figure as last year. ^ This, thanks to the efforts of theprevious Minister of Fuel and Power and the co-jperation of theC.E.A,, is already lower than the Authority had hoped far nextyear - and it implies &quot;a substantial slowing down of the ruralelectrification programme&quot; which we clearly must accept.     But I am afraid that we must ask for more,      I suggest that a further 5 million - about 7%/o - be deferred.19,    In addition, well over  100 million is planned for generating stations.     Most of this is for stations now being built and forplant already being made,   &apos; But some part will almost certainly befor stations to be started, and for contracts for plant to be placedwithin the year.      I cannot quantify the saving that can be made,but I do suggest that these projects be deferred.3/South of
South of.....Scotland Electricity Board20*    Their investment is said to he planned to increase from separately of ahout  15 million in 1955 to nearly  194&quot; million in 1956,The Board has only recently acquired an independent existence andit may he that estimating difficulties have still to he overcome:in any event, I cannot helieve that such an increase is practicahle0I suggest that in the fields hoth of distribution and generationreductions should he made parallel to those we are asking from theCentral Electricity Authority,Gas Council21*    The investment planned for 1956-5?&apos; is  56 million, nearly  5 million less than 1955-56,     I am very grateful for this reduction,which represents, I know, a very real effort.     But, none the less?I suggest a further deferment of  1  to  1-g- million, ahout 2-g$,The Air. Corporations22*    B,0.A,C. plans to spend over  16 million more this year, agreat part in dollars to huy D.C.7 aircraft on an insurance,B.E.A. plans to spend  i+i million more this year,      I make no positive suggestions, hut I do ask that the Minister examine most carefully with the Corporations whether some part of this largerinvestment cannot he deferred,CENTRAL GOVERNMENT23,    It is at present proposed that the total capital expenditure to he horne on Votes in 1956-57 should he ahout  21+0 million,nearly  1+0 million more than in 1955-56.     However essential all this expenditure may he, we cannot defend at this time so greatan increase,      I ask that all my colleagues look again to see whether some part of these programmes cannot he deferred.     Inparticular, I have the following proposals./Hospital Programmes
Hospital Programmes (Great Britain)2k.      15,7 million is to be spent in 1956-7 (inclusive ofScotland).      i;Ye are committed to programmes which will raiseexpenditure to  21 million in 1957/8.     We have twicereiterated that these programmes will not be cut.     Neverthe-less, I must ask for a reduction to  lh million in 1956/7*      i must also ask that commitments should not be made which willcompel us to carry the programme above  15 million in 1957/8-Atomic Energy25*     This is expected to rise from over  28 million this yearto nearly  hO million next year, though shortage of staffmay again prevent the Authority doing as much as it wouldlike.      I do not wish to hold back this vital accivity butsuggest that like everyone else, by trying to do a little lessin one year, they may help everyone, including themselves,to do a little more over a rather longer period.Post Office28o     A very lai&apos;ge increase, -from nearly  91 million to nearly 99 million,  is proposed.      In the altered circumstances,  I donot see how we can now justify an increase.      The Post Office,like other parts of the economy, must take account of thenational situation, and I must ask that their programme shouldbe kept at  91 m.Development Areas27*     Wo are spending about  6 million a year on buildingfactories and extending existing factories in the development areas - this at a time when our trouble is too much employment,not too little.     We cannot stop work already in hand, but i suggest that we ought to impone a 6-month standstill on new commitments.Government Building28.      In addition to the services mentioned above, otherincreases in Government building are proposed.     For example,expenditure on Food and Petroleum stores is to increase by nearly  3 millions, an increase of over 60%.      In view of the load on the building industry, I should like to see us spendingless on all Government building in 1956/57? but if this isimpossible we ought at least not to spend more.      I am asking the Minister of Works to look carefully at every project inconjunction with the Treasury with a view to possiblepostponement.Home Defence29*      It was recently decided to provide  55 millions for home Defence expenditure in 1956/57*      Of this total, 28 millions was for the development of various branches of theHome Defence organisation and the balance was for the stock-piling of food, and other items, including the consequentialstorages,    In view of our pressing current problems, I must ask for this decision to be reconsidered.    I accept the needfor recruiting and training the civil defence and allied services, for maintenance costs relating to the existingstockpile and for finishing works that are well on the way to completion.    But in present circumstances I see no positivemerit - and indeed I see great disadvantage - in buying food,/oil
oil and medical supplies for the stockpile;    if we stopped this we would save  7*5 million.     We need not go ahead so fastwith works for the storage of oil, and I suggest a cut of 1.5 million.      It is proposed to spend far more next year than this on the purchase of fire fighting equipment, and i suggest a cut of  2.5 million (from a total of  I+.5 million).I would stop the building of protective works for headquartersto control rooms,  saving  0.2+5 million.     And I would cut 1.5 million off the public utility works.      I would also cut the Post Office constructional work from  9 millions to 5 millions.      By these or other reductions I would bring thetotal for home defence down to about  38 millions.      No one would really be much the worse for this and the national finances and balance of payments  (in respect of the buying offood and oil) would benefit considerably.LOCAL AUTHORITIESCapital expenditure other than Housing, Education and Roads30.     There is no Central Government control over most of thisexcept through the loan sanction.      Investment in 1955/56 isestimated to amount to  122 million of which the main elementsare: - in.Water 37.9Sewerage 33.8Miscellaneous Local Services 19.health Services 5.1Coast Protection and Drainage 8.0&quot;Miscellaneous&quot; is running at $0% more in 1955/6 thanl95U/5*      In the first two quarters only  2.8 of applications were rejected.31.      I must ask that no further loan sanctions for&quot;Miscellaneous&quot; Services be granted for a period of 6 months,except to enable projects in progress to be completed or withthe approval of the Treasury to meet really exceptional circumstances.     For Water and Sewerage the control should be operated to reduce the total value of starts to the 195^/5level.      In both cases the position can be reviewed after months.Housing32.     The effects of the changes in the subsidy policy and interest rates cannot yet be estimated.     My predecessor agreed with the Minister of Housing and Local Government that heshould work - so far as he is able to influence matters - toproduce a total of 120,000 subsidised houses and 270,000houses in all, the latter being a figure for Great Britain.The next step in housing must be the abolition of the general needs subsidy and a revision of the Rent Restriction Acts withthe raising of controlled rents.33*     Until this has been done, we cannot reduce the subsidies on existing as distinct from newly constructed houses.      Ishould have liked to take this next step this session but I realise that for various reasons this is impracticable.     But,this being so, I regard it as essential that a Bill to modify the Rent Restriction Acts should be prepared and given first/place
place in the Autumn Session.     This means that we must determine the policy of the measure in the very near future because the drafting of the measure will involve many difficult points.We shall not he ready in the autumn if the Bill is not suh-stantially complete before the recess.      I. would ask thatpreparatory work should be pressed on and that a ministerial committee should be constituted forthwith to deal with thismatter.Education3k.      In 195k/5  63 million of work was started.     Projectscosting  80 million have been authorised to start in 1955/6.Actual investment in 1955/6 is about  57*5 million.     The load on the economy is rising at about  5 million a year.     For1956/7 the proposed programme of starts is:- m.1.     Primarj/ and Secondary Schools 572.      Further Education 93.      Other Education Services(Training Colleges, special schools etc.) 3h.     Minor Capital Projects (uncontrolled)estimated at 11. 80   &apos;35,      In addition it is now proposed to increase the plannedexpenditure on technical education over the next five years from  k5 million to  71 mill3 on *      lijX0 expenditure under item kmay be underestimated.36.      In November, I95k the Cabinet approved the Minister ofEducation&apos;s proposals for rural reorganisation which were thenexpected to cost about  20 million spread over five years,and limited to  5 million in the first year.      No large scaleincrease in technical education building was then proposed. 12 million of rural reorganisation was started in 1955/6,and next year&apos;s programme includes  6 million.     There is still 22 million more to be started in three years.      The totalcost of this programme is twice as much as when the cabinet approved it.      This work is not essential to provide school places for the bulge or for movement of population.      In viewof the impending increase in the technical education programmeI must ask:-(a) That Local Education Authorities be instructed to defer until 1957/8 any rural reorganisation projectsalready authorised but not started.(b) That the rest of the rural reorganisation programmebe deferred until after the bulge has beenprovided for.(c) That the total programme of education building startsin 1956/7 be reduced from  80 million to  70 million.(d) The miscellaneous uncontrolled investment must notrise in 1956/7 above the estimate of  11 million./37-     If
37*      If these plans for the educational programmes are agreed,it may be necessary, in order to ensure that the new totallimits are observed, to withdraw the present arrangement bywhich Local Authorities are not subject to control for projectscosting less than  10,000.      I must ask the Minister toconsider this.38.     A comparable reduction should also he made in theprogramme of the Scottish Education Department.Roads39*     We are at present committed to a programme of expenditureon major works and new roads which will cost  16 millions in1956/57 and rise to a maximum of some  hO millions in 1959/60.I am not immediately concerned with the years after 1956/575which we can discuss later.     The Minister has, however,suggested an addition to the programme of some  6 millions,of which about  600,000 would be spent in 1956/57.      I cannot agree to such an addition.      It is difficult to see how roadscan be exempted from making some contribution to the solutionof the problem we now face.      I must therefore ask the Ministerto examine whether it is not possible for him somewhat to slow down his programme in 1956/57 so as to show a positivereduction of the expenditure previously agreed for 1956/57*PRIVATE INDUSTRY AND COMMERCEhO.      por the first time the President of the Board of trade has received from a large and representative sample of firmsa forecast of their intentions.     This forecast, which we musttreat with great caution until we have more experience of itsreliability, suggests that private industry is planning for atleast as large an increase in investment in 1956 as occurred in 1955*     Desirable though this is in itself, it is happeningtoo quickly.hi.     Since the abolition of building licensing in 195^, wehave no method of direct control over private investment.We have to rely on monetary and fiscal measures, on which, as stated in paragraph 6, I propose to say something to mycolleagues.h2.      The consequences of a continuance of this overexuherantinvestment boom are so serious that I have been considering whether we should not re-introduce some direct control ofbuilding.     The difficulties of doing this are admittedly great.It would require legislation of a most unattractive kind.It would be necessary to build up the staff of the Ministryof Works, and probably of the &quot;sponsoring&quot; Departments aswell - a move which would take some time.      The control whenintroduced would not be fully satisfactory in its operation for several months.     We should probably have to begin bya &quot;crash&quot; operation, prohibiting all new starts;    this wouldinevltahly create a number of embarrassing individualproblems.     But the situation is such that I feel I must presson with an examination of this and I am asking the Ministerof Works to work out the outline of a scheme./i+3 *     But
JU3-      But whether or not we can take some measure of direct control of private investment, a deferment of capitalexpenditure of the nationalised industries, centralgovernment and local authorities is vital.     Politically,if we institute building control, we should have to beable to demonstrate that the public sector was being createdcomparably.     If we decide not to institute building control, then the need to take adequate action in thepublic sector becomes the more imperative.III.      GOVERNMENT EXPENDITUREhlu    The rate of Government expenditure has a double impactupon the inflationary position.     In the first place, so far as concerns expenditure on capital account, it adds to the burdenof already over-loaded, industries, especially building andengineerings     In the second place, a reduction in government expenditure would diminish the Government&apos;s demands on ourlabour and other resources, and the purchasing power whichresults from Government disbursements:    and by making it. possiblefor the Government to borrow less would assist our credit policyeProm these points of view I may find it necessary to ask mycolleagues to effect further reductions of expenditure in thecourse of the year, within the Estimates as finally approved./DEPENCJE
defence+5. Defence is the heaviest of our necessary burdens and wemust make economies wherever we can. It is not too early to select our objectives.      I suggest the following:The Navy2+6.      I have no specific proposals to make at this stage onthe strength of the Navy or the character of its armaments.I would hope however that uhe drive for economy will not be relaxed, and in particular that the Navy (and the other services as well) will see that there is no unnecessaryaccumulation of stocks.The Army2+7.      The War Office have already said that a generous payaward (which they have been given) might make it possible forthem to manage with six regular divisions and five brigades,I should be grateful to know how this would be accomplished,by what date,  and what the full consequential savings would be.In the meantime I suggest that we should aim at reducing theArmy by one Division.      If possible, this should be done by reducing the number of Divisions in Germany by one.      In thisway we should save not merely the cost of the Division but alsothe burden on our balance of payments of maintaining a Divisionoverseas.      If this should not prove possible, we should seekour Allies&apos; agreement to regarding one of the Divisions inGermany as our strategic reserve.The R.A.F.2+8.    It seems likely that as the years go by the air defence ofthis country,  so far as it is practicable at all, will dependless and less on manned fighters and more and more on the use ofgiiided weapons.    I suggest that the Defence Committee should beasked to consider this matter with a view to recommending a date by which this new concept of air defence should become effective in the meantime we should aim at progressive reductions in theamounts spent on manned fighters,   starting with research anddevelopment into fighter aircraft.Defence Research and Development2+9.    Our expenditure on Defence Research and Development goesup and up.    I believe we may already have reached the point atwhich not only defence but the civil economy suffers through our effort to do too&apos;much.h.    I propose that, as a first step, an objective statement should be prepared of the impact on industryand on our scientific and technical resources of the Services1demands.    Here again effort must be made more selective./CIVIL
CIVIL EXPENDITUREBread Sup sidy50.    I propose that the bread subsidy should be abolished.    Itcosts  1+1 m. a year.    It involves a subsidy and price control -methods which have been almost entirely abandoned by this government as instruments of our economic policy.    The bakers,large and small, want to get rid of it.    The result weald be anincrease of 1-g- points on the retail price index.    It is equalto 2jjd. on the 1-f lb. loaf (which costs 7-g-d.) and the averageexpenditure on. bread per head per week would go up from 1s. 3d.to 1s.  8d.Milk51 .    I propose that the retail price of milk should be raisedby -g-d. per pint.    This would save  20 m. in a full year.    the retail price of milk has not been changed since August 1954,though costs of distribution have risen sharply.    To judge bypast experience,  consumption should not fall significantly.    TheAll Items Index would rise by 0,h3 points.Agricultural Review52.    The agricultural subsidies will cost about  210 m. thisyear.    There has been a big rise in costs and the farmers willpress hard for an increase.    We&apos;must resist this and strive&apos; fora positive reduction.   Moreover, whatever the total figures,we must try to distribute the subsidies in ways which will besthelp our economy.   For instance, we should give an incentive tothe fullest use of home-grown feedingstuffs by encouraging theproduction&apos; of animals which live on the land rather than on imports - that is,  cattle and sheep rather than pigs and hens.In order to achieve these objectives it may be necessary, and indeed salutary,  to impose a settlement.   We shall be consideringproposals about this at the end of January.Social Services53. The only practical ways of securing immediate economieslie in the investment field and have been dealt with earlier in this paper.5I4-.    There is also the question of school meals.    On this Iawait a report from the Minister of Education.55.    In the longer term I hope for some economies from theenquiry to be undertaken by the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s Committee ofMinisters.Administrative Expenses56.    The Civil Service has already been reduced by about50,000&apos; since the end of 1951.   But we must do&apos;more.    ThePrime Minister has promised a reduction of 10-15,000 over aperiod.    If, as I hope, we carry out the recommendation of thePriestley Commission as regards hours and overtime and therebyget rid of the present anomalous and expensive arrangements whereby a lot of regular overtime is worked, this may mean that departments may have to bring about a slightly larger reductionthan the 10,000-15,000 promised by the Prime Minister.    this reduction covers tho Service Departments as well as the civil departments./57.    The
57,    The reduction proposed cannot he brought about by a uniform percentage cut over all Departments.    If my colleagues agree,  I propose that the Treasury should in the first instancediscuss with Departments how the reduction can best be spread.I am sure that all my colleagues will help in this essentialmeasure.    But it is clear that we cannot bring about thereduction proposed simply by improved organisation, although this will make its contribution.   To some extent reductionwill involve the curtailment or even the abolition of certain minor services now carried out and the lowering of the standardof other services.   We can save a lot of staff by doingcertain things less elaborately.   A special scrutiny must alsobe applied to staff overseas.   Here there is a double saving to be secured.   Not only a saving to the Exchequer but areduction in the burden on the balance of payments.   The testwe must apply is whether the employment of officers overseas isessential, net whether it is simply d.desirable.    I hope we shall also make a concerted endeavour to reduce the size of the delegations which visit so many international conferences.58,   Equally I must ask my colleagues in the Service departments to make a contribution by reducing the number of service personnel employed in their Departments.IV.    IMPORTSGoal Supplies55.    I have asked the Minister of Fuel, and Power what can bedone to reduce the heavy burden placed upon our balance ofpayments this winter by imported coal.    The Minister tells mehe has already arranged to reduce the winter import programmefrom 6.5 million tons to 5.3 million&apos;tons,  a saving of1.2 million tons and over  8 million, and is consideringurgently whether more can be done.    This will be a big help, andI am grateful for the Minister&apos;s co-operation,60.    The Minister will shortly be circulating a paper on thegeneral fuel and power situation.    One point I would like to stress at this stage is the importance,  in our present difficulties,  of maintaining open-cast coal production.   Theagricultural pros and cons and the compensation problems willhave to be looked at urgently.Steel61.    The import of steel is also very expensive.    The presentcontrol of steel prices conceals the cost of imports andoperates as an incentive to the export of unfinished and semi-finished steel,  thus to some extent diverting supplies fromexports with much higher conversion, values.   Furthermore, wehave to remember that higher steel prices are bound&apos;to give the steel industry a stronger incentive to expand steel-making capacity;    and all the indications are that a substantialexpansion of capacity is going to be badly needed in the next decade.62.    I am, of course,  aware that dearer steel would affect thecost of our engineering exports.   But I am sure that thebalance of economic advantage lies on the side of ending this price control,  and I therefore propose that a study should bemade at once of what this step would involve./Import Controls&apos;
Import Controls63.    The increase in imports is one of our main difficulties.I am therefore considering whether some intensification of import controls would he helpful.   But I must warn mycolleagues that such action, even if decided upon, could notin any way he a substitute for the other measures I amproposing.6k,    The effectiveness of Increased import controls is necessarily limited hy such things as retaliation hy othercountries and possible loss of confidence in sterling.    Theymay also give rise to the need for internal controls such asallocation.   But I have already asked for this question to heexamined as a matter of urgency,  and I may shortly haveproposals to place before my colleagues.65,    If we hesitate to take the necessary steps over internalpolicies,  a situation may develop in which we may have to carry-out something in the nature of e &quot;crash&quot; plan of a mostdrastic character to limit imports.    There is no need to contemplate such, action now.   But I propose to have a planprepared to meet such a contingency.      I must, however, warnmy colleagues.es that even a rumour that the Government&apos;was considering such a plan might result in forestalling, with themost adverse consequences for our &quot;balance of payments.V.    CONCLUS ION66,    As I said in the opening paragraphs of this paper, Iwould 1 ike to announce as many as possible of the measures setout at the earliest possible moment.67.    I recognise that some of the measures proposed (forexample, certain of those in the defence field) need a gooddeal of shaping and working out before they can reach the stage of a public announcement.   Nevertheless, I attach greatimportance to acting at once,  and to acting over as wide afield as possible.    It is clear that in carrying out themeasures contained in this paper statements made by ministers in and out of Parliament,  and instructions to local authorities,will have to be reviewed and new instructions given.68.    As I see it, we cannot succeed unless we are resolute inour determination to do whatever is necessary to rid ourselvesof the inflation which, notwithstanding the appearances ofoutward prosperity,  is threatening the stability of our economic life.    I see no way of doing this unless the nation asa whole is led by the Government to accept the fact that we are trying,   as a nation,  to do far more than we can achieve,, thatthe totality of our resources, is overstrained,,69.    This is not a situation which can be dealt with by a cuthere and a cut there.    So far as possible all fields   ofnational activity must make a contribution.    Further the more readily this proposition is agreed to,  the less difficulty weshall have in carrying out our proposals.70.    These proposals form the first part of a programme, whichwill have to be judged as a whole in relation to the Budget.Critics may say that most attention will be drawn to measureswhich will increase the cost of living and fall most heavily onthe poorer sections of the community.    It is too early to see/what
what may he needed in the Budget,  though it will afford anopportunity to deal with the general balance of my programmeBut if our policy is successful,  it will produce a lessinflationary climate,  in which lies the best hope for stableprices.    It is not one or two points on the cost of livingwhich are at stake, but a halt to the continual increase inprices which has been almost uninterrupted since the end ofthe war.H. M.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.20th January. 1956.

</content>
</cab>
