<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/79/0 images: 101-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
OSECRETC.P.(56) 2327th January, 1956COPY NO.cCABINETARMS FOR INDIA AND PAKISTANNote by tne Chancellor of the exchequer the attached memorandum, which has been prepared by officials of the Departments immediately concerned,  sets out the detail, and discussesthe merits, of two proposals for assisting India and Pakistan to acquireBritish arms.2. The proposals in each case are strongly supported by the Common-wealth Secretary and in the Indian case by the Minister of Supply.3,      As the proposals, while important in themselves,  raise considera-tions of general policy, I have thought it right to bring them to the attentionof my colleagues for discussion in the Cabinet.H.M.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.27th January, 1956.ARMS FOR INDIA AND PAKISTANIntroduction1.      In recent months a considerable number of proposals for aid of onekind or another to foreign countries have been put forward.    For the mostpart these arise directly or indirectly from the more overtly active policy adopted by the Soviet bloc towards the Near and Middle East.    Two suchX^proposals are currently the subject of Ministerial correspondence:-(i)   The waiver by Her Majesty&apos;s Government of all or part of the research and development levy on 60Canberra aircraft which the English Electric company are negotiating to sell to India.     The total amount ofthe levy involved is some  600, 000.-1
(ii) A gift to Pakistan of iOO Bofors guns for which otherwise a charge of about  50, 000 would bemade,2.     Details of the Proposals(i) Canberras for India.     The negotiations - in which a Ministry ofSupply representative went out to India to participate - have been going on for some time.    Price is not the only outstanding point but it is saidto be a significant one.    Originally the English Electric Company quoteda price of  209,000 per aircraft.     This was unattractive to the indians in comparison with the price quoted by the Russians for the rival russian aircraft.     The Company was therefore persuaded by Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment to improve its offer, not by reducing the price, but byagreeing to instal some technical deviceSf, which the Indians wanted andwhich cost about  10,000 per aircraft, without increasing the price.These devices did not, however, include as. 21 Radar (which mightwell cost about  20, 000 per aircraft).     The Acting High Commissioner in new Delhi thinks it is important to include this equipment without anincrease of price if India is to be persuaded to buy the Canberras.    TheCompany were reluctant to make further concessions, both because they considered their price a fair one and because, having regard to their other business in India, they were fearful of giving an impression thattheir initial quotations were apt to be inflated.     They have however nowsaid they would go half-way towards meeting the cost&apos;of the as. 21provided the Ministry of Supply would help by reducing its research anddevelopment charge to cover the other half of the cost.    If the as. 21Radar is to be included and the quoted price is not to be increased, it isestimated that a total waiver of the research and development levy wouldbe involved in this suggestion.    Because of the political importance attached to the project the Commonwealth Secretary and the Minister ofSupply propose that the research and development levy be waived but ctreopposed to the waiver being specially shown in Votes,(ii) Dofors for Pakistan.    The guns, which are known to be wantedby Pakistan, are part of the surplus which has arisen as a result of therecent decision to disband Anti-Aircraft Command.    They are thought tobe saleable at 10 per cent of vocabulary price;   on this basis 100 gunswould fetch about  50, 000.    The Pakistanis have made, through theusual procurement channels, an enquiry for 27 of these guns, with thepossibility of an order for a further 69 later and have been told that theprice would be about  500 (or about  600 with ancillaries).3.      Arguments in favour of these proposals(a) Canberras for India(i) For political and strategic reasons it is consideredimportant, if possible, to stop the Russians frompenetrating into India&apos;s Air Force.    Further, her majesty&apos;s Government have shown themselvesinterested in the negotiations and would suffera distinct reverse were they unsuccessful.(ii) From the economic point of view the sale of theCanberras represents an important &apos;deal&apos; in animportant market and it is better to forgo thedevelopment levy if by so doing we can secure an export worth upwards of   1 2 millions than to lose thebusiness altogether - in which case we should not getany levy either.
(b) Bofcrs for Pakistan(i) It is important to retain Pakitan&apos;s goodwill and toavoid giving any grounds for the criticism that,while neutralist countries such as Egypt and Indiaget the best of both worlds, Pakistani membership of the Commonwealth as well as of the South EaotAsia Treaty Organisation and the Bagdad Pact countsfor nothing.    The fact that we are unable to hlepPakistan by any impressive show of public support for her against India means that we should regard it as all the more important to help her in any way we can.(ii) The value of the guns in question is not large and the guns are no longer required by the United Kingdom.4.      Arguments against these proposals(a) General.     The United Kingdom, in its present period of economicand balance of payments strain, cannot afford to subsidise overseesGovernments.     (The Defence Committee recently agreed that everyeffort should be made to secure economies in defence expenditure over-seas (D.C,(55) 16th Meeting, Item 3)).(b) Canberras for India(i) A considerable amount of money is involved.(ii) Either the waiver is made public by being shown inVotes or it is not.    If it is, there will almost inevitably be pressure for similar concessions on other occasions (the Americans have always beenunhappy about research and development charges intheir offshore contracts, for instance).    If it isnot it is very doubtful whether our obligations toParliament will have been discharged.(iii) We do not know whether the English Electric Companyhas made every concession that could reasonably beexpected or whether it is taking advantage of HerMajestys Governments interest in the case.     TheCompany have refused to reveal their expectedprofit margins in the transaction.(iv) Price is not the only outstanding point;   and it isnot known whether the amount of the priceconcession will suffice.(c) Bofors for Pakistan(i) The money directly involved is less, but the principle is the same.    News of the gift would probably leadto pressure for other assistance (Pakir tan herselfis already hoping for price reductions on the warships).    Further if the Pakistanis heard of the concession to India on Canberras they would increase their pressure for other assistance.    A system ofauctioning, under which we tried to keep a balance
between amounts of aid to these two - or indeedother - countries would be self-perpetuating andwould soon become intolera?ole,(ii) If we give surplus anti-aircraft equipment to pakistan we shall establish a very embarrassingprecedent vis-a-vis other countries, includingcountries in the North Atlantic Treaty Organisatii *nand the Commonwealth.    In this connection it hasalready been agreed for political reasons to sellguns to the Lebanese at a special reduced price of 400 (including ancillaries).27th January, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
