<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/79/0 images: 177-210</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
16 ZJ:(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP.(56) 34 ,   COPY NG613th February, 1956CABINETRESTRICTIVE TRADE PRACTICES bill memorandum by the Lord chancellor the Committee ox Ministers which was set up under my chairmanship to consider the report of the Monopolies Commission on Coll-ecclve Discrimination   has been engaged on the preparation of a Bill todeal with restrictive trade practices.     The Committee have completed their examination and I now present the draft Restrictive Trade PracticesBill for the Cabinet&apos;s consideration.2. The Bill implements the statements of policy made by theGovernment in the debates upon this subject which took place in bothHouses of Parliament in July 1955.3, Broadly the problem which has confronted us has been tofind a fair and just method of dealing with restrictive trade practices which avoided both the feint of criminality and arbitrary assumptionsassociated with, such systems as the Sherman Act procedure as practisedin America, and, on the other hand, the long delays and incessantpolitical controversy which was becoming inherent in methods associatedwith the Monopolies Commission in this country.    We believe that themethod which is described below and. contained in the Bill provides what will generally be regarded as a sensible and workmanlike approach to theproblem.    We do not pretend that in a field at once so novel and socontroversial, we will have been able to solve at one stroke all theproblems associated with it.     This Bill should however be a good beginning.REGISTRATION4. The izxai part of xhs Bill provides for the registration of certain restrictive trade agreements.     The field (clause 5) is wider than those dealt with in the Report of the Monopolies Commission onCollective Discrimination;  it includes for example common price rings.It covers oral as well as written agreements and makes provision to dealwith arrangements based upon the recommendations of Trade Associations,It does not include activities expressly authorised by statute or agreements which relate exclusively to exports - see paragraph 12 below.    It doesnot include restrictive practices by labour,5. The method of registration (clause 7) is for the Board ofTrade to make an Order specifying any of the practices in clause 5 to becalled up and such an Order if it seems convenient can postpone the registration in the case of certain industries.     This provision would., forexample,  enable the Board of Trade to postpone registration of restrictive arrangements in steel until after they had received a report upon these practices from the Steel Board,
6. The register will be public,  subject only to the power toplace certain agreements in a special section e0g, those the publicationof which might do damage to our export ti*a:de or our security or other interests.    Public Knowledge of what restrictive agreements do existis a necessary prerequisite to the removal of those which are eitherunnecessary or contrary to the public interest (clause 9).EXAMINATION7. The next stage is concerned with the examination of theagreement and here we have had to determine some difficult issuesconcerned with the nature of the Tribunal, the nature of the issue to bedetermined and the procedures to be adopted.8. The provisions relating to the Tribunal follow the decisionof the Cabinet (C.M0(5S) 47th Conclusions, Minute 5),     The Tribunal,which will be known as the Restrictive Practices Court will be a judicialone.    It will consist of five Judges and will include as part of it laymenwith knowledge of or experience in industry, commerce or public affairs,all appointed by the Lord Chancellor (clauses 2-4),9, The Restrictive Practices Court will have the tack of determining whether the agreements brought before them are or are notcontrary to the public interest.     They will do this in the light of thejusticiable issue defined in clause 16 of the Bill.     This clause does not differ greatly from that which was considered by the Cabinet and generally agreed in December,, (CuM, (55) 46th Conclusions, Minute 5),    I would call attention to clause 16\if which relates to the factor of unemployment.This subsection with which the Minister of Labour agrees, disallows aplea based on temporary unemployment and directs the courfs attentionto the position regarding unemployment as a vhole in an area and notmerely to unemployment in the industry in question.    Where the courtdetermines a restrictive practice to be contrary to the public interest,the court may order the parties to the agreement to refrain from giving effect to the agreement or from making any other agreement to the likeeffect.    In brief,  if an industry wishes to continue a practice of this kindit will have to show that it is doing so for one of these defined purposes and not operating to any unreasonable extent againct the public interest.We believe that this clause gives a fair opening to industry to presentthe arguments normally advanced in favour of their practices.    It isimportant that it should not be widened.10o On the question of procedure we have been much concerned to ensure that the proceeding should not be represented as some kind ofprosectuion by the Board of Trade ox- any other Department against theindustry concerned.     To this end we have got to secure that the conductof the case and the presentation of the public interest aspect of the matter should be as independent as possible of political control or parliamentary discussion,     To this end we propose (clause 1) the appointment by theCrown of a Registrar responsible not only for maintaining the register of Agreements but for preparing and initiating proceedings before the restrictive Practices Coitrt, which clause 2 of the Bill establishes.     the registrar will be advised by the Treasury Solicitor and will be representedbefore the Court by Counsel nominated by the Attorney-General.    Thisarrangement will secure virtual independence of action for the Registrar.In so far as any general question could arise the Committee suggest thatin the very special circumstances the Treasury might be prepared to answer in Parliament for matters affecting the of the Registrar.
11. A difficult problem has confronted us as to whether a discretion should be retained to exempt any agreement from call-up beforethe Court.    We have not specifically provided in the Bill that all agree-tnSixes should be call.?.! up since to do so might lead to the taunt that theprocedure would take too lo.ng.    Equally we have taken care to ensurethat no-one should have discretion to exempt agreements from examinationbefore the Court and so be open to pressure to exempt an industry.     the essence of these proceedings are that they are judicial and they must remain so.    In practi.ee we have three good answers to the charge that all this will take a long time.That any procedure including that recommendedby the majority report of the Monopolies commission would have taken just as long.    The Sherman Actis still active 65 years after its introduction.That we can control the order in which matters are dealt with so that we can seek to bring up some of the more important issues and thosedeciding matters of general principle (clause l(2))early.We provide in clause 18(2)(c) for a summaryprocedure for dealing with cases where decisionsof the Court appear to have established a precedent.MONOPOLIES COMMISSIONThere remain a number of problems outside the field ofthose referrable to the Restrictive Practices Court.    Monopolies of scaleclearly do not fit into any justiciable system.    Pure export agreementsraising as they often do matters which touch on issues of our externalpolitical and commercial policy are better dealt with so far as possibleoutside the procedures described above.    At the same time we cannotleave these matters with no machinery for examination.    We accordinglyretain the Monopolies Commission for this purpose.    V/e take power to.turn it into a more compact and smaller body better suited to these more limited purposes (clause 22).    We also propose new arrangements whichwill make it easier to preserve the confidential character of certain exportarrangements which upon enquiry are found not to operate against thepublic interest (clause 25(2)).13. We deal with the problem of transitional arrangements between the old and new procedures in Part III of the Bill.    Here it willperhaps suffice to say that some interruption of work upon the problemof restrictive practices is inevitable in the process of such a change.The arrangements which we propose are designed to secure first thatthere shall be the minimum danger of a clash of opinion between theCommission and the new Court and second that the Government shall not put itself into the position of judging matters which are by the Billremitted to the Court for deterrrdnation.RESALE PRICE MAINTENANCE.15. Part. II of the Bill deals with resale price maintenance.Any Bill which purported to deal with restrictive practices and failed tograpple with this field would be rightly subjected to severe criticism.There is no solution to it which will prove universally acceptable.(a)(b)(c)
16. The problem briefly is as follows.    Many manufacturersseek to secure that no retailer should sell their products below a price which they determine.    Though the keeping of prices above a certainprescribed level is not the most obvious of our present day needs thereare quite respectable arguments in favour of the manufacturer who wishes to have his goods sold at a level and a stable price,,    What has beencondemned is the elaborate machinery which has been set up to enforcethis system.    Indeed as both the Lloyd-Jacob Report and the majority-report ox the Monopolies Commission point out this machinery and the size and extent of the associations seeking to enforce the practice render it even more inflexible and more open to objection.    When trade associations become involved in this process of enforcement all membersof the association are expected to maintain prices and generally to maintainthem upon principles laid down by the association which allows littlelatitude for passing on to the consumer the benefits of more efficientmethods of distribution,    Manufacturers and retailers have tended insuch circumstances to join together for the purpose of enforcing resale price maintenance through an elaborate system of fines, stop   listsand private courts.17. The Bill proposes to render unlawful the collectiveenforcement of resale price maintenance (clause 19).     The stop list or&quot;black list&quot; used for this purpose and the Private Trade Court authorisingor purporting to authorise the cutting off of supply to a retailer willbecome unlawful at the same time.    Instead a new right will be establishedwhich will enable such individual manufacturers who wish to price maintain their gcods to do so through the ordinary courts.    If they attach conditions to the sale of such goods they will in future be able to enforce that conditionby action in the Courts not only against the dealer to whom they suppliedthem but also against subsequent dealers who buy the goods with knowledgeof the conditions attached (clause 20).10o While these provisions follow in general the recommend-atiens of the Lloyd-Jacob Report they will of course be controversial.Those who wish to see the end of resale price maintenance will criticise the fact that we legalise its individual enforcement.    Those who likeresale price maintenance will say, and say with some truth, that theabolition of collective enforcement even with the new forms of legalenforcement by individuals will greatly weaken the system and make itmuch harder particularly for a smaller manufacturer to ensure that hisproducts are price maintained.19. We have examined in some detail these variousdifficulties and v/e are satisfied that the approach in this Bill is the best that can be devised at any rate at this stage.    It eliminates the collectiveenforcement by trade associations with the inflexibility which inevitablyaccompanied such a system.    It provides a method whereby individuals who really wish to maintain their prices can seek to do so.     Individualresale price maintenance can be justified upon respectable economic grounds but it is not, an end to which all other objects should be sacrificed..CONCLUSIONS20. This Bill furnishes the basis of a new approach to the complex and controversial problem of restrictive trade practices on theemployers &apos; side.    Its essential features may be summarised as follows:-(a)        The public registration of restrictive trade practices.
(b) The establishment of a Judicial tribunal to- determine whether or not they arein the public interest.(c) The laying down of criteria upon which such an issue can be judged with the onus of proof upon those who seek tojustify this practice.(d) The rendering unlawful of the collectiveenforcement of resale price maintenancecoupled with the provision of new methods to enable individuals to secure themaintenance of the prices which they maychoose to fix.(e) The formation of a smaller and morecompact Monpolies Commission for dealingwith these matters which are inappropriate for reference to the new Court.These matters have been closely examined by your committee.    The state of the Parliamentary Time-table suggests thatthe Bill should be approved for presentation as soon as possible.K.House of Lords, S. V/. 1.11 th February, 1 956.
CONFIDENTIALRestrictive Trade Practices bill arrangement OF clauses part IRegistration and Judicial Investigation of restrictive Trading AgreementsEstablishment of Registrar and Restrictive Practices CourtClause1.   Appointment and functions of Registrar.2. &apos; Establishment of Restrictive Practices Court.3.  Nomination of judges as members of Court.4.  Appointment of other members of Court.Registration of Agreements5. Agreements to which Part I applies.6. Excepted agreements and restrictions.7. Classes of agreements to be registered.8. Duty to furnish particulars for registration.9. General provisions as to the register.10. Rectification of register, etc.Supplementary provisions as to registration11. Power of Registrar to obtain information.12. Offences in connection with registration.13. Commencement of proceedings and where.14. Regulations for purposes of registration.Judicial investigation of registered Agreements15. Jurisdiction and powers of Court.16. Presumption as to the public interest.17. Variation of decisions of the Court.18. Rules as to procedure.121-7 A
iiRestrictive Trade Practices       4 &amp; 5 Eliz. part IIEnforcement of Conditions as to Resale PricesClause19.  Prohibition of agreements for collective enforcement of conditions as to resale prices.20.  Individual enforcement by legal proceedings of conditionsas to resale prices.21.  Supplementary provisions.Part IIIConsequential and other Provisions as to monopolies and Restrictive Practices Acts, 1948 and 195322.  Reconstitution of Monopolies Commission.23.  Future scope of references to Monopolies Commission.24.  Provisions as to orders of competent authorities unders. 10 of Act of 1948.Part IVMiscellaneous and General25. Provisions relating to export agreements.26. Increase of number of judges of High Court and Court of session.27. Restriction on disclosure of information.28. Proceedings of Board of Trade.29. Expenses, etc.30. Interpretation.31. Application to Northern Ireland.32. Short title and commencement.Schedule Supplementary provisions as to proceedings of restrictive Practices Court.
4 &amp; 5 Eliz. 2      Restrictive Trade Practices1DRAFTof  aB   JL   JLj   JLjtoProvide for the registration of certain restrictive trading A-D- *956agreements, and for the prohibition of such agreementswhen contrary to the public interest; to prohibit the collective enforcement of conditions regulating theresale price of goods, and to make further provisionfor the individual enforcement of such conditions bylegal proceedings; to amend the Monopolies and restrictive Practices Acts, 1948 and 1953; to providefor the appointment of additional judges of theHigh Court and of the Court of Session; and for other purposes connected with the matters aforesaid.BE it enacted by the Queen&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and Commons, in this present parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5. Part IRegistration and Judicial Investigation of RestrictiveTrading AgreementsEstablishment of Registrar and Restrictive Practices court . (1) For the purposes of this Part of this Act, Her Majesty Appointment10 may appoint an officer to be known as the Registrar of Restric- and functionstive Trading Agreements (in this Act referred to as &quot; the of ReSistrar-Registrar &quot;), who shall hold office during Her Majesty&apos;s pleasure.(2) The Registrar shall be charged with the duty of main-taining a register of agreements which are subject to registration15 under this Part of this Act, and of taking proceedings before the121-7 A 2
2 Restrictive Trade Practices       4 &amp; 5 Eliz. 2A.D. 1956Part I cont.Establishmentof RestrictivePracticesCourt.Court (subject to such directions as may be given by the Boardof Trade with respect to the order in which such proceedings areto be taken) in respect of the agreements of which particularsare from time to time entered or filed in the register.(3) The Registrar may appoint such assistant registrars and such other officers and servants as he may, with the consent ofthe Treasury as to numbers and conditions of service, determine.(4) The Registrar shall have an official seal for the authentica-tion of documents required for purposes of this Part of this Act;and the Documentary Evidence Act, 1868, shall have effect as if 10the Registrar were included in the first column of the Scheduleto that Act and any assistant registrar or other officer authorisedto act on behalf of the Registrar were mentioned in the second column of that Schedule.(5) There shall be paid to any person holding the office of 15Registrar such salary or other emoluments as may be determinedby the Treasury.(6) In the case of any such holder of the office of Registrar asmay be determined by the Treasury, there shall be paid suchpension, allowance or gratuity to or in respect of him on his 20retirement or death, or such contributions or other paymentstowards provision for such a pension, allowance or gratuity, asmay be so determined(7) As soon as may be after the making of any determinationunder the last foregoing subsection, the Treasury shall lay before 25each House of Parliament a statement of the amount of the pension, allowance or gratuity or contributions or other paymentstowards pension, allowance or gratuity, as the case may be,payable in pursuance of the determination.2.- (1) For the purposes of this Part of this Act there shall 30be established a Court to be known as the Restrictive PracticesCourt (in this Part of this Act referred to as &quot; the Court &quot;).(2) The Court shall consist of five judges nominated undersection three of this Act, and not more than nine other members appointed under section four of this Act.(3) The Court shall be a court of record and have an officialseal which shall be judicially noticed; and any order of theCourt shall be enforceable -(a) in England and Wales and Northern Ireland, as if itwere an order of the High Court;\b) in Scotland, as if it were an order of the Court of session.(4) The supplementary provisions set out in the Schedule tothis Act shall have effect with respect to the proceedings of theCourt.(5) The Lord Chancellor may appoint such officers and servants of the Court as he may, with the approval of the3540
4 &amp; 5 Eliz. 2Restrictive Trade Practices3Treasury as to numbers and conditions of service, determine; A.D. 1956and the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1950, shall have effect as     Part Iif service as an officer or servant of the Court were service in an     -cont.established capacity in the permanent civil service of the State5 in an appointment held directly from the Crown.3. (1) The following judges shall be members of the Court, Nominationthat is to say:- &quot; of judges as members of(a) three puisne judges of the High Court nominated by the Court.Lord Chancellor;10       (b) one judge of the Court of Session nominated by the lord president of that Court;(c) one judge of the Supreme Court of Northern Irelandnominated by the Lord Chief Justice of NorthernIreland.15 (2) A judge of any court who is nominated under this section shall not be required to sit in any place outside the jurisdiction of that court, and shall be required to perform his duties as a judge of that court only when his attendance on the restrictive practices Court is not required.20 (3) In the case of the temporary absence or inability to act of a judge nominated under this section, the Lord Chancellor,the Lord President of the Court of Session, or the Lord chief justice of Northern Ireland, as the case may be, may nominateanother judge of the same court to act temporarily in his place,25 and a judge so nominated shall, when so acting, have all thefunctions of the judge in whose place he acts.(4) No judge shall be nominated under this section except withhis consent.4. (1) The   members   of   the   Court   other  than   judges Appointment30 nominated under the last foregoing section may be appointed of other by Her Majesty on the recommendation of the Lord Chancellor, members ofand any person recommended for appointment as such a member  our &quot;shall be a person appearing to the Lord Chancellor to be qualified by virtue of his knowledge of or experience in industry,35 commerce or public affairs.(2) A member of the Court appointed under this section (inthis section referred to as an appointed member) shall hold office for such period not less than three years as may bedetermined at the time of his appointment, and shall be eligible40 for reappointment:Provided that (a) an appointed member may at any time by notice inwriting to the Lord Chancellor resign his office;
Restrictive Trade Practices4 &amp; 5 Eliz. 2A.D. 1956 (6) the Lord Chancellor may, if he thinks fit, remove anyPart I appointed member for inability or misbehaviour.-cont.        ^) jn ^ cage 0       temporary absence or inability to act of an appointed member, the Lord Chancellor may appoint atemporary member to act in place of that member, and a tern- 5porary member shall, when so acting have all the functions ofan appointed member.(4) There may be paid to the appointed members and to any temporary member such remuneration as the Lord Chancellormay, with the approval of the Treasury, determine. 10(5) Subsections (6) and (7) of section one of this Act shallapply in relation to the office of appointed member as they apply in relation to the office of Registrar, but as if for references to the Treasury there were substituted references, in the saidsubsection (6) to the Lord Chancellor acting with the approval 15of the Treasury, and in the said subsection (7) to the LordChancellor.Registration of AgreementsAgreements to     5. (1) Subject to the provisions of the next following section,which Part I    this Part of this Act applies to any agreement between persons 20applies. carrying on business within the United Kingdom in the pro-due tion or wholesale or retail supply of goods, or in theapplication to goods of any process of manufacture, whether with or without other parties, being an agreement under which mutualrestrictions, whether identical or not, are accepted by the parties 25carrying on business as aforesaid or any of them in respect ofany one or more of the following matters, that is to say:  (a) the prices to be charged, quoted or paid for goodssupplied, offered or acquired, or for the application ofany process of manufacture to goods ; 30(b) the terms or conditions (other than terms as to prices)on or subject to which goods are to be supplied oracquired or any such process is to be applied to goods ;(c) the quantities or descriptions of goods to be produced,supplied or acquired, or to which any such process is 35to be applied ;(d) the processes of manufacture to be applied to any goods,or the goods to which any such process is to be applied ;or(e) the persons or classes of persons to, for or from whom, 40or the areas or places in or from which, goods areto be supplied or acquired, or any such process applied.(2) In this Part of this Act &quot; agreement&quot; includes any agree-ment or arrangement, whether or not it is or is intended to beenforceble (apart from any provision of this Act) by legal pro- 45ceedings, and references in this Part of this Act to restrictions
accepted under an agreement shall be construed accordingly;   A.D. 1956and for the purposes of this Part of this Act- Part I(a) an agreement which confers privileges or benefits only      cont-upon such parties as comply with conditions as to any such matters as are described in paragraphs (a) to (e)of subsection (1) of this section, or imposes obligationsupon parties who do not comply with such conditions,shall be treated as an agreement under which restric-tions are accepted by each of the parties in respect of10 those matters ; and(b) without prejudice to the generality of the foregoingparagraph, an obligation on the part of any party to anagreement to make payments calculated by referenceto the quantity of goods produced or supplied by him,15 or to which any process of manufacture is applied byhim, shall be treated as a restriction in respect of the quantities of those goods to be produced or supplied,or to which that process is to be applied.(3) This Part of this Act shall apply in relation to any agreement20 made between an association composed of such persons as are mentioned in the said subsection (1) and any other such person,or between two or more such associations, as it applies to anagreement between such persons; and for the purposes of thisPart of this Act any restrictions accepted by any such association25 under such an agreement shall be treated as accepted mutuallyby the members for the time being of the Association.(4) Where recommendations (whether express or implied) aremade by or on behalf of any such association as aforesaid to its members or to any class of its members, as to the action to be taken30 or not taken by them in respect of any such matters as are described in paragraphs (a) to (e) of the said subsection (1), thisPart of this Act shall apply in relation to the agreement for theconstitution of the association as if each such member werethereby required to comply with the recommendations, notwith-35 standing that the agreement does not so provide or expresslyprovides to the contrary.6. (1) This Part of this Act does not apply to any scheme or Exceptedagreement which is expressly authorised by or under any enact- agreements andment, or to any agreement to which the only parties are inter- restnctlons-40 connected bodies corporate or persons carrying on business in partnership with each other.(2) This Part of this Act does not apply to any contract forthe sale of goods, or for the application of any process of manu-facture of goods, which imposes no such restrictions as are45 described in section five of this Act except in respect of those goods.
Restrictive Trade Practices       4 &amp; 5 Eliz. 2(3) This Part of this Act does not apply to any licence granted by the proprietor or any licensee of a patent, any assignment ofa patent, or any agreement for such a licence or assignment,being a licence, assignment or agreement which imposes no such restrictions aforesaid except in respect of the patented article, 5the patented process, or articles made by that process.(4) In determining whether an agreement is an agreement towhich this Part of this Act applies, no account shall be taken ofany such restriction as follows, that is to say (a) a restriction which relates exclusively to the production 10of goods, or the application of any process of manu-facture to goods, outside the United Kingdom, to thesupply of goods to be delivered outside the United King-dom, or to the acquisition of goods to be delivered out-side the United Kingdom and not imported into the 15United Kingdom for entry for home use ; or(b) a restriction which affects or otherwise relates to theworkmen to be employed or not employed by anyperson, or as to the remuneration, conditions of employ-ment, hours of work or working conditions of such 20workmen,and for the purposes of this subsection &quot; workmensame meaning as in the Industrial Courts Act, 1919.has the classes ofagreements7. (1) Subject to the provisions of this section, every agree-ment to which this Part of this Act applies shall be subject to 25to be registered, registration thereunder.(2) The foregoing subsection shall come into force on such date as the Board of Trade may by order appoint, and differentdates may be appointed under this subsection in relation toagreements of different classes. 30(3) An order under the last foregoing subsection may describe the classes of agreements to which it applies by reference to anyone or more of the following matters, that is to say (a) the trade or industry in which the persons by whomrestrictions are accepted are engaged, or the class of 35business carried on by such persons ;(b) the character of the restrictions accepted, or the goods,processes, transactions, areas or places affected by such restrictions; or(c) any other features which appear to the Board to be 40expedient.(4) The Board of Trade may by order direct that this section shall cease to have effect (subject to such saving or transitional provisions as may be contained in the order) in relation to agree-ments of any class in respect of which it is for the time being 45Part I- cont.
in force ; and subsection (3) of this section shall apply in relation   AD. 1956(5) The powers of the Board of Trade to make orders underthis section shall be exercisable by statutory instrument; and5 a draft of any statutory instrument containing such an order shall be laid before Parliament.8.-(1) Within the period specified in this section the following Duty toparticulars shall be furnished to the Registrar in respect of every furnishagreement which is subject to registration under this Part of this particulars10 Act, that is to say- registrant(a) the names of the persons who are parties to the agree-ment (including, in the case of an agreement made byany such association as is mentioned in subsection (3)of section five of this Act, the names of the members15 of the association); and(b) the whole of the terms of the agreement, whether or notrelating to any such restrictions as are described in sub-section (1) of section five of this Act.(2) If at any time after particulars of an agreement have20 been furnished under this section that agreement is varied(whether in respect of the parties or in respect of the terms) ordetermined otherwise than by efrluxion of time, particulars of the variation or determination shall be furnished to the Registrarwithin the period specified in this section.25 (3) The particulars to be furnished under this section in respectof an agreement shall be furnished (a) in so far as the agreement, or any variation or determina-tion of the agreement, is made by an instrument inwriting, by the production of the original or a true copy30 of that instrument;(b) in so far as the agreement, or any variation or determina-tion of the agreement, is not so made, by the productionof a memorandum in writing signed by the party by whom the particulars are furnished.35 (4) The particulars to be furnished under this section in respectof an agreement shall be furnished within such period, beginning with the date on which the agreement is made or becomes subjectto registration under this Part of this Act, whichever is the later,Or with the date of the variation or determination of the agree-40 ment, as the case may be, as may be prescribed by the order ofthe Board of Trade under section seven of this Act by virtue ofwhich the agreement is subject to registration.(5) If default is made in furnishing particulars under thissection in respect of an agreement, the Registrar may serve45 notice upon any person within the United Kingdom who is partyto any such order.Part I cont.121B
8Restrictive Trade Practices TJ  4 &amp;j5IEliz. 2to the agreement (or, in the case of default in furnishing par-ticulars of the determination of an agreement, any person withinthe United Kingdom who was party thereto immediately before its determination) requiring him to make good the default; andif that person fails to make good the default within fourteen 5days after the service of the notice, the High Court may, on theapplication of the Registrar (a) make an order directing that person to make good thedefault within such time as may be specified in theorder; or 10(b) authorise the Registrar to treat as particulars dulyfurnished to him under this Part of this Act any docu-ment or information in bis possession relating to theagreement.(6) In the application of the last foregoing subsection to Scot- 15land, for any reference to the High Court there shall be sub-stituted a reference to the Court of Session.9.-(1) The register for the purposes of this Part of this Actshall be kept by the Registrar at such premises within the UnitedKingdom as the Registrar may determine. 20(2) The register shall be kept in such form as may be pre-scribed by regulations made under section fourteen of this Act,and the Registrar shall enter or file therein such particulars asmay be so prescribed of agreements subject to registration underthis Part of this Act, being particulars duly furnished to him 25under this Part of this Act by parties thereto, or documents or information which he is authorised by the Court to treat asparticulars so furnished.(3) Regulations made as aforesaid shall provide for themaintenance of a special section of the register, and for the 30entry or filing in that section of such particulars as the Boardof Trade may direct, being (a) particulars containing information the publication ofwhich would in the opinion of the Board be contraryto the public interest; 35(b) particulars containing information as to any secretprocess of manufacture or as to the presence,absence or situation of any mineral or other depositsor as to any other similar matter, being information the publication of which, in the opinion of the Board 40would substantially damage the legitimate business interests of any person.(4) The register, other than the special section, shall beopen to public inspection during such hours and subject to payment of such fee as may be prescribed by regulations made 45under section fourteen of this Act.
(5) Any person may, upon payment of such fee as may be A.D; 1956&quot;prescribed by regulations made as aforesaid, require the Registrar     Part Ito supply to him a copy of or extract from any particulars      cont.entered or filed in the register, other than the special section,5 certified by the Registrar to be a true copy or extract.(6) No process for compelling the production of the register .   .or of any other document kept by the Registrar shall issue fromany court except with the leave of the court, and any suchprocess if issued shall bear a statement that it is issued with the10 leave of the court.(7) A copy of or extract from any document entered or filedin the register, certified under the hand of the Registrar (whoseofficial position it shall not be necessary to prove), shall in alllegal proceedings be admissible in evidence as of equal validity15 with the original.10. (1) The High Court may, on the application of any Rectificationperson aggrieved, order the register to be rectified by the removal of register, etc.of particulars included therein in respect of any agreement whichis not subject to registration under this Part of this Act.20 (2) The High Court may, on the application of any personparty to an agreement, or on the application of the Registrarin respect of any agreement of which particulars have beenfurnished to him under this Part of this Act, declare whetheror not the agreement is one to which this Part of this Act applies,25 and if so whether or not it is subject to registration under sectionseven of this Act.(3) Where application is made under subsection (2) of thissection by any party to an agreement before the expiration ofthe period within which, if the agreement is subject to registra-30 tion under this Part of this Act, particulars are required to be furnished under section eight of this Act, then (a) if particulars of the agreement have not been sofurnished before the commencement of the proceedings,the said period shall be extended by a period equal35 to the period during which the proceedings and anyappeal therein are pending, and such further period,if any, as the court may direct; and(b) if particulars have been so furnished, the Registrar shallnot enter or file particulars of the agreement in the40 register during the period during which the proceedings and any appeal therein are pending.(4) Notice of any application to the court under this section,other than an application by the Registrar, shall be served onthe Registrar in accordance with rules of court, and the Registrar45 shall be entitled, in accordance with such rules, to appear andbe heard on the application.121 B 2
ftA-JD,: 1956 (5) In the application of this section to Scotland, for anyPaivt I reference to the High Court there shall be substituted a reference-rcont.     to the Court of Session.Power ofRegistrarto obtain information.Offences inconnectionwithregistration.Supplementary provisions as to registration11. (1) If the Registrar has reasonable cause to believe that any person carrying on within the United Kingdom any suchbusiness as is described in subsection (1) of section five of thisAct is or may be party to an agreement subject to registrationunder this Part of this Act, he may give notice to that personrequiring him, within such time as may be specified in the notice, 10to notify the Registrar whether he is party to any agreementrelating to any such matters as are described in paragraphs (a)to (e) of the said subsection (1), and if so to furnish to the registrar such particulars as may be so specified of that agreement. 15&apos; (2) The Registrar may give notice to any person by whomparticulars are furnished under section eight of this Act inrespect of an agreement, or to any other person being partyto the agreement, requiring him to furnish such further docu-ments or information in his possession or control as the Registrar 20considers expedient for the purposes of or in connection withthe registration of the agreement.(3) In any case where the Registrar has given or is empoweredto give notice to any person under the foregoing provisions ofthis section, any officer duly authorised in that behalf by the 25Registrar may, on production if so required of his authority, atany reasonable time enter any premises on or from which that person carries on business, and may inspect and take copies ofor extracts from any documents found on those premises which appear to that officer to be material for the purposes of registra- 30tion under this Part of this Act.12. (1) If any person fails without reasonable excuse tocomply with a notice duly given to him under the last foregoing section, or obstructs any officer in the exercise of his powers under subsection (3) of that section, he shall be guilty of an 35offence and shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine notexceeding one hundred pounds.(2) If any person who furnishes or is required to furnish anyparticulars, documents or information under this Part of thisAct,  40(a) makes any statement, or furnishes any document, whichhe knows to be false in a material particular; or(b) recklessly makes any statement, or furnishes any docu-ment, which is false in a material particular ; or
(c) wilfully alters, suppresses or destroys any document 1956;which he is required to furnish as aforesaid, Part Ihe shall be guilty of an offence under this section, and shall be mM&apos;liable on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not  exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds, or to both such imprisonment and such a fine, or on conviction on indictment to imprisonment for a term not exceed-ing two years or to a fine, or to both such imprisonment and a fine.10 (3) If any default in respect of which a person is convicted of an offence under subsection (1) of this section continuesafter the conviction, that person shall be guilty of a furtheroffence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceed-ing one hundred pounds, or not exceeding ten pounds for every15 day on which the default continues within the three months nextfollowing his conviction for the first-mentioned offence, which-ever is the greater; and for the purposes of this subsection a default in respect of the furnishing of any particulars, documentsor information shall be deemed to continue until the particulars,20 documents or information have been furnished.(4) Where an offence under this section committed bya body corporate is proved to have been committedwith the consent or connivance of, or to be attributable to anyneglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other25 similar officer of the body corporate or any person who waspurporting to act in any such capacity, he as well as the body corporate shall be guilty of that offence and shall be liable tobe proceeded against and punished accordingly. i(5) In this section &quot; director &quot;, in relation to a body corporate30 established by or under any enactment for the purpose of carry-ing on under national ownership any industry or part of an industry or undertaking, being a body corporate whose affairsare managed by its members, means a member of that body corporate.35    13. (1) No proceedings for an offence under this Part of this Commence-Act shall be instituted in England and Wales or Northern Ireland ment QJ.except by or with the consent of the Director of Public Prosecu- andCwherfStions or the Registrar.(2) Notwithstanding anything in section one hundred and four40 of the Magistrates&apos; Courts Act, 1952, or in any corresponding. enactment relating to summary proceedings in Northern Ireland,an information relating to an offence under this Part of this Actmay, subject to the provisions of subsection (4) of this section,be tried by a magistrates&apos; court or by a court of summary45 jurisdiction in Northern Ireland, if it is laid at any time withintwelve months after the date on which evidence sufficient in
fazr-m -A.iD. 1956., the opinion of the Director of Public Prosecutions or thePart! Registrar, as the case may be, to justify the proceedings comes cont.     to his knowledge.(3) Notwithstanding anything in section twenty-three of the summary Jurisdiction (Scotland) Act, 1954, proceedings in  scotland for an offence aganst this Part of this Act may, subjectto the provisions of subsection (4) of this section, be commencedat any time within twelve months after the date on whichevidence sufficient in the opinion of the Registrar to justify a report to the Lord Advocate with a view to consideration of 10the question of proceedings comes to the knowledge of the registrar.(4) No information shall be laid or proceedings commenced in respect of any such offence as aforesaid more than three yearsafter the commission of the offence. 15(5) For the purposes of subsections (2) and (3) of this section,a certificate of the Director of Public Prosecutions or the registrar, as the case may be, as to the date on which such evidence as aforesaid came to his knowledge shall be conclusive evidence. 20(6) An offence under section twelve of this Act may be tried by a court of summary jurisdiction either in the county or placein which the offence was actually committed or in any county or place in which the alleged offender carries on business.Regulations        14. (1) Subject to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the 25for purposes    Registrar may make such regulations as he thinks expedientof registration. jof  pUrpGses  Gf registration  under  this Part  of this  Actand for purposes connected therewith, and in particular, but without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision (a) for regulating the procedure to be followed in connection 30: with the furnishing of particulars, information and documents under sections eight and eleven of this Act;(b) for prescribing the form of any notice, certificate orother document to be given, made or furnished under; . the foregoing provisions of this Part of this Act;        35&quot;.,   . (c) for regulating the inspection of the register or of any document kept by the Registrar ;(d) for prescribing anything authorised or required by thisPart of this Act to be prescribed by regulations madeunder this section. 40(2) Any such regulations prescribing a fee for inspection ofthe register or for the supply of copies of or extracts fromparticulars entered or filed therein, shall be made with theapproval of the Treasury.
(3) The power of the Registrar to make regulations under A.D. 1956this section shall be exercisable by statutory instrument, and the     Part IStatutory Instruments Act, 1946, shall apply to such regulations     -cont.as it applies to regulations made by a Minister of the CrownI 5 within the meaning of that Act.(4) Any statutory instrument containing regulations madeunder this section shall be laid before Parliament after beingmade.Judicial investigation of registered Agreements10   .15. (1) The Court shall have jurisdiction, on the application jurisdiction of the Registrar in respect of any agreement of which particulars and powers are for the time being registered under Part I of this Act, to p^^es^6declare whether or not any restrictions by virtue of which the courtsaid Part I applies to the agreement are contrary to the public15 interest.(2) Where any such restrictions are determined by the court to be contrary to the public interest, the Court may, upon theapplication of the Registrar, make such order as appears to theCourt to be proper for restraining all or any of the persons20 party to the agreement who are party to the proceedings (a) from giving effect to, or enforcing or purporting toenforce, the agreement in respect of those restrictions;(b) from making any other agreement (whether with thesame parties Or with other parties) to the like effect.25 (3) The powers of the Court under this section shall not beaffected by any variation or determination of an agreementeffected after the commencement of the proceedings.(4) The Registrar shall cause notice of any declaration or order made under this section to be entered in the register.30    16. For the purposes of any proceedings before the Court Presumptionunder the last foregoing section, a restriction accepted in pur- as to thesuance of any agreement shall be deemed to be contrary to the public interest,public interest unless the Court is satisfied (a) that the restriction is reasonably necessary for the pro-35 tection of the public in connection with the purchase,consumption, installation or use of goods requiringspecial knowledge or skill in that connection;(b) that the removal of the restriction would deny to thepublic as purchasers, consumers or users of any goods40 other specific and substantial benefits or advantagesenjoyed or likely to be enjoyed by them as such,whether by virtue of the restriction itself or of any arrangements or operations resulting therefrom ;
(c) that the restriction is reasonably necessary to counteractmeasures taken by any person not party to the agree-ment with a view to preventing or restricting competi-tion in or in relation to the trade or business in whichthe persons party thereto are engaged ; ,: 5(d) that the restriction is reasonably necessary to enablethe persons party to the agreement to negotiate fairterms for the supply or acquisition of goods to or fromany one person, or any two or more persons being inter-connected bodies corporate, not party thereto who con- 10trols or together control a preponderant part of thetrade or business of acquiring or supplying such goods ;(e) that the restriction is necessary for the purposes of ascheme certified by the Board of Trade under PartXXIII of the Income Tax Act, 1952 (which relates to 15contributions and payments under schemes or rationa-lising industry);(/) that, having regard to the conditions actually obtainingor reasonably foreseen at the time of the application,the removal of the restriction would be likely to have 20a serious and persistent adverse effect on the general level of unemployment in an area, or in areas taken together, in which a substantial proportion of the trade or industry to which the agreement relates is situated,or to cause a substantial reduction in the volume or 25earnings of the export trade of the United Kingdom ; or(g) that the restriction is reasonably required for purposesconnected with the maintenance of any other restrictionaccepted by the parties, whether under the same agree-ment or under any other agreement betv/een them, 30being a restriction which is found by the Court not tobe contrary to the public interest upon grounds otherthan those specified in this paragraph, or has been sofound in previous proceedings before the Court.and (in any such case) that the restriction has not operated and 35is not calculated to operate to an unreasonable extent to the detriment of persons not parties to the agreement being pur-chasers, consumers or users of goods produced or sold by suchparties, or persons engaged or seeking to become engaged in thetrade or business of selling such goods or of producing or selling 40similar goods, or otherwise to the detriment of the public.17. (1) The Court may, upon application made in accord-ance with this section, discharge any previous determination ofthe Court in respect of any restriction (including any order made
by the Court in pursuance of the determination) and substitutesuch other determination, and make such order in pursuancethereof, as appears to the Court to be proper at the time of the hearing of the application.5 (2) The provisions of section sixteen of this Act shall apply with the necessary modifications in relation to proceedings onan application under this section as they apply in relation to theproceedings therein mentioned.(3) An application under this section may be made by the10 Registrar or by any person who is, or was at the time of theprevious determination of the Court, subject to or entitled tothe benefit of the restriction in question.(4) No application shall be made under this section except with the leave of the Court, and such leave shall not be granted15 except upon prima facie evidence of a material change in the relevant circumstances.18. (1) Subject to the foregoing provisions of this Part of Rules as tothis Act and to the provisions of the Schedule to this Act, the procedure,procedure in or in connection with any proceedings before the20 Court and, subject to the approval of the Treasury, the feeschargeable in respect of such proceedings, shall be such as maybe determined by rules made by the Lord Chancellor.(2) Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing pro-vision, rules made under this section may provide 25 (a) for regulating the persons to be made respondents to any application by the Registrar under this Part of thisAct;(b) for securing, by means of preliminary statements offacts and contentions, and by the production of docu-30 ments, the administration of interrogatories and other methods of discovery, that all material facts and con-siderations are brought before the Court;(c) for enabling the Court to determine in a summary wayany issue arising in relation to an agreement which35 appears to the Court to be governed by principles estab-lished in any previous proceedings before the Court.(3) The power of the Lord Chancellor to make rules under thissection shall be exercisable by statutory instrument; and any statutory instrument containing such rules shall be laid before40 Parliament after being made.A.D. 1956Part I cont.121C
Prohibition of agreements forcollectiveenforcementof conditionsas to resale prices.Part IIEnforcement of Conditions as to Resale Prices19. (1) Subject to the provisions of this section, it shall beunlawful for any two or more persons carrying on business inthe United Kingdom as suppliers of any goods to make or carry 5, out any agreement or arrangement (a) to withhold supplies of goods for delivery in the UnitedKingdom from dealers who resell or have resold goodsin breach of any condition as to the price at which those goods may be resold ; or 10(b) to refuse to supply goods for delivery in the UnitedKingdom to such dealers except on terms and condi-tions which are less favourable than those applicablein the case of other dealers carrying on business in similar circumstances. 15(2) Subject to the provisions of this section, it shall be unlaw-ful for any two or more persons carrying on business in theUnited Kingdom as dealers in any goods to make or carry out any agreement or arrangement (a) to withhold orders for supplies of goods for delivery in 20the United Kingdom from suppliers who supply or havesupplied goods otherwise than subject to such a condi-tion as aforesaid ; or(b) to discriminate in their handling of goods against goodssupplied by such suppliers. 25(3) The foregoing provisions of this section shall not applyto the following agreements or arrangements, that is to say:- (a) an agreement or arrangement to which the only parties are two or more inter-connected bodies corporate, ortwo or more persons carrying on business in partner- 30ship with each other;(b) a contract for the sale of any goods which relatesexclusively to those goods.(4) This section applies in relation to an association com-posed of persons carrying on business as mentioned in sub- 35section (1) or subsection (2) of this section as it applies inrelation to a person so carrying on business ; and without pre-judice to the foregoing provision it shall be unlawful for anysuch association, or any person acting on behalf of any suchassociation, to make to members of the association or any class 40of such members any recommendation to act as described inparagraph (a) or paragraph (b) of the said subsection. (1) or thesaid subsection (2), as the case may be.
(5) No criminal proceedings shall lie against any person on   A.D. 1956the ground that he has committed, or aided, abetted, counselled    Part nor procured the commission of, or conspired or attempted to      cont.commit, or incited others to commit, any contravention of this section.(6) Without prejudice to the right of any person to bring civil proceedings in respect of tany contravention or apprehendedcontravention of this section, compliance with this section shallbe enforceable by civil proceedings on behalf of the Crown for10 an injunction or other appropriate relief.(7) Section four of the Trade Disputes Act, 1906 (which pro-hibits actions of tort against trade unions) shall not apply to proceedings under this section.20. (1) Where goods are sold by a supplier subject to a individual15 condition as to the price at which those goods may be resold, enforcementeither generally or by or to a specified class or person, thatD^ lQsalcondition may, subject to the provisions of this section, be]^^d?j^senforced by the supplier against any person not party to the as to resaiesale who subsequently acquires the goods with notice of the prices.20 condition as if he had been party thereto.(2) A condition shall not be enforceable by virtue of thissection (a) in respect of the resale of any goods by a person whoacquires those goods by retail purchase, or by any25 person who acquires them, whether immediately or not,from such a person;(b) in respect of the resale of any goods pursuant to anorder of any court, or by way of execution or distress.,-,     (3) Nothing in this section shall be construed as enabling any30 person to enforce a condition imposed in pursuance of any restriction which is declared by an order of the restrictive practices Court for the time being in force under Part I of thisAct to be contrary to the public interest.(4) If in any proceedings it is proved that goods sold by the35 plaintiff have been resold by the defendant in breach of a con-dition which is enforceable against him by virtue of this section,the court may, if it thinks fit, grant an injunction restraining the defendant from reselling in breach of any such condition any goods already sold or thereafter to be sold by the plaintiff,40 whether of the same description as the goods proved to have beenresold as aforesaid or of any other description.21. (1) For the purposes of this Part of this Act a condition Supplementaryas to the amount of discount which may be allowed on the resale provisions,of any goods, or as to the price which may be paid on the121 C 2
A.D. 1956 resale of any goods for other goods taken by way of exchange,Part II shall be treated as a condition as to the price at which goods cont.     may be resold.(2) In this Part of this Act any reference to selling goodsincludes a reference to letting goods under a hire-purchase agree- 5ment within the meaning of the Hire-Purchase Act, 1938, and inrelation to goods let under any such agreement any referenceto the price shall be construed as a reference to the cash pricewithin the meaning of section two of that Act.(3) In the application of this section to Scotland, for references 10to a hire-purchase agreement within the meaning of the Hire-Purchase Act, 1938, and to the cash price within the meaning of section two of that Act there shall be substituted respectivelyreferences to a contract to which the Hire-Purchase and SmallDebt (Scotland) Act, 1932 applies, or would apply if the limita- 15tion as to value contained in section one of that Act wereomitted, and to the price at which a prospective hirer under sucha contract could have purchased the goods for cash; and for references to the plaintiff, the defendant or an injunction thereshall be substituted references respectively to the pursuer, the 20defender and an interdict.(4) In the application of this section to Northern Ireland forany reference to the Hire-Purchase Act, 1938 or to section twoof that Act there shall be substituted a reference to any corre-sponding enactment for the time being in force in Northern 25Ireland.Part IIIConsequential and Other Provisions as toMonopolies and Restrictive Practices Acts, 1948 and 1953Reconstitution 22. (1) As from the date on which this section comes into 30of Monopolies force, the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices CommissionCommission, established under the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices(Inquiry and Control) Act, 1948 (in this Part of this Act referredto as &quot; the Act of 1948 &quot;) shall be known as the monopolies commission, and every member of that Commission holding 35office on that date shall cease to hold office.(2) Notwithstanding anything in subsection (3) of section oneof the Act of 1948 (which prohibits the re-appointment ofmembers of the Commission other than the chairman and deputy chairmen) any member of the said Commission who ceases to 40hold office by virtue of this section shall be eligible for re-appointment; but the said subsection (3) shall have effect inrelation to the period for which a member who is re-appointedmay hold office, and the period to which the term of office ofsuch a member may be extended as if that member had not 45ceased to hold office as aforesaid.
(3) The maximum number of members of the said Com-   A.D. 1956mission who may be appointed under subsection (2) of section    Part IIIone of the Act of 1948 (which provides that the Commission      cont.shall consist of not more than twenty-five members) shall be5 reduced to ten; and accordingly in the said subsection (2) forthe words &quot; twenty-five &quot; there shall be substituted the word&quot; ten &quot;.(4) The functions of the said Commission shall cease to be exercisable by separate groups of members, and accordingly10 section two of the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices Corn-mission Act, 1953 (in this section referred to as &quot; the Act of1953 &quot;) and the Second Schedule to that Act (which make provi-sion for the exercise of functions of the said Commission bygroups of members working at the same time) are hereby15 repealed.(5) The power of the Board of Trade under section one ofthe Act of 1953 to appoint deputy chairmen of the said Com-mission shall cease to be exercisable ; and accordingly subsection(3) of the said section one is hereby repealed, and the said section20 and the First Schedule to the Act of 1953, shall have effect asif every reference therein to a deputy chairman were omitted.(6) This section shall come into force on such date as maybe appointed by order made by the Board of Trade by statutory instrument.25    23. (1) For the purposes of any reference made to the Future scopeMonopolies Commission after the commencement of this Act of referencesunder section two of the Act of 1948 conditions to which that g J^^jJ&quot;Act applies shall not be deemed to prevail as respects the supply  ommisslon-of goods of any description, the application of any process to30 goods of any description or the export of goods of any descrip-tion, by reason of any agreement to which Part I of this Actapplies.(2) In relation to any such reference as aforesaid, subsection(1) of section five of that Act (which provides that such con-35 ditions shall be deemed to prevail as respects exports of goodsif any one person produces at least one-third of all the goodsproduced in the United Kingdom) shall have effect as if afterthe words &quot; any one person &quot; there were inserted the words &quot; orany   two   or   more   persons   being   inter-connected   bodies40 corporate &quot;.(3) Except so far as the Board of Trade may otherwise directin any particular case, any reference or requirement to report made to the said Commission under the Act of 1948 beforethe commencement of this Act, in respect of which the Commis-45 sion have not made a final report to the Board, shall lapse on
the commencement of this Act, and any proceedings of theCommission thereunder shall be discontinued accordingly.(4) The proviso to subsection (4) of section six of the Act of1948 (which restricts the powers of the Board of Trade to varyreferences made to the Commission under that Act) and the 5proviso to subsection (1) of section fifteen of that Act (whichrestricts the power of the Board to require the Commission toreport on general questions) shall cease to have effect; and section twelve of that Act (which enables the Board to refer tothe Commission questions as to compliance with recommenda- iotions of the Commission or of competent authorities) shall cease to have effect in relation to any recommendations contained ina report issued by the Commission in pursuance of a reference made before the commencement of this Act.Provisions asto orders ofcompetentauthoritiesunder s. 10of Act of1948.24. (1) Except as provided by this section, no order shall 15be made after the commencement of this Act under section tenof the Act of 1948-(a) declaring unlawful the making or carrying out of any agreement which, if in force, would be an agreement towhich Part I of this Act applies; or 20(b) requiring the determination of any agreement to whichthe said Part I applies.(2) The Restrictive Practices Court may, upon application made by any person who desires to make any agreement which,if made, would be an agreement to which Part I of this Act 25applies, being an agreement the making of which is unlawfulby virtue of any order in force under the said section ten, dis-charge or vary that order so far as it appears to the court to be necessary to enable that agreement to be made if the Courtis satisfied that no restrictions proposed to be accepted under 30the agreement would be contrary to the public interest.(3) Where, before the commencement of this Act, any under-taking or assurance has been given by any person to a com-petent authority within the meaning of the said section ten thatany agreement (being an agreement to which Part I of this Act 35applies or would apply if the agreement were in force) will bedetermined, or will not be made (a) the provisions of subsection (2) of this section shallapply in relation to the undertaking or assurance as ifit were an order under the said section ten ; and 40(b) subject to any order made by the Court under the saidsubsection (2) as applied by the foregoing paragraph,ah order under the said section ten may, if the under-taking or assurance is not complied with, be made tothe like effect as the undertaking or assurance. 45Part III-cont.
(4) The Registrar shall be the respondent to any application A.D. 1956made under this section; and the provisions of section sixteen Part iii of this Act shall apply with the necessary modifications in rela-     -cont.tion to proceedings on any such application as they apply in  relation to the proceedings therein mentioned.(5) No application shall be made under this section until theexpiration of the period of three years beginning with the dateof the commencement of this Act.(6) Subsection (6) of section ten of the Act of 1948 (which10 provides for the revocation or variation of orders under that section) shall not apply to any order made under that sectionbefore the commencement of this Act.Part IVMiscellaneous and General15    2So (1) In relation to any agreement which is excepted by Provisionsvirtue of section six of this Act from the agreements to which relating to part I of this Act applies by reason of the fact that restrictions exPortaccepted thereunder relate exclusively to the supply of goods a8reemen s-by export from the United Kingdom, the provisions of sections20 seven, eight and eleven of this Act shall apply in relation toagreements to which this section applies as they apply in relationto agreements subject to registration under the said Part I, butas if for any reference in those provisions to the Registrar therewere substituted a reference to the Board of Trade, and sections25 twelve and thirteen of this Act shall apply accordingly.(2) Notwithstanding anything in section nine of the Mono-monopolies and Restrictive Practices (Inquiry and Control) Act, 1948,the Board of Trade shall not be required to lay before Parliamentany report made to them by the Monopolies Commission which30 relates exclusively to exports of goods from the United Kingdom,or any part of a report so made which exclusively tosuch exports, unless, according to the report, conditions to which that Act applies in fact prevail as respects those exports, andthose conditions, or things done as a result of, or for the purpose35 of preserving, those conditions, operate or may be expected to operate against the public interest.26.  (1) The number of puisne judges of the High Court who Increase ofmay be appointed under the Supreme Court of Judicature (Con- number ofsolidation) Act, 1925, shall be increased by three; and accord- coS^ncl40 ingly subsection (1) of section two of the said Act of 1925 and Court ofsubsections (1) and (2) of section one of the Supreme Court of Session.Judicature (Amendment) Act, 1944, shall have effect as if forthe word &quot; thirty-nine &quot; wherever that word occurs, there were substituted the word &quot; forty-two &quot;.
A.D. 1956       (2) The number of judges of the Court of Session who mayPart IV    be appointed shall be increased to sixteen, and accordingly cont.     subsection (1) of section one of the Administration of Justice(Scotland) Act, 1948, shall have effect as if for the word&quot; fifteen &quot; there were substituted the word &quot; sixteen &quot;. 5Restriction on 27. (1) No information with respect to any particular tradedisclosure of or business which has been obtained under or by virtue of this information. Act shall, so long as that trade or business continues to becarried on, be disclosed without the consent of the person for thetime being carrying on that trade or business, unless the dis- 10closure is for the purpose of facilitating the performance of anyfunctions of the Board of Trade or the Registrar under this Act,or under the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices (Inquiry andControl) Act, 1948, or for the purposes of, or of any report of,any proceedings before the Restrictive Practices Court or any ^other legal proceedings, whether civil or criminal, under thisAct or arising out of the carrying of this Act into effect.(2) Nothing in this section shall be construed as limiting the particulars which may be entered or filed in, or may be made public as part of, the register under Part I of this Act. 20(3) Any person who discloses any information in contraven-tion of this section shall be guilty of an offence, and shall be liable on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term notexceeding three months, or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such a fine, or on 25conviction on indictment to imprisonment for a term notexceeding two years or to a fine, or to both such imprisonmentand a fine.28. Anything required or authorised by or under this Act tobe done by, to or before the Board of Trade may be done by, 30to or before the President of the Board, any Minister of state with duties concerning the affairs of the Board, any Secretary,Under-Secretary, or Assistant Secretary of the Board, or anyperson authorised in that behalf by the President.Expenses, etc.     29. (1) There shall be defrayed out of moneys provided by 35Parliament (a) any sums required for the payment of remuneration orexpenses of the Registrar (including remuneration pay-able to Assistant Registrars or other officers or servants of the Registrar); 4q(b) any sums required for the payment of the remuneration of appointed members of the Restrictive PracticesCourt or of expenses of that Court (including remunera-tion of officers and servants of the Court);Proceedingsof Boardof Trade.
(c) any sums required for the payment of pensions, allow- A.D. 1956ances or gratuities, or contributions or other payments part IVtowards provision for pensions, allowances or gratuities,  cont.in respect of persons who have held office as Registrar5             or as appointed member of the said Court);(d) any increase attributable to this Act in the sums payableout of moneys provided as aforesaid under the Super-annuation Acts, 1834 to 1950.(2) There shall be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund and10 out of moneys provided by Parliament respectively any increaseattributable to section twenty-six of this Act in the sums requiredto be so defrayed.(3) Any fees received by the Registrar under this Act shallbe paid into the Exchequer.15    30. (1) In this Act the following expressions have the Interpretation,meanings hereby respectively assigned to them, that is to say:  &quot; enactment&quot; includes an enactment of the Parliament ofNorthern Ireland;&quot; goods &quot; includes ships and aircraft, minerals, substances20 and animals (including fish), and references to the pro-duction of goods include references to the getting of minerals and the taking of such animals;&quot; inter-connected bodies corporate &quot; means bodies corpor-ate which are members of the same group, and for the25 purposes of this definition &quot; group &quot; means a body corporate and all other bodies corporate which are itssubsidiaries within the meaning of section one hundredand fifty-four of the Companies Act, 1948 ;&quot; price &quot; includes a charge of any description ;2Q       &quot; the Registrar &quot; means the registrar appointed under Part Iof this Act;&quot; supply &quot; includes supply by way of lease or hire, and&quot; acquire &quot; shall be construed accordingly.(2) This Act applies to buildings, structures and other works,35 and to the construction or carrying out of buildings, structuresand other works by contractors, as it applies to goods and thesupply of goods.(3) For the purposes of this Act a person shall not be deemedto carry on a business within the United Kingdom by reason40 only of the fact that he is represented for the purposes of thatbusiness by an agent within the United Kingdom.121 D
(c) any sums required for the payment of pensions, allow- A.d. 1956ances or gratuities, or contributions or other payments Part IVtowards provision for pensions, allowances or gratuities,      cont.in respect of persons who have held office as Registrar5             or as appointed member of the said Court) ;(d) any increase attributable to this Act in the sums payableout of moneys provided as aforesaid under the Super-annuation Acts, 1834 to 1950.(2) There shall be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund and10 out of moneys provided by Parliament respectively any increaseattributable to section twenty-six of this Act in the sums requiredto be so defrayed.(3) Any fees received by the Registrar under this Act shallbe paid into the Exchequer.15    30. (1) In this Act the following expressions have the Interpretation,meanings hereby respectively assigned to them, that is to say:  &quot; enactment&quot; includes an enactment of the Parliament ofNorthern Ireland;&quot; goods &quot; includes ships and aircraft, minerals, substances20 and animals (including fish), and references to the pro-duction of goods include references to the getting of minerals and the taking of such animals;&quot; inter-connected bodies corporate &quot; means bodies corpor-ate which are members of the same group, and for the25 purposes of this definition &quot; group &quot; means a body corporate and all other bodies corporate which are itssubsidiaries within the meaning of section one hundredand fifty-four of the Companies Act, 1948 ;&quot; price &quot; includes a charge of any description ;3Q       &quot; the Registrar &quot; means the registrar appointed under Part Iof this Act;&quot; supply &quot; includes supply by way of lease or hire, and&quot; acquire &quot; shall be construed accordingly.(2) This Act applies to buildings, structures and other works,35 and to the construction or carrying out of buildings, structuresand other works by contractors, as it applies to goods and thesupply of goods.(3) For the purposes of this Act a person shall not be deemedto carry on a business within the United Kingdom by reason40 only of the fact that he is represented for the purposes of thatbusiness by an agent within the United Kingdom.121 d
Applicationto NorthernIreland.Short title and com-mencement.(4) Any reference in this Act to any other enactment is a reference thereto as amended, and includes a reference thereto as extended or applied, by or under any subsequent enactment,including this Act.31__(1) It is  hereby declared that this Act extends to   5Northern Ireland, but the Parliament of Northern Ireland shallhave the same power to pass Acts with respect to any matter asthey would have had if this Act had not passed and, in the eventof any inconsistency between any Act of the Parliament ofNorthern Ireland duly passed after the passing of this Act and 10any provision of or any order or other instrument under thisAct, the Act of the Parliament of Northern Ireland shall, inNorthern Ireland, prevail.(2) In the application of this Act to Northern Ireland &quot; sum-mary conviction&quot; means conviction in accordance with the 15enactments (including enactments of the Parliament of NorthernIreland) for the time being in force in Northern Ireland relatingto summary jurisdiction.32. (1) This Act may be cited as the Restrictive trade practices Act, 1956. 20(2) This Act (except section twenty-two) shall come into force on the day of nineteenhundred and fifty-six.Part IV cont.
9SCHEDULE a.d.Section 2.Supplementary Provisions as to Proceedings of restrictive Practices CourtI. The Court may sit at such times and in such place or places in any part of the United Kingdom as may be most con-venient for the determination of proceedings before it.2. The central office of the Court shall be in London ; and theCourt when sitting in public in London shall sit at the Royal courts of Justice, or at such other place as the Lord Chancellor may from10 time to time appoint.3. The Court may sit either as a single court or in two or more divisions concurrently and either in private or in open court.4. For the hearing of any proceedings the Court shall consist ofa judge, who shall be president, and at least two other members.15 5. On the hearing of any proceedings, the opinion of the judgeor judges sitting as members of the Court upon any question of lawshall prevail; but except as aforesaid the decision of the Court shallbe taken by all the members sitting, or, in the event of a difference of opinion by the votes of the majority of those members, and, in20 the event of an equality of votes, the president shall be entitled toa second or casting vote.6. The judgment of the Court in any proceedings shall be delivered by the president.7. The decision of the Court on a question of fact shall be final:25 but an appeal shall lie on any question of law from any decisionor order of the Court (a) in the case of proceedings in England and Wales or inNorthern Ireland, to the Court of Appeal;(6) in the case of proceedings in Scotland, to the Court of30 Session.8. Any appeal under the last foregoing paragraph to the Courtof Session shall be by way of stated case.9. The Court shall not have power to award any sum by wayof costs to any party to proceedings before it.35    10. Subject to the provisions of this Schedule the Court shall (a) for the purposes of proceedings in England and Wales or inNorthern Ireland, have the same powers, rights, privileges and authority and observe the same practice with regard tothe right of audience as a judge of the High Court;40 (b) for the purposes of proceedings in Scotland have the same powers, rights, privileges and authority and observe thesame practice with regard to the right of audience as a judge of the Court of Session.II. No person shall be punished for contempt of the Court45 except by or with the consent of a judge who is a member of theCourt.
CONFIDENTIALRestrictive Trade PracticesDRAFTo f aBILLTo provide for the registration of certainrestrictive trading agreements, and forthe prohibition of such agreements whencontrary to the public interest ; to prohibit the collective enforcement of conditions regulating the resale price ofgoods, and to make further provisionfor the individual enforcement of suchconditions by legal proceedings; toamend the Monopolies and restrictive practices Acts, 1948 and 1953; toprovide for the appointment of additional judges of the High Court; and of theCourt of Session; and for other purposesconnected with the matters aforesaid.CCCLXXI K (7)Wth February, 1956121-7(38838)

</content>
</cab>
