<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/79/0 images: 211-213</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP, (56) 3 5 COPY NO.   Lf^t13 th P ?february, 1956CABINETFAMILY ALLOWANCES (AMENDMENT) bill memorandum by the Minister of Pensions and National InsuranceAt the suggestion of the Lord Privy Seal, I am circulatingparticulars of the Family Allowances (Amendment) Bill, and the argument in favour of its early introduction.A&quot;   OBJECTS OF THE DILL2.      The Bill has seven clauses of which three are substantive and therest consequential or formal.     Its main object is to extend the payment of family allowances for children at school up to their 10th birthdays, witha similar extension for apprentices.The present position is that family allowance stops at the normalschool-leaving age (15) except where the child continues at school or isan apprentice, when the allowance is paid up to the 31st July following the 16th birthday.3,      In addition, the Bill will carry out Parliamentary pledges toextend the age to 16 for handicapped children who cannot go to school.4.      It will legalise an existing local authority practice of allowingchildren committed to care to go home for trial periods, and it willprovide family allowances for such periods,    (This was part of an other-wise unacceptable Private Memberfs Bill which Mr, John Tilney introduced in January, 1955, and later agreed to withdraw).5.      Finally, the Bill will remove an unfortunate limitation on ourpowers to reach reciprocal agreements with other countries.6.      The reasons why it is in my view important to proceed with this bill this session are:-(a) because we have repeatedly committed ourselves todoing so;(b) it will bring relief to an important section of the communitywho are either keeping their children voluntarily at school or fitting them for skilled work by apprenticingthem to a trade.-1 -
icqIda-I-  Notably in reply to Questions from Dr. King (31.5.54), Mr. J.B, Hynd(21. 2. 55) and Mr. Oliver (14. 3. 55).7.      The history of the matter is sot out below.8,      The Conservative Party:s Election Manifesto, which was published in April, 1955, included the following reference in the section on&quot;Education&quot;:-    &quot;We accept the case that family allowances should be paid as long as a child is at school&quot;.9.      The Cabinet on 2nd June, 1955, agreed that certain Bills,including the Family Allowances Bill, should constitute the main features of the legislative programme for the present session (C.M.(55) 11thConclusions, Minute 4).10.    The Queen&apos;s Speech at the Cpening of Parliament (9th June, 1955)said   &quot;A Bill will be laid before you to extend the period during whichfamily allowances are payable for children who remain at school&quot;,(Hansard, Col. 44).11 o    During the Debate on the Address, Dr. Edith Surnmerskillreferred to the Government&apos;s promise in The Queen&apos;s Speech and she andother Members asked for the clarification of certain points.    In replyMr. Peake, as he then was,  stated that the Government had in mind that the age limit should be raised to 18, and that &quot;certainly we are goingto make some provision in the Bill for handicapped children, in respectof whom I have given undertakings previously in the House&quot;&apos;&quot;......&quot;.He went on,    &quot;We shall prepare our proposals and the House will see thesejust as soon as the Bill can be introduced,     I cannot, however, hold out any hope of it being introduced before we adjourn for the sumrrer recess. . . %(Hansard, Col. 447).1Z0    On 5th July Mr. Peake put his proposals before the Home AffairsCommittee   (H0F.(55) 25).     These weie approved by the Committee on0th July (H0P0(55.) 6th Meeting, Minute 3), and he was authorised toprepare the necessary legislation.    On 15th July the Cabinet invited theMinisters concerned &quot;to continue their efforts to ensure that the family allowances Bill was introduced before Parliament rose for the summer recess&quot;.     (C0M. (55) 22nd Conclusions, Minute 7).13.    In the Debate on Economic and Financial Policy (31st October, 1955)the Prime Minister saicls-&quot;Ngw about the question which the R.T.. hon. Gentleman (Mr. Herbert Morrison)has asked about the various undertakings wehave given and where we stand in respect ofthem.....Extension of family allowances.A.s long as the child is at school, thatstands.....&quot;.    (Hansard, Col. 799).14.    On 4th July, 21st November and 5th December,  1955,Parliamentary Questions were asked about.handicapped children or thosestaying at school after 16.    (Hansard, Cols. 746, V/. 74 and W. 16).    Inhis replies Mr. Peake referred to his statement in the Debate on theA.ddress and in one instance to the Prime Minister&apos;s statement on31st October also.
15.    Generally I would acid that the Bill (with the possible exceptionof the Agriculture (Safety, Health and Welfare Provisions) Bill) was the major measure of social legislation included in The Queen&apos;s Speech,and that my Department has received a considerable amount of corres-330nden.ee from M,P. &apos;s and others which shows that the measure iseagerly awaited by many parents.c0 go:;t.16.    The immediate cost to the Exchequer is not likely to exceed 2 millions with a further  ^ million on the National Insurance funds for dependent children and widowed mothers.    Since the Bill was approvedby the Legislation Committee the Government Actuary has been able tomake a closer estimate of the future cost to those Funds and is now ofthe opinion that it will reach  If millions in 25 years&apos; time (instead of Z-g- millions in 15-20 years&apos; time)*D.   DATE OF OPERATION17.    In order to prevent anomalies the change with respect to family allowances should come into operation on 1st August, that is on the dayfollowing the date (31st July) on which a number of children would other-wise cease to be eligible for allowances.J.A.B-C.Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance,W.C.2.11th February, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
