<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/79/0 images: 363-367</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
LEGISLATION TO ABOLISH THE DEATH penalty for MURDERMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the home department and Minister for Welsh -affairs have been thinking over the problem that confronts us as a result ofthe rejection of the Governments advice on capital punishment.    It seems tome very difficult for us to introduce a Government Bill to abolish the death penalty.    I do not see how we could advocate a step which we have sorecently urged the House, for reasons which still seem to me to be cogent,to reject.    I think that people outside the House who are against abolitionwould be very critical if we executed a volte face of this kind;   and we should put those of our supporters who voted with us in an impossible position if,having urged them to vote according to conscience on the motion, we put theWhips on to compel them to vote in support of the Bill.2,      I believe that it would be more in keeping with the realities of thesituation to take the line that this is a matter which the House, by defeatingthe Governments motion on a free vote, has taken out of the hands of theGovernment and that it is, therefore, appropriate that the Bill should benot a Government Bill but a House of Commons Bill sponsored by those on both sides of the House who were successful in carrying the abolitionistamendment.    Mr. Silverman&apos;s Bill, a copy of which is attached, is backed by, among others, Mr. Chuter Ede and Mr. Clement Davies, and I seenothing undignified or inappropriate in finding time for a measure which haswide and respected support.    It seems to me far better for the Governmentto make way gracefully for those who believe in abolition than to put ourselveinto the equivocal position of sponsoring a measure which we have made itperfectly clear we consider to be contrary to the best interests of thecountry.3.      Whatever we decide about legislation, I have no doubt that I shall beexpected to make a statement on the exercise of the Prerogative.    I cannotabrogate capital punishment by administrative action in anticipation of achange in the law and I cannot announce that a reprieve will be recommended in every case.    I must continue to consider each case on its merits, but Ishall give full weight to considerations arising out of the uncertainty aboutthe future of the death penalty.4.     I propose, therefore, to make a statement on the following lines&quot;It would be wrong for the Secretary of State for Scotlandand me to abrogate capital punishment by administrative action in anticipation of the amendment of the law or to fail to apply our minds to the circumstances of each particular case.    In consider-(THIS^DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF PIER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government secret,P0(56) 43 COPY NO.   5 021st February, 1956CABINET
ing, as each case comes before us, whether to recommend the exercise of the Royal Prerogative of Mercy, we shall continue to give full weight to all relevant considerations,including the views on the subject of capital punishmentexpressed in this House. &quot;5.      This was the line taken by Mr, Chuter Ede in 1948 (Official Reportof 10th June, Col. 2304  et seq), after he had realised that his originalstatement of his intention to recommend a reprieve in all future cases wasuncons titutional.6.      Before I make a statement in Parliament I think it would be right for me to inform Her Majesty.7.      I recommend that we should announce our readiness to give time toMr, Silverman&apos;s Bill and that so far as the exercise of the Prerogative isconcerned I should make a statement in the House on the lines proposed inparagraph 4 above.G. LiJL. -G.Home Office, S. W. 1.21st February, 1956.
Wuz. 2Death Penalty (Abolition)1ABILT OAbolish or for a period suspend the passing and   a.d. 1956execution of the death sentence on conviction of murder and to substitute an alternative penalty therefor.BE it enacted by the Queen&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and Commons, in this present parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5    1. (1) During the continuance in force of this Act, no person Abolitionshall be sentenced by a court to death for murder; and every of deathenactment requiring a court to pronounce or record a sentence penalty.of death in any case of murder shall be construed as requiring the court to sentence the offender to imprisonment for life.10 (2) Nothing in this Act shall affect the provisions of sectionfifty-three of the Children and Young Persons Act, 1933 (whichprohibits the passing of sentence of death against a person under the age of eighteen years, and requires the court, in lieuthereof, to sentence him to be detained during Her Majesty&apos;s15 Pleasure).(3) In the application of this Act to Scotland the reference tosentencing to imprisonment for life shall be construed as a reference to sentencing to penal servitude for life, and for the reference to the Children and Young Persons Act, 1933, and20 section fifty-three thereof there shall be substituted a referenceto the Children and Young Persons (Scotland) Act, 1937, and section fifty-seven thereof.[Bill 50]
Death Penalty (Abolition)2. (1) This Act may be cited as the Death Penalty (Abolition)Act, 1956.(2) This Act shall continue in force for a period beginning with the passing of this Act and ending as hereinafter provided.(3) If at any time not earlier than a period of five years 5beginning with the passing of this Act an Address is presented to Her Majesty by each House of Parliament praying that thisAct shall not continue in force beyond such date as shall betherein specified Her Majesty may by Order in Council make provision for that purpose, and this Act shall expire on such date 10as such Order in Council may appoint but without prejudice tothe validity of anything previously done thereunder, but if nosuch Order in Council is made within a period of ten yearsbeginning with the passing of this Act then this Act shall there-after continue in force without limitation of time. 15a.D. 1956Short title,commence-ment and duration.Death Penalty (Abolition)ABILLTo abolish or for a period suspend thepassing and execution of the death sentence on conviction of murder andto substitute an alternative penaltytherefor.Ordered to be brought in byMr. Sydney Silverman, Mr. Ede,Mr. Clement Davies, Mr. Bevan,Mr. Montgomery Hyde, Mr. Paton,Mr. Daines, Dr. Barnett Stross,Mr. Wedgwood Bemi, Mr. Paget,Sir Beverley Baxter and Mr. WadeOrdered, by The House of Commons,to be printed, 15 November 1955londonprinted and published by her majestvs stationery office price 3d. net[Bill 50](38749)
Death Penalty (Abolition)2. (1) This Act may be cited as the Death Penalty (Abolition)Act, 1956.(2) This Act shall continue in force for a period beginning with the passing of this Act and ending as hereinafter provided.(3) If at any time not earlier than a period of five years 5beginning with the passing of this Act an Address is presented to Her Majesty by each House of Parliament praying that thisAct shall not continue in force beyond such date as shall betherein specified Her Majesty may by Order in Council make provision for that purpose, and this Act shall expire on such date 10as such Order in Council may appoint but without prejudice tothe validity of anything previously done thereunder, but if nosuch Order in Council is made within a period of ten yearsbeginning with the passing of this Act then this Act shall there-after continue in force without limitation of time. 15A.D. 1956Short title,commence-ment and duration.Deatlr Penalty (Abolition)BILLTo abolish or for a period suspend thepassing and execution of the death sentence on conviction of murder andto substitute an alternative penaltytherefor.Ordered to be brought in byMr. Sydney Silverman, Mr. Ede,Mr. Clement Davies, Mr. Bevan,Mr. Montgomery Hyde, Mr. Paton,Mr. Daines, Dr. Barnett Stross,Mr. Wedgwood Benn, Mr. Paget,Sir Beverley Baxter and Mr. WadeOrdered, by The House of Commons,to be printed, 15 November 1955londonprinted and published by her majestvs stationery office price 3d. net[Bill 50](38749)

</content>
</cab>
