<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/54/16 images: 190-208</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CC(74) 16thConclusionsCOPY no cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 16 MAY 1974at 10. 00 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon ShirTsy Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs (Items 1-3)The Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for Energy&apos;&apos;Tj&apos;-&apos;.: \\ jThe Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science
0The Rt Hon Merlyn Rees MP The Rt Hon Fred Peart mp secretary of State for Northern Ireland Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy seal the FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Samuel Silkin QC MP The Rt Hon Judith Hart mp attorney General (Items 1-4) Minister of Overseas Development (ItemThe Rt Hon Robert Mellish mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat sir John hunt mr P D Nairne (Items 3 and 8)Mr H F T Smith (Items 1, 2 and 3)Mr P Banner (Items 4, 5 and 7)Mr J A Hamilton (Item 6)Mr J Anson (Item 6)Mr J Roberts (Items 1 and 2)Mr K R Stowe (Items 4 and 5)Mr D Evans (Item 3)Mr R B S Johnston (Item 8)contents item Subject page 1.        CHILE 1.2.        SUPPLY OF WASP HELICOPTER TO SOUTH AFRICA 43.        FOREIGN affairs middle East 5Soviet Union 5European Community: Renegotiation 54. PARLIAMENTARY affairs debate on National Health Service Pay 8Members&apos; Outside Financial Interests 85.        SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF MEMBERS OFPARLIAMENT 96.        TOP SALARIES REVIEW BODY 107.        POLITICAL ACTIVITIES OF SPECIAL ADVISERS to ministers 118.        ROAD TANKER DRIVERS 13iiSECRET
1.        The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Secretaryof State for Industry (C(74) 31) on the overhauling of aero engines for Hunter aircraft; by the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary(C(74) 32) on the attitude of the United States Government; and bythe Attorney General (C(74) 44) on the legal issues involved.    they also had before them a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet(C(74) 36) covering a factual paper by officials.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that in his memorandum he proposed that Rolls Royce (1971) Ltd (RR(71))should be told to notify the Chilean Government that they werenot able to continue engine overhauls or to supply further spares;that the engines with RR(71) or in transit should be returnedunoverhauled; and that if necessary we should cancel, refuse, ormodify export licences.    The factual note by officials showed that although the manufacturers (Hawker Siddeley) had certain obligations to provide spare parts for the airframes of the Hunteraircraft, there was no Government responsibility.    There were some outstanding orders covering airframe and associatedequipment.    It had been argued that by preventing the enginesbeing overhauled and spares for them being supplied, the prospects for arms sales in other countries might be harmed; and he recognised that legal considerations must also be taken intoaccount, although it seemed that these might not present greatdifficulty.    But the decision to be taken was essentially a politicalone.    Great political difficulties would arise if the government decided that the arrangements should continue.    The problem would be partly solved if the Chileans were to decide of their own accord to take back the engines awaiting overhaul; as hiscolleagues would have seen from a letter from the Head of the chilean Air Force Mission in London to RR(71), this might be their intention.THE ATTORNEY GENERAL agreed that if the Chileans asked forthe engines to be returned in their present state this would be helpful.    The Chilean letter had become available after he had prepared his advice, which therefore rested on the assumptionthat the Chileans would not be co-operative.    The proposals putforward by the Secretary of State.for Industry presented consider-able legal difficulties.    If the Government attempted to persuadeRR(71) to break their contract it would lay itself open to the riskof action for damages.    There would be no objection to invitingRR(71) to exercise such rights as they might have to bring the contract to an end; but this would not have the immediate effectof stopping the overhaul and ending the supply of spares.    Therewas provision to terminate the contract for overhauling at 3 monthsnotice but if RR(71) availed themselves of this provision theywould remain obliged to complete the overhaul of the enginesalready in their hands and to overhaul any further engines thatmight be delivered to them within the three months period.    The
contract contained no break clause in respect of the supply of spares, and although it might be argued that it would be reasonable to end this obligation on one year&apos;s notice (or possiblyless if it could be shown that the Chileans could obtain sparesfrom some other country) the obligation to continue to providespares would remain in force during the period of notice.    if both the overhauling and supply of spares were to be stoppedimmediately, this would require the exercise of the Government&apos;power to control exports.    There was a bare possibility thatgovernmental intervention of this kind would render us liable tolegal action and it would be important to consider how to apply the controls in such a way as to reduce this risk to a minimum.He would remind his colleagues, however, that the previousLabour Administration had enabled the Chilean Government toobtain the Hunters, by arranging for the release of the aircraft from the Royal Air Force.    In 1969 we had in fact encouragedChile to buy the aircraft, and fundamentally to change our positionin 1974 because there has been a change of regime in Chile coulddangerously undermine ourdnternational reputation for good faith.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that hewas unable to support the proposals of the Secretary of State for industry.    He was concerned at the consequences of such a courseboth for our international interests and for the domestic situation.The Government had shown very clearly by the measures it hadalready taken what it felt about the present Chilean regime.    the pressure now being exerted upon the Government in regard to theaircraft and warships came from a relatively limited sector ofopinion.    If this minority were to prevail, the Government wouldin future be vulnerable to further pressures of the same kind on  .other issues.    Our reputation for reliability would be damaged.The right course was to maintain that contracts in force must behonoured.    The Government should not therefore ask RR(71) tobreak their contracts; nor should we use the weapon of export control, which would also have the probable result of attractingChilean retaliation.    The correct course was to ask RR(71) to eiidtheir contractual obligation as soon as possible: they should avail themselves of the right to terminate on three months&apos; notice their?contract to overhaul the engines, and they should seek to terminate their obligations to provide spares within the shortest possible time.    We should not ask RR(71) to refrain from meetingsuch obligations as would remain during the period of notice.    Asregards the indication that the Chilean Government might baconsidering asking for the engines to be returned in their present state, he was not in favour of an official approach to the Chileansabout this.
In discussion it was argued that the stand which had been taken by &apos;the Labour Party when in Opposition was unequivocal and that it was politically necessary for the Government to act accordingly.    Thedecision to allow the warships to go to Chile was considered wrongby many of the Governments supporters, and if we continued tohelp the Chilean Air Force there would be deep resentment.    the argument that if we took action against Chile this would haverepercussive effects on our trade with other countries was open to challenge: Chile was clearly a special case, but even if we were,obliged to make some sacrifices, they should be accepted.    It wasalso suggested, however, that the attitude of Union members was by no means monolithic: some Unions did not agree with the callby the Amalgamated Union of Engineering Workers (AUEW) to withhold labour from the warships, and the call had been rejected by a considerable number of AUEW members.    It was also argued that although we ourselves considered Chile to be an exceptionalcase, other potential customers might assume that whenever a country incurred the hostility of a sufficiently influential section ofopinion here, contracts between us and that country were liable to be broken.    It was noted that whatever course was taken ir relation tothe contract to overhaul the engines, the workers at East Kilbridewould probably continue to refuse to carry out the work,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that it was generally agreed in principle that any provision of arms and equip-ment to the Chilean Air Force should be brought to an end as soon aspossible.    The question for decision was the means by which thisshould be done.    It was desirable to avoid Government interventionsince this could damage our international standing as reliabletrading partners, and could lead to legal difficulties.    We should therefore try to get RR(71) to give the necessary three months&apos;notice to terminate their obligation to overhaul engines, and theircontractual obligations to provide spare parts should also be broughtto an end as soon as possible.    If the obligation could be terminatedin this way, within the contractual framework, there would be far less reason to fear adverse repercussions on bur international trade.    If RR(71) were unwilling to proceed in this way, or if arrangements for terminating the obligation to supply spares withina reasonable time could not be agreed, the Cabinet would have to review .the position again.    He and the Ministers immediately concerned would consider the public presentation of the decision reached.The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.2.      Invited the Secretary of State for Industry to proceedwith RR(71) accordingly.
2;        The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the attorney general (C(74) 39) on the legal aspects of the supply of aWestlandWasp helicopter to South Africa together with a noteby the Secretary of the Cabinet (C(74) 40) circulating a paper by officials on the factual background to the sale.THE ATTORNEY GENERAL said that in 1971 the South african government had ordered 7 West land Wasp helicopters.    Theorder was placed after the Conservative Government had announced their acceptance of the advice of the Law Officers ofthe day, which had been published as a White Paper (Cmnd 4589)that they were under an obligation to permit the export of Wasphelicopters to equip the three frigates supplied under the simonstown Agreement.    Six of these helicopters had been delivered.    The seventh was due to be completed in June and an export licence, issued by the previous Administration, was heldby the South African Embassy, .  He had been asked -whether the revocation of this export licence would be consistent with ourlegal obligations.    He adhered to the view, expressed by the ShadowLaw Officers at the time, that the Opinion of the ConservativeLaw Officers in 1971 overstated our legal obligations under the simonstown Agreement.   But events since then had altered thelegal position.    In his opinion the revocation of the export licence for the Wasp helicopter would conflict with our internationallegal obligations, and he could not advise that the licence be revoked or that any steps be taken to prevent delivery of thehelicopter.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a short discussion, said thatin view of the clear warning he and his colleagues had given when in opposition, that if the Conservative Government decided to sellarms to South Africa an incoming Labour-Government wouldrepudiate the contracts, the South African Government were awarewhen they concluded the contract that it would be at risk.    TheCabinet agreed that the licence should be revoked.    We must bearin mind the strong feeling in Black Africa.    He would consider further, in consultation with the Foreign and commonwealth secretary, how this decision might best be announced; it mightbe convenient to combine this with an announcement on the supplyof equipment to Chile.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.
3. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat the efforts of the American Secretary of State, Dr Kissinger,to secure an arrangement between Israel and Syria which would end the fighting, had reached a delicate stage and it was notpossible to predict the outcome.    The shocking events of theprevious day, when many schoolchildren were killed or woundedafter being taken hostage by Arab terrorists, were no doubtintended to frustrate Dr Kissinger&apos;s mission, and would certainly have set it back.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that inrecent conversation with the Soviet Ambassador the PrimeMinister and he had taken a firm line, in the context of improvingrelations, about the difficulty encountered by our ambassador in Moscow in obtaining access to the Soviet leaders.    our ambassador had been received by the Soviet Foreign Minister,Mr Gromyko, the previous day and was seeing the Soviet PrimeMinister, Mr Kosygin, that day.    There were also indications of improved prospects for trade with the Soviet Union.The Cabinet -1.      Took note of the statements by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY recalled that he had reported to the Cabinet on 2 May the conclusions reached by the Ministerial Committee on European CommunityStrategy (ECS) on the principal elements in the renegotiationpackage which we should seek from the Community.    Thesecovered fairer treatment for the United Kingdom in the community budget; the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) and the measuresof reform, access and price arrangements we should seek; andour trade and aid objectives in relation to Commonwealth and developing countries.    He had informed the Cabinet that bilateralconsultations with both Community and Commonwealth countries would be undertaken at official level.    Of the community countries, only France had refused to take part in bilateral discussions and this was perhaps understandable in view of thepresent stage of the Presidential Election.    Bilaterals had now taken place with all the other Community countries; we had explained in detail our case for a change in our contribution to theCommunity budget, but for tactical reasons we had held in reserve
the substance of the solutions we might propose.    He would circulate in due course a full analysis of the outcome of the consultations with Commonwealth countries.    Very briefly the overall impression was that the Commonwealth approached ourideas on renegotiation with no sentiment and we must expect hardbargaining, particularly on  tie questions of getting better access to the United Kingdom and to the Community markets, and ofsecuring remunerative prices.    Both the New Zealand Governmentand the countries of the Commonwealth Sugar Agreement (CSA) had now decided to send representatives to this country for further discussions.The next stage in the renegotiation process would be the meetingof the Council of Ministers (Foreign Affairs) in Luxembourg on  June.    Both from the bilateral consultations which had been taking place, and from a recent meeting with M Ortoli, thePresident of the Commission, it seemed unlikely that the council would be able on that occasion to go further than to discuss the procedures for handling renegotiation.    There would be further work during the summer, but serious negotiation could not beexpected until the autumn.The ECS Committee had now been able to consider thoroughlyfurther matters relating to renegotiation arising on Regional andIndustrial Policies.    The Committee had concluded that we shouldbe ready to continue to discuss the proposed Regional development fund (RDF) if other Governments wished, partly because the Fundmight be of value to the United Kingdom and partly because  theestablishment of a satisfactory RDF was an important objectivefor the Italian and Irish Governments and it would be tacticallywrong to forfeit their goodwill during the renegotiation period byblocking progress.    But we should have to make it clear that wewould not expect final decisions to be taken before we could see theprobable outcome of renegotiation, notably on the Community Budget.The Committee had considered Regional Aids against the background of experience relating to our own aid policies.    It was considered in our interest to participate in the Community Working Party witha view to securing our own objectives in the context of formulatingrules on regional aid for the Community as a whole.    We should need to obtain satisfactory results, and to ensure that we achievedadequate flexibility for our future policies; we should continue to reserve our position on the right to propose Treaty amendment if our essential needs could not otherwise be met.    We should alsoundertake a deeper study of the problem of capital movements,which had potentially important implications for regional policies.Our approach on industrial policy should be to explain to theCouncil that, while we did not wish to harm other community countries, the British Government was committed to an inter-ventionist policy and would require assurances about the way in
which the Treaties and the Community rules might be applied toour industrial measures and, in particular, to our policies for steel.    The Secretary of State for Industry would be discussingour objectives in a constructive way with the Commission.In the light of this ECS discussion he proposed in outlining furtherour renegotiating objectives at the Council Meeting on 4 June tosay that Community Regional and Industrial Policies raisedimportant problems for this country, and that they must therefore have a central place in renegotiation.    He would continueto keep the.Cabinet informed as to the further stages in the renegotiation process.    In the meantime the Legislation -Committee under the chairmanship of the Lord President would begetting on with the task of examining the role of Parliament in thegeneral context of our renegotiation policy.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said theCabinet was in general agreement with the approach to the next stage of renegotiation.    The detailed and tactical presentation ofour case must now be left for the Foreign and commonwealth secretary to settle, although he would of course consult hiscolleagues directly concerned as appropriate.    Since we were nowin a situation of continuing negotiation it would not be appropriate for the Foreign and Commonwealth secretary&apos;s statement in theCouncil on 4 June to be issued as a White Paper although it might be useful to make it available to the Press.The Cabinet -2.      Took note with approval of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of the discussion.3.      Invited the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretaryto be guided accordingly.
f&quot;i ...PARLIAMENTARY     4, The Cabinet were informed of the business to be takenAFFAIRS in the House of Commons during the following week.    It was proposed that the House should adjourn for the Whitsun Recesson 24 May and resume on 10 June.Debate on national health service PayIt was important to avoid giving the impression that any decisionto set up an independent inquiry into nurses1 pay had been takenin response to pressure from the Opposition, and it wastherefore desirable that any such decision should be reached in time for an announcement to be made during, or in advanceof, the debate on National Health Service pay which was to takeplace on 23 May after the conclusion of the debate on the Motionto adjourn for the Whits un Recess.    There was a good prospect that this could be arranged, although there would have to befurther discussions with the Trades Union Congress and careful thought would have to be given to the danger ofrepercussions and to the poSsible heed for parallel action inrelation to other groups - for example, teachers.    If necessary,a report on the outcome of this further work, might be made tothe Cabinet on the.morning of 23 May so that the Secretary ofState for Social Services would be able to meet representativesof the Staff Side, that afternoon and then make an announcement in the course of the Debate.    On this basis it did not seem necessary to alter the arrangements for the Prime Minister tomeet representatives hi the nurses on 20 May.    It was reported that the provisions which had been included in many payagreements for increases to be made in pay in response to increases in the retail price index above a certain level were likely to come into effect shortly.    The Ministers concerned would be giving careful thought to the very difficultpresentational problems which would arise and should report their conclusions to the Prime Minister.     ,:,Members1 OutsideFinancialIntereststPreviousReference:CC(74) 15thConclusions,Minute 2THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that he had put the Cabinets proposals concerning a register of Members1interests to the Parliamentary Labour Party at its meetingon Wednesday evening, when they had been agreed.    It would,however, be necessary for the draft of the resolution setting upthe Select Committee which had been circulated at that meeting to be extended, so that it could meet all the proceduralrequirements for such a proposal.    Mr Hamilton had carriedan amendment at the Party meeting specifically applying theregister to the Lords and to lobby correspondents.    But itwould be imprudent to do this without prior consideration by the 8
Select Committee and, with the agreement of the Chairman ofthe Parliamentary Labour Party, he proposed not to embodythis amendment in the Governments resolutions.    Instead the revised version would require the Select Committee to consider what classes of person (if any) other than Members ought to berequired to register.    As to timing, he expected the SelectCommittee to report very quicikly on that part of their remitconcerned with registrable interests: he did not consider it practicable to tie them to a specific date but in his speech onthe resolutions he would make it clear that the House should havereceived and, if possible, have considered the Committee&apos;sreport on these aspects before the Summer Recess.    The reporton the possible extension of registration beyond Members might take longer to prepare.    He proposed to table the resolutionsthat evening and they would be taken on Wednesday 22 May on a free vote.The Cabinet -Took note.5.        The Cabinet considered a memorandum by theLord President of the Council (C(74) 42) about the salaries and allowances of Members of Parliament.THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that there was great pressure from Members for some increase to be made intheir salaries and allowances, the current rates of which were introduced in January 1972 following the review undertaken by the top Salaries Review Body (TSRB).    The report of the TSRB had then said that such reviews should take place only at intervals of about four years, corresponding roughly to the lifetime of p.Parliament of normal length, although intermediateadjustments were not excluded.    He did not think it right inpresent conditions to initiate another general review ofMembers&apos; salaries and allowances but he proposed that the TSRBshould be asked to carry out a limited review of the levels of the allowances, which were demonstrably inadequate.    TheChairman of TSRB had informally agreed that if asked the TSRBcould carry out such a review very quickly.    If the cabinet agreed, he proposed to make an early announcement of thislimited reference to TSRB.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, saidthat the Cabinet agreed that the TSRB should be asked to under-take a speedy and limited review of the level of Members1allowances, and that no commitment should be entered into inrespect of Members1 salaries.    Even a move towards increases9CQNF5DESMTIAL
in allowances would be sensitive politically and it would be helpful therefore to give prominence to the very real problemsof Members&apos; secretaries, whose current salaries were inadequate but could only be increased at the expense ofMembers themselves.    There was a case for a fundamentalreview of the way in which provision was made for Members&apos;secretaries; but it would be premature to enter into any commitment to this, especially since discussions were currentlytaking place with the Opposition about financial assistance to opposition parties, which might well include inter aliaprovision for adequate secretarial and research support in adifferent form from the present secretarial allowance.    Asregards the Lords, an increase in the Lords&apos; attendance allowance should also be considered and an announcement to this effect be made simultaneously with an announcement of the TSRBreference on Members^ allowances.    There was, however, acase for considering such an increase in the context of establishing a closer relationship between entitlement to the allowance andthe actual incurring of expenses; and the Lord Privy Seal andthe Lord President should examine the matter further.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion and invited theLord President to proceed accordingly, in consultationwith the Lord Privy Seal on peers&apos; allowances.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by theLord President of the Council. Their discussion and theconclusions reached are recorded separately.10
7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the PrimeMinister about the rules governing the political activities ofspecial advisers to Ministers (C(74) 41).THE PRIME MINISTER said that hitherto the rules governing thepolitical activities of civil servants had applied also to special .advisers.    This meant that an adviser should not allow himself to be adopted as a Parliamentary candidate without first resigninghis appointment as an adviser or making arrangements to beremunerated from other than public funds, and that he shouldnot offer himself for election or serve as a member of a localauthority while paid from public funds.    These rules had in thepast been applied strictly, and in 1971, as a result of Questionswhich he himself nad asked in the House of Commons, an adviserappointed by the previous Administration had resigned hismembership of a local authority.    There were at present two ministers with special advisers who were members of localauthorities, and the question arose whether the application ofthe existing rules to advisers should not be reviewed, bearing inmind the more extensive appointment of such advisers by governments of either political complexion, and the changingpublic attitude, particularly following the Fulton Report, towardsthe involvement of public employees in political work.In discussion, it was argued that the source of an adviser&apos;sremuneration was not relevant: the question at issue was whether his functions as an adviser might be incompatible with his functions as a member of a local authority or as a Parliamentary candidate.So far as local government was concerned, a possible conflict ofloyalty could in practice be prevented by requiring him to observecertain conditions - for example, he might be asked not to serve on any local authority committee working in a field for which his minister had responsibility;  not to speak publicly or in the Councilon such matters;   and not to be present if his Minister receiveda deputation from his local authority.    But given that possibleconflicts of loyalty could thus be avoided, it was very desirable,if the potential %value of special advisers was to be fully realised,that they should be actively engaged in political Hfe.    Moreover,they were not wholly analogous with permanent civil servants in thatthey would cease to hold their appointments immediately a changeof Government took place, so that the need to preserve politicalneutrality did not arise with the same force - indeed, one of their most useful functions was precisely to advise Ministers on apoHtical basis.    Moreover, even in the permanent Civil Servicethere was no absolute ban on participation in local government:the current instructions were that Departments could givepermission to serve on local authorities to the maximum extentcompatible .with the maintenance of political impartiality; and(with the exception of Private Office staff) it was normally only atthe level of Assistant Secretary and above that it might be necessary
to refuse permission.    No major change of principle would therefore be involved in allowing special advisers to serve on localauthorities.    As regards Parliamentary candidature, there seemed no reason why the relevant Statutory Instrument should notbe amended so as to allow a special adviser to stand for Parliament,provided that he resigned as an adviser immediately he was elected.A similar question could arise in relation to Peers; and there seemed no reason why a Peer should not act as a special adviserprovided that he did not speak or vote in the House of Lords,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the principle at issue was not primarily the source of a special adviser&apos;s remuneration but the question whether his duties as an adviser were incompatible with political activity.They inclined to the view that the present rules should be relaxed soas to allow special advisers to take part in local government atthe discretion of their Departments subject to certain generally accepted conventions.    But the Lord President should arrangefor the circulation to the Cabinet of a memorandum examining thematter further, and in particular making recommendations as toany conditions, perhaps on the lines mentioned in the discussion,which it might be desirable for Departments to impose whenauthorising participation in local government.     The memorandum should also, in the light of the Cabinet1 s discussion, examine further the position of special advisers in relation to parliamentary candidature and the conditions under which Peers might beappointed as special advisers.    No announcement should be made until the Cabinet had discussed the matter further; but specialadvisers who had already been appointed could be informed thatthere was at present no question of their being required to give upexisting membership of a local authority or of discontinuing their remuneration from public funds.    When the Cabinet had considered the matter further it would probably be desirable tohave discussions with the Opposition in advance of any announce-ment, and it might prove helpful to relate those discussions to themore general question of financial help for Opposition Parties incarrying out their Parliamentary functions.The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.2.      Invited the Lord President of the Council to circulate a memorandum on the Hnes indicated in the summing up.12
8.        THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT saidthat Shell-Mex and BP and the Esso Petroleum Company, whichtogether controlled about three-quarters of oil tanker movement,had made a pay offer to their tanker drivers which the transport and General Workers Union (TGWU) had recommended their members to accept.    At union delegate conferences held earlierthat week a decision had been taken, by a small majority, to reject the offer and to instruct the TGWU to seek a meeting withhim.    Although the delegate conferences had agreed that normal working should continue, unofficial action had been taken by the shell-Mex/BP drivers in several, areas and this had now spread to Esso.    At present the effect of this action was small, but ifit spread widely the situation would be most serious.    He had met mr. Jackson, senior official of the TGWU, on the previous day and agreed to a further meeting with TGWU representatives on 20 May.This information had been sent to TGWU branches, and to theemployers, and he hoped it would enable the industrial action to be contained over the week-end.       In the meantime, he would arrange for the Pay Board to explore whether there might be anyscope, within the code, for an improved offer although there seemed little prospect for this.    His officials were also examiningways of making the pay offer more attractive j he would in any casetell the TGWU that within a few months statutory controls would be lifted and they would be free to bargain with the employers.    Asettlement by agreement was imperative; full backing should begiven to the TGWU who were anxious to contain the unofficialaction.    The contingency plans, which required the use of troops and the declaration of a State of Emergency, would be an unsatisfactory way of dealing with the situation which could develop.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR ENERGY said that the unofficialaction by drivers had taken the form of overtime bans, partialloading of vehicles and 24 hour strikes.    If the action spread, itcould lead to supplies throughout the country being cut by15 to 25 per cent, which would cause difficulties for vital users.A more severe reduction, affecting one area only, such as Scotland,would be difficult to handle since bringing in Servicemen in one area could precipitate a national stoppage.Although the unofficial action had now spread beyond Shell-Mex/BPto Esso and Petrofina, the total effect on supplies was not yetsignificant.   In Scotland however the action which had begun atGrangemouth had spread and was potentially troublesome.    NoPress reports of the stoppage had appeared.THE HOME SECRETARY said that the Civil Contingencies Unithad considered what the Government might do if the unofficialaction spread-..   Servicemen could only move about 20 per cent of normal oil supplies, and since their employment would be likely
to precipitate a nation-wide strike implementing the contingency-plan should be a last resort.    On the other hand, it might benecessary to take a risk and use Servicemen in a limited area ifthere were no other way of getting supplies to vital users.Several days&apos; notice were required before Servicemen could startmoving petrol and oil, arid it would take three to five days for theoperation to build up to full capacity.    He had authorised, withincentral Government, all possible covert planning of this contingencyto be carried out; but wider consultations, including discussions between army districts and local representatives of the oil industry,briefing of Chief Constables, confidential discussion with Post Officeunions and preparations for Press advertising carried, in total, a risk of the contingency plans leaking out.    On balance, the damage which a leakage of the Governments plans might cause byexacerbating the industrial situation and by leading to a run on thepetrol stations outweighed the benefits of a quicker reaction time.He would consider the situation again with the Civil ContingenciesUnit in the light of the outcome of the Secretary of State forEmployments meeting on 20 May with the TGWU.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that the Secretary of State for employment should continue his efforts to reach a settlement which had thesupport of the TGWU.    The Home Secretary, in consultation withthe Secretary of State for Energy, should continue to watch thesituation but, bearing in mind the risks of a leakage, should not carry further the consultations about plans to deal with a stoppage until the outcome of the further meeting with the TGWU was known.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister1 summing up of their discussion and invited theSecretary of State for Employment and the HomeSecretary to be guided ac cor Singly.Cabinet Office16 May 197414
9TOP salaries review BODYThird InterimReportCABINETCONFIDENTIAL annex cc(74) 16th Conclusions, Minute 6Thursday 16 May 1974 at 10. 00 am the Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Lord President ofthe Council (C(74) 43) about the third interim report of the top salaries Review Body (TSRB).THE LORD PRESIDENT said that a Ministerial meeting on 26 Aprilhad agreed by a large majority that the main recommendations ofthe third interim report of the TSRB should be accepted.    TheMeeting had however felt doubts about the recommendation that the groups covered by the report should benefit from thresholdagreements as permitted by the Pay Code, giving an extra 40p aweek for each 1 per cent step in the retail price index over thethreshold level.    It had been felt that this would look ridiculousand would make it more difficult to set up a voluntary incomes policy.    He had discussed the matter with the Chairman of theTSRB, who had said that he hoped the Review Body would not over-react, but they would be sad if, for the first time, one of their recommendations was rejected.    This was not an issue of greatimportance, and it was a matter of judgment how far it would be anirritant to the trades unions.    On balance, he recommended thatthe TSRB recommendations should be implemented in full.In discussion, it was argued that at a time when some groups, likethe nurses, were having to fight for much smaller increases, itwas unsatisfactory for higher-paid groups to receive increases of 350 under an automatic procedure..   At the meeting on 26 April,it had been suggested that a preferable course might be to denyincreases to all those earning more than  10, 000 a year, and for cabinet Ministers&apos; salaries to be reduced to that level.    Thethreshold proposal, in particular, was derisory and should be rejected, particularly as other groups, such as engineers, wouldhave to bargain for the award of any such arrangements.    Asregards the other recommendations, even if these might now have tobe accepted as the report had already been received, the wholequestion of top salaries should.be referred to the Royal CommissionCOPY NO.
on Income Distribution as soon as it was set up.    The timing ofany announcement on the third interim report also needed to befurther considered: it should be chosen so as to attract theminimum publicity, and it was for consideration whether it couldnot be postponed until after the end of statutory pay control.    Onthe other hand, it was argued that the groups concerned would only receive, after tax, a small proportion of the  350 increase.Having regard to inflation and the recent increases in personaltaxation, their net purchasing power might well fall, over theyear, by up to 20 per cent.    Y/hile this did not eliminate thepresentational problem, it had been recognised in the past that themanagement of nationalised industries could suffer if a ceiling was imposed on the public sector and not on the private sector.    the aim of the Royal Commission on Income Distribution should be toput the spotlight on the private sector, which was better furnished with, for example, expense accounts and, in some cases, alsoable to draw on capital.    As regards the! threshold proposal, thepoint was of limited importance one way or the other, but if thresholdagreements were not given to Civil Service Under Secretaries,this would create an anomaly since the Assistant Secretaries wouldhave overtaken them by the end of the year.    A possible solution might be to allow threshold agreements only to those earning lessthan  10, 000 a year.    As regards the timing, a short delay wouldbe possible, but the report had already been in the Government&apos;shands for some time, and the report of the Review Body on armed forces pay was being dealt with more speedily.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that thegeneral feeling in the Cabinet was in favour of accepting the main recommendations of the TSRB third interim report, but therecommendation on threshold agreements should be further considered to see whether the award of such agreements only tothose earning less than  10, 000 a year would avoid anomalies inthe Civil Service.    The timing of an announcement should also befurther considered in the light of the points made in discussion.When these two points had been examined, the Cabinet would resume their consideration of the matter with the aim of reaching a decision in the following week.The Cabinet -Invited the Lord President to consider the suggestionthat threshold agreements should be awarded only tothose earning less than  10, 000 a year, and to examinethe question of the timing of an announcement, and toreport his conclusions on these points to the cabinet at their next meeting.Cabinet Office


</content>
</cab>
