<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/38 images: 424-427</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1945.The circulation of this paper has faeen strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use ofJotpy No.W.P. (45) 288.8th May, 1945.WAR CABINET.WHEAT IMPORTS FOR INDIA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.THE Indian food grains Requirements Committee has been unable to find asolution for the problem of wheat supplies for India.2. I recently placed before the Chiefs of Staff the critical position of indian this respect, which is briefly as follows. Last January India undertook, on certain conditions, to accept the additional economic strain arising from approvedoperations to be based on India; foremost amongst these conditions was the pro-vision by His Majesty&apos;s Government of 70,000 tons of food grains in each of thefirst four months of 1945 and an undertaking to do their utmost thereafter tosecure and transport the reasonable requirements of India for food grains on a scale sufficient to enable the Government of India to forestall shortages and maintain control of prices.3. Against this initial requirement of 280,000 tons in 4 months, only90,000 tons have been shipped and no forward undertaking has been given; while a deterioration in the internal supply position as compared with the situation inJanuary has reduced available resources other than imports by a further200,000 tons. Taken together, these disappointments of expectations and adversedevelopments have completely eliminated the carry-over in the hands of the CentralFood Department with which they counted on beginning the new crop year. TheGovernment of India&apos;s need for imports to enable them to carry the approvedoperational load over the year the 1st May, 1945, to the 30th April. 1946. has thusbeen increased : and though meanwhile preparation of India as the base forthese operations continues, the Government of India, with the full support ofLord Wavell, have represented that the conditions on which they undertook the strain involved have not been fulfilled, and that without imports on the scale forwhich they have now asked the reception of further forces and even the conductof operations on the present scale will in their judgment be adversely affected.4. On the case thus presented the Chiefs of Staff stated as their conclusionthat &quot; meeting the military requirement involves the import of food grains neces-sary both for the forces deployed and to be deployed for India and South-East Asia,and for.the stability and security of India as a base.&quot; They left the quantity toexpert decision. The Government of India have assessed their need for loadingsover the year March 1945 to February 1946 at just under 1^ million tons, with ahigh rate of arrivals in the critical summer months.5. To avoid the difficulty presented by a programme of shipments over solong a period, I asked the food grains Committee for (1) a very urgent effort to ship 50,000 tons as an emergency measure;(2) loadings at the rate of 135,000 tons a month from May to August (july to October arrival), the position being re-examined in Julyp(3) permission to make an announcement in the House of Commons of futureintentions in general terms.[29848]
6. In response to this the Minister of War Transport wias unable, in viewof his commitments, and of the priorities given to relief and other supplies, tooffer more than a &quot; target figure &quot; of 65,000 to 70,000 tons a month subject to cabinet approval.7. The Government of India&apos;s demand, very strongly endorsed byLord Wavell, is based upon the necessity, for the purposes stressed by the Chiefsof Staff, of importing adequate supplies to meet the Defence demand and for maintaining the confidence essential to bring out the new wheat crop, procure-ment of which is an even more important element in meeting their needs and inavoiding the ever-present risk of another famine.8. For this purpose no contingent target will suffice and I ask the WarCabinet, if the operational demands on India are to stand, to authorise suchpriority for Indian supplies as will enable a definite promise to be given of the quantities indicated above for the next four months (with further consideration in July) and, to cover the remainder of the crop year (i.e., May 1945 to April1946), to empower me to make a statement in general terms to be agreed withthe Indian food grains Requirements Committee.L. S. A.India Office, 8th May, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
