<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/7/15 images: 226-237</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  September 1940.SECRET. 7-.- Copy No.W.P. (R.) (40) 195.September 26, 1940.BE KEPT UNDER -LOCK[t Is requested that special car^ejaay be Mjahjalsure tftt secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.REPORTS FOR MONTH OF AUGUST 1940 FOR THE DOMINIONS,INDIA, BURMA, AND THE COLONIES, PROTECTORATES and mandated TERRITORIES.THE DOMINIONS.Report by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.CANADA.1. General Position.THE Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Air has paid a shortvisit to Canadia by the flying-boat Clare. Captain Balfour discussed with canadian Ministers and officials a number of questions connected with the EmpireAir Training Scheme and air co-operation generally.In the Canadian House of Commons on the 6th August the Prime minister was asked about the position of the French Minister in Canada. The PrimeMinister, in replying, said that, while the relations with France at the presenttime were &quot;obscure,&quot; the policy of the Canadian Government was not to severdiplomatic relations with France to the extent of asking the French Minister to retire, and that this policy was well known and understood by the UnitedKingdom Government.The Prime Minister also mentioned that the Canadian Government had inmind filling the vacant appointment of Minister to Japan, but had decided to await an opportune moment for this.The question of establishing a Canadian Legation in one of the south american Republics and of Canadian representation in India was also referredto by Mr. Mackenzie King.In reply to a question asking why Canada did not take a place in the Pan-American Union, the Prime Minister said that the present time was inopportunefor this; moreover, no invitation to Canada to do so had been given, and, in anycase, such action on the part of Canada would be construed &quot; by the enemy asweakness on Canada&apos;s part and as a sign of disintegration of the Empire.&quot;2. Naval, Military and Air Activities.Following a meeting between the Prime Minister of Canada and thePresident of the United States on the 18th August, an announcement was made that the Canadian and United States Governments had decided to set up a joint permanent Defence Board for the study of common defence problems. the membership of the Board was announced very shortly afterwards; in each casethe respective countries appointed civilians as their chief representatives,Mr. Biggar, a well-known barrister of  Ottawa,  for Canada,  and  Mayor
La Guardia of New York for the United States. The Board has met at Ottawa,has toured the eastern Canadian defences, and is shortly to meet again in washington. In view of the assumption by Canada of a measure of responsibilityfor the defence of Newfoundland and the conclusion of the above agreementbetween Canada and the United States, the Canadian Government have been invited to appoint a representative at the discussions to be held with the UnitedStates as regards the detailed arrangements required to give effect- to the UnitedKingdom-United States agreement, which includes the grant of leases in newfoundland.It has not been possible to release a second destroyer from the Royal Navy for purchase by the Canadian Government, but the Royal Canadian Navy will mana number of the destroyers now being obtained from the United States ofAmerica.The Canadian Government have agreed to the diversion to Freetown of two9 - 2-inch gun equipments which were earmarked for Halifax.The first Brigade Group of the 2nd Canadian Division has arrived in theUnited Kingdom. The Canadian battalion in the West Indies is being concentrated at Jamaica.The fighter squadron of the Royal Canadian Air Force in this country hasnow been in action against the enemy.The Empire Air Training Scheme is in advance of Schedule. Twenty-twoschools were in operation and 2,643 pupils in training by the beginning of August,and it is hoped to complete this year construction works for all schools due to open in 1941.3. Economic Activities.Mr. Howe, the Minister of Munitions and Supply, recently announced thatthe total capital expenditure on new munitions plants, &amp;c, in Canada plannedby the Canadian and United Kingdom Governments jointly was now about 50,000,000, and that these plants would yield an annual output of munitionsvalued at some  180,000,000.COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.4. General Position.The Commonwealth Government have decided to appoint Sir John Lathamas first Australian Minister to Tokyo. Commenting on suggestions in theJapanese press that this decision indicated a lessening of Australia^ dependence on the United Kingdom, and a realignment of her policy towards Japan, thePrime Minister, Mr. Menzies, said that any such notions were to be completelyrejected. Far from being weakened, the relations between Australia and theUnited Kingdom were becoming stronger, and the despatch of diplomatic .repre-sentatives abroad was intended as &apos;&apos; an addition to, not a subtraction from, the diplomatic strength of the Empire.&quot;A general election was held on the 21st September.In opening the Labour Election campaign, Mr. Curtin, Leader of the labour opposition, stated that Labour was inflexibly devoted to the British cause.Temporary appointments, of Mr. Fadden as Minister for Civil Aviation, andSenator McBricle as Minister for Defence, in place of Ministers killed in therecent air crash at Canberra, are announced in the press.5. Naval, Military and Air Activities.H.M.A.S. Hobart took a very important part in the evacuation of british somali land. The Commonwealth Government have made dispositions to enable a vessel of the Royal Australian Navy to visit New Caledonia if the situation inthat French colony should make it desirable.The best use to be made of the partly trained 7th Australian Division isunder discussion with the Commonwealth Government.Royal Australian Air Force personnel for an army co-operation squadronhave been sent to the Middle East.
NEW ZEALAND.6. General Position.The recent formation of a War Cabinet including two members of theOpposition with Ministerial rank has improved the political outlook, but thereare signs that public opinion in New Zealand will eventually induce the Govern-ment to form a full Coalition Government. This, however, is not likely to happenuntil the war enters a more critical phase than the present.The Arbitration Court has awarded a 5 per cent, increase in wages as fromthe 12th August.The intense interest displayed by the press in Japan&apos;s actions died downtowards the end of the month.A Home Guard, on the lines of the United Kingdom Home Guard, and aWomen&apos;s War Service Auxiliary, with the object of co-ordinating the activitiesof women war workers and assisting in mobilising women workers for industry,have been formed.The New Zealand Government have arranged for a representative of theGovernment, with suitable escort, to visit Tahiti, where a provisionalpro-de Gaulle Government has been set up.Seven mine sweeping vessels are in commission in New Zealand waters.At the request of the United Kingdom Government, a New Zealand surveybattery is being raised for service in the Middle East.The New Zealand Government are planning to provide if required air reconnaissance in the area New Hebrides-Fiji-Tonga.The total applications for entry into the Air Force received up to thebeginning of August were 7,700 for flying training and 7,800 for non-flying training. A total of 460 trained personnel have been sent to the United Kingdomsince the outbreak of war.In opening the 5th Session of the Union Parliament on the 24th August, theGovernor-General referred to the considerable expansion which had taken placein the scale of the Union&apos;s defence expenditure.On the 29th August, General Hertzog introduced a motion demandingimmediate peace with Germany and Italy. The Prime Minister, in a crushingreply, said that the Opposition was prepared to conclude any sort of peace. Solong as Great Britain commanded the seas and continued to bring the Air Forceinto the front rank, victory would be hers. The Government would no longertolerate subversive activities. The &quot; peace motion &quot; was subsequently defeatedby 83 votes to 65.Dr. Verwoerd, the editor of the Transvaler, has been charged under theemergency regulations. He was acquitted owing to his absence on holiday whenthe article appeared, but three members of his staff were fined. The pro-Govern-ment press indignantly reject Mr. FIoover&apos;s plea for raising the blockade. Eventhe extreme Nationalist papers have ceased to proclaim the certainty of a Germanvictory.The total strength of the Union forces is now 95,000, of whom 81,000 are on full-time service. The South African Air Force includes 630 flying officers and900 air gunners.The Union Government have despatched a quantity of mechanical transport to Kenya, including 670 3-ton lorries and 630 1-ton and f-ton light vehicles,and General Smuts has agreed to draft further substantial forces to the east african front.7. Naval, Military and Air Activities.UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.8. General Position.9. Naval, Military and Air Activities.
EIRE.10. General Position.There is again little change to report in the political situation in Eire. the bombing of.an Eire ship in Eire territorial waters, the crash of a German bomberin Eire and the dropping of bombs on villages in Co. Wexford, which caused the death of three persons and injured another, no doubt had some effect onopinion in Eire, but press comment there was extremely restrained. The eire government protested against the bombing of the Eire vessel and the dropping of bombs in Co. Wexford. The German Government have apologised for the bombing of the ship.The trade negotiations with the Eire Government which began last Aprilhave now reached a further definite stage. After reference to the War cabinet an offer has been made to the Eire authorities whereby the United KingdomGovernment would pay  500,000 to a Board to be established by the eire government to control the export of fat cattle. The Board would then distributethe money amongst its members. In return the United Kingdom would getcertain snipping and other facilities, of which the most important in presentcircumstances might be the permission to use Eire ports for the transhipmentof goods from deep-sea vessels to smaller ships, should such a course become necessary owing to the restriction of port facilities in Great Britain. This offeris still under consideration by the Eire authorities.NEWFOUNDLAND.11. General position.Representatives of the Canadian Government, including the Air Minister,visited St. John&apos;s to discuss various matters mainly concerned with the naval andair defence of the Island, and its relation to the Canadian Defence Scheme.The recent agreement between the United Kingdom and the United Statesincluded the grant of naval and air leases in Newfoundland to the United States.The exact site of the leases has still to be determined, but was roughly defined in the United Kingdom note as on the Avalon Peninsula and the southern coast of new foundland. The Newfoundland Government was consulted prior to theexchange of letters, and the Governor indicated that the proposal should meet with approval locally. The Governor has been informed that the United KingdomGovernment would welcome the appointment of a Newfoundland representative at the discussions with the United States on the detailed arrangements to be madeto carry out the agreement.12. Naval, Military and Air Force Activities.The Royal Navy.The 10th Contingent (190 men) have arrived in the United Kingdom, makinga total of 1,806 in all.The Army.The 5th Contingent (147 men) have arrived in the United Kingdom, makinga total of 1,066 in all.Royal Air Force.Thirty-four ground staff personnel have arrived in the United Kingdom.The first quota of Newfoundland trainees, as pilots, observers and air-gunners,have left for Canada under the Empire Air Training Scheme.13. Economic Action.Three hundred and seventy of the recruits for the Newfoundland ForestryUnit have been repatriated. The number of loggers now at work in this countryis about 2,800.The question of requisitioning thirteen French trawlers operating from st. Pierre, and the disposal of the salt fish output of St. Pierre is engaging theattention of the Newfoundland Government.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA.14. General Position.Messages from His Majesty The King and the United Kingdom Governmenthave been sent on the occasion of Southern Rhodesia&apos;s Jubilee.The Minister for Internal Affairs has resigned from the Rhodesian LabourParty, of which he was formerly the leader, as a result of a decision of the partynot to participate in a National Government. The Labour party has, however,undertaken to support the Government in all measures connected with the war.15. Military and Air Force Activities.As a result of the calling-up of men under the Southern Rhodesia NationalService Act, 450 men are in full-time training and over 1,100 are in part-timetraining. One hundred men suitable for immediate commissions are being sentto East Africa to reinforce Southern Rhodesia personnel serving with Africanunits in that theatre. A reconnaissance unit is also under training, it will consist of an Armoured Car Company and a mechanised infantry company withancillary headquarters detachments.Recruits for a Rhodesia African Regiment and an African labour battalionare in training.INDIA.Report by the Secretary of State for India.16. Political Situation.On the 8th August the Governor-General issued, with the approval of theWar Cabinet, his statement designed to produce a provisional basis forco-operation between the political parties and the Central Government in furthering India&apos;s war effort, and to define further the intentions of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment for the revision of the Constitution already promised at theconclusion of the war. On the 22nd August the Congress Working committee by formal resolution rejected the offer, and followed up this pronouncement by two further resolutions which appear to have been intended as a warning that congress will probably feel itself driven to resort to civil disobedience or someother form of direct action, and intends to ignore, so far as Congress volunteersare concerned, the ban on drilling and the wearing of uniform recently imposedunder the Defence of India Rules. Mr. Nehru is evidently anxious to precipitatea direct issue with the Government, but it is by no means certain that he will be supported by Mr. Gandhi, who would seem to be ready to reassume control of congress policy and has asked for an interview with the Viceroy. A meeting ofthe All-India Congress Committee is summoned for the 15th September.On the 31st August the Working Committee of the All-India Moslem Leagueadopted a resolution which appears to amount to acceptance in principle. Theyhave removed their ban on co-operation in War Committees, and has instructedorganisations connected with the League to conform to the orders as regardsdrilling and uniforms.Meanwhile the Governor-General has been establishing contact with theleaders of Parties other than the Congress, and I am awaiting his proposals asthe result of these discussions for the new appointments to be made, to his executive Council and for the membership of the War Advisory Council. it remains, of course, to be seen how far the attitude of the Congress High Commandwill continue to be accepted by the Party generally.17. Military Affairs.1. The first echelon of the Indian Division referred to in the report for march, which was originally earmarked for the defence of the Anglo-iranian oil fields, has left India for Egypt and the Sudan. The remainder will sail inSeptember.
2. One Field Regiment, R.A., without horses or Indian personnel, has been dispatched from India to Egypt, where it will be mechanised from existing resources.3. During August His Majesty&apos;s Government asked the Government ofIndia to provide an Indian Battalion to replace a British Battalion inSomaliland. This Battalion has now sailed, but, in view of the changed situation,it is likely to be sent to Egypt.4. One Mountain Battery and the Bikaner Camel Corps (Indian StateForces), originally destined for Somaliland, are to form part of the garrison of aden.5. Two Indian Infantry Battalions from Aden took part in the recent operations in Somaliland.6. The War Office propose to form two Pack Transport Companies from theIndian Animal Transport Companies which were evacuated from France. It isintended to employ them primarily in Scotland.18. Foreign and Frontier Relations.(i) Afghanistan. ^The general situation in Afghanistan has been quiet.The signing of the Trade Agreement between Russia and Afghanistan hashad a good effect on public opinion and the fear of a Russian invasion hasdiminished. German propaganda continues with full force but rather less effect.The continued German delay in launching a large-scale attack on Britain isrestoring confidence in British ability and determination to resist and eventually to overcome Germany.The agreement for the purchase of 10,000 tons of Afghan cotton by theGovernment of India has now been formally concluded by an exchange of letterswith the Afghan Government.The Afghans were grateful for His Majesty&apos;s Government^ decision inregard to a purchase of Afghan wool, but, meanwhile, the bulk of the available supply had been disposed of to the Russians. The question whether negotiations should be continued for the purchase of the small quantity still remaining for disposal and possibly also with a view to the purchase of the next clip, whichis due in September-October, is under consideration.(ii) North-West Frontier Province. There has been an increase inlawlessness in Waziristan, mainly in the north. The chief trouble during themonth has been with the Daurs, a tribe in the North Waziristan Agency. action had to be taken against one of their villages on the 7th August by the TochiScouts and again by regular troops on the 17th August. As a result the politicalsituation in the Lower Daur area has much improved, and 90 per cent, of a fineof 10,000 rupees imposed on these tribesmen has been paid. The Upper Daursituation is still reported to be doubtful.Outside Waziristan the rest of the frontier has remained quiet. The Nawabof Dir has contributed Rs. 30,000 to the Viceroy&apos;s War Purposes Fund.(iii) Sinkiang. The Consul-General at Kashgar replied as instructed to thelatest demand of the Provincial authorities for the closure of his wireless station,and there have as yet been no further developments.(iv) Persian Gulf. The progress of air attacks on England have been followed with interest in Muscat, and there is general confidence that invasionwill fail. Similarly in Koweit German air losses and the slight extent of the damage done by the raids have strengthened confidence.(v) French Settlements in India. The position has remained satisfactory,though the attitude of the Governor since his original message to general de Gaulle has been somewhat equivocal. The Government of India have been instructed that every effort should be made to&quot;induce him to declare openly infavour of General de Gaulle.19. Indian States.Nothing to report.
20. Economic.During August a Mission, under the leadership of Sir Alexander Roger,started for India to advise His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Government ofIndia on the problem of increasing India&apos;s output of munitions and other military stores. The purpose of the Mission, which is under the direction of theMinistry of Supply, is to enable India not only to meet her own needs for homedefence, but to make an even greater contribution than she does at present to thegeneral war effort of the Empire, and in particular to the equipment and supplyof the forces in the Middle East and East of Suez.While the Mission is in India the Eastern Group Conference referred toin last month&apos;s report will meet at New Delhi, and the Mission will thereby be greatly helped in relating its plans for the expansion of production in Indiato the capacities of the other countries represented at the Conference and to the wider strategical requirements of our forces in the East and Near East.21. Finance.Nothing to report.BURMA.Report by the Secretary of State for Burma.22. General.The position in the Districts is reported to be peaceful. In Rangoon somemeetings have been held to protest against the alleged repressive measures of theGovernment of Burma, but on the whole they were not well attended and the tone of the speeches was mild.The ex-Premier, Dr. Ba Maw, who, as reported in July, resigned his seatin the House of Representatives on the ground that he could better work for thefreedom of Burma outside than inside the Legislature, was arrested on the6th August. According to a Reuter&apos;s report, he was sentenced to a year&apos;srigorous imprisonment on the 29th August. The other ex-Minister against whomaction has been taken, Dr. Thein Maung, has not yet been brought to trialbecause of illness. In an address to the Legislature on the 26th August theGovernor made a statement on Burma&apos;s constitutional progress and appealed forunity and co-operation in the Empire&apos;s war effort.A motion was moved in the Senate on the 28th August disapproving theadministration of the Defence of Burma Act and Rules, and the Premier. U. Pu,is reported to have taken a strong line in opposing it. He said that it was theduty of Government to maintain law and order to ensure that nothing occurred to  affect the successful prosecution of the war, and that irresponsible action, evenby party leaders, likely to cause disorder would not be tolerated. The motion was defeated by 12 votes to 8.The Premier is also reported to have delivered a very effective address at the students&apos; Union, Rangoon University, in which he gave the reasons for theMinistry offering unconditional support to Britain in the prosecution of the war.23. Press and Public Opinion.The arrest of Dr. Ba Maw caused a stir in the Leftist Burmese Press, whichseized the opportunity to condemn the drastic use of the Defence of Burma Rules.On the other hand, U. Pu&apos;s University Union speech was regarded as a sincereand earnest exposition of Burma&apos;s position in the war, although it was condemnedby the Leftist Press on the ground that Burmans must work for themselves toobtain freedom.The news of the aerial attack on Britain is reported not to have perturbedthe press, which is also said to have been unanimous in acclaiming Mr. Churchill&apos;sspeech as inspiring and stimulating.An organisation for propaganda in the Districts has been started. the broadcasts in Burmese by the B.B.C. began on the 2nd September.
24. Defence.Defence measures are proceeding as quickly as possible. A supplementaryBudget for over Rs. 74 lakhs for defence expenditure was introduced in theLegislature on the 26th August.25. External Relations.Nothing to report.26. Economic.Three thousand tons of timber and 200 tons of pig lead are being shipped tothe Middle East Command, with further supplies to follow.THE COLONIAL EMPIRE.Report by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.(Note. In this Report &quot; Colonies &quot; is used to cover not only the Colonies inthe restricted sense, but also Protectorates and Mandated Territories, and&quot;Colonial Governors&quot; is used to include High Commissioners and theBritish Resident, Zanzibar.)27. Military Affairs.Somaliland.I do not propose to deal in this report with the military aspects of theItalian invasion or the political repercussions of the British evacuation.Arrangements are now being made to absorb the civil officials of the SomalilandGovernment into Colonial Government employment elsewhere so far as possible.The Governor of British Somaliland, Mr. V. G. Glenday, C.M.G., is now in kenya.East African Intelligence Centre.It has been decided in principle to establish a civil, political and securityintelligence centre at Nairobi under the general control of Sir Philip Mitchell,Deputy Chairman of the Conference of East African Governors. The centrewill receive material from neighbouring British and foreign territories and will maintain liaison with other similar centres elsewhere and with theGovernments of the Union of South Africa, Southern Rhodesia, India and burma.Control of West African Forces.It has been decided, in consultation with the War Office and the Treasury,that, in view of the appointment of a General Officer Commanding, West Africa,the War Office shall assume full operational, administrative and financial control of military forces in West Africa.Defence Facilities for United States in Caribbean Area.An announcement has been made of the decision to grant the United StatesGovernment 99-year leases of sites in Bermuda, Bahamas, Jamaica, Trinidad,British Guiana, Antigua (Leeward Islands) and St. Lucia (Windward Islands).The detailed arrangements to give effect to this decision are now being worked out.28. Situation in the French Colonies.Early in August emissaries of General de Gaulle left this country forWest Africa, where they were joined by Colonel de Larminat, who had gonethere from Syria. These emissaries made useful contacts among Frenchcommunities in each of the British West African Colonies. From Nigeriathey got into touch with those elements in the Province of Chad and in theFrench Cameroons which were out of sympathy with the official policy o
9111obedience to Vichy. Colonel de Larrninat went on the 19th August toLeopoldville, in the Belgian Congo, to investigate the possibility of bringing about a coup d&apos;Etat in the neighbouring&quot; town of Brazzaville, which is thecapital of French Equatorial Africa.On the 26th August the Governor and Military Commander of theProvince of Chad announced their decision to adhere to the cause of the Allies.On the following day representatives of General de Gaulle landed at Duala inthe French Cameroons ; they reported that they were greeted with enthusiasmby the population and the garrison and on the 28th August they announcedthat the mandate over the territory would thenceforward be exercised by them on behalf of Free France. Meanwhile, a coup d&apos;Etat was taking place inBrazzaville in favour of General de Gaulle. The Governor-General of french equatorial Africa fled to Leopoldville and on the 30th August Colonel deLanninat crossed the border to Brazzaville and there assumed full powers ofgovernment. General de Gaulle has since promoted Colonel de Larrninat tothe rank of general and has appointed him High Commissioner for french equatorial Africa.Little is yet known of the reactions to these events in French West africa and their effect has still to be felt in other French possessions overseas.Meanwhile, the position in the Western Pacific remains unstable; but thelocal French administration in the Anglo-French condominium of the new hebrides have declared themselves definitely on the side of the Allies and have placed themselves under the general direction of General de Gaulle. There arealso indications that some of the authorities in New Caledonia still wish, andmay be able, to withstand the pressure on them to accept the orders of Vichy.Since the close of the month Tahiti has declared for General de Gaulle. in french Guiana there is said to be a strong and growing body of opposition to aceptance of the armistice.29. Internment.Enemy aliens interned in Tanganyika, Kenya and Uganda have beentransferred to the Union of South Africa, and arrangements are now beingmade for the removal of internees from the West African Colonies to Jamaica.A summary of the Home Secretary&apos;s statement of policy in regard to therelease of Germans and Austrians from internment has been telegraphed to allColonial Governments.30. Exchange Control and Export and Import Licensing.Colonial Governments have now been instructed to grant no export licences for the French Colonial Empire without prior reference to the Secretary ofState.In common with the rest of the sterling areas in the British Empire,Colonial Governments are preventing the importation of Bank of Englandnotes except under licence in order to prevent the enemy profiting from suppliesof these notes which they have taken over in occupied territory.31. Supply of Colonial Products.The purchase of 180,000 more tons of rubber by the United States Govern-ment has now been agreed to on conditions that are considered satisfactory.It is, however, not the present intention to negotiate for increased sales of tin.In view of the possibility of a smelter being set up in the United States whichwill attract Bolivian supplies of the ore, it is considered essential that tinstocks in the United Kingdom should be raised, and, if this is to be done, it isimpossible to undertake further supplies to the United States.Mainly as a result of large diversions of cargoes due to the French collapse,the problem of disposing of palm kernels and palm oil in West Africa became more acute and the Ministry of Food were compelled to urge a further reductionin price. Eventually, however, it was decided to accept an alternative proposal of the Governor of Nigeria that all further purchases should be prohibited in theWestern Provinces. The Governor considered that this course would be the lesser of two evils, but difficulties must be expected.[21772] c
35. Bahamas.Governors His Royal Highness the Duke of Windsor assumed administration of theNo^oo^f       government on the 17th August.August 17,1940.Governors A loan of , 250,000 free of interest has been made to His Majesty&apos;sNo6 95&amp; Conn-   Government for the duration of the war.dential, of36. Windward Islands.GovernorstelegramsNos. 413 and414 ofAugust 10,1940.ActingGovernorstelegram No.480 of August 6,1940.ActingGovernorstelegramNo. 451 ofJuly 26, 1940.Secretary ofState&apos;s tele-gram No. 426 ofAugust 2,1940.ActingGovernorstelegramNo. 478, most secret, ofAugust 3, 1940.TelegramNo. 216,government house, Secret,of August 4,1940.The Grenada Government has made a gift of  15,000 to &quot; His Majesty, hisheirs and. successors &quot; for war purposes.37. Ceylon.Informal discussions will take place in November between representa-tives of the Ceylon Government and of the Government of India at which all outstanding questions will come under review. A notice has been published in the press.38. Hong Kong.Lieutenant-General E. F. Norton, C.B., D.S.O., M.C., formerly commanding the. Western District, India, assumed the administration of the colony on the6th August.Unofficial members of the Legislative Council strongly opposed the costof evacuation of British European women and children falling on Colonialrevenue on the ground that the cost would thus be borne predominantly bynon-Europeans. His Majesty&apos;s Government has offered to bear 50 per cent,of the cost on the assumption that the rest will be borne by the familiesconcerned. The question whether any part of the balance not borne byevacuated families should be met from Colonial funds is still under discussion.In accordance with the decision of His Majesty&apos;s Government to take action against certain Japanese individuals in the Empire, Mr. Yamaguchi,head of a firm of that name, was detained under the Defence Regulations.39. Malaya. -The measures taken against Japanese subjects in Malaya included the detention of a Japanese journalist at Singapore named Kobayashi and theexpulsion from Malaya of a Formosan.32. Maintenance of Supplies to Colonial Dependencies.The maintenance of supplies to the Mediterranean, especially Malta, hascontinued to receive constant attention. Proposals have been approved inprinciple for the importation of all food-stuffs and other essentials into Maltaby the Colonial Government and for their distribution through organised poolsof local dealers. Stocks are to be built up as far as possible to eight months&apos;supply, falling to six months before the arrival of convoys, which it is planned to arrange at intervals of two months.33. Currency.Some apprehension exists about a possible shortage of currency in theWest Indies, partly owing to abnormal transfers of bank deposits to thosecolonies by persons seeking greater security and partly owing to the possibilityof a local &quot;run&quot; on the banks if Britain were invaded or communications were temporarily interrupted. Arrangements have been made for increased suppliesof notes as an emergency reserve.Reports on Particular, Colonies.34. West Indies.The Comptroller of the West Indian Development and Welfare Fund hasbeen appointed, and appointments have been made to the posts of Advisers tothe Comptroller on Agriculture, Education, Labour and Health.
The Legislative Councils of the Straits Settlements and the federated malay States have approved the raising of loans locally of 25 million and 20million dollars (Straits) respectively, as a gift to His Majesty&apos;s Government.40. Gibraltar.The evacuation of the civilian population from Gibraltar has continued. Atotal of about 13,000 persons have now left the Fortress for Madeira (2,000) andfor this country (11,000), and consideration is being given to the question of evacuating a further 3,000 persons whom the Governor is anxious should leave.TelegramNo. 221,government house,Confidential, ofAugust 10,1940.41. Cyprus.Shipping and marketing difficulties are seriously affecting the economic life of the Colony, and assistance on a considerable scale is being given to producers of carobs and grapes who for these reasons cannot dispose of their produce.Similar assistance on a large scale will probably be required for the other export industries.42. Mauritius and Seychelles.Plans have now been made for raising pioneer units in both Colonies for employment with the military forces in the Middle East. The arrangements are well advanced and recruiting should begin before long.43. Fiji and the Western Pacific.Like other Colonies Fiji and the Western Pacific dependencies have gravedifficulty in marketing one of their principal export commodities, copra.44. Palestine and Trans-Jordan.During August the general situation in Palestine has not changed.Local Arab politics remain at a discount, but among the less educatedArabs there has been a recrudescence of rumours about a renewed Arab rising.This is mainly due to the return to Palestine of a number of gangsters. Theirmovements, however, have been severely hampered by military and police action and their propaganda has had little effect on the Arab population as a whole,who show little interest in the moves.Some Arab circles still think that Hitler is invincible and consequentlyforesee a relaxation of British control in this country. This has resulted insome increase in \.,bbery by small armed gangs in rural Palestine and, in a fewinstances, reluct .nce to pay taxes.In general 30th Arabs and Jews show increased confidence in Britain&apos;power of resistance and ability to win the war in the long run. This is mainly due to Hitler&apos;s failure so far to embark on his announced invasion of Britainand to Italy&apos;s comparative inactivity against Egypt. The occupation of british somali land does not seem to have greatly affected local confidence.Arab casualties in air raids on Haifa hardened Arab feeling against theItalians. Obviously false reports broadcast from Berlin have helped to shakelocal belief in German news reports.Dissension in Jewish political circles appears to be increasing. Inparticular the death of Mr. Jabotinsky may result in a split among theRevisionists and greater activity by the more extreme section of the party.There have been serious clashes between the Flistadruth and the Revisionistsin Herzliya settlement and in Tel Aviv, in which one Revisionist was fatallyinjured.   The party has withdrawn from the Vaad Leumi executive.The response, especially from the Jews, to the recruiting campaign for theRoyal Air Force was so satisfactory that lists were closed, temporarily at least,early in August. Enlistment in the Army ancillary services has been slower ingeneral, as Jews wish to enlist for combatant service and Arabs do not wish tobe liable for service outside Palestine.Trans-Jordan remains normal.


</content>
</cab>
