<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/43/31 images: 252-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. - Copy No.W.M. (44)115th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 115 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Defence MapRoom on Monday, 4th September, 1944, at 12-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Sir Edward BridgesThe Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.Secretary.Contents.minute no. Subject.1      Prisoners of WarDisposal of Russians captured in Normandy.2      Poland    ....      .... .  ....      ....      ....3      France    ....      .....    ....      ....      ....Proposed visit by T.U.C. Delegation.Page101010[28233-2]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1944.
Prisonersof War.Disposal ofRussiansCaptured inNormandy.(previous reference erence:W.M.(44)91stConclusions,Minute 6.)1. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (44) 492) about thedisposal of Soviet prisoners captured in France and in the middle east.   The Foreign Secretary proposed&apos; (i) that we should agree to the Soviet Governments request to repatriate their prisoners from the United Kingdom;(ii) that we should instruct the Middle East authorities tosend back all Russians whom the Soviet authoritieswished to have back, irrespective of whether or not themen wished to return; and that the practice of obtainingstatements from the Soviet prisoners as to their willing-ness to return should be discontinued;(iii) to explain to the Soviet. Government that shortage ofshipping made it impossible for us to accede to their request that we should arrange for repatriation from theUnited Kingdom.After a short discussion the War Cabinet approved these. proposals.Poland. 2.   The War Cabinet discussed the position of the Polish(Previous        Underground Army in Warsaw.reference: The discussion and conclusions reached are recorded in theW.M. (44) 111th Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Conclusions,Minute 7.)France. 3.   The War Cabinet were informed that arrangements had proposed Visit been made for a T.U.C. Delegation to visit Normandy.   Now that by T.U.C. Paris had been liberated, the Delegation wished to visit Paris andDelegation. to make contacts with the C.G.T.The War Cabinet-Agreed to the Foreign Secretary&apos;s suggestion that heshould inform Sir Walter Citrine that the position inParis was still difficult, and that the military authorities were opposed to visitors to Paris at the present time, butthat he would be informed as soon as conditions made a visit possible.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,4dh September, 1944.
g.r. yi27(this document is the property op his britannic majesty&apos;s government)secret no CIRCULATION RECORDw.m.(hh)  115TH CONCLUSIONS(Monday, b/fch September, ISUk - 12.30 p.m.)PRANCE.W.M. (hk)ll2thConclusions,Minute 3.In addition to the matters dealt with in theagenda of this meeting (attended by members of the WarCabinet only) a number of other questions were referredto.THE PRIME MINISTER said that there should be nochange in our relations with the French National Committeeuntil he (the Prime Minister) had had an opportunityof discussion with President Roosevelt.   He added that he thought we should encourage the Prench to put themselves on theircountry as soon as might be,, and that he thought thatthere would be a process of continual modification in theconstitution of the Prench National Committee.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY referred to the proposals in his memorandum (W.P. (kh) k7k) that a representativeof the Prench National Committee should be invited toattend a meeting of the Economic Advisory Council fordiscussion of the armistice terms with Germany.   Thismemorandum had been discussed by the War Cabinet at their meeting on the 29th August, and had been approved.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he raised no objectionto such ad hoc participation.defence regulations.Regulation 18B.THE PRIME MINISTER referred to the discussion which he had had with the   Home Secretary aboutRegulation 18B. He.(the Prime Minister) wanted Regulation 18Babolished when the war with Germany came to an end,and all persons detained under that Regulation released and habeas corpus restored to its full vigour.THE HOME SECRETARY said that he had no objectionto letting Regulation 18B lapse, on the understandingthat it might be necessary to take powers to detainpersons reasonably believed to be helping the Japanese.This, however, would be a relatively small matter.The matter v/as not discussed from the point of viewof reaching a decision, and no formal conclusion wasreached.prefabricatediicOss.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he was disturbedabout the position and was asking that a small committeeshould be set up to examine the position and report tohim on his return.TRAVELFACILITIESW.M. (hh.) 111thConclusions,Minute 5.Reference was made to the decision reached by theWar Cabinet on Monday, 28th August, that Mr. R.R. Stokes&apos;application should be granted insofar as it rested on business grounds which could be substantiated.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he was strongly opposed

to Mr, Stokes&apos; request being granted.    If he were allowed to go, there would be pro tantodelay in the immense list of people who had strongclaims for travel facilities on compassionate grounds.    He saw no reason why this individual&apos;application should be granted.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said there was noquestion of the Cabinet affording him any specialtravelling facilities.   All the decision involvedwas that Mr, Stokes should be treated in the same way as any other business man with large engineeringinterests in Turkey, who on account of those interests, applied to visit Turkey.    Moreover, herather thought that action had already been taken.No formal conclusion v/as recorded.




</content>
</cab>
