<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 8-8</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
    [This Document  is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.                      Printed for the Cabinet.  May 1936.SECRET.CP. Ill (36).                                               Copy No.........                                 CABINET.Denunciation of the Ottawa  Agreement.     MEMORANDUM  BY THE  SECRETARY OF STATE  FOR  INDIA.    My colleagues will have learnt from the Press of two  recent events of some importance in the commercial relations of  this country and India, the resolution ofthe Legislative Assembly in favour of  the  denunciation of the Ottawa Agreement,and the presentation of  their Report by the Special. Tariff Board  presided over  bySir Alexander Murray on the rates of duty on Lancashire goods imported into India.    The Government of India are  pledged  to  accept  the  resolution  regarding the ottawa Agreement, and Lord Willingdon has told me that in the  course of the nextfew days the Government of India will ask me to give formal notice of denunciationaccompanied by a request for  the opening of negotiations for  a new Agreement.The terms of the existing Agreement provide for six months&apos; notice of terminationso that there is at least that period available  for  negotiations.   In agreement withthe Board of Trade, 1 have decided to leave  to the  Government of India the initiative in regard  to negotiation.    The Report of the Tariff Board is summarised in the Government of  India&apos;telegram  of 31st March, of which a  copy is appended.   The Report is not yetpublished and it is less favourable to  Lancashire than might  have been  hoped.I am awaiting the proposals of the Government  of India for action on it, but theposition is complicated first by the delay in the  presentation of  the Report whichhas made it impossible  to legislate on it in the Budget Session of the Assemblyjust coming to an end (the next session would be held in September); and secondlyby the fact that the  contractual obligation upon the  Government of India  to carryout the recommendations is based on a Supplementary Agreement which terminatesalong with the main Ottawa Agreement.  Meanwhile that is, until the denunciation of the Ottawa Agreement takes effect India&apos;s obligation remains  valid.                                                                       Z.  India Office,      1st May 1936.        Telegram -from Government of India, Commerce Department, dated                               31st March 1936.   822.  Cotton duties.  Murray Report was  received to-day and copy has been dispatched by Private Secretary to the Viceroy by to-day&apos;s air mail.   Following are recommendations:-     (a) Bordered, bleached, and coloured (excluding prints) cotton piece-goods            20 per cent, ad valorem.    (5) Plain  grey  cotton piece-goods 20 per cent, ad valorem, or 3^ annas per           pound, whichever is higher.    (c) Printed  goods in view of the fact that textile printing industry is in           infancy and sufficient costings not available, Board make no recommen-           dation regarding duties necessary on printed goods.    (of) Artificial silk and  artificial  silk and  cotton  mixed fabrics in  view of           dominating influence of Japanese on  prices in Indian markets, Board           is unable to make estimate of duties necessary  against British goods.    (e) Cotton yarn Board recommend 5 per cent, ad valorem or 1^ annas per           pound on counts of fifties and below and 5 per cent, on  counts over           fifties.471075  5.86

</content>
</cab>
