<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 85-86</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  April 1936.CONFIDENTIAL:                                                Copy No.CP. 122  (36).CABINET.THE ITALO-ABYSSINIAN DISPUTE.Views  of  M. Flandin on Policy  to be followed by the French  Government in        regard to the I talo-Abyssinian Dispute and other Questions.    I CIRCULATE to my colleagues the text of a record of a  conversation onthe 24th April betvVeen His Majesty&apos;s Minister in Paris and the French Ministerfor Foreign Affairs.                                                                   A.  E.    Foreign Office, April 27, 1936.    I had a long talk with M. Flandin after luncheon yesterday.  His conversa-tion took the  form of the somewhat empirical  &quot; tour d&apos;horizon,&quot; in which  heindulges so readily, and consequently nothing very precise emerged, but  I  have placed it on record as it  is conceivable that M. Flandin may still  be in officeafter the elections, and he at least made his own position fairly clear.    He began by saying that he was very apprehensive of the danger of  a Nazicoup in Austria which, though engineered from Berlin,  would take the form ofan internal movement;  scaremongers even predicted such  a  coup for the weekbetween the two French polling days 26th April and the 3rd May. What wouldwe do then ?  I said that I imagined we would consult with them in accordancewith our agreed  policy, but that in the present circumstances with the Italo-Ethiopian conflict still on the hands of the League, the range of action was very limited.  Well, M.  Flandin said, France would be obliged to take action.   Hehad had to  put  up with the reoccupation of  the Rhineland,  but no  FrenchGovernment on the top of that could allow the Anschluss to be effected unopposed.Everything depended  on us.  I disagreed, and said that in this  case it  seemedto me  that everything  depended on Mussolini.   It  was his turn  to make  a contribution to the settlement of Europe, and it was for the French Governmentto bring pressure to bear on him to do so.   He agreed and said that he was readyto exercise to the utmost such  influence as he possessed at Rome.  He would  do anything in the bounds of possibility to put  an end to the  war in Abyssinia.He  could not do  the  impossible,  but  if we had  any  reasonably  concreteplan to suggest, he  would do  his  best  to  persuade Mussolini  to accept  it.What  would our attitude be on the  11th  May?  I said that  we had made our position clear at  the last  meeting and that I did not foresee  any change..He then proceeded to  explain that we must not count on the French government being able to go very  far to meet us; even a Government of the Left after theelections.  I had  said, he added, that I had been disappointed by M. Boncour&apos;sspeech last Monday, that was a proof of the difficulty of his position; for therewas no greater idealist or champion of the League in any country than M. Boncour,       8561   [13129]
2but M. Boncour had made that speech, quite spontaneously, because he realised  pthat to-day it was a,s far as France would follow him, and he did not wish to  Iraise false hopes in any quarter.  The position in France had changed.  The Italo-  IAbyssinian problem had been  overshadowed by the German menace,  and eventhe parties of the Left, who had been most loyal to the League, now felt that theyhad to choose between  Italy and  Germany; without  hesitating they  chose  theformer, for much as they hated Mussolini they hated Hitler and Germany  far more, especially the extremists inspired by Moscow with violent hostility to  the nazi regime.  For this  reason it would be a mistake to count on support of  the left for a &quot; sanction &quot; policy.  It would be extremely difficult to maintain existingsanctions, impossible to extend them.     Could we not find any practicable solution?  Mussolini, who took the shortview, wanted immediate satisfaction.  We, taking the  long  view, and assured ofour position and interests in the future, could afford to make concessions.  I repliedthat concessions of principle were the most difficult concessions to make, and he knew how deeply we felt about this particular question in England.  As we weretalking frankly I must  tell him that we had been shocked by his intervention inthe discussion about the use of poison-gas it had  seemed to us to amount to a defence of the Italian action, which had roused the deepest resentment in England.He said that he had not meant it in that way. He had merely tried to pour oil ontroubled waters, and to prevent feelings being further inflamed M.  Flandin was clearly uneasy  at this point,  and  said that he was horrified at the  extent  of anti-British  feeling in France,  and anti-French  and anti-Italian  feeling  inEngland, which would render extremely difficult any co-operation in  dealing withthe problem of Austria,  to which he  then reverted.  I  remarked that  there appeared little hope of reviving the Stresa front at present if ever; and he thenwent on  to say that he foresaw  the necessity  of  a  regrouping of Powers aregrouping which was the idea underlying the regional pacts of the French peaceplan. France, England, Belgium and the Netherlands would have to ensure peace in the West, with or without Germany; France and Italy and, if we survived  thepresent crisis, Austria,  would have to hold the  South.  The Balkan and LittleEntentes,  supported  by  France and, he optimistically  hoped,  strengthened by arapprochement between  Yugoslavia and Italy, would have to guarantee the South-East.  As for the East,  Russia would have to look after that.  France had quiteenough troubles elsewhere, without having to look after Russia and Poland intothe bargain !    The programme, which he outlined, is certainly one which should keep  theQuai d&apos;Orsay and his other colleagues busy; but, accustomed though one is toquickly shifting scenes,  it is not so long since the Eastern Pact and. the Franco-Soviet  Treaty occupied the centre of the stage, and  I confess I was  surprised  bythe alacrity with which  M. Flandin proposed to disinterest himself in the fate of eastern Europe.    Throughout our conversation I found M. Flandin if anything more receptiveand less dogmatic than usual.   The fact is, however, that he, like  almost every other Frenchman at  the  present  moment, is  overwhelmed by the menace  ofGermany.  Beside this  preoccupation  every other problem  sinks into insignifi-cance : in their  heart of hearts they feel that they have  not been very clever aboutAbyssinia; once more  these mingled  feelings  of  panic and frustration ventthemselves in blind recrimination against us, and our alleged failure to fulfil ourLocarno pledges.  Unreasonable and exasperating as they are, this seems to  meto be the frame of mind prevalent  in France to-day, and we shall have to reckonwith it in laying our plans for the meeting at Geneva on the 11th May.                                                  H. LLOYD THOMAS.    Paris, April 24, 1936.

</content>
</cab>
