<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 197-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  May 1936.                    1 &amp;SECRET.                                                         CoPy N(KCP. 140(36).CABINET.THE INTERNATIONAL  SITUATION.    I CIRCULATE herewith, for the convenience of my colleagues, the records of conversations which I have had in the course of last week with other delegates at Geneva, together with brief records of the Council proceedings  regarding thedispute between Italy  and Abyssinia. Since  in  thus collecting these conversa-tions  under  one  cover an exceptional  course  is  being  pursued  which  onlyexceptional circumstances would warrant,  I  should  be  grateful if the greatest care could be taken to respect their very confidential character.                                                                    A.  E.    Foreign  Office,  May 16, 1936.                                  No.  1.(No.  50.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)                                        Geneva, May 10, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-         &quot; Turkish  Minister for Foreign Affairs asked to see me this morning,    when we had a general discussion on the  situation at this meeting of the    Council.  M. Aras, whom I found by no means unduly depressed, was clear    that on no pretext must any decision be taken at the Council this time.  It    was necessary at first to await  the formation of the new French  Government.    He thought  the best course would be to adjourn discussions of the Italian-    Ethiopian dispute sine die, leaving to the President of the Council the task    of calling that body together  in an emergency session whenever  he saw fit.    Actually this would probably not be before the last week in June. M. Aras    thought effect of this delay would be to give the Italians cause to think.         &quot; In  the   meantime,  Turkish  Minister for  Foreign Affairs thought     Committee of Eighteen should be called together and in some form or other     reaffirm existing sanctions, perhaps by instructing its experts to examine     their working afresh.  I  understood M. Aras thought meeting of Committee     of Eighteen necessary lest, if position were not clearly stated, some countries     might be tempted to start to raise sanctions; this was also the preoccupation     stated by M. Massigli in  a brief  conversation which I had with him this     morning.         &quot; Turkish Minister  for  Foreign  Affairs then spoke of  more  general     aspects of Mediterranean situation.  It was important, he argued, to bear     in mind that until a satisfactory agreement was reached between League and     Italy the latter country  remained under article 16, whether sanctions were     actually in force or not.   The  importance of this was that mutual assistance     provisions of article 16 also remained in force.  Within the next year Italy     would either  have to come to an  arrangement with other  Mediterranean     Powers through the League, which would  establish peace, or she would find       8608  [13232]                                                B
herself  in  extreme difficulty  owing  to  her internal  situation,  or signor mussolini would be compelled to embark upon  some further adventure.  in last-named event, which M. Aras  thought on the whole the  least probable,the adventure would be based either on Albania or Dodecanese or, as turkish minister for Foreign Affairs thought most probable,  it might be directed against Egypt or the Sudan.  In any  of these three events the mutual assistance  provisions of  the Covenant  would be  of  the greatest  value.Moreover, if Italy were aware that they continued in force, this would be animportant deterrent.    &quot; I replied that I found it hard to believe that Italy, having securedAbyssinia,  would risk loss of everything by attacking  the British Empire.To this M. Aras replied  that she certainly would not do so unless driven toit  by the combination of internal  difficulties and wild irresponsibility suchas he feared was now the characteristic of Italian people.    &quot; M. Aras went on to indicate what he would regard as  a satisfactoryMediterranean settlement.   There  should be a  pact between MediterraneanPowers and an agreement as to naval forces.   This the Foreign  Ministerseemed somewhat optimistically to  believe should be on basis of Italy havingone-third of Great Britain&apos;s naval forces, and each of the Powers of BalkanEntente having one-third of Italy&apos;s.    &apos;&apos; M. Aras continued that he thought it most important that Italy shouldbe made to feel her isolation and that  nobody should enter into conversations with her.   If Great Britain firmly took up this attitude, then  he was  quiteconfident no  other  Mediterranean Power  would act otherwise.  I assuredM. Aras that we had, in fact, no intention of entering into conversations with italy under 1906 treaty or,  indeed,  in independent conversations of any kind.    &quot; Two  features  impressed me  from  this conversation.   First, thatM. Aras did not seem to consider His Majesty&apos;s Governments prestige had suffered by recent events.  On the contrary, he assured me of support andfriendship  of Yugoslavia,  Turkey  and Greece.  Secondly,  M.  Aras scarcelymentioned  Germany,  and  for him clearly it is Italian dictator  only thatexists.&quot;                                   No. 2.(No. 54.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)     .                                  Geneva, May 10, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-        &quot; M. de Graeff, Dutch  Foreign Minister, asked to see me this evening    when he gave me some account of the meeting of neutral Powers, which had    taken place at Geneva to-day (Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Finland, Holland,    Switzerland and Spain).        &quot; The Foreign Ministers of all these countries, except Spain, are now in    Geneva, and M.  van Zeeland arrives to-night.        &quot; The neutral group, M. de Graeff explained, had decided in favour of    maintaining  the existing sanctions, and had also agreed that their repre-    sentatives on the Council  should  strongly  contest any attempt  that  the    Italian  representative might make to claim that Abyssinia had now no right    to be represented at Geneva.        &quot; M. de Graeff added, in confidence, that he had taken the view at the    meeting of neutral Powers that only course now left to the League, if it was    to preserve  its  dignity, was  to expel  Italy.  He added  that some  other    members of the neutral group had not fully shared his view, since they feared    that departure  of  Italy might  be followed by that of Switzerland and    Austria, with consequent dangers of  disintegration.    M. de  Madariaga,    whom I had seen earlier in the afternoon, thought it possible that Italy might    threaten withdrawal from the League if sanctions were continued.  In such    an eventuality,  M.  de  Madariaga appeared  to  favour the League  then    expelling Italy,  instead of awaiting her withdrawal at the end of two years.    Generally, there is an atmosphere of considerably greater determination than    at the last meeting of  the Council.&quot;
No. 3.(No. 55.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)Geneva, May 11,  1936.FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-    &quot; M. Paul-Boncour came to see me this morning immediately after his arrival at Geneva.    &apos;&apos; He seemed tired and depressed and full of  anxiety  for the future.He appears to think that Italy&apos;s withdrawal from the League can hardlynow be avoided,  and he is  impressed by dangers  of new constellation ofdissatisfied States, which may, he fears, be in process of formation, composedof Italy, Germany, Japan, Austria and  Hungary.    &quot; He described  briefly  interview which  French Ambassador had  had with Signor Mussolini in the middle of last week, at which representations of French  Government in regard to  any policy of annexation had passedunheeded.  He regretted that His Majesty&apos;s Government had not been ableto associate themselves with  this step.  He  also  recalled  reserves whichAmbassador had since made  on  behalf of  French Government  to SignorSuvich.    &quot; Italian  Government were now,  he thought, in a mood to contest boththe appearance of Italo-Abyssinian question on agenda of present session and representation of  Abyssinia on Council.  It would not be possible, hesaid, for Council to admit Italian thesis on either point, and if break with italy had to come, it was better that it should be on a point of procedure onwhich  Italy was  unmistakably in the wrong than on a point of substancewhere  there might be  room for argument.  But he clearly contemplatedprospect of Italy&apos;s withdrawal with the greatest distaste.    &apos;&apos; French  Government were, as a result  of the elections, in  a difficult position and  wished  to do  nothing to compromise  situation  for   their successors.   Unless, as he feared, Italians intended to force the issue now, hewould be content to leave things as they were until  new Government was in power.  In any event, he was anxious to  work in closest harmony with myself and to pursue our common course as calmly as possible.&quot;FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-    &quot; Portuguese Minister for Foreign Affairs and M. de Vasconcellos came to see me this morning to  discuss general situation.    &quot; I  found Portuguese  Minister  for Foreign Affairs  disturbed as toloss of prestige which he felt had been suffered by the League and (whichwas important for Portugal) by Great Britain.  He himself did not see whatwas to be gained by simply adjourning  all consideration of Italo-Ethiopiandispute until some later session of the Council.    &quot; I  asked him what he thought ought to  be done if  Council  were toproceed with consideration of the question now.   He replied that the Leaguehad now to make a choice between two courses.  It could either recognisethat it had failed in  the present dispute, that  collective security could notbe made  a reality in present circumstances, and that it  must therefore takestock of  its own situation and proceed to reform itself, or it could proclaimthat the  responsibility which had been  accepted by members of  the league in the present dispute  would  continue  to  be performed.   He obviouslypreferred the first course.     &apos;&apos; I  told him  that I  thought  there  were  twro things which  made itimprobable that  any such  choice could usefully be  made at the presentmoment.   The first  was that there was, as yet, no French Government whichwas capable of taking any definite step.  The second was that there was, atleast, the possibility of Italian action at the present Council, which wouldprecipitate a crisis on quite different lines.   There were some who  thought,M. Boncour amongst  them,  that we might  be faced  wdth withdrawal ofNo. 4.(No.  56.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)Geneva, May 11,  1936.[13232]B 2
Italy from the League either on a point of procedure (i.e., whether Abyssinianquestion should appear  on agenda or  whether  Abyssinian representative should sit on the Council) or, alternatively, upon refusal by members of theLeague of an Italian demand for immediate raising of sanctions.    &apos;&apos; Portuguese Minister  for Foreign  Affairs quite agreed that if therewere to be adjournment now, sanctions ought not to be raised for the present,but he thought it desirable that  the reason for  an adjournment  should bethe position of the French Government and considered that it was for french delegation themselves to propose it.&quot;                                   No.  5.(No. 57.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)                                       Geneva, May 11, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-        &apos;&apos; Colonel Beck asked to see me this morning, when we had a conversation    on international situation.  He said that his main preoccupation about Italo-    Abyssinian dispute was the same as  it had always been.   Its ultimate effect    upon international relations would depend upon its duration.  If it lasted    too long, it would inevitably bring serious complications in its train.  It had    already brought one in the shape of reoccupation of the Rhineland.   He    had,  therefore, urged  upon neutral  States, some of whom had  seemed to    visualise no final settlement of the dispute until Assembly in September, the    importance of trying to reach some results next month.  He did not suggest    for a  moment that sanctions should be raised  at  once,  though  they  were    not very popular  in  Poland.   There  was no  need for undue haste,  still    less for showing signs  of panic.   None the less, he thought it desirable that    we should try  and secure  some arrangements  at a special  session of the    Council in June.        &apos;&apos; M.  Beck expressed  himself as  very well  pleased  with  our note to    German Government.   It had had a good reception in Poland, and the Polish    Government were  particularly  gratified at  our reference to political  and    territorial status of Europe. This was just what everybody wanted to know    from Germany.  M. Beck added that his Ambassador at Berlin had reported    that Germany disliked two features of the note  in particular.    First, the    mention of Soviet Russia,  and,  secondly,  the form, which they considered    seemed to show that doubt was conceivable about Germany&apos;s good faith.        &quot; M. Beck added that he did not share these views.        &apos;&apos; M. Beck said that he had made certain enquiries, more particularly of    General Gombos,  who  was  personally known to him, about the rumours of    trouble in Austria. He had been unable to confirm that these rumours had    any present foundation.&quot;                                   No. 6.(No. 25.  Saving.)(Telegraphic.)                                       Geneva, May 11,  1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-         &apos;&apos; Ninety-second session of Council of League of Nations was opened this    afternoon.   It was the turn of the United Kingdom representative to preside.         &apos;&apos; On the adoption of the agenda of the session, the Italian representative    (Baron Aloisi) stated his desire to make  a declaration in regard to inclusion    in the agenda of the dispute between Italy and Ethiopia.         &apos;&apos; In accordance with the  established procedure, I then asked the repre-    sentative of Ethiopia (M. Molde Mariam) to come to the Council table.         &apos;&apos; Baron Aloisi said that  the  Italian delegation  could not agree to the    presence of the so-called Ethiopian representative  at  the  Council table.    There  was  no  semblance of organisation  of an  Ethiopian State,  and no    sovereignty other than Italian  sovereignty existed  in  Ethiopia.  He was,    therefore, unable to take part  in the discussion of this item in the agenda.
                                 5                               .   H3    &quot; Baron Aloisi then left the Council table.         &apos;    &apos;&apos; M. Wolde Mariam said that Ethiopia was a member of the League.She was not an aggressor,  but a victim of aggression.    Ethiopia had notviolated international law or any rules of international conduct.  She couldnot, therefore, be prevented from stating her case before the Council.    &apos;&apos; I  then  asked the  Council whether  the dispute between  Italy  and ethiopia should continue to figure in the agenda, and gave it as my opinionthat it should be included.  I emphasised that the question at present beforethe Council was  one of  procedure  only.   The  Spanish  representative(M. de  Madariaga) and  the Danish  representative  (M. Munch)  havingexpressed their concurrence, and no  member of the Council having dissented,the item was declared to stand.&quot;                                   No.  7.-(No. 63.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)                                      Geneva,  May 12, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-         &quot; I had a conversation with M.  Litvinov this morning in the course of    which  he expressed himself with  considerable frankness on present inter-    national situation.         &apos;&apos; As regards Italo-Abyssinian conflict, the League  would,  he thought,    be compelled in June to choose  between  two alternatives.  Either we must    press on with sanctions to the end, including  imposition of a blockade and    even closing of the Canal, or must determine to obtain what we could as a    price for dropping existing sanctions.  Only thus could the Emperor recover    his throne.  Soviet Government were prepared to agree to either of these two    courses.  If His Majesty&apos;s  Government  were to decide  for  the first, then    Soviet  Government were prepared to follow us  to the end.  If we decided    for the second, then we should  determine  what price we  wished to  obtain    for raising of  sanctions.  It was essential that Italy  should make some    contribution to the future security of Europe.  That contribution must be    both general and local.   Her future attitude to collective  security as a whole    must be  made clear.   Europe  must know on which side Italy stood.  Her    local contribution was  needed to  make even plainer her  attitude towards    Austria.  It was not enough to say that action would be taken in the event    of military aggression  by Germany since &apos;  Anschluss &apos; might come by other    means, and Italy must show herself ready to deal with it  by whatever means    it came.         &apos;&apos; M. Litvinov added that he had expressed  some such  views as these to    Baron  Aloisi last night.  Latter had not  unduly demurred  as to necessity of    Italy making some contribution.         &quot; M. Litvinov then reviewed the League&apos;s action in the  course of the last    seven months.   He laid the blame for the League&apos;s failure  squarely upon    M. Laval, whose actions in Rome in January 1935 and also at Geneva later in    the year were mainly responsible for what had followed. M. Litvinov was not    himself convinced that if the League had taken united action to close the Suez    Canal  to Italy last year there would have been war.  The League, however,    decided upon other lines of action, and these  had been proved  to be based    upon a miscalculation.   We had all  anticipated that the war in Abyssinia    would have lasted at least a year.  If it had, he had  no doubt that sanctions    would have played their part.  In the circumstances he was not so pessimistic    as to the future; the League had done more  on this occasion than it had done    in Manchuria.  After all, it was no small achievement for some  fifty nations    to have agreed to take economic action.  Next time they might be willing to    go further.         &quot; M. Litvinov  admitted that nations  could not be expected to take    military action in parts of the world where they had no  vital interest.   It    would be some time before the world reached that stage.   In  the meantime,    however, he contended vehemently that existing obligations of the Covenant
must be maintained, though article 16  could  be  interpreted as limited  to continue action such as had been taken in present dispute.   In addition,  ingiven areas, nations could undertake  limited  commitments  to  render eachother military assistance.  (This point closely resembles that expressed  tome by M. de Madariaga recently.)  M. Litvinov said he thought it essentialthat nations should make their position plain in respect of their Leagueobligations with the least possible delay, so that at September Assembly theLeague could see its future clearly.     &quot; M. Litvinov  then  spoke  of  Germany.  He  expressed himself  as generally satisfied with terms of our note,  although some points might-havebeen put more crisply.  He hoped, however, that  we should now leave theGermans to answer  it.  It would, he was  convinced, be a great mistake  tofollow up our  questions  by anything in the nature of a ministerial  visit,because we should then become entangled in a negotiation and the significance of our questions would become blurred.  It was the  essence of any negotiationthat there must be some modification in each point of view, and we should soon be telling the Germans which questions we were interested in and  which wewere not.  This was a prospect which M. Litvinov  did  not welcome.  Ingeneral, Soviet Foreign Minister was at no pains to conceal his apprehensionregarding Germany&apos;s intentions.&quot;                                   No. 8.(No. 61.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)  R.                                   Geneva; May 12, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-        &apos;&apos; At opening of private meeting of  Council this afternoon Secretary-    General stated that  he had had a visit from  Baron Aloisi at noon to-day.    Baron  Aloisi had said that under orders from Italian Government he  was    leaving Geneva immediately with his delegation.  M. Avenol had asked  him    the significance of this step.  Baron Aloisi had replied that he was unable    himself to  make any statement  on this point.  He had  received very    summary instructions and he was merely carrying them out.        &apos;&apos; Council then made necessary arrangements for presentation of reports    for which Italian representative was rapporteur.        &apos;&apos; Agenda of meeting, the dispute  between Italy and Abyssinia,  was    adopted.        &quot; In public session I informed  Council as President that as a result of    exchange of views between various members of  the Council I would submit a    resolution on their behalf.  Text of this resolution is contained in my  imme-    diately following  telegram.        &quot;Abyssinian  representative (M.  Wolde  Mariam) then invited  his    secretary to read  a declaration.  Abyssinian Government requested Council    to condemn new claim of Italy to suppress by violence a member of the League.    They asked Council to apply at last article 16 in its entirety so that in future    all States, both great and small, might be protected from aggression.   It  was    a tragic  moment for Abyssinia  and a  grave  situation for  the League of    Nations.   The future and existence of the League might depend on the nature    of the resolution which the Council adopted to-day.        &apos;&apos; Argentine  representative  (Sr. Ruiz Guinazu) said  that in  view of    present serious situation and in order to safeguard fundamental principles of    the Covenant, Argentine Government accepted the resolution, but  made a    reservation in regard to adjournment of discussion.        &quot; Chilean representative  (Sr.  Rivas  Vicuna)  accepted  proposal  for    adjournment.  He declared that, without prejudging substance of problem.    Chilean Government was  of opinion that, since war  had  come to  an end,    sanctions should be raised as having no  further object.  Sanctions hurt the    countries applying them as well as the country against which they were    applied.  In raising, sanctions Chilean Government thought that a contribu-    tion would be made to solution of economic depression.        &quot; Ecuadorean representative (Sr. Zaldumbide) approved adjournment    of substance of question, but was unable  to subscribe to last paragraph of
resolution.   Ecuadorean Government considered that as soon as Italy  had declared herself ready to enter into  negotiations, the situation should havebeen simplified by the raising of sanctions.  Conciliation could not proceedunder pressure of sanctions.  Ecuadorean Government  would not associateitself with maintenance of  sanctions,  which  were  only one  means of accelerating the end of hostilities.  He admitted that principle of sanctionshad been laid down by common agreement, but pointed out  the governments had been asked individually to enact decrees and were perfectly free to takea decision in regard to the application of sanctions.  They were equally  free to decide to raise them, and it was for this reason that Ecuador had not thought it  necessary to communicate to Committee of Eighteen its decisionon the subject.  He would vote for adjournment subject to this reservation.No further observations being made, I declared that, subject to declarationswhich had  been made, the resolution represented the general opinion of theCouncil and was adopted.     &quot; Council then adjourned.&quot;                                   No.  9.(No. 62.  L.N.)(Telegraphic.)  R.                                   Geneva, May 12,  1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-         &quot;  Following is text referred to in my immediately preceding telegram :          &quot;  &apos; The Council, having met to  consider the dispute between Italy and    Ethiopia, recalls the conclusions reached and decisions in this matter in    League of  Nations since 3rd October, 1935,  is of opinion that  further time    is necessary to permit its members  to consider the situation created by grave    new steps taken by the Italian Government, decides to resume  deliberations    on this subject on 15th June, and considers that in the meantime there is    no  cause for modifying measures previously adopted in collaboration by    members of the League.&apos; &quot;                                  No. 10.(No. 26.  Saving.)(Telegraphic.)                                       Geneva, May 12, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-         &quot; M. Pouritch  asked to see  me this  evening,  when  he spoke  with    remarkable candour about the present international situation.   He was well    satisfied with the present meeting of the Council.  The important considera-    tion, however, was what was to happen in June.  Much would depend upon    His  Majesty&apos;s Government.  M.  Pouritch had  had  a conversation  with    M. Blum in Paris, which had lasted nearly two hours, and the  latter had    stated  that his policy would be a return to the  old tradition  of France     co-operation with Britain and with the Little Entente. M. Blum had been    particularly emphatic as to his desire to work closely with His Majesty&apos;s    Government,  and had expressed a  hope that  he  might see  me on my way    through Paris. M. Pouritch was confident that we could count on  M. Blum&apos;s    co-operation in any course which we might decide to take at the next meeting    of the  Council.         &quot; I  replied that I was fully conscious of the importance of the  next-    Council meeting, but I was not in a position to tell M. Pouritch now what    lines we should then propose to take.  Clearly very careful consideration    would  be necessary.   M.  Pouritch agreed, but maintained   that it was    imperative now to look far ahead in deciding our immediate conduct.  In his    view the future of the Mediterranean was at stake.  I would be aware that    the prestige  of  His  Majesty&apos;s Government  had  suffered during  recent
months.  As an example of this M. Pouritch mentioned how the GreekGovernment, despite its  continued reliance on His Majesty&apos;s Government,had made it plain at the  last meeting of the Balkan Entente that they couldonly join in action with the other Balkan Powers on condition that Albaniaw7as  not opposed to such action.  I would appreciate that this  meant thatGreece was not prepared  to act against Italy.     &quot; I replied that I was not myself  unduly perturbed about statementsas to our prestige.  It was quite true that we were disappointed with the outcome of  the League&apos;s efforts in this dispute, but  there had been other times in history when our prestige was supposed to have suffered, and I saw no reason why, in this instance, when our action had not been taken on behalfof British interests,  but  only collectively with the  League on behalf of  itsjoint responsibility, we should be expected to hang our heads.     &quot; M. Pouritch, however, continued to maintain that however just myarguments,   the  fact   remained  that   people  respected   force,  and sign or Mussolini had shown force.  He had defied  the League and done so with success.  Whatever the  future  might hold,  he  was  convinced that signor Mussolini would  not remain content with his  present  achievements.He would be an extremely uncomfortable neighbour hereafter, both in  europe and in Africa.  All therefore depended on the future of the Mediterranean.If Signor Mussolini could assert his  superiority there, and maintain that position, then, if he might speak frankly, wdiat was the future  of Egypt andthe Sudan ?     &quot;I replied  that, so far&apos;as I was  aware, there  was  no question  ofSignor Mussolini having a superiority  in the Mediterranean.   I did notbelieve for a moment that the Duce would be so foolish as to take any actionagainst us, but I must make it clear that if we had advocated no more vigorousaction at Geneva it was not because we had any doubt as to our own positionin a military sense in the Mediterranean.     &apos;&apos; M. Pouritch said that however that might be, the impression in some quarters was otherwise, and he feared that Signor  Mussolini,  elated by his present victory,  would  give much  trouble.   He  scouted the  idea that marshall Badoglio  would have  any great  difficulty in  subduing Abyssinia.All previous colonial calculations must  be modified  by the experience  of modern weapons.   Admittedly,  Signor Mussolini would be short of  money,but so was Herr Hitler, and that did not prevent the latter from building  upthe strongest army in the world.     &quot; In short, M. Pouritch wished to emphasise to me that  inevitably, ina year  or two at most, we should have trouble with Signor Mussolini, who,in the  meanwhile, would be an  increasingly provocative neighbour.  would it not be better to deal with the situation now, and  have done  with it, when we should have a friendly France, the support of Yugoslavia and Turkey,and  Herr Hitler himself not ready to make trouble 1  A year or two hence the moment  might be much less  suitable for us.     &quot; I replied that if  M. Pouritch meant by that  why didn&apos;t  we go towar, His Majesty&apos;s Government had no intention whatever of resorting toany  such course.  Indeed, I thought that it was Signor Mussolinhs  shrewdappreciation of this fact that  had been of considerable  service to  him inrecent  months.     &apos;&apos; M. Pouritch admitted that this was so, and added that he  was  not fora moment suggesting that  we should  pick a quarrel.   At the same  time itwas surely necessary now to show steady and stiff resistance. Otherwise, thefuture of the League and the outlook for Mediterranean countries would begrim indeed.  Speaking for his Government, he therefore ventured to advise that at the  least  we should decide at the next meeting of the Council tomaintain the existing sanctions.   If we  would do this and adjourn  alldiscussion of the subject until the following September, the result would beto weaken  Signor  Mussolinhs authority.   His own people would begin tothink  the capture of Addis Ababa a poor recompense for the  continuedsuffering which prolonged  sanctions would  impose.   It was quite  true thatthere was now no Abyssinia to work for, but there was still the Emperor andthere was still the aggression.  The League ought to show, backed by the newFrench Government, a steady resistance to such aggression.  It could refuseto recognise the new Government of Abyssinia, and some of the  Powers might
also send Ministers to be accredited  to  the  Emperor  wherever he might ultimately take up  residence.  M. Pouritch specially urged the  importanceof maintaining the sanction front, and then, if Signor Mussolini were foolishenough to take provocative action, we should all be united and prepared.     &quot; In any event, as the representative of  a nation which had a  deepfriendship and respect for His Majesty&apos;s Government,  he wanted to makeit clear that, in his view, the future of  much in addition to Abyssinia would depend upon the next meeting of the Council.  He saw a vision already of italian black troops in Europe.   His own anxiety,  as the representative ofa small Power, would be easily understood.   Since in  June  England andFrance would be closer together than they  had  been at  any  time sinceM. Lavahs foolish policy had been entered upon, now was the moment steadilyto maintain  our attitude, and we should then be confident of the support ofthe League  as a whole.&quot;                                  No.  11.(No. 27.  Saving.)(Telegraphic.)                                       Geneva, May 13, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-         &quot; M. Titulescu asked to see me this evening, when he spoke of the out-    come of the present meeting of the Council, and insisted that the solidarity    shown by the Powers represented was remarkable. He also expressed himself    as well pleased with the meeting  of  the Little Entente  and Balkan Powers    which had recently taken place at Belgrade.  A similar meeting was to be    held at Bucharest between the 6th and 8th of next month, in order that these    Powers might consult before the next meeting of the Council.  In addition    to this, staff conversations had been arranged.         &apos;&quot;&apos; M. Titulescu stated that he wished to repeat to me officially on behalf    of his Government what he had already mentioned to me personally, that the    Roumanian Government were fully prepared to follow His Majesty&apos;s Govern-    men! in any course which they thought fit to pursue in  the present dispute.    They were willing to maintain sanctions.  They  were even willing to add to    them, and if they had to choose between following France and Great Britain    in present circumstances,  they would follow the latter.   He had made this    clear to M. Paul-Boncour.         &quot; M. Titulescu said that it was very difficult  to determine what was to be    done in the Abyssinian affair.  He  could,  see no solution which gave any    credit to the League.  After  all,  we  did want Italian  collaboration  in    Europe, particularly for Austria.  The Roumanian Foreign Minister several    times repeated his apprehensions as to Germany&apos;s intentions in Austria. Yet    what kind of Italy was it with  which  we were expected to  collaborate?    What confidence could be placed in her ?  In all the circumstances it might be    wisest,  when the Council met  in June, to declare that in no circumstances    would the League recognise what  Italy had done in  Abyssinia,  to maintain    Abyssinia&apos;s independent  membership  of the League,  but to  admit  that    sanctions had failed to achieve their  objective, and to fix a date upon which    they would be raised.  M. Titulescu expressed no enthusiasm for this course,    and  repeated that he was willing to follow  any  other which His Majesty&apos;s    Government might consider preferable.         &quot; The Roumanian Foreign Minister went on to express some anxiety at    recent expressions of public opinion in the United Kingdom.  Was it really    our intention to take no further part in European affairs 1   Were we going-    back into isolation?  If so, it would  seem rather hard on those nations who    had  done all we had  asked of them in the present dispute.  Why  had    Roumania lost  so much trade in this dispute ?   It was  in  an endeavour  to    prove that the  Covenant would work.,. Now were they to be told that they    must be left in the future without  any help %  If this were to be the position,    however,  M. Titulescu maintained that he would prefer  to be told of it and    be enabled to make what arrangements were possible with Germany.       [13232]                                                     &apos; c
     v I replied that so far as I was aware no Government announcement ofany  kind had been made as  to our  future attitude to the League and our future obligations under the Covenant.   Nor could there be one for sometime to come.  We  had to consider carefully the lessons of the last fewmonths, consult  with the Dominions and determine our policy.  What didM. Titulescu suggest would be the proper basis for future League action?     &apos;&apos; He replied that article 16 should  remain,  and  that economic andfinancial sanctions should be automatic on the League&apos;s declaration of the aggressor.  He would not, however, be so foolish as to ask Britain  to fight for  Roumania.  There would have to be regional pacts  for given areas, inwhich nations&apos; vital interests were at stake, and where, in consequence, theywould fight.  But it was necessary for His Majesty&apos;s Government to face thisquestion.  Could they really remain outside Central Europe.  The  defenceof France.and  Belgium was, he supposed,  a  vital  British interest.  if germany attacked Czechoslovakia, France was bound to attack Germany, andGermany would consequently attack France.   We surely  could not hold thatin those circumstances we should do nothing ?   In other words, it was difficultto believe that there .could be a war in Europe  which was not a european war. He quite realised that  public opinion in various countries could not beexpected to  appreciate this argument, but it was essential that governments should  have  it  in  mind.   I  did  not  think it  necessary to  express toM.  Titulescu the  doubt  that  I personally feel  as to  whether,  in thecircumstances which he mentioned, France would, in fact, march  to the help of Czechoslovakia.     &apos;&apos; Reverting  to  the  Italo-Abyssinian dispute, M.. Titulescu  said he presumed that it was owing to the attitude of France and to our own militaryweakness that we had not resorted  to military sanctions.   If France had shown willingness to join with us,  would we  have closed  the  Canal?   Ireplied that this was a question which no human being could answer becauseits hypothesis seemed to me so unreal.  M. Titulescu rejoined that  Sir samuel hoare had  told him that if  France had given such a lead, we should haveacted.  In any  event, he  presumed that we were not spending  so  many millions now on armaments merely for fun, but because  we realised we hadto put  our  defences in order in all parts of the world against challengesthat might  come.  If Germany were to  obtain the hegemony of  Europe,  if she  were then to make friends with Japan,  as  was perfectly possible, howvery anxious  the outlook would  be  for the British Empire.     &quot;In a  passing  reference to a Mediterranean pact,  M. Titulescu  statesthat the Yugoslav Government were not  anxious for such a pact.  They did: not  wish to  negotiate with Italy at the present time.  M. Titulescu contestedthis view, and  suggested  that  the  importance  of this  pact would not beItaly&apos;s signature, but the signature of the other  Mediterranean Powers.  Atpresent these  were held together  by paragraph 3 of article 16.  If sanctionswere lifted, however,  that union would disappear.  A Mediterranean pact,which Italy could join if she wished, would remove this weakness.     &quot; In conclusion, M. Titulescu summed up his policy as being a wish tosee  the British  Empire the dominant Power  in world politics, and France,on account  of the more binding engagements she was prepared to take, thepredominating Power in continental politics.&quot;                                  No. 12.          Record of a Conversation with M. van Zeeland on May 14.    I HAD two conversations of considerable length with M. van Zeeland during his visit  to Geneva,  and  found  him,  like  everyone else  here,  considerablypreoccupied at the confusion into which the League&apos;s failure over Abyssinia hadthrown the  policies  of the  Powers who were the  principal supporters of theLeague.  If matters were to be righted, M. van Zeeland maintained,  then this could only be as the outcome of the initiative of one of the great two Westerndemocracies, or  preferably  of  both together.   The sooner this  initiative  could
be taken the better, for the longer the period of uncertainty the more the dictatorPowers would gain.  M. van  Zeeland added  that the real purpose of his visit to Geneva was to have a conversation with  me,  and to try to learn in whatdirection the mind of His Majesty&apos;s Government was working;  for I knew howanxious he was to keep his policy closely in step with ours.    2.  M. van Zeeland was very emphatic upon the seriousness of the hour; a tremendous responsibility lay upon His Majesty&apos;s Government.   If we  would determine our course and pursue it firmly, all would yet be  well,  for the bulkof the other nations would line  up  behind us. But if we  appeared hesitant ordismayed, then the outlook  for  Europe was gloomy indeed.    3.  I replied that it was all very  well to say that everything depended uponthe initiative of  His Majesty&apos;s  Government  and perhaps France  also,  and I realise the responsibilities upon  us.  None the less it was easier  to say that theinitiative  must be taken than  to  decide upon the  proper  course in presentconditions.  It was inevitable that those  countries who  had  based their  policyupon the League should be thrown into confusion by the League&apos;s failure in this instance.  We had always been conscious  of  this  danger,  and this was one ofthe reasons why we had done our best to make action by  the League a success in this instance.  There seemed to me to be two separate though related problems to envisage.  First the  solution of the Italo-Abyssinian dispute,  and secondlythe future of the League itself.  As  to the  second, we were already engaged upona study of the lessons to be learnt from the events of the last seven months.  this study would necessitate consultation with  the  Dominions, but  in due course, andsome time  before  the meeting of the  Assembly in the autumn,  we hoped to bein a position to make clear the position of His Majesty&apos;s  Government.  It wouldthen be for the other nations to determine whether they were prepared to  followus or not.    4.  M. van Zeeland replied  that he perfectly  agreed with my analysis, andwas much relieved  to hear that Flis Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared to takea definite line as to the League&apos;s future. His own  view was that it was essentialthat a nation&apos;s obligations to fight should  be limited to those areas  in respect ofwhich it had a vital interest.  He would like to see the League reorganised upona two-storey  foundation.  To  do this  it was not necessary  to  seek to amend theCovenant, which M. van Zeeland, together with most Ministers here, regards asan almost insuperable task.  All that  was needed could probably be obtained byan  amendment  of  the resolutions of 1921.  There might be  two storeys in the structure of League obligations  in  the future.  The  first should be universallyshared by all members, and should be limited to economic and  financial sanctions.The second would  consist in regional undertakings to give military assistance.M.  van Zeeland gave an example. He did not know whether  or  not the british people were willing to fight for Austria.  That  was  the affair of the British people and their Government, but, if theytwere, there  would no doubt be greater security in Europe. If not, it would be possible, under  the scheme he visualised,  definatly to exclude such an  obligation from their commitments.    5.  M.  van Zeeland  then turned to  a discussion of the  Italo-Ethiopiandispute.  He shares the view almost universally held here that the major portionof the blame must be laid upon the French Government in general and  M.  Lavalin particular for their failure to co-operate whole-heartedly.   As to the future.his inclination was clearly  to  liquidate  the matter as  speedily  as possibleconsistent with saving some  vestige of the League&apos;s reputation.   It has, indeed,been remarkable to note during the present session  of the Council how it is thosenations who are most obsessed by fear of  Germany who  are most eager to havedone with  the Italo-Abyssinian  dispute.   Though  this is no  doubt natural, theextent of this preoccupation is steadily growing. Denmark and Holland are theonly two  of  Germany&apos;s neighbours to show  a decided  determination to keepsanctions in force.                                                      ANTHONY EDEN.    Geneva, May 14, 1936.          Record of a Conversation with M. van Zeeland on May 14.(Very Confidential.)    M. VAN ZEELAND emphasised that time was now working against us in sofar as the German problem was concerned.   Not only was Germany&apos;s rearmament      [13232]                                                     c  2
 proceeding apace,  but her occupation  of  the Rhineland was becoming both an accomplished and  an accepted  fact.   I would realise how serious that was  for Belgium, and how preoccupied public opinion in that country was with  the problem.  I replied that we fully appreciated this, but that none the less Belgium was not left without any security at all.  We had made it plain in the London agreements, as I had done previously in the House of Commons, that His Majesty&apos;s Government would come  to the aid of  Belgium  or  France if either  of these countries was the  victim  of an unprovoked aggression.   M. van Zeeland said that he fully appreciated the value of this, and also of the Staff talks which had taken place in London.  In this connexion, M. van Zeeland  was  anxious  to put to me very confidentially a preoccupation which had long been present to his mind. Was it not greatly to the interest of both our countries that Staff conversations should take place  between Belgium  and  the United Kingdom apart from  the tripartite  conversations which  had taken place in London?   He was confident that the French Government could have no objection  to such  a course, since they themselves, he understood, made  it plain that what they hoped for from His Majesty&apos;s  Government was not  help for themselves in case of need, but help  for Belgium.     M. van Zeeland explained that he did not suggest any formal Staff meetings such as would necessitate visits from senior officers from one country to the other. All that was required could very well  be  carried out, and M. van Zeelancl was convinced very usefully carried out,  by the military attaches.  M. van Zeeland gave me certain instances of the kind of subjects which he thought could thus be usefully discussed.   There was  the question  of  air co-operation.  The Belgian air force was admittedly  small, but it was not insignificant, and it was clear that if it was to play its role to  best advantage it should be able.to do so in close co-operation with British forces.   There was the question of landing grounds, and of the type of aircraft used  by the Belgian forces.  It might be of advantage if consideration could be given  to the possibility of the types being  used by the Belgian  air force  being  similar to those employed  by us.   Again  there were strategic considerations.  As to the part to be played by Belgium, he would not conceal from me that  for political reasons he did not wish the Belgian army to operate between two sections of  the French army.  If any British military  forces were  to come to the aid of Belgium  in the event of  an unprovoked  aggression, then he would like  them to be on the left of the  Belgian forces, whereas French troops would be on  the right of  the Belgian army.  Or, alternatively, if Britain was not going to send any military forces, then he would wish  the Belgian armies to remain on the left of the French armies, and British support to be given at sea. M. van Zeeland also mentioned the question of Belgian coast defence, which I told him that I understood had been mentioned at the Staff conversations in London.    2.  Finally, M. van Zeeland mentioned one further problem which might be discussed between us, namely, that of munitions.  An important part of Belgian munitions plant was stationed in  territory near to the German frontier,  which would have to be abandoned early in  the event of a Belgian invasion.  It  might therefore be useful if  we could have discussions on the  question of munitionsupply.    3.  The Belgian Prime Minister stressed that, in making these suggestions, he was not contemplating asking us to undertake any new political commitment, but since we had undertaken to go to the help  of  Belgium in the event of her being the victim of an unprovoked aggression, he could not help feeling that there was a great deal to be said for making these arrangements in advance.    4.  I replied that I would certainly report what he had said to my colleagues, but in the meanwhile there was a preliminary observation which I wished  to make.  M. van Zeeland would recall that the German Government had specifically asked us whether we were prepared, in the event of a pact of mutual assistance being negotiated to take the place of Locarno, to open  these  Staff conversations to Germany also, and we had replied that we were.    5.  M.  van Zeeland maintained that this would cause no difficulty.  He had already had Staff conversations  with  the French and  had on  two  occasions been approached by the Germans and asked whether he would have  such conversations with them also.  On both occasions he had at once replied &quot;  yes,&quot; but,  in fact, nothing further had materialised.  He would not be at all embarrassed at havingconversations  with  Germany  also, but he&apos; was  quite convinced  that, in  fact, Germany would never engage in them, for she  could not  do  so without giving
                                  No. 13.(No.  29.  Saving.)(Telegraphic.)  En clair.                             Geneva, May 13, 1936.    FOLLOWING from Secretary of State :-        &quot; M. Politis. came to see me this morning, when he displayed consider-    able anxiety as to  the future in the Mediterranean.  His Government were    anxious for some information both as to the policy and intentions  of His    Majesty&apos;s Government.   Rumours were current that some drastic change in    British  policy in respect of the Mediterranean was imminent.  It had even    been reported to him that the Prime Minister had stated that the problem in    the Mediterranean was now over and that British anxiety as to  the future    was oceanic.        &apos;&apos; Upon my asking M. Politis what he  inferred  from this,  he replied    that the implication was clearly that His Majesty&apos;s Government no longer    had the same interest in the Mediterranean owing to the  changed  conditions    in that  sea, and that they proposed to  secure their route  to the East via the    Cape.  If this were in truth our policjr,  then clearly a fundamental reorienta-    tion was  called for  from  all the other Mediterranean Powers.  I replied    that there was  not a word of truth in the remarks attributed to  the Prime    Minister, nor had our policy in respect of the Mediterranean  undergone any    modification whatever.   M. Politis expressed himself  as much relieved by                                     1.3certain information, and that information would not be evidence of her peacefulintentions.    6.   Finally, I told M. van Zeeland that while his suggestion would certainly be carefully considered by us,  I was very  doubtful whether the present was thebest moment for entering upon such conversations.  We were trying hard to get a negotiation going as a result of which a new agreement would, we hoped, be arrived at with Germany, and I feared that any intimation that we were engaging in these conversations  with Belgium might  be  seized upon by  the  GermanGovernment as a pretext to return an unfavourable reply.   I would, however,consider carefully what M. van Zeeland had said, and let him have a reply indue course.    7.   The Belgian Prime Minister told me that the elections  in his country would take place shortly.  He was personally in  a somewhat peculiar position,since he was not a member of any political party,  and there were elements in hisnational Government who were now engaged in a party campaign  against eachother.  This did not concern him.  In fact,  each of  the parties was claiming credit for the  improvement in Belgiunhs national prosperity which had  taken place.As far as the future was concerned, he w^as doubtful  whether or not  he would continue as Prime Minister.   He had  only undertaken to serve  for a year, andthat year was now over, and he was not very anxious to continue.   In any eventhe would certainly not continue except upon terms.    8.   I  replied  that  I was very perturbed  to hear of the  possibility thatM. van Zeeland might not continue to be available to co-operate with us.  I knew that I was speaking for all my colleagues if I said that, frankly, we viewed withdismay the prospect of losing him, for his  collaboration in this difficult time hadbeen  quite  invaluable.    9.   M. van  Zeeland  replied  that he much appreciated  the kindness and sympathy  with which he had consistently been treated by  myself and  by HisMajesty&apos;s  Government as a whole.  He had  not yet taken his final decision, andhe could tell me, confidentially, that the King of the Belgians was pressing himvery strongly to remain.  All must depend,  however, on a variety of circumstances,and on whether the terms, upon which he would insist in order to continue &quot;usefullyhis present work, would be accepted or not.                                                      ANTHONY EDEN.    Geneva, May  14, 1936.
this assurance.  He remained, however, gravely troubled about the prospects of the meeting on the 15th June.    &quot; He believed that sanctions still had a certain value. By the 15th Junethat value would have diminished, and after that meeting he thought it likelyto become negligible.  Nations  were  beginning  to  withdraw  from the sanctions  front one  by  one, and  this would prove the most unsatisfactoryending possible to the League&apos;s present endeavour.  It was essential that weshould face realities.  Unhappily, League action  had not saved Abyssinia.It was better, therefore, to admit this fact and  to seek some  constructiveissue for present embarrassments.  I would be aware of the extent to whichHis Majesty&apos;s Governments prestige had suffered on  account of the events of the last few months.  French prestige had, moreover, suffered more still.and for anyone who cared  for the only things that made civilisation worthwhile, the diminishing authority of the two great Western democracies wasa source of acute anxiety.  We must have no illusions; with the passage  oftime Signor Mussolini  would become more  and more insolent,  unless some means  were  found  to check  him  by  making  it  clear  that the  otherMediterranean Powers were in unison.    &quot; M. Politis then mentioned a recent incident when the pupils of a schoolin Corfu had telegraphed to Signor Mussolini asking him to take over the island.  This was but a straw, but it had its significance.    &quot; In  addition,  Italian  and  German  propaganda were  both  active.M.  Politis could not help thinking that it was  time that His  Majesty&apos;sGovernment took steps to counter the effects of this propaganda.  He himself had never had any doubt that the British fleet was fully capable of dealingwith the  Italian fleet.  But there  were many  rumours to the contraryassiduously disseminated by Italy, and what in the last resort mattered wasnot the truth, but what people believed.  If the  nations became  convincedthat Britain was unwilling  or unable to defend her vital interests, therewould in  the end be no means of proving  that they were wrong, save  by military action.   To avoid this dilemma it  was imperative to manifest our confidence.  M. Politis  gave an example of German  propaganda when  he stated that a  German newspaper had recently  published an article  to theeffect that, while we were rapidly building machines for our new air force,we could not get pilots.  We wanted 1,200,  and could  scarcely get half that number.   I told M.  Politis that he  would appreciate that there was not a word of truth in that allegation, and that the recruiting of pilots constitutedno difficulty at all.  M.  Politis replied that he was not  at all surprised at myreply, but that it was not enough that he was convinced.  It was surely time that His Majesty&apos;s Government, themselves took steps to counter  propaganda which sought to establish our decadence.    &apos;&apos; In his view the solution of the present difficulty  was to  be found  ina Mediterranean pact.  If His Majesty&apos;s  Government and France  wouldjointly come forward and make clear that in their  view the present situationin the Mediterranean was unsatisfactory and must be remedied,  and proposea joint mutual assistance pact in the Mediterranean for that purpose, theywould at  once  receive  the enthusiastic and unanimous support of all the balkan States.  Such a  pact once negotiated  between His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment, France and the Balkan States could be open  to Italy.  It was certainlydoubtful if Italy would sign it, but in any event the  negotiation of  such a pact and the Anglo-French solidarity  thus  displayed  could not but have a salutary effect upon  Italy.   Something of this kind must surely be done ifthe present illusion of  a steadily weakening France and Britain  was to  bedispelled.   To-day,  His Majesty&apos;s Government  was too much like a boxerin the ring who did  nothing but receive blows.    &quot; Germany was to-day very active in the Balkans.  She was, for instance,making overtures to Yugoslavia,  and offering the latter protection  against italy.  Of course, the  Yugoslavs would not be so easily  seduced.  their confidence in His Majesty&apos;s Government was great, and the Prince Regentplayed a  considerable  part in maintaining that confidence.  (Within thelast few hours. I received a message from the Yugoslav Prime Minister whichthe Yugoslav representative here assures me comes, in fact, from  Prince Paulhimself, to the effect that great anxiety is being felt  in Belgrade  at the apparent  uncertainty of  British  policy.)  M.  Politis maintained  that  if
                                 3 5before 15th June His Majesty&apos;s Government and the French Government could make a  joint declaration in favour of a Mediterranean pact, and receive, asthey would, an immediate  response from the Balkan Powers, this would beinvaluable in re-establishing the situation with which the Council would be confronted.   If a  new venture assuring peace in the Mediterranean could now be  launched, means could  be  found under cover of it to liquidate the abyssinian affair,  but if we were to allow matters to drift, M. Politis couldscarcely  exaggerate  the  anxiety with which  he  viewed the future in theMediterranean.     &apos;&apos; In reference to Germany, M. Politis maintained that it was neither in southern nor in Eastern  Europe that Germany would launch her attack.  if in truth she sought, and he was  convinced  she  did, for the hegemony ofEurope, why, after all, should she  attack in the south?   No military actionthere was  necessary.  By  the  help  of Nazi propaganda  Austria musteventually be hers.   That was decided already, and then by similar propa-ganda she would stir up the German minority in Czechoslovakia.   The wormwould gnaw the apple  silently, but none the less effectively, and ultimatelyit would be rotted.  But to achieve this Germany need not move a  soldier.Roads were not being built towards the south; aerodromes were not being constructed  in the east; gun emplacements were  not  being built  on  the czechoslovak frontier.   All these activities were  on the Dutch, the belgian and now on the French frontiers.  What, after all, would Germany gain bya war in the east or south if she knew that when  she had finished with thisshe had  to  face the two great Western democracies, by then thoroughlyalarmed and hastily rearming ?  On the contrary, he was convinced that whilegiving every indication of being occupied elsewhere, Germany&apos;s efforts whenit was made would  be directed against the only two Powers that could preventher domination of Europe.     &apos; An interesting feature of this  conversation was that M.  Politis was at no pains to  conceal that it was the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwhich interested him most at this time.  I am convinced that  his preoccu-pation with the Mediterranean  was genuine.  He had all the  appearance of a sensitive, and even frightened, householder who fears that the policemanhas changed his beat at the near approach of the burglar.  He is reluctant to believe it as  yet, but the fears which he expresses so frankly are probablyshared to a lesser  degree by his tougher colleagues in the Balkan Entente.     &quot; The  insidious  effects of M. Laval5s policy and of  the Paris proposalsof last December are in truth only just beginning to appear.  Those countries and  those  politicians  whose  policy  was  based  upon  full  Anglo-french -operation find their judgment confused by France5s instability, and their confidence  undermined  by  continuous  German  and  Italian  propagandadirected to show that the British  lion to-day has neither tooth nor claw.55TR  2847/125/67]                  No. 14.                    Despatch to Sir H. C hilt on (Madrid).(No. 244.)Sir,                                           Foreign Office, May 16, 1936.    I HAD a final conversation with M. de Madariaga on Thursday before leavingGeneva.  He began by saying he had had an interview with M. Bova Scoppa, whowas in charge of Italian interests at Geneva after Baron Aloisi5s departure.  Thelatter had  complained of the League5s  attitude under  the  leadership of HisMajesty5s Government, and had deplored the decision of the Council under mypresidency  to allow the Abyssinian representative to come to the Council table.M. de Madariaga had resented the suggestion that this decision was in any waymine it had been taken unanimously by the Council, and he had told M. BovaScoppa that, in his view, the Italian press made a great mistake in attempting tomake a personal issue of what was a national difference of opinion.  He had addedthat the Italians might have had a much more difficult  individual to deal withthan myself.  To this M. Bova Scoppa agreed, and volunteered that the stories of
[R  2846/125/67]                  No.  15.                      Despatch to Sir 67. Clerk (Paris).(No. 904.)Sir,                                            Foreign Office, May 16, 1936.    I  HAD a final  conversation  with M.  Avenol before  leaving  Geneva  onThursday, the 14th May.  He stated that it was his intention to go to Paris in thecourse of next week in order to make contact with M.  Blum  and  discuss thesituation with the French Government.  If he thought that he could be of any assistance to me after these conversations  had taken place, he would be glad tocome  on to London.   M. Avenol said it was essential to analyse with care thecomplexities of the present international situation, for the future of Europe mightwell depend upon the  decisions arrived at in the course of the  next few weeks.M. Avenol thought it important to keep an eye on the policy of the Soviet Govern-ment, and this would be more than ever necessary were M. Herriot to be ForeignMinister.  He did not mean that in  the new French Government consideration for the  Soviets  would be  a dominating consideration.    That would be  anexaggeration.   M. Blum and the Socialists were not particularly friendly to the communists, but  clearly M.  Litvinov  and his friends would be a more important influence than they had been with M. Laval or M. Flandin.  The significance of soviet policy lay in their attitude towards Germany.  They were if anything evenmore obsessed by the fear of Germany than France.  This had been shown recentlyby what M. Avenol considered to be  M. Litvinov&apos;s clear desire to  liquidate the Italo-Abyssinian  affair.  The Soviet Foreign Ministers attitude throughout this  a personal difference between Signor Mussolini and I were pure nonsense.   He  knew that the Duce was far from having any personal enmity towards me for the  part I had played in this dispute.      M.  de Madariaga went on to speak of the alternative courses which  most  delegates  appeared to consider now  concerned the League, either to continue  sanctions  under a risk of war  in order to prove the League &apos;s  authority or to  liquidate  matters  as  best  we may  at  the  next  session  of  the   Council.  M. de Madariaga said that there was a Spanish saying that life became  really  dangerous when  there were  &quot; two bulls in the ring.&quot;    This was unhappily  Europe&apos;s  position to-day.   There were two dictators.    If it were not for the  existence of Herr Hitler, he would be quite willing to contemplate an increasing-  pressure on Signor Mussolini, and if His Majesty&apos;s  Government were to decide to.  do so now, he was fairly confident that his Government would follow.    The late  Spanish Government had shown its disposition to do so and the present Spanish  Government  was likely,  he felt sure,  to be willing to  go further  than its pre-- predecessors.    What,  however,  troubled  M. de  Madariaga  was  his  fear  of  Herr Hitler&apos;s  intentions.  AVhat would be the position in  Europe  if Signor  Mussolini had not been dealt with successfully and  hostilities broke out in which  Britain lost at least 25 per cent, of her fleet and France a corresponding proportion  of her military forces ?  Surely it was impossible to believe that Herr Llitler would  not seek to profit  from such a situation.  This was what made him feel that it was  necessary to  be extremely cautious, and it was for  this reason that he  criticised  Lord Cecil and those who spoke like him, for they did not seem to appreciate the  realities of the present situation.  He yielded to none in his desire to maintain  the authority of the League, but it was foolish to ignore the situation created by  the existence of two dictators, who had no sympathy for the ideals upon which the  League was based.       M. de Madariaga said be did not believe that there was any likelihood of the  two dictators  coming together; on the  contrary,  he thought it  possible that  Herr Hitler  would attempt a coup in  Austria before Signor Mussolini was able  to bring back his troops from Africa; therefore, the next few months must be a  period full of  difficulty, in which, by  some means, an attempt must be made to  restore confidence in the leadership of  the two Western  democracies.                                                    I am, &amp;c.                                                        ANTHONY  EDEN.
dispute had been very realist, more so than that of the French Government.  Untilthe time of the Ffoare-Laval proposals he had been in the forefront of the sanc-tionist forces,  i.e., as long as he thought that the authority of the League couldbe made to prevail, he was prepared to play his  full part in  the hope that theLeague could  be made effective against  Germany hereafter.   Now, however, itwas clear that the League had failed to stop the war, and in these circumstancesM.  Avenol felt sure  that M.  Litvinov&apos;s one desire was to bring Italy  back intothe European family as soon as possible. The anxiety in M. Avenohs mind waslest M. Litvinov should use his influence upon the French Government to make arapprochement with  Germany more difficult.  He  did not believe that  the soviet governments influence would be comparable to that of His Majesty&apos;s Government,but it  was an element of  which account must now be  taken, and accordinglyM.  Avenol proposed  to warn the French Government against Russian advice inrespect of negotiations between the three great Western Powers.    The Secretary-General also emphasised that upon  the attitude which this:country took up in the next few weeks would depend to a considerable extent herreal authority in the Mediterranean for some time to come.   The smaller countriesbordering on the Mediterranean had followed our lead in respect of sanctions.It was, he thought, vital for the reputation of His Majesty&apos;s Government that theyshould not now be left in the lurch.  I asked M. Avenoi  to explain a  little moredefinitely what he meant, and it appeared that he had in mind a negotiation ofof a Mediterranean Pact to restore confidence in that sea.  I told the  Secretary-General in reply that if  his conception was that we should admit  failure in abyssinia, call off sanctions and all sit  round a table together to negotiate a pact of mutual assistance with Italy  in the Mediterranean, then I really did not thinkthat this was  a programme which the  British public would be ready to  follow,prepared though they  probably  were to  follow  almost  any  lead  that they considered fair and practicable in the  present difficulties.  M. Avenol said thathe fully appreciated this, but perhaps it would not be necessary to sit down with italy  in the first instance.  Nor again was it indispensable to talk about pactsat this juncture.  For M. Politis the word  &quot;pact&quot; was an &quot;open sesame.&quot;  Theimportant thing to show was that Britain and France  were  still interested inthe Mediterranean and meant to keep their positions in that sea.  To do this itmight  suffice if at the next meeting of the Council His Majesty&apos;s Governmentand the French Government, either or both of them, would propose to the council that the Mediterranean  Powers at present  at Geneva  should  there  and thenembark upon an examination of the political situation in that sea with a viewto deciding upon any steps that should be taken to reinforce peace in that region.The advantage of  such a procedure would  be that Italy would presumably notbe present at the next Council meeting,  and  therefore that this examination couldbe begun without her.    In the course of his remarks, M. Avenol made some reference to the attitudeof Yugoslavia.  That country&apos;s  position was somewhat different from that of herother  Mediterranean neighbours.   To put matters crudely, she would  not  beunhappy to  see hostilities between Britain and  Italy, as  she w^ould  be  herselfthereby relieved of the menace of her increasingly arrogant neighbour.                                                  I am, &amp;c.                                                      ANTHONY  EDEN.[C 3692/92/62]                    No. 16.                     Despatch to Sir G. Clerk (Paris).(No. 898.)                                            Foreign Office,Sir,                                                         May 15, 1936.    I CALLED upon M. Flandin at his house in Paris this morning.  I foundhim looking far from well, and  he stated that he would have to undergo an operation for his arm in June, when some bits of bone had to be removed, after which he hoped that it would at length begin to heal.    2.   I began by thanking M. Flandin for agreeing to my seeing M. Blum, andhe at once stated that he was very glad I was to have an opportunity to do this,for he was sure it would be most helpful.  He himself had had some conversation      [13232]                                                      D
 with M. Blum, and he felt sure that his intentions were good.  The only question was whether he would be allowed by his more extreme followers to carry out these intentions in their entirety.  In  the meanwhile, M.  Flandin considered that the new  French Government  would last  longer  than many political observers  in France were prepared to admit.   He himself thought it would last a year, and he hoped  it would  last  eighteen months, for there was much work to be done internally which a Socialist Government would be  particularly well placed to carry out.  So far as his foreign  policy was concerned, M.  Blum had  not yet decided who would be his Foreign Minister.  He was still  pressing M. Herriot very  hard, but the latter had not so far agreed to accept the post.  M. Flandin appeared to think the most likely outcome was that at the last minute M. Herriot would accept.  It appears that there is some personal ill-feeling between M. Blum and M. Paul-Boncour, and M. Flandin was convinced that  the latter would not be appointed Foreign Minister if- M. Blum could possibly avoid it.  If, however, M. Paul-Boncour were ruled out and M. Herriot would not accept, it was difficult indeed to see who could be found to go to the Quai d&apos;Orsay.     3.  M. Flandin stated that  he thought I would  find M. Blum  reasonable to deal with in  foreign affairs, but he hoped himself that we should soon be able to liquidate the Italo-Abyssinian affair, otherwise he feared lest we and the French Government should start ah international auction, the latter asking us to bid for their support in the Abyssinian  affair in return for support from us for every kind  of &quot; ideologic  en Europe.&quot;   The Socialist  party  in  France were strong supporters of all  forms of protocols,  but these were not practical  politics  at this time.    4.  M. Flandin then repeated to me what M. Blum had told him he had  said at his interview with Mr. Attlee.  M.  Blum had made it plain that the Labour party in England must not look to the new French Government  to ask for an increase of sanctions, nor would  the new  French Government seek to embarrass His Majesty&apos;s  Government through the Socialists in London.  M.  Flandin  was quite confident that M. Blum&apos;s assurances in this respect could be fully accepted.    5.  M. Flandin  then  asked me how  I  now proposed  to  deal  with the abyssinian problem.  Did  I propose to have any exchanges  of views with Rome direct ?  I replied that that was certainly not our intention at present. He then stated that there were two matters as to which he wished to consult me in order that he might,  if possible,  follow the same course.   First, we had both receiveda communication  announcing Italy&apos;s annexation of Abyssinia and the crowning of  the King  as  Emperor.  In  this  connexion,  M.  Flandin referred  to  his conversation with the Italian Ambassador, of which  M. Paul-Boncour had given me the enclosed record.  What reply was now to be sent to this intimation ?   We discussed several  alternatives,  and  agreed that the best  form was merely  to acknowledge  it under reserves which would include  the possibility of  a further reply later.  M. Flandin was anxious,  in addition,  to add  a reserve under the 1908  treaty, for he said that he feared that the annexation, and the new form  of Government that had been set up as a. part of it, might be held later by the Italian Government to have  overridden  any previous undertaking.  I  replied  that I would consider this point, but I  was not myself anxious to make any representa- tions under the 1906 treaty, for I feared that this could easily be misinterpreted, and His Majesty&apos;s Government did not wish to appear as being anxious to obtain what they could from the unhappy Abyssinian corpse.   M. Flandin fully agreed that this possibility ought to be fully guarded against, and I undertook to consider further the form of this reply, and to communicate with M.  Flandin through the French Ambassador in London.     6.  The  second  matter which M.  Flandin wished to discuss was the with- drawal of the troops which we and the French Government had sent to Diredawa and Addis Ababa.   What reply were we returning  to the Italian request for a reduction of these garrisons ?  He thought it desirable that we should act together. I replied that I fully concurred whth this  desire, which I knew to be also that of Sir S. Barton.  M. Flandin suggested that perhaps we could both reply that our additional reinforcements sent into Abyssinia last autumn would be withdrawn. This, I understood, would leave the French with some forty men at Addis Ababa, and would leave  us with our original Legation guard.  On this  subject also I undertook to send a message to the French Government as soon as possible.     7.  We then came back  to the Italo-Abyssinian dispute.  In this connexion M. Flandin maintained that the  Mediterranean Pact, which  he had first proposed
to me when he came to London last January, was the only possible solution.   the anxieties of the small Powers in the Mediterranean were now serious, and he was convinced that both His Majesty&apos;s Government and Prance would gain materiallyfrom such a pact,  and he did not think that  Italy-could refuse to sign it.  Inhis view it would not be wise to negotiate the pact without Italy and then askher to sign later, for Signor Mussolini would probably then refuse to do so just as Herr Hitler had always maintained  that he would not sign a treaty handed to him already made.  The essential  decisions which we all had now to come towas whether or not the Mediterranean was an  area of the world where we had a vital interest.   He was himself confident that  article 16 would never be appliedagain where there were no vital interests, but if our interests in the Mediterraneanwere vital then we should all stand to gain by the negotiation of a pact whichwould do much to steady the European situation.    8.   M. Elandin showed  himself  profoundly  pessimistic as to  the  attitude which  the  Chancellor  of  the  German  Reich  would  take  up  towards theqiuestionnaire.   He thought that the answer would be delayed as long as possible,and that  Herr Hitler  might  come  out  with a new  economic and  financialprogramme in order to avoid answering our questions.  He had heard that experts in both these  Departments had been very busy in Berlin of  late, and he had thought it right to warn M. Blum of this, so that he might make some  mention of these matters in advance  in his speech to-day and  thus to some extent cut the ground from under Herr  Hitler&apos;s feet if he were thinking of such a methodfor avoiding answers to the vital questions which had been put to him.  M. Flandinfurther showed a conviction that Germany and Italy would come together before long.  I replied that I had some difficulty in believing this since both Herr hitler and Signor Mussolini wished  to play  the major role in Central  Europe, and  therewas scarcely room for  the two men in so confined an area.  M.  Flandin admittedthis, but maintained that Central Europe was of small account when comparedwith world dominion as represented by the vast possessions of the British Empireand of  France.  In these circumstances it might  not be impossible  for thetwo dictators  to compromise about  Central Europe in order  that  they mightgain their larger objectives elsewhere.                                 Enclosure.Record of a Conversation between the French  Minister for Foreign Affairs and              the Italian Ambassador at Paris on May 8, 1936.(Translation.)    THE Italian Ambassador informed me on Friday afternoon of his Govern-ments intention to proceed to the annexation pure and simple of Ethiopia.    I at once informed him, in the clearest manner, that it was  impossible for theFrench Government to admit  that so summary  a movement could constitute thepolitical settlement of a situation which, both in law and in fact, was so complex and so serious.  I reminded  M.  Cerruti of the declarations  which he  himself had made to me on several occasions, in the course of the preceding months, on thesubject of peace conditions envisaged by the Italian Government.  Baron Aloisihad, for his part, informed me at Geneva of the Italian Governments intention of including among those peace conditions the maintenance, under a special regime,of the  Amharic  bloc; and,  while  preserving the  confidential  nature  of  this communication, I had had to inform Mr.  Eden of it in order  to calm a certain british anxiety on this subject.  I  could not,  therefore,  to-day associate myselfwith a  solution which was in such flagrant contradiction with those assurances.I did not understand how M. Mussolini, knowing as he did all the  implications of the questions which had been  raised in law by  the Italo-Ethiopian problem and all the extent of  their political repercussions, could follow such a course.    M. Cerruti remarked that Italy was not responsible for the situation of factwith which she had found herself suddenly confronted; the  Emperots flight, the disappearance or  submission of all the Rases,  the abolition, in a word, of everyEthiopian authority, had demonstrated the non-existence of Ethiopia as a Stateand the impossibility of improvising a central Power in that country.      [13232]            &apos;                                           E
     I reminded him that in Morocco France had preserved respect for a nativesovereignty, because she had desired to consider it, in law, as a necessity.     I emphasised the  importance of  the question of form, which  Italy was  allthe more able to safeguard in  that she had realised, in substance, the essentialobjects of her enterprise in Ethiopia.  If this question of form was not settled ina reasonable manner, very serious international difficulties might be created, forwhich Italy would be entirely responsible.  The Italian Government could not, infact, expect the League of Nations simply to take note of the total disappearance of one of its members, as the result of action on the part of another of its members.     On M.  Cerruti invoking, in justification, the situation of India with regardto England, I felt bound to point out  to him that such a comparison was entirelyinapposite.  I made it  clear in  any case that France could not accept in this waya simple annexation of Ethiopia, an annexation which, quite apart from theCovenant of the League of Nations, would  constitute a violation of the treaty of1906 and would depart from the Rome Agreement of 1935.     The Italian Ambassador naturally declared that Italy, in substituting herselfcompletely for  the sovereignty of the  Negus, fully intended to respect  all Frenchinterests in  Ethiopia.   I  remarked  that  there  was a great difference in thesituation of an Ethiopia under exclusive  Italian sovereignty.   As regards, inparticular,  the  French interests  involved  in  the  railway from  Jibuti  toAddis  Ababa,  what guarantee would there be that Italy  would not  to-morrowconstruct a new railway line in competition with ours 1  In this respect, as in all others, I must make all reserves with  regard to France&apos;s conventional rights.     In  emphasising once more the political  interest which the Italian  Govern-ment had in safeguarding form, at least,  in  its direct settlement of the Italo-Ethiopian conflict, I urged the irreparable  mistake  which Italy might commit inriding roughshod over the opinions of all the peoples who were sincerely attachedto the League  of Nations.   In Central Europe,  in  particular, the  situation was too serious for  Italy&apos;s gesture not to call forth further political reactions there.     In  conclusion,  I formally  requested M.  Cerruti to inform his Governmenturgently of the most express reserves which the French  Government made withregard to the annexation pure and simple of Ethiopia by Italy.     In  informing  you  of the  considerations  represented  to M.  Cerruti considerations  which it is not certain will  be faithfully transmitted to the headof the  Italian  Government I  should be glad if you would  communicate  most urgently and  before   the  meeting  of the  Fascist Grand Council to  thePalazzo Chigi  the  reserves  and observations which, on our  side,  the plan whichhas been communicated to us has called forth.[C  3693/92/62]                   No.  17.                      Despatch to Sir G. Clerk (Paris).(No. 899.)                                           Foreign Office,Sir,                                                         May 15, 1936.    I HAD an opportunity for informal conversation this morning with M. Blum,whom I had only met once before, at Sir Charles Mendbs flat in Paris.  M. Blum,who was  very cordial in his welcome,  impressed me as being sincere in the emphasis  which he laid upon his belief  in Anglo-French co-operation.  In thisrespect  he should  be an improvement  on his predecessors for he clearly has  nolove of dictatorships wherever they may be.  On the other hand, he struck me asbeing somewhat doctrinaire in his outlook, and he has of course never held office in any Government before.    2.  M. Blum  asserted that it was essential that our two countries should work  together.  This was  the indispensable  foundation upon  which  all elsedepended.  I  replied that I was in full agreement with this  and was glad tobe able  to tell him so within the first few minutes  of our first  meeting.   At thesame time M.  Blum would appreciate that the chief objective of British foreignpolicy  was to bring about  an agreement between the  three Great  Powers  of western Europe.  I would therefore  ask for  his  help in this  task and  moreparticularly in our efforts to bring about a negotiation  with Germany.
    3.  M. Blum, who  raised no objection to  this, somewhat surprised  me bycommenting that he  understood  that  the Soviet  Government wished  for thispolicy.  I replied that this was far from  being my impression since the Sovietswere more likely  to be apprehensive than otherwise of  a settlement in  western europe since they feared though wrongly that this left them more exposed inthe east.  M. Blum showed no enthusiasm for a new Locarno, which he seemedto think a retrograde step as compared with Sir Samuel Hoare&apos;s  speech of last september, which visualised persistent  resistance to aggression wherever it might take place. M. Blum, indeed, expressed his preference for a Locarno which would apply to Europe  as  a whole and is still  an advocate of the protocol  of 1924.I remarked that whatever might be the conception of collective security, and asto this  it was clear  that every nation should  be  willing to  play its full parteverywhere,  I was afraid that one  of the lessons which must be learnt from recent events was that  nations would not, in  fact, take steps that  involved a major risk of war unless  their own  national interests were directly  affected.M.  Blum  assented to this and stated  that it was on this account that he was still so anxious  to  secure international  disarmament.   Without that neitherthe protocol  nor  collective security  could work effectively.   Did I not agree?I replied that, while  fully sharing M. Blum&apos;s conception  of the ideal to be aimed at, it seemed to me hardly attainable at present in a world in which dictatorshipsplayed so large a part.   M. Blum somewhat reluctantly assented.    4.  M. Blum then spoke to me in the frankest terms of  his  relations withthe Labour party in  England.  He said that he was anxious that from the firstthere  should  be no possibility of  misunderstanding on  this subject.  He was aSocialist,  and naturally  had  had friendly relations with the Labour party inEngland.  But he had explained  to  Mr. Attlee when he visited him that  in no circumstances would he work with  the  English  Labour party in order to embarrass His Majesty&apos;s Government.   No country would tolerate for a momentaction by a party  from abroad which constituted interference in its own  domesticpolitics.  Not for  a moment would M. Blum consider indulging in such practices,nor, indeed, had Mr. Attlee even hinted that he should.  (It  is being stated inParis that Mr. Attlee&apos;s  visit was,  in  fact, something  of an  embarrassment toM.  Blum and his supporters,  and  there is some  comment  on  the fact thatMr. Attlee and Mr. Baker did not visit the British Embassy at any time during their stay.)    5.  We then  discussed the situation created by the Italo-Abyssinian dispute.M.  Blum asked me what were the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government, since hewas most anxious to conform to them  if possible.   I replied that I had not yet had an opportunity for consultation with my colleagues, and I was anxious for alittle  leisure  to turn over in my  mind the outcome of  the many conversations which I had had  in Geneva in the last few daArs.  At the same time I could not fail to notice that many people at Geneva thought that the League would be faced in June with two alternatives.  The first was that  we should say that we had inno wajr modified our  original attitude to this dispute, that we  were-not preparedto modify our original  verdict  about aggression or to recognise  its fruits, andthat we were determined to maintain, and if necessary increase, existing sanctionsuntil Italy was willing to negotiate a peace upon terms Avithin the framework ofthe League and in the spirit of the Covenant.  There were two difficulties in thiscourse.   The first was that if  it was successfully  prosecuted it  would almost certainly lead to war; the second was  that, in vieAv of the collapse of Abyssiniaand the Emperor&apos;s flight, the task of restoring anything like the status  quo antein Abyssinia would  become a prodigious one.   The second  alternative was to admit that sanctions had failed to attain  their  object, but to refuse to recogniseItaly&apos;s conquest or to revoke the League&apos;s  previous verdict upon her actions, andto consider what, if  anything, could be done to organise a more secure  order ofthings in the Mediterranean.  M. Blum did not appear  to be  much attracted to either of these courses.  France Avould  not be able  to propose the former, thoughshe would concur in  it if the League wished  for it.  Incidentally,  he added thathe was not so certain about the danger of  war;  there was certainly a  grave risk.He Avas convinced that  six months ago war would not have broken out had theLeague proceeded to more extreme  measures, for he Avas sure that there was aconsiderable element of bluff in Signor  Mussolini&apos;s  make-up.  On the other hand,M. Blum declared that he definitely did not want to raise sanctions as his firstact as Prime Minister.  He would prefer to keep them on for a while.  I replied
that some felt that they should be kept on until the meeting of the Assembly inSeptember, the argument  being that such a decision could only be taken by theLeague&apos;s most representative body.  At the same time the difficulty of this course,which appeared to appeal somewhat to M. Blum, was that the nations might wellask, as M. Sandier had asked, what were these sanctions then being kept on for ?     6.  M. Blum then referred to the Mediterranean Pact.   Was it the concept-tion that we should negotiate one  with Italy,  or that we should negotiate oneapart  from  Italy?   The two propositions were entirely distinct.   He saw thatthere might be serious embarrassment in calling  off sanctions and negotiating a mediterranean pact with Italy.  At the same  time, the countries in the Medi-terranean who were clearly nervous were entitled to some measure of protection,more particularly if they were in clanger of being victims on account of the action they had taken in enforcing  sanctions.  Would it not be possible to combine themaintenance of sanctions with the negotiation  of a Mediterranean pact?   Ireplied that I had gathered  that something of this kind  had appeared to be inM. Avenohs mind from the course of a conversation which  I had had with himyesterday.   Certainly, if this course were pursued, it would have this advantage,that since Italy would not presumably be present at Geneva while sanctions werein force, a Mediterranean pact, were it thought desirable to negotiate  one (onthis subject I was quite ignorant at present of the view of  His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment), could be  negotiated in the absence  of Italy and Italy could be  asked to&apos;sign it if she thought fit.  Another advantage of this proposal would be that itwould constitute an initiative by the British and French Governments and mightbe supposed therefore to  do  something to restore their authority in the Medi-terranean.   M.  Blum concluded  that,  if we could get a  Mediterranean  pact and a new  Locarno, and if, eventually,  we could get  Hitler to agree to  an Eastern pact, then nearly all Europe would be  in a system of collective security and we could breathe more freely.    7.  M. Blum showed some apprehension at Sir Austen Chamberlahis speech and at a trend  of British public opinion which he feared indicated  that we proposed to  abandon our  leadership of  the League. He  hoped that  this wouldnot be so, since then the French Government  would be  thrust  into a  lead atGeneva.  He thought any rivalry of this kind would be bad.  I replied that Ihoped we should move in step in future,  which was far preferable to either of us being in the van.    8.  M. Blum  agreed  and commented on the  difference  of outlook between public opinions in France  and Great Britain. Apparently, some people in GreatBritain were criticising His  Majesty&apos;s  Government for their failure to lead inthe Italo-Abyssinian dispute.  In France,  however, M. Blum declared, &quot; you are regarded as a sanctionist Power par excellence.  Clearly, therefore, I cannot takea lead in advance of what you would be prepared to do.  My public would neverunderstand that at all.&quot;    9.  In reference to  the  relations  of  Signor Mussolini and Herr Hitler,M. Blum expressed his conviction that it would not be possible to keep these twodictators apart.   Sooner or later  their policies would converge.  He was afraid that British public opinion was at  the moment making the  same mistake aboutHerr Hitler as  French public opinion  had made  about  Italy :  the  latter had attempted to secure Signor Mussolini&apos;s support against Herr Hitler, and now it looked as though we were attempting to  secure  Herr Hitler&apos;s support  againstSignor Mussolini.   I replied  that no intention of the kind was in our mind.   Allthat we wished to do was to rebuild the structure of peace in Western Europe.  Iwas convinced that the conception of playing off one dictator  against another had never entered the mind of the British public.

</content>
</cab>
