<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 246-246</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.&quot;&apos;               Printed for  the Cabinet.   May  1936.                                                    Copy No....v..&quot;;.!......                            CABINET.                  &apos;           I                    Government of India Act, 1935.         Approval by Parliament of Draft Instruments of Instructions to                             Provincial Governors.     MEMORANDUM  BY THE SECRETARY  OF STATE FOR INDIA.   As my colleagues may be aware, Parliament  has already  approved six of thedraft Orders to be made under the new India and Burma  Acts, but a considerablenumber still remain  to be approved.  If  Parliament accepts 1st April  1937 as thedate for Provincial Autonomy (there is a provision to this effect in one of the orders to be discussed immediately after the Whitsun recess), it will be necessary to securethat all the Orders which are  to come  into force on that date have been approvednot later  than, say,  the end  of  February next.   My general  plan  is,  however, tosecure  approval to as  many as possible of those still outstanding (other than those relating to the  Federation,  which,  of  course, will  be dealt with  later) beforeParliament rises  for the  summer recess, in  order to avoid the  difficulties whichmight arise through  lack of Parliamentary time in the autumn and after Christmasif any considerable number of them were then still outstanding.   I should add thatI do not anticipate that more than a few of them will give  rise to discussion.   Besides the  Orders in Council, however, Parliament  has  also  to  approve thedraft Instructions to  be issued to the Governors and these may possibly require an appreciable amount of  time in both Houses.   The Instructions, unlike  the  Orders,cannot be amended by Parliament, but  must be  either approved or disapproved.If, however, it were  clear from  the discussions  in  either House that there was a determined move, which the Government found difficulty in resisting, to secure the alteration of the draft Instructions, the only course available would be  to withdraw the draft under discussion and to substitute a fresh one, this  necessarily involving a second discussion in  either  or both Houses, as the case might be.   The Joint Select  Committee specifically recommended that if the &quot;conditions in bengal&quot; (in respect  of terrorism) &quot;at the time of  the  inauguration of provincial autonomy have not  materially improved, it would,  in our judgment, be  essentialthat the  Governor  of the Province should exercise  the powers we have justdescribed&quot;  (now embodied in section  57  of the Act)  &quot;forthwith  and should  bedirected to do so in  his Instructions,  which  in this as in other respects  would remain in force  until amended  with the consent  of  Parliament.&quot;   This recom-mendation was  doubtless based  on the assumption that the  draft Instruments of instructions to the Governors would come under the consideration of Parliamentquite shortly before  the inauguration of Provincial  Autonomy.  It would, however,in  my opinion, be impossible with prudence to postpone to the period  betweenthe  reassembling of Parliament after Christmas and,  say, the  end  of february the  submission  to Parliament  of  these important documents,  which it will  be essential  to have in being on  1st April  1937.  Any material  delay in the processof their  approval at so late  a stage, or any serious congestion of parliamentary business at that time, might well necessitate postponement at the  last  moment of the date fixed for  the  commencement of  the  Act, which  would  produce great and most unfortunate confusion.  On the other hand, if  the Instructions were to bebrought before Parliament during June or  July  of this year, objections  mightbe  raised to approving  the  Instructions, at all  events those to the  Governor of bengal,  so long in advance  and necessarily, therefore, without the data on  which to form a judgment in  connection with  the Joint Committee&apos;s recommendationjust referred to.    The proposal, therefore, to which I seek the approval of my  colleagues  is thatthe  necessary  time, whatever it may prove to be, in both Houses shall be found forthis business on convenient  dates between the reassembly of Parliament after the summer recess and its rising for the Christmas recess.   Otherwise  we should not,in  my  view, be justified in postponing the Instructions till the autumn since, as Ihave already explained, I  think that it is  essential  that they should  be  approved by Parliament not later than Christmas.  This proposal would have the additional advantage of relieving the already burdened Parliamentary programme  for June and July.    INDIA OFFICE,                                                         z        22nd May 1936.      4837   75  5.36SECRET.OP. 145 (36).

</content>
</cab>
