<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 380-388</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HI3  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERjrtMBxfT.                                             CORY iVO.     41 9/36.G A B I N E T.STATE OP TRADE - APRIL, 1936,Note &quot;by the President  of  the  Board  of  Trade.     I circulate to my colleagues a  summary of  thereports submitted to the Board of Trade  Advisory  Councilon the state of trade iii April, 1936.Board of Trade,   27th May, 1936.
ENTIAL.A.C. 351.BOARD OP TRADE ADVISORY COUNCIL.STATE OP TRADE - APRIL,1936.  Summary of reports submitte d by members ofthe Board of Trade Advisory Council (supplementedin some cases with statistical information fromother sources).     OVERSEAS TRADE.   Imports in April at  66.7 m. were 6.8 m. more than in April, 1935.   Over 60;.- of the risewas in food and raw materials.   Of the increase of  2.4 m.in manufactured goods, over  1 m. related to non-ferrousmetal products, nearly  g-ra. to iron and steel products and nearly  * m, to machinery.   Exports of United Kingdomproduce,  33. 4rn. , were  413,000 more and re-exports, 5.9 m., were  1.7m. more than in April, 1935..     EMPLOYMENT.    The total number of unemployed persons on the registers at the 27th April, 1,331,230, was 50,301fewer than at 23rd March,     The main variations were:-London .......   --11,004      North Eastern   + 9,572South Eastern.   - 9,569      North Western   - 6,694South Western.   - 6,699      Scotland       - -11,963Midlands.....   - 5,653      Wales....... -  - 8,236    &quot;&quot;N-     The estimated number of insured persons aged 16-64 inemployment was 10,712,000 - 82,000 more than at 23rd Marchand 371,000 more than at 15th April, 1935.    The improvementsince March was most marked in building and public workscontracting, engineering, shipbuilding, etc.,  metal goods,tinplate, electrical apparatus,  motor vehicle etc.,furniture, and food manufacture, tailoring etc., brick andtile making, road transport, shipping, the distributive trades and the hotel, etc., services.    There were a furtherdecline in the coal mining industry and slight setbacks Inthe woollen and hosiery industries.     RAILWAY TRAPPIG.   In the four weeks ended 26th Aprilrailway traffic receipts increased by  397,000 (3.58%) compeled\
with the corresponding period of 1933.   The? increase in passenger traffic amounted to 1.09  ;  in merchandise, minerals and livestock to 7.01;.:.;&apos; and in coal, coke and patent fuel  to3.18,.     SPUPPING,    The Chamber of Shipping index number offreights (1913 - 100) was 85,81 as  against 89.19  in Marchand 77.61 a year ago.   Tramp shipping is reported to heseriously affected by the suspension of the export trade(particularly in coal; to Italy,     COAL*   The average weekly output of coal during the13 weeks ended 25th April  was 4,62 m. tons as comparedwith 4.48 m. tons in the corresponding period a year ago -an increase of 3.2;.-.-..   The average number of wage-earnersemployed was 1/.- less than a year before.     Exports in. April amounted to 2.54 rru tons comparedwith 2.88 ra. tons in April,  1933, the reduction being very largely in respect of exports  to Italy.     IRON Ax-ID STEEL.    All sections of the industry werebusy.   Output is in many cases sold ahead well into thethird quarter.     Pig iron output (629,300 tons; was 19.7&apos;.; greater thanin April, 1935,    Average daily output was 550 tons greaterthan in March;  3 more furnaces were in blasts    Thoughmost producers were operating at  .capacity,  it was difficultto meet the demand,     Crude steel output (991,500 tons - 22,5 - more than ayear ago) reached a further record.    Imports brought semerelief to the semi-finished steel markets;  most homeproducers&apos;  output is sold many weeks ahead.     Business In finished steel,  though quieter, remained.satisfactory;  export business was slow,;     Scotland.    Conditions  generally remained active,  buttube exports showed some reaction (owing to  Continentalcompetition),   Boiler makers were busier than for some time past.    Order books are well filled.                          -2-
      North East Coast.  Despite an increase in price, demand for&quot;basic pig iron exceeded output;  heavy local requirements have  further reduced shipments from Tees ports.   It was difficult to place orders for &quot;billets and bars.   Sheet rollersexperienced a slow domestic demand and poor export trade.      Sheffield.  Active conditions continued.   Generalhome  demand was strong and overseas orders were expanding.Producers of special and stainless steels were working atcapacity.      South Wales.  Demand for all kinds of steel was well maintained.   Export trade in tinplates improved;  tinplateworks were operating (early May) at 61% of capacity.   Exporttrade in galvanised steel sheets did not improve.     MOTOR INDUSTRY.  The number of motor vehicles newlyregistered in March was 46,025, which is 3,895 more than ayear ago.   The increase in private cars was 1,985.     Exports of new private cars and chassis in Aprilamounted to 4,486 and of new commercial vehicles and chassisto 1,038, showing when compared with April,  1935, increases of 2.2% and 19.3% respectively.     ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.   The international situation hasaffected overseas business but, thanks to home demand,  thegeneral outlook continues  promising.    There was a further improvement in heavy engineering orders.    Consumption ofelectricity amounted to 1,554 m.  units - 16.8 per cent  morethan in April,  1935.     ENGINEERING.    Progress has been maintained and the strengthening of confidence is reflected in  the i nc r e a s i ngvolume of orders placed.    Exports  of machinery were valued at  3.3 m.  as compared with  3.2 m.  in April,  1935.                      -3-
    LIGHT METAL INDUSTRIES.    Conditions  generally remain satisfactory.    The  non-ferrous  metal  trade  is  brisk and a  shortage  of  skilled  labour  is  being  felt.   Despite extensions  to  works, many  sections  of  the  tool  trades find difficulty in giving  deliveries.    The  presswork. trade  is extremely busy.    Continental competition in  metal smallwares  is  keen.    GOTTOlu   There was little  change in  activity.   Average weekly  deliveries oi raw cotton  to  spinners  were 27.99  m.  lbs.  against  27.52m.  lbs.  in March.    Takings of  Indian cotton increased  but takings of  American and Egyptian cottons declined.   American raw  cotton  prices were  steady, Indian  prices  increased and Egyptian prices fell  slightly.   Spinners&apos;  margins  were  little  affected. Yarn  exports at 11.94 m. lbs.  were  1.4 m.  lbs.  less than in March (due  partly to the smaller number of working days),  but  1.47 m. lbs. more  than a year ago.   Exports of piece  goods  at 141.2 m.  sq. yds. were 32.1 m.  less  than in March and 18.3 m,  less  than in April, 1935,    The decrease, as compared with March, was spread over most markets;  exports to India  fell  by  12 m, and to British  WestAfrica by 5-g- in. sq.  yds.     The  immediate   outlook is hardly favourable,  but the reductions  in Canadian duties on textile imports from the United Kingdom are welcomed.   VP PL.   activity declined,  jjar ticularly in theworsted  section.   Raw wool prices were  steady.     Exports of  tops,  yarns  and tissues were  less than  in March  (a longer working  month);  the fall in tissues  was considerable,Eoreign  customers are hesitant in placing  new orders and there are signs of a  slackening  in home  demands.
   SILK AND ARTIFICIAL SILK.    There was little change in  the  rayon  yarn  trade  but  an improvement isexpected soon.   Demand  for  staple  fibre continuedvery  satisfactory.   The  underwear  trade was disappointingand business in piece goods  was bad, owing mainly to  the cold  weather.   Exports of all-rayon and of rayon mixturefabrics were larger  than  in  April,  1935.      On the whole  the silk trade was quiet.   HIDES AND LEATHER.   Hide prices eased somewhattowards the end of April.    In  the  leather trade business was on the whole fairly good.   CHEMICALS,    ales of  alkalies and chlorine productswere  satisfactory.   Deliveries of  industrial nitrogenproducts were  maintained  at  a high  level.   The recentsteady expansion in  home  sales  of dye stuffs (as comparedwith  1935) was checked, but  foreign sales were greaterthan  in April, 1935.   Total exports of fertilizers aresmaller this season  than  last,  though Empire sales haveincreased;  considerable  home orders for sulphate arestill coming in.   x-*QTTERY.   Although export sales of general earthenwareimproved slightly in March,  total sales for the first quarter of this year were considerably less than a yearago.    Other sections had on the whole a satisfactorymonth.   RARER.    Demand,  well  maintained at first,  becameunusually slack in certain sections after Easter.    Theexport trade was slightly better than a year ago.Newsprint imports from Canada and Newfoundland wereexceptionally heavy.   Large arrivals of Scandinaviankraft (sold forward  before the  general price increase)are likely to aiiect future demand here.
   RETAIL TRAPS.   The money value of retail sales inMarch was 7.9% greater than in March, 1935.   All areasshared in the improvement.   Sales of food and perishablesrose by 9.5% and of other merchandise by 5.2%.    Preliminaryreturns tend to show a less favourable experience in April.   CA-7.NI)IAN TRADE.     Economic conditions in March showed a slight recession and the physical volume of business was less than in February.   Nickel and zinc exports andnewsprint production, however, established records for march, while electric power production reached a new highpoint.   Activity in the primary iron and steel industrs&apos;though less than in February,  was greater than in anyrecent March.    Total exports were greater than in anyMarch since 1929.   AUSTRALIAN TRADE.    2,558,179 bales of -wool were received into store from the 1st July to the 31st march last, as compared with 2,627,107 a year previously, the quantities sold or shipped being 2,455,153 and 2,110,570bales respectively.   &quot;Wheat and flour shipments from the1st December,  1955, to the 23th April were equivalentto 55.5 m,  bushels of wheat against 49.2 m. bushels a yearago.   Butter shipments from the 1st July to the 25th Aprilamounted to 35,534 tons as compared with 107,383 tons ayear ago.    Imports of merchandise during March amountedto  8.64 m. (Australian currency) as compared with  8.44 m.a year before..   SOUTH AFRICAN TRADE.   There was substantial surplus inthe national accounts for the year ended March, 1935.Certain Customs Duties are to be-  removed  and others  reduced.Considerable expenditure on railway and harbourdevelopment is foreshadowed.
                                                     a fcj                                                     Cs JjJ &amp;     Imports in February were 15.10/0 greater than inFebruary, 1935.   Exports  (excluding gold) were o.2% less, dueprincipally to decreases in exports of diamonds and maize.Gold output was considerably greater than in February,  1935.Coal production continued  to expand.   In January there was a seasonal recession in the  manufacturing industries.     INDIAN TRADE.   Imports in April 12.5% in value less thanin April, 1935;  exports were about 40?? higher.   Standing-crops are reported to be generally in fair condition.   the supplementary forecast for the cotton crop is 5.7 m. bales ascompared with the forecast of 4.8 m. bales for last year1scrop.     SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.     Argentina.  The new -wheat and linseed crops are being sownunder excellent conditions.   Live stock and wool prices havebeen maintained.   The grain market continued dull.   Maizeshipments increased but shipments of wheat,  linseed, etc., fellsubstantially in the first quarter of 1936,  as compared with1935;  fruit exports expanded considerably.    Total exports inthe first quarter of 1936 were 6.4% in value (20% in volume)less than in the first quarter of 1935, but imports increasedby 1% (15.8% in volume).     Brazil.   The coffee market remained depressed.   shipments of coffee from 1st July, 1935 to 25th April were 2492 greaterthan in the corresponding period for the 1934/35 crop.    Thecotton market continued firm.    Germany&apos;s share of Brazil&apos;strade increased, and the United Kingdom share decreased, in1935.     Chile.   The produce market continued active during April.     Peru.   The sugar market was quiet.   Sales of cotton were fairly brisk.    The volume of cotton exports in 1935 reached a                        -7-
9 Hf&amp;  *^record, but the value was slightly less than in 1934.      Colombia.  Coffee exports during January and February we.&quot; rather larger in volume than in the corresponding period of 1935;   gold output was 37% greater.      Uruguay.  Wool exports from 1st October, 1935 to the 31st March were. 43% greater in volume than a year before. Total exports in 1935 increased (in value)  by 36.7% but imports decreased by 4.4% as compared with 1934;  Uruguay&apos;s favourable &quot;visible&quot; balance of trade with the United Kingdom greatly increased.

</content>
</cab>
