<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 411-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                                               this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENT    fcX                    Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1936.                    ^MlSECRET.                                                         Copy No. 0 a,----                                                                   ?j HJCP. 15S (36).CABINET.AIR  SERVICES IN THE MEDITERRANEAN.  Joint Memorandum  by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the                         Secretary of State for Air.    TOWARDS the end of 1935  it was learned that the German  company,Lufthansa, had  put forward proposals to the  Greek Government by which theywould co-operate with  Greek air interests in the development of commercial  air services in and  from  Greece.  These  proposals were designed to provide  the greeks with the financial and material assistance which they  require in orderto establish services to Egypt and to the Eastern Mediterranean generally, andin taking their  part in a &quot; reseau  aerien balkanique &apos;&apos;  in which they desire toparticipate with the Balkan States.    It was felt at the time that the acceptance of these German proposals by  theGreek Government would constitute a  serious danger to British interests.   Notonly would it mean the development of  German air services through the Balkansinto the Eastern Mediterranean and possibly also to Egypt, and the establishmentof German-controlled aerodromes and  supply stores  in  Greece;  it would also give to the Germans  such a  general control over Greek aviation that they mightbe in a position seriously  to obstruct the operation of the British main  far eastern trunk services through that country; and finally it would be an importantadvance in the process of German financial and commercial penetration in Greece,.which have already been the subject of some anxiety to His Majesty&apos;s Government.    Urgent representations  were therefore made to the  Greek Government  notto close with the German offer until British  air interests should have  had  anopportunity to put forward counter-proposals for Anglo-Greek co-operation inthis field, and   an undertaking to  this effect was  obtained in January  last.Representatives  of the  Air Ministry and of Imperial Airways visited Athens inMarch to  ascertain the requirements of the Greek Government, and as a resultof their recommendations Imperial Airways were invited early in April to  state their  views on  and to submit  preliminary  proposals  covering  two schemes,.namely :     (1)  A shuttle service between Greece and Egypt to be operated by Imperial          Airways, either through  an Anglo-Hellenic company  or, if necessary,          under the Greek flag.    (2)  An extension to Athens, possibly  as a joint Anglo-Greek enterprise, of          the present Imperial AirwTays service from London to Budapest.    As  regards  scheme (1)  the company  have now stated that they would  be willing to put forward detailed plans  for a weekly service on a route Athens-Crete-Alexandria.   As, however,  this route  does not  in  their opinion  offereconomic mileage by  itself, they suggest that it should be combined with weeklyservices to Italy (Brindisi) via Jannina, and to Turkey (Istanbul) via  Salonica.The total annual mileage flown under  these proposals would be approximately160,000  miles, and Imperial  Airways estimate that after taking into account the anticipated revenue from traffic the operations would result in a net  annual lossof approximately  25,000.      8652   [13339]
    The decision of  the  Cabinet  is  required  as  to  whether  payments ofapproximately   25,000 per  annum for five  years  can be  made  to imperial airways, by way of subsidy or otherwise, in order to cover the losses which theywould incur in undertaking these services.  It has hitherto been the policy  thatsubsidy payments from Air Votes could be made only to British companies forthe improvement of communications directly  connected  with British territory.In the present  case, the services requiring  support will probably be operated bynominally Greek  companies, and though the appearance of subsidising a foreigncompany- could  no doubt be avoided by making  the payments to Imperial Airwaysunder some other head, the fact will remain that the payments will be in respectof operations falling  outside the category  of  British civil aviation schemes forwhich  assistance from Air Votes is normally considered to  be  available.  Suchderogation from  the principles on which subsidies  are normally made availablewould  require  to be   justified  on  political,  strategic and general  commercial considerations.    In  weighing these considerations it is necessary to take  into account theEgyptian as well as the Greek aspect of the question.  The Egyptian Governmentare no less anxious than the Greek to establish an air service  across the Mediter-ranean, and before giving  facilities in Egypt  to an Anglo-Greek company,  theywill require rights for an Egyptian company to  fly to Athens. There are at presenttwo rival Egyptian companies  anxious to  enter into this field; the one is MisrAirwork, an Egyptian company affiliated  with air work  (Limited),  of  Heston,England, which  has always  been regarded as the chosen  instrument  of Anglo-Egyptian co-operation in  civil  aviation;  the  other  is the Horus  Company, an institution recently formed under the auspices of the Deutsche Lufthansa for thepurpose of operating from Cairo via Athens to Vienna, there to link up with theGeimran company&apos;s European lines.    The Horus  Company has the  importantadvantage over its rival that since  it possesses the support of powerful  Germaninterests in finance and material, it is able to offer to operate the service withoutsubsidy from the Egyptian Government, and with adequate machines,  whereasMisr  air work  would  require subsidy and does not at present possess machineslarge enough for the route.    There is only  one method of meeting the double danger presented by theGerman proposals in Greece and the formation of the Horus  Company in Egypt,and that is to provide, under British management and with British financial support, the service which both the  Egyptian and the  Greek Governments are determined to have.  If Imperial Airways can be enabled to start the Anglo-Greekservices which they have  proposed it would probably be possible to invite  MisrAirwork to take a part in these operations, either in close co-operation with theAnglo-Greek Company or by a working arrangement, and this evidence of thesupport of His Majesty&apos;s  Government should suffice to  enable Misr air work toobtain  the Egyptian   Governments nomination for this purpose  together  withan Egyptian subsidy.  An additional safeguard would be that Imperial Airwayscould possibly  obtain  from the  Greek Government in return for organising theGreek services which  they have proposed,  an  undertaking not to grant facilities in Greece to any Egyptian company other than Misr air work.     It will thus be seen that the provision by His Majesty&apos;s Government of thesubsidy payments necessary to enable Imperial Airways&quot; to start  the services which they  have proposed is essential if the  efforts which German interests aremaking to obtain a footing in Egyptian, and a large measure of control in Greek,civil  aviation  are to be  countered.   There are, however,  two  other  equally important reasons for encouraging the establishment  of British-controlled air services on  the Athens-Cairo route.  In  the first  place, if  and when imperial airways extend to Athens  their present London-Budapest service,  there will have been created an alternative British air route across Europe to the Far East (via Cologne, Leipzig, Prague, Vienna, Budapest, Athens and Cairo) which might be of great importance to His Majesty&apos;s Government if the political difficulties of the route through  France and Italy were  at any time to become threatening. Secondly, the  consolidation of British  air communications in Greece  and in the East Mediterranean  generally might have an important  strategic value in the event of it being  found necessary,  as a  solution of present difficulties in the Mediterranean,  to enter into closer relations  with Greece  and Turkey than have existed hitherto. This is a possibility in  regard to which a separate paper will be circulated shortly.
    It should be added that the. Interdepartmental Committee on Air Communi-cations, under the Chairmanship of Sir Warren Fisher, has recently recommendedthat the political and strategic  considerations  involved  render essential  the promotion  of services  on the  lines suggested  under  British influence.  TheCommittee also  considered that it  is of  great  importance to obtain  an early decision, and to  take the preliminary steps as a matter  of urgency.    The problem raised,  however, is intrinsically external to pure  air  policy,and is therefore submitted to the  Cabinet as a  question for decision on general political and strategic grounds.                                                                     A. E.                                                                     S    June 10, 1936.

</content>
</cab>
