<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/262/0 images: 459-460</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1936.                   3II 3SECRET.                                                        Copy No.   41CP. 166  (36).                                             -CABINET.THE ITALO-ABYSSINIAN DISPUTE.        Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.    I CIRCULATE, for the information of my colleagues, a note of a further discussion which the Foreign Secretary  and I  have had  with  representativesof the Dominions on the subject of sanctions and the Italo-Abyssinian dispute.                                                  (Initialled)      M. M.    Dominions Office, June 1936.                                   INOTE.    THE Foreign Secretary and I had a further discussion with the DominionHigh Commissioners  last night  on  the question  of sanctions  and  the Italo-Abyssinian dispute.  In addition to all the High Commissioners,  Dr. Earle Pageand Mr. Menzies were present.    The same difference of opinion as to the policy to be pursued at the league council and Assembly meetings as had appeared at the earlier discussions (whichI have already reported orally to my colleagues) was still evident.  On the one side, Mr. te Water, expressing the official view of his  Government, was in favourof a more or less indefinite continuance of sanctions.  On the other side,  Mr. Bruceand the two Australian Ministers, speaking the mind of their Government,  were strongly inclined in favour of  the immediate  lifting of sanctions, accompaniedby various declarations by the members of the League on the lines of Mr. Bruce&apos;suggestions at the previous discussions.   Mr.  Massey had received no  indication of the views of his Government.  Sir James Parr  maintained the attitude thathis Government would support whatever policy the  United Kingdom  government proposed. Mr. Dulanty repeated that, in Mr. de Valera&apos;s view, sanctions shouldbe maintained unless, as a result, there was a serious risk of an European war.    Despite the considerable difference of opinion between those present, everyoneshowed genuine anxiety that the Governments of the Commonwealth should speak with the same voice when  the meetings take place at  Geneva.   Mr. Dulanty was anxious for this, and Mr. te Water also was clearly eager that some compromisemight be found which would enable him also to come  into line.  But unless some such compromise proved acceptable, he felt bound  to say that he would have toexpress frankly and fully the views of his Government as they had already  been stated.    Mr.  Massey, speaking personally, said  that he  thought there  were gravedangers in either of the courses suggested by Mr. te Water or  by Mr. Bruce.  Hecould see nothing but disaster for  the  League if sanctions were  maintainedindefinitely, only to peter  out  without  achieving much.  On the other hand, hethought that the immediate raising of sanctions would  be a  profound shock to world opinion which supported the League, and that  this policy would lead to agreat loss of the League&apos;s and the British Empire&apos;s prestige.   He  wondered whether there was not some middle course; whether, for  instance, the machinery      [13358]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
of the League could be made to work so that the issue was postponed for a while.Could the Assembly  produce some excuse for saying that sanctions could not be lifted at once and that they could not take the decision until their regular meeting in the autumn ?  This delay would give tizne for the ill-effects of sanctions in italy to be more seriously  felt, and for this pressure to induce Mussolini in some way or other to make concessions.  &quot;What was in his mind, as in the minds of the otherspresent, was the desirability of some sort  of undertaking that Mussolini wouldnot raise a black army in Abyssinia, and that generally he would administer thecountry according to mandate principles.     The High Commissioners and Australian Ministers all appreciated (1) thatit would almost  certainly be impossible for Mussolini to make  concessions to theLeague  as such,  and (2) that from the point of view of the League itself it was undesirable  that its  members should lift sanctions  as a result  of a bad bargainstruck with the aggressor.     In  the light of  this a great deal of discussion took place on Mr. Massey&apos;suggestion.  Finally, Mr. Bruce said that in his vieAV there were only two possible alternative  policies.   One  was  to  raise  sanctions  immediately,   with  theaccompanying declarations,  the other was to find some means of carryingMr.  Massey&apos;s suggestion into  effect.   He suggested  (though  he  would  notnecessarily advocate  the proposal himself) that  it might be done in this way :  themembers of  the  League might issue a declaration to the world to the effect thatthey had been endeavouring to stop aggression, that they were still preoccupied with  the problem  of how to check aggressors,  that this lay at the  root of  theproblem of maintaining peace, that various lessons were to be learned from their experience during the  last seven months; that they were now  considering whatthose lessons were  and what they might require in the way of a reconstitution ofthe League; and that until their examination of  this problem was  complete itwould be premature for sanctions to be  raised.   In  effect this would  enablesanctions to be kept on until the  League  Assembly meeting in September, andwould avoid the formal suggestion that they were being kept on for the purposeof securing terms from Mussolini.    It appeared that the Dominion representatives might be able to agree  on some such policy as this but that the idea would require careful thought.   Theywere anxious to  know what the United Kingdom Governments policy would be,as they particularly desired to find themselves in agreement with that. But theyappreciated that although the Cabinet was conducting a careful examination ofthe whole problem, it could not be expected  to reach  final conclusions until shortly before the Geneva meetings, as changes in  the situation might occur at any timeup to the last moment.  The Foreign Secretary indicated the tentative ideas which united Kingdom Ministers were exploring.    In the course of the discussion, the suggestion was made that Great Britainmight join in an  Eastern Mediterranean  pact, that  is, in a mutual guaranteearrangement with Turkey and Greece.  If either of  those countries were attacked(for example, on account of the part v/hich they had  played in sanctions) GreatBritain  wpuld come to their aid, and likewise,  if an attack were made on GreatBritain  in the Eastern Mediterranean or  on Egypt, we should have the assistanceof those two Powers.  In the latter case we should be able to secure a good naval base in  the  Eastern Mediterranean, which we had not got at present.    TheDominion representatives thought  this  a  good suggestion, not  only from  thepractical point of view, but from  the  point of  view of British prestige.    Theworld would be impressed by a declaration which meant that Great Britain was going to stand by the smaller Powers if any attempt were made to punish them fortheir part in sanctions.                                                                   M. M.June 9, 1936.

</content>
</cab>
