<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/64/0 images: 275-276</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET1ST DECEMBER,  1955THE FEW RIFLE &quot;AND AMMUNITION .   &quot;&quot;Memorandum by the Secretary of State for war there have recently been extensive trials and development by Canada, Belgium and ourselves with United States observersconcerning the ,280 and .300 inch Calibre round.    As a restxltstandardisation with the .300 inch round in the United StatesT65 case was recommended:    the U.S.A. military authoritiesagreed.2.     At the same time various new rifles to fire this roundhad been undergoing trials.   We ourselves have just completedtrials ox? the latest type EN rifle (designed by a Belgian firm)and consider it suitable for adoption &quot;by the army.    It is asgood as our own EM2. rifle and has proved more reliable.    It is asimpler rifle and will therefore be cheaper and easier to manufacture.    Canada has decided to order 2,000 of these riflesfor troop trials, and there is a strong possibility that bothwill ultimately adopt this weapon.3.     The Army wishes to rearm with this weapon and our firstrequirement will be for about 150,000.    This may seem a lowfigure but it is considered sufficient for about 15i Divisionsylargely because a much higher proportion than previously willbe armed with the new sub-machine carbine.    In addition, we hope to sell rifles to the Dominions, possibly the north atlantic Treaty Organisation, and there will be a certainnumber needed by the Navy and Air Force.km      I do not at present propose to make a statement aboutthe adoption of a nev/ rifle because we have promised Canada,the U.S.A. and Belgium that the Standing Group should make an agreed statement by all the countries concerned in orderto underline the degree of standardisation which has beenobtaitied.\,j r\ o 1*UrvU our R Copy NO.CABINETI    /5.      I now ask for agreement(a) to order 5,000 FN rifles to carry out trooptrials as quickly as possible;    and(b) for the Minister of Supply to concludenegotiations with the FN Company for manufacturing rights in the United Kingdom.A.H.The War Office, S.W.1.30TH NOVEMBER, 1953.
cabinetThe attached paper (C. (53) 339)will be considered at to-morrow&apos;smeeting of the Cabinet under Item 2of the Agenda,Cabinet Office, S.W.1.30TH NOVEMBER, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
