<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/64/0 images: 285-286</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2,7  TELEVISION development memorandum by the Postmaster-general  was asked to submit a memorandum on possible ways of modifying the White Paper proposals to introduce into the competitiveprogrammes an element not directly financed from advertisements.(C.C,(53) 75th Conclusions, Minute 5).CABINET OFHCRECORD copy copy NO.cabinet. Three ways of doing this are set out below:-(i)      A small annual sum to be allocated to the new corporation from licence revenue.     For example-, about -! million could be obtained by the addition of-2/- on everytelevision licence (as estimated at mid 1955) - this amount wouldbe one-eighth of that now spent by the 3.B.C, on television.The objection to this is that the money would be raised from viewers, many of whom would be unable or would not wish to receive the competitive programmes.(ii.)      In its contracts with the programme companies thenew Corporation would, of course, be expected to ask notonly for an economic rent for its facilities but also for a proportion of the companies&apos; profits or revenue.     TheCorporation would use some of this money for developingits system but could also devote some of it to financingcultural or educational programmes.A possible objection to this is that the money would still come ultimately from advertising, although it would, ofcourse, be independently administered by the public corporation.To cover the initial period during which there would not be much money forthcoming, a small portion of the licence revenuecould be allocated to the new Corporation as a loan to be repaid in due course to the B.B.C.secret.(53) 3427TK DECEMBER, 1953
(iii)      A small proportion of licence revenue to be allocated to the new Corporation in exchange for a proportion of the advertising revenue received by thenew Corporation which would be paid by them to the B.B.C,Such a direct allocation from funds received fromadvertisements is unlikely to be as acceptable to theB.B.C, as the loan arrangements mentioned above;  indeed,the arrangement might well be felt to savour too much ofhuckstering.     There is also the objection that for thefirst two years the B.B.C, might be subsidising thedevelopment of its competitors;  but in the long run sucha scheme would enable advertising revenue to &quot;fructifythe whole enterprise&quot; as the Archbishop of Canterburysuggested it should.3. I very much doubt whether method (i) is practical politicsbut something on the lines of either method (ii) or (iii) is well worthconsideration.    If method (ii) would satisfy our supporters who havemisgivings it would certainly be the simplest.D.Post Office Headquarters, E.C.1, ,5TH DECEMBER, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
