<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/64/0 images: 340-340</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2loSECRET .&apos; &apos;.   cRECORD COPY ifC.(53) 359 COPY NO.24TH DECEMBER, 1953CABINETEXPENDITURE ON THE OVERSEAS INFORMATIONgERVICES m X954/55Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department and Minister for Welsh AffairsThe Lord Privy Seal, the Minister of Labour and I were invited by the Cabinet at their meeting on 26th November (C. C. (53) 72nd Conclusions,Minute 6) to examine the Report of the Drogheda Committee on the overseas information Services (annexed to C. (53) 305), and the following memoranda -C. (53) 260, 310, 315 and 321 - and to submit recommendations to the Cabinet.We have heard the views of interested Ministers and now present ourinterim recommendations on the immediate question whether there shouldbe an increase in expenditure on the overseas information services during1954/55.    This would be necessary if the modified proposals put forward bythe overseas Departments in C. (53) 315 were adopted.2,        We were impressed by the strength of the arguments brought forward for some expansion of the overseas information services.    we felt, nevertheless, that the general need for limiting Government expenditurein the interests of the national economy was of greater importance and wetherefore recommend that there should be no overall expansion of these services in 1954/55,3.        We should not wish to rule out the possibility of adjustments eitherbetween Departments within the total figure or between the different services of a single Department within its total.    The problem of the risingcost of maintaining existing services could probably be dealt with betweenthe overseas Departments and the Treasury in the usual way without theneed for detailed decisions by Ministers.    There are obvious attractionsin using some of the savings recommended by the Drogheda Committee tomeet these rising costs as suggested in paragraph 6 of C. (53) 321.    Onthe other hand, it will probably be necessary eventually to publish asummary of the Drogheda Report and the Governments decisions on it,and it might be very difficult to defend acceptance of the recommendations which involve savings coupled with rejection of those involving increased expenditure.4.        We propose to resume our consideration of the Drogheda report and the related papers at an early date and to submit recommendations aboutthe scope of the overseas information services from 1955 onwards,*. D.M.F.Home Office, S, W. 1.23RD DECEMBER, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
