<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/64/0 images: 348-349</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1953SECRETC. (53) 36430th December, 1953CABINETTREATY AND AGREEMENTS WITH LIBYAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs- As promised on 23rd July, I circulate the following summary of the treaty and the Military and Financal Agreements which was signed by H.M. Minister in libya on 29th July.  (C.C. (53) 45th Conclusions, Minute 5.)2. All three instruments are valid for twenty years and, if not then terminated,will run on until one year after notice has been given by either Party. They areto be reviewed at the end of ten years, without, however, any obligation to revisethem.The Treaty of Friendship and Alliance3. The text of the Treaty (Cmd. 8914) is substantially the same as thatapproved by the Cabinet on 24th February (C.C. (53) 14th Conclusions, Minute 5).Within the framework of the United Nations Charter, and without prejudice toobligations under existing agreements, the two Parties will aid each other in caseof war; concert together in case of a threat to either Party; and assist each otherthroughout by means of the provision of military facilities by Libya and financialassistance by the United Kingdom. The terms of this mutual assistance in themilitary and financial fields are to be agreed upon, and they appear in the military agreement and Financial Agreement.4. The Arab League Covenant, as an existing convention to which Libya isa party, is mentioned in the text of the Treaty instead of in a public Exchange of letters as was proposed in February.The Military Agreement5. The broad effect of this document is that British forces may be stationed in libya, with reasonable privileges and firm tenure of a substantial amount of accommodation, for the duration of the Agreement.6. The British forces, defined to include civilian employees, camp followersand dependents (but not the employees of contractors) may number up to 25,000in peace-time under a secretly agreed Minute. This number may be varied by further secret agreement between the two Governments.7. The privileges accorded to the British forces in general include immunity from customs and income tax and aliens registration, though the civilians will haveto obtain visas. As regards crimes the service tribunals will have exclusivejurisdiction, where jurisdiction is conferred by English law, for offences in thegarrison areas, or on duty, or against United Kingdom persons, property or security.The Libyan Courts will have jurisdiction for other offences, but will consider sympathetically our requests for waiver. They will also give us custody of prisonerson remand, so that only after conviction would a member of the British forcesspend any length of time in a local prison. This is a slightly better arrangement for the visiting force than the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation StatusAgreement. It also leaves us free, by legislation here, to give the service tribunalseffective jurisdiction over the civilian component.45407BINE I   Ori .GORD copy copy No.84
Foreign Office, S.W.1,29th December, 1953.8. The accommodation we are to acquire is listed as &quot; agreed lands &quot; ofwhich we have exclusive and uninterrupted use for the duration of the Agreement.The agreed lands comprise, as regards the Army, less ready-made quarters than we had hoped, because we have had to agree to vacate the bulk of our accommoda-tion within a five-mile ring from the centre of the twin capitals, Tripoli andBenghazi; but we still have a number of barracks outside the two capitals, and land on which to build as necessary. Training areas present no difficulty in thislargely desert country. The Navy are to have what they want; and the Air force are to have exclusive tenure of El Adem airfield and lodging rights at Tripoli civilairport. 19. In order to secure agreement we have had to promise (in a secret Exchangeof Notes: the Agreement itself being left vague on this point) to give the Libyansour permanent constructions when we leave. The United States Government hadunfortunately made this concession in the unratified United States-Libyan Agree-ment of December 1951. Nevertheless, it should be possible to avoid treating this as a precedent for other countries, and we did not in practice hope to securepayment from the Libyans, who could not afford it. iThe Financial Agreement10. Whereas the Temporary Financial Agreement with Libya of13th December, 1951, said that we would cover the deficit on a budget agreed between the two Governments, Libyan resistance to such annual joint scrutiny oftheir budget has obliged us to provide in the present long-term Agreement thatwe will pay agreed fixed sums as plain financial assistance : related to Libyan needsbut not designed to cover their budget deficit.11. We undertake in the present Agreement to pay  3f million a year duringthe first five years ( 1 million for development and  2f million for budgetaryassistance), and such financial assistance annually during the following periods offive years as may be agreed between the two Governments to be suitable for thepurpose of &quot; assisting Libya to enjoy conditions of financial stability and orderlyeconomic development.&quot;12. The Libyan Government undertake to apply the funds in accordance withthe foregoing purpose, and to provide evidence about their disbursement.Operation of the Treaty and Agreements13. The interim arrangements which had been made in order to ensurecontinuity expired on 31st July and could not be extended for political reasons in libya. In order, therefore, to cover the interval preceding ratification, an Exchangeof. Notes was signed simultaneously with the Treaty and Agreements, bringing them into immediate effect.14. The Treaty and Agreements came into final effect on the exchange ofinstruments of ratification, which took place on 7th December.A. E.

</content>
</cab>
