<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/18 images: 368-379</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government most SECRET.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO.SCANDINAVIA..GeneralPolicy.previous reference:r.M.(39) 18 th conclusions, .Minute 10).W.M.  (40) 20th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 10.Confidential Annex.THIS SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that M. Prytz, the Swedish Minister, was leavingLondon for Stockholm that day, and that he himselfeither that day or the following day proposed to havea general discussion with M. Wallenberg, who had arranged to return to Sweden on Wednesday, the 24thJanuary, 1940.     In the meanwhile, the War Cabinet would no doubt have noted that, according to a report containedin Telegram No. 34 (R), dated 20th January, 1940, fromHis Majesty&apos;s Minister, Oslo,   M. Koht, theNorwegian Minister for Foreign Affairs, during a debate in the Storting, had spoken of Norwegian lossesat sea, in the course of which he had admitted that thes.s. DEPTFORD might have been sunk by a german submarine. . He (M. Koht) had gone on to say that awhole month after this had happened, British and Frenchnewspapers had declared that Norway was unable to keepthe war out of her territory and that consequently theAllies should encroach upon it with their warships.The Norwegian Foreign Minister had argued that there wasno justification for such an attitude, and had gone reactions far as to say that even if it were true that oneof the belligerent powers was violating Norwegianneutrality, that fact did not give the other side any right whatever to act in a similar manner.    The wholespeech had been most unhelpful from our point of view.

THE LORD PRIVY SEAL expressed anxietyregarding the scale of ore deliveries by Sweden toGermany.     On the basis of the 1938 figures, germany would receive 9,700,000 tons out of a total of12,700,000 tons as compared with 1,600,000 tons dueto us.     Moreover, it appeared from the latestreport by the Minister of Economic Warfare     .  .(W. P. (R. ) (40) 22), that deliveries of ore to germany from Narvik were on the increase, since out of thetotal 325,000 tons for the month of January, it was believed that no less than 100,000 tons had been shipped to Germany since the beginning of the presentyear.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that the French Government had informed himalso that our estimates of deliveries of ore from narvik to Germany were lower than those which theyhad formed.   He proposed to discuss the whole matterduring his Interview  with M.. Wallenberg. - On thegeneral question of the Swedish Government&apos;s trade agreement, there was,., it should be remembered a&quot;gentlemenfs agreement&quot; between the Swedes and ourselves, that the former should do everything possible, in the way of raising technical difficulties,to,slow down the rate of deliveries to Germany. 1 Thefigures cited by the Lord Privy Seal certainlysuggested, however, that deliveries from Narvikwere on the increase;   and he would look into thematter.

THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was clear that the Germans were making desperateefforts to increase the shipments of ore from narvik.    He inquired whether it had yet &quot;beenpossible to follow up the suggestion which he had made at the meeting of the War Cabinet noted in the margin, regarding giving of publicity to the deliberate and repeated attacks by German submarineson Swedish and Norwegian vessels.   The latestinstance was that of the Swedish s, s, PA JALA, the sinking of which was reported in that day&apos;s press;this ship had been engaged not in trade with thiscountry, but in carrying grain from the Argentineto Sweden.    It was not sufficient for the neutralsto say they did not wish to be drawn into the war,since in fact they had already been so drawn byGermany.    The only question was whether they intended to maintain a one-sided attitude of neutrality against ourselves.   By assisting theGermans, through increasing the export of ore, theywere piling up the case for us to takecountervailing action.   In this connexion it was worth while considering whether the laying of minesby us in Norwegian territorial waters was open tosuch strong objection as ordering our destroyersto operate inside territorial waters.   The Swedesand the Iforwegians also should be made to understandthat there were limits to our patience.In reply to a question by the First LordOf the Admiralty, THE SECRETARY OF STATE FORFOREIGN AFFAIRS said that it was doubtful whether,even if Germany had been declared the aggressor

tagainst Poland by the League of Nations, it wouldbe possible to argue that the Swedes and the norwegians were bound under Article 16 of theCovenant to withhold supplies of ore from Narvik,in view of the fact that some two or three yearspreviously, the Assembly of the League had passedan interpretitave resolution under which each country was given the right to judge what action,if any, it should take under that Article ofthe CovenantsTHE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER said thatthe speech by M. Koht in the Norwegian Storting hadbeen most unfair since the particulars of the losses of Norwegian ships had been given in sucha way as to suggest that we were as much to blameas the Germans0THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was.obvious that M0 Koht had gone out of his way tomake excuses for the Germans,,     He regarded it as ofgreat importance that the Dominions should bebrought to realise the true position in this matterand he suggested that the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should take appropriate stepsto this end.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR DOMINIONAFFAIRS said that the Dominion High commissioners in London were no doubt aware of the position.He would, however, despatch a reasoned telegram on the whole subject to each of the DominionGovernments.

In reply to a question &quot;by the Lord privy seal, the SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said, on the general question of the Narvik oresupplies, he had made it clear to M. Colban, theNorwegian Minister, that we had made certain suggestions for remedying the situation which we regarded as intolerable, and that we expectedto receive&quot; from him very shortly a communicationeither commenting on our suggestions or making countersuggestions.    He realised the need for not lettingmatters slide, but he proposed to give M. Colban aday or two more before returning to the subject.The ?!far Cabinet agreed:-That the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should address tothe Dominion Governments a telegramsetting out for their informationfull particulars regarding thetreatment by Germany of Scandinavianshipping, not only when trading to thiscountry, but also when engaged in tradewith other parts of the world.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.22nd January, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
