<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/15/11 images: 104-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(ffHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. )TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY, . . . ^most,   SECRET.It is requester^hal special ca, e may he taken ensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO.W.Mo(4Q) 259th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 2.Confidential Annex.(26th September, 1940 - 12 Noon.)OPERATION&quot;MENACE&quot;.(previous ousRef er enc e sW.M.(40) 258thConclusions,Minute 2.)THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY read thefollowing telegram which had been received from theGommander-in-Chief, South Atlantic, on the previous afternoon:-&quot;following from General de Gaulle.   BeginsI have decided to go direct to Konakry and land my troops there.     My intention is torally French Guinea and march on Bamakowith a view to eventually operating againstDakar.     Request to be covered by fleetduring landing.     I suggest Force &quot;A&quot; goesto Freetown from where they could act insupport if needed.     Ends.     Requestimmediate reply&quot;.In reply, telegrams had been despatchedas follows:-To General de Gaulle:      &quot;We are naturallyanxious to help you but we should like toknow more precisely the nature of support which you would expect for your operations in French Guinea from Force &quot;A&quot;or such partof it as may be able to remain at Freetown&quot;.To the Commander-ih-Chief, South Atlantic:&quot;Submit your views on General de Gaulleksproposals for landing at Konakri and operations in French Guinea and/or suchreply as he may make to our telegram 0115/26,asking for more precise information as tothe nature of the support he requires&quot;.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it. would clearly be rather a blow to General de Gaulle if he were now togo to Duala,-:     From the point of view of prestige,the Konakry proposal was, no doubt, more attactiveto him.THE FIRST SEA LORD gave particulars.of theFrench forces of the Vichy Government which had recently been put into Konakry.     These included anumber of guns.The First Sea Lord added that it&apos;was understood that General de Gaulle now Wished    tosend his force to Freetown in the first instance.

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs thought that we could not decide on the next stepto be taken, until we had received a reply to ourtelegrams to General de Gaulle and the BritishCommanders,,      In general he was not in favour ofmaking another attempt at landing on the west african coast merely on the principle that&quot;something must be done&quot;0    If an opportunitypresented itself where there was a good prospect that a landing by General de Gaulle might be decisive, well and goodo      But   while we must continue to back General de Gaulle - we ought not to provoke an action with the pro-Vichy forcesin West Africa unless we were pretty sure of success,,It was important for our prestige not to make orto continue unsuccessful attempts0The best course might well be for general de Gaulle to land at Duala in order to consolidate the position of the Free French Forcesin French Equatorial Africa, or again General de -Gaulle&apos;s forces might be used in the defence ofEgypt6For the moment the important thing was togive all the encouragement we could to the anti-German forces which were at work in the French Empire.     Before Dakar it had seemed that Frenchopinion was moving steadily in our direction, andaway from Germany.   Dakar might call a halt tothese developments0   But at least the Dakar episodeought to increase French self-confidence.    It shouldbe our aim to see that this rising confidencedeveloped in an anti-German, rather than an anti-British sense.    Let us be beware of plucking thefruit before it was ripe.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed that we shouldbe careful of embarking upon new adventures withinadequate preparations.    But nothing was easieror uore fatal than to relapse., into a-policy &quot;of.mere negation.     He thought history would showthat Dakar had failed as the result, not of rashnessbut of excess of care.    It was not to be supposedthat General de Gaulle had proposed a landing atKonakri without some assurances of support from french Hmt Guinea.. For the moment the only prudent coursewe&quot; to await General de Gaulle&apos;s reply to our telegram^In the discussion the following additionalpoints were made:(i)   She ill success of operation &quot;Menace&quot; mightbe expected to weaken the position of theFree French Forces in French equaltorial africa unless General de Gaulle took somepositive action to strengthen that position.    This was one of the arguments for a landing at Duala0

(ii)    THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR THE COLONIESfavoured a landing by General de Gaulleat Duala since this would &quot;be strengthen-ing an already sound position.    It was important to stabilise the positionin those areas in our favour.    He was opposed to landings at either Konakryor. Freetown.    Any action which might lead to an attack on Freetown &quot;by french naval forces ought to he avoided.(iii)    THE FIRST SStk LORD said that air attacks on Gibraltar had continued on theprevious day.    Presumably they were merely .in retaliation for Dakar andwould cease unless we attempted some further adventure in French West Africa,(iv)   The First S-e&amp; Lord thought that wewere in a position to deal with any threat from the French naval forces in west African waters.   At the same time he was reluctant to see naval forces,which were badly needed elsewhere, tiedup by an operation at Konakry.The War Cabinet:-(1) Deferred a decision as to thedestination of General de Gaulle&apos;sforce, and of the finaldisposition of Force &quot;A&quot; pendingreceipt of the replies to the telegrams sent to General de gaulle and the British Commanders.(2) Invited the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs, afterconsultation with the PrimeMinister, to telegraph to theDominion Prime Ministers informing them fully of the course of operation &quot;Menace&quot; and of thereasons for the breaking off ofthe Operation.   It should be made clear that the information inthe telegram was for the personal information of the Dominion PrimeMinisters^(3) Invited the Minister of information to tell the Press and the B.B.C.that no British warships had been sunk as the result of theoperation, and that some of our ships had been hit in the duel withthe Dakar forts, but none had been seriously damaged.Richmond Terrace, S,W,1*




</content>
</cab>
