<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 51-56</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THIS gitQPJflggY OP HIS BHICTAHIC MAJESTOVS GOTMRNMBIW)S B C E S T.105(26) . COPY HQ.        VG A B I M jj ToHO US E OP LORDS KiSSFOHMoUote by the Lord Privy seal in connection with the    He port of the lordChancellor&apos;s Committee upon   the Keform of the House of iLords,  it may  ba useful for the Cabinet to read the Memorandum which Lord S el borne submitted as head of the deputation of the Executive Committee of the National Unionist and Conservative Association to the Prime Minister.      With the Prime Minister1 s leave, therefore, I circulate it to the Cabinet.&apos; S.March 9 th,  1926 iIICop. 27  (26).
copy, OF STATEMT Oii&apos; THE DEPUTATION Qy THISigsquTivs committee, council acts confjj&amp;ence&apos; Off gHS, fl+U, AND -OtAy TO TH&amp; - jeigMB MINTSgEB Oi-I OCTOBER,  6. 19S5,At the outset we wish to ensure ourselves that you are not under a misapprehension as to the position we take up or as to the considerations we would urge upon you and upon Hie Majesty1 a Government.   We do not &quot;believe that any Second Chamber,  however,  composed, can &quot;curb&quot; a democracy or prevent a revolution, if the people really desire a revolution.Our country is a democracy and we accept the full consequences of that fact.     If a majority of the olactors really desire to carry into effect the policy of the Socialist party, to abolish private capital, to nationalise all the means of production, distribution or exchange, to substitute a republic for a monarchy,, or to exchange the present system of parliamentary government for something very different, these changes will take place and we shall have to submit.But it Is a  grotesque travesty of democracy that these changes should be able to take place, although the majority of the electors may be wholly opposed to them.      This is possible in Great Britain to-day, but not in any other free, and civilised country in the world.     No other country chooses to run such a risk.      Jivery other country has by one constitutional device or another made sure that fundamental changes of thin nature shall not place, unless themajority of the electors are determined that they shall take place .The Parliament Act of 1911 was avowedly a temporary stop-gap measux&apos;e, so stamped by its own preamble,&apos; and the completion of the readjustment of the constitution was
described by the Liberal Minister of the  day, My Asquith., as &quot;a debt of honour which brooked no delay&quot;.      That was 14 years ago,  but no attempt has been made to redeem that pledge.She Conservative and Unionist Government might fall to-morrow through some chance of political warfare and. a Socialist Government might be returned to power with a clear majority of its own in the House of Commons; not because the majority of the electors had accepted or approved the Socialist programme, but because they had been angry or annoyed with something which the Conservative and Unionist Government had done or had not done.Then would come the Socialist opportunity under the Parliament Act.      ./e know that there are moderate men in the Socialist party;    but the Socialist programme, accepted by moderate and extremists alike,  is a revolutionary programme, and wo are convinced that in a Socialists1  government the power would rest not with the moderate but with the extreme men.The Socialist programme is an immense one, but by the use of the Parliament Act,  it could all be passed into law within five years, and the Socialists could then dissolve on a completed programme, but on untried legislation and much of the mischief done would be irreparable.Under a. section of the Parliament Act,  if the house of Commons passes a bill three times in the game form in two years, and the House of Lords rejects that bill or amends- it in a way unacceptable to the house of Commons,  it is automatically presented to the Xing for the r.oyal assent and becomes an Act of Parliament.      In our opinion, the first thing a Socialist government would do would be to re-enact D.O.H.A. in a permanent form under this section of the Par1iament Act.
*J 1,9&apos;/i&apos;e assert this confidently, because, although the Socialist party have been careful not to disclose their plan of campaign in advance, they have stated again and again that the present forms of parliamentary procedure in the House of Commons are obstructive, absurd, antiquated and fatal to their realisation of their policy, and that they are going to sweep them away directly they get the chance.We assert that they will re-enact D^O-road because D,O.H.Ac is a precedent before their eyas which would exactly meet their needs.      The form that the new 31..0-R.A. would take would be something like this.      If the House of Commons passed a resolution in favour, say, of the nationalisation of the banks or of the land,  or in favour of a republic,  that is all that the House of Commons would have ,to do ,      The resolution would be given effect to by an Order in Council, the details oi &quot;which would be settled by a Committee of the Cabinet, assisted by &quot;experts&quot; from the Socialist headquarters in Hccleston Square,   and by the parliamentary draftsman; and the Order in Council would have the legal force of an Act of Parliament.      By this plan not only would the House of lords be ignored but all control over the details of legislation would be removal from the house of Commons;  and in the three years of the life of the social&amp;St majority in the House of Commons, which would remain after the first two years h.ad been spent in re-enacting D*0*R.A., the whole Socialist policy could be put on the Statute book and the dissolution could take place without its ill effects having ma&amp;o themselves fully manifest.If it is urged that public opinion would show itself so manifestly hostile to this procedure that it would be defeated, we are not able to agree *     In the first place tnere is to-day no one public opinion. The public opinion which moves the Socialists does not
move us ,  and the public opinion which moves us does not move the Socialists.      In the second place, we do not bel:i ove that a majority of the electors sufficiently understand the necessity and value of the forms of procedure of the House of Commons quickly to resent the attack which the Socialists will make upon them. In our opinion the Socialist majority in the House of Commons would  &quot;sit tight7&apos; during the two years,  in which D*O.R.A. was being re-enacted, and then the mischief would be lone.we foresee is entirely in accordance with the methods adopted by the Trade Union Congress and Socialist party in m/an&amp;ging their own internal affairs,  and with the hussian methods so much admired by British Socialists.at our command is that the  question at issue is no question of the powers or privileges of the Peers, but that it is no loss than this - how can the rights of the majority of the electors be so safeguarded, that no fundamental issues can be settled otherwise than they deliberately wish that they should be settled ?     Put thus, we assert that the subject is a popular one and not an unpopular ong.manner we have indicated and. in certain other respects, and the House of Lords has got to be reformed.      To frqma. and propose the necessary legislation is the business ofMajesty&apos;s Government. agree that they must deal withe two parts of one question simultaneously,  though weWe wish also to point out the the procedure point wa w.ould mske to you with allThe Parliament Act has got to be amend-bd in thesuggest that they might well be dealt with in two separatehills,
Before the war all Members of Parliament and candidates thoroughly understood this question and were aware of its vast importance..      The electorate also were familiar with it.      Then came the war and it came down like a shutter on the past.     Mew questions of great moment arose out of the war absorbing public interest and a new electorate has arisen which knows little or nothing about this question^ and many Members of Parliament and candidates are also very dimly aware of its importance.     At the general election in October, 19 4? you used these words at Perth to the people of Scotland -T,So I think it is our duty to consider, within &quot;the framework of the Parliament Act, whether it is practicable &quot;to make provision for the machinery of the Second Chamber for preserving the ultimate authority in legislation to the &quot;considered judgment of the people&quot;..v&apos;e accept those words as covering the whole field which has to be covered^ but we appeal to you to^re^eat them and develop them to the people of England, and to give the lead on the subject to your followers which they are looking for and which they sorely need.

</content>
</cab>
