<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 57-68</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;QNf! DENT SAL LIBRARYmmSG R E To CP.  10 6 (26S THE PRgyrg^ HI^^I^NIC^rK^yqPvEf JMEN1visas1   PfMl   B ^ TOY NO:    OOREPORT OF THE COAL COMMISSIONRecommendations requiring Government Action (other than the nationalisation of Royalties )eMemorandum.bv Secretary for MinescIt is unnecessary to summarise the findings and recommendations of the Commissionj      it would he impossible to improve on the clear and concise  summary given in the last chapter of their Report-It will be necessary for the Government to consider two questions without delay.      The first is whether, or to what extent, they accept those of the Commission&apos;s recommendations that can only be put into effect by legislative or administrative action.      The second is what policy is to be followed to meet what the Commission call &quot;the present  situation&quot;,:      The decision on the second point must depend to some extent upon the decision on the first;    and it is with the first alone that the present memorandum deals.      It takes the chapters of the Report one by one,  sets out the recommondations that would require action by the Government, and comments on theme      (Recommendations to which effect could be given without action by the Government are ignored).It will be seen that one of these recommendations has already been considered an^rejected by the present Government,      With two others the Department is in emphatic disagreement.      The grounds of disagreement are fully explained.      This is done rather In order that
the criticism to which these proposals are open may be fully preBor.it to the minds of Lin 1st or s then by wry of a suggestion that the Government ought to reject them. The importance of a declaration by the Government that they accept the -deport unreservedly if they feel able to do sc is obvious,  especially in view of the emphasis with which the Comnisalon record their view that the immediate reduction of wages recommended, by them &quot;should depend upon the acceptance by all parties of such measures of re-organisation, as will sec 111=6 to the industry a new lease of prosperity leading to higher wages&quot;,      &quot;Acceptance&quot; by the Government at this stage does not, of course, mean a31 undertaking to give effect to all the recommendations in all eventualitiesj    It merely means that the Government will not,  of their own motion, refuse to take the steps that the Commission have recommended they should take; how far they may actually be called upon to do so must depend largely on the attitude of tie other  &quot;parties&quot;.neither Chapter I (on the demand, for British coal) -nor Chanter II  (on tie British coal reserves) contains a ny recomr.er.da11ons .Chapter III , on the Utilisation of Coal, makes thefollowing three recommendations :assistance      (l) That &quot;the Government should give sympathetic Lowmperature    consideration to airy or op o sals of the Fuel Research rbonisat ion.ee pp ,25-    Board for the further investigation of processes of low Temperature Carbonisation on a commercial scale.&quot; (2) That &quot;if and when the Fuel Research Board is able to report that a smokeless semi-cole  is available as suitable as ra.w coal  ........,,  the Department a which.are large users of coal should be instructed to purchase the semi-coke in prefer enice
MM i :This is a matter for the Department of scientific and Industrial Research rather than the Lines Department;hut the recommendations are so cautiously worded thatit seems perfectly safe to accept themo -Co-ordinar-      (3)    That a &quot;standing Conference&quot;  should be formed under tion of electrical      some such title as the    National Fuel and Power Gas and CoalIndustries,    Committee&quot; representative of the electrical,  coal and (See pp.28-31). g&amp;s industries for the purpose of &quot;a continuous and comprehensive survey of the heat,  light and power requirements of the country .....It would exercise functions which would he advisory and not, executive.      Its primarytask would be to ensure that, while a healthy competitionshould be maintained, where it sir. legitimate, between these various interests,  their energies should be devolped in a manner complementary, in the main, to one another.This Is put forward not as a &quot;definite recommendation&quot;but as a &quot;suggestion for&apos;consideration&quot;.      It is perhaps a little nebulous..      It Is difficult to visualise  justhow such a body would set about its task,  or whom,  Inpractice,  it would &quot;advise&quot;.      But no exception can be taker,to the idea underlying the recommendation, and in any casea general acceptance of the recommendations in the Reportdoes not here mean more than an und.erta.king to considerthe suggestion.    Obviously the Government could not commit themselves further than this without consultation withthe industries cone erne-.1.More money     Chapter IV. Research.      The only recommendation in this for research,        chapter directly affecting the Lines Department is &quot;that (See ppc.39-43),, the valuable work now being done on safety and health becontinued and developed.      As this work is financed almost entirely out of the Liners&apos;   vYelf are Fund, this recommendation does not necessarily mean any further expenditure from public funds,      Certain other recommendations about the development of research by the industry itself
apparently point to increased expenditure by the Department of Scientific end Industrial Research, and that Department will no doubt advise the Government on the point.      There can be no doubt that the coal raining industry in general has beon backward in research, largely owing to its excessive individualism. Chanter V contains a  long survey of &quot;the Structure of the industry&apos;,      It come a to the conclusion that, generally speaking,  the existing units are too small and that amalgamat ions are desirable,  but that the right procedure is rather to. foster amalgam?.tions for which there is a spontaneous movement within the industry than to try to inppso then by cut.side authority.    The exact nature of the machinery recoi mended is rather obscure,  but the intention is clear enough., viz;  (a.) that it should be made impossible for  schemes of amalgamation to be venderod abortive by , f or inst,ance , failure to agree on financial terms,  or, by resistance by an un-reasonable minority,  and (b)  that provision should be made under which,  If,  after a lapse of three years,  the Mines Department certifies that  this scheme of fostering amalgamation from within has hot proved sufficiently successful  ,  it would be possible for concerns which ought to amigamate but refuse to do so to be taken over compulsorily by some entorprising outsider.The t;iining Association will probably have a good deal to say about these prcoosnls.      But, by comparison with the &quot;Duekhan&quot; Scheme, wl ich the Government of the day accoptedd.n 1919,   they certainly do not. err on the side of being too drastic,  and public  opinion will,, no doubt, expect the- Government to accept them.      The arguments on each side are fully set out in cages 49-62 of the report.
1ifChapter VI is a reasoned rejection of the proposals put forward for nationalisation of mines and contains no recommendations.Underground Chapter VII, recommending the nationalisation ofway leaves.(See po84) royalties,  is dealt with  in a separate memorandum (Uoo2)But it includes a recommendation not strictly germane to its main subject that &quot;the right to impose a charge for underground wayleaves where no service Is rendered or detriment suffered should he abolished for the future&apos; What the Commission meant was not that charges of this sort already created should he abolished, but that they should not be allowed to be created in future. The proposals, for the nationalisation of royalties do not altogether meet the point,  for there will  still be other minerals (and some coal) in the hands of private owners.    The principle is one that is likely to commend itself to public opinion, but some clearer wordsthan &quot;where no service is rendered or detrimentsuffered&quot;will be needed for purposes of legislation.ffiiunicipai trading Ohapter VIII, on Distribution,, makes two recommendations ffln coal.(See pp.92 93).     (l) That Local Authorities should be empowered to tradein coal.    The Commission say this rather dubiously, notfeeling certain that it will do any good,  and recommendthat the Mines Department should review the situationafter the lapse of two years.This proposal was before the present Cabinet inMarch 1925,  and was  rejected by them.    A full statementof the arguments for and against the proposal wasfurnished at that time.jjjfflicial sampling (S)        That inquiries should be made in the principal mpd- analysis.l(oee PP&quot;?4;&amp; 95)&apos;coal importing -countries with a view to calling aninternational conference  (should It seem desirable) to discuss whether it would be useful and practicable to
establish a Public Authority,   recognised by foreign purchasers,  for the purpose of sampling and analysing cargoes of export ooal at the loading ports.This is a question that must be discussed with the colliery owners, but there can be no reason why the Government should not at once express their willingness to do their part-A Standing Chapter IX,  on the Conveyance of coal,  advocatesCommittee onMineral Trans-       improvements in railway transport, e .g. by a greater (See pp.104-106). raeasure 0f standardisation of wagons, an increased provision of wagons of larger capacity, and an extension of the principle of common user.    In order to secure progress on these lines, the Commission recommend(a) that a Joint Committee of the Ministry of Transport and Mines Department should be appointed, whose duty it would be to see that &quot;continuous attention was given to those matters&quot; and to report to Parliament annually;(b) that the appropriate Department, (presumably the Ministry of Transport)  should be given power to make regulations for the standardisation of wagons,  on the recommendation of the  Joint Committee;(c) that if legislation is necessary to enable the Railway Companies to give effect to the Commissions recommendation for preferential rates on large capacity and common user wagons,  it should be passed.These again will have to be discussed with the Railway Companies and the Coal Trade.    But there does not seem to be any reason  (subject to the view of the Ministry of Transport) why the Government should not &quot;accept&quot; then.Oha-pter X - General Observations on the Relations between Employers and Employed - amd Chap^te^XI,  on Output, contain no recommendations requiring action by the  Government.
Oucrpulsory Chapter XII, contains an exhaustive exam!not!on of the profit-sharing wages system end makes numerous recommendations for its [See ppol41-3; .                                                                                                  xuoimprovement.    The only one that requires action by the Government is the recommendation that profit-sharing schemes should be made compulsory.    &quot;We suggest&quot; they say &quot;that by suitable legislation colliery undertakings generally should be required, within a stated period, to adopt schemes providing that of all the profits hereafter distributed above a standard dividend on the existing capital.. .**a fixed proportion sh ould be   &apos;. reserved as shares to be issued to employeeso&quot;The Commission were impressed by the importance, as a cause of unrest,  of the fact that under any system of determining wages rates on a larger unit than that which determines profits,  it is inevitable that many concerns should make very large profitSc    This is their proposal for allaying this unrest.    Prom this point of view the Government should, it is suggested, not only accept it, but press the two sidet  faith neither of whom it is likely to find favoiir) also to accept it.      On the wider question of the policy of doing this sort of thing by legislation, the Ministry of labour will no doubt give their views.    It may be mentioned that in Prance the Government, as mineral owner, imposes a condition of this sort in all its mining leases. Chapter XIII on Hours.    The conclusion is arrived at that the men ought not to have a longer working day (unless they freely choose that alternative to a reduction in wages) but that the two following points ought t o be considered :
ffGreater elastic ffeity in th estatutory S-egulation of Kours .IfSee p .  175) .lite mat ive of Mines Depart-llanb Return, rasee p ^ 183 ) .[ransfer of pem.plc.yed liners ?ee pp. 188-9)Ewtuifi eat ions m Mine liana gers Ilsee p; 190)fa) Whether the law might not he made rather more elastic in order to prevent the  &quot;quite disproportionate loss of time and earnings&quot; that is sometimes caused hy its present rigidity.(b) Whether the definition of working time by the day rather than by the week is always essential; whether the daily limit might not be extended to 8 hours or evenmore provided that a total of 42 was not exceeded inthe week*These are obviously points which  the Mining Association and Miners1  Federation will have to discuss with  one another;    but the  Government can  safely offer to ask Parliament to give effect to any recommendation on which they may agree.In Chapter XIY relating to &quot;Regularity of Work&quot;, the only recommendation affecting the Government is a minor one about the wording of a Mines Department Return of absenteeism.     Effect will be given to this. Chapter XV on Recruiting and Personnel makes two re commend ati ons:(a) That mine owners end miners,  either nationallyor by districts, should consider in con junction with the Ministry of labour practical steps for securing the transfer of unemployed miners from one district to another.The Ministry of Labour will no doubt be willing to do their part in this.    A somewhat similar recommend-ation is made in Chapter XXI.(b) That the Mines Department should consider whether the  regulations governing the qualifications  of mine Managers are not of such a nature as to deter men of good general education from entering the  industry.This will be dene.
Chapter -XVI deals with Safety end Health and contains no recommcndations.Chapter XVII on Housing, makes no specific redommenda-tions requiring Government action.Chapter XVIII on Welfare recommends:Royalties to (a) That royalties should contribute to the Welfarecontribute tothe Welfare Fund to the extent of 5fi (roughly L25O.000 a fund ^ &apos; &apos;    .(see p.209) year);pithead baths       (b) that pithead baths should he made generally to he compulsory.(see pp.204-208)  compulsory.(c) that the cost of this should be met from the welfare Fund.The proposed contribution cf the royalty owners to the Welfare Fund is dealt with in the memorandum (Ho.2)on Nationalisation of Royalties.    As to the proposal that pithead baths should he made compulsory, few people would deny that this ought to have been donelong ago.    But the proposal that the money for thisshould be found from the Miners1 Welfare Fund,instead of by the colliery owners themselves, maywell be the subject of criticism.    This view was expressed to the Commission by the Department inthe following note, privately communicated to them.&quot;Surely modern opinion recognises generally that an employer of labour in a process that is bound to make the workmen filthy is under a moral obligation to provide facilities to them to make themselves clean again before they leave his premises,    This has long be.en recognised in - foreign countries;   why should&quot;we set any lower standard .for ourselves?    If this is the right way to look at it, what justification can there be for treating pithead baths in any different way from any other essential part of the equipment . of a colliery;    Surely the fact that  the obligation has been so long disregarded,  and the colliery owners have so long had the enjoyment of the capital that ought to have been looked&apos;up, reinforces rather than weakens the argument.
tatutory Pit Committee-see pp.813-816) .The  only reason given in the draft is &quot;the present economic condition of the industry&quot;. Is this really an;; reason -at all ?   ho-one has ever suggested that a law should at any time he passed requiring baths to be ,eroctad everywhere, instantly-      The natural- thing to do would be to require the owner a to erect them within a certain period - say five years, or even longer.      The state of the industry at the time of the passing of the Act is immaterial.     During the period prescribed the industry will have had its normal ups and downs;    and collieries must take the opportunity of the first  &quot;up&quot; to lay by money for tho purpose-.      In the three years 19 2E-3-4 (one bad year,  one good and ono fair) the profits ,of the industry (after setting off losses) were about  50 ,000 ,-000 *      To have had to find four or five millions even in this short period, would not have hurt the Indus try.The proposal that the hoyalty. Owne r should be called upon to bear part of the cost seems to be open to tho same criticism.     would it not be difficult to persuado Parliament that it was right to confiscate part of the income of sfvary large ^number of Individuals (many of them/modest means) in order to relieve colliery owners of part of an obligation that they ought to have discharged years ago ?&quot;It is und rstood that the reason why the Commission found it impossible to accept this view was that they could not reconcile a recommendation to impose this heavy new charge on the industry with their description of its present -parlous economic condition. Chapter XIX,  &quot;Association of the workers&quot; deals chiefly with Part II  of the Mining Industry Act,  1920.      This measure, as is well known, set up a system of statutoryjoint committees of owners and men In a regular hierarchy from the pit to the &quot;national Board.&quot; and provided that in certain circumstances mandatory force might be given to the  cecision of the higher bodies.      The Miners federation In the first instance, and the Mining Association later, refused to take the necessary steps to set up these Committees,  and the provisions of Part II lapsed,  in accordance with a section of the Act which provided that this should happen if either side failed to avail themselves of them.      The Miners
Federation, in evidence before the Commission, strongly pressed for the revival of Part II.      The Commissiondo not recommend this in its  entirety (holding that forthe district and nations,! machinery the existingvoluntary committees meet the case) but do recommendthat the statutory obligation to set up pit committees should be revived.     This proposal is open to serious objection, as was pointed out to the Commission in thefollowing note  :&quot;In the earlier part of this chapter the point is made with much force that it  is far better to leave these matters to voluntary action than to &quot;the compulsion of an Act of Parliament and the rigidity of departmental regulations&quot;.      It is pointed out that a considerable amount of machinery of this sort has been the  &quot;spontaneous croation of the industry itself&quot;; but that the machinery has not extended to the captaine. The conclusion is therefore regretfully reached that compulsion must be applied to the pit.Ought not the conclusion rather to be that, since compulsion by Act of Parliament and departmental regulations is in practice futile if not mischievous, there is nothing for it but merely to exhort the industry to extend the machinery downwards.     Bven if an Act of Parliament could take the horse to the water (which may well bo questioned) it seems hardly possible that it could make it drink.      From the administrative point of view the  job of nationalising royalties is far less formidable than the job of compelling managers to set up Committees.      The prospect of the  apartment being constantly dragged into squabbles on this subject with no real powers behind them except the absurd one of prosecuting a manager, is really alarmingo      hor would even that remedy generally be open, for nothing would be easier than to observe the form of Act and Regulations but to make them nugatory by disregarding their spirit. Form here, is nothing;    spirit is everything.      To say this is not in the least to question the truth of all that the Commission say about the desirability of pit committees.      The professed fears of owners and. managers are absurd;    properly run, the committees can do nothing but good.   But must we not be on our guard against making the mistake that America has made of imagining the legislature to be omnipotent?     May it not be that a matter such as this, in which the vital point is not the existence of a machine but the spirit in which it is worked, is one In which the legislature ought to recognise its impotence?&quot;Ths&apos; Commission were no doubt impressed by thedifficulty of taking this view about a measure which hadalready been placed on the Statute Book and on the revival of which the miners evidently set such great
Hi oimport anco.Chap t er XX , dealing with Profits, malr.es no rec omraen&amp;a-tions.Chapter XXI    contains the Commissions proposals for moating the  present situation.      This raises questions of a different kind from those dealt with in this memorandum and will be the subject of a separate memorandum (Bo.3).      The  only definite recommendation that it makes that requires departmental action is contained in Its concluding words that  &quot; should the occasion arise after the discontinuance of the Subsidy the Government should be ready to take all practicable measures for the assistance of any labour that may be displaced or for facilitating its transfer, and should provide such funds as might be  required for this purp ose * &quot;This ia a matter primarily for the Ministry of labour.G* lu I&amp;1CB-F0X.M ine s he pa r t m an t.March 10 th.,19  5 .

</content>
</cab>
