<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 459-466</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S I era S T &apos;2   -I N E T Codv No.CP,  llgjfgjjj &quot; *IMIl^JL. MABOTISG COMMISSION. Memorandum by the Secretary of Stats for l-ominion Affairs.I feel bound to draw the earnest attention of my colleague to the attached telegram from Mi&apos;. Bruce on our proposals for Empire Marketing and to ash for a decision which will enable me to reply to it.    In that telegram, while acquiescing in our proposals as a temporary expedient pending the Imperial Confer-ence, and accepting the view that British Agriculture should be included in the scope of the Marketing Commissions activi-ties,  he protests in the strongest terms both against the form of organisation set up and against our failure to fulfil our promise as regards ths amount to be expended.On the first point there ought to be no difficulty in making clear to him that he is under a misunderstanding both as to the nature of our own proposals and as to those of the Imperial Economic Committee.    The organisation we are proposing, though under a Cabinet Minister in order to  secure the Parlia-mentary responsibility which the Imperial Economic Committee itself admitted as necessary,  is in no sense departmental,, Nor Is there any danger,  the principle of non-surrenderable grant-in-aid once having been admitted , of undue Treasury interference,  or of Parliament wishing to vary the amount. The auefition whether a Bill might be  desirable to ensure the continuance of the work of the Commission if we went out of office is a matter which might be discussed at the Imperial Conference.      On ths other hand the Imperial Economic Committee(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRXTAIOIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVKRJMiSKT)
always contemplated that the body actually entrusted with the expenditure of British money should be a British body and subject to the United Kingdom Parliament and not an inter-Imperial body responsible to all the Governments such as Mr. Bruce suggests.    A body of that sort could only be constituted on a satisfactory basis if all the parties represented on it were also contributors.    Mr. Bruce1s proposal in this respect is a novel one which cannot be usefully discussed before the Imperial conference meets,  but is not very likely to commend itself to either Canada or South Africa.Much more serious is the second charge - to which we have no reply - that we are not fulfilling our promise, given In December 1924,  that we should spend  1,000,000 annually on helping Empire marketing in lieu of the preferences promised in 1923.    The natural interpretation of that promise undoubtedly was that it should take effect in the ooming financial year,  i.e.. 1925-26, and our proposals do inevitably expose us to Mr. Bruce&apos;a criticism that the British Government  &quot;has avoided its obligation for one year entirely, has reduced it by a half for another year and only gives effect to its full under-taking in the third year&quot;.On this point I have no doubt that Mr. Bruce is voicing what will be the view of all those in the Dominions - and here also - who care about Empire co-operation and wish to help British trade.    Our decision, unless we modify it,  is bound to be severe, slap in the face for those who have believed in the sincerity of the Prime Minister1s electoral manifesto that Empire development is &quot;the first and dominant item in our policy&quot;. Its reaction on the whole of ourvImperial relations may be incalculable.   During the years immediately ahead of us&apos;
10th March,  1926,it is going to be a very close issue whether the oentri fugal forces which are making for the break up of the Empire arc not to prevail over the forces making for a continued and closer unity.    In suoh a situation it is surely unwise to  expose ourselves to the Reserved accusation that in a matter affecting the interests of the Dominions we do not attempt to fulfil our promises .I fully realise the difficulties of the present financial situation.    But I    ould nevertheless earnest! appeal to the Cabinet to reconsider its decision.    If we cannot see our way to making tho amount lor the coming year the full  1,000,000,  we could at least announce that the missing  500,000 will be added over the next two years.    That announcement made now, when the scheme itself is being made public, will help a great deal to assure its favourable reception here and in the Dominions,  and to prepare a reasonable atmospher for  the Imperial Conference.L.S.A.Dominions Office,
Telegram from the Governor General of the Commonwealth of Australia to the Secretary of State for Dominion    Affairs,  dated 6th March, 1926.Received! Dominions Office 2.20 p.m. and 5.5 pom.  6th March,  19261No.  D.O.  56,Confidential.    Following for Prime Minister from my Prime Minister:    Begins:-   lour telegram of 1st March &apos; we have considered proposals set out in your telegram for   ... sriving effect to the recommendations of the Imperial Economic Committee and are prepared to accept them as a temporary expedient until the whole question can be discussed in October at the Imperial Conference.    In doing so however I desire tomake it clear that we hold the view most strongly that the Administration of grant should have been placed in the hands of an Executive Commission as recommended in the Heport of the Imperial Economic Committee freed from all departmental control.With regard to the two specific points you raise we arein complete agreement with the proposal to extend the scopeof grant to embrace home as well as Dominions produce as weconsider that if any action is to be effective it must bebased on the principle of preserving to the fullest oxtentthe interests of the consumers and benefit Empire producersas a whole which of course includes British producers.(?)Australian producers have no desire to advantaged at the expense of British producers but do desire that they should have the fullest opportunities in the British markets subject to the necessary safeguarding of interests of British producers We are also prepared to agree to your suggestions that an additional member of the Imperial Economic Committee should be nominated to represent British agricultural interests.
[16 &amp; 17 Geo. 5.]    Post Office (Sites).3shewn on the deposited plans and described in the A.D, 1926. deposited books of reference.  (2) Any lands acquired by the Postmaster-General for the purposes of the public service under the authority 5 of this Act shall be vested in and be held by him in his corporate capacity on behalf of His Majesty His Heirs and Successors for the purpose of the post office.3. In settling any question of disputed purchase Cbmpensa-money  or  compensation  under  this  Act  the  official tion in case10 arbitrator settling the same shall not award any sum of G* recently money for or in respect of any improvement alteration buflcfinss or building made or erected or any interest in the lands created after the twentieth day of November nineteen hundred and twenty-five if in the opinion of such arbi-15 trator the improvement alteration or building or the creation of the interest in respect of which the claim is made was not reasonably necessary and was made or created with a view to obtaining or increasing compensa-tion under this Act.20 4. If any omission misstatement or erroneous Correction description is found to have been made of any lands or of errors, of any owners lessees or occupiers of any lands shewn &amp;c&quot; or intended to be shewn on the deposited plans or described in the deposited books of reference the Post-25 master-General may apply to two justices for the correction thereof after giving ten days&apos; notice to the owners lessees or occupiers of the lands affected by. the proposed correction and if it appears to the justices that such omission misstatement or erroneous description 30 arose from mistake they shall so certify stating the particulars thereof and their certificate shall be deposited as if the same had originally formed part of the deposited plans or deposited books of reference (as the case may be) and shall be kept therewith and shall be deemed to 35 be part thereof and thereupon the deposited plans or deposited books of reference (as the case requires) shall be deemed to be corrected according to the certificate and the Postmaster-General may enter on purchase take hold and use the lands to which the certificate relates 40 accordingly.5. It shall be lawful for the Postmaster-General and Power to for his surveyors officers and workmen at all reasonable q^^^1&quot; times in the daytime to enter into and upon any of the enter iarujs58 A3
What I have said above indicates the acquiescence of my government in the proposal(s)  set out in your telegram of1st March.        At the same time I think, that it is desirablethat I should  indicate to you quite frankly how my government regard the whole position.    In doing so I desire to make itclear that we recognise that proposed grant is a voluntarygift bj  the British Government and you will I am sure freeme from any suspioion of looking a gift horse in the mouthwhen I offer certain criticisms with regard to the actionwhich it is now proposed to take.At the Imperial Economic Conference in 192 3 certain proposals were agreed to with your Government which contemplatedan increase in preference granted to Empire produce,    Theseproposals were not put into force by the Ramsay MacdonaldGovernments    When you. retui-ned to Office you proposed to giveeffect to them but found with regard to some that you wereprecluded from action by the pledges giving during the GeneralElection,    To meet this position and show the good faith ofyour Government you in a speech made in December 1924 indicated that in substitution for the recommendations of the 1923Conference that could not be given effect to you would make anannual grant of . 1.000,000 to enable the Dominions to secure a larger share of that part of the Home markets which had tobe supplied from importation from abroad.    In the dominions office Memorandum of 5th March setting out tertrs of referenceto the Imperial Economic Committee, mention is made of the speech above cjuoted and it is indicated that the Committeewould be invited to make recommendations regarding schsme(s)which would  effect objeot(s) referred to in your speech.As the statement of your Government&apos;s intention was madein December 1924 and   effect was given to the 1923 Conference&apos;arecommendations for increased Preferences in the Budget of?assumed1925-6 my Government assumes    that the million pounds would
also be made available during that year and  that  This money would be available to give effect to the recommendations of the Imperial Economic Committee as soon as they were formulated. &apos;vVe now find that nothing is to be allocated for years 1925-6 and  only  500,000 for years 1926-27.    I have no &quot;doubt Treasury-would urge that there was no necessity to find the money as there was no avenue for its expenditure.    To that I would reply that the recommendations of the Committee were submitted in July of last year and  that in any case it is proposed that the money should be found as a grant-in-aid and even if amount was not spent in the financial year it would be.available for future requirements.Put broadly the criticism that I suggest which can be advanced  is that your Government undertook to give effect to the recommendations of the 1923 Conference that it substituted for part of those recommendaticns an annual grant of  1,000,000 and that it has avoided its obligations for one year entirely has reduced it by a half for another year and only fT-ives effect to its full undertaking in the third year. You   -ill realise how undesirable such a  criticism is in view of the feeling which has to be combated  from some quarters that Britain is not assisting Australia very materially in her markets in exchange for  8,000,000 preference that Britain is receiving in the Australian markets.    I would further   ;oint out that it is most desirable that  the full amount should be available from the beginning of financial year - 1985-26 in order to meet the necessary expenditure under more important schemes which no doubt the committee will submit in the future.Under the proposal in your telegram of the 1st March it is contemplated  that the amount involved should be submitted annually to Parliament.    This course we consider
most undesirable as it throws a question of Empire policy upon which all the Dominions and your Government declare themselves agreed back annually into the maelstrom of politics.t&apos;/a feel that the grant should be definitely allocated for a period of say five years which could be done byembodying proposals in a Bill submitted to Parliament.    Weare also strongly of opinion that the expenditure should beTinder the control of a Commission of representatives of(?)self-governing parts of the Empire with additional represents-tion for Crown Colonies and dependencies,  that such commis-sion should be freed from all political or departmental control and should report to  the heads of each of the respective governments.    Such action would ensure continuance of a definite policy over a period and would enable the whole matter to be placed upon a proper basis.    If the allotment is to be made as suggested upon estimates annually and would be controlled by what is in effect a departmental committee it will undoubtedly fall under the influence of the Treasury with considerable danger of its curtailment if not total elimination.    While I have felt compelled to set out the view that my government hold in this matter as I indicated above we are prepared  to accept the proposal(s) in your telegram of 1st March2&apos; as a temporary expedient to obviate delay and we cordially agree with your final para-graph that public interest necessitates an early an.nou.nce-ment as to what action your government proposes to take in. the matter. Message ends.  No. D;0. 41c

</content>
</cab>
