<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 547-549</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government. 1Printed for the Cabinet.SECRET. Copy No.  iCP. 129 (26;.CABINET.EAST AFRICAN AND PALESTINE LOANS.Method of Raising the proposed Loans of  10,000,000 and  4,500,000respectively.(Circulated by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.)1. THE origin of the proposed East African Guaranteed Loan was a recom-mendation in the Report of the East African Commission to the effect that, in order to ensure the economic development of the East African territories, His Majesty&apos;s Government should undertake to guarantee as to principal and interest a loan of  10,000,000, and that the arrangement should include the interest being payable by the Imperial Exchequer for the first five years, i e., during the construction period.2. The Cabinet at their meeting on the 23rd October, .1925, agreed to approve in principle the above proposal. Their approval did not, however, extend to the suggestion that the British taxpayer should be called upon to pay the interest on the loan for the first five years, and I think all are agreed that such a course would not be justifiable, and that were this to be provided for in the Bill to be laid before Parliament it would be difficult to get it accepted by the House of Commons.3. The origin of the proposed Palestine Loan and its guarantee by His Majesty&apos;s Government has already been set out in CP. 71 (26) of February 1926, and the principle of an Imperial guarantee was accepted more than a year and a half ago.4. The net result of an Imperial gxiarantee will be that, while the Exchequer will incur no direct liability, the territories concerned will, subject to Parliament approving the Bill, get money for the improvement of their transport and for their economic development on better terms than they could have done without such a guarantee, since with one exception they are not Colonies and cannot therefore issue on their own security stocks ranking as trustee investments under the Colonial Stock Acts.In estimating the contingent liability of the Imperial Exchequer, it must be remembered (a.) That most of the territories are already self-supporting, and that in those-cases where they are not the principle of supplementing their revenues by grants or loans-in-aid has always been recognised.(6.) That the proposed loans are mainly for remunerative works.(c) That the finances of all the territories are under the control of the Secretary of State for the Colonies, whose duty it will be, in view of the guarantee, to-watch those finances speciallv for the protection of the British taxpayer.(d.) That, guarantee or no guarantee, the Imperial Government could not afford to stand by and do nothing were a British Colony or Protectorate in danger of defaulting. Similar considerations apply to Palestine, which, though administered under an &quot;A&quot; Mandate, is in effect directly controlled by the British Government.(e.) That the effect of the guarantees on the credit of the Imperial Government may be regarded as negligible, the total amount concerned being so small as compared with the obligations of that Government. [143.24].
5. A question lias arisen as to how the loans should be issued, i.e., whether through the Crown Agents for the Colonies like any ordinary Colonial loan-or through the Bank of England.6. I take the view that the issue should be made through the Crown Agents, since a guaranteed loan, equally with one that is not guaranteed, is borrowed by the local Government concerned on the security of its own revenues, and I submit that the only&apos; difference is that in the former case (i.e., a guaranteed loan) there is for the public the added security of the Treasury guarantee.7. On the other hand, I understand that the Treasury take the view that on account of the guarantees the loans should be issued through the Bank of England, as in the case of British funds proper and guaranteed loans of borrowers other than Colonial Governments.8. The matter is, in my opinion, of importance in the interest of the general credit of the Colonies in the London stock market. That credit stands high so high that the prices of unguaranteed &quot; Crown Colony stocks &quot; issued under the Colonial Stock Acts are not far below those of corresponding British Government stocks and it is closely associated with the Crown Agents, with whom the stocks are domiciled. A Crown Agents&apos; loan in the eyes of the market means a loan issued with the approval of the Secretary of State for the Colonies, for which he is therefore responsible, and it is believed that this is the factor on which the investing public, to whom the Colonies themselves are little known, mainly rely. The flotation by the Crown Agents of loans guaranteed by the Imperial Government will tend to improve the general prestige of loans raised by the Crown Agents, while the placing of such loans in other hands bearing in mind the ignorance of the public in such matters -may have some effect in the contrary direction, and generally be to the detriment of such Colonial loans as may have to be raised in the future.9. What, however, may be described as the more tangible and immediate issue is whether the commissions on the issue and subsequent management of the East African and Palestine Loans shall be paid to the Crown Agents or to the Bank of England.As Secretary of State for the Colonies, I am responsible for the administration of the Crown Agents&apos; Office, which is paid for by the commissions received on the various kinds of business transacted by the department. Some of this business is performed without any remuneration, and for some the commission charged is just enough, or less than enough, to meet the cost of the work ; whereas loan issues are some of the few kinds of business yielding a profit which goes to. meet the deficit on other classes of work. On several occasions since the war the expenses of the Crown Agents&apos; Office have not been covered by the commissions earned, and I wish to leave no stone unturned which will avoid my having to ask the Colonies and Protectorates to pay more than they now do towards the upkeep of the Office. This is especially desirable in view of the fact that in some Colonies there would be considerable opposition to any suggestion for an increase in the charges now made.Consequently I attach considerable importance to the net income to be made in connection with the handling of these loans going to the Crown Agents&apos; Office rather than to a private financial institution ; and I feel that, as the guarantees are to be given for the benefit of the Colonies and Palestine, the commissions should also properly go to these territories, as they will in effect do if they are received by the Crown Agents&apos; Office, which acts for the Palestine Government in exactly the same way as it does for any Colonial Government.10. There is a further argument from the point of view of East Africa. When a Colonial Government has decided to issue a loan for construction works, it is the usual practice for the Crown Agents to finance the works by means of temporary advances from the liquid funds of other Colonies in their charge, and to defer the public issue of the loan till a substantial proportion of the money has been spent. The advantages of this practice are obvious among others the postponement of the contributions to the sinking fund for the redemption of the loan. The Crown Agents are able to make these advances on the security of the ordinance authorising the loan, and with the knowledge that, if the other Colonies require their money to be repaid for their own use, it is in the Crown Agents&apos; own hands, with the approval of the Secretary of State, to issue the loan at any time. Similar considerations would apply in the case of Palestine.11. In the circumstances, I am strongly of opinion that the &quot; 10,000,000 Guaranteed East African Loan and the  4,500,000 Guaranteed Palestine Loan should be issued in the ordinary way through the Crown Agents, unless it can be proved that it would in practice have an injurious effect if a loan, guaranteed by the Imperial
Government, were to be issued otherwise than by the Bank of England. In this connection I would point out that the Mauritius 3 per Cent. Guaranteed Loan issued by and domiciled with the Crown Agents is quoted in the Stock Lists under the heading &quot; British Funds,&quot; and I can see no reason why the East African and Palestine Guaranteed Loans should not be similarly treated.12. I submit that the question of fixing the price of issue and interest does not arise, since, for a guaranteed loan, I should naturally be guided on this point by the Treasury view and I should issue instructions to&apos;the Crown Agents accordingly.L. S. A.Colonial Office, March 24, 1926.

</content>
</cab>
