<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 999-1021</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT. !0RST.CABINET. TRADE OUTLOOK. Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate the last monthly review of trade prospects which I have received from my Advisory Council.The uncertainty of the coal situation is having a depressing effect on future business.   But taking this into account, the prospects as outlined by the different trades are reasonably-satisfactory,Ootton Is still very badj but no considerable improvement can be expected there, until the price of raw cotton rises.The satisfactory condition of the rubber manufacturing industry and the desire expressed for stable prices supports the request of the   Colonial Secretary for a revised stabilisation, scheme at a higher figure.The volume of steel produced increased considerably in February, and still more in March, the March figure being 784,100 tons.    British steel makers have made an agreement regarding home basic prices, and the International rail pool has been re-established.The account of Indian Trade tendencies and prospects is interesting.P. 160 (26).(Intd.) P.0.-L.Board of Trade,23rd April,  1926.
v 676CONFIDENTIAL Tho Trade Outlook. Index.Iron and Stoel........................,.......... non-Ferrous Metals............................... 2Shipbuilding and Engineering..................... 5Electrical Trades....................../......... 4Cotton........................................... 5Wool............................................. 6Artificial Silk.......................,.......... 7Chomicals........................................ 7Pottery.......................................... 8Rubber........................................... general Trade and Banking........................ 9Shipping......................................... 12R ail ways......................................... 13Unemployment..................................... 15Australian Trade ,................................ 16New Zealand Trade................................ 16Indian Trade...................................: . I6South American Trade............................. 18Trade in China................................... I9Statistical Data................................. Annex.
CONFIDENTIAL. IRON   &amp;    STEEL.Since receipt of Mr. Dorman&apos;s letter the following figures have become available:-March 1926 March 1925Pig Iron&apos; Production..........        568,500 tons   607,900 tonsSteel .,......................        784,100 684,700Imports of Iron and Steel----       258,500 244,900Exports    *      &quot;      &quot;        &quot;      ____        406,500      &quot;     312,200Furnaces in blast at end of March 1926 ......  151Tl&quot;The production of pig iron in February amounted to 502,000 tons, compared with 533,500 tons in January, and 541,900 tons in February, 1925.*   There were 146 furnaces in blast at the end of February, a nett increase of 2 since the beginning of that month - three furnaces having been put into blast and one blown out.&quot;The production of steel Ingots and castings amounted to 703,800 tons, compared with 640,400 tons in January, and 652,300 tons in February, 1925.&quot;The Imports of iron and steel during the month of February amounted to 228,500 tons, as compared with 221,700 tons in January, and 234,900 ton3 in February, 1925.    Our exports amounted to 339,500 tons, as compared with&apos; 336,700 tons in January, and 298,700 tons in February 1925.&quot;The Pig Iron market has remained very quiet indeed during the past month, the approach of the Easter holidays&apos; causing a general slackening off all round in the position. Such material as is being made is generally being disposed of, but there Is no Inducement for Makers to increase production.&quot;it will be observed that the production of steel during February substantially increased.    This was due to the starting up of fresh plants which had been idle,    The production of 703,800 tons Is the largest monthly output since May, 1924.&apos;   &quot;The position of the steel trade is very apathetic, due to the uncertainty of the outcome of the coal negotiations. A few orders have been placed, but these are all for prompt delivery, and there is a complete absence of any desire to buy ahead on the part of consumers.&quot;An agreement has been arrived at between British Steelmakers regarding horrebasis prices, which will have the very advantageous effect of generally stabilising the market.&quot;The Black and Galvanised Sheet Trade is firm, most Makers being booked to the end of June, but there has been a general slackening off in prices.    This is accounted for by the reduction in the price of spelter and sheet bars brought about by the falling Continental currency.    Continental sheet bars can now be bought at about  4.15.0, and billets at about  4.12. 6d.  per ton delivered c, I. f.  Tees.&quot;The Wire Trade is in a very serious condition indeed, worse than can ever be remembered by those at present engaged in the trade.    There are practically no orders being placed, and such as are, are going to Germany at ridiculously low prices, the Germans quoting as low as  4 per ton below the figures- asked by British Makers.
STEEL.SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR   reported that the home trade in special steels was fair.    The trade was getting great numbers of orders, but these were very small.    Prices were a shade lower. There had been tremendous competition recently, and very little profit in prices at the present time. The exports for March were a little higher In value than for the previous month but lower than for March last year.   He thought this was entirely a question of price, and that the volume in March was certainly as great as the volume a year ago.    Canada and South America were both good markets; Australia, India, New Zealand, and South Africa were only moderate; Jaoan was Improving very steadily,and as regards China it was really wonderful what business we were doing there in spite of the circumstances.    The European market was in complete chaosj    the French trade was dead except for very small orders for special steels which they could not make themselves.    There were signs that in Germany they were getting to the bottom of their depression, and that gradually from now on they might recover.    If they did they would once more become perhaps a serious competitor.    It was going to be difficult to maintain the April export figures, as far as he could judge from the trades he was concerned in, but the position was not nearly as bad as it had been;    there was still a good volume of trade being done.NON-FERROUS METALS.SIR CECIL BUDD regretted that he had nothing good to report on the base metal industry, with one exception, galvanised iron.    The scale of operations was considerably less than it had been last year.    In Lead the consumption in this country was probably nearer 20 than 15 per cent less.    To some extent this might be due to the fact that prices had been falling and people had been holding off.    But there were, of course, other circumstances which affected many industries beside this.    Sir Cecil could confirm from very recent informationIRON &amp; STEEL   ( Contd. )&quot;Whilst there ia no definite improvement in the Shipbuilding position, a few ships have been placed, most of the material for which has been secured by British Steel Makers.&quot;There is a general hesitant feeling in the Constructional Engineering Trady, there being a dearth of enquiry and orders for small structural work.    There are, however, one or two fairly large enquiries in the market.    Prioea are very keen due to cutting by firms who are badly in need of work.&quot;I see no prospect of any improvement in the Iron and Steel trade until a settlement is arrived at between the Miners and Mine Ov-ners,    It must be borne in mind, however, that it is of vital importance to the Industry to have cheap coal, and even a small increase on today&apos;s prices cannot but have a very serious effect on the trade as a whole.&quot;
SHIPBUILDING AND ENGINEERING.SIR J. TH0RNYCR0FT considered that a good indication of the keenness of shipbuilders to get orders would be found in a series of tenders which were received recently for a vessel valued at about  100,000, which had to be built&quot;in this country.    The specification was a very close one, so that there was no question of the firms being on different footings. 12 to 14 of the leading shipbuilders in the country quoted. Some had evidently covered their establishment charges, but more than half had evidently covered only the bare cost of labour and material. It had been suggested in certain quarters that British manufacturers were not up to the mark in going for warship orders.    But they were doing all they did in pre-war days, and It could hardly be suggested that they did not then do their best.     It was difficult, however,  to get an order against the prices which could be quoted by Continental firms, with the facilities which their Governments gave.    Both the Italian and French Governments said to their warship builders,  &quot;Get as much money as you. can from the Foreign Government for whom you are building.    You may have to wait five or six years; but if, when the ship is finished, - and you will not build it too quickly - the money is not forth-coming, we will take her over ourselves and pay you any balance that may be outstanding&quot;.As regards motor vehicles, manufacturers seemed generally to bu well employed, though they were not getting the share of the trade which they ought to have, owing to foreign importations.On the question of a national wage, the position was very difficult at present    for engineering firms who are not in the favoured trades and for firms engaged in shipbuilding. The Engineering Employers1 Federation were taking the line at present that there must be national negotiation.    irhere there were certain trades which could not afford to pay and. other trades which could afford to pay,  it was perhaps worth while keeping the trades which could afford to pay in good conditionNON-FERROUS METALS    ( CONTD, )what Mr. Brand had said with regard to Germany,   (see section on &quot;General Trade and Banking&quot;).    There was acute industrialdepression there still.    The A.E.G.  was using today about600 tons of copper a month, instead of 3,000 tons, and inother directions there were similar conditions.    Theindustries in Germany were, as Mr.  Brand mentioned, amalgamatingin one form or another, very largely, it seemed, on thebasis of standardisation of manufacture at the differentworks.    In the United States a commission had been studyingthis question lately, and had reported.    Mainly through mr.. Hoover&apos;s initiative,  industry had made great advances in the matter of standardisation.    He had got the manufacturers to go in for standardisation and cheapen cost of manufacture.That was a thing which it had always seemed to Sir Cecil,might be studied much more here (Se;e also the &quot;Pottery&quot; section).
CONFIDENTIAL. SHIPBUILDING AND ENGINEERING (CONTD.)by authorizing them to give Increases in wages.    There was not much&quot; doubt that increases would be forced out of the employers in certain &quot;trades.    At the same time one could not have area rates of wages,&apos; because there would be mixed-up rates of wages in different areas.There was one important factor, however, which Sir J. Thornycroft did not think many people had realised, and that was the extent to which men have left the Trades Unions since the last threatened strike.    Firms had b*3en asked to make returns of their men who were members of Trades Unions, and the men had had to prove whether they were members or not  and an extraordinary change appeared to have taken place.    Men said &quot;vJhy should we belong to a Trade Union now?   ,Te get uncovenanted benefit, which is a sort of sick club benefit, Wo g^t the club doctor in tho State doctor; in fact we get everything which the old Trade Union did for us&quot;.    If there was an industrial dispute, a fairly big proportion of the men would go on&quot; working, in firms which had satisfactory^business and who could pay bonuses.    The men in such firms were Contented at present because they were on piece work and bonus;   but in general engineering, shipbuilding, and so on, this could not at present be done.ELECTRICAL TRADES. SIR PHILIP NASH wrote:     -*l&apos;&quot;Electrical Manufacturers are considerably perturbed as a result of the reception    the Government Electricity (Supply) Bill has had from the Supply Authorities.    There has&quot; been&apos;, as I pointed out at a previous meeting of the Board of Trade Advisory Council, a very distinct drop in the amount of home business offering, particularly in regard to generating and other large plant.    My own view of the matter, and I think it is that of most electrical manufacturers, Is that the Govern-ment Bill is perfectly right in principle, but the terms of the Bill are such that the future of electric supply under-takings is very seriously interfered with, and therefore those controlling such undertakings will not embark on any develop-ment, or extensions of their plant until their position under the bill is made clear, and a considerable time must elapse before this can take place.    Manufacturers of electrical plant rely very greatly on the assurance of the Attorney General, given on second reading of the Bill, to the effect that the Government would meet any reasonable amendment, but would resist any attempt to wreck the Bill.    Manufacturers are very much in accord with this attitude, and will watch with very close interest the proceedings of the Standing Committee in whose hands the Bill now rests.    In the meantime, as I have indicated above, the electrical manufacturing industry, as far as the home market is concerned, must suffer a severe setback in heavy plant.    On the other hand, now that the terms of the Bill are made public, and it has become plain therefrom that distribution rights of electricity supply are not interfered with, the market for small apparatus is recovering.    This applies also to domestic appliances.
COTTON.COLONEL SEDDON BROrN was afraid that his report was as bad as it could possibly be from Lancashire.    The American section of the trade was still on short time.    The Egyptian section was running full time at the moment, but even the trade in that section was being affected very seriously especially by the financial crisis in Germany.    Mar e looms were stopping in the &quot;eaving industry every day.    India was recently one of our&quot;best friends for buying, but that state of things had ceased, - they hoped only temporarily7&quot;.    On the whole Col.  Seddon Brown thought that the Lancashire cotton trade was, at the moment, in as serious a position as it could be. A large amount of the trouble seemed to be d&apos;xe to the fact that the whole world appeared to have lost confidence in the price of the raw article.    People who had thought we should&apos; be very lucky if we got what we called cheap cotton, say 9d. American cotton, were now talking quite freely about the possibility of 6d.  cotton.    Until that sort of feeling got out of buyers &apos; minds throughout the world we could not hope for improvement.Those people who hoped that cotton would renain steady seemed to be disappointed at the large acreage which had been planted in America.    America had been trying to make us believe that cotton was at a price which showed a loss to the grower; and it had been thought that that would naturally be reflected in a reduced acreage.    But that was not what had happened,    *&apos;e were arriving at a season of the year when the Crop Reports would determine the price of cotton,    le should soon forget about the present cotton, and prices ?;ould be fixed on the prospects of the new cotton, but he felt confident that we should have to see cotton steady at least, if not with a little rlae in price, before trade could recover.- In the American section they were vrorking with one day a week stopped, but that was not nearly sufficient.    Their figures showed that for the past two or three weeks the off-take of yarn had not been half the production.SIR VTILLI A.M CLARE LESS, referring to the question of stocks of cotton goods in China, mentioned in particular the heavy stocks of Japanese goods.    These were sufficiently large thoroughly to cloud1 the future prospects of Manchester piece goods.    They might interfere, from a credit point of view apart fromELECTRICAL TRADES (CONTD. )&quot;Speaking for my own Company, as an indication of the effect of the diminution in the volume of home orders, we have had to discharge between 400 and 500 men since the beginning of the year, although we have more than maintained the volume of export orders during that period.    Generally speaking the prospects of the export market for heavy machinery are good, and this country is receiving its full share of that market, although prices continue to be unremunerative, due to the severity of world competition. &quot;
COTTuN (CONTD).anything else, with the demand for piece goods from Lancashire of quite a different class from the Japanese coods themselves.      The conseouences of these heavy Japanese accumulations in China was being felt sporadically in other markets, such as Java and Rangoon.      Japanese cloth was coming more into competition with ours than we had been accustomed to find it doing, and in rather a lighter fabric than we had been used to finding from them.      The present unfavourable conditions would, Sir William thought, very likely pass away;    but China was the natural outlet for Japan, and for the time being the position was difficult for us.?;ith regard to India,  Calcutta had been quite a good buyer till recently.     The political upsets there had certainly not been exaggerated in the Press, and the commercial effect was perhaps greater than the size of the disturbance would indicate.     For a good part of this year Calcutta was booked for heavy shipments, and there was a fear that merchants who bought the goods would not be able to dispose of them as well as they had hoped.     Bombay was not doing well;    in Java there had been a great clearance of stocks;    in Egypt and Syria still the same congestion, together v-lth pronounced Italian competition in dyed goods. It was understood that, in printed goods, the Italians had improved very much in design and in the general appearance of their products, but were.losing some reputation for the quality of the fabric.      They were putting on a much lower class of fabric a very nice design, and though the goods were pleasing to the eye they were not satisfactory in use. Morocco was still holding back;    the V.est Coast of Africa had been better, and South America had been better.Sir W. Clare Lees agreed with What Colonel Seddon Brown had said.      The general feeling and sentiment in Manchester were depressed at present.     Colonel Seddon thrown had spoken of a day a week stopped, which sounded perhaps a small matter, but the depressing effects of that day a week were out of all proportion to the mathematical proportion of it;    it did away with the best part of the peoples&apos; wages and the entire profit of many of the producers.      our total production of bleached goods, which was the largest section of cotton exports,  amounted at present to about lu or 12 per cent less than it had been this time last year.WOOL.MR. ANDREWS said that the position at the present time was still about the same as it had been last month in Bradford. Wool prices had been very stable for the last six months; and as the Council was aware, stability was always in our favour. The demand was strong in all the finest qualities;    in men&apos;s wear there was a very good demand indeed for the very best worsteds.    there was a very poor demand for the inferior qualities.     At regards women &apos;s wear there is a good demand for the finest quality, and there again one found the same thine - a very poor demand for.inferior quality.     As far as
WOOL    (CUjjTD) .employment was concerned, it was just about stationary;    if anything, there was a little improvement.      In combing the situation was good:    in spinning very good.     In the Merino section spinning was still very bad in the lover qualities, and that was largely on account of the German position.      The industry was finding it a little easier to get in money from Germany, and was of opinion that if things were not at their worst in Germany they were very near it, and an improvement might be looked for about August.      One. thing that was rather troubling the trade was that although they were fairly busy, they had very few orders on their books.     Nobody seemed to imow whether they ought to buy or not.     They attributed that partly to the Safeguarding of Industries application, which related specially to the trade in women&apos;s v e ar.There was no doubt that during the last few months Bradford had been busy, on account of the Safeguarding of Industries application having the same effect on the trade as if an import duty was actually in force, because no-one knew whether a duty would come into force or not, and in the meantime buyers had to have the goods;    and instead of being placed in France the orders had been placed, y-ith British manufacturers, because this was the only means of making sure of delivery.ARTIFICIAL SILK..MR. ADD I SOI! wrote:-11 The month of March as compared with February, shews a slight improvement on the whole, the chief demand in the Rome Market being from the Hosiery Trade.&quot;The reaving Trade is again taking a slight interest in Artificial Silk, but the continued depression over the whole Trade does not make the outlook very hopeful.     Leek and Macclesfleld still remain quiet, and the Braid Trade is practically dead, such demand as tnere is coming from the firms engaged in Hosiery and Knitting.&quot;Foreign Markets - The month has been noticeable for the large weight of finer Deniers put on order by Japan.      The remaining Countries do not call for special comment. Competitive Spinners still seem to be burdened with large stocks and are willing to taice almost any price in order to liquidate their holdingsCHEMICALS .MR. PERRY reported that the volume of trade In the chemical industry, though still below normal, had not altered in the last few months;    but generally speaking there had been a distinct tendency on the part of manufacturers to accept lover prices, without any corresponding decrease in their cost of production. Therefore while the amount of trade passing remained about the same, the earning pov:er of the industry was probably falling, and the industry vould be&apos; still less able to bear burdensome
CHEMICALS  ( CuNTD ) *taxation.      The heavy section of the industry continued to suffer rather severely from the continued slump in consumption In the Far East, China and Japan.As on previous occasions reference must he made to the very black spot in the Industry, the chemical fertiliser and acid section.      That section was undoubtedly faced with moat serious problems owing to the continued growth of Continental competition in our home markets.POTTERY.MR. HoLLTNS considered that, on the whole the Pottery trade was in a fairly good situation, but there were consider-able variations in the several sections.     The export branches were very well indeed, and the home trade showed some slight improvement.     Sanitary earthenware and sanitary fireclay were still generally busy, and in building materials the trade was very fair.     The few firms doing a Pine China trade were exceptionally busy, for export.      There had been many inquiries for tea-ware, cups and saucers;   but the difficulty was that this was not by itself a paying proposition.      It was the firing which made it unremunerative;   we could not fill out kilns simply with tea-ware, because it would be too costly.      There must be other lines to run with it to make it pay;    otherwise a big demand could be had for that.     In answer to the President, Mr. Hollins said that mass production had been undertaken successfully in one instance whereas in another it had not been successful;    they had continuous kilns but the products were not good at all.      There were great difficulties In mass production In the china trade, because the articles were so varied and the total required was not so very large.      The English and Scottish stoneware trade was still in a bad x&quot;/ay.Short time was still being worked, but the total figures of unemployment, including short time, had very much decreased, as shown by the Exchange figures and also by Trade Union figure On the whole, the outlook for the coming few month seemed to promise well, but of course a coal stoppage would gravely affect it.     Seeing that 15 tons of coal went to 1 ton of product it was a serious matter for the pottery business.RUBBER.MR. JOHNSTON said that conditions in the rubber manufactur ing industry were on the whole rather satisfactory.     The tyre section had been very well employed.     We were suffering, of course, from fluctuations in the price of raw material, which was a disadvantage because buyers held off expecting a reduction which might or might not come.      Rubber footwear had been very active indeed.      The supply of general rubber goods to engineering concerns and general
RUBBER (OONTD.)industrial oonoerns had been quite good also. The   rubber industry rather regarded itself as a little body feeling the pulse of small industry.es generally, and he had the impression that trade was quite fair at present, apart from the heavy industries.The rubber industry in its export branches was quite good, particularly the trade to British Dominions.    In Continental countries conditions were of course very bad. France was almost impossible, Belgium nearly so:    with Italy trade was quite impossible.    Speaking generally, any Continental export, apart from the North of Europe, was difficult.      South America was quite good at the moment.    Generally speaking the conditions in the rubber industry were improving and certainly were much better than they were last year.GENERAL    TRADE.MR. MACHIN wrote:-&quot;I am sorry not to be able to report any substantial increase in the volume of trade.    We appear to be holding our own, but a want of confidence resulting from the unsettled condition of the Labour market, especially in connection with Coal, is undoubtedly hindering the develop-ment of industry in almost all its branches.&quot;I think it should be known that the burden of taxation is still viewed with the gravest concern by practically all the leading Chambers of Commerce in the United Kingdom.    I am just now considering the programme for our Annual Meeting? and the resolutions on this subject which have reached me emphasise the widespread conoern that exists on this vital question.&quot;While business in the Home market is holding its own, the improvement in the export trade is exceedingly slow. Indeed, the position is being made more difficult by the inflated currencies in some important markets, and there can be no doubt that the effect of the increase in the French Tariff must have a serious result in many important industries in this country&quot;.GENERAL TRADE AND BANKING-SIR FELIX SCHUSTER observed that the Reports from the branches of the National Provincial Bank in different parts varied very much;  they spoke quite hopefully in certain quarters, in other quarters they were not so happy.    The Cotton trade was depressed, but everything depended on the Coal situation.-9-............ &quot; .....- &apos;.....- ...MMnMWMH.
CONFIDENTIAL. GENERAL TRADE AND BANKING- (CONTD.)As to Banking, it was remarkable that there had been a constant fall in bank deposits accompanied by a rise in advances.    In 1925,  the deposits at the London Clearing Banks were in January    1,693 millions;  in February they went down to  1,682 millions, and in March to  1,643 millions.    This year they were in January  1,675 millions, in February  1,643 millions, in March  1,624 millions.    Advances on the other hand had risen.      They were in 1925; in January  834 millions, in February  837 millions, in March  857 millions.    In 1926 they were; in January  873 millions, in February  879 millions, in March  892 millions.    It was difficult to explain adequately, but it showed that the bank position was becoming,  - he would not say, strained, - but it was getting to a condition in which most banks found their proportion of advances quite high enough, and could not increase that proportion very much unless deposits increased again. There must be great restraint in making new advances, and Sir Felix was afraid that must affect our trade later on.    Of course it was the condition of trade at present - stagnant in parts - which was the cause of this increase in advances, but the situation at present showed that there was not very much spare money about for advancing in the future.SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR was very much interested in the figures that Sir Felix Schuster had given because he had intended to mention that, from their experience in the north of England, taxation this year had had a very severe effect on trade; people had tried to pay their taxes so as to balance the Budget, but in this lay part of the significance of Sir Felix Schuster*s figures.    Traders had had high taxation now for so long that they had not been able to put reserves into their business as they formerly did, and they were getting down more to the position of having to pay out cash.    That was why bank deposits were lower and advances higher.    And Sir Arthur knew that the payment of taxes this last time had had a very serious effect on the payment of accounts, which had been very much more difficult to collect.    *e had gone back to something like the 1920-21 period as regards the getting in of money.    No doubt, however, people would gradually recover.The coal situation and also the engineering labour situation were causing a good deal of unrest and want of enterprise.    It appeared also that the national wage question was going to be a very big factor.    It was felt by industrialists in the North that the country could not be run on a national wage basis,  - a national railway wage, a national coal wage, a national transport wage, and. other national wages which could not be fair in all the different districts:    that this would be putting a burden on the trade of the country which we should not be able to carry. Sir A. Balfour thought that was one of the most important features of the present negotiations. /See also &quot;Shipbuilding   and Engineering&quot; section/.
CONFIDENTIAL. GENERAL TRADE AND BANKING (CONTD. )MR. TENNANT observed that the reports he had received from the branches ef the Westminster Bank bore out what Colonel Seddon Brown and Sir William Clare Lees had said about the cotton trade.     In some of the other trades there seemed to be a certain improvement, and in particular, in shlp-bullding and the hosiery trade.With regard to the question of decreases in money lodged and increases in advances during the quarter, movements of that kind generally took place every year between January and April, very largely owing to the activities of the tax collector, but still it was a remarkable thing that, over the year, advances had continually gone up and deposits had gone down.MR. BRAND said that he would give his impression of Germany up to a few days ago.     Of course they were suffering from very great industrial depression.     They still said they had 2,000,000 unemployed, but they all seemed to think, as Sir Arthur Balfour said (see &quot;Steel&quot; section) that they were at the bottom of the tie pre s s i on or had turned the corner. One of the results of the depression and the liquidation of stocks, together with the holding of a lot of money from abroad, and very high taxation and large Government balances, had been a tremendous cheapening In the price of short money. Call money and monthly money was about the same now in Germany as it was here.     The result again of that had been a boom on the Stook Exchange and a large rise In the price of most shares.     It seemed to be generally the opinion that perhaps this had gone as far as it ought to go, and that it was largely what they call a foreign move.     Long money was still very dear.     The banks were being blamed for charging so much, for having such a big margin between what they gave for deposits and what they charged for overdrafts. It was also stated that they ought to reduce staffs a great deal more than they have done.     One bank had already reduced Its staff from 29,000 employees, at the height of inflation, to 8,500;   and they said there was still a considerable reduction to be made.     The German investor was beginning to buy German issues again.     There had been several very successful Municipal issues and State issues, and they were beginning to make industrial issues.     It was also said that Germans were beginning to buy back from America some of the good and high-yielding German Investments which had been placed in the United States.     So there were signs of the saving of capital in favour of local Issues.The Americans were still very active in Germany. Mr. Brand was told that there were now representatives of 35 American bond houses in Berlin trying to see whether they could get business, besides the representatives of all the big banks like the National City Bank.     They were all naturally trying to get the- business of the new Steel Trust. A striking thing in Germany was the general tendency towards big amalgamations.     They had the Chemical amalgamation and the Steel amalgamation;   it was said that the North German Lloyd and the Hamburg Amerika were going to amalgamate, and in all industries one saw this extraordinary organisation;    e.g. in potash, sugar, &amp;c.     The sugar indixstry, as the Council would perhaps be aware, were discussing a loan in London.   That was a combination of 180 or 200 sugar factories-U
GENERAL TRADE AND BANKING (CONTD.).to raise a common loan and spread it out among themselves In proportion.    They had abandoned what they call the vortical amalgamation, the sort of Stinnee amalgamation, in favour of the horizontal amalgamation.    It sssmed tho general tendency to amalgamate horizontally at tho moment.They now said that their technical efficiency was more or less up to the American but their   markets did not give them scope; and thoreforo thoro was a good deal of talk of a European movement to reduoo tariffs, and havo a big homo market in Europe for European industry such as America has in tho United States.With regard to the French franc, tho Germans had great experience of the practical difficulty of stopping inflation. Tho view Mr, Brand had heard was that it was an extremely difficult problem to know how to stop tho franc:    that it could not be done merely by raising money rates, taking in credit, and so forthj but that the great problem was how taxation could over catch up increases in Government expenditure.   As you imposed taxation so your expenditure incroased, owing to the rise in prices, and it was an extremely difficult thing to stop Government expenditure and increase your taxes sufficiently to make both ends meet. It might be doubted whether tho recent taxes imposed in France were anything like sufficient in themselves to make both ends moot. There was a statement in that day&apos;s &quot;Times&quot; of how prices were increasing and Government employees demanding more salary.    In Belgium, it appeared that stabilization had been temporarily abandoned, until their debt settlement was made and until they had come to a little more unity among themselves as to what they were going to do.    The bankshitherto had beon rather against the whole scheme, and of course they were very much affected by the French francThe impression created by a general survey was that the demand for oapital in Europe and all over the world was so great that, so far as we had a free and open market here, we were not likely to have very cheap rates for money.SHIPPING.SIR ALAN ANDERSON    wrotei-&quot;The Index Number of Tramp Shipping Freights for March 1926 was nearly 5% lower than in February 1926, and 16% lower than in March 1925.    The Index Number was in fact the lowest recorded since Its compilation in 1920 was commenced, the previous minimum being 22.06-in July 1925.    The more noticeable falls during March were in freights from India, Australia and the United Statos. Increases were recorded in River Plate Rentes, more or less balanced by falls in the outward coal freights.&quot;While complete figures are not available of the idle tonnage on the 1st April, 1926,  there Is an indication that the improvement in the weight of coal exports, 4.34 million tons in February with 28 days as compared   with
SHIPPING (CONTD.).4.15 million tons in January with 31 days, has been accompanied by some improvement in the employment of shipping.    The partial returns show a reduction of laid up tonnage on the Tyne and in South Wales&quot;.Sir Alan Anderson also sent the following further figures J-TONNAGE UNDER CONSTRUCTION.December 31st 1925..September 30th 1925.December 31st 192 4..TONKAGE LAUNCHED.in U.K... Abroad...In U.K ... Abroad...In U.K.,. Abroad...Gross Tons.885,013 1.184,5522,069 ,5451,009,155 1,197,7502 ,206,9051,296,971 1,173 ,4652 , 470 , 456Gt. Britain &amp; Ireland.Abroad.Total.Quarter ended.December 31st, 1925... September 30th, 1925.. December 31st, 1924...TONNAGE COMMENCED.Quarter ended.December 31st, 1925... September 3 0th, 1925.. December 31st, 192 4...Gross&apos; Tons.   Gross Tons. Gross Tons216,481 225,236 352,629160,986 260,551 19 4,594RAILWAYS .274,839 250,378 194,356182,290 2 44,002 290,601491,320 475,614 546,985343 ,276 504,553 485,195MR. HURCOMB said that the latest figures of freight tonnage were those for January 1926.   As compared with January 1925,they showed a decrease of just over 1,000,000 tons, there being 367,000 tons less in general merchandise, 515,000 tons less in &quot;other Minerals&quot;, and smaller decreases in coal and live stock. The decreases were spread, though in varying degrees, over all the major groups of traffic.   The receipts for the four amalgamated Companies for the first 13 weeks of the year showed an aggregate increase, over the corresponding period of last year,
RAILWAYS    (CONTD.)of about  800,000, all four groups participating in the improvement.    That figure, however, had to be viewed with some reserve, beoau.se of the incidence of Easter.   Almost the whole of this increase was In passenger receipts.    This year Easter fell in those 13 weeks, and consequently the passenger receipts would be high, and the freight receipts somewhat depressed, by the loss of working days, whereas last year Easter fell outside the first 13 weeks.    Therefore too much stress could not be laid on a comparison.Mr, Hurcomb thought that in looking at passenger receipts there was an uncertain factor ahead which it was rather difficult to gauge, namely the effect of there being no Wembley traffic this year.    Whether or not the people who travelled to Wembley last year would take equivalent journeys elsewhere this year one could not say.He might also mention that on the previous day the Railway Rates Tribunal began its hearings on the new Schedule of Charges under the Railways Act.   Hitherto it had been occupied In settling various preliminary matters, such as the - standard revenue which the Companies were to be entitled to earn if they could and the amount of expenditure which was to be allowed for in a future year.   Having substantially settled those matters, they were now beginning their hearing on the actual Schedule of Charges, and the various representative bodies of traders were appearing before the Tribunal represented by Counsel.SIR HERBERT WALKER wrote as follows : -&quot;From the reports I have received from the General Managers of the Grouped Railways, there appears from the point of view of Railway Traffic to be only a very slight improvement in the Trade Position.    For the first twelve weeks of this year, as compared with the corresponding period last year, whereas the L.M.S.  Company show a slight decrease in tonnage under all heads,  (1) Merchandise, (2) Coal,  Coke and Patent Fuel,   (3) Other minerals,  the Great Western and London North Eastern show a slight improvement.     Again, while there is an increase of 3.84  in the shipment of coal at the North Eastern Port3 there is a slight decrease in South Wales for the twelve weeks ended March 28th.&quot;The comparative return of Railway Traffic Receipts of the four Companies for the same periods is as under:-
UNEMPLOYMENT (CONTIJ. )As to the number of people who had ceased to register on account of being disqualified, a White Paper had been published which gave this as about 10,000.     That left out of account those who did not register at all owing to more restricted conditions of benefit.     The Ministry had no clear Information as to the number of these, but it was thought not to be large.AUSTRALIAN TRADE .MR. SANDERSON reported that the agricultural and pastoral outlook had, in general, Improved, though some districts were still;suffering from insufficient rain.     On the whole there had been great Improvement as the result of last month.     The wool season was practically over, the wheat season was finishing, fruit was at present being shipped freely;   and generally the period of the year had been reached when attention would be turned mainly to next season&apos;s production.The butter output had been affected by the dry weather, as was usual at this time of year.     The Australian Meat Council stated that the export of beef from Queensland would be considerably short of last season.     The fruit season had been affected by the dry weather, and In Victoria by the bush fires, and a somewhat lesser quantity had been produced. There had been very close inspection of all export fruit, with the result that the condition of the fruit arriving here was much better both in grading and quality, and it was hoped that this would be reflected in prices later on.NEW ZEALAND TRADE.SIR JAMES ALLEN remarked that the position of the Dominion financially was good.     The financial year ended 31st March and although he had not learned the actual balance which resulted, he had every reason to believe it was a satisfactory one.     In so far as migration affected trade from this country he thought we might look for an increased demand for United Kingdom goods, in view of the fact that the New Zealand Government had increased the quota of migrants that they could take every year, by another 3,500 a year.INDIAN TRADE.MR. LINDSAY agreed with Sir .7. Clare Lees (see &quot;Cotton&quot; section) that the troubles In Calcutta had come at a very unfortunate time.   There had been distinct evidence of increased buying of Lancashire goods, chiefly by the Calcutta market, and
INDIAN TRADE (CONTD.).these troubles meant that these piece goods would not be cleared as rapidly as one might have expected.    There had been also a distinct increase of Indian buying in China.    The total imports of piece goods into India in December amounted to 100 million yards, and they increased in January to 170 million, which was satisfactory.    But India&apos;s buying at present seemed to be going in fits and starts.   During the seven years since the war India had bought, alternately, 1,000 million yards In 1919-20, 1,500 million the next year, 1,000 million the next year, 1,500 million the next year, 1,500 million the next year, 1,800 million the next year, and 1,450 million in 1925-26.There had been a tremendous change of taste in cotton piece goods since before the war.    In the old days India used to import them in the following proportions of grey, white and coloured:   2 bales of grey to 1 of white and 1 of coloured.    Grey was half the total.   After the war, when the price of goods went up so extensively, naturally the demand for grey goods, which were the cheapest of the three advance-dj and the imports became 5 bales of grey to 5 of white and 2 of coloured.    The grey goods had advanced in proportion to the coloured but the white had also advanced, and to-day the proportion in these Imports was, 7 of grey to 5 of white and 4 of coloured.   White goods had advanced very considerably in proportion to the other two, and it was in white goods that the United Kingdom held her own.   Before the war Lancashire did 99 per cent, of the total trade in grey, 98^ per cent, in white, 92^- per cent. In coloured.    In grey she now did only 80 per cent, in coloured only 75 per cent, but in white she still did 96 per cent, almost the same percentage as before the war.   So that the taste in whites had advanced and that was the particular line in which the British manufacturer held his own.Sir William Clare Lees observed that the white goods were the most Immune from oriental competition, either of India or Japan, and were really one of the staple articles of life. Further, in the bleaching of goods we were, he thought, pre-eminent in this country.   We are almost secure from foreign competition in this line of trade In the open markets of the world.Mr. Lindsay added that there was, further, the question of the relation of the price that India got for her goods and the price she had to pay for imported goods.    He found, on turning back to the figures of 1920 and 1921, India was then paying 3-1 times more than she did before the war, for cotton goods, and was getting about 75 per cent, more than she did before the war for her agricultural produce, rice, wheat, oil seeds, hides and skins, and so on.    That margin, had, however, contracted very much, and now India was paying about 75 per cent, to 80 per cent, over the pre-war level for her imported goods, - cotton piece goods, sugar, and so on, - and was getting between 40 and 50 per cent, more for her own produce.   So that we seemed to be drawing near the time when India would be in a better position to buy. What she particularly required now was greater confidence as to
INDIAN TRADE (C ON TP. ) .the future course of prices.    It might he a good thing if local tastes in India were studied so that some estimate could be formed as to their future course.   White goods were obviously on the increase, and this country should take full advantage of the Increase in this demand.   Mixtures of artificial silk and cotton were also growing much more popular in India;    at present the United Kingdom have half that trade, and possibly a greater proportion still might be done.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.MR. HOSE wrote as follows:- &quot;Final official figures of the values of imports and exports of Argentina during the year 1925 were published on 14th March last, and, in correction of a previous official estimate, showed a surplus of imports. Thereupon a weak tendency in the exchange became pronounced, the quotation registered on the 15th March and again en the 23rd March having been 43-446d,   the lowest level recorded since May, 1925.   The decline in the exchange may also be partly attributed to the comparatively poor European demand for fine cereals, and it is to be noted that a recent partial recovery in grain quotations has been accompanied by an advance in the sterling^value of the peso this month to the current quotation of 44fd.&quot;The difficulties so far experienced in disposing of this season&apos;s wheat crop and the uncertain outlook for Argentina !s export trade have no doubt been the chief factors responsible for the dull conditions ruling in the Import trades.   Mail advices recently to hand state that wholesalers find it very difficult to make extensive sales, retailers being anxious in most cases to effect a reduction in stocks.    The markets in both cotton and woollen manufactures are inactive, although a slightly increased demand has been in evidence for yarns, especially for those of artificial silk.&quot;in general, a somewhat disappointing commencement has been made in Argentina to a year which promised at ono time to be a very prosperous one, and the commercial outlook would now appear to be principally dependent upon the success-ful marketing of this year&apos;s wheat and maize, and, in this connection, the yield of the maize crop is expected to compare very favourably with that of the record harvest of the year 1923-24.&quot;A small estimated export surplus was established in the foreign trade of Uruguay last year, and a steady tendency Is maintained in exchange at around parity.   Sales of Winter goods In the Republic are proceeding in a normal-manrer, and it Is satisfactory to note that the very dry conditions in the agricultural districts have been considerably relieved by a general rainfall, which a few weeks ago was most urgently needed.
SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE  (CONTD. )&quot;In Brazil, importers appear to be purchasing fairly freely.     A setback has occurred in exchange, the sterling value of the milreis having been reduced to just under 7d., which may be partly in connection with a seasonal decline in coffee prices.     The monetary situation, however, has distinctly Improved.     Loans may be obtained with greater freedom and at lower rates of Interest than has been the case for some time past.     Generally speaking, a distinct improvement has occurred In business conditions during the past few months.&quot;With regard to Chile, the new Banco Central de Chile is functioning satisfactorily, the Government Is now stabilised, and the tendency In exchange continues firm. The latest available statistics of the foreign trade of the Republic indicate further expansion in the value of both imports and exports.     The industrial and commercial outlook is at present -not unsatisfactory, but an adverse factor in the situation is the uncertainty as to the outcome of the dispute regarding the sovereignty of the Tacna and Arica Provinces.     Efforts to oarry out the proposed Plebiscite appear to have been accompanied by serious difficulties, which the parties, are endeavouring to overcome by means of special conferences at Washington.&quot;TRADE IN CHINA.MR. LANDALE stated that as regards Engineering, Inquiries for machinery had much Improved of late in China, and there was some prospect of increased business.     As to imports, stocks of piece goods in the country were very low, and if the Civil War would come to an end large orders would, be obtainable.      In exports there was very little doing In oil seeds owing to lack of demand from the Continent.     A good business had been done in untanned goatskins to both Europe and America.     Silk export continued good.With regard to the political position, it was earnestly to be hoped that the policy of inaction adopted by the Pov?ers during the past few years would now be superseded by some joint diplomatic appeal to the Military Leaders to sink their personal differences and unite In forming a strong Central Government.      It was doubtful whether the Chinese unaided could put an end to the chaos which now prevailed in the North, but It was thought they would be responsive to some assistance of the League of Nations order.     The improved condition of the four or five Provinces around Shanghai showed the great recuperative power of the country.With regard to the railways, in the military encircling movement round Peking, the railways leading to that point, namely, the Peking Mukden Railway, the Peking Hankow Railway, and the Tientsin Pukow Railway, continued to be occupied by troops, and a great deal of damage was being
CONFIDENTIAL.TRADE IN CHINA.    (contd..)done to the traok and rolling stock.     If the recent coup d&apos;Etat in Peking led to no cessation of fighting, it was difficult to see how these Railways would be demilitarised without some form of outside intervention j and, if they were not demilitarised, how the loan obligations depending upon them could be met.       The Shanghai Nanking Railway and the Shanghai Hangchow Railway were making good progress towards recovering their financial position, and if the public service was not interfered with they should be in a position in a few months to have some cash to expend on urgent and needful repairs.       The boycott of Hongkong by the Canton Authorities had been the oause of increasing the earnings of the Canton Kowloon Railway, and something had been done by the Railway towards liquidating its debts for material and stores supplied.
CONFIDENTIAL. ANNEX.Some leading statistical data indicating the trend of the Economic situation in Great Britain.(Infsrmation to loth April, 1926).Latest.AMont,h earlier .A Year ear lie?.At corres-ponding date in 1913.oyment: Employed on live Tgister (including prsons on short me receiving Benefit )..........*Llvray Receipts : &apos; ods Traffic (Gross) Breat Britain:leek ended........oduction:oal, output duringweek ended........ig Iron output during month......teel output duringaonth.............ices: Wholesale : card of Trade Index umber (1913 slOO)Pood..............Materials.........Total.............ited Kingdom: [radett :Net Imports.......Exports (DomesticProduce).........vessels laid up in Iriited Kingdom ports.British ..........Foreign..........shipping Freights : hamber of Shipping Index Number(1920 - 100)   .....nk Clearings : ountry Cheque and Provincial, weekended...........ney Market :&amp;nk Rate ........k et rat e 3 months 1ank Bills  .......discount (3 months1 reasury Bills )   . .5th April Wholly un-employed 739,800Other____310,000Total.. 1,049,800(iOthApril 1,679,100Tons.  rdApril 4,633,400March568 ,500 784,100150.5 141.0 144. 494,778,30366,399,6 47N.et tons .! i93,321 14,343810,874_283^2 081,09 4,082 j     1^66,300   2,107,000 j 1,727,400Tons. Tons.5,285,100 I 5,293,300I502,000 ! 607,900703,800 j 684,700155.6   i 171.7143.6   I 163.3147.8    j 166.3 83,623,950 100,090,49962 , 8 14,2 44.      ,. ...... .       Net tons 1st Jan.    393,321 1st0ct556,567 - * &quot; &quot;      17,797March    21.86 DthApril 87,339,000 j 9th April        5%4^8A: i&quot;       4.7s. 6. Old!22.98 83,744,0005/o43/8 , 47/l6;i  4.7s. 10 ,54d.70,305,279Net tons. 469,951 18,30126.08 83,316,0005 j 4.3s. 4.18dNocomparable data.1,217,100Tons. 5,83 0,000*855,000f638f600fAverage for 1913 &quot; 100.51,709,584 41, 690,31023.4047, a 58,060hi4i4/o* Approximate weekly average for April 1913. t Monthly average for 1913.i&apos;i The figures for the present year and for a year ago include the trade cf Great Britain and Northern Ireland with the Irish Free State and exclude the direct foreign trade of the Irish Free State;   the 1913 figures are exclusive of the former and Inclusive of the latter.


</content>
</cab>
