<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 1190-1190</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Btajesty&apos;a Government. 833SECRET.Copy&quot; No. K&apos; &apos;0CP. 1/4 (26).THE CABINET.GOVERNMENT LANDS AND BUILDINGS.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.The Chancellor of the Exchequers proposal, OP. 103 (26), involves, so far as the     119 War Office is concerned, considerable administrative disadvantages and does not appear to &quot;General offer in compensation any appreciable economy.   At all the stages of a land purchase      60 under the proposed scheme reference will be necessary between the War Office and the Inland Revenue Department, and at each stage there is a danger of delay occurring.   In addition, during the actual conduct of negotiations, points will arise requiring settlement, which it will not be possible for an outside department to dispose of so expeditiously as can a branch of the War Office, which is in close touch with other branches and familiar with their requirements.Nor can I see any grounds for assuming that the actual work of valuation and purchase will be more efficiently conducted by a Department which is not concerned exclusively with the special requirements of the War Office and Air Ministry but has many other important preoccupations.The scope for economy in this field is not large and I doubt whether any saving would in fact be made. The total normal cost of that portion of the War Office Lands Branch which is at present engaged on valuations and negotiations for the War Office and Air Ministry is about  4,200. But the work of this section is not con-fined to valuation and negotiation ; questions are referred to it in connection with the administration of War Department and Air Ministry property and other matters which would be outside the scope of the Inland Revenue Valuers. As the work which it is proposed to hand over to the Inland Revenue cannot, I anticipate, be carried out with celerity and efficiency without some addition to the present staff in that office, the economy that will be effected by the change cannot be very considerable.I am of opinion, however, that the present organization of the War Office Lands Branch, which performs functions also for the Air Ministry, is not entirely satisfactory, and I have made proposals to the Secretary of State for Air with the object of facilitating economies and co-ordination. At present the staff of one section of the War Office Lands Branch is earmarked to act for, and is paid by, the Air Ministry. This separation of the Air Ministry work is uneconomical ; by a re-organization under which the duties connected with Air Ministry lands would be generally diffused throughout the Lands Branch, I anticipate that a reduction in cost from  12,500, the total normal cost of the Lands Branch, to about  11,300 would be possible. This re-organization would also facilitate co-operation, the need for which has recently been emphasised by the action of the Air Ministry in approaching proprietors of certain land forming part of a large area for the purchase of which, by the War Department, Treasury sanction has already been sought. In my view the only satisfactory method not only of securing reductions in the staff of the joint department but also of avoiding the repetition of such incidents in future is the reorganization of the Lands Branch on a real interdepartmental footing. It is on these lines rather than by the intervention of a third department that economy coupled with the efficient conduct of the business of the Lands Branch can best be secured.L. W.-E.The War Office,28th April, 1926.(B26/17)   100   4/26   w.o.p.   264i)

</content>
</cab>
