<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 1233-1234</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
86IJT8 DOCUMENT.13 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC.MAJESTY&apos;S GOVBRNMBNT.CP. 183(26.)- COAL CRISIS AND. RJIQRGAIII2ATLQN*^MSl BY THE PKHJSIDSNT OF THE BOARD Off EDUCATION,During the next few weeks the energies of the Government and the attention of the Country will he absorbed in fighting the general strike and Parliamentary time may be largely taken up in considering the measures which the Government think necessary for this purpose.   The   strike will not end until it has been defeated.   On the other hand, its defeat alone will not lead to a settlement which would permit a revival of trade unless theGovernment are able to take some Btsps to prepare for such a settle-ment in the meantime, even while the strike is continuing.   At the present moment the Miners and the other Unions, indefensible as their action has been, have just one argument which, however weak in itself, is of a kind that may have&quot; a certain-weight with public opinion in the long run.   That argument is that they have no certainty as to re-organisation&quot;, that the Owners are known to be reluctant to &quot;re-organize&quot;, and that the Government have taken no definite action.   The Government have, in fact, not made a &quot;firm offer&quot; of re-organication so far as re-organization depends upon them.   The Governmenfs original statement mads their action on the re-organization proposals of the Commission dependent upon the acceptance of the Report by both parties and their attitude up to the last has been that re-organization and an immediate reduction of wages must go hand in hand.   This attitude is clearly appropriate to negotiations such as we have been conducting but. once those negotiations have broken down, it ceases to be a strictly logical attitude,        hvnothesi, re-organization is necessary on its own merits and we have now said that this re-organization should be put in hand immediately.
I venture,therefore, to surest to my colleagues&quot;that to should immediately take steps to show thecountry that we are prepared to proceed with the reorganizationof the industry.   My knowledge of the subject is not sufficient to enable me to make concrete suggestions withany confidence, tut It soems to roe that we should be able totake action in the following matters immediately:-(1) The establishment of the National Fuel and Power Committee and the announcement of our proposals in regard to research set forth in CP. 141(26).(2) The establishment of the Standing Joint Committee on Mineral Transport.(3) The introduction of legislation making pit head baths compulsory and levying the 5 per cent on royalties for this purpose.(4) The revival of that portion of Part II.. of the Act of 1920 relating to Pit Committees.(5) The introduction of legislation giving the liinee Department power to effect a compulsory transfer of interests under existing leases for the purpose cf promoting amalgamations in the circum-stances contemplated by the Commission^ Report.So far as the last three items are concerned I realise the danger of committing Parliament and thecountry to definite legislation in advance of a settlementwhen that legislation may be distasteful to one or both of theparties in the Industry and, even if it were possible, Ishould not suggest that such legislation should actually be passed during the emergency, but I feel that a Bill orBills should be introduced for these    purposes as a basis for discussion and as a concrete sign of the Government&apos;sreadiness to promote re-organisation.E.P.

</content>
</cab>
