<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 1238-1241</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OE HIS BRIM NIC M&amp;J33TY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)3 E C R BJ COPY NO.  grg^*G ^ B-1 N E TIRAK:: POLICY COMMITTEE.THIRD    REPORT-1. At the meeting of the Cabinet held on the 28th April, 1926, (Cabinet 19 (26) Conclusion 4), the Cabinet agreed -xxxxxxxxxxx(b)    That in view of the Importance of reaching a solution as soon as possible the Cabinet Committee on Policy in Irak,  presided over by tho Lord Privy Seal,   should he reassembled as soon as the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs is ready,  and that it should have authority to approve the necessary instructions for putting into execution the policy of securing a  settlement with Turkey on the lines indicated.xxxxxxxxxxx2.      The Committee met on the 3rd May,  agreed  to the general terms of the instructions whioh should be given to Sir Ronald Lindsay, and upon the understanding that this course was desired by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, requested the Foreign Office to.draft a telegram embodying these instruc-tions for the approval of the Chairman..3o      The telegram,  as approved by the Chairman,    was despatched to Sir Ronald Lindsay on the morning of the 4th. May;    and a oopy is attached as an Appendix to this Report.4.      This telegram was also repeated to the High Commissioner for Irak, to whom tho Secretary of Sta te for the Colonies has undertaken to communicate the necessary instructions.S:i gnod on behalf of th e Committee SALISBURY.Chairman..Whitehall Gardens,  3.W.1, hay 10th, 1986.
4th May, 1926.Sir R* Lindsay,. Angora.My telegram No. 6 (of 24 April,    Negotiations for Turco-Anglo-Irak Treaty).As regards the oil question; re-distribution of the share capital in the Turkish Petroleum Company would raise wollnigh insurmountable difficulties and the Company will not agree to any Increase ih the amount of the royalties payable by them to the Irak Government.     His Majesty&apos;s Government have, therefore, decided that all efforts must be concentrated on obtaining assignment to Turkey of a certain percentage of Irak Government1 s royalties.      It appears to His Ma.majesty&apos;s Government that preferable scale would be for whole period of concession at minimum rate of 10 per cento which you are authorised to raise to 15 per cent. If essential.An alternative on which you will report after exploring, the ground would be a limited period,  e * g-.,  25 years,  to coincide with maximum period of our special  relations with Irak as defined by recent Anglo-Irak Treaty,      In that case percentage must naturally be higher up to maximum of 25 per cent.      In either case Turks will appreciate fact that oil may not be workable for first few years and that there may in consequence be no royalties for similar period.Irak Prime Minister favoured an alternative scheme whereby His Majesty1s Government would offer Turkey assistance to effect an Improvement In communications between Turkey and Irak and in particular the construction of railway between Nisibln and Mosul, a fixed percentage of oil Royalties of Irak Government being set aside annually for this purpose.      It would, however, be understoodAPPENDIX.COPY OF A TELEGRAM FROM THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FORE EN AFFAIRS TO SIR RONALD LINDSAY. (Repeated to the High Commissioner for IRAK,BAGHDAD.
that on completion of the railway the Turkish section thereof would be made over to the Turklsh Government free of cost.      H.M.G. are unaware of any desire on part of Turks themselves for such railway development,      On contrary,   Turks might in our opinion regard it with suspicion as a disguised form of British penetration into Turkish territory, even though railway would he begun at Turkish end.      Attitude of Turks has, however, recently changed so completely that even this scheme may now be palatable at Angora,   especially In view of enquiry by Turkish M.F.A.  reported in your telegram No* 4 (of April 22) para.  2.You are therefore authorised to bear this proposal in mind in oral negctiations and to make such use of it as may appear to you desirable.      Should Turks rise to this fly you would let them understand that royalties to be ear-marked for this purpose would be on similar terms as first proposal,  viz. 25 per- centc for 25 years or at lower rate for longer period,,Objection to this proposal is possibility that trace would cross Syrian territory,  in which case prior negotiations with French would be essential and considerable delay might thereby be involved.If danger foreshadowed in your telegram No. --9 of 29th April that territorial cession may be revived, materialises, you are authorised to  adhere to offer of territorial adjustment within limits already approved.      You will of course abstain from taking initiative on this point which would,  in view of great concession in matter cf- royalties,  embarrass H.M.G. vls-a^vis of Irak Government.If we read situation a right,  Turks are obsessed with fear of Isolation and they desire above all security.      I am not unmindful of your previous remarks regarding Turkish view of League of Nations,      It seems to me however possible
that In their present temper their attitude on this subject may have changed,,      You should therefore,  If opportunity offers, explain to them that membership of League would furnish all advantages in matter of security which Turkish M.F.A. had in mind when he asked for pact of mutual neutrality. Repeated to Baghdad,

</content>
</cab>
