<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 1255-1261</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[S DOGUMBIfT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .FORE T.COPY NO:P . 189  (26).CABINET,(aleo 0,R.S.  (26) 1^)CIVIL CONSTABULARY RESERVE COMMITTEE.REPORT&apos; OF THE INTEE-DEPARTMENTAL SUB-committees the Civil Constabulary Reserve Committee of theCabinet at their meeting held at 3 p,m. on the 3rdM ay ,  1926, a gr e e d: -(l)    That the Home Secretary should continue to swear in Special Donstables on a voluntary basis to a total of 50,000.(2)    That the Secretary of State for War should immediately order the headquarters of all territorial units actively to form companies of the Civil Constabulary Reserve, which will be a paid whole-time force of sworn-in Special Constables organized in unit formations wearing plain clothes but supplied wlfeh brassards, steel helmets and truncheons.     The administration of this force should rest exclusively with the War Office.(3)    The Home Secretary should not recruit any paid Special Constables,      He should release as soon as the emergency  permits any territorial Special Constables who may wish to rejoin their own units.(4)    The Secretary of State for War will for the next few days at any rate not recruit for the Civil Constabulary Reserve any outsiders, except ex-military men known and trusted at the territorial headquarter s,(5)   As soon as the Secretary of State for War notifies the Home Secretary that companies of the Civil Constabulary Reserve have been formed, the Home Secretary should be entitled to draw upon them se needs be for the purpose of aiding the police.
While these companies would not act together as much as possible, their tactical employment will be directed by the Chief Commissioner of Police.

(?) All the above applies to London, is urgent, and is to be asked upon forthwith upon the authority of the Cabinet.

(7) In the Provinces the War Office will ? the ? of the various Commands to issue the same orders to the territorial units, subject to such, modifications as may be found necessary by the Expert Committee, and actively to promote the formation of Civil Resc? Companies. The terms of the instructions to the G.O.C. in C. to be agreed between the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for War. The G.O&apos;s ? will also be instructed to place themselves in communication with the County and Borough Police authorities, informing them that they are preparing these Forces and that as soon as they are ready they will be at their disposal in the case of emergency. Action in this case also should be immediate.

(8) In a few days when we see how the situation develops and how the formation of the new Force proceeds, the question of whether the territorial centres should be allowed to recruit for the Civil Constabulary Reserve will be considered, and the Home Secretary will also consider whether he can release for full time service in the C.C.R. some of his present volunteer Special Constables.

(9) In the event of the embodiment of the Territorial Army all the Territorials in the C.C.R. will immediately rejoin their units, lay
Q Q 9aside their police stot us end resume military duty under  the Jfer Office *      Outsiders who may have been engaged will    revert to the Special Constabulary under the Home office a(10)   An Expert Committee will assemble immediately to draw up the detailed terms of pay, etc,., and to Implement these general decisions.(11)   The provisional organization set up by the Home Secretary under Generals Scott and Percy with any arrangements with regard to depots, to be transferred, to the War Office forthwith.In accordance with Conclusion (10) above,  the Sub-Committee was set up, composed as follows:-Colonel Sir R.S, MAY, K.B, C *B-. C.M.G., D,S,0o, Director of Recruiting and 0rganisaticn, War Office, (CHAIRMAft).Brig,-General Sir WILLIAM H0RW00D, K.C.B., D.S.O., Chief Commissioner of Police.Mr . J.F, MOYLAN, CB.E. ...Scotland YardsMr. A6Lo DIXON, C.B.,  C.g b e ,.......Home Office.Mr. A ,W. Hurst, C.B*,..**......Treasury.Sir JOHN LAMB,  K.C VB-.e ..............Under Secretary forScotland.Major H.L.  I3MAY, D.S.0 0 . .     )) Joint Secretaries.Ma j or A ,A 0 B. Dowler ......**.)The Sub-Committee met at 6 p.m. on the 7th May. They agreed: -(a) That the Civil Constabulary Reserve shouldbo housed in Territorial Drill Halls, and any other accommodation which may be suitable.(b) That the transportation of units to and from the scene of their employment should be the responsibility of the Chief Commissioner of Police, in co-operation with the Ministry of Transport.
0 9 9(c)    That the Civil Constabulary Haservo shouldreceive pay at the following ratesConst&amp;blo  ... ...      ...      5/- per diom,Sargoant    ... ...      ...      6/-    &quot;Inspector ... ...      ...      7/6    &quot;Commander ... ...      ...    10/-    &quot;ii1!In addition, all ranks will receive an allowance of 5/&apos;- per week &quot;Plain Clothes&quot;allowance to cover clothing,washing and incidentals;(d)    That tho Civil Constabulary Reserve shouldbe Organised in areas to correspond with the Metropolitan Police Areas,(o)    That the unit organisation should correspond to that of the Metropolitan Police, viz.,&apos; &apos; companies of SCO under a commander; each company consisting of 4 sections;  each section consisting of one inspector, two sergeants, 50 constables;(f) That in tho first instance provision should be made for a force of 10,000 men;(g) That the appeal for recruits for the Civil Constabulary. Reserve, which is attached as an appendix to this Report, should be broadcasted as soon as the terms of the appeal have boon approved by the CabinetCommittee;(h) That all preparatory action such as the earmarking of Drill Halls, the appointment of administrative of floors and staff, the collection of the necessary equipment, &amp;c., should be initiated by ths War office for thwith;(i) That recruiting should commence on Monday, 10th May, 19.26, at 7 a.m.;.(j)    That tho age limit of recruits should ba 50 y ears ;(k)    That, owing to tho need for urgency, there will bo no medical examination of recruits in.the first instance, but tho question of instituting such an examination will be considered later;(l)    That armlets and. truncheons , up to thelimit of 10,000 referred to in If) above, will be provided by the Chief Commissioner of Police;    all other ecnlpment being provided by ths War lriica;
(m)  That, with rogard to Conclusion 7 of the Cabinet Committee in reepact of tha isxtonsion of this schema to the Provinces, the necessary lot tars to Chairmen of Territorial Army Associations, Chief Constahlea and GaCs C* in OeCoasaa&amp;da should., be drafted by the war   Office and Homo Office &amp;tx  suMltt&amp;d gor the approval of the Cabinet Committee.(n) That the Sub-Committoe should be a standing Oomciittoo to watch tha progress and to deal with such inter-departmesatal questions as may arias from time to time.Signed on behalf of the Sub-Committee,H. 8.   MAY.direct &amp;r of Recruiting and Organisation, WAR OFFICE--  CHAIHMA2J-2,  Whitehall Gardens,  3*\f. 1. 8 th Kay,  1926 .-5-
APPENDS *APPEAL BY THP G 0V MMiJE. I POP A CIVIL C ON 3 TABU LAKY RPSPEVP.1.     There are at present two fore as attached to the Polios called tho &quot;Metropolitan Special Constabulary Pasorve&quot; and the &quot;Metropolitan Special iiaargoncy Constabulary&quot; compos ad of patriotic citizens who are willing to give such time as they can spare to helping tha Police in their duty of keeping order and protecting tho Public.There are in these forces at present about    25,000 citizens. Owing, however, to tha tactios employed   by ill-disposod persons, who are taking advantage of tha present crisis to interfere with the rights of the community, it has become nocossary to expand, and to organise a further force of loyal citizens who are able and willing to give their whole time towards helping tha Metropolitan and City Police.This now Porco will bo designated &quot;Tha Civil Constabulary Reserve&quot; and will be paid whole time Porce of sworn-in Special Constables,  organised in units, wearing plain clothes, but supplied with armlets,  etaol-helmots and truncheons.2.      The following will be eligible to join :-(a) Officers and Other Hanks of the Territorial Army, including those already serving as Special    Constables, as soon as tha services of tho latter can be spared.(b) Px-military men who can be vouched for at Territorial Army units headquarters.Age Limit - 50 years..N.B.   Men engaged on vital public services should remain in   their present employment.5.     Pay will be at the following daily rates :-commands........,..10/-&quot; per diem,Inspactor ...........  7/6       &quot;Sargaant  ...... .......  6 / -        &quot;Constable .. ..... ....... b/-       &quot;
An allowance of b/- a week will be given to each man to cover clothing, washing and incidentals,Army rations will be provided free and also accommodation,Until such time as rations can be issued a subsistence allowance of 2/6 a day will bo given to each man.In case of injuryP personnel will be dealt with under the &quot;Special Constables Order&quot;,Units of the Civil Constabulary Reserve will be so organised that Members of the same territorial Army Unit who enrol for service will serve together and under their own officers,Uj2iJis-*&amp;^t&amp;^^Army. j^a^aw^^ for^e^.^ s eunits - are- asked, to-.en3?o 1 oIn this time of real emergency,, employers are earnestly requested to encourage and give every facility to their employees to enrol themselves.Recruiting officer, for the Civil Constabulary Reserve will be established and- openecjbn Monday, 10th May, 1926, iii all drill halls of the. 4g43a-^an7i Sfith-London-jJlvioloaio^ fcrritorio IV &amp;*mg-&amp;.t 7 a0m.Full details will be explained to Intending recruits,..

</content>
</cab>
