<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/179/0 images: 1264-1265</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]     printed for the Cabinet.   May 1926.SECRET Copy No. 3QO.P. 192 (26).CABINET.GOVERNMENT   LANDS   AND   BUILDINGS.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.THE view of the Air Ministry on Sir Howard Frank&apos;s report in 1922 was expressed in a memorandum to the Cabinet (CP. 4284,dated 12th October 1922) the gist of which was to associate the Air Ministry with the Admiralty and the War Office in assenting to the centralisation (as regards lands at home) of valuation and purchase, provided that management was a sole responsibility of the owner department.I see no reason to depart in substance from this view. It is, however, an essential proviso that, as indicated in the Chancellor&apos;s Memorandum, there should be in the Air Ministry itself an adequate expert staff not only to deal with estate management, short-term lettings and the upkeep of aerodromes, but also to assist in determining the questions of policy in respect of land purchase, for which the Air Ministry must remain responsible to Parliament.I note also that the Admiralty, the only Service Department with actual exper-ience of working with the Inland Revenue,&apos; stipulate that the legal work of settling the contract and deeds (with the Treasury Solicitor) should be carried through by the owner department, and I presume that this correctly interprets what is intended.If the centralisation of Lands Work is accepted, the arrangements described in the foregoing paragraph will be suitable for the requirements of the Air Ministry. The Secretary of State for War, however, makes some observations which seem to be intended to show that, whatever happens, the extent of departmental control reserved by the War Office and all other departments to themselves is not suitable for the Air Ministry. This is a position which I naturally cannot accept. The question whether some saving can be made in the joint organisation of the War Office and the Air Ministry, if and so long as it continues, is one which I am naturally ready to discuss with him, but I see no need for troubling the Cabinet with it.The Secretary of State for War refers to an episode in which the Air Ministry Section of the Lands Branch approached proprietors of land which the War Depart-ment was intending to purchase, and leaves it to be inferred that such episodes might be of frequent occurrence under the present organisation. This is quite misleading. What happened in this instance was that, owing to the secrecy deemed necessary in connection with a large War Office scheme, the Air Ministry Section of the Lands Branch was left without the guidance which it normally has in regard to current War Office proposals. Even if in the special circumstances such guidance could not be given, it was always within the power of the Director of Lands to ascertain what proposals, however tentative, were being ventilated by the Air Ministry, since the Air Ministry Section, although in specially close liaison with the Air Ministry, forms part of his Branch : in fact I should be quite as much entitled to make out of this episode a grievance against the War Office, as the Secretary of State for War is to make it a grievance against the Air Ministry. In any case the lesson, for what it is worth, appears to be that any two Government Departments might have the same site in view, and that all should therefore operate through a central agency.[14525]
In order that the effect of a decision in this matter may be clear, I append the following table, showing what I conceive to be the intention of the Chancellor of the Exchequer^ proposal as regards the division of departmental functions in the acquisition of land : 1. Policy of purchase and determination of area within which site can be selected :   Individual Department. 2. Preliminary valuation of sites and advice on market values of land indifferent regions :   Inland Revenue. 3. Negotiations for purchase :   Inland Revenue.4. Settlement of Contract:   Individual Department,  in conjunction withInland Revenue. 5. Management of land (Estate) :   Individual Department.The Inland Revenue to be in touch with the individual Department as necessary throughout stages 2 to 4.If the Air Ministry is treated as an &quot; Individual Department &quot; under this scheme, I am prepared to accept it.S. H.Air Ministry, May 1926.

</content>
</cab>
