<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/1/65 images: 599-606</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1939.

SECRET. CopjJIa.

W.M. (39)

65th Conclusions.

TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.

It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.

WAR CABINET 65 (39).

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1, on Monday, October 30, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.

Present :

The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).

The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.

Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon. Lord Chatfield, Minister for Coordination of Defence.

The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha, M.P., Secretary of State for War.

The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.

The following were also present:

The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.

The    Right    Hon.    Winston S. Churchill, M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty. The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,

M.P., Secretary of State for Air. The   Right   Hon.   Lord Hankey, Minister without Portfolio.

The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home Department and Minister of Home Security.

The Most Hon. the Marquess of Zetland, Secretary of State for India and Secretary of State for Burma (Item 6).

Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N. Newall, Chief of the Air Staff (Items 1-7).

The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P., Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.

Sir Horace j. Wilson, Permanent Secretary to the Treasury.

Admiral of the Fleet Sir Dudley Pound, First Sea Lord and Chief of Naval Staff (Items 1-7). General Sir W. Edmund Ironside, Chief of the Imperial General Staff (Items 1-7).

Secretariat. Sir Edward Bridges. Major-General H. L. Ismay. Colonel L. C. Hollis, R.M. Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N. Mr. F. Hemming. Mr. W. D. Wilkinson. Wing Commander W. Elliot.

[20239]


WAR CABINET 65 (39).

Contents.

Minute

No.                                   Subject. Page.

1 The Air Situation ......(&apos;............ 543

2 The Naval Situation.................. 543

3 Security of Fleet Bases ............... 543

4 The Military Situation ............... 543

Letter from Lord Gort.

5 The Naval, Military and Air Situation ......... 544

6 Visit of Dominion Ministers ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 544

Review of Strategical Situation.

7 Equipment of proposed Egyptian Volunteer Force       ... 544

8 The Vatican..................... 544

9 Policy of the Soviet Government    ...      ...      ...      ... 545

10 Air Force Training in Canada ......                       ...      ... 545

Expenditure to be met by the United Kingdom.

11 Eire ......... ......  ...... 546

Control of communications between Eire, Northern Ireland and this country.


543

W.M. 65 (39).

The Air fjj   The Secretary of State for Air said that the destroyer

Situation. force, which was carrying out a sweep to investigate whether the

(Previous Germans were using trawlers to assist their aircraft, had reported

Reference: earlier in the morning that they were being shadowed by German

W.M. (39) 64th aircraft.   A number of reconnaissance and fighter squadrons had

Conclusions, been sent out to endeavour to make contact.

Minute l.) The German aircraft, which had been reported on the previous day as shot down, had been found to be practically intact.

The War Cabinet took note of this statement.

The Naval 2.   The First Lord of the A dmiralty said that the torpedoed

Situation. British ship reported as being still afloat on the previous day, had (Previous now sunk. Another British ship had been torpedoed, but she was Reference: in tow and it was hoped to bring her into port. A Norwegian ship, W.M. (39) 64th bound from Norway to Antwerp, had been sunk by a mine in an Conclusions, area which, as a result of the finding of German mines, had been Minute 2.)       proclaimed dangerous.

The body of the Captain of U-12 had been found near Calais.

It seemed safe to add this submarine to the list of those definitely

known to have been destroyed.

The War Cabinet took note of this statement.

Security of 3.   The First Lord of the Admiralty gave the War Cabinet

Fleet Bases. certain information as to action taken in regard to this matter, and

(Previous as t  Fleet dispositions.

Reference: Considerable discussion took place on this subject, which also

W.M. (39) 63rd touched on certain aspects of the possibility of seaborne attack on

Conclusions Great Britain.   A record of this discussion is contained in the

Minute 3.) Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.

The Military 4.   The Secretary of State for War informed the War Cabinet

Situation.        that one more German Division was reported to be in the Saar. (Previous Extracts from a letter from Lord Gort stated that the Western

Reference- Front was fast becoming waterlogged, and would be quite unfit for WM (39) 64th the launching of an attack. The health of the troops was good, Conclusions thanks to ample food and exercise. It was proposed to withdraw Minute 3)&apos; units where possible to back areas to give them training during the Letter from winter months. Lord Gort hoped that the Prime Minister would Lord Gort.       visit the Front. wlS^&apos; v &amp;

Reference was made to the length of our lines of communication in France.

The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that a limited use was already being made of Le Havre, and when the facilities at this port had been further developed it was the intention to make use of alternative ports. The danger of moving our base closer to the Front was, of course, that it brought it within range of German air attack.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.

[20239]


544

The Naval, Mill-       5.   The War Cabinet took note of the Weekly Resume&quot; No. 8

tary and Air     by the Chiefs of Staff (Paper W.P. (39) 101).

Situation.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 57th Conclusions, Minute 5.)

Visit of 6.   The War Cabinet had before them a Review of the

Dominion Strategical Situation, prepared by the Chiefs of Staff (Paper Ministers. W.P. (39) 103).

Review of In the course of discussion the view was expressed that, while

Strategical       the facts were correctly stated in the Paper, the presentation Situation.        required amendment. As at present drafted, the Review seemed to (Previous        lay undue emphasis on the advantages which Germany enjoyed, and Reference:       the disadvantages from which we suffered.  General agreement was W.M. (39) 54th expressed with this view.   A suggestion made by the Minister Conclusions,      without Portfolio, that the concluding sentence in paragraph 43 Minute 12.)      should be omitted, was also agreed to.  This paragraph suggested that the military effort of the Dominions, with the exception of Canada, might best be employed in the Middle East, and this suggestion might not be altogether acceptable to the Dominions at the present stage.

The War Cabinet 

Invited the Chiefs of Staff to re-draft the Review of the Strategical Situation, in the the light of the suggestions made, and to submit the revised draft to the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.

Equipment of

proposed

Egyptian

Volunteer

Force.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 7th Conclusions, Minute 4.)

7. The Secretary of Stale for War recalled that at the Meeting noted in the margin the War Cabinet had been informed of the concern evinced by the Egyptian Government as to the large number of Egyptian regular troops locked up on internal security duties in Egypt. The Egyptian Prime Minister had suggested the supply from Great Britain, gratis, of the equipment necessary for the organisation of an Egyptian Volunteer Force. He (the Secretary of State for War) had been invited to ascertain whether the equipment could be provided and to submit recommendations to the War Cabinet.

His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Cairo, the General Officer Commanding British Troops in Egypt, and General Macready had all been consulted and had advised against equipping the Volunteer Force until it had been trained. No further communication had been received from the Egyptian Government, and he therefore suggested that the scheme should be dropped.

The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed.

The War Cabinet agreed that no further action should be taken on this question unless and until the Egyptian Government raised the matter again.

The Vatican. 8.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attention

to telegram No. 83 (R), dated the 28th October, 1939, from His Majesty&apos;s Minister to the Holy See, in regard to the encyclical published by the Pope the previous day, which from our point of view could be regarded as very satisfactory. After dealing with religious questions and the role of the Church in the present crisis,


545 W.M. 65 (39).

the Pope strongly condemned certain fundamental errors of the present time; for example, the laicising of society, the unlimited authority of the State over the individual, and the unilateral annulment of treaties, which destroyed that mutual confidence so essential to peaceful life between countries. At the conclusion of the encyclical His Holiness expressed deep sympathy with all oppressed beings, and especially the Poles.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

9. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he had no information regarding either the nature of the statement of policy which it was alleged in the Press that M. Stalin proposed to make that week, or in regard to the extent, if any, to which the U.S.S.R. was providing assistance to Germany.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

10. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had received a telegram from Lord Riverdale, who was now in Ottawa, in regard to the financial aspects of the plan for Imperial co-operation 4n Canada for the training of 50,000 pilots and air crew personnel a year for the Royal Air Force. The necessary personnel would be drawn from Canada, Australia, New Zealand and this country. The urgency of the matter lay in the fact that this question would be discussed by the Canadian Cabinet at a meeting to be held the following day (the 31st October, 1939), and it was essential that, before that meeting, Lord Riverdale should know whether we were prepared to accept our part of the financial burden proposed. The position might be summarised as follows : 

The expenditure involved, which would need to be met partly in sterling and partly in Canadian dollars, covered a period of 3-| years, and was as follows : 

(i) Expenditure to be met in sterling. Provision from this country of training machines and instructors .  50 millions.

(ii) Expenditure in Canadian dollars: $687 millions. (Capital expenditure, $260 millions; maintenance, $427 millions.)

The proposed allocation of the expenditure was as follows: 

Millions.

United Kingdom     ...      ...&quot;   ...      ...  50

Canada ............... $343^

Australia and New Zealand (in proportions

to be determined later)......... $343^

Neither Australia nor New Zealand was in a position to provide Canadian dollars, and we should therefore have to undertake to find the exchange (which amounted to the payment in gold of the sum in question). The transaction would be equivalent to our making loans to the two Dominions concerned, and repayment of any substantial part was not likely before the end of the war.

Continuing, the Chancellor of the Exchequer said that this scheme was of the utmost importance to the prosecution of the war. The provision of Canadian dollars on this scale would, however, involve


546

an equivalent reduction in the expenditure in dollars which would be possible for other urgent war purposes. If, therefore, this expenditure was to be incurred, it was necessary for the War Cabinet to give it an absolute priority.

The Secretary of State for Air said that the Canadian plan was designed to provide us with the number of pilots and air crew personnel required for the monthly programme of aircraft production already authorised. If for any other reason we were unable to achieve that programme, the expenditure in Canada would be correspondingly reduced. The expenditure would be spread over a considerable period, and the bulk would fall to be paid in the later years. Due credit should be given to the very heavy financial burden which under this scheme Canada would herself assume.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

(a) to approve the proposal of the Chancellor of the Exchequer

that, in order to render possible the scheme for training 50,000 pilots and air crew personnel annually in Canada, His Majesty&apos;s Government should undertake to provide, in Canadian dollars, that portion of the cost of the scheme ($343^ millions) to be borne by Australia and New Zealand over a period of 3^ years, the sums so advanced to be repaid in sterling by the two Dominions concerned, it being recognised that in large part such repayment might have to take place after the war;

(b) that the provision of Canadian dollars for this transaction

should be accepted as having priority over other demands, it being understood that the provision of dollars on this scale would involve an equivalent reduction in the expenditure in dollars which would be available for other war purposes;

(c) that the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of

State for Air should concert the terms of a telegram to be despatched to Lord Riverdale informing him of the Cabinet&apos;s decision.

Eire.

Control of communications between Eire, Northern Ireland and this country.

11. The First Lord of the Admiralty invited the attention of the War Cabinet to the position regarding telephone conversations between this country and Eire. There was as yet no arrangement by which the censorship authorities &apos;&apos; listened in &quot; to such conversations. This was an inexplicable gap in our defences and we were running the risk of a leakage of vital information. It must not be forgotten that a German Minister was still in residence in Dublin.

The Secretary of State for War, in explaining the existing arrangements, said that there would be no difficulty in arranging for the censorship of telephone conversations with Eire. &quot; Censorship &quot; in these circumstances meant &quot; listening in.&quot; This could be arranged without publicity and without the parties to the conversation being aware that they were overheard. On the other hand, the censoring of letters between this country and Eire would mean a considerable increase in the staff of the Censorship Department. The Eire Government had themselves already instituted a censorship over letters, telegrams, the press and broadcasting. Friendly relations existed between the Eire censorship authorities and our own.

The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs pointed out that no effective check would be provided against the leakage of information unless telephone conversations with Northern Ireland were also controlled.


547

W.M. 65 (39).

The War Cabinet agreed : 

(a) To invite the Secretary of State for War, in consultation

with the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, to arrange for censorship of telephone conversations between this country, Eire and Northern Ireland.

(b) To invite the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs to

consider whether the above decision should be communicated to Mr. Dulanty.

(c) In the event of any additional measure of control over

communications between this country and Eire being considered desirable, to invite the Secretary of State for War to consult with the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, with a view to framing a further recommendation to the War Cabinet.

Richmond Terrace, S.W.I, October 30, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
