<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/105/0 images: 353-355</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUI;IE.;T IS TKJB PROPERTY OF HIS ERITALIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT) *CABINET. MOST SECRET. HOIiEE AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.CP, 1267. STRIKES IN THE CIVIL SERVICE.Interim Report to the Cabinet(Reference: Conference of Ministers, May 4th.1920,Concluei on 1.)The Committee have considered the general question submitted to them and make the following recommendations:-1,   Heads of Departments should be authorised summarily to dismiss any established Civil Servant who strikes without notice, on the ground of desertion of duty.The Pensions System has a steadying effect.     The fear of loss of pension acts as a deterrent against striking and the right of the Government to reduce pensions for infidelity is a weapon which they should not lightly throw away.Heads of Departments should, therefore, be authorised wherever it appears to them to be necessary, that is to say if a strike is seriously apprehended, to warn established Civil Servants in their employment that any established Servant striking will be regarded as having terminated his service, that he may not be reinstated and that even if reinstated he is liable to be penalised in respect of pay, pension and promotion,2.   Heads of Departments should be warned, however, that it is the view of the Cabinet that in the event of a strike on a large scale it would in the long run be impossible to persist in such a policy, and that in all probability &quot;no victimisation&quot; would be an essential term in any
settlement.     In other words, the Head of the Department should exercise his own deaoretion in dealing with individual eases or with strikes upon a large scale. He might, for instance, come to the conclusion that it would &quot;be unfair to penali se particular .strikes for action they had taken unwi11ingly.through the force of external compulsion, or he might consider that a temporary lapse might be condoned by subsequent good conduct:    or again, that no great public interest was compromised at the moment by the action of the strikers.     In all such cases the Head of a Department might find it expedient to exact something less than the full penalty attaching to a strike among the established Servants of. his Department, or even on consideration to remit it altogether,3,   The Committee were also of opinion.that a special responsibility attaches to Civil Servants graded above manual labourers and operatives, and occupying responsible positions.     Any established Civil Servants of this class who strike without notice should not be.re-instated,4.   The Committee considered the suggestion that a warning should be issued that all Civil Servants whostrike will be regarded as having-terminated their engagementsIt was contended on the one hand that in the event of a strikemany of those.taking part in it would complain that theyhad not been warned of their position and had not appreciated that such action ipso facto would terminate their engagements;on the other hand it was agreed that in the Post Officeand other Departments of Government the risks attaching toa strike without notioe were. alivasr&amp;yappreciated, ,5.   It was- suggested that the legal position of an Established Civil Servant who deserts, his duty should be referred to the Law Officers for their opinion and that at an appropriate moment the opinion of the Law Officers should be published by a question and .answer in the House of Commons.
The - Committee - were divided in opinion whether&apos; this proposal should or should not &quot;be adopted.6.     In view of the - limitations on the effective and oerta-i n prohibition cf strikes to whi c.h allusion has been made in the preceding paragraphs, the Committee felt that something more was needed and that probably legislation would be necessary.. The Committee have, therefore, requested tho Home Secretary in consultation with the Treasury and the Board of trade to prepare a draft Bill for the consideration of the Committee making it an offence for established. Civil Servants to strike without one month&apos;s notice, - on the understanding that the Committee are not yet committed to such a proposal.. . - (Ggd) H.A..L.&apos; FISHER, ..Chairman.Whitehall Gardens, 12th ; ay 1020.

</content>
</cab>
