<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/105/0 images: 377-397</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Till? I^OfiCAB 1:70?.^?// gllTISTRY OF ;-&apos;I?J?.;S B ILL.AMemorandum by the President of the Board\Lli ------------I circulate herewith a draft of the Ministry of Mines Bill,The Bill deals only with-:(a) powers of oontrol during any emergency periodthat may continue aftor 31st August next,(b) the future ordering of the industry on apermanent basis, including the establish-ment of a sub-Ministry of Mines, and(c) to some extent with provisions for the Im-provement of social conditions.It is essential that a Bill should be passed before 31st August when the powers under which control is now operated, come to an end.The complicated question of the acquisition of royalties by the State has not been included in the draft now submitted, as it is certain that if tJb-U, controversial policy were made the subject of discussion in. the present session it would be impossible to get the Bill through within the limited period at our disposal.R.S. H0R1IE13th Lay, 1920,
Ministry of Mines Bill.ARRANGEMENT OE CLAUSES.Part I.Establishment of Ministry op Mines.Clause.1.   Appointment of Secretary of Mines.2.   General powers and duties.3.   Powers of regulating price and export of coal.4.   Advisory Committees.5.   Staff remuneration and expenses.6.   Seal, style, and acts of Secretary of Mines.7.   Ability of Secretary of Mines to sit in Parliament.* Part II.Regulation of Coal Mines.8. Pit and district committees, and area and national boards.9. Constitution and functions of pit committees.10. Constitution and functions of district committees.11. Constitution and functions of area boards.12. Additional powers of district committees and area boards.13. Constitution and functions of National Board.14.   Power of Secretary of Mines to direct companies with recommendations of schemes. 15.  rees to members and expenses of committees and boards. 16.   Undertaking by workers in coal mines not to cease workpending proceedings for settlement of disputes. 17.   Access to information.18.  Power to require provision of washing accommodation, &amp;c. in mines.Schemes as to drainage, &amp;c. 48-7 A
Paet III. General.Establishment of fund for improvement of social conditionsof colliery workers. Accounts, statistics, and returns. Power to hold inquiries. Interpretation. Short title. Schedules.
DRAFTof aBILLforEstablishing a Ministry of Mines, and for regulating the ad. 1920. coal industry, and for other purposes connected with the mining industry and the persons employed therein.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5 Part I.Establishment of Ministry of Mines.1. Eor the purpose of securing the most effective develop- Appoint-ment and utilisation of the mineral resources of the United genttof   f Kingdom and the safety and welfare of those engaged in the uinL.^0 10 mining industry, it shall be lawful for His Majesty to appoint a minister of mines, who shall, by virtue of his office, be an additional Parliamentary secretary of the Board of Trade and shall be called the Secretary of Mines, and shall hold office during His Majesty&apos;s pleasure.15       2. (1) It shall be the duty of the Secretary of Mines, general in the exercise and performance of the powers and duties l)0wersandP      -1 ii-i - duties.transferred to or conferred or imposed on him by or in pur-suance of this Act subject to any general directions which may be given by the Board of Trade, to take steps to carry out the 20 purposes aforesaid, and there shall, as and from such date or 48-7 A 2 &apos;
dates as His Majesty in Council may determine, be transferred to the Secretary of Mines-(a) all the powers and duties of the Board of Trade with respect to the mining industry;ib) all the powers of a Secretary of State under enactments 5 relating  to  coal  mineS) metalliferous   mines, and quarries;[(c) all the powers of the Minister of Munitions under the Petroleum Production Act, 1918].(2) If in regard to any powers and duties of any other 10 Government department relating to mines or minerals or the mining industry or the persons engaged therein, whether conferred by statute or otherwise, it is deemed expedient that such powers and duties should be transferred to the Secretary of Mines, or be exercised or performed by the Secretary of Mines con- 15 currently or in consultation with the Government department concerned, His Majesty in Council may by order make provision for the purpose.(3) The Secretary of Mines shall undertake the collection, preparation, and publication of statistics relating to the mining 20 &quot;industry, and the initiation and direction of research with a view to improving the methods of conducting mining operations, and to effecting economy in working expenses and consumption, and to improving the safety and health of the workers.(4) His Majesty in Council may by order make such con- 25 sequential and supplemental provisions as appear necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving full effect to any transfer of powers or duties by or under this Act, including provision for the transfer and vesting of any property, rights, and liabilities held, enjoyed, or incurred by any Government department in 30 connection with any powers or duties transferred, and may make such adaptations in the Acts or regulations relating to such powers or duties as appear necessary to make exerciseable by the Secretary of Mines and his officers, the powers and duties so transferred. 35(5) In connection with the transfer of powers and duties to the Secretary of Mines by or under this Act, the provisions set out in the Pirst Schedule to this Act shall have effect.
3. (1) Eor a period of one year after the thirty-first day A.d. 1920. of August, nineteen hundred and twenty, it shall he lawful for p()W^7of the Secretary of Mines, subject to the approval of the Board of regulating Trade, from time to time to give directions- price * .&apos; a , export 015       (a) regulating the price to be charged for coal sold for consumption in the United Kingdom; and(b) regulating the export of coal.(2) Where any such directions are given it shall be lawful for the Secretary of Mines, subject to the like approval, also to10 give directions as to the wages to be paid to workers in coal mines and by order to regulate the distribution of profits, and any such order shall contain provisions framed on principles similar to the principles on which the provisions of the Coal Mines (Emergency) Act, 1920, are framed so as to secure, as15 far as practicable, an equitable distribution as between different collieries:Provided that lief ore any such order is made a draft thereof shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament, and the order shall not be made unless the draft has been approved by 20 resolution of both Houses of Parliament, nor, if modifications in the draft are agreed to by both Houses, otherwise than as so modified.(3) If any person sells, or offers for sale, or exports, or attempts to export any coal in contravention of any directions25 given under this section or otherwise contravenes any such directions, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds, or, in the case of a contravention of the directions as to the price or export of coal, at the discretion of the court, to a fine not exceeding30 treble the amount by which the sum paid or payable on any coal sold or exported by him in contravention of any such directions exceeds the maximum sum which would have been paid or payable for the coal if there had been no such contravention.35 (4) The powers of giving such directions and making such orders as. aforesaid may be exercised by the Secretary of Mines subject to the like approval after the expiration of the said one year if the exercise of such powers is authorised by a resolution passed by both Houses of Parliament.
A.I). 1920. 4. (1) The Secretary of Mines shall appoint a committee Advisory ^or the purpose of giving to him advice and assistance on matters Committees, connected with his powers and duties under this Act relating to coal and the coal industry, and may appoint one or more other committees for the purpose of giving him advice and assistance 5 on matters connected with any of his other powers and duties, and in appointing members of any such committee the Secretary of Mines shall act after consultation with the various interests concerned, and the Secretary of Mines shall take into con-sideration any representations which may be made to him by 10 any such committee.(2) The Committee as respects coal and the coal industry shall consist of a chairman and twenty-four other persons, of whom Pour shall be representatives of the owners of coal mines; 15 Pour shall be representatives of workers in coal mines; Three   shall  be  representatives  of  employers  in   other industries;Three   shall   be   representatives   of   workers   in  other industries; 20One shall be a representative of mining engineers;One shall be a representative of the Universities which are approved institutions or universities for the purposes of section nine of the Coal Mines Act, 1911; One shall be a representative of the royal Society; 25One shall be a representative of the medical profession; One shall be a representative of coal exporters; Two shall be representatives of the management of coal mines;One shall be a representative of the Chambers of Commerce; 30 One shall be a representative of co-operative societies; One shall be a representative of coal factors and coal merchants.5.-(1) The Secretary of Mines may appoint such assistant secretaries, officers, and servants as the Secretary of Mines 35 may, subject to the consent of the Treasury as to number, determine.(2) There shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament to the Secretary of Mines an annual salary not exceeding two thousand pounds,  and  to  the assistant secretaries, inspectors, 40Staff re-munerationandsxpeuses.
officers, and servants of the department of the Secretary of A.D. 1920, Mines such salaries or remuneration as the Treasury may from time to time determine.(3) The expenses of the department of the Secretary of Mines, 5 to such amount as may be sanctioned by the. Treasury, shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament.(4) There shall he transferred and attached to the depart-ment of the Secretary of Mines such of the persons employed under any other Government department in or about the 10 execution of the powers and duties transferred by or under this Act to the Secretary of Mines, as the Secretary of Mines and the other Government department, with the sanction of the Treasury, may determine.(5) The Secretary of Mines may from time to time distribute 15 the business of the department amongst the several persons transferred and attached thereto in pursuance of this Act, in such manner as he may think right, and those officers shall perform such duties in relation to that business as may be directed by the Secretary of Mines:20 Provided that such persons shall be in no worse position as respects the tenure of office, salary, or superannuation allow-ances than they would have been if this Act had not been passed.6. (1) The Secretary of Mines may sue and be sued as, Seal, style, 25 and may for all purposes be described by the name of, the *ntl acts ol ,r &apos; Secretary of secretary ot Mines. Mines(2) The Secretary of Mines shall have an official seal, which shall be officially and judicially noticed, and shall be authenticated by the signature of the Secretary of Mines, or of an assistant 30 secretary, or any person authorised by the Secretary of Mines to act in that behalf.[(3) Por the purpose of acquiring and holding land the Secretary of Mines for the time being shall be a corporation sole by name of the Secretary oE Mines, and all land vested in the 35 Secretary of Mines shall be held in trust for His Majesty for the purposes of this Act.](4) Upon and by virtue of the appointment of any person to be Secretary of Mines, ail property of whatever description, and the benefit of all deeds, contracts, bonds, securities, or things 40 in action, vested in his predecessor at the time of his predecessor
a.d. 1920. ceasing to hold office shall by virtue of this Act be deemed to have been transferred to and to vest in and enure for the benefit of the person so appointed, in the same manner as respects such deeds, contracts, bonds, and securities, as if he had been contracted with instead of his predecessor, and as if his name had been 5 inserted therein instead of the name of his predecessor.(5) Subsections (2) to (4) of section eleven, and sub-sections (2) and (3) of section twelve, of the New Ministries and Secretaries Act, 1916, shall apply to the Secretary of Mines and to the department of the Secretary of Mines and to the 10 office of Secretary of Mines in like manner as they apply to the Ministers and Ministries mentioned in those sections.Ability of 7.-(l) The office of Secretary of Mines shall not renderMhlosto sit the holder thereof incapable of being elected to or sitting or in Pailia-    voting as a member of the Commons House of Parliament.       15incut.(2) The person avIio is first appointed to be Secretary of . Mines shall not by reason of such appointment, if a member of the Commons House of Parliament, vacate his seat as such member.Part II. 20Regulation of Coal Mines.Pit and 8. The Secretary of Mines shall, subject to the approval of district      the Board of Trade, by regulations provide for the constitution committees, . .and area and       (a) of a pit committee for every coal mine, except that it nawonal shall not be necessary to constitute a pit committee for 25boards. 17 inany mine where the average number of workers employed below ground does not exceed thirty, and that in the case of two or more adjoining mines belonging to the same owner a single pit committee may, if the regulations so provide, be constituted for 30 all such mines;(b) of a district committee for each of the districts men-tioned in Part. I of the Second Schedule to this Act;(c) of an area board for each of the areas mentioned in Part II. of that Schedule; 35(d) of a National Board; having such functions as may, subject to the provisions of this Act, be prescribed by the regulations, and the procedure of the
several committees and boards shall be such as may be pre- A.D. 1920. scribed by the regulations:     .Provided that (i) where a district is co-extensive with an area the 5 district committee shall perform the functions ofthe area board as well as of the district committee;(ii) districts and areas may be varied by order of theSecretary of Mines  after  consultation with the National Board;10 (iii) where a mine situate in one district has for industrial purposes been customarily dealt with as if it were a mine situate in an adjoining district, that mine shall for. the purposes of this Part of the Act, if the owner and the workers employed in or about15 the mine so agree, be treated as being situate insuch adjoining district.9. (1) A pit committee shall comprise representatives of constitution the owners and  management of the mine and of workers .  fu&quot;c&quot;.0 ,    turns 01 pitemployed in or about the mine selected from amongst their committees. 20 own number, so however that the representatives of the workers shall constitute at least half of the number of the pit committee.(2) The functions of a pit committee shall be to discuss and make recommendations with respect to (a) the safety, health, and welfare of the workers; 25       [h) the causes which adversely affect output;(c) reports made on an inspection under section sixteen ofthe Coal Mines Act, 1911, which reports shall be referred to the committee by the manager;(d) disputes arising in connection with the mine including 30 disputes as to wages;(e) any other questions and matters relating to the minewhich may be prescribed by the regulations.(3) The regulations shall provide for matters which cannot be satisfactorily disposed of by the pit committee being referred 35 to the district committee, and for the holding of meetings of pit committees at intervals of not less than a month.(4) Por enabling a pit committee to exercise their functions under paragraphs (a) and (b) of subsection (2) of this section, the committee shall be entitled to be furnished by the manager 40 of the mine with such statistics as they may require for the . 48 B
A.d. 1920. purpose, and may appoint two of their members, one being a representative of the management, and one being a representative of the workers, to make periodical inspections of the mine or any part thereof and to report the result of their inspections to the committee, and- the persons so appointed shall have all such 5 facilities for the purpose of making inspections as persons appointed to make inspections under section sixteen of the Coal Mines Act, 1911, and that section shall apply accordingly.(5) Any recommendations of the pit committee made on any report under section sixteen of the Coal Mines Act, 191.1, 10 which has been referred to the committee, and on any other matters to which that Act relates, shall be sent to the inspector of the division.Constitution       10. (1) A district committee shall comprise representa-tions of      tives of the owners and management of the coal mines in the 15 district       district, and an equal number of representatives of workerscommittees.   employed in 0r suc]1 times.(2) A district committee shall take into consideration (a) questions affecting the district of the same nature asthose which may be the subject of discussion and 20 recommendations by a pit committee;(b) any questions other than as aforesaid which may bereferred to them by a pit committee;(c) any questions which may be referred to them bythe area board, the National Board, or the Secretary 25 of Mines;and may make recommendations in respect thereof, and may in any case when their recommendations are not complied with, or in any other case where they think fit, and in particular where the matter appears to the committee to be one proper to 30 be dealt with by the area board rather than by the district committee, refer the matter to the area board.Constitution 11. (1) An area board shall comprise representatives of and function ^    owners and management of the coal mines in the areaoi area aboards. nominated by the representatives of the owners and management 35 who are members of the various district committees within the area, and an equal number of representatives of workers employed in or about such mines nominated by the represen-tatives of workers who are members of the district committees within the area, in accordance with such regulations. 40
(2) The area board shall take into consideration  ad. 1020.(a) questions affecting the area of the same nature as those which may be the subject of consideration by a district committee;5 (6) any questions which may be referred to them by a district committee;(c) any questions which may he referred to them by the National Board or the Secretary of Mines,and may make recommendations in respect thereof, and may 10 in any case where the recommendations are not complied with, or in any other case where they think fit, and in particular where the matter appears to the committee to be one proper to be dealt with by the National Board rather than by the area board, refer the matter to the National Board.15 (3) An area hoard shall formulate, at such intervals and on such principles as may be prescribed by the National Board, schemes for adjusting the remuneration of the workers within the area having regard to the profits of the industry within the area, and any such scheme when formulated shall be submitted20 to the National Board for their approval, and if approved by them shall he referred to the Secretary of Mines, and for the purposes of this subsection the owners of mines in the area shall furnish to accountants appointed by the area board such information as they may require in order that they may ascer-25 tain for the information of the area board particulars of the output, cost of production, proceeds and profits in the area as a whole:Provided that no such scheme shall be formulated whilst1an order made by the Secretary of Mines under Part I. of this 30 Act as to the distribution of profits is in force.12. The Secretary of Mines may, by regulations, provide Additional for the district committees or area boards determining any P?wers of,. -, . . i - 1    i   p        ,i .      district corn-questions and exercising any powers which before the passing mittecs an(lof this Act can be determined or exercised by a conciliation area hoards.35 board or by a joint district board constituted under the Coal Mines (Minimum Wage) Act, 1912; but the regulations shall provide for the appointment of an independent chairman, with a casting vote, to preside at meetings of any district committee or area board when determining any such question or exercising40 any such power.&apos;     48 B 2
10A.D. 1920. 13.-(1) The National Board shall comprise representativesConstitution Qf the owners and management of coal mines throughout theand func- United Kingdom, and an equal number of representatives ofNational workers employed in or about such mines.(2) The National Board shall take into consideration-        * (ft) questions affecting the coal mining industry as a whole, of the same nature as may he the subject of consideration by an area board;(b) any questions which may be referred to them by an area board;(c) any question which may be referred to them by theSecretary of Mines;(ft7) any question as to wages in coal mines of general application;and may make recommendations in respect thereof, and may 15 in any case when their recommendations are not complied with, or in any other case where they think fit, refer any such question to the Secretary of Mines.(2) The National Board shall also determine, subject to the approval of the Secretary of Mines, the principles on which 20 schemes by area boards under this Part of this Act for adjusting the remuneration of workers are to be framed, and shall con-sider all such schemes when submitted to them for their approval.Power of 14. The Secretary of Mines may give directions requiring 25Secretary of compliance with any recommendations of or schemes approved direct com- by the National Board, and it shall be the duty of every panies with person affected by those directions to comply therewith, and if lions and&quot; &quot; anv sucn Person to do so he shall be guilty of an offence schemes.     against the Coal Mines Act, 1911: 30Provided that the Secretary of Mines may in any case and shall if so required by the National Board refer to the Advisory Committee constituted under this Act for enquiry and report, the question whether directions are to be so given as aforesaid requiring compliance with any recommendations of the 35 . National Board.Fees to 15. There shall be paid to the mmebers of pit committees,members     district committees and area boards [and the National Board]and expenses .of com-      such fees for attendance at meetings thereof as may be pre-
lingat the mine such suitable and sufficient accommodation and accommoda-facilities for taking baths, drying clothes, and taking meals as miues. C*&apos; may be specified in the directions, and if he fails to do so 40 shall be guilty of an offence under that Act.scribed by the regulations, and such payments, together with  A-D- i92()-any expenses incurred by such committees and boards in the orittees and discharge of their functions, including the remuneration of the 00iinls-secretary [and other officers] of such committees and boards, 5 shall-(a) in the case of pit committees, be payable by the owner of the mine; and(b) in the case of district committees and area  boards[and the National Board] be apportioned amongst the 10 owners of the various mines in the district or area[or throughout the United Kingdom  as the case may be] in accordance with the regulations;and the sums so payable by or apportioned to the owner of any mine shall be defrayed as part of the working expenses of 15 the mine, and shall be recoverable summarily as a civil debt at the instance of the secretary or other officer of the committee or board concerned.16. It &quot;shall be an implied term of any contract for the Undertakingemployment of a workman in a coal mine that he thereby j,f ,!!?ikcra20 enters into an undertaking in such form as may be prescribed mines not toby the district committee or area board that he will not in con- ceasf. w. ... pending pro-sequence of any dispute affecting mines in the area or any ceedings for of them give notice to determine his contract, nor combine settlement of to cease work, unless and until the question in dispute has  UP 25 been considered by the district committee or the area board acting as a conciliation board under this Part of this Act and the committee or board have failed to settle the dispute.17.   The National Board and any area board or district Access to -   committee shall have a right of access to any returns and informatlon-30 accounts furnished to the Secretary of Mines under this Act which they may show to the satisfaction of the Secretary of &apos; Mines to be required for the purposes of their powers under this Part of this Act.18. (1) Notwithstanding anything in section seventy-seven Power to 35 of the Coal Mines Act, 1911, the owner of any coal mine shall, ^^ne j?r0&quot; if so directed by the Secretary of Mines, provide and maintain Waslai
A.D. 1920. (2) The expenses incurred in providing such accommodation and facilities as aforesaid [in pursuance of such directions] shall he treated as expenses of the trade or business carried on by the owner.Schemes as 19. (1) It shall be lawful for the Secretary of Mines 5 todriuuage, a^er consultation with a district committee or area board or holding such other inquiry as he may think fit to make schemes with respect to any&apos; group of coal mines as to the drainage thereof or the working of barrier coal, and as to the apportion-ment as between the owners of the coal mine in question of 10 any expenditure for a common purpose that may be required by any such scheme.[(2) The provisions of section eighty-six and Part I, of the Second Schedule to the Coal Mines Act, T 911, with respect to the making general regulations shall apply with the necessary 15 modifications to schemes under this section.]Part III. General.Establish- 20. (1) There shall be constituted a fund to be appliedment of fund for such purposes connected with the improvement of the 20 meriiofrOVe&quot; health, comfort and social conditions, including housing accom-social condi- modation, of colliery workers and the improvement of mining tl*ll*er        education as the Secretary of Mines, subject to the approval workers.     of the Board of Trade may prescribe.(2) The owners of every coal mine shall in every year 25 before the thirty-first day of March pay into the said fund a sum equal to one penny a ton of the output Jof the mine during the previous calendar year, and the sums so payable in respect of any mine shall be defrayed as part of the working expenses of the mine and shall be recoverable either as a debt due 30 to the Crown or by the Secretary of Mines summarily as a civil debt.(3) The duty of allocating the money from time to time standing to the credit of the said fund to the several purposes aforesaid shall be vested in a committee consisting of five persons, 35 of whom one, who shall be chairman, shall be appointed by the Secretary of Mines; one shall be appointed by the General Medical Council, after consultation with the Minister of Health and the Board of Health for Scotland; one shall be appointed
l)y the Mining Association of  Great Britain, one  shall he a.D. 1920. appointed by the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain, and one shall he appointed by the Colliery Managers&apos; Association.(4) Payments out of and into the fund, and all other matters 5 relating to the fund, and moneys standing to the credit of the fund (including temporary investments thereof) shall be made and regulated in such manner as the Secretary of Mines, subject to the approval of the Treasury, may direct.(5) The Secretary of Mines shall in each year cause an 10 account to be prepared and transmitted to the Controller and Auditor-General for examination, showing the receipts into and issues out of the said fund in the financial year ended the thirty-first day of March preceding, and the Controller and Auditor-General shall certify and report upon the same, and such account 15 and report shall be laid before Parliament by the Secretary of Mines.21. It shall be the duty of the owners, agents, and managers Accounts,&apos; tics, eturns.of any mine, and any other person engaged in the mining a^[&apos;*.tK &apos;industry, to furnish to the Secretary of Mines, in such manner 20 and form as he may direct, such accounts, statistics, returns, and plans as he may require for the purpose of his powers and duties under this Act.22. (1) The Secretary of Mines may hold such inquiries Power to as he considers necessary or desirable for the purposes of this &quot;Si&quot;1&quot;25 Act, and the Secretary of Mines and, if authorised by the Secretary of Mines, the person appointed to hold any such inquiry, may, by order, require any person, subject to the payment or tender of the reasonable expenses of his attendance, to attend as a witness and give evidence, or to produce any30 documents in his possession or power which relate to any matter in question at the inquiry, and are such as would be subject to production in a court of law, and, if any person fails without reasonable excuse to comply with any of the provisions of any such order, he shall be liable, on summary conviction, to35 a fine not exceeding five pounds, and the person holding the inquiry shall have power to take evidence on oath and for that purpose to administer oaths.(2) Notices of inquiries may be given andt published in accordance with such general or special directions as the Secretary 40 of Mines may give.
A.D. 1920. (3) The powers of the Secretary of Mines under this section shall he in addition to and not in derogation of any powers of holding inquiries transferred to him from any other Govern-ment department under this Act.interpreta- 23. For the purposes of this Act, unless the context otherwise tion.requires: The expression &quot;coal mine&quot; means a mine to which the Coal Mines Act, 1911, applies, and &quot;owner&quot; in relation to a coal mine has the same meaning as in that Act.The expression &quot; management&quot; in relation to a coal mine 10 includes the manager, under managers, technical and administrative  staff,  officials, deputies,   firemen and examiners of the mine.The expression &quot; output&quot; in relation to a coal mine means the tonnage in saleable coal raised and weighed at 15 the pithead.Short title. 24. This Act may he cited as the Ministry of Mines Act,1920.
schedules.a.1). 1920.FIRST SCHEDULE.Transitory Provisions.1. In the construction and for the purposes of any Act of Parlia-5 ment, judgment, decree, order, award, deed, contract, regulation, hyelaw, or other document passed or made before the transfer to the Secretary of Mines from any other Government department of any powers or duties by or under this Act, but so far only as may be necessary for the purpose of such transfer, the name of the Secretary 10 of Mines shall be substituted for the name of the other Government department.2. Where anything has been commenced by or under the authority of any other Government department before the transfer to the Secretary of Mines of any powers or duties by or under this Act, and 15 such thing is in relation to the powers or duties so transferred, such thing may be carried on and completed by or under the authority of the Secretary of Mines.3. Where at the time of the transfer of any powers or duties by or under this Act any legal proceeding is pending to which any 20 Government department is a party, and such proceeding has reference to the powers and duties transferred by or under this Act, the Secretary of Mines shall be substituted in such proceeding for the other Govern-ment department, and such proceeding shall not abate by reason of the substitution.25SECOND SCHEDULE.Part I.Coat- Districts.1. Northumberland. 2. Durham.303. Cumberland.4. South Yorkshire. 5. West Yorkshire.-6. Lancashire and Cheshire.7. Nottinghamshire.358. Derbyshire, exclusive of South Derbyshire.9, South Derbyshire. 10. Cannock Chase.
11. North Staffordshire.12. South Staffordshire, exclusive of Cannock Chase and EastWorcestershire. 13. Shropshire.1. Northern ; comprising the districts of Northumberland, Durham, 20and Cumberland. 2. North-western;   comprising the  districts of  Lancashire andCheshire, North Wales, North Staffordshire, and CannockChase.3. Midland; comprising West Yorkshire, South Yorkshire, Notting- 25 hamshire, Derbyshire, South Derbyshire, Leicestershire and Warwickshire.4. Western; comprising South Staffordshire, Shropshire, Forest of Dean, Gloucestershire, Somersetshire, Ireland and Kent.5. South Wales; comprising the district of Monmouthshire and 30 South Wales.6. Scotland; comprising the districts of Lanarkshire, Ayrshire, Fife and Clackmannan, and the Lothians,14. Leicestershire. 15. Warwickshire. 16. Forest of Dean. 17. Gloucestershire. 38. Somersetshire.19. Monmouthshire and South Wales. 20. North Wales. 21. Lanarkshire. 22. Ayrshire.23. Fife and Clackmannan. 24. The Lothians. 25. Kent.   &apos;. 26. Ireland.51015Part II,Coal Areas.

ministry of mines.DEAf TOF AbillPor establishing a Ministry of Mines, and for regulating the coal industry, and for other purposes connected with the mining industry and the persons employed therein.XLIL   (7.)27th April 1920.

</content>
</cab>
