<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/105/0 images: 543-546</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CP.1297.TEE CONVERSATIONS AT HYTHE.(Bote by the Secretary)The following lote has been prepared in order to communi-cate to the Cabinet the decisions reached at the Uythe Conference. Most of these have already be on published.FgsJ^flQment of the Spa Conference.In view of the fact that the German elections are due totake place on June 6th, it was agreed that it would be advisable to postpone the Spa Conference.until Monday, June 81st.     Thefollowing communication to the German Government was approved&quot;The attention of the Allied Governments &quot;has been drawn to the fact that the&apos;German national elections are due to .take place cn June 6th.     The primary pur-pose of the Spa Conference Is to enable the heads of the Allied Governments to examine with the responsible heads of the German Government, the serious questions raised by the failure of Germany to fulfil the solemn obligations which it assumed when its representatives signed and ratified the Treaty of Versailles, and also arrangements for securing its future execution.     It . is of the utmost importance that once this Conference assembles it should not be distracted or delayed by external pre-occupations,     The Allied Governments, therefore, consider that the Conference to examine the execution of the Treaty of Versailles as.proposed by  ; them in their letter of April 27th and accepted by tho German Government should be postponed until Monday June Slst.     They would be glad to learn if the Gorman Government consents to this.&quot;Before this can be presented to the German Government, howe/6r, the Italian and Belgian Governments will have to be consulted.It is intended to publish the Hote when it la sent to the Germans, so that the German electors will realise that the object of the Conference at Spa is not to alter the Treaty, but to discuss the means of carrying it out.Procedure(This docuraoQt is the property of His Britannic Ma jeatySa Government.CONFIDENTIAL.
As a preliminary to the Meetings at Spa, it was agreed -(a) That the French Government should prepare a list with full particulars of the points on which Germany has failed to execute the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles, with a view to its presentation to the German Government before the Meeting at Spa.(b) The above list should bo sent to the British Govern-ment for approval before being presented to the German Government.There was somo considerable discussion about the procedure at Spa, and the understanding was that the Germans should be asked to give their reasons in regard to their falure to execute the Treaty and their proposals as regards tho parts still remain-ing to be executed.     The   representatives of the Allies should ask the Germans for any explanations they require and should then deliberate among themselves on the German replies.Disarmament.The Conclusions on disarmament were as follows :-(a) Disarmament of Germany should be placed first on the Agenda of the Spa Conference.(b) Pending the Spa Conference the Allies should make every effort to induce Germany to carry out the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles in regard to disarmament.finance.The greater part of the conversations were occupied with the question of Finance, which was considered under three headings(a) Settlement by Germany of her obligations to the Allies:(b) The division among themselves of the amounts to be received from Germany by the Allies:(c) The Debt between the Allies and one another and the United States of America.The principal object of the French representatives was to divide the claims of the Allies into classes and to give priority in a certain order to these classes.   The reason for the french proposal, to which they constantly reverted throughout thediscussion, was to secure priority for the devastated regions.This proposal was.quite inacceptable to the British Government
for a number of reasons, among which the more important were the following.     Its acceptance would have re-opened the settlement in regard to priorities which had only been reached last March after months of discussion, and to which the adher-ence of the Dominions had only been obtained with the utmost difficulty.     It would also have put below the claims ofBelgium, the claims in which the British Government for the main part, and the Dominions for practically the whole of their share of reparation, are concerned, namely, the claim for Pensions and Allowances, etc.Following on the rejection of this scheme, a number of proposals and counter-proposals were made which were eventually remitted for the meeting of the Experts referred to in the final decision, which has already been published, and which was es follows :-1..    The British and Preach Governments recognise that, on the one hand, it is to the general interest that reparation for losses and damages caused by the War should be secured as soon as possible, and that with this object in view the necessary resources should be made effectively available without delay;   and on the other hand that it is desirable that Germany should be put in a position to regain her financial autonomy by a speedy fulfilment of her obligations.8.     The two Governments are further of opinion that, in order to provide a solution for the economic difficulties which are gravely weighing upon the general situation of the world, and in order to mark a definite beginning of the era of peace, it is important to arrive at a settlement which will embrace the whole body of the International liabilities which have been left as a legacy of the War, and which will, at the same time, ensure a parallel liquidation of the Inter-Allied War Debts and of the Reparation Debts of the Central Empire.3.     Accordingly experts from each of the two countries will be charged :-(a) To prepare Immediately for examination by their two Governments proposals for fixing a minimum total for the German debt which will be capable of acceptance by the Allies and at the same time compatible with Germany&apos;s capacity to pay:(b) To determine the methods of payment and o&apos;f capitalisation of Germany&apos;s debt which will be best calculated to assure the realisation of the general views above expressed:(o)   To establish the conditions for the division between the Allies of the payments made by Ger-many in accordance with agreements which, tfa the case of certain Allied countries have already-been arrived at, and which, remain to bo dofinite-ly settled in the case of other Allied countries.
The Meeting o  --Experts will take place immediately in London, Great Britain being represented by Mr.Bleokett cf the Treasury, and France by H.Avenol.(sgd)   M.P.A.HA1MY. , Whitehall Gardens, 3. vs.,I. 17th May,,, 19SO.  .

</content>
</cab>
