<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 496-502</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL;                        No. 20    MONTHLY STATEMENT                of  Employment  of  British Vessels    on 31st DECEMBER 1919.(a)  1,600 Gross Tonnage and  over.(b)  500-1,599 Gross Tonnage.SHIPPING INTELLIGENCE SECTION (R.B.),     MINISTRY OF SHIPPING,         LONDON, S.W.1.
CONFIDENTIAL;   &quot;                   2(a)  Employment of British Vessels  of 1,600  Gros                       Excluding vessels in such employment (e.g., in the Great Lakes) as1919.									Passenger Vessels.		Cargo Vessels (Tramps and Linen	May.	June.	July.	Aug.	Sept.	Oct.	Nov.	Dec.		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage102 137 49 135 5 59 1 1 1 14 78 7 39 30 .1 209 130 86 27 1,780	107 115 32 95 4 54 1 5 84 2 20 12 1 224 148 94 32 1,878	107 94 10 83 4 45 6 75 4 4 1 146 121 102 27 2,081	97 90 9 64 5 35 59 165 150 I 92 34 2,110	72 85 9 57 4 34 1 41 1 194 149 4 87 48 2,132	58 61 10 70 T 4 23 1 1 30 1 227 156 13 111 53 2,125	35 47 10 48 4 18 2 29 237 153 16 97 49 2,201	30 46 10 41 15 17 250 108 9 100 34 2,272	I. $Requisitioned Vessels:  (excluding Wheat, see b.) (a) British : Navy -War Office -Sugar -Pyrites and Iron Ore. Other minerals and general cargoes. -1 Repairing (from Services in I., /.r., with no indi-cation of return to owner&apos;s account). .&apos;- &apos;. Australia India -Other colonies, &amp;c. France -----Italy - - - - -Other Allies, &amp;c. - - -(b) Vessels carrying Cereals and similar food stuffs for discharge in:  United Kingdom - - -France - - - - -Italy..... Other destinations -II. Vessels under notice of rcqui-sition but not yet allocated \ . to a particular Service. . III. Vessels temporarily released to I owners with an obligation to resume Government Service. TOTALS -IV. Vessels at present free from Admiralty requisition^:  $(a) Vessels trading on behalf of Allied Governments, fyc. France ..... Italy - - - - -United States -Other Allies - - - -Neutrals, &amp;c. -(b) Other Vessels not included under previous heads.* TOTALS -V. Vessels fitted for carriage of petroleum in bulk. VI. Passenger and Cargo Vessels &apos; launched and completing. t(* w J j&amp;feAND - TOTAL :1 -: -	11 31 2 9	35,612 178,239 6,799 41,618	19 15 10 6 9 24 6 17	54,96 81,98 40,571 13,77 29,07i 82,42 30,45! 81,50!									53 2 1 3 569	262,268 3,999 13,518 8,923 3,685,747	106 248. 107 9 97 34 1,703	414,78 851,72! 406,765 41,03! 376,90a 113,011 7,499,1452,891 232 57	2,908 236 57	2,911 234 69	2,911 232 61	2,918 223 73 3,214	2,944 222 70	2,946 225 - 80	2,932 230 91 3,253		628	3,974,455	2,304	9,703,3ol1 J									No. 2,932 230 91		V Tonnage. 13,677,805 1,197,434 439,740	3,180	3,201	3,214	3,204		3,236	3,251			&quot; 3,253 !&quot;		I --45,314,979*	For notes, t&amp;jKgtW&quot; -;
Tonnage  and  over  on  31st  December  1919,render them not available for ocean-going trade or requisition.ANALYSIS  OF  FREE  VESSELS  SHOWN UNDER  IV. (B).	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnago.(1) Colonial registered vessels permanently abroad:  / \ A ,. ( Passenger vessels -(a) Australia - - i r\ 1 v &apos; \ Cargo vessels -n\ ri i Passenger vessels -(o) Canada - - -^ n 0 , v &apos; ( Cargo vessels -r \ n 1 - e ( Passenger vessels (c) Other Colonies, &amp;c. \ n &amp; , v J 1 Cargo vessels - - - . -(2) \United Kingdom registered vessels trading abroad:  (a) Passenger vessels - - - - - -(b) Cargo vessels - -- -- -- -(3) Passenger vessels repairing or surveying - - - -Cargo vessels repairing or surveying (4) Other vessels (not under full requisition) :  XPassenger Liners on berth - -..... JCargo Liners loading on berth, including Tramps chartered lo Liner Cos., &amp;c. * Vessels trading for Colonies but not permanently abroad Cereals for discharge in United Kingdom - - - -Cereals for discharge in Europe, destination not determined -Ore, phosphates, lead, &amp;c, for discharge in United Kingdom Sugar, rum, nitrates, &amp;c, for discharge in United Kingdom -Oils, kernels, timber, &amp;c, for discharge in United Kingdom Timber for discharge in United Kingdom -General cargo for discharge in United Kingdom -Coasting United Kingdom...... Cable repairing and laying ------* Whaling supplies -.....--	20 85 13 33 8 34	60,810 240,628 35,230 119,275 20,670 91,779	193 1211 227 1,280$ 451	568,392 319,600 1,131,465 7,530,292 1,635,143	76 45	191,050 128,550			76 151	520,110 611,355			363 917	2,828,506 4,701,786			67 131 10 61 13 26 22 66 47 5 3	267,165 563,764 44,526 192,745 53,815 80,307 73,197 229,447 101,598 19,442 9,137									2,272	11,184,892 1                                         NOTES.   * For analysis, see page 3.   J For analysis, nee page 4.   5 To ascertain the number of vessels actually in the service of the Allies on the date of this return the number given underI. and IV&quot;. on page 2 must be included. In addition, a number of vessels shown under ore, phosphates, lead, &amp;c, under(3) on page 4 load outward for an Allied Government.  A comparison of  the numbers shown under I. and IV. for the 8 months does not therefore give an accurate criterion of the vessels in Allied service at the different peiiods.   T &quot;  Requisition &quot; is here used to mean &quot; requisition for  full Government service.&quot;   cp In &quot;Requisitioned vessels&quot; and &quot;Vessels repairing (from Services in I.) &quot; are included 100-408,156 G.T. Goverument-owned vessels, prize vessels, and time-chartered foreign vessels sailing under the British flag.0 (33) AS 7933  Pk 432 75 1/20  E&amp;S  (Sch C 56)
Detailed Analysis of Passenger  and Cargo Liners included under IV.  (b)                                       See note at foot of page 3.                                       I. To UNITED KINGDOM.                       (Including Liners discharging part cargoes in near Continental Ports.)NO. OF PASSENGER   V ESSELS.NO.   TONNAGE.NO. OF CARGO  VESSELS,NO.   TONNAGE.ROUTE.  3,648  7,081 65,380155,931764,833332,813 56,988646,481276,820 81,808 18,6682,410,45121,948 5,833 6,98413,14051,72047,41357,92345,56216,37657,86912,53.^48,73932,013418,0552.828,506 25 45 31 38 50113 76212 86 22  87061420231236 62610 9 616 J2011 1211917 31,900 13,450145,700191,050 1 44045  88,672  127,259  121,507  170,478  333,576  661,523  503,2831,102,935  418,003  101,855  15,0363,644,127 64,861103,745137,198 71,580220,919 29,541125,555 32,660 35,436 28,844 62,423  4,225104,746 30,698  5,2281,057,6594,701,786  1,775 10,280116,495128,550Egyptian Ports and ILK.Mediterranean (other than Egyptian Ports), Bay Ports, and U.K.W. Africa and U.K.S. and E. Africa and ILK.Australia and New Zealand and U.K.India and Burmah (up to and including Rangoon) and U.K.Straits (including Singapore and Java) and Far East and  ILK.N. America (including Canada and Gulf) and ILK.S. America (Atlantic) and U.K.West Coast N. and S. America and U.K.Scandinavia and U.K.Total.II. To  COUNTRIES  OTHER THAN UNITED KINGDOM.ROUTE.Mediterranean and Bay Ports, and N. America (including Canada and Gulf).Africa (W., S. &amp; E.) and N. America (including Canada and Gulf).India and Burmah (up to and including Rangoon) and N. America (including CanadaJ  Gulf).                                                                  [Australia and New Zealand and N. America East Coast (including Canada and Gulf)!Straits (including Singapore and Java) and Far East and N. America, E. and W. COALIndia and S. America (Atlantic and Pacific).N. America and S. America.Australia and New Zealand and West Coast N. and S. America.India and South and East Africa.India and Australia.India and Far East.India and Egyptian and Mediterranean Ports.Indian Coastal Trade.N. America and  Canada and Central A.meiica.Australia and Egyptian Ports.Total.Grand Total.Ill-OTHER UNITED KINGDOM  REGISTERED VESSELS  TRADING  ABROJAREA OF TRADING ROUTES.In Australian Seas.In American (including Canadian) Seas.In other Seas (principally Indian, Chinese, and Java Seas).Total.
COMPARATIVE  STATEMENTS.(1) COMPARISON BETWEEN BRITISH TONNAGE JULY 1914 AND 31ST DECEMBER 1919.	No. of Vessels.	Tonnage.		No of Vessels.	Tonnage.July 1914 -Add :-Launched -Transferred from foreign flags and other causes. Prizes - - - -Alterations to gross tonnage (net gain). Totals	4,068 1,286 366 144	17,516,876 6,038,257 1,493,284. 611,778 219,423	Deduct:  War losses -Vessels interned in enemy ports or captured. Marine losses Transferred to foreign flags and other causes. Totals	1,775 283 553	7,424,190 1,042.308 2,098,141	5,864	25,879,618		2,611	10,564,639 -Position 31st Decemher 1919 = 3,253 of 15,314,979 tons.(2) COMPARISON BETWEEN MONTHLY  NET REDUCTION OR INCREASE IN VESSELS AVAILABLE FOR                       TRADE OR REQUISITION (excluding Oilers).January 1919.	February 1919.	March 1919.	April 1919.	May 1919.	June 1919.	July 1919.	August 1919.	September 1919.	October 1919.	November 1919.	December 1919.Gain 28	Gain 13	Loss 19	Nil	Gain I	Gain 17	Gain 15	Loss 10	19	Gain 23	Gain 12	Loss 3The alterations during December 1919 were as follows:                                   Additions.                                   Deductions.Launched -    -    -    -    -    -   -32    Marine loss     ------   4Transfers from Foreign flags and other causes   2    Transferred to foreign flags and other causes   33Net loss......       337                                          37(3) COMPARISON BETWEEN MONTHLY NUMBER OF REQUISITIONED VESSELS  FOR ARMY,  NAVY, AND                       ALLIES (excluding Wheat, Sugar, Ore, and Oilers).January 1919.	February 1919.	March 1919.	April 1919.	May 1919.	June 1919.	July 1919.	August 1919.	-September 1919.	October 1919.	November 1919.	December 1919.843	870	652	481	400	345	301	265	233	193	131	117(4) COMPARISON BETWEEN MONTHLY TOTAL FIGURE OF BRITISH VESSELS, 1,600 GROSS TONS AND OVER (including vessels launched and completing but excluding Oilers).											January 1919.	February 1919.	March 1919.	April 1919.	May 1919.	June 1919.	July 1919.	August 1919.	September 1919.	October 1919.	November 1919.	December 1919.2,953	2,966	2,947	2,947	2,948	2,965	2,980	2,972	2,991	3,014	3,026	3,023
()(b) Employment  of British Vessels of 500-	Passenger. Vessels.		Cargo Vessels. (Tramps, Cargo Liners, and Coasters.)		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.I. Requititioned vessels:  British : Navy -War Office..... Other munitions and general cargo Repairing india ------France - - - - - - -Other Allies ------IT. Vessels under notice of requisition but not yet allocated to a particular service. 111. Vessels temporarily released to owners with an obligation to resume Government service. f.V. Vessels at present free from requisition:  (a) Vessels trading on behalf of Allied Govern-ments, fyc.:  France -Italy - -..... Other Allies ------Neutrals, &amp;c. - - - - -. (&amp;) Other vessels not included under previous heads* Total - - - -V. Vessels fitted for carriage of petroleum in bulk -VI. Passenger and cargo vessels launched and completing GRAND TOTAL -	9 4 2 6 3 2 162	6,673 4,502 2,030 6,661 2,494 2,879 171,193	23 6 1 1 1 216 2 49 17 463	21,791 4,751 882 754 884 199,926 2,103 45,127 20,708 464,476	188	196,432	779	761,402 *	No. 967 7 12		V Tonnage. 957,834 7,142 14,383		986		979,359	* For analysis, tee page 7.
1,599 Gross Tonnage on 31st December 1919.ANALYSIS OF FREE VESSELS SHOWN UNDER IV. (b). 					No.	Gross Tonnage.	Total.								No.	Gross Tonnage.^1) Colonial registered vessels permanently abroad:  ,\ A ,. 1 Passenger vessels &apos; -(a) Australia i n 0 , v &apos; \ Cargo vessels...... n , Passenger vessels -(0) banana - i n 0 , v &apos; \ Cargo vessels ------( \ OtVi 1 Passenger vessels &quot; ( Cargo vessels ------					10 41 7 35 1 36	10,716 42,169 8,298 37,923 926 41,171	130 66 60 85 264 20	141,203 65,701 62,676 90,442 252,645 23,002(2) United. Kingdom registered vessels trading abroad :  / \ . ,. &quot;( Passenger vessels..... (a) Australia I n * , v &apos; ( Cargo vessels...... ,IN r. , Passenger vessels -----(b) Canada - ) Cargo ^ ...... / * 1 ( Passenger vessels - -(c) Other - j CargQ -esgels...... 3) Passenger vessels repairing, fyc, or laid up -Cargo vessels repairing, fyc., or laid up -					6 4 9 15 32	6,610 5,125 9,596 16illl 28,259							21 39	23,509 39,167										-	Passenger.		Cargo.		Total.				NTo.	Gross Tonnage.	No.	Gross Tonnage.	No.	Gross Tonnage.		(4) Liners on berth (excluding regular coasting lines):  U.K.-Med. U.K.-Holland -U.K.-W.C. Africa ILK. Norway -U.K.-Channel Islands and !N&quot;. France. (5) Coasting (including regular coasting lines and Miscel-laneous coasting vessels). l[6) Miscellaneous cargoes from overseas for discharge in U.K.:-Pitwood - - -Whale oil General (including timber other than pit-wood). Pyrite3 and iron ore	16 1 13	18,289 1,143 11,920	12 21 6 12 4	12,832 20,446 8,265 14,786 2,761	12 37 6 13 17	12,832 38,735 8,265 15,929 14,681			74	75,156	190	177,489	264	252,645			 	 -	2 1 12 4 1	2,052 1,105 14,995 4,313 537	2 1 12 4 1	2,052 1,105 14,995 4,313 537							1	k	625	635,669

</content>
</cab>
