<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 520-524</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENT.SECRET.THE  CABINET.EVACUATION  OF  THE BALTIC  PROVINCES BY GERMAN                                TROOPS.01544908      MEMORANDUM BY  THE SECRETARY  OF  STATE FOR  WAR.    I circulate to my colleagues a report from Brigadier-General A. J. Turner, C.M.G.,D.S.O.,  Commanding  the  British Military  Mission, Tilsit, on the conduct of theGermans  in  evacuating the  Baltic  Provinces,  enclosing  reports  on the insultingbehaviour of a German officer towards a British officer in the performance of his duty.    The Foreign Office have informed the War Office  that  the  Supreme  Council hascalled the  attention  of the German Government to the acts  of violence committedagainst officers of the Mission,  which necessitate the punishment of the offenders..WINSTON  S./CHURCHILL.THE WAB OFFICE.      30th January. 1920.  To the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, from Brigadier- General A. J. Turner,                                C.M.G., D.S.O.Sir,    1. I  have  the honour   to  submit the  following  supplementary report.   Theevacuation of the German forces is now nearing completion, and though you have been kept informed of the  progress of events by my interim reports, I consider it advisable to give you at this juncture some general impressions with reference to  the evacuationand the general situation in East Prussia.    2. The Baltic adventure  has been entirely controlled and planned by the military party. The German War Office,  the Reichswehr Commander at Konigsberg, and theVlth Corps Commander at Tilsit are  all thoroughly implicated.  Bermondt has been a mere puppet.   Their object has probably been threefold :     (i.) To show the  German people the impotence of the  Supreme Council, and the           complete indifference of the Military Party towards orders from the Allies.    (ii.) To make a German colony in Courland, or in any case to embarrass the Allies           in their settlement of the  Baltic Provinces.   (iii.) To have ready a striking force at hand to upset the Government.    o. The ostensible reason that of fighting Bolshevism was merely a red herringacross  the trail to deceive their  own people in  Prussia, to gain  the  support of thegullible Russian Party at Berlin, and to help their intrigues in Russian affairs generally.How successful they have been in  this  is clear to anyone who has been in touch withany of the leading Russians in Berlin, even those of Entente sympathy.    4. When the Commission first arrived the  general  attitude  of all the  MilitaryCommands towards Bermondfs force was one of  complete detachment.  Bermondfstroops were no longer  regarded  as  German; they  had  refused to  obey orders,  andhowever regrettable such lack of discipline might be, it was no longer any concern ofthe German  Command.  Then  came  the successful Lettish  offensive, and unlessBermondfs  troops were reinforced, there was  every  possibility  of their  beingannihilated.  This was not at all the intention of the German Military Party.   Theonly way in which they could have any right to send them formed detachments was for    (B20/76) 100  1/20 H&amp;S  7900WO
Bermondt to submit his  troops to German authority, which was accordingly done onthe 16th November.  One was at first inclined to regard this change of attitude as dueto the presence of the Commission, but I am convinced that, though this may have beena factor, it was not the reason for such a  complete alteration in the situation as tookplace within 24 hours.  The immediate departure of General von Eberhardt, the  corps commander at Tilsit, to take over the command of a very critical military situation wasthe first result of the change.  It was clear that unless the  Commission restrained theLetts and  the Lithuanians the latter now showing a strong desire  to t;ike part Eberhardt  would   require  reinforcements.   General  von  Nebefs  detachment  thenarrived  at Tilsit,   bound for  the  scene  of  hostilities.   The Commission,  however,prevented its crossing the frontier,  but at the same time promised to do all it  could toensure a safe evacuation of the German troops by rail.   The  Commission, by the intervention of its  Control Officers, managed to break off the  combat and tried to induce the  Lithuanians  to respect  the  previous  line  of dernarkation (arranged  betweenLithuania and General von  Eberhardt on 31st October); but it  became  obvious thatthe Lithuanians could not be held back.     5.  This  brought about on  the  24th  of  November the offer by Germany  of an armistice between  the Germans  and Lithuanians, by which  an unhindered evacuationwas  guaranteed in exchange for the handing over of all military stores and a sufficiencyof rolling stock.  A time limit was given for acceptance, failing which reinforcementswould be sent.  The time limit was such  that, owing  to delay in the delivery of the telegram, no answer from the Lithuanian Government could  be received  iu time.   Theoffer was not really an honest one,  but was made merely to  thrust the onus of furthermilitary intervention on the  Lithuanians.   This, however,  was prevented by theimmediate  acceptance of the offer by the Commission on behalf of Lithuania.     6.  Colonel Dosse, who represented  the  Commission at General von Eberhardt&apos;headquarters, where the  German  delegates  were, made various arrangements inaccordance with the policy of the Commission :      (i.) The evacuation  to  be carried out by  rail and  completed by  the 13th the           Germans having asked for six weeks.     (ii.) Allied Control Officers to supervise  the evacuation  and see no stores in depots           were removed.  ,   (iii.) No  pillage, looting or disturbance to take place, and all requisitions to be paid           for.     7.  It became  evident at a very early date that, except for the evacuation of troops,General von  Eberhardt  had  not the slightest intention of carrying out his obligations.Stores  were openly withdrawn,  sometimes destroyed in situ.   The whole country waspillaged and  devastated.  Remonstrance  was useless,  the  only answer made wasthat the troops were out of hand.  The Allied officers were treated with  every kind ofdisrespect, threatened with violence, and,  being prevented  from  carrying  out their duties, were rendered entirely useless as a control.   In this respect I attach a copy of a document,  Appendix I.,  describing a gross insult to a British officer in the performance of his duty, on the part of a German officer and entirely without provocation.  I trustthe British Government will not let the matter  rest until the German officer is dulypunished.     8.  Meanwhile the evacuation  was proceeding slowly every train was filled withloot, war material, stolen horses  and cattle our protestations were useless.  Then cameindications that the Iron Division were not unlikely to proceed by march route so as togive them  every chance to pillage the country.   A  written  undertaking was obtainedfrom General von  Eberhardt that such would not be the case and that the Iron division would be sent down by rail.  This undertaking, like every other,  was  in due  coursebroken by von Eberhardt and two-thirds of the Iron Division finally marched to Memelby three columns,  so as to give them every opportunity to- carry out  their fell purpose.The flimsy excuse  for this move  was the danger of the Letts interfering with the with-drawal  by railway between  Murajievo and  Shavli, for which there was no cause, as theLettish troops were in hand and their Commander was carrying out loyally the wishes of the Commission in spite of great provocation.     9.  General von Eberhardt, while never losing an opportunity of drawing  attentionto what he pleases to call his military honour, has proved himself to be a person who is entirely devoid of any scruples or good faith.   His complete neglect of the safety of theAllied officers entrusted  to his charge deserves the strongest condemnation.    The lackof any effort to prevent the atrocities  committed  by the  troops under his  command
    * Neisse is on the border of a plebiscite area aud Memel iu the future does not form part of theGerman Empire.  That such locations are intended to embarrass the future action of the Allies cannot be doubted, and if the Iron Division remains at Memel, The Supreme Council can with every confidence look forward to future trouble.    (7noo)\ merits  his  inclusion among the number whose  personal misdeeds are to become  the subject of investigation.  The withdrawal by road of the Iron Division is a characteristic example  of his bad faith.   The move had  commenced forty-eight  hours  before he informed us, and the incidents he brought forward as a pretext for the move took place after the troops had been set in motion.     10. The evacuation of the Baltic Provinces has  been effected, but  to say that  the Mission has been a success would  deceive no one.  This has not been  the fault  of  the Mission, but is a result of the policy of the  Supreme Council which has consistently refused to give the Mission any other weapon but the moral weight of its presence.  The whole country, according to reports of  the Allied Control  Officers,  has been entirely devastated, all live stock removed and the inhabitants systematically  robbed and illtreated.  The peasants have been left without the means  of tilling  their fields, and measures of relief will  be necessary without delay.  Further, reparation for  the gross insults  to Allied officers, the entire lack of faith on the  part of the Germans in breaking their agreement, and the return of a sufficiency of rolling-stock to  both Latvia and Lithuania for economic needs,  are  matters which require immediate  attention.  This latter point has been carefully investigated by a Special Railway  Commission  appointed by us, and the precise amount to be handed over has  been decided.   It is absolutely necessary, both from a  point of view of policy  and for the  necessities of the countries concerned, that immediate reparation be made.  To  leave this to be settled by  the Peace Reparation  Committee is perfectly futile.   The return of a fixed quantity of horses, cattle and  rolling stock, and a heavy  immediate  fine  and- punishment for   crimes committed,  should be insisted on forthwith ; and unless  this is done the German Military Party will realize that  the  Allies  will  permit them to laugh at the  conditions of  the Peace Treaty, and difficulties of a like nature will continue to  arise in all the plebiscite areas.     11. East Prussia does not realize that  Germany has lost the war.  The Military Party is all  powerful and militarism in all  its forms is rampant.   Personally  I have little doubt  of the plot  to overthrow the  Government at the  opportune moment, or of the power of the Military Party to do so.   They are simply waiting for the time when the Peace shall have been ratified and the whole onus of it can be thrown on the present Government.   Propaganda  encouraging  militarism  is  being disseminated everywhere, especially by the Ober President of East Prussia, Herr Winning, and takes the  form, of anti-Bolshevism, the Germans having stated that all Latvians and  Lithuanians are Bolshevists, and by this pretence they  are  hoping to maintain a  large army  in East Prussia.  At the same time there is strong reason to believe that the Germans  are aiding the Bolsheviks in Lithuania both by propaganda  and distribution of  arms.   To throw dust in our  eyes the number of Reichswehr troops will not be excessive, but with all the forms of  Einwohnerwehr Truppen,  Sicherheit Truppen, and  Grenzschutz Truppen, a considerable  army, the numbers  of which it  is quite  impossible  to  discover,  will be available.  Konigsberg is the  centre of  all  activities, here the General  Commanding, von Estoff, is an effete old man, merely a  figurehead, and the  situation is controlled by his Chief of  Staff, Colonel von Burkner, a veritable monumental example of Prussianjunkerdom in its highest and most concentrated form.   The proposed distribution of the troops from  the Baltic Provinces is as follows :-     Bermondfs Russians to  Neisse,  and  the  German  contingent  to Slade  (near          Hanover).   The Iron Division,  however, has marched  to Memel and  unless-          pressure is put on the  German Government it is likely  to stay there,    The          selection of both Mernel and Neisse  is curious from  the point of view of         future location of Allied troops when ratification  takes  place.*   As a police         force, if conditions do not change, I consider the proposed  strength  of the          Allied garrison of the Memel  district  to be inadequate,  and if it cannot be         suitably increased it will be useless and may be a source of anxiety.     12.  As regards  the Russian  troops,  only a very small proportion  was consideredsuitable for  action with anti-Bolshevik forces supported by the Allies, and it is  hopedthat  the Allied governments will arrange for their support and transfer : the matter hasbeen placed  in the hands  of  General Malcolm.   The remainder are worthless, and  areonly useful  to the Germans for further propaganda.   Their leaders are men  of  straw,
without any conscience or scruples.  The Supreme War  Council  has  been asked  toensure that neither Bermondt nor his troops leave Germany to join Denikin.     13. General Niessel  has  proved himself a  man of  exceptional  ability,  with awonderful  memory and of  great  eloquence ;  he is a man of  decision,  but jumps  to conclusions.   He  suffers,  however, from his  qualities and  his eloquence at  timesprevents him from adhering  to essentials.   He  has been uniformly  courteous to a degree to all members of the Mission and it has been a pleasure to work with him.     14. For Admiral Hopmann, the head of the German delegates, I have nothing butadmiration.  He has throughout acted straight, with candour and yet firmness towards us, but he has had to play a lone hand.    The Military Chiefs have  uniformly kept himbadly informed and have  entirely  disregarded the full powers  entrusted to him by hisGovernment.     15. Finally, I wish to draw the attention of the authorities to the present state ofaffairs in Prussia.     I hope 1 am not an alarmist, but  unless  the Allies take  stronger measures  toenforce  respect  to  their decisions serious trouble may be expected.  The only  thingrespected is the  thick stick.   The anaemic attitude of the Supreme  Council  in entirelyfailing to enforce its decisions has caused it to become the subject of derision amongstthe German military.   East Prussia is  not tired  of war.   At present  it is enrichedwith all the horses, cattle  and  spoil of Latvia  and Lithuania.   Nowhere in the world to-day  are there  more horses  than  in  this  neighbourhood notwithstanding  the&apos;considerable number we see  despatched  by train to the interior  of Germany.  Unlessswift and adequate retribution is insisted upon for all the misdeeds in the Baltic states to show the military party the game is  not worth the  candle, the Baltic  trouble will prove itself to be only  the first act  of  a  well thought-out policy  which aims at  there-establishment of monarchy and militarism  which  will ever  prevent the peace ofEurope being on a firm basis.                                          A. J. TUKNER, Brigadier-General,                                                           Allied Baltic Mission.   Tilsit,     9th December, 1919.
APPENDIX  I.                                                 I.      To General Vincent, Commission Jor the evacuation of the Baltic Provinces, from Lieutenant Geoffrey                          E. Lloyd Wilson, Army Cyclist Corps, British Army.Sir,    I have the honour to inform you that on the night of the 23rd November about 1 o&apos;clock in the morning1,a train stopped at the station of Tilsit.   Amongst the passengers on this train was a detachment of Germansoldiers of  the  34th Squadron with  their  aeroplanes,  motors  and  material complete, commanded  byLieutenant Knedel.  Having been informed that the German liaison officer would be waiting for me  on the platform, and as I did not know him, I addressed  myself  to an  officer who was at  that moment talking tosome German soldiers, asking him if he was the liaison  officer.   This officer immediately answered me in an extremely insulting  manner  and having roundly cursed  me, finally ordered me to clear off the platform.   Iwent to the other end of the train  hoping to find the liaison officer.   Lieutenant Knedel followed me withhis men and grasping my shoulder ordered me again to clear off the platform immediately, at the same time he spat on me. He seemed quite mad.   As he had with  him his soldiers and I had only a French orderly Iretired to the Commission^ Office where I waited for the German  liaison officer.   I told the orderly whoaccompanied me to remain on the platform and to see that the train did not  leave the station without myhaving  examined it.  About twenty minutes later the orderly returned saying that Lieutenant Knedel had ordered the platform to be cleared and  that the same lieutenant was placing machine guns on the line.Later Lieutenant Knedel  refused  to  leave  the  machine  guns at  Tilsit  and  again spoke and acted in aninsupportable  manner.                   i               I have the honour to be, &amp;c,                                                       GBOPFKEY  B. LLOYD WILSON, Lieutenant,                                                                  Army Cyclist Corps,                                                Attached to the Commission for the evacuation of the                                                                   Baltic Provinces.  Tilsit,.       3rd December, 1919.                                                 II.    1. I demand that  severe  action should be  taken against Lieutenant Knedel, 34th  German AviationSquadrcn.  It is necessary that the Commission should be informed of the actions taken, so that the Officersof Control should feel themselves protected.   I find it useless to underline  the seriousness of this  insultagainst officers of the Entente who are unarmed and whose behaviour is an example of correctness.    2. The machine guns on  the train had to be left as Lieutenant Knedel  himself declared they did notbelong to his squadron.  Lieutenant Knedel refused to do it.                                                                  General VINCENT (French Army).  Tilsit,      4th December, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
