<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 564-565</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENT.351   CP. 549I P^^^^/y                THE CABINET.NSgflALL          DISPOSAL  OF CANTEEN PROFITS AND CONSTITUTIONOF  THE UNITED  SERVICES FUND.Gen. No.  2223&quot;       MEMORANDUM BY THE  SECRETARY  OF STATE FOR  WAR.    1.  The machinery for carrying  out  the  scheme for administering the CanteenProfits  (G.T.  7595), which  was approved in  principle by  the  Cabinet in  July  last(W.C. 598(7)  has not been found, in the light of experience, such as to ensure smoothworking, and  is not adapted to the special problems with which  the  United ServicesFund has to deal.    2.  The Admiralty have  not yet decided whether they will place the  administrationof the Navy&apos;s share of Canteen Profits in the hands of the United Services Fund, butthey are negotiating with Lord Byng on the subject.    3.  Lord  Byng, after conference with the principal ex-service  associations, has proposed the  following modifications of the scheme  to which I  have given approvalsubject to the Cabinet&apos;s covering sanction :      (i.)  A single Council of Management should take the place of the Central Council           and Board of Management originally proposed.             (a.) Its Chairman should be nominated by the Crown on the advice of                   the  Prime Minister, but the Crown  should  have no  power  of                   removal.             (b.) It should consist of 15 members (appointed for a  limited  term and                   with power to co-opt three additional members) nine  from the                   three  principal   existing   societies  of  ex-service  men,  three                   nominated  by the  Chairman to represent ex-service  men not                   members of the existing Societies of ex-service men, and three                   women nominated by a women&apos;s sub-committee to be formed.     (ii.) Area and District Committees  composed  of ex-service, representatives, the           Chairman  of the Area Committee  to be nominated or  approved  by the           Chairman of the Council of Management.     (iii.) The beneficiaries  of the Fund  to be ex-service  officers and  men  and  their           dependents, not to  be  confined to  those who served during the recent war,           but not to include those now serving.         In  order that the  Fund should not be applied for political or similar purposes,           provision  is made that none of  the money is  to go to any Association           represented on the Committee.     (iv.) The &quot;United Services Fund&quot;  to be  independent of, and not responsible to,           any Government Department.     4. This  scheme differs from that  approved  by the Cabinet  in the following principles:      (i.) Serving officers and men cease to be beneficiaries of the Fund, and responsibility           for their welfare in this respect reverts to the departments  concerned (*.e.,           the War Office  and the Air Ministry).    (ii.) The Army Council and the Air  Council are  to have no responsibility for and           are not to nominate the Council of Management;  in the original scheme the           Service Departments were  to  nominate eighteen  out of thirty members of           the Central Council.    (iii.) The composition of the new Council of Management gives a majority of places           to the principal war organizations of ex-service men and  no representation           to  such pre-war  organizations  as  the  Soldiers&apos;  and  Sailors&apos; Families&apos;           Association.     (B20/78) 100 2/20 H&amp;S  7902wo
     5. The Fund will thus be administered by representatives of its  beneficiaries, andits Council of Management Mall contain no official or financial authority  outside theirranks.     6. As the Fund is to be independent of the War Office and the Air Ministry, andin view of questions in Parliament, the problem of Ministerial responsibility arises.  Inthe meantime  the Secretary  of State for War is undertaking this duty, and to thisLord Byng raises  no  objection  as a  temporary  expedient,  but as a permanentarrangement it  is  most desirable that  some neutral Minister should  assume  this responsibility,  and I suggest that this  Minister might  appropriately  be  the FinancialSecretary  to the Treasury.                                               WINSTON  S. CHURCHILL.&apos;THE WAR  OFFICE,           2nd February, 1920.4

</content>
</cab>
