<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 589-594</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
    IN the absence of Lord Curzon, I circulate the attached statement on the negotia-tions now in progress at Copenhagen for an exchange1 of British and Russian prisonerswhich has been prepared in the Foreign Office.                                            HARDINGE OF PENSHURST.
-/fl[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.)&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;SI376Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1920.SECRET.The Negotiations at Copenhagen between Mr. 0&apos;Grady,  M.P., and M. Litvinoff  for the Exchange of British and Russian Prisoners of War and Civilians.    HIS Majesty&apos;s  Government have  been negotiating  for  months  past  with theSoviet  Government  for  the  repatriation of the British  prisoners of Avar  in  Russiaand for the release of those British civilians who are either detained by the SovietGovernment or otherwise prevented from leaving that country.    These  negotiations  were during the  summer carried on by wireless  messagesbetween the respective Governments, but the Soviet Government refused to continuethem  except after  a  meeting  with a British  representative.   After considerabledifficulty it was arranged that this meeting should take place in Denmark, and on the24th November, M.  Litvinoff reached Copenhagen  to confer with Mr. 0&apos;Grady, whohad been sent on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government.    As soon as  the negotiations  opened, it became clear that M, Litvinoff would not besatisfied with a mere  exchange of Russians in  England and British in Russia.  his first  proposal was that His  Majesty&apos;s Government should not  only  release russian prisoners and civilians in this country, but should give certain guarantees for removingall obstacles in the way of the return to their country of all Soviet Russian nationals in Great Britain,  Archangel,  Murmansk,  Caucasus, and Caspian  districts,  Persia,India, Germany, Austria, and the  neutral countries of Europe.  As to the Russians inEngland, he admitted that&apos; he was indifferent whether they remained here or returnedhome.  Mr.  0&apos;Grady was at  once  instructed definitely to reject any  arrangement bywhich  the repatriation of the British in Russia should be  made dependent  on there patriation  of  Russians  in  countries  outside British  jurisdiction, and as  a result offurther discussions the negotiations were broken off by M. Litvinoff  because the SovietGovernment were  unable  to permit their  continuation on a purely Russo-Britishbasis.    On doing so M. Litvinoff issued a press communique, which was so worded thathe gave the impression  that he  would be content with less than he had first required,and  Mr.  0&apos;Grady was accordingly  instructed  to make  a further attempt  to find  asatisfactory solution.    His  Majesty&apos;s Government have since made  very considerable concessions, andthe only remaining points on which an agreement has not been reached are     1.  The claim  of  the  Soviet   G overnment.  to  have  a representative   on  the           International Commission for the repatriation of  Russian prisoners of war           in Germany, should  such a Commission eventually be constituted.    2. The release by the Archangel Government of certain Soviet prisoners in their           hands.     As regards 1,  His Majesty&apos;s  Government are unable to do more than support theSoviet contention should&apos; the Commission ma;  rialise, which is doubtful.     As regards 2,  His  Majesty&apos;s Government  have been in communication with theArchangel Government for the release of certain of these prisoners whose names were submitted by M. Litvinoff.   These prisoners can in no way be considered under Britishjurisdiction now, whether they were originally captured by British troops or not;  but his  Majestys Government  have  used  their good offices in the matter, and with thefollowing result:  General Miller is willing to release certain of these prisoners as soonas they can be  identified and provided that they wish to return to Soviet Russia, buthe in turn requires the release of certain &quot; White &quot; prisoners  in the hands of the SovietGovernment.       [2200]                                                           B
     This contention is perfectly legitimate, in view of the fact that when he himselfattempted to arrange an exchange the Soviet  Government refused to &quot; negotiate withrebels.&quot;  M. Litvinoff, when the matter of these  &quot;White&quot;  officers was raised, stated,on the other hand, that, it was entirely a matter for  the &quot;Reds&quot;  and the &quot;Whites.&quot;M. LitvinofFs attitude is totally unreasonable.   If his Government refuses to negotiate with Archangel  and expects  His Majesty&apos;s Government to obtain the  release of theSoviet adherents  in the  hands of General Miller, it is impossible for us to entertainM. LitvinofFs suggestion that we have no locus standi in the matter of the &quot; White &quot;officers.     If, on the other hand, the Soviet Government are prepared to effect an  exchangewith Archangel they should say so, and conduct separate negotiations for this purpose,a course of  action which would be  welcomed  by  His Majesty&apos;s  Government  asnarrowing the scope of Mr. 0&apos;Grady&apos;s discussions.     Tt is clearly an obligation of  honour for His Majesty&apos;s  Government to  secure therelease of these &quot; White &quot; officers if they are themselves to obtain any advantages fromthe release of the &quot; Reds &quot; at Archangel.     A draft agreei: ient has been prepared on these lines, and if  M. Litvinoff is stillunwilling to accept the numerous concessions herein outlined, it  is for  consideration whether (1) His Majesty&apos;s Government  should instruct Mr.  0&apos;Grady to break off thenegotiations, or  (2) publish the terms  of the proposed contract and give the  SovietGovernment five days&apos;  grace in which to consider the  question.  The first alternative would, of course, be an exceedingly grave step, as there would be no obvious method ofsecuring  the repatriation of the British in Russia.
3377                                   Enclosure.  Draft  Agreement  between His Majesty&apos;s Government  and  the  Soviet            Government of Russia for the Exchange of Prisoners.    THE British Government and  the Russian Soviet Government, being desirous of effecting an exchange of combatant  and civilian prisoners and others and of facilitating the return of their nationals respectively,  have agreed as follows :                  ARTICLE  1. Repatriation of Russian Combatants.    The British Government will  repatriate  all  Russian combatant  prisoners in theBritish  Empire or in any  territory over which  the  British  Government  at presentexercises direct authority.                  ARTICLE 2. Repatriation of Russian Civilians.    The British&quot; Government will repatriate all Russian civilians in the British Empireor in  any territory where  the British Government exercises direct authority, whetherthey are at liberty, interned, or imprisoned, who are willing to return to Russia.               ARTICLE 3. Repatriation of certain specified Russians.    The provisions of Articles 1 and 2 will apply to Russians captured in the  Caucasusor the Caspian and in Persia whose names, so far as they can  be identified, appear  ona list of such persons submitted by  the Soviet Government to the British Government.               ARTICLE 4. Repatriation of Russians from Archangel.    The British Government undertakes, subject to  the  provisions  of Article 8, tosecure the delivery to the Soviet Government  of the Russian  combatant prisoners and civilian  officials who are in the custody  of the Archangel Government and who havebeen captured  at any  time since  the landing of the British  forces in  North Russia.This undertaking will  apply to all  those  whose  release  is  desired by  the SovietGovernment and who themselves desire to leave  the territory under the control of theArchangel Government.  This undertaking will include also the persons whose namesappear on the list already submitted by the Soviet Government, which list is set out in annex (A) to this Agreement, in so far as they can be identified.                        ARTICLE  5. Transport Facilities.    The British Government undertakes to provide transport facilities for all personswho will be repatriated in accordance with the provisions of Articles 1, 2, and 3 of thisAgreement.    The British Government further undertakes to render  every possible assistance,so far as sea transport is  concerned, if it should become necessary to do no, for there patriation of Russian nationals who are at present  either  prisoners in  or who areunable to leave Denmark, Holland, Belgium, and Switzerland.   This undertaking is subject  to the conclusion by the Soviet Government of agreements with the  Govern-ments of the above-mentioned States  for the repatriation of the persons concerned.!    The British  Government  further undertakes  to  make  representations to theGovernments of the Baltic States for the granting of the necessary facilities for the safeconveyance of  all persons who are  to be repatriated in accordance with the provisionsof the foregoing Articles.            ARTICLE 6. Proposed International Comrhission in Berlin.    In  the event of the establishment of an International Commission in Berlin forthe repatriation of Russian prisoners of war in Germany, the British  Governmentundertakes to support,  so far  as it  lies within its power to do so, the claims of theSoviet Government to be represented on  such a Commission and to have equal  rights    [2200]              &apos;                                                 C
with other members of the Commission.   These rights are understood to include com-nxunication with the Soviet Government by their representative and  the making ofarrangements  with the  Commission  for  the  speedy  repatriation  of  those russian prisoners of war at present in Germany who desire to return to Soviet Russia.                  ARTICLE 7. Repatriation of British Prisoners.     The Soviet Government will repatriate all British combatants and civilian prisoners and all other British nationals at present in Soviet Russia who wish to return to any portion of the British Empire.      ARTICLE 8. Repatriation of Russian Combatants of the Archangel Forces.   &apos;  In return for the undertaking given by the British Government in Article 4 above to secure the delivery to the Soviet Government of those nationals captured  in north russia, whose names  appear in Annex (A), the  Soviet  Government on its  part  willreturn to the  Archangel Government all officers, doctors, and military clerks of the5th North Rifle Regiment and the 2nd Battalion of the Artillery Division captured onthe Onega who wish  to return to North Russia.  This undertaking  includes those persons whose names appear on the  list  contained in Annex iB) to this  Agreement.Arrangements  for this exchange  of  prisoners  will be  subsequently arrived at bymeans of direct communications between the military authorities on the spot.                     ARTICLE  9. Operation of this Agreement.     Notwithstanding any delay which may take place before the putting into force ofthe arrangements  contemplated in Articles 4, 5,  6, and  8, the  British  and  soviet governments respectively undertake to carry out  the provisions of Articles 1,2, 3, and7 immediately after the signing of the Agreement.                   Signed on behalf of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government:Signed on behalf of the Russian Soviet Government:
                   ANNEX (A). 1.  KRIVENKO, Ivan. 2.  GULIAEFF, Andrew. 3.  LEVATCHEV, Nikifor. 4.  IVANOVSKY. 5.  BLOCHIN. -6.  MASSORIN. 7.  KLEVER, Ian. 8.  TEMESJNIKOV. 9.  AKSENOV.10.  PEELOVSKY.11.  OLUNIN, Porfiriy.12.  VARAKIN, Peter.13.  TCHERTOV, G-avriil.14.  EDEMSKY, Diraitri.15.  OKTJNEV, Michail Alexandrowitch.16.  BYSOV,  Ivan Aadrianovitch.  .17.  MOROSOV, Alexandre Fokitch.18.  BARSUGIN, Alexey Ivanowitch.19.  PODSHIVALOV, Grigory Hitch.20.  MICHAILOV, Alexey Alexandrowitch.21.  LISSKOV, Peter Alexewitch.22.  HECHOTCHEV, Ivan Grigoriewitch.23.  RUMIN, Andrey Ivonowitch.24.  GORONTCHAROVSKY, Egor.25.  PADORIN, Ivan Petrowitch.26.  MARTUSHOY, Vasiliy Hitch.                   ANNEX (B). 1. Colonel MIKHEIEPF. 2. Captain MATZIEVSKY (Assistant to Colonel Mikheieff). 3. Captain KLAVE  (CO. of the 1st Battalion). 4. Captain SOLOVSKY (CO. of the Battery). 5. Major BOLDYREFF (Chief of the Regimental Staff). 6. Captain SALATKO-PETRISTSHEFF (5th Regiment). 7. Lieutenant EVSEIEFF (5th Regiment). 8. Lieutenant NOYIKOFF (5th Regiment). 9. 2nd Lieutenant MAKHNOFF.10. The Regimental  Priest, SIBIRTSEFF.o

</content>
</cab>
