<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 736-741</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-rantULS  BJLX&apos;       )                 RKPORT OK VISIT TO IRKLAOT/ JARUAKY 1920                         (circulated for Information).        The places I  Visited were Belfast, Lame,Bailycaetle, Antrim,  Newcastle, Donaghadee, Bangor,Dublin and Blaokrock.        As the Municipal  Elections  took place onJanuary 15th,  I had an opportunity  cf seeing Irianelection methods,  and the proportional Representa-tion scheme at work.        Irish people take considerably more interestin their elections than we do  on&apos;this side; but agreat deal of personation and  other  illegal practicestake place.        Proportional Representation appears to be avery cumbersome and expensive system,  and far toointricate for the average elector.   Mr. A.W. Hunderfordof the Old Town Hall, Belfast,  Ytoo  was in charge ofthe Unionist organisation!  can confirm this opinion and furnish information, on the subject,  capitalmay be made out of the fact that the Unionist partylost a number of seats in Ulster at the  election; butit is the opinion of the leading Unionists in Belfastthat little political significance  can be attachedto these  elections, and that at the,next electionUnionists will regain their position^      k  In Ulster,  I interviewed a  very largenumber of people,  including Members of parliament,Aldermen, Councillors,  pressmen,  prominent businessmen, officials of the Unionist  party,, leaders of the orange Order, and many  working  men.        I was Bomewhat  surprised to find that littleinterest was taken  in the  Government*s proposalsfor Home Rule,  and  it would  appear that the lackof interest in the  question  is.due to the fact that people in Ulster are very  dubious as to whether thePrime Minister really intends  to proceed *vith theBill, and that  even if  the Government are serious Ulsteris convinced that she has  little to fear.        I stated that mythat the Government wereand this information wasant Belfast pressmen.information was to the effect in earnest about the scheme,corroborated by two import-
r.m        X found that Sir Edward careon1a popularityhad. in no way ^diminished,, and the Ulster unionist arty, in my opinion, will loyally  follow any advice that he may give as regards the,Government&apos;s proposals.         The main interest  as far as Ulster is con- ceramic-ed appeals  to \$  the boundaries of the new province. Most of the people  withtfhom I discussed this question were of opinion that  the&apos;v*iole of the province  should be excluded;&apos;$ut&apos; on the  other hand, the people in the inner circles .ho!d  the view that the new province should consist  of the six  counties, the idea being that the inclusion of&quot; Donegal,  Cavan and lonaghan would pi-provide suoh an access o-f  strength tc the Roman Catho-* lie Party?  that ,the supremacy of the Unionists would be seriously threatened..  Further, with Home Rule not a vital issue,,&apos;  there  is  a  real danger that on certain questions thVUnioniat Labour party in Ulster might vote-with the Roman catholics *         X gathered  that  the Roman Catholics are strongly in favpur  of the  exclusion of the whole ef the province, .and that their opposition to the Bill is likely ta^e &quot;greatly  diminished if the area is to be the nine ut^ties. -         Great bitterness exists in Belfast between Sinn Fein and t&apos;ieRationalists, and the Unionist Councillor who  swaa  returned for the Falls Division told me that. Whereas during.his contest he met with courteous treatment from his opponents, the nationalist and Sinn Fein candidates met with gi-^dt hostility, and in. fact the Sinn $eih and!  Katlonalist^ouncillc^s who - have been returned  for the Falls Division,would  iot even speak to 6n.e another,           &apos;- .       &apos;  A very  careful survey cf the situation in  . &quot;Ulster leads me to.  believe that although amendments to the Bill may be, put forward by the Ulster Unionist Party, yet Ulster, will not resist the Bill because the Unionist party&apos;  realise that, if a settlement can be obtained now, they will secure infinitel/ better terms than they could hope for from a new parliament, in which, in&amp;ll probability the Labour Party would have much, stronger  representation.  ,         ,         Ulster  appears to  be in a satisfactory condition; and I was informed  that  Belfast to* day is far more pros- ferous than she has ever been during her history.  On  he-.other hand, the state  of the rest of. Ireland is really appalling*         1 was prepared te  find thiiw in Dublin in an  - tnsatisfartery, condition,  but they were considerably-worse than I anticipated.  Everybody seems to suspect hisneighbour;  people are  afraid to venture out after daxx; roVb-eriee, burglarl-es, assaults and raids for arms, take place every day.  The majority of these  r oases ^are not reported in  the press because people are afraid to give  evidence to the police, fearing that if they do so  worse will befall them.         The Sinn Feiners have plenty of arms and ammunition; and I was informed that it is the opinion if Dublin castle that the  murders which have recentlyYtaken place have been committed by Irish-American
 &quot;gun^mon&quot;  -  and  It would seem  that there is a very grave  danger of  very serious events  taking place in the near future  unless something oan be  done to relieve the situation.     It  is feared that  tho discipline of the Royal Irish  Constabulary may  break down, and  that there will be  a  repetition of the indiscriminate firing at  Thurles.     I must  also add that if any police officials are murdered in  Ulster, it is  probable that reprisals on  a large scale may    occur;  and  in oorroboration of this I may state that the morning after the murder of Commissioner Redmond, formerly a popular Royal Irish Constabulary officer in Belfast, the Queen1s Island shipyard men nearly got out of hand, and it required a great deal of  persuasion to keep them at  their  work.     The&quot;recently appointed Protestant Bishop of Tuam told a friend of mine that he  had received information to  the effect that the  young Irish students at Maynooth had recently been singing the  &quot;Red Flag&quot;, and tha* in three  or four parishes  in the  South, where the priests had denounced the&quot;  outrages, they had been boycotted by  their congregations.     During  my visit to Dublin I called upon Mr, John Bv,  Walsh, the Secretary of, the  Irish Unionist Alliance.  I explained  the situation to him as I saw it, and  at his request  I attended a  meeting of his Standing Committee, at  which Mr, W.M, Jellett, K.C. ,M,P,, was in the Chair,   I addressed this meeting, and after-  - wards  discussed  the position with the Committee,     I learnt that the  Irish Unionist Alliance were bitterly opposed to the Governments proposals, and that they strongly  resent  the attitude of some of  the Unionist  leaders in this country who they oontend  are  sacrificing the 400,000  Protestants in the South  and West,     It  would appear that the  Irish  Unionist Alliance and the Ulster Unionists are not on the best of  terms.  (I am told by the Ulstermen  that this is due to the fact  that in 1918 the Southerners refused te  give  Ulster any help as regards physical resistance). They hope, however, that Ulster will oppose the Bill - and I was informed  that lord $eufBteam wes in  London  trying to induce Sir Edward Caraon to lead the opposition to the Bill,     The Irish Unionist Alliance are anxious to run a big  campaign in this  country, and  at  present are dolag  a  good deal of work  by means  of distribution of  leaixets  and  through the medium of the Press.   It was also their intention to hold a number of meetings;/but I  pointed out to them  the  futility of  such a  cam- paign  -  and  I believe I succeeded  in convincing  them that such  a  campaign would not have  any appreciable effect in  this country. They  are  badly off for money.
I told Mr. Jollott that my information was that the Government were determined to proceed with their scheme; but he said that his information was quite to the contrary, and that he had been assured by a gentleman closely in touch with the Prime Minister that the Bill would never be produced.

I also visited the Unionist Anti-Partition League, and had a long conversation with their officials, and also  with Mr. B. Maddocks, D.L., a member of their Executive. This League has a fund of some £13,000 - and of course with Lord Iveagh behind it, there is no question about their being able to carry out an active campaign. At present they are devoting their attention to propaganda through the Press and by distribution of leaflets.  It is probable that they will shortly open an office in London.

It was stated in the Dublin Press a little time ago that the two Unionists organisations would amalgamate and carry out a joint compaign; but I am convinced that this will not take place, because, although the views of both organisations are almost identical, there is a great deal of personal fooling between members of the respective executives which will prevent any fusion.

The Irish Unionist Alliance people told me that the Anti-Partition League represents nobody but some ninety noblemen and country gentlemen.

The Anti-Partition League say that the Irish Unionist Alliance consists of nonentities; that it has no funds, and is really a negligible quantity.

Lord Farnham, the President of the Irish Unionist Alliance, is, I understand, an able man; but the main prop of this Association is Mr. W.M. Jollett, K.C.,M.P., who, according to the Anti-Partition people is "a sound man,  but has no constructive policy and his speeches mainly consist of  platitudes."

Lord Lidleton and Lord Donoughmore apparently are the main hopes of the Anti-Partition League- and it is a fact that Lord  Lidleton, early in 1919, obtained the signatures of a number of Irish Peers to a document pleding them to support a Home Rule Bill on the lines of the Bill which was drafted by Mr. Justice Powell. I have seen several of these documents myself. The Irish Unionist Alliance say that several of the poors who signed this document have now altered their minds.

The Anti-Partition League think that the opposition to the Bill in the House of Commons will be slight; but they are hopeful of amending the Bill very considerably in the House of Lords, and they say that they believe they have sufficient promises of support to hold it up for two years.


           I might, add,  however,  that Mr. Ma*ktooke told meprivately that  he thought that  snich a  towee  of action wouldhe very disastrous to the House of Lords.           $he Irish Unionist  Allianoe hope  and  expect Ulsterto oppose the Bill.           The Antl-ParUtioh League  think that Ulster will accept the Bill,  as she will get  practioally ell  ehe wants.           I visited the Pour Courts and nad a  long  cenversa-tion with Mr.R.R,8mylie, who is one of the  executive  of theIrish Unionist Alliance, and he introduced  me to a member ofbarristers.   I gathered that they were etrangly opposed to theGovernment sefoeme, as the creation of a separate Parliament in ulster would he a great loss to the Bar from a  financial pointof view.   Several of the barristers told me that they felt thatthe Unionist Party in Great Britain had betrayed them and intheir opinion the position of the Protestants in the  South and west would he intolerable.           Amongst the barristers there appears te  he an opinionthat the Government would proceed with the  Bill.           1 had hoped to have interviewed Mr.  Justice Mooreand Mr. Justice Powell.   Mr.  Justice Moore was approached byan intimate friend tc ask if he would  see  me, but he felt itwould oe very unwise for me to see either  of the Judges atpresent.           Amongst other people I met  X should like  to mentionMr. George Raid, the Solicitor to the Irish $ost Office.           I also had some valuable information from a well-known Dublin tradesman who is a Roman Catholic and an English-man by birth, but who has been resident in Dublin for over40 years.           As a result of the many enquiries X made  it wouldseem that Sinn Fein is at present undecided as to its attitudetowards the Governments Bill.  A Btrong section apparently areaverse to have anything to do *ith the measure.  Some peoplethought that Sinn Fein might at first  offer considerable  opposi-tion but that they would eventually come in.  Other  people  areof opinion that if Sinn Fein does oome in. the first aot  will beto declare an Independent Republic.           Mr.  Jelletb stated that  his  information was to theeffect that Sinn Fein would have nothing to  do with the Bill.           In conclusion,  I think Ulster will  accept the  Bill;but it Is extremely doubtful as to what  the  attitude will be ofSinn Fein, the Roman Hierarchy, and the  nationalists.  It wouldeeem as if the Bishops are seriously alarmed about the growth of bolshevism, and Borne people think that they  would agree topartition in order to put  an end, to the  terrible  outrages whichare taking place.
           Personally j  all the information that  I     abletc obtain points to the fact that  if the Government  aarrythe ,Btll through, people will be found in the South  towork the Bill.           ;           I might add that during my visit I met thefollowing members of the National Democratic Labour Party:-Messrs. J.A.Seddon,M.P,,   M.T.  Gimm, M.P.,  CJesson, M.P.,and J.F.Gre*n, M.P.   -This deputation only visited Ulster,and in my opinion male a mistake in not going South.They appear to be very impressed by -what they had seen in ulster and seem to be strongly opposed to the setting  upof any Irish Republio, or to the coercion of Ulster in anyshape or form.           The Irish Unionist  Alliance are  circularisingall their branches with a view to summoning a conferenceof representatives to consider the Government * a  Home  -Rule Bill as soon as the terms are known.           The Ulster Unionist Party are very annoyodaccount of the fact that,a- Sinn Fein meeting is to boheld&apos; at the Albert Hall on February lith.  They contend thatas Sinn Fein is pr^&amp;oMXm&amp;i in Ireland,  this meeting shouldbe prc^CUimdJiere.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,      February 4th. 1920.x 6 m

</content>
</cab>
