<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 885-886</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
          (THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF&apos;         HIS BNTA.i.j; .  :\*;:.VJR:-I1.;0JVERN *vant) PiiRAPIlRfiSJilFSSGElM IT^&apos;5EeT^eFii^^eneral of Canada to the Secretary of State for the Colonies.               Dated  5th February (Received Colonial  Office 8*35 a,,m, 6th February 1920) luNribtHuAL     February 5fch*   Relations between League of Nations and various members of the British Empire.   With reference to your cypher telegram of January 22nd my Ministers realise the importance of this problem and recognise the necessity in order to avoid undesirable confusion of careful provision for consultation^  Some doubt arises as to how far this problem is in any acute form raised by the  particular question of channel of communication with  league Secretariat and before reaching a final conclusion they would be glad to have the obssrvations of His Majesty5s Government on the f oil wing point B E       ... Your telegram implies that Secretariat it s el f v/il 1. ha v e s ome imp art ant jurisdi ct i on in questions of policy involving serious controversial issues with, possibilities -of unfortunate divergencies of view..   My Ministers had conceived,thst ouch. questions would either be (1), for assembly; in which case the. Canadian representative in attendance,  after consulting vathCttawa and with other members of theBritish $mpiro. delegation prasset would present theview of the Canadian Government or (2)  for oouncil:, in which case the British representative could throughthe existing channels of communication  between HisMajesbyTs Government and the Canadian Government sbtainspecial view of Canadian Government. On this aspectthey would.be glad. to. have the observations of. Hi3Majesty&apos;s Government also some further  indication of                                               precisely
precisely how it is contemplated the  League  Secretariatvail work and what its scope will be:    secondly  fromthe terms of your telegram my Ministers  assume  thatall communications between (?nation)s parties  to  theLeague and the League Secretariat will be  availablefor information of proposed Donirjiom&apos;  representative and for such observations as their Governments  imrydesire to make.   My Ministers would like  to be(?advised whether) if (?in) any amangeme n t that  mayfinally be reached in this matter some provision  mightnot be made for rendering the intelligence which  is received from day to day by His Majesty&apos;s Governmentconcerning Foreign Affairs available  to proposedCanadian representative.    Three,  &quot;Whether there has yet been any indicationon the part of members of League of an intention toappoint special representatives to reside at the seat  of the League.    Four.   In  the case cf United Kingdom whatauthority precisely will  the Secretary General of theLeague address  whether for  example Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs  or Prime Minister.    Five,   In  the case of  other members of the Leaguecould you advise  what is  contemplated in this respect.    Some further  description of  the branch  (?of)  cabinet secretariat referred to in  your  telegram  its operations,its composition,  and its  relation  to  the Foreign  office would also be  of  assistance.                                DEVONSHIRE

</content>
</cab>
