<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 897-899</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
7frig, POCUMSI^ IS THE PROPERTY Ofr Hig BRIT AM IC MAJESTY&apos;S CrOVEMCTT^                                                                 619                              &amp;ABIN13T.If 35 C 1 &apos;E T.L P, ?9lMINISTER RESPONSIBLE! TO PARLIATOTT OF TOTOKIJsTGfblFGOv3mil\tm&quot;IF-RBSFI!CT &quot;Oft IRISITAFFAIRS.. Memorandum &quot;by the Chief Secretary for Ireland.       In the donates on previous Home Rule Bills it wag recog-nised that there must be a Minister of the United Kingdom-^krvern-ment responsible for Irish affairs which would include suchmatters as services not within the powers of tho local Parlia-ments or Governments, and legislation with respect tf* those services and affecting Ireland, e,nd the giving or withholding ofHis Majesty&apos;s assent to Bills passed by the local legislature.       No definite statement was made in 1893 or 1912 as to the title or precise position of this Minister, hut an amendmentproposing that there should be a separate secretary for ireland was resisted by the Government in 1^93 *       The following extracts indicate the Government views in1893 and  1912:-                          189.3.       MR. MORLEY:  &quot;The Government have never thought that itwould he expedient to have someone corresponding to the chief secretary, hut there will be a Minister here, probably the HomeSecretary as in the old days, to answer all questions gentlemenmay choose to put as to Irish administration,  That was the old system, and the Government see no reason why it should not be revived&quot; (3rd July, 1893).       MR. GLADSTONE:  &quot;The Hon.Member desires to have on thepart of this House a perpetual supervision over all executivetransactions in Ireland and that consequently the existingMinister should be retained.  The object of the Government,,however,  is to get rid altogether of that supervision, and certainly we do not intend to set up a Minister to whom dozensof questions at a time may be put with regard to Irish localmatters&quot; (4th July, 1893).
                            - 2 -                             1912*       MR. AStyTJITHi  ffI was asked by an Hon.  Member oppositewhether in the event of the Government of Ireland Bill  becoming lairit was intended to rotain the Offioe of Chief Secretary.   I repliedthat though it would be essential to have a Minister in this Housewho would answer for tho Crown, the probability was that  he wouldbe known by some other,name.  I think I may .say perfectly clearlywe shall have a Minister here to answer in this House for a good many thingo, and to answer for the Acts of the Lord Lieutenantdetermined upon the advice and responsibility *f the Governmenthere.  Clearly wo must have a Minister for that purpose,  whether heis called Chief Secretary or some other name. - It is impossible to designate by name of offioe what particular Minister will be entrust-ad with this duty.  It may be a Secretary of  State or it  may be a minister with a special title appropriate to  the particular office,but he certainly must be a Minister of great  importance,  and Ithink it is perfectly clear from the nature of the responsibilityplaced upon him that the Government as a whole will share his *responsibility&quot;.       MR. MITCHELL-THOMSON&quot;:  ;,Io we understand that this minister is to be of Cabinet ranx&quot;?       MR, AStyUITH:  &quot;I said so&quot;.       MR. MITCHKLL-THOMSOlSf:  !,And occupying a position identical with that of a Secretary of State&quot;?       ICR, ASCjUITH:  nX canft undertake to answer for my successors.I dare say I shall never have anything to do  with it, but, so far atI can epeak, I certainly think he ought to be of Cabinet  rank1&apos;-(4th T^-comber. 1912).       It may be stated as a general proposition that the lesd ex-tensive the powers of the local Parliament and Government, the moreimportant becomes tho position of the Minister responsible for Irishaffairs, and that the establishment of two local Parliaments andGovernmentB will extend greatly the duties of tho Lord Lieutenant asrepresentative of the C?own, and will involve a corresponding exten-sion of tho matters for which the Irish Minister will be  responsible
Irish Office,  S/tf.l.    9th February,  192C.te Parliament.       If,  and when,  tho  two local Parliaments unite, theposition would,  of course,  be as  in 1912, end the suggestionthen made by the Prime Minister would moot the oasc.                      (Intd.)  I. M.

</content>
</cab>
