<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/97/0 images: 920-925</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 t  DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY 0? HIS. BRIT AMI C gAJESTYVS OOVBRTOiNT,)^f&quot; &apos; &apos; &quot;   &apos;        *&apos;.............i.    mil i, . i,       I, i mi, ,imn. i................mm ..........mmmmmfSECRET.                            CABINET,0* P* $97.                      &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;               I KTERKAT I ON AL gINAKCIAL SITUATION.            Mote-fry the ghanoeXlor of the Exchequer,      I circulate for the information of the cabinet a telegram which I received from the British embassy at Washington and a oopy of my reply.                         (intd.)  A. C.treasury. S.W.1,     9th February, 1920.
 Be&quot;cypher of telegram.from Mr. Lindsay (&quot;Washington)           * to Foreign Office, Despatched January 27th, 1920. Received 12.5 p*m. January 28th, 1920.                   ............No. 64-.       Mr. Leffingwell of United States Treasury asked mo tomeet him yesterday and talked about financial negotiations, that have been proceeding.  So far as question of interest is conoenv-ed United States Treasury desired, so far as their duty to congress would allow, to assist in no niggardly spirit and he wasaaxiOUs that His Majesty&apos;e Government should realise this.  he realised that olose contact that had existed between two Treasur-ies during war could not continue now to same degree but he ex-pressed concern at manner in which as he thought they had recent-ly lost contact and he evidently thought sufficient  use had notbeen made of Rathbone in whom Administration has great confidence.Talking on broader lines he said that be foresaw likelihood ofgreat financial difficulties in America in future.  continent of Europe he looked on as almost irretrievably lost  and GreatBritain gravely imperilled by danger sc created.  Yet he admittedhe waa tsufeh in the dark at a moment when he would greatlyappreciate any enlightenmert r  or instance he would like toknow what Chancellor of the Exchequer thought of situation andwhether he could see his way through.  Whatever happened he was convinced good policy would always require American and BritishTreasuries to work in harmony together and as long as he himself had any influence he would always direct it in that  direction.       Above is very confidential.
REPLY TO I.Following for Lindsay (?faehington).        Your No. 64*  You may convey following toLeffingwell as a confidential communication from theChancellor of the Exchequer or use It as a basis ofcommunication from yourself as you think most desirable.        I greatly value friendly confidence ofLeffingwell.  It is my earnest wish to maintain intimaterelations between two Treasuries and to work in closest possible harmony.  I greatly regret that I have notbeen able to meet Rathbone owing to my inability to leaveLondon and impossibility of his leaving Paris.  The british treasury has no permanent representative In Paris,Blackett has however managed tc jmAxtain some personalcontact by visits to Paris in October and January andI understand that Rathbonefs relations with Bradbury theBritish Reparation Commissioner, are exceedingly friendly.Physical separation has alone prevented contact withRathbone being as close as we should have desired.        Lindsay tells me that you foresee likelihood ofgreat financial difficulties in America In future, thatyou look on continental toope as irretrievably lost andGreat Britain as gravely Imperilled by the danger socreated.  I am not sure whether you mean to refer to thedanger created by financial difficulties in America or that resulting from the situation in oontSrdiiiaJ Europe.In my view however the financial and economic problemsof the world are so closely inter-connected, thai it &apos;Jrs not necessary to distinguish-between the two possible intor-interpretations.        So far as concerns  .he United Kingdom, our situation though full ef dirflculty gives nc cause for
despondency.  I believe that with the beginning of 1920.we reached the peak of our National Debt.  We have paidoff  60,000,000 of debt in January out of surplus ofrevenue over expenditure, and during the same period therehas bQon a Satisfactory reduction amounting to  26,000,000in our Currency Note Circulation.  I have steadily inview a policy-of gradual but not violent deflation of credit, and I am confident of being able without seriousaddition to our present very heavy taxation t6 have a surplus of revenue over expenditure in 1920/1 afterproviding for a minimum sinking fund of one half percent on our gross national debt.  Our exports visibleand invisible are already I believe sufficient to balanceour Importa and the beat estimates which I can obtainpoint to the likelihood of a favourable balance during1S20 of not far short of  200ir000,000.        If therefore the position of the tfctfted Kingdomoould be treated In isolation from the test of the worldI should fee1 no anxiety.        But the position in continential Europe&apos; profoundlyaffetts that  of the United Kingdom.  In order to do theexport trade  estimated above for 1920 it will be necessaryfor the United Kingdom to advance very large sums to itscustomers an  mainly to  continental Europe.  Indeed itmay be necessary for it  to advance more than the full amount of the estimated  balance of  200,000,000 and itselfto borrov on  commercial  credits in the United States.The British Government has set its face against advancesby eAs Government  to another, with the special exceptionof relief for such countries as Austria and Poland.$he advances  I  speak of  are of course private credits.But I have  little  confidence that the R.T. are potentialcontinental borrowers  sufficiently solvent to justifythe receipt of  such large advances.  Without dwelling on
conditions in Russia and Cental Europe, much depends upon succeas of French Oovernment in raising increased taxation and in reducing adverse balance of trade.Conditions in Belgium and Germany and even Italy appearto me to some extent more hopeful.  The reply which theBritish Oovernment will shortly publish to the Memorialfor an international financial Conference will probablyfurther explain the British Government^ attitude inthese matters.        t now turn to the relations between Europe and america.  We for our part since last summer have beenable without serious difficulty to cover all our government purchases without additional borrowing outside the UnitedKingdom.  Our Government liabilities abroad are nowpractically confined to those in the two Americas.  I hopethat by March 31st even this will show reduction for theyear but cost both of debt and purchases becomes increas-ingly burdensome owing to the fall of sterling exchange.        In my view this fall Is almost entirely due tothe credits, public and private, which we have been forcedto give to continental  Europe Just as our debt to UnitedStates is almost wholly due to loans we made to Alliesduring war, so that dollar sterling exchange is not really a measure of Anglo-American but of Europe-American conditions.Thus any Improvement In the credit ot continental countries would pro tanto relieve the strain on us.        The question ot postponement of interest and fundingof short term obligations being, as I hope, now settled,the one matter relating to British Government finance inthe United States of America which causes me seriousuneasiness is, the Anglo-French loan which matures in October.I should feel no difficulty were the British liabilitylimited to one half of the total of the Anglo-French loan.I would then pay off a large part or even the whole.  My                   \                   \
trouble arises from tho PrenchL.^sharo^ and in the^.st^rtaort I am responsible for the whcxU.$600*000*^00^I do not however despair of a  solution.        I do not with to be misunderstood, so I hastento add that I have ho thought  of invitditi^-finaxLCial -hielpfrom the United States treasury.  The one point whioh i will venture to moke in this connection is that yourinsistence on repayment of the Pittman silver advanceshas seemed to me to be severe  in present circumstances,as it deprives us of available exchange to the full amountef the repayments effected and costs us a very heavy, lossen exchange.        Turning to more general considerations, it is evident that a financial crisis in America would  gravelyendanger incipient recover^bf  Continent14  Europe.  Itla impossible to foresee the consequences.   With  theContinent a pre? to bankruptcy and possibly  to anarchy,and the United States of America unable to provide creditscf any sort owing to an internal crisis, the nmlA ,$oB3lu anwould Indeed be serious&apos;.        If  1 may  fenture on what I fear is controversial^ground!, I may  sa^that it  Is largely because of thesegangers that we should welcome a general caxu$ellat&amp;This o Interwove rnmenta\\ war debts.  Moral effect  would be-eiren^greater than practical  change  and  fresh hApe an4-cjonfidence,would  spring &quot;UD everywhere.                                        V        Existence  of these  international  debts detersNeutrals.from giving assistance,  checks  private  credita.and Will T  feaar prove a disturbing factor  in future international relations.

</content>
</cab>
