<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/220/0 images: 59-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^DOCUMENT I!TO  BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.m itIt is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document. OVDRIHW-TTT).COPY NO.CABINET. IRON AND STEEL INDUSTRY. Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.At the meeting of the Cabinet on the 18th February I referred to the confidential Report which has been prepared by Mr. 0. Bruce Gardner, managing director of Securities Management Trust, on the structure of the Iron and Steel Industry of Great Britain, incorporating plans for rationalisation, The summary of this Report, which I then promised to circulate for the information of my colleagues,  is now attached.The preparation of this Report,  it should be understood, followed upon the presentation (in confidence) of the Government Steel Report to certain representatives of the Industry and of the City.      It will be remembered that the Government. Report recommended the     formation of regional schemes of reorganisation;    the present document is therefore the conrplement to the Government Report.It is important that no public reference should be made to Mr. Bruce Gardner&apos;s Report, which was given to me on that understanding.W.G.Board of Trade,26th February, 1931.
t QREPORT BY MR.C.   BRUCE GARDNER ON THE STRUOTUS33 OF THE IRON AND STEEL INDUSTRY OF GREAT BRITAIN INCORPORATING PLAITS FOR RATIONALISATION,1, Mr. Bruce Gardner is Managing Director of Securities Management Trust, Limited,  the company formed under the auspices of the Bank of England to assist in the reorganisation of industry. Mr. Gardner, who has himself great practical experience of the iron and steel industry, in the preparation of this Report has consulted leading personalities of the industry in the different districts.      It is understood that the conclusions in the Report meet with the approval of those who were thus consulted.     These individuals, however, gave their assistance and advice in a personal capacity, and not as representing the firms with which they are connected.2. After reproducing statistical information regarding the supply of materials and the production of ii*on and steel the Report discusses briefly the technical features of iron and steel manufacture.     Particulars of the distribution of iron and steel production in the country, and of the imports and exports for 1929 are given in the Appendix to this note.3. The year 1929 has been taken as the basis of the Report. Mr. Gardner points out that, if the 1930 statistics of the industry are examined, there is revealed a serious falling off in the pig iron and steel output and correspondingly in all the activities of the industry.      The export figures declined from 4,379,000 tons in 1929 to about 3,250,000 tons in 1930, or a reduction of about 25.8 per cent, while our imports of foreign steel and iron were as great if not greater in 1930 than in 1929, the figure for 1929 having been 2,S16,000 tons.      Our total steel output for 1930 was only about 7,300,000 tons as compared with 9,536,200 tons for 1929,  or a reduction of about 24.5 per cent. In pig iron also the output has drooped correspondingly, from
7,410,600 tone for 19S9 to 6,200,000 tons for 1930, a fall of about 16.3 per cent.     This problem of the loss of output is obviously a dominating factor in formulating any plan of rationalisation:    it has the most serious consequences on steel production costs and its repercussions have far-reaching consequences.Mr. Gardner expresses the definite opinion that, while there are other matters of serious importance which affect manufacturing costs and should be dealt with, the benefits and savings to be secured from the rationalisation of both manufacture and selling methods are in themselves so great that the reorganisation of the iron and steel industry should be carried through without further delay.4. As an introduction to the proposed scheme of rationalisation for the industry, the Report brings together the available statistics regarding production in the differentdistricts and classifies the industry by products and byregional districts.     The classification by products is -I. Pig Iron, Ingots, Blooms, Billets, Rails, Joists, Section and Plates.2. General Forgings and Armaments.3. Steel Castings.4. Steel Tubes.5. Tin Plate Rollers.6. Galvanised Sheets and Black Sheet Rollers. 7. Wire Drawers and Manufactures. 8. Re-Rollers, and by districts is( a) Scotland(b) North--East Coast.(c) Midland and North-West Coast.(d) South Vales.5. The scheme of reorganisation is based upon these fourRegional Districts.
In outlining the scheme the Report says that it is possible to group the firms in their main products and the problem is simplified if it is considered mainly, in the first case, as the rationalisation of the steel production of the companies chiefly occupied in producing pig iron and steel, and manufacturing Blooms, Billets, Rails, Joists, Bars and Plates (Group 1), Forgings and Armaments (Group 2), Steel Castings (Group 3), Tube Making (Group 4).      Tin Plate Rollers (Group 6), Galvanised Sheets and Black Sheet Rollers (Group 6), Wire Drawers and Manufactures (Group 7)  and Re-Rollers (Group S) must in the first instance be considered separate industries, because, being finishing industries, they are attached in some cases to composite steel producing firms and in other cases are separate firms and use a considerable amount of semi-rolled imported steel as their raw material.     It is stated that organisation and consolidation should take place in these branches of the industry with the object of linking up with the proposed new steel producing combines in each of the-four Regional Districts. .   In this way the new regional steel producing combines should as far as possible become the manufacturers of all steel required in their District and the suppliers of the raw material of the finishing industries.6. There then follows a discussion of the recommended reorganisation of the heavy iron and steel branches in the. four Regional Districts. ( i)  Scotland.Investigations are now proceeding with the object of forming a scheme for the amalgamation into one corporation of five companies (since these proposals were initiated two of the companies have already agreed upon amalgamation within them-selves).      This amalgamation would bring under one control four of the six steel producing concerns at present operating and
mthree of the eight pig iron producers.     It is thought that one of the two remaining steel works might he brought into the corporation later, hut that as the blast furnace plants outside the proposed amalgamation are in the main the property of Colliery Companies and produce Scottish foundry pig iron it is not necessary at present to include them.      It is suggested that when this amalgamation has been carried through develop-development should take place on the following lines -(a) Unified control to carry through reorganisation and concentration of production in selected plants.(b) Erection of modern coke oven and blast furnaceequipment to enable Scotland to be largely independent in regard to pig iron.(c) At a later stage consideration to be given to thedesirability of the installation of a modern rolling mill together with additional blast furnace plant.,Any decision regarding new building must be preceded by a careful comparison between the cost of production in Scotland and the cost of obtaining pig iron from Lincolnshire or Northamptonshire.(ii) North East Coast..The basis of the reorganisation here is a proposed amalgamation of two groups, the Dorman Long group and the South Durham group.     With regard to steel the only important firm which would then be left outside is the Consett Iron Company and it is thought that if the larger consolidation is eventually attained there may possibly be arranged a basis of operation that will embrace the Consett Iron Company also-There are also a number of pig iron producers which it is not proposed to include at present,In the event of the amalgamation of the two groups being brought about, the proposed scheme of development is divided into two stages, the whole scheme covering a period of 2-2^ years to carry through.      Stage 1 provides for (a) unification of the two groups (b) redistribution of the
manufacturing operations to show the &quot;best costs, (c) reconstruction and additions to the existing plant.      Stage 2 provides, in addition, for (a) a modern central coking plant on a new site, (b) a new modern rolling mill (c)  further extension of works and improvements.These proposals allow for the growth which may he expected from better organisation and improvement of existing plant.     The new company will control all its requirements for materials and practically all the v/orks are situated on tidal water.(iii) liidland and North West Coast.This district is, in the Report, divided into two divisions;    the first includes Lincolnshire, South Yorkshire, North Staffordshire and South Lancashire and the second North Lancashire and Cumberland.     An amalgamation of two of the concerns in Lincolnshire is suggested.      It is proposed that further consideration should be given to the possibility of constructing a new plant to meet the requirements of the South wales industries for sheet and tin plate bars, and a suggestion for transferring some of the galvanised sheet industry from South Wales to Lincolnshire is made on technical grounds.      In Yorkshire the major portion of the heavy steel production is already under one control, but it is suggested that some of the production of structural shapes of one firm outside this control might be transferred to Lincolnshire, while retaining the production of the higher grade qualities near Sheffield.     The development which is already taking place of the plant of the Lancashire Steel Corporation is referred to, and it is suggested that at some later date the steel works in North Staffordshire might be acquired, and some part of its business distributed between Lancashire, Sheffield and Lincolnshire.      The scheme for this division is stated as -
(a) The co-ordination and development of the heavy steel trade, as now &quot;based on the Lincolnshire ore field.(h) A similar arrangement in the Sheffield area.(c) Combined administrative control of these two areas, coupled with a community of interests with the Lancashire Steel Corporation.The proposal for Division (b) (North Lancashire and Cumberland)  is that the five works should be amalgamated, that the output should be redistributed and concentrated and that this division should be linked up with Division (a).At a later date, consideration should be given to the provision of further plant, when the necessary reorganisation Y/ithin the existing establishments has been carried through.(iv) South Wales.The recent arrangement between Guest Keen &amp; Nettlefold, Limited, and Baldwins, Limited, is sufficient to give control of the situation in this area.      The proposals for development are, for the initial stage, (a)  the installation at Cardiff of new rail and section mills and a smaller  -merchant bar mill and (b) alteration and addition to some existing plant.      The second part of the scheme involves (a) a final concentration of all steel production at Cardiff by developing and modernising the plate mills and (b) additions to melting shops and power plant.7, The Report then proceeds to deal with the other sections of the industry.(i) General Eorg.ihg,3, and Armaments.;It is shown that the manufacture of forgings is carried on mainly in the Midland and North-West Coast region, but to a substantial extent also in Scotland and on the North-East Coast.     No definite proposals are made, but it is pointed out that the amalgamation of the interests of Armstrong Whitworth, Tickers and Cammell Laird has produced the English Steel
Corporation, Limited, and that John Brown &amp; Company, Limited, and Firth&apos;s,Limited, have a community of interests.      The view is expressed that in course of time there will he further merger which would have the effect of bringing the heavy engineering forging and armament makers in the country under one organisation.(ii) Castings.There are makers of steel castings in all the four Regional Districts, but the Midland and North-West Coast district make some 60$ of the whole and South Wales a very small proportion. It is remarked that whatever general scheme of rational reorganisation is applied to the heavy iron and steel group in the direction of improved efficiency and cost of production should affect the operations of the forgings and castings groups, and that further advantage would be obtained by the development of new methods, better equipments, and by suitable construction of interests to effect centralisation.(iii) Steel TubesoTwo of the largest companies have recently become affiliated and it is said that negotiations are in progress with the only other two important companies in the industry: If these negotiations are successful the whole industry will be under one control.     The proposed scheme of development includes the erection in Northamptonshire of new modern iron and steel plant which would meet part of the requirements of the tube companies as well as supplying part of the country&apos;s requirements of basic Bessemer steel, which is at present, obtainable only from the Continent.( iv) Tin i-IatestThe need for a home supply of steel bars at a world&apos;s market price is referred to and the question of the adaptation and modification of a steel plant in South Wales to supply the
industry is discussed.     The possibility, however, of further development of the basic Bessemer process in Lincolnshire or Northamptonshire in order to supply the tin plate industry is mentioned, and in this connection it is said that close consideration is necessary to determine the relative advantages to the tin plate industry of obtaining its material in this way, or by the tin plate industry itself being developed in the steel producing districts.     Attention is drawn to the large number of units in the industry, some of them badly situated geographically and it is stated that it is desirable that some scheme should be evolved within the industry for concentration of manufacture, and further development of the best situated plants.(v) Galvanised Sheets and.Black Sheets.,It is claimed in the Report that the sheet industry is efficient, that the equipment of the works is well up-to-date and that developments have been undertaken so far as practicable.      The difficulty of attempting to bring about further combination among the sheet makers arises partly through their being spread over the whole country, and partly because many of them are joined up with primary steel producers.     Development on these lines,  It is thought, should take place through the sheet mills being joined to the steel companies, and drawing their supplies from the nearest source. It is said that meetings are already taking place to discuss amalgamations, but the works which are drawing their supplies at a low price from abroad are more profitable than the works that are attached to a British steel plant and it has not been found possible to obtain an agreed basis of valuation.(vi) The Wire Industry.This industry is mainly concentrated in the Lancashire and Sheffield districts and the opinion is&apos; expressed that the
wire manufacturers should formulate plans for uniting together   in those areas and linking up with the regional steel producing units (i.e. for Lancashire, The Lancashire Steel Corporation   and for Sheffield, The United Steel Company).(vii) Re-Rolling Industry.It is pointed out that there are some 113 re-rollers in the country, (i.e.  firms that buy semi--finished steel and roll it into more finished shapes)  and that a great deal of the material bought by these firms is imported.      The increasing imports of more finished material and consequent increasing difficulties of this branch of the industry are referred to, and the opinion is expressed that the re-rollers should themselves consider the formation of groups for more efficient production and distribution and that ultimately these groups should be linked up with the regional combines.8. It is proposed that a central organisation should be set up by the four Regional Districts to co-ordinate the sales both for home and abroad, and having power to negotiate with foreign steel producers in regard to the regulation of output, the prices of their main products, etc.9. Finally, the suggestion is put- forward that, in order that the future of the British iron and steel industry may be planned and developed on the best and most efficient lines, to the benefit not only of the steel producer but also of the user of his product, the industry should -set up an Advisory Steel Production Council.     This Council should be fully representative of all the interests in the various branches of the industry and, with access to all necessary information, its chief object should be to co-ordinate and adjust productive capacity and future development as between the Regional Districts, with due regard to all the relevant factors.     The
Council should also give special consideration to the needs of the finishing trades which use as their raw material these -finished products of the steel-maker.     In this connection Mr. Gardner emphasises the risk of proceeding with future developments in any piecemeal fashion and the necessity of dealing with the reorganisation and development of the industry on a national basis.     Unless this is done, new money provided for the industry may be misspent and the industry damaged rather than helped.
APPENDIX.iron and Steel Production - different districts _ of U.K.Pig Iron.Distri ct.No. of blast furnaces in existence.No. in blast. Sept. 1930.Production 1929.Tons.Steel.Production of steel Ingots &amp; Testings.1929.Tons.y. Leicester, e, &amp; Northants.is of Lanes. &amp; ) irks. )ef field. )olnshire.Coast.and.iffs. Shropshire pester &amp; Warwick.Ith Wales &amp; lohmouth.It Coast.TOTALS.563125 95 894823 434102411 25 13.   10i    1041,174, 2008        !       472,400864,700 2, 349,100 607,100439,900926,500 755,400-4-iI  7,589,300j.416,6001,217,000 (Sheffield only)733,5002,208,300&quot;1,581,600912,5002,336,100 230,6009,636,200
Import and Export trade in Iron and Steel and Manufactures thereof analysed by Ports of entry. 1929Ports of Entry.Thames &amp; South Coast ..........Mersey and Solway Firth .......Scotland...................North East Coast ...........Hunter to/but excluding Thames. Bristol Channel...............Imports, Tons.282,776 443,747 592,294 210,653 207,071 599,401Exports, Tons.86,182 496,743 280,348 596,682 103,636 859,213

</content>
</cab>
