<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/220/0 images: 180-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is the property..of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.C K iji T . COPY No;, fC A B I E a T .60(31)StMDAY OPTING OF PLACES OF ENTjjjATAIMMKNT . Memorandum by the Home Secretary.At its meeting on the 18th instant  (Cahinet Conclusions14(31),   Conclusion 10)  the Cabinet agreed(1)    that the L aw Officers of the Crown shouldbe asked,   in consultation with the Home Office, to advise the Cabinet as to the present position of the law resulting from the recent decisions of the Courts;(2) that I should discuss the whole situation wi th the leaders of the Opposition Parties and should ascertain  their view;(3)    and that I should report the result of myenquiries at the next meeting of the Cabinet.With regard to the question as to the exact position of the law,  the Attorney General informs me that he is in entire agreement with the viev/ expressed by my advisers at the Home Office that the Sunday Observance Act,  1780,  would clearly apply to any public meeting,  political or otherwise,  or to any form of public entertainment or amusement to which persons are admitted by payment of money or by ticket sold for money.    The Act provides that &quot;any house,   room or other place, which shall be opened or used for publick entertainment  or amusement or for publi ckly debating on any sub,1ect whatsoever upon any part of the Lord&apos;s Day called Sunday and to which persons shall be admitted by payment of money or by tickets  sold for money,  shall be deemed a disorderly house or place&quot;.The Attorney General has also advised that (l)    the decision previously come to in the case  of Williams v. Wright  (quoted in my memorandum C.P. 48(31))  -under which it was held that an entertainment,, to which admission was free but a charge was made for reserved seats, was not prohibited by the Act - is of very doubtful
Talidity;    and(2)    it is probable that Sunday entertainments conducted by a Society which distributes tickets amongst its members in return for their annual subscription are also illegal. The Attorney General has also expressed to me the hope that steps may be taken to bring the law into harmony with public opinion at the earliest possible moment.In pursuance of the second decision of the Cabinet, I have now had an opportunity of discussing the whole question with Mr. Baldwin and Mr. Lloyd George.Mr. Baldwin informs me that he is in general agreement with the proposals set out in my memorandum (C.P.48(31), and I gathered that he personally and the majority of his Party would support a proposal to regularise,   so far as relates to cinemas and concerts,  the practice which obtained before the recent judgments:   &apos; As regards theatres,  Mr. Baldwin was not so definite,  but he inclines to the view that it would be desirable to leave  the question whether similar treatment should be accorded to theatres to be determined by a free vote of the House.Mr. Lloyd George on the other hand explained that his Party, whom he had consulted, were very much divided on this question and included many Members who were averse from any relaxation of the law relating to the Sunday opening of places of entertainment.      I gathered,  however,  that, if the Government decided to introduce a Bill on the lines proposed, Mr. Lloyd George,  if he voted at a.ll, would give his own vote in support,  and that in his vie&apos;;; decisions  should be left freely to the House.It is for the Cabinet now to decide,  in the light of the discussions which I have reported,  whether it  is in the public interest that immediate legislation should be introduced by the Government and what form that legislation should take.
-validity;    and(2) it is probable that Sunday entertainments conducted by a Society which distributes tickets amongst its members in return for their annual subscription are also illegal.The Attorney General has also expressed to me the hope that steps may be taken to bring the law into harmony with public opinion at the earliest possible moment.In pursuance of the second decision of the Cabinet, I have now had an opportunity of discussing the whole question with Mr. Baldwin and Mr. Lloyd George.Mr. Baldwin informs me that he is in general agreement with the proposals set out in my memorandum (CP.48(31), and I gathered that he personally and the majority of his Party would support a proposal to regularise,  so far as relates to cinemas and concerts,  the practice which obtained before the recent judgments.      As regards theatres,  Mr. Baldwin was not so definite, but he inclines to the view that  it would be desirable to leave the question whether similar treatment should be accorded to theatres to be determined by a free vote of the House.Mr. Lloyd George on the other hand explained that his Party, whom he had consulted, were very much divided on this question and included many Members who were averse from any relaxation of the lav/ relating to the Sunday opening of places of entertainment.      I gathered,  however,   that,  if the Government decided to introduce a Bill on the lines proposed, Mr. Lloyd George,  if he voted a.t all, would give his 07irn vote in support, and that in his view decisions should be left freely to the House.It is for the Cabinet no;&quot; to decide,  in the light of the discussions which. I have reported,  whether it is in the public interest that immediate legislation should be introduced by the Government and what form that legislation should take.
My own view is  that our best  course is to introduce  legislation to enable Local Authorities to restore the status quo so far as concerns cinemas and concerts,  and that we should be well advised to leave it to the House to determine by a free vote, and on an amendment which any Member may move, whether similar treatment should be accorded to theatres.If the Cabinet decided that legislation should be introduced, I would strongly recommend that our Bill should      1 include a provision to deal with the numerous actions which have recently been instituted by common informers suing for penalties for infringements of the Sunday Observance Act. I am informed that the total of the penalties claimed in these actions amounts  to several millions of pounds.      These penalties follow automatically upon proof of the  complaint.      It is true that there is power under the Remission of Penalties Act,  1875, to remit any penalties awarded, but there is no power to take any action as regards the costs which,  if the plaintiff wins his case, he is entitled to recover on the full scale.      I have consulted the Attorney General as to the best method of dealing with these outstanding actions and he advises me that the best course is to include in our proposed Bill a provision on the lines of Section 1(1) of the Indemnity Act,  1920, which provides that &quot;if any proceeding (to which the Act relates) has been instituted whether before or after the passing of this Act,  it shall be discharged and made void,  subject to such order as to costs as the Court or a Judge thereof may think fit to make&quot;.The Attorney General remarks&quot; that,  while he is not normally in favour of retrospective legislation of this sort,  he thinks that in this case it is abundantly justified,  and in that view I entirely concur.J.R.C.ME OFFICE:24th February,  1931.

</content>
</cab>
