<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/220/0 images: 205-206</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Mkis document is the property of His Britannjo Majesty&apos;s Government-CABINETI- MATERNAL MORTALITYH  63(31) .Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Health..By Cabinet Minute 55(30)   of the 24th of September, 1930^  it was decided that I should proceed with the . alternative and less costly scheme for dealing with maternal mortality (Cabinet Paper C.P. 300(30)) but announce that I was in consultation with the authorities concerned as to the larger scheme it being laid down that no cost should be caused to the Exchequer under the latter scheme before 1st April, 193E and that I should do my utmost to secure economies on my vote to counterbalance the cost o.f it.By Cabinet Minute 57 (30)  of the 30th of September, it was decided that the policy of the government on this question should be made known preferably at the Llandudno Conference.Acting on these minutes,  I duly announced the policy at Llandudno and I sent a circular to local authorities . early in December as to the alternative and less costly scheme.      I was proposing to begin my negotiations as to the larger scheme by discussing it at an early meeting of the Approved Societies Consultative Council.     At this stage I received a letter from the Chancellor of the Exchequer expressing the view that the scheme should be postponed. The Chancellor^ reasons are that the Cabinet decision in September was really in the nature of a i^ostponement, that, the scheme y/as approved only on the clear understanding that it should involve no cost to the Exchequer before 1st April, 1832, that the financial position has become much more serious since September and it has become quite clear that 1932 will be as difficult a year for the Exchequer as 1931,  and that,  as statedCopy No.
f 0 9JU O Uin the Chancellor^ recent speech,  it will., not he possible to embark on large new expenditure till prosperity returns.Whilst I fully appreciate the point of view of the Chancellor,  I feel that before I can accept it,  I must have a decision of the Cabinet, since it was the Cabinet who decided that I should proceed on certain lines and should make a public announcement of the policy.      As to the iuerits I will only say (1)   that there is very strong feeling in the party and especially among our women members and among many women&apos;s organisations on this subject (2)   that the negotiations to be undertaken will in any case be most protracted and difficult (3)  that the attitude of local authorities towards increased expenditure is steadily becoming stiffer as time goes on and (4)   that, unless these particular negotiations are put in hand soon,  it will tend to become involved with the negotiations for the new block grant under the Local Government Act 1929 which will have to be completed in time for that grant to take    effect before April 1933 and must therefore&apos; start at least a year before that date.C Intld..)  A..G.inistry of Health, February 87th,

</content>
</cab>
