<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/220/0 images: 278-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
l-J *jTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTiipoYl (31) slORET.COPY NOo , industrial RELATIONS,Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Labour,,As my colleagues are no doubt aware proposals for wage adjustments are being negotiated upon or are under discussion in a number of important industriesD    A memorandum giving brief details is circulated herewith. In practically all cases,  there is joint machinery which is being fully operated and5 while the possibility of ultimate disagreement musts  of courses be taken into account;, there is not at present reason to suppose that settlement will not be reached,, In each case my Department is keeping in close touch with the positions(Intdc) Mo Go Be16th March,  1931,
9 r.* ai.j     -JM E M 0 R A K D U most claim for an advance by the Unions first made in 1924 resulted in an increase&apos; in the bonus from 10/- to 12/- in the case of time-workers in August9 1927*    No alteration has since taken place a further claim was the subject first of negotiations and. then of approach to the Government v/ith a request for an Inquiry similar to those in the Cotton and Iron and Steel Industries.    This T,vas refused by the Government in October,  1930*Following the issue of a pamphlet on the general industrial situation,, the Engineering .&quot;.jnployers addressed to the Unions on 11th December,  1930, an invitation to a conference &quot;for the purpose of considering the whole question of wages and working conditions in the Industry&quot;c    At the conference attended by 42 trade unions on 30th January,  the employers put forward the following proposals:A working week of 43 instead of 47 hours; -reduction of the overtime and night shift    and piece-work rates and consideration of the two questions of the manning of machines and demarcation of labour. The Unions met on 24th February and a further conference with the Employers was held on 11th March.    At this conference the Unions stated reasons against the proposed changes.    It was finally agreed that the position should be examined by a Joint Committee.RAII^AYS^The finding of the rational wages Board is now under consideration by the companies and the Unions and the latter will probably hold delegate conferences.    It appears that the proposal as to the daily spread-over of hours which was apparently made by the Board in order to leave untouched
9 r.&apos; ithe principle of the guaranteed day, will he the subject of considerable discussion.As regards railway shopmen, who are not covered by the National \wages Board procedure,  the claim of the Companies to reduce the war wage and the unions&apos;  counter-claims were the subject of disagreement  on the Railway Shopmen&apos;s Council on 26th Januaryo    The Companies pressed the unions to agree to the reference of the claim for reduction to the Industrial Court. The unions cannot agree to this course but they are prepared to make a further endeavour to reach a settlement by negotiation, BUILDING TRAPS. England and Wales,Following a meeting of the National Joint Council for the Building Industry in february, , 19303 at which a reduction on the cost-of--living sliding scale was announced, and as a result of representations from the operatives5 a Joint Committee was set up to review the National Agreement in the light of developments in the industry.    The Committee held several meetings. but no agreement could be reached.    The operatives&apos;  side then gave notice9 expiring on 31st March,19319 to terminate their affiliation to the National Joint Council,At a meeting of the Council in february,  1931, at whioh a further cost-of-living reduction was announced,  it was agreed that negotiations should be resumed so that a new agreement should be arranged before the expiration of the Operatives&apos; notice.    Further meetings of the joint negotiating committee are being held and a meeting of all the Union Lxecutives is to be held on Friday, 20th Marchs to consider the present position the claims of the Operatives include stabilisation and revision of the sliding scale, five day   week of 40 hours, payment for time lost through inclement weather, etc.    The
9 f.: oLiEmployers are asking for greater elasticity in the working rules,  grading of labourers, payment hy results, and choice of labour to operate mechanical tools,. Scotland.,Scotland is not new covered by the National Joint Council for the Building Industry,  the Employers affected having terminated their affiliation by notice expiring on 31st December, 1930.    At no  time was the Council really representative as the majority of the employers&apos;   organisations were purely Scottish and had separate, agreements with their operativesoTwo of the largest Employers&apos; Associations have now federated and are in negotiation with the    ational Federation of Building Trade Operatives with a view to setting up a separate permanent joint body for Scotland.    Meanwhile wage rates have been stabilised until 31st March, 1931c    A provisional Joint Council has been set up, but the negotiations for a new agree-nent have not so far been successful, and in fact have reached deadlock.    The Employers at first asked for-2d. per hour reduction in wages, but this has been modified to Id. per hour, with a labourers&apos;  rate equal to two-thirds of the craftsmen&apos;s rate instead of three-quarters as at present.    The Operatives are asking for stabilisation of the present rates.These negotiations do not include the painting, plastering and plumbing interests.    As regards painters there is a separate agreement which has been renewed for twelve months from 1st January, 1931,  the rate fixed heing Id. per hour below that for 1939.    In the plastering trade there is a separate agreement under which rates of pay are varied in accordance with fluctua-tions in other skilled craftsmen&apos;s rates in Scotland, and it is presumed, that no variation will be made until the new Joint Council has agreed upon rates for the other classes of skilled&quot;    3c !  .
9   aij Jlabouro    There is no separate agreement for plumbers, but it is assumed that, as in the past,  their rates will follow those fixed under any general agreement that may be made. BOOT AND SHOE INDUSTRYcThe Central Authority in this industry is the National Con-ference (dating back to 1909)  of the Federated Associations of Boot and Shoe Manufacturers and the National Union of Boot and Shoe Operatives.The Conference met on the 20th October, 1930, under the chair-manship of Mr. Addington Willis to consider proposals presented by both sides for the revision of the National Agreement, 1923.The claim made by the Union includes substitution of a 44 hour week for the present 43 hour week, a minimum of 60s.  for men at 21 years and a minimum of 40s. for women at 20 years.    The claim made by the Employers includes revision of piece rates, division of work into new grades,  a minimum of 52s.  for men at 21 years.The Conference adjourned after three days deliberations, having agreed to the appointment of a Sub-Committee under the Chairmanship of Mr. Addington V/illis, and meetings took place as well as many informal discussions, but no agreement could be reached, and this was reported to the adjourned rational Conference on 8th January last.    Both sides made suggestions at this Conference that the whole question of revision of piece rates should be referred to the Local Arbitration Boards for investigation, but disagreement arose on the wording of the reference hack, and so the Conference terminated.The Employers gave the necessary six months notice to terminate the National Agreement, but they suggested that two on each sideshould meet with the Independent Chairman for a further discussion.The Union afterwards held a special delegate meeting on the12th March, and,  subject to the withdrawal of the employers&apos; notice the Council were instructed to make the best possible settlement on the basis of the employers&apos; proposals.    It is to be noted that, while the employers v/ere once highly organised, no more than 4$% are now members of the Federation.4.
POTTERY.The parties to the difference in the pottery industry (for which there is a Joint Industrial Council) are the British Pottery Manufacturers&apos; Federation, acting for the Employers and the National Society of pottery Workers,  the National Union of Enginemen, Firemen, Mechanics, Motormen and Electrical Workers and the Transport and General Workers&apos; Union, acting for the workpeople.Wages, hours and conditions in the Industry are regulated under the General Award of 1924 and provision is made for the yearly exchange of notices for the purpose of adjusting departmental piece prices and making such minor modifications in the award as may- he necessary from time to time.        These notices are presented on the 11th Februarjr and due to expire on the 25th March unless agreement is reached in the interval .In February of this year the Employers made a claim for 15 per cent, reduction in the wages of men,  and minor adjustments in the wages of women and juveniles.      The Union made a counter-claim for 25 per cent, increase for all female workers and for all male potters attendants, piece rate adjustments, limitation of apprentices and displacement of women employed as placers and dippers.A Conference has taken place between the parties, but no progress was made and the Secretary of the Employers&apos; Federation has now sent a communication to the Unions giving notice to terminate the engagement of all employees on the 25th March.      The Union, following constitutional procedure, has asked formally for a meeting of the Joint Industrial Council and this will take place on 16th March. The three Honorary Members,Messrs Henry Clay, Rowntree and We thered have been asked to he present.5.T***-l-timw......iiiiiiri&apos; ilium..............mrniriiffiiiiin        ......-......n   iinriin
O ftBLEACHING    AND DgXLNG.The parties to the difference in the bleaching and dyeing industry are  the Allied Association of Bleachers and Dyers, Printers and Finishers,, for the Employers,  and the Joint Dyers&apos; Executive for the Y/orkpeople.      The most important Union concerned is the Amalgamated Society of Dyers, Bleachers,  Finishers and Kindred Trades.The original claim made by the Employers was for a 15 per cent,  reduction, but this has been modified to a definite demand for 10 per cent,  reduction off gross earnings. This is in addition to the automatic reductions which have taken place owing to the fall in the cost of living,  and which have meant decreases of from lOd.  per week for juveniles to about 3s.per week for adults during the past year.Conferences have been held, but no settlement has been reached.      The Unions have suggested to the Employers that dividends,  etc.,   should first be reduced.      The Joint Executive also informed the Employers that no useful purpose would be  served in continuing negotiations on the claim, made by the Employers.      This attitude was modified,  and,  at the invitation of the Employers,  the full Negotiating Body of the . Unions met the corresponding body of Employers on the 2nd March.      No progress whatever was made, nor have any arrangements been made for a further meeting.     The position is under the consideration of the Employers. ELECTRICAL CONTRACTING,LONDON DISTRICT.As a result of the refusal of a-contractor,  engaged on the new Fo.rd  factory at Dagenham to pay the London rate, a strike took place.      The boundary of the London area passes through Dagenham.      A special increase of -fd. an hour was given in the London area on the understanding that the union would strictly    observe agreements..      The employers regard the strike at Dagenham as a breach of this understanding
and have decided to withdraw the ird-and so to reduce the rate to l/9td.throughout London.       A discussion on the National&apos; Joint industrial Council has failed to secure a settlement and,  at present^ the union proposesto resist the reduction by-strikes at establishments where it is put into operation at the end of next week.      It is not improbable that the Executive of the union will seek a further meeting with the employers. If no action has been taken by Monday,  the Department will intervene.7.

</content>
</cab>
