<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/66/7 images: 48-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1945.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (45) 7.2nd June, 1945.CABINET.THE GERMAN MILITARY SURRENDER.Note by the Secretary.BY direction of the Prime Minister, I circulate herewith the following documents relating to the German military surrender at Rheims and Berlin : 1. Authority from Gross Admiral Doenitz to General Oberst Jodl datedthe 6th May, 1945.2. Act of Military Surrender, signed by General Oberst Jodl in Rheims onthe 7th May, 1945.3. Undertaking given by certain German Emissaries to the Allied HighCommands, signed by General Oberst Jodl in Rheims on the7th May, 1945.4. Authority from Gross Admiral Doenitz to General Field-Marshal Keitel,General Admiral Von Friedeburg and General Oberst Stumpf, datedthe 7th May, 1945.5. Act of Military Surrender (English version) signed by General Field-Marshal Keitel, General Admiral Von Friedeburg and General OberstStumpf in Berlin on the 8th May, 1945.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES.Cabinet Offices, S. W. 1,2nd June, 1945.1. Authority from  Gross Admiral  Doenitz to  General  Oberst  Jodldated 6th May, 1945.Hauptquartier, den 6. Mai 1945.Ich bevollmachtige Generaloberst Jodl, Chef des Wehrmachtfuhrungsstabesim Oberkommando der Wehrmacht, zum Abschluss eines Waffenstillstands-abkommens mit dem Hauptquartier des Generals Eisenhower.DOENITZ,Cross Admiral.Only this text in English is authoritative.2.   Act of Military Surrender signed by General Oberst Jodl in Rheims on 7th May, 1945.1. We the undersigned, acting by authority of the German High Com-mand, hereby surrender unconditionally to the Supreme Commander, Allied[29931]
Expeditionary Force and simultaneously to the Soviet High Command all forces on land, sea, and in the air who are at this date under German control.2. The German High Command will at once issue orders to all german military, naval and air authorities and to all forces under German control to ceaseactive operations at 2301 hours Central European time on the 8th May and toremain in the positions occupied at that time. No ship, vessel, or aircraft is to bescuttled, or any damage done to their hull, machinery or equipment.3. The German High Command will at once issue to the appropriate com-manders, and ensure the carrying out of any further orders issued by the supreme commander, Allied Expeditionary Force and by the Soviet High Command.4. This act of military surrender is without prejudice to, and will be super-superseded by any general instrument of surrender imposed by, or on behalf of theUnited Nations and applicable to Germany and the German armed forces as awhole.5. In the event of the German High Command or any of the forces under their control failing to act in accordance with this Act of Surrender, the supreme commander, Allied Expeditionary Force and the Soviet High Command will take such punitive or other action as they deem appropriate.Signed at Rheims, France, at 0241 on the 7th day of May, 1945.On behalf of the German High Command.JODL.In the presence of :On behalf of the Supreme Com-mander,   Allied   Expeditionary      On  behalf  of  the  Soviet  HighForce. Command.W. B. SMITH. SUSLOPAROFF.F. SEVEZ,Major-General,   French   Army[Witness).3. Undertaking given by certain German Emissaries to the Allied HighCommands, signed by General Oberst Jodl in Rheims on 7th May,1945.It is agreed by the German emissaries undersigned that the followingGerman officers will arrive at a place and time designated by the supreme commander, Allied Expeditionary Force, and the Soviet High Command,prepared, with plenary powers, to execute a formal ratification on behalf of theGerman High Command of this act of Unconditional Surrender of the german armed forces : Chief of the High Command.Commander-in-Chief of the Army.Commander-in-Chief of the Navy.Commander-in-Chief of the Air Forces.Signed.JODL,Representing the German High Command.Dated 0241, 7th May, 1945,Rheims, France.
4. Authority from Gross Admiral Doenitz to General Field-MarshalKeitel, General Admiral von Friedeburg and General Oberst Stumpf,dated 7th May, 1945.Der Oberste Befehlshaber (Abschrift.)der Wehrmacht.(Bitte in der Antwort vorstehendesGeschaftszeichen, das Datum undkurzen Inhalt anzugeben.) Hauptquartier, den 7. Mai 1945.Ich bevollmachtigeGeneralfeldmarschall Keitel als  Chef des  Oberkommandos derWehrmacht und zugleich als Oberbefehlshaber des Heeres,Generaladmiral    von    Friedeburg    als    Oberbefehlshaber    derKriegsmarine,Generaloberst Stumpf als Vertreter  des  Oberbefehlshabers derLuftwaffezur Ratifizierung der bedingungslosen Kapitulation der Deutschen Streitkraftegegenuber dem Oberbefehlshaber der Alliierten Expeditionsstreitkrafte und demSowyet-Oberkommando.DOENITZ,Gross Admiral.5. Act of Military Surrender (English Version) signed by GeneralField-Marshal Keitel, General Admiral von Friedeburg and GeneralOberst Stumpf in Berlin on the 8th May, 1945.1. We the undersigned, acting by authority of the German High Command,hereby surrender unconditionally to the Supreme Commander, allied expeditionary Force and simultaneously to the Supreme High Command of theRed Army all forces on land, at sea, and in the air who are at this date under german control.2. The German High Command will at once issue orders to all german military, naval and air authorities and to all forces under German control to cease active operations at 2301 hours Central European time on 8th May, 1945,to remain in the positions occupied at that time and to disarm completely,handing over their weapons and equipment to the local allied commanders orofficers designated by Representatives of the Allied Supreme Commands. Noship, vessel, or aircraft is to be scuttled, or any damage done to their hull,machinery or equipment, and also to machines of all kinds, armament, apparatus,and all the technical means of prosecution of war in general.3. The German High Command will at once issue to the appropriatecommanders, and ensure the carrying out of any further orders issued by theSupreme Commander, Allied Expeditionary Force and by the Supreme high command of the Red Army.4. This act of military surrender is without prejudice to, and will besuperseded by any general instrument of surrender imposed by, or on behalf ofthe United Nations and applicable to Germany and the German armed forces as a whole,5.   In the event of the German High Command or any of the forces under their control failing to act in accordance with this Act of Surrender, the Supreme .Commander, Allied Expeditionary Force and the Supreme High Command ofthe Red Army will take such punitive or other action as they deem appropriate.
6. This Act is drawn up in the English, Russian and German languages.The English and Russian are the only authentic texts.Signed at Berlin on the 8th day of May, 1945.Von FRIEDEBURG. KEITEL. STUMPF.On behalf of the German High Command.In the presence of :A. W. TEDDER.r\   u -u r*  * 4.x.   o n On behalf of the Supreme HighOn behalf of the Supreme Com- Command of the Red Army :mander. Allied ExpeditionaryForce. ZHUKOV.At the signing also were present as witnesses :F. de LATTRE de TASSIGNY, CARL SPAATZ,General Commanding in Chief General     Commanding   UnitedFirst French Army. States Strategic Air Forces.



</content>
</cab>
