<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/84/2 images: 7-8</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   CCC86) 28th Conclusions Thursday 17 July 1986 IMMIGRATION CpNTROLS AT LONDON AIRPORT


   MOST CONFIDENTIAL RECORD

TO

CC(86) 28th Conclusions Thursday 17 July 1986

IMMIGRATION THE HOME SECRETARY said that, as he had previously warned colleagues, CONTROLS AT the pressures on the immigration services at London Airport had become LONDON	very great. He was considering whether to introduce a visa requirement

AIRPORT	for nationals of five Commonwealth countries, including Nigeria and

Ghana, but had decided after consultation with the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to postpone further consideration of such a step until after the forthcoming meeting of seven Commonwealth Prime Ministers. The problem was, however, especially acute in relation to Nigeria. The arrival of unusually large numbers of people from Nigeria, many of them on extra unscheduled flights, had produced a further sharp increase on the strains faced by the immigration services at London Airport. The facilities were over-crowded; conditions of squalor now obtained. The staff were understandably dissatisfied. It appeared that the main reason for the sudden influx of Nigerians was rumours in Nigeria of an impending increase in air fares to the United Kingdom. He believed that, if Nigeria could not be persuaded to halt the extra flights to the United Kingdom, he would have as a matter of urgency to introduce visas for Nigerians wishing to visit this country. The reasons, relating to the over-strain of the immigration services, would be convincing; a decision on visas should thus be seen by the public as unrelated to the problems of South Africa. He would consult the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary, the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry and other Ministers closely interested about the question of a visa regime for Nigeria.

In discussion, the view was expressed that the difficulties for the immigration services at London Airport should take priority over other considerations in this matter. At the same time, it was noted that the introduction of a visa regime for Nigeria would cost   7 million net per annum and that there would be significant initial costs as well. The public reaction in this country to the introduction of visas for Nigerians would probably be positive.

The Cabinet -

1.	Invited the Home Secretary, in consultation with the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and other interested Ministers, to consider further as a matter

of urgency the question of introducing visas for Nigerians.

2.	Noted that it might in any case be necessary during the Recess to introduce visas for visitors from Nigeria and four other Commonwealth countries.

Cabinet Office 18 July 1986



</content>
</cab>
