<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/71/0 images: 374-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
U DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT *)g^R E To366COPY NO:CABINET      59  (58).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held in thePrime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons,to-day, Monday, June 27th,  1932,  at 5.30 p.m.AGENDA.m1.    DISARMAMENT,  THE BRITISH PLAN.(Reference Cabinet 38 (32) Conclusion 2.)Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,  covering draft declaration- of British Disarmament Policy.CP.  226(32) - Revise    -    circulated herewith.Note by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,  covering further report of &quot;private conversations&quot;,  etc.CP.  228(32)    -    already circulated.TO TAKE NOTE OFs-2.    THE DEVELOPMENT   ( LOAN GUARANTEES AND GRANTS) ACT.   1929.(Reference Cabinet 35(32) Cohclusion 6.)Memorandum by the Lord President of theCouncil.CP.  229(32)    -    to be circulated.(Signed) R.B.HOWORTH.. Deputy Secretary, Cabinet-Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.27th June,  1932.
f\ fi(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S EGRET, COPY NO.cabinet    59 (38).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held in thePrime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons,on Monday, June 27th. 1938, at 5.30 p.m.AGENDUM.DISARMAMENT.      THE BRITISH PLAN.(Reference Cabinet 38 (38) Conclusion 2).Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.CP.  226 (32)    -   To be circulated.(Signed) R.B. HOWORTHDeputy Secretary,    Cabinet.8, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.124th June, 1932.
CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;room, House of Commons, onMonday, June 27th, 1932,  at.30 .p.m,PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lerd President of the Council,    (In the Chair).e Right Hon.Sir Herbert Samuel, G.C.B.,G.B.E., Mi.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.e Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War,e Right Hon.J-,H;   Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.le Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K.G., M.V.Q., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.The&quot;TisoQunt Sankey,g.b.e.,Lord Chancellor..The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,K.C.V.O., O.B.E. ,K.C.,MP.,Secretary of   State forForeign Affairs,The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E., M.C., M.P.,Secretary of State fcrthe Colonies,The Right Hon.Sir Archibald Sinclair,Bt. , C.M.G. , M.P. ,Secretary of State forScotland,.e Right Hon. The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young, The Viscount Snowden,G,B.E., D.S.O., D.S.C., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.Minister of Health.e Eight Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres-Monsell,G.B.E., M.P., First Lord ofthe Admiralty.Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,C-.B.E., M.P., Minister ofLabour.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O., M.P., Ministerof Agriculture andFisheries.Major The Right Hon.W, Qrmsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.*    ,    *    ,    ,    ,    ,    ,Mr. R,B, Howorth, C.B., C.M.G., Deputy Secretary, Cabinet,
flitrffi DISARMAMENTi^iFERENGE.con(ra o . oGENERAL POLICY,it / (ji)t -(Previous&apos;ReferenceCabinet38 (32)Conclusion 2)1.     With reference to the Conclusion mentionedin the margin, the Cabinet   had before them aMemorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Paper CP. 226 (32)) covering a draft declaration of British Disarmament Policy, thenaval, military and air proposals of which were authorised by the respective Defence Departments.It was stated in the Memorandum that thedraft was being submitted to the Prime Minister andhis colleagues at Lausanne and that it would benecessary to consult the Dominions before making any declaration in public.   Assuming that a satisfactorystatement can be agreed, the Memorandum set out thearguments for putting it forward at the earliestpossible moment by announcement in Parliament withcontemporaneous circulation at Geneva.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS read to the Cabinet the telegrams (Appendix I) which had passed on this subject between the Prime Ministerand&apos;himself since their last Meeting.   He proposedto return by air to Switzerland on June 28th andto confer with the Prime Minister, the Chancellorof the Exchequer and the President of the Board ofTrade on the evening of that day.    If it was decidedto proceed with the British declaration of policythere should be no repetition of the somevirhattheatrical procedure followed when the Hooverdeclaration was published, but at the proper momentcopies of our declaration should be circulated toall the Delegations at Geneva simultaneously withits announcement in the House of Commons.THE CABINET adopted the draft declaration
subject to the following alterations:-Page lo paragraph 1, line 2: delete &quot;striking&quot;.Page 2. paragraph 2: the first sentence to read:-&quot;First, the Government of the UnitedKingdom desire to put on record their agreement with the further principlethat the three problems of Military,- , Naval and Air disarmament are inter-connected.&quot;Page 2o paragraph&apos;2, line 13: for &quot;anticipation&quot;read &quot;advance&quot;.Page 20 paragraph 2: delete sub-paragraph (b).Page 5. paragraph 9 (4): $he wording of this sub-paragraph to be settled by theSecretary of State for Foreign affairs in consultation with the First Lordof the Admiralty.Page 90 paragraph 13: delete second sub-paragraph and insert the following:-&quot;They propose that the High ContractingParties should agree between themselvesin respect of their air forces upon(l) the complete prohibition of allbombing   from the air save within limits to be laid down by an internation-al convention.   Attacks upon the civilian population would be prohibited,,The convention would define as preciselyas possible the limits of permissiblemilitary objectives;(2)    a strict limitation in the un-laden weight of all military and naval aircraft (troop carriers and flying boats excepted);(3) the numbers of all kinds ofmilitary and naval aircraft to be restricted.&quot;Page 9. paragraph 14. The Home Secretary was invited to draft this paragraph.Note:As a result of discussion the Cabinet decided   ,to retain paragraphs 4 and 9 as drafted in CP.226(32).For the text of the Declaration of BritishDisarmament Policy as approved by the Cabinet, seeAppendix II.
In the course of discussion special attention was directed, inter alia, to the following points arising on the draft declaration:-(l)    It was suggested that the declaration should contain an intimation that our navalproposals are qualitative rather thanquantitative and that while their immediate effect will he appreciable it will hesubstantial in the future, and also a specificwarning to the effect that so far from areduction in the cruiser category beingpossible, an increase will actually benecessary in the future to meet our reguire-:&apos;!&quot;V-mentSoIt was generally agreed, however, thatthese and other like considerations couldmore appropriately and conveniently beinserted in the White Paper explanatory ofthe Declaration which would in any case haveto be laid before Parliament0(2)    It was also agreed, that, on the whole, itwould be best to make no reference tnparagraph 5 to possible reactions on the size of coast defence guns of a reduction inthe gun-calibre of capital ships.(3)   The Cabinet were informed that for technical reasons it was undesirable inpresent circumstances to fix a lowermaximum than 22,000 tons with 11 inch guns for capital ships.
. Sfil(4)    Steps should be t aken to demonstrate the-unfairness to this country of the Hooverproposals - for example, if adopted we shouldhave to scrap 4 Hawkins Class and 17 CountyClass cruisers while the U.S.A. would only have to contribute one old 8&quot; gun cruiser and would be allowed 33?000 tons of newcruiser construction.(5)    It was agreed that it would be best to omitfrom the declaration the suggestion that ifthe British proposals were adopted they wouldregulate all further naval construction,including that of Powers Y/hich are not included in the Washington and London NavalTreaties and which may be contemplating new construction in the near future.(6)   The British proposals will facilitateFranco-Italian naval agreement, but it shouldbe left to the French or Italians to pointout their advantage in this respect.(7)   Attention was drawn to the inconsistencyof Mr, Hoover in advocating the total abolition of all tanks at the moment when theAmerican representatives were agreeing in the&quot;private conversations&quot; that the lightertypes were essential for defence purposes and should be retained.(8)   No reference should be made in our proposals to the question of international!sation ofcivil aviation.
It would be necessarys ifthe subject was mentioned in the declaration,to explain precisely what was meant and how the proposal was to be implemented.    In anycase the U.S.A. would never consent toparticipate in any international!sationscheme,The Cabinet were informed that   the position asregards India was that India could acceptMr. Hoover&apos;s quantitative proposals without qualifica-tion.    As regards his qualitative proposals she could accept the land proposals but wanted to put in a pleafor light tanks, she would like to retain the powerto bomb for her frontier requirements. International-isation of civil aviation, if extended to India wouldbe very unpopular from the point of view of indian national sentiment.In regard to future procedure it was generally agreed   that this must be left to be determined by thePrime Minister and his colleagues in Switzerland inthe light of all the relevant circumstances.   In theopinion of the Cabinet it was9 however, very important from the home point of view that a reasoned declaration in regard to the American proposals should bepublished as soon as possible.    In particular we ought not to hold our hands indefinitely for fear ofoffending American, susceptibilities.    If we agreed toobtain AmericaVs assent before making our declarationwe should he involved in embarrassing delays and
might ultimately find ourselves forced to publishand then be charged with breach of faith,   We hadbeen treated very badly by the Americans in thematter of the Hoover Declaration and in the mannerin which it had been promulgated, and it was difficult to see what claim they had to anyconsideration,,On the other hand there was much to be said for taking the French into our confidence before any announcement was made,    In this connection it wassuggested that our declaration might be indicatedconfidentially to the French and American representa-tives in a further &quot;private conversation&quot;.    It was,however, felt that the publication of the Hooverproposals made the continuance of these &quot;provate conversations&quot; very difficult, and that probablysome other.procedure would have to be devised,,Reference was also made to the importance ofindicating the general nature of our proposals tothe Italians and Germans before actual publication.In any case the dominions should be informedforthwith of the contents of the draft declarationas approved by the Cabinet,THE CABINET agreed(l) To take note that the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs proposed immediately on his arrival in Switzerland on June 28thto confer with the Prime Minister, theChancellor of the Exchequer and thePresident of the Board of Trade on thedeclaration of British Disarmament Policyin the form approved by the Cabinet.(2) That the future procedure in regard tothe declaration should be d etermlned by thePrime Minister and his colleagues inSwitzerland in the light of all the relevant circumstances.
(3)    To request the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to convey to the PrimeMinister and his colleagues the generalviews of the Cabinet on the subject of future procedure and in particular their- very strong and definite opinion that9if possibleo an announcement in parliament should be made this week simultaneously with publication at Geneva0(4)     That the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs should be authorised to communicate to the Dominions (other than the IrishFree State) the draft declaration in theform approved by the Cabinet at the sametime making it clear that the document vrasa draft which had been prepared with aview to issue if9 as a result of furtherconsideration it is decided to publish a declaration.
31 Qso2. In the course of the discussion summarised inthe previous Conclusion,  the HOME SECRETARY enquire whether, in the event of a maximum limit of size&quot;being agreed upon in the case of tanks and militaryand naval aircraft, the Government contemplated that existing oversize tanks and planes should he scrappedon the coming into operation of the Convention, orwhether Powers possessing such oversize tanks andplanes should he allowed to retain them until theywere worn out.The Home Secretary also enquired whether itwas our intention to maintain the maximum size of bombing aeroplanes at 3-tons, or whether we wereprepared to accept a lower maximum.With regard to the first question theSECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR agreed that oversize planesshould be scrapped.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR agreed thatoversize tanks should be scrapped if the maximum limit of the size of tanks was agreed at 20-tons or over.If, however, a lower maximum limit than 20-tons wasagreed upon he (the Secretary of State for War) musthave an opportunity of reconsidering the matter.With regard to the second question, theSECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR undertook to consider -themaximum size of bombing aeroplanes in consultation withhis Advisers,, and to inform the Home Secretary as tothe result.The Cabinet took note of, and approved the arrangements summarised above withregard to oversize tanks and aeroplanesand the maximum size of bombing planes.80
DISARMAMENTCONFERENCE.O     13     tfi      Q     QGENERALPOLICY.budgetary limitation:&quot;provate conversations&quot;PROCEDURE.(PreviousReferenceCabinet38(32)conclusion)3. With reference to the Conclusion mentionedin the margin, the Cabinet had before them a Note(Paper CP. 228 (32)) by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs covering (l) a Report of the&quot;Private Conversations&quot; at Geneva on Wednesdayand Thursday last, this Report being in continuation of the Conversations circulated as Annex I to paper CP. 222 (32); and (2) the exchange of messagesbetween Mr. Stimson and the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs following upon President Hoover1sDeclaration, and the discussion at Geneva on june 22nd.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR HOME affairs explained that it had been agreed with the american and French Representatives that it would be difficult for the three Delegations to discuss the HooverProposal in the &quot;Private Conversations&quot; withoutfurther opportunity of consulting their Governments,and it had therefore been decided to proceed with theconsideration of the most important item remainingon the Agenda, namely Budgetary Limitation.He had understood that the Cabinet were somewhatreluctant to adopt Budgetary Limitation on the grounds that, while we had drastically reduced our expenditureon armaments since the War, other countries hadeither not reduced or had been increasing their expenditure, and that the actual proposals whichhad been before the Cabinet would have operated invarious ways most unfairly against this country.
Throughout the discussions on this subject, which hadtaken place on the 23rd and 24th June, he (the HomeSecretary) had emphasised on several occasions that thediscussions must he regarded as entirely non-committaland as purely tentative, and that the proposals had notbeen considered by the British Government and must he regarded merely as a basis for discussion.The Cabinet were reminded that this subject hadbeen considered by a special Cabinet Committee which,after consultation with the Dominion Representatives, had reported against the principle of Budgetary Limitation.Certain of the Dominions were even more opposed than wewere to the principle, and for very excellent andconvincing reasons.    The Cabinet had, in effect, acceptedthe Report of the Committee, and the Dominions had been assured that they need have no apprehensions in regardto Budgetary Limitation.     It was understood that theUnited Kingdom Representatives at Geneva had been warnedas to the objections of the Dominions to the principleof Budgetary Limitation, and as to the desirability ofthe Dominion Representatives being consulted before thisquestion was raised.at the &quot;Private Conversations&quot;.The Home Secretary explained that he hadreceived the impression at Geneva that the Dominions didnot object in principle to Budgetary Limitation, but towhat might be regarded as a matter of detail, namelyglobal application of the principle to the UnitedKingdom and the Dominions.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR reminded theCabinet that the United Kingdom Representatives at Geneva
had apparently favoured global limitation on the groundthat it would allow any economies in one Service resultingfrom the Disarmament Convention to be used, if desired, inmailing good our present or future deficiencies in other services.    It was impossible for the War Office to accept any such suggestion.     As the Cabinet v/ere aware, theArmy had been reduced to the lowest possible limits, and thespecial economies of last Autumn had only been found by thenon replacement of munitions, the postponement of essentialbuilding programmes, and the abandonment for this year  oftraining of the Territorials.     These economies could not be repeated next year, and it  was quite impossible for theWar Office to continue at the present level of expenditure.The proposition that the War Office should agree toglobal limitation was not one that it was possible for himto entertain.      The question was not one of figures;no further economies were possible.     The economiescontemplated in the Declaration were inapplicable to theUnited Kingdom since we were not building large tanks orspending money on material for chemical or bacteriologicalwarfare, while the personnel of the Army had beenreduced below even the &apos;policeT component basis.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR HOME affairs pointed out that the British Representatives at Genevahad themselves represented the unfairness of takingpresent figures and attempting to effect all-roundreductions on them.     The French Delegation had recognisedthis, and had admitted that, in proposing any cut, account would have to be taken of the recent trend in each country.
The Cabinet were reminded that the Admiralty-regarded the principle of Budgetary Limitation as open tothe gravest objections.   The French had good reason to favour the principle of global limitation, because their expenditure on armaments in recent years had been at itshighest, while that of other countries, including theUnited Kingdom, had been reduced to the lowest possible level.      The Admiralty had only been able to secure the economy cuts this year by postponing essential expenditure;and these cuts, as in the case of the Army, could not be repeated.In the course of further discussion it was pointedout that before there could be any question of even a provisional agreement in regard to Budgetary Limitation,it would be necessary for the Representatives of theUnited States of America to accept the principle, and this they had always declined to do on the ground of constitutional difficulties.     The suggestion was made that it would probably be found undesirable to continuethe &quot;private conversations&quot; after the publication of theBritish Disarmament Declaration, and that probably thebest arrangement would be to have general discussions atGeneva on the American and British Declarations; and thatafter these discussions the Conference should adjournuntil the Autumn.It was pointed out, however, that there was a strong desire at Geneva to reach definite decisions before theend of July, with a view to leaving the Expert and othercommittees to prepare a draft Convention for the consider-ation of the Conference in the Autumn.     It was generally
agreed that this was much too optimistic a view of what could possibly be effected before the end of July,and that there was much to be said for the plan of asecond reading Debate on the American and BritishDeclarations, to be followed by an adjournment toenable the principal States to confer among themselves with a view to reaching the greatest possible measureof agreement before the Conference reassembled inthe Autumn.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,27th June, 1932.
APPENDIX.    I.Cypher telegram to British Delegation, (Lausanne),Foreign Office, 24th June, 1932. 10.00 p.m.No.  9.IMPORTANT.   .Following from Secretary of State for PrimeMinister.Cabinet decided to-day to hold further meetingabout our disarmament policy with special reference to president Hoover&apos;s manifesto next Monday afternoon at 5.30.Parliamentary Questions and other enquiries seem to make it essential that we should put out as soon as possible someconnected statement of our attitude to American proposals.I am to draft such a statement during the week-end and am therefore not returning to Switzerland till Tuesday.Londonderry will be here and we are asking Samuel also toreturn tomorrow for Monday&apos;s meeting.2. I hope that you will approve this course whichI am convinced has become necessary since we cannot leave theHoover proposals without some considered declaration.      i hope to be able to submit draft of this for consideration ofyourself, Chamberlain and Runciman by Monday morning.      Ifthis could be agreed after Monday&apos;s Cabinet I should proposeto consult Dominions and make statement, public by circulatingit at Geneva at the same time that it was made in Parliament.All this however depends on whether we can formulate astatement covering the ground.
3. Samuel is willing to return tomorrow,Saturday- evening, if you approve but would much liketo come over to Lausanne first and explain certaintentative     suggestions connected with budgetary limitation.     So far as I understand it, one of thedifficulties seems to be that in some cases our defence services cannot agree to remain on theirpresent figures of expenditure.     Also a globaltotal raises difficulty with the Dominions.      Ishould not in any case propose to include thesedetailed matters in the proposed general statement.
Decypher.Mr. Perowne, (Lausanne),D.1,30 a,m.25th June, 1932.26th June, 1932.r.9.30 a.m.26th June, 1932.No.. 19.--o-o-o-o-o-o-IMMBDIATE.Following from Prime Minister for Secretary ofState.Personal.Your telegram No. 9.I have had consultation with Ministers here after hearing from Sir H. Samuel report that he will make toyou on Sunday afternoon.As at present advised we are doubtful as to whetherit is desirable or possible to make any further pronounce--ment at present on Hoover Plan as a whole.     Naval proposals in particular require very careful study in detail.Tffe hope that you will send us terms of your draft state-in ent by telegraph on Sunday in order to give us time to putour considered views before French Minister.
Cypher telegram to British Delegation (Lausanne)..Foreign Office, 26th June, 1932,    10.21 p.m.No. 11.IMMEDIATE.Following from Secretary of State for Prime Minister:Your telegram No. 19.My immediately follo-wing telegrams contain the text of the draft -which is being circulated to the Cabinet forits meeting at 5.30 on Monday.     Though not a final draftit represents much collaboration and the proposals have the specific approval of the three service departments.Questions in Parliament asking for Government&apos;s attitudetowards Hoover proposals illustrate the difficulty of makingno further statement.     If a satisfactory statement couldbe approved, it might be announced in Parliament at the sametime as it is circulated at Geneva.
From SWITZERLAND.Decypher,British Delegation (Lausanne)27th June, 1932.(hy telephone) 12.50 p.m.     2727th June, 1932.12.50 p.m.27th June, 1932.No. 21.IMMEDIATE.Following from Prime Minister.Ministers here unable to gauge accurately,pressure in the Commons and country for further declarationbut they see dangers ahead.     They would have preferred a procedure by which Ministers in London having heard and discussed reportfrom those working in Geneva would have indicated their views.Geneva Ministers would then return immediately and six membersof Cabinet here would consider whole position at once, perhapssound other delegations here specially Americans and make finalrecommendation to London Ministers.     Telegrams giving proposed statement to Cabinet came too late to enable us to study it indetail.     Number 14 is not yet decyphered and cannot be inour hands before noon.     In any event we should require toknow comments of Services and Ministers in London if we are tomake useful contribution to Government decision.I lunched with Davis and Gibson yesterday.     Theywould like further examination with us before any new declara-tion is made unless it is decidedly helpful and it would be advisable to resume contact with them without delay.We are greatly concerned to maintain the best relationspossible with America as we are firmly convinced not only agood agreement on debts9 but on other important matters, depends on this.
APPENDIX II0      SECRET,DECLARATION OF BRITISH DISARMAMENT policy as approved &quot;by the Cabinet on June 27th 1952.(Cabinet 39(53) Conclusion 1).1.     The Government of the United Kingdom welcome President Hoover&apos;declaration, alike because it calls for a really substantial measureof actual disarmament and because it seeks to apply the two principles for which the United Kingdom delegation has been contending from theopening of the Conference - the principles of quantitative and of quali-tative limitation.     As President Hoover says &quot;Reduction should becarried out not only by broad general cuts in armaments but by increas-ing the comparative power of defence through decreases in the powerof the attack&quot;.Success at Geneva depends upon general agreement, and the Ameri-can delegation has made it plain that President Hoover&apos;s proposals are.put forward as a contribution to an agreed general programme.     TheUnited Kingdom Government have already advanced wide suggestions oftheir own.     These, while they differ in some important respects asto method or measure, are inspired by the same purpose, and a compari-son will show that already there is a substantial area of common ground.Without interrupting or anticipating detailed discussions whichmust take place with the other delegations represented at Geneva, itis convenient at this moment to set out in broad outline the maincharacteristics of the British proposals.     They in their turn shouldbe regarded, not as a declaration of isolated action, but as a contri-
2.      First, the Government of the United Kingdomdesire to put on record their agreement with thefurther principle that the three problems ofMilitary, Naval and Air disarmament are inter-connected.International agreement cannot be attained without an adequate contribution from all three sources.Inasmuch as Britain, like the United States, findsher strongest arm in the navy, the contribution whichconcerns her most is to be found in this sphere,in which, as is well known, contributions to dis-armament on the largest scale have already beenmade in advance of the General Disarmament Conference.Nevertheless the British Government now offer a further contribution as part of a general world settlement.3.      It is now proposed to set out under the threenecessary heads the manner in which the Governmentof the United Kingdom would suggest that these principles Could be applied.-2-
Naval Proposals.4.      These proposals cover all types of vessel - capital ships,aircraft carriers,  cruisers, destroyers and submarines.It is essential that proposals that are intended to beadopted by general agreement should make due provision   forvarying circumstances.      Having regard to the widely -scatteredresponsibilities of the British Navy and to the conjoint interestsof the members of the British Commonwealth, it is not practicable to cut down the number of naval units beyond a certain point,even though other Powers, whose responsibilities are more con-centrated, might find it possible to do so.      But it is perfectlypossible and in the highest degree desirable to adopt a mode oftreatment which will secure by other means the large reductionsat which we are all aiming.      The present Treaty limits of size and gun calibre are far too high,and the United KingdomGovernment consider     that a very large reduction, amounting tofebout one third in the case both of capital ships and cruisers,can be made in future construction.5.      As regards capital ships, the position under the existingNaval Treaties is that the maximum size for future constructionhas been fixed at 35,000 tons and the gun at 16 inches.      Asbetween Britain, the United States and Japan, however, no further capital ship construction can be undertaken until the year 1937.The proportions of such ships as between these three Powers is inthe ratio 15 : 15 :  9.      Now, the total tonnage of a category ofships can be reduced either by diminishing their number or bydiminishing their size.      The American proposal to reduce 15capital ships to 10 would leave the size of these enormouslyexpensive vessels untouched.      Not only so but&apos; guns of 16 inchcalibre would remain in any future construction of capital ships.Every figure in -
volved in these huge dimensions - initial cost, upkeep, personnel,ammunition,stores, docks, - would he maintained at the highest level.      The United Kingdom proposal, while securing no less^reduction in total tonnage, avoids these consequences by (I)reducing the size of the gun,  (2) reducing the size of the ship.For example, if the calibre of the gun is reduced to 12 inchesthe maximum size of the ship can be reduced from 35,000 to 25,000tons, and an immense saving is effected under both heads, bothinitially and consequentially.6.     But the Government of the United Kingdom are prepared to go beyond this.      They are ready to apply the same principles tocruisers, and to reduce their maximum size and gun-calibre by international agreement from the present figure of 10,000 tonsand 8 inches to 7,000 tons and 6.1 inches.      It would then bepossible to reduce the dimensions in the case of capital shipsstill further and fix a maximum of 22,000 tons with 11 inch guns.This will nearly halve the initial cost of any future capital ship and greatly reduce the cost of maintenance.      Thus the wholescale would come down together and their would be a definitereturn to smaller dimensions.      On this basis the British proposal would effect an ultimate reduction in capital-ship tonnagealone of 195,000 tons, whereas the comparable figure under theUnited States proposal would be about 175,000.7.      As regards aire:raft carriers, the Government of the UnitedKingdom are in substantial agreement with President Hoover&apos;sproposals.      They propose a reduction in the size of the aircraft carrier from 27,000 to 22,000 tons with consequent reduction in total tonnage from 135,000 to 110,000 tons.8.      Special reference must be made to the Submarine,      The Britishview has been, and is, that the submarine should be entirely abolished.l?If its abolition can be secured, this will at once lead to areduction of approximately one-third in destroyer
tonnage.    If international agreement to abolish submarines isfound impossible cf attainment, ocean going submarines should begot rid of by limiting the size to 250 tons, and the total tonnage to the lowest figure upon which agreement can be reached.9.      Consequentlyj the   Government of the United Kingdom puts forward fer immediate adoption by international agreement thefollowing set of proposals relating to the navies of the world:(l) Reduce the maximum size *f any future capital ship to22,000 trns, and the maximum calibre of the guns carried to 11inches.(2) Reduce the maximum size cf cruisers hereafter constructedtq 7,000 tons, and maximum calibre of guns to 6.1 inches.(3) Even if international agreement on point 2 cannot besecured, the Government of the United Kingdom would still urge that the maximum size of capital ships should be reduced to25,000 tons and their guns to 12 inches as a maximum.(4) Reduce the maxima for aircraft carriers to 22,000 tonswith 6.1 inch guns..(5) Abolish submarines.(6) Reduce destroyer tonnage by approximately one third, thisdepending on the abolition of submarines.(7)  If submarines cannot be completely abolished, fix their maximum surface displacement at 250 tons, with a strictlimitation both of total tonnage and number of units.The British proposals in the r,aval sphere, taken together,will be f**und in the case of the British Navy to involve anet total ultimate reduction of no less than 281,700 tons,and an immediate reduction of about 1.00,000 tons.
LAND PROPOSALS.10.    In the realm of land disarmament it is satisfactory to find that the proposals already put forward by HisMajesty&apos;s Government appear to be in harmony with the spiritwhich has inspired the latest proposals of President Hoover.Naturally it will be necessary carefully to examine thedetails of the American proposals before expressing a finalopinion on their suitability to the situation of each country.11.    To consider in turn the four categories to which theseproposals relate;-(a) In regard to chemical and bacteriological warfareHis Majesty&apos;s Government have already joined in rejecting the use of these methods of warfare and therefore cordiallywelcome the United States proposals under this head.(b) In regard to land guns, His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave proposed the abolition of all mobile guns of a calibregreater than 155 mm.   (6.1 inches calibre).      Considerablestress was laid in the discussion at Geneva, on thedifficulties due to the problem of drawing any clear lineof demarcation between fixed and mobile artillery.      HisMajesty&apos;s Government believe, however, that the difficulty is theoretical rather than practical.     Under this headalso His Majesty&apos;s Government find themselves, therefore, infull accord with the proposals of the United StatesGovernment.
(c) In regard to the strength of land armies,    HisMajesty&apos;s Government have consistently placed in the forefront of their proposals for land disarmament the examination of measures for the reduction of effectivesto the lowest level compatible with national safety.Without waiting for agreement to be reached on this head,His Majesty&apos;s Government have already reduced their own forces to the minimum numbers required for the preservation of internal order and for the defence of their overseas possesions and communications.The United States proposal for a division of land forces into a &quot;police component&quot; and a &quot;defencecomponent&quot; raises points of some difficulty and willrequire very careful examination;    but so far as HisMajesty&apos;s Government understand the suggested basisof calculation, the result will be to show that theBritish land forces have already been reduced substantially below the number recognised to be necessary for themaintenance of internal order, without making any allowance for the forces needed for the protection of lines of communication between the United Kingdom and the overseas territories.(d) In regard to tanks, His Majesty&apos;s Government havealready advocated the abolition of all tanks above aweight of 20 tons, which by their characteristics are specially suitable for offensive employment in battle.In the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Government to advocate the abolition of all tanks would not contribute in the longrun to the cause of disarmament.
Tanks of the lighter type cannot he regarded as specificallyoffensive weapons.      Their comparatively light armour andtheir reduced capacity for crossing trenches render themunsuitable for the assaultsf highly organised defences.But as a means of saving the life of the soldiers, aswell as of economisimg man power,tanks are invaluable.      Ina small voluntarily enlisted army like our own they constitute an    essential compensation for lack of numbers whichit would be impossible to surrender.      As far as this countryis concerned, in view of its world-wide responsibilities, anygeneral prohibiticn would require an increase in our presentland forces in terms  of man power,  and thus,  as a measure of disarmament would tend to defeat its own ends.12.    It will be seen therefore that in the realm of landdisarmament the proposals of the United States Government,  sofar as they relate to matters which directly touch the land forces of the United Kingdom and ef the countries of the BritishCommonwealth, approximate very closely to those already putforward by   His Majesty&apos;s Government; and that in the total oftheir effectives His Majesty&apos;s Government have been able alreadyto put into practice a measure of disarmament which goes beyondthe standards proposed by President Hoover.-8-
13. There is no aspect of international disarmament morevitally urgent than the adoption without delay of the most effective measures to preserve the civilian population fromthe fearful horrors of bombardment from the air.      The Gevern-ment of the United Kingdom would be prepared to go to any length, in agreement with other Powers, to achieve this object,and if more drastic measures are proposed from any other quarterand are shown to be practicable,  they will examine them with theutmost sympathy.They propose that the High Contracting Parties should agree between themselves in respect of their air forces thatthere should be(l)      the complete prohibition of all bombing from theair save within limits to be laid down by aninternational convention.     Attacks upon the civilian population would be prohibited.      The convention woulddefine as precisely as possible the limits ofpermissible military objectives;(2)      a strict limitation in the unladen weight of all military and naval aircraft (  troop carriers and flying boats excepted);(3)      a restriction in the numbers of all kinds of military and naval aircraft.
APPENDIX    II.ANNEX.After the Meeting of the Cabinet on June &apos;27tk.the Home Secretary settled, in consultation with theService Departments, the three concluding paragraphs ofthe draft Declaration attached hereto.On June 28th the First Lord of the Admiraltyrequested the Home Secretary to arrange for the inclusion in any statement of British Disarmament proposals of a table,a copy of which is also attached hereto.(Intd.) r.B.H.Deputy Secretary, Cabinet,28th June, 1932
14. One of the most notable of the reductions proposedby President Hoover is the diminution by one-third in thenumber of effectives forming part of what   is termed theDefence Component of Armies, as distinct from the PoliceComponent;    together with a limitation of the PoliceComponent in accordance with a fixed standard.     We earnestlytrust that the countries concerned will accept this proposal.The United Kingdom Government, having abolished conscriptionafter the War, possesses no Defence Component at all as defined in the Presidents proposals, while, as previouslystated, its Police Component is already considerably belowthe standard of strength that his plan would authorise.15,       It is indeed essential to bear in mind the extentof British disarmament already effected, both on sea and, by measures additional to the abolition of conscription, on lend.If a comparison is made with the year before the War, it will be,y.:found that in completed ships the capital ships of the BritishCommonwealth have been reduced from 69 to 15, its cruisers from108 to 52, its destroyers from 285 to 147 and its submarines from74 to 52.     The personnel of the British Army, including itscontingents in India, has been reduced in the same period from259,000 men to 207,000j    and this has been effected by the disband&quot;ment of 9 regiments of calvary, 61 batteries and companies of artillery, 21 companies of Royal
3^ Qsi a-   iEngineers, 21 battalions of infantry and 6 battalions of colonial and troops locally enrolled.      In audition therehas been during the same period a net reduction of personnel of the Indian Army of approximately 20,000 men.     The air arm was in its infancy in 1914 and no comparison can be madewith that date, but it must be mentioned that in the numberof military and naval aeroplanes the United Kingdom standsonly fifth in the list of States;    and that of the aircraftauthorised for home defence in 1923 by the United KingdomGovernment, with the approval of Parliament, 20 per cent. .have not in fact been constructed,16. Great and far-reaching as these reductions havebeen - beyond comparison greater than any which have been effected elsewhere outside the countries disarmed by theTreaty of Versailles - His Majesty&apos;s Government(s) in theUnited Kingdom, /&quot;the Dominions and india? are ready,and indeed eager, to join in further measures for which general agreement can be attained.     The proposals whichaccordingly are now made constitute an additional contribu-tion, practical and extensive, to the effort to relieve theheavy burdens which the maintenance of existing standardsimposes upon the world, and which the world expects us, bya great common effort, effectively to diminish.This statement is only appropriate if it has been agreedthat the United Kingdom representatives should speak onbehalf of the whole British Commonwealth, including theDominions and India.
EVENTUAL REDUCTION IN TONNAGE AT PRESENTPERMITTED TO BRITISH COMMONWEALTH BY THEWASHINGTON &amp; LONDON NAVAL TREATIES WHICHWOULD RESULT- FROM THE BRITISH PROPOSALS.(a) Capital Ships- 150,000(b) Aircraft Carriers(c) Submarines(d) Cruisers(e) Destroyers- 45,000 Conditional on proposal__regarding cruisers..- 195,000- 85,000- 58,700*   41,000 Increase.50,000 Conditional on abolition of submarines,Total Nett Reduction881,700 tons./&quot;NOTE;    The Admiralty have particularly requested, that the above Table may be included in any^statement of British Disarmament proposals^/

</content>
</cab>
