<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/5/36 images: 536-547</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY-rS GOVEPJ^IEITT.SECRET o COPY NO. StTfnP.   (R.) (40)86.W A R__CABINET.OIL POSITION.Twenty-Sixth Weekly Report submitted by the Secretaryfor Mines covering the period up to midnight on the3rd March, 1940.     (Previous Report:    Paper W.P.(R, )(40)  75.)(Initialled) G. l.Richmond Terrace,S.W.  1.5th March, 1940,

colTwenty-sixth Weekly Keport on the Oil Position..Stocks of petroleum for the Services show no appreciablechange from those reported in lest week&apos;s return, hut it is interesting to note that the stock of moto!1 spirit for theB.E.F.  shows a further increase.On the civil side the stock of motor spirit fell slightly.Stock of kerosene again decreased, hut the position of other products improved.    The rapid fall in fuel oil   stockspreviously observed was checked but a substantial increase is required to re-establish a satisfactory position.    TheAdmiralty have agreed to place at the disposal of &apos;civil&apos;  twotankers now in naval service for two voyages each.    other measures are also under consideration.    The deliveries ofvaporising oil reflected the increased demand from farmers,but the increase was more than offset by the fall in demandfor burning oil.The number of tankers which arrived in this country during the week was thirteen of which four were engaged on admiralty Service.    This was a decrease of ten on theprevious week.    These fluctuations in tanker arrivals are dueto the irregular arrival of convoys.Particulars in respect of the past six weeks, togetherwith the weekly average for the three pre-war months and forthe past five months are set out in Table II.For the reason given above the total quantity of allproducts imported during the week (Table III) was 126,500 tons,a decrease of 48 per cent, when compared with the previousweek.The total imports during February (Table IV) were slightly lower than those for January.The forward programme for the four weeks ending30th March (Table V) continues to show an improvement over those of recent weeks.

Table     I.Table II.Table III.Table    IV.Table V,Table    VI.Deliveries for consumption continued at a fairly high level.    (Table VI).-QjOTBo The export of creosote has been prohibited except under  -License as creosote can be used as fuel oil.      The estimatedstock in storage at the present time is about 130,000 tons.In addition,  there are at the various distilleries,  stocksof crude tar and tar products which could in an emergencybe used as fuel,  estimated at about  00,000 tons.Arrangements are now being made, by discussions betweenthe Tar Distillers,  the Creosote producers and the petroleum Board, for the latter to be provided with creosoteor creosote/pitch mixture,  suitable for use as fuel oil,at the rate of  0,000 tons per month,  during, the next12 months.The following tables are appended;-Stocks  (a)  Service,(b) Civil.Tanker arrivals.Tonnage of imports on weekly basis.Tonnages imported during past five months.Forward programme of tanker arrivals.Consumption from civil stocks.

193915th Feb.1940Kingdomviation Spirit i            900&apos;otor Spirit 300-el and Diesel Oil 3,050,000ucricating Oil 5,500^rseas:el &quot;and Diesel Oil j 2, 936,000ucricating Oil^?IOEi &quot;united Kingdomiotor Spiritiessl1 Oilucricating Oil&apos;l3IssL3j5 ( B, S. F. )Dtor SpiritLesel Oilucricating OilraFISTRY900144,9005,0003,200iited KingdomL at ion SpiritICO octane other GradesTotaluori eating Oil153,000323;OOP476,00017,400Tons1,5802102,706,0004,8602,577,5004,250127,200-6,55012,65055,0002,1503,470196,000514,0(30510,00052nd Feb. ,194029th Feb.,194054,000Tons1,3602102,683,0004,8202,604,000ns4,310137,2406,52015 ,08033,5102,0603 .4-20199,000517,000516,00054,1001,3201902,675,0004,7702,586,0004,330157,9206,25014,49040,8002,0005,260199,000525,000522,OOP54,000&quot;overseas (West of Suez)nation Spirit100 octane other Grades 500Total I SOPjubricating Oil       I 205,60019,4002i000(B.E.F. )4,60018,6002,500(B.E.F.)!)i) Not yet available)Lviltor andmer Spirit&apos;oseneporising Oilher GradesTotalsj Diesel anduel OilSeating Oils;tte and Process;ls-ocalsTABLE i (b).51st Aug., j     15th Feb.1959 1940 tons 1,051,00055,000206,000241,000985,000255,000455,0003,965,000Tons1,098,00081,000148,000229,000555,000181,000239,-900i 22nd Feb., 29th Feb.Weeks19401940TonsTons1,100,000     11,085,000  I   19I86,000155,000221,OOP516,000181,OPP255,OOP85,0P0 I 39&amp;-/122,000  !     7tt205,00011517,000187,000922^255,OOP I Included2,280,000       j 8,253,000!2,247,OOP iabove.k Eased on deliveries during previous four week,/ This is high because the deliveries during the first threeweeks have been on a very low level owing to bad weather..TABLE I  (a).

TAB1E II.Tanker Arrivals.Weekly Average;June - August, 1939For 4 weeks ended: -3Cth September,193928th October,  193925th November,  193923rd December, 193920th January,  1940&apos;.86k ending27th January,  19403rd February, 194010th February, 194017th February, 194024th February, 19402nd March,  1940East CoastWest Coast;GrandAdmiralty	Others	Total	Admiralty  iOthers		Total	Totali 2 1 li	16 &amp;ir 2 si 7 6	16 5i 2i si 9i	1 1 li 2i	14 7i 7i 9i 8 10	15 7i 8 11 ioi 12	31 13 ioi 18i 19 . 2li2 2 1 2 1 1	7 6 8 3 4 2    ]	9 8 9 5 5 3	......   ^ 2 3 2 O  -3	15 8 8 10 17 7	19 10 11 12 19 10	28 18 20 17 24 13k During June-August only 1 Admiralty tanker discharged at an east Coast port.During the 4 weeks ended 30th September, 6 prize cargoes or part cargoes are included;    during the 4 weeks ended28th October the number was 2.TABLE III.Weekly Average.Tonnages of imports on weekly basis.Ai rJune-August,1939   -For 4 weeks ended 30th September, 1939&quot;      28th October, 1939&quot;      25th November, 1939&quot;     23rd December, 1939&quot;      20th January,  1940uitiiiritiiiiWeek ending27th January, 19403rd February,, 1S4010th February, 194017th February, 194024th February, 19402nd March, 1940Civil,TonsiMinistryj    andi War Office,j    Tons262,200131,10091,400153,100138,900144,200194,400127,500158,200j129,700181,50083,900i3006,00013,4008,30020,30018,20014,90019,0003,10029,700x900j Admi raltyTons7,80010,60030,50042,60061,10054,40037,70048,80043,10032,30041,500Total.Tons270,000131,4C0108,000197,000189,800225,6001267,000180,1001226,0001175,900; 243,300.x1126,300x Includes 9,300 tons of Motor Spirit discharged at Havre on accountof War Office supplies to the B.E.F.

-5-TABLE IV.September, 1939October, 1939November, 1939December, 1939January, 1940-February, 1940TOTAL- -v.-. :                  .... . Admiralty		Othe rs		Total	Tankers No. 7 12 28 20 15	Cargoes Tons 64,600 124,900 285,500 195,300 165,700	Tankers No. 52 49 60 68 72 68	Cargoes Tons 525,700 494,200 657,300 670,500 755,000 694,900	T anke rs No. 52 56 72 96 92 85	Cargoes Tons 525,700 558,800 782,200 956,000 950,300 860,60082	856,000	569	5,777,600	451	4,615,600TABLE V.Tankers (excluding those on-Admiralty account)  arrived or expectedto arrive during the four weeks ending 50th March, 1940.Number of Tankers;Products:Aviation spirit motor and other Spirit Kerosene Lubricating oil gas, Diesel and Fuel oils crude Oil(subject to correction)85Tons51,900TotalTABLE VI.289,20078,20080,500202,900116,900819,400    (Weekly average204,850)Corresponding figure in last week&apos;s retun188,900.Consumption of Petroleum Products.Consumption from civil stocks since the outbreak of war compared withthe 1938 average weekly consumption and the Oil Board estimate of requirementsMotorandOtherSpiritkeroseneGas, Fuel Lub-_________________________________m  I    and       I ricat-Vaporising j Other   [Diesel     i ingOil        j Grades joils j OilsWeekly Average for 1958Oil Board estimated weekly consumption weekly Average for 4 weeks ended:30th September, 193929th October, 193925th November, 193923rd December, 193920th January, 1940Week Ending:22th January, 1940wrd February, 194010th February, 194017th February, 194024th February, 19402nd March, 1940Tons95,00070,000112,00052,00062,00063,00057,00053,00047,00000,00061,00055., 00062*000Tons1 Tons15,00012,000Tons66,000Tons9,000!62, 000     .11,5005,2004, 7005, 7002,9002,5001,2008001,4001,6001,9004,000110,900i10,400ill,500(15,600j17,000I 25,000&quot;19,90020,00018,00018,20015,20065,00050,00062,00070,000&apos;64,80062,00060,00067,00062,00067,00068.000&apos;&apos;16,000&apos;16,000ai,5oo111,500110,800j 9,000! 6,000j 8,900ao,ooo10,000! 8,000


</content>
</cab>
