<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/17/10 images: 72-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  January 1941.SECRET;W.M. (41)10th Conclusions.Copy iNo.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AMD KBIT.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 10 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, January 27, 1941, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon.,Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Aircraft Production.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and Minister ofNational Service.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Item 8).The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper,M.P., Minister of Information.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chiefof Naval Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 1-6).The Right Hon. H. D. Margesson,M.P., Secretary of State for War. &quot;The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland(Item 6).The Right Hon. Malcolm MacDonald,M.P., Minister of Health (Item 6).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-6).General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Air   Chief   Marshal   Sir   CharlesSecretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Xaior-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[22159]
WAR CABINET 10 (41).Contents.minute no. Subject.1.      Naval, Military and Air Operations .........Air Operations.Naval Operations.Military Operations:. Libya.Eritrea.2.      Italian East AfricaAbyssinia:Position of the White Population.Attitude towards the Emperor Haile Selassie.3*      Belgium............................King of the Belgians.4.      United States of america the Lease-Lend Bill.5.      Man-Power&apos;    - Fighting Service requirements:Registration and calling up.6.      Chemical Warfare     ....      .....      ....      ....      ....Precautionary measures.7.  ; Royal Navy    ....     ....     .... ....-Dartmouth Scholarships.8.      United States of America    ....      ........Disclosure of Secret Information on Supply Matters.9.     Royal Air Force........ ........Proposed Contribution to Benevolent Fund from Public Funds.
Naval, Militaryand? air operations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (41) 9thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.naval operations.MilitaryOperations.Libya.Eritrea.in1.   The Chiefs of Staff: jnade the following reportsamplification of the information contained in Cabinet War RoomRecords 509-512.On the night of the 26th/27th 17 of our bombers had attackedHanover.There was evidence that some 20 per cent, of the German first-line air strength had been moved from aerodromes facing thiscountry to other theatres or to the interior of Germany.The present lull was, however, due to unfavourable weather conditions.The Illustrious had arrived at Alexandria. Enemy aircraft had failed to locate her, but the escorting forces had been unsuccess-fully attacked by dive-bombers.Five Norwegian ships totalling some 27,000 tons had success-fully broken out of the Skagerrak, and reached this country. Theyhad on board a valuable cargo of machine tools. This operationreflected great credit on those who had planned and executed it.The enemy force at Mechili was stronger than anticipated, butplans were in hand for dealing with it.At Tobruk over 25,000 prisoners had been taken.Our forces were closing in on enemy forces holding positionsround Agordat and Barentu. Over 1,100 prisoners had now been captured in these operations.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Italian EastAfrica.Abyssinia.Position of theWhitePopulation.Attitudetowards theEmperor HaileSelassie.(previous reference erence:W.M. (4i) 9tbConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Prime Minister said that the white population in abyssinia, numbering some 200,000, might be in great danger if therevolt spread. The duty of making the first move lay with theItalian authorities, who had made no suggestions to us. We couldnot take any steps on the matter at the moment, but he invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to watch the situation.As invited by the Cabinet, he had telegraphed to General Smutsregarding our attitude towards the Emperor, Haile Selassie(telegram No. 92 of the 26th January). General Wavell foresawcertain difficulties, which, however, could be met, provided it wasmade clear to the Emperor.that he should take the advice of theCommander-in-Chief, Middie East, on all matters which affected the conduct of the war.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Belgium. 3;   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theKing of the Belgian Government had expressed anxiety regarding the attitudeBelgians. of the King of the Belgians, and feared that he might make a dealwith the Germans and form some kind of Government. The onlyaction that could usefully be taken at the moment was to arrange that private messages should be sent to him encouraging him tostiffen his attitude. He would consult the Prime Minister on this:; matter. -   -   - - -The War Cabinet took note of this statement.[22159].b--2-
United States ofAmerica.The; Lease-LendBill:    &apos; &apos;(Previous &apos;\ -Reference:W.M. (41) 5thConclusions,.Minute 8.)4. The Prime Minister said that Mr. Hopkins had receiveda message from President Roosevelt requesting him to cable to america at once a list of our most immediate demands which couldbe met during the next few months. The President hoped that the&quot; Lease-Lend &quot; Bill would be passed into law towards the end ofFebruary.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Man-Power.Fighting service requirements.Registration and.calling-up.(previous references:W.M. (41) 1stConclusions,Minute 12, andW.M. (41) 9thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Labour and National Service (W.P. (G.) (40) 336).The Prime Minister said he had received the proposals of theSecretary of State for War for a. more economical use of the man-power already serving in the Army, but was not yet ready to discuss them. In the meantime, he saw no objection to the issue of a &apos;Proclamation to enable the remaining age groups between 18 and40 to be registered.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he intended, simultaneously with the issue of the Proclamation, to announce that he was considering the revision of the Schedule of reserved Occupations, on the basis that exemption from MilitaryService would increasingly be made dependent on the work actuallybeing done by any man reserved, as well as on his occupation andage.He considered that he had dealt with the pledge that men under20 should be among the latest classes to be called up by virtue of a passage in his speech in the House of Commons on the 21st January.The War Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Labour and National service to submit for approval by The King in Council a proclamation making the remaining age groups between18 and 40 liable for service under the National Service(Armed Forces) Act, and to proceed with the registration in the order shown, of the following classes, 19, 37, 38,39, 40.Chemical ,-Warfare.precautionary measures.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 8thConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The War Cabinet had before them a Report by the Chiefsof Staff (W.P. (41) 14) and a Memorandum by the Home secretary and Minister of Home Security (W.P, (41) 15).In discussion the following points were made: (1) A rapid and widespread improvement in the preparednessof the civil population to meet a sudden gas attack couldnot be secured unless the present ban against publicity for antf-gas preparations was relaxed..; (2) The public should once more begin carrying their respirators, about with-them.   Ministers could set an example. -(3) Attention was drawn to paragraph 17 of ;W.P. (41) 15 inwhich it was stated-&quot; Now. that shelters are being used for sleeping,adequate ventilation is of the first importance. Itis impracticable to reconcile this with efficient gas-proofing.&quot;It was important that Departments should speak with one voice on anti-gas policy.(4) The main danger to be faced was the concentrated use against key positions: e&apos;.g., the main West Coast ports.
The, War, Cabinet^-. -      -(i) Took nbteof W.P. (41)14 and, 15.(li) Invited the Lord Privy Seal, in consultation with theMinisters concerned, to examine our precautionary measures, against gas attack, and concert such measures as might be necessary to bring them to a state of readiness.The Lord Privy Seal should report to the WarCabinet in a week&apos;s time.(iii) Agreed that there should be some easement of the banagainst Press and broadcast publicity about anti-gasmeasures.(iv) Invited the Home Secretary and Minister of home security to circulate, for the information of the WarCabinet, the draft pamphlet on anti-gas precautions.Royal-Navy.&apos; 7.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theDartmouth     &apos; First Lord of the Admiralty (W P. (G.) (41) 10) containing proposalsScholarships!     for broadening the field of entry for commissioned officers in theNavy.The ; Prime Minister said that he strongly favoured theseproposals. Nevertheless, they would need to be carefully introduced,if all sense of social inequality was to be avoided.The War Cabinet^-(i) Approved in principle the proposals in W.P. (G.) (41) 10.(ii) Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty to settle thefinancial and other details of his scheme in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and any other ministers concerned, including any modifications to fitthe Scottish educational system.United States ofAmerica.disclosure of secret information on supply Matters.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 301stConclusions,Minute 6.)Royal Air Force.ProposedContribution toBenevolentFund from public Funds.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 2ndConclusions,,.Minute 6.) &apos;8. The War Cabinet approved the proposals in a Paper bythe Minister of Aircraft Production (W.P. (41) 12) that the powersand duties of the Committee on disclosure to the United States ofsecret information on Supply matters should be transferred to theNorth American Supply Committee.9. The War Cabinet had before them a further Memorandumon this subject by the Minister of Aircraft Production (W.P. (G.)(41)11). -The main points in discussion were as follows:-(1) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that a grant of 1 million from public funds at this time would notbe in conformity with the burdens which the public werebeing asked to bear.(2) If a grant were to be made to the Soya! Air ForceBenevolent Fund, grants would also have to be made toother Service Benevolent Funds. Mention was also madeof1 the ^Mercantile-Marine and Civil Defence Services.It was suggested that State grants to these BenevolentFunds might more appropriately be made towards theend of the war.     &apos;
(3) While there might be a case oil merits for grants from public funds to Service Charities, it was argued that itwas undesirable that such a grant should be linked up with a Fund which had an entirely different purpose,namely, the Spitfire Fund. T(4) Large grants from public funds to Service Charities might reduce the subscriptions at present received..(5) Most of the subscribers to the Spitfire Fund thought thattheir subscriptions increased the number of aircraftavailable to the Royal Air Force. This was not so, andtheir subscriptions only lightened the burden on theExchequer. Was it right that the public should continueto subscribe large sums of money under a misapprehension-hension? From the point of view of the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer, however, it was important not to stop the flow of gifts to the Exchequer.(6) It was suggested that an announcement should now bemade that the next  1 million subscribed to the SpitfireFund would be devoted to Service Charities.A variant of this suggestion would be to say thatall the Spitfires obtainable had now been ordered; thatcontributions for this purpose were not required; andthat, until further notice, subscriptions to the fund would be divided between the charities of the three services.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he wouldlike time to give consideration to this suggestion.The War Cabinet-Invited   the   Minister   of   Aircraft   Production,   theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of Statefor Air to consult together in regard to the suggestionsoutlined in (6).Great George Street, S.W. 1,January 27, 1941.



</content>
</cab>
