<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/45/8 images: 80-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s goyernmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1944.27The circulation of this paper, has been strictly limited,   It is issued for the personal use of :-4&amp; UMOST SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 8..7th January, 1944.WAR CABINET.RECORDS OF THE ANGLO-AMERICAN-RUSSIAN conversations in TEHRAN AND OF THE ANGLO-AMERICAN-TURKISHCONVERSATIONS IN CAIRO.I circulate for the information of my colleagues records of the above twoconversations.W. S. C.10, Downing Street, S.W.I.7th January, 1944.[26609a]

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government most SECRET.TEHRAN CONFERENCE.Record of a conversation between the Prime Minister and Marshal Stalinon the 28th November.Record of a conversation between the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, M. Molotov and Mr. Hopkins on the 30th November.Record of  a conversation between  the  Prime Minister,  president roosevelt and Marshal Stalin at luncheon on the 30th November.Record of a conversation at luncheon in the Soviet Embassy, Tehran, onthe 1st December.Record of a conversation at  the Soviet Embassy,  Tehran, on the1st December.Record of a conversation at  the Soviet Embassy,  Tehran,  on the1st December.Record of a conversation at  the  Soviet Embassy,  Tehran, on the1st December.Record of a conversation at  the  Soviet Embassy,  Tehran, on the1st December.0)Record of Conversation between the Prime Minister and Marshal Stalinat Tehran on 28th November, 1943.THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that this was a historical meeting,and that so much depended upon the friendship of the three Heads of Govern-ment and the decisions reached at this Conference.MARSFIAL STALIN suggested that they should first consider the worstthat might happen. He thought that Germany had every possibility of recoveringfrom this war and might start on a new war within a comparatively short time.He was afraid of German nationalism. This was a possibility and allowancesmust be made for it. After Versailles peace seemed assured, but Germanyrecovered very quickly. We must therefore establish a strong body to preventGermany starting a new war.   He was convinced that she would recover.THE PRIME MINISTER asked how soon.MARSHAL STALIN thought it might be within fifteen to twenty years.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that the world must be made safe for atleast fifty years. If it was only for fifteen to twenty years, then we would havebetrayed our soldiers.MARSHAL STALIN thought that we should consider the economic side ofthe question. The Germans were an able people, very industrious and cultured,and they would recover quickly.THE PRIME MINISTER said that certain measures would have to been forced. He would forbid all aviation civil and military, and he would forbidthe General Staff system.MARSHAL STALIN asked whether he would also forbid the existence ofwatchmakers&apos; and furniture factories which could easily be turned into factoriesfor making parts of shells and into aircraft factories. The Germans had producedtoy rifles which had been used for teaching hundreds of thousands of men how toshoot.12230   [26609]15
THE PRIME MINISTER said nothing was final. The world rolled on.We have now learnt something. Our duty was to make the world safe for atleast fifty years (a) by disarmament, (b) by&apos;preventing rearmament, (c) by super-vision of German factories, (d) by forbidding all aviation, and (e) by territorialchanges of a far-reaching character.MARSHAL STALIN thought that that was correct, but Germany would work through other countries.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it all came back to a question of whether Great Britain, the United States and the U.S.S.R. kept a close friendship and supervised Germany in their mutual interest. He said they should not beafraid to give orders as soon as they saw any danger.MARSHAL STALIN said there had been control after the last war, but ithad failed.THE PRIME MINISTER said people were inexperienced. The last war wasnot to the same extent a national war and Russia was not a party at the peace con-,ference. It was different this time. He had a feeling that Prussia should be isolated and reduced, that Bavaria, Austria and Hungary might form a broad, peacefulcow-like confederation. He thought Prussia should be dealt with more severelythan the other parts of the Reich, so that the latter would not want to go in with Prussia.MARSHAL STALIN thought all this was very good but insufficient.THE PRIME MINISTER said that Russia would have her army. GreatBritain and the United States navies and air forces. In addition, all three powers would have their other forces, all strongly armed, and they must notassume any obligation to disarm. They were the trustees for the peace of theworld. If they failed, there would be, perhaps, 100 years of chaos. If theywere strong they would carry out their trusteeship.MARSHAL STALIN said he would think it over.THE PRIME MINISTER said that there was more than merely keeping the peace. The three Powers should guide the future of the world. He was nota Communist and he did not want to enforce any principles on other nations.But he asked for freedom and for the right of all nations to develop as they liked.He said that they must keep friends in order to ensure happy homes in allcountries.     -      -MARSHAL STALIN asked what was to happen with Germany.THE PRIME MINISTER replied that he was not against toilers inGermany, but only against the leaders and against dangerous combinations.MARSHAL STALIN said that there were many toilers in the german divisions, who fought under orders. When he asked German prisoners who came from the labour classes why they fought for Hitler, they replied that theywere executing orders.   He shot such prisoners.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that they should discuss the polish question.MARSHAL STALIN agreed and invited the Prime Minister to begin.THE PRIME MINISTER said we had declared war on account of Poland.Poland was therefore important to us. Nothing was more important than thesecurity of the Russian western frontier. But he had given no pledges aboutfrontiers. He wanted heart-to-heart talks with the Russians about this. When the Marshal felt like telling us what he thought about it,the matter could be discussed and they could reach some agreement, and theMarshal should tell him what was necessary for the defence of the westernfrontiers of Russia.MARSHAL STALIN said he did not feel the need to ask himself how toact.   So far his heart did not feel stimulated.[tie meant that the Prime Minister should become more precise/!.
THE PRIME MINISTER said that after this war in Europe, whichmight end in 1944, the Soviet Union would be overwhelmingly strong and russia would have a great responsibility for hundreds of years in any decision shetook with regard to Poland. Personally, he thought Poland might move west-wards like soldiers taking two steps left close. If Poland trod on some Germantoes, that could not be helped, but there must be a strong Poland. This instrumentwas needed in the orchestra of Europe.MARSHAL STALIN said the Polish people had their culture and theirlanguage, which must exist.   They could not be extirpated.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed and asked if we were to draw frontierlines.MARSHAL STALIN said Yes.THE PRIME MINISTER said he had no power from Parliament, nor he believed had the President, to define any frontier lines. He suggested that theymight now, in Tehran, see if the three Heads of Government, working in agree-ment, could form some sort of policy which might be pressed upon the Polesand which we could recommend to the Poles, and advise them to accept.MARSHAL STALIN said we could have a look.THE PRIME MINISTER said we should be lucky if we could.MARSHAL STALIN asked whether it would be without Polish participa-tion.THE PRIME MINISTER replied in the affirmative and said that this wasall informally between themselves, and they could go to the Poles later.MARSHAL STALIN agreed.Mr. EDEN said he had been much struck by what the Marshal had saidthat afternoon to the effect that the Poles could go as far west as the Oder.He saw hope in that and was much encouraged.MARSHAL STALIN asked whether we thought he was going to swallowPoland up.Mr. EDEN said he did not know how much the Russians were going toeat.   How much would they leave undigested \MARSHAL STALIN said the Russians did not want anything belongingto other people, although they might have a bite at Germany.Mr. EDEN said what Poland lost in the east she might gain in the west.MARSHAL STALIN said.possibly they might, but he did not know.THE PRIME MINISTER demonstrated with the help of three matcheshis idea of Poland moving westwards, which pleased Marshal Stalin.(2)Record of a Conversation between Mr. Eden, M. Molotov and Mr. HarryHopkins at His Majesty&apos;s Legation, Tehran, on 30th November, 1943.There was some general discussion on the subject of the control of strategicbases after the war.M. MOLOTOV said that Marshal Stalin bad-referred to Bizerta and Dakaras examples of points which should be controlled by Great Britain and the UnitedStates to ensure control of the Mediterranean and the Atlantic. What was mr. Eden&apos;s view ?Mr. EDEN stated that His Majesty&apos;s Government did not want any moreterritory, but he considered that strategic points in enemy territory should passunder the control of the United Nations. Strategic points on French territorywere a more difficult question owing to our former close relations with the Frenchand our desire to see France strong again. The French, however, should realiseand be willing to make their contribution by making some strategic points[26609] B 2
available to the United Nations. If Great Britain had been able to do this withregard to the bases leased to the United States, the French might be persuaded to do the same.  It was not a question of pride.Mr. HOPKINS pointed out that we did not know what would be the strategicpoints and the strength required to hold them until we knew the potentialenemies. Mr. Roosevelt felt that it was essential for the U.S.S.R., the UnitedStates and Great Britain to agree on these points and make sure that no nationwould arm against another. Although Germany and Japan would be defeated,the public would still regard these nations as potential enemies. As regards bases in the Pacific against Japanese aggression, there would be no difficulties. Forexample, in giving the Philippines independence the United States Governmentcould still make sure that the United States had naval and air bases in the philippines under agreement between the U.S.S.R., Great Britain, the UnitedStates. Also if Formosa returned to China there should be bases thereadministered by the United Nations.M. MOLOTOV said that this question deserved attention.Mr. HOPKINS said that President Roosevelt saw two problems in the pacific. The United States did not want to take over mandated islands whichwere now under the Japanese. They would like the United Nations to decidemutually the type of bases and strengths required in these islands. Our three powers should keep the strong points which they at present held, and maintainthose points in order to keep the peace with air, sea and land forces if necessary.But it was easy for the United States to discuss such strategic strong points inEurope since the United States had no territory in Europe potentially threatened by Germany.M. MOLOTOV asked what about the Dutch islands with regard to theJapanese.Mr, HOPKINS said this was a difficult question, but he was referring mainly to the enforcement of peace against Germany. It would be easier for the U.S.S.R.and Great Britain to enforce peace from their strong points. With regard tostrategic points which were in territory historically unfriendly over a long period to Great Britain and the U.S.S.R., it would not be difficult to decide. Thedifficulty would arise with points which we considered essential to maintain thepeace which were located in friendly territory. This was a most importantproblem and it would be. useful if Marshal Stalin and the Prime Minister coulddiscuss this, but as this would take a long time the Foreign Ministers would haveto do it.The conversation turned to the question of Turkey. Mr. EDEN said thathe would like to make a few suggestions for what they were worth.M. MOLOTOV said that they were in favour of bringing Turkey into thewar now, not in the future. Marshal Stalin does not think that Turkey willenter the war, but it is worth trying.Mr. EDEN said that M. Molotov had been more optimistic in Moscow.M. MOLOTOV said that since then Mr. Eden had had negotiations with turkey. After he had heard the Turks&apos; reply he was less optimistic.Mr. HOPKINS interposed that in Moscow the initiative in attempting to getTurkey into the war had been taken by the Russians and very strongly. his impression was that the Russians felt that if the United States and Great Britainjoined in the representations to Turkey we could get that country into the war.Also he thought that the Russians considered Turkey&apos;s entry into the war fromthe military point of view as important. Mr. roosevelt&apos;s impression now wasthat the Russians did not feel so strongly about gettingi Turkey into the war.At any rate Marshal Stalin has repeatedly said that we were unlikely to getTurkey in. The President would like to know if Russia has changed her mind as to getting the Turks into the war.   Surely we all would like her to come in.M. MOLOTOV asked if Mr. Eden had spoken to the Turks in the name ofall three United Nations.Mr. EDEN said that he had felt authorised to do so.M. MOLOTOV considered that Mr. Eden was fully entitled to do so under our Protocol.
Mr. HOPKINS said that from the point of view of the United States hewas perfectly correct.M. MOLOTOV said that Turkey&apos;s unfavourable reply was bound to havean effect on their point of view. But he must repeat Marshal Stalin&apos;s reply tothe Prime Minister that Turkey should declare war this year and not next, alsothat if Bulgaria continued in her hostile attitude, not only would Russia breakdiplomatic relations with her, but she would consider a state of war to exist between herself and Bulgaria if Turkey came into the war.Mr. EDEN expressed satisfaction.M. MOLOTOV said that this showed their point of view. He would likean explanation of Mr. Churchill&apos;s statement regarding Turkey&apos;s refusal to comeinto the war and, in that case, Turkey giving up her rights over the Bosphorusand the Dardanelles.Mr. EDEN said that he thought that Mr. Churchill meant by this that itwould alter the whole basis of friendship between Great Britain and Turkey.He did not think that he had meant more. Mr. Eden then put forward a proposalto ask President Inonti to come to Cairo and confer with the Prime Ministerand President Roosevelt on their way back. If the Russians would like to comethey were welcome.   What did M. Molotov think of this idea?M. MOLOTOV thought it was a good idea, but he would ask Marshal Stalin.Mr. HOPKINS interposed that he had reason to believe that we were coming to substantial understanding, perhaps before the day was over, about the pointsrelating to the conduct of the war.M. MOLOTOV said this was of primary importance and that without it allother questions would not achieve their purpose.M. MOLOTOV said he was convinced that, if the Moscow Conference had &apos;succeeded in adding vigour to their peoples, the meetings of the three Heads ofState must inspire the people still further.Mr. HOPKINS said that Turkey &apos;s entry into the war related to our militarystrategy. The American and the British Chiefs of Staff agreed that in order tosupport Turkey we must make a commitment. If we were to force Turkey intothe war we would have to occupy Rhodes and the Dodecanese. This could easily be done when Turkey entered the war, but the Chiefs of Staff considered that thiswould delay &quot;Overlord.&quot;M. MOLOTOV said that this was highly undesirable.Mr. HOPKINS said that we could not discuss bringing Turkey into the warapart from military problems. Psychologically it was clear that Turkey&apos;s entry into the war would be of,tremendous advantage. For example, Finland might askRussia for peace.M. MOLOTOV asked if Mr. Hopkins connected the entry of Turkey into thewar with delaying operation &quot; Overlord.&quot;Mr. HOPKINS said that the Chiefs of Staff considered that Turkey wouldnot declare war unless we seized the Dodecanese.M. MOLOTOV said that in any case if the delay of &quot; Overlord &quot; was envisaged, this would not correspond to the point of view held by the Red Army.Mr. HOPKINS stated that President Roosevelt was under the impression that the Chiefs of Staff, not having examined the question of Turkey&apos;s entry indetail, offered a force to Turkey which was inadequate. The President would want to examine this question before he had talks with the President of Turkey.He was sure that Turkey&apos;s entry into the war would require a military force from our side. He was extremely hopeful that the two points raised by Marshal Stalinwould be resolved to-day to his satisfaction. The two points in question were an assurance about &apos;&apos; Overlord &apos;&apos; and its timing and, secondly, the question of aCommander for the operation.M. MOLOTOV said that he understood that bringing Turkey into the war would cause a delay in &quot; Overlord.&quot;   If so, Marshal Stalin was against this.Mr. HOPKINS said he thought that the three heads of Governments would agree on the points raised by Marshal Stalin.
M. MOLOTOV said if they agreed, what question could there be of delay.Mr. EDEN said that as he saw it, the situation was that if these points were agreed on between the heads of Government, they could agree on all other points.M. MOLOTOV said that in that case he understood that Turkey&apos;s entry intothe war would not postpone &apos;: Overlord.&quot;After further discussion Mr. EDEN referred to supplies to Tito, and theRussian desire to establish a base of supplies in North Africa. The Russians werewelcome to do so and, if desired, he could arrange accommodation next to ourbase in Cairo.M. MOLOTOV warmly welcomed this, and said he would forward the names of the Soviet Mission to be sent to this base through Sir A. Clark Kerr. Hewondered whether it would be a good idea to send this mission both to the partisans and to Mihailovic.Mr. EDEN was not sure whether this was physically possible owing tointervening German forces. A separate mission might be necessary. He would speak to M. Molotov again about this.Mr. EDEN then referred to the question of Poland. Marshal Stalin and thePrime Minister had had a brief discussion about Poland on the previous evening.He wished to say that he did not want this question to be a source of friction between the three countries, if it could be avoided. If the question could be resolved by an agreement to which Poland could subscribe that Poland should taketwo steps to the left, then we could examine the size of these steps. He said thathe did not mean to include the Americans in this statement of view.*Mr. HOPKINS said that President Roosevelt would say all that was on his mind about Poland to Marshal Stalin.   M. Molotov agreed that it was desirable. to discuss the Polish question.After Mr. Hopkins and Mr. Eden had made a few remarks about theAmerican elections, M. MOLOTOV stated that the elections would be satisfactory as showing that the union of the three Great Powers was strong. The people likestrength and friendliness.Mr. HOPKINS stated that the Moscow Conference had had a great effect in America.On Mr. EDEN&apos;S initiative it was agreed that the Foreign Ministers should meet at luncheon to-morrow7, and M. Molotov proposed that they should come toluncheon with him.(3) &apos;Record of a Conversation between the Prime Minister, President Rooseveltand Marshal Stalin at Luncheon on 30th November, 1943.Warm Water Ports.MARSHAL STALIN raised the question of warm water ports.THE PRIME MINISTER said there were no obstacles.MARSHAL STALIN said if there were no obstacles on the part of GreatBritain, then the question of the regime of the Dardanelles would have to beconsidered. Russia had no outlet and perhaps a new regime could help them.There had been various regimes, the Treaty of Sevres, the Treaty of Montreux, &amp;c.At that time Great Britain wanted, to suppress Russia. If she did not want to do so now Great Britain would have to help.THE PRIME MINISTER said he wanted to get Turkey into the war andthis was an awkward moment for raising the question.MARSHAL STALIN said the time would come later.THE PRIME MINISTER said he expected Russia would sail the ocean with her navy and merchant fleet and. we would welcome her ships.MARSHAL STALIN said Lord Curzon had had other ideas.THE PRIME MINISTER said that in those days we did not see eye to eye.
m PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that the Baltic should be free to all thenations for merchant shipping. There should be free zones in the ports andtrustees should be appointed for the Kiel Canal. He said, the Dardanelles oughtto be free to the commerce of the world.MARSHAL STALIN asked whether this would apply to Russian commerce.THE PRESIDENT and THE PRIME MINISTER agreed.MARSHAL STALIN then asked what could be done for Russia in theEar East.THE PRIME MINISTER first asked whether the Marshal had agreed tothe communique about China.MARSHAL STALIN thought it was a good communique and he had nocomments to make. But Russia would have something to add. when she herselfwas active in that part of the world.THE PRIME MINISTER said that Russia had Vladivostok in the Far East,MARSHAL STALIN pointed out that the port was closed and depended onthe Straits of Tsushima.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT suggested Dairen as a free port,MARSHAL STALIN mentioned that Petropavlosk was available, but therewas no railway communication with it. At present the only exit that the russians had was Murmansk.-THE PRIME MINISTER said that the government of the world must beentrusted to satisfied nations, who wished nothing more for themselves than whatthey had. If the government were in the hands of hungry nations, there would always be danger. But none of us had any reason to seek for anything more.The peace would be kept by people v/ho live in their own way and who were notambitious. Our power placed us above the rest. We were like rich men in theirhabitations.(4)Record of a Conversation at Luncheon in the Soviet Embassy, Tehran, on- 1st December, 1943.Present:The Prime Minister.President Roosevelt.Marshal Stalin.Mr. Eden.M. Molotov.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Sir A. Clark Kerr.Mr. Harriman.Turkey.Mr. HOPKINS asked what were the implications of asking Turkey to comeinto the war. The implications were the support we would have to give Turkey.This was a strategic question.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that inonu would ask what we could do.THE PRIME MINISTER said that we had in Egypt 17 squadrons not under the Anglo-American command. In addition, Air Marshal Tedder hadthree squadrons which *we could provide. They were chiefly fighters and couldbe used for the protection of Turkey. In addition we had three regiments ofA.A. This was all we had promised. We had not promised Turkey any troops.She has 50 divisions equipped and there was no necessity for any troops to be sent,THE PRESIDENT said that until the landing craft situation had been studied we should be careful in making promises to President Inonu, as thatmight interfere with our agreement of yesterday. ,
MARSHAL STALIN said that if Turkey entered the war she would makepart of her territory available.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed and said Ploesti would be vulnerable.We were not offering Turkey anything that was not ours to give, and we were only giving three squadrons from the Central Mediterranean to make up thenumber from 17 to 20. Perhaps the Americans could add a few bomber squadronswhich could be used from Turkey. We had said that we would only give airprotection. We had no army available. As for the landing craft required inMarch for the single operation, thev could be sandwiched in between Italy and&quot;Overlord.&quot;THE PRESIDENT hoped that the landing craft could be sandwiched inbetween Italy and &quot; Overlord,&quot; but casualties of landing craft were very heavy,and in the case of &apos;&apos; Overlord &apos;&apos; they would want all they could get. The landing-craft would have to be ready in Corsica and Sardinia by the 1st April in order tobe prepared for the 1st May.THE PRIME MINISTER said he saw no difficulty. We had made no offersto Turkey nor did he know when inonu would accept any offers. The president would be in Cairo and could see what his staffs would have to say. We Britishcould only offer 20 squadrons. The Turks did not need any army; they neededair protection.   In addition, Inonu might not come to Cairo.MARSHAL STALIN said that he might fall ill.THE PRIME MINISTER said that if he refused to come and the president had to leave he proposed to go and see him in Adana. He. would go in a cruiser.Inonu&quot; would come there, and the Prime Minister would put the case before him of what we would do and the not very pleasing picture of what he would get if he did not come in. The Prime Minister would then report the result, and we wouldnot have the worry about landing craft.Mr. HOPKINS said that the military forces required to support Turkeyhad been examined only from the British point of view and not the American. Thequestion was, should we invite Inonti before we had reached some agreement asto precisely what we could offer&apos;? Some of the American air people felt that abomber group should be put in to make the operation successful. Were weasking inonu to come down before the Chiefs of Staff could settle what tooffer? Of course, the remarks made at the previous day&apos;s meeting of foreign secretaries had been made before the question of unity of command and yester-day&apos;s agreement had been settled.THE PRIME MINISTER said that there was no necessity for landing craft in order to help Turkey. -MARSHAL STALIN asked whether that meant that we were not invitingInonii to go to Cairo.THE PRIME MINISTER said that we must have an agreement before the interview as to what we were offering.MARSHAL STALIN asked whether it could not be reached here withoutthe military people.THE PRIME MINISTER said that with regard to landing craft, whichwere the bottle neck, some might be forthcoming from the Indian Ocean or the pacific or a larger number could be built. If this could not be done we shouldhave to give up something, but it was agreed that &apos;&apos; Overlord &apos;&apos; was not to suffer.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said he wanted to explain the situation inthe South-West Pacific and the operation in Burma to help the Chinese. ThePrime Minister had suggested that landing craft should be provided from the pacific, That was impossible. Distances were too great and every day the americans were proceeding north in the Gilbert and Marshal Islands to attackJapanese supply lines.  All the landing craft would be needed there.Mr. HOPKINS said that the Marshal should understand that we did not know how much landing craft we should offer Inonu if he came into the war. Wewould have to make up our minds how much landing craft we would require for the operation against Rhodes.
THE PRIME MINISTER said there was no commitment about Rhodes orany other island. There was only a commitment about air bases on the mainlandand there was no commitment in landing craft.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that if he were inonu he would ask forCrete and other islands to be taken.THE PRIME MINISTER said what he [the Prime Minister] wanted wasair bases in the region of Smyrna and Badrun. Those airfields had been constructed by us. When we got them and put in squadrons we would drive theGermans out of the air in that area. It paid us anyhow to lose one aircraft forevery German machine shot down. We would starve out the German garrisons on-the islands. If Turkey took an active part in operations, that would be all right,but the islands would fall of themselves. It would not be necessary to attackRhodes. The islands had to be supplied by Germany and if we had air cover from turkey our destroyers could cut down German convoys, which they could not do atpresent because Germany had command in the air. Turkish bases would give uscontinued pressure against the Germans and that would be a preparation for&quot;Overlord.&quot;MARSHAL STALIN said that was correct.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said he agreed to go on with 20 squadrons andsome bombers, but no amphibious operations.THE PRIME MINISTER asked what were we offering Turkey ? Limitedmeans of air protection and A.A. The winter was approaching and there wouldbe no invasion of Turkey by Germany. We would continue to supply her witharms. There was the priceless opportunity of accepting the Soviet invitation for turkey to sit beside them at the peace conference. There was the assurance that,if Bulgaria attacked Turkey because the latter had declared war on Germany,the Soviet Union would retaliate on Bulgaria, a thing which had never happenedbefore. Then there was the offer of association with the victorious Powers andour good offices and friendship.MARSHAL STALIN asked what measures did Mr. Churchill expect fromthe Soviet Union in case Turkey declared war on Germany, as the result of whichBulgaria attacked Turkey and the Soviet broke off relations with Bulgaria and declared war on the latter.THE PRIME MINISTER said he was not asking for anything, but, if theSoviet armies advanced through Odessa, they would create a great effect amongthe population in Bulgaria, As for the Turkish army, they had rifles, braveinfantry, fairly good artillery, but no A.A. guns, no aircraft and very few tanks.We had established military schools, but they were not attended regularly. TheTurks were not clever, and they were not quick to learn. The Turkish army wasa brave army, but not modern. Twenty-five million pounds had been spent onweapons, mainly American, and we had conveyed these.MARSHAL STALIN said it was possible Turkey would not have to fight.They would give us their air bases; that might be the course of events and itwould be good.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked Mr. Eden to state what the Turks had said in Cairo.Mr. EDEN said he had told the Turkish Foreign Minister that he could give us air bases and Germany would not attack Turkey. The Foreign minister had replied that he could not accept that. Germany would react against Turkishprovocation. Turkey would rather come in by- agreement than indirectly as aresult of such action as had been suggested.THE PRIME MINISTER said that was so. When they asked Turkey tostrain their neutrality by giving us their air bases as in the case of Portugal,they replied : &quot; Oh no, we cannot play a passive role; and if we asked them to start war in earnest, they replied :  &quot; Oh no, we are not sufficiently armed.&quot;THE PRIME MINISTER proposed, if necessary, to try other methods. IfTurkey refused, she would forfeit her chance to sit at the peace conference. she would be treated as other neutrals. We would say that Great Britain had nofurther interest in her affairs and we would stop the supply of arms.[26609] .    . c
Mr. EDEN said he would like to get quite clear in his mind the demandsthat were to be made on Turkey : was it understood that Turkey should go to warwith Germany and no one else ?MARSHAL STALIN said Yes, only with Germany.Mr. EDEN asked if the following was right: if, as a result, the Germansmade Bulgaria join them in the war with Turkey, the Soviet Government would go to war with Bulgaria.MARSHAL STALIN said that that was right.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, for himself, he would be satisfied withstrained neutrality.MARSHAL STALIN remarked that there was another possibility : Turkeymight declare war on Germany. Germany might require Bulgaria to attackTurkey. Bulgaria might refuse, and the Germans might then occupy Bulgaria,and Bulgaria might appeal to the U.S.S.R.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he was doubtful whether anything like this would happen, but, if it did, it would be all right. If Turkey refused to goto war we would have to think of something else.M. MOLOTOV said that at the conference on the day before yesterdayMr. Churchill said that, if Turkey did not enter the war, then her rights to theDardanelles and the Bosphorus could not remain unaffected. What did that mean ?THE PRIME MINISTER replied that he was far from his Cabinet, butthat he certainly thought that the regime of the Straits deserved review; forinstance, Japan was a party to the Treaty of Montreux.THE PRESIDENT said that he believed that if Turkey went to war theDardanelles should be made free to merchant ships or warships of the world,subject to policing by the policing nations.M. MOLOTOV said that as a Black Sea Power the Soviet Union had a special interest in the Dardanelles, but that he would&apos;not insist on this question to-day.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, as Turkey was our ally, and if sheentered the war, we would be ready to discuss the question in a friendly spirit.But if she refused to enter the war, then he would have to tell her that GreatBritain did not mind very much about the solution proposed by the President,that Britain would take a cold view about Turkey and that Turkey would be advised to discuss her affairs with the Soviet Union at any rate to a large extent.THE PRIME MINISTER then asked whether he would have to speak onbehalf of the three Powers if he met the Turkish r/resident, or whether therewould be a Soviet representative if the talks took place at Cairo.M. MOLOTOV said that the Soviet Government would be represented atCairo by the Soviet Ambassador to Angora and by M. Vyshinski, who would comespecially from Algiers.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he thought the Turks would prefer tobe wheedled into the war by Great Britain rather than as a result of an ultimatumby the three Powers. But he would be willing to have recourse to either of thespmethods.MARSHAL STALIN said &quot; All right.&quot;
(5)Record of a Conversation at Luncheon at the Soviet Embassy, Tehran, on1st December, 1943.Present:The Prime Minister.President Roosevelt.Marshal Stalin.Mr. Eden.M. Molotov.Mr, Harry Hopkins.Sir A. Clark Kerr.Mr. Harriman.Italian Ships.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT began by saying there were two questions tobe discussed : Poland and Germany.M. MOLOTOV asked whether the Soviet Government could not be given a reply about the Italian ships.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that his reply was very simple. A largenumber of merchant ships and a smaller number of warships could be used bythe three nations during the war and then could be distributed by title. Itwould be best until then for those to use these ships who could use them best.M. MOLOTOV said that Russia would be able to make good use of these ships, even if they were not given outright into Russian hands. They could beused in the interests of the United Nations.THE PRIME MINISTER asked where the Soviet Government would likethem delivered.MARSHAL STALIN said in the Black Sea and, if this were not possible,then in the north. If Turkey did not come into the war the Black Sea would beimpossible.   But good use of them could be made in the north.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this was a very small thing after allthe efforts that Russia was making or had made.MARSHAL STALIN said that he well knew that the United States andthe United Kingdom needed ships and that he was not asking for very much.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT agreed.THE PRIME MINISTER said he was for it, and asked Marshal Stalinto give him and the President a little time to handle the matter with the Italians,adding that we had insisted on the surrender of the whole Italian fleet.MARSHAL STALIN said again that he thought he could make good useof the ships and that he would hand them back after the war.THE PRIME MINISTER said he liked to see the ships go to the black Sea, and that perhaps he might at the same time send some of HisMajesty&apos;s Ships with them.MARSHAL STALIN said &quot; Good.&quot;THE PRIME MINISTER said that Russia must have complete controlof the Black Sea. He and the President needed time to arrange the matter withthe Italians, for they (the Italians) were helping with some of their smaller ships in patrol work, and some of their submarines were carrying important supplies.The matter would have to be so arranged that there would be no mutiny in theItalian fleet and no scuttling of ships. He suggested that a couple of months would be enough for him and the President to handle the Italians like a oathandling a mouse.   &apos;&apos; In two months a battleship and a cruiser : would that do ? &quot;MARSHAL STALIN said &quot; What about the end of January?&quot;[26609]
PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT agreed andTHE PRIME MINISTER said Yes, that the ships would pass underRussian orders by that date, after refitting.MARSHAL STALIN said that Russian crews would have to be putinto them.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT remarked that it would take some time forthe new crews to learn how to handle the.ships.THE PRIME MINISTER said if we got into the Black Sea we should like to help with the work of cleaning the Russian ships of their foul bottoms.The fall of Sevastopol must have made this difficult for the Russians. We shouldbe glad to help.MARSHAL STALIN said that this would be a good thing.THE PRIME MINISTER went on to say that he would like to put 4 or submarines into the Black Sea, especially if there were a chance of drowningsome of the Germans and Roumanians who were now in the Crimea. But wewould abide by Marshal Stalin&apos;s wishes.   We had no ambitions in the Black Sea.MARSHAL STALIN replied that that was good, and that he would be grateful for any help.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this was one of the things whichmight be asked of Turkey if she only accepted strained neutrality. We hadbetween 30 and 40 submarines in the Mediterranean. Turkey should let us slipthem through the Dardanelles by night. Our submarine officers would think itan honour to fight side by side with the Soviet Black Sea fleet. It would onlybe a small contribution, but he would like to make it. The American submarines were sinking a lot of Japanese ships in the Pacific, and we in the Mediterraneanhad been sinking a very large number of Italian and German ships. We thoughtsubmarine warfare improper, but we had been forced to do a lot of it.(6)Record   of   a Conversation   at   the   Soviet   Embassy,   Tehran,   on1st December,  1943.Present :The Prime Minister.President Roosevelt.Marshal Stalin.Mr. Eclen.M. Molotov.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Sir A. Clark Kerr.Mr. Harriman.Poland.The discussion then turned on Poland.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT began by saying that it was his hope thatthere could be a resumption of relations between the Polish and. soviet governments, so that any decision taken could be accepted by the Polish Govern-ment. Thus it would be much easier. But he had to recognise that there were difficulties.MARSHAL STALIN asked with what Government he would have tonegotiate. The Polish Government and their friends in Poland were in contact with the Germans. They killed the partisans. Neither the President nor thePrime Minister could have any idea of what was now going on in Poland.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT remarked that he had. recognised that therewere difficulties.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Polish matter was an important one for us in the United Kingdom, because we had declared war on Germany on
account of her invasion of Poland. It had astonished him that Mr. Chamberlain,after not having fought for the Czechs at Munich, had suddenly given a guarantee to Poland in April 1939, when he had thrown away the other much more favour-able opportunity. The Prime Minister had&apos; been astonished that Mr. Chamberlainshould go back to a policy of war and guarantee Poland. He had been astonishedbut he had also been glad. Although Great Britain had been totally unpreparedwe had declared war on Germany and had also played a great part in screwingthe French up. The French had, gone down, but we had had the luck to be an island and we had gone on fighting. We felt very strongly about it because it wasthe German attack on Poland which had led us into war. He understood thatthe Russians had a different historical background, but he hoped that our russian allies would see our point and understand how largely Poland bulked for us.We had, done what we had done and we did not regret it. He had understood the Russian policy at the beginning of the war. At that time Great britain was very weak, and then there had been the policy of Munich and the Frenchbetrayal of the guarantee to Czechoslovakia. He had understood that the SovietGovernment had not wished to risk their existence on such uncertainties. Nowit was all different, and he hoped that Marshal Stalin would understand, if wewere asked why we had gone to war, our answer would have to be that we had promised Poland that if she were attacked we would go to war.THE PRIME MINISTER went on to say that he had in mind the picture ofthe three matches Germany, Poland and the Soviet Union. One of the mainobjects of the Allies was to achieve the security of the Soviet western frontier and so to prevent an attack by Germany in the future. Here he remindedMarshal Stalin that mention had been made by the Marshal of the line of theOder -in the west.MARSHAL STALIN (interrupting) said that the day before yesterday therehad been no mention of re-establishing relations with the Polish Government.It had been a question of prescribing something to the Poles. To-day the matter had been put quite differently. Russia, even more than other States, was inter-ested in good relations with Poland because for her it was a question of thesecurity of her frontiers. Russia was in favour of the reconstruction, develop-ment and expansion of Poland mainly at the expense of Germany. But heseparated Poland from the Polish Government in exile. He had broken offrelations - with the Polish Government in exile not on: account of caprice, but because the Polish Government in exile had joined with Hitler in slanderouspropaganda against Russia.. It had all been in the press. What was there to guarantee that it would not happen again&apos;? He would like to have a guarantee that the Polish Government in exile would not kill partisans, but on the Contrarywould urge the Poles to fight the Germans and not concern themselves with anymachinations. He would welcome any government which would take active measures and he would be glad to renew relations with them. But he was by no means sure that the Polish Government in exile was ever likely to become thekind of government it ought to be. If the Polish Government were to go hand inhand with the partisans and have no relations with the Germans in Poland., hewould be glad enough to see the question settled. Here he reverted to the matterof the three matches.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it would be a great help if round that very table we could learn what were the Russian ideas about the frontiers. Hewould then be glad to put the matter before the Poles and to say frankly if hethought the conditions fair. His Majesty&apos;s Government (he was only speakingfor His Majesty&apos;s Government) would like to be able to tell the Poles that the plan was a good one and, the best that they were likely to get, and that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would not argue against the Soviet Government at the peace table.Then we could get on with the Presidents idea of resuming relations. What we wanted was a strong and independent Poland, friendly to Russia.MARSHAL STALIN said that that was true, but that the Poles could notbe allowed to seize the Ukraine and White Russian territory. That was not fair.According to the 1939 frontier the soil of the Ukraine and White Russia wasreturned to the Ukraine and to White Russia. Soviet Russia adhered to the frontiers of 1939, for they appeared to be ethnologically the right ones.Mr. EDEN asked if this meant the Ribbeiitrop-Molotov line.MARSHAL STALIN said : &quot; Call it whatever you like.&quot;.M. MOLOTOV remarked that it was generally called the Curzon Line.
Mr. EDEN said no, there were differences which were important.M. MOLOTOV said there were no essential differences.THE PRIME MINISTER then produced a map and showed the curzon line and the 1939 line and indicated also the line of the Oder.Mr. EDEN suggested that the south end of the Curzon Line had never beendefined in terms.At this point the meeting broke up into groups. There was a generalgathering round the Prime Minister&apos;s map and round a map which was produced by the Americans, and it was difficult to take notes of the conversation.Mr. EDEN suggested that the Curzon Line was intended to pass to the east of Lvov.MARSHAL STALIN replied that the line on the Prime Minister&apos;s map hadnot been drawn right. Lvov should be left on the Russian side and the line should go westwards towards Przemysl, adding that M. Molotov would get a mapof the Curzon Line and a description of it.THE PRIME MINISTER said he would be grateful.MARSHAL STALIN here remarked that he did not want any Polishpopulation, and that if he found any district inhabited by Poles he would gladlygive it up.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked if he might put a question.   Did the.frontier of East Prussia and the territory east of the Oder approximate to the size of the eastern provinces of Poland itself %MARSHAL STALIN said that he did not know and that it had not beenmeasured.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the value of this land was muchgreater than the Pripet Marshes. It was industrial and it would make a much better Poland. We should like to be able to say to the Poles that the russians were right, and to tell the Poles that they must agree that they had had a fairdeal. If the Poles did not accept, we could not help it. And here he made itclear that he was speaking for the British alone, adding that the President hadmany Poles in the United States who were his fellow-citizens.MARSHAL STALIN said again that if it were proved to him that anydistrict were Polish, he would not claim it, and here he made some shadowing onthe map west of the Curzon Line and south of Vilna, which he admitted to be mainly Polish.At this point the meeting again broke up, and there was a prolonged study ofthe Oder Line on a map.   When this came to an end THE PRIME MINISTER said that he liked the picture, and that he would say to the Poles that if they did not accept it they would be fools, and he wouldremind them that but for the Red Army they would have been utterly destroyed.He would point out to them that they had been given a fine place to live in, morethan 300 miles each way.MARSHAL STALIN said that it would indeed be a large, industrial State.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it would be a State friendly to Russia.MARSHAL STALIN replied that Russia wanted a friendly Poland.THE PRIME MINISTER said to Mr. Eden, with some emphasis, that hewas not going to break his heart about this cession of parts of Germany to Polandor about Lvov.Mr. EDEN said that if Marshal Stalin would take the Curzon and OderLines as a basis on which to argue that might provide a basis.At this point M. MOLOTOV produced the Russian version of the curzon line, and a text of a wireless telegram from Lord Curzon giving all the placenames.THE PRIME MINISTER asked whether M. Molotov would object to thePoles getting the Oppeln district.M. MOLOTOV replied that he did not foresee any objection.
THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Poles would be wise to take ouradvice. They were getting a country 300 miles square, and that he was notprepared to make a great squawk about Lvov, and (turning to Marshal Stalin)he added that he did not think that we were very far off in principle.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked Marshal Stalin whether he thought a transfer of population on a voluntary basis would be possible.MARSHAL STALIN said that probably it would be.j[Here the discussion about Poland came to an end.)(7)Record of a Conversation at the Soviet Embassy, Tehran, on 1st December,1943.Present:The Prime Minister.President Roosevelt.Marshal Stalin.Mr. Eden.M. Molotov.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Sir A. Clark Kerr.Mr Harriman.Finland.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked Marshal Stalin whether he was ready todiscuss Finland.MARSHAL STALIN said Yes.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked whether the United States Governmentcould do anything to help to get Finland out of the war.MARSHAL STALIN said that recently the Vice-Minister for &apos;ForeignAffairs of Sweden had asked Madame Kollontay what Russia thought aboutFinland, and had told her that the Finns were afraid that Russia wanted to turnFinland into a Russian province. The Finns would like to know. The SovietGovernment had replied that the U.S.S.R. had no wish to make Finland a provinceunless the Finns forced her to do so. Madame Kollontay then had been instructedto tell the Finns that the Soviet Government would have no objection to receiving a Finnish delegation in Moscow. But they wished the Finns to state their iews about dropping out of the war and their conditions. In Tehran he had just received the gist of the Finnish reply, which was conveyed to him throughM. Boheman. The reply did not make any mention of Finland&apos;s desire todissociate herself from Germany. It raised the question of frontiers. The Finnssuggested that as a basis of discussion the 1939 frontier should be adopted withsome corrections in favour of the Soviet Union. They did not say whatMarshal Stalin thought, that the Finns were not really anxious to conduct seriousnegotiations.   Their conditions were unacceptable and the Finns well knew it.THE PRIME MINISTER said that that was interesting.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that it was not only interesting but it wasvery unsatisfactory.MARSPIAL STALIN said that the Finns still hoped for a German victory,or at any rate some elements in Finland had a strong belief that the Germans were going to win.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked if it would help if the United StatesGovernment recommended the Finns to go to Moscow.MARSHAL STALIN replied that they were ready enough to go to Moscow,but it would not do much good if they went with the programme they proposed.
THE PRIME MINISTER said that in the days of the Russo-Finnish war hehad been sympathetic to Finland, but that he had turned against her when shecame into the war against the U.S.S.R.   That was disgraceful.MARSHAL STALIN agreed.THE PRIME MINISTER said that Russia must have certain things:security for Leningrad and its approaches. The position of the Soviet Union asa permanent naval and air power in the Baltic must be assured. But he had tosay that the people in the United Kingdom would be unhappy if the Finns wereincorporated in the U.S.S.R. against their will. He had therefore been glad to hear what Marshal Stalin had said. He did not think it would be much good toask for indemnities. The Finns might cut down a few trees, but that would not do much good.MARSHAL STALIN said that he did not want money, but the finns wouldbe well able to make good the damage they had caused to the Soviet Union within,say, 5 or 8 years, by^supplying Russia with paper, wood and many other things.He thought the Finns should&quot; be given a lesson, and he was determined to getcompensation.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he imagined that the harm the Finnsdid to Russia by their improper attack far exceeded what a poor country likeFinland could supply, and he added that there was now ringing in his ears thefamous slogan :  &quot; No annexations and no indemnities.&quot;Here the Prime Minister suggested that Marshal Stalin would not be pleasedwith him for having said that.MARSHAL STALIN (with a broad grin) replied : &apos;; I have told you thatI am becoming a Conservative.&quot;THE PRIME MINISTER then asked . what we wanted. We had&quot; Overlord,&quot; the proposed attack on the South of France, Italy and the russian front, and perhaps Turkey would soon be in the war. He would like to haveSweden in the wrar and Finland out of the war by the spring.MARSHAL STALIN said that would be good.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked whether, in the. event of Finland&apos;sbreaking with Germany, she could throw out the German troops.MARSHAL STALIN said the Finns had wanted to talk, but they had recently brought the number of their divisions on the Finnish front from 16 to 21,and that did not look like talking.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that this had been because they wanted to bargain and said :  &quot; Let us get the 21 divisions out.&quot;MARSHAL STALIN said : Yes, provided that it was not at the expenseof Russia.M. MOLOTOV here intervened and began to tell the story of 27 monthsof bombing and bombardment of Leningrad by the Finns and the Germans.THE PRIME MINISTER said that Great Britain&apos;s policy was to make thewestern frontiers of Russia secure.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that he was inclined to believe that the finns would be ready to move out of the Karelian Isthmus, but they hoped to beable to retain Viborg (here Marshal Stalin interjected &quot;Nothing doing aboutViborg&quot;) and the Peninsula of Hango. Could there not be an arrangement bywhich Hango should be demilitarised and made into a bathing beach and thus nolonger a threat ?THE PRIME MINISTER said that he did not wish to press the SovietGovernment so far as Great Britain was concerned. We had broken with the finns and we were waiting for Russia to say what she needed. We should thenperhaps plead for leniency, but we should leave it to the Soviet Union, which had suffered so much, to take the initiative.MARSHAL STALIN said that the most important thing was to restore theviolated treaty. He had told the United States Government in February about his conditions, when they wanted to mediate, and he had so informed HisMajesty&apos;s Government, but probably the United States Government had failed to persuade the Finns to accept.
PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that at that time the Finns would notlisten.MARSHAL STALIN said that they had signed a treaty and broken it.Everyone was ready to wage a war to modify a treaty. If the cession of Hangopresented a difficulty he would be willing to take Petsamo instead. He did not insist on Hango provided that he got Petsamo back. After all, it had in the firstinstance been a gift to Finland from Russia. The Soviet Union would prefer tohave a frontier with Norway so that Finland would not be a wedge betweenthe two countries.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that that was a fair exchange.THE PRIME MINISTER said that we wanted two things :-1. That Russia should be satisfied with her frontiers.2. That the Finns should be free and independent and live as well as theycould in those very uncomfortable regions. But we did not want toput any pressure on Russia.MARSHAL STALIN said that after all allies could squeeze each other ifthey wanted to from time to time. But let the Finns live. That would be all rightso long as half the damage they had done were made good.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked whether it would be any use if the Finnswere to go to Moscow without any conditions.MARSHAL STALIN said that if there were no assurances that anagreement would be concluded, then an expedition to Moscow would be ofadvantage to Germany, who would make capital out of any failure. This appliedalso to the aggressive elements in Finland, who would say that the Russians didnot really want peace.THE PRIME MINISTER said that would be a lie and that we would allsay so loudly.MARSHAL STALIN said &quot;All right, let them come if you insist.&quot;THE PRIME MINISTER said that His Majesty&apos;s Government were readyto leave the matter to Marshal Stalin, provided that the Finns were left with reasonable territories.   We should then perhaps have some comments to offer.MARSHAL STALIN said that that was obvious, and we were fully entitledto comment, and added that, if the President thought it worth while, let the Finnsgo to Moscow; he had no objection.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that the present Finnish leaders were pro-German and that they would not be much good, but that if there were others wecould get somewhere.MARSHAL STALIN thought it would be better to have others, but he didnot object even to Ryti. Anyone, even the devil, might come, he was not afraid of devils.THE PRIME MINISTER said he hoped Marshal Stalin would handle thequestion in relation to the possibility of Sweden&apos;s coming into the war in timefor our general offensive in May.MARSHAL STALIN agreed but said that he could not diverge from severalconditions : 1. Restoration of the 1940 Treaty.2. Hango or Petsamo.   (Here he added that Hango was leased to the soviet union, but he would propose to take Petsamo.) -3. Compensation in kind as to 50 per cent, for damage.   Quantities could bediscussed later.4. A breach with Germany.5. The expulsion of all Germans.6. Demobilisation.THE PRIME MINISTER replied that as to compensation it was easy-enough to do damage, but very hard to repair it, and that it was bad for any one country to fall into tribute to another. It did not work and could not be done.But so far as Germany was concerned, the Soviet Government should take all her[26609] d
(8)Record of a Conversation at the Soviet Embassy, Tehran, on 1st December,1943.Present:The Prime Minister.President Roosevelt.Marshal Stalin.Mr. Eden.M. Molotov.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Sir A. Clark Kerr.Mr. Harriman.Germany.MARSHAL STALIN then asked if there were any other questions.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said there was the question of Germany. Ifit was decided to divide Germany up this could be done in 3 or 15 ways.MARSHAL STALIN said that he would like to see Germany split up.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT agreed.MARSHAL STALIN suggested that the Prime Minister would object.THE PRIME MINISTER said No, he would not. He was in favour ofthe partition of Germany, more especially in the splitting up of Prussia andthe separation of Bavaria. But he must protest that he was still living at Lvovand had not yet got as far as Germany.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that so that there could be some discussionhe and his advisers had had a shot some three months ago at a plan. This involved the dividing of Germany into three parts.MARSHAL STALIN (with a grin) suggested that Mr. Churchill was notlistening because he was not inclined to see Germany split up.machines to repair the ruin done to the Soviet industries, whereas the Finns had only poor little musk rats and ermine and they had nothing to give.MARSHAL STALIN said (with a grin) &apos;&apos; what about your slogan againstindemnities ?&apos;&apos;THE PRIME MINISTER said that here there was no question ofindemnities, it was reconstruction.MARSHAL STALIN said that the Finns might perhaps be given anopportunity to repay the damage they had done in, say, 5 to 8 years.THE PRIME MINISTER said : No more than that, adding that experience showed large indemnities did not work.MARSHAL STALIN proposed to occupy a region of Finland if the Finnsdid not pay, but if they did pay the Russians would withdraw within the year.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had not yet been elected a Sovietcommissar, but that if he were he would advise against this. There were muchbigger things to think about.MARSHAL STALIN asked whether Finns would accept all the other points.THE PRIME MINISTER replied that we were behind the Russians and ready to help them at every turn, but we must think of the May battle.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that he was ready to stand behind all that had been said.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he liked all this talk.
THE PRIME MINISTER said that he considered that the root of the evillay in Prussia, in the Prussian Army and General Staff.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT asked that the whole picture should be examined and that after that a return should be made to the component parts.THE PRIME MINISTER said he wanted a map.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT then explained that the plan for the splittingup of Germany into five parts was as follows : (1) Prussia.(2) Hanover and the north-west part of Germany.(3) Saxony and the Leipzig area.(4) Hesse-Darmstadt, Hesse-Gassel, and the section south of the Rhine.(5) Bavaria, Baden and Wurtemburg.These five sections would be self-governing, but there were two more that wouldbe governed by the United Nations : (1) Kiel and its canal and Hamburg.(2) The Ruhr and the Saar.These would be under the control of the United Nations as trustees. He wasonly throwing it out as an idea which might be talked over.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that he might use the American idiomand say that the President had &quot; said a mouthful,&quot; and that Mr. roosevelt&apos;s plan was a new one to him. In his opinion there were two things : one constructiveand the other destructive. He had two clear ideas in his mind. First was theisolation of Prussia. What was to be done to Prussia after that was onlysecondary. Then he would like to detach Bayaria, Wurtemburg, the Palatinate,Saxony and Baden. Whereas he would treat Prussia harshly, he would makethings easier for the second group, which he would like to see work in with what he called a Danubian Confederation. The people of these parts of germany were not the most ferocious, and he would like to see them live tolerably, and in ageneration they would feel differently. South Germans were not going to startanother war, and we would have to make it worth their while to forget Prussia.He did not much mind whether there were one or two groups, and he askedMarshal Stalin whether he would be prepared to go into action on this front.MARSHAL STALIN said Yes, hut that he preferred a plan for the partition of Germany if Germany was to be broken up, something like the Presidents plan which he preferred as being more likely to weaken Germany. When one had todeal with large masses of German troops, one found them all fighting like devils,as the British and American armies would soon learn. The Austrians alone weredifferent, and he described the way the Austrians surrendered. Germans were all the same. It was the Prussian officers that provided the cement. But funda-mentally there was no difference between North Germans and South Germans;for all Germans fought like beasts. We should be careful not to include the austrians in any kind of a combination. She had existed independently and could do so again. So also must Flungary exist independently. After breaking up Germany it would be most unwise to create new combinations, Danubian orotherwise.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said he agreed warmly. There was no difference between Germans, and Bavarians and Prussians were much the same.The Bavarians had no officer class, otherwise they were exactly like the Prussians,as the American troops had already discovered.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he did not wish to- be represented as not in favour of the partition of Germany, but that if Germany were dividedinto a number of parts as suggested,by the President, and these parts were notattached to other combinations, they would reunite. It was not a question of dividing Germany, so much as giving a life to the cut off bits, and making themcontent not to be dependent on the Greater Reich. Even if this were achievedfor fifty years, that would be a great deal.MARSHAL STALIN said that it was important not to create dead Statesthat could not be brought back to life. The Danubian combination would not beable to live, and the Germans would take advantage of this by putting flesh onsomething that was only a skeleton and thus creating a new great State. Herehe asked whether Hungary and Roumania would&apos; be members of any combination.
He then reiterated his views about the advantages that this combination would present to Germany in the future. It was far better to break up and scatter theGerman tribes. Of course they would want to unite, no matter how much theywere split up. They would always want to reunite. In this he saw great danger,which would have to be neutralised by various economic measures, and in the longrun by force if necessary. That was the only way to keep the peace. But if wewere to make a large combination with Germans in it, trouble was bound to come.We had to see to it that they were kept separate, and that Hungary and germans should not be coupled. There were no measures to be taken which excluded a movement towards reunion. Germans would always want to reunite and to take their revenge. It would be necessary to keep ourselves strong enough to beat them if they ever let loose another w-ar.THE PRIME MINISTER asked Marshal Stalin if he contemplated aEurope of little States, all disjointed, with no larger units at all.MARSHAL STALIN replied, not Europe, but Germany. Poland and france were large States. Roumania and Bulgaria were small States, butGermany must be divided.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that Germany had been safer when shewas divided into 107 small principalities.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had rather hoped that there would be larger units not 20 to 30 brigades, but 5 to 6 army corps.MARSHAL STALIN said that the question as to how many States thereshould be remained for discussion, but that Germany should at all costs be broken up so that she could not reunite.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that what he proposed was a method.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he would like to make it clear thatthe present was only a preliminary survey of a vast historical problem.MARSHAL STALIN said that it was certainly very preliminary.At this point the PRIME MINISTER brought the discussion back to poland. He said that he was not asking for any agreement, nor was he convincedon the matter himself, but he would rather like to get down something likewhat he had, just put on paper, and he produced the following formula: &quot; Itwas thought in principle that the home of the Polish State and nation shouldbe between the so-called Curzon Line and the line of the Oder, including forPoland East Prussia (as defined) and Oppeln : but the actual tracing of thefrontier line required careful study and possibly disentanglement of populationat some points.&quot;PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT now brought the discussion back to Germanyand suggested that a special committee of the three Powers should be set up,or a committee under the London Commission to make a study of the question,keeping in close contact with Washington and Moscow, and reporting itsfindings which would facilitate the study of the problem in those capitals.MARSHAL STALIN agreed.THE PRIME MINISTER protested that the Polish problem was much more urgent. The Poles would make a clatter. Why not a formula on which hecould say something like this to them : &quot; I do not know if the Russians would approve, but I think that I might get it for you. You see you are being welllooked after.&quot; He added that we would never get the Poles to say that they were satisfied.   Nothing would satisfy the Poles.MARSHAL STALIN (with a grin) &quot; The Poles in London seem to be mostreasonable people.&quot; The Marshal then said that the Russians would like tohave the warm water port of Konigsberg and he sketched a possible line on the map. This would put Russia on the neck of Germany. If he got this he wouldbe ready enough to agree to the Prime Minister&apos;s formula.THE PRIME MINISTER asked what about Lvov.MARSHAL STALIN said he would accept the Curzon Line.
ANGLO-AMERICAN-TURKISH CONVERSATIONS IN CAIRO.1) Record of the First Meeting, 4th December, 1943.&apos;2) Record of the Second Meeting, 4th December, 1943.;3) Record of the Third Meeting, 5th December, 1943.4) Record of the Fourth Meeting, 5th December, 1943.&apos;5) Record of the Fifth Meeting, 6th December, 1943.6) Record of the Sixth Meeting, 6th December, 1943.7) Record of the Seventh Meeting, 7th December, 1943(1)Record of Informal Meeting held at President Inonu&apos;s Villa,4th December, 1943.Present :President inonu.M. Numan Menemencioglu.The Prime Minister.Mr. Eden.Sir Alexander Cadogan.Sir II. Knatchbull-Hugessen.THE PRIME MINISTER opened by explaining that the situation had improved greatly since the Adana meeting. Next year would be a crucial year.Germany would be attacked from all sides and would be beaten, if not we should go on. This meant that the danger to Turkey was much less. Therefore we wanted to discuss the situation freely as friends. Speaking frankly, it was very important to begin at once the reinforcement of Turkey&apos;s aerodromes, to multiplythe defence of Turkish cities, to instal anti-aircraft guns, radio location, &amp;c, andto provide experts. But the experts must be sent in thousands. They could come in mufti. It was important to diminish the risk which would arise when theGermans attacked. Preparations must be increased. As an instance the PrimeMinister mentioned that the Germans must be fully aware of the meetings going on in Cairo at the moment. They did not attack because the defences were so strong. We could do the same thing for the Turks and could begin at once ifthey would let us. We were not ready to attack in the Near East. The presentperiod was an interval during which the Turks must be got ready. Neverthelesstime pressed.^ PRESIDENT INONU said that suggestions had already been made by HisMajesty&apos;s Government for certain preparations to be undertaken. The Turks had replied that they would agree to everything except the infiltration of personnel.Personnel could not be camouflaged.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this could be discussed. The germans could be given vague answers. The direct threat would be from Bulgaria, butthis had been mentioned to the Soviet Government. Stalin had stated that ifTurkey declared war on Germany or was attacked by Germany and if inconsequence Bulgaria attacked Turkey Russia would at once declare war onBulgaria.   Marshal Stalin was absolutely clear about this.   There was therefore[26609] f-
no question of Russia and Bulgaria joining against Turkey. If we could prepareTurkey against air attack he was certain that Turkey would be safe.PRESIDENT INONU said that the answer given on the 17th November bythe Turkish Government to the questions asked of Numan in Cairo had simplifiedthe position. But there was the practical side to be considered. If the British hadfulfilled the Adana promises Turkey would have been much more ready.THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that the danger was now much less.PRESIDENT INONU said that the position was that we had decided to reinforce the Turkish Army but the tempo had been very slow.THE PRIME MINISTER remarked that in any case we had spent 25 million on it.PRESIDENT INONU said that the position against German air-attack wasfeeble. On land also it was weak when the Bulgarian Army was considered.Turkey must be able to avoid destruction at beginning.THE SECRETARY OF STATE suggested that infiltration, includinginfiltration of troops, should be put into motion as quickly as possible.PRESIDENT INONtT said that this would bring an immediate declarationof war on Turkey for which she was not yet prepared. If war were to become a fait accompli now, what object would there be. What purpose could Turkeyserve and what contribution could she make ?THE PRIME MINISTER said Turkey could make the greatest possible con-tribution. He did not now ask Turkey to invade Bulgaria, though this might arise later. But it was likely that in the event of Turkey entering the warRoumania might drop out.   She had already made proposals for surrender.PRESIDENT INONt) said that in the present passive position of Turkeyshe could,do nothing.  Their efforts would be negligible.THE PRIME MINISTER expressed disagreement with this. If we could use the Turkish bases we could dominate the islands, the fleet could get up to theStraits, we could chase the German air-forces out of the ^aegean and attack enemyconvoys. In fact we could clear up the whole region. Turkey need only stand toarms and give us the necessary bases. It was for Turkey to choose the extent ofher effort. Once her defences were completed her position would be good. If forinstance the opportunity came next year we could go ahead. Possibly ifBulgaria became aware of the Russian intentions she would not declare war on Turkey.PRESIDENT INONU said that we were discussing the same question as hadbeen put by the Foreign Secretary to Numan a month ago. We were askingTurkey to act as a base while remaining on the defensive till the moment came for action, whether alone or jointly. Co-operation on land in the event of attack was not at present foreseen. As to air no plan for reinforcement had beenenvisaged.   What was the plan for this 1THE PRIME MINISTER said that at least 20 squadrons would be provided and that the United States of America would provide bombers. The latter wasnot yet arranged, but it would be easy. Turkey&apos;s requirements in tanks might alsobe met, but rail transport was difficult.   Sea transport would be necessary.PRESIDENT INONU said that after the proposals put to the TurkishGovernment last week they were already beginning forming batteries. But theBritish idea was that preparations should be made for defending their own bases.THE PRIME MINISTER said that these preparations would also protectTurkey^THE PRESIDENT said that all this was part of a plan decided on by theGeneral Staffs, but it was also necessary to strengthen the Turks themselves apartfrom this plan.. THE PRIME MINISTER said that when Turkey had taken her decision in principle and secretly we could at once decide all these points and decide how to make Turkey as strong as possible for the rupture. Every day was of value.It was necessary to take risks to get things ready. We must decide how manyguns we required, where they were to be placed, &amp;c. As soon as the policy hadbeen settled things could be arranged.
PRESIDENT INONtT said that the Allies were occupied and could not atpresent contemplate co-operation in the neighbourhood of Turkey.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed. We were occupied elsewhere. But theTurkish Army was strong though not fully equipped. It would be a seriousthing to attack Turkey. It would be impossible to maintain four or five british divisions in the ^aegean at present. It was important that&apos; Russia was invitingTurkey to enter the war. He was certain that Russia would keep good faith. IfTurkey agreed to come in she would be seated with the victorious Powers. GreatBritain and the United States gave their full assent to the Russian invitation.It was, of course, impossible to foresee the future, but Russia had again signedwith ourselves and the United States a guarantee of the independence andintegrity of Persia.PRESIDENT INONU remarked that the Germans had prepared the bulgarian Army better than we had prepared the Turks.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this was quite true. At the beginningof the war Turkey felt conscious of her strength. But the importance ofmechanised and motorised equipment had since become clear. The Turks did not possess this, and therefore turned to us. We had once been in the same state.Now, however, there were arms and equipment in abundance and the stocks weredeveloping, though transport and training present difficulties. Since Adana the picture had greatly changed.PRESIDENT INONU said that at the meeting which was to take place at o&apos;clock he would explain the Turkish position officially. In effect, the answerwould be as follows : This winter, without preparation, to risk provoking a declaration of warand being destroyed, Turkey could not enter the war. If the Prime minister thought Turkey could be of use, the National Party had already been consulted and Turkish policy had been reaffirmed in principle. Turkey was the ally ofGreat Britain and must work with her, but not for objects of little importance. Itwas therefore necessary to make a plan for the preparation of the Turkish army.Let Great Britain make logical proposals. The object was to strengthen theTurkish army. After that a military plan, including the action to be taken by turkey, should be made. At present His Majesty&apos;s Government asked forstronger defensive preparations, after which Turkey is to provide bases for theBritish and nothing else.THE PRIME MINISTER said &quot; no &quot;; the more Turkey could do the better.We must make plans prudently and not advance against strong lines withoutpreparation. As soon as Turkey was in the war we would help to the utmost.But the necessary arrangements must be made. The period of danger would bewhile Turkey was being fitted out and when the enemy became annoyed by thesepreparations.PRESIDENT INONU said that the infiltration of personnel must nofbeallowed to become a cause of provocation. If Turkey were attacked, Britishaeroplanes would at once arrive.  Therefore, the aerodromes must be ready.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the period of danger would be beforethe arrival of the British air support.&apos; PRESIDENT INONU, referring to the proposals put to the Turkish Govern-ment last week, said that they would do their best to meet our requirements.THE PRIME MINISTER said, the political future was important and mustbe borne in mind. Russia would be very strong. It would be best to be on the sideof Russia and also of the United States and Great Britain: Our confidence in russian loyalty had increased since the Tehran meeting. Russia desired Turkishfriendship and was not likely to betray Turkey.PRESIDENT INONU said that solidarity with Great Britain pleasedTurkey. They had no suspicions. But it was first necessary to consider thepractical side.  No plan was possible without adequate preparation.THE PRIME MINISTER said that these plans were to be examined. time must not be lost. We must push the preparations on quickly and not fear there actions of the enemy.M. MENEMENCIOGLU said that Turkey did not fear the period.of preparation.   Risks must be taken.[26609] e 2
THE PRIME MINISTER said that perhaps in a few weeks, when Turkey was equipped, they would be ready to take their decision. The decision was for turkey, but it was for the Allies to make that decision possible. Perhaps the entry of Turkey into the war by itself would bring about the collapse of hungary and Roumania, and perhaps even of Bulgaria. If that were to occur the germans would be driven back, to the Danube.  Turkey would have rendered a vast service.PRESIDENT INONU said that Turkey must be prepared. He was glad tosee that Mr. Churchill had returned to the position at the Adana meeting. he agreed that there was not a moment to lose. He went on that it was essentialHis Majesty&apos;s Government should say that Turkey had been faithful to the alliance.At this point the discussion had to be suspended, as it was time for thegeneral meeting.(2)Record of Meeting held at President Roosevelt&apos;s Villa on 4th Decemberat 5 p.m.Present:President Roosevelt.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Mr. L. Steinhardt, United States Ambassador to Turkey.President inonu.M. Numan Menemencioglu.M. Surreya Anderman, Private Secretary to President inonu.Mr. Churchill.Mr. Eden.Sir A. Cadogan.Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen.Air Vice-Marshal George.mr. Helm.(M. Surreya Anderman acted as Interpreter.)PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT welcomed the opportunity of discussion withthe Turkish President. It was important that as many Nations as possible should join the United Nations, now numbering about 35, and Turkey&apos;s accession to theUnited Nations would be welcomed. They were concerned not only with winningthe war but also with the period after the war, and for both unity of Nations wasnecessary to achieve the purpose of them all. At Tehran important decisions hadbeen reached.(1) As regards the tvar itself. Agreement had been come to for operations in 1944 for Russian, British and American Forces in such a way that an Anglo-American Second Front would be opened on a very large scale. This would betimed with an increase of Russian pressure, so that attacks would be developedagainst Germany from all sides.(2) As regards -post-war problems. It must be seen to that Germany and japan did not start another war in 20 years&apos; time.Mr. CHURCHILL pointed out that he had assured the Turkish president and Government that the British Government would not invoke the alliance orask them to join the war unless and until such action could be taken without unfairrisk for Turkey, for whom he had great regard. He now thought the moment had come when Turkey should very seriously consider associating herself with thegreat Allies. The dangers which had been present at the time of the Adana Con-ference had now very largely passed away. The advantages to Turkey from joining in the war would be permanent and lasting, more particularly from thepoint of view of Turkish relations with Russia. These were causing Turkeyanxiety, but if Turkey accepted the invitation being put to her, Turco-Russianrelations would be put on the best possible footing. Turkey would sit on the bench with Russia, America and the United Kingdom and the other united nations. Turkey&apos;s great friend and Ally felt it would be a pity if she now missedher chance.   In a few months, perhaps six, German resistance might be broken,
and Turkey, if she did not accept the invitation now, might then find herself alone,not on the Bench, but wandering about in Court. It would be dangerous if Turkeynow missed the chance of joining the English-speaking peoples, numbering,excluding coloured races, some two hundred million souls. There were risks eitherway. But if Turkey associated herself with the United Nations she would also be associated with Russia, one of the strongest military Powers in the world, if notthe strongest, at any rate in Europe and Asia. President Roosevelt and he hadbeen authorised by Marshal Stalin to assure President Inonu that, if Turkeyentered the war against Germany or if Germany attacked Turkey, and Bulgariatook action, Russia would at once declare war on Bulgaria.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT remarked that Marshal Stalin had been very clear about that.  The moment Bulgaria acted, Russia would declare war.Mr. CHURCHILL also asked President inonu to note that at Tehran theSoviet Union had signed, with Great Britain and the United States, a new under-taking to respect Persia.Mr. Churchill said that these were important declarations. If in thecircumstances Turkey should feel inclined, at the request of her Ally, GreatBritain, who was now invoking the Alliance, and of the two greatest Powers inthe world, America and the Soviet Union, to throw in her lot with them in the nea,rfuture, we could then go ahead and consider how best to help Turkey with herpreparations, more particularly against the possibility of German and Bulgarianaerial attack. The publicity side was also most important, as the greatest possibletime should be gained for preparation before everything became known. Finallyit would be necessary to discuss the nature of the campaign to be waged by Turkey,i.e., whether it should take an offensive or defensive form.Mr. Churchill said that the entry of Turkey into the Grand Alliance of35 Nations would bring about great international changes. Roumania was now begging for peace. Hungary wished to get out of the war. Bulgaria was greatly divided. Mr. churchill&apos;s own opinion (and he had been associated with european politics for about 35 years) was that the entry of Turkey into thewar, arranged in the right way and at the right time, would bring about a seriesof landslides in these countries.   It would be most fruitful and welcome.After a brief interval PRESIDENT INONU said that he attached thegreatest importance to this meeting. When he learnt that President Rooseveltand Mr. Churchill wished to study and discuss the situation with him in fullsympathy and friendship, the possibility of the discussion was envisaged by his country and by the Turkish Assembly with the greatest confidence. He expressedthanks for the invitation and for the offer of study.THE TURKISH PRESIDENT said that since the beginning his country had taken a clear decision to stand beside those who were fighting the cause ofthe United Nations. She had been one of the first so to state her position clearly.The war had shown great fluctuations and difficulties, but throughout Turkeyhad remained firmly anchored to her Alliance with Great Britain, and to the ideaswhich she postulated for the future of humanity. In this decision Turkey hadnot been moved by any egotistical or personal interest.In connection with the object in view, it was equitable to think of the methodwhich those who had provoked this war had used to convince their peoples vengeance, &amp;c. Turkey had been one of the greatest victims of the last war.From the first moment, however, she had decided firmly and seriously to collabc-rate with those who were fighting for the fraternity of peoples, and she had remained faithful throughout the years. These had not been without risks for turkey. She had been alone and isolated. Great Britain had gone through ahard time and had fought gallantly. In her own way Turkey had done her best and she had sacrificed none of her principles.PRESIDENT INONU said that he did not want to go over all the ground,but President Roosevelt and Mr. Churchill would remember that the Turkishattitude had been appreciated,.and the Turks were very pleased at the repeatedassurances of this appreciation. At the moment when Germany was about to declare war on Greece, she gave as one of the reasons for doing so that the Greekshad sent an officer to Ankara for consultation. (Mr. CHURCHILL pointed outthat it had only been a pretext.) PRESIDENT INONU said that this wastypical, and no doubt had Germany thought it worth while to make Turkey pay for her policy, she would have done so.
Mow, however, PRESIDENT INONTJ continued, the situation had totallychanged.&apos; Mr. Churchill had outlined the advantages which would accrue to turkey if she joined in the war. President Inomi must, however, first point outthat so long as Turkey was not in the war she was not in danger. He could not accept the thesis that there would be danger for Turkey in staying out. Turkey&apos;attitude was not a matter for discussion. Turkey knew her engagement and she had replied to the invitation. She wished to collaborate with her Allies. Sheremained faithful to the principles which she had embraced from the first moment.The points which President Roosevelt and Mr. Churchill had disclosed were of great importance. The Soviet engagement about Persia and collaboration inconnection with Bulgaria were of appreciable value. The Turkish reply of the17th November had reaffirmed Turkey&apos;s desire to collaborate. Naturally Turkeyhad to state conditions, political and otherwise. But practical considerations,i.e., military needs, &amp;c, came before all others. Turkey was alone. If Germanydeclared war on her, the situation would be dangerous. Turkey was not prepared.From the beginning of the war there had been talk of preparation, and help had come along, sometimes quickly and sometimes more slowly. To a certain extentthis was fair. The Turks had asked for aeroplanes and tanks, but these had often been refused. The President had agreed to these not being supplied when he was assured that they were needed for active operations. In face of this assurance hehad had nothing to say. If, however, the reason was not active military require-ments elsewhere, but because, for one consideration or another, it was not desiredto supply them, the position was entirely different.A general discussion ensued at this point as to what the Turkish President &apos;meant by consideration. He said that in spite of events Turkish cordiality had remained steadfast. When the Germans were at Stalingrad and El Alamein,i.e., at the most dangerous moment of all. the Turks had renewed their assurances.On one occasion a British statement had linked together Turkey and Spain asneutrals and the Turks had at once taken exception to this. The Turks hadnot changed, and they did not tolerate suspicion. Actually, and althoughTurkey was feeble, she had done well behind her curtain, and the Turks werehappy about what they had done. To the British Ambassador, at the dangerousmoment, he had repeated his advice &quot; be strong in Egypt.&quot; All this backgroundconscientiously pushed him to a decision. But he was not ready. SupposingGermany collapsed to-night or to-morrow, everybody would be happy, he alone would be anxious, because Turkey had not come in.Mr. CHURCHILL said that he had always realised that Turkey&apos;spreoccupation was Russia. But Turkey&apos;s only sure course was with the Allies.As he had said at Adana, if Turkey were to come with the Allies at the chosenmoment, it would be in the interest not only of Turkey but of the whole world.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said there was no implication of a threat.The advantages to Turkey had been explained. The United States was,000 miles away, but would always remain Turkey&apos;s friend. The UnitedKingdom would also be the friend of her old Ally. The big question for Turkey was Russia, and if he (President Roosevelt) were President of Turkey, he would consider very seriously the advantages offered by the opportunity of makingfriends with Russia Mr. CHURCHILL interjected &quot; to bind themselves withRussia,&quot;PRESIDENT INONtT said he dealt with the past in order to arrive at one point. He had wanted to explain Turkey&apos;s entirely loyal attitude. The war might finish with or without Turkey&apos;s collaboration. In neither event wouldegotistical factors dominate. He had, of course, to pay attention to the interestsof his country, but Turkey remained faithful to her original decision of associa^-tion with the common cause. The Minister for Foreign Affairs had responded to the invitation of a month ago, and the Turkish Government had replied.Turkey wished to be with the Allies. But there was the practical side, and thepractical difficulties must be resolved. Turkey was not prepared. If the Allieswere prepared to meet the minimum essential requirements of Turkey, and ifafter these had been met Turkey could be useful to the Allies, &quot;we will comewith you.&quot;But the Germans would understand. They knew that there was effectivecollaboration, and that Turkey was doing many things which were incompatible with neutrality. It was for this reason and in order to gain time for prepara-tion that the Germans bad been told that the Allies had asked Turkey to comeinto the war, but that she had refused.   It was possible that Germany did not
believe this statement. In any case, she would watch every development most carefully. So far Germany had raised no strong objection to Turkey&apos;s actions.There had been no serious protests against her unneutral actions. Turkey wasnot in the war and perhaps Germany still thought that she would not come into it. But if the day came when Germany was persuaded that Turkey was cominginto the war, the Germans would react to the utmost of their ability.Mr. CHURCHILL agreed, but said that Germany could not do nearly asmuch as she could have done previously.PRESIDENT INONU said that the Turks had considered all these things.It was true that Germany could not execute a campaign from Istanbul to Syria.She could, however, by air action do vast destruction and could seize Istanbul.She had the material readily available to the westward of Turkey, where it hadbeen concentrated for two reasons, as a menace to Turkey and to prevent theAllies getting at her.PRESIDENT INONU said, however, that for him there was one practical point, i.e., the capacity to defend herself with the minimum indispensablerequirements. It was essential that in the period of preparation the germans should not be provoked. If the Allies have no confidence in Turkey they wouldnot discuss future developments until the period of preparation was over. . Ifthey had confidence they could discuss plans now.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT remarked that this was reasonable.PRESIDENT INONU said that so far preparations and supplies had notbeen.encouraging. If a new decision were taken it would depend on the Allieshow long it would be before Turkey was ready. He could not say. Butessential things must be provided. Turkey had mobilised everything she had,even material dating from the Middle Ages.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT enquired the position as regards anti-tankand anti-aircraft guns, and was told that so far about 800 of the latter had beenprovided.Mr. CHURCHILL said that this was more than the United Kingdom had at the outbreak of war.PRESIDENT INONU said that no doubt Turkey&apos;s Allies sometimes askedthemselves why they should go on.sending supplies to Turkey if she was nevergoing to come into the war. The Turks for their part complained that although they were not given supplies, they were still asked to come into the war. It wasa vicious circle. But Turkey could be got in for the last stage of the war ifthere were collaboration. He would be glad if the war were over in two monthswithout Turkey acquiring any glory. He thought, however, that the war wouldlast another year, and there was therefore plenty of time for Turkey to help.Mr. CHURCHILL said it was most important that Turkey should decide toenter the war when her influence would be greatest, and so take her place among the victorious nations. It was essential to shorten as much as possible the conflict,which was costing so much in blood and treasure.PRESIDENT INONU said he could contemplate two things (1) a plan of preparation involving supplies to Turkey, and (2) a plan of collaboration. Itwas naturally essential that effective collaboration should be studied by themilitary experts, and he hoped it would be studied on a big basis. What wouldsuit Turkey best would be that she should fight side by side with British and\me.rican contingents in her own part of the world. The President andMr. Churchill could, however, say that they had made their plans embracing thewhole field of world operations, and that Turkey&apos;s-role was so and so. That hewould understand. What he would not accept was a background of suspicion of Turkey&apos;s intentions, and a demand to come into the war blindly, with astatement that when Turkey had entered the war.she would be told what herpart was to be.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT and Mr. CHURCHILL vigorously disclaimedany such intention. Discussions could start now on the two stages indicated,and PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT, said that there was no question of Turkeybeing asked to come in and wait for a month or six weeks without any airprotection. They contemplated building up that protection at once. when that had been done by a certain date, Turkey could come in without the risk
of having Istanbul bombed to the ground. If President inonu could accept this in principle, the military authorities could take up the question and get .ready.Me. CHURCHILL pointed out that this work was already in hand, andhe hoped that in a few weeks the preparations would be complete so thatthe air bases could then be used for attacks on German-held islands. A pro-gramme could be arranged.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT suggested that nothing should be done to induce German attacks.Mr. CHURCHILL said that there was always a danger of this. TheTurks had been asked to allow 7,000 personnel to be infiltrated, and that involvedsome risk.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT suggested that the personnel might enterTurkey in plain clothes.Mr. CHURCHILL said that it would be impossible to avoid dangerousmoments. It might be that two-thirds of the preparatory work would becompleted when the Germans would become convinced that Turkey was irrevocablycommitted and would act. This danger could not be eliminated. It should,however, be reduced to a minimum by precautions, camouflage, &amp;c.PRESIDENT INONU said that the period of preparation would be adelicate one in spite of all precautions.. These precautions must, however, betaken and preparations made sincerely and seriously. He did not think that four or five or six weeks would be enough for the preparations, but. if in that timethe anti-aircraft preparations were got ready, that would, be something.Mr. CHURCHILL said that in six or seven weeks the anti-aircraft defencescould be in a good state. Moreover, in that time the strategic situation mighthave changed appreciably. There might, for instance, be a considerable changein the strategic situation as a result of the Russian advance towards Roumania.Mr. CHURCHILL then said that he contemplated a programme somewhaton the following lines :  (1) A declaration after the present Conference that Turkish policy had not changed.(2) A period of approximately six weeks during which material, especially for anti-aircraft defence, w^ould be pushed into Turkey.(3) Immediately thereafter, the placing of British and American combatsquadrons on the prepared airfields.(4) German protest and Turkey;s diplomatic reply, but steady continuation of reinforcement and preparation.(5) Reactions in the satellite countries Bulgaria, Roumania and Hungary.These reactions would be very important, as they would dominate theattitude of Germany. Throughout this period Turkey would continueto send supplies, including chrome (but only a little), to Germany.The Germans would be afraid to push things too far. They wouldbe afraid of the Turkish advance towards belligerency having theeffect on Bulgaria of making her change sides.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT confirmed that in this phase American heavy bombers, which had already made two raids on Sofia, would be attacking Bulgariaon a scale much greater than they had done hitherto.Mr. CHURCHILL added that at the right moment in this stage the bulgarian Government would learn that a Bulgarian declaration of war on Turkey would automatically mean a Russian declaration of war on Bulgaria.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT again stressed the importance of this Russianassurance, and remarked that he had been surprised when Marshal Stalin hadvolunteered it.At this stage (7 p.m.) the meeting was adjourned. -PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT suggested that President inonu would no doubtwish to consider what had been said and the conversations would be continuedlater.
(3)Record of Meeting held at President Roosevelt;s Villa onthe 5th December at 3 p.m.Present:President Roosevelt.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Mr. L. Steinhardt, United States Ambassador to Turkey.President inonu.M. Numan Menemencioglu.M. Cevat Acikalin.M. Surreya Andaman, Private Secretary to President Inorm.M. Sadi Kavour.M. Tor gut Menemencioglu.Mr. Churchill.Mr. Eden.Sir Alexander Cadogan.Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen.General Sir Maitland Wilson.Air Marshal Sir Sholto Douglas.Air Vice-Marshal George.Mr. Helm.(M. Surreya Anderman acted as Interpreter.)Prior to the full meeting President Roosevelt had been in conference withthe Turkish representatives. On the arrival of His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador atAnkara, but before the arrival of Mr. Churchill and Mr. Eden, president roosevelt had explained what he had been saying to the Turks. Though he didnot know what Mr. Churchill might say, it seemed to him that there could be three stages. He saw objection to dates for these stages though there should be ageneral date. In the first phase he felt that the delivery of the Adana material,which he understood was considerably behind, should be got on with as quickly as possible. Also in this first phase the airfields and other defences should becompleted and mechanics, &amp;c, got into place. The aeroplanes themselves would only arrive in the last twenty-four hours of this phase.President Roosevelt&apos;s second phase w^ould overlap the first. It was what hewould call the co-operative period, during which he regarded as a real necessitythe establishment of a small Anglo-Turkish-American Military Committee ofthree. General Wilson would be the obvious British representative and withhim would be some American general and a high Turkish officer, probably an air officer. This Committee would take care of many military developments forthe next three, four or five months. They would know all that was going on asregards military plans and activities, e.g., as regards Crete, Rhodes, &amp;c.Then, according to President Roosevelt, there was the third phase political.It was not very necessary to have full conversations with the Americans or theBritish. But it was very necessary with the Russians. The President thoughtit would be a mistake to defer the political phase until everything else had beentied up. The Russians were now in a good mood and now was the time to talk.President Roosevelt doubted whether dates could be fixed for these stages.-PRESIDENT INONU remarked that the practical side must be envisaged.If the Russians continued to insist on dates Turkey would be in the war, in four or five weeks. It was not practical for Turkey to come into the war and for discussions then to start. He very much regretted that the Russians were notat the Conference. The Soviet Ambassador was helpless and it would have been most useful if the Russians could have been there so that they could realise thateverybody was trying to help but that the method of fixed dates was impracticable.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT thought there was much in this and summarised the position as being that the Turks did not want to be caught withtheir pants down.AIR MARSHAL SIR SHOLTO DOUGLAS said that this would dependon the extent of infiltration in the preparatory period.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that the target date was dependent on progress.[26609] f
GENERAL WILSON said that they did not want a scramble. They wanted to get the equipment and everything in so as to be in a position to operate within24 hours. If things had to be rushed they would not be used to the best advantage.It would be best if nothing happened before all was ready.(At this stage Mr. Churchill and Mr. Eden joined the meeting.)PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT then briefly summarised the above, remarkingthat he thought it a mistake to date each stage. The final date might be deter-mined but not the date of the intermediate stages. He understood that therehad been a fall-down on Adana promises. As an instance he quoted that 1,800trucks had been promised but only 800 delivered. These past delays to-dayaffected Turkey&apos;s ability to defend herself.Mr. CHURCHILL said that there was another factor. The Turks had not taken full advantage of the school and tuition opportunities offered to them, andthis had affected their ability to absorb the available material. In this connexionAir Marshal Sir Sholto Douglas pointed out that 70 aircraft (54 Hurricanes and18 Beauforts) had been waiting ready for the Turks to collect for the last three months.PRESIDENT INONU reminded Mr. Churchill of his remark at Adanawhen inspecting newly arrived Hurricanes, that we no longer regarded these asthe most modern. They were in fact out of date. No doubt imperative considera-tions had made it impossible to supply better planes.Mr. CHURCHILL said that the situation had greatly changed sinceAdana. In the interval Italy had fallen, and it had been necessary to take military supplies for the battlefields in the Central Mediterranean. As a result the Eastern Mediterranean had not received full supplies. Even so Turkish sea and railway transport had been fully engaged since Adana, and the greater partof the Adana supplies had been delivered. The result was that to-day the Turkswere much stronger than they had been at Adana.PRESIDENT INONU said that the position taken up by Mr. Churchillat Adana had been generous and comprehensible. The situation to-day was not so clear and in fact was not known. Frankly he did not know what was required.Was it not possible to get out of the impasse ? If a date was fixed for pushingTurkey into the war in the near future, s.g., in a matter of weeks, there wouldbe an impasse. Was not the decision of Turkey to come into the war of some importance ?Mr. CHURCHILL said it was fundamental. It represented a new stage.The principle had been established.   It remained to study the method.PRESIDENT INONU said the question seemed to be when Turkey would enter the war. She had stated her conditions. He had spoken of plans of preparation and collaboration. Her representatives wanted to know how theycould render service. They wanted to know the risks they would run and howtheir forces would be used.Mr. CHURCHILL assented.PRESIDENT INONU remarked that the question of when Turkey wouldbe ready was a practical one. It depended on preparation. Just before lunch hehad received a plan. (Mr. Eden remarked that this plan had been based on atelegram from Tehran.) President Inonu went on to say that since Adana250 medium anti-aircraft guns had been delivered; of these ahout half were in use and the other half had arrived in recent months. The Turks were agreeable to giving them to British personnel to handle.AIR VICE-MARSHAL GEORGE remarked that there were 138 of theseanti-aircraft guns to be taken over. According to General Wilson, they would bereplaced by guns already in the Middle East.Mr. CFIURCHILL said that the replacement guns were here but that theymust not go into store.   They should go straight to the- airfields.PRESIDENT INONU said that this (the Tehran plan), though somethingby itself, was not a sufficient preparation for an army. He had thought it acomplete plan, and it seemed to him to be only a semblance of preparation.Mr. CHURCHILL remarked that it was not so bad as that. It seemed toMr. Churchill that first of all there should be the period of preparation.   He
hoped that this could begin at once. Throughout it transport facilities shouldbe utilised to the maximum extent. Perhaps a period of six weeks would berequired. Throughout this period everything would be camouflaged, though the flow would steadily grow. But Turkish policy outwardly would be unchanged.No doubt the Germans would be suspicious, but the development would gosteadily on.PRESIDENT INONU remarked that if the experts studied the necessary measures for two or three clays they would no doubt .be able to say wheneverything would be ready.Mr. CHURCHILL replied that within a period of six weeks it ought tobe possible to make considerable preparations against air attack.Mr. Churchill said that the second stage would then come, i.e., British and american aircraft would come to the fields prepared for them.PRESIDENT INONU said that the Turks must regard the day of the arrival of the aircraft as the day of the declaration of war. They must regard the arrival of the Allied aircraft with the utmost seriousness, and must count itas the beginning of a state of war with Germany.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that it was not desired that war shouldoccur until the fields were ready or indeed until everything was ready. he explained that by everything he meant everything in connexion with . thepreparation and defence of the airfields.PRESIDENT INONU said that as he understood the position, the airfieldswould be prepared in six weeks as one part of a general plan of preparations.After six weeks the Allied planes would arrive. Mr. Churchill seemed to thinkthat this did not necessarily mean a declaration of war by either side. In that event preparations would continue to go on, e.g., for two months (Mr. Churchillsuggested one month) or two weeks, and that then the Turks should take theinitiative in declaring war.Mr. CHURCHILL said preparations would continue so long as they werenot interrupted. Effective air protection would be provided when everything wasin place. Then would come the third phase when it could be arranged to employforces against the German-held islands. At the same time American aircraft would bomb Bulgarian airfields and so reduce the possibility of air attack on Turkey. Russia also would warn Bulgaria, This might be somewhere about the15th or 20th January. He did not want to push Turkey into a bad position and perhaps she might be ready for effective action about the end of February.PRESIDENT INONU said that he could not contemplate the conclusionof the first stage mentioned by Mr. Churchill and the arrival of the Allied aero-planes without the expectation or intention of a declaration of war.Mr. CHURCHILL said this was not certain.PRESIDENT INONU said he must be able to explain the position to his people. He must say that there had been no provocation. Turkey&apos;s engagementsto Britain were known and it was right that Turkey should be prepared to defendherself. He understood that if Turkey were attacked the aircraft would be thereto help her within 24 hours.Mr. Churchill, Mr. Eden and Air Marshal Sir Sholto Douglas explainedthat this would depend on the moment of attack. If Germany were to attackimmediately the Turks returned to Angora and before any preparations had beenmade, air assistance could not arrive for a week. If the attack came 15 days after the beginning of the period of preparation, there would be a delay of or 4 days. If, however, it were delayed for a month after the beginning ofthe preparatory period, the planes would be&quot; there in 24 hours. Thus,Mr. Churchill pointed out, it was very important that the period of infiltrationshould be as long as possible so that the planes could come effectively into actionimmediately they arrived.At the request of President inonu, M. NUMAN said that the discussions had perhaps rather wandered and that there might be some misunderstanding. Ithad not been President Inonu&apos;s purpose to ask how soon the Allied squadronswould arrive. His point was the danger of war at the end of the 6 weeks&apos;period of preparation. This danger might be 100 per cent., but even if it were[26609] f 2
only 30 per cent, the Turks must still regard it as 100 per cent., and M. Numansaid that Turkey could not envisage being in the war at the end of this periodof preparation.Mr, EDEN enquired what therefore was the Turkish proposal.PRESIDENT INONU said that a general plan of preparation must beagreed among the experts. Both parties must play a part in reaching a decision as to what was a reasonable, practical plan. The British would then be able toestimate the period required for its execution. Within that period the plan of future collaboration could be developed and the contemplated political discussions could be engaged. The Allies must however give up the idea of having turkey in the war within 6 weeks.  Otherwise the discussions had reached an impasse.M. NUMAN said that the difference between the two sides seemed to beessentially that, whereas the Allies regarded time as being the determining factor,the Turks regard preparations as being that factor. The Turkish Presidentwanted a plan of preparation. It might be that that could be completed in  days. If it could, then the Turks would come in in 5 days. If, however,it took 5 months the Allies on their side must accept that period.Mr. CHURCHILL said he was in sympathy with much of what M. Numanhad said. The preparatory period would, however, be over when the squadronscould land in force and be in action within 24 hours. The guns would bethere to defend the nests but the fighters were the birds which used thesenests. Mr. Churchill explained that what he asked for was the inception at theearliest possible moment and in full vigour of the preparatory plan. This meantthe arrival of supplies and material and of men in mufti against the arrival ofthe protecting air squadrons. Once this protection was established the situation would become dangerous for the enemy. In the intervening period, i.e., beforethe arrival of the protecting squadrons, the situation would be dangerous for turkey. Once the airfields were ready the squadrons could come in within24 hours, He doubted whether the Germans would then declare war on Turkey.&quot; Perhaps they would not attack. The Turkish Government could saythat the squadrons were there for Turkish protection. Once there, Turkey wouldbe defended. The personnel would come in advance and the squadrons later.This Avas what had happened at Lisbon. He knew that the circumstances Averenot the same.   They were, hoAvever, similar.M. NUMAN contested this. He pointed out that the Germans could not attack the Azores.Mr. CHURCHILL replied that this Avas so but that the Germans could havebombed Lisbon. President Roosevelt and he had always thought that the GermansAvould not bomb Lisbon. They had an interest in not doing so. PortugueseAvolfram was important to Germany it Avas in fact the chrome of Portugal.The position Avas much the same as regards Turkey. What point would there be in Germany attacking her ?M. NUMAN suggested that the question of the Azores be left alone. the atlantic battle had been decided. The use of Turkish bases was quite a different matter since it would be for direct attack on Germany.PRESIDENT INONU enquired what differences there were between whatthe Prime Minister had said and what the British had negotiated. Avith theTurkish General Staff.AIR MARSHAL SIR SHOLTO DOUGLAS said there was no realdifference.   The Air Attache had merely been discussing the first phase.M. NUMAN pointed out that there had been 5 points in the discussions ofthe Service Attaches. Some of these were practicable. Others were not. TheTurks could not agree to the infiltration of personnel but they could and. didagree to the infiltration of the requisite number of specialists.SIR H. KNATCHBULL-HUGESSEN pointed out that the Service Attacheshad asked for the infiltration of 7,000 personnel. This figure had now beenreduced to 2,000.At the request of President Inonu M. NUMAN explained that the questionof the preparation of the airfields was not the only question. There must be ageneral plan of which the question of airfields would form a part, indeed perhaps the principal part and the one requiring the greatest priority.  He suggested the
despatch of experts to Angora to discuss the general plan and to make anyother necessary proposals.Mr. CHURCHILL said that he wanted the preparations to begin at once,i.e., to get supplies, material and personnel introduced into Turkey forthwithand so get the air fields ready. This must be done with the utmost discretion andsecrecy. There would be no overt change of Turkish policy. It was, however,essential that it should begin at once and when the air fields were ready for theplanes, we should then want them to come in. The Turkish position would thenbe completely changed.M. NUMAN said there was one small point on which he hoped for agreement,namely, that there were two questions : that of the period of preparation andthat of the declaration of war. He considered that the entry of personnel would provoke war. The second stage would come with the arrival of the squadrons,for within a few days thereafter Turkey would be at war. It was necessary to separate these two points now. At the same time it was, however, also necessaryto begin preparations now.Mr. CHURCHILL remarked that the discussion seemed to have got intoa vicious circle. We were satisfied that no preparation could be effective withoutthe introduction of personnel, while the Turks refused the introduction of personnel because of the danger of provoking Germany. Thus no preparationcould be made against Germany being provoked.(At this stage the meeting was adjourned and on the resumption it wassuggested that, before a further plenary meeting was held, a discussion shouldtake place between a small committee headed by Mr. Hopkins, M. Numan andMr. Eden.   The meeting of this committee was arranged for 6 p.m.)(4)Draft Record of Meeting held at Villa Casey at 7 p.m. on 5th December, 1943.Present:M. Numan Menemencioglu.M. Cevat Acikalin.M. Surreya Anderman, Private Secretary to President inonu.M. Sadi Kavour.M. Torgut Menemencioglu.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Mr. L Steinhardt, United States Ambassador to Turkey.Mr. Eden.Sir Alexander Cadogan.Sir H, Knatchbull-Hugessen.General Sir H. Maitland Wilson.Air Marshal Sir W. Sholto Douglas.Air Vice-Marshal George.Brigadier Stayner.Mr. Helm.(M. Torgut Menemencioglu acted as interpreter.)Mr. EDEN opened the meeting by suggesting that Air Marshal Sir SholtoDouglas should explain what was proposed since he had a feeling that the Turkswere under a wrong impression.M. NUMAN thanked Mr. Eden. He said he would be glad to listen. he must however make it clear that he could not commit himself on military matters which were the concern of the experts and on which he was not competent.SIR SHOLTO DOUGLAS said that he was not going to deal with techni-calities. He was merely going to make a general expose to show why we wantedadvance infiltration.   In this there were two main objects : the first to provide
adequate defence for the most vulnerable points and the second to provide a force for offensive operations in the aegean. As regards the first, the vulnerable points were Istanbul, Izmir and Zonguldak. For these it was proposed to send in17 squadrons (12 of them Spitfires) and 5 regiments of light and 5 of heavyanti-aircraft guns. For purposes of defence it was essential to have an adequatewarning system and also adequate anti-aircraft defence for the air fields onwhich would depend the defence of Istanbul and other vulnerable places. until these essentials had been secured it would not be feasible to introduce thenecessary squadrons. This brought the Air Marshal to infiltration and his proposals were : (1) For radio location and operations room 200-250 specialists and 20-30vehicles.(2) Signals personnel for radio location and for linking air fields withoperations room 400 persons.(3) Key specialist personnel of anti-aircraft guns 420 persons.(4) Additional personnel for radio location, i.e., for extension of system round the coast from Zonguldak to Antalya 300 persons.(5) Administrative personnel for dumps, &amp;c-500 persons.This represented a total of about 2,000 personnel.The introduction of this personnel was the problem. Until something like this had been introduced Turkey would not be in a position of security when themoment of need came. .Mr. EDEN remarked that when all this personnel had been brought in the squadrons could be flown in in 24 hours for the defence of Turkey if Turkey were attacked. The complete effectiveness of defence would of course also be depen-dent on Turkey doing her share as promised with personnel for the anti-aircraft guns. It was as a result of the promise of this personnel that the estimatedinfiltration needs had been reduced from 7,000 to 2,000. Thus it could be seenwhat were the indispensable minimum needs to be introduced during the period of preparation.M. NUMAN said that he took the &quot;infiltration to be part of the generalminimum plan. He could not say whether the number of squadrons was adequate,though it sounded good. He obviously must however make a reservation on thequestion of their utility.Mr. EDEN stressed that in our opinion what Sir Sholto Douglas had explained was the minimum necessary for Turkey&apos;s protection. In addition weshould of course be ready to specify the material which we should be prepared tosupply for use by the Turks themselves.M. NUMAN remarked that matters were advancing. There was not animpasse. The arrival of foreigners was very important. Even a civilian arriving in Turkey to serve would be known to Germany and the latter would not beindifferent. He did not want to provoke the Germans before a certain degree of preparation could be achieved. Mr. Churchill had described this as a viciouscircle. He (M. Numan) did not agree but saw the problem from a different pointof view. He was ready to accept the requisite number of technicians for thematerial supplied. How many technicians these might be he did not know. Thatwould be a matter for the Turkish General Staff. Fie could not however acceptpersonnel additional to the proper complement of technicians.Mr. EDEN remarked that the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs musthave confidence. There surely could be no question of our wanting to introduceone&apos; single specialist more than was necessary. But how could the TurkishGeneral Staff say whether particular personnel was necessary or not? Duringthe preparatory period we did not wish to rush things any more than the Turksdid.  But we did want to get the preparations completed quickly.M. NUMAN said that the Turks had the same object. They did not wishto provoke the Germans. He could not agree to the introduction of personnelbut he did agree to the introduction of technicians, though he must make areserve regarding the number of these. What he had said amounted to anacceptance in principle of technicians for the material promised.Mr. HOPKINS remarked that President Inonu had several times spoken ofTurkey&apos;s minimum, defence requirements. He wondered if he was right in assuming that this did not refer to infiltration and air materials but to other
needs. He assumed that the British had been discussing such questions with theTurkish General Staff. Had the British any idea of Turkish minimum require-ments \ Did they, for instance, include anti-aircraft guns and aircraft ? Thisbrought up the question of the commitments to be made and he realised that itwas necessary to get personnel introduced in advance. But he wished to be clear in his own mind about the details.Mr. EDEN thought this was a good question. It seemed to him that therewere two points the material to be used by us in order to give protection to turkey, and the material to be given to Turkey for use by the Turks themselves.Mr. HOPKINS mentioned that there was also the Anglo-American force to go into Turkey in the event of war.Mr. EDEN said that in the first instance this was air alone and anti-aircraft.M. NUMAN said he wished to make an observation and to compare whatTurkey had got with what she had asked for. After the Adana conference the Turks had prepared a list of requirements which had been more or lessdiscussed. Later the British had entered into a definite commitment for delivery on the basis of that list. The Turkish list had remained a dead letter.The British list had not been much better (Mr. EDEN said that he could not agree). M. NUMAN went on to say that only some 4 per cent, of the items onthe general list had been delivered to Turkey. He did not wish to makereproaches. He would only state facts and mentioned in particular the caseof lorries of which 300 a month had been promised. For some time deliverieshad been about 160 or 180 a month. . In recent months there had been nodeliveries at all. Deliveries did, in fact, represent a very small proportion ofpromises.Mr. EDEN said that he could not accept M. Numan&apos;s figues. He must make it plain that the position now was not the position as it had been atAdana and he personally would not consider recommending his Government nowto supply to Turkey all of the material which had been discussed at Adana.M. NUMAN remarked that his had only been an observation.GENERAL WILSON said that even if it had been possible to supply allthe items on the Turkish Adana lists, it would have taken the Turkish railwaysthree years to carry them. As it was, Turkey had, since Adana, been supplied with 350 tanks, 48 self-propelled guns, nearly 300 anti-aircraft guns (over 100of them heavy) 300 field and&apos; medium guns, 200 mortars, rather less than 500anti-tank guns, an enormous quantity (about 99,000) of various guns andautomatics, 420 mortars, and about 1 million anti-tank mines for the defenceof Turkey. It was unfortunately true that there had been a shortage of delivery of motor transport. This had happened because the transport did not exist in the Eastern Mediterranean. The Turks had, however, said at Adanathat they had enough to defend themselves except for three anti-tank units andaviation support.Mr. HOPKINS expressed surprise at the extent of material assistancealready given since Adana. He wished, however, to clear the position up. Ashe understood things, the Allies had agreed, in the event of war, to put in air squadrons and anti-aircraft guns and personnel. How far removed were wefrom what were President inonu&apos;s minimum requirements in the event of war ?M. NUMAN said that if it were desired to negotiate on the basis of thesepast figures, he also could cite figures. At one moment 40 air squadrons hadbeen promised in the event of war. This had been reduced by half. Thepercentage of deliveries was not impressive. As for circumstances, he agreedthat they had changed since Adana, but things had turned out exactly as theyhad been foreseen at Adana.Mr. HOPKINS said it seemed necessary to get to grips with the problem.Was he to understand that the Turkish President considered he should havetwice the air force suggested % Was he to understand that the anti-tankpreparation was not enough ? Were the Turkish railways a limiting factor, inso far as concerned Turkey coming into the warl He asked, because, if Turkey was not coming into the war she must understand that these munitions, sovitally required elsewhere, would not come into Turkey at all.
M. NUMAN remarked that there must be some misunderstanding. Theposition had been quite clearly stated. The President had announced his intention of coming into the war. The question of material had, however,always been a serious one. At the time when the Anglo-Turkish Alliance wasnegotiated there had, at first, been a clause which postponed the operation ofthe Alliance until supplies were provided. He had realised that the supplies couldnot be provided and the clause had been suppressed. Since then and until now,supplies had still not been available. To-day, Turkey lacked everything. Notonly anti-aircraft guns and tanks but every sort of war material. He did not suggest that the Adana lists or any other list or anything like either of them should be supplied. He did, however, think that there ought to be a list of reasonable requirements. The Turks would not ask the impossible and with amaximum effort a list could readily be drawn up.Mr. EDEN said we had given the list of all that we wished to introducefor the defence of Turkey. If this were agreed we could then fix up what wecould provide for use by the Turks. But we did not want the preparation ofdefence to be delayed during the consideration of the second list.M. NUMAN said he agreed, but that it must be part of a general plan inwhich the air preparations would, of course, take complete precedence.Mr. EDEN enquired what general plan&quot;? M. NUMAN answered that it wasnecessary to decide the minimum requirements of Turkey if she were to enter the war.   A list would be necessary.Mr. HOPKINS said he understood that the limiting factor was motor transport. Was it a limiting factor for anti-aircraft personnel&apos;? There hadbeen talk of years for the introduction of requirements. We were dealing inweeks.M. NUMAN pointed to General Wilson&apos;s statement that two or three years would have been necessary to introduce the items on the Adana lists. Hadone-third of these been introduced in the year since Adana?SIR H. KNATCHBULL-HUGESSEN suggested that we were all wastingour time in discussing the past. It was a wasted effort. In the interval every-thing had changed, and it would be a waste of transport even to send to turkey to-day the material contemplated at Adana. Surely we should look at the future and not at the past.M. NUMAN welcomed the Ambassador&apos;s interjection and said he quiteagreed. He wanted to propose something practical. Could we not at once send to Angora the two Generals (one British, one American) proposed by president roosevelt so that they could concert at once with the Turkish General Staff and establish a list of requirements and work out complete collaboration ?Mr. EDEN said that this was something apart from the fundamentalquestion. We had this afternoon given to our Turkish friends a list of what we thought necessary for the defence of Turkey against attack. This must be thebasis of working. In addition, we could discuss further material, but he couldnot accept the delay involved in the addition of other material quite unknown.M. NUMAN said that the President had answered Mr. Eden&apos;s point. Hehad said that 2,000 men and 600 vehicles were not enough for the defenceof Turkey, though they were no doubt enough for the defence of British air bases.Mr. EDEN pointed out that they were not for the defence of British air bases,but for that of Istanbul, Izmir and Zonguldak.M. NUMAN remarked that the Turks could not contemplate Turkishdefence being entrusted to the British. What they would and did contemplatewas the defence of Turkey by the Turks with British help.AIR MARSHAL SIR SHOLTO DOUGLAS pointed out that air defencedepended essentially on fighters, and this must be defended by anti-aircraft guns.The first essential was to get the fighter defence established.Mr. EDEN said that there were two points : The first, what we introduced for the security of Turkey; and the second, the other things which the Turksmust have before Turkey could take action.GENERAL WILSON explained that what had been, mentioned hitherto was for Turkish defence.   It was only an advance guard.   Actually, the total force
contemplated would be 32,000 troops (11,600 of them air) and 6,000 guns and vehicles (375 guns, representing 5 light and 5 heavy anti-aircraft regiments).Mr. EDEN said the urgent plan was one for immediate defence, and theexecution of this represented the dangerous period.M. NUMAN having remarked that he could not comment on these figures,SIR H. KNATCHBULL-HUGESSEN pointed out that, as men and materialwere introduced, the danger to Turkey would be correspondingly diminished. Thefirst problem was to ensure safety and then to build up.M. NUMAN said Turkey was coming into the war. It was necessary to draw up a plan of preparation and a plan of collaboration, and at the same time to take up political matters in another direction.Mr. HOPKINS having remarked that reinforcement would be limited bytransport facilities, and that, as regards priority for air, we already give theTurks what they can take, said he must come to the main point. The war had reached a critical stage. It was impossible to divert to a neutral country warmaterial which was not to be used against Germany. The British Prime minister had been authorised to express the hope of the United States and of Russia that turkey would enter the war at an early date. We knew that when a nation went to war with Germany she might suffer losses -the United Kingdom, Russia andthe United States had suffered severe losses. He knew that Turkey wanted toenter the war. In the last analysis a country went to war in its own interests.We wanted Turkey in the war even if she could not have all she wanted. GreatBritain, Russia and the United States had not all they wanted when they entered the war. At this critical period in the war the entry of Turkey might save the lives of hundreds of thousands of Allied nationals. The 1st January was not a set date, but Turkish participation might not be useful after very long after that date. We wanted Turkey to enter the war willingly and whole-heartedly.We should like Turkey to enter the war about February, even though we knew that in doing so Turkey might suffer. We hoped Turkey would enter because all allied military and political opinion considered that her entry would shorten thewar. Only the Turks themselves could speak for Turkish self-interest. If,however, discussions were prolonged about the adequacy of material, &amp;c, -Turkey&apos;s entry would be futile. Turkey could be sure that if she came in we would do everything we could all possible military and air support would be affordedher. He knew he was correctly interpreting President Roosevelt when he saidthat he hoped that Turkey would in her own interests come in willingly and whole-heartedly.Mr. EDEN said that he wished to have the Turkish position correctly under-stood, and M. NUMAN confirmed that it was as follows : (1) Our proposals for infiltration were accepted in principle, but M. Numanmade a reservation as regards numbers pending consideration by theTurkish General Staff.(2) If the programme imrolving infiltration were accepted Turkey will not take action which she considers might lead her into a state of warwith Germany until material and supplies for her use have been given,and the figures of these yet remain to be determined.(3) Mr. Eden understood that Turkey had political questions to raise. he did not know what these were.As regards (3) M. Numan referred to the Russian undertaking regardingBulgaria. He thought that this was the sort of point which he would like todiscuss with the Russians. There were other points which he would also like todiscuss. But these discussions could take place during the period of preparation and would in no way delay either preparation or &quot;collaboration.Mr. EDEN enquired whether there were any other points to be put down.M. NUMAN said that Mr. Hopkins had spoken of willing entry. This wasalso the desire of the Turks. They must, however, have a minimum of essentialpreparations. Moreover, this was a commitment to the Turkish people and tothe Party.Mr. EDEN enquired what Turkey wanted under (2). Was it not possible forthese requirements to be stated without discussions at Angora1?[26609] g
M. NUMAN repeated that he was not competent to say what the military needs were. All he asked for was comprehension. It lay in our hands todetermine when Turkey could enter the war, since this would be determined bythe supply of the necessary material.M. Numan confirmed that, as he had previously said, the infiltrationprogramme under (1) above could go ahead while the discussion of (2) was inprogress.(At this stage (8-15 p.m.) the meeting was adjourned.)(5)Record of a Meeting held at 4 p.m. on 6th December at President In6nu&apos;sVilla.Present :President inonu.M. Menemencioglu.M. Acikalin.The Prime Minister.The Secretary of State.Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had tried to put on paper the plan of action as he saw it. He gave the President a paper to read which he had prepared the same morning. He explained that it was only unofficial and represented his own thoughts. He was prepared to discuss Turkey&apos;s political position and the positive action which Turkey could take, but he did not intend- to force the pace.PRESIDENT INONU said that the Prime Minister had asked for a plan of operation.THE PRIME MINISTER explained that this was a preliminary plan.THE PRESIDENT went on to say that Turkey asked for a plan ofco-operation. As President Inonu saw it, in the present plan Turkey was to await enemy action and always be ready for German or Bulgarian intervention.During this time the Turkish task would be to furnish bases for the Allies.THE PRIME MINISTER said that on this basis no one could talk ofpositive intervention in the interval. He thought it most unlikely that Bulgariawould attack.   Turkey, therefore, would not be invaded.THE PRESIDENT observed that the air battles would begin.THE PRIME MINISTER replied that as soon as the Allied squadrons came in Turkey would have considerable defence. The Germans were not so powerfulnow as in January. If Turkey wanted to do more, this might be arranged. Thebest thing for Turkey was to be as strong as possible before the decisive moment.In addition, discussions would take place during the preliminary period for a positive plan of action by Turkey for the moment when Turkey declared war.The General Staffs would arrange this. Armoured divisions and two or threeanti-tank regiments would be sent, subject to transport. As soon as Smyrna andthe route to the Straits was open much more could be done.THE SECRETARY OF STATE said that once the aegean was open it mightbe possible to put a small British armoured force beside the Turks.THE PRIME MINISTER said that there were also great political questions-the pledges to be given to Turkey by the United States, Great Britain and russia. The basis of it all was to take Turkey into comradeship. Turkey wasnot asked to exhaust her resources. The mere fact of Turkey&apos;s early entry intothe war might result in the collapse of the Balkan satellites. Turkey would notbe secure until the air squadrons had been flown in. She would be bombardedbut not invaded.
THE PRESIDENT, summing up, understood that till March or afterwards,until Germany had been encircled, Turkey would remain alone, except for theprotection of the air squadrons which the Allies could send. It was difficult for Turkey to decide. Another essential thing to know was whether the Secretaryof State proposed that this decision should be taken by the end of the year.THE PRIME MINISTER said &quot; No.&quot;  It should be taken two months later.PRESIDENT INONU said that the National Assembly had discussed this and had decided on the line of action which he should take in the conversations.The present proposal was something different. It presented great difficulty. he understood the political side of the matter, but argued that Great Britain didnot contemplate allowing time for the equipment of the Turkish army.THE PRIME MINISTER said that time pressed. If Turkey lost four or five months matters would proceed without the Turks. It was important for turkey to be on the side of the United Nations. Possibly in six months&apos; time we should not require the Turks. He desired fellowship. Turkey should decidenow. If within six months Turkey did nothing and took no risks her positionwould suffer. We all had difficulty in handling Russia. Turkey would be secureif she was allied with Russia. It was impossible for Turkey to remain in thecoulisses.  We were suggesting a wise method of procedure.PRESIDENT INONU said that Turkey was now on a peace footing. Toget on to a war footing they would require the necessary equipment.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the equipment could not.be provideduntil the road was open. The scheme which he proposed was the only solution.He did not ask for an immediate answer.(6)Record of Meeting held at President Roosevelt&apos;s Villa at 5 p.m. on 6th December, 1943.Present:President Roosevelt.Mr. Harry Hopkins.Mr. L. Steinhardt, United States Ambassador to Turkey.President Inonti.M. Numan Menemencioglu.M. Cevat Acikalin.M. Surreya Anderman, Private Secretary of President Inbnii.M. Sadi Kavour.M. Torgut Menemencioglu.Mr. Churchill.Mr. Eden.Sir Alexander Cadogan.Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen.- General Sir Maitland Wilson.Air Marshal Sir Sholto Douglas.Admiral Sir Algernon Willis.Air Vice-Marshal George.Mr. Helm.(M. Surreya Anderman acted as Interpreter.)Prior to the meeting President Roosevelt, Mr. Churchill and the TurkishPresident had been in private conference.Mr. CHURCHILL said that the Turkish President had decided to postponehis departure until midnight on the 7th December. This would provide anopportunity for going over the ground in greater detail. He had submitted to thePresident a plan of action and this would raise the question of how it was to becarried out if Turkey were attacked and drawn into the war. In the interval a[26609] g 2
plan would be drawn up for Turkish action in conjunction with the great Allies.There was also the question of political guarantees, if Turkey by her actionsshould be drawn into the conflict. It was right and proper that in this event theAllies should see Turkey through,PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT remarked that when it came to the discussionof political guarantees it would be desired to include Soviet representatives.THE TURKISH PRESIDENT said he had been in contact withMr. Churchill during the afternoon when the essential points had been made.They would be able to discuss these to-morrow when the position would be clearerin all directions. He thought, however, that one feature governed the solution ofthe whole question, namely, the period for material preparation. After that oameother phases. As the President now understood it, however, such a period of preparation was not envisaged, or rather that a mixed method was contemplated.This was a cardinal point.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT thought in the first period Turkey would commit only neutral acts. She would receive equipment and material(Mr. Churchill personnel) and men in mufti. Mr. Churchill remarked that inthese conditions the Germans would not want to break with Turkey.THE TURKISH PRESIDENT said that for months Turkey would face theGerman army alone. He had not contemplated this. He had thought that whenthe Germans declared war the Turks would be in touch with some Anglo-American forces. But in this period of months the Turks would be alone with theGermans. This was a great question, and the President did not think he coulddecide upon it.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT remarked that he did not think that theGermans would declare war in the first period.PRESIDENT &quot;INONU said that their record showed that the Germansalways attacked for prevention. When they saw after a certain time that Turkeyhad taken her place openly with the Allies they would use this argument and attack.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT pointed out that the Turks had already been receiving supplies on a considerable scale without the Germans taking exceptionthereto. Why then should the Turks worry now ? In the first period there wouldbe no question of the Turks taking the kind of action which would justify theGermans attacking them. Surely the work on airfields and the introduction ofmaterial flak, &amp;c, i.e., the same sort of thing as had been going on in the past,could continue. This would apply to lease-lend material and the trucks previouslypromised would be delivered. In fact there would be no change except that therewould be an accelerated tempo.Me. EDEN remarked that the technicians would also have to come in. Thiswas essential.PRESIDENT INONU said that the Turks had replied to Mr. Eden&apos;s request for air bases for the Allies. It had been said that the provision of these wouldnot provoke war. The Turks had replied that they must regard the matter as very serious because they were convinced that it would provoke war. This meantcontemplating Turkey&apos;s entry into the war. The Turkish army was not ready and the country was exposed to enemy air attack. They must, therefore, haveassistance and there would have to be a period of preparation. According to theplan action would begin at the end of this phase. We were now in the first phaseand he understood that it was thought that preparation would take too long at atime when the Allies could not wait. The Allies seemed to think that the TurkishGovernment should act in spite of risks.   This was difficult.Mr. EDEN said that a German land attack was most improbable, especiallyin view of the warning which Russia had promised to give to Bulgaria.PRESIDENT INONU said that Turkey would be exposed to air attack, andalso to land attack by the Bulgarian army fortified by the Germans. president roosevelt doubted whether Bulgaria would face a hostile Russia.PRESIDENT INONU said that perhaps a hostile Russia would induceBulgaria to hold back, perhaps it would not. The present Bulgarian Governmentwas completely committed to Germany.
PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT did not think that Bulgaria would declare war on Turkey, and he doubted whether the Germans had enough men to stage aGerman land offensive against Turkey by way of Bulgaria. President Inoniithought, however, that the Germans would be able to get to Istanbul.In reply to a question by President Roosevelt PRESIDENT INONtT saidthat Turkey had about forty divisions scattered about the country. They werenot prepared. If the Allies had been able to give the desired material assistancein the past the Turkish Government could have replied affirmatively to any demand. As it was they had put all available material, including some very oldstuff, into service. They had hoped that this entirely out-of-date material wouldbe replaced by new material.  How was it possible to get out of the impasse ?Mr. CHURCHILL said that the first thing was to prepare the nests forthe birds. This must be done secretly and discreetly in order not to alarm theGermans. The equipment and personnel agreed upon would be put in. Thenwould come the second phase when all was ready and when the air squadronswould arrive within twenty-four hours. From that moment Turkey would have much greater security than during the preliminary period.PRESIDENT INONU said that even if the twenty air squadrons had arrived or were ready to come in, it would not be possible to say that Turkey was ready. Complete plans for assistance would have to be made and material wouldhave to come in for the fortification of the army. In the event of attack theAllies would have to assist. Only one part of the preparation for this assistance was being discussed. The rest was being left to wait. But during the prepara-tory period proposed in the discussions, he must prepare his army, mobilise it and concentrate it. Much had been done but it was most inadequate, and a sort of concentration must take place. All this was apparently to be finished by the15th February, and the Turkish army must be put on a war footing, for theGermans would strike at the first sign of the entry of the twenty squadrons.Mr. CHURCHILL enquired whether the Turkish army was not alreadymobilised and was informed that it was half mobilised.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT suggested that if mobilisation had first to takeplace it would take a long time and suggested, as did Mr. Churchill, that in anycase mobilisation would surely be more provocative than work on airfields.PRESIDENT INONU said - that precipitate action without preparationseemed to be contemplated.   He did not see any possibility of undertaking this.Mr. CHURCHILL remarked that the Turkish President seemed to think there was a serious danger of invasion. He, however, thought invasionby Bulgaria was most unlikely.PRESIDENT INONU said it was a matter of opinion. One could not besure what the enemy would do. Both the Bulgarians and the Germans had forces on the Turkish frontier, and the Turks must calculate that they would all beused.Mr. CHURCHILL thought that it was impossible to get to a conclusion at.this meeting.   He would like to go over the ground with the Turkish president on the 7th December together with documents.   The discussion could not be concluded this evening.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that what he envisaged was to talk of thefirst period and to set an objective date for it. This date would not be a hard and fast one, but it would be something to aim at. During this period, whichwould be in two parts, the Turks would give the Germans and Bulgarians noexcuse whatever for declaring war on Turkey. In the first part of the periodwork on the airfields would go ahead exactly as had happened before, and supplies and equipment, delivery of which was behind-hand, would be sent forward.Neither of these would give any excuse to the Germans.The delivery by the Americans of the thousand lorries with which they werebehind-hand would give the Germans no excuse or provocation. At the sametime mechanics, equipment, radar and technical equipment would come in as ithad done before, and none of this would provide an excuse for Germany.Mr. CHURCHILL interjected that the flow would be on the same lines as before but on a much more intense scale, otherwise Turkey would not be ready.
PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that as regards work on the airfields, thework would go on as before and Turkish labour would be employed. This action would not provoke the Germans.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT went on to say that in the second part of hiscontemplated first period the Turks would bring more of their troops scatteredthroughout the country to the European side of the Bosphorus. Turkey had theright to do this without provoking an attack. It was President RoosevehVsexpectation (not alone his hope) that Turkey could get through the whole of thisperiod without attack or war. At the end of it the tempo would be accelerated,but by that time preparations would have got so far that the twenty squadronscould be brought in and be in action within twenty-four hours if Turkey were attacked.PRESIDENT INONU said it was a question of practical things. He was afraid that hopes could not be realised. The standpoint of the British was that turkey must come in as soon as possible. If he said yes the plan would be that proposed by Mr. Churchill, then Turkey would begin to mobilise. The firstthing would be to facilitate the arrival of the British squadrons. Mr. ChurchilFsexpectation would then be realised. But this would mean Turkey&apos;s immediateentry into the war and the only assistance she would receive would be air assist-ance. The Turks contended&apos; that they were not ready for immediate entry.Their view was that a planned preparation must be made before Turkey couidenter. It seemed to be thought that in contending thus, the Turks were merelydragging things out and adopting delaying tactics.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that the Allies also were not ready, for the twenty squadrons would only be ready on the 15th February and Mr. Churchillsaid that he was asking for the squadrons to come in on the 15th February.PRESIDENT INONTJ said, however, that other things were necessary, inparticular the army had to be strengthened.Mr. &quot;CHURCHILL enquired how long this would take. In view of thepaucity of Turkish communications it would take months to make the Turkisharmy completely strong so as to enable Turkey to be safe, and by that time thereprobably would be no desire that Turkey should come in. The war was going on and the moment for Turkey would pass. This was a serious possibility forthe Turks.Mr. ROOSEVELT, remarked that the Turkish army was very good,particularly the infantry. Its artillery was good, especially for ground warfare.It needed improved communications and aviation. He had been wonderingwhether by the 15th February the Turkish army could not be trained and concen-trated in the north to an extent adequate to ward off attack with the aid ofair support.PRESIDENT INONU said that if this was a question only of mobilisationand concentration it could be clone, or at least for the greater part. But at theend of it the Turkish army would only have its present material. Technicalpoints were now being discussed, and Mr. Churchill said that the strengthening of the Turkish army would take months and months. It was twenty days sincethe Turkish Government had given their reply of the 17th November, and nothinghad happened in the interval. Turkey&apos;s material needs could be studied andascertained in a week, and then the Allies could say, on the basis of supply andtransport possibilities, how long it would take before Turkey was ready.Mr. CHURCHILL pointed out that Turkish communications had been fully occupied since the delivery of the Turkish note on the 17th November. TheTurkish army was good; it had been mobilised for four years. It was aconsiderable force, much stronger than the Bulgarian army, and it had already received much. It was true that it had not received as much as the Turks wouldhave liked, but he considered that the danger of a Bulgarian land attack was negligible.Mr. CHURCHILL suggested that it would be better to adjourn thediscussions. If President Roosevelt would confide the further discussions to him,he would continue conversations with President Inonu on the 7th December andreport to President Roosevelt by telegram.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said that he would have liked to have been hereto complete the discussions, but that he must leave on the 7th December.  He urged
very strongly that serious consideration should be given to the question of how much could be done before the 15th February without giving offence to Germanyand Bulgaria.PRESIDENT INONtr said the situation seemed to be that Turkey wouldintervene on the 15th February (President Roosevelt and Mr. Churchill at oncecontested this). There would be a period of preparation. What could the Alliesgive Turkey in two months ? What could be carried ? The Turkish General staff would study these points. But what would happen after the 15th February?That, he presumed, would be the period for action.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT said it would not necessarily be the period for action. But from the 15th February the Turks would be expected to do&apos; things which were no longer neutral. It meant that there would be two months beforeBulgaria or Germany would attack, and Mr. Churchill remarked that in thattime Bulgaria might well be out of the war.PRESIDENT INONIT wondered what the level of preparations would be intwo months.   It could not be determined without study.Mr. CHURCHILL said that this would be gone into in the further conversations. To the Turkish Presidents remark that he had no military expertswith him, Mr. Churchill said that the Allies would say what they could put in.PRESIDENT INONU said he would wait for this information. He couldnot say whether it would be enough, but he would take the information and returnto Ankara. He would, however, be obliged to reserve his reply. to president Roosevelt&apos;s remark that his Chief of Staff (General Somerville) would arrive to-morrow and be here for two days, the Turkish President enquired whythere should not be Staff talks.Mr, CHURCHILL pointed out that time was too pressing and that the twenty squadrons had to be got ready.PRESIDENT INONU said that in three or four days he would be ready to reply. The decision would be taken on all the facts. They found themselves ina situation which was fixed by time, but he would see what could be providedwithin two months and the Turkish Staff would offer their observations, includingmodifications and additions.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT thought that agreement should be reached onthat. It was useless to talk about other matters, This was the core of the whole problem. He would leave General Somerville, or his assistant, to pursue thediscussions, which were mainly military. M. Numan again remarked that theTurks had no military experts, but Mr. Churchill pointed out that the question should be discussed and the Turks then send their observations.Mr. EDEN stressed that not everything should be adjourned for considera-tion at Ankara.   Things must be pushed forward.Mr. CHURCHILL cautioned that at the best not much could be provided forthe Turkish army. The Turkish communications would be blocked by the delivery of the air programme. The agreed material and technicians must go forward,and there would not be much room for anything else. The Turks must, therefore,not put their military material expectations too high as otherwise all hopes wouldbe killed.PRESIDENT INONU said he was forcing himself to try to find a possibleposition in the Allied programme. He was doing so with the best will in theworld. But he must make the position clear. So far the Turks had no material.A preparatory period of two months was now proposed to him- He had not saidthat this was enough. The Allies had the material*and the transport, but he didnot know how much was going to be available. He understood, however, thatthe main effort was to be concentrated on aviation material and personnel.(Mr. Churchill interjected that air was the only danger.) At present, as theTurkish President saw it, it was contemplated that Turkey would enter thewar with anti-aircraft preparation alone.PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT then suggested the conclusion of the meeting and kept back the Turkish President to whom he wished to bid goodbye.
(7)Record of a Meeting at Casey Villa on 7th December, 1943, Morning.Present:President inonu.M. Menemeneioglu.M. Acikalin.Prime Minister.Secretary of State for. Foreign Affairs.His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Angora,THE PRIME MINISTER put to President inonu the proposal that by theloth February all measures should be taken to render possible the fly-in of the20 Allied squadrons. The Prime Minister would be ready after the 15th february to consult with the Turkish Government before the fly-in is carried out. By thattime the situation may have evolved. The Balkan satellites may be on the pointof falling out of the war. We should expect all measures to have been taken bythe 15th February to render the fly-in possible. It would not be possible to forecast enemy action between now and the 15th February. The President ofthe United States had said that Germany would be given no excuse to attackTurkey in this interval. Germany would not consider excuses but only whetherit was worth her while to attack Turkey. Therefore by the 15th February weshall know more about the German reaction. We have agreed on the preliminarysteps and the work on the airfields must be finished as quickly as possible. after that on the 15th February, if the preparations are complete, he will ask whetherthe squadrons can come in and the matter can be discussed as between friends and allies. If after the 15th February Turkey will not receive the Alliedsquadrons and wishes to prolong the discussions of the equipment of the Turkisharmy, then the Prime Minister will be forced to form other plans. The Alliedsquadrons cannot be wasted, they would have to be used elsewhere. The15th February will be the critical and serious moment. But if we are forced, after that, to send the squadrons elsewhere, the question cannot be reopened with turkey. It must be closed. We should have to tell our other Allies that our policy with Turkey had failed. If the Turkish answer is favourable we would beginas quickly as possible to send in further material. But before the 15th FebruaryTurkish communications would be blocked with the material for the airfields. Itwas the Prime Minister&quot;s opinion that Bulgaria would not attack and it was even uncertain whether the Germans would push Bulgaria to attack, becauseif Bulgaria did so she would have to withdraw her nine divisions from Yugo-slavia and. this would create difficulty for the Germans.PRESIDENT INONU understood that the Prime Minister had resumed the conversations of the last two or three days.M. MENEMENCIOGLU said that the Turks had said all they had to say-in the last three days.PRESIDENT INONU said that he had the impression that on the essentialquestion both sides had reserved their own opinions. The Turks had foreseentwo periods : (1) preparation and (2) effective co-operation. This had beenaccepted by the National Assembly and had formed the subject of the answer ofthe 17th November given by the Turkish Government. On the other hand, thePrime Minister considered only the first period, which was purely one for prepara-tion, especially as regards the airfields.THE PRIME MINISTER explained that this was because he did not regard invasion as a serious danger.PRESIDENT INONU asked whether he had rightly understood that thePrime Minister had not excluded the supply of other goods either before or afterthe 15th February.THE PRIME MINISTER said certainly not. The quicker the supplies were sent the better.PRESIDENT INONU asked whether the Prime Minister thought that these supplies should be complete before action was taken.
4550THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was not necessary that the supplies for the Army should be complete by the 15th February, and for the Turks to insist on this would be the same as saying that they would not come in. Tocomplete supplies for the Turkish army is to adjourn the final Turkish decisionindefinitely. On that basis the chance of shortening the war by Turkey&apos;s entrywould be lost.PRESIDENT INONU said that he thought the difference between the two sides was in their appreciation of German strength. The Allies thought that inthe present situation Germany could not do much harm to Turkey.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this applied only to land attack : air bombardment was very possible.PRESIDENT INONU said that all war risks were natural and would have-to be taken. The Turkish Government saw Germany as stretching from the crimea to Rhodes and with Turkey encircled, and they felt that Germany hadfresh forces with which she could attack. If in these circumstances Turkey was left without a minimum of the essential supplies she would be seriously menacedon land. He explained a weak point in the present Turkish military position.At the beginning of November one class had been released from the colours. Anew class of recruits was now being called up. On the basis of a decision by the15th February, Turkey would have to strengthen the army by 2 or 3 classes.Another point was that at the present date the period of mud in Thrace had notyet begun. The President went on to say that he had explained the situation a&amp;he saw it. His technicians were not with him and he could not go further intodetail. It was a serious question for the Government to give a positive answer on matters which went beyond the decision of the Grand National Assembly. Asto the political question in the preparatory period, it was necessary to work fora closer definition of the political situation. If he had understood the PrimeMinister rightly, Mr. Churchill required his answer now, or soon, so that thesituation to be taken up in the future could be defined. He would do all he could to give a clear and accurate answer in 3 or 4 clays.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the final answer was not required till the 15th February, but that in the interval we must at once begin preparations.PRESIDENT INONU understood the position. &apos; The answer he proposedto give in 3 or 4 days was to the question whether and in what manner he wouldengage in the preparations. He would tell us the conditions in which turkey would come in or take the risks likely to bring her in. After having consideredthe Prime Minister&apos;s statement Turkey must give an answer. The Presidentasked that an expert should be sent to Angora to study the technical questionsmore closely. The Turkish answer had been given in principle. The TurkishGovernment thought that a general plan was necessary, not for the sake ofprolonging the discussions but for practical reasons. It was the Prime Minister&apos;opinion that the preparations proposed up to the 15th February were sufficient,In the interval it would be quite possible to form a general plan.THE PRIME MINISTER said that if the President envisaged a longprogramme of re-equipment taking into account the difficulty of communications and so forth, that was the same as saying that the negotiations were ended. Itwould be easy for Turkey to make prohibitive conditions and in that case theAllied forces must be sent elsewhere.PRESIDENT INONU said that this was a serious statement touching a fundamental point. He would define the position as follows : (a) Given that theTurkish answer is a simple acceptance of the Prime Ministers proposal, namely to go on with the preparations till the 15th February and take the final decisionthen, that would be the best answer that the Prime Minister could require.(b) Alternatively to consider Allied needs and&apos; add the Turkish need for a plan which both sides could accept. If Turkey accepted, the preparations could continue, if not, the Prime Minister would have the right to change his plans.THE PRIME MINISTER remarked that that would mean a completechange of policy. In that event the war would move westwards and turkey would lose the chance of coming in and of reaping the advantages which entry intothe war would promise her.M. MENEMENCIOGLU asked whether by change of policy the PrimeMinister was referring to the Anglo-Turkish Alliance.[26609] ii
THE PRIME MINISTER replied that the Alliance would cease to have any value for war purposes. The moment would have gone when Turkey could render the great service we asked. Turkey would stay where she was. Friendship would remain, but as an effective ally for the war Turkey would count for nothing.We should win, but without Turkey. Turkey&apos;s entry into the war was important for us as it gave a chance of includina; Turkey with the Allies in the future.PRESIDENT INONU said that for Turkey fidelity to Great Britain wasa,n essential conception both during and after the war. If this was also theBritish view he thought it was not impossible to find a solution.THE PRIME MINISTER mentioned a suggested line of procedure subse-quently handed in writing to the President and shown here as Annex A.Mr. EDEN said that as regards the Alliance we were faithful to our engage-ments and wished to work with our Turkish friends. But if the time for turkey&apos;s entry into the war came and went, it was inevitable that the spirit ofthe Alliance would be affected.THE PRIME MINISTER expressed the view that Bulgaria would not attack Turkey when she knew that this would entail a Russian declaration of war on her.M MENEMENCIOGLU asked whether the Russian declaration of war would be given equally if Bulgaria allowed Germany all facilities in and throughBulgaria for an attack on Russia, without attacking herself.Mr. EDEN undertook to put this question to the Soviet Government,THE PRIME MINISTER said that he could not guarantee that the germans would not bomb Istanbul and Smyrna. But if our squaarons were there theGermans would have serious losses. He thought it very possible by the end ofFebruary that the situation would be reassuring for Turkey. It would be easier to see clearly then than now and in the interval the. preparations did not commitTurkey to&apos;give a favourable answer to our appeal to send air squadrons after the15th February. The President was quite free to say yes or no without reproach.All that would have happened would be that we had sacrificed war material fornothing. If Germany did not attack Turkey, Turkey could remain in relationswith her, we should not ask Turkey to declare war. Time would thus be.gainedfor sending in further supplies. In this way Turkey would be in a very strong position and would emerge unexhausted, with the advantage of co-operation withthe victorious allies. The Prime Minister wanted Turkey to be strong after thewar and to be friends with Great Britain, the United States and Russia. turkey and Great Britain had common interests and the Prime Minister wanted toprotect them. The Prime Minister then handed the annexed paper to PresidentInonu, who read it and said that it was clear, and that there was nothing more tosay. The Prime Minister pointed out that there were two things to be done.The President would consult the National Assembly and give his answer in four or five days. Those days could also be employed in pressing on with preparationsand sending in specialists. This was agreed to and the number of specialists tobe sent in the five days was limited to 250. At this point the Chiefs of Staffjoined the meeting and handed the Prime Minister a paper which showed that between now and the 15th February, in addition to the supplies required for theA.A. guns and airfields, a total of 58;900 tons could be sent to Turkey by rail for turkey&apos;s own use, given the full co-operation of the Turkish railways, and inaddition as many more supplies as could be carried by sea.It was agreed that the next steps should be as follows : 1. British experts should go to Angora. This was agreed to by thePresident.2. General Kiazim Orbay and General Cefik Cakmak and a naval repre-sentative of the Turkish General Staff should come to Cairo. ThePresident reserved his final answer to this question till his return toAngora.3. Matters should then be followed up by the despatch of more british officers to Angora to continue the conversations.
4751ANNEX A.1.   Air preparations and other supplies till the 15th February.2.   Discussion of war plans.3.   Programme of munitions import.4.   Discussion of political questions.15th February.   Allies ask permission to &quot; fly in.&quot;If reply negative.Allies direct all resources to another theatre and must abandon hope ofwartime co-operation with Turkey.// reply &quot; Yes.&quot;1.   Continuation at fullest speed of programme of import munitions forArmy and Air.2.   Opening of the sea route to Turkey.3.   Reinforcement by British anti-tank and armoured units.4.   Execution of agreed plan with full force of Allies and Turkey.






</content>
</cab>
